<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AndApol"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;


]>
<TEI.2 id="AndApol">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">An Apology for Crudity</title>
<title type="sort">apology for crudity</title>
<author>Anderson, Sherwood, 1876-1941</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>Text prepared by the 1997-98 J. Wallace Sieg Graduate Fellow Jennifer Easley for the
University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">11</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AndApol</idno>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475669</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">An Apology for Crudity</title>
<title level="j">The Dial, Volume 63</title>
<title type="sort">apology for crudity</title>
<author>Sherwood Anderson</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 437-438</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Dial Publishing Co., Inc.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1917-11-08">November 8, 1917</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa library, Call No: AP2.D48</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1917">1917</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; non-fiction</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-08">August, 1997</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jennifer Easley, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
	<pb n="437"/>
<head>
AN APOLOGY FOR CRUDITY<lb/>
BY SHERWOOD ANDERSON
</head>

<p>For a long time I have believed that crudity is an inevitable
quality in the production of a really significant present-day
American literature.  How indeed is one to escape the obvious fact
that there is as yet no native subtlety of thought or living among us?
And if we are a crude and childlike people how can our literature
hope to escape the influence of that fact?  Why indeed should we
want it to escape?
</p><p>If you are in doubt as to the crudity of thought in America, try
an experiment.  Come out of your offices, where you sit writing and
thinking, and try living with us.  Get on a train at Pittsburg and go
west to the mountains of Colorado.  Stop for a time in our towns
and cities.  Stay for a week in some Iowa corn-shipping town and
for another week in one of the Chicago clubs.  As you loiter about
read our newspapers and listen to our conversations, remembering,
if you will, that as you see us in the towns and cities, so we are.  We
are not subtle enough to conceal ourselves and he who runs with
open eyes through the Mississippi Valley may read the story of the
Mississippi Valley.
</p><p>It is a marvelous story and we have not yet begun to tell the
half of it.  A little, I think I know why.  It is because we who write
have drawn ourselves away.  We have not had faith in our people
and in the story of our people.  If we are crude and childlike, that is
our story and our writing men must learn to dare to come among us
until they know the story.  The telling of the story depends, I
believe, upon their learning that lesson and accepting that burden.
</p><p>To my room, which is on a street near the loop in the city of
Chicago, come men who write.  They talk and I talk.  We are fools.
We talk of writers of the old world and the beauty and subtlety of
the work they do.  Below us the roaring city lies like a great animal
on the prairies, but we do not run out to the prairies.  We stay in our
rooms and talk.
</p><p>And so, having listened to talk and having myself talked
overmuch, I grow weary of talk and walk in the streets.  As I walk
alone, an old truth comes home to me and I know that we shall
never have an American literature until we return to faith in
ourselves and to the facing of our own limitations.  We must, in
some way, become in ourselves more like our fellows, more simple
and real.
</p><p>For surely it does not follow that because we Americans are a
people without subtlety, we are a dull or uninteresting people.  Our
literature is dull, but we are not.  One remembers how Dostoevsky
had faith in the simplicity of the Russians and what he achieved.
He lived and he expressed the life of his time and people.  The thing
that he did brings hope of achievement for our men.
</p><p>But let us first of all accept certain truths.  Why should we
Americans aspire to a subtlety that belongs not to us but to old lands
and places?  Why talk of intellectuality and of intellectual life when
we have not accepted the life that we have?  There is death on that
road and following it has brought death into much of American
writing.  Can you doubt what I say?  Consider the smooth slickness
of the average magazine story.</p>
   <pb n="438"/>
<p>There is often great subtlety of plot and phrase, but there is no
reality.  Can such work live?  The answer is that the most popular
magazine story or novel does not live in our minds for a month.
</p><p>And what are we to do about it?  To me it seems that as writers
we shall have to throw ourselves with greater daring into the life
here.  We shall have to begin to write out of the people and not for
the people.  We shall have to find within ourselves a little of that
courage.  To continue along the road we are travelling is
unthinkable.  To draw ourselves apart, to live in little groups and
console ourselves with the thought that we are achieving
intellectuality, is to get nowhere.  By such a road we can hope only
to go on producing a literature that has nothing to do with life as it
is lived in these United States.
</p><p>To be sure, the doing of the thing I am talking about will not
be easy.  America is a land of objective writing and thinking.  New
paths will have to be made.  The subjective impulse is almost
unknown to us.  Because it is close to life, it works out into crude
and broken forms.  It leads along a road that such American masters
of prose as James and Howells did not want to take, but if we are to
get anywhere, we shall have to travel that road.
</p><p>The road is rough and the times are pitiless.  Who, knowing
our America and understanding the life in our towns and cities, can
close his eyes to the fact that life here is for the most part an ugly
affair?  As a people we have given ourselves to industrialism, and
industrialism is not lovely.  If anyone can find beauty in an
American factory town, I wish he would show me the way.  For
myself, I cannot find it.  To me, and I am living in industrial life,
the whole thing is as ugly as modern war.  I have to accept that fact
and I believe a great step forward will have been taken when it is
more generally accepted.
</p><p>But why, I am asked, is crudity and ugliness necessary?  Why
cannot a man like Mr. Dreiser write in the spirit of the early
Americans, why cannot he see fun in life?  What we want is the
note of health.  In the work of Mark Twain there was something
wholesome and sweet.  Why cannot the modern man be also
wholesome and sweet?
</p><p>To this I make answer that to me a man, say like Mr. Dreiser,
is wholesome.  He is true to something in the life about him, and
truth is always wholesome.  Twain and Whitman wrote out of
another age, out of an age and a land of forests and rivers.  The
dominant note of American life in their time was the noisy,
swaggering raftsman and the hairy-breasted woodsman.  To-day it is
not so.  The dominant note in American life to-day is the factory
hand.  When we have digested that fact, we can begin to approach
the task of the present-day novelist with a new point of view.
</p><p>It is, I believe, self-evident that the work of the novelist must
always lie somewhat outside the field of philosophic thought.  Your
true novelist is a man gone a little mad with the life of his times.  As
he goes through life he lives, not in himself, but in many people.
Through his brain march figures and groups of figures.  Out of the
many figures, one emerges.  If he be at all sensitive to the life about
him and that life be crude, the figure that emerges will be crude and
will crudely express itself.
</p><p>I do not know how far a man may go on the road of subjective
writing.  The matter, I admit, puzzles me.  There is something
approaching insanity in the very idea of sinking yourself too deeply
into modern American industrial life.
</p><p>But it is my contention that there is no other road.  If one
would avoid neat, slick writing, he must at least attempt to be
brother to his brothers and live as the men of his time live.  He must
share with them the crude expression of their lives.  To our
grandchildren the privilege of attempting to produce a school of
American writing that has delicacy and color may come as a matter
of course.  One hopes that will be true, but it is not true now.  And
that is why, with so many of the younger Americans, I put my faith
in the modern literary adventurers.  We shall, I am sure, have much
crude, blundering American writing before the gift of beauty and
subtlety in prose shall honestly belong to us.</p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>


