<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AnoBone"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="AnoBone">
	<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Bones Opens a "Spout" Shop</title>
<title type="sort">bones opens a spout shop</title>
<author>Anonymous</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
					<name>Stephen Railton</name>
					<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
					<name/>
					<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
					<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
			<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">9</num> kilobytes</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
				<idno type="ETC">AnoBone</idno>
				<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475679</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Bones Opens a "Spout" Shop</title>
<title level="m">Minstrel Gags and End Men's Hand-book. Being a collection
							of Ethiopian dialogues. Plantation scenes. Eccentric doings. Humorous
							lectures. Laughable interludes. End men's jokes. Burlesque speeches.
							Witticisms. Conundrums, Yarns. Plantation Songs, and dances, etc.; in
							Anti-abolition Tracts and Anti-Black Stereotypes, Part I</title>
<title type="sort">bones opens a spout shop</title>
<author>Anonymous</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
							<name>John David Smith</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
					<extent>pp. 116-17</extent>
					<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Dick &amp; Fitzgerald, Publishers</publisher>
						<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
						<date certainty="uncertain" value="">n.d.</date>
						<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVA Library call number E 449 .A57
							1993</idno>
</publicationStmt>
					<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Anti-abolition Tracts and Anti-Black Stereotypes, Part I, edited by
								John David Smith, and published in New York by Garland Publishing,
								Inc., 1993, as Volume One in the series Anti-Black Thought
								1863-1925, contains a photo facsimile of the Minstrel Gags and End
								Men's Hand-book, first published in the 19th century, from which
								this electronic text was created.</p>
</note>
						</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
				<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
					word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
				<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general
					use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
				<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
					establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
			</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="" certainty="uncertain">n.d.</date>
</creation>
			<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
			<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; fiction</term>
</keywords>
				</textClass>
</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-06">June 1997</date>
				<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
					<name>Carol Osborne, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
				<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>
			<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
				<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
					<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
				<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

	<text id="d1">

		<body id="d2">


			<div1 type="story" id="d3">
				<pb n="116" id="AnoBone116"/>
				<head>BONES OPENS A "SPOUT" SHOP.</head>
				<lb/>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Interlocutor.</hi> What are you thinking about, Mr. Bones? What
					is there on your mind this evening?</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Bones.</hi> I was jis' thinking 'bout dat business I was in
					some time ago. I started in de &mdash; what you call dat business dat da hab
					free balls hanging out?</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Interlocutor.</hi> Oh, you mean the pawnbroker.</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Bones.</hi> Yes, I was a pawnbroker wen I went in de bis, but I
					was a dead broaker wen I came out.</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Interlocutor.</hi> Let us hear of your experience as a
					pawnbroker.</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Bones.</hi> Well, having nofing to do I fout I'd start de
					broaking business; so I rented a room, got free balls what I found laying around
					loose in a ten pin alley, and hung 'em out.</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Interlocutor.</hi> And what success did you have?</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Bones.</hi> I'll tell you. De fust man dat cum in had a big
					paper bundel under his arm; he looked all around, den begin to open de bundel,
					den he look all around agin.</p>

				<pb n="117" id="AnoBone117"/>
				<p><hi rend="italic">Interlocutor.</hi> He was suspicious, I suspect.</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Bones.</hi> Spec he was. At las' he open de bundel and took out
					a ole hammer, an' wanted two dollars on it.</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Interlocutor.</hi> And what did you do about it then?</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Bones</hi> Hammered him over de head wid a club. De next one
					dat come in was a Dutchman, wid a big hunk of Limburger cheese in his hand. He
					wanted to pawn it.</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Interlocutor.</hi> What did you tell him?</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Bones.</hi> Told him to "cheese it" an' go. And de next man had
					a push cart.</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Interlocutor.</hi> A push cart! What did he want to do with
					that?</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Bones.</hi> Wanted to pawn it; it was all broke, and he wanted
					'nuf on it to get a new one.</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Interlocutor.</hi> What did you do with him?</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Bones.</hi> Took him up on de roof, put him in de cart, an'
					pushed him off. De nex' man had he leg ob a stove.</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Interlocutor.</hi> A leg of a stove! What did he want to do
					with that?</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Bones.</hi> Wanted to pawn it.</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Interlocutor.</hi> Wanted to pawn the leg of a stove? What did
					you do with him?</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Bones</hi> Stove in his plug hat wid it. De nex' man dat come
					in was a woming.</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Interlocutor.</hi> A lady, sir. And what did <hi rend="italic"
						>she</hi> want?</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Bones </hi> She wanted to pawn a chaw of tobacer, and I was
					goin' to chaw off her ear, but I seen she had a feller outside to back her. Den
					come a man wid fourteen suits ob old close, and dar wosent haf ob a suit in de
					hole lot.</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Interlocutor.</hi> And what did he want?</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Bones.</hi> Wanted to pawn dem, an' he wanted nuf on dem
					fourteen ole suits to buy seven new suits.</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Interlocutor.</hi> What is that? Do I hear right? He wanted
					enough on the fourteen old suits to buy seven new suits?</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Bones.</hi> Dat's it.</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Interlocutor.</hi> And what conclusion did you come to in
					regard to the clothes?</p>

				<p><hi rend="italic">Bones.</hi> I concluded to close up shop, an' I did so, an'
				never ben in de biz sence.</p>
			</div1>

		</body>
		<back id="d4">
			<div1 type="note" id="d5">

				<p>Here are the two conversations between Jim and Huck that seem most clearly to
					echo these kinds of routines. Of course, these are not the only kinds of
					conversations the two runaways have, but they are the parts of the novel that MT
					first took with him on the "Twins of Genius" tour with Cable, and they helped
					shape the contemporary public's perception of the novel. Apparently when Richard
					Gilder heard MT perform Jim's account of his speculations and his diatribe
					against King Solomon, he talked MT into letting him publish additional
					installments of the novel in his <hi rend="italic">Century Magazine</hi>. These
					colloquys not only made up the entire installment that appeared in the January
					issue of the <hi rend="italic">Century</hi>; the punchline of Jim's account of
					his "speculatin'" was changed to make it sound even more like a minstrel show routine (see Prepublishing Huck):</p>

			</div1>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
