<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AnoElmo"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="AnoElmo">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"St. Elmo" and its Author</title>
<title type="sort">st elmo and its author</title>
<author>Anonymous</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">11</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AnoElmo</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475681</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"'St. Elmo' and its Author" from "Chronicle and Comment."</title>
<title level="j">Bookman</title>
<title type="sort">st elmo and its author from chronicle and comment</title>
<author>Anonymous</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Dodd, Mead and Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1902-09">September 1902</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 16</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>"'St. Elmo' and its Author" from "Chronicle and Comment."  <hi rend="italic">Bookman</hi> 16 (Sept. 1902): 12-14.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1902-09">September 1902</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-02">February 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added Header; Tagged with TEI.2-compatible SGML; Parsed against local
"teilite" dtd.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<front id="d2">

<titlePage id="d3"><pb n="12"/><docTitle>
<titlePart> "St. Elmo" and its Author</titlePart>
</docTitle></titlePage>
</front>
<body id="d4">
<div1 type="essay" id="d5">
<p>In the rush to keep any sort of pace with the lighter and noisier
literature of the day it is pleasant and worth while occasionally
to spend a few minutes looking over the publishers' lists at the
ends of the popular novels of thirty odd years ago, and from them
to contrast the tastes of the past and the present generations&mdash;a
contrast which is very far from being entirely flattering to the
readers of to-day.  At the head of such lists we may be sure to
find the names of those writers who corresponded with the authors
of what are now known as "the best sellers"&mdash;we realise the claims
that Mary J. Holmes and Ann S. Stevens and Augusta J. Evans and May
Agnes Fleming then had to popular attention.  We recognise many
laudable ambitions in the advertisements of books dealing with "the
habits of good society," with "the nice points of taste and good
manners, and the art of making oneself agreeable," with "the art of
polite conversation," and the forms in which letters of business,
of friendship, of society, of respectful endearment should be
couched.  At first sight all this is likely to provoke rather
contemptuous amusement.  And how unjustly!  The forms may be quaint
and obsolete, but the sentiments are homely and praiseworthy, and
in similar literature of to-day there are just as many platitudes,
just as much that is silly and not nearly so much that is sincere.
The average highly successful novel of that time was no more
literature than is the average highly successful novel of to-day,
and the old was generally marked, it must be acknowledged, by an
airiness and pedantry that to-day would not reach the public
without pretty severe editing.  On the other hand, however, the old
novels almost always had stories to tell, and they told them in a
manner to make them from end to end vitally interesting to that
class of readers to which they were designed to appeal.

</p><p>     With the exception of Mrs. Stowe's <hi rend="italic">Uncle Tom's Cabin</hi>,
and the possible exception of General Wallace's <hi rend="italic">Ben Hur</hi>,
there has probably never been a novel written by an American author
that is to be found, well thumbed and yet carefully preserved, in
so many humble libraries as Mrs. Augusta Evans Wilson's <hi rend="italic">St.
Elmo</hi>.  Even to-day, obsolete as it is in form and style, it may
be called an early chapter in the code of life.  In a certain way,
it has a significance very much broader than its significance as a
mere novel.  In the literary development of many young Americans it
has marked a stage, a period.  If one cannot look back and remember
the time when one thought of <hi rend="italic">St. Elmo</hi> as one of the finest
and grandest of all novels, something has surely been missed.  Most
of us can recall quite readily days when we thrilled at the awful
story of the hero's lost youth, and were stirred to amazement and
admiration over Edna Earl's knowledge of the Unknowable.  Perhaps
St. Elmo's sardonic bitterness no longer impresses us; perhaps we
have come to realise that all the tragic gloom of his demeanour was
only a ridiculous pose; and as for Edna Earl, there is no doubt
that she is entitled to a very high place as a public nuisance
among the heroines of fiction.  There never was a book written more
open to ridicule.  And yet, when that inclination to ridicule comes
we pause, half ashamed.  For under all the pompous phraseology we
feel 
	<pb n="13"/> 
	<gap desc="Illustration not included" reason="unknown"/>
<pb n="14"/>
that there was a story to
be told; that not a line of it was penned that was not inspired by
sincerity and a belief in lofty ideals; and that it has done much
to brighten the lives of many hundreds of thousands of readers.
<hi rend="italic">St. Elmo</hi> is a paradox.  It is utterly and flatly absurd; and
yet it is a noble work, the work of a noble woman.

</p><p>     One cannot spend much time at the task of reviewing the
current books of the day without occasionally feeling a twinge of
envy when thinking of the opportunities of the reviewers of other
days.  Who would not like to have had a fling at <hi rend="italic">Vanity Fair</hi>
when it was coming out in installments; to have had the chance to
have hailed enthusiastically the rising genius of Dickens, or to
have sat down gravely to the composition of a critical screed anent
a new tale by the Wizard of the North?  It is very interesting and
worth while occasionally to spend time poring over rusty libraries
in the search for contemporary criticism of the great books of the
early half of the century.  How many of the puny verdicts have been
overthrown by the great judgment of posterity?  Of course,
<hi rend="italic">we</hi> are quite sure that <hi rend="italic">we</hi> should never have blundered
so egregiously; that <hi rend="italic">we</hi> should never have dismissed a great
masterpiece with a few curt lines of faint praise or a half column
of cocky abuse.  We should have liked to have tried our fist at
them all.  We should have acclaimed highly the genius of Irving,
Hawthorne and Poe, and predicted the many startling events which
were to result from the publication of <hi rend="italic">Uncle Tom's Cabin</hi>.
When we came to Mrs. Wilson's <hi rend="italic">St. Elmo</hi>, we should, of
course, have been the first to point out its resemblance to
Charlotte Bronte's <hi rend="italic">Jane Eyre;</hi> to show that Edna Earl was
simply an impossible Jane Eyre in another environment, and that St.
Elmo Murray was simply a very stilted and noisy Edward Rochester.
All this and more we should have done; at least, we can think so
now in pleasant day-dreams.

</p><p>     More than sixteen years have elapsed since the publication of
Mrs. Wilson's <hi rend="italic">At the Mercy of Tiberius</hi>, which she herself,
as well as the public at large, long regarded as her last book.
But two years ago she went to work again and wrote the story, <hi rend="italic">A
Speckled Bird</hi>, which her publishers are now bringing out.  This
is the only one of her novels which was not written at Ashland, the
Wilson estate near Mobile.  Her first book, <hi rend="italic">Inez</hi>, appeared
in 1855, and was far from being immediately successful.  Mr. Derby,
in his <hi rend="italic">Fifty Years Among Books, Authors and Publishers</hi>, has
told the story of her first visit to his office in the later
fifties, when she came to submit the manuscript of <hi rend="italic">Beulah</hi>.
She was accompanied by a cousin, a nervous and fiery young
Southerner, who spent his time during the interview between author
and publisher apparently examining the backs of the books lining
the room.  He afterward confessed to Mr. Derby that he had been
listening very attentively, and that he had made up his mind, in
case of a rejection, to hurl the volumes at the publisher's head.
<hi rend="italic">Beulah</hi> appeared in 1859.  Mrs. Wilson's third novel,
<hi rend="italic">Macaria</hi>, had an adventurous career.  It was published at
Richmond in 1862, under a Confederate States copyright: a United
States copyright was not obtained for it until 1868.  <hi rend="italic">Vashti</hi>
appeared in 1869, <hi rend="italic">Infelice</hi> in 1875, and <hi rend="italic">At the Mercy of
Tiberius</hi> not until twelve years later.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
