<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AnoJewe"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="AnoJewe">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Miss Jewett</title>
<title type="sort">miss jewett</title>
<author>Jewett, Sarah Orne: review: anonymous</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">16</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AnoJewe</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475686</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Miss Jewett</title>
<title type="sort">miss jewett</title>
<author>Anonymous</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<date value="1894-01">January 1894</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>73</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 73 (Jan. 1894): 130-133.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1894-01">January 1894</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction ; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-08">August 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header; Tagged text with TEI2-compatible SGML; Parsed against
"teilite" dtd.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">


<body id="d2">
<div1 type="article" id="d3"><pb n="130" id="AnoJewe130"/>
<head>MISS JEWETT.</head>
<div2 type="text" id="d4">

<p>The publication in the same season of the latest collection of
Miss Jewett's stories<ref target="n1">1</ref> and an illustrated edition of her earliest
book<ref target="n2">2</ref> gives opportunity for a glance at the growth in artistic
skill of one of our most happily endowed writers.  Twenty years
have elapsed since the first of the sketches appeared which, with
others strung upon a light thread of personal narrative, formed the
little volume now gracefully illustrated.  The drawings which Mr.
and Mrs. Woodbury have made for its decoration, it is not unfair to
say, present in their variety and choice of subject the salient
features of Miss Jewett's art with the delicacy of touch and the
firmness of line which she is to-day disclosing in her maturer
work.  Figures, landscapes, interiors, all are delightfully
expressive of Miss Jewett; but their fine drawing, vividness of
portraiture, and reserve of force belong to the Deephaven which
Miss Jewett might write to-day.  The feeling is the same; it is the
art which has become more definite and clear.  The designs are
pictures where the text is a sketch.  As an example, how thoroughly
satisfactory is the picture of Miss Brandon at her Piano, in which
Mrs. Woodbury has caught Miss Jewett's sketch capitally, and filled
it out!  One exception should be made.  Good as is the portrait of
Mrs. Dockum, and admirably as Mrs. Woodbury has reproduced Miss
Jewett's idea, the author's own portrait of Mrs. Dockum, as

<pb n="131" id="AnoJewe131"/>
delineated in that excellent woman's address when introduced, is a
bit of characterization as good as anything she is doing to-day.
There are other passages in Deephaven which the reader will recall,
equally humorous in conception and true in drawing.  Such are those
that portray the figures in the chapter The Captains, the sketch of
Mrs. Bonny in her search for a tumbler, the meek widow with the
appearance of a thin black beetle and a voice like the wail of the
banshee, the funeral procession, and, in her various appearances,
the carefully wrought Mrs. Kew.  From time to time, and very often
at that, the reader is surprised by the success with which a girl
scarcely out of her teens caught the likenesses of these shore
folk, and gave to her sketches a breadth as well as a refinement
which seemed to come from careful training, yet really, we must
believe, were the unerring product of a genuine gift of literary
art illumined and warmed by an affectionate sympathy.
</p><p>Miss Jewett tells us in her interesting preface&mdash;or rather
reminds us, for she had been obliged to say it before&mdash;that her
village and its people were not the simple result of camera work.
The truthfulness, the fidelity to nature, and the frank, winning
manner of the narrative easily persuaded readers that this young
writer was innocently recording personal experience, and varying
but slightly from actual fact.  Much of this illusion was no doubt
produced by the assumption of a sort of dual autobiographic
character, but more, we think, by that frequent expression of
delicate charity which was so refined and thoughtful, so
instantaneous in its action when occasion arose, that the reader at
once identified the writer with her creation, and, by a singular
suppression of logic, believed her capable of doing what the
character of the story-teller as delineated would have made
impossible.  Here was a most unconscious tribute to Miss Jewett's
art; for art it is, of a high order, which shines clearly in
Deephaven, and reconciles one readily to that immaturity which Miss
Jewett herself, in her preface, half humorously deprecates.
</p><p>It is perhaps not far out of the way to say that Deephaven
accurately embodies creative girlhood, as Andersen's stories, for
instance, embody creative childhood.  The book reproduces the angle
of vision of that most elusive creature, the young girl, not as she
is made by novelists, but as she is by nature, with all her
capacity for enjoyment of life and her latent sense of
responsibility, which turns into ready sympathy at a touch, and
always discloses itself in a charity which is as sensitive as her
delicately balanced nature can make it.  Kitty Lancaster and Helen
Denis look on this decayed gentility and sea-blown human life with
laughing eyes, but they draw back at the least suspicion of
laughing at the spectacle.  For this reason the book is likely to
have a long life, for it will appeal successively to generations
that repeat the period for which it stands; and it will do this all
the more surely because it reflects the vision of the young girl
turned upon the outer world, and not turned in on herself.
</p><p>It is natural for an author, when she is speaking of her work,
to dwell upon those ethical considerations which underlie her
purpose, and Miss Jewett speaks with a gentle earnestness of the
impelling motive which sent Deephaven into the world; but we know
well that in this instance, as in others, it was the delight of a
beautiful art which made the book in its form possible.  However
critically the reader may intend to read it, as the early
production of a writer with an assured position, he yields very
soon to the charm of the narrative and the characterization, and
recognizes through all the apparent naturalness the ease of the
true artist.  In the books which have followed Deephaven there have
been at times expressions of a more conscious <pb n="132" id="AnoJewe132"/> purpose of
construction, and it has been apparent that Miss Jewett, aware of
the somewhat fragmentary and sketchy character of her writing, has
aimed at a more deliberate structure; but the naturalness, the
direct look at life, the clear sense of the value of the moment,
have always been her protection against an artificial method; and
with an increase of experience has come also an access of strength,
though this strength has been shown rather in a firmer conception
of the contrasting pathos and humor of life than in any outburst of
passion or kindling emotion.
</p><p>The volume of short stories which stands latest in the
honorable series is delightful by reason of the freshness of the
several situations and the delicacy with which they are expressed.
As we have intimated, it is situations rather than dramatic action
with which Miss Jewett concerns herself, and situations especially
which illustrate character.  Thus, in the volume before us, A
Native of Winby sets forth the return to his old village home of a
man who has won fame; his appearance, large as life, in the little
schoolhouse which knew his boyish inconspicuousness; and his
encounter with a woman who, as a girl, had known the boy.  It is
indicative of the reserve of Miss Jewett, her nice sense of the
limits of her art, that she does not resort to any conventional
device of rounding out her story, and Mr. Laneway does not pair off
with Abby Hender as an effective conclusion.  Miss Jewett cares
more for the real interest of the situation, for the working of
such a nature as Mr. Laneway's in this half-egotistic, half-shamefaced return.  Decoration Day, again, as a story, could be
told in a few lines, but as a reflection of a half-buried patriotic
emotion it is of moving power.  Rarely, we think, has this writer
shown so well the fine reserve of her art.  By the low tone in
which all the scenes of this homely revival of patriotism are
painted, she has touched the quiet, responsive passion.  The
Passing of Sister Barsett has a witty climax, but, after all, it is
the inimitable humor and pathos of the conversation between the two
women which make the story a patch of New England life; and if
there had been no witty turn, the reader still would have had his
half-hour's worth.  The Flight of Betsey Lane is the most complete
story in the book, but it is a tale of adventure illustrative of
character, and never does the reader lose his interest in the
quaint figure who has the delightful escapade from any strong
attraction to the issue of the story.  In The Failure of David
Berry, the absence of any plot is made more conspicuous by the
presence of a little shadowy personage who, in the hands of an
artist intent on a story, would have emerged out of the shadow into
some sort of fairy godmother's sunshine.  As it is, she goes back
weeping into the obscurity from which she came, and, with scarcely
a lineament for the reader to decipher, remains in his mind as one
of the most real, most lifelike, of the few dramatis personae of
the story.  It would be hard to find a better illustration of the
power of Miss Jewett's imaginative sympathy to call into being and
give endurance to a fleeting image of human life.
</p><p>The last two sketches in the book have a special interest by
their intimation, which we have pointed out before, of a direction
which Miss Jewett's art may take in the way of subjects.  In her
previous collection of short stories, The Luck of the Bogans was an
excursion into the field of Irish New England, and wholly
successful, as it seemed to us; a little surprising, also, as
showing how, when the writer left more familiar ground, she
disclosed a vigor of handling which the material seemed to require.
So here, in the graphic story Between Mass and Vespers, where the
persons are all American Irish, with true instinct she apprehends
the nature of her material, and again uses her pen in the
delineation of a rougher, ruder life; yet <pb n="133" id="AnoJewe133"/> her inborn
charity and refinement find a congenial subject in the fatherly
priest.  The last story in the book, A Little Captive Maid, is a
still greater success.  Here she has made the central figure a
young Irish girl, and has woven her fortunes with those of an
invalid, willful New England sea-captain.  This latter personage is
one whom we could trust confidently in Miss Jewett's hands, as we
remember the gallery of his companions painted by her; but if any
one fancies that Miss Jewett is indebted for her success to a mere
concentration of her art on a few types among which she had grown
up, let him observe the speech and manner, and further still the
nature, of Nora Connelly, and he will see that the artist who drew
her might be trusted with any subject where her sympathy and
insight had clear opportunity.  This story, with its blending of
the native and foreign, is as delicate and winning a study of life
as any in which the New England character alone is depicted, and it
invites the hope that Miss Jewett's art will include hereafter more
of such suggestive contrasts.
</p><p>Thus, our examination of these two books not only discloses a
genuineness of gift, which has been developed by conscientious
practice into an assurance of artistic power, the more confident in
that it recognizes the scope of its effectiveness, but intimates
also a widening of the field of vision.  It is scarcely to be
expected that Miss Jewett will ever attain the constructive power
which holds in the grasp a variety of complex activities and
controls their energy, directing it to some conclusive end; but her
imagination is strong to conceive a genuine situation, to
illustrate it through varied character, to illuminate it with humor
and dewy pathos; and as she extends the range of her characters, so
she is likely to display even more invention in the choice of
situations which shall give opportunity to those delightful
characters who spring at her bidding from no one class, and even
from no one nation.  Especially do we hope that she will mark in
the art of literature that elusive period of New England life
through which we are passing, when so many streams of race are now
opposing, now blending, now flowing side by side.  She has caught
and held firmly some phases of that life which are already
historical.  Let her record with equal art some phases of that life
still in formation, and she will lay the foundations of a fresh
fame.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="notes" id="d5">
<head>Notes</head>

<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">1.</seg> <p><hi rend="italic"> A Native of Winby, and Other Tales</hi>.  By SARAH ORNE
JEWETT.  Boston and New York: Houghton, Mifflin &amp; Co. 1893.</p></note>

<note id="n2"><seg type="note-symbol">2.</seg> <p><hi rend="italic"> Deephaven</hi>.  By SARAH ORNE JEWETT.  Illustrated by
CHARLES and MARCIA WOODBURY.  Boston and New York: Houghton,
Mifflin &amp; Co. 1894.</p></note>

</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
