<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AusBret"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>


<TEI.2 id="AusBret">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Jimville: A Bret Harte Town</title>
<title type="sort">jimville a bret harte town</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">17</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AusBret</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475701</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Jimville: A Bret Harte Town</title>
<title type="sort">jimville a bret harte town</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Edited by</resp>
<name>editor</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<date value="1902">1902</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Vol. 90</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Verification made against printed text</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1902">1902</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman and Kelly Tetterton, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header, basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head>
Austin, Mary.  "Jimville: A Bret Harte Town."
<lb/>
<hi rend="italic"> Atlantic Monthly</hi> 90 (1902): 690-694.
</head>
<pb n="690"/>

<p>WHEN Mr. Harte found himself with a fresh palette and his
particular local color fading from the West, he did what he
considered the only safe thing, and carried his young impression
away to be worked on untroubled by any newer fact.  He should have
gone to Jimville.  There he would have found cast up on the ore-ribbed hills the bleached timbers of more tales, and better ones.
</p><p>You could not think of Jimville as anything more than a
survival, like the herb-eating, bony-cased old tortoise that pokes
cheerfully about those borders some thousands of years beyond his
proper epoch.  Not that Jimville is old, <pb n="691"/>  but it has an
atmosphere favorable to the type of a half century back, if not
"forty-niners," of that breed.  It is said of Jimville that getting
away from it is such a piece of work that it encourages permanence
in the population; the fact is that most have been drawn there by
some real likeness or liking.  Not however that I would deny the
difficulty of getting into or out of that cove of reminder, I who
have made the journey so many times at great pains of a poor body.
Any way you go at it, Jimville is about three days from anywhere in
particular.  North or south, after the railroad there is a stage
journey of such interminable monotony as induces forgetfulness of
all previous states of existence.
</p><p>The road to Jimville is the happy hunting-ground of old
stagecoaches bought up from superseded routes the West over,
rocking, lumbering, wide vehicles far gone in the order of romance,
coaches that Vasquez has held up, from whose high seats express
messengers have shot or been shot as their luck held.  This is to
comfort you when the driver stops to rummage for wire to mend a
failing bolt.  There is enough of this sort of thing to quite
prepare you to believe what the driver insists, namely, that all
that country and Jimville are held together by wire.
</p><p>First on the way to Jimville you cross a lonely open land,
with a hint in the sky of things going on under the horizon, a
palpitant, white, hot land where the wheels gird at the sand and
the midday heaven shuts it in breathlessly like a tent.  So in
still weather; and when the wind blows there is occupation enough
for the passengers, shifting seats to hold down the windward side
of the wagging coach.  This is a mere trifle.  The Jimville stage
is built for five passengers, but when you have seven, with four
trunks, several parcels, three sacks of grain, the mail and
express, you begin to understand that proverb about the road which
has been reported to you.  In time you learn to engage the high
seat beside the driver, where you get good air and the best
company.  Beyond the desert rise the lava flats, scoriae strewn;
sharp-cutting walls of narrow canons; league-wide, frozen puddles
of black rock, intolerable and forbidding.  Beyond the lava the
mouths that spewed it out, ragged-lipped, ruined craters
shouldering to the cloud-line, mostly of red earth, as red as a red
heifer.  These have some comforting of shrubs and grass.  You get
the very spirit of the meaning of that country when you see Little
Pete feeding his sheep in the red, choked maw of an old vent,&mdash;a
kind of silly pastoral gentleness that glozes over an elemental
violence.  Beyond the craters rise worn, auriferous hills of a
quiet sort, tumbled together; a valley full of mists; whitish green
scrub; and bright small panting lizards; then Jimville.
</p><p>The town looks to have spilled out of Squaw Gulch, and that,
in fact, is the sequence of its growth.  It began around the Bully
Boy and Theresa group of mines midway up Squaw Gulch, spreading
down to the smelter at the mouth of the ravine.  The freight wagons
dumped their loads as near to the hill as the slope allowed, and
Jimville grew in between.  Above the Gulch begins a pine wood with
sparsely grown thickets of lilac, azalea, and odorous blossoming
shrubs.
</p><p>Squaw Gulch is a very sharp, steep, ragged-walled ravine, and
that part of Jimville which is built in it has only one street,&mdash;in
summer paved with bone-white cobbles, in the wet months a frothy
yellow flood.  All between the ore dumps and solitary small cabins,
pieced out with tin cans and packing-cases, run footpaths drawing
down to the Silver Dollar saloon.  When Jimville was having the
time of its life the Silver Dollar had those same coins let into
the bar top for a border, but the proprietor pried them out when
the glory departed.  There are three hundred<pb n="692"/> inhabitants in
Jimville and four bars, though you are not to argue anything from
that.
</p><p>Hear now how Jimville came by its name.  Jim Calkins
discovered the Bully Boy, Jim Baker located the Theresa.  When Jim
Jenkins opened an eating-house in his tent he chalked up on the
flap, "Best Meals in Jimville, "$1.00," and the name stuck.
</p><p>There was more human interest in the origin of Squaw Gulch,
though it tickled no humor.  It was Dimmick's squaw from Aurora
way.  If Dimmick had been anything except New Englander he would
have called her <hi rend="italic"> Mahala</hi>, but that would not have bettered his
behavior.  Dimmick made a strike, went East, and the squaw who had
been to him as his wife took to drink.  That was the bald way of
stating it in the Aurora country.  The milk of human kindness, like
some wine, must not be uncorked too much in speech lest it lose
savor.  This is what they did.  The woman would have returned to
her own people, being far gone with child, but the drink worked her
bane.  By the river of this ravine her pains overtook her.  There
Jim Calkins, prospecting, found her dying with a three days' babe
nozzling at her breast.  Jim heartened her for the end, buried her,
and walked back to Poso eighteen miles, the child poking in the
folds of his denim shirt with small mewing noises, and won support
for it from the rough-handed folks of that place.  Then he came
back to Squaw Gulch, so named from that day, and discovered the
Bully Boy.  Jim humbly regarded this piece of luck as interposed
for his reward, and I for one believed him.  If it had been in
mediaeval times you would have had a legend or a ballad.  Bret
Harte would have given you a tale.  You see in me a mere recorder,
for I know what is best for you; you shall blow out this bubble
from your own breath.
</p><p>You would never get into any proper relation to Jimville
unless you could slough off and swallow your acquired prejudices as
a lizard does his skin.  Once wanting some womanly attentions, the
stage driver assured me I might have them at the Nine-Mile House
from the lady barkeeper.  The phrase tickled all my after-dinner-coffee sense of humor into an anticipation of Poker Flat.  The
stage driver proved himself really right, though you are not to
suppose from this that Jimville had no conventions and no caste.
They work out these things in the personal equation largely.
Almost every latitude of behavior is allowed a good fellow, one no
liar, a free spender, and a backer of his friends' quarrels.  You
are respected in as much ground as you can shoot over, in as many
pretensions as you can make good.
</p><p>That probably explains Mr. Fanshawe, the gentlemanly faro
dealer of those parts, built for the role of Oakhurst, going white-shirted and frock-coated in a community of overalls; and persuading
you that whatever shifts and tricks of the game were laid to his
deal, he could not practice them on a person of your penetration.
But he does.  By his own account and the evidence of his manners he
had been bred for a clergyman, and he certainly has gifts for the
part.  You find him always in possession of your point of view, and
with an evident, though not obtrusive desire to stand well with
you.  For an account of his killings, for his way with women and
the way of women with him, I refer you to Brown of Calaveras and
some others of that stripe.  His improprieties had a certain
sanction of long standing not accorded to the gay ladies who wore
Mr. Fanshawe's favors.  There were perhaps too many of them.  On
the whole, the point of the moral distinctions of Jimville appears
to be a point of honor, with an absence of humorous appreciation
that strangers mistake for dullness.  At Jimville they see behavior
as history and judge it by facts, untroubled by invention and the
dramatic sense.  You glimpse a crude sense of equity in their
<pb n="693"/>  dealings with Wilkins who had shot a man at Lone Tree fairly,
in an open quarrel.  Rumor of it reached Jimville before Wilkins
rested there in flight.  I saw Wilkins, all Jimville saw him; in
fact, he came into the Silver Dollar when we were holding a church
fair and bought a pink silk pincushion.  I have often wondered what
became of it.  Some of us shook hands with him, not because we did
not know, but because we had not been officially notified, and
there were those present who knew how it was themselves.  When the
sheriff arrived Wilkins had moved on, and Jimville organized a
posse and brought him back, because the sheriff was a Jimville man
and we had to stand by him.
</p><p>I said we had the church fair at the Silver Dollar.  We had
most things there, dances, town meetings, and the kinetoscope
exhibition of the Passion Play.  The Silver Dollar had been built
when the borders of Jimville spread from Minton to the red hill the
Defiance twisted through.  "Side-Winder" Smith scrubbed the floor
for us and moved the bar to the back room.  The fair was designed
for the support of the circuit rider who preached to the few that
would hear, and buried us all in turn.  He was the symbol of
Jimville's respectability, although he was of a sect that held
dancing among the cardinal sins.  The management took no chances on
offending the minister; at 11:30 they tendered him the receipts of
the evening in the chairman's hat, as a delicate intimation that
the fair was closed.  The company filed out of the front door and
around to the back.  Then the dance began formally with no feelings
hurt.  These were the sort of courtesies, common enough in Jimville
that brought tears of delicate inner laughter.
</p><p>There were others besides Mr. Fanshawe who had walked out of
Mr. Harte's demesne to Jimville and wore names that smacked of the
soil, "Alkali Bill," "Pike" Wilson, "Three Finger," and "Mono Jim;"
fierce, shy, profane, sun-dried derelicts of the windy hills; who
each owned, or had owned, a mine and was wishful to own one again.
They laid up on the worn benches of the Silver Dollar or the Same
Old Luck like beached vessels, and their talk ran on endlessly of
"strike" and "contact" and "mother lode," and worked around to
fights and hold-ups, villainy, haunts, and the hoodoo of the
Minietta, told austerely without imagination.
</p><p>Do not suppose I am going to repeat it all; you who want these
things written up from the point of view of people who do not do
them every day would get no savor in their speech.
</p><p>Says Three Finger, relating the history of the Mariposa, "I
took it off'n Tom Beatty, cheap, after his brother Bill was shot."
</p><p>Says Jim Jenkins, "What was the matter of him?"
</p><p>"Who?  Bill?  Abe Johnson shot him; he was fooling around
Johnson's wife, an' Tom sold me the mine dirt cheap."
</p><p>"Why didn't he work it himself."
</p><p>"Him?  Oh, he was laying for Abe and calculated to have to
leave the country pretty quick."
</p><p>"Huh!" says Jim Jenkins, and the tale flows smoothly on.
</p><p>Yearly the spring fret floats the loose population of Jimville
out into the desolate waste hot lands, guiding by the peaks and a
few rarely touched water holes, always, always with the golden
hope.  They develop prospects and grow rich, develop others and
grow poor but never embittered.  Say the hills, It is all one,
there is gold enough, time enough, and men enough to come after
you.  And at Jimville they understand the language of the hills.
</p><p>Jimville does not know a great deal about the crust of the
earth, it prefers a "hunch."  That is an intimation from the gods
that if you go over a brown back of the hills, by a dripping
spring, up Coso way, you will find what is worth while.  I have
never heard that the failure of any particular hunch disproved
<pb n="694"/> proved the principle.  Somehow the rawness of the land favors
the sense of personal relation to the supernatural.  There is not
much intervention of crops, cities, clothes, and manners between
you and the organizing forces to cut off communication.  All this
begets in Jimville a state that passes explanation unless you will
accept an explanation that passes belief.  Along with killing and
drunkenness, coveting of women, charity, simplicity, there is a
certain indifference, blankness, emptiness if you will, of all
vaporings, no bubbling of the pot,&mdash;it wants the German to coin a
word for that,&mdash;no bread-envy, no brother-fervor.  Western writers
have not sensed it yet (perhaps Lummis a little); they smack the
savor of lawlessness too much upon their tongues, but you have
these to witness it is not mean-spiritedness.  It is pure Greek in
that it represents the courage to shear off what is not worth
while.  Beyond that it endures without sniveling, renounces without
self-pity, fears no death, rates itself not too great in the scheme
of things; so do beasts, so did St. Jerome in the desert, so also
in the elder day did gods.  Life, its performance, cessation, is no
new thing to gape and wonder at.
</p><p>Here you have the repose of the perfectly accepted instinct
which includes passion and death in its perquisites.  I suppose
that the end of all our hammering and yawping will be something
like the point of view of Jimville.  The only difference will be in
the decorations.
</p>
<signed>                              <hi rend="italic"> Mary Austin.</hi>
</signed>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
