<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AusHood"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="AusHood">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Hoodoo of the Minnietta</title>
<title type="sort">hoodoo of the minnietta</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">18</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AusHood</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475707</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Hoodoo of the Minnietta</title>
<title type="sort">hoodoo of the minnietta</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Edited by</resp>
<name>editor</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Century Magazine</publisher>
<date value="1907-07">July 1907</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Vol. 74</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Verification made against printed text</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1907">1907</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman and Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head>Austin, Mary.  "The Hoodoo of the Minnietta."
<lb/>
<hi rend="italic"> Century Magazine</hi> 74 (July 1907): 450-453.
<lb/>
Author of "Isidro"
</head>
<pb n="450"/>
<p>
SOUTH by east from the leprous shore of Owens Lake, untangling the
network of trails that lead toward the lava flanks of Coso, one
comes at last to the Minnietta, a crumbling tunnel, a ruined
smelter, and a row of sun-warped dwellings in a narrow gully faced
by tall, skeleton-white cliffs.
</p><p>It lies so secretly in the cut of the country rock, and has so
somber a tone in the stark, wide light, that you perceive it at
once to be one of those places that contribute to the fixed belief
of mining countries that the hot essences of greed and hate and
lust are absorbed, as it were, by the means that provoke them, and
inhere in houses, lands, or stones, to work mischief to the
possessor.  This is common in new and untamed lands, where
destinies are worked out in plain sight.  Manuel de Borba could not
persuade the sheriff to accept as a gift the knife with which he
killed Mariana, and no miner acquainted with its hoodoo will have
anything to do with the Minnietta.
</p><p>Antone discovered it in a forgotten year.  No one knew his
other name: at Panamint he was called Dutchy, after the use of
mining camps, from which you gather that he might have been a
German, Swede, Norwegian, Dane, or even a Dutchman.  He was a
foreigner, very sick when he came to the hills, sicker when he left
them; and he discovered the ledge in a three-weeks prospecting
trip, from which he returned to Jake Hogan's cabin with his pockets
full of ore, elate, penniless, and utterly worn.
</p><p>He talked it all out with Hogan, on into the night, with the
candle guttering in a bottle and the winking specimens spread out
on the table between them.  The ore was heavy and dull, and had the
greasy feel of richness.  Between the pains of a racking cough,
Antone promised himself great things.  He talked on afterward in
his bunk, maunderingly, as his fever rose, to which succeeded the
stupor of exhaustion.  That was why, three days later, not being
able to attend to it himself, he asked Hogan to have the ore
assayed and to bring him the report.  And the report was so little
in the eye of his expectation that a week later, loathing the
filthy cabin and the ill-cooked food, feeling death in his throat,
all his thought set toward home, Antone accepted the two hundred
dollars which Hogan offered him for all right and interest in his
claim.  Hogan considerately saw him off on the Mojave stage, and
immediately gathered his pack to set out for a certain gully faced
by tall white cliffs, where the outcrop was heavy and dull, with a
greasy feel.
</p><p>Long afterward, when rage had made him drunk, Hogan&mdash;his
wickedness, as it were, an added poison to his curse&mdash;explained
how, when it was full dark, when the one street was barred with
blocks of light from dance-houses full of roaring song, he had gone
down to the assay office, the light of the furnace glowing low and
evilly along the ground, with other specimens than Antone's, but so
like them in all but richness that Dutchy, <pb n="451"/>  turning in his
blanket and shaken terribly with coughing, never knew.  That, said
Hogan, when he cursed the men who had done him out of the
Minnietta, was the sort of man he was; as much as to say, being a
toad, he spat venom, and was not to be trod upon.  But at the time
he must have thought more cheerfully of his offense.
</p><p>Within a month it was known in all the Panamint and Coso
camps, and as far north as Cerro Gordo, that Jake Hogan had made a
good strike at the Minnietta.
</p><p>Hogan organized a stock company to open the mine and build a
smelter, and began to grow rich amazingly.  Jigging burro trains
went up and down with water; eighteen-mule freighters trailed in
with supplies in a wake of tawny dust.  Beflounced and fluttered
women, last indubitable evidence of a prosperous camp, preened
themselves in the cabins set askew under the white cliffs.
</p><p>It is not given to every man to deal successfully with mining-stock companies.  Hogan prospecting a grub-stake and Hogan owner of
the Minnietta, putting out its thousands a week, were much the same
person.  Because he was ignorant, Hogan did not understand his
stock company when he had organized it; and because he had come
into his property by stealth, feared to lose it by conspiracy.
Before the end of the second year, Hogan and the Minnietta Mining
and Milling Company were taking away each other's characters openly
in court.
</p><p>Hogan got a judgment that gave him little less than half what
he asked; contumaciously he carried it to a higher court, and got
a reversal of judgment that gave him nothing at all.  So at the
last he went out of Minnietta with little more than he had brought
into it,&mdash;folly and shame, you understand, peering with painted
faces from the little cabins under the cliff, had had their
pickings of him,&mdash;and going, cursed it with fluency and all his
might.  Tunnel and shaft and winze, he cursed it; sheave and cross-cut; pulley and belt; and blast and fall-rope under the hoist.  As
he had made it, he cursed it in every part.  Those who heard him
maintain that in the cursing of Hogan was wrought the hoodoo of the
Minnietta; but, in fact, it began in the fake assay which Hogan
carried to Antone in his bed, a villainy of which he despoiled
himself in his cursing, with the wantonness by which a man, checked
in an evil, reveals the iniquity in which he shaped it.
</p><p>After that the Minnietta Mining and Milling Company was not
uniformly prosperous; the price of silver went down or the quality
of the ore fell off, and there were months at a time when the mine
was shut down while the directors settled their private squabbles.
Now and then, and always at inopportune moments, the company had
streaks of economy.
</p><p>In one of these they happened upon McKenna for superintendent,
whose particular qualification was that he was cheap, and being no
spender at the best of times, was not always careful to draw his
salary at the end of the month.  This was very bad business for a
mining country, as McKenna came to know when the next shut-down
found him with a salary some fifteen months in arrears.  He said
uncomplimentary things about the management, but did not
unnecessarily harass the directors, because he held his job on
half-pay until work began again&mdash;all of which was still unpaid when
the mine reopened with a small force in April.
</p><p>By this time, you understand, the Minnietta Mining and Milling
Company was in a bad way.  When the ore was of high grade or the
price of silver went up a few points, they could work the mine at
a profit; when neither of these things happened, it ran at a loss,
and McKenna was their chief creditor.  All this time the flux of
mining life slacked throughout that district&mdash;slacked and dribbled
away down the trails of desolate gulches; poured off quick, as it
had come, like the sudden rains that burst over those ranges,
leaving it scarred with dump and shaft and track.  Houses, full of
the cheap, garish furniture of the camps, warped apart in the sun;
rabbits ran in and out of the sagging sills.  Five days' desolation
lay between the world and the Minnietta.
</p><p>During the shut-down McKenna stayed and looked after the mine,
because, as he said, it owed him so much that he could not afford
to neglect it; but really because the desert had him, catlike,
between her paws.  So he stayed on, and tinkered <pb n="452"/>  about
repairs for the mill and the smelter.  After one such session he
was observed to go about in the tumultuous silence of a man with a
doubtful project; also he ceased to vex the management greatly
about his arrears of salary.  That was about a year before the
Minnietta was shut down altogether.
</p><p>In the course of time McKenna, as the chief creditor, brought
suit, attached the property of the company, and got a judgment by
default.
</p><p>At that time he could have had the whole district on the same
terms, for something had happened or was about to happen in some
other quarter which made the value of silver to the ton about half
the cost of working it.  The first thing McKenna did when he came
into possession was to rip up the smelter.
</p><p>This was before the cyanide process was discovered, and the
smelter was of the rudest description, and McKenna had repaired it.
Four great bars of virgin silver, half the length of a man's body
and of incredible thickness, he took out of it in the way of
leakings.  McKenna used it to put the property in working order.
The thing which was about to happen in Germany or Argentina or
wherever, had not happened, or, if it had, not with the anticipated
effect.  Silver went up.  McKenna looked to the management himself,
grew sleek, and married a wife.  But the hoodoo worked.
</p><p>In the second year Mrs. McKenna had a child, and it died.  Did
I say somewhere that women mostly hate the desert?  Women, unless
they have very large and simple souls, need cover&mdash;clothes, you
know, and furniture, social observances to screen them, conventions
to get behind.  Life, when it leaps upon them large and naked,
shocks their souls into disorder.  Mrs. McKenna at the Minnietta
had the arm-long grave under the skeleton cliffs, and McKenna, with
no screen to his commonness.  Her mind traveled back and forth from
these and down the gulch to a vista of treeless, discolored hills.
Finally, for very emptiness, it fixed upon McKenna's assistant.
The assistant was also common, but he had a little veil of
unfamiliarity, and Mrs. McKenna was the only woman within three
days.  I do not say that, given the conditions, the thing that
happened would not have happened without the hoodoo, but it served
to take McKenna's mind off the mine, and the hoodoo cut in between.
After a while the two went out of the story by way of the Mojave
stage, and McKenna, leaving the mine in charge of Jordan, whom he
had promoted from his foreman's job to be superintendent, was
supposed to have gone in search of his wife.  Whether he found her,
or if the hoodoo stayed by him in the place where he had gone,
nobody ever heard.  I think myself that it inheres where it was
bred, in the hollow of the comfortless, thick hills.  He was,
however, bound to lose the mine in some such case as he had got it.
</p><p>Jordan was the man McKenna had to help him when he ripped up
the smelter; he knew exactly how the Minnietta came into his
employer's hands, and thought well of it.  In every mining-camp
there are men incurably unable to be taught by the logic of events.
McKenna was certain not to come near the mine again; might
reasonably wish to be quit of it.  This he might have done
profitably, except for the hoodoo, for the grade of ore was
increasingly rich.  Jordan, as a practical miner, was much about
the tunnel, and being left to himself too much, had time for
thought, and, as I have said, he was the sort of man who admired
the sort of thing McKenna had done.  Along in the early summer the
direction of the work in the main gallery was altered at never so
slight an angle, and in due course of time was boarded over.
</p><p>Jordan reported to McKenna that, as the main lead appeared to
be nearly worked out, it would be better to put the mine on the
market before the fact became generally known.  Eventually this was
done.  The selling price was not large, but considering what
McKenna thought he knew of the property, and what the purchasers,
tipped by Jordan, did know, it was satisfactory to both parties.
In some unexplained way the Minnietta came shortly into the hands
of the foreman, Dan Jordan, who ripped up the siding, and uncovered
a body of high-grade ore.
</p><p>The Minnietta is a nearly horizontal vein in a crumbling
country rock that necessitates timbering and an elaborate system of
props and siding.  The new <pb n="453"/>  owner had all the petty,
fiddling ways of a man accustomed to days' wages.  He bought
second-hand timbers from abandoned mines, and took unnecessary
risks in the matter of siding, and the men grumbled.
</p><p>Jordan did not get on well with his men; he gave himself airs,
and suspected an attempt to cry down his new dignities.  He was
swollen and sullen with the pride of his prosperity.  By this time
the conviction of the hoodoo was well abroad in that country, and
men were few and fearful who could be hired to work in the
Minnietta.  When there was a good twenty thousand on the dump the
men refused to go into the tunnel again until certain things were
remedied.  Jordan, who did not believe in it, cursed the hoodoo,
cursed the hands, and went down into the tunnel, trailing abuse
behind him for the men who followed timorously far at his back.
</p><p>"Better keep this side the cut, sir," said one of them,
respectfully enough.  "Them props ain't no ways safe."  Jordan
kicked the prop scornfully for answer, and when the men, starting
back from the sound of falling, dared to approach him, they found
him quite dead, his skull crushed and buried under the crumbling
rock.
</p><p>After that the Minnietta passed in due course to Jordan's
heirs, two families of cousins who knew nothing of silver mines
except that they were supposed to be eminently desirable.
</p><p>Now, as they had come into the property through no fault of
theirs, if the hoodoo were nothing more than the logical tendency
of evil-doing to draw to and consume the evil-doer, they should
have been beyond its reach.  This would have been the case if, as
you suppose, the hoodoo were a myth begotten of a series of
fortuitous events.  But you, between the church and the police,
whose every emanation of the soul is shred to tatters by the
yammering of kin and neighbor, what do you know of the great,
silent spaces across which the voice of law and opinion reaches as
small as the rustle of blown sand?  There the castings of a man's
soul lie still in whatever shape of hate and rage he threw them
from him.
</p><p>There are places in Lost Valley where, in the early fifties,
emigrant trains went through&mdash;places so void of wind and jostling
weather that the wheel-tracks still lie upon the sand, clear from
that single passing; other places where, as at the Minnietta, the
rock of men's passions lies in the hollow desertness like an
infection, as if every timber had absorbed mischief instead of
moisture, and every bolt gives it off in lieu of rust.
</p><p>If it were not so, there is no reason why the heirs of Dan
Jordan should have gone to law about it while the price of silver
went down and down.  They stripped themselves in litigation while
the timbers sagged in the tunnel and the cuts choked with rubble.
The ore on the dump, by no means worth twenty thousand by this
time, went to a lawyer who had been a very decent sort until he
became dissolute through prosperity and neglected his family.  The
battens of the mill, warped through successive summers, fell off,
and the boards shrunk from one another and curled at the edges like
the lips of men dead and sun-dried in the desert.  And the two
cousins, who were once very good friends, do not speak.  And if
they should come together, or the price of silver go up, say, three
points, I do not know, unless they are able to charge the
enterprise with some counter passion of nobility to sacrifice, how
they will escape the hoodoo of the Minnietta.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
