<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AusSong"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="AusSong">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Song-Makers</title>
<title type="sort">song makers</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">22</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AusSong</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475718</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Song-Makers</title>
<title type="sort">song makers</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Edited by</resp>
<name>editor</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<date value="1911-08">Aug. 1911</date>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Verification made against printed text</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1911">1911</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head>                   "THE SONG-MAKERS"<lb/>
                     BY MARY AUSTIN<lb/>
(Aug. 1911): 239-247. </head>

<pb n="239"/>

<p>THE talk had been going on for nearly an hour without
affording me an occasion for saying anything, which was exceedingly
tiresome.
</p><p>"The fact is," said the Professor, and the rest of the company
agreed with him, "that the only place you can hear Wagner as he
should be, is at Bayreuth."  The pines outside quivered at this
announcement, and a blear old sea fog came and peered through the
panes at us.  Suddenly the fire-log snapped asunder.
</p><p>The red glow leaped into a three-inch point of flame.
Instantly the fog caught it by reflection a rod outside and made of
it a desert camp-fire spiring upward from the crossed ends of the
back log.  Dark against it by some superior sort of refraction from
my mind I could see the dreaming face of my friend Tinnemaha, the
Medicine-man.
</p><p>What I thought the Professor had said was that the only place
nowadays where you could see any genuine song-dancing is in
Shoshone Land, and, out of the velvet desert dark beyond, Kern
River Jim answered him.
</p><p>"But in the old days," said he, "right here in Sagharanite
there was a Chisera who could sing the wind up out of the west with
the rains behind it; and she could sing the rain away, too, when
she had done with it; and you could no more be still when you heard
her than the wind could, but you must get upon your feet and dance
what she sang."
</p><p>"In Shoshone Land," said Tinnemaha, "I remember a man who
could dance the heart out of your bosom.  He made a rattle of ram's
horn stopped with a round of mescal stem, and would keep time with
it.  He taught me to dance some of his songs for a bag of taboose,
but I could never match with him, for the best of his singing was
that he made it new for every occasion." <pb n="240"/>
</p><p>What the Professor was actually saying at that moment was that
Wagner's intellectuality made it improbable that the French should
ever be able to interpret him, but I went on listening to
Tinnemaha, for, besides being much the same sort of talk, it was
vastly more interesting.
</p><p>"Nowadays in the schools," said he, "they teach our children
white men's songs, but they do not lay hold on your insides as the
old songs do.  White man's songs, they talk too much."  He dropped
out of his native speech into the clipped English in which he
courteously held any criticism of white men's ways should be
couched.  "What man sings too much with his mouth," said he, "but
Shoshone sings here"&mdash;he extended his hand across his body, palm
inward, with that most expressive gesture of the Indian to include
the whole region of the solar plexus, the seat of the Inside Man
who sings and is sung to&mdash;"here."  The hand moved outward, slightly
clutching at the strings of sympathy.T
dancin'; he cryin' while he singin'.  'Tain't the words that make
him cry.  I'ss what he thinkin' 'bout when he sing."
</p><p>"Last night," said Kern River Jim, "I dreamed that I sang, and
when I awoke I was crying, but my song had gone from me."
</p><p>"It was the wolf-song," said Tinnemaha; and we were quiet
while the flames lapped and flickered, musing on what I have told
you in another place, how there was a man who, when the people met
together, had no song and greatly desired one and was unhappy over
it.  Then one day he bought a song from the wolf for a basket of
tule roots and sang it amid the tribe that night until the earth
under him was beaten to a fine dust and he fell into the deep
trance which waits beyond the last ecstasy of song.
</p><p>So the wolf came in the night and stole his song away.  I
remembered me of an equally old tale of a Saxon singer, and I
thought, Beast-god or Man-god, the myth told quite as much as I had
been able to fathom for myself of the source of all songs, dropping
into the mind spread to receive them, quietly as the shed ashes of
the fire.
</p><p>"But all your songs," I wished to know, "do they come so from
inside you?"
</p><p>"Every man's own song," they averred, "the one he makes for
himself, and no one dares sing without his per-<pb n="241"/> mission.  But
sometimes when it is a very good song he bequeaths it to his
friend, and the tribe uses it; other times a man's song is so
precious that no one gets to know very well what it is about, and
it dies with him."
</p><p>"And when does a man make a song?"
</p><p>"How can I tell?" questioned Tinnemaha.  "It is when his
Inside Man is raised up within him.  Perhaps when he has killed his
first buck or made a woman to know that he is man.  When his son is
born or his enemy is slain.  Who knows his great moment?"
</p><p>"There was one I knew," said Kern River Jim, "who made a song
when he was drunk.  Three days he had herded the Bar-N cattle up
Tunawai in a sand-storm, scarcely eating or sleeping while the
storm lasted, and when it was done the foreman gave him as much
whiskey as he liked, and when he was well drunken he made a song."
Jim's eyes twinkled.  "It was a good song."
</p><p>I remembered to have heard that air, the most lugubrious
Indian melody I had known, and thought I should have felt just that
way if I had been thoroughly intoxicated, but Jim esteemed it
humorous.
</p><p>We fell a-talking then of the songs that are not personal, but
come down to the people from old times: cradle-songs, love-songs,
songs for the beginning and the end of journeys.
</p><p>Tinnemaha stood up and began to sing one of Victory:

</p><p>                   "Ha . . . ah&mdash;a,
</p><p>                    Ha . . . ah&mdash;a!"

A sharp, throaty noise, as if the Inside Man had waked and fed on
what he relished:

</p><p>                    "Ha . . . ah-a!"

while the Medicine-man stamped and swayed:

</p><p>                "Come, O ye buzzards,
</p><p>                 The feast is prepared!
</p><p>                 Ha . . . ah!"

until I could fairly hear the sweep of their wide wings between the
naked dead and naked heaven.
</p><p>"My father saw that song made when he was a young man and we
fought the Mojaves.  We had killed the best of their fighting men
and taken away their weapons, for they had long arrows that
entangled in the brush so that they could not shoot so fast as our
men with the shorter shafts. <pb n="242"/>  The dead were beginning to
swell, and one of our men danced among them and made a song.
</p><p>"Then one and another of ours took it from him, and all the
way home they danced it until the women heard them returning on the
trails.  So the song came to the Shoshones."
</p><p>"And do you always dance when you sing?"
</p><p>"How else should it be?" said Tinnemaha, with mild amazement.
</p><p>"First," said he, "the song <hi rend="italic">is</hi>, then there are three
things&mdash;the dance and the music&mdash;

</p><p>                    "Ha . . . ah&mdash;a!"

</p><p>The muscles of his chest rippled under the thin cotton shirt,
the throaty syllables gurgled out of him as though jarred by the
rhythm of his dancing.  "And then," he finished, "there are the
words.  Sometimes the words are very old and are forgotten, and the
people make new words, but it is not a new song because of that.
The song is behind them."
</p><p>It flashed upon me inwardly as accounting for the
accompaniment of meaningless syllables that ran along with much of
their tribal ceremonial, swelling with the movement of the ritual
into even billows of song with just a sentence or two like a riffle
of foam on the crest of each; the song behind the song singing
itself out of all their memories and knowledges.
</p><p>"Give me that song again which you danced for me at the
beginning of wild almond bloom," I begged, beating with my hands a
sketch of the body rhythm that accompanied it.

</p><p>             "The grass is on the mountain,"

crooned Kern River Jim.  "It is a very old song of the Paiutes."
</p><p>And the song behind it?" I urged.

</p><p>     "'Oh, a long time
</p><p>       The snow is over all the mountain.
</p><p>        The deer have come down and the big-horn,
</p><p>       They have passed over Waban.
</p><p>       A long time now we have eaten seeds
</p><p>       And dried flesh of the summer's killing,
</p><p>       We are wearied of our huts.
</p><p>       The mists have come down like a tent,
</p><p>       They have hid the mountain.
</p><p>       And on a day suddenly comes the sun.
</p><p>       The mists are withered away,
</p><p>       The grass is seen on the mountain!" <pb n="243"/>

</p><p>"Therefore," said Jim, "we make a dance and go to the meadow
to look for taboose and the young shoots of the tule.
</p><p>"Also," said he, "I remember a song a woman made to me on Kern
River.  I had come to it late in the evening and found it big with
rains.  The woman had a wickiup on the other side and went about
her fire to tend the cakes; I called across to her, but I did not
attempt the river because of the flood, and I saw that the woman
was alone and no man came to her.  By and by when it was dark she
piled pitchy boughs on the fire till it leaped up and showed the
straight high pines and the river between us like a thick, hurrying
snake.  Then she made a song and I heard it above the water.  So I
went into the river as I was, and the woman pulled me out half dead
on the other side.  But I did not mind it because of the song."
</p><p>"And the song was?"
</p><p>"The fire burns," quoted Jim.  "It leaps up and nobody is
warmed by it.  Though it was a very long time ago, I have never
forgotten it."  I did not ask him for the song behind that. . . .
</p><p>Once when I had tried to persuade Poco Bill to render a love-song he had refused on the ground that "white men don't like those
kind of words.  Thass all right song for Paiute, but with white man
those words mean bad."  Later when one of the women translated the
song for me I felt how immeasurably we had dropped behind the
Indian in having no words with which to communicate the issues of
life except such as "mean bad."
</p><p>"But still," I insisted, "I do not understand why you must
dance.  We also have many songs, but we do not dance to them."
</p><p>Something drifted down to me just then from the talk going on
over my head to remind me that when the white man sings best and
most expensively he comes as near dancing as is compatible with the
utmost breath: feet of innumerable choruses twinkled across my
memory, but I didn't exactly see my way to explain that to the
Medicine-man.  I had heard a great deal that evening of how a
certain cantatrice had waved her arms and swung her magnificent
torso in the part of Lucia; there was not a whisper of why.  I had
seen the bucks in the beginning of October pawing up the earth in
deep ravines, pawing and tossing their branched foreheads with a
slow, majestic rhythm, and once at Buena <pb n="244"/>  Vista, where the
slough fell over the ruined drop into the vast reedy lagoon, long
since drained away to profitable fields, there in the middle of the
hot morning mist I had seen the dipping of the pelicans to their
mates, the strange wing-bowing, the retreats and advances of tall
water-birds, with the white expanse of wing feather against the
fawn-colored land, most like the extended arms and floating
draperies that flee forever about the red ground of an Etruscan
vase.  I had seen these and divers wonders that, with due respect
to Mr. Darwin, I didn't altogether accept as the procreant urge of
the world.
</p><p>That was a good theory as far as it went, but it failed to
explain the dance of the Grass on the Mountain, nor why the tenor
felt obliged to declare his undying opposition to the basso with
both arms at length in the direction of his chest expansion.
</p><p>At any rate, it would be interesting to know what the
Medicine-man said of it.  He said it very much to the point.
</p><p>"We dance always," said he.  "It is the shortest road to the
Friend of the Soul of Man."
</p><p>I had heard more or less of this Friend among all the Indians
I had known or known about, under various names: Great Spirit, The
Mystery, The Power, The Trues, God or Holy Ghost.  It has nothing
to do with their ordinary spirits or supernaturals, has no
appearance and no history.  It is the supreme intelligence,
perhaps, that plane of consciousness touched in great crises along
which runs from mind to mind communicating fire.  Through it cures
are affected and messages transmitted from the dead.
</p><p>"By dancing," said the Medicine-man, "the Inside Man erects
itself, it is lifted up, it lays hold on the Friend; then singing
comes, and many things are possible that were not."
</p><p>"What things?"
</p><p>Tinnemaha considered.  "Do you know Mahala Joe?"
</p><p>"Who was condemned to wear a woman's dress because he once ran
away from battle?"
</p><p>"He was scarcely grown and it was his first fight," said the
Medicine-man, excusingly.  "But it is not an easy thing to appear
as a woman in the face of men, and Joe has told me often that
unless he had danced greatly, until the Friend knew him for a very
man, he could not have continued in it."
</p><p>"It was he," continued Jim, "who danced the fear out of our
minds during the great sickness." <pb n="245"/>
</p><p>This was an epidemic of pneumonia which decimated the
campodies a few years back, and Tinnemaha nearly lost his life in
it, according to the Paiute law, because his own dancing failed to
check the progress of the disorder.
</p><p>"That," he acknowledged, "was because there was no fear in the
mind of Mahala Joe.  But it is true that by dancing much for one's
self the power grows.  There was Carson Charlie.  His father had
been shot by a Washoe in a very old quarrel, and Charlie should
have killed the killer, but he had been to Carson to school where
they showed him the Jesus road and he was soft-hearted.  Then I
took him apart in the hills, for his father was my friend and it is
not right that the son should grow fat while the killer of his
father is abroad.  Three days we danced and sang together, and it
was not easy for Charlie, he had been to school so long; but I
taught him our ancient dances.  Three days I strove with him,
fasting, and in the end he found the Friend."
</p><p>"And&mdash;?" I queried&mdash;the flicker of a smile played on the face
of Tinnemaha&mdash;"and he was also not so soft-hearted."
</p><p>He took up my thought and carried it on beyond the personal
instance.  "It is so," he said; "by dancing power comes to medicine
the souls of men."
</p><p>"And the bodies?"  But, in fact, he had no phrases to signify
the partition of man into physical and spiritual which is the graft
of theology on an unscientific observation of life.
</p><p>What he really believed was that if the Inside Man was
invulnerable, as he might be made by Good Medicine, to assault of
weapon or disease, so would his outside be.  I had seen a Shoshone
Medicine-dancer cure an abscess on the lungs by this method, and a
Methodist Evangelist brings souls to healing by singing of hymns
and pounding the pulpit, and found the processes not entirely
dissimilar, but it hadn't occurred to me until now to attempt the
valuation of literature and art on the same basis.  O Dante!  O
Bach!  The shortest road to the Friend of the Soul of Man!
</p><p>I explained to Tinnemaha that we had songs and other matters
of our own with which merely to be confronted was to be shot upward
into the plane of power, but we hadn't been able, except in rare
instances, to manage it with our dances.
</p><p>"That," said the Medicine-man, "is because you do not dance to
yourselves."  He went on to say that once when he <pb n="246"/>  had been
to Reno, in the matter of the Washoe Boundary Dispute, he had seen
some dancing-women at a theater, and he was quite explicit as to
the effect upon his outside.  But when a man danced to himself and
the Friend, it was otherwise.  He thought it was reasonable, the
Inside Man being so entangled with the body that when it began to
move itself aright the body would respond first, and when, by free
motion the spirit ascended, then the song came and visions and
healing.
</p><p>"It is so," he explained, "that it is more fortunate to die in
battle.  For if a man dies before disease has eaten him, he can the
better make his song." . . .  It had taken, of course, much more
explanation than this, on divers occasions, for me to understand
that death to an Indian is no such catastrophe as we modernly
conceive it; rather an incident which even their gods and Great
Ones are liable to suffer, but it needed no further touch just then
to have me see in all manner of dying rites, death songs, battle
cries, extreme unction, a vine of the spirit climbing till it laid
hold on the Friend and sustained itself in the swelling of Jordan.
I knew without doubt where I should go if I died immediately upon
reading:
</p>
<lg type="verse">
<l>"I was with Hercules and Cadmus once</l>
<l>When in the woods of Crete they bayed the bear."</l></lg>

<p>Good Medicine!  There I had the whole business of song-makers;
painted songs, printed songs, or whatever; not to preach, not to
please merely, but to make a short road to the mood of power, to
touch the Friend.  But you had by Tinnemaha's account to touch him
yourself first, to swing up by the skirts of the Great Moment and
to let down a hand to stumbling men.
</p><p>The fire snapped and went out; the two ends of the back log
burned so far asunder that unless you had seen the live flame at
work on them you couldn't have told that they belonged together any
more than the two ends of the conversations&mdash;mine with the
Medicine-man, and the talk within the room, which had by this time
fallen off into that reminiscent exchange of dates and places, as
to when you last heard Melba or where you saw the portrait of
Whistler's mother, which many estimable folk pursue determinedly
under the fond imagination that they are talking Art.
</p><p>As the company rose for breaking up I stood up with <pb n="247"/>
them, and it occurred to somebody to inquire why I hadn't said
anything for quite an hour.
</p><p>"I was thinking," I said by way of reply, "that I should like
to write a song like this."
</p><p>I swung my arms out, palms upward, the chest raised, the body
slightly swaying forward, saluting the six Quarters, as I had seen
the Medicine-man in the business of the cure of souls, and the
company, especially the younger portion of it, looked at me
commiseratingly.  They understood that it was not my fault that I
hadn't at that time had the advantage of the Metropolitan Museum
and Covent Garden, and they meant, of course, to be kind.  I could
see the Professor, visibly in the interest of hospitality, hold
back a disposition to lecture me.  But they do not know even yet
why I didn't particularly mind it.
</p><p>                              MARY AUSTIN.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
