<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AusWalk"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="AusWalk">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Walking Woman</title>
<title type="sort">walking woman</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">20</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AusWalk</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475721</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Walking Woman</title>
<title type="sort">walking woman</title>
<author>Mary Austin</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<date value="1907">1907</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>100</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>"The Walking Woman."  <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 100 (1907): 216-220.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1907">1907</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction ; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-08">August 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header; Tagged with TEI2-compatible SGML; parsed against "teilite"
dtd</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<pb n="216"/>
<head>                         THE WALKING WOMAN
<lb/>
                          BY MARY AUSTIN
</head>
<p>THE first time of my hearing of her was at Temblor.  We had
come all one day between blunt whitish bluffs rising from mirage
water, with a thick pale wake of dust billowing from the wheels,
all the dead wall of the foothills sliding and shimmering with
heat, to learn that the Walking Woman had passed us somewhere in
the dizzying dimness, going down to the Tulares on her own feet.
We heard of her again in the Carrisal, and again at Adobe Station,
where she had passed a week before the shearing, and at last I had
a glimpse of her at the Eighteen-Mile House as I went hurriedly
northward on the Mojave stage; and afterward sheepherders at whose
camps she slept, and cowboys at rodeos, told me as much of her way
of life as they could understand.  Like enough they told her as
much of mine.  That was very little.  She was the Walking Woman,
and no one knew her name, but because she was a sort of whom men
speak respectfully, they called her to her face, Mrs. Walker, and
she answered to it if she was so inclined.  She came and went about
our western world on no discoverable errand, and whether she had
some place of refuge where she lay by in the interim, or whether
between her seldom, unaccountable appearances in our quarter she
went on steadily walking, was never learned.  She came and went,
oftenest in a kind of muse of travel which the untrammeled space
begets, or at rare intervals flooding wondrously with talk, never
of herself, but of things she had known and seen.  She must have
seen some rare happenings too&mdash;by report.  She was at Maverick the
time of the Big Snow, and at Tres Pinos when they brought home the
body of Morena; and if anybody could have told whether de Borba
killed Mariana for spite or defense, it would have been she, only
she could not be found when most wanted.  She was at Tunawai at the
time of the cloud-burst, and if she had cared for it could have
known most desirable things of the ways of trail-making, burrow-habiting small things.
</p><p>All of which should have made her worth meeting, though it was
not, in fact, for such things I was wishful to meet her; and as it
turned out, it was not of these things we talked when at last we
came together.  For one thing, she was a woman, not old, who had
gone about alone in a country where the number of women is as one
in fifteen.  She had eaten and slept at the herders' camps, and
laid by for days at one-man stations whose masters had no other
touch of human kind than the passing of chance prospectors or the
halting of the tri-weekly stage.  She had been set on her way by
teamsters who lifted her out of white, hot desertness and put her
down at the crossing of unnamed ways, days distant from anywhere.
And through all this she passed unarmed and unoffended.  I had the
best testimony to this, the witness of the men themselves.  I think
they talked of it because they were so much surprised at it.  It
was not, on the whole, what they expected of themselves.
</p><p>Well I understand that nature which wastes its borders with
too eager burning, beyond which rim of desolation it flares forever
quick and white, and have had some inkling of the isolating calm of
a desire too high to stoop to satisfaction.  But you could not
think of these things pertaining to the Walking Woman, and if there
were ever any truth in the exemption from offense residing in a
frame of behavior called ladylike, it should have been inoperative
here.  What this <pb n="217"/>  really means is that you get no affront so
long as your behavior in the estimate of the particular audience
invites none.  In the estimate of the immediate audience&mdash;conduct
which affords protection in Mayfair gets you no consideration in
Maverick.  And by no canon could it be considered ladylike to go
about on your own feet, with a blanket and a black bag and almost
no money in your purse, in and about the haunts of rude and
solitary men.
</p><p>There were other things that pointed the wish for a personal
encounter with the Walking Woman.  One of them was the
contradictious reports of her, as to whether she was comely, for
example.  Report said yes, and again, plain to the point of
deformity.  She had a twist to her face, some said; a hitch to one
shoulder; they averred she limped as she walked.  But by the
distance she covered she should have been straight and young.  As
to sanity, equal incertitude.  On the mere evidence of her way of
life she was cracked, not quite broken, but unserviceable.  Yet in
her talk there was both wisdom and information, and the word she
brought about trails and waterholes was as reliable as an Indian's.
</p><p>By her own account she had begun by walking off an illness.
There had been an invalid to be taken care of for years, leaving
her at last broken in body, and with no recourse but her own feet
to carry her out of that predicament.  It seemed there had been,
besides the death of her invalid, some other worrying affairs, upon
which, and the nature of her illness, she was never quite clear, so
that it might very well have been an unsoundness of mind which
drove her to the open, sobered and healed at last by the large
soundness of nature.  It must have been about that time that she
lost her name.  I am convinced that she never told it because she
did not know it herself.  She was the Walking Woman, and the
country people called her Mrs. Walker.  At the time I knew her,
though she wore short hair and a man's boots and had a fine down
over all her face from exposure to the weather, she was perfectly
sweet and sane.
</p><p>I had met her occasionally at ranch houses and road stations,
and had got as much acquaintance as the place allowed; but for the
things I wished to know there wanted a time of leisure and
isolation.  And when the occasion came we talked altogether of
other things.
</p><p>It was at Warm Spring in the Little Antelope I came upon her
in the heart of a clear forenoon.  The spring lies off a mile from
the main trail and has the only trees about it known in that
country.  First you come upon a pool of waste full of weeds of a
poisonous dark green, every reed ringed about the water level with
a muddy white incrustation.  Then the three oaks appear staggering
on the slope, and the spring sobs and blubbers below them in ashy-colored mud.  All the hills of that country have the down plunge
toward the desert and back abruptly toward the Sierra.  The grass
is thick and brittle and bleached straw-color toward the end of the
season.  As I rode up the swale of the spring I saw the Walking
Woman sitting where the grass was deepest, with her black bag and
blanket, which she carried on a stick, beside her.  It was one of
those days when the genius of talk flows as smoothly as the rivers
of mirage through the blue hot desert morning.
</p><p>You are not to suppose that in my report of a Borderer I give
you the words only, but the full meaning of the speech.  Very often
the words are merely the punctuation of thought, rather the crests
of the long waves of intercommunicative silences.  Yet the speech
of the Walking Woman was fuller than most.
</p><p>The best of our talk that day began in some dropped word of
hers from which I inferred that she had had a child.  I was
surprised at that, and then wondered why I should have been
surprised, for it is the most natural of all experiences to have
children.  I said something of that purport, and also that it was
one of <pb n="218"/>  the perquisites of living I should be least willing
to do without.  And that led to the Walking Woman saying that there
were three things which if you had known, you could cut out all the
rest, and they were good any way you got them, but best if, as in
her case, they were related to and grew each one out of the others.
It was while she talked that I decided that she really did have a
twist to her face, a sort of natural warp or skew into which it
fell when it was worn merely as a countenance, but which
disappeared the moment it became the vehicle of thought or feeling.
</p><p>The first of the experiences the Walking Woman had found most
worth while had come to her in a sand storm on the south slope of
Tehachapi in a dateless spring.  I judged it should have been about
the time she began to find herself, after the period of worry and
loss in which her wandering began.  She had come, in a day pricked
full of intimations of a storm, to the camp of Filon Geraud, whose
companion shepherd had gone a three days' passear to Mojave for
supplies.  Geraud was of great hardihood, red-blooded, of a full
laughing eye and an indubitable spark for women.  It was the season
of the year when there is a soft bloom on the days, but the nights
are cowering cold and the lambs tender, not yet flockwise.  At such
times a sand storm works incalculable disaster.  The lift of the
wind is so great that the whole surface of the ground appears to
travel upon it slantwise, thinning out miles high in air.  In the
intolerable smother the lambs are lost from the ewes; neither dogs
nor man make headway against it.
</p><p>The morning flared through a horizon of yellow smudge, and by
mid-forenoon the flock broke.
</p><p>"There were but the two of us to deal with the trouble," said
the Walking Woman.  "Until that time I had not known how strong I
was nor how good it is to run when running is worth while.  The
flock traveled down the wind, the sand bit our faces; we called,
and after a time heard the words broken and beaten small by the
wind.  But after a little we had not to call.  All the time of our
running in the yellow dusk of day and the black dark of night, I
knew where Filon was.  A flock-length away, I knew him.  Feel?
What should I feel?  I knew.  I ran with the flock and turned it
this way and that as Filon would have.
</p><p>"Such was the force of the wind that when we came together we
held by one another and talked a little between pantings.  We
snatched and ate what we could as we ran.  All that day and night
until the next afternoon the camp kit was not out of the cayaques.
But we held the flock.  We herded them under a butte when the wind
fell off a little, and the lambs sucked; when the storm rose they
broke, but we kept upon their track and brought them together
again.  At night the wind quieted and we slept by turns, at least
Filon slept.  I lay on the ground when my turn was, tired and beat
with the storm.  I was no more tired than the earth was.  The sand
filled in the creases of the blanket, and where I turned, dripped
back upon the ground.  But we saved the sheep.  Some ewes there
were that would not give down their milk because of the worry of
the storm, and the lambs died.  But we kept the flocks together.
And I was not tired."
</p><p>The Walking Woman stretched out her arms and clasped herself,
rocking in them as if she would have hugged the recollection to her
breast.
</p><p>"For you see," said she, "I worked with a man, without
excusing, without any burden of me of looking or seeming.  Not
fiddling or fumbling as women work, and hoping it will all turn out
for the best.  It was not for Filon to ask, Can you, or Will you.
He said, Do, and I did.  And my work was good.  We held the flock.
And that," said the Walking Woman, the twist coming in her face
again, "is one of the things that make you able to do without the
others." <pb n="219"/>
</p><p>"Yes," I said; and then, "What others?"
</p><p>"Oh," she said as if it pricked her, "the looking and the
seeming."
</p><p>And I had not thought until that time that one who had the
courage to be the Walking Woman would have cared!  We sat and
looked at the pattern of the thick crushed grass on the slope,
wavering in the fierce noon like the waterings in the coat of a
tranquil beast; the ache of a world-old bitterness sobbed and
whispered in the spring.  At last,&mdash;
</p><p>"It is by the looking and the seeming," said I, "that the
opportunity finds you out."
</p><p>"Filon found out," said the Walking Woman.  She smiled; and
went on from that to tell me how, when the wind went down about
four o'clock and left the afternoon clear and tender, the flock
began to feed, and they had out the kit from the cayaques, and
cooked a meal.  When it was over, and Filon had his pipe between
his teeth, he came over from his side of the fire, of his own
notion, and stretched himself on the ground beside her.  Of his own
notion.  There was that in the way she said it that made it seem as
if nothing of the sort had happened before to the Walking Woman,
and for a moment I thought she was about to tell me one of the
things I wished to know; but she went on to say what Filon had said
to her of her work with the flock.  Obvious, kindly things, such as
any man in sheer decency would have said, so that there must have
something more gone with the words to make them so treasured of the
Walking Woman.
</p><p>"We were very comfortable," said she, "and not so tired as we
expected to be.  Filon leaned upon his elbow.  I had not noticed
until then how broad he was in the shoulders and how strong in the
arms.  And we had saved the flock together.  We felt that.  There
was something that said together, in the slope of his shoulders
toward me.  It was around his mouth and on the cheek high up under
the shine of his eyes.  And under the shine the look&mdash;the look that
said, 'We are of one sort and one mind'&mdash;his eyes that were the
color of the flat water in the toulares&mdash;do you know the look?"
</p><p>"I know it."
</p><p>"The wind was stopped and all the earth smelt of dust, and
Filon understood very well that what I had done with him I could
not have done so well with another.  And the look&mdash;the look in the
eyes&mdash;"
</p><p>"Ah-ah&mdash;!"
</p><p>I have always said, I will say again, I do not know why at
this point the Walking Woman touched me.  If it were merely a
response to my unconscious throb of sympathy, or the unpremeditated
way of her heart to declare that this, after all, was the best of
all indispensable experiences; or if in some flash of forward
vision, encompassing the unimpassioned years, the stir, the
movement of tenderness were for <hi rend="italic"> me</hi>&mdash;but no; as often as I have
thought of it, I have thought of a different reason, but no
conclusive one, why the Walking Woman should have put out her hand
and laid it on my arm.
</p><p>"To work together, to love together," said the Walking Woman,
withdrawing her hand again; "there you have two of the things; the
other you know."
</p><p>"The mouth at the breast," said I.
</p><p>"The lips and the hands," said the Walking Woman, "The little,
pushing hands and the small cry."  There ensued a pause of fullest
understanding, while the land before us swam in the noon, and a
dove in the oaks behind the spring began to call.  A little red fox
came out of the hills and lapped delicately at the pool.
</p><p>"I stayed with Filon until the fall," said she.  "All that
summer in the Sierras, until it was time to turn south on the
trail.  It was a good time, and longer than he could be expected to
have loved one like me.  And besides, I was no longer able to keep
the trail.  My baby was born in October."
</p><p>Whatever more there was to say to <pb n="220"/>  this, the Walking
Woman's hand said it, straying with remembering gesture to her
breast.  There are so many ways of loving and working, but only one
way of the first-born.  She added after an interval, that she did
not know if she would have given up her walking to keep at home and
tend him, or whether the thought of her son's small feet running
beside her in the trails would have driven her to the open again.
The baby had not stayed long enough for that.  "And whenever the
wind blows in the night," said the Walking Woman, "I wake and
wonder if he is well covered."
</p><p>She took up her black bag and her blanket; there was the ranch
house of Dos Palos to be made before night, and she went as
outliers do, without a hope expressed of another meeting and no
word of good-by.  She was the Walking Woman.  That was it.  She had
walked off all sense of society-made values, and, knowing the best
when the best came to her, was able to take it.  Work,&mdash;as I
believed; love,&mdash;as the Walking Woman had proved it; a child,&mdash;as
you subscribe to it.  But look you: it was the naked thing the
Walking Woman grasped, not dressed and tricked out, for instance,
by prejudices in favor of certain occupations; and love, man love,
taken as it came, not picked over and rejected if it carried no
obligation of permanency; and a child; <hi rend="italic"> any</hi> way you get it, a
child is good to have, say nature and the Walking Woman; to have it
and not to wait upon a proper concurrence of so many decorations
that the event may not come at all.
</p><p>At least one of us is wrong.  To work and to love and to bear
children.  <hi rend="italic"> That</hi> sounds easy enough.  But the way we live
establishes so many things of much more importance.
</p><p>Far down the dim, hot valley I could see the Walking Woman
with her blanket and black bag over her shoulder.  She had a queer
sidelong gait, as if in fact she had a twist all through her.
</p><p>Recollecting suddenly that people called her lame, I ran down
to the open place below the spring where she had passed.  There in
the bare, hot sand the track of her two feet bore evenly and white.

</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
