<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AusYear"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="AusYear">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Spring o' the Year</title>
<title type="sort">spring o the year</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">26</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AusYear</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475724</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Spring o' the Year</title>
<title type="sort">spring o the year</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Edited by</resp>
<name>editor</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Century Magazine</publisher>
<date value="1908-04">April 1908</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Vol. 75</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Verification made against printed text</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1908">1908</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="article" id="d3">
<head>Austin, Mary.  "Spring o' the Year."
<lb/>
<hi rend="italic"> Century Magazine</hi> 75 (April 1908): 923-928.
<lb/>
Author of "Isidro"
</head>

<pb n="923"/>

<p>WHEN Don Pedro Ruiz, owner of five hundred fat wethers and two
hundred ewes, was a little bowed in the back and a little frosty
about the temples, a sickness got abroad among his sheep and took
a good half of them.  The next year a bear stampeded the flock
toward a forty-foot barranca over which two hundred pitched to
destruction.  After that Don Pedro went down to La Liebre and hired
out as a herder.  The superintendent thereupon gave him a lamb
band, flock-wise, seasoned ewes, mostly with twin lambs; and
because there was old kindness between him and the superintendent
of La Liebre, and because he had by long usage established a right
to much good pasture in the neighborhood of Wild Rose, Don Pedro
was allowed to take the flock out in his own charge, with a couple
of dogs, and no companion herder except to set him on his way.
</p><p>Being master of his movements, he was able to spend much more
time with his family than falls to the lot of the hired herder.
This was important, for Don Pedro had at that time, besides the
Sen~ora Ruiz, who was fat and comfortable, a daughter grown up as
tall and slim as a moonbeam, with saint's eyes and a mouth as soft
and scarlet as a crumpled pomegranate flower.  She was of
marriageable age and needed a father's care.
</p><p>It was ten flock journeys from La Liebre to the meadow of Wild
Rose, below Tres Pin~os, where Don Pedro had his house, the <hi rend="italic">
ramada</hi> of vines, a long, low two-walled hut, the fig-tree, the
pomegranates, and the scarlet strings of chilis drying in the sun.
That is, it was ten journeys, taken leisurely, when the grass was
rank and the chili-cojote in bloom.  It was barely seven in the
fall of the year, with the feed scant and only one water-hole
between the ranch-house and Wild Rose.  Don Pedro would bring up
the flock from the shearing, by which time the grazing would be in
its prime; here he could feed for six weeks within sight of his own
hearth smoke and candle.
</p><p>Then he swung out desertward to little green oases and can~on
floors that caught the run-off of the quick winter rains for other
six weeks, by which time the meadow of Wild Rose would be grown
again.  Thus the old man had the more leisure for adoring his
daughter of the saint's eyes.
</p><p>He was not so good at that business, however, as Ruy Garcia,
who had, besides a perfect rosary of adoring names for her, a most
remarkably fine voice for singing them, and a very good guitar,
which he brought out from Tres Pin~os twice in the week to strum in
the ramada.  He might have come oftener but that the old Don looked
so sourly upon him, and the eyes of Felicita, misty and tender with
music, had, so Ruy Garcia, who had expressive eyes himself and knew
how to use them, assured himself, no spark in them for Ruy Garcia.
</p><p>When matters were at this pass there came a winter of
extraordinary rains, and Don Pedro contracted rheumatism.  Then,
since it would have been a blasphemy, as Heaven had sent him a
daughter, to wish for a son, he thanked God that, being a daughter,
Felicita was such as she was.  She had been brought up with the
sheep, of course; she had brought up the dogs herself by hand.  If
they served Don Pedro and the flock willingly, judge how they ran
their feet off at the bidding of this tall, slim girl who went at
the rounding-up as if it were a new and merry play invented
expressly to give herd dogs an occasion for being proud of <pb n="924"/>
themselves.  She would be out in the blue-ringed dawn before the
flock had begun to feed, having covered the two or three miles
between them and the house light-footed and laughing.  She set the
flock in motion where the feed was tallest, and by the time old
Pedro crawled aching from his blankets, she would be blowing the
coals under his coffee-pot.  Don Pedro called her Santissima,
Daughter of Saints, Prop of his House, and other names not less
fervent and glowing than those of Ruy Garcia, who had got beyond
name-calling and adored her dumbly, awed and absurdly happy to sit
with her in the idle noons when the flock panted, each with its
head under its neighbor's belly, while old Ruiz slept under the
bitter-brush and the sun marched solemnly like the Host in the
clean, high heaven.  And for his forbearance in the matter of
perfervid declarations, Felicita rewarded him by sending him out
with the dogs to the evening round-up.  Days of wind and lowering
cloud she had the flock all under her hand while the old Don's wife
nursed his pains with hot drinks and flannels.
</p><p>It was reported that Ruy Garcia, when he was told that the
Ruiz girl had turned herd-girl to her father's sheep, spending
whole days in the open a flock journey from home, set spurs to his
horse and never left off galloping until he had found her.  But he
could never win her consent to so much as being seen in her
neighborhood unless Don Pedro was about.  He succeeded so far in
seeing her that when the rain came drumming on the broad leaves of
the mallow, he sent the girl and the old man to the house, and he,
Ruy Garcia, who despised sheep and thought a whole day out of the
saddle misspent, kept the flock alone.  Which proves that he was a
very astute young man or that he really loved her.  Don Pedro
softened much toward young Garcia in those days, and the Sen~ora
Ruiz made him toothsome enchiladas and <hi rend="italic"> chile relleno</hi>.
</p><p>But there were times, and you may be sure the young man never
heard of them, for Felicita was a modest girl and the pride of
Pedro Ruiz was great, when she slept with the flock and warded them
through the night.  She would lie out there on the shadeless,
turtle-backed hills sweeping girdlewise about Wild Rose, and bed
the flock so as always to point the star of her mother's candle in
the window of her home.  Three times when the twilight-fire was
lighted she made it to wink with the flare of burning greasewood,
and in the morning sent smoke, tall and thin, of green sage.  Then
Pedro and his wife would understand that it was well with the
flock, and bless the saints accordingly.  The girl would put on her
father's clothes for the work,&mdash;she was full as tall as he, though
as slender and swaying as a stalk of mariposa,&mdash;and when she had
strapped on an old horse-pistol, had a very pretty swagger that
made her parents laugh with a choke in the throat and a "Santa
Maria, was there ever such a child as ours!"  No, never, Ruy Garcia
could have told them.  The girl came to no harm; indeed, there was
none she could come to in the open wilderness.  But she got a most
glowing color, and her hair blew every way, like tendrils of the
megarrhiza.
</p><p>Don Pedro's ailment did not mend with the winter, and what
with medicines, and the herder's wage being no more than a dollar
a day, with food and tobacco, it seemed less than ever expedient to
hire another man in his place.  Besides, if the flock went down to
the shearing at La Liebre without Ruiz, it was doubtful if ever he
got another to tend.  It was kindness only that won him this&mdash;
kindness and a reputation for skill with lambs; for the band
numbered less than a thousand, and it was cheaper to run three
thousand in a bunch, with two men to handle them.  So when the haze
of spring began to brood over the land, and Pedro Ruiz had taken to
his bed, it began to be also an anxious matter how the flock could
be brought to the shearing.  It would be two weeks going, for Ruiz
was permitted to keep the flock at Wild Rose for lambing, and the
lambs were tender, and ten days returning.  All the way lay through
open desert until the last, when it turned into the pass between
the broad-headed oaks that kept the contours of the hills.
</p><p>Pedro Ruiz and his wife lay awake in their bed far into the
night discussing what was to be done about it; but Felicita on the
hill-slope with the flock, had never but one opinion.  She would go
with the flock herself.
</p><p>"Felicita <hi rend="italic"> mia</hi>," said her father, "you <pb n="925"/>  are the best
of daughters, but the thing is impossible.  Even if you were a boy,
impossible; it is too hard for you."
</p><p>"I will go as a boy," said Felicita.  "Who is there to guess?"
There was that in her father's eyes when he looked at her that said
it would not be hard guessing.
</p><p>"I am as tall as a boy," she said, merrily, "and I think I
have a beard coming," presenting the minute velvet down of her
cheek for inspection.  Then she got down on her knees by his bed
and had her arms around him.  After that old Pedro blessed God for
the gift of a child, and surrendered.
</p><p>When it became necessary to take Ruy Garcia into confidence,
he was scandalized.
</p><p>"It is too hard for you.  It is man's work," he said.
</p><p>Felicita tossed her head.  "But where is the man?"
</p><p>"Felicita!"
</p><p>The girl relented, seeing tears in his eyes.
</p><p>"I know you would do it, Ruy; but we cannot afford to hire
you, and cannot take it as a gift."
</p><p>"But let me go with you, to make sure no harm comes to you,"
he pleaded.
</p><p>"What harm could come?  Would you rob me of my good name?"
</p><p>"Garcia is a good name," said the boy, stoutly, though he
blushed hotly all over to say it.  "I would give it to you if I
might go with you."
</p><p>"No, no, Ruy.  You are kind, but the best you can do is to get
me some clothes.  I cannot go into La Liebre with my father's
things.  Get me some clothes that will look as if they belonged to
me.  I am only a little smaller than you."
</p><p>A very pretty boy she looked when she was properly dressed for
it, but Ruy Garcia had another shock when he found all her lovely
hair must come off.  And with Felicita laughing, Sen~ora Ruiz
snuffing, and old Pedro wiping his eyes in the bed, he dared not so
much as hint at a wish for one of those thick, wavy locks.
</p><p>"Why have you your blankets tied on your saddle, Ruy?" asked
the girl.  The boy kept his eyes on the ground.
</p><p>"I go on a journey&mdash;to Posada.  I have some work there.  I
shall be gone a month or six weeks."
</p><p>"By which time," said Felicita, "I shall be back from La
Liebre.  Come and hear my adventures."
</p><p>The boy looked at her very earnestly and tender-eyed, but with
never a word.
</p><p>A great many unpleasant things might have happened to Felicita
going south with the flock along the foot of the Sierra wall; no
rain fell to distress her, no wind arose to scatter the flock.
Coyotes ringed her sheep with demoniac noises, but got none of the
lambs, and the deadly milkweed did not spring about her trail.  She
saw no dust of other flocks; they had all gone south for the
lambing two months before.  Here and there about the washes were
pleasant splashes of spring.  One would say they had spilled over
the mountain rim from the fulgent San Joaquin.
</p><p>Rising at dawn, when the flock began to feed, Felicita made
her breakfast of coffee and great lumps of bread.  By mid-morning,
when the sheep lay down or dozed upon their feet, huddled in an
open space, she cooked a meal, and took her noon siesta under the
sage.  Then the flock fed, traveling south until moonrise, when the
dogs bedded them, and the girl crept into her blankets with a lump
of bread which she was often too tired to eat; and slept till the
dogs waked her.
</p><p>It was remarkable that the first night out Felicita had been
nervous and wakeful and the dogs had barked; but by the second
night she felt the friendly presence of the wilderness: it pervaded
all her sleep.  Felicita had never heard of any supernatural being
but the saints and the blessed Personages; therefore she
acknowledged their protection in her prayers, like the good girl
she was.
</p><p>At the eighteen-mile house she had dinner with teamsters who
called her "bub," to her great satisfaction.  The next day a
prospector, passing, asked her for the makings of a cigarette.  Ruy
Garcia had provided her for that contingency.  So by no greater
hardship than the responsibility of the lambs involved, and with
growing assurance of her boy's disguise, she came to the ranch-house of La Liebre, among the oaks.  What she should do there had
been agreed upon at home.
</p><p>"Sen~or?"
</p><p>The superintendent of La Liebre looked up from his tally-books
to see a <pb n="926"/>  wondrously slim lad, Raphael-eyed, with a face
burned as dusky red as a pomegranate in the sun, wearing a
shepherd's dress, with two herd dogs at his knees.
</p><p>"I am Pedro Ruiz, son of Pedro Ruiz, whom you know.  I have
brought my father's flock, also a letter."  He took it forthwith
out of his hat, showing a lovely head of rough-cropped, wavy hair.
The letter was a most wordy and moving appeal to the Sen~or
Superintendente to have regard for his past faithfulness and the
excellent condition of the flock, and to return them in the charge
of this, his most dutiful son; and in the meantime to keep the lad
as much as possible under his eye, as he was somewhat ill furnished
for the riot of shearings.
</p><p>"I should think so," thought the superintendent, eying the lad
all over.  Young Pedro blushed the darker, and hung his head.  A
modest lad.
</p><p>"And you brought the flock from Wild Rose yourself?  You are
young for the work."
</p><p>"If you will but look," said the boy.  "They are in good
condition.  One new lamb for every ewe, and over two hundred of
those that had twins."  All this being exactly as the letter had
said, the superintendent approved the lad, had his blankets spread
in the patio, kept him to run between the ranch-house and the
shearing-pens.  By this means young Pedro was able to avoid much
that would have been difficult for a girl to bear; for the shearing
is holiday-time, and wine goes freely about.
</p><p>Pedro Ruiz had not been long a hired herder, and only one of
those who drew in at La Liebre knew much of his affairs.  That was
Jules Giraud, as quizzing and gossipy an old rascal as ever wagged
an unshaven chin.  He came in late from the Sierra pastures, and
was put to help at the sacking-frame.  Here he had a glimpse of the
slender lad who ran at the superintendent's word.
</p><p>"A likely lad," said old Jules, "born to be a breaker of
hearts; Pedro Ruiz, is he," he said, when he had asked, and been
answered, "son of Don Pedro?  Well, I have known the old man these
ten years back, but I have heard of no son.  A daughter he had who
should have been about the age of this one&mdash;"  Giraud broke off to
look long and keenly after the boy.  In the course of a day or two
he made an opportunity to ask after Don Pedro's health, "and the
rest of your brothers and sisters," said Jules.
</p><p>"I am my father's only child," said the boy, carelessly, and
then suddenly blushed a deep, painful red.
</p><p>"Ho, ho!" said old Jules, under his breath.  He kept what he
thought to himself, for next day the parting of the flocks began,
and Jules had already purposed going up along the desert at the
foot of the Sierra wall.
</p><p>Felicita was beyond everything glad to be upon the trail
again.  The hazardous week of the shearing past, the feed abundant,
spring in the air, under foot, in the heart, every day shining as
a jewel, she sang as she walked in the dust of the flock.  The
first day's travel lay through the shallow can~on of oaks, the
evening wound up at the edge of the chaparral.  Other fires winked
at night in the tender twilight-haze; bells of the flocks carried
far in the night.  Felicita had no means of knowing that the
nearest of the fires was of Jules Giraud, and slept, a sense of
friendly presence all about her, as mindlessly as her own sheep.
</p><p>The next day at the noon halt old Jules came up with her.  The
girl scented danger at once, became nervous and anxious-eyed.  The
horse-pistol was in the saddle-bag on the pack-burro that fed
forward with the flock.  She had forgotten there was such a thing
as danger in the world.  Jules was complimentary and insinuating
and sentimental.  He drew close, growing more assured, and enjoying
her torment.  He said of shepherding that it was a lonely life.
One needed a companion now&mdash;for the lovely days, and the nights.
Ah, the nights with the stars like fires!  The knuckles of the
girl's hand grasping the herder's staff were stretched white.
</p><p>"For the trail one needs a companion, assuredly," said Jules,
coming nearer; "for choice, a lovely maid, about your size.  Curse
me, but you have glorious eyes, boy; they go quite through me.
Almost they might be a girl's.  Do you know, if you were a girl,
now, what I would do to you?"  This!"  He was about to snatch a
kiss.  Felicita struck at him fiercely with her staff, and burst
into tears&mdash;and by the act stood confessed a <pb n="927"/>  girl.  Jules
Giraud was rubbing his bruised head, the girl's hands were at her
eyes, therefore neither of them saw quite what happened.  There was
a hurry and scramble of feet, a jet of soft, hissing, hot Spanish
curses, and something whirling through the air that knocked old
Jules flat, and stood over him, flashing and threatening.
</p><p>"Dog of a herder," it said, "shall I send you to the devil at
once or save you to be hanged?"  Jules, though he was half-stunned
with astonishment, thought himself no fool.  A personable and
infuriated young man springing out upon you at the mere snatching
of a kiss from a pretty girl in boy's clothes meant but one thing
to Jules.  He winked feebly as he lay supinely between Ruy Garcia's
feet.
</p><p>"My good fellow, I had no idea the girl was yours.  'Twas no
more than a kiss I wanted."
</p><p>Ruy Garcia left him, and went over to where the girl stood
sobbing.
</p><p>"Are you hurt, Felicita?" he faltered, not so much as daring
to touch her.  Jules sat up and regarded them.
</p><p>"Go ahead, young man," he leered.  "She'll not crack you with
her staff, I'll warrant."
</p><p>"If you say another word, I shall crack your head open," said
Ruy, stoutly.  "I am going to marry her."
</p><p>He looked at Felicita anxiously, to see how she would take
this.  Felicita dried her eyes; whereupon Ruy Garcia put his arm
around her.  He turned to the herder.
</p><p>"She did not know I had come," he said.  "She came because her
father was ill, and I followed to see that she met with no harm.
It is the business of men to protect women, not to molest them."
</p><p>Giraud was a Frenchman, therefore a sentimentalist.  He gave
them a very pretty blessing as he got upon his feet, and took
himself to his own flock, but the young people did not hear him.
There had occurred a miracle.  Felicita trembled; the shock of her
trembling passed to Ruy Garcia; his head swam.  What shining of the
saint's eyes, what glow along the burnt splendor of her cheek
assured him, what tingling of the soft young palms that clung
together, I know not.  Quivering lip strayed to lip.  Ah, a
miracle!
</p><p>Felicita spoke first, withdrawing with gentle dignity.
</p><p>"Ruy, you have done wrongly."
</p><p>"What, to knock over old Jules?" said the boy, aghast.
Felicita's eyes swam with tears.
</p><p>"For that I thank you, and my father will thank you better
when I am home; but in following me you did wrong.  It might have
got me much mistaken."
</p><p>"Did you think I would have let you go alone?  Besides, what
does it matter, if we are going to be married?"  It was impossible
for Felicita to be more rosy and dewy-eyed than she was, but she
held him off gravely.
</p><p>"For that there is the more reason nobody should breathe upon
my name."  It is the surpassing miracle of love that it rises
superior to loving.  Ruy Garcia was made to see that so long as the
girl wandered abroad in boy's guise he must drop back into the
silent, the unrewarded guardian of the trail; and adoring her as
being no lower than the saints save perhaps in the matter of being
kissable, content to have it so.
</p><p>They went up, then, a week's journey toward Wild Rose.  By day
they sighted each other moving dimly in the mist of spring.  By
twilight their fires signaled in the dusk.  By night, lying miles
apart on the sentient earth, they thrilled to each other under the
starry spaces.  Gilias and lupins ran purple under foot; miles of
burnt gold of poppies spread about the knees of the mountain.  The
new-shorn flock went whitely in the midst of rank pasture; bloom of
the sky-blue larkspurs muffled the bells.  They passed the
eighteen-mile house, passed Red Butte, swung out to avoid the
gulches about Coyote Holes, scrambled up the gorge of Black Rock,
sighted the lazy, low-backed hills about Wild Rose.  Day by day the
horse of Ruy Garcia, obeying the heart of his master rather than
the rein, edged toward the flock of Pedro Ruiz.  The last day but
one the two solemn young things went voiceless within hail.  The
last day saw them draw together at the meadow of Wild Rose.
</p><p>There was an excellent excuse of a bunch of surpassing lilies
which Ruy Garcia would give to Felicita.  Such <pb n="928"/>  flowers
bloom on the desert in wet years only.  Felicita took them gravely,
with dropped eyes.  Ruy Garcia walked with his bridle on his arm.
They broke through the thicket of wild almonds, droning with bees
and heavy with perfume.  There was a foot-deep gully here that
Felicita must be helped over.  She had been ten flock journeys to
La Liebre and back, but Ruy Garcia must needs give her his hand
over the gully.
</p><p>They went on thus, hand in hand, until they sighted the roof
under the fig-tree.
</p><p>"Confess," said Ruy Garcia, "that you are glad I came."
</p><p>"For the sake of what happened to Jules Giraud, yes," said
Felicita.
</p><p>"For nothing else?"
</p><p>"What else?"
</p><p>"This."  Ruy Garcia's horse started as if it had heard an
order to move on.
</p><p>"Tell me," said Ruy, with his arm around her&mdash;"in all that two
weeks going, did you not feel me near you, not once?"
</p><p>"Better than that&mdash;I knew it."
</p><p>"Knew it?  But how?"
</p><p>"I guessed it in the beginning, when I saw your blankets tied
behind the saddle, and the woman at the eighteen-mile house told me
you had passed that day.  Besides, I knew&mdash;you would not leave me&mdash;
"
</p><p>"Oh, adorable one!  Felicita <hi rend="italic"> mia!"</hi> said Ruy Garcia.
</p><p>The flock, scenting the home pastures, jangled on hurriedly,
the dogs upon their heels.  The light fell low and struck sidelong
through the hills.  Little white gilias, musky and sweet, came out
underfoot, and white stars overhead.  The flock blethered at the
home corral, and old Pedro Ruiz, hobbling out to let them in, stood
a long time at the bars wondering what had become of Felicita.

</p></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
