<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="BarNegr"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="BarNegr">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">What the Southern Negro is Doing for Himself</title>
<title type="sort">what the southern negro is doing for himself</title>
<author>Barrows, Samuel J.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">42</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">BarNegr</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475727</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">What the Southern Negro is Doing for Himself</title>
<title level="j">Atlantic Monthly</title>
<title type="sort">what the southern negro is doing for himself</title>
<author>Samuel J. Barrows</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
<date value="1891-06">June 1891</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Vol. 67 pp. 805-815</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions
for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the
text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1891-06">June 1891</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>African American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-10">October 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header; Tagged with TEI.2-compatible SGML; Parsed against
teilite.dtd.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="805"/>
<head>  WHAT THE SOUTHERN NEGRO IS DOING FOR HIMSELF. </head>

<p>FOR twenty-six years the Negro has had his freedom, and now the
question is, What use has he made of it?  I have just returned from
an extended trip through the South, arranged and made solely for
the purpose of getting an answer to the question, What is the
colored man doing for himself?  I have traveled through Virginia,
the Carolinas, Georgia, Alabama, Mississippi, Louisiana, returning
through Tennessee, the District of Columbia, and Maryland.  In the
course of this journey, covering 3500 miles, I have visited
schools, colleges, and industrial institutions in most of the large
centres of the South, from Baltimore to New Orleans.  I have gone
through the Black Belt, inspected the agricultural districts,
visited farms and cabins, and have seen every phase of Negro life,
from the destitution of the one-room cabin to the homes of the
comfortable and prosperous, and every degree of social standing,
from the convicts in the chain gang in the New Orleans Parish
prison and the Birmingham mines to ministers, lawyers, doctors, and
bankers on the top round of the social ladder.  As a result of this
observation and experience, I have some interesting evidence as to
what the Negro is doing for himself.
</p><p> Under slavery the Negro was mainly a plantation laborer.
Freedom found him where slavery left him.  While there has been
some transmigration to the South and North, the shifting of
population since the war has not been great.  The Negro and his
descendants remain pretty much in the places where they lived when
the war closed.  Three courses were open to him as a free man:
first, to rent his own labor; secondly, to rent and work the land
of his former master; thirdly, to buy and work a farm for himself.
All these courses have in turn been accepted.  As a simple farm
laborer the Negro has small opportunity to accumulate.  His wages
do not average over fifty or sixty cents a day.  Two tendencies are
observable in the agricultural districts of the South: one is the
exceptional aggregation of immense farms under white ownership,
worked by Negro laborers; the other is the segmentation of the old
plantations into small farms let out to Negro tenants.  In Georgia,
for example, one white farmer owns 20,000 acres of land, and
employs a vast number of Negroes.  But in the districts I have
visited the breaking up of the old plantations into small farms has
been the more common process.  All through the Black Belt and the
adjacent country, plantations have been cut up and rented to
Negroes in "one-mule farms" of from twenty-five to thirty acres
each.  Other things being equal, the step from the position of a
man who simply lets out his own labor to the position of one who
hires a field for its exercise is a step in advance.  It furnishes
conditions which stimulate intelligence, self-interest, and power
of self-help; it is the roadway towards earning a farm and a home.
Great numbers of Negroes have taken this initiative.  But <pb n="806"/>
the transition is not easily made.  Farms are not to be had for the
asking.  The Negro was not a capitalist.  He was without credit,
and his capacity for managing his own affairs was distrusted.  He
has had to contend, and is still contending, with an onerous system
of commercial oppression which keeps him down.  This is the
mortgage system, or the lien on the crop, which prevails very
extensively in the Black Belt.  The colored man who hires twenty-five or thirty acres of land pays at the lowest one bale of cotton,
worth about $50; or sometimes he pays as much as two or two and a
half bales, equivalent to $100 or $125 rent.  When we know that
land can be bought at from five to seven dollars an acre, we see
that the rent in some cases equals half the value of the farm.  If
the Negro raised all his own corn, meat, and vegetables, he would
still be able to make progress, but he is dependent for clothes and
much of his provisions upon the storekeeper.  As he cannot buy with
ready money, he mortgages his crop, paying twenty and twenty-five
per cent, and in exceptional cases one hundred per cent, interest
on the amount of his bill.  It matters not that he does not begin
to draw his goods for three months after the contract is made; he
pays interest just the same on the whole amount from the beginning.
Add to this that the Negro is charged in the first instance three
or four prices for what he buys, and it can easily be seen that
when the crop is all gathered little or nothing of it belongs to
him.  "I go to Pennsylvania," said a colored farmer, "and can buy
sugar for six and a half cents a pound, but in North Carolina it is
eleven cents.  The merchant is making a vast profit."  The colored
race has emerged from civil bondage.  The next step will be to come
out of a bondage which is financial.
</p><p> To know, therefore, what the colored man is doing for himself
we must know the conditions from which he has to rise.  These are
hard enough, but not beyond the capacity of the Negro to break
through them, as is shown in thousands of instances.  Thus in
Virginia and Kentucky and Tennessee the condition of things is much
better than further south, and the colored man, in spite of these
obstacles, is rapidly becoming a farmowner and householder.  "In
North Carolina," said Bishop Moore, "our people are buying land
wherever they can get it."  Land ranges from ten to fifteen dollars
an acre, in some places running as low as eight dollars.  The
bishop himself has a little farm of thirty-three acres, near
Salisbury, that cost thirty-four dollars an acre.  "I am so anxious
to see my race improve," he said, "that I should like to have a
great deal more done, but in view of the small wages we get for
labor we are doing pretty well."  In Tennessee, experts assured me
that the colored people are buying land throughout the country, and
the mortgage system does not prevail extensively.  As we go south
and enter the Black Belt, the conditions vary with the fertility of
the soil, the intelligence of the people, and the degree of
education.  A great difference is sometimes apparent in different
counties in the same State.  Thus in Lee County, Georgia, the
people are largely laborers, working for wages.  But in Marion
County fifty per cent of the people own homes, and some of them
have large plantations.  In Sumter and Terrell counties, they
likewise live mostly on farms.  In the latter county, I was told
that in a small city of 10,000 nearly all the colored people own
their homes, and live in cabins or houses varying in size from one
room to eight.  The same difference is seen in Alabama.  In Russell
County the blacks are much behind those of Pike County, where there
are better schools and more freedom from the mortgage system.  In
Bullock County, much government land has been preempted by the
Negroes.  In one section <pb n="807"/>  of that county the colored people
are prosperous, one man of exceptional thrift owning 300 acres,
twelve good mules, and four horses, and raising his own meat and
potatoes.  In Coffee County, the people are just beginning to rent
their homes.  In Elmore County, many have farms of fifty acres.  In
Macon County, not much land is owned.  In Barbour County, land is
mainly rented, but there are many who have stock.  In the southern
part of Randolph County, about half of the blacks own their land.
In one township of Lee County, nearly all the colored people own
their homes.  At Notasulga, about half the people have farms
ranging from twenty-five to one hundred and fifty acres.  Here I
learned of one prosperous woman farmer, who raises three or four
bales of cotton, as well as potatoes, chickens, and cows.  In the
vicinity of Birmingham, farms are owned ranging from fifty to two
hundred acres.
</p><p> The home-buying that is going on in the agricultural districts
is going on also in the cities.  In Montgomery, street after street
is owned by colored people.  In Chattanooga, one third of the
colored people own their homes.  Suburban lots range in cost from
$350 to $400.  A cottage costs in the neighborhood of $600 to $650.
In Birmingham, colored people pay $10 or $12 a month rent.  A
number of householders have gardens with two or three acres of
land.  Some were fortunate enough to purchase land before the
prices went up, and have profited by the rise.
</p><p> The Negro is also venturing as a tradesman.  In all the large
cities, and even in the smaller towns, in the South, he is hanging
out his sign.  Two young men have engaged in the grocery business
at Tuskegee, Alabama.  Their credit is good at the bank, and I was
told that they were doing more for their race by their industry and
thrift than could be done by any amount of talk.  The colored
grocers in Birmingham are sharing the prosperity of this thriving
city.  Near a little place which I visited in the Black Belt, a
colored school-teacher, who got his education with hand and brain
at Tuskegee, had bought for $225 a lot of land, and established a
grocery store.  At Tuscaloosa, the livery stable man who drove me
owns several horses and carriages, and is doing well.  Thus, in
whatever direction one goes, he can find Negroes who are rising by
force of education and of character.  The influence of such schools
as Hampton, Atlanta, and Tuskegee is felt all through the South in
the stimulus given to industrial occupations.  Tuskegee has turned
out a number of printers, who have made themselves independent, and
get patronage from both white and colored customers.  One has a
printing office in Montgomery.  Another has opened an office in
Texas.  The growth of journalism and the gradual reduction of
illiteracy among the colored people will make a way for many
printers.  In all the mechanical trades, colored men are finding
places as blacksmiths, wheelwrights, masons, bricklayers,
carpenters, tinsmiths, harnessmakers, shoemakers, and machinists.
In Washington, colored brickmakers are earning from four to five
dollars a day.  Hod-carriers receive $1.50.  A boy trained in the
industrial department of Atlanta University has built a schoolhouse
in Alabama on contract.  This boy can earn $2.50 a day with his
hands and tools, and is besides a college graduate.
</p><p> In slavery times there was no stimulus to Negro inventiveness.
Before the war, an application made at the United States Patent
Office for a patent for a Negro inventor was denied, on the ground
that he was a slave.  With industrial education and diversified
mechanical pursuits, the Negro brain is becoming adaptive and
creative.  The records of the United States Patent Office make no
distinction between white and colored inventors.  It is impossible
to furnish statistics, <pb n="808"/>  therefore, showing how much the
colored man has done in this direction.  The chief of the issue
division surmises that there may be between five and ten thousand
colored patentees, but this estimate has no reliable basis, being
derived simply from the casual reports of attorneys in paying their
fees.  A colored assistant examiner in the Patent Office department
has, however, placed at my service a list of some fifty patents
taken out by colored people, which show the scope of their
inventive genius.  In the list of things represented are an
improved gridiron, a locomotive smokestack, a cornstalk harvester,
a shield for infantry and artillery, a fire extinguisher, a dough
kneader, a cotton cultivator, life-preserving apparatus, a
furniture caster, a biscuit cutter, a rotary engine, a printing
press, a file holder, a window ventilator for railroad cars, an
automatic switch for railroads, and a telephone transmitter.  The
electric inventions are said to have a good deal of merit, and have
been assigned to a prominent company.  In Birmingham, a colored
inventor is making money out of his patent.
</p><p> With the purchase of homes and the accumulation of property,
the colored people are gradually changing their condition of
living.  It is seen at its worst in the miserable one-room cabins
of the country districts, and in the alley population of such
cities as Washington and Baltimore.  In the Black Belt, the typical
home is a rude log cabin, without windows, and with one door and a
stick chimney.  The door is usually kept open during the day, in
fair weather, to admit light, which at night is furnished by a pine
knot.  Into such cabins a whole family is frequently crowded.  In
Alabama, I heard of twenty-five persons living in three rooms.  The
genial climate permits a good deal of outdoor living, and the
babies need no sand yards to be made for their benefit.  The mother
sets them out on the ground, and lets them roll.  Bad as the one-room cabin is, it is not so bad as the tenement house in the slums
of the great cities.  The Negro, too, can rival the Chinaman in
practicing economy.  Sixty cents a week, spent in pork, meal, and
syrup, will keep him well alive.  At Athens, Georgia, a colored man
testified in court that "a man can live mighty good on thirty-five
cents a week."
</p><p> The social evolution of the Negro can be seen even by the
casual observer.  A house with a window, even if closed with a
shutter, is an improvement over one which has only a door, and a
double-room house is an improvement over one with a single room.
The influence of new ambition is seen later in the growth of the
cabin into a two-story house, and at the dinner table in a more
varied bill of fare.  At Pensacola, where the wages received for
loading vessels are unusually good, the laborer is prosperous, and
a colored censor said, deprecatingly: "The live 'most too high as
far as eating is concerned; some of them eat as fine food as
millionaires."  A Methodist bishop told me that in Montgomery
$24,000 was spent annually on excursions.  The Negro is surely
learning how to earn his dollar, but he has not learned how to
spend it.  He is buying his experience dear.  The patent-medicine
vender and the sewing-machine peddler draw no distinctions in
regard to color, and the black often insists on spending his money
as foolishly as his white brother.  In one little country cabin
stood a wooden clock worth about $1.25, for which a woman had paid
$10, giving new sarcasm to the proverb that "time is money."  Yet
the Negro's knowledge of what a dollar will buy is growing.
</p><p> New social ambitions are manifest even in the humblest cabins.
The illustrated newspaper furnishes decoration for the walls.  The
old people can admire the pictures, and the younger ones can read
the text.  The cheap chromo <pb n="809"/>  follows, until by and by the
evolution of taste produces a house such as one I visited in
Washington, in which three beautiful copies of celebrated Madonnas
were hanging on the walls.  In the cities social development is
going on more rapidly, though here we also find greater social
degradation.  With all their destitution, the people in the country
cabins are not tempted by the liquor saloons.
</p><p> The social progress of the Negro is well illustrated by two
historic cities,&mdash;the federal capital at Washington and the former
capital of the Confederacy at Montgomery.  The casual traveler, who
sees the alley districts and the settlements around the railroads,
forms no better idea of the social development of the Negro than he
does of Northern whites, if he confines his inspection to similar
localities.  In Montgomery, under the guidance of Dr. Dorsette, a
colored physician and a respected citizen, I had an opportunity to
see the homes of the colored people at their best.  In some of the
streets, the whites occupy one side, and the blacks the other.
Occasionally the colors alternate, like the squares on a
checkerboard.  It is not easy externally to tell one from the
other.  The interiors of these homes, especially of the younger and
more progressive people, are comfortably and tastefully furnished.
The rooms are as high as those of their white neighbors, well
carpeted and papered, while the piano or the cabinet organ suggests
loftier musical tastes than that of the plantation banjo.  While in
most respects the movement or development of the white and colored
races runs on parallel lines, in music they seem to be going in
opposite directions.  Though I traveled all through the South, in
urban, suburban, and agricultural districts, from Baltimore to New
Orleans, the only banjo I heard was played in Atlanta by a white
man.  Returning to Boston, one of the first sights which met my
eyes was that of a fashionable young lady carrying the instrument
the Negro is discarding.  I was twice serenaded at Tuskegee, once
by a brass band, once by a string band, and I slept well after both
performances.  In New Orleans, I was astounded at the strange
phenomenon of a colored hand-organ grinder.  Whether this
represents a state of musical development or degeneracy, as
compared with the banjo, I will not undertake, in the present state
of Northern fascination, to decide.  It is estimated that there are
from 250 to 300 pianos and cabinet organs in the homes of colored
people in Montgomery.
</p><p> The pride of the colored people in buying these homes and
furnishing them is a healthful form of domestic ambition, requiring
sacrifice and resolute concentration of purpose.  A fine house on
a corner lot was shown me which had been bought with the savings of
a hackman.  Even in the poorer districts it is interesting to note
the ambition to improve.  "I have seen these houses grow," said the
doctor.  "There is one in which lives an old woman.  She began with
one room, then built on another; then finished off one, and now has
just finished off the other.  It has taken her some time, but she
has done it."
</p><p> Immediately after the war I lived at the national capital.
Thousands of destitute blacks from Virginia and further south had
settled in the barracks around the city.  They owned little more
than the clothes on their backs, and most of these had been given
to them.  The change in these districts is remarkable.  Large
numbers of people live in their own homes.  There is not much
squalor outside of the alley population.  Even the poorest houses
have some comforts and show some endeavor to improve.  A similar
story may be told of Baltimore.
</p><p> Standards among the negroes are becoming as varied as among
the whites.  In some districts I was informed that a colored man
had very little standing with his own people unless he had a trade
or <pb n="810"/>  profession.  It is inevitable, too, that cliques and
affiliations should be formed, with the advantage and disadvantage
which come from such social differentiation.  Two aristocracies are
appearing in the colored race,&mdash;the aristocracy of culture and the
aristocracy of wealth.  Fortunately, at present, in the younger
generation culture and prosperity are moving together.  The colored
man's standard of wealth is relatively much smaller than that of
the white man.  There are no Negro millionaires that I know of; but
there is growing up a class of men with fortunes ranging from
$15,000 to $100,000.  This accumulation has been going on in recent
years with increasing rapidity.  The colored people in North
Carolina are said to have amassed more in the last five years than
they did in the twenty years preceding.  In most of the States,
there are no data from which the amount of taxes paid by the
Negroes can be separated from that paid by the whites, or the
valuation of their property ascertained.  It is one good result of
the Fourteenth Amendment that no distinction is made in law between
property owned by whites and that owned by blacks.  Georgia is the
only State in which the comptroller is able to furnish the figures
for 1890.  The amount of taxes paid by the whites in that State was
$1,599,977.75; by the colored people, $48,795.13.  The property of
whites was assessed at a valuation of $404,287,311; the property of
blacks, at a valuation of $12,332,003.  The Census Bureau at
Washington has the material for making these comparisons in the
different States, and as the question is now one of sociology, and
not of politics, it is to be hoped that the figures which
illustrate the progress of the Negro may be published.  The total
valuation of Negro property in the South has been given as
$150,000,000 or $200,000,000.  There are those who maintain that
the colored man does not receive full credit for what he is paying.
In North Carolina, a daily Democratic paper claimed, about two
months ago, that the colored people are paying about three times
the tax they are credited with by actual statistics.
</p><p> There are conspicuous cases of individual prosperity in nearly
all the large centres and in the agricultural districts.  Thus, in
Montgomery, Alabama, a colored barber, originally a slave, has
accumulated property amounting to $75,000 or $100,000.  An ex-slave
in Mississippi has bought one of the plantations that formerly
belonged to Jefferson Davis.  The colored people of Maryland are
said to possess property to the amount of $9,000,000.  In
Baltimore, there are several colored men worth $15,000 each, three
or four worth from $40,000 to $60,000, and the estate of a Negro
recently deceased was appraised at $100,000.  In Washington, also,
colored men have profited by the rise of real estate, and a few are
possessed of ample fortunes.  These instances might be greatly
multiplied from my notes.
</p><p> The subject of Negro education is vast and absorbing.  Among
its varied aspects two are of special and correlative interest:
first, What is education doing for the Negro; secondly, What is the
Negro doing for education?  In this paper I can refer only to the
latter topic.  But these questions cannot be absolutely separated.
No man "receives an education" who does not get a good deal of it
himself.  The student is not so much inert material; he reacts on
the forces which impress him.  The Negroes are showing their
awakened and eager interest in education by the zeal with which
they are embracing their opportunities.  Everywhere I found in
colleges, normal institutes, and district schools fresh, live
interest.  In some sections, the eagerness of the colored people
for knowledge amounts to an absolute thirst.  In Alabama, the state
superintendent of education, a former Confederate major, assured me
that the colored people in that <pb n="811"/>  State are more interested
in education than the whites are.  Nothing shows better this zeal
for education than the sacrifices made to secure it.  President
Bumstead, of Atlanta University, asks, "Where in the history of the
world have so large a mass of equally poor and unlettered people
done so much to help themselves in educational work?"  This
challenge will long remain unanswered.  The students of Atlanta
University pay thirty-four per cent of the expenses of that
institution.  A letter from the treasurer of Harvard College
informs me that about the same proportion of its expenses is paid
from tuition fees.  If we compare the wealth represented by the
students of Harvard with that represented by the colored students
of Atlanta, we shall find how large a sacrifice the latter are
making in order to do so much.  It must be remembered, also, that
at Harvard tuition fees and other expenses are mostly paid by
parents and guardians; at Atlanta they are paid by the students
themselves, and to a large degree by personal labor.  President
Bumstead calculates that for every million dollars contributed by
the North at least a half million is contributed by the colored
people for educational purposes.  Though it is difficult to get the
material for such large and general totals, it is easy to furnish
a vast number of facts illustrating the truth that in the very
process of getting his education the Negro is learning the lesson
of self-help.  Among the denominational colleges, the Livingston
Institute at Salisbury, North Carolina, is a good illustration of
this capacity for self-help.  It receives no state aid.  The
colored people of the Zion Methodist Episcopal church give $8000
towards the support of this school.  The students give towards
their own support not less than $6000 more.  The president, Dr.
Price, one of the ablest colored orators of the South, is a
conspicuous example of what the colored man can do for himself.
</p><p> Another remarkable illustration is furnished by the Tuskegee
Normal School.  This institution was started in 1881 by a Hampton
graduate, Mr. Booker T. Washington, on a state appropriation of
$2000.  It has grown from 30 pupils to 450, with 31 teachers.
During the last year 200 applicants had to be turned away for want
of room.  Fourteen hundred acres of land and fourteen school
buildings form a part of the equipment.  While friends of
education, North and South, have generously helped its growth, the
success of the school is due largely to the executive ability of
Mr. Washington and his officers.  General Armstrong says, "I think
it is the noblest and grandest work of any colored man in the
land."  All the teachers are colored.  Of the fourteen school
buildings, eight have been erected, in whole or in part, by the
students.  The school is broadly unsectarian.  It is teaching the
colored people the dignity of labor and how to get out of debt.  It
is an agricultural and industrial school combined.  Its stimulating
and renovating influence is felt all through the Black Belt.
</p><p> One of the most important results of the excellent work done
by Hampton, Atlanta, and Tuskegee is seen in the radiating
influence they exert through the country in stimulating primary
education.  In most of the communities of the lower Southern
States, the money derived from local taxation is not sufficient to
keep the school more than three months in the year, and the pay of
teachers is poor.  The interest of these communities is so
quickened by a good teacher that the people raise money to extend
the school time and supplement the pay of the teacher.  A few
examples taken from many will illustrate.  In one district in
Alabama, the school time was thus extended by private subscription
from three months to seven.  In Coffee County, the teacher's salary
was increased from ten to twenty-five dollars <pb n="812"/>  a month.  In
many cases the raising of this extra sum means a good deal of self-denial.  As the State makes no appropriation for school-houses,
most of the schools in the Black Belt are held in churches, which
gives rise to sectarian jealousy and disturbance.  To overcome
these difficulties and build school-houses, additional sacrifice is
required.  In a district of Butler County, Alabama, the children
formed a "one cent society."  They brought to the teacher a penny
a day.  About thirty dollars was raised to buy land, and the
school-teacher, a colored girl, helped to clear it and burn the
brush.  In one township, where the school fund is sufficient for
seven or nine months, the teachers are paid thirty-five dollars a
month.  In Lee County, the people "supplement" for an assistant
teacher.  One district school which I visited, eighteen miles from
Tuskegee, taught by a graduate of its institute, well illustrated
the advantage of industrial education.  Having learned the
carpenter's trade at the normal school, he was able, with the help
of his pupils, to build a fine new school-house.  The girls often
do better than the men.  One, who teaches about twenty-five miles
from Tuskegee, has now a good two-story school building with four
rooms.  She has two assistant teachers, who live with her in the
building.  She has revolutionized that section of the country.  A
Hampton student whom I met once applied for a school in his
district, as he wished to learn to read and write.  He was told
that there was not a sufficient number of children.  Then he
offered to give a school building, if the town would furnish a
teacher.  With the aid of his father he carried out the plan, and
established a good school.  Samuel Smiles might easily make a
library of books on Self-Help out of thousands of individual
examples furnished by the colored people.
</p><p> The interest in education is seen also in the self-denial and
sacrifice which parents make to keep their children at school.
This sacrifice falls chiefly on the mothers.  A student told me
that two thirds of the younger scholars at Tuskegee were sent by
their mothers.  Very often the mother is a widow.  She may get
twenty dollars a month, or eight, or only four, for her labor.  Out
of this small sum she sends to college and clothes her boy or girl.
"I know mothers," said a student, "who get three dollars a month,
and out of that pay one dollar for the rent, and yet send their
children to school."  To do this they will wash all day and half
the night.  Said a colored clergyman in Chattanooga: "Sometimes,
when I go about and see how hard many of these mothers work, I feel
almost inclined to say, 'You ought to keep your child at home;' but
they hold on with wonderful persistence.  Two girls graduated from
Atlanta University.  Their mother had been washing several years to
keep them in school.  She came up to see them graduate.  She was
one of the happiest mothers I ever saw."  At Selma University, some
of the students walk from ten to fifteen miles a day in going to
and from the university.
</p><p> There is one education which the children get; there is
another which they give to their parents.  The influence of the
normal school reacts on the home life.  The boys and girls at
Hampton and Tuskegee are taught to keep house.  They are not
satisfied to live in the old way, when they go home.  "I have
seen," says Professor Washington, "the influence of the daughter so
potent, when she got home, that the father has torn down the old
house, and built another and better one."
</p><p> The result of higher education is seen in the rise of a
professional class.  I remember the time when a colored doctor was
a curiosity even in Washington; but colored physicians, lawyers,
journalists, college professors, dentists, educated clergymen, and
teachers are now to <pb n="813"/>  be found in all the large cities of the
South.  In Montgomery, Dr. Dorsette has built up a thriving
practice.  He has erected a three-story brick building, on the
lower floor of which are two stores, one of them a large and well-equipped drug store.  A hall above is used for the accommodation of
colored societies.  In Birmingham, there are two practicing
physicians, one dentist, and one lawyer.  At Selma, the practicing
physician is a graduate of the university.  There is also a
pharmacist, owning his drug store, who studied at Howard
University.  There are six colored lawyers and seven colored
physicians in Baltimore.  The professional men command the
confidence and support of their own people.
</p><p> Journalism is growing slowly.  There are now about fifty-five
well established Negro newspapers and journals.  Thirty-seven are
in the Southern States; seven are monthlies and two are semi-monthlies.  The aggregate weekly circulation of all is about
805,000 copies.  There are other ephemeral journals, not included
in this list.  The largest circulation, 15,000, is claimed for the
Indianapolis Freeman.
</p><p> The colored people are determined to have their churches, and
they subscribe, in proportion to their means, large sums to sustain
them.  Last year the Zion Methodist Episcopal church in North
Carolina raised $84,000 to support its religious institutions.
This amount represents but one State and but one denomination.  The
churches built reflect fairly the social standard of the people.
In the comparatively new city of Birmingham, there are seven
comfortable colored churches, ranging in cost from $2000 to
$15,000.  In Washington, two churches cost nearly $30,000 each, and
the money has been raised almost exclusively by the colored people.
In Baltimore, there are forty-four colored churches, holding a
large amount of property.  The old-time preacher still fills the
pulpit in many communities, and the old slaves are loath to give up
the hysteric emotionalism of revival preaching.  The younger and
progressive Negroes are breaking away from it, and demanding
preachers whose intelligence and education secure respect.  They
are giving up, too, the old slave melodies.  Modern Protestant
hymnology is substituted.  The universities and theological schools
are meeting the demand for better preachers.  The colored people
are also ambitious to pay their preachers as much as the whites pay
theirs.  In Montgomery, one colored preacher has a salary of $1200
a year with a parsonage.  In another city in Alabama, $1800 is
paid.
</p><p> The standard of morality is rising, also.  There is more
respect for property now that the Negro is learning what mine and
thine mean.  An eminent judge of Louisiana assured me that
intoxication among the colored people is the principal cause of
crime, but that crime does not exist to the same extent that it
formerly did.  Marriage, he said, had changed largely the condition
of their society.  The Negroes are seeking to make this a matter of
importance, so that their rights of property may be respected.  The
temperance movement makes headway.  In Methodist conferences in
North Carolina, and possibly elsewhere, no one is admitted to the
ministry who uses liquor or tobacco.
</p><p> The colored people do more towards taking care of their
unfortunate classes than is generally realized.  With all the
destitution that exists, there is almost no mendicancy.  When one
considers how much is done in the North for hospitals, homes, and
institutions of every sort, and how little in the South, it is
apparent that aid must come from some other quarter.  The colored
orphan asylum established by Mrs. Steele in Chattanooga is, I am
told, the only Protestant colored orphan asylum south of
Washington.  What, then, becomes of orphan <pb n="814"/>  children?  They
are adopted.  I have met such children in many homes, and their
love and respect for their foster parents refute the charge that
the Negro is incapable of gratitude.  Thus the colored people have
instinctively and of necessity adopted the placing-out system for
orphans, which, other things being equal, is the best disposition
that can be made of them.
</p><p> In other respects the colored people have developed a laudable
disposition to take care of their own poor.  In addition to the Odd
Fellows, Masons, and Knights of Pythias, benevolent and fraternal
organizations are multiplying.  The city churches are feeling a new
impulse to such work.  Brotherhoods, Good Samaritan societies, and
mutual benefit organizations are established.  Members of these
organizations are allowed a regular stipend when sick.  In New
Orleans, the colored people have started a widows' home, and have
collected enough money to buy a piece of ground and to put up a
respectable building.  In Montgomery, I visited the Hale Infirmary,
founded by the late Joseph Hale and his wife, leading colored
citizens.  It is a large two-story building, especially designed by
the son-in-law of the founder for hospital purposes.  Such gifts
and such organizations show that there is a disposition among the
colored people to adopt the practices of a higher order of society.
It is charged that the Negro imitates the vices of the white; it is
often overlooked that he also imitates his virtues.  A good
illustration of practical Christianity was given by the Young Men's
Christian Association at Tuskegee, in building, last year, a little
house for an old colored woman.  A colored teacher paid the cost of
the lumber, and the young men gave the labor.  They are planning
more work of this kind.  One interesting case of Negro generosity
shows the reverses of fortune which followed emancipation.  An ex-slave in Louisiana bought a farm, paid for it, and became
prosperous.  Not long after his old master came to him in a state
of destitution.  The Negro took him in, kept him for a week, and
gave him a suit of clothes on his departure.
</p><p> Under slavery the Negroes were not organized, except in
churches.  The organic spirit must have time for growth.
Cooperation has made no great headway.  In various States and
counties the Farmers' Alliance is attracting attention, many of the
Negroes hoping to find relief through it from the bondage of the
mortgage system.  Small stock companies for various purposes exist
in a number of cities.  A little has been done in the way of
building associations.  There is one at Atlanta, with branches and
local boards elsewhere; others at Tuskegee, Montgomery, Selma,
Baltimore, and Washington.  In Baltimore there are three or four
such associations, but the German organizations, managed by white
people, have had much more of their patronage.  A daily paper of
Charlotte, North Carolina, in speaking of the loan associations
there, said that the colored shareholders were outstripping the
white.  It was noticeable that they paid more promptly.  A penny
savings bank, chartered under state law, was organized at
Chattanooga about ten months ago.  It has already one thousand
depositors, the amounts ranging from two cents to one thousand
dollars.  The white as well as the colored children are being
educated to save by this bank.  In Birmingham, a similar
institution was opened last October, and has about three thousand
depositors.  A school savings bank or postal savings bank system,
as recommended by the Mohonk Negro conference, would be of great
benefit to the colored people.
</p><p> A full report of what the colored man is doing for himself
within the old slave States can be given only when the census
reports are elaborated, or when such a thorough record of his
progress is made in every State as Dr. Jeffrey A. Brackett has made
for the State of Maryland.  All that has been attempted in this
article is to give such indications and evidence as can readily be
obtained by one who travels through the South, on this mission,
with his eyes and ears open.
</p><p> To sum up, then, the facts which show what the Negro is doing
for himself, it is clear that the new generation of Afric-Americans
is animated by a progressive spirit.  They are raising and
following their own leaders.  They are rapidly copying the organic,
industrial, and administrative features of white society.  They
have discovered that industrial redemption is not to be found in
legislative and political measures.  In spite of oppressive usury
and extortion, the colored man is buying farms, building homes,
accumulating property, establishing himself in trade, learning the
mechanic arts, devising inventions, and entering the professions.
Education he sees to be the pathway to prosperity, and is making
immense sacrifices to secure it.  He is passing into the higher
stages of social evolution.  In religion the "old-timer" is giving
way to the educated preacher.  Religion is becoming more ethical.
The colored people are doing much to take care of their own
unfortunate classes.  The cooperative spirit is slowly spreading
through trades unions, building associations, and benevolent
guilds.  In no way is the colored man doing more for himself than
by silently and steadily developing a sense of self-respect, new
capacity for self-support, and a pride in his race, which more than
anything else secure for him the respect and fraternal feeling of
his white neighbors.
</p><signed>                      <hi rend="italic">Samuel J. Barrows.</hi></signed>



</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
