<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="BeeHost"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="BeeHost">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"Hosts and Guests"</title>
<title type="sort">hosts and guests</title>
<author>Beerbohm, Max, Sir, 1872-1956</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">31</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">BeeHost</idno>
<date value="1999">1999</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1999 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475731</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"Hosts and Guests"</title>
<title level="j">Harper`s Monthly</title>
<title type="sort">hosts and guests</title>
<author>Max Beerbohm</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harper &amp; Brothers</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1919">1919</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: University of Virginia Library call number AP 2 .H3 v. 139</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This essay appeared in v. 139 (August 1919), 425-431.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1919">1919</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1999-07">July 1999</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Lisa Spiro</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="425"/>
<head>HOSTS AND GUESTS
<lb/>
BY MAX BEERBOHM
</head>
<p>BEAUTIFULLY vague though the English language is, with its
meanings merging into one another as softly as the facts of
landscape in the moist English climate, and much addicted though
we always have been to ways of compromise, and averse from sharp
hard logical outlines, we do not call a host a guest, nor a guest a
host.  The ancient Romans did so.  They, with a language that was
as lucid as their climate and was a perfect expression of the sharp
hard logical outlook fostered by that climate, had but one word for
those two things.  Nor have their equally acute descendants done
what might have been expected of them in this matter.
<hi rend="italic">H&ocirc;te</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ospite</hi> and <hi rend="italic">huesped</hi> are as
mysteriously equivocal as <hi rend="italic">hospes</hi>.  By weight of all this
authority I find myself being dragged to the conclusion that a host
and a guest must be the same thing, after all.  Yet in a dim and
muzzy way, deep down in my breast, I feel sure that they are
different.  Compromise, you see, as usual.  I take it that strictly the
two things <hi rend="italic">are</hi> one, but that our division of them is yet
another instance of that sterling common sense by which, etc., etc.
</p><p> I would go even so far as to say that the difference is more
than merely circumstantial and particular.  I seem to discern also a
temperamental and general difference.  You ask me to dine with
you in a restaurant, I say I shall be delighted, you order the meal, I
praise it, you pay for it, I have the pleasant sensation of not paying
for it; and it is well that each of us should have a label according to
the part he plays in this transaction.  But the two labels are
applicable in a larger and more philosophic way.  In every human
being one or the other of these two instincts is predominant: the
active or positive instinct to offer hospitality, the negative or
passive, instinct to accept it.  And either of these instincts is so
significant of character that one might well say that mankind is
divisible into two great classes: hosts and guests.
</p><p> I have already (see third sentence of foregoing paragraph)
somewhat prepared you for the shock of a confession which candor
now forces from me.  I am one of the guests.  You are, however, so
shocked that you will read no more of me?  Bravo!  Your refusal
indicates that you have not a guestish soul.  Here am I trying to
entertain you, and you will not be entertained.  You stand shouting
that it is more blessed to give than to receive.  Very well.  For my
part, I would rather read than write, any day.  You shall write this
essay for me.  Be it never so humble, I shall give it my best
attention and manage to say something nice about it.  I am sorry to
see you calming suddenly down.  Nothing but a sense of duty to
myself, and to guests in general, makes me resume my pen.  I
believe guests to be as numerous, really, as hosts.  It may be that
even you, if you examine yourself dispassionately, will find that
you are one of them.  In which case, you may yet thank me for some
comfort.  I think there are good qualities to be found in guests, and
some bad ones in even the best hosts.
</p><p> Our deepest instincts, bad or good, are those which we share
with the rest of the animal creation.  To offer hospitality, or to
accept it, is but an instinct which man has acquired in the long
course of his self-development.  Lions do not ask one another to
their lairs, nor do


<pb n="426"/>

birds keep open nest.  Certain wolves and tigers, it is true, have been
so seduced by man from their natural state that they will deign to
accept man's hospitality.  But when you give a bone to your dog,
does he run out and invite another dog to share it with him? &mdash; and
does your cat insist on having a circle of other cats around her
saucer of milk?  Quite the contrary.  A deep sense of personal
property is common to all these creatures.  Thousands of years
hence they may have acquired some willingness to share things with
their friends.  Or, rather, dogs may; cats, I think, not.  Meanwhile,
let us not be censorious.  Though certain monkeys assuredly were of
finer and more malleable stuff than any wolves or tigers, it was a
very long time indeed before even we began to be hospitable.  The
cavemen did not entertain.  It may be that now and again &mdash; say,
toward the end of the Stone Age &mdash; one or another among the more
enlightened of them said to his wife, while she plucked an eagle that
he had snared the day before, "That red-haired man who lives in the
next valley seems to be a decent, harmless sort of man.  And
sometimes I fancy he is rather lonely.  I think I will ask him to dine
with us to-night," and presently, going out, met the red-haired man
and said to him: "Are you doing anything to-night?  If not, won't
you dine with us?  It would be a great pleasure to my wife.  Only
ourselves.  Come just as you are."  "That is most good of you, but,"
stammered the red-haired man, "as ill-luck will have it, I <hi rend="italic">am</hi>
engaged to-night.  A long-standing, formal invitation.  I wish I could
get out of it, but I simply can't.  I have a morbid conscientiousness
about such things."  Thus we see that the will to offer hospitality
was an earlier growth than the will to accept it.  But we must
beware of thinking these two things identical with the mere will to
give and the mere will to receive.  It is unlikely that the red-haired
man would have refused a slice of eagle if it had been offered to
him where he stood.  And it is still more unlikely that his friend
would have handed it to him.  Such is not the way of hosts.  The
hospitable instinct is not wholly altruistic.  There is pride and
egoism mixed up with it, as I shall show.
</p><p> Meanwhile, why did the red-haired man babble those excuses?
It was because he scented danger.  He was not by nature suspicious,
but &mdash; what possible motive, except murder, could this man have for
enticing him to that cave?  Acquaintance in the open valley was all
very well and pleasant, but a strange den after dark &mdash; no, no!  You
despise him for his fears.  Yet these were not really so absurd as
they may seem.  As man progressed in civilization, and grew to be
definitely gregarious, hospitality became more a matter of course.
But even then it was not above suspicion.  It was not hedged around
with those unwritten laws which make it the safe and eligible thing
we know to-day.  In the annals of hospitality there are many pages
that make painful reading; many a great dark blot is there which the
Recording Angel may wish, but will not be able, to wipe out with a
tear.
</p><p> If I were a host, I should ignore those tomes.  Being a guest, I
sometimes glance into them, but with more of horror, I assure you,
than of malicious amusement.  I carefully avoid those which treat of
hospitality among barbarous races.  Things done in the best periods
of the most enlightened peoples are quite bad enough.  The
Israelites were the salt of the earth.  But can you imagine a deed of
colder-blooded treachery than Jael's?  You would think it must have
been held accursed by even the basest minds.  Yet thus sang
Deborah and Barak, "Blessed above women shall Jael the wife of
Heber the Kenite be; blessed shall she be among women in the
tent."  And Barak, remember, was a gallant soldier, and Deborah
was a prophetess who "judged Israel at that time."  So much for
ideals of hospitality among the children of Israel.
</p><p> Of the Homeric Greeks it may be said


<pb n="427"/>

that they, too, were the salt of the earth; and it may be added that in
their pungent and antiseptic quality there was mingled a measure of
sweetness, not to be found in the children of Israel.  I do not say
outright that Odysseus ought not to have slain the suitors.  That is a
debatable point.  It is true that they were guests under his roof.  But
he had not invited them.  Let us give him the benefit of the doubt.  I
am thinking of another episode in his life.  By what Circe did, and
by his disregard of what she had done, a searching light is cast on
the laxity of Homeric Greek notions as to what was due to guests.
Odysseus was a clever, but not a bad man, and his standard of
general conduct was high enough.  Yet, having foiled Circe in her
purpose to turn him into a swine, and having forced her to restore
his comrades to human shape, he did not let pass the barrier of his
teeth any such winged words as "Now will I bide no more under thy
roof, Circe, but fare across the sea with my dear comrades, even
unto mine own home, for that which thou didst was an evil thing,
and one not meet to be done unto strangers by the daughter of a
god."  He seems to have said nothing in particular, to have accepted
with alacrity the invitation that he and his dear comrades should
prolong their visit, and to have prolonged it with them for a whole
year, in the course of which Circe bore him a son, named
Telegonus.  As Matthew Arnold would have said, "What a set!"
</p><p> My eye roves, for relief, to those shelves where the later annals
are.  I take down a tome at random.  Rome in the fifteenth century:
civilization never was more brilliant than there and then.  I imagine;
and yet &mdash; no, I replace that tome.  I saw enough in it to remind me
the Borgias selected and laid down rare poisons in their cellars with
as much thought as they gave to their vintage wines.  Extraordinary!
&mdash; but the Romans do not seem to have thought so.  An invitation to
dine at Palazzo Borghese was accounted the highest social honor.  I
am aware that in recent books of Italian history there has been a
tendency to whiten the Borgias' characters.  But I myself hold to the
old romantic black way of looking at the Borgias.  I maintain that
though you would often in the fifteenth century have heard the
snobbish Roman say, in a would-be offhand tone, "I am dining with
the Borgias to-night," no Roman ever was able to say, "I dined last
night with the Borgias."
</p><p> To mankind in general Macbeth and Lady Macbeth stand out
as the supreme type of all that a host and hostess should not be.
Hence the marked coolness of Scotsmen toward Shakespeare, hence
the untiring efforts of that proud and sensitive race to set up Burns
in his stead.  It is a risky thing to offer sympathy to the proud and
sensitive, yet I must say that I think the Scots have a real grievance.
The two actual, historic Macbeths were no worse than innumerable
other couples in other lands that had not yet fully struggled out of
barbarism.  It is hard that Shakespeare happened on the story of that
particular pair, and so made it immortal.  But he meant no harm,
and, let Scotsmen believe me, did positive good.  Scotch hospitality
is proverbial.  As much in Scotland as in America does the English
visitor blush when he thinks how perfunctory and niggard, in
comparison, English hospitality is.  It was Scotland that first
formalized hospitality, made of it an exacting code of honor, with
the basic principle that the guest must in all circumstances be
respected and at all costs protected.  Jacobite history bristles with
examples of the heroic sacrifices made by hosts for their guests,
sacrifices of their own safety, and even of their own political
convictions, for fear of infringing, however slightly, that sacred
code of theirs.  And what was the origin of all this noble pedantry?
Shakespeare's "Macbeth."
</p><p> Perhaps if England were a bleak and rugged country, like
Scotland, or a new


<pb n="428"/>

country, like America, the foreign visitor would be more
overwhelmed with kindness here than he is.  The landscapes of our
countryside are so charming, London abounds in public monuments
so redolent of history, so romantic and engrossing, that we are
perhaps too apt to think the foreign visitor would have neither time
nor inclination to sit dawdling in private dining-rooms.  Assuredly
there is no lack of hospitable impulse among the English.  In what
may be called mutual hospitality they touch a high level.  The
French entertain one another far less frequently.  So do the Italians.
In England the native guest has a very good time indeed &mdash; though of
course he pays for it, in some measure, by acting as host, too, from
time to time.
</p><p> In practice, no, there cannot be any absolute division of
mankind into my two categories, hosts and guests.  But
psychologically a guest does not cease to be a guest when he gives a
dinner, nor is a host not a host when he accepts one.  The amount of
entertaining that a guest need do is a matter wholly for his own
conscience.  He will soon find that he does not receive less
hospitality for offering little; and he would not receive less if he
offered none.  The amount received by him depends wholly on the
degree of his agreeableness.  Pride makes an occasional host of him;
but he does not shine in that capacity.  Nor do hosts want him to
assay it.  If they accept an invitation from him, they do so only
because they wish not to hurt his feelings.  As guests they are fish
out of water.
</p><p> Circumstances do, of course, react on character.  It is
conventional for the rich to give, and for the poor to receive.  Riches
do tent to foster in you the instincts of a host, and poverty does
create an atmosphere favorable to the growth of guestish instincts.
But strong bents make their own way.  Not all guests are to be found
among the needy, nor all hosts among the affluent.  For sixteen
years, after my education was, by courtesy, finished &mdash; from the age,
that is, of twenty-two to the age of thirty-eight &mdash; I lived in London,
seeing all sorts of people all the while; and I came across many a
rich man who, like the master of the shepherd Corin, was "of
churlish disposition" and little recked "to find the way to heaven by
doing deeds of hospitality."  On the other hand, I knew quite poor
men who were incorrigibly hospitable.
</p><p> To such men, all honor.  The most I dare claim for myself is
that if I had been rich I should have been better than Corin's master.
Even as it was, I did my best.  But I had no authentic joy in doing it.
Without the spur of pride I might conceivably have not done it at
all.  There recurs to me from among memories of my boyhood an
episode that is rather significant.  In my school, as in most others,
we received now and again "hampers" from home.  At the midday
dinner, in every house, we all ate together; but at breakfast and
supper we ate in four or five separate "messes."  It was customary
for the receiver of a hamper to share the contents with his
messmates.  On one occasion I received, instead of the usual
variegated hamper, a box containing twelve sausage-rolls.  It
happened that when this box arrived and was opened by me there
was no one around.  Of sausage-rolls I was particularly fond.  I am
sorry to say that I carried the box up to my cubicle, and, having
eaten two of the sausage-rolls, said nothing to my friends that day
about the other ten, nor anything about them when, three days later,
I had eaten them all alone.
</p><p> Thirty years have elapsed, my school-fellows are scattered far
and wide, the chance that this page may meet the eyes of some of
them does not much dismay me; but I am glad there was no
collective and contemporary judgment by them on my strange
exploit.  What defense could I have offered?  Suppose I had said,
"You see, I am so essentially a guest," the plea would have carried
little weight.  And yet it would not have


<pb n="429"/>

been a worthless plea.  On receipt of a hamper, a boy did rise,
always, in the esteem of his mess-mates.  His sardines, his
marmalade, his potted meat, at any rate while they lasted, did make
us think that his parents "must be awfully decent," and that he was a
not unworthy son.  He had become our central figure, we expected
him to lead the conversation, we liked listening to him, his jokes
were good.  With those twelve sausage-rolls I could have dominated
my fellows for a while.  But I had not a dominant nature.  Leading
abashed me, I was happiest in the comity of the crowd.  Having
received a hamper, I should have passed muster.  I suppose I was
always glad when it was finished, glad to fall back into the ranks.
</p><p> Boys (as will have been surmised from my record of the effect
of hampers) are all of them potential guests.  It is only as they grow
up that some of them harden into hosts.  It is likely enough that if I,
when I grew up, had been rich, my natural bent to guestship would
have been diverted, and I, too, have become a (sort of) host.  And
perhaps I should have passed muster, I suppose I did pass muster
whenever, in the course of my long residence in London, I did
entertain friends.  But the memory of those occasions is not dear to
me &mdash; especially not the memory of those that were in the more
distinguished restaurants.  Somewhere in the back of my brain,
while I tried to lead the conversation brightly, was always the
haunting fear that I had not brought enough money in my pocket.  I
never let this fear master me.  I never said to any one, "Will you
have a liqueur?" &mdash; always, "What liqueur will you have?"  But I
postponed as far as possible the evil moment of asking for the bill.
When I had, in the proper casual tone (I hope and believe), at length
asked for it, I wished always it were not brought to me folded on a
plate, as though the amount were so hideously high that I alone
must be privy to it.  So soon as it was laid beside me, I wanted to
know the worst at once.  But I pretended to be so engrossed in talk
that I was unaware of the bill's presence, and I was careful to be
always in the middle of a sentence when I raised the upper fold and
took my not (I hope) frozen glance.  In point of fact, the amount
was always much less than I had feared.  Pessimism does win us
great happy moments.
</p><p> Meals in the restaurants of Soho tested less severely the pauper
guest masquerading as host.  But to them one could not ask rich
persons &mdash; nor even poor persons unless one knew them very well.
Soho is so uncertain that the fare is often not good enough to be
palmed off on even one's poorest and oldest friends.  A very
magnetic host, with a great gift for bluffing, might, no doubt, even
in Soho's worst moments, diffuse among his guests a conviction that
all was of the best.  But I never was good at bluffing.  I had always
to let food speak for itself.  "It's cheap" was the only p&aelig;an that
in Soho's bad moments ever occurred to me, and this of course I did
not utter.  And <hi rend="italic">was</hi> it so cheap, after all?  Soho induces a
certain optimism.  A bill there was always larger than I had thought
it would be.
</p><p> Every one, even the richest and most munificent of men, pays
much by check more light-heartedly than he pays little in specie.  In
restaurants I should have liked always to give checks.  But in any
restaurant I was so much more often seen as guest than as host that I
never felt sure the proprietor would trust me.  Only in my club did I
know the luxury, or rather the painlessness, of entertaining by
check.  A check &mdash; especially a club check, supplied for the use of
members, not a leaf torn out of his own book &mdash; makes so little mark
on any man's imagination.  Offering hospitality in any club, I was
inwardly calm.  If my guest was by nature a guest, I managed to
forget somewhat that I myself was a guest by nature.  But if my
guest was a true and habitual host, I did feel that we were in an
absurdly false relation; and it was not without difficulty that I could
restrain


<pb n="430"/>

myself from saying to him, "This is all very well, you know, but &mdash;
frankly: your place is at the head of your own table."
</p><p> The host as guest is far, far worse than the guest as host.  He
never even passes muster.  The guest, in virtue of a certain hability
that is part of his natural equipment, can more or less ape the ways
of a host.  But the host, with his more positive temperament, does
not even attempt the graces of a guest.  By "graces" I do not mean to
imply anything artificial.  The guest's manners are, rather, as wild
flowers springing from good rich soil &mdash; the soil of genuine modesty
and gratitude.  He honorably wishes to please in return for the
pleasure he is receiving.  He wonders that people should be so kind
to him, and, without knowing it, is very kind to <hi rend="italic">them</hi>.  But
the host, as I said earlier in this essay, is a guest against his own
will.  That is the root of the mischief.  He feels that it is more
blessed, etc., and that he is conferring rather than accepting a favor.
He does not adjust himself.  He forgets his place.  He leads the
conversation.  He tries genially to draw you out.  He never
comments on the goodness of the wine.  He looks at his watch
abruptly and says he must be off.  He doesn't say he has had a
delightful time.  In fact, his place is at the head of his own table.
</p><p> His own table, over his own cellar, under his own roof &mdash; it is
only there that you see him at his best.  To a club or restaurant he
may sometimes invite you, but not there, not there, my child, do you
get the full savor of his quality.  In life or literature there has been
no better host than Old Wardle.  Appalling though he would have
been as a guest in club or restaurant, it is hardly less painful to think
of him as a host there.  At Dingley Dell, with an ample gesture, he
made you free of all that was his.  He could not have given you a
club or a restaurant.  Nor, when you come to think of it, did he give
you Dingley Dell.  The place remained his.  None knew better than
Old Wardle that this was so.  Hospitality, as we have agreed, is not
one of the most deep-rooted instincts in man, whereas the sense of
possession certainly is.  Not even Old Wardle was a communist.
"This," you may be sure he said to himself, "is <hi rend="italic">my</hi> roof,
these are <hi rend="italic">my</hi> horses, that's a picture of <hi rend="italic">my</hi> dear old
grandfather."  And "This," he would say to us, "is <hi rend="italic">my</hi> roof:
sleep soundly under it.  These are <hi rend="italic">my</hi> horses: ride them.
That's a portrait of <hi rend="italic">my</hi> dear old grandfather: have a good
look at it."  But he did not ask us to walk off with any of these
things.  Not even what he actually did give us would he regard as
having passed out of his possession.  "That," he would muse, if we
were torpid after dinner, "is <hi rend="italic">my</hi> roast beef," and "That," if
we staggered on the way to bed, "is <hi rend="italic">my</hi> cold milk punch."
"But surely," you interrupt me, "to give and then not feel that one
has given is the very best of all ways of giving."  I agree.  I hope you
didn't think I was trying to disparage Old Wardle.  I was merely
keeping my promise to point out that from among the motives of
even the best hosts pride and egoism are not absent.
</p><p> Every virtue, as we were taught in youth, is a mean between
two extremes; and I think any virtue is the better understood by us if
we glance at the vice on either side of it.  I take it that the virtue of
hospitality stands midway between churlishness and mere
ostentation.  Far to the left of the good host stands he who doesn't
want to see anything of any one; far to the right, he who wants a
horde of people to be always seeing something of <hi rend="italic">him</hi>.  I
conjecture that the figure on the left, just discernible through my
field-glasses, is that of old Corin's master.  His name was never
revealed to us, but Corin's brief account of his character suffices.
"Deeds of hospitality" is a dismal phrase that could have occurred
only to the servant of a very dismal master.  Not less tell-tale is
Corin's idea that men who do these "deeds" do them only to save
their souls in the next world.  It is a pity Shakespeare did not
actually bring


<pb n="431"/>

Corin's master on to the stage.  One would have liked to see the old
man genuinely touched by the charming eloquence of Rosalind's
appeal for a crust of bread, and conscious that he would probably go
to heaven if he granted it, and yet not quite able to grant it.  Far
away though he stands to the left of the good host, he has yet
something in common with that third person discernible on the right
&mdash; that speck yonder, which I believe to be Lucullus.  Nothing that
we know of Lucullus suggests that he was less inhuman than the
churl of Arden.  It does not appear that he had a single friend, or
that he wished for one.  His lavishness was indiscriminate except in
that he entertained only the rich.  One would have liked to dine with
him, but not even in the act of digestion could one have felt that he
had a heart.  One would have acknowledged that in all the material
resources of his art he was a master, and also that he practised his
art for sheer love of it, wishing to be admired for nothing but his
mastery, and cocking no eye on any of those ulterior objects but for
which some of the most prominent hosts would not entertain at all.
But the very fact that he was an artist is repulsive.  When hospitality
becomes an art it loses its very soul.  With this reflection I look
away from Lucullus and, fixing my gaze on the middle ground, am
the better able to appreciate the excellence of the figure that stands
before me &mdash; the figure of Old Wardle.  Some pride and egoism in
that capacious breast, yes, but a great heart full of kindness, and
ever a warm spontaneous welcome to the stranger in need and to all
old friends and young.  Hark! he is shouting something.  He is
asking us both down to Dingley Dell.  And you have shouted back
that you will be delighted.  Ah, did I not suspect from the first that
you, too, were perhaps a guest?
</p><p> But &mdash; I constrain you in the act of rushing off to pack your
things &mdash; one moment: this essay has yet to be finished.  We have
yet to glance at those two extremes between which the mean is good
guestship.  Far to the right of the good guest, we descry the parasite;
far to the left, the churl again.  Not the same churl, perhaps.  We do
not know that Corin's master was ever sampled as a guest.  I am
inclined to call yonder speck Dante &mdash; Dante Alighieri, of whom we
do know that he received during his exile much hospitality from
many hosts and repaid them by writing how bitter was the bread in
their houses, and how steep the stairs were.  To think of dour Dante
as a guest is less dispiriting only than to think what he would have
been as a host had it ever occurred to him to entertain any one or
anything except a deep regard for Beatrice; and one turns with
positive relief to have a glimpse of the parasite &mdash; Mr. Smurge, I
presume, "whose gratitude was as boundless as his appetite, and his
presence as unsought as it appeared to be inevitable."  But now,
how gracious and admirable is the central figure &mdash; radiating
gratitude, but not too much of it; never intrusive, ever within call;
full of dignity, yet all amenable; quiet, yet lively; never echoing,
ever amplifying; never contradicting, but often lighting the way to
truth; an ornament, an inspiration, anywhere.
</p><p> Such is he.  But <hi rend="italic">who</hi> is he?  It is easier to confess a
defect than to claim a quality.  I have told you that when I lived in
London I was nothing as a host; but I will not claim to have been a
perfect guest.  Nor indeed was I.  I was a good one, but, looking
back, I see myself not quite in the center &mdash; slightly to the left,
slightly to the churlish side.  I was rather <hi rend="italic">too</hi> quiet, and I did
sometimes contradict.  And, though I always liked to be invited
anywhere, I very often preferred to stay at home.  If any one
hereafter shall form a collection of the notes written by me in reply
to invitations, I am afraid he will gradually suppose me to have
been more in request than ever I really was, and to have been also a
great invalid, and a great traveler.
</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
