<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="BieFavo"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="BieFavo">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">My Favorite Murder</title>
<title type="sort">my favorite murder</title>
<author>Bierce, Ambrose</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">22</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">BieFavo</idno>
<date value="1993">1993</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1993 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475736</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>created for Alan Howard's ENLT 255 class,spring 1994</p>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Works of Ambrose Bierce</title>
<title type="sort">collected works of ambrose bierce</title>
<author>Ambrose Bierce</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Neale Publishing Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York; Washington</pubPlace>
<date value="1911">1911</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>vol. 8</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>University of Virginia library copy: PS1097.A1 1909
v.8 copy 2</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>spell-check and verification made against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1888">1888</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-01">January 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Scanned in text electronically; removed errors created by
scanning; spellchecked; TEI tagging added; unambiguous line-end
hyphenation removed</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="text" id="d3">

<pb n="147" id="BieFavo147"/>

<p>HAVING murdered my mother under
circumstances of singular
atrocity, I was arrested and put
upon my trial, which lasted
seven years. In charging the jury, the judge
of the Court of Acquittal remarked that it was
one of the most ghastly crimes that he had ever
been called upon to explain away.
</p><p>At this, my attorney rose and said:
</p><p>"May it please your Honor, crimes are
ghastly or agreeable only by comparison. If
you were familiar with the details of my
client's previous murder of his uncle you
would discern in his later offense (if offense
it may be called) something in the nature of
tender forbearance and filial consideration for
the feelings of the victim. The appalling
ferocity of the former assassination was indeed
inconsistent with any hypothesis but that of
guilt; and had it not been for the fact that the
honorable judge before whom he was tried
was the president of a life insurance company
<pb n="148" id="BieFavo148"/>
that took risks on hanging, and in which my
client held a policy, it is hard to see how he
could decently have been acquitted. If your
Honor would like to hear about it for instruction
and guidance of your Honor's mind, this
unfortunate man, my client, will consent to
give himself the pain of relating it under
oath."
</p><p>The district attorney said: "Your Honor, I
object. Such a statement would be in the
nature of evidence, and the testimony in this
case is closed. The prisoner's statement should
have been introduced three years ago, in the
spring of 1881."
</p><p>"In a statutory sense," said the judge, "you
are right, and in the Court of Objections and
Technicalities you would get a ruling in your
favor. But not in a Court of Acquittal. The
objection is overruled."
</p><p>"I except," said the district attorney.
</p><p>"You cannot do that," the judge said. "I
must remind you that in order to take an exception
you must first get this case transferred
for a time to the Court of Exceptions on a
formal motion duly supported by affidavits.
A motion to that effect by your predecessor in
office was denied by me during the first year
of this trial. Mr. Clerk, swear the prisoner."
<pb n="149" id="BieFavo149"/>
</p><p>The customary oath having been administered,
I made the following statement, which
impressed the judge with so strong a sense of
the comparative triviality of the offense for
which I was on trial that he made no further
search for mitigating circumstances, but
simply instructed the jury to acquit, and I left
the court, without a stain upon my reputation:
</p><p>"I was born in I856 in Kalamakee, Mich.,
of honest and reputable parents, one of whom
Heaven has mercifully spared to comfort me
in my later years. In I867 the family came to
California and settled near Nigger Head,
where my father opened a road agency and
prospered beyond the dreams of avarice. He
was a reticent, saturnine man then, though his
increasing years have now somewhat relaxed
the austerity of his disposition, and I believe
that nothing but his memory of the sad event
for which I am now on trial prevents him from
manifesting a genuine hilarity.
</p><p>"Four years after we had set up the road
agency an itinerant preacher came along, and
having no other way to pay for the night's
lodging that we gave him, favored us with
an exhortation of such power that, praise God,
we were all converted to religion. My father
at once sent for his brother the Hon. William
<pb n="150" id="BieFavo150"/>
Ridley of Stockton, and on his arrival turned
over the agency to him, charging him nothing
for the franchise nor plant &mdash; the latter consisting
of a Winchester rifle, a sawed-off shotgun,
and an assortment of masks made out of flour
sacks. The family then moved to Ghost Rock
and opened a dance house. It was called 'The
Saints' Rest Hurdy-Gurdy,' and the proceedings
each night began with prayer. It was
there that my now sainted mother, by her grace
in the dance, acquired the sobriquet of 'The
Bucking Walrus.'
</p><p>"In the fall of '75 I had occasion to visit
Coyote, on the road to Mahala, and took the
stage at Ghost Rock. There were four other
passengers. About three miles beyond Nigger
Head, persons whom I identified as my
Uncle William and his two sons held up the
stage. Finding nothing in the express box,
they went through the passengers. I acted a
most honorable part in the affair, placing myself
in line with the others, holding up my
hands and permitting myself to be deprived
of forty dollars and a gold watch. From my
behavior no one could have suspected that I
knew the gentlemen who gave the entertainment.
A few days later, when I went to Nigger
Head and asked for the return of my
<pb n="151" id="BieFavo151"/>
money and watch my uncle and cousins swore
they knew nothing of the matter, and they
affected a belief that my father and I had done
the job ourselves in dishonest violation of commercial
good faith. Uncle William even
threatened to retaliate by starting an opposition
dance house at Ghost Rock. As 'The
Saints' Rest' had become rather unpopular, I
saw that this would assuredly ruin it and
prove a paying enterprise, so I told my uncle
that I was willing to overlook the past if he
would take me into the scheme and keep the
partnership a secret from my father. This
fair offer he rejected, and I then perceived
that it would be better and more satisfactory
if he were dead.
</p><p>"My plans to that end were soon perfected,
and communicating them to my dear parents
I had the gratification of receiving their approval.
My father said he was proud of me,
and my mother promised that although her
religion forbade her to assist in taking human
life I should have the advantage of her prayers
for my success. As a preliminary measure
looking to my security in case of detection I
made an application for membership in that
powerful order, the Knights of Murder, and
in due course was received as a member of the
<pb n="152" id="BieFavo152"/>
Ghost Rock commandery. On the day that
my probation ended I was for the first time
permitted to inspect the records of the order
and learn who belonged to it &mdash; all the rites of
initiation having been conducted in masks.
Fancy my delight when, in looking over the
roll of membership, I found the third name
to be that of my uncle, who indeed was junior
vice-chancellor of the order! Here was an
opportunity exceeding my wildest dreams &mdash; to
murder I could add insubordination and
treachery. It was what my good mother
would have called 'a special Providence.'
</p><p>"At about this time something occurred
which caused my cup of joy, already full, to
overflow on all sides, a circular cataract of
bliss. Three men, strangers in that locality,
were arrested for the stage robbery in which
I had lost my money and watch. They were
brought to trial and, despite my efforts to clear
them and fasten the guilt upon three of the
most respectable and worthy citizens of Ghost
Rock, convicted on the clearest proof. The
murder would now be as wanton and reasonless
as I could wish.
</p><p>"One morning I shouldered my Winchester
rifle, and going over to my uncle's house, near
Nigger Head, asked my Aunt Mary, his wife,
<pb n="153" id="BieFavo153"/>
if he were at home, adding that I had come to
kill him. My aunt replied with her peculiar
smile that so many gentleman called on that
errand and were afterward carried away without
having performed it that I must excuse
her for doubting my good faith in the matter.
She said I did not look as if I would kill anybody,
so, as a proof of good faith I leveled my
rifle and wounded a Chinaman who happened
to be passing the house. She said she knew
whole families that could do a thing of that
kind, but Bill Ridley was a horse of another
color. She said, however, that I would find
him over on the other side of the creek in the
sheep lot; and she added that she hoped the
best man would win.
</p><p>"My Aunt Mary was one of the most fair-minded women that I have ever met.
</p><p>"I found my uncle down on his knees
engaged in skinning a sheep. Seeing that he
had neither gun nor pistol handy I had not the
heart to shoot him, so I approached him,
greeted him pleasantly and struck him a
powerful blow on the head with the butt of
my rifle. I have a very good delivery and
Uncle William lay down on his side, then
rolled over on his back, spread out his fingers
and shivered. Before he could recover the use
<pb n="154" id="BieFavo154"/>
of his limbs I seized the knife that he had been
using and cut his hamstrings. You know,
doubtless, that when you sever the tend o
achillis the patient has no further use of his
leg; it is just the same as if he had no leg.
Well, I parted them both, and when he revived
he was at my service. As soon as he comprehended
the situation, he said:
</p><p>" 'Samuel, you have got the drop on me and
can afford to be generous. I have only one
thing to ask of you, and that is that you carry
me to the house and finish me in the bosom of
my family.'
</p><p>"I told him I thought that a pretty reasonable
request and I would do so if he would let
me put him into a wheat sack; he would be
easier to carry that way and if we were seen by
the neighbors en route it would cause less
remark. He agreed to that, and going to the
barn I got a sack. This, however, did not fit
him; it was too short and much wider than he;
so I bent his legs, forced his knees up against
his breast and got him into it that way, tying
the sack above his head. He was a heavy man
and I had all that I could do to get him on
my back, but I staggered along for some distance
until I came to a swing that some of the
children had suspended to the branch of an
<pb n="155" id="BieFavo155"/>
oak. Here I laid him down and sat upon him
to rest, and the sight of the rope gave me a
happy inspiration. In twenty minutes my
uncle, still in the sack, swung free to the sport
of the wind.
</p><p>"I had taken down the rope, tied one end
tightly about the mouth of the bag, thrown the
other across the limb and hauled him up about
five feet from the ground. Fastening the other
end of the rope also about the mouth of the
sack, I had the satisfaction to see my uncle
converted into a large, fine pendulum. I must
add that he was not himself entirely aware of
the nature of the change that he had undergone
in his relation to the exterior world, though in
justice to a good man's memory I ought to
say that I do not think he would in any case
have wasted much of my time in vain remonstrance.
</p><p>"Uncle William had a ram that was famous
in all that region as a fighter. It was in a state
of chronic constitutional indignation. Some
deep disappointment in early life had soured
its disposition and it had declared war upon
the whole world. To say that it would butt
anything accessible is but faintly to express the
nature and scope of its military activity: the
universe was its antagonist; its methods that
<pb n="156" id="BieFavo156"/>
of a projectile. It fought like the angels and
devils, in mid-air, cleaving the atmosphere like
a bird, describing a parabolic curve and descending
upon its victim at just the exact angle
of incidence to make the most of its velocity
and weight. Its momentum, calculated in
foot-tons, was something incredible. It had
been seen to destroy a four year old bull by a
single impact upon that animal's gnarly forehead.
No stone wall had ever been known to
resist its downward swoop; there were no trees
tough enough to stay it; it would splinter them
into matchwood and defile their leafy honors
in the dust. This irascible and implacable
brute &mdash; this incarnate thunderbolt &mdash; this monster
of the upper deep, I had seen reposing in
the shade of an adjacent tree, dreaming dreams
of conquest and glory. It was with a view to
summoning it forth to the field of honor that
I suspended its master in the manner described.
</p><p>"Having completed my preparations, I imparted
to the avuncular pendulum a gentle
oscillation, and retiring to cover behind a contiguous
rock, lifted up my voice in a long rasping
cry whose diminishing final note was
drowned in a noise like that of a swearing cat,
which emanated from the sack. Instantly that
<pb n="157" id="BieFavo157"/>
formidable sheep was upon its feet and had
taken in the military situation at a glance. In
a few moments it had approached, stamping,
to within fifty yards of the swinging foeman,
who, now retreating and anon advancing,
seemed to invite the fray. Suddenly I saw the
beast's head drop earthward as if depressed
by the weight of its enormous horns; then a
dim, white, wavy streak of sheep prolonged
itself from that spot in a generally horizontal
direction to within about four yards of a
point immediately beneath the enemy. There
it struck sharply upward, and before it had
faded from my gaze at the place whence it
had set out I heard a horrid thump and a
piercing scream, and my poor uncle shot forward,
with a slack rope higher than the limb
to which he was attached. Here the rope
tautened with a jerk, arresting his flight,
and back he swung in a breathless curve to
the other end of his arc. The ram had fallen,
a heap of indistinguishable legs, wool and
horns, but pulling itself together and dodging
as its antagonist swept downward it retired
at random, alternately shaking its head and
stamping its fore-feet. When it had backed
about the same distance as that from which
it had delivered the assault it paused again,
<pb n="158" id="BieFavo158"/>
bowed its head as if in prayer for victory and
again shot forward, dimly visible as before &mdash;
a prolonging white streak with monstrous undulations,
ending with a sharp ascension. Its
course this time was at a right angle to its
former one, and its impatience so great that
it struck the enemy before he had nearly
reached the lowest point of his arc. In consequence
he went flying round and round in
a horizontal circle whose radius was about
equal to half the length of the rope, which I
forgot to say was nearly twenty feet long. His
shrieks, crescendo in approach and diminuiendo
in recession, made the rapidity of his
revolution more obvious to the ear than to the
eye. He had evidently not yet been struck
in a vital spot. His posture in the sack and
the distance from the ground at which he
hung compelled the ram to operate upon his
lower extremities and the end of his back.
Like a plant that has struck its root into some
poisonous mineral, my poor uncle was dying
slowly upward.
</p><p>"After delivering its second blow the ram
had not again retired. The fever of battle
burned hot in its heart; its brain was intoxicated
with the wine of strife. Like a pugilist
who in his rage forgets his skill and fights
<pb n="159" id="BieFavo159"/>
ineffectively at half-arm's length, the angry
beast endeavored to reach its fleeting foe by
awkward vertical leaps as he passed overhead,
sometimes, indeed, succeeding in striking
him feebly, but more frequently overthrown
by its own misguided eagerness. But
as the impetus was exhausted and the man's
circles narrowed in scope and diminished in
speed, bringing him nearer to the ground,
these tactics produced better results, eliciting
a superior quality of screams, which I greatly
enjoyed.
</p><p>"Suddenly, as if the bugles had sung truce,
the ram suspended hostilities and walked
away, thoughtfully wrinkling and smoothing
its great aquiline nose, and occasionally cropping
a bunch of grass and slowly munching
it. It seemed to have tired of war's alarms
and resolved to beat the sword into a plowshare
and cultivate the arts of peace. Steadily
it held its course away from the field of fame
until it had gained a distance of nearly a quarter
of a mile. There it stopped and stood
with its rear to the foe, chewing its cud and
apparently half asleep. I observed, however,
an occasional slight turn of its head, as if its
apathy were more affected than real.
</p><p>"Meantime Uncle William's shrieks had
<pb n="160" id="BieFavo160"/>
abated with his motion, and nothing was
heard from him but long, low moans, and
at long intervals my name, uttered in pleading
tones exceedingly grateful to my ear.
Evidently the man had not the faintest notion
of what was being done to him, and was inexpressibly
terrified. When Death comes
cloaked in mystery he is terrible indeed. Little
by little my uncle's oscillations diminished,
and finally he hung motionless. I went to
him and was about to give him the coup de
grace, when I heard and felt a succession of
smart shocks which shook the ground like a
series of light earthquakes, and turning in the
direction of the ram, saw a long cloud of dust
approaching me with inconceivable rapidity
and alarming effect! At a distance of some
thirty yards away it stopped short, and from
the near end of it rose into the air what I
at first thought a great white bird. Its ascent
was so smooth and easy and regular that I
could not realize its extraordinary celerity,
and was lost in admiration of its grace. To
this day the impression remains that it was a
slow, deliberate movement, the ram &mdash; for it
was that animal &mdash; being upborne by some
power other than its own impetus, and supported
through the successive stages of its
<pb n="161" id="BieFavo161"/>
flight with infinite tenderness and care. My
eyes followed its progress through the air
with unspeakable pleasure, all the greater by
contrast with my former terror of its approach
by land. Onward and upward the noble animal
sailed, its head bent down almost between
its knees, its fore-feet thrown back, its hinder
legs trailing to rear like the legs of a soaring
heron.
</p><p>"At a height of forty or fifty feet, as
fond recollection presents it to view, it attained
its zenith and appeared to remain an
instant stationary; then, tilting suddenly forward
without altering the relative position of
its parts, it shot downward on a steeper and
steeper course with augmenting velocity,
passed immediately above me with a noise
like the rush of a cannon shot and struck my
poor uncle almost squarely on the top of
the head! So frightful was the impact that
not only the man's neck was broken, but the
rope too; and the body of the deceased, forced
against the earth, was crushed to pulp beneath
the awful front of that meteoric sheep! The
concussion stopped all the clocks between
Lone Hand and Dutch Dan's, and Professor
Davidson, a distinguished authority in matters
seismic, who happened to be in the vicinity,
<pb n="162" id="BieFavo162"/>
promptly explained that the vibrations
were from north to southwest.
</p><p>"Altogether, I cannot help thinking that in
point of artistic atrocity my murder of Uncle
William has seldom been excelled."
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
