<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="Bur2Nar"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;



]>

<TEI.2 id="Bur2Nar">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"Letter of Thomas Brattle, F. R. S., 1692";
from Narratives of the Witchcraft Cases, 1648-1706</title>
<title type="sort">letter of thomas brattle, f r s 1692 from narratives of the witchcraft cases 1648 1706</title>
<author>Burr, George Lincoln, 1857-1938</author>
<editor>Burr, George Lincoln, 1857-1938</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>Apex Data Services and the
University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">63</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">Bur2Nar</idno>
<date value="1998">1998</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1998 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476583</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"Letter of Thomas Brattle, F. R. S., 1692"</title>
<title level="m">Narratives of the Witchcraft Cases, 1648-1706</title>
<title type="sort">letter of thomas brattle, f r s 1692</title>
<editor>Burr, George Lincoln, 1857-1938</editor>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing
part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center
scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1692">1692</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1998-12">December 1998</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Stephen Ramsay, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item/>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">
<div1 type="work" id="d3">
<pb n="165"/>
<head>LETTER OF THOMAS BRATTLE, F. R. S., 1692</head>

<pb n="167"/>

<div2 type="introduction" id="d4">
<head>INTRODUCTION</head>


<p><hi rend="small-caps">From</hi> that April day when Mr. Lawson
closed his account it was long before another eye-witness undertook a narrative.
Yet great things were doing. At Salem accusation and hearing went on apace, and
the jails grew crowded, awaiting the session of a court. On May 14 arrived from
England President Increase Mather, bringing the new charter, and with him the
new governor, Sir William Phips. What the governor thought of the emergency
and how he dealt with it we shall presently learn from his own pen. But other
pens were earlier busy. Perhaps the most notable was that of Thomas Brattle,
who early in October addressed the following letter to some clerical
correspondent. Who this divine may have been whose questions the letter answers
is unknown: our document is not the original, but a copy without superscription,
and from its contents we can infer no more than that he lived or had lived in the
colony. But Thomas Brattle we know well. &ldquo;He was,&rdquo; wrote
President Leverett of Harvard at his death, &ldquo;a gentleman by his birth and
education of the first order in this country.&rdquo; Born at Boston, in 1658, of
wealthy parentage, a graduate and a master of arts of Harvard, then a traveller
and a student abroad, he won such distinction as a mathematician, and notably as
an astronomer, as to be made a member of the Royal Society, and was in close
touch with the world of scholars; but his career was that of an opulent and
cultivated Boston merchant, and for twenty years, from 1693 to his death in
1713, he was treasurer of Harvard College. &ldquo;In the Church,&rdquo; said
of him the Boston <hi rend="italic">News-Letter</hi>, &ldquo;he was
known and valued for his Catholick Charity to all of the reformed


<pb n="168"/>


Religion, but more especially his great Veneration for the Church of England,
although his general and more constant communion was with the
Nonconformists.&rdquo; In other words, he was of the liberal party in religion
and politics, an eminent opponent of the Puritan theocracy, and he did not escape
the epithets &ldquo;apostate&rdquo; and &ldquo;infidel.&rdquo;</p>


<p>The letter here printed did not see print in his own day; but that the present
copy exists suggests that it may have been meant to circulate in
manuscript,<ref target="n43">[43]</ref> and
it is not impossible that it was even written for that purpose. Yet if so, we may
be sure it was used with discretion. It was his grand-nephew, the then well-known
Thomas Brattle, Esq., of Cambridge, who late in the eighteenth century
communicated it to the Massachusetts Historical Society.<ref target="n44">[44]</ref> From that manuscript
copy it is here reprinted.</p>


<note id="n43"><seg type="note-symbol">[43].</seg> <p>The suggestion is that of Sibley, in his sketch of Brattle's life
(<hi rend="italic">Harvard Graduates</hi>, II. 489-498), the best summary of
what is known of him. That the extant copy is without superscription, and signed
by initials only, may point to such a use. It must not be forgotten that it was
written on the eve of the session of the General Court.</p></note>

<note id="n44"><seg type="note-symbol">[44].</seg> <p>It was first published in that society's <hi rend="italic">Collections</hi>, V. 61-79.</p></note>
</div2>
<pb n="169"/>

<div2 type="section" id="d5">
<head>LETTER OF THOMAS BRATTLE, F. R. S., 1692</head>
<opener>
<dateline><date value="1692-10-08"><hi rend="italic">October</hi> 8, 1692.</date></dateline>
<salute><hi rend="italic">Reverend Sir</hi>,</salute>
</opener>

<p><hi rend="small-caps">Your's</hi> I received the other day, and am
very ready to serve you to my uttmost. I should be very loath to bring myself into
any snare by my freedom with you, and therefore hope that you will put the best
construction on what I write, and secure me from such as would interprett my
lines otherwise than they are designed. Obedience to lawfull authority I evermore
accounted a great duty; and willingly I would not practise any thing that might
thwart and contradict such a principle. Too many are ready to despise dominions,
and speak evil of Dignities; and I am sure the mischiefs, which arise from a
factious and rebellious spirit, are very sad and notorious; insomuch that I would
sooner bite my finger's ends than willingly cast dirt on authority, or any way
offer reproach to it: Far, therefore, be it from me, to have any thing to do with
those men your letter mentions, whom you acknowledge to be men of a factious
spirit, and never more in their element than when they are declaiming against
men in public place, and contriving methods that tend to the disturbance of the
common peace. I never accounted it a credit to my cause, to have the good liking
of such men. <hi rend="italic">My son!</hi> (says Solomon)
<hi rend="italic">fear thou the Lord and the King, and meddle not with them that
are given to change</hi>. Prov. xxiv. 21. However, Sir, I never thought Judges
infallible; but reckoned that they, as well as private men, might err; and that
when they were guilty of erring, standers by, who possibly had not half their
judgment, might, notwithstanding, be able to detect and behold their errors. And
furthermore, when errors of that nature are thus detected and observed, I never
thought it an interfering with dutifullness and subjection for one man to
communicate his thoughts to another thereabout; and with modesty


<pb n="170"/>


and due reverence to debate the premised failings; at least, when errours are
fundamental, and palpably pervert the great end of authority and government: for
as to circumstantial errours, I must confesse my principle is, that it is the duty of
a good subject to cover with his silence a multitude of them. But I shall no longer
detain you with my preface, but passe to some things you look for, and whether
you expect such freedome from me, yea or no, yet shall you find, that I am very
open to communicate my thoughts unto you, and in plain terms to tell you what
my opinion is of the Salem proceedings.</p>


<p>First, as to the method which the Salem Justices do take in their
examinations, it is truly this: A warrant being issued out to apprehend the persons
that are charged and complained of by the afflicted children, (as they are called);
said persons are brought before the Justices, (the afflicted being present.) The
Justices ask the apprehended why they afflict those poor children; to which the
apprehended answer, they do not afflict them. The Justices order the apprehended
to look upon the said children, which accordingly they do; and at the time of that
look, (I dare not say by that look, as the Salem Gentlemen do) the afflicted are
cast into a fitt. The apprehended are then blinded, and ordered to touch the
afflicted; and at that touch, tho' not by the touch, (as above) the afflicted
ordinarily do come out of their fitts. The afflicted persons then declare and
affirm, that the apprehended have afflicted them; upon which the apprehended
persons, tho' of never so good repute, are forthwith committed to prison, on
suspicion for witchcraft. One of the Salem Justices<ref target="n45">[45]</ref> was pleased to tell Mr.
Alden,<ref target="n46">[46]</ref> (when upon his examination) that truly he had been acquainted with him
these many years; and had always accounted him a good man; but indeed now he
should be obliged to change his opinion. This, there are more than one or two did
hear, and are ready to swear to, if not in so many words, yet as to its natural and
plain meaning. He saw reason to change his opinion of Mr. Alden, because that
at the time he touched the poor child, the poor child came out of her fitt.


<pb n="171"/>


I suppose his Honour never made the experiment, whether there was not as much
virtue in his own hand, as there was in Mr. Alden's, to cure by a touch. I know
a man that will venture two to one with any Salemite whatever, that let the matter
be duly managed, and the afflicted person shall come out of her fitt upon the
touch of the most religious hand in Salem. It is worthily noted by some, that at
some times the afflicted will not presently come out of their fitts upon the touch
of the suspected; and then, forsooth, they are ordered by the Justices to grasp
hard, harder yet, etc. insomuch that at length the afflicted come out of their fitts;
and the reason is very good, because that a touch of any hand, and processe of
time, will work the cure; infallibly they will do it, as experience teaches.</p>


<p>I cannot but condemn this method of the Justices, of making this touch of
the hand a rule to discover witchcraft; because I am fully persuaded that it is
sorcery, and a superstitious method, and that which we have no rule for, either
from reason or religion. The Salem Justices, at least some of them, do assert, that
the cure of the afflicted persons is a natural effect of this touch; and they are so
well instructed in the Cartesian philosophy, and in the doctrine of <hi
rend="italic">effluvia</hi>, that they undertake to give a demonstration how
this touch does cure the afflicted persons; and the account they give of it is this;
that by this touch, the venemous and malignant particles, that were ejected from
the eye, do, by this means, return to the body whence they came, and so leave
the afflicted persons pure and whole. I must confesse to you, that I am no small
admirer of the Cartesian philosophy; but yet I have not so learned it. Certainly
this is a strain that it will by no means allow of.</p>


<p>I would fain know of these Salem Gentlemen, but as yet could never know,
how it comes about, that if these apprehended persons are witches, and, by a look
of the eye, do cast the afflicted into their fitts by poisoning them, how it comes
about, I say, that, by a look of their eye, they do not cast others into fitts, and
poison others by their looks; and in particular, tender, fearfull women, who often
are beheld by them, and as likely as any in the whole world to receive an ill
impression from them. This Salem philosophy, some men may call the


<pb n="172"/>


new philosophy; but I think it rather deserves the name of Salem superstition and
sorcery, and it is not fitt to be named in a land of such light as New-England is.
I think the matter might be better solved another way; but I shall not make any
attempt that way, further than to say, that these afflicted children, (as they are
called,) do hold correspondence with the devill, even in the esteem and account
of the S. G.;<ref target="n47">[47]</ref> for when the black man, <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> (say
these gentlemen,) the Devill, does appear to them, they ask him many questions,
and accordingly give information to the inquirer; and if this is not holding
correspondence with the devill, and something worse, I know not what is.</p>


<p>But furthermore, I would fain know of these Salem Justices what need there
is of further proof and evidence to convict and condemn these apprehended
persons, than this look and touch, if so be they are so certain that this falling
down and arising up, when there is a look and a touch, are natural effects of the
said look and touch, and so a perfect demonstration and proof of witchcraft in
those persons. What can the Jury or Judges desire more, to convict any man of
witchcraft, than a plain demonstration, that the said man is a witch? Now if this
look and touch, circumstanced as before, be a plain demonstration, (as their
Philosophy teaches,) what need they seek for further evidences, when, after all,
it can be but a demonstration?</p>


<p>But let this pass with the S. G. for never so plain and natural a
demonstration; yet certain is it, that the reasonable part of the world, when
acquainted herewith, will laugh at the demonstration, and conclude that the said
S. G. are actually possessed, at least, with ignorance and folly.</p>


<p>I most admire<ref target="n48">[48]</ref> that Mr. N. N.<ref target="n49">[49]</ref> the Reverend Teacher at Salem, who was
educated at the School of Knowledge, and is certainly a learned, a charitable, and
a good man, though all the devils in Hell, and all the possessed girls in Salem,
should say to the contrary; at him, (I say,) I do most admire; that he should cry
up the above mentioned philosophy after the manner that he does. I can assure
you, that I can bring you more than two, or twice two, (very credible persons)
that will


<pb n="173"/>


affirm, that they have heard him vindicate the above mentioned demonstration as
very reasonable.</p>


<p>Secondly, with respect to the confessours, (as they are improperly called,)
or such as confesse themselves to be witches, (the second thing you inquire into
in your letter), there are now about fifty of them in Prison; many of which I have
again and again seen and heard; and I cannot but tell you, that my faith is strong
concerning them, that they are deluded, imposed upon, and under the influence
of some evill spirit; and therefore unfitt to be evidences either against themselves,
or any one else. I now speak of one sort of them, and of others afterward.</p>


<p>These confessours, (as they are called,) do very often contradict
themselves, as inconsistently as is usual for any crazed, distempered person to do.
This the S. G. do see and take notice of; and even the Judges themselves have,
at some times, taken these confessours in flat lyes, or contradictions, even in the
Courts; By reason of which, one would have thought, that the Judges would have
frowned upon the said confessours, discarded them, and not minded one tittle of
any thing that they said; but instead thereof, (as sure as we are men,) the Judges
vindicate these confessours, and salve their contradictions, by proclaiming, that
the Devill takes away their memory, and imposes upon their brain. If this reflects
any where, I am very sorry for it: I can but assure you, that, upon the word of
an honest man, it is truth, and that I can bring you many credible persons to
witnesse it, who have been eye and ear wittnesses to these things.</p>


<p>These confessours then, at least some of them, even in the Judges' own
account, are under the influence of the Devill; and the brain of these Confessours
is imposed upon by the Devill, even in the Judges' account. But now, if, in the
Judges' account, these confessours are under the influence of the Devill, and their
brains are affected and imposed upon by the Devill, so that they are not their own
men, why then should these Judges, or any other men, make such account of, and
set so much by, the words of these Confessours, as they do? In short, I argue
thus:</p>


<p>If the Devill does actually take away the memory of them at some times,
certainly the Devill, at other times, may very


<pb n="174"/>


reasonably be thought to affect their fancyes, and to represent false ideas to their
imagination. But now, if it be thus granted, that the Devill is able to represent
false ideas (to speak vulgarly) to the imaginations of the confessours, what man
of sense will regard the confessions, or any of the words, of these
confessours?</p>


<p>The great cry of many of our neighbours now is, What, will you not
believe the confessours? Will you not believe men and women who confesse that
they have signed to the Devill's book? that they were baptized by the Devill; and
that they were at the mock-sacrament once and again? What! will you not believe
that this is witchcraft, and that such and such men are witches, altho' the
confessours do own and assert it?</p>


<p>Thus, I say, many of our good neighbours do argue; but methinks they
might soon be convinced that there is nothing at all in all these their arguings, if
they would but duly consider of the premises.</p>


<p>In the mean time, I think we must rest satisfyed in it, and be thankfull to
God for it, that all men are not thus bereft of their senses; but that we have here
and there considerate and thinking men, who will not thus be imposed upon, and
abused, by the subtle endeavours of the crafty one.</p>


<p>In the next place, I proceed to the form of their inditements, and the Trials
thereupon.</p>


<p>The Inditement runs for sorcery and witchcraft, acted upon the body of
such an one, (say M. Warren), at such a particular time, (say April 14, '92,) and
at divers other times before and after, whereby the said M. W. is wasted and
consumed, pined, etc.</p>


<p>Now for the proof of the said sorcery and witchcraft, the prisoner at the bar
pleading not guilty.</p>


<p>1. The afflicted persons are brought into Court; and after much patience
and pains taken with them, do take their oaths, that the prisoner at the bar did
afflict them: And here I think it very observable, that often, when the afflicted
do mean and intend only the appearance and shape of such an one, (say G.
Proctour) yet they positively swear that G. Proctour did afflict them; and they
have been allowed so to do; as tho' there was no real difference between G.
Proctour and the shape of G.

<pb n="175"/>




Proctour. This, methinks, may readily prove a stumbling block to the Jury, lead
them into a very fundamental errour, and occasion innocent blood, yea the
innocentest blood imaginable, to be in great danger. Whom it belongs unto, to be
eyes unto the blind, and to remove such stumbling blocks, I know full well; and
yet you and every one else, do know as well as I who do not.<ref target="n50">[50]</ref></p>


<p>2. The confessours do declare what they know of the said prisoner; and
some of the confessours are allowed to give their oaths; a thing which I believe
was never heard of in this world; that such as confesse themselves to be witches,
to have renounced God and Christ, and all that is sacred, should yet be allowed
and ordered to swear by the name of the great God! This indeed seemeth to me
to be a grosse taking of God's name in vain. I know the S. G. do say, that there
is hopes that the said Confessours have repented; I shall only say, that if they
have repented, it is well for themselves; but if they have not, it is very ill for you
know who. But then,</p>


<p>3. Whoever can be an evidence against the prisoner at the bar is ordered
to come into Court; and here it scarce ever fails but that evidences, of one nature
and another, are brought in, tho', I think, all of them altogether aliene to the
matter of inditement; for they none of them do respect witchcraft upon the bodyes
of the afflicted, which is the alone matter of charge in the inditement.</p>


<p>4. They are searched by a Jury; and as to some of them, the Jury brought
in, that [on] such or such a place there was a preternatural excrescence. And I
wonder what person there is, whether man or woman, of whom it cannot be said
but that, in some part of their body or other, there is a preternatural excrescence.
The term is a very general and inclusive term.</p>


<p>Some of the S. G. are very forward to censure and condemn the poor
prisoner at the bar, because he sheds no tears: but such betray great ignorance in
the nature of passion, and as great heedlessnesse as to common passages of a
man's life. Some there are who never shed tears; others there are that ordinarily
shed tears upon light occasions, and yet for their lives cannot shed a tear when
the deepest sorrow is upon their hearts; and who is there that knows not these
things? Who

<pb n="176"/>




knows not that an ecstasye of Joy will sometimes fetch teares, when as the quite
contrary passion will shutt them close up? Why then should any be so silly and
foolish as to take an argument from this appearance? But this is by the by. In
short, the prisoner at the bar is indited for sorcery and witchcraft acted upon the
bodyes of the afflicted. Now, for the proof of this, I reckon that the only
pertinent evidences brought in are the evidences of the said afflicted.</p>


<p>It is true, that over and above the evidences of the afflicted persons, there
are many evidences brought in, against the prisoner at the bar; either that he was
at a witch meeting, or that he performed things which could not be done by an
ordinary natural power; or that she sold butter to a saylor, which proving bad at
sea, and the seamen exclaiming against her, she appeared, and soon after there
was a storm, or the like. But what if there were ten thousand evidences of this
nature; how do they prove the matter of inditement! And if they do not reach the
matter of inditement, then I think it is clear, that the prisoner at the bar is brought
in guilty, and condemned, merely from the evidences of the afflicted
persons.</p>


<p>The S. G. will by no means allow, that any are brought in guilty, and
condemned, by virtue of spectre Evidence, (as it is called,) <hi
rend="italic">i. e.</hi> the evidence of these afflicted persons, who are said
to have spectral eyes; but whether it is not purely by virtue of these spectre
evidences, that these persons are found guilty, (considering what before has been
said,) I leave you, and any man of sense, to judge and determine. When any man
is indited for murthering the person of A. B. and all the direct evidence be, that
the said man pistolled the shadow of the said A. B. tho' there be never so many
evidences that the said person murthered C. D., E. F. and ten more persons, yet
all this will not amount to a legal proof, that he murthered A. B.; and upon that
inditement, the person cannot be legally brought in guilty of the said inditement;
it must be upon this supposition, that the evidence of a man's pistolling the
shadow of A. B. is a legal evidence to prove that the said man did murther the
person of A. B. Now no man will be so much out of his witts as to make this a
legal evidence; and yet this seems to be our case; and how to apply it is very easy
and obvious.</p>


<pb n="177"/>


<p>As to the late executions,<ref target="n51">[51]</ref> I shall only tell you, that in the opinion of many
unprejudiced, considerate and considerable spectatours, some of the condemned
went out of the world not only with as great protestations, but also with as good
shews of innocency, as men could do.</p>


<p>They protested their innocency as in the presence of the great God, whom
forthwith they were to appear before: they wished, and declared their wish, that
their blood might be the last innocent blood shed upon that account. With great
affection<ref target="n52">[52]</ref> they intreated Mr. C. M.<ref target="n53">[53]</ref> to pray with them: they prayed that God
would discover what witchcrafts were among us; they forgave their accusers; they
spake without reflection on Jury and Judges, for bringing them in guilty, and
condemning them: they prayed earnestly for pardon for all other sins, and for an
interest in the pretious blood of our dear Redeemer; and seemed to be very
sincere, upright, and sensible of their circumstances on all accounts; especially
Proctor and Willard, whose whole management of themselves, from the Goal to
the Gallows, and whilst at the Gallows, was very affecting and melting to the
hearts of some considerable Spectatours, whom I could mention to
you: &mdash; but they are executed, and so I leave them.</p>


<p>Many things I cannot but admire and wonder at, an account of which I shall
here send you.</p>


<p>And 1. I do admire that some particular persons, and particularly Mrs.
Thatcher of Boston,<ref target="n54">[54]</ref> should be much complained of by the afflicted persons, and
yet that the Justices should never issue out their warrants to apprehend them,

<pb n="178"/>




when as upon the same account they issue out their warrants for the apprehending
and imprisoning many others.</p>


<p>This occasions much discourse and many hot words, and is a very great
scandal and stumbling block to many good people; certainly distributive Justice
should have its course, without respect to persons; and altho' the said Mrs.
Thatcher be mother in law to Mr. Corwin,<ref target="n55">[55]</ref> who is one of the Justices and
Judges, yet if Justice and conscience do oblige them to apprehend others on the
account of the afflicted their complaints, I cannot see how, without injustice and
violence to conscience, Mrs. Thatcher can escape, when it is well known how
much she is, and has been, complained of.</p>


<p>2. I cannot but admire that Mr. H. U.<ref target="n56">[56]</ref> (whom we all think innocent,)
should yet be apprehended on this account, and ordered to prison, by a mittimus
under Mr. Lynd's<ref target="n57">[57]</ref> his hand, and yet that he should be suffered, for above a
fortnight, to be in a private house; and after that, to quitt the house, the town,
and the Province, and yet that authority should not take effectual notice of it.
Methinks that same Justice, that actually imprisoned others, and refused bail for
them on any terms, should not be satisfyed without actually imprisoning Mr. U.
and refusing bail for him, when his case is known to be the very same with the
case of those others.</p>


<p>If he may be suffered to go away, why may not others? If others may not
be suffered to go, how in Justice can he be allowed herein?</p>


<p>3. If our Justices do think that Mrs. C.<ref target="n58">[58]</ref> Mr. E.<ref target="n59">[59]</ref> and his
wife, Mr. A.<ref target="n60">[60]</ref>
and others, were capital offenders, and justly imprisoned on a capital account, I
do admire that the said Justices should hear of their escape from prison, and
where they are gone and entertained, and yet not send forthwith to the said
places,<ref target="n61">[61]</ref> for the surrendering of them, that Justice might be done them. In other
Capitalls<ref target="n62">[62]</ref> this has been practised;

<pb n="179"/>




why then is it not practised in this case, if really judged to be so heinous
as is made for?</p>


<p>4. I cannot but admire, that any should go with their distempered friends
and relations to the afflicted children, to know what their distempered friends ayl;
whether they are not bewitched; who it is that afflicts them, and the like. It is
true, I know no reason why these afflicted may not be consulted as well as any
other, if so be that it was only their natural and ordinary knowledge that was had
recourse to: but it is not on this notion that these afflicted children are sought
unto; but as they have a supernatural knowledge; a knowledge which they obtain
by their holding correspondence with spectres or evill spirits, as they themselves
grant. This consulting of these afflicted children, as abovesaid, seems to me to
be a very grosse evill, a real abomination, not fitt to be known in N.
E.<ref target="n63">[63]</ref> and yet
is a thing practised, not only by Tom and John &mdash; I mean the ruder and
more ignorant sort &mdash; but by many who professe high, and passe among us
for some of the better sort. This is that which aggravates the evil, and makes it
heinous and tremendous; and yet this is not the worst of it, for, as sure as I now
write to you, even some of our civil leaders, and spiritual teachers, who, (I
think,) should punish and preach down such sorcery and wickedness, do yet allow
of, encourage, yea, and practise this very abomination.</p>


<p>I know there are several worthy Gentlemen in Salem, who account this
practise as an abomination, have trembled to see the methods of this nature which
others have used, and have declared themselves to think the practise to be very
evill and corrupt; but all avails little with the abettours of the said practice.</p>


<p>A person from Boston, of no small note, carried up his child to Salem,
(near 20 miles,) on purpose that he might consult the afflicted about his child;
which accordingly he did; and the afflicted told him, that his child was afflicted
by Mrs. Cary and Mrs. Obinson.<ref target="n64">[64]</ref> The man returned to Boston, and went
forthwith to the Justices for a warrant to seise the said

<pb n="180"/>




Obinson, (the said Cary being out of the way); but the Boston Justices saw reason
to deny a warrant. The Rev. Mr. I. M.<ref target="n65">[65]</ref> of Boston, took occasion severely to
reprove the said man; asking him whether there was not a God in Boston, that he
should go to the Devill in Salem for advice; warning him very seriously against
such naughty practices; which, I hope, proved to the conviction and good of the
said person; if not, his blood will be upon his own head.</p>


<p>This consulting of these afflicted children, about their sick, was the
unhappy begining of the unhappy troubles at poor Andover: Horse and man were
sent up to Salem Village, from the said Andover, for some of the said afflicted;
and more than one or two of them were carried down to see Ballard's
wife,<ref target="n66">[66]</ref> and
to tell who it was that did afflict her. I understand that the said B. took advice
before he took this method; but what pity was it, that he should meet with, and
hearken to such bad Counsellours? Poor Andover does now rue the day that ever
the said afflicted went among them; they lament their folly, and are an object of
great pity and commiseration. Capt. B.<ref target="n67">[67]</ref>
and Mr. St.<ref target="n68">[68]</ref> are complained of by the
afflicted, have left the town, and do abscond. Deacon Fry's wife, Capt'n
Osgood's wife, and some others, remarkably pious and good people in repute, are
apprehended and imprisoned; and that that is more admirable, the forementioned
women are become a kind of confessours, being first brought thereto by the
urgings and arguings of their good husbands, who, having taken up that corrupt
and highly pernicious opinion, that whoever were accused by the afflicted, were
guilty, did break charity with their dear wives, upon their being accused, and
urge them to confesse their guilt; which so far prevailed with them as to make
them say, they were afraid of their being in the snare of the Devill; and which,
through the rude and bar

<pb n="181"/>




barous methods<ref target="n1">[*]</ref> that were afterwards used at Salem, issued in somewhat plainer
degrees of confession, and was attended with imprisonment. The good Deacon
and Captain are now sensible of the errour they were in; do grieve and mourn
bitterly, that they should break their charity with their wives, and urge them to
confesse themselves witches. They now see and acknowledge their rashnesse and
uncharitablenesse, and are very fitt objects for the pity and prayers of every good
Christian. Now I am writing concerning Andover, I cannot omit the opportunity
of sending you this information; that Whereas there is a report spread abroad the
country, how that they were much addicted to Sorcery in the said town, and that
there were fourty men in it that could raise the Devill as well as any astrologer,
and the like; after the best search that I can make into it, it proves a mere
slander, and a very unrighteous imputation.</p>


<p>The Rev'd Elders of the said place were much surprized upon their hearing
of the said Report, and faithfully made inquiry about it; but the whole of
naughtiness, that they could discover and find out, was only this, that two or
three girls had foolishly made use of the sieve and scissors,<ref target="n70">[70]</ref> as children have
done in other towns. This method of the girls I do not Justifye in any measure;
but yet I think it very hard and unreasonable, that a town should lye under the
blemish and

<pb n="182"/>




scandal of sorceryes and conjuration, merely for the inconsiderate practices of
two or three girls in the said town.</p>


<p>5. I cannot but admire that the Justices, whom I think to be well-meaning
men, should so far give ear to the Devill, as merely upon his authority to issue
out their warrants, and apprehend people. Liberty was evermore accounted the
great priviledge of an Englishman; but certainly, if the Devill will be heard
against us, and his testimony taken, to the siezing and apprehending of us, our
liberty vanishes, and we are fools if we boast of our liberty. Now, that the
Justices have thus far given ear to the Devill, I think may be mathematically
demonstrated to any man of common sense: And for the demonstration and proof
hereof, I desire, only, that these two things may be duly considered, <hi
rend="italic">viz.</hi></p>


<p>1. That several persons have been apprehended purely upon the complaints
of these afflicted, to whom the afflicted were perfect strangers, and had not the
least knowledge of imaginable, before they were apprehended.</p>


<p>2. That the afflicted do own and assert, and the Justices do grant, that the
Devill does inform and tell the afflicted the names of those persons that are thus
unknown unto them. Now these two things being duly considered, I think it will
appear evident to any one, that the Devill's information is the fundamental
testimony that is gone upon in the apprehending of the aforesaid people.</p>


<p>If I believe such or such an assertion as comes immediately from the
Minister of God in the pulpitt, because it is the word of the everliving God, I
build my faith on God's testimony: and if I practise upon it, this my practice is
properly built on the word of God: even so in the case before us,</p>


<p>If I believe the afflicted persons as informed by the Devill, and act
thereupon, this my act may properly be said to be grounded upon the testimony
or information of the Devill. And now, if things are thus, I think it ought to be
for a lamentation to you and me, and all such as would be accounted good
Christians.</p>


<p>If any should see the force of this argument, and upon it say, (as I heard
a wise and good Judge once propose,) that they know not but that God almighty,
or a good spirit, does give this information to these afflicted persons; I make
answer

<pb n="183"/>




thereto, and say, that it is most certain that it is neither almighty God, nor yet
any good Spirit, that gives this information; and my Reason is good, because God
is a God of truth; and the good Spirits will not lye; whereas these informations
have several times proved false, when the accused were brought before the
afflicted.</p>


<p>6. I cannot but admire that these afflicted persons should be so much
countenanced and encouraged in their accusations as they are: I often think of the
Groton woman, that was afflicted, an account of which we have in print, and is
a most certain truth, not to be doubted of.<ref target="n71">[71]</ref> I shall only say, that there was as
much ground, in the hour of it, to countenance the said Groton woman, and to
apprehend and imprison, on her accusations, as there is now to countenance these
afflicted persons, and to apprehend and imprison on their accusations. But
furthermore, it is worthy of our deepest consideration, that in the conclusion,
(after multitudes have been imprisoned, and many have been put to death,) these
afflicted persons should own that all was a mere fancy and delusion of the
Devill's, as the Groton woman did own and acknowledge with respect to herself;
if, I say, in after times, this be acknowledged by them, how can the Justices,
Judges, or any else concerned in these matters, look back upon these things
without the greatest of sorrow and grief imaginable? I confesse to you, it makes
me tremble when I seriously consider of this thing. I have heard that the chief
judge<ref target="n72">[72]</ref> has expressed himself very hardly of the accused woman at Groton, as
tho' he believed her to be a witch to this day; but by such as knew the said
woman, this is judged a very uncharitable opinion of the

<pb n="184"/>




said Judge, and I do not understand that any are proselyted thereto.</p>


<p>Rev'd Sir, these things I cannot but admire and wonder at. Now, if so be
it is the effect of my dullness that I thus admire, I hope you will pity, not censure
me: but if, on the contrary, these things are just matter of admiration, I know that
you will join with me in expressing your admiration hereat.</p>


<p>The chief Judge is very zealous in these proceedings, and says, he is very
clear as to all that hath as yet been acted by this Court, and, as far as ever I
could perceive, is very impatient in hearing any thing that looks another way. I
very highly honour and reverence the wisdome and integrity of the said Judge,
and hope that this matter shall not diminish my veneration for his honour;
however, I cannot but say, my great fear is, that wisdome and counsell are
withheld from his honour as to this matter, which yet I look upon not so much
as a Judgment to his honour as to this poor land.</p>


<p>But altho' the Chief Judge, and some of the other Judges, be very zealous
in these proceedings, yet this you may take for a truth, that there are several
about the Bay, men for understanding, Judgment, and Piety, inferiour to few, (if
any,) in N. E. that do utterly condemn the said proceedings, and do freely deliver
their Judgment in the case to be this, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> that these
methods will utterly ruine and undoe poor N. E. I shall nominate some of these
to you, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> The hon'ble Simon Bradstreet, Esq.
(our late Governor); the hon'ble Thomas Danforth, Esq. (our late Deputy
Governor); the Rev'd Mr. Increase Mather, and the Rev'd Mr. Samuel Willard.
Major N. Saltonstall, Esq. who was one of the Judges, has left the Court, and is
very much dissatisfyed with the proceedings of it. Excepting Mr. Hale, Mr.
Noyes, and Mr. Parris, the Rev'd Elders, almost throughout the whole Country,
are very much dissatisfyed. Several of the late Justices, <hi
rend="italic">viz.</hi> Thomas Graves, Esq. N. Byfield, Esq. Francis
Foxcroft, Esq. are much dissatisfyed; also several of the present Justices; and in
particular, some of the Boston Justices, were resolved rather to throw up their
commissions than be active in disturbing the liberty of their Majesties' subjects,
merely on the accusations of these afflicted, possessed children.</p>


<pb n="185"/>


<p>Finally; the principal Gentlemen in Boston, and thereabout, are generally
agreed that irregular and dangerous methods have been taken as to these
matters.</p>


<p>Sir, I would not willingly lead you into any errour, and therefore would
desire you to note,</p>


<p>1. That when I call these afflicted &ldquo;the afflicted children,&rdquo; I
would not be understood as though I meant, that all that are afflicted are <hi
rend="italic">children</hi>: there are several young men and women that
are afflicted, as well as children: but this term has most prevailed among us,
because of the younger sort that were first afflicted, and therefore I make use of
it.</p>


<p>2. That when I speak of the Salem Gentlemen, I would not be understood
as tho' I meant every Individual Gentleman in Salem; nor yet as tho' I meant,
that there were no men but in Salem that run upon these notions: some term they
must have, and this seems not improper, because in Salem this sort of Gentlemen
does most abound.</p>


<p>3. That other Justices in the Country, besides the Salem Justices, have
issued out their warrants, and imprisoned, on the accusations of the afflicted as
aforesaid; and therefore, when I speak of the Salem Justices, I do not mean them
exclusively.</p>


<p>4. That as to the above mentioned Judges, that are commissionated for this
Court at Salem, five of them do belong to Suffolk county; four of which five do
belong to Boston;<ref target="n73">[73]</ref> and therefore I see no reason why Boston should talk of
Salem, as tho' their own Judges had had no hand in these proceedings at
Salem.</p>


<p>Nineteen persons have now been executed, and one pressed to death for a
mute: seven more are condemned; two of which are reprieved, because they
pretend their being with child; one, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> Mrs.
Bradbury of Salisbury, from the intercession of some friends; and two or three
more, because they are confessours.<ref target="n74">[74]</ref></p>


<p>The Court is adjourned to the first Tuesday in November, then to be kept
at Salem; between this and then will be [the]

<pb n="186"/>




great assembly,<ref target="n75">[75]</ref> and this matter will be a peculiar matter of their agitation. I
think it is matter of earnest supplication and prayer to almighty God, that he
would afford his gracious presence to the said assembly, and direct them aright
in this weighty matter. Our hopes are here; and if, at this Juncture, God does not
graciously appear for us, I think we may conclude that N. E. is undone and
undone.</p>


<p>I am very sensible, that it is irksome and disagreeable to go back, when a
man's doing so is an implication that he has been walking in a wrong path:
however, nothing is more honourable than, upon due conviction, to retract and
undo, (so far as may be,) what has been amiss and irregular.</p>


<p>I would hope that, in the conclusion, both the Judges and Justices will see
and acknowledge that such were their best friends and advisers as disswaded from
the methods which they have taken, tho' hitherto they have been angry with them,
and apt to speak very hardly of them.</p>


<p>I cannot but highly applaud, and think it our duty to be very thankfull, for
the endeavours of several Elders,<ref target="n76">[76]</ref> whose lips, (I think,) should preserve
knowledge, and whose counsell should, I think, have been more regarded, in a
case of this nature, than as yet it has been: in particular, I cannot but think very
honourably of the endeavours of a Rev'd person in Boston,<ref target="n77">[77]</ref> whose good affection
to his countrey in general,

<pb n="187"/>




and spiritual relation to three of the Judges in particular, has made him very
solicitous and industrious in this matter; and I am fully persuaded, that had his
notions and proposals been hearkened to, and followed, when these troubles were
in their birth, in an ordinary way, they would never have grown unto that heigth
which now they have. He has as yet mett with little but unkindness, abuse, and
reproach from many men; but I trust that, in after times, his wisdome and service
will find a more universal acknowledgment; and if not, his reward is with the
Lord.</p>


<p>Two or three things I should have hinted to you before, but they slipped my
thoughts in their proper place.</p>


<p>Many of these afflicted persons, who have scores of strange fitts in a day,
yet in the intervals of time are hale and hearty, robust and lusty, as tho' nothing
had afflicted them. I Remember that when the chief Judge gave the first Jury their
charge, he told them, that they were not to mind whether the bodies of the said
afflicted were really pined and consumed, as was expressed in the inditement; but
whether the said afflicted did not suffer from the accused such afflictions as
naturally

<pb n="188"/>




<hi rend="italic">tended</hi> to their being pined and consumed, wasted,
etc. This, (said he,) is a pining and consuming in the sense of the law. I add
not.</p>


<p>Furthermore: These afflicted persons do say, and often have declared it,
that they can see Spectres when their eyes are shutt, as well as when they are
open. This one thing I evermore accounted as very observable, and that which
might serve as a good key to unlock the nature of these mysterious troubles, if
duly improved by us. Can they see Spectres when their eyes are shutt? I am sure
they lye, at least speak falsely, if they say so; for the thing, in nature, is an utter
impossibility. It is true, they may strongly fancye, or have things represented to
their imagination, when their eyes are shutt; and I think this is all which ought
to be allowed to these blind, nonsensical girls; and if our officers and Courts have
apprehended, imprisoned, condemned, and executed our guiltlesse neighbours,
certainly our errour is great, and we shall rue it in the conclusion. There are two
or three other things that I have observed in and by these afflicted persons, which
make me strongly suspect that the Devill imposes upon their brains, and deludes
their fancye and imagination; and that

<pb n="189"/>




the Devill's book (which they say has been offered them) is a mere fancye of
theirs, and no reality: That the witches' meeting, the Devill's Baptism, and mock
sacraments, which they oft speak of, are nothing else but the effect of their
fancye, depraved and deluded by the Devill, and not a Reality to be regarded or
minded by any wise man. And whereas the Confessours have owned and asserted
the said meetings, the said Baptism, and mock Sacrament, (which the S. G. and
some others, make much account of) I am very apt to think, that, did you know
the circumstances of the said Confessours, you would not be swayed thereby, any
otherwise than to be confirmed, that all is perfect Devilism, and an Hellish design
to ruine and destroy this poor land: For whereas there are of the said Confessours
55 in number, some of them are known to be distracted, crazed women,
something of which you may see by a petition lately offered to the chief Judge,
a copy whereof I may now send you;<ref target="n78">[78]</ref> others of them denyed their guilt, and
maintained their innocency for above eighteen hours, after most violent,
distracting, and draggooning<ref target="n79">[79]</ref> methods had been used with them, to make them
confesse. Such methods they were, that more than one of the said confessours did
since tell many, with teares in their eyes, that they thought their very lives would
have gone out of their bodyes; and wished that they might have been cast into the
lowest dungeon, rather than be tortured with such repeated buzzings and
chuckings and unreasonable urgings as they were treated withal.</p>


<p>They soon recanted their confessions, acknowledging, with sorrow and
grief, that it was an hour of great temptation with them; and I am very apt to
think, that as for five or six of the said confessours, if they are not very good
Christian women, it will be no easy matter to find so many good Christian
women in N. E. But, finally, as to about thirty of these fiftyfive Confessours,
they are possessed (I reckon) with the Devill, and afflicted as the children are,
and therefore not fitt to be regarded as to any thing they say of themselves or
others. And whereas the S. G. do say that these confessours made

<pb n="190"/>




their Confessions before they were afflicted, it is absolutely contrary to universal
experience, as far as ever I could understand. It is true, that some of these have
made their confession before they had their falling, tumbling fitts, but yet not
absolutely before they had any fitts and marks of possession, for (as the S. G.
know full well) when these persons were about first confessing, their mouths
would be stopped, and their throats affected, as tho' there was danger of
strangling, and afterward (it is true) came their tumbling fitts. So that, I say, the
confessions of these persons were in the beginning of their fitts, and not truly
before their fitts, as the S. G. would make us believe.</p>


<p>Thus, (Sir,) I have given you as full a narrative of these matters as readily
occurs to my mind, and I think every word of it is matter of fact; the several
glosses and descants whereupon, by way of Reasoning, I refer to your Judgment,
whether to approve or disapprove.</p>


<p>What will be the issue of these troubles, God only knows; I am afraid that
ages will not wear off that reproach and those stains which these things will leave
behind them upon our land. I pray God pity us, Humble us, Forgive us, and
appear mercifully for us in this our mount of distress: Herewith I conclude, and
subscribe myself,</p>

<closer>
<salute>Reverend Sir, your real friend and humble servant,</salute>
<signed>T. B.</signed>
</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="notes" id="d6">

<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol"></seg><p></p></note> 
<note id="n45"><seg type="note-symbol">[45].</seg> <p>Bartholomew Gedney.</p></note>

<note id="n46"><seg type="note-symbol">[46].</seg> <p>Captain John Alden, of Boston, son of the John Alden of the <hi rend="italic">Mayflower</hi> and of Longfellow's poem.
For Alden's own account of this episode see pp. 353-355, below.</p></note>

<note id="n47"><seg type="note-symbol">[47].</seg> <p><hi rend="italic">I. e.</hi>, Salem gentlemen &mdash; and so
hereafter.</p></note>

<note id="n48"><seg type="note-symbol">[48].</seg> <p>Marvel, am surprised.</p></note>

<note id="n49"><seg type="note-symbol">[49].</seg> <p>Nicholas Noyes.</p></note>

<note id="n50"><seg type="note-symbol">[50].</seg> <p>He means, of course, the judges.</p></note>

<note id="n51"><seg type="note-symbol">[51].</seg> <p>The names presently mentioned would seem to show that he has
especially in mind the executions of August 19, and his words suggest that he was
present on this occasion. Those then executed, besides John Proctor and John
Willard, were the Rev. George Burroughs, George Jacobs, and Martha Carrier.
For two other accounts of their death, both perhaps by eye-witnesses, see
below, pp. 360-364. But there had been executions also on June 10,
July 19, and September 22.</p></note>

<note id="n52"><seg type="note-symbol">[52].</seg> <p>Emotion, earnestness.</p></note>

<note id="n53"><seg type="note-symbol">[53].</seg> <p>Cotton Mather.</p></note>

<note id="n54"><seg type="note-symbol">[54].</seg> <p>Mrs. Margaret Thacher (1625-1694), widow of the Rev. Thomas Thacher
(d. 1678), first minister of the Old South Church. She was the only child of the
wealthy Boston merchant Henry Webb, and had been left by a first marriage the
widow of Jacob Sheafe, then the richest man in Boston.</p></note>

<note id="n55"><seg type="note-symbol">[55].</seg> <p>Jonathan Corwin, of Salem.</p></note>

<note id="n56"><seg type="note-symbol">[56].</seg> <p>Hezekiah Usher (1639-1697), a prominent Boston merchant.</p></note>

<note id="n57"><seg type="note-symbol">[57].</seg> <p>Doubtless Joseph Lynde (1637-1727), of Charlestown &mdash; since June
a member of the Council under the new Mather charter.</p></note>

<note id="n58"><seg type="note-symbol">[58].</seg> <p>Mrs. Nathaniel Cary, of Charlestown. See pp.
349-352.</p></note>

<note id="n59"><seg type="note-symbol">[59].</seg> <p>Philip English, of Salem. See p. 371 and note 1.</p></note>

<note id="n60"><seg type="note-symbol">[60].</seg> <p>John Alden, of Boston. See p. 170, note 2.</p></note>

<note id="n61"><seg type="note-symbol">[61].</seg> <p><hi rend="italic">I. e.</hi>, to New York.</p></note>

<note id="n62"><seg type="note-symbol">[62].</seg> <p><hi rend="italic">I. e.</hi>, capital cases.</p></note>

<note id="n63"><seg type="note-symbol">[63].</seg> <p>New England.</p></note>

<note id="n64"><seg type="note-symbol">[64].</seg> <p>Mrs. Obinson was probably the wife of William Obinson, or Obbinson,
a Boston tanner.</p></note>

<note id="n65"><seg type="note-symbol">[65].</seg> <p>Increase Mather.</p></note>

<note id="n66"><seg type="note-symbol">[66].</seg> <p>Mrs. Joseph Ballard. See below, pp. 371-372; and, for
more as to this Andover episode, pp. 241-244, 418-420. The records of the
Andover cases are printed by Woodward in his <hi rend="italic">Records of
Salem Witchcraft</hi> (Roxbury, 1864), and there are chapters on the episode
in Abiel Abbot's <hi rend="italic">History of Andover</hi> (Andover,
1829) and Sarah Loring Bailey's <hi rend="italic">Historical Sketches of
Andover</hi> (Boston, 1880).</p></note>

<note id="n67"><seg type="note-symbol">[67].</seg> <p>Dudley Bradstreet. See p. 372.</p></note>

<note id="n68"><seg type="note-symbol">[68].</seg> <p>Stevens? The conjecture is Mrs. Bailey's (<hi rend="italic">Historical
Sketches of Andover</hi>, 228).</p></note>

<note id="n68a"><seg type="note-symbol">[*]</seg><p>You may possibly think that my terms are too severe; but should I tell
you what a kind of Blade was employed in bringing these women to their
confession; what methods from damnation were taken; with what violence urged;
how unseasonably they were kept up; what buzzings and chuckings of the hand
were used, and the like, I am sure that you would call them, (as I do), rude and
barbarous methods.</p></note>
	
	<note target="n69"><p>[Marginal note in the original.]</p></note>

<note id="n69"><seg type="note-symbol">[69].</seg> <p>What Brattle may mean by &ldquo;methods from <hi rend="italic">damnation</hi>&rdquo; is a puzzle to the editor. Perhaps
&ldquo;damnation&rdquo; is only a euphemism for &ldquo;hell.&rdquo;
Possibly he thinks of that clause in the Massachusetts laws (<hi rend="italic">Body of Liberties of</hi> 1641, art.
45; <hi rend="italic">Lawes and Libertyes</hi>, 1660, p. 67; 1672, p. 129) which
permits a prisoner &ldquo;in some capital case, when he is first fully convicted
by clear and sufficient evidence to be guilty,&rdquo; to be tortured for the
discovery of his accomplices, yet not with such tortures as are barbarous and
inhuman. What he means by &ldquo;buzzings and chuckings of the hand,&rdquo;
<hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi>, whisperings and wheedlings, will grow clear
if one turn to pp. 374-376, and read what these Andover women themselves tell
of the methods used with them.</p></note>

<note id="n70"><seg type="note-symbol">[70].</seg> <p>A mode of divination much in vogue in New England as in Old. Called
also &ldquo;sieve and shears&rdquo; or &ldquo;riddle and shears&rdquo;: the
learned name is <hi rend="italic">coscinomancy</hi>.</p></note>

<note id="n71"><seg type="note-symbol">[71].</seg> <p>&ldquo;The Groton woman&rdquo; was Elizabeth Knapp, and the
&ldquo;account in print&rdquo; probably that of Increase Mather reprinted
above, pp. 21-23, though possibly Willard's sermon (see p. 21, note 4) is
meant.</p></note>

<note id="n72"><seg type="note-symbol">[72].</seg> <p>William Stoughton, the new lieutenant-governor. He had been educated
for the ministry in the Harvard class of 1650, and went to England, where he
preached for some ten years, receiving meanwhile at Oxford his mastership in
arts and the honor of a fellowship; but, ejected at the Restoration, he returned to
New England, and there, though counted an able preacher, declined a settlement
and drifted into public life. He seems to have set store by his learning in
theology, and to the end to have maintained the Devil's impotence to personate
by a spectre any but a guilty witch. As to his career see the careful study by
Sibley, in his <hi rend="italic">Harvard Graduates</hi> (I. 194-208).</p></note>

<note id="n73"><seg type="note-symbol">[73].</seg> <p>See p. 355. Richards, Sargent, Sewall, Winthrop, were
of Boston; Stoughton of Dorchester, close by. Only Gedney was of Salem, till
Corwin was called in to replace Saltonstall (who was of Haverhill).</p></note>

<note id="n74"><seg type="note-symbol">[74].</seg> <p>As to all these see below, pp. 360-374.</p></note>

<note id="n75"><seg type="note-symbol">[75].</seg> <p>The General Court. It convened on October 12. Its attitude as to the
Salem trials is thus tersely intimated in Judge Sewall's diary: &ldquo;Oct. 26,
1692. A Bill is sent in about calling a Fast and Convocation of Ministers, that
[we] may be led in the right way as to the Witchcrafts. The season and manner
of doing it, is such, that the Court of Oyer and Terminer count themselves
thereby dismissed. 29 Nos and 33 yeas to the Bill.&rdquo; The bill itself has
been printed (from the Mass. Archives, XI. 70) by G. H. Moore, in the
<hi rend="italic">Proceedings</hi> of the American Antiquarian Society (n. s.,
II. 172); and that those of Brattle's mind had not relied alone on prayer to
influence the assembly may be seen by the petition printed in the
<hi rend="italic">N. E. Hist. and Gen. Register</hi>, XXVII. 55, and in the
<hi rend="italic">Proceedings </hi> of the American Antiquarian Society, n. s., V. 246 (see also
<hi rend="italic">Proceedings</hi>, n. s., II. 171).</p></note>

<note id="n76"><seg type="note-symbol">[76].</seg> <p>The ministers, now practically the only &ldquo;elders.&rdquo;</p></note>

<note id="n77"><seg type="note-symbol">[77].</seg> <p>It has been generally assumed, and with reason, that this &ldquo;Rev'd
person&rdquo; was the Rev. Samuel Willard. Three of the judges (Sargent,
Sewall, and Winthrop) were members of his church (the Old South), and, unless
one suspect Brattle of intent to mislead, &ldquo;spiritual relation&rdquo; must
here mean a pastor's. The phrase &ldquo;good affection to the country&rdquo;
suggests, too, one who, like Willard, shared Brattle's political views. We have
seen already (p. 23) what caution in 1671 he used in the case of Elizabeth Knapp;
and, if the &ldquo;notions and proposals&rdquo; meant by Brattle are now lost,
we have from his pen what puts his position in 1692 beyond all
question &mdash; a little dialogue, published anonymously while the troubles were
at their height, which with fairness and courtesy, but with striking clearness and
boldness, argues against the iniquity of the procedure. Its title runs: <hi rend="italic">Some Miscellany Observations on our Present Debates respecting
Witchcrafts, in a Dialogue between S. and B. By P. E. and J. A. Philadelphia,
Printed by William Bradford, for Hezekiah Usher</hi>. 1692.
&ldquo;S.&rdquo; and &ldquo;B.&rdquo; undoubtedly mean Salem and Boston.
Philadelphia and Bradford probably had as little to do with the book (the type is
not Bradford's) as did Hezekiah Usher, P. E. (Philip English), or J. A. (John
Alden), three notable fugitives from Salem justice. All alike were merely remote
enough to bear in safety the imputation of such a book. John Alden and Hezekiah
Usher were members of Willard's church; and Philip English and his wife he
visited while in custody at Boston, and probably was a party to their escape. At
least the Rev. William Bentley, of Salem, recording in his diary, May 21, 1793,
what their great-granddaughter Susanna Hathorne had told him, relates that
Willard and Moodey &ldquo;visited them and invited them to the public worship
on the day before they were to return to Salem for trial. Their text was that they
that are persecuted in one city, let them flee to another. After Meeting the
Ministers visited them at the Gaol, and asked them whether they took notice of
the discourse, and told them their danger and urged them to escape since so many
had suffered. Mr. English replied, `God will not permit them to touch me.' Mrs.
English said: `Do you not think the sufferers innocent?' He (Moody) said `Yes.'
She then added, `Why may we not suffer also?' The Ministers then told him if
he would not carry his wife away they would.&rdquo; (Quoted by R. D. Paine,
in his <hi rend="italic">Ships and Sailors of Old Salem</hi>, from
Bentley's privately printed diary, which seems to give the tale in a more primitive
form than his letter to Alden, in the Mass. Hist. Soc., <hi
rend="italic">Collections</hi>, X.) &ldquo;It ought never to be
forgotten,&rdquo; said Willard's colleague, Ebenezer Pemberton, preaching in
1707 his funeral sermon, &ldquo;with what Prudence, Courage and Zeal he
appeared for the Good of this People in that Dark and Mysterious Season when
we were assaulted from the Invisible World. And how singularly Instrumental he
was in discovering the Cheats and Delusions of Satan, which did threaten to stain
our Land with Blood and to deluge it with all manner of Woes.&rdquo; True,
Judge Sewall, mentioning in 1696 (<hi rend="italic">Diary</hi>, I. 433)
Willard's sermon at the day of public prayer, says that he spake smartly
&ldquo;at last&rdquo; about the Salem witchcraft; but &ldquo;at last&rdquo;
here means &ldquo;at the end,&rdquo; &ldquo;as the peroration of his
sermon.&rdquo; It is clearly Willard whom Cotton Mather has especially in mind
when in his life of Phips and again in his <hi rend="italic">Magnalia</hi>
(bk. II., p. 62) he sets forth the views of those &ldquo;who from the beginning
were very much dissatisfied with these proceedings,&rdquo; having
&ldquo;already known of one at the Town of Groton&rdquo; who had falsely
accused a neighbor. The strange suggestion of W. F. Poole that Brattle here
means Cotton Mather himself, is adequately answered by Upham, in his <hi
rend="italic">Salem Witchcraft and Cotton Mather</hi>.</p></note>

<note id="n78"><seg type="note-symbol">[78].</seg> <p>The paper meant is doubtless that printed at pp. 374-375, below.</p></note>

<note id="n79"><seg type="note-symbol">[79].</seg> <p>The attempt of Louis XIV. to force his Protestant subjects to abandon
their faith by turning loose his dragoons upon them had already furnished the
English language with this new word.</p></note>
	<pb n="191"/>
</div2>
</div1>



</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>


