<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="BurLodu"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>


<TEI.2 id="BurLodu">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Lodusky</title>
<title type="sort">lodusky</title>
<author>Burnett, Frances Hodgson</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Charles Keller</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">68</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">BurLodu</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475762</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Lodusky</title>
<title>Scribner's Monthly</title>
<title type="sort">lodusky</title>
<author>Frances Hodgson Burnett</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Frances Hart &amp; Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1877-09">September, 1877</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Scribner's Monthly, Vol. 14, September, 1877, No.
5, pp. 673-687</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic
Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding
line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text
Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed
of the text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in
AusEmma1 for page one of Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1877-09">September, 1877</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
<term>Young Readers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-11">November, 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Bryson Clevenger, Jr.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>TEI header, TEI tagging</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">




<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="673"/>
<head>
LODUSKY<lb/>
by<lb/>
Frances Hodgson Burnett<lb/>
SCRIBNER'S MONTHLY<lb/>
VOL. XIV.<lb/>           SEPTEMBER, 1877.<lb/>              NO.
5.<lb/>
pp. 673-687</head>

<p>THEY were rather an incongruous element amid the festivities,
but they bore themselves very well, notwithstanding, and seemed
to be sufficiently interested.  The elder of the two&mdash;a tall,
slender, middle-aged woman with a somewhat severe, though
delicate face,&mdash;sat quietly apart, looking on at the tough dances
and games with a keen relish of their primitive uncouthness, but
the younger, a slight alert creature, moved here and there, her
large, changeable eyes looking larger through their glow of
excitement. </p><p>"Thet gal thar," drawled a tall mountaineer
who supported himself against the chimney and spat with placid
regularity into the fire.  "They tell me thet gal thar hes writ
things as has been in print.  They say she's powerful smart&mdash;arns
her livin' by it.  'T least thet's what Jake Harney says, n'
they's a-boardin' at Harney's.  The old woman's some of her kin,
'n' goes 'long with her when she travels 'round."
</p><p>There was one fiddler at work sawing industriously at one
time which did good service throughout the entertainment, there
was a little furious and erratic reel-dancing and much loud
laughter and good-natured, even if somewhat personal, jest.  The
room was one of two which formed the house, the walls were of
log, the lights the cheery yellow flare of great pine-knots flung
one after the other upon the embers.
</p><p>"I am glad I thought of North Carolina," Rebecca Noble
said to herself.  There is a strong hint of Rembrandt in this&mdash;
the bright yellow light, the uncouth figures.  Ah! who is that?"
</p><p>A short time after, she made her way through the crowd to
her relative's corner among the shadows.  She looked eager and
excited, and spoke in a quick, breathless fashion.
</p><p>"I want to show you something, if you have not already
seen it," she said.  "There is in this room, Aunt Miriam, the
most wonderful creature your eyes ever rested on!  You must
prepare yourself to be startled.  Look toward the door&mdash;at that
tall girl standing with her hands behind her." </p><p>She was
attired in a calico of flaunting pattern and leaned against the
log-wall in an indifferent attitude, regarding the company from
under the heavy lashes of her eyes, which had a look of stillness
in them which was yet not repose.  There was something even
secretive in her expression, as if she watched them furtively for
reasons of her own.  At her side stood a big discontented-looking
young man who confronted aggressively two or three other young
men equally big, if not equally discontented, who seemed to be
arguing some point with him and endeavoring to engage the
attention of his companion.  The girl, however, simply responded
to their appeals with an occasional smile, ambiguous, if not
scornful.
</p><p>"How I wish I could hear them!" exclaimed Miss Noble.
</p><p>It was her habit to utilize any material she chanced to
find, and she had really made her summer jaunt to North Carolina
in search of material, but she was not thinking of utilizing this
girl as she managed to keep near her during the remainder of the
evening.  She had merely found something to be keenly interested
in, her interest in any human novelty being, on occasion,
intense.  In this case her interest increased instead of
diminished.  She found the girl comporting herself in her natural
position as belle, with a calm which was slightly suggestive of
"the noble savage."  Each admirer seemed to be treated with
indifference alike, though there were some who, for reasons best
known to themselves, evidently felt that they stood more securely
than the rest.  She moved through game VOL. XIV.&mdash;43.

<pb n="674"/>  and dance with a slow yet free grace; she spoke
seldom, and in a low, bell-like monotone, containing no hint of
any possible emotional development, and for the rest, her shadow
of a disdainful smile seemed to stand her in good stead.  Clearly
as she stood out from among her companions from the first, at the
close of the evening she assumed a position actually dramatic.
</p><p>The big young mountaineer, who, despite his discontent,
was a very handsome fellow indeed, had held his own against his
rivals stubbornly during the evening, but when, after the final
dance, he went in search of his charge, he found that he was not
first.
</p><p>She had fallen into her old attitude against the wall, her
hands behind her, and was listening to the appeal of a brawny
youth with a hunting-knife in his belt.
</p><p>"Dusk," he was saying, "I'm not such a chicken-hearted
chap as to let a gal go back on me.  Ye sed I mout hev yer
comp'ny home, 'n' I'm a-gwine to hev it, Dave Humes or no Dave
Humes."
    Dusk merely smiled tolerantly.
    "Are ye?" she said.
</p><p>Rebecca Noble, who stood within a few feet of them, was
sure that the lover who approached was the Dave Humes in
question, he advanced with such an angry stride, and laying his
hand on his rival's shoulder, turned him aside so cavalierly.
</p><p>"No he aint," he put in; "not an' me about.  I brought ye,
an' I'll take ye home, Lodusky, or me and him 'll settle it."
</p><p>The other advanced a step, looking a trifle pale and
disheveled.  He placed himself square in front of Lodusky.
</p><p>"Dusk Dunbar," he said, "you're the one to settle it.
Which on us is a-gwine home with ye&mdash;me or him?  Ye haint
promised the two of us, hev ye?" </p><p>There was certainly a
suddenly lit spark of exultation in the girl's coolly dropped
eyes.
</p><p>"Settle it betwixt ye," she answered with her exasperating
half-smile again.
</p><p>They had attracted attention by this time, and were
becoming the center figures of a group of lookers-on.
</p><p>The first had evidently lost his temper.  She was the one
who should settle it, he proclaimed loudly again.  She had
promised one man her "comp'ny" and had come with another.
</p><p>There was so much fierce anger in his face that Miss Noble
drew a little nearer, and felt her own blood warmed.
</p><p>"Which on us is it to be?" he cried.
</p><p>There was a quick, strong movement on the part of the
young man, Dave, and he was whirled aside for a second time.
</p><p>"It's to be me," he was answered.  "I'm the man to settle
that&mdash;I don't leave it to no gal to settle."
</p><p>In two seconds the lookers-on fell back in dismay and
there was a cry of terror from the women.  Two lithe, long-limbed
figures were struggling fiercely together and there was a flash
of knives in the air.     Rebecca Noble sprang forward.
</p><p>"They will kill each other," she said.  "Stop them!
</p><p>That they would have done each other deadly injury seemed
more than probable, but there were cool heads and hands as strong
as their own in the room and in a few minutes they had been
dragged apart and stood, each held back by the arms, staring at
each other and panting.  The lank peace-maker in blue jeans who
held Dave Humes shook him gently and with amiable toleration of
his folly.
</p><p>"Look 'ere, boys," he said, "this yere's all a pack of
foolishness, ye know&mdash;all a pack of foolishness.  There aint no
sense in it&mdash;it's jest foolishness."
</p><p>Rebecca cast a quick glance at the girl Lodusky.  She
leaned against the wall just as she had done before; she was as
cool as ever though the spark which hinted at exultation still
shone steadily in her eye. </p><p>When the two ladies reached the
log-cabin at which they had taken up their abode, they found that
the story of the event of the evening was before them.  Their
hostess, whose habit it was to present herself with erratic talk
or information at all hours, met them with hospitable eagerness.
</p><p>"Waal now," she began, "jest to think o' them thar fool
boys a-lettin' into one another in thet thar way.  I never hearn
tell o' sich foolishness.  Young folks <hi rend="italic"> is</hi> so foolish.
'N' they drord knives?"  This in the tone of suggestive query.
</p><p>"Yes," answered Miss Noble, "they drew knives."
</p><p>"They did!" benignly.  "Lord! what fools!  Waal now, an'
Dusk&mdash;what did Dusk do?"
</p><p>"She stood by and looked on " was the reply.{sic}
</p><p>"Lord!" with the inimitable mountain drawl; "ye don't say
so!  But it's jest like her&mdash;thet is.  She's so cur'us, Dusk is.
Thar aint no gettin' at her.  Ye know the gals ses as she's
allers doin' fust one quare thing

<pb n="675"/> 'n' then another to get the boys mad at each other.
But Lor', pr'aps 'taint so!  Dusk's powerful good-lookin', and
gals is jealous, ye know."
</p><p>"Do you think," questioned Miss Noble, "that they really
would have killed each other?"
</p><p>"Lord! yaas," placidly.  "They went to do it.  Both Dan'l
and Dave's kinder fiery, 'n' they'd nuther on 'em hev give in
with Dusk a-lookin' on&mdash;they'd hev cut theirselves to pieces
fust.  Young folks <hi rend="italic"> is</hi> so foolish; gettin' mad about a
gal!  Lord knows gals is plenty enough." </p><p>"Not girls like
this one," said Miss Noble, laughing a little. </p><p>"Waal now,
she <hi rend="italic"> is</hi> good-lookin', aint she?  But she's cur'us, Dusk
is&mdash;she's a cur'us creetur."
</p><p>"Curious!" echoed Rebecca, finding the term vague even
while suggestive. </p><p>"Yaas," she said, expansively, "she's
cur'us, kinder onsosherble 'n' notionate.  Now Dusk is&mdash;cur'us.
She's so still and sot, 'n' Nath Dunbar and Mandy they think a
heap on her, 'n' they do the best they kin by her, but she don't
never seem to keer about 'em no way.  Fur all she's so still,
she's powerful sot on fine dressin' an' rich folkses ways.  Nath
he once tuk her to Asheville, 'n' seems like she's kinder never
got over it, but keeps a-broodin' 'bout the way they done
thar,'n' how their clothes looked, 'n' all thet.  She knows she's
handsum 'n' she likes to see other folks knows it, though she
never says much.  I hed to laugh at my Hamp once; Hamp he aint no
fool, an' he'd been tuk with her a spell like the rest o' the
boys, but he got chock full of her, 'n' one day we was a-talkin',
'n' the old man he says, `Waal now, that gal's a hard wad.  She's
cur'us, an' thar's no two ways about it.'  An' Hamp he gives a
bit of a laugh kinder mad, 'n' he ses, `Yes, she's cur'us&mdash;cur'us
as &mdash;!  May be he felt kinder roughed up about her yet&mdash;but I
hed to laugh."
</p><p>The next morning Miss Noble devoted to letter-writing.  In
one of her letters, a bright one, of a tone rather warmer than
the rest, she gave her correspondent a very forcible description
of the entertainment of the evening before and its closing scene.
</p><p>"I think it will interest him," she said half aloud, as
she wrote upon the envelope the first part of the address, "Mr.
Paul Lennox." </p><p>A shadow falling across the sunshine in the
door-way checked her and made her look up.
</p><p>It had rather an arousing effect upon her to find herself
confronting the young woman, Lodusky, who stood upon the
threshold, regarding her with an air entirely composed, slightly
mingled with interest.
</p><p>"I was in at Mis' Harney's," she remarked, as if the
explanation was upon the whole rather superfluous, "'n' I thought
I'd come in 'n' see ye." </p><p>During her sojourn of three weeks
Rebecca had learned enough of the laws of mountain society to
understand that the occasion only demanded of her friendliness of
demeanor and perfect freedom from ceremony.  She rose and placed
a chair for her guest.
    "I am glad to see you," she said.
    Lodusky seated herself
</p><p>It was entirely unnecessary to attempt to set her at ease;
her composure was perfect.  The flaunting-patterned calico must
have been a matter of full dress.  It had been replaced by a
blue-and-white-checked homespun gown&mdash;a coarse cotton garment
short and scant.  Her feet were bare, and their bareness was only
a revelation of greater beauty, so perfect was their arched
slenderness.  Miss Dunbar crossed them with unembarrassed freedom
and looked at the stranger as if she found her worth steady
inspection. </p><p>"Thet that's a purty dress you're a-wearin',"
she vouchsafed at length. </p><p>Rebecca glanced down at her
costume.  Being a sensible young person, she had attired herself
in apparel suitable for mountain rambling.  Her dress was simple
pilgrim gray, taut made and trim; but she never lost an air of
distinction which rendered abundant adornments a secondary
matter. </p><p>"It is very plain," she answered.  "I believe its
chief object is to be as little in the way as possible."
</p><p>"'Taint much trimmed," responded the girl, "but it looks
kinder nice, 'n' it sets well.  Ye come from the city, Mis'
Harney says." </p><p>"From New York," said Rebecca.  She felt
sure that she saw in the tawny brown depths of the girl's eyes a
kind of secret eagerness, and this expressed itself openly in her
reply.
</p><p>"I don't blame no one fur wantin' to live in a city," she
said, with a kind of discontent.  "A body might most as soon be
dead as live this way." </p><p>Rebecca gave her a keen glance.
"Don't you like the quiet?" she asked.  "What is it you don't
like?"</p>

<pb n="676"/>
<p>"I don't like nothin' about it," scornfully.  "Thar's nothin'
here." </p><p>Very slowly a lurking, half-hidden smile showed
itself about her fine month.
</p><p>"I'm not goin' to stay here allers," she said.
    "You want to go away?" said Rebecca.
    She nodded.
</p><p>"I <hi rend="italic"> am</hi> goin'," she answered, "some o' these
days." </p><p>"Where?" asked Rebecca, a little coldly,
recognizing as she did a repellant element in the girt.
    The reply was succinct enough:
</p><p>"I don't know whar, 'n' I don't keer whar&mdash;but I'm goin'."
</p><p>She turned her eyes toward the great wall of forest-covered mountain, lifting its height before the open door, and
the blood showed its deep glow upon her cheek.
</p><p>"Some o' these days," she added; "as shore as I'm a
woman." </p><p>When they talked the matter over afterward, Miss
Thorne's remarks were at once decided and severe.
</p><p>"Shall I tell you what my opinion is, Rebecca?" she said.
"It is my opinion that there is evil enough in the creature to be
the ruin of the whole community.  She is bad at the core."
</p><p>"I would rather believe," said Rebecca musingly, "that she
was only inordinately vain."  Almost instantaneously her musing
was broken by a light laugh.  "She has dressed her hair as I
dress mine," she said, "only it was done better.  I could not
have arranged it so well.  She saw it last night, and was quick
enough to take in the style at a glance."
</p><p>At the beginning of the next week there occurred an event
which changed materially the ordinary routine of life in the
cabin.  Heretofore the two sojourners among the mountain
fastnesses had walked and climbed under the escort of a small,
tow-headed Harney.  But one evening as she sat sketching on her
favorite flat seat of rock, Miss Noble somewhat alarmed this
youth by dropping her paper and starting to her feet.
</p><p>"Orlander" Harney sat and stared at her with black eyes
and opened mouth.  The red came and went under her fair skin, and
she breathed quickly. </p><p>"Oh," she cried softly, "how <hi rend="italic">
could</hi> I be mistaken!" </p><p>That she was not mistaken
became evident immediately.  At the very moment she spoke, the
advancing horseman, whose appearance had so roused her, glanced
upward along the path and caught sight of her figure.  He lifted
his hat in gay greeting and struck his horse lightly with his
whip.  Rebecca bent down and picked up her portfolio.
</p><p>"You may go home," she said quietly to the boy.  "I shall
be there soon; and you may tell Miss Thorne that Mr. Lennox has
come."  She was at the base of the rock when the stranger drew
rein.  "How is this?" she asked with bright uplifted eyes.  "We
did not think&mdash;"
</p><p>It occurred to Lennox that he had never recognized her
peculiar charm so fully as he did at this moment.  Rebecca Noble,
though not a beauty, possessed a subtle grace of look and air
which was not easily resisted,&mdash;and just now, as she held out her
hand, the clear sweetness of her face shadowed by her piquantly
plain hat of rough straw, he felt the influence of this element
more strongly than ever before.
</p><p>"There was no reason why I should not come," he said,
"since you did not forbid me."
</p><p>At sunset they returned to the cabin.  Lennox led his
rather sorry-looking animal by the bridle, and trusting to its
meekness of aspect, devoted his attention wholly to his
companion.
</p><p>"Thet's Nath Dunbar's critter," commented "Mis'". Harney,
standing at the door.  "They've powerful poor 'commodations fur
boardin', but I reckon Nath must 'a' tuk him in."
</p><p>"Then," said Rebecca, learning that this was the case,
"then you have seen Lodusky."
</p><p>But he had not seen Lodusky, it seemed.  She had not been
at home when he arrived, and he had only remained in the house
long enough to make necessary arrangements before leaving it to
go in search of his friends. </p><p>The bare, rough-walled room
was very cheery that night.  Lennox brought with him the gossip
of the great world, to which he gave an air of freshness and
spice that rendered it very acceptable to the temporary hermits.
Outside, the moon shone with a light as clear as day, though
softer, and the tender night breezes stirred the pine-tops and
nestled among the laurels; inside, by the beautiful barbarous
light of the flaring pine-knots on the hearth, two talkers, at
least, found the hours fly swiftly.
</p><p>When these two bade each other goodnight, it was only
natural that they should

<pb n="677"/> reach the point toward which they had been veering
for twelve months.
</p><p>Miss Thorne remained in the room, drawing nearer the fire
with an amiable little shiver, well excused by the mountain
coolness, but Rebecca was beguiled into stepping out into the
moonlight.  The brightness of the moon and the blackness of the
shadows cast by trees and rocks and undergrowth, seemed somehow
to heighten the effect of the intense and utter stillness
reigning around them,&mdash;even the occasional distant cry of some
wandering wild creature, marked rather than broke in upon the
silence.  Rebecca's glance about her was half nervous.
</p><p>"It is very beautiful," she said, "and it moves one
strongly; but I am not sure that it is not, in some of one's
moods, just a little oppressive." </p><p>It is possible Lennox
did not hear her.  He was looking down at her with eager eyes.
Suddenly he had caught her hand to his lips and kissed it.
</p><p>"You know why I am here, Rebecca," he said.  "Surely, all
my hoping is not vain?"
</p><p>She looked pale and a little startled; but she lifted her
face and did not draw herself away.
</p><p>"Is it?" he asked again.  "Have I come on a hopeless
errand?" </p><p>"No," she answered.  "You have not."
</p><p>His words came freely enough then and with fire.  When
Rebecca re-entered the cabin her large eyes shone in her small,
sweet face, and her lips wore a charming curve.
</p><p>Miss Thorne turned in her chair to look at her and was
betrayed into a smile. </p><p>"Mr. Lennox has gone, of course,"
she said.
    "Yes."
</p><p>Then, after a brief silence, in which Rebecca pushed the
pine-knots with her foot, the elder lady spoke again.
</p><p>"Don't you think you may as well tell me about it, Beck,
my child?" she said.
</p><p>Beck looked down and shook her head with very charming
gravity. </p><p>"Why should I?" she asked.  "When&mdash;when you
know."
</p><p>Lennox rode his mildly disposed but violently gaited steed
homeward in that reposeful state of bliss known only to accepted
lovers.  He had plucked his flower at last; he was no longer one
of the many; he was ecstatically content.  Uncertainty had no
charm for him, and he  was by no means the first discoverer of
the subtle fineness her admirers found so difficult to describe
in Miss Noble.  Granted that she was not a beauty, judged
rigidly, still he had found in her soft, clear eye, in her color,
in her charming voice, even in her little gestures, something
which reached him as an artist and touched him as a man.
</p><p>"One cannot exactly account for other women's paling
before her," he said to him-himself;{sic} "but they do&mdash;and lose
significance."  And then he laughed tenderly.  At this moment, it
was true, every other thing on earth paled and lost significance.
</p><p>That the family of his host had retired made itself
evident to him when he dismounted at the house.  To the silence
of the night was added the silence of slumber.  No one was to be
seen; a small cow, rendered lean by active climbing in search of
sustenance, breathed peacefully near the tumble-down fence; the
ubiquitous, long-legged yellow dog, rendered trustful by long
seclusion, aroused himself from his nap to greet the arrival with
a series of heavy raps upon the rickety porch-floor with a solid
but languid tail.  Lennox stepped over him in reaching for the
gourd hanging upon the post, and he did not consider it incumbent
upon himself to rise.
</p><p>In a little hollow at the road-side was the spring from
which the household supplies of water were obtained.  Finding
none in the wooden bucket, Lennox took the gourd with the
intention of going down to the hollow to quench his thirst.
</p><p>"We've powerful good water," his host had said in the
afternoon, "'n' it's nigh the house, too.  I built the house yer
a-purpose,&mdash;on 'count of its bein' nigh."
</p><p>He was unconsciously dwelling upon this statement as he
walked, and trying to recall correctly the mountain drawl and
twang.
</p><p>"She," he said (there was only one "she for him tonight)&mdash;
"she will be sure to catch it and reproduce it in all its shades
to the life." </p><p>He was only a few feet from the spring
itself and he stopped with a sharp exclamation of the most
uncontrollable amazement,&mdash;stopped and stared straight before
him.  It was a pretty, dell-like place, darkly shadowed on one
side but bathed in tile flooding moonlight on the other, and it
was something he saw in this flood of moonlight which almost
caused him to doubt for the moment the evidence of his senses.
</p><p>How it was possible for him to believe

<pb n="678"/> that there really could stand in such a spot a girl
attired in black velvet of stagy cut and trimmings, he could not
comprehend, but a few feet from him there certainly stood such a
girl, who bent her lithe, round shape over the spring, gazing
into its depths with all the eagerness of an insatiable vanity.
</p><p>"I can't see nothin'," he heard her say impatiently.  "I
can't see nothin' nohow."
</p><p>Despite the beauty, his first glance could not help
showing him she was a figure so incongruous and inconsistent as
to be almost <hi rend="italic"> bizarre</hi>.  When she stood upright
revealing fully her tall figure in its shabby finery, he felt
something like resentment.  He made a restive movement which she
heard.  The bit of broken looking-glass she held in her hand fell
into the water, she uttered a shamefaced, angry cry.
</p><p>"What d'ye want?" she exclaimed.
</p><p>"What are ye a-doin'?  I didn't know as no one "was a-lookin'.  I&mdash;" </p><p>Her head was flung backward, her full
throat looked like a pillar of marble against the black edge of
her dress, her air was fierce.  He would not have been an artist
if he had not been powerfully struck with a sense of her
picturesqueness.
</p><p>But he did not smile at all as he answered:
</p><p>"I board at the house there.  I returned home late and was
thirsty.  I came here for water to drink."
</p><p>Her temper died down as suddenly as it had flamed, and she
seemed given up to a miserable, shamed trepidation.
</p><p>"Oh!" she said, "don't ye tell 'em&mdash;don't&mdash;I&mdash;I'm Dusk
Dunbar." </p><p>Then, as was very natural, he became curious and
possibly did smile&mdash;a very little.
</p><p>"What in the name of all that is fantastic are you doing?"
</p><p>She made an effort at being defiant and succeeded pretty
well. </p><p>"I wasn't doin' no harm," she said.  "I was&mdash;
dressin' up a bit.  It aint nobody's business."
</p><p>"That's true," he answered coolly.  "At all events it is
not mine&mdash;though it is rather late for a lady to be alone at such
a place.  However, if you have no objection I will get what I
came for and go back." </p><p>She said nothing when he stepped
down and filled the gourd, but she regarded him with a sort of
irritable watchfulness as he drank. </p><p>"Are ye&mdash;are ye a-goin' to tell?" she faltered, when he had finished. </p><p>"No,"
he answered as coolly as before.  "Why should I?" </p><p>Then he
gave her a long look from head to foot.  The dress was a poor
enough velveteen and had a cast-off air, but it clung to her
figure finely, and its sleeves were picturesque with puffs at the
shoulder and slashings of white,&mdash;indeed the moonlight made her
all black and white; her eyes, which were tawny brown by day,
were black as velvet now under the straight lines of her brows,
and her face was pure dead fairness itself.
</p><p>When, his look ended, his eyes met hers, she drew back
with an impatient movement.
</p><p>"Ye look as if&mdash;as if ye thought I didn't get it honest,"
she exclaimed petulantly, "but I did."
</p><p>That drew his glance toward her dress again, for of course
she referred to that, and he could not help asking her a point-blank question.     "Where <hi rend="italic"> did</hi> you get it?" he said.
</p><p>There was a slow flippancy about the manner of her reply
which annoyed him by its variance with her beauty&mdash;but the
beauty!  How the moonlight and the black and white brought it out
as she leaned against the rock, looking at him from under her
lashes!
</p><p>"Are ye goin' to tell the folks up at the house?" she
demanded.  "They don't know nothin', and I don't want 'em to
know."
    He shrugged his shoulders negatively.
</p><p>She laughed with a hint of cool slyness and triumph.
</p><p>"I got it at Asheville," she said.  "I went with father
when they was a show thar, 'n' the women stayed at the same
tavern we was at, 'n' one of 'em tuk up with me 'n' I done
somethin' for her&mdash;carried a letter or two," breaking into the
sly, triumphant laugh again, "'n' she giv' me the dress fur pay.
</p><p>What d' ye think of it?  Is it becomin'?"
</p><p>The suddenness of the change of manner with which she said
these last words was indescribable.  She stood upright, her head
up, her hands fallen at her sides, her eyes cool and straight&mdash;
her whole presence confronting him with the power of which she
was conscious.
    "Is it?" she repeated.
</p><p>He was a gentleman from instinct and from training, having
ordinarily quite a lofty repugnance for all profanity and
brusqueness, and yet somehow,&mdash;account for it as

<pb n="679"/> you will,&mdash;he had the next instant answered her with
positive brutality.
    "Yes," he answered.  "Damnably!"
</p><p>When the words were spoken and he heard their sound fall
upon the soft night air, he was as keenly disgusted as he would
have been if he had heard them uttered by another man.  It was
not until afterward when he had had leisure to think the matter
over that he comprehended vaguely the force which had moved him.
</p><p>But his companion received them without discomfiture.
Indeed, it really occurred to him at the moment that there was a
possibility that she would have been less pleased with all
expression more choice. </p><p>"I come down here to-night," she
said, "because I never git no chance to do nothin' up at the
house.  I'm not a-goin' to let <hi rend="italic"> them</hi> know.  Never mind
why, but ye mustn't tell 'em."
</p><p>He felt haughtily anxious to get back to his proper
position. </p><p>"Why should I he said again.  "It is no concern
of mine." </p><p>Then for the first time he noticed the manner in
which she had striven to dress her hair in the style of her
model, Rebecca Noble, and this irritated him unwendurably.  He
waved his hand toward it with a gesture of distaste.
</p><p>"Don't do that again," he said.  "That is not becoming at
least"&mdash;though he was angrily conscious that it was.
</p><p>She bent over the spring with a hint of alarm in her
expression. </p><p>"Aint it?" she said, and the eager rapidity
with which she lifted her hands and began to alter it almost drew
a smile from him despite his mood. </p><p>"I done it like hern,"
she began, and stopped suddenly to look up at him.  "You know
her," she added; "they're at Harney's.  Father said ye'd went to
see her jest as soon as ye got here."
</p><p>"I know her," was his short reply.
</p><p>He picked up the drinking-gourd and turned away.
</p><p>"Good-night," he said.
</p><p>"Good-night."
</p><p>At the top of the rocky incline he looked back at her.
</p><p>She was kneeling upon the brink of the spring, her sleeve
pushed up to her shoulder, her hand and arm in the water, dipping
for the fragment of looking-glass.

</p><p>It was really not wholly inconsistent that he should not
directly describe the interview in his next meeting with his
betrothed.  Indeed, Rebecca was rather struck by the coolness
with which he treated the subject when he explained that he had
seen the girl and found her beauty all it had been painted.
</p><p>"Is it possible," she asked, "that she did not quite
please you?" </p><p>"Are you sure," he returned, "that she quite
pleases <hi rend="italic"> you</hi>?"     Rebecca gave a moment to reflection.
</p><p>"But her beauty&mdash;" she began, when it was over.
</p><p>"Oh!" he interposed, "as a matter of color and curve and
proportion she is perfect; one must admit that, however
reluctantly."
    Rebecca laughed.
    "why `reluctantly?'" she said.
</p><p>It was his turn to give a moment to reflection.  His face
shadowed, and he looked a little disturbed.
</p><p>"I don't know," he replied at length; "I give it up."
</p><p>He had expected to see a great deal of the girl, but
somehow he saw her even oftener than he had anticipated.  During
the time he spent in the house, chance seemed to throw her
continually in his path or under his eye.  From his window he saw
her carrying water from the spring, driving the small agile cow
to and from the mountain pasturage, or idling in the shade.  Upon
the whole it was oftener this last than any other occupation.
With her neglected knitting in her hands she would sit for hours
under a certain low-spreading cedar not far from the door, bare-footed, coarsely clad, beautiful, every tinge of the sun, every
indifferent leisurely movement, a new suggestion of a new grace.
</p><p>It would have been impossible to resist the temptation to
watch her; and this Lennox did at first almost unconsciously.
Then he did more.  One beautiful still morning she stood under
the cedar, her hand thrown lightly above her head to catch at a
bough, and as she remained motionless, he made a sketch of her.
When it was finished he was seized with the whimsical impulse to
go out and show it to her.
</p><p>She took it with all uncomprehending air, but the moment
she saw what it was a flush of triumphant joy lighted up her
face.
</p><p>"It's me," she cried in a low eager voice.  Me!  Do I look
like that thar?  Do I?"
</p><p>"You look as that would look if it had color, and was more
complete."     She glanced up at him sharply.
    "D'ye mean if it was han'somer?"</p>

<pb n="680"/>
<p>He was tempted into adding to her excitement with a
compliment. </p><p>"Yes," he said, "very much handsomer than I
could ever hope to make it."
    A slow deep red rose to her face.
    "Give it to me!" she demanded.
</p><p>"If you will stand in the same position until I have drawn
another&mdash;certainly," he returned.
</p><p>He was fully convinced that when she repeated the attitude
there would be added to it a look of consciousness.
</p><p>When she settled into position and caught at the bough
again, he watched in some distaste for the growth of the
nervously complaisant air, but it did not appear.  She was
unconsciousness itself.
</p><p>It is possible that Rebecca Noble had never been so happy
during her whole life as she was during this one summer.  Her
enjoyment of every wild beauty and novelty was immeasurably keen.
Just at this time to be shut out, and to be as it were high above
the world, added zest to her pleasure. </p><p>"Ah," she said once
to her lover, "happiness is better here&mdash;one can taste it
slowly."
</p><p>Fatigue seemed impossible to her.  With Lennox as her
companion she performed miracles in the way of walking and
climbing, and explored the mountain fastnesses for miles around.
Her step grew firm and elastic, her color richer, her laugh had a
buoyant ring.  She had never been so nearly a beautiful woman as
she was sometimes when she came back to the cabin after a ramble,
bright and sun-flushed, her hands full of laurel and vines.
</p><p>"Your gown of `hodden-gray' is wonderfully becoming,
Beck," Lennox said again and again with a secret exulting pride
in her.
</p><p>Their plans for the future took tone from their blissful,
unconventional life.  They could not settle down until they had
seen the world.  They would go here and there, and perhaps, if
they found it pleasanter so, not settle down at all.  There were
certain clay-white closely built villages, whose tumbledown
houses jostled each other upon divers precipitous cliffs on the
wayside between Florence and Rome, toward which Lennox's compass
seemed always to point.  He rather argued that the fact of their
not being di-lated upon in the guide-books rendered them
additionally interesting.  Rebecca had her fancies too, and
together they managed to talk a good deal of tender romantic
nonsense which was purely their own business, and gave the summer
days a delicate yet distinct flavor.
</p><p>The evening after the sketch was made they spent upon the
mountain-side together.  When they stopped to rest, Lennox flung
himself upon the ground at Rebecca's feet, and lay looking up at
the far away blue of the sky in which a slow-flying bird circled
lazily.  Rebecca, with a cluster of pink and white laurel in her
hand, proceeded with a metaphysical and poetic harangue she had
previously begun.
</p><p>"To my eyes," she said, "it has a pathetic air of
loneliness&mdash;pathetic and yet not exactly sorrowful.  It knows
nothing but its own pure, brave, silent life.  It is only
pathetic to a worldling&mdash;wordlings like us.  How fallen we must
be to find a life desolate because it has only nature for a
companion!"
</p><p>She stopped with an idle laugh, waiting for an ironical
reply from the "worldling" at her feet; but he remained silent,
still looking upward at the clear deep blue.
</p><p>As she glanced toward him she saw something lying upon the
grass between them and bent to pick it up.  It was the sketch
which he had forgotten and which had slipped from the portfolio.
</p><p>"You have dropped something," she said, and seeing what it
was, uttered an exclamation of pleasure.
</p><p>He came back to earth with a start, and, recognizing the
sketch, looked more than half irritated.
    "Oh! it is that, is it?" he said.
</p><p>"It is perfect!" she exclaimed.  "What a picture it will
make!" </p><p>"It is not to be a picture," he answered.  "It was
not intended to be anything more than a sketch."
</p><p>"But why not?" she asked.  "It is too good to lose.  You
never had such a model in your life before."
    "No," he answered grudgingly.
</p><p>The hand with which Rebecca held the sketch dropped. She
turned her attention to her lover, and a speculative interest
grew in her face. </p><p>"That girl,"&mdash;she said slowly, after a
mental summing up occupying a few seconds,&mdash;"that girl irritates
you&mdash;irritates you."
    He laughed faintly.
</p><p>"I believe she does," he replied, "yes, `irritates' is the
word to use."
</p><p>And yet if this were true, his first act upon returning
home was a singular one.
</p><p>He was rather late, but the girl Lodusky

<pb n="681"/> was sitting in the moonlight at the door.  He stopped
and spoke to her. </p><p>"If I should wish to paint you," he said
rather coldly, "would you do me the favor of sitting to me?"
</p><p>She did not answer him at once, but seemed to weigh his
words as she looked out across the moonlight.
</p><p>"Ye mean, will I let ye put me in a picter?" she said at
last.     He nodded.
    "Yes," she answered.
</p><p>I reckon he told ye he was a-paintin' Dusk's picter,"
"Mis'" Harney said to her boarders a week later.
</p><p>"Mr. Lennox," returned Rebecca, "yes, he told us."
</p><p>"I thort so," nodding benignly.  "Waal now, Dusk'll make a
powerful nice picter if she don't git contrairy.  The trouble
with Dusk is her a-gittin' contrary.  She's as like old Hance
Dunbar as she kin be.  I mean in some ways.  Lord knows,
'twouldn't do to say she was like him in everythin'."
</p><p>Naturally, Miss Noble made some iniquiries into the nature
of old Hance Dunbar's "contrairiness."  Secretly, she had a
desire to account for Lodusky according to established theory.
</p><p>"I wonder ye haint heern of him," said Mis'" Harney.  "He
was jest awful&mdash;old Hance!  He was Nath's daddy, an' Lord! the
wickedest feller!  Folks was afeared of him.  No one darsn't to
go a-nigh him when he'd git mad-a-rippin' 'in' a-rearin' 'n' a-chargin'.  'N' he never got no religion, mind ye; he died jest
that a-way.  He was allers a hankerin' arter seein' the world,
'n' he went off an' staid off a right smart while,&mdash;nine or ten
year,&mdash;'n' lived in all sorts o' ways in them big cities.  When
he come back he was a sight to see, sick 'n' pore 'n' holler-eyed, but as wicked as ever.  Dusk was a little thing 'n' he was
a old man, but he'd laugh 'n' tell her to take care of her face
'n' be a smart gal.  He was drefful sick at last 'n' suffered a
heap, 'n' one day he got up offen his bed 'n' tuk down Nath's gun
'n' shot hisself as cool as could be.  He hadn't no patience 'n'
he said, `When a der-derned man had lived through what he had 'n'
then wouldn't die, it was time to kill him.'  Seems like it
sorter 'counts fur Dusk, she don't git her cur'usness from her
own folks; Nath an' Mandy's mighty clever, both on 'em."
</p><p>Perhaps it does 'count for Dusk," Rebecca said, after
telling the tale to Lennox.  "It must be a fearful thing to have
such blood in one's veins and feel it on fire.  Let us," she
continued with a smile, "be as charitable as possible."
</p><p>When the picture was fairly under way, Lennox's visits to
the Harneys' cabin were somewhat less frequent.  The mood in
which she found he had gradually begun to regard his work aroused
in Rebecca a faint wonder.  He seemed hardly to like it, and yet
to be fascinated by it.  He was averse to speaking freely of it,
and still he thought of it continually.  Frequently when they
were together, he wore an absent, perturbed air.
</p><p>"You do not look content," she said to him once.
</p><p>He passed his hand quickly across his forehead and smiled,
plainly with an effort, but he made no reply.
</p><p>The picture progressed rather slowly upon the whole.
Rebecca had thought the subject a little fantastic at first and
yet had been attracted by it.  A girl in a peculiar dress of
black and white bent over a spring with an impatient air trying
in vain to catch a glimpse of her beauty in the reflection of the
moonlight.
</p><p>"It's our spring, shore," commented" Mis'" Dunbar.  "N'
its Dusk&mdash;but Lord! how fine she's fixed.  Ye're as fine as ye
want to be in the picter, Dusk, if ye wa'n't never fine afore.
Don't ye wish ye had sich dressin' as thet thar now?"
</p><p>The sittings were at the outset peculiarly silent.  There
was no untimely motion or change of expression, and yet no trying
passiveness.  The girl gave any position a look of
unconsciousness quite wonderful.  Privately, Lennox was convinced
that she was an actress from habit&mdash;that her ease was the result
of life-long practice.  Sometimes he found his own consciousness
of her steady gaze almost unbearable.  He always turned to meet
her deep eyes fixed upon him with an expression he could not
fathom.  Frequently he thought it an expression of dislike&mdash;of
secret resentment&mdash;of subtle defiance.  There came at last a time
when he knew that he turned toward her again and again because he
felt that he must&mdash;because he had a feverish wish to see if the
look had changed.
</p><p>Once when he did this he saw that it <hi rend="italic"> had</hi>
changed.  She had moved a little, her eyes were dilated with a
fire which startled him beyond self-control, her color came and
went, she breathed fast.  The next instant she sprang from her
chair.
</p><p>"I wont stand it no longer," she cried panting; "no
longer&mdash;I wont!" </p><p>Her ire was magnificent.  She flung her

<pb n="682"/> head back, and struck her side with her clenched
hand.
</p><p>"No longer!" she said; "not a minute!"
</p><p>Lennox advanced one step and stood, palette in hand,
gazing at her. </p><p>"What have I done?" he asked.  "What?"
</p><p>"What?" she echoed with contemptuous scorn.  "Nothin'!
<hi rend="italic"> But d'ye think don't know ye?"</hi>
</p><p>"Know me!" he repeated after her mechanically, finding it
impossible to remove his glance from her.
</p><p>"What d'ye take me fur?" she demanded.  "A fool?  Yes, I
was a fool&mdash;a fool to come here, 'n' set 'n' let ye&mdash;let ye
despise me!" in a final outburst.
</p><p>Still he could only echo her again, and say "Despise you!"
</p><p>Her voice lowered itself into an actual fierceness of
tone. </p><p>"Ye've done it from first to last," she said.
"Would ye look at her like ye look at me?  Would ye turn half way
'n' look at her 'n' then turn back as if&mdash;as if&mdash;.  Aint there"&mdash;
her eyes ablaze&mdash;"aint there no <hi rend="italic"> life</hi> to me?"
    "Stop!" he began hoarsely,
</p><p>"I'm beneath her, am I?" she persisted, "ME beneath
another woman&mdash;Dusk Dunbar!  It's the first time!"
</p><p>She walked toward the door as if to leave him, but
suddenly she stopped.  A passionate tremor shook her; he saw her
throat swell.  She threw her arm up against the logs of the wall
and dropped her face upon it, sobbing tumultuously.
</p><p>There was a pause of perhaps three seconds.  Then Lennox
moved slowly toward her.  Almost unconsciously he laid his hand
upon her heaving shoulder and so stood trembling a little.

</p><p>When Rebecca paid her next visit to the picture it struck
her that it appeared at a standstill.  As she looked at it her
lover saw a vague trouble growing slowly in her eyes.
</p><p>"What!" he remarked.  "It does not please you?"
</p><p>"I think," she answered,&mdash;"I feel as if it had not pleased
you." </p><p>He fell back a few paces and stood scanning it with
an impression at once hard and curious.
</p><p>"Please me!" he exclaimed in a voice almost strident.  "It
should.  She has beauty enough."
</p><p>On her return  home that day Rebecca drew forth from the
recesses of her trunk her neglected writing folio and a store of
paper. </p><p>Miss Thorne, entering the room, found her kneeling
over the trunk, and spoke to her.
    "What are you going to do?" she asked.
    Rebecca smiled faintly.
</p><p>"What I ought to have begun before," she said.  "I am
behindhand with my work."
</p><p>She laid the folio and her ink-stand upon the table, and
made certain methodical arrangements for her labor.  She worked
diligently all day, and looked slightly pale and wearied when she
rose from her seat in the evening.  Until eleven o'clock she sat
at the open door, sometimes talking quietly, sometimes silent and
listening to the wind among the pines.  She did not mention her
lover's name, and he did not come.  She spent many a day and
night in the same manner after this.  For the present the long,
idle rambles and unconventional moon-lit talks were over.  It was
tacitly understood between herself and her aunt that Lennox's
labor occupied him.
</p><p>"It seems a strange time to begin a picture&mdash;during a
summer holiday," said Miss Thorne a little sharply upon one
occasion.
</p><p>Rebecca laughed with an air of cheer.
</p><p>"No time is a strange time to an artist," she answered.
"Art is a mistress who gives no holidays."
</p><p>She was continually her bright, erect, alert self.  The
woman who loved her dearly and had known her from her earliest
childhood, found her sagacity and knowledge set at naught as it
were.  She had been accustomed to see her niece admired far
beyond the usual lot of women; she had gradually learned to feel
it only natural that she should inspire quite a strong sentiment
even in casual acquaintances.  She had felt the delicate power of
her fascination herself, but never at her best and brightest had
she found her more charming or quicker of wit and fancy than she
was now.
</p><p>Even Lennox, coming every few days with a worn-out look
and touched with a haggard shadow, made no outward change in her.
</p><p>"She does not look," said the elder lady to herself, "like
a neglected woman."  And then the sound of the phrase struck her
with a sharp incredulous pain.  "A neglected woman!" she
repeated,&mdash;"Beck!"
</p><p>She did not understand, and was not weak enough to ask
questions.</p>

<pb n="683"/>
<p>Lennox came and went, and Rebecca gained upon her work until
she could no longer say she was behindhand.  The readers of her
letters and sketches found them fresh and sparkling, "as if,"
wrote a friend, "you were braced both mentally and physically by
the mountain air."
</p><p>But once in the middle of the night Miss Thorne awakened
with a mysterious shock to find the place at her side empty and
her niece sitting at the open window in a quiet which suggested
that she might not have moved for an hour.
</p><p>She obeyed her strong first impulse, and rose and went to
her. </p><p>She laid her hand on her shoulder, and shook her
gently. </p><p>"Beck!" she demanded, "what are you doing?"
</p><p>When the girl turned slowly round, she started at the
sight of her cold, miserable pallor.
</p><p>"I am doing nothing&mdash;nothing," she answered.  "Why did you
get up?  It's a fine night, isn't it?"
</p><p>Despite her discretion, Miss Thorne broke down into a
blunder. </p><p>"You&mdash;you never look like this in the day-time!"
she exclaimed. </p><p>"No," was the reply given with cool
deliberateness.  No; I would rather <hi rend="italic"> die</hi>."
</p><p>For the moment she was fairly incomprehensible.  There was
in the set of her eye and the expression of her fair, clear face,
the least hint of dogged obstinacy.
    Beck&mdash;" she began.
</p><p>"You ought not to have got up," said Beck.  "It is enough
to look `like this' at night when I am by myself.  Go back to
bed, if you please." </p><p>Miss Thorne went back to bed meekly.
She was at once alarmed and subdued.  She felt as if she had had
a puzzling interview with a stranger. </p><p>In these days Lennox
regarded his model with morbid interest.  A subtle change was
perceptible in her.  Her rich color deepened, she held herself
more erect, her eye had a larger pride and light.  She was a
finer creature than ever, and yet&mdash;she came at his call.  He
never ceased to wonder at it.  Sometimes the knowledge of his
power stirred within him a vast impatience, sometimes he was
hardened by it, but somehow it never touched him, though he was
thrown into tumult&mdash;bound against his will.  He could not say
that he understood her.  Her very passiveness baffled him and
caused him to ask himself what it meant.  She spoke little, and
her emotional phases seemed reluctant, but her motionless face
and slowly raised eye always held a meaning of their own.
</p><p>On an occasion when he mentioned his approaching
departure, she started as if she had received a blow, and he
turned to see her redden and pale alternately, her face full of
alarm.
</p><p>"What is the matter?" he asked brusquely.
</p><p>"I&mdash;hadn't bin thinkin' on it," she stammered.  "I'd
kinder forgot." </p><p>He turned to his easel again and painted
rapidly for a few minutes.  Then he felt a light touch on his
arm.  She had left her seat noiselessy and stood beside him.  She
gave him a passionate, protesting look.  A fire of excitement
seemed to have sprung up within her and given her a defiant
daring. </p><p>"D'ye think I'll stay here&mdash;when ye're gone&mdash;like
I did before?" she said.
</p><p>She had revealed herself in many curious lights to him,
but no previous revelation had been so wonderful as was the swift
change of mood and hearing which took place in her at this
instant.  In a moment she had melted into soft tears, her lips
were tremulous, her voice dropped into a shaken whisper.
</p><p>"I've allers wanted to go away," she said.  "I&mdash;I've
allers said I would.  I want to go to a city somewhar&mdash;I don't
keer whar.  I might git work&mdash;I've heerd of folks as did.
P'r'aps some un ud hire me!" </p><p>He stared at her like a man
fascinated.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">" You</hi> go to the city alone!" he said under his
breath.  <hi rend="italic">" You</hi> try to get work!"
</p><p>"Yes," she answered.  "Don't ye know no one&mdash;"
    He stopped her.
</p><p>"No," he said, "I don't.  It would be a dangerous business
unless you had friends.  As for me, I shall not be in America
long.  As soon as I am married I go with my wife to Europe."
</p><p>He heard a sharp click in her throat.  Her tears were
dried and she was looking straight at him.
</p><p>"Are ye a-goin' to be married?" she asked.
    "Yes."
</p><p>To&mdash;<hi rend="italic"> her?"</hi> with a gesture in the direction of
the Harneys' cabin.
    "Yes."
</p><p>"Oh!" and she walked out of the room.</p>

<pb n="684"/>
<p>He did not see her for three days, and the picture stood
still.  He went to the Harneys' and found Rebecca packing her
trunk.
</p><p>"We are going back to New York," she said.
    "Why?" he asked.
    "Because our holiday is over."
</p><p>Miss Thorne regarded him with chill severity.
</p><p>"When may we expect to see you?" she inquired.
</p><p>He really felt half stupefied,&mdash;as if for the time being
his will was paralyzed.
    "I don't know," he answered.
</p><p>He tried to think that he was treated badly and coldly.
He told himself that he had done nothing to deserve this style of
thing, that he had simply been busy and absorbed in his work, and
that if he had at times appeared preoccupied it was not to be
wondered at.  But when he looked at Rebecca he did not put these
thoughts into words; he did not even say that of course he should
follow them soon, since there was nothing to detain him but a
sketch or two he had meant to make.
</p><p>By night they were gone and he was left restless and
miserable.  He was so restless that he could not sleep but
wandered down toward the spring.  He stopped at the exact point
at which he had stopped on the night of his arrival&mdash;at the top
of the zigzag little path leading down the rocky incline.  He
stopped because he heard a sound of passionate sobbing.  He
descended slowly.  He knew the sound&mdash;angry, fierce,
uncontrollable&mdash;because be had heard it before.  It checked
itself the instant he reached the ground.  Lodusky leaning
against a projecting rock kept her eyes fixed upon the water.
</p><p>"Why did you come here?" he demanded, a little excitedly.
"What are you crying for?  What has hurt you?"
</p><p>"Nothin'," in a voice low and unsteady.
</p><p>He drew a little nearer to her and for the first time was
touched.  She would not look at him, she was softened and
altered, in her whole appearance, by a new pallor.
</p><p>"Have&mdash;" he began, "have I?"
</p><p>"You!" she cried, turning on him with a bitter, almost
wild, gesture.  <hi rend="italic">" You</hi> wouldn't keer if I was struck
<hi rend="italic"> dead</hi> afore ye!" </p><p>"Look here," he said to her,
with an agitation he could not master.  "Let me tell you
something about myself.  If you think I am a passably good fellow
you are mistaken.  I am a bad fellow, a poor fellow, an ignoble
fellow.  You don't understand?" as she gazed at him in
bewilderment.  "No, of course, you don't.  God knows I didn't
myself until within the last two weeks.  It's folly to say such
things to you; perhaps I say them half to satisfy myself.  But I
mean to show you that I am not to be trusted.  I think perhaps I
am too poor a fellow to love any woman honestly and altogether.
I followed one woman here, and then after all let another make me
waver&mdash;"
    "Another!" she faltered.
    He fixed his eyes on her almost coldly.
    "You," he said.
</p><p>He seemed to cast the word at her and wonder what she
would make of it.  He waited a second or so before he went on.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">" You</hi>, and yet you are not the woman I love
either.  Good God!  What a villain I must be.  I am an insult to
every woman that breathes.  It is not even you&mdash;though I can't
break from you, and you have made me despise myself.  There! do
you know now&mdash;do you see now that I am not worth&mdash;"
</p><p>The next instant he started backward.  Before he had time
for a thought she had uttered a low cry, and flung herself down
at his feet. </p><p>"I don't keer," she panted; "I wont keer fuir
nothin',&mdash;whether ye're good or bad,&mdash;only don't leave me here
when ye go away."

</p><p>A week later Lennox arose one morning and set about the
task of getting his belongings together.  He had been up late and
had slept heavily and long.  He felt exhausted and looked so.
</p><p>The day before, his model had given him his last sitting.
The picture stood finished upon the easel.  It was a thorough and
artistic piece of work, and yet the sight of it was at times
unbearable to him.  There were times again, however, when it
fascinated him anew when he went and stood opposite to it,
regarding it with an intense gaze.  He scarcely, knew how the
last week had passed.  It seemed to have been spent in alternate
feverish struggles and reckless abandonment to impulse.  He had
let himself drift here and there, he had at last gone so far as
to tell himself that the time had arrived when baseness was
possible to him.
</p><p>"I don't promise you an easy life," he had said to Dusk
the night before.  "I tell you I am a bad fellow, and I have lost
something through you that I cared for.  You may wish yourself
back again."</p>

<pb n="685"/>
<p>"If you leave me," she said, "I'll kill myself!" and she
struck her hands together.
</p><p>For the moment he was filled, as he often was, with a
sense of passionate admiration.  It was true he saw her as no
other creature had ever seen her before, that so far as such a
thing was possible with her, she loved him&mdash;loved him with a
fierce, unreserved, yet narrow passion. </p><p>He had little
actual packing to do&mdash;merely the collecting of a few masculine
odds and ends, and then his artistic accompaniments.  Nothing was
of consequence but these; the rest were tossed together
indifferently, but the picture was to be left until the last
moment, that its paint might be dry beyond a doubt.
</p><p>Having completed his preparations he went out.  He had the
day before him, and scarcely knew what to do with it, but it must
be killed in one way or another.  He wandered up the mountain and
at last lay down with his cigar among the laurels.  He was full
of a strange excitement which now thrilled, now annoyed him.
</p><p>He came back in the middie of the afternoon and laughed a
rather half-hearted laugh at the excellent Mandy's comment upon
his jaded appearance. </p><p>"Ye look kinder tuckered out," she
said.  Ye'd oughtn't ter walked so fur when ye was a-gwine off
to-night.  Ye'd orter rested."
</p><p>She stopped the churn-dasher and regarded him with a good-natured air of interest.
</p><p>"Hev ye seed Dusk to say good-bye to her?" she added.
"She's went over the mountain ter help Mirandy Stillins with her
soap.  She wont be back fur a day or two."
</p><p>He went into his room and shut the door.  A fierce
repulsion sickened him.  He had heretofore held himself with a
certain degree of inward loftiness; he had so condemned the
follies and sins of other men, and here he found himself involved
in a low and common villainy, in the deceits which belonged to
his crime, and which preyed upon simplicity and ignorant trust.
</p><p>He went and stood before his easel, hot with a blush of
self-scorn. </p><p>"Has it come to this?" he muttered through his
clenched teeth-"to <hi rend="italic"> this!"</hi>
</p><p>He made an excited forward movement; his foot touched the
supports of the easel, jarring it roughly; the picture fell upon
the floor. </p><p>"What?" he cried out.  "Beck!  You!  Great
God!"
</p><p>For before him, revealed by the picture's fall, the easel
held one of the fairest memories he had of the woman he had
proved himself too fickle and slight to value rightly.
</p><p>It was merely a sketch made rapidly one day soon after his
arrival and never wholly completed, but it had been touched with
fire and feeling, and the face looked out from the canvas with
eyes whose soft happiness stung him to the quick with the
memories they brought.  He had meant to finish it and had left it
upon the easel that he might turn to it at any moment, and it had
remained there, covered by a stronger rival&mdash;forgotten.
</p><p>He sat down in a chair and his brow fell upon his hands.
He felt as if he had been clutched and dragged backward by a
powerful arm. </p><p>When at last he rose, he strode to the
picture lying upon the floor, ground it under his heel and
spurned it from him with an imprecation. </p><p>He was, at a
certain hour, to reach a particular bend in the road some miles
distant.  He was to walk to this place and if he found no one
there, to wait.
</p><p>When at sunset that evening he reached it, he was half an
hour before the time specified, but he was not the first at the
tryst.  He was within twenty yards of the spot when a figure rose
from the roots of a tree and stood waiting for him&mdash;the girl Dusk
with a little bundle in her hand. </p><p>She was not flushed or
tremulous with any hint of mental excitement; she awaited him
with a fine repose, even the glow of the dying sun having no
power to add to her color, but as he drew near he saw her look
gradually change.  She did not so much as stir, but the change
grew slowly, slowly upon her face and developed there into
definite shape&mdash;the shape of secret, repressed dread.
</p><p>"What is it," she asked when he at last confronted her,
"that ails ye?" </p><p>She uttered the words in a half whisper,
as if she had not the power to speak louder, and he saw the hand
hanging at her side close itself.     "What is it&mdash;that ails ye?"
</p><p>He waited a few seconds before he answered her.
</p><p>"Look at me," he said at last, "and see."
</p><p>She did look at him.  For the space of ten seconds their
eyes were fixed upon each other in a long, bitter look.  Then her
little bundle dropped on the ground.</p>

<pb n="686"/>
<p>"Ye've went back on me," she said under her breath again.
"Ye've went back on me!"
</p><p>He had thought she might make some passionate outcry, but
she did not yet.  A white wrath was in her face and her chest
heaved, but she spoke slowly and low, her hands fallen down by
her side.
</p><p>"Ye've went back on me," she said.  "An' <hi rend="italic"> I knew ye
would</hi>." </p><p>He felt that the odor of his utter falseness
tainted the pure air about him; he had been false all round,&mdash;to
himself, to his love, to his ideals,&mdash;even in a baser way here.
</p><p>"Yes," he answered her with a bitterness she did not
understand, "I've gone back on you."  Then as if to himself, "I
could not even reach perfection in villainy."
</p><p>Then her rage and misery broke forth.
</p><p>"Yer a coward!" she said, with gasps between her words.
"Yer afraid!  I'd sooner&mdash;I'd sooner ye'd killed me&mdash;<hi rend="italic">
dead!"</hi>
</p><p>Her voice shrilled itself into a smothered shriek, she
cast herself face downward upon the earth and lay there clutching
amid her sobs at the grass.
</p><p>He looked down at her in a cold, stunned fashion.
</p><p>"Do you think," he said hoarsely, "that you can loathe me
as I loathe myself?  Do you think you can call me one shameful
name I don't know I deserve?  If you can, for God's sake let me
have it."
    She struck her fist against the earth.
</p><p>"Thar wasn't a man I ever saw," she said, "that didn't
foller after me, 'n' do fur me, 'n' wait fur a word from me.
They'd hev let me set my foot on 'em if I'd said it.  Thar wasn't
nothin' I mightn't hev done&mdash;not nothin'.  An' now&mdash;an' now&mdash;"
and she tore the grass from its earth and flung it from her.
</p><p>"Go on," he said.  "Go on and say your worst."
</p><p>Her worst was bad enough, but he almost exulted under the
blows she dealt him.  He felt their horrible sting a vague
comfort.  He had fallen low enough surely when it was a comfort
to be told that he was a liar, a poltroon and a scoundrel.
</p><p>The sun had been down an hour when it was over and she had
risen and taken up her bundle.
</p><p>"Why don't ye ask me to forgive ye?" she said with a
scathing sneer.  "Why don't ye ask me to forgive ye&mdash;an' say ye
didn't mean to do it?" </p><p>He fell back a pace and was silent.
With what grace would the words have fallen from his lips?  And
yet he knew that he had not <hi rend="italic"> meant</hi> to do it.
</p><p>She turned away and at a distance of a few feet stopped.
She gave him a last look&mdash;a fierce one in its contempt and anger,
and her affluence of beauty had never been so stubborn a fact
before.
</p><p>"Ye think ye've left me behind," she said.  "An' so ye
hev&mdash;but it aint fur allers.  The time'll come when mebbe ye'll
see me ag'in." </p><p>He returned to New York, but he had been
there a week before he went to Rebecca.  Finally, however, he
awoke one morning feeling that the time had come for the last
scene of his miserable drama.  He presented himself at the house
and sent up his name, and in three minutes Rebecca came to him.
</p><p>It struck him with a new thrill of wretchedness to see
that she wore by chance the very dress she had worn the day he
had made the sketch&mdash;a pale, pure-looking gray with a scarf of
white lace loosely fastened at her throat.  Next, he saw that
there was a painful change in her, that she looked frail and
worn, as if she had been ill.  His first words he scarcely heard
and never remembered.  He had not come to make a defense, but a
naked, bitter confession.  As he made it low and monotonously, in
brief, harsh words, holding no sparing for himself, Rebecca stood
with her hand upon the mantel looking at him with simple
directness.    There was no rebuke in her look, but there was
weariness.  It occurred to him once or twice and with a terribly
humiliating pang, that she was tired of him,&mdash;tired of it all.
</p><p>"I have lost you," he ended. "And I have lost myself.  I
have seen myself as I am,&mdash;a poorer figure, a grosser one than I
ever dreamed of being, even in the eyes of my worst enemy.
Henceforth, this figure will be my companion.  It is as if I
looked at myself in a bad glass, but now, though the reflection
is a pitiable one, the glass is true."
</p><p>"You think," she said, after a short silence, "of going
away?"     "Yes."
    "Where?
    "To Europe."
</p><p>"Oh!" she ejaculated, with a soft, desperate sound of
pain. </p><p>His eyes had been downcast and he raised them.
</p><p>"Yes," he said, mournfully.  "We were to have gone
together."     "Yes," she answered, "together."</p>

<pb n="687"/>
<p>Her eyes were wet.
</p><p>"I was very happy," she said, "for a little while."
</p><p>She held out her hand.
</p><p>"But," she added, as if finishing a sentence.  "You have
been truer to me than you think."
</p><p>"No&mdash;no," he groaned.
</p><p>"Yes, truer to me than you think&mdash;and truer to yourself.
It was I you loved&mdash;I!  There have been times when I thought I
must give that up, but now I know I need not.  It was I.
Sometime, perhaps,&mdash;sometime,&mdash;not now&mdash;" </p><p>Her voice
broke, she did not finish, the end was a sob.  Their eyes rested
upon each other a few seconds, and then he released her hand and
went away.
</p><p>He was absent for two years, and during that time his
friends heard much good of him.  He lived the life of a recluse
and a hard worker.  He learned to know his own strength, and
taught the world to recognize it also. </p><p>At the end of the
second year, being in Paris, he went one night to the <hi rend="italic">
Nouvelle Opera</hi>.  Toward the close of the second act he
became conscious of a little excited stir among those surrounding
him.  Every glass seemed directed toward a new arrival who stood
erect and cool in one of the stage-boxes.  She might have been
Cleopatra.  Her costume was of a creamy satin, she was covered
with jewels and she stood up confronting the house, as it
regarded her, with <hi rend="italic"> sang froid.</hi>
</p><p>Lennox rose hurriedly and left the place.  He was glad to
breathe the bitterly cold but pure night air.  She had made no
idle prophecy.  He had seen her again!
</p><p>There hung upon the wall of his private room a picture
whose completion had been the first work after his landing.  He
went in to it and looked at it with something like adoration.
</p><p>"Sometime," he said, "perhaps now," and the next week he
was on his way home.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
