<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CanArti"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="CanArti">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Artist</title>
<title type="sort">artist</title>
<author>Canfield, Dorothy</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">22</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CanArti</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475780</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Artist</title>
<title type="sort">artist</title>
<author>Dorothy Canfield</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner's</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1911">1911</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Scribner's Magazine</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1911">1911</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-02">February 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Monique Dull, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>TEI markup added.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">



<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="289"/>
<head> THE ARTIST </head>
<p>
After the sickening stench of personality in theatrical life," the
great Madame Orloff told the doctor with her usual free-handed use
of language, "it is like breathing a thin, pure air to be here
again with our dear inhuman old Vieyra.  He hypnotizes me into his
own belief that nothing matters &mdash; not broken hearts, nor death, nor
success, nor first love, nor old age &mdash; nothing but the chiaroscuro
of his latest acquisition."
</p><p>The picture-dealer looked at her in silence, bringing the
point of his white beard up to his chin with a meditative fist.
The big surgeon gazed about him with appreciative eyes, touched his
mustache to his gold-lined coffee-cup, and sighed contentedly.
"You're not the only one, my dear Olga," he said, "who finds
Vieyra's hard heart a blessing.  When I am here in his magnificent
old den, listening to one of his frank accounts of his own artistic
acumen and rejoicing in his beautiful possessions, why the rest of
the world &mdash; real humanity &mdash; seems in retrospect like one great
hospital full of shrieking incurables."
</p><p>"Oh, humanity &mdash; !"  The actress thrust it away with one of her
startling, vivid gestures.
</p><p>"You think it very clever, my distinguished friends, to
discuss me before my face," commented the old picture-dealer
indifferently.  He fingered the bright-colored decorations on his
breast, looking down at them with absent eyes.  After a moment he
added, "and to show your in-ti-mate knowledge of my character."
</p><p>Only its careful correctness betrayed the foreignness of his
speech.
</p><p>"Oh, character &mdash; !"  Madame Orloff repudiated the conception in
a vague murmur.
</p><p>There was a pause in which the three gazed idly at the fire's
reflection in the brass of the superb old andirons.  Then, "Haven't
you something new to show us?" asked the woman.  "Some genuine
Masaccio, picked up in a hill-town monastery &mdash; a real Ribera?"
</p><p>The small old Jew drew a long breath.  "Yes, I have something
new."  He hesitated, opened his lips, closed them again and,
looking at the fire, "Oh yes, very new indeed &mdash; new to me."
</p><p>"Is it here?"  The great surgeon looked about the picture-covered walls.
</p><p>"No; I have it in &mdash; you know, what you call the inner
sanctuary &mdash; the light here is not good enough."
</p><p>The actress stood up, her glittering dress flashing a thousand
eyes at the fire.  "Let me see it," she commanded.  "I would like
to see something new to you."
</p><p>"You shall amuse yourself by identifying the artist without my
aid," said old Vieyra.
</p><p>He opened a door, held back a portiere, let his guests pass
through into a darkened room, turned on a softly brilliant light,
and: "Whom do you make the artist?" he said.  He did not look at
the picture.  He looked at the faces of his guests, and after a
long silent pause, he smiled faintly into his beard.  "Let us go
back to the fire," he said, and clicked them into darkness again.
</p><p>"And what do you say?" he asked as they sat down.
</p><p>"By Jove!" cried the doctor.  "By Jove!"
</p><p>Madame Orloff turned on the collector the sombre glow of her
deep-set eyes.  "I have dreamed it," she said.
</p><p>"It is real," said Vieyra.  "You are the first to see it.  I
wished to observe how &mdash; "
</p><p>"It's an unknown Vermeer!"  The doctor brought his big white
hand down loudly on this discovery.  "Nobody but Vermeer could have
done the plaster wall in the sunlight.  And the girl's strange gray
head-dress must be seventeenth-century Dutch of some province I
don't &mdash; "
</p><p>"I am a rich man, for a picture-dealer," said Vieyra, "but
only national governments can afford to buy Vermeers nowadays."
<pb n="290"/>
</p><p>"But you picked it up from some corner, some attic, some
stable &mdash; "
</p><p>"Yes, I picked it up from a stable," said the collector.
</p><p>The actress laid her slender, burning fingers on his cool old
hand.  "Tell us &mdash; tell us," she urged.  "There is something
different here."
</p><p>"Yes, there is something different," he stirred in his chair
and thrust out his lips.  "So different that I don't know if you &mdash; "
</p><p>"Try me! try me!" she assured him ardently.  "You have
educated me well to your standards all these years."
</p><p>At this he looked at her, startled, frowning, attentive, and
ended by shaking off her hand.  "No, I will not tell you."
</p><p>"You shall &mdash; " her eyes commanded, adjured him.  There was a
silence.  "I will understand," she said under her breath.
</p><p>"You will not understand," he said in the same tone; but aloud
he began: "I heard of it first from an American picture-dealer over
here scraping up a mock-Barbizon collection for a new millionaire.
He wanted to get my judgment, he said, on a canvas that had been
brought in to him by a cousin of his children's governess.  I was
to be sure to see it when I went to New York &mdash; you knew, did you
not, that I had been called to New York to testify in the
prosecution of Paullsen for selling a signed copy?"
</p><p>"Did you really go?" asked the doctor.  "I thought you swore
that nothing could take you to America."
</p><p>"I went," said the old man grimly.  "Paullsen did me a bad
turn once, thirty years ago.  And while I was there I went to see
the unknown canvas.  The dealer half apologized for taking my
time &mdash; said he did not as a rule pay any attention to freak things
brought in from country holes by amateurs, but &mdash; I remember his
wording &mdash; this thing, some ways he looked at it, didn't seem bad
somehow."
</p><p>The collector paused, passed his tongue over his lips, and
said briefly: "Then he showed it to me.  It was the young girl and
kitten in there."
</p><p>"By Jove!" cried the doctor.
</p><p>"You have too exciting a profession, my good old dear," said
the actress.  "Some day you will die of a heart failure."
</p><p>"Not after living through that!"
</p><p>"What did you tell him?"
</p><p>"I asked for the address of the cousin of his childrens'
governess.  When I had it I bought a ticket to the place, and when
I reached there I found myself at the end of all things &mdash; an
abomination of desolation.  Do you know America, either of you?"
</p><p>The doctor shook his head.
</p><p>"I have toured there three times," said the actress.
</p><p>"Did you ever hear of a place called Pennsylvania?"
</p><p>Madame Orloff smiled.  "It is as large as five Englands."
</p><p>"It is inhabited by an insufferable sect of fanatics called
Quakers, who live in preposterously ugly little wooden houses of
the most naked cleanliness, who will not swear, who have no priests
and no doctrine, apparently, but the blasphemous one that color,
sacred, holy color is an evil thing, and that gray is the only
virtuous &mdash; "
</p><p>The actress laughed.  "There are other people in
Pennsylvania," she protested.
</p><p>Vieyra ignored her.  "In a wretched huddle of little houses
they call a village I found the cousin, a seller of letter-paper
and cheap chromos, who knew nothing of the picture except that it
was brought to him to sell by the countryman who sold him butter.
I found the address of the butter-maker, and drove endless miles
over execrable roads to his house, and encountered his mother, a
stolid, middle-aged woman, who looked at me out of the most uncanny
quiet eyes &mdash; all the fanatics there have the extraordinary eyes &mdash;
from under a strange, gray head-dress, and asked: 'Is it about the
picture?  For you don't want to let on to anybody but me.  Nobody
but the family knows he paints 'em!'"
</p><p>At this the doctor burst out: "Gracious powers!  You don't
mean he is a living man!"
</p><p>"Let him alone!"  The actress turned with a lithe petulance on
the big Briton.
</p><p>"And there I had it all," the narrator went on; "the old woman
could tell me what I wished to know, she said.  He was her uncle,
the only brother of her mother, and he had brought up her and her
brothers and sisters.  She knew &mdash; oh, she knew with good reason, all
of his life.  All, that is, but the beginning.  She had heard from
older Quakers that he had been wild in his youth (he had always
been, she told me gravely, <pb n="291"/>  queer) and she knew that he had
travelled far in his young days, very, very far.
</p><p>"'To New York?' I ventured.
</p><p>"'Oh, no, beyond that.  Across the water.'
</p><p>"'To Paris?'
</p><p>"That she didn't know.  It was a foreign country at least, and
he had stayed there two, three years, until he was called back by
her father's death &mdash; his brother-in-law's &mdash; to take care of his
mother, and his sister and the children.  Here her mind went back
to my question, and she said she had something perhaps I could tell
from, where he had been.  She kept it in her Bible.  He had given
it to her when she was a child as a reward the day she had kept her
little brother from falling in the fire.  She brought it out.  It
was a sketch, hasty, vigorous, suggestive, haunting as the original
itself, of the Leonardo da Vinci Ste. Anne.
</p><p>"Yes, I told her, now I knew where he had been.  And they had
called him back from there &mdash; <hi rend="italic">here?</hi>
</p><p>"'When my father died,' she repeated, 'my uncle was all my
grandmother and my mother had.  We were five little children, and
the oldest not seven, and we were all very poor.'
</p><p>"'How old was your uncle then?' I asked.
</p><p>"'A young man &mdash; he was younger than my mother.  Perhaps he was
twenty-five.'
</p><p>"I looked at the sketch in my hand.  Twenty-five, and called
back from Paris &mdash; <hi rend="italic">here!</hi>
</p><p>"'When did he go back?'
</p><p>"'Oh, he never went back.'  She told me this quite placidly,
as she said everything else.  'He never went back at all.'
</p><p>"He had stayed there the rest of his life, and worked the
little farm that was all his sister had, and made a living for
them &mdash; not large, the farm being poor and he not a first-class
farmer, but still enough.  He had always been kind to them &mdash; if he
was quite queer and absent.  She had heard her grandmother say that
at first, the first ten years, perhaps, he had had strange, gloomy,
savage fits, like a person possessed that you read of in the Bible;
but she herself could never remember him as anything but quiet and
smiling.  He had a very queer smile, unlike any one else, as I
would notice for myself when I went to see him about the picture.
You could tell him by that, and by his being very lame.
</p><p>"That brought me back with a start.  I rushed at her with
questions.  'How about the picture?  Were there others?  Were there
many?  Had he always painted?  Had he never shown them to any one?
Was he painting now?
</p><p>"She could not tell me much.  It had been a detail of their
common life she had but absently remarked, as though she had lived
with a man who collected snail-shells, or studied the post-marks on
letters.  She had never noticed &mdash; that was the answer to most of my
questions.  No, she did not think there were very many now, though
he must have painted 'most a million.  He was always at it, every
minute he could spare from farming.  But they had been so poor he
had not felt he could afford many canvases.  The paints cost a good
deal too.  So he painted them over and over, first one thing and
then another, as he happened to fancy.  He painted in the horse-barn.  'Had a place rigged up,' in her phrase, in one corner of the
room where the hay was stored, and had cut a big window in the roof
that was apt to let in water on the hay if the rain came from the
east.
</p><p>"'What did he paint?'  'Oh, anything.  He was queer about
that.  He'd paint <hi rend="italic">any</hi>thing!  He did one picture of nothing but
the corner of the barn-yard, with a big white sow and some little
pigs in the straw, early in the morning, when the dew was on
everything.  He had thought quite a lot of that, but he had had to
paint over it to make the picture of her little sister with the
yellow kittie &mdash; the one she'd sent down to the village to try to
sell, the one &mdash; '
</p><p>"'Yes, yes,' I told her, 'the one I saw.  But did he never try
to sell any himself?  Did he never even show them to any one?'
</p><p>"She hesitated, tried to remember, and said that once when
they were very poor, and there was a big doctor's bill to pay, he
<hi rend="italic">had</hi> sent a picture down to New York.  But it was sent back.
They had made a good deal of fun of it, the people down there,
because it wasn't finished off enough.  She thought her uncle's
feelings had been hurt by their letter.  The express down and back
had cost a good deal too, and the only frame he had got broken.
Altogether, she guessed that discouraged him.  Anyhow, he'd never
tried again.  He seemed to get <pb n="292"/>  so after a while that he
didn't care whether anybody liked them or even saw them or not &mdash; he
just painted them to amuse himself, she guessed.  He seemed to get
a good deal of comfort out of it.  It made his face very still and
smiling to paint.  Nobody around there so much as knew he did it,
the farm was so far from neighbors.
</p><p>"'Twas a real lonely place, she told me, and she had been glad
to marry and come down in the valley to live closer to folks.  Her
uncle had given her her wedding outfit.  He had done real well by
them all, and they were grateful; and now he was getting feeble and
had trouble with his heart, they wanted to do something for him.
They had thought, perhaps, they could sell some of his pictures for
enough to hire a man to help him with the farm work.  She had heard
that pictures were coming into fashion more than they had been, and
she had borrowed that one of her little sister and the kittie, and
without her uncle's knowing anything about it, had sent it off.
She was about discouraged waiting for somebody down in the city to
make up his mind whether he'd buy it or not.
</p><p>"I asked her a thousand other questions but she could answer
none of them.  The only detail I could get from her being an
account of her uncle's habit of 'staring' for sometimes a half an
hour at something, without once looking away.  She'd seen him stop
that way, when he'd be husking corn maybe, and stare at a place
where a sunbeam came in on a pile of corn.  It put him back quite
considerable in his work, that habit, but they had nothing to
complain of.  He'd done well by them, when you considered they
weren't his own children.
</p><p>"'Hadn't he ever tried to break away?' I asked her, amazed.
'To leave them?  To go back?'
</p><p>"She told me: 'Oh, no, he was the only support his mother and
his sister had, and there were all the little children.  He <hi rend="italic">had</hi>
to stay.'"
</p><p>The actress broke in fiercely: "Oh, stop! stop! it makes me
sick to hear about.  I could boil them in oil, that family!  Quick!
You saw him?  You brought him away?  You &mdash; "
</p><p>"I saw him," said Vieyra, "yes, I saw him."
</p><p>Madame Orloff leaned toward him, her eyebrows a line of
painful attention.
</p><p>"I drove that afternoon up to a still tinier village in the
mountains near where he lived, and there I slept that night &mdash; or, at
least, I lay in a bed."
</p><p>"Of course, you could not sleep," broke in the listening
woman; "I shall not to-night."
</p><p>"When dawn came I dressed and went out to wander until people
should be awake.  I walked far, through fields, and then through a
wood as red as red-gold &mdash; like nothing I ever saw.  It was in
October, and the sun was late to rise.  When I came out on an
uplying heath, the mists were just beginning to roll away from the
valley below.  As I stood there, leaning against a tree in the edge
of the wood, some cows came by, little, pinched, lean cows, and a
young dog bounding along, and then, after them, slowly, an old man
in gray &mdash; very lame."
</p><p>The actress closed her eyes.
</p><p>"He did not see me.  He whistled to the dog and stroked his
head, and then as the cows went through a gate, he turned and faced
the rising sun, the light full on his face.  He looked at the
valley coming into sight through the mists.  He was so close to me
I could have tossed a stone to him &mdash; I shall never know how long he
stood there &mdash; how long I had that face before me."
</p><p>The narrator was silent.  Madame Orloff opened her eyes and
looked at him piercingly.
</p><p>"I cannot tell you &mdash; I cannot!" he answered her.  "Who can tell
of life and death and a new birth?  It was as though I were
thinking with my fingernails, or the hair of my head &mdash; a part of me
I had never before dreamed had feeling.  My eyes were dazzled.  I
could have bowed myself to the earth like Moses before the burning
bush.  How can I tell you &mdash; ?  How can I tell you?"
</p><p>"He was &mdash; ?" breathed the woman.
</p><p>"Hubert van Eyck might have painted God the Father with those
eyes &mdash; that mouth &mdash; that face of patient power &mdash; of selfless, still
beatitude. &mdash; Once the dog, nestling by his side, whimpered and
licked his hand.  He looked down, he turned his eyes away from his
vision, and looked down at the animal and smiled.  Jehovah!  What
a smile.  It seemed to me then that if God loves humanity, he can
have no kinder smile for us.  And then he looked back <pb n="293"/>
across the valley &mdash; at the sky, at the mountains, at the smoke
rising from the houses below us &mdash; he looked at the world &mdash; at some
vision, some knowledge &mdash; what he saw &mdash; what he saw &mdash; !
</p><p>"I did not know when he went.  I was alone in that crimson
wood.
</p><p>"I went back to the village.  I went back to the city.  I
would not speak to him till I had some honor worthy to offer him.
I tried to think what would mean most to him.  I remembered the
drawing of the Ste. Anne.  I remembered his years in Paris, and I
knew what would seem most honor to him.  I cabled Drouot of the
Luxembourg Gallery.  I waited in New York till he came.  I showed
him the picture.  I told him the story.  He was on fire!
</p><p>"We were to go back to the mountains together, to tell him
that his picture would hang in the Luxembourg, and then in the
Louvre &mdash; that in all probability he would be decorated by the French
government, that other pictures of his would live for all time in
Paris, in London, in Brussels &mdash; a letter came from the woman, his
niece.  He was dead."
</p><p>The actress fell back in her chair, her hands over her face.
</p><p>The surgeon stirred wrathfully.  "Heavens and earth, Vieyra,
what a beastly, ghastly, brutally tragic horror are you telling us,
anyhow!"
</p><p>The old Jew moistened his lips and was silent.  After a moment
he said: "I should not have told you.  I knew you could not
understand."
</p><p>Madame Orloff looked up sharply.  "Do you mean &mdash; is it possible
that <hi rend="italic">you</hi> mean that if we had seen him &mdash; had seen that look &mdash; we
would &mdash; that he had had all that an artist &mdash; "
</p><p>The picture-dealer addressed himself to her, turning his back
on the doctor.  "I went back to the funeral, to the mountains.  The
niece told me that before he died he smiled suddenly on them all
and said: 'I have had a happy life.'  I had taken a palm to lay on
his coffin, and after I had looked long at his dead face, I put
aside the palm.  I felt that if he had lived I could never have
spoken to him &mdash; could never have told him."
</p><p>The old Jew looked down at the decorations on his breast, and
around at the picture-covered walls.  He made a sweeping gesture.
</p><p>"What had I to offer him?" he said. </p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

