<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CanMill"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="CanMill">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Story of Ralph Miller / By Dorothy Canfield ; Author of "A Philanthropic Honeymoon," "The Rescue," "Moonshine"</title>
<title type="sort">story of ralph miller by dorothy canfield author of a philanthropic honeymoon, the rescue moonshine</title>
<author>Canfield, Dorothy</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">28</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CanMill</idno>
<date value="1999">1999</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1999 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475785</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Story of Ralph Miller</title>
<title level="m">Munsey`s magazine.</title>
<title type="sort">story of ralph miller</title>
<author>Dorothy Canfield</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>New York.</pubPlace>
<date value="1906">1906.</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Alderman Library AP2.M8 v.36 1906-1907</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1907">1906-1907.</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>feminine</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1999-04">April, 1999</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Matthew Gibson, Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">


<div1 type="story" id="d3">
	
	<head>THE STORY OF RALPH MILLER<lb/>
		BY DOROTHY CANFIELD<lb/>
		AUTHOR OF "A PHILANTHROPIC HONEYMOON," "THE RESCUE," "MOONSHINE"</head>

<div2 type="part" n="1" id="d4">

<p>THE Miller family was a devotedly
united one, and family councils
were common things with them, but
never had they assembled with such anxious faces and earnest, apprehensive
voices.  As usual, Mrs. Miller dominated
the group, striking the key
customary firmness.  "Something must
be done to save the boy from an irreparable mistake.  We may thank Heaven
for the lucky chance by which we discovered what is going on.  It is not too
late to rescue him."
</p><p>She looked about the little circle with
a determined expression on her aquiline
face.  As usual, they all responded in
the key which she had begun, running
up and down the gamut of agreement,
from Aunt Caroline's doubtful "Yes,
but Fanny, what can <hi rend="italic">be</hi> done?  I think
as you do, but &mdash;" to Mr. Miller's
hearty "I depend on you, Fanny!  You'll
know how to manage it."
</p><p>Only Cousin Richard was silent.  One
never knew whether he was joining in
the common harmony or was executing
a melody of his own, so consistently did
he, as a rule, keep his grim mouth closed.
On that account Mrs. Miller passed him
over in the fervor of her explanations
and plans.
</p><p>"It's a common enough mistake," she
went on.  "He has no conception of the
nature of social distinctions, and, besides
that, I suppose scarcely any boy grows
up without fancying he's in love with
a woman old enough to be his mother.
I dare say the woman has made him believe she's desperately in love, and
Ralph's generosity has betrayed him into
responding to a fancied claim on him."
</p><p>Aunt Caroline threw in a fluttered
protest.  "Perhaps, Fanny, dearest, she
<hi rend="italic">is</hi> fond of him.  I've always heard her
so well spoken of by the other teachers."
</p><p>Mrs. Miller snorted.  "Do you suppose for a moment that if Ralph hadn't
inherited his uncle's money she would
have done anything but laugh at him?"
</p><p>Cousin Dick flicked the ash from his
cigar with an expressionless face, but
Mrs. Miller instinctively turned toward
him as if he were about to speak.  However, he put the cigar back in his mouth,
ran his finger through his wiry white
hair, and regarded her in silence with
steady eyes.  Fanny went on with her
monologue:
</p><p>"I should be a recreant mother if I
weren't willing to exert myself in every
possible way &mdash; even the most painful one.
I mean to go and see this absurd
old maid, and &mdash; and &mdash; I mean to go and
<hi rend="italic">see</hi> her!  I think I can put an end to the
whole nonsense.  The idea!  She must be
twelve years older than he!  She used to
correct his little compositions in the high
school.  It was a mistake not sending
him East to college, just as I wished at
the time.  He must go away now.  Richard shall take him to Europe when he
sails next week."
</p><p>Mr. Miller protested.  "Oh, Fanny,
do you think that is necessary?  It will
keep him from graduating from college
this spring with his class."
</p><p>His wife swept aside all obstacles.
"What's that to saving our only son
from a foolish infatuation?  A boy with
his brains and wealth and social position
doesn't <hi rend="italic">need</hi> to graduate."
</p><p>Cousin Richard seemed to be preparing to say something.  He took his cigar
out of his mouth, ground the end in the
ash-tray until the last red spark was
gone, and then stood up, drawing his
coat about his spare, upright figure.
</p><p>"You'll make a mistake if you interfere in this, Frances," he said, in a dry,
colorless way.  "I'll take the lad abroad,


<pb n="325"/>

if you say, but you'll be making a mistake if you go to Miss Wilson or try and
bully Ralph.  I think, from what he said
to me, he is in love with her.  Ralph is
a man, almost &mdash; he'll be twenty-one in a
few months, and in his own way he's
mature for his years.  You can't run his
destiny the way you run your chapter
of the D. A. R."
</p><p>Mrs. Miller broke out in a passion of
protest.  Dick was crazy &mdash; she hoped she
knew her duty to protect dear, generous,
impulsive, ignorant Ralph, her only son
&mdash; her only child.  She would have tact;
she knew Miss Wilson was a perfectly
respectable person; but how preposterous!  The difference in their station, if
there was nothing else &mdash; Ralph Miller,
only son of the Millers of Millerstown,
and Rachel Wilson, teacher of English
in the public high school!  Why, her
father was a carpenter, and her mother
used to go out as nurse before she was
married!
</p><p>"They're both dead," remarked
Cousin Richard, his hand on the knob
of the door.
</p><p>"As if that made any difference!"
cried Fanny to his retreating back.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="part" n="2" id="d5"><head>II</head>

<p>MRS. MILLER was a brave woman, accustomed to the command not only of
others but of herself; but she felt an
odd dryness in her throat as she stood
waiting for a response to her ring at the
bell over which was fixed an old-fashioned brass plate marked "Wilson."  Since
the death of her parents Mary Wilson
had lived on alone in the house where
she was born, a little white cottage with
a quaint, prim garden about it, redolent
of old-fashioned perfumes and filled
with memories of her mother's mild,
faded presence.  The flower garden had
been the gentle passion of the older woman's life, and Mary could not look out
upon the neat beds and luxuriant old
shrubs without a momentary vision of
her mother's stooped shoulders bending
over the roses, or hearing her slow, light
footfall in the now so empty gravel
paths.
</p><p>Inside, the low-ceilinged rooms were
as sensibly filled with her father's simple, kindly spirit.  The thousand ingenious contrivances for lightening the
work of the household, the shelves and
brackets here and there, the windows
lowered to the floor so that her little
mother could look out on the garden as
she sat sewing, the window-seat box for
Mary's toys when she was a child &mdash; all
surrounded the lonely woman with a
sense of remembered affection and care.
</p><p>Mrs. Miller rang the bell again.  It
resounded through a house patently empty.  She drew out her watch and noticed
that she was ahead of time.  The high
school, two squares away, would not be
dismissed for five minutes.  She looked
about for a place to wait, and sank down
on a bench under an arbor of wistaria,
just then in full bloom, in the leafless
luxuriance of early spring.  Fanny relaxed, in spite of herself, in the
quiet perfumed silence of the little garden.  She was fond of flowers herself,
and noticed with an absently approving
eye the healthy vigor of the lilacs and
peonies, beginning to leaf.  Rows of
sweet peas were just thrusting green
bowed heads through the brown earth.
</p><p>For a moment the mother knew an
instant's rest from the turmoil of anxiety
about her son.  But it surged up in her
at the sound of the gate clicking behind
her.  She turned and saw Mary Wilson
walking up the path, her fair uncovered
head shining in the sunlight.  Mrs.
Miller rose, her knees shaking under her,
her mouth parched, but with the determination of a mother fighting for her
young gleaming from her dark eyes.
The other woman stopped, surprised and
hesitating.
</p><p>Mrs. Miller came forward.  She knew
the teacher by sight, remembering her
from the days when the family had
laughed at Ralph's boyish admiration
for her.  "This is Mrs. Miller," she said
in a neutral voice, and then, with a sudden flash, "I am Ralph Miller's mother,
and I have come to talk to you about
him!"
</p><p>Mary Wilson flushed a slow, painful
red up to the roots of her blond hair,
but she commanded her voice enough to
say evenly: "Won't you come into my
house, Mrs. Miller?"
</p><p>She opened the door, stood on one side
to let the older woman pass, and they
both entered the little living-room in a
complete silence.  A canary swinging


<pb n="326"/>

in the open window burst into a roulade
of joyful welcome to his mistress.  Mary
carried him into another room, and, returning, found Mrs. Miller seated in
the cretonne-covered chair her father
had made her mother.  The school-teacher sat down across the room and
waited, her hands tightly clasped.
</p><p>Mrs. Miller hesitated at first for
words, but when she began they came in
a rush: "Miss Wilson, you see in me
a very unhappy woman.  I have just
learned of my son's engagement to you,
and I have come to reason with you
about it; to use every inducement I can
think of to induce you to break so absurd, so unnatural a relationship.  You
may ask me why I do not go to my son.
I have done so, and I come here with a
heart aching from the first quarrel with
my only child, from the first harsh words
my boy has ever given me."
</p><p>Her voice trembled, but she set her
lips together firmly for a moment and
went on: "You are an intelligent woman, of some experience.  You cannot have
lived to your age" &mdash; Mary winced at
this &mdash; "without knowing how preposterous a marriage between you and my son
would be, how it would expose you both
to ridicule and humiliation, and how it
would mean unhappiness in the end for
you.  Ralph is not yet twenty-one, and
you must be over thirty &mdash;"
</p><p>Mary interrupted her.  "I am thirty-four, Mrs. Miller; but your son loves
me."
</p><p>The mother gave an impatient gesture.  "Love!  What does a child his
age know about love!  He is the victim
of an ordinary foolish infatuation.  He
undoubtedly does admire you greatly and
respect you, and probably he has a
great affection for you, but as for loving
you &mdash; he doesn't know, he <hi rend="italic">can't</hi> know,
the meaning of the word."
</p><p>Mary's clasped hands tightened.
"What you say would be true in all
cases but one out of a thousand, but this
is the one time it is not true.  Ralph has
always been an unusual boy.  You must
not think, Mrs. Miller, that I have not
tormented myself over the difference in
our ages and stations as much as you,
but I know Ralph through and through"
&mdash; her face paled with a sudden exaltation of certainty &mdash; "and he is unlike
others of his age.  He is a man, in spite
of his youth, and he loves with a man's
love."
</p><p>Mrs. Miller's countenance wore the
half-shocked, half-scornful expression
of middle-aged Puritans when a passion
is spoken of.  "I didn't suppose you
still clung to those immature, romantic
ideas of life.  I should think you were
old enough to see more clearly, but I
suppose an unmarried woman, no matter
how old she is, is always a child.  Marriage is not a matter of romance.  Love
must be at the bottom of it all, of course,
but married life is made up of a thousand prosaic details where weightier
matters than passion decide the course
of things.  You say Ralph 'loves' you.
Perhaps he does now; but think, if the
unsparing light of the intimacy of married life were thrown on you!  Think!
When he is finished with his medical
course he will be twenty-five &mdash; a young
man of twenty-five &mdash; and you will be
nearly forty."
</p><p>Mary groaned and hid her face
in her hands.  The mother went on, encouraged, her eyes glowing with the holy
cruelty of fanatics.
</p><p>"You don't look your age now, it is
true, at least to men's eyes; but you
know, and every woman who sees you
knows, how near you are to middle age.
Think what anguish it would be for you
to see Ralph suddenly conscious of your
first gray hairs or the wrinkles deepening about your mouth!  Think what
humiliation it would be to have people
pointing at you and to know that they
were saying, 'There goes the sentimental old maid who married one of her
high-school pupils!'"
</p><p>Mary cried aloud in pain and stood
up, throwing her arms above her head.
"Do you think I care for an instant
what people would say?  Why, I love
Ralph.  I <hi rend="italic">love</hi> him!  He is the only
man in the world for me.  I, who would
die to serve him &mdash; would I care what
gossiping people say?"
</p><p>So intense, so unreserved an ardor
rang in her voice that for a moment the
mother was silenced, though her courage rose as Mary, with a sudden lapse
into miserable uncertainty, said brokenly, "It is only for his own sake that I
hesitate &mdash;"


<pb n="327"/>

</p><p>Mrs. Miller was quick to see the opening.  Her voice softened as she laid her
hand on Mary's shoulder.  "My dear,"
she said, almost kindly, "no one knows
how terribly I pity you.  I believe you
wholly.  When I came here, I confess
I had a different conception of your
character.  I even thought it might be
Ralph's independent fortune which &mdash;"
</p><p>At Mary's scornful, blazing look she
choked and hurried on: "But I see you
are a good woman, who really loves my
son.  And it is in the name of that
love that I appeal to you now.  I do
not speak of the difference in station
between you, although I believe honestly that is almost impossible to cross, but
I appeal to you to save the man you love
from wrecking his life.  You know &mdash;
you must know &mdash; as I do, that in spite
of all pretty phrases your plan is an insane one.  You must feel that he cannot
know himself yet.  If you know him so
intimately as you say, you must be aware
how wildly and impulsively generous he
is.  If he thought the shadow of an obligation to you rested on him he would
give himself eagerly to living up to what
you expected.  Be as generous as he!
Don't take advantage of his youth, his
utter inexperience &mdash;"  She was pleading as for her life.
</p><p>Mary Wilson looked at her with smoldering eyes, and caught her up with an
eagerness as intense as her own.  "You
don't know what you're asking.  It must
be you have never loved.  It is like
asking me to hold my breath until I die
&mdash; it is superhuman.  Think!" she cried
in quivering appeal &mdash; "think of what it
would mean to the Ralph we both know,
the sensitive, exquisitely honorable, self-doubting soul, to have always with him
a love like mine, a steady, enduring, understanding affection, sure with the certainty of maturity, always to be a shield
between him and the world which is so
cruel to gentle and delicately organized
beings such as he is!  Think what I
could be to him &mdash; how I could guard
him and steady him in his belief in himself!  I would give every atom of my
heart and intelligence to making him
happy and strong &mdash;"  She was choked
with tears, and stopped, sobbing.
</p><p>Mrs. Miller shook her head.  "That
is a mother's love you are describing.  He
has one mother; he does not need another.  The common lot should be his.
He should not be shielded and guarded,
even by a great affection.  He should
shield and guard another.  Only so
could he ever grow.  He must marry,
not some one who has lived through the
experience he must have, but some one
young, ignorant, like himself, with whom
he can grow in power, whose very mistakes will be strengthening to him, whom
he must lead and uphold."
</p><p>Through the strong, firm body of the
younger woman there was running a
series of convulsive shudders.  She sank
into a chair and laid her head in her
hands.  Mrs. Miller talked on and on,
sure that she had hit upon the right line.
She was surprised at the depth of pity
she felt for the motionless figure before
her, shaken from time to time with a
dry sob, but she was fighting for the
happiness of her child, and conviction
grew within her as she talked.  Finally
there was a long silence, significant and
portentous, throbbing with the premonition of a decision.  Mary lifted her head
and looked about her with tired eyes.
</p><p>"You are right," she said in a low
tone, quite steady.  "I will do as you
say.  It is best for Ralph."
</p><p>Mrs. Miller broke down for the first
time, and wept loudly in her handkerchief.  "You are a noble woman!" she
said between her sobs.  "I can never
be grateful enough to your generosity."
</p><p>The other said quietly: "It is not
for you I am doing it.  It is for Ralph"
&mdash; and then, with a sudden return to her
white exaltation &mdash; "for Ralph, whom I
love as no one was ever loved before,
since for his good I am willing to sacrifice his belief in me."  Her fervor subsided again, and she was only very pale
and still as she closed the door on her
visitor, saying: "You need have no fear.
Ralph will never come back to me."
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="part" n="3" id="d6"><head>III</head>

<p>IT was a long, still summer in Millerstown.  Mary Wilson worked in her
garden, her shoulders beginning to be
stooped, as her mother's had been.  Mrs.
Miller walked about the park-like setting to her large house &mdash; the "mansion,"
as it was called by the inhabitants of
Millerstown, who admired and envied


<pb n="328"/>

the Millers with a curious mixture of
respect for rank and jealous fear of condescension.
</p><p>Mrs. Miller lived on the letters of
Cousin Richard, the grim, devoted man
to whom they had confided the utterly
crushed boy who had returned to them
from Mary Wilson's cottage.  The old
cousin wrote, on the whole, encouragingly.  Ralph was looking better, had more
color, seemed to be going about and
sightseeing.  He had been examined
lately by a doctor, who said he was as
sound as a bell.  He &mdash; Dick &mdash; thought
that Ralph seemed listless and preoccupied, but perhaps that was natural under
the circumstances.  At any rate, he was
well, and grew handsomer every day.
All the women in the street turned and
looked after him.
</p><p>"He is well &mdash; he is well!" Mrs.
Miller said it over and over to herself,
extracting every drop of comfort possible out of it.  Her heart yearned over
her son's sorrow, but she was jubilant
in her rescue of him.  So long as the
sensitive lad, as delicate as a girl, did not
fall ill with his foolish worry, she could
hope for nothing better.  The medicine
was working as she had hoped.  The
change, the new experiences, the acquaintance with other people of wholly
different views &mdash; all would make a new
creature of him and bring him back to
her to laugh at his idle romance.
</p><p>The last news received before they
started home in the fall was quite as
reassuring as the rest had been.  Dick
was obliged to stay in London over one
sailing, but Ralph was to come on alone
and visit New York while he waited
for his cousin before they began the journey west to Millerstown.  Ralph was
well, and seemed more like himself than
for some time.
</p><p>The eight days of the silence of the
ocean voyage passed quietly in Millerstown, and then came a thunderclap, a
telegram from Ralph, in New York, the
day he landed:

</p><p>I was married this morning to Dottie
Coster, of London.  We will go to Millers-town in two weeks.  She was a member of
the chorus of the Alhambra in London.
She is eighteen years old.

</p><p>The savage brutality of the announcement and the keen thrust of the last
sentence made Mrs. Miller's heart stand
still.  In an anguish beyond words she
showed the telegram to her husband.
When cousin Richard arrived alone, a
week later, he found a broken and aged
woman waiting to hear what he had to
say.  Trusting in her old self-confident
strength and hard courage to bear the
truth, he did not spare her.  He told
the story in his dry, concise way, his
weather-beaten old face twisted with a
sorrow which made it almost grotesque.
</p><p>"Yes, I saw them.  Yes, she is an
actress, a chorus-girl, rather &mdash; not even
an actress &mdash; a common cockney chorus-girl, with a foolish, pretty face, if she
wouldn't spoil it with paint.  She's respectable enough, I fancy; too young
to be anything else.  Ralph met her on
the steamer.  The first night out they
sighted an iceberg, and all the passengers were called up to see it.  The girl
got things twisted somehow &mdash; thought
there was a wreck and that they were all
going to the bottom, and when she found
there was no danger burst out crying
and saying she'd hoped she was going
to die; there was nothing for her to do
but die.
</p><p>"You can guess how that would stir
Ralph's chivalrous spirit of protection,
and he made her tell what her story
was.  It seems she'd embarked with an
engagement with a chorus in New York,
and after the steamer had sailed a delayed letter had been handed to her canceling the contract.  She had no money,
no friends, nowhere to go when she landed in New York, nowhere to return even
in London, since her father, a scene-shifter in the Alhambra, had died just
before she sailed.  You can imagine the
rest of the journey &mdash; Ralph and his impetuous chivalry and sore heart, and this
clinging, helpless, pretty creature looking up to him as to a beautiful young
god of strength and wisdom.
</p><p>"Ralph told me he didn't love her.
'How can I ever love again?' he said.
'But she loves me, and it is something
to do with a disabled and wrecked life
to make her happy and protect her
against herself.  Mary told me I was
a hopelessly immature boy whom no
grown woman could really love.  Dottie is more immature than I &mdash; I am of
importance to some one, at least.'"


<pb n="329"/>

</p><p>Cousin Dick stopped short.  His voice
had been growing harsher and harsher,
till it broke suddenly.  "Damn it!" he
exclaimed, "I wish I could cry as you're
doing, Fanny; it seems to me I'll have
a stroke if I don't!"  He got up and
strode out of the room, his hand at his
wrinkled old throat.  At the door he
paused and said the final thing in his
miserable message.  "Ralph told me to
say: 'I hope my parents think Dottie
is young enough.'"
</p><p>In the storm of the family council,
afterward, Fanny Miller's clear mind
failed her.  She was utterly confused
and broken, a rudderless ship adrift on
the raging torrent of condemnation.  Her
husband could not find words bitter
enough to characterize Ralph's conduct
and the disgrace he had brought upon
them.
</p><p>"He may come home!" he raged.
"I'll never forbid my house to my only
son; but greet the girl he's married I
will not, nor shall any of you!  What
it is to have a child who overwhelms
you with shame!"
</p><p>Aunt Caroline murmured agitatedly:
"Oh, what will people think!  We can't
introduce her to any one.  I <hi rend="italic">don't</hi> want
to speak to an actress!"
</p><p>Only Cousin Dick was silent.  He
looked at Fanny as if he expected some
action from her, but she was too distraught to plan or do anything but shudder as wave after wave of realization
of what she had done swept over her.
Suddenly there rose before her distracted
mind the vision of Mary Wilson's shining face.  "Oh!" she cried to herself,
"she loved Ralph; she will tell me what
to do!"
</p><p>Into the white tranquillity of the little
living-room she rushed like one seeking
sanctuary, and poured out to the tall,
strong woman the pitiable story, sobbing
convulsively and clinging to her like a
child.  Mary sat for a time in a silence
only broken by the trills and sweet high
notes of the canary.  When she spoke
it was with a still desolation of wo that
frightened Mrs. Miller into quiet.
</p><p>"Between us we have ruined his life &mdash;
we have utterly ruined his life &mdash;"
</p><p>Fanny broke in with eager self-reproach: "No words can tell how I
blame myself for what I did in &mdash;"
But Mary's even voice went on: "I do
not blame you; I blame myself.  I knew
Ralph.  I knew in my heart that this
was a time when your worldly wisdom
was the maddest folly.  I should have
been strong enough to stand between
you and your son and save him from
your pharisaical self-confidence &mdash; but
that is past!  I cannot endure to think
what I should have done.  What we
must think now is that we must in some
miraculous way save some little, little
remnants of his happiness.  To give our
whole lives to doing that is a miserably
small return for the injury we have done
him.  No &mdash; oh, no!" she cried suddenly,
rising and throwing off Mrs. Miller, who
was still clinging to her, <hi rend="italic">"I</hi> may not
have even that poor consolation.  I may
not come near to him.  He must never
see me.  He has loved me, he may love
me yet, he may always love me, and the
only thing I can do for him is to stand
far off!"
</p><p>"But <hi rend="italic">you!"</hi> &mdash; she took the mother by
the shoulders with an almost savage grip
&mdash; "you must work for both of us!  You
must at least give me that small satisfaction &mdash; that you will do everything I
would do in your place.  You must give
your every breath to shielding him from
the consequences of this step, you must
welcome his wife, you must make her
happy in this wretched town of gossips,
you must love her, you must transform
her by a sheer passion of desire into a fit
companion for your son!  You must sustain him in fidelity to her, you must make
him love her, if only for her weakness!"
</p><p>The grip of her hands was so tense
that the other woman almost cried out.
Fanny looked at the white face, again
glowing with an exaltation of devotion.
She did not dare embrace her.  She felt
a solemn awe of her.
</p><p>And it was with this awe still in her
heart that she went down to the train to
meet Ralph and his wife.  It was Fanny
Miller's body that moved, but Mary
Wilson's spirit animated it.  She smiled
at Ralph's drawn, unhappy face; she
smiled at the awkward, half-shy, half-bold creature by his side; and it was
with Mary Wilson's own love shining in
her eyes that she drew Dottie to her and
kissed the slack mouth, stained and disfigured with rouge.
</p>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
