<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CanResc"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="CanResc">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Rescue / By Dorothy Canfield.</title>
<title type="sort">rescue by dorothy canfield</title>
<author>Canfield, Dorothy</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">16</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CanResc</idno>
<date value="1999">1999</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1999 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475788</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Rescue</title>
<title level="j">Munsey`s Magazine vol.36,no.1(Oct. 1906): 58-60.</title>
<title type="sort">rescue</title>
<author>Dorothy Canfield</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1906">1906</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Alderman Library, Call no: AP2 .M8 v.36 1906-07</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1906">1906</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>feminine</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1999-05">May, 1999</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Matthew Gibson, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" id="d3"><head>THE RESCUE<lb/>
BY DOROTHY CANFIELD<lb/>
AUTHOR OF "MOONSHINE," "THE BLISS OF SOLITUDE," ETC.</head>



<pb n="58"/>



<p>THE old man controlled himself with
a violent effort, and stopped his
storming commands, daunted by the face
of fierce opposition which the girl turned
to him.  He wheeled about and relieved
his mind by a few clamorous, angry
chords on the great piano against which
he was leaning.  There was a moment's
silence before he faced her again &mdash; a
silence full of faint reminiscent murmurs
and echoes from the music-soaked walls
of the bare little room.  The tense rigidity of the girl's slenderness relaxed a
little; and when the master again looked
at her, the stormy light of revolt was
gone from her eyes, leaving their usual
curious, half-absent brooding.
</p><p>The old man shook back his long white
hair, and began afresh in a new manner.
</p><p>"I am not so unreasonable as you
think," he said in an argumentative tone.
"I know well enough I have no legal
right to order your life in any way; but"
&mdash; his voice broke in a grieved quaver &mdash;
<hi rend="italic">"some</hi> rights I have &mdash; your old master?"
</p><p>The girl's eyes softened.
</p><p>Every right a human parent can have
over his child you have, a thousand times
stronger, over me &mdash; you, who are the
parent of my soul, who have made me
what I am.  But no parent has the right
to forbid his child <hi rend="italic">life!"</hi>
</p><p>"I don't forbid you life!  I am human
as well as you, and I have been young!
There have been women in my life, and
from them I have drawn my best inspiration.  I did not marry because I felt my
art would suffer &mdash; love and marriage are
two different things; but I don't forbid
you even marriage &mdash; least of all, love!
Love all you can, marry if you must; but,
in the name of heaven, do not select the
one man who is separated from you by
an impassable chasm.  You admit yourself that he has no musical feeling!"
</p><p>"He does not know one note from
another," said the girl firmly, "and I
love him for it."
</p><p>"You are insane!  You are simply unfit to govern your life!" cried the other,
in an irresistible burst of choking fury.
"What mad idea have you in your head
to say that?"  He calmed himself again,
one shaking hand at his wrinkled old
throat.  "And an American who is not
rich!  And a college professor!  You,
with your training and knowledge of the
world of live men and women, to bury
yourself in the gossiping, deadening existence of any company of schoolmasters
&mdash; but in America!  And Western America!  You can have no faintest remnant
of reason left, to think of such a thing!"
</p><p>The disciple smiled.
</p><p>"It has been long since you have been
in love, <hi rend="italic">maestro mio!"</hi> she said.
</p><p>"In love!  Do you know what that
means in America?  It means a lure to
get you &mdash; <hi rend="italic">you</hi>, Federiga Potowska &mdash; to do
his housework, to make and maintain a
tiresome social position for him, to bear
his children, and to sink every spark of
your individual life and health and
strength in bringing them up!"
</p><p>Federiga hesitated and then said with
a sudden half bold, half terrified rush:
</p><p>"What better can I do with my vigor
and health?"
</p><p>The old man screamed aloud in a sort
of frenzy.
</p><p>"You blaspheme!  You blaspheme!
You are beside yourself!"
</p><p>And then he sank on the seat before
the piano, and, laying his head on the
keys, he wept aloud, like a child or a
heart-broken old man.  The girl's face
was drawn in nervous lines of agitation,
and she spoke pleadingly.
</p><p>"Oh, no, I didn't mean that.  Henry
will never require me to give up my


<pb n="59"/>

music.  Dear master, you love me; why
deny me the right to take this one golden
opportunity of my life?"
</p><p>"The one golden opportunity!  Have
you no memory?  How many men have
you refused &mdash; men who were mad for
love of you, who could appreciate your
music, which is your soul, as well as your
body and mind.  But this half man, this
barbarian who owns himself tone deaf!"
</p><p>"That is just it &mdash; can't you see?  He
is the only man who has ever loved me &mdash;
<hi rend="italic">me!</hi>  My music is not myself, it is only a
manifestation."
</p><p>"It is not that I am going over the
old ground that a woman of genius
should not marry at all, but it is as if the
most beautiful woman in the world
should insist on marrying a blind man."
</p><p>"Master, tell me truly; I am speaking to you from my heart.  If I had married Alexis Nicolaievitch, as you wished
&mdash; Alexis Nicolaievitch, who would have
given me passionate love, position, freedom from care, and an almost insane
admiration for my music &mdash; and if, on my
wedding-day, my right hand had become
paralyzed, <hi rend="italic">what would have happened?"</hi>
</p><p>The old man defended himself from
this thrust almost indignantly as from an
unfair weapon.
</p><p>"Why, of course!  What do you expect?  Your music is a part of you.  What
have you a right to ask of human men?"
</p><p>Federiga's eyes suddenly blazed with
a wild joy.
</p><p>"That's it!  That's it!  That's all one
has a <hi rend="italic">right</hi> to expect!  But by some unheard-of good fortune I escape the common fate.  I alone can be sure that I am
really loved.  It <hi rend="italic">is</hi> as if a beautiful
woman should marry a blind man!  Do
you suppose, after a woman has lived
long enough to see the barrier that
beauty puts between her and men, after
she has seen the sort of love it calls forth
&mdash; do you suppose, if she could find a
blind man who would love her, herself,
truly and passionately, that she would
not leave all the world to follow him?"
</p><p>The old man stared at her in blank
bewilderment.
</p><p>"You are simply mad!  You have refined on insane subtleties until you cannot see the simplest truths of nature.
What is beauty for, but to draw the hearts
of men?  What are you but your music?"
</p><p>"So I have always feared!  I had come
to feel it as inevitable, as part of the
sadness of human life.  I have thought
that the most beautiful woman never
could find a blind man who would love
her; that, in truth, she was nothing but
her beauty."
</p><p>The musician beat frantically upon the
keys, evoking a clangorous discord of
maddened exasperation.
</p><p>"God in heaven grant me patience!
That such a fool should have such a
genius!  How <hi rend="italic">can</hi> a man love a woman
but for her qualities?  You would not <hi rend="italic">be</hi>
you without your music!"
</p><p>"So I feared, so I feared, although I
cherished the wild hope that all women
have, until it is crushed out of them, that
somewhere there would be a man who
would, by loving it, prove that I had
something beyond the outward show that
all the world may see.  Music has been
like a prison to me, which has shut me
away from all humanity.  Henry Livingstone has delivered me from my bondage,
and I am so happy that it seems at times
I must die of joy."
</p><p>"But me &mdash; do you never think of me?
I have given these last ten years of my
life to you; and without a quiver of remorse, without a sign of self-reproach
for your desertion, you leave me."
</p><p>Tears stood, large and glittering, in
the girl's eyes.
</p><p>"Oh, master, that is the hard part!
There is where you make it bitter for me!
Do you think I have no remorse?"
</p><p>The old man seized with pathetic
eagerness upon this sign of weakening.
</p><p>"Child, child, tell me it is all a bad
dream &mdash; a fancy that has passed!"  The
tears rolled down the girl's cheeks, paled
by the stress of the struggle.  She was
so evidently laboring under some overpowering emotion that the other started
up, eager hope in his eyes.  "You have
seen reason, Federiga!  You are rescued!"
</p><p>He pushed her with an affectionate
roughness into a chair, and bent his stiff
old frame to kneel beside her, his face all
alight with hypnotic fervor, and so impassioned an earnestness breathing from
him that Federiga sank back, her hand
over her eyes.  She did not move from
this position during a long time, while
the master painted with a flaming wealth
of words the golden and glorious future


<pb n="60"/>

which lay before her.  Wrought up by the
intensity of his feeling, he had an inspired certainty that he was succeeding,
that he was hitting the weak places in her
arguments, that the curious, intangible
barriers in the girl's mind were giving
way before the irresistible rush of his eloquence.  He held up her hand, her long
white artist hand, and felt that he made
her realize to the point of breaking nerves
the entrancing possibilities that lay in
its firm grasp.  He appealed to her ambition, the highest form of it he could
imagine; he appealed to her love for him,
and to the debt she owed him; he argued,
with cruelly sharp divination of her character, that the life she had planned would
be a desolate one, a continual horror of
abnegation of the best in her.  He felt
himself in one of those crises of emotion when speech is no longer a barrier to
expression, when the flame of feeling
burns itself palpably to view.
</p><p>And yet, as his agitation grew, and as
he felt hers respond to it, even this
heaven-sent gift of speech was not
enough.  He struggled in the grasp of
a passion higher and keener than he could
put into words, and, with a musician's
instinct, he turned to the piano.  Federiga
saw his purpose, and, breaking the quivering stillness in which she had listened
to him, she cried in an agony of fear:
</p><p>"Oh, no!  Not that!  Don't play to
me!  Don't play to me!"
</p><p>She sprang from her chair and rushed
across the room toward the door, as if
to escape.  The old man, quicker and
stronger than she, put her on one side
roughly, locked the door, and darted back
to the piano, his eyes alight with an imperious certainty of victory.  Federiga
sank down by the door, in the farthest
corner of the room, and put her hands
over her ears with a frenzied gesture;
but after the first puissant chords resounded, her hands dropped despairingly,
and she turned to gaze helplessly at the
magician of sound who was weaving relentlessly the most mighty of his spells.
</p><p>Even as he played, the old master
knew that he was touching the highest
achievement of his life.  All the forces
of his nature were fused into one overwhelming and indomitable resolve to protect the sanctuary of all he held most
sacred.  It was as if his life had been one
long preparation for this moment, so
consciously did he pour into his music
all the potent vitality gained from battles
won in a life of combat for an ideal.
</p><p>After an interval, the defenseless girl
on the other side of the room rose to her
feet as though under a spell, and made
her way blindly across the floor to the
piano.  The player did not look up, but
into the already maddeningly poignant
splendor of his harmonies he infused a
yet more piercing quality of intimate
beauty.  For a long time the three &mdash; the
invincible master, the conquered woman,
and the gloriously resounding instrument &mdash; throbbed and glowed and lived as
one.  And then the old man suddenly
stopped and looked full at Federiga.
</p><p>The room hummed and whispered
about them with the haunting murmurs
of a huge sea-shell.  The girl's slender
body shook almost visibly, and across the
unearthly pallor of her face there still
vibrated inaudible echoes, like the unheard voice of a stringless and dumb
violin that answers with all its fibers the
long-drawn call of another instrument.
</p><p>"Ah, Federiga, am I not right?  Is
there anything else to live for?  See, I
put it on the highest ground.  Do not
live for your music because of the joy
of it &mdash; even because of the heavenly joy
of it &mdash; but for the sake of the divine thing
itself.  You are a priestess chosen by fate
to minister at the altar.  You are necessary to the sacred art.  Consecrate yourself to it &mdash; to the thing which makes us
both what we are."
</p><p>He rose and led her to the piano gently,
as if not to break the spell which lay
upon her.  At the touch of the instrument the blood came to her face in a rush.
She sank upon the seat before it, and
spread out her arms upon it with a fierce,
hungry gesture of devotion which went to
the old man's heart.  She bowed her
bright head above the keys, she laid her
warm cheek upon their cold surface.  She
kissed their deathlike whiteness with her
red lips in a fervor which the master took
to be the passion of consecration.
</p><p>"Heaven be praised!" she cried in
a loud voice of joy.  "You are too late!"
</p><p>"Too late?" he asked.
</p><p>"Too late!  Too late!  Too late!
Thank God, I was married to Henry
Livingstone this morning!"

</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
