<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CarConc"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="CarConc">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Concerning Cheapness</title>
<title type="sort">concerning cheapness</title>
<author>Carroll, Charles</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Charles E. Keller</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">18</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CarConc</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475790</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Concerning Cheapness</title>
<title type="sort">concerning cheapness</title>
<author>Charles Carroll</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner's Monthly</publisher>
<date value="1877">1877</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 13</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 314-317</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text
Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of
the text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in
SpeFQue1 for page one of Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1877">1877</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-03">March 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Timothy Jarrett</name>
</respStmt>
<item>minimal TEI markup</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">



<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="314"/>
<head>Concerning Cheapness</head>
<p>"Hang it all! there goes another!"</p>
<p>"Another what?" said the Pedagogue, looking up from lazy
absorption in his easy-chair and the last Review.</p>
<p>"Why, that's the third pair of those dollar gloves of Brown's that
I've split within the last week or two, trying to struggle into them in a
hurry."</p>
<p>"Sorry for you," as he calmly turned another leaf; "but if I wanted
to be unamiable, I should say it served you right for buying cheap
things."</p>
<p>"Cheap!" I retorted, testily.  "What in poverty's name is a fellow
with my salary to do, but buy cheap things or go without?"</p>
<p>"Go without, I should say, unless he can get good ones.  You
don't seem to have made a very brilliant speculation out of that lot of
rat-skin which Brown sells you for kid.  By your own showing, you have
used up three dollars' worth of the rubbish without a penny's worth of
advantage, when for the same money you might have been gorgeous in
Jones' or Robinson's, at your last two or three parties, and had
something left over that would clean.  See here!" he continued, dropping
his magazine; "sit down a moment; the evening's young yet; you can't
go to the Gunnybags's at eight o'clock, you know.  Take another
cigarette, and give me one, while I free my mind a bit on one of the
delusions of the age.  If I can bring you to a right way of thinking, I
may save you a few dollars and much bother in the course of the next
year, to say nothing of the proud satisfaction of knowing yourself wiser
than your neighbors."</p>
<p>Now, my chum, whom I choose to nickname the Pedagogue, was
an odd fish, with no little experience of men and things in his queer,
out-of-the-way fashion.  Cranky and a little irritable sometimes, he was
still a good scholar, a cool observer, and something of a thinker.  Even
when most impetuous or wrongheaded, he was, for all his verbose
fluency, generally original, and rarely dull.  A long and patient study of
the ways and means of making his dollar bill go as far as another man's
two, had given him ample right to speak in the premises, and the tone of
paradox in his words piqued my curiosity.  So drawing another chair to
the fire, and handing him my last bundle of "caporal," I propped my
patent-leathers on the grate, <hi rend="italic">more Americano</hi>, and waited for
the stream of talk which was sure to come.

<pb n="315"/> </p>
<p>"Cheap!  My dear boy," said the philosopher, sending a long
stream of amber smoke into the fire-place, and gazing meditatively after
it, &mdash; <hi rend="italic">"nothing</hi> is cheap!  There's no such thing as cheapness.
I find every one wasting time, labor, thought, heart, and hope, to say
nothing of conscience, in the effort to get the good things of this life for
less than the market rate.  I see, or think I see, that the only price at
which anything good can be had, is among the higher, &mdash; indeed,
excluding certain very glaring cases of ill-judgment, or caprice, &mdash; among
the highest of the ruling figures.  Occasionally a man pays, no doubt, too
much for a thing; occasionally, too, by some happy and exceptional
chance, he may slip into a 'good thing,' and get full money's worth for
materially less than money value; but in the long run, I devoutly believe,
that in ninety-nine cases out of the hundred, the more you pay for a
thing the better you are served, even in proportion to your price.  The
attempt to get anything worth having, at less than the higher ruling
figures, as I said before, is futile, and generally ends in spending more
in cash, let alone trouble and disappointment, than if you had honestly
met the issue and spent liberally at the start.</p>
<p>"In matters of every-day use, most men are fair judges.  Any fool
knows whether his beefsteak is tender, or his coat fits him; and so I take
it as almost an axiom, that where a man sells an article of general use,
his commodity is, in the long run, judged on its merits; is sought,
consumed, and paid for in pretty accurate correspondence to its real
worth.  As soon as a workman begins to do good work, he begins to
command the market; he can get his price, and be sure he will ask all he
can get.  There is small chance of a good workman going long unknown.
How many mute, inglorious Miltons there may be in the world, I don't
know; but I don't believe there are many mute, inglorious Pooles, and
Worths, and Delmonicos.  Notice, when any one has found what he
thinks a clever artisan or furnisher, how anxiously he spreads the
information, if only for the little vanity of discovery and the credit of
being useful to his friends.  And with the inflow of custom, of course
comes a rise of prices in the individual case, as in the general
market.</p>
<p>"You will tell me, no doubt, that the modest artisan who has a
small shop, in a cheap locality, a small or inexpensive family,
exceptional facilities for getting his raw material, and the like, <hi rend="italic">can
afford</hi> to undersell his 'swell' competitor, who has a more
expensive establishment and appurtenances.  But the simple fact is, that
he <hi rend="italic">doesn't</hi>; or if so, not for long.  Why should he?  The man
who finds he can turn out as good a shoe, or sewing-machine, or grand
piano, as any in the market, is pretty sure, in the first place, to get the
customers, and then to ask the highest market price for his goods.  After
this, he is apt, at least, to forsake his more modest line of business, and
turn 'swell' himself.  If he stick to his quieter scale of outlay, that is just
so much more in his pocket, but no saving to his customer.</p>
<p>"I used, I confess, to think differently, and wasted uncounted
trouble in hunting up cheap furnishers.  I have scolded about Broadway
prices, and ransacked side streets and down-town lanes and corners for
cheap tailors, restaurants, apothecaries, grocers, or what not, but always
with much the same result.  The gain in price was generally slight, the
loss in quality, style, finish, durability, and so on, both constant and
perceptible.  When I occasionally found an article in some by-corner
which could fairly be called a bargain, I found I had spent in fussing
about it enough time and energy to earn the whole price several times
over, &mdash; even at the very limited money value which my time bears to
me" (glancing at a pile of manuscript on his writing-desk).  "People
don't sufficiently consider, in this matter," he went on, "how great is the
value of mere <hi rend="italic">insurance</hi> afforded by high-class, and therefore
high-priced, establishments.  If I can find, as practically I often can, a
butcher who gives me the best of meat nineteen days out of twenty, it is
worth a heavy percentage more to me to deal steadily with him at any
prices within reason, than to try to bring down my expense account by
buying of his cheaper and less responsible rivals, who give me a good
article to-day, and then disappoint me to-morrow.</p>
<p>"And that brings me to another view of the matter.  Beyond mere
evident and momentary use, there are a multitude of more subtle
considerations which often constitute the main value of the article; and in
matters of higher utility and more aesthetic employment, are pretty sure
to do so.  Nervous waste and friction are the great bugbears of existence;
nervous tonic and economy its prime blessings.  And the things which
most promote these refined advantages I have generally found to be
costly at the outset; though, emphatically, cheapest in the long run.
Take, for instance, the vulgar but very necessary business of eating.
There are, all

<pb n="316"/> over the town, hosts of places where you are offered
for a few shillings the same amount of mere ostensible beef and potatoes,
salad and pudding, as you get at Delmonico's or 'The Brunswick,' for
nearly as many dollars.  But, granting that your economical dinner tastes
as good as the dear one, &mdash; a large assumption, &mdash; and that it is equally
nutritious, &mdash; a still greater, &mdash; next comes what I call the nervous
element in the matter.  I get my Nassau street meal in crush, noise, and
hurry, heat and bad air.  My waiter is careless or slovenly, my service
uncomely or unclean, my whole surroundings uncomfortable.  When I
pay the outrageous prices of the 'swell' restaurant, I am buying not
merely so much carbon and nitrogen, but shining glass and silver, snowy
linen, cool fountains and green leaves, trained attendance and quiet,
graceful company.  The cheap 'feed' stays my hunger, but leaves me
with a moral and aesthetic, if not a physical dyspepsia.  The <hi rend="italic">parti
fin</hi> digests better, keeps me personally happy for an hour, and
leaves me in good humor and trim for the evening.</p>
<p>"And Simpson, the bank cashier, who lodged with his family just
below me, used to chuckle at the notion of getting for a thousand a year,
just as good an apartment as his head director, old Discount, who pays
five at 'The Stevens.'  But just look at the thing a moment.  To get
down town from Third avenue above Sixtieth street took Simpson ever
so much more time in the morning and hurried him with his rising and
his breakfast.  Mrs. Simpson had to depend on the cars for all matters of
shopping or calling, and, when she walked out, had to run the gauntlet
of half a dozen outlying settlements of shabbiness, in which stables,
coal-yards, grog-shops, oyster-saloons and tenement-houses were among
the less disagreeable features.  Anything like starting out, impromptu, of
an evening for social visiting, theater or concert, was almost out of the
question; and Mrs. Simpson, who had her own little social ambitions,
found her visiting-list dropping off, because she was too far off the
"beat" of her leisurely and fashionable acquaintance.  Altogether, I
should say, that the inconvenience and general vexation arising from the
situation alone might have been worth two thousand a year to Simpson in
mere worry, though in the simple matter of being comfortably and
warmly housed, perhaps he was as well off as Discount."</p>
<p>"But it seems to me," I broke in, "that you are preaching a
doctrine of unmitigated 'swelldom,' as you would call it yourself.  To
hear you, one would think that it was impossible to be respectable or
comfortable without an outlay of fifteen or twenty thousand a year, that
the honest fellow who has to live on three or four had no business
among decent people, but must make up his mind to abject privation and
humiliation for himself and his family.  The lust of the eye and the pride
of life, to say nothing of other forms of selfishness, bear a chief part in
your social philosophy; and the beauty of simple living and honest
content which you used to praise seems to have lost its value.  Your
doctrine, carried out to the bitter end, would be frightfully demoralizing.
To make a handsome income would become the first and whole duty of
man, and the poor fellow who can't might just as well put an end to
himself at once!"</p>
<p>"Softly, my lad! " said the Pedagogue gravely.  "You exaggerate
my statement, or rather, you misconceive it.  I am not talking morals,
but socio-dynamics, as I call it.  I didn't say, &mdash; did I? &mdash; that all these
considerations which affect our choice in methods of living are highly
laudable or philosophic.  I only say that they <hi rend="italic">exist</hi>, that they
are with most men prime motors in their efforts after the means of
expense, and their regulation of the expense when the means are gained.
No, no, you mustn't misinterpret me.  My system allows plenty of room
for frugality, simplicity, good sense, pluck, and self-denial.  It doesn't
follow that it's necessary, or even desirable, to have all the splendors
and luxuries of life, only you mustn't deny that they are splendid and
luxurious.  What you can't have, go without, of course, like a man, but
don't make yourself absurd by trying to believe or make your neighbor
believe that you can get around plain natural laws, and buy any good
thing without paying its full price in hard cash or hard work.  And that
reminds me that there is a high moral side to our talk which I have
hardly touched on.  When we get above mere personal habit and
expenditure, and come to education, literature, art, civil administration,
government &mdash; ah! there we are on different ground.  There, I should like
to show you, some day when you have time, that there not only
<hi rend="italic">is</hi> no such thing as cheapness, but never can be or ought to
be.  I think it might be easy to prove by the simplest economic
principles, that a cheap picture must be an abomination, cheap
architecture a sham, cheap erudition an absurdity &mdash; that we are
misgoverned by cheap legislators,

<pb n="317"/>
misrepresented by cheap diplomates, mistaught by cheap educators, and
misled by cheap books.  I could illustrate &mdash; but bless me! my dear
fellow," he broke off, looking at the clock, "I have nearly talked away
your evening, and it's time for you to start.  And see here!" he called
out from the landing, "take my advice and <hi rend="italic">don't</hi> take the
street-cars.  Get a cab at the corner.  It's drizzling, you know, and it
wont pay to have your first waltz with Miss Gunnybags in a damp tie
and muddy boots! </p>

</div1>
<div1 type="poem" id="d4">
<head>THE LAST PINE.</head>
<lg type="verse">
<l>Where the fallow-colored hill</l>
<l>   Juts against a cloudy wreath &mdash; </l>
<l>   Gray the sky, the ground beneath</l>
<l>White with shreds from winter's quill &mdash; </l>
</lg><lg type="verse">
<l>Holds a pine of giant girth</l>
<l>   All alone a patience grim</l>
<l>   In the ghastly cold, the dim</l>
<l>Sifted light that wraps the earth</l>
</lg><lg type="verse">
<l>Like a soldier strictly charged</l>
<l>   Never from his watch to yield:</l>
<l>   Long ago was hushed the field,</l>
<l>All his comrades long discharged;</l>
</lg><lg type="verse">
<l>Solid hangs the icy tear,</l>
<l>   Numb his arms with creeping frost,</l>
<l>   And his senses four are lost</l>
<l>In a bitter strife to bear:</l>
</lg><lg type="verse">
<l>Yet unmoved he keepeth post,</l>
<l>   Dim of sight but list'ning still,</l>
<l>   Lest across the lonely hill</l>
<l>Call the bugles of the host.</l>
</lg><lg type="verse">
<l>Once upon a silent day</l>
<l>   Heaved the tree such breaths profound,</l>
<l>   Air was carded into sound;</l>
<l>Thus the pine was heard to say:</l>
</lg><lg type="verse">
<l>               "One by one,</l>
<l>Though they towered high and wide,</l>
<l>Sank my brothers by my side;</l>
<l>Fell away my friends of youth</l>
<l>Death on them had never ruth.</l>
<l>               One by one</l>
<l>Dropped my warming arms of green,</l>
<l>Till I stand of branches lean;</l>
<l>Straight the woodpecker may shoot</l>
<l>From my crown to knotted root:</l>
<l>               All is done!</l>
</lg><lg type="verse">
<l>               "I am past.</l>
<l>Once I dwelt with fellows dear,</l>
<l>Once I felt the green sod near;</l>
<l>               Year by year</l>
<l>In the choir of our wood</l>
<l>Crashed a singer where he stood,</l>
<l>And the boughs that rained forever,</l>
<l>Lowest first, then upward ever.</l>
</lg>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

