<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CatComm"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="CatComm">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Professor's Commencement</title>
<title type="sort">professors commencement</title>
<author>Cather, Willa Sibert</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name>Jessamy Town</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">27</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CatComm</idno>
<date value="1996-10">October, 1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475794</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Professor's Commencement</title>
<title type="sort">professors commencement</title>
<author>Willa Sibert Cather</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>481-488</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>J.T. and E. Buckingham</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston, Mass.</pubPlace>
<date value="1902-06">June 1902</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: Print version not available.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>ns 26</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1902">1902</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-10">October, 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jessamy Town, Electronic Text Center, UVa</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="481"/>
<head>
              <hi rend="bold">The Professor's Commencement</hi>
<lb/>
                     By Willa Sibert Cather
</head>

<p>THE professor sat at his library table at six
o'clock in the morning.  He had risen with the sun, which is up
betimes in June.  An uncut volume of "Huxley's Life and Letters" lay
open on the table before him, but he tapped the pages absently with
his paper-knife and his eyes were fixed unseeingly on the St. Gaudens
medallion of Stevenson on the opposite wall.  The professor's library
testified to the superior quality of his taste in art as well as to
his wide and varied scholarship.  Only by a miracle of taste could so
unpretentious a room have been made so attractive; it was as dainty as
a boudoir and as original in color scheme as a painter's studio.  The
walls were hung with photographs of the works of the best modern
painters,&mdash;Burne-Jones, Rossetti, Corot, and a dozen others.  Above
the mantel were delicate reproductions in color of some of Fra
Angelica's* most beautiful paintings.  The rugs were exquisite in
pattern and color, pieces of weaving that the Professor had picked up
himself in his wanderings in the Orient.  On close inspection, however,
the contents of the book-shelves formed the most remarkable feature of
the library.  The shelves were almost equally apportioned to the
accommodation of works on literature and science, suggesting a form of
bigamy rarely encountered in society.  The collection of works of pure
literature was wide enough to include nearly all the major languages of
modern Europe, besides the Greek and Roman classics.  </p><p>To an
interpretive observer nearly everything that was to be found in the
Professor's library was represented in his personality.  Occasionally,
when he read Hawthorne's "Great Stone Face" with his classes, some
clear sighted student wondered whether the man ever realized how
completely he illustrated the allegory in himself.  The Professor was
truly a part of all that he had met, and he had managed to meet most
of the good things that the mind of man had desired.  In his face
there was much of the laborious precision of the scientist and not a
little of Fra Angelico and of the lyric poets whose influence had
prolonged his youth well into the fifties.  His pupils always
remembered the Professor's face long after they had forgotten the
things he had endeavored to teach them.  He had the bold, prominent
nose and chin of the oldest and most beloved of American actors, and
the high, broad forehead which Nature loves to build about her finely
adjusted minds.  The grave, large outlines of his face were softened
by an infinite kindness of mouth and eye.  His mouth, indeed, was as
sensitive and mobile as that of a young man, and, given certain
passages from "Tristram and Isolde" or certain lines from Heine, his
eyes would flash out at you like wet corn-flowers after a


<pb n="482"/>


spring shower.  His hair was very thick, straight, and silver
white.  This, with his clear skin, gave him a somewhat actor-like
appearance.  He was slight of build and exceedingly frail, with
delicate, sensitive hands curving back at the finger ends, with dark
purple veins showing prominently on the back.  They were exceedingly
small, white as a girl's, and well-kept as a pianist's.  </p><p>As the
Professor sat caressing his Huxley, a lady entered.  </p><p>"It is
half past six, Emerson, and breakfast will be served at seven."
Anyone would have recognized her as the Professor's older sister, for
she was a sort of simplified and expurgated edition of himself, the
more alert and masculine character of the two, and the scholar's
protecting angel.  She wore a white lace cap on her head and a knitted
shawl about her shoulders.  Though she had been a widow for
twenty-five years and more, she was always called Miss Agatha Graves.
She scanned her brother critically and having satisfied herself that
his linen was immaculate and his white tie a fresh one, she remarked,
"You were up early this morning, even for you."  </p><p>"The roses
never have the fragrance that they have in the first sun, they give
out their best then," said her brother nodding toward the window where
the garden roses thrust their pink heads close to the screen as though
they would not be kept outside.  "And I have something on my mind,
Agatha," he continued, nervously fingering the sandalwood
paper-cutter, "I feel distraught and weary.  You know how I shrink from
changes of any sort, and this&mdash;why this is the most alarming thing
that has ever confronted me.  It is absolutely cutting my life off at
the stalk, and who knows whether it will bud again?"  </p><p>Miss
Agatha turned sharply about from the window where she had been
standing, and gravely studied her brother's drooping shoulders and
dejected figure.  </p><p>"There you go at your old tricks, Em," she
remonstrated.  "I have heard many kinds of ability attributed to you,
but to my mind no one has ever put his finger on the right spot.  Your
real gift is for getting all the possible pain out of life, and
extracting needless annoyance from commonplace and trivial things.
Here you have buried yourself for the best part of your life in that
High School, for motives Quixotic to an absurdity.  If you had chosen
a University I should not complain, but in that place all your best
tools have rusted.  Granted that you have done your work a little
better than the people about you, it's no great place in which to
excel,&mdash;a city high school where failures in every trade drift to
teach the business they cannot make a living by.  Now it is time that
you do something to justify the faith your friends have always had in
you.  You owe something to them and to your own name."  </p><p>"I have
builded myself a monument more lasting than brass," quoted the
Professor softly, balancing the tips of his slender fingers together.
</p><p>"Nonsense, Emerson!" said Miss Agatha impatiently.  "You are a
sentimentalist and your vanity is that of a child.  As for those
slovenly persons with offensive manners whom you call your colleagues,
do you fancy they appreciate you?  They are as envious as

<pb n="483"/>

green gourds and their mouths pucker when they pay you
compliments.  I hope you are not so unsophisticated as to believe all
the sentimental twaddle of your old students.  When they want
recommendations to some school board, or run for a city office and
want your vote, they come here and say that you have been the
inspiration of their lives, and I believe in my heart that you are
goose enough to accept it all."  </p><p>"As for my <hi rend="italic">confreres</hi>,"
said the Professor smiling, "I have no doubt that each one receives in
the bosom of his family exactly the same advice that you are giving
me.  If there dwell an appreciated man on earth I have never met him.
As for the students, I believe I have, to some at least, in a measure
supplied a vital element that their environment failed to give them.
Whether they realize this or not is of slight importance; it is in the
very nature of youth to forget its sources, physical and mental
alike.  If one labors at all in the garden of youth, it must be free
from the passion of seeing things grow, from an innate love of
watching the strange processes of the brain under varying influences
and limitations.  He gets no more thanks than the novelist gets from
the character he creates, nor does he deserve them.  He has the whole
human comedy before him in embryo, the beginning of all passions and
all achievements.  As I have often told you, this city is a disputed
strategic point.  It controls a vast manufacturing region given over
to sordid and materialistic ideals.  Any work that has been done here
for aesthetics* cannot be lost.  I suppose we shall win in the end,
but the reign of Mammon has been long and oppressive.  You remember
when I was a boy working in the fields how we used to read Bunyan's
"Holy War" at night?  Well, I have always felt very much as though I
were keeping the Ear Gate of the town of Mansoul, and I know not
whether the Captains, who succeed me be trusty or no."  </p><p>Miss
Agatha was visibly moved, but she shook her head.  "Well, I wish you
had gone into the church, Emerson.  I respect your motives, but there
are more tares than wheat in your crop, I suspect."  </p><p>"My dear
girl," said the Professor, his eye brightening, "that is the very
reason for the sowing.  There is a picture by Vedder of the Enemy
Sowing Tares at the foot of the cross, and his seeds are golden coins.
That is the call to arms; the other side never sleeps; in the
theatres, in the newspapers, in the mills and offices and coal fields,
by day and by night the enemy sows tares."  </p><p>As the Professor
slowly climbed the hill to the High School that morning, he indulged
in his favorite fancy, that the old grey stone building was a fortress
set upon the dominant acclivity of that great manufacturing city, a
stronghold of knowledge in the heart of Mammon's kingdom, a Pharos to
all those drifting, storm-driven lives in the valley below, where
mills and factories thronged, blackening the winding shores of the
river, which was dotted with coal barges and frantic, puffing little
tugs.  The High School commanded the heart of the city, which was like
that of any other manufacturing town&mdash;a scene of bleakness and naked
ugliness and of that remorseless desolation which follows upon the
fiercest lust of man.  The beautiful valley, where long ago two limpid
<pb n="484"/>  rivers met at the foot of wooded heights, had
become a scorched and blackened waste.  The river banks were lined
with bellowing mills which broke the silence of the night with periodic
crashes of sound, filled the valley with heavy carboniferous smoke, and
sent the chilled products of their red forges to all parts of the known
world,&mdash;to fashion railways in Siberia, bridges in Australia, and to
tear the virgin soil of Africa.  To the west, across the river, rose
the steep bluffs, faintly etched through the brown smoke, rising five
hundred feet, almost as sheer as a precipice, traversed by cranes and
inclines and checkered by winding yellow paths like sheep trails which
lead to the wretched habitations clinging to the face of the cliff,
the lairs of the vicious and the poor, miserable rodents of
civilization.  In the middle of the stream, among the tugs and barges,
were the dredging boats, hoisting muck and filth from the clogged
channel.  It was difficult to believe that this was the shining river
which tumbles down the steep hills of the lumbering district, odorous
of wet spruce logs and echoing the ring of axes and the song of the
raftsmen, come to this black ugliness at last, with not one throb of
its woodland passion and bright vehemence left.  </p><p>For thirty
years the Professor's class-room had overlooked this scene which
caused him unceasing admiration and regret.  For thirty years he had
cried out against the image set up there as the Hebrew prophets cried
out against the pride and blind prosperity of Tyre.  Nominally he was
a professor of English Literature, but his real work had been to try
to secure for youth the rights of youth; the right to be generous, to
dream, to enjoy; to feel a little the seduction of the old Romance,
and to yield a little.  His students were boys and girls from the
factories and offices, destined to return thither, and hypnotized by
the glitter of yellow metal.  They were practical, provident,
unimaginative, and mercenary at sixteen.  Often, when some lad was
reading aloud in the class-room, the puffing of the engines in the
switch yard at the foot of the hill would drown the verse and the
young voice entirely, and the Professor would murmur sadly to himself:
"Not even this respite is left to us; even here the voice of youth is
drowned by the voice of the taskmaster that waits for them all
impatiently enough."  </p><p>Never had his duty seemed to call him so
urgently as on this morning when he was to lay down his arms.  As he
entered the building he met the boys carrying palms up into the chapel
for class-day exercises, and it occurred to him for the first time
that this was his last commencement, a commencement without
congratulations and without flowers.  When he went into the chapel to
drill the seniors on their commencement orations, he was unable to fix
his mind upon his work.  For thirty years he had heard youth say
exactly the same thing in the same place; had heard young men swear
fealty to the truth, pay honor to the pursuit of noble pleasures, and
pledge themselves "to follow knowledge like a sinking star beyond the
utmost bound of human thought."  How many, he asked himself, had kept
their vows?  He could remember the occasion of his own commencement in
that same chapel; the story that every senior class still told the
juniors, of the Professor's humiliation


<pb n="485"/>

and disgrace when, in
attempting to recite "Horatius at the Bridge," he had been unable to
recall one word of the poem following
</p>
<lg type="stanza"><l><hi rend="italic">"Then out spake bold Horatius</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">The Captain of the gate;"</hi></l> </lg>
<p>
and after some moments of agonizing silence he had shame-facedly left
the platform.  Even the least receptive of the Professor's students
realized that he had risen to a much higher plane of scholarship than
any of his colleagues, and they delighted to tell this story of the
frail, exquisite, little man whom generations of students had called
"the bold Horatius."  </p><p>All the morning the Professor was busy
putting his desk and bookcases in order, impeded by the painful
consciousness that he was doing it for the last time.  He made many
trips to the window and often lapsed into periods of idleness.  The
room had been connected in one way and another with most of his
intellectual passions, and was as full of sentimental associations for
him as the haunts of his courtship days are to a lover.  At two
o'clock he met his last class, which was just finishing "Sohrab and
Rustum," and he was forced to ask one of the boys to read and
interpret the majestic closing lines on the "shorn and parceled oxus."
What the boy's comment was the Professor never knew, he felt so close a
kinship to that wearied river that he sat stupefied, with his hand
shading his eyes and his fingers twitching.  When the bell rang
announcing the end of the hour; he felt a sudden pain clutch his
heart; he had a vague hope that the students would gather around his
desk to discuss some point that youth loves to discuss, as they often
did, but their work was over and they hurried out, eager for their
freedom, while the professor sat helplessly watching them.
</p><p>That evening a banquet was given to the retiring professor in
the chapel, but Miss Agatha had to exert all her native power of
command to induce him to go.  He had come home so melancholy and
unnerved that after laying out his dress clothes she literally had to
put them on him.  When he was in his shirt sleeves and Miss Agatha had
carefully brushed his beautiful white hair and arranged his tie, she
wheeled him sharply about and retreated to a chair.  </p><p>"Now
Emerson, say your piece," she commanded.  </p><p>Plucking up his shirt
sleeves and making sure of his cuffs, the Professor began valiantly:
</p>
<lg type="stanza"> <l><hi rend="italic">"Lars Porsena of Clusium</hi></l> <l><hi rend="italic">By the nine
gods he swore,"</hi></l> </lg>

<p>It was all Miss Agatha's idea.
After the invitations to the banquet were out and she discovered that
half-a-dozen of the Professor's own classmates and many of his old
students were to be present, she divined that it would be a tearful
and depressing occasion.  Emerson, she knew, was an indifferent
speaker when his heart was touched, so she had decided that after a
silence of thirty-five years Horatius should be heard from.  The idea
of correcting his youthful failure in his old age had rather pleased
the Professor on the whole, and he had set to work to memorize Lord
Macaulay's lay, rehearsing in private to Miss Agatha, who had drilled
him for that fatal exploit of his commencement night.  </p><p>After
this dress rehearsal the Professor's<pb n="486"/> spirits rose,
and during the carriage ride he even made several feeble efforts to
joke with his sister.  But later in the evening when he sat down at
the end of the long table in the dusky chapel, green with palms for
commencement week, he fell into deep depression.  The guests chattered
and boasted and gossiped, but the guest of honor sat silent, staring
at the candles.  Beside him sat old Fairbrother, of the Greek
department, who had come into the faculty in the fifth year of
Graves's professorship, and had married a pretty senior girl who had
rejected Graves's timid suit.  She had been dead this many a year;
since his bereavement lonely old Fairbrother had clung to Graves, and
now the Professor felt a singular sense of support in his presence.
</p><p>The Professor tried to tell himself that now his holiday time
had come, and that he had earned it; that now he could take up the
work he had looked forward to and prepared for for years, his History
of Modern Painting, the Italian section of which was already
practically complete.  But his heart told him that he had no longer
the strength to take up independent work.  Now that the current of
young life had cut away from him and into a new channel, he felt like
a ruin of some extinct civilization, like a harbor from which the sea
has receded.  He realized that he had been living by external
stimulation from the warm young blood about him, and now that it had
left him, all his decrepitude was horribly exposed.  All those
hundreds of thirsty young lives had drunk him dry.  He compared
himself to one of those granite colossi of antique lands, from which
each traveller has chipped a bit of stone until only a mutilated torso
is left.  </p><p>He looked reflectively down the long table, picking
out the faces of his colleagues here and there, souls that had toiled
and wrought and thought with him, that simple, unworldly sect of
people he loved.  They were still discussing the difficulties of the
third conjugation, as they had done there for twenty years.  They were
cases of arrested development, most of them.  Always in contact with
immature minds, they had kept the simplicity and many of the callow
enthusiasms of youth.  Those facts and formulae which interest the
rest of the world for but a few years at most, were still the vital
facts of life for them.  They believed quite sincerely in the supreme
importance of quadratic equations, and the rule for the special verbs
that govern the dative was a part of their decalogue.  And he
himself&mdash;what had he done with the youth, the strength, the enthusiasm
and splendid equipment he had brought there from Harvard thirty years
ago?  He had come to stay but a little while&mdash;five years at the most,
until he could save money enough to defray the expense of a course in
some German university.  But then the battle had claimed him; the
desire had come upon him to bring some message of repose and peace to
the youth of this work-driven, joyless people, to cry the name of
beauty so loud that the roar of the mills could not drown it.  Then the
reward of his first labors had come in the person of his one and only
genius; his restless, incorrigible pupil with the gentle eyes and
manner of a girl, at once timid and utterly reckless, who had seen
even as Graves saw; who had suffered a little, sung a little, struck
the <pb n="487"/>  true lyric note, and died wretchedly at
three-and-twenty in his master's arms, the victim of a tragedy as old
as the world and as grim as Samson, the Israelite's.  </p><p>He looked
about at his comrades and wondered what they had done with their
lives.  Doubtless they had deceived themselves as he had done.  With
youth always about them, they had believed themselves of it.  Like the
monk in the legend they had wandered a little way into the wood to
hear the bird's song&mdash;the magical song of youth so engrossing and so
treacherous, and they had come back to their cloister to find
themselves old men&mdash;spent warriors who could only chatter on the wall,
like grass-hoppers and sigh at the beauty of Helen as she passed.
</p><p>The toasts were nearly over, but the Professor had heard none of
the appreciative and enthusiastic things that his students and
colleagues had said of him.  He read a deeper meaning into this
parting than they had done and his thoughts stopped his ears.  He
heard Miss Agatha clear her throat and caught her meaning glance.
Realizing that everyone was waiting for him, he,* blinked his eyes
like a man heavy with sleep and arose.  </p><p>"How handsome he
looks," murmured the woman looking at his fine old face and silver
hair.  The Professor's remarks were as vague as they were brief.
After expressing his thanks for the honor done him, he stated that he
had still some work to finish among them, which had been too long
incomplete.  Then with as much of his school-boy attitude as he could
remember, and a smile on his gentle lips, he began his
</p>
<lg type="stanza"> <l><hi rend="italic">"Lars Porsena of Clusium, by the Nine</hi></l> <l
rend="indent">Gods he swore</l> <l><hi rend="italic">That the proud house of Tarquin
should</hi></l> <l rend="indent"><hi rend="italic">suffer wrong no more."</hi></l>
</lg>
<p>
A murmur
of laughter ran up and down the long table, and Dr. Maitland, the
great theologian, who had vainly tried to prompt his stage-struck
fellow graduate thirty-five years ago, laughed until his nose glasses
fell off and dangled across his black waistcoat.  Miss Agatha was
highly elated over the success of her idea, but the Professor had no
heart in what he was doing, and the merriment rather hurt him.  Surely
this was a time for silence and reflection, if ever such time was.
Memories crowded upon him faster than the lines he spoke, and the warm
eyes turned upon him, full of pride and affection for their scholar
and their "great man," moved him almost beyond endurance.
</p>
<lg type="stanza"><l><hi rend="italic">"&mdash;the Consul's brow was sad</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">And the Consul's speech was low,"</hi></l> </lg>
<p>
he read, and suited the action
marvellously to the word.  His eyes wandered to the chapel rostrum.
Thirty-five years ago he had stood there repeating those same lines, a
young man, resolute and gifted, with the strength of Ulysses and the
courage of Hector, with the kingdoms of the earth and the treasures of
the ages at his feet, and the singing rose in his heart; a spasm of
emotion contracted the old man's vocal cords.
</p>
<lg type="stanza"><l><hi rend="italic">Outspake the bold Horatius,</hi></l> <l><hi rend="italic">The Captain of the
gate."</hi></l> </lg>
<p>
he faltered;&mdash;his white hand nervously sought his
collar, then the hook on his breast where his glasses usually hung,
and at last tremulously for his <pb n="488"/>  handkerchief; then
with a gesture of utter defeat, the Professor sat down.  There was a
tearful silence; white handkerchiefs fluttered down the table as from
a magician's wand, and Miss Agatha was sobbing.  Dr. Maitland arose to
his feet, his face distorted between laughter and tears.  "I ask you
all," he cried, "whether Horatius has any need to speak, for has he
not kept the bridge these thirty years?  God bless him!"  </p><p>"It's
all right, so don't worry about it, Emerson," said Miss Agatha as they
got into the carriage.  "At least they were appreciative, which is
more than I would have believed."  </p><p>"Ah, Agatha," said the
Professor, wiping his face wearily with his crumpled handkerchief, "I
am a hopeless dunce, and you ought to have known better.  If you could
make nothing of me at twenty, you showed poor judgment to undertake it
at fifty-five.  I was not made to shine, for they put a woman's heart
in me."</p>

</div1>
</body>

</text>
</TEI.2>
