<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CatEldo"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="CatEldo">

<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">El Dorado: A Kansas Recessional</title>
<title type="sort">el dorado a kansas recessional</title>
<author>Cather, Willa Sibert</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">49</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CatEldo</idno>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475795</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">El Dorado: A Kansas Recessional</title>
<title level="j">The New England Magazine</title>
<title type="sort">el dorado a kansas recessional</title>
<author>Willa Sibert Cather</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 351-369</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>New England Magazine Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
<date value="1901">1901</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: Alderman Library, MicFilm S-1077 Reel 7</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>New England Magazine, n.s. 24, No. 4 (June 1901)</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1901">1901</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-01">January 1997</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Stephen Ramsay, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">



<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
	<pb n="357"/>
<head>EL DORADO: A KANSAS RECESSIONAL.<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">By Willa Sibert Cather.</hi> </head>

<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d4">
<head>I.</head>

<p>PEOPLE who have been so unfortunate as to have travelled in western
Kansas will remember the Solomon valley for its unique and peculiar
desolation.  The river is a turbid, muddy little stream, that crawls along
between naked bluffs, choked and split by sand bars, and with nothing
whatever of that fabled haste to reach the sea.  Though there can be little
doubt that the Solomon is heartily disgusted with the country through
which it flows, it makes no haste to quit it.  Indeed, it is one of the most
futile little streams under the sun, and never gets anywhere.  Its sluggish
current splits among the sand bars and buries itself in the mud until it
literally dries up from weariness and <hi rend="italic">ennui</hi>,
without ever reaching
anything.  The hot winds and the river have been contending for the
empire of the valley for years, and the river has had decidedly the worst
of it.  Never having been a notably ambitious stream, in time it grew tired
of giving its strength to moisten barren fields and corn that never
matured.  Beyond the river with its belt of amber woodland rose the
bluffs, ragged, broken, covered with shaggy red grass and bare of trees,
save for the few stunted oaks that grew upon their steep sides.  They were
pathetic little trees, that sent their roots down through thirty feet of hard
clay bluff to the river level.  They were as old as the first settler could
remember, and yet no one could assert that they had ever grown an inch.
They seldom, if ever, bore acorns; it took all the nourishment that soil
could give just to exist.  There was a sort of mysterious kinship between
those trees and the men who lived, or tried to live, there.  They were alike
in more ways than one.
</p><p>Across the river stretched the level land like the top of an oven.  It
was a country flat and featureless, without tones or shadows, without
accent or emphasis of any kind to break its vast monotony.  It was a
scene done entirely in high lights, without relief, without a single
commanding eminence to rest the eye upon.  The flat plains rolled to the
unbroken horizon vacant and void, forever reaching in empty yearning
toward something they never attained.  The tilled fields were even more
discouraging to look upon than the unbroken land.  Although it was late
in the autumn, the corn was not three feet high.  The leaves were seared
and yellow, and as for tassels, there were none.  Nature always dispenses
with superfluous appendages; and what use had Solomon valley corn for
tassels?  Ears were only a tradition there, fabulous fruits like the golden
apples of the Hesperides; and many a brawny Hercules had died in his
own sweat trying to obtain them.  Sometimes, in the dusk of night, when
the winds were not quite so hot as usual and only the stars could hear, the
dry little corn leaves whispered to each other that once, long ago, real
yellow ears grew in the Solomon valley.
</p><p>Near the river was a solitary frame building, low and wide, with a
high sham front, like most stores in Kansas villages.  Over the door was
painted in faded letters, "Josiah Bywaters, Dry Goods, Groceries and
Notions."  In front of the store ran a straight strip of ground, grass grown
and weedy, which looked as if it might once have been a road.  Here and
there, on either side of this deserted
<pb n="358"/>
way of traffic, were half
demolished buildings and excavations where the weeds grew high, which
might once have been the sites of houses.  For this was once El Dorado,
the Queen City of the Plains, the Metropolis of Western Kansas, the
coming Commercial Centre of the West.
</p><p>Whatever may have been there once, now there were only those
empty, windowless buildings, that one little store, and the lonely old man
whose name was painted over the door.  Inside the store, on a chair tilted
back against the counter, with his pipe in his mouth and a big gray cat on
his knee, sat the proprietor.  His appearance was not that of the average
citizen of western Kansas, and a very little of his conversation told you
that he had come from civilization somewhere.  He was tall and straight,
with an almost military bearing, and an iron jaw.  He was thin, but
perhaps that was due to his diet.  His cat was thin, too, and that was
surely owing to its diet, which consisted solely of crackers and water,
except when now and then it could catch a gopher; and Solomon valley
gophers are so thin that they never tempt the ambition of any discerning
cat.  If Colonel Bywaters's manner of living had anything to do with his
attenuation, it was the solitude rather than any other hardship that was
responsible.  He was a sort of "Last Man."  The tide of emigration had
gone out and had left him high and dry, stranded on a Kansas bluff.  He
was living where the rattlesnakes and sunflowers found it difficult to
exist.
</p><p>The Colonel was a man of determination; he had sunk his money
in this wilderness and he had determined to wait until he had got it out.
His capital had represented the industry of a lifetime.  He had made it
all down in Virginia, where fortunes are not made in a day.  He had often
told himself that he had been a fool to quit a country of honest men for a
desert like this.  But he had come West, worse than that, he had come to
western Kansas, even to the Solomon valley, and he must abide the
consequences.  Even after the whole delusion was dispelled, and the
fraud exposed, when the other buildings had been torn down or moved
away, when the Eastern brokers had foreclosed their mortgages and held
the land empty for miles around, Colonel Bywaters had stubbornly
refused to realize that the game was up.  Every one had told him that the
best thing he could do was to get out of the country; but he refused to
listen to advice.  Perhaps he had an unreasoning conviction that money
could not absolutely vanish, and that, if he stayed there long enough, his
must some time come back to him.  Perhaps, even had he wished to go,
he actually lacked the means wherewith to get away.  At any rate, there
he remained, becoming almost a part of that vast solitude, trying to live
the life of an upright Christian gentleman in this desert, with a heart
heavy and homesick for his kind, always living over again in memory the
details of that old, peaceful life in the valley of Virginia.  He rose at six,
as he had always done, ate his meagre breakfast and swept out his store,
arranged his faded calicoes and fly-specked fruit cans in the window, and
then sat down to wait.  Generally he waited until bedtime.  In three years
he had not sold fifty dollars' worth.  Men were almost unknown beings in
that region, and men with money were utterly so.  When the town broke
up, a few of the inhabitants had tried to farm a little,&mdash;tried until they had
no grain to sow and no horses to plough and no money to get away with.
They were dead, most of them.  The only human faces the Colonel ever
saw were the starved, bronzed countenances of the poor fellows who
sometimes passed in wagons, plodding along with their wives and
children and cook stoves
<pb n="359"/>
and feather beds, trying to get back
to "God's country."  They never bought anything; they only stopped to
water their horses and swear a little, and then drove slowly eastward
Once a little girl had cried so bitterly for the red stick candy in the
window that her father had taken the last nickel out of his worn, flat
pocketbook.  But the Colonel was too kind a man to take his money, so
he gave the child the money and the candy, too; and he also gave her a
little pair of red mittens that the moths had got into, which last she
accepted gratefully, though it was August.
</p><p>The first day of the week brought the exceptions in the monotonous
routine of the Colonel's life.  He never rose till nine o'clock on Sunday.
Then, in honor of the day, he shaved his chin and brushed out his
mustache, and dressed himself in his black suit that had been made for
him down in Winchester four years ago.  This suit of clothes was an
object of great care with the Colonel, and every Sunday night he brushed
it out and folded it away in camphor gum.  Generally he fished on
Sunday.  Not that there are any fish in the Solomon; indeed, the mud
turtles, having exhausted all the nutriment in the mud, have pretty much
died out.  But the Colonel was fond of fishing, and fish he would.  So in
season, every Sunday morning, he would catch a bottle of flies for bait
and take his pole and, after locking his store against impossible intruders,
he would go gravely down the street.  He really went through the weed
patch, but to himself and his cat he always spoke of it as the street.
</p></div2>

<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d5">
<head>II.</head>

<p>On this particular afternoon, as the Colonel sat watching the
autumn sunlight play upon the floor, he was feeling more bitterly
discouraged than usual.  It was exactly four years ago that day that Major
Penelton had brought into his store on Water Street a tall, broad
shouldered young man, with the frankest blue eyes and a good-natured
smile, whom he introduced as Mr. Apollo Gump of Kansas.  After a little
general conversation, the young man had asked him if he wished to
invest in Western lands.  No, the Colonel did not want to put out any
money in the West.  He had no faith in any of the new states.  Very well;
Apollo did not wish to persuade him.  But some way he saw a good deal
of the young man, who was a clever, open-handed sort of a chap, who
drank good whiskey and told a good story so that it lost nothing in the
telling.  So many were the hints he threw out of the fortunes made every
day in Western real estate, that in spite of himself the Colonel began to
think about it.  Soon letters began pouring in upon him, letters from
doctors, merchants, bankers, all with a large map on the envelope,
representing a town with all the railroads of the West running into it.
Above this spidery object was printed the name, El Dorado.  These
communications all assured him of the beauty of the location, the
marvellous fertility of the surrounding country, the commercial and
educational advantages of the town.  Apollo seemed to take a wonderful
liking to him; he often had him to dine with him at the little hotel, and
took him down to Washington to hear Patti, assuring him all the time that
the theatres of Kansas City were much better than anything in the East,
and that one heard much better music there.  The end of the matter was
that when Apollo went back to Kansas the Colonel sold out his business
and went with him.  They were accompanied by half a dozen men from
Baltimore, Washington and the smaller towns about, whom Apollo had
induced to invest in the fertile tracts of land about El Dorado and in stock
in the Gump banking house.
</p><p>The Colonel was not a little surprised
<pb n="360"/>
to find that El
Dorado, the metropolis of western Kansas, was a mere cluster of frame
houses beside a muddy stream, that there was not a railroad within
twenty-five miles, and that the much boasted waterworks consisted of a
number of lead pipes running from the big windmill tank on the hill; but
Apollo assured him that high buildings were dangerous in that windy
country, that the railroads were anxious and eager to come as soon as
the town voted bonds, and that the waterworks&mdash;pipes, pumps, filters and
all, a complete "Holly" system&mdash;were ordered and would be put in in the
spring.  The Colonel did not quite understand how an academy of arts
and science could be conducted in the three-room sod shack on the hill;
but Aristotle Gump showed him the plan of a stately building with an
imposing bell-tower that hung over the desk in his office, assuring him
that it would go up in May, and that the workmen from Topeka were
already engaged for the job.  He was surprised, too, to find so few people
in a town of two thousand inhabitants; but he was told that most of the
business men had gone East to settle up their affairs, and would be back
in the spring with their new goods.  Indeed, in Ezekiel Gump's office, the
Colonel saw hundreds of letters, long glowing letters, from these absent
citizens, telling of their great business schemes and their unshaken faith
in the golden future of El Dorado.  There were few houses, indeed, but
there were acres and acres of foundations; there were few businesses in
operation, but there were hundreds of promises; and Apollo laughingly
said that Western towns were built on promises.
</p><p>But what most puzzled the Colonel was the vast number and
importance of the Gumps.  The Gumps seemed to be at the head of
everything.  The eldest brother was Isaiah Gump, the minister, a red
faced, clean shaven man, with a bald pate and dark, wrinkled little hands.
Then there were De Witt Gump, the physician and druggist; Chesterfield
Gump, the general dry goods merchant; Aristotle Gump, architect and
builder, and professor of mathematics in the Gump Academy; Hezekiah
Gump, the hardware merchant and president of the El Dorado Board of
Trade; Ezekiel Gump, real estate agent, superintendent of waterworks,
professor of natural sciences, etc.  These were the Gumps.  But stay,&mdash;
were there not also Almira Gump, who taught history and Italian in the
academy, and Venus Gump, who conducted a dressmaking and millinery
establishment?  The Colonel learned from Apollo that the Gump brothers
had bought the land and founded the town, that it was, in short, a
monument of Gump enterprise, it having been their long cherished
ambition to become municipal promoters.
</p><p>The Sunday after the Colonel's arrival, Isaiah preached a sermon on
the rebuilding of Jerusalem, and told how the Jews built each man before
his own door, with a trowel in one hand and a sword in the other.  This
was preliminary to urging the citizens of El Dorado to build sidewalks
before their respective residences.  He gave a long and eloquent
discourse upon the builders of great cities from Menes, Nimrod and
Romulus down, and among these celebrated personages, the Gumps were
by no means forgotten.
</p><p>After the sermon, the Colonel went to dine with Apollo at the little
hotel.  As they sat over their claret and cigars, Apollo said, "Colonel, if
you can work any kind of a deal with Zeke, I would advise you to buy up
your land before the railroad comes, for land is sure to go up then.  It's a
good plan out here to buy before a road comes and sell as soon as
possible afterwards."
</p><p>"About how much would you advise me to invest in land, Mr.
Gump?" inquired the Colonel.
</p><p>"Well, if I were you, I would about halve my pile.  Half I would put
<pb n="361"/>
into real estate and half into bank stock.  Then you've got both
realty and personal security and you are pretty safe."
</p><p>"I think I will get back into business.  I may as well open a little
shop and give your brother Chesterfield a little competition.  I find I have
been in the harness so long that I scarcely know what to do with myself
out of it.  I am too old to learn to be a gentleman of leisure."
</p><p>"That's a good idea; but whatever you do, do it before the road
comes.  That's where the mistake is made in Western towns; men buy at
high tide of the boom instead of having foresight enough to buy before.
A boom makes the man it finds; but woe to the man it leaves in its
track."  A year later the Colonel found that Apollo had spoken a great
truth.
</p><p>"I think I rather like that land your brother showed me yesterday.
Right next to the 'eighty' Mr. Thompson just bought.  I would a little
rather get tilled land, though."
</p><p>"Now, Colonel, you are buying this land to sell; and wild land will
sell just as well as any.  You don't want to bother with crops; that's for
the fellows that come in later.  Let them do the digging.  As soon as you
have made up your mind, I want to spring a little scheme on you.  I want
to run you for city mayor next spring; and as soon as you have invested,
we can begin to talk it up."
</p><p>That suggestion pleased the Colonel and it rather soothed his
conscience.  He had his own scruples about land speculation; it seemed
to him a good deal like gambling.  But if he could really make an effort
to further the interests of the town, he felt he would have a better right to
make his fortune there.
</p><p>After dinner they went out to look at Apollo's blooded horses, and
then to Apollo's rooms over the bank to smoke.  Apollo's rooms were
very interesting apartments.  They were decorated with boxing gloves,
ball bats, fishing rods, an old pair of foils and pictures of innumerable
theatrical people, mostly vaudeville celebrities and ladies of the ballet.
As the Colonel showed some interest in these, Apollo began rattling off
their names and various accomplishments, professional and otherwise,
with a familiarity that astonished the old gentleman.  One, he declared,
could do the best double dislocation act on the horizontal bars to be seen
in Europe or America, and his talents had been highly applauded by the
Prince of Wales.  Another was the best burnt cork artist of his time; and
another a languishing blond lady, whose generous outlines were
accentuated by the nature of her attire, he declared was "the neatest thing
in tights that ever struck Kansas City."  From Apollo that was a sweeping
statement; for Kansas City was the unit of measure which he applied to
the universe.  At one end of his sleeping room there was a large, full
length painting of a handsome, smiling woman, in short skirts and
spangles.  She stood on the toe of her left foot, her right foot raised, her
arms lifted, her body thrown back in a pose of easy abandon.  She was
just beginning to dance, and there was something of lassitude in the
movement of the picture.  Behind her hung a dark red curtain, creating a
daring effect of color through the sheer whiteness of her skirts, and the
footlights threw a strong glare up into her triumphant face.  It was
broadly and boldly painted, something after the manner of Degas, but
handled less cruelly than his subjects.  The name at the bottom of the
picture was that of a young American painter, then better known in Paris
than in his own country.  There were several photographs of the same
person ranged about on Apollo's dressing case, and, as he thought her
extremely beautiful, and as Apollo had not mentioned her, the Colonel
politely inquired who she was.
</p><p>"She was called Therese Barittini,"
<pb n="362"/>
replied Apollo, not
looking at the picture.
</p><p>"I never heard of her," remarked the Colonel, wondering at Apollo's
strange manner.
</p><p>"Probably not; she is dead," said Apollo shortly; and as the Colonel
saw that he did not wish to discuss the subject, he let it drop.  But he
could never refrain from looking at that picture when he was in Apollo's
room; and he had conjectures of his own.  Incidentally he learned that
Apollo had grown up about the theatres of Kansas City, ushering as a
boy, and later working up to the box office.  Had he known more of the
theatres of that river metropolis, the Colonel would have realized that
they are bad places for a boy.  As it was, he attributed Apollo's
exaggerated manner and many of his bad habits to his early environment.
</p><p>It chanced that the next day was the day for voting on railroad
bonds, and of course bonds were voted.  There was great rejoicing
among the builders of the city.  The Gump band was out, and Apollo
fired a fine display of fireworks which he had ordered from Kansas City
in anticipation of the happy event.  Those fireworks must have cost
Apollo a nice little sum, for there were a great many of them.  Why, there
were actually some of the blackened rocket sticks lying around the streets
next spring when every one knew that the railroad companies had never
heard of such a place as El Dorado.
</p><p>None of the Gumps had their families with them; they were to
come out in the spring.  They spoke often and affectionately of their
families,&mdash;all but Apollo, who never mentioned having any.  The Colonel
had supposed that he had never been married, until one day when he and
Apollo were dining with Isaiah.  Isaiah, after droning away in his prosy
fashion about his wife and little ones and commenting upon the beauty of
family ties, began moralizing upon Apollo's unfortunate marriage.
Apollo, who had been growing whiter and whiter, rose, set down his
glass and, reaching across the table, struck the Reverend Isaiah in the
mouth.  This was the first that the Colonel saw of the bitter altercations
which sometimes arose among the Gump brothers.
</p><p>By the close of the winter the Colonel had put out his money and
opened his store.  Everything went on at a lively enough pace in El
Dorado.  Men took large risks because their neighbors did, as blind to the
chances against them as the frequenters of the bucket shops on Wall
Street.  Hope was in the atmosphere, and each man was immersed in his
own particular dream of fortune.  One thinking man might have saved the
community; but many communities have gone to ruin through the lack of
that rare man.  Afterwards, when the news of the great Gump swindle
spread abroad over the land, and its unique details commanded a
column's space in one of the New York papers, financiers laughed and
said that a child could have grasped the situation.  The inhabitants of El
Dorado were chiefly men who had made a little capital working for
corporations in large cities, and were incompetent to manage an
independent business.  They had been mere machines in a great system,
consulted by no one, subject to complete control.  Here they were
"prominent citizens," men of affairs, and their vanity and self-confidence
expanded unduly.  The rest were farming people who came to make
homes and paid little attention to what went on in the town.  And the
farmer is always swindled, no matter by whom offences come.  The crash
may start in Wall Street, but it ends in the hillside farms and on the
prairie.  No matter where the lightning strikes, it blackens the soil at last.
</p><p>As the winter wore away, Apollo Gump drank harder than ever,
drank alone in his rooms now, indulging in the solitary form of the vice,
which
<pb n="363"/>
is its worse form.  No one saw much of him after
business hours.  He was gloomy and abstracted and seemed to dread even
the necessary intercourse with men which his position in the bank
entailed.  The Gump brothers commissioned the Colonel to remonstrate
with him upon the error of his ways, which he did without much effect.
Still, there were many likable things about Apollo.  He was different
from the rest; his face was finer and franker, in spite of its heavy marks
of dissipation, and his heart was kinder.  His dogs were better treated
than many men's children.  His brothers were very clever fellows, some
of them, all of them free handed enough, except old Isaiah, who was the
greatest bore and the sorriest rascal of them all.  But the Colonel liked
Apollo best.  The great end of his life was to serve Mammon, but on the
side he served other and better gods.  Dante's lowest hell was a frozen
one; and wherever Apollo's tortured soul writhes, it is not there; that is
reserved for colder and perhaps cleaner men than he.
</p><p>At last spring came, that fabled spring, when all the business men
were to return to El Dorado, when the Gump Academy was to be built,
when the waterworks were to be put in, when the Gumps were to
welcome their wives and children.  Chesterfield, Hezekiah and Aristotle
had gone East to see to bringing out their families, and the Colonel was
impatiently awaiting their return, as the real estate business seemed to be
at a standstill and he could get no satisfaction from Apollo about the
condition of affairs.  One night there came a telegram from New York,
brought post haste across the country from the nearest station,
announcing that the father of the Gumps was dying, and summoning the
other brothers to his bedside.  There was great excitement in El Dorado at
these tidings, and the sympathy of its inhabitants was so genuine that
they scarcely stopped to think what the departure of the Gumps might
mean.
</p><p>De Witt and Ezekiel left the next day accompanied by Miss Venus
and Miss Almira.  Apollo and Isaiah remained to look after the bank.
The Colonel began to feel anxious, realizing that the Gumps had things
pretty much in their own hands and that if the death of their father should
make any material difference in their projects and they should decide to
leave Kansas for good, the town and his interests would be wofully
undone.  Still, he said very little, not thinking it a time to bring up
business considerations; for even Apollo looked worried and harassed
and was entirely sober for days together.
</p><p>The Gumps left on Monday.  On the following Sunday Isaiah
delivered a particularly powerful discourse on the mutability of riches.
He compared temporal wealth to stock in the great bank of God, which
paid such rich dividends of grace daily, hourly.  He earnestly exhorted his
hearers to choose the good part and lay up for themselves treasures in
heaven, where moths cannot corrupt nor thieves break through and steal.
Apollo was not at church that morning.  The next morning the man who
took care of Apollo's blooded horses found that two of them were
missing.  When he went to report this to Apollo he got no response to his
knock, and, not succeeding in finding Isaiah, he went to consult the
Colonel.  Together they went back to Apollo's room and broke in the
door.  They found the room in wretched disorder, with clothing strewn
about over the furniture; but nothing was missing save Apollo's grip
and revolver, the picture of the theatrical looking person that had hung
in his sleeping room, and Apollo himself.  Then the truth dawned upon
the Colonel.  The Gumps had gone, taking with them the Gump banking
funds, land funds, city improvement funds, academy funds, and all funds,
both public and private.
<pb n="364"/>
</p><p>As soon as the news of the hegira of the Gumps got abroad,
carriages and horses came from all the towns in the country, bringing to
the citizens of El Dorado their attentive creditors.  All the townsmen had
paid fabulous prices for their land, borrowed money on it, put the money
into the Gump bank, and done their business principally on credit
obtained on the Gump indorsement.  Now that their money was gone,
they discovered that the land was worth nothing, was a desert which the
fertile imagination of the Gumps had made to blossom as the rose.  The
loan companies also discovered the worthlessness of the land, and used
every possible means to induce the tenants to remain on it; but the entire
country was panic-stricken and would near no argument.  Their one
desire was to get away from this desolate spot, where they had been
duped.  The infuriated creditors tore down the houses and carried even
the foundation stones away.  Scarcely a house in the town had been paid
for; the money had been paid to Aristotle Gump, contractor and builder,
who had done his business in the East almost entirely on credit.  The loan
agents and various other creditors literally put the town into wagons and
carried it off.  Meanwhile, the popular indignation was turned against the
Colonel as having been immediately associated with the Gumps and
implicated in their dishonesty.  In vain did he protest his innocence.
When men are hurt they must have something to turn upon, like children
who kick the door that pinches their fingers.  So the poor old Colonel,
who was utterly ruined and one of the heaviest losers, was accused of
having untold wealth hidden away somewhere in the bluffs; and all the
tempest of wrath and hatred which the Gumps had raised broke over his
head.  He was glad, indeed, when the town was utterly deserted, and he
could live without the continual fear of those reproachful and suspicious
glances.  Often as he sat watching those barren bluffs, he wondered
whether some day the whole grand delusion would not pass away, and
this great West, with its cities built on borrowed capital, its business done
on credit, its temporary homes, its drifting, restless population, become
panic-stricken and disappear, vanish utterly and completely, as a bubble
that bursts, as a dream that is done.  He hated Western Kansas; and yet in
a way he pitied this poor brown country, which seemed as lonely as
himself and as unhappy.  No one cared for it, for its soil or its rivers.
Every one wanted to speculate in it.  It seemed as if God himself had only
made it for purposes of speculation and was tired of the deal and doing
his best to get it off his hands and deed it over to the Other Party.
</p></div2>

<div2 type="section" n="3" id="d6">
<head>III.</head>

<p>On this particular morning, the fourth anniversary of the fatal
advent of Apollo Gump into his store at Winchester, as the Colonel sat
smoking in his chair, a covered wagon came toiling slowly up from
the south.  The horses were thin and fagged, and it was all that they could
do to drag the creaking wagon.  The harness was old and patched with
rope.  Over the hames and along the back strap hung pieces of sunflower
brush to serve as fly nets.  The wagon stopped at the well and two little
boys clambered out and came trotting up the path toward the store.  As
they came the Colonel heard them chattering together in a broad
Southern dialect; and the sound of his own tongue was sweet to his ears.
</p><p>"What is it, boys?" he asked, coming to the door.
</p><p>"Say, boss, kin we git some watah at yo' well?"
</p><p>"Of course you can, boys.  Git all you want."
</p><p>"Thank yo', sir ;" and the lads trotted back to the wagon.
</p><p>The Colonel took up his stick and
<pb n="365"/>
followed them.  He had
not seen such good natured, tow-headed little chaps for a long while; and
he was fond of children.  A little girl, dressed in that particularly ugly
shade of red in which farming people seem to delight, clambered out of
the wagon and went up to the well with a tin cup, picking her way
carefully with her bare feet to avoid the sand burrs.  A fretful voice called
from the wagon.
</p><p>"Law me, boys, haint you most got that watah yit?"
</p><p>A wan woman's face appeared at the front of the wagon, and she sat
down and coughed heavily, holding her hand over her chest as if it hurt
her.  The little girl filled the tin cup and ran toward the wagon.
</p><p>"Howdy do, sir?" said the woman, turning to the Colonel as soon as
she had finished drinking.
</p><p>"Right smart, ma am, thank 'ee."
</p><p>"Mercy, air yo' from the South?  Virginy?  Laws!  I am from
Mizzoura myself an' I wisht I was back there.  I 'low we'd be well enough
off if we could git back to Pap."
</p><p>She looked wistfully off toward the southwest and put her hand to
her side again.  There was something in the look of her big, hollow eyes
that touched the Colonel.  He told her she had better stay there a few days
and rest the horses,&mdash;she did not look well enough to go on.
</p><p>"No, thank yo', sir, we must git on.  I'll be better in the mornin',
maybe.  I was feelin' right smart yisterday.  It's my lungs, the slow
consumption.  I think I'll last till I git back to Pap.  There has been a good
deal of the consumption in our family, an' they most all last."  She talked
nervously on, breathing heavily between her words.  "Haint there a town
Eldorader somewheres about here?"

</p><p>The Colonel flushed painfully.  "Yes, this is El Dorado."
</p><p>"Law me, purty lookin' town!" said the woman, laughing dismally.
"Superb's better'n this."  She pronounced Superb as though it had but one
syllable.  "They got a blacksmith shop an' a hardware store there,
anyways.  I am from nigh Superb, yo' see.  We moved there ten years
ago, when the country was lookin' mighty green and purty.  It's all done
burnt up long ago.  It's that dry we couldn't raise any garden stuff there
these three years.  Everything's gone now, exceptin' these horses Pap give
me when I was married.  No, my man haint with me; he died jist afore we
come away.  A bull gored him through an' through, an' he crawled
outsiden the bob-wire fence and died.  It was mighty hard.  He didn't
want to die there; he craved to die in Mizzoura.  We shot the bull and
brought t'other cattle with us; but they all died on the way."
</p><p>She closed her eyes and leaned back against the side of the wagon.
Suddenly she roused herself and said:
</p><p>"Law me, boys, this must be the sto' that man told us on.  Yo' see
our meat and stuff give out most a week ago, an' we been a livin' on
pancakes ever since.  We was all gittin' sick, fur we turned agin' 'em,
when we met a feller on horseback down the valley, a mighty nice lookin'
feller, an' he give us five dollars an' told us we'd find a store someers up
here an' could git some groceries."
</p><p>"It must have been one of them loan company fellows," said the
Colonel meditatively.  "They still come sneakin' about once in a while,
though I don't know what they're after.  They haven't left us much but the
dirt, an' I reckon that wouldn't do 'em much good if they could carry it
off."
</p><p>"That I can't tell yo'.  I never seen him befo',&mdash;but he was a mighty
kind sort of a feller.  He give us the money, and he give me some
brandy."
</p><p>The Colonel helped her out of the wagon, and they went up to the
store, while the boys watered the horses.  Their purchases were soon
made; but the Colonel refused to take their money.
<pb n="366"/>
</p><p>"No, ma'am, I can't do that.  You'll need your money before you get
to Missouri.  It's all in the family, between blood kin like.  We're both
from the South; and I reckon it would have been enough better for us if
we'd never left it."
</p><p>"Thank yo' mighty kindly, sir.  Yo' sholey can't be doin' much
business heah; better git in an' go with us.  Good day to yo', an' thank you
kindly, sir."
</p><p>The Colonel stood wistfully watching the wagon until it rolled
slowly out of sight, and then went back to his store, and with a sigh sat
down,&mdash;sat down to wait until water came from the rock and verdure
from the desert, a sort of Sphinx of the Solomon who sat waiting for the
end of time.  This was a day when his mind dwelt even more than usual
upon his misfortunes, and homesickness was heavy upon him, and he
yearned for his own people and the faces of his kindred; for the long
Virginia twilights in which he and Major Denney used to sit under the
great trees in the courthouse yard, living the siege of Richmond over
again; for the old comrades who took a drink with him at the Taylor
House bar; for the little children who rolled their hoops before his door
every morning, and went nutting with him in the fall; for the Great North
Mountains, where the frosts would soon be kindling the maples and
hickories into flame; for the soft purple of the Blue Ridge lying off to the
eastward; and for that sound which every Virginian hears forever and
forever in his dreams, that rhythmic song of deathless devotion, deep and
solemn as the cadence of epic verse, which the Potomac and Shenandoah
sing to the Virginia shore as they meet at Harper's Ferry.  To every exile
from the Valley of Virginia that sound is as the voice of his mother,
bidding him keep his honor clean, and forever calling him to come home.
The Colonel had stopped his horse there on the moonlight night in '62
when he rode away to the wars, and listened long to that sound; and
looking up at the towering grandeur of Maryland heights above him, he
had lifted his hand and sworn the oath that every young Virginian swore
and that every young Virginian kept.  For if the blood shed for those
noble rivers could have been poured into their flood, they would have run
crimson to the sea; and it is of that that they sing alway as they meet,
chanting the story over and over in the moonlight and the sunlight,
through time and change unable to forget all that wasted glory of youth,
all that heroic love.  Before now, when the old man had heard them
calling to him in the lonely winter nights, he had bowed his head in his
hands and wept in an almost physical passion of homesickness.
</p><p>Toward evening the clouds banked up in the western sky, and with
the night a violent storm set in, one of those drenching rains that always
come too late in that country, after a barren summer has waned into a
fruitless autumn.  For some reason he felt indisposed to go to bed.  He sat
watching the lightning from the window and listening to the swollen
Solomon, that tore between its muddy banks with a sullen roar, as though
it resented this intrusion upon its accustomed calm and indolence.  Once
he thought he saw a light flash from one of the bluffs across the river, but
on going to the door all was dark.  At last he regretfully put out his lamp
and went to bed.
</p></div2>

<div2 type="section" n="4" id="d7">
<head>IV.</head>

<p>That night, a few hours before, when the storm was at its worst, a
horseman had come galloping along the bank of the Solomon.  He drew
rein at the foot of a steep, naked bluff and sat in his saddle looking about
him.  It was a sorry night for a man to be out.  The blackness of the sky
seemed to bear down upon him, save when now and then it was
<pb n="367"/>
ripped from end to end by a jagged thrust of lightning, which rent it like
the veil of the temple.  At each flash he could see the muddy water of the
swollen river whirling along wraiths of white foam over the little
shivering willows.  Save for that one lonely light across the river, there
was no sign of man.  He dismounted from his horse and, tying it to a
sapling, he took a spade, strapped to the saddle, and began to climb the
bluff.  The water from the uplands was running down the hill wearing
channels in the soft stone and made the grass so slippery that he could
scarcely stand.  When he reached the top he took a dark lantern from his
pocket and lit it, sheltering it under the cape of his mackintosh; then he
set it behind a clump of bunch grass.  Starting from a lone oak, he
carefully paced a distance and began to dig.  His clothing was wet
through, and even his mackintosh was wet enough to impede his arms.
He impatiently threw off everything but his shirt and trousers and fell to
work again.  His shirt was wet and his necktie hung like a rag under his
collar.  His black hair hung wet over his white forehead, his brows were
drawn together and his teeth were set.  His eyes were fixed on the
ground, and he worked with the desperation of a man who works to
forget.  He drove the spade in to the top at every thrust and threw the
soggy earth far down the hillside, blistering his white hands with the
rigor of his toil.  The rain beat ceaselessly in his face and dripped from
his hair and mustache; but he never paused save when now and then he
heard some strange sound from the river.  Then he started, shut off the
light from his dark lantern and waited until all was quiet.
</p><p>When he had been digging for some time, he knelt down and thrust
his arm into the hole to feel its depth.  Close beside him he heard a shrill,
whirring, metallic sound which a man who hears it once remembers to
his dying day.  He felt a sharp pain in the big vein of his right arm and
sprang to his feet with an oath; and then the rattlesnake, having been the
avenger of many, slid quietly off through the wet grass.
</p></div2>

<div2 type="section" n="5" id="d8">
<head>V.</head>

<p>Next morning the sun rose radiantly over the valley of the Solomon.
The sky was blue and warm as the skies of the South, the hard, straight
line of the horizon was softened by a little smokelike haze, and the
yellow leaves of the cottonwoods, still wet from the drenching rain,
gleamed in the sunshine, and through the scant foliage the white bark
glittered like polished silver.  All the land was washed fresh and clean
from the dust of the desert summer.  It was a day of opal lights, a day set
in a heaven of gold and turquoise and bathed in sapphirine airs; one of
those rare and perfect days that happen only in desert countries, where
Nature seems sometimes to repent of her own pitilessness and by the
glory of her skies seems trying to compensate for the desolation of the
lands that stretch beneath them.  But when the Colonel came out to view
the ravages of the storm the exultant beauty of the morning moved him
little.  He knew how false it was and how fleeting.  He knew how soon
Nature forgets.  Across the river he heard a horse whinnying in the
bushes.  Surprised and curious, he went over to see what it might mean.
The horse stood, saddled and bridled, among the sumac bushes, and at
the back of the saddle carried a long waterproof roll.  He seemed uneasy
and stood pawing the wet ground and chewing at the withered leaves.
Looking about the Colonel could see no rider and he went up the bluff to
look for him.  And there he found him.  About five paces from the oak
tree was a newly dug hole, with the spade still sticking upright in the
earth.  The grass around it was cut and
<pb n="368"/>
crushed as though it had
been beaten by a strong man in his rage.  Beside the hole was the body of
a man.  His shirt was torn open to the waist and was wet and spattered
with mud; his left hand was wound in the long grass beside him; his
right, swollen and black, was thrown over his head; the eyes were wide
open, and the teeth were set hard upon the lower lip.  The face was the
handsome, dissolute face of Apollo Gump.
</p><p>The Colonel lifted him up and laid him under the little tree.  A
glance at his arm told how he died.  There was a brandy flask beside him,
and the wound had been enlarged with his knife, but the snake had struck
a vein and the poison had been too swift.  Taking up the spade, the
Colonel set to work to finish what the dead man had begun.  At a depth
of about four feet he found a wooden box, cased in tin.  He whistled
softly to himself as he loosened the earth about it.  So the Gumps had not
been so clever, after all; they had brought down more game than they
could bag, and at the last moment they had been compelled to bury part
of their spoil.  For what else on earth or in heaven would Apollo Gump
have risked his rascally neck in the Solomon valley?
</p><p>But no, there was no money, only the picture of the handsome,
theatrical looking woman he had seen in Apollo's room, a few spangled
stage dresses, a lot of woman's clothing, dainty garments that looked like
a trousseau and some tiny gowns made for a little, little baby, that had
never been worn.  That was all.  The Colonel drew a long breath of
astonishment, and stood looking at the picture.  There, at the back of the
saddle, was the waterproof roll which was to have carried it away.  This
then was Apollo Gump's weakness, and this was the supreme irony that
life had held in store for him, that when he had done evil without penalty
and all his sins had left him scathless, his one poor virtue should bring
him to his death!  As the Colonel glanced at that poor distorted body,
lying there in the sunlight amid the glistening grasses, he felt for a
moment a throb of that old affection he had once known for him.
Already the spiders had woven a rainbow web over that set, white face, a
gossamer film of protection against man's vengeance; and it seemed as
though Nature had already begun her magnificent and complete work of
pardon, as though the ground cried out for him, to take him into her
forgiving breast and make him again a part of the clean and fruitful earth.
</p><p>When he searched the dead man's body he found a leather belt and
pouch strapped about his waist next his skin.  In this were ten thousand
dollars in bank notes and a ticket to San Francisco.  The Colonel quietly
counted the money and put it into his own pocket.
</p><p>"There, sir, I've waited a long time to square my account with you.
You owe me six thousand still, but they say a dead man's debts are
cancelled and I'll take your horse and call it square.  If there is a
recording angel that keeps the run of these things, you can tell him you
are square with me and take that much off your poor soul; you'll have
enough to answer for without that, God knows."
</p><p>That afternoon the Colonel dragged up the bluff a long rough box
made from weather boards torn from his store.  He brought over his best
suit of clothes from its odorous camphor chest and with much difficulty
succeeded in forcing it on to the stiffened limbs of the dead man.
</p><p>"Apollo, I liked you mighty well.  It cut me to the heart when you
turned rascal,&mdash;and you were a damned rascal.  But I'll give you a decent
burial, because you loved somebody once.  I always knew you were too
good a fellow for your trade and that you'd trip up in it somewhere.  This
would never have happened to those precious brothers
<pb n="369"/>
of yours.
I guess I won't say any prayers over you.  The Lord knows you better than
I do; there have been worse men who have lived and died Christians.  If I
thought any words of mine could help you out, I'd say 'em free.  But the
Lord has been forgiving sin from the beginning of the world, till it must
have kept him pretty busy before now.  He knows his business by this
time.  But I hope it will go a bit easy with you, Apollo, that I do."
</p><p>He sunk the box in the hole and made a pillow of the light spangled
dresses and laid the dead man in upon them.  Over him he laid the picture
of the handsome, smiling woman, who was smiling still.  And so he
buried them.
</p><p>Next day, having got his money out of the place, the Colonel set
fire to his old store and urged his horse eastward, never once casting
back a look at the last smoking ruin of El Dorado.
</p><p>In the spring the sunflowers grew tall and fair over every street and
house site; and they grew just as fair over the mound beside the oak tree
on the bluff.  For if Nature forgets, she also forgives.  She at least holds
no grudge, up in her high place, where she watches the poles of the
heavens.  The tree itself has stopped growing altogether.  It has
concluded that it is not worth the effort.  The river creeps lazily through
the mud; it knows that the sea would be only a great, dirty, salty pond if it
should reach it.  Year by year it buries itself deeper in the black mud, and
burrows among the rotting roots of the dead willows, wondering why a
river should ever have been put there at all.
</p>

</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
