<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CheBouq"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="CheBouq">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Bouquet</title>
<title type="sort">bouquet</title>
<author>Chesnutt, Charles Waddell, 1858-1932</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">27</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CheBouq</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475801</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Bouquet</title>
<title type="sort">bouquet</title>
<author>Charles W. Chesnutt</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 84</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 648-654</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library
Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using
Microsoft Word spell checker</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text
Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are
composed of the text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as
in SpeFQue1 for page one of Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction, prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-02">February 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Timothy O. Jarrett</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="648"/>
<head>Chesnutt, Charles W.  "The Bouquet."  <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 84 (1899):
648-654.</head>


<p>MARY MYROVER's friends were somewhat surprised when she
began to teach a colored school.  Miss Myrover's friends are mentioned
here, because nowhere more than in a Southern town is public opinion a
force which cannot be lightly contravened.  Public opinion, however, did
not oppose Miss Myrover's teaching colored children; in fact, all the
colored public schools in town &mdash; and there were several &mdash; were taught
by white teachers, and had been so taught since the state had undertaken
to provide free public instruction for all children within its boundaries.
Previous to that time there had been a Freedman's Bureau school and a
Presbyterian missionary school, but these had been withdrawn when the
need for them became less pressing.  The colored people of the town had
been for some time agitating their right to teach their own schools, but
as yet the claim had not been conceded.</p>
<p>The reason Miss Myrover's course created some surprise was not,
therefore, the fact that a Southern white woman should teach a colored
school; it lay in the fact that up to this time no woman of just her quality
had taken up such work.  Most of the teachers of colored schools were
not of those who had constituted the aristocracy of the old regime; they
might be said rather to represent the new order of things, in which labor
was in time to become honorable, and men were, after a somewhat
longer time, to depend, for their place in society, upon themselves rather
than upon their ancestors.  But Mary Myrover belonged to one of the
proudest of the old families.  Her ancestors had been people of
distinction in Virginia before a collateral branch of the main stock had
settled in North Carolina.  Before the war they had been able to live up
to their pedigree.  But the war brought sad changes.  Miss Myrover's
father &mdash; the Colonel Myrover who led a gallant but desperate charge at
Vicksburg &mdash; had fallen on the battlefield, and his tomb in the white
cemetery was a shrine for the family.  On the Confederate Memorial
Day no other grave was so profusely decorated with flowers, and in the
oration pronounced the name of Colonel Myrover was always used to
illustrate the highest type of patriotic devotion and self-sacrifice.  Miss
Myrover's brother, too, had fallen in the conflict; but his bones lay in
some unknown trench, with those of a thousand others who had fallen on
the same field.  Ay, more, her lover, who had hoped to come home in
the full tide of victory and claim his bride as a reward for gallantry, had
shared the fate of her father and brother.  When the war was over, the
remnant of the family found itself involved in the common ruin, &mdash; more
deeply involved, indeed, than some others; for Colonel Myrover had
believed in the ultimate triumph of his cause, and had invested most of
his wealth in Confederate bonds, which were now only so much waste
paper.</p>
<p>There had been a little left.  Mrs. Myrover was thrifty, and had
laid by a few hundred dollars, which she kept in the house to meet
unforeseen contingencies.  There remained, too, their home, with an
ample garden and a well-stocked orchard, besides a considerable tract of
country land, partly cleared, but productive of very little revenue.</p>

<p>With their shrunken resources, Miss Myrover and her mother were
able to hold up their heads without embarrassment for some years after
the close of the war.  But when things were adjusted to the changed
conditions, and the stream of life began to flow more vigorously

<pb n="649"/>
in the new channels, they saw themselves in danger of dropping behind,
unless in some way they could add to their meagre income.  Miss
Myrover looked over the field of employment, never very wide for
women in the South, and found it occupied.  The only available position
she could be supposed prepared to fill, and which she could take without
distinct loss of caste, was that of a teacher, and there was no vacancy
except in one of the colored schools.  Even teaching was a doubtful
experiment; it was not what she would have preferred, but it was the
best that could be done.</p>
<p>"I don't like it, Mary," said her mother.  "It's a long step from
owning such people to teaching them.  What do they need with
education?  It will only make them unfit for work."</p>
<p>"They're free now, mother, and perhaps they'll work better if
they're taught something.  Besides, it's only a business arrangement, and
doesn't involve any closer contact than we have with our
servants."</p>
<p>"Well, I should say not!" sniffed the old lady.  "Not one of them
will ever dare to presume on your position to take any liberties with us.
<hi rend="italic">I</hi>'ll see to that."</p>
<p>Miss Myrover began her work as a teacher in the autumn, at the
opening of the school year.  It was a novel experience at first.  Though
there always had been negro servants in the house, and though on the
streets colored people were more numerous than her own people, and
though she was so familiar with their dialect that she might almost be
said to speak it, barring certain characteristic grammatical inaccuracies,
she had never been brought in personal contact with so many of them at
once as when she confronted the fifty or sixty faces &mdash; of colors ranging
from a white almost as clear as her own to the darkest livery of the sun --which were gathered in the schoolroom on the morning when she began
her duties.  Some of the inherited prejudice of her caste, too, made itself
felt, though she tried to repress any outward sign of it; and she could
perceive that the children were not altogether responsive; they, likewise,
were not entirely free from antagonism.  The work was unfamiliar to
her.  She was not physically very strong, and at the close of the first day
she went home with a splitting headache.  If she could have resigned
then and there without causing comment or annoyance to others, she
would have felt it a privilege to do so.  But a night's rest banished her
headache and improved her spirits, and the next morning she went to her
work with renewed vigor, fortified by the experience of the first
day.</p>
<p>Miss Myrover's second day was more satisfactory.  She had some
natural talent for organization, though she had never known it, and in the
course of the day she got her classes formed and lessons under way.  In
a week or two she began to classify her pupils in her own mind, as
bright or stupid, mischievous or well behaved, lazy or industrious, as the
case might be, and to regulate her discipline accordingly.  That she had
come of a long line of ancestors who had exercised authority and
mastership was perhaps not without its effect upon her character, and
enabled her more readily to maintain good order in the school.  When
she was fairly broken in she found the work rather to her liking, and
derived much pleasure from such success as she achieved as a
teacher.</p>
<p>It was natural that she should be more attracted to some of her
pupils than to others.  Perhaps her favorite &mdash; or rather, the one she liked
best, for she was too fair and just for conscious favoritism &mdash; was Sophy
Tucker.  Just the ground for the teacher's liking for Sophy might not at
first be apparent.  The girl was far from the whitest of Miss Myrover's
pupils; in fact, she was one of the darker ones.  She was not the
brightest in intellect, though she always tried

<pb n="650"/>
to learn her lessons.  She was not the best dressed, for her mother was a
poor widow, who went out washing and scrubbing for a living.  Perhaps
the real tie between them was Sophy's intense devotion to the teacher.  It
had manifested itself almost from the first day of the school, in the rapt
look of admiration Miss Myrover always saw on the little black face
turned toward her.  In it there was nothing of envy, nothing of regret;
nothing but worship for the beautiful white lady &mdash; she was not especially
handsome, but to Sophy her beauty was almost divine &mdash; who had come
to teach her.  If Miss Myrover dropped a book, Sophy was the first to
spring and pick it up; if she wished a chair moved, Sophy seemed to
anticipate her wish; and so of all the numberless little services that can
be rendered in a school-room.</p>
<p>Miss Myrover was fond of flowers, and liked to have them about
her.  The children soon learned of this taste of hers, and kept the vases
on her desk filled with blossoms during their season.  Sophy was perhaps
the most active in providing them.  If she could not get garden flowers,
she would make excursions to the woods in the early morning, and bring
in great dew-laden bunches of bay, or jasmine, or some other fragrant
forest flower which she knew the teacher loved.</p>
<p>"When I die, Sophy," Miss Myrover said to the child one day, "I
want to be covered with roses.  And when they bury me, I'm sure I shall
rest better if my grave is banked with flowers, and roses are planted at
my head and at my feet."</p>
<p>Miss Myrover was at first amused at Sophy's devotion; but when
she grew more accustomed to it, she found it rather to her liking.  It had
a sort of flavor of the old regime, and she felt, when she bestowed her
kindly notice upon her little black attendant, some of the feudal
condescension of the mistress toward the slave.  She was kind to Sophy,
and permitted her to play the role she had assumed, which caused
sometimes a little jealousy among the other girls.  Once she gave Sophy
a yellow ribbon which she took from her own hair.  The child carried it
home, and cherished it as a priceless treasure, to be worn only on the
greatest occasions.</p>
<p>Sophy had a rival in her attachment to the teacher, but the rivalry
was altogether friendly.  Miss Myrover had a little dog, a white spaniel,
answering to the name of Prince.  Prince was a dog of high degree, and
would have very little to do with the children of the school; he made an
exception, however, in the case of Sophy, whose devotion for his
mistress he seemed to comprehend.  He was a clever dog, and could
fetch and carry, sit up on his haunches, extend his paw to shake hands,
and possessed several other canine accomplishments.  He was very fond
of his mistress, and always, unless shut up at home, accompanied her to
school, where he spent most of his time lying under the teacher's desk,
or, in cold weather, by the stove, except when he would go out now and
then and chase an imaginary rabbit round the yard, presumably for
exercise.</p>
<p>At school Sophy and Prince vied with each other in their attentions
to Miss Myrover.  But when school was over, Prince went away with
her, and Sophy stayed behind; for Miss Myrover was white and Sophy
was black, which they both understood perfectly well.  Miss Myrover
taught the colored children, but she could not be seen with them in
public.  If they occasionally met her on the street, they did not expect
her to speak to them, unless she happened to be alone and no other white
person was in sight.  If any of the children felt slighted, she was not
aware of it, for she intended no slight; she had not been brought up to
speak to negroes on the street, and she could not act differently

<pb n="651"/>
from other people.  And though she was a woman of sentiment and
capable of deep feeling, her training had been such that she hardly
expected to find in those of darker hue than herself the same
susceptibility &mdash; varying in degree, perhaps, but yet the same in kind --that gave to her own life the alternations of feeling that made it most
worth living.</p>
<p>Once Miss Myrover wished to carry home a parcel of books.  She
had the bundle in her hand when Sophy came up.</p>
<p>"Lemme tote yo' bundle fer yer, Miss Ma'y?" she asked eagerly.
"I'm gwine yo' way."</p>
<p>"Thank you, Sophy," was the reply.  "I'll be glad if you
will."</p>
<p>Sophy followed the teacher at a respectful distance.  When they
reached Miss Myrover's home Sophy carried the bundle to the doorstep,
where Miss Myrover took it and thanked her.</p>
<p>Mrs. Myrover came out on the piazza as Sophy was moving away.
She said, in the child's hearing, and perhaps with the intention that she
should hear: "Mary, I wish you wouldn't let those little darkies follow
you to the house.  I don't want them in the yard.  I should think you'd
have enough of them all day."</p>
<p>"Very well, mother," replied her daughter.  "I won't bring any
more of them.  The child was only doing me a favor."</p>
<p>Mrs. Myrover was an invalid, and opposition or irritation of any
kind brought on nervous paroxysms that made her miserable, and made
life a burden to the rest of the household; so that Mary seldom crossed
her whims.  She did not bring Sophy to the house again, nor did Sophy
again offer her services as porter.</p>
<p>One day in spring Sophy brought her teacher a bouquet of yellow
roses.</p>
<p>"Dey come off'n my own bush, Miss Ma'y," she said proudly,
"an' I didn' let nobody e'se pull 'em, but saved 'em all fer you, 'cause I
know you likes roses so much.  I'm gwine bring 'em all ter you as long
as dey las'."</p>
<p>"Thank you, Sophy," said the teacher; "you are a very good
girl."</p>
<p>For another year Mary Myrover taught the colored school, and did
excellent service.  The children made rapid progress under her tuition,
and learned to love her well; for they saw and appreciated, as well as
children could, her fidelity to a trust that she might have slighted, as
some others did, without much fear of criticism.  Toward the end of her
second year she sickened, and after a brief illness died.</p>
<p>Old Mrs. Myrover was inconsolable.  She ascribed her daughter's
death to her labors as teacher of negro children.  Just how the color of
the pupils had produced the fatal effects she did not stop to explain.  But
she was too old, and had suffered too deeply from the war, in body and
mind and estate, ever to reconcile herself to the changed order of things
following the return of peace; and with an unsound yet not unnatural
logic, she visited some of her displeasure upon those who had profited
most, though passively, by her losses.</p>
<p>"I always feared something would happen to Mary," she said.  "It
seemed unnatural for her to be wearing herself out teaching little negroes
who ought to have been working for her.  But the world has hardly been
a fit place to live in since the war, and when I follow her, as I must
before long, I shall not be sorry to go."</p>
<p>She gave strict orders that no colored people should be admitted to
the house.  Some of her friends heard of this, and remonstrated.  They
knew the teacher was loved by the pupils, and felt that sincere respect
from the humble would be a worthy tribute to the proudest.  But Mrs.
Myrover was obdurate.</p>
<p>"They had my daughter when she was alive," she said, "and
they've killed her.  But she's mine now, and I won't have them come
near her.  I don't want

<pb n="652"/>
one of them at the funeral or anywhere around."</p>
<p>For a month before Miss Myrover's death Sophy had been
watching her rosebush &mdash; the one that bore the yellow roses &mdash; for the
first buds of spring, and when these appeared had awaited impatiently
their gradual unfolding.  But not until her teacher's death had they
become full-blown roses.  When Miss Myrover died, Sophy determined
to pluck the roses and lay them on her coffin.  Perhaps, she thought,
they might even put them in her hand or on her breast.  For Sophy
remembered Miss Myrover's thanks and praise when she had brought
her the yellow roses the spring before.</p>
<p>On the morning of the day set for the funeral Sophy washed her
face until it shone, combed and brushed her hair with painful
conscientiousness, put on her best frock, plucked her yellow roses, and,
tying them with the treasured ribbon her teacher had given her, set out
for Miss Myrover's home.</p>
<p>She went round to the side gate &mdash; the house stood on a corner &mdash;
and stole up the path to the kitchen.  A colored woman, whom she did
not know, came to the door.</p>
<p>"W'at yer want, chile?" she inquired.</p>
<p>"Kin I see Miss Ma'y?" asked Sophy timidly.</p>
<p>"I don' know, honey.  Ole Miss Myrover say she don' want no
cullud folks roun' de house endyoin' dis fun'al.  I'll look an' see if she's
roun' de front room, whar de co'pse is.  You sed-down heah an' keep
still, an' ef she's upstairs maybe I kin git yer in dere a minute.  Ef I
can't, I kin put yo' bokay 'mongs' de res', whar she won't know nuthin'
erbout it."</p>
<p>A moment after she had gone there was a step in the hall, and old
Mrs. Myrover came into the kitchen.</p>
<p>"Dinah!" she said in a peevish tone.  "Dinah!"</p>
<p>Receiving no answer, Mrs. Myrover peered around the kitchen,
and caught sight of Sophy.</p>
<p>"What are you doing here?" she demanded.</p>
<p>"I &mdash; I'm-m waitin' ter see de cook, ma'am," stammered
Sophy.</p>
<p>"The cook isn't here now.  I don't know where she is.  Besides,
my daughter is to be buried to-day, and I won't have any one visiting the
servants until the funeral is over.  Come back some other day, or see the
cook at her own home in the evening."</p>
<p>She stood waiting for the child to go, and under the keen glance of
her eyes Sophy, feeling as though she had been caught in some
disgraceful act, hurried down the walk and out of the gate, with her
bouquet in her hand.</p>
<p>"Dinah," said Mrs. Myrover, when the cook came back, "I don't
want any strange people admitted here to-day.  The house will be full of
our friends, and we have no room for others."</p>
<p>"Yas'm," said the cook.  She understood perfectly what her
mistress meant; and what the cook thought about her mistress was a
matter of no consequence.</p>
<p>The funeral services were held at St. John's Episcopal Church,
where the Myrovers had always worshiped.  Quite a number of Miss
Myrover's pupils went to the church to attend the services.  The church
was not a large one.  There was a small gallery at the rear, to which
colored people were admitted, if they chose to come, at ordinary
services; and those who wished to be present at the funeral supposed that
the usual custom would prevail.  They were therefore surprised, when
they went to the side entrance, by which colored people gained access to
the gallery stairs, to be met by an usher who barred their passage.</p>

<p>"I'm sorry," he said, "but I have had orders to admit no one until
the friends of the family have all been seated.  If you wish to wait until
the white people have all gone in, and there's any room left, you may be
able to get into the

<pb n="653"/>
back part of the gallery.  Of course I can't tell yet whether there'll be
any room or not."</p>
<p>Now the statement of the usher was a very reasonable one; but,
strange to say, none of the colored people chose to remain except Sophy.
She still hoped to use her floral offering for its destined end, in some
way, though she did not know just how.  She waited in the yard until the
church was filled with white people, and a number who could not gain
admittance were standing about the doors.  Then she went round to the
side of the church, and, depositing her bouquet carefully on an old
mossy gravestone, climbed up on the projecting sill of a window near the
chancel.  The window was of stained glass, of somewhat ancient make.
The church was old, had indeed been built in colonial times, and the
stained glass had been brought from England.  The design of the window
showed Jesus blessing little children.  Time had dealt gently with the
window; but just at the feet of the figure of Jesus a small triangular piece
of glass had been broken out.  To this aperture Sophy applied her eyes,
and through it saw and heard what she could of the services
within.</p>
<p>Before the chancel, on trestles draped in black, stood the sombre
casket in which lay all that was mortal of her dear teacher.  The top of
the casket was covered with flowers; and lying stretched out underneath
it she saw Miss Myrover's little white dog, Prince.  He had followed the
body to the church, and, slipping in unnoticed among the mourners, had
taken his place, from which no one had the heart to remove him.</p>

<p>The white-robed rector read the solemn service for the dead, and
then delivered a brief address, in which he spoke of the uncertainty of
life, and, to the believer, the certain blessedness of eternity.  He spoke
of Miss Myrover's kindly spirit, and, as an illustration of her love and
self-sacrifice for others, referred to her labors as a teacher of the poor
ignorant negroes who had been placed in their midst by an all-wise
Providence, and whom it was their duty to guide and direct in the station
in which God had put them.  Then the organ pealed, a prayer was said,
and the long cortege moved from the church to the cemetery, about half
a mile away, where the body was to be interred.</p>
<p>When the services were over, Sophy sprang down from her perch,
and, taking her flowers, followed the procession.  She did not walk with
the rest, but at a proper and respectful distance from the last mourner.
No one noticed the little black girl with the bunch of yellow flowers, or
thought of her as interested in the funeral.</p>
<p>The cortege reached the cemetery and filed slowly through the
gate; but Sophy stood outside, looking at a small sign in white letters on
a black background: &mdash; </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">"Notice</hi>.  This cemetery is for white people only.
Others please keep out."</p>
<p>Sophy, thanks to Miss Myrover's painstaking instruction, could
read this sign very distinctly.  In fact, she had often read it before.  For
Sophy was a child who loved beauty, in a blind, groping sort of way,
and had sometimes stood by the fence of the cemetery and looked
through at the green mounds and shaded walks and blooming flowers
within, and wished that she could walk among them.  She knew, too,
that the little sign on the gate, though so courteously worded, was no
mere formality; for she had heard how a colored man, who had
wandered into the cemetery on a hot night and fallen asleep on the flat
top of a tomb, had been arrested as a vagrant and fined five dollars,
which he had worked out on the streets, with a ball-and-chain
attachment, at twenty-five cents a day.  Since that time the cemetery gate
had been locked at night.</p>
<p>So Sophy stayed outside, and looked through the fence.  Her poor
bouquet had begun to droop by this time, and

<pb n="654"/>
the yellow ribbon had lost some of its freshness.  Sophy could see the
rector standing by the grave, the mourners gathered round; she could
faintly distinguish the solemn words with which ashes were committed to
ashes, and dust to dust.  She heard the hollow thud of the earth falling
on the coffin; and she leaned against the iron fence, sobbing softly, until
the grave was filled and rounded off, and the wreaths and other floral
pieces were disposed upon it.  When the mourners began to move toward
the gate, Sophy walked slowly down the street, in a direction opposite to
that taken by most of the people who came out.</p>
<p>When they had all gone away, and the sexton had come out and
locked the gate behind him, Sophy crept back.  Her roses were faded
now, and from some of them the petals had fallen.  She stood there
irresolute, loath to leave with her heart's desire unsatisfied, when, as her
eyes fell upon the teacher's last resting place, she saw lying beside the
new-made grave what looked like a small bundle of white wool.
Sophy's eyes lighted up with a sudden glow.</p>
<p>"Prince!  Here, Prince!" she called.</p>
<p>The little dog rose, and trotted down to the gate.  Sophy pushed
the poor bouquet between the iron bars.  "Take that ter Miss Ma'y,
Prince," she said, "that's a good doggie."</p>
<p>The dog wagged his tail intelligently, took the bouquet carefully in
his mouth, carried it to his mistress's grave, and laid it among the other
flowers.  The bunch of roses was so small that from where she stood
Sophy could see only a dash of yellow against the white background of
the mass of flowers.</p>
<p>When Prince had performed his mission he turned his eyes toward
Sophy inquiringly, and when she gave him a nod of approval lay down
and resumed his watch by the graveside.  Sophy looked at him a moment
with a feeling very much like envy, and then turned and moved slowly
away.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Charles W. Chesnutt</hi></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
