<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CheBaxt"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="CheBaxt">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Baxter's Procrustes</title>
<title type="sort">baxters procrustes</title>
<author>Chesnutt, Charles Waddell, 1858-1932</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">31</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CheBaxt</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475800</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Baxter's Procrustes</title>
<title type="sort">baxters procrustes</title>
<author>Charles W. Chesnutt</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1904">1904</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>93</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 823-830</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1904">1904</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-08">August 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>minimal TEI tagging</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head>Chesnutt, Charles W.  "Baxter's Procrustes."
<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 93 (1904): 823-830.</head>

<pb n="823"/>

<p>BAXTER'S Procrustes is one of the publications of the Bodleian
Club.  The Bodleian Club is composed of gentlemen of culture, who
are interested in books and book-collecting.  It was named, very
obviously, after the famous library of the same name, and not only
became in our city a sort of shrine for local worshipers of fine
bindings and rare editions, but was visited occasionally by
pilgrims from afar.  The Bodleian has entertained Mark Twain,
Joseph Jefferson, and other literary and histrionic celebrities.
It possesses quite a collection of personal mementos of
distinguished authors, among them a paperweight which once belonged
to Goethe, a lead pencil used by Emerson, an autograph letter of
Matthew Arnold, and a chip from a tree felled by Mr. Gladstone.
Its library contains a number of rare books, including a fine
collection on chess, of which game several of the members are
enthusiastic devotees.
</p><p>The activities of the club are not, however, confined entirely
to books.  We have a very handsome clubhouse, and much taste and
discrimination have been exercised in its adornment.  There are
many good paintings, including portraits of the various presidents
of the club, which adorn the entrance hall.  After books, perhaps
the most distinctive feature of the club is our collection of
pipes.  In a large rack in the smoking-room &mdash; really a superfluity,
since smoking is permitted all over the house &mdash; is as complete an
assortment of pipes as perhaps exists in the civilized world.
Indeed, it is an unwritten rule of the club that no one is eligible
for membership who cannot produce a new variety of pipe, which is
filed with his application for membership, and, if he passes,
deposited with the club collection, he, however, retaining the
title in himself.  Once a year, upon the anniversary of the death
of Sir Walter Raleigh, who it will be remembered, first introduced
tobacco into England, the full membership of the club, as a rule,
turns out.  A large supply of the very best smoking mixture is laid
in.  At nine o'clock sharp each member takes his pipe from the
rack, fills it with tobacco, and then the whole club, with the
president at the head, all smoking furiously, march in solemn
procession from room to room, upstairs and downstairs, making the
tour of the clubhouse and returning to the smoking-room.  The
president then delivers an address, and each member is called upon
to say something, either by way of a quotation or an original
sentiment, in praise of the virtues of nicotine.  This ceremony &mdash;
facetiously known as "hitting the pipe" &mdash; being thus concluded, the
membership pipes are carefully cleaned out and replaced in the club
rack.
</p><p>As I have said, however, the <hi rend="italic">raison d'etre</hi> of the club,
and the feature upon which its fame chiefly rests, is its
collection of rare books, and of these by far the most interesting
are its own publications.  Even its catalogues are works of art,
published in numbered editions, and sought by libraries and book-collectors.  Early in its history it began the occasional
publication of books which should meet the club standard, &mdash; books in
which emphasis should be laid upon the qualities that make a book
valuable in the eyes of collectors.  Of these, age could not, of
course, be imparted, but in the matter of fine and curious
bindings, of hand-made linen papers, of uncut or deckle edges, of
wide margins and limited editions, the club could control its own
publications.  The matter of contents was, it must be confessed, a
less important consideration.  At first it was felt by the
publishing committee that nothing but the finest products of the
human
<pb n="824"/>
mind should be selected for enshrinement in the
beautiful volumes which the club should issue.  The length of the
work was an important consideration, &mdash; long things were not
compatible with wide margins and graceful slenderness.  For
instance, we brought out Coleridge's Ancient Mariner, an essay by
Emerson, and another by Thoreau.  Our Rubaiyat of Omar Khayyam was
Heron-Allen's translation of the original MS in the Bodleian
Library at Oxford, which, though less poetical than FitzGerald's,
was not so common.  Several years ago we began to publish the works
of our own members.  Bascom's Essay on Pipes was a very creditable
performance.  It was published in a limited edition of one hundred
copies, and since it had not previously appeared elsewhere and was
copyrighted by the club, it was sufficiently rare to be valuable
for that reason.  The second publication of local origin was
Baxter's Procrustes.
</p><p>I have omitted to say that once or twice a year, at a meeting
of which notice has been given, an auction is held at the Bodleian.
The members of the club send in their duplicate copies, or books
they for any reason wish to dispose of, which are auctioned off to
the highest bidder.  At these sales, which are well attended, the
club's publications have of recent years formed the leading
feature.  Three years ago, number three of Bascom's Essay on Pipes
sold for fifteen dollars; &mdash; the original cost of publication was one
dollar and seventy-five cents.  Later in the evening an uncut copy
of the same brought thirty dollars.  At the next auction the price
of the cut copy was run up to twenty-five dollars, while the uncut
copy was knocked down at seventy-five dollars.  The club had always
appreciated the value of uncut copies, but this financial
indorsement enhanced their desirability immensely.  This rise in
the Essay on Pipes was not without a sympathetic effect upon all
the club publications.  The Emerson essay rose from three dollars
to seventeen, and the Thoreau, being by an author less widely read,
and, by his own confession commercially unsuccessful, brought a
somewhat higher figure.  The prices, thus inflated, were not
permitted to come down appreciably.  Since every member of the club
possessed one or more of these valuable editions, they were all
manifestly interested in keeping up the price.  The publication,
however, which brought the highest prices, and, but for the sober
second thought, might have wrecked the whole system, was Baxter's
Procrustes.
</p><p>Baxter was, perhaps, the most scholarly member of the club.
A graduate of Harvard, he had traveled extensively, had read
widely, and while not so enthusiastic a collector as some of us,
possessed as fine a private library as any man of his age in the
city.  He was about thirty-five when he joined the club, and
apparently some bitter experience &mdash; some disappointment in love or
ambition &mdash; had left its mark upon his character.  With light, curly
hair, fair complexion, and gray eyes, one would have expected
Baxter to be genial of temper, with a tendency toward wordiness of
speech.  But though he had occasional flashes of humor, his
ordinary demeanor was characterized by a mild cynicism, which, with
his gloomy pessimistic philosophy, so foreign to the temperament
that should accompany his physical type, could only be accounted
for upon the hypothesis of some secret sorrow such as I have
suggested.  What it might be no one knew.  He had means and social
position, and was an uncommonly handsome man.  The fact that he
remained unmarried at thirty-five furnished some support for the
theory of a disappointment in love, though this the several
intimates of Baxter who belonged to the club were not able to
verify.
</p><p>It had occurred to me, in a vague way, that perhaps Baxter
might be an unsuccessful author.  That he was a poet we knew very
well, and typewritten
<pb n="825"/>
copies of his verses had occasionally
circulated among us.  But Baxter had always expressed such a
profound contempt for modern literature, had always spoken in terms
of such unmeasured pity for the slaves of the pen, who were
dependent upon the whim of an undiscriminating public for
recognition and a livelihood, that no one of us had ever suspected
him of aspirations toward publication, until, as I have said, it
occurred to me one day that Baxter's attitude with regard to
publication might be viewed in the light of effect as well as of
cause &mdash; that his scorn of publicity might as easily arise from
failure to achieve it, as his never having published might be due
to his preconceived disdain of the vulgar popularity which one must
share with the pugilist or balloonist of the hour.
</p><p>The notion of publishing Baxter's Procrustes did not emanate
from Baxter, &mdash; I must do him the justice to say this.  But he had
spoken to several of the fellows about the theme of his poem, until
the notion that Baxter was at work upon something fine had become
pretty well disseminated throughout our membership.  He would
occasionally read brief passages to a small coterie of friends in
the sitting-room or library, &mdash; never more than ten lines at once, or
to more than five people at a time, &mdash; and these excerpts gave at
least a few of us a pretty fair idea of the motive and scope of the
poem.  As I, for one, gathered, it was quite along the line of
Baxter's philosophy.  Society was the Procrustes which, like the
Greek bandit of old, caught every man born into the world, and
endeavored to fit him to some preconceived standard, generally to
the one for which he was least adapted.  The world was full of men
and women who were merely square pegs in round holes, and <hi rend="italic">vice
versa</hi>.  Most marriages were unhappy because the contracting
parties were not properly mated.  Religion was mostly superstition,
science for the most part sciolism, popular education merely a
means of forcing the stupid and repressing the bright, so that all
the youth of the rising generation might conform to the same dull,
dead level of democratic mediocrity.  Life would soon become so
monotonously uniform and so uniformly monotonous as to be scarce
worth the living.
</p><p>It was Smith, I think, who first proposed that the club
publish Baxter's Procrustes.  The poet himself did not seem
enthusiastic when the subject was broached; he demurred for some
little time, protesting that the poem was not worthy of
publication.  But when it was proposed that the edition be limited
to fifty copies he agreed to consider the proposition.  When I
suggested, having in mind my secret theory of Baxter's failure in
authorship, that the edition would at least be in the hands of
friends, that it would be difficult for a hostile critic to secure
a copy, and that if it should not achieve success from a literary
point of view, the extent of the failure would be limited to the
size of the edition, Baxter was visibly impressed.  When the
literary committee at length decided to request formally of Baxter
the privilege of publishing his Procrustes, he consented, with
evident reluctance, upon condition that he should supervise the
printing, binding, and delivery of the books, merely submitting to
the committee, in advance, the manuscript, and taking their views
in regard to the bookmaking.
</p><p>The manuscript was duly presented to the literary committee.
Baxter having expressed the desire that the poem be not read aloud
at a meeting of the club, as was the custom, since he wished it to
be given to the world clad in suitable garb, the committee went
even farther.  Having entire confidence in Baxter's taste and
scholarship, they, with great delicacy, refrained from even reading
the manuscript, contenting themselves with Baxter's statement of
the general theme and the topics grouped under it.  The
<pb n="826"/>
details of the bookmaking, however, were gone into thoroughly.  The
paper was to be of hand-made linen, from the Kelmscott Mills; the
type black-letter, with rubricated initials.  The cover, which was
Baxter's own selection, was to be of dark green morocco, with a
cap-and-bells border in red inlays, and doublures of maroon morocco
with a blind-tooled design.  Baxter was authorized to contract with
the printer and superintend the publication.  The whole edition of
fifty numbered copies was to be disposed of at auction, in advance,
to the highest bidder, only one copy to each, the proceeds to be
devoted to paying for the printing and binding, the remainder, if
any, to go into the club treasury, and Baxter himself to receive
one copy by way of remuneration.  Baxter was inclined to protest at
this, on the ground that his copy would probably be worth more than
the royalties on the edition, at the usual ten per cent, would
amount to, but was finally prevailed upon to accept an author's
copy.
</p><p>While the Procrustes was under consideration, some one read,
at one of our meetings, a note from some magazine, which stated
that a sealed copy of a new translation of Campanella's Sonnets,
published by the Grolier Club, had been sold for three hundred
dollars.  This impressed the members greatly.  It was a novel idea.
A new work might thus be enshrined in a sort of holy of holies,
which, if the collector so desired, could be forever sacred from
the profanation of any vulgar or unappreciative eye.  The possessor
of such a treasure could enjoy it by the eye of imagination, having
at the same time the exaltation of grasping what was for others the
unattainable.  The literary committee were so impressed with this
idea that they presented it to Baxter in regard to the Procrustes.
Baxter making no objection, the subscribers who might wish their
copies delivered sealed were directed to notify the author.  I sent
in my name.  A fine book, after all, was an investment, and if
there was any way of enhancing its rarity, and therefore its value,
I was quite willing to enjoy such an advantage.
</p><p>When the Procrustes was ready for distribution, each
subscriber received his copy by mail, in a neat pasteboard box.
Each number was wrapped in a thin and transparent but very strong
paper through which the cover design and tooling were clearly
visible.  The number of the copy was indorsed upon the wrapper, the
folds of which were securely fastened at each end with sealing-wax,
upon which was impressed, as a guaranty of its inviolateness, the
monogram of the club.
</p><p>At the next meeting of the Bodleian, a great deal was said
about the Procrustes, and it was unanimously agreed that no finer
specimen of bookmaking had ever been published by the club.  By a
curious coincidence, no one had brought his copy with him, and the
two club copies had not yet been received from the binder, who,
Baxter had reported was retaining them for some extra fine work.
Upon resolution, offered by a member who had not subscribed for the
volume, a committee of three was appointed to review the Procrustes
at the next literary meeting of the club.  Of this committee it was
my doubtful fortune to constitute one.
</p><p>In pursuance of my duty in the premises, it of course became
necessary for me to read the Procrustes.  In all probability I
should have cut my own copy for this purpose, had not one of the
club auctions intervened between my appointment and the date set
for the discussion of the Procrustes.  At this meeting a copy of
the book, still sealed, was offered for sale, and bought by a non-subscriber for the unprecedented price of one hundred and fifty
dollars.  After this a proper regard for my own interests would not
permit me to spoil my copy by opening it, and I was therefore
compelled to procure my information concerning the
<pb n="827"/>
poem
from some other source.  As I had no desire to appear mercenary, I
said nothing about my own copy, and made no attempt to borrow.  I
did, however, casually remark to Baxter that I should like to look
at his copy of the proof sheets, since I wished to make some
extended quotations for my review, and would rather not trust my
copy to a typist for that purpose.  Baxter assured me, with every
evidence of regret, that he had considered them of so little
importance that he had thrown them into the fire.  This
indifference of Baxter to literary values struck me as just a
little overdone.  The proof sheets of Hamlet, corrected in
Shakespeare's own hand, would be well-nigh priceless.
</p><p>At the next meeting of the club I observed that Thompson and
Davis, who were with me on the reviewing committee, very soon
brought up the question of the Procrustes in conversation in the
smoking-room, and seemed anxious to get from the members their
views concerning Baxter's production, I supposed upon the theory
that the appreciation of any book review would depend more or less
upon the degree to which it reflected the opinion of those to whom
the review should be presented.  I presumed, of course, that
Thompson and Davis had each read the book, &mdash; they were among the
subscribers, &mdash; and I was desirous of getting their point of view.
</p><p>"What do you think," I inquired, "of the passage on Social
Systems?"  I have forgotten to say that the poem was in blank
verse, and divided into parts, each with an appropriate title.
</p><p>"Well," replied Davis, it seemed to me a little cautiously,
"it is not exactly Spencerian, although it squints at the
Spencerian view, with a slight deflection toward Hegelianism.  I
should consider it an harmonious fusion of the best views of all
the modern philosophers, with a strong Baxterian flavor."
</p><p>"Yes," said Thompson, "the charm of the chapter lies in this
very quality.  The style is an emanation from Baxter's own
intellect, &mdash; he has written himself into the poem.  By knowing
Baxter we are able to appreciate the book, and after having read
the book we feel that we are so much the more intimately acquainted
with Baxter, &mdash; the real Baxter."
</p><p>Baxter had come in during this colloquy, and was standing by
the fireplace smoking a pipe.  I was not exactly sure whether the
faint smile which marked his face was a token of pleasure or
cynicism; it was Baxterian, however, and I had already learned that
Baxter's opinions upon any subject were not to be gathered always
from his facial expression.  For instance, when the club porter's
crippled child died Baxter remarked, it seemed to me unfeelingly,
that the poor little devil was doubtless better off, and that the
porter himself had certainly been relieved of a burden; and only a
week later the porter told me in confidence that Baxter had paid
for an expensive operation, undertaken in the hope of prolonging
the child's life.  I therefore drew no conclusions from Baxter's
somewhat enigmatical smile.  He left the room at this point in the
conversation, somewhat to my relief.
</p><p>"By the way, Jones," said Davis, addressing me, "are you
impressed by Baxter's views on Degeneration?"
</p><p>Having often heard Baxter express himself upon the general
downward tendency of modern civilization, I felt safe in discussing
his views in a broad and general manner.
</p><p>"I think," I replied, "that they are in harmony with those of
Schopenhauer, without his bitterness; with those of Nordau, without
his flippancy.  His materialism is Haeckel's, presented with
something of the charm of Omar Khayyam."
</p><p>"Yes," chimed in Davis, "it answers the strenuous demand of
our day, &mdash; dissatisfaction with an unjustified optimism, &mdash; and voices
for us the courage of human philosophy facing the unknown."
</p><p>I had a vague recollection of having
<pb n="828"/>
read something
like this somewhere, but so much has been written, that one can
scarcely discuss any subject of importance without unconsciously
borrowing, now and then, the thoughts or the language of others.
Quotation, like imitation, is a superior grade of flattery.
</p><p>"The Procrustes," said Thompson, to whom the metrical review
had been apportioned, "is couched in sonorous lines, of haunting
melody and charm; and yet so closely inter-related as to be
scarcely quotable with justice to the author.  To be appreciated
the poem should be read as a whole, &mdash; I shall say as much in my
review.  What shall you say of the letter-press?" he concluded,
addressing me.  I was supposed to discuss the technical excellence
of the volume from the connoisseur's viewpoint.
</p><p>"The setting," I replied judicially, "is worthy of the gem.
The dark green cover, elaborately tooled, the old English
lettering, the heavy linen paper, mark this as one of our very
choicest publications.  The letter-press is of course De Vinne's
best, &mdash; there is nothing better on this side of the Atlantic.  The
text is a beautiful, slender stream, meandering gracefully through
a wide meadow of margin."
</p><p>For some reason I left the room for a minute.  As I stepped
into the hall, I almost ran into Baxter, who was standing near the
door, facing a hunting print of a somewhat humorous character, hung
upon the wall, and smiling with an immensely pleased expression.
</p><p>"What a ridiculous scene!" he remarked.  "Look at that fat old
squire on that tall hunter!  I'll wager dollars to doughnuts that
he won't get over the first fence!"
</p><p>It was a very good bluff, but did not deceive me.  Under his
mask of unconcern, Baxter was anxious to learn what we thought of
his poem, and had stationed himself in the hall that he might
overhear our discussion without embarrassing us by his presence.
He had covered up his delight at our appreciation by this simulated
interest in the hunting print.

</p><p>When the night came for the review of the Procrustes there was
a large attendance of members, and several visitors, among them a
young English cousin of one of the members, on his first visit to
the United States; some of us had met him at other clubs, and in
society, and had found him a very jolly boy, with a youthful
exuberance of spirits and a naive ignorance of things American that
made his views refreshing and, at times, amusing.
</p><p>The critical essays were well considered, if a trifle vague.
Baxter received credit for poetic skill of a high order.
</p><p>"Our brother Baxter," said Thompson, "should no longer bury
his talent in a napkin.  This gem, of course, belongs to the club,
but the same brain from which issued this exquisite emanation can
produce others to inspire and charm an appreciative world."
</p><p>"The author's view of life," said Davis, "as expressed in
these beautiful lines, will help us to fit our shoulders for the
heavy burden of life, by bringing to our realization those profound
truths of philosophy which find hope in despair and pleasure in
pain.  When he shall see fit to give to the wider world, in fuller
form, the thoughts of which we have been vouchsafed this foretaste,
let us hope that some little ray of his fame may rest upon the
Bodleian, from which can never be taken away the proud privilege of
saying that he was one of its members."
</p><p>I then pointed out the beauties of the volume as a piece of
bookmaking.  I knew, from conversation with the publication
committee, the style of type and rubrication, and could see the
cover through the wrapper of my sealed copy.  The dark green
morocco, I said, in summing up, typified the author's serious view
of life, as a thing to be endured as patiently as might be.  The
cap-and-bells
<pb n="829"/>
border was significant of the shams by which
the optimist sought to delude himself into the view that life was
a desirable thing.  The intricate blind-tooling of the doublure
shadowed forth the blind fate which left us in ignorance of our
future and our past, or of even what the day itself might bring
forth.  The black-letter type, with rubricated initials, signified
a philosophic pessimism enlightened by the conviction that in duty
one might find, after all, an excuse for life and a hope for
humanity.  Applying this test to the club, this work, which might
be said to represent all that the Bodleian stood for, was in itself
sufficient to justify the club's existence.  If the Bodleian had
done nothing else, if it should do nothing more, it had produced a
masterpiece.
</p><p>There was a sealed copy of the Procrustes, belonging, I
believe, to one of the committee, lying on the table by which I
stood, and I had picked it up and held it in my hand for a moment,
to emphasize one of my periods, but had laid it down immediately.
I noted, as I sat down, that young Hunkin, our English visitor, who
sat on the other side of the table, had picked up the volume and
was examining it with interest.  When the last review was read, and
the generous applause had subsided, there were cries for Baxter.
</p><p>"Baxter!  Baxter!  Author!  Author!"
</p><p>Baxter had been sitting over in a corner during the reading of
the reviews, and had succeeded remarkably well, it seemed to me, in
concealing, under his mask of cynical indifference, the exultation
which I was sure he must feel.  But this outburst of enthusiasm was
too much even for Baxter, and it was clear that he was struggling
with strong emotion when he rose to speak.
</p><p>"Gentlemen, and fellow members of the Bodleian, it gives me
unaffected pleasure &mdash; sincere pleasure &mdash; some day you may know how
much pleasure &mdash; I cannot trust myself to say it now &mdash; to see the
evident care with which your committee have read my poor verses,
and the responsive sympathy with which my friends have entered into
my views of life and conduct.  I thank you again, and again, and
when I say that I am too full for utterance, &mdash; I'm sure you will
excuse me from saying any more."
</p><p>Baxter took his seat, and the applause had begun again when it
was broken by a sudden exclamation.
</p><p>"By Jove!" exclaimed our English visitor, who still sat behind
the table, "what an extraordinary book!"
</p><p>Every one gathered around him.
</p><p>"You see," he exclaimed; holding up the volume, "you fellows
said so much about the bally book that I wanted to see what it was
like; so I untied the ribbon, and cut the leaves with the paper
knife lying here, and found &mdash; and found that there wasn't a single
line in it, don't you know!"
</p><p>Blank consternation followed this announcement, which proved
only too true.  Every one knew instinctively, without further
investigation, that the club had been badly sold.  In the resulting
confusion Baxter escaped, but later was waited upon by a committee,
to whom he made the rather lame excuse that he had always regarded
uncut and sealed books as tommy-rot, and that he had merely been
curious to see how far the thing could go; and that the result had
justified his belief that a book with nothing in it was just as
useful to a book-collector as one embodying a work of genius.  He
offered to pay all the bills for the sham Procrustes, or to replace
the blank copies with the real thing, as we might choose.  Of
course, after such an insult, the club did not care for the poem.
He was permitted to pay the expense, however, and it was more than
hinted to him that his resignation from the club would be favorably
acted upon.  He never sent it in, and, as he went to Europe shortly
afterwards, the affair had time to blow over.
</p><p>In our first disgust at Baxter's duplicity,
<pb n="830"/>
most of us
cut our copies of the Procrustes, some of us mailed them to Baxter
with cutting notes, and others threw them into the fire.  A few
wiser spirits held on to theirs, and this fact leaking out, it
began to dawn upon the minds of the real collectors among us that
the volume was something unique in the way of a publication.
</p><p>"Baxter," said our president one evening to a select few of us
who sat around the fireplace, "was wiser than we knew, or than he
perhaps appreciated.  His Procrustes, from the collector's point of
view, is entirely logical, and might be considered as the acme of
bookmaking.  To the true collector, a book is a work of art, of
which the contents are no more important than the words of an
opera.  Fine binding is a desideratum, and, for its cost, that of
the Procrustes could not be improved upon.  The paper is above
criticism.  The true collector loves wide margins, and the
Procrustes, being all margin, merely touches the vanishing point of
the perspective.  The smaller the edition, the greater the
collector's eagerness to acquire a copy.  There are but six uncut
copies left, I am told, of the Procrustes, and three sealed copies,
of one of which I am the fortunate possessor."
</p><p>After this deliverance, it is not surprising that, at our next
auction, a sealed copy of Baxter's Procrustes was knocked down,
after spirited bidding, for two hundred and fifty dollars, the
highest price ever brought by a single volume published by the
club.
                              <hi rend="italic">Charles W. Chesnutt.</hi><lb/>
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
