<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CheWife"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="CheWife">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Wife of his Youth</title>
<title type="sort">wife of his youth</title>
<author>Chesnutt, Charles Waddell, 1858-1932</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">29</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CheWife</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475816</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Wife of his Youth</title>
<title type="sort">wife of his youth</title>
<author>Charles W. Chesnutt</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1898">1898</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 82</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 55-61</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library
Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text
Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are
composed of the text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as
in SpeFQue1 for page one of Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1898">1898</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-03">March 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Timothy O. Jarrett</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">



<div1 type="section" n="1" id="d3"><pb n="55"/>
<head>1</head>
<p>MR. RYDER was going to give a ball.  There were several
reasons why this was an opportune time for such an event.</p>
<p>Mr. Ryder might aptly be called the dean of the Blue Veins.  The
original Blue Veins were a little society of colored persons organized in
a certain Northern city shortly after the war.  Its purpose was to
establish and maintain correct social standards among a people whose
social condition presented almost unlimited room  for improvement.  By
accident, combined perhaps with some natural affinity, the society
consisted of individuals who were, generally speaking, more white than
black.  Some envious outsider made the suggestion that no one was
eligible for membership who was not white enough to show blue veins.
The suggestion was readily adopted by those who were not of the
favored few, and since that time the society, though possessing a longer
and more pretentious name, had been known far and wide as the "Blue
Vein Society," and its members as the "Blue Veins."</p>
<p>The Blue Veins did not allow that any such requirement existed for
admission to their circle, but, on the contrary, declared that  character
and culture were the only things considered; and that if most of their
members were light-colored, it was because such persons, as a rule, had
had better opportunities to qualify themselves for membership.  Opinions
differed, too, as to the usefulness of the society.  There  were those who
had been known to assail it violently as a glaring example of the very
prejudice from which the colored race had suffered most; and later,
when such critics had succeeded in getting on the inside, they had been
heard to maintain with zeal and earnestness that the society was a
life-boat, an anchor, a bulwark and a shield, a pillar of cloud by day and
of fire by night, to guide their people through the social wilderness.
Another alleged prerequisite for Blue Vein membership was that of free
birth; and while there was really no such requirement,  it is doubtless
true that very few of the members would have been unable to meet it if
there had been.  If there were one or two of the older members who had
come up from the South and from slavery, their history presented enough
romantic circumstances to rob their servile origin of its grosser aspects.
While there were no such tests of eligibility, it is true that the Blue Veins
had their notions on these subjects, and that not all of them were equally
liberal in regard to the things they collectively disclaimed.  Mr. Ryder
was one of the most conservative.  Though he had not been among the
founders of the society, but had come in some years later, his genius for
social leadership was such that he had speedily become its recognized
adviser and head, the custodian of its standards, and the preserver of its
traditions.  He shaped its social policy, was active in providing for its
entertainment, and when the interest fell off, as it sometimes did, he
fanned the embers until they burst again into a cheerful flame.     There
were still other reasons for his popularity.  While he was not as white as
some of the Blue Veins, his appearance was such as to confer distinction
upon them.  His features were of a refined type, his hair was almost
straight; he was always neatly dressed; his manners were irreproachable,
and his morals above suspicion.  He had come to Groveland a young
man, and obtaining employment in the office of a railroad company as
messenger had in time worked himself

<pb n="56"/>
up to the position of stationery clerk, having charge of the distribution of
the office supplies for the whole company.  Although the lack of early
training had hindered the orderly development of a naturally fine mind, it
had not prevented him from doing a great deal of reading or from
forming decidedly literary tastes.  Poetry was his passion.  He could
repeat whole pages of the great English poets ; and if his pronunciation
was sometimes faulty, his eye, his voice, his gestures, would respond to
the changing sentiment with a precision that revealed a poetic soul, and
disarm criticism.  He was economical, and had saved money; he owned
and occupied a very comfortable house on a respectable street.  His
residence was handsomely furnished, containing among other things a
good library, especially rich in poetry, a piano, and some choice
engravings.  He generally shared his house with some young couple,
who looked after his wants and were company for him; for Mr. Ryder
was a single man.  In the early days of his connection with the Blue
Veins he had been regarded as quite a catch, and ladies and their
mothers had manoeuvred with much ingenuity to capture him.  Not,
however, until Mrs. Molly Dixon visited Groveland had any woman ever
made him wish to change his condition to that of a married man.</p>
<p>Mrs. Dixon had come to Groveland from Washington in the
spring, and before the summer was over she had won Mr. Ryder's heart.
She possessed many attractive qualities.  She was much younger than he;
in  fact, he was old enough to have been her father, though no one knew
exactly how old he was.  She was whiter than he, and better educated.
She had moved in the best colored society of the country, at Washington,
and had taught in the schools of that city.  Such a superior person had
been eagerly welcomed to the Blue Vein Society, and had taken a leading
part in its activities.  Mr. Ryder had at first been attracted by her charms
of person, for she was very good looking and not over twenty-five; then
by her refined manners and by the vivacity of her wit.  Her husband had
been a government clerk, and at his death had left a considerable life
insurance.  She was visiting friends in Groveland, and, finding the town
and the people to her liking, had prolonged her stay indefinitely.  She
had not seemed displeased at Mr. Ryder's attentions, but on the contrary
had given him every proper encouragement; indeed, a younger and less
cautious man would long since have spoken.  But he had made up his
mind, and had only to determine the time when he would ask her to be
his wife.  He decided to give a ball in her honor, and at some time
during the evening of the ball to offer her his heart and hand.  He had
no special fears about the outcotme, but, with a little touch of romance,
he wanted the surroundings to be in harmony with his own feelings when
he should have received the answer he expected.</p>
<p>Mr. Ryder resolved that this ball should mark an epoch in the
social history of Groveland.  He knew, of course, &mdash; no one could know
better, &mdash; the entertainments that had taken place in past years, and what
must be done to surpass them.  His ball must be worthy of the lady in
whose honor it was to be given, and must, by the quality of its guests,
set an example for the future.  He had observed of late a growing
liberality, almost a laxity, in social matters, even among members of his
own set, and had several times been forced to meet in a social way
persons whose complexions and callings in life were hardly up to the
standard which he considered proper for the society to maintain.  He had
a theory of his own.</p>
<p>"I have no race prejudice," he would say, "but we people of mixed
blood are ground between the upper and the nether millstone.  Our fate
lies between absorption by the white race and extinction

<pb n="57"/>
in the black.  The one doesn't want us yet, but may take us in time.
The other would welcome us, but it would be for us a backward step.
'With malice towards none, with charity for all,' we must do the best we
can for ourselves and those who are to follow us.  Self-preservation is
the first law of nature."</p>
<p>His ball would serve by its exclusiveness to counteract leveling
tendencies, and his marriage with Mrs. Dixon would help to further the
upward process of absorption he had been wishing and waiting for.
</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="section" n="2" id="d4">
<head>2</head>
<p>The ball was to take place on Friday night.  The house had been
put in order, the carpets covered with canvas, the halls and stairs
decorated with palms and potted plants; and in the afternoon Mr. Ryder
sat on his front porch, which the shade of a vine running up over a wire
netting made a cool and pleasant lounging-place.  He expected to
respond to the toast "The Ladies," at the supper, and from a volume of
Tennyson &mdash; his favorite poet &mdash; was fortifying himself with apt
quotations.  The volume was open at A Dream of Fair Women.  His
eyes fell on these lines, and he read them aloud to judge better of their
effect:&mdash;  "At length I saw a lady within call.    Stiller than chisell'd
marble, standing there; A daughter of the gods, divinely tall,    And
most divinely fair."  He marked the verse, and turning the page read the
stanza beginning,&mdash; </p>
<l>"O sweet pale Margaret,</l>
<l> O rare pale Margaret." </l>
<p>
He weighed the passage a moment, and decided that it would not do.
Mrs. Dixon was the palest lady he expected at the ball, and she was of a
rather ruddy complexion, and of lively disposition and buxom build.  So
he ran over the leaves until his eye rested on the description of Queen
Guinevere:&mdash;
</p>
<lg type="verse">
<l>   "She seem'd a part of joyous Spring:</l>
<l>A gown of grass-green silk she wore,</l>
<l>Buckled with golden clasps before;</l>
<l>A light-green tuft of plumes she bore</l>
<l>   Closed in a golden ring.</l>
<l>.   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .</l>
<l>"She look'd so lovely, as she sway'd</l>
<l>   The rein with dainty finger-tips,</l>
<l>A man had given all other bliss,</l>
<l>And all his worldly worth for this,</l>
<l>To waste his whole heart in one kiss</l>
<l>   Upon her perfect lips." </l>
</lg>
<p>As Mr. Ryder murmured these words audibly, with an appreciative
thrill, he heard the latch of his gate click, and a light footfall sounding
on the steps.  He turned his head, and saw a woman standing before the
door.</p>
<p>She was a little woman, not five feet tall, and proportioned to her
height.  Although she stood erect, and looked around her with very
bright and restless eyes, she seemed quite old; for her face was crossed
and recrossed with a hundred wrinkles, and around the edges of her
bonnet could be seen protruding here and there a tuft of short gray wool.
She wore a blue calico gown of ancient cut, a little red shawl fastened
around her shoulders with an old-fashioned brass brooch, and a large
bonnet profusely ornamented with faded red and yellow artificial
flowers.  And she was very black &mdash; so black that her toothless gums,
revealed when she opened her mouth to speak, were not red, but blue.
She looked like a bit of the old plantation life, summoned up from the
past by the wave of a magician's wand, as the poet's fancy had called
into being the gracious shapes of which Mr. Ryder had just been
reading.</p>
<p>He rose from his chair and came over to where she stood.</p>
<p>"Good-afternoon, madam," he said.</p>
<p>"Good-evenin', suh," she answered, ducking suddenly with a
quaint curtsy.  Her voice was shrill and piping, but softened somewhat
by age.  "Is dis yere whar Mistuh Ryduh lib, suh?" she asked, looking
around her doubtfully,

<pb n="58"/>
and glancing into the open windows, through which some of the
preparations for the evening were visible.</p>
<p>"Yes," he replied, with an air of kindly patronage, unconsciously
flattered by her manner, "I am Mr. Ryder.  Did you want to see
me?"</p>
<p>"Yas, suh, ef I ain't 'sturbin' of you too much."</p>
<p>"Not at all.  Have a seat over here behind the vine, where it is
cool.  What can I do for you?"</p>
<p>"'Scuse me, suh," she continued, when she had sat down on the
edge of a chair, "'scuse me, suh, I's lookin' for my husban'.  I heerd
you wuz a big man an' had libbed heah a long time, an' I 'lowed you
wouldn't min' ef I'd come roun' an' ax you ef you'd eber heerd of a
merlatter man by de name er Sam Taylor 'quirin' roun' in de chu'ches
ermongs' de people fer his wife 'Liza Jane?"</p>
<p>Mr. Ryder seemed to think for a moment.</p>
<p>"There used to be many such cases right after the war," he said,
"but it has been so long that I have forgotten them.  There are very few
now.  But tell me your story, and it may refresh my memory."</p>
<p>She sat back farther in her chair so as to be more comfortable, and
folded her withered hands in her lap.</p>
<p>"My name's 'Liza," she began, "'Liza Jane.  Wen I wuz young I
us'ter b'long ter Marse Bob Smif, down in old Missourn.  I wuz bawn
down dere.  W'en I wuz a gal I wuz married ter a man named Jim.  But
Jim died, an' after dat I married a merlatter man named Sam Taylor.
Sam wuz free-bawn, but his mammy and daddy died, an' de w'ite folks
'prenticed him ter my marster fer ter work fer 'im 'tel he wuz growed
up.  Sam worked in de fiel', an' I wuz de cook.  One day Ma'y Ann,
ole miss's maid, come rushin' out ter de kitchen, an' says she, ''Liza
Jane, ole marse gwine sell yo' Sam down de ribber.'</p>
<p>"'Go way f'm yere,' says I; 'my husban's free!'</p>
<p>"'Don' make no diff'ence.  I heerd ole marse tell ole miss he wuz
gwine take yo' Sam 'way wid 'im ter-morrow, fer he needed money, an'
he knowed whar he could git a t'ousan' dollars fer Sam an' no questions
axed.'</p>
<p>"W'en Sam come home f'm de fiel', dat night, I tole him 'bout ole
marse gwine steal 'im, an' Sam run erway.  His time wuz mos' up, an'
he swo' dat w'en he wuz twenty-one he would come back an' he'p me
run erway, er else save up de money ter buy my freedom.  An' I know
he'd 'a' done it, fer he thought a heap er me, Sam did.  But w'en he
come back he didn' fin' me, fer I wuzn' dere.  Ole marse had heerd dat
I warned Sam, so he had me whip' an' sol' down de ribber.</p>
<p>"Den de wah broke out, an' w'en it wuz ober de cullud folks wuz
scattered.  I went back ter de ole home; but Sam wuzn' dere, an' I
couldn' l'arn nuffin' 'bout 'im.  But I knowed he'd be'n dere to look fer
me an' hadn' foun' me, an' had gone erway ter hunt fer me.</p>
<p>"I's be'n lookin' fer 'im eber sence," she added simply, as though
twenty-five years were but a couple of weeks, "an' I knows he's be'n
lookin' fer me.  Fer he sot a heap er sto' by me, Sam did, an' I know
he's be'n huntin' fer me all dese years,&mdash;'less'n he's be'n sick er sump'n,
so he couldn' work, er out'n his head, so he couldn' 'member his
promise.  I went back down de ribber, fer I 'lowed he'd gone down dere
lookin' fer me.  I's be'n ter Noo Orleens, an' Atlanty, an' Charleston,
an' Richmon'; an' w'en I'd be'n all ober de Souf I come ter de Norf.
Fer I knows I'll fin' 'im some er dese days," she added softly, "er he'll
fin' me, an' den we'll bofe be as happy in freedom as we wuz in de ole
days befo' de wah."  A smile stole over her withered countenance as she
paused a moment, and her bright eyes softened into a far-away look.
</p>

<pb n="59"/>
<p>This was the substance of the old woman's story.  She had
wandered a little here and there.  Mr. Ryder was looking at her
curiously when she finished.</p>
<p>"How have you lived all these years?" he asked.</p>
<p>"Cookin', suh.  I's a good cook.  Does you know anybody w'at
needs a good cook, suh?  I's stoppin' wid a cullud fam'ly roun' de
corner yonder 'tel I kin fin' a place."</p>
<p>"Do you really expect to find your husband?  He may be dead long
ago."</p>
<p>She shook her head emphatically.  "Oh no, he ain' dead.  De signs
an' de tokens tells me.  I dremp three nights runnin' on'y dis las' week
dat I foun' him."</p>
<p>"He may have married another woman.  Your slave marriage
would not have prevented him, for you never lived with him after the
war, and without that your marriage doesn't count."</p>
<p>"Wouldn' make no diff'ence wid Sam.  He wouldn' marry no
yuther 'ooman 'tel he foun' out 'bout me.  I knows it," she added.
"Sump'n's be'n tellin' me all dese years dat I's gwine fin' Sam 'fo I
dies."</p>
<p>"Perhaps he's outgrown you, and climbed up in the world where
he wouldn't care to have you find him."</p>
<p>"No, indeed, suh," she replied, "Sam ain' dat kin' er man.  He
wuz good ter me, Sam wuz, but he wuzn' much good ter nobody e'se,
fer he wuz one er de triflin'es' han's on de plantation.  I 'spec's ter haf
ter suppo't 'im w'en I fin' 'im, fer he nebber would work 'less'n he had
ter.  But den he wuz free, an' he didn' git no pay fer his work, an' I
don' blame 'im much.  Mebbe he's done better sence he run erway, but
I ain' 'spectin' much."</p>
<p>"You may have passed him on the street a hundred times during
the twenty-five years, and not have known him; time works great
changes."</p>
<p>She smiled incredulously.  "I'd know 'im 'mongs' a hund'ed men.
Fer dey wuzn' no yuther merlatter man like my man Sam, an' I couldn'
be mistook.  I's toted his picture roun' wid me twenty-five years."</p>

<p>"May I see it?" asked Mr. Ryder.  "It might help me to remember
whether I have seen the original."</p>
<p>As she drew a small parcel from her bosom, he saw that it was
fastened to a string that went around her neck.  Removing several
wrappers, she brought to light an old-fashioned daguerreotype in a black
case.  He looked long and intently at the portrait.  It was faded with
time, but the features were still distinct, and it was easy to see what
manner of man it had represented.</p>
<p>He closed the case, and with a slow movement handed it back to
her.</p>
<p>"I don't know of any man in town who goes by that name," he
said, "nor have I heard of any one making such inquiries.  But if you
will leave me your address, I will give the matter some attention, and if
I find out anything I will let you know."</p>
<p>She gave him the number of a house in the neighborhood, and
went away, after thanking him warmly.</p>
<p>He wrote down the address on the flyleaf of the volume of
Tennyson, and, when she had gone, rose to his feet and stood looking
after her curiously.  As she walked down the street with mincing step, he
saw several persons whom she passed turn and look back at her with a
smile of kindly amusement.  When she had turned the corner, he went
upstairs to his bedroom, and stood for a long time before the mirror of
his dressing-case, gazing thoughtfully at the reflection of his own face.
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="3" id="d5">
<head>3</head>

<p>At eight o'clock the ballroom was a blaze of light and the guests
had begun to assemble; for there was a literary programme and some
routine business

<pb n="60"/>
of the society to be gone through with before the dancing.  A black
servant in evening dress waited at the door and directed the guests to the
dressing-rooms.</p>
<p>The occasion was long memorable among the colored people of the
city; not alone for the dress and display, but for the high average of
intelligence and culture that distinguished the gathering as a whole.
There were a number of school-teachers, several young doctors, three or
four lawyers, some professional singers, an editor, a lieutenant in the
United States army spending his furlough in the city, and others in
various polite callings; these were colored, though most of them would
not have attracted even a casual glance because of any marked difference
from white people.  Most of the ladies were in evening costume, and
dress coats and dancing-pumps were the rule among the men.  A band of
string music, stationed in an alcove behind a row of palms, played
popular airs while the guests were gathering.</p>
<p>The dancing began at half past nine.  At eleven o'clock supper was
served.  Mr. Ryder had left the ballroom some little time before the
intermission, but reappeared at the supper-table.  The spread was worthy
of the occasion, and the guests did full justice to it.  When the coffee
had been served, the toastmaster, Mr. Solomon Sadler, rapped for order.
He made a brief introductory speech, complimenting host and guests,
and then presented in their order the toasts of the evening.  They were
responded to with a very fair display of after-dinner wit.</p>
<p>"The last toast," said the toast-master, when he reached the end of
the list, "is one which must appeal to us all.  There is no one of us of
the sterner sex who is not at some time dependent upon woman,&mdash;in
infancy for protection, in manhood for companionship, in old age for
care and comforting.  Our good host has been trying to live alone, but
the fair faces I see around me to-night prove that he too is largely
dependent upon the gentler sex for most that makes life worth
living,&mdash;the society and love of friends,&mdash;and rumor is at fault if he does
not soon yield entire subjection to one of them.  Mr. Ryder will now
respond to the toast,&mdash;The Ladies."</p>
<p>There was a pensive look in Mr. Ryder's eyes as he took the floor
and adjusted his eyeglasses.  He began by speaking of woman as the gift
of Heaven to man, and after some general observations on the relations
of the sexes he said: "But perhaps the quality which most distinguishes
woman is her fidelity and devotion to those she loves.  History is full of
examples, but has recorded none more striking than one which only
to-day came under my notice."</p>
<p>He then related, simply but effectively, the story told by his visitor
of the afternoon.  He told it in the same soft dialect, which came readily
to his lips, while the company listened attentively and sympathetically.
For the story had awakened a responsive thrill in many hearts.  There
were some present who had seen, and others who had heard their fathers
and grandfathers tell, the wrongs and sufferings of this past generation,
and all of them still felt, in their darker moments, the shadow hanging
over them.  Mr. Ryder went on:&mdash;</p>
<p>"Such devotion and such confidence are rare even among women.
There are many who would have searched a year, some who would have
waited five years, a few who might have hoped ten years; but for
twenty-five years this woman has retained her affection for and her faith
in a man she has not seen or heard of in all that time.</p>
<p>"She came to me to-day in the hope that I might be able to help
her find this long-lost husband.  And when she was gone I gave my
fancy rein, and imagined a case I will put to you.</p>
<p>"Suppose that this husband, soon after his escape, had learned that
his wife

<pb n="61"/>
had been sold away, and that such inquiries as he could make brought no
information of her whereabouts.  Suppose that he was young, and she
much older than he; that he was light, and she was black; that their
marriage was a slave marriage, and legally binding only if they chose to
make it so after the war.  Suppose, too, that he made his way to the
North, as some of us have done, and there, where he had larger
opportunities, had improved them, and had in the course of all these
years grown to be as different from the ignorant boy who ran away from
fear of slavery as the day is from the night.  Suppose, even, that he had
qualified himself, by industry, by thrift, and by study, to win the
friendship and be considered worthy the society of such people as these I
see around me to-night, gracing my board and filling my heart with
gladness; for I am old enough to remember the day when such a
gathering would not have been possible in this land.  Suppose, too, that,
as the years went by, this man's memory of the past grew more and
more indistinct, until at last it was rarely, except in his dreams, that any
image of this bygone period rose before his mind.  And then suppose
that accident should bring to his knowledge the fact that the wife of his
youth, the wife he had left behind him,&mdash;not one who had walked by his
side and kept pace with him in his upward struggle, but one upon whom
advancing years and a laborious life had set their mark,&mdash;was alive and
seeking him, but that he was absolutely safe from recognition or
discovery, unless he chose to reveal himself.  My friends, what would
the man do?  I will suppose that he was one who loved honor, and tried
to deal justly with all men.  I will even carry the case further, and
suppose that perhaps he had set his heart upon another, whom he had
hoped to call his own.  What would he do, or rather what ought he to
do, in such a crisis of a lifetime?</p>
<p>"It seemed to me that he might hesitate, and I imagined that I was
an old friend, a near friend, and that he had come to me for advice; and
I argued the case with him.  I tried to discuss it impartially.  After we
had looked upon the matter from every point of view, I said to him, in
words that we all know: </p>
<p>'This above all: to thine own self be true,</p>
<p> And it must follow, as the night the day,</p>
<p> Thou canst not then be false to any man.' </p>
<p>Then, finally, I put the question to him, 'Shall you acknowledge
her?'</p>
<p>"And now, ladies and gentlemen, friends and companions, I ask
you, what should he have done?"</p>
<p>There was something in Mr. Ryder's voice that stirred the hearts
of those who sat around him.  It suggested more than mere sympathy
with an imaginary situation; it seemed rather in the nature of a personal
appeal.  It was observed, too, that his look rested more especially upon
Mrs. lDixon, with a mingled expression of renunciation and
inquiry.</p>
<p>She had listened, with parted lips and streaming eyes.  She was the
first to speak: "He should have acknowledged her."</p>
<p>"Yes," they all echoed, "he should have acknowledged her."</p>

<p>"My friends and companions," responded Mr. Ryder, "I thank
you, one and all.  It is the answer I expected, for I knew your
hearts."</p>
<p>He turned and walked toward the closed door of an adjoining
room, while every eye followed him in wondering curiosity.  He came
back in a moment, leading by the hand his visitor of the afternoon, who
stood startled and trembling at the sudden plunge into this scene of
brilliant gayety.  She was neatly dressed in gray, and wore the white cap
of an elderly woman.</p>
<p>"Ladies and gentlemen," he said, "this is the woman, and I am the
man, whose story I have told you.  Permit me to introduce to you the
wife of my youth." </p>
<p>                                   <hi rend="italic">Charles W. Chesnutt</hi></p>


</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

