<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="ChoRegr"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="ChoRegr">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Regret.</title>
<title type="sort">regret</title>
<author>Chopin, Kate</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">13</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">ChoRegr</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475820</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Regret.</title>
<title type="sort">regret</title>
<author>Kate Chopin</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>e.g. Editor / Translator / Annotator</resp>
<name/>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>Edition information, e.g. 1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Century Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1895">1895</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>The Century Illustrated Monthly Magazine:
50 (n.s. 28) (May 1895): 147-49.</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Copy consulted: AP2.C4 1895 Alderman Library</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1895">1895</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction, prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-05">May 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Lorrie Chisholm, Electronic Text Center, University of
Virginia Library System.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Minimal TEI tagging, ran electronic spell-check and removed
unambiguous line-end hyphenation.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
 <text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="147"/>
<head>REGRET.</head>

<p>MAMZELLE AUR&Eacute;LIE possessed a good strong figure, ruddy cheeks,
hair that was changing from brown to gray, and a determined eye.
She wore a man's hat about the farm, and an old blue army overcoat
when it was cold, and sometimes top-boots.
</p><p>Mamzelle Aur&eacute;lie had never thought of marrying.  She had
never been in love.  At the age of twenty she had received a
proposal, which she had promptly declined, and at the age of fifty
she had not yet lived to regret it.
</p><p>So she was quite alone in the world, except for her dog Ponto,
and the negroes who lived in her cabins and worked her crops, and
the fowls, a few cows, a couple of mules, her gun (with which she
shot chicken-hawks), and her religion.
</p><p>One morning Mamzelle Aur&eacute;lie stood upon her gallery,
contemplating, with arms akimbo, a small band of very small
children who, to all intents and purposes, might have fallen from
the clouds, so unexpected and bewildering was their coming, and so
unwelcome.  They were the children of her nearest neighbor, Odile,
who was not such a near neighbor, after all.
</p><p>The young woman had appeared but five minutes before,
accompanied by these four children.  In her arms she carried little
&Eacute;lodie; she dragged Ti Nomme by an unwilling hand; while
Marc&eacute;line and Marc&eacute;lette followed with irresolute steps.
</p><p>Her face was red and disfigured from tears and excitement.
She had been summoned to a neighboring parish by the dangerous
illness of her mother; her husband was away in Texas&mdash;it seemed to
her a million miles away; and Valsin was waiting with the mule-cart
to drive her to the station.
</p><p>"It's no question, Mamzelle Aur&eacute;lie; you jus' got to keep
those youngsters fo' me tell I come back.  <hi rend="italic">Dieu sait</hi>, I
wouldn' botha you with 'em if it was any otha way to do!  Make 'em
mine you, Mamzelle Aur&eacute;lie; don' spare 'em.  Me, there, I'm half
crazy between the chil'ren, an' L&eacute;on not home, an' maybe not even
to fine po' <hi rend="italic">maman</hi> alive <hi rend="italic">encore!"</hi>&mdash;a harrowing

<pb n="148"/>
possibility which drove Odile to take a final hasty and convulsive
leave of her disconsolate family.
</p><p>She left them crowded into the narrow strip of shade on the
porch of the long, low house; the white sunlight was beating in on
the white old boards; some chickens were scratching in the grass at
the foot of the steps, and one had boldly mounted, and was stepping
heavily, solemnly, and aimlessly across the gallery.  There was a
pleasant odor of pinks in the air, and the sound of negroes'
laughter was coming across the flowering cotton-field.
</p><p>Mamzelle Aur&eacute;lie stood contemplating the children.  She
looked with a critical eye upon Marc&eacute;line, who had been left
staggering beneath the weight of the chubby &Eacute;lodie.  She surveyed
with the same calculating air Marc&eacute;lette mingling her silent tears
with the audible grief and rebellion of Ti Nomme.  During those few
contemplative moments she was collecting herself, determining upon
a line of action which should be identical with a line of duty.
She began by feeding them.
</p><p>If Mamzelle Aur&eacute;lie's responsibilities might have begun and
ended there, they could easily have been dismissed; for her larder
was amply provided against an emergency of this nature.  But little
children are not little pigs: they require and demand attentions
which were wholly unexpected by Mamzelle Aur&eacute;lie, and which she
was ill prepared to give.
</p><p>She was, indeed, very inapt in her management of Odile's
children during the first few days.  How could she know that
Marc&eacute;lette always wept when spoken to in a loud and commanding
tone of voice?  It was a peculiarity of Marc&eacute;lette's.  She became
acquainted with Ti Nomme's passion for flowers only when he had
plucked all the choicest gardenias and pinks for the apparent
purpose of critically studying their botanical construction.
</p><p>"'T ain't enough to tell 'im, Mamzelle Aur&eacute;lie," Marc&eacute;line
instructed her; "you got to tie 'im in a chair.  It's w'at
<hi rend="italic">maman</hi> all time do w'en he's bad: she tie 'im in a chair."
The chair in which Mamzelle Aur&eacute;lie tied Ti Nomme was roomy and
comfortable, and he seized the opportunity to take a nap in it, the
afternoon being warm.
</p><p>At night, when she ordered them one and all to bed as she
would have shooed the chickens into the hen-house, they stayed
uncomprehending before her.  What about the little white nightgowns
that had to be taken from the pillow-slip in which they were
brought over, and shaken by some strong hand till they snapped like
ox-whips?  What about the tub of water which had to be brought and
set in the middle of the floor, in which the little tired, dusty,
sun-browned feet had every one to be washed sweet and clean?  And
it made Marc&eacute;line and Marc&eacute;lette laugh merrily&mdash;the idea that
Mamzelle Aur&eacute;lie should for a moment have believed that Ti Nomme
could fall asleep without being told the story of Croque-mitaine or
Loup-garou, or both; or that &Eacute;lodie could fall asleep at all
without being rocked and sung to.
</p><p>"I tell you, Aunt Ruby," Mamzelle Aur&eacute;lie informed her cook
in confidence; "me, I'd rather manage a dozen plantation' than fo'
chil'ren.  It's <hi rend="italic">terrassent!  Bont&eacute;!</hi> don't talk to me about
chil'ren!"
</p><p>"T ain' ispected sich as you would know airy thing 'bout 'em,
Mamzelle Aur&eacute;lie.  I see dat plainly yistiddy w'en I spy dat li'le
chile playin' wid yo' baskit o' keys.  You don' know dat makes
chillun grow up hard-headed, to play wid keys?  Des like it make
'em teeth hard to look in a lookin'-glass.  Them's the things you
got to know in the raisin' an' manigement o' chillun."
</p><p>Mamzelle Aur&eacute;lie certainly did not pretend or aspire to such
subtle and far-reaching knowledge on the subject as Aunt Ruby
possessed, who had "raised five an' bared [buried] six" in her day.
She was glad enough to learn a few little mother-tricks to serve
the moment's need.
</p><p>Ti Nomme's sticky fingers compelled her to unearth white
aprons that she had not worn for years, and she had to accustom
herself to his moist kisses&mdash;the expressions of an affectionate and
exuberant nature.  She got down her sewing-basket, which she seldom
used, from the top shelf of the armoire, and placed it within the
ready and easy reach which torn slips and buttonless waists
demanded.  It took her some days to become accustomed to the
laughing, the crying, the chattering that echoed through the house
and around it all day long.  And it was not the first or the second
night that she could sleep comfortably with little &Eacute;lodie's hot,
plump body pressed close against her, and the little one's warm
breath beating her cheek like the fanning of a bird's wing.
</p><p>But at the end of two weeks Mamzelle Aur&eacute;lie had grown quite
used to these things, and she no longer complained.
</p><p>It was also at the end of two weeks that Mamzelle Aur&eacute;lie,
one evening, looking away toward the crib where the cattle were
being fed, saw Valsin's blue cart turning the bend of the road.
Odile sat beside the mulatto, upright and alert.  As they drew
near, the young woman's beaming face indicated that her home-coming
was a happy one.
</p><p>But this coming, unannounced and unexpected, threw Mamzelle
Aur&eacute;lie into a flutter that was almost agitation.  The children
had to be gathered.  Where was Ti Nomme?  Yonder in the shed,
putting an edge on his knife

<pb n="149"/>
at the grindstone.  And
Marc&eacute;line and Marc&eacute;lette?  Cutting and fashioning doll-rags in
the corner of the gallery.  As for &Eacute;lodie, she was safe enough in
Mamzelle Aur&eacute;lie's arms; and she had screamed with delight at
sight of the familiar blue cart which was bringing her mother back
to her.

</p><p>THE excitement was all over, and they were gone.  How still it
was when they were gone!  Mamzelle Aur&eacute;lie stood upon the gallery,
looking and listening.  She could no longer see the cart; the red
sunset and the blue-gray twilight had together flung a purple mist
across the fields and road that hid it from her view.  She could no
longer hear the wheezing and creaking of its wheels.  But she could
still faintly hear the shrill, glad voices of the children.
</p><p>She turned into the house.  There was much work awaiting her,
for the children had left a sad disorder behind them; but she did
not at once set about the task of righting it.  Mamzelle Aur&eacute;lie
seated herself beside the table.  She gave one slow glance through
the room, into which the evening shadows were creeping and
deepening around her solitary figure.  She let her head fall down
upon her bended arm, and began to cry.  Oh, but she cried!  Not
softly, as women often do.  She cried like a man, with sobs that
seemed to tear her very soul.  She did not notice Ponto licking her
hand.</p>
<signed><hi rend="italic">Kate Chopin.</hi></signed>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
