<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CosInst"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="CosInst">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"Instead of an Article : About Pittsburg and, Incidentally, about Editing a Magazine"</title>
<title type="sort">instead of an article about pittsburg and, incidentally about editing a magazine</title>
<author>Cosegrave, John O`Hara ; Nordman, J. Jerome ; Whitlock, Brand</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Charles Keller</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">33</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CosInst</idno>
<date value="2000">2000</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2000 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475835</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Instead of an Article: About Pittsburg and, Incidentally, about Editing a Magazine</title>
<title level="j">Everybody`s Magazine</title>
<title type="sort">instead of an article about pittsburg and, incidentally about editing a magazine</title>
<author>John O`Hara Cosgrave ; J. Jerome Nordman ; Brand Whitlock</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>6 Pages</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Ridgeway company</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1910-08">August, 1910</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Alderman Library, University of Virginia AP2 .E9 v.23 1910</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1910-08">August, 1910</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2000-01">January, 2000</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Samuel Turner, The Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="209"/>
<head>INSTEAD OF AN ARTICLE<lb/>
About Pittsburg and, Incidentally,<lb/>
about Editing a Magazine</head>

<div2 type="section" id="d4">


<p>Important articles in magazines of the type
of "COLLIER'S," "MCCLURE'S," the "AMERICAN,"
and "EVERYBODY'S," like plays,
are rewritten rather than written. Too begin
with, there must be the idea, then to find the
man or woman best able to embody it. That
settled, the author must steep himself in his
subject. When he acquires mastery, his
findings are written down and submitted to
the editor. This may take months; it often
requires years.
</p>
<p>It has happened that the editor did not
know what he wanted until he read this first
draft. Now he has the subject spread before
him by an authority. His associates all read
it and criticise. Sometimes that first draft is
flawless, but most often it is returned to the
author with direction for reconstruction. The
process may be repeated half a dozen times.
Finally the manuscript is satisfactory, which
means that it is valuable, simply expressed,
and readable. It is in shape for publication.
It is put into type and sent around to outside
experts who are the representative authorities
on the subject.
</p>
<p>In these days a magazine can afford to have
its conclusions disputed, but its facts must be
incontrovertible. Perhaps the trouble the
big publications take to be right&mdash;and that
means square and just, as well as accurate&mdash;
explains such prestige and influence as they
now enjoy in America.
</p>
<p>At a women's club gathering in Mississippi,
recently, Harris Dickson told his audience
something about an article of his that had
recently appeared in "EVERYBODY'S." He
explained that a manuscript written by another
man had been sent him to put in shape. The
facts were there, and the moral, but the
treatment was technical. It lacked carrying
power. Dickson knew nothing of the other
author, and so proceeded to get up the subject
at first hand. He took not one of the
facts for granted. After three months he
returned the revised manuscript to the magazine.
It was sent back, with specific directions
for rewriting. In due course he again
remailed it to the editor, who congratulated
him on his achievement&mdash;for that is what it
was. Then the article, having attained a
satisfactory form (it was on Fraternal
Insurance), was sent round among the experts.
The first man who read it was a high official
of one of the old line insurance companies,
but a hearty believer in the fraternal system.
He returned it with approval and an elaborate
criticism. Then it was submitted to the
chief insurance commissioner of a western
state&mdash;the undoubted political authority on
the subject. The approval and criticisms of
both men, with the manuscript, were again
forwarded to Mr. Dickson. The necessary
corrections having been incorporated, the
manuscript was ready for the printer. To
make assurance doubly sure, proofs were sent
out to prominent officials of leading fraternal
organizations, who returned them with
most commendatory letters. And then, and
only then, did it appear in the magazine.
</p>
<p>Mr. Dickson's audience, doubtless under
the impression that magazines are produced
by editors out of the contributions sent them
by mail, expressed surprise that so much time,
effort, and money should be devoted to what
seemed a comparatively unimportant subject.
Yet it involved a matter that concerned five
million men and their families, and a tremendous
controversy. Its appearance has made
the controversy even keener, and of course
the enemies of sanity and good order in
fraternalism are now hurling bolts at us.
However, when we have done our part and
know we are right, we stay put.
</p>
<p>Mr. Dickson told part of what to us is a
familiar story. In this instance he knew
nothing of the time and trouble the author
and ourselves had taken just to get together
the facts and place them in the right perspective.
We began on this particular article in
November, 1906, and during the interval it

<pb n="210"/>

was being worked at or over by one of some
dozen men. The same is true of most of our
big series. "The Woman's Invasion" represented
two and a half years of work. Fifteen
months elapsed between the delivery of Judge
Lindsey's first manuscript and the beginning
of publication in the magazine. Trained
writers, the best men we know about, are out
investigating and gathering the facts for the
articles we will print a year hence. This is the
process of magazine making to-day. It is not
peculiar to "EVERYBODY'S"; it is the rule
with "COLLIER'S," "MCCLURE'S," the
AMERICAN, and SUCCESS."</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" id="d5">
<head>INSTEAD OF AN ARTICLE</head>

<p>This is all by way of introduction to the
story of an article that was not written.
About the time the Pittsburg flare-up began
to show itself in the papers, it occurred to us
that some exposition of the situation there
would be of value and interest to our readers.
Before going about it, we debated it very carefully.
Some of us in the office (and this magazine
is edited by all of us) were fairly familiar
with the subject, and we believed it would
subserve no useful purpose to tackle it along
the "Shame of the Cities" lines. We agreed
that the way to approach Pittsburg was to
consider what had happened there, not as a
sporadic outburst, but as an economic
symptom. Whom could we get that was far
enough from the controversies involved to
treat the subject objectively and with a big
perspective? Brand Whitlock. The Mayor
of Toledo knows more about cities and their
governments, and the evils that arise within
them, than any other man, and he can write
&mdash;with knowledge, with sympathy, with clarity.
Also he knew Pittsburg. So we telegraphed
to find if he was free to write an article,
and, when he replied in the affirmative,
the following letter was sent him:</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="letter" id="d6">

<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1910-04-01">April 1, 1910.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>
<name type="person">DEAR MR. WHITLOCK:</name>
</salute>
</opener>

<p>The article we want is on Pittsburg. It
is neither our purpose nor our desire merely
to "muckrake" Pittsburg or any other city.
The eruption there is typical of similar
conditions in other great civic centers throughout
the country, and it seems to us it might be
made the text of a diagnosis of the whole
municipal problem in America.
</p>
<p>Here are a few thoughts that occur to me
which might be represented:
</p>
<p>We have come to realize that the real
trouble in our country is Privilege. Big business,
in its ruthless pursuit of results, has the
ultimate responsibility for the ills that
confront us in political, social, and commercial
life. The graft scandals, the bank defalcations,
etc., are simply symptoms of internal
disorders. They are the eruptions of the disease.
</p>
<p>Pittsburg might be called the typical get-rich-quick community. Its great wealth is
based on the abundant coal and iron with
which the Creator loaded its environment.
Down on those deposits fasten thousands of
Americans seized with the mania of money-making. They coin the coal and iron into
millions. They work feverishly; they work
their men furiously. It's a mad, frenzied
scramble for success and sensation. To get
rich quicker, they exact excessive protection
from Congress&mdash;first to prop up infant
industries, then to consolidate abnormal profits.
If the government undertakes to deny their
demands, they bluster first, then intrigue,
then intimidate. Mills are closed down; the
"prosperity" of the country is threatened,
lobbies are organized, corruption funds
subscribed, until Congress succumbs and new
"jokers" are written into steel tariffs.
</p>
<p>In the meantime a huge city is upreared.
But this city is run for the benefit of its
industries, not for the comfort of its inhabitants.
Street railway, gas, electric corporations
are organized, ostensibly to serve the
community, actually enabling a greedy group
to make more money. Again, what cannot be
gained by request is won by force and guile.
</p>
<p>Over and over again the various processes
are repeated, until you have built up a sort
of City Monstrous, dedicated to machinery,
in which all the men and many of the women
are just machines, and there is no ideal save
that of feverish industrial adventure and
accomplishment. Power&mdash;blind, ruthless,
marvel-working, bending backs and bodies to its
will&mdash;is Pittsburg's god, and Success its
divine attribute Success that spells Gold, the
instrument of exploitation and sensation.
What wonder that weaker men, confronted by
the colossal rewards of industrial conquest,
are frenzied with the gold fever? In the
absence of communal patriotism, graft becomes
an incident. Graft and greed are the minor
watchwords of success. Get money, anyway&mdash;
but get it. Is it surprising that cashiers graft,
that aldermen graft, that city officials graft,
that there's a very pandemonium of graft?
Isn't it the way the other fellows get rich?
<pb n="211"/>
</p>
<p>All of a sudden the poison clogs the pores,
and the infection blotches the surface&mdash;and
every one is horrified. The great manufacturers,
the great merchants, the great lawyers&mdash;
high priests of the Power God&mdash;throw up their
hands. Can such things be? Dreadful,
horrible!&mdash;blindly oblivious of their own
responsibility for the epidemic.
</p>
<p>More startling still to the conquerors were
the pitiless revelations of the <hi rend="italic">Survey</hi>, exhibiting
in mathematical terms the cost to the
human factor of this monstrous material
success. Hordes of anaemic, emaciated men and
women, exhausted by long hours of toil, piled
thick in wretched hovels, underfed, half-clothed, dragging out a miserable existence
unrelieved by leisure or rest or recreation&mdash;
the Juggernaut toll of efficiency&mdash;of the passion
for results at any price. Against this
horror, what avails Pittsburg's panorama of
splendid churches, of lordly palaces, of noble
art museums, of great orchestras, richly
endowed educational institutions&mdash;the
patriotic tribute of the conquerors to
civilization? What is this boasted civilization
of ours worth&mdash;not Pittsburg's only, for
Pittsburg is an incident&mdash;if it be reared on
the wrecked and depleted bodies of men at
its base?
</p>
<p>There would then be the opportunity in the
article to suggest the regenerated Pittsburg&mdash;
all this furious energy hitherto devoted to
material success turned to social betterment
and decent government. The turn of the
worker comes. The conquerors, having
learned that they cannot take greedily what
belongs to a community, and find happiness,
turn magnificently to the rescue of their own
downtrodden. The old question&mdash;what does it
profit a man if he gains the whole world and
loses his soul?&mdash;has been burned into Pittsburg
humanity once again.
</p>
<p>For several years the newspapers have
carried stories about these successive scandals
in Pittsburg, until people have in a
measure become confused as to how they
connect, whether all are really parts of
the same story. I doubt if the average
man who reads the article in the morning
paper has a clear grasp of what has been
going on, and he can't discover it without
hunting back through the files. Once we
published an article by Owen Wister about
the Capitol frauds in Pennsylvania, after the
newspapers had been printing countless columns
on the subject for months, and it was
one of the most successful articles we have
used, because of the way it crystallized and
interpreted the whole occurrence.
</p>
<p>A similar service is here suggested. Write
the story of Pittsburg dramatically; crystallize
the big exposures of the last few years through
which bankers and politicians have been going
to prison, culminating with the present
crisis in the City Council; bring out the
economic significance of these occurrences to
Pittsburg, to the United States. Such an
article will help all of us to see where we are
"at," will help develop civic consciousness in
New York, Chicago, San Francisco. It is
immensely well worth doing.
</p>
<p>I'm not dictating your article. What is
written here is purely suggestive. You must
tell what you see and find in your own way.
You will, anyway. You know most of the
facts. You are in touch with the balance.
We'll help to get material. If you will, you
can put up an article that the country will
read. We'd like copy as soon as possible.
</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute><lb/>
<signed><name type="person">J. O'H. COSGRAVE,
                                   Editor.
</name>
</signed>
</closer>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" id="d7">

<p>Mr. Whitlock, replied, expressing willingness
to handle the subject along the lines indicated,
and asked for whatever assistance we
could render him. William Hard, a member
of our editorial force, had spent some time in
Pittsburg, acquiring material for his "Woman's
Invasion," and he recommended J. J.
Nordman, a reporter of that city, as the best
man to equip Mr. Whitlock with the historical
details of the exposure. He would thus have
immediately a succinct, up-to-date statement
of the case for his use as a skeleton.
</p>
<p>Mr. Nordman was willing to help, and
soon after got into communication with Mr.
Whitlock. Here is an account of his service,
which was accompanied by a letter from District
Attorney Blakeley, certifying to his reliability
and knowledge of the facts.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="letter" id="d8">

<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1910-05-10">May 10, 1910.</date>
<name type="person">HON. BRAND WHITLOCK, Toledo, Ohio.
</name>
</dateline>
<salute>
Dear Sir:
</salute>
</opener>

<p>Mr. Cosgrave has asked me to forward you
matter bearing on the Pittsburg graft expos&eacute; and such
clippings as I may have.
</p>
<p>I shall weave the facts together with no effort
towards literary form, but rather in letter form, and
present it to you not later than Monday next.
</p>
<p>Enclosed please find what I have termed a
"Retrospect," being a review of the political conditions
leading to and making possible the present expos&eacute;.
</p>
<p>Such clippings as I have will be forwarded with
matter. I enclose letter from Mr. Blakeley.
</p>


<closer>
<salute>
Very respectfully,
</salute>
<signed><name type="person">
J. JEROME NORDMAN.</name>
</signed>
</closer>

<pb n="212"/>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" id="d9">


<p>After that we waited, rather impatiently,
it must be confessed, for Whitlock's manuscript.
After the passage of other admonitory
letters and telegrams, we received the following
letter. We print it "instead of an article."
In our opinion, it is an extraordinarily valuable
summary of the whole subject of municipal
misrule. It goes far and beyond Pittsburg,
and deep into economic, social, and
national conditions of which that city is but
an instance and an illustration. And, moreover,
it sets forth just how such an article,
could we find the right man to do it, should
be written. Here it is:
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="letter" id="d10">


<opener>
<dateline>
<name type="place">
Executive Offices<lb/>
THE CITY OF TOLEDO</name>
<date value="1910-06-03">3 June, 1910.</date>
<name type="person">
JOHN O'HARA COSGRAVE, Esquire,<lb/>
Editor EVERYBODY'S MAGAZINE.</name>
</dateline>
<salute>
DEAR MR. COSGRAVE:
</salute>
</opener>


<p>The Pittsburg story is big, too big and too
important and too significant to do at second
hand. I have had a valuable correspondence
with Mr. Nordman, and he has most kindly
put his information, and in clear form, at my
disposal. He has sent me his scrapbook of
newspaper clippings, and he has written me
at length and in detail of the various exposures
and prosecutions. I have made inquiries,
too, from friends, and I have been
thinking over the story that you propose.
But it won't go, and I have concluded that it
ought not to go in that form; and that is the
only form in which it is possible for me now
to tell it.
</p>

<p>I find just what I expected to find, or I find
the familiar symptoms of what I expected to
find. The intelligent answers to the several
questions I put to Mr. Nordman after our
first few letters are exactly what I expected
them to be. One city is all cities; and all
exhibit the same effects, proceeding from the
same causes. Look about you, anywhere,
and if you see graft, and bribery, and corruption,
you'll find a bi-partisan machine controlling
nominations and elections to municipal
offices, and representing the few who consider
themselves privileged to exploit the
people by means of franchises in public
utilities, etc. It's as easy as it is for a physician
to tell what ails a sallow and emaciated
Southern "cracker" who shivers with chills
one day, and burns up with fever the next.
</p>

<p>And so, in Pittsburg, I found the usual
Republican machine with its big boss, the
usual Democratic machine and its little boss,
and the two, as usual, working together, the
Democratic boss and his tools rewarded by a
few small offices on "bi-partisan" boards,
and the like; then the street railway system
and other public utility corporations which
these bosses represent, and for which they
procure franchises. And after this, the "better
element," the "eminently respectable"
citizens, supporting this combination, enjoying
the fruits of its labor, and influencing the
business interests of the city in the way that
gives such perfect exemplification of the evils
of class government in our cities&mdash;the same,
old, sordid story.
</p>

<p>The revelations, as they are called&mdash;though
by this time they should have ceased to be
revelations, and have become "recognitions"
in this country&mdash;made by the newspaper clippings
before me are the expected indications
of the deeper, underlying causes. The superficial
observer sees in them merely a corrupt
council; and, from the fact that councilmen
have taken bribes, he makes the daring
deduction that some one gave them the bribes;
he sees that councilmen have been grafting,
and then is na&iuml;vely astonished by the revelation
that some business men higher up, although
not very much higher up, have been caught
and publicly disgraced. He sees, too, a
brave and fearless prosecutor who is sending
these men to prison; and there are the usual
predictions that out of all this there is to come
to Pittsburg "good" government&mdash;that is,
government by honest men, to be aided, perhaps,
by the adoption of the commission
plan. That is to say, we have here the
subject only in its personal aspect, and not in its
institutional, sociological, economic aspect.
</p>

<div3 type="part" id="d11">
<head>THE SAME OLD STORY OF GRAFT</head>

<p>Now, to be frank, the story of the grafting
doesn't interest me much, though it is as saddening
and depressing as ever; and I can't
work up enough enthusiasm for that feature of
it to write anything that would be worth your
while to print, or worth anybody's while to
read. Toward the subject I feel the same
apathy that was felt toward the ordinary
newspaper account of some casualty by
Thoreau, who would not read, as you will
remember, the accounts&mdash;for example&mdash;of
crimes and accidents, because, having once
grasped the principle, he felt it unnecessary
to multiply, indefinitely, instances of that
principle. The story of Pittsburg, so far as it
has been related to me, is merely the old,
<pb n="213"/>
squalid story of municipal graft. I have the
names and the dates in an orderly and logical
way&mdash;who were sent to the penitentiary, and
when, and for what particular crime, and
what the judge said in pronouncing sentence,
etc. All of this has been told over and over
and over again in the newspapers and magazines
during the last few years; the only
difference lies in the names and the dates and
the place. Indeed, Pittsburg's story in this
respect is hardly as interesting as the old
stories&mdash;it is, if anything, more commonplace,
more squalid.
</p>
<p>But behind all this, there is, of course, a
story, and a big one, as you unerringly divined.
Reading between the lines of the dry
recital of facts with which I have been
provided, and peering a little way behind the
scenes, I come, I think, upon the real story,
the one that some one should write, the one
that some one should print.
</p>
<p>The first chapter, perhaps, is the story of
the old political machines in Pittsburg, and of
that interesting, and&mdash;in certain elemental,
human senses&mdash;strong personality, Chris
Magee, the boss&mdash;who has a monument.
</p>
<p>Then, there is another personality, of a
different sort, in Blakeley, the district attorney.
My accounts are meager and bald, and yet
I catch glimpses of a striking personality.
This district attorney, I should imagine, is a
man with the best ideals of the legal profession,
honest, capable, sincere, and unafraid;
a man, withal, who knows life and politics and
can play the game without being soiled in its
many contacts. What draws me to him,
even at this distance, is that he seems to have
little of the Puritan in him, as there is too apt
to be in prosecutors who convict, and push
their victims within prison doors. And he is
another chapter of the story. But I don't
know Blakeley; I can't describe him, I can't
interpret him, and I haven't the time nor the
opportunity just now to become acquainted
with him.
</p>
<p>Then there is the story of the organization
of the Civic League, or whatever they call it,
and especially the story of its operations.
These good citizens, it seems, hired a detective
to come and run their men down for them. To
me the private detective is not the most inspiring
and heroic figure on our modern scene; but
that is neither here nor there. One of these
detectives evidently has not only ability but
versatility, and in an interesting manner
combines the occupation of a detective with the
profession of an evangelist. It was not,
however, he who worked the old panel game&mdash;
much as a black paramour might work it
down in the Tenderloin&mdash;on certain councilmen,
led them into a trap, and then exposed
them&mdash;an achievement in confused morals
that has not been permitted to go unapplauded.
There are those, of course, in every
city who could think fondly and smugly of
themselves as doing, in this way, pre&euml;minently
the will of God; and such deeds not infrequently
make men self-righteous.
</p>
<p>But, of course, I may be mistaken about
the present application of this generalization,
and, as I should like to be just, or, what is
better, to be charitable, I should hesitate, on
such unsupported conclusions, to write it
down for the public eye. There are, of
course, those who with logic can justify the
larger end by the smaller means, and thus
excuse certain deviations from the straight
line of the moral ideal, and thereby hold one
back from the temptation to divide his moral
indignation about equally between pursuer
and pursued. But, if he claimed one's sympathy
for the pursuers, he could not prevent one's
pity from going to the ruined councilmen.
</p>
</div3>

<div3 type="part" id="d12">
<head> THE SHOCK TO CARNEGIE</head>

<p>But beyond all this&mdash;and here I think I
touch on the real story&mdash;there is the peculiar
temper and tendency of Pittsburg. Pittsburg
is an artistic center; fortunes have been
lavished in endowing schools and universities
and palaces for art, on symphonies and
oratorios. All the expressions of a new, ruling
plutocracy are easily discernible here, as in
all such epochs of society recorded in history;
just, for instance, as Ferrero describes them
in the last phases of the Roman Republic.
And when Carnegie returns, he sheds tears
and wrings his hands because of the corruption
that has been exposed, and he fails, as
many in Pittsburg seem to fail, to note the
necessary, if subtle, relation that must exist
between all this corruption and debauchery
between all this art and music, and&mdash;shall I
say?&mdash;the tariff on steel.
</p>
<p>This, however, isn't all; though this is part.
Pittsburg is a moral town; the most moral, in
the conventional sense, in all America. She
won't even allow the kids to play baseball on
a back lot on Sunday. A woman, an old
friend of mine who lives in Pittsburg, said:
"I think it very unfortunate that the <hi rend="italic">Survey</hi>
was published. It overlooks Pittsburg's good
points. For instance, Pittsburg has more
<pb n="214"/>
churches than any city of its size in America.
More people of our class go to church than in
any place I ever saw; more money is given to
charity. People just pour out of their houses
and into the churches on Sunday morning."
She was quite serious&mdash;and she expressed
Pittsburg, or the ruling class of Pittsburg,
exactly.
</p>
<p>Now I don't mean to say that Pittsburg is
especially hypocritical; but she does seem to
be pharisaical. The article about Pittsburg
should find its beginnings, perhaps, away
back in the days of scholasticism, and come
down through the moss hags of Scotland; and
its title should be "Pious Pittsburg," or
something like that. Written properly&mdash;if I am
right&mdash;it would be an eloquent exposition of
phariseeism at its apotheosis.
</p>
</div3>

<div3 type="part" id="d13">
<head>THE REAL STORY OF PITTSBURG</head>

<p>Now I can't write this, because I haven't
the evidence to prove what I see, or think I
see. All I have is the mere outline&mdash;and the
outline applies, as I have said, to most cities.
What one should have is the color, the detail,
the thousand and one little things in the way
of personality&mdash;you know what I mean; all
that which is necessary to "lend artistic
verisimilitude to an otherwise bald and
unconvincing narrative." (I wish I were in
New York to-night! I'd go to the Casino and
see the revival of "The Mikado.") The
Pittsburg story can't be written, and it should
not be written, without this; and to do it
properly one would have to spend much time
in Pittsburg and become saturated with the
atmosphere of the place; and when he
emerged, if he ever did emerge, he would be
ready to undertake this rather stupendous
study in psychology. I do not feel at all
equipped for this task, and no amount of
material without the personal contact could
equip me for this service. With my material,
I could only write the old and squalid story
of a rather commonplace exposure of
municipal grafting, and that wouldn't be worth
while.
</p>
<p>The story of Pittsburg would be all that the
story of any city is&mdash;as I have indicated: the
bi-partisan machine, the public service
corporation, etc.&mdash;but it would be more. It
would illustrate the curious effects of long
acceptance of cold, intellectual theories in place
of religion, and how this develops the ability
to separate morals and manners; how one's
theology needn't interfere with one's religion,
and all that. It would be the story of the
union of politics and business; and the trail
would lead up to those proud and insolent
aristocracies that are founded on the purchase
of the privilege of making the laws, and
down to those stews of horror where they pay
for the privilege of breaking the laws. It
would be the story of Chris Magee, the good-natured, human boss; of Blakeley, the upright
prosecutor; of the methods of hired
detectives and the corruption of officialdom.
Pittsburg has riches, art, organized charity,
and piety; but she lacks wealth, beauty,
social justice, and religion. And sending the
"bad" to prison, and electing the "good" to
office, and changing the paper charters of the
city, are not going to work any real reform.
They think they'll get "good government"
and "civic righteousness," and then their
problems will be solved. This is what they
propose to do; this is all they tell us now, and
I can't write a story on that. The story
would be as futile as little legal reforms.
</p>
<p>It is, however, consoling and inspiring to
believe&mdash;yes, to know&mdash;that there are in Pittsburg&mdash;
as in all cities&mdash;hundreds of thousands
of decent, virtuous, wholesome, toiling people;
that these make up by far the larger part of
the population, too, and that they will save
Pittsburg, and make her as good as she is
great. It is a fact stimulating to the imagination
and encouraging to the soul that, in all
these stores and shops and mills, there are
hard-working, modest, unknown thousands
who are pure and loyal, who are humanity's
hope; that even the most stunted and abused
figures out of the <hi rend="italic">Survey</hi> give more promise
than that class which rides upon their backs
and devours them as it rides.
</p>
<p>Good government, efficient government, if
by those phrases is meant, as is usually meant,
government by the "good"&mdash;whoever they
may be!&mdash;and the efficient, will not do; it will
avail nothing to Pittsburg or to any city, to
substitute for grafters, great or petty,
personally honest men who will legally give away
franchises for nothing, instead of bartering
them illegally for big bribes. Pittsburg can't
be saved by an aristocracy of the better element,
she can be saved only by democracy&mdash;
with a very little "d." And she will be saved
that way some day, never fear, though not
until all the other cities are similarly saved.
</p>
<p>I shall await with interest what you think
of my suggestions.</p>
</div3>
<closer>
<salute>Your ever sincere friend,
</salute>
<signed>
<name type="person">BRAND WHITLOCK.</name>
</signed>
</closer>
</div2>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
