<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CraFlan"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="CraFlan">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Flanagan and His Short Filibustering Adventure.</title>
<title type="sort">flanagan and his short filibustering adventure</title>
<author>Crane, Stephen, 1871-1900</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">37</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CraFlan</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475841</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Flanagan and His Short Filibustering Adventure.</title>
<title type="sort">flanagan and his short filibustering adventure</title>
<author>Stephen Crane.</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The S. S. McClure Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1897">1897</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">McClure's Magazine</hi> 9 (Oct. 1897): 1045-1052.</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1897">1897</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-12">December 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Deirdre Johnson, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header added, basic TEI markup added.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">



<body id="d2">
	
	<div1 type="story" id="d3">
	
<pb n="1045"/>
<head>FLANAGAN<lb/>
AND HIS SHORT FILIBUSTERING ADVENTURE.<lb/>
BY STEPHEN CRANE,<lb/>
 Author of "The Red Badge of Courage," "The Third Violet," etc.</head>


<div2 type="chapter" n="1" id="d4">
<head>I.</head>
<p>
"I HAVE got twenty men at me back who will fight to the death,"
said the warrior to the old filibuster.
</p><p>"And they can be blowed for all me," replied the old
filibuster.  "Common as sparrows.  Cheap as cigarettes.  Show me
twenty men with steel clamps on their mouths, with holes in their
heads where memory ought to be, and I want 'em.  But twenty brave
men, merely?  I'd rather have twenty brave onions."
</p><p>Thereupon the warrior removed sadly, feeling that no salaams
were paid to valor in these days of mechanical excellence.
</p><p>Valor, in truth, is no bad thing to have when filibustering,
but many medals are to be won by the man who knows not the meaning
of pow-wow, before or afterwards.  Twenty brave men with tongues
hung lightly may make trouble rise from the ground like smoke from
grass because of their subsequent fiery pride, whereas twenty cow-eyed villains who accept unrighteous and far-compelling kicks as
they do the rain of heaven may halo the ultimate history of an
expedition with gold and plentifully bedeck their names, winning
forty years of gratitude from patriots, simply by remaining silent.
As for the cause, it may be only that they have no friends or other
credulous furniture.
</p><p>If it were not for the curse of the swinging tongue, it is
surely to be said that the filibustering industry, flourishing now
in the United States, would be pie.  Under correct conditions, it
is merely a matter of dealing with some little detectives whose
skill at search is rated by those who pay them at a value of twelve
or twenty dollars each week.  It is nearly axiomatic that normally
a twelve-dollar-per-week detective cannot defeat a one-hundred-thousand-dollar filibustering excursion.  Against the criminal the
detective represents the commonwealth; but in this other case he
represents his desire to show cause why his salary should be paid.
He represents himself, merely, and he counts no more than a
grocer's clerk.
</p><p>But the pride of the successful filibuster often smites him
and his cause like an ax, and men who have not confided in their
mothers go prone with him.  It can make the dome of the Capitol
tremble and incite the Senators to overturning benches.  It can
increase the salaries of detectives who could not detect the
location of a pain in the chest.  It is a wonderful thing, this
pride.
</p><p>Filibustering was once such a simple game.  It was managed
blandly by gentle captains and smooth and undisturbed gentlemen who
at other times dealt in the law, soap, medicine, and bananas.  It
was a great pity that the little cote of doves in Washington was
obliged to rustle officially, and naval men were kept from their
berths at night, and sundry custom-house people got wiggings, all
because the returned adventurer pow-wowed in his pride.  A yellow
and red banner would have been long since smothered in a shame of
defeat if a contract to filibuster had been let to some admirable
organization like one of our trusts.
</p><p>And yet the game is not obsolete.  It is still played by the
wise and the silent, men whose names are not display-typed and
blathered from one end of the country to the other.
</p><p>There is in mind now a man who knew one side of a fence from
the other side when he looked sharply.  They were hunting for
captains then to command the first vessels of what has since become
a famous little fleet.  One was recommended to this man, and he
said: "Send him down to my office, and I'll look him over."  He was
an attorney, and he liked to lean back in his chair, twirl a paper-knife, and let the other fellow talk.
</p><p>The seafaring man came, and stood, and appeared confounded.
The attorney asked the terrible first question of the filibuster <pb n="1046"/>  to the applicant.  He said: "Why do you want to go?"
</p><p>The captain reflected, changed his attitude three times, and
decided ultimately that he didn't know.  He seemed greatly ashamed.
The attorney, looking at him, saw that he had eyes that resembled
a lambkin's eyes.
</p><p>"Glory?" said the attorney at last.
</p><p>"No-o," said the captain.
</p><p>"Pay?"
</p><p>"No-o.  Not that, so much."
</p><p>"Think they'll give you a land grant when they win out?"
</p><p>"No.  Never thought."
</p><p>"No glory.  No immense pay.  No land grant.  What are you
going for, then?"
</p><p>"Well, I don't know," said the captain, with his glance on the
floor, and shifting his position again.  "I don't know.  I guess
it's just for fun, mostly."  The attorney asked him out to have a
drink.
</p><p>When he stood on the bridge of his out-going steamer, the
attorney saw him again.  His shore meekness and uncertainty were
gone.  He was clear-eyed and strong, aroused like a mastiff at
night.  He took his cigar out of his mouth and yelled some sudden
language at the deck.
</p><p>This steamer had about her a quality of unholy mediaeval
disrepair which is usually accounted the principal prerogative of
the United States revenue marine.  There is many a seaworthy
icehouse if she was a good ship.  She swashed through the seas as
genially as an old wooden clock, burying her head under waves that
came only like children at play, and on board it cost a ducking to
go from anywhere to anywhere.
</p><p>The captain had commanded vessels that shore people thought
were liners, but when a man gets the ant of desire-to-see-what-it's-like stirring in his heart, he will wallow out to sea in a
pail.  The thing surpasses a man's love for his sweetheart.  The
great tank-steamer "Thunder Voice" had long been Flanagan's
sweetheart, but he was far happier off Hatteras, watching this
wretched little portmanteau boom down the slant of a wave.
</p><p>The crew scraped acquaintance, one with another, gradually.
Each man came ultimately to ask his neighbor what particular turn
of ill-fortune or inherited deviltry caused him to try this voyage.
When one frank, bold man saw another frank, bold man aboard, he
smiled, and they became friends.  There was not a mind on board the
ship that was not fastened to the dangers of the coast of Cuba and
taking wonder at this prospect and delight in it.  Still, in jovial
moments, they termed each other accursed idiots.
</p><p>At first there was some trouble in the engine-room, where
there were many steel animals, for the most part painted red, and
in other places very shiny, bewildering, complex, incomprehensible
to anyone who don't care, usually thumping, thumping, thumping with
the monotony of a snore.
</p><p>It seems that this engine was as whimsical as a gas-meter.
The chief engineer was a fine old fellow with a gray mustache, but
the engine told him that it didn't intend to budge until it felt
better.  He came to the bridge, and said: "The blamed old thing has
laid down on us, sir."
</p><p>"Who was on duty?" roared the captain.
</p><p>"The second, sir."
</p><p>"Why didn't he call you?"
</p><p>"Don't know, sir."  Later the stokers had occasion to thank
the stars that they were not second engineers.
</p><p>The "Foundling" was soundly thrashed by the waves for
loitering while the captain and the engineers fought the obstinate
machinery.  During this wait on the sea, the first gloom came to
the faces of the company.  The ocean is wide, and a ship is a small
place for the feet, and an ill ship is worriment.  Even when she
was again under way, the gloom was still upon the crew.  From time
to time men went to the engine-room doors and, looking down, wanted
to ask questions of the chief engineer, who slowly prowled to and
fro and watched with careful eye his red-painted mysteries.  No man
wished to have a companion know that he was anxious, and so
questions were caught at the lips.  Perhaps none commented save the
first mate, who remarked to the captain: "Wonder what the bally old
thing will do, sir, when we're chased by a Spanish cruiser?"
</p><p>The captain merely grinned.  Later he looked over the side and
said to himself with scorn: "Sixteen knots!  Sixteen knots!
Sixteen hinges on the inner gates of Hades!  Sixteen knots!  Seven
is her gait, and nine if you crack her up to it."
</p><p>There may never be a captain whose crew can't sniff his
misgivings.  They scent it as a herd scents the menace far through
the trees and over the ridges.  A captain that does not know that
he is on a foundering ship sometimes can take his men to tea and
buttered toast twelve min-<pb n="1047"/> utes before the disaster; but let
him fret for a moment in the loneliness of his cabin, and in no
time it affects the liver of a distant and sensitive seaman.  Even
as Flanagan reflected on the "Foundling," viewing her as a
filibuster, word arrived that a winter of discontent had come to
the stoke-room.
</p><p>The captain knew that it requires sky to give a man courage.
He sent for a stoker and talked to him on the bridge.  The man,
standing under the sky, instantly and shamefacedly denied all
knowledge of the business.  Nevertheless a jaw had presently to be
broken by a fist because the "Foundling" could only steam nine
knots and because the stoke-room has no sky, no wind, no bright
horizon.
</p><p>When the "Foundling" was somewhere off Savannah, a blow came
from the northeast, and the steamer, headed southeast, rolled like
a boiling potato.  The first mate was a fine officer, and so a wave
crashed him into the deck-house and broke his arm.  The cook was a
good cook, and so the heave of the ship flung him heels over head
with a pot of boiling water, and caused him to lose interest in
everything save his legs.  "By the piper," said Flanagan to
himself, "this filibustering is no trick with cards."
</p><p>Later there was more trouble in the stoke-room.  All the
stokers participated save the one with a broken jaw, who had become
discouraged.  The captain had an excellent chest development.  When
he went aft, roaring, it was plain that a man could beat carpets
with a voice like that one.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="2" id="d5">
<head>II.</head>

<p>ONE night the "Foundling" was off the southern coast of
Florida and running at half speed toward the shore.  The captain
was on the bridge.  "Four flashes at intervals of one minute," he
said to himself, gazing steadfastly toward the beach.  Suddenly a
yellow eye opened in the black face of the night, and looked at the
"Foundling," and closed again.  The captain studied his watch and
the shore.  Three times more the eye opened and looked at the
"Foundling" and closed again.  The captain called to the vague
figures on the deck below him.  "Answer it."  The flash of a light
from the bow of the steamer displayed for a moment in golden color
the crests of the inriding waves.
</p><p>The "Foundling" lay to and waited.  The long swells rolled her
gracefully, and her two stub masts, reaching into the darkness,
swung with the solemnity of batons timing a dirge.  When the ship
had left Boston she had been as encrusted with ice as a Dakota
stage-driver's beard; but now the gentle wind of Florida softly
swayed the lock on the forehead of the coatless Flanagan, and he
lit a new cigar without troubling to make a shield of his hands.
</p><p>Finally a dark boat came plashing over the waves.  As it came
very near, the captain leaned forward and perceived that the men in
her rowed like seamstresses, and at the same time a voice hailed
him in bad English.  "It's a dead sure connection," said he to
himself.
</p><p>At sea, to load two hundred thousand rounds of rifle
ammunition, seven hundred and fifty rifles, two rapid-fire field
guns, with a hundred shells, forty bundles of machetes, and a
hundred pounds of dynamite, from yawls and by men who are not born
stevedores, and in a heavy ground swell and with the search-light
of a United States cruiser sometimes flashing like lightning in the
sky to the southward, is no business for a Sunday-school class.
When at last the "Foundling" was steaming for the open, over the
gray sea, at dawn, there was not a man of the forty come aboard
from the Florida shore, nor of the fifteen sailed from Boston, who
was not glad, standing with his hair matted to his forehead with
sweat, smiling at the broad wake of the "Foundling" and the dim
streak on the horizon which was Florida.
</p><p>But there is a point of the compass in these waters which men
call the northeast.  When the strong winds come from that
direction, they kick up a turmoil that is not good for a
"Foundling" stuffed with coal and war-stores.  In the gale which
came, this ship was no more than a drunken soldier.
</p><p>The Cuban leader, standing on the bridge with the captain, was
presently informed that of his men thirty-nine out of a possible
thirty-nine were seasick.  And in truth they were seasick.  There
are degrees in this complaint, but that matter was waived between
them.  They were all sick to the limits.  They strewed the deck in
every posture of human anguish; and when the "Foundling" ducked and
water came sluicing down from the bows, they let it sluice.  They
were satisfied if they could keep their heads clear of the wash;
and if they could not keep their heads clear of the wash, they
didn't <pb n="1048"/>  care.  Presently the "Foundling" swung her course
to the southeast, and the waves pounded her broadside.  The
patriots were all ordered below decks, and there they howled and
measured their misery one against another.  All day the "Foundling"
plopped and foundered over a blazing bright meadow of an ocean
whereon the white foam was like flowers.
</p><p>The captain on the bridge mused and studied the bare horizon.
He said a strong word to himself, and the word was more in
amazement than in indignation or sorrow.  "Thirty-nine seasick
passengers, the mate with a broken arm, a stoker with a broken jaw,
the cook with a pair of scalded legs, and an engine likely to be
taken with all these diseases, if not more.  If I get back to a
home port with a spoke of the wheel gripped in my hands, it'll be
fair luck."
</p><p>There is a kind of corn whisky bred in Florida which the
natives declare is potent in the proportion of seven fights to a
drink.  Some of the Cuban volunteers had had the forethought to
bring a small quantity of this whisky aboard with them, and being
now in the fire-room and seasick, and feeling that they would not
care to drink liquor for two or three years to come, they
gracefully tendered their portions to the stokers.  The stokers
accepted these gifts without avidity, but with a certain
earnestness of manner.
</p><p>As they were stokers and toiling, the whirl of emotion was
delayed, but it arrived ultimately and with emphasis.  One stoker
called another stoker a weird name, and the latter, righteously
inflamed at it, smote his mate with an iron shovel, and the man
fell headlong over a heap of coal which crashed gently, while piece
after piece rattled down upon the deck.
</p><p>A third stoker was providentially enraged at the scene, and
assailed the second stoker.  They fought for some moments, while
the seasick Cubans sprawled on the deck watched with languid,
rolling glances the ferocity of this scuffle.  One was so
indifferent to the strategic importance of the space he occupied
that he was kicked in the shins.
</p><p>When the second engineer came to separate the combatants, he
was sincere in his efforts, and he came near to disabling them for
life.
</p><p>The captain said, "I'll go down there and&mdash;"  But the leader
of the Cubans restrained him.  "No, no," he cried, "you must not.
We must treat them like children, very gently, all the time, you
see, or else when we get back to a United States port they will&mdash;
what you call&mdash;spring?  Yes&mdash;spring the whole business.  We must&mdash;
jolly them.  You see?"
</p><p>"You mean," said the captain, thoughtfully, "they are likely
to get mad and give the expedition dead away when we reach port
again unless we blarney them now?"
</p><p>"Yes, yes," cried the Cuban leader, "unless we are so very
gentle with them they will make many troubles afterwards for us in
the newspapers and then in court."
</p><p>"Well, but I won't have my crew&mdash;" began the captain.
</p><p>"But you must," interrupted the Cuban.  "You must.  It is the
only thing.  You are like the captain of a pirate ship.  You see?
Only you can't throw them overboard like him.  You see?"
</p><p>"Hum," said the captain, "this here filibustering business has
got a lot to it when you come to look it over."
</p><p>He called the fighting stokers to the bridge, and the three
came meek and considerably battered.  He was lecturing them
soundly, but sensibly, when he suddenly tripped a sentence and
cried: "Here!  Where's that other fellow?  How does it come he
wasn't in the fight?"
</p><p>The row of stokers cried at once eagerly: "He's hurt, sir.
He's got a broken jaw, sir."
</p><p>"So he has.  So he has," murmured the captain, much
embarrassed.
</p><p>And because of all these affairs the "Foundling" steamed
toward Cuba with its crew in a sling, if one may be allowed to
speak in that way.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="3" id="d6">
<head>III.</head>

<p>AT night the "Foundling" approached the coast like a thief.
Her lights were muffled so that from the deck the sea shone with
its own radiance, like the faint shimmer of some kinds of silk.
The men on deck spoke in whispers, and even down in the fire-room
the hidden stokers, working before the blood-red furnace doors,
used no words and walked tip-toe.  The stars were out in the blue-velvet sky, and their light with the soft shine of the sea caused
the coast to appear black as the side of a coffin.  The surf boomed
in low thunder on the distant beach.
</p><p>The "Foundling's" engines ceased their thumping for a time.
She glided quietly forward until a bell chimed faintly <pb n="1049"/>  in
the engine-room.  Then she paused, with a flourish of
phosphorescent waters.
</p><p>"Give the signal," said the captain.  Three times a flash of
light went from the bow.  There was a moment of waiting.  Then an
eye like the one on the coast of Florida opened and closed, opened
and closed, opened and closed.  The Cubans, grouped in a great
shadow on deck, burst into a low chatter of delight.  A hiss from
their leader silenced them.
</p><p>"Well?" said the captain.
</p><p>"All right," said the leader.
</p><p>At the giving of the word it was not apparent that anyone on
board of the "Foundling" had ever been seasick.  The boats were
lowered swiftly, too swiftly.  Boxes of cartridges were dragged
from the hold and passed over the side with a rapidity that made
men in the boats exclaim against it.  They were being bombarded.
When a boat headed for shore, its rowers pulled like madmen.  The
captain paced slowly to and fro on the bridge.  In the engine-room
the engineers stood at their station, and in the stoke-hole the
firemen fidgeted silently around the furnace doors.
</p><p>On the bridge Flanagan reflected.  "Oh, I don't know," he
observed, "this filibustering business isn't so bad.  Pretty soon
I'll be off to sea again, with nothing to do but some big lying
when I get into port."
</p><p>In one of the boats returning from shore came twelve Cuban
officers, the greater number of them convalescing from wounds,
while two or three of them had been ordered to America on
commissions from the insurgents.  The captain welcomed them, and
assured them of a speedy and safe voyage.
</p><p>Presently he went again to the bridge and scanned the horizon.
The sea was lonely like the spaces amid the suns.  The captain
grinned, and softly smote his chest.  "It's dead easy," he said.
</p><p>It was near the end of the cargo, and the men were breathing
like spent horses, although their elation grew with each moment,
when suddenly a voice spoke from the sky.  It was not a loud voice,
but the quality of it brought every man on deck to full stop and
motionless, as if they had all been changed to wax.  "Captain,"
said the man at the masthead, "there's a light to the west'ard,
sir.  Think it's a steamer, sir."
</p><p>There was a still moment until the captain called: "Well, keep
your eye on it now."  Speaking to the deck, he said: "Go ahead with
your unloading."
</p><p>The second engineer went to the galley to borrow a tin cup.
"Hear the news, second?" asked the cook.  "Steamer coming up from
the west'ard."
</p><p>"Gee!" said the second engineer.  In the engine-room he said
to the chief: "Steamer coming up to the west'ard, sir."
</p><p>The chief engineer began to test various little machines with
which his domain was decorated.  Finally he addressed the stoke-room.  "Boys, I want you to look sharp now.  There's a steamer
coming up to the west'ard."
</p><p>"All right, sir," said the stoke-room.
</p><p>From time to time the captain hailed the masthead.  "How is
she now?"
</p><p>"Seems to be coming down on us pretty fast, sir."
</p><p>The Cuban leader came anxiously to the captain.  "Do you think
we can save all the cargo?  It is rather delicate business.  No?"
</p><p>"Go ahead," said Flanagan.  "Fire away.  I'll wait for you."
</p><p>There continued the hurried shuffling of feet on deck and the
low cries of the men unloading the cargo.  In the engine-room the
chief and his assistant were staring at the gong.  In the stoke-room the firemen breathed through their teeth.  A shovel slipped
from where it leaned against the side and banged on the floor.  The
stokers started and looked around quickly.
</p><p>Climbing to the rail and holding on to a stay, the captain
gazed westward.  A light had raised out of the deep.  After
watching this light for a time he called to the Cuban leader,
"Well, as soon as you're ready now, we might as well be skipping
out."
</p><p>Finally the Cuban leader told him: "Well, this is the last
load.  As soon as the boats come back you can be off."
</p><p>"Shan't wait for the boats," said the captain.  "That fellow
is too close."  As the last boat went shoreward, the "Foundling"
turned, and like a black shadow stole seaward to cross the bows of
the oncoming steamer.  "Waited about ten minutes too long," said
the captain to himself.
</p><p>Suddenly the light in the west vanished.  "Hum," said
Flanagan, "he's up to some meanness."  Everyone outside of the
engine-room was set on watch.  The "Foundling," going at full speed
into the northeast, slashed a wonderful trail of blue silver on the
dark bosom of the sea.
</p><p>A man on deck cried out hurriedly, <pb n="1050"/>  "There she is,
sir."  Many eyes searched the western gloom, and one after another
the glances of the men found a tiny black shadow on the deep, with
a line of white beneath it.  "He couldn't be heading better if he
had a line to us," said Flanagan.
</p><p>There was a thin flash of red in the darkness.  It was long
and keen like a crimson rapier.  A short, sharp report sounded, and
then a shot whined swiftly in the air and blipped into the sea.
The captain had been about to take a bit of plug tobacco at the
beginning of this incident, and his arm was raised.  He remained
like a frozen figure while the shot whined, and then, as it blipped
in the sea, his hand went to his mouth and he bit the plug.  He
looked wide-eyed at the shadow with its line of white.
</p><p>The senior Cuban officer came hurriedly to the bridge.  "It is
no good to surrender," he cried; "they would only shoot or hang all
of us."
</p><p>There was another thin red flash and a report.  A loud,
whirring noise passed over the ship.
</p><p>"I'm not going to surrender," said the captain, hanging with
both hands to the rail.  He appeared like a man whose traditions of
peace are clinched in his heart.  He was as astonished as if his
hat had turned into a dog.  Presently he wheeled quickly and said:
"What kind of a gun is that?"
</p><p>"It is a one-pounder," cried the Cuban officer.  "The boat is
one of those little gunboats made from a yacht.  You see?"
</p><p>"Well, if it's only a yawl, he'll sink us in five more
minutes," said Flanagan.  For a moment he looked helplessly off at
the horizon.  His under jaw hung low.  But, a moment later,
something touched him like a stiletto point of inspiration.  He
leaped to the pilot house and roared at the man at the wheel.  The
"Foundling" sheered suddenly to starboard, made a clumsy turn, and
Flanagan was bellowing through the tube to the engine-room before
anybody discovered that the old basket was heading straight for the
Spanish gunboat.  The ship lunged forward like a draught-horse on
the gallop.
</p><p>This strange manoeuver by the "Foundling" first dealt
consternation on board.  Men instinctively crouched on the instant,
and then swore their supreme oath, which was unheard by their own
ears.
</p><p>Later, the manoeuver of the "Foundling" dealt consternation on
board of the gunboat.  She had been going victoriously forward,
dim-eyed from the fury of her pursuit.  Then this tall, threatening
shape had suddenly loomed over her like a giant apparition.
</p><p>The people on board the "Foundling" heard panic shouts, hoarse
orders.  The little gunboat was paralyzed with astonishment.
</p><p>Suddenly Flanagan yelled with rage and sprang for the wheel.
The helmsman had turned his eyes away.  As the captain whirled the
wheel far to starboard, he heard a crunch as the "Foundling,"
lifted on a wave, smashed her shoulder against the gunboat, and he
saw, shooting past, a little launch sort of a thing with men on her
that ran this way and that way.  The Cuban officers, joined by the
cook and a seaman, emptied their revolvers into the surprised
terror of the seas.
</p><p>There was naturally no pursuit.  Under comfortable speed the
"Foundling" stood to the northward.
</p><p>The captain went to his berth chuckling.  "There, now," he
said.  "There now!"</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="4" id="d7">
<head>IV.</head>

<p>WHEN Flanagan came again on deck, the first mate, his arm in
a sling, walked the bridge.  Flanagan was smiling a wide smile.
The bridge of the "Foundling" was dipping afar and then afar.  With
each lunge of the little steamer the water seethed and boomed
alongside and the spray dashed high and swiftly.
</p><p>"Well," said Flanagan, inflating himself, "we've had a great
deal of a time, and we've come through it all right, and thank
heaven it is all over."
</p><p>The sky in the northeast was of a dull brick-red in tone,
shaded here and there by black masses that billowed out in some
fashion from the flat heavens.
</p><p>"Look there," said the mate.
</p><p>"Hum," said the captain.  "Looks like a blow, don't it?"
</p><p>Later the surface of the water rippled and flickered in the
preliminary wind.  The sea had become the color of lead.  The
swashing sound of the waves on the sides of the "Foundling" was now
provided with some manner of ominous significance.  The men's
shouts were hoarse.
</p><p>A squall struck the "Foundling" on her starboard quarter, and
she leaned under the force of it as if she were never to return to
the even keel.  "I'll be glad when we get in," said the mate.  "I'm
going to quit then.  I've got enough." <pb n="1051"/>
</p><p>The steamer crawled on into the northwest.  The white water
sweeping out from her deadened the chug-chug-chug of the tired old
engines.
</p><p>Once, when the boat careened, she laid her shoulder flat on
the sea and rested in that manner.  The mate, looking down the
bridge, which slanted more than a coal-chute, whistled softly to
himself.  Slowly, heavily, the "Foundling" arose to meet another
sea.
</p><p>At night, waves thundered mightily on the bows of the steamer,
and water, lit with the beautiful phosphorescent glamour, went
boiling and howling along the deck.
</p><p>By good fortune the chief engineer crawled safely, but utterly
drenched, to the galley for coffee.  "Well, how goes it, chief?"
said the cook, standing with his fat arms folded, in order to prove
that he could balance himself under any condition.
</p><p>The engineer shook his head slowly.  "This old biscuit-box
will never see port again.  Why, she'll fall to pieces."
</p><p>Finally, at night, the captain said: "Launch the boats."  The
Cubans hovered about him.  "Is the ship going to sink?"  The
captain addressed them politely.  "Gentlemen, we are in trouble,
but all I ask of you is that you do just what I tell you, and no
harm will come to anybody."
</p><p>The mate directed the lowering of the first boat, and the men
performed this task with all decency, like people at the side of a
grave.
</p><p>A young oiler came to the captain.  "The chief sends word,
sir, that the water is almost up to the fires."
</p><p>"Keep at it as long as you can."
</p><p>"Keep at it as long as we can, sir."
</p><p>Flanagan took the senior Cuban officer to the rail, and, as
the steamer sheered high on a great sea, showed him a yellow dot on
the horizon.  It was smaller than a needle when its point is toward
you.
</p><p>"There," said the captain.  The wind-driven spray was lashing
his face.  "That's Jupiter Light on the Florida coast.  Put your
men in the boat we've just launched, and the mate will take you to
that light."
</p><p>Afterward Flanagan turned to the chief engineer.  "We can
never beach her," said the old man.  "The stokers have got to quit
in a minute."  Tears were in his eyes.
</p><p>The "Foundling" was a wounded thing.  She lay on the water
with gasping engines, and each wave resembled her death blow.
</p><p>Now the way of a good ship on the sea is finer than sword-play.  But this is when she is alive.  If a time comes that the
ship dies, then her way is the way of a floating old glove, and she
has that much vim, spirit, buoyancy.  At this time many men on the
"Foundling" suddenly came to know that they were clinging to a
corpse.
</p><p>The captain went to the stoke-room, and what he saw as he
swung down the companion suddenly turned him hesitant and dumb.  He
had served the sea for many years, but this fire-room said
something to him which he had not heard in his other voyages.
Water was swirling to and fro with the roll of the ship, fuming
greasily around half-strangled machinery that still attempted to
perform its duty.  Steam arose from the water, and through its
clouds shone the red glare of the dying fires.  As for the stokers,
death might have been with silence in this room.  One lay in his
berth, ;his hands under his head, staring moodily at the wall.  One
sat near the foot of the companion, his face hidden in his arms.
One leaned against the side, and gazed at the snarling water as it
rose and its mad eddies among the machinery.  In the unholy red
light and gray mist of this stifling dim inferno they were strange
figures with their silence and their immobility.  The wretched
"Foundling" groaned deeply as she lifted, and groaned deeply as she
sank into the trough, while hurried waves then thundered over her
with the noise of landslides.
</p><p>But Flanagan took control of himself suddenly, and then he
stirred the fire-room.  The stillness had been so unearthly that he
was not altogether inapprehensive of strange and grim deeds when he
charged into them, but precisely as they had submitted to the sea
so they submitted to Flanagan.  For a moment they rolled their eyes
like hurt cows, but they obeyed the voice.  The situation simply
required a voice.
</p><p>When the captain returned to the deck, the hue of this fire-room was in his mind, and then he understood doom and its weight
and complexion.
</p><p>When finally the "Foundling" sank, she shifted and settled as
calmly as an animal curls down in the bush grass.  Away over the
waves three bobbing boats paused to witness this quiet death.  It
was a slow manoeuver, altogether without the pageantry of uproar,
but it flashed pallor into the faces of all men who saw it, and
they groaned when they said: "There she goes!"  Suddenly the
captain whirled and knocked his head on the gunwale.  He <pb n="1052"/>
sobbed for a time, and then he sobbed and swore also.</p>
<lb/>
<p>There was a dance at the Imperial Inn.  During the evening
some irresponsible young men came from the beach, bringing the
statement that several boatloads of people had been perceived off
shore.  It was a charming dance, and none cared to take time to
believe this tale.  The fountain in the courtyard plashed softly,
and couple after couple paraded through the aisles of palms where
lamps with red shades threw a rose light upon the gleaming leaves.
High on some balcony a mocking-bird called into the evening.  The
band played its waltzes slumberously, and its music to the people
among the palms came faintly and like the melodies in dreams.
</p><p>Sometimes a woman said: "Oh, it is not really true, is it,
that there was a wreck out at sea?"
</p><p>A man usually said: "No, of course not."
</p><p>At last, however, a youth came violently from the beach.  He
was triumphant in manner.  "They're out there," he cried.  "A whole
boatload!"  He received eager attention, and he told all that he
supposed.  His news destroyed the dance.  After a time the band was
playing delightfully to space.  The guests had donned wraps and
hurried to the beach.  One little girl cried: "Oh, mamma, may I go
too?"  Being refused permission, she pouted.
</p><p>As they came from the shelter of the great hotel, the wind was
blowing swiftly from the sea, and at intervals a breaker shone
livid.  The women shuddered, and their bending companions seized
opportunity to draw the cloaks closer.  The sand of the beach was
wet, and dainty slippers made imprints in it clear and deep.
</p><p>"Oh, dear," said a girl, "supposin' they were out there
drowning while we were dancing!"
</p><p>"Oh, nonsense!" said her younger brother; "that don't happen."
</p><p>"Well, it might, you know, Roger.  How can you tell?"
</p><p>A man who was not her brother gazed at her then with profound
admiration.  Later she complained of the damp sand, and drawing
back her skirts, looked ruefully at her little feet.
</p><p>A mother's son was venturing too near to the water in his
interest and excitement.  Occasionally she cautioned and reproached
him from the background.
</p><p>Save for the white glare of the breakers, the sea was a great
wind-crossed void.  From the throng of charming women floated the
perfume of many flowers.  Later there floated to them a body with
a calm face of an Irish type.  The expedition of the "Foundling"
will never be historic.</p>

</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
