<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CraScot"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="CraScot">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Scotch Express</title>
<title type="sort">scotch express</title>
<author>Crane, Stephen, 1871-1900</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">32</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CraScot</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475846</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Images have not been included from the print version, which was
unavailable.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Scotch Express</title>
<title level="j">McClure's</title>
<title type="sort">scotch express</title>
<author>Stephen Crane</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>Volume 12</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>273-283.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>S.S. McClure, Ltd.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1899-01">January 1899</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Copy consulted:</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions
for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-05">May 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Catherine Tousignant</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">


<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> <pb n="273"/>
<head>THE SCOTCH EXPRESS.<lb/>
BY STEPHEN CRANE.<lb/>
Author of "The Red Badge of Courage," "The Open Boat," etc.<lb/>

The illustrations are from drawings by the late W. L. Sonntag, Jr.,
who made the journey in company with Mr. Crane, expressly for
McCLURE'S MAGAZINE.  It was only a short time after these drawings
were completed that Mr. Sonntag died&mdash;in the very prime of his fine
powers and to the deep regret of all who knew him or his work.</head>

<p>THE entrance to Euston Station is of itself sufficiently imposing.
It is a high portico of brown stone, old and grim, in form a casual
imitation, no doubt, of the front of the temple of Nike Apteros, with a
recollection of the Egyptians proclaimed at the flanks.  The frieze,
where of old would prance an exuberant processional of gods, is, in
this case, bare of decoration, but upon the epistyle is written in
simple, stern letters the word, "EUSTON."  The legend reared high by
the gloomy Pelagic columns stares down a wide    <pb n="274"/>
avenue.  In short, this entrance to a railway station does not in any
resemble the entrance to a railway station.  It is more the front of
some venerable bank.  But it has another dignity, which is not born of
form.  To a great degree, it is to the English and to those who are in
England the gate to Scotland.

</p><p>The little hansoms are continually speeding through the gate,
dashing between the legs of the solemn temple; the four-wheelers, their
tops crowded with luggage, roll in and out constantly, and the footways
beat under the trampling of the people.  Of course, there are the
suburbs and a hundred towns along the line, and Liverpool, the
beginning of an important sea path to America, and the great
manufacturing cities of the North; but if one stands at this gate in
August particularly, one must note the number of men with gun-cases,
the number of women who surely [illustration omitted] have
Tam-o'-Shanters and plaids concealed within their luggage, ready for
the moors.  There is, during the latter part of that month, a
wholesale flight from London to Scotland which recalls the July
throngs leaving New York for the shore or the mountains.

</p><p>The hansoms, after passing through this impressive portal of the
station, bowl smoothly across a courtyard which is in the center of the
terminal hotel, an institution dear to most railways in Europe.  The
traveler lands amid a swarm of porters, and then proceeds cheerfully to
take the customary trouble for his luggage.  America provides a
contrivance in a thousand situations where Europe provides a man or
perhaps a number of men, and the work of our brass check is here done
by porters, directed by the traveler himself.  The men lack the memory
of the check; the check never forgets its identity.  Moreover, the
European railways generously furnish the porters at the expense of the
traveler.  Nevertheless, if these men have not the invincible business
precision of the check, and if they have to be tipped, it can be
asserted for those who care that in Europe one-half of the populace
waits on the other half most diligently and well.

</p><p>Against the masonry of a platform, under the vaulted arch of the
train-house, lay a long string of coaches.  They were painted white on
the bulging part, which led half-way down from the top, and the bodies
were a deep bottle-green.  There was a group of porters placing luggage
in the van, and a great many others were busy with the affairs of
passengers, tossing smaller bits of luggage into the racks over the
seats, and bustling

   <pb n="275"/>

here and there on short quests.  The guard of the train, a tall man
who resembled one of the first Napoleon's veterans, was caring for the
distribution of passengers into the various bins.  They were all third
and first-class.

</p><p>The train was at this time engineless, but presently a railway
"flier," painted a glowing vermilion, slid modestly down and took its
place at the [illustration omitted] head.  The guard walked along the
platform, and decisively closed each door.  He wore a dark blue uniform
thoroughly decorated with silver braid in the guise of leaves.  The
way of him gave to this business the importance of a ceremony.
Meanwhile the fireman had climbed down from the cab and raised his
hand, ready to transfer a signal to the driver, who stood looking at
his watch.  In the interval there had something progressed in the
large signal-box that stands guard at Euston.  This high house
contains many levers, standing in thick, shining ranks.  It perfectly
resembles an organ in some great church, if it were not that these
rows of numbered and indexed handles typify something more acutely
human than does a key-board.  It requires four men to play this
organ-like thing, and the strains never cease.  Night and day, day and
night, these four men are walking to and fro, from this lever to that
lever, and under their hands the great machine raises its endless hymn
of a world at work, the fall and rise of signals and the clicking swing
of switches.

</p><p>And so as the vermilion engine stood waiting and looking from
the shadow of the curve-roofed station, a man in the signal-house had
played the notes which informed the engine of its freedom.  The driver
saw the fall of those proper semaphores which gave him liberty to
speak to his steel friend.  A certain combination in the economy of
the London and Northwestern Railway, a combination which had spread
from the men who sweep out the carriages through innumerable minds to
the general manager himself, had resulted in the law that the
vermilion engine, with its long string of white and bottle-green
coaches, was to start forthwith toward Scotland.

</p><p>Presently the fireman, standing with his face toward the rear,
let fall his hand.  "All right," he said.  The driver turned a wheel,
and as the fireman slipped back, the train moved along the platform at
the pace of a mouse.  To those in the tranquil carriages this starting
was probably as easy as the sliding of one's hand over a greased
surface, but in the engine there was more to it.  The monster roared
suddenly and loudly, and sprang forward impetuously.  A wrong-headed
or maddened draft-horse will plunge in its collar sometimes when going
up a hill.  But this load of burdened carriages followed imperturbably
at the gait of turtles.  They were not to be stirred from their way of
dignified exit by the impatient engine.  The crowd of porters and
transient people stood

   <pb n="276"/>

respectful.  They looked with the indefinite wonder of the
railway-station sight-seer upon the faces at the windows of the
passing coaches.  This train was off for Scotland.  It had started
from the

home of one accent to the home of another accent.  It was going from
manner to manner, from habit to habit, and in the minds of these London
spectators there surely floated dim images of the traditional kilts,
the burring speech, the grouse, the canniness, the oat-meal, all the
elements of a romantic Scotland.

</p><p>The train swung impressively around the signal-house, and headed
up a brick-walled cut.  In starting this heavy string of coaches, the
engine breathed explosively.  It gasped, and heaved, and bellowed;
once, for a moment, the wheels spun on the rails, and a convulsive
tremor shook the great steel frame.

</p><p>The train itself, however, moved through this deep cut in the
body of London with coolness and precision, and the employees of the
railway, knowing the train's mission, tacitly presented arms at its
passing.  To the travelers in the carriages, the suburbs of London
must have been one long monotony of carefully made walls of stone or
brick.  But after the hill was climbed, the train fled through
pictures of red habitations of men on a green earth.

</p><p>But the noise in the cab did not greatly change its measure.
Even though the speed was now high, the tremendous thumping to be heard
in the cab was as alive with strained effort and as slow in beat as the
breathing of a half-drowned man.  At the side of the track, for
instance, the sound doubtless would strike the ear in the familiar
succession of incredibly rapid puffs; but in the cab itself, this
land-racer breathes very like its friend, the marine engine.
Everybody who has spent time on shipboard has forever in his head a
reminiscence of the steady and methodical pounding of the engines, and
perhaps it is curious that this relative, which can whirl over the
land at such a pace, breathes in the leisurely tones that a man heeds
when he lies awake at night in his berth.

</p><p>There had been no fog in London, but here on the edge of the
city a heavy wind was blowing, and the driver leaned aside and yelled
that it was a very bad day for traveling on an engine.  The
engine-cabs of England, as of all Europe, are seldom made for the
comfort of the men.  One finds very often this apparent disregard for
the man who does the work&mdash;this indifference to the man who occupies a
position which for the exercise of temperance, of courage, of honesty,
has no equal at the altitude of prime ministers.  The American
engineer is the gilded occupant of a salon in comparison with his
brother in Europe.  The man who was guiding this five-hundred-ton
bolt, aimed by the officials of the railway at Scotland, could not
have been as comfortable as a shrill gibbering boatman of the Orient.
The narrow and bare bench at his side of the cab was not directly
intended for his use, because it was so low that he would be prevented
by it from looking out of the ship's port-hole which served him as a
window.  The fireman, on his side, had other difficulties.  His legs
would have had to straggle over some pipes at the only spot where
there was a prospect, and the builders had also strategically placed a
large steel bolt.  Of course it is plain that the companies
consistently believe that the men will do their work better if they
are kept standing.  The roof of the cab was not altogether

   <pb n="277"/>

a roof.  It was merely a projection of two feet of metal from the
bulkhead which formed the front of the cab.  There were practically no
sides to it, and the large cinders from the soft coal whirled around
in sheets.  From time to time the driver took a handkerchief from his
pocket and wiped his blinking eyes.

</p><p>London was now well to the rear.  The vermilion engine had been
for some time flying like the wind.  This train averages, between
London and Carlisle, forty-nine and nine-tenth miles an hour.  It is a
distance of 299 miles.  There is one stop.  It occurs at Crewe, and
endures five minutes.  In consequence, the block-signals flashed by
seemingly at the end of the moment in which they were sighted.

</p><p>There can be no question of the statement that the road-beds of
English railways are at present immeasurably superior to the American
road-beds.  Of course there is a clear reason.  It is known to every
traveler that peoples of the Continent of Europe have no right at all
to own railways.  Those lines of travel are too childish and trivial
for expression.  A correct fate would deprive the Continent of its
railways, and give them to somebody who knew about them.  The
continental idea of a railway is to surround a mass of machinery with
forty rings of ultra-military [illustration omitted] law, and then
they believe they have one complete.  The Americans and the English
are the railway peoples.  That our road-beds are poorer than the
English road-beds is because of the fact that we were suddenly obliged
to build thousands upon thousands of miles of railway, and the English
were obliged to slowly build tens upon tens of miles.  A road-bed from
New York to San Francisco, with stations, bridges, and crossings of
the kind that the London and Northwestern owns from London to Glasgow,
would cost a sum large enough to support the German army for a term of
years.  The whole way is constructed with the care that inspired the
creators of some of our now obsolete forts along the Atlantic coast.
An American engineer, with his knowledge of the difficulties he had to
encounter&mdash;the wide rivers with variable banks, the mountain chains,
perhaps the long spaces of absolute desert; in fact, all the
perplexities of a vast and somewhat new country&mdash;would not dare spent
a respectable portion of his allowance on seventy feet of granite wall
over a gully, when he knew he could make an embankment with little
cost by heaving up the dirt and stones from here and there.  But the
English road is all made in the pattern

   <pb n="278"/>


by which the Romans built their highways.  After England is dead,
savants will find narrow streaks of masonry leading from ruin to
ruin.  Of course this does not always seem convincingly admirable.  It
sometimes resembles energy poured into a rat-hole.  There is a vale
between expediency and the convenience of posterity, a mid-ground
which enables men to surely benefit the hereafter people by valiantly
advancing the present; and the point is that, if some laborers live in
unhealthy tenements in Cornwall, one is likely to view with incomplete
satisfaction the record of long and patient labor and thought
displayed by an eight-foot drain for a non-existent, impossible
rivulet in the North.  This sentence does not sound strictly fair, but
the meaning one wishes to convey is that, if an English company spies
in its dream the ghost of an ancient valley that later becomes a hill,
it would construct for it a magnificent steel trestle, and consider
that a duty had been performed in proper accordance with the company's
conscience.  But after all is said of it, the accidents and the miles
of railway operated in England is not in proportion to the accidents
and the miles of railway operated in the United States.  The reason
can be divided into three parts&mdash;older conditions, superior caution,
and road-bed.  And of these, the greatest is older conditions.

</p><p>In this flight toward Scotland one seldom encountered a grade
crossing.  In nine cases out of ten there was either a bridge or a
tunnel.  The platforms of even the remote country stations were all of
ponderous masonry in contrast to our constructions of planking.  There
was always to be seen, as we thundered toward a station of this kind,
a number of porters in uniform, who requested the retreat of any one
who had not the wit to give us plenty of room.  And then, as the
shrill warning of the whistle pierced even the uproar that was about
us, came the wild joy of the rush past a station.  It was something in
the nature of a triumphal procession conducted at thrilling speed.
Perhaps there was a curve of infinite grace, a sudden hollow explosive
effect made by the passing of a signal-box that was close to the
track, and then the deadly lunge to shave the edge of a long
platform.  There were always a number of people standing afar, with
their eyes riveted upon this projectile, and to be on the engine was
to feel their interest and admiration in the terror and grandeur of
this sweep.  A boy allowed to ride with the driver of the band-wagon
as a circus parade winds through one of our village streets could not
exceed for egotism the temper of a new man in the cab of a train like
this one.  This valkyrie journey on the back of the vermilion engine,
with the shouting of the wind, the deep, mighty panting of the steed,
the gray blur at the track-side, the flowing quicksilver ribbon of the
other rails, the sudden clash as a switch intersects, all the din and
fury of this ride, was of a splendor that caused one to look abroad at
the quiet, green landscape and believe that it was of a phlegm quite
beyond patience.  It should have been dark, rain-shot, and windy;
thunder should have rolled across its sky.

</p><p>It seemed, somehow, that if the driver should for a moment take
his hands from his engine, it might swerve from the track as a horse
from the road.  Once, indeed, as he stood wiping his fingers on a bit
of waste, there must have been something ludicrous in the way the
solitary passenger regarded him.  Without those finely firm hands on
the bridle, the engine might rear and bolt for the pleasant farms
lying in the sunshine at either side.

</p><p>This driver was worth contemplation.  He was simply a quiet,
middle-aged man, bearded, and with the little wrinkles of habitual
geniality and kindliness spreading from the eyes toward the temple, who
stood at his post always gazing out, through his round window, while,
from time to time, his hands went from here to there over his levers.
He seldom changed either attitude or expression.  There surely is no
engine-driver who does not feel the beauty of the business, but the
emotion lies deep, and mainly inarticulate, as it does in the mind of
a man who has experienced a good and beautiful wife for many years.
This driver's face displayed nothing but the cool sanity of a man
whose thought was buried intelligently in his business.  If there was
any fierce drama in it, there was no sign upon him.  He was so lost
   <pb n="279"/>   in dreams of speed and signals and steam, that one
speculated if the wonder of his tempestuous charge and its career over
England touched him, this impassive rider of a fiery thing.

</p><p>It should be a well-known fact that, all over the world, the
engine-driver is the finest type of man that is grown.  He is the pick
of the earth.  He is altogether more worthy than the soldier, and
better than the men who move on the sea in ships.  He is not paid too
much; nor do his glories weight his brow; but for outright
performance, carried on constantly, coolly, and without elation, by a
temperate, honest, clear minded man, he is the further point.  And so
the lone human at his station in a cab, guarding money, lives, and the
honor of the road, is a beautiful sight.  The whole thing is
aesthetic.  The fireman presents the same charm, but in [illustration
omitted] a less degree, in that he is bound to appear as an apprentice
to the finished manhood of the driver.  In his eyes, turned always in
question and confidence toward his superior, one finds this quality;
but his aspirations are so direct that one sees the same type in
evolution.

</p><p>There may be a popular idea that the fireman's principal
function is to hang his head out of the cab and sight interesting
objects in the landscape.  As a matter of fact, he is always at work.
The dragon is insatiate.  The fireman is continually swinging open the
furnace-door, whereat a red shine flows out upon the floor of the cab,
and shoveling in immense mouthfuls of coal to a fire that is almost
diabolic in its madness.  The feeding, feeding, feeding goes on until
it appears as if it is the muscles of the fireman's arms that are
speeding the long train.  An engine

   <pb n="280"/>


running over sixty-five miles an hour, with 500 tons to drag, has an
appetite in proportion to this task.

</p><p>View of the clear-shining English scenery is often interrupted
between London and Crewe by long and short tunnels.  The first one was
disconcerting.  Suddenly one knew that the train was shooting toward a
black mouth in the hills.  It swiftly yawned wider, and then in a
moment the engine dove into a place inhabited by every demon of wind
and noise.  The speed had not been checked, and the uproar was so
great that in effect one was simply standing at the center of a vast,
black-walled sphere.  The tubular construction which one's reason
proclaimed had no meaning at all.  It was a black sphere, alive with
shrieks.  But then on the surface of it there was to be seen a little
needle-point of light, and this widened to a detail of unreal
landscape.  It was the world; the train was going to escape from this
cauldron, this abyss of howling darkness.  If a man looks through the
brilliant water of a tropical pool, he can sometimes see coloring the
marvels at the bottom the blue that was on the sky and the green that
was on the foliage of this detail.  And the picture shimmered in the
heat-rays of a new and remarkable sun.  It was when the train bolted
out into the open air that one knew that it was his own earth.

</p><p>Once train met train in a tunnel.  Upon the painting in the
perfectly circular frame formed by the mouth there appeared a black
square with sparks bursting from it.  This square expanded until it hid
everything, and a moment later came the crash of the passing.  It was
enough to make a man lose his sense of balance.  It was a momentary
inferno when the fireman opened the furnace-door and was bathed in
blood-red light as he fed the fires.

</p><p>The effect of a tunnel varied when there was a curve in it.
One was merely whirling then heels over head, apparently, in the dark,
echoing bowels of the earth.  There was no needle-point of light to
which one's eyes clung as to a star.

</p><p>From London to Crewe, the stern arm of the semaphore never made
the train pause even for an instant.  There was always a clear track.
It was great to see, far in the distance, a goods train whooping
smokily for the north of England on one of the four
   <pb n="281"/>
tracks.  The overtaking of such a train was a thing of
magnificent nothing for the long-strided engine, and as the flying
express passed its weaker brother, one heard one or two feeble and
immature puffs from the other engine, saw the fireman wave his hand to
his luckier fellow, saw a string of foolish, clanking flat-cars, their
freights covered with tarpaulins, and then the train was lost to the
rear.

</p><p>The driver twisted his wheel and worked some levers, and the
rhythmical chunking of the engine gradually ceased.  Gliding at a speed
that was still high, the train curved to the left, and swung down a
sharp incline, to move with an imperial dignity through the railway
yard at Rugby.  There was a maze of switches, innumerable engines
noisily pushing cars here and there, crowds of workmen who turned to
look, a sinuous curve around the long train-shed, whose high wall
resounded with the rumble of the passing express; and then, almost
immediately, it seemed, came the open country again.  Rugby had been a
dream which one could properly doubt.


</p><p>At last the relaxed engine, with the same majesty of ease, swung
into the high-roofed station at Crewe, and stopped on a platform lined
with porters and citizens.  There was instant bustle, and in the
interest of the moment no one seemed particularly to notice the tired
vermilion engine being led away.

</p><p>There is a five-minute stop at Crewe.  A tandem of engines slid
up, and buckled fast to the train for the journey to Carlisle.

</p><p>In the meantime, all the regulation items of peace and comfort
had happened on the train itself.  The dining-car was in the center of
the train.  It was divided into two parts, the one being a dining-room
for first-class passengers, and the other a dining-room for the
third-class passengers.  They were separated by the kitchens and the
larder.  The engine, with all its rioting and roaring, had dragged to
Crewe a car in which numbers of passengers were lunching in a
tranquillity that was almost domestic, on an average menu of a chop
and potatoes, a salad, cheese, and a bottle of beer.  Betimes they
watched through the windows the great chimney-marked towns of northern
England.    <pb n="282"/>   They were waited upon by a young man of
London, who was supported by a lad who resembled an American
bell-boy.  The rather elaborate menu and service of the Pullman
dining-car is not known in England or on the Continent.  Warmed roast
beef is the exact symbol of a European dinner, when one is traveling
on a railway.

</p><p>This express is named, both by the public and the company, the
"Corridor Train," because a coach with a corridor is an unusual thing
in England, and so the title has a distinctive meaning.  Of course, in
America, where there is no car which has not what we call an aisle, it
would define nothing.  The corridors are all at one side of the car.
Doors open from thence to little compartments made to seat four, or
perhaps six, persons.  The first-class carriages are very comfortable
indeed, being heavily upholstered in dark, hard-wearing stuffs, with a
bulging rest for the head.  The third-class accommodations on this
train are almost as comfortable as the first-class, and attract a kind
of people that are not usually seen traveling third-class in Europe.
Many people sacrifice their habit, in the matter of this train, to the
fine conditions of the lower fare.

</p><p>One of the feats of the train is an electric button in each
compartment.  Commonly an electric button is placed high on the side of
the carriage as an alarm signal, and it is unlawful to push it unless
one is in serious need of assistance from the guard.  But these bells
also rang in the dining-car, and were supposed to open negotiations
for tea or whatever.  A new function has been projected on an ancient
custom.  No genius has yet appeared to separate these two meanings.
Each bell rings an alarm and a bid for tea or whatever.  It is perfect
in theory then that, if one rings for tea, the guard comes to
interrupt the murder, and that if one is being murdered, the attendant
appears with tea.  At any rate, the guard was forever being called
from his reports and his comfortable seat in the forward end of the
luggage-van by thrilling alarms.  He often prowled the length of the
train with hardihood and determination, merely to meet a request for a
sandwich.

</p><p>The train entered Carlisle at the beginning of twilight.  This
is the border town, and an engine of the Caledonian Railway, manned by
two men of broad speech, came to take the place of the tandem.  The
engine of these men of the North was much smaller than the others, but
her cab was much larger, and would be a fair shelter on a stormy
night.  They had also built seats with hooks by which
   <pb n="283"/>
they hang them to the rail, and thus are still enabled to see
through the round windows without dislocating their necks.  All the
human parts of the cab were covered with oilcloth.  The wind that
swirled from the dim twilight horizon made the warm glow from the
fur-[illustration omitted]nace to be a grateful thing.

</p><p>As the train shot out of Carlisle, a glance backward could
learn of the faint yellow blocks of light from the carriages marked on
the dimmed ground.  The signals were now lamps, and shone palely
against the sky.  The express was entering night as if night were
Scotland.

</p><p>There was a long toil to the summit of the hills, and then
began the booming ride down the slope.  There were many curves.
Sometimes could be seen two or three signal lights at one time,
twisting off in some new direction.  Minus the lights and some yards
of glistening rails, Scotland was only a blend of black and weird
shapes.  Forests which one could hardly imagine as weltering in the
dewy placidity of evening sank to the rear as if the gods had bade
them.  The dark loom of a house quickly dissolved before the eyes.  A
station with its lamps became a broad yellow band that, to a deficient
sense, was only a few yards in length.  Below, in a deep valley, a
silver glare on the waters of a river made equal time with the train.
Signals appeared, grew, and vanished.  In the wind and the mystery of
the night, it was like sailing in an enchanted gloom.  The vague
profiles of hills ran like snakes across the somber sky.  A strange
shape boldly and formidably confronted the train, and then melted to a
long dash of track as clean as sword-blades.

</p><p>The vicinity of Glasgow is unmistakable.  The flames of
pauseless industries are here and there marked on the distance.  Vast
factories stand close to the track, and reaching chimneys emit roseate
flames.  At last one may see upon a wall the strong reflection from
furnaces, and against it the impish and inky figures of workingmen.  A
long, prison-like row of tenements, not at all resembling London, but
in one way resembling New York, appeared to the left, and then sank
out of sight like a phantom.

</p><p>At last the driver stopped the brave effort of his engine.  The
100 miles were come to the edge.  The average speed of forty-nine and
one-third miles each hour had been made, and it remained only to glide
with the hauteur of a great express through the yard and into the
station at Glasgow.

</p><p>A wide and splendid collection of signal-lamps flowed toward the
engine.  With delicacy and care the train clanked over some switches,
passed the signals, and then there shone a great blaze of arc-lamps,
defining the wide sweep of the station roof.  Smoothly, proudly, with
all that vast dignity which had surrounded its exit from London, the
express moved along its platform.  It was the entrance into a gorgeous
drawing-room of a man that was sure of everything.

</p><p>The porters and the people crowded forward.  In their minds
there may have floated dim images of the traditional music-halls, the
bobbies, the 'buses, the 'Arrys and 'Arriets, the swells of London.
</p>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

