<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CutHapp"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="CutHapp">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Happiest Time / By Mary Stewart Cutting</title>
<title type="sort">happiest time by mary stewart cutting</title>
<author>Cutting, Mary Stewart</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>wiretap</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">29</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CutHapp</idno>
<date value="2000">2000</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2000 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475856</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Story from collection.</p>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Little Stories of Married Life</title>
<title type="sort">little stories of married life</title>
<author>Cutting, Mary Stewart Doubleday, 1851-1924</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>McClure, Phillips &amp; Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1902">1902</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  University of Virginia, Alderman Library PS 3505 .U98L5 1902a</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1902">1902</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>feminine</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2000-06">June 2000</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jeffrey D. Feldman, University of Virginia Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI tags and header.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head>The Happiest Time</head>
<p>
"AREN'T you coming to church with me this morning?"
</p><p>
"Well&mdash;not <hi rend="italic">this</hi> morning, I think, petty."
</p><p>
"You <hi rend="italic">said</hi> you would."
</p><p>
"Yes, I know I did, but I have a slight cold. I don't think it would be best
for me, really, petty. I've been working pretty hard this week." Mr. Belmore
carefully deposited a pile of newspapers beside his armchair upon the floor
of the little library, removing and opening the top layer for perusal as
he spoke, his eyes already glued to the headlines. "A quiet day will do me
lots of good. I'll tell you what it is&mdash;I'll promise to go with you next
Sunday if you say so."
</p><p>
"You always promise you'll go next Sunday." Mrs. Belmore, a brown-haired,
clear-eyed young woman in a blue and white spotted morning gown, looked
doubtfully, yet with manifest yielding, at her husband. Mr. Belmore presented
the radiantly clean and peaceful aspect of the man who has risen at nine
o'clock instead of the customary seven, and bathed and dressed in the sweet
unhurried calm that belongs only to the first day of the week, poking dilatorily
among chiffonier drawers, discovering hitherto forgotten garments in his
closet, and leisurely fumbling over a change of shirt-studs before coming
down to consume the breakfast kept waiting for him.
</p><p>
"Of course I know it's your only day at home&mdash;" Mrs. Belmore reverted
to her occupation of deftly setting the chairs in their rightful places,
and straightening the books on the tables. "I suppose I <hi rend="italic">ought</hi> to insist
on your going&mdash;when you promised&mdash;but still&mdash;" She gave a sigh
of relinquishment. "I suppose you <hi rend="italic">do</hi> need the rest," she added. "We
can have a nice afternoon together, anyway. You can finish reading that story
aloud, and we'll go out and take a good look at the garden. I think the beans
were planted too close under the pear tree last year&mdash;that was the reason
they didn't come up right. Edith Barnes and Alan Wilson are coming out from
town after dinner for the rest of the day, but that won't make any difference
to us."
</p><p>
<hi rend="italic">"What?"</hi>
</p><p>
"Now, Herbert, how could I help asking them? You know the boarding-house
she and her mother live in. Edith never gets a chance to see him alone. They're
saving up now to get married&mdash;they've been engaged a year&mdash;so he
can't spend any more money for theatres and things, and they just have to
walk and walk the streets, unless they go visiting, and they've been almost
everywhere, Edith says. She wrote and asked me to have them for this Sunday;
he's been away for a whole week somewhere up in the State. I think it's
pathetic." In the warmth of explanation Mrs. Belmore had unwittingly removed
the pile of newspapers from the floor to an ottoman at the further end of
the room. "Edith says she knows it's the happiest time of their lives, and
she does want to get some of the benefit of it, poor girl."
</p><p>
"What do they want to be engaged for, anyway?"
</p><p>
<hi rend="italic">"Herbert!</hi> How ridiculous! You are the most unreasonable man at times
for a sensible one that I ever laid my eyes on. Why did <hi rend="italic">we</hi> want to
be engaged?"
</p><p>
"That was different." Mr. Belmore's tone conveyed a permanent satisfaction
with his own case. "If every woman were like you, petty&mdash;I never
<hi rend="italic">could</hi> stand Edith, she's one of your clever girls; there's something
about her that always sets my teeth on edge. As for Wilson&mdash;oh, Wilson's
just a usual kind of a fool, like myself. Hello, where are my
newspapers&mdash;and what in thunder makes it so cold? You don't mean to say
you've got the window open?"
</p><p>
Mrs. Belmore had a habit of airing the rooms in the morning, which her husband
approved of theoretically, and combated intensely in practice. After the
window was banged shut she could hear him rattling at the furnace below to
turn on an extra flow of heat before settling down once more in comfort.
Although the April sun was bright, there was still a chill in the air.
</p><p>
She looked in upon him, gowned and bonneted for church, sweet and placid
of mien, followed by two little girls, brave in their Sunday best, all big
hats and ribboned hair and little starchy ruffles showing below their brown
coats. Mrs. Belmore stooped over her husband's chair to kiss him good-by.
</p><p>
"You won't have to talk to Edith and Alan at all," she said, as if continuing
the conversation from where they had left off. "All we have to do is to let
them have the parlor or the library. They'll entertain each other."
</p><p>
"Oh, don't you bother about that. Now go ahead or you'll be late; and don't
forget to say your prayers for me, too. That's right, always go to church
with your mother, girlies."
</p><p>
"I <hi rend="italic">wish</hi> you were going, too." Mrs. Belmore looked at her husband
lingeringly.
</p><p>
"I wish I were, petty," said Mr. Belmore with a prompt mendacity so evidently
inspired by affection that his wife condoned it at once.
</p><p>
She thought of him more than once during the service with generous satisfaction
in his comfortable morning. She wished she had thought it right to remain
at home, too, as she did sometimes, but there were the children to be considered.
But she and Herbert would have the afternoon together, and take part of it
to see about planting the garden, a plot of twenty feet square in the rear
of the suburban villa.
</p><p>
The Sunday visit to the garden was almost a sacrament. They might look at
it on other days, but it was only on Sunday, beginning with the early spring,
that husband and wife strolled around the little patch together, first planning
where to start the summer crop of vegetables and afterward watching the green
things poking their spikes up through the mould, and growing, growing. He
did the planting and working in the long light evenings after he came home,
while she held the papers of seeds for him; but it was only on Sunday that
he could really watch the green things grow, and learn to know each separate
leaf intimately, and count the blossoms on the beans and the cucumbers. From
the pure pleasure of the first radish through all the various wiltings and
shrivelings incident to amateur gardening in summer deluge and drought, to
the triumphant survival of tomato plants and cucumber vines, running riot
over everything in the fall of the year, the little garden played its old
part as paradise to these two, who became more fully one in the watching
of the miracle of growth. When they gathered the pears from the little tree
in the corner of the plot, before the frost, and picked the few little green
tomatoes that remained on the dwindling stems, it was like garnering a store
of peaceful happiness. Every stage of the garden was a romance. Mrs. Belmore
could go to church without her husband, but to have him survey the garden
without her would have been the touch beyond.
</p><p>
It must be horrid, anyway, she thought, to have to go every morning into
town in those smoky cars and crowded ferryboats; just to run into town twice
a week tired her out. Now he would have finished his paper&mdash;now little
Dorothy would have come in, red cheeked from her walk, to kiss daddy before
her nap&mdash;now he must be pottering around among his possessions and looking
out for her. She knew so well how he would look when he came to the door
to meet her. The sudden sight of either one to the other always shed a reflected
light, like the glow of the sun. It was with a feeling of wonder that she
marked its disappearance, after a brief gleam, as he not only opened the
door, but came out on the piazza to greet her, and closed it behind him.
</p><p>
"They're in there&mdash;Edith and Alan." He pointed over his shoulder with
his thumb. "I thought they weren't coming until after dinner."
</p><p>
"Why, they weren't."
</p><p>
"Well, they're in the parlor, just the same. Came out over an hour ago. Great
Scott, I wished I'd gone with you. I'm worn out."
</p><p>
"You don't mean to say you've stayed with them all the time!" Mrs. Belmore
looked scandalized.
</p><p>
"I should say I had; I couldn't lose 'em. Whichever room I went to they followed;
at least she did and he came after. I went from pillar to post, I give you
my word, petty, but Edith had me by the neck; she never let go her grip for
an instant. They won't speak to each other, you see; only to me. I haven't
had a chance to even finish the paper. I've had the deuce of a time! I don't
know what you are going to do about it."
</p><p>
"Never mind; it will be all right now," said Mrs. Belmore reassuringly. She
pushed past him into the parlor, where sat a tall, straight girl with straight,
light brows, a long straight nose, and a straight mouth with a droop at the
corners. In the room beyond, a thickset, dark young man with glasses and
a nervous expression was looking at pictures. It did not require a Solomon
to discover at a glance how the land lay.
</p><p>
If Mrs. Belmore had counted easily on her powers of conciliation she was
disappointed this time. After the dinner, whereat the conversation was dragged
laboriously round four sides of a square, except when the two little girls
made some slight diversion, and the several futile attempts when the meal
was over to leave the lovers alone together, Mrs. Belmore resigned herself,
perforce, to the loss of her cherished afternoon.
</p><p>
"It's no use; we'll have to give up the reading," she said to her husband
rapidly, in one of her comings and goings. "Perhaps later, dear. But it's
really dreadful; here we've been talking of religion and beet-root sugar
and smallpox, when any one can see that her heart is breaking."
</p><p>
"I think he is getting the worst of it," said Mr. Belmore impartially.
</p><p>
"Oh, it won't hurt <hi rend="italic">him</hi>."
</p><p>
"Well, you've given them plenty of opportunities to make up."
</p><p>
"Yes; but he doesn't know how."
</p><p>
She added in a louder tone, "You take Mr. Wilson up to your den for a while,
Herbert; Ethel and I are going to have a cosey little time with the children;
aren't we, dear?"
</p><p>
"Have a cigar?" said Mr. Belmore as the two men seated themselves comfortably
in a couple of wooden armchairs in the sunny little apartment hung with a
miscellaneous collection of guns, swords, and rods, the drawing of a bloated
trout, and a dusty pair of antlers.
</p><p>
"Thank you; I'm not smoking now," said Mr. Wilson with a hungry look at the
open box on the table beside him.
</p><p>
"Oh!" said his host genially, "so you're at that stage of the game. Well,
I've been there myself. You have my sympathy. But this won't last, you know."
</p><p>
"Does your wife like smoking?"
</p><p>
"Loves it," said Mr. Belmore, sinking the fact of his official limit to four
cigars a day. "That is, of course, she thinks it's a dirty habit, and unhealthy,
and all that sort of thing, you know; but it doesn't make any
<hi rend="italic">difference</hi> to her&mdash;not a pin's worth; Cheer up, old fellow; you'll
get to this place, too."
</p><p>
"Looks like it," said the other bitterly. "Here I haven't seen her for a
week&mdash;I came two hundred miles on purpose yesterday, and now she won't
even look at me. I don't know what's the matter&mdash;haven't the least
idea&mdash;and I can't <hi rend="italic">get</hi> her to tell me. I have to be off to-morrow
at seven o'clock, too&mdash;I call it pretty hard lines."
</p><p>
"Let me see," said Mr. Belmore judicially, knitting his brows as if burrowing
into the past as he smoked. "Perhaps I can help you out. What have you been
writing to her? Telling her all about what you've been doing, and just sending
your love at the end? They don't like that, you know."
</p><p>
Mr. Wilson shook his head. "No; upon my soul, I've done nothing but tell
her how I&mdash;how I was looking forward to&mdash;oh, hang it, Belmore, the
letters have been all <hi rend="italic">right</hi>, I know that."
</p><p>
"H'm," said Mr. Belmore, "there's got to be <hi rend="italic">something</hi> back of it,
you know. Seen any girls since you've been gone?"
</p><p>
Mr. Wilson hastened to shake his head more emphatically than before. "Not
one," he asseverated with the relief of complete innocence. "Didn't even
meet a soul I knew, except Brower&mdash;you remember Dick Brower? I went into
a jeweler's to get my glasses mended and found him buying a souvenir spoon
for his fiancee."
</p><p>
"O&mdash;o&mdash;h!" said Mr. Belmore intelligently, "and did you buy a present
for Edith?"
</p><p>
"No, I didn't. She made me promise not to buy anything more for her; she
thinks I'm spending too much money, and that I ought to economize."
</p><p>
"And did you tell her about Brower?"
</p><p>
"Why, of course I did&mdash;as we were coming out this morning."
</p><p>
Mr. Wilson stared blankly at his friend.
</p><p>
"Chump!" said Mr. Belmore. He bit off the end of a new cigar and threw it
away. "Wilson, my poor fellow, you're so besotted in ignorance that I don't
know how to let the light in on you. A man is a fool by the side of his fiancee,
anyhow."
</p><p>
"I don't know what you mean," said the bewildered Wilson stiffly. <hi rend="italic">"I</hi>
don't know what I'm to do."
</p><p>
"No, of course you don't&mdash;but Edith does&mdash;you can just trust her
for that. A girl <hi rend="italic">always</hi> knows what a man ought to do&mdash;she can
give him cards and spades and beat him every time."
</p><p>
"Then why doesn't she <hi rend="italic">tell</hi> me what she wants? I asked her to,
particularly."
</p><p>
"Oh, no! She'll tell you everything the opposite&mdash;that is, half the time.
She'll put every obstacle possible in your way, to see if you're man enough
to walk over 'em; that's what she wants to find out; if you're man enough
to have your own way in spite of her; and, of course, if you aren't, you're
an awful disappointment."
</p><p>
"Are you sure?" said Mr. Wilson deeply, after an awestruck pause. "Half the
time, you say. But how am I to find out when she means&mdash;I give you my
word, Belmore, that I thought&mdash;I suppose I could have brought her a small
present, anyway, in spite of what she said; a souvenir spoon&mdash;but she
hates souvenir spoons."
</p><p>
"You'll have to cipher it out for yourself, old man," said Mr. Belmore.
<hi rend="italic">"I</hi> don't set out to interpret any woman's moods. I only give you cold,
bare facts. But if I were you," he added impartially, "I'd go down after
a while and try and get her alone, you know, and say something. You can,
if you try." A swish of skirts outside of the open door made Mr. Wilson jump
forward as Mrs. Belmore came in sight with her friend. The latter had her
arm around the older woman, and her form drooped toward her as they passed
the two men. The eyes of the girl were red, and her lips had a patient quiver.
Mr. Wilson gave an exclamation and sprang forward as she disappeared in the
further room.
</p><p>
It was some hours later that the husband and wife met unexpectedly upon the
stairs with a glad surprise.
</p><p>
"You don't mean to say it's you&mdash;alone!" he whispered.
</p><p>
"Wait&mdash;is she coming up?" They clutched each other spasmodically as they
listened to the sound of a deflecting footstep. There was a breathless moment,
and then the chords of a funeral march boomed forth upon the air. The loud
pedal was doing its best to supplement those long and strenuous fingers.
</p><p>
The listeners breathed a sigh of relief.
</p><p>
"He's gone to the station for a time table," whispered the husband with a
delighted grin; "though I can stand him all right. We had a nice walk with
the little girls, after he got tired of playing hide and seek. I wished you
were with us. You must be about used up. How are you getting along with her?"
</p><p>
"Oh, pretty well." She let herself be drawn down on the hall window seat
at the top of the landing. "You see, Edith really feels dreadfully, poor
girl,"
</p><p>
"What about?"
</p><p>
"Herbert, she isn't really sure that she loves him."
</p><p>
"Isn't sure! After they've been engaged for a year!"
</p><p>
"That's just it. She says if they had been married out of hand, in the first
flush of the novelty, she wouldn't have had time, perhaps, to have any doubts.
But it's the seeing him all the time that's made her think."
</p><p>
"Made her think <hi rend="italic">what?"</hi>
</p><p>
"Whether she loves him or not; whether they are really suited. I remember
that I used to feel that way about you, dear. Oh, you know, Herbert, it's
a very serious thing for a girl. She says she knows her whole life is at
stake; she thinks about it all the time."
</p><p>
"How about his?"
</p><p>
"Well, that's what I said," admitted Mrs. Belmore. "She says that she feels
that <hi rend="italic">he</hi> is so rational and self-poised that she makes little difference
in his life either way&mdash;it has come to her all at once. She says his
looking at everything in a matter-of-fact way just chills her; she longs
for a whole-souled enthusiasm that can sweep everything before it. She feels
that if they are married she will have to keep up the ideal for both of them,
and she doesn't know whether she can."
</p><p>
"No, she can't," said Mr. Belmore.
</p><p>
"She says she could if she loved him enough," pursued Mrs. Belmore. "It's
the if that kills her. She says that when she wakes up in the morning she
feels as if she'd die if she didn't see him before night, and when she
<hi rend="italic">does</hi> see him it's all a dreadful disappointment to her; she can't
talk to him at all, she feels perfectly hard and stony; then, the moment
he's gone, she's crazy to have him back again. She cries herself thin over
it."
</p><p>
"She's pretty bony, anyway," said Mr. Belmore impartially.
</p><p>
"Even his appearance changes to her. She says sometimes he looks like a Greek
god, so that she could go down on her knees to him, and at other
times&mdash; Once she happened to catch a glimpse of him in a horrid
red sweater, polishing his shoes, and she said she didn't get over it for
weeks; he looked positively <hi rend="italic">ordinary</hi>&mdash;like some of the men you
see in the trolley cars."
</p><p>
"Oh, good gracious!" protested Mr. Belmore feebly. "Oh, good <hi rend="italic">gracious</hi>,
petty! This is <hi rend="italic">too</hi> much."
</p><p>
"Hush&mdash;don't laugh so loud&mdash;be quiet," said his wife anxiously.
</p><p>
"If Wilson <hi rend="italic">ever</hi> looks like a Greek god to her, she's all right, she
loves him&mdash;you can tell her so for me. <hi rend="italic">Wilson!</hi> Here are we sitting
up here like a pair of lovers, and they&mdash;Hello!"
</p><p>
The hall door opened and shut, the piano lid closed simultaneously with a
bang, and there was a swirl of skirts again toward the staircase that scattered
the guilty pair on the landing. The hostess heaved a patient sigh.
</p><p>
"They <hi rend="italic">shall</hi> speak," said Mrs. Belmore when another hour had gone with
the situation still unchanged. Her gentle voice had a note of determination.
"I can't understand why he doesn't <hi rend="italic">make</hi> her. She is literally crying
her eyes out, because the whole day has been lost. Why didn't you send him
into the parlor for a book, as I told you to, when I came up to take care
of Dorothy?"
</p><p>
"He wouldn't go&mdash;he said he wasn't doing the kindergarten act any more.
Hang it, I don't blame him. A man objects to being made a fool of before
people, and he's tired of it. Here he goes off again to-morrow for two weeks,
and she with no more heart than&mdash;"
</p><p>
"Where is he now?" asked Mrs. Belmore.
</p><p>
"Upstairs in my room, smoking."
</p><p>
<hi rend="italic">"Smoking!</hi> I thought he'd promised her solemnly not to smoke."
</p><p>
"Yes, he did; but he says he doesn't care a&mdash;red apple; he's going to
have some comfort out of the day. I've left him with a box of cigars; good
ones, too. He's having the time of his life."
</p><p>
"O&mdash;o&mdash;h!" said Mrs. Belmore, with the rapt expression of one who
sees beyond the veil. When she spoke it was with impressive slowness. "When
you hear me come downstairs with Edith and go in the parlor, you wait a moment
and then bring him down&mdash;<hi rend="italic">with his cigar</hi>&mdash;into the library.
Do you understand?"
</p><p>
"No," said Mr. Belmore.
</p><p>
"Oh, Herbert! If she sees him <hi rend="italic">smoking</hi>&mdash;! There's no time to lose,
for I have to get tea to-night. When I call you, leave him and come at once,
do you hear? Don't stop a minute&mdash;just come, before they get a chance
to follow."
</p><p>
"You bet I'll come," said Mr. Belmore, "like a bird to its&mdash;I will, really,
petty."
</p><p>
That he nearly knocked her down by his wildly tragic rush when she called
from the back hall, "Herbert, please come at once! I can't turn off the water,"
was a mere detail&mdash;they clung to each other in silent laughter, behind
the enshrouding portieres, not daring to move. The footfall of the deserted
Edith was heard advancing from the front room to the library, and her clear
and solemn voice, as of one actuated only by the lofty dictates of duty,
penetrated distinctly to the listeners.
</p><p>
"Alan Wilson, is it possible that you are <hi rend="italic">smoking?</hi> Have you broken
your promised word?"
</p><p>
"Well, they're at it at last," said Mr. Belmore, relapsing into a chair in
the kitchen with a sigh of relief, and drawing a folded newspaper from his
pocket. "I wouldn't be in his shoes for a farm."
</p><p>
"Oh, it will be all right now," said Mrs. Belmore serenely. She added with
some irrelevancy, "I've left the children to undress each other; they've
been <hi rend="italic">so</hi> good. It's been such a different day, though, from what we
had planned."
</p><p>
"It's too bad that you have to get the tea."
</p><p>
"Oh, I don't mind that a bit."
</p><p>
She had tucked up the silken skirt of her gown and was deftly measuring out
coffee&mdash;after the swift, preliminary shaking of the fire with which every
woman takes possession of a kitchen&mdash;pouring the water into the coffee-pot
from the steaming kettle, and then vibrating between the kitchen closet and
the butler's pantry with the quick, capable movements of one who knows her
ground thoroughly. "Really, it isn't any trouble. Margaret leaves half of
the things ready, you know. If you'll just lift down that dish of salad for
me&mdash;and the cold chicken is beside it. I hate to ask you to get up,
but&mdash;Thank you. How good the coffee smells! I know you always like the
coffee I make."
</p><p>
"You bet I do," said Mr. Belmore with fervor. "Say, petty, you don't think
you could come out now and take a look at the garden? I'm almost sure the
peas are beginning to show."
</p><p>
"No; I'm afraid there isn't time. We'll have to give it up for this Sunday."
She paused for a great effort. "If you'd like to go by yourself, dear&mdash;"
</p><p>
"Wouldn't you mind?"
</p><p>
She paused again, looking at him with her clear-eyed seriousness.
</p><p>
"I don't think I mind now, but I might&mdash;afterward."
</p><p>
If he had hesitated, it was for a hardly appreciable second. "And I don't
want to go," he protested stoutly, "it wouldn't be the same thing at all
without you."
</p><p>
&mdash;"Everything is ready now," said his wife. "Though I do hate to disturb Edith
and Alan. I'll just run up and hear the children say their prayers before
I put those things on the table. If you would just take a look at the
furnace"&mdash;it was the sentence Mr. Belmore had been dreading&mdash;"and
then you can come up and kiss the children good-night."
</p><p>
Mr. Belmore, on his way up from stoking, caught a glimpse projected from
the parlor mirror through an aperture in the doorway which the portieres
had left uncovered. The reflection was of a girl, with tear-stained face
and closed eyes, her head upon a young man's shoulder, while his lips were
touchingly pressed to her hair. The picture might have been called "After
the Storm," the wreckage was so plainly apparent. As Mr. Belmore turned after
ascending the flight of stairs he came full in sight of another picture,
spread out to view in the room at the end of the hall. He stood unseen in
the shadow regarding it.
</p><p>
His wife sat in a low chair near one of the two white beds; little Dorothy's
crib was in their room beyond. The three children were perched on the foot
of the nearest bed, white-gowned, with rosy faces and neatly brushed hair.
While he looked, the youngest child gave a birdlike flutter and jump, and
lighted on the floor, falling on her knees, with her bowed head in the mother's
lap, her hands upraised. As she finished the murmured prayer, helped by the
tender mother voice, she rose and stood to one side, in infantine seriousness,
while the next one spread her white, plumes for the same flight, waiting
afterward in reverent line with the first as the third hovered down.
</p><p>
It was plain to see from the mother's face that she had striven to put all
earthly thoughts aside in the performance of this sacred office of ministering
to innocence; her eyes must be holy when her children's looked up at her
on their way to God.
</p><p>
This was the little inner chapel, the Sanctuary of Home, where she was priestess
by Divine right. It would have been an indifferent man, indeed, who had not
fallen upon his knees in spirit, in company with this little household of
faith, in mute recognition of the love and peace and order that crowned his
days.
</p><p>
He kissed the laughing children as they clung to him, before she turned down
the light. When she came out of the room he was waiting for her. He put his
arm around her as he said, with the darling tenderness that made her life:
</p><p>
"Come along, old sweetness. We've got to go down and stir up those lunatics
again. Call <hi rend="italic">that</hi> 'the happiest time of your life!' <hi rend="italic">We</hi> know
better than that, don't we, petty? I'll tell you what it is: I'll go to church
with you next Sunday, if you say so!"

</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
