<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DavAged"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="DavAged">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Middle-Aged Woman</title>
<title type="sort">middle aged woman</title>
<author>Davis, Rebecca Harding, 1831-1910</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">18</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">DavAged</idno>
<date value="1999">1999</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1999 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475858</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Middle-Aged Woman</title>
<title level="j">Scribner`s Monthly</title>
<title type="sort">middle aged woman</title>
<author>Rebecca Harding Davis</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>22 v. : ill. ; 24-25 cm.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner &amp; Co</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1875">1871-1881</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: UVa Library, AP2.C4 V. 10 1875</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This article appeared in v. 10, no. 3 (July 1875), p. 345-347.</p>
</note>
<note>
<p>The article is not signed and is attibuted to "R.D.H" in the table of contents.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1875">1875</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>feminine</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1999-01">January, 1999</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jennifer Easley, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">

<div1 type="article" id="d3">
<head>
THE MIDDLE-AGED WOMAN.
</head>

<pb n="345"/>
<p>CHOOSE any artist that you know    &mdash;    the one with the kindliest
nature and the finest perceptions    &mdash;    and ask him to give you his idea
of the genius of the commonplace, and any word for it, he paints
you a middle-aged woman.  The thing, he will say, proves itself.
Here is a creature jogging on leisurely at midday in the sight of all
men along a well-tramped road.  The mists of dawn are far behind
her; she has not yet reached the shadows of evening.  The softness
and blushes, and shy, sparkling glances of the girl she was, have
long been absorbed into muddy thick skin, sodden outlines, rational
eyes.  There are crows' feet at either temple, and yellowish blotches
on the flesh below the soggy under-jaw.  Her chestnut-brown hair
used to warm and glitter in the sun, and after a few years it will
make a white crown upon her head, a sacred halo to her children;
but just now it is stiff with a greasy hair dye, and is of an unclean
and indescribable hue.

</p><p>Young girls, with that misty dawn about them, may lack both
beauty and wit; but there is a charm in their fresh untainted
homeliness, in the ardor of their foolishness.  They pour forth their
thoughts in silly school essays, and they seem to run no deeper than
roses and moonlight and eternal friendships.  They talk all day long
about their lovers and pretty finery, and we listen with delight to it
all, and do not ask for common sense any more than we would in
the chatter of the swallows building their nests.  It is the fresh
morning air which blows about them and revives us.  It is because
they "bear white shields of expectation."

</p><p>But the middle-aged woman expects nothing; she has proved,
gauged it all.  She does not carry a white shield, that we all can see,
but a basket of undarned stockings.  Her talk is of butter and cures
of catarrh, and if she adverts to roses, it is to tell you the secret of
her success in raising them and the manure which they prefer.

</p><p>What can any artist, with either pen or pencil, make of this bare
ordinary shape?  Shakespeare himself, driven to the limning of her
can only

</p><lg type="verse">
<l>"Let husbands know
</l><l>Their wives have sense like them; they see, and smell,
</l><l>And have their palates, both for sweet and sour."
</l></lg>

<p>The average American husband does not lack such practical
knowledge of his wife.  There may have been an uncertain glamour
about her in the days when she stood, half child, half woman, trying
to unbar with her soft pink-tinted hand certain doors of life.  It may
gather around her again in old age, when the dreadful prophetic
shadow begins to fall upon her gray head.  But in middle-age she is
the unromantic center of an unromantic world of daily dinners,
anxieties about children, and worries about cooks and
chambermaid.  Underneath all this the husband may have a dateless
love, even passion for his wife, just as he has a stone foundation for
the house he lives in.  But he does not drag his friends down to the
cellar every day to examine his foundation; and he does not pose at
his wife's feet in public, or write verses in her honor.  When his
affection takes that form of chills and fever there is a strong
probability that poses and verses will some day be tested in a
divorce suit.

</p><p>It is certain, however, that this woman, just at the age when the
poet and novelist will have none of her, is the fittest subject for the
student of human nature.  After thirty her whims have hardened into
prejudices, her foibles into character.  There she is unmistakably,
domestic machine, fool, saint.  The features of the landscape are
surely best seen at high noon.  If the misty romance is gone from
her it is because she grapples now with the real pain and joy and
devils that beset life.  Dolly at sixteen finds herself neglected at a
ball, and writes in her diary of relentless destiny, of intolerable
loneliness.  At forty she finds herself a widow, penniless, with half
a dozen children, and goes out bravely to get machine-sewing to do.
At sixteen she weeps poetic tears over the fate of the lost Pleiad;
some day she will lay her little baby in the grave and go on with her
work, carrying a cheerful face through the house "for the sake of
father and the boys;" only at night, when she misses the little hand
fumbling at her breast, daring to cry her bitter tears out upon her
pillow, when none but God can see or hear.

</p><p>Whoever would gain a clear idea of the condition of American
society, too, must take the middle-aged woman as the index.  The
generation of gray-headed grandmothers are carrying out of the
world its old-fashioned


<pb n="346"/>

prejudices; the young woman is in an uneasy transition stage, not
quite sure whether she would rather next week write a book, be
married, or perform a capital operation in surgery.

</p><p>But take a woman of forty anywhere in the States, and you have
an embodied history and prophecy of the social condition of the
country, practical and minute as you can find nowhere else except
in a daily newspaper.

</p><p>If you have a curiosity, for example, to inspect the development
of woman from the fifteenth century until now, there is no need of
materialized spirits to make up the panorama.  For the beginning,
take a horse or mule, and penetrate for a hundred miles or two the
mountains of North Carolina, making friends as you go with the
farmers' wives.  There is her biography written, page after page,
clearer than type.  If you want white villanage, go into the hovels in
the Nantahela range, where your hostess shall give you corn-cakes
and fried opossum (which you eat with your fingers), and rye coffee
poured into a gourd.  This matron has, therefore, no dishes to wash
and no beds to make, as by an ingenious contrivance the boards of
the floor are lifted at night, disclosing a trench filled with straw, in
which the whole family kennel.  Life is reduced for her to the
simple elements of child-bearing and eating as necessities, and the
luxury of wearing a hoop-skirt (which invariably hangs on the wall)
under the calico rag yclept a dress.

</p><p>Down in the gorges cut by the Okonalufta you will find a house
made of a dozen log huts squatted together with open passage-ways
between, through which a cart could be driven.  Pigs and chickens run
riot through these passages in summer, and bears in winter come down at
night and peer curiously into them.  My friend, Mistress Pitloe, is the
head of this household.  Her loom, heavy and home-made, with logs for
beams, stands in one of the passages.  The indigo-dyed cloth, which she,
her husband and sons, all wear, was sheared in the wool, carded, spun,
woven, and sewed by herself.  She is a tall, raw-boned woman of fifty,
scrupulously clean, with grizzled hair drawn back from the dark,
clear-cut face, which betrays her French Huguenot descent.  Squire
Pitloe (Colonel in the war) is the wealthiest farmer in the country, a
knowing politician, as politics go there.  His son edits "The Haywood
County Times."  In Pennsylvania his wife would drive her old horses and
family carriage into town, and in her seeded black silk preside as
chairman of committees on jelly or pianos at the State fair.  But
Mistress Pitloe, as she is called, has not left the farm for five years;
her chances for reading consists of the Bible and a yellow pile of
Baptist tracts which lie on the chest of drawers.  They belonged to her
father, she tells you, but she never has had time to read them.

</p><p>Her house has not a glass window in it; the walls inside show the
bare logs with the mud chunking; empty boxes serve for chairs; but
she has hung white homespun netting from ceiling to floor; the
delicate cleanliness everywhere, the very smell of the drying herbs
overhead, somehow convince you that you are in the house of a
chaste wife and careful mother.

</p><p>She goes afield every day with the Squire and the farm-hands
(both white and black) to plow or hoe corn, and hurries back to help
the negro cook with the dinner.  When it is served, she sits down
with her husband and sons, but only to wait on them; she eats with
the servants, and is held in effect their social companion and equal.
Yet, if you talk with her for an hour, you find her more keen-witted
and just than any man of the household; she will give you shrewd
hints of the real condition of the freed slaves or polygamous
Cherokees about her    &mdash;    a condition her husband has hardly yet
suspected to exist.  But it has not yet occurred to her that
emancipation waits for her.  She is no more inclined to question the
limitations which make a beast of burden of her, than she is to
quarrel with the monotonous hill-ranges, clad in the funereal black
of the balsam, that have shut her in since her birth.

</p><p>I tremble to think of the consequences should Mrs. Fanning, or
any other emancipated Bostonian, be tempted next summer to
penetrate this prison-house of nature, and share the fried chicken
and corn bread of Squire Pitloe at his boarding rate of one dollar per
week.  How her freed soul would yearn to carry back Mistress
Pitloe, and produce her in the parlors of the Radical Club as she
might a bone of the Megalosaurus, or any other relic of an extinct
era!

</p><p>But I am tolerably sure that grave, slow-spoken Mistress Pitloe
would put this lady, or any other reformer, outside of her gates in
two days' time.  To her, and to her like, an unusual idea of any sort
has always something in it of indecent and devilish.

</p><p>Could any contrast be stronger in Mrs. Fanning's eyes than that
of this obscure, gray-headed

<pb n="347"/>

drudge, and brilliant little Mrs. Pettit, whose thoughts and
opinions everybody has heard, but who is only known in the flesh to
a small coterie in New York?  She is too diffident to appear in
public as lecturer or even reader, and too unconventional to tolerate
the fashionable mobs of society.  People who have been stirred by
her trenchant editorials, or have felt the tears rise and their hearts
soften at the pathos of her poems, manage with difficulty to
penetrate to her home, and are amazed to find a little roly-poly,
rose-tinted, merry dot of a woman, busied with orphan asylums, or
cr&egrave;ches for babies, or any other business which will bring
children about her.  Her husband is Professor J. Petit, well known to
the scientific world; he confesses that for much of the research in
German libraries, and all the statistics of his great work on "The
Political History of European Peoples," we are indebted to his wife,
who felt it her duty to be his helpmate in that work as much as in
preparing the delicious game suppers in which his soul delights.

</p><p>During the last two years, as all the writing world knows, Mrs.
Petit has had charge of one of the leading monthly periodicals of the
country, the popular author whose name weights it as editor being
only a figure-head for the public eye.  She has a little closet of an
office in the publishing house, where she sits for five hours each
day in close-fitting gown of brown serge, grappling with the heap of
manuscripts that grows with every mail.  There is probably no
subject or fact known to modern thought with which she is not thus
brought in contact in the course of the year.  At 4 P. M. she locks
her office door, and goes home, and there is not a more picturesque,
or better-dressed woman, or daintier dinner in New York, than those
which welcome her husband, and her boys an hour later.  Her sons
are very proud of their little mother; there is nothing which she does
not know, they will tell you, though perhaps babies and pottery are
her strong points.  She is infallible in questions of teething, and
doles out the most advanced theories of hygiene to young mothers.
Collectors of rare china, or Japanese bronzes, take their specimens
to her for a final verdict; indeed, one can hardly tell whether her
touch is more affectionate and tender when handling a new-born
baby or an old cracked tea-pot.

</p><p>But, after all, Mrs. Petit, pen in hand in her office, and Mistress
Pitloe holding the plow, have only taken different handles of the
same electric battery.  As far as each is able, she is making life
healthfuller and cheerfuller, and nearer to God for her husband and
children and neighbors, whether these last mean a few half-breed
Indians or the hundred thousand readers of a magazine.  It is
precisely the same work as that of countless other unpicturesque,
middle-aged women, from Maine woods to Pennsylvania villages,
or California ranches    &mdash;    the great, decent, religious, unknown
majority, never to be interviewed, or published in any shape, out of
those daily lives grow the modesties, the strength, the virtue of
American homes, the safety of our future.

</p><p>Such women, whether they be wives of millionaires or laborers,
always make real again in the world the one poetic ideal of a
middle-aged woman    &mdash;    Bunyan's Christiana, who set out with her
little ones along the weary way from the City of Destruction to the dark
flood which barred heaven from them.  It is worth while for wives and
mothers, even now in 1875, to read of her daily work    &mdash;    how she
urged her boys, and carried her babies in her arms, and did not fall
into the Slough of Despond, as her husband had done, and never forgot to
take Mercy along with her.  How one day her task was to face Apollyon,
and the next, to "cure Matthew of stomach-gripes from eating green
apples."  How there gathered about her, in the course of the long,
painful journey, children's children and friends, and the poor, the
lame, and the blind, and walked with her, and were a joyous, happy
company, until the end came.  There is nothing to me more pathetic in
any history than the words which tell of how one day the messenger came
to this gray-haired woman to say that her work as wife and mother at
last was done.  Then she called her children about her, and was
gladdened in that last hour to see that they had kept their garments so
white; and after she had put them in the care of her old friends, she
went down with a beckon of farewell into the dark river, beyond which
the gate stood open where her Lord waited for her, and the husband of
her youth, and was seen no more.

</p><p>"And at her departure her children wept.  But Greatheart played
upon the well-tuned cymbal and the harp for joy."
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
