<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DouAppe"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="DouAppe">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">An Appeal to Congress for Impartial Suffrage</title>
<title type="sort">appeal to congress for impartial suffrage</title>
<author>Douglass, Frederick, 1817?-1895</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">25</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">DouAppe</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475878</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">An Appeal to Congress for Impartial Suffrage</title>
<title type="sort">appeal to congress for impartial suffrage</title>
<author>Frederick Douglass</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<date value="1867-01">January 1867</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>19</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 112-117</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Any other pertinent information, e.g spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of
the text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for
page one of Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1867">1867</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term>
<term>democracy</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-02">February 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>changed COCOA tags to TEI tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
<pb n="112"/>
<head>
Douglass, Frederick.  "An Appeal to Congress for Impartial Suffrage."
<lb/>
Atlantic Monthly 19 (Jan. 1867): 112-117.
</head>
<p>A VERY limited statement of the argument for impartial
suffrage, and for including the negro in the body politic, would
require more space than can be reasonably asked here.  It is
supported by reasons as broad as the nature of man, and as numerous
as the wants of society.  Man is the only government-making animal
in the world.  His right to a participation in the production and
operation of government is an inference from his nature, as direct
and self-evident as is his right to acquire property or education.
It is no less a crime against the manhood of a man, to declare that
he shall not share in the making and directing of the government
under which he lives, than to say that he shall not acquire
property and education.  The fundamental and unanswerable argument
in favor of the enfranchisement of the negro is found in the
undisputed fact of his manhood.  He is a man, and by every fact and
argument by which any man can sustain his right to vote, the negro
can sustain his right equally.  It is plain that, if the right
belongs to any, it belongs to all.  The doctrine that some men have
no rights that others are bound to respect, is a doctrine which we
must banish as we have banished slavery, from which it emanated.
If black men have no rights in the eyes of white men, of course the
whites can have none in the eyes of the blacks.  The result is a
war of races, and the annihilation of all proper human relations.
</p><p>But suffrage for the negro, while easily sustained upon
abstract principles, demands consideration upon what are recognized
as the urgent necessities of
<pb n="113"/>
the case.  It is a measure of
relief, &mdash; a shield to break the force of a blow already descending
with violence, and render it harmless.  The work of destruction has
already been set in motion all over the South.  Peace to the
country has literally meant war to the loyal men of the South,
white and black; and negro suffrage is the measure to arrest and
put an end to that dreadful strife.
</p><p>Something then, not by way of argument, (for that has been
done by Charles Sumner, Thaddeus Stevens, Wendell Phillips, Gerrit
Smith, and other able men,) but rather of statement and appeal.
</p><p>For better or for worse, (as in some of the old marriage
ceremonies,) the negroes are evidently a permanent part of the
American population.  They are too numerous and useful to be
colonized, and too enduring and self-perpetuating to disappear by
natural causes.  Here they are, four millions of them, and, for
weal or for woe, here they must remain.  Their history is parallel
to that of the country; but while the history of the latter has
been cheerful and bright with blessings, theirs has been heavy and
dark with agonies and curses.  What O'Connell said of the history
of Ireland may with greater truth be said of the negro's.  It may
be "traced like a wounded man through a crowd, by the blood."  Yet
the negroes have marvellously survived all the exterminating forces
of slavery, and have emerged at the end of two hundred and fifty
years of bondage, not morose, misanthropic, and revengeful, but
cheerful, hopeful, and forgiving.  They now stand before Congress
and the country, not complaining of the past, but simply asking for
a better future.  The spectacle of these dusky millions thus
imploring, not demanding, is touching; and if American statesmen
could be moved by a simple appeal to the nobler elements of human
nature, if they had not fallen, seemingly, into the incurable habit
of weighing and measuring every proposition of reform by some
standard of profit and loss, doing wrong from choice, and right
only from necessity or some urgent demand of human selfishness, it
would be enough to plead for the negroes on the score of past
services and sufferings.  But no such appeal shall be relied on
here.  Hardships, services, sufferings, and sacrifices are all
waived.  It is true that they came to the relief of the country at
the hour of its extremest need.  It is true that, in many of the
rebellious States, they were almost the only reliable friends the
nation had throughout the whole tremendous war.  It is true that,
notwithstanding their alleged ignorance, they were wiser than their
masters, and knew enough to be loyal, while those masters only knew
enough to be rebels and traitors.  It is true that they fought side
by side in the loyal cause with our gallant and patriotic white
soldiers, and that, but for their help, &mdash; divided as the loyal
States were, &mdash; the Rebels might have succeeded in breaking up the
Union, thereby entailing border wars and troubles of unknown
duration and incalculable calamity.  All this and more is true of
these loyal negroes.  Many daring exploits will be told to their
credit.  Impartial history will paint them as men who deserved well
of their country.  It will tell how they forded and swam rivers,
with what consummate address they evaded the sharp-eyed Rebel
pickets, how they toiled in the darkness of night through the
tangled marshes of briers and thorns, barefooted and weary, running
the risk of losing their lives, to warn our generals of Rebel
schemes to surprise and destroy our loyal army.  It will tell how
these poor people, whose rights we still despised, behaved to our
wounded soldiers, when found cold, hungry, and bleeding on the
deserted battle-field; how they assisted our escaping prisoners
from Andersonville, Belle Isle, Castle Thunder, and elsewhere,
sharing with them their wretched crusts, and otherwise affording
them aid and comfort; how they promptly responded to the trumpet
call for their services, fighting against a foe that denied them
the rights of civilized warfare, and for a government which was
without the courage to assert those rights and avenge
<pb n="114"/>
their
violation in their behalf; with what gallantry they flung
themselves upon Rebel fortifications, meeting death as fearlessly
as any other troops in the service.  But upon none of these things
is reliance placed.  These facts speak to the better dispositions
of the human heart; but they seem of little weight with the
opponents of impartial suffrage.
</p><p>It is true that a strong plea for equal suffrage might be
addressed to the national sense of honor.  Something, too, might be
said of national gratitude.  A nation might well hesitate before
the temptation to betray its allies.  There is something
immeasurably mean, to say nothing of the cruelty, in placing the
loyal negroes of the South under the political power of their Rebel
masters.  To make peace with our enemies is all well enough; but to
prefer our enemies and sacrifice our friends, &mdash; to exalt our enemies
and cast down our friends, &mdash; to clothe our enemies, who sought the
destruction of the government, with all political power, and leave
our friends powerless in their hands, &mdash; is an act which need not be
characterized here.  We asked the negroes to espouse our cause, to
be our friends, to fight for us, and against their masters; and
now, after they have done all that we asked them to do, &mdash; helped us
to conquer their masters, and thereby directed toward themselves
the furious hate of the vanquished, &mdash; it is proposed in some
quarters to turn them over to the political control of the common
enemy of the government and of the negro.  But of this let nothing
be said in this place.  Waiving humanity, national honor, the
claims of gratitude, the precious satisfaction arising from deeds
of charity and justice to the weak and defenceless, &mdash; the appeal for
impartial suffrage addresses itself with great pertinency to the
darkest, coldest, and flintiest side of the human heart, and would
wring righteousness from the unfeeling calculations of human
selfishness.
</p><p>For in respect to this grand measure it is the good fortune of
the negro that enlightened selfishness, not less than justice,
fights on his side.  National interest and national duty, if
elsewhere separated, are firmly united here.  The American people
can, perhaps, afford to brave the censure of surrounding nations
for the manifest injustice and meanness of excluding its faithful
black soldiers from the ballot-box, but it cannot afford to allow
the moral and mental energies of rapidly increasing millions to be
consigned to hopeless degradation.
</p><p>Strong as we are, we need the energy that slumbers in the
black man's arm to make us stronger.  We want no longer any heavy-footed, melancholy service from the negro.  We want the cheerful
activity of the quickened manhood of these sable millions.  Nor can
we afford to endure the moral blight which the existence of a
degraded and hated class must necessarily inflict upon any people
among whom such a class may exist.  Exclude the negroes as a class
from political rights, &mdash; teach them that the high and manly
privilege of suffrage is to be enjoyed by white citizens only, &mdash;
that they may bear the burdens of the state, but that they are to
have no part in its direction or its honors, &mdash; and you at once
deprive them of one of the main incentives to manly character and
patriotic devotion to the interests of the government; in a word,
you stamp them as a degraded <hi rend="italic">caste</hi>, &mdash; you teach them to despise
themselves, and all others to despise them.  Men are so constituted
that they largely derive their ideas of their abilities and their
possibilities from the settled judgments of their fellow-men, and
especially from such as they read in the institutions under which
they live.  If these bless them, they are blest indeed; but if
these blast them, they are blasted indeed.  Give the negro the
elective franchise, and you give him at once a powerful motive for
all noble exertion, and make him a man among men.  A character is
demanded of him, and here as elsewhere demand favors supply.  It is
nothing against this reasoning that all men who vote are not good
men or good citizens.  It is enough that the
<pb n="115"/>
possession and
exercise of the elective franchise is in itself an appeal to the
nobler elements of manhood, and imposes education as essential to
the safety of society.
</p><p>To appreciate the full force of this argument, it must be
observed, that disfranchisement in a republican government based
upon the idea of human equality and universal suffrage, is a very
different thing from disfranchisement in governments based upon the
idea of the divine right of kings, or the entire subjugation of the
masses.  Masses of men can take care of themselves.  Besides, the
disabilities imposed upon all are necessarily without that bitter
and stinging element of invidiousness which attaches to
disfranchisement in a republic.  What is common to all works no
special sense of degradation to any.  But in a country like ours,
where men of all nations, kindred, and tongues are freely
enfranchised, and allowed to vote, to say to the negro, You shall
not vote, is to deal his manhood a staggering blow, and to burn
into his soul a bitter and goading sense of wrong, or else work in
him a stupid indifference to all the elements of a manly character.
As a nation, we cannot afford to have amongst us either this
indifference and stupidity, or that burning sense of wrong.  These
sable millions are too powerful to be allowed to remain either
indifferent or discontented.  Enfranchise them, and they become
self-respecting and country-loving citizens.  Disfranchise them,
and the mark of Cain is set upon them less mercifully than upon the
first murderer, for no man was to hurt him.  But this mark of
inferiority &mdash; all the more palpable because of a difference of
color &mdash; not only dooms the negro to be a vagabond, but makes him the
prey of insult and outrage everywhere.  While nothing may be urged
here as to the past services of the negro, it is quite within the
line of this appeal to remind the nation of the possibility that a
time may come when the services of the negro may be a second time
required.  History is said to repeat itself, and, if so, having
wanted the negro once, we may want him again.  Can that
statesmanship be wise which would leave the negro good ground to
hesitate, when the exigencies of the country required his prompt
assistance?  Can that be sound statesmanship which leaves millions
of men in gloomy discontent, and possibly in a state of alienation
in the day of national trouble?  Was not the nation stronger when
two hundred thousand sable soldiers were hurled against the Rebel
fortifications, than it would have been without them?  Arming the
negro was an urgent military necessity three years ago, &mdash; are we
sure that another quite as pressing may not await us?  Casting
aside all thought of justice and magnanimity, is it wise to impose
upon the negro all the burdens involved in sustaining government
against foes within and foes without, to make him equal sharer in
all sacrifices for the public good, to tax him in peace and
conscript him in war, and then coldly exclude him from the ballot-box?
</p><p>Look across the sea.  Is Ireland, in her present condition,
fretful, discontented, compelled to support an establishment in
which she does not believe, and which the vast majority of her
people abhor, a source of power or of weakness to Great Britain?
Is not Austria wise in removing all ground of complaint against her
on the part of Hungary?  And does not the Emperor of Russia act
wisely, as well as generously, when he not only breaks up the
bondage of the serf, but extends him all the advantages of Russian
citizenship?  Is the present movement in England in favor of
manhood suffrage &mdash; for the purpose of bringing four millions of
British subjects into full sympathy and co-operation with the
British government &mdash; a wise and humane movement, or otherwise?  Is
the existence of a rebellious element in our borders &mdash; which New
Orleans, Memphis, and Texas show to be only disarmed, but at heart
as malignant as ever, only waiting for an opportunity to reassert
<pb n="116"/>
itself with fire and sword &mdash; a reason for leaving four
millions of the nation's truest friends with just cause of
complaint against the Federal government?  If the doctrine that
taxation should go hand in hand with representation can be appealed
to in behalf of recent traitors and rebels, may it not properly be
asserted in behalf of a people who have ever been loyal and
faithful to the government?  The answers to these questions are too
obvious to require statement.  Disguise it as we may, we are still
a divided nation.  The Rebel States have still an anti-national
policy.  Massachusetts and South Carolina may draw tears from the
eyes of our tender-hearted President by walking arm in arm into his
Philadelphia Convention, but a citizen of Massachusetts is still an
alien in the Palmetto State.  There is that, all over the South,
which frightens Yankee industry, capital, and skill from its
borders.  We have crushed the Rebellion, but not its hopes or its
malign purposes.  The South fought for perfect and permanent
control over the Southern laborer.  It was a war of the rich
against the poor.  They who waged it had no objection to the
government, while they could use it as a means of confirming their
power over the laborer.  They fought the government, not because
they hated the government as such, but because they found it, as
they thought, in the way between them and their one grand purpose
of rendering permanent and indestructible their authority and power
over the Southern laborer.  Though the battle is for the present
lost, the hope of gaining this object still exists, and pervades
the whole South with a feverish excitement.  We have thus far only
gained a Union without unity, marriage without love, victory
without peace.  The hope of gaining by politics what they lost by
the sword, is the secret of all this Southern unrest; and that hope
must be extinguished before national ideas and objects can take
full possession of the Southern mind.  There is but one safe and
constitutional way to banish that mischievous hope from the South,
and that is by lifting the laborer beyond the unfriendly political
designs of his former master.  Give the negro the elective
franchise, and you at once destroy the purely sectional policy, and
wheel the Southern States into line with national interests and
national objects.  The last and shrewdest turn of Southern politics
is a recognition of the necessity of getting into Congress
immediately, and at any price.  The South will comply with any
conditions but suffrage for the negro.  It will swallow all the
unconstitutional test oaths, repeal all the ordinances of
Secession, repudiate the Rebel debt, promise to pay the debt
incurred in conquering its people, pass all the constitutional
amendments, if only it can have the negro left under its political
control.  The proposition is as modest as that made on the
mountain: "All these things will I give unto thee if thou wilt fall
down and worship me."
</p><p>But why are the Southerners so willing to make these
sacrifices?  The answer plainly is, they see in this policy the
only hope of saving something of their old sectional peculiarities
and power.  Once firmly seated in Congress, their alliance with
Northern Democrats re-established, their States restored to their
former position inside the Union, they can easily find means of
keeping the Federal government entirely too busy with other
important matters to pay much attention to the local affairs of the
Southern States.  Under the potent shield of State Rights, the game
would be in their own hands.  Does any sane man doubt for a moment
that the men who followed Jefferson Davis through the late terrible
Rebellion, often marching barefooted and hungry, naked and
penniless, and who now only profess an enforced loyalty, would
plunge this country into a foreign war to-day, if they could
thereby gain their coveted independence, and their still more
coveted mastery over the negroes?  Plainly enough, the peace not
less than the prosperity of this country is involved in the great
measure of impartial suffrage.  King Cotton is deposed,
<pb n="117"/>
but
only deposed, and is ready to-day to reassert all his ancient
pretensions upon the first favorable opportunity.  Foreign
countries abound with his agents.  They are able, vigilant,
devoted.  The young men of the South burn with the desire to regain
what they call the lost cause; the women are noisily malignant
towards the Federal government.  In fact, all the elements of
treason and rebellion are there under the thinnest disguise which
necessity can impose.
</p><p>What, then, is the work before Congress?  It is to save the
people of the South from themselves, and the nation from detriment
on their account.  Congress must supplant the evident sectional
tendencies of the South by national dispositions and tendencies.
It must cause national ideas and objects to take the lead and
control the politics of those States.  It must cease to recognize
the old slave-masters as the only competent persons to rule the
South.  In a word, it must enfranchise the negro, and by means of
the loyal negroes and the loyal white men of the South build up a
national party there, and in time bridge the chasm between North
and South, so that our country may have a common liberty and a
common civilization.  The new wine must be put into new bottles.
The lamb may not be trusted with the wolf.  Loyalty is hardly safe
with traitors.
</p><p>Statesmen of America! beware what you do.  The ploughshare of
rebellion has gone through the land beam-deep.  The soil is in
readiness, and the seed-time has come.  Nations, not less than
individuals, reap as they sow.  The dreadful calamities of the past
few years came not by accident, nor unbidden, from the ground.  You
shudder to-day at the harvest of blood sown in the spring-time of
the Republic by your patriot fathers.  The principle of slavery,
which they tolerated under the erroneous impression that it would
soon die out, became at last the dominant principle and power at
the South.  It early mastered the Constitution, became superior to
the Union, and enthroned itself above the law.
</p><p>Freedom of speech and of the press it slowly but successfully
banished from the South, dictated its own code of honor and manners
to the nation, brandished the bludgeon and the bowie-knife over
Congressional debate, sapped the foundations of loyalty, dried up
the springs of patriotism, blotted out the testimonies of the
fathers against oppression, padlocked the pulpit, expelled liberty
from its literature, invented nonsensical theories about master-races and slave-races of men, and in due season produced a
Rebellion fierce, foul, and bloody.
</p><p>This evil principle again seeks admission into our body
politic.  It comes now in shape of a denial of political rights to
four million loyal colored people.  The South does not now ask for
slavery.  It only asks for a large degraded <hi rend="italic">caste</hi>, which shall
have no political rights.  This ends the case.  Statesmen, beware
what you do.  The destiny of unborn and unnumbered generations is
in your hands.  Will you repeat the mistake of your fathers, who
sinned ignorantly? or will you profit by the blood-bought wisdom
all round you, and forever expel every vestige of the old
abomination from our national borders?  As you members of the
Thirty-ninth Congress decide, will the country be peaceful, united,
and happy, or troubled, divided, and miserable.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
