<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DubTrai"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="DubTrai">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Of the Training of Black Men</title>
<title type="sort">of the training of black men</title>
<author>Du Bois, W. E. Burghardt</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">36</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">DubTrai</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475900</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Of the Training of Black Men</title>
<title type="sort">of the training of black men</title>
<author>W. E. Burghardt Du Bois</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1902">1902</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 90</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 289-297</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1902">1902</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term>
<term>democracy</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>African American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-08">August 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Minimal TEI tagging</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">

<div1 type="article" id="d3"><pb n="289"/>
<head>
Du Bois, W. E. Burghardt.  "Of the Training of Black Men."<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 90 (1902): 289-297.</head>

<p>FROM the shimmering swirl of waters where many, many thoughts
ago the slave-ship first saw the square tower of Jamestown have
flowed down to our day three streams of thinking: one from the
larger world here and over-seas, saying, the multiplying of human
wants in culture lands calls for the world-wide co-operation of men
in satisfying them.  Hence arises a new human unity, pulling the
ends of earth nearer, and all men, black, yellow, and white.  The
larger humanity strives to feel in this contact of living nations
and sleeping hordes a thrill of new life in the world, crying, If
the contact of Life and Sleep be Death, shame on such Life.  To be
sure, behind this thought lurks the afterthought of force and
dominion, &mdash; the making of brown men to delve when the temptation of
beads and red calico cloys.
</p><p>The second thought streaming from the death-ship and the
curving river is the thought of the older South: the sincere and
passionate belief that somewhere between men and cattle God created
a <hi rend="italic">tertium quid</hi>, and called it a Negro, &mdash; a clownish, simple
creature, at times even lovable within its limitations, but
straitly foreordained to walk within the Veil.  To be sure, behind
the thought lurks the afterthought, &mdash; some of them with favoring
chance might become men, but in sheer self-defense we dare not let
them, and build about them walls so high, and hang between them and
the light a veil so thick, that they shall not even think of
breaking through.
</p><p>And last of all there trickles down that third and darker
thought, the thought of the things themselves, the confused half-conscious mutter of men who are black and whitened, crying Liberty,
Freedom, Opportunity &mdash; vouchsafe to us, O boastful World, the chance
of living men!  To be sure, behind the thought lurks the
afterthought: suppose, after all, the World is right and we are
less than men?  Suppose this mad impulse within is all wrong, some
mock mirage from the untrue?
</p><p>So here we stand among thoughts of human unity, even through
conquest and slavery; the inferiority of black men, even if forced
by fraud; a shriek in the night for the freedom of men who
themselves are not yet sure of their right to demand it.  This is
the tangle of thought and afterthought wherein we are called to
solve the problem of training men for life.
</p><p>Behind all its curiousness, so attractive alike to sage and
dilettante, lie its dim dangers, throwing across us shadows at once
grotesque and awful.  Plain it is to us that what the world seeks
through desert and wild we have within our threshold; &mdash; a stalwart
laboring force, suited to the semi-tropics; if, deaf to the voice
of the Zeitgeist, we refuse to use and develop these men, we risk
poverty and loss.  If, on the other hand, seized by the brutal
afterthought, we debauch the race thus caught
<pb n="290"/>
in our
talons, selfishly sucking their blood and brains in the future as
in the past, what shall save us from national decadence?  Only that
saner selfishness which, Education teaches men, can find the rights
of all in the whirl of work.
</p><p>Again, we may decry the color prejudice of the South, yet it
remains a heavy fact.  Such curious kinks of the human mind exist
and must be reckoned with soberly.  They cannot be laughed away,
nor always successfully stormed at, nor easily abolished by act of
legislature.  And yet they cannot be encouraged by being let alone.
They must be recognized as facts, but unpleasant facts; things that
stand in the way of civilization and religion and common decency.
They can be met in but one way: by the breadth and broadening of
human reason, by catholicity of taste and culture.  And so, too,
the native ambition and aspiration of men, even though they be
black, backward, and ungraceful, must not lightly be dealt with.
To stimulate wildly weak and untrained minds is to play with mighty
fires; to flout their striving idly is to welcome a harvest of
brutish crime and shameless lethargy in our very laps.  The guiding
of thought and the deft coordination of deed is at once the path of
honor and humanity.
</p><p>And so, in this great question of reconciling three vast and
partially contradictory streams of thought, the one panacea of
Education leaps to the lips of all; such human training as will
best use the labor of all men without enslaving or brutalizing;
such training as will give us poise to encourage the prejudices
that bulwark society, and stamp out those that in sheer barbarity
deafen us to the wail of prisoned souls within the Veil, and the
mounting fury of shackled men.
</p><p>But when we have vaguely said Education will set this tangle
straight, what have we uttered but a truism?  Training for life
teaches living; but what training for the profitable living
together of black men and white?  Two hundred years ago our task
would have seemed easier.  Then Dr. Johnson blandly assured us that
education was needed solely for the embellishments of life, and was
useless for ordinary vermin.  To-day we have climbed to heights
where we would open at least the outer courts of knowledge to all,
display its treasures to many, and select the few to whom its
mystery of Truth is revealed, not wholly by truth or the accidents
of the stock market, but at least in part according to deftness and
aim, talent and character.  This programme, however, we are sorely
puzzled in carrying out through that part of the land where the
blight of slavery fell hardest, and where we are dealing with two
backward peoples.  To make here in human education that ever
necessary combination of the permanent and the contingent &mdash; of the
ideal and the practical in workable equilibrium &mdash; has been there, as
it ever must be in every age and place, a matter of infinite
experiment and frequent mistakes.
</p><p>In rough approximation we may point out four varying decades
of work in Southern education since the Civil War.  From the close
of the war until 1876 was the period of uncertain groping and
temporary relief.  There were army schools, mission schools, and
schools of the Freedmen's Bureau in chaotic disarrangement, seeking
system and cooperation.  Then followed ten years of constructive
definite effort toward the building of complete school systems in
the South.  Normal schools and colleges were founded for the
freedmen, and teachers trained there to man the public schools.
There was the inevitable tendency of war to underestimate the
prejudice of the master and the ignorance of the slave, and all
seemed clear sailing out of the wreckage of the storm.  Meantime,
starting in this decade yet especially developing from 1885 to
1895, began the industrial revolution of the South.  The land saw
glimpses
<pb n="291"/>
of a new destiny and the stirring of new ideals.
The educational system striving to complete itself saw new
obstacles and a field of work ever broader and deeper.  The Negro
colleges, hurriedly founded, were inadequately equipped,
illogically distributed, and of varying efficiency and grade; the
normal and high schools were doing little more than common school
work, and the common schools were training but a third of the
children who ought to be in them, and training these too often
poorly.  At the same time the white South, by reason of its sudden
conversion from the slavery ideal, by so much the more became set
and strengthened in its racial prejudice, and crystallized it into
harsh law and harsher custom; while the marvelous pushing forward
of the poor white daily threatened to take even bread and butter
from the mouths of the heavily handicapped sons of the freedmen.
In the midst, then, of the larger problem of Negro education sprang
up the more practical question of work, the inevitable economic
quandary that faces a people in the transition from slavery to
freedom, and especially those who make that change amid hate and
prejudice, lawlessness and ruthless competition.
</p><p>The industrial school springing to notice in this decade, but
coming to full recognition in the decade beginning with 1895, was
the proffered answer to this combined educational and economic
crisis, and an answer of singular wisdom and timeliness.  From the
very first in nearly all the schools some attention had been given
to training in handiwork, but now was this training first raised to
a dignity that brought it in direct touch with the South's
magnificent industrial development, and given an emphasis which
reminded black folk that before the Temple of Knowledge swing the
Gates of Toil.
</p><p>Yet after all they are but gates, and when turning our eyes
from the temporary and the contingent in the Negro problem to the
broader question of the permanent uplifting and civilization of
black men in America, we have a right to inquire, as this
enthusiasm for material advancement mounts to its height, if after
all the industrial school is the final and sufficient answer in the
training of the Negro race; and to ask gently, but in all
sincerity, the ever recurring query of the ages, Is not life more
than meat, and the body more than raiment?  And men ask this to-day
all the more eagerly because of sinister signs in recent
educational movements.  The tendency is here born of slavery and
quickened to renewed life by the crazy imperialism of the day, to
regard human beings as among the material resources of a land to be
trained with an eye single to future dividends.  Race prejudices,
which keep brown and black men in their "places," we are coming to
regard as useful allies with such a theory, no matter how much they
may dull the ambition and sicken the hearts of struggling human
beings.  And above all, we daily hear that an education that
encourages aspiration, that sets the loftiest of ideals and seeks
as an end culture and character than bread-winning, is the
privilege of white men and the danger and delusion of black.
</p><p>Especially has criticism been directed against the former
educational efforts to aid the Negro.  In the four periods I have
mentioned, we find first boundless, planless enthusiasm and
sacrifice; then the preparation of teachers for a vast public
school system; then the launching and expansion of that school
system amid increasing difficulties; and finally the training of
workmen for the new and growing industries.  This development has
been sharply ridiculed as a logical anomaly and flat reversal of
nature.  Soothly we have been told that first industrial and manual
training should have taught the Negro to work, then simple schools
should have taught him to read and write, and finally, after years,
high and normal schools could
<pb n="292"/>
have completed the system, as
intelligence and wealth demanded.
</p><p>That a system logically so complete was historically
impossible, it needs but a little thought to prove.  Progress in
human affairs is more often a pull than a push, surging forward of
the exceptional man, and the lifting of his duller brethren slowly
and painfully to his vantage ground.  Thus it was no accident that
gave birth to universities centuries before the common schools,
that made fair Harvard the first flower of our wilderness.  So in
the South: the mass of the freedmen at the end of the war lacked
the intelligence so necessary to modern workingmen.  They must
first have the common school to teach them to read, write, and
cipher.  The white teachers who flocked South went to establish
such a common school system.  They had no idea of founding
colleges; they themselves at first would have laughed at the idea.
But they faced, as all men since them have faced, that central
paradox of the South, the social separation of the races.  Then it
was the sudden volcanic rupture of nearly all relations between
black and white, in work and government and family life.  Since
then a new adjustment of relations in economic and political
affairs has grown up, &mdash; an adjustment subtle and difficult to grasp,
yet singularly ingenious, which leaves still that frightful chasm
at the color line across which men pass at their peril.  Thus, then
and now, there stand in the South two separate worlds; and separate
not simply in the higher realms of social intercourse, but also in
church and school, on railway and street car, in hotels and
theatres, in streets and city sections, in books and newspapers, in
asylums and jails, in hospitals and graveyards.  There is still
enough of contact for large economic and group cooperation, but the
separation is so thorough and deep, that it absolutely precludes
for the present between the races anything like that sympathetic
and effective group training and leadership of the one by the
other, such as the American Negro and all backward peoples must
have for effectual progress.
</p><p>This the missionaries of '68 soon saw; and if effective
industrial and trade schools were impractical before the
establishment of a common school system, just as certainly no
adequate common schools could be founded until there were teachers
to teach them.  Southern whites would not teach them; Northern
whites in sufficient numbers could not be had.  If the Negro was to
learn, he must teach himself, and the most effective help that
could be given him was the establishment of schools to train Negro
teachers.  This conclusion was slowly but surely reached by every
student of the situation until simultaneously, in widely separated
regions, without consultation or systematic plan, there arose a
series of institutions designed to furnish teachers for the
untaught.  Above the sneers of critics at the obvious defects of
this procedure must ever stand its one crushing rejoinder: in a
single generation they put thirty thousand black teachers in the
South; they wiped out the illiteracy of the majority of the black
people of the land, and they made Tuskegee possible.
</p><p>Such higher training schools tended naturally to deepen
broader development: at first they were common and grammar schools,
then some became high schools.  And finally, by 1900, some thirty-four had one year or more of studies of college grade.  This
development was reached with different degrees of speed in
different institutions: Hampton is still a high school, while Fisk
University started her college in 1871, and Spelman Seminary about
1896.  In all cases the aim was identical: to maintain the
standards of the lower training by giving teachers and leaders the
best practicable training; and above all to furnish the black world
with adequate standards of human culture and lofty ideals of life.
It was
<pb n="293"/>
not enough that the teachers of teachers should be
trained in technical normal methods; they must also, so far as
possible, be broad-minded, cultured men and women, to scatter
civilization among a people whose ignorance was not simply of
letters, but of life itself.
</p><p>It can thus be seen that the work of education in the South
began with higher institutions of training, which threw off as
their foliage common schools, and later industrial schools, and at
the same time strove to shoot their roots ever deeper toward
college and university training.  That this was an inevitable and
necessary development, sooner or later, goes without saying; but
there has been, and still is, a question in many minds if the
natural growth was not forced, and if the higher training was not
either overdone or done with cheap and unsound methods.  Among
white Southerners this feeling is widespread and positive.  A
prominent Southern journal voiced this in a recent editorial:
</p><p>"The experiment that has been made to give the colored
students classical training has not been satisfactory.  Even though
many were able to pursue the course, most of them did so in a
parrot-like way, learning what was taught, but not seeming to
appropriate the truth and import of their instruction, and
graduating without sensible aim or valuable occupation for their
future.  The whole scheme has proved a waste of time, efforts, and
the money of the state."
</p><p>While most far-minded men would recognize this as extreme and
overdrawn, still without doubt many are asking, Are there a
sufficient number of Negroes ready for college training to warrant
the undertaking?  Are not too many students prematurely forced into
this work?  Does it not have the effect of dissatisfying the young
Negro with his environment?  And do these graduates succeed in real
life?  Such natural questions cannot be evaded, nor on the other
hand must a nation naturally skeptical as to Negro ability assume
an unfavorable answer without careful inquiry and patient openness
to conviction.  We must not forget that most Americans answer all
queries regarding the Negro <hi rend="italic">a priori</hi>, and that the least that
human courtesy can do is to listen to evidence.
</p><p>The advocates of the higher education of the Negro would be
the last to deny the incompleteness and glaring defects of the
present system: too many institutions have attempted to do college
work, the work in some cases has not been thoroughly done, and
quantity rather than quality has sometimes been sought.  But all
this can be said of higher education throughout the land: it is the
almost inevitable incident of educational growth, and leaves the
deeper question of the legitimate demand for the higher training of
Negroes untouched.  And this latter question can be settled in but
one way &mdash; by a first-hand study of the facts.  If we leave out of
view all institutions which have not actually graduated students
from a course higher than that of a New England high school, even
though they be called colleges; if then we take the thirty-four
remaining institutions, we may clear up many misapprehensions by
asking searchingly, What kind of institutions are they, what do
they teach, and what sort of men do they graduate?
</p><p>And first we may say that this type of college, including
Atlanta, Fisk and Howard, Wilberforce and Lincoln, Biddle, Shaw,
and the rest, is peculiar, almost unique.  Through the shining
trees that whisper before me as I write, I catch glimpses of a
boulder of New England granite, covering a grave, which graduates
of Atlanta University have placed there: &mdash;

          "IN GRATEFUL MEMORY OF THEIR<lb/>
           FORMER TEACHER AND FRIEND<lb/>
           AND OF THE UNSELFISH LIFE HE<lb/>
           LIVED, AND THE NOBLE WORK HE<lb/>
           WROUGHT; THAT THEY, THEIR<lb/>
           CHILDREN, AND THEIR CHILDREN'S<lb/>
           CHILDREN MIGHT BE<lb/>
                   BLESSED."<lb/>
<pb n="294"/>

</p><p>This was the gift of New England to the freed Negro: not alms,
but a friend; not cash, but character.  It was not and is not money
these seething millions want, but love and sympathy, the pulse of
hearts beating with red blood; a gift which to-day only their own
kindred and race can bring to the masses, but which once saintly
souls brought to their favored children in the crusade of the
sixties, that finest thing in American history, and one of the few
things untainted by sordid greed and cheap vainglory.  The teachers
in these institutions came not to keep the Negroes in their place,
but to raise them out of their places where the filth of slavery
had wallowed them.  The colleges they founded were social
settlements; homes where the best of the sons of the freedmen came
in close and sympathetic touch with the best traditions of New
England.  They lived and ate together, studies and worked, hoped
and harkened in the dawning light.  In actual formal content their
curriculum was doubtless old-fashioned, but in educational power it
was supreme, for it was the contact of living souls.
</p><p>From such schools about two thousand Negroes have gone forth
with the bachelor's degree.  The number in itself is enough to put
at rest the argument that too large a proportion of Negroes are
receiving higher training.  If the ratio to population of all Negro
students throughout the land, in both college and secondary
training, be counted, Commissioner Harris assures us "it must be
increased to five times its present average" to equal the average
of the land.
</p><p>Fifty years ago the ability of Negro students in any
appreciable numbers to master a modern college course would have
been difficult to prove.  To-day it is proved by the fact that four
hundred Negroes, many of whom have been reported as brilliant
students, have received the bachelor's degree from Harvard, Yale,
Oberlin, and seventy other leading colleges.  Here we have, then,
nearly twenty-five hundred Negro graduates, of whom the crucial
query must be made.  How far did their training fit them for life?
It is of course extremely difficult to collect satisfactory data on
such a point, &mdash; difficult to reach the men, to get trustworthy
testimony, and to gauge that testimony by any generally acceptable
criterion of success.  In 1900, the Conference at Atlanta
University undertook to study these graduates, and published the
results.  First they sought to know what these graduates were
doing, and succeeded in getting answers from nearly two thirds of
the living.  The direct testimony was in almost all cases
corroborated by the reports of the colleges where they graduated,
so that in the main the reports were worthy of credence.  Fifty-three per cent of these graduates were teachers, &mdash; presidents of
institutions, heads of normal schools, principals of city school
systems, and the like.  Seventeen per cent were clergymen; another
seventeen per cent were in the professions, chiefly as physicians.
Over six per cent were merchants, farmers, and artisans, and four
per cent were in the government civil service.  Granting even that
a considerable proportion of the third unheard from are
unsuccessful, this is a record of usefulness.  Personally I know
many hundreds of these graduates and have corresponded with more
than a thousand; through others I have followed carefully the life-work of scores; I have taught some of them and some of the pupils
whom they have taught, lived in homes which they have builded, and
looked at life through their eyes.  Comparing them as a class with
my fellow students in New England and in Europe, I cannot hesitate
in saying that nowhere have I met men and women with a broader
spirit of helpfulness, with deeper devotion to their life-work, or
with more consecrated determination to succeed in the face of
bitter difficulties than among Negro college-bred men.
<pb n="295"/>
They
have, to be sure, their proportion of ne'er-do-weels, their pedants
and lettered fools, but they have a surprisingly small proportion
of them; they have not that culture of manner which we
instinctively associate with university men, forgetting that in
reality it is the heritage from cultured homes, and that no people
a generation removed from slavery can escape a certain unpleasant
rawness and <hi rend="italic">gaucherie</hi>, despite the best of training.
</p><p>With all their larger vision and deeper sensibility, these men
have usually been conservative, careful leaders.  They have seldom
been agitators, have withstood the temptation to head the mob, and
have worked steadily and faithfully in a thousand communities in
the South.  As teachers they have given the South a commendable
system of city schools and large numbers of private normal schools
and academies.  Colored college-bred men have worked side by side
with white college graduates at Hampton; almost from the beginning
the backbone of Tuskegee's teaching force has been formed of
graduates from Fisk and Atlanta.  And to-day the institute is
filled with college graduates, from the energetic wife of the
principal down to the teacher of agriculture, including nearly half
of the executive council and a majority of the heads of
departments.  In the professions, college men are slowly but surely
leavening the Negro church, are healing and preventing the
devastations of disease, and beginning to furnish legal protection
for the liberty and property of the toiling masses.  All this is
needful work.  Who would do it if Negroes did not?  How could
Negroes do it if they were not trained carefully for it?  If white
people need colleges to furnish teachers, ministers, lawyers, and
doctors, do black people need nothing of the sort?
</p><p>If it be true that there are an appreciable number of Negro
youth in the land capable by character and talent to receive that
higher training, the end of which is culture, and if the two and a
half thousand who have had something of this training in the past
have in the main proved themselves useful to their race and
generation, the question then comes, What place in the future
development of the South might the Negro college and college-bred
man to occupy?  That the present social separation and acute race
sensitiveness must eventually yield to the influences of culture as
the South grows civilized is clear.  But such transformation calls
for singular wisdom and patience.  If, while the healing of this
vast sore is progressing, the races are to live for many years side
by side, united in economic effort, obeying a common government,
sensitive to mutual thought and feeling, yet subtly and silently
separate in many matters of deeper human intimacy &mdash; if this unusual
and dangerous development is to progress amid peace and order,
mutual respect and growing intelligence, it will call for social
surgery at once the delicatest and nicest in modern history.  It
will demand broad-minded, upright men both white and black, and in
its final accomplishment American civilization will triumph.  So
far as white men are concerned, this fact is to-day being
recognized in the South, and a happy renaissance of university
education seems imminent.  But the very voices that cry Hail! to
this good work are, strange to relate, largely silent or
antagonistic to the higher education of the Negro.
</p><p>Strange to relate! for this is certain, no secure civilization
can be built in the South with the Negro as an ignorant, turbulent
proletariat.  Suppose we seek to remedy this by making them
laborers and nothing more: they are not fools, they have tasted of
the Tree of Life, and they will not cease to think, will not cease
attempting to read the riddle of the world.  By taking away their
best equipped teachers and leaders, by slamming the door of
opportunity in the faces of their bolder and brighter minds, will
you make them satisfied with their
<pb n="296"/>
lot? or will you not
rather transfer their leading from the hands of men taught to think
to the hands of untrained demagogues?  We ought not to forget that
despite the pressure of poverty, and despite the active
discouragement and even ridicule of friends, the demand for higher
training steadily increases among Negro youth: there were, in the
years from 1875 to 1880, twenty-two Negro graduates from Northern
colleges; from 1885 to 1895 there were forty-three, and from 1895
to 1900, nearly 100 graduates.  From Southern Negro colleges there
were, in the same three periods, 143, 413, and over 500 graduates.
Here, then, is the plain thirst for training; by refusing to give
this Talented Tenth the key to knowledge can any sane man imagine
that they will lightly lay aside their yearning and contentedly
become hewers of wood and drawers of water?
</p><p>No.  The dangerously clear logic of the Negro's position will
more and more loudly assert itself in that day when increasing
wealth and more intricate social organization preclude the South
from being, as it so largely is, simply an armed camp for
intimidating black folk.  Such waste of energy cannot be spared if
the South is to catch up with civilization.  And as the black third
of the land grows in thrift and skill, unless skillfully guided in
its larger philosophy, it must more and more brood over the red
past and the creeping, crooked present, until it grasps a gospel of
revolt and revenge and throws its new-found energies athwart the
current of advance.  Even to-day the masses of the Negroes see all
too clearly the anomalies of their position and the moral
crookedness of yours.  You may marshal strong indictments against
them, but their counter-cries, lacking though they be in formal
logic, have burning truths within them which you may not wholly
ignore, O Southern Gentlemen!  If you deplore their presence here,
they ask, Who brought us?  When you shriek, Deliver us from the
vision of intermarriage, they answer, that legal marriage is
infinitely better than systematic concubinage and prostitution.
And if in just fury you accuse their vagabonds of violating women,
they also in fury quite as just may wail: the rape which your
gentlemen have done against helpless black women in defiance of
your own laws is written on the foreheads of two millions of
mulattoes, and written in ineffaceable blood.  And finally, when
you fasten crime upon this race as its peculiar trait, they answer
that slavery was the arch-crime, and lynching and lawlessness its
twin abortion; that color and race are not crimes, and yet they it
is which in this land receive most unceasing condemnation, North,
East, South, and West.
</p><p>I will not say such arguments are wholly justified &mdash; I will not
insist that there is no other side to the shield; but I do say that
of the nine millions of Negroes in this nation, there is scarcely
one out of the cradle to whom these arguments do not daily present
themselves in the guise of terrible truth.  I insist that the
question of the future is how best to keep these millions from
brooding over the wrongs of the past and the difficulties of the
present, so that all their energies may be bent toward a cheerful
striving and cooperation with their white neighbors toward a
larger, juster, and fuller future.  That one wise method of doing
this lies in the closer knitting of the Negro to the great
industrial possibilities of the South is a great truth.  And this
the common schools and the manual training and trade schools are
working to accomplish.  But these alone are not enough.  The
foundations of knowledge in this race, as in others, must be sunk
deep in the college and university if we would build a solid,
permanent structure.  Internal problems of social advance must
inevitably come, &mdash; problems of work and wages, of families and
homes, of morals and the true valuing of the things
<pb n="297"/>
of life; and all these and other inevitable problems of civilization
the Negro must meet and solve largely for himself, by reason of his
isolation; and can there be any possible solution other than by
study and thought and an appeal to the rich experience of the past?
Is there not, with such a group and in such a crisis, infinitely
more danger to be apprehended from half-trained minds and shallow
thinking than from over-education and over-refinement?  Surely we
have wit enough to found a Negro college so manned and equipped as
to steer successfully between the dilettante and the fool.  We
shall hardly induce black men to believe that if their bellies be
full it matters little about their brains.  They already dimly
perceive that the paths of peace winding between honest toil and
dignified manhood call for the guidance of skilled thinkers, the
loving, reverent comradeship between the black lowly and black men
emancipated by training and culture.
</p><p>The function of the Negro college then is clear: it must
maintain the standards of popular education, it must seek the
social regeneration of the Negro, and it must help in the solution
of problems of race contact and cooperation.  And finally, beyond
all this, it must develop men.  Above our modern socialism, and out
of the worship of the mass, must persist and evolve that higher
individualism which the centres of culture protect; there must come
a loftier respect for the sovereign human soul that seeks to know
itself and the world about it; that seeks a freedom for expansion
and self-development; that will love and hate and labor in its own
way, untrammeled alike by old and new.  Such souls aforetime have
inspired and guided worlds, and if we be not wholly bewitched by
our Rhine-gold, they shall again.  Herein the longing of black men
must have respect: the rich and bitter depth of their experience,
the unknown treasures of their inner life, the strange rendings of
nature they have seen, may give the world new points of view and
make their loving, living, and doing precious to all human hearts.
And to themselves in these the days that try their souls the chance
to soar in the dim blue air above the smoke is to their finer
spirits boon and guerdon for what they lose on earth by being
black.

</p><p>I sit with Shakespeare and he winces not.  Across the color
line I move arm in arm with Balzac and Dumas, where smiling men and
welcoming women glide in gilded halls.  From out the caves of
Evening that swing between the strong-limbed earth and the tracery
of the stars, I summon Aristotle and Aurelius and what soul I will,
and they come all graciously with no scorn nor condescension.  So,
wed with Truth, I dwell above the Veil.  Is this the life you
grudge us, O knightly America?  Is this the life you long to change
into the dull red hideousness of Georgia?  Are you so afraid lest
peering from this high Pisgah, between Philistine and Amalekite, we
sight the Promised Land?
</p>
<signed>                              <hi rend="italic">W. E. Burghardt Du Bois.</hi>
</signed>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
