<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DufWrit"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="DufWrit">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Writings of George MacDonald</title>
<title type="sort">writings of george macdonald</title>
<author>Duffield, Samuel W.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">12</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">DufWrit</idno>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475901</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Writings of George MacDonald</title>
<title level="j">Scribner's Monthly, Vol. I</title>
<title type="sort">writings of george macdonald</title>
<author>Samuel W. Duffield</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 87-88</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner &amp; Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1870-11">November 1870</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVA library call number AP 2.C4</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1870">1870</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; non-fiction</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-07">July 1997</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Carol Osborne, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
	<pb n="87"/>
<head>The Writings of George MacDonald.<lb/>
Samuel W. Duffield</head>
    <p> IN something less than three years we have become acquainted
with a new name in literature.  It has drifted to us across the
Atlantic, and with it has come a vague hint of a personality
whereof in future we may know more.  The works of this hand and
brain are mainly in a poetical prose, with an occasional relapse
into verse.  His books sell largely, and he is better known as "the
author of <hi rend="italic">Annals of a Quiet Neighborhood"</hi> than as George
MacDonald.</p>
    <p> Lately he appears among us as the editor of <hi rend="italic">Good Words for
the Young</hi>, always, however, forgetting the prefix "Rev.," and
carrying that balancing "LL.D." as "the draigon" of his own Robert
Falconer carried the weight which steadied her in mid-air.  We hear
of him as a tall man, of earnest demeanor and shaggy beard,
proclaiming now and then in clear and forcible speech his own
peculiar doctrines of "righteousness, temperance, and judgment to
come."  He is reputed to have the ear of his audience on these rare
occasions, and certainly, if the humanity of his books is a test,
he deserves it.</p>
    <p> As far back as <hi rend="italic">Phantastes, a Faery Romance</hi>, his
imaginative style seems to have begun.  <hi rend="italic">Within and Without</hi>,
a poem of about the same date, shows more deliberate thought &mdash;
perhaps more metaphysics than poetry.  But these two books, which
were at the beginning of his fame (if indeed he had no share in the
composition of <hi rend="italic">The Green Hand, a Short Yarn</hi>), have been
entirely displaced to American readers by other and more mature
productions.</p>
    <p> First, we had as reprints, <hi rend="italic">Alec Forbes of Howglen</hi>, and
<hi rend="italic">Guild Court, a London Story</hi>.  To these succeeded the
importation of <hi rend="italic">The Disciple and Other Poems</hi>, another volume
entitled <hi rend="italic">Unspoken Sermons</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic">Annals of a Quiet
Neighborhood</hi>, with its sequel, <hi rend="italic">The Seaboard Parish</hi>.
Next came <hi rend="italic">David Elginbrod</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Robert Falconer</hi>, both
reprints; and current literature was at the same date refreshed by
a series of articles on the <hi rend="italic">Miracles of Our Lord</hi>, in the
<hi rend="italic">Sunday Magazine</hi>, and by <hi rend="italic">Ranald Bannerman's Boyhood</hi>,
and <hi rend="italic">At the Back of the North Wind</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Good Words for the
Young</hi>.</p>
    <p> In attendance upon these, Mr. MacDonald sent forth a volume of
the Sunday Library, uniform with Chas. Kingsley's <hi rend="italic">Hermits</hi>
and Miss Yonge's <hi rend="italic">Pupils of St. John the Divine</hi>, which was
styled <hi rend="italic">England's Antiphon</hi>.  It is a most important
contribution to our knowledge of the singers and songs of the
English Church.</p>
    <p> In all these books there is a vein of consistent, fresh,
original thought, often expressed in language extremely apt and
powerful.  It tends towards the religious at all times, and
particularly it tends to that blunt plainness as to hypocrisy and
cant and sham of every kind in which our dear departed masters,
Thackeray and Dickens, took the lead.  But to compare Mr. MacDonald
with either, or with both, would be unfair.  He has not the same
elements in him.  He cannot, if he would, write in their light,
easy, man-of-the-world style, which, like Saladin's scimetar [sic],
cuts deep and to the quick.</p>
    <p> As his is now a considerable place among us, I have thought
that a <hi rend="italic">r&eacute;sum&eacute;</hi> of his method and writings might
aid in a fuller appreciation of the man's actual talent &mdash; not to
say his genius of a certain sort.</p>
    <p> His novels are, with one exception, Scotch in scene, and with
a great deal of the dialect about them.  Their central figure is
much the same &mdash; a boy, who, while a hearty, active lad,
nevertheless has his fancies and his thoughts.  This fine fellow's
life possesses many points of humor &mdash; especially in <hi rend="italic">Alec
Forbes</hi> &mdash; and introduces scenes and pictures which are at times
simply exquisite.  This education of the hero evolves the
&aelig;sthetic from its lurking-place within him.  A female
presence casts a halo of protecting beauty and goodness over his
path.  He has stalwart male friends &mdash; adherents of the cast-iron
theology of the North, or else scapegraces of a droll and facetious
turn, in whom he detects the good beneath the bad.  He generally
befriends or finds in the horizon of his career some forsaken boy,
of a curious devotedness.  Relatives
<pb n="88"/>
or near friends, of
the pure Scottish type, are around him, who, like Falconer's
grandmother, have warm hearts under bosoms calmly cold.  And, as
nearly as words can achieve it, we have a process of photography
going on from the day we set eyes upon our principal actor until he
goes off the stage, with the closing of the book.</p>
    <p> For all this, Mr. MacDonald's abundant observation, fruitful
fancy, and thorough sympathy, fit him excellently well.  Leaving
out such eccentric persons as Count Halko, in <hi rend="italic">David
Elginbrod</hi>, who practises mesmerism and electrical
bewilderments, his characters stick to common facts, and invest
ordinary things with the charm of spicy conversation, and a
minuteness which never degenerates into tedious recapitulation.
Wit sparkles in the speech of Cosmo Cupples as naturally as a brook
laughs in the sun, and you may be profoundly sure that the talk
will ripple freshly up whenever any obstruction appears in the
channel.</p>
     <p>The books are of their own kind.  They are professedly of high
intention &mdash; the later ones, by which I do not mean our latest
reprints, being the best.  One cannot read them without being
stimulated to something nobler and purer, for they may honestly be
called both.  They are a mine of original and quaint similitudes,
and their deep perceptions of human nature are certainly
remarkable.  To have realized some of the scenes as he has, Mr.
MacDonald must have known the student-life of Aberdeen, and the
boy-life of a little Scotch town.  Nature, from smallest to
largest, must have been carefully under his notice.  And in the
world, so wide as it is to all of us, he has seen the little flower
grow up in a life, or the great storm sweep over it.</p>
    <p> This is notably the case in the <hi rend="italic">Annals of a Quiet
Neighborhood</hi>, and its sequel, the latter being by no means the
best.  Here he is shown as a close pathologist.  Disease of mind
and disease of body, as influencing or off-setting each other, he
has acutely studied.  As a matter of art, the London
<hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi> was right when it called this application of
knowledge in this book "something wonderful."  The sentences
sometimes are like the soliloquy of one thinking aloud upon
creation, chaos, and infinity.  And of course, as this is from the
clergyman's standpoint, Mr. MacDonald is freer, more natural, and
(except in <hi rend="italic">Alec Forbes</hi>) more successful here than anywhere
else.</p>
    <p> On the whole, Mr. George MacDonald is a power already, and
will soon be a greater one.  If we fully agree with him, we shall
grow enthusiastic over his earnest defence of his ideas.  If we
differ from him, it will be with the respect due to an honorable
opponent who hits hard, and whom it requires skill and brains to
meet.  Let it stand to his credit, that in an age of loose
literature he is, like Scott and Dickens and Thackeray, pure-minded.  He writes better English (because more imaginative and
loftier) than Charles Reade, or any of that ilk.  And while Wilkie
Collins outdoes him in plot, he outdoes Wilkie Collins and the rest
of the plotters in delicacy and sweetness of touch.  But it is
already too plan that (unless he gets more leisure) the work which
he has done, and which the world has on its bookshelves, will be
the best of his doing.  Should George MacDonald rise hereafter
above this present point, high and good as it is, he will merit and
receive distinguished praise.  And, as a man hardly at the entrance
of middle-life, there is no reason why this should not be.  His
hand has not lost its cunning, and his eye is still undimmed.</p>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

