<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DunPurs"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;

]>
<TEI.2 id="DunPurs">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Pursuit of Riches / Dunne, F. P.</title>
<title type="sort">pursuit of riches dunne, f p</title>
<author>Dunne, F. P.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Nakedword</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">11</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">DunPurs</idno>
<date value="2000">2000</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2000 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475904</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Pursuit of Riches</title>
<title level="m">Dissertations by Mr. Dooley</title>
<title type="sort">pursuit of riches</title>
<author>Dunne, F. P.</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>3 p.l., 3-312, [1] p. 20 cm.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harper &amp; brothers</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York and London</pubPlace>
<date value="1906">1906</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Alderman Library Call Number PN6161 .D8 1906</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>[Notes about the original source]</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1906">1906</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2000-04">April 2000</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>J. Nathaniel Goldsmith, The Electronic Text Center at The University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI headers and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<front id="d2">
<titlePage id="d3">
	<pb/>
<docTitle>
<titlePart type="main">
Mr Dooley on the Pursuit of Riches
</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<byline>
by
<docAuthor>F. P. Dunne, 1904</docAuthor>
</byline>
</titlePage>
</front>
<body id="d4">
<div1 type="story" id="d5">
<p>
Dear me, I wisht I had money," said Mr, Hennessy.
</p><p>
"So do I," said Mr. Dooley. "I need it."
</p><p>
"Ye wudden't get it fr'm me," said Mr. Hennessy.
</p><p>
"If I didn't," said Mr. Dooley, "'twud be because I was poor or tired. But
what d'ye want money f'r? Supposin' I lost me head an' handed over all me
accumylated wealth? What wud ye do with that gr-reat fortune? Befure ye had
spint half iv it, ye'd be so sick ye'd come to me an' hand me back th' remainin'
eighteen dollars.
</p><p>
"A man has more fun wishin' f'r th' things he hasn't got thin injyin' th'
things he has got. Life, Hinnissy, is like a Pullman dinin' car: a fine bill
iv fare, but nawthin' to eat. Ye go in fresh an' hungry, tuck ye'er napkin
in ye'er collar, an' square away at th' list iv groceries that th' black
man hands ye. What'll ye have first? Ye think ye'd like to be famous an'
ye ordher a dish iv fame an' bid th' waither make it good an' hot. He's gone
an age, an' whin he comes back ye'er appytite is departed. Ye taste th' ordher
an' says ye: 'Why, it's cold an' full iv broken glass.' 'Tbat's th' way we
always sarve Fame on this car,' says th' coon. 'Don't ye think ye'd like
money f'r th' sicond coorse? Misther Rockyfellar over there has had forty-two helpin's,' says he. 'It don't seem to agree with him,' says ye, 'but
ye may bring me some,' ye say. Away he goes an' stays till ye're bald an'
ye'er teeth fall out, an' ye set dhrummin' on th' table an' lookin' out at
th' scenery. By an' by he comes back with ye'er ordher, but jus' as he's
goin' to hand it to ye, Rockyfellar grabs th' plate. 'What kind iv a car
is this?' says ye. 'Don't I get annything to eat? Can't ye give me a little
happiness?' 'I wudden't ricommend th' happiness,' says th' waither. 'It's
canned an' it kilt th' las' man that thried it.' 'Well, gracious,' says ye,
'I've got to have something. Give me a little good health an' I'll thry to
make a meal out iv that.' 'Sorry, sir,' says th' black man, 'but we're all
out iv good health. Besides,' he says, takin' ye gintly by th' ar-rm, 'we're
goin' into th' deepo an' ye'll have to get out,' he says.
</p><p>
"An' there ye ar-re. Ye'll niver get money onless ye fix th' waither an'
grab th' dishes away fr'm th' other passengers. An' ye won't do that. So
ye'll niver be rich. No poor man iver will be. Wan iv th' sthrangest things
about life is that th' poor who need th' money th' most ar-re th' very wans
that niver have it. A poor man is a poor man an' a rich man is a rich man.
Ye're ayether born poor or rich. It don't make anny diff'rence whether or
not ye have money to begin with. If ye're born to be rich, ye'll be rich,
an' if ye're born to be poor, ye'll be poor. Th' buttons on ye'er vest tell
th' story. Rich man, poor man, beggar man, rich man, or wurruds to that effect.
I always find that I have ayether two buttons or six.
</p><p>
"A poor man is a man that rayfuses to cash in. Ye don't get annything f'r
nawthin', an' to gather in a millyon iv thim beautiful lithographs iv Salmon
P. Chase, ye have to go down ivry day with something undher ye'er ar-rm to
th' great pawnshop. Whin Hogan wants four dollars be takes th' clock down
to Moses. Whin Rockyfellar wants tin millyon, he puts up his peace iv mind
or his health or something akelly valyable. If Hogan wud hock his priceless
habit iv sleepin' late in th' mornin' he wud be able to tell th' time iv
day whin be got up without goin' to tb' corner dhrug store.
</p><p>
"Look at McMullin. He's rowlin' in it. It bulges his pocket an' inflates
his convarsation. Whin he looks at me, I always feel that he's wondhrin'
how much I'd bring at a forced sale. Well, McMullin an' I had th' same start,
about forty yards behind scratch an' Vanderbilt to beat. They always put
th' best man in anny race behind th' line. Befure McMullin gets through he'll
pass Vanderbilt, carry away th' tape on his shorldhers, an' run two or three
times around th' thrack. But me an' him started th' same way. Th' on'y diffrence
was that he wud cash in an' I wudden't. Th' on'y thing I iver ixpicted to
get money on was me dhream iv avarice. I always had that. I cud dhream iv
money as hard as anny mam ye iver see an' can still. But I niver thought
iv wurrukin' f'r it. I've always looked on it as dishon'rable to wurruk f'r
money. I wurruk f'r exercise an' I get what th' lawyers call an honoraryium
be dilutin' th' spirits. Th' on'y way I iver expict to make a cint is to
have it left to me be a rich relation, an' I'm th' pluthycrat iv me fam'ly,
or to stub me toe on a gambler's roll or stop a runaway horse f'r Pierpont
Morgan. An' th' horse mustn't be runnin' too fast. He must be jus' goin'
to stop, on'y Morgan don't know it, havin' fainted. Whin he comes to, he
finds me at th' bridle, modestly waitin' f'r him to weep on me bosom. But
as f'r scramblin' down town arly in th' mornin' an' buyin' chattel morgedges,
I niver thought iv it. I get up at siven o'clock. I wudden't get up at a
quarther to siven f'r all th' money I dhream about. I have a lot iv things
ar-round here I cud cash in if I cared f'r money. I have th' priceless gift
iv laziness. It's made me what I am, an' that's th' very first thing ivry
rich man cashes in. Th' millyonaires ye r-read about thryin' to give th'
rest iv th' wurruld a good time be runnin' over thim in autymobills all started
with a large stock iv indolence which they cashed in. Now, whin they cud
enjoy it, they can't buy it back. Thin I have me good health. Ye can always
get money on that. An' I have me frinds; I rayfuse to cash thim in, I don't
know that I cud get much on thim, but if I wanted to be a millyonaire, I'd
tuck you an' Hogan an' Donahue undher me ar-rm an' carry ye down to Mose.
</p><p>
"McMullin did cash. He had no more laziness thin me, but he cashed it in
befure he was twinty-wan. He cashed in his good health, a large stock iv
fam'ly ties, th' affiction if his wife, th' comforts iv home, an' wan frind
afther another. Wanst in a while, late in life, he'd thry to redeem a pledge,
but he niver cud. They wasn't annything in th' wurruld that McMullin wudden't
change f'r th' roly-boly. He cashed in his vote, his pathreetism, his rellijon,
his rilitives, an' fin'lly his hair. Ye heerd about him, didn't ye? He's
lost ivry hair on his head. They ain't a spear iv vigitation left on him.
He's as arid as th' desert iv Sahara. His head looks like an iceberg in th'
moonlight. He was in here th' other day, bewailin' his fate. 'It's a gr-reat
misfortune,' says he. 'What did ye get f'r it?' says I. 'That's th' throuble,'
says he. 'Well, don't complain,' says I. 'Think what ye save in barber's
bills,' I says, an' he wint away lookin' much cheered up.
</p><p>
"No, Hinnissy, you an' I, me frind, was not cut out be Provydence to be
millyionaires. If ye had nawthin' but money, ye'd have nawthin' but money.
Ye can't ate it, sleep it, dhrink it, or carry it away with ye. Ye've got
a lot iv things that McMullin hasn't got. Annybody that goes down to Mose's
won't see ye'er peace iv mind hangin' in th' window as an unredeemed pledge.
An' annyhow, if ye're really in search iv a fortune, perhaps I cud help ye.
Wud a dollar an' a half be anny use to ye?"
</p><p>
"Life is full iv disappointments," said Mr. Hennessy.
</p><p>
"It is," said Mr. Dooley, "if ye feel that way. It's thrue that a good many
have thried it an' none have come back f'r a post-gradjate coorse. But still
it ain't so bad as a career f'r a young man. Ye niver get what ye ordher,
but it's pretty good if ye'er appytite ain't keen an' ye care f'r th' scenery."
</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
