<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="EwiHear"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="EwiHear">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Heart of the Race Problem</title>
<title type="sort">heart of the race problem</title>
<author>Ewing, Quincy</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">36</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">EwiHear</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475950</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Heart of the Race Problem</title>
<title type="sort">heart of the race problem</title>
<author>Ewing, Quincy</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1909">1909</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 103</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 389-397</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1909">1909</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction; prose</term>
<term>African American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-08">August 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Minimal TEI tagging</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">



<div1 type="article" id="d3"><pb n="389"/>
<head>Ewing, Quincy.  "The Heart of the Race Problem."  <lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 103 (1909): 389-397.</head>

<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d4">

<p>"And, instead of going to the Congress of the United States
and saying there is no distinction made in Mississippi, because of
color or previous condition of servitude, tell the truth, and say
this: 'We tried for many years to live in Mississippi, and share
sovereignty and dominion with the Negro, and we saw our
institutions crumbling. . . .  We rose in the majesty and highest
type of Anglo-Saxon manhood, and took the reins of government out
of the hands of the carpet-bagger and the Negro, and, so help us
God, from now on we will never share any sovereignty or dominion
with him again.'" &mdash; Governor JAMES K. VARDAMAN, Mississippi, 1904.

</p><p>DURING the past decade, newspaper and magazine articles
galore, and not a few books, have been written on what is called
the "Race Problem," the problem caused by the presence in this
country of some ten millions of black and variously-shaded colored
people known as Negroes.  But, strange as it may sound, the writer
has no hesitation in saying that at this date there appears to be
no clear conception anywhere, on the part of most people, as to
just what the essential problem is which confronts the white
inhabitants of the country because they have for fellow-citizens
(nominally) ten million Negroes.  Ask the average man, ask even the
average editor or professor anywhere, what the race problem is, the
heart of it; why, in this land with its millions of foreigners of
all nationalities, <hi rend="italic">the</hi> race problem of problems should be
caused by ten million Negroes, not foreigners but native to the
soil through several generations; and in all probability you will
get some such answer as this: &mdash;
</p><p>"The Negroes, as a rule, are very ignorant, are very lazy, are
very brutal, are very criminal.  But a little way removed from
savagery, they are incapable of adopting the white man's moral
code, of assimilating the white man's moral sentiments, of striving
toward the white man's moral ideals.  They are creatures of brutal,
untamed instincts, and uncontrolled feral passions, which give
frequent expression of themselves in crimes of horrible ferocity.
They are, in brief, an uncivilized, semi-savage people, living in
a civilization to which they are unequal, partaking to a limited
degree of its benefits, performing in no degree its duties.
Because they are spatially in a civilization to which they are
morally and intellectually repugnant, they cannot but be as a
foreign irritant to the body social.  The problem is, How shall the
body social adjust itself, daily, hourly, to this irritant; how
feel at ease and safe in spite of it?  How shall the white
inhabitants of the land, with their centuries of inherited
superiority, conserve their civilization and carry it forward to a
yet higher plane, hampered by ten million black inhabitants of the
same land with their centuries of inherited inferiority?"
</p><p>To the foregoing answer, this might now and again be added, or
advanced independently in reply to our question: "Personal aversion
on the part of the white person for the Negro; personal aversion
accounted for by nothing the individual Negro is, or is not,
intellectually and morally; accounted for by the fact, simply, that
he is a Negro, that he has a black or colored skin, that he is
different, of another kind."
</p><p>Now, certainly, there are very few average men or
philosophers, to whom the answer given to our question would not
seem to state, or at any rate fairly indicate, the race problem in
its essence.  But, however few they be, I do not hesitate to align
myself with them as one who does not believe that the essential
race problem
<pb n="390"/>
as it exists in the South (whatever it be in
the North) is stated, or even fairly indicated, in the foregoing
answer.  In Northern and Western communities, where he is
outnumbered by many thousands of white people, the Negro may be
accounted a problem, because he is lazy, or ignorant, or brutal, or
criminal, or all these things together; or because he is black and
different.  But in Southern communities, where the Negro is not
outnumbered by many thousands of white people, the race problem,
essentially, and in its most acute form, is something distinct from
his laziness or ignorance, or brutality, or criminality, or all-round intellectual and moral inferiority to the white man.  That
problem as the South knows and deals with it would exist, as
certainly as it does to-day, if there were no shadow of excuse for
the conviction that the Negro is more lazy, or more ignorant, or
more criminal, or more brutal, or more anything else he ought not
to be, or less anything else he ought to be, than other men.  In
other words, let it be supposed that the average Negro is as a
matter of fact the equal, morally and intellectually, of the
average white man of the same class, and the race problem declines
to vanish, declines to budge.  We shall see why, presently.  The
statements just made demand immediate justification.  For they are
doubtless surprising to a degree, and to some readers may prove
startling.
</p><p>I proceed to justify them as briefly as possible, asking the
reader to bear in mind that very much more might be said along this
line than I allow myself space to say.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d5">

<p>That the Negro is not a problem because he is lazy, because he
declines to work, is evidenced by the patent fact that in virtually
every Southern community he is sought as a laborer in fields,
mills, mines, and that in very many Southern communities the vexing
problem for employers is not too many, but too few Negroes.  In
certain agricultural sections, notably in the Louisiana sugar
district, quite a number of Italians ("Dagoes") are employed.  The
reason is not dissatisfaction with Negro labor, but simply that
there is not enough of it to meet the requirements of the large
plantations.  There is, perhaps, not one of these plantations on
which any able-bodied Negro could not get employment for the
asking; and as a rule, the Negroes are given, not the work which
demands the lowest, but that which demands the highest, efficiency:
they are the ploughmen, the teamsters, the foremen.  If any one
doubts that Negroes are wanted as laborers in Southern communities,
very much wanted, let him go to any such community and attempt to
inveigle a few dozen of the laziest away.  He will be likely to
take his life in his hands, after the usual warning is disregarded!
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="3" id="d6">


<p>The small politician's trump-card, played early and late, and in
all seasons, that the Negro is a black shadow over the Southland
because of his excessive criminality, serves well the politician's
purpose, &mdash; it wins his game; but only because the game is played and
won on a board where fictions, not facts, are dominant.  Nothing is
easier than to offer so-called proofs of the contention that the
Negro's tendency to crime is something peculiar to his race; there
are the jail and penitentiary and gallows statistics, for instance.
But surely it should not be difficult for these so-called proofs to
present themselves in their true light to any one who takes the
trouble to consider two weighty and conspicuous facts: this, first,
that the Negroes occupy everywhere in this country the lowest
social and industrial plane, the plane which everywhere else
supplies the jail, the penitentiary, the gallows, with the greatest
number of their victims; and secondly this, that in the section of
the country where these penal statistics are gathered, all the
machinery
<pb n="391"/>
of justice is in the hands of white men.
</p><p>No Negro is a sheriff, or judge, or justice of the peace, or
grand or petit juryman, or member of a pardoning board.  Charged
with crime, again and again, the black man must go to jail; he is
unable to give bond; he is defended, not by the ablest, but by the
poorest lawyers, often by an unwilling appointee of the court; he
lacks the benefit of that personal appeal to judge and jury, so
often enjoyed by other defendants, which would make them <hi rend="italic">want</hi>
to believe him innocent until proven guilty; he faces, on the
contrary, a judge and jury who hold him in some measure of contempt
as a man, regardless of his guilt or innocence.  He is without
means, except occasionally, to fight his case through appeals to
higher courts, and errors sleep in many a record that on review
would upset the verdict.  In the light of such considerations, it
would seem impossible that criminal statistics should not bear hard
upon the Negro race, even supposing it to be a fact that that race
of all races in the world is the <hi rend="italic">least</hi> criminal.
</p><p>Let it be admitted without question that in most Southern
communities the crimes and misdemeanors of the Negroes exceed those
committed by an equal number of white people, and we have admitted
nothing that at all explains or accounts for the race problem.  For
is it not equally true that in every other community the doers of
society's rough work, the recipients of its meagrest rewards, are
chargeable, relatively, with the greatest number of crimes and
misdemeanors?  Is it not true, as well in Massachusetts and
Connecticut as in Louisiana and Mississippi, that the vast majority
of those occupying prison cells are members of the social lowest
class? that the vast majority condemned, after trial, to hard labor
with their hands were accustomed to such labor before their
judicial condemnation?   Nothing is more preposterous than the idea
that the race problem means more Negroes hanged, more Negroes
imprisoned, more Negroes in mines and chain-gangs, than white
people!  If the Negro did not furnish the great bulk of the grist
for the grinding of our penal machinery in the Southern states, he
would constitute the racial miracle of this and all ages!
</p><p>My own conviction is, and I speak with the experience of forty
years' residence in Southern states, that the Negro is not more
given to crimes and misdemeanors than the laboring population of
any other section of the country.  But be this as it may, it is
abundantly certain that no race of people anywhere are more easily
controlled than the Negroes by the guardians of law and order; and
there are none anywhere so easily punished for disobedience to the
statutes and mandates of their economic superiors.  Courts and
juries may be sometimes subject to just criticism for undue
leniency toward white defendants; but that courts and juries are
ever subject to just criticism for undue leniency in dealing with
black defendants is the sheerest nonsense.
</p><p>The frequent charge that the Negro's worst crimes partake of
a brutality that is peculiarly racial, is not supported by facts.
I need not enlarge upon this statement further than to say that the
Negro's worst crimes, with all their shocking accompaniments, are,
not seldom, but often, duplicated by white men.  Let any one who
doubts the statement observe for one week the criminal statistics
of any cosmopolitan newspaper, and he will have his doubt removed.
</p><p>Assuredly we do not hit upon the essence of the race problem
in the Negro's propensity to crime!
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="4" id="d7">


<p>Do we hit upon it in his ignorance, in the fact that an
immense number of the black people are illiterate, not knowing the
first from the last letter of the alphabet?  Hardly.  For, almost
to a man, the people who most parade and most rail at the race
problem in private conversation, on the political platform, and in
the pages of newspapers, books, and periodicals,
<pb n="392"/>
are
disposed rather to lament, than to assist, the passing of the
Negro's ignorance.  Ex-Governor Vardaman, of Mississippi, used the
following language in a message to the legislature of that state,
January, 1906: &mdash;
</p><p>"The startling facts revealed by the census show that those
[Negroes] who can read and write are more criminal than the
illiterate, which is true of no other element of our population. .
. .  The state for many years, at great expense to the tax-payers,
has maintained a system of Negro education which has produced
disappointing results, and I am opposed to the perpetuation of this
system.  My own idea is, that the character of education for the
Negro ought to be changed.  If, after forty years of earnest
effort, and the expenditure of fabulous sums to educate his head,
we have only succeeded in making a criminal of him and impairing
his usefulness and efficiency as a laborer, wisdom would suggest
that we make another experiment and see if we cannot improve him by
educating his hand and his heart. . . .  Slavery is the only
process by which he has ever been partially civilized.  God
Almighty created the Negro for a menial, he is essentially a
servant."
</p><p>This is the reply of an ex-governor of one of our blackest
states to those who contend that the negro is a problem, a "burden
carried by the white people of the South," because of his ignorance
and consequent inefficiency; and that the lightening of the burden
depends upon more money spent, more earnest efforts made, for the
schooling of the black people.  According to this ex-governor, and
there are thousands who agree with him in and out of Mississippi,
the race problem is heightened, rather than mitigated, by all
attempts to increase the negro's intellectual efficiency.  The more
ignorant he is, the less burdensome he is to the white man,
provided his heart be good, and his hands skillful enough to do the
service of a menial.  Nothing but slavery ever partially civilized
him, nothing but slavery continued in some form can civilize him
further!
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="5" id="d8">


<p>If we listen vainly for the heart-throb of the race problem in
the Negro's laziness, and criminality, and brutality, and
ignorance, and inefficiency, do we detect it with clearness and
certainty in the personal aversion felt by the white people for the
black people, aversion which the white people can no more help
feeling than the black people can help exciting?  Is this the real
trouble, the real burden, the real tragedy and sorrow of our white
population in those sections of the country where the Negroes are
many, &mdash; that they are compelled to dwell face to face, day by day,
with an inferior, degraded population, repulsive to their finer
sensibilities, obnoxious to them in countless ways inexplicable?
Facts are far from furnishing an affirmative answer.  However
pronounced may be the feeling of personal aversion toward the
Negroes in Northern communities, where they are few, or known at
long range, or casually, there is no such thing in Southern
communities as personal aversion for the Negro pronounced enough to
be responsible for anything resembling a problem.  How could there
be in the South, where from infancy we have all been as familiar
with black faces as with white; where many of us fell asleep in the
laps of black mammies, and had for playmates Ephrom, Izik, Zeke,
black mammy's grandchildren; where most of us have had our meals
prepared by black cooks, and been waited on by black house-servants
and dining-room servants, and ridden in carriages and buggies with
black hostlers?  We are so used to the black people in the South,
their mere personal presence is so far from being responsible for
our race problem, that the South would not seem Southern without
them, as it would not without its crape myrtles, and live-oaks, and
magnolias, its cotton and its sugar-cane!
<pb n="393"/>
</p><p>It is very easy to go astray in regard to the matter of
personal aversion toward the members of alien races, to magnify
greatly the reality and importance of it.  What seems race-aversion
is frequently something else, namely, revulsion aroused by the
presence of the strange, the unusual, the uncanny, the not-understood.  Such revulsion is aroused, not only by the members of
alien races, alien and unfamiliar, but as certainly by strange
animals of not more terrifying appearance than the well-loved cow
and horse; and it would be aroused as really and as painfully,
doubtless, by the sudden proximity of one of Milton's archangels.
It was not necessarily race-aversion which made Emerson, and may
have made many another Concord philosopher, uncomfortable in the
presence of a Negro, any more than it is race-aversion which makes
the Fifth Avenue boy run from the gentle farmyard cow; any more
than it is race-aversion which would make me uncomfortable in the
presence of Li Hung Chang.  The Negro, simply, it may be, was a
mystery to Emerson, as the farmyard cow is a mystery to the Fifth
Avenue boy, as the Chinaman is a mystery to me.
</p><p>The Negro is <hi rend="italic">not</hi> a mystery to people whom he has nursed
and waited on, whose language he has spoken, whose ways, good and
bad, he has copied for generations; and his personal presence does
not render them uncomfortable, not, at any rate, uncomfortable
enough to beget the sense of a burden or a problem.
</p><p>It may be very difficult for Northern readers, to whom the
Negro is in reality a stranger, a foreigner, to appreciate fully
the force of what has just been said; but appreciated by them it
must be, or they can never hope to realize the innermost meaning of
the race problem in the South.

</p><p>So much for what the race problem is not.  Let me without
further delay state what it is.  The foundation of it, true or
false, is the white man's conviction that the Negro as a race, and
as an individual, is his inferior: not human in the sense that he
is human, not entitled to the exercise of human rights in the sense
that he is entitled to the exercise of them.  The problem itself,
the essence of it, the heart of it, is the white man's
determination to make good this conviction, coupled with constant
anxiety lest, by some means, he should fail to make it good.  The
race problem, in other words, is <hi rend="italic">not</hi> that the Negro is what he
is in relation to the white man, the white man's inferior; but
this, rather: How to keep him what he is in relation to the white
man; how to prevent his ever achieving or becoming that which would
justify the belief on his part, or on the part of other people,
that he and the white man stand on common human ground.
</p><p>That such is the heart of the problem should be made evident
by this general consideration alone: namely, that everywhere in the
South friction between the races is entirely absent so long as the
Negro justifies the white man's opinion of him as an inferior; is
grateful for privileges and lays no claim to <hi rend="italic">rights</hi>.  Let him
seem content to be as the South insists he shall be, and not only
is he not harshly treated, not abused, and never boycotted, but he
is shown much kindness and generosity, and employment awaits him
for the asking.  Trouble brews when he begins to manifest those
qualities, to reveal those tastes, to give vent to those ambitions,
which are supposed to be characteristic exclusively of the higher
human type, and which, unless restrained, would result in
confounding the lower with the higher.  The expression "Good
Nigger" means everywhere in the South a real Negro, from the
Southern standpoint, one who in no respect gets out of focus with
that standpoint; the expression "Bad Nigger" means universally one
who in some respect, not necessarily criminal, does get out of
focus with it.  So, stated differently, the race problem is the
problem how to keep the Negro in focus with the traditional
standpoint.
</p><p>But we are very far from needing to rely
<pb n="394"/>
upon any
general consideration in support of the proposition advanced above.
It is supported by evidences on every hand, waiting only the eye of
recognition.  Scarcely a day passes but something is said or done
with this end in view, to emphasize, lest they forget, the
conviction for both white man and Negro that the latter is and must
remain an inferior.  Let me instance a few such evidences.
</p><p>Consider, first, the "Jim Crow" legislation in the manner of
its enforcement.  Such legislation is supposed to have for its
object the separation of the races in trains, street-cars, etc., to
save the white people from occasional contact with drunken, rowdy,
ill-smelling Negroes, and to prevent personal encounters between
the whites and blacks.  How is this object attained in the street
cars of Southern cities?  Members of the different races occupy the
same cars, separated only by absurdly inadequate little open-mesh
wire screens, so tiny and light that a conductor can move them from
one seat to another with the strength of his little finger.
Needless to add, these screens would serve to obscure neither
sound, sight, nor smell of drunken rowdies who sat behind them!  In
summer cars black and white passengers may be separated not even by
a make-believe screen; they are simply required, respectively, to
occupy certain seats in the front or the back end of the cars.
</p><p>In Birmingham, Alabama, the front seats are assigned to
Negroes in all closed cars, and the back seats in all open ones.
Why the front seats in the one case, and the back seats in the
other, it is not easy to understand in the light of the letter and
alleged spirit of the Jim Crow law!  The underlying purpose of the
law is clearly not the separation of the races in space; for public
sentiment does not insist upon its fulfillment to that end.  The
underlying purpose of it would seem to be the separation of the
races in status.  The doctrine of inequality would be attacked if
white and black passengers rode in public conveyances on equal
terms; therefore the Negro who rides in a public conveyance must do
so, not as of undoubted right, but as with the white man's
permission, subject to the white man's regulation.  <hi rend="italic">"This place
you may occupy, that other you may not, because I am I and you are
you, lest to you or me it should be obscured that I am I and you
are you."</hi>  Such is the real spirit of the Jim Crow laws.
</p><p>Why is it that in every Southern city no Negro is allowed to
witness a dramatic performance, or a baseball game, from a first-class seat?  In every large city, there are hundreds of Negroes who
would gladly pay for first-class seats at the theatre and the
baseball game, were they permitted to.  It can hardly be that
permission is withheld because theatres and baseball games are so
well attended by half the population that first-class seats could
not be furnished for the other half.  As a matter of fact, theatre-auditoriums and baseball grand-stands are seldom crowded; the rule
is, not all first-class seats occupied, but many vacant.  Surely as
simple as moving from seat to seat a make-shift screen in a street-car, would it be to set apart a certain number of seats in the
dress-circle of every theatre, and in the grand-stand of every
baseball park, for Negro patrons.  The reason why this is not done
is perfectly obvious: it would be intolerable to the average
Southern man or woman to sit through the hours of a theatrical
performance or a baseball game on terms of equal accommodation with
Negroes, even with a screen between.  Negroes would look out of
place, out of status, in the dress circle or the grand-stand; their
place, signifying their status, is the peanut-gallery, or the
bleachers.  There, neither they nor others will be tempted to
forget that as things are they must continue.
</p><p>How shall we account for the "intense feeling" (to quote the
language of the mayor or New Orleans) occasioned in that city one
day, last July, when it was flashed over the wires that the first
prize in the National Spelling Contest had been
<pb n="395"/>
won by a
Negro girl, in competition with white children from New Orleans and
other Southern cities?  The indignation of at least one of the
leading New Orleans papers verged upon hysterics; the editor's
rhetoric visited upon some foulest crime could hardly have been
more inflamed than in denunciation of the fact that, on the far-away shore of Lake Erie, New Orleans white children had competed at
a spelling bee with a Negro girl.  The superintendent of the New
Orleans schools was roundly denounced in many quarters for
permitting his wards to compete with a Negro; and there were broad
hints in "Letters from the People" to the papers that his
resignation was in order.
</p><p>Certainly in the days following the National Spelling Contest
the race problem was in evidence, if it ever was, in New Orleans
and the South!  Did it show itself, then, as the problem of Negro
crime, or brutality, or laziness?  Assuredly not!  Of the Negro's
personal repulsiveness?  By no means!  There was no evidence of
Negro criminality, or brutality, or laziness in the Negro child's
victory; and every day in the South, in their games and otherwise,
hundreds of white children of the best families are in closer
personal contact with little Negroes than were the white children
who took part in the Cleveland spelling bee.  The "intense feeling"
can be explained on one ground only: the Negro girl's victory was
an affront to the tradition of the Negro's inferiority; it
suggested &mdash; perhaps indicated &mdash; that, given equal opportunities, all
Negroes are not necessarily the intellectual inferiors of all white
people.  What other explanation is rationally conceivable?  If the
race problem means in the South to its white inhabitants the burden
and tragedy of having to dwell face to face with an intellectually
and morally backward people, why should not the Negro girl's
triumph have occasioned intense feeling of pleasure, rather than
displeasure, by its suggestion that her race is not intellectually
hopeless?
</p><p>Consider further that while no Negro, no matter what his
occupation, or personal refinement, or intellectual culture, or
moral character, is allowed to travel in a Pullman car between
state lines, or to enter as a guest a hotel patronized by white
people, the blackest of Negro nurses and valets are given food and
shelter in all first-class hotels, and occasion neither disgust,
nor surprise in the Pullman cars.  Here again the heart of the race
problem is laid bare.  The black nurse with a white baby in her
arms, the black valet looking after the comfort of a white invalid,
have the label of their inferiority conspicuously upon them; they
understand themselves, and everybody understands them, to be
servants, enjoying certain privileges for the sake of the person
served.  Almost anything, the Negro may do in the South, and
anywhere he may go, provided the manner of his doing and his doing
is that of an inferior.  Such is the premium put upon his
inferiority; such his inducement to maintain it.
</p><p>The point here insisted on may be made clearer, if already it
is not clear enough, by this consideration, that the man who would
lose social caste for dining with an Irish street-sweeper might be
congratulated for dining with an Irish educator; but President
Roosevelt would scarcely have given greater offense by entertaining
a Negro laborer at the White House than he gave by inviting to
lunch there the Principal of Tuskegee Institute.  The race problem
being what it is, the status of any Negro is logically the status
of every other.  There are recognizable degrees of inferiority
among Negroes themselves; some are vastly superior to others.  But
there is only one degree of inferiority separating the Negro from
the white person, attached to all Negroes alike.  The logic of the
situation requires that to be any sort of black man is to be
inferior to any sort of white man; and from this logic there is no
departure in the South.
</p><p>Inconsistent, perhaps, with what has been said may seem the
defeat in the Louisiana Legislature (1908) of the anti-miscegenation bill, a measure designed
<pb n="396"/>
to prohibit sexual
cohabitation between white persons and Negroes; to be specific,
between white men and Negro women.  But there was no inconsistency
whatever in the defeat of that bill.  In all times and places, the
status of that portion of the female population, Lecky's martyred
"priestesses of humanity," whose existence men have demanded for
the gratification of unlawful passion, has been that of social
outcasts.  They have no rights that they can insist upon; they are
simply privileged to exist by society's permission, and may be any
moment legislated out of their vocation.  Hence the defeat of an
anti-miscegenation measure by Southern legislators cannot be
construed as a failure on their part to live up to their conviction
of race-superiority.  It must be construed, rather, as legislative
unwillingness to restrict the white man's liberty; to dictate by
statute the kind of social outcast which he may use as a mere means
to the gratification of his passion.  To concede to Negro women the
status of a degraded and proscribed class, is not in any sense to
overlook or obscure their racial inferiority, but on the contrary,
it may be, to emphasize it.  Precisely the same principle, in a
word, compasses the defeat of an anti-miscegenation bill which
would compass the defeat of a measure to prohibit Negro servants
from occupying seats in Pullman cars.
</p><p>At the risk of reiteration, I must in concluding this article
take sharp issue with the view of a recent very able writer, who
asks the question, "What, essentially, is the Race Problem?" and
answers it thus: "The race problem is the problem of living with
human beings who are not like us, whether they are in our
estimation our 'superiors' or inferiors, whether they have kinky
hair or pigtails, whether they are slant-eyed, hook-nosed, or
thick-lipped.  In its essence, it is the same problem, magnified,
which besets every neighborhood, even every family."
</p><p>I have contended so far, and I here repeat, that the race
problem is essentially <hi rend="italic">not</hi> what this writer declares it to be.
It is emphatically not, in the South, "the problem of living with
human beings who are not like us, whether they are in our
estimation our superiors or inferiors."  It may be, it probably is,
that in the North, where the Negro is largely a stranger, a
foreigner, very much to the same degree that the Chinese are
strangers and foreigners in the South; and where, consequently, the
Negro's personal repulsiveness is a much more significant force
than it is in the South.  Assuredly there would be no race problem,
anywhere, were there no contact with others unlike ourselves!  The
unlikeness of the unlike is everywhere its indispensable
foundation.  But we get nowhither unless we carefully distinguish
between the foundation of the problem and the problem itself.
There is nothing in the unlikeness of the unlike that is
necessarily problematical; it may be simply accepted and dealt with
as a fact, like any other fact.  The problem arises only when the
people of one race are minded to adopt and act upon some policy
more or less oppressive or repressive in dealing with the people of
another race.  In the absence of some such policy, there has never
been a race problem since the world began.  It is the existence of
such a policy become traditional, and supported by immovable
conviction, which constitutes the race problem of the Southern
states.
</p><p>There was an immensely tragic race problem distressing the
South fifty years ago; but who will suggest that it was the problem
of "living with human beings who are not like us?"  The problem
then was, clearly, how to make good a certain conviction concerning
the unlike, how to maintain a certain policy in dealing with them.
What else is it today?  The problem, How to maintain the
institution of chattel slavery, ceased to be at Appomattox; the
problem, How to maintain the social, industrial, and civic
inferiority of the descendants of chattel slaves, succeeded it, and
is the race problem of the South at the present time.  There is no
other.
<pb n="397"/>
</p><p>Whether the policy adopted by the white South, and supported,
as I have said, by immovable conviction, is expedient or
inexpedient, wise or unwise, righteous or unrighteous, these are
questions which I have not sought to answer one way or another in
this article.  Perhaps they cannot be answered at all in our time.
Certain is it, that their only real and satisfactory answer will be
many years ahead of the present generation.
</p><p>In the mean time, nothing could be more unwarranted, than to
suppose that the race problem of one section of this country is
peculiar to that section, because its white inhabitants are
themselves in some sense peculiar; because they are peculiarly
prejudiced, because they are peculiarly behind the hour which the
high clock of civilization has struck.  Remove the white
inhabitants of the South, give their place to the white people of
any other section of the United States, and, beyond a peradventure,
the Southern race problem, as I have defined it, would continue to
be &mdash; revealed, perhaps, in ways more perplexing, more intense and
tragic.
</p>

</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
