<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="FleNeda"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="FleNeda">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Nedawi</title>
<title type="sort">nedawi</title>
<author>La Flesche, Suzette</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">25</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">FleNeda</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475960</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Nedawi</title>
<title type="sort">nedawi</title>
<author>La Flesche, Suzette</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>St. Nicholas Magazine</publisher>
<date value="1881-01">Jan. 1881</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Volume 8</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Verification made against printed text</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1881">1881</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman and Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head>La Flesche, Suzette.  "Nedawi."
<lb/>
<hi rend="italic"> (An Indian Story from Real Life.)</hi>
<lb/>
BY "BRIGHT EYES."
<lb/>
<hi rend="italic"> St. Nicholas</hi> 8 (Jan. 1881): 225-30.</head>

<pb n="225"/>

<p>
"NEDAWI!" called her mother, "take your little brother while I go
with your sister for some wood."  Nedawi ran into the tent,
bringing back her little red blanket, but the brown-faced, roly-poly baby, who had been having a comfortable nap in spite of being
all the while tied straight to his board, woke with a merry crow
just as the mother was about to attach him, board and all, to
Nedawi's neck.  So he was taken from the board instead, and, after
he had kicked in happy freedom for a moment, Nedawi stood in front
of her mother, who placed Habazhu on the little girl's back, and
drew the blanket over him, leaving his arms free.  She next put
into his hand a little hollow gourd, filled with seeds, which
served as a rattle; Nedawi held both ends of the blanket tightly in
front of her, and was then ready to walk around with the little
man.
</p><p>Where should she go?  Yonder was a group of young girls
playing a game of <hi rend="italic"> konci</hi>, or dice.  The dice were five plum-seeds, scorched black, and had little stars and quarter-moons
instead of numbers.  She went over and stood by the group, gently
rock-<pb n="226"/>ing herself from side to side, pretty much as white
children do when reciting the multiplication table.  The girls
would toss up the wooden bowl, letting it drop with a gentle thud
on the pillow beneath, the falling dice making a pleasant clatter
which the baby liked to hear.  The stakes were a little heap of
beads, rings, and bracelets.  The laughter and exclamations of the
girls, as some successful toss brought down the dice three stars
and two quarter-moons (the highest throw), made Nedawi wish that
she, too, were a young girl, and could win and wear all those
pretty things.  How gay she would look!  Just then, the little
glittering heap caught baby's eye.  He tried to wriggle out of the
blanket to get to it, but Nedawi held tight.  Then he set up a
yell.  Nedawi walked away very reluctantly, because she wanted to
stay and see who would win.  She went to her mother's tent, but
found it deserted.  Her father and brothers had gone to the chase.
A herd of buffalo had been seen that morning, and all the men in
the tribe had gone, and would not be back till night.  Her mother,
her sister, and the women of the household had gone to the river
for wood and water.  The tent looked enticingly cool, with the
sides turned up to let the breeze sweep through, and the straw mats
and soft robes seemed to invite her to lie down on them and dream
the afternoon away, as she was too apt to do.  She did not yield to
the temptation, however, for she knew Mother would not like it, but
walked over to her cousin Metai's tent.  She found her cousin
"keeping house" with a number of little girls, and stood <pb n="227"/> to
watch them while they put up little tents, just large enough to
hold one or two girls.
</p><p>"Nedawi, come and play," said Metai.  "You can make the fire
and cook.  I'll ask Mother for something to cook."
</p><p>"But what shall I do with Habazhu?" said Nedawi.
</p><p>"I'll tell you.  Put him in my tent, and make believe he's our
little old grandfather."
</p><p>Forthwith he was transferred from Nedawi's back to the little
tent.  But Habazhu had a decided objection to staying in the dark
little place, where he could not see anything, and crept out of the
door on his hands and knees.  Nedawi collected a little heap of
sticks, all ready for the fire, and went off to get a fire-brand to
light it with.  While she was gone, Habazhu crawled up to a bowl of
water which stood by the intended fire-place, and began dabbling in
it with his chubby little hands, splashing the water all over the
sticks prepared for the fire.  Then he thought he would like a
drink.  He tried to lift the bowl in both hands, but only succeeded
in spilling the water over himself and the fire-place.
</p><p>When Nedawi returned, she stood aghast; then, throwing down
the brand, she took her little brother by the shoulders and, I am
sorry to say, shook him violently, jerked him up, and dumped him
down by the door of the little tent from which he had crawled.
"You bad little boy!" she said.  "It's too bad that I have to take
care of you when I want to play."
</p><p>You see, she was no more perfect than any little white girl
who gets into a temper now and then.  The baby's lip quivered, and
he began to cry.  Metai said to Nedawi: "I think it's real mean for
you to shake him, when he doesn't know any better."
</p><p>Metai picked up baby and tried to comfort him.  She kissed him
over and over, and talked to him in baby language.  Nedawi's
conscience, if the little savage could be said to have any, was
troubling her.  She loved her baby brother dearly, even though she
did get out of patience with him now and then.
</p><p>"I'll put a clean little shirt on him and pack him again,"
said she, suddenly.  Then she took off his little wet shirt, wrung
it out, and spread it on the tall grass to dry in the sun.  Then
she went home, and, going to a pretty painted skin in which her
mother kept his clothes, she selected the red shirt, which she
thought was the prettiest.  She was in such a hurry, however, that
she forgot to close and tie up the skin again, and she carelessly
left his clean shirts lying around as she had laid them out.  When
Baby was on her back again, she walked around with him, giving
directions and overseeing the other girls at their play, determined
to do that rather than nothing.
</p><p>The other children were good-natured, and took her ordering as
gracefully as they could.  Metai made the fire in a new place, and
then went to ask her mother to give her something to cook.  Her
mother gave her a piece of dried buffalo meat, as hard as a chip
and as brittle as glass.  Metai broke it up into small pieces, and
put the pieces into a little tin pail of water, which she hung over
the fire.  "Now," she said, "when the meat is cooked and the soup
is made, I will call you all to a feast, and Habazhu shall be the
chief."
</p><p>They all laughed.  But alas for human calculations!  During
the last few minutes, a shy little girl, with soft, wistful black
eyes, had been watching them from a little distance.  She had on a
faded, shabby blanket and a ragged dress.
</p><p>"Metai," said Nedawi, "let's ask that girl to play with us;
she looks so lonesome."
</p><p>"Well," said Metai, doubtfully, "I don't care; but my mother
said she didn't want me to play with ragged little girls."
</p><p>"My father says we must be kind to poor little girls, and help
them all we can; so <hi rend="italic"> I'm</hi> going to play with her if <hi rend="italic"> you</hi>
don't," said Nedawi, loftily.
</p><p>Although Metai was the hostess, Nedawi was the leading spirit,
and had her own way, as usual.  She walked up to the little
creature and said, "Come and play with us, if you want to."  The
little girl's eyes brightened, and she laughed.  Then she suddenly
drew from under her blanket a pretty bark basket, filled with the
most delicious red and yellow plums.  "My brother picked them in
the woods, and I give them to you," was all she said.  Nedawi
managed to free one hand, and took the offering with an exclamation
of delight, which drew the other girls quickly around.  Instead of
saying "Oh!  Oh!" as you would have said, they cried "Hin!  Hin!"
which expressed their feeling quite as well, perhaps.
</p><p>"Let us have them for our feast," said Metai, taking them.
</p><p>Little Indian children are taught to share everything with one
another, so it did not seem strange to Nedawi to have her gift
looked on as common property.  But, while the attention of the
little group had been concentrated on the matter in hand, a party
of mischievous boys, passing by, caught sight of the little tents
and the tin pail hanging over the fire.  Simultaneously, they set
up a war-whoop and, dashing into the deserted camp, they sent the
tent-poles scattering right and left, and snatching up whatever
they could lay hands on, including the tin pail and its contents,
they retreated.  The little girls, startled by the sudden raid on
their property, looked up.  Rage possessed their little <pb n="228"/>
souls.  Giving shrieks of anger, they started in pursuit.  What did
Nedawi do?  She forgot plums, baby, and everything.  The ends of
the blanket slipped from her grasp, and she darted forward like an
arrow after her companions.
</p><p>Finding the chase hopeless, the little girls came to a stand-still, and some of them began to cry.  The boys had stopped, too;
and seeing the tears flow, being good-hearted boys in spite of
their mischief, they surrendered at discretion.  They threw back
the articles they had taken, not daring to come near.  They did not
consider it manly for big boys like themselves to strike or hurt
little girls, even though they delighted in teasing them, and they
knew from experience that they would be at the mercy of the
offended party if they went near enough to be touched.  The boy who
had the dinner brought the little pail which had contained it as
near as he dared, and setting it down ran away.
</p><p>"You have spilt all our soup.  There's hardly any of it left.
You bad boys!" said one of the girls.
</p><p>They crowded around with lamentations over their lost dinner.
The boys began to feel remorseful.
</p><p>"Let's go into the woods and get them some plums to make up
for it."
</p><p>"Say, girls, hand us your pail, and we'll fill it up with
plums for you."
</p><p>So the affair was settled.
</p><p>But, meanwhile, what became of the baby left so
unceremoniously in the tall grass?  First he opened his black eyes
wide at this style of treatment.  He was not used to it.  Before he
had time, however, to make up his mind whether to laugh or cry, his
mother came to the rescue.  She had just come home and thrown the
wood off her back, when she caught sight of Nedawi dropping him.
She ran to pick him up, and finding him unhurt, kissed him over and
over.  Some of the neighbors had run up to see what was the matter.
She said to them:
</p><p>"I never did see such a thoughtless, heedless child as my
Nedawi.  She really has 'no ears.'  I don't know what in the world
will ever become of her.  When something new interests her, she
forgets everything else.  It was just like her to act in this way."
</p><p>Then they all laughed, and one of them said:
</p><p>"Never mind&mdash;she will grow wiser as she grows older," after
which consoling remark they went away to their own tents.
</p><p>It was of no use to call Nedawi back.  She was too far off.
</p><p>Habazhu was given over to the care of the nurse, who had just
returned from her visit.  An hour or two after, Nedawi came home.
</p><p>"Mother!" she exclaimed, as she saw her mother frying bread
for supper, "I am so hungry.  Can I have some of that bread?"
</p><p>"Where is your little brother?" was the unexpected reply.
</p><p>Nedawi started.  Where <hi rend="italic"> had</hi> she left him?  She tried to
think.
</p><p>"Why, mother, the last I remember I was packing him, and&mdash;and,
oh, Mother! you <hi rend="italic"> know</hi> where he is.  Please tell me."
</p><p>"When you find him and bring him back to me, perhaps I shall
forgive you," was the cold reply.
</p><p>This was dreadful.  Her mother had never treated her in that
way before.  She burst into tears, and started out to find Habazhu,
crying all the way.  She knew that her mother knew where baby was,
or she would not have taken it so coolly; and she knew also that
her mother expected her to bring him home.  As she went stumbling
along through the grass, she felt herself seized and held in
somebody's strong arms, and a great, round, hearty voice said:
</p><p>"What's the matter with my little niece?  Have all her friends
deserted her that she is wailing like this?  Or has her little dog
died?  I thought Nedawi was a brave little woman."
</p><p>It was her uncle Two Crows.  She managed to tell him, through
her sobs, the whole story.  She knew, if she told him herself, he
would not laugh at her about it, for he would sympathize in her
troubles, though he was a great tease.  When she ceased, he said to
her: "Well, your mother wants you to be more careful next time, I
suppose; and, by the way, I think I saw a little boy who looked
very much like Habazhu, in my tent."
</p><p>Sure enough, she found him there with his nurse.  When she got
home with them, she found her mother,&mdash;her own dear self,&mdash;and,
after giving her a big hug, she sat quietly down by the fire,
resolved to be very good in the future.  She did not sit long,
however, for soon a neighing of horses, and the running of girls
and children through the camp to meet the hunters, proclaimed their
return.  All was bustle and gladness throughout the camp.  There
had been a successful chase, and the led horses were laden with
buffalo meat.  These horses were led by the young girls to the
tents to be unpacked, while the boys took the hunting-horses to
water and tether in the grass.  Fathers, as they dismounted, took
their little children in their arms, tired as they were.  Nedawi
was as happy as any in the camp, for her seventeen-year-old
brother, White Hawk, had killed his first buffalo, and had declared
that the skin should become Nedawi's robe, as soon as it was tanned
and painted.
</p><p>What a pleasant evening that was to Nedawi, when the whole
family sat around a great fire, roasting the huge buffalo ribs, and
she played with <pb n="229"/> her little brother Habazhu, stopping now
and then to listen to the adventures of the day, which her father
and brothers were relating!  The scene was truly a delightful one,
the camp-fires lighting up the pleasant family groups here and
there, as the flames rose and fell.  The bit of prairie where the
tribe had camped had a clear little stream running through it, with
shadowy hills around, while over all hung the clear, star-lit sky.
It seemed as if nature were trying to protect the poor waifs of
humanity clustered in that spot.  Nedawi felt the beauty of the
scene, and was just thinking of nestling down by her father to
enjoy it dreamily, when her brothers called for a dance.  The
little drum was brought forth, and Nedawi danced to its
accompaniment and her brothers' singing.  She danced gravely, as
became a little maiden whose duty it was to entertain the family
circle.  While she was dancing, a little boy, about her own age,
was seen hovering near.  He would appear, and, when spoken to,
would disappear in the tall, thick grass.
</p><p>It was Mischief, a playmate of Nedawi's.  Everybody called him
"Mischief," because mischief appeared in every action of his.  It
shone from his eyes and played all over his face.
</p><p>"You little plague," said White Hawk; "what do you want?"
</p><p>For answer, the "little plague" turned a somersault just out
of White Hawk's reach.  When the singing was resumed, Mischief
crept quietly up behind White Hawk, and, keeping just within the
shadow, mimicked Nedawi's grave dancing, and he looked so funny
that Nedawi suddenly laughed, which was precisely Mischief's
object.  But before he could get out of reach, as he intended,
Thunder, Nedawi's other brother, who had been having an eye on him,
clutched tight hold of him, and Mischief was landed in front of the
fire-place, in full view of the whole family.  "Now," said Thunder,
"you are my prisoner.  You stay there and dance with nedawi."
Mischief knew there was no escape, so he submitted with a good
grace.  He went through all sorts of antics, shaking his fists in
the air, twirling suddenly around and putting his head close to the
ground, keeping time with the accompaniment through it all.
</p><p>Nedawi danced staidly on, now and then frowning at him; but
she knew of old that he was irrepressible.  When Nedawi sat down,
he threw into her lap a little dark something and was off like a
shot, yelling at the top of his voice, either in triumph at his
recent achievements or as a practice for future war-whoops.
</p><p>"Nedawi, what is it?" said her mother.
</p><p>Nedawi took it to the fire, when the something proved to be a
poor little bird.
</p><p>"I thought he had something in his hand when he was shaking
his fist in the air," said Nedawi's sister, Nazainza, laughing.
</p><p>"Poor little thing!" said Nedawi; "it is almost dead."
</p><p>She put its bill into the water, and tenderly tried to make it
drink.  The water seemed to revive it somewhat.
</p><p>"I'll wrap it up in something warm," said Nedawi, "and may be
it will sing in the morning."
</p><p>"Let me see it," said Nedawi's father.
</p><p>Nedawi carried it to him.
</p><p>"Don't you feel sorry for it, daughter?"
</p><p>"Yes, Father," she answered.
</p><p>"Then take it to the tall grass, yonder, and put it down where
no one will step on it, and, as you put it down, say: 'God, I give
you back your little bird.  As I pity it, pity me.'"
</p><p>"And will God take care of it?" said Nedawi, reverently, and
opening her black eyes wide at the thought.
</p><p>"Yes," said her father.
</p><p>"Well, I will do as you say," said Nedawi, and she walked
slowly out of the tent.
</p><p>Then she took it over to the tall, thick grass, and making a
nice, cozy little nest for it, left it there, saying just what her
father had told her to say.  When she came back, she said:
</p><p>"Father, I said it."
</p><p>"That was right, little daughter," and Nedawi was happy at her
father's commendation.
</p><p>Nedawi always slept with her grandmother and sister, exactly
in the middle of the circle formed by the wigwam, with her feet to
the fire-place.  That place in the tent was always her
grandmother's place, just as the right-hand side of the tent was
her father's and mother's, and the left-hand her brothers'.  There
never was any confusion.  The tribe was divided into bands, and
every band was composed of several families.  Each band had its
chief, and the whole tribe was ruled by the head-chief, who was
Nedawi's father.  He had his own particular band besides.  Every
tent had its own place in the band, and every band had its own
particular place in the great circle forming the camp.  Each chief
was a representative, in council, of the men composing his band,
while over all was the head-chief.  The executive power was vested
in the "soldiers' lodge," and when decisions were arrived at in
council, it was the duty of its soldiers to execute all its orders,
and punish all violations of the tribal laws.  The office of "town-crier" was held by several old men, whose duty it was "to cry out"
through the camp the announcements of councils, invitations to
feasts, and to give notice of anything in which the whole tribe
were called on to take part. <pb n="230"/>
</p><p>Well, before Nedawi went to sleep this evening, she hugged her
grandmother, and said to her:
</p><p>"Please tell me a story."
</p><p>Her grandmother said:
</p><p>"I cannot, because it is summer.  In the winter I will tell
you stories."
</p><p>"Why not in summer?" said Nedawi.
</p><p>"Because, when people tell stories and legends in summer, the
snakes come around to listen.  You don't want any snakes to come
near us to-night, do you?"
</p><p>"But," said Nedawi, "I have not seen any snakes for the
longest times, and if you tell it right softly they wont hear you."
</p><p>"Nedawi," said her mother, "don't bother your grandmother.
She is tired and wants to sleep."
</p><p>Thereupon Grandmother's heart felt sorry for her pet, and she
said to Nedawi:
</p><p>"Well, if you will keep still and go right to sleep when I am
through, I will tell you how the turkeys came to have red eyelids.
</p><p>"Once upon a time, there was an old woman living all alone
with her grandson, Rabbit.  He was noted for his cunning and for
his tricks, which he played on every one.  One day, the old woman
said to him, 'Grandson, I am hungry for some meat.'  Then the boy
took his bow and arrows, and in the evening he came home with a
deer on his shoulders, which he threw at her feet, and said, 'Will
that satisfy you?'  She said, 'Yes, grandson.'  They lived on that
meat several days, and when it was gone, she said to him again,
'Grandson, I am hungry for some meat.'  This time he went without
his bow and arrows, but he took a bag with him.  When he got into
the woods, he called all the turkeys together.  They gathered
around him, and he said to them: 'I am going to sing to you, while
you shut your eyes and dance.  If one of you opens his eyes while
I am singing, his eyelids shall turn red.'  Then they all stood in
a row, shut their eyes, as he had told them, and began to dance,
and this is the song he sang to them while they danced:

</p><p>          "'Ha! wadamba thike
</p><p>   Inshta zhida, inshta zhida,
</p><p>            Imba theonda,
</p><p>            Imba theonda.'

[The literal translation is:

</p><p>          "Ho! he who peeps
</p><p>           Red eyes, red eyes,
</p><p>           Flap your wings,
</p><p>           Flap your wings."]

</p><p>"Now, while they were dancing away, with their eyes shut, the
boy took them, one by one, and put them into his bag.  But the last
one in the row began to think it very strange that his companions
made no noise, so he gave one peep, screamed in his fright, 'They
are making 'way with us!' and fled away.  The boy took his bag of
turkeys home to his grandmother, but ever after that the turkeys
had red eyelids."
</p><p>Nedawi gave a sigh of satisfaction when the story was
finished, and would have asked for more, but just then her brothers
came in from a dance which they had been attending in some
neighbor's tent.  She knew her lullaby time had come.  Her brothers
always sang before they slept either love or dancing songs, beating
time on their breasts, the regular beats making a sort of
accompaniment for the singing.  Nedawi loved best of all to hear
her father's war-songs, for he had a musical voice, and few were
the evenings when she had gone to sleep without hearing a lullaby
from her father or brothers.  Among the Indians, it is the fathers
who sing, instead of the mothers.  Women sing only on state
occasions, when the tribe have a great dance, or at something of
the sort.  Mothers "croon" their babies to sleep, instead of
singing.
</p><p>Gradually the singing ceased, and the brothers slept as well
as Nedawi, and quiet reigned over the whole camp.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
