<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="FreGift"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="FreGift">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Last Gift</title>
<title type="sort">last gift</title>
<author>Freeman, Mary Eleanor Wilkins, 1852-1930</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss ( )</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">36</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">FreGift</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475966</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Last Gift</title>
<title type="sort">last gift</title>
<author>Mary E. Wilkins Freeman</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harper's Monthly</publisher>
<date value="1903-02">Feb 1903</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>106</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Harper's Monthly</hi> 106 (Feb. 1903): 439-446.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1903">1903</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction ; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-07">July 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header; Tagged text with TEI2-compatible SGML markup; Parsed
against teilite.dtd.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="439"/>
<head>The Last Gift <lb/>
<hi rend="italic">BY MARY E. WILKINS FREEMAN</hi></head>

<p>ROBINSON CARNES pilgrimmed along the country road between Sanderson
and Elmville.  He wore a shabby clerical suit, and he carried a
rusty black bag which might have contained sermons.  It did
actually hold one sermon, a favorite which he had delivered many
times in many pulpits, and in which he felt a certain covert pride
of authorship.
</p><p>The bag contained, besides the sermon, two old shirts with
frayed cuffs, three collars, one pocket-handkerchief, a Bible, and
a few ancient toilet articles.  These were all his worldly goods,
except the clothes he wore, and a matter of forty-odd cents in his
old wallet.  Robinson Carnes subsisted after a curious parasitical
fashion.  He travelled about the country with his rusty black bag,
journeying from place to place&mdash;no matter what place, so long as it
held an evangelical church.  Straight to the parson of the church
he went, stated his name and calling, produced certain vouchers in
proof of the same, and inquired if he knew of any opening for a
clergyman out of employment, if he had heard of any country pulpit
in which an itinerant preacher might find humble harbor.  He never
obtained any permanent situation; he sometimes supplied a pulpit
for a day, or officiated at a funeral or wedding, but that was all.
But he never failed to receive hospitality, some sufficient meals,
and a lodging for one night at least in the parsonage guest-chamber.
</p><p>Although Carnes's living was so precarious, he looked neither
forlorn nor hungry.  He had, in fact, had at noon an excellent
dinner of roast beef at the home of the Presbyterian minister in
Sanderson.  It was the day before Christmas, and a certain subtle
stir of festive significance was in the very air.  Every now and
then a wagon laden with young hemlocks, and trailing with greens,
passed him.  The road was strewn with evergreen sprigs and stray
branches, with an occasional jewel-like sprinkle of holly berries.
Often he heard a silvery burst of laughter and chatter, and boys
and girls appeared from a skirting wood with their arms laden with
green vines and branches.  He also met country carriages whose
occupants had their laps heaped with parcels of Christmas presents.
These last gave the tramp preacher a feeling of melancholy so
intense that it amounted to pain.  It was to him like the sight of
a tavern to a drunkard when his pockets are empty and his thirst is
great.  It touched Robinson Carnes in his tenderest point.  He had
fallen a victim in early youth to a singular species of spiritual
dissipation.  Possessed by nature of a most unselfish love for his
kind, and an involuntary generosity, this tendency, laudable in
itself, had become in time like a flower run wild until it was a
weed.  His love of giving amounted to a pure and innocent but
unruly passion.  It had at one time assumed such proportions that
it barely escaped being recognized as actual mania.  As it was,
people, even those who had benefited by his reckless generosity,
spoke of him as a mild idiot.
</p><p>There had been a day of plenty with him, for he had fallen
joint heir to a large and reasonably profitable New England farm,
and a small sum in bank.  The other heir was his younger brother.
His brother had just married; Robinson told him to live on the farm
and give him a small percentage of the profits yearly.  When the
crops failed through bad weather and mismanagement, he said easily,
without the slightest sense of self-sacrifice, that the brother
need not pay him the percentage that year.  The brother did not pay
it, as a matter of course, the next year, and in fact never did.
In three years the brother's wife was ailing, and the family
increasing, and he was in debt for the taxes.  Robinson paid them
all, and he
<pb n="440"/>  continued paying them as long as his money in
the bank lasted.  He wished his brother to keep his intact, on
account of his family.  Then he gave from his poor salary to
everything and everybody.  Then he was in debt for his board.  He
rented a small room, and lived, it was said, on oatmeal porridge
until the debt was paid.
</p><p>Robinson Carnes had a fierce honesty.  When he was in debt, he
felt, for the first time in his life, disgraced, and like hiding
his head.  He often reflected with the greatest shame upon that
period of his life when he had an impulse to go out of his way to
avoid the woman whom he owed.  He felt nothing like it now,
although to some his present mode of existence might savor of
beggary.  He considered that in some fashion he generally rendered
an equivalent for the hospitality which kept the breath of life in
him.  Sometimes the minister who entertained him was ailing, and he
preached the sermon in his black bag in his stead.  Sometimes he
did some copying for him; often he had toiled to good purpose at
his wood-pile or in his garden; he had even assisted the minister's
wife with her carpet-beating in her spring cleaning.  He had now
nothing to be ashamed of, but he felt his very memory burn with
shame when he remembered that time of debt.  That had been the end
of his career as a regularly settled minister.  People might have
forgiven the debt, but they could not forgive nor overlook the fact
that while in such dire straits he had given away the only decent
coat which he owned to wear in the pulpit, and also that he had
given away to a needy family, swarming with half-fed children, the
cakes and pies with which some female members of his parish had
presented him to alleviate his oatmeal diet.  That last had in
reality decided the matter.  He was requested to resign.
</p><p>So Robinson Carnes resigned his pastorate, and had never been
successful in obtaining another.  He went out of the village on
foot.  He had given away every dollar of the last instalment of his
meagre salary to a woman in sore straits.  He had given away his
trunk years ago to a young man about to be married and settle in
the West.  He regretted leaving his sermons behind because of the
lack of a trunk.  He stored them in a barrel in the garret of one
of the deacon's houses.  He stowed away what he could of his poor
little possessions in his black bag, feeling thankful that no one
had seemed to need that also.  Since he had given away his best
coat, he had only his old one, which was very shabby.  When he
shook hands with his half-hearted friends at parting, he was
careful not to raise his right arm too high, lest he reveal a sad
rip in the under-arm seam.  Since, he had had several coats
bestowed upon him by his clerical friends, when an old one was on
the verge of total disruption, but the new coat was always at
variance as to its right under-arm seams.  Robinson Carnes had
thereby acquired such an exceedingly cautious habit of extending
his right arm as to give rise to frequent inquiries whether he had
put his shoulder out of joint, or had rheumatism.  Now the ripped
seam was concealed by an old but very respectable and warm overcoat
which the Presbyterian minister in Sanderson had bestowed upon him,
and which he had requited by an interpretation of the original
Greek of one of the gospels, which aided the minister materially in
the composition of his Christmas sermons.  Carnes was an excellent
Hebrew and Greek scholar, and his entertainer was rusty and had
never been very proficient.  Robinson had been in the theological
seminary with this man, and had often come to his aid when there.
Robinson had also set up the Christmas tree for the Sunday-school
in the church vestry.  He was exceedingly skilful with his hands.
The Christmas tree had awakened in him the old passion, and his
face saddened as he looked at the inviting spread of branches.
</p><p>"I wish I had something to hang on the tree for your children
and the Sunday-school," he said, wistfully, to the minister; and
the other man, who knew his history, received his speech in meaning
silence.  But when Carnes repeated his remark, being anxious that
his poor little gift of a Christmas wish, which was all that he had
to offer, might at least be accepted, the other replied coldly that
one's first duty was to one's self, and unjustified giving was
pauperizing to the giver and the recipient.
<pb n="441"/>
</p><p>Then poor Robinson Carnes, abashed, for he understood the
purport of the speech, bade the minister good-by meekly, and went
his way.  When he saw the other Christmas trees on the road to
Elmville, his wistful sadness became intensified.  He felt the full
bitterness of having absolutely nothing to give, of having even a
kindly wish scorned when the wish was his last coin.  He felt
utterly bankrupt as to benefits towards his fellow-creatures, that
sorest bankruptcy for him who can understand it.
</p><p>Carnes had just watched a wagon loaded with Christmas greens
pass slowly out of sight around a bend in the road, when he came
unexpectedly upon a forlorn company.  They were so forlorn, and so
unusual in the heart of a prosperous State, that he could hardly
believe his eyes at first.  They seemed impossible.  There were six
of them in all: a man, two women&mdash;one young and one old&mdash;and three
children: one a baby two years old, the others five and eight.  The
man stood bolt-upright, staring straight ahead with blank eyes; the
women were seated on the low stone wall which bordered the road.
The younger, the mother, held the five-year-old child; the older,
evidently the grandmother, held the youngest; the eldest&mdash;all were
girls&mdash;sat apart, huddled upon herself, her small back hooped,
hugging herself with her thin arms in an effort to keep warm.  As
Carnes drew near, she looked at him, and an impulse of flight was
evident in her eyes.  The younger of the two women surveyed him
with a sort of apathy which partook of anger.  The youngest child,
in the old woman's lap, was wailing aloud.  The grandmother did not
try to hush it.  Her face, full of a dumb appeal to and questioning
of something which Carnes felt dimly was beyond him, gazed over the
small head in a soiled white hood which beat wrathfully against her
withered bosom.  The woman wore an old shawl which was warm; she
kept a corner well wrapped about the crying child.  The younger
woman was very thinly clad.  Her hat had a pathetic last summer's
rose in it.  Now and then a long rigor of chill passed over her; at
such times her meagre body seemed to elongate, her arms held the
little girl on her lap like two clamps.  The man, standing still,
with face turned toward the sky over the distant horizon line, gave
a glance at Carnes with eyes which bore no curiosity or interest,
but were simply indifferent.  He looked away again, and Carnes felt
that he was forgotten, while his shadow and the man's still
intermingled.
</p><p>Then Carnes broke the silence.  He stepped in front of the
man.  "See here, friend," he said, "what's the matter?"
</p><p>The man looked at him perforce.  He was past words.  He had
come to that pass where speech as a means of expression seemed
superfluous.  His look said as much to his questioner.  "You ask me
what is the matter?" the look said.  "Are you <hi rend="italic">blind?"</hi>  But
the question in the man's dull eyes was not resentful.  He was not
one in whom misery arouses resentment against others or Providence.
Fate seemed to have paralyzed him, as the clutch of a carnivorous
animal is said to paralyze a victim.
</p><p>"What is it?" Carnes inquired again.  "What is the matter?"
</p><p>Still the man did not answer, but the younger of the two women
did.  She spoke with great force, but her lips were stiff, and
apparently not a muscle of her face moved.  "I'll tell you what the
matter is," said she.  "He's good for nothing. He's a no-account
man.  He ain't fit to take care of a family.  That's what's the
matter."  Then the other woman bore her testimony, which was
horrible from its intensity and its triviality.  It was the tragedy
of a pin-prick in a meagre soul.
</p><p>"He's left my hair-cloth sofy an' my feather bed," said she,
in a high shrill plaint.
</p><p>Then the forlorn male, badgered betwixt the two females of his
species, who were, as it often happens with birds, of a finer,
fiercer sort than he, broke silence with a feeble note of
expostulation.  "Now, don't, mother," said he.  "You shall hev that
sofy and that feather bed agin."
</p><p>The younger woman rose, setting the little girl on the frozen
ground so hard that she began to cry.  "Have 'em back?  How is she
goin' to have 'em back?" she demanded.  "There's the hair-cloth
sofy she earned and set her eyes by, and there's the feather bed
she's always slept on, left over there in Sanderson, stored
<pb n="442"/>
away in a dirty old barn.  How's she goin' to ever get 'em again?
What's the poor old woman goin' to sit on an' sleep on?"
</p><p>"We'll go back an' git 'em," muttered the man.  "Don't, Emmy."
</p><p>"Yes, I will!  I'll tell the truth, and I don't care who knows
it.  You're a no-account man.  How are we goin' to git 'em back,
I'd like to know?  You hain't a cent and you can't get work.  If I
was a man, I'd git work if it killed me.  How is your mother goin'
to git that sofy and that feather bed again as long as she lives?
And that ain't all&mdash;there's all my nice furniture that I worked and
earned before I was married; you didn't earn none of it except jest
that one bedstead and bureau that you bought.  I earned all the
other things workin' in the shop myself, and there they all be
stored in that dirty old barn to be eaten up by rats, and covered
with dust."
</p><p>"We will get 'em back.  Don't, Emmy."
</p><p>"How'll you get 'em back?  You're a good-for-nothin' man.  You
ain't fit to support a family."
</p><p>"He's left my sofy an' feather bed," reiterated the old woman.
</p><p>The old man looked helplessly from one to the other; then he
cast a glance at Carnes&mdash;that look full of agony and appeal which
one man gives another in such a crisis when he is set upon by those
whom he cannot fight.
</p><p>Carnes, when he met his fellow-man's piteous look, felt at
once an impulse of partisanship.  He stepped close to him and laid
a hand on the thin shoulder in the thin coat.  "See here, friend,"
he said, "tell me all about it."  The compassion in Carnes's voice
was a power in itself; he had, moreover, a great deal of the
clergyman evident, as well in his manner as in the cut of his
clothes.
</p><p>The man hesitated a moment, then he began, and the story of
his woes flowed like a stream.  It was a simple story enough.  The
man was evidently one of those who work well and faithfully while
in harness, like a horse.  Taken out, he was naked and helpless and
ashamed, without spirit enough to leave his old hitching-posts and
beaten roads of life, and gallop in new pastures unbridled.  He
became a poor nondescript, not knowing what he knew.  The man,
whose name was William Jarvis, had worked in a shoe factory ever
since he was a boy.  He had been an industrious and skilled
workman, but had met with many vicissitudes.  He had left a poor
position for an exceedingly lucrative one in a large factory in
Sanderson, and had moved there with his family.  Then the factory
had been closed through the bankruptcy of the owner.  Since then he
had had a hard time.  He had left his family in Sanderson in their
little rented house, and he had been about the country seeking in
vain for employment.  Then he had returned, to find that the old
factory was to be reopened in a month's time, and then he could
have a job, but every cent of his money was gone, and he was in
debt.  Not only Jarvis's money was gone, but his credit.  The
tradesmen had learned to be wary about trusting the shifting
factory population.
</p><p>The rent was due on the house; Jarvis paid that, and was
literally penniless.  He packed his humble furniture, and stored it
in a neighbor's barn, on condition that it should be taken for
storage if he did not claim it within a year.
</p><p>Then he and his family set forth.  It was the hopeless,
senseless sort of exodus which might have been expected of people
like these who deal only with the present, being incapacitated,
like some insects, from any but a limited vision in one direction.
Carnes received a confused impression, from a confused statement of
the man, that they had a hope of being able to reach a town in the
northern part of the State, where the wife had some distant
relatives, and the others of this poor clan might possibly come to
their rescue.  They had had a hope of friendly lifts in northward-journeying wagons.  But there had been no lifts, and they had
advanced only about five miles toward their forlorn Mecca on the
day before Christmas.  The children were unable to walk farther,
and the parents were unable to carry them.  The grandmother, too,
was at the end of her strength.  The weather was very cold, and
snow threatened.  They were none too warmly clad.  They had only
the small luggage which they could carry&mdash;an old valise, and a
bundle tied up in an old shawl.  The middle child had an old doll
that had lost one arm, her blond wig, and an eye, but
<pb n="443"/>  was
going on her travels in her best, faded pink muslin dress and a bit
of blue sash.  The child stood sobbing wearily, but she still held
fast to the doll.  The eldest girl eyed her with tender solicitude.
She had outgrown dolls.  She got a dingy little handkerchief from
her pocket and folded it cornerwise for a shawl; then she got down
from the wall and pinned it closely around the doll.  "There," she
said, "that is better."  After that the children themselves felt
warmer.
</p><p>Carnes saw everything&mdash;the people, the doll, their poor little
possessions,&mdash;and an agony of pity, which from the nature of the
man and its futility became actual torture, seized him.  He looked
at the other man who had confided in him, at the women who now
seemed to watch him with a lingering hope of assistance.  He opened
his mouth to speak, but he said nothing.  What could he say?"
</p><p>Then the man, William Jarvis, added something to his poor
story.  Two weeks before, he had slipped on the ice and injured his
shoulder; he had strained it with moving, and it was causing him
much distress.  Indeed, his face, which was strained with pain as
well as misery, bore witness to the truth of that.
</p><p>The wife had eyed her husband with growing concentration
during this last.  When he had finished, her face brightened with
tenderness; she made a sudden move forward and threw her arms
around him, and began to weep in a sort of rage of pity and love
and remorse.  "Poor Willy! poor Willy!" she sobbed.  "Here we've
been abusin' you when you've worked like a dog with your shoulder
'most killin' you.  You've always done the best you could.  I don't
care who says you haven't.  I'd like to hear anybody say you
haven't.  I guess they wouldn't darse say it twice to me."  She
turned on the old woman with unreasoning fury.  "Hold your tongue
about your old hair-cloth sofy an' your feather bed, grandma!" said
she.  "Ain't he your own son?  I guess you won't die if you lose
your old hair-cloth sofy an' your feather bed!  The stuffin's all
comin' out of your old sofy, anyhow!  You'd ought to be ashamed of
yourself, grandma!  Ain't he your own son?"
</p><p>"I guess he was my son afore he was your husband," returned
the old woman with spirit.  "I ain't pesterin' of him any more'n
you be, Emmy Jarvis."  With that she began to weep shrilly like a
child, leaning her face against the head of the crying child in her
lap.  The little girl with the doll set up a fresh pipe of woe; the
doll slipped to the ground.  The elder sister got down from the
stone wall and gathered it up and fondled it.  "You've dropped poor
Angelina and hurt her, Nannie," said she, reproachfully.
</p><p>"Poor Willy!" again sobbed his wife, "you've been treated like
a dog by them you had a right to expect something better of, an' I
don't care if I do say so."
</p><p>Again the man's eyes, overlooking his wife's head, sought the
other man's for an understanding of his peculiar masculine
distress.
</p><p>Carnes returned the look with such utter comprehension and
perfect compassion as would have lifted the other's burden for all
time could it have taken practical form.  In reality, Carnes, at
this juncture, suffered more than the man.  Here was a whole family
penniless, suffering.  Here was a man with the impulse of a
thousand Samaritans to bring succor, but positively helpless to
lift a finger toward any alleviation of their misery.  It became
evident to him in a flash what the outside view of the situation
would be: that the only course for a man of ordinary sense and
reason was to return to Sanderson and notify the authorities of
this suicidal venture; that it was his duty for the sake of the
helpless children to have them cared for by force, if there was no
other way.  But still, this course he could not bring himself to
follow.  It seemed an infringement upon all the poor souls had left
in the world&mdash;their individual freedom.  He could not do it, and
yet what else was there to do?  He thought of his forty cents, his
only available assets against this heavy arrear of pity and
generosity, with fury.  At that moment the philanthropist without
resources, the Samaritan without his flask of oil, was fairly
dangerous to himself from this terrible blocking of almost abnormal
impulses for good.  It seemed to him that he must die or go mad if
he could not do something for these people.  He cast about his
eyes,
<pb n="444"/>  like a drowning man, and he saw in a field on the
left, quite a distance away, a small house; only its chimneys were
visible above a gentle slope.  A thought struck him.  "Wait a
moment," he ordered, and leaped the stone wall and ran across the
field, crunching the frozen herbage until his footsteps echoed
loudly.  The forlorn family watched him.  It was only a short time
before he returned.  He caught up the second little girl from the
ground.  "Come," cried Carnes in an excited voice.  "Come.  Nobody
lives in that house over there!  I can get in!  There is a shed
with hay in it!  There's a fireplace!  There's plenty of wood to
pick up in the grove behind it!  Come!"
</p><p>His tone was wild with elation.  Here was something which
could be done.  It was small, but something.  The others were moved
by his enthusiasm.  Their faces lightened.  The father caught the
youngest child from the grandmother; the mother took the eldest by
the hand.  They all started, the old grandmother outracing them,
with a quick, short-stepped toddle like a child.  "See your mother
go," said the wife, and she fairly laughed.  In fact, the old woman
was almost at her last gasp, and it was an extreme effort of
nature, a final spurt of nerve and will.
</p><p>The house was a substantial cottage, in fair repair.  The door
at the back was unlocked.  Carnes threw it open, and ushered in the
people as if they had been his guests.  A frightful chill struck
them as they entered.  It was much colder than outside, with a
concentration of chill which overwhelmed like an actual presence of
wintry death.  The children, all except the eldest girl, who hugged
the doll tightly, and whispered to her not to mind, it would be
warm pretty soon, began to cry again.  This was a new deprivation
added to the old.  They had expected something from the stranger,
and he had betrayed them.  The grandmother leaned exhausted against
the wall; her lips moved, but nothing could be heard.  The wife
caught up the youngest crying child and shook her.
</p><p>"Be still, will you?" she said, in a furious voice.  "We've
got enough to put up with without your bawling."  Then she kissed
and fondled it, and her own tears dropped fast on its wet face.
</p><p>But not one whit of Carnes's enthusiasm abated.  He beckoned
the man, who sprang to his bidding.  They brought wood from the
grove behind the house.  Carnes built a fire on the old hearth, and
he found some old boxes in the little barn.  He rigged up some
seats with boards, and barrels for backs; he spread hay on the
boards for cushions.  The warmth and light of the fire filled the
room.  All of a sudden it was furnished and inhabited.  Their faces
began to relax and lighten.  The awful blue tints of cold gave
place to soft rose and white.  The children began to laugh.
</p><p>"What did I tell you?" the eldest girl asked the doll, and she
danced it before the ruddy glow.  The wife bade her husband sit
with his lame shoulder next the fire.  The youngest child climbed
into her grandmother's lap again, and sat with her thumb in her
mouth surveying the fire.  She was hungry, but she sucked her own
thumb, and she was warm.  The old woman nodded peacefully.  She had
taken off her bonnet, and her white head gleamed with a rosy tint
in the firelight.
</p><p>Carnes was radiant for a few minutes.  He stood surveying the
transformation he had wrought.  "Well, now this is better," he
said, and he laughed like a child.  Then suddenly his face fell
again.  This was not a solution of the problem.  He had simply
stated it.  There was no food, there was no permanent shelter.
Then the second little girl, who was the most delicate and nervous
of them all, began to cry again.  "I want somefin to eat," she
wailed.  Her father, who had been watching them with as much
delight as Carnes, also experienced a revulsion.  Again he looked
at Carnes.
</p><p>"Yes," said the wife in a bitter tone, "here is a fire and a
roof over us, but we may get turned out any minute, if anybody sees
the smoke comin' out of the chimney, and there's nothin' to eat."
</p><p>The eldest little girl's lip quivered.  She hugged the doll
more closely.
</p><p>"Don't cry, and you shall have a piece of cake pretty soon,"
she whispered.  The man continued to look at Carnes, who suddenly
stood straight and threw up his head with a resolute look.  "I'm
going, but I will come back very soon," said he, "and then we'll
have supper.  Don't
<pb n="445"/>  worry.  Put enough wood on the fire to
keep warm."  Then he went out.
</p><p>He hurried across the field to the road under the lowering
quiet of the gray sky.  His resolve was stanch, but his heart
failed him.  Again the agony of balked compassion was over him.  He
looked ahead over the reach of frozen highway without a traveller
in sight, he looked up at the awful winter sky threatening with
storm, and he was in a mood of blasphemy.  There was that misery,
there was he with the willingness to relieve, and&mdash;forty cents.  It
was a time when money reached a value beyond itself, when it
represented the treasure of heaven.  This poor forty cents would
buy bread, at least, and a little milk.  It would keep them alive
a few hours, but that was only a part of the difficulty solved.
The cold was intense, and they were not adequately protected
against it.  There were an old woman and three children.  He was
only giving them the most ephemeral aid, and what would come next?
</p><p>Carnes, standing there in the road all alone, mechanically
thrust his hand in his pocket for the feel of his forty cents; but
instead of putting his hand in his own coat pocket, he thrust it in
the pocket of the overcoat which the minister in Sanderson had
given him.  He pulled out, instead of his own poor old wallet, a
prosperous portly one of black seal-skin.  He did not at first
realize what it meant.  He stood staring vacuously.  Then he knew.
The minister in Sanderson had left his own wallet in the overcoat
pocket.  The coat was one which he had been wearing until his new
one had come from the tailor's the day before.
</p><p>Carnes stood gazing at this pocketbook; then he slowly, with
shaking fingers, opened it.  There were papers which he saw at a
glance were valuable, and there was a large roll of bills.  Carnes
began counting them slowly.  He sat down on the stone wall the
while.  His legs trembled so that he could scarcely stand.  There
was over two hundred dollars in bills in the wallet.  Carnes sat
awhile regarding the bills.  A strange expression was coming over
his gentle, scholarly, somewhat weak face&mdash;an expression evil and
unworthy in its original meaning, but, as it were, glorified by the
motive which actuated it.  The man's face became full of a most
angelic greed of money.  He was thinking what he could do with only
a hundred dollars of that other man's money.  He knew with no
hesitation that he would run to Elmville, hire a carriage, take the
distressed family back to Sanderson to their old house, pay the
rent a month in advance, pay their debts, get the stored furniture,
help them set it up, give them money to buy fuel and provisions for
the month before the factory reopened.  A hundred dollars of that
money in his hand, which did not belong to him, meant respite for
distress which would be like a taste of heaven; it meant perhaps
life instead of death; it meant perhaps more than earthly life,
perhaps spiritual life, to save this family from the awful test of
despair.
</p><p>Carnes separated a hundred dollars from the rest.  He put it
in his own old wallet.  He replaced the remainder in the
minister's, and he went on to Elmville.
</p><p>It was ten o'clock on Christmas eve before Robinson Carnes,
having left the Jarvis family reinstated in their old home, warmed
and fed, and happier perhaps than they had ever been or perhaps
ever would be, went to the vestry blazing with light in which the
Christmas tree was being held.  He stood in the door and saw the
minister, portly and smiling, seated well forward.  As he watched,
the minister's name was called, and he received a package.  The
minister was a man with a wealthy parish; he had, moreover, money
of his own, and not a large reputation for giving.  Carnes
reflected upon this as he stood there.  It seemed to him that with
such a man his chances of mercy were small.  He had his mind
steeled for the worst.  He considered, as he stood there, his very
good chance of arraignment, of imprisonment.  "It may mean State
prison for me," he thought.  Then a wave of happiness came over
him.  "Anyway," he told himself, "they have the money."  He did not
conceive of the possibility of the minister taking away the money
from that poverty and distress; that was past his imagination.
"They have the money," he kept repeating.  It also occurred to him,
for he was strong in the doctrine of his church creed, that he had
possibly incurred a heavier than earthly justice for his deed; and
then he told himself again, "Well, they have it."
<pb n="446"/>
</p><p>A mental picture of the family in warmth and comfort in their
home came before him, and while he reflected upon theft and its
penalty, he smiled like an angel.  Presently he called a little boy
near by and sent him to the minister.
</p><p>"Ask Mr. Abbott if he will please see Mr. Carnes a moment," he
said.  "Say he has something important to tell him."
</p><p>Soon the boy returned, and his manner unconsciously aped Mr.
Abbot.
</p><p>"Mr. Abbot says he is sorry, but he cannot leave just now,"
he said.  It was evident that the minister wished to shake off the
mendicant of his holy profession.
</p><p>Carnes took the rebuff meekly, but he bade the boy wait a
moment.  He took a pencil from his pocket and wrote something on a
scrap of paper.  He wrote this:
</p><p>"I found this wallet in your pocket in the coat which you gave
me.  I have stolen one hundred dollars to relieve the necessities
of a poor family.  I await your pleasure.  Robinson Carnes."
</p><p>The boy passed up the aisle with the pocket-book and the note.
Carnes, watching, saw a sudden convulsive motion of the minister's
shoulders in his direction, but he did not turn his head.  His name
was called again for a present as the boy passed down the aisle,
returning to Carnes.
</p><p>Again the boy unconsciously aped Mr. Abbot's  manner as he
addressed Carnes.  It was conclusive, coldly disapproving, non-retaliative, dismissing.  Carnes knew the minister, and he had no
doubt.  "Mr. Abbot says that he has no need to see you, that you
can go when you wish," said the boy.  Carnes knew that he was quite
free, that no penalty would attach to his theft.
</p><p>The snow had begun to fall as Robinson Carnes took his way out
of Sanderson on the road to Elmville, but the earth had come into
a sort of celestial atmosphere which obliterated the storm for
human hearts.  All around were innocent happiness and festivity,
and the display of love by loving-gifts.  The poor minister was
alone on a stormy road on Christmas eve.  He had no presentiment of
anything bright in his future: he did not know that he was to find
an asylum and a friend for life in the clergyman in the town toward
which his face was set.  He travelled on, bending his shoulders
before the sleety wind.  His heart was heavier and heavier before
the sense of his own guilt.  He felt to the full that he had done
a great wrong.  He had stolen, and stolen from his benefactor.  He
had taken off the minister's coat and laid it gently over the back
of a settee in the vestry before he left, but that made no
difference.  If only he had not stolen from the man who had given
him his coat.  And yet he always had, along with the remorse, that
light of great joy which could not be wholly darkened by any
thought of self, when he reflected upon the poor family who were
happy.  He thought that possibly the minister had in reality been
glad, although he condemned him.  He began to love him and thank
him for his generosity.  He pulled his thin coat closely around him
and went on.  He had given the last gift which he had to give&mdash;his
own honesty.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
