<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="FriChek"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="FriChek">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Anton Chekhov</title>
<title type="sort">anton chekhov</title>
<author>Friedland, Louis S.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">17</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">FriChek</idno>
<date value="1998">1998</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1998 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475968</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Anton Chekhov</title>
<title level="j">The Dial, Vol. 64 (3 Jan. 1918)</title>
<title type="sort">anton chekhov</title>
<author>Louis S. Friedland</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 27-29</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Kraus Reprint Corporation</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1966">1966</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVA Library call number AP2 .D48 v. 64-65 1918</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>The Kraus edition is a reprint of the 1918 edition of The Dial, published in Chicago.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1918">1918</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1998-05">May, 1998</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Carol Osborne, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI tags and header</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="article" id="d3"> <pb n="27"/>
<head><hi rend="italic">Anton Chekhov</hi></head>
<note><p>
THE TALES OF CHEKHOV (to be complete in eight volumes).
     Four volumes: The Darling, and Other Stories; The Duel, and Other
     Stories; The Lady with the Dog and Other Stories; The Party, and
     Other Stories.  (New York: Macmillan Co.; $1.50 each.)<lb/>
     THE HOUSE WITH THE MEZZANINE, AND OTHER
     STORIES.  (New York: Scribner's; $1.25.)</p></note>

<p>We are about to come into possession of Chekhov.  It will be a
priceless possession, for Chekhov is indispensable to our understanding
of the psychology of the great people that has introduced into the present
world situation an element so complex, so disturbing, so tragic and
beautiful.  Chekhov is the faithful reporter, unerring, intuitive, direct.  He
never bears false witness.  The essence of his art lies in a fine restraint,
an avoidance of the sensational and the spectacular.  His reticence reveals
the elusive and lights up the enigmatic.  And what a keen, voracious
observer he was!  Endless is the procession of types that passes through
his pages &mdash; the whole world of Russians of his day: country gentlemen,
chinovniks, waitresses, ladies of fashion, shopgirls, town physicians,
Zemstvo doctors, innkeepers, peasants, herdsmen, soldiers, tradesmen,
every type of the intelligentsia, children, men and women of every class
and occupation.  Chekhov describes them all with a pen that knows no
bias.  He eschews specialization in types.  In a letter written to his friend
Plescheyev, Chekhov draws in one stroke a swift, subtle parallel between
the two authors, Shcheglov and Korolenko, and then he goes on to say,
"But, Allah, Kerim!  Why do they both specialize?  One refuses to part
with his prisoners, the other feeds his readers on staff officers.  I
recognize specialization in art, such as genres, landscape, history; I
understand the 'emploi' of the actor, the school of the musician, but I
cannot accept such specialization as prisoners, officers, priests.  This is
no longer specialization; it is bias."  Chekhov ignores no phase of the life
of his day.  This inclusiveness, this large and noble avidity that refuses to
be circumscribed by class or kind or importance, makes the sum of his
stories both ample and satisfying.  His work illuminates the whole of
Russian life, the main thoroughfares, the bypaths, the unfrequented
recesses.  Without Chekhov, how are we to embark on the discovery of
Russia?
</p><p>Within the limits of his day Chekhov is the perfect guide because
his interpretations of a life that is alien to us have the essential qualities
of

   <pb n="28"/>

veracity and credibility.  It is the spirit of wide-eyed, tolerant,
dispassionate perception that gives Chekhov's works their character of
true evidence.  For him, subtle and balanced in his sensibilities, all reality
is innately artistic.  With no apparent effort, he lifts everything: the
commonplace, the threadbare, even the banal, to the high plane of art.
The relations of ordinary existence, the sombre dullness, the gray
emptiness of uninspired life acquire interest and meaning.  He creates, as
the Russian critic Leon Shestov says, "from the void."  Others flee from
these things as from the valley of the shadow of death; Chekhov gives
them color, harmony, inevitability; they become significant, infinitely
sad, infinitely human.  We may wish to turn away from these aspects of
reality, we may wish to take refuge in dreams and visions and hopes, but
the artist constrains us to stay; his tales become credible and strangely
familiar.  With poignant regret we acknowledge them as a true
representation of our own lives.
</p><p>A representation of life, but not an explanation.  Chekhov, almost
alone among the great Russians, does not set himself the task of solving
the riddles of the universe.  He is the honest physician who knows no
panaceas and is skeptical as to palliatives.  Explanations,
commandments, reconciliations, consolings &mdash; he has none of these to
offer.  He shuns the admonitions and the comfortable words of the moral
teacher, the impatient outcries of the embittered rebel, the grandiose
creations of the symbolist, the vicarious solace of the mystic.  He
counsels neither rebellion nor acceptance.
</p><p>For this shrinking from all forms of dogmatism, for this absence of
burning indignation and passionate protest, most Russians hold Chekhov
strictly to account.  They refuse to forgive him for not coming to
conclusions with life.  Against what some of them are pleased to call his
"complacency in political and social matters" they invoke the lines of the
poet Nekrassov:
</p>
<lg type="verse">
<l>He loves not the land of his fathers
</l><l>Who sings without sorrow and anger.</l>
</lg>

<p>Chekhov was not unaware of his countrymen's predilection for strong,
flaming words on the "accursed problems of life."  But he was resolved
to remain true to his temperament.  And what was Chekhov's
temperament?  In one of his letters to his friend Souvorin, after dwelling
on the soothing effects of Nature on his spirits, he writes, "Nature
reconciles man, that is, makes him indifferent.  <hi rend="italic">And in this world one
must be indifferent.</hi>  Only dissatisfied people can look at things
clearly, can be just, and do work.  Of course, this includes only
thoughtful and noble persons; egoists and empty folk are indifferent as it
is."  These words, I think, will give us a clue to an understanding of
Chekhov's attitude to life.  Nor do they stand alone.  Again and again, in
his letters, Chekhov replies in the same strain to those who complain that
he has not solved the moral or ethical questions that arise in his stories.  I
quote from a few of his letters to Souvorin:</p>

<q>"The business of the writer of fiction is only to depict how and
under what circumstances people speak and think about such problems as
God, pessimism, etc.  The artist should not be a judge of his personages
and of what they say, but only an unbiassed witness.  I overhear a
conversation on pessimism between two Russians, and my business is to
report the conversation as I heard it, and let the jury, I. e., the readers,
decide as to its value.  My business is only to be talented, that is, to be
able to distinguish between important and unimportant testimony, to be
able to illuminate the characters and speak in their language. . .  And if
an artist in whom the crowd has faith dares announce that he understands
nothing of what he sees &mdash; this alone constitutes a large acquisition in the
realm of thought and is a great step forward."  "In my talks with the
writing brethren I always maintain that it is not the business of the artist
to decide narrowly specific questions.  It is bad if the artist undertakes
something he does not understand.  For special problems there are
specialists. . .  But an artist is to judge only of what he understands.  His
sphere is just as limited as that of any other specialist.  This I repeat and
on this I always insist.  That in his sphere there are no problems but only
answers, may be said by one who never wrote and never had to deal with
images.  The artist observes, selects, guesses, contracts.  These acts
alone, in their nature, presuppose the existence of problems.  If he had no
problem before him there would be no need of selecting and of guessing.
. .  You are right in demanding from an artist a serious attitude to his
work.  You confuse two conceptions: <hi rend="italic">the solution of the problem</hi>
and <hi rend="italic">the correct statement of the problem</hi>."  "You scold me for
being objective and attribute this in me to an indifference toward good
and evil and to a lack of ideals, etc.  When I depict horse-thieves you
want me to say: 'To steal horses is evil.'  But everybody knows this
without my saying it.  Let the thieves be judged by a sworn jury &mdash; my
business is to show them as they are. . .  Of course, it would be fine to
harmonize art with sermons, but in my case it would be very difficult,
and, so far as my technique goes, almost impossible.  You realize, do you
not, that to depict horse-thieves within the space of seven hundred lines I
must always speak and think as they do, feel as they feel?  Otherwise, if I
were to add subjective elements, the image would become blurred and
the story would not be compact, as all short stories should be."
</q>
<p>This artistic credo does not express the spirit of heartless
indifference.  It comes from the

   <pb n="29"/>

resolve to present reality as seen by a calm, balanced, comprehensive,
luminous temperament.  Chekhov's attitude is one of clear-eyed refusal to
grapple with the unattainable.  In the stories and plays of this artist there
is no coldness and hardness.  Despite the reticence and the stern
suppression of emotion personal to the author, you discern in these
works, in the letters, and in the volume on the convict-colony at Sakhalin,
the tender, sensitive physician, the mild, understanding eye, the kindly,
aching heart.
</p><p>To the everlasting question of the Russians, "What is to be done?"
Chekhov answers, sometimes with a sad wistfulness, sometimes with a
tender compassion, now with a merry twinkle, now with quiet
resignation, "I do not know."  "Is there a way out?"  And again the reply,
"I do not know."  For him, too, the rest is silence.  Life goes on, but it has
no swing, no forward propulsion.  It is a strange, rhythmless life that
Chekhov surveys, a life without great adventures or feverish activity.  It
is life playing on muted strings, under gray skies, and in a time of dark
reaction.  And Chekhov stands awed in the presence of failure, of tragic
insufficiency, of death-in-life, of broken hopes, broken hearts.
Disillusionment has come to blight the energies and the spirit of these
men and women and children.  In all but a few there is some sad
imperfection, some fatal <hi rend="italic">&aacute;martia</hi> that makes them the
playthings of the imperturbable Fates.  And the story of every one in the
long procession is only another of life's little ironies.  To view this
stagnation over which the spirit of the Lord has not passed, to discern it
all, to bear the consciousness of it in the heart, one must possess
something of the imperturbability, the impassivity, the indifference of
Nature.  One must be, as Chekhov was, a physician who knew himself
doomed to an early death.
</p><p>I have been asked, "Are Chekhov's stories true to life?  Do they
convey the impression of reality?  Is the life of the greater number of men
and women so colorless, so passive, so full of dull regret, so unfulfilled
of all desire?"  I do not know.  But I have stood in the great City, on
Broadway, at the time when the clock struck the hour of six, and I have
seen the men and women pour forth from the shops and stores and
factories.  Thousands upon thousands, they emerge after the long
confinement of the day's work, and in a swift procession they walk home
in the gathering dusk.  What are the sudden revelations, the wondrous
surprises that the future has in store for them &mdash; for the millions like them
to whom the great adventures in life are a journey underground, supper,
the marvels of the motion pictures, sleep?  Ah, Chekhov knew!  He knew
of the glory of childhood, the dreams of youth, the miracle of hope and
fresh beginnings; and he knew the dreary emptiness in the hearts of those
who return home at the end of the day.  He knew of the ceaseless quest
for happiness, for a fuller life, for rest.  And he knew that, high or low,
whatever the path we follow, we are never far from the endless
procession of the disillusioned.
</p><p>But is there no release, and no fulfilment?  Whenever I stand where
the long line of those who hurry home in the gathering dusk passes by, I
can see, in the west, through the great canyon that is the city street, the
glory of the setting sun.  There the sky is strangely beautiful.  It seems to
bend over a new and a different world.  Who can tell?  But in that world
there seems to be joy and work, beauty and laughter, sunshine, freedom,
stretching of limbs, rest.  And, wondering whether we can create that
world, no longer from the void, I recall Chekhov's many quiet words of
encouragement and hope.  Sonia speaks such words in the closing scene
of "Uncle Vanya":
</p><p>"What can we do?  We must live our lives.  [<hi rend="italic">A pause.</hi>]  Yes,
we shall live, Uncle Vanya.  We shall live through the long procession of
days before us, and through the long evenings; we shall patiently bear the
trials that fate imposes on us; we shall work for others without rest, both
now and when we are old; and when our last hour comes we shall meet it
humbly, and there, beyond the grave, we shall say that we have suffered
and wept, that our life was bitter, and God will have pity on us.  Ah, then,
dear, dear Uncle, we shall see that bright and beautiful life; we shall
rejoice and look back upon our sorrow here; a tender smile &mdash; and &mdash; we
shall rest.  I have faith, Uncle, fervent, passionate faith.  [<hi rend="italic">Sonia kneels
down before her uncle and lays her head upon his hands</hi>]  We shall
rest.  We shall rest.  We shall see heaven shining like a jewel.  We shall
see all evil and all our pain sink away in the great compassion that shall
enfold the world.  Our life will be as peaceful and tender as a caress.  I
have faith; I have faith."
</p>
<closer>
<signed>LOUIS S. FRIEDLAND.</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

