<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="GalImpe"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="GalImpe">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Imperishable Fiction: An Inquiry into the Short Life of the
'Best Sellers' Reveals the Methods Which Brought into Being the Novels that
Endure</title>
<title type="sort">imperishable fiction an inquiry into the short life of the best sellers reveals the methods which brought into being the novels that endure</title>
<author>Le Gallienne, Richard</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Charles Keller</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">33</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">GalImpe</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475974</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Imperishable Fiction: An Inquiry into the Short Life of the
'Best Sellers' Reveals the Methods which Brought into Being the Novels that
Endure</title>
<title type="sort">imperishable fiction an inquiry into the short life of the best sellers reveals the methods which brought into being the novels that endure</title>
<author>Richard Le Gallienne</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
<name>Munsey's Magazine</name>
</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1914">1914</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 51</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Text used during checking: AP2 .M8 v.51. 1914, UVa Library.
MUNSEY'S MAGAZINE VOLUME LI February, 1914 Number I pp. 134-140.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1914">1914</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-06">June 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Steve Shoemaker</name>
</respStmt>
<item>TEI header and basic markup</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
<head>MUNSEY'S MAGAZINE VOLUME LI <lb/>
February, 1914 Number I pp. 134-140 <lb/>
IMPERISHABLE FICTION<lb/>
AN INQUIRY INTO THE SHORT LIFE OF THE "BEST SELLERS"<lb/>
REVEALS THE METHODS WHICH BROUGHT INTO<lb/>
BEING THE NOVELS THAT ENDURE<lb/>
by Richard Le Gallienne
</head>

<p>
<pb n="134"/>
THE longevity of trees is said to be in proportion to the
slowness of their growth.  It has to do no little as well with
the depth and area of their roots and the richness of the soil in
which they find themselves.  When the sower went forth to sow, it
will be remembered, that which soon sprang up as soon withered
away.  It was the seed that was content to "bring forth fruit
with patience" that finally won out and survived the others.
</p><p>These humble, old-fashioned illustrations occur to me as I
apply myself to the consideration of the question provoked by the
lightning overproduction of modern fiction and modern literature
generally: the question of the flourishing longevity of the
fiction of the past as compared with the swift oblivion which
seems almost invariably to overtake the much-advertised
"masterpieces" of the present.
</p><p>I read somewhere a ballad asking where are the "best sellers"
of yesteryear?  The ballad-maker might well ask, and one might
reecho with Villon:  "Mother of God, ah! where are they?"  During
the last twenty years they have been as the sands on the seashore
for multitude, yet I think one would be hard set to name a dozen
of them whose titles even are still on the lips of men&mdash;whereas
several quieter books published during that same period,
unheralded by trumpet or fire-balloon, are seen serenely to be
ascending to a sure place in the literary firmament.
</p><p>What can be the reason?  Can the decay of these forgotten
phenomena of modern fiction, so lavishly crowned with laurels
manufactured in the offices of their own publishers, have
anything to do with the hectic rapidity of their growth, and may
there be some truth in the supposition that the novels, and books
generally, that live longest are those that took the longest to
write, or, at all events, underwent the longest periods of
gestation?
</p><p>Some fifteen years or so ago one of the most successful
manufacturers of best sellers was Guy Boothby, whose "Dr. Nikola"
is perhaps still remembered.  Unhappily he did not live long to
enjoy the fruits of his industrious dexterity.  I bring his case
to mind as typical of the modern machine-made methods.
</p><p>I had read in a newspaper that he did his "writing" by
phonograph, and chancing to meet him somewhere, asked him about
it.  His response was to invite me to come down to his charming
country house on the Thames and see how he did it.  Boothby was a
fine, manly fellow, utterly without "side" or any illusions as to
the quality of his work.  He loved good literature too
well&mdash;Walter Pater, incongruously enough, was one of his
idols&mdash;to dream that he could make it.  Nor was the making of
literature by any means his first preoccupation, as he made
clear, with winning frankness, within a few moments of my
arriving at his home.
</p><p>Taking me out into his grounds, he brought me to some
extensive kennels, where he showed me with pride some fifty or so
prize dogs; then he took me to his stables, his face shining with
pleasure in his thoroughbreds; and again he led the way to a vast
hennery, populated with innumerable prize fowls.
</p><p>"These are the things I care about," he
<pb n="135"/>said, "and
I write the stuff for which it appears I have a certain knack
only because it enables me to buy them!"
</p><p>Would that all writers of best sellers were as engagingly
honest.  No few of them, however, write no better and affect the
airs of genius into the bargain.
</p><p>Then Boothby took me into his "study," the entire literary
apparatus of which consisted of three phonographs; and he
explained that, when he had dictated a certain amount of a novel
into one of them, he handed it over to his secretary in another
room, who set it going and transcribed what he had spoken into
the machine; he, meanwhile, proceeding to fill up another record.
And he concluded airily by saying with a laugh that he had a
novel of 60,000 words to deliver in ten days, and was just on the
point of beginning it!
</p><p>Boothby's method was, I believe, somewhat unusual in those
days.  Since then it has become something like the rule.  Not so
much as regards the phonograph, perhaps, but with respect to the
breathless speed of production.
</p><div2 type="chapter" id="d4">
<head>A NOVEL IN A WEEK</head>

<p>I am informed by an editor, associated with magazines that
use no less than a million and a half words of fiction a month,
that he has among his contributors more than one writer on whom
he can rely to turn off a novel of 60,000 words in six days, and
that he can put his finger on twenty novelists who think nothing
of writing a novel of a hundred thousand words in anywhere from
sixty to ninety days.  He recalled to me, too, the case of a
well-known novelist who has recently contracted to supply a
publisher with four novels in one year, each novel to run to not
less than a hundred thousand words.  One thinks of the Scotsman
with his "Where's your Willie Shakespeare now?"
</p><p>Even Balzac's titanic industry must hide its diminished head
before such appalling fecundity; and what would Horace have to
say to such froglike verbal spawning, with his famous "labor of
the file" and his counsel to writers "to take a subject equal to
your powers, and consider long what your shoulders refuse, what
they are able to bear."  It is to be feared that "the monument
more enduring than brass" is not erected with such rapidity.  The
only brass associated with the modern best seller is to be found
in the advertisements; and, indeed, all that both purveyor and
consumer seem to care about may well be summed up in the
publisher's recommendation quoted by Professor Phelps:  "This
book goes with a rush and ends with a smash."  Such, one might
add, is the beginning and ending of all literary rockets.
</p></div2><div2 type="chapter" id="d5">
<head>PRODUCTION UNDER HANDICAPS</head>

<p>Now let us recall some fiction that has been in the world
anywhere from, say, three hundred years to fifty years and is yet
vigorously alive, and, in many instances, to be classed still
with the best sellers.
</p><p>"Don Quixote," for example, was published in 1605, but is
still actively selling.  Why?  May it perhaps be that it was some
six years in the writing, and that a great man, who was soldier
as well as writer, charged it with the vitality of all his blood
and tears and laughter, all the hard-won humanity of years of
manful living, those five years as a slave in Algiers (actually
beginning it in prison once more at La Mancha), and all the stern
struggle of a storm-tossed life faced with heroic steadfastness
and gaiety of heart?
</p><p>Take another book which, if it is not read as much as it used
to be, and still deserves to be, is certainly far from being
forgotten&mdash;"Gil Blas."  Published in 1715&mdash;that is, its first two
parts&mdash;it has now two centuries of popularity to its credit, and
is still as racy with humanity as ever; but, though Le Sage was a
rapid and voluminous writer, over this one book which alone the
world remembers it is significant to note that he expended
unusual time and pains.  He was forty-seven years old when the
first two parts were published.  The third part was not published
till 1724, and eleven years more were to elapse before the issue
of the fourth and final part in 1735.
</p><p>A still older book that is still one of the world's best
sellers, "The Pilgrim's Progress," can hardly be conceived as
being dashed off in sixty or ninety days, and would hardly have
endured so long had not Bunyan put into it those twelve years of
soul torment in Bedford gaol.  "Robinson Crusoe" still sells its
annual thousands, whereas others of its author's books no less
skilfully written are practically forgotten, doubtless because
Defoe, fifty-eight years old at its publication, had concentrated
in it the ripe experience of a lifetime.  Though <pb n="136"/>a boy's
book to us, he clearly intended it for an allegory of his own
arduous, solitary life.
</p><p>"I, Robinson Crusoe," we read, "do affirm that the story,
though allegorical, is also historical, and that it is the
beautiful representation of a life of unexampled misfortune, and
of a variety not to be met with in this world."
</p><p>"The Vicar of Wakefield," as we know, was no hurried piece of
work.  Indeed, Goldsmith went about it in so leisurely a fashion
as to leave it neglected in a drawer of his desk, till Johnson
rescued it, according to the proverbial anecdote; and even then
its publisher, Newbery, was in no hurry, for he kept it by him
another two years before giving it to the printer and to
immortality.  It was certainly one of those fruits "brought forth
with patience" all round.
</p></div2><div2 type="chapter" id="d6">
<head>TIME AS A RESERVE FORCE</head>
<p>"Tom Jones" is another such slow-growing masterpiece.
Written in the sad years immediately following the death of his
dearly loved wife, Fielding, dedicating it to Lord Lyttelton,
says:  "I here present you with the labors of some years of my
life"; and it need scarcely be added that the book, as in the
case of all real masterpieces, represented not merely the time
expended on it, but all the accumulated experience of Fielding's
very human history.
</p><p>Yes!  Whistler's famous answer to Ruskin's counsel holds good
of all imperishable literature.  Had he the assurance to ask two
hundred guineas for a picture that only took a day to paint?  No,
replied Whistler, he asked it for "the training of a lifetime";
and it is this training of a lifetime, in addition to the actual
time expended on composition, that constitutes the reserve force
of all great works of fiction, and is entirely lacking in most
modern novels, however superficially brilliant be their
workmanship.
</p><p>For this reason books like George Borrow's "Lavengro" and
"Romany Rye," failures on their publication, grow greater rather
than less with the passage of time.  Their writers, out of the
sheer sincerity of their natures, furnished them, as by magic,
with an inexhaustible provision of life-giving "ichor."  To quote
from Milton, "a good book is the precious life-blood of a master
spirit, embalmed and treasured up on purpose to a life beyond
life."
</p><p>Of this immortality principle in literature Milton himself,
it need hardly be said, is one of the great exemplars.  He was
but thirty-two when he first projected "Paradise Lost," and
through all the intervening years of hazardous political industry
he had kept the seed warm in his heart, its fruit only to be
brought forth with tragic patience in those seven years of
blindness and imminent peril of the scaffold which followed his
fiftieth birthday.
</p><p>The case of poets is not irrelevant to our theme, for the
conditions of all great literature, whatever its nature, are the
same.  Therefore, we may recall Dante, whose "Divine Comedy" was
with him from his thirty-fifth year till the year of his death,
the bitter-sweet companion of twenty years of exile.  Goethe,
again, finished at eighty the "Faust" he had conceived at twenty.
</p><p>Spenser was at work on his "Faerie Queene," alongside his
preoccupation with state business, for nearly twenty years.  Pope
was twelve years translating Homer, and I think there is little
doubt that Gray's "Elegy" owes much of its staying power to the
Horatian deliberation with which he polished and repolished it
through eight years.
</p><p>If we are to believe Poe's "Philosophy of Composition," and
there is, I think, more truth in it than is generally allowed,
the vitality of "The Raven," as that, too, of his genuinely
imperishable fictions, is less due to inspiration than to the
mathematical painstaking of their composition.
</p><p>But, perhaps, of all poets, the story of Vergil is most
instructive for an age of "get-rich-quick " litterateurs.  On his
"Georgics" alone he worked seven years, and, after working eleven
years on the "AEneid," he was still so dissatisfied with it that
on his death-bed he besought his friends to burn it, and on their
refusal, commanded his servants to bring the manuscript that he
might burn it himself.  But, fortunately, Augustus had heard
portions of it, and the imperial veto overpowered the poet's
infanticidal desire.
</p><p>But, to return to the novelists, it may at first sight seem
that the great writer who, with the Waverley Novels, inaugurated
the modern era of cyclonic booms and mammoth sales, was an
exception to the classic formula of creation which we <pb n="137"/>are
endeavoring to make good.  Stevenson, we have been told, used to
despair as he thought of Scott's "immense fecundity of invention"
and "careless, masterly ease."
</p><p>"I cannot compete with that," he says&mdash;"what makes me sick is
to think of Scott turning out `Guy Mannering' in three weeks."
</p><p>Scott's speed is, indeed, one of the marvels of literary
history, yet in his case, perhaps more than in that of any other
novelist, it must be remembered that this speed had, in an
unusual degree, that "training of a lifetime" to rely upon, as
from his earliest boyhood all Scott's faculties had been
consciously as well as unconsciously engaged in absorbing and, by
the aid of his astonishing memory, preserving the vast materials
on which he was able thus carelessly to draw.
</p><p>Moreover, those who have read his manly autobiography know
that this speed was by no means all "ease," as witness the almost
tragic composition of "The Bride of Lammermoor."  If ever a
writer scorned delights and lived laborious days, it was Walter
Scott.  At the same time the condition of his fame in the present
day bears out the general truth of my contention, for there is
little doubt that he would be more widely read than he is were it
not for those too frequent <hi rend="italic">longueurs</hi> and inert paddings which
resulted from his too hurried workmanship.
 </p>
</div2><div2 type="chapter" id="d7">
<head>STORIES WHICH FIRST WERE LIVED</head>

<p>Jane Austen is another example of comparatively rapid
creation, writing three of her best-known novels, "Pride and
Prejudice" "Sense and Sensibility," and "Northanger Abbey"
between the ages of twenty-one and twenty-three.  Yet "Pride and
Prejudice," which practically survives the others, took her ten
months to complete, and all her writings, it has again to be
said, had first been deeply and intimately "lived."
</p><p>Charlotte Bronte was a year in writing "Jane Eyre," spurred
on to new effort by the recent rejection of "The Professor," but
to write such a book in a year cannot be called overhasty
production when one considers how much of "Jane Eyre" was drawn
from Charlotte Bronte's own life, and also how she and her
sisters had been experimenting with literature from their
earliest childhood.
</p><p>Thackeray considered an allowance of two years sufficient for
the writing of a good novel, but that seems little enough when
one takes into account the length of his best-known books, not to
mention the perfection of their craftsmanship.  Dickens, for all
the prodigious bulk of his output, was rather a steady than a
rapid writer.  He considered, says Forster, "three of his not
very large manuscript pages a good, and four an excellent, day's
work."
</p><p>"David Copperfield" was about a year and nine months in the
writing, having been begun in the opening of 1849 and completed
in October, 1850.  "Bleak House" took a little longer, having
been begun in November, 1851, and completed in August, 1853.
"Hard Times" was a hasty piece of work, written between the
winter of 1853 and the summer of 1854, and it cannot be
considered one of Dickens's notable successes.
</p><p>George Meredith wrote four of his greatest novels in seven
years, "Richard Feverel," "Evan Harrington," "Sandra Belloni,"
and "Rhoda Fleming" being produced between 1859 and 1866.  His
poem, "Modern Love," was also written during that period.
</p><p>George Eliot was a much-meditating painstaking writer, though
"Adam Bede" cost her little more than a year's work.  Her novels,
however, as a rule, did not come forth without prayer and
fasting, and, in the course of their creation, she used often to
suffer from "hopelessness and melancholy."  "Romola," to which
she devoted long and studious preparation, she was often on the
point of giving up, and in regard to it she gives expression to a
literary ideal to which the gentleman with the contract for four
novels a year, referred to in the outset of this paper, is
probably a stranger.
</p><p>"It may turn out," she says, "that I can't work freely and
fully enough in the medium I have chosen, and in that case I must
give, it up; for I will never write anything to which my whole
heart, mind, and conscience don't consent; so that I may feel it
was something&mdash;however small&mdash;which wanted to be done in this
world, and that I am just the organ for that small bit of work."
</p><p>Charles Kingsley who, if not a great novelist, has to his
credit in "Westward Ho" one romance at least which, in the old
phrase, "the world will not willingly <pb n="138"/>let die," was as
conscientious in his work as he was brilliant.
</p><p>Says a friend who was with him while he was writing
"Hypatia":  "He took extraordinary pains to be accurate.  We
spent one whole day in searching the four folio volumes of
Synesius for a fact he thought was there, and which was found
there at last."
</p><p>The writer of perhaps the greatest historical novel in the
English language, "The Cloister and the Hearth," was what one
might call a glutton for thoroughness.  Of himself Charles Reade
has said:  "I studied the great art of fiction closely for
fifteen years before I presumed to write a line.  I was a ripe
critic before I became an artist."  His commonplace books, on the
entries in which and the indexing he was accustomed to spend one
whole day out of each week, cataloguing the notes of his
multifarious reading and pasting in cuttings from newspapers
likely to be useful in novel-building, completely filled one of
the rooms in his house.  In his will he left these open to the
inspection of literary students who cared to study the methods
which he had found so serviceable.
</p><p>To name one or two more English novelists:  Thomas Hardy's
novels would seem to have the slow growth of deep-rooted things.
His greatest work, "The Return of the Native," was on the stocks
for four years, though a year seems to have sufficed for "Far
from the Madding Crowd."
</p>
</div2><div2 type="chapter" id="d8">
<head>THE WAYS OF STEVENSON AND HAWTHORNE</head>

<p>The meticulous practise of Stevenson is proverbial, but this
glimpse of his method is worth catching again.  "The first draft
of a story," records Mr. Charles D. Lanier, "Stevenson wrote out
roughly, or dictated to Lloyd Osbourne.  When all the colors were
in hand for the complete picture, he invariably penned it
himself, with exceeding care. . . .  If the first copy did not
please him, he patiently made a second or a third draft.  In his
stern, self-imposed apprenticeship of phrase-making he had
prepared himself for these workmanlike methods by the practise of
rewriting his trial stories into dramas and then reworking them
into stories again."
</p><p>Nathaniel Hawthorne brought the devoted, one might say, the
devotional, spirit of the true artist to all his work, but "The
Scarlet Letter" was written at a good pace when once started,
though, as usual, the germ had been in Hawthorne's mind for many
years.  The story of its beginning is one of the many touching
anecdotes in that history of authorship which Carlyle compared to
the Newgate Calendar.  Incidentally, too, it witnesses that an
author occasionally meets with a good wife,
</p><p>One wintry autumn day in Salem Hawthorne returned home
earlier than usual from the custom-house.  With pale lips, he
said to his wife:  "I am turned out of office."  To which
she&mdash;God bless her!&mdash;cheerily replied:  "Very well I now you can
write your book!" and immediately set about lighting his study
fire and generally making things comfortable for his work.
</p><p>The book was "The Scarlet Letter," and was completed by the
following February, Hawthorne, as his wife said, writing
"immensely" on it day after day, nine hours a day.  When
finished, Hawthorne seems to have been dispirited about the
story, and put it away in a drawer; but the good James T. Fields
chanced soon to call on him, and asked him if he had anything for
him to publish.
</p><p>"Who," asked Hawthorne gloomily, would risk publishing a book
from me, the most unpopular writer in America?"
</p><p>"I would," was Fields's rejoinder, and after some further
sparring, Hawthorne owned up.
</p><p>"As you have found me out," said he, "take what I have
written and tell me if it is good for anything"; and Fields went
away with the manuscript of what is, without any question,
America's greatest novel.
</p><p>Turning to the great novelists of France, with one or two
exceptions, they all bear out the theory of longevity in
literature which I have been endeavoring to support.  It must
reluctantly be confessed that one of the most fascinatingly vital
of them all, Alexandre Dumas, is one of the exceptions, born
improvisator as he was; yet immense research, it needs hardly be
said, went to the making of his enormous library of romance&mdash;even
though, it be allowed, that much of that work was done for him by
his "disciples."
</p><p>George Sand was another facile, all too facile, writer.  Here
is a description of her method:  "To write novels was to her only
a process of nature.  She seated herself before her table at ten
o'clock, with scarcely a plot and only the slightest acquaintance
with her characters, and until five in the evening, while her
hand guided <pb n="139"/>a pen, the novel wrote itself.  Next day, and
the next, it was the same.  By and by the novel had written
itself in full and another was unfolding."
</p><p>Whether George Sand is still alive as a novelist, apart from
her place as an historic personality, I leave others to decide;
but I am very sure that she would be read a great deal more than
she is if she had not so confidently left her novels&mdash;to write
themselves.  Different, indeed, was the method of Balzac, toiling
year after year at his colossal task of "The Human Comedy,"
sometimes working eighteen hours a day, and never less than
twelve, and that "in the midst of protested bills, business
annoyances, the most cruel financial straits in utter solitude
and lack of all consolation."  But then Balzac was sustained by
one of those great dreams, without whose aid no lasting
literature is produced, the dream, "by infinite patience and
courage, to compose for the France of the nineteenth century,
that history of morals which the old civilizations of Rome,
Athens, Memphis, and India have left untold."
</p><p>To fulfil this he was able to live, for a long period, on a
daily expenditure of "three sous for bread, two for milk, and
three for firing."  But doubtless it had been different if his
dream had been prize puppies, a garage full of motor-cars, or a
translation into the Four Hundred.
</p></div2><div2 type="chapter" id="d9">
<head>A REAL AUTHOR IN CAPTIVITY</head>

<p>Victor Hugo, again, was one of the herculean artists working,
in Emerson's phrase, "in a sad sincerity," with the patience of
an ant and the energy of a volcano.  Of his "Les
Miserables"&mdash;perhaps the greatest novel ever written, as it is, I
suppose, easily the longest&mdash;he said, "it takes me nearly as long
to publish a book as to write one"; and he was at work on "Les
Miserables," off and on, for nearly fifteen years.  Of his
writing "Notre Dame" (that other colossus of fiction) this quaint
picture has been preserved.  He had made vast historical
preparations for it, but ever there seemed still more to make,
till at length his publisher grew impatient, and under his
pressure Hugo at last made a start&mdash;after this fashion:
</p><p>"He purchased a great gray woolen wrapper that covered him
from head to foot, he locked up all his clothes lest he should be
tempted to go out, and, carrying off his ink-bottle to his study,
applied himself to his labor just as if he had been in prison.
He never left the table except for food and sleep, and the sole
recreation that he allowed himself was an hour's chat after
dinner with M. Pierre Leroux, or any other friend who might drop
in, and to whom he would occasionally read over his day's work."
</p><p>Daudet, whose <hi rend="italic">Tartarin</hi> bids fair to remain one of the
world's types, like <hi rend="italic">Don Quixote</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Mr. Micawber</hi>, for all
his natural Provencal gift of improvisation and, indeed, from his
self-recognized necessity of keeping it in check, was another
strenuous artist.  He wrote each manuscript three times over, he
told his biographer, and would write it as many more if he could;
and his son, in writing of him, has this truth to say of his, as
of all living work:  "The fact is that labor does not begin at
the moment when the artist takes his pen.  It begins in sustained
reflection and in the thought which accumulates images and sifts
them, garners and winnows them out, and compels life to keep
control over imagination, and imagination to expand and enlarge
life."
</p><p>Zola is perhaps unduly depreciated nowadays, but certainly,
if Carlyle's "infinite capacity for taking pains" as a recipe for
genius ever was put to the test, it was by the author of the
Rougon-Macquart series.  Talking of rewriting, Prosper Merimee,
best known for "Carmen," is said to have rewritten his "Colomba"
no less than sixteen times; as our Anglo-Saxon Kipling, it used
to be told, wrote his short stories seven times over.

</p></div2><div2 type="chapter" id="d10">
<head>THE PAINSTAKING OF FLAUBERT</head>

<p>But, of course, the classical example of the artist-fanatic
in modern times was Gustave Flaubert.  His agonies in quest of
the <hi rend="italic">mot propre</hi>, the one and only word, are proverbial, and
are said literally to have broken down his nerves.  Mr. Huneker
has told of him that "he would annotate three hundred volumes for
a page of facts. . . .  In twenty pages he sometimes saved three
or four from destruction," and, in the course of twenty-six
years' polishing and pruning of "The Temptation of Saint
Anthony," he reduced his original manuscript of 540 pages down to
136, even reducing it still further after its first publication.
</p><p>On "Madame Bovary" he worked six
<pb n="140"/>
years, and in
writing
"Salammbo," which took him no less time, he studied the scenery
on the spot and exhausted the resources of the Imperial Library
in his search for documentary evidences.
</p><p>Flaubert may be said to have carried his passion for
perfection to the point of mania, and it will be a question with
some whether, with all his pains, he can be called a great
novelist, after all.  But that he was a great stylist and a
master in the art of making terrible and beautiful bas-reliefs
admits of no doubt.
</p><p>To be a great world-novelist you need an all-embracing
humanity as well, such as we find in Tolstoy's "War and
Peace"&mdash;but that great book, need one say, came of no slipshod
speed of improvisation.  On the contrary, Tolstoy corrected and
recorrected it so often that his wife, who acted as his
amanuensis, is said to have copied the whole enormous manuscript
no less than seven times!
</p><p>Yes! though it be doubtless true, in Mr. Kipling's famous
phrase, that </p>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>There are nine and sixty ways</l>
<l>Of inditing tribal lays,</l>
<l>And every blessed one of them is right,</l>
</lg>
<p>
I think that the whole nine and sixty of them include somewhere
in their method those sole preservative virtues of truth to life
and passionate artistic integrity.  The longest-lived books,
whatever their nature, have usually been the longest growing; and
even those lasting things of literature that have seemed, as it
were, to spring up in a night, have been long in secret
preparation in a soil mysteriously enriched and refined by the
hid processes of time.
</p></div2>
<div2 type="poem" id="d11">
<head>BALLADE OF PERFUMES</head>

<lg type="stanza" n="1">
<l>Haunting the air float perfumes of all time,</l>
<l>    Fantoms of nard anointing unknown kings,</l>
<l>Ghosts of the incense circling orient clime,</l>
<l>    Wraiths of the myrrh that clouded Nike's wings.</l>
<l>Cinnamon, aloes, champak&mdash;spicy things</l>
<l>    Strange to the nostrils freight each sunny ray:</l>
<l>To me more pregnant is the storm that brings</l>
<l>    The tang and tingle of the clean salt spray.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="stanza" n="2">
<l>Jinn of the East, prevade our smoke and grime, </l>
<l> Heavy with musk that wreathed the tombs of Mings, </l>
<l>Flaunting about our streets of nauseous slime </l>
<l>    Sandalwood, jinko's sacred offerings, </l>
<l>Swooning patchouli, fragrancy that clings&mdash; </l>
<l>    Seeking to drug our senses to their sway: </l>
<l>To me more potent is the spume that flings </l>
<l>    The tang and tingle of the clean salt spray. </l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza" n="3">

<l>Jasmine and rose have long been held sublime;
</l><l>    Odorous rapture high in the orchid swings;
</l><l>Out of exotic petal, leaf, and cyme,
</l><l>    Lovely, alive, the clever pander wrings
</l><l>Attars to tempt all vain soft overlings&mdash;
</l><l>    Essenced delight for all with purse to pay:
</l><l>To me all-priceless is the brine that stings,
</l><l>    The tang and tingle of the clean salt spray. </l>
</lg>
<lg type="stanza" n="4">
<head>ENVOY</head>
<l>Flora, although your wood-and-meadow springs</l>
<l>    Ravish and witch when flowered fresh by May,</l>
<l>How brief their spell: forever Triton sings</l>
<l>    The tang and tingle of the clean salt spray.</l>
</lg>
<signed>Richard Butler Glaenzer</signed>

</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
