<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="GilPoet"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="GilPoet">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Poet's Fame</title>
<title type="sort">poets fame</title>
<author>Gilder, Richard Watson</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Charles Keller</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">8</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">GilPoet</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475984</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Poet's Fame</title>
<title type="sort">poets fame</title>
<author>Richard Watson Gilder</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner's Monthly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1878-11">November 1878</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 17, no. 1</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 111-112</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1878">1878</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; poetry</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-05">May 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>minimal TEI tagging</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<front id="d2">

<titlePage id="d3">
	<pb/>
<docImprint>
SCRIBNER'S MONTHLY<lb/>
VOL. XVII. NOVEMBER, 1878.  NO. 1.<lb/>
pp. 111-112<lb/>
</docImprint>
<titlePart type="main">
THE POET'S FAME.<lb/>
</titlePart>
<docAuthor>
by<lb/>
Richard Watson Gilder<lb/>
</docAuthor>
</titlePage>
</front>

<body id="d4">



<div1 type="poem" id="d5"><pb n="111"/>
<head>THE POET'S FAME.</head>

<lg type="verse">
<l>   Many the songs of power the poet had wrought,</l>
<l>To shake the hearts of men.  Yea, he had caught</l>
<l>The murmuring and inarticulate sound</l>
<l>That comes at midnight from the darkened ground</l>
<l>When the earth sleeps; for this he framed a word</l>
<l>Of human speech, and hearts were strangely stirred</l>
<l>That listened.  And for him the evening dew</l>
<l>Fell with a sound of music, and the blue</l>
<l>Of the deep, starry sky he had the art</l>
<l>To put in language that did seem a part</l>
<l>Of the great scope and progeny of nature.</l>
<l>In woods, or waves, or winds, there was no creature</l>
<l>Mysterious to him.  He was too wise</l>
<l>Either to fear, or follow, or despise</l>
<l>Whom men call Science, &mdash; for he knew full well</l>
<l>What she had told, or still might live to tell,</l>
<l>Was known to him before her very birth;</l>
<l>Yea, that there was no secret of the earth,</l>
<l>Nor of the waters under, nor the skies,</l>
<l>That had been hidden from the poet's eyes;</l>
<l>By him there was no ocean unexplored,</l>
<l>Nor any savage coast that had not roared</l>
<l>Its music in his ears.</l>
<pb n="112"/>
<l>                   He loved the town, &mdash; </l>
<l>Not less he loved the ever-deepening brown</l>
<l>Of summer twilights on the enchanted hills;</l>
<l>Where he might listen to the starts and thrills</l>
<l>Of birds that sang and rustled in the trees,</l>
<l>Or watch the footsteps of the wandering breeze</l>
<l>And the birds' shadows as they fluttered by</l>
<l>Or slowly wheeled across the unclouded sky.</l>
<l>All these were written on his very soul, &mdash; </l>
<l>But be knew, too, the utmost distant goal</l>
<l>Of the human mind.  His fiery thought did run</l>
<l>To Time's beginnings, ere yon central sun</l>
<l>Had warmed to life the swarming broods of men.</l>
<l>In waking dreams, his many-visioned ken</l>
<l>Clutched the large, final destiny of things.</l>
<l>He heard the starry music, and the wings</l>
<l>Of spiritual beings fanned the air</l>
<l>About him.  Yet the loud and angry blare</l>
<l>Of tempests found an echo in his verse,</l>
<l>And it was here that lovers did rehearse</l>
<l>The ditties they would sing when, not too soon,</l>
<l>Came the warm night, &mdash; shadows, and stars, and moon</l>
<l>Who heard his songs were filled with noble rage,</l>
<l>And wars took fire from his prophetic page:</l>
<l>Most righteous wars, wherein, 'midst blood and tears,</l>
<l>The world rushed onward through a thousand years.</l>
<l>Nathless, he made the gentle sounds of peace</l>
<l>Heroic, &mdash; bade the nation's anger cease!</l>
<l>Bitter his songs of grief for those who fell &mdash; </l>
<l>And for all this the people loved him well.</l>
</lg><lg type="verse">
<l>   They loved him well, and therefore, on a day,</l>
<l>They said, with one accord:  "Behold how gray</l>
<l>Our poet's head hath grown!  Ere 'tis too late</l>
<l>Come, let us crown him in our Hall of State;</l>
<l>Let the bells ring, fill the wide air with praise,</l>
<l>And spread his fame to other lands and days!"</l>
</lg><lg type="verse">
<l>   So was it done, and deep his joy therein.</l>
<l>But passing home at night, from out the din</l>
<l>Of the loud Hall, the poet, unaware,</l>
<l>Moved through a lonely and dim-lighted square &mdash; </l>
<l>There was the smell of lilacs in the air,</l>
<l>And then the sudden singing of a bird,</l>
<l>Startled by his slow tread.  What memory stirred</l>
<l>Within his brain he told not.  Yet this night &mdash; </l>
<l>Still lingering when the eastern heavens were bright &mdash; </l>
<l>He wove a song of such immortal art</l>
<l>That there is not in all the world one heart, &mdash; </l>
<l>One human heart unmoved by it.  Long! long!</l>
<l>The laurel-crown has failed, but not that song</l>
<l>Born of the night and sorrow; and where he lies</l>
<l>At rest beneath the ever-shifting skies,</l>
<l>Age after age, from far-off lands they come,</l>
<l>Not without flowers, to seek the poet's tomb.</l>
</lg>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
