<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="GorPers"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>
<TEI.2 id="GorPers">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Personal Recollections of Anton Pavlovitch Chekhov</title>
<title type="sort">personal recollections of anton pavlovitch chekhov</title>
<author>Gorky, Maxim</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">24</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">GorPers</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476984</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Electronic version has not been checked against print source by Electronic Text Center.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Personal Recollections of Anton Pavlovitch Chekhov</title>
<title level="j">The Independent</title>
<title type="sort">personal recollections of anton pavlovitch chekhov</title>
<author>Maxim Gorky</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Translator</resp>
<name>Lizzie B. Gorin</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp 299-304</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<date value="1905-08-10">August 10, 1905</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print source not available.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>The Independent, Vol. 59, 10 August 1905</p>
</note>
<note>
<p>Bibliographic information for print source not checked against original.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1905">1905</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; essay</term>
<term>Literature in Translation</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-10">October 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Stephen Ramsay, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">



<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="299"/>
<head>               <hi rend="bold">Personal Recollections of Anton<lb/>
                 Pavlovitch Chekhov<lb/>
                  BY MAXIM GORKY</hi>
</head>

<p>
<note><p>[As a narrative of the visit of the best known of Russian short
story
writers to another regarded as still greater, the following article has an
especial interest.  Maxim Gorky has long been popular in this country, and
his imprisonment on the charge of conspiracy to overthrow the Government
has recently brought him into greater prominence.  Chekhov's stories are
now beginning to be translated into English, and since they are much wider
in scope and more varied in style than Gorky's they are likely to find
more readers among us.  According to Tolstoy Chekhov is the founder of a
new school of literature, and his influence will be lastingly felt
throughout the world.  He was born in 1860, the son of a serf who had
freed himself by his own ability.  He was educated as a physician in the
University of Moscow, and began to write for college journals at the age
of nineteen.  His death last year is deeply regretted, since he was at the
<orig reg="height">hight</orig> of his powers of production and his stories were becoming
somewhat more optimistic in tone.  The illustrations accompanying this
article are all taken from caricatures originally published in Russian
newspapers and magazines.  The translation is by Lizzie B.
Gorin.&mdash;EDITOR.]</p></note>
</p>

<p>I BELIEVE that every man when in the presence of Anton
Pavlovitch felt the desire of being simpler, truer, more like his
natural self, and I observed many times how
people threw off the gaudy attire of bookish phrases and all the
other cheap finery of high-sounding, bombastic words in which our
Russian loves to adorn himself, like the savage in his fish-teeth and
shells and feathers, in the foolish desire of aping the Europeans.
Anton Pavlovitch heartily disliked fish-teeth and cocks' feathers.  In
fact, everything striking, gaudy and foreign donned by some one to
"give himself additional importance" irritated and threw him into
confusion.  And I have noticed that every time he met an
overdressed, bombastic person he felt inclined to free him from his
burdensome and unnecessary tinsel trappings, which distorted the
natural face and living soul of his interlocutor.  All his life Anton
Pavlovitch lived on the wealth of his soul; he was always his natural
self and kept himself internally free, not taking into consideration
what others may have expected of him or others of less delicacy
demanded for a moment.  He disliked conversations on "high"
themes&mdash;the sort of conversations with which our dear Russian
generally loves to amuse himself, forgetting that it is ridiculous to
speak of costly clothing which we are to have in the future when at
present we are lacking even a decent pair of trousers.
</p><p>Himself beautiful and simple, he loved simplicity, reality and
sincerity, and he had a special way of making those with whom he
came in contact simpler and better.</p>
<pb n="300"/>


<p>I remember that once he was visited by three richly dressed
ladies.  After filling his rooms with the rustle of their silk skirts and
strong perfumery, they decorously seated themselves opposite their
host, feigning that they were very much interested in politics, and
began to "put questions."
</p><p>"Anton Pavlovitch, with what do you suppose this war will
end?"
</p><p>Anton Pavlovitch coughed slightly and, after thinking for a
moment, replied in his serious, gentle voice:
</p><p>"In all probability&mdash;in peace."
</p><p>"Well, yes&mdash;of course!  But who will win?  The Greeks or the
Turks?"
</p><p>"It seems to me that the one who is stronger is sure to win."
</p><p>"And who, in your opinion, is the stronger?" the ladies asked,
vying with each other.
</p><p>"Those who are more intelligent and better fed."
</p><p>"Oh, how witty!" exclaimed one lady.
</p><p>"And whom do you like more, Anton Pavlovitch, the Greeks
or the Turks?"
</p><p>Anton Pavlovitch looked at her and replied with a kind, gentle
smile:
</p><p>"I like marmalade&mdash;don't you?"
</p><p>"Very!" she exclaimed vivaciously.
</p><p>"Of apricots!" sedately corroborated another.
</p><p>And the third added with great relish, half closing her eyes: "It
has a delicious aroma!"
</p><p>And all three began to speak with great animation of
marmalade, thereby showing that on this particular question they
possessed a splendid erudition and a thorough knowledge of the
subject.  It was evident that they were glad of the opportunity not to
strain their minds in feigning an interest in either Greek or Turk,
neither of whom they had ever thought of until the very moment.
</p><p>On leaving Anton Pavlovitch they said merrily:
</p><p>"We shall send you some nice marmalade!"
</p><p>"You have had a nice conversation!" I remarked after they had
left.
</p><p>"It is necessary that every one should speak his own language,"
he laughingly said.
</p><p>On another occasion I found with him a young and very
handsome assistant district attorney.  He was standing before
Chekhov and speaking in a very animated way, shaking his curly
head:
</p><p>"In your story, 'The Malefactor,' you have brought before us a
very intricate question.  If I should acknowledge in Denise
Grigorieff an objective vicious will, conscious of the crime he
commits, I would feel compelled to put him into jail without the
least scruple, because that is what the interests of society demand.
But he is a savage; he had committed the crime unconsciously, and
I feel sorry for him!  But if I should deal with him as with a creature
who acted without understanding and therefore treat him with
clemency, what guarantee can I give to society, whose interests I am
bound to defend, that this Denise will not again meddle with the
rails and thereby cause a terrible disaster?  This is the question!
What, therefore, is to be done?"
</p><p>He stopped, threw back his shoulders and stared scrutinizingly
into the face of Anton Pavlovitch.  He was dressed in a brand new
uniform and his breast buttons shone as self-consciously and
stupidly as the eyes in the neat little face of the youthful zealot of
justice.
</p><p>"If I were the judge," Anton Pavlovitch replied earnestly, "I
would acquit Denise."
</p><p>"But on what ground?"
</p><p>"I would simply say to him: 'See here, Denise, you have not
yet ripened
<pb n="301"/>
into the type of a conscious criminal; go and
ripen!"
</p><p>The jurist laughed, but immediately continued with his former
pompous earnestness:
</p><p>"No, my revered Anton Pavlovitch.  The question you put
forth in your story can only be decided in the interest of society,
whose life and property I am called upon to defend.  Denise is a
savage, yes, but at the same time he is also a criminal&mdash;this is the
truth!"
</p><p>"How do you like the gramophone?" Chekhov suddenly asked,
very kindly.
</p><p>"Oh, very much indeed!  It is a wonderful invention," the
youth replied vivaciously.
</p><p>"And I cannot bear it!" Anton Pavlovitch sadly confessed.
</p><p>"Why?"
</p><p>"Because it sings and speaks without feeling anything, and it
all comes out like a caricature&mdash;dead.  Are you interested in
photography?"
</p><p>It came out that he was a passionate admirer of the
photographers' art and he immediately began to speak of it with
great enthusiasm, entirely forgetting the gramophone, tho he had so
much in common with that "wonderful invention," as Chekhov so
cleverly and truly observed.  And once more I saw peeping from out
the uniform a funny little man who as yet felt himself as much at
home in the position he occupied in life as a young pup feels at the
chase.
</p><p>After escorting his guest to the door Anton Pavlovitch said
gloomily:
</p><p>"And such a pimple on the face of justice is deciding people's
destinies!"
</p><p>And after a moment's silence he added: "It seems to me that
district attorneys love to angle fish."
</p><p>He possessed the art of detecting and bring out triviality&mdash;an art
attainable only to men of very high demands upon life, and which is
created only through a passionate desire that people should be
simple and beautifully harmonious.  Triviality always found in him
a keen and cruel judge.
</p><p>Some one said in his presence that a certain publisher of a
popular magazine, a man who always talked of the necessity of love
and mercy toward others, had without any reason insulted a
conductor of a railroad and generally treated his subordinates very
badly.
</p><p>"Well!  Is that anything surprising?" said Anton Pavlovitch,
frowning and smiling at the same moment.  "Is he not an aristocrat&mdash;an educated person?  Did he not attend the seminary?  Has not his
father worn bast-shoes and does he not wear patent leather boots?"
</p><p>And in the tone in which he pronounced these words was
something which at once made the "aristocrat" appear both
insignificant and ridiculous.
</p><p>"A very talented man!" he once said, speaking of a certain
journalist.  "He writes so nobly, always, and compassionately&mdash;sweetly&mdash;sweetly&mdash;calls his wife in the presence of strangers a fool&mdash;keeps his servants in a damp room and complains that the
chambermaid suffers with rheumatism."
</p><p>"Do you like N. N., Anton Pavlovitch?"
</p><p>"Yes, very much.  A pleasant man," Chekhov agreed,
coughing.  "He knows everything&mdash;reads much; he swallowed three
books of mine.  He is very absent-minded.  To-day he tells you that
you are a splendid fellow, and the very next day he will inform
some one that you are cheating your servants out of their wages, and
that you have stolen the silk socks from the husband of your
mistress&mdash;black ones with blue stripes."
</p><p>Some one complained in his presence of the tediousness and
heaviness of the "serious" sections of the larger magazines.
</p><p>"Do not read the articles," Anton Pavlovitch persuasively
advised.  "They are the so-called friendly literature&mdash;a literature
between comrades.  The authors of these articles are Messrs.
Krasnov (red), Bielov (white), and Chernov (black).  One writes an
article, the other

<pb n="302"/>
objects to it, and the
third reconciles the contradictions of both.  It looks very much like
a game of whist, a dummy for the fourth partner in the game.  And
not one of the three of them ever asked himself the simple question,
why the reader needs all this.
</p><p>"Critics are very similar to the gad-flies which are always
hindering the horse in his work," he used to say with the clever
smile of his.  "The horse plows and strains its every muscle like the
strings on a counter-bass; suddenly the gad-fly descends upon his
back and begins to tickle him and to buzz, and the poor horse frets
and waves his tail.  What does the gad-fly buzz about?  It hardly
knows itself.  It simply possesses a restless nature and wants to
introduce itself to every one's notice&mdash;'know ye that I also am a
resident of this globe!  As you can well hear, I can even buzz&mdash;I can
buzz about everything!'  For the last twenty-five years I have been
diligently reading what the critics had to say about my stories and I
cannot remember to have found one useful indication or one good
advice in all these years.  Only once Skabichevsky made an
impression on me when he wrote that I would 'die in a drunken
state, somewhere under a hedge.'"
</p><p>There always lurked in his gray, sad eyes a fine, ironical smile,
but at times they could become cold, sharp and hard; at such times
his flexible, soulful voice sounded harder, and it seemed to me at
such moments that this modest, delicate man would stand up for his
rights and defend them against an evilly disposed power, if he
should find it necessary, with vigor and strength, to the very last
breath.</p>

<p>At times it seemed to me that there was in his relation to
people a feeling of utter hopelessness, something akin to a cold,
quiet despair.
</p><p>"A Russian is a remarkable being!" he once said to me.  "He is
very much like a sieve; everything goes through him.  In his youth
he greedily fills his soul with everything he can lay his hands on and
at the age of thirty all that remains of it is a kind of grayish rubbish.
To live well, worthy of a human being, one must labor.  Work
lovingly, faithfully&mdash;and with us nobody is able to do this.  An
architect sits down to the card-table or spends his time in the wings
of the theaters as soon as he has succeeded in constructing two or
three decent buildings.  A doctor as quick as he succeeds in building
up a lucrative practice for himself loses all interest in science and
never reads anything aside from the 'News in Therapeutics.'  And at
forty he is earnestly convinced that all diseases emanate from chills.
I have never yet met an official who to some extent understood the
importance of his work.  He generally sits at the capital or
Government-city and composes papers which are sent to Zmiev or
Smargon for execution.  But he thinks as little of those whom his
papers at Zmiev or Smargon deprive of their freedom as an atheist
thinks of the agonies of purgatory.  A lawyer, after he once makes a
name for himself in a successfully conducted law suit, does not
trouble himself any longer with defending just cases; he takes up
the defense of rich corporations, plays on the races, eats oysters and
represents himself as a connoisseur of fine arts.  An actor, after
rendering a few decent <hi rend="italic">r&ocirc;les</hi>, gives up studying any
further, dons a cylinder hat and proclaims himself a genius.  Russia
as a whole is a land of greedy, indolent people, who eat much and
daintily, drink, love to sleep in the daytime and snore while so
occupied.  They marry because a wife keeps the house in order, and
keep a mistress because it elevates them in the eyes of society.
Their psychology is purely canine; if you beat them they hide in
their kennels, yelping softly.  If you caress them they lie upon their
backs with raised paws and a wagging tail."
</p><p>His words sounded cold and con-<pb n="303"/>
temptuous, fraught
with a deep sadness.  Despising, he also pitied, and if I happened to
rail at some one in his presence Anton Pavlovitch would
immediately take up his defense.
</p><p>"Don't!  Why should you?  And he an old man; he is almost
seventy."
</p><p>Or:
</p><p>"He is still so young&mdash;it is only because of his foolishness."
</p><p>And when he spoke in this way I did not see any aversion in
his face.
</p><p>In youth triviality seems only ludicrous and insignificant, but it
slowly envelops its victim in its grayish mist, penetrates his brain,
pollutes his blood like a poison or the fumes of charcoal, and the
man soon becomes like an old sign-board eaten through and through
with rust; it looks as if something was painted upon it once upon a
time, but now it is impossible to distinguish what it was.
</p><p>Anton Pavlovitch Chekhov had already shown in his very first
stories that he was able to discover in the murky sea of triviality its
tragically somber jokes; one has only to read carefully his
"humoristic" stories to be convinced how much cruelty and
depravity the author saw and hid with modest shame under the
exterior of droll and comical situations.
</p><p>He was modestly chaste and could not permit himself to say to
people loudly and frankly, "Do be more decent!" vainly hoping that
they might themselves perceive the necessity of it.  Hating
everything trivial and dirty, he depicted the abominations of life in
the noble and lofty language of a poet and with the gentle, ironical
smile of the humorist.  And under the beautiful exterior of his
stories is hardly noticeable the full bitterness of the reproach
conveyed by them.
</p><p>Reading, the daughter of the respected public laughs heartily,
hardly noticing the disgusting derision of the overfed "Barin"
toward a poor, forlorn creature, alone in a foreign land, among
strange people and surroundings.  And in almost every one of
Chekhov's humoristic stories I hear the same low, deep sigh of a
pure, truly human heart, a hopeless sigh of compassion toward
people who cannot respect their human dignity and resistlessly obey
a brutal power, living like slaves and believing
in nothing, aside from the necessity of gulping down every day as
much as possible of the fat cabbage-soup, and who feel nothing
beside the fear of some one strong and impudent who may fall upon
them and give them a sound beating.
</p><p>No one understood as keenly and clearly as did Chekhov the
tragedy of a petty life, and no one before him so mercilessly and
truly depicted to the people the picture of the sad and shameless life
they lead in their murky, monotonous, everyday existence.
</p><p>His greatest enemy was triviality; he wrestled with it all his
life, he laughed at it and wrote about it with an unimpassioned,
sharp pen.  He could find the moldiness of triviality, even where
everything seemed on the first glance to be very well arranged, with
comfort and even with certain splendor&mdash;and triviality revenged
itself upon its worst enemy by playing on the dead a disgustingly
vulgar prank by placing his body&mdash;the body of a poet&mdash;in a car "For
the transportation of fresh oysters."
</p><p>That dirty green car seems to me nothing less than the great
triumphant grin of triviality over its worn-out enemy, and in the
countless "recollections" of the daily press I perceive the
hypocritical sorrowfulness beyond which I feel the cold, evil-smelling breath of that same triviality, secretly rejoicing in the early
death of its enemy.
</p><p>Reading the stories of Anton Pavlovitch Chekhov one feels as
on a sad day in late fall, when the air is so transparent and the bare
trees, narrow houses and gray looking people are so sharply
<pb n="304"/>
outlined in it.  Everything seems so strange and lonely,
motionless and helpless.  The deep blue distances are deserted and
blend readily with the pale sky, breathing with melancholy cold
upon the earth covered with frozen mud.  The mind of the author,
like the late fall sun, lights up with cruel clearness the broken roads,
crooked streets, narrow, dirty houses in which pitiful little people
are suffocating with <hi rend="italic">ennui</hi> and indolence, filling their
houses with a senseless, sleepy bustle.
</p><p>Here is "The Little Soul" running uneasily here and there, a
dear, gentle little woman who can love so much and so lavishly.
She may be stricken in the face and she will not even dare to groan
aloud, gentle slave.  Side by side with her sadly stands Olga from
"The Three Sisters."  She also loves much, and patiently obeys all
the caprices of the depraved and vulgar wife of her indolent brother;
the lives of her sisters are ruined before her eyes and she weeps and
cannot be of any help to anybody.  She has not even one vigorous
word of protest in her heart against all these iniquities.
</p><p>Here is the tearful Ranevskaia and the other former owners of
the "Cherry Grove"&mdash;egotistical like children and decrepit like old
people.  They have missed dying at the right time and are whining,
not able to comprehend what is happening around them&mdash;parasites,
without any power of finding a new support for themselves which
would keep them alive with its live blood.  The insignificant student
Trofimov, who can speak so nicely on the necessity of labor, idles
away his time, seeking a cure for his <hi rend="italic">ennui</hi> in his foolish
derision of Varia, who works her fingers to the bone for the benefit
of an indolent crew.
</p><p>Vershinin dreams of the beautiful life people will lead in three
hundred years, without seeing that all around him everything is
going to ruin; that under his very eyes Solenoy is ready, from sheer
foolishness and out of <hi rend="italic">ennui</hi>, to kill the pitiful Baron
Tuzendbach.
</p><p>Before the eyes of the reader pass an endless file of slaves of
love, of foolishness and indolence, of greed of good things of the
earth&mdash;slaves of a dark fear of life.  They walk with a vague fear and
fill life with incoherent speeches of the future, feeling that in the
present they are out of place.
</p><p>At times among the grayish crowd a shout is heard; this means
that Ivanov or Treplov at last understood what he ought to do and&mdash;died.
</p><p>Many of them dream so beautifully of how nice life will be
after two hundred years have passed, and no one even thinks of
putting to himself the simple question: But who will make that life
beautiful if we will spend all our time in idle dreams?
</p><p>Past all this crowd of helpless people went a great, wise,
attentive man; he looked upon all these tedious inhabitants of the
land of his birth and said with a sad smile, in a gentle but
reproachful tone, with a hopeless sadness in face and heart, in a
beautiful, sincere voice:
</p><p>"You live very badly, gentlemen!  It is a shame to live so!"</p>

<closer>
<dateline>ST. PETERSBURG, RUSSIA.</dateline>
</closer>

</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

