<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="GorProf"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="GorProf">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Womanliness as a Profession</title>
<title type="sort">womanliness as a profession</title>
<author>Gorren, Aline</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">27</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">GorProf</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476003</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Womanliness as a Profession</title>
<title type="sort">womanliness as a profession</title>
<author>Gorren, Aline</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner's Magazine</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1894-05">May 1894</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Volume 15</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Verification made against printed text</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1894">1894</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman and Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="article" id="d3">
<head>
Gorren, Aline.  "Womanliness as a Profession."
<lb/>
<hi rend="italic"> Scribner's Magazine</hi> 15 (May 1894): 610-615.
</head>

<pb n="610"/>

<p>THE question here discussed was one sure to arise, among us,
in America, sooner or later; and one, among the thoughtful, and
those who watch the signs of the future, also sure to arouse
interest of a special and peculiar kind.  With the increasing
facilities for the higher intellectual development now offered to
the American woman, along with her sisters the world over&mdash;only in
greater degree, and more generally, to the American woman than to
any other&mdash;the effect which such development would have upon her
essential womanliness was bound to become a matter of anxious
observation.  It is so become, in many quarters, now.  People are
trying to find out how the "higher education" affects the women of
other countries, and seeking to compare the notes and suggestions
thus gathered up with what is to be seen here.  Whether the higher
education shall be given the sex is no longer at all the affair
considered.  It is conceded that the thing must be done; the
experiment is made; the point now is to observe what will come
next.  For, certainly, unless we were very short-sighted, we were
prepared for the fact that something would come next.  One subjects
nothing organic to a changed environment with any sane impression
that it will remain exactly as it was before the change.
</p><p>At this present moment those who, with us, are giving
attention to this problem are divided into two camps.  The first
camp gives forth an utterance already grown familiar in a short
space of time.  Its tone is laudatory.  It testifies that women are
daily gaining in self-reliance; that the methodical training their
minds receive to fit them for professions and for business
positions, tends to render them, even in general matters, more
accurate in conception, more precise in execution, less under the
dominion of the sudden impulse and instinct, more capable of
reasoning, and of judging of things as reason, unimpassionedly,
presents them.  All these consequences of woman's higher
intellectual activities are pronounced to be unquestioned.  The
praise rises here and there to the key of enthusiasm.  If women
have, in this brief span, accomplished so much, what, it is asked,
will they not yet accomplish?  There is a joyful clamor in the air.
But there is the second camp; the second view.  And it is to be
remarked that there are some authoritative voices in this other and
quieter chorus; and that from thence there comes a vision which
seems to reach a little farther and deeper, which appears to have
an intuition for the substance and drift of things, rather than for
the temporary show of them.  In this second group of observers are
men who have had university training; men whose occupations are
literary, intellectual, artistic; and men of science; physicians
notably.  These men do not say so much about the new roads that
women are travelling; but they think more.  And it is beginning to
be borne in upon us that their thinking is touched with a doubt, a
delicate apprehension.  The man whose own intellectual faculties
<pb n="611"/>  have the ripeness and the flexible play that the largest
culture gives, is beginning to ask himself whether the
intellectualized American womanhood promises to be as <hi rend="italic">
interesting</hi> as womanhood always should be on this earth.  If he
happen to have studied the young girls who leave our women's
colleges, the young women who act as professors in the same, the
youthful doctresses in our large cities, he is conscious, on the
whole, of a faint, chill misgiving.  It is not that these exponents
of the new feminine ambition have not many most admirable results
to show in justification of that ambition.  It is that, with all
these admirable qualities, there is a lack of <hi rend="italic"> quality</hi>,
precisely; of <hi rend="italic"> the</hi> quality; the womanly quality.  Now, when such
a man as has been described recognizes this, he is apt to turn
cold, and to ask himself whether there be not something amiss in a
scheme of education which brings together all the elements of
influence, and then leaves out altogether the one magic ingredient
which shall set the forces of that influence free.  The physician,
on his part, does not concern himself with womanly magic; or with
the high spiritual and aesthetic uses of influence at all.  His
view goes to the roots of life.  But what he assures us that he
sees there, and the opinions which he derives from what he sees,
are not more encouraging.  The strain of the higher education, he
says, the preparation for collegiate courses, undermines, in
American girls, the bases of physical health.  Women whose
constitution has been subjected to this mental strain at a time
when it was unfit for divided labor, go through after-life, all too
often, as sufferers, incapable of fulfilling adequately the
essential functions of womanhood, of gaining or giving happiness as
wife or mother.  Moreover, the physician attributes, not directly
to too much intellectual knowledge, certainly, but indirectly to
the restlessness, the desire for personal freedom, instilled in
women by all the fresh departures taken by their sex, that
disinclination to assume the graver sacrifices of marriage, that
tendency to look upon its deeper significance as a cross, now
characterizing an increasingly large number of young wives, whose
interests are social rather than mental.  With the first contention
of our physician it is not in the purpose of these remarks to deal;
excepting in so far as to mention that knowledge of the lives of
European girls, who have gone through a course of study as exacting
as any demanded here, discloses no such examples of invalidism as
the medical man would point to among our women.  With the second
contention&mdash;that the modern American woman, of the most cultivated
classes, and in the largest cities, cares less and less to be a
mother, cares even perhaps less and less to be a wife, these
remarks have, however, to deal; for the imputation meets the
disappointment of the university man, of the American of culture,
on the same ground, and the conclusions of both agree as to the
same fact&mdash;the absence, namely, of the womanly in the
representative American woman of the moment.
</p><p>At this juncture it may be well to look a little more closely
at what is understood by womanliness.  Here we are confronted at
once by the perception that a different meaning would be attached
to the word, according as it would be used by the peoples of the
Latin extraction and by ourselves.  To those peoples, who have the
collective-social ideal, in opposition to our Anglo-Saxon
individualist ideal, the value, the preciousness, and the intrinsic
efficacy of all things must lie in the greater or less degree of
thoroughness and perfection with which they evolve into visible act
and function the principle of diversity, of specialization,
inherent in their being.  The ideal of the social races has been
defined as "the ideal of the equality of individuals in a graduated
order of functions;" and our own individualist ideal as "the ideal
of the equality of individuals in a general equality of functions."
For a Frenchman, an Italian, a Spaniard, then, womanliness in a
woman means personification, in every individual case, of those
abstract conceptions which the feminine principle eternally
typifies.  On the one hand, womanliness will consist, therefore, in
a constant, passive charm, the human expression, as it were,
<pb n="612"/>
of the silent allurement which nature has made, throughout all
her orders, the typical attitude of the feminine.  This, so to put
it, is the physical characteristic.  On the other hand, womanliness
will mean divination of mysteries not seen by sight, nor
apprehended by reason, but conveyed to woman, instinctively, by her
closer contact with the most sacred and occult operations of
nature, and reacting from her upon man in the form of an ethereal
stimulant to finer endeavor, a vague, high promise of divine
rewards.  This is the spiritual characteristic.  The Latin is, to
both this physical and this spiritual characteristic of
womanliness, more sensitive than the Anglo-Saxon.  Wherefore it
happens that he respects women both less and more than the Anglo-Saxon.  The notion of womanliness of the Englishman, the American,
is more neutral, has less of either extreme.  The element of
allurement, of charm, does not count so much for him&mdash;whereby it
chances that, from certain aspects, his civilization is the
cleaner.  The spiritual characteristic predominates over the
physical in his ideal.  The womanly woman is the good mother, the
devoted wife, the gentle sister, the quiet guardian of the hearth-fire.  Yet she is not so much the holder of those mysteries of
which we spoke, and thus her position, while never so low, perhaps,
as it is possible for it to become with the Latin peoples, is
never, either, in some senses, so high.  If the best definition of
womanliness that one can arrive at be, in brief, that it is the
consciousness in women of their difference from men&mdash;and there is
none, so far as one can see, more adequate, one is inclined to
acknowledge that the idea of the Latin is at least the fuller, the
more complete.  It was to the most happy fusion of the charm on the
one side, and of the spiritual influence on the other, to which
were due some of those Frenchwomen of the eighteenth century,
which, even to the Anglo-Saxon, seem a type of attractive, of
womanly women.  But, be this as it may, the Frenchman, the Italian,
holds fast to his belief in specialization, in the separate, the
"graduated order of functions."  For him to conceive of any plan of
training or influence which should make women more like men in the
essential attributes of character&mdash;which should do away, at a blow,
with the subtlest and deepest distinction in nature&mdash;would be to go
counter to the direction of his entire civilization.  Our
individualist civilization, with its equality of individuals "in an
equality of functions," its pervading feeling that what one man can
do another man can do also&mdash;and, <hi rend="italic"> ergo</hi>, that what one man can do
a woman can likewise&mdash;tends, on the contrary, in every way to
efface, instead of emphasizing, the difference in the social and
mental attributes of the sexes.  In America, where Anglo-Saxon
individualism has reached its supreme expression, there is also
found most strongly the trend of equalization between women and
men.  All this, in substance, has been said before.  But what has
not been sufficiently noted is the present want of logic in
referring to advanced education, a lack of womanliness in American
women, when the deficiency, if it exist, is the result of the
combined elements of our social life.
</p><p>The thoughtful man who has misgivings looks over to France,
and asks what the outcome of advanced feminine education is there;
whether women there, under its effect, tend to become less womanly,
less wifely, less motherly, less capable of the domesticities, and
less interested in them.  His query may, so far, be rapidly
answered in the negative.  Moreover, it is the least likely of
things that it ever will be answered otherwise.  M. Jules Simon,
than whom no one in France has done more for the cause of the
higher instruction of women, recently wrote of his experience in
obtaining a minor decoration for a certain young woman, whose
deserts such official recognition seemed to be, in terms which in
their entirety one would like to reproduce on this page.  After
pronouncing himself as averse to the idea of decorating women, on
the plea that, not the act of conferring the decoration, but the
desire for that public distinction in the woman herself, offended
some instinct in him, he owns that he finally yielded to the
pressure brought upon him by the <pb n="613"/>  young woman's friends, and
ended by becoming as keen about the project as they were, and,
putting into play such official machinery as he could control, by
obtaining the coveted order, which, executed in the best manner by
the jeweller <hi rend="italic"> a la mode</hi>, was duly placed beneath the candidate's
napkin at dinner.  During the little function that followed
innocent enthusiasm ran high, and tears lay close to smiles.  But,
on the morrow, a knock at the door of M. Simon ushered in the young
woman, who, a little shy, a little deprecating, deposited the order
on his desk.  She had decided not to accept it.  Unqualified
resentment on the part of her sponsor, who sees himself made
ridiculous, the fruit of all his official efforts thrown back upon
him without ceremony.  But the young woman was saying gently,
appealingly: <hi rend="italic">" Mon parrain</hi>, have we many greater painters than
Rosa Bonheur?"  "No."  "Have there been greater instances of
heroism on the battle-field than have been displayed by some of our
Sisters of Charity, our hospital nurses?  Then, until the great
orders&mdash;the greatest orders, the men's orders, go to them, I must
leave this here."  And, detecting the softening in her old friend's
eye, she tapped him prettily on the arm with her glove.  "I saw, my
sponsor," smiling, "the daintiest of little bracelets in a shop-window.  If you were to buy me that, instead?"
</p><p>Our own women of progressive ideas may not think well of this
charming anecdote, perhaps.  But it is a little story, perfectly
illustrative of the woman of the Latin races, who, to-day, has
entered the advanced movement.  It defines the attitude with which
she holds herself there.  You meet, in Paris, a girl who has taken
the highest degrees that the Republic confers.  You find her like
any other <hi rend="italic"> jeune fille</hi>; unassuming, saying little, home-loving;
and, you hear, very thoroughly drilled in household duties.  There
is no restlessness in her, no straining, apparently, after new
social conditions.  She fits into the framework of her surroundings
quite, it would seem, as she would have done before the higher
instruction was thought of.  There are traces of a state of things
more familiar to us, in Italian and French life, to be sure.  But
they are to be met in the great social world, where Anglomania
prevails, bringing with it the mannish brusquerie and emancipation
of the modern woman who aims to be a "good fellow."  And this is
not the woman whose influence is deepest upon the national life
anywhere.
</p><p>Nor should one make the mistake of supposing that if advanced
education does not, in the Latin countries, impair the womanliness
of the mass of women who enjoy its benefits, while here, in
America, that undesirable result appears to be achieved, the reason
is to be sought in the different courses of instruction which may
be pursued in the two cases.  There are such distinctions, and they
have their effect.  But the real cause lies in the two different
civilizations, the two different environments.  No amount of
instruction for them, unless the whole national spirit of France
should be changed, will ever, it is to be surmised, lessen in
Frenchwomen the keen instinct of a special function&mdash;social,
spiritual, emotional.  One may <hi rend="italic"> a priori</hi> suppose that wider
knowledge, and a firmer grasp of facts, may indeed broaden and
deepen, and philosophize, this instinct, so that it might be deemed
possible that the first contributions to those sociological studies
which, in the natural distribution of labor, will eventually fall
to the share of women, and for which they are especially fitted,
will come from the highly trained and intellectual woman of the
Latin race, rather than from her Anglo-Saxon cousin, be she, on her
side, ever so highly trained, and intellectual likewise.  If the
latter shall be found to have taken a false departure, to be on the
wrong track, to be wasting time in seeking to establish an
impossible "equality of functions" between herself and the other
sex, we shall be manifestly unjust in placing the whole brunt of
the evil on the new development of her brain powers.  Education
only intensifies the predispositions implanted by the racial ideal.
If, in America, it should make women less womanly, it is that our
American life fosters germs that tend to that result from the
initial stages of growth. <pb n="614"/>
</p><p>The first effect of our American plan of coeducation, and of
the large liberty of intercourse not only allowed to our girls and
boys, but thrust upon them, is to do away, so far as may be, with
the feeling of separateness.  There is nothing in the callow love-making that springs from this juvenile association that is likely
to make a girl deeply conscious of her womanhood.  She is, in the
tone of her thought and life, not very different from the young
boys to whom she either does, or does not, multitudinously engage
herself.  This is what we prefer.  We think it saner, healthier.
That point is not here discussed.  But it is certain that we cannot
eat our cake and have it too.  Furthermore, if the manner of the
girl's relations with the other sex, at the beginning of her
career, is not such as would be calculated to develop the sense of
her difference from men, which we are agreed is the essence of the
quality of womanliness, neither are the later conditions that
surround her in society to make good the deficiency.  Practically,
we have, in America, no social intercourse between men and women.
After the unripe boy-and-girl period has been passed, and both
sexes have entered into consciousness of themselves, each goes very
much its own way.  The woman of the new fashion meets men in
business offices, in the varied exercise of her new avocations, but
it is as one good comrade meets another.  The married woman, among
the large mass of Americans, has, for masculine society, her
husband.  This, again, is as we wish it to be.  But it may be that
an unnecessary alarm, a false Puritanism, too much seek, with us,
to prevent the natural, mutually improving intercourse of mature
men and women.  Those attractive and womanly women of the French
salons were what they were because the men of their time made them
so.  They stocked their wits, not from books, but from the talk of
the men who gathered about them to enjoy an interchange of ideas.
They learned HOW TO LIVE from life itself.  They had the subtle
intuition of the relative values and positions of things that is
the fruit of the highest feminine culture; the <hi rend="italic"> connaissances
generales</hi>, which a French author pronounces indispensable to any
womanly effectiveness.  Americans rest too exclusively in the fact
that some of these women were not morally irreproachable.  Others
were, and these wielded equal influence, equal charm.  To-day, in
France, the meeting of men and women in society, for the
interchange of ideas, is said to be less easy and prevalent than in
days gone by.  A recent writer grieves over "the malicious wind
that seems to scatter and disperse" those groups which people would
like to form for the purpose of rational and agreeable talk.  But
enough of this facility of meeting remains to educate the
Frenchwoman in the consciousness of herself; in the understanding
of her weak and her strong points; enough to form her, in short, in
the profession of womanliness; that profession which is, at the end
of the ends, the one absolutely essential, the one which,
unmastered, makes all others go for naught.
</p><p>Obviously, with the conditions for it thus failing, this
profession will not be brought to the same perfect pitch with us;
and not even according to the Anglo-Saxon ideal of womanliness,
which we have seen to be a less complex one than the Latin, one
more quiet, more intimate.  For there are social conditions, or,
more precisely, emotional conditions&mdash;here we have the great
word!&mdash;that make women womanly, and keep them even so in the
American conception of the guardian of the hearth-fire, and the
gentle and steadfast helpmate.  If these be sufficiently strong,
the highest stimulus that will be given to woman's brains can, in
all safety, be trusted never to make her wish to wander very far
astray from her initial missions.  But they are, as it appears, not
sufficiently strong in America.  And of this American men cannot
rightfully complain, since what they are now beginning to see about
them, and to deprecate, is first the consequence of their own mode
of life, which they could alter if they chose, and second, the
consequence of their national temperament, which, of course, they
cannot alter.  For the average American male is a cold creature,
outside of his business and his politics; one who courts <pb n="615"/>
and marries, by instinct, but in whom apprehension of the heights
and depths of these delicate matters is as yet in the rudimentary
stage.  This lack of the emotional in the atmosphere with which he
surrounds himself reacts perceptibly on the American woman.  He
glories in it himself.  But there are times when he does not love
its results so well.  It has been deplored that the American girl
should show so un-American a fancy for marrying into foreign
nobilities.  Titles are supposed to be the word of the incantation,
in all these cases.  It is soothing to the American to tell himself
this; but it is not a conclusion borne out by the facts.  Any
knowledge at all thorough of these international marriages
discloses too many instances in which the affections are involved,
as well as the ambitions.  The American girl may smile at the
prospect of the name and the blazon, and the bridegroom consider
carefully the settlements that will come with the bride.  And still
this does not shut out the fact that the two young people may be
very much in love with each other.  Some of these marriages are
unhappy.  So are some marriages among Americans.  But it would be
foolish to refuse to recognize the many times when they are, on the
contrary, extremely happy.  As a lover, the European has several
points in his favor beyond the American; and the American girl has
never been slow to find this out.
</p><p>An Italian, a man of wide and generous culture, was given,
some time since, several of the novels of Mr. Howells to read.
After absorbing them attentively he inquired if the women therein
portrayed would, by Americans, be considered representative.  He
was told that, taking the average American woman the land through,
they might so be considered.  <hi rend="italic">" Che tipi!</hi>&mdash;What curious types;"
was his thoughtful comment, in a moment.  "It must be in some part
the fault of your American men.  Your women do not seem to have
received the higher cultivation of the sentiments, of the
emotions."  What he felt was the lack of measure and harmony, and
the presence of that which was either hysterical and crude, or bald
and partly sexless, in the feminine nature dissected by Mr.
Howells's pen.
</p><p>For there is a culture of the emotions.  And so long as nature
persists in developing the centre part of women's brain less than
that of men, and the back part more, there will be some good reason
why this culture should be an important matter.  Nothing is brought
to our consciousness more clearly, in these last years of the
century, than the sense that the study of the emotions must indeed
soon descend from the vague and cloudy regions which hitherto have
been its abode, into its rightful place under the light of modern
experimental knowledge.  The latest drift of physiology, of
psychiatry, points steadily in this direction.  We are beginning to
divine that the passions have their laws and their hygiene; even as
the delicate problems of the will may some day be solved with
scientific exactitude.  Upon these matters&mdash;never second, in life,
to the importance of the pure idea&mdash;we look, with the advancement
of the mental differentiation of the sexes to see the women of the
future throw the clearest illumination.  Already those whom we feel
to be typical in the best way, have intuitions here transcending
those of men.  Meanwhile, if the Anglo-Saxon woman make the mistake
of supposing that the most extreme development possible to her
along the lines of the intellect can free her from the claims which
look to her from the emotional side of life, it is perhaps not a
fatal one.  It is by way of intellectual knowledge that many women,
after some uncertain stumbling, may enter, in the fullest sense,
into the right comprehension of the great law of specialization.
</p>
</div1></body></text></TEI.2>
