<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="GriIndi"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="GriIndi">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Indian on the Reservation</title>
<title type="sort">indian on the reservation</title>
<author>Grinnell, George Bird</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">52</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">GriIndi</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476010</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Indian on the Reservation</title>
<title type="sort">indian on the reservation</title>
<author>George Bird Grinnell</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 83, pp. 255-267</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the
text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-04">April 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Timothy Jarrett, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>TEI markup</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="essay" id="d3">

<pb n="255"/>

<p>WHEN an Indian tribe had given up fighting, surrendered to the
whites, and taken up a reservation life, its position was that of a group
of men in the stone age of development, suddenly brought into contact
with modern methods, and required on the instant to renounce all they
had ever been taught and all they had inherited; to alter their practices of
life, their beliefs, and their ways of thought; and to conform to manners
and ways representing the highest point reached by civilization.  It is
beyond the power of our imagination to grasp the actual meaning to any
people of such a condition of things.  History records no similar case
with which we can compare it.  And if it is hard for us to comprehend
such a situation, what must it have been for the savage to understand it,
and, still more, to act it out?</p>
<p>On no two reservations was life precisely the same, yet on all of
them it was the same in this: that it was different from old times; that
the people no longer came and went at their own pleasure, but were
confined by metes and bounds, and were subject to the orders of persons
whom they themselves had not chosen to obey as chiefs.  With the
irksomeness of confinement came a change in physical conditions and
health.  The toils of the warpath and the hunting trail had ceased.  Men
who had been active in all the ordinary pursuits of their earlier life had
now no occupation.  They took no exercise, but sat about grieving over
the good old times which were gone, and brooding over the
present.</p>
<p>Cut off from their old free life of roving hunters, the Indians were
forced to endure an existence without interest or occupation, and to see
their people, old and young, dying about them faster than they had ever
died in former days.  They saw before them no prospect save of an
indefinite continuance of the same state of things.  They had nothing to
look forward to nor anything to hope for.  They were like men sentenced
to life imprisonment, with blank walls all about them,&mdash;walls which they
could never hope to pass.  Yet, as the years went by, the Indians grew
more or less accustomed to these miseries and felt them less acutely,
though to the older men and women memory still made life a bitter
thing.  But the people came to regard the hardships as unavoidable, and
accepted them with a sad stoicism as a part of the new and
incomprehensible situation.</p>
<p>The Indians had been brought to a reservation and were to be
civilized.  Let us see how they were handled,&mdash;what sort of men were set
to instruct these grown-up children; to persuade, to urge, and to
command them to do white men's work; to perform the difficult and
delicate task of changing wild savages and roaming hunters to civilized
laborers.  To be successful, such work calls for infinite patience and
tact, together with the constant realization that the tasks required of these
people are wholly new and uncomprehended by them.  Before they can
perform them, they must understand why and how their work is to be
done.</p>
<p>It is obvious that the Indians can be taught the white man's ways
only by actual contact with white men, and that this contact can be had
only with those living on the reservation to which the Indians are
confined.  Such white men are the employees of the Indian Bureau and
the missionaries.</p>
<p>The task of civilizing the Indians really depends almost wholly
upon the agent who is set over them.  He represents the Great Father; he
alone has

<pb n="256"/>  authority.  It is for him to explain to them the benefits
of toil, to reward the industrious, to punish the refractory, to encourage
the unsuccessful, and to direct the ambitious.  He can lead the tribe to
see that work is necessary, and can induce them to work; or he can let
the Indians take their own way, and face their problems without
assistance.  If he has enthusiasm for his work and a real desire to see the
people advance, he can infuse into them some part of his own energy,
and make them believe that actual benefits to themselves and to their
children will follow their efforts.</p>
<p>An Indian agent has absolute control of affairs on his reservation,
subject only to the approval of the Department of the Interior at
Washington, which two or three times a year may send out an inspector
to look after him.  His position is one of great responsibility, for he has
to administer a business representing each year from $50,000 to
$200,000.  His power on the reservation is more nearly absolute than
anything else that we in this country know of.  He has not the authority
to order out his Indians to instant execution, but in practice this is the
only power that he does not possess.  Over property, liberty, and the
actions of every-day life he has absolute authority.  No Indian can
receive food, no Indian can obtain a tool, no Indian can live in his home,
unless the agent is willing.  He holds in the hollow of his hand the
welfare of the tribe and of each one of its individuals.</p>
<p>The man who bears these responsibilities and is clothed with these
powers over his fellow men should be of high character and good
abilities, such a one as would be chosen for the manager of a
considerable business.  He should feel the responsibility of his position,
and not be satisfied merely to get along as easily as possible and to draw
his salary regularly.  The good agent really stands in the relation of a
parent toward his Indians; and as a father instructs, punishes, and
rewards his children, so the agent should firmly, but kindly, govern the
people who are under him.  They recognize this relation, and often speak
of the agent as their father.  In the ordinary pursuits of life, a man
qualified by training and temperament for such a place would receive a
good salary; he ought to receive it here,&mdash;at least thrice the pittance that
is now paid to Indian agents.  Such a man ought to be retained in office
so long as he would remain, and should not be turned out with the
coming in of each new administration.</p>
<p>But the Indian service long constituted an important part of the
spoils which until recently belonged wholly to the victors in the political
contest.  The position of agent is still a part of these spoils, and at
present most of the offices are portioned out to the Senators and
Congressmen of the various states.  There are a few army officers acting
as Indian agents,&mdash;among whom there has rarely been one who was
incompetent,&mdash;but a large share of the civilian officials have been
political appointees, minor ward or county politicians who obtain the
office as a reward for vote-getting, or else "good fellows" who have
failed in every business that they have undertaken, and now fall back on
this place for a living.  Men of this class cannot be expected to care for
their people; often they are concerned only for their pay and their
perquisites.  Perhaps, in a vague way, they advise the Indians "to follow
the white man's road," and then leave them to find out for themselves
what that road is and whither it leads.  Some Indian agents are men of
high character, but none are well paid; for they receive only from $1500
to $2000 per annum,&mdash;small compensation for the never ending worries
and detail of their position, to say nothing of the isolation of life at an
Indian agency.  The unwisdom of paying so poorly men who have such
important work to do has long

<pb n="257"/>  been understood, and many years ago, during President
Grant's administration, some of the religious dominations, to which the
control of the Indians had been intrusted, chose as Indian agents men
fitted for the task, and themselves added to the government salary a
further compensation from their own funds.</p>
<p>The position of Indian agent is one full of annoyances, full of
temptations.  He should be a man of patience and shrewdness, kindly yet
firm; a man of character, absolutely truthful.  He must be willing to
make over and over again the same elaborate explanations of the simplest
matters; to resist attempts to impose on or to frighten him; to take a
decided stand and never recede from it; to incur the lasting hostility of
the white men, Indians, and men of mixed blood who received special
favors from the previous agent, and who now expect the same from him.
Most agents appear to imagine that their position is one which calls
especially for office work, and much of their time, therefore, is spent in
the office, overseeing the making out of papers; giving out orders for
flour, sugar, coffee, sacks, and other things requested by the Indians;
acting, in fact, much like a retail country storekeeper.  The truth is that
an agent should spend the greater part of his time in the saddle or in his
wagon, traveling about among his people; learning the personality of
each; finding out how each family lives, what improvements the man has
made on his place, what property he has, how he is taking care of it and
what use he is putting it to.  The agent thus learns what each man
requires and how far he is deserving.  He also appears to his Indians to
be taking an active interest in their welfare and to be more or less in
sympathy with them; and there is nothing that an Indian appreciates
more, nothing which is to him a stronger incentive to try to do well,
than the exhibition of such sympathy.</p>
<p>The agent is assisted by a force of clerks, farmers, and other
employees, each of whom is brought into closest contact with the
Indians, and thus may wield a tremendous influence for good or for evil.
These men, as a rule, take their tone from the agent.  If he is energetic
and enthusiastic, they follow his lead at the pace he sets.  If he is rough,
brutal, and profane in his dealing with the Indians, they are so too.  If he
is dishonest, they are dishonest.  If he is weak, a stronger man soon
gains an ascendency over him, and becomes practically the ruling power
on the reservation.  Often the clerks appear to regard it as an imposition
that they have to attend to the Indians' wants, and are harsh in their
intercourse with them, cursing them freely and treating them with the
greatest indignity.  Often, too, the agency farmers, whose immediate
duty it is to instruct the people in the pursuits of civilization, do anything
rather than that.  They potter about the agency, or they are stablemen, or
they work in the blacksmith shop, or put up new buildings, or paint and
whitewash old ones, or spend much of their time at the butchering and
the issue,&mdash;do anything, in fact, except to teach the Indians farming and
oversee their work.</p>
<p>The United States army has given us by far the best class of men
who have ever held the position of Indian agents; they have usually had a
training in military business, and work on a system; they have no private
ends to serve, and no affiliations with the white population adjacent to
the reservation.  When detailed to the service, they go to the posts
assigned them to do their duty as they understand it; that duty being to
make the Indians self-supporting and civilized, to protect them from
white aggression, and, in general, to govern them according to the
principles of justice and right.  This view is different from that held by
the average Indian agent, and so the work done by army officers is very
different from that of most civilians, and

<pb n="258"/>  very much better.  Among the civilians are notable
exceptions to the rule,&mdash;a few men who have done work that could hardly
have been excelled; but for all that such men are the exceptions; the rule
remains.  Among the army officers, on the other hand, a careless or
incompetent agent is rare.</p>
<p>First and last, much has been done for the Indians by missionaries
sent out by the various denominations.  Many are earnest men who try
hard to do their whole duty by the Indians; but a missionaries, after all,
are only men, some of them are careless, lazy, and inefficient, while a
considerable portion lack any understanding of how to handle men.  Of
the least efficient among them it may be said that if they do no good,
they at least do little harm, while there are many whose services to
Christianity and to civilization are very great.  I have in mind an army
chaplain whose work among some Indians who incidentally came within
the sphere of his influence was so effective that it will never be forgotten
by them.  The man was a true follower of the Master, and instead of
attempting at once to force upon the Indians the acceptance of religious
doctrines, he showed them only sympathy and friendliness.  When he
had won their good will, they readily gave ear to the simple religious
precepts that he taught.  Admirable missionary work is done, too, by the
Roman Catholic priests and sisters who are stationed on many of the
Western reservations.  They accomplish in a silent, unsuspected way a
great deal of good.</p>
<p>It may obviously be objected to all purely religious work among
the Indians that it is caring for the soul before the body is cared for.  It
is hard for a man to pray with a good heart when he is hungry, nor is it
easy to concentrate the attention on the doctrine of the Trinity when his
little ones are crying for food.  Before the Indian can be Christianized he
must be civilized and taught how to earn his living; after he has learned
this lesson, and has acquired some of the mental habits of civilized
people, the ground will have been prepared for the sowing of the seeds
of religion.</p>
<p>There is a practical form of missionary work, seldom seen, which
cannot be too highly applauded.  I have seen it practiced on the
Blackfoot reservation by the Rev. E. S. Dutcher.  This good man
preaches on Sunday to those who come to hear him in the little church
which his own hands built, and on other days of the week he takes his
tools&mdash;for he has learned the carpenter's trade&mdash;and goes about over the
reservation, helping the Indians to hang the doors and set the window
frames in their houses, or to set the fence posts and stretch the wire for
their pasture fences.  Often his wife goes with him; and while he works
out of doors with the men, she is busy within, teaching the women how
to bake good bread or make the family clothing.  Missionary work such
as this, where practical religion is made a part of the daily life, and soul
and mind and body are cared for at once, accomplishes lasting
results.</p>
<p>For many years good people have been endeavoring to devise plans
which should at once transform the Indian from a rover and a warrior to
a sedentary laborer.  Men of various trades and professions, from the
soldier to the theologian, have studied the Indian problem, and many
different methods have been suggested for rendering the wild man
civilized and self-supporting.  The author of each has had most perfect
confidence that his remedy was the one certain to cure all ills brought to
the Indians by contact with the white man.  Some of these projects have
had fair trial; yet the progress of the race has not been so rapid as to
justify the faith that any of these means of civilization&mdash;except when
engineered with unusual energy and wisdom&mdash;would do the work

<pb n="259"/>  claimed for it, while in some cases the experiments
have brought disaster to the Indians.</p>
<p>The sincerity and earnestness of a majority of such philanthropists
cannot be doubted, but in all their reasoning about Indians there has been
one point of weakness: they had no personal knowledge of the inner life
of the people they were trying to help.  Their theories appear to have
assumed that Indians are precisely like white men, except that their
minds are blank and plastic, ready to receive any impression that may be
inscribed on them.  These friends of the Indians had little acquaintance
with Indian character; they did not appreciate the human nature of the
people.  They did not know that their minds were already occupied by a
multitude of notions and beliefs that were firmly fixed there,&mdash; rooted
and grounded by an inheritance of a thousand years.  Still less did they
comprehend the Indian's intense conservatism, the tenacity with which he
clings to the beliefs which have been handed down to him by uncounted
generations.</p>
<p>The plans of the philanthropists who were anxious to benefit the
race were based on the general proposition that all Indians should
become farmers.  As most civilized men earn their living by tilling the
soil, they took it for granted that the Indian could do the same, and must
become civilized in that way.  They were profoundly ignorant of the
surroundings of the Indian and of the land he dwelt in, and did not know
that over a very large part of the West no crops can be grown unless the
soil is well irrigated.  They seem to have imagined the great plains a
fertile country&mdash; perhaps like the prairies of Illinois&mdash;where, if land were
ploughed and seed sown, bounteous harvests would be sure to follow.
They did not understand that many of the Indian reservations consist of
the most arid and barren lands that the sun ever shone one,&mdash;a waterless,
desolate, soul-withering region, whose terrors are incomprehensible to
those who have never traveled over it.  They did not know that many of
the reservations are situated in the land of thirst, where water is the one
priceless thing, and its lack the greatest horror.  Many years and much
effort have therefore been wasted in trying to teach the Indian how to
raise crops in regions where white farmers could not possibly make a
living; yet, up to a short time ago, the authorities, clinging to the
antiquated notions of those who would make all Indians agriculturists,
continued to insist that the Indians should sow in the desert, even though
they could never hope to reap.  Only within a few years has it been
learned that in a country adapted for stock-raising Indians should raise
stock, and in a farming country they should farm.  Yet ever since these
tribes have been known to us, the Pueblos and others, who have always
practiced irrigation, and the Navajoes, who have long been herdsmen,
have furnished examples of this adaptation to environment, and have
shown us that different peoples should be treated according to the
different conditions which surround them.</p>
<p>One civilizing idea has by this time become impressed on all the
Indians of this country: they comprehend to-day that they must work if
they would live.  The time when food, a blanket, a gun, and some
ammunition satisfied the Indians' wants has gone, never to return.
Association with civilized people has brought the need for the things of
civilization, which can only be had for money.  The Indians see that,
under the new conditions, money is as necessary to them as it is to the
white men.  They recognize that the government will not support them
forever.  So they are intensely anxious to work, to earn money.  On
many reservations they wear out the patience of the agent by continually
asking him for work, when he has no work to give them.  On the
reservation of the Northern

<pb n="260"/>  Cheyennes, for the last two or three years, there has
been an opportunity for a few men to secure work as laborers on the
great irrigating ditch in course of construction on the adjacent Crow
reservation.  So long as men were wanted for this work, the Cheyenne
agent was kept busy giving out passes to his people who wished to labor
on the ditch.  All the able-bodied men in the tribe would have gone, if
there had been work for all.  On the Blackfoot reservation, agents have
told me of having fifteen or twenty applications a day for the job of
going into the mountains to cut wood and haul it away for fuel.  The
Indians are ready to hire out to any one who will pay them, and they
will work as hard, as long, and as faithfully as any laborers.  Usually,
there is little or no work to be had.  Even the students who come back
from the Eastern boarding schools equipped with knowledge of English
and a trade, and fitted for a place in the blacksmith's or wheelwright's
shop or for a position as industrial teacher at the agency day school, are
only occasionally employed about the agency in the various positions
which they might fill.</p>
<p>This, then, is one of the chief obstacles to the Indian's progress,
the difficulty of earning a livelihood.  After he has succeeded in doing
this, he must learn how to keep his money when he gets it,&mdash;in other
words, the lesson of thrift.  The old-time Indian was hospitable,
open-handed, and generous, to the last degree.  The new Indian must
learn to be close-fisted.  As he progresses toward self-support, it is not
very hard for him to accumulate horses, cattle, tools, and furniture; but
to deal with money merely as money is as yet a very serious problem.
If he has money, it burns in his pocket, and he feels that he must spend
it.  The time will come when Indians will have bank accounts, but that
time&mdash;except among the civilized tribes&mdash;has not yet been reached.</p>
<p>Under the most favorable circumstances&mdash;with instruction and
encouragement&mdash;it is hard enough for the Indian to change himself into a
patient laborer, willing to toil day after day at his unpleasing task.  Too
often, in addition to the difficulties which are inevitable, his
advancement is retarded or stopped by his being robbed of his lands by
methods which he is powerless to resist.  The courts protect citizens; but
the Indian is not a citizen, and nothing protects him.  Congress has the
sole power to order how he shall live, and where.  Most thoughtful
people believe that in the past the Indians have been greatly wronged by
the whites, but imagine that this is no longer the case.  Let us see.</p>

<p>The greatest corruption of our Indian affairs took place not very
long after the close of the war of the Rebellion.  In those days, to be an
Indian agent, trader, or contractor was to be on a highroad to fortune, if
one made the most of his advantages.  The contracts for supplies of
every sort were in the hands of a small group of men, who controlled
them all, and, what was more important, to a great extent controlled the
agents and employees of the Indian Bureau, in the field.  Attacks on the
Indian ring were made from time to time with more or less success,
reforms in the service and its methods were gradually introduced, and
the opportunities for robbery grew less.  The actual wholesale stealing of
the food and clothing provided by the government has ceased, for the
most part, or has degenerated into petty pilfering.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, methods are still found by which the money of the
Indians may be diverted from its proper objects to find its way into the
pockets of white men.  One of these is the hiring of unnecessary
attorneys for them.  There are on file before the Court of Claims in
Washington many thousands of dollars' worth of claims for alleged
Indian depredations, and suits against various Indian tribes and the
United States are being

<pb n="261"/>  carried on before that court.  These suits are defended
by the Attorney-General's office, and any judgment recovered runs
against both the Indian tribe and the United States.  If the tribe has no
money to pay a judgment rendered against it, the United States must do
so.  But of late years most of the treaties made with Indians provide that
none of the money appropriated under the treaty shall be used to pay
depredation claims, and the ratification by Congress of an agreement of
this nature puts the money of the tribe out of the reach of the Court of
Claims, and so protects the Indians.  Moreover, under a ruling of the
Interior Department, made a number of years ago, it was determined that
no tribes, except two, have any money available for the payment of such
claims, and this ruling has hitherto been sustained.  Nevertheless, it is a
form of legal industry recognized in Washington, for a lawyer to visit an
agency and inform the chiefs that claims amounting to many thousands
of dollars have been filed against the tribe, and that they may have to
pay these claims.  By alarming them about the safety of their money, it
is not difficult for the lawyer to induce them to make a contract retaining
him as their attorney to defend the suits.  Contracts of this kind are
invalid until approved by the Secretary of the Interior, who is constantly
pestered by the lawyers and their political friends to give his assent to
them.  But since the Indians have no funds which can be used to pay
such judgments rendered against them, since the law specifically forbids
the use of their funds for such a purpose, and since, therefore, they can
have no money interest whatever in the suits, it is manifestly a great
wrong that these contracts should be approved by the department, and
that the money appropriated for the Indians' support should go to fill the
pockets of lawyers.  Yet I have in mind a single law firm in Washington
which, by its contracts with different tribes of Indians, who are protected
by their treaty and so in no wise need attorneys, is likely to receive this
year over $8000,&mdash;and for doing nothing.  There was absolutely nothing
for them to do.  The defense they pretended to give the Indian did not
require.  There was nothing for them to defend him against.  The real
defense he needs is against the lawyers themselves.  It is hardly
necessary to add that a large proportion of the depredation claims filed
against the different tribes are barefacedly fraudulent.</p>
<p>Indians are now subject to encroachments, conducted, not by an
Indian ring, but by the government, which, in its ignorance, does injury
to this race as serious as ever was done by any group of individuals.
These encroachments are begun by white people living near the Indians,
who covet the land possessed by them, and usually secured to them by
pledges of the government's faith, and who endeavor to gain possession
of it by lawful means; that is, by inducing the government to break that
faith and violate those pledges.</p>
<p>Wherever its reservation may be, an Indian tribe is bitterly
opposed by local popular feeling.  Its people are hated because they are
Indians, and envied because they hold lands that white men might own.
In thought, if not in words, its white neighbors say of a tribe, "Cut it
down; why cumbereth it the ground?"  Local prejudice and local greed
combine to force the Indians&mdash;who have no representative in
Congress&mdash;from their homes, where perhaps they may have made some
improvements, and to which often they are deeply attached.  The people
who wish them removed do not care where they are taken, if only it is
away, somewhere else.  Their object is to secure the land which they
hope to have thrown open to settlement.</p>
<p>This is how the plan of expulsion is carried out.  A treaty having
been made with a tribe of Indians, a certain tract of country is assigned
to them as a permanent

<pb n="262"/> home.  After a time the land near them becomes settled,
and the white people crowd about the reservation.  The reservation may
be good for something: it may be imagined to contain mines of coal or
precious metals, or it may be a good cattle range, or the land may have
valuable water on it.  When this is the case, the people living in the
neighborhood begin to urge upon their delegate, or their Congressman,
or their Senator, the importance of moving the Indians, and throwing
open their reservation to settlement.  Both Senator and Congressman
naturally wish to oblige their constituents, and forthwith a bill is
introduced or a section is added to the Indian Appropriation Bill,
providing for the desired removal.  Most members of Congress, knowing
nothing of the rights or wrongs of the measure, take it for granted that
the local member must know what ought to be done, and are very likely
to assent to it.</p>
<p>Less than ten years ago, I was present on a reservation in the
Indian Territory when a commission was negotiating with the Indians to
induce them to take their lands in severalty, and to sell the surplus.  The
commissioners made no secret of the fact that the administration had
urged them to carry through the sale, because at the next election they
wished to go before the people with the statement that they had thrown
open to settlement by the public a certain number of acres of Indian
reservations.  This statement would influence many votes in the West; it
would be a good political cry.  The negotiations began, and by
persuasion, promises, and at last by threats, about one third of the
Indians were induced to sign the agreement.  After that signatures came
in very slowly.  The commissioners hired their interpreters to assist them
to obtain signers.  The attorneys, who claimed that they had been
retained by the Indians to defend their rights, worked hard to induce the
people to sign.  These attorneys were working on a contingent fee,&mdash;"the
usual ten per cent for collection,"&mdash;and of course would receive nothing
unless the treaty went through and the sale was made.  Indians who were
corrupt were hired, I was told, to vote more than once; signing first the
name by which they went at the time, then the name which they had
borne earlier in life, and later perhaps some still earlier name.  The
names of absent schoolboys were added to the list, on the mere statement
by some Indian that they were in favor of the sale.  So, by cajoling,
promising, bribing, browbeating, bullying, and using illegal votes, the
sale, which was bitterly opposed by one half the tribe, was at last carried
through by a bare majority.</p>
<p>Even to-day the same thing is going on.  Among the measures
recently before Congress was one looking to the removal of the Northern
Cheyennes from their present reservation in Montana to "some other
place."  The territory occupied by these people, although very small, is a
fine stock range, which the neighboring cattlemen long to possess for
their herds.  Besides working with might and main on their
representatives in Congress to secure the removal of these Indians to
another reservation, these cattlemen endeavor to manufacture a public
sentiment against the Indians by continually sending out press reports of
the ill doings of the Northern Cheyennes, and two or three times a year
Montana press dispatches to the newspapers tell of threatened outbreaks
by these people.  As a matter of fact, the Indians are entirely well
disposed, but they realize that an attempt is being made to take them
away from their old country, and are uneasy and fearful lest it should
succeed.  Yet when these Indians surrendered, nearly twenty years ago,
General Miles, representing the government, solemnly promised them
that they should reside here on this piece of land so long as they should
be friendly

<pb n="263"/>  with the United States.  This promise was subsequently
repeated by high officials in Washington; yet to-day these Cheyennes
fear that they will be moved, and are prevented from working on their
homes by the apprehension that as soon as they accomplish anything
these homes will be taken from them.  Several years' work has been
necessary to convince the authorities at Washington that the title of these
Indians to their reservation should be confirmed, and that the white men
settled on the reservation should be moved away.</p>
<p>There is now in contemplation a measure to take from the
Metlakahtla Indians of Alaska&mdash;on the ground that there are mines on
it&mdash;a large portion of the island allotted to them by the government more
than ten years ago.  This is a case of great hardship,&mdash;that of a tribe of
Indians who, with the help of one intelligent and devoted white friend,
have become civilized and self-supporting by their own exertions.  They
moved from British to United States territory in search of freedom, and
in their new home they have built a town, have a sawmill and a salmon
cannery, and govern themselves.  They ask nothing from any one, save
the poor privilege of living undisturbed on the rock where they are
settled.  But now it is proposed to take a part of this away from them,
and so to deprive them of the water power which runs their sawmill and
their cannery, of most of their timber land, and of the stream which
furnishes the salmon on which they subsist.</p>
<p>Last spring, on the day of my arrival at the Blackfoot agency I
found there two strange Indians, who told me that they were Kutenais,
living on the Flathead reservation; that their chief had heard that I was
coming out to see the Blackfeet, and that I was the man who helped
Indians, and therefore he had sent them as messengers, on foot, across
the mountains, a distance of 150 miles, in order that they might tell me
of the hard lot of the Kutenais, to see if I could not help them.  They
said that there were over eighty families of Kutenais living near Dayton
Creek, on Lake Macdonald; that they received no rations from the
government; that they had been told to take up farms on their
reservation, and had done so; but that after they had built their houses,
fenced in their land, and planted their little crops, the white people had
come to them and told them to move away, that their homes were not on
the reservation and did not belong to them.  At first they had refused to
move, but at last, when the whites had said that if they did not go the
Great Father would send troops to move them, they gave up and went
away.  Now there is no place left on their reservation where they can
farm, as all the country is rocky, timber-covered mountains.  The faith
that had led these men to take this long, toilsome journey to tell me their
story was pathetic enough, and the sense of my utter inability to help
them was humiliating, but there was nothing that I could do.</p>
<p>A search through the reports of the Indian commissioner shows
that these Indians were recently ejected from lands which they had
occupied since 1855, on account of a mistake made by a surveyor in
locating the boundaries of the reservation.  The farms that they had
striven to cultivate proved to be without the corrected boundary line, and
as soon as this was discovered the neighboring whites insisted on the
removal of the Indians.  As the land did actually lie outside of the
reservation, the Indians of course had no claim to it, and were forced to
give it up.  After this, in 1891, the agent for the Kutenais, acting under
the Dawes Severalty Act, allotted to eighteen of the Indians claims off
the reservation and upon the land from which they had been expelled.
Of these claims, three were allowed, while fifteen have for seven years
been suspended by the Land Office.  White people have settled in the
valley of Dayton Creek and built

<pb n="264"/>  their fences about the plots held by the Indians, who
have now no means of reaching their claims except by trespassing on the
land occupied by the whites, which they are warned not to do.  within
the white men's fences can be seen still standing the rotting rails and
posts of the inclosures built years ago by the Indians when these claims
were first allotted to them, and they strove to work as the white man
works, and to improve their little farms as he does his.  No wonder they
are discouraged and hopeless at the result of their efforts, and it is hardly
to be imagined that they will ever again make any real effort to become
self-supporting so long as the memory of this wrong remains.  Some
method of repairing this injustice and of helping these Indians ought to
be found.</p>
<p>No argument is needed to prove the discouraging effect on
Indians&mdash;or indeed on men of any race or color&mdash;of such uncertainty
about their location.  If a white man were given the fairest tract of wild
land on the continent, with the understanding that he might be ejected
from his tenancy at any moment, he would have little motive to improve
it, and would put on it just as little labor as he could get along with.
Indians feel and act in precisely the same way.  Whether they are moved
or not, the uncertainty under which they live takes away from them all
motive for industry and self-help.</p>
<p>Indians are perfectly capable of making progress in the arts of
civilization.  This is shown by what has been accomplished during the
last nine years by the Blackfoot Indians of northern Montana, with whose
affairs I have long been closely familiar.  A dozen years ago I won their
confidence and regard and became deeply interested in them, and ever
since I have acted as their counselor and next friend.  To bring about the
results obtained, it has been necessary to watch them carefully, to advise
them against the commission of follies, to persuade them to industry, to
reprove them for wrong-doing; in fact, to try to teach them to exercise
what white men call ordinary common sense in the affairs of life,
checking them or spurring them on as circumstances required.  When I
first knew the Blackfeet they were wild Indians, wearing blankets and
robes, living for the most part in lodges and on a reservation remote
from railroad or civilization.  Except their ponies they had no property.
They had no desire to work, nor any belief that it would be to their
advantage to do so.</p>
<p>The country which they inhabit lies on the flanks of the Rocky
Mountains, just south of the parallel of forty-nine degrees, at an
elevation of 3000 or 4000 feet, and is far too high, cold, and dry for the
successful practice of agriculture.  For years the Indian Bureau had been
trying to induce them to farm, but nothing had ever been grown on the
reservation except an occasional crop of oats and potatoes.  The region,
however, is an excellent cattle range.  In 1888 I determined that if these
Indians were ever to become self-supporting it must be by cattle-raising,
and a statement of the conditions convinced General Morgan, then Indian
commissioner, that the experiment was worth trying.  My visits of the
next two years to the reservation were devoted to elaborate explanations
to the Indians of the value to them of cattle; of the importance of never
killing them for food, and of caring for them in winter, so that they
should live, do well, and breed.  It was explained that at the end of four
years those who followed the advice given would have animals which
they could sell, and that the money received for the beeves would be
theirs to use as they might please.  The idea of having cattle which they
should own individually, and not as a tribe, was wholly new to them;
when it was understood it was very welcome, and the prospect created
quite an excitement in the community.  A majority of the men cut hay
for the stock that

<pb n="265"/>  was to come, and built sheds and shelters to protect it
from the winter's storms.</p>
<p>In 1890 about 1000 cattle were issued.  Some families received
only a single cow, others two, and others four or five.  All went well
with them.  The succeeding winter was mild; no cattle died, and the calf
crop was large.  The people took great pride in their new possessions,
and watched and tended them with much devotion.  At intervals of a
year or two more and more cattle were issued to them, until they had
received about 10,000, and in the year 1897 it was estimated that, with
the increase, the Blackfeet had between 20,000 and 22,000 head of
cattle.  Besides this, for three years past they have sold a great deal of
beef; and their faith in the promises made to them, which led them for
four years to refrain from eating their cattle and to take good care of
them, has been abundantly justified.  They have found a way by which
money can be earned, and have come to understand that their future
depends on their cattle and the care they take of them.  It must not be
supposed that all the men of the tribe have done equally well.  While
many have been unfailingly faithful, some have neglected their stock, or
traded it off, or let it wander away.  But, on the whole, they have done
well, wonderfully well for Indians, and have been as steadfast and
industrious as white men would have been.</p>
<p>The branding of the calves and the round-ups have been in charge
of the agency employees, and this work has often been very much
neglected.  The Indians are not permitted to brand their calves, and they
have suffered heavy losses by the failure of the government employees to
brand those born in the fall of the year.  These autumn calves, having
been weaned and separated from the mothers, by spring become
mavericks, animals whose ownership is not known, and so they are
branded by any one who may find them, chiefly by the half-breeds and
white men living on the reservation, who are more familiar than are the
Indians with the white cattleman's way of accumulating a herd.</p>
<p>The years during which the Blackfeet have had cattle have not
been years of ease and comfort.  The people have had their troubles and
perplexities, but the effort has been made to give them aid and direction
by letters, by frequent visits, by consultations, by encouragement and
advice, and by praise or severe reproof as either was needed.  Often
from old White Calf, long the chief of these people, a message is
received something like this: "I want you to come to us quickly.  There
are many things to be talked over.  We are blind once more.  We need
you to open our eyes."  Thus, what the Blackfeet need, and all other
Indians with them, is, not the good will to labor and to strive, but proper
direction, in order that they may labor and strive effectively.  They lack
that discretion and judgment in dealing with every-day matters which
inheritance, training, and experience have brought to most middle-aged
business men, and these must be exercised for them.  The power to look
at things through the white man's eyes must be supplied to them.  They
must be made to share the wisdom of the white race.  If the Indian
Bureau at Washington can be induced to see that the Blackfeet cattle are
properly handled, the future is assured; but the Indian Bureau, being
really a clerical office for the transaction of Indian business, often knows
little about the actual condition of the people.</p>
<p>The wish to better their present condition is not peculiar to any
particular tribe nor to any section of country.  If they can be convinced
that it will be for their advantage, all Indians are ready and willing to put
forth effort; but when only failure rewards the work they perform, they
become discouraged and think that they can never succeed.  The Indian
of to-day is living his life on the reservation, where he occupies a house
and has acquired a certain degree of self-control.

<pb n="266"/>  He is anxious to have a better living than he gets now,
and is willing to work hard to secure it.  He has given up many of his
old wild ways and beliefs.  He is a savage who has been more than half
tamed.  Civilization has brought to this Indian many hardships; it has
abridged his liberty, has caused disease, has weakened or broken down
many of the fine savage qualities that he once possessed, and has
introduced him to liquor.  As yet it has not brought him much that is
good except humility and some self-control.  His rights are little
safeguarded, except so far as the Indian Rights Association can
occasionally protect him.  He has been taught but little of the
individual's responsibilities.  He is sometimes subjected to gross
injustice.</p>
<p>His inability to speak our tongue or to think our thoughts must
always be remembered in considering the Indian.  He is voiceless; he is
unable to claim any rights for himself or to tell his side of any story, for
he has no method of communicating with civilized people except through
an interpreter.  He cannot speak for himself, and he has no one to speak
for him, no one to advocate his cause.  Even the young men who have
been away to school and have learned how to speak good English speak
it as a foreign tongue.  They think in their own language, and translate
their Indian thoughts into English, which is often not to be understood
without further explanation.  The Indian's psychological condition is
bewildered and confused.  Inheriting the beliefs of his people, developed
through thousands of years, he is suddenly told that all these beliefs are
false.  His faith in his own creed is destroyed; but while we have taken
from him his old beliefs, we have not known enough to give him new
ones which he can understand.  Thus his mind is in a whirl, and he feels
that there is nothing sure, nothing that he can depend on. </p>
<p>What the Indians require to-day is something more than mere food
and clothing.  They need to be directed with some intelligence and
interest.  The conditions of each tribe or each agency should be studied
by a fairly intelligent and experienced person, and the particular method
thus determined to be the one best suited to the needs of the people
should be employed.  Agents and agency employees who are careless or
indifferent should not be retained in the Indian service, and it should be
the business of the inspectors actually to learn how far the employees
residing permanently on the reservation are sincerely interested in the
Indians under their charge.  It is gratifying to notice that the force of
inspectors has recently been increased, and that a number of those
holding the position feel a deep interest in their work, and are willing to
follow up the agency employees so that they will be obliged to do their
duty.  The farmers employed on reservations where agriculture can be
practiced should be real farmers.  They should not pass their time in
loafing about the agency.  They should spend seedtime and harvest out
among the camps and settlements, teaching the Indians how to perform
the various operations of farming.  The farmers on reservations where
the Indians are stock-raisers should be practical cattlemen.  They should
understand their duties, and have something of the loyalty of the old-time
cowboy.  The cattle should be really cared for; stray cattle belonging to
neighboring whites should be kept off the reservation, and the Indians'
cattle held on it.  The Indians should be taught how to brand and care
for their own stock.  They should not be allowed to sell or kill it except
by the agent's permission.</p>
<p>Liquor should be kept off the reservation, and those dealing in it
or using it should be punished with extreme severity; in other words, the
law should be enforced.  The Department of the Interior and the
Department of Justice must act together in this matter.  In the

<pb n="267"/>  past it has rather been the practice of each of these
departments to throw the responsibility on the other.</p>
<p>We can do no more for the Indian than fit him to fight the battle of
life, and we must begin by teaching him about its material things.  He
will readily learn industry and the white man's way, if he sees before
him a reward for his work.  The task of teaching him saving, thrift, is
more difficult, since all his training leads him to share whatever he has
with others.  In order that he may compete with the white man, he must
be taught to speak English and to read and write.  This can be taught
only to the children, but a part of whom at present attend school.  There
is the widest possible difference in the efficiency of the agency schools,
and very great diversity of opinion exists as to the relative advantages of
reservation and of Eastern boarding schools.  The subject is a large one,
and not now to be treated; but it is obvious that the Eastern schools
cannot care for any great proportion of the children, and that good
reservation schools are imperatively required.</p>
<p>We need not inquire here what is to be the ultimate fate of this
race.  Much more to the purpose is it to consider their present
perplexities and immediate needs, and to endeavor as well as we may to
help them along over the steep, rough trail by which they are climbing
upward toward civilization and self-support.  The obstacles which lie in
the path are many, but they are not insuperable, and they may be greatly
lessened by intelligent aid and encouragement.  Interest in the Indian is
steadily increasing.  Many thoughtful people are coming to recognize
that he possesses qualities that are worth studying.  Writers take him for
their theme, sculptors model him, and painters use for subjects scenes
from his old wild life.  Intelligent people who study him wish to know
more about him, and soon learn his true character and give him his true
place, demanding for the race the consideration which it ought to
have.</p>
<p>The task of giving help to the Indian is one worthy the best
thought and effort of the country.  The noblest work that any man can do
is to make life easier for some of his fellows, and in the visible results
which follow the stretching out of a hand in help and sympathy to an
Indian tribe may be found rich reward and ample encouragement to
renewed activity.  I know of no field in which he who is really interested
in his fellows may labor with a surer prospect of appreciation by those
he is trying to help, or a more abundant certainty of answering effort by
them.  When once the Indian's confidence has been won, he strives
earnestly to live up to the standard set before him by his white friend,
and to repay by aspiration and endeavor all that has been done in his
behalf.</p>
<p>The Indians must still do battle, but in conflicts unlike those of the
olden time.  They may still win victories, but the victories will be of
peace.  The day has passed, too, when one may achieve glory by a
campaign against hostile Indians, but worthier triumphs and more lasting
rewards await him who shall fight by their side in this new and desperate
struggle. </p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
