<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HadElec"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;

]>
<TEI.2 id="HadElec">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Electronic Churches</title>
<title type="sort">electronic churches</title>
<author>Hadden, Jeffrey</author>
<editor>Fichter, Joseph</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Compiler</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Jeffrey Hadden, http://religiousbroadcasting.lib.virginia.edu/pubs</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">43</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HadElec</idno>
<date value="2003">2003</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2003 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476014</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Alternatives to American Mainline Churches</title>
<title type="sort">alternatives to american mainline churches</title>
<author>Jeffrey Hadden</author>
<editor>Joseph H. Fichter</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Compiler</resp>
<name/>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>20 pp.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Rose of Sharon Press</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1983">1983</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Author's personal copy</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing
part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1983">1983</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2003-01">January 2003</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Irene Oh</name>
</respStmt>
<item/>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
<head>The Electronic Churches</head>

<p>In recent years the
electronic church has become a source of great controversy.
The initial critics, largely mainline Protestant leaders,
charged that the electronic church constitutes a threat to
local congregations. The television preachers, critics
argued, make it too easy for people to get their religion in
the comfort of their living rooms. <ref target="n1">[1]</ref>
The perceived threat of
losing communicants from the pews and dollars from the
offering plate has resulted in a barrage of wide-ranging
attacks on the televangelists.</p>

<p>In 1979 a few of the syndicated
televangelists began airing partisan political views on a
wide range of issues. Jerry Falwell, for example, founded a
political organization he called The Moral Majority, and
James Robison accepted the vice-presidency of another
religious-political organization, The Roundtable. This move
of a handful of televangelists into the political arena
resulted in additional volleys of criticism being hurled at
the electronic churches. <ref target="n2">[2]</ref>
Mainline Protestants, who had
earlier perceived religious telecasting as a threat, were
joined by large sectors of the Catholic and Jewish
communities as well as by liberals in the secular society
who feared the mixing of evangelical zeal and right-wing
politics.</p>

<p>Neither of these controversies is likely
to dissipate in the near future. During the current decade,
it appears quite likely that we will witness yet a third
dimension of the electronic church controversy the
utilization of the airwaves to develop both new
denominations and possibly new religlons.</p>

<p>The seeds of both new denominations and
new religious movements are already apparent in existing
religious programming. Why this is so can be more easily
grasped if one understands (1) <hi rend="italic">how </hi>the electronic
church developed. <hi rend="italic">(2) who </hi>largely controls it and
why, and (3) <hi rend="italic">why </hi>it has been</p>

<pb n="160"/>

<p>so phenomenally successful during the past
decade. The first objective of this chapter will be to
establish these linkages. Having accomplished this task, the
paper will then analyze why and how new denominations and
new religions will be likely to emerge.</p>

<p>To anticipate the first task to be
accomplished, let us note that there exists an almost
inexorable relationship between the way in which the
electronic church developed and the people who control it,
which ties in with the reasons why they have been
successful. First, the electronic church was made possible
by rapidly expanding technologies that have revolutionized
communication possibilities. At the center of this
communications revolution is the computer, the utilization
of which is obviously not denied to other religious
organizations.</p>

<p>The electronic church is utilized and
controlled predominantly by evangelical Christians because
the logic and imperatives of the technology are compatible
with their theological stance toward proselytization. The
more reserved orientation toward proselytization on the part
of the mainline Protestant churches, as well as their
somewhat more complex theology, places serious restrictions
on their ability to engage in the "market model"
<ref target="n3">[3]</ref>  implicit
in the electronic church.</p>

<p>Finally, the phenomenal success of the
electronic church during this past decade is, in part, a
function of the intelligent application of the available
technology. But more importantly is the drift some would say
stampede of American culture towards conservatism. Dean
Kelley's perspective analysis of why conservative churches
are growing is correct in the identification of "certainty,"
"ultimate answers" and "meaning" as central to the
evangelical success formula.<ref target="n4">[4]</ref>
 These components are central
also to the success formula developed by the
televangelists.</p>

<pb n="161"/>

<p><hi rend="italic">Stages of Growth</hi></p>

<p>The growth and expansion of the electronic
church parallel the development of all modern electronic
communication. Historically. there have been three crucial
communications revolutions: the invention of writing, the
invention of movable type, and the advent of electronic
communication, which is barely 100 years old, dating from
the invention of the telephone. The development of the
electronic church has been affected by three distinct
generational phases of electronic communications. The first
begins with the birth of the radio. The first voice was
transmitted by radio in 1906,<ref target="n5">[5]</ref>
 and Congress acted in 1912 to
establish licensing procedures. The inauguration of
programmed professional radio broadcasting dates only to
1920 in Pittsburgh and the church was there almost from the
beginning. Within a month of regular broadcasting, radio
station KDKA in Pittsburgh carried a live broadcast from
Calvary Episcopal Church. Radio exploded in America in the
1920s. Within five years there were over six hundred
stations. Fully ten percent of these stations were owned by
religious organizations, and most engaged in some religious
broadcasting.<ref target="n6">[6]</ref></p>

<p>The second generation of electronic
communication emerged with television during the 1950s. By
the end of that decade nine of every ten households
possessed at least one TV set. The technology and cost of
television initially required a much greater centralization
of broadcasting than was the case with radio. This meant a
much narrower selection of programming. Nevertheless,
religious telecasting was available almost from the
beginning of this marvelous medium. Its first star was
Fulton Sheen, the Catholic bishop with a twinkle in his eye.
an impeccable delivery and an angel to clean his
chalkboard.<ref target="n7">[7]</ref></p>

<p>But evangelicals, who eventually would
dominate television airwaves. early recognized the potential
of this medium.<ref target="n8">[8]</ref>
 In 1952 when Rex Humbard spotted a crowd
gathered at the window of a department store in Akron
to</p>

<pb n="162"/>

<p>watch this marvelous new gadget called a
television set, he knew immediately he had to put it to work
broadcasting the gospel. He left his family of itinerant
tent preachers and settled down in Akron so that he could
start a television program. Oral Roberts brought the cameras
into his gospel tent in the mid-50s. At about the same time,
a young man named Jerry Falwell founded a Baptist church in
an abandoned soft drink bottling plant in Lynchburg,
Virginia. Long before he had any dreams of developing a
nationwide ministry, he used television to build a 17,000
member congregation.</p>

<p>The third phase of electronic
communications is not so easily dated. In some respects it
can be considered an integral part of electronic ministries
from the outset.<ref target="n9">[9]</ref>
 In another sense, the sophistication of
the communication techniques, based on computer technology
which permits rapid storage and retrieval of information, is
so vastly improved as to represent a qualitative rather than
a quantitative advance. Also critical to this third
generation of electronic communication is the creation of
feedback loops which permit direct communication between
those who utilize the air-waves and their
audiences.</p>

<p>From fairly early in radio broadcasting,
many religious programs were financially dependent for
survival on listening audiences. The most common and
probably most successful technique to encourage listener
support was to offer free printed materials (at times these
were available for sale or for a "love offering"), and to
compile a mailing list of names of those who responded. For
the most part, early electronic preachers knew little about
the audiences they were dependent upon for contributions.
This remained essentially true well into the
1960s.<ref target="n10">[10]</ref>
</p>

<p>The first revolutionary breakthrough in
communicating with audiences was pioneered by Pat Robertson
on WYAHTV in Portsmouth, Virginia. Telephone lines installed
to receive pledges during a 1963 telethon to keep the tiny
station on the air were transformed into prayer lines.
In</p>

<pb n="163"/>

<p>1980, Robertson's Christian Broadcasting
Network handled 1.9 million calls requesting prayer and
counseling.Twentyfour hour prayer and counseling lines have
become an integral part of many of the electronic
churches.</p>



<p>In its development, the electronic church
is first of all a manifestation of a rapidly expanding
technology which has revolutionized all communication. At
the core of the revolution is the computer, with its
continually accelerating speed of operation and a sharply
declining per-unit cost. Without the computer, the modern
telephone centers operated by Robertson, Jim Bakker and
others would not be possible. And without the parapersonal
services performed by volunteer counselors, it is doubtful
that these electronic church enterprises could long operate
in the black. Persons who call for prayer or counseling make
up an important part of the mailing lists the electronic
churches use to solicit money.</p>



<p>Again computer technology is at the heart
of fundraising. The mailing lists of contributors and
potential contributors of the major electronic church
operations number quite literally in the millions. The
practical value of the computer is that it allows the
preachers to mount giant direct-mail campaigns, sending out
millions of fundraising letters as if passing one huge
collection plate. By concentrating on the names and
addresses of those who pay off, they can work on upgrading
the size of contributions while simultaneously reducing the
overall costs of fundraising.</p>



<p>This technology is applied widely in
voluntary associations, business, government and politics.
Unlike the original undifferentiated mailing lists, the new
systems are such that a substantial amount of information
about the people behind the names and addresses can now be
compiled. This information can be stored, sorted and
retrieved with lightning speed at nominal cost. In the
specialized trade of direct mail, promoters constantly test
different sales "pitches," different words and themes, to
sell anything from coins and lingerie to politicians and
magazines. The professionals gath-</p>

<pb n="164"/>

<p>er once a year to distribute Golden
Mailbox awards to the most successful marketeers. They can
compare one sales pitch with another down to a thousandth of
a percentage point of response.</p>

<p>The televangelists have yet to recognize
the precision of such testing. To date they have largely
adapted direct-mail technology to their own needs. Given a
little more time and experience it is inevitable that they
will become much more sophisticated. This greater
sophistication will permit them <hi rend="italic">both </hi>to better meet
the needs of those in their audiences who write or call for
help and to target fundraising appeals that meet their
greatest vulnerabilities. Promoters of the electronic church
encourage their listeners and viewers to write or call and
share their problems and needs. Out of these pleas for help,
the televangelists are building monumental data banks on the
most intimate personal problems mentioned by the millions
who phone or write.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Promoters and Proselytizers</hi></p>

<p>Even the most casual observer will
note that the religious airwaves are dominated by
evangelicals, and that this is not accidental. Both the
market economy and this technology are compatible with
evangelical Christians' theological stance toward
proselytizing. For better or worse, air time in our society
is seldom available free of charge, and generally, the
larger the audience one wishes to reach, the more it costs.
Because utilization of the airwaves means participation in
the free enterprise market, those who do so are
overwhelmingly the ones who have something to sell.
<ref target="n11">[11]</ref>
</p>

<p>Evangelicals fit this criterion rather
well, for they take literally Christ's command to "Go ye
into all the world, and preach the gospel to every creature"
(Mark 16:15). The airwaves have opened up, as never before,
the possibility of spreading the Good News from sea to sea
and around the globe. The basic question is: How are they to
pay? And the answer is not difficult to find. While
spreading the gospel,</p>

<pb n="165"/>

<p>they encourage those who are already
saved, or who have benefited from this electronic ministry,
to contribute to the continuation of the good
work.</p>

<p>Their success in raising money over the
air is nothing short of phenomenal. At least a half-dozen of
the major television ministries have operating budgets
exceeding $50 million annually. A little simple arithmetic
puts these large sums of money in perspective. All of the
televangelists attempt to enroll viewers as regular
contributors. By pledging a modest figure, usually $15 per
month, you can become a "faith partner," "prayer key family
member," "700 Club member," or whatever. A person who
faithfully meets this pledge contributes $180 annually. But
chances are that those who do this will also respond at
least once during the year to one of the many special
appeals made both on the air and via direct mail. Let us say
they contribute, on average, an additional $20 for a total
annual contribution of $Z00. At that rate, it takes only
five thousand regulars to send in a million dollars. A
quarter-of-a-million regulars, thus, could produce the $50
million budget. A fact sheet released by CBN in 1981 claimed
285,000 members of The 700 Club who donate $15 per month or
more plus an additional 175000 persons who have
donated.</p>

<p>To enlist this many people, one has to
reach a fairly large proportion of regular viewers. The
evangelicals know how to do this. They go directly to the
heartstrings. Get right with God. Get right with your loved
ones. Get right with yourself. However the appeal is made,
it is almost always emotionally charged. Obviously, it
works. The evidence, however, suggests that many of their
contributors do not stay with them long. Those who do can be
counted on, with a little prodding, to increase their annual
contributions.</p>

<p>What we see is a confluence of theological
orientation toward proselytization and an organization of
broadcast media which works to the benefit of evangelicals
but against other religious groups. Communications
specialists from Prot</p>

<pb n="166"/>

<p>estant and Catholic churches were warned
by psychologist Liebert that the conflict over the
electronic church "has every hallmark of an intensifying war
of survival among battling Christian groups."
<ref target="n12">[12]</ref>
Evangelicals because they believe they are being faithful
to the great commandment to preach the gospel to all the
world, have no difficulty using gimmicks and strong
emotional appeals to raise the money to keep their programs
on the air.</p>

<p>This is not the case with the mainline
Protestant and Catholic traditions. First of all, they have
a rather more sedate concept of evangelism, witness and
Christ's commandment to spread the Good News. Furthermore,
their tastes in worship do not appeal to the masses who
think that Bach is a beer and Haydn used to be the
quarterback of the Rams. Finally, the very thought of using
the techniques required to raise money over the airwaves is
simply repugnant to elites in the mainline
traditions.</p>

<p>As a result, disgruntled mainliners remain
on the sidelines complaining about the cheap grace and the
dangerous political messages of the televangelists. In the
meantime, the number of evangelicals who are getting in on
the action is growing phenomenally. In 1980, the number of
syndicated religious programs grew from sixty-six to ninety-
seven. Whether the televangelists will be able to sustain
their marvelous gospel spreading machines in the face of
this much competition remains to be seen. The free
enterprise system, which they all support, could be the very
source of their financial collapse as they outbid one
another for the most lucrative air times.</p>

<p>The million-dollar-a-week habit of the
televangelists plus the increasing competition is likely to
get some of them into financial trouble. While a few may go
under, the electronic church will survive. The reason why
this is so can best be understood by coming to grips with
the persistence and significance of evangelical faith in
American culture. When T. George Harris wrote "Our
intellectuals are out to</p>

<pb n="167"/>

<p>lunch...as unaware of religion's danger as
its hope,"<ref target="n13">[13]</ref>
 he must certainly have been thinking also of
pious liberals, religious and secular, who continue to treat
evangelical religion as though it were an archaic religious
form, peculiarly persistent in some regions of the country,
but not a significant factor in American culture.</p>

<p>George Gallup declared 1976 "the year of
the evangelical," but what that date really symbolized was
the nonevangelicals' discovery that this sector of American
society. Previously presumed to be an insignificant fringe,
was in fact very large. Perhaps it was also a turning point
for evangelicals when they found that their world view was
shared by a far larger proportion of American society than
they had previously imagined.</p>

<p>It was the presence of this very large
evangelical population which made the rapid expansion of the
electronic church possible in the first place. To see the
potential of the electronic church, we need to grasp the
social context in which it grew and flourished. However
unpopular the concept, resulting from its use by an
unpopular president, "malaise" is an appropriate term to
capture the American experience dating roughly from the
assassination of John F. Kennedy. We have lost our leaders.
We lost a war which tore us apart at home. We lost
confidence in business and government. A president once
admired by millions left office in disgrace. Inflation
soars. Energy is scarce. International tensions mount one
upon another. And for many who were over thirty during the
sixties, the radical changes in young people's values and
lifestyles underscored the loss of a taken-for-granted
morality that was once as integral to American culture as
baseball, popcorn and Chevrolet.</p>

<p>All of this bad news is so much the harder
to take because television brings all the blood and guts and
gore and hate and civil strife into the private sanctuary of
our homes. And in addition to broadcasting the news,
television magnifies the bad news by creating crime series
and produc-</p>

<pb n="168"/>

<p>ing dramas that seem to condone lifestyles
and language which affront the old values. It should have
come as no surprise to learn that religious broadcasting
would appeal to a segment of society angered and frustrated
by all that has happened to disrupt their simpler and more
tranquil world. And if one had understood how parapersonal
communications and direct-mail technology could be combined
to raise big money, one could have foreseen the growth in
the electronic church that took place in the 1970s. But
what can we expect of the electric church in the
future?<ref target="n14">[14]</ref>
</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">The Drive to Success</hi></p>

<p>The electronic churches appear to be
driven by two axiomatic principles. The first is that the
television ministries themselves prosper in direct
proportion to the boldness of their ancillary building
projects. Oral Roberts built a university and is now
endeavoring to complete a mammoth health care complex which
includes a medical school. Jerry Falwell has launched a
college he hopes will eventually become a university with
50,000 students. Pat Robertson is building a broadcasting
network and a university. Jim Bakker's Heritage U.S.A. is a
"total living center." Robert Schuller's Crystal Cathedral
is a stunning architectural achievement.</p>

<p>The second axiom governing the television
ministries is that they are most successful financially when
they are, or appear to be, on the brink of financial
disaster. The more they can persuade their audiences that
they really are about to go bankrupt, the more the money
flows into their mail rooms.</p>

<p>Professional money raisers feel they have
a pretty good handle on the psychological dynamics of
giving. Crises and bricks-and-mortar projects provide the
best opportunity to tap the philanthropic instinct. People
deserve a helping hand in their hour of great
need especially those who are doing the Lord's work. If
responding to crises is pure altruism. the bricks-and-mortar
projects provide the opportunity to</p>

<pb n="169"/>

<p>contribute to something that will endure
beyond one's own mortal presence on this earth. Those who
contributed to the Crystal Cathedral could feel they were
buying a little piece of immortality. Jimmy Swaggart; the
latest of the televangelists to launch a major building
project, offered his followers the opportunity to claim a
square foot of his World Ministry Center for $50 or, for
$500, one could be listed in the ''Living Stone Honor Book."
Jim Bakker, who cries on camera to punctuate the seriousness
of his recurring financial crises, recently encouraged his
followers to claim an acre of Heritage U.S.A. for a gift of
$1,000 and help pay off the overdue mortgage. If you came to
Charlotte, you could present your check to Jim in front of
the PTL Club television audience.</p>

<p>If crises, real or contrived, and buckling
projects are successful means for raising money, both have
inherent dangers. Crises. Iike drug habits, have the
tendency of requiring larger and larger doses to get a fix.
Furthermore. there may be a limit to the number of times a
televangelist can plead crisis before his loyalist followers
begin to question the credibility of the claim. The
propensity of the televangelists to equate their dreams to
God's will, and their childlike trust that the almighty will
deliver the bucks to pay for their projects, no matter how
ambitious, portends a disastrous conclusion someday. That
there are now more televangelists themselves competing for
money from a total audience that has not increased
appreciably in a half-dozen years may serve to hasten the
day when one or more of the major ministries
collapses.<ref target="n15">[15]</ref>
</p>

<p>It is this precarious quality of the
electronic churches that will eventually lead some of them
into the franchising business. None of the televangelists
has strong ties to a denominational body. Oral Roberts
joined the Methodist Church some years back, but he is not
subject to the discipline of that church body. Robert
Schuller is a member of the Reformed Church of America, a
point he remembers</p>

<pb n="170"/>

<p>when he wants to remind people that he is
a mainline Protestant. Jim Bakker's following is
substantially Assemblies of God folks, but Bakker's ministry
has no denominational ties. And so it is with most of the
others there are essentially no organizational constraints
to hold them to an existing denomination.</p>

<p>One of the strongest arguments pointing to
the inevitability of television ministers starting their own
denominations is the fact that they are substantially
dealing with a revolving door audience. Very often people
get involved in watching religious programs during some
personal crisis. The crisis having passed, they gradually
drift away from the religious program(s) that brought them
comfort. And as their viewing drops off, so also are they
likely to drop the television minister from their list of
charitable contributions. Viewed from an organizational
perspective, this represents membership loss and obviously,
financial loss.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Audiences Into Congregations</hi></p>

<p>If only a small proportion of persons
who give to a television ministry could be converted into
members of a local church organized by the televangelists, a
much more stable financial base could be built. Good
programming. magazines, cassettes, prayer lines, etc., all
serve to reinforce commitment to the television ministries,
but none of these services can be as effective in sustaining
organizational commitment as regular face-to-face contact.
Organizing audiences into congregations, thus, would
substantially reduce the high turnover rate of contributors.
Controlled from the top down, local congregations could be
developed with little or no drain on revenues flowing in to
support the national television ministry. And. since the
local churches effectively belong to the national
organization, their central mission activity would be to
support the television ministry and its ancillary
projects.</p>

<p>Persons who write or call the national
ministry would</p>

<pb n="171"/>

<p>form the initial pool for recruitment of
members. A skillful blending of communications technology
and face-to-face recruiting techniques developed by groups
like the Mormons could result in rapid church development.
The televangelists and their local organizers could expect
to receive a good bit of criticism for "robbing'' the pews
of other churches, but member "snatching" has been going on
for a long time among proselytizing evangelicals.
Furthermore, it is likely that recruiting would be most
successful among persons who were dissatisfied with their
present church affiliation and, hence, had sharply reduced
their level of participation.</p>

<p>It is precisely because the audiences of
the televangelists are constantly changing that television
presents tremendous possibilities for building local
congregations. In addition to the millions of churchgoing
evangelicals who view religious television programs, there
are literally tens of millions of unaffiliated but nominally
believing Christians the unchurched as shown by the 1978
Gallup study.<ref target="n16">[16]</ref>
The potential pool of recruits, thus, is
vast.</p>

<p>Research evidence indicates that door-to-
door proselytizing is not a very effective way to recruit
new members. But the disciples of televangelists could use
this face-to-face contact to leave literature both about the
local congregation and the television ministry. This kind of
contact could produce multiple opportunities for follow-ups
which do not exist when people say "no" to a doorknocker's
invitation to enter their home for the purpose of
proselytizing. The person contacted may decide to watch the
television program this is certainly much less threatening
than allowing strangers into one's home. And having taken
this step, one may then call or write or request prayer or
materials offered on the program. And, eventually, the
person who was turned away at the door may be invited
back.</p>

<p>In short, the television ministries are
faced with the serious need to develop a solid base of
ongoing support. Founding the local congregations from the
ranks of their</p>

<pb n="172"/>

<p>television audiences provides an important
channel for the accomplishment of this objective. The
relative ease and limited cost of developing local churches,
plus the potential rewards, will prove too tempting to pass
up.</p>

<p>Some of the television ministries are
better positioned than others to go into the franchising
business. Perhaps best positioned to move in this direction
is Jerry Falwell. <ref target="n17">[17]</ref>
 For all intents and purposes he
already has the organizational structure in place. In
addition to Liberty Baptist College, Falwell also founded
and operates Liberty Baptist Seminary. It currently enrolls
170 students and Falwell claims that his seminary graduates
have already started 200 new independent Baptist churches.
Among his many ambitious goals for the current decade is the
establishment of 5,000 new churches. Falwell denies any
interest in founding a new denomination. To date, the new
churches have no formal ties although some have taken the
name Liberty Baptist. Falwell has great personal charisma
and his students are intensely loyal to him. Were Falwell
inclined, it would take little effort to transform
independent Baptists into Falwellian Baptists.</p>

<p>Pat Robertson has in place a different
kind of structure that could be transformed into the local
congregations. The Christian Broadcasting Network maintains
prayer and counseling centers in eighty-three cities in
America. Many of the 10,000 volunteer counselors could be
transformed into cadres of local congregations. And, the
fact that counselors are usually only minutes away from
those who call for prayers or help greatly facilitates the
opportunities for face-to-face contact. <ref target="n18">[18]</ref>
 And, in this
context, where people have voluntarily sought help, the
probability of transforming contacts into converts is
considerable.</p>

<p>Twenty-nine of CBN's prayer and counseling
centers are full-time, 24-hour-a-day operations. Excluding
Virginia Beach, the headquarters which receives calls
nationwide. the average number of calls per month in early
1981 was almost 2,000. These roughly 25,000 calls a year
could go a</p>

<pb n="173"/>

<p>long way toward building a local church.
Robertson does not yet have a seminary as part of CBN
University, but he is a very resourceful man. Staffing local
congregations, should he decide to go that route, would not
create a great problem. If other televangelists are not as
ideally organized to create new denominations as Falwell and
Robertson, they still possess considerable resources to
build churches that would owe allegiance to them.</p>

<p>One has to ask the question, of course,
why have not the electronic churches already put their
considerable resources to work to build new denominations.
There are at least two important reasons. First, the
electronic ministries are still very young. They have been
too busy getting where they are now to have had time to
mobilize resources to create local congregations. Only now
have they developed national audiences and an organizational
base to launch such a bold undertaking.</p>

<p>A second kind of response is that there is
a significant psychological barrier. On the one hand there
is a moral hesitancy. Almost all of the televangelists have
repeatedly claimed that they provide a support and
supplementary ministry to the local congregation not
competition or an alternative. It requires some mental
gymnastics to begin deliberately to establish local churches
while simultaneously denying that one is in competition with
other local churches. The other source of hesitancy is
motivated sheerly by an economic consideration. If they went
about the business of organizing local congregations, would
they alienate loyal viewers and financial supporters who are
active in local congregations?</p>

<p>My own judgment is that neither moral
hesitancy nor fear of economic reprisals will constitute
serious barriers to organizing local congregations once the
televangelists see the advantages and build the foundation
to launch new church projects. Their rationale, of course.
will be that they are filling a need unmet by others. Their
experience in refer</p>

<pb n="174"/>

<p>ring new converts to local congregations,
they will argue, was too often unsuccessful because the
local church failed to adequately shepherd the newly won
souls.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">The New Electronic Religion</hi></p>
<p>If the cathode tube provides a
powerful medium for creating new denominations in America,
what of its potential to spawn new religions? The line that
separates new religions from sectarian splits can be
ambiguous. Whenever the group in question is socially
visible, resolution of ambiguity is a political process. The
Unification Church sees itself as an extension of the
Christian faith, its leader being the recipient of special
revelation and, perhaps, a special mission. The National
Council of Churches of Christ in the U.S., supporting the
generally negative reactions of America to Reverend Moon and
his followers, has denounced the Unification Church's claim
to being Christian and its application for membership.
<ref target="n19">[19]</ref>
The teachings of Jim Jones, leader of the People's Temple,
moved well beyond even a remote resemblance to the Christian
faith long before the tragedy that took 900 1ives in Guyana.
Still, in spite of the negative publicity People's Temple
received in the Bay Area, the status of the group as a
congregation in good standing with the Disciples of Christ
was not challenged.<ref target="n20">[20]</ref>
 By any criteria, the teachings of Sun
Myung Moon are closer to the core of Christian theology than
the teachings of Jim Jones. Yet, the former's claim to
Christian heritage is denied while the theological teachings
of the latter remain largely unexplored.</p>

<p>If by a new religion in America we mean a
faith which is generally perceived by political consensus
not to be spiritually kin to one of the Protestant, Catholic
or Jewish traditions, the prospect for creating new
religions via the use of telecasting is fairly remote.
Without being perceived as Christian (or Jewish) it would be
extremely difficult to attract a aufficiently large and
sympathetic audience to raise the monies required to pay for
air time. Furthermore,</p>

<pb n="175"/>

<p>any visible group that is perceived to be
a "new" religion could be expected to be harassed by media
and various government watchdogs alike. Hence, television
would seem an unlikely medium to <hi rend="italic">build </hi>a following
for a group perceived to be new.</p>

<p>On the other hand, it is quite conceivable
that a television minister, perceived to be in the Christian
tradition, could gradually evolve principles or teachings
which, again by political consensus, move so far beyond the
range of accepted that they are defined as "new." To
illustrate, let's look at a real case and project
hypothetical developments.</p>

<p>Robert Schuller calls his theology
"possibility thinking." He acknowledges debt to Norman
Vincent Peale who wrote and preached about the "power of
positive thinking." Both men steadfastly claim that the
principles they teach are firmly anchored in the Christian
faith. Let us assume that somewhere down the line Schuller
begins to preach that sin is negative thought and original
sin is self-doubt. Furthermore, let us assume he goes a step
further and argues that many of the teachings of the Old and
New Testament are antiquated myths that need to be
jettisoned in light of knowledge about man gained by
scientific methods. Would Schuller have overstepped the
boundaries of Christian theology to create a new religion?
Certainly many would think so. We need not project the
scenario to see how others would respond in order to make
the point that television ministers, because they tend to be
charismatic and have large followings, have the potential to
reshape religious doctrine perhaps even to the point of
creating new religions.</p>

<p>The central argument developed in this
paper is that the electronic churches have moved beyond a
role that might be described as ancillary or supportive to
the local congregations. While existing evidence does not
support the widely held assumption that the televangelists
are succeeding to the detriment of the local congregation,
there is clearly a structural basis for competition for
scarce financial</p>

<pb n="176"/>

<p>resources. It is argued here that growing
competition among the televangelists themselves will almost
certainly lead some of them to seek a solid base of support
by establishing local congregations. This development most
certainly will result in protracted conflict both with local
churches and denominations most directly competitive
theologically. Finally, it is suggested that the electronic
churches have the potential to create new religions by
evolving theologies that move outside the boundaries of
existing groups. The potential for new religious groups to
use the television airwaves to proselytize, however, is
quite limited.</p>


<div2 type="notes" id="d4">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">[1]</seg> <p>In an earlier age, when radio was the
medium, the question was raised, "Should Churches be Shut
Off the Air?" <hi rend="italic">The Christian Century,</hi> May 12,
1927.</p></note>

<note id="n2"><seg type="note-symbol">[2]</seg> <p>See the discussion in Jeffrey K. Hadden
and Charles E. Swann, "Born-Again Politics," in <hi rend="italic">Prime Time
Preachers: The Rising Power of Televangelism</hi>
(Reading: Addison-Wesley, 1981).</p></note>


<note id="n3"><seg type="note-symbol">[3]</seg> <p>Aspects of religious competition and
cooperation were earlier discussed by Peter Berger, "A
Market Model for the Analysis of Ecumenicity," <hi rend="italic">Social
Research </hi>30, no. 1 (Spring 1963): 77-93.</p></note>


<note id="n4"><seg type="note-symbol">[4]</seg> <p>Dean M. Kelley, Why Conservative
<hi rend="italic">Churches </hi>Are Growing (New York: Harper and Row,
1972).</p></note>

<note id="n5"><seg type="note-symbol">[5]</seg> <p>It was an informal religious program
sent from Massachusetts to the ships at sea on Christmas
Eve. See A.F. Harlow, <hi rend="italic">Old Wires and New Waves</hi> (New
York: Appleton-Century, 1936).</p></note>

<note id="n6"><seg type="note-symbol">[6]</seg> <p>The audience of the "Radio Priest" was
estimated in the tens of millions. See Wallace Stegner, "The
Radio Priest and His Flock." in Isabel Leighton, ea., <hi rend="italic">The
Aspirin Age</hi> (New York: Simon and Schuster, 1949); also
Charles J. Tull. <hi rend="italic">Father Coughlin and the New Deal
</hi>(Syracuse: Syracuse University Press, 1965).</p></note>


<note id="n7"><seg type="note-symbol">[7]</seg> <p>See D.P. Noonan. <hi rend="italic">The Passion
of Fulton Sheen </hi>(New York: Dodd, Mead,
1972).</p></note>


<note id="n8"><seg type="note-symbol">[8]</seg> <p>The chief charismatic predecessors of
contemporary televangelists are studied by David Harreil,
<hi rend="italic">All Things Are Possible </hi>(Bloomington: Indiana
University Press, 1975).</p></note>

<note id="n9"><seg type="note-symbol">[9]</seg> <p>Everett Parker, David Barry, and Dallas
Smythe, <hi rend="italic">The TelevisionRadio Audience and Religion
</hi>(New York: Harper and Brothers, 1955).</p></note>

<pb n="177"/>

<note id="n10"><seg type="note-symbol">[10]</seg> <p>See Hadden and Swann. "This Business of
TV Religion."</p></note>

<note id="n11"><seg type="note-symbol">[11]</seg> <p>See Virginia S. Owens. <hi rend="italic">The Total Image:
or Selling Jesus in the Modern Age</hi>
(Grand Rapids: Eerdmans, 1980).</p></note>

<note id="n12"><seg type="note-symbol">[12]</seg> <p>Quoted by Hadden and Swann. p.7.</p></note>

<note id="n13"><seg type="note-symbol">[13]</seg> <p>He calls them "spiritual innocents."
T. George Harris, "Introduction" to Hadden and Swann. p.
xiv.</p></note>

<note id="n14"><seg type="note-symbol">[14]</seg> <p>The term "electric" is preferred by Ben
Armstrong, <hi rend="italic">The Electric Church</hi> (Nashville: Thomas
Nelson, 1979).</p></note>

<note id="n15"><seg type="note-symbol">[15]</seg> <p>Exaggeration of the size of audiences
is corrected by recourse to Arbitron figures. See William
Martin, "The Birth of a Media Myth." Atlantic, 247, no. 6
(June 1981): 7, 10. 11, 16.</p></note>

<note id="n16"><seg type="note-symbol">[16]</seg> <p>George Gallup, <hi rend="italic">Profile of the
Christian Marketplace 1980 </hi>(Newport Beach: American
Research Corporation. 1980).</p></note>

<note id="n17"><seg type="note-symbol">[17]</seg> <p>See Gerald Strober and Ruth Tomczak,
<hi rend="italic">Jerry Falwell: Aflame for God </hi>(Nashville:
Thomas Nelson. 1979).</p></note>

<note id="n18"><seg type="note-symbol">[18]</seg> <p>Such personal contact with counselors
predates the electronic church. See David Altheide and John
Johnson. "Counting Souls: A Study of Counseling at
Evangelical Crusades," <hi rend="italic">Pacific Sociological Review</hi>,
20, no. 3 (July 1977): 323-48.</p></note>

<note id="n19"><seg type="note-symbol">[19]</seg> <p>See the "study document" of the
Commission on Faith and Order, "Critique of the Theology of
the Unification Church," in Irving Louis Horowitz, ea.,
<hi rend="italic">Science, Sin and Scholarship</hi> (Cambridge: MIT Press.
1978), pp. 102-18.</p></note>

<note id="n20"><seg type="note-symbol">[20]</seg> <p>See the "corrective" analysis by James
T. Richardson, "People's Temple and Jonestown: A Corrective
Comparison and Critique." <hi rend="italic">Journal for the Scientific
Study of Religion </hi>19, no. 3 (September 1980):
239-55.</p></note>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
