<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HadPrea"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;

]>
<TEI.2 id="HadPrea">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Are the Prime Time Preachers Past Their Prime?</title>
<title type="sort">are the prime time preachers past their prime</title>
<author>Hadden, Jeffrey K., Swann, Charles E.</author>
<editor>primary editor first [last name, first name] ; maximum of three</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>religiousbroadcasting.lib.virginia.edu/pubs</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">22</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HadPrea</idno>
<date value="2001">2001</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2001 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476018</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Are the Prime Time Preachers Past Their Prime?</title>
<title type="sort">are the prime time preachers past their prime</title>
<author>Jeffrey K. Hadden, Charles E. Swann</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>11 pp.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville</pubPlace>
<date value="1982">1982</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  electronic version/religiousbroadcasting.lib.virginia.edu</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Originally published as a discussion paper published by "People for the American Way."</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1982">1982</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
<term>CORD</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>Religion, Democracy, Sociology</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2003-04">April 2003</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jason Smick</name>
</respStmt>
<item/>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">

<div1 type="article" id="d3">
<head>Are the Prime Time Preachers Past Their Prime?</head>



<p>After a half-century of working out the implications and permutations of the
New Deal, America is struggling with changes that challenge many of its values
and policies. It is a struggle about the role of government in our lives -- what
it may and may not do, what it should and should not do, and what it must and
must not do.</p>

<p>The challengers to both traditional liberal and conservative interests and
ideology have been lumped together as "the New Right." However, there are sufficiently
different goals between those who seek sweeping changes in America to warrant
differentiating between the political New Right and the New Christian Right.
</p>


<p>The power base of the political New Right in this struggle to change America
is substantially secular and finds its locus in <hi rend="italic">interests,</hi> largely economic.
The power base of the New Christian Right is <hi rend="italic">sentiment</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ideology,
</hi> which are only partially religious in character. When the organizational
skills of the former are combined with the potential of the latter to mobilize
broad support, the resulting coalition can muster considerably more power than
is possible among just the New Right's network of special interest groups.</p>


<pb n="1"/>

<p>In our book, <hi rend="italic">Prime Time Preachers,</hi> we argued that the New Christian Right
has a long-range advantage in the struggle to reshape America&Ntilde;an advantage
not only over the political New Right but also over every other competing interest
group currently on the scene. We gave them this edge because of their mastery of
modern communications technology and their unique access to mass media. But there
is more to it than this. Here is a summary of the resources and potential which
uniquely position the Radical Religious Right to play a vital role in shaping
this nation's future.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Media Access.</hi>  No other interest group has ever possessed as much
access to media to promote ideology as the Christian religious broadcasters.
The latest figures reported by the National Religious Broadcasters show that
there are 1,108 religious radio stations and 65 religious television stations
in this country. Three Christian networks broadcast programming 24 hours a
day which can be picked up via satellite nationwide, and several other networks
are on more abbreviated schedules.</p>







<p>The latest Arbitron figures show that 88 daily or weekly syndicated religious
programs are drawing 22,844,000 combined viewers. While the total combined audience
for religious television programs has been relatively stable for seven years now,
recent developments suggest that there could be sizable audience growth ahead.
</p>



<p>First, the number of syndicated programs has grown by 40% during the last two
years. This offers a significant pool of talent from which new leaders may emerge
as some of the current televangelists advance in years and retire. Second, Oral
Roberts and Rex Humbard, the long-time leaders in the audience sweepstakes, have

<pb n="2"/>




changed their formats and seem to be rebounding after having suffered serious
audience losses in recent rating periods. Third, our preliminary research indicates
that as greater proportions of American homes are wired for cable television,
audiences for religious programs will increase significantly.</p>

<p>Furthermore, as direct-mail research has made abundantly clear, it is not the
size of the audience that is critical, but the congruence of interests between
what is promoted and who receives the message. Those who like what they hear from
Jerry Falwell or Pat Robertson or James Kennedy will likely end up on mailing
lists which will provide them with printed material to reinforce their commitment
to the cause. Already the politically oriented televangelists are speaking to
far larger audiences than Martin Luther King, Jr., addressed, for example, when
he was the unchallenged leader of the civil rights movement.</p>

<p>While many evangelicals and fundamentalists have been taught that religion
and politics don't mix, there is a natural affinity between fundamentalist theology
and right-wing politics. To date, only a few radio and television preachers have
tried to politicize their audiences. But the very warm receptions New Right political
speakers have received at the annual conventions of the evangelical National Religious
Broadcasters in recent years suggest that their latent political consciousness
is merely waiting to be mobilized.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Finances.</hi>  Social movements can be launched by voluntary labor, but
to become effective agents of social change, they need money. The televangelists
could not survive without converting audience response into financial contributions
to pay for air time. It takes over</p>


<pb n="3"/>



<p>a million dollars a week to fund Falwell's "Old-Time Gospel Hour" and the various
Liberty Baptist College projects he promotes on the air. He can't afford to lose
TV program contributions to the Moral Majority, but he has all the technical skills
he needs to raise significant sums of money for his political activities as well.
So do the other politically minded televangelists.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Organization.</hi>  No political organization, however popular its ideas,
can be built overnight. The claims of organizational strength made by groups like
Moral Majority and Christian Voice in 1980 were a sham; only political novices
would have tried to get away with them. But in the two years since these organizations
first gained national visibility, they have begun to acquire organizational skills.
This is so, in large measure, because of alliances between New Christian Right
and political New Right organizations. Even Falwell, who is fiercely independent
and who initially kept New Right leaders at arm's length, is beginning to pay
attention to Paul Weyrich, Howard Phillips, and the New Right's other key organizational
development strategists. To the extent that the New Right and the New Christian
Right coalition can be held together, the latter will benefit significantly from
the organizational skills of the former.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Legitimacy.</hi>  All social movement organizations claim that God is on
their side. No significant social movement has ever succeeded without making a
convincing case that its goals and the wishes of the Almighty were the same. Without
persuasive God-talk, many otherwise sympathetic bystanders will fail to be transformed
into movement constituents.</p>

<p>The American Labor movement successfully borrowed gospel tunes and superimposed
labor folk lyrics. Those tunes and lyrics carried the "gospel truth" to the common
man in a way that was more</p>


<pb n="4"/>



<p>authentic than the pious rhetoric of J.P. Morgan, who tried to convince Americans
that God was a <hi rend="italic">laissez-faire capitalist.</hi> During the civil rights movement,
the lyrics of liberation and faith were often the same, and the key leaders of the
movement were men of God. As one ranking Southern Senator allegedly put it, "There
wouldn't have been a civil rights movement if a bunch of damned preachers hadn't
gotten the idea that segregation was a moral issue."</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Demographics.</hi>  America is on the threshold of a demographic revolution
which will reshape the character of this society for as far into the future as
anyone can imagine. Simply put, America is growing older. Fewer and fewer people
die young and more and more live longer. As a result, ever greater proportions
of the total population are old. This aging of the nation is a permanent condition
and it has never happened before.</p>

<p>This demographic reality portends a more conservative America for several reasons.
First, as individuals become older they tend to accept a religious world view.
Second, older people tend to hold more conservative or orthodox religious views.
Third, there is a close connection between conservative religious views and conservative
political views.</p>



<p>Thus, as America becomes older, it will also become more conservative. Those
who believe that the current wave of conservatism is an aberration from the long
established progressive trend in America need to study carefully the implications
of this gradual aging process. The TV preacher-politicians aren't likely to fade
away, despite the predictions and pronouncements of journalists who cover the
New Christian Right. As a consequence, much of what we read in the papers is
downright misleading regarding the future of the New Christian Right.</p>

<pb n="5"/>

<p>The mass media constitute a lens through which we are afforded glimpses of
what is happening in the world beyond our immediate experience. What we know
about this world is largely determined by the decisions of reporters and editors
who define what is news and by commentators who decide what is worthy of analytical
treatment.</p>

<p>We do not wish to raise anew all the knotty questions surrounding the issue
of objectivity and bias in news reporting. Our thesis is that neither reporters
nor the legions of commentators who analyze the news were well prepared for the
religiopolitical story which began unfolding in earnest in early 1980. The result
has been a great deal of kneejerk reporting which, if analyzed with any care,
reveals more about reporters' values than the phenomenon under examination.</p>

<p>A study of journalists' political and religious values, conducted by Robert
Lichter and Stanley Rothman and published in <hi rend="italic">Public Opinion</hi> last fall, confirms
many people's suspicions. Eighty-one percent of the media personnel surveyed voted
for Carter over Ford, and an identical proportion earlier picked McGovern over
Nixon. In 1964, 96 percent selected Johnson over Goldwater. Half of the media
members surveyed reported no religious affiliation. Eighty-six percent said they
seldom or never attend religious services, and only eight percent said they attend
church or synagogue weekly.</p>

<p>That the large majority of reporters are personally not in tune either with
the political or religious values espoused by the television preachers is only
part of their problem in reporting a story of this magnitude. Equally important,
their lack of cultural knowledge about conservative religious traditions in America
hampers their ability to understand what is happening.</p>

<pb n="6"/>

<p>We have identified three distinct stages of reporting about the New Christian
Right. Each stage reflects reporters' presuppositions, considering their level
of understanding at the time.</p>



<p>First came the period of <hi rend="italic">discovery and alarm.</hi> Reporters
might well have ignored the 1980 "Washington forJesus Rally" if a cadre of Washington-based
mainline church leaders hadn't insisted that the media pay attention. Media consciousness
of the political involvement of conservative Christians increased several-fold
when Jerry Falwell and his Moral Majority showed up in force at the National Republican
Convention in Detroit. A few weeks later, the media showed up 250 strong in Dallas
to watch several leading televangelists share the podium with Ronald Reagan at
a two-day meeting called the National Affairs Briefing.</p>



<p>Election results, attributed to the New Christian Right, intensified reporters'
alarm. Critics responded with a countermobilization of resources. Established
organizations like the ACLU and Common Cause sought to mobilize their existing
constituencies. And new organizations like People for the American Way and Americans
for Common Sense sprang into existence to do battle with the right.</p>

<p>In the second stage of media response, reporters focused on an <hi rend="italic">assessment
of resources</hi> as they began to discover that many of the New Christian Right's
claims were exaggerated. Jerry Falwell, in particular, had conned the press. He
didn't have 25 to 50 million viewers of the "Old-Time Gospel Hour," as he had
variously claimed, but something closer to 1.5 million. Neither did Moral Majority
have the 4 million members it claimed. Its mailing list was only about one-tenth
that size. Simple arithmetic made it clear that Moral Majority</p>

<pb n="7"/>

<p>could not possibly have registered and influenced the millions of voters it
claimed. Post-election public opinion polls showed that only a small minority
of the country considered themselves sympathetic with the Moral Majority. Moreover,
when Moral Majority sympathizers were asked for their views on specific issues
important to Moral Majority leadership, very large proportions disagreed with
the leadership.</p>

<p>The truth of the matter is that Jerry Falwell had for months made fools of
the press: the country boy had taken the city sophisticates for a ride. At first,
reporters were reluctant to admit that they had been fooled. But when the evidence
mounted, the media launched a counterattack aimed at discrediting Falwell. They
did their best to present him as a liar while trying to ignore the fact that they
had earlier fallen for his made-up statistics.</p>

<p>The Moral Majority story might have gone away quickly, but Falwell failed to
fade like a morning glory in the noonday sun. The more publicity he got, the more
he seemed to thrive, even when the coverage was unfavorable. By mid-summer of
1981, Falwell was receiving phone calls from Ronald Reagan and Menachem Begin
asking for his support. He sassed the President and got away with it, and then
led a delegation of TV preachers to Blair House to meet with the Prime Minister
of Israel. A man who could command the attention of heads of state must have a
power base somewhere. So the media were hesitant to conclude that the emperor
had no clothes.</p>

<p>The third period of response is characterized by a <hi rend="italic">debunking and dismissal</hi>
of Falwell, and with him the Moral Majority and other New Christian Right organizations.
Reporters' realistic assessment of resources clearly provided the foundation for
the eventual debunking,</p>

<pb n="8"/>

<p>but, as noted above, Falwell and company remained too visible to ignore even
after the facts were known.</p>

<p>We contributed significantly to the evidence eventually used to debunk
Falwell, but dismissing him and the New Christian Right was not the intent of
our analysis in <hi rend="italic">Prime Time Preachers.</hi> Our intent was to argue that,
notwithstanding the limited impact of the New Christian Right on the 1980 elections,
their potential as a significant political force should not be measured in terms
of that election, or even the 1982 and 1984 elections, for that matter.</p>

<p>We were careful to distinguish between the political New Right and the New
Christian Right because they are not the same in terms of origins, constituencies,
or goals. It was some time, however, before this distinction became clear to
many reporters. Weeks, even months, after the 1980 elections, major New Right
organizations, e.g., the National Conservative Political Action Committee
(NCPAC), Conservative Caucus, Heritage Foundation, and RAVCO, along with their
most eminent personalities, were treated by many representatives of the press
as merely part of Jerry Falwell's Moral Majority following.</p>

<p>Today, almost all reporters and analysts know that this is not the case. But
many have bought the alternative view that Falwell and the entire cadre of political
activists of the Religious Right are merely puppets of the New Right strong men.
This view is not correct either, but it has played an important role in debunking
the political power of the televangelists in general, and Falwell in particular.
</p>

<p>Right now, Jerry Falwell and his New Christian Right allies interpret God's
will in terms too rigid to</p>

<pb n="9"/>

<p>enlist the real majority of Americans. But America stands ready to be mobilized
for God, country, and the family. For all of our exposure to cultural relativism,
we have not become an amoral or immoral nation. Daniel Yankelovich has his finger
on the pulse of a lot of educated, middle-aged, middle-class Americans when he
says that while we may personally cherish the changes brought on by the cultural
revolution of the 60s, we're not completely comfortable passing this heritage
on to our children. Burton Pines also is on target in identifying a significant
segment of Americans who feel we have gone far enough and that now it is time
to return to traditional values.</p>

<p>How these sentiments may mesh with the agendas of the New Right and New Christian
Right are not entirely clear. The economic interests of the New Right are too
narrow to command the loyalty of a majority of Americans. We share Kevin Phillips'
sense that already Americans are disillusioned with the real agenda of the New
Right and that this disillusionment portends an uncertain and unstable political
future.</p>

<p>America will not be stampeded into Jerry Falwell's moral and political solutions.
But he and his fellow televangelists have already won the battle to define the
agenda. To the extent that Jerry Falwell is unwilling to modify his stringent
fundamentalist morality to accommodate the mainstream of American conservatism,
he will fade from the scene and someone else more flexible will ascend in the
electronic pulpit as a moral and spiritual leader.</p>

<p>But the fact remains that those "kooky fundamentalists"--who secular intellectuals
thought disappeared from America after the Scopes trial--have returned to define
the agenda and thereby shape</p>

<pb n="10"/>

<p>the direction of American culture as we rush toward the 21st century. Whether
they will contribute to the salvation or the destruction of this nation will only
be known as the future relinquishes its mysteries. But those who think that the
New Christian Right is a mere footnote to this nation's history are in for a
big surprise.</p>

<p>
*This is the third in a series of issue papers prepared for PEOPLE FOR THE AMERICAN
WAY (1982). Jeffrey K. Hadden is Chairman of the Department of Sociology at the
University of Virginia. Charles E. Swann is Vice President of Union Theological
Seminary in Richmond, Virginia. Hadden and Swann co-authored <hi rend="italic">Prime Time
Preachers:</hi> Reading, MA: Addison-Wesley Publishing Company, Inc. 1981.
</p>

<pb n="11"/>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
