<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HadTelr"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;

]>
<TEI.2 id="HadTelr">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Televangelism in America</title>
<title type="sort">televangelism in america</title>
<author>Hadden, Jeffrey K.; Shupe, Anson</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">48</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HadTelr</idno>
<date value="2003">2003</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2003 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476019</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Illustrations have been included from the original source.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Social Compass:  International Review of Sociology of Religion</title>
<title type="parallel">Social Compass:  Revue Internationale De Sociologie De La Religion</title>
<title level="m">Vol. XXXIV/1, 1987</title>
<title type="sort">social compass international review of sociology of religion</title>
<author>Jeffrey K. Hadden, Anson Shupe</author>
<editor>A. Bastenier</editor>
</titleStmt>
<extent>61-75 pp.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Centre de Recherches Socio-Religieuses</publisher>
<pubPlace>Universite Catholique de Louvain</pubPlace>
<date value="1987">1987</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  University of Virginia Library BL60.S6 V. 33-34</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Appears in a special issue on religion and the popular media.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been
joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing
analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1987">1987</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
<language id="fre">french</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term>
<term>religion</term>
<term>sociology</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
<term>CORD</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2003-08-21">August 21, 2003</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jason Smick, University of Virginia E-text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item/>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
<head>Televangelism in America</head>

<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d4">
<head><hi rend="bold">1. THE ORIGINS OF TELEVANGELISM</hi></head>

<p>The electric church and the multibillion-dollar enterprise of televangelism
did not arrive overnight, born full-blown like the goddess Athena from the head
of Zeus. Television preaching has organization and strategic roots over a
century and a half old.</p>

<p>Out of the great American nineteenth century urban revivals and the sweeping
cultural transformation that historians term religious Great Awakenings arose
new groups to plan, promote, and stage evangelistic crusades. These groups were
different from existing churches and denominations. They were totally
independent and autonomous. But they crossed sectarian boundaries and drew
their support from Christians who belonged to a wide variety of churches. They
were <hi rend="italic">parachurhes</hi>. </p>

<p>The modern electric empires of the Pat Robertsons, the Jerry Falwells, the
Billy Grahams, and the Jimmy Swaggarts are the direct descendants of these
<hi rend="italic">parachurches</hi>.  Modern televangelists have the revivalists of past
generations to thank for the ways they run their ministries. The original
<hi rend="italic">parachurch</hi> revivalists devised deliberate strategies for manipulating
conversions and staging huge, impressive public crusades. They built great
organizations and improved techniques to raise money and mobilize believers
by the tens of thousands.</p>

<pb n="61"/>

<p>Most importantly, the skills and managerial savvy they accumulated was not lost.
Indeed, it was preserved and passed down through generations of evangelists.</p>

<p>Three giants of <hi rend="italic">parachurch</hi> revivalism stand out in particular;
Charles Grandison Finney (1792-1875), Dwight L. Moody (1837-1899), and Billy
Sunday (1862-1935). As Razelle Frankl (1987) has shown, these three men honed
the skills of swaying large audiences into highly sophisticated and consciously
rationalized techniques of modern organizational efficiency. Though each made
separate contributions to the growth of the parachurch phenomenon, it is
helpful if we think of them as part of a cumulative process. Each revivalist
(and dozens of lesser ones like them) built upon the wisdom of his
predecessors.</p>

<p>Unlike those before him who saw revivals as a gift from God, Finney (a
former lawyer) saw individual conversions as humanly organized and orchestrated
products. He developed rational techniques and wrote a manual on how to conduct
successful revivals. Moody (a former business man) improved on the
organization, the public relations, and financial dimensions of conducting
crusades. Sunday (a former professional baseball player) took their accumulated
knowledge one step further by development of even more efficient organizational
division of labor and the ingredient of entertainment and flamboyant
shownmanship.</p>

<p>There is little that is different between the city-wide revivals staged by
Charles Finney (and improved upon by successors Moody and Sunday) and the
"crusades" organized by contemporary counterparts such as the Rev.
Billy Graham. Graham has the added assistance of electronic communications
technologies. But, in principle, his crusades follow the rationale first pioneered
by Finney more than a century-and-a-half ago.</p>

<p>Thus, when the electronic technology became sufficiently advanced the modern
preachers already had their strategies in place. Had these developments in
staging revivals and building <hi rend="italic">parachurch</hi> networks not been pioneered
in the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, religious broadcasting would
not be in the important position in American life that it is today. And the
prospects for politically oriented preachers launching national moral-political
crusades, even possibly a presidential campaign such as that of Pat Robertson,
would have been still more remote.</p>

<p>Then in the 1920s the technology emerged. The free enterprise economic
philosophy has shaped radio and television broadcasting more decisively in the
United States than in any other nation. This distinctive, though nearly
taken-for-granted, character of broadcasting in America has had a profound
impact on the development of religious broadcasting there. Broadcasting is
regulated, but compared to other nations the U.S. Federal Communications
Commission gives local stations and networks a great deal of liberty in setting
their own polices and procedures.</p>

<p>It is unequivocally assumed that broadcasters have a right to pursue
policies which will render them a profit. So long as some small proportion of
their broadcasting is devoted to the "public interest", and if they
do not engage in programming that is judged grossly offensive, stations and
networks can pretty much broadcast whatever they wish.</p>

<pb n="62"/>

<p>Almost from the inception of regularly scheduled broadcasting in
the 1920s, religious programming has been considered to be "in the public
interest". Most stations and networks offered some air time on a
sustaining (tree) basis for religious groups to present programming. From the
very beginning, the demand for air time by evangelists and religious advocates
exceeded that which broadcasters were willing to devote to this purpose.
Therefore policies to determine who would be granted access had to be developed
(Jennings: 483).</p>

<p>The first national radio network was the National Broadcasting Company,
formed in 1926, followed by the Columbia Broadcasting System in 1927. From the
beginning, NBC offered no commercial time for religious broadcasting and
allocated what time it chose to offer tree through the aegis of the old
(liberal) Federal Council of Churches (Ibid: 484).</p>

<p>CBS, of financial necessity, did offer commercial time, but switched to
gratis time only in 1931 as a means to get rid of the outspoken Catholic priest
Father Charles E. Coughlin (Ibid: 489). Thereafter, CBS selected persons to
appear on the CBS Church of the Air. They retained their own advisory board but
also relied heavily on the Federal Council. By 1934 the Department of National
Religious Radio of the FCC with twenty-four cooperating denominations had some
oversight over six regularly scheduled network programs (Saunders: 20).</p>

<p>The Mutual Broadcasting System was the only network to offer commercial time
without restriction from 1935 to 1944 (Ibid: 22). Two of the more notable
programs it broadcast (although not for this entire time period) were Charles
E. Fuller's Old-Fashioned Revival Hour and The Lutheran Hour sponsored by the
Lutheran Church, Missouri Synod and featuring Walter A. Maier.</p>

<p>The Christian Century, the leading liberal Protestant periodical, published
an attack on "religious racketeers" who "use radio preaching as
a medium of exploitation" (cited in Murch: 1913). The author accused
Mutual of tolerating programs like the Lutheran Hour because they were
financially lucrative. He called for the termination of all paid religious
broadcasting and, failing this, a "rule of the Federal Communications
Commission against the sale of time for religious broadcasting." </p>

<p>James DeForest Murch, a towering figure of evangelical Protestantism during
this period, accused Frank R. Goodman, Chairman of the Federal Council of
Churches 'Department of National Religious Radio of leading a campaign to
squeeze evangelicals off the air. Goodman, he claimed, had "signed up
fifty or more radio stations ' with ironclad contracts obliging them to use the
Federal Council approved programs and no other'", (Ibid: 174).</p>

<p>The Federal Council of Churches', and later National Council of Churches'
officials have always denied that they had any role in pressuring networks to
develop programming under their aegis to exclude evangelicals. But the evidence
is clear that evangelical Protestants did nor share in the free time granted by
the networks and, further, that there existed a campaign to pressure Mutual
into the "no commercial time" policy.</p>

<p>In March of 1944 Mutual announced changes in their paid-time broadcasting
that severely curtailed access. Among the restrictions adopted by Mutual were
(1) restriction of broadcasts to thirty-minutes, (2) a prohibition against the
use of air time to solicit funds to pay for the broadcasts,

<pb n="63"/>

and (3) broadcasting on Sunday mornings only. The reason for this policy change,
concludes Ralph Jennings, author of the most comprehensive study of radio religious
broadcasting: "strong criticism from mainstream Protestantism as cases of
alleged abuses mounted" (Jennings: 490).</p>

<p>Evangelicals understood what was happening and had been mobilizing to fight
back. Their first major effort toward developing cooperation among evangelicals
occurred two years earlier, in 1942, at a National Conference for United Action
Among Evangelicals. The National Association of Evangelicals (NAE) was formed
as a direct result of this convention, and evangelical religious broadcasts
took a prominent role in this meeting (Armstrong: 49).</p>

<p>In April, 1944, just a month after Mutual announced its policy changes that
restricted evangelical access, 150 evangelical broadcasters met in Columbus,
Ohio and formed the National Religious Broadcasters (Jennings: 317). Their
first official act was to retain a Washington based communications attorney to
provide "counsel in the preparation of a Constitution and Bylaws and a
general policy and program" (Murch: 175). And from that moment forward,
the tide began to shift. They convened again in Chicago in September for a
Constitutional Convention.</p>

<p>With the creation of the National Religious Broadcasters, the collective
fate of evangelical broadcasters began to change. In time, they would become a
decisive factor in the shift of the balance of power from liberal Protestants
to conservative evangelicals. NRB launched an aggressive public relations
program to promote their case. They adopted a Code of Ethics which they
declared was a "veritable Declaration of Independence from radio
racketeers". They called on the Federal Communications Commission to help
ameliorate the maldistribution of air time. They also petitioned the networks
to reconsider their policies.</p>

<p>At least some results were forthcoming in pretty short order. That same
year, Mutual allocated six and a half hours of free time to NAE (Jennings:
312). NBC's Blue Network, which would become the American Broadcasting Company,
also offered time to NAE on a restricted basis.</p>

<p>After an early burst of visible successes, NRB lost some of its thrust and
vitality. This is a typical pattern with virtually all social movement
organizations. Visible signs of success are likely to be interpreted by
participants as evidence of victory. Perceiving victory in success, participants
lose their sense of zeal and enthusiasm. They slacken on financial
contributions and ignore appeals for redoubling of mobilization efforts. As a
result, a movement organization becomes vulnerable at the very moment its
supporters appear to have won, or are about to win.</p>

<p>This vulnerability was not missed by the liberal Protestants, now
reorganized as the National Council of Churches. When television expanded
rapidly in the early 1950s, the NCC pursued an initiative to assure exclusive
representation with the networks. CBS, leery because of earlier conflict with
evangelicals, added the Southern Baptists to its consortium of liberal
Protestants, Catholics, and Jews. As the Southern Baptists were not members of
NRB, this conciliatory gesture was hardly welcomed with enthusiasm by NRB
affiliates. Other networks developed interfaith programming also, but
evangelical Christians were basically excluded from access to the time
available.</p>

<pb n="64"/>

<p>Because of his phenomenal popularity, Billy Graham was able to
cut through the liberal church monopoly and acquire network television time,
both gratis and purchased. But the rank-and-file NRB evangelicals were
effectively locked out of network television time. This access policy has not
changed even today; religious broadcasters must contract for programming on a
station-by-station basis.</p>

<p>A new initiative of opposition to paid religious broadcasting developed at
the state level. This campaign was endorsed by the Broadcasting and Film
Commission of the National Council (Murch: 179). These renewed hostilities with
liberal Protestants and the failure to get in on network television served to
invigorate the National Religious Broadcasters.</p>

<p>Since 1956 the NRB has held its annual meetings in Washington. Being in
Washington paid dividends that were sufficiently obvious to NRB leadership.
They have established lobbying and liason relationships. They have an annual
Congressional Breakfast that is better attended today than it was a few years
ago when there were fewer conservatives in the Congress. They get on well with
the Federal Communications Commission and hold an annual luncheon in their
honor. They retain counsel to represent them before the FCC -- Richard Wiley,
former chairman of the FCC. The presidents of the National Association of
Broadcasters and the networks have accepted their invitation to speak. And in
recent years, the convention has been highlighted by the appearance of Ronald
Reagan. In a word, the members of NRB have learned their way around Washington.</p>

<p>The success of the National Religious Broadcasters and its constituent
members has been a gradual process. But if there was a single development that
turned the tide in their favor it was a policy directive from the FCC in 1960
which ruled that no important public interest is served by differentiating
between gratis airtime and commercially sponsored programming.</p>

<p>To grasp the significance of this ruling, we need to consider the
Communications Act of 1934 which authorized the FCC to grant broadcasting
licenses. The granting of a license, in effect, constitutes a monopoly to use a
scarce commodity, namely a specific airwave, to transmit messages. In short, it
has always been presumed that stations "owe" some proportion of their
broadcast time to general "public interest" in exchange for this
monopoly right. From the beginning, religious broadcasting has been designated
as public interest broadcasting. And hence, the argument of the National
Council of Churches that the stations and networks are obliged to give free
time for religious broadcasting.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">The implication of the 1960 ruling was that local stations could sell
airtime for religious programs and still get "public interest credit"
in the eyes of the FCC overseers</hi>. Several important developments followed.
First, the ruling buoyed the evangelical broadcasters commitment to buy
commercial time. Second, in their resolve to buy time, they began a cycle of
fierce competition with each other. This competition enhanced the value of the
time slots with the result that many local stations, which had previously
followed network policies of not selling air time for religious broadcasting,
decided to cash in on the new demand.</p>

<p>Evangelicals bought their way onto the air in unprecedented numbers. While
this was happening, a technological innovation further enhanced their

<pb n="65"/>

ability to expand the number of stations on which they could appear -- the invention of
the videotape. Prior to the videotape, films of programs had to be mailed
around the country, from station to station. It was an expensive process and
program content had to be planned carefully to avoid appearing badly out of
date or out of sync.</p>

<p>The video tape permitted mass production of a program which could be sent
out and aired during the same week all across the country. By videotaping a few
weeks early, programming could be scheduled to correspond to the calendar,
something that was virtually impossible with films. The latter would be aired
on one station and then shipped to another for airing the following week, and so
on. With videotape, Easter services could be broadcast on Easter, Christmas
services at Christmas, etc. This synchronization of broadcasting with the
calendar greatly enhanced the appeal of programs.</p>

<p>The implications of the FCC policy directive were devastating for programs
that had been carried on a sustaining basis. Why should local stations give
time to broadcast religious programs when syndicated broadcasters were bidding
against each other to buy air time? As a business proposition it didn't make
any sense. Local station managers did see the dollars and cents of it and, as a
result, they dropped sustaining-time programs produced both by their own
network and by individual denominations.</p>

<p>The collective impact of these market decisions is dramatically demonstrated
in a report by the Communications Committee of the U.S. Catholic Conference to
the FCC in 1979 (cited in Horsfield: 89). In 1959, fifty-three percent of all
religious broadcasting in America was paid-time programming. Following the FCC
ruling, that proportion increased to nine-two percent by 1977.</p>

<p>Televangelism, now fully in the hands of the evangelicals and
fundamentalists, has arrived in force.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d5">
<head><hi rend="bold">2. TELEVANGELISM'S "GOSPEL OF PROSPERITY"</hi></head>

<p>What all television ministries have in common, which would in time
revolutionize religious broadcasting, is their relationship to their audience.
Whereas commercial broadcasting sells advertising to support programming, the
electric church sells Jesus, itself, and usually some wonderful project.</p>

<p>These "bricks and mortar" projects are frequently schools and
universities (such as Oral Roberts University or Jerry Falwell's Liberty
Baptist University). Pat Robertson began with the development of a television
network and then expanded into a graduate university (CBN University). Jim
Bakker's Heritage Village, USA has become a religious amusement park on the order
of a spiritual Disneyland -- an extension of missionizing work and, hence,
deserving of charitable contributions.</p>

<p>Televangelists solicit support from their audiences for their projects,
offering premiums in exchange for donations. Over time, their solicitation
tactics have become increasingly refined. While some electric church
organizations utilize professional fund raising organizations, many have
developed sophistication that exceeds the capabilities of many professional
fund raising

<pb n="66"/>

organizations. And many of their critics would relish the opportunity to employ
the skills of the electric church to raise money for their favorite charity
or project.</p>

<p>With increased competition, air time has become very expensive for
televangelists. And with costs increasing faster than audiences, there is an
ever present prospect that the logic of the whole process could crumble.
Broadcasting seems to have become an instrument to pay off bills incurred in
the pursuit of their many projects rather than an end in itself. Billy Graham
biographer Marshall Frady found this inverted process at work with the
crusades. In the beginning, Graham's crusades came to exist for the purpose of
saving souls. Then, over time, they came to exist "for the sake of their
own self-propagation." But with the passage of still more time they
"existed for their televised reproductions." Hence, "the
television event... existed to produce more television events" (Frady:
314).</p>

<p>The reason is clear: Theology is not done in a vacuum. It is done in a
medium, a context. And the values and pressures of the context help shape the
theology. The medium is not neutral to the message.</p>

<p>The fundraising tactics of televangelists such as Pat Robertson, no less
than his colleagues, are a prime example of this truism. These have been
undoubtedly the most controversial aspect of the electric church. Indeed, the
relentless pressures of broadcasting costs which televangelists face, and their
ambitions to engage in other brick and mortar ventures, have made their appeals
for cash more than just necessary elements of their ministries. <hi rend="italic">Fundraising
has become an integral part of prime time religion's theology.</hi></p>

<p>There are an assortment of variations on a common theme, but most
televangelists end up at a common point: the Gospel of Prosperity. According to
this theology, God wants you to be financially prosperous and content. Poverty
or ill-health are not really in God's providence; they are problems in your
Christian attitude and understanding. Sacrifice and suffering have little to do
with the contemporary Christian message.</p>

<p>Many televangelists say the keys to financial success are actually embedded
in the New Testament. By supporting their particular ministries with donations,
they assure viewers, anyone can learn what these keys are.</p>

<p>Pat Robertson calls these rules "Kingdom Principles," taught by
Jesus Christ and "as valid for our lives as the laws of thermodynamics or
the law of gravity." They are there in the Bible, but for them to be
discerned you need the Virginia Beach televangelist as a guide. Then the
Christian Gospel becomes a potpourri of information that can be applied to all
sorts of secular situations. Says Robertson: "The Bible, quite bluntly, is
a workable guidebook for politics, government, business, families, and all the
affairs of mankind" (Robertson, 1982: 44).</p>

<p>In particular, God works on a principle of reciprocity. The more money you
send to Him (presumably, in Robertson's case, through his "The 700
Club" television program) the more God will return materially on your
investment. Robertson writes in <hi rend="italic">The Secret Kingdom</hi>:</p>

<p>If we want to release the superabundance of the kingdom of heaven, we first
give... I am as certain of this as of anything in my life. If you are in
financial trouble, the smartest thing you can do is to start giving money
away....Your return, poured into your lap, will be great, pressed down and
running over (Ibid: 108-9).</p>

<pb n="67"/>

<p>Oral Roberts refers to his twist on the same theme as <hi rend="italic">seed-faith</hi>.
Contributions to his ministry have the potential to return mighty dividends,
spiritual and material, within this lifetime. (He once wrote an article in his <hi rend="italic">Abundant
Life</hi> magazine entitled "You Sow It, Then God Will Grow It.") While
the concept can be applied to various aspects of life, it gives viewers a
special justification for contributing to Roberts since he claims to have
uncovered the dynamics of how God apportions miracles.</p>

<p>In <hi rend="italic">Miracle of Seed-Faith</hi> (1974 -- the 24th printing) Roberts
discusses Three Key Principles of seed-faith and how to make
"blessing-pact convenants" with God. There is, for example, the Law
of Sowing and Reaping ("Remember, only what you give can God multiply
back.") and his frank admonishment: "If you want God to supply your
financial needs, then give SEED-MONEY for Him to reproduce and multiply"
(Roberts: 21,27).</p>

<p>Dallas, Texas based Kenneth Copeland, Roberts' pupil, on the other hand,
preaches "Prosperity Theology" based on biblical laws. He has written
a string of best-selling books on the subject, including <hi rend="italic">The Laws of
Prosperity</hi>. His wife, Gloria, recently wrote one entitled <hi rend="italic">God's Will
is Prosperity</hi>.</p>

<p>Televangelists have probably received their greatest criticism because of
their fundraising tactics. It may be that successful televangelists are on a
collision course with an eventual backlash against their very strategies for
success. Even Billy Graham has been known of late to criticise televangelists',
'endless projects, money-raising campaigns, and tearful warnings of
bankruptcy'.</p>

<p>Yet what is so remarkable in all of this enterprise is how so many of the
televangelists, because of pressures to meet their payroll, pay their bills,
and finance their ambitious building projects have found it irresistible to
integrate fundraising appeals into sermons and theologies.</p>

<p>Sociologist Razelle Frankl studied video telecasts of Oral Roberts, Robert
Schuller, Jim Bakker, Rex Humbard, Jimmy Swaggart, Jerry Falwell, James
Robison, and Pat Robertson in 1981 and found that no preacher used less than 10
percent of broadcast time for direct fundraising appeals. <hi rend="italic">Two-thirds</hi>
of the televangelists' appeals for money were targeted at the personal needs of
the viewer.</p>

<p>"In addition", she discovered, "television preachers made
funding appeals that were integrated into the program content and were not as
easily distinguished as commercial appeals." The result was what Frankl
termed a "hybrid" of traditional revivalism and television. "The
ministries are combining religious norms and broadcasting norms" (Frankl,
1984: 137).</p>

<p>Thus have the financial exigencies of the televangelists become part of the
Great Commission. The theology of a television preacher such as Pat Robertson
is closely intertwined with the budget of this electronic empire. Electric
Christianity is not simply traditional Christianity broadcast across cable
channels and beamed around the globe by satellites. It is a transformed
message, befitting the needs of those who purport merely to serve it.</p>

<p>What essentially happened was that technology has circled back on the
televangelists' broadcasting. These preachers have found that their enormous
broadcasting costs dictate that they run constant fund-raising campaigns. The
"saved" and "born-again" have to be continually cajoled with
new incentives to give to these ministries. Using computers, word-processors,
and toll-free telephone banks, the electric ministers have developed
sophisticated ways of

<pb n="68"/>

creating a sense of personal relationship between viewer and evangelist, between
donor and parachurch. And, as we have seen, the medium has to affect the message.</p>

<p>The subtleties of theology do not carry well over television. This medium is
fundamentally visual, not cerebral. It is not an easy medium to master. Perhaps
that is why many liberal critics of Pat Robertson and other televangelists are
so quick to mistakenly dismiss what they preach as raw hucksterism. Robertson
and his colleagues have successfully adapted to their environment by packaging
a message in terms.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="3" id="d6">
<head><hi rend="bold">3. TELEVANGELISM'S AUDIENCE SIZE CONTROVERSY</hi></head>

<p>"The Great Audience Size Debate" has preoccupied both
televangelism's supporters and critics. In its early years the electric
church's televangelists made sweeping, even fantastic claims of broad viewer
support with minimal evidence. For example, in the early 1980s the Rev. Jerry
Falwell claimed to have a total viewership for the <hi rend="italic">Old-Time Gospel Hour</hi>
of 50 million. Such exaggerations have been common coming from televangelists.</p>

<p>At the same time, the A.C. Nielsen Company and the Arbitron Company are the
two major organizations in the United States that monitor television viewing
habits. In principle Nielsen and Arbitron have the technological capability to
measure all radio and television audiences in the country on a continuing
basis. For the top programs, television networks and advertisers desire to have
more or less continuous information because a small proportional shift in an
audience share can warrant a change in advertising charges. Thus, for the very
largest programs, and the largest audience markets, Nielsen and Arbitron are
more or less continuously monitoring audience size.</p>

<p>Using data from these respective companies, social scientists Hadden and
Swann (1981:47) and Martin (1981: 11) demonstrated that <hi rend="italic">the audience size
for the syndicated religious broadcasters was much smaller than the claims that
had been made by many of the ministries</hi>. Martin reported an audience of
13.8 million for the top ten programs in the Nielsen ratings for November, 1980
(Ibid). Hadden and Swann reported a total of 20.5 million for Arbitron's 66
syndicated programs, with a total of 14.9 millions for the top ten programs -- a
mere discrepancy of eight percent for data gathered nine months apart (Hadden
and Swann: 50).</p>

<p>The infusion of such facts into the controversy did not settle the debate
about audience size and trends. If anything, it added fuel to the flames. The
reason this was so that lots of people have vested interests in how many people
are watching and how the numbers are interpreted.</p>

<p>It should not have come as a surprise that religious broadcasters themselves
were not happy with these numbers -- particularly those who had public ally
claimed vastly larger audiences for themselves than the Arbitron and Nielsen
syndicated, religious, program analysis showed.</p>

<p>Ironically, some of the electric church's strongest adversaries also
challenged these smaller audience estimates. For example, <hi rend="italic">if</hi> the
number of persons watching Jerry Falwell and other politically minded
televangelists was

<pb n="69"/>

much smaller than they claimed, then the raison d'etre of Norman Lear's
<hi rend="italic">People for the American Way</hi> (a liberal organization opposing the
political activities of televangelists) was diminished. In short, the greater
the audience size of the religious right televangelists, the greater the perceived
threat and, hence, the greater the urgency to support countermovement organizations
like PAW that had been formed to do battle with the New Christian Right.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, another group of adversaries argued that the Arbitron and Nielsen
figures overestimated the "real" audience size of the televangelists
(Fore, 1981: 940). These figures, they argued, do not take into account the
duplication of audience when the same person watches more than one religious
program.</p>

<p>Debate about how many people are watching religious programming was one
factor which led to the creation of an ad hoc committee to investigate the
effects of religious television. The <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi> committee grew out of the
Consultation on the Electronic Church sponsored by the National Council of
Churches in February, 1980.</p>

<p>From the beginning, the project was conceived as bipartisan and the
composition of the committee consisted of a coalition of evangelical religious
broadcasters and the "mainline" church traditions. It was co-chaired
by William Fore, Director of the National Council of Churches Communication
Commission, and Ben Armstrong, Executive Director of the National Religious
Broadcasters (Hadden and Frankl).</p>

<p>The <hi rend="italic">ad-hoc</hi> committee on Religion and Television raised over
$150,000 and commissioned The Annenberg School of Communications and The Gallup
Organization to conduct the research. Even before research had commenced, the
Religion and Television Research Project was heralded as "the
definitive" investigation of religious broadcasting.</p>

<p>In the Spring of 1984 the long awaited study on the electric church appeared
(Gerbner, et. al.). Throughout the duration of the study, the two investigative
teams worked independently. George Gerbner, Dean of the Annenberg School, was
responsible for coordinating and integrating a final report.</p>

<p>As it turned out, there was little integration of the two investigations.
"De facto", they became two studies, with the Gallup study appearing
as an appendix to the Annenberg study. The findings of the two studies were at
odds on several critical points including the important question of how many
people are watching.</p>

<p>The two research teams used different methods to measure audience size and,
with hind-sight, it is not particularly surprising that they came up with
radically different conclusions. Piggy-backing on Arbitron "sweep"
data, the Annenberg term came up with a figure of 24.7 million total viewers.
Then, going to viewing diaries kept by a sample of Arbitron respondents, they
concluded that the non-duplicated audience was 13.3 million. In contrast, the
Gallup survey asked people if they had watched a religious television program
during the previous month. Thirty-two percent, which would represent
approximately 70 million viewers, claimed that they had.</p>

<p>The Annenberg measure was for one week, the Gallup measure for a month.
Certainly, if there was duplication during a week, the amount of duplication
would increase over the course of a month. Thus, the discrepancy of over five
hundred percent -- 13.3 million versus approximately 70 million -- was even
greater than it appears to the eye.</p>

<pb n="70"/>

<p>Naturally, the audience figures were disputed by the religious
broadcasters who wished to see them larger. So the great audience size debate
seemed to be back to where it started.</p>

<p>But not quite. There remained the puzzlement of why some adversaries of the
electric church, who had earlier bought into the myth of huge audiences, had
abruptly changed their minds and became adamant in pressing the case for even
smaller audiences than those measured by Arbitron and Nielsen.</p>

<p>For example, Williar Fore, the chief spokesperson of the National Council of
Churches, wrote in a July 1980 <hi rend="italic">TV Guide</hi> article that "some 47% of
Americans see at least one religious program a week on TV" (Fore, 1980:
15). Later, when the Annenberg team reported the weekly
"unduplicated" viewing audience for religious programs at 13.3
million, Fore whittled the number down to a mere 7.2 million (Fore, 1984: 711).</p>

<p>Why this great reversal? We think that the "mainline" Protestant
communications leaders now see their chances of tapping into sustaining (free)
time as enhanced if they can "prove" that the current syndicated
broadcasters are not reaching nearly as many people as they claim. Given the
confusing nature of the data, and the absurdity of claims made by others, why
not claim that the electric pews are empty -- or nearly so?</p>

<p>If hardly anyone is watching the current offerings, so this logic goes, then
stations and networks <hi rend="italic">should</hi> give the liberal churches free time so
they can produce programs that are more in keeping with the tastes of
"mainline Protestants". It follows that this programming will attract
much larger audiences.</p>

<p>In pursuit of this strategy, the liberal church leaders have created another
myth which is just as exaggerated and misleading as the myth of exaggerated
audience size which was debunked in 1981 by Hadden and Swann and William
Martin.</p>

<p>We call this new fabrication the <hi rend="italic">myth of the tiny and insignificant
remnant</hi>. It seeks to create a self-fulfilling prophecy. If nobody believes
that anybody is watching, then perhaps nobody else will tune in. And if nobody
is watching, according to purveyor of the myth, how can broadcasters ethically
justify selling airtime to the televangelist charlatans?</p>

<p>Part of the source of the confusion over audience size lies in the fact that
measuring a television audience is not as simple and direct a task as counting
how many people attend church services in a local congregation or how many
people go through a turn-stile at a football game. In these instances, we are
satisfied with the notion that people are either present or not present.</p>

<p>The question of presence or non-presence is not so easily determined with a
television audience. Most people don't watch television the way they attend a
church service or an athletic contest. They tune in late and depart early; they
switch channels and they leave the room. In front of a television set, people
generally feel at greater liberty to talk with one another than they do in
church. They may do lots of other things while they are "watching"
television -- accept an incoming phone call, prepare breakfast, eat, do dishes,
get ready to go out, etc.</p>

<p>Undoubtedly the most reliable study to date is one conducted in 1985 by the
Nielsen Company for televangelist Pat Robertson's Christian Broadcasting
Network (Clark and Virts, 1985). CBN's <hi rend="italic">The 700 Club</hi>, hosted by
Robertson, is broadcast five days a week for 90 minutes, or a total of
seven-and-a-half

<pb n="71"/>

hours per week. This study took into account such
factors as duplication (i.e., that some viewers watch more than one religious
program) and the length of time a program might be watched (i.e., in its
entirety, for a quarter-hour only). The highlights of the CBN/Nielsen study
showed among other things:</p>

<p>- The cumulative audience sizes were significantly larger for the
ten programs studied than were the average quarter-hour audiences.</p>

<p>- The average quarter-hour audience size for <hi rend="italic">The 700 Club,</hi> using
Nielsen's conventional measure, was 424,500 households. The cumulative 90
minute daily audience was 2,547,500 households. The weekly total was 7,216,500,
and the monthly grand total of viewers came to 16,300,000. In a word, the daily
cumulative audience is 6 times larger than the average quarter-hour, the weekly
audience 38 times larger.</p>

<p>- Pat Robertson's <hi rend="italic">700 Club</hi> program had a weekly audience of 12
million viewers, or 29 million cumulative viewers in a single month. On any
given day 4.4 million Americans watched hi show -- many times more persons than
Paul of Tarsus ever witnessed to in the First Century A.D. after he left the
road to Damascus as Christianity's most famous missionary.</p>

<p>- The top 10 television programs had an average quarter-hour audience of
just under 8 million. The cumulative figure for a week comes to 27 million and
for the month it is measured at 68 million!</p>

<p>The CBN/Nielsen study also confirms the suspicion that a significant
proportion of the audience estimates, regardless of the method of measurement,
consist of duplication, that is, multiple counting of people. Still, the total
cumulation of religious television viewed is far from insignificant.</p>

<p>The cumulated monthly audience for the top ten religious programs was 67.7
million households, but the unduplicated cum is 34.1 million households. On a
monthly basis, thus, the duplicated cum is 98% larger. Nielsen estimates a
total of 85.9 million TV households in America (<hi rend="italic">Washington Post</hi>11/13/85).
In essence, the unduplicated figure for an average week is 21%.</p>

<p>The answer to the question "Is anybody listening?" is an
unequivocal YES! The audiences are not as huge as some of the televangelists
and their supporters were maintaining prior to the introduction of Nielsen and
Arbitron. But just as certainly, neither are the audiences as small as some of
their adversaries would like the American public to believe.</p>

<p>And this brings us back full cycle to the politicized nature of religious
television audience statistics. In 1980 it was the perceived potential of
mobilizing viewers for political purposes that made Americans conscious of
audience size. Now, beyond just the infighting of liberals and conservatives,
audience size has taken on a political significance of its own.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="4" id="d7">
<head><hi rend="bold">4. TELEVANGELISM AND THE COMING CULTURAL REVOLUTION<lb/>
IN AMERICA</hi></head>

<p>The electronic communications revolution, of which televangelists are a
part, is reshaping American religion. This technological supertrend inundates
the country's images, presented in alluring new packages that are both
fascinating and yet superficial. The result is a cultural revolution, altering
the values and lifestyles of many Americans and yet also creating the
undercurrents of a backlash.</p>

<p>One specific effect is political mobilization. In this sense televangelists
have played an important role, for they have taken advantage of the
decontextualized nature of much mass communications information to help
crystallize a partisan constituency.</p>

<p>Television, transistors, microchips, videotapes, computers, and space
satellites have made the phenomenological construction and managing of news,
according to professional journalistic norms and commercial requirements, a
series of disjointed happenings without contexts. Pace and depth of news
coverage are too rapid and shallow, respectively, to deal adequately with much
of the flow of events. The recurring and significant images of television, in
particular, pivot on impressions and relatively little substance.</p>

<p>Mass media does not expand our knowledge about particular subjects nearly so
much as it selects certain issues and events upon which to focus, however
transiently, viewer attention. Whatever else, the images on the telescreen must
sustain interest so that the viewer does not switch channels. To guard against
boredom, the images must be fast-paced, thus building in the inevitability of
superficiality.</p>

<p>This pessimistic evaluation of American's mass media news coverage is not
ours alone. Indeed, it is the consensus of virtually all social scientists who
have researched journalism and television (e.g., Altheide, 1976; Badikian,
1971; Epstein, 1975, 1974; Gans, 1980; Parenti, 1986; Schwartz, 1983; Tuchman,
1978). Added to it are the religious indifference and even irreligion of the
average media professional (see, e.g., Hadden and Shupe, forthcoming) which
renders he or she unable to appreciate news in any but a secular, skeptical
perspective.</p>

<p>The result is that, faced with new religious events or trends unfolding,
many media communicators react with a mixture of professional cynicism,
ignorance, and bemusement. And American evangelical/conservative Christians
have had to confront a mass media which presents news devoid of any meaning for
the religious values which otherwise permeate all aspects of their lives.</p>

<p>The usual break-neck speed of the electronic media's handling of news is one
important reason why twentieth century conservative Christians in the U.S. have
had to wait until recently to be mobilized for social change. Secular
television in particular has dealt with many moral and political topics,
usually out of context and certainly not in any explicitly Christian
perspective. This fact worked against evangelical Christians crystallizing
their sentiments and opinions about national and international developments.</p>

<pb n="73"/>

<p>Until now evangelicals who did persist in interpreting their
world along Christian lines (e.g., putting a biblical slant on issues such as
prayer and curriculum content in public schools, national economic policies, or
U.S. military presence in the Middle East) found themselves estranged from the
secular news establishment. Previously, these were difficult times in which to
maintain a coherent Christian worldview when the mass media offered no
worldview at all.</p>

<p>The ultimate political significance of American televangelism is that it has
served as a crucible, or rallying point, within (or around) which the
grievances, concerns, and worldviews of evangelical Christians could coalesce.
Televangelism has provided conservative Christians with entertainment, worship,
news and interpretation without depending on the secular mass media. Grassroots
supporters can be tapped directly through telephone lines and by mail.
Consciousness-of-kind can be raised and reinforced on a daily basis, and it can
all be done within a religious context not accountable to established churches
or denominations.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="5" id="d8">
<head><hi rend="bold">5. THE FUTURE OF TELEVANGELISM</hi></head>

<p>Televangelism, largely an American phenomenon, has two features:</p>

<p>First, various televangelists have been aggressively expanding their
broadcast ministries around the world. Pat Robertson, for example, has his
programming beamed to 43 countries, five days a week. Many of these are Third
World nations where the biblical apocalyptic and millenial themes of many
conservative televangelists are popularly received.</p>

<p>Expansion of the electric church in the USA has shown no signs of slowing,
particularly since the widespread availability of cable television. As
satellite communications become more common, even in the world's more remote
regions, it is likely that "electronic religion" will grow, perhaps
taking on indigenous forms when local regions incorporate it into their own
developing communications systems.</p>

<p>Second, televangelism deals with the ultimate values and grievances of life,
and inevitably it becomes a critic of the secular status quo as well as a
prophetic voice of change. It can become the center point towards which
individual discontent can gravitate. And televangelists -- who are so adroit at
building commitments for financial support -- can channel such discontent for
political purposes. The political potential of televangelism is only now
beginning to be realized in North America. That too may change with its
expansion around the globe.</p>

<pb n="74"/>

</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

