<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HapTols"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;

]>

<TEI.2 id="HapTols">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Tolstoy's "Kreutzer Sonata"</title>
<title type="sort">tolstoys kreutzer sonata</title>
<author>Hapgood, Isabel F.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>On-Line Tolstoy Library</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">22</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HapTols</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476025</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Tolstoy's "Kreutzer Sonata"</title>
<title level="j">The Nation</title>
<title type="sort">tolstoys kreutzer sonata</title>
<author>Isabel F. Hapgood</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>J. H. Richards</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1890">1890</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>First published in The Nation, Vol. 50 (April 17, 1890): 313-15.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1890-04-17">April 17, 1890</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-07">July 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Matthew G. Kirschenbaum</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI.2-conformant header and tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="work" id="d3"> <pb n="313" id="HapTols313"/>
<head>Tolstoi's "Kreutzer Sonata."</head>

<p>NIEDERDORF, TYROL, March 29, 1890</p>

    <p>What are the legitimate bounds of realism?  To what
point is it permissible to describe in repulsive detail
the hideous and unseemly things of this world, simply
because they exist, when it is quite impossible to say
what the effect will be upon thousands of people to whom
such description conveys the first knowledge of the
existence of evil?  It has been proved that public
executions, far from inspiring horror of the deeds which
led to them, and deterring others from the commission of
like deeds, through fear of the result thus presented,
actually give rise to crimes copied after those which are
thus brought to general attention.  The same thing is true
in the case of crimes which are minutely described in the
newspapers.  But books?  On the whole, although a
sensational realistic book may never reach as many people
as an article published in the popular newspaper, it
probably produces as much effect because of the weight and
respectability which the binding and comparatively high
price give to it.</p><p>
    One has occasion to reflect upon this topic rather
frequently in these days of "psychological" romances; but
it is not often necessary, I think, to meditate so
seriously as one is forced to do over Count Lyoff
Tolstoi's last story.</p><p>
    When I first reached Russia, in the autumn of 1887, I
heard that Count Tolstoi was writing a new tale:  it began
on the railway, and a man murdered his wife, and it was to
be of the searching psychological type exemplified by Ivan
Ilyitch.  So much seemed to be known in well-informed
circles.  I asked no questions when I made the Count's
acquaintance a year later.  But one evening last July,
during a visit I made to Yasnaya Polyana, at the
Countess's invitation, the Count spoke to me of his story
as being near completion, and asked me to translate it
when it should be finished.  I promised, and inquired
whether it was in a condition for me to read.  "You may
read the last version if you like," he answered, "but I
would rather have you wait."  His wife showed me sheets of
the fourth version, which she was then copying, and
advised me not to waste time in reading it, as it was
quite likely that he might suddenly see the subject in a
totally different light, and write it all over again from
that point of view.  So I read nothing, asked no
questions, and waited, being informed from time to time
that the book was progressing.  How many different
versions were finally made, I do not know, but this winter
one of these versions began to make the rounds in
Petersburg.  The solitary manuscript flew rapidly from
hand to hand.  I was warned, however, that it or any copy
from it would be imperfect, incomplete, and not approved
by the author, who was at work upon the final version.  I
contented myself with the verdict of those who were too
impatient to wait, and who had not been promised the first
complete copy, as I had been.  That verdict was,
"Shocking!" "Beauties mingled with horrors," and so forth.
It was said that it was not allowed to be printed -the
usual cry; but, as there is nothing religious or political
in it, its morality must have been the cause of the
prohibition, if true.</p><p>
    At length I received the first copy of the genuine
story (the second went to the Danish translator), with the
information that, although the substance was nearly
identical with that of the version which had already been
circulating, and which was said to be in process of
translation into foreign languages, the execution had been
so altered that "not one stone was left upon another" in
some places, while in others whole pages, and even
chapters, had been completely rewritten by the author.
My copy was corrected by the author especially with a view
to translation, and was, therefore, to be regarded as the
only one sanctioned by him for rendering into other
tongues, and this version is yet unattainable in St.
Petersburg.</p><p>
    Why, then, do I not translate a work from the famous
and much-admired Russian author?  Because, in spite of due
gratitude to Count Tolstoi for favoring me with the first
copy, and in spite of my faith in his conviction that such
treatment of such a subject is needed and will do good, I
cannot agree with him.  It recalls the fable of his
countryman, Kriloff, about the man who borrowed his
neighbor's water cask, used it for wine, and returned it
impregnated with vinous fumes to such a degree that the
unfortunate lender was obliged to throw it away, after
using every possible means, during the space of two years,
to expel the taint so that the water should be pure once
more.</p><p>
    "Too frank and not decent," was one of the Petersburg
verdicts upon this Kreutzer Sonata.  This is so true that,
although thus forewarned, I was startled at the idea that
it could possibly be beneficial, and, destroying the
translation which I had begun, I wrote promptly to decline
the task.  It is probable that the author and his blindly
devoted admirers will consider that I have committed an
unpardonable sin.  But they must remember that his
"comedy", The Realm of Darkness, although it was acted in
private, in high Petersburg society, and in public in
Paris, has never been translated into English, so far as I
am aware, at least.  I yield to no one in my admiration
for and appreciation of Tolstoi's genius, as displayed in
certain of his works.  I tried to get American publishers
to bring out War and Peace and Anna Karenin in 1881, five
years before American readers were treated to the mangled
versions of those works through the French.  They
declined, and one noted Boston publisher said, with great
frankness:  "No one in Russia knows how to write except
Turgeneff, and he is far above the heads of Bostonians."
I predicted a change of opinion, and if I am now morally
compelled to appear unfaithful to my own former
admiration, my regret is certainly more deep and sincere
than even the regret of those who merely repent their
failure to grasp an opportunity for making money, or of
those who, consciously or unconsciously, follow the
literary fashion of the hour.</p><p>
    But I will turn to the book.  After making   <pb n="314" id="HapTols314"/>    due
allowance for the ordinary freedom of speech, which has
greater latitude in Russia (as elsewhere in Europe) than
is customary in America, I find the language of the
Kreutzer Sonata to be too excessive in its candor.  At the
same time I admit that if that subject was to be treated
in that way, no other language would have answered the
purpose.  I mention this first because it is the first
thing which strikes the reader, and because it is also the
special thing which hovers over the horrors of the tale
with an added dread, and lingers long behind in the
reader's mind, like a moral bad taste in the mouth.  Next,
the style and construction.  The construction is good, as
is usual with the author.  The style errs in the direction
in which all his books are faulty, viz., repetition.  The
unnecessary repetition of words or phrases occurs in his
greatest works, while in the later, the polemical,
writings, it has become greatly exaggerated.  It forms a
feature of this book, and although it gives strength at
times, it is too marked on the whole.  One must think that
this tautology is deliberate on the author's part, since
he is never in haste to publish uncorrected matter; but
the result is harshness, which increases with every fresh
work.  Nevertheless, the book is well written.  And the
story?  It is that of a man who kills his wife out of
jealousy for a semi-professional violinist, who plays
Beethoven's Kreutzer Sonata with her one evening.</p><p>
    The author begins by narrating how he is making a long
journey by rail.  In the compartment with him are a lawyer
and a lady, masculine in appearance and attire, who
converse, and a gray-haired man with brilliant eyes, who
avoids all attempts to talk with him and utters a peculiar
sound from time to time.  A merchant and a clerk enter the
railway carriage at one of the stations.  A partly
inaudible conversation between the masculine lady and the
lawyer about some woman who has fallen out with her
husband, leads the lawyer to remark upon the amount of
attention which is being bestowed all over Europe upon the
question of divorce, and to say that there was nothing of
the sort in olden days.  The merchant answers him that
there were cases even in old times, but they were less
frequent; and people had become too "cultured" nowadays.
In the discussion which ensues, the merchant advocates the
old-fashioned arrangement of marriages by parents, and
strict government on the part of the husband, as most
conducive to wedded happiness, alleging that love will
come in due season.  The masculine lady argues that it is
stupid to join in marriage two people who do not love each
other and then feel surprised if discord ensues between
them, and that the day for such unions is past.  The
merchant maintains that the day for obeying the New
Testament rule, "Let the wife fear her husband," will
never pass away; that although unfaithfulness, which is
assumed to be impossible on the part of the wife, may
happen in other classes, in the merchant class it does not
happen, and that the carouses of married men at the fair,
which the narrator has heard him relating, and of which he
reminds him, form a special topic which must be excluded
from the discussion.</p><p>
    Here the merchant leaves the train, but the
conversation is continued by the passenger with gray hair
and brilliant eyes inquiring to what sort of love the
masculine lady has reference.  What is "true love," and
how long must it last -a month, two days, or half an hour
-when it has been defined as the preference for some one
man or woman above all other men or women in the world!
He contends that only in romances does this preference
last for a lifetime, as per theory; whereas in real life
it endures for a year, generally much less, and is felt by
every man for every pretty woman; also, that this love is
never mutual, and if it were, and if it lasted a lifetime
on one side, it would not on the other.  Identity of
ideals, spiritual likeness, he does not admit as a ground
for entering upon marriage.  He gives a brief sketch of
the manner, in his opinion, in which marriages are entered
upon, winding up:  "And the result of this is that
frightful hell which makes men take to drink, shoot
themselves, poison, and murder themselves and each other."</p><p>
    The lawyer, with a view to putting an end to the
unseemly conversation, replies that "there are undoubtedly
critical episodes in married life."  Whereupon the speaker
remarks:  "I see that you recognize me.  I am Pozdnisheff,
the man with whom occurred the critical episode of
murdering his wife."  In fact, no one knows anything of
him, but the lawyer and masculine lady change into another
compartment as soon as possible, while Pozdnisheff offers
to withdraw if his presence is disagreeable to the
narrator.  Finding that it is not, he offers to while away
the night by relating the story of his life.  I may remark
here, in view of the above, that the author gives not a
hint of his own opinion as to which is preferable, a
marriage of love or a marriage de convenience, and also that
some of the points suggested do not seem to be answered
thereafter.</p><p>
     Pozdnisheff begins his tale with his introduction to
evil at the age of sixteen.  Shorn of digressions, his
story would be brief.  But the digressions attack many
accepted views of things -or views which he says are
accepted.  The present order of society and life, modes of
marriage, dress, and so forth, form the topics of these
digressions.  Pozdnisheff states that he has taken to
analyzing the subject since his own life reached a climax
in his crime.  Many of these remarks I recognize as
substantially identical with attacks on those subjects
contained in all the author's serious writings.  The
sentence, "I never see a woman clad in ball attire that I
do not feel like shouting, `Police!' and ordering her to
be removed as dangerous," closely corresponds to former
utterances upon low-necked dresses and so on.  He repeats
former denunciations of higher education for women, but,
astonishing to relate, instead of winding up with the
moral that women should devote themselves solely to
becoming the mothers of the largest possible families, he
praises the Shakers because they do not marry, and
declares that woman will only rise to a higher plane,
cease to rule in false ways as an offset to oppression,
and acquire her full rights, when virginity shall have
become the highest ideal of womanhood.</p><p>
    I am tempted to a personal digression at this point.
Count Tolstoi one day praised the Shakers in this manner
before a table full of people.  I was afraid to ask him
his meaning, lest he should explain in detail, so I
questioned his wife in private as to whether this new
departure was not somewhat inconsistent with his
previously advocated views on woman's vocation.  She
replied:  "Probably it is inconsistent; but my husband
changes his opinions every two years, you know."  The
explanation which venture to offer is, that just at that
time he was reading Mr. Boswell's An Undiscovered Country,
and that he is impressionable.  At all events, however
clearly one can understand from these too frank
digressions what a man should not do, it is quite
impossible to comprehend how he thinks a woman should
dress, behave, and live.</p><p>
    Returning to the thread of his story, Pozdnisheff
relates how he proposed for his wife after a very brief
acquaintance, fascinated by her jersey, her well-dressed
hair, and a boating excursion, and adds that, had it not
been for the tailors who dressed her well, and the close
jersey, etc., he should never have married.  This does not
agree with the statement that all through his vicious
bachelorhood he had firmly intended to marry if he could
find any one good enough for him.  An interesting point
here is that he shows his betrothed his bachelor diary,
just as Levin shows his to Kitty in Anna Karenin, and with
precisely the same effect, only less well told.  The
repetition of this incident and the probable rarity of
such diaries seem to hint at a personal experience.</p><p>
    They are married.  The description of the honeymoon
and of their married life nearly up to the date of the
final catastrophe is, like what precedes, unquotable.
Suffice it to say that they quarrel promptly and continue
to quarrel frequently and fiercely, eventually using their
five children as moral battering rams, so to speak,
against each other.   This last is very well done.  At
about the age of thirty, his wife becomes plump and
prettier, and begins to take an interest again in pretty
clothes.  His mad jealousy interprets this into a quest
for a lover, though there are no proofs of such a thing
even alleged.  The description of his jealousy is,
however, the best part of the book.  Presently the object
for jealousy for whom the husband has been on the lookout,
makes his appearance in the person of a handsome young
man, of good family, who has been educated in Paris by a
relative, as he has no money, and who has become a very
fine and semi-professional violinist.  The young man comes
to call on his old acquaintance, Pozdnisheff, on his
return to his native land.  Pozdnisheff instantly fixes
upon him, in his own mind, as the fated lover.
Nevertheless, or rather in consequence of this, he is
unusually cordial, introduces the musician to his wife
(quite unnecessarily), and begs him to bring his violin
that very evening and play duets with her.  The musician
comes, behaves with perfect propriety, as Pozdnisheff
admits, but jealousy causes him to see what he expects.
He urges the musician to dine and play at his house on the
following Sunday, still impelled by the fancies of his own
disordered brain.  The musician accepts; but, having
called in the interim to decide upon the proper music to
present to the company, he drives Pozdnisheff to such a
pitch of unreason that the latter uses vile language to
his innocent wife and throws things at her, whereupon she
promptly retires and takes poison.</p><p>
    She is rescued, a reconciliation ensues, the dinner
comes off, and the Kreutzer Sonata in the evening is a
great success upon the violin and piano.  But the
husband's jealousy and imagination are all alive, and
interpret every glance of the players to suit himself.  On
taking leave that evening, the musician bids Pozdnisheff
and his wife a final farewell.  Pozdnisheff is going to
the country on business, and the musician says that he
shall leave Moscow himself before the former's return,
intimating that he shall not call upon Madame during her
husband's absence.  Pozdnisheff goes to the country in a
tranquil frame of mind, but a letter from his wife, in
which she mentions that the musician has called to fetch
her the music he promised, sets his jealousy aflame again.
He hastens back to Moscow, finds the musician eating
supper with his wife, and murders her.  On trial he is
acquitted on the plea of "justifiable homicide" and when
the narrator of   <pb n="315" id="HapTols315"/>   the story meets him in the train, he is on
his way to a small estate in one of the southern
governments, his children remaining with his dead wife's
sister.</p><p>
    The whole book is a violent and roughly worded attack
upon the evils of animal passion.  In that sense, it is
moral.  Translation, even with copious excisions, is
impossible, in my opinion, and also inadvisable.  The men
against whom it is directed will not mend their ways from
the reading of it, even if they fully grasp the idea that
unhappiness and mad jealousy and crime are the outcome of
their ways, as Pozdnisheff is made to say in terms as
plain as the language will admit of, and in terms much
plainer than are usually employed in polite society.  On
the other hand, the book can, I am sure, do no good to the
people at whom it is not launched.  It is decidedly a case
where ignorance is bliss, and where uncontaminated minds
will carry away a taint which a few will be able to throw
off, but which will linger with the majority as the wine
of the fable lingered in the cask meant for pure water.
Such morbid psychology can hardly be of service, it seems
to me, much as I dislike to criticise Count Tolstoi.</p>

<signed>ISABEL F. HAPGOOD</signed>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

