<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HarDime"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="HarDime">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"The Dime Novel in American Life"</title>
<title type="sort">the dime novel in american life</title>
<author>Harvey, Charles M.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">36</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HarDime</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476027</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"The Dime Novel in American Life"</title>
<title type="sort">the dime novel in american life</title>
<author>Charles M. Harvey</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Atlantic Monthly (Houghton, Mifflin and Company)</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston and New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1907">1907</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Vol. 100, pp. 37-45.</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Checked against University of Virginia library copy: AP2 A8</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1907">1907</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction; prose</term>
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-06">June 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header and minimal TEI tagging</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="section" n="1" id="d3"><pb n="37"/>
<head>I</head>

<p>ARE not more crimes perpetrated these days in the name of the
dime novels than Madame Roland ever imagined were committed in the
name of liberty?  It looks that way.  Nearly every sort of
misdemeanor into which the fantastic element enters, from train
robbery to house-burning, is laid to them.
</p><p>But these offending books must be only base counterfeits of
the originals of their name.  When the average American of fifty
years of age or upward hears about dime novels he thinks of
Beadle's.  They were the first and the best of their order.
Although nearly all of them bubbled over with thrills, they were
not of a character to provoke breaches of the peace.  For a few
years they had a great run, incited many imitations, all of a lower
grade; and at length, after suffering a gradual deterioration in
quality, dropped out under the competition.  Many of Beadle's
original novels deserved the social and financial conquests which
they won.
</p><p>What boy of the sixties can ever forget Beadle's novels!  To
the average youngster of that time the advent of each of those
books seemed to be an event of world consequence.  The day which
gave him his first glimpse of each of them set itself apart forever
from the roll of common days.  How the boys swarmed into and
through stores and news-stands to buy copies as they came hot from
the press!  And the fortunate ones who got there before the supply
gave out &mdash; how triumphantly they carried them off to the rendezvous,
where eager groups awaited their arrival!  What silver-tongued
orator of any age or land ever had such sympathetic and
enthusiastic audiences as did the happy youths at those trysting-places, who were detailed to read those wild deeds of forest,
prairie, and mountain!
</p><p>And how those heroes and heroines and their allies, their
enemies and their doings, cling to the memory across the gulf of
years!  The writer of this article has a far more vivid picture of
some of the red and white paladins whom he met in Beadle's pages
than he has of any of Red Cloud's, Spotted Tail's, or Black
Kettle's fierce raiders, whom he saw at unpleasantly close range,
or of the white warriors who alternately defeated them and were
defeated by them, in the irruptions into Kansas, Nebraska, the
Dakotas, and Wyoming, in the later sixties and early seventies.
through Beadle's hypnotic spell, &mdash; </p>
<l>     "Bliss was it in that dawn to be alive,</l>
<l>      But to be young was very heaven."</l>
<p>Soon after the middle of the nineteenth century the Beadles
began selling ten cent books, each a complete work in its field.
They comprised manuals of games of many kinds, family medicine,
etiquette, letter-writing, dreams, cookery, prose and poetical
quotations, and so on.  Most of these attained such a sale that the
publication of little books on American adventure suggested itself.
</p><p>Irwin P. Beadle, his brother Erastus F. Beadle, and Robert
Adams were the founders of the Beadle publications.  Orville J.
Victor was the editor.  Beadle's dime novels, issued once in each
month at first, but much oftener subsequently, made their
appearance in 1860.  Many Americans who were old enough to read at
that time remember 1860 better from that circumstance than they do
because it was the year of Lincoln's election and the secession of
South Carolina.
</p><p>These little books ranged from 25,000

<pb n="38"/>
to 30,000 words,
or about a third of the average bound novel of to-day.
Conveniently shaped for the pocket, they promptly became an
inseparable part of the outfit of the boy (and to some extent of
the girl also) of the period.  Their paper covers were salmon-colored.  And they were just as free from yellowness on the inside
as they were on the outside.
</p><p>Orville J. Victor organized victory for the house of Beadle.
He selected some writers of ability and standing to contribute to
his series.  He discovered other writers who made reputations in
higher fields of literature afterward.  He invented a few writers
who quickly "made good."  Rules of possibility, morality, and
action in the narrative were laid down by him, which all writers
had to observe.  Mr. Victor himself, who, at the age of eighty, is
to-day not only alive but also mentally and physically alert, had
done some good journalistic and literary work before the first of
Beadle's novels was issued.  He had edited two or three papers, was
a leading contributor to <hi rend="italic">Graham's Magazine</hi>, a well known
periodical of the days just before the Civil War, and had written
some short biographies of Paul Jones, Israel Putnam, and other
American heroes.
</p><p>A contributor to the <hi rend="italic">North American Review</hi>, writing a
little over forty years ago in that periodical, said this: &mdash;
</p><p>"A young friend of ours was recently suffering from that most
harassing of complaints, convalescence, of which the remedy
consists in copious draughts of amusement, prescribed by the
patient.  Literature was imperatively called for, and administered
in the shape of Sir Walter Scott's novels.  These did very well for
a day or two, when, the convalescence running into satiety of the
most malignant type, a new remedy was demanded, and the clamor de
profundis arose: 'I wish I had a dime novel.'  The coveted
medicament was obtained, and at once took vigorous hold of the
system."
</p><p>That was a typical boy of the sixties.  There were millions
like him, as well as many thousands of girls, back in the spacious
times of Abraham Lincoln.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Malaeska, the Indian Wife of the White Hunter</hi>, by Mrs. Ann
S. Stephens, published in the summer of 1860, was the first of
Beadle's dime novels.  Although forgotten long since, Mrs. Stephens
was as well known to the literary world of that year as Edith
Wharton or Mrs. Deland is to that of 1907, and she was much better
known to the social world than is either of these writers.
</p><p>Like many greater novelists of the olden day, &mdash; Scott, Cooper,
and others, &mdash; Mrs. Stephens began her chapters with a poetical
quotation; but she departed from most of her contemporaries and
predecessors in rejecting the "happy ending."  The time of the
tale, the eighteenth century, saw a large part of the country east
of the Alleghenies still in possession of the red man.  After her
father killed her white husband, Malaeska carried their child to
her father-in-law Danforth in New York City a town which was more
familiar with sights of the blanket Indian then than Tahlequah or
Pawhuska is to-day), was prevented by Danforth from revealing her
relationship, and went back alone to her tribe.  Years afterward
she returned, met her son just as he was about to be wedded, told
him of his Indian blood, and in the general catastrophe he killed
himself and she died.
</p><p>The plot was crude, but there was action in it.  Editor Victor
always insisted on action in his stories.  In Malaeska herself
there was some vitality.  A little of the aroma of the forest swept
through the book's pages.  Mrs. Stephens received $250 for the
story; but the compensation for these tales usually ranged from
$100 to $150.
</p><p>Harry Cavendish's <hi rend="italic">Privateer Cruise</hi>, Mrs. Metta V. Victor's
<hi rend="italic">Backwoods Bride</hi>, and Col. A. J. H. Duganne's <hi rend="italic">Massasoit's
Daughter</hi> were a few of the best known of the earlier Beadle's.
Mrs. Victor was the wife of the editor of the series, and

<pb n="39"/>
she had won some reputation as a writer before she appeared in this
company.  She wrote half a score of stories for the Beadles.  By
far the most popular of them all was <hi rend="italic">Maum Guinea and Her
Plantation Children</hi>.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Maum Guinea</hi> was a tale of slave life, and appeared in the
early part of the Civil War.  It was spirited and pathetic, and had
a good deal of "local color;" its sales exceeded 100,000 copies,
and it was translated into several languages.  "It is as absorbing
as <hi rend="italic">Uncle Tom's Cabin</hi>," was the judgment which Lincoln was said
to have passed on it.  The New York <hi rend="italic">Tribune</hi>, the New York
<hi rend="italic">Evening Post</hi>, and other prominent papers in that day of large
deeds, when newspaper space was valuable, gave some space to Mrs.
Victor's story.
</p><p>One day in the fall of 1860 a bustling youth of twenty crossed
from the wilds of New Jersey, entered the office at 141 William
Street, New York, and laid a manuscript on the desk of Editor
Victor.  It was a great moment in the annals of the house of
Beadle.  The boy was Edward S. Ellis.  The manuscript told the
adventures of <hi rend="italic">Seth Jones, or the Captive of the Frontier</hi>, the
most successful novel which ever bore the Beadle imprint.
</p><p>A few years later Dr. Ellis, who is alive to-day, graduated
from the 10-cent into the $1.50 class of fiction writers, and he
has also, in the past fifth of a century, written histories and
educational works, some of which have been very popular.  His
juveniles, many of which have been translated into several
languages, exceed in number the sixty-seven years of his life.  His
readers, diffused through America, Europe, Asia, Africa, and the
islands of the sea, won't allow him to stop.  As a writer of Indian
tales he easily holds the world's long-distance record.
</p><p>"How de do?  How de do?  Ain't frightened, I hope.  It's
nobody but me, Seth Jones of New Hampshire."
</p><p>As read to-day, these words, for thousands of Americans, will
rouse recollections which will turn time's flight backward several
decades.  This salutation was Seth Jones's introduction to Alfred
Haverland (and likewise to the reader of the story) at Haverland's
clearing in the wilderness of Western New York near the close of
the eighteenth century.  They may also serve to recall, faintly at
least, the woodcut picture on the cover of the book, of a stalwart
bearded man garbed in fringed hunting shirt, fringed breeches, and
coonskin cap, and armed with rifle, powder-horn, and knife.  To-day, costume, armament, and picture would strike the observer as
archaic; but on the scale of their time all were adequate.
</p><p>Seth, who had been a scout among the Green Mountain boys under
Ethan Allen in the war of the Revolution a few years earlier, and
who was fully equipped in the tricks of the fighting frontiersman's
trade, told Haverland that the Indians of the vicinity were about
to go on the war-path again, and his warning was immediately
verified by the capture of Haverland's sixteen-year-old daughter
Ina, and by the burning of Haverland's house just as the latter and
his wife had fled from it to seek refuge at a white settlement
twenty miles away.  Just at this moment Evarard Graham, a
sweetheart of Ina, turned up, and, under Seth's leadership, joined
in the cautious pursuit of the Indians and their captive.  After
some wonderful, though not inherently impossible, adventures,
lasting several days, Ina was recovered, and she and her rescuers
reached the settlement and safety.
</p><p>About this time it was divulged that Seth Jones was a myth,
that his real name was Eugene Morton, and that his uncouth garb and
language were a mask which he assumed in searching the frontier for
his affianced, Mary Haverland, sister of the backwoodsman in the
tale, from whom he had become separated during the Revolutionary
War.  He discovered her soon after he met Alfred at the clearing;
but he postponed revealing himself until the clouds rolled by.
There was a double wedding &mdash; Ina

<pb n="40"/>
and Graham, Mary and Morton &mdash;
with a fiddler and revelry as accompaniments.  And then &mdash;
</p><p>"Slumber, with the exception of the sentinels at the block
house, fell upon the village.  Perhaps the Indians had no wish to
break in upon such a happy settlement, for they made no
demonstration through the night.  Sweetly and peacefully they all
slept.  Sweetly and peacefully they entered on life's duties on the
morrow.  And sweetly and peacefully these happy settlers ascended
and went down the hillside of life."
</p><p>Believing that this tale could be made a "best seller," the
counting-room rose to the occasion with Napoleonic audacity.  One
morning the residents of most of the big towns of the United States
found staring at them from gutters and dead walls the words, "Seth
Jones," which were followed a week afterward by "Who's Seth Jones?"
The book's appearance on the news-stands in immense stacks a few
days later answered that query.  This booming and the plaudits of
its readers quickly exhausted several editions, and sent the sales
ultimately up to more than 600,000 copies, in half a dozen
languages.
</p><p>The Civil War, which started about three quarters of a year
after the advent of Beadle's novels, opened a new and vast market
for them.  In their leisure moments the soldiers craved cheap and
exciting reading.  Beadle bundled it like bales of hay and sent it
to them in carloads.  And, in their rate of increase, the carloads
kept step with the expanding armies.
</p><p>Mrs. Stephens, Col. Duganne, Mrs. Victor, Mrs. Mary A. Denison
(who wrote <hi rend="italic">Chip, the Cave Child</hi>, and a few other novels for
this series) and Dr. Ellis, fairly represented the Beadle
contributors when the corps was at its best estate.  Of all the
persons connected with these publications in their great days, only
Ellis, Mrs. Denison, and Editor Victor are alive to-day.
</p><p>Prosperity killed Beadle.  He would have done better had he
done worse.  The streams of money which flowed to him made 141
William Street seem, to some envious persons, like a branch of
Secretary Chase's United States Treasury.  Rivals sprang up in New
York, Boston, Chicago, and other places, who pandered to passions
which Beadle shunned.  These soon began to take away many of his
patrons, and with the hope of regaining his ascendency he lowered
the tone of his publications.  It was vain.  The days of his
supremacy never returned.
</p><p>The blow which hit Beadle first and hardest came from his own
household.  "Over there is a man," said Erastus F. Beadle, the head
of the firm, one day, to one of his leading contributors, "who will
be content with his routine work forever."  He referred to George
Munro, who was a bookkeeper for the house.  The original partners
had by that time been reduced in number by the withdrawal of Irwin
P. Beadle, leaving in the concern Erastus F. Beadle and Robert
Adams.  Less than a year after Beadle passed this judgment, Munro
stepped out, hunted up Irwin P. Beadle, and the two began
publishing Munro's "Ten Cent Novels."  That was in 1866.  With the
Munro competition began the decline and fall of the house of
Beadle.
</p><p>Munro's novels won a large patronage from the start, and in
connection with these he drifted into other fields of publication,
establishing the <hi rend="italic">Fireside Companion</hi> in 1867, and beginning the
"Seaside Library" in 1877.  The latter contained the work of many
foreign writers of ability.  At the time of his death in 1896 Munro
had amassed a fortune of ten million dollars.
</p><p>Beadle's pocket-form publications were changed into the large
folio page "Beadle's Dime Library" in 1876, and the name Beadle and
Adams still figures on dime and half-dime publications issued by N.
J. Ivers and Company, New York.  But the glory of the house of
Beadle vanished when the pocket-form tales passed on.
</p>
</div1>


<div1 type="section" n="2" id="d4"><pb n="41"/>
<head>II</head>

<p>By the close of the seventies several sorts of "dime," "half-dime," and "nickel" novels appeared, the Indian eventually dropping
out as the reservation corraled him, and the cowboy, the detective,
and the train robber taking his place.  At length the dime novel &mdash; a
term applied to all the cheap fiction indiscriminately &mdash; became an
atrocity.  Many are published to-day in the United States, and
almost as many like them in quality and scope are printed in
England.
</p><p>Not all the dime novels, though, even of to-day, deserve this
epithet.  Between some of them and some of the bound novels the
only recognizable difference is the difference between ten cents
and $1.50.
</p><p>Of the writers of the "dimes" and the "half-dimes" of the past
third of a century the best were Thomas C. Harbaugh, Albert W.
Aiken, Edward L. Wheeler, Joseph W. Badger, Jr., and Col. Prentiss
Ingraham.  There are whole "libraries" of Buffalo Bill "dimes," but
Ingraham wrote most of them.  Bill himself is credited with the
authorship of about a dozen of them.  Among them is <hi rend="italic">Death
Trailer, the Chief of the Scouts, or Life and Love in a Frontier
Fort</hi>.  As Colonel Cody had seen something of life, and possibly of
love, at frontier posts, the reader would presume that this book
would be the "real thing."  It starts out briskly, as most of the
"dimes" did: &mdash;
</p><p>"Mingling with the rumble of wheels and the rattle of hoofs
upon the stone road, came the clear notes of a bugle, piercing the
deepest recesses of the chapparals, and floating far off over the
prairie until the sound died away upon the evening air.  Suddenly
out of a dense piece of timber dashed a horseman, well mounted, and
wearing the uniform of an officer of the cavalry of the United
States army."
</p><p>Dime novel horses never trot or walk, &mdash; they always gallop.
The officer who dashed out of the timber was Col. Hugh Decatur, the
place was Texas, near the Rio Grande, and the colonel, with his
daughter Helen and an escort of four dragoons, was on the way to
Nebraska, where he was to take command of a military post.  After
a breathless succession of encounters with Cortina's Mexican
guerrillas, road agents, renegade jayhawkers and villains of a
promiscuous and desperate order of villainy, &mdash; in which regulators,
avengers of different kinds, British noblemen, and other titled
personages figure, and in which daylight is let into many sorts of
mysteries, &mdash; the end came at Castle Glyndon, in England, where Helen
became Lady Radcliffe.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Injun Dick, Detective, or Tracked from the Rockies to New
York</hi>, is a typical tale by Aiken, who was probably the most
skillful, and nearly the most prolific, of writers of detective
stories.
</p><p>"You have seen your last sunrise, as I am going to shoot."
</p><p>Thus the story opened.  There was no preface.  In dime novels
deeds and not words talk.  Scene: A mining camp on the Bear River,
in southwestern Colorado.  Personages: Dick Talbot, hero of a score
of Aiken's tales; Joe Bowers, another Aiken favorite; Limber Bee,
and Limber's wife, Alethea, "about twenty-five, tall and queenly,
with the most magnificent hair, and eyes black as the raven's
wing."  Limber, drunk as usual, and insanely jealous of Talbot, was
to be the executioner, and Talbot the victim.
</p><p>"You have been trying to separate me from my wife, the
peerless Alethea, and you must die."
</p><p>Right here Joe Bowers's frying-pan, loaded with flapjacks, hit
Limber in the face; he went down under the blow; the bullet
intended for Talbot flew wide of the mark, and Talbot sprang upon
him and held him down until he begged for mercy.  Alethea, angry at
Talbot for sparing Limber, revenged herself subsequently on both by
running away with a mysterious stranger, who assassinated Limber,
and by making off with Talbot's, Bowers's, and Limber's gold,
hidden in their cabin.  Tracked across the

<pb n="42"/>
continent, the
stranger, who turned out to be Malachi Everest, a notorious
burglar, was encountered red-handed in robbing a safe in New York,
and killed by Talbot.
</p><p>Aiken had a record of one story a week for a long time.  When
pressed, Wheeler and Badger often equaled this gait.  Some of the
dime-novel writers had several aliases.  Col. Thomas C. Harbaugh
wrote under his own name and those of Capt. Howard Holmes and Maj.
A. F. Grant (in the "Old Cap. Collier" series).  Though retired
from the dime providing business, Col. Harbaugh is an active
contributor to-day to literary papers in Chicago and other places.
</p><p>The most prolific, however, of all the dime novelists was Col.
Prentiss Ingraham, who wrote more than six hundred cheap stories in
all, besides many plays and poems.  One of his "dimes," forty
thousand words, was written on a "rush" order in twenty-four hours,
and that was before the popularization of the typewriter.  It has
been mentioned here that Ingraham wrote most of the Buffalo Bill
stories.  Ingraham had been an officer in the Confederate army, and
afterward served under Juarez in Mexico, in the Austrian army
against Prussia, in Crete against Turkey, and in part of the Cuban
war of 1868-78 against Spain; and he had traveled widely in Europe,
Asia, and Africa.  He led a far more adventurous life than Buffalo
Bill, and more adventurous than did the hero of almost any of his
own tales.  In <hi rend="italic">A Rolling Stone</hi>, one of Beadle's books, his
friend William R. Eyster, a well-known dime novelist, told some of
the story of Ingraham's life.  In the past quarter of a century the
average compensation to Aiken, Ingraham, and their associates was
$150 for writing "dimes," and $100 for "half-dimes."
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="3" id="d5">
<head>III</head>

<p>What did the dime novel stand for?  What influence did it have
on the minds of its readers?  What forces did it represent in the
evolution of American society?
</p><p>The aim of the original dime novel was to give, in cheap and
wholesome form, a picture of American wild life.  At the time when
it began to be published, 1860, less than fifteen years had passed
since the country's boundary had been pushed from the Sabine, the
Red, and the Arkansas rivers, and the Rocky Mountains, onward to
the Pacific.  In that decade and a half we had gained Texas,
Oregon, New Mexico, and California, and had enlarged the national
area to an extent equal to that of the entire territory east of the
Mississippi.  A real frontier in 1860 along the line of the
Missouri and the Arkansas, with thousands of fighting Indians
beyond that line, and some of them east of it, gave the reader an
ardent concern in the adventures in <hi rend="italic">Malaeska, Seth Jones,
Massasoit</hi>, and other tales which told of life when the frontier
was in New York, Massachusetts, and Pennsylvania.  These tales had
both contemporaneousness and vitality.
</p><p>"As editor I sought the best work of the best writers in that
particular field of fiction," said Mr. Victor a few years ago to
the author of this article.  "All was up to an excellent standard
of literary merit.  The detective and love story came later, when
rank competition on the ten-cent trade made it seem necessary to
introduce these elements.  Almost without exception the original
dime novels were good.  Their moral was high.  All were clean and
instructive."
</p><p>This judgment by the man who shaped these little books will be
accepted by most persons who remember them in their best days.
Ethically they were uplifting.  The hard drinkers, and the
grotesquely profane and picturesquely depraved persons who take
leading roles in many of the dime novels of recent times were
inexorably shut out from their progenitors of Beadle's days.
</p><p>These tales incited a love of reading among the youth of the
country.  Though

<pb n="43"/>
making no pretensions to be historical
novels, they often dealt with historical personages.  Many of the
boys and girls who encountered Pontiac, Boone, the renegade Girty,
Mad Anthony, Kenton, and Black Hawk in their pages were incited to
find out something more about those characters and their times, and
thus they were introduced to much of the nation's story and
geography.  Manliness and womanliness among the readers were
cultivated by these little books, not by homilies, but by example.
It can be truthfully said that the taste and tone of the life of
the generation which grew up with these tales were improved by
them.
</p><p>No age limit was set up among Beadle's readers.  Lincoln was
one of them.  So was Seward, and Henry Wilson of Massachusetts.
Report of a later day had it that Toombs &mdash; who, however, as an
officer of the Confederacy, was on the wrong side to find them
accessible in their early days &mdash; was a devourer of these tales when
he could get at them.  "The man," said Zachariah Chandler, "who
does not enjoy <hi rend="italic">Onomoo, the Huron</hi>, has no right to live."
</p><p>One at least of Beadle's tales registered itself in the
politics of the time.  <hi rend="italic">Maum Guinea</hi>, Mrs. Victor's slavery tale,
which issued at a critical moment in the Civil War, and which,
republished in London (all Beadle's novels were republished in
London until 1866), circulated by the tens of thousands in England,
had a powerful influence in aid of the Union cause at a time when
a large part of the people of that country favored the recognition
of the independence of the Southern Confederacy.  Mr. Victor's own
"Address to the English People," issued at the same time, and in
connection with the London edition of the novels, was widely
distributed in England, and helped to overcome the sentiment which
was clamoring for the breaking of the blockade and the purchase of
Southern cotton for Lancashire's idle mills.
</p><p>"My dear fellow," said Henry Ward Beecher to Mr. Victor
afterward, "your little book and Mrs. Victor's novel were a telling
series of shots in the right spot."  This is testimony which
counts.  Beecher was a special commissioner from Lincoln to England
in 1863, to counteract the hostility to the Union cause in the
Palmerston cabinet and among the aristocracy.
</p><p>The very small claim which the black man ever had upon the
dime novelists ended with Appomattox and emancipation; but the red
man had a far longer and more prosperous career.  While Red Cloud,
Black Kettle, and their compatriots ravaged the frontier, the
Indian tales had an easy ascendancy.  The annihilation of Colonel
Fetterman and one hundred of his troops near Fort Phil Kearney in
1866, and the slaughter of Custer and two hundred and fifty of his
men on the Little Big Horn in 1876, sold forest and prairie stories
by millions of copies.  But that was near the end of the Indian's
service for the fictionists.  The campaign against Chief Joseph and
the Nez Perces in 1877, and the rounding up of Geronimo and the
Apaches in 1886, shut up the last of the descendants of King Philip
and Pontiac on the reservations, and the novelists had to turn to
other fields for material.  Before Sitting Bull's ghost-dance
irruption at Pine Ridge in 1890, the cowboy and detective tales had
supplanted the Indian story in the popular favor.
</p><p>For a few years the Santa Fe trader and the cowboy ran a
flourishing career among the dime novelists.  Soon after the
Mexican war Capt. Mayne Reid, one of the heroes of that conflict,
began his tales of the Southwest &mdash; <hi rend="italic">Rifle Rangers, Scalp Hunters,
Captain of the Rifles</hi>, and the rest of them, &mdash; some of which told
of bloody deeds along the Santa Fe trail, and a few of which were
reprinted among Beadle and Adams's "dimes" and "half-dimes."  Like
most of the early cowboy tales, these stories had Indians among
their leading characters, intermixed with "Greasers."

<pb n="44"/>
</p><p>The alien white ingredient in these tales injected an element
of variety which the youthful reader appreciated.  Reid had seen
the Mexican at close range.  He knew enough of the Mexican language
to make his imprecations and objurgations &mdash; his "Sacre-e-s" and
"Carambas" &mdash; sound real.  This delighted the boy readers, and set
the fashion in profanity which later writers in this field
followed.  Reid, J. E. Badger, Oll Coomes, P. S. Warne, and others,
who told of the wild riders of the plains, red, yellow, and white,
made every foot of ground between the Missouri and the Sierra
Nevadas, and the Arkansas and the Rio Grande, familiar to dime
novel-readers.
</p><p>More than a quarter of a century ago, however, the Atchison,
Topeka and Santa Fe railway ended the days of the old trail and its
story tellers.  Between the railroads which transported the cattle
from the ranges to the stockyards, and the barbed wire fences of
the settlers who are abolishing the ranges, the cowboy as a
picturesque feature of the Western landscape has passed out, and
the dime novel will know him no more.  This leaves the detective in
possession of the stage.
</p><p>In certain directions the detective tale has attractions for
writers and readers beyond those offered by the average Indian
story.  The white "bad man" is more versatile in his badness than
is his red or yellow counterpart.  His field of activities is far
wider.  For the past half century the Indian's operations have been
shut in between the Missouri and the Sierra Nevada Mountains, but
the white crook's ravages have covered the whole landscape between
the two oceans.  Aiken's <hi rend="italic">Black Hoods of the Shasta</hi> made life
exhilarating in the neighborhood of the Golden Gate, but in most of
his most popular tales the action centred in New York.  In Boston,
St. Louis, Philadelphia, New Orleans, St. Paul, and other towns,
the Vidocqs of Harold Payne, William H. Manning, Edward Willett, J.
W. Osbon, and others cut their Gordian knots.
</p><p>Calling the roll of the items in the vast output of Wheeler,
Ingraham, Aiken, and their associates, it would seem that there
could not be enough truth in the United States to last them.  No
complaint of this sort, however, was ever made by any of their
constituents.  In their pages the reader encountered life in all
tints of shade and brightness.  His imagination was kindled.  He
was incited to do things; and commonly the things which he wanted
to do were heroic.
</p><p>There were no problems in any of the dime novels, old or new,
not even in <hi rend="italic">Maum Guinea</hi>.  Duganne's <hi rend="italic">Massasoit</hi> appeared
before psychology was invented.  If a paragraph or two of Arthur
Dimmesdale's soul torture had strayed into any of Beadle's novels,
the whole series would have been ruined.  The things which were
done in those little books were physical, and they were told in
language that made pictures in the mind.  There were no verbal
puzzles in any of them, like those which James or Meredith impose.
Long ago James said novelists ought to make their readers do a
share of the work.  Capt. Mark Wilton, Major S. S. Hall, Dr. Frank
Powell, and their coworkers believed that their duty to their
readers was to entertain them.
</p><p>Between the writer and his constituents there was a bond of
affection which incited him to make them glad to be alive.  In the
mind of every healthy boy there is romance.  For that boy's
entertainment the producer of dime fiction strewed romance through
farm, mining camp, and city street.  Out of his surroundings,
however sordid, the boy was lifted.  He became, to himself, the
centre of the universe.  At the particular spot on the globe on
which he stood all the parallels and the meridians converged.  In
no more intense a degree than this did exaltation ever come to the
Count of Monte Cristo; &mdash; the world was his.  What was Edmond
Dantes's paltry twenty million dollars to the vast treasures,
physical and spiritual, spread out by Osbon before "Plucky Paul,
the Boy Prospector," and his tens

<pb n="45"/>
of thousands or hundreds
of thousands of readers?
</p><p>And the boy got all of this without any prefaces.  The action
began right in the first line.  No little Peterkin ever needed to
ask any Old Kaspar what this was all about.  The battles with
Indians and "Greasers," the capture of road agents and bank
burglars, and the retribution which hit the villain who attempted
to cheat the girl out of her patrimony, told their story in
language so plain that the wayfaring man, though a fool, never made
any mistake in grasping it.
</p><p>From Beadle's days onward most of the dime tales have been
American.  Names, scenes, atmosphere, are familiar.  In reading
them the American boy's soul soared and sang.  This is why the
average youth who found <hi rend="italic">Rob Roy</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Ivanhoe</hi> dull was
immensely entertained by Ellis's <hi rend="italic">Bill Biddon</hi>, or Leon Lewis's
<hi rend="italic">Daredeath Dick, King of the Cowboys</hi>.
</p><p>Were these things all illusions?  Many of them were, yet they
were pleasing illusions.  Illusions jolt us every day, which the
dime novelists never touch, and which we would not want to read
about.  Some of us might like occasionally to see time's clock
turned back to the days when the world was young enough and rich
enough to have illusions that make us glad.
</p><p>Was everything that the dime necromancers told us melodrama?
Much of it unquestionably was.  But an age which has seen a nation
rise from Balboa's isthmus at the wave of a Prospero wand from
Washington; which has recently looked on while a people in the
Caribbean committed suicide; which is watching Nome's argonauts, up
under the Pole Star, rival the glories of the Comstock under the
reign of Mackay, Flood, and O'Brien; and which held its breath in
November, 1906, while Roosevelt and Croker, like Castor and Pollux,
rushed to rescue the nation from a New York editor who had built up
an army in a night, has no right to object to melodrama in fiction.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
