<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HawCant"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="HawCant">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Canterbury Pilgrims</title>
<title type="sort">canterbury pilgrims</title>
<author>Hawthorne, Nathaniel, 1804-1864</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Charles Keller</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">25</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HawCant</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476036</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Canterbury Pilgrims</title>
<title level="m">The Complete Novels and Selected Tales of Nathaniel Hawthorne</title>
<title type="sort">canterbury pilgrims</title>
<author>Nathaniel Hawthorne</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
<name>Norman Holmes Pearson</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>Modern Library Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>pp 1196-1203.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Random House, Inc.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1937">1937</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa Library call number PS 1850 1937</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1851">1851</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-09">September 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" id="d3"> <pb n="1196"/>
<head>THE CANTERBURY PILGRIMS</head>

<p>THE summer moon, which shines in so many a tale, was beaming over
a broad extent of uneven country. Some of its brightest rays were
flung
into a spring of water, where no traveller, toiling, as the writer
has, up
the hilly road beside which it gushes, ever failed to quench his
thirst.
The work of neat hands and considerate art was visible about this
blessed
fountain. An open cistern, hewn and hollowed out of solid stone,
was
placed above the waters, which filled it to the brim, but by some
invisible
outlet were conveyed away without dripping down its sides. Though
the
basin had not room for another drop, and the continual gush of
water
made a tremor on the surface, there was a secret charm that forbade
it
to overflow. I remember, that when I had slaked my summer thirst,
and
sat panting by the cistern, it was my fanciful theory that Nature
could
not afford to lavish so pure a liquid, as she does the waters of
all meaner
fountains.
   <pb n="1197"/>
</p><p>While the moon was hanging almost perpendicularly over this
spot,
two figures appeared on the summit of the hill, and came with
noiseless
footsteps down towards the spring. They were then in the first
freshness
of youth; nor is there a wrinkle now on either of their brows, and
yet
they wore a strange, old-fashioned garb. One, a young man with
ruddy
cheeks, walked beneath the canopy of a broad-brimmed gray hat; he
seemed to have inherited his great-grandsire's square-skirted coat,
and a
waistcoat that extended its immense flaps to his knees; his brown
locks,
also, hung down behind, in a mode unknown to our times. By his side
was a sweet young damsel, her fair features sheltered by a prim
little
bonnet, within which appeared the vestal muslin of a cap; her
closet
long-waisted gown, and indeed her whole attire, might have been
worn
by some rustic beauty who had faded half a century before. But that
there was something too warm and life-like in them, I would here
have
compared this couple to the ghosts of two young lovers who had died
long since in the glow of passion, and now were straying out of
their
graves, to renew the old vows, and shadow forth the unforgotten
kiss of
their earthly lips, beside the moonlit spring.
</p><p>``Thee and I will rest here a moment, Miriam,'' said the
young man,
as they drew near the stone cistern, ``for there is no fear that
the elders
know what we have done; and this may be the last time we shall ever
taste this water.''
</p><p>Thus speaking, with a little sadness in his face, which was
also visible
in that of his companion, he made her sit down on a stone, and was
about to place himself very close to her side; she, however,
repelled him,
though not unkindly.
</p><p>``Nay, Josiah,'' said she, giving him a timid push with her
maiden
hand, ``thee must sit farther off, on that other stone, with the
spring between us. What would the sisters say, if thee were to sit
so close
to me?''
</p><p>``But we are of the world's people now, Miriam,'' answered
Josiah.
</p><p>The girl persisted in her prudery, nor did the youth, in
fact, seem altogether free from a similar sort of shyness; so they
sat apart
from each
other, gazing up the hill, where the moonlight discovered the tops
of a
group of buildings. While their attention was thus occupied, a
party of
travellers, who had come wearily up the long ascent, made a halt to
refresh themselves at the spring. There were three men, a woman,
and
a
little girl and boy. Their attire was mean, covered with the dust
of the
summer's day, and damp with the night-dew; they all looked
woebegone, as if the cares and sorrows of the world had made their
steps
heavier as they climbed the hill; even the two little children
appeared
older
in evil days than the young man and maiden who had first approached
the spring.
</p><p>``Good evening to you, young folks,'' was the salutation of
the travellers; and ``Good evening, friends,'' replied the youth
and
damsel.
</p><p>``Is that white building the Shaker meeting-house?'' asked
one of the
strangers. ``And are those the red roofs of the Shaker village?''
   <pb n="1198"/>
</p><p>``Friend, it is the Shaker village,'' answered Josiah, after
some hesitation.
</p><p>The travellers, who, from the first, had looked suspiciously
at the garb
of these young people, now taxed them with an intention which all
the
circumstances, indeed, rendered too obvious to be mistaken.
</p><p>``It is true, friends,'' replied the young man, summoning up
his courage. ``Miriam and I have a gift to love each other, and we
are
going
among the world's people, to live after their fashion. And ye know
that
we do not transgress the law of the land; and neither ye, nor the
elders
themselves, have a right to hinder us.''
</p><p>``Yet you think it expedient to depart without
leave-taking,'' remarked
one of the travellers.
</p><p>``Yea, ye-a,'' said Josiah, reluctantly, ``because father
Job is a very
awful man to speak with; and being aged himself, he has but little
charity for what he calls the iniquities of the flesh.''
</p><p>``Well,'' said the stranger, ``we will neither use force to
bring you back
to the village, nor will we betray you to the elders. But sit you
here
awhile, and when you have heard what we shall tell you of the world
which we have left, and into which you are going, perhaps you will
turn
back with us of your own accord. What say you?'' added he, turning
to
his companions. ``We have travelled thus far without becoming known
to each other. Shall we tell our stories, here by this pleasant
spring, for
our own pastime, and the benefit of these misguided young lovers?''
</p><p>In accordance with this proposal, the whole party stationed
themselves round the stone cistern; the two children, being very
weary,
fell
asleep upon the damp earth, and the pretty Shaker girl, whose
feelings
were those of a nun or a Turkish lady, crept as close as possible
to the
female traveller, and as far as she well could from the unknown
men.
The same person who had hitherto been the chief spokesman now stood
up, waving his hat in his hand, and suffered the moonlight to fall
full
upon his front.
</p><p>``In me,'' said he, with a certain majesty of
utterance,&mdash;``in me, you
behold a poet.''
</p><p>Though a lithographic print of this gentleman is extant, it
may be
well to notice that he was now nearly forty, a thin and stooping
figure,
in a black coat, out at elbows; notwithstanding the ill condition
of his
attire, there were about him several tokens of a peculiar sort of
foppery,
unworthy of a mature man, particularly in the arrangement of his
hair
which was so disposed as to give all possible loftiness and breadth
to his
forehead. However, he had an intelligent eye, and, on the whole, a
marked countenance.
</p><p>``A poet!'' repeated the young Shaker, a little puzzled how
to understand such a designation, seldom heard in the utilitarian
community
where he had spent his life. ``Oh, ay, Miriam, he means a
varse-maker,
thee must know.''
</p><p>This remark jarred upon the susceptible nerves of the poet;
nor could
he help wondering what strange fatality had put into this young
man's
   <pb n="1199"/>
mouth an epithet, which ill-natured people had affirmed to be more
proper to his merit than the one assumed by himself.
</p><p>``True, I am a verse-maker,'' he resumed, ``but my verse is
no more
than the material body into which I breathe the celestial soul of
thought.
Alas! how many a pang has it cost me, this same insensibility to
the
ethereal essence of poetry, with which you have here tortured me
again,
at the moment when I am to relinquish my profession forever! O
Fate!
why hast thou warred with Nature, turning all her higher and more
perfect gifts to the ruin of me, their possessor? What is the voice
of
song,
when the world lacks the ear of taste? How can I rejoice in my
strength
and delicacy of feeling, when they have but made great sorrows out
of
little ones? Have I dreaded scorn like death, and yearned for fame
as
others pant for vital air, only to find myself in a middle state
between
obscurity and infamy? But I have my revenge! I could have given
existence to a thousand bright creations. I crush them into my
heart,
and
there let them putrefy! I shake off the dust of my feet against my
countrymen! But posterity, tracing my footsteps up this weary hill,
will cry
shame upon the unworthy age that drove one of the fathers of
American
song to end his days in a Shaker village! ''
</p><p>During this harangue, the speaker gesticulated with great
energy, and,
as poetry is the natural language of passion, there appeared reason
to
apprehend his final explosion into an ode extempore. The reader
must
understand that, for all these bitter words, he was a kind, gentle,
harmless, poor fellow enough, whom Nature, tossing her ingredients
together
without looking at her recipe, had sent into the world with too
much of
one sort of brain, and hardly any of another.
</p><p>``Friend,'' said the young Shaker, in some perplexity,
``thee seemest to
have met with great troubles; and, doubtless, I should pity them,
if&mdash;if
I could but understand what they were.''
</p><p>``Happy in your ignorance!'' replied the poet, with an air
of sublime
superiority. ``To your coarser mind, perhaps, I may seem to speak
of
more important griefs when I add, what I had wellnigh forgotten,
that
I am out at elbows, and almost starved to death. At any rate, you
have
the advice and example of one individual to warn you back; for I am
come hither, a disappointed man, flinging aside the fragments of my
hopes, and seeking shelter in the calm retreat which you are so
anxious
to leave.''
</p><p>``I thank thee, friend,'' rejoined the youth, ``but I do not
mean to be a
poet, nor, Heaven be praised! do I think Miriam ever made a varse
in
her life. So we need not fear thy disappointments. But, Miriam,''
he
added, with real concern, ``thee knowest that the elders admit
nobody
that has not a gift to be useful. Now, what under the sun can they
do
with this poor varse-maker?''
</p><p>``Nay, Josiah, do not thee discourage the poor man,'' said
the girl, in
all simplicity and kindness. ``Our hymns are very rough, and
perhaps
they may trust him to smooth them.''
</p><p>Without noticing this hint of professional employment, the
poet
   <pb n="1200"/>
turned away, and gave himself up to a sort of vague reverie, which
he
called thought. Sometimes he watched the moon, pouring a silvery
liquid
on the clouds, through which it slowly melted till they became all
bright; then he saw the same sweet radiance dancing on the leafy
trees
which rustled as if to shake it off, or sleeping on the high tops
of hills,
or hovering down in distant valleys, like the material of unshaped
dreams; lastly, he looked into the spring, and there the light was
mingling with the water. In its crystal bosom, too, beholding all
heaven reflected there, he found an emblem of a pure and tranquil
breast. He
listened to that most ethereal of all sounds, the song of crickets,
coming in
full choir upon the wind, and fancied that, if moonlight could be
heard,
it would sound just like that. Finally, he took a draught at the
Shaker
spring, and, as if it were the true Castalia, was forthwith moved
to compose a lyric, a Farewell to his Harp, which he swore should
be its
closing
strain, the last verse that an ungrateful world should have from
him.
This effusion, with two or three other little pieces, subsequently
written,
he took the first opportunity to send, by one of the Shaker
brethren, to
Concord, where they were published in the New Hampshire Patriot.
</p><p>Meantime, another of the Canterbury pilgrims, one so
different from
the poet that the delicate fancy of the latter could hardly have
conceived
of him, began to relate his sad experience. He was a small man, of
quick
and unquiet gestures, about fifty years old, with a narrow
forehead, all
wrinkled and drawn together. He held in his hand a pencil, and a
card
of some commission-merchant in foreign parts, on the back of which,
for
there was light enough to read or write by, he seemed ready to
figure
out a calculation.
</p><p>``Young man,'' said he, abruptly, ``what quantity of land do
the Shakers own here, in Canterbury?''
</p><p>``That is more than I can tell thee, friend,'' answered
Josiah, ``but it
is a very rich establishment, and for a long way by the roadside
thee
may guess the land to be ours, by the neatness of the fences.''
</p><p>``And what may be the value of the whole,'' continued the
stranger,
``with all the buildings and improvements, pretty nearly, in round
numbers?''
</p><p>``Oh, a monstrous sum,&mdash;more than I can reckon,'' replied
the young
Shaker.
</p><p>``Well, sir,'' said the pilgrim, ``there was a day, and not
very long ago,
neither, when I stood at my counting-room window, and watched the
signal flags of three of my own ships entering the harbor, from the
East
Indies, from Liverpool, and from up the Straits, and I would not
have
given the invoice of the least of them for the title-deeds of this
whole
Shaker settlement. You stare. Perhaps, now, you won't believe that
I
could have put more value on a little piece of paper, no bigger
than the
palm of your hand, than all these solid acres of grain, grass, and
pasture-land would sell for?''
</p><p>``I won't dispute it, friend,'' answered Josiah, ``but I
know I had
   <pb n="1201"/>
rather have fifty acres of this good land than a whole sheet of thy
paper.''
</p><p>``You may say so now,'' said the ruined merchant, bitterly,
``for my
name would not be worth the paper I should write it on. Of course,
you
must have heard of my failure?''
</p><p>And the stranger mentioned his name, which, however mighty
it might
have been in the commercial world, the young Shaker had never heard
of among the Canterbury hills.
</p><p>``Not heard of my failure!'' exclaimed the merchant,
considerably
piqued. ``Why, it was spoken of on 'Change in London, and from
Boston to New Orleans men trembled in their shoes. At all events,
I
did fail,
and you see me here on my road to the Shaker village, where,
doubtless
(for the Shakers are a shrewd sect), they will have a due respect
for my
experience, and give me the management of the trading part of the
concern, in which case I think I can pledge myself to double their
capital in
four or five years. Turn back with me, young man; for though you
will
never meet with my good luck, you can hardly escape my bad.''
</p><p>``I will not turn back for this,'' replied Josiah. calmly,
``any more than
for the advice of the varse-maker, between whom and thee, friend,
I see
a sort of likeness, though I can't justly say where it lies. But
Miriam
and I can earn our daily bread among the world's people as well as
in
the Shaker village. And do we want anything more, Miriam?''
</p><p>``Nothing more, Josiah,'' said the girl, quietly.
</p><p>``Yea, Miriam, and daily bread for some other little mouths,
if God
send them,'' observed the simple Shaker lad.
</p><p>Miriam did not reply, but looked down into the spring, where
she encountered the image of her own pretty face, blushing within
the
prim
little bonnet. The third pilgrim now took up the conversation. He
was a
sunburnt countryman, of tall frame and bony strength, on whose rude
and manly face there appeared a darker, more sullen and obstinate
despondency, than on those of either the poet or the merchant.
</p><p>``Well, now, youngster,'' he began, ``these folks have had
their say, so
I'll take my turn. My story will cut but a poor figure by the side
of
theirs; for I never supposed that I could have a right to meat and
drink,
and great praise besides, only for tagging rhymes together, as it
seems
this man does; nor ever tried to get the substance of hundreds into
my
own hands, like the trader there. When I was about of your years,
I
married me a wife,&mdash;just such a neat and pretty young woman as
Miriam, if that's her name,&mdash;and all I asked of Providence was an
ordinary
blessing on the sweat of my brow, so that we might be decent and
comfortable, and have daily bread for ourselves, and for some other
little
mouths that we soon had to feed. We had no very great prospects
before
us; but I never wanted to be idle; and I thought it a matter of
course
that the Lord would help me, because I was willing to help
myself.''
</p><p>``And didn't He help thee, friend?'' demanded Josiah, with
some eagerness.
   <pb n="2102"/>
</p><p>``No,'' said the yeoman, sullenly; ``for then you would not
have seen
me here. I have labored hard for years; and my means have been
growing narrower, and my living poorer, and my heart colder and
heavier,
all the time; till at last I could bear it no longer. I set myself
down to
calculate whether I had best go on the Oregon expedition, or come
here
to the Shaker village; but I had not hope enough left in me to
begin the
world over again; and, to make my story short, here I am. And now,
youngster, take my advice, and turn back; or else, some few years
hence, you'll have to climb this hill, with as heavy a heart as
mine.''
</p><p>This simple story had a strong effect on the young
fugitives. The misfortunes of the poet and merchant had won little
sympathy from
their
plain good sense and unworldly feelings, qualities which made them
such
unprejudiced and inflexible judges, that few men would have chosen
to
take the opinion of this youth and maiden as to the wisdom or folly
of
their pursuits. But here was one whose simple wishes had resembled
their own, and who, after efforts which almost gave him a right to
claim
success from fate, had failed in accomplishing them.
</p><p>``But thy wife, friend?'' exclaimed the younger man. ``What
became
of the pretty girl, like Miriam? Oh, I am afraid she is dead!''
</p><p>``Yea, poor man, she must be dead,&mdash;she and the children,
too,''
sobbed Miriam.
</p><p>The female pilgrim had been leaning over the spring, wherein
latterly
a tear or two might have been seen to fall, and form its little
circle on
the surface of the water. She now looked up, disclosing features
still
comely, but which had acquired an expression of fretfulness, in the
same
long course of evil fortune that had thrown a sullen gloom over the
temper of the unprosperous yeoman.
</p><p>``I am his wife,'' said she, a shade of irritability just
perceptible in
the sadness of her tone. ``These poor little things, asleep on the
ground,
are two of our children. We had two more, but God has provided
better
for them than we could, by taking them to Himself.''
</p><p>``And what would thee advise Josiah and me to do?'' asked
Miriam,
this being the first question which she had put to either of the
strangers.
</p><p>`` 'Tis a thing almost against nature for a woman to try to
part true
lovers,'' answered the yeoman's wife, after a pause; ``but I'll
speak as
truly to you as if these were my dying words. Though my husband
told
you some of our troubles, he didn't mention the greatest, and that
which
makes all the rest so hard to bear. If you and your sweetheart
marry,
you'll be kind and pleasant to each other for a year or two, and
while
that's the case, you never will repent; but, by and by, he'll grow
gloomy,
rough, and hard to please, and you'll be peevish, and full of
little angry
fits, and apt to be complaining by the fireside, when he comes to
rest
himself from his troubles out of doors; so your love will wear away
by
little and little, and leave you miserable at last. It has been so
with us;
and yet my husband and I were true lovers once, if ever two young
folks
were .''
</p><p>As she ceased, the yeoman and his wife exchanged a glance,
in which
   <pb n="1203"/>
there was more and warmer affection than they had supposed to have
escaped the frost of a wintry fate, in either of their breasts. At
that moment, when they stood on the utmost verge of married life,
one word
fitly
spoken, or perhaps one peculiar look, had they had mutual
confidence
enough to reciprocate it, might have renewed all their old
feelings, and
sent them back, resolved to sustain each other amid the struggles
of the
world. But the crisis passed and never came again. Just then, also,
the
children, roused by their mother's voice, looked up, and added
their
wailing accents to the testimony borne by all the Canterbury
pilgrims
against the world from which they fled.
</p><p>``We are tired and hungry!'' cried they. ``Is it far to the
Shaker village?''
</p><p>The Shaker youth and maiden looked mournfully into each
other's
eyes. They had but stepped across the threshold of their homes,
when
lo! the dark array of cares and sorrows that rose up to warn them
back.
The varied narratives of the strangers had arranged themselves into
a
parable; they seemed not merely instances of woful fate that had
befallen others, but shadowy omens of disappointed hope and
unavailing
toil, domestic grief and estranged affection, that would cloud the
onward
path of these poor fugitives. But after one instant's hesitation,
they
opened their arms, and sealed their resolve with as pure and fond
an
embrace as ever youthful love had hallowed.
</p><p>``We will not go back,'' said they. ``The world never can be
dark to us,
for we will always love one another.''
</p><p>Then the Canterbury pilgrims went up the hill, while the
poet chanted
a drear and desperate stanza of the Farewell to his Harp, fitting
music
for that melancholy band. They sought a home where all former ties
of
nature or society would be sundered, and all old distinctions
levelled,
and a cold and passionless security be substituted for mortal hope
and
fear, as in that other refuge of the world's weary outcasts, the
grave.
The lovers drank at the Shaker spring, and then, with chastened
hopes,
but more confiding affections, went on to mingle in an untried
life.</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

