<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HawHoll"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="HawHoll">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Hollow of the Three Hills</title>
<title type="sort">hollow of the three hills</title>
<author>Hawthorne, Nathaniel, 1804-1864</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Charles Keller</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">13</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HawHoll</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476049</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Hollow of the Three Hills</title>
<title level="m">The Complete Novels and Selected Tales of Nathaniel Hawthorne</title>
<title type="sort">hollow of the three hills</title>
<author>Nathaniel Hawthorne</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
<name>Norman Holmes Pearson</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>Modern Library Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>pp 941-944.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Random House, Inc.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1937">1937</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa Library call number PS 1850 1937</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1837">1837</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-09">September 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="story" id="d3"> <pb n="941"/>
<head>THE HOLLOW OF THE THREE HILLS</head>

<p>IN those strange old times, when fantastic dreams and madmen's
reveries
were realized among the actual circumstances of life, two persons
met together at an appointed hour and place. One was a lady,
graceful in
form
and fair of feature, though pale and troubled, and smitten with an
untimely blight in what should have been the fullest bloom of her
years; the
other was an ancient and meanly-dressed woman, of ill-favored
aspect,
and so withered, shrunken, and decrepit, that even the space since
she began to decay must have exceeded the ordinary term of human
existence.
In the spot where they encountered, no mortal could observe them.
Three
little hills stood near each other, and down in the midst of them
sunk a
hollow basin, almost mathematically circular, two or three hundred
feet
in breadth, and of such depth that a stately cedar might but just
be visible
   <pb n="942"/>
above the sides. Dwarf pines were numerous upon the hills, and
partly fringed the outer verge of the intermediate hollow, within
which
there
was nothing but the brown grass of October, and here and there a
tree
trunk that had fallen long ago, and lay mouldering with no green
successsor from its roots. One of these masses of decaying wood,
formerly
a majestic oak, rested close beside a pool of green and sluggish
water
at the
bottom of the basin. Such scenes as this (so gray tradition tells)
were
once the resort of the Power of Evil and his plighted subjects; and
here,
at midnight or on the dim verge of evening, they were said to stand
round
the mantling pool, disturbing its putrid waters in the performance
of an
impious baptismal rite. The chill beauty of an autumnal sunset was
now
gilding the three hill-tops, whence a paler tint stole down their
sides into
the hollow.
</p><p>``Here is our pleasant meeting come to pass,'' said the aged
crone, ``according as thou hast desired. Say quickly what thou
wouldst have of
me,
for there is but a short hour that we may tarry here.''
</p><p>As the old withered woman spoke, a smile glimmered on her
countenance, like lamplight on the wall of a sepulchre. The lady
trembled, and
cast her eyes upward to the verge of the basin, as if meditating to
return
with her purpose unaccomplished. But it was not so ordained.
</p><p>``I am a stranger in this land, as you know,'' said she at
length.
``Whence I come it matters not; but I have left those behind me
with
whom my fate was intimately bound, and from whom I am cut off
forever.
There is a weight in my bosom that I cannot away with, and I have
come
hither to inquire of their welfare.''
</p><p>``And who is there by this green pool that can bring thee
news from the
ends of the earth?'' cried the old woman, peering into the lady's
face.
``Not from my lips mayst thou hear these tidings; yet, be thou
bold, and
the daylight shall not pass away from yonder hill-top before thy
wish be
granted.''
</p><p>``I will do your bidding though I die,'' replied the lady
desperately.
</p><p>The old woman seated herself on the trunk of the fallen
tree, threw
aside the hood that shrouded her gray locks, and beckoned her
companion to draw near.
</p><p>``Kneel down,'' she said, ``and lay your forehead on my
knees.''
</p><p>She hesitated a moment, but the anxiety that had long been
kindling
burned fiercely up within her. As she knelt down, the border of her
garment was dipped into the pool; she laid her forehead on the old
woman's
knees, and the latter drew a cloak about the lady's face, so that
she was in
darkness. Then she heard the muttered words of prayer, in the midst
of
which she started, and would have arisen.
</p><p>``Let me flee,&mdash;let me flee and hide myself, that they may
not look upon
me!'' she cried. But, with returning recollection, she hushed
herself, and
was still as death.
</p><p>For it seemed as if other voices&mdash;familiar in infancy, and
unforgotten
through many wanderings, and in all the vicissitudes of her heart
and fortune&mdash;were mingling with the accents of the prayer. At first
the
words
   <pb n="943"/>
were faint and indistinct, not rendered so by distance, but rather
resembling the dim pages of a book which we strive to read by an
imperfect and
gradually brightening light. In such a manner, as the prayer
proceeded,
did those voices strengthen upon the ear; till at length the
petition ended,
and the conversation of an aged man, and of a woman broken and
decayed like himself, became distinctly audible to the lady as she
knelt. But
those strangers appeared not to stand in the hollow depth between
the
three hills. Their voices were encompassed and re&euml;choed by the
walls of a
chamber, the windows of which were rattling in the breeze; the
regular vibration of a clock, the crackling of a fire, and the
tinkling of
the embers as
they fell among the ashes, rendered the scene almost as vivid as if
painted
to the eye. By a melancholy hearth sat these two old people, the
man
calmly despondent, the woman querulous and tearful, and their words
were all of sorrow. They spoke of a daughter, a wanderer they knew
not
where, bearing dishonor along with her, and leaving shame and
affliction
to bring their gray heads to the grave. They alluded also to other
and
more recent woe, but in the midst of their talk their voices seemed
to melt
into the sound of the wind sweeping mournfully among the autumn
leaves; and when the lady lifted her eyes, there was she kneeling
in the
hollow between three hills.
</p><p>``A weary and lonesome time yonder old couple have of it,''
remarked
the old woman, smiling in the lady's face.
</p><p>``And did you also hear them?'' exclaimed she, a sense of
intolerable
humiliation triumphing over her agony and fear.
</p><p>``Yea; and we have yet more to hear,'' replied the old
woman. ``Wherefore, cover thy face quickly.''
</p><p>Again the withered hag poured forth the monotonous words of
a prayer
that was not meant to be acceptable in heaven; and soon, in the
pauses of
her breath, strange murmurings began to thicken, gradually
increasing so
as to drown and overpower the charm by which they grew. Shrieks
pierced
through the obscurity of sound, and were succeeded by the singing
of
sweet female voices, which, in their turn, gave way to a wild roar
of
laughter, broken suddenly by groanings and sobs, forming altogether
a
ghastly confusion of terror and mourning and mirth. Chains were
rattling,
fierce and stern voices uttered threats, and the scourge resounded
at their
command. All these noises deepened and became substantial to the
listener's ear, till she could distinguish every soft and dreamy
accent
of the love
songs that died causelessly into funeral hymns. She shuddered at
the unprovoked wrath which blazed up like the spontaneous kindling
of
flames
and she grew faint at the fearful merriment raging miserably around
her.
In the midst of this wild scene, where unbound passions jostled
each other
in a drunken career, there was one solemn voice of a man, and a
manly
and melodious voice it might once have been. He went to and fro
continually, and his feet sounded upon the floor. In each member of
that
frenzied
company, whose own burning thoughts had become their exclusive
world,
he sought an auditor for the story of his individual wrong, and
interpreted
their laughter and tears as his reward of scorn or pity. He spoke
of woman's
   <pb n="944"/>
perfidy, of a wife who had broken her holiest vows, of a home
and
heart made desolate. Even as he went on, the shout, the laugh, the
shriek
the sob, rose up in unison, till they changed into the hollow,
fitful, and uneven sound of the wind, as it fought among the
pine-trees on those
three
lonely hills. The lady looked up, and there was the withered woman
smiling in her face.
</p><p>``Couldst thou have thought there were such merry times in
a madhouse?'' inquired the latter.
</p><p>``True, true,'' said the lady to herself; ``there is mirth
within its walls,
but misery, misery without.''
</p><p>``Wouldst thou hear more?'' demanded the old woman.
</p><p>``There is one other voice I would fain listen to again,''
replied the lady,
faintly.
</p><p>``Then, lay down thy head speedily upon my knees, that thou
mayst get
thee hence before the hour be past.''
</p><p>The golden skirts of day were yet lingering upon the hills,
but deep
shades obscured the hollow and the pool, as if sombre night were
rising
thence to overspread the world. Again that evil woman began to
weave
her spell. Long did it proceed unanswered, till the knolling of a
bell stole
in among the intervals of her words, like a clang that had
travelled far
over valley and rising ground, and was just ready to die in the
air. The
lady shook upon her companion's knees as she heard that boding
sound.
Stronger it grew and sadder, and deepened into the tone of a death
bell,
knolling dolefully from some ivy-mantled tower, and bearing tidings
of
mortality and woe to the cottage, to the hall, and to the solitary
wayfarer
that all might weep for the doom appointed in turn to them. Then
came a
measured tread, passing slowly, slowly on, as of mourners with a
coffin,
their garments trailing on the ground, so that the ear could
measure the
length of their melancholy array. Before them went the priest,
reading the
burial service, while the leaves of his book were rustling in the
breeze.
And though no voice but his was heard to speak aloud, still there
were
revilings and anathemas, whispered but distinct, from women and
from
men, breathed against the daughter who had wrung the aged hearts of
her
parents,&mdash;the wife who had betrayed the trusting fondness of her
husband,&mdash;the mother who had sinned against natural affection, and
left her
child to die. The sweeping sound of the funeral train faded away
like a
thin vapor, and the wind, that just before had seemed to shake the
coffin
pall, moaned sadly round the verge of the Hollow between three
Hills.
But when the old woman stirred the kneeling lady, she lifted not
her head.
</p><p>``Here has been a sweet hour's sport!'' said the withered
crone, chuckling to herself.</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

