<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="Hh1Ward"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="Hh1Ward">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Wards of the United States Government</title>
<title type="sort">wards of the united states government</title>
<author>H. H.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">38</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">Hh1Ward</idno>
<date value="1998">1998</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1998 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476075</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Judy Boss made the following corrections in this electronic version: p.778: Ind., ] Ind.; p. 779: 69.[ ] 69.]</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Wards of the United States Government</title>
<title type="sort">wards of the united states government</title>
<author>H.H.</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 776-782</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner &amp; Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: The Universsity of Virginia Library, call number AP2.C4, volume 19</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1880">1880</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine, feminine</term>
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1998-06">June 1998</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Anne Stinehart, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">



<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> <pb n="775"/>
<head>THE WARDS OF THE UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT</head>

<p>
     THAT the Indians should be called "wards" of the United States
Government, would seem a natural thing, significant of the natural
relation between the United States Government and the Indian.  The
dictionary definition of the word "ward" is "one under a guardian,"
and of the word "guardian," a "protector."  For white orphans under
age, guardians are appointed by law; and the same law defines the
duties and sets limit to the authority of such appointed guardians.
The guardianship comes to end when the orphan ward is of age.
This is one important difference between the white "wards" in our
country, and Indian "wards."  The Indian "ward" never comes of
age.  There are other differences, greater even than this; in fact, so
great that the term "ward" applied to the Indian, savors of a satire as
bitter as it was involuntary and unconscious on the part of the
Supreme Court, which, I believe, first used the epithet, or, if it did
not first use it, has used it since, as a convenient phrase of
"conveyance" of rights, not to the Indian, but from him; to define,
not what he might hope for, but what he must not expect; not what
he is, but what he is not; not what he may do, but what, being a
"ward," he is forever debarred from doing.  Among other things, he
may not make a contract with a white man, unless through his
guardian, the Government.  He may not hire an attorney to bring
any suit for him, unless by consent of his guardian, the Government.
Strangely enough, however, though as an individual he cannot make
a contract or bring a suit, he has, until six years ago, always been
considered fit, as a member of a tribe, to make a treaty; <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi>,
if the treaty were with the United States Government, his guardian.
</p><p>This relationship of "ward" and "guardian" between the Indian
and the United States Government is of long standing, as is also the
practice of treaty-making between them.  It began more than a
hundred years ago, when, oddly enough, the "wards" were more
powerful than the "guardian."  But even then, the object the United
States Government professed to have in view was "to elevate,
civilize, and educate" them "by furnishing them with useful,
domestic animals, and implements of husbandry."  This was the
verbal phrase in the treaty made with the Five Nations, in 1791.
There were treaties even earlier than this; notably, a treaty, "a
perpetual alliance, offensive and defensive," which we made with
the Delaware Indians in 1778.  It is a matter of history how well the
Delawares fought for us in the Revolutionary War.  They were
brave and efficient allies, and were inspired in their fighting not
only by the sentiment of loyalty to the "alliance," but by the hope of
the reward promised them, <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi>, "the territorial right to a
state as large as the State of Pennsylvania," and "a right to
representation in our Congress."   In 1785 the Delawares were
moved to Ohio and Indiana; in 1818, to Missouri and Arkansas; in
1829, to Kansas.  Here they were all gathered together under
renewed promises of a permanent home.  Where are they to-day?  In
Indian Territory,
   <pb n="776"/>
all that are left of them; some are with the Cherokees; some on
the Wichita Agency, where they are trying to farm, though last
summer, were unable to cultivate as much ground "as was
intended," "on account of loss of stock by horse thieves" [see
Report of Ind. Com. for 1877, p. 112]; it is a little inconvenient for
a "ward" at such distance from his "guardian," not to be able to
bring a suit against a thief, without authorization from the
"guardian."
</p><p>There are not so many of the "wards" now as there were once.
"We have, in two hundred and fifty years, wasted their numbers
from 2,500,000 down to 250,000; or a waste of number equal to all
their children born to them in the last 250 years," says the Minority
Report of the Joint Com. appointed by the two houses of the
XLIVth Congress, to consider the expediency of transferring the
Indian Bureau to the War Department.  Neither are they so well off
as they once were, for they have been compelled to sell the greater
portion of their lands to their "guardian."  "The United States
Government has taken absolute ownership of 3,232,936,351 acres
of their lands, leaving to all the tribes collectively only 97,745,009
acres of ground," says the same Report.  Nevertheless, they are not
yet paupers, neither do they live entirely on the charity of their
"guardian," as many people suppose, seeing mention made every
year of large sums of money appropriated by Congress for supplies
and payments to the different tribes of Indians.
</p><p>When the "wards" have made "treaties" and "sales" to their
guardian, the transaction has been thus: "Generally, the
commissioners who made the treaty estimated the value of the right
of occupancy of the Indians, and paid the consideration, either in a
gross sum or in an amount of money or goods.  The money is
delivered to the agents, or chiefs, or more frequently deposited with
the United States, invested in government securities, and held in
trust for the tribe to which it belongs.  The whole amount of these
trust funds is $13,069,475, on which interest of four and one-half
per cent. is allowed." [See "The Indian Problem, by Gardner
Hubbard," p. 11.]
</p><p>There are people &mdash; and their number seems increasing in our
country every day &mdash; who hold that the Indian's "right of occupancy"
was never any "right" at all &mdash; was nothing that he had the power to
sell, or white men need have troubled themselves to buy.  As a
nation, however, we have recognized this right in hundreds of
treaties, "confirmed by the Senate as are treaties with foreign
powers," and recognizing the Indian tribes "as nations with whom
the United States might contract, without derogating from its
sovereignty."

</p><p>
<q>"In the early history of the Western World, the principle was
fully recognized that, while sovereignty rested, not with the Indians,
but with the civilized power claiming by virtue of discovery, the
Indians were the rightful occupants, with a just and perfect claim to
retain possession and enjoy the use until they should be disposed
voluntarily to part with it.  Great Britain, Holland, France, and
Spain, the four powers claiming sovereignty, by virtue of discovery,
within the present territory of the United States, conceded no less
than this to the natives; while France, in the cession of the Province
of Louisiana, expressly renewed the rights allowed the Indians by
its own treaties and articles, 'until by mutual consent of the United
States and the said tribes or nations, other suitable articles shall
have been agreed upon." &mdash; ["The Indian Question.  By Francis A.
Walker, late United States Commissioner of Indian Affairs," page
10.]</q>

</p><p>The accumulated inconvenience, embarrassment, and costliness
of making such treaties and purchases by treaty, &mdash; perhaps, also,
some sense of the accumulating infamy of breaking such treaties
and violating the terms of such purchases by treaty &mdash; so weighed
upon the minds of the representatives of the American people, that
on the 3d of March, 1871, it was declared by an Act of Congress,
that:

</p><p><q>"No Indian nation or tribe within the territory of the United
States shall be acknowledged or recognized as an independent
nation, tribe, or power with whom the United States may contract
by treaty."  [See Sec. 2,079, Chap. II., Title XXVIII. of the United
States Revised Statutes.]</q>

Could it have been in satire that these law-makers added a clause to
the effect that this Act should not invalidate any treaties made
previous to that date?  Was there one treaty left which had not been
broken?
</p><p>There is a certain sort of defiant outspokenness in this Act which
compels a certain kind of respect.  It openly and &mdash; if legality of
phrase can make an outrage legal &mdash; legally takes away from the
Indian his one semblance of legal right, and leaves him, at last,
completely at the mercy of the untrammeled power of the
Government.  Nevertheless, I repeat, that for the Government to
trick and break faith with the Indians now seems one shade less
dishonorable than before; as to be a highwayman seems one shade
less degrading than to be a pickpocket.
</p><p>It is only a little more than fifty years
   <pb n="777"/>
since the British envoys at Ghent charged the United States with
"having reduced the Indians to the state of subjects living on
sufferance within their limits, and threatened thereby with total
extinction."  To this accusation our commissioners, John Quincy
Adams and Albert Gallatin, replied as follows:

</p><p><q>"The Indians residing within the United States are so far
independent that they live under their own customs and laws, and
not under the laws of the United States; that their rights on the lands
which they inhabit or hunt are secured to them by boundaries
defined in amicable treaties between the United States and
themselves; and that whenever those boundaries are varied, it is also
by amicable and voluntary treaties, by which they receive from the
United States ample compensation for every right they have to
surrender."</q>

This was in 1814.  Before the first half of the century had gone, we
had broken seven solemn treaties with the Creeks, eleven, equally
solemn, with the Cherokees, and as many with the Chickasaw and
Choctaw nations, to say nothing of those with smaller tribes.
</p><p>The experience of the Cherokees is a sad and infamous page of
our history.  A new treaty made with them, in 1828, begins:

</p><p><q><hi rend="italic">"Whereas</hi>, It being the anxious desire of the Government
of the United States to secure to the Cherokee nation of Indians a
permanent home, and which shall, under the most solemn guarantee
of the United States, be and remain theirs forever, a home that shall
never in all future time be embarrassed by having extended around
it lines, or placed over it the jurisdiction of a State or Territory, nor
be pressed upon by the extension over it in any way of the limits of
any existing State or Territory, the parties hereto do conclude the
following articles, viz.:"  *  *  *  [See U. S. Statutes at large, vol.
vii., p. 311.]</q>

Ten years later, the United States Government, at the request of the
State of Georgia, compelled the Cherokees to give up the lands
guaranteed to them by this treaty, and move to the Indian Territory.
By this time, the Cherokees were a civilized people; and there were
among them men who were sufficiently skilled in the use of words
to insist upon the insertion, in the treaty, of this clause:

</p><p><q>"Article V. &mdash; The United States hereby covenant and agree that
the lands ceded to the Cherokee nation in the foregoing article, shall
in no future time, without their consent, be included in the territorial
limits or jurisdiction of any State or Territory."</q>

The opening words of this treaty are full of pathos.

</p><p><q><hi rend="italic">"Whereas</hi>, The Cherokees are anxious to make some
arrangements with the Government of the United States, whereby
the difficulties they have experienced by a residence within the
settled parts of the United States, under the jurisdiction and laws of
the State governments, may be terminated; and with the view of
reuniting their people in one body, and securing a permanent home
for themselves and their posterity.  *  *  *," etc.</q>

And to-day a bill is before Congress to create a Territorial
government over these "lands ceded to the Cherokee nation."
</p><p>With the Winnebagoes the United States Government made five
treaties between 1816 and 1855.  The treaty of 1855 guaranteed to
them a reservation in Minnesota, where they lived until 1862,
"peaceably engaged in agriculture," and loyal to the United States,
even when surrounded and threatened by bands of hostile Sioux.
After the outbreak of the Sioux, the citizens of Minnesota were "so
determined that all Indians should be removed beyond the limits of
the State, that Congress passed an Act in 1863 providing for their
removal.  [See "The Indian Question.  By Francis A. Walker," p.
178.]  After the loss of many lives by exposure and starvation in
Dakota, they were finally settled in Nebraska, on a reservation
adjoining that of the Omahas.  Doubtless, when Nebraska becomes
as "determined" as Minnesota was in 1863, and as Georgia was in
1838, that "all Indians shall be removed" beyond her limits,
Nebraska will plead "precedents," as Colorado to-day is pleading
the long list of shameful precedents which have gone before.  When
Nebraska does this, then the Winnebagoes, the Omahas, the Sacs
and Foxes, the Otoes, the Missourias, and the Santee Sioux, all
living now on reservations ceded to or set apart for them there by
the Government, will be added to the list of "Removed to the Indian
Territory."
</p><p>The stories of the sufferings, deaths, and massacres which come
under the head of these "removals" would fill volumes; they can
never be fully told, because the dead cannot tell them.  From time to
time the hearts of the American people are sickened and rent by
sudden news of one more, such as the massacre of the Cheyennes at
Fort Robinson, or the dying of the Nez Perc&eacute;s and the
Poncas by hundreds in Indian Territory.  It would seem as if the
hearing of one of these tales were enough to arouse the whole
American nation to a sense of the cruelty of thus oppressing the
Indian.  But too often the tale is told from the white man's side, and
not
   <pb n="778"/>
from the Indian's; the murders which are the only defense or
retaliation left within the Indian's power, are held up to view as
unprovoked acts of barbarous savages.  And this, in spite of
testimony upon testimony, given by men who best know the facts of
Indian wars, and the real quality of the Indian nature.

</p><p><q>"It is only what the Indian does to the white man that is
published to the country, never what the white man does to the
Indian." &mdash; [Official Report of General Pope, June, 1864.]</q>

</p><p>The story of the Nez Perc&eacute; war, consequent on the
attempt of the United States Government to "remove" this tribe
from their homes, is still fresh in the minds of the American people,
and is not yet complete on the official records of the Government.
It is one of the few cases in which the Indian's side of the story has
been told, and it is, therefore, one of the few cases which can be
cited with anything like fairness.
</p><p>The three chief sources of information in regard to the
experiences of these Nez Perc&eacute; "wards" of the United States
Government are the official reports of Commissioners of Indian
Affairs, a remarkable paper written by Chief Joseph of the
Wal-lam-wat-kin band of Nez Perc&eacute;s, called "An Indian's
Views of Indian Affairs," and published in the "North American
Review" for April, 1879, and a reply to that article, written by
General O. O. Howard, called "The True Story of the Wallowa
Campaign," and published in the "North American Review" for
July, 1879.  It seems an oversight on the part of General Howard to
call his paper "The True Story of the Wallowa Campaign," when, in
fact, it speaks only of the events preceding the battles of that
campaign, of the councils, agreements and final decisions in the
matter of the removal of the Nez Perc&eacute;s, and only alludes in
a few words, near the close, to the fact of the fights and the
surrender of the Indians.  He says that some of the Indians
"treacherously escaped after the terms of surrender had been agreed
upon," and thus did "break and make void the said terms of
surrender."  Is this the law of nations at war?  If a few soldiers
contrive to run away, after an army has surrendered, does that
invalidate the conditions on which the generals of the two armies
had agreed?  General Howard expressly omits to state what those
"terms of surrender" were; and by this omission, he gives the
strongest proof that Chief Joseph, in his article, did not misrepresent
them.
</p><p>The beginning of the Nez Perc&eacute; trouble was in the
appointment, at Washington, of "a commission to visit the Nez
Perc&eacute; and other roving bands of Indians in Idaho, Oregon,
and Washington Territory."  [See Report of Ind. Com. for 1877, p.
211.]  This word "roving" is one of the many current phrases of
misrepresentation about the Indians.  "Roving bands," "nomadic
tribes," are catch-words for popular contempt and popular fear.  In
the true sense of the word, there is no such thing among our Indians
as a "nomadic tribe."
</p><p>Of these same Nez Perc&eacute; Indians, this same official
report (p. 80) says, they "seldom leave their homes except when
called away on business.  *  *  They do their trading semi-annually,
in the spring and fall, returning home as soon as they have got
through with their business!" and in the Report of the Indian
Commissioner for 1874, p. 12, we find this statement:

</p><p><q>"Experiences shows that no effort is more unsuccessful with an
Indian than that which proposes to remove him from the place of
his birth and the graves of his fathers.  Though a barren plain
without wood or water, he will not voluntarily exchange it for any
prairie or woodland, however inviting."</q>

</p><p>Between the accounts given by General Howard, and by Chief
Joseph, of the events preceding the Nez Perce war, there are
noticeable discrepancies.
</p><p>General Howard says that he listened to the "oft-repeated
Dreamer nonsense of the chief, 'Too-hool-hool-suit,' with no
impatience, but finally said to him:
</p><p>"Twenty times over I hear that the earth is your mother, and
about the chieftainship of the earth.  I want to hear it no more."
</p><p>Chief Joseph says:
</p><p>"General Howard lost his temper and said 'Shut up!  I don't want
to hear any more of such talk.'  Too-hool-hool-suit answered, 'Who
are you, that you ask us to talk, and then tell me I shan't talk?  Are
you the Great Spirit?  Did you make the world?'"
</p><p>General Howard, quoting from his record at the time, says:
</p><p>"The rough old fellow, in his most provoking tone, says
something in a short sentence, looking fiercely at me.  The
interpreter quickly says: 'He demands what person pretends to
divide this land, and put me on it?'  In the most decided voice, I
said, 'I am the man.  I stand here for the President, and there is no
spirit, bad or good, that will hinder me.  My orders are plain, and
will be executed.'"
   <pb n="779"/>
</p><p>Chief Joseph says: "General Howard replied, 'You are an
impudent fellow, and I will put you in the guard-house,' and then
ordered a soldier to arrest him."
</p><p>General Howard says: "After telling the Indians that this bad
advice would be their ruin, I asked the chiefs to go with me to look
at their land.  'The old man (Too-hool-hool-suit) shall not go.  I will
leave him with Colonel Perry.'  He says, 'Do you want to scare me
with reference to my body?'  I said, 'I will leave your body with
Colonel Perry.'  I then arose and led him out of the council, and
gave him into the charge of Colonel Perry."
</p><p>Chief Joseph says: "Too-hool-hool-suit made no resistance.  He
asked General Howard, 'Is that your order?  I don't care.  I have
expressed my heart to you.  I have nothing to take back.  I have
spoken for my country.  You can arrest me, but you cannot change
me, or make me take back what I have said.'  The soldiers came
forward and seized my friend, and took him to the guard-house.  My
men whispered among themselves whether they should let this thing
be done.  I counseled them to submit.  *  *  Too-hool-hool-suit was
prisoner for five days before he was released."
</p><p>General Howard, it will be observed, does not use the word
"arrested," but as he says, later, "Too-hool-hool-suit was released on
the pledge of Looking Glass and White Bird, and on his own earnest
promise to behave better," it is plain that Chief Joseph did not
misstate the facts.   This Indian chief, therefore, was put under
military arrest, and confined for five days, for uttering what General
Howard calls a "tirade" in a council to which the Indians had been
asked to come for the purpose of consultation and expression of
sentiment.
</p><p>Does not Chief Joseph speak common sense, as well as natural
feeling, in saying,
</p><p>I turned to my people and said, 'The arrest of Too-hool-hool-suit
was wrong, but we will not resent the insult.  We were invited to
this council to express our hearts, and we have done so.'"
</p><p>If such and so swift penalty as this, for "tirades" in council, were
the law of our land, especially in the District of Columbia, it would
be "no just cause of complaint" when Indians suffer it.  But
considering the frequency, length and safety of "tirades" in all parts
of America, it seems unjust not to permit Indians to deliver them.
However, they do come under the head of "spontaneous productions
of the soil"; and an Indian on a reservation is "invested with no such
proprietorship" in anything which comes under that head. &mdash;
[Annual Report of the Indian Com. for 1878, p. 69.]
</p><p>Chief Joseph and his band consented to move.  Chief Joseph
says:
</p><p>"I said in my heart that rather than have war I would give up my
country.  I would give up my father's grave.  I would give up
everything rather than have the blood of white men upon the hands
of my people."
</p><p>It was not easy for Joseph to bring his people to consent to move.
The young men wished to fight.  It has been told that, at this time,
Chief Joseph rode one day through his village, with a revolver in
each hand, saying he would shoot the first one of his warriors that
resisted the Government.  Finally, they gathered all the stock they
could find, and began the move.  A storm came, and raised the river
so high that some of the cattle could not be taken across.  Indian
guards were put in charge of the cattle left behind.  White men
attacked these guards and took the cattle.  After this Joseph could
no longer restrain his men, and the warfare began, which lasted over
two months.  It was a masterly campaign on the part of the Indians.
They were followed by General Howard; they had General Crook
on their right, and General Miles in front, but they were not once
hemmed in; and, at last, when they surrendered at Bear Paw
Mountain, in the Montana Hills, it was not because they were
beaten, but because, as Joseph says, "I would not bear to see my
wounded men and women suffer any longer; we had lost enough
already."  *  *  "We could have escaped from Bear Paw Mountain if
we had left our wounded, old women and children, behind.  We
were unwilling to do this.  We had never heard of a wounded Indian
recovering while in the hands of white men.  *  *  I believed
General Miles, or I never would have surrendered.  I have heard that
he has been censured for making the promise to return us to Lapwai.
He could not have made any other terms with me at that time.  I
could have held him in check until my friends came to my
assistance, and then neither of the generals nor their soldiers would
ever have left Bear Paw Mountain alive.  On the fifth day I went to
General Miles and gave up my gun, and said, 'From where the sun
now stands, I will fight no more.'  My people needed rest &mdash; we
wanted peace."
</p><p>The terms of this surrender were shamefully
   <pb n="780"/>
violated.  Joseph and his band were taken first to Fort
Leavenworth and then to the Indian Territory.  At Leavenworth they
were placed in the river bottom, with no water but the river water to
drink.
</p><p>"Many of my people sickened and died, and we buried them in
this strange land," says Joseph.  "I cannot tell how much my heart
suffered for my people while at Leavenworth.  The Great Spirit
Chief who rules above seemed to be looking some other way, and
did not see what was being done to my people."
</p><p>Yet with a marvelous magnanimity, and a clear-headed sense of
justice of which few men would be capable under the
circumstances, Joseph says:
</p><p>"I believe General Miles would have kept his word if he could
have done so.  I do not blame him for what we have suffered since
the surrender.  I do not know who is to blame.  We gave up all our
horses, over eleven hundred, and all our saddles, over one hundred,
and we have not heard from them since.  Somebody has got our
horses."
</p><p>This narrative of Chief Joseph's is profoundly touching; a very
Iliad of tragedy, of dignified and hopeless sorrow; and it stands
supported by the official records of the Indian Bureau.
</p><p>"After the arrival of Joseph and his band in the Indian Territory,
the bad effect of their location at Fort Leavenworth manifested
itself in the prostration by sickness at one time of 260 out of the
410; and 'within a few months' in the death of 'more than one
quarter of the entire number.'" &mdash; [Annual Report of the Indian
Commissioner, for 1878, p. 33.]
</p><p>"It will be borne in mind that Joseph has never made a treaty
with the United States and that he has never surrendered to the
Government the lands he claimed to own in Idaho.  *  *  Joseph and
his followers have shown themselves to be brave men and skillful
soldiers who, with one exception, have observed the rules of
civilized warfare.  *  *  These Indians were encroached upon by
white settlers, on soil they believed to be their own, and when these
encroachments became intolerable, they were compelled in their
own estimation to take up arms."  [Same Report, p. 34.]
</p><p>Chief Joseph and a remnant of his band are still in Indian
Territory, waiting anxiously the result of the movement now being
made by the Ponca chief, Standing Bear, and his friends and legal
advisors to obtain from the Supreme Court a decision which will
extend the protection of the civil law to every Indian in the country.
</p><p>The Nez Perc&eacute;s who escaped after this surrender took
refuge in the camp of the Sioux Chief, Sitting Bull, in Canada, and
no doubt they were able to add sarcastic emphasis to the assurances
given by General Terry to Sitting Bull that if he and his band would
return to the United States, they should be "treated in as friendly a
spirit as were other hostile Indians who surrendered to our military
forces."
</p><p>This council must have been a dramatic spectacle.  Three men
were sent by the United States Government into Canada, to hold
converse with some of the "wards" who had run away; empowered
to offer them, if they would come back, pardon and cows in
exchange for their horses and rifles.  General Terry said:

</p><p><q>"The President invites you to come to the boundary of his and
your country, and there give up your arms and ammunition, and
thence to go to the agencies to which he will assign you, and there
give up your horses, excepting those which are required for peace
purposes.  Your arms and horses will then be sold, and with all the
money obtained for them cows will be bought and sent to you." &mdash;
[Report of the Sec. of the Interior, 1877, p. 723.]
</q>
</p><p>The phrase "his and your country" seems a strange one, in a
paragraph of this sort.  It did not impress Sitting Bull very deeply,
and the allurements mentioned &mdash; the giving up all arms, horses, etc.,
and the certainty of being "assigned" to "agencies" here and there,
even with the prospect of "cows," did not entice him away from
Canada.  His reply is full of satire.  It would seem that even the
officers to whom it was addressed must, in spite of its affront to
their dignity, have enjoyed the speech.  He said:

</p><p><q>"For sixty-four years you have kept me and my people, and
treated us bad.  *  It is all the people on your side that have started
us to do all these depredations.  We could not go anywhere else, and
so we took refuge in this country.  *  *  You have got ears, and you
have got eyes to see with them, and you see how I live with these
people.  You see me?  Here I am.  If you think I am a fool, you are a
bigger fool than I am.  *  You come here to tell us lies, but we don't
want to hear them.  I don't wish any such language used to me &mdash;
that is, to tell me such lies in my Great Mother's house.  Don't you
say two more words.  Go back home where you came from.  This
country is mine, and I intend to stay here, and to raise this country
full of grown people.  *  *  I wish you to go back, and take it easy
going back."</q>

</p><p>Another chief said:

</p><p><q>"Sixty-four years ago you got our country, and
   <pb n="781"/>
you promised to take good care of us and keep us.  You ran from
one place to another, killing us and fighting us.  *  *  I come in to
these people here and <hi rend="italic">they give me permission to trade with the
traders</hi>.  That is <hi rend="italic">the way I make my living</hi>.  *  *  I am
going to live with these people here."
</q>
</p><p>So great was the scorn felt by these Indians for this embassy that
they even permitted a squaw to address it.

</p><p><q>"A squaw named 'The-One-that-Speaks-Once,' wife of
'The-Man-that-Scatters-the-Bear,' said: 'I was over at your country.
I wanted to raise my children over there, but you did not give me
any time.  I came over to this country to raise my children and have
a little peace.  That is all I have to say to you.  I wish you to go back
where you came from.  These are the people that I am going to stay
with and raise my children with."</q>

</p><p>After the Indians had finished speaking they asked if the
Commission had anything more to say, to which the Commission
answered that they had nothing more, and the conference closed.
"The Commission returned," says the Report (p. 413), "and Sitting
Bull and his adherents are no longer considered wards of the
Government."
</p><p>It is not strange that the Indians prefer Canada to the United
States.  There has been no war with or upon Indians there, since the
Revolution.  There are 100,000 Indians in Canada.  They are called
"the Indian subjects of her Majesty," and are held in every respect
amenable to the law and are in every respect protected by the law.
Says Bishop Whipple:

</p><p><q>"On one side the line is a nation that has spent $500,000,000 in
Indian wars, a people who have not a hundred miles between the
Atlantic and the Pacific which has not been the scene of a massacre,
a government which has not passed twenty years without an Indian
war; not one Indian tribe to whom it has given Christian
civilization, and which celebrates its centenary by another Indian
war.</q>
<q>"On the other side of the line are the same greedy, dominant,
Anglo-Saxon race &mdash; the same heathen.  Yet they have not spent one
dollar in Indian wars, and they have never had a massacre."
</q>
</p><p>The latest "removal" of "wards" and seizure of their lands is that
of the Poncas, who were removed from Dakota to Indian Territory
two years ago.  Their lands in Dakota had been ceded to them by
treaties in 1817, 1828, 1858, and 1865.  Article II. of the Treaty of
1865 says:

</p><p><q>"In consideration of the cession or release of that portion of the
reservation, above described, by the Ponca tribe of Indians to the
Government of the United States, the Government of the United
States, by way of rewarding them for their constant fidelity to the
Government and citizens thereof, and with a view of returning, to
the said tribe of Ponca Indians, their old burying-grounds and
corn-fields, hereby <hi rend="italic">cede</hi> and <hi rend="italic">relinquish</hi> to the tribe
of Ponca Indians the following described fractional townships."
</q>
</p><p>There follows a description of certain townships and sections.
The title is as strong a title as the Government can give.  No man,
no chartered railroad, has one any stronger.  These Poncas, it is
admitted, &mdash;

</p><p><q>"have always been friendly to the whites.  *  The orders of the
Government always met with obedient compliance at their hands.
Their removal from their homes on the Missouri River was, to them,
a great hardship.  They had been born and raised there.  They had
homes there in which they lived according to their ideas of comfort.
Many of them had engaged in agriculture, and possessed cattle and
agricultural implements." &mdash; [Official Report of the Secretary of the
Interior, p. 8.]
</q>
</p><p>In three months after the arrival of the Poncas in the Indian
Territory, over one hundred and fifty out of the seven hundred were
dead.  Then, one of the chiefs, named Standing Bear, ran away with
thirty of his people, and tried to return to Dakota.  He carried with
him the bones of his eldest son, who, when he was dying, had asked
his father to promise to bury him at home &mdash; a strange request for a
"nomadic" Indian to make!  The Government sent troops after this
band, overtook them, arrested them.  More than half were women
and children.  On their way back to the Indian Territory, they were
camped near Omaha.  Here they were visited by A. F. Tibbles, an
Omaha editor, who resolved to test the question of the legality of
their confinement as military prisoners.  The case was tried in the
Supreme Court of Nebraska, and by decision of Judge Dundy, the
Indians were set free.  They are the only free Indians in the United
States to-day, except a few who are under State governments.  The
first use Standing Bear made of his freedom was to journey to the
Eastern states, to endeavor to raise money to bring suits for the
recovery of the Ponca lands, and also suits in the Supreme Court of
the United States, to determine for all Indians, as Judge Dundy had
determined for him, that an Indian is a "person," and has all the
rights guaranteed by the Fourteenth Amendment.  This movement
has been responded to with great enthusiasm in some of the Eastern
cities, and all that money and public sentiment can do will be done
to help the cause of the Poncas, and in theirs, the cause of all the
other "wards of the Government."  Arrayed on the other side are the
colossal forces of selfishness, greed, love of power; and
   <pb n="782"/>
allied to these, the subtlest and most despicable of allies &mdash; our
national lack of a sense of honor.  These words sound harsh, but
what other words are truly applicable to a nation which, for one
hundred years, has broken every treaty it has made with a people
too feeble to punish its bad faith?
</p><p>Even since the first words of this article were written a United
States representative has angrily argued in Congress that it is very
hard if the Government will not, for Colorado's advantage, break a
few treaties, when it has broken so many for the advantage of other
States &mdash; has said this in so many words, and there was no man to
interrupt him with the cry of "shame!"
</p><p>What a logic of infamy!  Because a nation has broken treaties,
violated pledges, committed injustices and cruelties, for a hundred
years, it may as well go on breaking treaties, violating pledges,
being unjust and cruel?  Because we have had one century of
dishonor, must we have two?
</p>

</div1>



</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

