<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HigJack"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="HigJack">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mrs. Helen Jackson ("H.H.")</title>
<title type="sort">mrs helen jackson h h</title>
<author>Higginson, Thomas Wentworth, 1823-1911</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">46</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HigJack</idno>
<date value="1998">1998</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1998 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476077</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>The following changes have been made to the electronic version of this text:
p. 254: bode ] abode</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mrs. Helen Jackson ("H.H.")</title>
<title level="j">The Century Illustrated Monthly Magazine, volume 31</title>
<title type="sort">mrs helen jackson h h</title>
<author>Thomas Wentworth Higginson</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 251 -259</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Century Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1885">1885</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: University of Virginia Library, call number AP2.C4, volume 31</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1885">1885</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>poetry</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1998-06">June 1998</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Anne Stinehart, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">



<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> <pb n="251"/>
<head>MRS. HELEN JACKSON ("H. H.").</head>

<div2 type="section" id="d4">


<p>
IT is curious to see how promptly time begins to apply to the
memory of remarkable persons, as to their tombstones, an effacing
process that soon makes all inscriptions look alike.  Already we see
the beginnings of this tendency in regard to the late Mrs. Helen
Jackson.  The most brilliant, impetuous, and thoroughly individual
woman of her time, &mdash; one whose very temperament seemed
mingled of sunshine and fire, &mdash; she is already being portrayed
simply as a conventional Sunday-school saint.  It is undoubtedly
true that she wrote her first poetry as a bereaved mother and her last
prose as a zealous philanthropist; her life comprised both these
phases, and she thoroughly accepted them; but it included so much
more, it belonged to a personality so unique and in many respects so
fascinating, that those who knew her best can by no means spare her
for a commonplace canonization that takes the zest out of her
memory.  To describe her would be impossible except to the trained
skill of some French novelist; and she would have been a sealed
book to him, because no Frenchman could comprehend the curious
thread of firm New England texture that ran through her whole
being, tempering waywardness, keeping impulse from making
shipwreck of itself, and leading her whole life to a high and
concentrated purpose at last.  And when we remember that she
hated gossip about her own affairs, and was rarely willing to
mention to reporters any fact about herself, except her birthday, &mdash;
which she usually, with characteristic willfulness, put a year earlier
than it was, &mdash; it is peculiarly hard to do for her now that work which
she held in such aversion.  No fame or publicity could ever make
her seem, to those who knew her, anything but the most private and
intimate of friends; and to write about her at all seems the betrayal
of a confidence.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d5">
<head>I.</head>
<p>
     HELEN MARIA FISKE, the daughter of Nathan Wiley and
Deborah (Vinal) Fiske, was born at Amherst, Massachusetts,
October 18, 1831.  Her father was a native of Weston,
Massachusetts, was a graduate of Dartmouth College, and, after
being a tutor in that institution, became professor first of languages
and then of philosophy in Amherst College, having been previously
offered a professorship of mathematics at Middlebury College, &mdash; a
combination of facts indicating the variety of his attainments.  He
was also a Congregationalist minister and an author, publishing a
translation of Eschenburg's "Manual of Classical Literature," and
one or two books for children.  He died May 27, 1847, at Jerusalem,
whither he had gone for the benefit of his health.  His wife was a
native of Boston, and is mentioned with affection by all who knew
her; and the daughter used to say that her own sunny temperament
came from the mother's side.  She also had literary tastes, and wrote
the "Letters from a Cat," which her daughter afterwards edited, and
which show a genuine humor and a real power of expression.  She
died February 19, 1844, when her daughter Helen was twelve years
old.  Both parents held the strict Calvinistic faith, and the daughter
was reared in it, though she did not long remain there.
</p><p>     Mr. and Mrs. Fiske had two sons, who died young, and two
daughters, who lived to maturity; the younger of whom, Anne, is the
wife of Everett C. Banfield, Esquire, at one time solicitor of the
Treasury Department at Washington, and now a resident of
Wolfboro, New Hampshire.  The other, Helen, was a child of
uncommon versatility and vivacity; and her bright sayings were
often quoted, when she was but ten or twelve years old, in the
academical circle of the little college town.  She has herself
described in a lively paper, "The Naughtiest Day of my Life" ("St.
Nicholas," September-October, 1880), a childish feat of running
away from home in company with another little girl, on which
occasion the two children walked to Hadley, four miles, before they
were brought back.  The whole village had joined in the search for
them, and two professors from the college finally reclaimed the
wanderers.  There is something infinitely characteristic of the
mature woman in the description written by her mother, at the time,
of the close of that anxious day: "Helen walked in at a quarter
before ten o'clock at night, as rosy and smiling as possible, and
saying in her brightest tone, 'Oh, mother, I've had a perfectly
splendid time.'"
</p><p>     A child of this description may well have needed the discipline
of a variety of schools; and she had the advantage of at least two
good ones, &mdash; the well-known Ipswich (Massachusetts) Female
Seminary, and the private school of Rev. J. S. C. Abbott in New
York city.  She was married in Boston, when just twenty-one
(October 28, 1852), to Captain (afterwards
   <pb n="252"/>
Major) Edward B. Hunt, United States Army, whom she had first
met at Albany, New York, his brother, the Honorable Washington
Hunt, being at that time Governor of the State.  Captain and Mrs.
Hunt led the usual wandering life of military households, and were
quartered at a variety of posts.  As an engineer officer he held high
army rank, and he was also a man of considerable scientific
attainments.  Their first child, Murray, a beautiful boy, died of
dropsy in the brain, when eleven months old, at Tarrytown, New
York, in August, 1854.  Major Hunt was killed, October 2, 1863, at
Brooklyn, New York, while experimenting with an invention of his
own, called a "sea-miner," for firing projectiles under water.  Mrs.
Hunt still had her second boy, named Warren Horsford, after her
friends, General G. K. Warren and Professor Horsford, but
commonly called "Rennie."  He had, by testimony of all, a rare
combination of gifts and qualities, but died suddenly of diphtheria
at his aunt's home in West Roxbury, Massachusetts, on April 13,
1865.  Mrs. Hunt was thus left utterly bereaved, and the blow was
crushing.  It shows the strong relation between mother and child,
and the precocious character of her boy, that he made her promise
not to take her own life after he should be gone.  She made him
promise, in return, that if it were a possible thing he would
overcome all obstacles and come back from the other world to
speak to her; and the fact that this was never done kept her all her
life a disbeliever in Spiritualism: what Rennie could not do, she felt
must be impracticable.  For months after his death she shut herself
up from her nearest friends; and when she appeared among them at
last, she was smiling, vivacious, and outwardly unchanged.
</p><p>     Up to this time, although her life had been full of variety and
activity, it had been mainly domestic and social, and she had shown
no special signs of a literary vocation.  She loved society, was
personally very attractive, dressed charmingly, and had many
friends of both sexes.  Through her husband she knew many
superior men, but they belonged almost wholly to the military class,
or were those men of science whom she was wont to meet at the
scientific gatherings to which she accompanied Major Hunt.  It was
not till she went, at the age of thirty-four, to live in Newport, Rhode
Island, that she was brought much in contact with people whose
pursuits were literary; and it was partly, no doubt, through their
companionship that a fresh interest and a few employment opened
most unexpectedly before her.  How wholly she regarded her life as
prematurely ended at the close of its first phase may be seen by a
letter written soon after establishing herself in Newport, when she
had gone to West Point to superintend the removal of the remains of
her husband and children to that spot.  After speaking of the talents
and acquirements whose career was finished, she bitterly added:
"And I alone am left, who avail nothing."  She had yet to learn how
much her own life was to avail.
</p>

</div2><div2 type="section" n="2" id="d6">
<head>II.</head>
<p>
     WHEN she went to live in Newport (February 10, 1866), she
had already written poems, and had shown them to her friends.  She
had, indeed, when in her teens, published some girlish verses in the
Boston "Press and Post," but her mature compositions had all
related, so far as I know, to her personal bereavements.  Of these
she had published one in the "Nation" (July 20, 1865), this being the
very first volume of that periodical, which was edited by a personal
friend, and which gave at first more space to poetry than now.  This
poem was called "Lifted Over," and consisted of fourteen lines of
blank verse, referring to the death of her boy, and signed "Marah."
The fact of its publication makes it likely that, wherever she had
taken up her residence, she would have published more poetry of
the elegiac kind; but it is doubtful whether her lyre would have
reached a wide variety of notes, or whether she would have been
known as a prose writer at all, but for the stimulus and fresh
interests developed by her change of abode.  In the society of her
new friends she began for the first time to make a study of literary
style and methods; she interchanged criticism with others, and
welcomed it as applied to her own attempts; she soon ventured to
publish more poems, and then to try herself in prose.  The signature
"H. H." first appeared, I believe, in connection with the first thing
she published after her removal to Newport.  This was a poem
called "Tryst," in the "Nation" (April 12, 1866), followed soon by a
translation &mdash; almost the only one she ever made &mdash; from Victor
Hugo's "Le Soir" ("Nation," April 26, 1866), and by two poems
called "A Burial Service" (May 22) and "Old Lamps for New" (May
29) &mdash; this last being, perhaps by accident, unsigned.
</p><p>     These were soon followed by poems in the New York
"Independent," beginning with "Hagar" (August 2, 1866) and
"Bread on the Waters" (August 9, 1866) &mdash; she still keeping mainly
to her experiences of sorrow.  Her first attempt in prose, under her
own signature, appeared in the same newspaper for September 13,
1866, and was entitled "In the White Mountains."  It was a sketch of
a walk up Mount Washington from the Glen House,
   <pb n="253"/>
and, though spiritedly written, gave little indication of her rising so
far above the grade of the average summer correspondent as she
ultimately attained.  She also wrote an unsigned review of "Felix
Holt," in the same number.  From this time till her death she was an
occasional correspondent of that journal, writing for it, as its editors
say, three hundred and seventy-one articles in all.  She wrote also in
"Hearth and Home," and published a few poems in the New York
"Evening Post."
</p><p>     Thus launched into literature, she entered with the enthusiasm
of a child upon her new work.  She distrusted herself, was at first
fearful of each new undertaking, yet was eager to try everything,
and the moment each plunge was taken lost all fear.  I remember the
surprise with which she received the suggestion that no doubt
publishers would be happy to send her their books if she would only
review them; and her delight, as in a new world, when she opened
the first parcels.  From the beginning she composed with great
rapidity, writing on large sheets of yellow post-office paper,
eschewing pen and ink, and insisting that a lead-pencil alone could
keep pace with the swiftness of her thoughts.  The remarkable thing
was that, with all this quickness, she was always ready to revise and
correct, and was also a keen and minute critic on the writings of
others.  It was very surprising that one who was not really familiar
with any language but her own &mdash; for the Latin of her school-days
had already faded and even her French was at that time very
imperfect &mdash; should have such a perception of the details of style.
She had, however, been well trained in English at school, and used
to quote Kames's "Elements of Criticism" as one of the books she
had read there.  Both her father and mother had also taken an
interest in her early school compositions.
</p><p>     A statement has been lately made, on the authority of the late
Mr. R. W. Emerson, that she sent poems to the "Atlantic" in those
early days, and that they were rejected.  It is possible that my
memory may not include all the facts, but I am confident that this
statement is an error.  It is certain that she was repeatedly urged to
send something in that direction by a friend who then contributed
largely to the magazine, but she for a long time declined; saying that
the editors were overwhelmed with poor poetry, and that she would
wait for something of which she felt sure.  Accordingly she put into
that friend's hands her poem called "Coronation," with permission
to show it to Mr. Fields and let him have it if he wished, at a certain
price.  It was a high price for a new-comer to demand; but she was
inexorable, including rather curiously among her traits that of being
an excellent business woman, and generally getting for her wares
the price she set upon them.  Fields read it at once, and exclaimed,
"It's a good poem"; then read it again, and said, "It's a
<hi rend="italic">devilish</hi> good poem," and accepted it without hesitation.  It
appeared in the "Atlantic" for February, 1869, and another poem,
"The Way to Sing," followed it a year after; but Fields never quite
did justice to her poetry, while he greatly admired her prose, so that
she offered but little verse to that magazine.  Her "German
Landlady" appeared there (October, 1870), and was followed by a
long line of prose papers, continuing nearly until her death.  Her
little volume of "Verses" was printed rather reluctantly by Fields,
Osgood &amp; Co. (1870), she paying for the stereotype plates, as was
also the case with her first prose volume, "Bits of Travel" (1873),
published by their successors, James R. Osgood &amp; Co.  Soon after
this she transferred her books to Roberts Brothers, who issued "Bits
of Talk about Home Matters" (1873), and a much enlarged edition
of "Verses" (1874).
</p><p>     She spent in all five winters at Newport, always at the same
hospitable home, &mdash; Mrs. Hannah Dame's boarding-house, &mdash; and
always going somewhere among the mountains in summer, early
enough to keep off hay-fever, from which she suffered.  Then she
returned, late in autumn, preceded by great trunks and chests full of
pressed ferns and autumn leaves, which she dispensed royally
among her friends during the whole winter-time.  These Newport
seasons were interrupted by an absence of some fourteen months in
Europe (November, 1868, to February, 1870), and she had several
serious illnesses toward the latter part of the period.  Indeed, she
had an almost fatal attack while in Rome, and I am informed by the
friend with whom she traveled, Miss Sarah F. Clarke, of a peculiarly
characteristic act of hers when convalescent.  Going to Albano to
recruit, she refused to carry with her a professed nurse, as her
friends desired, but insisted on taking a young Italian girl of sixteen,
who had never had a vacation in her hard-working life, and to
whom the whole period of attendance would be a prolonged felicity.
</p><p>     In May, 1872, she went to California with her friend Miss
Sarah C. Woolsey; and in 1873-4, being convinced that her health
needed a thorough change of climate, tried the experiment of a
winter in Colorado.  This State became soon after her permanent
home; she being married in October, 1875, at her sister's house in
Wolfboro, New
   <pb n="254"/>
Hampshire, to Mr. William Sharpless Jackson, of Colorado Springs.
They were married by the ceremonial of the Society of Friends, the
bridegroom being of that persuasion.  For the remaining ten years of
her life she had a delightful abode and a happy domestic life,
although the demands of her health and her literary work, joined
with a restless and adventurous disposition, kept her a great deal in
motion between her new and her old haunts.  Nobody was ever a
more natural wanderer.  She always carried with her a compact store
of favorite pictures, Japanese prints, and the like; so that, within an
hour after she had taken possession of a room at the Parker House in
Boston or the Berkeley in New York, she would be sitting in a
tasteful boudoir of her own arranging.  With this came an equally
ready acceptance of the outdoor surroundings of each place; and in
migrating farther west, she soon knew more of Omaha or San
Francisco than the oldest inhabitant.  Her wonderful eye for external
nature traveled with her; she planned her house at Colorado Springs
with an unerring adaptation to the landscape, and on one occasion
welcomed a friend with more than twenty different vases of the
magnificent wild flowers of that region &mdash; each vase filled with a
great sheaf of a single species.  She had always lavished so much
adornment on one or two rooms that her friends had wondered what
she would do with a whole house; and those who visited her at
Colorado Springs beheld the fulfillment of their wonderings.
</p>

</div2><div2 type="section" n="3" id="d7">
<head>III.</head>

<p>     FOR the second time she was to encounter a wholly new
intellectual experience after adopting a new abode.  The literary
development, which had begun somewhat late, was to be merged
into a moral enthusiasm, beginning still later.  She wrote to an
intimate friend (January 17, 1880):

</p><p>
<q>     "I have done now, I believe, the last of the things I had said I
never would do; I have become what I have said a thousand times
was the most odious thing in life, 'a woman with a hobby.'  But I
cannot help it.  I think I feel as you must have felt in the old
abolition days.  I cannot think of anything else from night to
morning and from morning to night. . . .  I believe the time is
drawing near for a great change in our policy toward the Indian.  In
some respects, it seems to me, he is really worse off than the slaves;
they did have, in the majority of cases, good houses, and they were
not much more arbitrarily controlled than the Indian is by the agent
on a reservation.  He can order a corporal's guard to fire on an
Indian at any time he sees fit.  He is 'duly empowered by the
Government.'"
</q>
</p><p>
     In this same letter she announces her intention of going to
work for three months at the Astor Library on her "Century of
Dishonor"; and it is worth noticing that with all her enthusiasm she
does not disregard that careful literary execution which is to be the
means to her end; for in the same letter she writes to this friend, one
of her earliest critics: "I shall never write a sentence, so long as I
live, without studying it over from the stand-point of whether you
would think it could be bettered."  This shows that she did not, as
some have supposed, grow neglectful of literature in the interest of
reform; as if a carpenter were supposed to neglect his tools in order
to finish his job.
</p><p>     Her especial interest in the Indians was not the instantaneous
result of her Colorado life, but the travels and observations of those
first years were doubtless preparing the way for it.  It came to a
crisis in 1879, when she heard the Indians "Standing Bear" and
"Bright Eyes" lecture in Boston on the wrongs of the Poncas, and
afterwards met them in New York, at the house of her friend Mrs.
Botta.  Her immediate sympathy for them seemed very natural to
those who knew her, but it was hardly foreseen how strong and
engrossing that interest would become.  Henceforth she
subordinated literature not to an ulterior aim merely, for that she
had often done before, but to a single aim.  It must be remembered,
in illustration of this, that at least half the papers in her "Bits of
Talk" were written with a distinct moral purpose, and so were many
of her poems; and from this part of her work she had always great
enjoyment.  So ready were her sympathies that she read with
insatiable pleasure the letters that often came to her from lonely
women or anxious school-girls who had found help in her simple
domestic or religious poems, while her depths of passion would
only have frightened them, and they would have listened bewildered
to those sonnets which Emerson carried in his pocket-book and
pulled out to show his friends.  No, there was always a portion of
her literature itself which had as essentially a moral motive as had
"Ramona"; and, besides, she had always been ready to throw aside
her writing and devote whole days, in her impulsive way, to some
generous task.  For instance, she once, at the risk of great
unpopularity, invoked the aid of the city solicitor and half the
physicians in Newport to investigate the case of a poor boy who was
being, as she believed, starved to death, and whom the investigation
came too late to save.
</p><p>     Nor was the Indian question the first reform that had set her
thinking, although she was by temperament fastidious, and therefore
conservative.  On the great slavery question she had always, I
suspect, taken regular army views; she liked to have colored people
about
   <pb n="255"/>
her as servants, but was disposed to resent anything like equality;
yet she went with me to a jubilee meeting of the colored people of
Newport, after emancipation, and came away full of enthusiasm and
sympathy, with much contrition as to things she had previously said
and done.  She demurred at her Newport hostess's receiving a highly
educated young quadroon lady as a temporary boarder in the house,
but when the matter was finally compromised by her coming to tea,
Mrs. Hunt lavished kindnesses upon her, invited her to her private
parlor, and won her heart.  The same mixture of prejudice and
generosity marked her course in matters relating to the advancement
of her own sex.  Professedly abhorring woman suffrage, she went
with me to a convention on that subject in New York, under express
contract to write a satirical report in a leading newspaper; but was
so instantly won over &mdash; as many another has been &mdash; by the sweet
voice of Lucy Stone, that she defaulted as a correspondent, saying
to me, "Do you suppose I ever could write against anything which
that woman wishes to have done?"  Afterwards she hospitably
entertained the same lecturer when on the canvass in Colorado; and
a few months before her death she gave an English advocate of the
cause a letter to one of her Eastern friends, saying that her old
prejudices were somewhat shaken.  A California friend states,
indeed, that she sometimes felt moved to write something on the
legal and other disabilities of women.
</p><p>     But if other reforms had touched her a little, they had never
controlled or held her, until the especial interest in the Poncas arose.
After that she took up work in earnest, studied the facts,
corresponded with statesmen, and finally wrote her "Century of
Dishonor," as has been said.  Over this she fairly worked herself
sick, and was forced to go to Norway for refreshment with her
friends the Horsfords, leaving the proof-reading to be done by a
literary ally.  Several charming memorials of this trip appeared in
the magazines.  She afterwards received an appointment from the
United States Government to report on the condition and needs of
the California "Mission Indians," in connection with Abbott
Kinney, Esq.; and she visited all or most of those tribes for this
purpose, in the spring of 1883.  The report of the commissioners,
which is understood to have been mainly prepared by her, is as
clear, as full, and as sensible as if it had been written by the most
prosaic of mankind.  She also explored the history of the early
Spanish missions, whose story of enthusiasm and picturesqueness
won her heart; and she wrote the series of papers in regard to these
missions which appeared in this magazine.
</p><p>     During this whole period, moreover, she did not neglect her
earlier productions, but gathered them into volumes; publishing
"Bits of Talk for Young Folks" (1876) and "Bits of Travel at Home"
(1878).  She also issued separately (1879) a single poem, "The Story
of Boon."  This was founded on a tale told in "The English
Governess at the Siamese Court," by Mrs. A. H. Leonowens, a lady
whose enthusiasm and eloquence found ardent sympathy in Mrs.
Hunt, who for her sake laid down her strong hostility to women's
appearance on the platform, and zealously organized two lectures
for her friend.  She published also a little book of her mother's,
"Letters from a Cat" (1880), and followed it up by "Mammy
Tittleback's Stories" (1881), of her own; and "The Hunter of Cats of
Connorloa" (1884).  Another book, for rather older children, was
"Nelly's Silver Mine" (1878), and she wrote a little book called
"The Training of Children" (1882).  Then came "Ramona," first
published in the "Christian Union" in 1884, appearing there because
it had been written, as it were, at a white heat, and she could not
wait for the longer delays of a magazine.  It was issued in book
form that same year, and completes the list of her acknowledged
works.  It was no secret, however, that she wrote, in the "No Name"
series, "Mercy Philbrick's Choice" (1876) and "Hetty's Strange
History" (1877).  Into the question of other works that may have
been rightly or wrongly attributed to her, the present writer does not
propose to enter.
</p><p>     The sad story of her last illness need not here be recapitulated.
She seemed the victim of a series of misfortunes, beginning with the
long confinement incident to a severe fracture of the leg in June,
1884, this being followed by her transfer to a malarious residence in
California, and at last by the discovery of a concealed cancerous
affection that had baffled her physicians and herself.  During all this
period &mdash; much of it spent alone, with only a hired attendant, far
from all old friends, though she was cheered by the constant
kindness of newer ones &mdash; her sunny elasticity never failed; and
within a fortnight of her death she wrote long letters, in a clear and
vigorous hand, expressing only cheerful hopes for the future,
whether she should live or die.  One of the last of these was to
President Cleveland, to thank him for sustaining the rights of the
Indians.  Her husband, who had been imperatively detained in
Colorado by important business, was with her at the last, and she
passed away quietly but unconsciously, on the afternoon of August
12, 1885.  A temporary interment took place in San Francisco, the
services being performed by the Rev. Horatio Stebbins, who read,
very appropriately, the "Last
   <pb n="256"/>
Words," with which her little volume of verses ends.  It was the
precise memorial she would have desired; and the burial-place
assigned to her was also in accordance with her own expressed
wishes &mdash; it being a spot near the summit of the Cheyenne
Mountains, about four miles from Colorado Springs.
</p>

</div2><div2 type="section" n="4" id="d8">
<head>IV.</head>

<p>     The poetry of Mrs. Jackson unquestionably takes rank above
that of any American woman, and in the opinion of many above that
of any Englishwoman but Mrs. Browning.  Emerson, as is well
known, rated it above that of almost all American men.  Her works
include, first, the simple poetry of domestic life; secondly, love-poems of extraordinary intensity and imaginative fullness; thirdly,
verses showing most intimate sympathy with external nature; and
lastly, a few poems of the highest dignity and melody in the nature
of odes, such as "A Christmas Symphony" and "A Funeral March."
The poem which combines the most of depth and the most of
popular sympathy is that called "Spinning," where a symbol drawn
from common life assumes the sort of solemn expressiveness that
belongs to the humble actions of peasants in the pictures of the
French Millet.  Emerson's favorite was her sonnet called "Thought";
and other critics have given the palm for exquisiteness of musical
structure to her "Gondolieds."  But her poetry was only a small
portion of her literary work; and of the range and value of this
product, a good conception will be given when we say that a plan
was at one time seriously formed by the late Dr. Holland and his
associate in charge of this magazine, to let Mrs. Jackson's
contributions accumulate sufficiently to fill one number of the
periodical &mdash; poetry, fiction, travels, criticism, and all &mdash; and then
send it all forth as the product of one person.  The plan was finally
dismissed, as I am assured, not from the slightest doubt of its
practicability, but only because it might be viewed as sensational.  It
is probably the greatest compliment ever yet paid by editors, in the
whole history of magazine literature, to the resources of a single
contributor.
</p><p>     There is in her prose writings an even excellence of execution
which is not always to be found in her poetry, and which is
surpassed by hardly any American writer.  It is always clear, strong,
accurate, spirited, and forcible; she had a natural instinct for literary
structure, as well as style, and a positive genius for giving
characteristic and piquant titles to what she wrote.  It was her
delight not merely to explore the new, but to throw novel and
unexpected freshness around the old.  Before she had become so
wide a traveler she used to plan a book, to be called "Explorations"
or some such title, in which all the most familiar scenery was to be
described under fictitious names; and only the map appended would
gradually reveal, through its new local phraseology, that "Hide and
Seek Town"<ref target="n1">[*]</ref> was Princeton, Massachusetts, and so on indefinitely.
Her poetry sometimes offered deeper enigmas than these superficial
ones, and some of the best of it will never be fully comprehended
but by the few who had the key to the events or emotions that called
it forth.  So ardent were her sympathies that everything took color
from her personal ties; and her readiness to form these ties with
persons of all ages, both sexes, and every condition not only
afforded some of her greatest joys, but also brought the greatest
perils of her life; often involving misconception, perplexity, and
keen disappointment to herself and others.  Her friendships with
men had the frankness and openness that most women show only to
one another; and her friendships with women had the romance and
ideal atmosphere that her sex usually reserves for men.  There was
an utterly exotic and even tropical side of her nature, strangely
mingled with the traits that came from her New England blood.
Where her sympathy went, even in the least degree, there she was
ready to give all she had, &mdash; attention, time, trouble, money,
popularity, reputation, &mdash; and this with only too little thought of the
morrow.  The result was found not merely in many unreasonable
requests, but in inconvenient and unlooked-for expectations.
During the middle period of her life there was never any security
that the morning postman might not bring an impassioned letter
from some enamored young girl, proposing to come and spend her
life with her benefactress; or a proffer of hand and heart from some
worthy man, with whom she had mistakenly supposed herself to be
on a footing of the plainest good-fellowship.  It sometimes taxed all
her great resources of kindness and ready wit to extract herself from
such entanglements; and she never could be made to understand
how they had come about or why others succeeded them.
</p><p>     She had great virtues, marked inconsistencies, and plenty of
fascinating faults that came near to virtues.  She was never selfishly
ungenerous, but she was impulsive in her scorn of mean actions,
and was sometimes cruelly unjust to those whom she simply did not
understand; this misconception very often occurring, however, in
the too Quixotic defense of a friend or a principle.  To those
   <pb n="257"/>
who knew her best she was a person quite unique and utterly
inexhaustible; and though her remoteness of residence during the
last ten years had separated her from the society of many of her
earlier friends, there is not one of them who does not feel the world
deeply impoverished by her going out of it.  She did not belong to a
class; she left behind her no second; and neither memory nor fancy
can restore her as she was, or fully reproduce, even for those who
knew her best, that ardent and joyous personality.  And those who
recall her chiefly in gayer moods will find their remembrance
chastened by the thought that she could write, when finally face to
face with death, such poems as "Habeas Corpus," "Acquainted with
Grief," and "A Last Prayer," &mdash; poems which are here first
published, and which add a new dignity to the falling away of the
flesh and a new nobleness to human nature.
</p>

<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">*</seg> <p>See this magazine for August, 1876.</p></note>

</div2>

</div1><div1 type="poem" id="d9">
<head>THE LAST POEMS OF HELEN JACKSON (H. H.).</head>




<lg type="stanza">
<head>ACQUAINTED WITH GRIEF.</head>
<l>DOST know Grief well?  Hast known her long?
</l><l rend="indent">   So long, that not with gift or smile,
</l><l>Or gliding footstep in the throng,
</l><l rend="indent">   She can deceive thee by her guile?
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>So long, that with unflinching eyes
</l><l rend="indent">Thou smilest to thyself apart,
</l><l>To watch each flimsy, fresh disguise
</l><l rend="indent">She plans to stab anew thy heart?
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>So long, thou barrest up no door
</l><l rend="indent">To stay the coming of her feet?
</l><l>So long, thou answerest no more,
</l><l rend="indent">Lest in her ear thy cry be sweet?
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Dost know the voice in which she says,
</l><l rend="indent">   "No more henceforth our paths divide;
</l><l>In loneliest nights, in crowded days,
</l><l rend="indent">   I am forever by thy side"?
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Then dost thou know, perchance, the spell
</l><l rend="indent">   The gods laid on her at her birth, &mdash;
</l><l>The viewless gods who mingle well
</l><l rend="indent">   Strange love and hate of us on earth.
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Weapon and time, the hour, the place,
</l><l rend="indent">   All these are hers to take, to choose,
</l><l>To give us neither rest nor grace,
</l><l rend="indent">   Not one heart-throb to miss or lose.
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>All these are hers; yet stands she, slave,
</l><l rend="indent">   Helpless before our one behest:
</l><l>The gods, that we be shamed not, gave,
</l><l rend="indent">   And locked the secret in our breast.
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>She to the gazing world must bear
</l><l rend="indent">   Our crowns of triumph, if we bid;
</l><l>Loyal and mute, our colors wear,
</l><l rend="indent">   Sign of her own forever hid.
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Smile to our smile, song to our song,
</l><l rend="indent">   With songs and smiles our roses fling,
</l><l>Till men turn round in every throng,
</l><l rend="indent">   To note such joyous pleasuring,
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>And ask, next morn, with eyes that lend
</l><l rend="indent">   A fervor to the words they say,
</l><l>"What is her name, that radiant friend
</l><l rend="indent">   Who walked beside you yesterday?"
</l>
</lg>

<p>July 1st.</p>

<lg type="verse">
<head>FEALTY.</head>

<l>THE thing I count and hold as fealty,
</l><l>The only fealty to give or take,
</l><l>Doth never reckoning keep, and coldly make
</l><l>Bond to itself with this or that to be
</l><l>Content as wage; the wage unpaid, to free
</l><l>Its hand from service, and its love forsake,
</l><l>Its faith cast off, as one from dreams might wake
</l><l>At morn, and smiling watch the vision flee.
</l><l>Such fealty is treason in disguise.
</l><l>Who trusts it, his death-warrant sealed doth bear.
</l><l>Love looks at it with angry, wondering eyes;
</l><l>Love knows the face true fealty doth wear,
</l><l>The pulse that beats unchanged by alien air,
</l><l>Or hurts, or crimes, until the loved one dies.
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="verse">
<head>VISION.</head>

<l>
</l><l>BY subtile secrets of discovered law
</l><l>Men well have measured the horizon's round,
</l><l>Kept record of the speed of light and sound,
</l><l>Have close defined by reasoning without flaw
</l><l>The utmost human vision ever saw
</l><l>Unaided, and have arrant sought and found
</l><l>Devices countless to extend its bound.
</l><l>Bootless their secrets all!  My eyes but stray
</l><l>To eastward, and majestic, bright, arise
</l><l>Peaks of a range which three days distant lies!
</l><l>And of the faces, too, that light my day
</l><l>Most clear, one is a continent away,
</l><l>The other shines above the farthest skies!
</l>
</lg>




<lg type="stanza">
<head>THE POET'S FORGE.</head>
<l>HE lies on his back, the idling smith,
</l><l rend="indent">   A lazy, dreaming fellow is he;
</l><l>The sky is blue, or the sky is gray,
</l><l>He lies on his back the livelong day;
</l><l>Not a tool in sight; say what they may,
</l><l rend="indent">   A curious sort of a smith is he.
</l>
</lg>

   <pb n="258"/>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>The powers of the air are in league with him;
</l><l rend="indent">   The country around believes it well;
</l><l>The wondering folk draw spying near;
</l><l>Never sight nor sound do they see or hear;
</l><l>No wonder they feel a little fear;
</l><l rend="indent">   When is it his work is done so well?
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Never sight nor sound to see or hear;
</l><l rend="indent">   The powers of the air are in league with him;
</l><l>High over his head his metals swing,
</l><l>Fine gold and silver to shame the king;
</l><l>We might distinguish their glittering,
</l><l>   If once we could get in league with him.
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>High over his head his metals swing;
</l><l rend="indent">   He hammers them idly year by year,
</l><l>Hammers and chuckles a low refrain:
</l><l>"A bench and book are a ball and chain,
</l><l>The adze is better tool than the plane;
</l><l rend="indent">   What's the odds between now and next year!"
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Hammers and chuckles his low refrain,
</l><l rend="indent">   A lazy, dreaming fellow is he:
</l><l>When sudden, some day, his bells peal out,
</l><l>And men, at the sound, for gladness shout;
</l><l>He laughs and asks what it's all about;
</l><l rend="indent">   Oh, a curious sort of smith is he!
</l>
</lg>

<p>July 12th.</p>





<lg type="stanza">
<head>VANITY OF VANITIES.</head>
<l>BEE to the blossom, moth to the flame;
</l><l>Each to his passion; what's in a name!
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Red clover's sweetest, well the bee knows;
</l><l>No bee can suck it; lonely it blows.
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Deep lies its honey, out of reach, deep;
</l><l>What use in honey hidden to keep?
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Robbed in the autumn, starving for bread;
</l><l>Who stops to pity a honey-bee dead?
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Star-flames are brightest, blazing the skies;
</l><l>Only a hand's breadth the moth-wing flies.
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Fooled with a candle, scorched with a breath;
</l><l>Poor little miller, a tawdry death!
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Life is a honey, life is a flame;
</l><l>Each to his passion; what's in a name?
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Swinging and circling, face to the sun,
</l><l>Brief little planet, how it doth run!
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Bee-time and moth-time, add the amount;
</l><l>White heat and honey, who keeps the count?
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Gone some fine evening, a spark out-tost!
</l><l>The world no darker for one star lost!
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Bee to the blossom, moth to the flame;
</l><l>Each to his passion; what's in a name?
</l>
</lg>






<lg type="stanza">
<head>HABEAS CORPUS.</head>
<l>MY body, eh?  Friend Death, how now?
</l><l rend="indent">   Why all this tedious pomp of writ?
</l><l>Thou hast reclaimed it sure and slow
</l><l rend="indent">   For half a century, bit by bit.
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>In faith thou knowest more to-day
</l><l rend="indent">   Than I do where it can be found!
</l><l>This shriveled lump of suffering clay,
</l><l rend="indent">   To which I now am chained and bound,
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Has not of kith or kin a trace
</l><l rend="indent">   To the good body once I bore;
</l><l>Look at this shrunken, ghastly face:
</l><l>   Didst ever see that face before?
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Ah, well, friend Death, good friend thou art;
</l><l rend="indent">   Thy only fault thy lagging gait,
</l><l>Mistaken pity in thy heart
</l><l rend="indent">   For timorous ones that bid thee wait.
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Do quickly all thou hast to do,
</l><l rend="indent">   Nor I nor mine will hindrance make;
</l><l>I shall be free when thou art through;
</l><l rend="indent">   I grudge thee nought that thou must take!
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Stay!  I have lied; I grudge thee one,
</l><l rend="indent">   Yes, two I grudge thee at this last, &mdash;
</l><l>Two members which have faithful done
</l><l rend="indent">   My will and bidding in the past.
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>I grudge thee this right hand of mine,
</l><l rend="indent">   I grudge thee this quick-beating heart;
</l><l>They never gave me coward sign,
</l><l rend="indent">   Nor played me once a traitor's part.
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>I see now why in olden days
</l><l rend="indent">   Men in barbaric love or hate
</l><l>Nailed enemies' hands at wild crossways,
</l><l rend="indent">   Shrined leaders' hearts in costly state:
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>The symbol, sign, and instrument
</l><l rend="indent">   Of each soul's purpose, passion, strife,
</l><l>Of fires in which are poured and spent
</l><l rend="indent">   Their all of love, their all of life.
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>O feeble, mighty human hand!
</l><l rend="indent">   O fragile, dauntless human heart!
</l><l>The universe holds nothing planned
</l><l rend="indent">   With such sublime, transcendent art!
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Yes, Death, I own I grudge thee mine
</l><l rend="indent">   Poor little hand, so feeble now;
</l><l>Its wrinkled palm, its altered line,
</l><l rend="indent">   Its veins so pallid and so slow &mdash;
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>. . . (Unfinished here.)</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>Ah, well, friend Death, good friend thou art;
</l><l rend="indent">   I shall be free when thou art through.
</l><l>Take all there is &mdash; take hand and heart;
</l><l rend="indent">   There must be somewhere work to do.
</l>
</lg>

<p>August 7th.</p>


   <pb n="259"/>




<lg type="stanza">
<head>A LAST PRAYER.</head>
<l>FATHER, I scarcely dare to pray,
</l><l rend="indent">   So clear I see, now it is done,
</l><l>That I have wasted half my day,
</l><l rend="indent">   And left my work but just begun;
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>So clear I see that things I thought
</l><l rend="indent">   Were right or harmless were a sin;
</l><l>So clear I see that I have sought,
</l><l rend="indent">   Unconscious, selfish aims to win;
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>So clear I see that I have hurt
</l><l rend="indent">   The souls I might have helped to save,
</l><l>That I have slothful been, inert,
</l><l rend="indent">   Deaf to the calls thy leaders gave.
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>In outskirts of thy kingdoms vast,
</l><l rend="indent">   Father, the humblest spot give me;
</l><l>Set me the lowliest task thou hast,
</l><l rend="indent">   Let me repentant work for thee!
</l>
</lg>

<p>   August 8th.</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

