<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HigSpir"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="HigSpir">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Negro Spirituals</title>
<title type="sort">negro spirituals</title>
<author>Higginson, Thomas Wentworth, 1823-1911</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">47</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HigSpir</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476078</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Negro Spirituals</title>
<title type="sort">negro spirituals</title>
<author>Thomas Wentworth Higginson</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>Volume 19</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
<date value="1867-06">June, 1867</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Atlantic Monthly</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Text is from the Atlantic Monthly, Volume 19, June 1867:
685-94</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Spell-check not performed due to presence of dialect in text.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term>
<term>democracy</term>
<term>religion</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>African American</term>
<term>American Civil War</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-11">November 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Matthew G. Kirschenbaum, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia
Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI.2-conformant header and tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">

<div1 type="work" id="d3">
<pb n="685"/>

<div2 type="foreword" id="d4">
<head>NEGRO SPIRITUALS.</head>

<p>THE war brought to some of us, besides its direct experiences, many
a strange fulfilment of dreams of other days.  For instance, the
present writer had been a faithful student of the Scottish ballads,
and had always envied Sir Walter the delight of tracing them out
amid their own heather, and of writing them down piecemeal from the
lips of aged crones.  It was a strange enjoyment, therefore, to be
suddenly brought into the midst of a kindred world of unwritten
songs, as simple and indigenous as the Border Minstrelsy, more
uniformly plaintive, almost always more quaint, and often as
essentially poetic.</p>
<p>This interest was rather increased by the fact that I had for
many years heard of this class of songs under the name of "Negro
Spirituals," and had even heard some of them sung by friends from
South Carolina.  I could now gather on their own soil these strange
plants, which I had before seen as in museums alone.  True, the
individual songs rarely coincided; there was a line here, a chorus
there, &mdash; just enough to fix the class, but this was unmistakable.
It was not strange that they differed, for the range seemed almost
endless, and South Carolina, Georgia, and Florida seemed to have
nothing but the generic character in common, until all were mingled
in the united stock of camp-melodies.</p>
<p>Often in the starlit evening I have returned from some lonely
ride by the swift river, or on the plover-haunted barrens, and,
entering the camp, have silently approached some glimmering fire,
round which the dusky figures moved in the rhythmical barbaric
dance the negroes call a "shout," chanting, often harshly, but
always in the most perfect time, some monotonous refrain.  Writing
down in the darkness, as I best could, &mdash; perhaps with my hand in the
safe covert of my pocket, &mdash; the words of the song, I have afterwards
carried it to my tent, like some captured bird or insect, and then,
after examination, put it by.  Or, summoning one of the men at some
period of leisure, &mdash; Corporal Robert Sutton, for instance, whose
iron memory held all the details of a song as if it were a ford or
a forest, &mdash; I have completed the new specimen by supplying the
absent parts.  The music I could only retain by ear, and though the
more common strains were repeated often enough to fix their
impression, there were others that occurred only once or twice.</p>
<p>The words will be here given, as nearly as possible, in the
original dialect; and if the spelling seems sometimes inconsistent,
or the misspelling insufficient, it is because I could get no
nearer.  I wished to avoid what seems to me the only error of
Lowell's "Biglow Papers" in respect to dialect, &mdash; the occasional use
of an extreme misspelling, which merely confuses the eye, without
taking us any closer to the peculiarity of sound.</p>
<p>The favorite song in camp was the following, &mdash; sung with no
accompaniment but the measured clapping of hands and the clatter of
many feet.  It was sung perhaps twice as often as any other.  This
was partly due to the fact that it properly consisted of a chorus
alone, with which the verses of other songs might be combined at
random.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="poem" id="d5">
<head>I.  HOLD YOUR LIGHT.</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>"Hold your light, Brudder Robert, &mdash; </l>
    <l rend="indent">Hold your light,</l>
 <l>Hold your light on Canaan's shore.</l>
</lg><lg type="stanza">
<l>"What make ole Satan for follow me so?</l>
 <l>Satan ain't got notin' for do wid me.</l>
    <l rend="indent">Hold your light,</l>
    <l rend="indent">Hold your light,</l>
 <l>Hold your light on Canaan's shore."</l>
</lg>

<p>This would be sung for half an hour at a time, perhaps, each
person present being named in turn.  It seemed the simplest
primitive type of "spiritual."  The next in popularity was almost
as elementary, and, like this, named successively<pb n="686"/> each one
of the circle.  It was, however, much more resounding and convivial
in its music.</p>
 </div2>

<div2 type="poem" id="d6">
<head>II.  BOUND TO GO.</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"Jordan River, I'm bound to go,</l>
    <l rend="indent">Bound to go, bound to go, &mdash; </l>
 <l>Jordan River, I'm bound to go,</l>
    <l rend="indent">And bid 'em fare ye well.</l>
</lg><lg type="chorus">
<l>"My Brudder Robert, I'm bound to go,</l>
    <l rend="indent">Bound to go, &amp;c.</l>
</lg><lg type="chorus">
<l>"My Sister Lucy, I'm bound to go,</l>
    <l rend="indent">Bound to go, &amp;c.</l>
</lg>

<p>Sometimes it was "tink 'em" (think them) "fare ye well."  The
<hi rend="italic">ye</hi> was so detached that I thought at first it was "very" or
"vary well."</p>
<p>Another picturesque song, which seemed immensely popular, was
at first very bewildering to me.  I could not make out the first
words of the chorus, and called it the "Romandar," being reminded
of some Romaic song which I had formerly heard.  That association
quite fell in with the Orientalism of the new tent-life.</p>
 </div2>
<div2 type="poem" id="d7">
<head>III.  ROOM IN THERE.</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"O my mudder is gone! my mudder is gone!</l>
<l>My mudder is gone into heaven, my Lord!</l>
    <l rend="indent">I can't stay behind!</l>
<l>Dere's room in dar, room in dar,</l>
<l>Room in dar, in de heaven, my Lord!</l>
    <l rend="indent">I can't stay behind,</l>
<l>Can't stay behind, my dear,</l>
    <l rend="indent">I can't stay behind!</l>
</lg>
<lg type="chorus"><l>"O, my fader is gone!" &amp;c.</l></lg>

<lg type="chorus"><l>"O, de angels are gone!" &amp;c.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza"><l>"O, I'se been on de road!  I'se been on de road!</l>
<l>I'se been on de road into heaven, my Lord!</l>
    <l rend="indent">I can't stay behind!</l>
<l>O, room in dar, room in dar,</l>
<l>Room in dar, in de heaven, my Lord!</l>
    <l rend="indent">I can't stay behind!"</l></lg>

<p>By this time every man within hearing, from oldest to
youngest, would be wriggling and shuffling, as if through some
magic piper's bewitchment; for even those who at first affected
contemptuous indifference would be drawn into the vortex erelong.</p>
<p>Next to these in popularity ranked a class of songs belonging
emphatically to the Church Militant, and available for camp
purposes with very little strain upon their symbolism.  This, for
instance, had a true companions-in-arms heartiness about it, not
impaired by the feminine invocation at the end.</p>
 </div2>

<div2 type="poem" id="d8">
<head>IV.  HAIL MARY.</head>
<lg type="stanza">
     <l>"One more valiant soldier here,</l>
         <l rend="indent">One more valiant soldier here,</l>
      <l>One more valiant soldier here,</l>
         <l rend="indent">To help me bear de cross.</l>
      <l>O hail, Mary, hail!</l>
         <l rend="indent">Hail, Mary, hail!</l>
      <l>Hail, Mary, hail!</l>
         <l rend="indent">To help me bear de cross."</l>
</lg>

<p>I fancied that the original reading might have been "soul,"
instead of "soldier," &mdash; with some other syllable inserted, to fill
out the metre, &mdash; and that the "Hail, Mary," might denote a Roman
Catholic origin, as I had several men from St. Augustine who held
in a dim way to that faith.  It was a very ringing song, though not
so grandly jubilant as the next, which was really impressive as the
singers pealed it out, when marching or rowing or embarking.</p>
 </div2>

<div2 type="poem" id="d9">
<head>V.  MY ARMY CROSS OVER.</head>
<lg type="stanza">
     <l>"My army cross over,</l>
      <l>My army cross over.</l>
      <l>O, Pharaoh's army drownded!</l>
      <l>My army cross over.</l></lg>
<lg type="stanza">
     <l>"We'll cross de mighty river,</l>
         <l rend="indent">My army cross over;</l>
      <l>We'll cross de river Jordan,</l>
         <l rend="indent">My army cross over;</l>
      <l>We'll cross de danger water,</l>
         <l rend="indent">My army cross over;</l>
      <l>We'll cross de mighty Myo,</l>
         <l rend="indent">My army cross over.  (<hi rend="italic">Thrice.</hi>)</l>
         <l rend="indent">O, Pharaoh's army drownded!</l>
         <l rend="indent">My army cross over."</l></lg>

<p>I could get no explanation of the "mighty Myo," except that
one of the old men thought it meant the river of death.  Perhaps it
is an African word.  In the Cameroon dialect, "Mawa" signifies "to
die."</p>
<p>The next also has a military ring about it, and the first line
is well matched by the music.  The rest is conglomerate, and one or
two lines show a more Northern origin.  "Done" is a Virginia
shibboleth, quite distinct from the "been" which replaces it in
South Carolina.  Yet one of their best choruses, without any fixed
words, was, "De bell done ringing," for which, in <pb n="687"/>  proper
South Carolina dialect, would have been substituted, "De bell been
a-ring."  This refrain may have gone South with our army.</p>
 </div2>

<div2 type="poem" id="d10">
<head>VI.  RIDE IN, KIND SAVIOUR.</head>
<lg type="stanza">
     <l>"Ride in, kind Saviour!</l>
         <l rend="indent">No man can hinder me.</l>
      <l>O, Jesus is a mighty man!</l>
         <l rend="indent">No man, &amp;c.</l>
      <l>We're marching through Virginny fields.</l>
         <l>No man, &amp;c.</l>
      <l>O, Satan is a busy man,</l>
         <l rend="indent">No man, &amp;c.</l>
      <l>And he has his sword and shield,</l>
         <l rend="indent">No man, &amp;c.</l>
      <l>O, old Secesh done come and gone!</l>
         <l rend="indent">No man can hinder me."</l>
</lg>

<p>Sometimes they substituted "hinder <hi rend="italic">we</hi>," which was more
spicy to the ear, and more in keeping with the usual head-over-heels arrangement of their pronouns.</p>
<p>Almost all their songs were thoroughly religious in their
tone, however quaint in their expression, and were in a minor key,
both as to words and music.  The attitude is always the same, and,
as a commentary on the life of the race, is infinitely pathetic.
Nothing but patience for this life, &mdash; nothing but triumph in the
next.  Sometimes the present predominates, sometimes the future;
but the combination is always implied.  In the following, for
instance, we hear simply the patience.</p>
 </div2>

<div2 type="poem" id="d11">
<head>VII.  THIS WORLD ALMOST DONE.</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"Brudder, keep your lamp trimmin' and a-burnin',</l>
<l>Keep your lamp trimmin' and a-burnin',</l>
<l>Keep your lamp trimmin' and a-burnin',</l>
    <l rend="indent">For dis world most done.</l>
<l>So keep your lamp, &amp;c.</l>
    <l rend="indent">Dis world most done."</l>
</lg>

<p>But in the next, the final reward of patience is proclaimed as
plaintively.</p>
 </div2>

<div2 type="poem" id="d12">
<head>VIII.  I WANT TO GO HOME.</head>
<lg type="stanza">
     <l>"Dere's no rain to wet you,</l>
         <l rend="indent">O, yes, I want to go home.</l>
      <l>Dere's no sun to burn you,</l>
         <l rend="indent">O, yes, I want to go home;</l>
      <l>O, push along, believers,</l>
         <l rend="indent">O, yes, &amp;c.</l>
      <l>Dere's no hard trials,</l>
         <l rend="indent">O, yes, &amp;c.</l>
      <l>Dere's no whips a-crackin',</l>
         <l rend="indent">O, yes, &amp;c.</l>
      <l>My brudder on de wayside,</l>
         <l rend="indent">O, yes, &amp;c.</l>
      <l>O, push along, my brudder,</l>
         <l rend="indent">O, yes, &amp;c.</l>
      <l>Where dere's no stormy weather,</l>
         <l rend="indent">O, yes, &amp;c.</l>
      <l>Dere's no tribulation,</l>
         <l rend="indent">O, yes, &amp;c."</l>
</lg>

<p>This next was a boat-song, and timed well with the tug of the oar.</p>
 </div2>

<div2 type="poem" id="d13">
<head>IX.  THE COMING DAY.</head>
<lg type="stanza">
     <l>"I want to go to Canaan,</l>
      <l>I want to go to Canaan,</l>
      <l>I want to go to Canaan,</l>
         <l rend="indent">To meet 'em at de comin' day.</l>
      <l>O, remember, let me go to Cannan, (<hi rend="italic">Thrice.</hi>)</l>
         <l rend="indent">To meet 'em, &amp;c.</l>
      <l>O, brudder, let me go to Canaan, (<hi rend="italic">Thrice.</hi>)</l>
         <l rend="indent">To meet 'em, &amp;c.</l>
      <l>My brudder, you &mdash; oh I &mdash; remember (<hi rend="italic">Thrice.</hi>)</l>
         <l rend="indent">To meet 'em at de comin' day."</l>
</lg>

<p>The following begins with a startling affirmation, yet the
last line quite outdoes the first.  This, too, was a capital boat-song.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="poem" id="d14">
<head>X.  ONE MORE RIVER.</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>O, Jordan bank was a great old bank!</l>
    <l rend="indent">Dere ain't but one more river to cross.</l>
<l>We have some valiant soldier here,</l>
    <l rend="indent">Dere ain't, &amp;c.</l>
<l>O, Jordan stream will never run dry,</l>
    <l rend="indent">Dere ain't, &amp;c.</l>
<l>Dere's a hill on my leff, and he catch on my right,</l>
    <l rend="indent">Dere ain't but one more river to cross."</l>
</lg>

<p>I could get no explanation of this last riddle, except, "Dat
mean, if you go on de leff, go to 'struction, and if you go on de
right, go to God, for sure."</p>
<p>In others, more of spiritual conflict is implied, as in this
next.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="poem" id="d15">
<head>XI. O THE DYING LAMB!</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>"I wants to go where Moses trod,</l>
    <l rend="indent">O de dying Lamb!</l>
 <l>For Moses gone to de promised land,</l>
    <l rend="indent">O de dying Lamb!</l>
 <l>To drink from springs dat never run dry,</l>
    <l rend="indent">O, &amp;c.</l>
 <l>Cry O my Lord!</l>
    <l rend="indent">O, &amp;c.</l>
 <l>Before I'll stay in hell one day,</l>
    <l rend="indent">O, &amp;c.</l>
 <l>I'm in hopes to pray my sins away,</l>
    <l rend="indent">O, &amp;c.</l>
 <l>Cry O my Lord!</l>
    <l rend="indent">O, &amp;c.</l>
 <l>Brudder Moses promised for be dar too,</l>
    <l rend="indent">O, &amp;c.</l>
 <l>To drink from streams dat never run dry,</l>
    <l rend="indent">O de dying Lamb!"</l>
</lg>

<p>In the next, the conflict is at its height, and the lurid
imagery of the <pb n="688"/>  Apocalypse is brought to bear.  This book,
with the books of Moses, constituted their Bible; all that lay
between, even the narratives of the life of Jesus, they hardly
cared to read or to hear.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="poem" id="d16">
<head>XII.  DOWN IN THE VALLEY.</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>"We'll run and never tire,</l>
 <l>We'll run and never tire,</l>
 <l>We'll run and never tire,</l>
    <l rend="indent">Jesus set poor sinners free.</l>
 <l>Way down in de valley,</l>
    <l rend="indent">Who will rise and go with me!</l>
 <l>You've heern talk of Jesus,</l>
    <l rend="indent">Who set poor sinners free.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"De lightnin' and de flashin',</l>
 <l>De lightnin' and de flashin',</l>
 <l>De lightnin' and de flashin',</l>
    <l rend="indent">Jesus set poor sinners free.</l>
 <l>I can't stand de fire.  (<hi rend="italic">Thrice.</hi>)</l>
    <l rend="indent">Jesus set poor sinners free,</l>
 <l>De green trees a-flamin'.  (<hi rend="italic">Thrice.</hi>)</l>
    <l rend="indent">Jesus set poor sinners free,</l>
       <l rend="indent">Way down in de valley,</l>
          <l rend="indent">Who will rise and go with me?</l>
       <l rend="indent">You've heern talk of Jesus</l>
          <l rend="indent">Who set poor sinners free."</l>
</lg>

<p>"De valley" and "de lonesome valley" were familiar words in
their religious experience.  To descend into that region implied
the same process with the "anxious-seat" of the camp-meeting.  When
a young girl was supposed to enter it, she bound a handkerchief by
a peculiar knot over her head, and made it a point of honor not to
change a single garment till the day of her baptism, so that she
was sure of being in physical readiness for the cleansing rite,
whatever her spiritual mood might be.  More than once, in noticing
a damsel thus mystically kerchiefed, I have asked some dusky
attendant its meaning, and have received the unfailing answer, &mdash;
framed with their usual indifference to the genders of pronouns, &mdash;
"He in de lonesome valley, sa."</p>
<p>The next gives the same dramatic conflict, while its detached
and impersonal refrain gives it strikingly the character of the
Scotch and Scandinavian ballads.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="poem" id="d17">
<head>XIII.  CRY HOLY.</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>"Cry holy, holy!</l>
    <l rend="indent">Look at de people dat is born of God.</l>
<l>And I run down de valley, and I run down to pray,</l>
    <l rend="indent">Says, look at de people dat is born of God.</l>
<l>When I get dar, Cappen Satan was dar,</l>
    <l rend="indent">Says, look at, &amp;c.</l>
<l>Says, young man, young man, dere's no use for pray,</l>
    <l rend="indent">Says, look at, &amp;c.</l>
<l>For Jesus is dead, and God gone away,</l>
    <l rend="indent">Says, look at, &amp;c.</l>
<l>And I made him out a liar and I went my way,</l>
    <l rend="indent">Says, look at, &amp;c.</l>
   <l rend="indent">Sing holy, holy!</l>
</lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"O, Mary was a woman, and he had a one Son,</l>
    <l rend="indent">Says, look at, &amp;c.</l>
<l>And de Jews and de Romans had him hung,</l>
    <l rend="indent">Says, look at, &amp;c.</l>
   <l rend="indent">Cry holy, holy!</l>
</lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"And I tell you, sinner, you had better had pray,</l>
    <l rend="indent">Says, look at, &amp;c.</l>
<l>For hell is a dark and dismal place,</l>
    <l rend="indent">Says, look at, &amp;c.</l>
<l>And I tell you, sinner, and I wouldn't go dar!</l>
    <l rend="indent">Says, look at, &amp;c.</l>
   <l rend="indent">Cry holy, holy!"</l>
</lg>

<p>Here is an infinitely quaint description of the length of the
heavenly road: &mdash; </p>
</div2>

<div2 type="poem" id="d18">
<head>XIV.  O'ER THE CROSSING.</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"Yonder's my old mudder,</l>
    <l rend="indent">Been a-waggin' at de hill so long.</l>
<l>It's about time she'll cross over;</l>
    <l rend="indent">Get home bimeby.</l>
<l>Keep prayin', I do believe</l>
    <l rend="indent">We're a long time waggin' o'er de crossin'.</l>
<l>Keep prayin', I do believe</l>
    <l rend="indent">We'll get home to heaven bimeby.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"Hear dat mournful thunder</l>
    <l rend="indent">Roll from door to door,</l>
<l>Calling home God's children;</l>
    <l rend="indent">Get home bimeby.</l>
<l>Little chil'en, I do believe</l>
    <l rend="indent">We're a long time, &amp;c.</l>
<l>Little chil'en, I do believe</l>
    <l rend="indent">We'll get home, &amp;c.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"See dat forked lightnin'</l>
    <l rend="indent">Flash from tree to tree,</l>
<l>Callin' home God's chil'en;</l>
    <l rend="indent">Get home bimeby.</l>
<l>True believer, I do believe</l>
    <l rend="indent">We're a long time, &amp;c.</l>
<l>O brudders, I do believe,</l>
    <l rend="indent">We'll get home to heaven bimeby.</l>
</lg>

<p>One of the most singular pictures of future joys, and with a
fine flavor of hospitality about it, was this: &mdash; </p>
</div2>

<div2 type="poem" id="d19">
<head>XV.  WALK 'EM EASY.</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>"O, walk 'em easy round de heaven,</l>
<l>Walk 'em easy round de heaven,</l>
<l>Walk 'em easy round de heaven,</l>
    <l rend="indent">Dat all de people may join de band.</l>
<l>Walk 'em easy round de heaven.  (<hi rend="italic">Thrice.</hi>)</l>
    <l rend="indent">O, shout glory till 'em join dat band!"</l></lg>

<p>The chorus was usually the greater <pb n="689"/>  part of the song,
and often came in paradoxically, thus: &mdash; </p>
</div2>

<div2 type="poem" id="d20">
<head>XVI.  O YES, LORD.</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>"O, must I be like de foolish mans?</l>
        <l rend="indent">O yes, Lord!</l>
 <l>Will build de house on de sandy hill.</l>
        <l rend="indent">O yes, Lord!</l>
 <l>I'll build my house on Zion hill,</l>
        <l rend="indent">O yes, Lord!</l>
 <l>No wind nor rain can blow me down</l>
        <l rend="indent">O yes, Lord!"</l>
</lg>

<p>The next is very graceful and lyrical, and with more variety
of rhythm than usual: &mdash; </p>
</div2>

<div2 type="poem" id="d21">
<head>XVII.  BOW LOW, MARY.</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>"Bow low, Mary, bow low, Martha,</l>
    <l rend="indent">For Jesus come and lock de door,</l>
    <l rend="indent">And carry de keys away.</l>
 <l>Sail, sail, over yonder,</l>
 <l>And view de promised land.</l>
    <l rend="indent">For Jesus come, &amp;c.</l>
 <l>Weep, O Mary, bow low, Martha,</l>
    <l rend="indent">For Jesus come, &amp;c.</l>
 <l>Sail, sail, my true believer;</l>
 <l>Sail, sail, over yonder;</l>
 <l>Mary, bow low, Martha, bow low,</l>
    <l rend="indent">For Jesus come and lock de door</l>
    <l rend="indent">And carry de keys away."</l></lg>

<p>But of all the "spirituals" that which surprised me most, I
think, &mdash; perhaps because it was that in which external nature
furnished the images most directly, &mdash; was this.  With all my
experience of their ideal ways of speech, I was startled when first
I came on such a flower of poetry in that dark soil.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="poem" id="d22">
<head>XVIII.  I KNOW MOON-RISE.</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"I know moon-rise, I know star-rise,</l>
   <l rend="indent">Lay dis body down.</l>
<l>I walk in de moonlight, I walk in de starlight,</l>
   <l rend="indent">To lay dis body down.</l>
<l>I'll walk in de graveyard, I'll walk through de
     graveyard,</l>
   <l rend="indent">To lay dis body down.</l>
<l>I'll lie in de grave and stretch out my arms;</l>
   <l rend="indent">Lay dis body down.</l>
<l>I go to de judgment in de evenin' of de day,</l>
   <l rend="indent">When I lay dis body down;</l>
<l>And my soul and your soul will meet in de day</l>
   <l rend="indent">When I lay dis body down."</l>
</lg>

<p>"I'll lie in de grave and stretch out my arms."  Never, it
seems to me, since man first lived and suffered, was his infinite
longing for peace uttered more plaintively than in that line.</p>
<p>The next is one of the wildest and most striking of the whole
series: there is a mystical effect and a passionate striving
throughout the whole.  The Scriptural struggle between Jacob and
the angel, which is only dimly expressed in the words, seems all
uttered in the music.  I think it impressed my imagination more
powerfully than any other of these songs.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="poem" id="d23">
<head>XIX.  WRESTLING JACOB.</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>"O wrestlin' Jacob, Jacob, day's a-breakin';</l>
   <l rend="indent">I will not let thee go!</l>
<l>O wrestlin' Jacob, Jacob, day's a-breakin';</l>
   <l rend="indent">He will not let me go!</l>
<l>O, I hold my brudder wid a tremblin' hand;</l>
   <l rend="indent">I would not let him go!</l>
<l>I hold my sister wid a tremblin' hand;</l>
   <l rend="indent">I would not let her go!</l>
</lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"O, Jacob do hang from a tremblin' limb,</l>
   <l rend="indent">He would not let him go!</l>
<l>O, Jacob do hang from a tremblin' limb;</l>
   <l rend="indent">De Lord will bless my soul.</l>
<l>O wrestlin' Jacob, Jacob," &amp;c.</l>
</lg>

<p>Of "occasional hymns," properly so called, I noticed but one,
a funeral hymn for an infant, which is sung plaintively over and
over, without variety of words.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="poem" id="d24">
<head>XX.  THE BABY GONE HOME.</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>"De little baby gone home,</l>
 <l>De little baby gone home,</l>
 <l>De little baby gone along,</l>
    <l rend="indent">For to climb up Jacob's ladder.</l>
 <l>And I wish I'd been dar,</l>
 <l>I wish I'd been dar,</l>
 <l>I wish I'd been dar, my Lord,</l>
    <l rend="indent">For to climb up Jacob's ladder."</l></lg>

<p>Still simpler is this, which is yet quite sweet and touching.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="poem" id="d25">
<head>XXI.  JESUS WITH US.</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"He have been wid us, Jesus,</l>
    <l rend="indent">He still wid us, Jesus,</l>
 <l>He will be wid us, Jesus,</l>
    <l rend="indent">He wid us to the end."</l>
</lg>

<p>The next seemed to be a favorite about Christmas time, when
meditations on "de rollin' year" were frequent among them.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="poem" id="d26">
<head>XXII.  LORD, REMEMBER ME!</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"O do, Lord, remember me!</l>
    <l rend="indent">O do, Lord, remember me!</l>
 <l>O, do remember me, until de year roll round!</l>
    <l rend="indent">Do, Lord, remember me!</l>
</lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"If you want to die like Jesus died,</l>
    <l rend="indent">Lay in de grave,</l>
 <l>You would fold your arms and close your eyes</l>
    <l rend="indent">And die wid a free good will.</l> <pb n="690"/>
</lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"For Death is a simple ting,</l>
    <l rend="indent">And he go from door to door,</l>
 <l>And he knock down some, and he cripple up some,</l>
    <l rend="indent">And he leave some here to pray.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"O do, Lord, remember me!</l>
    <l rend="indent">O do, Lord, remember me!</l>
 <l>My old fader's gone till de year roll round;</l>
    <l rend="indent">Do, Lord, remember me!"</l>
</lg>

<p>The next was sung in such an operatic and rollicking way that
it was quite hard to fancy it a religious performance, which,
however, it was.  I heard it but once.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="poem" id="d27">
<head>XXIII.  EARLY IN THE MORNING.</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"I meet little Rosa early in de mornin',</l>
    <l rend="indent">O Jerusalem! early in de mornin';</l>
 <l>And I ax her, How you do, my darter?</l>
    <l rend="indent">O Jerusalem! early in de mornin'.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"I meet my mudder early in de mornin',</l>
    <l rend="indent">O Jerusalem! &amp;c.</l>
 <l>And I ax her, How you do, my mudder?</l>
    <l rend="indent">O Jerusalem! &amp;c.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"I meet Brudder Robert early in de mornin',</l>
    <l rend="indent">O Jerusalem! &amp;c.</l>
 <l>And I ax him, How you do, my sonny?</l>
    <l rend="indent">O Jerusalem! &amp;c.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"I meet Tittawisa early in de mornin,</l>
    <l rend="indent">O Jerusalem! &amp;c.</l>
 <l>And I ax her, How you do, my darter?</l>
    <l rend="indent">O Jerusalem! &amp;c.</l>
</lg>

<p>"Tittawisa" means "Sister Louisa."  In songs of this class the
name of every person present successively appears.</p>
<p>Their best marching song, and one which was invaluable to lift
their feet along, as they expressed it, was the following.  There
was a kind of spring and <hi rend="italic">lilt</hi> to it, quite indescribable by
words.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="poem" id="d28">
<head>XXIV.  GO IN THE WILDERNESS.</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"Jesus call you.  Go in de wilderness,</l>
    <l rend="indent">Go in de wilderness, go in de wilderness,</l>
 <l>Jesus call you.  Go in de wilderness</l>
    <l rend="indent">To wait upon de Lord,</l>
 <l>Go wait upon de Lord,</l>
 <l>Go wait upon de Lord,</l>
 <l>Go wait upon de Lord, my God,</l>
    <l rend="indent">He take away de sins of de world.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"Jesus a-waitin'.  Go in de wilderness,</l>
    <l rend="indent">Go, &amp;c.</l>
 <l>All dem chil'en go in de wilderness</l>
    <l rend="indent">To wait upon de Lord."</l>
</lg>

<p>The next was one of those which I had heard in boyish days,
brought North from Charleston.  But the chorus alone was identical;
the words were mainly different, and those here given are quaint
enough.</p>
 </div2>
<div2 type="poem" id="d29">
<head>XXV.  BLOW YOUR TRUMPET, GABRIEL.</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"O, blow your trumpet, Gabriel,</l>
    <l>Blow your trumpet louder;</l><l>
 And I want dat trumpet to blow me home</l><l>
    To my new Jerusalem.</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>"De prettiest ting dat ever I done</l><l>
 Was to serve de Lord when I was young,</l><l>
    So blow your trumpet, Gabriel, &amp;c.</l></lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"O, Satan is a liar, and he conjure too,</l><l>
 And if you don't mind, he'll conjure you.</l><l>
    So blow your trumpet, Gabriel, &amp;c.</l></lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"O, I was lost in de wilderness,</l><l>
 King Jesus hand me de candle down.</l><l>
    So blow your trumpet, Gabriel," &amp;c.</l></lg>

<p>The following contains one of those odd transformations of
proper names with which their Scriptural citations were often
enriched.  It rivals their text, "Paul may plant, and may polish
wid water," which I have elsewhere quoted, and in which the sainted
Apollos would hardly have recognized himself.</p>
 </div2>
<div2 type="poem" id="d30">
     <head>XXVI.  IN THE MORNING.</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"In de mornin',</l>
 <l>In de mornin',</l><l>
 Chil'en?  Yes, my Lord!</l><l>
    Don't you hear de trumpet sound?</l><l>
 If I had a-died when I was young,</l><l>
 I never would had de race for run,</l><l>
    Don't you hear de trumpet sound?</l>
</lg><lg type="stanza">
<l>"O Sam and Peter was fishin' in de sea,</l><l>
 And dey drop de net and follow my Lord.</l><l>
    Don't you hear de trumpet sound?</l>
</lg><lg type="stanza">
<l>"Dere's a silver spade for to dig my grave</l><l>
 And a golden chain for to let me down.</l><l>
    Don't you hear de trumpet sound?</l><l>
 In de mornin',</l><l>
 In de mornin',</l><l>
Chil'en?  Yes, my Lord!</l><l>
    Don't you hear de trumpet sound?"</l>
</lg>

<p>These golden and silver fancies remind one of the King of
Spain's daughter in "Mother Goose," and the golden apple, and the
silver pear, which are doubtless themselves but the vestiges of
some simple early composition like this.  The next has a humbler
and more domestic style of fancy.</p>
 </div2>
<div2 type="poem" id="d31">
<head>XXVII.  FARE YE WELL.</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"My true believers, fare ye well,</l>
 <l>Fare ye well, fare ye well,</l><l>
 Fare ye well, by de grace of God,</l><l>
    For I'm going home.</l> <pb n="691"/>
</lg>
<lg type="stanza"><l>
 Massa Jesus give me a little broom</l><l>
 For to sweep my heart clean,</l><l>
 And I will try, by de grace of God,</l><l>
    To win my way home."</l>
</lg>

<p>Among the songs not available for marching, but requiring the
concentrated enthusiasm of the camp, was "The Ship of Zion," of
which they had three wholly distinct versions, all quite exuberant
and tumultuous.</p>
 </div2>
<div2 type="poem" id="d32">
<head>XXVIII.  THE SHIP OF ZION.</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"Come along, come along,</l>
    <l>And let us go home,</l><l>
    O, glory, hallelujah!</l><l>
    Dis de ole ship o' Zion,</l><l>
        Halleloo!  Halleloo!</l><l>
    Dis de ole ship o' Zion,</l><l>
        Hallelujah!</l>
</lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"She has landed many a tousand,</l><l>
 She can land as many more.</l><l>
    O, glory, hallelujah! &amp;c.</l></lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"Do you tink she will be able</l><l>
 For to take us all home?</l><l>
    O, glory, hallelujah! &amp;c.</l></lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"You can tell 'em I'm a comin',</l><l>
    Halleloo!  Halleloo!</l><l>
 You can tell 'em I'm a comin',</l><l>
    Hallelujah!</l><l>
 Come along, come along," &amp;c.</l></lg>
 </div2>
<div2 type="poem" id="d33">
<head>XXIX.  THE SHIP OF ZION.  (<hi rend="italic">Second version.</hi>)</head>
<lg type="stanza"><l>
"Dis de good ole ship o' Zion,</l><l>
 Dis de good ole ship o' Zion,</l><l>
 Dis de good ole ship o' Zion,</l><l>
    And she's makin' for de Promise Land.</l><l>
 She hab angels for de sailors, (<hi rend="italic">Thrice.</hi>)</l><l>
    And she's, &amp;c.</l><l>
 And how you know dey's angels? (<hi rend="italic">Thrice.</hi>)</l><l>
    And she's, &amp;c.</l><l>
 Good Lord, shall I be de one? (<hi rend="italic">Thrice.</hi>)</l><l>
    And she's, &amp;c.</l></lg>
<lg type="stanza"><l>
"Dat ship is out a-sailin', sailin', sailin',</l><l>
    And she's, &amp;c.</l><l>
 She's a-sailin' mighty steady, steady, steady,</l><l>
    And she's, &amp;c.</l><l>
 She'll neither reel nor totter, totter, totter,</l><l>
    And she's, &amp;c.</l><l>
 She's a-sailin' away cold Jordan, Jordan, Jordan,</l><l>
    And she's, &amp;c.</l><l>
 King Jesus is de captain, captain, captain,</l><l>
    And she's makin' for de Promise Land."</l></lg>
 </div2>
<div2 type="poem" id="d34">
<head>XXX.  THE SHIP OF ZION (<hi rend="italic">Third version.</hi>)</head>
<lg type="stanza">
     <l>"De Gospel ship is sailin',</l><l>
         Hosann &mdash; sann.</l><l>
      O, Jesus is de captain,</l><l>
         Hosann &mdash; sann.</l><l>
      De angels are de sailors,</l><l>
         Hosann-sann.</l><l>
      O, is your bundle ready?</l><l>
         Hosann-sann.</l><l>
      O, have you got your ticket?</l><l>
         Hosann &mdash; sann."</l></lg>

<p>This abbreviated chorus is given with unspeakable unction.</p><p>
The three just given are modifications of an old camp-meeting
melody; and the same may be true of the three following, although
I cannot find them in the Methodist hymn-books.  Each, however, has
its characteristic modifications, which make it well worth giving.
In the second verse of this next, for instance, "Saviour" evidently
has become "soldier."</p>
 </div2>
<div2 type="poem" id="d35">
     <head>XXXI.  SWEET MUSIC.</head>
<lg type="stanza"><l>
"Sweet music in heaven,</l><l>
    Just beginning for to roll.</l><l>
 Don't you love God?</l><l>
    Glory, hallelujah!</l></lg>
<lg type="stanza"><l>
"Yes, late I heard my soldier say,</l><l>
 Come, heavy soul, I am de way.</l><l>
    Don't you love God?</l><l>
    Glory, hallelujah!</l></lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"I'll go and tell to sinners round</l><l>
 What a kind Saviour I have found.</l><l>
    Don't you love God?</l><l>
    Glory, hallelujah!</l></lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"My grief my burden long has been,</l><l>
 Because I was not cease from sin.</l><l>
    Don't you love God?</l><l>
    Glory, hallelujah!"</l></lg>
 </div2>
<div2 type="poem" id="d36">
     <head>XXXII.  GOOD NEWS.</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"O, good news!  O, good news!</l><l>
 De angels brought de tidings down,</l><l>
    Just comin' from de trone.</l>
</lg><lg type="stanza"><l>
"As grief from out my soul shall fly,</l><l>
    Just comin' from de trone;</l><l>
 I'll shout salvation when I die,</l><l>
    Good news, O, good news!</l><l>
    Just comin' from de trone.</l>
</lg><lg type="stanza">
<l>"Lord, I want to go to heaven when I die,</l><l>
 Good news, O, good news! &amp;c.</l></lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"De white folks call us a noisy crew,</l><l>
    Good news, O, good news!</l><l>
 But dis I know, we are happy too,</l><l>
    Just comin' from de trone."</l></lg>
 </div2>
<div2 type="poem" id="d37">
<head>XXXIII.  THE HEAVENLY ROAD.</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"You may talk of my name as much as you please,</l><l>
    And carry my name abroad,</l><l>
 But I really do believe I'm a child of God</l><l>
    As I walk in de heavenly road.</l><l>
 O, won't you go wid me? (<hi rend="italic">Thrice.</hi>)</l><l>
    For to keep our garments clean.</l>
</lg><lg type="stanza">
<l>"O, Satan is a mighty busy ole man,</l><l>
    And roll rocks in my way; <pb n="692"/> </l><l>
 But Jesus is my bosom friend,</l><l>
    And roll 'em out of de way.</l><l>
 O, won't you go wid me? (<hi rend="italic">Thrice.</hi>)</l><l>
    For to keep our garments clean.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="stanza"><l>"Come, my brudder, if you never did pray,</l><l>
    I hope you may pray to-night;</l><l>
 For I really believe I'm a child of God</l><l>
    As I walk in de heavenly road.</l><l>
 O, won't you," &amp;c.</l></lg>

<p>Some of the songs had played an historic part during the war.
For singing the next, for instance, the negroes had been put in
jail in Georgetown, S. C., at the outbreak of the Rebellion.
"We'll soon be free," was too dangerous an assertion; and though
the chant was an old one, it was no doubt sung with redoubled
emphasis during the new events.  "De Lord will call us home," was
evidently thought to be a symbolical verse; for, as a little
drummer-boy explained to me, showing all his white teeth as he sat
in the moonlight by the door of my tent, "Dey tink <hi rend="italic">de Lord</hi>
mean for say <hi rend="italic">de Yankees</hi>."</p>
 </div2>
<div2 type="poem" id="d38">
<head>XXXIV.  WE'LL SOON BE FREE.</head>
<lg type="stanza"><l>
     "We'll soon be free,</l><l>
      We'll soon be free,</l><l>
      We'll soon be free,</l><l>
         When de Lord will call us home.</l><l>
      My brudder, how long,</l><l>
      My brudder, how long,</l><l>
      My brudder, how long,</l><l>
         'Fore we done sufferin' here?</l><l>
      It won't be long (<hi rend="italic">Thrice.</hi>)</l><l>
         'For de Lord will call us home.</l><l>
      We'll walk de miry road (<hi rend="italic">Thrice.</hi>)</l><l>
         Where pleasure never dies.</l><l>
      We'll walk de golden street (<hi rend="italic">Thrice.</hi>)</l><l>
         Where pleasure never dies.</l><l>
      My brudder, how long (<hi rend="italic">Thrice.</hi>)</l><l>
         'Fore we done sufferin' here?</l><l>
      We'll soon be free (<hi rend="italic">Thrice.</hi>)</l><l>
         When Jesus sets me free.</l><l>
      We'll fight for liberty (<hi rend="italic">Thrice.</hi>)</l><l>
         When de Lord will call us home."</l></lg>

<p>The suspicion in this case was unfounded, but they had another
song to which the Rebellion had actually given rise.  This was
composed by nobody knew whom, &mdash; though it was the most recent,
doubtless, of all these "spirituals," &mdash; and had been sung in secret
to avoid detection.  It is certainly plaintive enough.  The peck of
corn and pint of salt were slavery's rations.</p>
 </div2>
<div2 type="poem" id="d39">
<head>XXXV.  MANY THOUSAND GO.</head>
<lg type="stanza"><l>
"No more peck o' corn for me,</l><l>
    No more, no more, &mdash; </l><l>
 No more peck o' corn for me,</l><l>
    Many tousand go.</l></lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"No more driver's lash for me, (<hi rend="italic">Twice.</hi>)</l>
    <l>No more, &amp;c.</l></lg>
<lg type="stanza"><l>
"No more pint o' salt for me, (<hi rend="italic">Twice.</hi>)</l>
    <l>No more, &amp;c.</l></lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>"No more hundred lash for me, (<hi rend="italic">Twice.</hi>)</l><l>
    No more, &amp;c.</l>
</lg><lg type="stanza">
<l>"No more mistress' call for me,</l>
    <l>No more, no more, &mdash; </l><l>
 No more mistress' call for me,</l><l>
    Many tousand go."</l></lg>

<p>Even of this last composition, however, we have only the
approximate date, and know nothing of the mode of composition.
Allan Ramsay says of the Scotch songs, that, no matter who made
them, they were soon attributed to the minister of the parish
whence they sprang.  And I always wondered, about these, whether
they had always a conscious and definite origin in some leading
mind, or whether they grew by gradual accretion, in an almost
unconscious way.  On this point I could get no information, though
I asked many questions, until at last, one day when I was being
rowed across from Beaufort to Ladies' Island, I found myself, with
delight, on the actual trail of a song.  One of the oarsmen, a
brisk young fellow, not a soldier, on being asked for his theory of
the matter, dropped out a coy confession.  "Some good sperituals,"
he said, "are start jess out o' curiosity.  I been a-raise a sing,
myself, once."</p><p>
My dream was fulfilled, and I had traced out, not the poem
alone, but the poet.  I implored him to proceed.</p><p>
"Once we boys," he said, "went for tote some rice, and de
nigger-driver, he keep a-callin' on us; and I say, 'O, de ole
nigger-driver!'  Den anudder said, 'Fust ting my mammy tole me was,
notin' so bad as nigger-driver.'  Den I made a sing, just puttin'
a word, and den anudder word."</p><p>
Then he began singing, and the men, after listening a moment,
joined in the chorus as if it were an old acquaintance, though they
evidently had never heard it before.  I saw how easily a new "sing"
took root among them.</p> <pb n="693"/>
 </div2>
<div2 type="poem" id="d40">
     <head>XXXVI.  THE DRIVER.</head>
<lg type="stanza"><l>
     "O, de ole nigger-driver!</l><l>
         O, gwine away!</l><l>
      Fust ting my mammy tell me,</l><l>
         O, gwine away!</l><l>
      Tell me 'bout de nigger-driver,</l><l>
         O, gwine away!</l><l>
      Nigger-driver second devil,</l><l>
         O, gwine away!</l><l>
      Best ting for do he driver,</l><l>
         O, gwine away!</l><l>
      Knock he down and spoil he labor,</l><l>
         O, gwine away!"</l></lg>

<p>It will be observed that, although this song is quite secular
in its character, its author yet called it a "spiritual."  I heard
but two songs among them, at any time, to which they would not,
perhaps, have given this generic name.  One of these consisted
simply in the endless repetition &mdash; after the manner of certain
college songs &mdash; of the mysterious line,

<q><l>"Rain fall and wet Becky Martin."</l></q></p>

<p>But who Becky Martin was, and why she should or should not be wet,
and whether the dryness was a reward or a penalty, none could say.
I got the impression that, in either case, the event was
posthumous, and that there was some tradition of grass not growing
over the grave of a sinner; but even this was vague, and all else
vaguer.</p><p>
The other song I heard but once, on a morning when a squad of
men came in from picket duty, and chanted it in the most rousing
way.  It had been a stormy and comfortless night, and the picket
station was very exposed.  It still rained in the morning when I
strolled to the edge of the camp, looking out for the men, and
wondering how they had stood it.  Presently they came striding
along the road, at a great pace, with their shining rubber blankets
worn as cloaks around them, the rain streaming from these and from
their equally shining faces, which were almost all upon the broad
grin, as they pealed out this remarkable ditty: &mdash; </p>
</div2>
<div2 type="poem" id="d41">
     <head>HANGMAN JOHNNY.</head>
<lg type="stanza"><l>
"O, dey call me Hangman Johnny!</l><l>
    O, ho!  O, ho!</l><l>
 But I never hang nobody,</l><l>
    O, hang, boys, hang!</l></lg>
<lg type="stanza"><l>
"O, dey call me Hangman Johnny!</l><l>
    O, ho!  O, ho!</l><l>
 But we'll all hang togedder,</l><l>
    O, hang, boys, hang!"</l></lg>

<p>My presence apparently checked the performance of another
verse, beginning, "De buckra 'list for money," apparently in
reference to the controversy about the pay-question, then just
beginning, and to the more mercenary aims they attributed to the
white soldiers.  But "Hangman Johnny" remained always a myth as
inscrutable as "Becky Martin."</p>
<p>As they learned all their songs by ear, they often strayed
into wholly new versions, which sometimes became popular, and
entirely banished the others.  This was amusingly the case, for
instance, with one phrase in the popular camp-song of "Marching
Along," which was entirely new to them until our quartermaster
taught it to them, at my request.  The words, "Gird on the armor,"
were to them a stumbling-block, and no wonder, until some ingenious
ear substituted, "Guide on de army," which was at once accepted,
and became universal.</p>

<p>
"We'll guide on de army, and be marching along."
is now the established version on the Sea Islands.</p>
<p>These quaint religious songs were to the men more than a
source of relaxation; they were a stimulus to courage and a tie to
heaven.  I never overheard in camp a profane or vulgar song.  With
the trifling exceptions given, all had a religious motive, while
the most secular melody could not have been more exciting.  A few
youths from Savannah, who were comparatively men of the world, had
learned some of the "Ethiopian Minstrel" ditties, imported from the
North.  These took no hold upon the mass; and, on the other hand,
they sang reluctantly, even on Sunday, the long and short metres of
the hymnbooks, always gladly yielding to the more potent excitement
of their own "spirituals."  By these they could sing themselves, as
had their fathers before them, out of the contemplation of <pb n="694"/>
their own low estate, into the sublime scenery of the Apocalypse.
I remember that this minor-keyed pathos used to seem to me almost
too sad to dwell upon, while slavery seemed destined to last for
generations; but now that their patience has had its perfect work,
history cannot afford to lose this portion of its record.  There is
no parallel instance of an oppressed race thus sustained by the
religious sentiment alone.  These songs are but the vocal
expression of the simplicity of their faith and the sublimity of
their long resignation.</p>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
