<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HinIntr"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="HinIntr">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Introduction to The Innocents Abroad, a Book of Travel in Pursuit of Pleasure: The Voyage Out</title>
<title type="sort">introduction to the innocents abroad, a book of travel in pursuit of pleasure the voyage out</title>
<author>Hingston, Edward P.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Stephen Railton</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">15</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HinIntr</idno>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476081</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Introduction</title>
<title level="m">The Innocents Abroad, a Book of Travel in Pursuit of Pleasure: The Voyage Out</title>
<title type="sort">introduction</title>
<author>Edward P. Hingston</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>This was a pirated edition of Mark Twain's Innocents Abroad</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>John Camden Hotten</publisher>
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
<date value="1870">1870</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVA Library call number PS1312 .A1 1870b</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1870">1870</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; non-fiction</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-06">June 1997</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Carol Osborne</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<front id="d2">
<div1 type="note" id="d3">
<p><hi rend="italic">The London publisher John Camden Hotten brought out a
pirated version of</hi> Innocents Abroad <hi rend="italic"> in 1870 in two
volumes, each with an elaborate title.  The first was called</hi> The
Innocents Abroad, A Book of Travel in Pursuit of Pleasure: The Voyage
Out <hi rend="italic">; the second,</hi> The New Pilgrim's Progress, A Book of
Travel in Pursuit of Pleasure: The Journey Home <hi rend="italic">.  The first
volume included the following Introduction, written by Edward P.
Hingston, an Englishman who met MT while touring the West as agent
for Artemus Ward.  There are a number of biographical errors
in it.</hi></p>
</div1>
</front>

<body id="d4">
<div1 type="article" id="d5"><head>Hingston's Introduction to British Innocents
</head>

<p>"I<lb/>
	<hi rend="small-caps">MIGHT</hi><lb/>
come to grief?"</p>

<p>"You might."</p>

<p>"Roll over a precipice perhaps, and break my neck?"</p>

<p>"Well; that's so.  Your temper might be tried in that way.  The
roads over the Sierra are pretty rough just now, and we are likely to
have ugly weather."</p>

<p>"Then, I think the game is hardly worth the candle, my friend.
No riding over the mountains alone for me.  Besides, what would there
be to see when I got to Nevada?"</p>

<p>"You would see the big silver mines."</p>

<p>"I have seen the Mexican ones.  They were large enough for me.
Is there anything else to repay me for the journey?"</p>

<p>"Yes.  You would see <hi rend="italic">Mark Twain</hi>."</p>

<p>"Ah!  I will go."</p>

<p>The foregoing is, as nearly as I can remember, an abstract of a
conversation with a literary friend in San Francisco, towards the close of
the year 1863.  I knew that in a few months I should have to visit
Nevada on business.  Why not avail myself of a leisure week and ride
over the Sierra to see the wonders of the new territory?  A mountain
summit 6000 feet high, snow, slippery paths, and very rough roads were
the hindrances.  I had read many of Mark Twain's
contributions to the press of the Great West.  I had heard numerous
reports of his telents, his jovial wit, his social singularities, and his
extreme good fellowship.  In one of the papers I had seen him styled &mdash;
"That moral phenomenon, Mark Twain."  Believing that a "moral
phenomenon" would be something to see, and that the conversation of a
man who could write so humorously would be worth listening to, I
started for Nevada.</p>

<p>At the town of Placerville I came to a halt.  My horse &mdash; a
borrowed one &mdash; did not at all care about seeing Mark Twain.  He
preferred to see a veterinary doctor.  The people of Placerville told me
that I had better make the journey in the stage-coach.  I did so; but not
till nearly two months later, when the roads were in better condition.
Then it was that I landed myself in Virginia City, a terraced town, built
on the side of Mount Davidson; and there it was that I met Mark
Twain.</p>

<p>"You will find him at the office of the <hi rend="italic">Territorial
Enterprise</hi>," was the direction I received.</p>

<p>Virginia City was but a few months old.  The <hi rend="italic">Territorial
Enterprise</hi> was a daily paper, well edited, copious in its
information, fortunate in its advertisements, of large dimensions, and
published every morning, where a year or two previous, there had been
the silence of the wilderness and the tents of the Indian savage.</p>

<p>The newspaper office was in C Street.  Its foundations were of
granite, its front of iron.  In its basement was a saloon for drink,
furnished with a piano, the use of which I was informed was "to tone
down the troubled spirits of the visitors."  Behind the drinking saloon
were two of Hoe's cylinder steam-printing presses.  On the first floor of
the building were the offices of mining share-brokers, and a wholesale
brandy store.  On the second story were some more brokers and some
attorneys, and on the third floor were the editorial offices of the paper.
I asked for Mr. Mark Twain, and hearing his name mentioned, the
gentleman of whom I was in quest called out to Mr. Wright, to whom I
had addressed myself&mdash;</p>

<p>"Dan, pass the gentleman into my den.  The noble animal is
here."</p>

<p>A young man, strongly built, ruddy in complexion, his hair of a
sunny hue, his eyes light and twinkling, in manner hearty, and nothing
of the student about him, but very much of the miner &mdash; one who looked
as if he could take his own part in a quarrel, strike a smart blow as
readily as he could say a telling thing, bluffly jolly, brusquely cordial,
off-handedly good-natured &mdash; such was the kind of man I found Mark
Twain to be.</p>

<p>Let it be borne in mind that from the windows of the newspaper
office the American desert was visible; that within a radius of ten miles
Indians were encamping amongst the sage-brush; that the whole city was
populated with miners, adventurers, Jew traders, gamblers, and all the
rough-and-tumble class which a mining town in a new territory collects
together, and it will be readily understood that a reporter for a daily
paper in such a place must neither go about his duties wearing light kid
gloves, nor be fastidious about having gilt edges to his note-books.  In
Mark Twain I found the very man I had expected to see &mdash; a flower of
the wilderness, tinged with the colour of the soil, the man of thought and
the man of action rolled into one, humorist and hard-worker, Momus in
a felt hat and jack-boots.  In the reporter of the <hi rend="italic">Territorial
Enterprise</hi> I became introduced to a Californian celebrity, rich in
eccentricities of thought, lively in fancy, quaint in remark, whose
residence upon the fringre of civilization had allowed his humour to
develop without restraint, and his speech to be racily idiomatic.</p>

<p>The name of M<hi rend="small-caps">ARK</hi> T<hi
rend="small-caps">WAIN</hi> is a <hi rend="italic">nom de
plume</hi> for Mr. Samuel L.
Clemens; whose father, Mr. Orion Clemens, held a high position in the
territorial government of Nevada.  Before visiting that territory Mark
Twain had afforded evidence of his literary ability on the Californian
side of the Sierra.  At the time of my introduction to him his talents had
scarcely rendered his name familiar to the public of Boston or New
York, and his expressed to Artemus Ward and myself a very earnest
desire to be better known in one of other of those cities.  Artemus
promised to get him appointed a contributor to the <hi rend="italic">New York
Mercury</hi>, a promise that I believe was faithfully kept.</p>

<p>Writing of himself and his friend Dan de Quille, his
<hi rend="italic">collaborateur</hi> on the Nevada paper in 1863, Mark Twain
says, in an advertisement of the <hi rend="italic">Territorial Enterprise</hi> &mdash;
"Our duty is to keep the universe thoroughly posted concerning murders
and street fights and balls and threatres, and pack-trains, and churches,
and lectures, and school-houses, and city military affairs, and highway
robberies, and Bible societies, and hay waggons, and the thousand other
things which it is within the province of local reporters to keep track of
and magnify into undue importance for the instruction of the readers of a
great daily newspaper.  Beyond this revelation everything connected with
these two experiments of Providence must for ever remain an
impenetrable mystery."</p>

<p>With the rapid development of a literature of its own, California
offered Mark Twain increased scope for his talents.  A series of
remarkably original articles, abounding in drollery and grotesque
humour, were contributed by him to various journals of San Francisco,
among which were the <hi rend="italic">Golden Era</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Californian</hi>,
and <hi rend="italic">Overland Monthly</hi>, and he soon became transferred from
the rough life of Nevada to undertake editorial duties in San Francisco.
The tale of "The Jumping Frog," a capitally told and richly conceived
humorous story of the California gold-mines, gave its author an
immediate and widespread popularity.  "The Jumping Frog" has been
republished everywhere, and is as well known to the readers of Australia
as it is to the literary public of London and New York.  It has been
highly praised by Mr. Tom Hood in the pages of <hi rend="italic">Fun</hi>, and a
friend of mine had it put into his hands by a Parsee merchant in
Bombay, who assured him that it was the funniest thing he could
read.</p>

<p>In the spring of 1867 an extraordinary pleasure-trip was projected
at New York.  A steamer was to leave that port in the summer, cross the
Atlantic, make the circuit of the Mediterranean, stop at the principal
places along the coast of Spain, Italy, Turkey, Greece, Egypt, and Syria;
the passengers were to visit Rome, Cairo, Jerusalem, and everywhere
else besides, see all places of interest, visit all historical sites, be back in
New York in time to attend to their winter duties, and all for the sum of
1250 dollars in American currency, or less than 200<hi rend="italic">l</hi>.
English.  The celebrated Rev. Ward Beecher was to have formed one of
the party, but did not carry out his intention.  Mark Twain went instead.
To the young humorist, fresh from the rough life of the Far West, the
Eastern world was full of the most attractive charms.  It would be
something to see how far Rome was like Sacramento, and whether there
was any resemblance between Cairo and San Francisco.  Besides, any
habits of the people at Naples and at Jerusalem were likely to be slightly
dissimilar to those of a camp of miners among the mountains of
Nevada.</p>

<p>The incidents of this famous excursion, and the results arrived at,
are detailed by Mark Twain in the two volumes now published.  The
first volume, entitled "The Innocents Abroad," gives the details of the
trip from New York as far as Naples; while the second volume, under
the title of the "New Pilgrim's Progress," furnishes an account of all that
the excursionists experienced in the Holy Land, and among the classic
localities of the Grecian and Syrian shores.</p>

<p>A most aptly chosen title is that of "The Innocents Abroad," so far
as Mark Twain is concerned.  He visited Europe and Asia without any of
the preparations for travel which most travellers undertake.  His object
was to see things as they are, and record the impressions they produced
on a man of hjmourous perception, who paid his first visit to Europe
without a travelling-tutor, a university education, or a stock of
conventional sentimentality packed in his carpet-bag.  Throughout the
trip he looked at all objects as an untravelled American might be
expected to look, and measured men and manners by the gauge he had
set up for himself among the gold-hills of California and the silver-mines
of half-civilized Nevada.</p>

<p>I believe that Mark Twain has never visited England.  Some time
since he wrote to me asking my opinion relative to his giving an
entertainment in London.  He has appeared in New York, and elsewhere
as a lecturer, and from his originality would, I have no doubt, be able to
repeat his lectures with success were he to visit this country.  But I never
met him in the character of a public entertainer, and can only speak from
experience of his remarkable talent as a humorous writer, and of his
cordial frankness and jovial good-fellowship as a friend and
companion.</p>
<p><lb/></p>
<p>E<hi rend="small-caps">DWARD</hi> P. H<hi
rend="small-caps">INGSTON.</hi></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

