<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HorRuss"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="HorRuss">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Russia's Tramp Novelist</title>
<title type="sort">russias tramp novelist</title>
<author>Hornblow, Arthur</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">14</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HorRuss</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476087</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Russia's Tramp Novelist</title>
<title level="j">The Bookman Magazine, Vol 13 No. 1</title>
<title type="sort">russias tramp novelist</title>
<author>Arthur Hornblow</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Dodd Mead &amp; Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1901-03">March, 1901</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: University of Virginia Alderman Library Call number AP 2 .78</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1901">1901</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-10">October 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Tom Lukas</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Checked against print source. Added tei conformant tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="statement" id="d3">
<head>RUSSIA'S TRAMP NOVELIST</head>
<pb n="51"/>
<p>A brief despatch from St. Petersburg recently announced that
Gorki, the celebrated tramp novelist, had destroyed the last chapters
of his new work, <hi rend="italic">The Moujiks</hi>, on which he has been
engaged, and that it is believed he has gone back to his old life of
vagrancy.
</p><p>Maximilian Gorki is a curious literary phenomenon, who
appeared in the Russian world of letters about seven years ago.  A
common tramp by profession and instincts, Gorki suddenly came
forward as the author of books which, for their human interest and
power of character drawing, have not been equalled by any Russian
writer since the first romances of Tolstoy.  The critics, while
marvelling at the prodigy, acknowledged the absolute freshness and
novelty of the writer's work, which has met with tremendous
popular success, and has to a certain extent revolutionised Russian
literature.
</p><p>According to Ivan Strannik, who introduces his remarkable
compatriot to foreign readers in a long article in the <hi rend="italic">Revue de
Paris</hi>, Gorki was born of very humble parents in Nizhni-Novgorod, a government of middle Russia, in 1868 or 1869&mdash;Gorki
himself is not quite sure which&mdash;and became an orphan when still a
child.  He was apprenticed to a shoe-maker, but, disliking the
sedentary life, he ran away.  He likewise deserted from an
engraver's office, after which he entered the studio of a painter of
religious pictures.  Next he was a scullery boy and then assistant to
a gardener.  He tried all these modes of life, and was content with
none of them.  When he was fifteen he could barely read, although
his grandfather took some pains to make him spell out words from
an old family Bible.  These early studies, however, only filled him
with disgust for learning until the day when, assistant cook on board
a steamboat, he was initiated by the chief cook into the joys of
French romance, which fired his imagination and filled him with a
ferocious desire to educate himself.
</p><p>He went to Kazan and tried to obtain free tuition in one of the
schools, but this he found impossible.  Disillusionised, he took a
situation as baker's by at the wages of three roubles a month, but
soon tiring of this and longing for the fresh air of the open country,
he deserted the bakery and became a common country tramp,
fraternising with every ragged vagrant he met on the road, but
always reading and neglecting no opportunity to educate himself.  A
few months later he was back in the city, acting as watchman, and
afterward he peddled kvass, a kind of sour beverage, in the streets.
Then came the opportunity that was to give him his first foothold in
the path of literature.  Chance brought him into relations with an
advocate, who took interest in him and helped him in his education.
Then, just as this new life seemed to be developing his genius, his
natural restlessness again asserted itself and once more led him to
resume his nomadic existence.  He tramped all over Russia on foot,
exercising every possible calling to eke out an existence, including
henceforth that of a man of letters.
</p><p>He made his literary <hi rend="italic">d&eacute;but</hi> with a short story
called "Makar Tchoudra," which was published in a country paper.
The story was more remarkable for what it promised for the future
than for what it gave, the style being as yet unformed and smacking
somewhat of the romantic school.  The scene is laid in a gypsy
camp, and the characters at times lack naturalness.  Nevertheless, in
this narrative can be seen already Gorki's most marked
characteristics&mdash;his passion for outdoor life and his inordinate love
of music and nature.
</p><p>Gorki's real <hi rend="italic">d&eacute;but</hi> dates from 1893.  He made
about that time the acquaintance of Korolenko, the writer, and with
his assistance published another story, entitled <hi rend="italic">Tchelkache</hi>,
the success of which was tremendous.  From then on Gorki threw
aside every convention and strove to give frank and direct
expression to his own views of life.  As until then his life had been
spent in the company of vagrants and he was himself a vagrant, he
decided to devote his Muse to singing the "Song of the Tramp."
</p><p>His favourite form is the short story.  During the last seven
years he has written thirty, which by their expressive brevity
sometimes recall the methods of Guy de Maupassant.  The plan of
these stories is extremely simple.  Often there are not more than two
characters&mdash;<pb n="52"/> an old beggar and his grandson, or a couple of
workmen, or a tramp and a Jew, two companions in misery.  The
interest of these stories is not in the development of a complicated
plot.  They are rather fragments of life or bits of biography from one
date to another.  Here is the plot of one story:
</p><p>A young peasant leaves his village to find work.  In a seaport
town he meets a ne'er-do-well, who persuades him to commit a
crime.  This entails a mysterious night expedition, which has for its
object the robbing of one of the vessels in the harbour.  The two
men have to run the gauntlet of the coast guards during the terrors
of night-time.  After escaping a thousand dangers the booty is
secured and is soon transformed into gold.  So much wealth dazzles
the peasant.  Pictures of an idle, luxurious life surge through his
obscure mind and disturb and tempt him.  Dissatisfied at the share
his comrade gives him, the peasant attempts to assassinate him and
steals his purse.  Then, tormented by remorse and fearing that the
bloodshed and robbery may bring him bad luck, he returns to the
man whom he has almost killed and, humbling himself, offers to
return the stolen money.  But the wounded man despises him,
throws the coveted money in his face and, as a supreme insult, ends
by forgiving him.
</p><p>The plot is made entirely subsidiary to the character drawing.
The style, despite its imperfections, is marvellously well adapted to
the subject, being vigorous and facile and varying according to the
needs of the story, now expressing all the abruptness and coarseness
necessary; at other times coloured and poetic, until it reaches almost
lyric heights.  Gorki is very uneven, according to his moods, and he
delights in fantastic pictures.  His work lacks premeditation, each
chapter representing his mood at the moment of penning it.
</p><p>All that Gorki relates he has seen.  All the scenes on land and
sea that he describes, says M. Strannik, he has observed during the
course of his adventurous career.  Each detail of his <hi rend="italic">mise-en-sc&egrave;ne</hi> recalls to him some bitter or happy memory.  The
life of the vagrant he depicts has been his own life.  The tramps
have been his comrades.  He has loved them or hated them.  This
explains the striking fidelity of his characters to life.  He does not
idealise the tramp; the sympathy he has for their courage and love
of liberty does not blind him.  He does not seek to conceal their
faults or condone their vices.  He paints the reality, but without
exaggerating its ugliness.  He does not avoid painful or coarse
scenes, but even in his most realistic passages he never shocks the
reader, because one feels that he is striving only to present the truth
as it is, and is not seeking to create a sensation by cheap methods.
He merely states things as they are and insists that they cannot be
changed, as they depend on immutable laws.  Gorki sees in his
characters only the spectacle of life.  He sees passion convulse them
as the wind raises the crests of the waves, and laughter pass over
their souls as the sunlight pierces the cloud.  He is, in the best
acceptation of the word, a realist.
</p><p>The introduction of the tramp into Russian literature is Gorki's
great innovation.  The earlier Russian writers were first interested in
the cultured classes; later they went as low in the social scale as the
<hi rend="italic">moujik</hi>.  The literature of the peasant, in fact, assumed great
importance.  It also had political significance and had much to do
with the emancipation of the serfs.  Yet a large class remained in the
shadow&mdash;that big army of vagrants, obeying no laws, common to all
countries, but larger, perhaps, in Russia than elsewhere.  The
Russian tramp, like his American brother, is recruited from all
classes of society, and one finds among them, in spite of the
complete bankruptcy of their past, picturesque signs of their origin,
that remain with them to the time when they finally disappear into
unknown graves.  Old soldiers, former students, printers, nobles,
schoolmasters, peasants, each has retained some distinctive mark of
his profession.  Among his tramps Gorki represents as being
particularly debased and devoid of all moral sentiment those
vagrants that once belonged to a higher social class.  He argues that
they have not become tramps in obedience to an instinct of liberty,
but rather owing to their idleness and cowardice, which rendered
them incapable of leading a well-conducted life.  Gorki despises
this kind of vagrant, and he never misses an opportunity in his
stories to disassociate them from nature's true vagabonds. <pb n="53"/>
</p><p>Although, for the most part, the tramps in Russia are recruited
among the peasants, there is between these two classes much
opposition and open hostility.  The tramp despises the peasant who
lives miserably on the little he has got.  The peasants, on the
contrary, abominate the tramp, because they fear him and perhaps
also because he tempts them to adopt their own idle, irresponsible
kind of existence.  But the hand-to-mouth life of the tramp, with its
lack of principles and domicile, offends the conservative instincts of
the true peasant.  If some of them join the army of tramps, it is
because in some districts the soil does not produce enough to
support the population.
</p><p>The success of Gorki has been tremendous; so great, in fact,
that it may have had the pernicious effect of checking his genius.
Almost as soon as he realised that he had received a place in
literature Gorki tried to take up other subjects.  But although
familiar with the life of the tramp, he was entirely out of his
element when portraying society people, and the few stories he has
written dealing with the upper classes are commonplace and did not
add to his reputation.
</p><p>His sudden disappearance from St. Petersburg is taken to mean
that once more that restlessness of soul and longing for the
unfettered life of the fields that has been with him all his life has
again seized him.  His friends say that he will reappear as suddenly
as he went away, bringing with him more material to add to the
store of human documents that have already made him famous.</p>
	
	<closer><hi rend="italic">Arthur Hornblow.</hi></closer>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

