<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HutPool"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-tech.ent"> %ISOtech;

]>
<TEI.2 id="HutPool">
	<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">THE WITCHCRAFT DELUSION OF 1692</title>
<title type="sort">witchcraft delusion of 1692</title>
<author>Gov. Thomas Hutchinson</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Commentator</resp>
					<name>William Frederick Poole. communicated with notes</name>
					<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
					<name>Electronic Text Center</name>
					<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
					<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
			<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">171</num> kilobytes</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
				<idno type="ETC">[HutPool]</idno>
				<date value="2001">2001</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 2001 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476589</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">THE WITCHCRAFT DELUSION OF 1692</title>
<title type="parallel">FROM AN UNPUBLISHED MANUSCRIPT (AN EARLY DRAFT OF HIS
							HISTORY OF MASSACHUSETTS) IN THE MASSACHUSETTS ARCHIVES.</title>
<title level="u">New England Historical Genealogical Historical Register,
							Vol. 24, pp. 381-414 (381)October, 1870.</title>
<title type="sort">witchcraft delusion of 1692</title>
<author>Gov. Thomas Hutchinson</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Commentator</resp>
							<name/>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
					<editionStmt>
<p>Microfilm. Ann Arbor, Mich. : University Microfilms. 2 microfilm reels ;
							35 mm. (American periodical series, 1800-1850 ; 1055- 1056</p>
</editionStmt>
					<extent>4 v. : ill. ; 23 cm</extent>
					<publicationStmt>
<publisher>New-England Historic, Genealogical Society,</publisher>
						<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
						<date value="1873" certainty="ca">1870-1873</date>
						<idno type="callNo">Micfilm S-10 reel 1055-1056.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
					</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
					word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
				<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to
					aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
			</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1692">1692</date>
</creation>
			<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
			<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
					<term>drama</term>
					<term>masculine</term>
					<term>Salem</term>
</keywords>
				</textClass>
</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2004-12">December 2004</date>
				<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
					<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
				<item>electronic copy created from the source printed in the New England Historical
					Genealogical Historical Register, Vol. 24, pp. 381-414 (381)October, 1870</item>
</change>
			<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
				<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
					<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
				<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>


	<text id="d1">
		<front id="d2">
			<titlePage id="d3">
				<pb/>

				<docImprint>New England Historical Genealogical Historical Register, Vol. 24, pp.
					381-414 (381)<date value="1870-10">October, 1870.</date></docImprint>

				<docTitle>
					<titlePart type="main">THE WITCHCRAFT DELUSION OF 1692.</titlePart>
				</docTitle>
				<byline>BY<docAuthor>GOV. THOMAS HUTCHINSON.</docAuthor></byline>
				<docTitle>
					<titlePart type="desc">FROM AN UNPUBLISHED MANUSCRIPT (AN EARLY DRAFT OF HIS
						HISTORY OF MASSACHUSETTS) IN THE MASSACHUSETTS ARCHIVES. Communicated, with
						Notes, by WILLIAM FREDERICK POOLE</titlePart>
				</docTitle>
			</titlePage>

		</front>
		<body id="d4">
			<div1 type="section" n="1" id="d5">
				<head>INTRODUCTION.</head>

				<p>IN May last I had occasion to consult the original manuscript of Gov.
					Hutchinson&rsquo;s second volume of the History of Massachusetts, which, it
					is well known, is among the Hutchinson papers in the State archives in Boston. I
					had never before seen the manuscript, and did not readily find the passage of
					which I was in search. The first portion of the manuscript seemed to be missing,
					and its place was supplied by matter which belonged to the Appendix. My first
					inpression &lsqb;sic&rsqb; was that the missing sheets were those which
					Gov. Hutchinson did not recover after the stamp-act riot of 1765. Finding the
					matter of the Appendix out of place, suggested that the volume might have been
					carelessly arranged for binding. On collating the manuscript the early portion
					was found in another part of the volume. This was the copy used by the printers.</p>

				<p>In my search I came to sheets which contained the subject matter of the printed
					text, but expressed in different language. I saw, on a closer examination, that
					this was an earlier draft, and the identical manuscript which had passed the
					ordeal of the riot of 1765; for portions of it were much defaced, and bore the
					marks of being trampled in the mud. The copy from which the volume was printed
					was evidently prepared at a later date. For the convenience of those who may
					hereafter consult this manuscript, I made in folio 7 &lpar;following the
					matter of the Appendix&rpar;, the following memoranda:&mdash;</p>

				<p>&ldquo;There has been an error in binding this manuscript. The matter which
					precedes this is Appendix No. 1 &lpar;printed pp. 449-481, edition 1767, and
					pp. 404-423, edition 1795. The first portion of the history proper, ending with
					manuscript page 28 &lpar;to printed p. 40, edition 1767, and p. 43, edition
					1795&rpar;, has been placed in folios 92-100. Page 29 is opposite. This is
					the manuscript from which the second volume was printed.</p>

				<p>&ldquo;In folio 55 is the beginning of another manuscript, an earlier draft,
					from which the author prepared the narrative which appears in the printed
					volume. The earlier draft, ending in folio 91, carries the substance of the
					narrative to the word &ldquo;Boston,&rdquo; on p. 313, edition of 1767,
					and p. 284, edition of 1795.</p>

				<p>&ldquo;These memoranda were made May 17, 1870 &lpar;with the approval of
					Mr. Secretary Warner&rpar;, at which time the earlier draft was first
					identified.&rdquo; &lsqb;SIGNED.&rsqb;</p>

				<p>Both manuscripts are wholly in the autograph of Gov. Hutchinson, and they seem to
					be prepared with equal care. In form of expression and phraseology they are
					quite unlike. Incidents and opinions contained in the earlier draft are changed,
					abridged and sometimes omitted in the later draft. In matters of fact the
					earlier draft is often more precise and accurate than the printed text, for the
					author doubtless prepared it with the original authorities before him.</p>

				<p>The researches of Gov. Hutchinson into the early annals of Massachusetts are of
					the highest historical value. He had opportunities of access to
					&lpar;382&rpar; original papers such as no person now possesses. He had
					the tastes, the capacity for close application and research, the judicial
					understanding and the freedom from prejudice and partizanship which characterize
					the genuine historian. His style, if not always elegant, is clear and simple,
					and singularly free from that sensational and rhetorical method of statement
					which is the bane of much of the historical writing of the present day.</p>

				<p>Each of the several editions of Gov. Hutchinsons History of Massachusetts has
					become rare, and a new and revised edition will soon be demanded. In the
					preparation of that work the earlier draft of the second volume, which has now
					come to light, will furnish important materials. For the purpose of exhibiting
					the character and value of this manuscript, and for contributing some additional
					information upon a special subject, I have extracted for publication that
					portion which treats the "Witchcraft Delusion of 1692.&rdquo;</p>

				<p>So far as a presentation of facts is concerned, no account of that dreadful
					tragedy has appeared which is more accurate and truthful than Gov.
					Hutchinson&rsquo;s narrative. His theory on the subject&mdash;that it
					was wholly the result of fraud and deception on the part of the
					&ldquo;afflicted children&rdquo;&mdash;will not be generally
					accepted at the present day, and his reasoning on this point will not be deemed
					conclusive. That there were fraud and deception attending it, no one will doubt;
					but there is now a tendency to trace an analogy between the phenomena then
					exhibited, and modern spiritual manifestations. No man of any reputation who
					lived in that generation, and saw what transpired at Salem Village and its
					vicinity, doubted that there was some influence then exerted which could not be
					explained by the known laws of matter or of mind. As these men left the stage,
					the theory of fraud was gradually accepted by their descendants; and at the
					period when Gov. Hutchinson wrote, it was well nigh the universal belief among
					the educated classes.</p>

				<p>For the information of persons interested in tracing the resemblance between the
					abnormal manifestations of our time and those of the seventeenth century, I have
					appended notes to the other cases mentioned by Gov. Hutchinson, which may lead
					such inquirers to a further knowledge of their psychological phenomena.</p>

				<p>The author&rsquo;s notes are indicated by stars, &amp;c., and are signed
					H. The editor&rsquo;s notes are indicated by numerals, and are signed P. W.
					F. P.</p>
			</div1>

			<div1 type="section" n="2" id="d6">
				
				<p>On [mutilated]<ref target="n1">[1]</ref> May, at a general council, there was an
					appointment of sheriffs, justices and other civil officers, and, among the rest,
					Commissioners of Oyer and Terminer for the trial of witches. Upon this occasion
					the Governor suffered the council to choose the officers, and he gave or refused
					his consent to the choice&mdash;a mistake which no other governor has made,
					and which was giving up a right derived to him from the charter, the great
					difference between a nomination and assent being very obvious.</p>

				<p>The old constitution being dissolved, it was absolutely necessary an Assembly
					should be called. What was the rule of law in the meantime might
					&lpar;383&rpar; be made a question; but at the first meeting of the
					General Assembly &lpar;the 8th of June&rpar; an act passed that all the
					laws of the Colony of Massachusetts Day and the Colony of New-Plymouth, not
					being repugnant to the laws of England, nor inconsistent with the charter,
					should be in force to the 10th of November, 1692, in the respective colonies,
					except where other provisions should be made by acts of assembly; and all
					justices of the peace had the same power given them in the execution of laws
					which magistrates used to have. No other acts were passed except two or three
					relative to the revenue; an act for erecting a naval office; another to enable
					the Governor, with the advice of the council, for six months to come, to raise
					and transport, or march the militia into either of the governments of Rhode
					Island, Connecticut, Narragansett or New-York; and another act for establishing
					a court of sessions of the peace, and inferior court of common pleas. The
					assembly was adjourned on the second of July to the second Wednesday in October.</p>

				<p>The confusion occasioned by the supposed witchcraft seems to have been the reason
					why nothing more was done towards a body of laws better adapted to the new
					constitution; for on the 2d of June the commissioners held their special court
					at Salem.</p>

				<p>Before I relate their proceedings, I will collect, as far as I am able, the
					several instances of what was called Witchcraft, from the beginning of the
					country.</p>

				<p>It is natural to suppose that the country, at the first entrance of the Europeans
					into it, afforded the most suitable scene, especially as a notion prevailed that
					the savages all worshipped the Devil; but I find no mention of witchcraft for
					the first twelve or fifteen years. About the year 1645,<ref target="n2"
					>[2]</ref> several people in Springfield, upon Connecticut River, were suspected
					of witchcraft, and a greater number were supposed to be bewitched; among the
					rest two of the minister&rsquo;s children.<ref target="n3"
					>[&sext;]</ref> Great pains were taken to prove the facts upon the suspected
					persons; and about the year 1650, a poor wretch, Mary Oliver<ref target="n4"
					>[3]</ref>, no doubt weary of her life, after long examination, was brought to
					confession. It does not appear that she was executed. </p>

				<p>(384) Whilst this inquiry was making, Margaret Jones<ref target="n5"
					>[&sext;]</ref> was executed at Charlestown.<ref target="n6">[4]</ref>
					Mention is made by Mr. Hale, of a woman at Dorchester,<ref target="n7">[5]</ref>
					&lpar;385&rpar; and another at Cambridge<ref target="n8">[6]</ref> about
					the same time, all denying what they were charged with, at their death; and soon
					after Mrs. Hibbins<ref target="n9">[&sext;]</ref><ref target="n10">[7]</ref>
					the magistrate&rsquo;s widow, was executed at Boston. In 1662, at Hartford,
					about 30 miles below Springfield, upon the same Connecticut River, one Ann Cole,
					whose father is said to have been a godly man who lived next door to a Dutch
					family, was supposed to be possessed by a Demon who sometimes spake Dutch and
					sometimes English, and sometimes an unintelligible language, the demons speaking
					in her things unknown to herself, and holding a conference, &amp;c. Several
					ministers who were present took the conference in writing with the names of the
					persons mentioned as actors; and, among the rest, of a woman in prison upon
					suspicion, &lsqb;one&rsqb; Greensmith. Upon examination she confessed
					also, and appeared to be astonished at the discovery, and owned that she and the
					rest had been familiar with a demon who had carnal knowledge of her, and though
					she had not made a formal covenant with him, yet she had promised always to be
					ready at his call, and was to have had a high frolick at Christmas, and then the
					agreement was to be signed. The woman upon this confession was executed.<ref
						target="n11">[&sext;]</ref><ref target="n12">[8]</ref> Goffe, the
					Regicide, says in his diary, January 20,&rsquo;62, that three witches were
					condemned at Hartford; and afterwards, Feb. 24, that the maids were well after
					one of the witches was hanged. In 1669, Susanna Martin, of Salisbury, was bound
					over to the Superior court upon suspicion of witchcraft, but discharged without
						trial.<ref target="n13">[9]</ref></p>

				<p>Another ventriloqua, Elizabeth Knap,<ref target="n14">[10]</ref> at Groton, in
					1671, much as Ann &lpar;386&rpar; Cole had done at Hartford, alarmed the
					people there. Her demon was not so cunning. He railed at the godly minister of
					the town, and at the same time uttered many blasphemous expressions; and then
					charged all her afflictions upon a good woman in the neighborhood. The woman had
					better fortune than perhaps as good an one had at Salem some years after.<ref
						target="n15">[&sext;]</ref> The people would not believe the Devil, and
					Elizabeth confessed that she had been deluded, and that it was the Devil himself
					who tormented her in the shape of good persons. In 1673, Eunice Cole<ref
						target="n16">[11]</ref>, of Hampton, was tried, and the jury found her not
					legally guilty; but that, and at the same time uttered many blasphemous
					expressions; and then charged all her afflictions upon a good woman in the
					neighborhood. The woman had better fortune than perhaps as good an one had at
					Salem some years after.<ref target="n15">[&sext;]</ref> The people would not
					believe the Devil, and Elizabeth confessed that she had been deluded, and that
					it was the Devil himself who tormented her in the shape of good persons. In
					1673, Eunice Cole<ref target="n16">[11]</ref>, of Hampton, was tried, and the
					jury found her not legally guilty; but that there were strong grounds to suspect
					her of familiarity with the Devil.</p>

				<p>In 1679, the house of William Morse,<ref target="n17">[12]</ref> of Newbury, was
					troubled with throwing bricks, stones and sticks, and playing so many pranks
					that he that believes the story told by Glanvil of the devils at Tedworth cannot
					avoid giving credit to this. It is worth observing that none of the family,
					except one boy, were afflicted. He was tossed about from one side of the room to
					the other, would have knives stuck in his back, and once one of them seemed to
					come out of his mouth. He would bark like a dog, and cluck like a hen, and once
					was carried away and could not be found for some time; but at length was
					discovered creeping on one side, dumb and lame, and, when able to express
					himself said &ldquo;that P&ndash;l<ref target="n18">[13]</ref> had
					carried him over the top of the house, and hurt him against a cart wheel in the
					barn.&rdquo; Morse took the boy to bed with him and his wife, and had the
					chamber pot with its contents thrown upon them, and they were severely pinched
					and pulled out of bed, &amp;c. These things are related very seriously,<ref
						target="n19">[&sext;]</ref> and it is a great wonder that P-l escaped;
					for it does not appear that anybody suspected the knavery of the boy.</p>

				<p>In 1683, the demons removed to Connecticut River again, where the
					&lpar;387&rpar; house of one Desborough <ref target="n20">[14]</ref> was
					molested, and stones, earth, &amp;c. thrown at him, not only through the
					windows, but doors, by an invisible band; and a fire, kindled nobody knew how,
					burnt up no small part of his estate. It seems one of Desborough&rsquo;s
					neighbors had a quarrel with him about a chest of clothes which Desborough
					detained; and, as soon as they were restored, the troubles ceased. All was
					charged upon the demons, and nobody, from anything which now appears, suspected
					the honest neighbor.</p>

				<p>In 1681, the house of George Walton,<ref target="n21">[15]</ref> a Quaker, at
					Portsmouth, in &lpar;388&rpar; New-Hampshire, was attacked in much the
					same manner. Walton had contention with a woman about a tract of land, and she
					was supposed to have done the mischief but by witchcraft.</p>

				<p>About the same time another house was infested at Salmon falls <ref target="n22"
						>[16]</ref> in New-Hampshire. And, in 1684, one Philip Smith,<ref
						target="n23">[17]</ref> a justice of the court, and representative of the
					town of Hadley, on Connecticut River, an hypochondriac person, supposed himself
					to be under an evil-hand; and suspected a woman, one of his neighbors; and,
					continuing in that state until he died, he was generally supposed to be
					bewitched to death.</p>

				<p>In 1685, a large and circumstantial account of all or most of these instances was
						published,<ref target="n24">[18]</ref> and anybody who doubted the truth of
					them would have been pronounced a Sadducee.</p>

				<p>In 1688 <ref target="n25">[19]</ref> begun a more alarming instance than any
					which preceded it. Four of the children of John Goodwin, a grave man and good
					liver at the north part of Boston, were generally believed to be bewitched. I
					have often heard those who were then upon the stage, speak of the great
					consternation it occasioned. The children were all remarkable for an ingenuity
					of temper, had been religiously educated, and were supposed to be incapable of
					imposture or fraud. The eldest was a girl about thirteen years of age, it is
					said, it may be something more. She had charged a laundress with taking away
					sonic of the family linen. The mother of the laundress was one of the wild
					Irish, and gave the girl very bad language; after which she fell into a sort of
					fits, which were said to have something diabolical in them. One of her sisters
					and two of her brothers, whose ages were not transmitted,<ref target="n26"
					>[20]</ref> soon followed her example, and they are said to have been tormented
					in the same parts of their bodies at the same time, though kept at a distance so
					as not to know one another&rsquo;s complaints. One thing was remarkable, and
					ought to have been taken more notice of, that all their complaints were in the
					day time, and that they slept comfortably all night. They were sometimes deaf,
					then dumb, then blind, and sometimes all these together. Their tongues would be
					drawn down their throats, then pulled out upon their chins. Their jaws, necks,
					shoulders, elbows, and all &lpar;389&rpar; their joints would appear to
					be dislocated, and they would make the most piteous outcries of being cut with
					knives and beat; and plain marks of wounds might afterwards be discovered. The
					ministers of Boston and Charlestown kept a day of fasting and prayer at the
					troubled house; and after that the youngest child made no more complaints. But
					the magistrates unfortunately interposed; and the old woman was apprehended,
					examined, committed and brought to trial, and seems neither to have owned nor
					denied her guilt, being either really a distracted person, or endeavoring to
					appear such; and, before sentence of death was passed, the opinion of physicians
					was taken; but they returned that she was compos mentis, and she was executed,
					declaring at her death the children should not, or perhaps it might be, would
					not be relieved by her death, and that others besides her had a hand in their
					afflictions. This no doubt came to the children&rsquo;s knowledge; and their
					complaints immediately increased beyond what they had ever been before. As this
					relation is in print,<ref target="n27">[21]</ref> and but few persons have
					doubted that there was a preternatural agency in the case of these children, and
					[as] Mr. Baxter, in a preface to an edition published in London, says:
					&ldquo;the evidence is so convincing that he must be a very obdurate
					Sadducee who will not believe,&rdquo; I will spend a little more time in
					examining it, than otherwise I should think convenient.</p>

				<p>The eldest is after this the principal subject; and was taken into a
					minister&rsquo;s <ref target="n28">[22]</ref> family, where for some days
					she behaved orderly, but after that suddenly fell into her fits. The relation
					chiefly consists of their being violently beaten by specters; put into red hot
					ovens, and their sweating and panting; having cold water thrown upon them, and
					then shivering; being roasted upon invisible spits; having their heads nailed to
					the floor, so as that they could hardly be pulled away; their joints first stiff
					and then limber; pins stuck into their flesh; choaked until they were black in
					the face; having the witches invisible chain upon them; dancing with a chair,
					like one riding on horseback; being able to read bad books, and blind if they
					looked into a good one; being drunk without anything to intoxicate.</p>

				<p>There is nothing in all this but what may be accounted for from craft and fraud,
					which children of that age are very capable of; or from agility of body, in
					which these children are exceeded by common tumblers much younger. There are
					some instances mentioned of another sort, namely of their being tormented when
					any person took up a bible to look into it &lpar;390&rpar; whilst the
					children were in the room, although their faces were another way, and they could
					not see it until it was laid aside; their telling of plate at the bottom of the
					well, which, it is said, they had never heard of before&mdash; and yet, in
					fact, plate had been lost there; of their eyes being put out when they were told
					to look to God, not only in English, but in Latin, Greek, or Hebrew; whereas
					from the Indian language no such effect followed, the Devil being said not to
					have understood that language <ref target="n29">[23]</ref>&mdash;all which
					serve only to evidence the inattention and the strong prejudice in favor of the
					children in those who were their observers. The strangest circumstance of all is
					that the children, after their return to their ordinary behavior, made
					profession of religion, and reckoned their affliction among the incentives to
					it. One of them was, many years after, one of my tenants, a grave, religious
					woman, [and] was never known to have made any confession of fraud, probably was
					never charged with it. But even all this is not miraculous.<ref target="n30"
						>[24]</ref> The account of this affair being made public obtained general
					credit.</p>

				<p>(391) At Salem was the next scene, and more tragical by far than any which had
					preceded.</p>

				<p>Whilst the tragedy was acting, there were but few people who doubted the hand of
					the Devil, and fewer that dared to own their doubts.</p>

				<p>When the Commissioners went through the town of Boston on their journey to Salem,
					they stopped at the house of Col. Hutchinson,<ref target="n31">[25]</ref> one of
					the council, who advised them, before they began any trial, to see if they could
					not whip the Devil out of the afflicted; but this advice was rejected.</p>

				<p>Many of the ministers of the country, who were much consulted in this affair, had
					a confirmed opinion of a very familiar intercourse between the visible and
					invisible worlds. This, together with the books which had been brought into the
					country not long before, containing relations of the like things in England,
					rendered the minds of the people in general susceptible of credit to every the
					like story related here. The works of Perkins<ref target="n32">[26]</ref> and
					other non-conformist divines were in the hands of many, and there is no doubt
					that Goodwin&rsquo;s children had read or heard the stories in Glanvil,<ref
						target="n33">[27]</ref> (392) having very exactly imitated them. Indeed all
					the examinations at Salem have, in almost all the circumstances, the like to
					match them in the account given to the world a little while before by this
					relator. This conformity, instead of rendering the afflicted suspected, was
					urged in confirmation of the truth of their stories, the Old-England demons and
					the New&ndash;, being so near alike. Nobody thought a parcel of young girls
					could have so much of the Devil in them as to combine together in an attempt to
					take away the lives of such a multitude of people as were accused by them. The
					authorities of Keble,<ref target="n34">[28]</ref> Dalton,<ref target="n35"
					>[29]</ref> and other lawyers of note, who lay down rules of conviction as
					absurd as any ever adopted in New-England, gave a color to the courts and juries
					in their proceedings, though no authority had so great weight as that of Sir
					Matthew Hale,<ref target="n36">[30]</ref> reverenced in the country for his
					gravity and piety, and his favorable opinion of the old Puritanism, as much as
					for his knowledge in the law. The trials of the witches in Suffolk had been
					published not long before.<ref target="n37">[31]</ref> The evidence here was of
					the same sort with what lead been judged sufficient to hang people there.
					Reproach then for hanging witches, although it has been often cast upon the
					people of New-England by those of Old&ndash;, yet it must have been done
					with an ill grace. We had their best authority to justify us; besides the
					prejudices of education [and] disposition from thence to give a serious, solemn
					construction to even common events in Providence, might be urged as an excuse
					here in some measure; but in England this was an age of as great gaiety as any
					age whatever, and of as great infidelity in general as any which preceded it.</p>

				<p>Sir William Phips, the Governor just arrived,<ref target="n38">[32]</ref> seems
					to have given in to the prevailing opinion. He was much under the direction of
					the spiritual fathers of the country. Mr. Stoughton, the Lieut. Governor, and at
					the head of the Court<ref target="n39">[33]</ref> for trial of the witches, and
					who had great influence upon the rest of the judges, had taken up this notion
					that, although the Devil might appear in the shape of a guilty person, yet be
					would never be permitted to assume the shape of an innocent person.<ref
						target="n40">[34]</ref> This opinion, at &lpar;393&rpar; first, was
					generally received and would not bear to be contradicted. Some of the most
					religious women who were accused, when they saw the appearance of distress and
					torture in the girls, and heard their solemn declarations that they saw, the
					shapes or specters of the accused afflicting them, persuaded themselves they
					were witches, and that the Devil, somehow or other, though they could not
					remember when, had taken possession of their evil hearts, and obtained some sort
					of assent to his afflicting in their shapes; and thereupon they confessed
					themselves to be guilty.</p>

				<p>Even to this day, the country seems rather to be divided in opinion whether it
					was the accused or the afflicted who were under some preternatural or diabolical
					possession, than whether the afflicted were under bodily distempers, or
					altogether guilty of fraud and imposture.</p>

				<p>The trial of Richard Hatheway,<ref target="n41">[35]</ref> before Lord Chief
					Justice Holt, opened the eyes of all except the lowest part of the people in
					England; and an act of Parliament in his late Majesty&rsquo;s reign<ref
						target="n42">[36]</ref> will prevent the prejudice which remains in them
					from the mischiefs it used to produce on juries in judicial proceedings. It is a
					great pity the like examples of conviction and punishment had not been made
					here. I hope an impartial narrative of the supposed witchcrafts at Salem will
					convince the New-England reader that there was no thing preternatural in the
					whole affair; but all proceeded from the most amazing wickedness of the
					accusers.</p>

				<p>In February, 1691 &lsqb;-2&rsqb;, a daughter and a niece of Mr.
						Parris,<ref target="n43">[37]</ref> the minister &lpar;394&rpar; of
					Salem village, girls of ten or eleven years of age, and one or two more girls in
					the neighborhood, made the same sort of complaints as Goodwin&rsquo;s
					children had done two or three &lsqb;four&rsqb; years before. The
					physicians, having no other way of accounting for the disorder, pronounced them
					bewitched. An Indian woman who lived with the minister, with her husband,<ref
						target="n44">[38]</ref> tried an experiment to find out the witch. This
					coming to the children&rsquo;s knowledge, they cried out upon the Indian
					woman as appearing to them, pinching, pricking and tormenting them, and fell
					into fits, became convulsed, distorted, &amp;c.</p>

				<p>Tituba, the name of the woman, who was a Spanish Indian, as some accounts tell
					us, owned that her mistress had taught her in her own country how to find out a
					witch ; but she denied her being one herself. Several private fasts were kept at
					the minister&rsquo;s house, and several more by the whole village, and by
					neighboring parishes, and a public fast through the colony to seek to God to
					rebuke Satan, &amp;c. Soon after the number of the complainants increased,
					and among them girls, two or three women, and some old enough to be admitted
					witnesses. These had their fits too, and cried out, not only upon Tituba, but
					upon an old melancholy distracted woman, Sarah Osburn; and a bed-rid old woman,
					Sarah Good. Tituba, urged to it by her master as she afterwards declared,<ref
						target="n45">[&sext;]</ref> confessed herself a witch, and that the two
					old women were confederates with her, and thereupon they were all committed to
					prison; and Tituba being searched was said to have the marks of the
					Devil&rsquo;s wounding her upon her body,<ref target="n46"
					>[&sext;]</ref> but more probably of Spanish cruelty. This was the first of
					March. About three weeks after two other women who were church-members and of
					good character, &lsqb;Martha&rsqb; Corey and &lsqb;Rebecca&rsqb;
					Nurse, were complained of, examined and would confess nothing, but were
					committed. Not only the three children, while the women were under examination,
					fell into their fits and had all their complaints, but the mother of one of the
					children and wife of Thomas Putnam complained of Nurse as tormenting her, and
					made most terrible shrieking to the amazement of all in the neighborhood. Such
					was the infatuation that a child<ref target="n47">[&sext;]</ref> of Sarah
					Good, not above four or five years old, was committed also, being charged with
					biting the afflicted who showed the print of small teeth upon their arms.</p>

				<p>Soon after, April 3, Sarah Cloyse, sister to Nurse, being at meeting, and Mr.
					Parris taking for his text John vi. 70, &ldquo;Have not I
					chosen&rsquo;you twelve, and one of you is a Devil?&rdquo; she was
					offended and went out of meeting, and she was soon after complained of, examined
					and committed; and about the same time Elizabeth Proctor was charged; and, her
					husband accompanying her to her examination, he was complained of also, and both
					&lpar;395&rpar; committed. The great imprudence, to say the best of it,
					in those who were in authority &lsqb;Hathorne and Corwin, local
					magistrates&rsqb;, in encouraging and putting words into the mouths of the
					accusers, or suffering others to do it, will appear by the examination of these
					persons remaining upon the files of the court. The accusers and accused were
					brought before the court. Mr. Parris, who had been over-officious from the
					beginning, was employed to examine these,<ref target="n48">[39]</ref> and most
					of the rest of the accused.</p>

				<p>At a court <ref target="n49">[40]</ref> held at Salem, 11th April, 1692, by the
					honoured Thomas Danforth, deputy governor. Q. John &lpar;i. e. the
					Indian&rpar;, who hurt you? A. Goody Proctor first, and then Goody Cloyse.
					Q. What did she do to you? A. She brought the book to me. Q. John, tell the
					truth, who hurts you? Have you been hurt? A. The first was a gentlewoman I saw.
					Q. Who next? A. Goody Cloyse. Q. But who hurt you next? A. Goody Proctor. Q.
					What did she do to you? A. She choked me, and brought the book. Q. How oft did
					she come to torment you? A. A good many times, she and Goody Cloyse. Q. Do they
					come to you in the night as well as the day? A. They come most in the day. Q.
					Who? A. Goody Cloyse and Goody Proctor. Q. Where did she take hold of you? A.
					Upon my throat, to stop my breath. Q. Do you know Goody Cloyse and Goody
					Proctor? A. Yes, here is Goody Cloyse. &lpar;Cloyse&rpar; When did I
					hurt thee? A. A great many times. &lpar;Cloyse&rpar; Oh, you are a
					grievous liar. Q. What did this Goody Cloyse do to you? A. She pinched and bit
					me till the blood came. Q. How long since s this woman came and hurt you? A.
					Yesterday at meeting. Q. At any time before? A. Yes, a great many times.</p>

				<p>Mary Walcot, who hurts you? A. Goody Cloyse. Q. What did she do to you? A. She
					hurt me. Q. Did she bring the book? A. Yes. Q. What were you to do with it? A.
					To touch it, and I should be well.&mdash; Then she fell into a fit. Q. Doth
					she come alone? A. Sometimes alone, and sometimes in company with Goody Nurse
					and Goody Corey, and a great many I do not know.&mdash;Then she fell into a
					fit again.</p>

				<p>Abigail Williams, did you see a company at Mr. Parris&rsquo;s house eat and
					drink? A. Yes Sir, that was their sacrament. Q. How many were there? A. About
					forty, and Goody Cloyse and Goody Good were their deacons. Q. What was it? A.
					They said it was our blood, and they had it twice that day. Q. Mary Walcot, have
					you seen a white man? A. Yes Sir, a great many times. Q. What sort of a man was
					he? A. A fine grave man, and when he came, he made all the witches to tremble.
					Abigail &lpar;396&rpar; Williams confirmed the same, and that they had
					such a sight at Deacon Ingersoll&rsquo;s Q. Who was at Deacon
					Ingersoll&rsquo;s then? A. Goody Cloyse, Goody Nurse, Goody Corey, and Goody
					Good.</p>

				<p>Then Sarah Cloyse asked for water, and sat down as one seized with a dying
					fainting fit; and several of the afflicted fell into fits, and some of them
					cried out, Oh! her spirit is gone to prison to her sister Nurse.</p>

				<p>Elizabeth Proctor, you understand whereof you are charged, viz. to be guilty of
					sundry acts of witchcraft; what say you to it? Speak the truth. And so you that
					are afflicted, you must speak the truth, as you will answer it before God
					another day.</p>

				<p>Mary Walcot, doth this woman hurt you? A. I never saw her so as to be hurt by
					her. Q. Mary Lewis, does she hurt you?&mdash;Her mouth was stopped. Q. Ann
					Putnam, does she hurt you?&mdash;She could not speak. Q. Abigail Williams,
					does site hurt you?&mdash;Her hand was thrust in her own mouth. Q. John
					&lpar;Indian&rpar;, does this woman hurt you? A. This is the woman that
					came in her shift and choked me. Q. Did she ever bring the book? A. Yes Sir. Q.
					What to do? A. To write. Q. What, this woman? A. Yes Sir. Q. Are you sure of it?
					A. Yes Sir.</p>

				<p>Again, Abigail Williams and Ann Putnam were spoke to by the court, but neither of
					them could make any answer, by reason of dumbness or other fits.</p>

				<p>What do you say, Goody Proctor, to these things? A. I take God in heaven to be my
					witness, that I know nothing of it, no more than the child unborn. Q. Ann
					Putnam, doth this woman hurt you? A. Yes Sir, a great many times.</p>

				<p>Then the accused looked upon them and they fell into fits. Q. She does not bring
					the book to you, does she? A. Yes Sir, often, and saith she hath made her maid
					to set her hand to it. Q. Abigail Williams, does this woman hurt you? A. Yes
					Sir, often. Q. Does she bring the book to you? A. Yes. Q. What would she have
					you do with it? A. To write in it and I shall be well. Did not you, said
					Abigail, tell me, that your maid <ref target="n50">[41]</ref> had written?
					&lpar;Proctor&rpar; Dear child, it is not so. There is another judgment,
					dear child. Then Abigail and Ann had fits. By-and-by they cried out, Look you,
					there is Goody Proctor upon the beam. By-and-by both of them cried out of
					Goodman Proctor himself, and said he was a wizard. Immediately many, if not all
					of the bewitched had grievous fits.</p>

				<p>Ann Putman, who hurt these? A. Goodman Proctor and his wife too. Afterwards, some
					of the afflicted cried: There is Proctor going to take up Mrs. Pope&rsquo;s
					feet; and her feet were immediately taken up. Q. What do you say, Goodman
					Proctor, to these things? A. I know not. I am innocent. Abigail Williams cried
					out, There is Goodman Proctor going to Mrs. Pope, and immediately said Pope fell
					into a fit. You see the Devil will deceive you; the children could see what you
					was going to do before the woman was hurt. I would advise you to repentance, for
					the Devil is about bringing you out.</p>

				<p>Abigail Williams cried out again, There is Goodman Proctor going to hurt Goody
					Bibber; and immediately Goody Bibber fell into a fit. There was the like of Mary
					Walcot, and divers others.</p>

				<p>Benjamin Gould gave in his testimony, that he had seen Goodman Corey and his
					wife, Proctor and his wife, Goody Cloyse, Goody Nurse, and Goody
					&lpar;397&rpar; Griggs in his chamber last Thursday night. Elizabeth
					Hubbard was in a trance during the whole examination. During the examination of
					Elizabeth Proctor, Abigail Williams and Ann Putnam both made offer to strike at
					said Proctor; but when Abigail&rsquo;s hand came near, it opened, whereas it
					was made up into a fist before, and came down exceeding lightly as it drew near
					to said Proctor, and at length with open and extended fingers touched
					Proctor&rsquo;s hood very lightly. Immediately Abigail cried out, her
					fingers, her fingers, her fingers burned, and Ann Putnam took on most grievously
					of her head, and sunk down.<ref target="n51">[42]</ref></p>

				<p>Salem, April 11th, 1692. Mr. Samuel Parris was desired by the honourable Thomas
					Danforth, deputy governor, and the council, to take in writing the aforesaid
					examinations, and accordingly took and delivered them in; and upon hearing the
					same, and seeing what was then seen, together with the charge of the afflicted
					persons, were by the advice of the Council all committed by us. <name
						type="transcriber">John Hathorne, Jonathan Corwin, Assistants.</name></p>

				<p>Facts often appear in their true light in after ages which had been seen in a
					false one by such as were upon the stage in the time of them. A strong bias is
					now evidently seen in favor of the accusers, and no measures were taken to
					discover the fraud. The same prejudice will appear through the whole process.</p>

				<p>John the Indian, one of these accusers, was husband to Tituba the first witch
					complained of. She confessed and was committed to prison. Her husband, no doubt,
					was convinced he should stand a better chance among the afflicted than the
					accused. It is most probable some of the women acted from the same principle. As
					the afflicted increased, so did the accused, of course. Great pains were taken
					to bring, some of them to confess; but in general the accused persisted in their
					innocency until the prisons were filled. At length the friends of some of the
					accused urged them to a confession, although they knew they were innocent, the
					magistrates declaring that confessing was the way to obtain mercy. The first
					confession, which remains upon the files, is of Deliverance Hobbs, May 11th,
					1692, being in prison. She owned everything she was required to do. The
					confessors, like the accusers, multiplied, the witches having always company
					with them, who were immediately sent for and examined. No wonder if they were
					affrighted to the last degree; they owned whatever their friends and magistrates
					would have them. Thus more than an hundred women, many of them of the most
					sober, virtuous livers, some of them of very reputable families in the towns
					&lpar;398&rpar; of Salem, Beverly, Andover, Billerica, Newbury, were
					apprehended and examined, and generally committed, although most of them who
					confessed, after three or four months imprisonment, were admitted to bail. These
					confessions were all very much of the same tenor. One of them may serve as a
					specimen.</p>

				<p>8th Sept. &rsquo;92. The examination and confession of Diary Osgood, wife of
					Capt. Osgood, of Andover, taken before John Hathorne, Esq. and other their
					Majesty&rsquo;s justices.</p>

				<p>She confesses, that about eleven years ago, when she was in a melancholy state
					and condition, she used to walk abroad in her orchard, and, upon a certain time,
					she saw the appearance of a cat at the end of the house, which yet she thought
					was a real cat. However, at that time it diverted her from praying to God, and
					instead thereof she prayed to the Devil; about which time she made a covenant
					with the Devil, who, as a black man, came to her and presented her a book, upon
					which site laid her finger and that left a red spot. And that upon her signing
					her book the devil told her he was her god, and that she should serve and
					worship him, and believes she consented to it. She says further, that about two
					years agone, she was carried through the air, in company with Deacon
					Frye&rsquo;s wife, Ebenezer Baker&rsquo;s wife, and Goody Tyler, to
					five-mile pond, where she was baptized by the Devil, who dipped her face in the
					water, and made her renounce her former baptism, and told her that she must be
					his, soul and body, forever, and that she must serve him, which she promised to
					do. She says, the renouncing her first baptism was after her dipping, and that
					she was transported back again through the air, in company with the fore-named
					persons, in the same manner as she went, and believes they were carried upon a
					pole. Q. How many persons were upon the pole? A. As I said before, viz. four
					persons and no more but whom she had named above. She confesses she has
					afflicted three persons, viz. John Sawdy, Martha Sprague and Rose Foster, and
					that she did it by pinching her bed clothes, and giving consent the Devil should
					do it in her shape, and that the Devil could not do it without her consent. She
					confesses the afflicting persons in the court, by the glance of her eye. She
					says, as she was coming down to Salem to be examined, she and the rest of the
					company with her stopped at Mr. Phillips&rsquo;s to refresh themselves; and
					the afflicted persons, being behind them upon the road, came up just as she was
					mounting again, and were then afflicted, and cried out upon her, so that she was
					forced to stay until they were all passed; and said she only looked that way
					towards them.</p>

				<p>Do you know the devil can <ref target="n52" type="ed">[&sext;]</ref> take the
					shape of an innocent person and afflict? A. I believe he cannot? Q. Who taught
					you this way of witchcraft? A. Satan, and that he promised her abundance of
					satisfaction and quietness in her future state, but never performed any thing;
					and that she has lived more miserably and more discontented since than ever
					before. She confesses further, that she herself, in company with Goody Parker,
					Goody Tyler and Goody Dean, had a meeting at Moses Tyler&rsquo;s house, last
					Monday night, to afflict, and that she and goody Dean carried the shape of Mr.
					Dean, the minister, between them, to make persons believe that Mr. Dean
					afflicted. Q. What hindered you from accomplishing what you intended? A. The
					Lord would not suffer it so to be, that the devil should afflict in an innocent
					person&rsquo;s shape. Q. Have you been at any other witch meeting? A. I know
					nothing thereof, as I shall answer in the presence of &lpar;399&rpar;
					God and his people; but said that the black man stood before her, and told her,
					that what she had confessed was a lie; notwithstanding, she said that what she
					had confessed was true, and thereto put her hand. Her husband being present was
					asked, if he judged his wife to be any way discomposed. He answered, that having
					lived with her so long, he doth not judge her to be any wise discomposed, but
					has cause to believe that what she has said is true.</p>

				<p>When Mistress Osgood was first called, she afflicted Martha Sprague and Rose
					Foster by the glance of her eyes, and recovered them out of their fits by the
					touch of her hand. Mary Lacey and Betty Johnson and Han nah Post saw Mistress
					Osgood afflicting Sprague and Foster. The said Hannah Post and Mary Lacey and
					Betty Johnson, jun. and Rose Foster and Mary Richardson were afflicted by
					Mistress Osgood, in the time of her examination, and recovered by her touching
					of their hands.</p>

				<p>&ldquo;I underwritten, being appointed by authority to take this examination,
					do testify upon oath, taken in court, that this is a true copy of the substance
					of it, to the best of my knowledge, 5th Jan. 1692-3. The within Mary Osgood was
					examined before their Majesties&rsquo; justices of peace in Salem. Attest
					John Higginson, Just. Peace.&rdquo;</p>

				<p>Owned before the Grand Jury 5 Jan. 1692-3. Robert Payne, Foreman.&rdquo; </p>

				<p>Mr. Hale, who had the character of an impartial relator, acknowledges that the
					confessors generally went off from their confessions; some saying
					&ldquo;they remembered nothing of what they had said,&rdquo; others said
					&ldquo;they had belied themselves,&rdquo; and yet he thinks, if the
					times had been calm, the condition of the confessors might have called for a
					melius inquirendum; and seems to think remarkable daughters and granddaughters
					confirming their mother&rsquo;s and grandmothers&rsquo; confession, and
					instances in the case of Goody Foster, her daughter Mary Lacey, and
					granddaughter Mary Lacey, jun. Their confessions happen to be preserved, and a
					few extracts from them will show there was no need of further inquiries.<ref
						target="n53" type="ed">[&sext;]</ref></p>

				<p>21st July, &rsquo;92. Before Major Gedney, Mr. Hathorne, Mr. Corwin and Capt.
					Higginson.</p>

				<p>Goody Foster, you remember we have three times spoken with you, and do you now
					remember what you then confessed to us? Her former confession was read, which
					she owned to be all true.</p>

				<p>You have been engaged in very great wickedness, and some have been left to
					hardness of heart to deny; but it seems that God will give you more favor than
					others, inasmuch as you relent. But your daughter here hath confessed some
					things that you did not tell us of. Your daughter was with you and Goody
					Carrier, when you did ride upon the stick. A. I did not know it. Q. How long
					have you known your daughter to be engaged? A. I cannot tell, nor have I any
					knowledge of it at all. Q. Did you see your daughter at the meeting? A. No. Q.
					Did not you know your daughter to be a witch? A. No. Q. Your daughter said she
					was at the witches meeting, and that you yourself stood at a distance off and
					did not partake at that meeting; and you yourself said so also; give us a
					relation from the beginning until now. A. I know none of their names that were
					there, but only Goody Carrier. Q. Would you know their frees if you saw them? A.
					I &lpar;400&rpar; cannot tell. Q. Were there not two companies in the
					field at the same time? A. I remember no more.</p>

				<p>Mary Warren, one of the afflicted, said that Goody Carrier&rsquo;s shape told
					her, that this Goody Foster had made her daughter a witch. Q. Do not you
					acknowledge that you did so about thirteen years ago? A. No, and I know no more
					of my daughter&rsquo;s being a witch than what day I shall die upon. Q. Are
					you willing your daughter should make a full and free confession? A. Yes. Q. Are
					you willing to do so too? A. Yes. Q. You cannot expect peace of conscience
					without a free confession. A. If I knew any thing more, I would speak it to the
					utmost. Goody Lacey, the daughter, called in, began thus; Oh, mother! how do you
					do? We have left Christ, and the Devil hath gat hold of us. How shall I get rid
					of this evil one? I desire God to break my rocky heart that I may get the
					victory this time. Q. Goody Foster, you cannot get rid of this snare, your heart
					and mouth is not open. A. I did not see the Devil, I was praying to the Lord. Q.
					What Lord? A. To God. Q. What God do witches pray to? A. I cannot tell, the Lord
					help me. Q. Goody Lacey, had you no discourse with your mother in your riding?
					A. No, I think I had not a word. Q. Who rid foremost on that stick to the
					village? A. I suppose my mother. Goody Foster said that Goody Carrier was
					foremost. Q. Goody Lacey, how many years ago since they were baptized? A. Three
					or four years ago, I suppose. Q. Who baptized them? A. The old serpent. Q. How
					did he do it? A. He dipped their heads in the water, saying they were his, and
					that he had power over them. Q. Where was this? A. At Fall&rsquo;s river. Q.
					How many were baptized that day? A. Some of the chief; I think there were six
					baptized. Q. Name them. A. I think they were of the higher powers. These were
					then removed.</p>

				<p>Mary Lacey, the grand-daughter, was brought in, and Mary Warren in a violent fit.
					Q. How dare you come in here, and bring the Devil with you, to afflict these
					poor creatures? A. I know nothing of it. Lacey laying her hand on
					Warren&rsquo;s arm; she recovered from her fit. Q. You are here accused for
					practising witchcraft upon Goody Ballard ; which way do you do it? A. I cannot
					tell. Where is my mother that made me a witch, and I knew it not? Q. Can you
					look upon that maid, Mary Warren, and not hurt her? Look upon her in a friendly
					way. She trying so to do, struck her down with her eyes. Q. Do you acknowledge
					now you are a witch? A. Yes. Q. How long have you been a witch? A. Not above a
					week. Q. Did the Devil appear to you? A. Yes. Q. In what shape? A. In the shape
					of a horse. Q. What did he say to you? A. He bid me not to be afraid of any
					tiring, and he would not bring me out; but he has proved a liar from the
					beginning. Q. When was this? A. I know not; above a week. Q. Did you set your
					hand to the book? A. No. Q. Did he bid you worship him? A. Yes; he bid me also
					afflict persons. You are now in the way to obtain mercy if you will confess and
					repent. She said, The Lord help me. Q. Do not you desire to be saved by Christ?
					A. Yes. Then you must confess freely what you know in this matter. She then
					proceeded. I was in bed, and the Devil came to me, and bid me obey him and I
					should want for nothing, and he would not bring me out. Q. But how long ago? A.
					A little more than a year. Q. Was that the first time? A. Yes. Q. How long was
					you gone from your father, when you run away? A. Two days. Q. Where had you your
					food? A. At John Stone&rsquo;s. Q. Did the Devil appear to you then, when
					you was abroad? A. No, but he put such thoughts in my mind as not to obey my
					parents. Q. Who did the &lpar;401&rpar; Devil bid you afflict? A.
					Timothy Swan. Richard Carrier comes often a-nights and has me to afflict
					persons. Q. Where do ye go? A. To Goody Ballard&rsquo;s sometimes. Q. How
					many of you were there at a time? A. Richard Carrier and his mother, and my
					mother and grandmother. Upon reading over the confession so far, Goody Lacey,
					the mother, owned this last particular. Q. How many more witches are there in
					Andover? A. I know no more, but Richard Carrier.</p>

				<p>Tell all the truth. A. I cannot yet. Q. Did you use at any time to ride upon a
					stick or pole? A. Yes. Q. How high? A. Sometimes above the trees. Q. Your mother
					struck down these afflicted persons, and she confessed so far, till at last she
					could shake hands with them freely and do them no hurt. Be you also free and
					tell the truth. What sort of worship did you do the Devil? A. He bid me pray to
					him and serve him and said he was a god and lord to me. Q. What meetings have
					you been at, at the village? A. I was once there and Richard Carrier rode with
					me on a pole, and the Devil carried us. Q. Did not some speak to you to afflict
					the people there? A. Yes, the Devil. Q. Was there not a man also among you
					there? A. None but the Devil. Q. What shape was the Devil in then? A. He was a
					black man, and had a high crowned hat. Q. Your mother and your grandmother say
					there was a minister there. How many men did you see there? A. I saw none but
					Richard Carrier. Q. Did you see none else? A. There was a minister there, and I
					think he is now in prison. Q. Were there not two <ref target="n54" type="ed"
						>[&sext;]</ref> ministers there? A. Cannot tell. Q. Was there not one
					Mr. Burroughs there? A. Yes.</p>

				<p>The examination contains many pages more of the same sort of proceedings which I
					am tired of transcribing. Mr. Hale mentions also the case of Richard Carrier,
					who was a lad of 18 years, accusing his mother, one that suffered, but this
					examination was managed just in the same way. He denied everything at first, but
					was drawn to confession of every thing that his examiners required.</p>

				<p>So seven or eight of the confessors are said to have witnessed against the
					minister Burroughs, but I have seen many examinations wherein he is accused just
					like this of Lacey. Richard Carrier&rsquo;s runs thus: &ldquo;We met in
					a green, which was the minister&rsquo;s pasture&mdash;we were in two
					companies at last. I think there was a few men with them.&mdash;I heard
					Sarah Good talk of a minister or two.&mdash;One of them was she that had
					been at the eastward; his name is Burroughs, and is a little man.&mdash;I
					remember not the other&rsquo;s name.&rdquo;</p>

				<p>After these examinations, the reader will find no great difficulty in giving
					credit to the recantations of the confessors when they apprehended themselves
					out of danger. One or two may be sufficient.</p>

				<p>&ldquo;We whose names are underwritten, inhabitants of Andover; when as that
					horrible and tremendous judgment beginning at Salem village in the year 1692, by
					some called witchcraft, first breaking forth at Mr. Paris&rsquo;s house,
					several young persons, being seemingly afflicted, did accuse several persons for
					afflicting them, and many there believing it so to be, we being inform
					&lpar;402&rpar; ed that, if a person was sick, the afflicted persons
					could tell what or who was the cause of that sickness: Joseph Ballard, of
					Andover, his wife being sick at the same time, he either from himself or by the
					advice of others, fetched two of the persons, called the afflicted persons, from
					Salem village to Andover, which was the beginning of that dreadful calamity that
					befel us in Andover, believing the said accusations to be true, sent for the
					said persons to come together to the meeting house in Andover, the afflicted
					persons being there. After Mr. Barnard had been at prayer, we were blindfolded,
					and our hands were laid upon the afflicted persons, they being in their fits and
					falling into their fits at our coming into their presence, as they said; and
					some led us and laid our hands upon them, and then they said they were well, and
					that we were guilty of afflicting of them; whereupon we were all seized, as
					prisoners, by a warrant from the justice of the peace, and forthwith carried to
					Salem. And by reason of that sudden surprisal, we knowing ourselves altogether
					innocent of that crime, we were all exceedingly astonished and amazed, and
					consternated and affrighted even our of our reason; and our nearest and dearest
					relations, seeing us in that dreadful condition, and knowing our great danger,
					apprehending that there was no other way to save our lives, as the case was then
					circumstanced, but by our confessing ourselves to be such and such persons as
					the afflicted represented us to be, they, our of tender love and pity, persuaded
					us to confess what we did confess. And indeed that confession, that it is said
					we made, was no other than what was suggested to us by some gentlemen, they
					telling us that we were witches, and they knew it, and we knew it, and they knew
					that we knew it, which made us think that it was so; and our understanding, our
					reason, our faculties almost gone, we were not capable of judging our condition;
					as also the hard measures they used with us rendered us incapable of making our
					defence, but said any thing and every thing which they desired, and most of what
					we said was but in effect a consenting to what they said. Some time after, when
					we were better composed, they telling us of what we had confessed, we did
					profess that we were innocent and ignorant of such things; and we hearing that
					Samuel Wardwell had renounced his confession, and quickly after condemned and
					executed, some of us were told that we were going after Wardwell.</p>

				<p>&ldquo;Mary Osgood, Deliverance Dane, Sarah Wilson, Mary Tiler, Abigail
					Barker, Hannah Tiler.&rdquo;</p>

				<p>These unhappy people were not only, in the manner which has been related, brought
					to confession, but also obliged to swear to the truth of it. At the Superior
					Court in January they all abode by their confessions. They could not tell what
					the disposition of the court and juries would be, and the temptation was the
					same as at the first examination. But there was one Margaret Jacobs, who had
					more courage than the rest. She had been brought not only to accuse herself, but
					Mr. Burroughs, the minister, and even her own grandfather. Before their
					execution, she was struck with horror, and begged forgiveness of Burroughs, who
					readily forgave her, and prayed with her, and for her. An imposthume in her head
					prevented her trial at the court of Oyer and Terminer. At the Superior Court in
					January she delivered a writing in the words following:&mdash;</p>

				<p>&ldquo;The humble declaration of Margaret Jacobs unto the honoured court now
					sitting at Salem, sheweth,</p>

				<p>&ldquo;That whereas your poor and humble declarant being closely confined
					here in Salem jail for the crime of witchcraft, which crime, thanks be to the
					Lord, I am altogether ignorant of, as will appear at the great day of
					&lpar;403&rpar; judgment. May it please the honoured court, I was cried
					out upon by some of the possessed persons, as afflicting of them; whereupon I
					was brought to my examination, which persons at the sight of me fell down, which
					did very much startle and affright me. The Lord above know I knew nothing, in
					the least measure, how or who afflicted them; they told me, without doubt I did,
					or else they would not fall down at me; they told me if I would not confess, I
					should be put down into the dungeon and would be hanged, but if I would confess
					I should have my life; the which did so affright me, with my own vile wicked
					heart, to save my life made me make the confession I did, which confession, may
					it please the honoured court, is altogether false and untrue. The very first
					night after I had made my confession, I was in such horror of conscience that I
					could not sleep, for fear the Devil should carry me away for telling such horrid
					lies. I was, may it please the honoured court, sworn to my confession, as I
					understand since, but then, at that time, was ignorant of it, not knowing what
					an oath did mean. The Lord, I hope, in whom I trust, out of the abundance of his
					mercy, will forgive me my false forswearing myself. What I said was altogether
					false, against my grandfather, and Mr. Burroughs, which I did to save my life
					and to have my liberty; but the Lord, charging it to my conscience, made me in
					so much horror, that I could not contain myself before I had denied my
					confession, which I did, though I saw nothing but death before me, choosing
					rather death with a quiet conscience, than to live in such horror, which I could
					not suffer. Whereupon my denying my confession, I was committed to close prison,
					where I have enjoyed more felicity in spirit a thousand times than I did before
					in my enlargement.</p>

				<p>&ldquo;And now, may it please your honours, your poor and humble declarant
					having, in part, given your honours a description of my condition, do leave it
					to your honours pious and judicious discretions to take pity and compassion on
					my young and tender years; to act and do with me as the Lord above and your
					honours shall see good, having no friend but the Lord to plead my cause for me;
					not being guilty in the least measure of the crime of witchcraft, nor any other
					sin that deserves death from man; and your poor and humble declarant shall
					forever pray, as she is bound in duty, for your honours&rsquo; happiness in
					this life, and eternal felicity in the world to come. So prays your honours
					declarant. Margaret Jacobs.&rdquo;</p>

				<p>I shall now proceed in the relation of facts. The accusers having charged a great
					number in the county of Essex, I find in the examinations frequent mention of
					strangers whose shapes or specters were unknown to the afflicted, and now and
					then the names of a person at Boston and other distant places. Several some time
					after mention Mr. Dean, one of the ministers of Andover, but touch him more
					tenderly, somewhat as Mrs. Osgood in her confession, than they do Burroughs. Mr.
					Dean probably was better known and esteemed than the other, or he would have
					stood a bad chance.</p>

				<p>Mr. Nathaniel Cary,<ref target="n55">[43]</ref> a gentleman of figure in the town
					of Charlestown, hearing that some at Salem had complained of his wife for
					afflicting them, they went to Salem together our of curiosity to see whether the
					afflicted knew her. They happened to arrive just as the justices were going into
					&lpar;404&rpar; the meeting house, where they held the court, to examine
					prisoners. All that were brought in were accused, and the girls fell into fits
					as usual, but no notice was taken of Mrs. Cary except that one or two of the
					afflicted came to her and asked her name. After the examination her husband went
					into a tavern, having encouragement that he should have an opportunity of
					discoursing with the girl who had accused his wife. There he met with John the
					afflicted Indian, who attended as a servant in the house. He had been there but
					a short time before the girls came in and tumbled about the floor, and cried out
					Cary, and a warrant from the justices was immediately sent to apprehend her. Two
					of the girls accused her, neither of whom she had ever heard of before, and soon
					after the Indian joined them. The justices, by her husband&rsquo;s account,
					used her very roughly, and it was to no purpose to make any defence or to offer
					any bail, but she was committed to prison in Boston and removed from thence by
					habeas corpus to Cambridge and there laid in irons. When the trials at Salem
					came on her husband went there, and finding how things were managed, thought it
					high time to contrive her escape. They fled to New-York, where Gov. Fletcher
					received them courteously. They petitioned for a trial in the county where they
					lived. If the judges supposed it necessary to try the offence where it was
					committed, her body being in Middlesex and her specter in Essex, it is probable
					they were under doubt.</p>

				<p>About a week after, viz. the latter end of May, some of the afflicted accused
					Capt. John Alden,<ref target="n56">[44]</ref> of Boston. He had been many years
					the master of a sloop in the country service employed between Boston and the
					eastern country, to supply the garrisons, &amp;c.; and the justices allowed
					had always had the character of an honest man, though one of them, Gidney, told
					him at his examination he then saw cause to think otherwise. Alden, in the
					account he gives, says that the accuser pointed first to another man and said
					nothing, but that upon the man who held her his stooping down to her ear, she
					cried out Alden, Alden, &amp;c. All were ordered into the street and a ring
					made, and then she cried out, There stands Alden, a bold fellow with his hat on,
					sells powder and shot to the Indians, lies with the squaws and has papooses. He
					was immediately taken into custody of the marshal&lsqb;George
					Herrick&rsqb; and required to deliver up his sword. A further examination
					was had in the meeting house, his hands held open by the officer that he might
					not pinch the afflicted, and upon their being struck down at the sight of him
					and making their usual cries he was committed to the jail in Boston, where he
					lay fifteen weeks, and then was prevailed on by his friends to make his escape,
					and to absent himself until the consternation of the people was a little abated,
					and they had recovered their senses.</p>

				<p>By this time about one hundred persons were in the several prisons <ref
						target="n57">[45]</ref> &lpar;405&rpar; charged with witchcraft. The
					court of Oyer and Terminer began at Salem the first week in June &lsqb;June
					2d&rsqb;. Only one of the accused, viz. Bridget Bishop,<ref target="n58"
						>[46]</ref> alias Oliver, was brought upon trial. She had been charged with
					witchcraft twenty years before, by a person who acknowledged his guilt in
					accusing her upon his death-bed; but being a fractious old woman the losses the
					neighbors met with in their cattle and poultry, or by oversetting their carts,
					&amp;c., were ascribed to her, and now given in evidence. This, together
					with the hearsay from the specters sworn to in court by the afflicted and
					confessing confederates, and an excrescence found some where upon her which was
					called a teat, was thought by court and jury plenary proof, and she was
					convicted, and on the 10th of June executed.</p>

				<p>The court adjourned to the 30th of June, and in the mean time the Governor and
					Council desired the opinion of several ministers upon the state of things as
					they then stood, which was given as follows:&mdash;</p>

				<p>&ldquo;The return of several ministers consulted by his excellency and the
					honorable council upon the present witchcraft in Salem village.</p>

				<p>Boston, June 15th, 1692.</p>

				<p>&ldquo;1. The afflicted state of our poor neighbours, that are now suffering
					by molestations from the invisible world, we apprehend so deplorable, that we
					think their condition calls for the utmost help of all persons in their several
					capacities.</p>

				<p>&ldquo;2. We cannot but, with all thankfulness, acknowledge the success which
					the merciful God has given unto the sedulous and assiduous endeavours of our
					honourable rulers, to detect the abominable witchcrafts which have been
					committed in the country, humbly praying, that the discovery of those mysterious
					and mischievous wickednesses may be perfected.</p>

				<p>&ldquo;3. We judge that, in the prosecution of these and all such
					witchcrafts, there is need of a very critical and exquisite caution, lest by too
					much credulity for things received only upon the Devil&rsquo;s authority,
					there be a door opened for a long train of miserable consequences, and Satan get
					an advantage over us; for we should not be ignorant of his devices.</p>

				<p>&ldquo;4. As in complaints upon witchcrafts, there may be matters of inquiry
					which do not amount unto matters of presumption, and there may be matters of
					presumption which yet may not be matters of conviction, so it is necessary, that
					all proceedings thereabout be managed with an exceeding tenderness towards those
					that may be complained of, especially if they have been persons formerly of an
					unblemished reputation.</p>

				<p>&ldquo;5. When the first inquiry is made into the circumstances of such as
					may lie under the just suspicion of witchcrafts, we could wish that there may be
					admitted as little as is possible of such noise, company and openness as may too
					hastily expose them that are examined, and that there may no thing be used as a
					test for the trial of the suspected, the lawfulness whereof may be doubted among
					the people of God; but that the directions given &lpar;406&rpar; by such
					judicious writers as Perkins and Bernard [be consulted in such a case].</p>

				<p>&ldquo;6. Presumptions whereupon persons may be committed, and, much more,
					convictions whereupon persons may be condemned as guilty of witchcrafts, ought
					certainly to be more considerable than barely the accused person&rsquo;s
					being represented by a specter unto the afflicted; inasmuch as it is an
					undoubted and notorious thing, that a demon may, by God&rsquo;s permission,
					appear, even to ill purposes, in the shape of an innocent, yea, and a virtuous
					man. Nor can we esteem alterations made in the sufferers, by a look or touch of
					the accused, to be an infallible evidence of guilt, but frequently liable to be
					abused by the Devil&rsquo;s legerdemains.</p>

				<p>&ldquo;7. We know not whether some remarkable affronts given to the Devils by
					our disbelieving those testimonies whose whole force and strength is from them
					alone, may not put a period unto the progress of the dreadful calamity begun
					upon us, in the accusations of so many persons, whereof some, we hope, are yet
					clear from the great transgression laid unto their charge.</p>

				<p>&ldquo;8. Nevertheless, we cannot but humbly recommend unto the government,
					the speedy and vigorous prosecution of such as have rendered themselves
					obnoxious, according to the direction given in the laws of God, and the
					wholesome statutes of the English nation, for the detection of
						witchcrafts&rdquo;<ref target="n59">[47]</ref></p>

				<p>The two first and the last sections of this advice took away the force of all the
					others, and the prosecutions went on with more vigor than before. The exquisite
					caution in separating the evidence upon the Devil&rsquo;s authority from the
					rest, in the third section, and the disbelieving those testimonies whose whole
					force is from the Devil alone in the seventh section, must have puzzled the
					judges, and they had need of some further authorities toguide them than Perkins
					or Bernard,<ref target="n60">[48]</ref> or any other books they were furnished
						with.<ref target="n61">[49]</ref></p>

				<p>I was at a loss until I met with this return, by what law they proceeded. The old
					constitution was dissolved; no laws of the colony were in force, witchcraft is
					no offence by the common law of England. The statute of &lpar;407&rpar;
					James I. was indeed more ancient than the colony charter, but no statute had
					ever been adopted here. The General Assembly had not then met, and there could
					have been no provision made by a Province law, but it seems by the eighth
					section that the English statutes were made the rule upon this extraordinary
					occasion. But what authority the court had to change the sentence from burning
					to hanging, I cannot conceive.<ref target="n62">[50]</ref> Before the other
					trials the law against witchcraft under the first charter was established with
					the other Colony laws. The authority by which the court sat may as well be
					called in question. No authority is given by the Province charter to any powers
					short of the whole General Court to constitute courts of justice. The Governor
					indeed, with the consent of the Council, appoints judges, commissioners of Oyer
					and Terminer, and all officers belonging to the courts. It is strange they did
					not tarry until the Assembly met. A judge shall not be punished for mere error
					of judgment, but it certainly behooves him, in a trial for life especially, to
					consider well by what authority he acts.</p>

				<p>The court was held again by adjournment at Salem, June 30. Six
					&lsqb;five&rsqb; women were brought upon trial, Sarah Good, Rebecca
					Nurse, Susannah Martin, Elizabeth Howe, and Sarah Wildes.<ref target="n63"
					>[51]</ref> The court and jury seemed to have had no difficulty with any but
					Nurse. She was a church member, and probably her good character caused the jury
					to bring in a verdict not guilty; but the accusers making a very great clamor
					and the court expressing their dissatisfaction with the verdict, the jury
					desired to go out again, and then brought her in guilty. The foreman of the jury
					gave the following certificate to satisfy her relations what induced an
					alteration of the verdict.</p>

				<p>&ldquo;July 4th, 1692.&rdquo;</p>

				<p>&ldquo;I Thomas Fisk, the subscriber hereof, being one of them that were of
					the jury the last week at Salem court, upon the trial of Rebekah Nurse,
					&amp;c. being desired, by some of the relations, to give a reason why the
					jury brought her in guilty, after the verdict, not guilty; I do hereby give my
					reasons to be as follows, viz.:</p>

				<p>When the verdict, not guilty, was &lsqb;given&rsqb;, the honoured court
					was pleased to object against it, saying to them, that they think they let slip
					the words which the prisoner at the bar spake against herself, which were spoken
					in reply to Goodwife Hobbs and her daughter, who had been faulty in setting
					their hands to the Devil&rsquo;s book, as they had confessed formerly; the
					words were, &lsquo;What do these persons give in evidence against me now?
					they used to come among us?&rsquo; After the honoured court had manifested
					their dissatisfaction of the verdict, several of the jury declared themselves
					desirous to go out again, and thereupon the honoured court gave leave; but when
					we came to consider the case, I could not tell how to take her words as an
					evidence against her, till she had a further opportunity to put her sense upon
					them, if she would take it; and then going into court, I mentioned the words
					aforesaid, which by one of the court were affirmed to have been spoken by her,
					she being then at the bar, but made no reply nor interpre&ndash;
					&lpar;408&rpar; tation of them; whereupon, these words were to me a
					principal evidence against her. Thomas Fisk:&rdquo;</p>

				<p>Nurse, being informed of the use which had been made of her words, gave in a
					declaration to the court, that &ldquo;when she said Hobbs and her daughter
					were of her company, she meant no more than that they were prisoners as well as
					herself; and that, being hard of hearing, she did not know what the foreman of
					the jury said.&rdquo; But her declaration had no effect.</p>

				<p>The minister of Salem Mr. &lsqb;Nicholas&rsqb; Noyes was over zealous in
					these prosecutions. He excommunicated this honest old woman after her
					condemnation. One part of the form seems to have been unnecessary, delivering
					her over to Satan. He supposed she had delivered herself up to him long before.
					But her life and conversation had been such, of which many testimonies were
					given, that the remembrance of it, as soon as the people returned to the use of
					their reason, must have wiped off all the reproach which had been occasioned by
					the manner of her death.</p>

				<p>Calef, who when he wrote was generally supposed to be under unreasonable
					prejudice against the country, which lessened the credit of his narrative, says
					that at the trial of Sarah Good, one of the afflicted fell into a fit, and after
					recovery cried out that the prisoner had stabbed her and broke the knife in
					doing it, and a piece of the knife was found upon the afflicted person; but a
					young man declared that the day before he broke that very knife and threw away a
					piece of it, this afflicted person being then present; and adds that the court
					bid her tell no more lies, but went on notwithstanding this fraud to improve her
					as a witness against other prisoners.<ref target="n64" type="ed"
					>[&sext;]</ref> This account, if true, would give me a more unfavorable
					opinion even of the integrity of the court, if I had not met with something not
					unlike to it in the trials before Sir Matthew Hale. The afflicted children in
					their fits upon the least touch from Rose Cullender, one of the supposed
					witches, would shriek out, which they would not do when touched by any other
					person. Lest there should be any fraud, Lord Cornwallis, Sir Edmund Bacon,
					Sergeant Keeling and other gentlemen attended one of the girls whilst she was in
					her fits at another part of the hall, and one of the witches was brought, and an
					apron put before the girl&rsquo;s eyes, but instead of the witch&rsquo;s
					hand another person&rsquo;s hand was taken to touch the girl, who thereupon
					shrieked out as she used to do. The gentlemen returned and declared to the court
					they believed the whole was an imposture. The witch was found guilty
					notwithstanding, and the judge and all the court wore fully satisfied with the
					verdict and awarded sentence accordingly.</p>

				<p>Susannah Martin had been suspected, ever since 1669, so that a great number of
					witch stories were told of her, and many of them given in evidence. One of the
					other being told by the minister at the place of execution, that she knew she
					was a witch, and therefore advised her to confess, she replied that he lied, and
					that she was no more a witch than he was a wizard, and if he took away her life,
					God would give him blood to drink.</p>

				<p>At one of these trials it is said that one of the accusers charged Mr. Willard, a
					minister of Boston, and that she was sent out of court, and afterwards a report
					spread that she was mistaken in the person.<ref target="n65" type="ed"
						>[&sext;]</ref> It is more probable that she intended
					&lsqb;John&rsqb; Willard, who was then in prison, and that it was given
					out that the audience were mistaken.</p>

				<p>At the next adjournment, Aug. 5th, George Burroughs, John Proctor
					&lpar;409&rpar; and Elizabeth his wife, John Willard, George Jacobs and
					Martha Carrier were all found guilty, condemned, and all executed the 19th of
					August, except Elizabeth Proctor, who escaped by pleading her belly.</p>

				<p>Burroughs had preached some years before, but it seems not to acceptance, at
					Salem village. Afterward he preached at Wells in the Province of Maine. As a
					specimen of the proceedings in all the trials we shall be a little more
					particular in relating his.</p>

				<p>The indictment was as follows.</p>

				<p>Anno Regis et Reginae, &amp;c. quarto.</p>

				<p>Essex ss. The jurors for our sovereign lord and lady the king and queen present,
					that George Burroughs, late of Falmouth in the province of Massachusetts Bay,
					clerk, the ninth day of May, in the fourth year of the reign of our sovereign
					lord and lady William and Mary, by the grace of God of England, Scotland, France
					and Ireland, king and queen, defenders of the faith, &amp;c. and divers
					other days and times, as well before as after, certain detestable arts called
					witchcrafts and sorceries, wickedly and feloniously hath used, practised and
					exercised, at and within the township of Salem, in the county of Essex
					aforesaid, in, upon and against one Mary Walcot, of Salem village, in the county
					of Essex, single woman; by which said wicked arts, the said Mary Walcot, the
					ninth day of May in the fourth year abovesaid, and divers other days and times
					as well before as after, was and is tortured, afflicted, pined, consumed, wasted
					and tormented, against the peace of our sovereign lord and lady the king and
					queen, and against the form of the statute in that case made and provided.
					Endorsed Billa vera. Three other bills were found for the like upon other
					persons, to all which he pleaded not guilty, and put himself upon trial,
					&amp;c.</p>

				<p>The afflicted and confessing witches were first examined, for although, by the
					advice of the elders, this kind of evidence was not to be deemed infallible; yet
					it was presumptive, and, with other circumstances, sufficient proof. It would be
					tedious to recite the whole of this evidence, specially as it was of the same
					sort with what has been already related in the confessions. The most material
					circumstance which distinguished him &lsqb;Burroughs&rsqb; from the
					rest, was, that he was to be a king in Satan&rsquo;s empire.</p>

				<p>The other evidence was that being a little man he had performed feats beyond the
					strength of a giant; particularly that he would take a gun of seven feet barrel
					behind the lock and hold it out with one hand; that he would take up a barrel of
					molasses or cider and carry them in a disadvantageous place and posture from a
					canoe to the shore; and when in his vindication be urged that an Indian which
					was there held out the gun as he did, the witnesses not seeing or not
					remembering any Indian, it was supposed it must be the black man or the devil,
					who, the witnesses swore, looks like an Indian.</p>

				<p>Besides this it was sworn that he had treated his wives, having been twice
					married, very harshly, and would pretend, when be had been absent from home,
					that he could tell what had been said to them, and that he persuaded them to
					swear, and to oblige themselves by a writing, which in the printed account of
					the trial is called &ldquo;a Covenant,&rdquo; not to reveal his secrets,
					and that they had privately complained to the neighbors that their house was
					haunted by spirits. One of his wife&rsquo;s brothers also swore that going
					out after strawberries they rode very softly&mdash;slowly, I
					suppose&mdash;two or three miles, when Burroughs went into the bushes, after
					which they rode back a quick pace, and when they came near home, to their
					astonishment found him on foot with them, and that he fell to chiding his wife
					for talking with her &lpar;410&rpar; brother about him, and said he knew
					their thoughts, which his brother intimated was more than the Devil knew, but
					Burroughs replied his god told him.</p>

				<p>The prisoner said, in his defence, a man was with him when his brother left him,
					which was also supposed to be the black man.</p>

				<p>This was the sum of the evidence. He is said to have used many twistings and
					turnings, and to have contradicted himself in making his defence. At his
					execution he concluded his prayer with the Lord&rsquo;s prayer, probably to
					show his innocence, for it was generally received that a witch could not say the
					Lord&rsquo;s prayer, and it was used as a test at the examinations when
					several of the old women, as children often do, blundered at give and forgive in
					the fourth and fifth petitions, and it was improved against them.</p>

				<p>September 9th, Martha Corey, Mary Esty, Alice Parker, Ann Pudcator, Dorcas Hoar
					and Mary Bradbury were tried; and Sept. 17 Margaret Scott, Wilmot Read, Samuel
					Wardwell, Mary Parker, Abigail Faulkner, Rebekah Eames, Mary Lacey, Ann Foster,
					Abigail Hobbs, and all received sentence of death. Those in italics were
					executed September 22d.</p>

				<p>Mary Esty, who was sister to Nurse, put into the court a petition in which she
					tells them that, although she was conscious of her own innocence, yet she did
					not ask her own life, but prayed them before they condemned any more they would
					examine some of the confessing witches, who she knew had belied themselves and
					others, which she was sure would appear in the world to which she was going, if
					it did not in this world.</p>

				<p>Those that were not executed probably confessed their guilt. All whose
					examinations remain on the files, of which there are three or four, did so.
					Wardwell had confessed, but recanted and suffered. His own wife, as well as his
					daughter, accused him and saved themselves. There are a great number of
					instances of children and parents accusing each other. I have met with no other
					than this of husbands or wives, and surely this one ought not to have been
					suffered.</p>

				<p>Giles Corey was the only person, besides what have been named, who suffered
					death. He, seeing the fate of those who had put themselves upon trial, refused
					to plead to the indictment; but the judges who were not careful enough in
					observing the rules of law in favor of the prisoners, took care to do it against
					this unhappy man, and he was pressed to death; the only instance I have ever
					heard of in any of the English colonies.<ref target="n66">[52]</ref> History
					fur&lpar;411&rpar; nishes us perhaps with as many instances of cruelty
					proceeding from superstition, as from the most savage barbarous temper of mind.</p>

				<p>Besides the irregularities which I have already mentioned in these trials, the
					court admitted evidence to be given of facts, not laid in the indictments, to
					prove witchcraft eight, ten or fifteen years before; indeed, no other sort of
					evidence was offered to prove facts in the indictments but the spectral
					evidence, which, in the opinion of the divines, was not sufficient. It would
					have been well if they had consulted lawyers <ref target="n67">[53]</ref> also,
					who would have told them that evidence ought not to be admitted even against the
					general character of persons charged criminally unless they offer evidence in
					favor of it, much less ought their whole lives to be arraigned and no
					opportunity given them of making defence.</p>

				<p>This court of Oyer and Terminer, happily for the country, sat no more. Nineteen
					persons had been executed; but the eyes of the country in general were not yet
					opened. The prison at Salem was so full that some were obliged to be removed,
					and many were in other prisons reserved for trial. The General Court which sat
					in October, although they had revived the old colony law which was in these
					words, &ldquo;If any man or woman be a witch, that is, hath or consulteth
					with a familiar spirit, they shall be put to death&rdquo;&mdash;yet this
					not being explicit enough, they enacted another in the words of the statute of
					King James, which continued in force until the trials were over, but both were
					afterwards disallowed by the crown.<ref target="n68">[54]</ref>
					&lpar;412&rpar; Another act was passed, constituting a Supreme
						Court,<ref target="n69">[55]</ref> which was to be held at Salem in January;
					but before that time many who had been forward in these prosecutions became
					sensible of their error. Time for consideration seems to be reason enough to be
					assigned for it; but another reason has been given. Ordinarily persons of the
					lowest rank, the dregs of the people, have had the misfortune of being charged
					with witchcraft; and although this was the case in many instances here, yet
					there were a number of women of as reputable families as any in the towns where
					they lived, who were charged and imprisoned, and several persons of still
					superior rank were hinted at by the pretended bewitched or the confessing,
					witches. The latter had no other way of saving themselves. Some of the persons
					were publicly named. Dudley Bradstreet, a justice of the peace, who had been
					appointed one of President Dudley&rsquo;s council, thought it necessary to
					abscond; so did his brother John Bradstreet, sons of the late Governor
					Bradstreet. Calef says it was intimated that Sir William Phips&rsquo;s lady
					was accused.<ref target="n70">[56]</ref> One at Boston complained of being
					afflicted by the secretary of Connecticut colony.<ref target="n71"
					>[&sext;]</ref></p>

				<p>At the Superior Court held at Salem in January, the grand jury found bills
					against about fifty persons, all but one or two women, who either were in
					prison, or under bonds for their appearance. They were all but three acquitted
					by the petty jury, and those three were pardoned by the Governor. Divers others
					were brought upon trial soon after at Charlestown in the county of Middlesex,
					and all acquitted. The juries changed sooner than the judges. The opinion which
					the latter had of their own superior understanding and judgment probably made
					them more backward in owning or discovering their errors. One of them, however,
					Mr. Sewall, who always had the character of great integrity, at a public fast
					sometime after gave in a bill, or note, to the minister, acknowledging his
					errors and desiring to humble himself in the sight of God and his people, and
					stood up while the note was reading.<ref target="n72">[57]</ref> It is said that
					the chief justice Mr. Stough &lpar;413&rpar; ton being informed of this
					act of one of his brethren, remarked upon it, that for himself, when he sat in
					judgment he had the fear of God before his eyes, and gave his opinion according
					to the best of his understanding, and although it might appear afterwards that
					he had been in an error, he saw no necessity of a public acknowledgment of it.
					One of the ministers, &lpar;414&rpar; who in the time of it approved of
					the court&rsquo;s proceeding, remarked in his diary soon after that many
					were of opinion innocent blood had been shed. The afflicted were never brought
					to trial for their imposture. Many of them are said to have proved profligate,
					abandoned people, and others to have passed the remainder of their lives in a
					state of obscurity and contempt.<ref target="n73">[58]</ref></p>

				<note id="n1">
					<seg type="note-symbol">&lsqb;1&rsqb;</seg>
					<p>The council met on the 16th, 17th, 20th, 24th and 27th of May, 1692. On the
						27th the appointments named &lpar;of sixty-seven justices, eight
						sheriffs, and two coroners&rpar; were made. The twenty-eight councillors
						were also authorized to act as justices in their own localities. This injury
						to the manuscript was occasioned by its being thrown into the street during
						the stamp-act riot on the evening of August 26, 1765, when Gov.
						Hutchinson&rsquo;s house was sacked. In his subsequent draft, as the
						date was missing, he did not supply it, but said &ldquo;At the first
						general council,&rdquo; &amp;c. This paragraph commences on page 8
						of the manuscript. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n2">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[2]</seg>
					<p>The date named for the beginning of the Springfield troubles is probably
						three or four years too early. Gov. Hutchinson relied for the date of what
						he supposed to be the earliest watch case in the Massachusetts Colony, on
						Johnson&rsquo;s Wonder Working Providence, p.199, where the date 1645
						stands at the head of the page. As I have explained in my reprint of Johnson
						&lpar;pp. xiii-xv.&rpar;, these headings are unreliable, and, quite
						likely&mdash;, were as often inserted by the printer as by the author.
						The date in the heading may be true as to some incident recorded on the page
						and erroneous as to other incidents. Keeping in mind the date when the work
						was written&mdash;from 1649 to 1651&mdash;the statement in the text
						involves no error. This portion was written in 1651. The author says,
						&ldquo;There hath of fate been more than one or two in this town
						&lsqb;Springfield&rsqb; greatly suspected of witchcraft; yet have
						they used much dilligence, both in finding them out, and for the Lords
						assisting them against their witchery, yet have they as is supposed,
						bewitched not a few persons, among whom two of the reverend Elders
						children.&rdquo; The cases came to examination and trial the same year
						the narrative was written, 1651, and the testimony offered covers the two
						previous years. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n3">
					<seg type="note-symbol">&lsqb;&sext;&rsqb;</seg>
					<p>Johnson. H.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n4">
					<seg type="note-symbol">&lsqb;3&rsqb;</seg>
					<p>The name of this woman was not Mary Oliver, but Mary Parsons. She was tried
						in Boston, May 13, 1651, on the charge of witchcraft and for murdering her
						own child. She was convicted on the latter charge on her own confession, and
						sentenced to be hanged. She was reprieved till May 29 &lpar;Mass. Rec.
						iv. p. i. p. 47&rpar;. In Judd&rsquo;s History of Hadley
						&lpar;p. 234&rpar;, it appears that Mary Parsons was again tried for
						witchcraft in 1661, and discharged. This is doubtless an error in copying or
						printing 1661 for 1651, when the trial already named took place; for in both
						instances she was charged with bewitching the children of Mr. Moxon the
						minister. Mr. Moxon returned to England in 1652.</p>

					<p>Hugh Parsons, her husband, had previously been tried and convicted of
						witchcraft; and the most damaging charges against him had been brought by
						his wife. Among these were the follo:&mdash;wing;1. Mrs. P. had an
						intimate friend Mrs. Smith, to whom she freely expressed her mind. Now Mrs.
						Smith was a person who went little abroad, and Mrs. P. was sure she would
						not speak of the secrets committed to her trust; and yet her husband knew
						all about their conversation. 2. He would be out late nights; and half an
						hour before he came home, she would hear strange noises about the house. 3.
						He would come home in a distempered mind, put out the fire, pull off the bed
						clothes, and throw peas about the house. 4. He would gabble in his sleep,
						have strange dreams, and say he had been fighting the Devil. The jury found
						him guilty. The magistrates set aside the verdict, and the case came before
						the General Court at Boston, May 31, 1652, when he was aquitted
						&lpar;Ibid. p. 96&par;. The numerous and very curious depositions in
						the Springfield cases may be seen in the Appendix of Drake&rsquo;s
						Annals of Witchcraft, 1869, pp. 219-258. Hutchinson &lpar;in note, vol.
						i. p.165&rpar; mentions the case of Hugh Parsons, but not that of his
						wife. He mentions it again &lpar;vol. ii. p. 22&rpar;, and does not
						seem to be aware that his Mary Oliver case was that of Parsons&rsquo;s
						wife. My references to Hutchinson are to the edition of 1795. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n5">
					<seg type="note-symbol">&lsqb;&sext;&rsqb;</seg>
					<p>Vol. i. p. 150. &lsqb;Hutchinson&rsquo;s references to his earlier
						vol. are to the ed. of 1761.&rsqb; H.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n6">
					<seg type="note-symbol">&lsqb;4&rsqb;</seg>
					<p>Margarct Jones was executed June, 1648, and was therefore by more than two
						years, so far as now appears, the first case of conviction and execution for
						witchcraft in the Massachusetts Colony. The case is reported in
						Winthrop&rsquo;s Journal, ii. p. 326, and Hale&rsquo;s Modest
						Inquiry concerning Witchcraft, p. 17. Mr. Hale relates incidents not
						recorded by Winthrop. On the day of her execution, he, then twelve years of
						age, went to her cell, &ldquo;in company with some neighbors who took
						great pains to bring her to confession and repentance; but she constantly
						professed herself Innocent of that crime.&rdquo; P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n7">
					<seg type="note-symbol">&lsqb;5&rsqb;</seg>
					<p>No writer on this subject seems hitherto to have given the name of the person
						who suffered at Dorchester. Mr. John Hale, In Modest Inquiry, 1697, p. 17,
						thus alludes to the matter: &ldquo;Another that suffered on that account
						sometime after was a Dorchester woman. &ldquo;And upon the day of her
						execution Mr. Thompson &lsqb;Wm. Tompson&rsqb;, minister of Brantry
						and J. P. her former minister took pains with her to bring her to
						repentance. And &ldquo;she utterly denyed her guilt of witchcraft, for
						she had when a single woman played the Harlot, and being with child, used
						means to destroy the fruit of her body to conceal her sin and shame; and
						although she did not effect it, yet she was a murderer In the sight of God
						for her endeavors and shewed great penitency for that sin; but owned nothing
						of the crime laid to her Charge.&rdquo; Mr. Drake in his Annals of
						Witchcraft, and the History of Dorchester, make no mention of this case.</p>

					<p>I think I have found a clue to the name of this Dorchester woman. Increase
						Mather, in his Remarkable Providences, 1684, gave some of the cases of
						witchcraft which had occurred in New-England. He sent a copy of this book to
						his brother Nathaniel, a minister in Dublin. In a letter, dated Dec. 31,
						1684, Nathaniel Mather acknowledged the receipt of the book, and says:
						&ldquo;Why did you not put in the story of Mrs. Hibbins wichtcrafts and
						the discovery thereof; and also of H. Lakes wife, of Dorchester, whom as I
						have heard the Devil drew in by appearing to her in the likeness, and acting
						the part of a child of hers then lately dead on whom her heart was much set;
						as also another of a girl in Connecticut, who was judged to die a real
						convert, though she died for the same crime?&mdash;stories, as I have
						heard then as remarkable for some circumstances as most I have
						read.&rdquo; &lpar;Mather Papers, Mass. Hist. Coll., vol. xxxviii.
						p, 58.&rpar; Mr. Mather probably heard these stories before ho went
						abroad. The precise date of his departure does not appear. It was, however,
						before March 23, 1650-51, when he writes from London. There was a Henry Lake
						residing in Dorchestcr in 1678, who, with his children, was named its the
						residuary legatees in the will of Thomas Lake, a prominent citizen of file
						town, who died Oct. 27, 1678 &lpar;History of Dorchester p.
						125&rpar;. Mr. Savage &lpar;Geneal. Dict.&rpar; says there was a
						Henry Lake, currier, in Salem, in 1649, &ldquo;who may have been the
						Henry Lake of Dorchester&rdquo;; but he makes no mention of his wife
						being executed for witchcraft.</p>

					<p>The details of the case as related by Mr. Mather are quite unlike those
						related by Mr. Hale. One or both of the statements must be incorrect. The
						error I think must be in that of Mr. Hale. Mr. Mather was a resident of
						Dorchester, and a graduate of the college in 1647. He gives the name of the
						person accused, and was so situated as to be familiar with all the
						incidents. Mr. Hale was a resident of Charlestown, and in 1650 was but
						fourteen years of age. He did not know the name of the person, and gives the
						same incidents to a Springfield case. He says, p. 19: &ldquo;There was
						another executed of Boston anno 1656&lsqb;Mrs. Hibbins&rsqb; for
						that crime; and two or three of Springfield, one of which confessed, and
						said the occasion of her familiarity with Satan was this: She had lost a
						child, and exceedingly discontented at it, and longed Oh that she night see
						her child again! And at last the Devil in likeness of her child came to her
						bed-side and talked with her, and asked to come into the bed to her that
						night and several nights after, and so entered into covenant with Satan and
						became a witch. This was the only confessor in those times in this
						government.&rdquo; If any person, other than Mary Parsons, was executed
						at Springfield for witchcraft, no details have come down to us. Increase
						Mather probably omitted to mention the cases of Mrs. Hibbins and Mrs. Lake,
						with which he must have been familiar, in deference to the feelings of their
						friends then living. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n8">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[6]</seg>
					<p>This was the case of Mrs. Kendal, of Cambridge, who was executed for
						bewitching to death a child of Goodman Genings, of Watertown. The principal
						evidence was that of a Watertown nurse, who testified that the said Kendal
						did make much of the child, and then the child was well, but quickly changed
						in color and died a few hours after. The court took this evidence without
						calling the parents of the child. After the execution the parents denied
						that their child was bewitched, and started that it died from imprudent
						exposure to cold by the nurse the night before. The nurse soon after was put
						in prison for adultery, and there died, and so the matter was not further
						inquired into. Hale&rsquo;s Modest Inquiry, p. 18.</p>

					<p>Rev. Lucius R. Paige, of Cambridgeport, has recently found in the Middlesex
						court records, 1660, another alleged case of witchcraft in Cambridge, which
						was tried that year. Winifred Holman, an aged widow, was accused by her
						neighbors, John Wilson and wife, their son John Gibson, Jr., and their
						daughter Rebecca, wife of Charles Stearns. Actions of defamation were
						commenced against these parties, and on the trial, they, by way of
						justification, presented their supposed proof of witchcraft, some details of
						which may be seen in Hist. and Geneal. Register, vol. xxiv. p. 59. Probably
						other cases were tried in the courts of that period, of which nothing is now
						known. John Dunton, in 1686, said there had been twenty cases of witchcraft
						recently tried in the colony. &lpar;Letters, p.72.&rpar; P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n9">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[&sext;]</seg>
					<p>Vol. i. p. 187. H.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n10">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[7]See</seg>
					<p>Mass. Rec., vol. iv. pt. 1, p. 269. Joshua Scottow&rsquo;s
						representation, dated March 7, 1655-6, that he did not intend to oppose the
						proceedings of the Court fit the case of Ann Hibbins, is in Mass. Archives,
						vol. cxxxv. fol. 1. She was executed June 19, 1656. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n11">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[&sext;]</seg>
					<p>Magnalia. H.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n12">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[8]The</seg>
					<p>case of Ann Cole was fully reported in a letter by Mr. Join whiting, minister
						at Hartford, under whose observation it occurred, to Increase Mather, dated
						Dec. 10, 1682. The document is one of the Mather Papers, and is printed in
						Mass. Hist. Soc. Coll., vol. xxxvii. pp. 466-469. An abstract oft the case
						is in Increase Mather&rsquo;s Remarkable Providences, chap. v. pp.
						96-99, London ed. 1856, and Cotton Mather&rsquo;s Magnalia, Hartford ed.
						1855, vol. ii. p. 448. Several of the incidents are not correctly stated by
						Hutchinson, either in the manuscript or printed text. Ann Cole did not live
						next door to a Duteh family. The name of the woman executed, Greensmith,
						appears in both abstracts by the Mathers, but not in Mr. Whiting&rsquo;s
						original statement. The woman and her husband were both executed. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n13">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[9]</seg>
					<p>This woman was one of the victims hanged for witchcraft at Salem, in 1692.
						The evidence offered at her examination is in Mather&rsquo;s Wonders,
						pp. 70-76; Calef&rsquo;s More Wonders, pp. 125-132, and
						Woodward&rsquo;s Records of Salem Witchcraft, vol. i. pp. 193-233. She
						bore the reputation of a witch for many years, and her suits at law
						frequently brought her name into the General Court records.&ndash;Mass
						Rec. iv. pt. 2, pp. 540, 555; v. pp. 6, 26. P. </p>
				</note>

				<note id="n14">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[10]</seg>
					<p>To a person interested in the psychological inquiries pertaining to the
						witchcraft manifestations of the seventeenth century, the case of Elizabeth
						Knapp is one of the most interesting that occurred in New-England. It took
						place twenty-one years before the great outbreak at Salem, and under
						circumstances which gave opportunity f&lsqb;sic&rsqb; or calm
						observation. Samuel Willard, afterwards pastor of the Old South Church, in
						Boston, and who distinguished himself by his prudent conduct in 1692, was
						the pastor of the church in Groton at the time, and was the daily attendant
						and spiritual adviser of the family. He wrote a full account of the case,
						which fortunately has been preserved, and is now printed in the Mather
						Papers, pp. 555-571. In this paper he has calmly discussed the question
						whether her distemper was real or counterfeit. At first he was inclined to
						the latter opinion, and at times she confessed as much; but in view of all
						the facts he was of the opinion that there was something preternatural in
						the case. Increase Mather has an abstract of Mr. Willard&rsquo;s account
						in Remarkable Providences, p. 99. See also Magnalia, vol. ii. p. 449. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n15">
					<seg type="note-symbol">&lsqb;&sext;&rsqb;</seg>
					<p>Rebeckah Nurse. H.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n16">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[11]</seg>
					<p>Complaints against Eunice Cole for being a witch were made as early as 1656,
						and were continued till 1680, when site was up before the Quarter Court at
						Hampton, and committed on suspicion of being a witch. During most of this
						period she was a town pauper. Thirty-five depositions and other original
						papers relating to Eunice Cole&rsquo;s case, from Sept. 4, 1656 to Jan
						7, 1673-4, are in Mass. Archives, vol. cxxxv. fol. 2-15. See also
						Drake&rsquo;s Annals of witchcraft, pp. 99-103. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n17">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[12]</seg>
					<p>In the printed text Gov. Hutchinson gives but four lines to the Morse case.
						Fuller details may be found in Remarkable Providences, pp. 101-111;
						Magnalia, vol. ii. pp. 450-452, and Drake&rsquo;s Annals, pp. 144-150.
						In his Appendix &lpar;pp. 258-296&rpar;, Mr. Drake has given
						depositions and other papers connected with the proceedings against Mrs.
						Morse. Other depositions, with a petition of Wm. Morse In behalf of his
						wife, are in Mass. Archives, vol. cxxxv. fol. 11-19.</p>

					<p>Mrs. Morse was convicted 20 May, 1680, and sentenced to be hanged. June 1,
						she was reprieved till the next session of the court. &ldquo;Nov. 3. The
						deputies, on perusal of the acts of the honored court of assistants relating
						to the woman condemned for witchcraft, do not understand the reason why
						execution of the sentence given against her by the court is not executed,
						and that her second reprieval seems to us to be beyond what the law will
						allow, and do therefore judge meet to declare ourselves against it, with
						reference to the concurrence of the honored magistrates hereto.&rdquo;
						This action was &ldquo;not consented to by the magistrates.&rdquo;
						&lpar;Ms. memoranda in Mass. Archives, vol. cxxxv. fol. 18.&rpar;
						The deputies subsequently voted to give her a new trial; but the magistrates
						refused. Between this disagreement of the deputies and magistrates she
						escaped punishment. She was released from prison, but never acquitted or
						pardoned. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n18">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[13]</seg>
					<p>Caleb Powel was the name of the person implicated. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n19">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[&sext;]</seg>
					<p>Magnalia. H.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n20">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[14]</seg>
					<p>John Russell, minister of Hadley &lpar;in whose house the regicides
						Whalley and Goff were long concealed&rpar;, communicated this case to
						Increase Mather under date of August 2, 1683. It occurred the year before at
						Hartford. An abstract is in Remarkable Providences, pp. 112-114, and
						Magnalia, vol. ii. p. 452. The original account is printed in Mather Papers,
						pp. 86-88. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n21">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[15]</seg>
					<p>An account of the Walton case was furnished to Increase Mather by Joshua
						Moody, then minister at Portsmouth. &lpar;Mather Papers, p.
						361.&rpar; The paper is given in Remarkable Providences, pp. 114-116,
						and Magnalia, vol. ii. p. 453.</p>

					<p>A long and circumstantial account of the disturbance in George
						Walton&rsquo;s house is the subject-matter of a tract, printed in
						London, 1698,15 pp. 4to., a copy of which is in the Dowse Library belonging
						to the Massachusetts Historical Society. The title of the tract is
							&ldquo;<hi rend="small-caps">LITHOBOLIA</hi>; or the <hi
							rend="small-caps">STONE THROWING DEVILM</hi>. Being an exact and true
						Account of the various actions of Infernal Spirits, or &lpar;Devils
						Incarnate&rpar; Witches, or both; and the great Disturbance and
						Amazement they gave to George Walton&rsquo;s family, at a place called
						Great Island, in the Province of New-Hampshire in New-England. By R. C. who
						was a sojourner in the same family the whole time, and an ocular witness of
						these Diabolic Inventions; the contents thereof being manifestly known to
						the inhabitants of that Province, and the persons of other provinces, and is
						upon record in his Majesty&rsquo;s Council Court held in that
						Province.&rdquo;</p>

					<p>The writer says, &ldquo;Some time ago being in America, in his
						Majesty&rsquo;s service, I was lodged in the said George
						Walton&rsquo;s house, a planter there. &rdquo;</p>

					<p>The following names appear as attestants of the truth of the narrative:
						&ldquo;Samuel Jennings, Governor of West-Jarsey; Walter Clark,
						Deputy-Governor of Road-Island; Arthur Cook; Matt. Borden of Road-Island;
						Oliver Hooton of Barbadoes, Merchant; T. Maul of Salem in N. E. merchant;
						Capt. Walter Barefoot; John Hussey and John Hussey&rsquo;s
						wife.&rdquo; The narrative treats of throwing about, by an invisible
						power, stones, brick-bats, hammers, mauls, crow-bars, spits and other
						domestic utensils, for the period of three months.</p>

					<p>&ldquo;R. C.,&rdquo; the author of the tract, I have no doubt, was
						Richard Chamberlayne, Secretary of the Province of New-Hampshire in 1683.
						That he resided at Great Island appears by his signature to several
						depositions printed in New-Hampshire Hist. Coll, vols. ii. and viii.
						Chamberlayne and Barefoot were among the prosecutors of Joshua Moody at
						Portsmouth the next year for not conducting his services according to the
						English Prayer Book, and occasioned his imprisonment for three months. It
						appears that Increase Mather was aware that Secretary Chamberlayne had
						prepared an account of the Walton case, and he wrote to Mr. Moody to procure
						it, together with a narrative of the Hortando case. Mr. Moody, July 14,
						1683, writes to Mr. Mather: &ldquo;About that at G. Walton&rsquo;s,
						because my interest runs low with the Secretary, I have desired Mr.
						Woodbridge to endeavor the obtaining it; and if he can get it, shall send it
						by the first; though if there should be any difficulty there about, you may
						do pretty well with what you have already.&rdquo; &lpar;Mather
						Papers, p. 359.&rpar; Mr. Moody writes again, August 23: &ldquo;My
						endeavors also have not been a-wanting to obtain the other &lsqb;the
						Walton case&rsqb;, but find it difficult. If more may be gotten, you may
						expect &lsqb;it&rsqb; when I come, or else must take up with what
						you had from me at first, which was the sum of what was then worthy of
						notice, only many other particular actions of like nature had been then and
						since. It began on a Lord&rsquo;s day, June 11, 1682, and so continued
						for a long time, only there was some respite now and then. The last thing
						&lsqb;printed sight&rsqb; I have heard of was the carrying away of
						several axes in the night, notwithstanding they were laid up, yea locked up
						very safe, as the owner thought at least, which was done this spring.
						&lsqb;Postscript.&rsqb; Before sealing of my letter came
						accidentally to my hand this enclosed that had from William Morse of Newbury
						concerning the troubles at his house in 1679. If it may be of use to me, you
						may please to peruse and return it.&rdquo; &lpar;lbid.
						360.&rpar;</p>

					<p>The Secretary doubtless declined to furnish the unlovely Puritans at the Bay
						with his narrative, and, on returning to England, he printed it in London in
						1693. The tract shows that Church-of-England men were quite as observant of
						signs and wonders as the Puritans. &ldquo;Who that peruses these
						preternatural occurrences,&rdquo; asks the writer, &ldquo;can
						possibly be so much of an enemy to his own soul and irrefutable reason, as
						obstinately to oppose himself to, or confusedly fluctuate in, the opinion
						and doctrine of demons or spirits, and witches?&rdquo;</p>

					<p>The tract is reprinted in Historical Magazine &lpar;N.Y., vol. v. pp.
						321-327&rpar;, and is followed &lpar;vol. vi. p. 159&rpar; with
						a statement, by Rev. Lucius Alden, on the persons and localities mentioned
						therein. Brewster&rsquo;s Rambles about Portsmouth, 2d series, 1869, has
						a chapter on the subject &lpar;pp. 313-351&rpar;, with Mr.
						Alden&rsquo;s,statement; but none of these writers seem to be aware that
						Richard Chamberlayne was the author of Lithobolia. Since writing the above I
						find the tract under the name of Richard Chamberlain in the British Museum
						Catalogue, 1814, and tile title was so copied into Watt and Lowndes. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n22">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[16]</seg>
					<p>This was the Hortando case, a brief narrative of which, &ldquo;sent in by
						an intelligent person,&rdquo; is given in Remarkable Providences, pp.
						116-118, and Magnalia, vol. ii. p. 453.</p>

					<p>&ldquo;The enclosed I transcribed from Mr. Tho. Broughton, who read to me
						what he took from the mouth of the woman and her husband, and judge it
						credible; though it be not the half of what is to be gotten. I expect from
						him a fuller and further account before I come down to the
						Commencement.&rdquo; &lpar;Mr. Moody to Mr. Mather, August 23, 1683.
						Mather Papers, p. 360.&rpar; The date, place and attending circumstances
						make it clear that this was &ldquo;the narrative sent in by an
						intelligent person,&rdquo; which Mr. Mather printed. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n23">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[17]</seg>
					<p>Gov. Hutchinson found this case reported in Magnalia, vol. ii. P. 454. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n24">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[18]</seg>
					<p>Increase Mather&rsquo;s Remarkable Providences is the work here alluded
						to; but the date should have been 1684, :and not 1685. The book was issued
						in the spring of 1684. Nathaniel Mather, in a letter to the author, dated
						Dec. 31, 1684, acknowledges receiving a copy on which &ldquo;was written
						in your hand 7 ber 16.&rdquo; &lpar;Mather Papers, p. 58.&rpar;
						John Bishop acknowledges the receipt of a copy, in a letter dated June 10,
						1684. &lpar;Ibid. p. 312.&rpar; This erroneous date, and a
						typographied error in the Magnalia, vol. ii. p. 473, have led some writers
						to suppose that Cotton Mather wrote his first book on witchcraft in 1685. He
						was then twenty-two years of age. Bcfore.1683 he published no works except
						Elegy on Rev. Nath. Collin.s, 1685, and The Boston Ephemeris, an Almanac for
						1683, neither of which are in the printed list of his works. His first
						writing on witchcraft was issued in 1689. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n25">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[19]</seg>
					<p>This date is correct. It is singular that in his final draft the author
						should be in doubt, and say, &ldquo;in 1687 or 1688.&rdquo; P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n26">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[20]</seg>
					<p>The names and ages of the children were as follows: Martha 13, John 11, Mercy
						7, Benjamin 5. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n27">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[21]</seg>
					<p>Cotton Mother&rsquo;s Remarkable Providences, Boston, 1689. 2d ed.
						London, 1691. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n28">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[22]</seg>
					<p>Cotton Mather&rsquo;s. On the 4th of October, 1688, Joshua Moody wrote a
						letter to Increase Mather, then in London, in which he spoke of the Goodwin
						case. &lpar;Mather Papers, pp. 367-8.&rpar; He says &ldquo;We
						have a very strange thing among us, which we know not what to make of,
						except it be witchcraft, as we think it must needs be. Three or four
						children of one Goodwin, a mason, that have been for some weeks grievously
						tormented, crying out of head, eyes, tongue, teeth; breaking their neck,
						back, thighs, knees, legs, feet, toes, &amp;c.; and then they roar out,
						Oh my head! Oh my neck! and from one part to an other the pain runs almost
						as fast as I write it. The pain is doubtless very exquisite, and the cries
						most dolorous and affecting; and this is noteable, that two or more of them
						cry out of the same pain in the same part, at the same time, and as the pain
						shifts to another place in one, so in the other, and thus it holds them for
						an hour together and more; and when the pain is over they eat, drink, walk,
						play, laugh, as at other times. They are generally&ndash; well a nights.
						A great many good Christians spent a day of prayer there. Mr. Morton came
						over and we each spent an hour in prayer; since which, the parents
						suspecting an old woman and her daughter living hard by, complaint was made
						to the justices, and compassion had so far, that the women were committed to
						prison and are there now. Yesterday I called in at the house, and was
						informed by the parent that since the women were confined the children have
						been well while out of the house; but as soon as any of them come into the
						house, then taken as formerly; so that now all their children keep at their
						neighbors&rsquo; houses. If any step home they are immediately
						afflicted, and while they keep out are well. I have been a little larger in
						this narrative because I know you have studied these things. We cannot but
						think the Devil has a hand in it by some Instrument. It is an example, in
						all the parts of it, not to be parallelled. You may inquire further of Mr.
						Oakes &lsqb;Edward, Jr., the bearer of the letter&rsqb;, whose uncle
						&lsqb;Dr. Thomas Oakes&rsqb; administered physic to them at first,
						and he will probably inform you more fully.&rdquo;</p>

					<p>We have here a motive other than curiosity or credulity, which led Mr. Mather
						to take one of the Goodwin children to his own house, where he kept her till
						spring and till she fully recovered. This letter of Mr. Moody&rsquo;s
						was prior to any writing on tile subject by Mr. Mather. An account of this
						case is in the Magnalia, vol. ii. pp. 456-465. See also North American
						Review, vol. cviii. pp. 350-359. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n29">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[23]</seg>
					<p>A friend skilled In the Indian dialects suggests that Mr. Mather&rsquo;s
						pronunciation of the Indian language was probably so imperfect that the
						Devil was excusable for not understanding it. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n30">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[24]</seg>
					<p>In the year 1720, at Littleton, in the Massachusetts Province, a family were
						supposed to be bewitched in much the same manner with this of
						Goodwin&rsquo;s. I shall give a brief account of the affair, and the
						manner how the fraud came to be disclosed, to show the similitude between
						the two cases, and to discourage parents from showing the least countenance
						to such pranks in their children.</p>

					<p>One J. B. of Littleton, had three daughters of 11, 9, &lsqb;and&rsqb;
						5 years of age. The eldest being a forward girl, and having heard and read
						many strange stories used to surprise the company where she was with her
						manner of relating them. Pleased with applause she went from stories to
						dreams, and from dreains to visions, attaining the art of swooning away. and
						being to all appearance breathless for some time; and upon her reviving
						would tell strange stories of what she had met with in this and other
						worlds. When she met with the words God, Christ or Holy Ghost in the Bible,
						she would drop down with scarce any signs of life in her. Strange noises
						were heard in the house, stones came down the chimney and did great
						mischief. It was common to find her in ponds of water, crying out she should
						be drowned, sometimes upon the top of the house, and sometimes upon the tops
						of trees, and, being asked, said she flew there; complained of beating and
						pinching by invisible hands which left the marks upon her. She complained of
						a woman of the town, one Mrs. D&mdash;&mdash;y, and that she
						appeared to her, and once her mother struck at the place where the girl said
						she saw D&mdash;&mdash;y, and thereupon the girl cried out you have
						struck her upon the belly, and it was found that D&mdash;&mdash;y
						complained of a hurt in her belly about the same time. Another time the
						mother struck at a place where the girl said there was a yellow bird, and
						she then told her mother she had hit the side of its head, and it turned out
						that D. was hurt in the side of her head at that time.</p>

					<p>D. being with child, when the first blow was struck, took to her bed soon
						after and died, and, as soon as it was known, the girl was well.</p>

					<p>The next daughter, after her sister had succeeded so well, imitated her in
						complaining of D. and outdid her in her feats of running to the top of the
						barn where a man could not have got without danger, and pretended she was
						carried in the air; but, upon the news of D.&rsquo;s death, shewas well
						too. The youngest though but five years old attempted the same things, and
						in some instances went beyond her sisters; but she would not be well until a
						considerable time after D.&rsquo;s death.</p>

					<p>The second daughter really believed the first bewitched, by her being in
						ponds, upon trees, &amp;c.; but had the curiosity to try if she could
						not do the same things. The third, seeing tier sisters were pitied and
						tenderly used, was willing to share with them. The eldest, seeing the others
						following her, let them into the secret, and then they acted in concert.</p>

					<p>The neighbors in general agreed they were under an evil hand; some affirmed
						they had seen them flying, and it was pronounced a piece of witchcraft, as
						much as ever had been at Salem. Their parents were indulgent to them, and
						though some of the people were not without suspicion of fraud, yet no great
						pains were taken to detect them. Physicians were employed to no purpose, and
						ministers prayed over them without success.</p>

					<p>After the children altered their behavior, they all persisted in it that
						there had been no fraud; and, although the affair lay with great weight upon
						the conscience of the eldest, and she would sometimes say to her next sister
						they should one time or other be discovered and brought to shame, yet it
						remained a long time a secret. The eldest, not having been baptized, desired
						and obtained baptism; and being examined by the minister as to her conduct
						in this affair, she persisted in her declarations of innocency. Having
						removed to Medford, she offered to join to the church there, in 1728, and
						gave a satisfactory account of herself to the minister of the town, who knew
						nothing of the share she had in this transaction; but, the Lord&rsquo;s
						day before she was to be admitted, he happened to preach from this text,
						&ldquo;He that speaketh lies shall not escape.&rdquo; The woman
						supposed the sermon to be intended for her, and went to the minister to
						inquire. He informed her nobody had been with him to object anything against
						her; but she had then determined to make a full confession, and disclosed
						the matter to him, owning the whole and every part to be the fraud of her
						and her sisters, and desired to make the most public acknowledgment of it in
						the face of the church, which was done accordingly. They had gone so far in
						their complaints that they found it necessary to accuse somebody, and
						pitched upon this particular woman, D&mdash;&mdash;, having no
						former prejudice again &lpar;sic&rpar; her. The woman&rsquo;s
						complaints, at the same time the children pretended she was struck,
						proceeded from other causes which were not properly inquired into. Once they
						were in danger of being detected by their father in oue instance of their
						fraud; but the grounds of suspicion were overlooked or neglected through his
						prejudice and credulity in favor of his children.</p>

					<p>Gov. Hutchinson condensed the above statement from a manuscript prepared by
						Ebenezer Turell, minister of Medford, to whom the confession was made, which
						has since been printed in full in Mass. Hist. Coll. vol. xx. pp. 6-22.
						Though fully in the belief that there were fraud and deception in the
						actions of the Littleton children, Mr. Turell could not divest himself of
						the idea that there was also diabolical agency manifested in these
						transactions. &ldquo;I make no doubt.&rdquo; he says &lpar;p.
						I6&rpar;, &ldquo;but in this sinning Satan was very
						officious.&rdquo; Again &lpar;p. 19&rpar; he gives this
						excellent advice: &ldquo;Never use any of the Devil&rsquo;s
						legerdemain tricks. You only gratify Satan, and invite him into your company
						to deceive you.&rdquo; Persons who can accept the possibility of
						diabolical agency will find in Mr. Turell&rsquo;s narrative ample scope
						for the exercise of their belief. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n31">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[25]</seg>
					<p>Elisha Hutchinson, a merchant In Boston, and grandfather of the author. He
						was the grandson of Mrs. Ann Hutchinson, who was banished, in 1637, for her
						religious opinions. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n32">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[26]</seg>
					<p>William Perkins, 1558-1602, a Puritan divine, and Fellow of Christ College,
						Cambridge. Several editions of his works, in three volumes folio, appeared
						from 1605 to 1635. One of his papers was on Witchcraft, and was a standard
						and, for the times, a charitable authority. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n33">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[27]</seg>
					<p>Joseph Glanvil, 1636-1680. He was chaplain in ordinary to his Majesty, and
						Fellow of the Royal Society. The title of the work here mentioned is
						&ldquo;Saducismus Triumphatus : or Full and Plain Evidence concerning
						Witches and Apparitions: with a letter of Dr. Henry More on the same
						subject; and an authentic but wonderful Story of certain Swedish Witches;
						done into English by Anth. Horneck, Preacher at the Savoy.&rdquo;
						London, 1681. 8vo. 328 pp. Several later editions were issued. The story of
						the Swedish witchcrafts contained in this volume is mentioned by Increase
						Mather in Remarkable Providences, 1684, p. 132, ed. 1856, and by Cotton
						Mather in Wonders of the Invisible World, 1693, pp. 44, 88. Mr. C. W. Upham,
						supposing that C. Mather was the only person in New England, in 1692, who
						knew of this case, bases an argument upon it in Salem Witchcraft and Cotton
						Mather, 1869, pp. 34,35. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n34">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[28]</seg>
					<p>Joseph Keble, 1632-1716, Fellow of All-Saint&rsquo;s College and a legal
						writer of little modern reputation. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n35">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[29]</seg>
					<p>Michael Dalton, 1554-1620, an English lawyer, author of several legal works
						which were popular in their time. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n36">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[30]</seg>
					<p>Amy Duny and Rose Callender, &ldquo;two wrinkled old women,&rdquo;
						were tried and convicted before Sir Matthew Hale at Bury St. Edmunds, county
						of Suffolk, in 1664-5. The case is reported in Tryals of the Witches,
						London, 1682. The document is copied into Howell&rsquo;s State Trials,
						vol. vi. pp. 647-702, to which is prefixed Gov. Hutchinson&rsquo;s
						entire account of witchcraft in New-England. An abstract of the case is in
						Wonders of the Invisible World, pp. 55-60; and allusions to the same are
						found in nearly all subsequent treatises on witchcraft. It is perhaps the
						most noted case on record, as Sir Matthew Hale here sanctioned by his great
						name the admission of spectral evidence, and the dogma that the devil could
						act only through persons in league with him, that is, actual witches. In the
						Dowse Library is &ldquo;A Discourse concerning the great mercy of God in
						preserving us from the Power and Malice of Evil Angels; written by Sir
						Matthew Hale, at Cambridge 26 March 1661 &lsqb;1665&rsqb;, upon
						occasion of a Tryal of certain Witches before him the week before at St.
						Edmund&rsquo;s Bury.&rdquo; London, 1693. 4to. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n37">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[31]</seg>
					<p>1684. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n38">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[32]</seg>
					<p>Sir William Phips arrival at Boston, May 14, 1692. Increase Mather returned
						from his four years&rsquo; mission as colonial agent in England, in the
						same vessel. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n39">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[33]</seg>
					<p>The organization and commission of the court is given in note 44. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n40">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[34]</seg>
					<p>&ldquo;A gentleman of more than ordinary understanding, learning and
						experience, desired me to write to New-England about your trials and
						convictions of witches; not being satisfied with the evidence upon which
						some who have been executed were found guilty. He told me, that in the time
						of the great reformation parliament, a certain person or persons laid a
						commission to discover and prosecute witches. Upon these prosecutions many
						were executed, in at least one county in England, until, at length, a
						gentleman of estate and of great character for piety was accused, which put
						an end to the commission. And the judges upon a re-hearing, reversed many
						judgments; but many lives had been taken away. All that I speak with much
						wonder that any man, much less a man of such abilities, learning and
						experience as Mr. Stoughton, should take up a persuasion, that the devil
						cannot assume the likeness of an innocent, to afflict another person. In my
						opinion, it is a persuasion utterly destitute of any solid reason to render
						it so much as probable, and besides, contradictory to many instances of fact
						in history. If you think good, you may acquaint Mr. Stoughton and the other
						judges with what I write.&amp; Letter From London to I. Mather, Jan. 9,
						1692-3.&rdquo; P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n41">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[35]</seg>
					<p>Richard Hatheway, a blacksmith&rsquo;s apprentice, was tried before Chief
						Justice Holt, March 25, 1702, for imposture. He pretended to be bewitched by
						Sarah Morduck, and to be restored from his fits only by drawing blood from
						her by scratching. She had been tried for witchcraft by the same court the
						year before, and acquitted. He pretended to vomit pins, and to fast for ten
						weeks. &ldquo;All the devils in hell,&rdquo; said the chief Justice,
						&ldquo;could not have helped you fast so long.&rdquo; Pins were
						found in his pocket; and being closely watched, it was ascertained that he
						partook of food when he assumed to be fasting. Another woman was brought in
						while he was in his fits, and by scratching her he recovered as well as
						before. He was sentenced to imprisonment for one year, and to stand in the
						pillory three times. Rev. Francis Hutchinson states the case in Historical
						Essay concerning Witchcraft, London 2d edition, 1720, p. 280, and it appears
						in Wonders of the Invisible World, pp. 55 and 60. The case with the evidence
						and arguments is reported in Howell&rsquo;s State Trials, vol. xiv. pp.
						639&mdash;669. Hatheway&rsquo;s master and mistress who sustained
						the apprentice in these impostures, were next prosecuted for assault on
						Sarah Morduck and for riot; and their trial is reported in the same volume.</p>

					<p>Howell&rsquo;s State Trials contain full reports of other witchcraft
						proceedings, viz.: case of Mary Smith, 1616, vol. ii. p. 1050; Proceeding
						against the Essex Witches, 1645, vol. iv. p. 817; and Proceedings against
						three Devon Witches, 1682, vol. viii. p. 1018. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n42">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[36]</seg>
					<p>Eleven trials for witchcraft were held before chief justice Holt, front 1694
						to 1702, in which he so charged the juries that they generally brought in
						verdicts of acquittal. The English statutes for the punishment of
						witchcraft, however, were not repealed till 1736. 9 Geo. II. chap. 5,
						Statutes at Large, vol. xvii. p. 3. P. </p>
				</note>

				<note id="n43">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[37]</seg>
					<p>&ldquo;An Account of the Life and Character of Rev. Samuel Parris, of
						Salem village, and of his connection with the Witchcraft Delusion of 1692.
						By Samuel P. Fowler &lsqb;of Danvers&rsqb;&rdquo;
						&lpar;Salem, 1857, 20 pp. 8vo.&rpar;, is the fullest and most
						impartial estimate of Mr. Parris&rsquo;s character which has appeared in
						print. Deacon Fowler is an officer of the original church of Salem village,
						now Danvers; he has the best collection of witch books in New-England, and
						is one of the most experienced antiquaries of the Essex Institute. He
						dispels much of the misapprehension which has existed respecting this noted
						clergyman.</p>

					<p>Mr. Parris remained with his people for five years after these events, and in
						the midst of local disputes outside of the witchcraft tragedy. Mr. Fowler
						says &lpar;p. 19&rpar;, &ldquo;It seems there was always a
						majority of the parish in favor of Mr. Parris remaining with them; and there
						appears to have been a very general mistake with regard to his dismission
						from his people, they supposing that he was hastily driven away from the
						village; whereas he continued and maintained himself through a ministerial
						quarrel of five years, until he &ldquo;saw fit to discontinue it, when
						he informed his church of his intentions.&rdquo;</p>

					<p>Mr. Fowler&rsquo;s entire paper is reprinted in Mr. Drake&rsquo;s
						Witchcraft Delusion in New-England, vol. iii. pp, 198-221. The anonymous
						Ballad of 1692, Giles Corey and Goodwyfe Corey, which Mr. Drake reprints in
						the same volume &lpar;pp. 17.3-177&rpar;, and supposes Mr. J. G.
						Whittier to have been the author&mdash; &ldquo;as but one person
						could have written it &ldquo;&mdash;was contributed to a Salem
						newspaper, more than thirty years ago, by Mr. Fitch Poole, of Danvers, now
						librarian of the Peabody Institute in Peabody. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n44">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[38]</seg>
					<p>John Indian and his wife Tituba were slaves. In the mittimus to the
						jailkeeper at Boston, she is described as &ldquo;an Indian woman
						belonging to Samuel Parris of Salem village &rdquo;
						&lpar;Woodward&rsquo;s Records of Salem Witchcraft, vol. i. p.
						15.&rpar; Calef &lpar;p. 19&rpar; says, &ldquo;she lay in
						jail till sold for her foes.&rdquo; The Salem delusion had its origin in
						the fetichism practised by these two ignorant Spanish-African slaves, whom
						Mr. Parris probably obtained from the Barbadoes, where he was at one time in
						business. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n45">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[&sext;]</seg>
					<p>R. Calef. &lsqb;More Wonders, p. 91.&rsqb; H.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n46">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[&sext;]</seg>
					<p>Hale. &lsqb;Modest Inquiry, p. 25, ed. 1711.&rsqb; H.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n47">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[&sext;]</seg>
					<p>Calef. &lsqb;p, 92.&rsqb; H.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n48">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[39]</seg>
					<p>This statement is a mistake, and is changed in the final draft. Mr. Parris on
						no occasion was employed to examine the accused. At the request of the
						magistrates he took down the evidence, he being a rapid and accurate penman.
						On the occasion mentioned in the next paragraph, Danforth put the questions,
						and the record is, &ldquo;Mr. Parris being desired and appointed to
						write out the examination, did take the same, and also read it before the
						council in public.&rdquo; P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n49">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[40]</seg>
					<p>This was a meeting of the council for a preliminary examination, and not
						&ldquo;a court&rdquo; for the trial of the accused. Danforth, deputy
						governor; Addington, secrctary, and Russell, Hathorne, Appleton, Sewall and
						Corwin, members of the council, were present. It was the only examination
						that Samuel Sewall attended. On his return to Boston he made this entry in
						his diary: &ldquo;April 11. 1692. Went to Salem, where, in the meeting
						house, the persons accused of witchcraft were examined; was a very great
						assembly; &lsquo;twas awful to see how the afflicted were
						agitated.&rdquo; At a later date lie inserted in the margin,
						&ldquo;Vae, vae, vae.&rdquo; These words have been taken by a late
						writer &ldquo;as expressions of much sensibility at the extent to which
						he had been misled. &ldquo;He did in later years regret, and well he
						might, the course he took in the witchcraft trials; but he never expressed,
						as the writer does, his disbelief in the reality of diabolical agency as
						exhibited at that examination. The occasion itself was mournful enough to
						draw forth these exclamations from one holding his opinions; and hence they
						are explained without a forced interpretation. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n50">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[41]</seg>
					<p>The maid here alluded to was Mary Warren, one of the most violent of the
						accusing girls. She was a domestic in Proctor&rsquo;s family. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n51">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[42]</seg>
					<p>The documents which Gov. Hutchinson printed belong with the court files at
						Salem, which have been very carefully arranged and mounted by Mr. William P.
						Upham. These papers, or such of them as remain, were printed &lpar;with
						many errors&rpar; by Mr. W. E. Woodward, in Records of Salem Witchcraft,
						Roxbury, 1865, 2 vols. sm. 4to. Among these the papers which Gov. Hutchinson
						printed do not appear. They were doubtless borrowed by him, and never
						returned. In the Massachusetts archives is a volume of witchcraft papers
						&lpar;vol. cxxxv.&rpar;, but these documents are not among them.</p>

					<p>In 1860, Mr. N. I. Bowditch presented a collection of original papers
						relating to Salem witchcraft, which once belonged to the Salem court files,
						to the Massachusetts Historical Society. More than sixty years ago these
						papers came into possession of the late Hon. John Pickering; who, says Mr.
						Bowditch, &ldquo;as he was a sworn officer of the court, had some
						scruples of conscience about retaining them himself; and therefore, after
						examining them, gave them to my lute father &lsqb;Dr. Nathaniel
						Bowditch&rsqb;. &lpar;Proceedings, 1860-62, p.
						31.&rpar;&rdquo; The collection has been arranged and elegantly
						bound at the expense of Mr. Bowditch. The volume does not contain the papers
						printed by Gov. Hutchinson, As Gov. Hutchinson printed only portions of
						these papers, and doubtless took others which he did not print, it is a
						matter of some historical interest to know the present location &lpar;if
						they exist&rpar; of the original papers which he used. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n52">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[&sext;]</seg>
					<p>It is can in the examination, but, I suppose, by the answer, should have been
						wrote can&rsquo;t. H.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n53">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[&sext;]</seg>
					<p>Mr. Perkins mentions eight or ten proofs of witchcraft, two only of which he
						supposes sufficient, viz.: the testimony of two witnesses and the confession
						of the party. This authority probably had weight with the court as well as
						with Mr. Hale; but Perkins says it is objected to the latter that a
						confession may be urged by force or threatening, &amp;c., or by a
						persuasion that it is the best course to save life or obtain liberty. H.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n54">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[&sext;]</seg>
					<p>&lsqb;Note in final draft.&rsqb; Mr. Deane, one of the ministers of
						Andover then near fourscore, seems to have been in danger. He is tenderly
						touched in several of the examinations, which might be owing to a fair
						character, and he may be one of the persons accused, who caused a
						discouragement to further prosecutions. Deliverance Deane being asked why
						she and the rest brought in Mr. Deane as afflicting persons, she answered,
						it was Satan&rsquo;s subtilty, for he told her he would put a sham upon
						all these things, and make people believe that he did afflict. She said Mrs.
						Osgood and she gave their consent the devil should bring Mr.
						Deane&rsquo;s shape to afflict. Being asked again if Mrs. Osgood and she
						acted this business, she said yes.&rdquo; Mr. Deane was much beholden to
						this woman. H.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n55">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[43]</seg>
					<p>Mr. Cary&rsquo;s account is in Calef, pp. 91-99.</p>

					<p>All my references to C. Mather&rsquo;s Wonders of the Invisible World,
						and to Calef, are to the London editions of 1693 and 1700. Mr. S. G. Drake
						reprints both works in his Witchcraft Delusion in New England
						&lpar;Roxbury, 1866, 3 vols. sm. 4to&rpar;, with the original
						paging. This is the best reprint of these noted books. An excellent and
						inexpensive edition of the &ldquo;Wonders&rdquo; appeared in J.
						Russell Smith&rsquo;s Library of Old Authors &lpar;London, 1862,
						16mo., in which the original paging is not indicated. This edition is
						especially desirable as it contains reprints of A Further Arrival of the
						Tryals of The New England Witches, 1693, and Cases of Conscience Concerning
						Evil Spirits personating Men, 1693, both by Increase Mather. There are
						several other reprints of the Wonders and of Calef&rsquo;s More Wonders;
						but they are carelessly done, and are not reliable for historical purposes.
						A copy &lpar;with one leaf missing&rpar; of the original Wonders
						&lpar;Boston 1692&rpar;, brought two hundred and ninety dollars at
						the Woodward auction sale in New-York, April 19, &mdash;. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n56">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[44]</seg>
					<p>See Calef, pp. 96-100. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n57">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[45]</seg>
					<p>The jails of Boston and Ipswich were filled, as well as that of Salem. Many
						of the accused were heads of families; the season for putting in crops was
						far advanced, and farm labor had been interrupted. &ldquo;Upon
						consideration,&rdquo; say the records of the Council for May 27, 1692,
						&ldquo;that there are many criminal offenders now in custody, some
						whereof have lain long, and many inconveniences attending the thronging of
						the gaols at this hot season of the year, there being no judicatories or
						courts of justice yet established: Ordered, That a special commission of
						Oyer and Terminer be made out to William Stoughton, John Richards, Nathaniel
						Salstonstall, Wait Winthrop, Bartholomew Gidney, Samuel Sewall, John
						Hathorne, Jonathan Corwin and Peter Sergent, Esquires, assigning them to be
						justices, or any five of them &lpar;whereof William Stoughton, John
						Richards and Bartholomew Gidney Esq&rsquo;s to be one&rpar; to
						inquire or hear and determine for this time, according to the law and custom
						of England and of this their Magesties&rsquo; Province, all and all
						manner of crimes and offences had, made, done, or perpetrated within the
						counties of Suffolk, Essex, Midddlesex, and each of them.&rdquo; George
						Corwin was the sheriff, and Geo. Herrick, marshal. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n58">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[46]</seg>
					<p>The testimony and other papers, in the case of Bridget Bishop, are in Records
						of Salem Witchcraft, Vol. 1, pp 131-172; Wonders of the Invisible World,
						pp.66-70; and Calef&rsquo;s More Wonders, pp. 119-126. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n59">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[47]</seg>
					<p>Gov. Hutchinson found this document in the Postscript of Increase
						Mather&rsquo;s Cases of Conscience 1693. His copy, in the early draft,
						is quite correct, except that the concluding words of the fifth section
						&ldquo;consulted in such a case&rdquo; were accidentally omitted. In
						making his final draft he probably noticed that the sentence was incomplete,
						and instead of recurring to the original authority, supplied words of his
						own: &ldquo;may be observed.&rdquo; This, and similar facts, show
						that he made little use of original authorities in preparing his final
						draft. In his last copy of this document, and in printing ten errors were
						made in words and transpositions, but one of which appear in the early
						draft. The most important error was defeat for detect in the second section.
						P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n60">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[48]</seg>
					<p>Richard Bernard, 1566-1651, a famous Puritan minister at Batcomb in Somerset.
						His Guide to Grand Jury&ndash;men in cases of Witchcraft
						&lpar;London, 1627&rpar;, says Increase Mather, &ldquo;is a
						solid and wise treatise. As for the judgment of the elders in New-England,
						so far as I can learn, they do generally concur with Mr. Perkins and Mr.
						Bernard.&rdquo; &lpar;Cases of Conscience, pp. 252-3, ed.
						1862.&rpar; P. </p>
				</note>

				<note id="n61">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[49]</seg>
					<p>Gov. Hutchinson omitted this paragraph when he prepared his next and final
						draft, which was a judicious proceeding. The above is a view of the document
						which may occur to a reader on a first and superficial examination; and it
						has been claimed by a late writer that &ldquo;the paper is so worded as
						to mislead.&rdquo; The paper was drawn by Cotton Mather; and was
						&ldquo;concurringly presented before his Excellency and Council by
						twelve ministers&rdquo; of Boston and the vicinity. &lpar;Cases of
						Conscience, Postscript.&rpar; Those twelve men knew the meaning of
						language; and it is hardly possible to believe that they would concur, at
						that solemn period, in a series of recommendations to the public authorities
						which carried a contradiction, if not a fraud, on the face of the document.
						Hutchinson&rsquo;s omission of the passage may be regarded as a
						retraction of his first impressions, resulting front further investigation.
						The advice, in my opinion, is wholly consistent; but this is not the place
						to discuss the point. I propose to do this on some other occasion. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n62">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[50]</seg>
					<p>This statement shows that Hutchinson had not seen the records of the council,
						a copy of which was made in the British State Paper office in 1846, and is
						now in the office of the Secretary of the State of Massachusetts. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n63">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[51]</seg>
					<p>Erroneously printed &ldquo;Wilder.&rdquo; The trials of Susannah
						Martin and Elizabeth How are in Records of Salem Witchcraft, vol. i.
						193-215, and vol. ii. pp. 69-93; Mather&rsquo;s Wonders, pp. 70-80,
						which, with the trials of Bishop, Burroughs and Carrier, were copied by
						Calef, pp. 114-139. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n64">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[&sext;]</seg>
					<p>Calef. H.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n65">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[&sext;]</seg>
					<p>Calef. H.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n66">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[52]</seg>
					<p>Samuel Sewall, one of the judges in the witchcraft trials, made; on this
						occasion, the following entry in his Diary&mdash;for the use of which I
						am indebted to the courtesy of the Massachusetts Historical Society:
						&ldquo;Monday, Sept. 19, 1692. About noon, at Salem, Giles Corey was
						pressed to death for standing mute; much pains was used with him two days,
						one after another, by the court and Capt. Gardner of Nantucket, who had been
						his acquaintance; but all in vain. Sept. 20. Now I hear from Salem, that
						about eighteen years ago, he was suspected to have stamped and pressed a man
						to death; but was cleared. &rsquo;Twas not remembered till Ann Putnam
						was told of it by said Corey&rsquo;s specter, the sabbath-day night
						before the execution.&rdquo;</p>

					<p>The following touching relation of the sufferings of the Corey family during
						the year 1692, is in Mass. Archives, vol. cxxxv. fol. 161. For the purpose
						of preserving the quaintness of the original document, I have copied it
						verbatim.</p>

					<p>&ldquo;To the Honrable Commite Apointed by the Generall Court to make
						enquire with Respect to the Suferings in The year 1692 &amp;c</p>

					<p>&ldquo;these are to giue you a Short Acount of our Sorrows and Suferings
						which was in the yere 1692 Some time in march our honerd father and mother
						Giles Corey &amp; martha his wife ware acused for Suposed wichcraft and
						imprisoncd and ware Remoued from on prison to another as from Salem to
						ipswitch &amp; from ipswitch to Boston and from Boston to Salem againe
						and soe remained in close imprisonment about four months we ware att the
						whole Charge of their maintainance which was very chargable and soe much the
						more being soe farr adistant from us as also by Reason of soe many remoues
						in all which we could doe not less then Acompanie them which further added
						both to our trouble and Charge and although that was very Great in the least
						of our greavence or cause of These lines but that which breakes our harts
						and for which wee goe mourning still is that our father was put to soe
						cruell a death as being prest to death our mother was put to death also
						though in another way And we Cannot Sufficiantly exspress our Griffe for the
						loss of our father and mother in such away Soe we Cannot Compute our
						exspences and coast but shall Comite to your wisdome to iudge of but after
						our fathers death the Shirfe thretend to size our fathers estate and for
						feare tharof we Complied with him and paid him eleuen pound six shillings in
						monie by which we have bee&lsqb;n&rsqb; greaty damnified &amp;
						impouerishd by being exposed to sell Creaturs and other things for litle
						more then half the worth of them to get the monie to pay as aforesd and to
						maintain our father &amp; mother in prison but that which is grieueous
						to us is that wee are not only impouerished but also Reproached and soe may
						bee for all genaratians and that wrongfully tow unless something bee done
						fore the remoueall thearof all which we humbly Commute to the honarable
						Court Praying God to direct to that which may be axceptable in his Sight and
						for the good of this land</p>

					<p>&ldquo;We Cannot Judge our necessary Expense to be less than Ten pounds</p>

					<p>&ldquo;September the 13th 1710</p>

					<p>Wee Subscrib your humbl Searuants in all Christian obedeance</p>

					<p>JOHN MOULTON who mared Elizabeth Corey daughtr of the abovesd in the behalf
						of the reast of that familie&rdquo; P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n67">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[53]</seg>
					<p>The author has already stated that the court chiefly relied on the decisions
						of Sir Matthew Hale, and &ldquo;the authorities of Keble, Dalton and
						other lawyers of note who lay down rules of conviction as absurd as any ever
						adopted in New-England.&rdquo; These illegal methods of procedure the
						judges certainly did not receive from the clergy, or from Perkins and
						Bernard, the clerical authorities recommended to them. Lord Campbell brings
						similar charges against Sir Matthew Hale, in connection with the Bury St.
						Edmund&rsquo;s trial. He says, &ldquo;he violated the plainest rules
						of justice, and really was the murderer of two innocent women. . . . . . I
						would very readily have pardoned him for an undoubted belief in witchcraft,
						and I should have considered that this belief detracted little from his
						character for discernment and humanity. . . . . . There not only was no
						evidence against them which ought to have weighed in the mind of any
						reasonable man who believed in witchcraft; but during the trial the
						imposture practised by the prosecutors was detected and exposed. The
						enormous violation of justice then perpetrated has become more revolting as
						the mists of ignorance which partly covered it, have been
						dispersed.&rdquo; &lpar;Lives of theChief Justices, vol. i. p. 561,
						563.&rpar; P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n68">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[54]</seg>
					<p>The colony law against witchcraft was re-enacted October 29, 1692. The
						statute of King James I. was passed December 14, and published two days
						later. Both were disallowed by the Privy Council, Aug. 22, 1695; the latter
						for &ldquo;being not found to agree with the statute of King James I.,
						whereby the dower is saved to the widow, and the inheritance to the heir of
						the party convicted.&rdquo; &lpar;Province Laws, 1869, vol. i. pp.
						55, 91.&rpar; P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n69">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[55]</seg>
					<p>The law was passed Nov. 25. December 7, William Stoughton was elected chief
						justice &lpar;receiving every vote present&rpar;, and Thomas
						Danforth, John Richards, Wait Winthrop and Samuel Sewall, receiving only
						majorities as associate judges. December 22, they received their
						commissions.</p>

					<p>Gov. Hutchinson states that the colony law against witchcraft was revived by
						the first act of the Provincial Assembly, passed June 15, and published June
						28, 1692, providing &ldquo;That all the local laws of Massachusetts Bay
						and New Plymouth, being not repugnant to the laws of England, do remain in
						full force, until the 10 day of November next.&rdquo; As the charges
						alleged in the witchcraft trials were committed, and proceedings instituted,
						before June 28, and the special court was instructed, May 27, to proceed
						under English law and custom, it is probable that the court tried and
						executed every one of its victims under English law, the statute of James I.
						Trials were held after the old colony law was re-enacted; but no persons
						were executed after September 22, 1692. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n70">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[56]</seg>
					<p>Nathaniel Saltonstall, of Haverhill, was also under suspicion. Judge Sewall,
						March 3, 1692-3, wrote to him a letter expressing disbelief in such reports,
						and sympathy for him and his family. The letter is in Judge
						Sewall&rsquo;s Diary under that date. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n71">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[&sext;]</seg>
					<p>&ldquo;As to what you mention, concerning that poor creature in your town
						that is afflicted, and mentioned my name to yourself and son, I return you
						hearty thanks for your Intimation about it, and for your charity therein
						mentioned; and I have great cause to bless God, who, of his mercy hitherto,
						hath not left me to fall into such an horrid evil.&rdquo; Extract from
						letter &lsqb;of Secretary Allen&rsqb; to I. Mather, Hartford, 18
						March, 92&lsqb;-3&rsqb;. H.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n72">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[57]</seg>
					<p>It is singular that Gov. Hutchinson did not give the date of this confession,
						which is noted in Calef. In this manuscript he says, &ldquo;sometime
						after.&rdquo; In the final draft he says, &ldquo;it was not long,
						before one of the judges was sensible of his error.&rdquo; The
						confession was made January 14, 1696-7, nearly five years after the error
						was committed to which he alludes. Up to this time, he gave little or no
						evidence of contrition in his Diary. He was now under deep domestic
						affliction. Of his thirteen children he had lost eight. On the 25th of
						December, 1696, he buried his little Sarah, two years old, and on the 22d of
						May previous an infant son. His Diary shows that his mind was in a state of
						abject despondency. After the religious type of the period he regarded these
						repeated strokes of Divine Providence as brought upon him by his own
						unworthiness. On the 11th of January, three days before the appointed first,
						he writes, &ldquo;God helped me to pray more than ordinarily, that he
						would make up our loss in the burial of our little daughter and other
						children, and that &lsqb;he&rsqb; would give us a child to serve
						him, pleading with him as the Institutor of marriage, and the author of
						every good work.&rdquo;</p>

					<p>Calef &lpar;p. 144&rpar; gives an abstract from memory of Judge
						Sewall&rsquo;s confession; and Dr. Abiel Holmes, who had seen the Diary,
						gives, in American Annals &lpar;vol. ii. p. 9&rpar;, a brief
						extract. The following, copied, by permission, from his original Diary now
						in possession of the Massachusetts Historical Society, is the paper entire:</p>

					<p>&rdquo;Copy of the Bill I put up on the Fast Day, giving it to Mr.
						Willard as he passed by, and standing up at the reading of it, and bowing
						when finished, in the afternoon.</p>

					<p>&rdquo;Samuel Sewall, sensible of the reiterated strokes of God upon
						himself and family; and being sensible, that as to the guilt contracted upon
						the opening of the late Commission of Oyer and Terminer, at Salem
						&lpar;to which the order of this day relates&rpar;, he is, upon many
						accounts, more concerned than any that he knows of, desires to take the
						blame and shame of it; asking pardon of men, and especially desiring prayers
						that God, who has an unlimited authority, would pardon that sin, and all
						other his sins, personal and relative: and according to his infinite
						benignity and sovereignty, not visit the sin of him, or of any other, upon
						himself or any of his, nor upon the land: but that he would powerfully
						defend him against all temptations to sin, for the future; and vouchsafe him
						the efficacious, saving conduct of his word and spirit.&rdquo;</p>

					<p>The following entry is the first indication I find in his diary, of
						sensitiveness or compunction for the part he took in the witchcraft trials.
						It was made December 24, 1696, while his little Sarah lay dead in his house:
						&ldquo;Sam &lsqb;his son&rsqb; recites to me, in Latin, Matthew
						xii. from the 6th to the end of the 12th verse. The 7th verse &lsqb;Quod
						si nossetis quid sit misericordiam volo, et non sacrificium, non
						condemnassetis inculpabiles&rsqb; did awfully bring to mind the Salem
						tragedy.&rdquo;</p>

					<p>The entire confession of Judge Sewall, its date and attending circumstances,
						will correct erroneous impressions concerning it. The subject matter
						confessed covers but one point: &ldquo;the guilt contracted upon the
						opening of the late commission of Oyer and Terminer at Salem.&rdquo; The
						court was opened June 2, 1692. We cannot be in doubt as to the nature of the
						guilt then contracted. It was the adoption of a rule of the court, by which
						the records made, and depositions received, at the preliminary examinations
						&lpar;which consisted almost wholly of spectral evidence&rpar;, were
						introduced, sworn to, and received as legal testimony in the trials of the
						accused. Out of this rule, which was wholly illegal, grew all the fatal
						results of the Salem trials. Judge Sewall was a parishioner of Samuel
						Willard, of the Old South Church in Boston, who regarded such evidence as
						the &ldquo;Devil&rsquo;s testimony&rdquo;; and whose judicious
						conduct during the trials is worthy of the highest commendation. He was the
						intimate friend of Increase and Cotton Mather, who both held similar views.
						Three days before &lpar;March 31&rpar;, Cotton Mather had written to
						John Riclaards, one of the judges, cautioning him against the use of
						spectral testimony. The letter, although addressed to his own parishioner,
						was doubtless intended for, and considered by, the whole court, and is
						called, by himself and his son, the &ldquo;letter to the
						judges.&rdquo; The letter says: &ldquo;If mankind have thus far once
						consented unto the credit of diabolical representations, the door is opened
						for the devils to obtain, from the courts in the invisible world, a license
						to proceed unto most hideous desolations upon the repute and repose of such
						as have been kept from the great transgression. Perhaps there are wise and
						good men, that may be ready to style him that shall advance this caution, a
						witch advocate; but, in the winding up, this caution will certainly he
						wished for.&rdquo; &lpar;Mass. Soc.&rsquo;s Hist. Coll.,
						xxxviii. p. 393.&rpar; In the face of such influences and associations
						Judge Sewall gave his voice in the court for legalizing spectral testimony!</p>

					<p>But for his confession we might never have known the position of Judge Sewall
						on the matter of spectral evidence, then the great question of debate in the
						Province; or have surmised the position of his three Boston associates,
						Richards, Winthrop and Sergeant. Saltonstall, living in Haverhill, did not
						attend the sittings of the court. The views of chief justice Stoughton in
						favor of admitting spectral testimony are well known; and those of the three
						Salem members of the commission, Hathorne, Corwin and Gedney, we have before
						us in the records of their examinations, than which nothing more atrocious
						can be imagined. If the four Boston members had stood out against the views
						of Stoughton and the Salem members, there had been a tie in the commission.
						Judge Sewall says, that, in the guilt. contracted, &ldquo;he is, upon
						many accounts, more concerned than any that he knows of.&rdquo; How can
						this be? Was it a morbid utterance of has desponding mind; or has it an
						historical significance? He was not at the head of the court, nor its most
						influential member. Nothing appears to show that he was zealous, as
						Stoughton was, on this point. The remark would be explained, if he alone, of
						the Boston judges, went over to Stoughton's views; and, by a majority vote,
						fixed the policy of the court. I know of no evidence outside the confession
						to sustain this hypothesis; and it is here thrown out only for the purpose
						of eliciting further information as to the position of the other three
						Boston judges. Brattle intimates that the members of the court were not a
						unit in their views. He says, &ldquo;But although the chief judge and
						some of the other judges be very zealous in these proceedings,&rdquo;
						&amp;c. I have seen no evidence that Richards, Winthrop, or Sergeant,
						after the policy of the court was fixed, did not sustain the action of their
						associates. The two theories respecting diabolical agency, which were then
						the subject of debate, I have treated at some length in North American
						Review, vol. cvii. pp. 337-397. P.</p>
				</note>

				<note id="n73">
					<seg type="note-symbol">[58]</seg>
					<p>October 17, 1711, the General Court passed an act reversing &ldquo;the
						several convictions, judgments, and attainders against the&rdquo;
						persons executed, and several who were condemned but not executed, and
						declaring that to be null and void. In December of the same years,
						&pound;578. 12s. were appropriated to pay the damages sustained by
						persons prosecuted for witchcraft in 1692. The act reversing the attainder
						shows that the popular belief in the diabolical nature of the witchcraft
						troubles had not abated twenty years after those events transpired. The act
						is in Records of Salem Witchcraft, vol. ii. pp. 216-218. It commences thus:
						&ldquo;Forasmuch as in the year of our Lord 1692, two severall towns
						within this Province were infested with a horrible witchcraft, or possession
						of devils,&rdquo; &amp;c. &ldquo;The influence and energy of the
						evil spirits so great at that time acting in and upon those who were the
						principal accusers and witnesses;&rdquo; and that &ldquo;some of the
						principal accusers and witnesses in those dark and severe prosecutions have
						since discovered themselves to be persons of profligate and vicious
						conversation&rdquo;&mdash;were the reasons assigned for the reversal
						of the attainder.</p>

					<p>As showing Gov. Hutchinson&rsquo;s latest opinions on the question,
						whether the manifestations at Salem village were wholly the result of fraud
						and imposture, I append a supplementary paragraph with which he closes the
						narrative in his final draft.</p>

					<p>&rdquo;The opinion which prevailed in New-England for many years after
						this tragedy, that there was something preternatural in it, and that it was
						not all the effect of fraud and imposture, proceeded from the reluctance in
						human nature to reject errors once imbibed. As the principal actors went off
						the stage this opinion was gradually lessened; but perhaps it was owing to a
						respect to the memory of their immediate ancestor, that many do not seem to
						be fully convinced. There are a great number of persons who are willing to
						suppose the accusers to have been under bodily disorders which affected
						their imaginations. This is kind and charitable, but seems to be winking the
						truth out of sight. A little attention must force conviction that the whole
						was a scene of fraud and imposture begun by young girls, who at first,
						perhaps, thought of nothing more than being pitied and indulged, and
						continued by adult persons who were afraid of being accused themselves. The
						one and the other, rather than confess their fraud, suffered the lives of so
						many innocents to be taken away through the credulity of judges and
						juries.&rdquo; P.</p>
				</note>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
