<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="JewDeco"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="JewDeco">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Decoration Day</title>
<title type="sort">decoration day</title>
<author>Jewett, Sarah Orne</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">33</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">JewDeco</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476111</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Dialogue in dialect. A few examples of spelling variations are "'"
for the final "g", "Scriptur'", "hosses" for "horses," "figgers"
for "figures," "holt" for "hold,""s'pose," "yaller," "Car'lina," "nowheres,
"sperit" for "spirit," "knowed" for "knew" "tain't," "Twa'n't," "divil,"
"'em" for "them," and innumerable ellipses,e.g. "'nother" for
"another," "Dan'l," "ag'inst," "han'ful," "a'ready."</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Decoration Day</title>
<title type="sort">decoration day</title>
<author>Sarah Orne Jewett</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harper &amp; Brothers, Publishers</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York: Franklin Square</pubPlace>
<date value="1892-06">June, 1892</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Harper's New Monthly Magazine</hi>
</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Vol LXXXV (June, 1892): 84-90.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center
scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of
the text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in
AusEmma1 for page one of  Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1892-06">June, 1892</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-12">December, 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Bryson Clevenger, Jr.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Minimal TEI tagging, TEI header, Spellchecking against print
version</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head>Jewett, Sarah Orne.  "Decoration Day." <lb/><hi rend="italic">Harper's New Monthly
Magazine</hi> 85 (June 1892): 84-90.</head>
<pb n="84"/>
<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d4">
<head>I.</head>
<p>
A WEEK before the 30th of May, three friends &mdash; John Stover and Henry
Merrill and Asa Brown &mdash; happened to meet on Saturday evening at
Barton's store at the Plains.  They were enjoying this idle hour
after a busy week.  After long easterly rains, the sun had at last
come out bright and clear, and all the Barlow farmers had been
planting.  There was even a good deal of ploughing left to be done,
the season was so backward.
</p><p> The three middle-aged men were old friends.  They had been
school-fellows, and when they were hardly out of their boyhood the
war came on, and they enlisted in the same company, on the same
day, and happened to march away elbow to elbow.  Then came the
great experience of a great war, and the years that followed their
return from the South had come to each almost alike.  They might
have been members of the same rustic household, they knew each
other's history so well.
</p><p> They were sitting on a low wooden bench at the left of the
store door as you went in.  People were coming and going on their
Saturday night errands &mdash; the post-office was in Barton's store &mdash; but
the friends talked on eagerly, without interrupting themselves,
except by an occasional nod of recognition.  They appeared to take
no notice at all of the neighbors whom they saw oftenest.  It was
a most beautiful evening; the two great elms were almost half in
leaf over the blacksmith shop which stood across the wide road.
Farther along were two small old-fashioned houses and the old white
church, with its pretty belfry of four arched sides and a tiny dome
at the top.  The large cockerel on the vane was pointing a little
south of west, and there was still light enough to make it shine
bravely against the deep blue eastern sky.  On the western side of
the road, near the store, were the parsonage and the storekeeper's
modern house, which had a French roof and some attempt at
decoration, which the long-established Barlow people called
gingerbread-work, and regarded with mingled pride and disdain.
These buildings made the tiny village called Barlow Plains.  They
stood in the middle of a long narrow strip of level ground.  They
were islanded by green fields and pastures.  There were hills
beyond; the mountains themselves seemed very near.  Scattered about
on the hill slopes were farm-houses, which stood so far apart, with
their clusters of out-buildings, that each looked lonely, and the
pine woods above seemed to besiege them all.  It was lighter on the
uplands than it was in the valley where the three men sat on their
bench, with their backs to the store and the western sky.
</p><p> "Well, here we be 'most into June, an' <pb n="85"/>
I ain't got a bush bean aboveground," lamented Henry Merrill.
</p><p> "Your land's always late, ain't it?  But you always catch
up with the rest on us," Asa Brown consoled him.  "I've often
observed that your land, though early planted, is late to sprout.
I view it there's a good week's difference betwixt me an' Stover
an' your folks, but come 1st o' July we all even up."
</p><p> "'Tis just so," said John Stover, taking his pipe out of
his mouth, as if he had a good deal more to say, and then replacing
it, as if he had changed his mind.
</p><p> "Made it extry hard having that long wet spell.  Can't none
on us take no day off this season," said Asa Brown; but nobody
thought it worth his while to respond to such evident truth.
</p><p> "Next Saturday'll be the 30th o' May &mdash; that's Decoration
day, ain't it? &mdash; come round again.  Lord! how the years slip by
after you git to be forty-five an' along there!" said Asa again.
"I s'pose some o' our folks'll go over to Alton to see the
procession, same's usual.  I've got to git one o' them small flags
to stick on our Joel's grave, an' Mis' Dexter always counts on
havin' some for Harrison's lot.  I calculate to get 'em somehow.
I must make time to ride over, but I don't know where the time's
comin' from out o' next week.  I wish the women folks would tend to
them things.  There's the spot where Eb Munson an' John Tighe lays
in the poor-farm lot, an' I did mean certain to buy flags for 'em
last year an' year before, but I went an' forgot it.  I'd like to
have folks that rode by notice 'em for once, if they was town
paupers.  Eb Munson was as darin' a man as ever stepped out to tuck
o' drum."
</p><p> "So he was," said John Stover, taking out his pipe with
decision and knocking out the ashes.  "Drink was his ruin; but I
wa'n't one that could be harsh with Eb, no matter what he done.  He
worked hard long's he could, too; but he wa'n't a like a sound man,
an' I think he took somethin' first not so much 'cause he loved it,
but to kind of keep his strength up so's he could work, an' then,
all of a sudden, rum clinched with him an' threw him.  Eb was
talkin' 'long o' me one day when he was about half full, an' says
he, right out, 'I wouldn't have fell to this state,' says he, 'if
I'd had me a home an' a little fam'ly; but it don't make no
difference to nobody, and it's the best comfort I seem to have, an'
I ain't goin' to do without it.  I'm ailin' all the time,' says he,
'an' if I keep middlin' full, I make out to hold my own an' to keep
along o' my work.'  I pitied Eb.  I says to him, 'You ain't goin'
to bring no shame on us old army boys, be you, Eb?  An' he says no,
he wa'n't.  I think if he'd lived to get one o' them big fat
pensions, he'd had it easier.  Eight dollars a month paid his
board, while he'd pick up what cheap work he could, an' then he got
so that decent folks didn't seem to want the bother of him, an' so
he come on the town."
</p><p> "There was somethin' else to it," said Henry Merrill,
soberly.  "Drink come natural to him, 'twas born in him, I expect,
an' there wa'n't nobody that could turn the divil out same's they
did in Scriptur'.  His father an' his gran'father was drinkin' men;
but they was kind-hearted an' good neighbors, an' never set out to
wrong nobody.  'Twas the custom to drink in their day; folks was
colder an' lived poorer in early times, an' that's how most of 'em
kept a-goin'.  But what stove Eb all up was his disapp'intment with
Marthy Peck &mdash; her forsakin' of him an' marryin' old John Down whilst
Eb was off to war.  I've always laid it up ag'inst her."
</p><p> "So've I," said Asa Brown.  "She didn't use the poor fellow
right.  I guess she was full as well off, but it's one thing to
show judgment, an' another thing to have heart."
</p><p> There was a long pause; the subject was too familiar to
need further comment.
</p><p> "There ain't no public sperit here in Barlow," announced
Asa Brown, with decision.  "I don't s'pose we could ever get up
anything for Decoration day.  I've felt kind of 'shamed, but it
always comes in a busy time; 'twa'n't no time to have it, anyway,
right in late plantin'."
</p><p> "'Tain't no use to look for public sperit 'less you've got
some yourself," observed John Stover, soberly; but something had
pleased him in the discouraged suggestion.  "Perhaps we could mark
the day this year.  It comes on a Saturday; that ain't nigh so bad
as bein' in the middle of the week."
</p><p> Nobody made any answer, and presently he went on:
</p><p> "There was a time along back when folks was too near the
war-time to give much thought to the bigness of it.  The
<pb n="86"/>  best fellows was them that had staid to home an'
worked their trades an' laid up money; but I don't know 's it's so
now."
</p><p> "Yes, the fellows that staid at home got all the fat
places, an' when we come back we felt dreadful behind the times,"
grumbled Asa Brown.  "I remember how 'twas."
</p><p> "They begun to call us hero an' old stick-in-the-mud just
about the same time," resumed Stover, with a chuckle.  "We wa'n't
no hand for strippin' woodland nor tradin' hosses them first few
years.  I don' know why 'twas we were so beat out.  The best most
on us could do was to sag right on to the old folks.  Father he
never wanted me to go to the war &mdash; 'twas partly his Quaker breed &mdash;
an' he used to be dreadful mortified with the way I hung round down
here to the store an' loafed round a-talkin' about when I was out
South, an' arguin' with folks that didn't know nothin' about what
the generals done.  There!  I see me now just as he see me then;
but after I had my boy strut out, I took holt o' the old farm 'long
o' father, an' I've made it bounce.  Look at them old meadows an'
see the herds' grass that come off of 'em last year!  I ain't
ashamed o' my place, if I did go to the war."
</p><p> "It all looks a sight bigger to me now than it did then,"
said Henry Merrill.  "Our goin' to the war I refer to.  We didn't
sense it no more than other folks did.  I used to be sick o'
hearin' their stuff about patriotism an' lovin' your country, an'
them pieces o' poetry women-folks wrote for the papers on the old
flag, an' our fallen heroes, an' them things; they didn't seem to
strike me in the right place; but I tell ye it kind o' starts me
now every time I come on the flag sudden &mdash; it does so.  A spell ago--'long in the fall, I guess it was &mdash; I was over to Alton tradin',
an' there was a fire company paradin'.  They'd got a prize at a
fair, an' had just come home on the cars, an' I heard the band; so
I stepped to the front o' the store where me an' my woman was, an'
the company felt well, an' was comin' along the street 'most as
good as troops.  I see the old flag a-comin', kind of blowin' back,
an' it went all over me.  Somethin' worked round in my throat; I
vow I come near cryin'.  I was glad nobody see me."
</p><p> "I'd go to war again in a minute," declared Stover, after
an expressive pause; "but I expect we should know better what we
was about.  I don' know but we've got too many rooted opinions now
to make us the best o' soldiers."
</p><p> "Martin Tighe an' John Tighe was considerable older than
the rest, and they done well," answered Henry Merrill, quickly.
"We three was the youngest of any, but we did think at the time we
knew the most."
</p><p> "Well, whatever you may say, that war give the country a
great start," said Asa Brown.  "I tell ye we just begin to see the
scope on't.  There was my cousin, you know, Dan'l Evans, that
stopped with us last winter; he was tellin' me that one o' his
coastin' trips he was into the port o' Beaufort lo'din' with
yaller-pine lumber, an' he was into an old buryin'-ground there is
there, an' he see a stone that had on it some young Southern
fellow's name that was killed in the war, an' under it, 'He died
for his
country.'  Dan'l knowed how I used to feel about them South
Car'lina goings on, an' I did feel kind o' red an' ugly for a
minute, an' then somethin' come over me, an' I says, 'Well, I don't
know but what the poor chap did, Dan Evans, when you come to view
it all round.'"
</p><p> The other men made no answer.
</p><p> "Le's see what we can do this year.  I don't care if we be
a poor han'ful," urged Henry Merrill.  "The young folks ought to
have the good of it; I'd like to have my boys see somethin'
different.  Le's get together what men there is.  How many's left,
anyhow?  I know there was thirty-seven went from old Barlow, three-month men an' all."
</p><p> "There can't be over eight, countin' out Martin Tighe; he
can't march," said Stover.  "No, 'tain't worth while."  But the
others did not notice his disapproval.
</p><p> "There's nine in all," announced Asa Brown, after pondering
and counting two or three times on his fingers.  "I can't make us
no more.  I never could carry figgers in my head."
</p><p> "I make nine," said Merrill.  "We'll have Martin ride, an'
Jesse Dean too, if he will.  He's awful lively on them canes o'
his.  An' there's Jo Wade &mdash; with his crutch; he's amazin' spry for
a short distance.  But we can't let 'em go afoot; they're decripped
men.  We'll make 'em all put on what they've got left o' their
uniforms, an' we'll scratch round an' have us a fife an' drum, an'
make the best show we can."
</p><p> "Why, Martin Tighe's boy, the next <pb n="87"/>  to
the oldest, is an excellent hand to play the fife!" said John
Stover, suddenly growing enthusiastic.  "If you two are set on it,
let's have a word with the minister to-morrow, an' see what he
says.  Perhaps he'll give out some kind of a notice.  You have to
have a good many bunches o' flowers.  I guess we'd better call a
meetin', some few on us, an' talk it over first o' the week.
'Twouldn't be no great of a range for us to take to march from the
old buryin'-ground at the meetin'-house here up to the poor-farm
an' round by Deacon Elwell's lane, so's to notice them two stones
he set up for his boys that was sunk on the man-o'-war.  I expect
they notice stones same's if the folks laid there, don't they?"
</p><p> He spoke wistfully.  The others knew that Stover was
thinking of the stone he had set up to the memory of his only
brother, whose nameless grave had been made somewhere in the
Wilderness.
</p><p> "I don't know but what they'll be mad if we don't go by
every house in town," he added, anxiously, as they rose to go home.
"'Tis a terrible scattered population in Barlow to favor with a
procession."
</p><p> It was a mild starlit night.  The three friends took their
separate ways presently, leaving the Plains road and crossing the
fields by foot-paths toward their farms.
</p></div2>
<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d5">
<head>                            II.
</head>
<p> The week went by, and the next Saturday morning brought fair
weather.  It was a busy morning on the farms &mdash; like any other; but
long before noon the teams of horses and oxen were seen going home
from work in the fields, and everybody got ready in haste for the
great event of the afternoon.  It was so seldom that any occasion
roused public interest in Barlow that there was an unexpected
response, and the green before the old white meeting-house was
covered with country wagons and groups of people, whole families
together, who had come on foot.  The old soldiers were to meet in
the church; at half past one the procession was to start, and on
its return the minister was to make an address in the old burying-ground.  John Stover had been a lieutenant in the army, so he was
made captain of the day.  A man from the next town had offered to
drum for them, and Martin Tighe's proud boy was present with his
fife.  He had a great longing &mdash; strange enough in that peaceful
sheep-raising neighborhood &mdash; to go into the army; but he and his
elder brother were the mainstay of their crippled father, and he
could not be spared from the large household until a younger
brother could take his place; so that all his fire and military
zeal went for the present into martial tunes, and the fife was the
safety-valve for his enthusiasm.
</p><p> The army men were used to seeing each other; everybody knew
everybody in the little country town of Barlow; but when one
comrade after another appeared in what remained of his
accoutrements, they felt the day to be greater than they had
planned, and the simple ceremony proved more solemn than any one
expected.  They could make no use of their everyday jokes and
friendly greetings.  Their old blue coats and tarnished army caps
looked faded and antiquated enough.  One of the men had nothing
left but his rusty canteen and rifle; but these he carried like
sacred emblems.  He had worn out all his army clothes long ago,
because when he was discharged he was too poor to buy any others.
</p><p> When the door of the church opened, the veterans were not
abashed by the size and silence of the crowd.  They came walking
two by two down the steps, and took their places in line as if
there were nobody looking on.  Their brief evolutions were like a
mystic rite.  The two lame men refused to do anything but march, as
best they could; but poor Martin Tighe, more disabled than they,
was brought out and lifted into Henry Merrill's best wagon, where
he sat up, straight and soldierly, with his boy for driver.  There
was a little flag in the whip socket before him, which flapped
gayly in the breeze.  It was such a long time since he had been
seen out-of-doors that everybody found him a great object of
interest, and paid him much attention.  Even those who were tired
of being asked to contribute to his support, who resented the fact
of his having a helpless wife and great family; who always insisted
that with his little pension and hopeless lameness, his fingerless
left hand and failing sight, he could support himself and his
household if he chose &mdash; even those persons came forward now to greet
him handsomely and with large approval.  To be sure, he enjoyed the
conversation of idlers, and his wife had a complaining way that was
the same as begging, especially since her boys began
<pb n="88"/>
to grow up and be of some use; and there were one or two near
neighbors who never let them really want; so other people, who had
cares enough of their own, could excuse themselves for forgetting
him the year round, and even call him shiftless.  But there were
none to look askance at Martin Tighe on Decoration day, as he sat
in the wagon, with his bleached face like a captive's, and his
thin, afflicted body.  He stretched out his whole hand impartially
to those who had remembered him and those who had forgotten both
his courage at Fredericksburg and his sorry need in Barlow.
</p><p> Henry Merrill had secured the engine company's large flag
in Alton, and now carried it proudly.  There were eight men in
line, two by two, and marching a good bit apart, to make their line
the longer.  The fife and drum struck up gallantly together, and
the little procession moved away slowly along the country road.  It
gave an unwonted touch of color to the landscape &mdash; the scarlet, the
blue, between the new-ploughed fields and budding road-side
thickets, between the wide dim ranges of the mountains, under the
great white clouds of the spring sky.  Such processions grow more
pathetic year by year; it will not be so long now before wondering
children will have seen the last.  The aging faces of the men, the
renewed comradeship, the quick beat of the hearts that remember,
the tenderness of those who think upon old sorrows &mdash; all these make
the day a lovelier and a sadder festival.  So men's hearts were
stirred, they knew not why, when they heard the shrill fife and the
incessant drum along the quiet Barlow road, and saw the handful of
old soldiers marching by.  Nobody thought of them as familiar men
and neighbors alone &mdash; they were a part of that army which saved its
country.  They had taken their lives in their hands and gone out to
fight &mdash; plain John Stover and Jesse Dean and the rest.  No matter if
every other day in the year they counted for little or much,
whether they were lame-footed and despised, whether their farms
were of poor soil or rich.
</p><p> The little troop went in slender line along the road; the
crowded country wagons and all the people who went afoot followed
Martin Tighe's wagon as if it were a great gathering at a country
funeral.  The route was short, and the long straggling line marched
slowly; it could go no faster than the lame men could walk. </p><p>
In one of the houses by the road-side an old woman sat by a window,
in an old-fashioned black gown, and clean white cap with a prim
border which bound her thin sharp features closely.  She had been
for a long time looking out eagerly over the snowberry and
cinnamon-rose bushes; her face was pressed close to the pane, and
presently she caught sight of the great flag.
</p><p> "Let me see 'em!  I've got to see 'em go by!" she pleaded,
trying to rise from her chair alone when she heard the fife, and
the women helped her to the door, and held her so that she could
stand and wait.  She had been an old woman when the war began; she
had sent two sons and two grandsons to the field; they were all
gone now.  As the men came by, she straightened her bent figure
with all the vigor of youth.  The fife and drum stopped suddenly;
the colors dipped.  She did not heed that, but her old eyes flashed
and then filled with tears to see the flag going to salute the
soldiers' graves.  "Thank ye, boys; thank ye!" she cried, in her
quavering voice, and they all cheered her.  The cheer went back
along the straggling line for old Grandmother Dexter, standing
there in her front door between the lilacs.  It was one of the
great moments of the day.
</p><p> The few old people at the poorhouse, too, were waiting to
see the show.  The keeper's young son, knowing that it was a day of
festivity, and not understanding exactly why, had put his toy flag
out of the gable window, and there it showed against the gray
clapboards like a gay flower.  It was the only bit of decoration
along the veterans' way, and they stopped and saluted it before
they broke ranks and went out to the field corner beyond the poor-farm barn to the bit of ground that held the paupers' unmarked
graves.  There was a solemn silence while Asa Brown went to the
back of Tighe's wagon, where such light freight was carried, and
brought two flags, and he and John Stover planted them straight in
the green sod.  They knew well enough where the right graves were,
for these had been made in a corner by themselves, with unwonted
sentiment.  And so Eben Munson and John Tighe were honored like the
rest, both by their flags and by great and unexpected
<pb n="89"/>
nosegays of spring flowers, daffies and flowering currant and
red tulips, which lay on the graves already.  John Stover and his
comrade glanced at each other curiously while they stood singing,
and then laid their own bunches of lilacs down and came away.
</p><p> Then something happened that almost none of the people in
the wagons understood.  Martin Tighe's boy, who played the fife,
had studied well his part, and on his poor short-winded instrument
now sounded taps as well as he could.  He had heard it done once in
Alton at a soldier's funeral.  The plaintive notes called sadly
over the fields, and echoed back from the hills.  The few veterans
could not look at each other; their eyes brimmed up with tears;
they could not have spoken.  Nothing called back old army days like
that.  They had a sudden vision of the Virginian camp, the hill-side dotted white with tents, the twinkling lights in other camps,
and far away the glow of smouldering fires.  They heard the bugle
call from post to post; they remembered the chilly winter night,
the wind in the pines, the laughter of the men.  Lights out!
Martin Tighe's boy sounded it again sharply.  It seemed as if poor
Eb Munson and John Tighe must hear it too in their narrow graves.
</p><p> The procession went on, and stopped here and there at the
little graveyards on the farms, leaving their bright flags to
flutter through summer and winter rains and snows, and to bleach in
the wind and sunshine.  When they returned to the church, the
minister made an address about the war, and every one listened with
new ears.  Most of what he said was familiar enough to his
listeners; they were used to reading those phrases about the
results of the war, the glorious future of the South, in their
weekly newspapers; but there never had been such a spirit of
patriotism and loyalty waked in Barlow as was waked that day by the
poor parade of the remnant of the Barlow soldiers.  They sent flags
to all the distant graves, and proud were those households who
claimed kinship with valor, and could drive or walk away with their
flags held up so that others could see that they, too, were of the
elect.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="3" id="d6">
<head>                           III.
</head>
<p> It is well that the days are long in the last of May, but John
Stover had to hurry more than usual with his evening work, and
then, having the longest distance to walk, he was much the latest
comer to the Plains store, where his two triumphant friends were
waiting for him impatiently on the bench.  They also had made
excuse of going to the post-office and doing an unnecessary errand
for their wives, and were talking together so busily that they had
gathered a group about them before the store.  When they saw Stover
coming, they rose hastily and crossed the road to meet him, as if
they were a committee in special session.  They leaned against the
post-and-board fence, after they had shaken hands with each other
solemnly.
</p><p> "Well, we've had a great day, 'ain't we, John?" asked Henry
Merrill.  "You did lead off splendid.  We've done a grand thing,
now, I tell you.  All the folks say we've got to keep it up every
year.  Everybody had to have a talk about it as I went home.  They
say they had no idea we should make such a show.  Lord!  I wish
we'd begun while there was more of us!"
</p><p> "That han'some flag was the great feature," said Asa Brown,
generously.  "I want to pay my part for hirin' it.  An' then folks
was glad to see poor old Martin made o' some consequence."
</p><p> "There was half a dozen said to me that another year
they're goin' to have flags out, and trim up their places somehow
or 'nother.  Folks has feelin' enough, but you've got to rouse it,"
said Merrill.
</p><p> "I have thought o' joinin' the Grand Army over to Alton
time an' again, but it's a good ways to go, an' then the expense
has been o' some consideration," Asa continued.  "I don't know but
two or three over there.  You know, most o' the Alton men nat'rally
went out in the rigiments t'other side o' the line, an' they was in
other battles, an' never camped nowheres nigh us.  Seems to me we
ought to have home feelin' enough to do what we can right here."
</p><p> "The minister says to me this afternoon that he was goin'
to arrange an' have some talks in the meetin'-house next winter,
an' have some of us tell where we was in the South; an' one night
'twill be about camp life, an' one about the long marches, an' then
about the battles &mdash; that would take some time &mdash; an' tell all we could
about the boys that was killed, an' their record, so they wouldn't
be forgot.  He said some of the
<pb n="90"/>  folks must have
the letters we wrote home from the front, an' we could make out
quite a history of us.  I call Elder Dallas a very smart man; he'd
planned it all out a'ready, for the benefit o' the young folks, he
said,"
announced Henry Merrill, in a tone of approval.
</p><p> "I s'pose there ain't none of us but could add a little
somethin'," answered John Stover, modestly.  "'Twould re'lly learn
the young folks a good deal.  I should be scared numb to try an'
speak from the pulpit.  That ain't what the elder means, is it?
Now I had a good chance to see somethin' o' Washin'ton.  I shook
hands with President Lincoln, an' I always think I'm worth lookin'
at for that, if I ain't for nothin' else.  'Twas that time I was
just out o' hospit'l, an' able to crawl about some.  Well, we'll
see how 'tis when winter comes.  I never thought I had no gift for
public speakin', 'less 'twas for drivin' cattle or pollin' the
house town-meetin' days.  Here!  I've got somethin' in mind.  You
needn't speak about it if I tell it to ye," he added, suddenly.
"You know all them han'some flowers that was laid on to Eb Munson's
grave an' Tighe's?  I mistrusted you thought the same thing I did
by the way you looked.  They come from Marthy Down's front yard.
My woman told me when we got home that she knew 'em in a minute;
there wa'n't nobody in town had that kind o' red flowers but her.
She must ha' kind o' harked back to the days when she was Marthy
Peck.  She must have come with 'em after dark &mdash; or else dreadful
early in the mornin'."
</p><p> Henry Merrill cleared his throat.  "There ain't nothin'
half-way 'bout Mis' Down," he said.  "I wouldn't ha' spoken 'bout
this 'less you had led right on to it; but I overtook her when I
was gittin' towards home this afternoon, an' I see by her looks she
was worked up a good deal; but we talked about how well things had
gone off, an' she wanted to know what expenses we'd been put to,
an' I told her; an' she said she'd give five dollars any day I'd
stop in for it.  An' then she spoke right out.  'I'm alone in the
world,' says she, 'and somethin' to do with, an' I'd like to have
a plain stone put up to Eb Munson's grave, with the number of his
rigiment on it, an' I'll pay the bill.  'Tain't out o' Mr. Down's
money,' she says; ''tis mine, an' I want you to see to it.'  I said
I would, but we'd made a plot to git some o' them soldiers' head-stones that's provided by the government.  'Twas a shame it had
been overlooked so long.  'No,' says she; 'I'm goin' to pay for
Eb's myself.'  An' I told her there wouldn't be no objection.
Don't ary one o' you speak about it.  'Twouldn't be fair.  She was
real well-appearin'.  I never felt to respect Marthy so before."
</p><p> "We was kind o' hard on her sometimes, but folks couldn't
help it.  I've seen her pass Eb right by in the road an' never look
at him when he first come home," said John Stover.
</p><p> "If she hadn't felt bad, she wouldn't have cared one way or
t'other," insisted Henry Merrill.  "'Tain't for us to judge.
Sometimes folks has to get along in years before they see things
fair.  Come; I must be goin'.  I'm tired as an old dog."
</p><p> "It seemed kind o' natural to be steppin' out together
again.  Strange we three got through with so little damage, an' so
many dropped round us," said Asa Brown.  "I've never been one mite
sorry I went out in old A Company.  I was thinkin' when I was
marchin' to-day, though, that we should all have to take to the
wagons before long an' do our marchin' on wheels, so many of us
felt kind o' stiff.  There's one thing &mdash; folks won't never say again
that we don't show no public sperit here in old Barlow."
</p>

</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
