<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="JewQuee"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="JewQuee">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Queen's Twin</title>
<title type="sort">queens twin</title>
<author>Jewett, Sarah Orne</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss ( )</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">45</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">JewQuee</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476118</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Queen's Twin</title>
<title level="j">Atlantic Monthly</title>
<title type="sort">queens twin</title>
<author>Sarah Orne Jewett</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Atlantic monthly company</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
<date value="1898">1898</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>83</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Jewett, Sarah Orne.  "The Queen's Twin."  <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi>
     83 (1898): 235-246.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1898">1898</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-04">April 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header; Tagged with TEI.2-compatible SGML; Parsed against
local "teilite" dtd.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">

<div1 type="chapter" id="d3"><pb n="235"/>
<head>
                           I. </head>

<p>THE coast of Maine was in former years brought so near to
foreign shores by its busy fleet of ships that among the older men
and women one still finds a surprising proportion of travelers.
Each seaward stretching headland with its high-set houses, each
island of a single farm, has sent its spies to view many a land of
Eshcol.  One may see plain, contented old faces at the windows,
whose eyes have looked at far-away ports, and known the splendors
of the Eastern world.  They shame the easy voyager of the North
Atlantic and the Mediterranean; they have rounded the Cape of Good
Hope and braved the angry seas of Cape Horn in small wooden ships;
they have brought up their hardy boys and girls on narrow decks;
they were among the last of the Northmen's children to go
adventuring to unknown shores.  More than this one cannot give to
a young state for its enlightenment.  The sea captains and the
captains' wives of Maine knew something of the wide world, and
never mistook their native parishes for the whole instead of a part
thereof; they knew not only Thomaston and Castine and Portland, but
London and Bristol and Bordeaux, and the strange-mannered harbors
of the China Sea.

</p><p>One September day, when I was nearly at the end of a summer
spent in a village called Dunnet Landing, on the Maine coast, my
friend Mrs. Todd, in whose house I lived, came home from a long,
solitary stroll in the wild pastures, with an eager look, as if she
were just starting on a hopeful quest instead of returning.  She
brought a little basket with blackberries enough for supper, and
held it toward me so that I could <pb n="236"/>  see that there were also
some late and surprising raspberries sprinkled on top, but she made
no comment upon her wayfaring.  I could tell plainly that she had
something very important to say.
</p><p>"You haven't brought home a leaf of anything?" I ventured to
this practiced herb-gatherer.  "You were saying yesterday that the
witch-hazel might be in bloom."
</p><p>"I dare say, dear," she answered in a lofty manner.  "I ain't
goin' to say it wasn't; I ain't much concerned either way 'bout the
facts o' witch-hazel.  Truth is, I've been off visitin'; there's an
old Indian footpath leadin' over towards the Back Shore, through
the great heron swamp, that anybody can't travel over all summer.
You have to seize your time some day just now, while the low
ground's summer-dried as it is to-day, and before the fall rains
set in.  I never thought of it till I was out o' sight o' home, and
I says to myself, 'To-day's the day certain!' and stepped along
smart as I could.  Yes; I've been visitin'.  I did get into one
spot that was wet underfoot before I noticed; you wait till I get
me a pair o' dry woolen stockin's, in case of cold, and I'll come
an' tell ye."
</p><p>Mrs. Todd disappeared,&mdash;I could see that something had deeply
interested her.  She might have fallen in with either the sea
serpent or the lost tribes of Israel, such was her air of mystery
and satisfaction.  She had been away since just before mid-morning,
and as I sat waiting by my window I saw the last red glow of autumn
sunshine flare along the grey rocks of the shore and leave them
cold again, and touch the far sails of some coastwise schooners so
that they stood like golden houses on the sea.
</p><p>I was left to wonder longer than I liked.  Mrs. Todd was
making an evening fire and putting things in train for supper;
presently she returned, still looking warm and cheerful after her
long walk.
</p><p>"There's a beautiful view from a hill over where I've been,"
she told me; "yes, there's a beautiful prospect of land and sea.
You wouldn't discern the hill from any distance, but 'tis the
pretty situation of it that counts.  I sat there a long spell, and
I did wish for you.  No, I didn't know a word about goin' when I
set out this mornin'."  (As if I had openly reproached her!)  "I
only felt one o' them travelin' fits comin' on, an' I ketched up my
little basket; I didn't know but I might turn and come back, time
for dinner.  I thought it wise to set out your luncheon for you in
case I didn't.  Hope you had all you wanted; yes, I hope you had
enough?"
</p><p>"Oh yes, indeed!" said I.  My landlady was always peculiarly
bountiful in her supplies when she left me to fare for myself, as
if she made a sort of peace-offering or affectionate apology.
</p><p>"You know that hill with the old house right on top, over
beyond the heron swamp?  You'll excuse me for explainin'," Mrs.
Todd began, "but you ain't so apt to strike inland as you be to go
right alongshore.  You know that hill; there's a path leadin' right
over to it that you have to look sharp to find nowadays.  It
belonged to the up-country Indians when they had to make a carry to
the Landing here, to get to the out' islands.  I've heard the old
folks say that there used to be a place across a ledge where they'd
worn a deep track with their moccasin feet, but I never could find
it.  'Tis so overgrown in some places that you keep losin' the path
in the bushes, and findin' it as you can, but it runs pretty
straight considerin' the lay o' the land, and I keep my eye on the
sun and the moss that grows one side o' the tree trunks.  Some
brook's been choked up, and the swamp's bigger than it used to be.
Yes; I did get in deep enough, one place!"
</p><p>I showed the solicitude that I felt.  Mrs. Todd was no longer
young, and, in spite of her strong great frame and spirited
<pb n="237"/>
behavior, I knew that certain ills were apt to seize upon her, and
would some day end by leaving her lame and ailing.
</p><p>"Don't you go to worryin' about me," she insisted.  "Settin'
still's the only way the Evil One'll ever get the upper hand o' me.
Keep me movin' enough, an' I'm twenty year old summer an' winter
both.  I don't know why 'tis, but I've never happened to mention
the one I've been to see.  I don't know why I never happened to
speak the name of Abby Martin, for I often give her a thought; but
'tis a dreadful out-o'-the-way place where she lives, and I haven't
seen her myself for three or four years.  She's a real good,
interesting woman, and we're well acquainted; she's nigher mother's
age than mine, but she's very young-feeling.  She made me a nice
cup o' tea, and I don't know but I should have stopped all night if
I could have got word to you not to worry."
</p><p>Then there was a serious silence before Mrs. Todd spoke again
to make a formal announcement.
</p><p>"She is the Queen's Twin," and Mrs. Todd looked steadily to
see how I might bear the great surprise.
</p><p>"The Queen's Twin?" I repeated.
</p><p>"Yes; she's come to feel a real interest in the Queen, and
anybody can see how natural 'tis.  They were born the very same
day, and you would be astonished to see what a number o' other
things have corresponded.  She was speaking o' some o' the facts to
me to-day, an' you'd think she'd never done nothing but read
history.  I see how earnest she was about it as I never did before.
I've often and often heard her allude to the facts; but now she's
got to be old, and the hurry's all over with her work, she's come
to live a good deal in her thoughts, as folks often do, and I tell
you 'tis a sight o' company for her.  If you want to hear about
Queen Victoria, why, Mis' Abby Martin'll tell you everything.  And
the prospect from that hill I spoke of is as beautiful as anything
in this world; 'tis worth while your goin' over to see her, just
for that."
</p><p>"When can you go again?" I demanded eagerly.
</p><p>"I should say to-morrow," answered Mrs. Todd,&mdash;"yes, I should
say to-morrow; but I expect 'twould be better to take one day to
rest, in between.  I considered that question as I was comin' home,
but I hurried so that there wa'n't much time to think.  It's a
dreadful long way to go with a horse.  You have to go 'most as far
as the old Bowden place, an' turn off to the left, a master long,
rough road; an' then you have to turn right round as soon as you
get there, if you mean to get home before nine o'clock at night.
But to strike across country from here, there's plenty o' time in
the shortest day, and you can have a good hour or two's visit
besides.  'Tain't but a very few miles, and it's pretty all the way
along.  There used to be a few good families over there, but
they've died and scattered, so now she's far from neighbors.
There, she really cried, she was so glad to see anybody comin'.
You'll be amused to hear her talk about the Queen, but I thought
twice or three times, as I set there, 'twas about all the company
she'd got."
</p><p>"Could we go day after to-morrow?" I asked.
</p><p>"'Twould suit me exactly," said Mrs. Todd.



</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" id="d4">
<head>
                           II. </head>

<p>One can never be so certain of good New England weather as in
the days when a long easterly storm has blown away the warm late-summer mists, and cooled the air so that however bright the
sunshine is by day, the nights come nearer and nearer to
frostiness.  There was a cold freshness in the morning air when
Mrs. Todd and I locked the house door behind us; we took the key of
the fields into our own hands that day, and put <pb n="238"/>  out across
country as one puts out to sea.  When we reached the top of the
ridge behind the town, it seemed as if we had anxiously passed the
harbor bar, and were comfortably in open sea at last.
</p><p>"There, now!" proclaimed Mrs. Todd, taking a long breath.
"Now I do feel safe.  It's just the weather that's liable to bring
somebody to spend the day.  I've had a feeling of Mis' Elder Caplin
from North Point bein' close upon me ever since I waked up this
mornin', an' I didn't want to be hampered with our present plans.
She's a great hand to visit; she'll be spendin' the day somewhere
from now till Thanksgivin'; but there's plenty o' places at the
Landin' where she goes, an' if I ain't there she'll just select
another.  I thought mother might be in, too, 'tis so pleasant; but
I run up the road to look off this mornin' before you was awake,
and there was no sign o' the boat.  If they hadn't started by that
time, they wouldn't start just as the tide is now; besides, I see
a lot o' mackerelmen headin' Green Island way, and they'll detain
William.  No, we're safe now; an' if mother should be comin' in to-morrow, we'll have all this to tell her.  She an' Mis' Abby
Martin's very old friends."
</p><p>We were walking down the long pasture slopes, toward the dark
woods and thickets of the low ground.  They stretched away
northward like an unbroken wilderness; the early mists still dulled
much of the color, and made the uplands beyond look like a very
far-off country.
</p><p>"It ain't so far as it looks from here," said my companion
reassuringly; "but we've got no time to spare, either," and she
hurried on, leading the way with a fine sort of spirit in her step.
Presently we struck into the old Indian footpath, which could be
plainly seen across the long-unploughed turf of the pastures, and
followed it among the thick, low-growing spruces.  There the ground
was smooth and brown underfoot, and the thin-stemmed trees held a
dark and shadowy roof overhead.  We walked a long way without
speaking; sometimes we had to push aside the branches, and
sometimes we walked in a broad aisle where the trees were larger.
It was a solitary wood, birdless and beastless; there was not even
a rabbit to be seen, or a crow high in air to break the silence.
</p><p>"I don't believe the Queen ever saw such a lonesome trail as
this," said Mrs. Todd, as if she followed the thoughts that were in
my mind.  Our visit to Mrs. Abby Martin seemed in some strange way
to concern the high affairs of royalty.  I had just been thinking
of English landscapes, and of the solemn hills of Scotland with
their lonely cottages and stone-walled sheepfolds, and the
wandering flocks on high cloudy pastures.  I had often been struck
by the quick interest and familiar allusion to certain members of
the royal house which one found in distant neighborhoods of New
England.  Whether some old instincts of personal loyalty have
survived all changes of time and national vicissitudes, or whether
it is only that the Queen's own character and disposition have won
friends for her so far away, it is impossible to tell.  But to hear
of a twin sister was the most surprising proof of intimacy of all,
and I must confess that there was something remarkably exciting to
the imagination in my morning walk.  To think of being presented at
Court in the usual way was, for the moment, quite commonplace.



</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" id="d5">
<head>
                          III. </head>

<p>Mrs. Todd was swinging her basket to and fro like a schoolgirl
as she walked, and at this moment it slipped from her hand and
rolled lightly along the ground.  I picket it up and gave it to
her, whereupon she lifted the cover and looked in with anxiety.
</p><p>"'Tis only a few little things, but I don't want to lose 'em,"
she explained <pb n="239"/>  humbly.  "'Twas lucky you took the other
basket if I was goin' to roll it round.  Mis' Abby Martin
complained o' lacking some pretty pink silk to finish one o' her
little frames, an' I thought I'd carry her some, and I had a bunch
o' gold thread that had been in a box o' mine this twenty year.  I
never was one to do much fancywork, but we're all liable to be
swept away by fashion.  And then there's a small packet o' very
choice herbs that I gave a good deal of attention to; they'll
smarten her up, and give her the best of appetites, come spring.
She was tellin' me that spring weather is very wiltin' an' tryin'
to her, and she was beginnin' to dread it already.  Mother's just
the same way.  If I could prevail on mother to take some o' these
remedies in good season, 'twould make a world o' difference; but
she gets all downhill before I have a chance to hear of it, and
then William comes in to tell me, sighin' and bewailin' how feeble
mother is.  'Why can't you remember 'bout them good herbs that I
never let her be without?' I say to him,&mdash;he does provoke me so;
and then off he goes, sulky enough, down to his boat.  Next thing
I know, she comes in to go to meetin', wantin' to speak to
everybody and feelin' like a girl.  Mis' Martin's case is very much
the same, but she's nobody to watch her.  William's kind o' slow-moulded, but there, any William's better than none when you get to
be Mis' Martin's age."
</p><p>"Hadn't she any children?" I asked.
</p><p>"Quite a number," replied Mrs. Todd grandly; "but some are
gone, and the rest are married and settled.  She never was a great
hand to go about visitin'.  I don't know but Mis' Martin might be
called a little peculiar.  Even her own folks has to make company
of her: she never slips in and lives right along with the rest as
if 'twas at home, even in her own children's houses.  I heard one
o' her sons' wives say once she'd much rather have the Queen to
spend the day, if she could choose between the two; but I never
thought Abby was so difficult as that.  I used to love to have her
come.  She may have been sort o' ceremonious, but very pleasant and
sprightly if you had sense enough to treat her her own way.  I
always think she'd know just how to live with great folks, and feel
easier 'long of them an' their ways.  Her son's wife's a great
driver with farm work, boards a great tableful o' men in hayin'-time, an' feels right in her element.  I don't say but she's a good
woman an' smart, but sort o' rough.  Anybody that's gentle-mannered
an' precise like Mis' Martin would be a sort o' restraint.
</p><p>"There's all sorts o' folks in the country, same's there is in
the city," concluded Mrs. Todd gravely, and I as gravely agreed.
The thick woods were behind us now, and the sun was shining clear
overhead; the morning mists were gone, and a faint blue haze
softened the distance; as we climbed the hill where we were to see
the view it seemed like a summer day.  There was an old house on
the height, facing southward; a mere forsaken shell of an old house
with empty windows that looked like blind eyes.  The frost-bitten
grass grew close about it like brown fur, and there was a single
crooked bough of lilac holding its green leaves close by the door.
</p><p>"We'll just have a good piece of bread an' butter now," said
the commander of the expedition, "and then we'll hang up the basket
on some peg inside the house, out o' the way o' the sheep, and have
a han'some entertainment as we're comin' back.  She'll be all
through her little dinner when we get there, Mis' Martin will; but
she'll want to make us some tea, an' we must have our visit, an' be
startin' back pretty soon after two.  I don't want to cross all
that low ground again after it's begun to grow chilly.  An' it
looks to me as if the clouds might begin to gather late in the
afternoon." <pb n="240"/>
</p><p>Before us lay a splendid world of sea and shore.  The autumn
colors brightened the landscape already; here and there at the edge
of a dark tract of pointed firs stood a row of bright swamp maples
like scarlet flowers.  The blue sea and the great tide inlets were
untroubled by the lightest winds.
</p><p>"Poor land, this is," sighed Mrs. Todd, as we sat down to rest
on the worn doorstep.  "I've known three good hard-workin' families
that come here full o' hope an' pride, and tried to make somethin'
o' this farm, but it beat 'em all.  There's one small field that's
excellent for potatoes if you let half of it rest every year, but
the land's always hungry.  Now you see them little peaked-topped
spruces an' fir balsams comin' up over the hill all green an'
hearty; they've got it all their own way!  Seems sometimes as if
wild natur' got jealous over a certain spot, and wanted to do just
as she'd a mind to.  You'll see here; she'll do her own ploughin'
an' harrowin' with frost an' wet, an' plant just what she wants,
and wait for her own crops.  Man can't do nothin' with it, try as
he may.  I tell you, those little trees means business!"
</p><p>I looked down the slope, and felt as if we ourselves were
likely to be surrounded and overcome if we lingered too long.
There was a vigor of growth, a persistence and savagery about the
sturdy little trees, that put weak human nature at complete
defiance.  One felt a sudden pity for the men and women who had
been worsted after a long fight in that lonely place; one felt a
sudden fear of the unconquerable immediate forces of nature, as
acute as the irresistible moment of a thunderstorm.
</p><p>"I can recollect the time when folks were shy o' those woods
we just come through," said Mrs. Todd seriously.  "The men folks
themselves never'd venture into 'em alone; if their cattle got
strayed, they'd collect whoever they could get and start off all
together.  They said a person was liable to get bewildered in there
alone, and in old times folks had been lost.  I expect there was
considerable fear left over from the old Indian times and the poor
days o' witchcraft; anyway, I've seen bold men act kind o' timid.
Some women o' the Asa Bowden family went out one afternoon
berryin', when I was a girl, and got lost and was out all night;
they found 'em middle o' the mornin' next day, not half a mile from
home, scared 'most to death, an' sayin' they'd heard wolves and
other beasts sufficient for a caravan.  Poor creatur's, they'd
strayed at last into a kind of low place amongst some alders, an'
one of 'em was so overset she never got over it, an' went off in a
sort o' slow decline.  'Twas like them victims that drowns in a
foot o' water, but their minds did suffer dreadful.  Some folks is
born afraid of the woods and all wild places, but I must say
they've always been like home to me."
</p><p>I glanced at the resolute, confident face of my companion.
Life was very strong in her, as if some force of nature were
personified in this simple-hearted woman, and gave her cousinship
to the ancient deities.  She might have walked the primeval fields
of Sicily; her strong gingham skirts might at that very moment bend
the slender stalks of asphodel, and be fragrant with trodden thyme,
instead of the brown wind-brushed grass of New England and frost-bitten goldenrod.  She was a great soul, was Mrs. Todd, and I her
humble follower, as we went our way to visit the Queen's Twin,
leaving the bright view of the sea behind us, and descending to a
lower countryside through the dry pastures and fields.
</p><p>The farms all wore a look of gathering age, though the
settlement was, after all, so young.  The fences were already
fragile, and it seemed as if the first impulse of agriculture had
soon spent itself without hope of renewal.  The better houses were
always those that had <pb n="241"/>  some hold upon the riches of the sea;
a house that could not harbor a fishing boat in some neighboring
inlet was far from being sure of every-day comforts.  The land
alone was not enough to live upon in that stony region; it belonged
by right to the forest, and to the forest it fast returned.  From
the top of the hill where we had been sitting we had seen
prosperity in the dim distance, where the land was good and the sun
shone upon fat barns, and where warm-looking houses with three or
four chimneys apiece stood high on their solid ridge above the bay.
</p><p>As we drew nearer to Mrs. Martin's, it was sad to see what
poor bushy fields, what thin and empty dwelling-places, had been
left by those who had chosen this disappointing part of the
northern country for their home.  We crossed the last field and
came into a narrow rain-washed road, and Mrs. Todd looked eager and
expectant, and said that we were almost at our journey's end.
</p><p>"I do hope Mis' Martin'll ask you into her best room, where
she keeps all the Queen's pictures.  Yes, I think likely she will
ask you; but 'tain't everybody she deems worthy to visit 'em, I can
tell you!" said Mrs. Todd warningly.  "She's been collectin' 'em
an' cuttin' 'em out o' newspapers an' magazines time out o' mind;
and if she heard of anybody sailin' for an English port, she'd
contrive to get a little money to 'em and ask to have the last
likeness there was.  She's 'most covered her best-room wall now:
she keeps that room shut up sacred as a meetin'-house!  'I won't
say but I have my favorites amongst 'em,' she told me t'other day,
'but they're all beautiful to me as they can be.'  And she's made
some kind o' pretty little frames for 'em all.  You know there's
always a new fashion o' frames comin' round: first 'twas shellwork,
and then 'twas pine cones, and beadwork's had its day, and now
she's much concerned with perforated cardboard worked with silk.
I tell you, that best room's a sight to see!  But you mustn't look
for anything elegant," continued Mrs. Todd, after a moment's
reflection.  "Mis' Martin's always been in very poor, strugglin'
circumstances.  She had ambition for her children, though they took
right after their father an' had little for themselves; she wa'n't
over an' above well married, however kind she may see fit to speak.
She's been patient an' hard-workin' all her life, and always high
above makin' mean complaints of other folks.  I expect all this
business about the Queen has buoyed her over many a shoal place in
life.  Yes, you might say that Abby'd been a slave, but there ain't
any slave but has some freedom."



</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" id="d6">
<head>
                           IV. </head>

<p>Presently I saw a low gray house standing on a grassy bank
close to the road.  The door was at the side, facing us, and a
tangle of snowberry bushes and cinnamon roses grew to the level of
the window sills.  On the doorstep stood a bent-shouldered little
old woman.  There was an air of welcome and of unmistakable dignity
about her.  "She sees us coming!" exclaimed Mrs. Todd in an excited
whisper.  "There, I told her I might be over this way again, if the
weather held good, and if I came I'd bring you.  She said right off
she'd take great pleasure in havin' a visit from you.  I was
surprised; she's usually so retirin'."
</p><p>Even this reassurance did not quell a faint apprehension on
our part; there was something distinctly formal in the occasion,
and one felt that consciousness of inadequacy which is never easy
for the humblest pride to bear.  On the way I had torn my dress in
an unexpected encounter with a little thorn bush; I could now
imagine how it felt to be going to Court and forgetting one's
feathers or Court train. <pb n="242"/>
</p><p>The Queen's Twin was oblivious of such trifles; she stood
waiting with a calm look until we came near enough to take her kind
hand.  She was a beautiful old woman, with clear eyes and a lovely
quietness and genuineness of manner; there was not a trace of
anything pretentious about her, or high-flown, as Mrs. Todd would
say comprehensively.  Beauty in age is rare enough in women who
have spent their lives in the hard work of a farmhouse; but autumn-like and withered as this woman may have looked, her features had
kept, or rather gained, a great refinement.  She led us into her
old kitchen, and gave us seats, and took one of the little
straight-backed chairs herself, and sat a short distance away, as
if she were giving audience to an ambassador.  It seemed as if we
should all be standing; one could not help feeling that the habits
of her life were more ceremonious, but that for the moment she
assumed the simplicities of the occasion.
</p><p>Mrs. Todd was always Mrs. Todd,&mdash;too great and self-possessed
a soul for any occasion to ruffle.  I admired her calmness, and
presently the slow current of neighborhood talk carried us easily
along; we spoke of the weather and the small adventures of the way,
and then, as if I were after all not a stranger, our hostess turned
almost affectionately to speak to me.
</p><p>"The weather will be growing dark in London now.  I expect
that you've been in London, dear?" she said.
</p><p>"Oh yes," I answered.  "Only last year."
</p><p>"It is a great many years since I was there; along in the
forties," said Mrs. Martin.  'Twas the only voyage I ever made.
Most of my neighbors have been great travelers.  My brother was
master of a vessel, and his wife usually sailed with him; but that
year she had a young child more frail than the others, and she
dreaded the care of it at sea.  It happened that my brother got a
chance for my husband to go as supercargo, being a good accountant,
and came one day to urge him to take it.  He was very ill disposed
to the sea, but he had met with losses, and I saw my own
opportunity and persuaded them both to let me go too.  In those
days they didn't object to a woman's being aboard to wash and mend;
the voyages were sometimes very long.  And that was the way I come
to see the Queen."
</p><p>Mrs. Martin was looking straight in my eyes, to see if I
showed any genuine interest in the most interesting person in the
world.
</p><p>"Oh, I am glad you saw the Queen," I hastened to say.  "Mrs.
Todd has told me that you and she were born the very same day."
</p><p>"We were indeed, dear," said Mrs. Martin, and she leaned back
comfortably and smiled as she had not smiled before.  Mrs. Todd
gave a satisfied nod and glance, as if to say that things were
going on as well as possible in this anxious moment.
</p><p>"Yes," Mrs. Martin resumed, as she drew her chair a little
nearer, "'twas a very remarkable thing: we were born the same day,
and at exactly the same hour, after you allowed for all the
difference in time.  My father figured it out sea-fashion.  Her
Royal Majesty and I opened our eyes upon this world together: say
what you may, 'tis a bond between us."
</p><p>Mrs. Todd assented with an air of triumph, and untied her hat
strings and threw them back over her shoulders with a gallant air.
</p><p>"And I married a man by the name of Albert, just the same as
she did; and all by chance, for I didn't get the news that she had
an Albert, too, till a fortnight afterward; news was slower coming
then than it is now.  My first baby was a girl, and I called her
Victoria after my mate; but the next one was a boy, and my husband
wanted the right to name him, and took his own name and <pb n="243"/>  his
brother Edward's; and pretty soon I saw in the paper that the
little Prince o' Wales had been christened just the same.  After
that I made excuse to wait till I knew what she'd named her
children.  I didn't want to break the chain, so I had an Alfred and
my darling Alice that I lost long before she lost hers, and there
I stopped.  If I'd only had a dear daughter to stay at home with
me, same's her youngest one, I should have been so thankful!  But
if only one of us could have a little Beatrice, I'm glad 'twas the
Queen; we've both seen trouble, but she's had the most care."
</p><p>I asked Mrs. Martin if she lived alone all the year, and was
told that she did except for a visit now and then from one of her
grandchildren, "the only one that really likes to come an' stay
quiet 'long o' grandma.  She always says, quick as she's through
her schoolin' she's goin' to live with me all the time.  But she's
very pretty an' has taking ways," said Mrs. Martin, looking both
proud and wistful, "so I can tell nothing at all about it.  Yes,
I've been alone most o' the time since my Albert was taken away,
and that's a great many years; he had a long time o' failing and
sickness first."  (Mrs. Todd's foot gave an impatient scuff on the
floor.)  "An' I've always lived right here.  I ain't like the
Queen's Majesty, for this is the only palace I've got," said the
dear old thing, smiling again.  "I'm glad of it, too.  I don't like
changing about, an' our stations in life are set very different.
I don't require what the Queen does, but sometimes I've thought
'twas left to me to do the plain things she don't have time for.
I expect she's a beautiful housekeeper; nobody couldn't have done
better in her high place, and she's been as good a mother as she's
been a queen."
</p><p>"I guess she has, Abby," agreed Mrs. Todd instantly.  "How was
it you happened to get such a good look at her?  I meant to ask you
again when I was here t'other day."
</p><p>"Our ship was layin' in the Thames, right there above Wapping.
We was dischargin' cargo, and under orders to clear as quick as we
could for Bordeaux to take on an excellent freight o' French
goods," explained Mrs. Martin eagerly.  "I heard that the Queen was
goin' to a great review of her army, and would drive out o' her
Buckin'ham Palace about ten o'clock in the mornin'; and I run aft
to Albert, my husband, and brother Horace where they was standin'
together by the hatchway, and told 'em they must one of 'em take
me.  They laughed, I was in such a hurry, and said they couldn't
go; and I found they meant it and got sort of impatient when I
begun to talk, and I was 'most broken-hearted; 'twas 'most all the
reason I had for makin' that hard voyage.  Albert couldn't help
often reproachin' me, for he did so resent the sea, an' I'd known
how 'twould be before we sailed; but I'd minded nothin' all the way
till then, and I just crep' back to my cabin an' begun to cry.
They was disappointed about their ship's cook, an' I'd cooked for
fo'c's'le an' cabin myself all the way over; 'twas dreadful hard
work, 'specially in rough weather; we'd had head winds an' a six
weeks' voyage.  They'd acted sort of ashamed o' me when I pled so
to go ashore, an' that hurt my feelin's most of all.  But Albert
come below pretty soon.  I'd never given way so in my life, an' he
begun to act frightened, and treated me gentle, just as he did when
we was goin' to be married; an' when I got over sobbin' he went on
deck an' saw Horace an' talked it over what they could do; they
really had their duty to the vessel, and couldn't be spared that
day.  Horace was real good when he understood everything, an' he
come an' told me I'd more than worked my passage, an' was goin' to
do just as I liked now we was in port.  He'd engaged a cook, too,
that was comin' aboard that mornin', <pb n="244"/>  and he was goin' to
send the ship's carpenter with me, a nice fellow from up Thomaston
way; he'd gone to put on his shore clothes as quick's he could.  So
then I got ready, and we started off in the small boat and rowed up
river.  I was afraid we were too late, but the tide was setting up
very strong, and we landed an' left the boat to a keeper, and I run
all the way up those great streets and across a park.  'Twas a
great day, with sights o' folks everywhere, but 'twas just as if
they was nothin' but wax images to me.  I kep' askin' my way, an'
runnin' on, with the carpenter comin' after as best he could; and
just as I worked to the front o' the crowd by the palace the gates
was flung open and out she came,&mdash;all prancin' horses and shinin'
gold,&mdash;and in a beautiful carriage there she sat: 'twas a moment o'
heaven to me.  I saw her plain, and she looked right at me so
pleasant and happy, just as if she knew there was somethin'
different between us from other folks."
</p><p>There was a moment when the Queen's Twin could not go on, and
neither of her listeners could ask a question.
</p><p>"Prince Albert was sitting right beside her in the carriage,"
she continued.  "Oh, he was a beautiful man.  Yes, dear, I saw 'em
both together, just as I see you now; and then she was gone out o'
sight in another minute, and the common crowd was spread all over
the place, pushin' an' cheerin'.  'Twas some kind o' holiday, an'
the carpenter and I got separated, an' then I found him again after
I didn't think I should, an' he was all for makin' a day of it and
goin' to show me all the sights,&mdash;he'd been in London before; but
I didn't want nothin' else, an' we went back through the streets
down to the waterside an' took the boat.  I remember I mended an
old coat o' my Albert's as good as I could, sittin' in the sun on
the quarter deck all that afternoon, and 'twas all as if I was
livin' in a lovely dream.  I don't know how to explain it, but
there hasn't been no friend I've felt so near to me ever since."
</p><p>One could not say much, only listen.  Mrs. Todd put in a
discerning question now and then, and Mrs. Martin's eyes shone
brighter and brighter as she talked.  What a lovely gift of
imagination and true affection was in this fond old heart!  I
looked about the plain New England kitchen, with its wood-smoked
walls, its homely braided rugs on the worn floor, and all its
simple furnishings.  The loud-ticking clock seemed to encourage us
to speak.  At the other side of the room was an early newspaper
portrait of Her Majesty the Queen of Great Britain and Ireland.  On
a shelf below were some flowers in a little glass dish, as if they
were put before a shrine.
</p><p>"If I could have had more to read, I should have known 'most
everything about her," said Mrs. Martin wistfully.  "I've made the
most of what I did have, and thought it over and over till it came
clear.  I sometimes seem to have her all my own, as if we'd lived
right together.  I've often walked out into the woods alone and
told her what my troubles was, and it always seemed as if she told
me 'twas all right, an' we must have patience.  I've got her
beautiful book about the Highlands,&mdash;'twas dear Mis' Todd here that
found out about her printing it, and got a copy for me; and it's
been a treasure to my heart, just as if 'twas written right to me.
I always read it Sundays now for my Sunday treat.  Before that I
used to have to imagine a good deal; but when I come to read her
book, I knew what I expected was all true.  We do think alike about
so many things," said the Queen's Twin, with affectionate
certainty.  "You see, there is something between us, being born
just at the same time: 'tis what they call a birthright.  She's had
great tasks put upon her, being the Queen, an' mine has been the
humble lot; but she's done the best she could, nobody can say to
the contrary, and there's something <pb n="245"/>  between us; she's been
the great lesson I've had to live by.  She's been everything to me.
An' when she had her Jubilee, oh, how my heart was with her!"
</p><p>"There, 'twouldn't play the part in her life it has in mine,"
said Mrs. Martin generously, in answer to something one of her
listeners had said.  "Sometimes I think, now she's older, she might
like to know about us.  When I think how few old friends anybody
has left at our age, I suppose it may be just the same with her as
it is with me; perhaps she would like to know how we came into life
together.  But I've had a great advantage in seeing her, an' I can
always fancy her goin' on while she don't know nothin' yet about
me,&mdash;except she may feel my love stayin' her heart sometimes, an'
not know just where it comes from.  An' I dream about our being
together out in some pretty fields, young as ever we was, and
holdin' hands as we walk along.  I'd like to know if she ever has
that dream, too.  I used to have days when I made believe she did
know, an' was comin' to see me," confessed the speaker shyly, with
a little flush on her cheeks, "and I'd plan what I could have nice
for supper; and I wasn't goin' to let anybody know she was here
havin' a good rest, except I'd wish you, Almira Todd, or dear Mis'
Blackett would happen in, for you'd know just how to talk with her.
You see, she likes to be up in Scotland, right out in the wild
country, better than she does anywhere else."
</p><p>"I'd really love to take her out to see mother at Green
Island," said Mrs. Todd, with a sudden impulse.
</p><p>"Oh yes, I should love to have you," answered Mrs. Martin, and
then she began to speak in a lower tone.  "One day I got thinkin'
so about my dear Queen," she said, "an' livin' so in my thoughts,
that I went to work an' got all ready for her, just as if she was
really comin'.  I never told this to a livin' soul before, but I
feel you'll understand.  I put my best fine sheets and blankets I
spun an' wove myself, on her bed, and I picked some pretty flowers
and put 'em all round the house; an' I worked as hard an' happy as
I could all day, and had as nice a supper ready as I could get,
sort of tellin' myself a story all the time.  She was comin', an'
I was goin' to see her again, an' I kep' it up until nightfall; an'
when I see the dark an' it come to me I was all alone, the dream
left me, an' I sat down on the doorstep an' felt all foolish an'
tired.  An' if you'll believe it, I heard steps comin', an' an old
cousin o' mine come wanderin' along, one I was apt to be shy of.
She wasn't all there, as folks used to say, but harmless enough,
and a kind of poor old talking body.  An' I went right to meet her
when I first heard her call, 'stead o' hidin', as I sometimes did,
an' she come in dreadful willin', an' we set down to supper
together; 'twas a supper I should have had no heart to eat alone."
</p><p>"I don't believe she ever had such a splendid time in her life
as she did then.  I heard her tell all about it afterward!"
exclaimed Mrs. Todd compassionately.  "There, now I hear all this,
it seems just as if the Queen might have known, and couldn't come
herself, so she sent that poor old creatur' that was always in
need!"
</p><p>Mrs. Martin looked timidly at Mrs. Todd, and then at me.
"'Twas childish o' me to go an' get supper," she confessed.
</p><p>"I guess you wa'n't the first one to do that," said Mrs. Todd.
"No, I guess you wa'n't the first one who's got supper that way,
Abby"&mdash;and then for a moment she could say no more.
</p><p>Mrs. Todd and Mrs. Martin had moved their chairs a little, so
that they faced each other, and I, at one side, could see them
both.
</p><p>"No, you never told me o' that before, Abby," said Mrs. Todd
gently.  "Don't it show that, for folks that have any fancy in 'em,
such beautiful dreams is <pb n="246"/>  the real part o' life?  But to
most folks the common things that happens outside 'em is all in
all."
</p><p>Mrs. Martin did not appear to understand at first, strange to
say, when the secret of her heart was put into words; then a glow
of pleasure and comprehension shone upon her face.  "Why, I believe
you're right, Almira!" she said, and turned to me.
</p><p>"Wouldn't you like to look at my pictures of the Queen?" she
asked, and we rose and went into the best room.



</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" id="d7">
<head>
                           V. </head>

<p>The midday visit seemed very short.  September hours are brief
to match the shortening days.  The great subject was dismissed for
a while after our visit to the Queen's pictures, and my companions
spoke much of lesser persons until we drank the cup of tea which
Mrs. Todd had foreseen.  I happily remembered that the Queen
herself is said to like a proper cup of tea, and this at once
seemed to make her Majesty kindly join so remote and reverent a
company.
</p><p>Mrs. Martin's thin cheeks took on a pretty color like a
girl's.  "Somehow, I always have thought of her when I made it
extra good," she said.  "I've got a real china cup that belonged to
my grandmother, and I believe I shall call it hers now."
</p><p>"Why don't you?" responded Mrs. Todd warmly, with a delightful
smile.
</p><p>Later they spoke of a promised visit which was to be made in
the Indian summer to the Landing and Green Island; but I observed
that Mrs. Todd presented the little parcel of dried herbs, with
full directions for a cure-all in the spring, as if there were no
real chance of their meeting again first.  As we looked back from
the turn of the road the Queen's Twin was still standing on the
door-step watching us away, and Mrs. Todd stopped and stood still
for a moment before she waved her hand again.
</p><p>"There's one thing certain, dear," she said to me, with great
discernment: "it ain't as if we left her all alone!"
</p><p>Then we set out upon our long way home, over the hill where we
lingered in the afternoon sunshine, and through the dark woods
across the heron swamp.
</p><signed><hi rend="italic">Sarah Orne Jewett.</hi></signed>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
