<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="JewWhit"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="JewWhit">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The White Rose Road</title>
<title type="sort">white rose road</title>
<author>Jewett, Sarah Orne</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">29</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">JewWhit</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476121</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The White Rose Road</title>
<title type="sort">white rose road</title>
<author>Sarah Orne Jewett</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition, serial publication</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
<date value="1889-09">Sept. 1889</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Atlantic Monthly</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1889-09">Sept. 1889</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-11">November 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Monique Dull, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Basic conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="353"/>
<head>THE WHITE ROSE ROAD.</head>
<p>Being a New Englander, it is natural that I should first speak
about the weather.  Only the middle of June, the green fields, and
blue sky, and bright sun, with a touch of northern mountain wind
blowing straight toward the sea, could make such a day, and that is
all one can say about it.  We were driving seaward through a part
of the country which has been least changed in the last thirty
years,&mdash;among farms which have been won from swampy lowland, and
rocky, stump-buttressed hillsides; where the forests wall in the
fields, and send their outposts year by year farther into the
pastures.  There is a year or two in the history of these pastures
before they have arrived at the dignity of being called woodland,
and yet are too much shaded and overgrown by young trees to give
proper pasturage, when they make delightful harbors for the small
wild creatures which yet remain, and for wild flowers and berries.
Here you send an astonished rabbit scurrying to his burrow, and
there you startle yourself with a partridge, who seems to get the
best of the encounter.  Sometimes you see a hen partridge and her
brood of chickens crossing your path with an air of comfortable
door-yard security.  As you drive along the narrow, grassy road,
you see many charming sights and delightful nooks on either hand,
where the young trees spring out of a close-cropped turf that
carpets the ground like velvet.  Toward the east and the quaint
fishing village of Ogunquit I find the most delightful woodland
roads.  There is little left of the large timber which once filled
the region, but much young growth, and there are hundreds of acres
of cleared land and pasture ground where the forests are springing
fast and covering the country once more, as if they had no idea of
losing in their war with civilization and the intruding white
settler.  The pine woods and the Indians seem to be next of kin,
and the former owners of this corner of New England are the only
proper figures to paint into such landscapes.  The twilight under
tall pines seems to be untenanted and to lack something, at first
sight, as if one opened the door of an empty house.  A farmer
passing through with his axe is but an intruder, and children
straying home from school give one a feeling of solicitude at their
unprotectedness.  The pines are the red man's house, and it may be
hazardous even yet for the gray farmhouses to stand so near the
eaves of the forest.  I have noticed a distrust of the deep woods,
among elderly people, which was something more than a fear of
losing their way.  It was a feeling of defenselessness against some
unrecognized but malicious influence.
</p><p>Driving through the long woodland way, shaded and chilly when
you are out of the sun; across the Great Works River and its pretty
elm-grown intervale; across the short bridges of brown brooks;
delayed now and then by the sight of ripe strawberries in sunny
spots by the roadside, one comes to a higher open country, where
farm joins farm,

<pb n="354"/>  and the cleared fields lie all along the
highway, while the woods are pushed back a good distance on either
hand.  The wooded hills, bleak here and there with granite ledges,
rise beyond.  The houses are beside the road, with green door-yards
and large barns, almost empty now, and with wide doors standing
open, as if they were already expecting the hay crop to be brought
in.  The tall green grass is waving in the fields as the wind goes
over, and there is a fragrance of whiteweed and ripe strawberries
and clover blowing through the sunshiny barns, with their lean
sides and their festoons of brown, dusty cobwebs; dull, comfortable
creatures they appear to imaginative eyes, waiting hungrily for
their yearly meal.  The eaves-swallows are teasing their sleepy
shapes, like the birds which flit about great beasts; gay, movable,
irreverent, almost derisive, those barn-swallows fly to and fro in
the still, clear air.
</p><p>The noise of our wheels brings fewer faces to the windows than
usual, and we lose the pleasure of seeing some of our friends who
are apt to be looking out, and to whom we like to say good-day.
Some funeral must be taking place, or perhaps the women may have
gone out into the fields.  It is hoeing-time and strawberry-time,
and already we have seen some of the younger women at work among
the corn and potatoes.  One sight will be charming to remember.  On
a green hillside sloping to the west, near one of the houses, a
thin little girl was working away lustily with a big hoe on a patch
of land perhaps fifty feet by twenty.  There were all sorts of
things growing there, as if a child's fancy had made the choice,&mdash;
straight rows of turnips and carrots and beets, a little of
everything, one might say; but the only touch of color was from a
long border of useful sage in full bloom of dull blue, on the upper
side.  I am sure this was called Katy's or Becky's <hi rend="italic">piece</hi> by the
elder members of the family.  One can imagine how the young
creature had planned it in the spring, and persuaded the men to
plough and harrow it, and since then had stoutly done all the work
herself, and meant to send the harvest of the piece to market, and
pocket her honest gains, as they came in, for some great end.  She
was as thin as a grasshopper, this busy little gardener, and hardly
turned to give us a glance, as we drove slowly up the hill close
by.  The sun will brown and dry her like a spear of grass on that
hot slope, but a spark of fine spirit is in the small body, and I
wish her a famous crop.  I hate to say that the piece looked
backward, all except the sage, and that it was a heavy bit of land
for the clumsy hoe to pick at.  The only puzzle is what she
proposes to do with so long a row of sage.  Yet there may be a
large family with a downfall of measles yet ahead, and she does not
mean to be caught without sage-tea.  It is time it were cut, at any
rate.
</p><p>Along this road every one of the old farmhouses has at least
one tall bush of white roses by the door,&mdash;a most lovely sight,
with buds and blossoms and unvexed green leaves.  I wish that I
knew the history of them, and whence the first bush was brought.
Perhaps from England itself, like a red rose that I know in
Kittery, and the new shoots from the root were given to one
neighbor after another all through the district.  The bushes are
slender, but they grow tall without climbing against the wall, and
sway to and fro in the wind with a grace of youth and an
inexpressible charm of beauty.  How many lovers must have picked
them on Sunday evenings, in all the bygone years, and carried them
along the roads or by the pasture foot-paths, hiding them clumsily
under their Sunday coats if they caught sight of any one coming.
Here, too, where the sea wind nips many a young life before its
prime, how often the white

<pb n="355"/>
roses have been put into paler hands, and withered there!
</p><p>In spite of the serene and placid look of the old houses, one
who has always known them cannot help thinking of the sorrows of
these farms and their almost undiverted toil.  Near the little
gardener's plot we turned from the main road and drove through
lately cleared woodland up to an old farmhouse, high on a ledgy
hill, whence there is a fine view of the country seaward and
mountainward.  There were few of the once large household left
there: only the old farmer, who was crippled by war wounds, active,
cheerful man that he was once, and two young orphan children.
There has been much hard work spent on the place.  Every generation
has toiled from youth to age without being able to make much beyond
a living.  The dollars that can be saved are but few, and sickness
and death have often brought their bitter cost.  The mistress of
the farm was helpless for many years; through all the summers and
winters she sat in her pillowed rocking-chair in the plain room.
She could watch the seldom-visited lane, and beyond it, a little
way across the fields, were the woods; besides these, only the
clouds in the sky.  She could not lift her food to her mouth; she
could not be her brother's working partner.  She never went into
another woman's house to see her works and ways, but sat there,
aching and tired, vexed by flies and by heat, and isolated in long
storms.  Yet the whole country-side neighbored her with true
affection.  Her spirit grew stronger as her body grew weaker, and
the doctors, who grieved because they could do so little with their
skill, were never confronted by that malady of the spirit, a desire
for ease and laziness, which makes the soundest of bodies useless
and complaining.  The thought of her blooms in one's mind like the
whitest of flowers; it makes one braver and more thankful to
remember the simple faith and patience with which she bore her pain
and trouble.  How often she must have said, "I wish I could do
something for you in return," when she was doing a thousand times
more than if, like her neighbors, she followed the simple round of
daily life!  She was doing constant kindness by her example; but
nobody can tell the woe of her long days and nights, the solitude
of her spirit, as she was being lifted by such hard ways to the
knowledge of higher truth and experience.  Think of her pain when,
one after another, her housemates fell ill and died, and she could
not tend them!  And now, in the same worn chair where she lived and
slept sat her brother, helpless too, thinking of her, and missing
her more than if she had been sometimes away from home, like other
women.  Even a stranger would miss her in the house.
</p><p>There sat the old farmer, looking down the lane in his turn,
bearing his afflictions with a patient sternness that may have been
born of watching his sister's serenity.  There was a half-withered
white rose lying within his reach.  Some days nobody came up the
lane, and the wild birds that ventured near the house and the
clouds that blew over were his only entertainment.  He had a fine
face, of the older New England type, clean-shaven and strong-featured,&mdash;a type that is fast passing away.  He might have been a
Cumberland dalesman, such were his dignity, and self-possession,
and English soberness of manner.  His large frame was built for
hard work, for lifting great weights and pushing his plough through
new-cleared land.  We felt at home together, and each knew many
things that the other did of earlier days, and of losses that had
come with time.  I remembered coming to the old house often in my
childhood; it was in this very farm lane that I first saw anemones,
and learned what to call them.  After we drove away, this crippled
man must have thought a long time about my elders and

<pb n="356"/>
betters, as if he were reading their story out of a book.  I
suppose he has hauled many a stick of timber pine down for the
ship-yards, and gone through the village so early in the winter
morning that I, waking in my warm bed, only heard the sleds creak
through the frozen snow as the slow oxen plodded by.
</p><p>Near the house a trout brook comes plashing over the ledges.
At one place there is a most exquisite waterfall, to which neither
painter's brush nor writer's pen can do justice.  The sunlight
falls through flickering leaves into the deep glen, and makes the
foam whiter and the brook more golden-brown.  You can hear the
merry noise of it all night, all day, in the house.  A little way
above the farmstead, it comes through marshy ground, which I fear
has been the cause of much illness and sorrow to the poor, troubled
family.  I had a thrill of pain, as it seemed to me that the brook
was mocking at all that trouble with its wild carelessness and loud
laughter, as it hurried away down the glen.
</p><p>When we had said good-by and were turning the horses away,
there suddenly appeared in a foot-path that led down from one of
the green hills the young grand-niece, just coming home from
school.  She was as quick as a bird, and as shy in her little pink
gown, and balanced herself on one foot, like a flower.  The brother
was the elder of the two orphans; he was the old man's delight and
dependence by day, while his hired man was afield.  The sober
country boy had learned to wait and tend, and the young people were
indeed a joy in that lonely household.  There was no sign that they
ever played like other children,&mdash;no truckle-cart in the yard, no
doll, no bits of broken crockery in order on a rock.  They had
learned a fashion of life from their elders, and already could lift
and carry their share of the burdens of life.
</p><p>It was a country of wild flowers; the last of the columbines
were clinging to the hillsides; down in the small, fenced meadows
belonging to the farm were meadow rue just coming in flower, and
red and white clover; the golden buttercups were thicker than the
grass, while many mulleins were standing straight and slender among
the pine stumps, with their first blossoms atop.  Rudbeckias had
found their way in, and appeared more than ever like bold
foreigners.  Their names should be translated into country speech,
and the children ought to call them "rude-beckies," by way of
relating them to bouncing-bets and sweet-williams.  The pasture
grass was green and thick after the plentiful rains, and the busy
cattle took little notice of us as they browsed steadily and
tinkled their pleasant bells.  Looking off, the smooth, round back
of Great Hill caught the sunlight with its fields of young grain,
and all the long, wooded slopes and valleys were fresh and fair in
the June weather, away toward the blue New Hampshire hills on the
northern horizon.  Seaward stood Agamenticus, dark with its pitch
pines, and the far sea itself, blue and calm, ruled the uneven
country with its unchangeable line.
</p><p>Out on the white rose road again, we saw more of the rose-trees than ever, and now and then a carefully tended flower garden,
always delightful to see and to think about.  They are not made by
merely looking through a florist's catalogue, and ordering this or
that new seedling and a proper selection of bulbs or shrubs;
everything in a country garden has its history and personal
association.  The old bushes, the perennials, are apt to have most
tender relationship with the hands that planted them long ago.
There is a constant exchange of such treasures between the
neighbors, and in the spring slips and cuttings may be seen rooting
on the window ledges, while the house plants give endless work all
winter long, since they need careful protection against frost in
long nights of

<pb n="357"/>  the severe weather.  A flower-loving woman
brings back from every one of her infrequent journeys some treasure
of flower-seeds or a huge miscellaneous nosegay.  Time to work in
the little plot of pleasure-ground is hardly won by the busy
mistress of the farmhouse.  The most appealing collection of
flowering plants and vines that I ever saw was in Virginia, once,
above the exquisite valley spanned by the Natural Bridge, far too
little known or praised.  I had noticed an old log house, as I
learned to know the outlook from the picturesque hotel, and was
sure that it must give a charming view from its perch on the summit
of a hill.
</p><p>One day I went there,&mdash;one April day, when the whole landscape
was full of color from the budding trees,&mdash;and before I could look
at the view I caught sight of some rare vines, already in leaf,
about the dilapidated walls of the cabin.  Then across the low
paling I saw the brilliant colors of tulips and daffodils, and the
most exquisite narcissus.  There were many rose-bushes; in fact,
the whole top of the hill had been a flower garden, once well cared
for and carefully ordered.  It was all the work of an old woman of
Scotch-Irish descent, who had been busy with the cares of life, and
a very hard worker; yet I was told that to gratify her love for
flowers she would often go afoot many miles over those rough
Virginia roads, with some root or cutting from her own garden to
barter for a new rose or a brighter blossom of some sort, with
which she would return in triumph.  I fancied that sometimes she
had to go by night on these charming quests.  I could see her
business-like, small figure setting forth down the steep path, when
she had a good conscience toward her housekeeping and the children
were in order to be left.  I am sure that her friends thought of
her when they were away from home and could bring her an offering
of something rare.  Alas, she had grown too old and feeble to care
for her dear blossoms any longer, and had been forced to go to live
with a married son.  I dare say that she was thinking of her garden
that very day, and wondering if this thing or that were not in
bloom, and perhaps had a heartache at the thought that her tenants,
the careless colored children, might tread the young shoots of
peony and rose, and make havoc in the herb-bed.  It was an uncommon
collection, made by years of patient toil and self-sacrifice.
</p><p>I thought of that deserted Southern garden as I followed my
own New England road.  The flower plots were in gay bloom all along
the way; almost every house had some flowers before it, sometimes
carefully fenced about by stakes and barrel staves from the
miscreant hens and chickens which lurked everywhere, and liked a
good scratch and fluffing in soft earth this year as well as any
other.  The world seemed full of young life.  There were calves
tethered in pleasant shady spots, and puppies and kittens
adventuring from the door-ways.  The trees were full of birds:
bobolinks, and cat-birds, and yellow-hammers, and golden robins,
and sometimes a thrush, for the afternoon was wearing late.  We
passed the spring which once marked the boundary where three towns
met,&mdash;Berwick, York, and Wells,&mdash;a famous spot in the early
settlement of the country, but many of its old traditions are now
forgotten.  One of the omnipresent regicides of Charles the First
is believed to have hidden himself for a long time under a great
rock close by.  The story runs that he made his miserable home in
this den for several years, but I believe that there is no record
that more than three of the regicides escaped to this country, and
their wanderings are otherwise accounted for.  There is a firm
belief that one of them came to York, and was the ancestor of many
persons now living there, but I do not know whether he can have
been the hero of

<pb n="358"/>  the Baker's Spring hermitage beside.  We
stopped to drink some of the delicious water, which never fails to
flow cold and clear under the shade of a great oak, and were amused
with the sight of a flock of gay little country children who passed
by in deep conversation.  What could such atoms of humanity be
talking about?  "Old times," said John, the master of horse, with
instant decision.
</p><p>We met now and then a man or woman, who stopped to give us a
hospitable greeting; but there was no staying for visits, lest the
daylight might fail us.  It was delightful to find this old-established neighborhood so thriving and populous, for a few days
before I had driven over three miles of road, and passed only one
house that was tenanted, and six cellars or crumbling chimneys
where good farmhouses had been, the lilacs blooming in solitude,
and the fields, cleared with so much difficulty a century or two
ago, all going back to the original woodland from which they were
won.  What would the old farmers say to see the fate of their
worthy bequest to the younger generation?  They would wag their
heads sorrowfully, with sad foreboding.
</p><p>After we had passed more woodland and a well-known quarry,
where, for a wonder, the derrick was not creaking and not a single
hammer was clinking at the stone wedges, we did not see any one
hoeing in the fields, as we had seen so many on the white rose
road, the other side of the hills.  Presently we met two or three
people walking sedately, clad in their best clothes.  There was a
subdued air of public excitement and concern, and one of us
remembered that there had been a death in the neighborhood; this
was the day of the funeral.  The man had been known to us in former
years.  We had an instinct to hide our unsympathetic pleasuring,
but there was nothing to be done except to follow our homeward road
straight by the house.
</p><p>The occasion was nearly ended by this time: the borrowed
chairs were being set out into the yard in little groups; even the
funeral supper had been eaten, and the brothers and sisters and
near relatives of the departed man were just going home.  The new
grave showed plainly out in the green field near by.  He had
belonged to one of the ancient families of the region, long settled
on this old farm by the narrow river; they had given their name to
a bridge, and the bridge had christened the meeting-house which
stood close by.  We were much struck by the solemn figure of the
mother, a very old woman, as she walked toward her own home with
some of her remaining children.  I had not thought to see her
again, knowing her great age and infirmity.  She was like a
presence out of the last century, tall and still erect, dark-eyed
and of striking features, and a firm look not modern, but as if her
mind were still set upon an earlier and simpler scheme of life.  An
air of dominion cloaked her finely.  She had long been queen of her
surroundings and law-giver to her great family.  Royalty is a
quality, one of Nature's gifts, and there one might behold it as
truly as if Victoria Regina Imperatrix had passed by.  The natural
instincts common to humanity were there undisguised, unconcealed,
simply accepted.  We had seen a royal progress; she was the central
figure of that rural society; as you looked at the little group,
you could see her only.  Now that she came abroad so rarely, her
presence was not without deep significance, and so she took her
homeward way with a primitive kind of majesty.
</p><p>It was evident that the neighborhood was in great excitement
and quite thrown out of its usual placidity.  An acquaintance came
from a small house farther down the road, and we stopped for a word
with him.  We spoke of the funeral, and were told something of the
man who had died.  "Yes, and there's a

<pb n="359"/>  man layin' very sick
here," said our friend in an excited whisper.  <hi rend="italic">"He</hi> won't last
but a day or two.  There's another man buried yesterday that was
struck by lightnin', comin' home acrost a field when that great
shower begun.  The lightnin' stove through his hat and run down all
over him, and ploughed a spot in the ground."  There was a knot of
people about the door; the minister of that scattered parish stood
among them, and they all looked at us eagerly, as if we too might
be carrying news of a fresh disaster through the country-side.
</p><p>Somehow the melancholy tales did not touch our sympathies as
they ought, and we could not see the pathetic side of them as at
another time, the day was so full of cheer and the sky and earth so
glorious.  The very fields looked busy with their early summer
growth, the horses began to think of the clack of the oat-bin
cover, and we were hurried along between the silvery willows and
the rustling alders, taking time to gather a handful of stray-away
conserve roses by the road-side; and where the highway made a long
bend eastward among the farms, two of us left the carriage, and
followed a foot-path along the green river bank and through the
pastures, coming out to the road again only a minute later than the
horses.  I believe that it is the old Indian trail followed from
the salmon falls farther down the river, where the up-country
Indians came to dry the plentiful fish for their winter supplies.
I have traced the greater part of this deep-worn foot-path, which
goes straight as an arrow across the country, the first day's trail
being from the falls (where Mason's settlers came in 1627, and
built their Great Works of a saw-mill with a gang of saws, and
presently a grist-mill beside) to Emery's Bridge.  I should like to
follow the old foot-path still farther.  I found part of it by
accident a long time ago.  Once, as you came close to the river,
you were sure to find fishermen scattered along,&mdash;sometimes I
myself have been discovered; but it is not much use to go fishing
any more.  If some public-spirited person would kindly be the Frank
Buckland of New England, and try to have the laws enforced that
protect the inland fisheries, he would do his country great
service.  Years ago there were so many salmon that, as an
enthusiastic old friend once assured me, "you could walk across on
them below the falls;" but now they are unknown, simply because
certain substances which would enrich the farms are thrown from
factories and tanneries into our clear New England streams.  Good
river fish are growing very scarce.  The smelt, and bass, and shad
have all left this upper branch of the Piscataqua, as the salmon
left it long ago, and the supply of one necessary sort of good
cheap food is lost to a growing community, for the lack of a little
thought and care in the factory companies and saw-mills, and the
building in some cases of fish-ways over the dams.  I think that
the need of preaching against this bad economy is very great.  The
sight of a proud lad with a string of undersized trout will scatter
half the idlers in town into the pastures next day, but everybody
patiently accepts the depopulation of a fine clear river, where the
tide comes fresh from the sea to be tainted by the spoiled stream,
which started from its mountain sources as pure as heart could
wish.  Man has done his best to ruin the world he lives in, one is
tempted to say at impulsive first thought; but after all, as I
mounted the last hill before reaching the village, the houses took
on a new look of comfort and pleasantness, the fields that I knew
so well were a fresher green than before, the sun was down, and the
provocations of the day seemed very slight compared to the
satisfaction.  I believed that with a little more time we should
grow wiser about our fish and other things beside.
</p><p>It will be good to remember the white

<pb n="360"/>  rose road and
its quietness in many a busy town day to come.  As I think of these
slight sketches, I wonder if they will have to others a tinge of
sadness; but I have seldom spent an afternoon so full of pleasure
and fresh and delighted consciousness of the possibilities of rural
life.
</p>
<trailer><hi rend="italic">Sarah Orne Jewett.</hi></trailer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
