<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="JonHumo"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;

]>
<TEI.2 id="JonHumo">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Every Man in his Humour</title>
<title type="sort">every man in his humour</title>
<author>Jonson, Ben</author>
<editor>Watson, Robert N.</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Robert N. Watson</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">208</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">JonHumo</idno>
<date value="2001">2001</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2001 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476128</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Page images from the original 1616 version have been added for comparison to this text. The electronic text presented here is Robert Watson's modernized version of the 1616 version.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Every Man in his Humour</title>
<title type="sort">every man in his humour</title>
<author>Ben Jonson</author>
<editor>Robert N. Watson</editor>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>New Mermaids</publisher>
<date value="1998">1998</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: The electronic typescript from Robert Watson and some comparison with the digital images of original</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Page images from the 1616 version have been refered to by the id attributes on the pb elements.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1616">1616</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
<language id="lat">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2004-08">8/04</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>XML tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<front id="d2">

<titlePage id="d3">
	<pb/>
<docTitle>
<titlePart type="main">Every Man In His Humour</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<byline>ed. Robert N. Watson
</byline>
<docImprint>
New Mermaids edition, <date value="1998">1998</date>
</docImprint>
</titlePage>

<div1 type="preface" id="d4">

<pb id="n101-003"/>

<opener><salute>TO THE MOST LEARNED, AND MY HONOURED FRIEND,<lb/>
Master Camden, CLARENTIAUX.</salute></opener>

<p>SIR, There are, no doubt, a supercilious race in the world, who will esteem all office done you in this kind an injury, so solemn a vice it is with them to use the authority of their ignorance to the crying down of poetry, or the professors; but my gratitude must not leave to	 correct their error, since I am none of those that can suffer the benefits conferred upon my youth to perish with my age. It is a frail memory that remembers but present things; and, had the favour of the times so conspired with my disposition as it could have brought forth other, or better, you had had the same proportion and number of the fruits, the first. Now, I pray you to accept this: such, wherein neither the confession of my manners shall make you blush; nor of my studies, repent you to have been the instructor.  And, for the profession of my thankfulness, I am sure it will, with good men, find either praise, or excuse.</p>

<closer><signed>Your true lover,<lb/>
BEN. JONSON.</signed></closer>
</div1>

<div1 type="section" id="d5">

<pb id="n101-004"/>

<head>The Persons of the Play.</head>
<list>
<item>KNOWELL an old gentleman</item>
<item>EDWARD KNOWELL his son</item>
<item>BRAINWORM the father's man</item>
<item>MASTER STEPHEN a country gull [Edward's cousin]</item>
<item>[GEORGE] DOWNRIGHT a plain squire</item>
<item>WELLBRED his half-brother [and Dame Kitely's brother]</item>
<item>JUSTICE CLEMENT an old merry magistrate</item>
<item>ROGER FORMAL his clerk</item>
<item>[THOMAS] KITELY a merchant</item>
<item>DAME KITELY his wife</item>
<item>MISTRESS BRIDGET his sister</item>
<item>MASTER MATTHEW the town gull</item>
<item>[THOMAS] CASH Kitely's man</item>
<item>[OLIVER] COB a water-bearer</item>
<item>TIB his wife</item>
<item>CAPTAIN BOBADILL a Paul's-man</item>
<item>[SERVANTS, etc.]</item>
</list>
</div1>

</front>

<body id="d6">


<div1 type="prologue" id="d7">
<pb id="n101-005"/>
<stage type="setting">The Scene: London</stage>


<sp><speaker>Prologue</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Though need make many Poets, and some such</l>
<l>As art and nature have not bettered much;</l>
<l>Yet ours, for want, hath not so loved the stage,</l>
<l>As he dare serve th'ill customs of the age,</l>
<l>Or purchase your delight at such a rate,</l>
<l>As, for it, he himself must justly hate.</l>
<l>To make a child, now swaddled, to proceed</l>
<l>Man, and then shoot up, in one beard and weed,</l>
<l>Past threescore years; or, with three rusty swords,</l>
<l>And help of some few foot-and-half-foot words,</l>
<l>Fight over York and Lancaster's long jars;</l>
<l>And in the tiring-house bring wounds to scars.</l>
<l>He rather prays you will be pleased to see</l>
<l>One such, today, as other plays should be.</l>
<l>Where neither Chorus wafts you o'er the seas;</l>
<l>Nor creaking throne comes down, the boys to please;</l>
<l>Nor nimble squib is seen, to make afeared</l>
<l>The gentlewomen; nor rolled bullet heard</l>
<l>To say, it thunders; nor tempestuous drum</l>
<l>Rumbles, to tell you when the storm doth come;</l>
<l>But deeds, and language, such as men do use;</l>
<l>And persons, such as Comedy would choose,</l>
<l>When she would show an image of the times,</l>
<l>And sport with human follies, not with crimes--</l>

<pb id="n101-006"/>

<l>Except, we make 'em such by loving still</l>
<l>Our popular errors, when we know they're ill.</l>
<l>I mean such errors, as you'll all confess</l>
<l>By laughing at them, they deserve no less;</l>
<l>Which when you heartily do, there's hope left, then,</l>
<l>You, that have so graced monsters, may like men.</l>
</lg>
</sp>
</div1>

<div1 type="act" n="1" id="d8">
<head>Act I</head>

<div2 type="scene" n="1" id="d9">
<head>Act I, Scene i</head>

<stage type="setting">[Enter] KNOWELL, BRAINWORM</stage>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>A goodly day toward!  And a fresh morning!  Brainworm,</l>
<l>Call up your young master: bid him rise, sir.</l>
<l>Tell him I have some business to employ him.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<lg>
<l>I will sir, presently.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>But hear you, sirrah,</l>
<l>If he be at his book, disturb him not.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<lg>
<l> 			       Well sir.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit BRAINWORM]</stage>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>How happy yet should I esteem myself</l>
<l>Could I (by any practice) wean the boy</l>
<l>From one vain course of study he affects.</l>
<l>He is a scholar, if a man may trust</l>
<l>The liberal voice of fame in her report,</l>
<l>Of good account in both our universities,</l>
<l>Either of which hath favoured him with graces;</l>
<l>But their indulgence must not spring in me</l>
<l>A fond opinion, that he cannot err.</l>
<l>Myself was once a student; and, indeed,</l>
<l>Fed with the self-same humour he is now,</l>
<l>Dreaming on nought but idle poetry,</l>
<l>That fruitless and unprofitable art,</l>
<l>Good unto none, but least to the professors,</l>
<l>Which then I thought the mistress of all knowledge:</l>
<l>But since, time and the truth have waked my judgement,</l>
<l>And reason taught me better to distinguish</l>
<l>The vain from th'useful learnings.</l>
</lg>
<stage type="setting">[Enter STEPHEN]</stage>
<lg>
<l>Cousin Stephen!</l>
<l>What news with you, that you are here so early?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Nothing, but e'en come to see how you do, uncle.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>That's kindly done, you are welcome, coz.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Aye, I know that, sir, I would not ha' come else. How do my cousin Edward, uncle?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>Oh, well, coz, go in and see; I doubt he be scarcestirring yet.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Uncle, afore I go in, can you tell me an' he have e'er a
book of the sciences of hawking, and hunting? I would fain
borrow it.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>Why, I hope you will not a-hawking now, will you?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>No, wusse; but I'll practice against next year, uncle: I have bought me a hawk, and a hood, and bells, and all; I lack nothing but a book to keep it by.</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-007"/>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>Oh, most ridiculous.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Nay, look you now, you are angry, uncle; why you know, an a' man have not skill in the hawking and hunting languages nowadays, I'll not give a rush for him.  They are more studied than the Greek or the Latin. He is for no gallants' company without 'em. And by gad's lid I scorn it, I, so I do, to be a consort for every humdrum; hang 'em, scroyles, there's nothing in 'em i' the world. What do you talk on it? Because I dwell at Hogsden, I shall keep company with none but the archers of Finsbury? Or the citizens that come a ducking to Islington ponds? A fine jest, i' faith! 'Slid, a gentleman mun show himself like a gentleman. Uncle, I pray you be not angry, I know what I have to do, I trow, I am no novice.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>You are a prodigal absurd coxcomb; go to.</l>
<l>Nay, never look at me, it's I that speak.</l>
<l>Take't as you will sir, I'll not flatter you.</l>
<l>Ha' you not yet found means enow to waste</l>
<l>That which your friends have left you, but you must</l>
<l>Go cast away your money on a kite,</l>
<l>And know not how to keep it, when you ha' done?</l>
<l>Oh it's comely! This will make you a gentleman!</l>
<l>Well, cousin, well! I see you are e'en past hope</l>
<l>Of all reclaim. Aye, so, now you are told on it,</l>
<l>You look another way.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<lg>
<l>What would you ha' me do?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>What would I have you do? I'll tell you kinsman:</l>
<l>Learn to be wise, and practice how to thrive,</l>
<l>That would I have you do; and not to spend</l>
<l>Your coin on every bauble that you fancy,</l>
<l>Or every foolish brain that humours you.</l>
<l>I would not have you to invade each place,</l>
<l>Nor thrust yourself on all societies,</l>
<l>Till men's affections, or your own desert,</l>
<l>Should worthily invite you to your rank.</l>
<l>He that is so respectless in his courses</l>
<l>Oft sells his reputation at cheap market.</l>
<l>Nor would I, you should melt away yourself</l>
<l>In flashing bravery, lest while you affect</l>
<l>To make a blaze of gentry to the world,</l>
<l>A little puff of scorn extinguish it,</l>
<l>And you be left like an unsavoury snuff,</l>
<l>Whose property is only to offend.</l>
<l>I'd ha' you sober, and contain yourself:</l>
<l>Not, that your sail be bigger than your boat;</l>
<l>But moderate your expenses now (at first),</l>
<l>As you may keep the same proportion still;</l>
<l>Nor stand so much on your gentility,</l>

<pb id="n101-008"/>

<l>Which is an airy and mere borrowed thing,</l>
<l>From dead men's dust and bones, and none of yours</l>
<l>Except you make or hold it. Who comes here?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter a SERVANT]</stage>

<sp><speaker>SERVANT</speaker>
<p>Save you, gentlemen.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Nay, we don't stand much on our gentility, friend; yet, you are welcome, and I assure you, mine uncle here is a man of a thousand a year, Middlesex land; he has but one son in all the world, I am his next heir (at the common law), Master Stephen, as simple as I stand here, if my cousin die (as there's hope he will), I have a pretty living o' mine own too, beside, hard by here.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>SERVANT</speaker>
<p>In good time, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>In good time, sir? Why! and in very good time, sir. You do not flout, friend, do you?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>SERVANT</speaker>
<p>Not I, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Not you, sir? You were not best, sir; an' you should, here be them can perceive it, and that quickly too; go to. And they can give it again soundly too an' need be.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>SERVANT</speaker>
<p>Why, sir, let this satisfy you: good faith, I had no such intent.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Sir, an' I thought you had, I would talk with you, and that presently.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>SERVANT</speaker>
<p>Good Master Stephen, so you may, sir, at your pleasure.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>And so I would sir, good my saucy companion, an' you were not o' mine uncle's ground, I can tell you; though I do not stand upon my gentility neither in't.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>Cousin! Cousin! Will this ne'er be left?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Whoreson base fellow! A mechanical serving-man! By this cudgel, an't were not for shame, I would--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>What would you do, you peremptory gull?</l>
<l>If you cannot be quiet, get you hence.</l>
<l>You see the honest man demeans himself</l>
<l>Modestly towards you, giving no reply</l>
<l>To your unseasoned, quarrelling, rude fashion;</l>
<l>And still you huff it, with a kind of carriage</l>
<l>As void of wit as of humanity.</l>
<l>Go, get you in; 'fore heaven, I am ashamed</l>
<l>Thou hast a kinsman's interest in me.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit STEPHEN]</stage>

<sp><speaker>SERVANT</speaker>
<p>I pray you, sir, is this Master Knowell's house?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>Yes, marry, is it sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>SERVANT</speaker>
<p>I should inquire for a gentleman here, one Master Edward Knowell;

<pb id="n101-009"/>

do you know any such, sir, I pray you?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>I should forget myself else, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>SERVANT</speaker>
<p>Are you the gentleman? Cry you mercy sir: I was required by a gentleman i' the city, as I rode out at this end o' the town, to deliver you this letter, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>To me, sir! What do you mean? Pray you, remember your court'sy.</p> <stage type="delivery">[Reads]</stage> <p>`To his most selected friend, Master Edward Knowell.' What might the gentleman's name be, sir, that sent it? Nay, pray you, be covered.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>SERVANT</speaker>
<p>One Master Wellbred, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>Master Wellbred! A young gentleman, is he not?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>SERVANT</speaker>
<p>The same, sir; Master Kitely married his sister, the rich merchant i' the Old Jewry.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>You say very true. Brainworm!</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter BRAINWORM]</stage>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>Make this honest friend drink here;</p> <stage type="delivery">[To SERVANT]</stage> <p>pray you go in.</p>
<stage type="setting">[Exeunt BRAINWORM and SERVANT]</stage>
<lg>
<l>This letter is directed to my son;</l>
<l>Yet, I am Edward Knowell too, and may</l>
<l>With the safe conscience of good manners use</l>
<l>The fellow's error to my satisfaction.</l>
<l>Well, I will break it ope (old men are curious),</l>
<l>Be it but for the style's sake, and the phrase,</l>
<l>To see if both do answer my son's praises,</l>
<l>Who is, almost, grown the idolater</l>
</lg>
<p>Of this young Wellbred. What have we here? What's this?</p>
<stage type="delivery">[Reads]</stage> <p>'Why, Ned, I beseech thee: has thou forsworn all thy friends i' the Old Jewry? Or dost thou think us all Jews that inhabit there, yet? If thou dost, come over, and but see our frippery; change an old shirt for a whole smock with us. Do not conceive that antipathy between us and Hogsden, as was between Jews and hogs' flesh. Leave thy vigilant father alone to number over his green apricots, evening and morning, o' the north-west wall; an' I had been his son, I had saved him the labour, long since; if taking in all the young wenches that pass by at the back door, and coddling every kernel of the fruit for 'em, would ha' served. But, prithee, come over to me, quickly, this morning: I have such a present for thee (our Turkey Company never sent the like to the Grand Signior)! One is a rhymer, sir, o' your own batch, your own leaven, but doth think himself Poet-mayor o' the town: willing to be shown, and worthy to be seen. The other--I will not venture his description with you till you come, because I would ha' you make hither with an appetite. If the worst of 'em be not worth your journey, draw your bill of charges,

<pb id="n101-010"/>

as unconscionable as any Guildhall verdict will give it you, and you shall be allowed your viaticum.</p>
<p>From the Windmill.'</p>
<lg>
<l>From the Bordello, it might come as well;</l>
<l>The Spittle, or Pict-hatch. Is this the man</l>
<l>My son hath sung so for the happiest wit,</l>
<l>The choicest brain, the times hath sent us forth?</l>
<l>I know not what he may be in the arts,</l>
<l>Nor what in schools; but surely, for his manners,</l>
<l>I judge him a profane and dissolute wretch;</l>
<l>Worse, by possession of such great good gifts,</l>
<l>Being the master of so loose a spirit.</l>
<l>Why, what unhallowed ruffian would have writ</l>
<l>In such a scurrilous manner to a friend!</l>
<l>Why should he think I tell my apricots?</l>
<l>Or play th' Hesperian dragon with my fruit,</l>
<l>To watch it? Well, my son, I had thought</l>
<l>You'd had more judgement, t'have made election</l>
<l>Of your companions, than t'have ta'en on trust</l>
<l>Such petulant, jeering gamesters, that can spare</l>
<l>No argument or subject from their jest.</l>
<l>But I perceive, affection makes a fool</l>
<l>Of any man, too much the father. Brainworm!</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter BRAINWORM]</stage>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>Is the fellow gone that brought this letter?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Yes, sir, a pretty while since.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>And where's your young master?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>In his chamber, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>He spake not with the fellow, did he?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>No, sir, he saw him not.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>Take you this letter, and deliver it my son, but with no notice that I have opened it, on your life.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Oh lord, sir, that were a jest indeed!</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit]</stage>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>I am resolved, I will not stop his journey;</l>
<l>Nor practice any violent mean, to stay</l>
<l>The unbridled course of youth in him; for that,</l>
<l>Restrained, grows more impatient; and, in kind,</l>
<l>Like to the eager but the generous greyhound,</l>
<l>Who, ne'er so little from his game withheld,</l>
<l>Turns head, and leaps up at his holder's throat.</l>
<l>There is a way of winning more by love,</l>
<l>And urging of the modesty, than fear:</l>
<l>Force works on servile natures, not the free.</l>
<l>He that's compelled to goodness, may be good;</l>

<pb id="n101-011"/>

<l>But 'tis but for that fit; where others, drawn</l>
<l>By softness and example, get a habit.</l>
<l>Then, if they stray, but warn 'em: and the same</l>
<l>They should for virtue've done, they'll do for shame.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit]</stage>

</div2>

<div2 type="scene" n="2" id="d10">
<head>Act I, Scene ii</head>

<stage type="setting">[Enter] EDWARD [holding a letter], BRAINWORM</stage>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Did he open it, sayest thou?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Yes, o' my word, sir, and read the contents.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>That scarce contents me. What countenance, prithee, made he, i' the reading of it? Was he angry, or pleased?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Nay sir, I saw him not read it, nor open it, I assure your Worship.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>No? How know'st thou, then, that he did either?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Marry, sir, because he charged me, on my life, to tell nobody that he opened it; which, unless he had done, he would never fear to have it revealed.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>That's true; well, I thank thee, Brainworm.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="delivery">[He studies the letter]</stage>

<stage type="setting">[Enter STEPHEN]</stage>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Oh, Brainworm, did'st thou not see a fellow here in a what-sha'-call-him doublet? He brought mine uncle a letter e'en now.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Yes, Master Stephen, what of him?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Oh, I ha' such a mind to beat him. Where is he? Canst thou tell?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Faith, he is not of that mind: he is gone, Master Stephen.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Gone? Which way? When went he? How long since?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>He is rid hence. He took horse at the street door.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>And I stayed i' the fields! Whoreson scanderbag rogue! Oh that I had a horse to fetch him back again.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Why, you may ha' my master's gelding, to save your longing, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>But I ha' no boots, that's the spite on't.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Why, a fine wisp of hay, rolled hard, Master Stephen.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>No, faith, it's no boot to follow him now: let him e'en go, and hang. 'Pray thee, help to truss me a little. He does so vex me--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>You'll be worse vexed, when you are trussed, Master Stephen. Best keep unbraced, and walk yourself till you be cold: your choler may founder you else.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>By my faith, and so I will, now thou tell'st me on't.  How dost thou like my leg, Brainworm?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>A very good leg, Master Stephen! But the woollen stocking does not commend it so well.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Foh, the stockings be good enough, now summer is coming on, for the dust. I'll have a pair of silk again' winter, that I go to dwell i' the

<pb id="n101-012"/>

town. I think my leg would show in a silk-hose.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Believe me, Master Stephen, rarely well.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>In sadness, I think it would: I have a reasonable good leg.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>You have an excellent good leg, Master Stephen, but I cannot stay to praise it longer now, and I am very sorry for't.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Another time will serve, Brainworm. Gramercy for this.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit BRAINWORM]</stage>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Ha, ha, ha!	laughs having read the letter</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>'Slid, I hope, he laughs not at me; an' he do--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Here was a letter, indeed, to be intercepted by a man's father, and do him good with him! He cannot but think most virtuously, both of me, and the sender, sure; that make the careful costermonger of him in our 'familiar Epistles'. Well, if he read this with patience, I'll be gelt, and troll ballads for Master John Trundle, yonder, the rest of my mortality. It is true, and likely, my father may have as much patience as another man; for he takes very much physic, and oft taking physic makes a man very patient. But would your packet, Master Wellbred, had arrived at him, in such a minute of his patience; then we had known the end of it, which now is doubtful, and threatens--[Sees STEPHEN] What! My wise cousin! Nay, then, I'll furnish our feast with one gull more toward the mess. He writes to me of a brace, and here's one, that's three. Oh, for a fourth; Fortune, if ever thou'lt use thine eyes, I entreat thee--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Oh, now I see who he laughed at. He laughed at somebody in that letter. By this good light, an' he had laughed at me-</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>How now, cousin Stephen, melancholy?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Yes, a little. I thought you had laughed at me, cousin.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Why, what an' I had, coz, what would you ha' done?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>By this light, I would ha' told mine uncle.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Nay, if you would ha' told your uncle, I did laugh at you, coz.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Did you, indeed?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Yes, indeed.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Why, then--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>What then?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>I am satisfied, it is sufficient.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Why, be so, gentle coz. And, I pray you let me entreat a  courtesy of you. I am sent for, this morning, by a friend i' the Old Jewry to come to him.  It's but crossing over the fields to  Moorgate. Will you bear me company? I protest, it is not to draw you into bond, or any plot against the state, coz.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Sir, that's all one, an' 'twere: you shall command me twice so far as Moorgate to do you good in such a matter. Do you think  I would leave you? I protest--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>No, no, you shall not protest, coz.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>By my fackins, but I will, by your leave; I'll protest more to my friend than I'll speak of at this time.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>You speak very well, coz.</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-013"/>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Nay, not so, neither, you shall pardon me; but I speak to serve my turn.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Your turn, coz? Do you know what you say? A gentleman of your sort, parts, carriage, and estimation, to talk o' your turn i' this company, and to me alone, like a tankard-bearer at a  conduit! Fie. A wight that (hitherto) his every step hath left the  stamp of a great foot behind him, as every word the savour of a  strong spirit! And he! This man!  So graced, gilded, or (to use a  more fit metaphor) so tin-foiled by nature, as not ten housewives' pewter (again' a good time) shows more bright to the world than he!  And he (as I said last, so I say again, and still shall say it)--this man!--to conceal such real ornaments as these, and shadow their glory, as a milliner's wife does her wrought stomacher, with a smoky lawn, or a black cyprus? Oh, coz! It cannot be answered, go not about it. Drake's old ship, at Deptford, may sooner circle the world again. Come, wrong not the quality of your desert with looking downward, coz; but hold up your head, so: and let the Idea of what you are be portrayed i' your face, that men may read i' your physnomy, 'Here, within this place, is to be seen the true, rare, and accomplished monster, or miracle of nature', which is all one. What think you of this, coz?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Why, I do think of it, and I will be more proud, and melancholy,  and gentleman-like, than I have been: I'll ensure you.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>Why, that's resolute Master Stephen! [Aside] Now, if I can but hold him up to his height, as it is happily begun, it will do well for a suburb-humour: we may hap have a match with the city, and play him for forty pound. Come, coz.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>I'll follow you.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Follow me? You must go before.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Nay, an' I must, I will. Pray you, show me, good cousin.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exeunt]</stage>

</div2>

<div2 type="scene" n="3" id="d11">
<head>Act I, Scene iii</head>

<stage type="setting">[Enter] MATTHEW</stage>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>I think this be the house: what ho?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[Within]</stage> 	<p>Who's there?</p> <stage type="delivery">[Opens the door]</stage> <p>Oh, Master Matthew! Gi' your worship good morrow.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>What! Cob! How dost thou, good Cob? Dost thou inhabit here, Cob?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Aye, sir, I and my lineage ha' kept a poor house here, in our days.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Thy lineage, Monsieur Cob, what lineage? What lineage?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Why, sir, an ancient lineage, and a princely. Mine ance'try came from a king's belly, no worse man; and yet no man neither (by your worship's leave, I did lie in that) but Herring the king of fish, from his belly I proceed, one o' the monarchs o' the world, I assure you. The first red herring that was broiled in Adam and Eve's kitchen do I fetch my pedigree

<pb id="n101-014"/>

from, by the harrots' books. His cob was my great-great-mighty-great grandfather.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Why mighty? Why mighty, I pray thee?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Oh, it was a mighty while ago, sir, and a mighty great cob.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>How know'st thou that?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>How know I? Why, I smell his ghost, ever and anon.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Smell a ghost? Oh unsavoury jest! And the ghost of a herring, Cob!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Aye, sir, with favour of your worship's nose, Master Matthew, why not the ghost of a herring-cob, as well as the ghost of rasher-bacon?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Roger Bacon, thou would'st say?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>I say rasher-bacon. They were both broiled o' the coals? And a man may smell broiled meat, I hope? You are a scholar: upsolve me that, now.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Oh raw ignorance! Cob, canst thou show me of a gentleman, one Captain Bobadill, where his lodging is?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Oh, my guest, sir, you mean!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Thy guest! Alas! Ha, ha.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Why do you laugh, sir? Do you not mean Captain Bobadill?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Cob, 'pray thee, advise thyself well: do not wrong the gentleman, and thyself too. I dare be sworn, he scorns thy house. He! He lodge in such a base, obscure place, as thy house! Tut, I know his disposition so well, he would not lie in thy bed, if thou'dst gi'it him.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>I will not give it him, though, sir. Mass, I thought somewhat was in't, we could not get him to bed all night! Well, sir, though he lie not o' my bed, he lies o' my bench: an't please you to go up, sir, you shall find him with two cushions under his head, and his cloak wrapped about him, as though he had neither won nor lost, and yet, I warrant, he ne'er cast better in his life than he has done tonight.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Why? Was he drunk?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Drunk, sir? You hear not me say so. Perhaps he swallowed a tavern-token, or some such device, sir: I have nothing to do withal. I deal with water, and not with wine. Gi'me my tankard there, ho.  God b'w'you, sir. It's six o'clock: I should ha' carried two turns, by this. What ho! My stopple! Come.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Lie in a water-bearer's house! A gentleman of his havings! Well, I'll tell him my mind.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter TIB, carrying the tankard and stopple]</stage>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>What, Tib, show this gentleman up to the Captain.</p> <stage type="setting">[Exit TIB and MATTHEW]</stage> <p>Oh, an' my house were the Brazen-head now, faith, it would e'en speak, 'Mo' fools yet'. You should ha' some now would take this Master Matthew to be a gentleman, at the least. His father's an honest man, a worshipful fishmonger, and so forth; and now does he creep and wriggle into acquaintance with all the brave gallants about the town, such as my guest is (oh, my guest is a fine man), and they flout him invincibly. He useth every

<pb id="n101-015"/>

day to a merchant's house, where I serve water, one Master Kitely's, i' the Old Jewry; and here's the jest, he is in love with my master's sister, Mistress Bridget, and calls her mistress; and there he will sit you a whole afternoon sometimes, reading o' these same abominable, vile (a pox on 'em, I cannot abide them) rascally verses, poyetry, poyetry, and speaking of interludes, 'twill make a man burst to hear him. And the wenches, they do so jeer, and tee-hee at him--well, should they do so much to me, I'd forswear them all, by the foot of Pharaoh. There's an oath! How many water-bearers shall you hear swear such an oath? Oh, I have a guest--he teaches me--he does swear the legiblest, of any man chistened: 'By St. George!' 'The foot of Pharaoh!' 'The body of me!' 'As I am a gentleman and a soldier!' Such dainty oaths! And withal, he does take this same filthy roguish tobacco the finest and cleanliest! It would do a man good to see the fume come forth at's tunnels! Well, he owes me forty shillings (my wife lent him out of her purse, by sixpence a time) besides his lodging: I would I had it. I shall ha'it, he says, the next Action. Helter skelter, hang sorrow, care'll kill a cat, up-tails all, and a louse for the hangman.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit]</stage>
</div2>

<div2 type="scene" n="4" id="d12">
<head>Act I, Scene iv</head>
<stage type="setting">BOBADILL is discovered lying on his bench</stage>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Hostess, hostess.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter TIB]</stage>

<sp><speaker>TIB</speaker>
<p>What say you, sir?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>A cup o' thy small beer, sweet hostess.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>TIB</speaker>
<p>Sir, there's a gentleman, below, would speak with you.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>A gentleman! 'Odso, I am not within.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>TIB</speaker>
<p>My husband told him you were, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>What a plague--what meant he?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[Below]</stage> <p>Captain Bobadill?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Who's there? (Take away the basin, good hostess.) Come up, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>TIB</speaker>
<p>He would desire you to come up, sir.</p> <stage type="setting">[Enter MATTHEW]</stage> <p>You come into a cleanly house, here.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit]</stage>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>'Save you, sir. 'Save you, Captain.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Gentle Master Matthew! Is it you, sir? Please you sit down.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Thank you, good Captain; you may see, I am somewhat audacious.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Not so, sir. I was requested to supper last night by a sort of gallants, where you were wished for, and drunk to, I assure you.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Vouchsafe me, by whom, good Captain.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Marry, by young Wellbred, and others. Why, hostess, a stool here, for this gentleman.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>No haste, sir, 'tis very well.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Body of me! It was so late ere we parted last night, I can scarce open my eyes, yet; I was but new risen, as you came. How passes the day abroad, sir? You can tell.</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-016"/>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Faith, some half hour to seven. Now, trust me, you have an exceeding fine lodging here, very neat, and private!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Aye, sir; sit down, I pray you. Master Matthew, in any case, possess no gentleman of our acquaintance with notice of my lodging.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Who? I sir? No.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Not that I need to care who know it, for the cabin is convenient, but in regard I would not be too popular, and generally visited, as some are.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>True, Captain, I conceive you.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>For, do you see, sir, by the heart of valour in me--except it be to some peculiar and choice spirits, to whom I am  extraordinarily engaged, as yourself, or so--I could not extend thus far.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Oh Lord, sir, I resolve so.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>I confess, I love a cleanly and quiet privacy, above all the tumult and roar of fortune. What new book ha' you there? What! 'Go by, Hieronymo'?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Aye, did you ever see it acted? Is't not well penned?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Well penned? I would fain see all the poets of these times pen such another play as that was! They'll prate and swagger, and keep a stir of art and devices, when (as I am a gentleman) read 'em, they are the most shallow, pitiful, barren fellows that live upon the face of the earth, again!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Indeed, here are a number of fine speeches in this book! 'Oh eyes, no eyes, but fountains fraught with tears'! There's a conceit!  'Fountains fraught with tears'! 'O life, no life, but lively form of death'! Another! 'Oh world, no world, but mass of public wrongs'!  A third! 'Confused and filled with murder and misdeeds'! A fourth!  Oh, the Muses! Is't not excellent? Is't not simply the best that ever you heard, Captain? Ha? How do you like it?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>'Tis good.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[Reads]</stage>
<lg>
<l>To thee, the purest object to my sense,</l>
<l>The most refind essence heaven covers,</l>
<l>Send I these lines, wherein I do commence</l>
<l>The happy state of turtle-billing lovers.</l>
<l>If they prove rough, unpolished, harsh and rude,</l>
<l>Haste made the waste. Thus, mildly, I conclude.</l>
<l>BOBADILL is making him ready all this while</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Nay, proceed, proceed. Where's this?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>This, sir? A toy o' mine own, in my nonage: the infancy of my Muses! But when will you come and see my study? Good faith, I can show you some very good things I have done of late. That boot becomes your leg passing well, Captain, methinks!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>So, so; it's the fashion gentlemen now use.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Troth, Captain, an' now you speak o' the fashion, Master  Wellbred's elder brother and I are fall'n out exceedingly.  This other day, I happened to enter into some discourse of a hanger, which I assure you, both for fashion and workmanship, was most peremptory-beautiful, and

<pb id="n101-017"/>

gentleman-like! Yet he condemned and cried it down for the most pied and ridiculous that ever he saw.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Squire Downright? The half-brother? Was't not?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Aye, sir, he.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Hang him, rook, he! Why, he has no more judgement than a  malt-horse. By St. George, I wonder you'd lose a thought upon such an animal: the most peremptory absurd clown of Christendom, this day, he is holden. I protest to you, as I am a gentleman and a soldier, I ne'er changed words with his like. By his discourse, he should eat nothing but hay.  He was born for the manger, pannier, or pack-saddle! He has not so much as a good phrase in his belly, but all old iron and rusty proverbs! A good commodity for some smith, to make hobnails of.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Aye, and he thinks to carry it away with his manhood still, where he comes. He brags he will gi' me the bastinado, as I hear.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>How! He the bastinado! How came he by that word, trow?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Nay, indeed, he said cudgel me; I termed it so for my more grace.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>That may be: for I was sure, it was none of his word. But, when?  When said he so?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Faith, yesterday, they say: a young gallant, a friend of mine told me so.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>By the foot of Pharaoh, an' 'twere my case now, I should send him a chartel, presently. The bastinado! A most proper, and sufficient dependence, warranted by the great Caranza. Come hither. You shall chartel him. I'll show you a trick or two you shall kill him with, at pleasure: the first stoccata, if you will, by this air.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Indeed, you have absolute knowledge i' the mystery, I have heard, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Of whom? Of whom ha' you heard it, I beseech you?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Troth, I have heard it spoken of divers, that you have very rare, and un-in-one-breath-utterable skill, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>By heaven, no, not I; no skill i' the earth: some small rudiments i' the science, as to know my time, distance, or so. I have professed it more for noblemen and gentlemen's use than mine own practice, I assure you. Hostess, accommodate us with another bed-staff here, quickly. [Enter TIB] Lend us another bed-staff. [Exit TIB] The woman does not understand the words of action. Look you, sir. Exalt not your point above this state, at any hand, and let your poniard maintain your defence, thus. [Enter TIB with bed-staff] Give it to the gentleman, and leave us. [Exit TIB] So, sir. Come on. Oh, twine your body more about, that you may fall to a more sweet comely gentleman-like guard. So, indifferent. Hollow your body more sir, thus. Now, stand fast o' your left leg, note your distance, keep your due proportion of time--oh, you disorder your point most irregularly!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>How is the bearing of it now, sir?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Oh, out of measure ill! A well-experienced hand would pass upon you, at pleasure.</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-018"/>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>How mean you, sir, pass upon me?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Why, thus, sir (make a thrust at me), come in upon the answer, control your point, and make a full career at the body. The best-practiced gallants of the time, name it the passada: a most desperate thrust, believe it!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Well, come, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Why, you do not manage your weapon with any facility or grace to invite me: I have no spirit to play with you. Your dearth of judgement renders you tedious.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>But one venue, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Venue! Fie. Most gross denomination, as ever I heard. Oh, the stoccata, while you live, sir. Note that. Come, put on your cloak, and we'll go to some private place where you are acquainted, some tavern or so--and have a bit--I'll send for one of these fencers, and he shall breathe you, by my direction; and then I will teach you your trick. You shall kill him with it, at the first, if you please. Why, I will learn you, by the true judgement of the eye, hand, and foot, to control any enemy's point i' the world. Should your adversary confront you with a pistol, 'twere nothing, by this hand, you should, by the same rule, control his bullet, in a line; except it were hail-shot, and spread. What money ha' you about you, Master Matthew?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Faith, I ha' not past a two shillings, or so.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>'Tis somewhat with the least; but, come. We will have a bunch of radish and salt, to taste our wine; and a pipe of tobacco, to close the orifice of the stomach; and then we'll call upon young Wellbred. Perhaps we shall meet the Corydon, his brother, there, and put him to the question.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exeunt]</stage>
</div2>
</div1>

<div1 type="act" n="2" id="d13">
<head>Act II</head>

<div2 type="scene" n="1" id="d14">
<head>Act II, Scene i</head>

<stage type="setting">[Enter] KITELY, CASH [and] DOWNRIGHT</stage>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Thomas, come hither,</l>
<l>There lies a note, within upon my desk;</l>
<l>Here, take my key; it is no matter, neither.</l>
<l>Where is the boy?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Within, sir, i' the warehouse.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Let him tell over, straight, that Spanish gold,</l>
<l>And weigh it, with th' pieces of eight. Do you</l>
<l>See the delivery of those silver stuffs,</l>
<l>To Master Lucar. Tell him, if he will,</l>
<l>He shall ha' the grograns, at the rate I told him,</l>
<l>And I will meet him on the Exchange, anon.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<p>Good, sir.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit]</stage>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>Do you see that fellow, brother Downright?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Aye, what of him?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>He is a jewel, brother.</l>

<pb id="n101-019"/>

<l>I took him of a child, up, at my door,</l>
<l>And christened him, gave him mine own name, Thomas;</l>
<l>Since bred him at the Hospital; where proving</l>
<l>A toward imp, I called him home, and taught him</l>
<l>So much, as I have made him my cashier,</l>
<l>And given him, who had none, a surname, Cash;</l>
<l>And find him in his place so full of faith</l>
<l>That I durst trust my life into his hands.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<lg>
<l>So would not I in any bastard's, brother--</l>
<l>As it is like he is--although I knew</l>
<l>Myself his father. But you said y'had somewhat</l>
<l>To tell me, gentle brother: what is't? What is't?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Faith, I am very loath to utter it,</l>
<l>As fearing, it may hurt your patience:</l>
<l>But that I know your judgement is of strength,</l>
<l>Against the nearness of affection--</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>What need this circumstance? Pray you be direct.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>I will not say how much I do ascribe</l>
<l>Unto your friendship; nor, in what regard</l>
<l>I hold your love; but, let my past behaviour,</l>
<l>And usage of your sister, but confirm</l>
<l>How well I've been affected to your-</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>You are too tedious, come to the matter, the matter.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Then, without further ceremony, thus.</l>
<l>My brother Wellbred, sir, I know not how,</l>
<l>Of late is much declined in what he was,</l>
<l>And greatly altered in his disposition.</l>
<l>When he came first to lodge here in my house,</l>
<l>Ne'er trust me if I were not proud of him:</l>
<l>Methought he bare himself in such a fashion,</l>
<l>So full of man, and sweetness in his carriage,</l>
<l>And (what was chief) it showed not borrowed in him,</l>
<l>But all he did became him as his own,</l>
<l>And seemed as perfect, proper, and possessed</l>
<l>As breath with life, or colour with the blood.</l>
<l>But, now, his course is so irregular,</l>
<l>So loose, affected, and deprived of grace,</l>
<l>And he himself withal so far fall'n off</l>
<l>From that first place, as scarce no note remains,</l>
<l>To tell men's judgements where he lately stood.</l>
<l>He's grown a stranger to all due respect,</l>
<l>Forgetful of his friends, and not content</l>
<l>To stale himself in all societies,</l>
<l>He makes my house here common as a mart,</l>
<l>A theatre, a public receptacle</l>

<pb id="n101-020"/>

<l>For giddy humour, and diseased riot;</l>
<l>And here (as in a tavern, or a stews)</l>
<l>He and his wild associates spend their hours,</l>
<l>In repetition of lascivious jests;</l>
<l>Swear, leap, drink, dance, and revel night by night;</l>
<l>Control my servants; and indeed what not?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>'Sdeynes, I know not what I should say to him, i' the whole world! He values me at a cracked three-farthings, for aught I see: it will never out o' the flesh that's bred i' the bone! I have told him enough, one would think, if that would serve. But counsel to him is as good as a shoulder of mutton to a sick horse. Well! He knows what to trust to, 'fore George. Let him spend, and spend, and domineer, till his heart ache; an' he think to be relieved by me, when he is got into one o' your city pounds, the Counters, he has the wrong sow by the ear, i' faith; and claps his dish at the wrong man's door. I'll lay my hand o' my halfpenny ere I part with't to fetch him out, I'll assure him.</p>
</sp>

<sp>
<speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>Nay, good brother, let it not trouble you thus.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>'Sdeath, he mads me, I could eat my very spur-leathers, for anger!  But why are you so tame? Why do you not speak to him, and tell him how he disquiets your house?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Oh, there are divers reasons to dissuade, brother.</l>
<l>But, would yourself vouchsafe to travail in it,</l>
<l>(Though but with plain and easy circumstance),</l>
<l>It would both come much better to his sense,</l>
<l>And savour less of stomach, or of passion.</l>
<l>You are his elder brother, and that title</l>
<l>Both gives and warrants you authority;</l>
<l>Which (by your presence seconded) must breed</l>
<l>A kind of duty in him, and regard;</l>
<l>Whereas, if I should intimate the least</l>
<l>It would but add contempt to his neglect,</l>
<l>Heap worse on ill, make up a pile of hatred</l>
<l>That, in the rearing, would come tottering down,</l>
<l>And, in the ruin, bury all our love.</l>
<l>Nay, more than this, brother, if I should speak</l>
<l>He would be ready from his heat of humour,</l>
<l>And overflowing of the vapour in him,</l>
<l>To blow the ears of his familiars</l>
<l>With the false breath of telling what disgraces,</l>
<l>And low disparagements, I had put upon him.</l>
<l>Whilst they, sir, to relieve him in the fable,</l>
<l>Make their loose comments upon every word,</l>
<l>Gesture, or look, I use; mock me all over,</l>
<l>From my flat cap unto my shining shoes;</l>
<l>And, out of their impetuous rioting fant'sies,</l>

<pb id="n101-021"/>

<l>Beget some slander, that shall dwell with me.</l>
<l>And what would that be, think you? Marry, this:</l>
<l>They would give out--because my wife is fair,</l>
<l>Myself but lately married, and my sister</l>
<l>Here sojourning a virgin in my house--</l>
<l>That I were jealous! Nay, as sure as death,</l>
<l>That they would say. And how that I had quarrelled</l>
<l>My brother purposely, thereby to find</l>
<l>An apt pretext to banish them my house.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Mass, perhaps so: they're like enough to do it.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Brother, they would, believe it: so should I,</l>
<l>Like one of these penurious quack-salvers,</l>
<l>But set the bills up to mine own disgrace,</l>
<l>And try experiments upon myself;</l>
<l>Lend scorn and envy opportunity</l>
<l>To stab my reputation, and good name-</l>
</lg>
</sp>


<stage type="setting">[Enter] MATTHEW [and] BOBADILL</stage>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>I will speak to him--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Speak to him? Away, by the foot of Pharaoh, you shall not, you shall not do him that grace.</p> <stage type="delivery">[To Kitely]</stage> <p>The time of day to you, gentleman o' the house. Is Master Wellbred stirring?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>How then? What should he do?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[To Kitely]</stage> <p>Gentleman of the house, it is to you: is he within, sir?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>He came not to his lodging tonight sir, I assure you.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[To Bobadill]</stage> <p>Why, do you hear? You.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>The gentleman-citizen hath satisfied me, I'll talk to no scavenger.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exeunt MATTHEW and BOBADILL]</stage>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>How, scavenger? Stay sir, stay.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>Nay, brother Downright.</p> <stage type="delivery">[Restrains him from attacking Bobadill]</stage>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>'Heart! Stand you away, an' you love me.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>You shall not follow him now, I pray you, brother, good faith  you shall not: I will overrule you.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Ha? Scavenger? Well, go to, I say little; but, by this good day (God forgive me I should swear) if I put it up so, say I am the rankest cow that ever pissed. 'Sdeynes, an' I swallow this, I'll ne'er draw my sword in the sight of Fleet Street again, while I live: I'll sit in a barn, with madge-howlet, and catch mice first. Scavenger? 'Heart, and I'll go near to fill that huge tumbrel-slop of yours, with somewhat, an' I have good luck: your Gargantua breech cannot carry it away so.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>Oh do not fret yourself thus, never think on't.</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-022"/>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>These are my brother's consorts, these! These are his comrades, his walking mates! He's a gallant, a Cavaliero too, right hangman cut! Let me not live, an' I could not find in my heart to swinge the whole gang of 'em, one after another, and begin with him first. I am grieved it should be said he is my brother, and take these courses. Well, as he brews, so he shall drink, 'fore George, again. Yet, he shall hear on't, and that tightly too, an' I live, i' faith.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>But, brother, let your reprehension, then,</l>
<l>Run in an easy current, not o'er-high</l>
<l>Carried with rashness, or devouring choler;</l>
<l>But rather use the soft persuading way</l>
<l>Whose powers will work more gently, and compose</l>
<l>Th'imperfect thoughts you labour to reclaim:</l>
<l>More winning than enforcing the consent.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Aye, aye, let me alone for that, I warrant you. Bell rings</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>How now? Oh, the bell rings to breakfast.</l>
<l>Brother, I pray you go in, and bear my wife</l>
<l>Company till I come; I'll but give order</l>
<l>For some dispatch of business to my servants--</l>
</lg>

<stage type="setting">[Exit DOWNRIGHT]</stage>

<stage type="setting">[COB passes by with his tankard]</stage>

<p>What, Cob? Our maids will have you by the back, i' faith, for coming so late this morning.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Perhaps so, sir; take heed somebody have not them by the belly, for walking so late in the evening.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit]</stage>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Well, yet my troubled spirit's somewhat eased,</l>
<l>Though not reposed in that security</l>
<l>As I could wish. But I must be content.</l>
<l>Howe'er I set a face on't to the world,</l>
<l>Would I had lost this finger, at a venture,</l>
<l>So Wellbred had ne'er lodged within my house.</l>
<l>Why't cannot be, where there is such resort</l>
<l>Of wanton gallants, and young revellers,</l>
<l>That any woman should be honest long.</l>
<l>Is't like, that factious beauty will preserve</l>
<l>The public weal of chastity, unshaken,</l>
<l>When such strong motives muster, and make head</l>
<l>Against her single peace? No, no. Beware,</l>
<l>When mutual appetite doth meet to treat,</l>
<l>And spirits of one kind, and quality,</l>
<l>Come once to parley, in the pride of blood:</l>
<l>It is no slow conspiracy that follows.</l>

<pb id="n101-023"/>

<l>Well, to be plain, if I but thought the time</l>
<l>Had answered their affections, all the world</l>
<l>Should not persuade me, but I were a cuckold.</l>
<l>Marry, I hope, they ha' not got that start:</l>
<l>For opportunity hath balked 'em yet,</l>
<l>And shall do still, while I have eyes and ears</l>
<l>To attend the impositions of my heart.</l>
<l>My presence shall be as an iron bar,</l>
<l>'Twixt the conspiring motions of desire:</l>
<l>Yea, every look or glance mine eye ejects</l>
<l>Shall check occasion, as one doth his slave,</l>
<l>When he forgets the limits of prescription.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter DAME KITELY and BRIDGET]</stage>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<p>Sister Bridget, pray you fetch down the rosewater above in the closet. [Exit BRIDGET] Sweetheart, will you come in to breakfast?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[Aside]</stage> <p>An' she have overheard me now?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<p>I pray thee, good muss, we stay for you.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[Aside]</stage> <p>By heaven I would not for a thousand angels!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<p>What ail you sweetheart, are you not well? Speak, good muss.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>Troth, my head aches extremely, on a sudden.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[Feeling his forehead]</stage> <p>Oh, the Lord!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>How now? What?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<p>Alas, how it burns! Muss, keep you warm; good truth, it is this new disease! There's a number are troubled withal! For love's sake, sweetheart, come in, out of the air.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[Aside]</stage> <p>How simple, and how subtle are her answers!
A new disease, and many troubled with it!
Why, true: she heard me, all the world to nothing.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<p>I pray thee, good sweetheart, come in; the air will do you harm, in troth.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[Aside]</stage>
<lg>
<l>The air! She has me i' the wind! Sweetheart!</l>
<l>I'll come to you presently: 'twill away, I hope.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<p>Pray heaven it do.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit DAME KITELY]</stage>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>A new disease? I know not, new or old,</l>
<l>But it may well be called poor mortals' plague:</l>
<l>For, like a pestilence, it doth infect</l>
<l>The houses of the brain. First, it begins</l>
<l>Solely to work upon the fantasy,</l>
<l>Filling her seat with such pestiferous air,</l>
<l>As soon corrupts the judgement; and from thence</l>
<l>Sends like contagion to the memory;</l>
<l>Still each to other giving the infection.</l>
<l>Which, as a subtle vapour, spreads itself,</l>
<l>Confusedly, through every sensive part,</l>
<l>Till not a thought or motion in the mind,</l>

<pb id="n101-024"/>

<l>Be free from the black poison of suspect.</l>
<l>Ah, but what misery 's it, to know this?</l>
<l>Or, knowing it, to want the mind's erection</l>
<l>In such extremes? Well, I will once more strive</l>
<l>(In spite of this black cloud) myself to be,</l>
<l>And shake the fever off, that thus shakes me.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit]</stage>
</div2>

<div2 type="scene" n="2" id="d15">
<head>Act II, Scene ii</head>

<stage type="setting">[Enter] BRAINWORM [disguised as a soldier]</stage>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>'Slid, I cannot choose but laugh, to see myself translated thus, from a poor creature to a creator; for now must I create an intolerable sort of lies, or my present profession loses the grace; and yet the lie to a man of my coat is as ominous a fruit as the fico. Oh sir, it holds for good polity ever, to have that outwardly in vilest estimation, that inwardly is most dear to us. So much for my borrowed shape. Well, the troth is, my old master intends to follow my young, dry foot, over Moorfields to London this morning; now I, knowing of this hunting-match, or rather conspiracy, and to insinuate with my young master (for so must we that are blue-waiters, and men of hope and service do, or perhaps we may wear motley at the year's end, and who wears motley, you know) have got me afore, in this disguise, determining here to lie in ambuscado, and intercept him in the mid-way. If I can but get his cloak, his purse, his hat, nay, anything, to cut him off, that is, to stay his journey, veni, vidi, vici, I may say with Captain Caesar, I am made for ever, i' faith. Well, now must I practice to get the true garb of one of these lance-knights, my arm here, and my</p> <stage type="setting">[Enter EDWARD and STEPHEN]</stage> <p>--young master! And his cousin, Master Stephen, as I am true counterfeit man of war, and no soldier!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>So sir, and how then, coz?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[Searching himself]</stage> <p>'Sfoot, I have lost my purse, I think.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>How? Lost your purse? Where? When had you it?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>I cannot tell. Stay!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>'Slid, I am afeared they will know me, would I could get by them.</p> <stage type="delivery">[Moves aside to conceal himself]</stage>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>What? Ha' you it?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>No, I think I was bewitched, I--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Nay, do not weep the loss, hang it, let it go.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Oh, it's here: no, an' it had been lost, I had not cared, but for a jet ring Mistress Mary sent me.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>A jet ring? Oh, the posy, the posy?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Fine, i' faith! 'Though fancy sleep, my love is deep.' Meaning that though I did not fancy her, yet she loved me dearly.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Most excellent!</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-025"/>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>And then, I sent her another, and my posy was: 'The deeper, the sweeter, I'll be judged by St. Peter.'</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>How, by St. Peter? I do not conceive that!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Marry, St. Peter, to make up the metre.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Well, there the Saint was your good patron, he helped you at your need: thank him, thank him.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<stage type="setting">[He is come back]</stage>
<p>I cannot take leave on 'em, so: I will venture, come what will. Gentlemen, please you change a few crowns for a very excellent good blade, here? I am a poor gentleman, a soldier, one that (in the better state of my fortunes) scorned so mean a refuge, but now it is the humour of necessity to have it so. You seem to be gentlemen, well affected to martial men, else I should rather die with silence, than live with shame; however, vouchsafe to remember, it is my want speaks, not myself. This condition agrees not with my spirit--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Where hast thou served?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>May it please you, sir, in all the late wars of Bohemia, Hungaria, Dalmatia, Poland, where not, sir? I have been a poor servitor, by sea and land, any time this fourteen years, and followed the fortunes of the best commanders in Christendom. I was twice shot at the taking of Aleppo, once at the relief of Vienna; I have been at Marseilles, Naples, and the Adriatic gulf, a gentleman-slave in the galleys, thrice, where I was most dangerously shot in the head, through both the thighs, and yet, being thus maimed, I am void of maintenance, nothing left me but my scars, the noted marks of my resolution.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>How will you sell this rapier, friend?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Generous sir, I refer it to your own judgement; you are a gentleman, give me what you please.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>True, I am a gentleman, I know that, friend; but what though? I pray you say, what would you ask?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>I assure you, the blade may become the side or thigh of the best prince in Europe.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Aye, with a velvet scabbard, I think.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Nay, an't be mine, it shall have a velvet scabbard, coz, that's flat: I'd not wear it as 'tis, an' you would give me an angel.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>At your worship's pleasure, sir: nay, 'tis a most pure Toledo.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>I had rather it were a Spaniard! But tell me, what shall I give you for it? An' it had a silver hilt--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Come, come, you shall not buy it; [To BRAINWORM] hold, there's a shilling fellow, take thy rapier.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Why, but I will buy it now, because you say so, and there's another shilling, fellow. I scorn to be outbidden. What, shall I walk with a cudgel, like Higginbottom? And may have a rapier, for money?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>You may buy one in the city.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Tut, I'll buy this i' the field, so I will, I have a mind to't, because 'tis a field rapier. Tell me your lowest price.</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-026"/>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>You shall not buy it, I say.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>By this money, but I will, though I give more than 'tis worth.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Come away, you are a fool.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Friend, I am a fool, that's granted: but I'll have it, for that word's sake.</p> <stage type="delivery">[To Brainworm]</stage> <p>Follow me, for your money.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>At your service, sir.</p>
</sp>


<stage type="setting">[Exeunt]</stage>
</div2>

<div2 type="scene" n="3" id="d16">
<head>Act II, Scene iii</head>
<stage type="setting">[Enter] KNOWELL</stage>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>I cannot lose the thought, yet, of this letter</l>
<l>Sent to my son; nor leave t'admire the change</l>
<l>Of manners, and the breeding of our youth,</l>
<l>Within the kingdom, since myself was one.</l>
<l>When I was young, he lived not in the stews,</l>
<l>Durst have conceived a scorn, and uttered it,</l>
<l>On a grey head: age was authority</l>
<l>Against a buffoon; and a man had, then,</l>
<l>A certain reverence paid unto his years,</l>
<l>That had none due unto his life. So much</l>
<l>The sanctity of some prevailed, for others.</l>
<l>But, now, we all are fall'n: youth, from their fear;</l>
<l>And age, from that which bred it, good example.</l>
<l>Nay, would ourselves were not the first, even parents,</l>
<l>That did destroy the hopes in our own children;</l>
<l>Or they not learned our vices in their cradles,</l>
<l>And sucked in our ill customs with their milk.</l>
<l>Ere all their teeth be born, or they can speak,</l>
<l>We make their palates cunning! The first words</l>
<l>We form their tongues with, are licentious jests!</l>
<l>Can it call "whore"? Cry "bastard"? Oh, then, kiss it,</l>
<l>A witty child! Can't swear? The father's darling!</l>
<l>Give it two plums. Nay, rather than't shall learn</l>
<l>No bawdy song, the mother'herself will teach it!</l>
<l>But this is in the infancy, the days</l>
<l>Of the long coat: when it puts on the breeches,</l>
<l>It will put off all this. Aye, it is like:</l>
<l>When it is gone into the bone already.</l>
<l>No, no: this dye goes deeper than the coat,</l>
<l>Or shirt, or skin. It stains, unto the liver</l>
<l>And heart, in some. And rather than it should not,</l>
<l>Note what we fathers do! Look how we live!</l>
<l>What mistresses we keep! At what expense,</l>
<l>In our sons' eyes! Where they may handle our gifts,</l>

<pb id="n101-027"/>

<l>Hear our lascivious courtships, see our dalliance,</l>
<l>Taste of the same provoking meats with us,</l>
<l>To ruin of our states! Nay, when our own</l>
<l>Portion is fled, to prey on their remainder,</l>
<l>We call them into fellowship of vice!</l>
<l>Bait 'em with the young chambermaid, to seal!</l>
<l>And teach 'em all bad ways, to buy affection!</l>
<l>This is one path! But there are millions more,</l>
<l>In which we spoil our own with leading them.</l>
<l>Well, I thank heaven, I never yet was he,</l>
<l>That travelled with my son, before sixteen,</l>
<l>To show him the Venetian courtesans.</l>
<l>Nor read the grammar of cheating I had made</l>
<l>To my sharp boy, at twelve: repeating still</l>
<l>The rule, 'Get money'; still, 'Get money, boy;</l>
<l>No matter by what means; money will do</l>
<l>More, boy, than my Lord's letter'. Neither have I</l>
<l>Dressed snails or mushrooms curiously before him,</l>
<l>Perfumed my sauces, and taught him to make 'em;</l>
<l>Preceding still, with my grey gluttony,</l>
<l>At all the ordinaries; and only feared</l>
<l>His palate should degenerate, not his manners.</l>
<l>These are the trade of fathers, now! However</l>
<l>My son, I hope, hath met within my threshold</l>
<l>None of these household precedents; which are strong</l>
<l>And swift to rape youth to their precipice.</l>
<l>But, let the house at home be ne'er so clean--</l>
<l>Swept, or kept sweet from filth; nay, dust, and cobwebs--</l>
<l>If he will live abroad, with his companions,</l>
<l>In dung, and leystalls; it is worth a fear.</l>
<l>Nor is the danger of conversing less</l>
<l>Than all that I have mentioned of example.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter BRAINWORM, still disguised]</stage>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[Aside]</stage> <p>My master? Nay, faith, have at you: I am fleshed now, I have sped so well.</p> <stage type="delivery">[To Knowell]</stage> <p>Worshipful sir, I beseech you, respect the estate of a poor soldier; I am ashamed of this base course of life (God's my comfort) but extremity provokes me to't, what remedy?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>I have not for you, now.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>By the faith I bear unto truth, gentleman, it is no ordinary custom in me, but only to preserve manhood. I protest to you, a man I have been, a man I may be, by your sweet bounty.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>'Pray thee, good friend, be satisfied.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Good sir, by that hand, you may do the part of a kind gentleman, in lending a poor soldier the price of two cans of beer (a matter of small value); the king of heaven shall pay you, and I shall rest thankful; sweet worship--</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-028"/>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>Nay, an' you be so importunate--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Oh, tender sir, need will have his course: I was not made to this vile use! Well, the edge of the enemy could not have abated me so much. It's hard when a man hath served in his Prince's cause, and be thus-- He weeps Honourable worship, let me derive a small piece of silver from you, it shall not be given in the course of time, by this good ground, I was fain to pawn my rapier last night for a poor supper, I had sucked the hilts long before, I am a pagan else: sweet honour.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Believe me, I am taken with some wonder,</l>
<l>To think a fellow of thy outward presence</l>
<l>Should (in the frame and fashion of his mind)</l>
<l>Be so degenerate, and sordid-base!</l>
<l>Art thou a man? And sham'st thou not to beg?</l>
<l>To practice such a servile kind of life?</l>
<l>Why, were thy education ne'er so mean,</l>
<l>Having thy limbs, a thousand fairer courses</l>
<l>Offer themselves to thy election.</l>
<l>Either the wars might still supply thy wants,</l>
<l>Or service of some virtuous gentleman,</l>
<l>Or honest labour: nay, what can I name,</l>
<l>But would become thee better than to beg?</l>
<l>But men of thy condition feed on sloth,</l>
<l>As doth the beetle, on the dung she breeds in,</l>
<l>Not caring how the metal of your minds</l>
<l>Is eaten with the rust of idleness.</l>
<l>Now, afore me, whate'er he be that should</l>
<l>Relieve a person of thy quality,</l>
<l>While thou insist's in this loose desperate course,</l>
<l>I would esteem the sin, not thine, but his.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Faith, sir, I would gladly find some other course, if so--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>Aye, you'd gladly find it, but you will not seek it.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Alas, sir, where should a man seek? In the wars, there's no ascent by desert in these days, but--and for service, would it were as soon purchased, as wished for (the air's my comfort). I know what I would say--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>What's thy name?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Please you, Fitz-sword, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Fitz-sword?</l>
<l>Say that a man should entertain thee now,</l>
<l>Wouldst thou be honest, humble, just, and true?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Sir, by the place and honour of a soldier--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Nay, nay, I like not those affected oaths;</l>
<l>Speak plainly man: what thinkst thou of my words?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Nothing, sir, but wish my fortunes were as happy, as my service should be honest.</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-029"/>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Well, follow me, I'll prove thee, if thy deeds</l>
<l>Will carry a proportion to thy words.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Yes sir, straight, I'll but garter my hose.</p> <stage type="delivery">[Exit KNOWELL]</stage> <p>Oh that my belly were hooped now, for I am ready to burst with laughing! Never was bottle or bagpipe fuller. 'Slid, was there ever seen a fox in years to betray himself thus? Now shall I be possessed of all his counsels; and, by that conduit, my young master. Well, he is resolved to prove my honesty; faith, and I am resolved to prove his patience: oh, I shall abuse him intolerably. This small piece of service will bring him clean out of love with the soldier, forever. He will never come within the sign of it, the sight of a cassock, or a musket-rest again. He will hate the musters at Mile End for it, to his dying day. It's no matter, let the world think me a bad counterfeit if I cannot give him the slip, at an instant; why, this is better than to have stayed his journey! Well, I'll follow him: oh, how I long to be employed.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit]</stage>
</div2>
</div1>

<div1 type="act" n="3" id="d17">
<head>Act III</head>

<div2 type="scene" n="1" id="d18">
<head>Act III, Scene i</head>

<stage type="setting">[Enter] MATTHEW, WELLBRED [and] BOBADILL</stage>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Yes, faith, sir, we were at your lodging to seek you, too.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Oh, I came not there tonight.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Your brother delivered us as much.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Who? My brother Downright?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>He. Master Wellbred, I know not in what kind you hold me, but let me say to you this: as sure as honour, I esteem it so much out of the sunshine of reputation to throw the least beam of regard upon such a--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Sir, I must hear no ill words of my brother.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>I protest to you, as I have a thing to be saved about me, I never saw any gentleman-like part--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Good Captain, faces about, to some other discourse.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>With your leave, sir, an' there were no more men living upon the face of the earth, I should not fancy him, by St. George.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Troth, nor I, he is of a rustical cut, I know not how: he doth not carry himself like a gentleman of fashion--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Oh, Master Matthew, that's a grace peculiar but to a few; quos aequus amavit Jupiter.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>I understand you sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>No question, you do, or you do not, sir.</p>
<stage type="setting">[EDWARD] enters [followed by STEPHEN]</stage>
<p>Ned Knowell! By my soul welcome; how dost thou, sweet spirit, my genius. 'Slid I shall love Apollo and the mad Thespian girls the better, while I live, for this; my dear Fury: now I see there's some love in thee!  Sirrah, these be the two I writ to thee of. Nay, what a drowsy humour is this now? Why dost thou not speak?</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-030"/>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Oh, you are a fine gallant, you sent me a rare letter!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Why, was't not rare?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Yes, I'll be sworn, I was ne'er guilty of reading the like: match it in all Pliny, or Symmachus' epistles, and I'll have my judgement burned in the ear for a rogue; make much of thy vein, for it is inimitable. But I mar'l what camel it was, that had the carriage of it? For doubtless, he was no ordinary beast that brought it!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Why?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Why, sayst thou? Why dost thou think that any reasonable  creature, especially in the morning (the sober time of the day too), could have mista'en my father for me?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>'Slid, you jest, I hope?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Indeed, the best use we can turn it to, is to make a jest on't, now; but I'll assure you, my father had the full view o' your  flourishing style, some hour before I saw it.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>What a dull slave was this! But, sirrah, what said he to it, i' faith?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Nay, I know not what he said; but I have a shrewd guess what he thought.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>What?  What?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Marry, that thou art some strange dissolute young fellow, and I a grain or two better, for keeping thee company.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Tut, that thought is like the moon in her last quarter, 'twill  change shortly; but, sirrah, I pray thee be acquainted with my  two hang-bys here.  Thou wilt take exceeding pleasure in 'em if thou hear'st 'em once go: my wind instruments. I'll wind 'em up--but what strange piece of silence is this? The sign of the Dumb Man?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Oh, sir, a kinsman of mine, one that may make your music the fuller, an' he please: he has his humour, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Oh, what is't?  What is't?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Nay, I'll neither do your judgement nor his folly that wrong, as to prepare your apprehension: I'll leave him to the mercy o' your search; if you can take him, so.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Well, Captain Bobadill, Master Matthew, pray you know this gentleman here, he is a friend of mine, and one that will deserve your affection.</p> <stage type="delivery">[To MASTER STEPHEN]</stage> <p>I know not your name sir, but I shall be glad of any occasion to render me more familiar to you.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>My name is Master Stephen, sir, I am this gentleman's own cousin, sir, his father is mine uncle, sir, I am somewhat melancholy, but you shall command me, sir, in whatsoever is incident to a gentleman.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[To [EDWARD] KNOWELL]</stage>  <p>Sir, I must tell you this, I am no general man, but for Master Wellbred's sake (you may embrace it at what height of favour you please) I do communicate with you; and conceive you to be a gentleman of some parts; I love few words.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>And I fewer, sir. I have scarce enow to thank you.</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-031"/>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>To MASTER STEPHEN But are you indeed, sir? So given to it?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Aye, truly, sir, I am mightily given to melancholy.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Oh, it's your only fine humour, sir, your true melancholy breeds your perfect fine wit, sir: I am melancholy myself divers times, sir, and then do I no more but take pen and paper presently, and overflow you half a score, or a dozen of sonnets, at a sitting.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Aside  Sure, he utters them then, by the gross.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Truly, sir, and I love such things, out of measure.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>I' faith, better than in measure, I'll undertake.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Why, I pray you, sir, make use of my study, it's at your  service.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>I thank you sir, I shall be bold, I warrant you; have you a stool there, to be melancholy upon?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>That I have, sir, and some papers there of mine own doing, at idle hours, that you'll say there's some sparks of wit in 'em, when you see them.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[Aside]</stage> <p>Would the sparks would kindle once, and become a fire amongst 'em, I might see self-love burnt for her heresy.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Cousin, is it well? Am I melancholy enough?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Oh, aye, excellent!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Captain Bobadill: why muse you so?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>He is melancholy, too.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Faith, sir, I was thinking of a most honourable piece of service, was performed tomorrow, being St. Mark's day: shall be some ten years, now.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>In what place, Captain?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Why, at the beleag'ring of Strigonium, where, in less than two hours, seven hundred resolute gentlemen as any were in Europe lost their lives upon the breach. I'll tell you, gentlemen, it was the first, but the best leaguer, that ever I beheld, with these eyes, except the taking in of--what do you call it, last year, by the Genowayes?--but that (of all other) was the most fatal and dangerous exploit that ever I was ranged in, since I first bore arms before the face of the enemy, as I am a gentleman, and soldier.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>'So, I had as lief as an angel, I could swear as well as that gentleman!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Then, you were a servitor, at both it seems! At Strigonium? And what-do-you-call't?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Oh Lord, sir! By St. George, I was the first man that entered the breach; and, had I not effected it with resolution, I had been slain, if I had had a million of lives.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>'Twas pity you had not ten: a cat's, and your own, i' faith.  But, was it possible?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[Aside to STEPHEN]</stage> <p>'Pray you, mark this discourse, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[To MATTHEW]</stage> <p>So I do.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>I assure you (upon my reputation) 'tis true, and yourself shall confess.</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-032"/>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>You must bring me to the rack first.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Observe me judicially, sweet sir: they had planted me three demi-culverins, just in the mouth of the breach; now, sir (as we were to give on), their master-gunner (a man of no mean skill and mark, you must think) confronts me with his linstock, ready to give fire; I, spying his intendment, discharged my petrionel in his bosom, and with these single arms, my poor rapier, ran violently upon the Moors that guarded the ordnance, and put 'em pell-mell to the sword.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>To the sword? To the rapier, Captain.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Oh, it was a good figure observed, sir! But did you all this, Captain, without hurting your blade?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Without any impeach, o' the earth: you shall perceive sir. It is the most fortunate weapon that ever rid on poor gentleman's thigh: shall I tell you, sir? You talk of Morglay, Excalibur, Durindana, or so? Tut, I lend no credit to that is fabled of 'em, I know the virtue of mine own, and therefore I dare, the boldlier, maintain it.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>I mar'l whether it be a Toledo, or no?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>A most perfect Toledo, I assure you, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>I have a countryman of his, here.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Pray you, let's see, sir: yes, faith, it is!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>This a Toledo? Pish.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Why do you pish, Captain?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>A Fleming, by heaven, I'll buy them for a guilder apiece, an' I would have a thousand of them.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>How say you, cousin? I told you thus much?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Where bought you it, Master Stephen?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Of a scurvy rogue soldier (a hundred of lice go with him), he swore it was a Toledo.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>A poor provant rapier, no better.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Mass, I think it be, indeed, now I look on't better.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Nay, the longer you look on't, the worse. Put it up, put it up.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Well, I will put it up, but by--(I ha' forgot the Captain's oath, I thought to ha' sworn by it)--an' e'er I meet him--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Oh, it is past help now, sir, you must have patience.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Whoreson coney-catching rascal! I could eat the very hilts for anger!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>A sign of good digestion! You have an ostrich stomach, cousin.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>A stomach? Would I had him here, you should see an' I 	had a stomach.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>It's better as 'tis; come, gentlemen, shall we go?</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-033"/>

<stage type="setting">[Enter] BRAINWORM [still disguised]</stage>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>A miracle, cousin, look here! Look here!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Oh, God's lid, by your leave, do you know me, sir?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Aye sir, I know you, by sight.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>You sold me a rapier, did you not?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Yes, marry, did I, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>You said it was a Toledo, ha?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>True, I did so.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>But it is none?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>No, sir, I confess it, it is none.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Do you confess it? Gentlemen, bear witness, he has confessed it.  By God's will, an' you had not confessed it--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Oh cousin, forbear, forbear.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Nay, I have done, cousin.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Why, you have done like a gentleman, he has confessed it, what would you more?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Yes, by his leave, he is a rascal, under his favour, do you see?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Aye, by his leave, he is, and under favour: a pretty piece of civility!</p> <stage type="delivery">[Aside]</stage> <p>Sirrah, how dost thou like him?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Oh, it's a most precious fool, make much on him; I can compare him to nothing more happily than a drum: for  everyone may play upon him.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>No, no, a child's whistle were far the fitter.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Sir, shall I entreat a word with you.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>With me, sir? You have not another Toledo to sell, ha' you?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>You are conceited, sir, <stage type="delivery">[Takes EDWARD aside]</stage> your name is Master Knowell, as I take it?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>You are i' the right; you mean not to proceed in the catechism, do you?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>No, sir, I am none of that coat.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Of as bare a coat, though; well, say sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Faith, sir, I am but servant to the drum extraordinary, and indeed (this smoky varnish being washed off, and three or four patches removed) I appear your worship's in reversion, after the decease of your good father: Brainworm.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Brainworm! 'Slight, what breath of a conjurer hath blown thee hither in this shape?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>The breath o' your letter, sir, this morning: the same that blew you to the Windmill, and your father after you.</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-034"/>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>My father?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Nay, never start, 'tis true, he has followed you over the fields, by the foot, as you would do a hare i' the snow.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Sirrah, Wellbred, what shall we do, sirrah? My father is come over, after me.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Thy father? Where is he?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>At Justice Clement's house here in Coleman Street, where he but stays my return; and then--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Who's this? Brainworm?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>The same, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Why how, i' the name of wit, com'st thou transmuted thus?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Faith, a device, a device; nay, for the love of reason, gentlemen, and avoiding the danger, stand not here, withdraw, and I'll tell you all.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>But, art thou sure he will stay thy return?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Do I live, sir? What a question is that?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>We'll prorogue his expectation, then, a little: Brainworm, thou shalt go with us. Come on, gentlemen, nay, I pray thee, sweet Ned, droop not: 'heart, an' our wits be so wretchedly dull that one old plodding brain can outstrip us all, would we were e'en pressed to make porters of; and serve out the remnant of our days in Thames Street, or at Custom House quay, in a civil war against the carmen.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Amen, amen, amen, say I.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exeunt]</stage>
</div2>

<div2 type="scene" n="2" id="d19">
<head>Act III, Scene ii</head>

<stage type="setting">[Enter] KITELY [and] CASH</stage>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>What says he, Thomas? Did you speak with him?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>He will expect you, sir, within this half hour.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Has he the money ready, can you tell?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Yes, sir, the money was brought in last night.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Oh, that's well; fetch me my cloak, my cloak.</l>
</lg>
<stage type="setting">[Exit CASH]</stage>
<lg>
<l>Stay, let me see, an hour, to go and come;</l>
<l>Aye, that will be the least; and then 'twill be</l>
<l>An hour before I can dispatch with him;</l>
<l>Or very near: well, I will say two hours.</l>
<l>Two hours? Ha? Things never dreamed of yet</l>
<l>May be contrived, aye, and effected too,</l>
<l>In two hours' absence; well, I will not go.</l>
<l>Two hours: no, fleering opportunity,</l>
<l>I will not give your subtlety that scope.</l>
<l>Who will not judge him worthy to be robbed,</l>
<l>That sets his doors wide open to a thief,</l>
<l>And shows the felon where his treasure lies?</l>
<l>Again, what earthy spirit but will attempt</l>

<pb id="n101-035"/>

<l>To taste the fruit of beauty's golden tree,</l>
<l>When leaden sleep seals up the dragon's eyes?</l>
<l>I will not go. Business, go by, for once.</l>
<l>No, beauty, no: you are of too good caract,</l>
<l>To be left so, without a guard, or open!</l>
<l>Your lustre too'll inflame, at any distance,</l>
<l>Draw courtship to you, as a jet doth straws,</l>
<l>Put motion in a stone, strike fire from ice,</l>
<l>Nay, make a porter leap you, with his burden!</l>
<l>You must be then kept up, close, and well-watched,</l>
<l>For, give you opportunity, no quicksand</l>
<l>Devours or swallows swifter! He that lends</l>
<l>His wife (if she be fair) or time, or place,</l>
<l>Compels her to be false. I will not go.</l>
<l>The dangers are too many. And, then, the dressing</l>
<l>Is a most main attractive! Our great heads,</l>
<l>Within the city, never were in safety,</l>
<l>Since our wives wore these little caps: I'll change 'em,</l>
<l>I'll change 'em straight, in mine. Mine shall no more</l>
<l>Wear three-piled acorns, to make my horns ache.</l>
<l>Nor will I go. I am resolved for that.</l>
</lg>
<stage type="setting">[Enter CASH, with cloak]</stage>
<lg>
<l>Carry in my cloak again. Yet, stay. Yet, do, too.</l>
<l>I will defer going, on all occasions.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Sir. Snare, your scrivener, will be there with th' bonds.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>That's true! Fool on me! I had clean forgot it,</l>
<l>I must go. What's o'clock?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Exchange time, sir.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[Aside]</stage>
<p>'Heart, then will Wellbred presently be here, too, With one or other of his loose consorts.</p>
<lg>
<l>I am a knave if I know what to say,</l>
<l>What course to take, or which way to resolve.</l>
<l>My brain (methinks) is like an hourglass,</l>
<l>Wherein my 'maginations run like sands,</l>
<l>Filling up time; but then are turned, and turned;</l>
<l>So that I know not what to stay upon,</l>
<l>And less, to put in act. It shall be so.</l>
<l>Nay, I dare build upon his secrecy,</l>
<l>He knows not to deceive me. Thomas?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Sir.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[Aside]</stage> <lg>
<l>Yet now I have bethought me, too, I will not.</l>
<l>Thomas, is Cob within?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>I think he be, sir.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[Aside]</stage> <lg>
<l>But he'll prate too, there's no speech of him.</l>
<l>No, there were no man o' the earth to Thomas,</l>
<l>If I durst trust him; there is all the doubt.</l>
<l>But, should he have a chink in him, I were gone,</l>
<l>Lost i' my fame for ever: talk for th' Exchange.</l>
<l>The manner he hath stood with, till this present,</l>

<pb id="n101-036"/>

<l>Doth promise no such change! What should I fear then?</l>
<l>Well, come what will, I'll tempt my fortune, once.</l>
<l>Thomas--you may deceive me, but, I hope--</l>
<l>Your love, to me, is more--</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Sir, if a servant's</l>
<l>Duty, with faith, may be called love, you are</l>
<l>More than in hope, you are possessed of it.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>I thank you, heartily, Thomas; gi' me your hand;</l>
<l>With all my heart, good Thomas. I have, Thomas,</l>
<l>A secret to impart unto you--but</l>
<l>When once you have it, I must seal your lips up:</l>
<l>So far I tell you, Thomas.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Sir, for that--</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Nay, hear me out. Think I esteem you, Thomas,</l>
<l>When I will let you in, thus, to my private.</l>
<l>It is a thing sits nearer to my crest</l>
<l>Than thou art ware of, Thomas. If thou should'st</l>
<l>Reveal it, but--</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>How? I reveal it?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Nay,</l>
<l>I do not think thou would'st; but if thou should'st:</l>
<l>'Twere a great weakness.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>A great treachery.</l>
<l>Give it no other name.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Thou wilt not do't, then?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Sir, if I do, mankind disclaim me, ever.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[Aside]</stage> <lg>
<l>He will not swear, he has some reservation,</l>
<l>Some concealed purpose, and close meaning, sure;</l>
<l>Else (being urged so much) how should he choose</l>
<l>But lend an oath to all this protestation?</l>
<l>He's no precisian, that I am certain of.</l>
<l>Nor rigid Roman Catholic. He'll play</l>
<l>At Fayles, and Tick-tack, I have heard him swear.</l>
<l>What should I think of it? Urge him again,</l>
<l>And by some other way? I will do so.</l>
<l>Well, Thomas, thou hast sworn not to disclose;</l>
<l>Yes, you did swear?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Not yet, sir, but I will,</l>
<l>Please you--</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>No, Thomas, I dare take thy word.</l>
<l>But; if thou wilt swear, do, as thou think'st good;</l>
<l>I am resolved without it; at thy pleasure.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>By my soul's safety then, sir, I protest.</l>
<l>My tongue shall ne'er take knowledge of a word</l>
<l>Delivered me in nature of your trust.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>It's too much, these ceremonies need not,</l>
<l>I know thy faith to be as firm as rock.</l>
<l>Thomas, come hither, near: we cannot be</l>
<l>Too private, in this business. So it is--</l>
<l>[Aside] Now he has sworn, I dare the safelier venture--</l>
<l>I have of late, by divers observations--</l>
</lg>
<stage type="delivery">[Aside]</stage>
<lg>
<l>But whether his oath can bind him, yea or no,</l>
<l>Being not taken lawfully? Ha? Say you?</l>

<pb id="n101-037"/>

<l>I will ask counsel, ere I do proceed--</l>
<l>Thomas, it will be now too late to stay,</l>
<l>I'll spy some fitter time soon, or tomorrow.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Sir, at your pleasure.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>I will think. And, Thomas,</l>
<l>I pray you search the books 'gainst my return,</l>
<l>For the receipts 'twixt me and Traps.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>I will, sir.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>And, hear you, if your mistress' brother, Wellbred,</l>
<l>Chance to bring hither any gentlemen</l>
<l>Ere I come back: let one straight bring me word.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Very well, sir.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>To the Exchange; do you hear?</l>
<l>Or here in Coleman Street, to Justice Clement's.</l>
<l>Forget it not, nor be not out of the way.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>I will not, sir.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>I pray you have a care on't.</l>
<l>Or whether he come or no, if any other,</l>
<l>Stranger or else, fail not to send me word.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>I shall not, sir.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Be't your special business</l>
<l>Now, to remember it.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Sir. I warrant you.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>But, Thomas, this is not the secret, Thomas,</l>
<l>I told you of.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>No, sir. I do suppose it.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Believe me, it is not.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Sir. I do believe you.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>By heaven, it is not, that's enough. But, Thomas,</l>
<l>I would not you should utter it, do you see,</l>
<l>To any creature living, yet, I care not.</l>
<l>Well, I must hence. Thomas, conceive thus much.</l>
<l>It was a trial of you, when I meant</l>
<l>So deep a secret to you, I mean not this,</l>
<l>But that I have to tell you, this is nothing, this.</l>
<l>But, Thomas, keep this from my wife, I charge you,</l>
<l>Locked up in silence, midnight, buried here.</l>
</lg>
<stage type="delivery">[Aside]</stage>
<lg>
<l>No greater hell, than to be slave to fear.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit]</stage>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>'Locked up in silence, midnight, buried here'.</l>
<l>Whence should this flood of passion (trow) take head? Ha?</l>
<l>Best dream no longer of this running humour,</l>
<l>For fear I sink! The violence of the stream</l>
<l>Already hath transported me so far,</l>
<l>That I can feel no ground at all! But soft,</l>
<l>Oh, 'tis our water-bearer: somewhat has crossed him, now.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter] COB</stage>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Fasting days? What would you tell me of fasting days? 'Slid, would they were all on a light fire for me. They say, the whole world shall be consumed with fire one day, but would I had these Ember-weeks and villainous Fridays burnt, in the meantime, and then--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<p>Why, how now, Cob, what moves thee to this choler? Ha?</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-038"/>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Collar, Master Thomas? I scorn your collar, I sir, I am none o' your cart-horse, though I carry, and draw water. An' you offer to ride me, with your collar, or halter either, I may hap show you a jade's trick, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<p>Oh, you'll slip your head out of the collar? Why, goodman Cob, you mistake me.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Nay, I have my rheum, and I can be angry as well as another, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<p>Thy rheum, Cob? Thy humour, thy humour! Thou mistak'st.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Humour? Mack, I think it be so, indeed; what is that humour? Some rare thing, I warrant.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<p>Marry, I'll tell thee, Cob: it is a gentleman-like monster, bred, in the special gallantry of our time, by affectation; and fed by folly.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>How? Must it be fed?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<p>Oh, aye, humour is nothing, if it be not fed. Didst thou never hear that? It's a common phrase, 'Feed my humour'.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>I'll none on it: humour, avaunt, I know you not, begone. Let who will make hungry meals for your monstership, it shall not be I. Feed you, quoth he? 'Slid, I ha' much ado to feed myself; especially on these lean rascally days, too; an't had been any other day but a fasting day (a plague on them all for me), by this light, one might have done the commonwealth good service, and have drowned them all i' the flood, two or three hundred thousand years ago. Oh, I do stomach them hugely! I have a maw now, an' 'twere for Sir Bevis his horse, against 'em.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<p>I pray thee, good Cob, what makes thee so out of love with fasting days?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Marry, that which will make any man out of love with 'em, I think: their bad conditions, an' you will needs know. First, they are of a Flemish breed, I am sure on't, for they ravin up more butter than all the days of the week beside; next, they stink of fish and leek-porridge miserably; thirdly, they'll keep a man devoutly hungry all day, and at night send him supperless to bed.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<p>Indeed, these are faults, Cob.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Nay, an' this were all, 'twere something, but they are the only known enemies to my generation. A fasting day no sooner comes, but my lineage goes to rack, poor cobs, they smoke for it, they are made martyrs o' the gridiron, they melt in passion: and your maids too know this, and yet would have me turn Hannibal, and eat my own fish and blood.  He pulls out a red herring  My princely coz, fear nothing: I have not the heart to devour you, an' I might be made as rich as King Cophetua. Oh, that I had room for my tears, I could weep salt water enough, now, to preserve the lives of ten thousand of my kin. But I may curse none but these filthy almanacs, for an't were not for them, these days of persecution would ne'er be known. I'll be hanged, an' some fishmonger's son do not make of 'em; and puts in more fasting days than he should do, because he would utter his father's dried stock-fish, and stinking conger.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<p>'Slight, peace, thou'lt be beaten like a stock-fish, else: here is Master Matthew. Now must I look out for a messenger to my master.</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-039"/>

<stage type="setting">[Exeunt]</stage>
</div2>

<div2 type="scene" n="3" id="d20">
<head>Act III, Scene iii</head>

<stage type="setting">[Enter] WELLBRED, EDWARD, BRAINWORM, BOBADILL,
MATTHEW [and] STEPHEN</stage>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Beshrew me, but it was an absolute good jest, and exceedingly well carried!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Aye, and our ignorance maintained it as well, did it not?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Yes, faith, but was't possible thou should'st not know him? I forgive Master Stephen, for he is stupidity itself!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>'Fore God, not I, an' I might have been joined patent with one of the seven wise masters for knowing him. He had so writhen himself into the habit of one of your poor infantry, your decayed, ruinous, worm-eaten gentlemen of the round: such as have vowed to sit on the skirts of the city, let your Provost and his half-dozen of halberdiers do what they can; and have translated begging out of the old hackney pace, to a fine easy amble, and made it run as smooth of the tongue as a shove-groat shilling. Into the likeness of one of these reformados had he moulded himself so perfectly, observing every trick of their action, as varying the accent, swearing with an emphasis, indeed all, with so special and exquisite a grace that (hadst thou seen him) thou wouldst have sworn he might have been sergeant-major, if not lieutenant-colonel to the regiment.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Why, Brainworm, who would have thought thou hadst been such an artificer?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>An artificer! An architect! Except a man had studied begging all his lifetime, and been a weaver of language, from his infancy, for the clothing of it, I never saw his rival!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Where got'st thou this coat, I mar'l?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Of a Houndsditch man, sir. One of the devil's near kinsmen, a broker.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>That cannot be, if the proverb hold; for, a crafty knave needs no broker.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>True sir, but I did need a broker, ergo.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Well put off--no crafty knave, you'll say.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Tut, he has more of these shifts.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>And yet where I have one, the broker has ten, sir.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter CASH]</stage>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<p>Francis, Martin, ne'er a one to be found, now? What a spite's this?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>How now, Thomas? Is my brother Kitely within?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<p>No sir, my master went forth e'en now; but Master Downright is within. Cob, what, Cob? Is he gone too?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Whither went your master, Thomas, canst thou tell?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<p>I know not, to Justice Clement's, I think, sir. Cob!</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-040"/>

<stage type="setting">[Exit CASH]</stage>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Justice Clement, what's he?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Why, dost thou not know him? He is a city magistrate, a justice here, an excellent good lawyer, and a great scholar; but the only mad, merry, old fellow in Europe! I showed him you, the other day.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Oh, is that he? I remember him now. Good faith, and he
has a very strange presence, methinks; it shows as if he stood out of the rank from other men. I have heard many of his jests i' university. They say, he will commit a man for taking the wall of his horse.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Aye, or wearing his cloak of one shoulder, or serving of God: anything indeed, if it come in the way of his humour.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">Goes in and out calling</stage>
<p>Gasper, Martin, Cob! 'Heart, where should they be, trow?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Master Kitely's man, 'pray thee vouchsafe us the lighting of this match.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<p>Fire on your match, no time but now to vouchsafe? Francis, Cob!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Body of me! Here's the remainder of seven pound, since yesterday was seven-night. 'Tis your right Trinidado! Did you never take any, Master Stephen?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>No truly, sir; but I'll learn to take it now, since you commend it, so.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Sir, believe me (upon my relation), for what I tell you, the world shall not reprove. I have been in the Indies (where this herb grows), where neither myself, nor a dozen gentlemen more (of my knowledge) have received the taste of any other nutriment in the world, for the space of one and twenty weeks, but the fume of this simple only. Therefore, it cannot be but 'tis most divine! Further, take it in the nature, in the true kind so, it makes an antidote that, had you taken the most deadly poisonous plant in all Italy, it should expel it, and clarify you, with as much ease as I speak. And, for your green wound, your Balsamum and your St. John's wort are all mere gulleries, and trash to it, especially your Trinidado; your Nicotian is good too. I could say what I know of the virtue of it, for the expulsion of rheums, raw humours, crudities, obstructions, with a thousand of this kind; but I profess myself no quacksalver. Only, thus much, by Hercules, I do hold it, and will affirm it (before any prince in Europe) to be the most sovereign and precious weed that ever the earth tendered to the use of man.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>This speech would ha' done decently in a tobacco-trader's mouth!</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter CASH and COB]</stage>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<p>At Justice Clement's, he is: in the middle of Coleman Street.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Oh, oh!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Where's the match I gave thee? Master Kitely's man?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<p>Would his match, and he, and pipe, and all were at Santo Domingo! I had forgot it.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit]</stage>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>By God's me, I mar'l what pleasure or felicity they have in taking this roguish tobacco! It's good for nothing but to choke a man, and fill him full of smoke and embers: there were four died out of one house,

<pb id="n101-041"/>

last week, with taking of it, and two more the bell went for yesternight; one of them (they say) will ne'er scape it: he voided a bushel of soot yesterday, upward and downward. By the stocks, an' there were no wiser men than I, I'd have it present whipping, man or woman, that should but deal with a tobacco-pipe; why, it will stifle them all in the end, as many as use it; it's little better than ratsbane, or rosaker.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">BOBADILL beats [COB] with a cudgel</stage>

<sp><speaker>ALL</speaker>
<p>Oh, good Captain, hold, hold.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>You base cullion, you.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter CASH, with the lighted match]</stage>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<p>Sir, here's your match;</p> <stage type="delivery">[To COB]</stage> <p>come, thou must needs be talking, too, thou'rt well enough served.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Nay, he will not meddle with his match, I warrant you: well, it shall be a dear beating, an' I live.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Do you prate? Do you murmur?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Nay, good Captain, will you regard the humour of a fool?</p> <stage type="delivery">[To COB]</stage> <p>Away, knave.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Thomas, get him away.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit CASH and COB]</stage>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>A whoreson filthy slave, a dung-worm, an excrement! Body o' Caesar, but that I scorn to let forth so mean a spirit, I'd ha' stabbed him to the earth.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Marry, the law forbid, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp>
<speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>By Pharaoh's foot, I would have done it.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[Aside]</stage> <p>Oh, he swears admirably! By Pharaoh's foot! Body o' Caesar! I shall never do it, sure, upon mine honour, and by St. George, no, I ha' not the right grace.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Master Stephen, will you any? By this air, the most divine tobacco that ever I drunk!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>None, I thank you, sir.</p> <stage type="setting">[Exit BOBADILL and MATTHEW]</stage> <p>Oh, this gentleman does it rarely too! But nothing like the other. By this air, as I am a gentleman: by-- Practising, to the post</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[Aside]</stage> <p>Master, glance, glance! Master Wellbred!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>As I have somewhat to be saved, I protest--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>You are a fool; it needs no affidavit.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Cousin, will you any tobacco?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Aye, sir! Upon my reputation--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>How now, cousin!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>I protest, as I am a gentleman, but no soldier, indeed--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>No, Master Stephen? As I remember, your name is entered
in the Artillery Garden.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Aye, sir, that's true: cousin, may I swear, as I am a soldier, by that?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Oh yes, that you may. It's all you have for your money.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Then, as I am a gentleman, and a soldier, it is divine tobacco!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>But soft, where's Master Matthew? Gone?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>No, sir, they went in here.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Oh, let's follow them: Master Matthew is gone to salute his mistress, in verse. We shall ha' the happiness to hear some of his poetry now. He never comes unfurnished. Brainworm?</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-042"/>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Brainworm? Where? Is this Brainworm?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Aye, cousin, no words of it, upon your gentility.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Not I, body of me, by this air, St. George, and the foot of Pharaoh!</p>
</sp>

<sp>
<speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Rare! Your cousin's discourse is simply drawn out with oaths.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>'Tis larded with 'em. A kind of French dressing, if you love it.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exeunt]</stage>
</div2>

<div2 type="scene" n="4" id="d21">
<head>Act III, Scene iv</head>

<stage type="setting">[Enter] KITELY [and] COB</stage>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>Ha? How many are there, sayest thou?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Marry, sir, your brother, Master Wellbred--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>Tut, beside him: what strangers are there, man?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Strangers? Let me see, one, two: mass, I know not well, there are so many.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>How? So many?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Aye, there's some five, or six of them, at most.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker> <stage type="delivery">[Aside]</stage>
<lg>
<l>A swarm, a swarm,</l>
<l>Spite of the devil, how they sting my head</l>
<l>With fork&egrave;d stings, thus wide and large!</l>
</lg>
<stage type="delivery">[He holds up fingers to indicate horns on his head]</stage>
<lg>
<l>But, Cob,</l>
<l>How long hast thou been coming hither, Cob?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>A little while, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp>
<speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>Didst thou come running?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>No, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>Nay, then I am familiar with thy haste!</p>
<stage type="delivery">[Aside]</stage>
<lg>
<l>Bane to my fortunes! What meant I to marry?</l>
<l>I, that before was ranked in such content,</l>
<l>My mind at rest too, in so soft a peace,</l>
<l>Being free master of mine own free thoughts,</l>
<l>And now become a slave? What? Never sigh,</l>
<l>Be of good cheer, man: for thou art a cuckold,</l>
<l>'Tis done, 'tis done! Nay, when such flowing store,</l>
<l>Plenty itself, falls in my wife's lap,</l>
<l>The cornu-copiae will be mine, I know. But, Cob,</l>
<l>What entertainment had they? I am sure</l>
<l>My sister, and my wife, would bid them welcome! Ha?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Like enough, sir, yet I heard not a word of it.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<l>No: their lips were sealed with kisses, and the voice</l>
<l>Drowned in a flood of joy, at their arrival,</l>
<l>Had lost her motion, state, and faculty.</l>
<l>Cob, which of them was't, that first kissed my wife?</l>
<l>My sister, I should say; my wife, alas,</l>
<l>I fear not her: ha? Who was it, say'st thou?</l>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>By my troth, sir, will you have the truth of it?</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-043"/>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>Oh aye, good Cob: I pray thee, heartily.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Then, I am a vagabond, and fitter for Bridewell than your worship's company, if I saw anybody to be kissed, unless they would have kissed the post in the middle of the warehouse; for there I left them all, at their tobacco, with a pox.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>How? Were they not gone in, then, ere thou cam'st?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Oh, no, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>Spite of the devil! What do I stay here, then? Cob, follow me.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit]</stage>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Nay, soft and fair, I have eggs on the spit: I cannot go yet, sir. Now am I for some five and fifty reasons hammering, hammering revenge; oh, for three or four gallons of vinegar, to sharpen my wits. Revenge; vinegar revenge; vinegar and mustard revenge; nay, an' he had not lyen in my house, 'twould never have grieved me, but being my guest, one that I'll be sworn my wife has lent him her smock off her back, while his one shirt has been at washing; pawned her neckerchers for clean bands for him; sold almost all my platters, to buy him tobacco; and he to turn monster of ingratitude, and strike his lawful host! Well, I hope to raise up an host of fury for't: here comes Justice Clement.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter] CLEMENT,KNOWELL [and] FORMAL</stage>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>What, 's Master Kitely gone? Roger?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>FORMAL</speaker>
<p>Aye, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>'Heart o' me! What made him leave us so abruptly? How now, sirrah? What make you here? What would you have, ha?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>An't please your worship, I am a poor neighbour of your worship's--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>A poor neighbour of mine? Why, speak, poor neighbour.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>I dwell, sir, at the sign of the Water-tankard, hard by the Green Lattice: I have paid scot and lot there, any time this eighteen years.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>To the Green Lattice?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>No, sir, to the parish: marry, I have seldom scaped scot-free, at the Lattice.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Oh, well! What business has my poor neighbour with me?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>An't like your worship, I am come to crave the peace of your worship.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Of me, knave? Peace of me, knave? Did I e'er hurt thee? Or threaten thee? Or wrong thee? Ha?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>No, sir, but your worship's warrant, for one that has wronged me, sir: his arms are at too much liberty, I would fain have them bound to a treaty of peace, an' my credit could compass it with your worship.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Thou goest far enough about for't, I'm sure.</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-044"/>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>Why, dost thou go in danger of thy life for him, friend?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>No sir; but I go in danger of my death, every hour, by his means: an' I die within a twelve-month and a day, I may swear, by the law of the land, that he killed me.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>How? How knave? Swear he killed thee? And by the law? What pretence? What colour hast thou for that?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Marry, an't please your worship, both black and blue: colour enough, I warrant you. I have it here, to show your worship.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>What is he that gave you this, sirrah?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>A gentleman, and a soldier, he says he is, o' the city here.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>A soldier o' the city? What call you him?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Captain Bobadill.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Bobadill? And why did he bob and beat you, sirrah? How began the quarrel betwixt you: ha? Speak truly, knave, I advise you.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Marry, indeed, an' please your worship, only because I
spake against their vagrant tobacco, as I came by 'em, when they were taking on't; for nothing else.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Ha? You speak against tobacco? Formal, his name.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>FORMAL</speaker>
<p>What's your name, sirrah?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Oliver, sir, Oliver Cob, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Tell Oliver Cob, he shall go to the jail, Formal.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>FORMAL</speaker>
<p>Oliver Cob, my master, Justice Clement, says, you shall go to the jail.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Oh, I beseech your worship, for God's sake, dear Master Justice.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Nay, God's precious: an' such drunkards, and tankards, as you are, come to dispute of tobacco once--I have done! Away with him.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Oh, good Master Justice, sweet old gentleman.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>Sweet Oliver, would I could do thee any good: Justice Clement, let me entreat you, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>What? A threadbare rascal! A beggar! A slave that never drunk out of better than piss-pot metal in his life! And he to deprave and abuse the virtue of an herb so generally received in the courts of princes, the chambers of nobles, the bowers of sweet ladies, the cabins of soldiers! Roger, away with him, by God's precious--I say, go to.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Dear Master Justice: let me be beaten again, I have deserved it; but not the prison, I beseech you.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>Alas, poor Oliver!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Roger, make him a warrant--he shall not go--I but fear the knave.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>FORMAL</speaker>
<p>Do not stink, sweet Oliver, you shall not go, my master will give you a warrant.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Oh, the Lord maintain his worship, his worthy worship.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Away, dispatch him. [Exeunt FORMAL and COB] How now, Master Knowell! In dumps? In dumps? Come, this becomes not.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>Sir, would I could not feel my cares--</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-045"/>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Your cares are nothing! They are like my cap, soon put on, and as soon put off. What? Your son is old enough to govern himself: let him run his course, it's the only way to make him a staid man. If he were an unthrift, a ruffian, a drunkard, or a licentious liver, then you had reason: you had reason to take care; but, being none of these, mirth's my witness, an' I had twice so many cares as you have, I'd drown them all in a cup of sack. Come, come, let's try it; I muse your parcel of a soldier returns not all this while.</p>
</sp>


<stage type="setting">[Exeunt]</stage>
</div2>
</div1>

<div1 type="act" n="4" id="d22">
<head>Act IV</head>

<div2 type="scene" n="1" id="d23">
<head>Act IV, Scene i</head>

<stage type="setting">[Enter] DOWNRIGHT [and] DAME KITELY</stage>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Well, sister, I tell you true; and you'll find it so, in the end.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<p>Alas, brother, what would you have me to do? I cannot help it: you see, my brother brings 'em in here, they are his friends.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>His friends? His fiends. 'Slud, they do nothing but haunt him, up and down, like a sort of unlucky sprites, and tempt him to all manner of villainy that can be thought of. Well, by this light, a little thing would make me play the devil with some of 'em; an't were not more for your husband's sake than anything else, I'd make the house too hot for the best on 'em: they should say, and swear, hell were broken loose ere they went hence. But, by God's will, 'tis nobody's fault but yours: for, an' you had done as you might have done, they should have been parboiled, and baked too, every mother's son, ere they should ha' come in, e'er a one of 'em.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<p>God's my life! Did you ever hear the like? What a strange man is this! Could I keep out all them, think you? I should put myself against half a dozen men, should I? Good faith, you'd mad the patient'st body in the world, to hear you talk so, without any sense or reason!</p>
</sp>


<stage type="setting">[Enter] MISTRESS BRIDGET, MASTER MATTHEW,
[and] BOBADILL, [followed by]
WELLBRED, STEPHEN, EDWARD [and] BRAINWORM</stage>

<sp><speaker>BRIDGET</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Servant, in troth, you are too prodigal</l>
<l>Of your wit's treasure, thus to pour it forth</l>
<l>Upon so mean a subject as my worth.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>You say well, mistress; and I mean as well.</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-046"/>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Hoy-day, here is stuff!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Oh, now stand close; pray heaven she can get him to read; he should do it of his own natural impudency.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRIDGET</speaker>
<p>Servant, what is this same, I pray you?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Marry, an elegy, an elegy, an odd toy--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>To mock an ape withal. Oh, I could sew up his mouth now.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<p>Sister, I pray you let's hear it.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Are you rhyme-given, too?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Mistress, I'll read it, if you please.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRIDGET</speaker>
<p>Pray you do, servant.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Oh, here's no foppery! Death, I can endure the stocks better.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit]</stage>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>What ails thy brother? Can he not hold his water at reading of a ballad?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Oh, no: a rhyme to him is worse than cheese or a bagpipe. But, mark, you lose the protestation.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Faith, I did it in an humour: I know not how it is; but, please you come near, sir. This gentleman has judgement, he knows how to censure of a--pray you sir, you can judge.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Not I, sir: upon my reputation, and by the foot of Pharaoh.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Oh, chide your cousin for swearing.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Not I, so long as he does not forswear himself.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Master Matthew, you abuse the expectation of your dear mistress, and her fair sister: fie, while you live, avoid this prolixity.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>I shall, sir: well, <foreign lang="lat">Incipere dulce</foreign>.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>How! <foreign lang="lat">Insipere dulce</foreign>? A sweet thing to be a fool, indeed.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>What, do you take <foreign lang="lat">Incipere</foreign> in that sense?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>You do not? You? This was your villainy, to gull him with a mot.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Oh, the benchers' phrase: <foreign lang="lat">pauca verba, pauca verba</foreign>.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Rare creature, let me speak without offence,</l>
<l>Would God my rude words had the influence,</l>
<l>To rule thy thoughts, as thy fair looks do mine,</l>
<l>Then should'st thou be his prisoner, who is thine.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>This is in Hero and Leander?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Oh, ay! Peace, we shall have more of this.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Be not unkind and fair, misshapen stuff</l>
<l>Is of behaviour boisterous, and rough.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>How like you that, sir?</p>
</sp>

<stage type="delivery">MASTER STEPHEN answers with shaking his head</stage>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>'Slight, he shakes his head like a bottle, to feel and there be any brain in it!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<lg>
<l>But observe the catastrophe, now:</l>
<l>And I in duty will exceed all other,</l>
<l>As you in beauty do excel love's mother.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Well, I'll have him free of the wit-brokers, for he utters nothing but stol'n remnants.</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-047"/>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Oh, forgive it him.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>A filching rogue? Hang him. And from the dead? It's worse than sacrilege.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Sister, what ha' you here? Verses? Pray you, let's see. Who made these verses? They are excellent good!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Oh, Master Wellbred, 'tis your disposition to say so sir. They were good i' the morning, I made 'em, extempore, this morning.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>How? Extempore?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>I would I might be hanged else; ask Captain Bobadill. He saw me write them, at the--(pox on it) the Star, yonder.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Can he find, in his heart, to curse the stars so?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Faith, his are even with him: they ha' cursed him enough already.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Cousin, how do you like this gentleman's verses?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Oh, admirable! The best that ever I heard, coz!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Body o' Caesar! They are admirable! The best that ever I heard, as I am a soldier.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter DOWNRIGHT]</stage>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>I am vexed, I can hold ne'er a bone of me still! Heart! I think they mean to build and breed here!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Sister, you have a simple servant here, that crowns your beauty with such encomions, and devices; you may see what it is to be the mistress of a wit that can make your perfections so transparent that every blear eye may look through them, and see him drowned over head and ears, in the deep well of desire. Sister Kitely, I marvel you get you not a servant that can rhyme and do tricks, too.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Oh, monster! Impudence itself! Tricks?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<p>Tricks, brother? What tricks?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRIDGET</speaker>
<p>Nay, speak, I pray you, what tricks?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<p>Aye, never spare anybody here; but say, what tricks?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRIDGET</speaker>
<p>Passion of my heart! Do tricks?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>'Slight, here's a trick vied, and revied! Why, you monkeys, you! What a caterwauling do you keep? Has he not given you rhymes, and verses, and tricks?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Oh, the fiend!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Nay, you, lamp of virginity, that take it in snuff so! Come and cherish this tame 'poetical fury' in your servant, you'll be begged else, shortly, for a concealment: go to, reward his muse. You cannot give him less than a shilling, in conscience, for the book he had it out of cost him a teston, at least. How now, gallants? Master Matthew? Captain? What? All sons of silence? No spirit?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Come, you might practice your ruffian-tricks somewhere
else, and not here, I wuss: this is no tavern, nor drinking-school, to vent your exploits in.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>How now! Whose cow has calved?</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-048"/>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Marry, that has mine, sir. Nay, boy, never look askance at me for the matter; I'll tell you of it, aye, sir, you, and your companions, mend yourselves, when I ha' done.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>My companions?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Yes sir, your companions, so I say, I am not afraid of you, nor them neither: your hang-bys here. You must have your poets, and your potlings, your soldados, and foolados, to follow you up and down the city, and here they must come to domineer, and swagger. [To MATTHEW and BOBADILL] Sirrah, you, ballad-singer, and slops, your fellow there, get you out: get you home; or, by this steel, I'll cut off your ears, and that presently.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>'Slight, stay, let's see what he dare do: cut off his ears? Cut a whetstone. You are an ass, do you see? Touch any man here, and by this hand, I'll run my rapier to the hilts in you.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Yea, that would I fain see, boy.
They all draw, and they of the house make out to part them</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<p>Oh Jesu! Murder! Thomas, Gaspar!</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter CASH]</stage>

<sp><speaker>BRIDGET</speaker>
<p>Help, help, Thomas.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Gentlemen, forebear, I pray you.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Well, sirrah, you, Holofernes: by my hand, I will pink your flesh full of holes with my rapier for this; I will, by this good heaven. They offer to fight again, and are parted  Nay, let him come, let him come, gentlemen, by the body of St. George, I'll not kill him.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<p>Hold, hold, good gentlemen.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>You whoreson, bragging coistril.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter] KITELY</stage>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Why, how now? What's the matter? What's the stir here?</l>
<l>Whence springs this quarrel? Thomas! Where is he?</l>
<l>Put up your weapons, and put off this rage.</l>
<l>My wife and sister, they are the cause of this--</l>
<l>What, Thomas? Where is this knave?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<p>Here, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Come, let's go: this is one of my brother's ancient humours, this.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>I am glad nobody was hurt by his ancient humour.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exeunt WELLBRED, STEPHEN, EDWARD, MATTHEW, BOBADILL and BRAINWORM]</stage>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>Why, how now, brother, who enforced this brawl?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>A sort of lewd rakehells, that care neither for God, nor the devil! And they must come here to read ballads, and roguery, and trash! I'll mar the knot of 'em ere I sleep, perhaps; especially Bob, there: he that's all manner of shapes! And 'Songs and Sonnets', his fellow.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRIDGET</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Brother, indeed, you are too violent,</l>
<l>Too sudden, in your humour; and you know</l>

<pb id="n101-049"/>

<l>My brother Wellbred's temper will not bear</l>
<l>Any reproof, chiefly in such a presence,</l>
<l>Where every slight disgrace he should receive</l>
<l>Might wound him in opinion and respect.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Respect? What talk you of respect 'mong such,</l>
<l>As ha' nor spark of manhood, nor good manners?</l>
<l>'Sdeynes, I am ashamed to hear you! Respect?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit]</stage>

<sp><speaker>BRIDGET</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Yes, there was one a civil gentleman,</l>
<l>And very worthily demeaned himself!</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Oh, that was some love of yours, sister!</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRIDGET</speaker>
<lg>
<l>A love of mine? I would it were no worse, brother!</l>
<l>You'd pay my portion sooner than you think for.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<p>Indeed, he seemed to be a gentleman of an exceeding fair disposition, and of very excellent good parts!</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exeunt DAME KITELY and BRIDGET]</stage>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Her love, by heaven! My wife's minion!</l>
<l>Fair disposition? Excellent good parts?</l>
<l>Death, these phrases are intolerable!</l>
<l>Good parts? How should she know his parts?</l>
<l>His parts? Well, well, well, well, well, well!</l>
<l>It is too plain, too clear. Thomas, come hither.</l>
<l>What, are they gone?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Aye, sir, they went in.</l>
<l>My mistress, and your sister--</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Are any of the gallants within?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>No, sir, they are all gone.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Art thou sure of it?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>I can assure you, sir.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>What gentleman was that they praised so, Thomas?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<p>One, they call him Master Knowell, a handsome young gentleman, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Aye, I thought so: my mind gave me as much.</l>
<l>I'll die but they have hid him i' the house,</l>
<l>Somewhere; I'll go and search. Go with me, Thomas.</l>
<l>Be true to me, and thou shalt find me a master.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exeunt]</stage>
</div2>

<div2 type="scene" n="2" id="d24">
<head>Act IV, Scene ii</head>

<stage type="setting">[Enter] COB</stage>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[Knocking]</stage> <p>What, Tib! Tib, I say!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>TIB</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[Within]</stage> <p>How now, what cuckold is that knocks so hard? [Opens the door] Oh, husband, is't you? What's the news?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Nay, you have stunned me, i' faith! You ha' giv'n me a knock o' the forehead will stick by me! Cuckold? 'Slid, cuckold?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>TIB</speaker>
<p>Away, you fool, did I know it was you, that knocked?

<pb id="n101-050"/>

Come, come, you may call me as bad, when you list.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>May I? Tib, you are a whore.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>TIB</speaker>
<p>You lie in your throat, husband.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>How, the lie? And in my throat too? Do you long to be stabbed, ha?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>TIB</speaker>
<p>Why, you are no soldier, I hope?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Oh, must you be stabbed by a soldier? Mass, that's true! When was Bobadill here? Your captain? That rogue, that foist, that fencing Burgullian? I'll tickle him, i' faith.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>TIB</speaker>
<p>Why, what's the matter? Trow!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Oh, he has basted me, rarely, sumptuously! But I have it here in black and white,</p> <stage type="delivery">[Shows his warrant]</stage> <p>for his black and blue, shall pay him. Oh, the Justice! The honestest old brave Trojan in London! I do honour the very flea of his dog. A plague on him though, he put me once in a villainous filthy fear; marry, it vanished away, like the smoke of tobacco; but I was smoked soundly first. I thank the devil, and his good angel, my guest. Well, wife, or Tib (which you will), get you in, and lock the door, I charge you, let nobody in to you; wife, nobody in to you: those are my words. Not Captain Bob himself, nor the fiend in his likeness; you are a woman; you have flesh and blood enough in you, to be tempted: therefore, keep the door, shut upon all comers.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>TIB</speaker>
<p>I warrant you, there shall nobody enter here, without my consent.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Nor with your consent, sweet Tib, and so I leave you.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>TIB</speaker>
<p>It's more than you know, whether you leave me so.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>How?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>TIB</speaker>
<p>Why, sweet.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Tut, sweet, or sour, thou art a flower,</l>
<l>Keep close thy door, I ask no more.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit COB and TIB, separately]</stage>
</div2>

<div2 type="scene" n="3" id="d25">
<head>Act IV, Scene iii</head>

<stage type="setting">[Enter] EDWARD, WELLBRED, STEPHEN [and]
BRAINWORM [still disguised]</stage>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Well, Brainworm, perform this business happily, and thou makest a purchase of my love forever.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>I' faith, now let thy spirits use their best faculties. But, at any hand, remember the message to my brother: for there's no other means to start him.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>I warrant you, sir, fear nothing: I have a nimble soul has waked all forces of my fancy, by this time, and put 'em in true motion. What you have possessed me withal, I'll discharge it amply, sir. Make it no question.</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-051"/>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Forth, and prosper, Brainworm. [Exit BRAINWORM] Faith, Ned, how dost thou approve of my abilities in this device?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Troth, well, howsoever; but it will come excellent, if it take.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Take, man? Why, it cannot choose but take, if the circumstances miscarry not; but, tell me, ingenuously, dost thou affect my sister Bridget, as thou pretend'st?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Friend, am I worth belief?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Come, do not protest. In faith, she is a maid of good ornament, and much modesty; and, except I conceived very worthily of her, thou shouldest not have her.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Nay, that I am afraid will be a question yet, whether I shall have her, or no.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>'Slid, thou shalt have her: by this light, thou shalt.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Nay, do not swear.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>By this hand, thou shalt have her: I'll go fetch her, presently. Point but where to meet, and as I am an honest man, I'll bring her.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Hold, hold, be temperate.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Why, by--what shall I swear by? Thou shalt have her, as I am--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>'Pray thee, be at peace, I am satisfied; and do believe thou wilt omit no offered occasion to make my desires complete.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Thou shalt see, and know, I will not.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exeunt]</stage>
</div2>

<div2 type="scene" n="4" id="d26">
<head>Act IV, Scene iv</head>

<stage type="setting">[Enter] FORMAL [and] KNOWELL</stage>

<sp><speaker>FORMAL</speaker>
<p>Was your man a soldier, sir?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Aye, a knave, I took him begging o' the way,</l>
<l>This morning, as I came over Moorfields!</l>
</lg>
<stage type="setting">[Enter BRAINWORM, still disguised]</stage>
<lg>
<l>Oh, here he is! You've made fair speed, believe me:</l>
<l>Where, i' the name of sloth, could you be thus--</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Marry, peace be my comfort, where I thought I should have had little comfort of your worship's service.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>How so?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Oh, sir! Your coming to the city, your entertainment of me, and your sending me to watch--indeed, all the circumstances either of your charge, or my employment--are as open to your son as to yourself!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>How should that be! Unless that villain, Brainworm,</l>
<l>Have told him of the letter, and discovered</l>
<l>All that I strictly charged him to conceal? 'Tis so!</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>I am partly o' the faith 'tis so indeed.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>But, how should he know thee to be my man?</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-052"/>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Nay, sir, I cannot tell; unless it be by the black art! Is not your son a scholar, sir?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Yes, but I hope his soul is not allied</l>
<l>Unto such hellish practices: if it were,</l>
<l>I had just cause to weep my part in him,</l>
<l>And curse the time of his creation.</l>
<l>But, where didst thou find them, Fitzsword?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>You should rather ask, where they found me, sir, for I'll be sworn I was going along in the street, thinking nothing, when (of a sudden) a voice calls, 'Master Knowell's man'; another cries, 'Soldier'; and thus, half a dozen of 'em, till they had called me within a house where I no sooner came but they seemed men, and out flew all their rapiers at my bosom, with some three- or four-score oaths to accompany 'em, and all to tell me I was but a dead man, if I did not confess where you were, and how I was employed, and about what; which, when they could not get out of me (as I protest, they must ha' dissected and made an anatomy o' me first, and so I told 'em) they locked me up into a room i' the top of a high house, whence, by great miracle (having a light heart) I slid down, by a bottom of packthread, into the street, and so 'scaped. But, sir, thus much I can assure you, for I heard it while I was locked up, there were a great many rich merchants, and brave citizens' wives with 'em at a feast, and your son, Master Edward, withdrew with one of 'em, and has 'pointed to meet her anon, at one Cob's house, a water-bearer that dwells by the wall. Now, there your worship shall be sure to take him, for there he preys, and fail he will not.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Nor will I fail, to break his match, I doubt not.</l>
<l>Go thou along with Justice Clement's man,</l>
<l>And stay there for me. At one Cob's house, say'st thou?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Aye, sir, there you shall have him.</p> <stage type="delivery">[Exit KNOWELL]</stage> <p>Yes? Invisible? Much wench, or much son! 'Slight, when he has stayed there, three or four hours, travailing with the expectation of wonders, and at length be delivered of air; oh, the sport that I should then take, to look on him, if I durst! But now I mean to appear no more afore him in this shape. I have another trick to act yet. Oh, that I were so happy as to light on a nupson, now, of this Justice's novice.</p> <stage type="delivery">[To FORMAL]</stage> <p>Sir, I make you stay somewhat long.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>FORMAL</speaker>
<p>Not a whit, sir. 'Pray you, what do you mean? Sir?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>I was putting up some papers--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>FORMAL</speaker>
<p>You ha' been lately in the wars, sir, it seems.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Marry have I, sir; to my loss; and expense of all,  almost--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>FORMAL</speaker>
<p>Troth, sir, I would be glad to bestow a pottle of wine o' you, if it please you to accept it--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Oh, sir-</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>FORMAL</speaker>
<p>But to hear the manner of your services, and your devices in the wars, they say they be very strange, and not like those a man reads in the Roman histories, or sees at Mile End.</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-053"/>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>No, I assure you, sir; why, at any time when it please you, I shall be ready to discourse to you, all I know;</p> <stage type="delivery">[Aside]</stage> <p>and more too, somewhat.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>FORMAL</speaker>
<p>No better time than now, sir: we'll go to the Windmill; there we shall have a cup of neat grist, we call it. I pray you, sir, let me request you to the Windmill.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>I'll follow you, sir,</p> <stage type="delivery">[Aside]</stage> <p>and make grist o' you, if I have good luck.</p>  <stage type="setting">[Exeunt]</stage>
</sp>
</div2>

<div2 type="scene" n="5" id="d27">
<head>Act IV, Scene v</head>

<stage type="setting">[Enter] MATTHEW, EDWARD, BOBADILL [and] STEPHEN</stage>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Sir, did your eyes ever taste the like clown of him, where we were today, Master Wellbred's half-brother? I think the whole earth cannot show his parallel, by this daylight.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>We were now speaking of him: Captain Bobadill tells me he is fall'n foul o' you, too.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Oh, aye, sir, he threatened me with the bastinado.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Aye, but I think I taught you prevention, this morning, for that-- You shall kill him, beyond question; if you be so generously minded.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Indeed, it is a most excellent trick!  	Practices at a post</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Oh, you do not give spirit enough to your motion, you are too tardy, too heavy! Oh, it must be done like lightning: hai!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Rare, Captain!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Tut, 'tis nothing an't be not done in a--punto!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Captain, did you ever prove yourself upon any of our masters of defence, here?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Oh, good sir! Yes, I hope, he has.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>I will tell you, sir. Upon my first coming to the city, after my long travail for knowledge (in that mystery only), there came three or four of 'em to me, at a gentleman's house, where it was my chance to be resident at that time, to entreat my presence at their schools, and withal so much importuned me that (I protest to you as I am a gentleman) I was ashamed of their rude demeanour, out of all measure. Well, I told 'em that to come to a public school, they should pardon me, it was opposite (in diameter) to my humour, but, if so they would give their attendance at my lodging, I protested to do them what right or favour I could, as I was a gentleman, and so forth.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>So, sir, then you tried their skill?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Alas, soon tried! You shall hear sir. Within two or three days after, they came; and, by honesty, fair sir, believe me, I graced them exceedingly, showed them some two or three tricks of prevention have purchased 'em, since, a credit, to admiration! They cannot deny this; and yet now, they hate me, and why? Because I am excellent, and for no other vile reason on the earth.</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-054"/>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>This is strange, and barbarous, as ever I heard!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Nay, for a more instance of their preposterous natures, but note, sir. They have assaulted me some three, four, five, six of them together, as I have walked alone, in divers skirts i' the town, as Turnbull, Whitechapel, Shoreditch, which were then my quarters, and since upon the Exchange, at my lodging, and at my ordinary; where I have driven them afore me, the whole length of a street, in the open view of all our gallants, pitying to hurt them, believe me. Yet, all this lenity will not o'ercome their spleen: they will be doing with the pismire, raising a hill a man may spurn abroad, with his foot, at pleasure. By myself, I could have slain them all, but I delight not in murder. I am loath to bear any other than this bastinado for 'em; yet, I hold it good polity not to go disarmed, for though I be skilful, I may be oppressed with multitudes.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Aye, believe me, may you sir; and (in my conceit) our whole nation should sustain the loss by it, if it were so.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Alas, no: what's a peculiar man, to a nation? Not seen.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Oh, but your skill, sir!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Indeed, that might be some loss; but, who respects it? I will tell you, sir, by the way of private, and under seal; I am a gentleman, and live here obscure, and to myself; but, were I known to Her Majesty and the Lords (observe me) I would undertake (upon this poor head, and life), for the public benefit of the state, not only to spare the entire lives of her subjects in general, but to save the one half, nay, three parts of her yearly charge in holding war, and against what enemy soever. And, how would I do it, think you?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Nay, I know not, nor can I conceive.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Why, thus, sir. I would select nineteen more, to myself, throughout the land: gentlemen they should be of good spirit, strong, and able constitution, I would choose them by an instinct, a character, that I have; and I would teach these nineteen the special rules, as your punto, your reverso, your stoccata, your imbroccata, your passada, your montanto; till they could all play very near, or altogether as well as myself. This done, say the enemy were forty thousand strong, we twenty would come into the field, the tenth of March, or thereabouts; and we would challenge twenty of the enemy; they could not, in their honour, refuse us; well, we would kill them; challenge twenty more, kill them; twenty more, kill them; twenty more, kill them too; and thus would we kill, every man, his twenty a day, that's twenty score; twenty score, that's two hundred; two hundred a day, five days a thousand; forty thousand; forty times five, five times forty, two hundred days kills them all up, by computation. And this will I venture my poor gentleman-like carcass to perform (provided there be no treason practiced upon us) by fair and discreet manhood, that is, civilly by the sword.</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-055"/>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Why, are you so sure of your hand, Captain, at all times?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Tut, never miss thrust, upon my reputation with you.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>I would not stand in Downright's state, then, an' you meet him, for the wealth of any one street in London.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Why, sir, you mistake me! If he were here now, by this welkin, I would not draw my weapon on him! Let this gentleman do his mind; but, I will bastinado him (by the bright sun) wherever I meet him.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Faith, and I'll have a fling at him, at my distance.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>God's so', look where he is: yonder he goes.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Walks over the stage
What peevish luck have I, I cannot meet with those bragging rascals?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>It's not he? Is it?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Yes, faith, it is he.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit DOWNRIGHT]</stage>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>I'll be hanged, then, if that were he.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Sir, keep your hanging good for some greater matter, for I assure you, that was he.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Upon my reputation, it was he.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Had I thought it had been he, he must not have gone so; but I can hardly be induced to believe it was he, yet.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>That I think, sir. But see, he is come again!</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter DOWNRIGHT]</stage>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Oh, Pharaoh's foot, have I found you? Come, draw, to
your tools: draw, gipsy, or I'll thrash you.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Gentleman of valour, I do believe in thee, hear me--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Draw your weapon, then.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Tall man, I never thought on it till now (body of me): I had a warrant of the peace served on me, even now, as I came along, by a water-bearer; this gentleman saw it, Master Matthew.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>'Sdeath, you will not draw, then?</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">He beats him, and disarms him: MATTHEW runs away</stage>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Hold, hold, under thy favour, forbear.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Prate again, as you like this, you whoreson foist, you. You'll control the point, you? Your consort is gone? Had he stayed, he had shared with you, sir.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit]</stage>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Well, gentlemen, bear witness, I was bound to the peace, by this good day.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>No, faith, it's an ill day, Captain, never reckon it other; but say you were bound to the peace, the law allows you to defend yourself: that'll prove but a poor excuse.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>I cannot tell, sir. I desire good construction, in fair sort. I never sustained the like disgrace (by heaven), sure I was struck with a planet thence, for I had no power to touch my weapon.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Aye, like enough, I have heard of many that have been beaten under a planet: go, get you to a surgeon.</p> <stage type="delivery">[Exit BOBADILL]</stage> <p>'Slid, an' these be your tricks, your passadas, and your montantos, I'll none of them. Oh, manners! That this

<pb id="n101-056"/>

age should bring forth such creatures! That nature should be at leisure to make' em! Come, coz.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Mass, I'll ha' this cloak.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>God's will, 'tis Downright's.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Nay, it's mine now, another might have ta'en up, as well as I: I'll wear it, so I will.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>How an' he see it? He'll challenge it, assure yourself.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Aye, but he shall not ha' it: I'll say I bought it.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Take heed you buy it not too dear, coz.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exeunt]</stage>
</div2>

<div2 type="scene" n="6" id="d28">
<head>Act IV, Scene vi</head>

<stage type="setting">[Enter] KITELY, WELLBRED, DAME KITELY, [and] BRIDGET</stage>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Now, trust me brother, you were much to blame,</l>
<l>T' incense his anger, and disturb the peace</l>
<l>Of my poor house, where there are sentinels</l>
<l>That every minute watch, to give alarms</l>
<l>Of civil war, without adjection</l>
<l>Of your assistance, or occasion.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>No harm done, brother, I warrant you: since there is no harm done. Anger costs a man nothing; and a tall man is never his own man, till he be angry. To keep his valour in obscurity is to keep himself, as it were, in a cloak-bag. What's a musician, unless he play? What's a tall man, unless he fight? For, indeed, all this my wise brother stands upon, absolutely; and that made me fall in with him so resolutely.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<p>Aye, but what harm might have come of it, brother?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Might, sister? So, might the good warm clothes your husband wears be poisoned, for anything he knows; or the wholesome wine he drunk, even now, at the table--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[Aside]</stage>
<lg>
<l>Now, God forbid: Oh me. Now I remember,</l>
<l>My wife drunk to me, last; and changed the cup;</l>
<l>And bade me wear this cursed suit today.</l>
<l>See if Heav'n suffer murder undiscovered!</l>
</lg>
<stage type="delivery">[To BRIDGET]</stage>
<lg>
<l>I feel me ill: give me some mithridate,</l>
<l>Some mithridate and oil, good sister, fetch me;</l>
<l>Oh, I am sick at heart! I burn, I burn.</l>
<l>If you will save my life, go, fetch it me.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Oh, strange humour! My very breath has poisoned him.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRIDGET</speaker>
<p>Good brother, be content, what do you mean?
The strength of these extreme conceits will kill you.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Beshrew your heart-blood, brother Wellbred, now,</l>

<pb id="n101-057"/>

<l>For putting such a toy into his head.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Is a fit simile, a toy? Will he be poisoned with a simile? Brother Kitely, what a strange and idle imagination is this? For shame, be wiser. O' my soul, there's no such matter.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>Am I not sick? How am I, then, not poisoned? Am I not poisoned? How am I, then, so sick?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<p>If you be sick, your own thoughts make you sick.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>His jealousy is the poison he has taken.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter] BRAINWORM. He comes disguised like Justice Clement's man.</stage>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Master Kitely, my master, Justice Clement, salutes you; and desires to speak with you, with all possible speed.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>No time but now? When, I think, I am sick? Very sick!
Well, I will wait upon his worship. Thomas! Cob!</p> <stage type="delivery">[Aside]</stage> <p>I must seek them out, and set 'em sentinels, till I return. Thomas! Cob! Thomas!</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit]</stage>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[Takes BRAINWORM aside]</stage> <p>This is perfectly rare, Brainworm! But how got'st thou this apparel, of the Justice's man?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Marry sir, my proper fine pen-man would needs bestow the grist o' me, at the Windmill, to hear some martial discourse, where so I marshalled him that I made him drunk with admiration! And, because too much heat was the cause of his distemper, I stripped him stark naked, as he lay along asleep, and borrowed his suit, to deliver this counterfeit message in, leaving a rusty armour and an old brown bill to watch him, till my return; which shall be, when I ha' pawned his apparel, and spent the better part o' the money, perhaps.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Well, thou art a successful merry knave, Brainworm, his absence will be a good subject for more mirth. I pray thee, return to thy young master, and will him to meet me, and my sister Bridget, at the Tower instantly: for here, tell him, the house is so stored with jealousy, there is no room for love to stand upright in. We must get our fortunes committed to some larger prison, say; and, than the Tower, I know no better air; nor where the liberty of the house may do us more present service. Away.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit BRAINWORM]</stage>

<stage type="setting">[Enter KITELY and CASH]</stage>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Come hither, Thomas. Now, my secret's ripe,</l>
<l>And thou shalt have it: lay to both thine ears.</l>
<l>Hark what I say to thee. I must go forth, Thomas.</l>
<l>Be careful of thy promise, keep good watch,</l>
<l>Note every gallant, and observe him well,</l>
<l>That enters in my absence, to thy mistress:</l>
<l>If she would show him rooms, the jest is stale,</l>
<l>Follow 'em, Thomas, or else hang on him,</l>
<l>And let him not go after; mark their looks;</l>
<l>Note if she offer but to see his band,</l>
<l>Or any other amorous toy, about him;</l>
<l>But praise his leg, or foot; or if she say,</l>
<l>The day is hot, and bid him feel her hand,</l>

<pb id="n101-058"/>

<l>How hot it is: oh, that's a monstrous thing!</l>
<l>Note me all this, good Thomas, mark their sighs,</l>
<l>And, if they do but whisper, break 'em off:</l>
<l>I'll bear thee out in it. Wilt thou do this?</l>
<l>Will thou be true, my Thomas?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>As truth's self, sir.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>Why, I believe thee; where is Cob, now? Cob?</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit]</stage>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<p>He's ever calling for Cob! I wonder how he employs Cob so!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Indeed, sister, to ask how he employs Cob is a necessary question for you, that are his wife, and a thing not very easy for you to be satisfied in; but this I'll assure you, Cob's wife is an excellent bawd, sister, and oftentimes your husband haunts her house, marry, to what end, I cannot altogether accuse him, imagine you what you think convenient. But, I have known fair hides have foul hearts ere now, sister.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<p>Never said you truer than that, brother, so much I can tell you for your learning. Thomas, fetch your cloak, and go with me, I'll after him presently.</p> <stage type="setting">[Exit CASH]</stage> <p>I would to fortune I could take him there, i' faith. I'd return him his own, I warrant him.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit]</stage>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>So, let 'em go: this may make sport anon. Now, my fair sister-in-law, that you knew but how happy a thing it were to be fair and beautiful!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRIDGET</speaker>
<p>That touches not me, brother.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>That's true; that's even the fault of it: for, indeed, beauty stands a woman in no stead, unless it procure her touching. But, sister, whether it touch you or no, it touches your beauties; and I am sure they will abide the touch. An' they do not, a plague of all ceruse, say I; and it touches me too in part, though not in the--Well, there's a dear and respected friend of mine, sister, stands very strongly, and worthily affected toward you, and hath vowed to inflame whole bonfires of zeal, at his heart, in honour of your perfections. I have already engaged my promise to bring you where you shall hear him confirm much more. Ned Knowell is the man, sister. There's no exception against the party. You are ripe for a husband; and a minute's loss to such an occasion is a great trespass in a wise beauty. What say you, sister? On my soul he loves you. Will you give him the meeting?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRIDGET</speaker>
<p>Faith, I had very little confidence in mine own constancy, brother, if I durst not meet a man; but this motion of yours savours of an old knight-adventurer's servant a little too much, methinks.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>What's that, sister?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRIDGET</speaker>
<p>Marry, of the squire.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>No matter if it did, I would be such an one for my friend, but see who is returned to hinder us!</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter KITELY]</stage>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>What villainy is this? Called out on a false message? There was some plot! I was not sent for. Bridget,

<pb id="n101-059"/>

where's your sister?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRIDGET</speaker>
<p>I think she be gone forth, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>How! Is my wife gone forth? Whither, for God's sake?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRIDGET</speaker>
<p>She's gone abroad with Thomas.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Abroad with Thomas? Oh, that villain dors me.</l>
<l>He hath discovered all unto my wife!</l>
<l>Beast that I was to trust him; whither, I pray you, went she? </l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRIDGET</speaker>
<p>I know not, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>I'll tell you, brother, whither I suspect she's gone.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>Whither, good brother?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>To Cob's house, I believe; but, keep my counsel.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>I will, I will; to Cob's house? Doth she haunt Cob's?</l>
<l>She's gone a' purpose, now, to cuckold me,</l>
<l>With that lewd rascal, who, to win her favour,</l>
<l>Hath told her all.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exit]</stage>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Come, he's once more gone.</l>
<l>Sister, let's lose no time: th' affair is worth it.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exeunt]</stage>
</div2>


<div2 type="scene" n="7" id="d29">
<head>Act IV, Scene vii</head>

<stage type="setting">[Enter] MATTHEW [and] BOBADILL</stage>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>I wonder, Captain, what they will say of my going away? Ha?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Why, what should they say, but as of a discreet gentleman? Quick, wary, respectful of nature's fair lineaments; and that's all.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Why, so! But what can they say of your beating?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>A rude part, a touch with soft wood, a kind of gross battery used, laid on strongly, borne most patiently; and that's all.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Aye, but would any man have offered it in Venice, as you say?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Tut, I assure you, no: you shall have there your Nobilis, your Gentilezza, come in bravely upon your reverse, stand you close, stand you firm, stand you fair, save your retricato with his left leg, come to the assalto with the right, thrust with brave steel, defy your base wood! But wherefore do I awake this remembrance? I was fascinated, by Jupiter, fascinated: but I will be unwitched, and revenged, by law.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Do you hear? Is't not best to get a warrant, and have him arrested, and brought before Justice Clement?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>It were not amiss: would we had it.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter] BRAINWORM [disguised as FORMAL]</stage>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Why, here comes his man, let's speak to him.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Agreed, do you speak.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Save you, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>With all my heart, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Sir, there is one Downright hath abused this gentleman, and myself, and we determine to make our amends by law; now, if you would do us the favour to procure a warrant, to bring afore your master,

<pb id="n101-060"/>

you shall be well considered, I assure you, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Sir, you know my service is my living: such favours as these, gotten of my master, is his only preferment; and therefore you must consider me, as I may make benefit of my place.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>How is that, sir?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Faith, sir, the thing is extraordinary, and the gentleman may be of great accompt; yet, be what he will, if you will lay me down a brace of angels in my hand, you shall have it, otherwise not.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>How shall we do, Captain? He asks a brace of angels, you have no money?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Not a cross, by fortune.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Nor I, as I am a gentleman, but twopence, left of my two shillings in the morning for wine and radish: let's find him some pawn.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Pawn? We have none to the value of his demand.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Oh, yes. I'll pawn this jewel in my ear, and you may pawn your silk stockings, and pull up your boots, they will ne'er be missed; it must be done now.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Well, an' there be no remedy; I'll step aside, and pull 'em off.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Do you hear, sir? We have no store of money at this time, but you shall have good pawns: look you, sir, this jewel, and that gentleman's silk stockings, because we would have it dispatched ere we went to our chambers.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>I am content, sir: I will get you the warrant presently; what's his name, say you? Downright?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Aye, aye, George Downright.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>What manner of man is he?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>A tall big man, sir; he goes in a cloak, most commonly, of silk russet, laid about with russet lace.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>'Tis very good, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Here sir, here's my jewel.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>And here are stockings.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Well, gentlemen, I'll procure you this warrant presently, but who will you have to serve it?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>That's true, Captain; that must be considered.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Body o' me, I know not! 'Tis service of danger!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Why, you were best get one o' the varlets o' the city, a sergeant. I'll appoint you one, if you please.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Will you, sir? Why, we can wish no better.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>We'll leave it to you, sir.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exeunt BOBADILL and MATTHEW]</stage>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>This is rare! Now will I go pawn this cloak of the Justice's man's at the brokers for a varlet's suit, and be the varlet myself; and get either more pawns, or more money of Downright, for the arrest.</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-061"/>

<stage type="setting">[Exit]</stage>
</div2>

<div2 type="scene" n="8" id="d30">
<head>Act IV, Scene viii</head>

<stage type="setting">[Enter] KNOWELL</stage>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>Oh, here it is, I am glad: I have found it now. Ho! Who is within, here?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>TIB</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[Within]</stage>
<p>I am within sir, what's your pleasure?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>To know who is within, besides yourself.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>TIB</speaker>
<p>Why, sir, you are no constable, I hope?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Oh! Fear you the constable? Then, I doubt not.</l>
<l>You have some guests within deserve that fear,</l>
<l>I'll fetch him straight.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>TIB</speaker> <stage type="delivery">[Opens the door]</stage>
<p>O' God's name, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>Go to. Come, tell me, is not young Knowell here?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>TIB</speaker>
<p>Young Knowell? I know none such, sir, o' mine honesty!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Your honesty? Dame, it flies too lightly from you;</l>
<l>There is no way but, fetch the constable.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>TIB</speaker>
<p>The constable? The man is mad, I think.</p>
</sp>


<stage type="setting">[Exit, closing the door]</stage>
<stage type="setting">[Enter DAME KITELY and CASH]</stage>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<p>Ho, who keeps house here?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Oh, this is the female copesmate of my son!</l>
<l>Now shall I meet him straight.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Knock, Thomas, hard.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CASH</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Ho, good wife?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter TIB]</stage>

<sp><speaker>TIB</speaker>
<p>Why, what's the matter with you?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Why, woman, grieves it you to ope your door?</l>
<l>Belike you get something to keep it shut.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>TIB</speaker>
<lg>
<l>What mean these questions, pray ye?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>So strange you make it? Is not my husband here?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Her husband!</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>My tried husband, Master Kitely.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>TIB</speaker>
<lg>
<l>I hope he needs not to be tried here.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>No, dame: he does it not for need, but pleasure.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>TIB</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Neither for need, nor pleasure, is he here.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>This is but a device, to balk me withal.</l>
</lg>
<stage type="setting">[Enter KITELY}</stage>
<lg>
<l>Soft, who is this? 'Tis not my son, disguised?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Spies her husband come, and runs to him</l>
<l>Oh, sir, have I forestalled your honest market?</l>
<l>Found your close walks? You stand amazed, now, do you?</l>
<l>I' faith, I am glad, I have smoked you yet at last!</l>
<l>Where is your jewel, trow? In; come, let's see her</l>
<l>(Fetch forth your huswife, dame): if she be fairer,</l>
<l>In any honest judgement, than myself,</l>
<l>I'll be content with it; but, she is change,</l>
<l>She feeds you fat, she soothes your appetite,</l>

<pb id="n101-062"/>

<l>And you are well? Your wife, an honest woman,</l>
<l>Is meat twice sod to you, sir? Oh, you treacher!</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>She cannot counterfeit thus palpably.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Out on thy more-than-strumpet's impudence!</l>
<l>Steal'st thou thus to thy haunts? And have I taken</l>
<l>Thy bawd, and thee, and thy companion,</l>
</lg>
<stage type="delivery">Pointing to OLD KNOWELL</stage>
<lg>
<l>This hoary-headed lecher, this old goat,</l>
<l>Close at your villainy, and would'st thou 'scuse it,</l>
<l>With this stale harlot's jest, accusing me? To him</l>
<l>Oh, old incontinent, dost not thou shame,</l>
<l>When all thy powers' inchastity is spent,</l>
<l>To have a mind so hot? And to entice,</l>
<l>And feed th' enticements of a lustful woman?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Out, I defy thee, I, dissembling wretch!</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Defy me, strumpet. Ask thy pander, here,</l>
</lg>
<stage type="delivery">[Pointing to CASH]</stage>
<lg>
<l>Can he deny it? Or that wicked elder?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Why, hear you, sir.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Tut, tut, tut: never speak.</l>
<l>Thy guilty conscience will discover thee.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>What lunacy is this, that haunts this man?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Well, good wife B-A-'-D, Cob's wife; and you,</l>
<l>That make your husband such a hoddy-doddy;</l>
<l>And you, young apple-squire; and old cuckold-maker;</l>
<l>I'll ha' you every one before a justice:</l>
<l>Nay, you shall answer it, I charge you go.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Marry, with all my heart, sir: I go willingly.</l>
<l>Though I do taste this as a trick, put on me</l>
<l>To punish my impertinent search--and justly;</l>
<l>And half forgive my son for the device.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Come, will you go?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Go? To thy shame, believe it.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter COB]</stage>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Why, what's the matter here? What's here to do?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Oh, Cob, art thou come? I have been abused,</l>
<l>And i' thy house. Never was man so wronged!</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<lg>
<l>'Slid, in my house, my master Kitely?</l>
<l>Who wrongs you in my house?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Marry, young lust in old; and old in young, here:</l>
<l>Thy wife's their bawd, here have I taken 'em.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>How? Bawd? Is my house come to that? Am I preferred thither?  Falls upon his wife and beats her  Did I charge you to keep your doors shut, Is'bel? And do you let 'em open for all comers?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Friend, know some cause before thou beat'st thy wife,</l>
<l>This's madness in thee.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Why? Is there no cause?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Yes, I'll show cause before the Justice, Cob:</l>

<pb id="n101-063"/>

<l>Come, let her go with me.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Nay, she shall go.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>TIB</speaker>
<p>Nay, I will go. I'll see an' you may be allowed to make a bundle o' hemp, o' your right and lawful wife thus, at every cuckoldly knave's pleasure. Why do you not go?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>A bitter quean. Come, we'll ha' you tamed.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exeunt]</stage>
</div2>

<div2 type="scene" n="9" id="d31">
<head>Act IV, Scene ix</head>

<stage type="setting">[Enter] BRAINWORM [disguised as a sergeant]</stage>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Well, of all my disguises yet, now am I most like myself, being in this sergeant's gown. A man of my present profession never counterfeits, till he lays hold upon a debtor, and says, he 'rests him, for then he brings him to all manner of unrest. A kind of little kings we are, bearing the diminutive of a mace, made like a young artichoke, that always carries pepper and salt in itself. Well, I know not what danger I undergo by this exploit; pray heaven, I come well off.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter MATTHEW and BOBADILL]</stage>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>See, I think yonder is the varlet, by his gown.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Let's go in quest of him.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>'Save you, friend, are not you here by appointment of Justice Clement's man?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Yes, an't please you, sir: he told me two gentlemen had willed him to procure a warrant from his master, which I have about me, to be served on one Downright.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>It is honestly done of you both; and see where the party comes you must arrest.   Serve it upon him, quickly, afore he be aware--</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter STEPHEN in DOWNRIGHT's cloak]</stage>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Bear back, Master Matthew.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Master Downright, I arrest you, i' the Queen's name, and must carry you afore a Justice, by virtue of this warrant.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Me, friend? I am no Downright, I, I am Master Stephen, you do not well to arrest me, I tell you, truly: I am in nobody's bonds, nor books, I, would you should know it. A plague on you heartily, for making me thus afraid afore my time.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Why, now are you deceived, gentlemen?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>He wears such a cloak, and that deceived us; but see, here 'a comes, indeed! This is he, officer.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter DOWNRIGHT]</stage>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Why, how now, Signior Gull! Are you turned filcher of late? Come, deliver my cloak.</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-064"/>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Your cloak, sir? I bought it, even now, in open market.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Master Downright, I have a warrant I must serve upon you, procured by these two gentlemen.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>These gentlemen? These rascals?</p> 	<stage type="setting">[Raises his cudgel]</stage>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Keep the peace, I charge you, in her Majesty's name.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>I obey thee. What must I do, officer?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Go before Master Justice Clement, to answer what they can object against you, sir. I will use you kindly, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>Come, let's before, and make the Justice, Captain--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>The varlet's a tall man, afore heaven!</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Exeunt MATTHEW and BOBADILL]</stage>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Gull, you'll gi' me my cloak?</p>
</sp>


<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Sir, I bought it, and I'll keep it.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>You will.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Aye, that I will.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[Gives BRAINWORM money]</stage>
<p>Officer, there's thy fee, arrest him.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Master Stephen, I must arrest you.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Arrest me, I scorn it. There, take your cloak, I'll none on't.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Nay, that shall not serve your turn now, sir. Officer, I'll go with thee, to the Justice's; bring him along.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Why, is not here your cloak? What would you have?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>I'll ha' you answer it, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Sir, I'll take your word; and this gentleman's, too, for his appearance.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>I'll ha' no words taken. Bring him along.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Sir, I may choose to do that: I may take bail.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>'Tis true, you may take bail, and choose--at another time; but you shall not, now, varlet. Bring him along, or I'll swinge you.</p>
<stage type="setting">[Raises cudgel]</stage>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Sir, I pity the gentleman's case. Here's your money again.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>'Sdeynes, tell not me of my money, bring him away, I say.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>I warrant you he will go with you of himself, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Yet more ado?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<stage type="delivery">[Aside]</stage> <p>I have made a fair mash on't.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Must I go?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>I know no remedy, Master Stephen.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Come along, afore me, here. I do not love your hanging
look behind.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Why, sir, I hope you cannot hang me for it. Can he, fellow?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>I think not, sir. It is but a whipping matter, sure!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Why, then, let him do his worst, I am resolute.</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-065"/>

<stage type="setting">[Exeunt]</stage>
</div2>
</div1>

<div1 type="act" n="5" id="d32">
<head>Act V</head>

<div2 type="scene" n="1" id="d33">
<head>Scene i</head>

<stage type="setting">[Enter] CLEMENT, KNOWELL, KITELY, DAME KITELY, TIB, CASH, COB [and] SERVANTS</stage>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Nay, but stay, stay, give me leave; my chair, sirrah. You, Master Knowell, say you went thither to meet your son.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>Aye, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>But who directed you thither?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>That did mine own man, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Where is he?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>Nay, I know not, now: I left him with your clerk, and appointed him to stay here for me.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>My clerk? About what time was this?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>Marry, between one and two, as I take it.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>And, what time came my man with the false message to you, Master Kitely?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>After two, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Very good; but, Mistress Kitely, how that you were at Cob's? Ha?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<p>An' please you, sir, I'll tell you: my brother, Wellbred, told me that Cob's house was a suspected place--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>So it appears, methinks; but, on.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<p>And that my husband used thither, daily.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>No matter, so he used himself well, mistress.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DAME KITELY</speaker>
<p>True sir, but you know what grows by such haunts, often-times.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>I see rank fruits of a jealous brain, Mistress Kitely; but, did you find your husband there, in that case, as you suspected?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>I found her there, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Did you so? That alters the case. Who gave you knowledge, of your wife's being there?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>Marry, that did my brother Wellbred.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>How? Wellbred first tell her? Then tell you, after? Where is Wellbred?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>Gone with my sister, sir, I know not whither.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Why, this is a mere trick, a device: you are gulled in this most grossly, all! Alas, poor wench, wert thou beaten for this?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>TIB</speaker>
<p>Yes, most pitifully, an't please you.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>And worthily, I hope: if it shall prove so.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Aye, that's like, and a piece of a sentence.  [Enter a SERVANT] How now, sir? What's the matter?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>SERVANT</speaker>
<p>Sir, there's a gentleman, i' the court without, desires to speak with your worship.</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-066"/>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>A gentleman? What's he?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>SERVANT</speaker>
<p>A soldier, sir, he says.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>A soldier? Take down my armour, my sword, quickly: a
soldier speak with me! Why, when knaves?  He arms himself Come on, come on, hold my cap there, so; give me my gorget, my sword. Stand by, I will end your matters anon-- Let the soldier enter.</p>
<stage type="setting">[Exit SERVANT. Enter] BOBADILL [and] MATTHEW</stage>
<p>Now, sir, what ha' you to say to me?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>By your worship's favour--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Nay, keep out, sir, I know not your pretence, you send me word, sir, you are a soldier: why, sir, you shall be answered here, here be them have been amongst soldiers. Sir, your pleasure.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Faith, sir, so it is, this gentleman and myself have been most uncivilly wronged, and beaten, by one Downright, a coarse fellow about the town here, and for mine own part, I protest, being a man in no sort given to this filthy humour of quarrelling, he hath assaulted me in the way of my peace; despoiled me of mine honour; disarmed me of my weapons; and rudely laid me along in the open streets, when I not so much as once offered to resist him.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Oh, God's precious! Is this the soldier? Here, take my
armour off quickly, 'twill make him swoon, I fear: he is not fit to look on't, that will put up a blow.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>MATTHEW</speaker>
<p>An't please your worship, he was bound to the peace.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Why, an' he were, sir, his hands were not bound, were they?</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter SERVANT]</stage>

<sp><speaker>SERVANT</speaker>
<p>There's one of the varlets of the city, sir, has brought two gentlemen here, one upon your worship's warrant.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>My warrant?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>SERVANT</speaker>
<p>Yes, sir. The officer says, procured by these two.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Bid him come in. Set by this picture.</p>
<stage type="setting">[Exit SERVANT. Enter] DOWNRIGHT, STEPHEN [and] BRAINWORM [still disguised as a sergeant]</stage>
<p>What, Master Downright! Are you brought at Master 	Freshwater's suit, here?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Aye, faith, sir. And here's another brought at my suit.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>What are you, sir?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>A gentleman, sir. Oh, uncle!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Uncle? Who? Master Knowell.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>Aye, sir! This is a wise kinsman of mine.</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-067"/>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>God's my witness, uncle, I am wronged here monstrously, he charges me with stealing of his cloak, and would I might never stir, if I did not find it in the street, by chance.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Oh, did you find it, now? You said you bought it, erewhile.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>And you said I stole it; nay, now my uncle is here, I'll do well enough with you.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Well, let this breathe a while; you, that have cause to complain there, stand forth: had you my warrant for this gentleman's apprehension?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Aye, an't please your worship.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Nay, do not speak in passion so; where had you it?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BOBADILL</speaker>
<p>Of your clerk, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>That's well! An' my clerk can make warrants, and my hand not at 'em! Where is the warrant? Officer, have you it?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>No, sir, your worship's man, Master Formal, bid me do it for these gentlemen, and he would be my discharge.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Why, Master Downright, are you such a novice, to be served, and never see the warrant?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Sir. He did not serve it on me.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>No? How then?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>DOWNRIGHT</speaker>
<p>Marry, sir, he came to me, and said, he must serve it, and he would use me kindly, and so--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Oh, God's pity, was it so, sir? He must serve it? Give me my long-sword there, and help me off; so. Come on, sir varlet, I must cut off your legs, sirrah.  Flourishes over [the kneeling Brainworm] with his long-sword  Nay, stand up, I'll use you kindly; I must cut off your legs, I say.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Oh, good sir, I beseech you; nay, good Master Justice.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>I must do it: there is no remedy. I must cut off your legs, sirrah, I must cut off your ears, you rascal, I must do it; I must cut off your nose, I must cut off your head.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Oh, good your worship.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Well, rise, how dost thou do, now? Dost thou feel thyself well? Hast thou no harm?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>No, I thank your good worship, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Why, so! I said, I must cut off thy legs, and I must cut off thy arms, and I must cut off thy head; but I did not do it. So, you said, you must serve this gentleman with my warrant, but you did not serve him. You knave, you slave, you rogue, do you say you must? Sirrah, away with him, to the jail, I'll teach you a trick, for your must, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Good sir, I beseech you, be good to me.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Tell him he shall to the jail, away with him, I say.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Nay, sir, if you will commit me, it shall be for committing more than this: I will not lose, by my travail, any grain of my fame certain.</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-068"/>

<stage type="delivery">[Pulls off his disguise]</stage>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>How is this!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>My man, Brainworm!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>Oh yes, uncle. Brainworm has been with my cousin Edward and I all this day.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>I told you all there was some device!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Nay, excellent Justice, since I have laid myself thus open to you, now stand strong for me: both with your sword, and your balance.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Body o' me, a merry knave! Give me a bowl of sack. If he belong to you, Master Knowell, I bespeak your patience.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>That is it I have most need of.</p> <stage type="delivery">[To KNOWELL]</stage> <p>Sir, if you'll pardon me only, I'll glory in all the rest of my exploits.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>Sir, you know I love not to have my favours come hard from me. You have your pardon; though I suspect you shrewdly for being of counsel with my son, against me.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Yes, faith, I have, sir; though you retained me doubly this morning for yourself: first, as Brainworm; after, as Fitzsword. I was your reformed soldier, sir. 'Twas I sent you to Cob's, upon the errand without end.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>Is it possible! Or that thou should'st disguise thy language so, as I should not know thee?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Oh, sir, this has been the day of my metamorphosis! It is not that shape alone that I have run through, today. I brought this gentleman, Master Kitely, a message too, in the form of Master Justice's man, here, to draw him out o' the way, as well as your worship; while Master Wellbred might make a conveyance of Mistress Bridget to my young master.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<p>How! My sister stol'n away?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>My son is not married, I hope!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Faith, sir, they are both as sure as love, a priest, and three thousand pound (which is her portion) can make 'em; and by this time are ready to bespeak their wedding supper at the Windmill, except some friend, here, prevent 'em, and invite 'em home.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Marry, that will I (I thank thee for putting me in mind on't). Sirrah, go you, and fetch 'em hither, upon my warrant.</p> <stage type="setting">[Exit SERVANT]</stage> <p>Neither's friends have cause to be sorry, if I know the young couple aright. Here, I drink to thee, for thy good news. But, I pray thee, what hast thou done with my man Formal?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>BRAINWORM</speaker>
<p>Faith, sir, after some ceremony past, as making him drunk, first with story, and then with wine (but all in kindness) and stripping him to his shirt, I left him in that cool vein, departed, sold your worship's warrant to these two, pawned his livery for that varlet's gown, to serve it in; and thus have brought myself, by my activity, to your worship's consideration.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>And I will consider thee in another cup of sack. Here's to thee, which having drunk off, this is my sentence. Pledge me. Thou hast done or

<pb id="n101-069"/>

assisted to nothing, in my judgement, but deserves to be pardoned for the wit o' the offence. If thy master, or any man here, be angry with thee, I shall suspect his ingine, while I know him, for't. How now? What noise is that?</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[Enter SERVANT]</stage>

<sp><speaker>SERVANT</speaker>
<p>Sir, it is Roger is come home.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Bring him in, bring him in.</p>
<stage type="setting">[Enter] FORMAL [in a suit of armour]</stage>
<p>What! Drunk in arms, against me? Your reason, your reason for this?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>FORMAL</speaker>
<p>I beseech your worship to pardon me: I happened into ill company by chance, that cast me into a sleep, and stripped me of all my clothes--</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Well, tell him I am Justice Clement, and do pardon him; but, what is this to your armour? What may that signify?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>FORMAL</speaker>
<p>An't please you, sir, it hung up i' the room where I was stripped; and I borrowed it of one o' the drawers, to come home in, because I was loath to do penance through the street i' my shirt.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Well, stand by a while. Who be these?</p>
<stage type="setting">[Enter] EDWARD, WELLBRED, [and] BRIDGET</stage>
<p>Oh, the young company, welcome, welcome. Gi' you joy. Nay, Mistress Bridget, blush not: you are not so fresh a bride but the news of it is come hither afore you. Master bridegroom, I ha' made your peace, give me your hand; so will I for all the rest, ere you forsake my roof.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>We are the more bound to your humanity, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Only these two have so little of man in 'em, they are no part of my care.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Yes, sir, let me pray you for this gentleman, he belongs to my sister, the bride.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>In what place, sir?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>Of her delight, sir, below the stairs, and in public: her poet, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>A poet? I will challenge him myself, presently, at extempore:</p>
<lg>
<l>Mount up thy Phlegon muse, and testify,</l>
<l>How Saturn, sitting in an ebon cloud,</l>
<l>Disrobed his podex white as ivory,</l>
<l>And, through the welkin, thundred all aloud.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>He is not for extempore, sir. He is all for the pocket-muse, please you command a sight of it.</p>
</sp>

<pb id="n101-070"/>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Yes, yes, search him for a taste of his vein.</p>
</sp>

<stage type="setting">[They search the pockets of MATTHEW, who resists]</stage>

<sp><speaker>WELLBRED</speaker>
<p>You must not deny the Queen's Justice, sir, under a writ o' rebellion.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>What! All this verse? Body o' me, he carries a whole realm, a commonwealth of paper, in's hose! Let's see some of his subjects!</p>
<lg>
<l>Unto the boundless Ocean of thy face,</l>
<l>Runs this poor river charged with streams of eyes.</l>
<l>How? This is stol'n!</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>A parody! A parody! With a kind of miraculous gift to make it absurder than it was.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Is all the rest, of this batch? Bring me a torch: lay it together, and give fire. Cleanse the air. Here was enough to have infected the whole city, if it had not been taken in time. See, see, how our poet's glory shines! Brighter and brighter! Still it increases! Oh, now it's at the highest; and now it declines as fast. You may see. <foreign lang="lat">Sic transit gloria mundi.</foreign></p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KNOWELL</speaker>
<p>There's an emblem for you, son, and your studies!</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Nay, no speech or act of mine be drawn against such as profess it worthily. They are not born every year, as an alderman. There goes more to the making of a good poet, than a sheriff, Master Kitely. You look upon me! Though I live i' the city here, amongst you, I will do more reverence to him, when I meet him, than I will to the mayor, out of his year. But, these paper-pedlars! These ink-dabblers! They cannot expect reprehension, or reproach. They have it with the fact.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
<p>Sir, you have saved me the labour of a defence.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>It shall be discourse for supper: between your father and me, if he dare undertake me. But, to dispatch away these, you sign o' the Soldier, and picture o' the Poet (but both so false I will not ha' you hanged out at my door till midnight), while we are at supper, you two shall penitently fast it in my court, without; and, if you will, you may pray there, that we may be so merry within as to forgive, or forget you, when we come out. Here's a third, because we tender your safety, shall watch you, he is provided for the purpose.</p> <stage type="delivery">[To Formal]</stage> <p>Look to your charge, sir.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>And what shall I do?</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Oh, I had lost a sheep, an' he had not bleated! Why, sir, you shall give Master Downright his cloak; and I will entreat him to take it. A trencher and a napkin you shall have, i' the buttery, and keep Cob and his wife company, here; whom I will entreat first to be reconciled, and you to endeavour with your wit to keep 'em so.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>STEPHEN</speaker>
<p>I'll do my best.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>COB</speaker>
<p>Why, now I see thou art honest, Tib, I receive thee as my dear and mortal wife again.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>TIB</speaker>
<p>And I you, as my loving and obedient husband.</p>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>Good complement! It will be their bridal night too. They are

<pb id="n101-071"/>

married anew. Come, I conjure the rest to put off all discontent. You, Master Downright, your anger; you, Master Knowell, your cares; Master Kitely, and his wife, their jealousy.</p>
<lg>
<l>For, I must tell you both, while that is fed,</l>
<l>Horns i' the mind are worse than o' the head.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>KITELY</speaker>
<lg>
<l>Sir, thus they go from me; kiss me, sweetheart.</l>
<l>'See what a drove of horns fly in the air,</l>
<l>Winged with my cleans&egrave;d, and my credulous breath!</l>
<l>Watch 'em, suspicious eyes, watch where they fall.</l>
<l>See, see! On heads, that think they've none at all!</l>
<l>Oh, what a plenteous world of this will come!</l>
<l>When air rains horns, all may be sure of some.</l>
<l>I ha' learned so much verse out of a jealous man's part in a play.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp><speaker>CLEMENT</speaker>
<p>'Tis well, 'tis well! This night we'll dedicate to friendship, love, and laughter. Master bridegroom, take your bride, and lead; every one, a fellow. Here is my mistress: Brainworm! To whom all my addresses of courtship shall have their reference. Whose adventures this day, when our grandchildren shall hear to be made a fable, I doubt not but it shall find both spectators, and applause.</p>
</sp>

</div2>
</div1>

</body>

</text>
</TEI.2>
