<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="KeeSeki"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="KeeSeki">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Sekidera Komachi</title>
<title type="sort">sekidera komachi</title>
<author>Keene translation: Brazell, Karen</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Charlotte Robertson and Winnie Chan</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">33</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">KeeSeki</idno>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476134</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Japanese Text Initiative</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>(ETC) The text has been given an id of KeeSeki because this
edition is commonly referred to as the Keene translation.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Sekidera Komachi</title>
<title level="m">Twenty Plays of the N&omacr; Theatre</title>
<title type="sort">sekidera komachi</title>
<author>Karen Brazell</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
<name>Donald Keene</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>pp. 15-34</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Columbia University Press</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1970">1970</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa Library call number PL 782 .E5K4</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Records of Civilization: Sources and Studies, number LXXXV</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>From <hi rend="italic">
<hi rend="bold">Twenty Plays of the No Theatre</hi>
</hi> edited
by Donald Keene.  Copyright (c) 1970 Columbia University Press.
Reprinted with permission of the publisher.  To order the
paperback edition of this book please call 1-800-944-8648 or
click on to the Web page:  http://www.cc.columbia.edu/cu/cup.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
<language id="rj">Romaji</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>drama; poetry; prose</term>
<term>Literature in Translation</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-09">September 1997</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added milestones to correspond with TylSeki.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="1997-02">February 1997</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Winnie Chan</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<front id="d2">

<pb n="66"/>

<div1 type="introduction" id="d3">
<head>INTRODUCTION</head>

<p>
<hi rend="italic">Komachi at Sekidera</hi> belongs to the third category.
It was probably written by Zeami, though some authorities hesitate to make
the attribution. The play is considered to be the loftiest and most
difficult of the entire N&omacr; repertory. In the past century only a few
great actors at the close of their careers have ventured to perform it. It
enjoys its high reputation because it celebrates, with the most exquisite
simplicity, the bittersweet delight of being alive. Childhood, maturity,
extreme old age, the pleasure and pain of life, are immediately
communicated. The play conveys a timeless moment in the brief interval
between birth and death. Its subject is poetry. Much of the great poetry
in N&omacr; lies somewhat outside the main Japanese poetic traditions, but
<hi rend="italic">Komachi at Sekidera</hi> is at once a superb N&omacr;
play and a splendid expression of the sources of Japanese poetry. The <hi rend="italic">shite</hi>
role is considered so difficult because there is
little an actor can add to the text unless he is supremely gifted. During
the first hour of the performance Komachi hardly stirs.
</p>

<p>
The setting is wonderfully appropriate. The time is the festival of
Tanabata, the seventh night of the seventh month: the one night of the
year when the Cowherd star can cross the River of Heaven to join the
Weaver-girl star. On earth all are celebrating


<pb n="67"/>
the lovers' brief reunion. Even at Sekidera, a place of quiet
renunciation, the priests and child acolytes are about to observe the
festival. But while talking about poetry with the aged woman who lives in
a hut nearby, the abbot of the temple discovers she is none other than Ono
no Komachi.
</p>

<p>
Komachi, a woman of great beauty and literary gifts, lived at the Heian
court during the ninth century. She became a legend in later times, with
many apocryphal stories surrounding the few known biographical facts. Five
N&omacr; plays about Komachi are in the present repertory; <hi rend="italic">Komachi and the Hundred Nights</hi> presents another aspect
of the Komachi legend, and <hi rend="italic">Sotoba Komachi</hi>
(translated in Keene, <hi rend="italic">Anthology of Japanese
Literature</hi>) ranks nearly on a level with <hi rend="italic">Komachi
at Sekidera.</hi>
</p>

<p>
The structure of the play is classic, and remarkable for its economy and
simplicity. Nothing jars, nothing is wasted. The moment when Komachi
admits her identity to the Abbot is particularly touching because so
unaffected.
</p>

<p>
Sekidera ("The Barrier Temple") still exists at &Omacr;tsu, a city east of
Kyoto; its modern name is Ch&omacr;anji.
</p>

<p>
<hi rend="italic">Komachi at Sekidera is</hi> in the repertory of all
schools of N&omacr;.
</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="section" id="d4">
<pb n="68"/>
<list>
<head>PERSONS</head>
<item>The Abbot of Sekidera (<hi rend="italic">waki</hi>)</item>
<item>Two Priests (<hi rend="italic">wakizure</hi></item>
<item>A Child (<hi rend="italic">kokata</hi>)</item>
<item>Ono No Komachi (<hi rend="italic">shite</hi>)</item>
</list>
</div1>


<div1 type="section" id="d5">
<p>PLACE</p>
<p>Sekidera in &Omacr;mi province
</p>


<p>TIME</p>
<p>The beginning of autumn: the seventh day of the seventh month
</p>
</div1>
</front>



<body id="d6">
<div1 type="play" id="d7"><pb n="69"/>
<head>KOMACHI AT SEKIDERA<lb/>
(<hi rend="italic">SEKIDERA KOMACHI</hi>)</head>

<stage>
The stage assistants bring forward a simple construction representing a
hut with a thatched roof.  It is covered with a cloth.  The Old Woman is
inside.
<lb/>
As the music begins the Child, the Abbot, and two Priests enter and face
each other onstage.  The Abbot and the Priests carry rosaries.
</stage>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki1"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Three Priests</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>So long awaited, autumn has come at last,</l>
<l>So long awaited, the lovers' autumn meeting!</l>
<l>Now let us begin the Festival of Stars.
<ref target="n69.1">[1]</ref></l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage>
The Abbot faces front.
</stage>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki2"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Abbot</speaker>
<p>
I am the chief priest of Sekidera in &Omacr;mi.  Today, the seventh day of the
Seventh month, we come to celebrate the Festival of Stars here in the
temple garden.  People say that the old woman who has built her hut at the
foot of the mountain knows all the secrets of the art of poetry.  So, on
this festive day dedicated to poetry, I am going to take the young people
to hear her stories.
</p>
</sp>

<stage>
He turns to the Child.
</stage>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki3"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Three Priests</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>Early autumn comes and brings a touch of chill.</l>
<l>We feel it in the wind and in our thinning locks.
<ref target="n69.2">[2]</ref></l>
<l>Soon, soon the Seventh Night will be on us.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage>
The Abbot faces front.
</stage>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki4"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Abbot</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>We bring offerings for the festival today,</l>
<l>The music of flutes and strings,</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki5"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Two Priests</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>And many poems</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki6"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Abbot</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>Composed in our native tongue.
<ref target="n69.3">[3]</ref></l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage>
He turns to the Child.
</stage>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki7"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Three Priests</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>Our prayers for skill at poetry are decked</l>
<l>With brightly colored streamers:</l>
<l>Fluttering ribbons, each a token of prayer,</l>
<l>Like silk threads woven into rich brocades</l>
<l>On looms of autumn flowers</l>
<l>And pampas grass pearly with dew.</l>


<pb n="70"/>
<l>The winds in the pines</l>
</lg>

<stage>
The Abbot faces front, takes a few steps, then returns to his former
position, indicating he has made a journey.
</stage>

<lg type="poem">
<l>Blend with the strings of the <hi rend="italic">koto</hi></l>
<l>To make music for the offerings tonight,
<ref target="n70.4">[4]</ref></l>
<l>Our offerings for this festive night.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage>
The Abbot and his companions are now at their destination.
</stage>

<sp>
<speaker>Abbot</speaker>
<p>
Here is the hut now.  Let us call on the old woman.
</p>

<stage>
To the Child.
</stage>

<p>
But first, please sit down.
</p>
</sp>

<stage>
All kneel.  A stage assistant removes the cloth around the hut, revealing
the Old Woman seated inside.  Paper strips inscribed with poems hang from
the crossbars of the hut frame.  The Old Woman wears the <hi rend="italic">uba</hi> mask.
</stage>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki8"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Old Woman</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>Days go by without a single bowl of food;</l>
<l>Whom can I ask for one?</l>
<l>At night my tattered rags fail to cover me,</l>
<l>But there is no way to patch the rents.</l>
<l>Each passing rain</l>
<l>Ages the crimson of the flowers;</l>
<l>The willows are tricked by the wind,</l>
<l>And their green gradually droops.
<ref target="n70.5">[5]</ref></l>
<l>Man has no second chance at youth;</l>
<l>He grows old.  The aged song thrush</l>
<l>Warbles again when spring has come,</l>
<l>But time does not revert to the past.</l>
<l>Oh, how I yearn for the days that are gone!</l>
<l>What would I do to recapture the past!</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage>
She weeps.  The Abbot and the Child rise, and go to kneel before her.
</stage>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki9"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Abbot</speaker>
<p>
Old woman, we have come to speak with you.
</p>
</sp>

<sp>
<speaker>Old Woman</speaker>
<p>
Who are you?
</p>
</sp>

<sp>
<speaker>Abbot</speaker>
<p>
I am a priest from Sekidera.  These young people are students of poetry.
They have heard of your talent, and I have brought them here to question
you about poetry and to learn something of your life.
</p>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki10"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Old Woman</speaker>
<p>
This is an unexpected visit!  The log buried in the earth has been so long
forgotten you must not expect it will put forth new sprouts.
<ref target="n70.6">[6]</ref>
Just remember this: If you will make


<pb n="71"/>
your heart the seed and your words the blossoms,
<ref target="n71.7">[7]</ref>
if you will steep yourself in the fragrance of the art, you will not fail
to accomplish true poetry.  But how praiseworthy that mere boys should
cherish a love of poetry!
</p>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki11"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Abbot</speaker>
<p>
May I ask you about a poem everyone knows, "The Harbor of Naniwa?"
<ref target="n71.8">[8]</ref>
Do you agree that it should be used as a first guide?
</p>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki12"/>
<sp>
<speaker> Old Woman</speaker>
<p>
Indeed I do.  Poetry goes back to the Age of the Gods, but the meters were
then irregular and the meanings difficult to understand.  "The Harbor of
Naniwa," however, belongs to the Age of Man.  It was composed for the
joyous occasion of an emperor's enthronement, and has long been beloved
for that reason.
<ref target="n71.9">[9]</ref>
</p>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki13"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Abbot</speaker>
<p>
The poem about Mount Asaka, which once soothed the heart of a prince, is
also beautifully written.
<ref target="n71.10">[10]</ref>
</p>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki14"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Old Woman</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>Truly, you understand the art,</l>
<l>For those two poems are the parents of all poetry.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki15"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Abbot</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>They serve as models for beginners.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki16"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Old Woman</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>Noblemen and peasantry alike,</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki17"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Abbot</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>City dwellers and country folk,</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki18"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Old Woman</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>Even commoners like ourselves</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki19"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Abbot</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>Take pleasure in composing poetry</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp>
<speaker>Old Woman</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>Following the promptings of our hearts.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki20"/>
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki21"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>Though the sands lapped by the waves</l>
<l>Of the lake in Omi should run out,</l>
<l>Though the sands of the shore should melt away,</l>
</lg>

<stage>
The Abbot and the Child return to kneel with the Priests.
</stage>

<lg type="poem">
<l>The words of poetry will never fail.
<ref target="n71.11">[11]</ref></l>
<l>They are enduring as evergreen boughs of pine,</l>
<l>Continuous as trailing branches of willow;</l>
<l>For poetry, whose source and seed is found</l>
<l>In the human heart, is everlasting.</l>
<l>Though ages pass and all things vanish,</l>
<l>As long as words of poetry remain,</l>
<l>Poems will leave their marks behind,</l>
<l>And the traces of poetry will never disappear.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki22"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Abbot</speaker>
<p>
Thank you for your words of explanation.  It is true that countless poems
survive from the past, but they are rarely by


<pb n="72"/>
women.  Few women know as much as you about poetry.  Tell me&mdash;the
poem
</p>
<lg type="poem">
<l>"I know my lover</l>
<l>Is coming tonight&mdash;</l>
<l>See how the spider</l>
<l>Spins her web:</l>
<l>That is a sure sign!"
<ref target="n72.12">[12]</ref></l>
</lg>
<p>Was that not by a woman?</p>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki23"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Old Woman</speaker>
<p>
Yes, that poem was written long ago by Princess Sotori, the consort of
Emperor Ingyo.  I tried, if only in form. to master her style.
</p>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki24"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Abbot</speaker>
<p>
Ah! You have studied the style of Princess Sotori?  I have heard that Ono
no Komachi, who's so much talked of these days, wrote in that style.
<ref target="n72.13">[13]</ref>
</p>

<lg type="poem">
<l>"Wretched that I am&mdash;</l>
<l>A floating water weed,</l>
<l>Broken from its roots&mdash;</l>
<l>If a stream should beckon,</l>
<l>I would follow it, I think."</l>
</lg>
<p>That poem is by Komachi.
</p>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki25"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Old Woman</speaker>
<p>
Yes, once my husband, Oe no Koreaki, took up with another woman, and I
grieved at the fickleness of the world.  Then, Funya no Yasuhide
<ref target="n72.14">[14]</ref>
invited me to accompany him to Mikawa, where he was to be the governor.  I
wrote that poem in response to his urging and to his promises that life in
the country would bring solace.
</p>

<lg type="poem">
<l>Alas, memories of the past!</l>
<l>So long forgotten, they rise up again</l>
<l>Before me as I talk to you.</l>
<l>Tears well up from my suffering heart.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage>
She weeps.
</stage>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki26"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Abbot</speaker>
<p>
Strange! This old woman says she wrote the poem "Wretched that I am." And
she says she wrote in the Sotori style, just as Komachi did.  She must be
nearly a hundred years old, and if Komachi were still alive today. . . .
And is there any reason why she couldn't be?  It <hi rend="italic">must</hi> be so!

<stage>
to the Old Woman.
</stage>

You are what is left of Ono no Komachi.  Do not deny it.
</p>
</sp>


<pb n="73"/>
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki27"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Old Woman</speaker>
<p>
Ah, I burn with shame to be called Komachi, I who wrote
</p>
<lg type="poem">
<l>"With no outward sign</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki28"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>It withers&mdash;</l>
<l>The flower in the human heart."
<ref target="n73.15">[15]</ref></l>
</lg>
<p>How ashamed I am to be seen!</p>
<lg type="poem">
<l>"Wretched that I am&mdash;</l>
<l>A floating water weed,</l>
<l>Broken from its roots&mdash;</l>
<l>If a stream should beckon,</l>
<l>I would follow it, I think."</l>
</lg>
<p>How ashamed I am!</p>


<stage>
She weeps.
</stage>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki29"/>
<lg type="poem">
<l>"Hide them though I may,</l>
<l>The tears keep flowing,</l>
<l>Too many for my sleeves to hold&mdash;</l>
<l>A rain of tears dissolving</l>
<l>Everything except the past."
<ref target="n73.16">[16]</ref></l>
</lg>
<p>Now that my life has reached its end,<lb/>
Like a withered flower,<lb/>
Why should there still be tears?</p>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki30"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Old Woman</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>"Longing for him,</l>
<l>I fell asleep,</l>
<l>Then he appeared before me . . ."
<ref target="n73.17">[17]</ref></l>
</lg>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki31"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>The joy I felt when I composed those lines</l>
<l>Is gone forever, but still my life goes on,</l>
<l>Attending the months and years as they come and go.</l>
<l>The dews of spring depart, and autumn frosts appear,</l>
<l>The leaves and grasses turn, and insect voices fade.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki32"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Old Woman</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>My life is over, and now I see</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki34"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>It was like a rose of Sharon that knows</l>
<l>Only a single day of glory.
<ref target="n73.18">[18]</ref></l>
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki35"/>
<l>"The living go on dying,</l>
<l>The dead increase in number;</l>
<l>Left in this world, ah&mdash;</l>
<l>How long must I go on</l>
<l>Lamenting for the dead?"
<ref target="n73.19">[19]</ref></l>
<l>And how long must I, who wrote that poem,</l>
<l>Live on, like flowers fallen, like leaves scattered,</l>


<pb n="74"/>
<l>With nothing left but life&mdash;dewlike, they always said.</l>
<l>Oh, how I long for the past!</l>
<l>My middle years were spent in yearning</l>
<l>For the distant glory of my youth.</l>
<l>Now even those days of wistful recollection</l>
<l>Have become such ancient history</l>
<l>I find myself wishing, if not for youth,</l>
<l>At least for middle age.</l>
<l>Long ago, wherever I spent a single night</l>
<l>My room would be bright with tortoise shell,</l>
<l>Golden flowers hung from the walls,</l>
<l>And in the door were strings of crystal beads.
<ref target="n74.20">[20]</ref></l>
<l>Brilliant as the Emperor's chair in grand procession</l>
<l>The jewellike gowns I wore, a hundred colors.</l>
<l>I lay on bright brocaded quilts</l>
<l>Within a pillowed bridal chamber.</l>
<l>Look at it now, my mud-daubed hut!</l>
<l>Can this be my resplendent room?</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp>
<speaker>Old Woman</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>The temple bell of Sekidera</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<sp>
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>Tolls the vanity of all creation&mdash;</l>
<l>To ancient ears a needless lesson.</l>
<l>A mountain wind blows down Osaka's slope</l>
<l>To moan the certainty of death;</l>
<l>Its message still eludes me.</l>
<l>Yet, when blossoms scatter and leaves fall,</l>
<l>Still in this hut I find my pleasure:</l>
<l>Grinding ink, I dip my brush and write.</l>
<l>My words are all dry, like seaweed on the shore.</l>
<l>Touching, they once said, but lacking strength
<ref target="n74.21">[21]</ref>&mdash;</l>
<l>My poems lacked strength because they were a woman's.</l>
<l>Now when I have grown decrepit</l>
<l>My poems are weaker still.  Their life is spent.</l>
<l>How wretched it is to be old!</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage>
She weeps.  The Child turns to the Abbot.
</stage>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki36"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Child</speaker>
<p>
I'm afraid we'll be late for the Festival of Stars.  Let's ask the old
lady to come with us.
</p>
</sp>

<stage>
The Abbot kneels before the Old Woman.
</stage>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki37"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Abbot</speaker>
<p>
Please join us on this Seventh Night, the Festival of Stars.
</p>
</sp>


<pb n="75"/>
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki38"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Old Woman</speaker>
<p>
Alas! An old woman should not intrude on such an occasion.  I cannot go.
</p>
</sp>

<stage>
She takes down the paper poem cards.
</stage>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki39"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Abbot</speaker>
<p>
What harm could come of it?  Please come with us.
</p>
</sp>

<stage>
He goes to the hut and helps the Old Woman to stand.
</stage>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki40"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>The Seventh Night&mdash;</l>
<l>How many years since first I offered the gods</l>
<l>Bamboo tied with colored streamers?</l>
<l>How long has shriveled old Komachi lived?</l>
</lg>

<stage>
Assisted by the Abbot and leaning on a staff, the Old Woman leaves the
hut.
</stage>

<lg type="poem">
<l>Has Ono no Komachi reached a hundred years?</l>
<l>Or even more?</l>
<l>I who used to watch the Festival of Stars,</l>
<l>Familiar of the noblest lords and ladies,</l>
</lg>

<stage>
She kneels beside the <hi rend="italic">shite</hi>-pillar.  The
Abbot goes back beside the others.
</stage>

<lg type="poem">
<l>Now stand in shameful hempen rags!</l>
<l>A sight too painful for eyes to bear! </l>
</lg>

<stage>
The Abbot weeps.
</stage>

<lg type="poem">
<l>Still, tonight we hold the Festival of Stars,</l>
</lg>
<stage>
The Child stands and mimes serving wine to the Old Woman.
</stage>

<lg type="poem">
<l>Tonight we celebrate the Seventh Night</l>
<l>With multitudes of offerings for the stars.</l>
<l>Prayer streamers hang from bamboo,</l>
</lg>

<stage>
While the following lines are being sung the Child goes to the
gazing-pillar, moves clockwise around the stage, then stands at the center
preparatory to beginning his dance.
</stage>

<lg type="poem">
<l>Music plays and cups of wine go round.</l>
<l>The young dancer-look how gracefully</l>
<l>He twirls his sleeves, like snow</l>
<l>Swirling in the moonlight.</l>
</lg>

<stage>
The Old Woman, still seated, watches the Child dance.
</stage>

<lg type="poem">
<l>We celebrate the Festival of Stars,</l>
<l>Streamers flutter from the bamboos . . .</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki41"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Old Woman</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>May it be celebrated through ages as many</l>
<l>As the joints of the bamboo!</l>
</lg>
</sp>


<pb n="76"/>
<stage>
The Old Woman, hardly aware of what she does, taps the rhythm with her
fan.
</stage>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki42"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>We pray for eternal prosperity;</l>
<l>We dance the "Ten Thousand Years."
<ref target="n76.22">[22]</ref></l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage>
The Child completes his dance, then sits as before.
</stage>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki43"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Old Woman</speaker>
<p>
How gracefully that boy has danced! I remember how, long ago in the
Palace, the Gosechi dancing girls swirled their sleeves five times at the
Harvest Festival.  They say that if a madman runs, even the sane will run
after him.  But tonight the proverb is reversed!  Enticed by the boy's
floating sleeves, see how a madwoman prances!
</p>

<stage>
She stands with the aid of her staff and begins her dance.
</stage>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki44"/>
<lg type="poem">
<l>One hundred years&mdash;</l>
<l>The dance of the butterfly</l>
<l>Who dreamt he had spent</l>
<l>A hundred years enfolded</l>
<l>Within a flower petal.
<ref target="n76.23">[23]</ref></l>
</lg>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki45"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>How sad it isl It breaks my heart</l>
<l>A flowering branch on a withered tree!</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki46"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Old Woman</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>I have forgotten how to move my hands.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki47"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>Unsteady feet, uncertain wave of sleeves,</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki48"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Old Woman</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>Billow after billow, floating wave on wave.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki49"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>My dancing sleeves rise up,</l>
<l>But sleeves cannot wave back the past.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage>
She goes before the hut.
</stage>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki50"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Old Woman</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>I miss those vanished days!</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage>
She kneels and weeps.
</stage>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki51"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>But as I dance the early autumn night,</l>
<l>The short night, gives way to dawn.</l>
<l>The temple bell of Sekidera tolls.</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki52"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Old Woman</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>A chorus of morning birdsong heralds</l>
</lg>
</sp>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki53"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>The coming dawn, the day's approaching light,</l>
<l>The dawn's fresh light that reveals my shame!</l>
<l>Where is the forest of Hazukashi?
<ref target="n76.24">[24]</ref></l>
</lg>
</sp>

<stage>
She stands, propping herself on her staff.
</stage>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki54"/>
<sp>
<speaker>Chorus</speaker>
<lg type="poem">
<l>Where is the forest of Hazukashi?</l>


<pb n="77"/>
<l>There is no forest here to hide my shame.</l>
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki55"/>
<l>Farewell, I take my leave.</l>
<l>Now, leaning heavily on her stick,</l>
<l>She slowly returns to her straw hut.</l>
</lg>

<stage>
She enters the hut, sits and weeps.
</stage>

<lg type="poem">
<l>The hundred-year-old woman you have spoken to</l>
<l>Is all that remains of famed Komachi,</l>
<l>Is all that is left of Ono no Komachi.</l>
</lg>
</sp>
</div1>
</body>



<back id="d8">

<div1 type="notes" id="d9"><pb n="78"/>
<head>Notes</head>

<note id="n69.1"><seg type="note-symbol">1. </seg> <p>The Tanabata Festival, of Chinese origin, is still celebrated in Japan
on the seventh day of the seventh month.  Bamboo branches are decorated
with five-colored streamers and with slips on which poems have been
written commemorating the lovers' meeting of the two stars.
</p></note>

<note id="n69.2"><seg type="note-symbol">2.</seg> <p> From some lines by PoChu-i included in the <hi rend="italic">Wakan
Roei Sh&umacr;</hi>, no. 204:	"Who could have arranged things so well?
The sighing cool wind and my thinning locks at once announce autumn is
here." A parallel is drawn between the coming of autumn in the world and
the coming of autumn to the person, evidenced by the thinning locks.
</p></note>

<note id="n69.3"><seg type="note-symbol">3.</seg> <p> Many poets wrote in Chinese, especially on formal occasions, but the
Japanese preferred their own language for their intimate feelings.
</p></note>

<note id="n70.4"><seg type="note-symbol">4.</seg> <p> The above three lines are based on a poem by the Consort Itsukinomiya
in the <hi rend="italic">Shuish&umacr;</hi>, no. 451.
</p></note>

<note id="n70.5"><seg type="note-symbol">5.</seg> <p> Derived from an anonymous poem in Chinese found in a commentary to the
historical work Hyakurensho.
</p></note>

<note id="n70.6"><seg type="note-symbol">6.</seg> <p> Quoted, with slight modifications, from the preface to the <hi rend="italic">Kokinsh&umacr;</hi>.
</p></note>

<note id="n71.7"><seg type="note-symbol">7.</seg> <p> Also from the preface to the <hi rend="italic">Kokinsh&umacr;</hi>.
</p></note>

<note id="n71.8"><seg type="note-symbol">8.</seg> <p> This is the "Naniwazu" poem: "In Naniwa Harbor/ The flowers
have come to the trees;/ They slept through the winter,/ But now it is the
spring&mdash;/ See how the blossoms have opened!" The preface to the <hi rend="italic">Kokinsh&umacr;</hi>
characterizes this poem and the one on
Asakayama, Mount Asaka, as the "father and mother of poetry." Both poems
are given considerable attention in <hi rend="italic">The Reed
Cutter</hi>.
</p></note>

<note id="n71.9"><seg type="note-symbol">9.</seg> <p> The poem was traditionally supposed to have been composed to encourage
the future Emperor Nintoku, who reigned in the fourth century A.D., to
accept the throne.
</p></note>

<note id="n71.10"><seg type="note-symbol">10.</seg> <p> The poem runs, literally: "Mount Asaka&mdash;/ Its reflection appears
In the mountain spring/ That is not shallow, and of you/ My thoughts are
not shallow either." The Prince of Kazuraki was sent to the distant
province of Mutsu where he was badly received by the governor.  He was so
angry that he refused to eat, but the governor's daughter cheered him by
offering sak&eacute; and reciting this poem.
</p></note>

<note id="n71.11"><seg type="note-symbol">11.</seg> <p> Based on lines from the <hi rend="italic">Kokinsh&umacr;</hi>
preface: "Though you count up my love you could never come to the end, not
even if you could count every grain of sand on the shore of the wild sea."
</p></note>

<note id="n72.12"><seg type="note-symbol">12.</seg> <p> An anonymous poem, no. 1110 in the <hi rend="italic">Kokinsh&umacr;</hi>.
</p></note>


<pb n="79"/>
<note id="n72.13"><seg type="note-symbol">13.</seg> <p> So stated in the preface to the <hi rend="italic">Kokinsh&umacr;</hi>.
</p></note>

<note id="n72.14"><seg type="note-symbol">14.</seg> <p> An early Heian poet, one of the "Six Immortals of Poetry," The
explanation of the "Wretched that I am" poem was traditional.</p></note>

<note id="n73.15"><seg type="note-symbol">15.</seg> <p> From poem no. 757 in the <hi rend="italic">Kokinsh&umacr;</hi>, by
Komachi.
</p></note>

<note id="n73.16"><seg type="note-symbol">16.</seg> <p> A poem by Abe no Kiyoyuki, no. 556 in the <hi rend="italic">Kokinsh&umacr;</hi>.
</p></note>

<note id="n73.17"><seg type="note-symbol">17.</seg> <p> The first part of a poem by Komachi, no. 552 in the <hi rend="italic">Kokinsh&umacr;</hi>. The last two lines run: "If I had
known it was a dream/ I should never have wakened."
</p></note>

<note id="n73.18"><seg type="note-symbol">18.</seg> <p> These lines are based on verses by Po Ch&uuml;-i, no. 291 in the <hi rend="italic">Wakan R&omacr;ei Sh&umacr;</hi>.
</p></note>

<note id="n73.19"><seg type="note-symbol">19.</seg> <p> A poem by Komachi, no. 850 in the <hi rend="italic">Shinkokinsh&umacr;</hi>.
</p></note>

<note id="n74.20"><seg type="note-symbol">20.</seg> <p> This description is based on a passage in the <hi rend="italic">Tamatsukuri Komachi Sosuisho</hi>, a work in Chinese,
apparently by a Buddhist priest of the Heian period, describing Komachi's
decline and her eventual salvation.
</p></note>

<note id="n74.21"><seg type="note-symbol">21.</seg> <p> The appraisal of Komachi's poetry given in the preface to the <hi rend="italic">Kokinsh&umacr;</hi>.
</p></note>

<note id="n76.22"><seg type="note-symbol">22.</seg> <p>The name of a gagaku dance, <hi rend="italic">Manzairaku</hi>.
</p></note>

<note id="n76.23"><seg type="note-symbol">23.</seg> <p> A reference to a poem by Oe no Masafusa in the collection <hi rend="italic">Horikawa-in
Ontoki Hyakushu Waka</hi>: "This world where I
have dwelt a hundred years lodged in a flower is the dream of a
butterfly." The poem in turn refers to a famous passage in Chuang Tzu.
See <hi rend="italic">The Complete Works of Chuang Tzu</hi> (New York,
1968), translated by Burton Watson, p. 49.
</p></note>

<note id="n76.24"><seg type="note-symbol">24.</seg> <p> Hazukashi, the name of a wood near Kyoto, also has the meaning
"ashamed."
</p></note>

</div1>
</back>
</text>
</TEI.2>

