<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="LutNobi"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="LutNobi"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">An Open Letter to the Christian Nobility / by Martin Luther</title>
<title type="sort">open letter to the christian nobility by martin luther</title>
<author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546</author>
<editor>Jacobs, C.M.</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Translator</resp> 
<name/> 
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Marsha Mundinger, Project Wittenberg www.inclnet.org/pub/resources/text/wittenberg/wittenberg-luther.html</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">275</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">LutNobi</idno> 
<date value="2001">2001</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2001 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476168</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>Works of Martin Luter: With Introductions and Notes, Vol. II</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Works of Martin Luter: With Introductions and Notes, Vol. II</title>
<title type="sort">works of martin luter with introductions and notes, vol ii</title>
<author>Martin Luther</author>
<editor>C.M. Jacobs</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Translator</resp> 
<name/>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>476 pp.</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>A.J. Holman Company</publisher> 
<pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace> 
<date value="1915">1915</date> 
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: ALDERMAN LIBRARY UVa:  BR330E.5 1930 v.2</idno>
</publicationStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1520">1520</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language> 
<language id="lat">Latin</language> 
<language id="ger">German</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term> 
<term>religion</term>
</keywords> 
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term> 
<term>prose</term> 
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2002-05">May 2002</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Irene Oh, The Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt> 
<item/>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
 
 
 
 
 
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> 
 
<div2 type="letter" id="d4"> 
<head>AN OPEN LETTER TO THE CHRISTIAN NOBILITY <lb/> 
OF THE GERMAN NATION <lb/> 
CONCERNING <lb/> 
THE REFORM OF THE CHRISTIAN ESTATE <lb/> 
<date value="1520">1520<lb/></date></head> 
 
<salute> 
To the Esteemed and Reverend Master <lb/> 
NICHOLAS VON AMSDORF <lb/> 
Licentiate Of holy Scripture and Canon at Wittenberg, <lb/> 
my special and kind friend; <lb/> 
Doctor Martin Luther. 
</salute> 
 
<p>The grace and peace of God be with thee, esteemed and reverend dear sir 
and friend.</p> 
<p> 
 
The time to keep silence has passed and the time to (Eccl 3:7) speak is 
come, as saith Ecclesiastes. I have followed out intention 
<ref target="n1">[1]</ref> 
 and brought 
together some matters touching the reform of the Christian Estate, to be 
laid before the Christian Nobility of the German Nation, in the hope that 
may deign to help His Church through the efforts of the laity, since the 
clergy, to whom this task more properly belongs, have grown quite 
indifferent. I am sending the whole thing to your Reverence, that you may 
pass judgment on it and, if necessary, improve it. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
I know full well that I shall not escape the charge of presumption in 
that I, a despised monk, venture to address such high and great Estates on 
matters of such moment, and to give advice to people of such high 
intelligence. I shall offer no apologies, no matter who may chide me. 
Perchance I owe my God and the world another pie of folly, and I have now 
made up my mind honestly to pay that debt, if I can do so, and for once to 
become court jester; if I fail, I still have one advantage, -- no one need 
buy me a cap or cut me my comb. 
<ref target="n2">[2]</ref> 
 It is a question which one will put the 
bells on the other. 
<ref target="n3">[3]</ref> 
 I must fulfill the proverb, "Whatever the world does, 
a monk must be it, even if he has to be painted in." 
<ref target="n4">[4]</ref> 
 More than once a 
fool has spoken wisely, and wise men often have been arrant (1 Cor 3:18) 
fools, as Paul says, "If any one will be wise, let him become a fool." 
Moreover since I am not only a fool, but also a sworn doctor of Holy 
Scripture, I am glad for the chant to fulfill my doctor's oath in this 
fool's way. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
I pray you, make my excuses to the moderately intelligent, for I know not 
how to earn the grace and favor of the immoderately intelligent, though I 
have often sought to do with great pains. Henceforth I neither desire nor 
regard their favor. God help us to seek not our own glory, but His alone! 
Amen. 
 
</p> 
 
<closer> 
<name type="place"> 
Wittenberg, in the house of the Augustinians, <lb/> 
on the Eve of St.John the Baptist 
</name> 
<date value="1520-06-23">(June 23rd), in the year fifteen hundred and twenty.</date> 
</closer> 
 
</div2> 
 
<div2 type="notes" id="d5"> 
 
<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">[1]</seg> <p><foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Unserm furnchmen 
nach</hi></foreign>. See Introduction, p.57. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n2"><seg type="note-symbol">[2]</seg> <p>An ironical comparison of the monks' cowl and tonsure 
with the headgear of the jester. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n3"><seg type="note-symbol">[3]</seg> <p>i.e., Which one turns out to be the real fool. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n4"><seg type="note-symbol">[4]</seg> <p>The proverb ran, <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">Monachus semper 
praesens</hi></foreign>, "a monk is always 
there." See WANDER, <foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Deutsches 
Sprichworterlexicon,</hi></foreign> under Monch, No. 
130. 
</p></note> 
 
</div2> 
 
<div2 type="section" id="d6"> 
<head> 
 
To <lb/> 
His Most Illustrious and Mighty Imperial Majesty, <lb/> 
and to <lb/> 
the Christian Nobility of the German Nation, <lb/> 
Doctor Martin Luther. 
 
</head> 
 
<div3 type="part" n="0" id="d7"> 
 
 
<p> 
 
Grace and power from God, Most Illustrious Majesty, and most gracious and 
dear Lords. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
It is not out of sheer forwardness or rashness that I, a single, poor 
man, have undertaken to address your worships. The distress and 
oppression which weigh down all the Estates of Christendom, especially 
of Germany, and which move not me alone, but everyone to cry out time 
and again, and to pray for help, <ref target="n5">[5]</ref> 
 have forced me even now to cry aloud that God may inspire some one with 
His Spirit to lend this suffering nation a helping hand. Oft times the 
councils <ref target="n6">[6]</ref> made some presence at reformation, 
but their attempts have been cleverly hindered by the guile of certain 
men and things have gone from bad to worse. I now intend, by the help of 
God, to throw some light upon the wiles and wickedness of these men, to 
the end that when they are known, they may not henceforth be so hurtful 
and so great a hindrance.  God has given us a noble youth to be our head 
and thereby has awakened great hopes of good in many hearts; <ref 
target="n7">[7]</ref> 
 wherefore it is meet that we should do our part and 
profitably use this time of grace. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
In this whole matter the first and most important thing is that we take 
earnest heed not to enter on it trusting great might or in human reason, 
even though all power in the world were ours; for God cannot and will not 
suffer a good work to be begun with trust in our own power or reason. Such 
works He crushes ruthlessly to earth, as it (Ps. 33:16) is written in the 
xxiii Psalm, "There is no king saved by the multitude of an host: a mighty 
man is not delivered by much strength." On this account, I fear, it came to 
pass of old that the good Emperors Frederick I 
<ref target="n8">[8]</ref> 
 and II 
<ref target="n9">[9]</ref> 
 and many other 
German emperors were shamefully oppressed and trodden under foot by the 
popes, although all the world feared them. It may be that they relied on own 
might more than on God, and therefore they had to fall. In our own times, 
too, what was it that raised the bloodthirsty Julius II 
<ref target="n10">[10]</ref> 
 to such heights? 
Nothing else, I fear, except that France, the Germans and Venice relied 
(Judges 20:21) upon themselves. The children of Benjamin slew 42,000 
Israelites 
<ref target="n11">[11]</ref> 
 because the latter relied on their own strength. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
That it may not so fare with us and our noble young Emperor Charles, we 
must be sure that in this matter are dealing not with men, but with the 
princes of hell, who can fill the world with war and bloodshed, but whom war 
and bloodshed do not overcome. We must go at this work despairing of 
physical force and humbly trusting God; we must seek God's help with earnest 
prayer, and fix our minds on nothing else than the misery and distress of 
suffering Christendom, without regard to the deserts of evil men. Otherwise 
we may start the game with great prospect of success, but when we get well 
into it the evil spirits will stir up such confusion that the whole world 
will swim in blood, and yet nothing will come of it. Let us act wisely, 
therefore, and in the fear of God. The more force we use, the greater our 
disaster if we do not act humbly and in God's fear. The popes and the Romans 
have hitherto been able, by the devil's help, to set kings at odds with one 
another, and they may well be able to do it again, if we proceed by our own 
might and cunning, without God's help. 
</p> 
 
</div3> 
 
<div3 type="notes" id="d8"> 
 
<note id="n5"><seg type="note-symbol">[5]</seg> <p>Evidently a reference to the Gravamina of the German Nation; See 
GEBHARDT, <foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Die Grav. Der Deutschen 
Nation</hi></foreign>, Breslau, 1895. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n6"><seg type="note-symbol">[6]</seg> <p>Councils of the Church, especially those of Constance (1414-18), and 
of Basel (1431-39). 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n7"><seg type="note-symbol">[7]</seg> <p>Charles V. was elected Emperor in 1519, when but twenty years of age. 
Hutten expresses his "hopes of good" from Charles in Vadiscus (BOCKING, IV, 
156). 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n8"><seg type="note-symbol">[8]</seg> <p>Frederick Barbarossa (1152-1190). 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n9"><seg type="note-symbol">[9]</seg> <p>Frederick II (1212-1250), grandson of Barbarossa and last of the 
great Hobenstaufen Emperors. He died under excommunication. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n10"><seg type="note-symbol">[10]</seg> <p>Pope Julius II (1503-1513). Notorious among the popes for his 
unscrupulous pursuit of political power, he was continually involved in war 
with one and another of the European powers over the possession of 
territories in Italy. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n11"><seg type="note-symbol">[11]</seg> <p>Luther's recollection of the figures was 
faulty. 
</p></note> 
</div3> 
 
<div3 type="part" n="1" id="d9"> 
 
<head>I. THE THREE WALLS OF THE ROMANISTS</head> 
 
<p> 
 
The Romanists <ref target="n12">[12]</ref>, with great adroitness, 
have built three walls about them, behind which they have hitherto 
defended themselves in such wise that no one has been able to reform 
them; and this has been the cause of terrible corruption throughout all 
Christendom. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
First, when pressed by The temporal power, they have made decrees and 
said that the temporal power has no jurisdiction over them, but, on the 
other hand, that the spiritual is above the temporal power. Second, when the 
attempt is made to reprove them out of the Scriptures, they raise the 
objection that the interpretation of the Scriptures belongs to no one except 
the pope. Third, if threatened with a council, they answer with the fable 
that no one can call a council but the pope. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
In this wise they have slyly stolen from us our three rods 
<ref target="n13">[13]</ref>, that they 
may go unpunished, and have ensconced themselves within the safe stronghold 
of these three walls, that they may practice all the knavery and wickedness 
which we now see. Even when they have been compelled to hold a council they 
have weakened its power in advance by previously binding the princes with an 
oath to let them remain as they are. Moreover, they have given the pope full 
authority over all the decisions of the council, so that it is all one 
whether there are many councils or no councils, -- except that they deceive 
us with puppet-shows and sham-battles. So terribly do they fear for their 
skin in a really free council! And they have intimidated kings and princes 
by making them believe it would be an offense against God not to obey them 
in all these knavish, crafty deceptions. 
<ref target="n14">[14]</ref> 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Josh. 6:20 Now God help us, and give us one of the trumpets with which 
the walls of Jericho were overthrown, that we may blow down these walls of 
straw and paper, and may set free the Christian rods for the punishment of 
sin, bringing to light the craft and deceit of the devil, to the end that 
through punishment we may reform ourselves, and once more attain God's 
favor. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Against the first wall we will direct our first attack. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
It is pure invention that pope, bishops, priests and monks are to be 
called the "spiritual estate"; princes, lords, artisans, and farmers the 
"temporal estate." That is indeed a fine bit of lying and hypocrisy. Yet no 
one should be frightened by it; and for this reason -- viz., that all 
Christians are truly of the "spiritual estate," and there is among them no 
difference at all but that of office, as Paul says in I Corinthians 12:12, 
We are all one body, yet every member has its own work, where by it serves 
every other, all because we have one baptism, one Gospel, one faith, and are 
all alike Christians; for baptism, Gospel and faith alone make us 
"spiritual" and a Christian people. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
But that a pope or a bishop anoints, confers tonsures; ordains, 
consecrates, or prescribes dress unlike that of the laity, this may make 
hypocrites and graven images, 
<ref target="n15">[15]</ref> 
 but it never makes a Christian or 
"spiritual" man. Through baptism all of us are consecrated to the 
priesthood, as St. Peter says in I Peter 2:9, "Ye are a royal priesthood, a 
priestly kingdom," and the book of Revelation says, Rev. 5:10 "Thou hast 
made us by Thy blood to be priests and kings." For if we had no higher 
consecration than pope or bishop gives, the consecration by pope or bishop 
would never make a priest, nor might anyone either say mass or preach a 
sermon or give absolution. Therefore when the bishop consecrates it is the 
same thing as if he, in the place and stead of the whole congregation, all 
of whom have like power, were to take one out of their number and charge him 
to use this power for the others; just as though ten brothers, all king's 
sons and equal heirs, were to choose one of themselves to rule the 
inheritance for them all, -- they would all be kings and equal in power, 
though one of them would be charged with the duty of ruling. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
To make it still clearer. If a little group of pious Christian laymen 
were taken captive and set down in a wilderness , and had among them no 
priest consecrated by a bishop, and if there in the wilderness they were to 
agree in choosing one of themselves, married or unmarried, and were to 
charge him with the office of baptizing, saying mass, absolving and 
preaching, such a man would be as truly a priest as though all bishops and 
popes had consecrated him. That is why in cases of necessity any one can 
baptize and give absolution, 
<ref target="n16">[16]</ref> 
 which would be impossible unless we were all 
priests. This great grace and power of baptism and of the Christian Estate 
they have well-nigh destroyed and caused us to forget through The canon 
law. 
<ref target="n17">[17]</ref> 
 It was in the manner aforesaid that Christians in olden days chose 
from their number bishops and priests, who were afterwards confirmed by 
other bishops, without all the show which now obtains. It was Thus that Sts. 
Augustine, 
<ref target="n18">[18]</ref> 
 Ambrose 
<ref target="n19">[19]</ref> 
 and Cyprian 
<ref target="n20">[20]</ref> 
 became bishops. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Since, then, the temporal authorities are baptized with the same baptism 
and have the same faith and Gospel as we, we must grant that they are 
priests and bishops, and count their office one which has a proper and a 
useful place in the Christian community. For whoever comes out the water of 
baptism 
<ref target="n21">[21]</ref> 
 can boast that he is already consecrated priest, bishop and 
pope, though it is not seemly that every one should exercise the office. 
Nay, just because we are all in like manner priests, no one must put himself 
forward and undertake, without our consent and election, to do what is in 
the power of all of us. For what is common to all, no one dare take upon 
himself without the will and the command of the community; and should it 
happen that one chosen for such an office were deposed for malfeasance, he 
would then be just what he was before he held office. Therefore a priest in 
Christendom is nothing else than an office-holder. While he is in office, he 
has precedence; when deposed, he is a peasant or a townsman like the rest. 
Beyond all doubt, then, a priest is no longer a priest when he is deposed. 
But now they have invented <hi rend="italic">characteres</hi> <foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">indelebiles</hi></foreign>, 
<ref target="n22">[22]</ref> and prate that a 
deposed priest is nevertheless something different from a mere layman. They 
even dream that a priest can never become a layman, or be anything else than 
a priest. All this is mere talk and man-made law. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
From all this it follows that there is really no difference between 
laymen and priests, princes and bishops, "spirituals" and "temporals," as 
they call them, except that of office and work, but not of "estate"; for 
they are all of the same estate, 
<ref target="n23">[23]</ref> 
 -- true priests, bishops and popes, -- 
though they are not all engaged in the same work, just as all priests and 
monks have not the same work. This is the teaching of St. Paul in Romans 
12:4 and I Corinthians 12:12, and of St. Peter in I Peter 2:9, as I have 
said above, viz., that we are all one body of Christ, the Head, all members 
one of another. Christ has not two different bodies, one "temporal ," the 
other "spiritual." He is one Head, and He has One body. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Therefore, just as Those who are now called "spiritual" -- priests, 
bishops or popes -- are neither different from other Christians nor superior 
to them, except that they are charged with the administration of the Word of 
God and the sacraments, which is their work and office, so it is with the 
temporal authorities, -- they bear sword and rod with which to punish the 
evil and to protect die good. A cobbler, a smith, a farmer, each has the 
work and office of his trade, and yet they are all alike consecrated priests 
and bishops, and every one by means of his own work or office must benefit 
and serve every other, that in this way many kinds of work may be done for 
the bodily and spiritual welfare of the community, even as all the members 
of the body serve one another. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
See, now, how Christian is the decree which says that the temporal power 
is not above the "spiritual estate" and may not punish it. 
<ref target="n24">[24]</ref> 
That is as much as to say that the hand shall lend no aid when the eye is 
suffering. Is 
it not unnatural, not to say unchristian, that one member should not help 
another and prevent its destruction? Verily, the more honorable the member, 
the more should the others help. I say then, since the temporal power is 
ordained of God to punish evil-doers and to protect them that do well, it 
should therefore be left free to perform it office without hindrance through 
the whole body of Christendom without respect of persons, whether it affect 
pope, bishops, priests, monks, nuns or anybody else. For if the mere fact 
that the temporal power has a smaller place among The Christian offices than 
has the office of preachers or confessors, or of the clergy, then the 
tailors, cobblers, masons, carpenters, pot-boys, tapsters, farmers, and all 
the secular tradesmen, should also be prevented from providing pope, 
bishops, priests and monks with shoes, clothing, houses, meat and drink, and 
from paying them tribute. But if these laymen are allowed to do their work 
unhindered, what do the Roman scribes mean by their laws, with which they 
withdraw themselves from the jurisdiction of the temporal Christian power, 
only so that the may be free to do evil and to fulfill what St. Peter has 
said: 2. Peter 2:1 "There shall be false teachers among you, and through 
covetousness shall they with feigned words make merchandise of you." 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
On this account the Christian temporal power should exercise its office 
without let or hindrance, regardless whether it be pope, bishop or priest 
whom it affects; whoever is guilty, let him suffer. All that the canon law 
has said to the contrary is sheer invention of Roman presumption. For Thus 
saith St. Paul to all Christians: Roman 13:1, 4 "Let every soul (I take that 
to mean the pope's soul also) be subject unto the higher powers; for they 
bear not the sword in vain, but are the ministers of God for the punishment 
of evildoers, and for the praise of them that do well." St. Peter also says: 
1 Peter 2:13, 15 "Submit yourselves unto every ordinance of man for the 
Lord's sake, for so is the will of God" He has also prophesied that such men 
shall come as will despise the temporal authorities; and this has come to 
pass through the canon law. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
So then, I think this first paper-wall is overthrown, since the temporal 
power has become a member of the body of Christendom, and is of the 
"spiritual estate," though its work is of a temporal nature. Therefore its 
work should extend freely and without hindrance to all the members of the 
whole body; it should punish and use force whenever guilt deserves or 
necessity demands, without regard to pope, bishops and priests,-let them 
hail threats and bans as much as they will. 
 
</p> 
<p>This is why guilty priests, if they are surrendered to the temporal 
law<ref target="n25">[25]</ref>, are first deprived of their priestly 
dignities, which would not be right unless the temporal sword had 
previously had authority over them by divine right. 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Again, it is intolerable that in the canon law so much importance is 
attached to the freedom, life and property of the clergy, as though the 
laity were not also as spiritual as good Christians as they, or did not 
belong to the Church. Why are your life and limb, your property and honor so 
free, and mine not? We are all alike Christians, and have baptism, faith, 
Spirit and all things alike. If a priest is killed, the land is laid under 
interdict, 
<ref target="n26">[26]</ref> 
 -- why not when a peasant is killed? Whence comes this great 
distinction between those who are equally Christians? Only from human laws 
and inventions! 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Moreover, it can be no good spirit who has invented such exceptions and 
granted to sin such license and impunity. For if we are bound to strive 
against the works and words of the evil spirit, and to drive him out in 
whatever way we can, as Christ commands and His Apostles, ought we, then to 
suffer it in silence when the pope or his satellites are bent on devilish 
words and works? Ought we for the sake of men to allow the suppression of 
divine commandments and truths which we have sworn in baptism to support 
with life and limb? Of a truth we should then have to answer all the souls 
that would thereby be abandoned and it astray. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
It must therefore have been the very prince of devils who said what is 
written in the canon law: "If the pope were so scandalously bad as to lead 
souls in crowds to the devil, yet he could not be deposed." 
<ref target="n27">[27]</ref> 
 On this 
accursed and devilish foundation they build at Rome, and think that we 
should let all the world go to the devil, rather than resist their knavery. 
If the fact that one man is set over others were sufficient reason why he 
should escape punishment, then no Christian could punish another, since 
Christ commands that every man shall esteem himself the lowliest and the 
least. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Where sin is, there is no escape from punishment; as St. Gregory 
<ref target="n28">[28]</ref> 
 also 
writes that we are indeed all equal, but guilt puts us in subjection one to 
another. Now we see how they whom God and the Apostles have made subject to 
the temporal sword deal with Christendom, depriving it of its liberty by 
their own wickedness, without warrant of Scripture. It is to be feared that 
this is a game of Antichrist 
<ref target="n29">[29]</ref> 
 or a sign that he is close at hand. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
The second wall 
<ref target="n30">[30]</ref> 
 is still more flimsy and worthless. They wish to be 
the only Masters of The Holy Scriptures, 
<ref target="n31">[31]</ref> 
 even though in all their lives 
they learn nothing from them. They assume for themselves sole authority, and 
with insolent juggling of words they would persuade us that the pope, 
whether he be a bad man or a good man, cannot err in matters of faith, 
<ref target="n32">[32]</ref> 
 
and yet they cannot prove a single letter of it. Hence it comes that so many 
heretical and unchristian, nay, even unnatural ordinances have a place in 
the canon law, of which, however, there is no present need to speak. For 
since they think that the Holy Spirit never leaves them, be they never so 
unlearned and wicked, they make bold to decree whatever they will. And if it 
were true, where would be the need or use of Holy Scriptures? Let us burn 
them, and be satisfied with the unlearned lords at Rome, who are possessed 
of the Holy Spirit, -- although He can possess only pious hearts! Unless I 
had read it myself, 
<ref target="n33">[33]</ref> 
 I could not have believed that the devil would make 
such clumsy pretensions at Rome, and find a following. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
But not to fight them with mere words, we will quote the Scriptures. St. 
Paul says in I Corinthians 14:30: "If to anyone something better is 
revealed, though he be sitting and listening to another in God's Word, then 
the first, who is speaking, shall hold his peace and give place." What would 
be the use of this commandment, if we were only to believe him who does the 
talking or who has the highest seat? Christ also says in John 6:45, that all 
Christians shall be taught of God. Thus it may well happen that the pope and 
his followers are wicked men, and no true Christians, not taught of God, not 
having true understanding. On the other hand, an ordinary man may have true 
understanding; why then should we not follow him? Has not the pope erred 
many times? Who would help Christendom when the pope errs, if we were not to 
believe another, who had the Scriptures on his side, more than the pope? 
 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Therefore it is a wickedly invented fable, and they cannot produce a 
letter in defense of it, that the interpretation of Scripture or the 
confirmation of its interpretation belongs to the pope alone. They have 
themselves usurped this power; and although they allege that this power was 
given to Peter when the keys were given to him, it is plain enough that the 
keys were not given to Peter alone, but to the whole community. 
<ref target="n34">[34]</ref> 
 
Moreover, the keys were not ordained for doctrine or government, but only 
for the binding and loosing of they arrogate to themselves is mere invention 
But Christ's word to Peter, Luke 22:32 "I have prayed for thee that thy 
faith fall not," cannot be applied to the pope, since the majority of the 
popes have been without faith, as they must themselves confess. Besides, it 
is not only for Peter that Christ prayed, but also for all Apostles and 
Christians, as he says in John 17:9, 20: "Father, I pray for those whom Thou 
hast given Me, and not for these only, but for all who believe on Me through 
their word." Is not this clear enough? 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Only think of it yourself! They must confess that there are pious 
Christians among us, who have the true faith, Spirit, understanding, word 
and mind of Christ. Why, then, should we reject their word and understanding 
and follow the pope, who has neither faith nor Spirit? That would be to deny 
the whole faith and the Christian Church. Moreover, it is not the pope alone 
who is always in the right, if the article of The Creed is correct: "I 
believe one holy Christian Church"; otherwise the prayer must run: "I 
believe in the pope at Rome," and so reduce the Christian Church to one man, 
-- which would be nothing else than a devilish and hellish error. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Besides, if we are all priests, as was said above, 
<ref target="n35">[35]</ref> 
 and all have one 
faith, one Gospel, one sacrament, why should we not also have the power to 
test and judge what is correct or incorrect in matters of faith? What 
becomes of the words of Paul in I Corinthians 2:15: "He that is spiritual 
judgeth all things, yet he himself is judged of no man," II Corinthians 
4:13: "We have all the same Spirit of faith"? Why, then, should not we 
perceive what squares with faith and what does not, as well as does an 
unbelieving pope? 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
All these and many other texts should make us bold and free, and we 
should not allow the Spirit of liberty, as Paul calls Him, to be frightened 
off by the fabrications of the popes, but we ought to go boldly forward to 
test all that they do or leave undone, according to our interpretation of 
the Scriptures, which rests on faith, and compel them to follow not their 
own interpretation, but the one that is better. In the olden days Abraham 
had to listen to Sarah, although she was in more complete subjection to him 
than we are to anyone on earth. Balaam's ass, also, was wiser than the 
prophet himself. If God then spoke an ass against a prophet, why should He 
not be able even now to speak by a righteous man against the pope? In like 
manner St. Paul rebukes St. Peter as a man in error. Therefore it behooves 
every Christian to espouse the cause of the faith, to understand and defend 
it, and to rebuke errors. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
The third wall falls of itself when the first two are down. For when the 
pope acts contrary to the Scriptures, it is our duty to stand by the 
Scriptures, to reprove him, and to constrain him, according to the word of 
Christ in Matthew 18:15: "If thy brother sin against thee, go and tell it 
him between thee and him alone; if he hear thee not, then take with thee one 
or two more; if he hear them not, tell it to the Church; if he hear not the 
Church, consider him a heathen." Here every member is commanded to care for 
every other. How much rather should we do this when the member that does 
evil is a ruling member, and by his evil-doing is the cause of much harm and 
offense to the rest! But if I am to accuse him before the Church, I must 
bring the Church together. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
They have no basis in Scripture for their contention that it belongs to 
the pope alone to call a council or confirm its actions; 
<ref target="n36">[36]</ref> 
 for this is 
based merely upon their own laws, which are valid only in so far as they are 
not injurious to Christendom or contrary to the laws of God. When the pope 
deserves punishment, such laws go out of force, since it is injurious to 
Christendom not to punish him by means of a council. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Thus we read in Acts 15:6 that it was not St. Peter who called the 
Apostolic Council, but the Apostles and elders. If, then, that right had 
belonged to St. Peter alone, the council would not have been a Christian 
council, but an heretical<foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">conciliabulum</hi></foreign>. 
<ref target="n37">[37]</ref> 
 Even the Council of Nicaea -- 
the most famous of all-was neither called nor confirmed by the Bishop of 
Rome, but by the Emperor Constantine, 
<ref target="n38">[38]</ref> 
 and many other emperors after him 
did the like, yet these councils were the most Christian of all. 
<ref target="n39">[39]</ref> 
 But if 
the pope alone had the right to call councils, then all then all councils 
must have been heretical. Moreover, if I consider the councils which the 
pope has created, I find that they have done nothing of special importance. 
 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Therefore, when necessity demands, and the pope is an offense to 
Christendom, the first man who is able should, a faithful member of the 
whole body, do what he can to bring about a truly free council. 
<ref target="n40">[40]</ref> 
 No one 
can do this so well as the temporal authorities, especially since now they 
also are fellow-Christians, fellow-priests, "fellow-spirituals," 
<ref target="n41">[41]</ref> 
 
fellow-lords over all things, and whenever it is needful or profitable, they 
should give free course to office and work in which God has put them above 
every man. Would it not be an unnatural thing, if a fire broke out in a 
city, and everybody were to stand by and it burn on and on and consume 
everything that could burn, for the sole reason that nobody had the 
authority of the burgomaster, or because, perhaps, the fire broke in the 
burgomaster's house? In such case is it not the duty of every citizen to 
arouse and call the rest? How much more should this be done in the spiritual 
city of Christ, if a fire of offense breaks out, whether in the papal 
government, or anywhere else? In the same way, if the enemy attacks a city, 
he who first rouses the others deserves honor and thanks; why then should he 
not deserve honor who makes known the presence of the enemy from hell, 
awakens the Christians, and calls them together? 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
But all their boasts of an authority which dare not opposed amount to 
nothing after all. No one in Christendom has authority to do injury, or to 
forbid the resisting of injury. There is no authority in the Church save 
edification. Therefore, if the pope were to use his authority to prevent the 
calling of a free council, and thus became a hindrance to the edification of 
the Church, we should have regard neither for him nor for his authority; and 
if he were to hurl his bans and thunderbolts, we should despise his conduct 
as that of a madman, and relying on God, hurl back the ban on him, and 
coerce him as best we could. For this presumptuous authority of his is 
nothing; he has no such authority, and he is quickly overthrown by a text of 
Scripture; for Paul says to the Corinthians, II Corinthians 10:8 "God has 
given us authority not for the destruction, but for the edification of 
Christendom." Who is ready to overleap this text? It is only the power of 
the devil and of Antichrist which resists the things that serve for the 
edification of Christendom; it is, therefore, in no wise to be obeyed, but 
is to be opposed with life and goods and all our strength. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Even though a miracle were to be done in the pope's behalf against the 
temporal powers, or though someone were to be stricken with a plague -- 
which they boast has sometimes happened -- it should be considered only the 
work of the devil, because of the weakness of our faith in God. Christ 
Himself prophesied in Matthew 24:24: "There shall come in My Name false 
Christs and false prophets, and do signs and wonders, so as to deceive even 
the elect," and Paul says in II Thessalonians 2:9, that Antichrist shall, 
through the power of Satan, be mighty in lying wonders. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Let us, therefore, hold fast to this: No Christian authority can do 
anything against Christ; as St. Paul says, II Corinthians 13:8: "We can do 
nothing against Christ, but for Christ." Whatever does aught against Christ 
is the power of Antichrist and of the devil, even though it were to rain and 
hail wonders and plagues. Wonders and plagues prove nothing, especially in 
these last evil times, for which all the Scriptures prophesy false wonders. 
Therefore we must cling with firm faith to the words of God, and then the 
devil will cease from wonders. 
 
</p> 
<p>Thus I hope that the false, lying terror with which the Romans have this 
long time made our conscience timid and stupid, has been allayed. They, like 
all of us, are subject to the temporal sword; they have no power to 
interpret the Scriptures by mere authority, without learning; they have no 
authority to prevent a council or, in sheer wantonness, to pledge it, bind 
it, or take away its liberty; but if they do this, they are in truth the 
communion of Antichrist and of the devil, and have nothing at all of Christ 
except the name. 
</p></div3> 
 
<div3 type="notes" id="d10"> 
 
 
<note id="n12"><seg type="note-symbol">[12]</seg> <p>The term "Romanist" is applied by Luther to the 
champions of the extreme form of papal supremacy, Cf. Vol. I, p. 343 f. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n13"><seg type="note-symbol">[13]</seg> <p>i.e., The three rods for the punishment of an evil 
pope. Vol. II, -- 5. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n14"><seg type="note-symbol">[14]</seg> <p><foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Spuknisse</hi></foreign>, 
literally "ghosts."  The gist of the sentence is, "the Romanists have 
frightened the world with ghost-stories." </p></note> 
 
<note id="n15"><seg type="note-symbol">[15]</seg> <p><foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Oelgotze</hi></foreign> - 
"an image anointed with holy oil to make it sacred"; in modern German, 
"a blockhead." </p></note> 
 
<note id="n16"><seg type="note-symbol">[16]</seg> <p>Lay-baptism in view of imminent death is a practice 
as old as the Christian Church. The right of the laity to administer 
baptism in such cases was expressly recognized by the Council of Elvira, 
in the year 306, and the decree of that Council became a part of the law 
of the Church. The right of the laity to give absolution in such cases 
rests on the principle that in the absence of the appointed official of 
the Church any Christian can do for any other Christian the things that 
are absolutely necessary for salvation, for "necessity knows no law." 
Cf. Vol. I, p. 30, note 2. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n17"><seg type="note-symbol">[17]</seg> <p>The canon law, called by Luther throughout this 
treatise and elsewhere, the "spiritual law," is a general name for the 
decrees of councils ("cannons" in the strict sense) and decisions of the 
popes ("decretals," "constitutions," etc.), promulgated by authority of 
the popes, and collected in the so-called <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">Corpus 
juriscanonici</hi></foreign>. It comprised the whole body of Church law, 
and embodied in legal forms the medieval theory of papal absolutism, 
which accounts for the bitterness with which Luther speaks of it, 
especially in this treatise. The <hi rend="italic">Corpus</hi> includes the following 
collections of cannons and decretals: The <hi rend="italic">Decretum of Gratian</hi> 
(1142), the <hi rend="italic">Liber Extra</hi> (1234), the <hi rend="italic">Liber Sextus</hi> 
(1298), the <hi rend="italic">Constitutiones Clementinae</hi> (1318 or 1317), and the 
two books of Extravagantes, -- the <hi rend="italic">Extravagantes of John XXIV</hi>, 
and the <hi rend="italic">Extravagantes Communes</hi>. The last pope whose decrees are 
included is Sixths IV (died 1484). See <hi rend="italic">Catholic Encyclo.</hi>, IV, 
pp. 391 ff. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n18"><seg type="note-symbol">[18]</seg> <p>Augustine, the master-theologian of the Ancient 
Church, bishop of Hippo in Africa from 395-430. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n19"><seg type="note-symbol">[19]</seg> <p>Ambrose, bishop of Milan from 374-397, had not yet 
been baptized at the time of his election to the episcopate, which was 
forced upon him by the unanimous voice of the people of the city. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n20"><seg type="note-symbol">[20]</seg> <p>Cyprian, bishop of Carthage, 247-258, is said to 
have consented to accept the office only when the congregation 
surrounded his house and besought him to yield to their entreaties. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n21"><seg type="note-symbol">[21]</seg> <p><foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Was ausz der Tauff krochen 
ist</hi></foreign>. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n22"><seg type="note-symbol">[22]</seg> <p>The <hi rend="italic">character</hi> <foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">indelebilis</hi></foreign>, or "indelible mark," received 
authoritative statement in the bull <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">Exultate 
Deo</hi></foreign> (1439). Eugenius 
IV, summing up the <hi rend="italic">Decrees of the Council of Florence</hi>, says: "Among 
these sacraments there are three -- baptism, confirmation, and orders -- 
which indelibly impress upon the soul a character, i.e., a certain spiritual 
mark which distinguishes them from the rest." (MIRBT, Quellen, 2d ed., No. 
150). The Council of Trent in its XXIII. Session, July 15, 1563. (MIRBT, No. 
312), defined the correct Roman teaching as follows: "Since in the sacrament 
of orders, as in baptism and confirmation, a character is impressed which 
cannot be destroyed or taken away, the Holy Synod justly condemns the 
opinion of those who assert that the priests of the New Testament have only 
temporary power, and that those once rightly ordained can again be made 
laymen, if they do not exercise the ministry of the Word of God." 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n23"><seg type="note-symbol">[23]</seg> <p>i.e., They are all Christians, among whom there can 
be no essential difference. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n24"><seg type="note-symbol">[24]</seg> <p>The sharp distinction which the Roman Church drew 
between clergy and laity found practical application in the contention 
that the clergy should be exempt from the jurisdiction of the civil 
courts, This is the so-called <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">privilegium 
fori</hi></foreign>, "benefit of clergy."  It was further claimed that 
the government of the clergy and the administration of Church property 
must be entirely in the hands of the Church authorities, and that no lay 
rulers might either make or enforce laws which in any way affected the 
Church. See <hi rend="italic">LEA, Studies in Church History</hi>, 169-219 and 
<foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Prot. Realencyk.</hi></foreign>, Vi, 594. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n25"><seg type="note-symbol">[25]</seg> <p>It was the contention of the Church authorities that 
priests charged with infraction of the laws of the state should first be 
tried in the ecclesiastical courts. If found guilty, they were degraded 
from the priesthood and handed over to the state authorities for 
punishment. Formula for degradation in the canon law, c. 2 in VI, de 
poen. (V, 9). See <foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Prot. 
Realencyk.</hi></foreign>, VI, 589. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n26"><seg type="note-symbol">[26]</seg> <p>The interdict is the prohibition of the 
administration of the sacraments and of the other rites of the Church 
within the territory upon which the interdict is laid (<foreign 
lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Realencyk.</hi></foreign>, IX, 208 f.). Its use was not 
uncommon in the Middle Ages, and during the time that the power of the 
popes was at its height it proved an effective means of bringing 
refractory rulers to terms. A famous instance is the interdict laid upon 
the Kingdom of England by Innocent III in 1208. Interdicts of more 
limited local extent were quite frequent. The use of the interdict as 
punishment for trifling infractions of church law was a subject of 
complaint at the diets of Worms (1521) and Nurnberg (1524). See A. 
WREDE, <foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Deutsche Reichstagsaktenn unter Kaiser 
Karl V.</hi></foreign>, II, pp. 685 f, III, 665. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n27"><seg type="note-symbol">[27]</seg> <p>The statement of which Luther here complains is 
found in the <hi rend="italic">Decretum of Gratian</hi>, Dist. XL, c. 6, Si papa. In 
his Epitome (see Introduction, p. 58), Prierias had quoted this canon 
against Luther, as follows: "A Pontifex indubitatus (i.e., a pope who is 
not accused of heresy or schism) cannot lawfully be deposed or judged 
either by a council or by the whole world, even if he is so scandalous 
as to lead people with him by crowds into the possession of hell." 
Luther's comment is: "Be astonished, O heaven; shudder, O earth! Behold, 
O Christians, what Rome is!" (Weimar Ed., VI, 336). </p></note> 
 
<note id="n28"><seg type="note-symbol">[28]</seg> <p>Gregory the Great, pope 590-604. The passage is found in 
<hi rend="italic">MIGEN</hi>, LXXVI, 203; LXXVII, 34. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n29"><seg type="note-symbol">[29]</seg> <p>Antichrist, the incarnation of all that is hostile 
to Christ and His Kingdom. His appearance is prophesied in 2 Thess. 
2:3-10 (the "man of sin, sitting in the temple of God"); 1 John 2:18, 
22:4:3, and Rev. 13. In the early Church the Fathers sometimes thought 
the prophecies fulfilled in the person of some especially pestilent 
heretic. Wyclif applied the term to the pope, -- "the pope would seem to 
be not the vicar of Christ, but the vicar of Antichrist" (see LOOFS, 
<foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Dogmengeschichte</hi></foreign>, 4th ed., p. 
649). </p></note> 
 
<note id="n30"><seg type="note-symbol">[30]</seg> <p>See above, p. 65. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n31"><seg type="note-symbol">[31]</seg> <p>According to academic usage, the holder of a 
Master's degree was authorized to expound the subject named in the 
degree. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n32"><seg type="note-symbol">[32]</seg> <p>The doctrine of papal infallibility was never 
officially sanctioned in the Middle Ages, but the claim of infallibility 
was repeatedly made by the champions of the more extreme view of papal 
power, e.g., Augustinus Triumphus (died 1328) in his <hi rend="italic">Summa de 
potestate Papae</hi>. In his attack upon the XCV Theses (<hi rend="italic">Dialogus de 
potestate Papae</hi>, Dec., 1517) Prierias had asserted, "The supreme 
pontiff (i.e., the pope) cannot err when giving a decision as pontiff, 
i.e., speaking officially (<foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">ex 
officio</hi></foreign>), and doing what in him lies to learn the truth"; 
and again, "Whoever does not rest upon the teaching of the Roman Church 
and the supreme pontiff as an infallible rule of faith, from which even 
Holy Scripture draws its vigor and authority, is a heretic" (Erl. Ed., 
op. Var./ arg., I, 348). In the Epitome he had said: "Even though the 
pope as an individual (<foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">singularis 
persona</hi></foreign>) can do wrong and hold a wrong faith, 
nevertheless as pope he cannot give a wrong decision" (Weimar Ed., VI, 
337). </p></note> 
 
<note id="n33"><seg type="note-symbol">[33]</seg> <p>Most recently in Prierias's <hi rend="italic">Epitome</hi>. See 
preceding note. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n34"><seg type="note-symbol">[34]</seg> <p>Luther had discussed the whole subject of the power 
of the keys in the Latin treatise, <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">Resolutio 
super propositione xiii. de potestate papae</hi></foreign>, of 1519 
(Weimar Ed., II, pp. 185 ff., and in the German treatise <hi rend="italic">The Papacy 
at Rome</hi> (Vol. I, pp. 337-394). </p></note> 
 
<note id="n35"><seg type="note-symbol">[35]</seg> <p>Pp. 66 ff. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n36"><seg type="note-symbol">[36]</seg> <p>Another contention of Prierias. In <date value="1518-11-28">1518 (Nov. 
28th)</date> Luther had appealed his cause from the decision of the 
pope, which he foresaw would be adverse, to the decision of a council to 
be held at some future time. In the <hi rend="italic">Epitome Prierias</hi> discusses 
this appeal, asserting, among other things, that "when there is one 
undisputed pontiff, it belongs to him alone to call a council.", and 
that "the decrees of councils neither bind nor hold <foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">nullum ligant vel astringunt</hi></foreign> unless they 
are confirmed by authority of the Roman pontiff" (Weimar Ed., Vi, 335). 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n37"><seg type="note-symbol">[37]</seg> <p>i.e., A mere gathering of people. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n38"><seg type="note-symbol">[38]</seg> <p>The council of Nicaea, the first of the great 
councils of the Church, assembled in 325 for the settlement of the Arian 
controversy.  Luther's statement that it was called by the Emperor 
Constantine, and that its decisions did not derive their validity from 
any papal confirmation, is historically correct. On Luther's statements 
about this council, see SCHAFER, <foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Luther als 
Kirchenhistoriker</hi></foreign>, pp. 291 ff.; KOHLER, <foreign 
lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Luther und die Kg.</hi></foreign>, pp. 148 ff. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n39"><seg type="note-symbol">[39]</seg> <p>Luther is here referring to the earlier so-called 
"ecumenical" councils. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n40"><seg type="note-symbol">[40]</seg> <p>i.e., A council which will not be subject to the 
pope. Cf. Erl. Ed., xxvi, III</p></note> 
 
<note id="n41"><seg type="note-symbol">[41]</seg> <p>i.e., They belong to the "spiritual estate"; see above, 
p.69. 
</p></note> 
 
</div3> 
 
<div3 type="part" n="2" id="d11"> 
<head>II. ABUSES TO BE DISCUSSED IN COUNCILS</head> 
 
<p>We shall now look at the matters which should be discussed in the 
councils, and with which popes, cardinals, bishops and all the scholars 
ought properly to be occupied day and night if they loved Christ and His 
Church. But if they neglect this duty, then let the laity 
<ref target="n42">[42]</ref> 
 and the 
temporal authorities see to it, regardless of bans and thunders; for an 
unjust ban is better than ten just releases, and an unjust release worse 
than ten just bans. Let us, therefore, awake, dear Germans, and fear God 
rather than men, that we may not share the fate of all the poor souls who 
are so lamentably lost through the shameful and devilish rule of the Romans, 
in which the devil daily takes a larger and larger place, -- if, indeed, it 
were possible that such a hellish rule could grow worse, a thing I can 
neither conceive nor believe.</p> 
 
<list type="ordered"> <item n="1"> 
 
1. It is a horrible and frightful 
thing that the ruler of Christendom, who boasts himself vicar of Christ 
and successor of St. Peter, lives in such worldly splendor that in this 
regard no king nor emperor can equal or approach him, and that he who 
claims the title of "most holy" and "most spiritual" is more worldly 
than the world itself. He wears a triple crown, when the greatest kings 
wear but a single crown; <ref target="n43">[43]</ref> if that is like 
the poverty of Christ and of St. Peter, then it is a new kind of 
likeness. When a word is said against it, they cry out "Heresy!" but 
that is because they do not wish to hear how unchristian and ungodly 
such a practice is. I think, however, that if the pope were with tears 
to pray to God, he would have to lay aside these crowns, for our God can 
suffer no pride; and his office is nothing else than this, -- daily to 
weep and pray for Christendom, and to set an example of all 
humility.<lb/> 
 
However that may be, this splendor of his is an offense, 
and the pope is bound on his soul's salvation to lay it aside, because 
St. Paul says, I Thess. 5:21: "Abstain from all outward shows, which 
give offense," and in Romans 12:17, "We should provide good, not only in 
the sight of God, but also in the sight of all men." An ordinary 
bishop's crown would be enough for the pope; he should be greater than 
others in wisdom and holiness, and leave the crown of pride to 
Antichrist, as did his predecessors several centuries ago. They say he 
is a lord of the world; that is a lie; for Christ, Whose vicar and 
officer he boasts himself to be, said before Pilate, John 17:36, My 
kingdom is not of this world," and no vicar's rule can go beyond his 
lord's. Moreover he is not the vicar of the glorified, but of the 
crucified Christ, as Paul says, I Cor 2:2, "I was willing to know 
nothing among you save Christ, and Him only as the Crucified"; and in 
Philippians 2:5, "So think of yourselves as ye see in Christ, Who 
emptied Himself and took upon Him the appearance of a servant"; and 
again in I Corinthians 1:23, "We preach Christ, the Crucified." Now they 
make the pope a vicar of the glorified Christ in heaven, and some of 
them have allowed the devil to rule them so completely that they have 
maintained that the pope is above the angels in heaven and has authority 
over them. <ref target="n44">[44]</ref> These are indeed the very 
works of the very Antichrist. </item><lb/> 
 
<item n="2"> 
 
2. What is the use in Christendom of those people who are called the 
cardinals? I shall tell you. Italy and Germany have many rich 
monasteries, foundations, benefices, and livings. No better way has been 
discovered to bring all these to Rome than by creating cardinals and 
giving them the bishoprics, monasteries and prelacies, and so 
overthrowing the worship of God. For this reason we now see Italy a very 
wilderness -- monasteries in ruins, bishoprics devoured, the prelacies 
and the revenues of all the churches drawn to Rome, cities decayed, land 
and people laid waste, because there is no more worship or preaching. 
Why? The cardinals must have the income.<ref target="n45">[45]</ref> 
No Turk could have so devastated Italy and suppressed the worship of 
God. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Now that Italy is sucked dry, they come into Germany, 
<ref target="n46">[46]</ref> and begin oh, so 
gently. But let us beware, or Germany will soon become like Italy. Already 
we have some cardinals; what the Romans seek by that the "drunken Germans" 
are not to understand until we have not a bishopric, a monastery, a living, 
a benefice, a heller or a pfennign left. Antichrist must take the treasures 
of the earth, as it was prophesied. So it goes on. They skim the cream off 
the bishoprics, monasteries and benefices, and because they do not yet 
venture to turn them all to shameful use, as they have done in Italy, they 
only practice for the present the sacred trickery of coupling together ten 
or twenty prelacies and taking a yearly portion from each of them, so as to 
make a tidy sum after all. The priory of Wurzburg yields a thousand gulden; 
that of Bamberg something; Mainz, Trier and the others, something more; and 
so from one to ten thousand gulden might be got together, in order that a 
cardinal might live at Rome like a rich king. 
 
<lb/> 
 
"After they are used to this, we will create thirty or forty cardinals in 
a day,<ref target="n47">[47]</ref> 
 and give to one Mount St. Michael at Bamberg 
<ref target="n48">[48]</ref> 
 and the bishopric 
of Wurzburg to boot, hang on to these a few rich livings, until churches and 
cities are waste, and after that we will say, 'We are Christ's vicars and 
shepherds of Christ's sheep; the mad, drunken Germans must put up with it.'" 
 
 
<lb/> 
 
I advise, however, that the number of the cardinals be reduced, or that 
the pope be made to keep them at his own expense. Twelve of them would be 
more than enough, and each of them might have an income of a thousand gulden 
a year. 
<ref target="n49">[49]</ref> 
 How comes it that we Germans must put up with such robbery and 
such extortion of our property, at the hands of the pope? If the Kingdom of 
France has prevented it, 
<ref target="n50">[50]</ref> 
 why do we Germans let them make such fools and 
apes of us? It would all be more bearable if in this way they only stole our 
property; but they lay waste the churches and rob Christ's sheep of their 
pious shepherds, and destroy the worship and the Word of God. Even if there 
were not a single cardinal, the Church would not go under. As it is they do 
nothing for the good of Christendom; they only wrangle about the incomes of 
bishoprics and prelacies, and that any robber could do. 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
 
<item n="3"> 
 
3. If ninety-nine parts of the papal court 
<ref target="n51">[51]</ref> 
 were done away and only the 
hundredth part allowed to remain, it would still be large enough to give 
decisions in matters of faith. Now, however, there is such a swarm of vermin 
yonder in Rome, all boasting that they are "papal," that there was nothing 
like it in Babylon. There are more than three thousand papal secretaries 
alone; who will count the other offices, when they are so many that they 
scarcely can be counted? And they all lie in wait for the prebends and 
benefices of Germany as wolves lie in wait for the sheep. I believe that 
Germany now gives much more to the sheep. I believe that Germany now gives 
much more to the pope at Rome than it gave in former times to the emperors. 
Indeed, some estimate that every year more than three hundred thousand 
gulden find their way from Germany to Rome, quite uselessly and fruitlessly; 
we get nothing for it but scorn and contempt. And yet we wonder that 
princes, nobles, cities, endowments, land and people are impoverished! We 
should rather wonder that we still have anything to eat! 
 
</item> 
</list> 
<lb/> 
 
<p> 
 
Since we here come to the heart of the matter, we will pause a little, 
and let it be seen that the Germans are not quite such gross fools as not to 
note or understand the sharp practices of the Romans. I do not now complain 
that at Rome God's command and Christian law are despised; for such is the 
state of Christendom, and particularly of Rome, that we may not now complain 
of such high matters. Nor do I complain that natural or temporal law and 
reason count for nothing. The case is worse even than that. I complain that 
they do not keep their own self-devised canon law, though it is, to be sure, 
mere tyranny, avarice and temporal splendor, rather than law. Let us see! 
 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
In former times German emperors and princes permitted the pope to receive 
the annates from all the benefices of the German nation, i.e., the half of 
the first year's revenues from each benefice. 
<ref target="n52">[52]</ref> 
 This permission was given, 
however, in order that by means of these large sums of money, the pope might 
accumulate a treasure for fighting against the Turks and infidels in defense 
of Christendom, so that the burden of the war might not rest too heavily 
upon the nobility, but that the clergy also should contribute something 
toward it. This single-hearted devotion of the German nation the popes have 
so used, that they have received this money for more than a hundred years, 
have now made of it a binding tax and tribute, and have not only accumulated 
no treasure, but have used the money to endow many orders and offices at 
Rome, and to provide these offices with salaries, as though the annates were 
a fixed rent. When they pretend that they are about to fight against the 
Turks, they send out emissaries to gather money. Oft-times they issue an 
indulgence on this same pretext of fighting the Turks, 
<ref target="n53">[53]</ref> 
 for they think 
the mad Germans are forever to remain utter and arrant fools, give them 
money without end, and satisfy their unspeakable greed; though we clearly 
see that not a heller of the annates or of the indulgence-money or of all 
the rest, is used against the Turks, but all of it goes into the bottomless 
bag. They lie and deceive, make laws and make agreements with us, and they 
do not intend to keep any of them. All this must be counted the work of 
Christ and St. Peter! Now, in this matter the German nation, bishops and 
princes, should consider that they too are Christians, and should protect 
the people, whom they are set to rule and guard in things temporal and 
spiritual, against these ravening wolves who, in sheep's clothing, pretend 
to be shepherds and rulers; and, since the annates are so shamefully abused 
and the stipulated conditions are not fulfilled, they should not permit 
their land and people to be so sadly robbed and ruined, against all justice; 
but by a law of the emperor or of the whole nation, they should either keep 
the annates at home or else abolish them again. 
<ref target="n54">[54]</ref> 
 For since the Romans do 
not keep the terms of the agreement, they have no right to the annates. 
Therefore the bishops and princes are bound to punish or prevent; such 
thievery and robbery, as the law requires. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
In this they should aid the pope and support him, for he is perchance too 
weak to prevent such an abuse all by himself; or if he were to undertake to 
defend and maintain this practice, they ought resist him and fight against 
him as against a wolf and a tyrant, for he has no authority to do or to 
defend evil. Moreover, if it were ever desired to accumulate such a treasure 
against the Turks, we ought in the future to have sense enough to see that 
the German nation would be a better custodian for it than the pope; for the 
German nation has people enough for the fighting, if only the money is 
forthcoming. It is with the annates as it has been with many another Roman 
pretence. Again, the year has been so divided between the pope and the 
ruling bishops and canons, 
<ref target="n55">[55]</ref> 
 that the pope has six months in the year -- 
every other month -- in which to bestow the benefices which fall vacant in 
his months. 
<ref target="n56">[56]</ref> 
 In this way almost all the benefices are absorbed by Rome, 
especially the very best livings and dignities, 
<ref target="n57">[57]</ref> 
 and when once they fall 
into the hands of Rome, they never come out of them again, though a vacancy 
may never again occur in the pope's month. Thus the canons are cheated. This 
is a genuine robbery, which intends to let nothing escape. Therefore it is 
high time that the "papal months" be altogether abolished, and that 
everything which they have brought to Rome be taken back again. For the 
princes and nobles should take measures that the stolen goods be returned, 
the thieves punished, and those who have abused privilege be deprived of 
privilege. If it is binding and valid when the pope on the day after his 
election makes, in his chancery, rules and laws whereby our foundations and 
livings are robbed, -- a thing which he has no right to do; then it should 
be still more valid if the Emperor Charles on the day after his 
coronation 
<ref target="n58">[58]</ref> 
 were to make rules and laws that not another benefice or 
living in all Germany shall be allowed to come into the hands of Rome by 
means of the "papal months," and that the livings which have already fallen 
into its hands shall be released, and redeemed from the Roman robbers; for 
he has this right by virtue of his office and his sword. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
But now the Roman See of Avarice and Robbery has not been able to await 
the time when all the benefices, one after another, would, by the "papal 
months," come into its power, but hastens, with insatiable appetite, to get 
possession of them all as speedily as possible; and so besides the annates 
and the "months" it has hit upon a device by which benefices and livings 
fall to Rome in three ways: 
 
</p> 
 
<p> 
 
First, If any one who holds a free 
<ref target="n59">[59]</ref> 
 living dies at Rome or on the 
way to Rome, his living must forever belong to the Roman-I should rather 
say the robbing-See; 
<ref target="n60">[60]</ref> 
 and yet they will not be called robbers; though 
they are guilty of such robbery as no one has ever heard or read about. 
 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Second, In case any one who belongs to the household of the pope or of 
the cardinals 
<ref target="n61">[61]</ref> 
 holds or takes over a benefice, or in case one who 
already holds a benefice afterwards enters the "household" of the pope or 
of a cardinal; but who can count the "household" of the pope and of the 
cardinals, when the pope, if he only goes on a pleasure-ride, takes with 
him three or four thousand mule-riders, eclipsing all emperors and kings? 
Christ and St. Peter went on foot in order that their vicars might have 
the more pomp and splendor. Now avarice has cleverly thought out another 
scheme, and brings it to pass that even here many; have the name of "papal 
servant," just as though they were in Rome; all in order that in every 
place the mere rascally little word "papal servant" may bring all 
benefices to Rome and tie them fast there forever. Are not these vexatious 
and devilish inventions? Let us beware! Soon Mainz; Madgeburg and 
Halberstadt will gently pass into the hands of Rome, and the cardinalate 
will be paid for dearly enough. 
<ref target="n62">[62]</ref> 
 "Afterwards we will make all the 
German bishops cardinal so that there will be nothing left outside." 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Third, When a contest has started at Rome over a benefice. 
<ref target="n63">[63]</ref> 
 This I 
hold to be almost the commonest and widest road for bringing livings to 
Rome. For when there is no contest at home, unnumbered knaves will be 
found at Rome to dig up contests out of the earth and assail livings at 
their will. Thus many a good priest has to lose his living, or settle the 
contest for a time by the payment of a sum of money. 
<ref target="n64">[64]</ref> 
 Such a living 
rightly or wrongly contested must also belong forever to the Roman See. It 
would be no wonder if God were to rain from heaven fire and brimstone and 
to sink Rome in the abyss, as He did Sodom and Gomorrah of old. Why should 
there be a pope in Christendom, if his power is used for nothing else than 
such archknavery, and if he protects and practices it? O noble princes and 
lords, how long will ye leave your lands and people naked to these 
ravening wolves! 
 
</p> 
 
<p> 
 
Since even these practices were not enough, and Avarice grew impatient 
at the long time it took to get hold of all the bishoprics, therefore my 
Lord Avarice devised the fiction that the bishoprics should be nominally 
abroad, but that their land and soil should be at Rome, and no bishop 
can be confirmed unless with a great sum of money he buy the <foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">pallium</hi></foreign>,<ref target="n65">[65]</ref> 
 and bind 
himself with terrible oaths to the pope's servant. 
<ref target="n66">[66]</ref> 
 This is the reason 
that no bishop ventures to act against the pope. That, too, is what the 
Romans were seeking when they imposed the oath, and thus the very richest 
bishoprics have fallen into debt and ruin. Mainz pays, as I hear, 20,000 
gulden. These be your Romans! To be sure they decreed of old in the canon 
law that the pallium should be bestowed gratis, the number of papal servants 
diminished, the contest lessened, the chapters 
<ref target="n67">[67]</ref> 
 and bishops allowed their 
liberty. But this did not bring in money, and so they turned over a new 
leaf, and all authority was taken from the bishops and chapters; they are 
made ciphers, and have no office nor authority nor work, but everything is 
ruled by the archknaves at Rome; soon they will have in hand even the office 
of sexton and bell-ringer in all the churches. All contests are brought to 
Rome, and by authority of the pope everyone does as he likes. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
What happened this very year? The Bishop of Strassburg 
<ref target="n68">[68]</ref> 
 wished to 
govern his chapter properly and to institute reforms in worship, and with 
this end in view made certain godly and Christian regulations. But my dear 
Lord Pope and the Holy Roman See, at the instigation of the priests, 
overthrew and altogether condemned this holy and spiritual ordinance. This 
is called "feeding the sheep of Christ!" Thus priests are to be encouraged 
against their own bishop, and their disobedience to divine law is to be 
protected! Antichrist himself, I hope, will not dare to put God to such open 
shame! There you have your pope after your own heart! Why did he do this? 
Ah! if one church were reformed, it would be a dangerous departure; Rome's 
turn too might come! Therefore it were better that no priest should be left 
at peace with another, that kings and princes should be set at odds, as has 
been the custom heretofore, and the world filled with the blood of 
Christians, only so the concord of Christians should not trouble the Holy 
Roman See with a reformation. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
So far we have been getting an idea of how 
they deal with livings which become vacant. But for tender-hearted Avarice 
the vacancies are too few, and so he brings his foresight to bear upon the 
benefices which are still occupied by their incumbents, so that they must be 
unfilled, even they are not unfilled. 
<ref target="n69">[69]</ref> 
 And this he does in many ways, as 
follows: 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
First, He lies in wait for fat prebends or bishoprics which are 
held by an old or a sick man, or by one with an alleged disability. To such 
an incumbent, without his desire or consent, the Holy See gives a 
coadjutor's i.e., an "assistant," for the coadjutor's benefit, because he is 
"papal servant," or has paid for the position, or has earned it by some 
other ignoble service to Rome. In this case the rights of the chapter or the 
rights of him who has the bestowal of the living 
<ref target="n70">[70]</ref> 
 must be surrendered, 
and the whole thing fall into the hands of Rome. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Second, There is a little 
word commend, 
<ref target="n71">[71]</ref> 
 by which the pope entrusts the keeping of a rich, fat 
monastery or church to a cardinal or to another oh his people, just as 
though I were to give you a hundred gulden to keep. This is not called the 
giving or bestowing of the monastery nor even its destruction, or the 
abolition of the worship of God, but only "giving it into keeping"; not that 
he to whom it is entrusted is to care for it, or build it up, but he is to 
drive out the incumbent, to receive the goods and revenues, and to install 
some apostate, renegade monk, 
<ref target="n72">[72]</ref> 
 who accepts five or six gulden a year and 
sits in the church all day selling pictures and images to the pilgrims, so 
that henceforth neither prayers nor masses are said there. If this were to 
be called destroying monasteries and abolishing the worship of God, then the 
pope would have to be called a destroyer of Christendom and an abolisher of 
God's worship, because this is his constant practice. That would be a hard 
saying at Rome, and so we must call it a commend or a "command to take 
charge" of the monastery. The pope can every year make commends out of four 
or more of these monasteries, a single one of which may have an income of 
more than six thousand gulden. This is the way the Romans increase the 
worship of God and preserve the monasteries. The Germans also are beginning 
to find it out. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Third, There are some benefices which they call 
<foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">incompatibilia</hi></foreign>, 
<ref target="n73">[73]</ref> 
 and which, according to 
the ordinances of the 
canon law, cannot be held by one man at the same time, as for instance, two 
parishes, two bishoprics and the like. In these cases the Holy Roman See of 
Avarice evades the canon law by making "glosses," 
<ref target="n74">[74]</ref> 
 called unio and 
incorporatio, i.e., by "incorporating" many <foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">incompatibilia</hi></foreign>, so that 
each becomes a part of every other and all of them together are looked upon 
as though they were one living. They are then no longer "incompatible," and 
the holy canon law is satisfied, in that it is no longer binding, except 
upon those who do not buy these "glosses" 
<ref target="n75">[75]</ref> 
 from the pope or his 
<foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">datarius</hi></foreign>. 
<ref target="n76">[76]</ref> 
 The <foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">unio</hi></foreign>, i.e., "uniting," is of the same nature. The 
pope binds many such benefices together like a bundle of sticks, and by 
virtue of this bond they are all regarded as one benefice. So there is at 
Rome one courtesan 
<ref target="n77">[77]</ref> 
 who holds, for himself alone, 22 parishes, 7 priories 
and 44 canonries besides, -- all by the help of that masterly "gloss," which 
holds that this is not illegal. What cardinals and other prelates have, 
everyone may imagine for himself. In this way the Germans are to have their 
purses eased and their itch cured. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Another of the "glosses" is the <foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">administratio</hi></foreign>, i.e., a man may have beside 
his bishopric, an abbacy or a dignity, <ref target="n78">[78]</ref> 
 and possess all the property which goes with it, only he 
has no other title than that of "administrator." 
<ref target="n79">[79]</ref> 
 For at Rome it is 
sufficient that words are changed and not the things they stand for; as 
though I were to teach that a bawdy-house keeper should have the name of 
"burgomaster's wife," and yet continue to ply her trade. This kind of Roman 
rule St. Peter foretold when he said, in II Peter 2:3: "There shall come 
false teachers, who in covetousness, with feigned words, shall make 
merchandise of you, to get their gains." 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Again, dear Roman Avarice has 
invented the custom of selling and bestowing livings to such advantage that 
the seller or disposer retains reversionary rights, 
<ref target="n80">[80]</ref> 
 upon them; to wit, 
if the incumbent dies, the benefice freely reverts to him who previously 
sold, bestowed or surrendered it. In this way they have made livings 
hereditary property, so that henceforth no one can come into possession of 
them, except the man to whom the seller is willing to dispose of them, or to 
whom he bequeaths his rights at death. Besides, there are many who transfer 
to others the mere title to a benefice from which those who get the title 
derive not a heller of income. It is now an old custom, too, to give another 
man a benefice and to reserve a certain part out of the annual revenue. 
<ref target="n81">[81]</ref> 
 
In olden times this was simony. 
<ref target="n82">[82]</ref> 
 Of these things there are so many more 
that they cannot all be counted. They treat livings more shamefully than the 
heathen beneath the cross treated the garments of Christ. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Yet all that has 
hitherto been said is ancient history and an every-day occurrence at Rome. 
Avarice has devised one thing more, which may, I hope, be his last morsel, 
and choke him. The pope has a noble little device called <foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">pectoralis 
reservatio</hi></foreign>, i.e., his "mental reservation," and <foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">proprius motus</hi></foreign>, 
i.e., the "arbitrary will of his authority." 
<ref target="n83">[83]</ref> 
 It goes like this. When one 
man has gotten a benefice at Rome, and the appointment has been regularly 
signed and sealed, according to custom, and there comes another, who brings 
money, or has laid the pope under obligation in some other way, of which we 
will not speak, and desires of the pope the same benefice, then the pope 
takes it from the first man and gives it to the second. 
<ref target="n84">[84]</ref> 
 If it is said 
that this is unjust, then the Most Holy Father must make some excuse, that 
he may not be reproved for doing such open violence to the law, and says 
that in his mind and heart he had reserved that benefice to himself and his 
own plenary disposal, although he had never before in his whole life either 
thought or heard of it. Thus he has now found a little "gloss" by which he 
can, in his own person, lie and deceive, and make a fool and an ape of 
anybody -- all this he does brazenly and openly, and yet he wishes to be the 
head of Christendom, though with his open lies he lets the Evil Spirit rule 
him. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
This arbitrary will and lying "reservation" of the pope creates in Rome 
a state of affairs which is unspeakable. There is buying, selling, 
bartering, trading, trafficking, lying, deceiving, robbing, stealing, 
luxury, harlotry, knavery, and every sort of contempt of God, and even the 
rule of Antichrist could not be more scandalous. Venice, Antwerp, Cairo 
<ref target="n85">[85]</ref> 
 
are nothing compared to this fair which is held at Rome and the business 
which is done there, except that in those other places they still observe 
and reason. At Rome everything goes as the devil wills, and out of this 
ocean like virtue flows into all the world. Is it a wonder that such people 
fear a reformation and a free council, and prefer to set all kings and 
princes at enmity rather than have them unite and bring about a council? Who 
could bear to have such knavery exposed if it were his own? 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Finally, for all 
this noble commerce the pope has built a warehouse, namely, the house of the 
<foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">datarius</hi></foreign>, 
<ref target="n86">[86]</ref> 
 in Rome. Thither all must come 
who deal after this fashion in 
benefices and livings. From him they must buy their "glosses" 
<ref target="n87">[87]</ref> 
 and get 
the power to practice such archknavery. In former times Rome was generous, 
and then justice had either to be bought or else suppressed with money, but 
now she has become exorbitant, and no one dare be a knave unless with a 
great sum he has first bought the right. If that is not a brothel above all 
the brothels one can imagine, then I do not know what brothel means. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
If you have money in this house, then you can come by all the things I 
have said; and not only these, but all sort of usury <ref 
target="n88">[88]</ref> 
 are here made honest, for a 
consideration, and the possession of all property acquired by theft or 
robbery is legalized. Here vows are dissolved; here monks at granted liberty 
to leave their orders; here marriage is on sale to the clergy; here bastards 
can become legitimate; here all dishonor and shame can come to honor; all 
ill repute and stigma of evil are here knighted and ennobled here is 
permitted the marriage which is within the forbidden degrees or has some 
other defect. 
<ref target="n89">[89]</ref> 
 Oh! what a taxing and a robbing rules there! It looks as 
though all the laws of the Church were made for one purpose only -- to be 
nothing but so many money-snares, from which a man must extricate 
himself, 
<ref target="n90">[90]</ref> 
 if he would be a Christian. Yea, here the devil becomes a 
saint, and a god to boot. What heaven and earth cannot, that this house can 
do! They call them compositions 
<ref target="n91">[91]</ref> 
! "Compositions" indeed! rather 
"confusions"! Oh, what a modest tax is the Rhine-toll, 
<ref target="n92">[92]</ref> 
 compared with the 
tribute taken by this holy house! 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Let no one accuse me of exaggeration! It 
is all so open that even at Rome they must confess the evil to be greater 
and more terrible than any one can say. I have not yet stirred up the 
hell-broth of personal vices, nor do I intend to do so. I speak of things 
which are common talk, and yet I have not words to tell them all. The 
bishops, the priests and, above all, the doctors in the universities, who 
draw their salaries for this purpose, should have done their duty and with 
common consent have written and cried out against these things; but they 
have done the very opposite. 
<ref target="n93">[93]</ref> 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
There remains one last word, and I must say 
that too. Since boundless Avarice has not been satisfied with all these 
treasures, which three great kings might well think sufficient, he now 
begins to transfer this trade and sell it to Fugger of Augsburg, 
<ref target="n94">[94]</ref> 
 so that 
the lending and trading and buying of bishoprics and benefices, and the 
driving of bargains in spiritual goods has now come to the right place, and 
spiritual and temporal goods have become one business. And now I would fain 
hear of a mind so lofty that it could imagine what this Roman Avarice might 
yet be able to do and has not already done; unless Fugger were to transfer 
or sell this combination of two lines of business to somebody else. I 
believe we have reached the limit. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
As for what they have stolen in all lands 
and still steal and extort, by means of indulgences, bulls, letters of 
confession, 
<ref target="n95">[95]</ref> 
 "butter-letters" 
<ref target="n96">[96]</ref> 
 and other <foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">confessionalia</hi></foreign>, 
<ref target="n97">[97]</ref> 
 
-- all this I consider mere patch-work, and like casting a single devil more 
into hell. 
<ref target="n98">[98]</ref> 
 Not that they bring in little, for a mighty king could well 
support himself on their returns, but they are not to be compared with the 
streams of treasure above mentioned. I shall also say nothing at present of 
how this indulgence money has been applied. Another time I shall inquire 
about that, for Campoflore, 
<ref target="n99">[99]</ref> 
 and Belvidere 
<ref target="n100">[100]</ref> 
 and certain other places 
probably know something about it. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Since, then, such devilish rule is not 
only open robbery and deceit, and the tyranny of the gates of hell, but also 
ruins Christendom in body and soul, it is our duty to use all diligence in 
protecting Christendom against such misery and destruction. If we would 
fight the Turks, let us make a beginning here, where they are at their 
worst. If we justly hang thieves and behead robbers, why should we let Roman 
Avarice go free? For he is the greatest thief and robber that has come or 
can come into the world, and all in the holy Name of Christ and of St. 
Peter! Who can longer endure it or keep silence? Almost everything he owns 
has been gotten by theft and robbery; that is the truth, and all history 
shows it. The pope never got by purchase such great properties that from his 
<foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">officia</hi></foreign> 
<ref target="n101">[101]</ref> 
 
alone he can raise about a million ducats, not to mention the 
mines of treasure named above and the income of his lands. Nor did it come 
to him by inheritance from Christ or from St. Peter; no one ever loaned it 
or gave it to him; it has not become his by virtue of immemorial use and 
enjoyment. Tell me, then, whence he can have it? Learn from this what they 
have in mind when they send out legates to collect money for use against the 
Turks. 
</p> 
 
 
 
 
</div3> 
 
<div3 type="notes" id="d12"> 
 
 
<note id="n42"><seg type="note-symbol">[42]</seg> <p><foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Der Haufe</hi></foreign>, 
i.e. Christians considered <hi rend="italic">en masse</hi>, without regard to official 
position in the Church. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n43"><seg type="note-symbol">[43]</seg> <p>The papal crown dates from the XI Century: the 
triple crown, or tiara, from the beginning of the XIV. It was intended 
to signify that very superiority of the pope to be rulers of this world, 
of which Luther here complains. See <foreign 
lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Realencyk.</hi></foreign>, X, 532, and literature there 
cited. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n44"><seg type="note-symbol">[44]</seg> <p>A statement made by Augustinus Triumphus. See above, 
p.73, note 5; and below, p. 246. Vol. II.-6. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n45"><seg type="note-symbol">[45]</seg> <p>The Cardinal della Rovere, afterwards Pope Julius 
II, held at one time the archbishopric of Avignon, the bishoprics of 
Bologna, Lausanne, Coutances, Viviers, Mende, Ostia and Velletri, and 
the abbacies of Nonantola, and Grottaferrata. This is but one 
illustration of the scandalous pluralism practiced by the cardinals. Cf. 
LEA, in Cambridge Mod. Hist., I, pp. 659 f. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n46"><seg type="note-symbol">[46]</seg> <p>The complaint that the cardinals were provided with 
incomes by appointment to German benefices goes back to the Council of 
Constance (1415). Cf. <hi rend="italic">BENRATH</hi>, p. 87, note 17. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n47"><seg type="note-symbol">[47]</seg> <p>The creation of new cardinals was a lucrative 
proceeding for the popes. On July 31, 1517, Leo X created thirty-one 
cardinals, and is said to have received from the new appointees about 
300,000 ducats. Needless to say, the cardinals expected to make up the 
fees out of the income of their livings. See Weimar Ed., VI, 417, note 
I, and PASTOR, <foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Gesch. der Papste 
IV</hi></foreign>, I, 137. Cf. Hutten's <hi rend="italic">Vadiscus</hi> (Bocking IV, 
188). </p></note> 
 
<note id="n48"><seg type="note-symbol">[48]</seg> <p>The famous Benedictine monastery just outside the 
city of Bamberg. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n49"><seg type="note-symbol">[49]</seg> <p>The proposal made at Constance (see above, p. 82, 
note 2) was more generous. It suggested a salary of three to four 
thousand gulden. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n50"><seg type="note-symbol">[50]</seg> <p>As early as the XIV Century both England and France 
had enacted laws prohibiting the very practices of which Luther here 
complains. It should be noted, however, that these laws were enforced 
only occasionally, and never very strictly. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n51"><seg type="note-symbol">[51]</seg> <p>The papal court or curia consisted of all the 
officials of various sorts who were employed in the transaction of papal 
business, including those who were in immediate attendance upon the 
person of the pope, the so-called "papal family." On the number of such 
officials in the XVI Century, see BENRATH, p. 88, note 18, where 
reference is made to 949 offices, exclusive of those which had to do 
with the administration of the city of Rome and of the States of the 
Church, and not including the members of the pope's "family." The 
<hi rend="italic">Gravamina</hi> of 1521 complain that the increase of these office in 
recent years has added greatly to the financial burdens of the German 
Church (WREDE, <foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Deutsche Reichstagaskten unter 
Kaiser Karl V</hi></foreign>, II, 675).</p></note> 
 
<note id="n52"><seg type="note-symbol">[52]</seg> <p>On the annates, see Vol. I, p. 383, note I. Early in 
their history, which dates from the beginning of the XIV, Century, the 
annates (<foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">fructus medii temporis</hi></foreign>) 
had become a fixed tax on all the Church offices which fell vacant, and 
the complaint of extortion in their appraisement and collection was 
frequently raised. The Council of Constance restricted the obligation to 
bishoprics and abbacies, and such other benefices as had a yearly income 
of more than 24 gulden. The Council of Basel (1439) resolved to abolish 
them entirely, but the resolution of the Council was inoperative, and in 
the Concordat of Vienna (1448) the German nation agreed to abide by the 
decision of Constance. On the use of the term "annates" to include other 
payments to the curia, especially the <foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">servitia</hi></foreign>, see <hi rend="italic">Catholic 
Encyclopedia</hi>, I, pp. 537 f. Luther here alleges that the annates 
are not applied to their ostensible purpose, viz. , the Crusade. This 
charge is repeated in the <hi rend="italic">Gravamina</hi> of the German Nation 
presented to the Diet of Worms (1521), with the additional allegation 
that the amount demanded in the way of annates has materially increase 
(A. WREDE, <foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Deutsche Reichstagsakten unter Kaiser 
Karl V.</hi></foreign>, II, pp. 675 f.). Similar complaints had been 
made at the Diet of Augsburg (1518), and were repeated at the Diet of 
Nurnberg (WREDE, op. cit., III, 660). Hutten calls the annates "a good 
fat robbery" (ed. Bocking, IV, 207). In England the annates were 
abolished by Act of Parliament (April 10, 1532)</p></note> 
 
<note id="n53"><seg type="note-symbol">[53]</seg> <p>On the crusading -- indulgences, see Vol. I, p. 18. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n54"><seg type="note-symbol">[54]</seg> <p>i.e., As was done by the Council of Basel. See 
above, p. 84, note 1. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n55"><seg type="note-symbol">[55]</seg> <p>The canons are the clergy attached to a cathedral 
church who constituted the "chapter" of that cathedral, and to whom the 
right to elect the bishop normally belonged. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n56"><seg type="note-symbol">[56]</seg> <p>This whole section deals with the abuse of the "right of 
reservation," i.e., the alleged right of the pope to appoint directly to 
vacant church positions. According to papal theory the right of appointment 
belonged absolutely to the pope, who graciously yielded the right to others 
under certain circumstances, reserving it to himself in other cases. The 
practice of reserving the appointments seems to date from the XII Century, 
and was originally an arbitrary exercise of papal authority. The rules which 
came to govern the reservation of appointments were regarded as limitations 
upon the authority of the pope. The rule of the "papal months," as it 
obtained in Germany in Luther's time, is found in the Concordat of Vienna of 
1448 (MIRBT, <foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Quellen</hi></foreign>, 2d ed., NO. 261, 
pp. 167 f.). It provides that livings, with the exception of the higher 
dignities in the cathedrals and the chief posts in the monasteries, which 
fall vacant in the months of February, April, June, August, October and 
December, shall be filled by the ordinary methods-elections, presentation, 
appointment by the bishop, etc. - but that vacancies occurring in the other 
months shall be filled by appointment of the pope. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n57"><seg type="note-symbol">[57]</seg> <p>i.e., Church offices which carried with them certain 
rights of jurisdiction and gave their possessors a certain honorary 
precedence over other officials of the Church. See MEYER in <foreign 
lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Realencyk.</hi></foreign>, IV, 658. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n58"><seg type="note-symbol">[58]</seg> <p>Charles V, though elected emperor, was not crowned 
until October 22d. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n59"><seg type="note-symbol">[59]</seg> <p>i.e., A living which has not hitherto been filled by papal 
appointment. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n60"><seg type="note-symbol">[60]</seg> <p>This rule, like that of the "papal months," is found 
in the Concordat of Vienna. Luther's complaint is reiterated in the 
<hi rend="italic">Gravamina</hi> of 1521. (WREDE, <foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Deutsche 
Reichstagsakten</hi></foreign>, etc., II, 673.) </p></note> 
 
<note id="n61"><seg type="note-symbol">[61]</seg> <p><foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Des Papstes und der Cardinale 
Gesinde</hi></foreign>, i.e., all those who were 
counted members of the "family" or "household" (called <foreign 
lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Dienstverwandte</hi></foreign> in 
the Gravamina of 1521) of the pope or of any of the cardinals. The term 
included those who were in immediate attendance upon the pope or the 
cardinals, and all those to whom, by virtue of any special connection with 
the curia, the name "papal servant" could be made to apply. These are the 
"courtesans" to whom Luther afterwards refers. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n62"><seg type="note-symbol">[62]</seg> <p>In 1513 Albrecht of Brandenburg was made Archbishop 
of Madgeburg and later in the same year Administrator of Halberstadt; in 
1514 he became Archbishop of Mainz as well. In 1518 he was made 
cardinal. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n63"><seg type="note-symbol">[63]</seg> <p>This rule, like the others mentioned above, is 
contained in the Concordat of Vienna. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n64"><seg type="note-symbol">[64]</seg> <p>Cf. The <hi rend="italic">Gravamina</hi> of 1521, NO. 20, <foreign 
lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Von anfechtung der cordissanen</hi></foreign> (see above, 
p.88, note 3), where the name <hi rend="italic">CORDissei</hi> is applied to the 
practice of attacking titles to benefices. (WREDE, op.  Cit., II, pp. 
677 f.) </p></note> 
 
<note id="n65"><seg type="note-symbol">[65]</seg> <p>The <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">pallium</hi></foreign> 
is a woolen shoulder-cape which is the emblem of the archbishop's 
office, and which must be secured from Rome. The bestowal of the 
<foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">pallium</hi></foreign> by the pope is a very 
ancient custom. Gregory I (590-604) mentions it as <hi rend="italic">prisca 
consuetude</hi> (Dist., C.c. 3). The cannon law prescribes (Dist. C.c. 
1) that the archbishop-elect must secure the <foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">pallium</hi></foreign> from Rome within three months of 
his election; otherwise he is forbidden to discharge any of the duties 
of his office. It is regarded as the necessary complement of his 
election and consecration, conferring the "plenitude of the pontifical 
office," and the name of archbishop. Luther's charge that it had to be 
purchased "with a great sum of money" is substantiated by similar 
complaints from the XII Century on, though the language of the canon law 
makes it evident that Luther's other contention is also correct, viz., 
that the <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">pallium</hi></foreign> was originally 
bestowed <hi rend="italic">gratis</hi>. The sum required from the different 
archbishops varied with the wealth of their see, and was a fixed sum in 
each case. The <hi rend="italic">Gravamina</hi> of 1521 complain that the price has 
been raised" "Although according to ancient ordinance the bishoprics of 
Mainz, Cologne, Salzburg, etc., were bound to pay for the <foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">pallium</hi></foreign> about 10,000 gulden and no more, 
they can now scarcely get a <foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">pallium</hi></foreign> from Rome for 20 or 24 thousand 
gulden." (WREDE, op. cit., II, 675.) </p></note> 
 
<note id="n66"><seg type="note-symbol">[66]</seg> <p>The oath of allegiance to the pope was required 
before the pallium could be bestowed (Dist. C.c. 1). The canon law 
describes this oath as one "of allegiance, obedience and unity" (X, I, 
6, c. 4). </p></note> 
 
<note id="n67"><seg type="note-symbol">[67]</seg> <p>See above, p.86. note 2. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n68"><seg type="note-symbol">[68]</seg> <p>cf. Luther to Spalatin, June 25, 152. (ENDERS, II, 
424; SMITH, NO.  271). </p></note> 
 
<note id="n69"><seg type="note-symbol">[69]</seg> <p>i.e., The benefices are treated as though they were 
vacant. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n70"><seg type="note-symbol">[70]</seg> <p>In the case of certain endowed benefices the right 
of nominate the incumbent was vested in individuals, usually of the 
nobility, and was hereditary in their family. This is the so-called 
<foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">jus patronum</hi></foreign>, or "right of 
patronage. The complaint that this right is disregarded is frequent in 
the <hi rend="italic">Gravamina</hi> of 1521.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n71"><seg type="note-symbol">[71]</seg> <p>Commendation was one of the practices by which the 
pope evaded the provision of the canon law which prescribed that the 
same man should not hold two livings with the cure of souls. The man who 
received an office in <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">in 
commendam</hi></foreign> was not required to fulfill the duties attached 
to the position and when a living or an abbacy was granted in this way 
during the incumbency of another, the recipient received its entire 
income during a subsequent vacancy. The practice was most common in the 
case of abbacies. At the Diet of Worms (1521), Duke George of Saxony, an 
outspoken opponent of Luther, was as emphatic in his protest against 
this practice as Luther himself (WREDE, op. cit., II, 665); his protest 
was incorporated in the <hi rend="italic">Gravamina</hi> (ibid., 672), and reappears 
in the Appendix (ibid., 708).</p></note> 
 
<note id="n72"><seg type="note-symbol">[72]</seg> <p>A monk who deserted his monastery was known as an 
"apostate." </p></note> 
 
<note id="n73"><seg type="note-symbol">[73]</seg> <p>i.e., Offices which cannot be united in the hands of 
one man. See e.g., note 3, p. 91. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n74"><seg type="note-symbol">[74]</seg> <p>A gloss is a note explanatory of a word of passage 
of doubtful meaning. The glosses are the earliest form of commentary on 
the Bible. The glosses of the canon law are the more or less 
authoritative comments of the teachers, and date from the time when the 
study of the canon law became a part of the theological curriculum. 
Their aim is chiefly to show how the law applies to practical case which 
may arise. The so-called <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">glossa 
ordinaria</hi></foreign> had in Luther's time an authority almost equal 
to that of the <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">corpus juris</hi></foreign> 
itself.  Cf. <hi rend="italic">Cath. Encyc.</hi>, VI, pp. 588f. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n75"><seg type="note-symbol">[75]</seg> <p>The thing which was bought was, of course, the 
dispensation, or permission to avail oneself of the gloss. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n76"><seg type="note-symbol">[76]</seg> <p><foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">Dataria</hi></foreign> is 
the name for that department of the curia which had to deal with the 
granting of dispensations and the disposal of benefices.  <foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">Datarius</hi></foreign> is the title of the official who 
presided over this department. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n77"><seg type="note-symbol">[77]</seg> <p>See above, p.88, note 2. For a catalogue of papal 
appointments bestowed upon two "courtesans," Johannes Zink and Johannes 
Ingenwinkel, see SCHULTE, <foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Die Fugger in 
Rom</hi></foreign>, I, pp. 282 ff.  Between 1513 and 1521, Zink received 
56 appointments, and Ingenwinkel received, between 1496 and 1521, no 
fewer than 106. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n78"><seg type="note-symbol">[78]</seg> <p>See above, p. 87, note 1. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n79"><seg type="note-symbol">[79]</seg> <p>So Albrecht of Mainz bore the title of "administrator" of 
Halberstadt. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n80"><seg type="note-symbol">[80]</seg> <p>The name of this practice was "regression" (<foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">regressus</hi></foreign>).</p></note> 
 
<note id="n81"><seg type="note-symbol">[81]</seg> <p>The complaint was made at Worms (1521) that it was 
impossible for a German to secure a clear title to a benefice at Rome 
unless he applied for it in the name of an Italian, to whom he was 
obliged to pay a percentage of the income, a yearly pension, or a fixed 
sum of money for the use of his name (WREDE, op. cit., II, 712).</p></note> 
 
<note id="n82"><seg type="note-symbol">[82]</seg> <p><hi rend="italic">Simony</hi> -- the sin of Simon Magus (Acts 
8:18-20) -- the sin committed by the sale or the purchase of an office 
or position which is formally conferred by a ritual act of the Church. 
In the ancient and earlier medieval Church the use of money to secure 
preferment was held to invalidate the title of the guilty party to the 
position thus secured, and the acceptance of money for such a purpose 
was an offense punishable by deposition and degradation. The "heresy of 
Simon" was conceived to be the greatest of all heresies. The traffic in 
Church offices, which became a flagrant abuse from the time of John XXII 
(1316-1334), would have been regarded in earlier days as the most 
atrocious simony. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n83"><seg type="note-symbol">[83]</seg> <p>The <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">reservatio 
mentalis</hi></foreign> or <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">in 
pectore</hi></foreign> is the natural consequence of the papal theory 
that the right of appointment to all Church offices of every grade 
belongs to the pope (see above, p. 86, note 3.)  According to the theory 
of the canonists (LANCELOTTI, <hi rend="italic">Institutiones juris canonici</hi>, 
Lib. I, Tit. XXVII) this right is exercised either <foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">per petitionemalterius</hi></foreign>, i.e., by 
confirmation of the election, appointment, etc., of others, or <foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">propriomotu</hi></foreign>, i.e., "on his own motion." In 
ordinary cases the exercise of the appointing power was limited by 
rules, which though bitterly complained of (see above, pp. 86 ff. and 
notes), were generally understood, but the theory allowed any given case 
to be made an exception to the rules. Of such a case it was said that it 
was "reserved in the heart of the Pope," and the appointment was then 
made "on his own motion." Hutten says of this <foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">reservatio in pectore</hi></foreign> that "it is an easy, 
agile and slippery thing, and bears no comparison to any other form of 
cheating" (ed. Bocking, IV, 215). </p></note> 
 
<note id="n84"><seg type="note-symbol">[84]</seg> <p>For a similar instances quoted at Worms (1521), see 
WREDE, op. cit., II, 710. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n85"><seg type="note-symbol">[85]</seg> <p>The three chief centers of foreign commerce in the 
XV and the early XVI Century. The annual fairs (<foreign 
lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Jahrmarkt</hi></foreign>), held at stated times in 
various cities, brought great numbers of merchants together from widely 
distant points, and were the times when the greater part of the 
wholesale business for the year was done. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n86"><seg type="note-symbol">[86]</seg> <p>Built by Innocent VIII (1484-1490). 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n87"><seg type="note-symbol">[87]</seg> <p>See above, p. 93, note 2. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n88"><seg type="note-symbol">[88]</seg> <p>The Church law forbade the taking of interest on 
loans of money. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n89"><seg type="note-symbol">[89]</seg> <p>During the Middle Ages all questions touching 
marriage and divorce, including, therefore, the question of the 
legitimacy of children, were governed by the laws of the Church, on the 
theory that marriage was a sacrament. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n90"><seg type="note-symbol">[90]</seg> <p>i.e., By buying dispensations. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n91"><seg type="note-symbol">[91]</seg> <p>The sums paid for special dispensations were so called. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n92"><seg type="note-symbol">[92]</seg> <p>The toll which the "robber-barons" of the Rhine 
levied upon merchants passing through their domains. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n93"><seg type="note-symbol">[93]</seg> <p><foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Ja wend das blat umb szo findistu 
es</hi></foreign> -- The translators have 
adopted the interpretation of O. CLEMEN, L's. <foreign 
lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Werke</hi></foreign>, I, 383. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n94"><seg type="note-symbol">[94]</seg> <p>The Fuggers of Augsburg were the greatest of the 
German capitalists in the XVI Century. They were international bankers, 
"the Rothschilds of the XVI Century." Their control of large capital 
enabled them to advance large sums of money to the territorial rulers, 
who were in a chronic state of need. In return for these favors they 
received monopolistic concessions by which their capital was further 
increased. The spiritual, as well as the temporal lords, availed 
themselves regularly of the services of this accommodating firm. They 
were the pope's financial representatives in Germany. On their 
connection with the indulgence against which Luther protested, see Vol. 
I, p. 21; on their relations with the papacy, see SCHULTE, <foreign 
lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Die Fugger in Rom</hi></foreign>, 2 Vols., Leipzig, 1904. 
Vol. II.-7</p></note> 
 
<note id="n95"><seg type="note-symbol">[95]</seg> <p>Certificates entitling the holder to choose his own 
confessor and authorizing the confessor to absolve him from certain 
classes of "reserved" sins; referred to in the XCV Theses as 
<hi rend="italic">confessionalia</hi>. Cf. Vol. I, p.22. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n96"><seg type="note-symbol">[96]</seg> <p>Certificates granting their possessor permission to 
eat milk, eggs, butter and cheese on fast days. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n97"><seg type="note-symbol">[97]</seg> <p>The word is used here in the broad sense, and means 
dispensations of all sorts, including those just mentioned, relating to 
penance. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n98"><seg type="note-symbol">[98]</seg> <p>Equivalent to "carrying coals to Newcastle." 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n99"><seg type="note-symbol">[99]</seg> <p>The <hi rend="italic">Campo di Fiore</hi>, a Roman market-place, 
restored and adorned at great expense by Eugenius IV (1431-1447), and 
his successors. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n100"><seg type="note-symbol">[100]</seg> <p>A part of the Vatican palace notorious as the 
banqueting-hall of Alexander VI (1492-1503), turned by Julius II 
(1503-1513) into a museum for the housing of his wonderful and expensive 
collection of ancient works of art. Luther is hinting that the 
indulgence money has been spent on these objects rather than on the 
maintenance of the Church. Cf. CLEMEN, I, 384, note 15. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n101"><seg type="note-symbol">[101]</seg> <p>i.e., The offices and positions in Rome which were 
for sale. See BENRATH, p. 88, note 18; p. 95, note 36. </p></note> 
 
</div3> 
 
<div3 type="part" n="3" id="d13"> 
 
<head>III. PROPOSALS FOR REFORM</head> 
 
<p> 
 
Now, although I am too small a man to make propositions which might 
effect a reform in this dreadful state of things, nevertheless I may as well 
sing my fool's song to the end, and say, so far as I am able, what could and 
should be done by the temporal authorities or by a general council. 
 
</p> 
 
<list type="ordered"> 
 
<item n="1"> 
 
1. Every prince, nobleman and 
city should boldly forbid their subjects to pay the annates to Rome and 
should abolish them entirely; <ref target="n102">[102]</ref> for the 
pope has broken the compact and made the annates a robbery, to the 
injury and shame of the whole German nation. He gives them to his 
friends, sells them for large amounts of money, and uses them to endow 
offices. He has thus lost his right to them, and deserves punishment. It 
is therefore the duty of the temporal authorities to protect the 
innocent and prevent injustice, as Paul teaches in Romans 13:4, and St. 
Peter in I Peter 2:14, and even the canon law in Case 16, Question 7 
<foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">de filiis</hi></foreign>.  <ref 
target="n103">[103]</ref> Thus it has come about that men are saying to 
the pope and his followers, <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">Tu 
ora</hi></foreign>, "Thou shalt pray"; to the emperor and his followers, 
<foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">Tu protege</hi></foreign>, "Thou shalt guard"; 
to the common man, <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">Tu labora</hi></foreign>, 
"Thou shalt work." Not, however, as though everyone were not to pray, 
guard and work; for the man who is diligent in his calling is praying, 
guarding and working in all that he does, but everyone should have his 
own especial task. 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="2"> 
 
 
 
2. Since the pope with his Roman practices -- his commends, 
<ref target="n104">[104]</ref> 
 
adjutories; 
<ref target="n105">[105]</ref> 
 reservations, 
<ref target="n106">[106]</ref> 
 <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">gratiae 
expectativae</hi></foreign>, 
<ref target="n107">[107]</ref> 
 papal 
months, 
<ref target="n108">[108]</ref> 
 incorporations, 
<ref target="n109">[109]</ref> 
 unions, 
<ref target="n110">[110]</ref> 
 pallia, 
<ref target="n111">[111]</ref> 
 rules in chancery, 
<ref target="n112">[112]</ref> 
 
and such like knavery -- usurps all the German foundations without authority 
and right, and gives and sells them to foreigners at Rome, who do nothing in 
German lands to earn them; and since he thereby robs the ordinaries 
<ref target="n113">[113]</ref> 
 of 
their rights, makes the bishops mere ciphers and figure-heads, and acts 
against his own canon law, against nature and against reason, until it has 
finally gone so far that out of sheer avarice the livings and benefices are 
sold to gross, ignorant asses and knaves at Rome, while pious and learned 
folk have no profit of their wisdom and merit, so that the poor people of 
the German nation have to go without good and learned prelates and thus go 
to ruin. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Therefore, the Christian nobility should set itself against the pope as 
against a common enemy and destroyer of Christendom, and should do this for 
the salvation of the poor souls who must go to ruin through his tyranny. 
They should. ordain, order, and decree, that henceforth no benefice shall be 
drawn into the hands of Rome, and that hereafter no appointment shall be 
obtained there in any manner whatsoever, but that the benefices shall be 
brought out and kept out from under this tyrannical authority; and they 
should restore to the ordinaries the right and office of ordering these 
benefices in the German nation as best they may. And if a "courtesan" were 
to come from Rome, he should receive a strict command either to keep his 
distance, or else to jump into the Rhine or the nearest river, and take the 
Roman ban, with its seals and letters, to a cold bath. They would then take 
note at Rome that the Germans are not always mad and drunken, but that they 
have really become Christians, and intend to permit no longer the mockery 
and scorn of the holy name of Christ, under which all this knavery and 
destruction of souls goes on, but have more regard to God and His glory than 
to the authority of men. 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="3"> 
 
 
 
3. An imperial law should be issued, that no bishop's cloak 
<ref target="n114">[114]</ref> 
 and no 
confirmation of any dignity 
<ref target="n115">[115]</ref> 
 whatsoever shall henceforth be secured from 
Rome, but that the ordinance of the most holy and most famous Council of 
Nicaea 
<ref target="n116">[116]</ref> 
 shall be restored, in which it is decreed that a bishop shall be 
confirmed by the two nearest bishops or by the archbishop. If the pope will 
break the statutes of this and of all other councils, what is the use of 
holding councils; or who has given him the authority thus to despise and 
break the rules of councils? 
 
<lb/> 
If he has this power then we should depose all bishops, archbishops and 
primates 
<ref target="n117">[117]</ref> 
 and make them mere parish-priests, so that the pope alone may 
be over them, as he now is. He leaves to bishops, archbishops and primates 
no regular authority or office, usurps everything for himself, and lets them 
keep only the name and empty title. It has gone so far that by his 
"exemptions" 
<ref target="n118">[118]</ref> 
 the monasteries, the abbots and the prelates are withdrawn 
from the regular authority of the bishops, so that there is no longer any 
order in Christendom. From this must follow what has followed -- relaxation 
of discipline and license to do evil everywhere -- so that I verily fear the 
pope can be called the "man of sin." 
<ref target="n119">[119]</ref> 
 There is in Christendom no discipline, 
no rule, no order; and who is to blame except the pope? This usurped 
authority of his he applies strictly to all the prelates, and takes away 
their rods; and he is generous to all subjects, giving them or selling them 
their liberty. 
 
<lb/> 
Nevertheless, for fear he may complain that he is robbed of his 
authority, it should be decreed that when the primates or archbishops are 
unable to settle a case, or when a controversy arises among themselves, such 
a case must be laid before the pope, but not every little matter. 
<ref target="n120">[120]</ref> 
 Thus 
it was done in olden times, and thus the famous Council of Nicaea 
decreed. 
<ref target="n121">[121]</ref> 
 If a case can be settled without the pope, then his Holiness 
should not be troubled with such minor matters, but give himself to that 
prayer, meditation and care for all Christendom, of which he boasts. This is 
what the Apostles did. They said, Acts 6:2, "It is not meet that we should 
leave the Word of God and serve tables, but we will keep to preaching and 
prayer and set others over the work." But now Rome stands for nothing else 
than the despising of the Gospel and of prayer, and for the serving of 
"tables," i.e., of temporal affairs, and the rule of the Apostles and of the 
pope agree as Christ agrees with Lucifer, heaven with hell, night with day; 
yet he is called "Vicar of Christ and Successor of the Apostles." 
 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="4"> 
 
 
4. It should be decreed that no temporal matter shall be taken to 
Rome, 
<ref target="n122">[122]</ref> 
 but that all such cases shall be left to the temporal authorities, 
as the Romans themselves decree in that canon law of theirs, which they do 
not keep. For it from the should be the duty of the pope, as the man most 
learned in the Scriptures and most Holy, not in name only, but in truth, to 
administer affairs which concern the faith and holy life of Christians, to 
hold the primates and arch-bishops to these things, and to help them in 
dealing with and caring for these matters. So St. Paul teaches in 
Corinthians 6:7, and takes the Corinthians severely to task for their 
concern with worldly things. For it works intolerable injury to all lands 
that such cases are tried at Rome. It increases the costs, and moreover the 
judges do not know the manners, laws and customs of the various countries, 
so that they often do violence to the facts and base their decisions on 
their own laws and opinions, and thus injustice is inevitably done the 
contestants. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Moreover, the outrageous extortion practiced by the <foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">officiales</hi></foreign> 
<ref target="n123">[123]</ref> 
 must 
be forbidden in all the dioceses, so that they may attend to nothing else 
than matters of faith and good morals, and leave to the temporal judges the 
things that concern money, property, life and honor. The temporal 
authorities, therefore, should not permit sentences of ban or exile when 
faith or right life is not concerned. Spiritual authorities should have rule 
over spiritual goods, as reason teaches; but spiritual goods are not money, 
nor anything pertaining to the body, but they are faith and good works. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Nevertheless it might be granted that cases which concern benefices or 
livings should be tried before bishops, archbishops and primates. Therefore, 
in order to decide contests and contentions, it might be possible for the 
Primate of Germany to maintain a general consistory, with auditors and 
chancellors, which should have control over the <foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">signaturae 
gratiae</hi></foreign> 
and <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">signaturae justitiae</hi></foreign>, 
<ref target="n124">[124]</ref> 
 that are now 
controlled at Rome, and 
which should be the final court of appeal for German cases. The officers of 
this consistory must not, however, be paid, as at Rome, by chance presents 
and gifts, and thereby acquire the habit of selling justice and injustice, 
which they now have to do at Rome because the pope gives them no 
remuneration, but allows them to fatten themselves on presents. For at Rome 
no one cares what is right or not right, but only what is money or not 
money. This court might, however, be paid out of the annates, or some other 
way might easily be devised, by those who are more intelligent and who have 
more experience in these matters than I. All I wish to do is to arouse and 
set to thinking those who have the ability and the inclination to help the 
German nation become once more free and Christian, after the wretched, 
heathenish and unchristian rule of the pope. 
 
 
</item> 
 
<lb/> 
 
<item n="5"> 
 
 
5. No more reservations should be valid, and no more benefices should be 
seized by Rome, even if the incumbent dies, or there is a contest, or the 
incumbent is a "servant" of a cardinal or of the pope; 
<ref target="n125">[125]</ref> 
 and it should be 
strictly forbidden and prevented that any "courtesan" 
<ref target="n126">[126]</ref> 
 should institute a 
contest over any benefice, so as to cite pious priests to Rome, harass them 
and drive them into lawsuits. If, in consequence of this prohibition, there 
should come from Rome a ban or an ecclesiastical censure, it should be 
disregarded, just as though a thief were to lay a man under the ban because 
he would not let him steal. Indeed they should be severely punished because 
they so blasphemously misuse the ban and the name of God to support their 
robbery, and with falsely devised threats would drive us to endure and to 
praise such blasphemy of God's name arid such abuse of Christian authority, 
and thus to become, in the sight of God, partakers in their rascality; it is 
our duty before God to resist it, for St. Paul, in Romans 1:32, reproves as 
guilty of death not only "those who do such things," but also those who 
consent to such things and allow them to be done. Most unbearable of all is 
the lying <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">reservatio pectoralis</hi></foreign>, 
<ref target="n127">[127]</ref> 
 whereby 
Christendom is so 
scandalously and openly put to shame and scorn, because its head deals in 
open lies, and out of love for the accursed money, shamelessly deceives and 
fools everybody. 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="6"> 
 
 
6. The <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">casus reservati</hi></foreign>, 
<ref target="n128">[128]</ref> 
 the 
"reserved cases," should also be 
abolished, for not only are they the means of extorting much money from the 
people, but by means of them the ravening tyrants ensnare and confuse many 
poor consciences to the intolerable injury of their faith in God. This is 
especially true of the ridiculous and childish cases about which they make 
so much ado in the <hi rend="italic">Bull Coena Domini</hi>, 
<ref target="n129">[129]</ref> 
 and which are not worth 
calling daily sins, still less cases so grave that the pope may not remit 
them by any indulgence; as for example, hindering a pilgrim on his way to 
Rome, furnishing weapons to the Turks, or tampering with papal letters. With 
such gross, crazy, clumsy things do they make fools of us! Sodom and 
Gomorrah, and all the sins which are committed and can be committed against 
the commandments of God are not reserved cases; but sins against what God 
has never commanded and what they have themselves devised, these must be 
reserved cases, solely that no one be hindered in bringing money to Rome, in 
order that, safe from the Turks, they may live in luxury and keep the world 
under their tyranny with their wanton, useless bulls and braves. 
<ref target="n130">[130]</ref> 
 
<lb/> 
 
All priests ought rightly to know, or else there should be a public 
ordinance to that effect, that no secret sin, of which a man has not been 
publicly accused, is a reserved case, and that every priest has the power to 
remit all sorts of sins, however they may be called, so long as they are 
secret; moreover that no abbot, bishop or pope has the power to reserve any 
such case to himself. 
<ref target="n131">[131]</ref> 
 If they attempt it, their reservation does not 
hold and is not valid, and they should be reproved, as men who without 
authority interfere in God's judgment, and without cause ensnare and burden 
poor, ignorant consciences. 
But if great public sins are committed, 
especially sins against God's commandments, then there is indeed a reason 
for reserved cases, but even then there should not be too many of them, and 
they should not be reserved arbitrarily and without cause; 1 Peter 5:3, for 
Christ has set in His Church not tyrants, but shepherds, as saith St. Peter. 
 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="7"> 
 
 
7. The Roman See should also do away with the <foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">officia</hi></foreign>,<ref target="n132">[132]</ref> 
and diminish the swarm of vermin at Rome, so that the pope's household 
can be supported by the pope's own purse. The pope should not allow his 
court to surpass in pomp and extravagance the courts of all kings, 
seeing that such a condition not only has never been serviceable to the 
cause of Christian faith, but the courtiers have been kept thereby from 
study and prayer, until they are scarce able to speak about the faith at 
all. This they proved quite plainly at the last Roman Council,<ref 
target="n133">[133]</ref> in which, amongst many other childish and 
frivolous things, they decreed that the soul of man is immortal and that 
every priest must say his prayers once a month on pain of losing his 
benefice. How shall matters which concern faith and the Church be 
decided by people so hardened and blinded by great avarice, wealth and 
worldly splendor, that they have only now decreed that the soul is 
immortal? It is no small shame to all Christians that at Rome they deal 
so disgracefully with the faith. If they had less wealth and pomp, they 
could pray and study better, and so become worthy and able to deal with 
matters of faith, as was the case in olden times when they were bishops, 
and did not presume to be kings over all kings. 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="8"> 
 
 
8. The hard and terrible oaths should be abolished, which the bishops are 
wrongfully compelled to render to the pope, 
<ref target="n134">[134]</ref> 
 and by which they are bound 
like servants, as that worthless and unlearned chapter, 
<foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">Significasti</hi></foreign>, 
<ref target="n135">[135]</ref> 
 arbitrarily and most 
stupidly decrees. It is not 
enough that they burden us in body, soul and property with their many mad 
laws, by which faith is weakened and Christendom ruined; but they seize upon 
the person and office and work of the bishops, and now upon the 
investiture 
<ref target="n136">[136]</ref> 
 also, which was in olden times the right of the 
German emperors, and in France and other kingdoms still belongs to the 
kings. 
 
<lb/> 
 
On this point they had great wars and disputes with the emperors, <ref 
target="n137">[137]</ref> until at last, with impudent authority, they 
took the right and have kept it until now; just as though the Germans, 
above all the Christians on earth, had to be the puppets of the pope and 
the Roman See and do and suffer what no one else will do and suffer. 
Since, then, this is sheer violence and robbery, hindering the regular 
authority of the bishops and injuring poor souls, therefore the emperor 
and 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="9"> 
 
 
9. The pope should have no authority over the emperor, except that he 
anoints and crowns him at the altar, just as a bishop anoints and crowns a 
king; 
<ref target="n138">[138]</ref> 
 and we should not henceforth yield to that devilish pride which 
compels the emperor to kiss the pope's feet or sit at his feet, or, as they 
claim, hold his stirrup or the bridle of his mule when he mounts for a ride; 
still less should he do homage and swear faithful allegiance to the pope, as 
the popes have shamelessly ventured to demand as if they possessed that 
right. The chapter <hi rend="italic">Solite</hi> 
<ref target="n139">[139]</ref> 
 in which the papal authority is raised 
above the imperial authority, is not worth a heller, nor are any of those 
who rest upon it or fear it; for it does nothing else than force the holy 
words of God out of their true meaning, and wrest them to human dreams, as I 
have showed in a Latin treatise. 
<ref target="n140">[140]</ref> 
 
<lb/> 
 
Such extravagant, over-presumptuous, and more than wicked doings of the 
pope have been devised by the devil, in order that under their cover he may 
in time bring in Antichrist, and raise the pope above God, as many are ready 
doing and have done. It is not proper for the pope to exalt himself above 
the temporal authorities, save only in spiritual offices such as preaching 
and absolving. 
In other things he is to be subject, as Paul and Peter teach, 
in Romans 13:1, and 1 Peter 2:13, and as I have said above.<ref 
target="n141">[141]</ref> His nobles are 
in duty bound to prevent and punish such tyranny. He is not vicar of Christ 
in heaven, but of Christ as He walked on earth. 
<ref target="n142">[142]</ref> 
 For Christ in heaven, in 
the form of a ruler, needs no vicar, but He sits and sees, does, and knows 
all things, and has all power. But He needs a vicar in the form of a 
servant, in which He walked on earth, toiling, preaching, suffering and 
dying. Now they turn it around, take from Christ the heavenly form of ruler 
and give it to the pope, leaving the form of a servant to perish utterly. He 
might almost be the "Counter-Christ" whom the Scriptures call Antichrist, 
for all his nature, work and doings are against Christ, for the destruction 
of Christ's nature and work. 
 
<lb/> 
 
It is also ridiculous and childish that the pope, with such perverted and 
deluded reasoning, boasts in his decretal <hi rend="italic">Pastoralis</hi>, 
<ref target="n143">[143]</ref> 
 that he is 
rightful heir to the Empire, in case of a vacancy. Who has given him this 
right? Did Christ, when He said, Luke 22:25, "The princes of the Gentiles 
are lords, but ye shall not be so"? Did St. Peter will it to him? It vexes 
me that we must read and learn such shameless, gross, crazy lies in the 
canon law, and must even hold them for Christian doctrine, when they are 
devilish lies. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Of the same sort is also that unheard-of lie about the "Donation of 
Constantine." 
<ref target="n144">[144]</ref> 
 It must have been some special plague of God that so many 
people of understanding have let themselves be talked into accepting such 
likes as these, which are so manifest and clumsy that I should think any 
drunken peasant could lie more adroitly and skillfully. How can a man rule 
an empire and at the same time continue to preach, pray, study and care for 
the poor? Yet these are the duties which properly and peculiarly belong to 
the pope, and they were imposed by Christ (Matthew 10:10) in such earnest 
that He even forbade His disciples to take with them cloak or money, since 
these duties can scarcely be performed by one who has to rule even a single 
household. Yet the pope would rule an empire and continue to be pope! This 
is a device of the knaves who would like, under the pope's name, to be lords 
of the world, and by means of the pope and the name of Christ, to restore 
the Roman Empire to its former state. 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="10"> 
 
 
10. The pope should restrain himself, take his fingers out of the pie, 
and claim no title to the Kingdom of Naples and Sicily. 
<ref target="n145">[145]</ref> 
 He has exactly 
as much right to that kingdom as I have, and yet he wishes to be its 
overlord. It is plunder got by violence, like almost all his other 
possessions. The emperor, therefore, should not grant him this fief, and if 
it has been granted, he should no longer give his consent to it, and should 
point him instead to the Bible and the prayer-books, so that he may preach 
and pray, and leave to temporal lords the ruling of lands and peoples, 
especially when no one has given them to him. 
 
<lb/> 
 
The same opinion should hold as regards Bologna, Imola, Vicenza, Ravenna 
and all the territories in the Mark of Ancona, in Romagna, and in other 
Italian lands, which the pope has taken by force and possesses without 
right. 
<ref target="n146">[146]</ref> 
 Moreover, he has meddled in these things against all the commands 
of Christ and of St. Paul. For thus saith St. Paul, 2 Timothy 2:3, "No one 
entangleth himself with worldly affairs, whose business it is to wait upon 
the divine knighthood". 
<ref target="n147">[147]</ref> 
 Now the pope should be the head and front of 
this knighthood, yet he meddles in worldly affairs more than any emperor or 
king. Why then he must be helped out of them and allowed to attend to his 
knighthood. Christ also, Whose vicar he boasts himself to be, was never 
willing to have aught to do with temporal rule; indeed, to one who asked of 
him a decision respecting his brother, He said, Luke 12:14, "Who made Me a 
judge over you?" But the pope rushes in unbidden, and boldly takes hold of 
everything as though he were a god, until he no longer knows what Christ is, 
Whose vicar he pretends to be. 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="11"> 
 
 
11. The kissing of the pope's feet 
<ref target="n148">[148]</ref> 
 should take place no more. It is 
an unchristian, nay, an anti-Christian thing for a poor sinful man to let 
his feet be kissed by one who is a hundred times better than himself. If it 
is done in honor of his authority, why does not the pope do the same to 
others in honor of their holiness? Compare the two -- Christ and the pope! 
John 13:1 ff., Christ washed His disciples' feet and dried them, and the 
disciples never washed His feet; the pope, as though he were higher than 
Christ, turns things around and, as a great favor, allows people to kiss his 
feet, though he ought properly to use all his power to prevent it, if anyone 
wished to do it; like Paul and Barnabas, who would not let the people of 
Lystra pay them divine honor, but said, Acts 14:11-16, "We are men like 
you." But our sycophants have gone so far as to make for us an idol, and now 
no one fears God so much as he fears the pope, no one pays Him such 
ceremonious honor. That they can endure! What they cannot endure is that a 
hair's-breadth should be taken away from the proud estate of the pope. Now 
if they were Christians, and held God's honor above their own, the pope 
would never be happy while he knew that God's honor was despised and his own 
exalted, and he would let no man pay him honor until he saw that God's honor 
was again exalted and was greater than his own. 
 
<lb/> 
 
<ref target="n149">[149]</ref> 
 It is another piece of the same scandalous pride, that the pope is 
not satisfied to ride or to be driven in a vehicle, but although he is 
strong and in good health, he has himself borne by men, with unheard-of 
splendor, like an idol. How, pray, does such satanic pride agree with the 
example of Christ, Who went on foot, as did all His disciples? Where has 
there ever been a worldly monarch who went about in such worldly glory as he 
who wishes to be the head of all those who are to despise and flee worldly 
glory, i.e., of Christians? Not that this in itself should give us very much 
concern, but we should rightly fear the wrath of God, if we flatter this 
kind of pride and do not show our indignation. It is enough that the pope 
should rant and play the fool in this wise; but that we should approve it 
and tolerate it, -- this too much. 
 
<lb/> 
 
For what Christian heart can or ought to take pleasure in seeing that 
when the pope wishes to receive the communion, he sits quiet, like a 
gracious lord, and has the sacrament passed to him on a golden rod by a 
bowing cardinal on bended knee? As though the holy sacrament were no worthy 
that a pope, a poor stinking sinner, should rise to show God honor, when all 
other Christians, who are much more holy than the Most Holy Father, the 
pope, receive it with all reverence! Would it be a wonder if God were to 
send a plague upon us all because we suffer such dishonor to be done Him by 
our prelates, and approve it, and by our silence or our flattery make 
ourselves partakers of such damnable pride? 
 
<lb/> 
 
It is the same way when he carries the sacrament in procession. He must 
be carried, but the sacrament is set before him, like a can of wine on the 
table. In short, at Rome Christ counts for nothing, the pope counts for 
everything; and yet they would compel us with threats to approve, and praise 
and honor such antichristian sins, though this is against God and against 
all Christian doctrine. Now God help a free Council to teach the pope that 
he too is a man, and is not more than God, as he presumes to be. 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="12"> 
 
 
12. Pilgrimages to Rome 
<ref target="n150">[150]</ref> 
 should either be abolished, or else no one 
should be allowed to make such a pilgrimage out of curiosity or because of a 
pious impulse, unless it is first recognized by his parish-priest, his town 
authorities or his overlord, that he has good and sufficient reason for it. 
I say this not because pilgrimages are bad, but because they are at this 
time ill-advised. For men see at Rome no good example, but only that which 
offends; and they have themselves made the proverb, "The nearer Rome, the 
worse Christians." 
<ref target="n151">[151]</ref> 
 Men bring back with them contempt for God and His 
commandments. It is said: "The first time one goes to Rome he seeks a 
rascal, the second time he finds him, the third time he brings him home with 
him." 
<ref target="n152">[152]</ref> 
 Now, however, they have become so clever that they make the three 
journeys at once, and they have verily brought back from Rome such pretty 
things that it were better never to have seen or known Rome. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Even if this reason did not exist, there is still another and a better: 
to wit, that by these pilgrimages men are led away into a false conceit and 
a misunderstanding of the divine commandments; for they think that this 
going on pilgrimage is a precious, good work, and this is not true. It is a 
very small good work, oftentimes an evil, delusive work, for God has not 
commanded it. But He has commanded that a man shall care for his wife and 
children, and look after such other duties as belong to the married state, 
and besides this, to serve and help his neighbor. Now it comes to pass that 
a man makes a pilgrimage to Rome when no one has commanded him to do so, 
spends fifty or a hundred gulden, more or less, and leaves his wife and 
child, or at least his neighbor, at home to suffer want. Yet the foolish 
fellow thinks to gloss over such disobedience and contempt of the divine 
commandments with his self-willed pilgriming, when it is really only 
curiosity or devilish delusion which leads him to it. The popes have helped 
this along with their false, feigned, foolish, "golden years," 
<ref target="n153">[153]</ref> 
 by which 
the people are excited, stirred up, torn away from God's commandments, and 
drawn toward their own deluded undertakings. Thus they have accomplished the 
very thing they should have forbidden; but it has brought in money and 
strengthened false authority, therefore it has had to continue, though it is 
against God and the salvation of souls. 
 
<lb/> 
 
In order to destroy in simple Christians this false, seductive faith, and 
to restore a true understanding of good works, all pilgrimages should be 
given up; for there is in them nothing good -- no commandment, no obedience 
-- but, on the contrary, numberless occasions for sin and for the despising 
of God's commandments. Hence come the many beggars, who by this pilgriming 
carry on endless knaveries and learn the habit of begging when they are not 
in want. Hence, too, come vagabondage, and many other ills which I shall not 
now recount. 
 
<lb/> 
 
If any one, now, wishes to go on pilgrimage or take a pilgrim's vow, he 
should first show his reasons to his parish-priest or to his lord. If it 
turns out that he wishes to do it for the sake of the good work, the priest 
or lord should boldly tread the vow and good work under foot, as though it 
were a lure of the devil, and show him how to apply the money and labor 
necessary for the pilgrimage to the keeping of God's commandments and to 
works a thousandfold better, viz., by spending it on his own family or on 
his poor neighbors. But if he wishes to make the pilgrimage out of 
curiosity, to see new lands and cities, he may be allowed to do as he likes. 
If, however, he has made the vow while ill, then such vows ought to be 
forbidden and canceled, and the commandments of God exalted, and he ought to 
be shown that he should henceforth be satisfied with the vow he made in 
baptism, 
<ref target="n154">[154]</ref> 
 to keep the commandments of God. And yet, in order to quiet his 
conscience, he may be allowed this once to perform his foolish vow. No one 
wants to walk in the straight and common path of God's commandments; 
everyone makes himself new roads and new vows, as though he had fulfilled 
all the commandments of God. 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="13"> 
 
 
13. Next we come to that great crowd who vow much and keep little. Be not 
angry, dear lords! Truly, I mean it well. It is the truth, and bitter-sweet, 
and it is this, -- the building of mendicant-houses 
<ref target="n155">[155]</ref> 
 should no more be 
permitted. God help us, there are already far too many of them! Would to God 
they were all done away, or at least given over to two or three orders! 
Wandering about the land has never brought any good, and never l bring any 
good. It is my advice, therefore, to put together ten of these houses, or as 
many as may be necessary, and out of them all to make one house, which will 
be well provided and need no more begging. It is much more important to 
consider what the common people need for their salvation, than what St. 
Francis, Dominic, St. Augustine 
<ref target="n156">[156]</ref> 
 or any other man has decreed; especially 
since things have not turned out as they expected. 
 
<lb/> 
 
The mendicants should also be relieved of preaching and hearing 
confession, except when they are called to this work by the express desire 
of bishops, parishes, congregations or the temporal authorities. Out of 
their preaching and shriving there has come nothing but hatred and envy 
between priests and monks, and great offense and hindrance to the common 
people. For this reason it should properly and deservedly cease, because it 
can well be dispensed with. 
<ref target="n157">[157]</ref> 
 It looks suspiciously as though it were not 
for nothing that the Holy Roman See has increased this army, so that the 
priests and bishops, tired of its tyranny, might not some time become too 
strong for it and begin a reformation which would not be to the liking of 
his Holiness. 
 
<lb/> 
 
At the same time the manifold divisions and differences within one and 
the same order should be abolished. These divisions have at times arisen for 
small reason and maintained themselves for still smaller, combating one 
another with unspeakable hatred and envy. 
<ref target="n158">[158]</ref> 
 Nevertheless the Christian 
faith, which can well exist without any of these distinctions, is lost by 
both sides, and a good Christian life is valued and sought after only in 
outward laws, works and forms; and this results only in the devising of 
hypocrisy and the destruction of souls, as everyone may see with his own 
eyes. 
 
<lb/> 
 
The pope must also be forbidden to found and confirm any more of these 
orders; nay, he must be commanded to abolish some of them and reduce their 
number, since the faith of Christ, which is alone the highest good and which 
exists without any orders, is in no small danger, because these many 
different works and forms easily mislead men into living for them instead of 
giving heed to the faith. Unless there are in the monasteries wise prelates, 
who preach and who concern themselves with faith more than with the rules of 
the orders, the order cannot but harm and delude simple souls who think only 
of works. 
 
<lb/> 
 
In our days, however, the prelates who have had faith and who founded the 
orders have almost all passed away. Just as in olden days among the children 
of Israel, when the fathers, who knew God's works and wonders, had passed 
away, the children, from ignorance of God's works and of faith, immediately 
became idolatrous and set up their own human works; so now, alas! these 
orders have lost the understanding of God's works and of faith, and only 
torture themselves pitifully, with labor and sorrow, in their own rules, 
laws and customs, and withal never come to a right understanding of a good 
spiritual life, as the Apostle declared when he said in 2 Timothy 3:5, 7: 
"They have the appearance of a spiritual life, yet there is nothing back of 
it; they are ever and ever learning, but they never come to a knowledge of 
what a true spiritual life is." There should be no monastery unless there 
were a spiritual prelate, learned in the Christian faith, to rule it, for no 
other kind of prelate can rule without injury and ruin, and the holier and 
better he appears to be in his outward works and life, the more injury and 
ruin he causes. 
 
<lb/> 
 
To my way of thinking it would be a necessary measure, especially in 
these perilous times of ours, that all foundations and monasteries should be 
re-established as they were at the first, in the days of the Apostles and 
for a long time afterwards, when they were all open to every man, and every 
man might remain in them as long as he pleased. For what were the 
foundations and monasteries except Christian schools in which the Scriptures 
and Christian living were taught, and people were trained to rule and to 
preach? So we read that St. Agnes 
<ref target="n159">[159]</ref> 
 went to school, and we still see the 
same practice in some of the nunneries, like that at Quedlinburg 
<ref target="n160">[160]</ref> 
 and 
others elsewhere. And in truth all monasteries and convents ought to be so 
free that God is served in them with free will and not with forced avarice. 
Afterward, however, they hedged them about with vows and turned them into a 
lifelong prison, so that these vows are thought to be of more account than 
the vows of baptism. What sort of fruit this has borne, we see, hear, read 
and learn more and more every day. 
 
<lb/> 
 
I suppose this advice of mine will be regarded as the height of 
foolishness; but I am not concerned about that just now. I advise what I 
think best; let him reject it who will! I see how the vows are kept, 
especially the vow of chastity, which has become so universal through these 
monasteries and yet is not commanded by Christ; on the contrary, it is given 
to very few to keep it, as He himself says, and St. Paul. (Matt. 19:11 ff., 
1 Cor. 7:7, Col. 2:20) I would have all men to be helped, and not have 
Christian souls caught in human, self-devised customs and laws. 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="14"> 
 
 
14. We also see how the priesthood has fallen, and how many a poor priest 
is overburdened with wife and child, and his conscience troubled, yet no one 
does anything to help him though he might easily be helped. Though pope and 
bishops may let things go as they go, and let them go to ruin if they will, 
I will save my conscience and open my month freely, whether it vex pope, 
bishops or any one else. 
Wherefore I say that according to the institution of Christ and the 
Apostles every city should have a priest or bishop, as St. Paul clearly says 
in Titus 1:6; and this priest should not be compelled to live without a 
wedded wife, but should be permitted to have one, as St. Paul says in I 
Timothy 3:2, and Titus 1:6, "A bishop should be a man who is blameless, and 
the husband of but one wedded wife, whose children are obedient and 
virtuous," etc. For with St. Paul a bishop and a priest are one and the same 
thing, as witness also St. Jerome. 
<ref target="n161">[161]</ref> 
 But of bishops as they now are; the 
Scriptures know nothing; they have been appointed by the ordinance of the 
Christian Church, that one of them may rule over many priests. 
 
<lb/> 
 
So then we clearly learn from the Apostle that it should be the custom 
for every town to choose out of the congregation 
<ref target="n162">[162]</ref> 
 a learned and pious 
citizen, entrust to him the office of the ministry, and support him at the 
expense of the community, leaving him free choice to marry or not. He should 
have with him several priests or deacons, who might also be married or not, 
as they chose, to help him rule the people of the community 
<ref target="n163">[163]</ref> 
 by means of 
preaching and the sacraments, as is still the practice in the Greek Church. 
At a later time, 
<ref target="n164">[164]</ref> 
 when there were so many persecutions and controversies 
with heretics, there were many holy fathers who of their own accord 
abstained from matrimony, to the end that they might the better devote 
themselves to study and be prepared at any time for death or for 
controversy. Then the Roman See interfered, out of sheer wantonness, and 
made a universal commandment forbidding priests to marry. 
<ref target="n165">[165]</ref> 
 This was done 
at the bidding of the devil, as St. Paul declares in I Timothy 4, "There 
shall come teachers who bring doctrines of devils, and forbid to marry." 
From this has arisen so much untold misery, occasion was given for the 
withdrawal of the Greek Church, 
<ref target="n166">[166]</ref> 
 and division, sin, shame and scandal 
were increased without end, - which is the result of everything the devil 
does. 
 
<lb/> 
 
What, then, shall we do about it? My advice is that matrimony be again 
made free, 
<ref target="n167">[167]</ref> 
 and that every one be left free choice to marry or not to 
marry. In that case, however, there must be a very different government and 
administration of Church property, the whole canon law must go to pieces and 
not many benefices find their way to Rome. 
<ref target="n168">[168]</ref> 
 I fear that greed has been a 
cause of this wretched unchaste chastity, and as a result of greed every man 
has wished to become a priest and everyone wants his son to study for the 
priesthood, not with the idea of living in chastity, for that could be done 
outside the priesthood, but of being supported in temporal things without 
care or labor, contrary to the command of God in Genesis 3:19, "In the sweat 
of thy face shalt thou eat thy bread." They have construed this to mean that 
their labor was to pray and say mass. 
 
<lb/> 
 
I am not referring here to popes, bishops, canons and monks. God has not 
instituted these offices. They have taken burdens on themselves; let them 
bear them. I would speak only of the ministry which God has instituted 
<ref target="n169">[169]</ref> 
 
and which is to rule a congregation by means of preaching and sacraments, 
whose incumbents are to live and be at home among the people. Such ministers 
should be granted liberty by a Christian council to marry, for the avoidance 
of temptation and sin. Gal. 1:8, For since God has not bound them, no one 
else ought to bind them or can bind them, even though he were an angel from 
heaven, still less if he be only a pope; and everything that the canon law 
decrees to the contrary is mere fable and idle talk. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Furthermore, I advise that henceforth neither at his consecration to the 
priesthood nor at any other time shall any one under any circumstances 
promise the bishop to live in celibacy, but shall declare to the bishop that 
he has no authority to demand such a vow, and that to demand it is the 
devil's own tyranny. 
 
<lb/> 
 
But if anyone is compelled to say or wishes to say, as do some, "so far 
as human frailty permits," 
<ref target="n170">[170]</ref> 
 let everyone frankly interpret these words 
negatively, to mean "I do not promise chastity." 
<ref target="n171">[171]</ref> 
 For human frailty does 
not permit a chaste life, 
<ref target="n172">[172]</ref> 
 but only angelic power and celestial might. 2 
Pet. 2:11. 
<ref target="n173">[173]</ref> 
 Thus he should keep his conscience free from all vows. 
 
<lb/> 
 
On the question whether those who are not yet married should marry or 
remain unmarried, I do not care to give advice either way. I leave that to 
common Christian order and to everyone's better judgment. But as regards the 
wretched multitude who now sit in shame and heaviness of conscience because 
their wives are called "priests' harlots" and their children "priests' 
children" I will not withhold my faithful counsel nor deprive them of the 
comfort which is their due, I say this boldly by my jester's right. 
<ref target="n174">[174]</ref> 
 
<lb/> 
 
You will find many a pious priest against whom no one has anything to say 
except that he is weak and has come to shame with a woman, though both 
parties may be minded with all their heart to live always together in wedded 
love and troth, if only they could do it with a clear conscience, even 
though they might have to bear public shame. Two such persons are certainly 
married before God. And I say that where they are thus minded, and so come 
to live together, they should boldly save their consciences; let him take 
and keep her as his wedded wife, and live honestly with her as her husband, 
caring nothing whether the pope will have it so or not, whether it be 
against canon law or human law. The salvation of your soul is of more 
importance than tyrannical, arbitrary, wicked laws, which are not necessary 
for salvation and are not commanded by God. Ex. 12:35 f. You should do like 
the children of Israel, who stole from the Egyptians the hire they had 
earned, or like a servant who steals from his wicked master the wages he has 
earned. In like manner steal thou from the pope thy wife and child! Let the 
man who has faith enough to venture this, boldly follow me; I shall not lead 
him astray. Though I have not the authority of a pope, I have the authority 
of a Christian to advise and help my neighbor against sins and temptations; 
and that, not without cause and reason. 
 
<lb/> 
 
First, not every priest can do without a woman, not only on account of 
the weakness of the flesh, but much more because of the necessities of the 
household. If he, then, may have a woman, and the pope grants him that, 
and yet may not have her in marriage, -- what is that but leaving a man 
and a woman alone and forbidding them to fall? It is as though one were to 
put fire and straw together and command that it shall neither smoke nor 
burn. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Second, The pope has as little power to command this, as he has to 
forbid eating, drinking, the natural movement of the bowels or growing 
fat. No one, therefore, is bound to keep it, but the pope is responsible 
for all the sins which are committed against this ordinance, for all the 
souls which are lost thereby, for all the consciences which are thereby 
confused and tortured; and therefore he has long deserved that some one 
should drive him out of the world, so many wretched souls has he strangled 
with this devil's snare; though I hope that there are many to whom God has 
been more gracious at their last hour than the pope has been in their 
life. Nothing good has ever come out of the papacy and its laws, nor ever 
will. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Third, Although the law of the pope is against it, nevertheless, when 
the estate of matrimony has been entered against the pope's law, then his 
law is at an end, and is no longer valid; for the commandment of God, 
which decrees that no one shall put man and wife asunder, takes precedence 
of the law of the pope; and the commandments of God must not be broken and 
neglected for the sake of the pope's commandment, though many mad jurists, 
in the papal interest, have devised "impediments" 
<ref target="n175">[175]</ref> 
 and have prevented, 
destroyed and confused the estate of matrimony, until by their means God's 
commandment has been altogether destroyed. To make a long story short, 
there are not in the whole "spiritual" law of the pope two lines which 
could be instructive to a pious Christian, and there are, alas! So many 
mistaken and dangerous laws that the best thing would be to make a bonfire 
of it. 
<ref target="n176">[176]</ref> 
 
<lb/> 
 
But if you say that this 
<ref target="n177">[177]</ref> 
 would give offense, and the pope must first 
grant dispensation, I reply that whatever offense is in it, is the fault of 
the Roman See, which has established such laws without right and against 
God; before God and the Scriptures it is no offense. Moreover, if the pope 
can grant dispensations from his avaricious and tyrannical laws for money's 
sake, then every Christian can grant dispensations from them -- for the sake 
of God and the salvation of souls. For Christ has set us free from all human 
laws, especially when they are opposed to God and the salvation of souls, as 
St. Paul teaches in Galatians 5:1 and 1 Corinthians 9:4 ff.; 10:23. 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="15"> 
 
15. Nor must I forget the poor convents! The evil spirit, who by human 
laws now confuses all estates in life, and has made them unbearable, has 
taken possession of certain abbots, abbesses and prelates also, and causes 
them so to govern their brethren and sisters as to send them the more 
speedily to hell, and make them lead a wretched life even here; for such is 
the log of all the devil's martyrs. That is to say, they have reserved to 
themselves in confession, all, or at least some, of the mortal sins which 
are secret, so that no brother, on his obedience and on pain of the ban, can 
absolve another from these sins. 
<ref target="n178">[178]</ref> 
 Now we do not always find angels 
everywhere, but we find also flesh and blood, which suffers all bannings and 
threatenings rather than confess secret sins to the prelates and the 
appointed confessors. Thus they go to the sacrament with such consciences 
that they become "irregular" 
<ref target="n179">[179]</ref> 
 and all sorts of other terrible things. O 
blind shepherds! O mad prelates! O ravening wolves! 
 
<lb/> 
 
To this I say: If a sin is public or notorious, then it is proper that 
the prelate alone should punish it, and of these sins only and no others he 
may make exceptions, and reserve them to himself over secret sins he has no 
authority, even though they were the worst sins that are or ever can be 
found, and if the prelate makes exceptions of these sins, he is a tyrant, 
for he has no such right and is interfering in the judgment of God. 
 
<lb/> 
 
And so I advise these children, brethren and sisters: If your superiors 
are unwilling to grant you permission to confess your secret sins to 
whomever you wish, then take them to whatever brother or sister you will and 
confess them, receive absolution, and then go and do whatever you wish and 
ought to do; only believe firmly that you are absolved, and nothing more is 
needed. And do not allow yourself to be troubled by ban, "irregularity," or 
any of the other things they threaten; these things are valid only in the 
case of public or notorious sins which one is unwilling to confess; they do 
not affect you at all. Why do you try by your threatenings, O blind prelate, 
to prevent secret sins? Let go what you cannot publicly prove, so that God's 
judgment and grace may also have its work in your subjects! He did not give 
them so entirely into your hands as to let them go entirely out of His own! 
Nay, what you have under your rule is but the smaller part. Let your statues 
be statutes, but do not exalt them to heaven, to the judgment-seat of God. 
 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="16"> 
 
 
16. It were also necessary to abolish all anniversary mortuary and "soul" 
masses, 
<ref target="n180">[180]</ref> 
 or at least to diminish their number, since we plainly see that 
they have become nothing but a mockery, by which God is deeply angered, and 
that their only purpose is money-getting, gorging and drunkenness. What kind 
of pleasure should God have in such a miserable gabbing or wretched vigils 
and masses, which is neither reading nor praying, and even when prayed, 
<ref target="n181">[181]</ref> 
 
they are performed not for God's sake and out of willing love, but for 
money's sake and because they are a bounden duty. Now it is not possible 
that any work not done out of willing love can please God or obtain anything 
from Him. And so it is altogether Christian to abolish, or at least 
diminish, everything which we see growing into an abuse, and which angers 
rather than reconciles God. It would please me more -- nay, it would be more 
acceptable to God and far better -- that a foundation, church or monastery 
should put all its anniversary masses and vigils together, and on one day, 
with hearty sincerity, devotion and faith, hold a true vigil and mass for 
all its benefactors, rather than hold them by the thousand every year, for 
each benefactor a special mass, without this devotion and faith. O dear 
Christians! God cares not for much praying, but for true praying! Nay, He 
condemns the many and long prayers, and says in Matthew 6:7; 23:14, they 
will only earn more punishment thereby. But avarice, which cannot trust God, 
brings such things to pass, fearing that otherwise it must die of hunger! 
 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="17"> 
 
 
17. Certain of the penalties or punishments of the canon law should also 
be abolished, especially the interdict,<ref target="n182">[182]</ref> which 
is, beyond all doubt, an invention of the evil Spirit. It is not a devil's 
work to try to atone for 
one sin with many greater sins? And yet, to put God's Word and worship to 
silence, or to do away with them, is a greater sin than strangling twenty 
popes at once, and far greater than killing a priest or keeping back some 
Church property. This is another of the tender virtues taught in the 
"spiritual law." For one of the reasons why this law is called "spiritual" 
is because it comes from the Spirit; not, however, from the Holy Spirit, but 
from the evil spirit. 
 
<lb/> 
 
The ban 
<ref target="n183">[183]</ref> 
 is to be used in no case except where the Scriptures prescribe 
its use, i.e., against those who do not hold the true faith, or who live in 
open sin; it is not to be used for the sake of temporal possessions. But now 
it is the other way around. Everyone believes and lives as he pleases, most 
of all those who use the ban to plunder and defame other people, and all the 
bans are now laid only on account of temporal possessions, for which we have 
no one to thank but the holy "spiritual lawlessness." 
<ref target="n184">[184]</ref> 
 Of this I have 
previously said more in the Discourse. 
<ref target="n185">[185]</ref> 
 
<lb/> 
 
The other punishments and penalties, -- suspension, irregularity, 
aggravation, reaggravation, deposition, lightnings, thunderings, cursings, 
damnings and the rest of these devices, -- should be buried ten fathoms deep 
in the earth, so that there should be neither name nor memory of them left 
on earth. The evil spirit, who has been let loose by the "spiritual law" has 
brought this terrible plague and misery into the heavenly kingdom of the 
holy Church, and has accomplished by it nothing else than the destruction 
and hindrance of souls, so that the word of Christ may well be applied to 
them 
<ref target="n186">[186]</ref> 
; Matthew 23:13: "Woe unto you scribes! Ye have taken upon your the 
authority to teach, and ye shut up the kingdom of heaven against men. Ye go 
not in yourselves, and ye suffer not them that are entering." 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="18"> 
 
 
18. All festivals 
<ref target="n187">[187]</ref> 
 should be abolished, and Sunday alone retained. If 
it were desired, however, to retain the festivals of Our Lady and of the 
greater saints, they should be transferred to Sunday, or observed only by a 
morning mass, after which all the rest of the day should be a working-day. 
The reason is this: The feast-days are now abused by drinking, gaming, 
idleness and all manner of sins, so that on the holy days we anger God more 
than on other days, and have altogether turned things around; the hold days 
are not holy and the working days are holy, and not only is no service done 
to God and His saints by the many holy days, but rather great dishonor. 
There are, indeed, some mad prelates who think they are doing a good work if 
they make a festival in honor of St. Ottilia or St. Barbara or some other 
saint, according to the promptings of their blind devotion; but they would 
be doing a far better work if they honored the saint by turning a 
saint's-day into a working day. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Over and above the spiritual injury, the common man receives two material 
injuries from this practice, i.e., he neglects his work and he spends more 
than at other times; nay, he also weakens his body and unfits it for work. 
We see this every day, yet no one thinks to make it better. We ought not to 
consider whether or not the pope has instituted the feasts, and whether we 
must have dispensation and permission to omit them. If a thing is opposed to 
God, and harmful to man in body and soul, any community, 
<ref target="n188">[188]</ref> 
 council 
<ref target="n189">[189]</ref> 
 or 
government has not only the right to abolish it and put a stop to it, 
without the will or knowledge or pope or bishop, but they are bound on their 
souls' salvation to prevent it, even against the will of pope and bishop, 
thought these ought to be themselves the first to forbid it. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Above all, we ought utterly to abolish the consecration days, 
<ref target="n190">[190]</ref> 
 since 
they have become nothing else than taverns, fairs and gaming places, 
<ref target="n191">[191]</ref> 
 and 
serve only to the increase of God's dishonor and to the damnation of souls. 
All the pretence about the custom having had the custom having had a good 
beginning and being a good work is of no avail. Did not God Himself set 
aside His own law, which He had given from heaven, when it was perverted and 
abused? And does He not still daily overturn what He has appointed and 
destroy what He has made, because of such perversion and abuse? As it is 
written of Him in Psalm 18:27, "With the perverted Thou wilt show Thyself 
perverse." 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="19"> 
 
 
19. The grades or degrees within which marriage is forbidden should be 
changed, as, for instance, the sponsorships and the third and fourth degrees 
and if the pope can grant dispensation in these matters for money and for 
the sake of the shameful traffic, 
<ref target="n192">[192]</ref> 
 then every parish priest may give the 
same dispensations gratis and for the salvation of souls. Yea, would to God 
that all the things which we must buy at Rome to free ourselves from that 
money-snare, the canon law, -- such things as indulgences, letters or 
indulgence, "butter-letters," 
<ref target="n193">[193]</ref> 
 "mass-letters," 
<ref target="n194">[194]</ref> 
 and all the rest of 
the <hi rend="italic">confessionalia</hi> 
<ref target="n195">[195]</ref> 
 and knaveries for the sale at Rome, with which 
the poor folk are deceived and robbed of their money; would to God, I say, 
that any priest could, without payment, do and omit all these things! For if 
the pope has the authority to sell his snares for money and his spiritual 
nets (I should say laws), 
<ref target="n196">[196]</ref> 
 surely any priest has much more authority to 
vrend his nets and for God's sake to tread them under foot. But if he has not 
this right, neither has the pope the right to sell them at his shameful 
fair. 
<ref target="n197">[197]</ref> 
 
<lb/> 
 
This is the place to say too that the fasts should be matters of liberty, 
and all sorts of food made free, as the Gospel makes them. (Matthew 15:11) 
For at Rome they themselves laugh at the fasts, making us foreigners eat the 
oil with which they would not grease their shoes, and afterwards selling us 
liberty to eat butter and all sorts of other things; yet the holy Apostle 
says that in all these things we already have liberty through the Gospel. (1 
Cor. 10:25 ff.) But they have caught us with their canon law and stolen our 
rights from us, so that we may have to buy them back with money. Thus they 
have made our consciences so timid and shy that it is no longer easy to 
preach about this liberty because the common people take such great offense, 
thinking it is a greater sin to eat butter than to lie, to swear, or even to 
live unchastely. Nevertheless, what men have decreed, that is the work of 
man; put it where you will, 
<ref target="n198">[198]</ref> 
 nothing good ever comes out of it. 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="20"> 
 
 
20. The forest chapels and rustic churches 
<ref target="n199">[199]</ref> 
 must be utterly destroyed, 
-- those, namely, to which the recent pilgrimages have been directed, -- 
Wilsnack, 
<ref target="n200">[200]</ref> 
 Sternberg, 
<ref target="n201">[201]</ref> 
 Trier, 
<ref target="n202">[202]</ref> 
 the Grimmenthal, 
<ref target="n203">[203]</ref> 
 and now 
Regensburg 
<ref target="n204">[204]</ref> 
 and a goodly number of others. Oh, what a terrible and heavy 
account will the bishops have to render, who permit this devilish deceit and 
receive its profits. 
<ref target="n205">[205]</ref> 
 They should be the first to forbid it, and yet they 
think it a divine and holy thing, and do not see that it is the devil's 
doing, to strengthen avarice, to create a false, feigned faith, to weaken 
the parish churches, to multiply taverns and harlotry, to waste money and 
labor, and to lead the poor folk by the nose. If they had only read the 
Scriptures to as good purpose as they have read their damnable canon law, 
they would know well how to deal with this matter. 
 
<lb/> 
 
That miracles are done at these places does not help things, for the evil 
spirit can do miracles, as Christ has told us in Matthew 24:24. If they took 
the matter seriously and forbade this sort of thing, the miracles would 
quickly come to an end; (Acts 5:39) on the other hand, if the thing were of 
God their prohibition would not hinder it. And if there were no other 
evidence that it is not of God, this would be enough, -- that people run to 
these places in excited crowds, as though they had lost their reason, like 
herds of cattle; for this cannot possible be the God. Moreover, God has 
commanded nothing of all this; there is neither obedience nor merit in it; 
the bishops, therefore, should boldly step in and keep the folk away. For 
what is not commanded -- and is concerned for self rather than for the 
commands of God -- that is surely the devil himself. Then, too, the parish 
churches receive injury, because they are held in smaller honor. In short, 
these things are signs of great unbelief among the people; if they truly 
believed, they would have all that they need in their own churches, for to 
them they are commanded to go. 
 
<lb/> 
 
But what shall I say? Every one 
<ref target="n206">[206]</ref> 
 plans only how he may establish and 
maintain such a place of pilgrimage in his diocese and is not at all 
concerned to have the people believe and live aright; the rulers are like 
the people; one blind man leads another. (Matthew 13:14) Nay, where 
pilgrimages are not successful, they begin to canonize saints, 
<ref target="n207">[207]</ref> 
 not in 
honor of the saints -- for they are sufficiently honored without 
canonization -- but in order to draw crowds and bring in money. Pope and 
bishop help along; it rains indulgences; there is always money enough for 
that. But for what God has commanded no one provides; no one runs after 
these things; there is no money for them. Alas, that we should be so blind! 
We not only give the devil his own way in his tricks, but we even strengthen 
him in his wantonness and increase his pranks. I would that the dear saints 
were left in peace, and the poor folk not lead astray! What spirit has given 
the pope the authority to canonize the saints? Who tells him whether they 
are saints or not? Are there not already sins enough on earth, that we too 
must tempt God, interfere in His judgment and set up the dear saints as 
lures for money? 
 
<lb/> 
 
Therefore I advise that the saints be left to canonize themselves. Yea, 
it is God alone who should canonize them. And let every man stay in his own 
parish, where he finds more than in all the shrines of pilgrimage, even 
though all the shrines were one. Here we find baptism, the sacrament, 
preaching and our neighbor, and these are greater things, than all the 
saints in heaven, for it is by God's Word and sacrament that they have all 
been made saints. So long as we despise such great things God is just in the 
wrathful judgment by which He appoints the devil to lead us hither and 
thither, to establish pilgrimages, to found churches and chapels, to secure 
the canonization of saints, and to do other such fool's-works, by which we 
depart from true faith into new, false misbelief. This is what he did in 
olden times to the people of Israel, when he led them away from the temple 
at Jerusalem to countless other places, though he did it in the name of God 
and under the plausible guise of holiness, though all the prophets preached 
against it and were persecuted for so doing. But now no one preaches against 
it, perhaps for fear that pope, priests and monks would persecute him also. 
In this way St. Antoninus of Florence 
<ref target="n208">[208]</ref> 
 and certain others must now be 
made saints and canonized, that their holiness, which would otherwise have 
served only for the glory of God and as a good example, may serve to bring 
in fame and money. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Although the canonizing of saints may have been good in olden times, it 
is not good now; just as many other things were good in olden times and are 
now scandalous and injurious, such as feast-days, church-treasures and 
church-adornment. For it is evident that through the canonizing of saints 
neither God's glory nor the improvement of Christians is sought, but only 
money and glory, in that one church wants to be something more and have 
something more than others, and would be sorry if another had the same thing 
and its advantage were common property. So entirely, in these last, evil 
days, have spiritual goods been misused and applied to the gaining of 
temporal goods, that everything, even God Himself, has been forced into the 
service of avarice. And even these special advantages lead only to 
dissensions, divisions and pride, in that the churches, differing from one 
another, hold each other in contempt, and exalt themselves one above 
another, though all the gifts which God bestows are the common and equal 
property of all churches and should only serve the cause of unity. The pope, 
too, is glad for the present state of affairs; he would be sorry if all 
Christians were equal and were at one. 
 
<lb/> 
 
This is the place to speak of the church licenses, bulls and other things 
which the pope sells at his flaying-place in Rome. We should either abolish 
them or disregard them, or at least make them the common property of all 
churches. For if he sells or gives away licenses and privileges, 
indulgences, graces, advantages, faculties 
<ref target="n209">[209]</ref> 
 to Wittenberg, to Halle, to 
Venice and, above, all to his own Rome, why does he not give these things to 
all churches alike? Is he not bound to do for all Christians, gratis and for 
God's sake, everything that he can, and even to shed his blood for them? 
Tell me, then, why he gives or sells to one church and not to another? Or 
must the accursed money make, in the eyes of His Holiness, so great a 
difference among Christians, who all have the same baptism, Word, faith, 
Christ, God and all things? (Eph. 4:4 f.) Are we to be blind while we have 
eyes to see, fools while we have our reason, that they expect us to worship 
such greed, knavery and humbug? He is a shepherd, -- yes, so long as you 
have money, and no longer! And yet they are not ashamed of their knavery, 
leading us hither and yon with their bulls! Their one concern is the 
accursed money, and nothing else! 
 
<lb/> 
 
My advice is this: If such fool's-work cannot be abolished, then every 
pious Christian man should open his eyes, and not be misled by the 
hypocritical Roman bulls and seals, stay at home in his own church and be 
content with his baptism, his Gospel, his faith, his Christ and with God, 
Who is everywhere the same; and let the pope remain a blind leader of the 
blind. (Matt. 15:4) Neither angel nor pope can give you as much as God gives 
you in your parish-church. Nay, the pope leads you away from the gifts of 
God, which you have without pay, to his gifts, which you must buy; and he 
have without pay, to his gifts, which you must buy; and he gives you 
lead 
<ref target="n210">[210]</ref> 
 for gold, hide for meat, the string for the purse, wax for honey, 
words for goods, the letter for the spirit. You see this before your very 
eyes, but you are unwilling to notice it. If you are to ride to heaven on 
his wax and parchment, your chariot will soon go to pieces, and you will 
fall into hell, not in God's name! 
 
<lb/> 
 
Let this be your fixed rule: What you must buy from the pope is neither 
good nor of God; for what is from God, to wit, the Gospel and the works of 
God; for what is from God, to wit, the Gospel and the works of God, is not 
only given without money, but the whole world is punished and damned because 
it has not been willing to receive it as a free gift. We have deserved of 
God that we should be so deceived, because we have despised His holy Word 
and the grace of baptism, as St. Paul says: 2 Thess. 2:11 f.: "God shall 
send a strong delusion upon all those who have not received the truth to 
their salvation, to the end that they may believe and follow after lies and 
knavery," which serves them right. 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="21"> 
 
 
21. One of our greatest necessities is the abolition of all begging 
throughout Christendom. Among Christians no one ought to go begging! It 
would also be easy to make a law, if only we had the courage and the serious 
intention, to the effect that every city should provide for its own poor, 
and admit no foreign beggars by whatever name they might be called, whether 
pilgrims or mendicant monks. Every city could support its own poor, and if 
it were too small, the people in the surrounding villages also should be 
exhorted to contribute, since in any case they have to feed so many 
vagabonds and knaves in the guise of mendicants. In this way, too, it could 
be known who were really poor and who not. 
 
<lb/> 
 
There would have to be an overseer or warden who knew all the poor and 
informed the city council or the priests what they needed; or some other 
better arrangement might be made. In my judgment there is no other business 
in which so much knavery and deceit are practiced as in begging, and yet it 
could all be easily abolished. Moreover, this free and universal begging 
hurts the common people. I have considered that each of the five or six 
mendicant orders 
<ref target="n211">[211]</ref> 
 visits the same place more than six or seven times 
every year; besides these there are the common beggars, the 
"stationaries" 
<ref target="n212">[212]</ref> 
 and the palmers, 
<ref target="n213">[213]</ref> 
 so that it has been reckoned that 
every town is laid under tribute about sixty times a year, not counting what 
is given to the government in taxes, imposts and assessments, what is stolen 
by the Roman See with its wares, and what is uselessly consumed. Thus it 
seems to me one of God's greatest miracles that we can continue to support 
ourselves. 
 
<lb/> 
 
To be sure, some think that in this way 
<ref target="n214">[214]</ref> 
 the poor would not be so well 
provided for and that not so many great stone houses and monasteries would 
be built. This I can well believe. Nor is it necessary. He who wishes to be 
poor should not be rich; and if he wishes to be rich, let him put his hand 
to the plow and seek his riches in the earth! It is enough if the poor are 
decently cared for, so that they do not die of hunger or of cold. It is not 
fitting that one man should live in idleness on another's labor, or be rich 
and live comfortably at the cost of another's discomfort, according to the 
present perverted custom; for St. Paul says, 2 Thess. 3:10: "If a man will 
not work, neither shall he eat." God has not decreed that any man shall live 
from another's goods save only the priests, who rule and preach, and these 
because of their spiritual labor, as Paul says in 1 Corinthians 9:14, and 
Christ also says to the Apostles, Luke 10:7: "Every laborer is worthy of his 
hire." 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="22"> 
 
 
22. It is also to be feared that the many masses <ref 
target="n215">[215]</ref> which are endowed in the 
foundation sand monasteries are not only of little use, but greatly arouse 
the wrath of God. It would therefore be profitable not to endow any more, 
but rather to abolish many that are already endowed, since we see that they 
are regarded only as sacrifices and good works, 
<ref target="n216">[216]</ref> though they are really 
sacraments, just like baptism and penance,<ref 
target="n217">[217]</ref> which profit only those who 
receive them, and no others. But now the custom has crept in, that masses 
are said for the living and the dead, and all hopes are built upon them; for 
this reason so many of them have been founded and the present state of 
affairs has come about. 
 
<lb/> 
 
My proposal is perhaps too novel an daring, especially for those who fear 
that through the discontinuance of these masses their trade and livelihood 
may be destroyed, and so I must refrain from saying more about it until we 
have come back to a correct understanding of what the mass is and what it is 
good for. These many years, alas, it has been made a trade practiced for a 
temporal livelihood, so that I would henceforth advise a man to become a 
shepherd or to seek some other trade rather than become a shepherd or to 
seek some other trade rather than become a priest or a monk, unless he first 
knows well what it is to celebrate mass. 
 
<lb/> 
 
I am not speaking, however, of the old foundations and cathedrals, which 
were doubtless established in order that the children of the nobility 
(since, according to the customs of the German nation not all of them can 
become heirs or rulers), might be provided for in these foundations, and 
there be free to serve God, to study, to become scholars and to make 
scholars. But I am speaking of the new foundations, which have been 
established only for the saying of prayers and masses; for after their 
example, even the old foundations have been burdened with like prayers and 
masses, so that they are of little or no profit; though it is also of God's 
grace that they too come at last, as they deserve, to the dregs, i.e., to 
the wailing of organs and of choral singers, and to dead, cold masses, by 
which the incomes of the worldly endowments are gotten and spent. Such 
things pope, bishops and doctors should examine and proscribe: but now it is 
they who are most given to them. They let everything pass, if only it brings 
in money; one blind man is always leading another. This is the work of 
avarice and of the spiritual law. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Again, no one person should be allowed any longer to hold more than one 
canonry or prebend. He must be content with a modest position, that some one 
else may also have something. This would do away with the excuses of those 
who say that they must hold more than one such office to "maintain a proper 
station." A "proper station" might be so broadly interpreted that a whole 
land would not be enough to maintain it! Moreover avarice and veiled 
distrust of God assuredly go with it, so that what is alleged to be the need 
of "a proper station" is often nothing else than avarice and distrust. 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="23"> 
 
 
23. Sodalities, 
<ref target="n218">[218]</ref> 
 indulgences, letters of indulgence, 
"butter-letter," 
<ref target="n219">[219]</ref> 
 mass-letters, 
<ref target="n220">[220]</ref> 
 dispensations, and everything else of 
the sort, are to be drowned and destroyed. There is nothing good in them. If 
the pope has the power to grant you dispensation to eat butter and to absent 
yourself from mass, then he ought also be able to leave this power to the 
priests, from whom, indeed, he has no right to take it. I speak especially 
of those fraternities in which indulgences, masses and good works are 
portioned out. Dear friend, in your baptism you entered into a fraternity 
with Christ, all the angels, saints and Christians on earth. Hold to this 
fraternity and live up to its demands, and you have fraternities enough. The 
others -- let them glitter as they will -- are but as counters compared with 
guldens. But if there were a fraternity which contributed money to feed the 
poor or to help somebody in some other way, such a one would be good, and 
would have its indulgence and its merit in heaven. Now, however, they have 
become excuses for gluttony and drunkenness.<ref target="n221">[221]</ref> 
 
<lb/> 
 
Above all, we should drive out of German lands the papal legates with 
their "faculties," 
<ref target="n222">[222]</ref> 
 which they sell us for large sums of money, though 
that is sheer knavery. For example, in return for money they legalize unjust 
gains, dissolve oaths, vows and agreements, break and teach men to break the 
faith and fealty which they have pledged to one another; and they say the 
pope has the authority to do this. It is the evil Spirit who bids them say 
this. Thus they sell us a doctrine of devils, and take money for teaching us 
sin and leading us to hell. 
 
<lb/> 
 
If there were no other evil wiles to prove the pope the true Antichrist, 
yet this one thing were enough to prove it. Hearest thou this, O pope, not 
most holy, but most sinful? O that God from heaven would soon destroy thy 
throne and sink it in the abyss of hell! Who hath given thee authority to 
exalt thyself above thy God, to break and to loose His commandments, and to 
teach Christians, especially the German nation, praised in all history for 
its nobility, its constancy and fidelity, to be inconstant, perjurers, 
traitors, profligates, faithless? God hath commanded to keep oath and faith 
even with an enemy, and thou undertakest to loose this His commandment, and 
ordainest in thine heretical, antichristian decretals that thou hast His 
power. Thus through thy throat and through thy pen the wicked Satan doth lie 
as he hath never lied before. O Christ, my Lord, look down, let the day of 
thy judgment break, and destroy the devil's nest at Rome! Here sitteth the 
man of whom St. Paul hath said (2 Thess. 2:3 f.) that he shall exalt himself 
above Thee, sit in Thy Church and set himself up as God, -- the man of sin 
and the son of perdition! What else is the papal power than only the 
teaching and increasing of sin and evil, the leading of souls to damnation 
under Thy name and guise? 
 
<lb/> 
 
In olden times the children of Israel had to keep the oath which they had 
unwittingly been deceived into giving to their enemies, the Gibeonites, and 
King Zedekiah was miserably lost, with all his people, because he broke this 
oath to the King of Babylon. (Josh. 9:19 ff.; 2 Kings 24:20; 25:4 ff.) Even 
among us, a hundred years ago, that fine king of Hungary and Poland, 
Wladislav, 
<ref target="n223">[223]</ref> 
 was slain by the Turk, with so many noble people, because he 
allowed himself to be deceived by the papal legate and cardinal, and broke 
the good and advantageous treaty which he had sworn with the Turk. The pious 
Emperor Sigismund had no good fortune after the Council of Constance, when 
allowed the knaves to break the safe-conduct which had been given to John 
Hus and Jerome, 
<ref target="n224">[224]</ref> 
 and all the trouble between us and the Bohemians was the 
consequence. Even in our own times, God help us! How much Christian blood 
has been shed over the oath and alliance which Pope Julius made between the 
Emperor Maximilian and King Louis of France, 
<ref target="n225">[225]</ref> 
 and afterwards broke? How 
could I tell all the troubles which the popes have stirred up by the 
devilish presumption with which they annul oaths and vows which have been 
made between great princes, making a jest of these things, and taking money 
for it. I have hopes that the judgment day is at the door; nothing can 
possibly be worse than the Roman See. He suppresses God's commandment, he 
exalts his own commandment over it; if he is not Antichrist, then let some 
one else tell who he can be! But more of this another time, and better. 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="24"> 
 
 
24. It is high time that we seriously and honestly consider the case of 
the Bohemians, 
<ref target="n226">[226]</ref> 
 and come into union with them so that the terrible 
slander, hatred and envy on both sides may cease. As befits my folly, I 
shall be the first to submit an opinion on this subject, with due deference 
to every one who may understand the case better than I. 
 
<lb/> 
 
First, We must honestly confess the truth, stop justifying ourselves, and 
grant the Bohemians that John Hus and Jerome of Prague were burned at 
Constance in violation of the papal, Christian, imperial safe-conduct and 
oath; whereby God's commandment was sinned against and the Bohemians were 
given ample cause for bitterness; and although they ought to have been 
perfect and to have patiently endured this great injustice and disobedience 
of God on our part, nevertheless they were not bound to approve of it and to 
acknowledge that it was well done. Nay, even to-day they should give up life 
and limb rather than confess that it is right to violate an imperial, papal 
Christian safe-conduct, and faithlessly to act contrary to it. So then, 
although it is the impatience of the Bohemians which is at fault, yet the 
pope and his followers are still more to blame for all the trouble, error 
and loss of souls that have followed upon that council. 
 
<lb/> 
 
I have no desire to pass judgment at this time upon John Hus's articles 
or to defend his errors, though I have not yet found any errors in his 
writings, and I am quite prepared to believe that it was neither fair 
judgment nor honest condemnation which was passed by those who, in their 
faithless dealing, violated a Christian safe-conduct and a commandment of 
God. Beyond doubt they were possessed rather by the evil spirit than by the 
Holy Spirit. No one will doubt that the Holy Spirit does not act contrary to 
the commandment of God; and no one is so ignorant as not to know that the 
violation of faith and of a safe-conduct is contrary to the commandment of 
God, even though they had been promised to the devil himself, still more 
when the promise was made to a mere heretic. It is also quite evident that 
such a promise was made to John Hus and the Bohemians and was not kept, but 
that he was burned in spite of it. I do not wish, however, to make John Hus 
a saint or a martyr, as do some of the Bohemians, though I confess that 
injustice was done him, and that his books and doctrines were unjustly 
condemned; for the judgments of God are secret and terrible, and no one save 
God alone should undertake to reveal or utter them. 
 
<lb/> 
 
All I wish to say is this: though he were never so wicked a heretic, 
nevertheless he was burned unjustly and against God's commandment, and the 
Bohemians should not be forced to approve of such conduct, or else we shall 
never come into unity. Not obstinacy but the open admission of truth must 
make us one. It is useless to pretend, as was done at the time, that a 
safe-conduct given to a heretic need not be kept. 
<ref target="n227">[227]</ref> 
 That is as much as to 
say that God's commandments are not to be kept to the end that God's 
commandments may be kept. The devil made them mad and foolish, so that they 
did not know what they were saying or doing. God has commanded that a 
safe-conduct shall be kept. This commandment we should keep though the world 
fall. How much more, when it is only a question of freeing a heretic! We 
should vanquish heretics with books, not with burning; for so the ancient 
fathers did. If it were a science to vanquish the heretics with fire, then 
the hangmen would be the most learned doctors on earth; we should no longer 
need to study, but he who overcame another by force might burn him at the 
stake. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Second, The emperor and the princes should send to the Bohemians some 
pious and sensible bishops and scholars; but by no means a cardinal or papal 
legate or inquisitor, for those people are utter ignoramuses as regards 
things Christian; they seek not the welfare of souls but, like all the 
pope's hypocrites, only their own power, profit and glory' indeed, they were 
the prime movers in this miserable business at Constance. The men thus sent 
into Bohemia should inform themselves about the faith of the Bohemians, and 
whether it be possible to unite all their sects. Then the pope should, for 
their souls' sake, lay aside his supremacy for the time being, and, 
according to the decree of the most Christian Council of Nicaea, 
<ref target="n228">[228]</ref> 
 allow 
the Bohemians to choose one of their number to be Archbishop of Prague, 
<ref target="n229">[229]</ref> 
 
and he should be confirmed by the bishop of Olmutz in Moravia, or the bishop 
of Gran in Hungary, or the bishop of Gnesen in Poland, or the bishop of 
Magdeburg in Germany. 
<ref target="n230">[230]</ref> 
 It will be enough if he is confirmed by one or two 
of these, as was the custom in the time of St. Cyprian. 
<ref target="n231">[231]</ref> 
 The pope has no 
right to oppose such an arrangement, and if he does oppose it, he becomes a 
wolf and a tyrant; no one should follow him and his ban should be met with a 
counter-ban. 
 
<lb/> 
 
If, however, it were desired, in honor of the See of St. Peter, to do 
this with the pope's consent, I should be satisfied, provided it does not 
cost the Bohemians a heller and the pope does not bind them at all nor make 
them subject to his tyrannies by oaths and obligations, as he does all other 
bishops, in despite of God and of justice. If he will not be satisfied with 
the honor of having his consent asked, then let them not bother any more 
about him 
<ref target="n232">[232]</ref> 
 and his rights, laws and tyrannies; let the election suffice, 
and let the blood of all the souls which are endangered cry out against him, 
for no one should consent to injustice; it is enough to have offered tyranny 
an honor. If it cannot be otherwise, then an election and approval by the 
common people can even now be quite as valid as a confirmation by a tyrant; 
but I hope this will not be necessary. Some of the Romans or the good 
bishops and scholars will sometime mare and oppose papal tyranny. 
 
<lb/> 
 
I would also advise against compelling them to abolish both kinds in the 
sacrament, 
<ref target="n233">[233]</ref> 
 since that is neither unchristian nor heretical, but they 
should be allowed to retain their own practice, if they wish. Yet the new 
bishop should be careful that no discord arise because of such a practice is 
wrong; 
<ref target="n234">[234]</ref> 
 just as it ought not to cause dissension that the clergy differ 
from the laity in manner of life and in dress. In like manner if they were 
unwilling to receive the Roman canon law, they should not be forced to do 
so, but we should first make sure that they live in accordance with faith 
and with the Scriptures. For Christian faith and life can well exist without 
the intolerable laws of the pope, nay, they cannot well exist unless there 
be fewer of these Roman laws, or none at all. In baptism we have become free 
and have been made subject to God's Word only; why should any man ensnare us 
in his words? As St. Paul says, 1 Cor. 7:23 and Gal. 5:1: "Ye have become 
free, be not servants of men," i.e. of those who rule with man-made laws. 
 
 
<lb/> 
 
If I knew that the Picards 
<ref target="n235">[235]</ref> 
 held no other error touching the sacrament 
of the altar except that they believe that the bread and wine are present in 
their true nature, but that the body and blood of Christ are truly present 
under them, then I would not condemn them, but would let them enter the 
obedience of the bishop of Prague. For it is not an article of faith that 
bread and wine are not essentially and naturally in the sacrament, but this 
is an opinion of St. Thomas 
<ref target="n236">[236]</ref> 
 and the pope. On the other hand, it is an 
article of faith that in the natural bread and wine the true natural body 
and blood of Christ are present. 
<ref target="n237">[237]</ref> 
 And so we should tolerate the opinions 
of both sides until they come to an agreement, because there is no danger in 
believing that bread is there or is not there. For we have to endure many 
practices and ordinances so long as they are not harmful to faith. On the 
other hand, if they had a different faith, 
<ref target="n238">[238]</ref> 
 I would rather have them 
outside the Church; yet I would teach them the truth. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Whatever other errors and schisms might be discovered in Bohemia should 
be tolerated until the archbishop had been restored and had gradually 
brought all the people together again in one common doctrine. They will 
assuredly never be united by force, nor by defiance, nor by haste; it will 
take time and forbearance. Had not even Christ to tarry with His disciples a 
long while and bear with their unbelief, until they believed His 
resurrections? If they but had again a regular bishop and church order, 
without Roman tyranny, I could hope that things would soon be better. 
 
<lb/> 
 
The restoration of the temporal goods which formerly belonged to the 
Church should not be too strictly demanded, but since we are Christians and 
each is bound to help the rest, it is in our power, for the sake of unity, 
to give them these things and let them keep them in the sight of God and 
men. For Christ says, Matt. 18:19 f.: "Where two are at one with each other 
on earth, there am I in the midst of them." Would to God that on both sides 
we were working toward this unity, offering our hands to one another in 
brotherly humility, and not standing stubbornly on our powers or rights! 
Love is greater and more necessary than the papacy at Rome, for there can be 
papacy without love and love without papacy. 
 
<lb/> 
 
With this counsel I shall have done what I could. If the pope or his 
followers hinder it, (Phil. 2:4), they shall render an account for seeking 
their own things rather than the things of their neighbor, contrary to the 
love of God. The pope ought to give up his papacy and all his possessions 
and honors, if he could by that means save one soul; but now he would let 
the world go to destruction rather than yield a hair's-breadth of his 
presumptuous authority. And yet he would be the "most holy"! Here my 
responsibility ends. 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="25"> 
 
 
 
25. The universities also need a good, thorough reformation -- I must say 
it no matter whom it vexes -- for everything which the papacy has instituted 
and ordered is directed only towards the increasing of sin and error. What 
else are the universities, if their present condition remains unchanged, 
than as the book of Maccabees says, 2 Macc. 4:9, 12: <foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">Gymnasia Epheborum 
et Graecae gloriae</hi></foreign>, 
<ref target="n239">[239]</ref> 
 in which loose living prevails, the Holy 
Scriptures and the Christian faith are little taught, and the blind, heathen 
master Aristotle 
<ref target="n240">[240]</ref> 
 rules alone, even more than Christ. In this regard my 
advice would be that Aristotle's <hi rend="italic">Physics</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Metaphysics</hi>, <hi rend="italic">On 
the Soul</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Ethics</hi>, which have hitherto been thought his best 
books, should be altogether discarded, together with all the rest of his 
books which boast of treating the things of nature, although nothing can be 
learned from the either of the things of nature or the things of the Spirit. 
Moreover no one has so far understood his meaning, and many souls have been 
burdened with profitless labor and study, at the cost of much precious time. 
I venture to say that any potter has more knowledge of nature than is 
written in these books. It grieves me to the heart that this damned, 
conceited, rascally heathen has with his false words deluded and made fools 
of so many of the best Christians. God has sent him as a plague upon us for 
our sins. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Why, this wretched man, in his best book, <hi rend="italic">On the Soul</hi>, teaches 
that the soul dies with the body, although many have tried with vain words 
to save his reputation. As though we had not the Holy Scriptures, in which 
we are abundantly instructed about all things, and of them Aristotle had not 
the faintest inkling! And yet this dead heathen has conquered and obstructed 
and almost suppressed the books of the living God, so that when I think of 
this miserable business I can believe nothing else than that the evil spirit 
has introduced the study of Aristotle. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Again, his book on <hi rend="italic">Ethics</hi> is the worst of all books. It flatly 
opposes divine grace and all Christian virtues, and yet it is considered one 
of his best works. Away with such books! Keep them away from all Christians! 
Let no one accuse me of exaggeration, or of condemning what I do not 
understand! My dear friend, I know well whereof I speak. I know my Aristotle 
as well as you or the likes of you. I have lectured on him 
<ref target="n241">[241]</ref> 
 and heard 
lectures on him, and I understand him better than do St. Thomas or 
Scotus. 
<ref target="n242">[242]</ref> 
 This I can say without pride, and if necessary I can prove it. I 
care not that so many great minds have wearied themselves over him for so 
many hundred years. Such objections do not disturb me as once they did; for 
it is plain as day that other errors have remained for even more centuries 
in the world and in the universities. 
 
<lb/> 
 
I should be glad to see Aristotle's books on <hi rend="italic">Logic</hi>, 
<hi rend="italic">Rhetoric</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Poetics</hi> retained or used in an abridged form as 
text-books for the profitable training of young people in speaking and 
preaching. But the commentaries and notes should be abolished, and as 
Cicero's <hi rend="italic">Rhetoric</hi> is read without commentaries and notes, so 
Aristotle's Logic should be read as it is, without such a mass of comments. 
But now neither speaking nor preaching is learned from it, and it has become 
nothing but a disputing and a weariness to the flesh. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Besides this there are the languages -- Latin, Greek and Hebrew -- the 
mathematical disciplines and history. But all this I give over to the 
specialists, and, indeed, the reform would come of itself, if we were only 
seriously bent upon it. In truth, much depends upon it; for it is here 
<ref target="n243">[243]</ref> 
 
that the Christian youth and the best of our people, with whom the future of 
Christendom lies, are to be educated and trained. Therefore I consider that 
there is no work more worthy of pope or emperor than a thorough reformation 
of the universities, and there is nothing worse or more worthy of the devil 
than unreformed universities. 
 
<lb/> 
 
The medical men I leave to reform their own faculties; the jurists and 
theologians I take as my share, and I say, in the first place, that it were 
well if the canon law, from the first letter to the last, and especially the 
decretals, were utterly blotted out. The Bible contains more than enough 
directions for all our living, and so the study of the canon law only stands 
in the way of the study of the Holy Scriptures; moreover, it smacks for the 
most part of mere avarice and pride. Even though there were much in it that 
is good, it might as well be destroyed, for the pope has taken the whole 
canon law captive and imprisoned it in the "chamber of his hear, 
<ref target="n244">[244]</ref> 
 so that 
the study of it is henceforth a waste of time and a farce. At present the 
canon law is not what is in the books, but what is in the sweet will of the 
pope and his flatterers. Your cause may be thoroughly established in the 
canon law; still the pope has his <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">scrinium 
pectoris</hi></foreign>, 
<ref target="n245">[245]</ref> 
 and all law 
and the whole world must be guided by that. Now it is oft times a knave, and 
even the devil himself, who rules this <foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">scrinium</hi></foreign>, and they boast that it is 
ruled by the Holy Spirit! Thus they deal with Christ's unfortunate people. 
They give them many laws and themselves keep none of them, but others they 
compel either to keep them or else to buy release. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Since, then, the pope and his followers have suspended the whole canon 
law, and since they pay no heed to it, but regard their own wanton will as a 
law exalting them above all the world, we should follow their example and 
for our part also reject these books. Why should we waste our time studying 
them? We could never discover the whole arbitrary will of the pope, which 
has now become the canon law. The canon law has arisen in the devil's name, 
let it fall in the name of God, and let there be no more <foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">doctores 
decretorum</hi></foreign> 
<ref target="n246">[246]</ref> 
 in the work, but only <foreign 
lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">doctores scrinii papalis</hi></foreign>, 
that is, "hypocrites of the pope"! It is said that there is no better 
temporal rule anywhere than among the Turks, who have neither spiritual nor 
temporal law, but only their Koran; and we must confess that there is no 
more shameful rule than among us, with our spiritual and temporal law, so 
that there is no estate which lives according to the light of nature, still 
less according to Holy Scripture. 
 
<lb/> 
 
The temporal law, -- God help us! What a wilderness it has become! 
<ref target="n247">[247]</ref> 
 
Though it is much better, wiser and more rational than the "spiritual law" 
which has nothing good about it except the name, still there is far too much 
of it. Surely the Holy Scriptures and good rulers would be law enough; as 
St. Paul says in 1 Corinthians 6:1: "Is there no one among you can judge his 
neighbor's cause, that ye must go to law before heathen courts?" It seems 
just to me that territorial laws and territorial customs should take 
precedence of the general imperial laws, and the imperial laws be used only 
in case of necessity. Would to God that as every land has its own peculiar 
character, so it were ruled by its own brief laws, as the lands were ruled 
before these imperial laws were invented, and many lands are still ruled 
without them! These diffuse and far-fetched laws are only a burden to the 
people, and hinder causes more than they help them. I hope, however, that 
others have given this matter more thought and attention than I am able to 
do. 
 
<lb/> 
 
My friends the theologians have spared themselves pains and labor; they 
leave the Bible in peace and read the Sentences. I should think that the 
Sentences 
<ref target="n248">[248]</ref> 
 ought to be the first study of young students in theology and 
the Bible ought to be the study for the doctors. But now it is turned 
around; the Bible come first, and is put aside when the bachelor's degree is 
reached, and the Sentences come last. They are attached forever to the 
doctorate, and that with such a solemn obligation that a man who is not a 
priest may indeed read may indeed the Bible, but the Sentences a priest must 
read. A married man, I observe, could be a Doctor of the Bible, but under no 
circumstances a Doctor of the Sentences. What good fortune can we expect if 
we act so perversely and in this way put the Bible, the holy Word of God, so 
far to the rear? Moreover the pope commands, with many severe words, that 
his laws are to be read and used in the schools and the courts, but little 
is said of the Gospel. Thus it is the custom that in the schools and the 
courts the Gospel lies idle in the dust under the bench, 
<ref target="n249">[249]</ref> 
 to the end that 
the pope's harmful laws may rule alone. 
 
<lb/> 
 
If we are called by the title of teachers 
<ref target="n250">[250]</ref> 
 of Holy Scripture, then we 
ought to be compelled, in accordance with our name, to teach the Holy 
Scriptures and nothing else, although even this title is too proud and 
boastful and no one ought to be proclaimed and crowned teacher of Holy 
Scripture. Yet it might be suffered, if the work justified the name; but 
now, under the despotism of the Sentences, we find among the theologians 
more of heathen and human opinion than of the holy and certain doctrine of 
Scripture. What, then, are we to do? I know of no other way than humbly to 
pray God to give us Doctors of Theology. Pope, emperor and universities may 
make Doctors of Arts, of Medicine, of Laws, of the Sentences; but be assured 
that no one will make a Doctor of Holy Scripture, save only the Holy Ghost 
from heaven, as Christ says in John 6:45: "They must all be taught of God 
Himself." Now the Holy Ghost does not concern Himself about red or brown 
birettas 
<ref target="n251">[251]</ref> 
 or other decorations, nor does He ask whether one is old or 
young, layman or priest, monk or secular, virgin or married; nay He spake of 
old by an ass, against the prophet who rode upon it. (Number 22:28). Would 
God that we were worthy to have such doctors given us, whether they were 
layman or priests, married or virgin. True, they now try to force the Holy 
Ghost into pope, bishops and doctors, although there is no sign or 
indication whatever that He is in them. 
 
<lb/> 
 
The number of theological books must also be lessened, and a selection 
made of the best of them. For it is not many books or much reading that 
makes men learned; but it is good things, however little of them, often 
read, that make men learned in the Scriptures, and make them godly, too. 
Indeed the writings of all the holy fathers should be read only for a time, 
in order that through them we may be led to the Holy Scriptures. As it is, 
however, we read them only to be absorbed in them and never come to the 
Scriptures. We are like men who study the sign-posts and never travel the 
road. The dear fathers wished, by their writings, to lead us to the 
Scriptures, but we so use them as to be led away from the Scriptures, though 
the Scriptures alone are our vineyard in which we ought to work and toil. 
 
 
<lb/> 
 
Above all, the foremost and most general subject of study, both in the 
higher and the lower schools, should be the Holy Scriptures, and for the 
young boys the Gospel. And would to God that every town had a girl's school 
also, in which the girls were taught the Gospel for an hour each day either 
in German or Latin. Indeed the schools, monasteries and nunneries began long 
ago with that end in view, and it was a praiseworthy and Christian purpose, 
as we learn from the story of St. Agnes 
<ref target="n252">[252]</ref> 
 and other of the saints. That 
was the time of holy virgins and martyrs, and then it was well with 
Christendom; but now they 
<ref target="n253">[253]</ref> 
 have come to nothing but praying and singing. 
Ought not every Christian at his ninth or tenth year to know the entire holy 
Gospel from which he derives his name 
<ref target="n254">[254]</ref> 
 and his life? A spinner or a 
seamstress teaches her daughter the trade in her early years; but now even 
the great, learned prelates and bishops themselves do not know the Gospel. 
 
 
<lb/> 
 
O how unjustly we deal with these poor young people who are committed to 
us for direction and instruction! We must give a terrible accounting for our 
neglect to set the Word of God before them. They fare as Jeremiah says in 
Lamentations 2:11 ff.: "Mine eyes are grown weary with weeping, my bowels 
are terrified, my liver is poured out upon the ground, because of the 
destruction of the daughter of my people, for the youth and the children 
perish in all the streets of the whole city; they said to their mothers, 
"Where is bread and wine? And they swooned as the wounded in the streets of 
the city and gave up the ghost in their mothers' bosom." This pitiful evil 
we do not see, -- how even now the young folk in the midst of Christendom 
languish and perish miserably for want of the Gospel, in which we ought to 
be giving them constant instruction and training. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Moreover, if the universities were diligent in the study of Holy 
Scripture, we should not send everybody there, as we do when all we ask is 
numbers, and everyone wishes to have a doctor's degree; but we should send 
only the best qualified students, who have previously been well trained in 
the lower schools. A prince or city council ought to see to this, and permit 
only the well qualified to be sent. But where the Holy Scriptures do not 
rule, there I advise no one to send his son. Everyone not unceasingly busy 
with the Word of God must become corrupt; that is why the people who are in 
the universities and who are trained there are the kind of people they are. 
For this no one is to blame with the training of the youth. For the 
universities ought to turn out only men who are experts in the Holy 
Scriptures, who can become bishops and priests, leaders in the fight against 
heretics, the devil and all the world. But where do you find this true? I 
greatly fear that the universities are wide gates of hell, if they do not 
diligently teach the Holy Scriptures and impress them on the youth. 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="26"> 
 
 
26. 
<ref target="n255">[255]</ref> 
I know full well that the Roman crowd will make pretensions and 
great boasts about how the pope took the Holy Roman Empire from the Greek 
Emperor 
<ref target="n256">[256]</ref> 
 and bestowed it on the Germans, for which honor and benevolence 
he is said to have justly deserved and obtained from the Germans submission 
and thanks and all good things. For this reason they will, perhaps, 
undertake to throw to the winds all attempts to reform them, and will not 
allow us to think about anything but the bestowal of the Roman Empire. For 
this cause they have heretofore persecuted and oppressed many a worthy 
emperor so arbitrarily and arrogantly that it is pity to tell of it, and 
with the same adroitness they have made themselves overlords of all the 
temporal powers and authorities, contrary to the Holy Gospel. Of this too I 
must therefore speak. 
 
<lb/> 
 
There is no doubt that the true Roman Empire, which the writings of the 
prophets foretold in Numbers 24:24 and in Daniel 2:39 ff., has long since 
been overthrown and brought to an end, as Balaam clearly prophesied in 
Numbers 24:24:, when he said: "The Romans shall come and overthrow the Jews; 
and afterwards they also shall be destroyed." That was brought to pass by 
the Goths, 
<ref target="n257">[257]</ref> 
 but especially when the Turkish Empire arose almost a 
thousand years ago, 
<ref target="n258">[258]</ref> 
 then in time Asia and Africa fell away, and finally 
Venice arose, and there remained to Rome nothing of its former power. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Now when the pope could not subdue to his arrogant will the Greeks and 
the emperor at Constantinople, who was hereditary Roman Emperor, he 
bethought himself of this device, viz., to rob him of his empire and his 
title and turn it over to the Germans, who were at that time warlike and of 
good repute, so as to bring the power of the Roman Empire under his control 
and give it away as a fief. So too it turned out. It was taken away from the 
emperor at Constantinople and its name and title were given to us Germans. 
Thereby we became the servants of the pope, and there is now a second Roman 
Empire, which the pope has built upon the Germans; for the other, which was 
first, has long since fallen, as I have said. 
 
<lb/> 
 
So then the Roman See has its will. It has taken possession of Rome, 
driven out the German Emperor and bound him with oaths not to dwell at Rome. 
He is to be Roman Emperor, and yet he is not to have possession of Rome, and 
besides he is at all times to be dependent upon the caprice of the pope and 
his followers, so that we have the name and they have the land and cities. 
hey have always abused our simplicity to serve their own arrogance and 
tyranny, and they call us mad Germans, who let ourselves be made apes and 
fools at their bidding. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Ah well! For God the Lord it is a small thing to toss empires and 
principalities to and fro! He is so generous with then that once in a while 
He gives a kingdom to a knave and takes it from a good man, sometimes by the 
treachery of wicked, faithless men and sometimes by heredity, as we read of 
the Kingdoms of Persia and Greece, and of almost all kingdoms; and Daniel 
2:21 and 4:14 says: "He Who ruleth over all things dwelleth in heaven, and 
it is He alone Who changeth kingdoms, tosseth them to and fro, and maketh 
them." Since, therefore, no one can think it a great thing to have a kingdom 
given him, especially if he is a Christian, we Germans too cannot be puffed 
up because a new Roman Empire is bestowed on us; for in His eyes it is a 
trifling gift, which He often gives to the most unworthy, as Daniel 4:35 
says: "All who dwell upon the earth are in His eyes as nothing, and He has 
power in all the kingdoms of men, to give them to whomsoever He will." 
 
<lb/> 
 
But although the pope unjustly and by violence robbed the true emperor of 
his Roman Empire, or of its name, and gave it to us Germans, it is certain, 
nevertheless, that in this matter God has used the pope's wickedness to give 
such an empire to the German nation, and after the fall of the first Roman 
Empire, to set up another, which still exists. And although we gave no 
occasion to this wickedness of the popes, and did not understand their false 
aims and purposes, nevertheless, through this papal trickery and roguery, we 
have already paid too dearly for our empire, with incalculable bloodshed, 
with the suppression of our liberty, with the risk of robbery of all our 
goods, especially the goods of the churches and canonries, and with the 
suffering of unspeakable deception and insult. We have the name of the 
empire, but the pope has our wealth, honor, body, life, soul and all that is 
ours. So we Germans are to be cheated in the trade. 
<ref target="n259">[259]</ref> 
 What the popes 
sought was to be emperors, and since they could not manage that, they at 
least succeeded in setting themselves over the emperors. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Because then, the empire has been given us without our fault, by the 
providence of God and the plotting of evil men, I would not advise that we 
give it up, but rather that we rule it wisely and in the fear of God, so 
long as it shall please Him. For, as has been said, it matters not to Him 
where an empire comes from; it is His will that it shall be ruled. Though 
the popes took it dishonestly from others, nevertheless we did not get it 
dishonestly. It is given us by the will of God through evil-minded men; and 
we have more regard for God's will than for the treacherous purpose of the 
popes, who, in bestowing it, wished to be emperors themselves, and more than 
emperors, and only to fool and mock us with the name. The King of Babylon 
also seized his empire by robbery and force; yet it was God's will that it 
should be ruled by the holy princes, Daniel, Hananiah, Azariah and Mishael; 
much more then is it His will that this empire be ruled by the Christian 
princes of Germany, regardless whether the pope stole it, or got it by 
robbery, or made it anew. It is all God's ordering, which came to pass 
before we knew of it. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Therefore the pope and his followers may not boast that they have done a 
great favor to the German nation by the bestowal of this Roman Empire. 
First, because they did not mean it for our good, but were rather taking 
advantage of our simplicity in order to strengthen themselves in their proud 
designs against the Roman Emperor at Constantinople, from whom the pope 
godlessly and lawlessly took this empire, a thing which he had no right to 
do. Second, because the pope's intention was not to give us the empire, but 
to get it for myself, that he might bring all our power, our freedom, 
wealth, body and soul into subjection to himself and use us (if God had not 
prevented) to subdue all the world. He clearly says so himself in his 
decretals, and he has attempted it, by many evil wiles, with a number of the 
German emperors. How beautifully we Germans have been taught our German! 
When we thought to be lords, we became slaves of the most deceitful tyrants; 
we have the name, title and insignia of the empire, but the pope has its 
treasures, its authority, its law and its liberty. So the pope gobbles the 
kernel, and we play with the empty hulls. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Now may God, Who by the wiles of tyrants has tossed this empire into our 
lap, and charged us with the ruling of it, help us to live up to the name, 
title and insignia, to rescue our liberty, and to show the Romans, for once, 
what it is that we, through them, have received from God! They boast that 
they have bestowed on us an empire. So be it, then! If it is true, then let 
the pope give us Rome and everything else which he has got from the empire; 
let him free our land from his intolerable taxing and robbing, and give us 
back our liberty, authority, wealth, honor, body and soul; let the empire be 
what an empire should be, and let his words and pretensions be fulfilled! 
 
 
<lb/> 
 
If he will not do that, they why all this shamming, these false and lying 
words and juggler's tricks? Is he not satisfied with having so rudely led 
this noble nation by the nose these many hundred years without ceasing? It 
does not follow that the pope must be above an emperor because he makes or 
crowns him. The prophet Samuel at God's command anointed and crowned Kings 
Saul and David, and yet he was their subject (1 Samuel 10:1; 16:13); and the 
prophet Nathan anointed King Solomon, but was not set over him on that 
account (1 Kings 1:38 f.); Elisha too had one of his servants anoint Jehu 
King of Israel, and yet they remained obedient and subject to him (2 Kings 
9:1 ff.). Except in the case of the pope, it has never happened in all the 
world's history that he who consecrated or crowned the king was over the 
king. He lets himself be crowned pope by three cardinals, who are under him, 
and he is nevertheless their superior. Why then should he, contrary to the 
example which he himself sets, and contrary to the custom and teaching of 
all the world and of the Scriptures, exalt himself above temporal 
authorities, or the empire, simply because he crowns or consecrates the 
emperor? It is enough that he should be the emperor's superior in divine 
things, to wit, in preaching, teaching and administering the sacraments, in 
which things, indeed, any bishop or priest is over every other man, as St. 
Ambrose in his See was over the emperor Theodosius, 
<ref target="n260">[260]</ref> 
 and the prophet 
Nathan over David, and Samuel over Saul. Therefore, let the German Emperor 
be really and truly emperor, and let not his authority or his sword be put 
down by this blind pretension of papal hypocrites, as though they were to be 
excepted from his dominion and themselves direct the temporal sword in all 
things. 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="27"> 
 
 
27. Enough has now been said about the failings of the clergy, though 
more of them can and will be found if these are properly considered. We 
would say something too about the failings of the temporal estate. 
 
 
</item> 
</list> 
</div3> 
 
<div3 type="notes" id="d14"> 
 
<note id="n102"><seg type="note-symbol">[102]</seg> <p>See (nobility.05; note 11), p. 84, note 1. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n103"><seg type="note-symbol">[103]</seg> <p>The passage is chapter 31, <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">Filiis vel 
nepotibus</hi></foreign>. It provides 
that in case the income of endowments bequeathed to the Church is misused, 
and appeals to the bishop and archbishop fail to correct the misuse, the 
heirs of the testator may appeal to the royal courts. Luther wishes this 
principle applied to the annates. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n104"><seg type="note-symbol">[104]</seg> <p>See above, pp. 91 f. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n105"><seg type="note-symbol">[105]</seg> <p>See above, p. 91. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n106"><seg type="note-symbol">[106]</seg> <p>See above, p. 94. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n107"><seg type="note-symbol">[107]</seg> <p>i.e., Promises to bestow on certain persons livings not yet vacant. 
Complaint of the evils arising out of the practice was continually heard 
from the year 1416. For the complaints made at Worms (1521), see WREDE, op. 
cit., II, 710. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n108"><seg type="note-symbol">[108]</seg> <p>See above, pp. 86 f. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n109"><seg type="note-symbol">[109]</seg> <p>See above, pp. 92 f. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n110"><seg type="note-symbol">[110]</seg> <p>See above, p. 93. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n111"><seg type="note-symbol">[111]</seg> <p>See above, p. 89. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n112"><seg type="note-symbol">[112]</seg> <p>Rules for the transaction of papal business, 
including such matters as appointments and the like. At Worms (1521) the 
Estates complain that these rules are made to the advantage of the 
"courtesans" and the disadvantage of the Germans. (WREDE, op. cit., II, 
pp. 675f.) </p></note> 
 
<note id="n113"><seg type="note-symbol">[113]</seg> <p>The local Church authorities, here equivalent to 
"the bishops." On use of term see <foreign 
lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Realencyk.</hi></foreign>, XIV, 424. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n114"><seg type="note-symbol">[114]</seg> <p>The sign of the episcopal office; as regards 
archbishops, the <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">pallium</hi></foreign>; see 
above, p. 89, and note. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n115"><seg type="note-symbol">[115]</seg> <p>See above, p. 87, note 1. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n116"><seg type="note-symbol">[116]</seg> <p>The first of the ecumenical councils (A. D. 325). 
The decree to which Luther here refers is cannon IV of that Council. Cf. 
KOHLER,<foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">L. Und die Kg.</hi></foreign>, pp. 139 
ff. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n117"><seg type="note-symbol">[117]</seg> <p>The primate is the ranking archbishop of a country. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n118"><seg type="note-symbol">[118]</seg> <p>"Exemption" was the practice by which monastic 
houses were withdrawn from the jurisdiction of the bishops and made 
directly subject to the pope.  The practice seems to have originated in 
the X Century with the famous monastery of Cluny (918), but it was 
almost universal in the case of the houses of the mendicant orders. The 
bishops made it a constant subject of complaint, and the Lateran Council 
(Dec. 19, 1516) passed a decree abolishing all monastic exemptions, 
though the decree does not seem to have been effective. See CREIGHTON, 
<hi rend="italic">History of the Papacy</hi>, V, 266. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n119"><seg type="note-symbol">[119]</seg> <p>i.e., Antichrist. See above, p. 73, note 2. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n120"><seg type="note-symbol">[120]</seg> <p>The papal interference in the conduct of the local 
Church courts was as flagrant as in the appointments, of which Luther 
has heretofore spoken.  At Worms (1521) it was complained that cases 
were cited to Rome as a court of first instance, and the demand was made 
that a regular course of appeals should be re-established. WREDE, op. 
cit., I, 672,718. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n121"><seg type="note-symbol">[121]</seg> <p>The reference is Canon V of the Council of Sardica 
(A. D. 343), incorporated in the cannon law as a cannon of Nicaea (Pt. 
II, qu. 6, c.5).  See KOHLER, <foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">L. Und die 
Kg.</hi></foreign>, 151. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n122"><seg type="note-symbol">[122]</seg> <p>i.e., Appealed to Rome for decision. This is the 
subject of the first of the 102 Gravamina of 1521 )WREDE, op. cit., II 
672). </p></note> 
 
<note id="n123"><seg type="note-symbol">[123]</seg> <p>The judges in the bishops' courts. The complaint 
is that they interfere with the administration of justice by citing into 
their courts cases which properly belong in the lay courts, and enforce 
their verdicts (usually fines) by means of ecclesiastical censures. The 
charges against these courts are specified in the <hi rend="italic">Gravamina</hi> of 
1521, Nos. 73-100 (WREDE, op.  cit., II 694-703). </p></note> 
 
<note id="n124"><seg type="note-symbol">[124]</seg> <p>The <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">signaturae 
gratiae</hi></foreign> and the <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">signaturae 
justitiae</hi></foreign> were the bureaus through which the pope 
regulated those matters of administration which belonged to his own 
special prerogative. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n125"><seg type="note-symbol">[125]</seg> <p>See above, pp. 88 f. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n126"><seg type="note-symbol">[126]</seg> <p>See above, p. 88, note 3. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n127"><seg type="note-symbol">[127]</seg> <p>See above, p. 94. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n128"><seg type="note-symbol">[128]</seg> <p>i.e., The cases in which a priest was forbidden to 
give absolution.  The reference here is to cases in which only the pope 
could absolve. Cf. The <hi rend="italic">XCV Theses</hi>, Vol. I, p. 30. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n129"><seg type="note-symbol">[129]</seg> <p>A papal bull published annually at Rome on Holy 
Thursday. It was directed against heretics, but to the condemnation of 
the heretics and their heresies was added a list of offenses which could 
received absolution only from the pope, or by his authorization. In 1522 
Luther translated this bull into German as a New Year present for the 
pope. (Weimar Ed., VIII, 691). On Luther's earlier utterances concerning 
it, see KOHLER, <foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">L. u. die Kg.</hi></foreign>, 
pp. 59 ff. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n130"><seg type="note-symbol">[130]</seg> <p>The breve is a papal decree, of equal authority 
with the bull, but differing from it in form, and usually dealing with 
matters of smaller importance. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n131"><seg type="note-symbol">[131]</seg> <p>Cf. Luther's earlier statement to the same effect 
in <hi rend="italic">A Discussion of Confession</hi>, Vol. I, pp. 96.f. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n132"><seg type="note-symbol">[132]</seg> <p>See above, p. 99. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n133"><seg type="note-symbol">[133]</seg> <p>The Fifth Lateran Council (1512-17). 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n134"><seg type="note-symbol">[134]</seg> <p>See above, p. 90, note 1. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n135"><seg type="note-symbol">[135]</seg> <p>In the cannon law, <hi rend="italic">Decretal. Greg. Lib. I, 
tit. 6, cap.  4</hi>. The decretal forbids the bestowing of the pallium 
(see above, p. 89, note 3) on an archbishop elect, until he shall first 
have sworn allegiance to the Holy See. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n136"><seg type="note-symbol">[136]</seg> <p>The induction of Church officials into office. The 
term was used particularly of the greater offices -- those of bishop and 
abbot. These offices carried with them the enjoyment of certain incomes, 
and the possession of certain temporal powers. For this reason the right 
of investiture was a bone of contention between popes and emperors 
during the Middle Ages. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n137"><seg type="note-symbol">[137]</seg> <p>Especially in the time of the Emperors Henry IV 
and V (1056-1125). </p></note> 
 
<note id="n138"><seg type="note-symbol">[138]</seg> <p>The German Empire was regarded during the Middle 
Ages as a continuation of the Roman Empire. (See below, p. 153.) The 
right to crown an emperor was held to be the prerogative of the pope; 
until the pope bestowed the imperial crown, the emperor bore the title, 
"King of the Romans." </p></note> 
 
<note id="n139"><seg type="note-symbol">[139]</seg> <p>In the canon law, <hi rend="italic">Decretal. Greg. Lib. I, tit. 
33, cap.  6</hi>. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n140"><seg type="note-symbol">[140]</seg> <p>In the treatise, <hi rend="italic">Resolutio Lutheriana super 
propositione XIII, de potestate papae</hi> (1520). Weimar Ed., II, 
pp. 217 ff.; Erl. Ed., op. var. Arg., III, pp. 293 ff. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n141"><seg type="note-symbol">[141]</seg> <p>See p. 70. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n142"><seg type="note-symbol">[142]</seg> <p>Cf. <hi rend="italic">The Papacy at Rome</hi>, Vol. I, pp. 357 f. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n143"><seg type="note-symbol">[143]</seg> <p>A decree of Pope Clement V of 1313, incorporated 
subsequently in the canon law, <hi rend="italic">Clement. lib. ii, tit. II, cap. 
2</hi>. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n144"><seg type="note-symbol">[144]</seg> <p>A forged document of the VIII Century, professing 
to come from the hand of the Emperor Constantine (306-337). The Donation 
conveyed to the pope title to the city of Rome (the capital had been 
removed to Constantinople), certain lands in Italy and "the islands of 
the sea." It was used by the popes of the Middle Ages to support their 
claims to worldly power, and its genuineness was not disputed. In 1440, 
however, Laurentius Valla, an Italian humanist, published a work in 
which he proved that the Donation was a forgery. This work was 
republished in Germany by Ulrich von Hutten in 1517, and seems to have 
come to Luther's attention in the early part of 1520, just before the 
composition of the present treatise (Cf. ENDERS II, 332). Luther 
subsequently (1537) issued an annotated translation of the text of the 
Donation (Erl. Ed., XXV, pp. 176 ff.). </p></note> 
 
<note id="n145"><seg type="note-symbol">[145]</seg> <p>The papal claim to temporal sovereignty over this 
little kingdom, which comprised the island of Sicily and certain 
territories in Southern Italy, goes back to the XI Century, and was 
steadily asserted during the whole of the later Middle Ages. It was one 
of the questions at issue in the conflict between the Emperor Frederick 
II (1200-1260) and the popes, and played an important part in the 
history of the stormy times which followed the fall of the Hobenstaufen. 
The popes claimed the right to award the kingdom to a ruler who would 
swear allegiance to the Holy See. The right to the kingdom was at this 
time contested between the royal houses of France and of Spain, of which 
latter house the Emperor Charles V was the head. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n146"><seg type="note-symbol">[146]</seg> <p>The popes claimed temporal sovereignty over a 
strip territory in Italy, beginning at Rome and stretching in a 
northeasterly direction across the peninsula to a point on the Adriatic 
south of Venice, including the cities and lands which Luther mentions. 
This formed the so-called "States of the Church." The attempt to 
consolidated the States and make the papal sovereignty effective 
involved Popes Alexander VI (1492-1503) and Julius II (1503-1513) in war 
and entangled them in political alliances with the European powers and 
petty Italian states. It resulted at last in actual war between Pope 
Clement VII and the Emperor Charles V (1526-1527). See <hi rend="italic">Cambridge 
Modern History</hi>, I, 104-143; 219-252, and literature cited pp. 
706-713; 727 f. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n147"><seg type="note-symbol">[147]</seg> <p>A free translation of the Vulgate, <hi rend="italic">Nemo 
militans Deo</hi>. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n148"><seg type="note-symbol">[148]</seg> <p>The kissing of the pope's feet was a part of the 
"adoration" which he claimed as his right. See above, p. 108. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n149"><seg type="note-symbol">[149]</seg> <p>The three paragraphs enclosed in brackets were 
added by Luther to the 2nd edition; see Introduction, p. 59. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n150"><seg type="note-symbol">[150]</seg> <p>The holy places of Rome had long been favorite 
objects of pilgrimage, and the practice had been zealously fostered by 
the popes through the institution of the "golden" or "jubilee years." 
Cf. Vol. I, p.  18, and below, p. 114. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n151"><seg type="note-symbol">[151]</seg> <p>Cf. The Italian proverb, "God is everywhere except 
at Rome; there He has a vicar." </p></note> 
 
<note id="n152"><seg type="note-symbol">[152]</seg> <p>Cf. Hutten's saying in <hi rend="italic">Vadiscus</hi>: "Three 
things there are which those who go to Rome usually bring home with 
them, a bad conscience, a ruined stomach and an empty purse." (ed. 
BOCKING, IV, p. 169.) Vol., II. - 8</p></note> 
 
<note id="n153"><seg type="note-symbol">[153]</seg> <p>The "golden" or "jubilee years" were the years 
when special rewards were attached to worship at the shrines of Rome. 
The custom was instituted by Boniface VIII in <date value="1300">1300</date>, and it 
was the intention to make every hundredth year a jubilee. In 
<date value="1343">1343</date> the interval between jubilees was fixed at fifty, in 
<date value="1389">1389</date> at thirty-three, in <date value="1473">1473</date> at twenty-five 
years. Cf. Vol. I, p. 18. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n154"><seg type="note-symbol">[154]</seg> <p>Cf. The statements in the <hi rend="italic">Treatise on Baptism</hi> and 
the<hi rend="italic">Discussion of Confession</hi>, Vol. I, pp. 68 ff., 98. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n155"><seg type="note-symbol">[155]</seg> <p>The houses, or monasteries, of the mendicant or 
"begging" orders -- the "friars." The members of these orders were sworn 
to support themselves on the alms of the faithful. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n156"><seg type="note-symbol">[156]</seg> <p>The three leading mendicant orders were the Franciscan (the 
Minorities, or "little brothers"), founded by St. Francis of Assisi (died 
1226), the Dominican (the "preaching brothers"), founded by St. Dominic 
(died 1221), and the Augustinians Hermits, to which Luther himself belonged, 
and which claimed foundation by St. Augustine (died 430). 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n157"><seg type="note-symbol">[157]</seg> <p>The interference of the friars in the duties of 
the parish clergy was a continual subject of complaint through this 
period. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n158"><seg type="note-symbol">[158]</seg> <p>By the middle of the XV Century there were eight 
distinct sects within the Franciscan order alone (See <foreign 
lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Realencyk.</hi></foreign>, Vi, pp. 212 ff.), and Luther 
had himself taken part in a vigorous dispute between two parties in the 
Augustinian order. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n159"><seg type="note-symbol">[159]</seg> <p>St. Agnes the Martyr, put to death in the 
beginning of the IV Century, one of the favorite saints of the Middle 
Ages. See SCHAFER, <foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">L. als 
Kirchenhistoriker</hi></foreign>, p. 235. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n160"><seg type="note-symbol">[160]</seg> <p>One of the most famous of the German convents, founded in 936. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n161"><seg type="note-symbol">[161]</seg> <p>The celebrated Church Father (died 420). The 
passages referred to are in <hi rend="italic">Migne</hi>, XXII, 656, and XXVI, 562. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n162"><seg type="note-symbol">[162]</seg> <p>Or "community" (<foreign 
lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Gemeine</hi></foreign>).  Cf. <hi rend="italic">The Papacy at 
Rome</hi>, Vol. I, p. 345, note 4. See also <foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Dass 
eine christl. Gemeine Recht und Mach habe</hi></foreign>, etc. Weimar 
Ed. XI, pp. 408 ff. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n163"><seg type="note-symbol">[163]</seg> <p>Or "congregation." See note 2. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n164"><seg type="note-symbol">[164]</seg> <p>i.e., At a time later than that of the Apostles. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n165"><seg type="note-symbol">[165]</seg> <p>The first absolute prohibition of marriage to the 
clergy is contained in a decree of Pope Siricius and dated 
<date value="385">385</date>. See H. C. LEA, <hi rend="italic">History of Sacerdotal 
Celibacy</hi>, 3d ed. (1907), I, pp. 59 ff. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n166"><seg type="note-symbol">[166]</seg> <p>The priests of the Greek Church are required to 
marry, and the controversy over celibacy was involved in the division 
between the Greek and Roman Churches. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n167"><seg type="note-symbol">[167]</seg> <p>Cf. Hutten's <hi rend="italic">Vadiscus</hi> (BOCKING, IV, 199). 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n168"><seg type="note-symbol">[168]</seg> <p>i.e., Lie in Roman appointment. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n169"><seg type="note-symbol">[169]</seg> <p>i.e., The ministry in the congregation. See above, p. 119. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n170"><seg type="note-symbol">[170]</seg> <p><foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">Quantum fragilitas humana 
permittit</hi></foreign>. A qualification of the 
vow. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n171"><seg type="note-symbol">[171]</seg> <p>i.e., Celibacy. <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">Non promitto 
castitatem</hi></foreign>. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n172"><seg type="note-symbol">[172]</seg> <p><foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">Fragilitas humana non permittit caste 
vivere.</hi></foreign> 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n173"><seg type="note-symbol">[173]</seg> <p><foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">Angelica fortitudo et coelestis 
virtus</hi></foreign>. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n174"><seg type="note-symbol">[174]</seg> <p>The court-jester was allowed unusual freedom of speech. See 
"Prefatory Letter" above, p. 62. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n175"><seg type="note-symbol">[175]</seg> <p>The laws governing marriage were entirely the laws 
of the Church.  The canon law prohibited marriage of blood-relatives as 
far as the seventh degree of consanguinity. In 1204 the prohibition was 
restricted to the first four degrees; lawful marriage within these 
degrees was possible only by dispensation, which was not all too 
difficult to secure, especially by those who were will willing to pay 
for it (see above, p. 96). The relation of god-parents to god-children 
was also held to establish a "spiritual consanguinity" which might serve 
as a bar to lawful marriage. See BENRATH, p. 103, note 74, and in the 
<hi rend="italic">Babylonian Captivity</hi>, below, p. 265. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n176"><seg type="note-symbol">[176]</seg> <p>This Luther actually did. When he burned the papal bull of 
excommunication (Dec. 10, 1520) a copy of the canon law was also given to 
the flames. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n177"><seg type="note-symbol">[177]</seg> <p>i.e., The marriage of the clergy. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n178"><seg type="note-symbol">[178]</seg> <p>On this sort of reserved cases see <hi rend="italic">Discussion 
of Confession</hi>, Vol. I, pp. 96 ff. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n179"><seg type="note-symbol">[179]</seg> <p>"Irregularity" is the condition of any member of a 
monastic order who has violated the prescriptions of the order and been 
deprived, in consequence, of the benefits enjoyed by those who live 
under the <hi rend="italic">regula</hi>, viz., the rule of the order. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n180"><seg type="note-symbol">[180]</seg> <p>The three kinds of masses are really but one 
thing, viz., masses for the dead, celebrated on certain fixed days in 
each year, in consideration of the enjoyment of certain incomes, 
received either out of bequeathed endowments or from the heirs of the 
supposed beneficiaries. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n181"><seg type="note-symbol">[181]</seg> <p>i.e., Even when the mass is decently said. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n182"><seg type="note-symbol">[182]</seg> <p>See above, p. 72, note 1. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n183"><seg type="note-symbol">[183]</seg> <p>See above, p. 104. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n184"><seg type="note-symbol">[184]</seg> <p><foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Das geistliche Unrecht.</hi></foreign> 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n185"><seg type="note-symbol">[185]</seg> <p>The <hi rend="italic">Treatise concerning the Ban</hi>, above, pp. 33 ff. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n186"><seg type="note-symbol">[186]</seg> <p>i.e., To those who teach enforce the canon law. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n187"><seg type="note-symbol">[187]</seg> <p>Luther means the saint's-days and minor religious 
holidays. See also the <hi rend="italic">Discourse on Good Works</hi>, Vol. I, pp. 240 
f. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n188"><seg type="note-symbol">[188]</seg> <p>Or "congregation." 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n189"><seg type="note-symbol">[189]</seg> <p>i.e., City-council. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n190"><seg type="note-symbol">[190]</seg> <p><foreign 
lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Kirchweihen</hi></foreign>, i.e., the anniversary 
celebration of the consecration of a church. These days had become feast 
days for the parish, and were observed in anything but a spiritual 
fashion. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n191"><seg type="note-symbol">[191]</seg> <p>i.e., Occasions for drunkenness, gain and gambling. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n192"><seg type="note-symbol">[192]</seg> <p>See above, pp. 96 f. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n193"><seg type="note-symbol">[193]</seg> <p>See above, p. 98, note 2 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n194"><seg type="note-symbol">[194]</seg> <p>Letters entitling their holder to the benefits of 
the masses founded by the sodalities or confraternities. See Benrath, p. 
103. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n195"><seg type="note-symbol">[195]</seg> <p>See above, p. 98, and Vol. I, p. 22. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n196"><seg type="note-symbol">[196]</seg> <p>The pun is untranslatable, -- <foreign 
lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Netz, Gesetz solt ich sagen</hi></foreign>. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n197"><seg type="note-symbol">[197]</seg> <p>What the pope sold was release from the "snares" 
and "nets," viz., dispensation. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n198"><seg type="note-symbol">[198]</seg> <p>i.e., Even into the law of the church. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n199"><seg type="note-symbol">[199]</seg> <p><foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Die wilden Kapellen und 
Feldkirchen</hi></foreign>, i.e., churches which are 
built in the country, where there are no congregations. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n200"><seg type="note-symbol">[200]</seg> <p>A little town in East Prussia, where was displayed 
a sacramental wafer, said to have been miraculously preserved from a 
fire which destroyed the church in 1383. It was alleged that at certain 
times this wafer exuded drops of blood, reverenced as the blood of 
Christ, and many miracles were said to have been performed by it. 
Wilsnack early became a favorite resort for pilgrims. In 1412 the 
archbishop of Prague, at the instigation of John Hus, forbade the 
Bohemians to go there. Despite the protests of the Universities of 
Leipzig and Erfurt, Pope Eugenius IV in 1446 granted special indulgences 
for this pilgrimage, and the popularity of the shrine was undiminished 
until the time the Reformation. Cf. <foreign 
lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Realencyk</hi></foreign>, xxi, pp. 347 ff.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n201"><seg type="note-symbol">[201]</seg> <p>In Meckleburg, where another relic of "the Holy Blood" 
was displayed after 1491. Cf. Benrath, pp. 104 f.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n202"><seg type="note-symbol">[202]</seg> <p>The "Holy Coat of Trier" was believed by the 
credulous to be the seamless coat of Christ, which the soldiers did not 
rend. It was first exhibited in 1512, but was said to have been 
presented to the cathedral church of Trier by the Empress Helena, mother 
of Constantine the Great. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n203"><seg type="note-symbol">[203]</seg> <p>Pilgrimage to the Grimmenthal in Meiningen began 
in 1449. An image of the Virgin, declared to have been miraculously 
created, was displayed there, and was alleged to work wonderful cures, 
especially of syphilis. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n204"><seg type="note-symbol">[204]</seg> <p>The "Fair Virgin (<foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">die schone 
Maria</hi></foreign>) of Regensburg" was an 
image of the Virgin similar to that exhibited in the Grimmenthal. The shrine 
was opened March 45, 1519, and within a month 50,000 pilgrims are said to 
have worshipped there. (Weimar Ed., VI, 447, note 1). For another 
explanation see Benrath, p. 105. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n205"><seg type="note-symbol">[205]</seg> <p>The pilgrimages were a source of large revenue, 
derived from the sale of medals which were worn as amulets, the fees for 
masses at the shrines, and the free-will offerings of the pilgrims. A 
large part of this revenue accrued to the bishop of the diocese, though 
the popes never overlooked the profits which the sale of indulgences for 
worship at these shrines could produce. In the <hi rend="italic">Gravamina</hi> of 
1521 complaint is made that the bishops demand at least 25 to 33 per 
cent of the offerings made at shrines of pilgrimage (WREDE, op. cit., 
II, 687). </p></note> 
 
<note id="n206"><seg type="note-symbol">[206]</seg> <p>i.e., Every bishop. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n207"><seg type="note-symbol">[207]</seg> <p>The possession of a saint gave a church a certain 
reputation and distinction, which was sufficiently coveted to make local 
Church authorities willing to pay roundly for the canonization of a 
departed bishop or other local dignitary. Cf. Hutten's <hi rend="italic">Vadiscus</hi> 
(Bocking, IV, 232). </p></note> 
 
<note id="n208"><seg type="note-symbol">[208]</seg> <p>Archbishop of Florence (died 1459). He was 
canonized, <date value="1523-05-31">May 31, 1523</date>, by Pope Hadrian VI. When Luther 
wrote this the process of canonization had already begun. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n209"><seg type="note-symbol">[209]</seg> <p><hi rend="italic">Indulta</hi>, i.e., grants of special privilege. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n210"><seg type="note-symbol">[210]</seg> <p>"Lead," the leaden seal attached to the bull; 
"hide", the parchment on which it is written; "the string," the ribbon 
or silken cord from which the seals depend; "wax," the seal holding the 
cord to the parchment. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n211"><seg type="note-symbol">[211]</seg> <p>Franciscans, Dominicans, Augustinians, Carmelites 
and Servites. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n212"><seg type="note-symbol">[212]</seg> <p><foreign 
lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Botschaften</hi></foreign>, interpreted by Benrath (p. 
105), Clemen (I, 406, note) and Weimar Ed. (VI, 406, note 1) as a 
reference to the <hi rend="italic">stationarii</hi>. They were wandering beggars who, 
for an alms, would enroll the contributor in the list of beneficiaries 
of their patron saint, an alleged insurance against disease, accident, 
etc. They were classified according to the names of their patron saints, 
St. Anthony, St. Hurbert, St.  Valentine, etc. Protest against their 
operations were raised at the Diets of Worms (1521) and Nurnberg (1523). 
Included in these protests are the <hi rend="italic">terminarii</hi>, i.e., the 
collectors of alms sent out by the mendicant orders. See WREDE, op. 
cit., II, 678, 688, III, 651, and Benrath, loc. cit. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n213"><seg type="note-symbol">[213]</seg> <p><foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Wallbruder</hi></foreign>, 
the professional pilgrims who spent their lives in wandering from one 
place of pilgrimage to another and subsisted on the alms of the 
faithful. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n214"><seg type="note-symbol">[214]</seg> <p>i.e., If the plan above proposed were adopted. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n215"><seg type="note-symbol">[215]</seg> <p>See above, p. 129, note 1. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n216"><seg type="note-symbol">[216]</seg> <p>See <hi rend="italic">Treatise on the New Testament</hi>, Vol. I, pp. 308 ff. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n217"><seg type="note-symbol">[217]</seg> <p>In the <hi rend="italic">Babylonian Captivity</hi> (below, pp. 
291 f.) Luther definitely excludes penance from the number of 
sacraments, but see also p. 177. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n218"><seg type="note-symbol">[218]</seg> <p>The <hi rend="italic">sodalities</hi> ("fraternities," 
"confraternities"), still an important institution in the Roman Church, 
flourished especially in the XVI Century. They are associations for 
devotional purposes. The members of the sodalities are obligated to the 
recitation of certain prayers and the attendance upon certain masses at 
stipulated times. By virtue of membership in the association each member 
is believed to participate in the benefits accruing from these "good 
works" of all the members. In the case of most of the 
<hi rend="italic">sodalities</hi> membership entitled the member to the enjoyment of 
certain indulgences. In <date value="1520">1520</date> Wittenberg boasted of 20 
fraternities, Cologne of 80, Hamburg of more than 100 (<foreign 
lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Realencyk.</hi></foreign>, III, 437). In 
<date value="1519">1519</date> Degenhard Peffinnger, of Wittenberg, was a member of 8 
such fraternities in his home city, and of 27 in other places. For 
Luther's view of the <hi rend="italic">sodalities</hi> see above, pp. 8, 26 ff. On the 
whole subject see Benrath, pp. 106 f.; KOLDE in <foreign 
lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Realencyk.</hi></foreign>, III, pp. 434 ff.; LEA, 
<hi rend="italic">Hist. Of Conf.  And Indulg.</hi>, III, pp. 470 ff. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n219"><seg type="note-symbol">[219]</seg> <p>See above, p. 98, note 2. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n220"><seg type="note-symbol">[220]</seg> <p>See above, p. 128, note 5. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n221"><seg type="note-symbol">[221]</seg> <p>The excesses committed at the feasts of the 
religious societies were often a public scandal. See LEA, <hi rend="italic">Hist. of 
Conf. and Indulg</hi>, III, pp.  437 ff. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n222"><seg type="note-symbol">[222]</seg> <p>"Faculties" were extraordinary powers, usually for 
the granting of indulgences and of absolution in "reserved cases" (see 
above, p. 105, note 3). They were bestowed by the pope and could be 
revoked by him at any time.  Sometimes they were given to local Church 
officials, but were usually held by the legates or commissaries sent 
from Rome. Complaints were made at the Diet of Worms (1520) and Nurnberg 
(1523) that the papal commissaries and legates interfered with the 
ordinary methods of ecclesiastical jurisdiction and appointment. See 
WREDE, op. cit., II, 673, III, 653. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n223"><seg type="note-symbol">[223]</seg> <p>Wladislav I forced the Sultan to sue for peace in 
1443. At the instigation of the papal legate, Cardinal Caesarini, who 
represented that the treaty had not been approved by the pope, and 
absolved the king from the fulfillment of its conditions he renewed the 
war in 1444. At the battle of Varna, Nov. 10th, 1444, the Hungarians 
were decisively defeated, and Wladislav and Caesarini both killed. See 
CREIGHTON, <hi rend="italic">Hist. of the Papacy</hi>, III, 67. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n224"><seg type="note-symbol">[224]</seg> <p>John Hus and Jerome of Prague were convicted of 
heresy by the Council of Constance and burned at the stake, the former 
July 6th, 1415, the latter May 30th, 1416. Hus had come to Constance 
under the safe-conduct of the Emperor Sigismund. Luther is in error when 
he assumes that Jerome had a similar safe-conduct. In September, 1415, 
the Council passed a decree which asserted that "either by natural, 
divine or human law was any promise to be observed to the prejudice of 
the catholic faith." On the whole matter of the safe-conduct and its 
violation see LEA, <hi rend="italic">Hist. of the Inquisition in the M.A.</hi>, II, 
pp. 453 ff. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n225"><seg type="note-symbol">[225]</seg> <p>The League of Cambray, negotiated in 1508 for war 
against Venice. In 1510 Venice made terms with the pope and detached him 
from the alliance, and the result was war between the pope and the King 
of France. See <hi rend="italic">Cambridge Modern History</hi>, I, pp. 130 ff., and 
literature there cited. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n226"><seg type="note-symbol">[226]</seg> <p>i.e., The Hussites. After the martyrdom of Hus his 
followers maintained for a time a strong organization in Bohemia, and 
resisted with arms all attempts to force them into conformity with the 
Roman Church. The Council of Basel succeeded (1434) in reconciling the 
more moderate party among the Bohemians (the Calixtines) by allowing the 
administration of the cup to the laity. The more extreme party, however, 
refused to subscribe the <hi rend="italic">Compactata</hi> of Basel. Though they soon 
ceased to be a factor in the political situation, they remained outside 
the Church and perpetuated the teachings of Hus in sectarian 
organizations. The most important of these, the so-called Bohemian 
Brethren, had extended into Poland and Prussia before Luther's time. See 
<foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Realencyk.</hi></foreign>, III, 465-467. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n227"><seg type="note-symbol">[227]</seg> <p>See above, p. 140, note 1. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n228"><seg type="note-symbol">[228]</seg> <p>See KOHLER, L. <foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Und die 
Kirchengesch.</hi></foreign>, 139, 151. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n229"><seg type="note-symbol">[229]</seg> <p>The Archbishop of Prague was primate of the Church 
in Bohemia. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n230"><seg type="note-symbol">[230]</seg> <p>The dioceses of these bishops were contiguous to 
that the Archbishop of Prague. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n231"><seg type="note-symbol">[231]</seg> <p>Bishop of Carthage, 249-258 A.D. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n232"><seg type="note-symbol">[232]</seg> <p><foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Lass man ihn ein gut jar 
haben</hi></foreign>, literally, ""Bid him good-day." 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n233"><seg type="note-symbol">[233]</seg> <p>One of the chief points of controversy between the 
Roman Church and the Hussites. The Roman Church administered to the 
laity only the bread, the Hussites used both elements. See below, pp. 
178 f. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n234"><seg type="note-symbol">[234]</seg> <p>Luther had not yet reached the conviction that the 
administration of the cup to the laity was a necessity, but see the 
argument in the <hi rend="italic">Babylonian Captivity</hi>, below, pp. 178 ff. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n235"><seg type="note-symbol">[235]</seg> <p>The Bohemian Brethren, who are here distinguished 
from the Hussites, Cf. <foreign 
lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Realencyk.</hi></foreign>, III, 452, 49. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n236"><seg type="note-symbol">[236]</seg> <p>St. Thomas Aquinas, the great Dominican theologian 
of the XIII.  Century (1225-74), whose influence is still dominant in 
Roman theology. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n237"><seg type="note-symbol">[237]</seg> <p>The view of the sacramental presence adopted by 
William of Occam.  For Luther's own view at this time, see below, pp. 
187 ff. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n238"><seg type="note-symbol">[238]</seg> <p>i.e., If they did not believe in the real presence 
of the body and blood of Christ in the Lord's Supper. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n239"><seg type="note-symbol">[239]</seg> <p>Places for training youths in Greek glory. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n240"><seg type="note-symbol">[240]</seg> <p>The philosophy of Aristotle dominated the 
mediaeval universities. It not only provided the forms in which 
theological and religious truth came to expression, but it was the basis 
of all scientific study in every department. The man who did not know 
Aristotle was an ignoramus. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n241"><seg type="note-symbol">[241]</seg> <p>Or, "I have read him." Luther's <foreign 
lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">lesen</hi></foreign> allows of either 
interpretation. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n242"><seg type="note-symbol">[242]</seg> <p>Duns Scotus, died 1308. In the XV and XVI 
Centuries he was regarded as the rival of Thomas Aquinas for first place 
among the theological teachers of the Church. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n243"><seg type="note-symbol">[243]</seg> <p>i.e., In the universities. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n244"><seg type="note-symbol">[244]</seg> <p>See above, pp. 94 f. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n245"><seg type="note-symbol">[245]</seg> <p>i.e., "The chamber of his heart." Boniface VIII 
(1294-1303) had decreed, <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">Romanus Pontifex jura 
omnia in scrinio pectories sui censetur habere</hi></foreign>," "the 
Roman pontiff has all laws in the chamber of his heart." This decree was 
received into the canon law (c. I, <hi rend="italic">de const.</hi> in VI to (I, 2)). 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n246"><seg type="note-symbol">[246]</seg> <p><foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">Doctores 
decretorum</hi></foreign>, "Doctor of Decrees," an academic degree 
occasionally given to professors of Canon Law doctor <hi rend="italic">scrinii 
papalis</hi>, "Doctor of the Papal Heart." </p></note> 
 
<note id="n247"><seg type="note-symbol">[247]</seg> <p>The introduction of Roman law into Germany, as the 
accepted law of the empire, had begun in the XII Century. With the decay 
of the feudal system and the increasing desire of the rulers to provide 
their government with some effective legal system, its application 
became more widespread, until by the end of the XV Century it was the 
accepted system of the empire.  The attempt to apply this ancient law to 
conditions utterly different from those of the time when it was 
formulated, and the continual conflict between the Roman law, the feudal 
customs and the remnants of Germanic legal ideas, naturally gave rise to 
a state of affairs which Luther could justly speak of as "a wilderness." 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n248"><seg type="note-symbol">[248]</seg> <p>"Sentences" (<foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italic">Sententiae, libri 
sententiarum</hi></foreign>) was the title of the 
text-books in theology. Theological instruction was largely by war of 
comment on the most famous book of Sentences, that of Peter Lombard. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n249"><seg type="note-symbol">[249]</seg> <p>Cf. Vol. 1, p. 7. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n250"><seg type="note-symbol">[250]</seg> <p>i.e., Doctors. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n251"><seg type="note-symbol">[251]</seg> <p>The head-dress of the doctors. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n252"><seg type="note-symbol">[252]</seg> <p>See above, p. 118, note 2. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n253"><seg type="note-symbol">[253]</seg> <p>i.e., The monasteries and nunneries. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n254"><seg type="note-symbol">[254]</seg> <p>i.e., The name of Christian. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n255"><seg type="note-symbol">[255]</seg> <p>This section did not appear in the first edition; 
see Introduction, p. 59. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n256"><seg type="note-symbol">[256]</seg> <p>Charles the Great, King of the Franks, was crowned 
Roman Emperor by Pope Leo III in the year 800 AD. He was a German, but 
regarded himself successor to the line of emperors who had ruled at 
Rome. The fiction was fostered by the popes, and the German kings, after 
receiving the papal coronation, were called Roman Emperors. From this 
came the name of the German Empire of the Middle Ages, "the Holy Roman 
Empire of the German Nation." The popes of the later Middle Ages claimed 
that the bestowal of the imperial dignity lay in the power of the pope, 
and Pope Clement V (1313) even claimed that in the event of a vacancy 
the pope was the possessor of the imperial power (cf. above, p. 109). On 
the whole subject see BRYCE, <hi rend="italic">Holy Roman Empire</hi>, 2d ed. (1904), 
and literature there cited. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n257"><seg type="note-symbol">[257]</seg> <p>The city of Rome was sacked by the Visigoths in 410. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n258"><seg type="note-symbol">[258]</seg> <p>Luther is characteristically careless about his 
chronology. By the "Turkish Empire" he means the Mohammedan power. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n259"><seg type="note-symbol">[259]</seg> <p><foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">So sol man die Deutschen 
teuschen und mit teuschen teuschenn</hi></foreign>, i.e., made Germans 
(Deutsche) by cheating (teuschen) them. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n260"><seg type="note-symbol">[260]</seg> <p>See Cambridge <hi rend="italic">Mediaeval History</hi>, I 
(1911), pp. 244 f. </p></note> 
 
</div3> 
 
<div3 type="part" n="4" id="d15"> 
 
<list type="ordered"> 
 
<item n="1"> 
 
 
1. There is great need of a general law and decree of the German nation 
against the extravagance and excess in dress, by which so many nobles and 
rich men are impoverished. 
<ref target="n261">[261]</ref> 
 God has given to us, as to other lands, 
enough wool, hair, flax and everything else which properly serves for the 
seemly and honorable dress of every rank, so that we do not need to spend 
and waste such enormous sums for silk and velvet and golden ornaments and 
other foreign wares. I believe that even if the pope had not robbed us 
Germans with his intolerable exactions, we should still have our hands 
more than full with these domestic robbers, the silk and velvet 
merchants. 
<ref target="n262">[262]</ref> 
 In the matter of clothes, as we see, everybody wants to be 
equal to everybody else, and pride and envy are aroused and increased 
among us, as we deserve. All this and much more misery would be avoided if 
our curiosity would only let us be thankful, and be satisfied with the 
goods which God has given us. 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="2"> 
 
 
2. In like manner it is also necessary to restrict the 
spice-traffic 
<ref target="n263">[263]</ref> 
 which is another of the great ships in which money is 
carried out of German lands. There grows among us, by God's grace, more to 
eat and drink than in any other land, and just as choice and good. Perhaps 
the proposals that I make may seem foolish and impossible and give the 
impression that I want to suppress the greatest of all trades, that of 
commerce; but I am doing what I can. If reforms are not generally 
introduced, then let every one who is willing reform himself. I do not see 
that many good customs have ever come to a land through commerce, and in 
ancient times God make His people of Israel dwell away from the sea on 
this account, and did not let them engage much in commerce. 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="3"> 
 
 
3. But the greatest misfortune of the German nation is certainly the 
traffic in annuities.<ref target="n264">[264]</ref> 
If that did not exist many a man would have to 
leave unbought his silk, velvets, golden ornaments, spices and ornaments 
of every sort. It has not existed much over a hundred years, and has 
already brought almost all princes, cities, endowed institutions, nobles 
and their heirs to poverty, misery and ruin; if it shall continue for 
another hundred years Germany cannot possibly have a pfennig left and we 
shall certainly have to devour one another. The devil invented the 
practice, and the pope, by confirming it, 
<ref target="n265">[265]</ref> has injured the whole world. 
 
 
<lb/> 
 
Therefore I ask and pray that everyone open his eyes to see the ruin of 
himself, his children and his heirs, which not only stands before the 
door, but already haunts the house, and that emperor, princes, lords and 
cities do their part that this trade be condemned as speedily as possible, 
and henceforth prevented, regardless whether or not the pope, with all his 
law and unlaw, is opposed to it, and whether or not benefices or church 
foundations are based upon it. It is better that there should be in a city 
one living based on an honest freehold or revenue, than a hundred based on 
an annuity; indeed a living based on an annuity is worse and more grievous 
than twenty based on freeholds. In truth this traffic in rents must be a 
sign and symbol that the world, for its grievous sins, has been sold to 
the devil, so that both temporal and spiritual possessions must fail us, 
and yet we do not notice it at all. 
 
<lb/> 
 
Here, too, we must put a bit in the mouth of the Fuggers and similar 
corporations. 
<ref target="n266">[266]</ref> 
How is it possible that in the lifetime of a single man 
such great possessions, worthy of a king, can be piled up, and yet 
everything be done legally and according to God's will?  I am not a 
mathematician, but I do not understand how a man with a hundred gulden 
can make a profit of twenty gulden in one year, nay, how with one gulden 
he can make another; 
<ref target="n267">[267]</ref> 
 and that, too, by another way than agriculture or 
cattle- raising, in which increase of wealth depends not on human wits, 
but on God's blessing. I commend this to the men of affairs. I am a 
theologian, and find nothing to blame in it except its evil and offending 
appearance, of which St. Paul says, 1 Thess. 5:22: "Avoid every appearance 
or show of evil." This I know well, that it would be much more pleasing to 
God if we increased agriculture and diminished commerce, and that they do 
much better who, according to the Scriptures, till the soil and seek their 
living from it, as was said to us and to all men in Adam, Gen. 3:17 ff.: 
"Accursed be the earth when thou laborest therein, it shall bear thee 
thistles and thorns, and in the sweat of thy face shalt thou eat thy 
bread." There is still much land lying untilled. 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="4"> 
 
 
4. Next comes the abuse of eating and drinking 
<ref target="n268">[268]</ref> 
 which gives us 
Germans a bad reputation in foreign lands, as though it were our special 
vice. Preaching cannot stop it; it has become too common, and has got too 
firmly the upper hand. The waste of money which it causes would be a small 
thing, were it not followed by other sins, -- murder, adultery, stealing, 
irreverence and all the vices. The temporal sword can do something to 
prevent it; or else it will be as Christ says: Luke 21:34 f.: "The last 
day shall come like a secret snare, when they shall be eating and 
drinking, marrying and wooing, building and planting, buying and selling." 
It is so much like that now that I verily believe the judgment day is at 
the door, though men are thinking least of all about it. 
 
 
</item> 
<lb/> 
<item n="5"> 
 
 
5. Finally is it not a pitiful thing that we Christians should 
maintain among us open and common houses of prostitution, though all of us 
are baptized unto chastity? I know very well what some say to this, to 
wit, that it is not the custom of any one people, that it is hard to break 
up, that it is better that there should be such houses than that married 
women, or maidens, or those of more honorable estate should be outraged. 
But should not the temporal, Christian government consider that in this 
heathen way the evil is not to be controlled? If the people of Israel 
could exist without such an abomination, why could not Christian people do 
as much? Nay, how do many cities, towns and villages exist without such 
houses? Why should not great cities exist without them? 
 
 
</item> 
 
</list> 
 
<p> 
 
In this, and in the other matters above mentioned, I have tried to point 
out how many good works the temporal government could do, and what should be 
the duty of every government, to the end that every one may learn what an 
awful responsibility it is to rule, and to have high station. What good 
would it do that an overlord were in his own life as holy as St. Peter, if 
he have not the purpose diligently to help his subjects in these matters? 
His very authority will condemn him! For it is the duty of the authorities 
to seek the highest good of their subjects. But if the authorities were to 
consider how the young people might be brought together in marriage, the 
hope of entering the married state would greatly help every one to endure 
and to resist temptation. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
But now every man is drawn to the priesthood or the monastic life, and 
among them, I fear, there is not one in a hundred who has any other reason 
than that he seeks a living, and doubts that he will ever be able to support 
himself in the estate of matrimony. Therefore they live wildly enough 
beforehand, and wish, as they say, to "wear out their lust," but rather wear 
it in, 
<ref target="n269">[269]</ref> 
 as experience shows. I find the proverb true, "Despair makes most 
of the monks and priests" 
<ref target="n270">[270]</ref> 
; and so things are as we see them. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
My faithful counsel is that, in order to avoid many sins which have 
become very common, neither boy nor maid should take the vow of chastity, or 
of the "spiritual life," before the age of thirty years. 
<ref target="n271">[271]</ref> 
 It is, as St. 
Paul says, a peculiar gift. Therefore let him whom God does not constrain (1 
Cor. 7:7), put off becoming a cleric and taking the vows. Nay, I will go 
farther and say, If you trust God so little that you are not willing to 
support yourself as a married man, and wish to become a cleric only because 
of this distrust, then for the sake of your own soul, I beg of you not to 
become a cleric, but rather a farmer, or whatever else you please. For if to 
obtain your temporal support you must have one measure of trust in God, you 
must have ten measures of trust to continue in the life of cleric. If you do 
not trust God to support you in the world, how will you trust him to support 
you in the Church? Alas, unbelief and distrust spoil everything and lead us 
into all misery, as we see in every estate of life! 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Much could be said of this miserable condition. The young people have no 
one to care for them. They all do as they please, and the government is of 
as much use to them as if it did not exist; and yet this should be the chief 
concern of pope, bishops, lords and councils. They wish to rule far and 
wide, and yet to help on one. O, what a rare bird will a lord and ruler be 
in heaven just on this account, even though he build a hundred churches for 
God and raise up all the dead! 
 
</p> 
</div3> 
 
<div3 type="notes" id="d16"> 
 
 
<note id="n261"><seg type="note-symbol">[261]</seg> <p>Such a law as Luther here suggests was proposed to 
the Diet of Worms (1521). Text in WREDE, <foreign 
lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Reichstagsakten</hi></foreign>, II, 335-341. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n262"><seg type="note-symbol">[262]</seg> <p>Cf. Luther's <foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Sermon von 
Kaufbandlung und Wuche</hi></foreign> of <date value="1524">1524</date>. (Weim. Ed. 
XV, pp. 293 ff.) </p></note> 
 
<note id="n263"><seg type="note-symbol">[263]</seg> <p>Spices were one of the chief articles of foreign 
commerce in the XVI Century. The discovery of the cape-route to India 
had given the Portuguese a practical monopoly of this trade. A 
comparative statement of the cost of spices for a period of years was 
reported to the Diet of Nurnberg (1523).  See WREDE, op. cit., III, 576. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n264"><seg type="note-symbol">[264]</seg> <p>The <foreign 
lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Zinskauf</hi></foreign> or <foreign 
lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Rentenkauf</hi></foreign> was a means for evading the 
prohibition of usury. The buyer purchased an annuity, but the purchase 
price was not regarded as a loan, for it could not be recalled, and the 
annual payments could not therefore be called interest. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n265"><seg type="note-symbol">[265]</seg> <p>The practice was legalized by the Lateran Council, 
<date value="1512">1512</date>. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n266"><seg type="note-symbol">[266]</seg> <p>The XVI Century was the hey-day of the great 
trading-companies, among which the Fuggers of Augsburg (see above, p. 
97, note 5) easily took first place. The effort of these companies was 
directed toward securing monopolies in the staple articles of commerce, 
and their ability to finance large enterprises made it possible for them 
to gain practical control of the home markets. The sharp rise in the 
cost of living which took place on the first half of the XVI Century was 
laid at their door. The Diet of Cologne (1522) had passed a stringent 
law against monopolies the subject (WREDE, <foreign 
lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Reichstagsakten</hi></foreign>, II, pp. 355 ff.)  "in 
somewhat heated language" (ibid., 842), but failed to agree upon methods 
of suppression. The subject was discussed again at the Diet of Nurnberg 
(1523) and various remedies were proposed (ibid., III, 556-599). 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n267"><seg type="note-symbol">[267]</seg> <p>The profits of the trading-companies were 
enormous. The 9 percent annually of the Welser (EHRENBERG, <foreign 
lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Zeitalter der Fugger</hi></foreign>, I, 195), pales into 
insignificance beside the 1634 percent by which the fortune of the 
Fuggers grew in twenty-one years (SCHULTE, <foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Die 
Fugger in Rom</hi></foreign>, I, 3). In <date value="1511">1511</date> a certain 
Bartholomew Rem invested 900 gulden in the Hochstetter company of 
Augsburg; by <date value="1517">1517</date> he claimed 33,000 gulden profit. The 
company was willing to settle at 26,000 and the resulting litigation 
caused the figures to become public (WREDE, op. cit., II, 842, note 4; 
III pp. 574 f.).  On Luther's view of capitalism see ECK, 
<hi rend="italic">Introduction to the Sermon <foreign lang="ger">von Kaufshandlung und 
Wucher</foreign></hi>, in Berl. Ed., VII, 494-513. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n268"><seg type="note-symbol">[268]</seg> <p>The Diets of Augsburg (1500) and Cologne (1512) 
had passed edicts against drunkenness. A committee of the Diet of Worms 
(1521) recommended that these earlier edicts be reaffirmed (WREDE, op. 
cit., II, pp. 343f.), but the Diet adjourned without acting on the 
recommendation (ibid., 737) Vol. II-11</p></note> 
 
<note id="n269"><seg type="note-symbol">[269]</seg> <p><foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Sie wollen ausbuben, so 
sich's vielmehr hineinbubt</hi></foreign>. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n270"><seg type="note-symbol">[270]</seg> <p>Cf. MULLER, <foreign lang="ger"><hi rend="italic">Luther's theol. 
Quellen</hi></foreign>, 1912, ch. I. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n271"><seg type="note-symbol">[271]</seg> <p>In the <hi rend="italic">Conitendi Ratio</hi> Luther had set the 
age for men at eighteen to twenty, for the women at fifteen to sixteen 
years. See Vol. I, p. 100. </p></note> 
 
</div3> 
 
<div3 type="part" n="5" id="d17"> 
<p> 
 
Let this suffice for this time! Of what the temporal powers and the 
nobility ought to do, I think I have said enough in the little book, <hi rend="italic">On 
Good Works</hi>. 
<ref target="n272">[272]</ref> 
 There is room for improvement in their lives and in 
their rule, and yet the abuses of the temporal power are not to be compared 
with those of the spiritual power, as I have there shown. 
<ref target="n273">[273]</ref> 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
I think too that I have pitched my song in a high key, have made many 
propositions which will be thought impossible and have attacked many things 
too sharply. But what am I to do? I am in duty bound to speak. If I were 
able, these are the things I should wish to do. I prefer the wrath of the 
world to the wrath of God; they can do no more than take my life. 
<ref target="n274">[274]</ref> 
 Many 
times heretofore I have made overtures of peace to my opponents; but as I 
now see, God has through them compelled me to open my mouth wider and wider 
and give them enough to say, bark, shout and write, since they have nothing 
else to do. Ah well, I know another little song about Rome and about 
them! 
<ref target="n275">[275]</ref> 
 If their ears itch for it I will sing them that sing too, and 
pitch the notes to the top of the scale. Understandest thou, dear Rome, what 
I mean? 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
I have many times offered my writings for investigation and judgment, but 
it has been of no use. To be sure, I know that if my cause is just, it must 
be condemned on earth, and approved only by Christ in heaven; for all the 
Scriptures show that the cause of Christians and of Christendom must be 
judged by God alone. Such a cause has never yet been approved by men on 
earth, but the opposition has always been too great and strong. It is my 
greatest care and fear that my cause may remain uncondemned, by which I 
should know for certain that it was not yet pleasing to God. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
Therefore let them boldly go to work, -- pope, bishop, priest, monk and 
scholar! They are the right people to persecute the truth, as they have ever 
done. 
 
</p> 
<p> 
 
God give us all a Christian mind, and especially to the Christian 
nobility of the German nation a right spiritual courage to do the best that 
can be done for the poor Church. Amen. 
 
</p> 
 
 
 
 
 
<closer> 
<name type="place"> 
Wittenberg, 
</name> 
<date value="1520">1520. 
</date> 
</closer> 
 
 
 
 
</div3> 
 
<div3 type="notes" id="d18"> 
 
<note id="n272"><seg type="note-symbol">[272]</seg> <p>Translated in this edition, Vol. I, pp. 184 ff.; 
see especially pp.  266 ff. </p></note> 
 
<note id="n273"><seg type="note-symbol">[273]</seg> <p>These sentences did not appear in the first edition. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n274"><seg type="note-symbol">[274]</seg> <p>See <hi rend="italic">Letter to Staupitz</hi>, Vol. I, p. 43. 
</p></note> 
 
<note id="n275"><seg type="note-symbol">[275]</seg> <p>This "little song" is the <hi rend="italic">Prelude on the 
Babylonian Captivity of the Church</hi>. See below, pp. 170 ff.</p></note> 
 
</div3> 
 
</div2> 
</div1> 
 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
