<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="MauMess"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="MauMess">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The New Indian Messiah</title>
<title type="sort">new indian messiah</title>
<author>Maus, Marion P.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">14</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">MauMess</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476175</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The New Indian Messiah</title>
<title level="j">Harper's Weekly</title>
<title type="sort">new indian messiah</title>
<author>Marion P. Maus</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harper's Weekly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1890-12-06">6 Dec 1890</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 34</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Harper's Weekly 34 (6 Dec 1890): 947.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the
text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1890">1890</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>Native American</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-08">August 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>tagged with TEI-conformant SGML</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">


<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="947"/>
<head>THE NEW INDIAN MESSIAH. <lb/>
BY LIEUTENANT MARION P. MAUS, U.S.A.</head>

<p> FOR many years we have regarded the Indian's belief in a
Supreme Being as very vague and undefined.  He has, however,
appeared to recognize a "Great Spirit" and a "happy hunting-ground," the home of the departed braves &mdash; a country where beautiful
prairies and forests are abounding in game, watered by cool
streams, forming an ideal Indian heaven.  This belief seems a part
of his nature, just as his love for his free and savage life, which
the advance of civilization is forcing him to renounce.  The
buffalo is a thing of the past, and even the elk, the antelope, and
the deer have nearly disappeared, and he finds he must live on the
bounty of the white man or starve.  For years he has been confined
to military reservations, and has chafed under the restraint thus
put upon him.  Little wonder he looks for a change, and longs for
his once free life, and gladly grasps the new belief in the red
Saviour, which is rapidly spreading to every Western tribe, and
which the great chief Red Cloud "says will spread over all the
earth."
</p><p> It seems impossible to trace the exact origin of this Indian
faith.  An Indian from the upper Columbia River, named Smohalla,
preached the doctrine of an Indian Messiah some ten years ago.
This Indian taught that there would be an upheaval of nature, which
would destroy the white man, and restore to the Indian his
ancestral remains, and that the dust of countless dead Indians
would spring to life, and would surround without one word of
warning each pale-face, who will be swept from the face of the
earth.  None of the deadly weapons of civilization or skill in
their use will avail, and the blood of eighty millions of whites
will atone for the wrongs done to the red race.  Within a few
months the belief in this new religion has spread from tribe to
tribe with marvellous rapidity.  Runners have traversed thousands
of miles to reach distant tribes and bear the glad tidings.  The
Arapahoes, the Shoshones, the great Sioux tribes, the Cheyennes,
both North and South, and many other tribes, have been taught the
faith; and the "ghost dance," the religious ceremony of the creed,
is being danced by all these tribes.
</p><p> While Accompanying Major-General Nelson A. Miles and the
Northern Cheyenne Commission to the various agencies in the
Northwest where the duties of the commission took them, Mr.
Frederic Remington and I took occasion to visit the scene of the
ghost dance on a plain near the White River, on the Pine Ridge
Agency, in South Dakota.  The Indians of this reservation are Sioux
and Cheyennes, Red Cloud being the principal chief.  This sacred
dance is probably in honor of the dead braves, who will soon return
to life, and many undoubtedly believe they may appear at any
moment.  Arranged in a circle, about three hundred of them,
alternately a man and a woman, they go round and round ever in the
same direction, while the air is filled with a dirge-like chant of
a graveyard significance.  Now and then one falls down exhausted in
a death-like swoon, and is rapidly carried away, while his place is
filled.  In this swoon, it is claimed, the Indian sees and communes
with the Messiah, and learns his wishes, and what is to come to
pass.  Once seen, they claim, he is never forgotten, and again and
again appears to the favored believer.
</p><p> While at the various agencies I had the opportunity to obtain
the statements of several of the apostles of this new religion.
Porcupine seems to be the great apostle, while Red Cloud, Sitting
Bull, Little Wound, and others also are prominent.  Porcupine, in
his statement to Major Carroll of his visit to Pyramid Lake, in
Nevada, tells of the circumstances of his journey in company with
some Bannocks and Shoshones.  He undoubtedly went to Salt Lake,
travelling by rail, and then by wagon, until he reached tribes
there who belong to the fish-eating class of Indians, who largely
live west of the Rocky Mountains, and are much more civilized than
those on the other side of the Rockies.  Here, he claimed, he met
several hundred of these Indians in white men's dress &mdash; fifteen or
sixteen tribes from the east side of the Rockies were represented &mdash;
and here he claims to have received a message from the Messiah,
saying the Indians should wait fourteen days, when he would appear
to them.  They also received a white nut which they were directed
to eat.  After waiting as directed, suddenly a great crowd of
Indians and whites appeared unto them, and the Christ was among
them.  He had his head bowed, and appeared, to his astonishment, an
Indian, for, he says, "I always believed that Christ was a white
man."  The Christ said: "I have sent for you, and am glad to see
you.  I am going to talk to you about your relatives who are dead
and gone.  My children, I want you to listen to all I have to say
to you.  I will teach you how to dance a dance, and I want you to
dance it.  Get ready for your dance, and then, when the dance is
over, I will talk to you."  Then they danced, the Christ singing.
They danced until late, when he said it was enough.  "The next
morning," Porcupine continues, "I saw Christ again, and this time
he looked different; he was not as dark as an Indian, nor as light
as a white man.  He had no beard, but very heavy eyebrows.  He was
a good-looking man.  We were told not to talk; and even if we
whispered, Christ would hear us.  He talked to us all day, and
began to sing, and then trembled all over violently for a while,
and afterward sat down.  We danced all night, the Christ lying down
as if he were dead.  The next morning, when we met again, the
Christ was with us.  He said: 'I am the man who made everything you
see around you; I am not lying to you, my children.  I made this
earth, and everything on it.  I have been to heaven, and seen your
dead friends, and have seen my own father and mother.  In the
beginning, after God made the earth, they sent me back to teach the
people; and when I came, the people were afraid of me, and treated
me badly.  This is what they did to me' (showing his scars).  'I
did not try to defend myself.  I found my children were bad, sw
went back to heaven, and left them.  I told them in so many hundred
years I would come back to see my children.  At the end of this
time I was sent back to try to teach them.  My father told me the
earth was getting old and worn out, and the people getting bad;
that I was to renew everything as it used to be, and make it
better.'  He said the dead would arise, and the earth, which was
too small for them, would be enlarged, and he would do away with
heaven, and make the earth big enough for all of us; that we must
all be friends.  In the fall of the year the youth of each one
would be renewed if he remained good, and no one would ever get
over forty years old.  I have returned to my tribe," said
Porcupine, "to tell all this.  The Christ said we must tell it to
every one."  In his statement Porcupine says nothing of the
destruction of the whites.  However, it must be remembered he was
talking to an army officer who had with him three troops of
cavalry.
</p><p> Red Cloud, who heard the story from the apostles who claimed
to have seen the Messiah, said, "If it was true, it would spread
all over the world"; but wisely remarked, "If it was not true, it
would melt away like the snow under the hot sun."  Little Wound,
who also claims to have seen Christ when he appeared at the
Shoshone camp, describes him as sitting under a wickiup (the name
for a shelter made of boughs in the shape of an Indian tent, or
tepee).  "The Messiah had long hair down to his shoulders, and when
I first saw him he seemed about twenty years old; the next day he
appeared thirty; the next, forty; and the next, an old man.  He
said, 'Come with me, and I will show you your dead relatives'; and
suddenly I heard a noise like that of a railroad train.  I was
carried through the air, and came to a field with a small house on
it.  I went in, and there was my mother and father and brother who
had died long ago.  My brother and father were both killed years
ago fighting the white man.  They came up to me crying, and I shook
hands with them."  The statement of Sitting Bull how he met the
Messiah is very significant of the teaching received from
missionaries of the Christian Christ, as will be seen.  He
describes a star he saw while he was hunting, which he followed
unconsciously.  Then he came upon a large number of Indians,
including many of his old friends who had been killed in various
fights with the white men.  Black Kettle, who was killed by Custer,
he mentions especially as being among them.  They were all arranged
in a large circle, and were dancing the ghost dance.  A man came to
him, who afterward he found was the Indian Messiah.  He shook
Sitting Bull by the hand, and said, "What would you like to eat?"
Sitting Bull said he would very much like some buffalo, as it had
been a very long time since he had eaten buffalo.  The Messiah
waved his hand, and a herd of buffalo appeared, and he went out and
killed one.
</p><p> There is no doubt that most of these Indians are sincere in
their belief in this new Messiah.  It suits them exactly.  It is
not strange that there should be many versions of how the
destruction of the white race and the restoration of the happy
hunting-grounds will be accomplished.  The manner in which this
will be accomplished has been explained in various ways, but it
seems generally believed that the Indians will all fall into a
trance, and when they awake they will find the whites will have
been buried, with all their civilization, many feet beneath the
surface of the earth, never to rise again, and the Indians, with
all the dead restored to life, will remain upon the earth &mdash; renewed
and made many times more beautiful &mdash; alone to enjoy it.  No more
reservations, no more white men, no more soldiers, to disturb them;
the prairies will be covered with grass waist-deep; the forest and
mountains alike will abound in buffalo, elk, deer, and antelope,
more abundant than ever.
</p><p> Another version is that the Messiah will put all the Indians
behind him and whites before him; will then roll a stratum of earth
thirty feet deep over the earth, burying the white men and all
their work beneath.  There is little doubt but that this belief is
a perversion of the Christian religion as taught by missionaries,
and in its present form suits the wishes and hopes of the Indians.
It is also very probable that this craze is furthered by the more
intelligent and vindictive of the Indians &mdash; many of them would be
glad to see anything happen to change their condition &mdash; and is
probably furthered by designing white men who would reap the
rewards of an Indian outbreak.
</p><p> Many of the Indians have joined the Mormon faith, and it is
believed that the teachings of the Mormons have encouraged these
prophecies, in order to increase their influence with the Indians.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

