<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="McgCove"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="McgCove">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Child of the Covenant</title>
<title type="sort">child of the covenant</title>
<author>McGlasson, Eva Wilder</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">16</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">McgCove</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476177</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Child of the Covenant</title>
<title type="sort">child of the covenant</title>
<author>Eva Wilder McGlasson</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harpers</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1893-05">May 1893</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>86</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>McGlasson, Eva Wilder.  "A Child of the Covenant."
<hi rend="italic">Harper's New Monthly Magazine</hi> 86 (May 1893): 897-899.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1893-05">May 1893</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction ; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-11">November 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header; Tagged with TEI.2-compatible SGML markup; Parsed against
"teilite" dtd</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">


<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="897"/>
<head>A CHILD OF THE COVENANT. <lb/>
BY EVA WILDER McGLASSON.</head>
<p>HE was a Georgian, the landlady said.  Indeed, he said so himself,
volubly enough, when there was any one to listen.  The difficulty
seemed to be that there was seldom any one to listen at such times
as found the Georgian ready for conversation.  The other boarders
were, for the most part, young men who went to work in the morning
just as he was getting well to sleep, and who came back at the hour
when the Georgian, clean-shaved and cheerful, was going out for the
night.  He was well-favored and young, with an air of good-fellowship in his yellow mustaches, and with a gay, reckless gleam
under the wide rim of his soft hat.
</p><p>It was particularly by reason of his handsomeness that the
girl who had the room over the parlor had noticed him.  She was
herself pretty enough to pronounce upon these matters with
authority, having a dark demure presence, with a Quakerish part in
her black hair and a flutter of little curls at the brow.  She was
from Kansas, the landlady said, and was spending the winter in New
York for the study of music, a statement borne out by certain
trills and quavers and trials of voice sweetly evident now and then
in the room over the parlor.
</p><p>When the young men of the house and the rest of the boarders,
two elderly women of hygienic habits, were made known to the girl,
she bowed soberly and in silence.  The hot-water potions of the old
women amused her a little, but she regarded the matter with outward
gravity; indeed, she was always rather grave, especially in her
bearing toward the young men.
</p><p>They were commonplace, all of them; variously so, but still
commonplace.  The Georgian&mdash;she hardly saw enough of him to decide
upon him beyond the impression he gave of good-breeding and good
humor.
</p><p>Once she asked the landlady if he was a journalist, that he
seemed to work only at night.
</p><p>"God knows," said the landlady, and her tone was not pious.
</p><p>She was a large woman with a queerly screwing gait, said to
result from a leg conjecturably wooden.  She wore crinoline, too,
which gave a certain validity to the surmise, and her temper was
such as coerced tolerance for cold mutton and warm salad.
</p><p>"He comes of good family," she said.  "His mother was here to
see him in the spring.  He staid in of nights while she was in the
city.  She was more of a lady than any one I 'most ever saw, and
just wrapped up in him&mdash;thought he was the best young man living.
I liked her.  That's why I put up with him; for he's a bad lot&mdash;he
is that."
</p><p>The girl wondered dimly as to the color of his sinning.  Then
remembering the acrimony of the voice which daily arraigned the
three servants of the house, and brought forth a flood of Hibernic
retort, she concluded that the Georgian's errors were probably
those to which open natures are prone&mdash;errors likely to meet short
shrift from natures as sour and narrow as was the landlady's.
</p><p>Thinking seriously upon the matter, she mounted the narrow
stairs.  A man stood aside in the landing to let her pass.  His
yellow mustaches seemed as if fluffy with gold-dust.  His head was
deferentially bared and abased.  It was the Georgian going down to
breakfast at three o'clock of the afternoon.  There was distant
<pb n="898"/> interest in his eye as it rested on the slight figure in
dark blue serge.
</p><p>The Western girl shut her door rather sharply.  She was aware
of blushing, and was not pleased with herself.
</p><p>Concerning the Georgian she heard little for some time.  Then
one day it befell that as she stood warming her hands at the parlor
register she heard voices in the hallway.  The elder of the
hygienic ladies was in speech with the landlady, and the listless
fall of her accents carried distinctly to the girl's ears.
</p><p>"I've just had such a sweet letter from her," the old woman
was saying.  "We correspond, you know.  I wanted to read you this
part.  Let me see&mdash;oh, here it is!  'At church this morning a dear
little baby, the child of an esteemed friend of our family, was
baptized.  Our pastor in his prayer included all children who had
received the ordinance at his hands, and it was the deepest
happiness to me to reflect that my beloved and only son was one of
these&mdash;indeed, a true child of the covenant.  I long for the time
when his affairs in New York will permit him to come South finally
and forever.  I feel that I have seen too little of him, his
college life and succeeding business enterprises having kept us
apart.  There is a great deal to be done in the South.  I know he
feels this to be so, and is deeply interested in plans for the
benefit of our poorer classes.  But I fear his sympathies will do
him injury.  Last week I sent him means toward aiding a poor young
musician he had come upon in his lonely walks.  He is always
seeking out the broken and wretched.  He wrote me very pitifully of
this young man, whom he found starving in a garret.  I was very
glad, as I always am, to be able to help him.  My boy's own income
from the estate does not enable him to do all that he would.'"
</p><p>There was an indignant murmur, in which the Kansas girl
distinguished terms of protestation.
</p><p>"She ought to know!" cried the landlady.  "She ought to know
that her son's deceiving her; that he's no more than a gamester and
scamp.  Out every night of his life!  I never laid eyes onto a more
dissipated young limb.  She ought to have the wool pulled from her
eyes.  I'm not saying anything about what he owes me"&mdash;the voice
lowered as if with a thought of caution, and rose again on a tide
of accusation&mdash;"six months' board and all that.  He keeps putting
me off with promises.  I'm tired of it.  If it wasn't for his
mother I'd of showed him the door long ago.  A child of the
covenant!  Makes me laugh!"
</p><p>Of the subject of this diatribe the Kansas girl saw less and
less.  His occupancy of the adjacent room was a matter of inference
rather than of knowledge.  Late in the night his neighbor was
occasionally awakened by the sound of a fumbling step on the
stairs.  Following it would be an uncertain metallic resonance, the
aimless adjustment of a key to its lock.  Once or twice, meeting
him in the hall, the girl, though her face was averted, saw that he
looked pale and worn.  There were hard lines at his lips.  He
seemed to shrink away as she stole by.
</p><p>On a certain morning, as she came along the corridor, a maid
with a tray stopped her.
</p><p>"Would yez tourn the knab av the door for me, miss?  Me hands
is full."
</p><p>"Is any one sick?" asked the other.
</p><p>"Och!  I'll never tell av it's sick or lazy he is&mdash;the
Sootherner.  He's not lift his bed the two days, and me with me
face like beef with toastin' bread fer him that he don't touch when
I bring it."  She thrust her tray into the crack of the door.
</p><p>Presently after a doctor seemed to be coming and going.  Then
it happened that the Kansas girl heard strange sounds indeed from
the Georgian's room.  Some one in there was gay, and sang wild
staves of bar-room ballads.  Some one, too, was afraid, and from a
burst of laughter broke into a pitiful wailing for help, beseeching
that they take away the row of little fiends who sat grimacing
along the bedside.
</p><p>The doctor's voice broke through these blended sounds with a
tone of expostulation.
</p><p>"He must be sent away.  He should have been sent sooner."
</p><p>The landlady's accents were keen with decision.  She intimated
that in her own house she was mistress.
</p><p>"Oh, well," sniffed the doctor.  His voice carried a sense of
comprehension.  She meant to turn the young man's misfortune to her
own advantage, to levy a tax upon his need.  There would be
exorbitant charges.  The doctor understood, but he only said: "Oh,
well, if he's got any relatives they ought to be summoned!
<pb n="899"/>
Eh?  Can't I bring him around?  My dear lady, no physician would be
justified in making such a statement.  There is marked congestion.
He must have been going at a pretty lively pace.  They generally
pull through; but this fellow&mdash;  A mother, has he?  You'd better
telegraph."
</p><p>The landlady seemed to hesitate.  "If she should see him this
way&mdash;  I don't know."  And she added: "I'll wait.  I won't
telegraph yet.  He'll pull through.  No use throwing money away."
</p><p>The Kansas girl felt a burning indignation at the harsh
literality of this resolve.  If the landlady did not telegraph on
the morrow, she herself would send word to the Georgian's mother
that her son was down with some strange, serious attack.
</p><p>But the next morning, while it was yet dark, the landlady sent
a message to Georgia.  The child of the covenant had died at three
o'clock of the night.
</p><p>A deep silence hung over the house; doors were shut softly.
The hygienic old ladies shuddered over the parlor register, drawing
their shoulder-shawls close and talking in startled whispers.
</p><p>As the Kansas girl went up to her room, the next day but one,
she met at the head of the stairs a woman with soft white hair.  It
was not one of the women of the house.  No hint of felt insoles or
spring heels lay in the fine long foot below the trailing black
skirts.  Traces of tears blurred the stranger's lovely old face.
Her eyes were drawn and dim, but her lips, despite their quivering,
wore a look of calm.
</p><p>The girl on the stair withheld her breath at sight of the tall
black form, for the room from which it stepped was the Georgian's
room, and she knew that the visitor must be the Georgian's mother.
Had she needed other evidence the brooch at the wrinkled, slender
throat would have sufficed, for the portrait painted delicately on
the ivory was that of a blue-eyed man, who, but for his obsolete
neckcloth and arrangement of hair, might have been the Georgian's
self.
</p><p>The older woman, taking note of the scared small face below
her, paused.
</p><p>"Pardon me," she said.  "You knew my boy?  You are the young
lady who sings?  He wrote of you once.  I feel that every one he
knew must always be dear to me."  She stopped because her voice had
broken.  "I am ashamed to give way so," she added, presently.  "It
is a privilege to lose a son as I have lost mine.  The fever he
died of was nobly contracted.  In my selfish love I have warned him
against the air of the poor quarters of the city.  But his love for
his fallen brothers&mdash;"  Her eyes filled.  "He meant to do a great
work among our people.  The whole South would have felt his
influence."
</p><p>"I know," breathed the girl, "I know."
</p><p>"He had talked with you of his plans?  He did to the landlady.
She's just been telling me how kind and gentle he was, how
circumspect, how thoughtful about everything, even the little money
matters young men sometimes regard lightly.  There was none like
him.  Oh!" she broke out, "God's hand is heavy upon me, but His
mercy upholds me!  Suppose my boy had been one who wrought folly
and wickedness?&mdash;how should I have endured&mdash;"  She turned suddenly
into the room, and the girl heard her sob out, "My boy! my baby!"
</p><p>Staring through the blinds the next morning the Western girl
saw two glittering ovals just below&mdash;the polished tops of vehicles
drawn up at the curb.  Over the steps of the house came the dull
black of a box end ringed with blossomy white.  Behind it walked
the Georgian's mother.  Her unveiled face was peaceful, and the
shadow of a smile haunted her lips.  She had an air of majesty, as
of one whose motherhood is glorified by some special consecration
of the child.
</p><p>Down the brownstone steps, a foot-breadth behind the gracious
figure of the Georgian's mother, the landlady screwed her way.  Her
crinoline heaved fitfully, and she wore an oldish velvet sacque
buttoned awry.  Her tight knob of gray hair under her flat green
bonnet looked like a knot in a tree below a big leaf.
</p><p>She was red faced as ever; her eyes were like little black
beads set in baked clay.  But as she stumped along, big, uncouth,
and ridiculous, there was something about her which made the Kansas
girl's breath catch.
</p><p>There was a clatter of wheels on the stones below.  The Kansas
girl took up her music.  And in her mind was a certain vague
consciousness that the most impressive figure in the little
commonplace enactment she had been witnessing was neither the
Georgian nor the Georgian's mother.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

