<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="McnTigh"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="McnTigh">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Tale of a Tightwad</title>
<title type="sort">tale of a tightwad</title>
<author>McNutt, William Slavens</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Charles E. Keller</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">33</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">McnTigh</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476179</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Tale of a Tightwad</title>
<title type="sort">tale of a tightwad</title>
<author>McNutt, William Slavens</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Munsey's Magazine</publisher>
<date value="1916-11">November 1916</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>No. 2</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 265-272</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1916">1916</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-02">February 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>updated header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="1994-03">March 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>SGML markup</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<front id="d2">
<titlePage id="d3">
	<pb/>
<docTitle>
<titlePart type="main">
                         MUNSEY'S MAGAZINE<lb/>

                            VOLUME LIX<lb/>

                               &mdash;<lb/>

                          November, 1916<lb/>
                             Number II<lb/>
                            pp. 265-272<lb/>


                     <hi rend="italic">The Tale of a Tightwad</hi><lb/>
</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<docAuthor>
                               <hi rend="italic">by</hi><lb/>
                     <hi rend="italic">William Slavens McNutt</hi><lb/>
</docAuthor>
</titlePage>
</front>
<body id="d4">
<div1 type="chapter" n="1" id="d5">
<head>I</head>
<pb n="265"/>
<p>I like dollars same as I like race-horses," the saleslady behind
the hotel cigar-counter explained.  "I like 'em when they're
movin', an' furnishin' some excitement to the onlookers.  A race-horse packed in a can don't make anybody's heart beat faster,
does it?  No!  Well, a dollar buried for life in a bank is my
idea of nothing useful.
</p><p> "It's all right to put a race-horse in his stall now an'
then, to let him get his growth, or recover his wind for the next
heat.  But they only bed a racehorse down in a nice pile of well-combed straw so that he can show more speed when they take him
out again.  It's perfectly all right to bed a dollar down in the
bank once in a while, to let it grow a few cents an' get its
breath back; but, man, don't forget where you put the poor thing.
</p><p> "A dollar is one of the best little friends I know of, if you
just give it a chance; but you can't hide it away in the dark
forever, like as if you was ashamed to be seen with it, an' then
expect it to sit up on its hind legs an' make you laugh when you
feel blue, can you?  What?  No!  Take it out an' pal around with
it now an' then.  Give it the air.  Let it run for you before
it's too late.  A horse won't go for you after it's dead, an' a
dollar won't go for you after you're dead.
</p><p> "Buh-lieve me, no!  You may be able to come back an' haunt
your wife if she marries somebody you never did like; but after
they pull off the parade that you only go one way with, you can't
startle a dollar!  You can mail it a low moan of anguish in your
astral envelope, but you can't make it hop over the counter and
come back disguised as six bits and a good cigar.  Not after the
undertaker's cashed in his percentage on you, you can't!  A
dollar ain't superstitious.  It don't believe in spooks.
</p><p> "If a dollar's your best friend, don't give it life
imprisonment without a fair trial.  Money talks; listen to what
it says, an' do it justice.  Don't ever get the habit.
</p><p> "What habit?  Why, the economy habit.  It's deadly.  It's
worse than drugs, or whisky, or even purple socks.  A cocain
fiend may be cured till he's so sick of the drug that he has to
take to his bed when the snow falls, but a habitual tightwad will
never come loose.
</p><p> "It's an awful habit.  It sneaks up on a man so!  Some good
guy with a flap to his pocket that opens both ways starts in
economizin' to buy somethin' he

<pb n="266"/>
wants.  Before he knows
it, he gets the habit, an' by the time he's got enough laid by to
pay for what he wants    &mdash;    he don't want it.  He couldn't buy it, if
he did.  The habit's sapped his will-power till his hands won't
behave any better'n a drunken man's legs.  He can put them in his
pockets for safety's sake when company's present, but he can't
get 'em out.  He can pick up a dollar, but he can't lay it down.
The habit's got him, an' he can't break it.
</p><p> "Oh, it's awful to watch one o' these economical knots tryin'
to untie itself!  It can't be done.  They'll get a few dollars'
worth of snarl untangled after a terrible struggle, an' then, all
of a sudden, they'll wind up again in a fancy design so close-knit that if two-bit pieces were the size of a flea's eye, the
Indian penny couldn't get his nose through the cracks to breathe.
Economy's an acquired habit with most of us    &mdash;    like olives an'
grand opera; but once you get it    &mdash;    curtain!  You'll never be able
to spend any money for fun, 'cause it's no fun for an economy
victim to spend money.  An' it's a habit you'll never break away
from.  You may stray, but you'll always go back to it.
</p><p> "Did you know Henry Wiggins, that used to live here in the
hotel?  No?  He was a long, lean, solemn squizzle from somewhere
in New England.  He always looked as if he'd just read a telegram
that was as bad as he thought it was before be opened it.
</p><p> "He had a lot of money, but he didn't feel good about it.  He
never thought about how much he had; all he could think about was
how much there was in the world that he didn't have.  If he'd
ever managed to get it all, he'd have felt still worse because
there wasn't any more to get.  He invested out here in real
estate and timber.  He was the same to a dollar as a curly-haired
leadin' man to a matinee girl.  He couldn't get away from it if
he tried    &mdash;    an' he never tried!
</p><p> "He had a good character, 'cause a bad one was expensive.
His lips never touched liquor, 'cause liquor costs money, an' the
dollar that touched him never touched nobody else!  Buh-lieve me,
no!  The only thing money ever said to him was `Hello!'  After he
got done greeting it, it never spoke again.
</p><p> "How he did hate a nickel!  He hated it for not bein' a dime.
Why, the man had chronic indigestion just from worryin' over what
his food cost him, while he ate.  He couldn't get any peace in
his sleep, because he had to pay rent for the room he snored in,
an' before he went anywheres he'd sit down an' do a sum to decide
whether to walk or to ride.  If he found out that the wear an'
tear on shoe-leather an' the loss of his time totaled up less
than the fare, he'd walk.
</p><p> "It was kind o' pitiful about Henry, at that.  He honestly
thought that each time he black-jacked a dollar an' laid it away
on the ice, he'd had a real good time; but he hadn't.  He didn't
get any real fun out of it.  He thought he did, but he had a
nagging suspicion all the time that in some way he was short-changing himself; an' it preyed on his mind.  He thought he'd
found a way to beat the grand average of human happiness without
contributin' to it; an' yet away down deep inside of himself he
knew he hadn't.
</p><p> "He knew he was wrong, so he spent most of his spare time
tellin' people how right he was.  Ain't that always the way?  If
a guy's right, he don't bother spreadin' the news; but if he's
wrong, he'll pay space rates for a chance to say that he ain't.
A guilty conscience is a regular phonograph with a perpetual-motion attachment, an' a good title for the one tone it plays
would be:  `I Ain't What I Know I Am.'  Ain't it so?
</p>
</div1><div1 type="chapter" n="2" id="d6">
<head>II</head>

<p> "It was that way with Henry Wiggins.  He couldn't talk to you
for five minutes without startin' in to tell you what a good time
he had bein' unhappy.  He used to lean on the counter there an'
tell me over an' over again that his vice was virtue.  Why, if
you drove him to
<pb n="267"/>
it, he'd argue that the orphans an' widows
of the country would all go to the poorhouse if he were to loosen
up an' spend anything.  He wasn't savin' up to give to anybody
that needed it, but he'd swear that poor people were better off
because he was what he called `frugal,' and that they would be
poorer if they got any part of what he had more of than he
needed.  He knew lots of words, but he couldn't fit 'em together
in any kind of an argument that sounded reasonable.
</p><p> "I agreed with him just as long as his stuff sounded funny to
me, but after a while it got stale, an' I told him something.
</p><p> "`Do you know what?'  I says to him one day. `You ain't deep;
you're just tight.  You're just a plain, ordinary, every-day
tightwad.  There's only one reason you hang on to money the way
you do,' I says to him. `You'd rather hang on than let go.  Don't
kid yourself into thinkin' that you shine your own shoes just to
give the poor little dago bootblack time to study English an'
learn to be President or something.  You black 'em yourself
because you'd rather bend over an' work than set still an' pay a
nickel for the privilege.  You ain't denyin' yourself nothin',' I
says, `just to set some widows or orphans a good example.  You're
not stingy,' I says, `because you think you ought to be stingy.
You're stingy,' I says to him, `just  because you're stingy.
You'd have a lot more fun if you were generous, an' you know it;
but you're so stingy you won't even give yourself a good time.
You think you're pretty wise for holding out on everybody,' I
says to him.  `Wise!' I says.  `Why, you're the champion book of
the universe!  A hick that lets a con man oil him for a piece o'
change may be a foolish fish,' I says; `but if he's a sucker,
you're a whole school of whales.  You double-cross yourself.  You
sell yourself a gold brick, an' when you find out it's brass you
won't believe it.  No!  You go an' buy more o' the same.  You've
been stingy an' miserable all your life,' I says to him.  `The
answer's easy.  Two an' two make four.  Loosen up an' be happy!'
</p><p> "Do you think he got sore?  Not a chance!  Just confidential.
</p><p> "`In a way you're right,' he admits. `But at the same time
you're absolutely wrong.  I am miserable,' he says. `I never have
had any fun, and sometimes I do feel as if I was cheating myself;
but I'm not,' he says.  `I only feel that way in my moments of
weakness.  I have a system,' he says; `a system that may take
time to work out to my advantage, but it will work,' he says.
`We're all out for the most we can get out of life, aren't we?
Sure.  Now some people spend money as they get it, for this,
that, and the other thing.  They spend it to go to theaters and
dances.  They spend it for nice clothes.  They spend it for fine
apartments and expensive food.  They spend it in tips in return
for good service and a smile from the people that serve them.
They spend it for many little things each day    &mdash;    many things which
I know they don't particularly want.
</p><p> "`That's where I'm different,' Henry goes on to tell me.
`I'm not stingy; I'm just playing my system.  I'm not going to
spend a nickel that I don't absolutely have to until I see
something that I like better than I like money    &mdash;    something that I
want more than I want anything else in the world.  When I find
that thing, I'll have the money to get it, and I will get it.  No
matter what it costs, I'll get it!  When I find the one thing
that will bring me happiness, you'll see whether I'm stingy or
not!  You'll see whether I can spend money or not.  Most people
haven't the stren(yth of character to wait for big happiness.
They must have it every day in retail lots.  I'm different.  I'm
going to wait until I find what I've absolutely got to have to
make me happy, and when I find it I'll be able to get it.  You
bet I will!  That's my system,' he says.  `I'm no fool!'
<pb n="268"/>
</p><p> "`Then you're a fine imitation,' I says.  `Accordin' to all
I've been able to dope out, the Lord figured out this game of
life pretty well.  He made happiness the reward for winnin' at
it, an' laid out a system of play that don't jibe with the one
you follow.  Accordin' to His system, a tip an' a kind word to
the bootblack in the mornin' entitles you to a chip o' happiness
out of the main pot.  The more you feed the kitty that goes to
them that ain't got the price to buy in on the big game, the more
luck you have with the hands you hold.  You've got into the habit
of cheatin' yourself, Mr. Wiggins,' I says.  `An' when you want
to hand yourself a square deal, you won't be able to break the
habit,' I says.
</p><p> "`Ah,won't I?' he says.  `You'll see!'
</p><p> "An' I saw!
</p>
</div1><div1 type="chapter" n="3" id="d7">
<head>III</head>

<p> "Wiggins was standin' right here by the counter, talkin' to
me, when he first laid eyes on Lily Martin.  As he watched her
walk across the lobby to the elevator his eyes bulged out till
they looked like a couple of blue glass marbles that was just
about to fall an' break.
</p><p> "`What a lovely girl!' he says.  `I wish I could meet her.'
</p><p> "I laugh.
</p><p> "`Lay off!' I says to him.  `Lily Martin an' her mother
haven't got any too much money of their own,' I says; `but
there's a whole flock of money goats blatting with sorrow because
Lily won't take all they've got    &mdash;    an' them, too!  Men,' I says to
him, `fight for the chance to spend regular money on her, an'
only the lucky ones get it.  You,' I says, `don't spend enough on
clothes in a year to buy her flowers for a week.  She ain't
accustomed to tightwads,' I says to him.
</p><p> "`But I want to meet her,' he says.  `I want to!'
</p><p> "I seen he meant it, an' it struck me funny.  I could see him
spendin' the evenin' with Lily Martin, an' askin' her to take a
walk around the block or have a stick of gum; so I told him I'd
fix it for him, an' then I got in touch with Bert Edgeley.
</p><p> "Bert was a fine scout.  Money was the only desirable thing
he didn't have.  He was a young mining-engineer, an' he was doin'
fine, both with his profession and with Lily Martin.  He was all
there with her that spring.  Her mother was a little sour on him
because he didn't have a check-book like some, but what he lacked
with the mother he made up with Lily, buh-lieve me!  So I got
hold of Bert an' gave him the straight dope about Wiggins.
</p><p> "`He's got a crush on Miss Martin,' I tell him. `If he gets a
chance to meet her, he'll probably buy a new fifty-cent tie to
make an impression.  After he's kicked in with the price of an
ice-cream soda, he'll think he's got some kind of a claim on her,
an' say things fit to laugh at,' I says.  `Put Miss Martin wise
first,' I says, `an' then make this human astringent known to
her.  There's some comedy in it,' I says to Bert.
</p><p> "An' he fell for it.  I introduce him to Wiggins, an' Bert
promises to take him to call on Miss Martin that night.  It was a
laugh from the start.  Wiggins was as excited as if somebody was
goin' to pay him a dollar he hadn't expected to get.  While he
was still talkin' to me about how glad he was to get the chance
to meet her, she come out of the elevator an' crossed the lobby
to the desk.  Wiggins squared off an' took a good, keen, Yankee
squint.  When she'd gone out, he turned to me, an' he says:
</p><p> "`That's the prettiest girl I ever saw in my life,' he says.
`I want her!' he says.  `I want her more than I ever yet wanted
anything, and I know,' he says, I that once I get acquainted with
her, I'll want her a darn sight more than I do now.  You think
I'm a tightwad,' he says.  `Now I'll show you that I'm not.  I've
seen what I want,' he says, `and I've got the money to help me
get it.  You'll see!'
</p><p> "I'll say one thing for the simp    &mdash;    he didn't waste no time.
I'd never seen <pb n="269"/> him with a suit of clothes on that cost him
more than ten dollars.  That night he showed up to meet Bert all
togged out in evening clothes and a top-hat; an' he had a bunch
of violets an' a box of candy for Miss Martin.  It was a real box
of candy, mind you, not a scoopful out of a bucket.  Honest!  For
the first time in his life, he'd gone an' spent good money on
himself just to get ready to meet her.
</p><p> "An' you know what?  He wasn't bad-lookin' when he was
dressed decent.  No, he wasn't.  I'd come to think of him as a
kind of a slob, seein' him togged out cheap, as I always had; but
with regular clothes on he was kind of handsome in a lean,
hungry, serious sort of way.  He looked real striking.
</p><p> "Well, he met Lily Martin according, to schedule, but what
come after the meeting come different than anything I'd planned.
Say, man!  The dead one come to life    &mdash;    honest he did.  An' such a
life!  Dinners an' dances an' parties an' theaters an' flowers!
All for Miss Martin, all paid for by Tightwad Wiggins that had
never so much as paid for havin' his shoes shined up to then.
</p><p> "An' he made people think he liked to part with his dough.
That was the weird part of it.  He ponied up with a smile; an' if
the smile was forced, it didn't show to the naked eye.  He put up
a campaign of entertainment that made Lily Martin an' her mother
dizzy with the speed of it. He paid for it, an' made 'em think it
come natural to him.  Oh, he was an actor!  I got to give him
credit.
</p><p> "Bert Edgeley had gone an' primed Miss Martin for a funny
hick that would give them all a good laugh if she would agree to
take a few minutes off an' meet him; an' instead o' that, Wiggins
give her the time of her young life.  How was she to know that
Henry had switched the cut on Bert?  It seemed to her that
Edgeley had gone an' slandered a lovely gentleman.  He only made
it all the worse by tryin' to explain to her that Wiggins was
really funny; that the money he was spendin' on her was the
biggest joke of all, an' all that.  No chance!  She was off Bert,
who was no gentleman to speak ill of such a splendid fellow as
Henry Wiggins, an' Henry had the inside track.
</p><p> "`You're a fine tipster!'  Bert says to me.  `I thought you
told me this Wiggins was a kind of something that ought to be in
vaudeville!  Didn't you say he spent his time alone because he
was too stingy to share with a friend?  What?  He's in and I'm
out.  I've tried to laugh, but there's nothing funny about it.
It's getting serious!'
</p><p> "`It won't last,' I tell him.
</p><p> "`No,' he says.  `Life won't last    &mdash;    not forever.  That's no
helpful hint.  You touted me into this; can't you tout me
out?'
</p><p> "`Don't worry,' I says.  `The man's a habitual tightwad.
He's playin' a part, an' playin' it fine,' I says, `but he'll
make a mistake.  He smiles while he's spendin' all this dough,' I
says; `but the smile hurts, buh-lieve me!  He'll forget an' groan
some o' these days, an' she'll get a chance to see him as be is.
Don't worry!'
</p>
</div1><div1 type="chapter" n="4" id="d8">
<head>IV</head>

<p> "But Bert did worry, an' so did I.  I liked Miss Martin, an'
I was gettin' scared for fear this Wiggins was goin' to play the
part outright up to the altar an' spend like a prince till the
weddin'-bells rung for him.  I knew what would happen to Lily
Martin if he ever got her that far.  She'd never lay eyes on a
thin dime from the time she once said `I do.'  Can you imagine
what Henry Wiggins would turn into after spendin' what he had
spent to get a woman, an' gettin' her?  Well, I can!
</p><p> "Wiggins was on my nerves, too.  He was so blamed triumphant!
Every time he come over to the stand here to buy a paper he'd tip
me a quarter.  Him that had never bought papers before!  Him that
had always sneaked into the lobby an' picked up the news of the
day second-hand from some crumpled sheet that a <pb n="270"/> human being
had read and thrown away.  He'd buy his own an' tip me a quarter!
</p><p> "`You're doin' pretty well,' I says to him one day, real
snappy.'  But don't bother to hand me any more quarters,' I says.
`I don't want blood-money,' I says.  `You act as if you liked it,
an' you act pretty well; but I know you bleed internally from the
rupture every time you jar yourself loose from one of these two-bit pieces.'
</p><p> "`You remember what I told you?' he says, still smilin'. `I
was never stingy.  I was simply saving my money to buy happiness
with when I saw what I knew would make me happy.  I've seen it,
and I don't think any one can acuse me now of being a tightwad.'
</p><p> "`No,' I says, `not now; but I know that the punishment
you're undergoin' is somethin' frightful.  You're doin' well, but
you can't stand the pain forever.'
</p><p> "`I'm having the time of my life,' he says, with a smile
still workin'.  `This is what I've had the strength to wait for.'
</p><p> "Oh, Wiggins was game!  He had the money, an' he sure spent
it like a drunken sailor.  Miss Martin said something about
liking to take a little trip among the islands in the Sound, and
Wiggins just carelessly steps out and buys the White Wave, a
forty-five-foot yacht, to take her where she wanted to go.  Can
you beat it?  He could have rented something, but he buys it!
That little boat was second-hand, but it stood him in a good five
hundred dollars in real money    &mdash;    an' just because she said she
would like the trip!  It had me beat.
</p><p> "They made up a party for the voyage, an' got the boss here
to let me off to go along as a kind of general ladies' maid an'
stewardess.  Bert Edgeley was along, an' five others besides
Wiggins an' the Martins, Bert was just as happy as a Mexican
hairless dog at the north pole.  He was playin' Wiggins's cards
for him right along, the poor simp!  Bert knew what Wiggins
really was.  Miss Martin had never seen him in his natural state,
so poor Bert's grouch goes with her for unmanly jealousy of a
generous and gentlemanly rival    &mdash;    an' he acts accordingly.
</p><p> "`I tried to give her the low-down on this fellow Wiggins,'
he says to me.  `I suppose it doesn't seem right to knock him
when I'm his guest, but great Scott, you an' I know that he's not
human!  I just can't sit by and see Lily fooled by a thing like
him; but when I try to tell her what he is, she thinks I'm
jealous of him.  An' I am,' he says.  `He's carried his bluff so
far, I'm worried white!'
</p><p> "`He'll crack,' I says, an' tried to think I meant it; but I
couldn't.  Henry Wiggins had my goat.
</p>
</div1><div1 type="chapter" n="5" id="d9">
<head>V</head>

<p> "It was fine sailin' down the Sound the first day out, but
about noon of the second we run into a bank of fog you couldn't
see ten feet through.  They shut her down to half speed, an' went
nosin' through it, blowin' the fog-whistle an' tryin' to keep a
general guess on where we were headin' for.  There'd been quite a
breeze in the mornin', an' there was a nasty little chop left.
We went wallowing through it for about half an hour, an' then,
all of a sudden, whang, crash, lickety-bang!  We hit a rock hard
enough to knock out a prize-fighter that's as good as he says he
is.  The bow of that boat scooted up on a nice little
accommodatin' wave that couldn't stay long, an' when the wave
moved on, the poor bow fell on that rock.  Some fall!  It knocked
a hole in the boat big enough for a good-sized river to run
through without gettin' dammed up.  The men got the life-boat
busy, an' found we were only a few yards from shore.  They got us
all off all right, but speed was necessary.  That five-hundred-dollar beauty of Wiggins's was spoilin' herself on that rock
mighty fast.
</p><p> "Scared as I was, I took pains to watch an' see if he'd
squeal.  He didn't.  When we got ashore, I took pains to mention
what a shame it was that the boat should be a total loss to him,
so soon after he'd bought it, an' he just laughed.
</p><p> "`There are other boats,' he says, in <pb n="271"/> an offhand way.
`I'm only troubled about this unavoidable inconvenience to the
ladies.'
</p><p> "We'd landed on a little beach at the foot of some high
rocks, an' we sat there for a half-hour or so, wonderin' where we
was.  Then the fog lifted, an' we got a little peek around.  We
was on one o' them steep little rocky islands that a mountain
goat couldn't make a mile an hour across.  It was a cinch that
wherever we was goin' from where we were, we wouldn't travel
afoot.  The only way away from there was by water.
</p><p> "The captain squinted around a little an' located himself.
He said we were only about two miles from Uniondale.
</p><p> "`Well, of all good fortune!' Wiggins chirps up, as happy as
a canary sounds.  `Uniondale, eh?  Well, we won't have to forego
our trip after all.  Just before I bought the White Wave a chap
from Uniondale approached me and tried to sell me his boat.  She
was in the harbor at Uniondale, and I didn't want to take the
time to run across here and look her over, so I bought the White
Wave.  I'll just row the two miles up to Uniondale with the
captain, buy the boat that's there, and return for you people in
a jiffy.  I understand it's a better boat than the White Wave
was, anyway.'
</p><p> "Just like that!  Five hundred dollars gone on the rocks, an'
he was happy 'cause he had the chance to spend another wad right
away quick.  Of course, every one tried to argue him out of doing
any such thing, but he wouldn't be dissuaded.  Not him!  An' he
was the Henry Wiggins that up to two months before that time
wouldn't tip his hat, if he could help it, on account of the wear
an' tear on the brim!
</p><p> "`If it should happen that I'm not able to buy the vessel I
have in mind, I'll hire some craft and come back for you at
once,' he says.  `I'm sorry on account of the inconvenience you
have been put to.'
</p><p> "So he got into the life-boat with the captain, an' they
rowed away for Uniondale.  All the rest of us, except Bert an'
me, sat there  an' said what a fine an' wonderful man Henry
Wiggins was.
</p>
</div1><div1 type="chapter" n="6" id="d10">
<head>VI</head>

<p> Well, we kept right on sitting.  Two hours went by, an' still
we sat.  Another hour passed, an' it began to rain, an' still we
sat.  Wiggins an' the captain had had time to row to Uniondale
an' get a boat built, it seemed to us, an' still we sat.  We got
soaking wet and shivering cold.  Some of the women begun to cry,
an' all the men begun to swear.  We wondered if Wiggins an' the
captain had been drowned, or if they'd only been wrecked again
an' were yet alive.  We wondered for a while, an' by an' by we
got so cold an' wet we didn't care.
</p><p> "It was pretty near dark when at last a fishin'-boat came
along an' we hailed it.  The fishermen put off a rowboat an' took
us aboard, an' we started for Uniondale.  There wasn't any cabin
on that fishing-boat, an' we were gettin' colder an' wetter all
the time.  We'd gone about a mile when we see a couple of men in
a boat in near shore.
</p><p> "`It's Wiggins an' the captain,' Edgeley says, an' the
fishermen steered in toward them.
</p><p> "It was Wiggins an' the captain, all right.  They was havin'
high words.  We could hear the captain speakin' his mind in a way
no hired man should speak to the guy that pays him.  We run
alongside of them an' stopped.
</p><p> I never see such anguish as there was on Wiggins's face.  He
seen us, but he hardly took notice.  The captain was different.
</p><p> "`Don't none of you people blame me,' he says in a loud
voice.  `This man Wiggins is crazy.  I been tryin' to get him to
go on for hours, an' he wouldn't budge.  The idea of him lettin'
you people set back there in the rain, an' likely get your death
of cold!  It ain't my fault.  He's crazy, I tell you!'
</p><p> "`But it's right down there between those two little rocks,'
Wiggins says.  `It's <pb n="272"/>
easy to get at.  I could get it, if I
wasn't so short-winded.  I can't stay under long enough to feel
around for it.  Won't you please try, captain?  It's right there
between those two little rocks, and the water's hardly up to your
neck now the tide's gone out so.'
</p><p> "`No, I won't try!' the captain yells at him.  `You're
crazy!'
</p><p> "`What's the matter?' Bert Edgeley says.
</p><p> "`I was sitting here counting my change while the captain
rowed, and I dropped a five-dollar gold piece overboard,' Wiggins
wails, wringin' his hands.  `It's right down there between those
two little rocks.  I know right where it is.  I could get it
easy, if I could hold my breath long enough to hunt around for
it.  Couldn't you just try for it once?  I'll show you right
where it is!'
</p><p> "Lily Martin stepped to the rail of the boat an' looked down
at Wiggins.  Her teeth had been chatterin' with the cold for two
or three hours, but she seemed to be warm enough all of a sudden.
</p><p> "`Have you been hunting for that five-dollar gold piece all
afternoon?' she asks in a tone of voice that would have made
Jesse James throw up his hands on suspicion.
</p><p> "Wiggins looks at her, an' I'll swear he hardly saw her.  His
mind was where it belonged    &mdash;    on money.
</p><p> "`It's right down there between those two little rocks,' he
says, like a kid recitin' a piece.  `It's only about five feet
under water, now that the tide's gone out so far.'
</p><p> "Lily turned her back on him an' held out her hand to Bert
Edgeley.
</p><p> "`I beg your pardon, Bert,' she says.  `I didn't understand!'
</p><p> "One of the boys give the fisherman the high sign, an' he
started the engine.  Wiggins scarcely paid any attention to our
leavin'.  He was too busy pleadin' with the captain to dive down
an' make a try for the five-dollar gold piece that was just
between the two little rocks.  The last we seen of the two of
'em, the captain was rowin' after us an' swearin' a blue streak.
Wiggins was standin' up, wringin' his hands an' beggin' for the
captain to wait an' let him make just one more try for it.  The
habit had him!
</p><p> "Wiggins moved from the hotel here to cheaper quarters, as
soon as he got back to town, an' I didn't see him for near six
months.  Then one afternoon I was leanin' over the counter,
readin' the account of Lily Martin's marriage to Bert Edgeley,
when Henry come shufflin' in.  He looked seedier an' sadder than
ever.
</p><p> "`I see they're married,' he says to me.  `I'm glad I
escaped!  I must have been mad, for a time,' he says.  `It was a
terrible expense!  You wouldn't believe how much I spent!'
</p><p> "You can't get away from it, I tell you.  It ain't done.
Economy's a nice pastime, but it's a terrible habit!"</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
