<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="MonPonc"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
]><TEI.2 id="MonPonc">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Ponca Account</title>
<title type="sort">ponca account</title>
<author>Montiero, Lorrie</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
<name>Montiero, Lorrie</name>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Thompson, Carolyn</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name>Thompson, Carolyn</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>American Native Press Archives and Sequoyah Research Center, University of Arkansas at Little Rock (http://www.anpa.ualr.edu)</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">23</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">MonPonc</idno>
<date value="2004-07-22">July 22, 2004</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2004 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476239</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">July 22, 2004</title>
<title type="sort">july 22, 2004</title>
<author>Lorrie Montiero</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
<name>Lorrie Montiero</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition. <date value="2004-07-22">July 22, 2004</date>
</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>Little Rock, Ar.</pubPlace>
<date value="2004-07-22">July 22, 2004</date>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the UALR American Native Press Archives and Sequoyah Research Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>Spell-check made against printed text using Microsoft Word spell checker.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's unique
cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of Jane
Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>White Eagle</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="text" id="d3">
<head>Ponca Account</head>
<byline>Edited by Lorrie Montiero</byline>
<div2 type="statement" id="d4">
<head>
<hi rend="bold">White Eagle edited by Lorrie Montiero</hi>
</head>
<p>WHITE EAGLE'S STATEMENT REGARDING THE REMOVAL OF THE PONCA INDIANS FROM
DAKOTA TERRITORY TO THE INDIAN TERRITORY.</p>
<p>Indian Territory, May 20, 1879</p>
<p>The following statement was made to me by White Eagle, the head chief of the
Ponca tribe. I translated it into English for him and give it just as he
gave it to me. My father and I had been sent by Mr. T.H. Tibbles to the
Ponca Reserve to find out the condition of the tribe, and gather all the
information we could. They told us of many things of which we could not tell
the half, and White Eagle asked me to write this statement for him so that
it could be read by all the white people.</p>
<p>BRIGHT EYES [Susette La Flesche].</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="work" id="d5" n="1">
<head>White Eagle's Statement</head>
<p>In the spring of 1877 we were all living quietly on our farms and at
work. We have been working on our farms for the last three years, and we
had laid plans to work harder than ever during the year of 1877, when
suddenly there came to our reserve a white man who professed to have
come from the President. His name was Kimble. He called us all to the
church, and we went. We had seen this man before, and he had appeared to
be a good friend of ours. He said to us: "The President has sent me with
a message to you. He has sent me to tell you that you must pack up and
move to Indian Territory." I answered him by saying, "Friend, I thought
that when the President desired to transact business with people he
usually consulted with them first, and then transacted his business with
them afterward. This is the first that I have heard of his desire to
remove us. Here are some men from the Yankton, Santee, and Omaha tribes,
and here are also some soldiers who are friends of ours; I ask them if
they have heard of this before. They have not. This has come on us
suddenly. Give us time to think about it. Although I am an Indian, I
want to tell God all about this before I do anything more. I want to
know and see for myself what I had better do. I want to ask God to help
me to decide."</p>
<p>I continued, "Now friends, if what you have told us from the President is
true, raise your hands." Kemble, the leading man, refused to raise his
hands. Hinman, who was with him, raised his hand, not up towards God,
but low down toward the ground. Kemble then jumped to his feet and said,
"The President told me to take you to the Indian Territory, and I have
both hands full of the money which it will require to move you down
there. When the President says anything it must be done. Everything is
settled, and it is just the same as though you were there already." I
answered, "I have never broken any of my treaties with the government.
What does the President want to take my land away from me for? The
President told me to work, and I have done it. He told me to not go on
the warpath, even if the white men took away my horses and cattle, or
killed my people. I promised I would not, and I have performed my
promise. Although other people often move from place to place, yet I
have always staid on our land. It is ours. My people have lived and died
on this land as far back as we can remember. I have sown wheat and
planted corn and have performed all my promises to the President. I have
raised enough on my farm to support myself, and now it seems just as
though the government were trying to drown me when he takes my land away
from me. We have always been peaceful. The land is our own. We do not
want to part with it. I have broken no treaties, and the President has
no right to take it from me."</p>
<p>Kemble arose and said, "Stop your talking; don't say any more. The
President told me to remove you as soon as I got here. The President is
going to send all the Indians to the Indian Territory. He intends you to
move first, so that you can have your choice of the best lands there.
You can do nothing. What the President has said will be done. I do not
want to say any more on this subject. The President says you must move;
get ready." I answered, "When people want to do anything, they think
about it first, talk about it with others, and then, after deliberation,
they decide. I want to think about it. I want to see the President and
talk the whole matter over with him, and then I will do what I think
best. I know it will not be to give up our land. You have no right to
move us in this way without our consent or will." Kemble then said, "You
must go right away. The President intends to the Santees and Yanktons
also, and I shall start tomorrow to tell them so."</p>
<p>The next day he started for the Sioux and returned. I again talked with
him. I said, "It will cost a great deal of money to remove us. Let the
President keep his money. We do not want it. It might hurt him to part
with it. Take the money, which you said you brought, back to him. We do
not want to use it, and we do not want to part with our land."</p>
<p>Kemble said, "The President has plenty of money and he will not miss it."
I said, "God made me and He also made you. Perhaps He made you long
before He did me, and that may be the reason that you, as a nation, are
more enterprising and powerful than we are. But God made me. I was born
here. He gave me this land, and it is mine. When your people first came
here and asked for our land our forefathers sold you some. When our
fathers sold you this land they made a treaty with your government,
which I now hold in my hand, and it is stated here how much was sold to
you and how much remained to us; and it is also stated here that the
land that we did not sell was ours. It belongs to none but us until we
choose to sell it. The government has no right to it. It is ours and we
do not wish to part with it.</p>
<p>Kemble answered by saying, "The President says that the treaty is
worthless. It will not do you any good. The President does not count it
as anything. When you get to the new country the President will give you
a new treaty, and you shall have a good title to your land there. As you
do not believe the President's message I will send a telegram to him."
The next day he brought the return telegram, and said, "I will read it
to you. You will see for yourselves whether what I have told you is true
or not. The President says in this telegram that he wants ten of your
chiefs to go to Washington, but he wants me first to take you to the
Indian Territory and see for yourselves, so that you may select a piece
of land there, and then go on to Washington afterwards to talk it over."
I answered, "We will go with you. If we are satisfied with the land we
will tell the President so, but if we are not satisfied we will say so also."</p>
<p>He then took us ten chiefs down there, and left us in Indian Territory
without money, pass, or interpreter, in a strange country, among a
strange people, because we would not select a piece of land. He wished
us to sign a paper saying that we would take that piece of land, and
because we would not, and asked to be taken to Washington as he had
promised, he left us to find our way back alone on foot. We could not
believe that he had been authorized to treat us with such indignity, and
we could not believe that the white people of the country would let such
a wrong done in their name pass unnoticed; so, on our return to the
Omaha Reserve, after enduring great hardship on the way, we made a
statement of all the facts, requesting a friend to see that it was
published in a paper. We also sent a telegram to the President, asking
him if he has authorized these men to treat us in this manner; but we
never received any answer.</p>
<p>After we had left the Omaha Reserve and had nearly reached home, we found
Kemble and some soldiers already there. They had frightened our people
and forced them to move in our absence, and they were just starting from
the reserve. When we met our people we said to them, "Stop. Do not go
on. When a man owns anything it is his until he gives it or sells it.
This land is ours. We have not given or sold it to the President. He has
no right to it. When we were left in the Indian Territory we believed
that the government had left us alone for good; and now we find that
this man has come back here, bringing the soldiers, and forcing you to
move in our absence. Do not go any further." They obeyed us.</p>
<p>Two days after our return home Kemble sent for us again. When we reached
the place we found the soldiers there, all armed, and Kemble sitting by
the side of an officer. I gave the treaty to the officer to examine. I
said to him, "I have never done anything wrong against the white people.
I have never broken any treaties. Now what have I done that your
soldiers stand here all armed against me? I have been working on my
land. I have done that which I thought my duty. I believed that your
soldiers were stationed here to protect me against all wrong and injury.
Now show me what I have done that you stand here with your soldiers in
arms against me? I have helped your soldiers. I have helped the white
people who live around here. I have always been peaceful. When the Sioux
carried off your cattle and horses and property, I have had it returned
to you when in my power. I thought that you, at least, would help me in
my time of trouble. Why do I find you here now armed against me? We had
always believed that your government had ordered your soldiers to
protect those who were peaceful and doing their duty, and to punish and
bear arms only against those who had committed crimes. A short time ago
I was here at work on my land. I was taken and left in the Indian
Territory to find my way back alone. I thought that after being treated
in the manner we were by this man, that when I came home I would find a
protection from my enemy in you. And now, instead, I find you armed
against me." I then turned to Kemble and said, "You profess to be a
Christian, and to love God; and yet you would love to see blood shed.
Have you no pity on the tears of these helpless women and children? We
would rather die here on our land than be forced to go. Kill us all here
on our land now, so that in the future when men will ask, 'Why have
these died?' it shall be answered, 'They died rather than be forced to
leave their land. They died to maintain their rights. And perhaps there
will be found some who will pity us and say, 'They only did what was right."</p>
<p>Kemble answered, "If blood is shed you only will be in fault. You only
will be the cause. You have exceeded the time in which the President
gave you to move by a good many days."</p>
<p>White Swan, or Frank La Flesche, then spoke to Kemble, and said, "You
have been here several times before. You professed to be a great
Christian and one of the chief ministers among your people. You preached
to us and told us about God. You told me to give myself to him and join
his people. I was willing and you baptized my family and myself. You
held me by the hand and said you were my friend, and I looked on you as
such. I never thought that you would ever try to lead me into the great
fire, the hell of your people. You told me that God loved us all; that
he had made laws which he wanted us to keep, and I promised that I would
try to keep them. When you asked me to keep these laws, I said to
myself, 'He is a good friend; he tells me good things, and wants me to
do right and to walk the god road.' I did not think then that you would
ever try to lead me into a bad road. You told me that God saw everything
we did. If so, He has seen the wrong and wickedness in this matter. When
I was baptized, and promised God that I would do as He wanted me to, I
meant it, and now (raising his hand to heaven) I call on God to witness
that I have tried to keep my promise; but you have lied to him. He is
the judge that I speak the truth. When you left us in Indian Territory I
thought that you had gone to tell the President that we refused to give
up our land; and now I come home to find that you have not. You said you
wanted to save my soul from hell when I should die; but now I find that
you wish to send my soul to hell while I am yet living, and I wish to
keep out of it. You professed to be our friend. Could you not so much as
have said to the President, 'These people do not want to part with their
land. You are powerful and they are weak. Have mercy on them and do not
make them go.' Could you not have done this much after all your
professions of friendship? I would like to see you go to a white man
yonder, who is living on his farm, and say to him, 'Get off from here,
the President wants this land and you must move on and go somewhere
else.' What do you suppose he would answer? The President has no more
right to take our land from us than he has that of the white man."</p>
<p>Kemble answered, "What you have said about God is all right; but this
business I have come to tend to has nothing to do with God or anything
of the kind. It is another subject altogether. You had better not say
that I want to lead you into hell. I want to lead you into the good
road. It is you who want to take the bad road. You ought to be on the
road to the Indian Territory by this time. The President will get out of
patience; so I want you to start tomorrow. The President wanted me to do
this errand as soon as I got here, but you have kept me waiting this
long. The President has sent me word that if you refuse to go I must
push you out. Your head-chief, White Eagle, has talked of the shedding
of blood rather than go. I did not want you to let God hear you say such
a thing, but he has heard you. This is all I have to say, and now I give
you in charge of this officer and his soldiers."</p>
<p>Then the Indian chief of the police arose and said: "Our chiefs here have
appointed me captain of our police, but they did not appoint me to bear
arms against the weak and innocent, but that I might help and protect
them. Your officer has brought his soldiers armed against my tribe. I
shall not resist him. If he chooses to kill us, unarmed as we are, he
can do it. You say your President has sent the money by you which is to
take us to the Indian Territory. Take it back to your President. We will
not leave our land, and we are afraid of the land in the Indian
Territory. Take your money home. When you took our chiefs to the Indian
Territory, you took some money to pay for their fare there. If the money
belonged to the President, we want you to give it back to him from our
own fund. This fund is the money which we received in payment for our
land which we sold." The man who made this speech was one of the first
to die when we reached the Indian Territory.</p>
<p>The next morning after this council the soldiers, some on horses and some
in wagons, went around to the houses, and where they found the doors
locked (for some of the people had shut up their houses and fled to the
woods), kicked or broke them open, and put their household goods, such
as could be carried with ease, into the wagons. In this way Kemble
started off with a party composed of about ten families, while the
soldiers remained behind with the rest of us. After this first party had
been carried off, I took an interpreter with me to Niobrara City, and
there found a lawyer, to whom I stated all these facts, and telling him
that I thought the whole thing had been done unlawfully; asked him to
help us maintain our rights. I wanted him to send a telegram to the
President, asking him whether he knew of what had been done in his name.
The lawyer said, "I will do so if you give me the money to pay for it."
I answered that I had no money, but that I had a horse which I could
sell to pay for the telegram. The lawyer sent a telegram, but he never
received an answer.</p>
<p>Meanwhile the first party, which Kemble had taken, had been left by him
on the other side of Niobrara, while he himself went to Washington. I
then collected those of us who were yet on the reserve together and,
gathering thirty four of our horses, we sold them to pay the lawyer's
expenses to Washington. When the lawyer got to Washington and went to
see the President, he found Kemble sitting and talking with him. While
we were awaiting the lawyer's return, we almost starved, as Campbell had
taken the provisions which belonged to us and carried them away with the
first party. After some time, the lawyer sent a telegram saying that he
had been unable to do anything for us, except to keep them from
fulfilling threat of starving and treating us with indignity on the way
down because of our refusal to go.</p>
<p>Before the lawyer had time to return, a new agent by the name of Howard
was sent to take us down. He remained on the other side of the river and
sent for us to come down, but we refused to go. He sent again, and went
to him. The place where we met him was in a wild place by the river
side. He spoke kindly to us, and was the first and only who did so of
those who had been sent from Washington. He said: "Friends, although I
am white and you are Indians, I am a man just as you are, and have a
heart just the same as yours. I know you have been treated unjustly, and
I feel sorry for you; but I cannot help you. The President has sent me
to take you down. I will do all in my power to make the journey
comfortable for you so that you may not suffer." I said to him, "Friend,
it is good when men meet as friends and talk kindly to each other. You
have spoken the first kind word we have heard for a long time. We had
made up our minds to resist and die on our own land rather than go to a
strange one to die; but, now you have come, we do not know what we will do."</p>
<p>We then separated, and calling all the men of our tribe together, I said
to them, "My people, we, your chiefs, have worked hard to save you from
this. We have resisted until we are worn out, and now we know not what
more we can do. We leave the matter into your hands to decide. If you
say that we fight and die on our lands, so be it." There was utter
silence. Not a word was spoken. We all arose and started for our homes,
and there we found that in our absence the soldiers had collected all
our women and children together, and were standing guard over them. The
soldiers got on their horses, went to all the houses, broke open the
doors, took our household utensils, put them in their wagons, and
pointing their bayonets at our people, ordered them to move. They took
all our plows, mowers, hay-forks, grindstones, farming implements of all
kind, and everything too heavy to be taken on a journey, and locked them
up in a large house. We never knew what became of them afterwards. Many
of these things of which we were robbed we had bought with money earned
by the work of our hands. They promised us more when we should get down
here, but we have never received anything in place of them.</p>
<p>We left in our land two hundred and thirty six houses, which we had built
with our own hands. We cut the logs, hauled them, and built them
ourselves. We have now in place of them six little shanties, built for
us by the government. They are one story high, with two doors and two
windows. They are full of holes and cracks, and let in the wind and
rain. We hear that our houses which we left in Dakota have all been
pulled down. To show how much the tribe had been robbed of, we will
count the household possessions of a single one of our families in
Dakota before we came down. Two stoves, one a kitchen-stove and the
other a parlor-stove, with all the accompanying utensils; two bedsteads,
two plows, and one double-plow; one harrow, one spade, two hay-forks,
one hand-saw, and one large two-handed saw; one grind-stone, one
hay-rake, a cupboard, and four chairs. We have now no stoves, chairs, or
bedsteads. We have nothing but our tents and their contents, composed
mostly of clothing. The tribe owned two reapers, eight mowers, a flour
and saw mill. They are gone from us also. We brought with us thirty-five
yoke of oxen. They all died when we got here, partly from the effects of
the toilsome journey, and partly by disease. We have not.</p>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
