<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="MuzHour"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="MuzHour">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Hour and the Woman</title>
<title type="sort">hour and the woman</title>
<author>Muzzey, Annie L.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">24</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">MuzHour</idno>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476245</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Hour and the Woman</title>
<title level="j">The Arena</title>
<title type="sort">hour and the woman</title>
<author>Annie L. Muzzy</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 263-272</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Arena Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: Alderman Library, MicFilm S-147 Reel 96</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>The Arena, Vol. 22, No.1 (July 1899).</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>Nonfiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Stephen Ramsay, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="1999-03">March 1999</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Elizabeth Styron, UVA Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Corrected and closed open tags; XML compliance check</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="text" id="d3"><pb n="263"/>
<head>THE HOUR AND THE WOMAN.</head>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>     A Woman&mdash;in so far as she beholdeth
</l><l>        Her one Beloved's face;
</l><l>     A Mother&mdash;with a great heart that enfoldeth
</l><l>        The children of the Race:
</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>     A body free and strong with that high beauty
</l><l>        That comes of perfect use, is built thereof:
</l><l>     A mind where Reason ruleth over Duty
</l><l>        And Justice reigns with Love.
</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza">
<l>     A self-poised royal soul, brave, wise and tender,
</l><l>        No longer blind and dumb;
</l><l>     A Human Being, of an unknown splendor
</l><l>        Is she who is to come.</l>
<l>
<bibl> &mdash; <name type="author"><hi rend="italic">Charlotte Perkins
Stetson.</hi></name></bibl>
</l>
</lg>

<p>PERHAPS to no one more than to the writer herself are these
prophetic lines applicable, though she aimed to picture only her
ideal woman.  To arrive even in a remote degree at the realization
of one's ideals is, in itself, a distinction that compels
admiration and inspires reverence.  The human craving to find in
poet and philosopher a living embodiment and exponent of the
thought flashed upon one's consciousness, is well satisfied in
Charlotte Perkins Stetson, whose word and work are synonymous.
</p><p>For a number of years the original verse of Mrs. Stetson has
been floating about in the newspapers, which, with all their
faults, are more or less fair records of the upward thought and
movement that show at what point of recognition we are in our march
of human progress.  It did not matter that the now world-famed
poem, "Similar Cases," was first printed in a periodical of limited
circulation among a few radical thinkers who dared to aspire to a
higher order of life than is possible in the existing state of
things.  It did not matter that "The Nationalist" itself went down
before the adverse winds that have wrecked many other brave crafts
setting sail for the port of Freedom.  This poem that first took
passage in the ship-of-war,&mdash;which by the way, went down only to
rise with ten-fold power in other forms&mdash;has since
<pb n="264"/>
made its
world voyage on its own strong, bright wings, claiming swift
recognition even with the "Neolithic Man," who is sufficiently
susceptible to its truth and humor to appreciate the satire on his
own "clinching argument," and to give hope that he, too, in the
slow evolution of the race, will "have to change his nature."
</p><p>Other poems of equal force and brilliancy, over the same
signature, have, from time to time, appealed to our slumbering
sense of truth and justice in respect to common customs which we
had accepted without thought; as things to be regretted, perhaps,
but still endured.  The keen, delicate lance that with one dart
pierces to the very center of sores that we have kept covered, has
been felt many times through the poems, under various familiar
titles, which have come to us in fragmentary ways during the last
half dozen years.  To find them collected in the first pamphlet
editions sent out from San Francisco in 1893 and 1895, was a real
delight which lost nothing in flavor to some of her admirers
because they could be shared with others for a half dollar.  A more
expensive, revised, and enlarged edition has been issued within the
last year.  It is called "In This Our World," and in it Mrs.
Stetson's admirers will find new claimants for favor.
</p><p>But just now our business is with Mrs. Stetson's latest work,
"Women and Economics,"<ref target="n264">1</ref> a philosophic
study of the economic
relations between men and women&mdash;a study which aims, as the author
says in her preface&mdash;"To show how some of the worst evils under
which we suffer, evils long supposed to be inherent and
ineradicable in our natures, are but the result of certain
arbitrary conditions of our own adoption; and how, by removing
those conditions, we may remove the resultant."
</p><p>The primal evil which Mrs. Stetson points out in our social
life, is the economic dependence of woman on the sex-relation.
From this false and unnatural position, sanctioned by human law and
sustained for centuries as an inviolable

<pb n="265"/>

custom, has proceeded the multitude of social perversions which the
present age has set about eradicating by this, that, and the other
so-called reform.  While granting that the sexuo-economic relation
has had its use in the earlier evolutionary stages of humanity, the
time has come, in the view of Mrs. Stetson, for a radical change in
the status of woman who can no longer find her sole environment in
man.

</p><p>"The inevitable trend of human life," she says, "is toward a
higher civilization; but while that civilization is confined to one
sex, it inevitably exaggerates sex-distinction until the increasing
evil of this condition is stronger than all the good of the
civilization attained, and the nation falls.  Civilization, be it
understood, does not consist in the acquisition of luxuries.
Social development is an organic development.  A civilized state is
one in which the citizens live in organic industrial relations. .
. .
</p><p>"The sexuo-economic relation serves to bring social
development to a certain level.  After that level is reached a
higher relation must be adopted, or the lifting process comes to an
end; and either the race succumbs to the morbid action of its own
forces, or some fresher race comes in and begins the course of
social evolution anew.  Under the stimulus of the sexuo-economic
relation one civilization after another has climbed up and fallen
down in weary succession.  It remains for us to develop a newer,
better form of sex-relation and of economic relation therewith, and
so grasp the fruits of all previous civilizations and grow on to
the beautiful results of higher ones.  The true and lasting social
progress beyond that which we have yet made, is based on a spirit
of inter-human love, not merely the inter-sexual, and it requires
an economic machinery organized and functioned for human needs.
The sexuo-economic relation drives man up to where he can become
fully human.  It deepens and develops the human soul until it is
able to conceive and fulfil the larger social uses in which our
further life must find expression.  But, unless the human soul sees
these new forces, feels them, gives way to them in loyal service,
it fails to reach the level from which all further progress must
proceed and falls back.  Again and again society has so risen, so
failed to grasp new duties, so fallen back.
</p><p>"Today it will not so fall again, because the social consciousness
<pb n="266"/> is at last so vital a force, in both men and
women,
that we feel clearly our human life cannot be lived on sex-lines
only.  We are so far individualized, so far socialized, that men
can work without the spur of exaggerated sex-stimulus, work for
some one besides mate and young, and women can love and serve
without the slavery of economic dependence&mdash;love better and serve
more.  Sex-stimulus begins and ends in individuals.  The social
spirit is a larger thing, a better thing, and brings with it a
larger, nobler life than we could know on a sex-basis solely."

</p><p>It must not be supposed that Mrs. Stetson's clear and
sustained argument militates at any point against marriage in its
truer and diviner sense.  On the contrary, the whole trend of her
reasoning is towards such freedom, such independence, as shall make
possible between the individual man and woman a union based on the
highest sentiment of love and social use, rather than on the low,
common plane of selfish passion and economic dependence.  None too
scathing is the scorn and shame with which the lower and baser
motives of marriage, so-called, are held up to our view by this
bold, logical thinker who fearlessly strips the illusion of false
sentiment from what passes in the world as love and wedlock.  The
process may be a little startling, but the flash of light which
penetrates and riddles the sham, reveals to us all the more clearly
the beauty and perfection of the true.
</p><p>It is not a fair treatment of "Women and Economics" to give
its bald, bare statements, wrested from the chain of argument that
harmonizes and shows the logical sequence and consistency of its
conclusions.  The best that can be done is to ask every reader to
lay aside all preconceived views and prejudices on the particular
subject in hand, and to bring to the study a calm, impartial spirit
of inquiry that does not shrink from admitting truths even when
they undermine the long-cherished theories and beliefs of heredity
and education.
</p><p>The conventional thinker will inevitably be shocked by Mrs.
Stetson's ungloved handling of a relation which has been from time
immemorial regarded as, on the one hand, sacred
<pb n="267"/>
and
beautiful, or, on the other, wanton and unmentionable.  But it is
sometimes necessary to be shocked before we can be moved to that
dispassionate, unbiased consideration which will qualify us to
distinguish between the real and the fictitious value of time-honored customs and institutions.  A great step is gained by the
woman who reads this book, if she catch a glimpse of larger
horizons, and begins to realize that any personal love which limits
her vision to mere temporal ends and fills her life with doubt,
anxiety, anguish, fear, dissatisfaction, and unrest, is unworthy of
the name of love, and must either be lifted to a higher plane or be
set aside altogether.  What Byron calls "the blind necessity of
loving" does not compel any human being to merge all individual
hopes and aspirations and possibilities in the unsympathetic sphere
of another life when from every side comes the appeal of nobler
objects for which to live and toil and sacrifice, the demand for
the larger good that embraces and benefits all.
</p><p>In this affirmation there is not a breath of irreverence for
love and marriage in the truer sense.  Rather is there a
declaration of freedom to reject the false and meretricious, and to
exalt the real and abiding union of man and woman, founded not on
the mere selfish and external relations, but on the deeper
spiritual sympathy and purposes that find in each the impelling
force of larger inspiration and accomplishment.
</p><p>No doubt, on this point, the author of "Women and Economics"
has yet a further and fuller word to speak.  She is too thorough an
evolutionist to stop on the threshold of a subject which she has
here barely opened to the shocked eyes of the conservative thinker,
satisfied with a form that has no in-breathing power of life and
substance.
</p><p>When Mrs. Stetson has waited long enough for the storm of
protest against her radical utterance to subside, we shall look for
the reconciling and fulfilling word of which this book is but the
<hi rend="italic">avant courier</hi>&mdash;a sort of John Baptist, in wild skins, going
before to stir the "Neolithic Mind" which is crying:
<q><lg type="poem"><l>This is chimerical!  Utopian! absurd!</l>
</lg></q>
</p>
<pb n="268"/>

<p>There is another problem connected with this profound subject
which some of us do not find settled by the brilliant argument that
makes "Women and Economics" what one of its critics has called "the
book of the age," and another has named "a force that must at last
be reckoned with."
</p><p>The question of economic independence for women is one very
difficult to dispose of in a day when strong able-bodied men go
about the streets begging for work that shall save them from the
almshouse or the penitentiary.
</p><p>It is true that Mrs. Stetson gives us in high light the ideal
picture of that kingdom of righteousness in which every member of
the human family shall have an equal place and opportunity for the
development of individual powers of use and happiness.
</p><p>This, indeed, is the end toward which all earnest, sincere
workers are striving.  But not until the industrial world is re-organized
and resystematized upon the platform of the golden rule,
can woman enter upon her career of absolute economic independence
without adding to the accumulated train of evils in the mad
struggle, when every hand clutches at both its own and its
brother's portion.  Possibly, to anticipate the best, the sudden
assumption of every woman to economic freedom and industrial rights
might precipitate the revolution which is to usher in that reign of
"peace and good will" forecast by all the prophets.
</p><p>Meantime no woman in sexual relations need consider herself a
dependent on such relation.  The matter is in her own hands.  When
she makes her own individual law in the sex-union it will be
respected.  For the rest, if she will follow her highest
convictions of right, without too many words about it, she will
arrive at a clearer vision of her own place and power.  It is
certainly not the man's place and power.  It is a new insight, a
new impulse that we want and not the accumulated force, in the same
direction, of women acting as men.
</p><p>Mrs. Stetson herself, is giving a fine example of free
womanhood in following her own high ideals, with a sincerity and
<pb n="269"/>
directness that wins the admiration of even those who do not
agree with her.
</p><p>As a masculine critic <ref target="n269">2</ref> remarks,
"No one can easily overpraise
the vigor, the clearness, and the acuteness of her writing."  And
he adds, "She writes, indeed, like a man, and like a very logical
and very able man."
</p><p>This is a mistake.  She writes simply like Charlotte Perkins
Stetson, a woman who, in the school of experience, has learned her
lessons, not automatically from the text-books of custom and
tradition, but with spiritual insight and a keen analytical sense
that penetrates to the heart of things,&mdash;that insists on a reason
for existing conditions, as well as upon the logical process of
reaching a higher state.  If there are errors in her vision she
will be swift to acknowledge them when discovered, for truth is
what she seeks.  Unquestionably she brings to her study of human
life the force and vigor and independence derived from the strong
ancestral Beecher stock from which she springs; for the powerful
influence and direction of heredity cannot be denied even with our
higher claims to heredity from God.  Added to a noble birthright,
a wise training has given to the world a woman of individual
character; one free enough and brave enough to speak her honest
understanding and judgment on a matter which the world of modern
men and women have accepted without thought, or with finger
prudishly pressed on lips that murmur secretly over conditions
regarded as inevitable and unalterable while nature endures.
</p><p>To some persons&mdash;perhaps to the majority&mdash;there appears a
certain hardness and rudeness of touch in Mrs. Stetson's treatment
of wifehood and motherhood, which is instinctively resented.  But
a closer study of her attitude toward these relations will reveal
an unusual reverence for all that is deepest, purest, and holiest
in them.  It is only the false sentiment that is riddled and cast
out in her keen analyzing process.  As a revelation of the spirit
of true motherhood turn to the not too familiar: </p>

<pb n="270"/>

<lg type="stanza">
    <head>MOTHER TO CHILD.</head>
<l>How best can I serve thee, my child, my child,
</l><l>Flesh of my flesh and dear heart of my heart!
</l><l>Once thou wast within me&mdash;I held thee&mdash;I fed thee&mdash;
</l><l>By the force of my loving and longing I led thee&mdash;
</l><l>Now we are apart!
</l></lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>I may blind thee with kisses, and crush with embracing,
</l><l>Thy warm mouth in my neck, our arms interlacing,
</l><l>But here in my body my soul lives alone,
</l><l>And thou answerest me from a house of thine own&mdash;
</l><l>The house which I builded!
</l></lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>Which we builded together, thy father and I&mdash;
</l><l>In which thou must live, O my darling, and die!
</l><l>Not one stone can I alter, not one atom relay,
</l><l>Not to save or defend thee, or help thee to stay,
</l><l>That gift is completed!
</l></lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>How best can I serve thee?  O child if thou knew
</l><l>How my heart aches with loving!  How deep and how true,
</l><l>How brave and enduring, how patient and strong,
</l><l>How longing for good, and how fearful of wrong
</l><l>Is the love of thy mother!
</l></lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>Could I crown thee with riches!  Surround, overflow thee
</l><l>With fame and with power till the whole world should
</l><l>     know thee;
</l><l>With wisdom and genius to hold the world still,
</l><l>To bring laughter and tears, joy and pain at thy will&mdash;
</l><l>Still&mdash;<hi rend="italic">thou</hi> mightst not be happy!
</l></lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>Such have lived&mdash;and in sorrow.  The greater the mind,
</l><l>The wider and deeper the grief it can find;
</l><l>The richer, the gladder, the more thou canst feel
</l><l>The keen stings that a lifetime is sure to reveal,
</l><l>O my child!  Must thou suffer?
</l></lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>Is there no way my life may save thine from a pain?
</l><l>Is the love of a mother no possible gain?
</l><l>No labor of Hercules&mdash;search for the Grail&mdash;
</l><l>No way for this wonderful love to avail?
</l><l>God in Heaven&mdash;Oh, teach me!
</l></lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>My prayer has been answered the pain thou must bear,
</l><l>Is the pain of the world's life, which thy life must share.
</l><l>Thou art one with the world&mdash;though I love thee the best;
</l><l>And to save thee from pain I must save all the rest,
</l><l>Well&mdash;with God's help I'll do it!
</l></lg>
<pb n="271"/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>Thou art one with the rest, I must love thee in them,
</l><l>Thou wilt sin with the rest and thy mother must stem
</l><l>The world's sin.  Thou wilt weep&mdash;and thy mother must dry
</l><l>The tears of the world lest her darling should cry.
</l><l>I will do it&mdash;God helping!
</l></lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>And I stand not alone, I will gather a band,
</l><l>Of all loving mothers from land unto land,
</l><l>Our children are part of the world!  Do you hear?
</l><l>They are one with the world, we must hold them all dear.
</l><l>Love all for the child's sake!
</l></lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>For the sake of my child I must hasten to save,
</l><l>All the children on earth from the jail and the grave,
</l><l>For so, and so only, I lighten the share
</l><l>Of the pain of the world that my darling must bear&mdash;
</l><l>Even so, and so only.</l>
</lg>
<p>When we have a race of mothers entering fully into the spirit
of this poem, then we shall have taken indeed a long step toward
that divine order of love which is the end of all our human
striving.  So far from undervaluing the vocation of maternity,
which has been conceded as the one unquestioned right of womanhood,
it must be acknowledged by even her severest critics, that Mrs.
Stetson exalts and broadens the office and power of motherhood.
But there must be the condition of free, brave womanhood to insure
such a race of mothers.
</p><p>However distant may appear the day when the principles of
"Women and Economics" shall be put to a practical test, we may
congratulate ourselves on the impulse to thought which has been
given by the book.  It is well to consider all possible underlying
causes of unhappy conditions which are bewailed, but accepted as
the mysterious providences of an inscrutable Law.  For the rest
each must determine individually in how far he or she may give
unqualified support to any radical movement toward a higher social
state.  It remains to be seen whether women, more than men, will
resist this relentless attack on the time-honored institution of
marriage as a means of livelihood, vested as it is, with the sacred
rites of the holiest of compacts.  But all changes from lower to
higher
<pb n="272"/>
levels are pushed by the power of thought, and if
the sex relation is lifted, in common perception, from the sensual
plane, and made to stand in its true character for something
greater than mere worldly considerations, then the author of "Women
and Economics," by her bold stroke, will have contributed her share
to the upward impetus.</p>

<closer>

                         <signed>ANNIE L. MUZZEY</signed><lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Joliet, Ill.</hi>

</closer>

</div1>
</body>
<back id="d4">

<div1 type="notes" id="d5">
<head>NOTES</head>
<p><note id="n264"><seg type="note-symbol">1.</seg> <p><bibl>"Women and Economics, a
Study of
the Economic Relations
Between Men and Women as a Factor in Social Evolution."
<author>By
Charlotte Perkins Stetson.</author>  Crown 8vo, pp. 340, Small, Maynard &amp;
Co., Boston.</bibl>
</p></note>
</p>

<p><note id="n269"><seg type="note-symbol">2.</seg> <p><bibl>Prof. Harry Thurston
Peck, in "The Cosmopolitan."</bibl>
</p></note></p>
</div1>
</back>
</text>
</TEI.2>

