<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="NewArtO"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="NewArtO">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">An Introduction to the Art of Rhetorick</title>
<title type="sort">introduction to the art of rhetorick</title>
<author>Newton, John, 1622-1678.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Christine Ruotolo, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>Christine Ruotolo, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">180</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">NewArtO</idno>
<date value="2001">2001</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2001 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476254</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">An Introduction to the Art of Rhetorick</title>
<title type="sort">introduction to the art of rhetorick</title>
<author>John Newton, 1622-1678.</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Printed by E.T. and R.H. for Thomas Passenger...and Ben. Hurlock</publisher>
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
<date value="1671">1671</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Page images from Early English Books Online</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2001-01">January 2001</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Christine Ruotolo</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">
<div1 type="chapter" n="1" id="d3"><pb n="1"/>
<head>CHAP. I.<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Of the Art of</hi> Rhetorick <hi rend="italic">in the
Generall.</hi></head>


<p><hi rend="italic">RHETORICK is the Art or faculty of eloquent and
delightfull speaking.</hi></p>

<p>
And this eloquent and delightfull speaking, is that which we usually call <hi
rend="italic">Oratory.</hi>
<pb n="2"/>
The difference therefore between a <hi rend="italic">Rhetorician</hi> and an
<hi rend="italic">Oratour</hi> is this; the <hi rend="italic">Rhetorician</hi>
delivers precepts and directions for this eloquent speaking, and the <hi
rend="italic">Oratour</hi> doth put these precepts and directions into
practice.
</p>

<p>
In this Art of <hi rend="italic">Rehtorick</hi> then or in these precepts and
directions for <hi rend="italic">Oratory,</hi> three things must be considered.
</p>
<p>
1. The <hi rend="italic">Matter</hi> about which it is conversant.
</p>
<p>
2. The <hi rend="italic">End</hi> for which it serveth.
</p>
<p>
3. The <hi rend="italic">Meanes</hi> by which that end may be attained.
</p>
<p>
The <hi rend="italic">Matter</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Subject</hi> of this
Art or facultie is any thing wahtsoever which may be discoursed or questioned;
any Theam or Case.
</p>
<p>
A Theam <hi rend="italic">is an infinite Question in which an inquiry is made
in the general concerning the Thesis or Position;</hi> as, <hi
rend="italic">whether it be fit to wage War.
</hi></p>
<p>
A Case <hi rend="italic">is a Question confined to persons and times, in which
a particular inquiry is made concerning the Hypothesis or matter in
dispute;</hi> as, <hi rend="italic">whether it be fit for</hi> England <hi
rend="italic">to wage War with the</hi> Dutch.
</p><p>
2. The <hi rend="italic">End</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Ends</hi> for which
Rhetorich serveth are these.
</p><p>
1. To tickle and delight the eares of
<pb n="3"/>
the Auditors that they may be willing to hear that which is intended to be
delivered.
</p><p>
2. To inform their judgments, and by stregth of argument to beget a beliefe of
that which is spoken.
</p><p>
3. To move the affections and beget a willingness either to do themselves, or to
assist in the actions of others, or to justifie that which is said or done.
</p><p>
Lastly, The <hi rend="italic">wayes</hi> and <hi rend="italic">meanes</hi> by
which these ends may be attained, are three, <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, <hi
rend="italic">Art</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Practice</hi>.
</p><p>
<hi rend="italic">Natural</hi> abilities do much conduce to the attaining of
this excellent faculty; for they that are naturally ingenious, and have a good
memory will easily attain to this Art of eloquent and delightfull speaking; but
where nature is defective, more care and diligence must be used, that the
defects of nature may be in part at least supplied by Art, whose best companion
is a general knowledge of things, which if a young Student have not as yet
attained into, it is at least necessary, that he should perfectly understand the
Theam or case propounded, or else the Rules of Art will stand him but in little
stead; for how sohould he dispose of <hi rend="italic">Matter</hi> before he
hath
<pb n="4"/>
it? And in vain do we speak of <hi rend="italic">Use</hi> and <hi
rend="italic">Practice</hi>, where <hi rend="italic">Knowledge</hi> which must
furnish us with <hi rend="italic">Matter</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Art</hi>
which must teach us to <hi rend="italic">dispose</hi> of it, are both wanting.
But naturall abilities being presupposed, and matter acquired by diligent
reading and observation; I shall here shew how those naturall endowments may be
by art improved, and the prepared matter so disposed and ordered, as that they
may make way for Use and Practice.
</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="2" id="d4">
<head>CHAP. II<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Of Invention.</hi></head>

<div2 type="section" id="d5">

<p>
The Rules of this Art or Faculty of Rhetoricall and delightfull speaking are
commonly reduced unto five heads, <hi rend="italic">Invention, Disposition,
Elocution, Memory</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Pronunciation</hi>.
</p><p>The first of these is <hi rend="italic">Invention</hi>, in which we must
consider three things; First, what we are <hi rend="italic">to invent</hi>,
Secondly by what Arguments we may confirm the <hi rend="italic">matter
invented</hi>: Thirdly, from what Topickes or generall heads, those Arguments
may be raised.
<pb n="5"/>
</p><p>
And <hi rend="italic">First</hi>, we are to consider what it is that we are to
invent; and the thing or matter which we are to invent or find out, is the scope
and purpose, of the intended Oration; that is, we must propound some certain
proposition, to which we mean to direct our speech; and of those several
propositions which may be raised from the Subject propounded, we should still
make choice of that, which is most agreeable to the sentence given, most
suteable to the present occasion, most profitable, and that which the Auditors
may probably best apprehend. But now a dayes our Oratours do much labour to find
out some acute proposition, and that proposition is so stilled, which under some
Allegory doth express a simple and a received truth: as in this expression; I
would advise you to set the Campe in order: the meaning is, I would advise you
to prepare for War: such propositions are not to be found fault with; but yet we
must take heed of affectation, yea and of lightness too, because gravity doth
become an Oratour; though young students may do well to pitch upon the most
plain and obvious propositions; and such easie arguments
<pb n="6"/>
as are most pertinient to the matter in hand; and after they can do this
tollerably well, they may by degrees aspire higher.
</p><p>
<hi rend="italic">Secondly</hi>, When you have resolved upon your proposition,
then you are to bethink your self of some Arguments by which that proposition
may be confirmed: for <hi rend="italic">an argument is a probable reason
brought, to perswade the Auditours of the truth of the Proposition.</hi>

</p><p>
I call it <hi rend="italic">a probable reason</hi>, because arguments are of
two sorts; some are certain, evident and necessary, and these are convincing:
as, that <hi rend="italic">Peter is not a beast, because he is indued with
reason</hi>; others are probable carrying with them some shew of truth; that is,
they seem to be true either from the general received opinion, or for the
similitude that they have with the truth, or from the event; and these are the
Arguments, which an Oratour should chiefly enquire after; not but that he may
also use such are demonstrable and undeniably true: but because he many times
hath to doe with such propositions as cannot be demonstrated, or if they can,
yet he useth probable arguments for the most part, because he is to
<pb n="7"/>
speake to such, as will be more easily perswaded by such arguments, as come
within their own sphere, which they can easily fathom, than by such as are
Demonstrative and beyond their apprehension.
</p><p>
<hi rend="italic">Thirdly</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Invention</hi>, we are to
conside the several Topicks or <hi rend="italic">common places</hi>, from
whence these probable Arguments may be invented or raised; and these are of two
sorts; <hi rend="italic">Intrinsecal</hi>, and <hi
rend="italic">Extrinsecal</hi>: those are called <hi
rend="italic">Intrinsecal</hi>, which are comprised in the matter which is
propounded of what kind soever it be; and all matter is comprised in one of
these three kinds of Cases or Causes, <hi rend="italic">Demonstrative</hi>, <hi
rend="italic">Deliberative</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Judicial</hi>.
</p><p>
The <hi rend="italic">Demonstrative Case</hi> is so called, because it <hi
rend="italic">doth Demonstrate the Nature of the Subject propounded</hi>.  And
is used either in the <hi rend="italic">Commendation</hi>, or <hi
rend="italic">Condemnation</hi> of persons, actions, or things. When it is used
by way of commendation, it is called an <hi rend="italic">Encomium</hi> or a
<hi rend="italic">Penegyrick</hi>: and when it is used by way of condemnation,
it is called an <hi rend="italic">Invective</hi>, if against some <hi
rend="italic">eminent Person</hi>, it is called <hi
rend="italic">Philippick</hi>.
</p><p>
The <hi rend="italic">deliberative Case</hi> is so called, <hi
rend="italic">from the deliberation or consideration that
<pb n="8"/>
should be taken before advice be given</hi>.
</p><p>
The <hi rend="italic">subject matter</hi> in <hi rend="italic">this case</hi>,
is <hi rend="italic">every contingent thing</hi>; every thing which is in our
own power.
</p><p>More particularly, if it be a <hi rend="italic">publick case</hi> there
are five things in which according to <hi rend="italic">Aristotle,
deliberation</hi> is required.</p><p>
1. In publick taxations. 2. In making of War and Peace. 3. In the guarding of
countries. 4. In importation and exportation of goods. 5. In the dispensing or
not dispensing with Laws.
</p><p>
But in <hi rend="italic">private cases</hi> the particular matters in which we
should deliberate, cannot be assigned, beacuse of the great variety; there being
nothing concering our selves or families, in which deliberation is not
convenient, if not necessary.
</p><p>
The <hi rend="italic">Judicial case</hi> may be so called, <hi rend="italic">from the delivering of our
Judgment or opinion of the matter propounded,</hi> whether <hi rend="italic">for</hi> or
<hi rend="italic">against,</hi> whether by way of <hi rend="italic">Accusation,</hi> or by way of
<hi rend="italic">Defence.</hi> And the <hi rend="italic">heads</hi> from whence Arguments may be raised in
these severall kinds of cases are either such as are <hi rend="italic">common to them all;</hi>
or such as are <hi rend="italic">peculiar to each kind:</hi> I will here speak of such
<pb n="9"/>
general wayes of inventing Arguments from the very matter propounded, as are
<hi rend="italic">common to all these cases or causes</hi>; and they being well understood, the
Ingenious and Judicious Oratour will need no direction for each severall kind of
causes in particular.
</p><p>
The <hi rend="italic">Topicks</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Heads</hi> for invention in the General are these
following.
</p><p>
1. <hi rend="italic">Definition</hi>. 2. <hi rend="italic">Division</hi>. 3.
<hi rend="italic">Notation</hi>. 4. <hi rend="italic">Conjugation</hi>. 5. <hi
rend="italic">Genus</hi>. 6. <hi rend="italic">Species</hi>. 7. <hi
rend="italic">Similitude</hi>. 8. <hi rend="italic">Dissimilitude</hi>. 9. <hi
rend="italic">Contraries</hi>. 10. <hi rend="italic">Opposites</hi>. 11. <hi
rend="italic">Comparison</hi>. 12. <hi rend="italic">Causes</hi>. 13. <hi
rend="italic">Effects</hi>. 14. <hi rend="italic">Adjuncts</hi>. 15. <hi
rend="italic">Antecedents</hi>. 16. <hi rend="italic">Consequents</hi>. All
other <hi rend="italic">Topicks</hi> from whence <hi rend="italic">Intrinsical
</hi>or <hi rend="italic">Artificial</hi> arguments may be raised, are
contained in these or may be derived from them.
</p><p>
The first of these Topicks I call <hi rend="italic">Definition</hi>. And, <hi
rend="italic">Definition is a Speech explaining or declaring what a thing
is</hi>. The <hi rend="italic">parts</hi> of a <hi
rend="italic">Definition</hi> according to the Logicians are these two 1. The
<hi rend="italic">Genus or general name</hi>; that is, a name that doth agree
with the thing defined, and also with several other things besides. 2. The <hi
rend="italic">Difference or particular name</hi>, that is, a name which doth
only agree with that which
<pb n="10"/>
is defined; for example, <hi rend="italic">Man is a living creature endued with
Reason</hi>. But such Definitions are seldome used by Orators, because they
afford but little matter for an Oration; but other wayes of Defining things,
which may be called Descriptions rather, and such are these that follow.
</p><p>
One way of <hi rend="italic">Defining</hi> things, much used by Oratours, is,
<hi rend="italic">to describe it by the parts thereof</hi>, which may be
sometimes large and yet elegant: of this way we have an axample in <hi
rend="italic">Causinus</hi>, who doth describe a <hi
rend="italic">Butterflie</hi> in this manner. "A Butterflie," saith he, "is a
small Animal, seldome seen in Cities but very frequently in the fields; it is of
a full, tender, soft, and flexible body, growing smaller and smaller to a little
length, on which a dispersed gentle down doth neatly shine; there stand out as
it were extended Horns, small as thrids, between which a pleasant light of his
shining eyes doth sparkle; but a special wonder is in his Wings, far beyond the
bulk of his little body, they are bedecked with flowers, adorned with Purple,
shine like Gold, and glitter with stars; being poysed with these, he flies as it
were with Oares into the air, disporting
<pb n="11"/>
himself, and cleaving almost to every stalke: sometimes he sucks the juice of
leaves with his most delicate trunk, sometimes he sweetly reposeth amongst
delightfull odors, other while with a renewed flight he soars aloft and escapes
the hands of insulting boyes, drawing in the air six hundred Meanders.
</p>
<p>A <hi rend="italic">Second</hi> way by which Oratours do <hi
rend="italic">define</hi> or rather <hi rend="italic">describe</hi> things, is
by such <hi rend="italic">effects, as do proceed from the four causes</hi>, and
this way doth as it were open a gate to a large field; only you must take heed,
that you reckon not every <hi rend="italic">minute</hi> or <hi
rend="italic">small matter</hi> for an <hi rend="italic">effect</hi>;
according to this way Saint Ambrose doth describe <hi rend="italic">drunkenness
</hi>to be an <hi rend="italic">incentive of madness, the fomenter of lust, and
the poyson to wisdome</hi>.
</p><p>
A <hi rend="italic">Third</hi> way is by <hi rend="italic">similitude</hi>;
but not according to the usual way of expressing them, by the particle, <hi
rend="italic">As</hi>: but by bare affirmation omitting the usual way of
comparison: for example: <hi rend="italic">What is our life? It is a market in
which we buy and sell; in which one deceiveth another, and in which every one
doth mind his own business; and hath a care of his own wealth: it is a Comedie,
in which every one doth act his own part, this man the part of a King, and that
of a peasant.</hi></p>

<pb n="12"/>

<p>
A <hi rend="italic">Fourth</hi> way is by <hi rend="italic">Synonomie,</hi> as
thus: <hi rend="italic">What else is a Lilly, but an ornament to the Earth, the
glory of Plants, the very eye of Flowers, the Jewel of the meadowes and Star of
the Fields, adorning the Earth, as the Stars do Heaven; giving as great a luster
to other flowers, as the Jasper stone doth to Gold, and as much delighting the
eye as the Sun the world.</hi>
</p>

<p>
A <hi rend="italic">Fifth</hi> way is by those <hi rend="italic">causes</hi>
by which <hi rend="italic">effects</hi> are produced; as the <hi
rend="italic">Material, formal, efficient</hi> and <hi rend="italic">finall
causes.</hi> For example, the Edifice which <hi
rend="italic">D&aelig;dalus</hi> hath raised with his own hand, of strong and
hewed stone, in a round form, is not only fortified against the injury of
weather; but hath also so much gracefullness in it, that it easeth the mind of
all care, yea and filleth it with delight; it is so neatly built, that you would
think it Heaven upon Earth.

</p>
<p>
A <hi rend="italic">Sixth</hi> way is by <hi rend="italic">negation; </hi>
when we first shew what a thing is not, and then what it is: Thus <hi
rend="italic">Babusius Lib.3.Epigr.</hi> doth describe a <hi
rend="italic">Friend.</hi>
</p>

<p>
A Friend <hi rend="italic">is not a bare voice, or empty nutshel, but a Friend
is known by his affection and behaviour, by his words and actions.
</hi>

</p><pb n="13"/>

<p>
A <hi rend="italic">Seventh</hi> way is by <hi rend="italic">adjuncts</hi> and
<hi rend="italic">proprieties</hi>; Thus our <hi rend="italic">blessed
Saviour</hi> is called, <hi rend="italic">The Assertor of humane liberty, the
master of Sanctitie, </hi> and <hi rend="italic">absolute perfection, the
everlasting fountain of all vertues.</hi> Thus <hi rend="italic">Solomon</hi>
is described: <hi rend="italic">Solomon that great miracle and Oracle of humane
Wisdome, the Master or Tutor of the World.</hi>

</p>
<p>
An <hi rend="italic">Eighth</hi> way, is first to describe the thing Ironically
according to the opinion of some, and then to explain the same, as in truth it
is, or at least according to your own thoughts and apprehensions of it.

</p>
<p>
The <hi rend="italic">Second Topick</hi> for <hi rend="italic">Invention</hi>
is <hi rend="italic">Division,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Distribution of the
matter propounded into its parts</hi>; thus the <hi rend="italic">life of
Man</hi> may be divided, into <hi rend="italic">Infancy, Childhood, Youth,
middle age, old-age.</hi>

</p>
<p>
Arguments may be raised from the <hi rend="italic">parts</hi> unto the <hi
rend="italic">whole,</hi> three wayes. 1. By <hi rend="italic">affirming</hi>
that of the <hi rend="italic">whole,</hi> which may be affirmed of <hi
rend="italic">all the parts</hi>; as if you would prove the <hi
rend="italic">whole Fabrick of a Huse</hi> to be defective; you may divide the
house, into <hi rend="italic">the walls, the roofe, and floores</hi>; and shew
the defects in each of these.
</p>

<p>
2. By <hi rend="italic">denying</hi> that of the <hi rend="italic">whole,</hi>
what may be denied of <hi rend="italic">all the parts</hi>; as if you
<pb n="14"/>
were to shew the inconvenience of sending Children to travell: you may enumerate
the several places adjoyning, and shew the inconveniences that may be in sending
them to any of those places; as suppose to <hi rend="italic">France</hi>, <hi
rend="italic">Spain</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi>, and by consequence
any whither else.

</p>
<p>
3. By making an affirmation <hi rend="italic">of one particular part</hi>,
omitting or rejecting the rest; as thus, <hi rend="italic">either he loves me
or hates me</hi>, for there is no third or mean; <hi rend="italic">but he doth
not love me, therefore he hates me</hi>.

</p>
<p>
This Topick may be elegantly used by way of <hi
rend="italic">Interrogation</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Repetition</hi>, <hi
rend="italic">Subjection</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Preterition</hi>, and <hi
rend="italic">Apostrophe</hi>. And example whereof, may be this excellent
description of a garden, as it is set forth by <hi rend="italic">Drexelius</hi>
in his <hi rend="italic">Nicetas</hi>. "There was," saith he, "a most pleasant
garden as it were a Paradise, the smiling Trees stood with their leaves budded,
which with a delightfull odour made the shadows gracefull, the gentle motion of
whose boughs made a sweet whistling noyse, amongst these a murmuring Rivulet,
clearer than any Chrystal, with running streams which did smoothly glide,
disturbing the pible stones with its singing waters: so that the motion thereof
was almost a Musicall harmony.
<pb n="15"/>
On either side were flowers, with <hi rend="italic">Zephyrus</hi>'s copious
family; on the one hand the silver Lillies from the green bank did smile (upon
you) on the other the purple Roses did glitter, from an other part the
Daffidillies white as Snow or Ivory, were set off with the Hyacinths red as
blood, yellow as gold; most pleasant gales of wind breathing from every part."

</p>
<p>
The <hi rend="italic">Third Topick</hi> is <hi rend="italic">Notation</hi>, or
<hi rend="italic">Etymologie</hi>, which is <hi rend="italic">the
interpretation of the word, shewing as well the original thereof, as the
signification</hi>: as <hi rend="italic">a Senate</hi> is so called because of
<hi rend="italic">convention of the Seniors</hi>, that is of old men. <hi
rend="italic">Etymology</hi> is more frequent amongst <hi
rend="italic">Grammarians</hi>, than <hi rend="italic">Orators,</hi> yet
sometimes there may be an occasion for it amongst them, even for ornament and
sweetness sake.

</p>
<p>
The <hi rend="italic">Fourth Topick</hi> is <hi
rend="italic">Conjugation</hi>: and <hi rend="italic">Conjugation</hi> is
either when <hi rend="italic">one word hath various endings,</hi> as <hi
rend="italic">Knife, knives</hi>; or when <hi rend="italic">several words do
come from, or are derived from one primitive;</hi> thus <hi
rend="italic">beautifull</hi> and <hi rend="italic">beautifullness</hi> are
both derived from <hi rend="italic">beauty.</hi> From this Topick we argue
thus, <hi rend="italic">If piety be a commendable quality, then he that is
pious is worthy of commendation.</hi>
</p>

<pb n="16"/>

<p>
<hi rend="italic">Conjugation</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Notation</hi> differ
in this; <hi rend="italic">Notation explains the word; Conjugation shewes its
derivation and various termination.</hi>

</p>
<p>
The <hi rend="italic">Fifth</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sixth Topicks</hi> are
<hi rend="italic">Genus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Species</hi>: now that is
called <hi rend="italic">Genus</hi>, which doth comprehend <hi
rend="italic">several things</hi> under it which are <hi rend="italic">really
different</hi> from one another. And that is called <hi rend="italic">Form</hi>
or <hi rend="italic">Species</hi>, which may with other things be referred to
<hi rend="italic">one common Genus</hi>: And thus this word (<hi
rend="italic">Art</hi>) is a <hi rend="italic">Genus</hi> in respect of the
seven liberal sciences, as <hi rend="italic">Grammar</hi>, <hi
rend="italic">Rhetorick</hi>, &amp;c. And these sciences <hi
rend="italic">Grammar</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Rhetorick</hi>, &amp;c. are the
<hi rend="italic">forms</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Species</hi> which are
contained under this <hi rend="italic">Genus</hi> or general term (Art.)
</p>

<p>
The first of these Topicks namely that which is called <hi
rend="italic">Genus</hi>, doth many times afford the Oratour plenty of matter;
for by this meanes a finite proposition, that is a propoisiton that is confined
to the circumstances of time, place and such like, is reduced to an infinite,
and hath all those restrictions taken from it.  From these Topicks we may argue
two ways.

</p>
<p>
1. That which is spoken of the <hi rend="italic">Genus</hi> may sometimes be
also spoken of the <hi rend="italic">Form</hi> or <hi
rend="italic">Species</hi>; as thus, <hi rend="italic">if vertue be to be
imbraced</hi>,
<pb n="17"/>
<hi rend="italic">then Temperance ought to be imbraced also.</hi>

</p>
<p>
2. That which is denied of the <hi rend="italic">Genus</hi>, may be also denied
of the <hi rend="italic">Species</hi>; as thus, <hi rend="italic">if no
liberal Art be necessary for a Souldier; then Rhetorick is not necessary for
him.</hi>
</p>

<p>
The seventh Topick is <hi rend="italic">Similitude;</hi> and similitude <hi
rend="italic">is the comparing of two or more things together, which are in
themselves diverse, but do agree in some particular.</hi> For Example, <hi
rend="italic">a shadow</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Glory</hi> are in themselves
very different things: but yet they agree in this, tha the shadow doth accompany
the body, and glory vertue. And hence <hi rend="italic">Tully</hi> saith, that
<hi rend="italic">Glory is the shadow of vertue.</hi> <hi
rend="italic">Similitude</hi> may be collected, either from words, actions or
fables; nay there is scarce any thing which may not in some particular be
compared with another, sometimes it is used for to prove, but most commonly for
illustration.

</p>
<p>
The eighth Topick is <hi rend="italic">Dissimilitude</hi>; and Dissimilitude
<hi rend="italic">is the disagreeing of two or more things in some
particular</hi>; from this Topick we argue thus: that which agreeth with one
thing that is unlike, doth not necessarily agree with another; &amp; that which
doth not agree with some one thing, may yet agree
<pb n="18"/>
with some other particular: For example, <hi rend="italic">Idle citizens care
not what mischief doth befall the Commonwealth; therefore the more generous and
publick spirited men, must endeavour to keep the Republick from danger.</hi>

</p>
<p>
The ninth Topick is from <hi rend="italic">Contraries</hi>; and those things
are said to be contraries, <hi rend="italic">which cannot both at the same time
agree with one and the same thing</hi>: thus no man can be said to be wise in
that thing, in which he is a fool.
</p>

<p>
<hi rend="italic">Contraries</hi> are distinguished into <hi
rend="italic">four</hi> ranks or kinds: <hi rend="italic">Adverse, Privitive,
Relative</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Contradictory</hi>; in these severall kinds
of contraries we are wont to argue either by way of affirmation or by way of
negation.
</p>

<p>
In those <hi rend="italic">Contraries</hi> which we call <hi
rend="italic">adverse</hi>, we argue rightly, if we deny that of one thing or
person, which we affirm of another, as thus; <hi rend="italic">there is no
safety in Warre, all men doe therefore desire peace.</hi>
</p>

<p>
In those <hi rend="italic">Contraries</hi>, which are <hi
rend="italic">Privative</hi>, we argue rightly, when one privative is denied of
that person, of which another is affirmed, as thus: <hi rend="italic">you wish
me poverty, because you envy my prosperous and wealthy condition. </hi>
</p>

<pb n="19"/>

<p>
In <hi rend="italic">Relative contraries</hi>, we argue rightly, when one is
inferred from the relation which it hath unto the other for example, <hi
rend="italic">if you be a Schollar, pray tell me who is your Master.</hi>

</p>
<p>
In <hi rend="italic">Contradictory contraries,</hi> we argue rightly, when one
being denied, the other is affirmed, or the contrary; as thus, <hi
rend="italic">He is just, he is not just.</hi>

</p>
<p>
The tenth Topick is from such things as are <hi rend="italic">opposite</hi> to
one another: And they are said to be <hi rend="italic">opposites</hi> to one
another, which can never agree together: as <hi rend="italic">wrath</hi> and
<hi rend="italic">friendship</hi>; from which sort of Topicks, the way of
arguing is, to deny that of one opposite which is affirmed of the other as thus,
<hi rend="italic">If</hi> Peter <hi rend="italic">have a mind to kill</hi>
Paul, <hi rend="italic">surely he can have no love for him.</hi>

</p>
<p>
In the use of these Topicks we must consider how things that are <hi
rend="italic">contraries, unlike</hi> or <hi rend="italic">oppoiste</hi>, do
differ from one another.  Those things are said to be <hi
rend="italic">contrary</hi>, which cannot agree with one another; things that
are <hi rend="italic">unlike</hi> doe not disagree, but are diverse; but in
things that are <hi rend="italic">opposite</hi>, when one of the <hi
rend="italic">contraries</hi> is expressed, we are to answer it by the <hi
rend="italic">effect</hi> of the other; as thus, <hi rend="italic">to
love</hi> and to <hi rend="italic">hurt;</hi> for <hi rend="italic">to
hurt</hi> doth proceed from <hi rend="italic">hatred</hi>, and <hi
rend="italic">hatred</hi> is <hi rend="italic">contrary unto love.
</hi>
<pb n="20"/>

</p><p>
The eleventh Topick is <hi rend="italic">Comparison</hi>, and Comparison <hi
rend="italic">is the comparing of one thing with another.</hi> This is either
<hi rend="italic">equall</hi> or <hi rend="italic">unequall.</hi>

</p>
<p>
Equal comparison <hi rend="italic">is</hi>, <hi rend="italic">when two equall
things ar compared together.</hi> As thus; <hi rend="italic">he hath deceived
thee, therefore he will deceive me also.</hi>

</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Unequall comparison</hi> is two waies, first when we argue
from the greater to the less: As, <hi rend="italic">God spared not the Angels
that sinned, how then shall he spare man?</hi>

</p>
<p>

Secondly, when we argue from the less to the greater: As, <hi
rend="italic">he will not let one sin go unpunished: much more will he
therefore punish a multitude of sins.</hi>

</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Comparison</hi> doth differ from <hi rend="italic">Similitude</hi>; in <hi
rend="italic">that</hi> two things are compared together in respect of some
third; but in <hi rend="italic">Similitude</hi> there is no respect unto a
third, but to one another only: as thus, <hi rend="italic">It is lawfull for
</hi>M. Antony<hi rend="italic"> to defend</hi> Clodius; <hi rend="italic">why
may not</hi> Tully <hi rend="italic">then defend Milo?</hi>  Here the
comparison is between <hi rend="italic">Tully</hi> and <hi
rend="italic">Anthony</hi>, but it is in respect of a third, that is, in
respect of <hi rend="italic">Defence.</hi>  But in this, <hi rend="italic">As
they that are sick, thinke all things loathsome, though never so sweet; so they
that are wicked cannot relish the best Societies</hi>: Here the <hi
rend="italic">sick in body</hi> are compared to the <hi rend="italic">sick in
mind,</hi> that is to the <hi rend="italic">wicked,</hi> but not in respect of
a
<pb n="21"/>
third, but in respect of their own corrupted tastes.
</p>

<p>
The twelvth Topick is from the <hi rend="italic">causes</hi> of things: And
that is said to be <hi rend="italic">a cause, from whence a thing may in any
sort be said to be produced.</hi>

</p>
<p>
We commonly reckon four sorts of <hi rend="italic">causes, Efficient, Material,
Formal and Finall.</hi>

</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">The efficient cause is that which maketh a thing</hi>: Thus
the Sun causeth or maketh the Day; to this may instruments and all other things
be referred, which do only assist in the making as well as those which make the
thing: as a Pen is an assistant in writing. From this cause we argue thus: If
the cause be granted, we grant the effect also: if it be praised or dispraised,
we praise or dispraise the effect also.

</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">The Material cause is that of which a thing is made, or is
imployed in</hi>; as money of Gold, and an Oratour about every matter or thing.
From this cause we argue thus; If matter be afforded, there may be such an
effect, and the goodness or the badness of the effect depends upon the goodness
or the badness of the matter.

</p>
<pb n="22"/>

<p>
<hi rend="italic">The formal cause is that by which the thing is what it is, or
that by which it is distinguished from other things.</hi>  Thus a Ship and a
Timber house do differ by the diverse disposing of the parts. In this<hi
rend="italic"></hi> cause we argue from the excellence or the meaness of the
form; the more excellent the form is, the better is the thing, and any
deficiency in the form doth make it the worse: and every thing should be
proportionable to his form: and hence a man should aim at immortal things,
because his soul (which is his form) is made immortal.

</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">The final cause is that for which a thing is made</hi>: and
the end for which we do anything, is generally one of these three, because it is
either honest, profitable or delightfull.  From this cause we argue according to
these Axiomes. <hi rend="italic">Such as the end is, such are the things that
are done to that end. If the end be good or bad, the things referred to that end
are good or bad also.</hi>

</p>
<p>
The thirteenth Topick is from the <hi rend="italic">Effects</hi>, and those are
said to be <hi rend="italic">Effects which are produced by their causes.</hi>
From these we argue either by inferring the cause, the effect being granted, or
by denying the cause, the effect being granted, or by denying the cause, the
effect being denied; or by commending
<pb n="23"/>
the cause, if the effects be good, or by condemning it, if the effects be bad:
and these heads drawn from the causes and effects, do afford great plenty of
matter for discourse.

</p>
<p>
The fourteenth Topick is from the <hi rend="italic">Adjuncts</hi>, and those
are said to be adjuncts, <hi rend="italic">which are joyned with the thing, but
not of necessity</hi>; to wit, such as are joyned to persons or things. <hi
rend="italic">Tully</hi> reckons up twelve of the first sort, <hi
rend="italic">viz.</hi> Of the <hi rend="italic">Person</hi>, as <hi
rend="italic">the Name, the Nature, Quality &amp;c, the Habit, the Fortune, the
Life, the Affection, the Studies, Councells, Actions, Chances, and
Speeches.</hi>  The <hi rend="italic">Adjuncts</hi> of a thing are commonly
six. <hi rend="italic">Place, Time Occasion, Manner, Faculty,</hi> and <hi
rend="italic">Instrument</hi>; but some there are which do reduce them to these
seven.

</p>
<l>
<hi rend="italic">Quis, quid, ubi, quibus auxiliis, cur, quomodo, quando.</hi>
</l>

<l>In <hi rend="italic">English</hi> thus,</l>

<l>First ask, <hi rend="italic">Who, What,</hi> and <hi
rend="italic">Where</hi>, and then,</l>
<l><hi rend="italic">What Aide,</hi> with <hi rend="italic">Why,</hi> and <hi
rend="italic">How</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">When.</hi></l>

<p>
<hi rend="italic">Quis, who,</hi> doth signifie the quality of the Person, in
which there must be considered
<pb n="24"/>

his nature, sex, age, nation, kindred and estate, in respect of his body, mind
and fortune.
</p>

<p>
<hi rend="italic">Quid, what,</hi> importeth an enquiry after the nature of the
thing, as whether it be of importance or not; whether great or small; noble or
ignoble.

</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Ubi, where,</hi> denotes the place.

</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Quibus auxiliis</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> with what aide</hi>,
notes an enquiry concerning the person, that joyned with him in the action, or
other instruments by which it was effected.

</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Cur, why,</hi> denotes the finall cause, with what intent or
to what end it was done.

</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Quomodo, how,</hi> shewes the manner of doing it, as namely
with what ease, or how hardly.

</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Quando, when,</hi> notes the time in which it was done, and
this head doth many times afford great plenty of matter.

</p>
<p>
The fifteenth and the sixteenth Topicks are the <hi
rend="italic">Antecedents</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Consequents</hi>.
Those are called <hi rend="italic">Antecedents, which go before the thing;</hi>
as, <hi rend="italic">you made him tremble, therefore he is sensible.</hi>

</p>
<p>
They are called <hi rend="italic">consequents, which do necessarily follow the
thing;</hi> as, <hi rend="italic">he that is thrust</hi>
<pb n="25"/>
<hi rend="italic">through the heart must needs dye</hi>.  From the <hi
rend="italic">Antecedents</hi> we argue thus.  The <hi
rend="italic">Antecedent</hi> being granted, the <hi
rend="italic">consequent</hi> must needs follow; as, <hi rend="italic">he is
wounded in the heart, therefore he will dye.</hi>  But from the <hi
rend="italic">Consequents</hi> we argue thus: If the <hi
rend="italic">consequent</hi> be affirmed, the <hi
rend="italic">antecedent</hi> is affirmed; as, <hi rend="italic">It is a great
gash, therefore it was a great blow that made it;</hi> if the <hi
rend="italic">Consequent</hi> be denied, the <hi rend="italic">antecedent</hi>
is denied also; as, <hi rend="italic">he is not dead, therefore he is not
wounded in the heart.</hi>  And these are the <hi
rend="italic">Intrinsecal</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Artificial</hi> Topicks
from whence arguments may be raised on any Theam or matter propounded. For
illustration sake, I will shew you, how, from these Topicks, a matter for an
Oration may be raised from this Theam or proposition, Clodius <hi
rend="italic">laid snares for</hi> Milo.

</p>

</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d6">
<head><hi rend="italic">The Praxis.</hi></head>

<p>
Every <hi rend="italic">Theam</hi> or <hi rend="italic">proposition</hi> doth
consist of three parts, a <hi rend="italic">Subject</hi>, a <hi
rend="italic">Predicate</hi>, and a <hi rend="italic">Copula.</hi> That is
called the <hi rend="italic">Subject</hi>, of <hi rend="italic">which we
speak;</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Predicate, that which is spoken of the
Subject</hi>; and the <hi rend="italic">Copula is some Verbe which joynes the
subject with the predicate.</hi> In this proposition <hi
rend="italic">Clodius</hi> is the <hi rend="italic">Subject</hi>, because it
is of him that we are to
<pb n="26"/>
speak, <hi rend="italic">to lay snares</hi> is the <hi
rend="italic">predicate</hi>, because that is the thing which is said of <hi
rend="italic">Clodius</hi>.

</p>
<p>
Now therefore if you would find out arguments on this Subject, consider well,
which is the <hi rend="italic">Subject</hi>, and which is the <hi
rend="italic">Predicate</hi> in your proposiiton: Then take the <hi
rend="italic">Subject</hi> and go through every Topick: first go to <hi
rend="italic">Definition,</hi> and ask what it is, what is the nature of it,
and how it is distinguished from other things. Then go to <hi
rend="italic">Division</hi>, and see into how many parts the <hi
rend="italic">Subject</hi> may be divided; and so forward from Topick to
Topick. And still observe to your self every argument, which doth by this means
arise from the <hi rend="italic">Subject</hi>, and applie it to the <hi
rend="italic">Predicate</hi>, so shall you easily see, whether it doth fully
confirme your proposition; and when you have done with the <hi
rend="italic">Subject</hi>, take the <hi rend="italic">Predicate</hi>, and run
through the several Topicks, with that also; but if the matter require it, and
that you judge it more convenient to take the whole proposition, than <hi
rend="italic">Subject</hi> and predicate apart by themselves, you may in that
manner run through all the heads of <hi rend="italic">Invention</hi>, but stay
not too long upon any one, for if matter offer not it self in one head go to
another, for every head perhaps may not afford matter,
<pb n="27"/>
at least not such as is apt and fit. But if you would know whether your argument
or matter be drawn from the <hi rend="italic">Subject</hi> or the <hi
rend="italic">predicate</hi>, put it into the form of <hi
rend="italic">Syllogism</hi>, and if the <hi rend="italic">Major</hi> be most
certain, you may couclude, that the argument is drawn from the <hi
rend="italic">Predicate</hi>, but if the <hi rend="italic">minor</hi> be most
certaine, it is then drawn from the <hi rend="italic">Subject</hi>. When you
have found your arguments which prove the proposition, you must reduce them also
into the form of <hi rend="italic">Syllogism,</hi> consisting of three
propositions; The <hi rend="italic">Major, Minor,</hi> and <hi
rend="italic">Conclusion</hi>; and then in the same manner as hath been shewed,
you must seek out arguments to confirm every proposition, if need be: to which
purpose, <hi rend="italic">Similies, Examples, Apothegmes,</hi> sentences and
such like are very serviceable and ought to be had in readiness. But for the
more easie finding out of convenient matter you must consult such bookes which
are written upon the subject in hand, among the rest <hi
rend="italic">Polyanthea, Theatrum vit&aelig; human&aelig;, Feltham's
Resolves,</hi> and such like.


</p>




<pb n="28"/>
</div2></div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="3" id="d7">
<head>CHAP. III<lb/>
Of the Sharpness and ingenuity becoming an Oration.</head>



<p>Such is the Curiosity of this age in which we live, as that it is grown weary
of these plain and ordinary waies, an requireth or expecteth in the very style
something more than ordinary; insomuch that now a daies he is not worthy the
name of an <hi rend="italic">Orator</hi>, that knowes not how to brandish an
Oration, by some sharp and witty flourishes. And therefore, that we may comply
with the present times, we will also speak something of that sharpness or
ingenuity, with which an oration should be adorned.

</p><p>And first I will shew you what is meant by <hi
rend="italic">sharpness</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ingenuity</hi>: as <hi
rend="italic">Material sharpness</hi> then, is <hi rend="italic">the meeting
of two lines or sides in one point</hi>: so <hi rend="italic">Metaphorical
sharpness is an agreeing discord, or a disagreeing concord</hi>, that is, we are
then
<pb n="29"/>
said to speake <hi rend="italic">smartly</hi> or <hi
rend="italic">wittily</hi>, <hi rend="italic">when the predicate and subject
of an oration, do agree with one another in one part, and disagree in
another.</hi>

</p><p>This <hi rend="italic">sharpness</hi> or <hi
rend="italic">acuteness</hi> is threefold, <hi rend="italic">unnatural,
pr&aelig;ternatural, or natural.</hi>

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Unnatural sharpness</hi> is, when two things agree
that are in themselves unlike, opposite and contrary, or any way differing; or
when there is a different application of the subject and predicate; as thus:</p>

<lg type="poem">
<l><hi rend="italic">The fire doth scorch and burn, and oftimes flame,</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">Yet see, cold blasts do now come from the same.</hi></l>
</lg>

<p>It is against nature that cold should proceed from fire. Yet seeing that many
by that meanes have defended their chastitie, and restrained the heat of lust,
it is fitly said, that cold proceeds from fire.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Pr&aelig;ternatural sharpness</hi> is that, which is
not indeed against nature, but yet is very unusual: as, <hi
rend="italic">Martial</hi>:</p>

<l><hi rend="italic">Delici&aelig; populi que fuerunt Domini.</hi></l>

<p><hi rend="italic">Natural sharpness</hi> is that which doth agree

<pb n="30"/>

with the nature of the thing; as <hi rend="italic">Martial</hi>:</p>

<l><hi rend="italic">Impensis vitam Principis annumeres.</hi></l>

<p><hi rend="italic">It is the Kings grace that you are alive.</hi>  As if he
had said thus, You are beholding to the King for your life; whereas naturally,
it becomes a King to preserve the lives of his subjects.

</p><p>The best of these three is that which is called <hi
rend="italic">unnatural</hi>, because it begetteth great admiration.

</p><p>The wayes by which this <hi rend="italic">disagreeing concord</hi>
between the <hi rend="italic">subject</hi> and the <hi
rend="italic">predicate</hi> may be made, are chiefly four:

</p><p>1. By annexing to the subject a disagreeing Epithite; as, <hi
rend="italic">an innocent ruin: a confused order.</hi>

</p><p>2. By annexing to the subject another disagreeing substantive. As, <hi
rend="italic">The Sun is a fountain of light.</hi>

</p><p>3. By a <hi rend="italic">Catacresis</hi> either in the <hi
rend="italic">Adjective</hi>, in the <hi rend="italic">Sustantive</hi>, or in
the <hi rend="italic">Verb</hi>. First in the <hi
rend="italic">Adjective</hi>; as, <hi rend="italic">a brazen forehead</hi>,
meaning <hi rend="italic">shameless</hi>.

</p><p>In the <hi rend="italic">Sustantive</hi>, as if you call <hi
rend="italic">Almes</hi>, <hi rend="italic">an holy rain</hi>, or <hi
rend="italic">a golden shower of piety.</hi>

</p><p>In the <hi rend="italic">Verb</hi>, as thus; <hi rend="italic">the
waters made
<pb n="31"/>
the Souldiers valiant and compelled them to fight:</hi> that is they
were the more couragious, because being near the Sea it was impossible to fly.

</p><p>4. When the <hi rend="italic">predicate</hi> is both affirmed and denied
of the subject in a different sence; as the Poet speaking of a Virgin that lost
her beauty to preserve her chastity said: <hi rend="italic">And then she
thought her self most beautifull, when she had lost her beauty</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Matter</hi> in which to exemplifie these severall
wayes of making an agreeing discord between the subject and the predicate in a
proposition may be had first from the Logicall Topicks of <hi
rend="italic">Definition</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Division</hi>, &amp;c. for
there is none of them so barren from whence with a little consideration you may
not collect something that is smart and ingenious. <hi
rend="italic">Biderm</hi>.</p>

<lg type="poem">
<l><hi rend="italic">Quid facimus? glaciata gelu si Lympha negetur,</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">Ex oculis hanstas funus habebit aquas.</hi></l>
</lg>

<lg type="poem">
<l><hi rend="italic">What shall we do? if th' water be by frost
congeal'd,</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">Our eyes shall water for the funeral yield.</hi></l>
</lg>

<p>Where he sheweth that tears are the waters

<pb n="32"/>

proper <hi rend="italic"></hi>for or becoming funerals.  To run through all the
Topicks would be tedious, only observe, that the chiefe for this matter, are
these, <hi rend="italic">Final causes, effects, adjuncts, contraries</hi> and
<hi rend="italic">opposites</hi>: for hence it will be easie to find something
consentaneous and dissentaneous to the subject.

</p><p>Secondly, <hi rend="italic">Matter</hi> may be had from some <hi
rend="italic">Paradox</hi>, or some unusual speech.

</p><p>And unto this head may those be reduced, which are drawn from pleasant
jests: as,

</p><p>First from <hi rend="italic">Metaphors</hi>; as if one seeing a horse
with an ill favoured mouth should say, <hi rend="italic">the Horse laughs</hi>.

</p><p>2. From a <hi rend="italic">Paronomasia</hi>: as, <hi
rend="italic">Eminent men of great note, are now a daies most subject to
imminent dangers.</hi>

</p><p>3. From the <hi rend="italic">Etymologie</hi> of the <hi
rend="italic">name</hi>:

</p><p>4. From some rare and pleasant <hi rend="italic">story</hi>.

</p><p>Thirdly, From some lesson of <hi rend="italic">Morality</hi>.

</p><p>Fourthly, From some <hi rend="italic">Ambiguous</hi> word.

</p><p>Fifthly, From some <hi rend="italic">Trope</hi> and <hi
rend="italic">Figure</hi> in Rhetorick, especially from some <hi
rend="italic">Metaphor, Allegory, Catachresis, Metonymie,
Prosopop&oelig;a</hi>, &amp;c.

</p><p>And now though these directions, for the finding out of something in a
proposition
<pb n="33"/>
that is smart and ingenious are in themselves good, yet methinks they are not
clear and perspicuous enough; here therefore I will set down what <hi
rend="italic">Horatius P. Matthias Sarbievius</hi> hath more plainly exprest by
way of <hi rend="italic">Praxis</hi>, though much to the same purpose.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">first Praxis</hi> is, when some magnitude, bulk,
majesty, authority, largness, or destruction is fitly applied to any thing, in a
doubtful sence; and is indifferent whether it be taken really or Morally.  Thus
<hi rend="italic">Seneca</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Epist. 66.</hi> saith, <hi
rend="italic">that Sc&aelig;vola being lame and unarmed, made war, and with
that lame hand he overcame two Kings</hi>.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">second Praxis</hi> is the contrary unto this, when
a thing is diminished either in quantity, or estimation, and in a doubtfull
sence.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">third Praxis</hi> is when this Sharpness doth
actually contain the cause, or doubtfully insinuate some truth of a contrary
effect.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">fourth Praxis</hi> is from the ambiguity of some
word or sentence, as when it doth in truth signifie one thing, but is in tended
to signifie another.  Thus when <hi rend="italic">Julius Montanus</hi> was
repeating his verses,
<pb n="34"/>
and having described the <hi rend="italic">rising</hi> of the Sun, and began to
describe the manner of his <hi rend="italic">setting</hi>, one of the company
would have gone his way; and being asked the reason, said, <hi
rend="italic">Could I heare him any longer than from Sunrise, to Sunset</hi>?

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">fifth Praxis</hi> is, when that is applied to an
inanimate thing, which is proper to a thing that hath life, yet so, as that the
sence and meaning is understood, by some action of the thing of which we speak,
being applied to something of a contrary nature.  Thus <hi
rend="italic">Pliny</hi> speaking to one, that went to plough, after he had
gotten the victory in battaile, saith: <hi rend="italic">The earth rejoyceth to
shew it self to one that is victorious, and being tilled by a conquerour, she
waxeth proud with her early fullness of princely fruites</hi>.  And thus Saint
<hi rend="italic">Augustin</hi> upon these words of Christ, <hi
rend="italic">I am the true light</hi>, saith, <hi rend="italic">Rise then
thou sluggard, the way it self doth come unto thee, and rouzeth thee from sleep,
rise and walk.</hi>

</p><p>He also speaketh acutely, who applieth naturall things to things
artificial.

</p><p>Thus the Poet, of one that had a long nose, saith,</p>

<pb n="35"/>

<lg type="poem">
<l><hi rend="italic">Si tuus ad Solem statuatur nasus, hiante</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">Ore, bene ostendet dentibus hora quota est.</hi></l>
</lg>

<lg type="poem">
<l><hi rend="italic">Hold ope your mouth, your nose to th' Sun direct,</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">So will your teeth the hour of th' day detect</hi>.</l>
</lg>

<p>The <hi rend="italic">Sixt Praxis</hi> is, when that which doth agree with
real persons, is applied to those that are not real.  So he in <hi
rend="italic">Plautus, Our hands have eyes, and think they see</hi>.  But this
way is most pleasing, when in one and the same thing, the application is both
true and false: such is that of <hi rend="italic">Augustus C&aelig;sar</hi>,
when he said, that <hi rend="italic">he had two nice daughters, which he was
compelled to beare with</hi>; the one was <hi rend="italic">his daughter
Julia</hi>; and the other <hi rend="italic">the common wealth</hi>.

</p><p>There is yet another way of Inventing that which is sharp and witty; that
is by comparing the matter with the Oratorical heads and Topicks: this may be
done <hi rend="italic">three</hi> wayes.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">First</hi>, by comparing the matter in hand with every
topick severally; by considering what the thing is which we are to speak, what
the <hi rend="italic">Parts</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Genus</hi>, <hi
rend="italic">Species, adjuncts</hi>
<pb n="36"/>
and the rest. Thus doth that <hi rend="italic">Prince</hi> of <hi
rend="italic">Roman</hi> Eloquence, deride the consulship of <hi
rend="italic">Vatinius</hi>, by reckoning up the parts of the year in which he
was not Consul : <hi rend="italic">There happened,</hi>saith he, <hi
rend="italic">a wonderfull thing in the year of</hi> Vatinius, <hi
rend="italic">for while he was Consul, there was neither Spring, nor Autumn,
neither Summer nor Winter</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Secondly</hi>, by comparing one head of the matter in
hand, with another different head of the same thing: as the <hi
rend="italic">definition</hi> of the thing with its <hi
rend="italic">adjuncts</hi>, or of the <hi rend="italic">effects</hi> with the
<hi rend="italic">Causes</hi>.  Thus <hi rend="italic">Valerius Maximus</hi>
by comparing the body with the soul, finds out this smart commendation of <hi
rend="italic">Lucretia: Lucretia</hi>, saith he, <hi rend="italic">that
mirrour of Roman chastitie, whose manlike courage was by an evil mistake of
fortune, confined to a female body</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Thirdly</hi>, by comparing the Topicks of one order,
with other Topicks of the same order, as <hi rend="italic">definition</hi> with
<hi rend="italic">definition, cause</hi> with <hi rend="italic">cause</hi>,
&amp;c. as for example, <hi rend="italic">the King whom</hi> Mutius
Sc&aelig;vola <hi rend="italic">could not conquer by his armed band, he made to
fly, by setting his hand on fire.</hi>  Here the acuteness lies, in comparing of
one cause with another, that is his armed hand, with his hand in the flames.
And thus much concerning <hi rend="italic">Invention</hi>.</p>
<pb n="37"/>
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="4" id="d8">
<head>CHAP. IV.
<hi rend="italic">Of disposition</hi>.
</head>

<p>Disposition <hi rend="italic">is the orderly placing of those things which
are Invented</hi>.  It is two fold.

</p><p>First, <hi rend="italic">Natural</hi>, in which tings are discoursed in
that order in which they were done, or in which according to nature, they should
be done: as if you were to commend a person, you should first begin with his
childhood, next his youth, and so to the other degrees of his age.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">second</hi> way is <hi
rend="italic">Artificial</hi>, which doth either for delight, or profit
diversly mingle and confound the matter, putting that in the end which should be
in the beginning, and the beginning in the end, that so he may both delight the
Auditours and hold them in suspence; which in an unexpected event doth not a
little please and delight the hearers.  Thus doth <hi rend="italic">Virgil</hi>
do in his <hi rend="italic">&AElig;neades</hi>, in which he speaketh of <hi
rend="italic">&AElig;neas</hi> his voyage into <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi>,
but not in the same order in which he began: thus doth <hi
rend="italic">Barclay</hi>
<pb n="38"/><hi rend="italic"></hi>
in his <hi rend="italic">Argenes</hi>, and thus do all that write either
Comedies or Tragedies.

</p><p>The Orator then having resolved of his proposition, must <hi
rend="italic">first</hi> consider of what Nature is, whether single or
consisting of several parts, and which of the parts should be first handled,
which next.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Secondly</hi>, He must choose some few of the best
arguments he hath invented, and place some solid argument in the beginning,
those that are less forcible in the midst, reserving still the best and most
convincing argument for the conclusion; because the Auditor at the first being
greedy of knowing must be prepossessed and convinced, but in the end he must be
strongly confirmed and forced.

</p><p>And the most perswasive arguments are those, which proceed from the <hi
rend="italic">Definition</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Distribution, Genus,
Causes,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Effects</hi> of the thing discoursed of, for
these explain the nature thereof: The less forcible arguments are such as are
collected from some trivial adjuncts and conjectures.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Thirdly</hi>, He must Logically dispose of these
reasons and arguments, first into Syllogisms, and then consider how to enlarge
them in an Oratorical manner.

<pb n="39"/>

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Fourthly</hi>, He must consider into what parts his
Oration should be divided.  Concerning the two last, I will a little enlarge my
self: And

</p><p><hi rend="italic">First</hi>, of the Logical Disposition of those
reasons and arguments which are invented, by way of Syllogisms, and the
enlarging of those Syllogisms in an Oratorical manner.

</p><p>A logical argumentation <hi rend="italic">is the disposition or
explication of the argument, which when it is perfect doth consist of three
parts, of which that which is put in the first place, Logicians call the
</hi>Major<hi rend="italic">, Rhetoricians the</hi> Proposition: <hi
rend="italic">That which is put in the second place, philosophers call the
</hi>Minor,<hi rend="italic"> Orators the</hi> Assumption: <hi
rend="italic">That which is put in the third place is by Logicians called the
</hi>conclusion<hi rend="italic">, by Rhetoricians the</hi> complexion <hi
rend="italic">or</hi> inference. And these <hi rend="italic">three
propositions,</hi> when they are regularly placed, are called a <hi
rend="italic">Syllogism</hi>, which must be framed from that proposition, and
cause or reason, which was before invented.

</p><p>For example, the proposition was, <hi rend="italic">That</hi> Clodius<hi
rend="italic"> is justly put to death: the</hi> Argument or reason given for it
is, because<hi rend="italic"> he was a treacherous person.</hi>  Now then form
your Syllogism thus: Take this cause and joyn it with the predicate of your
proposition, saying,
<pb n="40"/>


<hi rend="italic">Every treacherous person doth deserve to be put to
death</hi>: and this is your <hi rend="italic">Major.</hi> Then take the
subject of your proposition, and joyn that with the given cause and say, <hi
rend="italic">Clodius was a treacherous person </hi>; and that is your <hi
rend="italic">Minor:</hi> then bring in the proposition it self, saying, <hi
rend="italic">therefore Clodius serveth death,</hi> which is the conclusion,
and maketh up the whole Syllogism. The like may be done in any other; but
alwayes, consider, with what reasons, examples, sentences or similitudes your
<hi rend="italic">Major</hi> or Minor may be again confirmed, especially if
they
be in themselves weak &amp; but probably true; for if they be certain, they are
not then to be proved, but handsomely expressed. This done, consider how these
Syllogisms may be handled Oratorically; the which besides many others may be
effected nine several wayes.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">first</hi> and most usual is so to place the parts
of the Syllogism, as Logicians do, that is the <hi rend="italic">Major
</hi>first, and the arguments by which it may be proved. The <hi
rend="italic">Minor</hi> next with the arguments for that ; And lastly the <hi
rend="italic">Conclusion</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Example.</hi>

</p><p>Imagine that some King through ambition
<pb n="41"/>

<hi rend="italic">
</hi>of raigning had killed his brother Prince; And so make this proposition<hi
rend="italic">, The King ought to be deposed ;</hi> The<hi rend="italic">
Reason, because he is wicked </hi>: place this Logically thus : <hi
rend="italic">We ought not to endure a wicked man in the Kingdom ; The King is
a wicked man; Therefore he is not to ne endured in the Kingdome.</hi> The Reason
of the <hi rend="italic">Major</hi> is ; because otherwise we shall blemish our
reputation among forreigners , by whom we have been always esteemed honourable,
and promoters of vertue, but shall now be called patrons and servants of
wickedness. The <hi rend="italic">Reason</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Minor
</hi>is, that he through ambition having deceitfully killed his brother, hath
been injurious to nature and to us :  This proposition, may Rhetorically be thus
handled.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Major.</hi>

</p><p>Have we the Citizens of N. now at length made such progress in the love
of wickedness, as that we are not ashamed to see the power of our lives and
liberties put into the hands of a desperately wicked person? Shall we now any
longer honour the Prince in wickedness, or wickedness in the Prince ? till we
our selves are reckoned among the wicked.

<pb n="42"/>

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Reason</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Major</hi>.


Ah woe is me! O Citizens of <hi rend="italic">N</hi>. Ah the glory of our name,
bought with the blood our Ancestors, which we have so rashly prostituted,
through our own inadvertcy ! That we who were formerly reputed the patrons of
vertue, should now be reckoned the servants of wickedness. What will be said by
the bordering, what by the more remote nations ? Behold ( shall they say ) the
men for whose vertuous acts the world it self was too narrow ; who could imbrace
nothing, nor do any thing, but what was contained within, or did not exceed the
bounds of vertue : behold them now so far fallen into naughtiness, that laying
aside all modesty, they are not ashamed to adore wickedness in the Throne. And
what is the guise of the rest of the Citizens ? What is the reputation of the
nobles ? if by their approbation baseness doth thus triumph in the highest place
of dignity. Certainly they cannot but love wickedness, who do not only permit
it, but also honour it.
<pb n="43"/>
</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Minor.</hi>

</p><p>Had our King gloried in a wicked act committed upon one of the meanest of
his subjects ; he might perhaps have had some small pretence for his cruelty,
though it had been accomplished with bloody hands.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Reason</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Minor</hi>.

</p><p>But to be so inhumanely enraged against the Prince his brother, who was
setled in the Kindome by our free and generall consent, what is it but to
proclaime a Warre against us and nature it self, and by this one impietie, to
offend the tribunals of all Nations.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Approbation</hi>

</p><p>Truly, if we do well, in judging of the day by the morning, we may be no
false Prophets, in foreseeing, what kind of <hi rend="italic">Nero</hi> he will
prove to us, who begins to feed his cruelty with the blood of his own relations,
and hath there made an entrance to his cruelty, where others have ended theirs.

<pb n="44"/>

therefore O ye generous progeny of all vertue, and if you have any respect to
your abased name, or the glory of your Nation, depose that wicked person from
the Throne; let it be heard in the world, let it be known to all posterity, that
wickedness might be in the Kingdom , but could not goe unpunished, no not in the
Prince.

</p><p>2. The <hi rend="italic">second</hi> way of Rhetoricall arguing is to
put the <hi rend="italic">Minor</hi> with the <hi rend="italic">Reasons</hi>
thereof in the first place, the <hi rend="italic">Major</hi> next and the <hi
rend="italic">Reasons</hi> thereof , and lastly the <hi
rend="italic">Conclusion.
</hi>
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Example.
</hi>
</p><p>Let the proposition be the contrary to the former, Namely, That <hi
rend="italic">the King ought not to be deposed, or put to death, for any
hainous offence committed by him.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Reason</hi> is,
because in so doing, we shall blemish our own reputation. Place it Logically
thus. <hi rend="italic">We who are Citizens ought not to blemish our own
reputation ; but if we depose the King or put him to death, we shall blemish our
owne reputation; Therefore we ought neither to depose the King , nor put him to
death.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Reason</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Major
</hi>is, Because Reputation is the publick treasure, and

<pb n="45"/>
noble patrimony of a Common wealth, which we all ought highly to regard. The <hi
rend="italic">Reafon</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Minor</hi> is, Because that
hitherto we have been famous, for that we never did depose our Prince or put him
to death, and this honour we shall now lose, if we do either.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Approbation,</hi> Because our Ancestors have also
had wicked Princes; and yet they did let them alone. And this proposition may be
Rhetorically handled in this manner.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Minor.
</hi>
</p><p>I wish O Citizens of <hi rend="italic">N</hi>. that they who through
accursed and disloyal boldnesse, have by their cruel suffrages decreed to rob
the Prince not only of his Throne, but also of his life, would but consider the
consequence of it in after ages : I would have them consider that our same shall
be more stained by their rashness, than it could have been by a patient
submission to his cruelty.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Reason</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Minor.
</hi>
</p><p>For hitherto it hath been our peculiar honour that our natural Princes,
have been
<pb n="46"/>
ours , not more by their birth-right than by our affection; neither hath the
world ever heard, that our hands have been stained with the blood of any of our
Princes : which as it is our peculiar honour above other Nations ; so it ought
to be our great studie to continue it. But now if we should lay wicked hands on
our Prince, shall we not fall headlong from the glory of our reputation ? And be
with the rest deservedly hissed at for paracides for ever?

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Approbation</hi>.

</p><p>Or, look back upon your Ancestours, and let it be your care to tread in
their footsteps: Whose Kings although they were Heroes, yet they were also men,
and that they were all of them free from vice, or that none of them did burthen
the Throne with wickedness, doth seem to me unlikely ; yet they rather endured
the wickedness of their Prince, than to make themselves wicked by deposing them;
and were willing to exceed in submission, rather than in fury.

<pb n="47"/>
</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Major</hi> with the <hi rend="italic">Reason.
</hi>
</p><p>Why then shall we degenerate foules banish our fame? Why shall we cruel
wretches suffer men to hatch cruelty againft the common-wealth? We who in honour
are compelled to have a principall regard unto our glory , as being our publick
treasure, and the most noble patrimony of our Kingdome, and ought, one with his
armes, and another with his good works, another with Justice, another with
Clemency ever maintaine it, is the great Magazin of our honour.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Conclusion.</hi>

</p><p>The King hath acted wickedly against his brother, let not us act wickedly
against the King, neither let posterity deride us, for committing one
wickedness, to be revenged of another ; let us have regard to that proverbial
speech of wise men, <hi rend="italic">If a King be good, obey him, if evill,
endure his wickedness with patience.</hi>

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Third</hi> way of arguing Rhetorically is to put
the <hi rend="italic">Conclusion</hi> in the first place with the <hi
rend="italic">Major</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Minor</hi> added thereunto, by
the particles, <hi rend="italic">for, therefore, for this</hi>

<pb n="48"/>

<hi rend="italic">cause</hi>, &amp;c. And if any argument follow sometimes we find
the conclusion repeat and sometimes not: but if the Oration be short, as most of
our common orations are, the Conclusion is repeated at last, in other words.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Example.</hi>

</p><p>In a <hi rend="italic">Gratulatory speech</hi>, for some kindness
received : of which the <hi rend="italic">proposition</hi> is <hi
rend="italic">I owe you many thankes:</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Reason,
Because you have given me a preferment, and have passed by others who were my
competitors.
</hi>
Place it Logically thus: <hi rend="italic">He who hath gotten a preferment from
one who hath passed by others his competitors , he oweth the Don many thanks ;
But I have gotten such a preferment. Therefore, </hi>&amp;c. Rhetorically thus:

</p><p>Beginning with the <hi rend="italic">Conclusion.
</hi>
</p><p>Most gracious Soveraign, The thanks which I owe unto your Majesty, for
the preferment, which you have bestowed upon me are such as cannot be expressed
by words; much less can they ever be requited by me; and I am necessarily
enforced to take up the words before your most gracious Majesty,
<pb n="49"/>
<hi rend="italic">
</hi>which <hi rend="italic">Socrates</hi> once used to <hi
rend="italic">Plato ; </hi> who when he had nothing to give him which was
answerable to his kindness cried out, O Plato <hi rend="italic">accept of
</hi>Socrates. And seeing your kindnesses to me have far transcended them of <hi
rend="italic">Plato</hi> to<hi rend="italic"> Socrates,</hi> and also that I
my self cannot be a recompence sufficient for the kindness of a King, I do here
devote my self and all that I have to your Majesty in token of gratitude.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Major.
</hi>
</p><p>Ought not he to account himself highly engaged to obedience, on whom the
King of his own mere inclination, hath conferred that honour, which many near
him have in vain expected, and for which many have in vain petitioned ?

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Reafon</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Major.</hi>

</p><p>Certainly his favour is heightened by the expectations and petitions of
others, and one bounty becometh two when he that hath it, is adorned with a much
desired honour, and in being thus adorned is preferred before all his
Competitors. It is not unknown to any, what men, how much deserving of
<pb n="50"/>

your Majesty, and of their countrey, have made great suite for this dignity both
by themselves &amp; others; with whom, if I should come in competition, I could
be hardly any way compared: but your most gracious Majesty, most bountifully
supplying the imperfections of my actions with your own benigne charity, hath
alwaies looked upon me, as one that hath devoted himself to you, and the Common-wealth.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Conclusion</hi> repeated.

</p><p>What shall I now promise, but earnestly to endeavour that you may never
have occasion to think, that you have placed your kindness on an ungratefull
soul ? I do therefore most humbly lay down my self and my endeavours, all that I
have, and all their endeavours, at your Majesties feet, to be ordered according
to your will and pleasure: be pleased to command us, and you shall find our
lives to be of less value to us than your injunctions.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Fourth</hi> way of Arguing Rhetorically, is to put
the <hi rend="italic">Major</hi> with the <hi rend="italic">Reason,
</hi>thereof in the first place ; Secondly the <hi rend="italic">Conclusion,
</hi>and Thirdly the <hi rend="italic">Minor:</hi>  Fourthly, if

<pb n="51"/>

it seem necessary, the <hi rend="italic">Conclusion</hi> may be repeated in
other words.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Example.</hi>

</p><p>If you would congratulate the arrival of some Kings Ambassador, or any
great Person: you may make this proposition <hi rend="italic">:We ought to
rejoyce in your coming to us:</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Reason; Because you
are a great person.</hi> Place it Logically thus: <hi rend="italic">We ought to
rejoyce, at the coming of a great Person. But you are a great person. Therefore,
</hi>&amp;c. Rhetorically: thus, beginning with the Major.

</p><p>The stars cannot appear without rejoycing the inanimate world ; nor great
persons without affecting the souls of men, <hi rend="italic">N. N.</hi> Nature
hath given them this, that they can not be,but they must be profitable.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Reason</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Major.</hi>

</p><p>Vertue hath imposed this most beautiful necessitie, That great men can be
no where, but where they may shew favour and clemency to those that are under
them.

<pb n="52"/>

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Conclusion</hi>.

</p><p>Would to God you might this day see thorowly into all our souls, yea even
of <hi rend="italic">Momus,</hi> you might there behold Love and Fear, Joy and
Sorrow, desire and eloquence, wrestling together in our hearts, with no ordinary
conflict: for when we salute you as our great Guest we cannot well tell, whether
our fear should love, or our love fear your Excellencie ; whether our joy should
sorrow its straitness, or our sorrow joy your appearance; whether our desires
should speak, or our Eloquence wish: Oh that we were wholly joy, wholly love,
wholly desire, wholly Eloquence , that we might here in your presence , expresse
our affections towards you as we ought.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Minor</hi> with the <hi rend="italic">Approbation
</hi>thereof.

</p><p>The truth is, that not only the Nobleness of your birth, singular
wisdome, sweet cariage, and behaviour , and your other inestimable vertues, do
make you great in our eyes : but we also reverence your greatnesse, because you
are so in the judgment of
<pb n="53"/>

the whole Kingdome ; which having those beames of honour on your person, hath
published to the world, that you are her Starr. Our King hath greatly esteemed
you in making you not only of his privy Councell, but Arbitrator of it, when he
hath again and again declared you worthy to accompany him, not only in <hi
rend="italic">Germany</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Britain,</hi> but even in all
the parts of his own Kingdome, that you might here and every where, be esteemed
great. And all our borders will for ever owne your greatnesse, because you have
condescended to shew your illustrious presence and noble soul in our mean
confines:  all of us being sensible, that great men do augment their greatness
by their condescentions.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Fift</hi> way of arguing Rhetorically.

</p><p>Sometimes the <hi rend="italic">Major</hi> is omitted, and the <hi
rend="italic">Reason</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Major</hi> with its <hi
rend="italic">Approbation</hi> is put in its place ; Then the <hi
rend="italic">Conclusion,</hi> afterward the <hi rend="italic">Minor</hi> with
the proof thereof, and lastly the conclusion is repeated.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Example.</hi>

</p><p>Let the proportion be: <hi rend="italic">You ought not</hi>

<pb n="54"/>

<hi rend="italic">greatly to lament the death of your friends.</hi> The <hi
rend="italic">Reason</hi> is : <hi rend="italic">because death is a common
evill:</hi> place it Logically thus: <hi rend="italic">We ought not greatly to
lament a common evill; but the Death of our freinds is a common evill ;
Therefore </hi>&amp;c. The<hi rend="italic"> Reafon</hi> of the <hi
rend="italic">Major</hi> is <hi rend="italic">, because a common evill cannot
be eschewed;</hi> you may handle it Rhetorically thus.

</p><p>Wise men do agree that what cannot be avoided, ought patiently to be
endured.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Approbation :</hi> That so in not feeling it, it
may appear to us, as if it did not particularly concern us.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Conclusion </hi>: We then do certainly ill, to
give our selves over to grief , for the departure of our friends, and in some
sort to bury our joy, in the same grave with them.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Minor.</hi>

</p><p>For this evil doth not concern, assalt, or befall one onely person; but
it conerns all alike, it overfloweth all.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Reason</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Minor.</hi>

</p><p>For all things on which we live, whose life we enjoy, in the use of which
we are delighted, are bound to the same Condition, are all subject unto death.

<pb n="55"/>
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Confirmation.</hi> Morover our soul doth inhabit but
an infirm and weak cottage, which doth in it self consist of adverse and
contrary elements, and from without it self, is assalted with many and great
dangers. To which purpose <hi rend="italic">Seneca</hi> saith well, <hi
rend="italic">that we are deceived, when we look on our death, as if it were to
come; a great part thereof is past, and this very time which we live is death.</hi>

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Conclusion</hi> repeated <hi
rend="italic">:</hi>

</p><p>Divide then that grief among all men, which you have engrossed to your
self from the common bitterness of fortune; we all run the same fate, and must
all endure it; think not then that you do well, in giving your self up to too
much to grief.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Sixt</hi> way.

</p><p>Oftimes the <hi rend="italic">Major</hi> is omitted, and the <hi
rend="italic">Minor</hi> onely with the <hi rend="italic">Approbation
</hi>thereof; and the <hi rend="italic">Conclufion,</hi> are mentioned. This
argumentation is called an <hi rend="italic">Enthymem</hi>, of which the firt
part is called the <hi rend="italic">Antecedent,</hi> the other the <hi
rend="italic">consequent.</hi> And you may place them as you please, the <hi
rend="italic">Antecedent</hi> first and then the <hi rend="italic">Consequent,
</hi>or on the contrary.

<pb n="56"/>

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Example.</hi>

</p><p>Let the proposition be: <hi rend="italic">Youths are not to be bridled
with rigid discipline.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Reason : Because they are not
the better</hi> for <hi rend="italic">rigour, but the worse.</hi> Omitting the
<hi rend="italic">Major,</hi> place it Logically thus : <hi
rend="italic">Youths are the worse for the rigour of discipline, therefore they
ought not to be kept under a rigid Discipline.</hi> Oratorically thus.

</p><p>You erre greatly if you think that youth may be improved by severity and
fear of discipline; for though they may by an austere carriage seem to be
reclaimed, yet really and indeed, they become thereby the more dissolute : Go to
experiences and you shall find them, to be commonly the worst of all others, who
have passed their youth under the most severe discipline. As a torrent may for a
while be stopped by an overthwart bank, but while it stops, it is but gathering
its more strong floud, by which when the bank is broken; it doth redeem the
length of its cessation, with its more raging flux: so youth being bridled under
cruel pressures, after it is once freed from those lawes by wich it was
restrained, it doth become the more violently insolent and drowneth the Soul

<pb n="57"/>

in the pursuite of those Syren snares from which it was before debarred : for we
alwaies desire forbidden fruit, and to enjoy what we cannot obtain. This disease
of the soul is best cured by indulgence: for as <hi rend="italic">Ovid
</hi>excellently describes such tempers.</p>

<lg type="poem">
<l><hi rend="italic">Quod licet ingratum est, quot non licet acrius
urit.</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">&mdash;Ipsa potestas</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">Semina nequiti&aelig; languidiora facit.</hi></l>
</lg>
<lg type="poem">
<l><hi rend="italic">We loath what's lawfull, what not, we desire</hi>.</l>
<l><hi rend="italic">The power of doing, doth put out the fire.</hi></l>
</lg>

<p>The <hi rend="italic">Seventh</hi> way.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Cicero</hi> directeth <hi rend="italic">Herenaius,
</hi>first to place the <hi rend="italic">exposition</hi> or the thing to be
proved, Secondly the <hi rend="italic">Reason</hi> or <hi
rend="italic">Reasons</hi>, Thirdly the <hi rend="italic">Approbation</hi>:
Fourthly the <hi rend="italic">exornation</hi> or <hi
rend="italic">illustration</hi>, from the contrary, or from Example,
Similitude, Testimony or Sentences &amp;c. Fiftly the <hi
rend="italic">Complexion</hi> in which all is summed up; this is the most easie
way, and most fit for extemporary speeches.

<pb n="58"/>
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Example.</hi>

</p><p>Let the proposition be : <hi rend="italic">A</hi> <hi
rend="italic">little knavery and wantoness doth not hurt a youth.</hi> The <hi
rend="italic">Reasons. Because they cannot presently be thereupon accounted
bad.</hi> For a man can not be alwayes good;  And the clearest  day hath some
clouds: The <hi rend="italic">Approbation.</hi> <hi rend="italic">And those
who are now old men, were wanton when they were young.</hi> The <hi
rend="italic">Exornation</hi> from <hi rend="italic">Testimony </hi>: A
certain Poet said, <hi rend="italic">He depriveth the year of the Spring, who
would not permit a youth to be wanton.</hi> From <hi rend="italic">Sentences;
And every age ought to have that behaviour, which is most agreeable thereunto.
</hi>From the <hi rend="italic">Contrary. It is unseemly for an old man to
behave himself like a youth : Therefore it it also, unseemly for a youth to
behave himself like an old man.</hi> From <hi rend="italic">Similitude ; For if
Ale be not mad when it is new, it is never good when it is stale.</hi> This you
may handle Rhetorically thus.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Exposition.</hi> What great matter is it if a youth be
somewhat waggish, for a little while? The <hi rend="italic">Reasons :</hi> Do
the <hi rend="italic">Spaniards</hi> therefore drink water, because they temper
their Wine? or doth one fair day make a Summer?
<pb n="59"/>

And what man is wise at all times? The clearest day hath ever had some clouds.
Why do we then so scrutinously reprehend the very least fault in a youth, and
(if I may speek freely) all that leudness in them, which in our selves we called
but waggery.  What if they Crown the streets with their friendly concourse, or
pull one another by the hair in jest; or weary their armes with a kind Wrestling
and are not alwayes among the prophets, not alwayes toiling at their bookes, but
sometimes give themselves to dancing, laughing, and jesting; what other things,
I say, are these but the sports of youth; and keeping themselves in action, till
age and experience, lead them to more noble imployments. Unless then they
disguise their faces like melancholy persons, unless their eyes be for ever
condemned to the earth that they may there tell all the stones and atoms of
dust, unless they hang their heads upon their shoulders, and become devotionary
ghosts; they must be thought worthy of banishment to <hi
rend="italic">Gyarus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Thale</hi>.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Comprobation</hi>.

</p><p>Oh rigid <hi rend="italic">Catos,</hi> fit to be Judges of <hi
rend="italic">Manlius</hi>'s laws, either you have forgotten your own youth, or
you might from the

<pb n="60"/>
former indulgencies of your own folly, learn to connive for a while at ours;
neither durst you by violating the priviledges of our youth accuse nature when
(as the Poet saith well)  <hi rend="italic">to deprive youth of their waggery,
is to deprive the year of its spring.</hi>

</p><p>From <hi rend="italic">Testimonies</hi>:

</p><p>Every age hath its proper limits; and it is as necessary that the
behaviour of persons should be suiteable to their years, as for garments to be
fitted for the body.

</p><p>From the <hi rend="italic">Contrary</hi>.

</p><p>And if we may deride a youthfull old man, why may we not by the same rule
detest the behaviour of the aged in those that are young? And what cruelty is it
in the morning of age to exact the noondaies gravity, and when the twilight of
wisedome doth scarcely appeare, you require the sageness of the perfect day. You
give your Horses, and Bullocks liberty; to exercise their irregular caperings ;
and are you so blind, that what you see to be naturall in other creatures, you
cannot see to be so in your owne children. And (that I may speak with all
mildness) be pleased at least to take a sober draught of this truth,

<pb n="61"/>

even out a Barrel of Ale; unless the Ale when it is new do fill the Aire; the
Cellar, the barrell, with a malepert hurly burly; it will when it is old be
neither healthful for the bodie, nor pleasing to the Palate.  And hence an
exhortation might be made, to take well and beare with the wantonness of youth.


</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Eighth</hi> way of arguing Rhetorically.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Eighth</hi> way is by <hi
rend="italic">Induction</hi>; now Induction <hi rend="italic">is a speech,
which from undoubted premises, doth inferr some one conclusion.</hi>

</p><p>In this we must observe <hi rend="italic">two</hi> things.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">First,</hi> That the things premised be certain.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Secondly,</hi> That what is inferred have some
resemblance to the things premised. This way of arguing is most familiar unto an
Oratour, and doth most excellently set forth a matter. <hi
rend="italic">Causinus</hi> saith, <hi rend="italic">it sweetly instills
matter, and is in proving delightfull:</hi> and if the things inferred be many,
it affords a large field for discourse.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Example.
</hi>
</p><p>Let the propofition be this. <hi rend="italic">A man should be commended
from what he is, and not</hi>

<pb n="62"/>

<hi rend="italic">from what he hath.</hi> The<hi rend="italic"> Reason:
because a Ship, and a Sword, and a square are commended from what they are and
not from the ornaments that they have.  Seneca</hi> doth thus handle it
Rhetorically.<hi rend="italic">
</hi>
</p><p>We call not that a good Ship which is painted with curious colours or
which hath a gilded head, or a stern overlaid with Ivory, or which is loaded
with the riches or revenues of Kings; but that which is stable, strong and
sound, to bear through the raging Billowes of the Sea, which is easily governed
by the Helm, is able to beare a gale of wind, and is withall a nimble sayler. We
call not that a good sword which hath an embroidered belt or a scabbard set with
Jewells, but which hath a sharp edge and point, to hew in peices all that
standeth in its way. The goodness of a thing is not in its beauty, but in its
fitness for that use for which it properly is. Therefore in a man also we are
not to regard how much he ploweth, how much he lets out on usury, by how many he
is courted, in how magnificent a bed he lieth, in how rich a Cup he drinketh,
but how good he is in himself <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>

</p><p>To this way doth that also of the Scythian Ambassadours in <hi
rend="italic">Quintus Curtius</hi> appertain,

<pb n="63"/>

proving to Alexander, that he ought not too much to trust to his greatness and
fortitude, by an Induction thus: <hi rend="italic">What,</hi> say they, <hi
rend="italic">know you not that great trees grow along time, and in an hour are
cut down: he is a fool that covets the fruite and considereth not the height of
the tree, on which it growes: the Lyon hath sometime been the food of small
birds; and ruft doth consume the strongest steel: there is nothing secure from
being destroyed, even by the most contemptible instrument.
</hi>
</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Ninth</hi> way of arguing Rhetorically, is to
argue from <hi rend="italic">Example.</hi>

</p><p>Now an Example <hi rend="italic">is an imperfect Induction, or arguing
from one Similitude to another</hi>. And is done <hi rend="italic">two
</hi>waies especially.

</p><p>First, Explaining a thing by a <hi rend="italic">Protasis</hi> and an
<hi rend="italic">Apodasis;</hi> so this proposition, <hi rend="italic">A
Generall should be a lover of learning, as</hi> Julius C&aelig;sar <hi
rend="italic">was,</hi> is thus handled. The more famous that <hi
rend="italic">Julius C&aelig;sar</hi> was in his victories, the more did he
exercise his learning; and with the same hands he scattered those Palmes in his
Books, with which he won them from his enemies. Who
then

<pb n="64"/>

then can deny, but learning is well becoming the most warlike Prince or Emperour
? Nay if he despise not the best counsell that can be given him, if he mean to
arrive to the perfect perfection of a good Prince, he will labour for learning
with all his might, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Secondly,</hi> We argue from <hi
rend="italic">Example</hi>, when after the relation we presently add some
reasons, either by way of approbation or disallowance, as we are wont to do in
other parts of the oration; but after the reasons given we apply the thing to
the matter in hand, shewing in what it doth or doth not agree.  This daily
practice is very antient; but observe that the use of <hi
rend="italic">Examples</hi> is very graceful (and the same may be said of <hi
rend="italic">Sentences, Apothegmes, Hieroglypicks,</hi> &amp;c.) when by that
either in the beginning or in other parts of the Oration we express the same
thing, which we should otherwise have done in our words.

</p><p>For Example, I would say: O ye Judges ye ought to take heed, that ye
ascend not the Tribunal for hope of reward: I would do this by Example; <hi
rend="italic">Agathocles</hi>, when he went to give Judgment, was wont to say,
<hi rend="italic">Let us go to a Golden harvest</hi>.

<pb n="65"/>

Then I would add the reason which I should have added to my proposition, namely
it is a wicked thing to endeavour to grow rich by other mens wickedness.

</p><p>Afterwards I would more fully prove and enlarg it.  Or instead of this
example, I might have used this sentence: They that are intrusted with the
government of the common wealth, should not go to the administration of Justice,
as those that go into a Faire or market.  And to this sentence, may be added
some reasons and arguments to prove the reasonableness of that assertion.  But
you must be alwaies carefull, that the example or sentence may beare the same
sence with the thing, that is in that place to be explained.</p>
<pb n="66"/>

</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="5" id="d9">
<head>CHAP. V.<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Of the parts in an Oration.</hi></head>

<p>When by the former directions you have put the invented matter, in to a
certain order; then consider of how many parts your Oration shall consist. <hi
rend="italic">Tully</hi> tells us that an Oration ought generally to consists
of these five parts.

</p><p>1. <hi rend="italic">Exordium.</hi><lb/>
2. <hi rend="italic">Proposition.</hi><lb/>
3. <hi rend="italic">Narration.</hi><lb/>
4.<hi rend="italic"> Confirmation.</hi><lb/>
5.<hi rend="italic"> Peroration.</hi><lb/>

</p><p>As for <hi rend="italic">Confutation</hi> it is comprised in <hi
rend="italic">Confirmation.</hi> But all these parts, are not alwaies
necessary; for the ingenious Orator may as he shall see it convenient, sometimes
omit the <hi rend="italic">Narration,</hi> sometimes the <hi
rend="italic">Exordium</hi>, sometimes the <hi rend="italic">Peroration
</hi>or <hi rend="italic">Conclusion</hi>, yea &amp; the <hi
rend="italic">Confirmation</hi> is many times scarce discernible; as when the
things propounded

<pb n="67"/>
are certain, there is more need of ornament than proof , as in Gratulatory
Orations and the like. As for the placing of these parts, their natural order is
that which we have named them I. The <hi rend="italic">Exordium</hi>, 2. The
<hi rend="italic">Proposition, </hi>3. The <hi rend="italic">Narration</hi>,
if it be not thought fit to omit it. 4. The <hi
rend="italic">Confirmation</hi>; and lastly the <hi
rend="italic">Peroration.</hi>

</p><p>Of each of these I will here set down some few directions; and first for
<hi rend="italic">Exordiums</hi>.

</p><p>An Exordium <hi rend="italic">is as it were the door of the Oration, in
which the Oratour doth prepare the minds of the Auditors for that which is to
follow </hi>: and this is commonly done by one of these <hi rend="italic">three
</hi>waies; <hi rend="italic">by bespeaking their favour; by making them
docible;</hi> or<hi rend="italic"> by begging their attention.</hi> The favour
of the Auditorsis bespoke either from the person of the Oratour, from the
persons of the Auditors, from the persons of the Adversaries, or from the
subject matter of the discourse. The Orator may bespeake the favour of the
Auditors, in respect of himself, if his getsture and deportment be suitable unto
theirs that are his Auditors, and express himself modestly. And in respect of
the Auditors, if he shew how well they have deserved
<pb n="68"/>
of the Common wealth, of him; and other men. And in respect of the Adversaries,
if he modestly shew wherein they are faulty and render them to the Auditors
inaxcusable. And lastly in respect of the matter in hand, if he say, that it is
some excellent, necessary and profitable thing.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Secondly</hi>, the Orator may be said make the
Auditors docible, if he clear explain the thing of which he is to speake, and
how he purposeth to enlarge upon it.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Thirdly</hi>, the Attention will be quickned if he
saith, that he intends to speak of some great and wonderfull thing, and some
thing that is delightful, necessary, and very much concerns his Auditors , <hi
rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>

</p><p>An <hi rend="italic">Exordium</hi> may be said to be faulty, or not so
commendable. <hi rend="italic">First</hi>, if it be vulgar or common, that is,
such as may be used in many if not in all cases. <hi
rend="italic">Secondly</hi>, if it be long and tedious, not proportionable to
the length of the Oration. <hi rend="italic">Thirdly,</hi> if it consist of
some different matter, not suitable to the other parts of the Oration. <hi
rend="italic">Fourthly</hi> if it effect not that which is  required or
expected.

</p><p>And that is said to be a good <hi rend="italic">Exordium</hi>, which is
neate and elegant, fit for the purpose; making the Auditor docible and well
affected, and from which the access

<pb n="69"/>
to the proposition is not violent and forced, but easie and agreable. Though <hi
rend="italic">Tully</hi> doth very much insist on this, that all <hi
rend="italic">Exordiums</hi> should be such, as will afford an easie and proper
access unto the proposition; yet practice which is the best master, and a
diligent observing, what manner of <hi rend="italic">Exordiums</hi> others make
to their Orations, will afford the best directions; but yet Rhetoricians are
wont to prescribe some certain formes according to which, beginners may exercise
themselves in framing their <hi rend="italic">Exordiums</hi> aright: the
chiefest of them are these following.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">They first way.</hi>

</p><p><hi rend="italic">First</hi>, propound some proposition or protasis, by
which an easie access may be made to the proposed matter. <hi
rend="italic">Secondly,</hi> Add some Reason or Confirmation, to which if you
will some refutation may be annexed, for he that confirmeth truths, hath also
the liberty to refute falshoods. <hi rend="italic">Thirdly,</hi> Add some
confirmation of the reason. <hi rend="italic">Fourthly,</hi> make some
particular inference or conclusion, to which some reason may be also added, and
thence an access to the proposition.

<pb n="70"/>
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Example.</hi>

</p><p>Let the propostion be this. <hi rend="italic">I will (before you my
Auditors) defend my good name which wicked men have hurt.</hi> To this you may
make your entrance thus. <hi rend="italic">There is nothing which Malice doth
not violate, nothing which it will not gnaw with the teeth of slander, or make
nauseous with the black venome of contumelious sarcasmes.  To this base work it
hath not a little advantage by the ill nature of this age wherein we live, in
which men are so unmanly, as not only to contemn the works of vertue, but even
to oppress what ever is done by the rules of honesty; if otherwise they cannot,
they will at least do it with a mist of scurrilous and scoffing language.  And
shall not we at last, by our indulgence to vice so much increase the family of
</hi>Momus<hi rend="italic">, as that in the end, we shall all be ashamed of
honesty: if we can even yet tamely behold and suffer the most wicked crime to be
committed with applause and led in triumph, and virtues to be condemned to
banishment, nay to flouts and hatred.  I have been unwilling to be the first
raker in this kennell, but the storm which hath again and again beat upon my
head with renewed waves, hath quite wearied my patience,
</hi><pb n="71"/><hi rend="italic">
and I doubt that I shall wrong good men in any longer sparing the bad.  For now
they do not invade my fortunes, which in it selfe were a miserable thing, they
do not raze my walls and [unclear] which were mischevious enough, they do not
gape after my life and safety, which were more than inhumane; but having set
upon my good name, my honour and reputation, which is to a good man far dearer
than his life, they strive to overwhelm this with whole burthens of reproaches.
Therefore that this audaciousness of wicked fellowes, may be by you most prudent
Auditors at once suppressed, be courteous to me this day, and candidly hear what
I have to say for my self</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">The second way.</hi>

</p><p>First understand the proposition well, of which you intend to speake,
then draw from thence some general reason, which may contain the most material
thing in the propostion; then amplifie, and adorn this reafon, with Sentences,
Examples, Similitudes, &amp;c. then bring in the proposition it self, as some
particular assumption of that general discourse.

 <pb n="72"/>
</p><p>For Example, suppose you were to make an <hi rend="italic">Exordium</hi>
to a funerall Oration, upon the death of some noble man, according to these
directions, you might perform it in this manner.

</p><p>"This is a lesson so well known to all that all must die, that he would
surely be thought to be beside himself that should but think himself immortal.
For men alas! like running waters may not alwaies continue in one place: one day
thrusts out another, one yeare devoureth another, and one wave overwhelmeth
another: And like as earthen vessels are quickly broken and easily shivered into
many pieces; so are our bodies soon dissolved, and quickly reduced to earth from
whence we were taken; we may be killed with too much joy, we may be opressed
with too much sorrow, we may die praying and fall down laughing; we maybe
throttled with a hair, or strangled with a flie. And thus on a sudden we are and
we are not; alive to day and dead to morrow, and every hour we hasten nearer and
nearer our end. There needs no other or farther testimony to prove the
assertion, than that the many instances of mortality
<pb n="73"/>
which so daily and so hourly happen that it is hard to turn our eyes from them;
yea even this sad occasion of our present meeting shews us, that whatsoever
difference there is or may be in our way of living, in this there is none, in
this we are equall, the certain uncertainty of our dying: If either wealth or
honour, if either Friends, or Physick could vanquish death, or prevent the
grave, we had not met this day to lament the death of this Honourable person; we
had not seen this spectacle of mortality, but death alas respects no persons,
will have no denyal unto his summons, whether it be in the evening of our dayes,
when our hoary haires may seem to proclaim us as fit for his stroak, as the corn
is for the sickle, when white for the Harvest; or whether he come in the morning
of our life, when our bones are full of marrow and our bloud runs briskly in our
veines, which is his case whose funerall obsequies we are now to perform. As a
green Apple is sometimes rudely pulled from off that tree on which it grew, so
was this branch cut down, before he had lived one half of the age of man. He was
indeed born of noble and unspotted

<pb n="74"/>

Parents, but as if that wisedome were not tied to years, his discretion did
adorn his birth more, than his birth him, &amp;c."

</p><p><hi rend="italic">The third way.</hi>

</p><p><hi rend="italic">First</hi>, Propound some opinion contrary to your
own, either with or without a reason for it. Then <hi rend="italic">Secondly,
</hi>Deliver your own opinion, with a reason or two, or without any reason also.
<hi rend="italic">Thirdly</hi>, Deliver the contrary reason, if it shall be
necessary, and so come to your proposition; that is, propound something in your
preceding words, from whence you may inferre your proposition ether plainly, or
obscurely. Let the proposition, for example, be: <hi rend="italic">Wisdome is
most suiteable to Noble men </hi>: That you may deduce this, first lay down the
contrary opinion, namely, <hi rend="italic">There are many think that Wisdom
becometh none but common people</hi>. The <hi rend="italic">Reason</hi> of this
contrary opinon. <hi rend="italic">Because Noble men are born for the Warrs,
not for the Schools, and have their commendations from their estates.</hi> Your
own proper opinion: <hi rend="italic">This is an evill opinion and to be
confuted</hi>. The <hi rend="italic">Reason</hi> and answer to this contrary
<pb n="75"/>

opinion. <hi rend="italic">Because it is mischievous to the world</hi>. Access
to your proposition. <hi rend="italic">I will therefore shew that Wisdom is
most proper for a Noble man</hi>.

</p><p>The<hi rend="italic"> Topicks</hi> or heads from whence matter for an
<hi rend="italic">Exordium</hi> may best be had, the most famous Rhetoricians
have reduced unto these.

</p><p>First, <hi rend="italic">An enumeration of causes,</hi> when the Oratour
shewes the causes which moved him to speak as if he were to commend some Noble
person; he might begin his <hi rend="italic">Exordium</hi> thus: <hi
rend="italic">You need not wonder that I should speak, in the commendation of
this worthy person; these reasons have induced me </hi>(and here lay down the
reafons ) <hi rend="italic">Therefore I shall speake, </hi>&amp;c.

</p><p>Secondly, <hi rend="italic">The Adjuncts of the Person,</hi> either of
the Orator himself, or of the Auditor, or of him of whom you are to speak:

</p><p>Example of the first.

</p><p>If you were to praise some body, you might thus begin. <hi
rend="italic">To express the just praises of this person, there should be
indeed a more skilful Orator than my selfe, but yet I thought my selfe obliged
thereto, not only for my affection to him, but also to expresse my gratitude,
for the many favours which I have received from him.</hi>

<pb n="76"/>

</p><p>Example of the second.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Although my weakness might command me silence, yet
courteous Auditors, the wonted candor which you have shewed to others doth both
invite and encourage me to speak; Therefore &amp;c.
</hi>

</p><p>Example of the third.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Though the things so be commended in this person, are
so many and so great, that they would require a</hi> Demosthenes <hi
rend="italic">or a</hi> Tully <hi rend="italic">to set forth his worth; yet I
will endeavour, </hi>&amp;c.

</p><p>Thirdly, <hi rend="italic">The Adjuncts of place.</hi> Example; <hi
rend="italic">If I had considered the dignity of this place, I should not have
undertaken, to speak unto you this day </hi>(and here shew the Reasons) <hi
rend="italic">but I considered more your humanity, and the necessity of the
thing, and therefore. </hi>&amp;c.

</p><p>Fourthly, <hi rend="italic">The Adjuncts of Time;</hi> as thus: <hi
rend="italic">The time requires, that I should speak this day unto you,
</hi>(here shew the reasons.)

</p><p>Fiftly, <hi rend="italic">The Adjunct of person, time, manner and place
together</hi>.

</p><p>Sixthly, <hi rend="italic">The opinions and affections of men,</hi> for
men do either rejoyce, or are sad, or angry, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c</hi>. And
according to these or the like passions or affections you may find matter for an
<hi rend="italic">Exordium</hi>.

<pb n="77"/>

</p><p>Seventhly, <hi rend="italic">Some passions with which the Oratour
himself may be affected,</hi> as anger or grief or admiration, or gratitude, <hi
rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>

</p><p>Eighthly, <hi rend="italic">The difficulty of the thing of which you are
to speake.
</hi>
</p><p>Ninthly, <hi rend="italic">Contradiction or Accusation:</hi> Example; if
you would contradict another, you may say; <hi rend="italic">I like not this
mans opinion, because</hi>, &amp;c. and here shew the reasons. If you would accuse
another you may say: <hi rend="italic">It is not for ill will to you or any
mind to do mischief which hath perswaded me to accuse you, but the love I have
to the common, for Justice sake, and for necessity.</hi>

</p><p>Tenthly, Preterition; as thus: <hi rend="italic">I could speak of many
things, but because I will not tire you with them, I will only mention one or
two.</hi>

</p><p>Eleventhly, You may find matter for an Exordium, <hi rend="italic">from
what hath either been said or done before</hi>; as if you were to accuse some
person, you may say: <hi rend="italic">This is not the first time that this
person hath been thus accused, found guilty, and yet born with, but now it
cannot be sure thought fit, that he should be born with any longer.</hi>

</p><p>Twelvthly, <hi rend="italic">Comparing and opposing opinions and
persons</hi>: as suppose you were to

<pb n="78"/>

speak for peace; you migh say: <hi rend="italic">Many are for War and shedding
of blood; But I believe that we can have no greater blessing than the blessing
of Peace.</hi> Or if you would compare persons, you may do it thus: <hi
rend="italic">Some worthy and learned men have heretofore spoken of
this subject, with whom I am in no wise to be compared; but because the matter
concernes the Common wealth, I also will speake freely, </hi>&amp;c.  This for
<hi rend="italic">Exordiums.</hi>

</p><p>The second part of an oration is the <hi rend="italic">Proposition</hi>.
And the <hi rend="italic">Proposition</hi> is that part of the Oration in which
the Orator doth briefly deliver the summe of the whole matter of which he
intends to speak, and bespeaks the hearers attention if need be. Sometimes it
doth immediately follow the <hi rend="italic">Exordium</hi>; sometimes it
follows the <hi rend="italic">Narration;</hi> in what place soever it be put,
it must be short and clear, and fit for <hi rend="italic">Confirmation.
</hi>
</p><p>And here it is to be observed first, that a<hi rend="italic">
Proposition</hi> may <orig reg="be">de</orig> delivered two waies.

</p><p>First, <hi rend="italic">Openly</hi>, when the Orator doth plainly
declare the matter of which he meanes to speak.

</p><p>Secondly, <hi rend="italic">Darkly</hi>, when the matter of his Oration
is sufficiently known before hand,
or may easily be discerned from the content, or when the thing to be proved is
not laid

<pb n="79"/>

down as a distinct part from the <hi rend="italic">Exordium,</hi> but is
insinuated as a member thereof annexed, and further to be proved afterwards.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Secondly,</hi> it is to be observed, that when a
proposition is longer than usual, it ought to be divided into certain parts,
that so the Orator may the more fully explain the matter, and the Auditor the
better remember it.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Narration</hi> is another part of an Oration, by which
a relation is made of the matter or thing done. And this is either a distinct
part of the oration, and then for the most part it doth immediately follow the
<hi rend="italic">Exordium</hi>, that the <hi rend="italic">Proposition</hi>
with the <hi rend="italic">Confirmation</hi> thereof may be collected from it.
Or else it is joyned with the <hi rend="italic">Confirmation</hi>, which is to
be done in such Orations which assume the explanation of the thing done to prove
the matter in hand; for example: <hi rend="italic">if you were to prove that
some valiant person, had been a Souldier in some warre; it is necessary that you
should declare, what the particular actions were, in which he shewed his
valour.</hi>

</p><p>But now in that Narration which is made a distinct part of the Oration,
the thing done must be briefly and simply declared without any exaggeration: and
in such a

<pb n="80"/>

Narration as makes way for confirmation the things done may be illustrated, with
great neatness of language with, sentences and figures; &amp; some discourses
may be made concerning the worthiness of the action, with some amplification
from similitudes and comparisons: In a word, where ever you make a <hi
rend="italic">Protasis</hi> from any History or Fable, and afterwards make an
application thereof, there you must make your <hi rend="italic">Narration</hi>,
and this may be in any part of the 0ration, even in the <hi
rend="italic">Exordium</hi>: but these kinds of <hi
rend="italic">Narrations</hi> are most usefull in such Orations as are in
commendation or discommendation of persons, in which it is necessary to declare
their vertues or their vices.

</p><p>That your <hi rend="italic">Narration</hi> may be such as it ought, you
must observe,

</p><p>First, that the known matter must be briefely declared; the matter
unknown more largely.

</p><p>Secondly, that there be in it some apt sentenccs, and that it express the
manners of men,as their pride, covetousness, and the like; and to this purpose
an <hi rend="italic">Hypotyposis,</hi> or <hi
rend="italic">prosopop&oelig;a</hi> and such like figures are usefull, to wit,
when some persons are introduced in their melancholy or studious

<pb n="81"/>

mood, or speaking something which doth declare and manifest what their natural
inclinations are.

</p><p>Thirdly, that it be plain &amp; clear. And that it maybe so, you must
avoid all circumlocutions, the reckoning up of a multitude of things, and making
large Catalogues of persons, with frequent and long perentheses and useless
digressions.

</p><p>Fourthly, that it be probable. And that it may be so, you must have a
care, that the circumstances of time, manners, place and person be all suteable;
besides some testimonies may be briefly named, unless the person from whom the
<hi rend="italic">Narration</hi> is made be well known, and of good credit. But
if any thing be mentioned, not altogether probable, some admonishment must be
made thereof, either by adding the cause, as <hi rend="italic">a Covetous man
throwes away his wealth because he saw his life in danger</hi>; or, <hi
rend="italic">a Fox despiseth grapes, because they are out of his reach,</hi>
Or by confessing the improbability, if no defence can otherwise be made, and
that either plainly thus;
<hi rend="italic">It is wonderfull if we may believe the Poets</hi>: or with
some compensation thus; <hi rend="italic">It is strang, but yet it is
true</hi>: or by naming some witnesses thus; <hi rend="italic">I know not the
reason, but this it is affirmed by very sober</hi>

<pb n="82"/><hi rend="italic">
</hi>
<hi rend="italic">men</hi>. Or by desiring the Auditors that they would at
present admit the thing, which afterwards you will prove more fully.

</p><p>Fiftly, that all the things declared, may <orig reg="tend">ctend</orig>
to the end propounded and that <orig reg="confirmation">onfirmation</orig> may
easily follow thereupon. Moreover in declaring any thing let the Orator chiefly
observe, the persons, matter, time, place, manner, and cause, which do almost
happen in all cases; but yet all these circumstances are not alwayes necessary
to be expressed, but as many of them only, as the Oratour in his discretion
shall think fit.

</p><p>The Fourth part of an Oration is <hi rend="italic">Confirmation;</hi>
and <hi rend="italic">Confirmation</hi> is as it were the very heart and soul
by which an Oration may be chiefly said to live: or it is the chief part of an
Oration in which the arguments are produced by which we would prove our
proposition, &amp; refute or answer the contrary opinion of our adversary, if
need require. What is necessary in this behalf, may be collected from what hath
been already said. Seeing that <hi rend="italic">Confirmation</hi> doth consist
of the arguments that are invented, and the right disposition of them, both
which have been fully enough declared before. Thus much only I will adde, that
the Orator in <hi rend="italic">Confirmation</hi> may do well to remember,
<pb n="83"/>

<hi rend="italic">First,</hi> to name those Arguments in the beginning of his
<hi rend="italic">Confirmation</hi>, and also in the conclusion which carry
with them the greatest weight, and those of least concernment in the midst. <hi
rend="italic">Secondly</hi>, to take care, that his Oration may still gather
strength; and this will be done, if the following words be still more
significant than the former, and that the affections be most moved in the very
close thereof. <hi rend="italic">Thirdly,</hi> let him take care, that all his
Arguments doe fully prove his proposition. <hi rend="italic">Fourthly,
</hi>that he urge not his arguments in one and the same manner and forme, but
that he use variety of figures, and propound them sometimes by way of <hi
rend="italic">Syllogism</hi>, sometimes in an <hi rend="italic">Enthymem,
</hi>sometimes ommitting the <hi rend="italic">Major,</hi> sometimes the <hi
rend="italic">Conclusion,</hi> as he thinks it most convenient. <hi
rend="italic">Fiftly,</hi> let him find out the <hi rend="italic">Crinomenon,
</hi>use fit <hi rend="italic">Transitions Sentences, Digressions</hi> and <hi
rend="italic">Amplifications.</hi> And the <hi rend="italic">Crinomenon</hi>
is that proposition in the Argumentation, whether General or Particular, in
which the whole strength doth lie, and that being proved, the whole matter
seemeth to be proved also: this therefore the Orator must especially declare and
confirme.

</p><p>Here then observe, 1. That the <hi rend="italic">Crinomenon</hi>

<pb n="84"/>

is sometimes the same with the proposition of the whole Oration; and then the
greater varietie of arguments may be sound to prove the proposition. <hi
rend="italic">For Example</hi>, let the proposition be this; <hi
rend="italic">I will shew you that a King ought to love his subjects and the
Common wealth</hi>. The first argument is; <hi rend="italic">Because the head
ought to love the members; The King is the head, the subjects are the members.
</hi>Therefore <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> The second Argument is;<hi
rend="italic"> Every one ought to love his patrimony. The common wealth is the
Kings patrimony</hi>: Therefore <hi rend="italic">&amp;c. </hi> Here you see
that severall arguments may be brought to confirm the proposition, because the
<hi rend="italic">Crinomenon</hi> is the same with the general proposition of
the Oration.

</p><p>Note 2. That the <hi rend="italic">Crinomenon</hi> is sometimes
different from the Generall proposition in the Oration, and then there is but
one principal argument in the whole Oration, which we must endeavour to confirme
and amplifye. Moreover this <hi rend="italic">Crinomenon</hi> may be
discovered, if you put your principal Arguments into a true Syllogisticall form;
for the <hi rend="italic">Minor</hi> in the syllogism is sometimes the <hi
rend="italic">Crinomenon,</hi> as in the first argument of the Oration, which
<hi rend="italic">Tully</hi> made for <hi rend="italic">Milo. He that is a
Traitor deserves to be kill'd</hi>. Claudius <hi rend="italic">was</hi>

<pb n="85"/>

<hi rend="italic">a Traitor</hi>: Therefore; where the <hi
rend="italic">Major:</hi> is certainly true, the <hi rend="italic">Minor
</hi>only is to be proved; this therefore <hi rend="italic">Tully
</hi>endeavours to do throughout that whole Oration.

</p><p>Sometimes the <hi rend="italic">Major</hi> is the <hi
rend="italic">Crinomenon,</hi> as <hi rend="italic">Tully</hi> in his Oration
for <hi rend="italic">Sextus Roscius. No son would kill his father, but for
some great cause</hi>; Sextus Roscius <hi rend="italic">is a son</hi>:
Therefore In this Syllogism the <hi rend="italic">Minor</hi> is undoubtedly
true, and therefore the <hi rend="italic">Major</hi> only is to be proved, for
in that is the whole force. Sometimes the <hi rend="italic">Crinomenon</hi> is
in the <hi rend="italic">Major</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Minor</hi> both. For
example, <hi rend="italic">He killed Roscius that was advantaged by his death :
but the death of Roscius was advantagious to Capiton;</hi> Therefore. Here the
<hi rend="italic">Major</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Minor</hi> are both to
be proved. In the reading therefore, and in the composing of Orations, the <hi
rend="italic">Crinomenon</hi> must be regarded. But when the General
proposition hath several parts, there are several <hi
rend="italic">Crinomenons</hi> to be regarded.

</p><p>2. As for <hi rend="italic">Transtions,</hi> it is by them that the
arguments for confirmation have a dependance on one another, yea and the several
parts of the Oration also. And a <hi rend="italic">Transition</hi> is a kind of
speech by which we express what hath been said in few words, and briefly shew
what. yet remaineth to be spoken. It is either <hi rend="italic">perfect</hi>
or <hi rend="italic">imperfect.</hi> That

<pb n="86"/>
is a <hi rend="italic">perfect Transition</hi> which repeats the things spoken,
and infers the things that are to be said: as if you should say; <hi
rend="italic">Enough hath been said concerning the necessity of Arms; <orig
reg="let">let let</orig> us now see what advantage may come from them</hi>. An
<hi rend="italic">imperfect Transition</hi> is when we do not revoke the things
that are spoken, but only proceed to the things that are to be spoken, with
these or the like expressions. <hi rend="italic">But now, furthermore, adde to
this</hi>, and such like. And note also that one argument doth then properly
follow another, when in the end of one argument, such a sence thereof is given,
as will easily open a way of speaking and arguing further.

</p><p>3. Sometimes the Orator may declare the argument by way of <hi
rend="italic">Sentence,</hi> and this may be twofold, <hi rend="italic">plain
</hi>or <hi rend="italic">obscure</hi>.

</p><p>A<hi rend="italic"> plain Sentence</hi> is the declaration of the truth
in few words. Or, it is an universal speech concerning the good that is to be
done, and the evil that is to be eschewed; concerning God, religion, providence,
and other things belonging to the life and manners of men. For example;</p>

<lg type="poem">
<l><hi rend="italic">Nemo mortalium omnibus horis sapit</hi>;</l>
<l><hi rend="italic">No man is wise at all times</hi>.</l>
</lg>

<pb n="87"/>
<p>An <hi rend="italic">obscure sentence</hi> is a particular speech deducted
from a general, the circumstances of persons, time and place being added
thereunto; as thus; <hi rend="italic">It</hi> <hi rend="italic">cannot be,
</hi>O Peter, <hi rend="italic">that thou shouldest be always wise.</hi>

</p><p>These <hi rend="italic">Occult sentences</hi> are to be very frequently
used in any part of an Oration, for they do adorn it much, and are very taking
with the Auditors: <hi rend="italic">Plain sentences</hi> may be also used, but
these do best become old men and such as have experience; and are chiefly to be
used in grave matters.

</p><p>4. <hi rend="italic">Digressions</hi> are oft times and very gracefully
used in <hi rend="italic">Confirmation</hi>: in which something is touched
upon, which seemeth little to the purpose, but yet doth serve to illustrate the
matter in hand. And this may be done either <hi rend="italic">briefly</hi>, and
then there needeth no <hi rend="italic">transition</hi>; or else <hi
rend="italic">more largely,</hi> and then the Orator must recall himself; as
from a long and a by-path to his present purpose.

</p><p>The Orator may use <hi rend="italic">Digressions</hi>, when he is to
speak of universal and common things, as, of vices, virtues, slavery, liberty,
life, death and such like.

</p><p>As suppose one were to prove, that it were not fit to thrust a learned
man out of a City, he might make his digression on the praise of learning,
shewing as well the necessity

<pb n="88"/>
as the profit of it. Expositions of things done and descriptions of places,
persons, customs and such like, may be handsomely used in <hi
rend="italic">digressions.</hi>

</p><p>5.<hi rend="italic"> Amplification</hi> is a speech, which doth augment
that, which being nakedly related would seem small and trivial, by describing of
it by adjuncts and circumstances. It is twofold, of <hi
rend="italic">words</hi> and <hi rend="italic">things</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Amplification of words,</hi> is that by which the
matter is augmented by the choice of words, and manner of speech. And a <hi
rend="italic">speech</hi> may be augmented from one word several ways.

</p><p>1. By the addition of fit Epithites ; thus <hi rend="italic">Tully</hi>
doth amplifie and enlarge this one word <hi rend="italic">War</hi> saying, that
it is <hi rend="italic">an horrible and a villainous war, and full of all
wickedness</hi>.

</p><p>2. By the use of suteable Adverbs; as, <hi rend="italic">you may justly
and deservedly praise him</hi>.

</p><p>3. By definition or discription; as, <hi rend="italic">the hands of
wicked and pernicious men,</hi> instead
<hi rend="italic">of murtherers</hi>.

</p><p>4. By Notation; as, <hi rend="italic">the golden mouthed
</hi>Chrisostom.

</p><p>5. Synonomies, when many expressions are used which carry the same sence;
as, <hi rend="italic">this conjunction of minds, this conspiring together in
one, this most pleasant society of life</hi>,

<pb n="89"/>

in stead of <hi rend="italic">friendship</hi>.

</p><p>6.  By Paraphrase; as, <hi rend="italic">this saying of the common
people he minded us of a long time since</hi>, in stead of this, <hi
rend="italic">it is a common saying</hi>; or thus, <hi rend="italic">it was
that season of the year when the earth puts on her most gorgeous apparel to
entertain the sun</hi>, for, <hi rend="italic">it was in the spring.</hi>

</p><p>7. By Enumeration of parts, when the parts are expressed instead of the
whole; as, instead of saying, <hi rend="italic">this valley is set forth with
all the imbellishments that low ground is capable of</hi>, one may say:<hi
rend="italic"> The rich fields of corn and green meadows lie in several
divisions inter-checkered like great beds of flowers, and fresh glass pots in a
large garden. The corn-fields look as if the roots which were hid in them
complained, that by mistake of their own strength, through a great desire of
being fruitful, they had sent forth more stalks than they could well support,
and the overladen ears encreased that oppression; the sweet grass grew up so
thick in the meadows, that it seemed to be straightened for want of room, and
yet crouded closer to make way for those fragrant flowers of all sorts which
grew up with it; and these mingling their various colours as they best fitted
the several greens which they found there, made a shew like a rich carpet, where
grass was the ground, rarely made up with beautiful Embroideries of
flowerwork.</hi>

<pb n="90"/>

</p><p>8. By the commemoration of causes, or the antecedents and consequents of
things, as: <hi rend="italic">Thou hast done what thou canst to destroy this
city with the sword, and with arms and with the terror of an army, and the
wickedness of Consuls, and by besieging the most fortified Temples, by
prepossessing the Judges, by overawing the Courts of Judicature, at home and
abroad</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Amplification of things</hi> is, when the matter it
self is encreased and confirmed with grave sentences: yet it is formed
indifferently from the same places from whence the arguments are taken, seeing
there are many definitions or descriptions of one and the same thing: as history
is the witness of times, the light of truth, the memory of fashions, the
messenger of antiquity, the mistress of behaviour.

</p><p>2. When many consequences are reckoned up; <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi>
those things which may presently or hereafter follow: as if the proposition
were; <hi rend="italic">Many mischiefs may follow for want of due
consideration.</hi>

</p><p>This may be amplified in this manner. <hi rend="italic">What are the
consequences of inconsideration? By this means the opportunity of advancement is
neglected, the present possession of goods is utterly lost, together with our
own lives and the common</hi>

<pb n="91"/>

<hi rend="italic">safety of all.</hi>

</p><p>3. When many causes are reckoned up: as if the proposition were this; <hi
rend="italic">Never do that of which you shall have cause to repent you
afterwards</hi>. Which may be amplified in this manner.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">When you do that which is to be lamented, you act
inconsiderately, than which there is nothing more foolish: you are overcome with
passion, than which there is nothing more imprudent: you foresee not what may
follow, than which there is nothing more dangerous: you restrain not your unruly
lusts, than which there is nothing more indecent.</hi>

</p><p>4. When many effects are reckoned up; as, let the proposition be,
Antonius <hi rend="italic">did the Romans many mischiefs</hi>. Which may be
thus Amplified. <hi rend="italic">The Romans bewail the loss of three armies,
which</hi> Antonius<hi rend="italic"> destroyed.  They stand in need of wise
men, and those</hi> Antonius<hi rend="italic"> hath deprived them of.  Their
Authority and reputation is much weakened and impaired, and that they may thank
</hi>Antonius<hi rend="italic"> for.</hi>

</p><p>5. When many similitudes are brought: for example sake, let this be the
proposition.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">If small falts be not corrected, they will hardly be
mended when they are greater</hi>. Which
you may amplifie in this manner: <hi rend="italic">Extinguish those sparks of
wickedness, unless you purpose to</hi>

<pb n="92"/>

<hi rend="italic">be consumed; stop up those fountains, unless you mean to be
overflowed with those violent waters; take Physick in time, if you fear the
approach of some mortal disease.  For as fire which is kindled by small embers,
doth many times destroy whole Cities: as a River is by the droppings of small
springs increased to such a heap of waters as overfloweth the whole land: as
light distempers do occasion great diseases, and sweep away whole families: so
the vices of young men, unless they be timely suppressed, will be more and more
rooted in them, until they have bereft their minds of all vertue and common
honesty</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Confutation</hi> is a part or kind of <hi
rend="italic">Confirmation</hi>, in which we answer all objections: it doth
either proceed or follow confirmation, or may be here and there used in all the
parts of the Oration. And these objections may be either all answered together,
or those first, which are first made, and then the latter; or those first which
are most material, and the rest may fall of themselves; or the weakest first,
that they being avoided, the strongest arguments may be somewhat weakned. And
the manner of doing this, is by shewing, that the Adversaries allegation is
either false, impossible, uncertain, or impertinent, and the like: and because
this part of an Oration is full of heat, and sometimes

<pb n="93"/>

of fury, it doth admit of <hi rend="italic">Dialogisms</hi> or conferences,
Ironies, illusions, interrogations, execrations, and other like vehement figures
and affections.

</p><p>These objections are sometimes rejected with great scorn, sometimes
eluded not so much by strength of argument, as by voice and gesture.

</p><p>The Adversary is sometimes vexed with chiding; sometimes pressed with
Questions, and the dint of all his arguments sometimes blunted with the like
objections: sometimes there is no answer given to that which he requireth of us;
sometimes the answer is not given presently, but first suspended for a long
time.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Peroration</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Conclusion
</hi>is the last part of an Oration, in which the Orator should very much
endeavour to set an edge in the minds of his Auditors, and incline them to be of
his side; and here he should therefore use such figures, as are most proper to
move the affections; it doth chieflly consist of two parts, <hi
rend="italic">Enumeration</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Amplification.</hi>

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Enumeration</hi> is required, that the chief arguments
more largely opened in the former discourse may be briefly and clearly repeated
in a new form of words. <hi rend="italic">Amplification</hi>

<pb n="94"/>

desires, that this repetition may made, by some serious expressions, adorned
with sentences and figures. This part of the Oration ought therefore to be more
exactly composed; because by this the Orator is commonly the more or less
valued; for this the Auditor do best remember, and from hence do pass their
judgments of us.</p>

</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="6" id="d10">
<head>CHAP. VI.<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Of Elocution.</hi></head>

<p>OF all the parts of Rhetorick, <hi rend="italic">Elocution</hi> in my
judgment is the most excellent, for that it is but to little purpose to have a
good <hi rend="italic">invention,</hi> and an excellent way of <hi
rend="italic">methodizing</hi> or disposing of arguments, unless we can also
express them in apt and fitting words, and handsomely adorn them with <hi
rend="italic">Tropes</hi> and<hi rend="italic"> Figures.</hi> In the wording
therefore of an Oration care must be had, that the words thereof be first plain
and significant, and then neat and elegant, and hence this

<pb n="95"/>

part of <hi rend="italic">Rhetorick</hi> may be thus defined.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Elocution or the garnishing of speech, is an art by
which the speeeh is beautified with the elegancy of words and sentences. </hi>

</p><p>And this is performed two ways, by the fine manner of words called a
<hi rend="italic">Trope</hi>, or by the fine frame of speech called a <hi
rend="italic">Figure</hi>.

</p><p>A Trope <hi rend="italic">is such an Elocution or manner of speech, as
doth change the signification of a word into a different signification from the
natural</hi>.

</p><p>In a <hi rend="italic">Trope</hi> two things are to be considered.

</p><p>1. <hi rend="italic">The Affections.</hi>
</p><p>2. <hi rend="italic">The Kinds.</hi>

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Affections</hi> of a Trope are 4.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Catachresis <lb/>
Hyperbole <lb/>
Metalepsis <lb/>
Allegoria.<lb/></hi>

</p><p>Catachresis <hi rend="italic">is a harsh and unpleasant change of a
word</hi>; as namely when one word or name is put for another, not by any proper
relation, but by a kind of force. <hi rend="italic">He threatens me a good
turn.</hi> Enoch <hi rend="italic">was translated, that he should not see
death.</hi>

</p><p>Hyperbole <hi rend="italic">is a very false relation of a thing, or a
more bold excess of a Trope, which doth exceed belief, either by augmentation or
by diminution.</hi> Note, that though an <hi rend="italic">Hyperbole</hi> doth

<pb n="96"/>

vary from the truth, yet doth it not deceive us through fiction or such
variation.

</p><p>An <hi rend="italic">Hyperbole</hi> is twofold: <hi
rend="italic">Auxesis</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Meiosis</hi>.

</p><p>An <hi rend="italic">Auxesis</hi> is, when <hi rend="italic">for
augmentation sake or Amplification, we interpose a more vehement expression, in
his proper place</hi>; as when we say, <hi rend="italic">Magnificent</hi> for
<hi rend="italic">Liberal</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Cruel</hi> for <hi
rend="italic">Severe</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Sacrilegious</hi> for <hi
rend="italic">Wicked</hi>.

</p><p>A <hi rend="italic">Meiosis</hi>, or a <hi rend="italic">Tapinosis</hi>
is when <hi rend="italic">for extenuation sake we use a milder or more
favourable expression</hi>, than the matter requireth: as when we say a <hi
rend="italic">Flatterer</hi> is a <hi rend="italic">courteous and an affable
person</hi>.

</p><p>A Metalepsis <hi rend="italic">is that which conteineth many Tropes in
one expression</hi>; as when we by an improper speech, signifie, first that
which is improper, and by that improper speech perhaps another, and so forward
till we come to that which is proper, making way for transition by interposing a
mean degree; as <hi rend="italic">All the City was moved.</hi> Math. 21. 10.
where the <hi rend="italic">City</hi> is put for <hi
rend="italic">Jerusalem</hi>, by a <hi rend="italic">Synecdoche Generis</hi>:
and <hi rend="italic">Jerusalem</hi> for <hi rend="italic">its
inhabitants</hi>, by a <hi rend="italic">Metonymy of the subject</hi>.

</p><p>An ALLEGORY <hi rend="italic">is the continuation of a Trope, as where
many Tropes of the same</hi>

<pb n="97"/>

<hi rend="italic">kind are joyned together: as, put on the whole armour of God.
</hi>Ephes. 6. 11. <hi rend="italic">He shall be as a Tree planted by the
rivers of water</hi>. Psalm. 1.

</p><p>In an <hi rend="italic">Allegory</hi> observe to end with the same kind
of Trope with which you begin; or else the inconsequence will be absurd.

</p><p>The several kinds of Tropes are these four.

</p><p>1. <hi rend="italic">A Metonymy</hi>.
</p><p>2. <hi rend="italic">An Irony</hi>.
</p><p>3. <hi rend="italic">A Metaphore</hi>, and
</p><p>4. <hi rend="italic">A Synechdoche</hi>.

</p><p>A Metonymy<hi rend="italic"> is a Trope of the cause to the effect, of
the subject to the adjunct: and the contrary, of the effect to the cause, or of
the adjunct to the subject</hi>.

</p><p>4. There are four kinds of <hi rend="italic">Causes</hi>.

</p><p>1. The <hi rend="italic">Efficient cause</hi>, by which a thing is.
</p><p>2. The <hi rend="italic">Material cause</hi>, of which a thing is made.
</p><p>3. The <hi rend="italic">Formal cause</hi>, by which a thing is what it
is.
</p><p>4. The <hi rend="italic">Final cause</hi>, for which a thing is: of
which the two first only belong to our present purpose.

</p><p>A <hi rend="italic">Metonymy of the Cause</hi> is twofold, that is, of
the <hi rend="italic">Efficient</hi> or of the <hi rend="italic">Material
Cause</hi>.

</p><p>A <hi rend="italic">Metonymy of the efficient Cause</hi> is, when

<pb n="98"/>
the Author or inventor of any thing is put for those things which they have
effected, or of which he is Author, as <hi rend="italic">Mars</hi> for <hi
rend="italic">war, Vulcan</hi> for <hi rend="italic">fire, Neptune</hi> for
the <hi rend="italic">Sea, Ceres</hi> for <hi rend="italic">bread, Bacchus
</hi>for <hi rend="italic">wine, Venus</hi> for <hi rend="italic">love, Livie
</hi>for the <hi rend="italic">History written by Livie, Virgil</hi> for the
<hi rend="italic">poems or works composed by Virgil.</hi>

</p><p>And thus the <hi rend="italic">instrument</hi> is also put for the <hi
rend="italic">thing effected by it</hi>. As the <hi rend="italic">tongue</hi>
for <hi rend="italic">speech</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">hand</hi> for <hi
rend="italic">writing</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">sword</hi> for <hi
rend="italic">slaughter</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Arms</hi> for <hi
rend="italic">war</hi>.

</p><p>A <hi rend="italic">Metonymy of the Material Cause</hi> is, when the
name of the matter is put for the effect; as <hi rend="italic">Brass</hi> for
<hi rend="italic">brass mony</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Silver</hi> for <hi
rend="italic">Silver mony</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Gold</hi> for <hi
rend="italic">gold coin</hi>: <hi rend="italic">they worshipped wood and
stone</hi>; i.e. Idols made of wood and stone: <hi rend="italic">the iron
entered into his soul,</hi> i.e. fetters.

</p><p>A<hi rend="italic"> Metonymy of the effect</hi> is, when the efficient
cause is signified by the effects: as <hi rend="italic">Victory is by nature
proud and insolent</hi>; that is, it maketh men proud and insolent. <hi
rend="italic">Pale death;</hi> which <hi rend="italic">maketh pale.</hi>

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Note.</hi> That is called the effect which dependeth upon the efficient
cause.

</p><p>Thus <hi rend="italic">Wickedness</hi> is put for the ungodly [unclear]
of wicked actions, the <hi rend="italic">work</hi> for the [unclear].

<pb n="99"/>

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Quas meruit p&oelig;nas jam dedivillud opus.</hi>

</p><p><hi rend="italic">The work hath received that punishment which it did
deserve</hi>; that is <hi rend="italic">Ovid</hi> the Author of the work.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">A Metonymy of the Subject is,</hi> when the proper
name of any subject is made to signifie the adjunct.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Note</hi>. That is said to be a Subject, in which a
thing may be any way said to be or adhere.

</p><p>There may be <hi rend="italic">Metonymy of the subject</hi> these nine
several ways.

</p><p>1. When a Subject is put for an inherent accident; as, <hi
rend="italic">Curii</hi> for <hi rend="italic">Victory, Curius</hi> being the
name of a certain victorious Captain.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">2.</hi> When the thing conteining is put for the
conteined. As the <hi rend="italic">Cup</hi> for the <hi rend="italic">drink
</hi>in the Cup, the <hi rend="italic">purse</hi> for the <hi
rend="italic">mony</hi>.

</p><p>3. When the place is put for the inhabitants; as, The <hi
rend="italic">City</hi> for the <hi rend="italic">Citizens. They smote the
city with the sword,</hi> i.e. the men in it.

</p><p>4. When the place is put for the things done in the place; as, <hi
rend="italic">Psal.</hi> <hi rend="italic">68. 29. Because of thy Temple at
Jerusalem</hi>; where by Temple is understood the holy exercises and divine
worship used in the Temple.

<pb n="100"/>



</p><p>5. When the possessor is put for the thing possessed by him; as, <hi
rend="italic">Joel,</hi> 3. 20. <hi rend="italic">Judah shall be inhabited for
ever</hi>: where <hi rend="italic">Judah</hi> the Son of <hi
rend="italic">Jacob</hi> is put for the Land of <hi rend="italic">Jury</hi>,
which was promised to his posterity and by them possessed.

</p><p>6. When the Captain is put for his army; as, <hi rend="italic">Annibal
is conquered,</hi> that is,<hi rend="italic"> Annibal's</hi> army.

</p><p>7. When a Patron or advocate is put for his client; as, <hi
rend="italic">The cause will go against the Attorney General,</hi> that is,
against his client.

</p><p>8. When a thing which is done in time is put for the time in which it was
done; as, <hi rend="italic">Harvest</hi> for <hi rend="italic">Summer</hi>,
<hi rend="italic">Job</hi>. 32. 7. <hi rend="italic"> I said days should
speak, and multitude of years should teach wisdom</hi>, i. e, the aged who have
seen many days.

</p><p>9. When the name of the thing signified is put for the sign; as, <hi
rend="italic">Ovid. Fast</hi>: 1. <hi rend="italic">vers</hi>. 201.</p>

<lg type="poem">
<l><hi rend="italic">Juppiter angusta vix totus stabat in &aelig;de</hi>:</l>
<l><hi rend="italic">Inque Jovis dextra fictile fulmen erat</hi>.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="poem">
<l><hi rend="italic">In narrow court, Jove could scarce upright stand</hi>,</l>
<l><hi rend="italic">And held an earthen thunderbolt in's hand</hi>.</l>
</lg>
<bibl><hi rend="italic">Virg. Eclog. 3.</hi></bibl>

<pb n="101"/>

<l><hi rend="italic">Orpheaq</hi>; in medio posuit, sylvasq; sequentes.</l>

<p><hi rend="italic">In the midst he set</hi> Orpheus <hi rend="italic">and
the woods following</hi>, that is, the carved images of <hi
rend="italic">Orpheus</hi> and the woods.

</p><p>A <hi rend="italic">Metonymy of the adjunct is</hi>, when the adjunct is
put for the subject. <hi rend="italic">Gen</hi>. 31. 53. <hi
rend="italic">Jacob sware by the fear of his father</hi> Isaac, i.e. by God
whom <hi rend="italic">Isaac</hi> feared.

</p><p>There may be <hi rend="italic">a Metonymy of the adjunct</hi> eight
several ways.

</p><p>1. When the names of vertues are put for good men, of vices for wicked,
and of many other things for the persons to whom they belong, or to whom they
may be called Adjuncts; as, <hi rend="italic">on this side modesty contendeth,
impudence on that</hi>; where modesty is put for modest men, and impudence for
impudent men.

</p><p>2. When the thing conteined is put for the thing conteining; as, <hi
rend="italic">Psal.</hi> II.7. <hi rend="italic">The righteous Lord loverth
righteousness,</hi> i. e. righteous men.

</p><p>3. When the adjunct of the time is put for the subject. Thus the <hi
rend="italic">night</hi> is put for <hi rend="italic">sleep</hi>, which is
usually taken in the night. <hi rend="italic">Ephes</hi>. 5. 16. <hi
rend="italic">The days are evil</hi>, i. e. the hearts and conversations of the
men of these days are evil.

<pb n="102"/>

</p><p>4. When the Sign is put for the thing signified; as, The <hi
rend="italic">Scepter</hi> for the <hi rend="italic">Kingdome</hi>,  a<hi
rend="italic"> gown</hi> for <hi rend="italic">peace, Arms</hi> for<hi
rend="italic"> war.

</hi>

</p><p>5. When the thing placed is put for the place it self: <hi
rend="italic">we sought thee in all books</hi>, that is, in booksellers shops.

</p><p>6. When the Antecedent is put for the consequent; as, <hi
rend="italic">pray hear</hi>, meaning, pray observe.

</p><p>7. When the consequent is put for the antecedent; as, <hi
rend="italic">He is buried,</hi> instead of, he is dead.

</p><p>8. When one Concomitant is put for another; as, <hi
rend="italic">Annibal staid there,</hi> that is the Army of <hi
rend="italic">Anninal</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">An Irony is a Trope from one opposite to another</hi>;
or, <hi rend="italic">in which we speak by contraries</hi>.

</p><p>An <hi rend="italic">Irony</hi> may be perceived three ways 1. by the
manner of pronunciation; 2. by the person; 3. by the nature of the thing: for if
any of these do differ from the words, it is clear, that the intention doth
differ from them also.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Opposites</hi> are of two sorts, <hi
rend="italic">Unlike</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Contrary</hi>.

</p><p>All things of different natures are said to be unlike; as, <hi
rend="italic">A man, a Stone, a Book, a Dog</hi>;

<pb n="103"/>

and therefore one particular thing, may be equally opposed to many things. All
things are said to be contrary to one another that are of contrary natures: as
<hi rend="italic">light</hi> and <hi rend="italic">darkness</hi>, <hi
rend="italic">head</hi> and <hi rend="italic">cold</hi>: and therefore one
particular thing may be equally opposed to another particular.
<hi rend="italic">An Irony of a thing unlike</hi> is, when any thing is spoken
of one person and understood of another: whether it be affirmed of both, or
denyed of one, as, <hi rend="italic">Virgil Eclog. 3.</hi></p>

<lg type="poem">
<l><hi rend="italic">Tum credo cum me arbustum videre Myconis,</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">Atque mala vites incidere falce novellas.</hi></l>
</lg>
<lg type="poem">
<l><hi rend="italic">Sure 'twas when I in</hi> Mycon's <hi
rend="italic">ground was took,</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">Pruning his vines with an unwelcome hook.</hi></l>
</lg>
<p>Where <hi rend="italic">Menalcas</hi> naming himself means <hi
rend="italic">Dametas.</hi>

</p><p>Denied of one, as, <hi rend="italic">Ovid Metam. 13.</hi></p>

<l><hi rend="italic">Nec in his quisquam damnatus &amp; exul.</hi></l>

<l><hi rend="italic">None of these were either hanged or banished.</hi></l>

<p>Where <hi rend="italic">Ulysses</hi> accusing <hi rend="italic">Ajax</hi>
tells him that none of his kindred were either hanged or banished ; thereby
intimating that some of Ajax's generation were, to wit,
<pb n="104"/>
his father <hi rend="italic">Telamon,</hi> and his Uncle <hi
rend="italic">Peleus,</hi> for killing of Phoenix.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">An Irony from the contrary</hi> is, when one contrary
is signified by another; as,

</p>
<l><hi rend="italic">O Salve bene vir cucurasti  probe.</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">O thou art an honest man, thou hast done very
well:</hi></l>

<p>meaning that he was a very rogue and had been very careless.

</p><p>Paralepsis <hi rend="italic">is a kind of Irony, by which we seem to
pass by or take no notice of such things which yet we strictly observe and
remember</hi>.

</p><p>The forms of this figure are these; <hi rend="italic">I let pass, I am
silent, I omit, I will leave out, I say not</hi> &amp;c. as thus, <hi
rend="italic">I say nothing of your licentious life, incestuous marriage, or
your being perjured in such a cause,</hi> &amp;c. Where in a kind of elegancy we
seem to pass by those
crimes, which we do more eminently remember.

</p><p>Apopharis <hi rend="italic">is a kind of Irony, by which we deny to say
or do, which yet we speak with greatest earnestness, and do with all our might;
</hi>as, <hi rend="italic">nor will I mention these things, which if I
should, you could not I am sure, deny them</hi>. This figure differs from the
former, in nothing but the manner of speaking.

<pb n="105"/>

</p><p>A Metaphore <hi rend="italic">is a Trope by which we express our selves
by a word, which is of like signification, with that we mean</hi>. There is
nothing in the world, of which there is not another thing to which it may be
resembled; and therefore there is nothing from whence a <hi
rend="italic">Metaphore</hi> may not be deduced; as, <hi
rend="italic">Princeps caput Rei-public&aelig;e, The King is the head of the
common wealth.

</hi></p><p>There are eight sort of things especially, from which a <hi
rend="italic">Metaphore</hi> may be deduced.

</p><p>1. From sacred and holy things; as, <hi rend="italic">One man is a God
to another</hi>.

</p><p>2. From the Heavens;  as, <hi rend="italic">Virgil the sun of
Poets</hi>.

</p><p>3. From the Elements; as, <hi rend="italic">The fire of envy; the flood
of eloquence and Rhetorick</hi>.

</p><p>4. From Meteors; as <hi rend="italic">The lightning of an Oration</hi>.

</p><p>5. From Minerals; as, <hi rend="italic">Golden ages; an Iron
breast</hi>.

</p><p>6. From Vegetables; as, <hi rend="italic">The flower of nobility</hi>.

</p><p>7. From living creatures; as, <hi rend="italic">England is the eye of
Islands; Orators do bark not speak</hi>.

</p><p>8. From Artificial things; as, <hi rend="italic">Appion is the Cymbal of
the world</hi>, so called for his much talking.

<pb n="106"/>

And hence are these expressions, <hi rend="italic">To file a writing, to polish
an oration, to rip or unsow friendship</hi>.

</p><p>Synecdoche <hi rend="italic">is a Trope, by which a part is put for the
whole and the contrary;</hi> i. e.<hi rend="italic"> the whole is put for a
part</hi>.

</p><p>A <hi rend="italic">part</hi> is twofold. A <hi
rend="italic">Member</hi>, or A <hi rend="italic">Species</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">A Synecdoche of  a Member</hi> is, when by a member
the whole is signified. As the <hi rend="italic">Roof</hi> for the <hi
rend="italic">house</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">swords point</hi> for the <hi
rend="italic">sword it self</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">General</hi> for his <hi
rend="italic">Army</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">soul</hi> for a <hi
rend="italic">man.

</hi></p><p>Thus the singular number is put for the plural; as, <hi
rend="italic">The Roman was victor in battel</hi>, meaning the army of the
Romans.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Note</hi>. That the singular number is a part or
member of the plural, not a distinct nature: especially considering that every
multitude doth consist of unities, as of so many particulars.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">A Synecdoche of the Species</hi> is, when the <hi
rend="italic">Species</hi> is put for the Genus; as, when <hi
rend="italic">Aristides</hi> is put for a <hi rend="italic">just man</hi>, <hi
rend="italic">Cr&oelig;sus</hi> for a <hi rend="italic">rich man</hi>.

</p><p>Thus we put an infinite number for a great number; as, <hi
rend="italic">you may bring six hundred</hi>
<pb n="107"/>

<hi rend="italic">such</hi>; Six hundred, one species or sort of a great
number, for a great number in the general.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">A Synecdoche of the whole</hi> is, when the whole is
put for a part.

</p><p>The whole is either an <hi rend="italic">Integer</hi>, or <hi
rend="italic">A Genus</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">A Synecdoche of an Integer</hi> is, when an Integer is
put for a member; as, <hi rend="italic">His Army was so great as that it drank
the rivers dry</hi>: meaning a great part of the water in the rivers.

</p><p>Thus the plural number is put for the singular; as, <hi
rend="italic">Cicero</hi> to <hi rend="italic">Brutus</hi>; <hi
rend="italic">we deceived the people and seemed Orators:</hi> When the Orator
spake of himself only.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">A Synecdoche of the Genus</hi> is, when the General is
put for the Special; as, <hi rend="italic">a man</hi>
for <hi rend="italic">Catiline</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Vertue</hi> for <hi
rend="italic">fortitude</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Poet</hi> for <hi
rend="italic">Homer</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Virgil</hi>, <hi
rend="italic">Orator</hi> for <hi rend="italic">Demosthenes</hi> or <hi
rend="italic">Tully</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Mark</hi>. 16. 15. <hi
rend="italic">Preach the Gospel to every creature</hi>: meaning mankind only,
and not any other creature.

</p><p>Hitherto of <hi rend="italic">Tropes</hi> the first kind of elocution;
the second kind of elocution is by <hi rend="italic">Figure</hi>.</p>

<pb n="108"/>

</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="7" id="d11">
<head>CHAP. VII.</head>

<p>A Figure <hi rend="italic">is a kind of Elocution by which the form of a
speech is changed from its right and plain use</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">A Figure</hi> is either of A <hi
rend="italic">Word</hi>, or A <hi rend="italic">Sentence</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">A Figure of a word</hi> is that by which an Oration or
speech is composed of words aptly and sweetly suitable to one another. And this
consists either in the <hi rend="italic">Dimension</hi> or <hi
rend="italic">Repetition of sounds or words</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">A Figure in the Dimension of sounds</hi> is the sweet
number of sounds in a sentence.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Number</hi> is either <hi rend="italic">Poetical</hi>
or <hi rend="italic">Oratorical</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">A Poetical number</hi> is that, which is confined to a
perpetual observation of certain spaces.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">A Number Poetical</hi> is either <hi
rend="italic">Rhyme</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Meter</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Rhyme</hi> is a poetical number containing a certain
number of feet, without any regard to the quantity of Syllables whether long or
short. But here many times
<pb n="109"/>
there are several sentences joyned together in which the last Syllables are
like; as,
</p>
<lg type="poem">
<l><hi rend="italic">Dare to be true: nothing can need a lie:</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">A fault that needs it most, grows two thereby.</hi></l>
</lg>

<p><hi rend="italic">A Meter</hi> is a poetical number consisting of certain
feet, of which the last foot hath the last Syllable indifferent or common, that
is, long or short.

</p><p>In this kind of Poetical number, there is a liberty granted for a certain
<hi rend="italic">Metaplasm</hi> or transformation of a word, namely when there
is something wanting in it, or when there is too much, or when there is
something changed.

</p><p>There are four kinds of <hi rend="italic">Metaplasms.
</hi>
</p><p>1. By Elision or taking away something from the end of a word; in the
scanning of a verse.

</p><p>And this is either, <hi rend="italic">Synal&aelig;pha</hi> or <hi
rend="italic">Ecthlipsis</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Synal&aelig;pha</hi> is an elision or striking out of
one vowel before another in divers words; as, <hi rend="italic">'tis</hi>, for
<hi rend="italic">it is</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Ecthlipsis</hi> is when the letter <hi
rend="italic">m</hi> with his vowel is taken away, because the word following
beginneth with a vowel; as, <hi rend="italic">Syncer'est</hi>, for <hi
rend="italic">Syncerum est</hi>.

</p><p>2. The second kind of <hi rend="italic">Metaplasm</hi> is by
<pb n="110"/>
adding something to, or deducting something from a word: and of this there are
six kinds.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Prosthesis, Aph&aelig;resis, Epenthesis, Syncope,
Paragoge,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Apocope</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Prosthesis</hi> is the adding of a letter or Syllable
to the beginning of a word.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Aph&aelig;resis</hi> is the taking away of a letter or
a Syllable from the beginning of a word.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Epenthesis</hi> is the putting of a letter or Syllable
into the middle of a word.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Syncope</hi> is the taking away of a letter or
Syllable from the middle of a word.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Paragoge</hi> is the putting of a letter or syllable
to the end of a word.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Apocope</hi> is the taking of a letter or syllable
from the end of a word.

</p><p>3. The third kind of <hi rend="italic">Metaplasms</hi> is by dividing
and contracting of words, the one is called <hi rend="italic">Di&aelig;resis,
</hi>the other <hi rend="italic">Syn&aelig;resis</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Di&aelig;resis</hi> is that which maketh two syllables
of one.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Syn&aelig;resis</hi> is the contracting of two
syllables into one.

</p><p>4. The fourth kind of <hi rend="italic">Metaplasms</hi> is by changing
something in a word, and of this there are five kinds. <hi
rend="italic">Imesis, Metathesis, Antithesis, Diastole</hi> and <hi
rend="italic">Systole.</hi>

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Imesis</hi> is that which divides the parts of a
<pb n="111"/>
compound or simple word by putting another word between them.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Metathesis</hi> is the transposition or misplacing of
a letter in a word.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Antithesis</hi> is the putting of one letter for
another.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Diastole</hi> is that which maketh a short syllable
long.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Systole</hi> is that which maketh a long syllable
short.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Oratorical number</hi> doth indeed consist of feet,
but not of any certain number of feet, but of as many or as few as the Orator
pleaseth. And although for testimony or delight he may sometimes recite the
verses of others, yet must he not make verses, when he writeth prose. He should
not make the beginning or the end of a verse to be either the beginning or end
of prose. But a greater care is to be had of the close than either of the
beginning or middle of a speech, for in that the perfection of number doth
chiefly appear; but these things will be better understood by the practice of
the meanest Orator, than the precepts of the most skilful.

</p><p>What the <hi rend="italic">Figure of a word</hi> is, in the <hi
rend="italic">Dimension of the sound thereof,</hi> hath been shewed: now
followeth the <hi rend="italic">Figure of a word</hi> in respect of the <hi
rend="italic">repetition</hi> thereof.

<pb n="112"/>
</p><p>And this is twofold, <hi rend="italic">Like</hi>, or <hi
rend="italic">Unlike</hi>.

</p><p>A <hi rend="italic">Figure of a word in the repetition of like
sound</hi> is either <hi rend="italic">with</hi> or <hi rend="italic">without
intermission</hi>.

</p><p>Repetition of like sound <hi rend="italic">without intermission</hi> is
either an <hi rend="italic">Epizeuxis</hi> or an <hi
rend="italic">Anadiplosis</hi>.

</p><p>An <hi rend="italic">Epizeuxis</hi> is, when a like sound is repeated in
the same sentence witht intermission, and that either a part or a whole word.

</p><p>An <hi rend="italic">Epizeuxis</hi> or repetition of a whole word may be
in the beginning, middle or end of a sentence; as, <hi rend="italic">Ezek</hi>.
21. 9, 27. <hi rend="italic">A sword, a sword is sharpened</hi> &amp;c. <hi
rend="italic">I will overturn, overturn, overturn it</hi>.  And thus <hi
rend="italic">David</hi> bewaileth the death of his son <hi
rend="italic">Absolon</hi> in 2. <hi rend="italic">Sam</hi>. 18. 33. <hi
rend="italic">O my son</hi> Absolom<hi rend="italic">, my son, my son
</hi>Absolom<hi rend="italic">; would God I had died for thee, O
</hi>Absolom<hi rend="italic">, my son, my son</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">An Anadiplosis</hi> is, wen a like sund without
intermission is repeated in divers sentences, that is when it ends one and
begins another; as, in Dr. <hi rend="italic">Donne</hi>'s Poems, <hi
rend="italic">Page</hi> 210.</p>

<lg type="poem">
<l><hi rend="italic">If then, why I take not my leave she ask</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">Aske her again, why she did not unmask?</hi></l>
</lg>

<pb n="113"/>

<p>And in the use of this Figure there is sometimes a Climax; as when an <hi
rend="italic">Anadiplosis</hi> is continued with many degrees. <hi
rend="italic">Pro</hi> Milon: <hi rend="italic">Nor did he only render himself
to the people, but to the Senate: nor to the Senate only, but to the publick
Garisons and Armies: nor to these only, but even to him, with whom the Senate
hath intrusted the common-wealth. Ad</hi> Heren: <hi rend="italic">What hope of
liberty now remaineth; if it be lawful for them to do what they please, and that
they can do what is lawful, and dare do, what they can, and actually do, as much
as they dare, and you like whatever they do? Wherein we thought each line, each
word, each syllable breath'd out the passions of a clear and candid soul</hi>.
Howels <hi rend="italic">Ep.</hi> 3. <hi rend="italic">Epist</hi>.18.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Repetition of like sound</hi> but with some
intermission is either in the <hi rend="italic">same</hi> or in <hi
rend="italic">divers</hi> places.

</p><p>Repetition of like sound with intermission in the <hi rend="italic">same
place</hi> is either an <hi rend="italic">Anaphora</hi>, or an <hi
rend="italic">Epistrophe</hi>.

</p><p>An <hi rend="italic">Anaphora</hi> is, when a like sound is repeated in
the beginning of sentences; as,</p>

<lg type="poem">
<l><hi rend="italic">By art of sails and oars Seas ore divided;</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">By art the Charriot runs; by art love's guided.</hi></l>
</lg>
<bibl>Ovid <hi rend="italic">de Arte amandi. lib</hi>. 1. <hi
rend="italic">Carm</hi>. 3. and 4.</bibl>

<pb n="114"/>

<lg type="poem">
<l><hi rend="italic">'Tis safe and frequent, fraud through love to
frame.</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">'Tis safe and frequent, but deserveth blame.</hi></l>
</lg>
<bibl>Ovid <hi rend="italic">de Arte amandi</hi>. <hi rend="italic">lib</hi>.
1. <hi rend="italic">page</hi> 197.</bibl>

<p>An <hi rend="italic">Epistrophe</hi> is, when a like sound is repeated in
the close of sentences; as, 2 <hi rend="italic">Cor</hi> 11. 22.<hi
rend="italic"> Are they Hebrews? so am I: are they Israelites? so am I: are
they the seed of</hi> Abraham<hi rend="italic">? so am I</hi>.

</p><p>From an <hi rend="italic">Anaphora</hi> and an <hi
rend="italic">Epitrophe</hi> joyned together is made another figure called <hi
rend="italic">Symploce</hi>; which is, when a like sound is both in the
beginning and the ending of several sentences; as, <hi rend="italic">Can the
host of heaven help me? can Angels help me? can these inferiour creatures help
me.</hi>

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Repetition of like sound</hi> and with intermission,
in divers parts or places, is either an <hi rend="italic">Epanalipsis</hi> or
an <hi rend="italic">Epanados.
</hi>

</p><p>An <hi rend="italic">Epanalipsis</hi> is, when a like sound is repeated
in the beginning and ending of the same sentence; as, <hi rend="italic">In
sorrow was I born, and I must die in sorrow</hi>.  1. <hi
rend="italic">Cor</hi>. 3. 21, 22. <hi rend="italic">All things are yours,
whether things present, or things to come, all are yours</hi>.

</p><p>An <hi rend="italic">Epanodos</hi> is, when the like sound is in the
beginning and ending of divers sentences,
<pb n="115"/>

an <hi rend="italic">Anadiplosis</hi> coming between; as, Parthenia <hi
rend="italic">desired above all things to have</hi> Argalus; Argalus <hi
rend="italic">feared nothing but to miss</hi> Parthenia. <hi
rend="italic">Isaiah</hi> 5. 20. <hi rend="italic">Wo unto them who call good
evil, and evil good; who put darkness for light, and light for darkness; who
glory in their shame, and are ashamed of their glory</hi>.

</p>

<lg type="poem">
<l><hi rend="italic">Whether the worst, the child accurst</hi>,</l>
<l><hi rend="italic">Or else the cruel mother</hi>?</l>
<l><hi rend="italic">The mother worst, the child accurst</hi>,</l>
<l><hi rend="italic">As bad the one as th' other</hi>.</l>
</lg>

<p>Hitherto of the <hi rend="italic">Figure of a word repeated of like
sound</hi>, now follow two figures more made by the repetition of sounds
somewhat<hi rend="italic"> unlike, Paronomasia</hi> and <hi
rend="italic">Polyptoton</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Paronomasia</hi> is, when a word being changed in a
letter or a syllable, it is also changed in sence and signification; as, <hi
rend="italic">Though you</hi> advise<hi rend="italic"> me to repent, I have
not grace to follow your</hi> advice. Eminent<hi rend="italic"> men of great
note, are now a days most subject to</hi> imminent<hi rend="italic"> dangers.
'Tis not
so tedious to me as to others, to be thus</hi> immur'd<hi rend="italic">,
because I have been inured and habituated
unto troubles.</hi> Howels<hi rend="italic"> Epist. 1. Volu. sect. 6. Epist.
50.</hi>

<pb n="116"/>

</p><p>A <hi rend="italic">Polyptoton</hi> is,  when words of the same original
are reiterated but with some variation, whether it be in mood or tense or person
or number or any other; as, <hi rend="italic">Vanity of Vanities, all is
vanity. Deceiving and being deceived.  The Lord when he visiteth, in visiting
will visit you</hi>.</p>

</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="8" id="d12">
<head>CHAP. VIII.</head>

<p>Hitherto of a figure in reference to words. A Figure in reference to a <hi
rend="italic">sentence</hi> is a figure which affecteth the whole sentence with
some motion of the mind.

</p><p>A Figure in reference to a <hi rend="italic">sentence</hi> is either in
<hi rend="italic">absolute reasoning,</hi> or in.reasoning <hi
rend="italic">Dialogue-wise</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Logismus</hi> or<hi rend="italic"> absolute
reasoning</hi> is, when a sentence is composed without any talking with other
supposed.

</p><p>And this is either <hi rend="italic">Ecphonesis</hi>, a recalling of one
self, <hi rend="italic">Apostrophe or Prosopopeia</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Ecphonesis</hi> is a figure in reasoning, expressed or
understood by an Adverb of exclaiming: it is a very great instrument of

<pb n="117"/>

moving the mind, and affections of those to whom we speak.

</p><p>1<hi rend="italic">.</hi> By way of <hi rend="italic">Admiration</hi>;
as, <hi rend="italic">Oh the wonderful clemency</hi>! or, <hi rend="italic">Oh
happy people that are in such a case</hi>!

</p><p>2. <hi rend="italic">Derision</hi>; as, <hi rend="italic">Mark</hi> 15.
29. <hi rend="italic">Ah thou that destroyest the Temple and buildest it in
three days</hi>.

</p><p>3. <hi rend="italic">Wishing</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Psal</hi>. 14. 17.
<hi rend="italic">O that the salvation of Israel were come out of Sion</hi>.

</p><p>4. <hi rend="italic">Detestation</hi>; as, <hi rend="italic">Rom</hi>.
7. 24. <hi rend="italic">O wrethed man that I am, who shall deliver me from the
body of this death?</hi>

</p><p>5. <hi rend="italic">Reprehension</hi>; as, <hi rend="italic">O Foolish
Galathians who hath bewitched you </hi>&amp;c. <hi rend="italic">Gal</hi>. 3.
1.

</p><p>6. <hi rend="italic">Indignation</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Act</hi>. 13.
10. <hi rend="italic">O full of all subtility and mischief, thou child of the
Devil, thou enemy of all righteousness</hi>.

</p><p>7. <hi rend="italic">Love</hi>; as, <hi rend="italic">Psal</hi>. 84. 1.
<hi rend="italic">O how amiable are thy tabernacles, thou Lord of hosts</hi>.

</p><p>8. <hi rend="italic">Exultation</hi>; as, 1. Cor. 15. 15. <hi
rend="italic">O death where is thy sting, Oh grave where is thy victory?</hi>

</p><p>9. <hi rend="italic">Commiseration</hi> and <hi
rend="italic">Grief</hi>; as, Luke 13. 34. <hi rend="italic">O Jerusalem,
Jerusalem, which killest the Prophets</hi> &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">How often
would I have gathered thy children together</hi>, &amp;c.

</p><p>12. <hi rend="italic">Epiphonema</hi> is also a kind of exclamation,
which is wont to be added to the

<pb n="118"/>


end of the narration or explication of a matter. Thus the Psalmist having highly
set forth the glorious excellency of the name of God, in <hi
rend="italic">Psal. </hi>72<hi rend="italic">.</hi> shuts up his praise with
this acclamation; <hi rend="italic">Blessed be his glorious name for ever, and
let the whole earth be filled with his glory</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Recalling of ones self</hi> is, when something is
called back: and it is as it were a diminution of the over hastiness or heat of
speech: and this is either <hi rend="italic">Epanorthosis</hi> or <hi
rend="italic">Aposiopesis</hi>.

</p><p>An <hi rend="italic">Epanorthosis</hi> is, when something preceding is
called back by correcting it: as, <hi rend="italic">I had one only young man to
my Son; ah! what have I said? I had ? yea I had: it is now uncertain whether I
have or not.</hi>

</p><p>An <hi rend="italic">Aposiopesis</hi> is, when the close of a sentence
begun is stopped by keeping in a part which yet is understood; as, <hi
rend="italic">you rogue, if I live</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Heb</hi>. 3. 11.
<hi rend="italic">To whom I sware in my wrath, if they enter into my rest</hi>;
i.e. they shall never enter into my rest.

</p><p>Hitherto of perfect and absolute reasoning by way of exclamation and
revocation. Now followeth that which is in <hi rend="italic">Apostrophe</hi>
and <hi rend="italic">Prosopop&oelig;ia</hi>.

</p><p>An <hi rend="italic">Apostrophe</hi> is, when a speech is directed to
another, than was by the speech it self at first intended.

<pb n="119"/>
</p><p>And this may be done divers ways. As when a speech is directed

</p><p>1. To God. 2. To Angels good or bad. 3. To men in their several ranks,
whether absent or present, dead or alive, as Adversaries or friends, to the
present Auditors, or ones self. 4. To brute creatures, and 5. to things
inanimate.

</p><p>A <hi rend="italic">Prosopop&oelig;ia</hi> is, when in our Oration, we
suppose another person to be speaking. And by this figure, God, Angels, men dead
or alive, the heavens, earth, sea, and such like are brought in speaking,
hearing, &amp;c. As, <hi rend="italic">Josh</hi>. 24. 27. <hi
rend="italic">Behold this shall be a witness unto us; for it hath heard all the
words of the Lord which he hath spoken unto us</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic"></hi>A <hi rend="italic">Prosopop&oelig;ia</hi> is
either <hi rend="italic">imperfect</hi> or <hi rend="italic">perfect.</hi>

</p><p>An <hi rend="italic">Imperfect Prosopop&oelig;ia</hi> is,when anothers
speech is lightly declared and as it were by the by; as, <hi
rend="italic">Psal</hi>.11. 1. <hi rend="italic">David</hi> brings in the
wicked as saying unto his soul, <hi rend="italic">flee as a Bird unto your
mountain</hi>.

</p><p>A perfect <hi rend="italic">Prosopop&oelig;ia</hi> is when in our own
Oration the whole fiction of another person is plainly declared; as, <hi
rend="italic">Prov</hi>. 8. <hi rend="italic">Wisdome cryeth at the gates</hi>
&amp;c.<hi rend="italic"> Unto you, O men, I call</hi>, &amp;c. <hi
rend="italic">
</hi>

</p><p>A Figure in reasoning <hi rend="italic">Dialogue-wise</hi> is, when a
sentence is composed in form of a

<pb n="120"/>
conference; this consisteth in Question and Answer: of which kind of reasoning
there are two parts <hi rend="italic">Hypophora</hi> and <hi
rend="italic">Anthypophora</hi>.

</p><p>But <hi rend="italic">Dialogism</hi> or reasoning by Question and Answer
is twofold, <hi rend="italic">Consenting</hi> and <hi
rend="italic">Dissenting</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Dissenting</hi> is when ones answer doth impugne or
cross the objection.

</p><p>A Figure of a <hi rend="italic">dissenting Dialogism</hi> is either <hi
rend="italic">Deliberation</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Occupation</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Deliberation</hi> is either an <hi
rend="italic">Aporia</hi> or an <hi rend="italic">Anac&oelig;nosis</hi>.


</p><p>An <hi rend="italic">Aporia</hi> is a deliberation with ourselves;
as <hi rend="italic">Philip</hi>. 1. 22. <hi rend="italic">But if I live in
the flesh, this is the fruit of my labour: yet what I shall chose I know not;
for I am in a strait between two, having a desire to depart, and to be with
Christ, which is far better: nevertheless to abide in the flesh is more needful
for you</hi> &amp;c.

</p><p>An <hi rend="italic">Anac&oelig;nosis</hi> is, a deliberation with
others; as thus, <hi rend="italic">what shall I say? what think you? if it had
been your own case, would you have done otherwise</hi>?

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Occupation</hi> is when we prevent anothers objection
and give an answer to it our selves. This <hi rend="italic">Dialogism</hi>
therefore from the former part is called a <hi rend="italic">Prolepsis,
</hi>from the latter a <hi rend="italic">Prosapodosis.</hi>

</p><p>A <hi rend="italic">Prolepsis</hi> or an <hi rend="italic">Hypophora
</hi>propounds

<pb n="121"/>

the objection; as, <hi rend="italic">Isaiah</hi> 37. 23. <hi
rend="italic">Whom hast thou reproached, and blasphemed? And against whom hast
thou exalted thy voice, and lifted up thine eyes on high? even against the holy
one of Israel</hi>.

</p><p>A <hi rend="italic">Prosapodosis</hi> or an <hi
rend="italic">Anthypophora</hi> answers the objection; as, <hi
rend="italic">Rom</hi>. 6. 15. <hi rend="italic">What then? shall we sin
because we are not under the law, but under grace? God forbid</hi>.

</p><p>A <hi rend="italic">Prolepsis</hi> for the most part hath a <hi
rend="italic">Prosopop&oelig;ia</hi> joyned with it, and is therefore either
<hi rend="italic">oblique</hi> or <hi rend="italic">direct</hi>.

</p><p>An <hi rend="italic">Oblique Prolepsis</hi> is that which hath an
imperfect <hi rend="italic">Prosopop&oelig;ia</hi> joyned with it.

</p><p>A <hi rend="italic">Direct Prolepsis</hi> is that which hath a full <hi
rend="italic">Prosopop&oelig;ia</hi>; as, some one may say, <hi
rend="italic">is this then your Discipline? Do you thus instruct youth?</hi>

</p><p>A Figure of <hi rend="italic">Consenting Dialogism</hi> is, when ones
answer doth admit of the objection expressed or understood: yet so, as that from
thence the inconsequence of the objection may be shewed, if need be.

</p><p>But this is either an <hi rend="italic">Epitrope</hi> or a <hi
rend="italic">Synchoresis</hi>.


</p><p>An <hi rend="italic">Epitrope</hi> is when any ones fact is freely
permitted.  This is twofold <hi rend="italic">Serious</hi> or <hi
rend="italic">Ironical</hi>.

</p><p>Serious permission; as, <hi rend="italic">Take this Church</hi>

<pb n="122"/>

<hi rend="italic">plate, seeing thou hast need, for 'twas thy Ancestors
gift</hi>.

</p><p>Ironical permission; as <hi rend="italic">Eccles</hi>. 11. 9. <hi
rend="italic">Rejoyce O young man, and let thy heart chear thee</hi>, &amp;c.
<hi rend="italic">And walk in the ways of thy heart</hi>, &amp;c.

</p><p>A <hi rend="italic">Synchoresis</hi> is when some word or deed is
forgiven; as, <hi rend="italic">let him be sacrilegious, let him be a theef,
let him be the vilest person in the world; for all that he is a good Governour.
James </hi>2. 19.<hi rend="italic"> Thou believest that there is one God, thou
dost well: the Devils also believe and tremble.</hi></p>

</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="9" id="d13">
<head>CHAP. IX.<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Of Secundary Figures</hi>.</head>

<p>To these <hi rend="italic">Primary Figures</hi> of words and sentences there
may some <hi rend="italic">secundary figures</hi> be added in both kinds.

<pb n="123"/>
</p><p>The Secundary figures of a word are eight.

</p><p>1. <hi rend="italic">Ellipsis</hi>.<lb/>
2. <hi rend="italic">Pleonasmus</hi>.<lb/>
3. <hi rend="italic">Asyndeton</hi>.<lb/>
4. <hi rend="italic">Polysyndeton</hi>.<lb/>
5. <hi rend="italic">Hyperbaton</hi>.<lb/>
6. <hi rend="italic">Zeugma</hi>.<lb/>
7. <hi rend="italic">Antithesis</hi>.<lb/>
8. <hi rend="italic">Gr&aelig;cismus</hi>.


</p><p>An <hi rend="italic">Ellipsis</hi> is, when some necessary word, to
express the passion, is omitted in the construction; as, <hi
rend="italic">Isaiah</hi> 1. 13. <hi rend="italic">I cannot iniquity</hi>,
that is, I cannot bear iniquity.

</p><p>A <hi rend="italic">Pleonasmus</hi> is, when there is some word in an
oration, more than it seemeth to need; yet doth emphatically and eminently
express some vehemence and certainty; as, <hi rend="italic">I saw it with these
eyes</hi>.  And that which hath not such an emphasis is idle and vicious.

</p><p>An <hi rend="italic">Asyndeton</hi> is, when in a number of words, a
conjunction copulative is omitted, either through hast, or vehemence of speech;
as, <hi rend="italic">By thy folly and wickedness thou hast lost thy substance,
thy good name, thy friends, thy parents, and offended thy Creator</hi>.

</p><p>A <hi rend="italic">Polysyndeton</hi> is, when for gravity sake, more
conjunctions are used than seem needful, but not without some Emphasis; as, <hi
rend="italic">overmuch sleep also, and wine, and banquets, and queans, and
bathes enervate and enfeeble the body and mind</hi>.

<pb n="124"/>

</p><p>An <hi rend="italic">Hyperbaton</hi> is a <hi
rend="italic">Transposition</hi> of words from the right order of construction,
into some more neat and compact form, for elegancy and variety sake; as, <hi
rend="italic">Ephes</hi>. 1. <hi rend="italic">And you hath he quickened who
were dead in trespasses and sins</hi>.

</p><p>A <hi rend="italic">Zeugma</hi> is, when some verb or adjective but once
expressed in a sentence, is supposed to be referred to several others of divers
genders, numbers or persons, agreeing with that which is nearest; as; <hi
rend="italic">lust overcometh modesty, boldness fear</hi>, and<hi
rend="italic"> passion reason</hi>.

</p><p>This is threefold.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Prozeugma</hi>, when this common word is set in the
beginning; as, <hi rend="italic">For neither art thou he</hi>, Cataline, <hi
rend="italic">whom shame could at any time call back from dishonesty, fear from
perils, or reason from madness</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Mesozeugma</hi>, when in the middle; as, <hi
rend="italic">What a shame is this, that neither hope of reward, nor fear of
reproach could any thing move him, the perswasion of his friends, nor the love
of his Country?</hi>

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Hypozeugma</hi>, when in the end; as, <hi
rend="italic">the foundation of freedome, the fountain of equity, the safeguard
of wealth, and custody of life is preserved by law</hi>.

</p><p>An <hi rend="italic">Antithesis</hi> is, when the things Opposed do
answer one another; as, <hi rend="italic">Flattery procureth</hi>

<pb n="125"/>

<hi rend="italic">friendship, truth hatred</hi>.

</p><p>A <hi rend="italic">Gr&aelig;cimus</hi> is when the proper Idiom of the
Greek is used in another speech or language; as, <hi rend="italic">Edm. Spencer
Chap.</hi> 13<hi rend="italic">. For not to have been dipt in</hi> Lethe<hi
rend="italic"> lake, could save the son of</hi> Thetis<hi rend="italic"> from
to die</hi>; that is, <hi rend="italic">Achilles</hi>.

</p><p>To these may be added

</p><p>An <hi rend="italic">Hyperologia</hi> or an <hi rend="italic">Hyteron
Proteron</hi>, when that which in the natural order should be first spoken, is
brought in last; as, <hi rend="italic">he is in health and alive</hi>, for, he
is alive and in health.

</p><p>An <hi rend="italic">Antiprosis</hi>, when one case is put for another.

</p><p>An <hi rend="italic">Hypallage</hi>, when two words do commute or change
cases with one another; as, <hi rend="italic">Thou hast hid their heart from
understanding, Job</hi> 17. 4. that is, thou hast hid understanding from their
heart.

</p><p>The Secundary figures in a sentence are ten.

</p><p>1. <hi rend="italic">Parrhesia</hi>.<lb/>
2. <hi rend="italic">Erotesis</hi>.<lb/>
3. <hi rend="italic">Parenthesis</hi>.<lb/>
4. <hi rend="italic">Parathesis</hi>.<lb/>
5. <hi rend="italic">Periphrasis</hi>.<lb/>
6. <hi rend="italic">Synonymia</hi>.<lb/>
7. <hi rend="italic">Hypotyposis</hi>.<lb/>
8. <hi rend="italic">Pr&aelig;munitio</hi>.<lb/>
9. <hi rend="italic">Transitio</hi>.<lb/>
10. <hi rend="italic">Rejectio</hi>.


</p><p><hi rend="italic">Parrhesia</hi> is a free and a bold speaking of

<pb n="126"/>

such things in their presence whom we should fear or reverence, as are
displeasing or may provoke them to envy.

</p><p>And this is either when we confidently acknowledge and defend a fault not
proved against us, or when we boldly upbraid and rebuke others, for faults by
them committed.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Erotesis</hi> is a manner of speech, whereby we
either,

</p><p>1. Demand a question; as, <hi rend="italic">How oft shall any brother
sin against me, and I forgive him? till seven times? Matth</hi>. 18. 21. Or when
we

</p><p>2. Earnestly affirm and reprehend; as, <hi rend="italic">O faithless
Generation! how long shall I be with you? how long shall I suffer you? Mark
</hi>9. 19. Or when we

</p><p>3. Vehemently avouch the contrary, whether the interrogation be
affirmative or negative; as, <hi rend="italic">can the blind lead the blind?
shall they not both fall into the ditch?</hi> that is, the blind cannot lead the
blind, they shall both fall.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Parenthesis</hi> is the interposing of one or more
words of perfect sence, within another sentence, for the perfecting thereof;
without which interposition, the sence would yet be perfect and entire.

<pb n="127"/>

</p><p>Concerning which, two rules are observeable, viz.

</p><p>1. That the interposition should neither be long, nor frequent, because
it will render the sentence obscure.

</p><p>2. That one parenthesis be but seldome inserted within another; as, <hi
rend="italic">Are they ministers of Christ (I speak as a fool) I am more</hi>;
2 <hi rend="italic">Cor</hi>. 11. 23.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Parathesis</hi>, is a figure of construction, whereby
one substantive is for declaration and distinction sake added unto another in
the same case; as <hi rend="italic">the river Isis</hi>, or <hi
rend="italic">the river Wye</hi>. Judas <hi rend="italic">saith unto him, not
</hi>Iscariot. <hi rend="italic">John</hi> 14. 22.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Periphrasis</hi>, is the explication of a thing by
more words, which may be expressed by one.

</p><p>This figure is principally made four ways.

</p><p>1. When some notable enterprise, ones native countrey, or some strange
sect or opinion, is put instead of the proper name; as <hi rend="italic">The
writer of the Trojan war</hi> for Homer.

</p><p>2. In <hi rend="italic">Etymology</hi>, when the cause or reason of a
name is unfolded; as, a <hi rend="italic">man studious of wisdom</hi>, for a
Philosopher.

</p><p>3. In <hi rend="italic">Annotation</hi>, when by certain marks or tokens
something is described; as <hi rend="italic">Anger is a vehement heat of the
mind, which brings</hi>

<pb n="127"/>

<hi rend="italic">paleness to the countenance, burning to the eyes, and
trembling to the parts of the body</hi>.

</p><p>4. When a thing is described by definition; as, <hi rend="italic">the
art of speaking eloquently</hi>, for Rhetorick. <hi rend="italic">An oppressor
of the laws and liberties of the people</hi>, for a Tyrant.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Synonymia</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Palilogia</hi>,
is a heaping together of many words of one signifcation; as, <hi
rend="italic">Wisdome in a Poor man lyes as a thing despised, rejected,
oppressed, buried and utterly extinct</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Hypotyposis</hi> is a figure by which a whole matter
is particularly and orderly expressed, as that it seems to be represented unto
ocular inspection, as, <hi rend="italic">It is a place which now humbling it
self in fallowed plains, now proud in well husbanded hills, marries barren woods
to cultivated valleys, and joyns neat gardens to delicious fountains</hi>,
&amp;c.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Pr&aelig;munition</hi> or preparation is, when we
presuppose what may be said by way of defence for those, whom we intend to
reprehend or reprove.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Transition</hi> is that by which the parts of an
oration are joyned together. And this is

</p><p>1. <hi rend="italic">Perfect</hi>, by which is declared what hath been
spoken, and what remaineth to be said; as, <hi rend="italic">hitherto we have
spoken of tillage and Astronomy, now we will treat of </hi>&amp;c.

<pb n="129"/>

</p><p>2. <hi rend="italic">Imperfect</hi>, by which is declared either what
hath been said, or what remaineth to be spoken.

</p><p>This may be done eight several ways.

</p><p>1. By something that is equal or parallel; as, <hi rend="italic">Those
are most pleasant, nor are these less delightful</hi>.

</p><p>2. By something that is unequal; <hi rend="italic">you have heard very
sad things; but I shall now tell you sadder things than these</hi>.

</p><p>3. By something that is like.

</p><p>4. By something that is contrary; <hi rend="italic">These things he did
when he was young; hear now his vertuous progress in his elder days</hi>.

</p><p>5. By something that is divers; as, <hi rend="italic">you have heard of
his behaviour, I will now inform you of his learning</hi>.

</p><p>6. By preoccupation; as, <hi rend="italic">We will now hasten to the
rest, only give me leave to adde this one thing</hi>.

</p><p>7. By reprehension; <hi rend="italic">Why should I dwell on this
subject; I hasten to that which is the cause of all</hi>.

</p><p>8. From some consequent or relative; as, <hi rend="italic">you have
heard what I have done for him; hear now how he hath requited me</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Rejection</hi> is, when we deferre a thing to some
other time or place or wholly reject it as absurd and impertinent, and by no

<pb n="130"/>
means to be admitted of; as, <hi rend="italic">But of</hi> Lucuius<hi
rend="italic"> I will speak in some other place: and I will speak so, as that
my speech shall not falsely accuse him, or yet derogate from his just
praise</hi>.

</p><p>And thus much concerning <hi rend="italic">Elocution</hi>.  As for <hi
rend="italic">Memory</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Pronunciation</hi>, which are
the other two parts of Rhetorick, <hi rend="italic">i</hi> purposely omit them,
as being natural endowments, which may be better improved by constant practice,
than by any precepts which can be given.</p>

<trailer>Laus Deo.</trailer>
</div1>




</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

