<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="NurDep1"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;

]>
<TEI.2 id="NurDep1">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Rebecca Nurse Collection:
Ann Putnam, Sr. Vs. Martha Cory &amp; Rebecca Nurse</title>
<title type="sort">rebecca nurse collection ann putnam, sr vs martha cory &amp; rebecca nurse</title>
<author>Nurse, Rebecca</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Carolyn Fay, Electronic Text Center</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">6</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">NurDep1</idno>
<date value="1998">1998</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1998 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476590</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This document is part of a collection of documents pertaining to the Rebecca Nurse witchcraft trial of 1692 in Salem Village, Massachusetts, collected and edited by Richard B. Trask in "The Devil hath been raised." This electronic collection is a pilot project that is part of a larger digital enterprise which will collect together all of the documents pertaining to the Salem witchcraft trials. This enterprise is a project undertaken by the Electronic Text Center. Benjamin C. Ray, professor of Religious Studies, is the project supervisor.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Rebecca Nurse Collection:
Ann Putnam, Sr. Vs. Martha Cory &amp; Rebecca Nurse</title>
<title level="m">"The Devil hath been raised:" A Documentary History of the Salem Village Witchcraft Outbreak of March 1692</title>
<title type="sort">rebecca nurse collection ann putnam, sr vs martha cory &amp; rebecca nurse</title>
<author>Rebecca Nurse</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
<name>Richard B. Trask</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>Revised Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>p. 33</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Yeoman Press</publisher>
<pubPlace>Danvers, Mass.</pubPlace>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: personal copy</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1692-03-18">1692-03-18</date>;
<date value="1692-03-19">1692-03-19</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>feminine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1998-07">July 1998</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Carolyn Fay, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="statement" n="1692-05-31" id="d3">
<head>

	<hi rend="bold">FRIDAY.&amp; SATURDAY, MARCH 18 &amp; 19, 1692<lb/>
	Ann Putnam, Sr. Vs. Martha Cory &amp; Rebecca Nurse</hi>
</head>

<p>

<hi rend="italic">This is the first part of a deposition written in the handwriting of
Thomas Putnam concerning his wife, Ann, the mother of Ann Putnam, Jr. In
her testimony Mrs. Putnam tells of being afflicted not only by the
spectre of Goody Cory, but also by a new spectral tormentor, Rebecca
Nurse. Nurse was a Salem Village inhabitant and wife of Francis Nurse.
She was also a covenant member of the Salem Church.  This deposition was
sworn to on <date value="1692-05-31">May 31, 1692.</date></hi>

</p><p> The Deposition of Ann. putnam the wife of Thomas putnam agged
about 30 years who testifieth and saith that on the <date value="1692-03-18">18th march
1691&sol;92</date> 1 being wearied
out in helping to tend my poor afflected Child and Maid: about the middle
of the affiernoon I layd me down on the bed to take a little Rest and Immedi-atly I was allmost prest and Choaked to death: that had it not been for the
mircy of a gratious God and the help of those that ware with me: I could
not have lived many moments: and presently I saw the Apperishtion of Mar-tha Cory who did torter me so as I cannot Express Redy to tare me all to
peaces: and yn departed from me alitle while: but before I could recover
strenth or well take breath the Apperishtion of Martha Cory fell upon me
again with dreadfull tortors and hellish temtations to goe along with hir and
she also brought to me a little Red book in hir hand and a black pen urging
me vehemently to writ in hir book: and severall times that day she did most
greviously tortor me allmost redy to kill me and on the 19 th march: Martha
Cory againe appeared to me and also Rebekah nurs the wife of frances nurs
sen r:and they both did tortor: me agrate many times this day with such tor-tors as no toungu can express because I would not yeald to their Hellish tem-tations that had I not been upheild by an Allmighty Arme I could not have
lived while night ye 20 th march being sabboth day I had agrat deal of Respitt.
between my fitts:
</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

