<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="PeaSheh"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
<TEI.2 id="PeaSheh"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Shehens` Houn` Dogs</title>
<title type="sort">shehens houn dogs</title>
<author>Peattie, Elia Wilkinson, 1862-1935</author>
<respStmt> 
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">42</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">PeaSheh</idno> 
<date value="1999">1999</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1999 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:477251</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Shehens` Houn` Dogs</title>
<title level="j">Reader</title>
<title type="sort">shehens houn dogs</title>
<author>Elia Wilkinson Peattie</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Bobbs-Merrill Company</publisher> 
<pubPlace>Indianapolis</pubPlace> 
<date value="1907">1905-1908</date> 
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  UVa Library, S-687</idno>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This story appeared in v. 10 (June 1907), p. 73-84.</p>
</note> 
<note>
<p>On page 81, line 9, Judy Boss omitted the word "Bill" from the end of the line.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1907">1907</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term> 
<term>prose</term> 
<term>feminine</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1999-04">April 1999</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>June Griffin, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
<head> 
 
<hi rend="bold">Shehens' Houn' Dogs</hi><lb/> 
 
BY ELIA W. PEATTIE<lb/> 
 
Author of "The Shape of Fear," "The Door," etc. 
</head> 

<p> 
EDWARD Berenson, the Washington correspondent for the New 
York <hi rend="italic">News</hi>, descended from the sleeping-car at Hardin, 
Kentucky, and inquired for the stage to Ballington's Gap.  But there 
was, it appeared, no stage.  Neither was a conveyance to be hired.  
The community looked at Berenson and went by on the other side.  
He had, indeed, as he recollected, with a too confiding candor, 
registered himself from Washington, and there were reasons in 
plenty why strangers should not be taken over to Ballington's Gap 
promiscuously, so to speak, by the neighbors at Hardin.  Berenson 
had come down from Washington with a purpose, however, and he 
was not to be frustrated.  He wished to inquire    &mdash;    politely    &mdash;    why, for 
four generations, the Shehens and the Babbs had been killing each 
other.  He meant to put the question calmly and in the interest of 
scientific journalism, but he was quite determined to have it 
answered.  To this end he bought a lank mare for seventy-five 
dollars    &mdash;    "an th' fixin's thrown in, sah"    &mdash;    and set out upon a red 
road, bound for the Arcadian distance. 
</p><p>The mountains did not look like the 
 
<pb n="74"/> 
 
retreat of revengeful clans.  They wore, on the contrary, a 
benevolent aspect.  All that was visible was beautiful; and what lay 
beyond appeared enchanted.  The hill-sides flowered with laurel and 
azalea; the winds met on the heights like elate spirits, united after a 
too long separation; the sky was so near and so kind that it seemed 
after all as if the translation of the weary body into something 
immortal and impregnable to pain were not so mad a dream.  
Pleasant streams whispered through the pine woods, and the thrush 
sang from solitary places. 
</p><p>Berenson had ridden far, and the soft twilight was coming upon 
him, when he met the first human being since leaving Hardin.  It 
was a slight, sallow, graceful mountaineer with a long rifle flung in 
the easy hollow of his arm.  He emerged suddenly upon Berenson    &mdash;    
so suddenly as to disturb the none too sensitive nerves of the mare, 
who shied incautiously over the edge of the roadway.  The two 
saluted, and Berenson pulled in his nag. 
</p><p>"How far am I from Ballington's Gap, sir?" 
</p><p>"'Bout two mile, sah, if you don't go wrong at th' fawk.  Bin to 
Hardin?" 
</p><p>"Yes    &mdash;    I left the train there." 
</p><p>"Did the folks there send yo' on heah?" 
</p><p>"Well, they let me come," said Berenson with swift divination. 
</p><p>"That theah ole Pap Waddell's hoss yo' all ridin'?" 
</p><p>"Why, I believe it is    &mdash;    or was.  It's mine now." 
</p><p>"How much    &mdash;    if it's fair askin'?" 
</p><p>"Seventy-five dollars and the saddle thrown in." 
</p><p>A slow smile illuminated the sallow face    &mdash;    the sort of a smile 
that dawns when one perceives a joke.  The mountaineer drew a 
long dark plug of tobacco from his pocket. 
</p><p>"D'ye chaw?" he inquired with pensive sweetness. 
</p><p>"I smoke," said Berenson, and offered his pocket case of 
Havanas.  The two lighted up, and the man walked beside the mare 
as they proceeded. 
</p><p>"We-all bin havin' a good deal of disturbance raound heah, 
lately," volunteered the mountaineer. 
</p><p>"Yes, so I hear." 
</p><p>"What with the Shehens defendin' theah h'athstones, an th' 
Babbses raisin' hell, 'twas bad enough    &mdash;    trouble an' to spa-h.  An' 
now th' revinooers    &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"I didn't know they'd been giving you trouble lately." 
</p><p>Berenson did not feel that he ran any risk in identifying his 
companion with the "blockaders."  Loyal mountain sentiment, as he 
knew, was with the keepers of the stills. 
</p><p>"Yaas, they've bin amongst us ag'in.  As I was sayin', all this 
makes us more inquirin' than polite, sah, an' it's my place to find out 
the business of them that comes to the gap.  As we ah gittin' mighty 
neah thah this minute, I've got to come to th' p'int."  He smiled at 
Berenson ingratiatingly. 
</p><p>"Well," said Berenson, slipping from his horse and taking his 
place beside his inquisitor, "you shall have a full and complete 
answer.  I'm a newspaper man, and I've come down here to inquire 
into the meaning of this feud    &mdash;    this Shehen-Babb difficulty that has 
been going on down here for the past twenty-five years    &mdash;    or is it 
longer?" 
</p><p>"I don't know jes' the numbah of yeahs, but it's in the fourth 
generation, sah.  But I don't see why it should consahn outsidahs, 
sah." 
</p><p>Berenson looked at him with genuine interest.  He had a dignity 
and a grace that were almost distinguished.  He bore himself with 
nonchalance    &mdash;    something as might any clansman, certain of the 
rights of his position, and firm in his ability to protect his own.  He 
was young    &mdash;    not more than twenty-two.  His tan-colored jeans hung 
easily upon his lithe and muscular body.  His eyes had a kindly 
expression at moments, but in re- 
 
<pb n="75"/> 
 
pose were marked by a certain mournfulness. 
</p><p>"Well," said Berenson, "the newspapers have fallen into the way 
of thinking that everything is their business.  They are probably 
wrong, but as long as I work for them    &mdash;    and I don't know enough to 
make my living any other way    &mdash;    I shall act according to their 
policy.  Now, up North, we have become greatly interested in your 
feud.  We have quarrels of our own up there, but they are not 
inherited quarrels.  We don't carry on a fight from the grave to the 
cradle, and the cradle to the grave.  We don't keep on fighting after 
we've forgotten what the row is about, and we want to know why 
you do.  It strikes us that you have the habits of the old Highlanders, 
and that these vendettas of yours resemble the old wars of the clans 
   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"Waal," interrupted the other, with a philosophical intonation.  
"We all are Scotch or Irish, mostly." 
</p><p>"That's so!" cried Berenson.  "Of course you are!  Anyway, I've 
come down here to get an impartial account of the whole matter, 
and I want to meet any man    &mdash;    as many men as I can    &mdash;    who will 
give me the rights of it." 
</p><p>The mountaineer motioned Berenson to stop.  He turned to the 
side of the road, unslung a horn cup from his shoulder, and, 
stooping, brought it up filled with glistening spring water.  He held 
it out to Berenson with a charming gesture of hospitality.  Berenson 
bowed and accepted it. 
</p><p>"It's good watah," said the other.  "I'm fond of watah myself."  
He spoke as if his taste were rather exotic. 
</p><p>"Waal, I'm powahful glad, Mr.    &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"Berenson    &mdash;    Edward Berenson." 
</p><p>"   &mdash;    Berenson, that yo' bin so squah in tellin' me of yo' business.  
We don't have many visitahs from ovah yon.  'Bout th' only ones 
that come heah ah th' revinooers, an' I needn't say, sah, to a man like 
yo', that they ah not pahticularly welcome.  'Bout fo' yeahs ago a 
fellow from Mr. Wattehson's papah did come t' these pahts when 
they was some shootin', an' he took sides with th' Babbs."  (A 
pause.)  "He nevah went back."  They stopped on a level bit of road 
to breathe themselves, and Berenson received and returned the 
whimsical smile of his companion.  "But what I like about you," 
went on the mountaineer, "is that yo' said yo' was goin' to be 
impahshal.  I'm an impahshal man myself, and I think we should all 
be impahshal.  Th' trouble with outsiders is that they ah not 
impahshal." 
</p><p>"Well, it's a fine thing <hi rend="italic">to</hi> be," assented Berenson.  "You 
make judges out of stuff like that.  Any judges in your family?" 
</p><p>"One, sah." 
</p><p>"Still living?" 
</p><p>"No, sah.  Passed away las' yeah." 
</p><p>"What was his name?" 
</p><p>"Loren Shehen, sah." 
</p><p>Berenson's heart performed an acrobatic feat. 
</p><p>"Are you a Shehen, sir?" 
</p><p>"I have that honah, sah.  I'm th' last." 
</p><p>"You don't, I'm sure, mean that you are the last survivor?" 
</p><p>"No, sah, I do not.  I mean I'm the youngest bohn.  Theah's a 
numbah of us yet on Tulula mountain, sah.  Theah's my fathah, an' 
my two eldah brothahs, an my Uncle Dudley and one son of his, an' 
my second cousin Edgah    &mdash;    an' theah ah othahs, kinfolk, but not 
close related.  The Judge was with us last yeah, but he was killed, 
by a hull pahcel of Babbs    &mdash;    a hull yelpin' pack of 'em." 
</p><p>"You've lived here all your life, Mr. Shehen?" 
</p><p>The mountaineer's eyes twinkled. 
</p><p>"Waal, not yit, Mr. Berenson, but I expect to, sah." 
</p><p>Berenson smiled. 
</p><p>"I should think, however, that in spite of the impartial disposition 
which you say is native to you, Mr. Shehen, that you would have 
difficulty in dealing with the matter of the feud without some heat." 
 
 
<pb n="76"/> 
 
</p><p>"No heat at all, sah!  You don't git heated when yo' speak of 
rattlesnakes, do yeh?  They ah jest snakes!  You kill 'em when yo' 
kin.  Well, Babbs ah th' same.  They ah the meanest set of snakes 
that crawl on theah bellies.  That's an impahshal opinion, sah.  Yo' 
kin ask th' next man we meet." 
</p><p>Berenson gave up all effort to keep a sober face.  He grinned, 
then guffawed.  He made the rocks ring with his laughter.  The 
mountaineer regarded him indulgently. 
</p><p>"It's a true wohd," he said quietly. 
</p><p>"I haven't had your full name yet," said Berenson, when he got 
breath again. 
</p><p>"Bill Shehen, sah    &mdash;    young Bill." 
</p><p>"Well, I'm glad I met you, Mr. Shehen!  I want to hear your side 
of the story from beginning to end.  Now where can I put up?  I 
want to stay here for some time.  It's not alone on account of my 
paper.  I need the rest.  I'm tired.  I want to talk with all the Shehens 
I can, and all the Babbs I can." 
</p><p>"Now that's whah yo' make yo' mistake, sah.  Yo' cain't talk with 
both Shehens <hi rend="italic">an'</hi> Babbs.  If yo' go on to th' Gap with me, 
and bunk at my place to-night    &mdash;    an' yo' ah welcome, sah    &mdash;    yo've got 
to 'bide with us.  Yo' will be counted a Shehen sympathizah.  I don't 
suppose any one from th' outside kin ondehstand, sah.  I don't 
expect 'em to do so.  I thought about it a plenty.  It's jest this: bein' 
bohn a Shehen, yo' nuss hate fo' th' Babbs with yo' mothah's milk; 
bein' bohn a Babb, yo' git silly mad evah time yo' see a Shehen.  
Bein' of one kind, yo' cain't pass the othah kind on th' road; yo' cain't 
heah of anything they do without a cold feelin' in yo' stomach.  
When yo' git to fightin' 'em, yo' feel like shoutin' like the niggahs at 
praise meetin'.  I thought it ovah, sah, an' I've about come to the 
conclusion that it's a disease.  Folks call it a feud.  Well, I call it a 
disease    &mdash;    the Shehen-Babb disease." 
</p><p>Berenson put a hand on the man's shoulder. 
</p><p>"Well, then, William Shehen, if you've found that out, why don't 
you cure yourself?  If it's a disease, it's a fatal one!  It brings your 
men to untimely death, and your women to sorrow.  Don't set your 
sons    &mdash;    when you get them    &mdash;    in the way of inheriting the same 
fearful malady.  Get out and get away from it all.  Do something 
besides destroy and make bad whisky.  For you do make whisky, I 
suppose." 
</p><p>"Yaas," said the other gently, "but it ain't so damned bad."  His 
voice had soughing intonations, like the wind in the pines. 
</p><p>"I'll wager you've got a bottle of it in your pocket now," said 
Berenson. 
</p><p>"Waal!" the wind was never softer on a summer night. 
</p><p>"Well, I've a bottle of the ordinary whisky of commerce.  I'll bet 
mine is the smoother, the nuttier, and altogether the pleasanter." 
</p><p>Three buzzards sitting on the dead branch of a Norway pine 
received a shock from which they did not recover for several days.  
They had seen walking along the road two quiet men, one sad mare, 
and a long thin dog with a lame foot.  They suddenly beheld a swift 
change    &mdash;    a <hi rend="italic">tableau vivant</hi>.  One man stood at the point of 
the other man's rifle.  The mare had jerked away and was backing, 
with frightened eyes, toward the verge of the steep mountain side.  
The dog had crouched down as if to get out of the way of trouble. 
</p><p>"I believe yo' all ah a damned revinooer aftah all!" said Shehen.  
He did not raise his voice, but he spoke between closed teeth.  His 
blue gray eyes had become like points of steel.  Berenson, equally 
tall, in his dark, city clothes, his inappropriate derby above his long, 
office-bleached face, looked Shehen squarely in the eye. 
</p><p>"I'm not," he said.  "I'm just what I told you I was.  I haven't a 
firearm on me.  If you shoot, you kill an unarmed man.  Besides, 
you will have made a mis- 
<pb n="77"/> 
 
take.  The only trouble is, that while I like your jokes, you don't like 
mine.  Up North, when we don't like a man's jokes, we tell him he's 
an ass; we don't kill him." 
</p><p>The buzzards saw the tableau remain, for an appreciable 
moment, undisturbed.  Then the mountaineer lowered his rifle and 
flung it back upon his arm.  He looked shamefaced.  Something like 
tears came into his embarrassed eyes.  Berenson regarded him 
coldly.  The other, meeting the expression, flushed scarlet.  Then he 
shook his fist before Berenson's eyes. 
</p><p>"That's it," he cried.  "That's what I say!  The life heah makes    &mdash;    
fools of us!  We ah afeahd of shadows!  We have nothin' to show fo' 
ouah lives!  We live to kill    &mdash;    that's it    &mdash;    we live to kill.  What has my 
family done fo' the community?  What <hi rend="italic">is</hi> the community?  
It's a beautiful country, but what do we do with it?  We live like 
wolves, sah    &mdash;    like wolves.  Ain't that how we seem to yo' all?" 
</p><p>He was suddenly no more than a boy.  His height seemed, 
indeed, to have belied him.  He looked his passionate inquiry at 
Berenson, who warmed again into liking. 
</p><p>"Why don't you get out of it all?" demanded Berenson.  "Cut it!  
Quit it!  Vamoose!  Come where they're doing something    &mdash;    where 
they're talking about something worth while.  Why, you're an 
intelligent fellow.  You've courage.  You've had some education, 
too, haven't you?" 
</p><p>"Dad sent me to Hahdin to the Industrial school; an' I've some 
books.  I take pleasuah in readin', sah." 
</p><p>"I knew it!  Well, get out of this place and make a man of 
yourself." 
</p><p>Shehen said nothing.  To the acute disappointment of the 
buzzards, the horse was recaptured, the dog recovered, and the two 
men went on side by side. 
</p><p>The buzzards spread their wings, stretched their necks with a 
disgusted gesture, and flew away.  Silence fell upon the travelers.  
They were coming to a hamlet.  Back from the road, bowered in 
roses, was a tumble-down house.  It was built of logs, and divided in 
the center by an open chamber.  Three wolf-like dogs ran out to 
greet Shehen.  The mountaineer stopped to welcome them, rubbing 
his hands over their backs, scratching them behind the ears, and 
finally lifting one of them up in his arms. 
</p>

<p>"They seem to be very quiet hounds," said Berenson.  "How did 
you teach them to be so well behaved?" 
</p><p>Berenson's companion regarded him with amusement. 
</p><p>"Thah's reasons, sah, why the Shehens' houn-dogs <hi rend="italic">hes</hi> to 
be quiet.  We nevah did publish ouah place of residence!  But thah's 
times when they cain't be kep' still, an' that's when one of the clan 
has bad luck comin' to him.  They ah well trained, sah, but they do 
have theah times of howlin'!" 
</p><p>"And about that time," suggested 
 
 
<pb n="78"/> 
 
Berenson, "you want to get your rabbit-foot out." 
</p><p>Bill Shehen nodded. 
</p><p>"If you've got one handy," he agreed.  "Fathah an' th' boys have 
been in a little trouble this week.  They ah all away.  Come in and 
spend th' night, sah.  I want to talk to yo'." 
</p><p>It was said with the conviction that a refusal was impossible.  
And, indeed, Berenson considered it so.  They put up the horse, and 
went into the great living room, which ran across one entire side of 
the house    &mdash;    three bedrooms occupying the other side.  Shehen 
pointed to a crayon picture on the wall    &mdash;    the only picture in the 
room. 
</p><p>"That's my mothah," he said with a sweet and frank reverence.  
"She died last yeah."  The portrait was a poor one, but it could not 
conceal the look of fatality in the dead woman's eyes.  It was the 
same look that Berenson had noticed in the eyes of her son.  A wave 
of compassion for both of them swept over him.  He was left alone 
for a moment, and he stood before the crayon, seeing yet not seeing 
it. 
</p><p>They ate together, and then sat out beneath the hoary hemlocks, 
and watched the moon rise, scarlet, over the mountain's brow.  
Berenson felt at ease    &mdash;    at ease with the night, and the place, and the 
man.  The whip-poor-will iterated his foolish call from below them, 
and almost above their heads the hoot owl cried. 
</p><p>"I can't say but that I'd be willing to get along without those two 
birds," said Berenson. 
</p><p>"They ah very insistin'," agreed Shehen.  "Of co'se I know how to 
make that hoot owl shet up, but the whip-pooah-will is one too 
many for me." 
</p><p>"And how can you make the hoot owl hush?  By killing it?" 
</p><p>Shehen grinned. 
</p><p>"Thah's ways of doin' things up here that you all woulden' take 
stock in," he ventured. 
</p><p>"Well, I don't know about that.  What do you suggest?" 
</p><p>"Yo'all take off youah slippah, sah, an' change the right slippah 
to the lef' foot an' see what happens." 
</p><p>The industrious owl was in full cry as Berenson bent to obey this 
extraordinary request.  But her mournful gurgle died in her throat. 
</p><p>"She'll shet up now," murmured Shehen, lazily lighting his pipe.  
And so she did.  Not another sound issued from her depressing 
throat.  Berenson made the echoes ring with laughter. 
</p><p>"You don't believe such stuff, man?" 
</p><p>"No-o," pensively murmured the mountaineer.  "We don't none 
of us believe in it!  It jes' happens that a-way, that's all.  An' I may 
say, jes' fo' yo' info'mation, thet if yo' haven't on slippahs and it's 
inconvenient to change youah boots, heatin' a pokah red hot will do 
jes' as well." 
</p><p>"Thanks," said Berenson, and told of some family superstitions 
of his own. 
</p><p>But they talked of wiser things, too.  Shehen liked books, as he 
said, and he showed Berenson a catalogue of the year's publications, 
with the volumes he had purchased or proposed to buy, marked off.  
He turned to serious matters; was fascinated with popular science, 
and expressed a wish to have a "star-glass" of his own.  He knew the 
names of the constellations, it appeared, and he called his 
companion's attention to the color of the different stars. 
</p><p>"I may be wrong," the Washington man said to the mountaineer 
that night, "but I think you are wasting yourself here.  You ought to 
have more appreciation of yourself.  The only way you can take 
your own measure is by standing up alongside other men.  You're 
made for happiness and society and some nice girl's love, and good 
books and a home of your own.  I can't think why you've not seen 
all this for yourself." 
</p><p>The mountaineer reached a hand down to stroke one of the dogs. 
 
 
<pb n="79"/> 
 
</p><p>"I reckon I've seen it," he said.  "But my ole dad is one to have 
his way.  They call him the Ten-Tined Buck of Tulula mountain.  It 
never was much good runnin' counter to him." 
</p><p>"Will you come up to Washington with me if I get his consent?  
I'll stay here and get acquainted with him, and I'll locate you up 
there in some way.  I tell you, when the chance really offers he'll 
want you to avail yourself of it.  You'll see!" 
</p><p>The sound of the "branch" dripping over the rocks came to their 
ears.  The hermit thrush cast the soft pearls of his melody upon the 
air.  With infinite rustlings, the night settled about them, beneficent 
as a prayer. 
</p><p>"I mout try it up there," mused the mountaineer.  "But I was 
always a home-keepin' fellow." 
</p><p>Berenson went to bed perplexed.  The boy was as innocent and 
wistful as a girl, outlaw though he confessed himself.  Having    &mdash;    
inadvertently    &mdash;    finished too quickly and too disastrously his own 
individual interest in life, Berenson had fallen into a way of 
deriving vicarious zest by interfering in the lives of others.  And, the 
case of young Bill Shehen seemed to offer a rare opportunity for his 
benevolent vice. 
 
</p><p>Three weeks later Berenson went back to Washington.  The 
period of his investigation had not been without adventure    &mdash;    even 
danger.  He had made enemies and friends; he had felt partizanship.  
He had absorbed something of the point of view of these courteous, 
murderous, soft-voiced, battle-loving, mountain-whelped, clannish, 
affectionate, sentimental, law-defying men.  He liked them    &mdash;    liked 
their inconsistencies, their excesses, their barbarism, their 
hospitality, their piety, and their heathenism.  And he carried to 
Washington with him, as friend and companion, one William 
Shehen, junior, son of Tulula's "Ten-Tined Buck." 
</p><p>If Shehen was shy, he was also sociable.  He had a way with 
mountains    &mdash;    understood them and answered them    &mdash;    but he had a 
way with men, too.  He was always graceful, and he looked well in 
the soft gray suit which he got at Berenson's advice, and in the 
drooping gray felt hat.  He carried himself with nonchalance, took 
long, swinging strides, looked men almost too insistently in the eye, 
and was rather elaborate in his courtesy.  He had, as a part of his 
indestructible possession, a knowledge of how educated men talked.  
He had read, and he had remembered.  Away from his native 
environment, he employed something of this knowledge, which 
came within his literary, but not his actual, experience.  The soft 
tricks of his earth-born, forest-nurtured speech clung to him, but in 
Washington these were not marked as amazing.  His 
<hi rend="italic">na&iuml;vet&eacute;</hi> and his gentleness won him friends. 
</p><p>Berenson soon found an office position for him, and he filled it 
with faithfulness, though his patron never dropped in to see him that 
he was not distressed at the curious wistfulness in the boy's eyes.  
He who had known only his own will now submitted, from eight in 
the morning till half after five in the evening, to the will of others.  
His days were given up to minuti&aelig;, every last particle of 
which was laid out for him.  He had hitherto acted solely on his own 
initiative, or had followed the rough autocracy of old Bill, his 
father, the leader of his herd    &mdash;    the ten-tined buck of Tulula 
Mountain.  He was captive now    &mdash;    this wild creature, whose caprices 
had been his guide.  Berenson pitied him, yet expected ultimate 
happiness for him.  Civilization might be rather a stupid escape 
from barbarism, but after all, when a barbarian got to yearning for 
civilization, as Shehen had, it seemed best to give it to him. 
</p><p>Shehen went to the Presbyterian church, and he sang so well that 
the choirmaster requested him to join his 
 
 
<pb n="80"/> 
 
baritones, which the young mountaineer did, with unfeigned 
pleasure.  He sang with the open and flexible throat, knew his notes, 
and was as teachable as an intelligent child.  He boarded with a 
widow who had two daughters, one other boarder and a flower 
garden.  Bill used to work in the garden with the young daughter 
mornings before he went to the office.  Her name was Summer 
MacDonald.  She had had, far back, much the same ancestry as he.  
Something atavistic stirred in the two of them and gave them 
sympathies which could not be expressed.  Besides, they were both 
young, they were training roses and weeding mignonette together, 
and at night they sometimes took a walk in the moonlight.  They 
sang together, too, Summer selecting the songs, which were 
<hi rend="italic">adagio</hi> and <hi rend="italic">andantino</hi>, a trifle sad, and relating to 
love or religion.  She had been going to the Congregational church, 
but she changed now, and went off every Sunday morning with 
Shehen, and after a while she got admitted to the choir, too, though 
her voice was not strong. 
</p><p>Bill liked it, however, the way it was.  It flowed along like a 
pretty "branch" over the mica-starred soil of his mountains.  Her 
face was pale and delicate, and she wore white frocks, and a wide 
white hat with drooping blue plumes on it.  Even in the morning, 
about her work, she dressed in white, with fetching pink or blue 
gingham aprons, cut like a child's pinafore, covering them for 
neatness.  With her light braids down her back, she looked like a 
child.  She and Shehen were as happy as they could be.  They used, 
sometimes, when they were walking together in the garden, to catch 
hold of hands and swing back and forth, out of sheer lightness of 
heart, and just as little children do.  Bill never kissed her, but 
sometimes, when he was sleeping and the summer wind, perfumed 
from her garden, blew in upon him, he dreamt that she had kissed 
him.  The caress was as light as thistle down; it had the breath of 
violets, and it made him blush with happiness. 
</p><p>Berenson used to take Shehen around the Capitol, and to the 
Congressional Library and the Supreme Court Hall.  He talked to 
him, casually, of government, of ideals of law, of the responsibility 
of a nation.  He wished to make him comprehend what a nation 
meant, and to make clear that individualism need not include 
anarchy.  He gave him a very good notion of how anarchy worked 
in cities, and he was not surprised to find Bill condemning it utterly.  
He loathed city crime, too, which seemed to offend him as being 
squalid and treacherous.  Poverty touched him deeply.  He could 
save nothing.  He was always helping some one worse situated than 
himself.  Berenson used to wonder if he was coming to have any 
notion of why the moon-shiners were offenders against the good 
order of the government; but though Bill's impulses were all on the 
side of generosity and compassion, he still seemed to lack some 
comprehension of the real meaning of law.  Berenson could never 
cure him of the habit of going armed.  He would, at any time, have 
been willing to dispense with his uncomfortable collar, or his tie, 
but his toilet was never complete without his modest Smith and 
Wesson.  The fact that he was, in wearing it, breaking a legal 
regulation concerned him not at all.  It was a point of honor for a 
Shehen to go armed.  That finished it. 
</p><p>"You'll be getting a promotion some of these days, my boy," 
Berenson said to him.  "And then I suppose you and Miss Summer 
will be setting up for yourselves and making your own flower 
garden." 
</p><p>Bill settled a spray of heliotrope in his buttonhole.  Miss 
Summer had given it to him from her garden. 
</p><p>"I don't know," he said slowly.  "If she knew about Ballington's 
Gap and the still on Tulula Mountain, and all the 
 
 
<pb n="81"/> 
 
Babbs we all had killed, perhaps she wouldn't." 
</p><p>"Tell her the story and see what she says," urged Berenson. 
</p><p>"Yaas," smiled Bill, "eat the mushroom and see if you die!" 
</p><p>As time went on it seemed, however, as if the mountaineer 
would be likely to eat the mushroom.  Berenson used to meet Bill 
and Miss Summer together, dreamful, on summer nights, and he noticed what seraphic intonation could be 
given the simple word "we." 
</p>
 
 
<p>"Have you told her yet?" he ventured to ask one day. 
</p><p>"I out with the whole yahn," Bill confessed. 
</p><p>"And what was the effect of it?" 
</p><p>"Waal, it was as if she didn't quite follow me.  I reckon she 
thought I was layin' it on.  She said young men liked to play the 
Othello game    &mdash;    that they wanted to be loved for the dangers they 
had passed." 
</p><p>"Miss Summer is a student of Shakespeare, then?" 
</p><p>"We've been readin' it togethah," murmured Bill happily. 
</p><p>Berenson could not help priding himself on his man.  He felt that 
fine sense of partnership with the Creator which parents have when 
they regard a beautiful and virtuous child.  Shehen the civilized, the 
pacific, the bookish, the lover, the citizen, the law-abider, was in 
part his product.  Berenson talked of him at the newspaper office 
and at the club.  People asked to meet him, and Berenson liked 
nothing better than a Sunday afternoon in Bill's company.  
Berenson's friends regarded his <hi rend="italic">prot&eacute;g&eacute;</hi> with 
mingled amusement and affection, and the mountaineer found 
himself with a circle of surprisingly distinguished acquaintances. 
</p><p>Shehen finally brought word that he had rented a little cottage    &mdash;    
a four-roomed affair with a garden plot.  He had a charming view, 
and, with plenty of seeds and saplings from the Agricultural 
Department, he didn't see why he couldn't be perfectly happy.  All 
he and Miss Summer wished, apparently, was to be together, to 
have a roof in case of storm or nightfall    &mdash;    and both seemed more or 
less unlikely in their atmosphere of high noon and sun    &mdash;    and to 
have a patch of earth to grow perfumed things in.  Berenson was 
delighted.  He had not enjoyed life so much for a long time.  Having 
been under the necessity of setting aside the more idyllic 
department of life, he now regaled himself with his creature's 
happiness.  He had begun to visit the furniture stores with the view 
to a comprehensive wedding present, and he had set the day when 
he was to go with the prospective bride to make the selections. 
</p><p>Berenson had his own ideas about how a bride's little drawing-room ought to be furnished.  He had, indeed, treasured these ideas 
for many years.  Now, for the first time, he had an opportunity for 
putting them into execution. 
 
<pb n="82"/> 
 
</p><p>The evening before the day appointed for this agreeable task, 
Berenson and Bill had dinner together. 
</p><p>"I may be wrong," said the newspaper man, "and I hope I am, my 
boy, but it strikes me that you're not looking quite so enthusiastic as 
you should be.  Haven't you been sleeping well?  You look like a 
man who's been losing sleep." 
</p><p>"I sleep well enough, but    &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"Yes.  Well    &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"But three nights runnin' I've had the oddes' dream!" 
</p><p>"Not a disagreeable dream, I hope!  You've enough pleasant 
things to dream about, I should think." 
</p><p>"Well, yo' might call it a bad dream, an' yo' might not, Mr. 
Berenson.  It's    &mdash;    it's the houn's, yo' know.  I heah 'em bahkin' all up 
the side of Tulula    &mdash;    howlin' an' howlin' like somethin's goin' wrong.  
It gives me a dreadful honin' fo' home." 
</p><p>"Did you write to your father and brothers that you were to be 
married?" 
</p><p>"Oh, yes, sah, I wrote to all my kin.  I asked 'em to come daown, 
but I know they won't do that, sah.  An' what's moah, the knowledge 
that I was about to be married would keep 'em from tellin' me if 
anything <hi rend="italic">was</hi> goin' wrong." 
</p><p>"Well, I wouldn't worry.  Dreams are out of date, you know.  
You are dreaming because you are nervous, and you're nervous 
because you are going to be married.  That's all there is to that.  It's 
usual under the circumstances." 
</p><p>"I reckon," murmured the mountaineer, "but I suah did heah 
those houn' dogs!" 
</p><p>He said no more about it, and left Berenson, to make his way to 
his sweet-heart's house.  Berenson, strolling along before going to 
his rooms, saw the two of them pacing back and forth in the little 
garden.  He heard the low sound of their laughter.  They were quite 
safe in Arcady, he concluded, and went to his bed well pleased with 
the idyl of his making. 
</p><p>The next morning he awoke with the consciousness of a 
singularly paternal feeling.  He was to meet Miss MacDonald at ten, 
and nine o'clock found him at his club reading his paper and waiting 
for his breakfast. 
</p><p>He had unfolded his sheet and was settling back for the 
enjoyment of it when the door boy entered.  He was making for 
Berenson, and that gentleman of well-arranged habits felt a touch of 
annoyance. 
</p><p>"A gentleman and lady to see you, sir." 
</p><p>He presented a card.  On it were written in the girl's chirography 
the names of his lovers    &mdash;    just "Bill and Summer" in perfect 
confidence and unconventionality. 
</p><p>Something was wrong, evidently.  Every step that Berenson took 
toward the little parlor into which they had been shown convinced 
him that something was very wrong. 
</p><p>It was, indeed, two white and drawn faces that he encountered, 
and the second glance showed him the girl's face eloquent with 
appeal and the man's set in stern and obstinate lines. 
</p><p>"For Heaven's sake, what's the trouble?" he broke out, closing the 
door behind him. 
</p><p>Bill pointed a quivering finger at the paper Berenson had 
unconsciously retained. 
</p><p>"Have yo' read that, sah?" 
</p><p>"No, I haven't.  I was just about to when"    &mdash;    he had shaken the 
paper out and swept his practised glance over the headings.  There, 
in their ancient and fatal juxtaposition, were the names of Shehen 
and Babb!  Berenson's eye ate up the despatch.  The vendetta was 
on again.  Tulula Mountain was a battle-field.  Old Bill was slain.  
So was Loren, his eldest son.  So was Dudley, the brother of the 
elder William.  Dudley's two sons and William's second son, Lee, 
were entrenched in the old Shehen shack.  The Babbs held them 
there, be- 
 
<pb n="83"/> 
 
leaguered    &mdash;    kept them at bay on one side and held off the officers 
of the law on the other.  The Babbs, it appeared, had accessions to 
their side.  The trouble had broken out when some of the contending 
factions met, during a four days' rain-storm, where much corn 
whisky was dispensed. 
</p><p>"I'm going back, sah," announced Bill when Berenson lifted his 
eyes from the page. 
</p><p>"I brought him here to you, sir," cried the girl.  "I could do 
nothing with him! 
 
</p>
	<p>He came an hour ago and 
told me, and I've pleaded and pleaded." 
</p><p>"You'll go to your death!" broke in Berenson, seizing the 
mountaineer by the arm.  "Or you'll make a murderer of yourself    &mdash;    
which will be worse!  Don't be a fool!  Don't be a lunatic!  Your 
duty's here!  Look at that dear little girl.  Think what she    &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"They-all hev killed my ole dad," muttered Shehen.  The 
vernacular had tangled his tongue again. 
</p><p>"But I say you've no right to leave," protested Berenson, shaking 
him by the shoulder.  "You belong here with that girl.  Your honor 
is involved here, not in that death's hole back in the mountains." 
</p><p>Bill's face did not soften in the least.  His eyes were as cruel as 
bayonets; his face settled in battle lines.  He looked taller and his 
boyhood was gone from him. 
</p><p>"They-all have got Loren, too!"  It was as if Berenson's words 
had not penetrated to his understanding. 
</p><p>"You hear him!" sobbed the girl.  "Oh Bill!  Bill, dear!  I can't 
give you up.  Oh, all our happiness together, Bill    &mdash;    that we planned!  
And the home, Bill, and all we were going to do for mother and    &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"Great God, man," cried Berenson.  "I can't stand the torture of 
this, if you can!  You don't mean to stand there and break that girl's 
heart, do you?" 
</p><p>"I stand by my kin," said Bill.  But he seemed hardly to know 
what he was saying.  He had decided to take the ten o'clock train.  
He was in a daze; but the one idea persisted.  He was going to give 
the Babbs something to do.  If they wanted a target, they should 
have one.  In spirit he was climbing Tulula by 
 
 
<pb n="84"/> 
 
those secret paths which he and his clan knew.  He saw nothing save 
the motherly old mountain, with hidden and treacherous foemen in 
her fastnesses; he heard nothing but the howl of the Shehen "houn' 
dogs" lamenting the slain. 
</p><p>He would take nothing with him    &mdash;    none of the possessions he 
had accumulated with frank pride. 
</p><p>"I shan't be needin' much!" he said, a whimsical smile breaking 
his face for the first time.  "I'll fit myself out at Hahdin."  He was 
thinking of his armament. 
</p><p>Summer had given up.  After he had unclasped her arms from his 
neck, she made no further protest.  Her pride was wounded to the 
death.  Her world was taken from her    &mdash;    her East, her West, her 
moon, her sun    &mdash;    as the Gaelic rune has it. 
</p><p>She sank upon a divan, and the tears had dried in her eyes.  
Berenson went to her. 
</p><p>"There's nothing to be done," he whispered.  "I'll call a cab for 
you.  Go home to your mother    &mdash;    to her arms.  That's the best place, 
after all." 
</p><p>She stood up bravely, and he helped her from the room.  At the 
door she turned and gave one backward look.  Bill was standing as 
if turned to stone, but at that glance he threw his long, quivering 
hands over his face. 
</p><p>"Take her away," he groaned.  "Take her away." 
</p><p>So Berenson put her behind the curtained windows of a cab and 
stood while the vehicle drove down the sunlit street and out of sight. 
</p><p>Then he went back to the mountaineer.  He got him to break 
bread with him.  Bill would take little more    &mdash;    but he drained cup 
after cup of the black coffee.  Then they went together to the 
station.  They barely spoke.  There was nothing to say.  Berenson 
had not, for years, felt pain so dragging at the throat, the heart, the 
head, the feet of him.  He was clogged and burdened with it, and at 
the last had only an impatient desire to have the parting over and be 
through with the sharper misery. 
</p><p>Bill strode before him, unconsciously taking the long, springing 
lope of other days.  His blue eyes were repulsive, Berenson thought.  
All the sweetness had gone out of his face.  Though for a glimpse it 
returned, when Berenson, in a swift, uncontrollable emotion, 
embraced him    &mdash;    this consecrated, medi&aelig;val boy, with doom 
written large upon him.  So they parted.  Bill stood on the rear 
platform of the train, tall, grim, uplifted by his hate even more than 
he had ever been by love.  But after all, as Berenson reflected, love 
lay fiercely at the core even of his hate.  The long train swung 
around the curve with a mournful wail, and Berenson shuddered.  It 
sounded, for all the world, like "Shehens' houn' dogs" with their 
prophetic howl. 
 
</p> 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
