<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="PieStud"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
 
<TEI.2 id="PieStud"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Studies of Nature</title>
<title type="sort">studies of nature</title>
<author>Saint-Pierre, Bernadin de</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Barbara Smith, Dept. of English, University of Virginia</name> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">210</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">PieStud</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476295</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Studies of Nature</title>
<title type="sort">studies of nature</title>
<author>Saint-Pierre, Bernadin de</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Translator</resp> 
<name>Henry Hunter</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Joseph J.Woodward</publisher> 
<pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace> 
<date value="1836">1836</date>
</publicationStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Spell-check and verification made 
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term> 
<term>Literature in Translation</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-08">August 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>David L. Gants, Etext Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>UVa header added, basic TEI SGML encodng added.</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2"> 

<div1 type="essay" n="7" id="d3"> 
<pb n="125" id="PieStud125"/>

<p>The wretchedness of the lower orders is, therefore, the 
principal source of our physical and moral maladies.  There 
is another, no less fertile in mischief, I mean the education 
of children.  This branch of political economy engaged, 
among the ancients, the attention of the greatest legislators; 
with us education has no manner of reference to the constitution 
of the state.  In early life are formed the inclinations 
and aversions which influence the whole of our existence. 
Our first affections are likewise the last; they accompany us 
through life, reappear in old age, and then revive the sensibilities 
of childhood with still greater force than those of 
mature age.</p> 
<p>Wise Nature, in giving so much more force to early habits, 
intended that our happiness should depend on those most 
concerned to promote it&mdash;our parents; for on the affections 
they at that season inspire depends the affection we are one 
day called upon to return.  But with us, as soon as the child 
is born, he is transferred to a mercenary nurse.  The first 
bond Nature intended should attach him to his parents is 
burst asunder before it is formed.  The day will come, perhaps, 
when he will behold the funeral procession of those 
who gave him birth leave his father's door with as much 
indifference as they saw his cradle turned out.  He may be 
recalled home, it is true, at the age when the graces, when 
innocence, when the necessity of having an object of affection, 
should fix him there for ever.  But he is permitted to taste 
those sweets only to make him feel, in a little while, the 
bitterness of losing them.  He is sent to school, and boarded 
far from home.  There he is doomed to shed tears which no 
maternal hand is ever more to wipe away; there he is to 
form friendships with strangers pregnant with regret and 
repentance; and there he must learn to extinguish the 
natural affections of brother, sister, father, and mother, the 
most powerful and the sweetest chains by which Nature 
attaches us to our country.</p> 
<p>After this first horrid outrage committed on his young 
heart, others equally violent are offered to his understanding. 
His tender memory must be loaded with ablatives, conjunctions, 
<pb n="126" id="PieStud126"/>conjugations.  The blossom of human life is sacrificed 
to the metaphysical jargon of a dead language.  What 
Frenchman could submit to the torture of learning his own 
in that manner?  And if there be those who have exercised 
such laborious patience, do they speak better than persons 
who have never endured such drudgery?  Who writes best, 
a lady of the court, or a pedantic grammarian?  To learn to 
speak by grammar rules, is the same thing with learning to 
walk by the laws of equilibrium.  Practice teaches the grammar 
of a language, and the passions are our best instructors  
in the rhetoric of it.  A period of life all fire and activity is 
thus repressed by an unnatural constraint, transforming it 
into a state, sad, sedentary, and speculative, which has a 
dismal influence on the temperament, by ingrafting upon it 
maladies without number.</p> 
<p>Of love and ambition, the two moving principles of the 
human heart, the last is by far the most durable and dangerous. 
It dies last in the aged, and our education puts it prematurely 
in motion in the young.  It would be infinitely  
better to assist them in directing their early tender affections 
toward an amiable object.  Most men are destined to feel the 
power of this gentle passion, which Nature has made the 
firmest cement of society.  If their age forbid a commerce 
of early love, their affections ought to be directed into the 
channel of friendship, and thus battalions of friends might 
be formed among them, prepared to devote themselves in the 
service of their country.<note type="au" place="foot"><p>Children, at Sparta, 
were taught only to obey, to love virtue, to love their country, and to live 
in the most intimate union, till they were divided in their schools into two 
classes, of Lovers and Beloved.</p></note></p> 
<p>Ambition, give it what specious name you please, is the  
sworn enemy of all virtue, the source of the most dangerous 
and detestable vices, every one being disposed to gratify it in 
his own way.  It is forbidden by Nature and Religion.  But 
emulation, we are told, awakens talents.  It would be easy 
to demonstrate that the most celebrated writers, in every 
walk of literature, never were brought up at college, from 
Homer, acquainted with no language but his own, down to 
J. J. Rousseau, who was a very indifferent Latin scholar. 
How many young men have made a brilliant figure in the 
run of the classes, who were by and by totally eclipsed in the 
vast sphere of literature!  Italy is crowded with colleges 
<pb n="127" id="PieStud127"/>and academies; but can she boast, at this day, of so much 
as one man eminently distinguished?  Do we not see there, 
on the contrary, talents distracted, by ill-assorted societies, 
jealousies, cabals, intrigues, and ambition, become enfeebled 
and melt away?</p> 
<p>I think I perceive another reason of this decline; nothing 
is studies in those seminaries but methods and forms of learning, 
or what is called <hi rend="italic">manner</hi>.  This study, by fixing us in 
the track of a master, forces us out of the path of nature, the 
source of all talents.  Observe the arts brought to the highest 
perfection in France, and you will find they are those for 
which there is no public school, no prize, no academy; such 
as milliners, jewellers, hair-dressers, cooks, &amp;c.  We have, in 
is true, men of high reputation in the liberal arts, and in the 
sciences; but these men acquired their talents before they 
were admitted into academies.  But admitting that talents 
are formed in colleges, they would not for that be less prejudicial 
to the nation; for it is more important that a country 
should possess virtue than talents, and that men should be  
happy than renowned.  A treacherous glare covers the vices 
of those who succeed in our colleges.  But in the multitude 
of who never succeed, all the vices of a negative ambition are 
already in a state of fermentation, and prepared to burst forth, 
at the command of their leader, upon the world.</p> 
<p>After having elevated a poor boy about his equals, by the 
title of emperor, and even above the whole human race, by 
that of son of the church, he is cruelly brought low by rigorous 
and degrading punishments.<note type="au" place="foot"><p>Consult Montagne's 
Essays, book i. chap. 25.&mdash;Montagne was one of those men not educated at 
college.  He was instructed without tasting corporal punishment, and without 
emulation, under the paternal roof, by the gentlest of fathers, and by 
preceptors whose memory he has preciously embalmed in his writings.  He 
became, by means of an education diametrically opposite to ours, one of the 
best and most intelligent men of the nation.</p></note>  I have seen, at college, 
many a pretty creature, ready to swoon with pain, receive on 
their little hands a dozen sharp strokes; and by the infliction 
of this punishment, the skin separated from the tip of their 
fingers.  What shall be said of those infamous punishments, 
which produce a disgraceful effect on the morals of both 
scholars and regents?  It is impossible to enter on this subject 
without putting modesty to the blush.  And yet they 
are employed by priests!</p> 
<p>Our children, subverted by the vices of a faulty education 
<pb n="128" id="PieStud128"/>become false reasoners, knavish, hypocritical, envious, ugly, 
and wicked.  In proportion as they increase in age, they increase 
also in malignity and the spirit of contradiction.  Not 
a schoolboy knows any thing of the laws of his country, but 
some may have heard talk about those of the twelve tables. 
No one of them can tell how our own wars are conducted; 
but many can entertain you with those of the greeks and 
Romans.  They all know single combat is prohibited; yet 
many go to the fencing-schools, where the only thing taught 
is to fight duels.</p> 
<p>Others, destined to functions more peaceful, are put to 
school to learn the art of disputation.  Truth, we are gravely 
told, is struck out of the collision of opinions.  Out of disputations 
have arisen sophisms, paradoxes, errors of every 
kind.  Truth never shows her face before tyrants; and 
every man who disputes would be a tyrant if he could.  The 
light of truth has no resemblance to the fatal coruscations 
of thunder, but to the brightness of the sun when heaven is 
without a cloud.</p> 
<p>I shall not follow our youth into the world, where he would 
be sufficiently unhappy, supposing him to have preserved 
only that fear of blame and desire of commendation under 
which his studies were conducted.  Influenced by the opinion 
of another, himself possessing no steady principle, the silliest 
of women will rule over him with more unbounded empire 
than his professor.  All I plead for is, that children should 
be delivered, at least, from that tedious apprenticeship of 
misery, by which they are depraved, at the happiest and 
most amiable period of their existence, and which has afterward 
so much influence on their characters.  Man is born 
good, society renders him wicked, and our mode of education 
prepares the way for it.</p> 
<p>Trace the history of a villain's life, and we shall find his 
infancy has been miserable.  Where children were unhappy, 
I have observed them wicked and ugly; but where I saw 
them happy, they were beautiful and good.  In Holland and 
Flanders, where they are brought up with the greatest gentleness, 
their beauty is singularly remarkable.  You never 
hear them, as in our cities, uttering loud and bitter cries; 
still less are they threatened with the rod by their mothers 
and nurses; they are not gay, but contented.  You observe 
on their countenance an air of tranquillity and satisfaction 
<pb n="129" id="PieStud129"/>perfectly enchanting, and infinitely more interesting than 
the boisterous mirth of our young people, when they are no 
longer under the eye of their fathers or preceptors.</p> 
<p>This calmness diffused over all their actions, is the source 
of a happy composure during their whole life.  I never saw 
any country where parental tenderness was so strikingly expressed; 
the children repay in their old age the indulgence 
with which they were treated in helpless infancy.  By bonds 
so endearing are those people so powerfully attached to their 
country, that we find very few of them settling among strangers. 
With us, fathers like better to see children sprightly 
than good, because in an ambitious society, spirit raises man 
to the head of a party, but goodness makes dupes.  They 
have epigrams composed by their children; but wit being 
only the perception of the relations of society, children scarcely 
ever have any but what is borrowed.  Wit itself is frequently, 
in them, the proof of a miserable existence, as may be remarked 
in the schoolboys of our cities, who usually are 
sprightlier than the children of the peasantry; but in general 
they are all forward in point of feeling; and this reflects 
great blame on those who degrade them, at an age when they 
feel more delicately than men.</p> 
<p>Affecting instances of sensibility are not unfrequent in the 
children of the common people.  Walking through the Pre St. 
Gervais, about the setting in of winter, I observed a poor woman, 
lying along the ground, weeding a bed of sorrel; close by 
her was a little girl, of six years old at most, standing motionless 
and quite impurpled with the cold.  I addressed myself 
to the woman, who was indisposed, and inquired into the 
nature of her malady.  'Sir,' said she, 'for three months past, 
I have suffered severely from the rheumatism; but my disease  
gives me less pain than that poor child does: she will 
not quit me a single moment.  If I say to her, See, you are 
quite benumbed with cold, go and warm yourself; she replies, 
Alas! mother, if I leave you, your complaints will be your 
only companion.</p> 
<p>Another time, being in the park at Marly, I there found 
three children, two little girls, employed with singular activity 
in picking up the scattered sticks of dry wood, which they 
deposited in a basket, and a little boy, all in tatters, and extremely 
lean, devouring a morsel of bread.  I asked the tallest 
what she intended to do with the wood; she replied, 
<pb n="130" id="PieStud130"/>'Look, sir, at that poor boy; he is very miserable!  He is 
so unfortunate as to have a step-mother, who sends him out, 
all day long, to pick up wood: if he carries none home, he 
is beaten severely; when he happens to have got a little, and 
is carrying it off, the Swiss at the park gate takes it from 
him, and applies it to his own use.  He is half dead with 
hunger, and we have given him our breakfast.'  Having thus 
spoken, she and her companion filled the little basket; helped 
him up with it on his back, and ran away before their unhappy 
friend to the gate of the park, to see if he could pass unmolested.</p> 
<p>Foolish instructors!  Human nature, you tell us, is corrupted: 
yes, but you are the persons who corrupt it by contradictions, 
by unprofitable studies, by dangerous ambition, 
by shameful chastisements: and by an equitable reaction of 
Divine Justice, that feeble and unfortunate generation will 
one day give back to that which oppresses it, all the mischief 
which it first received.</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="essay" n="8" id="d4"> 
<head>STUDY EIGHTH. REPLY TO THE OBJECTIONS AGAINST A DIVINE PROVIDENCE, AND THE HOPES OF A LIFE TO COME, FOUNDED ON THE INCOMPREHENSIBLE NATURE OF GOD AND ON THE MISERIES OF A PRESENT STATE.</head> 
<p>'WHAT avails it me,' some one will say, 'that my tyrants 
are punished, if I am still to be the victim of tyranny?  Is it 
possible that such compensations should be the work of GOD? 
Great philosophers, who have devoted their whole life to the 
study of Nature, have refused to acknowledge its Author. 
Who hath seen GOD at any time?  What is it that constitutes 
GOD?  But taking it for granted that an intelligent BEING 
directs the affairs of this universe, man assuredly is abandoned 
to himself: no hand has traced his career: as far as he is 
concerned, there are, apparently, two Deities; the one inviting 
him to unbounded enjoyment, and the other dooming him 
to endless privation; one God of Nature, and another God of 
Religion.  Man is left totally uncertain whether of the two 
he is bound to please; and whatever be the choice which he 
<pb n="131" id="PieStud131"/>is determined to make, how can he tell whether he is rendering 
himself an object of love or of hatred?</p> 
<p>'His virtue itself fills him with doubts and scruples; it renders 
him miserable, both inwardly and outwardly; it reduces 
him to a state of perpetual warfare with himself, and with 
the world, to the interests of which he is obliged to make a  
sacrifice of himself.  If he is chaste, the world calls him impotent; 
if religious, he is accounted silly; if he discovers benignity 
of disposition, it is because he wants courage; if he 
devotes himself for the good of his country, he is fanatic; if 
simple, he is duped; if modest, he is supplanted; everywhere 
he is derided, betrayed, despised, now by the philosopher, and 
now by the devotee.  On what foundation can he build the 
hope of a recompense for so many struggles and mortifications? 
On a life to come?  What assurance has he of its existence? 
Where is the traveller that ever returned from 
thence?</p> 
<p>'What is the soul of man?  Where was it a hundred years 
ago?  Where will it be a century hence?  It expands with 
the senses, and expires when they expire.  What becomes of 
it in sleep, in a lethargy?  It is the illusion of pride to imagine 
it immortal: Nature universally points to death, in his 
monuments, in his appetites, in his loves, in his friendships: 
man is universally reduced to the necessity of drawing a veil 
over this idea.  In order to live less miserable, he ought to 
<hi rend="italic">divert</hi> himself, that is, as the word literally imports, he ought 
to <hi rend="italic">turn aside</hi> from that dismal perspective of woes which Nature 
is presenting to him on every side.  To what hopeless 
lobbers has she not subjected his miserable life?  The beasts 
of the field are a thousand times happier; clothed, lodged, 
fed by the hand of Nature, they give themselves up without 
solicitude to the indulgence of their passions, and finish their 
career without any presentiment of death, and without any 
fear of an hereafter.</p> 
<p>'If there be a GOD who presides over the destiny of all, he 
must be inimical to the felicity of the human race.  What is 
it to me that the earth is clothed with vegetables, if I have 
not the shade of a single tree at my disposal?  Of what importance 
to me are the laws of harmony and of love, which 
govern Nature, if I behold around me only objects faithless 
and deceiving; or if my fortune, my condition, my religion, 
impose celibacy upon my?  The general felicity diffused over 
<pb n="132" id="PieStud132"/>the earth, serves only as a bitter aggravation of my particular 
wretchedness.  What interest is it possible for me to take in 
the wisdom of an arrangement which renovates all things, 
if, as a consequence of that very arrangement, I feel myself 
sinking, and ready to be lost for ever?  One single wretch 
might arraign Providence, and say with Job the Arabian, 
chap. iii. 20, <hi rend="italic">Wherefore is light given to him that is in misery, 
and life unto the bitter in soul?</hi>  Alas! the appearances of happiness 
have been disclosed to the view of man, only to overwhelm 
him with despair of ever attaining it.  If a GOD, 
intelligent and beneficent, governs Nature, diabolical spirits 
direct and confound at least the affairs of the children of men.'</p> 
<p>I shall, first, reply to the principal authorities on which 
some of these objections are supported.  They are extracted, 
in part, from a celebrated poet, and a learned philosopher, 
namely, Lucretius and Pliny.</p> 
<p>Lucretius has clothed the philosophy of Empedocles and 
Epicurus in very beautiful verses.  His imagery is enchanting; 
but that philosophy of atoms, which adhere to each 
other by chance, is so completely absurd, that wherever it 
appears, the beauty of the poetry is impaired.  To what, we 
may ask him, do these primary atoms, out of which you construct 
the elements of Nature, owe their existence?  Who 
communicated to them the first movement?  How is it possible 
they should have given to the aggregation of a great 
number of bodies, a spirit of life, a sensibility, and a will, 
which they themselves possessed not?</p> 
<p>If you believe, with Leibnitz, that those <hi rend="italic">monads,</hi> or unities, 
have perceptions peculiar to themselves, you give up the 
laws of chance, and must allow to the elements of Nature 
the intelligence you refuse to its AUTHOR.  Descartes has 
subjected those impalpable principles to the laws of an ingenious 
geometry; and after him, the heard of philosophers, 
seduced by the facility of erecting all sorts of systems with 
the same materials, have applied to them, by turns, the laws 
of attraction, of fermentation, of crystallization; but all without 
success.</p> 
<p>Lucretius has thought proper to pursue a method still 
more strange, namely, that in a work, the professed object 
of which is to materialize the Deity, he sets out with deifying 
matter.  He has given way to this universal principle, that 
we find it impossible powerfully to interest mankind, whatever 
<pb n="133" id="PieStud133"/>be the object, without presenting to the mind some of 
the attributes of Deity.  On this hypothesis, therefore, in his 
first book <hi rend="italic">De Rerum Natura,</hi> he deifies Venus; ascribes to 
her the creation of the world; addresses prayers, and bestows 
on her person the epithet of sacred; he invests her with the 
character of goodness, justice, intelligence, and power, which 
belongs to GOD only; in a word, the attributes are so exactly 
the same, that, suppressing only the word Venus, in the 
invocation of his poem, you may apply it almost entirely to 
the Divine Wisdom.  He is constrained to admit, in the 
sequel of his poem, that this goddess, so wonderfully beneficent, 
is directly chargeable with the ruin of health, of fortune,  
and, sooner or later, with the loss of reputation: that, 
from the very lap of the pleasures which she bestows, there 
issues a something which imbitters enjoyment, torments a 
man, and renders him miserable.</p> 
<p>Pliny takes the directly opposite course.  In the very 
threshold of his Natural History, he affirms there is no God, 
and the whole work is an elaborate demonstration of the 
being of GOD.  His authority must be of considerable weight, 
as it is not that of a poet to whom opinions are a matter of 
indifference, provided he can produce a striking picture; nor 
that of a sectary, obstinately determined to support a party, 
whatever violence may be done to conscience; nor, finally, 
that of a flatterer, making his court to vicious princes.  Pliny 
wrote under the virtuous Titus, and dedicated his book to 
him.  He carries to such a height the love of truth, and 
contempt of the glory of the age in which he lived, as to 
condemn the victories of C'sar, in Rome itself, and when 
addressing a Roman emperor.  He is replete with humanity 
and virtue; and exposes the cruelty of masters to their slaves, 
the luxury of the great, nay, the dissolute conduct of several 
empresses.  He sometimes pronounces the panegyric of good 
men; and exalts even above the inventors of arts persons 
who have rendered themselves illustrious by their continency, 
modesty, and piety.</p> 
<p>His work is a combination of brilliancies, a real encyclopedia, 
containing the history of the knowledge and the errors 
of this time.  These last are sometimes imputed to him 
unjustly, for he frequently brings them forward in the view 
of refuting them.  The physicians and apothecaries, who 
have extracted many of their prescriptions from him, abuse 
<pb n="134" id="PieStud134"/>him, because he finds fault with their conjectural art and 
systematic spirit.  He abounds, besides, in curious information, 
in profound views, and interesting traditions; and what 
renders his performance invaluable, he uniformly expresses 
himself in a picturesque manner.  With all this taste, judgment, 
and knowledge, Pliny is an atheist.  Nature, from 
whom he has derived such various intelligence, may address 
him in the words of C'sar to Brutus: <hi rend="italic">What, you too, my son!</hi></p> 
<p>If I may be permitted to say it, in justification of Pliny, 
I believe his immortal work to be falsified, where is made 
to reason as an atheist.  All his commentators agree that 
no author has suffered more from the unfaithfulness of transcribers 
than he has done; that copies of his Natural History 
exist in which whole chapters are entirely different.  I shall 
here observe, that the writings of the ancients have passed 
through more than one unfaithful language, nay worse, 
more than one suspicious hand.  They have met with the 
fate of their monuments, among which their temples have 
been most of all degraded.  Their books have also been 
mutilated, chiefly in passages favourable to religion, or the 
reverse.  An instance of this we have in the transcription of 
Cicero's Treatise on the Nature of the Gods, in which the 
objections against Providence are omitted.</p> 
<p>Montagne upbraids the first Christians with having suppressed, 
on account of four or five articles which contradicted 
their creed, a part of the works of Cornelius Tacitus, 'though 
the emperor Tacitus, his relation, had, by his express edicts, 
furnished all the libraries in the world with them.'<note type="au" 
place="foot"><p>Essays, book ii, chap. xix.</p></note></p> 
<p>In our own days, every party exerts itself to run down the 
reputation and opinions opposed to it.  Mankind is, in the 
hands of religion and philosophy, like the old man in the 
fable, between two dames of different ages.  They had both 
a mind to trim his locks, each in her own way.  The younger 
picked out all the white hairs, which she could not bear; the 
old one, for an opposite reason, removed the black; consequently 
his head was speedily reduced to complete baldness.</p> 
<p>It is impossible to adduce a more satisfactory demonstration 
of this ancient infidelity of the two parties, than an interpolation 
to be found in the writings of Flavius Josephus, who 
was contemporary with Pliny.  He is made to say, in so 
<pb n="135" id="PieStud135"/>many words, that the Messiah was just born; and he continues 
his narration, to the end of a voluminous history, 
without once referring to this wonderful event.  How can it 
be believed that Josephus, who frequently indulges himself 
in a tedious detail of minute circumstances, should not have 
reverted a thousand and a thousand times to a birth so deeply 
interesting to his nation, considering that its very destiny 
was involved in that event, and that even the destruction of 
Jerusalem was only one of the consequences of the death of 
JESUS CHRIST?  He, on the contrary, perverts the meaning  
of the prophecies which announce Him, applying them to 
Vespasian and Titus; for he, as well as the other Jews, 
expected a Messiah triumphant.  Besides, had Josephus believed 
in CHRIST, would he not have embraced his religion?</p> 
<p>For a similar reason, is it credible that Pliny should commence 
his Natural History with denying the existence of GOD, 
and afterwards fill every page of it with expatiating on the 
wisdom, goodness, providence, and majesty of Nature; on 
the presages and premonitions, sent expressly from the gods; 
and even on the miracles divinely operated through the medium 
of dreams?</p> 
<p>Certain savage tribes have been adduced as examples of 
atheism, and every sequestered corner of the globe has been 
for this purpose explored.  But obscure tribes were no more 
intended to serve as an example to the human race, than certain 
mean and obscure families among ourselves could be 
proposed as proper models to the nation; especially when the 
object is to support by authority an opinion necessarily subversive 
of all society.  Besides, such assertions are absolutely 
false.  I have read the history of voyages from which 
they are extracted.  The travellers acknowledge they had 
but a transient view of those people, and were totally unacquainted 
with their languages.  They supposed there could 
be no religion among them, because they saw no temples; as 
if any other temple were necessary to the belief in GOD than 
that of Nature!  These same travellers contradict themselves, 
by relating that those nations, elsewhere represented 
as destitute of all religion, make obeisance to the moon, by 
prostrating themselves to the earth, or lifting up their hands 
to heaven: that they pay respect to the memory of their 
forefathers, and place viands on their tombs.  The immortality 
<pb n="136" id="PieStud136"/>of the soul, admitted how you will, necessarily supposes 
the existence of GOD.</p> 
<p>But if the first of all truths stood in need of testimony from 
men, we could collect that of the whole human race, from 
geniuses the most exalted, down to the lowest state of ignorance. 
This unanimity of testimony is of irresistible weight; 
for it is impossible that such a thing should exist on the earth 
as universal error.</p> 
<p>Newton, who pursued his researches into the laws of 
Nature so profoundly, never pronounced the name of GOD 
without moving his hat, and otherwise expressing the most 
devout respect.  He took pleasure in recalling this sublime 
idea, and considered it as the natural bond of union among 
all nations.  Corneille le Bruyn, the Dutch painter, relates, 
that happening to dine one day at his table, in company with 
several other foreigners, Newton, when the desert was served 
up, proposed a health to the men of every country who believe 
in GOD.  This was drinking the health of the human 
race.  A belief in GOD arises from the spectacle of Nature 
simply.  A poor ignorant Arabian of the desert was one day 
asked, How he came to be assured there was a God?  'In 
the same way,' he replied, 'that I am able to tell by the print 
impressed on the sand whether it was a man or a beast which 
passed that way.'<note type="au" place="foot"><p>Travels through Arabia, by 
Mons. d'Arvieux.</p></note></p> 
<p>Man, as has been said, cannot imagine any form, or produce  
a single idea, of which the model is not in Nature.  He 
expands his reason only on the reasons Nature has supplied. 
GOD must, therefore, necessarily exist, were it but for this, 
that man has an idea of him.  But if we attentively consider 
that every thing necessary to man exists in a most wonderful 
adaptation to his necessities, for the strongest of all reasons 
GOD likewise must exist, He who is the universal adaptation 
of all the societies of the human race.</p> 
<p>But I should wish to know, in what way those who doubt 
of his existence, on a review of the works of Nature, would 
desire to be assured of it?  Do they wish he should appear 
under a human form, and assume the figure of an old man, 
as he is painted in some of our churches?  They would say, 
this is a man.  Were He to invest himself with some unknown 
and celestial form, could we in a human body support the 
<pb n="137" id="PieStud137"/>sight?  The complete and unveiled display of even a single 
one of his works on the earth would be sufficient to confound 
our feeble organs.  For example, if the earth wheels around 
its axis, as is supposed, there is not a human being in existence, 
who, from a fixed point in the heavens, could view the 
rapidity of its motion without horror; for he would behold 
rivers, oceans, kingdoms, whirling about under his feet with 
a velocity almost thrice as great as a cannon-ball.  But even 
the swiftness of this diurnal rotation is a mere nothing: for 
the rapidity with which the globe describes its annual circle, 
and hurls us round the sun, is seventy-five times greater than 
that of a bullet shot from the cannon.  Were it but possible 
for the eye to view through the skin the mechanism of our 
own body, the sight would overwhelm us.  Durst we make 
a single movement if we saw our blood circulating, the nerves 
pulling, the lungs blowing, the humours filtrating, and all the 
incomprehensible assemblage of fibres, tubes, pumps, currents, 
pivots, which sustain an existence at once so frail and so presumptuous?</p> 
<p>Would we wish, on the contrary, that GOD should manifest 
himself in a manner more adapted to his own nature, by the 
direct and immediate communication of his intelligence, to 
the exclusion of every intervenient mean?</p> 
<p>When some striking truth or affecting sentiment impresses 
an audience at a theatre, some are melted into tears, others 
almost choked with an oppressed respiration, others quite in 
a transport, clapping their hands and stamping with their 
feet; the females in the boxes actually fainting away.  Were 
these violent agitations of spirit to go on progressively but for 
a few minutes only, the persons subject to them might lose 
their reason, perhaps life.  What would be the case, then, if 
the Source of all truth and feeling were to communicate himself 
to us in a mortal body?  GOD has placed us at a suitable 
distance from his infinite Majesty; near enough to perceive, 
but not so near as to be annihilated by it.  He veils intelligence 
under the forms of matter, and He restores our confidence 
respecting the movements of the material world by the 
sentiment of his intelligence.  If at any time he is pleased 
to communicate himself in a more intimate manner, it is not 
through the channel of haughty science, but through that of 
modest virtue.  He discloses himself to the simple, and hides 
his face from the proud.</p> 
<pb n="138" id="PieStud138"/><p>'But,' it is asked, 'what made GOD?  Why should there 
be a God?  Am I to call in question his existence because I 
am incapable of comprehending his origin?  This style of 
reasoning would lead us to conclude that man doe snot exist: 
for, Who made man?  Why should there be men?  Why am 
I in the world in the eighteenth century?  Why did I not 
arrive in some of the ages which went before? and, Wherefore 
should I not be here in those which are to come?  The 
existence of GOD is at all times necessary, and that of men 
only contingent.  Nay, the existence of man is the only apparently 
superfluous existence in the order established upon 
earth.  Many islands have been discovered without inhabitants, 
which presented abodes the most enchanting, from the 
disposition of the valleys, of the waters, of the woods, of the 
animals.  Man alone deranges the plans of Nature: he diverts 
the current from the fountain; he digs into the side of the 
hill; he sets the forest on fire; he massacres without mercy 
every thing that breathes; everywhere he degrades the earth, 
which could do very well without him.</p> 
<p>The harmony of this globe would be partially destroyed, 
perhaps entirely so, were but the smallest genus of plants to 
be suppressed; for its annihilation would leave a certain 
space of ground destitute of verdure, and thereby rob of its 
nourishment the species of insect which there found the 
support of life.  The destruction of the insect again would 
involve that of the species of bird which in these alone finds 
the food proper for their young; and so on to infinity.  The 
total ruin of the vegetable and animal kingdoms might take  
its rise from the failure of a single moss, as we may see that 
of an edifice commence in a small crevice.  But if the human 
race existed not, it would be impossible to suppose that any 
thing had been deranged: every brook, every plant, every 
animal, would always be in its place.  Indolent and haughty 
philosopher, who presumest to demand of Nature wherefore 
there should be a God, why demandest thou not rather 
wherefore there should be men?</p> 
<p>All his works speak of their AUTHOR.  The plain which 
gradually escapes from my eye, and the capacious vault of 
heaven which encompasses me on every side, convey to me 
an idea of his immensity; the fruits suspended on the bough 
within reach of my hand, announce his providential care; the 
constant revolution of the seasons display his wisdom; the 
<pb n="139" id="PieStud139"/>variety of provision which his bounty makes, in every climate, 
for the wants of every thing that lives, the stately port of the 
forests, the soft verdure of the meadow, the grouping of plants, 
the perfume and enamel of flowers, an infinite multitude of 
harmonies, known and unknown, are the magnificent languages 
which speak of Him to all men in a thousand and a 
thousand different dialects.  Nay, the very order of Nature 
is superfluous: GOD is the only being whom disorder invokes, 
and whom human weakness announces.  In order to attain 
the knowledge of his attributes, we need only have a feeling 
of our own imperfections.</p> 
<p>Man has given nothing to himself, he has received all.&mdash; 
But I should consider it an insult to the understanding of my 
reader, were I to insist longer on the proofs of the existence 
of GOD.  I shall now reply to the objections against his goodness.</p> 
<p>The laws which govern man are derived from the same 
plan of wisdom which has constructed the universe.  Man is 
not a being of a nature perfectly simple.  Virtue, which ought 
to be the great object of his pursuit on earth, is an effort which 
he makes over himself for the good of mankind, in the pleasing 
view of GOD only.  It proposes to him the Divine Wisdom 
as models, and presents the most secure and unerring 
path to happiness.  Study Nature, and you will perceive that 
nothing can be more adapted to the felicity of man, and that 
virtue carries her reward in her bosom, even in this world.</p> 
<p>Let us not complain that GOD has made an unfair distribution 
of his gifts, when we see the abundance in which bad 
men live.  Whatever is on the earth most useful, beautiful, 
and best, is within the reach of every man.  Obscurity is better 
than glory, and virtue than talents.  The light of the sun, 
a little field, a wife and children, are sufficient to employ a 
succession of pleasures to him.  Must he have luxuries too? 
A flower presents him colours more lovely than the pearl 
dragged from the abysses of the ocean; and a burning coal 
on his hearth has a brighter lustre, and is infinitely more useful, 
than the famous gem which glitters on the head of the 
Grand Mogul.</p> 
<p>After all, What did GOD owe to man?  Water from the 
fountain, a little fruit, wool to clothe him, as much land as 
he is able to cultivate with his own hands.  So much for the 
wants of his body.  As to those of the soul, it is sufficient 
<pb n="140" id="PieStud140"/>for him to possess in infancy the love of his parents; in 
maturity that of his wife; in old age the gratitude of his 
children; at all seasons the good will of his neighbours, the 
number of whom is restricted to four or five, according to the 
extent and form of his domain; so much knowledge of the 
globe as he can acquire by rambling about for half a day, 
so as to get home to his own bed at night, or, at most, to the 
extremity of his domestic horizon; such a sense of Providence 
as Nature bestows on all men, and which will spring 
up in his heart fully as well after he has made the circuit of 
his own field, as after returning from a voyage round the 
world.</p> 
<p>With corporeal enjoyments and mental gratifications like 
these he ought to be content; whatever more he desires is 
above his wants, and inconsistent with the distributions of 
Nature.  He cannot acquire superfluity but by the sacrifice 
of some necessary; public consideration he must purchase 
at the price of domestic happiness; and a name in the world 
of science by renouncing his repose.  Besides, these honours, 
attendants, riches, that submission, men so eagerly hunt after, 
are desired unjustly: a man cannot obtain them but by 
plundering and enslaving his fellow-citizens: their acquisition 
exposes to incredible labour and anxiety, the possession 
is disturbed by incessant care, and privation tears the heart 
with regret.  By pretended blessings such as these, health, 
reason, conscience, all, is depraved and lost.</p> 
<p>Virtuous persons, in truth, are sometimes destitute not only 
of the blessings of society, but of those of Nature.  To this 
I answer, that their calamities frequently are beneficial to 
them.  When persecuted by the world, they are usually incited 
to engage in some illustrious career.  Affliction is the 
path of great talents, or of great virtues, which are infinitely 
preferable.</p> 
<p>A resignation to the will of GOD ought in every situation 
to sooth the soul to peace.  But if the illusions of a vain 
world should ruffle our spirit, let me suggest a consideration 
which may go far toward restoring our tranquillity.  When 
any thing in Nature bears hard upon us, and inspires mistrust 
of its AUTHOR, let us suppose an order of things contrary to 
that which galls us, and we shall find a multitude of consequences 
resulting from this hypothesis that would involve 
much greater evils than those of which we complain.  If 
<pb n="141" id="PieStud141"/>you wish to justify the order of Nature, it is sufficient to 
deviate 
from it; and, in order to refute all human systems, nothing 
more is necessary than to admit them.</p> 
<p>For example, complaints are made of death: but if men 
were not to die, What would become of their posterity?  Long 
before now there would not have been room for them on the 
earth.  Death, therefore, is a benefit.  Men complain of the 
necessity of labouring: but unless they laboured, How could 
they pass their time?  The reputedly happy of the age, who 
have nothing to do, are at a loss how to employ it.  Labour, 
therefore, is a benefit.  Men envy the beasts the instinct 
which guides them: but if, from their birth, they knew, like 
them, all that they ever are to know, What should they do 
in the world?  They would saunter through it without interest 
or curiosity.  Ignorance, therefore, is a benefit.</p> 
<p>The other ills of Nature are equally necessary.  Pain of 
body and vexation of spirit are barriers erected by Nature to 
prevent our deviating from her laws.  But for pain bodies 
would be broken to pieces on the slightest shock; but for 
chagrin the mind would become the victim of every sickly 
appetite.  Diseases are the efforts of temperaments to purge 
off some noxious humour.  Nature employs disease not to  
destroy the body, but to preserve it; it is ever the consequence 
of some violation of her laws, physical and moral. 
The remedy is frequently obtained by leaving her to act in 
her own way.  The regimen of aliments restores our health 
of body, and that of men, tranquillity of mind.  Whatever 
opinions disturb our repose in society, they almost always 
vanish in solitude.  Sleep itself dispels our chagrin more 
gently and infallibly than a book of morals.  If our distresses 
are such as to break our rest, they may be mitigated by having 
recourse to GOD.  Here is the central point towards 
which all the paths of human life converge.  Prosperity, at  
all seasons, invites us to his presence, but adversity leaves us 
no choice.</p> 
<p>The evils of society are no part of the plan of Nature, but 
they demonstrate the existence of another order of things: 
for is it natural to imagine, that the BEING good and just, 
who has disposed every thing on earth to promote the happiness 
of man, will permit him to be deprived of it without 
punishing the wretch who dared to counteract his gracious 
designs?  Will He do nothing in behalf of the virtuous but 
<pb n="142" id="PieStud142"/>unfortunate man, whose constant study was to please him, 
when he has loaded with blessings so many miscreants who 
abuse them?  After having displayed a bounty which has 
met with no return, will he fail in executing necessary justice?</p> 
<p>'But,' we are told, 'every thing dies with us.  Here we  
ought to believe our own experience; we were nothing before 
our birth, and we shall be nothing after death.'  I adopt 
the analogy; but if I take my point of comparison from the 
moment I was nothing, and when I came into existence, 
what becomes of this argument?  Is not one positive proof 
better than all the negative proofs in the world?  You conclude 
from an unknown past to an unknown future to perpetuate 
the nothingness of man; and I, for my part, deduce 
my consequence from the present which I know, to the future 
which I do not know, as an assurance of this future 
existence.  I proceed on the presumption of a goodness and 
a justice to come, from the instances of goodness and justice 
which I see actually diffused over the universe.</p> 
<p>Besides, if we have in our present state the desire and 
presentiment only of a life to come; and if no one ever 
returned thence to give us information concerning it, the 
reason is, a proof more sensible would be inconsistent with the 
nature of our present life on the earth.  Evidence on this point 
must involve the same inconveniences with that of the existence 
of GOD.  Were we assured by some sensible demonstration 
that a world to come was prepared for us, I have the 
fullest conviction that all the pursuits of this world would 
from that instant be abandoned.  The passage from the 
one world to the other being in every man's power, the 
gulf would be quickly shot: but Nature has involved it in 
obscurity, and planted doubt and apprehension to guard the 
passage.</p> 
<p>It would appear, we are told by some, that the idea of the 
immortality of the soul could arise only from the speculations 
of men of genius, who, considering the combination of this 
universe, and the connexion which present scenes have with 
those which preceded them, must have thence concluded that 
they had a necessary connexion with futurity; or else that 
this idea of immortality was introduced by legislators to console 
mankind under the pressure of their political injustice. 
But if this were the case, how could it have found its way 
<pb n="143" id="PieStud143"/>into the deserts, and been diffused at once, over the islands 
of the South Seas and Lapland, over Asia and North America, 
among the inhabitants of Paris and those of the New 
Hebrides?  How is it possible that so many nations, separated 
by vast oceans, so different in manners and in language, 
should all believe in the immortality of the soul?  Whence 
could they have derived a belief so flatly contradicted by 
their daily experience?  They every day see their friends 
die, but the day never comes when any one reappears.</p> 
<p>Shall we be told that pride cherishes this fond opinion in 
their breasts?  What, is it pride that induces a wretched negro 
in the West Indies to hang himself, in the hope of returning 
to his own country, where a second state of slavery awaits 
him?  Other nations, such as the islanders of Otaheite, restrict 
the hope of this immortality to a renovation of precisely 
the same life they are going to leave.  Ah! the passions 
present to man far different plans of felicity; the miseries of 
his existence, and the illumination of his reason, would long 
ago have destroyed the life that is, had not the hope of a life 
to come been, in the human breast, the result of a supernatural 
feeling.</p> 
<p>But wherefore is man the only one of the animals subjected 
to other evils than those of Nature?  Wherefore should he 
have been abandoned to himself, disposed as he is to go 
astray?  He is, therefore, the victim of some malignant 
being.</p> 
<p>It is the province of religion to take us up where philosophy 
leaves us.  The nature of the ills we endure unfolds 
their origin.  If man renders himself unhappy, it is because 
he would himself be the arbiter of his own felicity.  Man is 
a god in exile.  The reign of Saturn, the Golden Age, Pandora's 
box, from which issued every evil, at the bottom of 
which hope only remained: a thousand similar allegories, 
diffused over all nations, attest the felicity and the fall of a 
first man.</p> 
<p>But there is no need to have recourse to foreign testimonies. 
We carry the most unquestionable evidence in ourselves. 
The beauties of Nature bear witness to the existence 
of GOD, and the miseries of man confirm the truths of religion. 
Animals are lodged, clothed, fed, by the hand of 
Nature, without care, and almost without labour.  Man alone 
is overwhelmed with calamity.  First, he is born naked; 
<pb n="144" id="PieStud144"/>and is possessed of so little instinct, that if his mother were 
not to rear him for several years he would perish of hunger, 
heat, or cold.  He knows nothing but from the experience 
of his parents.  They must find him a place to lodge, weave 
garments for him, provide his food for eight or ten years. 
Encomiums have been passed on certain countries for their 
fertility and mildness of climate, but I know of none where 
subsistence of the simplest kind does not cost man solicitude 
and labour.  In India he must be sheltered from heat, from 
rain, and from insects.  He must there cultivate rice, weed, 
thrash, shell, and dress it.  The banana, useful as it is, must 
be watered and hedged round, to secure it from the wild 
beasts.  Magazines of provisions must be provided during 
those seasons when the earth produces nothing.  When man 
has thus collected around him every thing necessary to a 
quiet and comfortable life, ambition, jealousy, avarice, gluttony, 
incontinency, or langour, take possession of his heart. 
He perishes, the victim of his own passions.  Undoubtedly 
to have sunk thus below the level of the beasts, man must 
have aspired at an equality with the DEITY.</p> 
<p>Wretched mortals!  See your happiness in virtue, and 
you will have no ground of complaint against Nature.  Despise 
that useless knowledge, those unreasonable prejudices, 
which have corrupted the earth, and which every age subverts  
in its turn.  Love those laws which are eternal.  Your 
destiny is not abandoned to chance, nor to mischievous demons. 
Recall those times, the recollection of which is still 
fresh among all nations.  The brute creation everywhere 
found the means of supporting life; man alone had neither 
aliment, nor clothing, nor instinct.</p> 
<p>Divine Wisdom left man to himself, in order to bring him 
back to GOD.  She scattered her blessings over the earth, 
that to gather them he might explore every region of it; that 
he might expand his reason by the inspection of her works, 
and that he might love her from a sense of benefits.  She 
placed between herself and him harmless pleasures, rapturous 
discoveries, pure delights, and endless hopes, to lead him 
to herself through the path of knowledge and happiness. 
She fenced his way on both sides, by fear, languor, remorse, 
pain, and all the ills of life, as boundaries destined to prevent 
him from losing himself.  The mother thus scatters fruit 
along the ground to induce her children to learn to walk; 
<pb n="145" id="PieStud145"/>she keeps at a little distance, smiles, calls, stretches out her 
arms towards him; but if he happens to fall, she flies to his 
assistance, wipes away his tears, and comforts him.</p> 
<p>Thus Providence relieves man, supplying his wants in a 
thousand extraordinary ways.  What would have become 
of him in the earliest ages, had he been abandoned to his own 
reason, still unaided by experience?  Where found he corn, 
a principal part of the food of so many nations, and which 
the earth, while it spontaneously produces all sorts of plants, 
nowhere exhibits?  Who taught him agriculture, an art so 
simple that the most stupid of mankind is capable of learning 
it, and yet so sublime, that the most intelligent of animals 
can never pretend to practise it?  There is scarcely an animal 
but what supports its life by vegetables, no one but 
what has daily experience of their reproduction, and does not 
employ, in quest of those that suit him, many more combinations 
than would have been necessary for resowing them.</p> 
<p>But on what did man himself subsist till an Isis or a Ceres 
revealed to him this blessing of the skies?  Who showed him, 
in the first ages of the world, the original fruits of the orchard, 
scattered over the forest, and the alimentary roots concealed 
in the bosom of the earth?  Must he not have died of hunger 
before he had collected a sufficiency to support life, or perished 
by poison before he had learned to select, or sunk under 
fatigue or restlessness before he had formed round his habitation 
grass-plots and arbours?  This art, the image of creation, 
was reserved for that being alone who bore the impression of 
the Divinity.</p> 
<p>If Providence had abandoned man to himself, on proceeding 
from the hands of the Creator, what would have become 
of him?  Could he have said to the plains: Ye unknown 
forests, show me the fruits, my inheritance?  Earth, open, 
and disclose, int he roots buried under thy surface, my destined 
aliment?  Ye plants, on which my life depends, manifest 
to me your qualities, and supply the instinct which Nature 
has denied?  Could he have had recourse, in his distress, to 
the compassion of the beasts, and, ready to perish with hunger, 
have said to the cow: Take me into the number of thy children,  
and let me share, with thy offspring, the produce of one 
of thy superfluous teats?  When the north wind made him 
shiver with cold, would the wild goat and timid sheep have 
run at his call to warm him with their fleeces?  Wandering, 
<pb n="146" id="PieStud146"/>without a protector or asylum, when he heard by night the 
howlings of ferocious animals demanding their prey, could 
he have made supplication to the generous dog, and said to 
him: Be thou my defender, and I will make thee my slave? 
Who could have subjected to his authority so many animals 
which stood in no need of him, which surpassed him in cunning, 
in speed, in strength, unless the hand which, notwithstanding 
his fall, destined him still to empire, had humbled 
their heads to the obedience of his will?</p> 
<p>How was it possible for him, with reason less infallible 
than their instinct, to raise himself up to the heavens, measure  
the course of the stars, cross the ocean, call down the 
thunder, and imitate most of the works and appearances of 
Nature?  We are astonished at these things now; but I am 
much rather astonished that a sense of Deity should have 
spoken to his heart long before a comprehension of the works 
of Nature had perfected his understanding.  View him in 
the state of nature, engaged in perpetual war with the elements, 
with beasts of prey, with his fellow-creatures, with 
himself; frequently reduced to situations of subjection no 
other animal could possibly support; and he is the only being 
who discovers, in the very depth of misery, the character of 
infinity, and the restlessness of immortality.  He erects 
trophies, engraves the record of his achievements on the 
bark of trees, celebrates his funeral obsequies, and puts 
reverence on the ashes of his forefathers, from whom he has 
received an inheritance so fatal.</p> 
<p>Agitated by the rage of love or vengeance, when he is not 
the victim of his fellow-men, he is their tyrant: and he alone 
knows that justice and goodness govern the world, and that 
virtue exalts man to heaven.  He receives from his cradle 
none of the presents of nature, no soft fleece, no plumage, 
no defensive armour, no tool, for a life to painful and so 
laborious; and he is the only being who invites the gods to 
his birth, to his nuptials, and to his funeral obsequies.</p> 
<p>However far he may have been misled by extravagant 
opinions, as often as he is struck by unexpected bursts of joy 
or grief, his soul, by an involuntary movement, takes refuge in 
the bosom of Deity.  He cries out: Ah, my GOD!  He raises 
to heaven suppliant hands, and eyes bathed with tears, in 
hope of there finding a father.  Ah! the wants of man bear 
witness to the providence of a Supreme Being.  He has made 
<pb n="147" id="PieStud147"/>man feeble and ignorant, only that he may stay himself on 
his strength, and illuminate himself by his light; and so far 
is it from being true, that chance or malignant spirits domineer 
over a world, where every thing concurred to destroy a 
creature so wretched, his preservation, his enjoyments, and 
his empire, demonstrate that, at all times, a beneficent GOD 
has been the friend and protector of human life.</p> 
</div1> 
 

<div1 type="essay" n="10" id="d5">
	<pb n="166" id="PieStud166"/> 
<head>STUDY TENTH. OF SOME GENERAL LAWS OF NATURE;</head>   
<div2 type="part" id="d6"> 
<head>AND FIRST, OF PHYSICAL LAWS.</head> 
<p>WE shall divide these laws into <hi rend="italic">physical</hi> and <hi rend="italic">moral,</hi> and 
endeavour to unfold the means of diminishing the sum of 
human wretchedness.  I am presuming to open a path hitherto 
unattempted, and dare not flatter myself that my progress and 
success keep pace with the ardour of my imagination and the 
anticipations of my heart.  But the imperfect materials I have 
collected may perhaps one day assist men of greater ability 
in raising to Nature a temple more worthy of her.</p> 
</div2><div2 type="part" id="d7"> 
<head>OF CONFORMITY.</head> 
<p>Though conformity be a perception of our reason, I place 
it at the head of our physical laws, because it is the first 
feeling we endeavour to gratify in examining natural objects. 
Nay, there is a connexion so intimate between the physical 
character of those objects and the instinct of every being 
possessed of sensibility, that a colour simply is sufficient to 
rouse the passions of animals.  A red object puts the bullock 
into a rage, and suggests to most fowls and fishes the idea 
of prey.  The objects of Nature display in man a feeling of 
a higher order, independent of his wants; it is that of conformity. 
It is by means of the multiplied conformities of 
Nature that man has formed his own reason; for <hi rend="italic">reason</hi> 
means nothing else but the <hi rend="italic">relation</hi> or <hi rend="italic">conformity</hi> of things 
that exist.</p> 
<p>Animals have a sensibility only of objects having conformities 
to their wants; and they have, in this respect, a 
share of reason as perfect as our own.  But man differs from 
animals in his capacity of extending this sentiment of conformity 
to all the relations of Nature, however foreign to his 
personal demands; and this extension of reason has procured 
him, by way of eminence, the denomination of a rational 
animal.</p> 
<p>It is true, that if all the particular rationality of animals 
were united, the sum would probably transcend the general 
reason of man; for human reason has devised most of its 
<pb n="167" id="PieStud167"/>arts and crafts from an imitation of their productions: besides, 
all animals come into the world with their peculiar industry, 
whereas man must acquire his by time and reflection, and 
by imitating the industry and skill of another.  But man 
excels them, not only by uniting in himself the intelligence 
of all, but by his capability of rising upward to the source of 
all conformities, to GOD himself.</p> 
<p>The only character which essentially distinguishes man 
from the animal is, he is a religious being.  They partake 
not with him of this sublime faculty, the principle of human 
intelligence.  By it man is exalted above the beasts, enabled 
to form a conception of the general plans of Nature, and supposes 
an order of things from having caught a glimpse of an 
Author.  It was not Nature which first pointed out GOD to 
man, but a sense of the DEITY in man which indicated to 
him the order of Nature.  The savages ar religious long 
before they are naturalists.</p> 
<p>Accordingly, by the sentiment of this universal conformity 
man is struck with all possible conformities, though foreign to 
him.  He takes an interest in the history of an insect; and 
if his attention is not engaged in behalf of all the insects 
which surround him, it is because he perceives not their relations, 
or else the constant habit of seeing them renders them 
insipid; perhaps it may be some contemptible prejudice, for 
he is affected still more by moral than physical ideas, and by 
his passions more than by his reason.</p> 
<p>We shall farther remark, that all the sentiments of conformity 
spring up in the heart of man at the sight of some 
useful end, which frequently has no relation to his own 
personal wants; it follows that man is naturally good, because 
he is rational; seeing the aspect alone of a conformity, 
though foreign to him, communicates pleasure.  From this 
natural sentiment of goodness the sight of well-proportioned 
animals conveys to us agreeable sensations, increasing in 
proportion as the creature unfolds its instinct.  Want of conformity 
also communicates a painful sensation, always excited 
at the sight of any thing incongruous.  We are shocked 
on looking at a monster, pained to see an animal wanting a 
foot or an eye, nay, at the sight of incongruity even in insensible 
objects.  Withered plants, mutilated trees, an ill-assorted 
edifice, hurt our feelings.  These sensations are perverted or 
suppressed in man only by prejudice or by education.</p> 
<pb n="168" id="PieStud168"/><p>A series of conformities, with a common centre, constitutes 
order.  There are conformities in the members of an animal, 
but order exists only in the body.  Conformity refers to the 
detail, order to the combination.  Order extends our pleasure, 
by collecting conformities, and fixes them by a determination 
towards one centre.  It discovers at once, in a single object, 
a succession of particular conformities, and the leading one 
to which they all refer.</p> 
<p>Thus, as being endowed with a reason which embraces all 
Nature, it affords us pleasure to review the relations between 
the proboscis of a bee and the nectareous juices of flowers; 
between those of her thighs, hollowed into spoons, and bristled 
with hairs, to the fine powder of the stamina which she there 
collects; the use of a long sting, furnished for the defence 
of her property, and all the conformities of the organs of this 
small insect, are more ingenious and in much greater number 
than those of the largest animals.</p> 
<p>The interest, however, grows upon us when we see her 
covered with a yellow powder, her thighs pendent and half 
oppressed with her burden, directing her flight across plains, 
rivers, and shady groves, under points of the wind, with which 
she is well acquainted, and alighting with a humming sound, 
on the cavernous trunk of some aged oak; that one, whose 
particular conformities we have been admiring, is only a single 
member of a numerous republic; this republic itself is but a 
small colony of the immense nation of bees spread over the 
whole earth, from the line to the shores of the frozen oceans. 
This nation again is subdivided into species, conformably 
to the variety of flowers; for some being destined to live on 
flowers which have no depth, such as the radiated, are armed 
with five hooks, to prevent their sliding on the petals.  Others, 
such as the bees of America, have no stings, because they 
construct their hives in the trunks of prickly trees, very common  
there, which accordingly afford them protection.  Many 
are the conformities among other species of bees, totally unknown 
to us; yet this vast nation is but one little family of 
the class of flies, of which we know, in our climate alone, 
near 6000 species, as distinct, as to forms and instincts, as 
bees themselves are from other flies.</p> 
<p>Were we to compare the relations of this volatile class, so 
<pb n="169" id="PieStud169"/>numerous in itself, with all the parts of the vegetable and 
animal kingdoms, we should find an innumerable multitude 
of different orders of conformity, endless classes, with their 
divisions and subdivisions, the minutest individual of which 
presents a very extensive sphere of conformities, are themselves 
only particular conformities, only rays and points in 
the general sphere, of which man alone occupies the centre, 
and apprehends the immensity.</p> 
<p>From a sense of the general order two sentiments obviously 
result; the one throws us imperceptibly into the bosom of 
the DEITY, and the other recalls us to the perception of our 
wants; the one exhibits to us, as the original cause, a Being 
infinitely intelligent without us; the other, as the ultimate 
end, a very limited being in our own person.  These sentiments 
characterize the spiritual and corporeal powers of man, 
and are the general sources of the pleasure we derive from 
the order of Nature.</p> 
<p>A bee has a sentiment of the order of her hive, yet knows 
not how the ants regulate their nest, though she may have 
seen them labour.  To no purpose would she resort, in the 
event of her hive's being destroyed, to seek refuge, as a republican, 
in the midst of their republic; she would meet from 
them no hospitality, no consideration, no compassion.  Hence 
it follows, that the society of animals could not subsist independent 
of the passions, nor human society independent of 
virtue.  Man alone, of all animals, possesses the sentiment 
of universal order, that of DEITY himself; and by carrying 
over the whole earth the virtues which are the fruits of it, 
whatever may be the differences which prejudice interposes 
between man and man, it is sure of alluring all hearts to itself.</p> 
</div2><div2 type="part" id="d8"> 
<head>OF HARMONY.</head> 
<p>Nature opposes beings to each other, in order to produce 
between them agreeable conformities.  This law has been 
acknowledged from the highest antiquity.  It is to be found 
in many passages of the holy Scriptures.  I produce one from 
the book of Ecclesiasticus:<note type="au" place="foot"><p>Chap. xiii. ver. 34, 
25.</p></note> 'All things are double one 
against another; and He hath made nothing unperfect: one 
thing establisheth the good of another.'</p> 
<p>I consider this great truth as the key of all philosophy. 
It has been fruitful in discovery, as well as that other: 
<pb n="170" id="PieStud170"/><hi rend="italic">Nothing has been created in vain.</hi>  It has been the source 
of 
taste in arts and eloquence.  Out of contraries arise the 
pleasures of vision, hearing, touching, tasting, and all the 
various attractions of beauty.  But from contraries likewise 
arise ugliness, discord, and all disgusting sensations.  Is it 
wonderful that Nature should employ the same causes to 
produce opposite effects?  When she opposes contraries to 
each other, painful affections are excited in us; but when she 
blends them, we are agreeably affected.  From the opposition 
of contraries springs discord, from their union results harmony.</p> 
<p>Let us find in Nature some proofs of this law.  Cold is the 
opposite of heat, light of darkness, earth of water; and the 
harmony of these contrary elements produces effects the most 
delightful; but if cold succeeds rapidly to heat, or heat to 
cold, most vegetables and animals are in danger of perishing. 
The light of the sun is agreeable; but if a black cloud suddenly 
intercepts the lustre of his rays, or if lightning bursts 
from the bosom of a dark night, the eye undergoes a painful 
sensation.</p> 
<p>Nature opposes, at sea, the white foam of the billows to the 
black colour of the rocks, to announce to mariners from afar 
the danger of shallows.  She frequently presents to them 
forms analogous to destruction, such as those of ferocious 
animals, edifices in ruins, or the keels of ships turned upward. 
She even extracts from these awful forms hollow noises resembling 
groans, and broken off by long intervals of silence. 
She employs also those clashing oppositions and ominous 
signs to express the characters of savage and dangerous animals. 
The lion strolling through the solitudes of Africa announces 
his approach by roarings resembling thunder.  The 
vivid and instantaneous flashes of fire, which dart from his 
eyes in the dark, exhibit besides the appearance of lightning. 
During the winter season the howlings of wolves in the forests 
of the north resemble the whistling of the winds among 
trees; the cries of birds of prey are shrill, piercing, and now 
and then interrupted by hollow notes.  Nay, some emit the 
sounds of a human being in pain.  Such is the lom, a species 
of sea-fowl, which feeds on the shelvy coasts of Lapland,<note type="au" 
place="foot"><p>See John Sch'ffer's History of Lapland.</p></note> on 
the dead bodies of animals thrown ashore: he cries like a 
man drowning.</p> 
<pb n="171" id="PieStud171"/><p>Noxious insects exhibit the same oppositions and signals 
of destruction.  The gnat, thirsting after human blood, announces 
himself to the eye by the white points on his brown-coloured body, and to the ear by his shrill notes, which disturb 
the tranquillity of the grove; the carnivorous wasp is 
speckled with black stripes on a yellow ground; and the insects 
which attack our persons more immediately, are distinguished 
by glaring oppositions of colour to the field on which 
they settle.</p> 
<p>But when two countraries come to be blended, the combination 
produces pleasure, beauty, and harmony.  I call the instant 
and the point of their union <hi rend="italic">harmonic expression.</hi>  This 
is the only principle I have perceived in Nature, for the elements 
themselves, as we have seen, are not simple; they 
always present accords formed of two contraries to analyses 
multiplied without end.  Thus the gentlest temperature, and 
the most favourable to every species of vegetation, are those 
of the seasons in which the cold is blended with heat, as 
spring and autumn.  They are then productive of two saps 
in trees, which the strongest heats of summer do not effect. 
The most agreeable production of light and darkness is perceptible 
at those seasons when they melt into each other, 
and form what painters call the <hi rend="italic">clear-obscure</hi> and <hi rend="italic">half-lights.</hi> 
Hence the most interesting hours of the day are those of 
morning and evening; when the shade and light strive for 
the mastery of the azure fields.  The most lovely prospects 
are those in which land and water are lost in each other; this 
suggested that observation of honest Plutarch, namely, that 
the pleasantest land-journeys are those along the shore of the 
sea; and the most delightful voyages those which are coasting 
along the land.  You will observe these same harmonies 
result from savours and sounds the most opposite, in the 
pleasures of the palate and of the ear.</p> 
<p>We shall proceed to examine the uniformity of this law, in 
the very principles by which Nature gives us the first sensations 
of her works, viz. colours, forms, and motions.</p> 
</div2><div2 type="part" id="d9"> 
<head>OF COLOURS.</head> 
<p>Colours, say naturalists, are refractions of light on bodies, 
demonstrated by the prism, which, by breaking a ray of the 
sun, decompounds it into seven coloured rays, displaying 
themselves in the following order: red, orange, yellow, 
<pb n="172" id="PieStud172"/>green, blue, indigo, and violet.  These are, as they will 
have it, the seven primitive colours; but as we do not know 
what is primitive in Nature, I shall content myself with a 
few reflections on the number and order of those seven pretended 
primitive colours.</p> 
<p>First, it is evident four of these are compounded; for 
orange is made up of yellow and red; green of yellow and 
blue; violet of blue and red; and indigo is only a tint of 
blue surcharged with black.  This reduces the solar colours 
to three primordial; namely, yellow, red, and blue; to which 
if we add white, the colour of light, and black, the privation 
of it, we shall have five simple colours, with which may be 
compounded all imaginable shades of colour.</p> 
<p>I must here observe, that our philosophical machinery 
deceives us with its affectation of superior intelligence, not 
only in ascribing false elements to Nature, as when the prism 
displays compound for primitive colours, but by stripping her 
of such as are true; for how many white and black bodies 
must be reckoned colourless, considering that this same 
prism does not exhibit their tints in the decomposition of 
the solar ray!</p> 
<p>This instrument leads us farther into an error respecting 
the natural order of these very colours, by making the red 
ray the first in the series, and the violet ray the last.  The 
order of colours in the prism, therefore, is only a triangular 
decomposition of a ray of cylindrical light, the two extremes 
of which, red and violet, participate the one of the other, 
without terminating it; so that the principle of colours, which 
is the white ray and its progressive decomposition, is no longer 
manifested in it.  I believe it is even possible to cut a crystal 
with so many angles as would give to the refractions of the 
solar ray an order entirely different, and multiply the pretended 
primitive colours far beyond the number seven.  The 
authority of such a polyedron would be as respectable as 
that of the prism, if the algebraists were to apply to it a few 
calculations, somewhat obscure, with a seasoning of the 
corpuscular philosophy, as they have done with regard to 
the effects of the triangular instrument.</p> 
<p>We shall employ a method, not quite so learned, to convey 
an idea of the generation of colours, and the decomposition 
of the solar ray.  Instead of examining them in a prism of 
glass, we shall consider them in the heavens, and there we 
<pb n="173" id="PieStud173"/>shall behold the five primordial colours unfold themselves in 
the order which we have indicated.</p> 
<p>In a fine summer's night, when the sky is loaded only 
with some light vapours, sufficient to stop and to refract the 
rays of the sun, walk out into an open plain, where the first 
fires of Aurora may be perceptible.  You will first observe 
the horizon whiten at the spot where she is to make her 
appearance; and this radiance, from its colour, has procured 
for it, in the French language, the name of <hi rend="italic">aube,</hi> (the dawn,) 
from the Latin word <hi rend="italic">alba,</hi> white.  This whiteness insensibly 
ascends in the heavens, assuming a tint of yellow some degrees 
above the horizon; the yellow as it rises passes into 
orange; and this shade of orange rises upward into the lively 
vermilion, which extends as far as the zenith.  From that 
point you will perceive in the heavens behind you the violet 
succeeding the vermilion, then the azure, after it the deep 
blue or indigo colour, and, last of all, the black, quite to the 
westward.</p> 
<p>Though this display of colours presents a multitude of 
intermediate shades, which rapidly succeed each other, yet 
at the moment the sun is going to exhibit his disk, the 
dazzling white is visible in the horizon, the pure yellow at 
an elevation of 45 degrees; the fire colour in the zenith; 
the pure blue 45 degrees under it, toward the west; and in 
the very west the dark veil of night still lingering on the 
horizon.  I think I have remarked this progression between 
the tropics, where there is scarcely any horizontal refraction 
to make the light prematurely encroach on the darkness, as 
in our climates.</p> 
<p>Sometimes the trade-winds, from the north-east or south-east, blow there, card the clouds through each other, then 
sweep them to the west, crossing and recrossing them over 
one another, like the osiers interwoven in a transparent basket. 
They throw over the sides of this chequered work the 
clouds which are not employed in the contexture, roll them 
up into enormous masses, as white as snow, draw them out 
along their extremities in the form of a crupper, and pile them 
upon each other, moulding them into the shape of mountains, 
caverns, and rocks; afterwards, as evening approaches, 
they grow somewhat calm, as if afraid of deranging their 
own workmanship.  When the sun sets behind this magnificent 
netting, a multitude of luminous rays are transmitted 
<pb n="174" id="PieStud174"/>through the interstices, which produce such an effect, that 
the two sides of the lozenge illuminated by them have the 
appearance of being girt with gold, and the other two in the 
shade seem tinged with ruddy orange.  Four or five divergent 
streams of light, emanated from the setting sun up to the 
zenith, clothe with fringes of gold the undeterminate summits 
of this celestial barrier, and strike with the reflexes of 
their fires the pyramids of the collateral aerial mountains, 
which then appear to consist of silver and vermilion.  At 
this moment of the evening are perceptible, amidst their redoubled 
ridges, a multitude of valleys extending into infinity, 
and distinguishing themselves at their opening by some shade 
of flesh or of rose colour.</p> 
<p>These celestial valleys present in their different contours 
inimitable tints of white, melting away into white, or shades 
lengthening themselves out without mixing over other shades. 
You see, here and there, issuing from the cavernous sides of 
those mountains, tides of light precipitating themselves, in 
ingots of gold and silver, over rocks of coral.  Here it is a 
gloomy rock, pierced through and through, disclosing, beyond 
the aperture, the pure azure of the firmament; there 
it is an extensive strand, covered with sands of gold, stretching 
over the rich ground of heaven; poppy-coloured, scarlet, 
and green as the emerald.</p> 
<p>The reverberation of those western colours diffuses itself 
over the sea, whose azure billows it glazes with saffron and 
purple.  The mariners, leaning over the gunwale of the ship, 
admire in silence those aerial landscapes.  Sometimes this 
sublime spectacle presents itself to them at the hour of prayer, 
and seems to invite them to lift up their hearts with their 
voices to the heavens.  It changes every instant into forms 
as variable as the shades, presenting celestial colours and 
forms which no pencil can pretend to imitate, and no language 
can describe.</p> 
<p>Travellers who have, at various seasons, ascended to the 
summits of the highest mountains on the globe, never could 
perceive, in the clouds below them, any thing but a gray and 
lead-coloured surface, similar to that of a lake.  The sun, 
notwithstanding, illuminated them with his whole light; 
and his rays might there combine all the laws of refraction 
to which our systems of physics have subjected them. 
Hence not a single shade of colour is employed in vain, 
<pb n="175" id="PieStud175"/>through the universe; those celestial decorations being made 
for the level of the earth, their magnificent point of view 
taken from the habitation of man.</p> 
<p>These admirable concerts of lights and forms, manifest 
only in the lower region of the clouds the least illuminated by 
the sun, are produced by laws with which I am totally unacquainted. 
But the whole are reducible to five colours: yellow, 
a generation from white; red, a deeper shade of yellow; blue, 
a strong tint of red; and black, the extreme tint of blue.  This 
progression cannot be doubted, on observing in the morning 
the expansion of the light in the heavens.  You there see 
those five colours, with their intermediate shades, generating 
each other nearly in this order: white, sulphur yellow, lemon 
yellow, yolk of egg yellow, orange, aurora colour, poppy red, 
full red, carmine red, purple, violet, azure, indigo, and black. 
Each colour seems to be only a strong tint of that which 
precedes it, and a faint tint of that which follows; thus the 
whole together appear to be only modulations of a progression, 
of which white is the first term, and black the last.</p> 
<p>Indeed trade cannot be carried on to any advantage, with 
the Negroes, Tartars, Americans, and East Indians, but 
through the medium of red cloths.  The testimonies of travellers 
are unanimous respecting the preference universally 
given to this colour.  I have indicated the universality of 
this taste, merely to demonstrate the falsehood of the philosophic 
axiom, that tastes are arbitrary, or that there are in 
Nature no laws for beauty, and that our tastes are the effects 
of prejudice.  The direct contrary of this is the truth; prejudice 
corrupts our natural tastes, otherwise the same over the 
whole earth.</p> 
<p>With red Nature heightens the brilliant parts of the most 
beautiful flowers.  She has given a complete clothing of it 
to the rose, the queen of the garden: and bestowed this tint 
on the blood, the principle of life in animals: she invests most 
of the feathered race, in India, with a plumage of this colour, 
especially in the season of love; and there are few birds without 
some shades, at least, of this rich hue.  Some preserve 
entirely the gray or brown ground of their plumage, but 
glazed over with red, as if they had been rolled in carmine; 
others are besprinkled with red, as if you had blown a scarlet 
powder over them.</p> 
<p>The red colour, situated in the midst of the five primordial 
<pb n="176" id="PieStud176"/>colours, is the harmonic expression of them by way of excellence; 
and the result of the union of two contraries, light and 
darkness.  There are, besides agreeable tints, compounded 
of the oppositions of extremes.  For example, of the second 
and fourth colour, that is, of yellow and blue, is formed green, 
which constitutes a very beautiful harmony, and ought, 
perhaps, to possess the second rank in beauty, among colours, 
as it possesses the second in their generation.  Nay, green appears 
to many, if not the most beautiful tint, at least the most 
lovely, because it is less dazzling than red, and more congenial 
to the eye.</p> 
<p>Colours may also have a powerful influence on the passions; 
and, as well as their harmonies, may be referred to the moral 
affections.  For example, making red the point of departure, 
which is the harmonic colour supereminently, and proceeding 
towards white in an ascending progression, the nearer 
you approach to this first term, the more lively and gay are 
the colours.  You will have in succession the poppy, orange, 
yellow, lemon, sulphur, and white.  On the contrary, the 
farther you proceed from red towards black, the sadder and 
more lugubrious are the colours; for this is the progression; 
purple, violet, blue, indigo, and black.</p> 
<p>In the harmonies to be formed, on both sides, by the union 
of opposite colours, the more that the tints of the ascending 
progression predominate, the more lively will be the harmonies 
produced; and the contrary will take place as the colours of 
the descending harmony shall prevail.  From this harmonic 
effect, green, compounded of yellow and blue, is so much 
more gay, as the yellow has the ascendant, and sad in proportion 
as the blue predominates.</p> 
<p>From this harmonic influence, white transfuses most gayety 
into all other tints, because it is light itself.  Nay, it produces, 
from opposition, a most delightful effect in the harmonies,  
which I call melancholy; for blended with violet, it 
gives the delicious hue of the lilac flower; mixed with blue,  
it makes azure; and with black, produces pearl-gray; but 
melted away into red, it exhibits the rose-colour, that enchanting 
tint, the flower of life.  But according to the predominance 
of black in gay colours, the effect produced is 
more mournful than that of unmixed black.  This becomes 
perceptible on blending it with yellow, orange, and red, 
thereby rendered dull and gloomy colours.  Red gives life 
<pb n="177" id="PieStud177"/>wherever it is infused, as white communicates gayety, and 
black sadness.</p> 
<p>It would be ridiculous to affect ignorance of the objections 
which may be started against the universality of these principles. 
We have represented white as a gay, and black as 
a sad colour.  Nevertheless, certain negro nations represent 
the devil as white; the inhabitants of the peninsula of India, 
in token of mourning, rub their forehead and temples with 
the powder of sandal-wood, the colour of which is a yellowish 
white.  The navigator La Barbinois says, that white is 
the colour of mourning among the Chinese.  From these instances 
it might be concluded, that the feeling of colour 
must be arbitrary, as it is not the same in all nations.</p> 
<p>I venture to offer the following reply to these objections. 
The black nations of Africa and Asia prefer white women 
to those of every other tint.  If there be negro nations who 
paint the devil white, it is from the strong feeling they have 
of the tyranny the whites exercise over them.  White, accordingly, 
having become with them a political colour, ceases 
to be a natural one.  Besides, the white of the devil is not 
a white beautifully harmonious, like that of the human 
figure, but a dead chalk white, such as that with which our 
painters illuminate the figures of phantoms and ghosts in 
their magical and infernal scenes.</p> 
<p>If this dazzling colour is the expression of mourning 
among the Indians and Chinese, the reason is, it contrasts 
harshly with the black skin of those nations.  The Indians 
are black.  The skin of the southern Chinese is much sun-burnt.  They derive their religion and leading customs from 
India, the inhabitants of which are black.  Their outward 
garments are of a gloomy colour; and the ornamental furniture 
of their houses consists of beautiful black varnished 
ware.  White must, therefore, produce a harsh dissonance 
with their furniture, dress, and above all, with the dusky 
colour of their skin.</p> 
<p>If those nations wore a black habit, in mourning, as we 
do, be their colour ever so deep, it would not form a clashing 
opposition in their dress.  The expression of grief, accordingly, 
is precisely the same with them as with us.  For if 
we in mourning oppose the black colour of our clothes to the 
white of our skin, thence to produce a funereal dissonance, 
the southern nations oppose the white colour of their garments 
<pb n="178" id="PieStud178"/>to the dusky colour of their skin, to produce the same 
effect.</p> 
<p>This variety of taste confirms the universality of the principles 
we have laid down respecting the causes of harmony 
and dissonance.  It farther demonstrates, that the agreeableness 
or disagreeableness of a colour resides not in one single 
shade, but in the harmony, or in the clashing contrast, of 
two opposite colours.</p> 
</div2><div2 type="part" id="d10"> 
<head>OF FORMS.</head> 
<p>If I am not mistaken, the principles of these, as of colours, 
are reducible to five, the line, triangle, circle, ellipse, and 
parabola.</p> 
<p>The line generates all forms, as the ray of light does all 
colours.  It goes on like the other, in its generations, step by 
step, producing first, by three fractions, the triangle, which of 
all others contains the smallest surfaces under the greatest 
of circuits.  The triangle afterward, composed itself of three 
triangles at the centre, produces the square, which consists 
of four triangles from the central point; the pentagon, which 
consists of five; the hexagon, which consists of six; and so 
of the rest of the polygons, up to the circle, composed of a 
multitude of triangles, whose summits are at its centre, and 
the bases at its circumference: and which, contrary to the 
triangle, contains the greatest of surfaces under the smallest 
of peripheries.  The form which has, hitherto, always been 
going on progressively, commencing with the line, relatively 
to a centre, up to the circle, afterwards deviates from it, and 
produces the ellipse, then the parabola, and finally all the 
other widened curves, the equations of which may all be referred 
to this last.  So that, under this aspect, the indefinite 
line has no common centre: the triangle has three points in 
its bounding lines, which have a common centre; the square 
has four; the pentagon five; the hexagon six; and the 
circle has all the points of its circumference regulated conformably 
to one common and only centre.  The ellipse begins 
to deviate from this regulation, and has two centres; and the 
parabola, as well as the other curves, which are analogous to 
it, have centres innumerable contained in their several axes, 
from which they remove farther and farther, forming something 
like funnels.</p> 
<p>On the supposition of this ascending generation of forms, 
<pb n="179" id="PieStud179"/>from the line, through the triangle, up to the circle; and 
their descending generation, from the circle, through the 
ellipse, to the parabola, I deduce, from these five elementary 
forms, all the forms of Nature; as, with five primordial colours, 
I compose all the possible shades of colour.</p> 
<p>The line presents the slenderest form, the circle the fullest, 
and the parabola the most obliquely fluted.  In this progression,  
the circle, which occupies the middle between these two 
extremes, is the most beautiful of all elementary forms, as red 
in the most beautiful primordial colour.  I presume not to say, 
that this form must be the most beautiful, because it is the 
figure of the stars, which, however, would be no contemptible 
reason; but, to employ only the testimony of our senses, it is 
the most grateful of both eye and touch; and the most susceptible 
of motion; finally, it is considered as most conformable 
to the taste of all nations, who employ it in their ornaments 
and architecture; and it is particularly conformable to 
the taste of children, who prefer it to every other, in the instruments 
of their amusement.</p> 
<p>It is remarkable, that these five elementary forms have the 
same analogies to each other which the five primordial colours 
have among themselves; so that if you proceed to their ascending 
generation, from the sphere toward the line, you will 
have forms angular, lively, and gay, which shall terminate in 
the straight line.  If, on the contrary, you descend from the 
sphere to the excavations of the parabola, you will be presented 
with a gradation of cavernous forms, so frightful in abysses 
and precipices.</p> 
<p>Farther, if you join the elementary forms to the primordial 
colours, term for term, you will observe their principal character 
mutually strengthen each other, at least in the two 
extremes, and in the harmonic expression of the centre: for 
the first two terms will give the white ray, that of light itself; 
the circular form, united to the red colour, will produce a 
figure analogous to the rose, composed of spherical portions, 
with carmine tints, and, from the effect of this double harmony, 
deemed the most beautiful of flowers.  Finally, black, 
added to the vacuity of the parabola, increases the gloom of 
retreating and cavernous forms.</p> 
<p>With these fine elementary forms may be composed figures 
as agreeable as the shades produced from the harmonies of 
the five primordial colours.  So that the more there shall 
<pb n="180" id="PieStud180"/>enter, into those mixed figures, of the two ascending terms 
of the progression, the more light and gay such figures will 
be; and the more the two descending terms shall predominate, 
the more heavy and dull will be the forms.  Thus, the 
form will be more elegant, as the first term, the straight line 
shall have the predominance.  For example, the column 
gives us pleasure, because it is a long cylinder, with the 
circle for its basis, and two straight lines, or a long quadrilateral 
figure, for its elevation.  But the palm-tree, of which 
it is an imitation, pleases still more, because the stellated 
and radiating forms of its palms, likewise taken from the 
straight line, constitute a very agreeable opposition with the 
roundness of its stem; and if to this you unite the harmonic 
form by way of excellence, namely, the circular, you will 
add inexpressibly to the grace of this beautiful tree.  This, 
likewise, Nature, who knows much more of the matter than 
we, has taken care to do, by suspending, at the basis of its 
divergent boughs, sometimes the oval date, and sometimes 
the rounded cocoa-nut.</p> 
<p>In general, as often as you employ the circular form, you 
will greatly enhance the agreeableness of it, by uniting it 
with the two contraries of which it is composed; for you will 
then have a complete elementary progression.  The circular 
form alone presents but one expression, the most beautiful 
of all, in truth; but united to its two extremes, it forms, if I 
may so express myself, an entire thought.</p> 
<p>It is, farther, from these harmonies, that long ridges of  
mountains, overtopped by lofty peaks of a pyramidical form, 
separated by deep valleys, delight us by their gracefulness 
and majesty.  If to these you add rivers meandering below, 
radiating poplars waving on their banks, flocks of cattle and 
shepherds, you will have vales similar to that of Tempe. 
The circular forms of the mountains, in such a landscape, 
are placed between their extremes, namely, the prominency 
of the rocks, and the cavity of the valleys.  But if you separate  
from it the harmonic expressions, that is, the circular 
wavings of those mountains, together with their peaceful 
inhabitants, and allow the extremes only to remain, you will 
then have the dreary prospect of Cape Horn; angular, perpendicular 
rocks, hanging over fathomless abysses.</p> 
<p>If to these you add oppositions of colour, as that of snow 
on the summits of the dusky rocks, the foam of the billows 
<pb n="181" id="PieStud181"/>breaking on the lurid shore, a pale sun in a gloomy sky, 
torrents of rain in the midst of summer, tremendous squalls 
of wind succeeded by sullen calms, a European vessel, on 
her way to spread desolation over the islands of the South 
Sea,<note type="ed" place="foot"><p>Would not the effect of this dreadful 
picture have been considerably strengthened, had our Author represented his 
European vessel as attempting to double Cape Horn <hi rend="italic">on her return</hi> from 
spreading devastation over the South Seas, and making shipwreck on that coast, 
<hi rend="italic">after</hi> the scene of blood was acted?  In this case we should have had 
the striking and instructive representation of the connexion between Human 
Guilt and Divine Justice; of the clashing collision of criminality and 
vengeance.&mdash;H. H.</p></note> running upon a rock when it is beginning to grow 
dark, 
firing from time to time guns, the signal of distress, the noise  
of which the echoes of those horrid deserts reverberate, the 
terrified Patagonian running in amazement to his cave; and 
you will have a complete view of that land of desolation, 
covered over with the shades of death.</p> 
</div2><div2 type="part" id="d11"> 
<head>OF MOVEMENTS.</head> 
<p>It remains that I suggest a few reflections on the subject 
of motions.  Of these we shall also distinguish five which are 
fundamental: self-motion, or the rotation of a body round 
itself, which supposes no change of place, and is the principle 
of all motion; such is, perhaps, that of the sun; after that, 
the perpendicular, circular, horizontal, and state of rest.  All 
movements may be referred to these five.  Nay, geometricians, 
who represent them likewise by figures, suppose the 
circular motion to be generated of the perpendicular and horizontal, 
and, to use their language, produced by the diagonal 
of their squares.</p> 
<p>I shall not insist on the analogies which actually exist between 
the white colour, the straight line, and self-motion, or 
rotation; the red colour, the spherical form, and circular 
motion; between darkness, vacuity, and rest.  I leave to the 
reader the pleasure of following up this idea, and forming to 
himself, with these elements of Nature, harmonies the most 
enchanting, with the additional charm of novelty.  I shall 
confine myself, at present, to a few hasty observations respecting 
motion.</p> 
<p>Of all movements, the harmonic or circular motion is 
the most agreeable.  Nature has diffused it over most of her 
works, and rendered even the vegetables in the earth susceptible 
of it.  Our plains represent this, when the winds form, 
<pb n="182" id="PieStud182"/>on the meadow or corn-field, a series of undulations, resembling 
the waves of the sea; or when they gently agitate, on 
the sides of the lofty mountains, the towering tops of the 
trees, waving them about in segments of a circle.  Most birds 
form portions of great circles as they play through the airy 
expanse, and seem to take pleasure in tracing, as they fly, 
curves and spiral motions.  Nature has bestowed this agreeable 
style of flying on many species of the feathered race, 
not otherwise to be prized for their song or plumage.  Such 
is the flight of the swallow.</p> 
<p>The case differs with respect to the movements of ferocious 
or noxious animals.  They advance leaping, springing, and 
join to slow movements others violently rapid; as in the 
motion of the cat watching a mouse: those of the tiger are 
exactly similar.  The same discordancy is observable in the 
flight of carnivorous birds.  The species of owl called the 
grand-duke floats through a tranquil sky, as if the wind carried 
him this way and that.  Tempests present, in the heavens, 
the same characters of destruction.  You sometimes perceive 
stormy clouds moving in opposite directions; now they 
fly like lightning, while others remain immoveable as the rock. 
In the tremendous hurricanes of the West Indies, the explosion 
is always preceded and followed by a dead calm.</p> 
<p>The more a body possesses of self-motion, or rotation, the 
more agreeable it appears, especially when united to the harmonic 
or circular motion.  From the effect of self-motion, 
every moral idea out of the question, animals interest us more 
than vegetables, because they have the principle of motion 
within themselves.</p> 
<p>Motion is the expression of life.  In this you see why Nature 
has multiplied the causes of it in all her works.  One of 
the great charms of a landscape is objects in motion; but this 
the pictures of most of our great masters frequently fail to 
express.  If you except those representing tempests, everywhere 
else their forests and meadows are motionless, and the 
water of their lakes congealed.  Yet the inversion of the 
leaves of trees presenting a gray or white underside; the 
undulations of the grass in valleys, and on the ridges of 
mountains; those which ruffle the surface of the waters, and 
the foam which whitens the shores, recall, with inexpressible 
pleasure, in a burning summer scene, the breath so gentle 
and cooling of the zephyrs.  To these might be added, with 
<pb n="183" id="PieStud183"/>infinite grace and powerful effect, the movements peculiar to 
the animals which inhabit them; it might be possible even 
to represent the motion and weight of a loaded carriage toiling 
up a hill, by expressing the dust of the crushed pebbles 
rising up behind its wheels.  Nay, I think the effects of the 
singing of birds, and of the echoes, might be rendered perceptible, by the 
expression of certain characters not necessary 
here to unfold.</p> 
<p>So far are our painters, those even whose talents are conspicuous, 
from paying attention to accessories so agreeable, 
that they omit them in subjects of which those accessories 
form the principal character.  For example, if they represent 
a chariot at full speed, they exhibit every spoke of the wheels. 
The horses, indeed, are galloping, but the chariot is immoveable. 
The wheels of a carriage, however, running with a 
rapid motion, present but one single surface; all their spokes 
are confounded to the eye.  I have seen, in modern pictures, 
machines in motion, wrestlers and warriors in action, but in 
no one of them did I ever find attention paid to these effects 
so simple, yet so expressive of the truth of Nature.  Our 
painters consider them as petty details, beneath the notice of 
a man of genius.  Nevertheless, they are traits of character.</p> 
<p>Details, frequently traits of character, are not to be despised. 
If our painters and sculptors withhold the expression 
of motion to landscapes, wrestlers, and chariots in the course, 
they bestow it on the portraits and statues of our great men. 
They represent them as angels sounding the alarm to judgment, 
with flowing hair, wild wandering eyes, the muscles 
of the face convulsed, and garments fluttering in the wind. 
These, they tell us, are the expressions of genius.  But persons 
of genius, and great men, are not bedlamites.  I have 
seen some of their portraits, on antiques, which represent them 
with a serene and tranquil air.  It is the property of inanimate 
matter, vegetables, and animals, to obey the movements 
of Nature; but a great man should have his emotions under 
command, and only as he exercises this empire does he merit 
the name of Great.</p> 
<p>I have just hinted the necessity of <hi rend="italic">conformity</hi> to artists, who 
will find it much more difficult to execute, than it is easy for 
me to criticise.  God forbid that I should give a moment's pain 
to men whose works have given me exquisite pleasure.  It 
was simply my wish to stimulate the ingenious to tread in 
<pb n="184" id="PieStud184"/>the steps of Nature, and pursue that track as far as genius 
can carry them.</p> 
<p>This would be the place to speak of music, for sounds are 
movements merely: but persons of much ability have treated 
this noble art with consummate skill.  If any foreign testimony 
could farther confirm me in the principles I have 
hitherto laid down, it is that of musicians, who have restricted 
harmonic expression to three sounds.  I might, like them, 
reduce to three terms the elementary generations of colours, 
forms, and motions; but they have omitted, in their fundamental 
basis, the generative principle, <hi rend="italic">sound,</hi> properly so 
called, and the negative term, silence; especially as this last 
produces powerful effects in the movements of music.</p> 
<p>These proportions might be extended to the progressions 
of tasting; the most agreeable of them have similar generations, 
as we know by experience to be the case with regard 
to most fruits, whose different stages of maturity successively 
present five savours, namely, the acid, sweet, sugary, vinous, 
and bitter.  They are acid while growing, sweet as they 
ripen, sugary in a state of perfect maturity, vinous in their 
fermentation, and bitter in a state of dryness.  Farther, we 
should find the most agreeable of these savours, namely, the 
sugary, is that which occupies the middle place in this progression, 
of which it is the harmonic term; that, from its 
nature, it forms new harmonies, by a combination with its 
extremes; for the beverages most grateful to the palate consist 
of acid and sugar, as the refreshing liquors prepared with 
citron-juice; or of sugar and bitter, such as coffee.</p> 
<p>Though I have a thorough conviction of the truth of these 
elementary generations, it would not, however, surprise me, 
should many of my readers dissent from what I have advanced. 
Our natural tastes are perverted by prejudices 
which determine our physical sensations, much more powerfully 
than these last give direction to our moral affections. 
I shall endeavour, in another place, to unfold the causes of 
these moral affections.  They stand in connexion with laws 
more sublime than any physical laws: while these last amuse 
our senses, the others speak to the heart, and calmly admonish 
us, that man is ordained to a much higher destination. 
All I have hitherto said on this subject, or hereafter may say, 
is reducible to this great law: Every thing in Nature is 
formed of contraries: from their harmonies the sentiment of 
<pb n="185" id="PieStud185"/>pleasure results, and out of their oppositions issues the 
sentiment 
of pain.</p> 
<p>This law extends also to morals.  Every truth, those of 
fact excepted, is the result of two contrary ideas.  It follows, 
that as often as we decompound a truth, by dialectics, we 
divide it into the two ideas of which it is constituted; and 
if we confine ourselves to one of its elementary ideas, as to 
a detached principle, and deduce consequences from it, we 
shall convert it into a source of endless disputation; for the 
other elementary idea, if pursued, will supply consequences 
diametrically opposite, themselves susceptible of contradictory 
decompositions without end.  The schools are admirably 
adapted to instruct us how to manage this process, and 
thither are we sent to form our judgement.</p> 
<p>All disorders, both physical and moral, are but the clashing 
opposition of two contraries.  If man would pay attention 
to this law, wranglings and mistakes would speedily cease; 
for every thing being composed of contraries, whoever affirms 
a simple proposition is only half right, as the contrary proposition 
has equally an existence in nature.</p> 
<p>There is perhaps in the world but one intellectual truth, 
pure, simple, and without contradiction.  Those who have 
denied it only support their negation on the apparent disorders 
of Nature, the extreme principles of which alone they 
contemplated; so that they have not demonstrated that 
God did not exist, but that He was not intelligent or good. 
Their error proceeds from their ignorance of natural laws. 
Besides, their arguments have been mostly founded on the 
disorders of men, who exist in an order different from that of 
Nature, and who alone of all beings endowed with perception 
have been committed to their own direction.</p> 
<p>As to the nature of GOD, I know that faith itself presents 
Him to us as the harmonic principle, not only with relation 
to all that surrounds Him, of which he is the Creator and 
Mover, but even in his essence divided into three persons. 
A single act of his will called us into being; the slightest 
communication of his works is sufficient to illuminate our 
reason; but I have a thorough persuasion that if the smallest 
ray of his divine essence were to communicate itself directly 
to us, in a human body, we must be annihilated.</p> 
<pb n="186" id="PieStud186"/> 
</div2><div2 type="part" id="d12"> 
<head>OF CONSONANCES.</head> 
<p>Consonances are repetitions of the same harmonies.  They 
increase our pleasures by multiplying and transferring the 
enjoyment of them to new scenes.  They farther communicate 
pleasure by convincing us that the same Intelligence 
has presided over the different plans of Nature, presenting 
throughout similar harmonies.  Consonances accordingly 
confer more pleasure than simple harmonies, as they convey 
the sentiments of extension and divinity, so congenial to the 
human soul.  Natural objects excite satisfaction only as they 
awaken intellectual feeling.</p> 
<p>The most beautiful harmonies are those which have the 
most consequences.  Nothing is more beautiful than the sun, 
nothing in nature so frequently repeated as his form and 
light.  He is variously reflected by refractions of the air, 
which exhibit him above the horizon before he is actually 
risen, and after he has set; by the parhelia, which reflect 
his disk sometimes twice or thrice in the misty clouds of the 
north; by the rainy clouds, in which his refracted rays trace 
an arch shaded with a thousand various colours; and by the 
waters, whose reflexes exhibit him where is not, in the 
bosom of meadows, amidst flowers besprinkled with dew, and 
in the shade of green forests.  The dull and inert earth, too, 
reflects him in the specular particles of gravels, micas, crystals, 
and rocks.  It presents to us the form of his disk and 
rays in the disks and petals of the myriads of radiated flowers 
with which it is covered.  In a word, this beautiful star has 
multiplied himself into infinity with unknown varieties, in 
the innumerable stars of the firmament, which he discovers 
to us when he quits our horizon; as if he had withdrawn 
himself from the consonances of the earth only to display to 
the delighted eye those of heaven.</p> 
<p>From this law of consonance it follows that what is best 
and beautiful in Nature, is also common and most frequently 
repeated.  To it we must ascribe the varieties of species in 
each genus, the more numerous as they genus is useful. 
There is no family in the vegetable kingdom so necessary as 
the gramineous, on which subsist not only quadrupeds but 
birds and insects, and there is no one whose species are so 
varied.  The millet of Africa, the maize of Brazil, the rice 
of Asia, the palm-sago of the Moluccas, the trunks of which 
<pb n="187" id="PieStud187"/>are filled with alimentary flour, are in consonance with the 
corns of Europe.  We shall find consonances of another kind 
in the same places, as if it had been the intention of Nature 
to multiply her benefits by varying only the form of them, 
without changing almost anything of their qualities.  Thus 
in our gardens, what a delightful and beneficial consonancy 
there is between the orange and citron trees, the apple and 
the pear, the walnut and the filbert; and in our farm-yards 
between the horse and the ass, the goose and the duck, the 
cow and the she-goat.</p> 
<p>Although each genus is in consonancy with itself from 
difference of sex, there are between the sexes contrasts giving 
energy to their loves from the very opposition of contraries, 
from which all harmony takes its birth; but without the 
general consonancy of form between them, sensible beings 
of the same genus never would have approached each other. 
Without this, one sex would have remained a stranger to the 
other.  Before each could have observed what the other possessed 
that corresponded to its necessities, the time of reflection 
would have absorbed that of love, and perhaps extinguished 
desire.  It is consonancy which attracts, and contrast 
which unites them.  There is not in any one genus an animal 
of one sex entirely different from one of the other in exterior 
forms; and if such differences are actually found, as certain 
naturalists pretend, in several species of fishes and insects, 
I am persuaded Nature placed the habitation of male and 
female very close to each other, and planted their nuptial 
couch near their cradle.</p> 
<p>There is a consonancy of forms more intimate still than 
every that of the two sexes, I mean the duplicity of the organs 
of each individual.  Every animal is double.  If you consider 
his two eyes, his two nostrils, his two ears, the number of his 
legs and arms disposed by pairs, you would be tempted to say, 
here are two animals glued the one to the other, and united 
under the same skin.  Nay, the single parts of his body, as 
the head, tail, and tongue, appear to be formed of two halves, 
compacted together by seams.  It is not so with the members 
properly so called: for example, one hand, one ear, one eye, 
cannot be divided into two similar halves; but the duplicity 
of form on the parts of the body distinguishes them essentially 
from the members; for the part of the body is double, and 
the member is single; the former is always single and alone, 
<pb n="188" id="PieStud188"/>and the latter always repeated.  Thus the head and tail of 
an animal are parts of its body, and the legs and ears are 
members.</p> 
<p>This most wonderful law of Nature destroys all the hypotheses 
which introduce chance into the organization of beings; 
for independently of its harmonies, it doubles the proofs of a 
Providence, who did not deem it sufficient to give one principal 
organ to animals adapted to each element in particular, 
such as the eye for the light, the ear for sound, the foot for 
the ground, but determined that they should have each of 
those organs by pairs.</p> 
<p>Certain sages have considered this admirable duplication 
as a predisposition of Providence, that the animal might 
always be able to supply the loss of one of the double organs, 
exposed as they are to so many accidents; but the interior parts 
of the body, which at first sight appear to be single, present 
on closer examination a similar duplicity of forms, even in 
the human body, where they are more confounded than in 
other animals.  Thus the five lobes of the lungs, one of which 
has a kind of division; the fissure of the liver; the supernal 
separation of the brain by the duplication of the <hi rend="italic">dura-mater</hi>; 
the <hi rend="italic">septum lucidum,</hi> similar to a leaf of talc, which separates 
the two anterior ventricles of it; the two ventricles of the 
heart; and the divisions of the other <hi rend="italic">viscera</hi> announce this 
double union, and seem to indicate, that <hi rend="italic">the very principle of 
life is the consonance of two similar harmonies.</hi></p> 
<p>From this duplicity of organs there results more utility than 
if they had been single.  Man with two eyes can take in at 
once more than half the horizon, with one only he could 
scarcely have embraced a third part.  Provided with two 
arms he can perform many actions he never could have accomplished 
with but one, such as raising upon his head a 
load of considerable size and weight, and clambering up a 
tree.  Had he been placed upon one leg, not only would his 
position be much more unsteady than on two, but he would 
be unable to walk; his progressive motion would be reduced 
to crawling or hopping, producing discord to the other parts 
of his body, and the variety of soils over which he is destined 
to move.</p> 
<p>If Nature has given a single exterior organ to animals, as 
the tail, it is because its use extends but to a single action, 
to which it is fully equivalent.  Besides, the tail from its situation 
<pb n="189" id="PieStud189"/>is secured against danger, and hardly any but very 
powerful animals have a long tail, as bulls, horses, and lions. 
Rabbits and hares have it very short.  In feeble animals 
which have one of considerable length, as the thornback, it 
is armed with prickles, or else it grows again, if it happens 
to be torn off by an accident, as in the case of a lizard. 
Finally, whatever may be the simplicity of its use, it is formed 
of two similar halves, as the other parts of the body.</p> 
<p>There are other interior consonances, which collect diagonally 
the different organs of the body, to form but one only 
and single animal of its two halves.  I leave to anatomists 
the investigation of this incomprehensible connexion; but 
the cruel experiments every day made on brutes, to discover 
these secret correspondencies of Nature, serve only to spread 
a thick veil over them; and the barbarous means employed 
by our modern physics, have an influence still more fatal on 
the morals of those who practise them; for, together with 
false information, they inspire them with the most atrocious 
of all vices, cruelty.</p> 
<p>If man may presume to put questions to Nature respecting 
the operations she is pleased to conceal, I should prefer the 
road of pleasure to that of pain.  Of the propriety of this sentiment 
I witnessed an instance at a country-seat in Normandy. 
Walking in an adjoining field with a young gentleman, we 
perceived bulls fighting.  He ran to them with his staff brandished, 
and the poor animals instantly gave up their contention.   
He went up to the most ferocious, and began to tickle 
him at the root of the tail.  The animal, whose eyes were 
still inflamed with rage, became motionless, with outstretched 
neck, expanded nostrils, transpiring the air with a satisfaction 
which most amusingly demonstrated the intimate correspondence 
between this extremity of his body and his head.</p> 
<p>The duplicity of organs is farther observable in the essential 
parts of vegetables, as the <hi rend="italic">anther'</hi> of the flowers, which 
are double bodies: in their petals, one half corresponding 
exactly to the other; in the lobes of their seed, &amp;c.  A single 
one of these parts, however, appears sufficient for the expansion 
and generation of the plant.  This observation applies 
to the very leaves, the halves of which are mostly correspondent; 
and if any one recedes from this order, undoubtedly the 
reason is worthy of investigation.</p> 
<p>These facts confirm the distinction between the parts and 
<pb n="190" id="PieStud190"/>members of a body; for in leaves where this duplicity occurs 
the vegetative faculty is usually to be found, which is diffused 
over the body of the vegetable itself; so that if you carefully 
replant those leaves at the proper season, the complete vegetable 
will thence be reproduced.  Perhaps it is because the 
interior organs of the tree are double that the principle of 
vegetative life is diffused even over its slips, which sprout 
again from one branch.  Nay, some have the power of perpetuating 
themselves by cuttings simply.  Of this we have 
a noted instance in the Memoirs of the Academy of Sciences. 
Two sisters became heiresses of an orange-tree; each insisted 
on having it thrown into her allotment.  At length, after 
much wrangling, and neither being disposed to resign her 
claim, it was settled that the tree should be cleft in two, and 
each take her half.  The orange-tree underwent the judgment 
pronounced by Solomon on the child&mdash;it was cleft 
asunder: each sister replanted her own half, and, wonderful 
to be told! the tree which had been separated by unsisterly 
animosity, received a new clothing of bark from the benignant 
hand of Nature.</p> 
<p>This universal consonance of forms suggested to man the 
idea of symmetry.  He has introduced it into most of the 
works of art, particularly architecture, as an essential part of 
order.  To such a degree is it the work of intelligence and 
combination, that I consider it as the principal character by 
which we distinguish organized bodies from such as are not 
so, however regular their assemblage may appear.</p> 
<p>In conformity to these reflections, on considering the globe 
of the earth, I observed that it too presented a duplicity of 
form.  From the beginning it had been my idea that this 
globe, being the production of an Intelligence, order must 
pervade it.  I had discerned the utility of islands, and even 
of banks, and of rocks, to protect the parts of continents most 
exposed to the currents of the ocean, at the extremities of 
which they are always situated.  I had also seen the utility 
of bays, removed from the currents of the ocean, and hollowed 
into deep retreats to shelter the discharge of rivers, and serve, 
by the tranquillity of their waters, as an asylum to the fishes, 
which retire thither to collect the spoils of vegetation there 
disgorged by the rivers.  I had admired them in detail, but 
had formed no conception of their combination.  My mind 
was bewildered, and I should without hesitation have ascribed 
<pb n="191" id="PieStud191"/>the whole to chance, had not the order I perceived in each of 
the parts suggested to me the possibility that it might exist 
also in the totality of the work.</p> 
<p>I shall now display the globe under a new aspect.  The 
reader will pardon a digression which exhibits to him one 
little fragment of the materials I had laid up for a geographical 
structure, but which tends to prove the universality of 
the laws I am endeavouring to establish.</p> 
<p>I first endeavoured to find out consonances between the 
northern and southern halves of the globe, but perceived only 
oppositions; the northern being, if I may so express myself, 
a terrestrial hemisphere, and the southern a maritime, and 
so different from each other, that the winter of one is the 
summer of the other; and the seas of the first hemisphere 
seem to be opposed to the lands and islands scattered over 
the second.  This contrast presented another analogy with 
an organized body, for every organized body has two halves 
in contrast, as there are two in consonance.</p> 
<p>I found in it then something like analogy with an animal, 
whose head should have been to the north, from the attraction 
of the magnet peculiar to our pole, which seems there to fix 
a <hi rend="italic">sensorium,</hi> as in the head of an animal: the heart under 
the line, from the constant heat of the torrid zone, which 
seems to determine this as the region of the heart: finally, 
the excretory organs in the southern part, in which the 
greatest seas, the vast receptacles of the alluvions of continents, 
are situated; and where we likewise find the greatest 
number of volcanoes, which may be considered as the excretory 
organs of the seas, whose bitumens and sulphurs they 
consume.  Besides, the sun, who sojourns five or six days 
longer in the northern hemisphere, seemed to present to me 
a more marked resemblance to the body of an animal, in 
which the heart, the centre of heat, is somewhat nearer to 
the head than to the lower extremities.</p> 
<p>Though these contrasts appeared sufficiently determinate 
to manifest order on the globe, and though I perceived something 
similar in vegetables distinguished into two parts, 
opposite in functions and forms, as the leaves and roots; I 
was afraid of giving scope to my imagination, and attempting 
to generalize the laws of Nature peculiar to each existence, 
by extending them to kingdoms not susceptible of the application. 
But I ceased to doubt of the general order of the 
<pb n="192" id="PieStud192"/>globe, when with two halves in contrast I found two others 
in consonance.  I was astonished, I confess, when I observed 
in its duplicity of forms members exactly repeated on that 
side and on this.</p> 
<p>The globe, considered from east to west, is divided, as all 
organized bodies are, into two similar halves, the Old and 
New World.  Each part mutually corresponds in the eastern 
and western hemispheres.  The lakes of Finland and the 
gulf of Archangel correspond to the lakes of Canada and 
Baffin's Bay; Nova Zembla to Greenland; the Baltic to 
Hudson's Bay; the islands of Great Britain and Ireland, 
which cover the first of these mediterraneans, to the islands 
of Good Fortune and Welcome, which protect the second; 
the Mediterranean, properly so called, to the Gulf of Mexico, 
which is a kind of mediterranean formed in part by islands. 
At the extremity of the Mediterranean we find the isthmus 
of Suez in consonance with the isthmus of Panama, placed 
at the bottom of the gulf of Mexico.  Conjoined by those 
isthmuses the peninsula of Africa presents itself in the Old 
World, and the peninsula of South America in the New. 
The principal rivers of these divisions of the globe front each 
other in like manner; for the Senegal discharges itself into 
the Atlantic directly opposite to the rive of the Amazons. 
Finally, each of these peninsulas, advancing toward the south 
pole, terminates in a cape equally noted for violent tempests,  
the Cape of Good Hope and Cape Horn.</p> 
<p>There are between these two hemispheres many other 
points of consonance on which I shall no longer insist. 
These different particulars, it is admitted, do not correspond 
exactly in the same latitudes; but they are disposed in the 
direction of a spiral line winding from east to west, and extending 
from north to south, so that these corresponding 
points proceed in a regular progression.  They are nearly of 
the same height, setting out from the north, as the Baltic and 
Hudson's Bay; and they lengthen in America, in proportion 
as it advances toward the south.  This progression is perceptible 
along the Old Continent, as may be seen from the form 
of its capes, which, taking the point of departure east, lengthen 
so much more south as they advance toward the west; 
such as the Cape of Kamtschatka in Asia, Cape Comorin in 
Arabia, the Cape of Good Hope in Africa, and finally, Cape 
Horn in America.</p> 
<pb n="193" id="PieStud193"/><p>These differences of proportion are to be accounted for from 
this, that the two terrestrial hemispheres are not projected in 
the same manner; for the Old Continent has its greatest 
breadth from east to west, and the New its greater extent 
from north to south; and it is manifest this difference of projection 
has been regulated by the AUTHOR of Nature for the 
same reasons which induced him to bestow double parts on 
animals, in order that, if necessity required, the one might 
supply what was deficient in the other, but principally that 
they might be of mutual assistance.</p> 
<p>If, for example, there existed only the ancient continent 
with the South Sea alone, the motion of that sea being much 
accelerated under the line by the regular winds from the east, 
would, after having surrounded the torrid zone, advance with 
incredible fury, and attack tremendously the land of Japan: 
for the size of the billows of the sea is always in proportion 
to its extent.  But from the disposition of the two continents 
the billows of the great eastern current of the Indian Ocean 
are partly retarded by the archipelagoes of the Moluccas and 
Philippine Islands; they are still farther broken by other 
islands, such as the Maldivia, by the capes of Arabia, and by 
that of Good Hope, which throws them back toward the 
south.  Before they reach Cape Horn they have to encounter 
new obstacles from the current of the south pole, which 
then crosses their course, and the change of the monsoon, 
which totally destroys the cause of the commotion at the end 
of six months.  Thus there is not a single current, easterly 
or northerly, which pervades so much as a quarter of the 
globe in the same direction.  Besides, the division of the 
parts of the globe into two, is so necessary to its general harmony, 
that if the channel of the Atlantic Ocean, which 
separates them, had no existence, all the oriental rivers of 
America and the occidental of Europe would be dried up; 
for those rivers owe their supplies only to the clouds which 
emanate from the sea.  Besides, the sun enlightening on 
our side only one terrestrial hemisphere, the mediterraneans 
of which would disappear, must burn it up with his rays; 
and at the same time, as he warmed on the other side a 
hemisphere of water only, most of the islands of which would 
sink of course, because the quantity of that sea must be increased 
by the subtraction of ours, an immensity of vapour 
would arise and go merely to waste.</p> 
<pb n="194" id="PieStud194"/><p>It would appear that, from these considerations, Nature 
has not placed in the torrid zone the greatest length of the 
continents, but only the mean breadth of America and Africa, 
because the action of the sun would there have been too 
vehement.  She has placed there, on the contrary, the longest 
diameter of the South Sea, and the greatest breadth of 
the Atlantic Ocean, and there she has collected the greatest 
quantity of islands in existence.  Farther, she has placed in 
the breadth of the continents, there lengthened out, the 
greatest bodies of running water in the world, all issuing 
from mountains of ice.  Again, for this reason, she has multiplied 
in the torrid zone and its vicinity, lofty chains of 
mountains covered with snow, and she directs thither the 
winds of the north and south pole, of which the trade-winds 
always partake.  Several of the great rivers which flow 
there are not situated precisely under the line, but in regions 
of the torrid zone, hotter than the line itself.</p> 
<p>From all this we have a glimpse of the necessity of two 
continents, mutually to check the movements of the ocean. 
Nature could not have disposed them otherwise, than by extending 
one lengthwise and the other in breadth, that the 
opposed currents of their ocean might balance each other, and 
that there might thence result a harmony adapted to their 
shores, and to the islands contained in their basons.</p> 
<p>Were we to suppose these two continents projected circularly, 
from east to west, under the two temperate zones, the circulation 
of the sea contained between them would be too violently 
accelerated by the east wind.  There could be no longer 
any communication by sea from the line toward the poles; 
consequently no icy effusions in that ocean, no tides, no cooling, 
and no renovation of its waters.  If we suppose, on the 
contrary, both continents extended from north to south, as 
America is, there would be no longer any oriental current in 
the ocean; the two halves of each sea would meet in the 
midst of their channel, and their polar effusions would there 
encounter each other with an impetuosity of commotion, of 
which the icy effusions precipitated from the Alps convey but  
a faint idea.  But by the alternate and opposite currents of 
the seas the icy effusions of our pole proceed, in summer, to 
cool Africa, Brazil, and the southern parts of Asia, forcing 
its way beyond the Cape of Good Hope, by the monsoon, 
which then carries the current of the ocean towards the east; 
<pb n="195" id="PieStud195"/>and during our winter the effusions of the south pole proceed 
towards the west, to moderate on the same shores the action 
of the sun, which is there unremitting.  By means of these 
two spiral motions of the seas, similar to those of the sun in 
the heavens, there is not a single drop of water but what may 
make the tour of the globe by evaporation under the line, 
dissolution into rain in the continent, and congelation under 
the pole.  These universal correspondences are so much the 
more worthy of being remarked, that they enter into all the 
plans of Nature, and present themselves in the rest of her 
works.</p> 
<p>From any other imaginable order would result other inconveniences, 
which I leave the reader to find out.  Hypotheses 
<hi rend="italic">ex absurdo</hi> are at once amusing and useful; they change, it 
is true, natural proportions into caricatures; but they have 
this advantage, that by convincing us of the weakness of our 
understanding, they impress us with a deep sense of the 
wisdom of Nature.</p> 
</div2><div2 type="part" id="d13"> 
<head>OF PROGRESSION.</head> 
<p>Progression is a series of consonances ascending or descending. 
Wherever we meet progression it produces exquisite 
pleasure, because it excites in the soul a sentiment of infinity.</p> 
<p>When the leaves of a vegetable are arranged round its 
branches, as the branches themselves are round the stem, there 
is consonancy, as in pines; but if the branches are farther disposed 
among themselves on similar plans, diminishing in 
magnitude, as in the pyramidical form of firs, there is progression; 
and if these trees are disposed in long avenues decreasing 
in height and colouring, like their particular mass, 
our pleasure is heightened, because the progression becomes 
infinite.</p> 
<p>From this instinct of infinity we take pleasure in viewing 
every object which presents a progression; as nursery-grounds, 
containing plans of different ages, hills flying off to the horizon 
in successive elevations, perspectives without a termination.</p> 
<p>Nature has not formed, after our limited manner, perspectives 
with one or two consonances; but she composes them 
of a multitude of different progressions to be found in the 
minutest of her works, of which they constitute the principal 
charm.  They are not the effect of any mechanical law, but 
<pb n="196" id="PieStud196"/>have been apportioned to each vegetable, to prolong the enjoyment 
of its fruit, conformably to the wants of man.  Some 
appear only during the season of heat, others can be preserved; 
but those designed to supply the accidental demands of mankind 
remain on the earth at all times.  Not only are these 
last enclosed in shells for their preservation, but they appear 
upon the tree at all seasons, and in every degree of maturity. 
In tropical countries, on the uninhabited shores of the islands,<note 
type="au" place="foot"><p>See Francis Pyrard's Voyage to the Maldives.</p></note> 
the cocoa-tree bears at once 12 or 15 clusters of cocoa-nuts, 
some in the bud, others in flower, others knit, others full of 
milk, and finally, some in a state of perfect maturity.  The 
cocoa is the seaman's tree.</p> 
<p>The productions of our corn-fields and vineyards present 
dispositions still more wonderful; for though the ear of corn 
has several faces, its grains come to maturity at the same 
time, from the mobility of its straw, which presents them to 
all the aspects of the sun.  The vine does not grow in form 
or a bush nor of a tree, but in hedge-rows; and though its 
berries be arranged in form of clusters, their transparency 
renders them throughout penetrable by the rays of the sun. 
Nature thus lays men under the necessity, from the spontaneous 
maturity of these fruits, destined to the general support 
of human life, to unite their labours, and mutually assist each 
other in the pleasant toils of the harvest and the vintage. 
The corn-field and the vineyard may be considered as the 
most powerful cements of society; for although nature has 
refused to the corn-plant and the vine the power of yielding 
their fruits at all seasons of the year, she has bestowed on the 
flour of the one and the wine of the other, the quality of being 
preservable for ages.</p> 
</div2><div2 type="part" id="d14"> 
<head>OF CONTRASTS.</head> 
<p>Contrasts differ from contraries in this, that contraries act 
but in one single point, and contrasts in their general combination. 
An object has but one contrary, but may have many  
contrasts.  White is the contrary of black; but it contrasts 
with blue, green, red, and various other colours.</p> 
<p>Nature, to distinguish the harmonies, consonances, and 
progressions of bodies, makes them exhibit contrasts.  This 
law is the less observed, being common.  Naturalists consider 
<pb n="197" id="PieStud197"/>the colour of bodies as simple accidents; and look on their  
very forms as the effect of some attraction, incubation, crystalization, 
&amp;c.  Books are composed to extend by analogies the 
mechanical effects of those laws to the different productions 
of Nature; but if they really possess so much power, how 
comes it that the sun has not long ere now filled the waters, 
the dry land, the forests, the heavens, the plains, and all the 
creatures over which he exercises so much influence with the 
uniform and monotonous effects of his light?  All these objects 
ought to assume his appearance, and present only white or 
yellow to our eyes, and be distinguished from each other only 
by their shades.  A landscape ought to exhibit no other effects 
but those of a cameo or of a print.  Latitudes, we are told, 
diversify the colour of them.  But if latitudes have this power, 
how comes it to pass that the productions of the same climate 
and of the same field have not all the same tints?  Whence 
is it that quadrupeds, which are born and die in the meadow, 
do not produce young ones green as the grass on which they 
feed?</p> 
<p>Nature has not satisfied herself with establishing particular 
harmonies in every species of beings to characterize them, 
but, that they might not be confounded among themselves, 
she exhibits them in contrasts.  In general, she has made 
herbs green, to detach them from the earth, and has given 
the colour of earth to animals which live on herbage, to distinguish 
them from the ground on which they stray.  This 
general contrast may be remarked in domestic animals, the 
yellow beasts of the forests, and all the granivorous birds 
which live among herbage or the foliage of trees, as the hen, 
partridge, quail, lark, sparrow, and many others of earthy 
colours, because they live among verdure.  But those who 
live on dingy grounds are clad in brilliant colours, as the 
bluish tomtit and the woodpecker, which scramble along the 
rind of trees in pursuit of insects, and many others.</p> 
<p>Nature universally opposes the colour of the animal to that 
of the ground on which it is destined to live; and this most 
admirable law admits not a single exception.  Flat fishes, 
but indifferent swimmers, and destined to live at the bottom 
of the sea, have the colour of the sands where they find their 
nourishment, being spotted, like the beach, with gray, yellow, 
black, red, and brown.  They are thus speckled, I admit, 
only on one side; but they are so sensible of this resemblance, 
<pb n="198" id="PieStud198"/>that when enclosed within the parks formed on the strand to 
entrap them, and observing the tide gradually retiring, they 
bury their fins in the sand, expecting its return, and present 
to the eye only their deceitful side.  It so perfectly resembles 
the ground on which they squat to conceal themselves, that 
it would be impossible for the fishermen to distinguish them 
from it without the help of sickles, which they draw in every 
direction along the surface of the sand, to detect by the touch 
what the eye could not discern.  This I have witnessed, more 
highly amused at the dexterity of the fishes than at that of 
the fishermen.</p> 
<p>Nature has bestowed at once, in the colours of innoxious 
animals, contrasts with the ground on which they live, and 
consonances with that which is adjacent, and has superadded 
the instinct of employing these alternately, as good or bad 
fortune prompts.  These wonderful accommodations may be 
remarked in most of our small birds, whose flight is feeble 
and of short duration.  The gray lark subsists among the 
grass of the plains: if terrified, she glides away, and takes 
her station between two little clods of earth, where she 
becomes invisible, and remains in perfect tranquillity.</p> 
<p>The same thing is true of the partridge.  I have no doubt 
that these defenceless birds have a sense of those contrasts 
and correspondences of colour, for I have remarked it even 
in insects; it is also conspicuous even in the cameleon, 
endowed with the incomprehensible faculty of assuming at 
pleasure the colour of the ground over which he moves.</p> 
<p>But in the age of weakness and inexperience Nature 
confounds the colour of harmless animals with that of the 
ground on which they inhabit, without committing to them 
the power of choice.  The young of pigeons, and of most 
granivorous fowls, are clothed with a greenish shaggy coat, 
resembling the mosses of their nests.  Caterpillars are blind, 
and have the complexion of the foliage and of the barks 
which they devour.  Nay, young fruits, before they are 
armed with prickles, or enclosed in cases, in bitter pulps, in 
hard shells, to protect their seeds, are, during the season of 
their expansion, green as the leaves which surround them. 
Some embryos, it is true, as those of certain pears, are ruddy 
and brown, but they are then of the colour of the bark of the 
tree to which they belong.  When those fruits have enclosed 
their seeds in kernels, or nuts, so as to be in no farther danger, 
<pb n="199" id="PieStud199"/>they then change colour, and give their respective trees their 
natural contrasts.  It is strikingly remarkable, that every 
fruit which has changed colour has seed in a state of 
maturity.</p> 
<p>The insects, in like manner, having deposited their robes 
of infancy, and now committed to their own experience, 
spread about over the world, to multiply the harmonies of it 
with the attire and instincts which Nature has conferred upon 
them.  Clouds of butterflies, which in their caterpillar state 
were confounded with the verdure of plants, now oppose the 
colours and forms of their wings to those of flowers.</p> 
<p>Nature doe snot employ those agreeable correspondences 
and contrasts in the decoration of noxious animals, nor even 
of dangerous vegetables.  Carnivorous or venomous animals 
form, at every age, and wherever they are, oppositions harsh 
and disgusting; but the useful bee is of the complexion of 
the <hi rend="italic">stamina</hi> and <hi rend="italic">calices</hi> of the flowers, where she reaps her 
innocent harvests.</p> 
<p>Poisonous plants also present disgusting contrasts, from the 
livid colours of their flowers, which are in harsh oppositions 
with the tender shades; from their nauseous and virulent 
smells; from their prickly foliage, of a dark-green hue, and 
clashing with white on the under side, as the aconite tribes.</p> 
<p>Such of the brute creation as are intended to live on two different 
grounds, are impressed with a double contrast in their 
colours.  Thus, for example, the kingfisher, which skims 
along rivers, is at once musk-coloured and glazed over with 
azure; so as to be detached from the dusky shores by his 
azure colour, and from the azure of the waters by his musk 
colour.  The duck, which dabbles on the same shores, has 
the body tinged of an ash colour, while the head and neck 
are of an emerald-green, so that he is perfectly distinguishable 
by the gray colour of his body, from the verdure of the 
aquatic plants among which he waddles, and by the verdure 
of his head and neck, from the dark-coloured mud where he 
finds part of his food, and in which, by another most astonishing 
contrast, he never soils his plumage.</p> 
<p>Nature opposes, then, the colours of every animal to those 
of the respective ground on which it is to be placed; and 
what confirms the truth of this law is, that the greatest part 
of birds which live on one ground only have but a single 
colour, and that one strongly contrasted with the colour of 
<pb n="200" id="PieStud200"/>the ground.  Accordingly, the birds which live aloft in the 
air, on the azure ground of the heavens, or in the bosom of 
the waters, in the midst of lakes, are mostly white, which 
of all colours forms the most striking contrast with blue, and 
is consequently most adapted to render them perceptible at 
a distance.</p> 
<p>There are others, which, to form a contrast with those last  
mentioned, detach themselves from the skies and waters by 
their black or dusky colours: as the crow, which is perceptible 
at so great a distance in the heavens, on the white 
ground of the clouds.  Hence it may be inferred, that when 
an animal is invested with but one single tint, he is intended 
but for one situation; and when he combines in himself the 
contrast of two opposite tints, that he lives on two grounds, 
the colours themselves of which are determined by that of 
the plumage, or hair, of the animal.  We must, however, 
guard against an unlimited generalization of this law, and 
consider it as harmonizing with the exceptions which wise 
Nature has established, for the preservation of animals; such 
as the whitening of them, to the north, in winter, as a remedy 
against cold, and imbrowning them to the south, during the 
ardours of summer, to shelter them from the effects of burning. 
What evidently demonstrates that these great effects 
of harmony are not mechanical results, is, that among the 
infinite number of birds which live in the higher regions of 
the air, or on the surface of the azure seas, there are none of 
the colour of blue; and that many birds which live between 
the tropics, in the bosom of black rocks, or under the shade 
of sullen forests, are azure-coloured.</p> 
<p>These harmonies are contrived for the use of man; and as 
a farther consequence of these correspondences with him, 
Nature has given to the birds which live remote from him,  
cries shrill, hoarse, and piercing, which render them perceptible 
at a distance, amidst their wild retreats.  She has bestowed 
sweet notes and melodious voices on the little birds 
of our groves, domesticated in our habitations, to heighten 
our delight, as well by their warbling as by the beauty of their 
colours.</p> 
<p>All the kingdoms of Nature present themselves to man 
with the same correspondences, the abysses of the ocean not 
excepted.  The fishes which live on animal substances, as 
the whole class of the cartilaginous do, have disgusting forms 
<pb n="201" id="PieStud201"/>and colours.  Fishes which live in the open sea, have colours 
marbled with white, black, brown, which distinguish them 
in the bosom of the azure billows.  But among those which 
frequent the dusky shores, and particularly such as are denominated 
<hi rend="italic">saxatile,</hi> because they live among rocks, are found 
fishes, the lustre of whose skin and scales surpasses all the 
efforts of the pencil, especially when alive.  The legions of 
mackarel and herrings diffuse the radiance of silver and azure 
over the northern strands of Europe.</p> 
<p>Among the black rocks of the seas of the Tropics, the fish 
known by the name of <hi rend="italic">captain</hi> is caught, whose colours vary 
with the latitude.  This beautiful fish, says Francis Cauche, 
which takes pleasure in the rocks, is streaked in form of 
lozenges; his scales are of a pale gold colour, and his back 
coloured and glazed over with laca, inclining toward vermillion. 
His dorsal fin and tail are waved with azure, fading 
away into green toward the extremities.  Here likewise is 
found the magnificent fish called the <hi rend="italic">sardin,</hi> which is adorned 
with scales of at once a gold and silver hue, crossed from 
head to tail by black lines, which admirably heighten their 
lustre.</p> 
<p>Wherever you see a brilliant fish, be assured his habitation 
is near the shore, and that he lives in the open ocean if he 
is of a dark colour.  This truth we may ascertain in the channels 
and on the banks of our own rivers.  The silver smelt 
and the bray, whose scales are employed in the formation of 
mock pearls, play on the strand of the Seine; whereas the 
eel, of the gloomy colour of slate, takes pleasure to dabble at 
the bottom of the stream.  We must not, however, pretend 
to generalize these laws, to the exclusion of exceptions. 
Nature subjects all to the mutual adaptation of beings, and 
to the enjoyment of man; for though the fishes on the shores 
have, in general, shining colours, there are several species of 
them invariably of a dark colour.</p> 
<p>The saxatile fishes, which can easily ensure their safety 
among the rocks, by agility in swimming, or by the facility 
of finding a retreat in their cavernous receptacles, or of there 
defending themselves against their enemies, by the armour 
which Nature has bestowed, have all of them lively and 
shining colours, the cartilaginous excepted.  All shell-fish 
which walk and migrate, and, consequently, have the power 
of choosing their asylum, are those, in their kind, which have 
<pb n="202" id="PieStud202"/>the richest colours and form, with the different grounds of the 
sea, secondary harmonies totally unknown: but those which 
do not change their situation, as most oysters, which frequently 
adhere to the rocks, or those which are perpetually 
at anchor in straits, as muscles, or those, in a word, which I 
believe are blind, like our land-snails, are of the colour of the 
ground they inhabit, to be less perceptible to their enemies.</p> 
<p>It is impossible to ascribe, as in the shell-fish of India, 
colours so charming to the action of the sun on those shells, 
covered as they are with tartars and rough coats; we may 
venture to affirm, that Nature has veiled their beauty, only 
to preserve it for the enjoyment of man, and placed them only 
on the verge of the shores, where the sea purifies, by tossing 
them about, to put them within his reach.  Thus she places 
the most brilliant shells in regions the most exposed to the 
ravages of the elements; and presents to the poor Patagonians 
spoons and cups, the lustre of which far surpasses the richest 
plate of polished nations.</p> 
<p>Hence it may be inferred, that fishes in general, and shell-fish in particular, which have two opposite colours, live on two 
different grounds, as we have observed in the case of birds, 
and that those which have only one colour frequently only one 
grounds.</p> 
<p>It must not be concluded, on the other hand, that such 
shell-fish are indebted for their colours to the rocks on which 
they adhere by suction; for it would thence follow, that the 
rocks of Magellan's strait, which produce muscles and limpets 
so rich in colouring, should be themselves inlaid with mother-of-pearl, opal, and amethyst; besides, every rock maintains 
shell-fish of very different colours.  Many of those marine 
harmonies have escaped me, for I then considered them as 
merely the effect of chance.  I looked at and admired them, 
but I observed them not: I suspected, however, even then, 
that the pleasure which their harmonic combination inspired, 
must be referable to some with which I am unacquainted.</p> 
<p>Enough has been said to demonstrate how much naturalists 
have mutilated the finest portion of natural history, by 
retailing isolated descriptions of animals and plants, without 
noticing the season when, and the place where, they are to be 
found.  By this negligence they strip them of all their beauty, 
for there is not an animal or plant existing, whose harmonic 
point is not fixed to a certain situation, to a certain hour of 
<pb n="203" id="PieStud203"/>the cay or night, to the rising or setting sun, to the phases of 
the moon, nay, to the very tempests; to say nothing of the 
other contrasts and correspondences resulting from these.</p> 
<p>I am so thoroughly persuaded of the existence of all those 
harmonies, that I doubt not, on seeing the colour of an animal, 
one might determine nearly that of the ground it inhabits; 
and by following up those indications, a road might be 
paved to curious discoveries.</p> 
<p>We meet with those contrasts even in the brute soils of the 
earth.  If a uniform and mechanical cause had produced the 
globe of the earth, it must have been universally of the same 
matter and colour: the hills, mountains, rocks, and sands, 
must have been amalgams, or the rubbish, of each other; but 
this is not found to be the case in any one district, however 
small.  In the same canton may be found red mountains, 
black rocks, white plains, and yellow sands; with substances 
as much varied as their colour.  I shall for the present only 
recommend to naturalists to study Nature, as the great 
painters do, by uniting the harmonies of the three kingdoms. 
Every one who observes in this manner, will find a new light 
diffused over the perusal of voyages and of natural history, 
though their authors scarcely ever speak of those contrasts. 
But every man will be himself in a condition to discover their 
delightful effects, in what is called brute Nature, I mean that 
with which man has not intermeddled.  As often as a natural 
object presents to you a sentiment of pleasure, you may rest 
assured it exhibits some harmonic concert.</p> 
<p>Beyond doubt, animals and plans of the same climate 
have not received from the sun, nor the elements, liveries so 
varied, and so characteristic.  Many new observations may 
be made upon their contrasts.  He who has not seen them 
in their natural place, has not yet become acquainted with 
their beauty or deformity.  Not only are they in opposition 
to the grounds of their respective habitations, but also between 
themselves, as to genus and genus; and it is worthy of 
remark, that when these contrasts are established, they exist 
in all the parts of the two individuals.  We shall speak of 
those plants in the following Study, by simply glancing at 
that delightful and inexhaustible subject.</p> 
<p>Those of animals are still farther extended; they are 
opposed in forms, gestures, and instincts; and with differences 
so decidedly marked, they love to associate with each other, 
<pb n="204" id="PieStud204"/>in the same places.  This consonance of tastes distinguishes 
beings in contrast, from those which are contrary, or enemies. 
Thus the bee and the butterfly extract the nectar of the same 
flowers; and the single-hoofed horse, snuffing up the wind, 
with his mane flowing over his graceful neck, delights to 
amble about airily over the same meadows on which the 
ponderous bull impresses his cloven foot; the dull and steady 
ass takes pleasure in scrambling over the rocks where the 
capricious goat frisks and bounds; the cat and dog live 
peaceably by the same fireside, unless where the tyranny of 
man has vitiated their dispositions, by a treatment calculated 
to excite hatreds and jealousies between them.</p> 
<p>Finally, contrasts exist not only in the works of Nature in 
general, but in each individual in particular, and constitute, 
as well as consonances, the organization of bodies.  If you  
examine one of those bodies, of whatever species, you will 
remark in it forms absolutely opposite, and, nevertheless, 
consonant.  It is thus that, in animals, the excretory organs 
contrast with those of nutrition.  the long tails of horses 
and bulls are opposed to the large side of their heads and 
necks, and come in as a supplement to the motions of these 
anterior parts, too unwieldy to drive away the insects that  
infest them.  On the contrary, the broad tail of the peacock 
forms a contrast with the length of the neck, and smallness 
of the head, of that magnificent bird.  The proportions of 
other animals present oppositions no less harmonic, nor less 
happily adapted to the necessities of each species.</p> 
<p>Harmonies, consonances, progressions, and contrasts, must, 
therefore, be reckoned among the first elements of Nature. 
To those we are indebted for the sentiments of order, beauty, 
pleasure, which spring up in the mind at sight of her works; 
and from her absence arise the uneasy feelings of disorder, 
ugliness, languor, and disgust.  They extend equally to all 
the kingdoms; and though I have limited myself to an 
examination of their effects in the vegetable kingdom only, 
it is impossible to deny myself the pleasure of indicating 
them, at least, in the human figure.  Here Nature has combined 
all the harmonic expressions in their highest degree of 
excellency.  All I can do is to trace a feeble sketch of it. 
Neither have I leisure to arrange more than a part of my 
observations on this vast and interesting subject.  But the 
little which I am going to advance will be sufficient to overturn 
<pb n="205" id="PieStud205"/>the position maintained by men of celebrity in the world 
of science, namely, That human beauty is arbitrary.</p> 
</div2><div2 type="part" id="d15"> 
<head>OF THE HUMAN FIGURE.</head> 
<p>All the harmonic expressions are combined in the human 
figure.  Observe the form of the head of man, which approaches 
to the spherical, <hi rend="italic">the</hi> form, by way of excellence.  I 
do not believe this configuration is common to it with that of 
any animal whatever.  On its anterior part is traced the oval 
of the face, terminated by the triangle of the nose, and encompassed 
by the radiations of the hair.  The head is supported 
by a neck of considerably less diameter than itself, 
which detaches it from the body by a concave part.</p> 
<p>This slight sketch presents, at the first glance, the five 
harmonic terms of the elementary generation of forms.  The 
hair exhibits lines; the nose the triangle; the head the 
sphere; the face the oval; and the void under the chin the 
parabola.  The neck, which, like a column, sustains the 
head, exhibits, likewise, the very agreeable harmonic form 
of the cylinder, composed of the circular and quadrilateral.</p> 
<p>These forms, however, are not traced in a stiff and geometrical 
manner, but imperceptibly run into each other, and 
mutually blend, as parts of the same whole.  The hair does 
not fall in straight lines, but flowing ringlets, and harmonizes 
with the oval of the face; the triangle of the nose is neither 
acute, nor a right angle; but, by the undulatory swelling of 
the nostrils, presents a harmony with the heart form of the 
mouth, and, sloping towards the forehead, melts away into 
the cavities of the eyes.  The spheroid of the head also amalgamates 
with the oval of the face.  The same thing holds 
with respect to the other parts, as Nature employs, in their 
general combination, the roundings of the forehead, cheeks, 
chin, and neck, that is, portions of the most beautiful of the 
harmonic expressions, namely, the sphere.</p> 
<p>There are, farther, proportions which form, with each other, 
pleasing harmonies and contrasts: as that of the forehead, 
which presents a quadrilateral form, in opposition to the triangle, 
composed of the eyes and mouth; and that of the ears, 
formed of very ingenious acoustic curves, not to be met with 
in the auditory organ of animals, because, in mere animals, 
the ear collects not, like that of man, all the modulations of 
speech.</p> 
<pb n="206" id="PieStud206"/><p>But I must expatiate more at large on the charming forms 
assigned by Nature to the eyes and mouth, placed in the full 
blaze of evidence, as the two active organs of the soul.  The 
mouth consists of two lips, the upper moulded into the shape 
of a heart, that form so lovely as to have become proverbial 
for its beauty; and the under rounded into a demi-cylindric 
segment.  In the opening between the lips, we have a glimpse 
of the quadrilateral figure of the teeth, whose perpendicular 
and parallel lines contrast most agreeably with the round 
forms adjoining, and so much the more, as we have seen,  
that the first generative term being brought into union with 
the supremely excellent harmonic term, that is, the straight 
lines with the spherical form, the most harmonic of all contrasts 
results from it.</p> 
<p>The same relations are to be found in the eyes, the forms  
of which combine still more the harmonic elementary expressions; 
as it was fit the chief of all the organs should do. 
They are two globes, fringed on the lids with eyelashes, 
radiating with divergent pencil strokes, which form with them 
a most delightful contrast, and present a striking consonance 
with the sun, after which they seem to have been modelled, 
having, like that orb, a spherical figure, encircled with divergent 
rays in the eyelashes; having a movement of self-rotation,  
and possessing the power, like him, of unveiling themselves 
in clouds by means of their lids.</p> 
<p>The same elementary harmonies may be traced in the 
colours of the head, and in its forms; in the face we have 
the pure white exhibited in the teeth and eyes; then the 
shades of yellow, which dissolve into its carnation, as painters 
well know; after that the red, the eminently excellent 
colour, which glows on the lips and cheeks.  You farther 
remark the blue of the veins, and sometimes that of the eyeballs; 
and finally, the black of the hair, which, by its opposition, 
gives relief to the colours of the face, as the vacuum 
of the neck detaches the forms of the head.</p> 
<p>Observe, that Nature employs not, in decorating the human 
face, colours harshly opposed; but blends them, as she does 
the forms, softly and insensibly into each other.  Thus, the 
white melts here into yellow, there into red.  The blue of the 
veins has a greenish cast.  The hair is rarely of a jet black; 
but brown, chestnut, flaxen, and in general of a colour into 
which a slight tint of the carnation enters, to prevent a 
<pb n="207" id="PieStud207"/>violently harsh opposition.  She also employs spherical segments 
in forming the muscles which unite the organs, and 
particularly to distinguish these organs she makes use of 
red.  She has accordingly extended a slight shade of it to 
the forehead, which is strengthened upon the cheeks, and  
applied pure and unmixed to the mouth, that organ of the 
heart, where it forms a most agreeable contrast with the 
whiteness of the teeth.  The union of this colour with that 
harmonic form, is the most powerful consonance of beauty; 
and it is worthy of remark, that wherever the spherical 
forms swell, there the colour strengthens, except in the eyes.</p> 
<p>As the eyes are the principal organs of the soul, they are 
destined to express all its emotions, which could not have 
been done with the harmonic red tint, for this would have 
given but one single expression.  Nature, in order there to 
express the contrary passions, has united in the eye the most 
opposite of colours, the white of the orbit and the black of 
the iris, and sometimes of the ball, which form a very harsh 
opposition, when the globes of the eye are displayed in the 
full extent of their diameter; but by means of the eyelids, 
which man can contract or dilate at pleasure, he is enabled 
to give them the expression of all the passions, from love to 
fury.</p> 
<p>Those eyes whose balls are blue are naturally the softest, 
because the opposition is then less harsh with the adjacent 
white; but they are terrible when animated with rage, from 
a moral contrast, which constrains us to consider those as the 
most formidable of all objects, that menace evil, after having 
encouraged us to expect good.  Persons, therefore, thus distinguished, 
ought to be carefully on their guard against 
treachery to that character of benevolence bestowed on them 
by Nature; for blue eyes express, by their colour, something 
enchantingly celestial.</p> 
<p>The movements of the muscles of the face would be difficult 
to describe, though it might be possible to explain their 
laws.  They must of necessity be referred to the moral 
affections.  Those of joy are horizontal, as if the soul, in the 
enjoyment of felicity, had a disposition to extend itself. 
Those of chagrin are perpendicular, as if, under the pressure 
of calamity, the mind was looking toward Heaven for refuge, 
or seeking it in the bosom of the earth.  In the alterations 
of colours, and contractions of forms, we shall discover the 
<pb n="208" id="PieStud208"/>truth of the principle we have laid down, that the expression 
of pleasure is in the harmony of contraries, blending with 
each other in colours, forms, and motions; and that the expression 
of pain consists in the violence of their oppositions. 
The eyes alone have motions ineffable; under the influence 
of strong emotions, they are suffused with tears, and thus 
seem to have a farther analogy with the orb of day, who, in 
the season of tempests, shrouds himself in rainy distillations.</p> 
<p>The principal organs of sense, four of which are placed in 
the head, have particular contrasts, which detach their 
spherical by means of radiated forms, and their shining 
colours by dusky tints.  Thus the bright organ of vision is 
contrasted by the eyebrows; those of smell and taste by 
the mustaches; the organ of hearing, by that part of the 
hair called the <hi rend="italic">favourite</hi> lock, which separates the ear from 
the face; and the face itself is distinguished from the rest 
of the head by the beard and hair.</p> 
<p>The human body alone unites in itself the modulations and  
concerts, inexpressibly agreeable, of the five elementary forms, 
and the five primordial colours, without exhibiting anything 
of the harsh and rude oppositions perceptible in the brute 
creation; of it alone the first touch is perceptible, and may 
be seen completely; other animals being disguised under 
hair, feathers, or scales, which conceal their limbs, shape, and 
skin.  Farther, it is the only form which, in its perpendicular 
attitude, displays all its positions and directions at once; 
for you can hardly perceive more of a quadruped, bird, or fish, 
than one half, in the horizontal position proper to them, because 
the upper part of their body conceals the under.</p> 
<p>Man's progressive motion is subject to neither the shocks 
nor the tardiness of movements of most quadrupeds, nor to the 
rapidity of that of birds; but is the result of movements the 
most harmonic, as his figure is of forms and colours the most 
delightful.</p> 
<p>The more that the consonances of the human figure are 
agreeable, the more disgusting are its dissonances.  Hence, 
on the face of the earth, nothing is so beautiful as a handsome 
man, nothing so shocking as a very ugly one.</p> 
<p>This farther suggests a reason why it will be for ever impossible 
for art to produce a perfect imitation of the human 
figure, from the difficulty of uniting in it all the harmonies; 
and from the still greater difficulty of effecting a complete 
<pb n="209" id="PieStud209"/>combination of those of a different nature.  The exertions of 
painters and sculptors in general do them much honour; but 
they demonstrate the weakness of Art, which falls below 
Nature just in proportion as it aims at uniting more of her 
harmonies.  Instead of blending them, as Nature herself 
does, Art can only place them in opposition.  This proves 
that harmony results from the union of two contraries, and 
discord from their collision: and the more agreeable the harmonies 
of an object are, the more disgusting are its discordances. 
Hence the real origin of pleasure and dislike, in 
physics as in morals, and the reason why the same object 
so frequently excites affection and aversion.</p> 
<p>Many interesting reflections remain to be made on the human 
figure, especially by connecting with it the moral sensations,  
which alone give expression to the features.  The 
physical beauty of man is so striking, in the eyes even of the 
animal creation, that to it principally must be ascribed the 
empire he everywhere exercises over them.  The feeble seek 
refuge under his protection; the most powerful tremble at sight 
of him.  The lark will save herself amidst troops of men, 
when she perceives the bird of prey hovering over her; the 
stag, when run down by the hounds, appeals with sobs for 
relief, to the compassion of persons accidentally passing that 
way; the India-hens, under the impulse of love, throw themselves 
chuckling at the feet of the country people; and it is 
well known with what familiarity monkeys and fowls of all 
kinds approach travellers in the forests of India.  But dangerous 
animals are seized with terror at the sight of man, 
unless driven from their natural bias by some pressing necessity. 
An elephant is led about in Asia by a little child; the 
African lion retires growling from the cabin of the Hottentot, 
and seeks for himself a kingdom untrodden by the foot of 
man; and the immense whale, amidst his native element, 
trembles and flees away before the puny bark of the Laplander. 
Thus is executed that all-potent law, which secured empire 
to man, though sunk in guilt and wretchedness: 'And 
the fear of you, and the dread of you, shall be upon every 
beast of the earth, and upon every fowl of the air; upon all 
that moveth upon the earth, and upon all the fishes of the 
sea; into your hand are they delivered.'  Gen. ix. 2.</p> 
<p>It is remarkable, that through all Nature, there is no animal, 
plant, fossil, nor even globe, but what has its consonance 
<pb n="210" id="PieStud210"/>and contrast out of itself, man alone excepted.  No one 
visible being enters into society with him but as his servant 
or slave.</p> 
<p>We must, undoubtedly, reckon among the human proportions, 
that law so universal, so wonderful, which produces 
males and females in equal numbers.  Did chance preside 
over the generations of the human race, as over our alliances, 
we should one year have an unmixed crop of male children, 
and another, a race entirely female.  Some nations would 
consist wholly of men, others of women; but all over the 
globe, the two sexes are born, within the same space of time, 
equal in number.  A consonance so regular demonstrates 
that a Providence watches over the affairs of mankind, notwithstanding 
the absurdity and disorder of human institutions. 
This is a standing testimony to the truth of our 
religion, which limits man to one woman in marriage, and 
by this conformity to natural laws, peculiar to itself, seems 
alone to have emanated from the AUTHOR of Nature.  A 
religion therefore which permits or connives at a plurality of 
wives, must be erroneous.</p> 
<p>Ah!how little acquainted are they with the laws of Nature, 
who, in the union of the two sexes, look for nothing 
farther than the pleasures of sense!  They are only culling 
the flowers of life, without once tasting its fruit.  The fair 
sex! this is the phrase of our men of pleasure; women are 
known to them under no other idea.  But the sex is fair only 
to persons who have no other faculty but eyesight.  It is, 
besides, to those who have a heart, the creative sex, which, 
at the peril of life, carries man for nine months in the womb; 
the cherishing sex, which suckles and tends him in infancy. 
It is the pious sex, which conducts him to the altar while yet 
a child, and teaches him to draw in, with the milk of the 
maternal breast, the love of a religion which the cruel policy 
of men would frequently render odious to him.  It is the 
pacific sex, which sheds not the blood of a fellow creature; 
the sympathizing sex, which ministers to the sick, and 
handles without hurting them.</p> 
<p>To no purpose does man pretend to boast of his power and 
strength; if his robust hands are able to subdue iron and 
brass, those of the woman, more dexterous and usefully employed, 
can spin into threads the flax and the fleeces of the 
sheep.  The one encounters gloomy care with the maxims 
<pb n="211" id="PieStud211"/>of philosophy, the other banishes it by sportiveness and 
gayety.  The one opposes to external evils the force of his 
reason; the other, far happier, eludes them by the mobility 
of hers.  If the man sometimes considers it as his glory to 
bid defiance to danger in the field of battle, the woman 
triumphs, in calmly meeting dangers more inevitable, and 
frequently more cruel, on her bed, and under the banners of 
pleasure.  Thus they have been created to support together 
the ills of life, and to form by their union the most powerful 
of consonances, and the sweetest of contrasts.</p> 
<p>I am obliged by the plan of my work to refrain from pursuing 
my reflections on subjects so interesting as the marriage 
and beauty of man and woman.  I must, however, hazard 
some farther observations, to induce others to dive into this 
rich mine.</p> 
<p>All philosophers who have studied man are agreed, and 
with good reason, that he is the most wretched of all animals. 
Most of them have been sensible that an associate 
was necessary to him to relieve his burdens, and they have 
made his happiness in part to consist in friendship.  This is 
an evident demonstration of human weakness and misery; 
for were man naturally strong, he would stand in no need of 
either associate or assistance.</p> 
<p>When the ancients represented perfect friendship, it was 
always restricted to two; for man is frequently reduced to 
the necessity of deriving his felicity from the concurring 
interposition of many beings similar to himself.  The principal 
reason for this restriction is deducible from the nature of the 
human heart, which from its very weakness is capable of 
attaching itself only to one object at once; and being compounded 
of opposite passions that maintain a perpetual counterpoise, 
is, in some sense, active and passive, and stands in 
need of loving and being beloved, of comforting and being 
comforted, of honouring and being honoured, and so on. 
These singular affections have ever been associated with virtuous 
and heroic actions; but when the union comprehended 
more persons than two, it was speedily dissolved by discord, 
or if permitted to subsist for any length of time, became 
famous only for the mischief which it brought on mankind.</p> 
<p>If the heart of man admits of but a single object, what 
judgment shall we form of our modern friendships, embracing 
as they do, a multiplicity?  Undoubtedly if a man has thirty 
<pb n="212" id="PieStud212"/>friends, he can bestow on each of them only the thirtieth part 
of his affection, and can receive in return no greater proportion 
of theirs.  He must of necessity, therefore, deceive them, 
for no one is disposed to be a friend by fractions.  But, if the 
truth may be told, such friendships are merely confederacies 
of ambition; relations interested and purely political, employed 
in practising mutual illusion, in the view of aggrandizing 
themselves at the expense of society, which would be productive 
of unspeakable mischief, were they more closely 
united and not counterbalanced by opposite confederacies. 
Almost all our general associations accordingly issue in 
intestine wars.</p> 
<p>The AUTHOR of Nature has given to each of us, in our 
species, a natural friend, completely adapted to all the demands 
of human life, capable of supplying all the affections 
of the heart, and all the restlessness of temperament.  He 
says, from the beginning of the world: 'It is not good that 
man should be alone: I will make him a help meet for him; 
&mdash;and the LORD GOD made woman, and brought her unto 
the man.'<note type="ed" place="foot"><p>Genesis, chap. ii. ver. 18, 22.</p></note> 
Woman pleases all our senses by her form and 
graces.  She has in her Character every thing than can interest 
the heart of man at every stage of life.  She merits, by 
the long and painful solicitudes she exercises over our infancy, 
our respect as a mother, and our gratitude as a nurse; afterward, 
as man advances to youth, she attracts all his love as 
a mistress; and in the maturity of manhood, all his tenderness 
as a wife, his confidence as a faithful steward, his protection, 
as being feeble; and even in old age she merits our 
highest consideration, as the source of posterity, and our intimacy, 
as a friend who has been our companion through life. 
Her gayety, nay, her very caprices, balance at all seasons the 
gravity and over-reflective constancy of man, and acquire 
reciprocally a preponderancy over him.</p> 
<p>Thus the defects of one sex, and the excess of the other, 
are an exact mutual compensation.  They are formed, if I 
may use the expression, to be grooved into each other, like the 
corresponding pieces of carpenter's-work, the prominent and 
retreating parts of which constitute a vessel fit to launch on 
the stormy ocean of life, and to attain additional strength 
from the very buffetings of the tempest.  Had we not been 
<pb n="213" id="PieStud213"/>informed by a sacred tradition, that woman was extracted 
from the side of man; and though this great truth were not 
every day manifested, in the wonderful birth of the children 
of the two sexes in equal numbers, we should be speedily 
instructed in it by our wants.  Man without the woman, and 
woman without the man, are imperfect beings in the order of 
Nature.  But the greater the contrast in their characters, the 
more complete union there is in their harmonies.  It is from 
their opposition in talents, tastes, and fortunes, that the most 
intense, the most durable affection is produced.  Marriage is 
therefore the friendship of Nature, and the only real union 
which is not exposed, like those among men, to estrangement, 
rivalship, jealousies, and the changes time is effecting in our 
inclinations.</p> 
<p>But wherefore are there so few happy marriages among us? 
I answer, because with us the sexes have divested themselves 
each of its proper nature, and assumed the other; because 
the women with us adopt the manners of men from education, 
and men the manners of women from habit.  The women 
have been despoiled of the graces and talents peculiar to their 
sex, by the masters, sciences, customs, and occupations of 
men.  There is no way left to bring both back to Nature, 
but to inspire them with a taste for religion.  By religion I 
do not mean attachment to ceremonies of systems of theology, 
but the religion of the heart, pure, simple, unostentatious; 
such as it is so beautifully depicted in the Gospel.</p> 
<p>Religion will restore to the two sexes not only their moral 
character, but physical beauty.  It is not climate, aliment, 
bodily exercise, nor all these together, which form human 
beauty; it is the moral sentiment of virtue, which cannot 
subsist independently of religion.  Aliment and exercise, no 
doubt, contribute greatly to the magnitude and the expansion 
of the body, but they have no influence on the beauty of the 
face, the true physiognomy of the soul.  It is not uncommon 
to see persons tall and robust disgustingly ugly; with the 
stature of a giant, and the face of a monkey.</p> 
<p>Beauty of face is to such a degree the expression of the 
harmonies of the soul, that, in every country, those classes 
of citizens who are obliged to live with others in a state of 
constraint, are sensibly the homeliest of society.  The truth 
of this observation may be ascertained, particularly among 
the noblesse of many of our provinces, who live with each 
<pb n="214" id="PieStud214"/>other in the perpetual jealousy of rank, and with their neighbours 
of an inferior order in a state of unremitting hostility, 
for the maintenance of their prerogatives.  The same thing 
does not hold good respecting the noblesse of some other of 
our provincial districts, and the nobility of other parts of 
Europe.  These, living in good understanding among themselves 
and with their compatriots, are in general the handsomest 
men of their nation, because their social and benevolent 
spirit is not in a state of incessant constraint and anxiety.</p> 
<p>To the same moral causes may be referred the beauty of 
the features of the Greek and Roman physiognomies, where 
we generally meet with models so exquisite in their statues 
and medallions.  They were beautiful, because happy; they 
lived in cordial union with their equals, and in favour with 
the citizens at large.  The descendants of those nations are 
far from exhibiting a resemblance to their ancestors, though 
the climate of their country is not in the smallest degree 
changed.</p> 
<p>To render children beautiful, they must be made physically, 
but, above all, morally happy.  You must prevent every 
possible occasion of vexation, not by kindling in their breasts 
dangerous and headstrong passions, but by teaching them 
to curb such as they have from Nature; and especially, by 
guarding against the communication of every thing unnatural, 
such as useless and irksome tasks, emulations, rivalships, and 
the like.</p> 
<p>The ugliness of a child may be imputed to his nurse or 
preceptor.  I have sometimes observed families singularly 
beautiful.  On inquiring into the cause of this, I have found 
that they were happy; that the mothers had suckled their 
own children; that these had learned their occupations 
under the paternal roof, and been treated with tenderness; 
that their parents were fondly attached to each other; that 
they all lived together in a state of liberty and cordiality, 
which rendered them good, happy, and satisfied.</p> 
<p>I have thence deduced, that we frequently make a false estimate 
of the happiness of human life.  On seeing here a gardener 
with the port of a Roman emperor, and there a great 
lord with the mask of a slave, I imagined at first Nature had 
committed a mistake.  But experience demonstrates, that 
the great lord in question, from his birth to his death, is placed 
in a series of positions, which permit him not to gratify his 
<pb n="215" id="PieStud215"/>own inclinations three times a year.  He must do the will, 
first of his preceptors and masters; in more advanced life, 
that of his prince, of ministers of state, of his rivals, nay, frequently 
that of his enemies: thus he finds fetters innumerable 
in his very dignities.  Our gardener passes his life without 
the slightest contradiction.  Like the centurion in the 
gospel, he says to his servant, Come, and he cometh; and to 
another, Do this, and he doeth it.  This demonstrates that 
Providence has assigned to our very passions a part widely 
different from that which society presents to them; for, in 
cases innumerable, the most unrelenting slavery is imposed 
with an accumulation of honours; and in the meanest of 
human conditions we frequently find the possession of the 
most unbounded empire.</p> 
<p>Besides, persons disfigured by the corruptive impression of 
vicious education and habits, have it in their power to reform 
their looks; and to acquire a beauty altogether irresistible, 
by being internally good, gentle, compassionate, sensible, beneficent, 
and devout.  These affections of a virtuous soul will 
impress on their features celestial characters, beautiful even 
in old age.</p> 
<p>But to no purpose will a man attempt to decorate his countenance 
with the indications of good qualities to which his 
heart is a stranger.  This false beauty produces an effect 
still more disgusting than the most decided ugliness: for 
when, attracted by an apparent goodness, we actually find 
dishonesty and perfidy, we are seized with horror, as when 
we find a serpent lurking on a bed of flowers.  We are bound 
to aspire then after moral beauty, that its divine irradiations 
may be diffused over our features and actions.  Though a 
prince himself may boast of birth, riches, credit, wit, the 
people to know him must look him in the face.  They form 
their judgment entirely from the physiognomy: it is in every 
country the first, and frequently the last letter of recommendation.</p> 
</div2><div2 type="part" id="d16"> 
<head>OF CONCERTS.</head> 
<p>Concert is an order formed of several harmonies of various 
kinds.  It differs from simple order in this, that the last is 
frequently nothing but a series of harmonies of the same 
species.</p> 
<p>Every particular work of Nature presents, in different kinds, 
<pb n="216" id="PieStud216"/>harmonies, consonances, contrasts; and forms a real concert. 
It may be remarked, on the subject of those harmonies and 
contrasts, that vegetables whose flowers have the least lustre 
are frequented by animals of the most brilliant colours, and 
that the most highly coloured vegetables serve as an asylum 
to the duskiest animals.  This is particularly evident in countries 
between the tropics, where the trees and herbage without 
flowers lodge and support birds, insects, nay, monkies 
of the most lively colours.</p> 
<p>In our temperate regions most of the birds are dull-coloured, 
because our vegetables have flowers and fruits with shining 
colours: our lively coloured birds and insects usually choose 
for their habitation vegetables that have no apparent flowers. 
Thus the heath-cock glitters on the gray verdure of the pine, 
whose apples serve him for food; and the goldfinch builds 
his nest in the rough fuller's-thistle.  On the contrary, birds 
of dusky hue inhabit shrubbery with gay-coloured flowers. 
The black-headed bullfinch builds his nest in the white thorn, 
and that lovely bird exhibits a farther consonance and contrast 
with the prickly shrub where he resides, by his blood-stained breast and sweet song.  The nightingale with brown 
plumage delights to nestle in the rose-bush, according to the 
traditions of the oriental poets, who have sung the loves of 
that melancholy bird for the rose.</p> 
<p>If to each plant are added its elementary harmonies, as 
those of the season when it appears, of the soil in which it 
vegetates, the effects of the dews, and the reflexes of the light 
on its foliage, the movements it undergoes from the action of 
the winds, its contrasts and consonances with other plants, 
and with quadrupeds, birds, and insects peculiar to it, and a 
delightful concert will be formed, the harmonies of which are 
still unknown to us.  By pursuing this track alone we can 
obtain a glimpse of the magnificent edifice of Nature.  I 
would entreat naturalists, persons fond of gardening, painters, 
nay poets, thus to prosecute their studies, and to take frequent 
draughts from this perennial spring of taste and delight.</p> 
<p>I know not at present what name I ought to give to the 
conformities those particular concerts have with man.  Certain 
it is, that every work of Nature strengthens its particular 
concert by the habitation of man, and communicates to it 
some expression of grandeur, gayety, terror, or majesty. 
She raises the physical character of her works to a sublime 
<pb n="217" id="PieStud217"/>moral character, by collecting them around mankind.  She 
not only employs particular concerts to express them, but 
when she means to expose them on the great scale, she combines 
a multitude of similar harmonies and contrasts to form 
one great general concert, which has only a single expression, 
let the field of representation be ever so extensive.</p> 
<p>To express, for example, the maleficent character of a 
venomous plant, she combines in it clashing oppositions of 
forms and colours, the indications of that maleficence; as 
retreating and bristly forms, livid colours, dark greens with 
white and black spots, virulent smells.....But when a whole 
district is to be characterized as unwholesome, she collects a 
multitude of similar dissonances.  The air is loaded with 
thick fogs, the turbid waters exhale only nauseous smells, no 
vegetable thrives on the putrid soil but such as are disgusting, 
the dracunculus, for instance, the flower of which exhibits 
the form, the colour, and the smell of an ulcer.  The 
yew-tree only arises in the cloudy atmosphere, whose red 
trunk and gloomy foliage serves as an asylum to owls.  If 
any animal seeks a retreat under its lurid shade, it is the 
blood-coloured centipede, or the toad crawling over the humid 
and rotten ground.  By these, or similar signs, Nature scares 
man away from noxious situations.</p> 
<p>If she intends to give him at sea the signal of an impending 
tempest, as she has opposed in ferocious animals the fiery 
glare of the eye to the thickness of the eyebrows; their 
stripes and spots to the yellow colour of their skin, and the 
stillness of their movements to the thundering noise of their 
voices; she collects also in the sky and on the deep many 
clashing oppositions, which in concert announce approaching 
devastation.  Dark clouds sweep through the air in the most 
horrible forms; here and there the pale fire of lightning 
bursts from the gloom; the noise of thunder from their dark 
womb resounds like the roaring of the celestial lion.  The 
orb of day, scarcely visible through their rainy and multiplied 
veils, emits long radiations of a wan and sickly light.  The 
leaden surface of the ocean sinks and swells into broad and 
white foaming surges.  A hollow murmuring noise seems to 
issue from those threatening billows.  The black shallows 
whiten at a distance, with horrid sounds, from time to time 
interrupted by ominous silence.  The sea, which alternately 
covers and reveals them, displays to the light of day their 
<pb n="218" id="PieStud218"/>cavernous foundations.  The Norwegian lom perches on one 
of their craggy points, uttering lamentable cries, like those of 
a drowning man.  The sea ospray rises aloft in the air, and 
not daring to commit herself to the impetuosity of the winds, 
struggles with a plaintive screaming voice against the tempest, 
which bends back her stubborn wings.  The black 
procellaria flutters about, grazing the foam of the waves, 
and seeks, in the cavity of their moving valleys, a shelter 
from the fury of the winds.  If this small and feeble bird 
happens to perceive a ship in the midst of the sea, he flees 
for refuge along her side, and as a reward for the protection 
which he solicits, announces the tempest to the mariner 
before it overtakes him.</p> 
<p>Nature uniformly proportions the signs of destruction to 
the magnitude of the danger.  Every storm has its peculiar 
character in particular latitudes; those of summer are unlike 
those of winter; and widely different is the spectacle of an 
enraged sea, shining at noonday under the rays of the sun, 
and that of the same sea illuminated, at the midnight hour, 
by a single flash of lightning.  Nature frequently accompanies 
the signs of the disorder which agitates the ocean, with agreeable 
expressions of harmony, that serve only to redouble the 
horror of the scene.  Tempests, off the Capes of Good Hope 
and Horn, in the full blaze of light, are inexpressibly tremendous. 
The soul stands aghast at sight of the indications of 
tranquillity converted into those of storm; the unclouded 
azure in the heavens, and the rainbow playing upon the 
waves.  The principles of harmony appear to be completely 
inverted.  Nature seems to have put on a character of perfidiousness, 
and to conceal fury under the mask of benevolence.</p> 
<p>If Nature, by introducing certain agreeable harmonies into 
scenes of discord, redoubles their confusion, she frequently 
throws in a discordance in concerts the most delightful, for 
the purpose of heightening the pleasurable effect.  She 
employs offensive contrasts only to chase man from some 
perilous situation.  In all the rest of her works she employs 
only harmonic mediums.</p> 
<p>In our harvest fields we find that charming shade of green, 
produced by the alliance of the two primordial opposite colours, 
the yellow and the blue.  This harmonic colour decompounds 
itself by another metamorphosis, toward the harvest time, 
<pb n="219" id="PieStud219"/>into the three primordial colours, namely, the yellow of the 
ripening corn, the red of the wild poppy, and the azure of 
the bluebottle.  These two plants are intermingled with the 
standing corn, all over Europe, let the farmer take what pains 
he may in sifting the grain and weeding his field.  They 
form, by their harmony, a rich purple tint, which rises admirably 
on the yellow ground of the corn-field.</p> 
<p>The corn-plant itself has relations innumerable with the 
wants of man and domestic animals.   It is neither too high 
nor too low for his stature, but is easily handled and reaped. 
It furnishes grain to his poultry, bran to his pigs, forage and 
litter to his black cattle and horses.  Every plant in his 
corn-field possesses virtues particularly adapted to the maladies 
incident to the condition of the labouring man.  The 
poppy cures the pleurisy, procures sleep, stops hemorrhages 
and spitting of blood.  The bluebottle is diuretic, vulnerary, 
cordial, and cooling, an antidote to the stings of venomous 
insects, and a remedy for inflammation of the eyes.  Thus 
the husbandman finds all needful pharmacy in the field which 
he cultivates.</p> 
<p>The culture of this staff of life discloses to man many other 
agreeable concerts with his fleeting existence.  The direction 
of its shadow informs him of the hour of the day; from its 
growth he learns the rapid flight of the seasons; he reckons  
the flux of his own fugitive years, by the succession of the 
guiltless harvests he has reaped.  He is haunted with no 
apprehension, like the inhabitants of great cities, of conjugal 
infidelity, or a too numerous posterity.  His labours are 
always surpassed by the benefits of Nature.  When the sun 
gets to the sign of Virgo, he summons his kindred, invites his 
neighbours, and leads them, at dawn of day, with sickle in 
hand, to the ripened field.  His heart exults with joy as he 
binds up the swelling sheaves, while his children dance 
around him, crowned with garlands of bluebottles and wild 
poppies.  The harmless play recalls to his memory the amusements 
of his own early days, and of his virtuous ancestors, 
whom he hopes at length to rejoin in a better and happier 
world.  The sight of his copious harvest demonstrates that 
there is a GOD; and every return of that joyous season, 
bringing to his recollection the delicious eras of his past existence, 
inspires him with gratitude to the Great Being who 
<pb n="220" id="PieStud220"/>has united the transient society of men by an eternal chain 
of blessings.</p> 
<p>Ye flowery meadows, ye majestic, murmuring forests, ye 
mossy fountains, ye desert rocks, frequented by the dove 
alone, ye enchanting solitudes, which charm by your ineffable 
concerts; happy is the man who shall be permitted to unveil 
your hidden beauties! but happier far is he who shall have 
it in his power calmly to enjoy them in the inheritance of his 
forefathers!</p> 
</div2><div2 type="part" id="d17"> 
<head>OF SOME OTHER LAWS OF NATURE, HITHERTO IMPERFECTLY KNOWN></head> 
<p>There are, besides those which have been mentioned, some 
physical laws not hitherto profoundly investigated, though 
we have had a glimmering of them, and made them the frequent 
subject of conversation.  Such is the law of attraction. 
It has been acknowledged in the planets, and in some metals, 
as in iron and the loadstone, in gold and mercury.  I believe 
attraction to be common to all metals, and even fossils; but 
that it acts in each in particular circumstances, not yet ascertained. 
Each of the metals, perhaps, may incline toward 
different points of the earth, as magnetic iron does to the 
north.  It would probably be necessary to ascertain this by 
experiment, that each metal should be armed with its proper 
attraction; which takes place when united to its contrary.</p> 
<p>How do we know whether a needle of gold, rubbed with 
mercury, might not have attractive poles, as a needle of steel 
has when rubbed with the magnet?  Thus prepared, it might 
possibly indicate the places which contain mines of that rich 
metal.  Perhaps it might determine the general points of 
direction to the east or west, which might indicate the longitudes 
more steadily than the variations of the magnetic needle.</p> 
<p>If there be a point at the pole, on which the globe revolves, 
there may possibly be one under the equator, from which 
commenced, and which may have determined, its motion of 
rotation.  It is, however, certain there exist many of those 
particular points of attraction, scattered over the earth, such 
as the matrices which renovate the mines of metals, by 
attracting to themselves the metallic parts dispersed in the 
elements.  Metals have besides other attractions; and I consider 
these as the principal matrices of all fossil bodies, and as 
<pb n="221" id="PieStud221"/>the ever active means employed by Nature for repairing the 
mountains and rocks, which the action of the other elements, 
but especially the injudicious labours of men, have an incessant 
tendency to impair.</p> 
<p>I shall here remark, on the subject of mines of gold, that 
they are placed, as well as those of all metals, not only on 
the most elevated part of continents, but in icy mountains. 
The gold mines of Peru and Chili are situated in the Cordilleras; 
those of Mexico in the vicinity of Mount St. Martha, 
covered with snow all the year round.  It may be said that 
all rivers which wash down particles of gold along their 
shores, issue from icy mountains.</p> 
<p>To this it may be objected, that gold was formerly found 
in Europe, in places where there were no icy mountains; nay, 
that some has been picked up on the surface of the ground, 
as in Brazil.  But, if I might venture to hazard a conjecture 
respecting the origin of this gold, I believe it to have proceeded 
from the total effusion of the ices of the mountains 
at the time of the deluge, when vegetable earths and minerals 
were forced along other countries, where their fragments 
were found, in the earlier ages, in grains, and even in larger 
masses.</p> 
<p>It would appear as if Nature, by burying the foci of 
this rich metal under the snows, had intended to fence it with 
ramparts still more inaccessible than the flinty bosom of the 
rock, lest the undismayed ardour of human avarice should at 
length destroy them entirely.  It has become the most 
powerful bond of society, the perpetual object of a life so 
rapidly hurrying to a close.  Alas! were Nature to inflict 
condign punishment on this insatiable thirst in the nations of 
Europe, for a metal so useless as a real necessary of human 
life, she has only to change the territory of some one of them 
into gold.  Every other nation would instantly flock thither, 
and soon exterminate its wretched inhabitants.  The Peruvians 
and Mexicans have had the dreadful experience of this.</p> 
<p>There are metals not so highly prized, but much more 
useful.  The peaks and crests of the mountains are filled 
with iron or copper, intermingled with a vitreous body of 
granite or of natural crystal, which attracts the rains and 
stormy clouds.  Seamen have seen, a thousand times, those 
peaks and crests covered with a cloudy cap concealing them 
from view, without once suspecting the cause of this appearance; 
<pb n="222" id="PieStud222"/>and philosophers, deducing their conclusions from 
charts, have taken those rocky protuberances for wrecks of 
a primitive earth, without troubling themselves about their 
effects.  They ought to have observed that those metallic 
pyramids and crests, as well as most mines of iron and copper, 
are to be found in elevated situations, and at the source 
of rivers, of which they are the primitive causes by their 
attractions.  Their general inattention to this subject is thus 
only to be accounted for; seamen observe, and do not reason; 
and the learned reason, but do not observe.  Undoubtedly, 
had the experience of the one been united to the sagacity of 
the other, prodigies of discovery might have been expected.</p> 
<p>I am persuaded we might acquire the art of forming, by 
electric stones, artificial fountains, which should attract the 
rainy clouds in dry situations, as chains and rods of iron 
attract thunder-clouds.  It is true princes must be at the  
expense of such costly and useful experiments; but they 
would immortalize their memory.  The Pharaohs, who built 
the pyramids of Egypt, would not have drawn upon themselves 
the curses of their subjects, as Pliny assures us they 
did, for their enormous and useless labours, had they reared, 
amidst the sands of Upper Egypt, an electrical pyramid, 
which might there have formed an artificial fountain.  The 
Arab who should resort thither at this day to quench his 
thirst, would still pronounce benedictions on names which, if 
we may believe the great Natural Historian, had already 
sunk into oblivion, and ceased to be mentioned in his time.</p> 
<p>For my own part, I think that several metals might be 
proper for producing similar effects.  A Prussian officer of 
rank informed me that having remarked vapours to be attracted 
by lead, he had employed it for drying the atmosphere 
of a powder-magazine, constructed under ground, in the 
throat of a bastion, but useless from its humidity.  He ordered 
the concave ceiling of the arch to be lined with lead, 
where the gunpowder was deposited in barrels; the vapours 
of the vault collected in great drops, on the leaden roof, run 
off in streamlets along the sides, and left the gunpowder  
barrels perfectly dry.</p> 
<p>There are many other harmonic laws as yet undiscovered; 
as the proportions of magnitudes, and durations of existence, 
of beings vegetative and sensible, which differ exceedingly, 
though their nutriment and climates may be the same.  Man, 
<pb n="223" id="PieStud223"/>while yet a youth, sees his dog die of old age; and also the 
sheep he fondled when a lamb.  Though the former lived 
at his own table, and the latter on the herbage of his meadow, 
neither the fidelity of the one, nor the temperance of 
the other, could prolong their days; whereas animals which 
live only on carrion and garbage live for ages, as the crow. 
In such researches we must follow the spirit of conformity, 
the basis of our own, and of the reason of Nature.</p> 
<p>By consulting this we shall find, that if such a carnivorous 
animal, the crow for instance, is long-lived, it is because 
his services and experience are long necessary for purifying 
the earth.  If an innocent animal lives but a little while, it 
is because his flesh and skin are necessary to man.  If the 
domestic dog, by his death, diffuses sorrow over the children 
of the family, Nature undoubtedly intended to give them, in 
the loss of an animal so worthy the affections and regret of 
man, the first experience of the privations with which human 
life is to be exercised.</p> 
<p>The duration of an animal's life is sometimes proportioned 
to that of the vegetable on which it feeds.  A multitude of 
caterpillars are born and die with the leaves by which their 
transitory existence is supported.  There are insects whose 
being is limited to five hours; such is the ephemera.  But 
as Nature has made nothing in vain, it is not credible that 
she should have created momentary lives, and beings infinitely 
minute, to fill up imaginary chains of existence.</p> 
<p>The aversions and instincts of animals emanate from laws 
of a superior order, into which we shall never be able to penetrate; 
but supposing those intimate conformities to elude our 
researches, they must be referred to the general conformity 
of beings, and especially to that of man.  There is nothing 
so luminous in the study of Nature, as to refer every thing 
that exists to the goodness of GOD, and to the demands of 
humanity.  This method of viewing objects not only discovers 
to us a multitude of unknown laws, but it sets bounds 
to those we do know, and believe to be universal.</p> 
<p>If Nature were governed by the laws of attraction only, 
every thing would be in a state of rest.  Bodies, tending 
toward one common centre, would there accumulate, and 
arrange themselves round it in the ratio of their gravity.  The 
substances which compose the globe would be so much 
heavier as they approached the centre, and those at the surface 
<pb n="224" id="PieStud224"/>would all be reduced to a level.  The bason of the seas 
would be choked with the wrecks of the land; and this magnificent 
architecture, formed of harmonies so various, would 
soon become an aquatic globe entirely.  All bodies, hurled 
downward by one common precipitation, would be condemned 
to an everlasting immobility.</p> 
<p>On the other hand, if the law of projection employed for 
explaining the motions of the heavenly bodies, on the supposition 
of their tendency to fly off in the tangent of a curve; 
if, I say, this law predominated, all bodies not actually adherent  
to the earth would be hurled from it, like stones from a 
sling: our globe itself, subjected to this law, would fly off 
from the sun never to return.  It would sometimes traverse 
the spaces of immensity, where no star would be perceptible 
for many ages; sometimes, swinging through regions where 
chance might have collected the matrices of creation, it might 
pass along amidst the elementary parts of suns, aggregated 
by the central laws of attraction, or scattered about in sparks 
and rays, by those of projection.</p> 
<p>But supposing these two contrary forces combined happily 
enough in favour of the globe, to fix it, with its vortex, in a 
corner of the firmament, where they should act without 
destroying themselves, it would present its equator to the 
sun as regularly as it describes its annual course round him. 
From those two constant motions never could be produced 
that other motion so varied, by which it daily inclines one of 
its poles toward the sun, till its axis has formed, on the plane 
of its annual circle, an angle of twenty-three degrees and a 
half; then that other retrograde motion, by which it presents 
to him, with equal regularity, the opposite pole.  Far from 
presenting to him alternately its poles, in order that his fertilizing 
heat may by turns melt their ices, it would regain 
them buried in eternal night and winter, with a part of the 
temperate zones, whereas the rest of its circumference would 
be burned up by the too constant fires of the tropics.</p> 
<p>But if we suppose a third variable law, which gives to the 
earth the movement that produces the seasons, and a fourth, 
which gives it the diurnal motion of rotation round itself; 
and that no one of these laws, so opposite, should ever surpass 
the others, and, at least, determine it to obey but one 
single impulsion; it would be impossible to affirm they had 
determined the forms and movements of the bodies on its 
<pb n="225" id="PieStud225"/>surface.  First, the force of projection, or centrifugal, would 
not have left upon it any one detached body.  On the other 
hand, the force of attraction, or gravity, would not have 
permitted the mountains to rise, and still less the metals, 
the heaviest part of them, to be placed at their summits, 
where they are usually found.</p> 
<p>Vegetables themselves, entirely subjected to the action of 
the elements, have configurations diversified without end. 
But how comes it that animals have the principles of so 
many motions, so entirely different?  Wherefore has not 
gravity nailed them down to the surface of the earth?  They 
ought to crawl along it at most.  How comes it to pass, that 
the laws which regulate the course of the stars, those laws 
whose influence has, in modern times, been made to extend 
even to the operations of the human soul, should permit the 
birds to rise into the air and fly as they please, notwithstanding 
the united powers of the attraction and projection of the globe?</p> 
<p>It is conformity, adaptation to use, which has regulated 
those laws, and generalized or suspended their effects subordinate 
to the necessities of sensible beings.  Though Nature 
employs an infinity of means, she permits man to know only 
the end she has in view.  Her works are subjected to rapid 
dissolutions; but she always suffers him to perceive the 
immortal consistency of her plans.  It is on this she wishes 
to fix his heart and mind.  She aims not at rendering man 
ingenious and proud, but good and happy.  She universally 
mitigates necessary evils; and multiplies blessings often 
superfluous.  In her harmonies, formed of contraries, she 
has opposed the empire od death to life; but life endures for 
an age, death only an instant.  She allows man to enjoy 
the expansions of beings, so delightful to behold; but conceals 
from him, with a precaution truly maternal, their transient 
state of dissolution.</p> 
<p>If an animal dies, if plants are decompounded in a morass, 
putrid emanations, and reptiles of a disgusting form, chase 
us away from them.  An infinite number of secondary beings 
are created for the purpose of hastening forward the decompositions. 
If cavernous mountains and rocks present appearances  
of ruin; owls, birds of prey, and ferocious animals, 
keep us at a distance.  Nature drives far from us the spectacles 
and the ministers of destruction, and allures us to her 
harmonies.</p> 
<pb n="226" id="PieStud226"/><p>From a profusion of this unbounded benevolence of Nature, 
the action of the sun is multiplied wherever it was most 
necessary, and mitigated where it might have been hurtful. 
When the orb of day has left us, the moon appears to reflect 
his light, with varieties in her phases which have relations, 
hitherto unknown, to a great number of species of animals, 
and especially of fishes, which travel only in the night-time, 
at the epochas which she indicates to them.  The farther the 
sun withdraws from one pole, the more are his rays refracted 
there; but when he has entirely abandoned it, then his lift 
is supplied in a most wonderful manner.  First, the moon, by 
a movement altogether incomprehensible, replaces him there, 
and appears perpetually above the horizon, as was observed 
in 1596, at Nova Zembla, by the unfortunate Dutchmen  
who wintered there, in the 76th degree of north latitude.</p> 
<p>In those dreadful climates Nature multiplies her resources, 
to bestow on sensible beings, and even on animals, the benefits  
of light and heat.  When the season returns, the sun reappears 
there before his natural term, as the Dutch mariners 
saw him to their astonishment above the horizon of Nova 
Zembla, on the 24th of January, fifteen days sooner than they 
expected him.  This return, so much earlier than their hopes, 
filled them with joy, and disconcerted the calculations of their 
intelligent pilot, the unfortunate Barents.</p> 
<p>Naturalists consider colours as accidents.  But if we attend 
to the general uses for which Nature employs them, we shall  
be persuaded there is not, even on rocks, a single shade impressed 
without a meaning and a purpose.  Let us observe 
the principal effects of the two extreme colours, white and 
black, with relation to the light.  Of all colours, white best 
reflects the rays of the sun, because it sends them back without 
any tint, as pure as it receives them; black, on the contrary, 
is the least adapted to their reflection, because it absorbs 
them.  Hence gardeners whiten the walls against which 
their espaliers are planted, to accelerate the maturity of their 
fruits, by the reverberation of the sun's rays; and opticians 
blacken the walls of the <hi rend="italic">camera-obscura,</hi> that their reflexes 
may not disturb the luminous picture on the tablet.</p> 
<p>Nature frequently employs contrary means for producing 
the same effect.  She makes glass with fire; she makes it 
too with water, crystal for instance: farther, she produces it 
from animal organization, such as certain transparent shell-<pb n="227" id="PieStud227"/>fish.  She forms the diamond by a process to us utterly unknown. 
Conclude now, because a body has been vitrified, it 
must certainly be by the effect of fire, and rear on this perception 
the system of the universe!  The utmost that we can do 
is to catch some harmonic instants in the existence of beings. 
That which is vitrifiable becomes calcareous, and what is calcareous 
changes into glass, by the action of the same fire. 
Deduce, then, from these simple modifications of the fossil 
kingdom, invariable characters for determining the general 
classes of it!</p> 
<p>On the other hand, Nature frequently employs the same 
means for producing effects directly contrary.  For example,  
to increase the heat over the lands of the north, and to mitigate  
it over those of the south, she makes use of opposite 
colours; she produces in both the same effects, by covering 
the face of both with rocks.  These rocks are essentially 
necessary to vegetation.</p> 
<p>Nature proposes to herself, universally, only the accommodation 
of beings possessed of sensibility.  This remark is all-important in the study of her works; otherwise, form the 
similitude which she employs, or the exceptions from them, 
we might be tempted to doubt of the consistency of her laws, 
instead of ascribing the majestic obscurity which pervades 
them to the multiplicity of her resources, and to the profundity 
of our own ignorance.</p> 
<p>This law of adaptation and conformity has been the source 
of all our discoveries.  It was this which wafted Columbus 
to America; because, as Herrera tells us,<note type="au" 
place="foot"><p>Herrera's History of the West-Indies, book i. chap. 2.</p></note> he 
thought, contrary 
to the opinion of the ancients, that the whole five zones 
must be inhabited, as GOD had not formed the earth to be a 
desert.  This law regulates our ideas respecting objects absolutely 
beyond the reach of our examination.  By means of 
it, though ignorant whether there may be men in the planets, 
we are assured there must be eyes, because there is light. 
It has awakened a sense of justice in the heart of every 
man, informing him there is another order of things after 
this life.  This law, in a word, is the most irresistible proof 
of the existence of GOD; for amidst such a multitude of 
adaptations, so ingenious and so numerous, that every day is 
presenting some with all the merit of novelty, the first of all, 
<pb n="228" id="PieStud228"/>which is the DEITY, must undoubtedly exist, as he is the 
general conformity of all particular conformities.</p> 
<p>How often, on coming out of the King's magnificent 
Cabinet of Natural History, do we stop mechanically to look 
at a gardener digging a hole in the field, or a carpenter hewing 
a piece of timber!  It looks as if we expected some new 
harmony to start out of the bosom of the earth, or burst from 
the side of a lump of oak.  We set no value on those we 
have just been enjoying, unless they lead us forward to 
others we do not know as yet.  But were the complete history 
given us of the stars of the firmament, and the invisible 
planets which encircle them, we should perceive a multitude 
of ineffable plans of intelligence and goodness, after which 
the heart would continue fondly to sigh: its last and only 
end is the DIVINITY himself.</p> 
</div2> 
</div1> 
 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
