<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="PouAoin"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="PouAoin"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Awoi No Uye</title>
<title type="sort">awoi no uye</title>
<author>Pound, Ezra and Fenollosa, Ernest</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>  
<name>Winnie Chan</name>  
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>  
<name/>  
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">20</num> kilobytes</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>  
<idno type="ETC">PouAoin</idno>  
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476329</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>  
<seriesStmt>
<p>Japanese Text Initiative</p>
</seriesStmt>  
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Footnotes in the print source have been moved to the end of the 
electronic document and numbered consecutively. For descriptive 
purposes, words or phrases preceding footnote markers in print source 
have been added to notes at the end of the electronic document.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>  
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Awoi No Uye</title>
<title level="m">"Noh" or Accomplishment: a Study of the Classical 
Stage in Japan</title>
<title type="sort">awoi no uye</title>
<author>Ezra Pound and Ernest Fenollosa</author>
</titleStmt>  
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt>  
<extent>pp. 193-205</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>MacMillan</publisher>  
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>  
<date value="1916">1916</date>  
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa Library call number PL 735 .F4 1916</idno>
</publicationStmt>  
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>  
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>  
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>  
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>  
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>  
</encodingDesc>  
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1916">1916</date>
</creation>  
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>  
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>drama; poetry; prose</term>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
</profileDesc>  
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-08">August 1997</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added milestones to correspond with WalAoin.</item>
</change>  
<change>
<date value="1996-12">December 1996</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Winnie Chan</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>  
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>  
<text id="d1"> 
 <front id="d2"> 
 
 <pb n="193"/>  
 
<div1 type="introduction" id="d3"> 
<head>AWOI NO UYE<lb/> 
A Play by Ujinobu<lb/> 
INTRODUCTION 
</head> 
 
<p> 
The story, as I understand it, is that the "Court Lady Awoi" (Flower of 
the East) is jealous of the other and later co-wives of Genji. This 
jealousy reaches its climax, and she goes off her head with it, when her 
carriage is overturned and broken at the Kami festival. The play opens 
with the death-bed of Awoi, and in Mrs. Fenollosa's diary I find the 
statement that "Awoi, her struggles, sickness, and death are represented 
by a red, flowered kimono, folded once length-wise, and laid at the front 
edge of the stage." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
The objective action is confined to the apparitions and exorcists. The 
demon of jealousy, tormenting Awoi, first appears in the form of the 
Princess Rakujo, then with the progress and success of the exorcism the 
jealous 
   
 
 <pb n="194"/>  
quintessence is driven out of this personal ghost, and appears in its own 
truly demonic ("hannya") form   &mdash;    "That awful face with its golden eyes 
and horns revealed."  The exorcist Miko is powerless against this demon, 
but the yamabushi exorcists, "advancing against it, making a grinding 
noise with the beads of their rosaries and striking against it," finally 
drive it away. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
The ambiguities of certain early parts of the play seem mainly due to the 
fact that the "Princess Rokujo," the concrete figure on the stage, is a 
phantom or image of Awoi no Uye's own jealousy. That is to say, Awoi is 
tormented by her own passion, and this passion obsesses her first in the 
form of a personal apparition of Rokujo, then in demonic form. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
This play was written before Ibsen declared that life is a "contest with 
the phantoms of the mind." The difficulties of the translator have lain in 
separating what belongs to Awoi herself from the things belonging to the 
ghost of Rokujo, very much as modern psychologists might have difficulty 
in detaching the personality or memories of an obsessed person from the 
personal memories of the obsession. Baldly: an obsessed person thinks he 
is Napoleon; an image of his own thought 
   
 
 <pb n="195"/>  
would be confused with scraps relating perhaps to St. Helena, Corsica, and 
Waterloo. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
The second confusion is the relation of the two apparitions. It seems 
difficult to make it clear that the "hannya" has been cast out of the 
ghostly personality, and that it had been, in a way, the motive force in 
the ghost's actions. And again we cannot make it too clear that the ghost 
is not actually a separate soul, but only a manifestation made possible 
through Awoi and her passion of jealousy. At least with this 
interpretation the play seems moderately coherent and lucid. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Rokujo or Awoi, whichever we choose to consider her, comes out of 
hell-gate in a chariot, "because people of her rank are always accustomed 
to go about in chariots. When they, or their ghosts, think of motion, they 
think of going in a chariot, therefore they take that form." There would 
be a model chariot shown somewhere at the back of the stage. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
The ambiguity of the apparition's opening line is, possibly, to arouse the 
curiosity of the audience. There will be an air of mystery, and they will 
not know whether it is to be the chariot associated with Genji's liaison 
with Yugawo, the beautiful heroine of the play 
   
 
 <pb n="196"/>  
Hajitomi, or whether it is the symbolic chariot drawn by a sheep, a deer, 
and an ox. But I think we are nearer the mark if we take Rokujo's 
enigmatic line, "I am come in three chariots," to mean that the formed 
idea of a chariot is derived from these events and from the mishap to 
Awoi's own chariot, all of which have combined and helped the spirit world 
to manifest itself concretely. Western students of ghostly folklore would 
tell you that the world of spirits is fluid and drifts about seeking 
shape. I do not wish to dogmatize on these points. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
The Fenollosa-Hirata draft calls the manifest spirit "The Princess 
Rokujo," and she attacks Awoi, who is represented by the folded kimono. 
Other texts seem to call this manifestation "Awoi no Uye," i.e. her mind 
or troubled spirit, and this spirit attacks her body. It will be perhaps 
simpler for the reader if I mark her speeches simply "Apparition," and 
those of the second form "Hannya." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
I do not know whether I can make the matter more plain or summarize it 
otherwise than by saying that the whole play is a dramatization, or 
externalization, of Awoi's jealousy. The passion makes her subject to the 
demon-possession. The demon first comes in a disguised and beautiful form. 
The prayer of 
   
 
 <pb n="197"/>  
the exorcist forces him first to appear in his true shape, and then to 
retreat. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
But the "disguised and beautiful form" is not a mere abstract sheet of 
matter. It is a sort of personal or living mask, having a ghost-life of 
its own; it is at once a shell of the princess, and a form, which is 
strengthened or made more palpable by the passion of Awoi. 
</p> 
</div1> 
</front> 
<body id="d4"> 
 
<div1 type="text" id="d5"> 
 
<head>AWOI NO UYE</head> 
 
<stage>Scene in Kioto</stage> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin1"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Daijin</speaker> 
<p> 
I am a subject in the service of the Blessed Emperor Shujakuin. They have 
called in the priests and the high priests for the sickness of Awoi no Uye 
of the house of Sadaijin. They prayed, but the gods give no sign. I am 
sent to Miko, the wise, to bid him pray to the spirits. Miko, will you 
pray to the earth? 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin2"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Miko</speaker> 
<lg type="stanza"> 
<l>Tenshojo, chishojo,</l> 
<l>Naigeshojo, Rakkonshojo.</l> 
</lg> 
 
<lg type="stanza"> 
<l>Earth, pure earth,</l> 
<l>Wither, by the sixteen roots</l> 
<l>(Wither this evil)!</l> 
</lg> 
</sp> 
   
 
 <pb n="198"/>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin3"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Apparition</speaker> 
<p> 
It may be, it may be, I come from the gate of hell in three coaches. I am 
sorry for Yugawo and the carriage with broken wheels. And the world is 
ploughed with sorrow as a field is furrowed with oxen. 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin4"/> 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin5"/> 
Man's life is a 
wheel on the axle, there is no turn whereby to escape. His hold is light 
as dew on the Basho leaf. It seems that the last spring's blossoms are 
only a dream in the mind. And we fools take it all, take it all as a 
matter of course. Oh, I am grown envious from sorrow. I come to seek 
consolation. 
 
<stage> 
Singing. 
</stage> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin6"/>  
Though I lie all night hid for shame in the secret carriage, looking at 
the moon for sorrow, yet I would not be seen by the moon. 
</p> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin7"/> 
<lg type="poem"> 
<l>Where Miko draws the magical bow,</l> 
<l>I would go to set my sorrow aloud.</l> 
</lg> 
 
<stage> 
Speaking. 
</stage> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin8"/>  
<p> 
Where does that sound of playing come from? It is the sound of the bow of 
Adzusa! 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin9"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Miko</speaker> 
<p> 
Though I went to the door of the square building, Adzumaya   &mdash;    
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin10"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Apparition</speaker> 
<p> 
   &mdash;   you thought no one came to knock. 
</p> 
</sp> 
   
 
 <pb n="199"/>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin11"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Miko</speaker> 
<p> 
How strange! It is a lady of high rank whom I do not know. She comes in a 
broken carriage, a green wife clings to the shaft. She weeps. 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin12"/> 
Is it   &mdash;    
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin13"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Daijin</speaker> 
<p> 
Yes, I think I know who it is. 
 
<stage> 
To the Apparition. 
</stage> 
 
I ask you to tell me your name. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin14"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Apparition</speaker> 
<p> 
In the world of the swift-moving lightning I have no servant or envoi, 
neither am I consumed with self-pity. I came aimlessly hither, drawn only 
by the sound of the bow. Who do you think I am? I am the spirit of the 
Princess Rokujo, 
<ref target="n199.1">[1]</ref> 
and when I was still in the world, spring was there with me. I feasted 
upon the cloud with the Sennin, 
<ref target="n199.2">[2]</ref> 
they shared in my feast of flowers. And on the Evening of Maple Leaves I 
had the moon for a mirror. I was drunk with colour and perfume. And for 
all my gay flare at that time I am now like a shut Morning-glory, awaiting 
the sunshine. And now I am come for a whim, I am come uncounting the hour, 
seizing upon no set 
   
 
 <pb n="200"/>  
moment. I would set my sorrow aside. Let some one else bear it awhile. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin15"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<p> 
Love turns back toward the lover, unkindness brings evil return. It is for 
no good deed or good purpose that you bring back a sorrow among us, our 
sorrows mount up without end. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin17"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Apparition</speaker> 
<p>The woman is hateful! I cannot keep back my blows. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<stage> 
She strikes. 
</stage> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin18"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Miko</speaker> 
<p> 
No. You are a princess of Rokujo! How can you do such things? Give 
over. Give over. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin19"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Apparition</speaker> 
<p> 
I cannot. However much you might pray. 
<stage> 
Reflectively, as if detached from her action, and describing it. 
</stage> 
So she went toward the pillow, and struck. Struck. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<sp> 
<speaker>Miko</speaker> 
<p> 
Then standing up   &mdash;    
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin21"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Apparition</speaker> 
<p> 
This hate is only repayment 
</p> 
</sp> 
   
 
 <pb n="201"/>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin22"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Miko</speaker> 
<p> 
The flame of jealousy   &mdash;    
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin23"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Apparition</speaker> 
<p> 
   &mdash;   will turn on one's own hand and burn. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin24"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Miko</speaker> 
<p> 
Do you not know? 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<sp> 
<speaker>Apparition</speaker> 
<p> 
Know! This is a just revenge. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin26"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<lg type="poem"> 
<l>Hateful, heart full of hate,</l> 
<l>Though you are full of tears</l> 
<l>Because of others' dark hatred,</l> 
<l>Your love for Genji</l> 
<l>Will not be struck out</l> 
<l>Like a fire-fly's flash in the dark.</l> 
</lg> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin27"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Apparition</speaker> 
<p> 
I, like a bush   &mdash;    
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin28"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<lg type="poem"> 
<l>   &mdash;   am a body that has no root.</l> 
<l>I fade as dew from the leaf,</l> 
<l>Partly for that cause I hate her,</l> 
<l>My love cannot be restored. . .</l> 
<l>Not even in a dream.</l> 
</lg> 
   
 
 <pb n="202"/>  
<p> 
It is a gleam cast up from the past. I am full of longing. I would be off 
in the secret coach, and crush her shade with me. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin29"/>
<sp> 
<speaker>Daijin</speaker> 
<p> 
Help. Awoi no Uye is sinking. Can you find Kohijiri of Tokokawa? 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin30"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Kiogen</speaker> 
<p> 
I will call him. I call him. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin31"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Waki (Kohijiri)</speaker> 
<p> 
Do you call me to a fit place for prayer? To the window of the nine 
wisdoms, to the cushion of the ten ranks, to a place full of holy waters, 
and where there is a clear moon? 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<sp> 
<speaker>Kiogen</speaker> 
<p> 
Yes, yes. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin33"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Waki</speaker> 
<p> 
How should I know? I do not go about in the world. You come from the 
Daijin. Wait. I am ready. I will come. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<stage> 
He crosses the stage or bridge. 
</stage> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin34"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Daijin</speaker> 
<p> 
I thank you for coming. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin35"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Waki</speaker> 
<p> 
Where is the patient? 
</p> 
</sp> 
   
 
 <pb n="203"/>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin36"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Daijin</speaker> 
<p> 
She is there on that bed. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin37"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Waki</speaker> 
<p> 
I will begin the exorcism at once. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin38"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Daijin</speaker> 
<p> 
I thank you. Please do so. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin39"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Waki</speaker> 
<stage> 
beginning the ritual 
</stage> 
<p> 
Then Gioja called upon En no Gioja, and he hung about his shoulders a 
cloak that had swept the dew of the seven jewels in climbing the peaks of 
Tai Kou and of Kori in Riobu. He wore the cassock of forbearance to keep 
out unholy things. He took the beads of red wood, the square beads with 
hard corners, and whirling and striking said prayer. But one prayer. 
</p> 
 
<lg type="poem"> 
<l>Namaku, Samanda, Basarada.</l> 
</lg> 
</sp> 
 
<stage> 
During this speech the APPARITION has disappeared. That is, the first 
SHITE, the PRINCESS OF ROKUJO. Her costume was "The under kimono black 
satin, tight from the knees down, embroidered with small, irregular, 
infrequent circles of flowers; the upper part, stiff gold 
   
 
 <pb n="204"/>  
brocade, just shot through with purples, greens, and reds." 
</stage> 
 
<stage> 
The HANNYA has come on. Clothed in a scarlet hakama, white upper dress, 
and "The terrible mask with golden eyes." She has held a white scarf over 
her head. She looks up. Here follows the great dance climax of the play. 
</stage> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin40"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Hannya</speaker> 
<stage> 
threatening 
</stage> 
<p> 
Oh, Gioja, turn back! Turn back, or you rue it. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin41"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Waki</speaker> 
<p> 
Let whatever evil spirit is here bow before Gioja, and know that Gioja 
will drive it out. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<stage> 
He continues whirling the rosary. 
</stage> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin42"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<stage> 
invoking the powerful good spirits 
</stage> 
<p> 
On the east stand Gosanze Miowo. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin43"/>   
<sp> 
<speaker>Hannya</speaker> 
<stage> 
opposing other great spirits 
</stage> 
<p> 
On the south stand Gundari Yasha. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin44"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<p> 
On the west stand Dai Itoku Miowo. 
</p> 
</sp>
   
 
 <pb n="205"/>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin45"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Hannya</speaker> 
<p> 
On the north stand Kongo   &mdash;    
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin46"/>   
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<p> 
   &mdash;   Yasha Miowo. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin47"/>   
<sp> 
<speaker>Hannya</speaker> 
<p> 
In the middle Dai Sei   &mdash;    
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin48"/>   
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<lg type="poem"> 
<l rend="indent">Fudo Miowo</l> 
<l>Namaku Samanda Basarada!</l> 
<l>Senda Makaroshana Sowataya</l> 
<l>Wun tarata Kamman,</l> 
<l>Choga Sessha Tokudai Chiye</l> 
<l>Chiga Shinja Sokushin Jobutsu.</l> 
</lg> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin49"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Hannya</speaker> 
<stage> 
overcome by the exorcism 
</stage> 
<p> 
O terrible names of the spirits. This is my last time. I cannot return 
here again. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Aoin50"/>   
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<p> 
By hearing the scripture the evil spirit is melted. Bosatsu came hither, 
his face was full of forbearance and pity. Pity has melted her heart, and 
she has gone into Buddha. Thanksgiving. 
</p> 
</sp>
   
</div1> 
</body>  
 
<back id="d6"> 
<div1 type="notes" id="d7"> 
<note id="n199.1"><seg type="note-symbol">[1:</seg> <p>I am the Princess Rokujo. . .] As in Western 
folk-lore, demons often appear first in some splendid disguise.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n199.2"><seg type="note-symbol">[2:</seg> <p>the Sennin] Spirits not unlike the Irish 
"Sidhe."</p></note> 
</div1> 
</back> 
 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
