<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="PouKage"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="PouKage"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Kagekiyo</title>
<title type="sort">kagekiyo</title>
<author>Pound, Ezra and Fenollosa, Ernest</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>  
<name>Winnie Chan</name>  
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>  
<name/>  
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">18</num> kilobytes</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>  
<idno type="ETC">PouKage</idno>  
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476331</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>  
<seriesStmt>
<p>Japanese Text Initiative</p>
</seriesStmt>  
<notesStmt>  
<note>
<p>Footnotes in the print source have been moved to the end of the 
electronic document and numbered consecutively. For descriptive 
purposes, words and phrases preceding footnote markers in print source 
have been added to footnotes at the end of the electronic document.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>  
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Kagekiyo</title>
<title level="m">"Noh" or Accomplishment: a Study of the Classical Stage in Japan</title>
<title type="sort">kagekiyo</title>
<author>Ezra Pound and Ernest Fenollosa</author>
</titleStmt>  
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt>  
<extent>pp. 177-188</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>MacMillan</publisher>  
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>  
<date value="1916">1916</date>  
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa Library call number PL 735 .F4 1916</idno>
</publicationStmt>  
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>  
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>  
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>  
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>  
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>  
</encodingDesc>  
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1916">1916</date>
</creation>  
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>  
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>drama; poetry; prose</term>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
</profileDesc>  
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-09">September 1997</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added milestones to correspond with WalKage.</item>
</change>  
<change>
<date value="1996-12">December 1996</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Winnie Chan</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>  
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>  
 
<text id="d1"> 
 

<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="play" id="d3"> <pb n="177"/>  
<head>KAGEKIYO<lb/> 
A Play in one Act, by Motokiyo 
</head> 
 
<list> 
<head>CHARACTERS</head> 
<item>Shite, Kagekiyo old and blind.</item> 
<item>Tsure, a girl, his daughter, called Hitomaru.</item> 
<item>Tomo, her attendant.</item> 
<item>Waki, a villager.</item> 
</list> 
 
<p>The scene is in HIUGA. 
</p> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage1"/>
<sp> 
<speaker>Girl and Attendant</speaker> 
<stage>chanting</stage> 
<p> 
What should it be; the body of dew, wholly at the mercy of wind? 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage2"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Girl</speaker> 
<lg type="poem"> 
<l>I am a girl named Hitomaru from the river valley Kamegaye-ga-Yatsu,</l> 
<l>My father, Akushichi-bioye Kagekiyo,</l> 
<l>Fought by the side of Heike,</l> 
<l>And is therefore hated by Genji.</l> 
<l>He was banished to Miyazaki in Hiuga,</l> 
<l>To waste out the end of his life.</l> 
 
 
<pb n="178"/>  
<l>Though I am unaccustomed to travel,</l> 
<l>I will try to go to my father.</l> 
</lg> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage3"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Girl and Attendant</speaker> 
 
<stage> 
describing the journey as they walk across the bridge and the stage 
</stage> 
<lg type="poem"> 
<l>Sleeping with the grass for our pillow,</l> 
<l>The dew has covered our sleeves.</l> 
</lg> 
 
<stage> 
Singing. 
</stage> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage4"/> 
<lg type="poem"> 
<l>Of whom shall I ask my way</l> 
<l>As I go out from Sagami province?</l> 
<l>Of whom in Totomi?</l> 
<l>I crossed the bay in a small hired boat</l> 
<l>And came to Yatsuhashi in Mikawa;</l> 
<l>Ah, when shall I see the City-on-the-cloud?</l> 
</lg> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage5"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Attendant</speaker> 
<p> 
As we have come so fast, we are now in Miyazaki of Hiuga. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
It is here you should ask for your father. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage6"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Kagekiyo</speaker> 
 
<stage> 
in another corner of the stage 
</stage> 
 
<p> 
Sitting at the gate of the pine wood I wear out the end of my years. I 
cannot see the clear light, I do not know how the time passes. I sit here 
in this dark hovel, with one coat for  
 
 
<pb n="179"/>  
the warm and the cold, and my body is but a framework of bones. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage7"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<p> 
May as well be a priest with black sleeves. Now having left the world in 
sorrow, I look upon my withered shape. There is no one to pity me now. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage8"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Girl</speaker> 
<p> 
Surely no one can live in that ruin, and yet a voice sounds from it. A 
beggar, perhaps. Let us take a few steps and see. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage9"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Kagekiyo</speaker> 
<p> 
My eyes will not show it me, yet the autumn wind is upon us. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage10"/>
<sp> 
<speaker>Girl</speaker> 
<p> 
The wind blows from an unknown past, and spreads our doubts through the 
world. The wind blows, and I have no rest, nor any place to find quiet. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage11"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Kagekiyo</speaker> 
<p> 
Neither in the world of passion, nor in the world of colour, nor in the 
world of non-colour, is there any such place of rest; beneath the one sky 
are they all. Whom shall I ask, and how answer? 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
 
<pb n="180"/>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage12"/>
<sp> 
<speaker>Girl</speaker> 
<p> 
Shall I ask the old man by the thatch? 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage13"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Kagekiyo</speaker> 
<p> 
Who are you? 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage14"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Girl</speaker> 
<p> 
Where does the exile live? 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage15"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Kagekiyo</speaker> 
<p> 
What exile? 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage16"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Girl</speaker> 
<p> 
One who is called Akushichi-bioye Kagekiyo, a noble who fought with Heike. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage17"/>
<sp> 
<speaker>Kagekiyo</speaker> 
<p> 
Indeed? I have heard of him, but I am blind, I have not looked in his 
face. I have heard of his wretched condition and pity him. You had better 
ask for him at the next place. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage18"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Attendant</speaker> 
 
<stage> 
to girl 
</stage> 
 
<p> 
It seems that he is not here, shall we ask further? 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<stage> 
They pass on. 
</stage> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage19"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Kagekiyo</speaker> 
<p> 
Strange, I feel that woman who has just passed is the child of that blind 
man. Long  
 
 
<pb n="181"/>  
ago I loved a courtesan in Atsuta, one time when I was in that place. But 
I thought our girl-child would be no use to us, and I left her with the 
head man in the valley of Kamegaye-ga-yatsu; and now she has gone by me 
and spoken, although she does not know who I am. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage20"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<lg type="poem"> 
<l>Although I have heard her voice,</l> 
<l>The pity is, that I cannot see her.</l> 
<l>And I have let her go by</l> 
<l>Without divulging my name.</l> 
<l>This is the true love of a father.</l> 
</lg> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage21"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Attendant</speaker> 
<stage> 
at further side of the stage 
</stage> 
<p> 
Is there any native about? 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage22"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Villager</speaker> 
<p> 
What do you want with me? 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage23"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Attendant</speaker> 
<p> 
Do you know where the exile lives? 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage24"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Villager</speaker> 
<p> 
What exile is it you want? 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage25"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Attendant</speaker> 
<p> 
Akushichi-bioye Kagekiyo, a noble of Heike's party. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
 
<pb n="182"/>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage26"/>
<sp> 
<speaker>Villager</speaker> 
<p> 
Did not you pass an old man under the edge of the mountain as you were 
coming that way? 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage27"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Attendant</speaker> 
<p> 
A blind beggar in a thatched cottage. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage28"/>
<sp> 
<speaker>Villager</speaker> 
<p> 
That fellow was Kagekiyo. What ails the lady, she shivers? 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage29"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Attendant</speaker> 
<p> 
A question you might well ask, she is the exile's daughter. She wanted to 
see her father once more, and so came hither to seek him. Will you take us 
to Kagekiyo? 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage30"/>
<sp> 
<speaker>Villager</speaker> 
<p> 
Bless my soul! Kagekiyo's daughter. Come, come, never mind, young miss. 
Now I will tell you, Kagekiyo went blind in both eyes, and so he shaved 
his crown and called himself "The blind man of Hiuga." He begs a bit from 
the passers, and the likes of us keep him; he'd be ashamed to tell you his 
name. However, I'll come along with you, and then I'll call out, 
"Kagekiyo!" and if he comes, you can see him and have a word with him. Let 
us along. 
</p> 
 
<stage>They cross the stage, and the  
 
 
<pb n="183"/>  
villager calls 
</stage> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage31"/> 
<p> 
Kagekiyo! Oh, there, Kagekiyo! 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage32"/>
<sp> 
<speaker>Kagekiyo</speaker> 
<p> 
Noise, noise! Some one came from my home to call me, but I sent them on. I 
couldn't be seen like this. Tears like the thousand lines in a rain storm, 
bitter tears soften my sleeve. Ten thousand things rise in a dream, and I 
wake in this hovel, wretched, just a nothing in the wide world. How can I 
answer when they call me by my right name? 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage33"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<p> 
Do not call out the name he had in his glory. You will move the bad blood 
in his heart. 
</p> 
 
<stage> 
Then, taking up Kagekiyo's thought 
</stage> 
 
<p> 
I am angry. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage34"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Kagekiyo</speaker> 
<p> 
Living here. . . 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage35"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<stage> 
going on with Kagekiyo's thought 
</stage> 
 
<p> 
I go on living here, hated by the people in power. A blind man without his 
staff. I am deformed, and therefore speak evil; excuse me. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage36"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Kagekiyo</speaker> 
<p> 
My eyes are darkened. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
 
<pb n="184"/>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage37"/>
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<p> 
Though my eyes are dark I understand the thoughts of another. I understand 
at a word. The wind comes down from the pine trees on the mountain, and 
snow comes down after the wind. The dream tells of my glory. I am loath to 
wake from the dream. I hear the waves running in the evening tide, as when 
I was with Heike. Shall I act out the old ballad? 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage38"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Kagekiyo</speaker> 
 
<stage> 
to the villager 
</stage> 
 
<p> 
I had a weight on my mind, I spoke to you very harshly; excuse me. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage39"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Villager</speaker> 
<p> 
You're always like that, never mind it. Has any one been here to see you? 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage40"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Kagekiyo</speaker> 
<p> 
No one but you. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage41"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Villager</speaker> 
<p> 
Go on! That is not true. Your daughter was here. Why couldn't you tell her 
the truth, she being so sad and so eager? I have brought her back now. 
Come now, speak with your father. Come along. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
 
<pb n="185"/>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage42"/>
<sp> 
<speaker>Girl</speaker> 
<p> 
Oh, Oh, I came such a long journey, under rain, under wind, wet with dew, 
over the frost; you do not see into my heart. It seems that a father's 
love goes when the child is not worth it. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage43"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Kagekiyo</speaker> 
<p> 
I meant to keep it concealed, but now they have found it all out. I shall 
drench you with the dew of my shame, you who are young as a flower. I tell 
you my name, and that we are father and child, yet I thought this would 
put dishonour upon you, and therefore I let you pass. Do not hold it 
against me. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage44"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<p> 
At first I was angry that my friends would no longer come near me. But now 
I have come to a time when I could not believe that even a child of my own 
would seek me out. 
</p> 
 
<stage> 
Singing. 
</stage> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage45"/> 
<lg type="poem"> 
<l>Upon all the boats of the men of Heike's faction</l> 
<l>Kagekiyo was the fighter most in call,</l> 
<l>Brave were his men, cunning sailors,</l> 
<l>And now even the leader</l> 
<l>Is worn out and dull as a horse.</l> 
</lg> 
</sp> 
 
 
<pb n="186"/>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage46"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Villager</speaker> 
 
<stage> 
to Kagekiyo 
</stage> 
 
<p> 
Many a fine thing is gone, sir, your daughter would like to ask you. . . . 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage47"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Kagekiyo</speaker> 
<p> 
What is it? 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage48"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Villager</speaker> 
<p> 
She has heard of your fame from the old days. Would you tell her the 
ballad? 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage51"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Kagekiyo</speaker> 
<p> 
Towards the end of the third month, it was in the third year of Juei. We 
men of Heike were in ships, the men of Genji were on land. Their war-tents 
stretched on the shore. We awaited decision. And Noto-no-Kami Noritsune 
said: "Last year in the hills of Harima, and in Midzushima, and in 
Hiyodorigoye of Bitchiu, we were defeated time and again, for Yoshitsune 
is tactful and cunning. Is there any way we can beat them?" Kagekiyo 
thought in his mind: "This Hangan Yoshitsune is neither god nor a devil, 
at the risk of my life I might do it." So he took leave of Noritsune and 
led a party against the shore, and all the men of Genji rushed on them. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
 
<pb n="187"/>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage52"/>
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<p> 
Kagekiyo cried, "You are haughty." His armour caught every turn of the 
sun. He drove them four ways before them. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage53"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Kagekiyo</speaker> 
<stage> 
excited and crying out 
</stage> 
 
<p> 
Samoshiya! Run, cowards! 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage54"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<p> 
He thought, how easy this killing. He rushed with his spear-haft gripped 
under his arm. He cried out, "I am Kagekiyo of the Heike." He rushed on to 
take them. He pierced through the helmet vizards of Miyonoya. Miyonoya 
fled twice, and again; and Kagekiyo cried: "You shall not escape me!" He 
leaped and wrenched off his helmet. "Eya!" The vizard broke and remained 
in his hand and Miyonoya still fled afar, and afar, and he looked back 
crying in terror, "How terrible, how heavy your arm!" And Kagekiyo called 
at him, "How tough the shaft of your neck is!" And they both laughed out 
over the battle, and went off each his own way. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Kage55"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<p> 
These were the deeds of old, but oh, to tell them! to be telling them over 
now in his  
 
 
<pb n="188"/>  
wretched condition. His life in the world is weary, he is near the end of 
his course. "Go back," he would say to his daughter. "Pray for me when I 
am gone from the world, for I shall then count upon you as we count on a 
lamp in the darkness . . . we who are blind." "I will stay," she said. 
Then she obeyed him, and only one voice is left. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
We tell this for the remembrance. Thus were the parent and child. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
 
<back id="d4"> 
<div1 type="note" id="d5"> 
<head>NOTE</head> 
<p> Fenollosa has left this memorandum on the stoicism of the last play: I 
asked Mr. Hirata how it could be considered natural or dutiful for the 
daughter to leave her father in such a condition. He said, "that the 
Japanese would not be in sympathy with such sternness now, but that it was 
the old Bushido spirit. The personality of the old man is worn out, no 
more good in this life. It would be sentimentality for her to remain with 
him. No good could be done. He could well restrain his love for her, 
better that she should pray for him and go on with the work of her normal 
life." </p> 
</div1> 
</back> 
 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
