<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="PulPueb"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>        
 
<TEI.2 id="PulPueb"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Pueblo of Acoma</title>
<title type="sort">pueblo of acoma</title>
<author>Pullen, Clarence</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">22</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">PulPueb</idno> 
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476339</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Pueblo of Acoma</title>
<title level="j">Harper's Weekly</title>
<title type="sort">pueblo of acoma</title>
<author>Clarence Pullen</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harper's Weekly</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1890-08-02">2 August 1890</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 34, pp. 594-595</p>
</seriesStmt>  
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the 
text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1890">1890</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term> 
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-08">August 1994</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Kelly Tetterton, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Minimal TEI tagging</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 

<text id="d1">  

<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="594"/>  
<head>Pullen, Clarence.  "The Pueblo of Acoma."  <hi rend="italic">Harper's Weekly</hi> 34, 
2 August 1890: 594-595.</head>

<p>PERHAPS the most interesting people among the aborigines of 
the American continent are the Pueblo (town) Indians of New Mexico 
and Arizona, who have an ethnological affinity, if not a direct 
kinship, with the succession of different migratory peoples, 
beginning with the Toltecs and ending with the Aztecs, who, between 
the seventh and the twelfth centuries, passed southward from the 
unknown region, Aztlan, to colonize the Valley of Mexico and its 
environing vales and plains.  The substantial and permanent 
character of the houses composing the pueblos of these tribes, each 
tiny town being an independent community; the primitive 
civilization that still prevails among their inhabitants, unchanged 
in centuries; the adherence of the people to pastoral, 
horticultural, and agricultural pursuits; their gentleness, 
hospitality, industry, and thrift; their bravery in defence of home 
and liberty; their chastity; and the isolation that each existing 
pueblo has maintained in the midst of surrounding tribes and the 
settlements of the whites &mdash; are all noteworthy characteristics; and 
in their social relations within each city these Indians afford as 
nearly as has ever been attained an example of rational and 
successful communism. 
</p><p>Among the nineteen communities of these Indians in New Mexico, 
the pueblo of Acoma, in Valencia County, ranks with Zuni in its 
attractiveness to the ethnologist and the archaeologist, and it is 
unique in location, being aptly termed "a city in the sky."  The 
surrounding country is of the most rugged, broken, and varied 
character, consisting of table-lands cut irregularly by precipitous 
canons and separated by mountain ranges.  A few miles to the west 
of Acoma, between that pueblo and Zuni, the lava flood poured forth 
in prehistoric times from a volcano now long extinct, overspreading 
the plain, cracked, as it cooled and hardened, into a long heap of 
enormous jagged black rocks, called by the Mexicans <hi rend="italic">malpais</hi> &mdash; a 
petrified torrent two miles in width and many miles in length, 
presenting, save for one narrow gap, through which winds a stony, 
difficult trail, an impassable barrier to the passage of man or 
beast.  East of this lava bed a large canon with precipitous sides 
expands into a valley four miles wide and ten miles long, opening 
to the northeast.  From the surface of this extensive basin rise 
great detached sandstone buttes in various forms of pinnacles &mdash;  
pyramids, pillars, and obelisks &mdash; some of which are several hundred 
feet high, the whole presenting a strange and grotesque spectacle, 
like a city of wonder-land.  On the level barren summit of an 
enormous isolated sandstone rock, or mesa, that rises steep and 
high from the plain, is situated the pueblo of Acoma, at an 
elevation of 7500 feet above the sea-level. 
</p><p>The first written account of this pueblo is by Castaneda, the 
historian of Coronado's military expedition into New Mexico in the 
year 1541, who relates that Captain Hernando de Alvarado, with a 
party of twenty men, while exploring the country to the eastward of 
Zuni, arrived at the village of Acoma &mdash; called by the natives A-go, 
and by the Spaniards Acuco &mdash; "a very strong place, built upon a rock 
very high, and on three sides perpendicular.  The inhabitants are 
great brigands, much dreaded by all the provinces."  The pueblo 
could muster two hundred warriors, and from their audacious and 
martial spirit and the security of their impregnable stronghold, 
the Acomas were able to defy the other pueblos, as well as their 
hereditary enemies the Navajos.  Castaneda's description of the 
village applies almost precisely to its appearance to-day.  He 
states that the sides of the rock on which it stood were so 
precipitous that the ascent of it by human beings was impossible 
except at one place, where a stairway led from the plain up to the 
village.  This stairway was of sufficient width for the first two 
hundred steps, but after ascending these, there were encountered 
one hundred steps far more difficult, and then a perpendicular 
ascent of twelve feet remained, which could only be climbed by the 
use of holes made in the face of the rock, which compelled the 
climber to make use of both hands and feet. 
</p><p>On the summit were heaped huge stones, which the defenders, 
without exposing themselves, could roll down on any assailants of 
their stronghold, so that no army, whatever its strength might be, 
could force a passage within the town.  Upon the flat top of the 
bluff was stored a large quantity of corn, and cisterns sunk in the 
solid rock supplied the inhabitants with water.  On the approach of 
the Spaniards, the Indians came down boldly into the plain, and 
tracing lines upon the ground, haughtily forbade them to pass over 
them; but when they saw the undaunted Alvarado prepare his company 
to attack them, they suddenly changed their tone, sued for peace, 
and in token of amity presented the Spaniards with a great quantity 
of poultry, together with bread, deer-skins, pine nuts, seeds, 
flour, and corn. 
</p><p>In the year 1598, when New Mexico first was colonized by the 
Spaniards under Juan de Onate, the Acomas attacked the Maestro de 
Campo, Juan de Zaldiver, and fifteen of his men, who were visiting 
their village, and killed the commander and all of his party except 
one officer and four men.  These five Spaniards, being pressed by 
the Indians, leaped boldly down the face of the cliff.  Strange to 
say, but one of the five was killed, the remainder reaching the 
bottom without fatal injury.  Two months later, a force of the 
Spaniards, under command of Vicente de Zaldivar, stormed the rock 
and town of Acoma, and its inhabitants afterward consented that 
Franciscan missionaries should make their home among them, the 
tribe eventually being converted to a nominal Christianity. 
</p><p>In the year 1680 the people of Acoma joined in the successful 
insurrection of the New-Mexican Pueblo Indians against their 
Spanish oppressors, and thereafter enjoyed a period of independence 
and paganism until 1692, when Governor Don Diego de Vargas Zapata 
Lujan, in his reconquest of the province of New Mexico, reached 
Acoma, and drew up his force before the rock.  After some 
negotiations the natives surrendered, and De Vargas and the pueblo 
chief, Mateo, publicly embraced each other, after which a large 
cross was erected, and the ceremony of absolution and a general 
baptism took place.  Since the beginning of the seventeenth century 
this pueblo has been, professedly at least, an orthodox Catholic 
community. 
</p><p>Acoma is situated about eighteen miles in a southeasterly 
direction from McCarthy Station on the Atlantic and Pacific 
Railway, midway between Albuquerque and Fort Wingate.  Its people, 
like those of Moqui and Zuni, have retained to a great extent their 
ancient customs.  The walls of light-tinted sandstone, "nearly 
everywhere vertical or overhanging," of the bluff or "penol" on 
which the town stands rise from two hundred and fifty to three 
hundred feet above the plain.  Against their bases the sand has 
blown in great drifts, extending far up into the recesses and 
fissures of the cliffs.  Until within recent years, as in the days 
of its discovery by Alvarado, only one path gave access to the top.  
It is a toilsome and dangerous route, winding along the edge of 
frightful chasms, leading up through fissures, and passing over 
crags.  In places steps have been hewn, and up the face of the 
naked rock holes have been cut to give a foothold to climbers, and 
the constant use of these holes by the Indians through centuries 
has worn them to the exact shape of the toe of a moccasin.  Up this 
steep path an Acoma Indian with a live sheep on his shoulders will 
run rapidly without helping his ascent in any way by the use of his 
hands. 
</p><p>The Acomas use this foot-path yet, but they have in recent 
years made on the opposite side a horse trail, very steep and 
difficult, which winds up over immense sand drifts and steep rocky 
ledges to the top of the rock.  Up this bridle-path animals that 
are accustomed to mountain climbing can go in single file.  The 
surface of the top of the mesa, comprising about ten acres, is 
naturally a rough naked space destitute of vegetation.  the town is 
constructed after the usual style of the pueblos of New Mexico, and 
consists of from sixty to seventy houses two or three stories high, 
built of adobe or of rubble-stone, rising terrace-shaped, with flat 
roofs.  There are no windows in the first story, or doors, except 
in the roof, which is reached by means of ladders.  Within the 
houses are several estufas, or apartments used as council-chambers 
and for the secret practice of the Acomas' ancient religious rites, 
including the maintenance of the sacred fire in honor of their 
ancient gods.  The two has about eight hundred inhabitants, and is 
divided by three parallel streets. 
</p><p>The people, in early days so warlike and arrogant, are now 
peaceable, and maintain themselves from their flocks and herds and 
the tillage of their agricultural lands, which lie from fourteen to 
sixteen miles from the pueblo, on the line of the Atlantic and 
Pacific Railroad, where they have their summer villages of Aconista 
and Pueblito.  Here they raise corn, beans, pumpkins, and melons, 
and have productive orchards of peaches and apricots.  Upon the 
cliff there are no springs, but there is a large water-tank about 
one hundred and fifty feet long, twenty feet broad, and five feet 
deep.  This tank is filled with snow in the winter, and during the 
summer rain-water is collected in it, furnishing the water required 
by the inhabitants.  The Acomas do all their cooking in earthen 
vessels of their own manufacture.  Their pottery is of fine quality 
and very handsome, being readily distinguishable among the coarser 
work of some of the other pueblos.  Furniture is unknown among 
them, and the people sleep on sheepskins spread on the floor.  
Their houses are neat and orderly, some of them being whitewashed 
without and within.  The roofs in the season are covered with 
drying 
<pb n="595"/>    
peaches and apricots, and against the walls hang 
festoons of bright red peppers and strings of pumpkins and 
muskmelons, cut into ropes and twisted into bunches, which are 
dried for winter use.  The horses, asses, cattle, sheep, and goats 
of the pueblo are herded in the great basin below the village, 
which is an excellent stock range.  The soil is of a nature to 
produce fine crops, but owing to the absence of watercourses it 
cannot be utilized for agriculture except through the construction 
of a reservoir system for the retention of the summer rains and 
floods, a work that may some day be undertaken, and which will 
probably be attended by successful results. 
</p><p>About a mile from Acoma is La Mesa Encantada (the Enchanted 
Hill), with perpendicular walls rising four hundred feet high from 
the plain.  There is a weird tradition of this lofty cliff related 
by Mr. James W. Steele, who states that on this mesa was anciently 
the home of the people of Acoma.  One day in harvest-time the whole 
population of the town &mdash; men, women, and children &mdash; with the 
exception of three ailing women, were in the valley below, working 
together, according to their custom on such occasions.  A 
cloudburst, as the sudden rain floods of the country are called, 
occurred up the valley, and a great wave swept down, undermining 
the sand upon which rested the narrow staircase of notched rock by 
which alone the top of the mesa could be reached.  When the people 
returned, they found that where the stairs had been, the whole side 
of the mesa had fallen in a heap in the valley below, leaving the 
summit absolutely inaccessible.  The three women could be seen 
above, wandering around the edges, waving their arms, and shouting, 
but no help could reach them.  The skeletons of these women lie 
somewhere on the summit, where still are the walls of the old city; 
but nobody has ascended the Mesa Encantada since the day of the 
disastrous flood. 
</p><p>Like the people of all the other New Mexican Pueblo tribes, 
the Acomas have their annual festivals, the origin of which is lost 
in the mystery of the prehistoric ages.  The Catholic priests put 
all the Christian veneering possible over the essential heathenism 
of the ceremonials, and under their influence these celebrations 
occur usually on or near some saint's day.  Conspicuous among these 
jubilations is the harvest festival, when, with games and dances, 
the people rejoice over the ripening of the fruits of the earth.  
After the performance of secret rites within the estufas, to which 
ceremonies no one not a member of the tribe is admitted, the 
maskers, musicians, and others, all decorated in paint, ribbons, 
and brass ornaments, stream forth into the open space before the 
village, where, with the peculiar stamping step attending all 
Indian performances of the kind, are continued the processions and 
dances, to the music of rude fifes, drums, and gong-beating.  In 
some of their dances the performers are attired in complete suits 
of buckskin, adorned with fringes, buttons, beads, feathers, and 
ribbons, completely covering the face and head, surmounted with 
horns, and having only small slits for sight and breathing. 
</p><p>The Pueblos, a provident folk who believe in intrenching 
themselves with all the supernatural powers, do not neglect on 
these occasions to visit the church to pay due obeisance to the 
Christian God and lesser divinities.  The church, a fine old 
structure of adobe, was rebuilt in 1702, after it had been 
dismantled in the Indian revolt of 1680.  It is a massive edifice 
one hundred and fifty feet long, forty feet wide, and forty feet 
high, with walls seven feet thick, standing, fronted by an 
extensive and ancient burial-ground, on the southern brink of the 
mesa.  The sand for this cemetery was brought up from the foot of 
the bluff, and placed in a depression at this point &mdash; an operation 
which, according to priestly tradition, occupied forty years.  The 
huge buttresses, one at each front corner of the church, are capped 
above the roof by rude belfries, in which swing two bells, which 
Indian tradition asserts to be the gift of the Queen of Spain at 
some period in the eighteenth century.  One of these bells bears 
the inscription, "San Pedro, A.D. 1710."  It is a wonder how these 
heavy bells, and the great pine beams, forty feet long, and of 
proportionate thickness, that cross the body of the church, were 
ever brought to the top of the mesa. 
</p><p>Adjoining the church are the ruins of the old Franciscan 
mission of San Estevan de Acoma, established, says the eminent 
archaeologist and historian Professor Ad. H. Baudelier [sic], by 
Fray Juan Ramirez not long after the year 1628, he naming the place 
after St. Sebastian on account of its rocky sides and the large 
number of pebbles accumulated on and about it.  Fray Ramirez 
returned to Mexico, and died there in 1664.  His successor was Fray 
Lucas Maldonado, from Tribujona, Mexico, also a Franciscan.  In 
fact, up to the uprising of the Indians of New Mexico under Pope 
and Catite in 1680, the Franciscan Order controlled all the 
missions among the Pueblos.  On August 10, 1680, twenty-one 
Franciscan friars were murdered in various parts of New Mexico, and 
among them Fray Maldonado, of Acoma.  After the reconquest of the 
province, twelve years later, by the Spaniards under Diego de 
Vargas, there were for several years occasional disturbances and 
bloodshed.  But by the beginning of the eighteenth century the 
province had become tranquillized, and the Pueblo Indians and the 
Spaniards had adjusted their requirements so as to get along 
together without a great amount of friction. 
</p><p>It is a strange and picturesque sight when within the thick 
walls of the old church, dimly lighted by deep windows like 
portholes, in which sheets of mica, or <hi rend="italic">yeso</hi> (transparent 
gypsum), serve for glass, the Indians, in the same fashion of dress 
which their ancestors wore when they built fires to the sun in 
ancient days &mdash; some wrapped in Navajo blankets, with broad black and 
white stripes, and great red diamond figures in the centre &mdash; pass to 
and from the altar, with its bright but impressive decorations.  
The church interior is decorated with two valuable pictures, the 
"Virgin and Child," and the "St. Joseph," which were brought from 
Spain more than two hundred years ago.  The ceiling is rudely 
frescoed in representation of the sun, moon, and stars, the work, 
in the beginning of the present century, of an artist priest, whose 
name is somewhere inscribed beneath the dust that for generations 
has been settling upon this labor of love and devotion. 
</p><p>The Acomas are a free and independent race, preserving their 
pure Indian descent and tribal characteristics.  they possess and 
jealously guard an antique, strongly made chest, secured by a giant 
padlock, in which are various old papers and parchments bestowed 
upon them by the early Spanish rulers, or bequeathed them by 
priests, comprising grants of privileges, title-deeds, missals, and 
other documents, which they regard with much reverence, and 
preserve with care.  Like the Zunis, and several other of the 
Pueblo tribes, the Acomas maintain in their principal estufa the 
sacred fire.  A member of a military commission visiting this 
pueblo twenty years ago relates that as a special honor the party 
were taken to the estufa.  To reach this underground apartment &mdash; a 
chamber about thirty feet long by fifteen feet in width &mdash; they 
descended a smoke-begrimed ladder through a trap-door, which also 
served as a chimney.  Seated around the fire, each with a loom in 
front of him, on which he was weaving a blanket, were four Indians, 
whose only garment was the breech-cloth.  The Indians told the 
visitors that these men were relieved at stated times by four 
others, and that the fire was kept forever burning, waiting for the 
coming of Montezuma, the demi-god of the golden or heroic age of 
the Pueblos, who had promised on his departure centuries ago to 
return to resume his sovereignty and to deliver and exalt his 
people. </p> 
<signed>CLARENCE PULLEN.</signed> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
