<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="RogStea"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="RogStea"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Steadfast Falters</title>
<title type="sort">steadfast falters</title>
<author>Rogers, E. Mandevill</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Charles Keller</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">250</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">RogStea</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476349</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Steadfast Falters</title>
<title type="sort">steadfast falters</title>
<author>Rogers, E. Mandevill</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Munsey's Magazine</publisher> 
<date value="1916-12">December 1916</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>3</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 515-570</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme 
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of 
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1916">1916</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-02">February 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>updated header and tags</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="1994-03">March 1994</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>SGML markup</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
 
<front id="d2"> 
<titlePage id="d3"> 
	<pb/>
<titlePart type="main">MUNSEY'S MAGAZINE<lb/> 
                        
                           VOLUME LIX<lb/> 
                        
                              &mdash;<lb/> 
                        
                         December, 1916<lb/> 
                           Number III<lb/> 
                           pp. 515-570<lb/> 
                        
                        
                        
                       <hi rend="italic">Steadfast Falters</hi><lb/> 
                       <hi rend="italic">A Complete Novel</hi><lb/> 
                    <hi rend="italic">by E. Mandevill Rogers</hi><lb/> 
</titlePart> 
<docImprint>                        
                <hi rend="italic">Copyright. 1916, by E. W. Scott</hi><lb/> 
</docImprint> 
</titlePage> 
</front>

<body id="d4">
<div1 type="chapter" n="1" id="d5">
	<pb n="515"/>  
<head>I</head> 
<p>Randolph Crosby's philosophy of life forbade his feeling or 
expressing emotion, except for the slender, fair-haired girl who 
stood beside him, and who had in a measure taken the place of the 
wife whose memory she perpetuated.  Nevertheless, the sight of 
the thoroughbreds as they filed past the club enclosure, their 
jockeys perching like monkeys on their glossy backs, made the 
muscles of his throat contract a little. 
</p><p>Excitement was an almost forgotten sensation for this man who 
had won as many as seven races in a day with horses he had bred 
and trained himself.  It gave him a pleasurable feeling that 
youth, with all its joys and enthusiasms, was not irrevocably 
gone. 
</p><p>"Steadfast looks in the pink of condition," remarked a tall 
man standing beside him, and sufficiently like him to proclaim 
their relationship. 
</p><p>George Crosby was tall and straight like his brother, with 
the erect, easy carriage for which the family had long been 
noted.  It was in the expression of eye and mouth that the main 
points of difference lay.  George's eyes were heavy, with thick 
lids which gave them a languid, rather tired look, and dark-blue 
shadows encircled them.  His lips were full, and drooped a little 
at the corners. 
</p><p>Randolph's eyes, on the contrary, looked out of an impassive, 
almost cynical face with the cold, critical gaze of one who for 
half a century had lived hard and, at times, fast.  In his desire 
to experience every sensation that life could offer, he might 
have followed paths that were shadowed and devious; but through 
it all he had carried a sense of responsibility to the code of 
his ancestors   &mdash;   "Play the game for all it's worth, but play it 
square!" 
</p><p>George, the younger of the brothers, maintained that 
Randolph's feeling in regard to family tradition was an 
obsession. 
</p><p>"Your Uncle Randolph's a bit dotty on the subject, Norman," 
he had remarked to his son one evening, in the confidence of an 
after-dinner chat, a slight sneer curling the corners of his 
lips.  "Leans over backward when it comes to a point of what he 
calls honor.  Personally, I don't see what difference it makes to 
the family tree." 
</p><p>Norman had replied ruefully: 
</p><p>"Wish I had a thousand dollars for each of the dusty old 
codgers!  It would come close to getting me out of debt." 
</p><p>His father had eyed the dissipated young face sharply. 
</p><p>"Just the same, don't hit it up too hard, my son.  The 
paternal exchequer has its limitations, you know, and your dad 
isn't too old to want some of the good things of life himself!" 
</p><p>And Norman had laughed, and said he wouldn't. 
<pb n="516"/>  
</p><p>He was standing beside his father now, watching the horses 
with a strained look on his white face. 
</p><p>"Pat says he's in perfect shape," replied Randolph Crosby, in 
answer to his brother's remark. 
</p><p>His keen eyes softened as they lingered on the horse who 
hitherto had always carried his colors to victory. 
</p><p>"Are you backing him?" asked George, glancing at the card he 
held in his hand. 
</p><p>His brother nodded. 
</p><p>"Went in rather deep this time.  It looks like such a sure 
thing.  The odds are pretty heavy, and you have to plunge a bit 
to make it worth while." 
</p><p>He turned to listen to his daughter, who was calling his 
attention to one of the other horses. 
</p><p>"Dad!" said Norman in a low voice, from which he could not 
entirely exclude the excitement he evidently felt.  "Steadfast 
isn't going to win!" 
</p><p>His father glanced at him quickly, his heavy eyes narrowing 
as he concentrated his attention on Norman's subdued tone. 
</p><p>"I've just left the stable," Norman went on; "and I tell you, 
Steadfast is <hi rend="italic">not</hi> going to win!" 
</p><p>George Crosby scrutinized his son's face for a moment in 
silence.  Then they moved quietly toward a thick-set man, with a 
diamond horseshoe pin in his vivid tie, who was standing on the 
outskirts of the crowd. 
</p><p>A short, faultlessly dressed man with a military carriage put 
his hand on Randolph Crosby's shoulder. 
</p><p>"Steadfast going to win, Rand?" he asked in a well-modulated 
voice. 
</p><p>Randolph Crosby lowered the glasses through which he had been 
following the string of horses as they moved'slowly up the 
stretch, and turned toward the speaker. 
</p><p>"Hope so, I'm sure, Tod," he answered. 
</p><p>Major Barry smiled at him affectionately. 
</p><p>"Advise my staking half my pay on him?" he asked. 
</p><p>Crosby smiled back at him half seriously. 
</p><p>"Betsy," he said, turning to his daughter, read your 
godfather a lecture.  He's on the verge of succumbing to 
temptation!" 
</p><p>Elizabeth turned, her bright face illumined by the smile 
which Major Barry always said made you feel that all nature had 
suddenly burst into song, and shook her finger at him. 
</p><p>"Really," she exclaimed, "if you boys don't behave, I shall 
have to take you home!  It's bad enough having one of my fathers 
plunging heavily; but if you both do, and Steadfast should lose, 
who is going to keep me supplied with gardenias?" 
</p><p>"Horrors!"  Major Barry raised his eyebrows in exaggerated 
concern.  "What a ghastly suggestion!  I shall most certainly 
refrain!" 
</p><p>With a laugh, he walked away with his light, springy step. 
</p><p>Randolph Crosby raised his glasses to his eyes and fixed them 
on the shifting group of horses on the far side of the green 
oval.  His hand was not as steady as usual as he readjusted the 
lenses, but it was in an even, perfectly controlled voice that he 
said "They're off!" as the barrier was sprung. 
</p><p>The words were taken up by the people in the grand stand on 
the other side of the railing, and simultaneously the crowd rose 
to its feet. 
</p><p>"Steadfast leads!  Steadfast leads!" came an exultant chorus 
of voices. 
</p><p>The horse had been a consistent winner ever since the season 
opened, and consequently was high in popular favor.  His capture 
of the richest stake of the year was taken almost as a foregone 
conclusion, and a great crowd had turned out to see the race and 
to bring home its share of the proceeds. 
</p><p>The horses swept into the home-stretch with Steadfast well in 
the van.  It looked as if the race was over, and Randolph Crosby 
was about to lower his glasses when he saw Steadfast falter. 
</p><p>It was only for a second.  The boy on the horse's back 
tightened the rein, and then gave him his head; but in that 
second before Steadfast regained his stride, Pursuit, who had 
been playing second to him all the year, and now was following 
close on his heels, gained perceptibly.  His nose crept up until 
it was outlined against Steadfast's quarter.  Then it blotted out 
Pat's white leg, and then it reached the band on the bridle. 
</p><p>"What's wrong with Steadfast?" 
</p><p>The question flashed through Randolph Crosby's mind. 
Certainly there was a marked difference in his running.  It was 
labored, forced, quite unlike the easy swing that had made him 
famous. 
</p><p>"Pursuit!  Pursuit!" 
</p><p>The cry broke in upon him in an agony of apprehension as the 
horses swept by the grand stand.   Pat was riding far forward, 
<pb n="517"/> urging Steadfast with hand and voice, and the jockey on 
Pursuit's back was whipping his mount briskly. 
</p><p>"Give Steadfast the whip!  The whip!" shouted the crowd in a 
frenzy of excitement; but Pat did not heed them, and the horses 
passed the judges' stand with Pursuit's nose a foot to the fore. 
</p><p>An angry tumult of disappointment surged over the crowd. 
Randolph Crosby's keen eyes were fixed on Pat's white face as he 
trotted back to the weighing-stand.  As the jockey raised his 
whip, Crosby's breath escaped through his lips in a little sigh, 
as if insensibly he had been holding it in expectation of 
something, he did not know quite what. 
</p><p>The fair girl beside him turned her sweet, troubled face to 
him. 
</p><p>"Oh, father!" she exclaimed, her blue eyes limpid with 
sympathy.  "I'm so sorry!" 
</p><p>"All in the day's work, Betsy!" he answered with an attempt 
at gaiety, looking fondly at her.  "Can't always win!  That would 
be monotonous.  I think I'll go and speak to Pat; he looks a bit 
cut up." 
</p><p>He strolled off through the brightly colored groups scattered 
over the lawn.  Elizabeth turned to the tall man beside her. 
</p><p>"Poor dad!" she said.  "He <hi rend="italic">is</hi> disappointed!  He idolizes 
that horse, and I can see it has really hurt him to have him 
beaten." 
</p><p>"It's too bad!  I am sorry!" returned Fairfax Cary, with a 
regretful glance at the erect gray head disappearing into the 
crowd.  "Steadfast is a great horse, but   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"You thought so, too!" exclaimed Elizabeth, with a quick 
glance at the clean-cut profile.  "I didn't want to say anything 
to father, but"   &mdash;   she looked inquiringly into the gray eyes fixed 
intently on her face   &mdash;   it seemed to me   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>She stopped abruptly, and the delicate color slowly deepened 
in her cheeks. 
</p><p>"You're looking very lovely this afternoon," said Cary in a 
low voice.  "I've been wanting to tell you so for two hours, but 
there's always such a crowd around you!" 
</p><p>Elizabeth laughed a little tremulously. 
</p><p>"What a relief it must be to get it off your mind at last!" 
she flashed back at him, with a look from under the broad brim of 
her hat that made the expression in his eyes deepen dangerously. 
</p><p>"It is," he assented seriously.  "That's a perfectly new 
dimple you've developed just under your right eye.  How dare you 
spring anything so distractingly   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"Where's your father, Elizabeth?" asked a full voice at the 
girl's elbow. 
</p><p>Elizabeth turned quickly and looked into the handsome, 
carefully penciled face beside her, whose prominent eyes were 
staring disapprovingly at Cary's lean, brown countenance. 
</p><p>"Oh, Aunt Maude, is it you?  Father went to the stables to 
speak to Pat.  He knew the boy would be heart-broken.  You 
remember Mr. Cary?" 
</p><p>She had introduced them numberless times before, but it 
always seemed to be necessary to repeat the formality.  She had 
adopted the habit of doing it immediately, in order to take away 
as much strain as possible from a situation which was always 
difficult when the two were together. 
</p><p>Cary raised his hat with the quizzical look in his eyes that 
Elizabeth had learned to expect, and bowed with an almost 
imperceptible exaggeration of his usual courtly manner. 
</p><p>Mrs. Crosby acknowledged the salutation mechanically, her 
full eyes wandering indifferently past him. 
</p><p>"Pat's not the only one who is heartbroken," she retorted 
abruptly.  "Practically every one was backing Steadfast, and I 
know several people who have been pretty hard hit."  The thin 
line of her mouth hardened.  She herself had lost more than she 
could afford on the race, and she was looking for some one on 
whom to lay the blame.  "How about you, Mr. Cary?" she went on, 
the vaguest suggestion of a sneer in the throaty voice.  "Or 
don't you ever bet?" 
</p><p>"Not often, Mrs. Crosby," answered Cary calmly.  "In the 
first place, I can't afford to lose; in the second, I don't 
follow the races closely enough to form an intelligent opinion on 
the relative merits of the horses." 
</p><p>Mrs. Crosby laughed a little unpleasantly. 
</p><p>"Then it is something besides the horses that brings you 
here?" she asked meaningly. 
</p><p>A slight flush spread over Cary's sensitive face, and the 
firm line of his chin stiffened. 
</p><p>"Oh, don't put me  quite outside the pale," he answered 
lightly.  "You know we Virginians love a good horse, and a race 
is an inspiring sight, even to one who has never been in a 
position to follow the sport   &mdash;   or <pb n="518"/> any other, for that 
matter," he added whimsically, with a side glance at Elizabeth. 
</p><p>She returned his look with a smile that caused Mrs. Crosby to 
hunch her plump shoulders uncomfortably as she realized her 
mistake. 
</p><p>Fairfax Cary had left the family estate in the Shenandoah 
Valley ten years before, and had come to New York with little 
besides the clothes on his back, and practically nothing in them. 
He had met Randolph Crosby in the settlement of an estate against 
which Crosby had a claim.  Struck by the young man's ability, 
Crosby had employed him in several minor cases of his own. 
Gradually social intercourse had developed from business 
relations, until Fairfax Cary became an acknowledged friend of 
the family, and was in frequent attendance on Elizabeth. 
</p><p>The intimacy had increased so fast that.  Mrs. Crosby had 
undertaken to remonstrate with her brother-in-law one afternoon 
when he had dropped in to tea. 
</p><p>"Good Heavens, Maude!" he had retorted impatiently.  "The 
girl isn't going to marry every man who takes her in to dinner!" 
</p><p>"No, Randolph," answered Mrs. Crosby in the long-suffering 
way that some women adopt when they feel that the men of their 
family are deliberately obtuse.  "Of course not; but she's going 
to marry one of them, and you know how easy it is to make a 
mistake.  A girl with Elizabeth's prospects is very attractive, 
especially to a man with none." 
</p><p>"I don't agree with you that Cary has no prospects.  He's a 
very able chap, and as straight as a string." 
</p><p>Mrs. Crosby had raised her penciled eyebrows slightly. 
</p><p>"Perhaps," she agreed unwillingly, "from a man's standpoint, 
he may"   &mdash;   there was the faintest possible emphasis on the word   &mdash;    
"be all that is desirable; but I'm sure, if Helen had lived, she 
would have agreed with me that Elizabeth is too rare a girl to be 
thrown away on an unknown." 
</p><p>A slight quiver had passed over Randolph Crosby's face at the 
mention of his wife's name.  For a moment he was silent, then he 
said: 
</p><p>"Better not call Fairfax Cary an unknown in Virginia!" 
</p><p>Mrs. Crosby had shrugged her shoulders. 
</p><p>"Virginia is not New York.  If you want Elizabeth to bury 
herself in the country, why, of course, I have nothing to say." 
She paused, then she added in a lowered voice:  "You know I've 
always felt that I must take as far as I can her mother's place 
to Elizabeth, and I can't see her sacrifice herself without a 
word of protest.  I love the girl as dearly as if she were the 
daughter who was denied to me." 
</p><p>She raised a lace-trimmed handkerchief and dabbed her eyes 
carefully. 
</p><p>"Awfully good of you, Maude, I'm sure," replied Crosby, 
uneasily moving his neatly incased foot.  "But I don't think we 
need either of us worry about Elizabeth.  She's as level-headed a 
young woman as I know, and when she makes up that mind of hers"   &mdash;    
he looked whimsically at his sister-in-law, a smile, half of 
pride, half of helplessness, spreading over his face   &mdash;   "I don't 
think there's any power in heaven or on earth that will move 
her!" 
</p><p>Mrs. Crosby had spread out her plump, jeweled fingers and 
raised her eyebrows meaningly, indicating that at least she had 
done her duty, and the rest lay with him. 
</p><p>She turned now to greet her husband and son as they emerged 
from the throng about them.  There was an intangible atmosphere 
of elation about them, and Norman's face was flushed. 
</p><p>"Too bad, Betty," he remarked in a rather thick voice to his 
cousin.  "Beastly hard luck!  Uncle Randolph's disappointed, I 
guess   &mdash;   what?  Great race, though!" 
</p><p>He pushed back his straw hat from his damp forehead, and 
taking out his cigarette-case, offered it to Cary with a, hand 
that shook perceptibly.  When Fairfax declined, he took out a 
cigarette, struck the end of it once or twice on the gold lid, 
lit it, and placed it between his loose lips. 
</p><p>"A lot of money changed hands," he remarked confidentially to 
Cary, his bloodshot eyes glistening. 
</p><p>The lines of the other man's face hardened, and unconsciously 
he drew himself up.  Turning to Elizabeth, he asked, in an 
undertone that excluded the others, if she would care to go to 
the paddock. 
</p><p>Elizabeth glanced at him in quick gratitude, and after a few 
words of explanation to her aunt they moved away. 
</p><p>Randolph Crosby, in the mean time, had succeeded in making 
his way through the groups of well-dressed men and women who, 
eager to sympathize with him and hear his <pb n="519"/> explanation of the 
defeat, were impeding his progress to the stable.  When he 
reached his destination, he found Pat watching Jim, the 
stable-boy, who was rubbing Steadfast down.  The boy's angry face 
was flushed, and a white line encircled his mouth. 
</p><p>"I tell ye it wa'n't no put-up game!" he was saying hotly to 
another boy, who sat on the bottom of an overturned pail.  "I 
rode a straight race!  What do ye take me fer, ye miserable 
tout?" 
</p><p>He turned threateningly toward the other.  The sneer that met 
him seemed to drive away his last vestige of self-control. 
Shaking his fist in the other boy's face, his little figure 
trembling with rage, Pat shouted: 
</p><p>"Ye're a low-mouthed, dirty, snivelin' liar, an' ye know 
ye're lyin'   &mdash;   "  He stopped abruptly as his eyes fell on his 
employer. 
</p><p>"Well, Pat," remarked Mr. Crosby quietly, watching with a 
half smile his jockey's tormentor as he slipped hastily away, 
what's it all about?" 
</p><p>The boy struggled vainly to regain his self-control. 
</p><p>"The miserable, rotten little kike   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"Yes, yes," broke in Mr. Crosby coolly.  "Leave all that 
out!" 
</p><p>Pat raised his working face and looked full into the dark 
eyes that somehow seemed to have lost their cynical expression. 
</p><p>"He said I pulled Steadfast!" he exclaimed.  "Said I lost on 
purpose!" 
</p><p>He turned away abruptly and laid his hand, as if to steady 
himself, on the horse's deep-breathing side. 
</p><p>"The dirty hound!" he muttered under his breath.  "An' me 
with every cart-wheel I could scrape together on the hoss! 
If he knowed what that race meant to me!" 
</p><p>Again Pat stopped, his voice trembling. 
</p><p>"Ye don't risk what ye've been workin' fer since ye wuz a 
kid, scrimpin' an' screwin' so as ye kin hev a place ter put yer 
sister where she'll be safe from that"   &mdash;   his eyes glanced 
significantly to the paddock, where flashily dressed men loitered 
about the horses, discoursing on their points to the painted 
women who accompanied them   &mdash;   It unless ye've got a dead-sure 
thing.  It ain't no fault o' mine that Steadfast didn't win that 
race   &mdash;   ye know that, don't ye, Mr. Crosby?" 
</p><p>He drove his hands into the pockets of his breeches and 
looked appealingly into the older man's face.  Mr. Crosby nodded. 
</p><p>"Why did Steadfast lose, Pat?" he asked gravely. 
</p><p>Pat shifted his position uneasily. 
</p><p>"I dunno, sir   &mdash;   I swear I don't.  The hoss wuz goin' like a 
bunch o' machinery, an' I thought I had the race won; an' then 
all ter once I feels him give, sudden like, just like somethin' 
inside him had broke down.  I done my best, but he'd lost his 
spring, an' I knowed then he couldn't win; but what the matter 
wuz   &mdash;   "  The boy shook his head despondently.  "Did ye hear the 
crowd yellin' at me to give him the whip?  <hi rend="italic">Steadfast!</hi>  Can ye 
beat that?  Lot they know about hosses!"  Pat's voice was 
brimming with scorn as he ran his hand over the animal's glossy 
neck.  "Why, it would ha' broke his heart!" 
</p><p>The horse turned his head and, fastening his great, velvety 
eyes on the boy, laid his muzzle on Pat's shoulder.  The boy hid 
his face quickly in the horse's mane, but not in time to prevent 
Crosby's seeing the pitifully quivering chin.  For a moment all 
that broke the silence was the stamping of the other horses in 
their stalls and the far-off throb of the band. 
</p><p>"Pat!" said Mr. Crosby at last.  "Come here, my lad   &mdash;   I want 
to ask you a question."  They drew a little apart until they were 
quite alone.  "Could any one have got at Steadfast?" 
</p><p>The question was almost inaudible, but the jockey's sharp 
ears caught it, and he shook his head in vehement denial. 
</p><p>"I ain't lef' him day or night, Mr. Crosby," he answered 
quickly.  "I even slep' In the stall   &mdash;   an' when I had ter go and 
change me togs I lef' Mr. Norman an' Molly with him.  Surely he 
couldn't ha' been no safer?" 
</p><p>The lad looked interrogatively at his employer.  Mr. Crosby 
shook his head, and after telling Pat not to worry any more about 
the race, and giving him some instructions for the following day, 
he walked back toward the clubhouse. 
</p><p>As he passed the paddock a short, stocky man in a check suit 
came toward him.  His deep-set eyes brightened as they caught 
sight of Randolph Crosby, and he stretched out a thick, muscular 
hand adorned with a large cameo ring. 
</p><p>"How-do, Mr. Crosby?  How are you?" he asked, taking an 
enormous unlighted cigar out of his mouth.  "What was wrong with 
Steadfast?" 
<pb n="520"/>  
</p><p>His keen black eyes, under their shaggy eyebrows, fixed 
themselves penetratingly on Crosby's face. 
</p><p>Randolph Crosby raised his eyebrows. 
</p><p>"Nothing, Tutney, as far as I know.  I've just been talking 
to Pat.  He says the horse was in perfect shape until the middle 
of the race; then he seemed to crumple up.  I can't understand 
it." 
</p><p>Tutney replaced the cigar in his mouth, and twisted it around 
and around with his tongue.  The expression on his immovable face 
never changed. 
</p><p>"Were you backin' him?" he asked bluntly, 
</p><p>Crosby nodded. 
</p><p>"That race cost me quite a lot of money," he replied quietly. 
" The odds were heavy, and it was a good purse." 
</p><p>Tutney grunted. 
</p><p>"Thought they were wrong!" 
</p><p>"What do you mean?" 
</p><p>The stocky man shifted his weight from one white-gaitered 
foot to the other and gave the cigar another twist. 
</p><p>"Oh, just some remarks I overheard.  Crowd's pretty sore   &mdash;    
always is when it loses!" 
</p><p>"What did you hear?" said Crosby, looking sharply at the 
other. 
</p><p>Tutney hesitated, and Crosby repeated his question in a 
quiet, cold voice. 
</p><p>"Why, they were sayin," the man began, lowering his voice, 
"that the Crosbys had won a lot of money on the race." 
</p><p>Crosby stared incredulously at the stolid face. 
</p><p>"Are they saying that?" he asked in an undertone, as if 
speaking to himself. 
</p><p>Tutney scrutinized the cold, impassive face sharply.  He took 
the cigar out of his mouth. 
</p><p>"Mr. Crosby," he said at last, "you and I have known each 
other for ten years   &mdash;   eleven, to be exact   &mdash;   haven't we?" 
</p><p>Crosby inclined his head. 
</p><p>"And we've had a good many deals together of one kind or 
another."  Again Tutney waited for the other man's assent.  "And 
in that time, in spite of the fact that there were plenty of 
chances for shady practise, I want to go on record as sayin' 
you're the squarest man I ever met, bar none!" 
</p><p>He turned abruptly away, as if ashamed of the emotion that 
had crept into his voice.  Randolph Crosby's keen eyes softened. 
</p><p>"Thank you, Tutney," he said quietly.  "That means a great 
deal, coming from you." 
</p><p>He stretched out his hand, and Tutney grasped it firmly. 
</p><p>"Good-by, Mr. Crosby," he said huskily.  He cleared his 
throat loudly.  "I'm off to South Africa to-morrow.  Got to look 
after things there a bit.  Let me know if at any time I can be of 
service to you." 
</p><p>Crosby thanked him again, and his eyes followed Tutney with 
an expression almost of tenderness as the stocky man disappeared 
into the crowd.  Then he resumed his walk toward the club 
enclosure.  Unconsciously his shoulders had straightened and his 
head gone up. 
</p><p>At the entrance he saw the Porter Chadwicks, who, with the 
Crosbys, had lunched at the clubhouse before the races. 
Chadwick glanced in Randolph Crosby's direction and said 
something in an undertone to his wife, and they passed quickly 
through the wicket. 
</p><p>A quiet smile played around the corners of Crosby's thin 
lips, but the tired, cynical look in his eyes deepened.  He 
stepped into the enclosure and almost ran into the arms of 
Griswold Peyton, who had been a classmate of his at Harvard, and 
was one of his most intimate friends.  Peyton started violently 
and turned scarlet. 
</p><p>"Too   &mdash;   too bad   &mdash;   about the   &mdash;   race, old man!" he stammered. 
"Must speak to   &mdash;   to   &mdash;   Mrs. Phillips.  See you again!" 
</p><p>He fled precipitately.  A slight frown contracted Crosby's 
straight brows, and his lips tightened.  He walked to where 
Elizabeth and Cary stood a little apart. 
</p><p>"Are you ready to go?" he asked his daughter.  "I don't want 
to hurry you, but as the races are over   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"Quite ready," answered Elizabeth. 
</p><p>She smiled joyously at her father, and her voice seemed 
brimming with the silver purity of the hermit-thrush.  She put 
her hand through his arm, and they turned to leave the enclosure. 
</p><p>"Oh, Betsy!"  A dark, vivacious face appeared at her 
shoulder.  "I was so afraid you would leave before I had a chance 
to speak to you!"  The speaker put out her hand to Randolph 
Crosby.  <hi rend="italic">"So sorry</hi> about the race!" 
</p><p>"Thank you, Trixie"; and Crosby's hand closed warmly over 
hers. 
<pb n="521"/>  
</p><p>"Beatrix! Beatrix!  Come here at once!" 
</p><p>The words came almost in a wail from a small, much-corseted 
woman in a purple <hi rend="italic">crepe de Chine</hi>, heavily trimmed with Cluny 
lace.    An expression of anguish shone through the powder on her 
horrified face. 
</p><p>"She only calls me that on occasions of great urgency!" 
laughed Trixie.  "I shall have to go; but remember, Betsy   &mdash;    
you're coming to me at Lawrence for a long visit this summer.  I 
won't be put off again!" 
</p><p>She pressed Elizabeth's hand, and with a nod to the men flew 
off to rejoin her mother. 
</p><p>"Mrs. Hunnewell seems rather upset," remarked Elizabeth 
wonderingly. 
</p><p>"Very much so," replied her father grimly. They started 
toward the exit.  "Why, Humphrey!" he exclaimed, and then 
stopped. 
</p><p>A tall, fine-looking man with iron-gray hair and mustache 
looked at him coldly and passed without speaking. 
</p><p>Randolph Crosby's face whitened.  With muscles so tense that 
they showed like cords through the skin, he walked to the waiting 
automobile.  He stood back for Elizabeth to enter; then he got in 
and dropped down beside her. 
</p><p>"Coming, Fairfax?" he asked in a voice strangely unlike his 
own.  "No?  Well, drop in soon.  All right, Foster   &mdash;   home, then!" 
</p><p>He settled back in his corner. 
</p><p>When the parlor-maid went into the library of the Crosbys' 
apartment the next morning and pulled up the shade, the sun fell 
full on the figure of Randolph Crosby, sunk deep in his big 
armchair.  His head was turned a little to one side, as if trying 
to catch a sound that eluded him, and over his lips hovered the 
faint shadow of a smile, not cynical or sarcastic, but as if the 
pettiness of life and its sordid estimates had passed him by 
forever, and he had found again the one who had always 
understood. 
</p> 
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="2" id="d6"> 
<head>II</head> 
 
<p>Mrs. George Crosby sat at her desk in the morning-room, a 
pile of unpaid bills before her and a thin line of worry between 
her eyebrows.  An indescribable atmosphere of unrest and 
weariness hovered about her, accentuating the traces of wear 
which years of struggle had left behind.  The limp folds of her 
tea-gown hanging dejectedly around her stressed her dispirited 
appearance.  The room, with its worn rug, soiled, 
cretonne-upholstered furniture and shabby hangings, seemed to 
fasten upon her the imprint of hard usage, as if to revenge 
itself for her neglect of it by proclaiming aloud, in the privacy 
of the third-floor back, what she fought with desperate 
determination to conceal from the critical eyes of the habitues 
of her perfectly appointed drawing-room. 
</p><p>She pushed away the papers petulantly is her husband entered 
the room. 
</p><p>"Really, George," she exclaimed irritably, turning toward 
him, "I don't see how I'm going to meet this additional expense! 
I've a pile of bills here now that there isn't the least prospect 
in the world of my ever being able to pay, and some of the people 
are positively uncivil in their demands.  Now, if I have to buy 
an entire mourning outfit, I don't see where I'm coming out!" 
</p><p>She looked at him in angry reproach. 
</p><p>"Too bad, old girl," returned her husband nonchalantly, 
sinking into a deep chair by the window and opening the newspaper 
he held.  "But don't blame me   &mdash;   it isn't my fault!" 
</p><p>"Don't be absurd, George!  Of course, Randolph's death isn't 
your fault; but I won't go to the length of saying that our being 
so strapped isn't!"  Her eyes ran impatiently over his relaxed 
figure.  "And I assure you I haven't the slightest intention of 
going to Newport this summer without the proper wardrobe.  If I 
have to put on mourning   &mdash;   and I suppose I must, or people will 
talk, and they're doing enough of that as it is   &mdash;   it's got to be 
of the best.  Cheap mourning is impossible; so you'll have to 
arrange to give me some money.  Remember, it's your brother, not 
mine!" 
</p><p>George Crosby lowered his paper irritably. 
</p><p>"Upon my word, Maude," he exclaimed, "you might show a little 
feeling!  The way you're acting is abominable.  One would think 
Randolph had died on purpose!" 
</p><p>"How do you know he didn't?" rejoined his wife with acerbity. 
"No one seems to have the faintest idea why he died.  Even the 
doctors can't agree.  Half of them say something about his heart, 
and the rest talk vaguely about a stroke.  For my part, I think 
the disgrace of that Steadfast affair was the cause." 
</p><p>"You mean?" 
</p><p>George Crosby gazed intently at his wife's face, haggard and 
worn without its customary make-up. 
<pb n="522"/>  
</p><p>"Oh, George!  Why do you make me go into details?  You know 
as well as I that there was something wrong with the horse on 
Thursday, and it was pretty generally suspected that he had been 
tampered with.  At all events, I saw some of Randolph's most 
intimate friends cut him dead as he was leaving the grounds, and 
Randolph was not the sort of man to stand that." 
</p><p>She looked meaningly into her husband's startled face. 
</p><p>"Poor old Rand!" 
</p><p>George Crosby's voice shook.  He turned his heavy eyes toward 
the window and stared, unseeing, at the backs of the houses 
opposite. 
</p><p>"It's horrid!  The whole thing is perfectly abominable!" 
continued his wife in a tone of extreme exasperation.  "Here I've 
gone to the expense of a complete outfit for the summer   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>Her husband jumped to his feet. 
</p><p>Yes, yes!" he exclaimed irritably.  "I'll get you the money 
somehow; but you'll have to make it go as far as possible." 
</p><p>"Trust me for that!" retorted his wife with a hard little 
laugh.  "Years of training have taught me to get as much out of a 
dollar as one hundred cents will buy, and maybe a little more, 
I'm sick of it!  I'm tired to death of having to plan and scrimp 
until even my fingers are beginning to look like claws!"  She 
held out her crooked fingers before him.  "How is it that 
Randolph had plenty of money and could live like a prince, while 
we've always been pinched to the last degree?" 
</p><p>George Crosby shrugged his shoulders and moved toward the 
door.  It was not the first time the question had been put to 
him, and it aroused, even now, a feeling of antagonism against 
the brother whose inheritance had been the same as his own, but 
who had increased his property tenfold, while George's had 
steadily dwindled. 
</p><p>"Perhaps an extravagant wife and son have had something to do 
with it!" he flung back over his shoulder as he lingered on the 
threshold.  "Well, poor Randolph can't enjoy his pile any more. 
What did you decide about Elizabeth?" 
</p><p>"She's coming to us, of course.  She can't live alone, and if 
I have her under my eye I can perhaps keep away undesirables." 
</p><p>She looked full at her husband, who nodded understandingly. 
</p><p>"Quite right, Maude; the girl's a catch, and is bound to have 
a lot of attention.  Much better to have her here.  Will she go 
with you to Newport?" 
</p><p>"Oh, yes; she needn't go out, and Norman will be there to 
amuse her.  I want the boy to take a good long rest this summer; 
he looks desperately thin." 
</p><p>"You can't lay that to overwork! replied her husband with a 
short laugh.  Almost the only thing that ever brings him to the 
office is the urgent need of funds." 
</p><p>"Like father, like son!" murmured his mother.  "I never 
noticed a deep love of work in you, either!" 
</p><p>"Maybe not, but my father wasn't so lenient as Norman's is, 
and I had to work when I was his age.  You can't blame me for 
wanting to take life a bit easy now."  He stretched luxuriously, 
and a self-indulgent smile widened the full lips.  "After all, 
one only lives once, and at my age there aren't so many years 
left to enjoy." 
</p><p>Mrs. Crosby shuddered. 
</p><p>I wish you wouldn't everlastingly keep referring to that 
extremely unpleasant subject.  It's positively gruesome!  We all 
have to die some time, of course, but there's no use in 
perpetually harping on the fact." 
</p><p>Crosby laughed again, lazily. 
</p><p>"Well, I'm off," he said, turning toward the stairs.  "I want 
to get Randolph's affairs straightened out as far as I can before 
the hot weather comes."  He paused once more.  "Tell Norman I 
expect him at twelve   &mdash;   that is, unless it's too early for him," he 
added with an exaggerated air of concern. 
</p><p>But when Norman finally appeared in his father's office, 
George Crosby foresaw at once, from the haggardness of the boy's 
face, what the interview portended.  These heated scenes had 
occurred with increasing frequency since Norman was fifteen, and 
were to be dreaded even more than the hardly less stormy 
encounters with the boy's mother. 
</p><p>Norman sank into the deep leather armchair that stood at the 
corner of his father's writing-table.  Swinging one leg over the 
other, he began nursing his slender, silk-incased ankle. 
</p><p>"I'm in the devil of a hole, dad!" he began moodily, 
</p><p>"You always are, aren't you?" retorted his father, with a 
scornful look from under his thick eyelids. 
<pb n="523"/>  
</p><p>Norman laughed uneasily. 
</p><p>"More or less," he admitted; "but this time it's no merry 
jest!" 
</p><p>"I have never found it so at any time," returned his father 
coldly. 
</p><p>Norman shifted his position uncomfortably.  His bloodshot 
eyes were wandering about the room; finally they came back to his 
father's face. 
</p><p>"I've had hard luck," he began with an effort; "deuced hard 
luck." 
</p><p>"Yes?"  George Crosby's tone was hardly encouraging. 
</p><p>Norman's eyes dropped to the Turkish rug which covered the 
floor. 
</p><p>"Well, what's the demnition total?" asked his father after a 
pause, attempting a facetiousness which the tone of his voice 
indicated he was far from feeling. 
</p><p>"Fifty thousand," said the boy desperately. 
</p><p>"Fifty thousand!  Good Heavens, boy, are you crazy?" 
</p><p>George Crosby leaned far out of his chair, his hands gripping 
the arms, his wide eyes for once alight, gazing incredulously 
into the sullen face before him. 
</p><p>Norman shook his head resentfully. 
</p><p>"Not yet, but I soon shall be, if this keeps on!" 
</p><p>"You   &mdash;   <hi rend="italic">you!"</hi> retorted his father, his face ablaze with 
anger.  "You'll have us all, your mother and me included, in the 
madhouse or in jail   &mdash;   I don't know which!  And it's only yourself 
you stop to think of!  Fifty thousand dollars!  Do you realize 
what that means to me?" 
</p><p>The boy's face blanched, and his sullen expression deepened. 
</p><p>How did it happen?" asked his father in a low voice, which he 
was evidently exerting his utmost will-power to control. 
</p><p>"Playing auction." 
</p><p>"Auction!  What stake?" 
</p><p>"Fifty cents." 
</p><p>"Fifty cents a point?"  An incredulous look stole over George 
Crosby's face.  "You say you were playing auction for fifty cents 
a <hi rend="italic">point</hi>?"  Then, as no answer was vouchsafed, he added, as if 
to himself:  "Just ten times my limit!" 
</p><p>For a moment neither spoke.  A tense, living silence wrapped 
itself about them, which the monotonous hum of the city booming 
in through the open window seemed to accentuate. 
</p><p>"How do you expect to pay this debt of   &mdash;   er   &mdash;   honor?" queried 
his father at last, a sneer curling the corners of his mouth. 
</p><p>The boy crouched back in his chair, as if for support, and 
raised miserable, hunted eyes to his father's grim face. 
</p><p>"I don't know, dad," he whispered huskily, "unless   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"Unless what?" 
</p><p>Norman swallowed hard.  He roused himself from his 
half-reclining position, and his slender figure suddenly became 
tense with energy. 
</p><p>"See here, dad!" he began.  "I've just heard of a wonderful 
proposition, perfectly safe, and a dead-sure thing," 
</p><p>His father looked at him suspiciously from under lowered 
lids. 
</p><p>"You've told me before of dead-sure things!" he retorted 
scornfully. 
</p><p>"But this one is absolutely on the level," Norman reiterated. 
"I happen to know the man who is at the head of it, and he swears 
that you would double your money in three months.  What's more, 
he proved it to me." 
</p><p>"How?" asked his father laconically. 
</p><p>"It's a rubber company, formed to take over the Belgian 
interests in the Congo.  At present prices rubber is a veritable 
goldmine, and the demand for it is unlimited.  They can't get 
enough on the other side, and you know how it's gone up here." 
</p><p>The color had come back into the boy's face, and his voice 
was quick and sharp.  George Crosby eyed him in silence. 
</p><p>"How much money does he want?" he asked at last. 
"Oh, a hundred thousand or so." 
</p><p>"My Heavens, boy!  You talk as if I were made of money!" 
</p><p>Norman's eyes dropped from his father's to the writing-table 
before which he sat.  It was strewn with papers.  They lingered 
there for a moment; then he looked back at his father 
significantly. 
</p><p>"I thought   &mdash;   perhaps," he hesitated, "you might   &mdash;   be willing to 
invest some   &mdash;   of   &mdash;   Uncle Randolph's money   &mdash;   in it." 
</p><p>George Crosby turned violently toward the boy, who was 
tensely awaiting the result of his suggestion. 
"Do you realize that that would be a State's prison offense?" he 
asked bluntly. 
</p><p>Norman's white face quivered. 
</p><p>"It's probably State's prison if you don't!" be retorted 
desperately. 
<pb n="524"/>  
</p><p>"What do you mean?"  The question came in a harsh voice 
strangely unlike George Crosby's usual suave tones. 
</p><p>"I mean this."  The boy was evidently goaded to desperation. 
"I raised the check you gave me for five hundred to fifty 
thousand to pay Henry Armstrong, and I gave it to him last 
night." 
</p><p>George Crosby turned slowly back to the writing-table, and 
his gray head dropped into his hands.  Lower and lower it sank 
until it fell on his outstretched arms, resting on the table. 
</p><p>Again that black silence folded itself about them.  Once or 
twice a deep sigh broke from the bowed figure, and the broad 
shoulders shuddered. 
</p><p>"Good God!"  The words seemed to have been wrung from him in 
spite of his efforts at restraint.  "Good God!" 
</p><p>A frightened look stole over Norman's face. 
</p><p>"Don't, dad, don't!" he whispered huskily, rising and laying 
a shaking hand on the older man's shoulder. 
</p><p>"Don't touch me!"  His father sprang to his feet, his eyes 
blazing, his drawn face working.  "You thief!" 
</p><p>Norman swayed back as if his father had struck him, and a 
look as of an animal at bay crept into his face. 
</p><p>"You   &mdash;   <hi rend="italic">you</hi> call me   &mdash;   that!" he breathed hoarsely.  <hi rend="italic">"You!</hi> 
Why, you don't know the meaning of the word honesty!  Don't talk 
to me!"  The words were tumbling out of his mouth in a frenzy of 
anger.  "Why, ever since I was a kid I've heard you and mother 
planning and arranging how you were going to get out of paying 
your bills!  And now <hi rend="italic">you</hi> call <hi rend="italic">me</hi> a thief!"  The young man's 
voice rose almost to a shriek.  "How do you expect me to be 
honest when I've been brought up never to pay for anything unless 
I had to?" 
</p><p>"Silence!" 
</p><p>George Crosby raised his hand as if to quell the torrent of 
words by force, if necessary.  For a moment father and son glared 
angrily into each other's face; then, with a catch in his breath 
that was almost a sob, the young man's slight figure crumpled up 
and fell into the chair behind him. 
</p><p>His father sank into his armchair, and his face fell forward 
on his chest.  His eyes, no longer languid, stared vacantly out 
of his strained, white face at the litter of papers before him. 
  It seemed as if some unseen spirit had cast a spell over him, 
robbing him forever of the atmosphere of youth which had long 
been the wonder and envy of his friends. 
</p><p>The consequences of the boy's act loomed dark and sinister 
over him; his son's words stung him with unanswerable force. 
</p><p> He passed his hands in a dazed way across his eyes, as if 
attempting to brush away a mist that obscured them, and the 
papers scattered on the table began to assume shape. 
Mechanically he stretched out his hand and took up a neat bundle 
secured by a rubber band.  He listlessly read the name on the 
wrapper. 
</p><p>Once more his head sank forward, and his eyes stared out 
before him, as if trying to penetrate the granite wall that 
concealed the future.  A hunted look crept into them, and the 
grip on the packet tightened.  He turned his head, but not his 
eyes, in the direction of the youth cowering in the depths of the 
big chair. 
</p><p>"You say you know the head of this   &mdash;   er   &mdash;   rubber concern?" he 
asked coldly. 
</p><p>The tense look on Norman Crosby's face lifted. 
</p><p>"Yes, sir," he answered.  "It's Henry C. Hargis." 
</p><p>"Hargis!  I know him.  If you should happen to run across 
him, tell him I should like to talk to him." 
</p><p>He turned again to the table. 
</p><p>Norman rose.  It seemed as if a heavy weight which had been 
crushing him had been removed, and he walked quickly to the door. 
With a backward glance toward the silent figure so absorbed as to 
be apparently oblivious to his existence, he slipped noiselessly 
out. 
</p> 
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="3" id="d7"> 
<head>III</head> 
 
<p>In the tasteful library in which her father's presence still 
seemed to linger Elizabeth Crosby wandered about, stopping now 
and again to touch tenderly some object that had been especially 
closely associated with him.  In the week that had elapsed since 
his death she had emerged from girlhood into the fuller estate of 
woman, but there still lingered about her that exquisite 
trustfulness of childhood, produced by the protecting arm of a 
love that had enveloped her like a garment. 
</p><p>She picked up a photograph of her father, <pb n="525"/> the look of 
sad tenderness deepening on her pale face. 
</p><p>"My precious dad!" she whispered, passing her hand 
caressingly over the face.  "I wonder if you know how I miss you! 
It's very lonely without you, dear." 
</p><p>She replaced the photograph on the table, her eyes blinded by 
tears, and groped her way to the armchair in which the last night 
of her father's life had been spent.  Sinking down on the arm, 
she laid her cheek against the spot where his head had rested. 
</p><p>"If only I could   &mdash;   have been with you   &mdash;   through it   &mdash;   all!" she 
murmured brokenly.  "I can't bear to think that you had to face 
it all alone, with no one that you loved to help you and say 
good-by.  Oh, that's the bitterest part of it all!  To think that 
you had to go without my being able to give you even a kiss, or 
one word to tell you how I love you!  If only I could let you 
know how grateful I am for all the happiness you gave me, and all 
the sacrifices you made for me!  And now you'll never know!  Oh, 
darling, couldn't you come back for just one little minute, just 
long enough to let me hold you in my arms and kiss you good-by?" 
</p><p>A great sob shook her slender form.  She sat up resolutely 
and pushed back the heavy golden coils of hair that had fallen 
over her forehead.  A watery little smile played over the pale 
face. 
</p><p>"Father wouldn't like me to give way like this," she thought 
self-reproachfully. 
</p><p>She got up and walked toward the door, glancing at the clock 
on the mantel as she passed it. 
</p><p>"Nearly five!" she exclaimed under her breath.  "I must 
hurry.  Fairfax is due now!" 
</p><p>It still lacked a few minutes of the hour when the portieres 
which separated the drawing-room from the library parted, and 
Fairfax Cary stepped into the room.  In an instant Elizabeth's 
light footsteps sounded on the stairs, and she came into the 
library holding out both hands in warm welcome. 
</p><p>"How glad I am to see you!" she exclaimed as their hands met. 
</p><p>"It's so good of you to let me come!" he answered, his eyes 
devouring her face.  Major Barry gave me your message." 
</p><p>"Dear Uncle Tod!" Elizabeth led the way to a roomy sofa and 
sank down into the corner.  "He has been very good to me." 
</p><p>Cary dropped down beside her. 
</p><p>"He naturally would be.  He idolized your father, and I know 
there isn't anything on earth he wouldn't do for him or for you. 
But tell me how you are." 
</p><p>"Oh, very well," she answered indifferently.  The thrushlike 
lilt had gone out of her voice and great shadows lay under her 
eyes.  "I'm a little tired, naturally; there's so much to be 
done."  She glanced wearily around the room.  "I'm giving up the 
apartment, you know." 
</p><p>Cary nodded sympathetically. 
</p><p>"That's a wrench, I'm sure." 
</p><p>"Yes," assented Elizabeth.  "We've been here so long   &mdash;   ever 
since I was a little girl; and although it's only rented, 
everything is so associated with   &mdash;   father that I feel as if I were 
living in a perpetual parting with him."  She resolutely forced 
back the great tears which had sprung to her eyes.  "But Aunt 
Maude thinks I'm too young to live alone, so I'm to go to them. 
Uncle George is my guardian until I'm twenty-eight.  I suppose 
they're right, but   &mdash;   "  She sighed.  Then she added in a sudden 
burst of confidence:  "I wish the three years were over!  You 
see, our ideas of what is worth while in life don't agree.  It's 
going to be hard for me to see my friends, too; and I detest 
Newport!" 
</p><p>"It isn't just the thing for you this summer," agreed Cary. 
"Can't you persuade Mrs. Crosby to go to a quieter place?" 
</p><p>"Dear me, no! I shouldn't think of asking her.  Imagine Aunt 
Maude cut off from her Newport season!  She'd be like a caged 
lion!"  A wistful look had crept into the girl's blue eyes. 
"Will you be coming down, do you think?" 
</p><p>Certainly not to stay with the Crosbys," he replied, a smile 
twitching at the corners of his lips. 
</p><p>Elizabeth laughed a little uncertainly. 
</p><p>"I don't understand it," she said thoughtfully.  "I don't see 
why aunt dislikes you; you are always so nice to her." 
</p><p>"She naturally thinks none but the most gorgeous butterflies 
should flutter around such a brilliant little candle." 
</p><p>A delicate flush crept into the girl's thin checks. 
</p><p>"How silly!" she exclaimed.  "I don't think even Aunt Maude 
could be so absurd!  No one could possibly think of you as a 
butterfly, and some day we shall all be trying to bask in the 
rays of your glory!" 
<pb n="526"/>  
</p><p>Fairfax Cary laughed.  Her praise and faith were very sweet 
to him, coming as they did after years of combat with obstacles 
the difficulties of which none but he had half realized. 
</p><p>"When that day comes   &mdash;   if it ever does," he said in a voice 
vibrant with feeling, "the glory will all be yours to do with as 
you like; for any success I may achieve will be entirely due to 
your faith in me and to your father's help." 
</p><p>Elizabeth raised her hand in protest. 
</p><p>"Oh, no," she denied vehemently.  "It was your ability that 
first attracted father's notice; and as for my faith in you, if 
you had not had the qualities, the faith would never have been 
inspired." 
</p><p>She looked at him triumphantly, as if defying him to refute 
her argument. 
</p><p>An overpowering desire to catch her in his arms and tell her 
of the place she held in his life took hold of Fairfax; but she 
looked so young, so unprotected, as she half reclined among the 
cushions of the deep corner, surrounded by the evidences of 
wealth, that he crushed it back. 
</p><p>"What right have I to ask her to marry me?" he thought 
savagely.  "She's lonely now, poor little girl, and she sees in 
me a man in whom her father believed, and who consequently has a 
sort of temporary glamour for her.  Wait until you have something 
real to offer her, man!  Even if she cares, it isn't right to 
take so much and give so little." 
</p><p>When do you go to Newport?" he asked aloud. 
</p><p>"Next week.  There are some legal matters to attend to and 
clothes to get."  She looked significantly at her black frock, 
"There are always so many things to do after   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"Yes, I know," Cary assented sympathetically.  "If there is 
anything I can do, I'm sure you'll remember that I would consider 
it a privilege to be allowed to help you." 
</p><p>Elizabeth thanked him with a wan little smile. 
</p><p>"And I want to tell you," he went on gently, "that I shall 
always think of your father as `one who dared do all that may 
become a man'   &mdash;   a man too fine to stoop to a meanness, too great 
of heart to profit through another's hurt." 
</p><p>Elizabeth looked at him gratefully, her eyes brimming with 
tears.  Impulsively she laid her hand on his arm. 
</p><p>"Ah," she murmured, "you were one of the few who really knew 
him for what he was!"  Her chin quivered.  "The rest"   &mdash;   she 
shrugged her shoulders sadly   &mdash;   "they mean to be consoling, but 
you   &mdash;   you're the first who has really comforted me." 
</p><p>Cary's hand closed warmly over her fingers, and his eyes 
looked fixedly into hers, as if trying to convey a message which 
the firm lips resolutely withheld. 
</p><p>"I shall miss you," she said sadly, withdrawing her hand. 
</p><p>Afraid to trust himself further, Fairfax rose. 
</p><p>"If at any time you need me," he said gently in his deep, 
even voice, "promise me that you will send for me!" 
</p><p>"I promise," answered Elizabeth readily. 
</p><p>"I want you to feel that you can call on me for anything at 
any time.  Will you remember?" 
</p><p>"Yes," replied the girl, putting her hand in his.  "Good-by!" 
</p><p>Her eyes followed the straight, thin figure, with its dark, 
proudly held head, as it disappeared into the hall, and a wave of 
desolate loneliness swept over her.  Unconsciously she took a 
quick step after him and held out her hands, but the outside door 
closed softly.  She stopped, and her hands fell to her sides. 
</p> 
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="4" id="d8"> 
<head>IV</head> 
 
<p>Notwithstanding Elizabeth's forebodings, the weeks that 
followed the Crosbys' move to Windy Bluff, their place at 
Newport, passed rapidly and almost happily for her.  Of course 
there were times when the realization of what she had lost by her 
father's death overcame her with almost unbearable pain; but as 
day followed day she became more or less accustomed to the 
loneliness which at first seemed insupportable.  She learned to 
watch the gay life about her with eyes that no longer shrank from 
the sight as from an overpowering light, 
</p><p>At first Mrs. Crosby had declined the invitations showered 
upon her, but by degrees she slipped back into the social swing, 
encouraged by the fact that Elizabeth seemed to take her going 
out as a matter of course.  But the girl resolutely refused to 
enter into the pastimes of her aunt's pleasure-loving friends. 
She spent her time at the grand piano in the music-room, with a 
book on the <pb n="527"/> ocean-lapped rocks in front of the Crosbys' 
house, or working at the Red Cross branch which had been 
organized in town by Mrs. Maitland Andrews. 
</p><p>Her uncle and aunt treated her with affectionate 
consideration, not pressing her too hard when they found that she 
was adamant in her desire for seclusion, but making her feel that 
her presence was at all times a pleasure to them.  It was only 
when Norman, after much letter-writing and telegraphing on the 
part of his mother, at last appeared at Windy Bluff that Mrs. 
Crosby interfered with the girl's wish for solitude. 
</p><p>"It isn't right, dear, for a girl of your age to spend so 
much time alone," she expostulated one afternoon when, after 
careful manipulation, she had succeeded in persuading Norman to 
ask Betty to take a sail with him in his sloop   &mdash;   an invitation 
which Betty bad politely declined.  "And then, too, Betty dear, 
Norman is very fond of you, and I think you might try to make his 
vacation pleasant.  It's so long since he's had a chance to get 
any outdoor sport, and he needs the fresh air." 
</p><p>So Betty pinned on a wide-brimmed hat and accompanied her 
cousin to the little white boat bobbing serenely on the sparkling 
waters of the harbor. 
</p><p>"Betty," said Norman, after the sails had been raised and the 
boat had slipped away from her moorings, "do you like that?" 
</p><p>He indicated the fast-retreating shore with a toss of his 
head. 
</p><p>"What?" asked Betty innocently. 
</p><p>"That," and again he gave the contemptuous toss. 
</p><p>"Do you mean Newport?" 
</p><p>An amused look crinkled the corners of her eyes.  Norman 
nodded and glanced up at the white sail stretching like a great 
wing above them. 
</p><p>"I do and   &mdash;   I don't," replied Betty thoughtfully.  "As a 
specimen of social life, it's perfection; as a specimen of human 
life, it's   &mdash;   "  She paused, and her face assumed an expression of 
deep seriousness. 
</p><p>"Rotten!" supplemented Norman understandingly.  "Just what I 
think.  How the mater can be so daffy about it is more than I can 
see.  Dad, too   &mdash;   he's not so bad, of course; but in his inmost 
heart, in spite of the fact that he pretends it bores him, he 
loves it, too.  Look out!  You're going to jibe!" 
</p><p>Betty shifted the tiller, and the boat danced along on her 
course, leaving two curling white waves bubbling behind her.  The 
rush of the exhilarating air on her face, the feeling of the boat 
under her controlling hand, brought a bright flush to her cheeks, 
and at least temporarily lightened the heavy burden of her 
sorrow. 
</p><p>"Now this   &mdash;   this is great!" exclaimed Norman enthusiastically. 
"You feel as if you were doing something!  Gee, Betty, it's fine 
having you to play with!" 
</p><p>In the few days he had been with them his eyes had partly 
lost their hunted, bloodshot look, and his pasty cheeks had begun 
to fill out and glow with a semblance of health. 
</p><p>"You're such a bully sort," he went on.  "You've a way about 
you that gets me   &mdash;   as if you had plenty of ballast aboard, and a 
gust of wind wouldn't be apt to capsize you!" 
</p><p>Betty laughed.  In spite of his dissipations, she was fond of 
her cousin, for she realized intuitively that his weakness of 
character was largely due to his defective bringing up. 
</p><p>Immersed in the social life about them, his pleasure-loving 
parents had left the boy to the care of servants during the early 
part of his life, and to even less desirable companions, most of 
whom were unknown to them, as the lad grew into manhood.  It was 
hardly to be wondered at that, with plenty of money, an inherited 
taste for excitement, and practically no supervision or 
restraining influence, he should have succumbed to the 
temptations which surrounded him. 
</p><p>"I suppose it's due to father," she answered.  "He was so 
wonderful   &mdash;   so keen for a good time, and yet he always seemed to 
know just when to stop.  `Drink the top and leave the dregs,' he 
used to say; and, after all"   &mdash;   she looked brightly into the face 
beside her, with its weak chin and loose lips   &mdash;   "the top is good 
enough, without the nastiness of the dregs!" 
</p><p>"It's so hard to stop, though, when you once get started." 
</p><p>"I know," assented Betty gravely; "but that's where you show 
the stuff you're made of   &mdash;   whether you're just sand, or sand and 
cement." 
</p><p>She smiled gently into the boy's troubled face. 
</p><p>"But suppose   &mdash;   suppose the cement has been entirely left out 
of your make-up!  <pb n="528"/> Suppose you're just sand, and shifting 
sand at that, and suppose you don't even want to be anything 
else!" 
</p><p>Norman moved restlessly and wound the sheet he held around 
his thin hand. 
</p><p>"I can't imagine any one, even if he doesn't acknowledge it, 
not wanting to stand up against what he knows will sooner or 
later be his ruin.  Father used to say that life was like any 
other business.  Everything we do goes down in the day-book on 
either the debit or the credit side.  Every once in a while we 
have to balance the book to find out how we stand in our 
bank-account.  It must be a horrid experience to find one has 
overdrawn!" 
</p><p>The boy did not reply, and kept his head resolutely turned 
away. 
</p><p>"Betty," he said at last, "if you found out that some one you 
thought was on the level had played you a dirty trick, what would 
you do?" 
</p><p>"Some one I really cared for?" 
</p><p>Betty's eyes searched his face thoughtfully.  Norman nodded, 
his eyes still fixed on the glistening expanse of water. 
</p><p>"Why, I don't know, I'm sure." Betty hesitated.  "You'd have 
to take so many things into consideration   &mdash;   the reason the person 
had for wronging you, the motives, I mean.  If it were done 
simply to injure you, why, of course, it would be hard; but if it 
were the result of some overwhelming force, some terrible 
temptation that had swept him off his feet, that would be 
different, and much easier to forgive.  Why do you ask?" 
</p><p>She looked at him curiously.  Norman moistened his dry lips. 
</p><p>"Oh, nothing!  I was just wondering," he replied evasively. 
</p><p>When they got back to the house they found Mr. and Mrs. 
Crosby on the broad veranda, Mrs. Crosby busying herself with the 
tea things, which had just been brought in.  In their absence 
George Crosby had returned from a flying trip to New York. 
</p><p>He looked unusually worn and exhausted.  In the past few 
weeks he had lost weight, and his skin hung loosely on his 
cheeks.  His eyes were hollow, and unnaturally bright and 
restless; and he had acquired a habit of tearing stray bits of 
paper, which his wife found extremely trying. 
</p><p>"There's a letter for you on the table, Betty," remarked her 
aunt, after a searching glance at the faces of the two young 
people. 
</p><p>Elizabeth picked up the letter, which was addressed in 
Beatrix Hunnewell's handwriting, and moved toward the steps 
leading to the ocean path. 
</p><p>"No tea?" called Mrs. Crosby. 
</p><p>"Not this afternoon, thank you, aunt." 
</p><p>A little flush had crept into her face, and her eyes were 
luminous.  She walked quickly down the gravel path to her 
favorite spot among the rocks and, sinking down on a smooth 
stone, opened the letter.  It ran: 
 
DEAR BETSY: 
</p><p>When are you coming to us?  I'm longing to see you, for I 
have so much to tell you that I can't very well write. 
</p><p>As I told you in my last letter, your friend, Fairfax Cary, 
has joined the club, and I'm seeing a great deal of him.  We play 
tennis together nearly every afternoon, and he very often comes 
back with me to dinner.  I don't know when I've met a man I 
admire so much.  He's so entirely free from all meannesses, and 
has such a wonderfully broad outlook!  He's coming this afternoon 
to take me for a ride in his new car, for he says it's too hot 
for me to play tennis. 
</p><p>I must stop now to dress.  I want to look my best, for I find 
Fairfax very <hi rend="italic">exigeant!</hi>  Write soon. 
        As ever, affectionately, 
                            TRIXIE. 
 
</p><p>As if scorched by a devastating heat, Elizabeth drooped 
against the rock behind her.  The flush ebbed out of her face, 
and her eyes took on the pained look of a wounded fawn.  The hand 
which held the letter fell into her lap, and she turned her eyes 
toward the harbor, where the gorgeous lights of the sunset lay 
reflected in molten masses of color.  Great angry clouds obscured 
the sun, without entirely hiding it, as it sank slowly into their 
embrace; and a silence breathless with sinister expectancy 
hovered over the waters. 
</p><p>The scene before her accorded perfectly with Betty's mood, 
and a very passion of revolt seized her.  Slowly her mind grasped 
the import of the letter.  Its air of joyous possession of a 
new-found  happiness stole over her like the insidious poison of 
a tropical plant, benumbing her senses, but leaving her brain 
alert.  With it came the feeling that Trixie, in spite of her 
protestations of friendship, had taken advantage of her absence 
to appropriate that which she knew Betty prized above all else. 
<pb n="529"/>  
</p><p>But did she know?  A thin frown of perplexity fluttered over 
Betty's straight brows.  Had even Betty herself known? 
</p><p>Scene after scene of her intercouse{sic} with Fairfax Cary 
sprang up vivid and lifelike before her, culminating in the hour 
that he had spent with her after her father's death.  With a 
little start of surprise, she was forced to admit that even she 
herself had not guessed the nature of her feeling for him. 
</p><p>"What a fool!  What a fool!" she murmured, clenching her 
hands impotently.  "And now it's too late!" 
</p><p>A wild desire to test the sincerity of his promise to come to 
her at any time or place swept over her; but even as she planned 
the meeting she knew it would never take place. 
</p><p>For a long time she sat motionless, her pale face turned 
toward the fading light.  Little by little the flaming brilliance 
softened into cool pinks and lilacs, melting at last into blue 
and neutral gray.  And then, out of the shadows, as if hung by an 
invisible hand, shone the light of the evening star.  Clearer and 
clearer it burned, with a steady effulgence that acted like balm 
on her wound; and at last a semblance of peace settled down upon 
her.  With a little sigh she roused herself and walked listlessly 
back to the house. 
</p><p>In the privacy of Mrs. Crosby's boudoir a stormy scene had 
been taking place. 
</p><p>The International and Congo Rubber Company, in which, at 
Norman's suggestion, George Crosby had invested heavily, was not 
proving the gold-mine of promise.  It was more like a bottomless 
pit which swallowed with avidity the funds fed to it, and 
demanded more with ever-increasing insistence.  To save what he 
had already invested, George Crosby desperately staked all that 
he could lay hands on. 
</p><p>The last statement of the concern had been the reason for his 
hurried trip to New York, and the unsatisfactory conditions that 
he found on his arrival at the company's offices had caused his 
worst fears to be realized.  Nearly all of Betty's fortune was 
already swept away. 
</p><p>He was pacing up and down the floor now, his face drawn, his 
eyes staring wildly from beneath his contracted brows.  Mrs. 
Crosby sat tense and rigid in a big chair by the window, and her 
son leaned against the mantelpiece.  Their faces were ghastly, 
and a frightened look lurked in Norman's eyes. 
</p><p>"George!  How could you have been so foolish?" demanded his 
wife, her angry eyes fixed on her husband. 
</p><p>George Crosby turned furiously to her. 
</p><p>"For Heaven's sake, Maude," he exclaimed between his teeth, 
"try not to make it any harder for me than it already is!  You 
know perfectly well why I did it   &mdash;   it was to save this young 
scoundrel from State's prison!"  He pointed a trembling finger at 
Norman, who cowered under the lash of his words.  "And now," he 
went on bitterly, "it looks as if I should have to take his 
place!" 
</p><p>"Can nothing be done?" 
</p><p>George Crosby spread out his hands hopelessly. 
</p><p>"I don't see any way out," he groaned, sinking into a deep 
chair. 
</p><p>The sight of his collapse galvanized Mrs. Crosby into action. 
</p><p>"Very well, then, I'll find a way!" she exclaimed grimly. 
"If you think I'm going to sit calmly by and accept the ruin you 
two men have brought on me, you have a very inadequate conception 
of my character.  I decline to be either the wife or the mother 
of a jailbird!" 
</p><p>Both men shrank from the scorn in her voice, but neither 
answered her.  Her husband took up an empty envelope and began 
feverishly tearing it to pieces, but at her "George, put that 
down!" he obediently laid the scraps in a neat little pile on the 
table at his elbow. 
</p><p>"How much of Randolph's money is gone?" she asked in a voice 
like ice. 
</p><p>"Practically all." 
</p><p>"You put everything into this rubber speculation?" 
</p><p>"All but the fifty thousand I had to refund the firm." 
</p><p>Norman shivered under the biting contempt in his father's 
voice and eyes. 
</p><p>"Well, Norman," said his mother coldly, "as far as I can see, 
as you are the one responsible for this catastrophe, you'll have 
to be the one to get us out!" 
</p><p>"How?"  The word came in a husky whisper, barely audible. 
</p><p>"By marrying Betty." 
</p><p>Norman gave a hoarse, mirthless laugh and looked for an 
instant with haggard eyes into his mother's face. 
</p><p>"Marry Betty!" he jeered.  "Why, that girl would as soon 
think of marrying me as <pb n="630"/> she would   &mdash;   "  The words trailed off 
into nothingness, and his head sank forward on his chest. 
</p><p>"Why?" demanded his mother. 
</p><p>"Why?  Because she knows I'm not fit to sit in the same room 
with her, much less marry her!" 
</p><p>"How does she know?  Have you been such a fool as to confide 
your   &mdash;   er   &mdash;   escapades to her?" 
</p><p>"Hardly!"  A sneer curled the boy's lips. 
</p><p>Give me credit for some sense!" 
</p><p>"You haven't led us to believe you had overmuch!" retorted 
his mother contemptuously. 
</p><p>The muscles of the boy's mouth tightened, and he glared for a 
moment at the pitiless face below him.  Then he shrugged his 
shoulders impatiently and returned to his moody contemplation of 
the rug. 
</p><p>"There is nothing," Mrs. Crosby went on impressively, "that a 
girl of Betty's temperament likes better than to reform a man.  I 
think if you could impress on her how much her influence could do 
for you, you would find that she was far from averse to marrying 
you.  I know she's extremely fond of you.  In fact, she told me 
so only this morning." 
</p><p>Evidently Norman doubted the truth of his mother's words; 
but, taught by long experience, he refrained from arguing the 
point with her. 
</p><p>"Did you ever stop to think that it's a pretty bum deal we're 
giving her?" he asked grimly. 
</p><p>"It's no time to think of that now," answered his mother 
impatiently.  "She will surely marry some one, and there's no 
reason on earth why she shouldn't be as happy with you as with 
any one else   &mdash;   that is, if you choose to make her so." 
</p><p>"Perhaps she would," assented the young man dubiously. 
"But I can't help feeling sorry for her." 
</p><p>"Sorry for her!  Sorry for her!  Naturally I'm sorry for her, 
too; but   &mdash;   how about your mother?" broke in Mrs. Crosby hotly. 
"Aren't you sorry for her?" 
</p><p>Norman was silent.  He knew that even the comparatively few 
years he had lived had made him unfit to be the husband of any 
woman.  Genuinely fond as he was of Elizabeth, the idea of 
injuring her beyond what he had already done was repellent to 
him, realizing as he did that even her influence could not wean 
him from the life that had ensnared him. 
</p><p>He was on the point of declining to fall in with his mother's 
plans when his eyes fell on the stricken figure of his father, 
huddled in the big chair, George Crosby's face was gray with the 
unearthly pallor of a mortal illness, and Norman stared at him in 
remorseful silence. 
</p><p>"All right, mother," he said huskily.  "I'll do my best." 
He hastily left the room. 
</p> 
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="5" id="d9"> 
<head>V</head> 
 
<p>It was an unusually silent party that gathered around the 
softly lighted table for dinner that evening, and the 
conversation, in spite of Mrs. Crosby's efforts to enliven it, 
dragged perceptibly.  Dish after dish left the room practically 
untouched, each one being so bent on concealing his or her lack 
of appetite that the same condition of the others passed 
unnoticed.  But of the frequency with which Norman's wine-glass 
was refilled his mother was more observant; and at last she 
indicated, with an imperious gesture that brought immediate 
compliance, that he had had enough. 
</p><p>It was with a distinct feeling of relief that, the meal being 
ended, Mrs. Crosby rose and, drawing Elizabeth's hand through her 
arm, led the girl to the veranda, which was lighted by the 
uncertain rays of a swinging lantern.  Sinking back among the 
cushions of a wicker sofa, she drew her niece down beside her. 
</p><p>"I feel as if I hadn't half told you how happy it makes me to 
have you here with us," she murmured, pressing Betty's arm 
gently.  "You're very dear to me, child!" 
</p><p>A rush of tenderness swept over Elizabeth.  Her parched soul, 
craving love with the intense desire begot by long denial, 
reached out with an inarticulate cry for the first demonstration 
of affection she had received since her father's death. 
</p><p>"Dear aunty!" she whispered brokenly, her hand clinging to 
the older woman's arm.  "You're very good to me.  I can never 
thank you enough!" 
</p><p>"No, dear," remonstrated her  aunt; "it is I who should be 
the grateful one.  You are filling the place in my heart of the 
little daughter I have always longed for.  Sons are very nice, 
Betty, but a mother's heart is always empty, and her life 
incomplete, until <pb n="531"/> she has the warm sympathy of a daughter 
who understands in a way impossible to a man.  I should love to 
feel that you were going to be with us always, that no one could 
ever take you away." 
</p><p>"No one ever will, aunty," whispered the girl tremulously. 
</p><p>The ache in her heart was becoming more and more unendurable, 
and she grasped eagerly at the home that she had accepted so 
reluctantly a few weeks before. 
</p><p>Mrs. Crosby gave her arm a gentle pat and then released her. 
</p><p>"That's right!" she exclaimed warmly; then, as the men came 
through the doorway, she added:  "Now let Norman take you on the 
rocks; the moonlight is gorgeous on the water to-night. 
Norman, fetch a wrap for Betty." 
</p><p>Norman threw a scarf over Betty's bare shoulders, rising 
white and smooth out of the filmy black of her gown.  She 
reluctantly accompanied him to the water's edge and sank down on 
the rock over which he had spread a rug.  He dropped down beside 
her, and for a while neither spoke. 
</p><p>Betty's eyes were fixed on the path of moonlight which 
wavered on the dark waters.  Her mind, wandering off to the 
Hunnewells' home, pictured Trixie and Fairfax Cary strolling 
along the paths of the rose-scented garden, or watching this same 
moon from the pagoda, with its curtain of fragrant honeysuckle. 
</p><p>Norman, too, seemed content to sit in silence, and puffed 
away vigorously at the cigar which apparently absorbed his 
attention.  At last he spoke. 
</p><p>"Betty," he began hesitatingly, " could you   &mdash;   love   &mdash;   a man you 
didn't   &mdash;   respect?" 
</p><p>"I don't know, I'm sure, Norman," replied Elizabeth 
uncertainly.  "Why do you ask?" 
</p><p>"Oh, I was just wondering how a girl like you would feel 
about that sort of thing   &mdash;   marriage, I mean, with a man who hadn't 
always   &mdash;   kept straight." 
</p><p>"Marriage!" breathed Betty almost fiercely.  "I'm never going 
to marry!" 
</p><p>Norman gave a little snort of incredulity. 
</p><p>"Ha!  That's what almost all girls say   &mdash;   generally just before 
they announce their engagements!" 
</p><p>"Well, in this case it's true," insisted Betty finally.  "I 
haven't the least intention of marrying   &mdash;   ever!" 
</p><p>"If you thought it would help some one   &mdash;   help him to keep out 
of trouble, and all that   &mdash;   wouldn't you?" 
</p><p>There was a wistful note in his voice.  Betty turned her 
eyes, in which the hurt look still lingered, to the recumbent 
figure of the boy beside her, his flushed face dimly visible in 
the uncertain light. 
</p><p>"Why do you ask?" she questioned wonderingly. 
</p><p>Norman turned impulsively to her. 
</p><p>"Just this, Betty.  I can't seem to be able to   &mdash;   keep 
straight.  I've tried my best, and I just can't do it; and I 
thought perhaps, if you could bring yourself to take me on   &mdash;    
you're so strong, I know   &mdash;   I could stand out against it all.  I'm 
sure I could!  Oh, Betty, don't you think you could bring 
yourself to marry me?" 
</p><p>The words came out in a torrent of desperation.  Betty looked 
at him as if, in spite of the fact that she heard them, their 
meaning had passed her by. 
</p><p>"Marry you?" she repeated vaguely. 
</p><p>"Yes, Betty   &mdash;   darling, I love you!" 
</p><p>He roused himself from his reclining position and, putting 
his arm around her, bent his head down to hers.  His breath, 
heavy with wine and the smell of the cigar, sickened her, and she 
pushed him away almost violently. 
</p><p>"Don't, Norman, don't!" 
</p><p>Norman took away his arm and, leaning his elbows on his 
drawn-up knees, stared gloomily before him. 
</p><p>"Well, I can't say I blame you," he remarked morosely. 
</p><p>Something in the boy's humility turned Betty's feeling of 
resentment into one of contrition. 
</p><p>"But, Norman," she exclaimed, "it isn't that!  Oh, please 
believe me!  I'd do anything in the world to help you, but I 
couldn't marry any one I didn't love.  Norman dear, you know I'm 
fond of you   &mdash;   really fond of you, but it isn't the same!" 
</p><p>"Do you think if I gave up drinking, and kept away from 
trouble generally, you could ever   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>But Betty shook her head emphatically. 
</p><p>"No, dear; it isn't the kind of feeling which, no matter how 
strong it grew, could ever turn into the love I must have for the 
man I'm going to marry." 
</p><p>For a moment neither spoke; then Norman said curiously: 
<pb n="532"/>  
</p><p>"Have you ever known a man you could love like that?" 
</p><p>Betty did not reply, and nothing but the splash of the waves 
as they dashed impotently against the rocks at their feet broke 
the silence. 
</p><p>"Who was it, Betty?" asked Norman at last.  "Was it Fairfax 
Cary?" 
</p><p>Betty started violently. 
</p><p>"Fairfax Cary?" she repeated in a startled voice.  "Oh, no!" 
</p><p>"I'll bet it was!" declared Norman. 
</p><p>He's just the sort of guy who would get a girl like you. 
Well, I wish you joy of him!  Awful prig, but he wouldn't keep 
you up nights worrying!"  He got up and stretched himself lazily. 
"Well, me for bed!  How about it, fair coz?" 
</p><p>Betty rose quickly to her feet and put her hand on Norman's 
shoulder. 
</p><p>"You're all wrong about my loving Mr. Cary, Norman," she said 
emphatically.  "It's absolutely untrue.  I don't care for him at 
all, except as a friend; but he isn't a prig, Norman.  He's the 
finest   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"All right!" agreed Norman indifferently, stooping to pick up 
the rug.  "But don't get so stewed about it!  I didn't say he 
wasn't." 
</p><p>They turned toward the house. 
</p><p>"It's no use, mater," he announced sullenly to his mother, 
after Betty had bid them good night.  "Just as I thought, she's 
in love with that Cary chap." 
</p><p>"Did she tell you so?" asked his mother sharply. 
</p><p>"Not in so many words, but she showed it pretty plainly. 
He's just the kind of man she would fall for   &mdash;   always gassing 
about ideals and uplift and all that hot air.  Any one could 
see   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"Well," ruminated his mother, half to herself, "perhaps when 
Elizabeth learns that her father did not leave behind him the 
savory reputation she sets such store by, she will realize that 
his daughter may not hold the same attraction as she did for a 
man of Cary's stamp." 
</p><p>"What do you mean?" asked the boy fearfully. 
</p><p>"Never mind what I mean, Normie.  Go to bed!  I think before 
long your pretty cousin will be thankful to marry you!" 
</p><p>But it was well past midnight before Mrs. Crosby followed the 
advice she gave her son, and even then it was not to sleep.  Hour 
after hour she lay staring at the moonlight filtering in through 
the filmy curtains, and causing the familiar objects in the room 
to assume grotesque and, to Mrs. Crosby's tortured mind, 
vindictive shapes. 
</p><p>Enraged at finding herself entangled in a net which wrapped 
itself tighter and tighter about her, threatening her very 
existence, she groped about blindly, feverishly, to find the 
means of escape which she insisted must exist.  It couldn't be 
that she, Maude Crosby, after all these years of comparative 
immunity   &mdash;   due to skilful manipulation on her part, she reminded 
herself   &mdash;   should come to grief because a girl, a mere child, 
opposed her will! 
</p><p>Keyed to its highest pitch, her mind reviewed the conditions 
that confronted her.  Plan after plan formulated itself, only to 
crumble away at the fancied touch of the girl's hand.  But at 
last a course of action presented itself which she thought would 
solve her difficulties, and she dropped off into a fitful doze. 
</p><p>The broad sunlight was streaming in through the open windows 
when she awoke and found her French maid standing by her bedside, 
a dainty tray containing Mrs. Crosby's breakfast in the girl's 
hands. 
</p> 
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="6" id="d10"> 
<head>VI</head> 
 
<p>The sultry atmosphere that had enveloped the Crosby household 
during dinner lasted throughout the next morning, but Elizabeth 
did not suspect that she was even remotely the cause of it. 
Accustomed to her aunt's moods, which succeeded one another with 
such frequency and rapidity that Betty had learned to regard them 
with a more or less amused tolerance, she avoided Mrs. Crosby by 
spending the morning at the Red Cross rooms.  But when the 
feeling of oppression lasted through luncheon, she began to fear 
that Norman had confided her rebuff of him to his parents, and 
that their changed attitude toward her was the evidence of their 
resentment. 
</p><p>When the meal was over she followed her uncle into his den, 
where he was generally to be found at times of domestic unrest. 
</p><p>"Uncle George," she began, pausing on the threshold. 
</p><p>"Come in, Betty," he replied from the depths of his leather 
chair.  "Come in   &mdash;   I want to talk to you." 
</p><p>Betty dropped down among the cushions on the window-seat. 
<pb n="533"/>  
</p><p>"That sounds nice!" she said with her bright smile. 
</p><p>Her uncle's likeness to her father had increased as the 
younger man lost weight, and with it his air of indolent ease; 
and in the months she had passed in his home, when she had 
learned something of the burden under which he labored, her 
affection for him had increased fourfold. 
</p><p>She watched him fondly as he reclined in his big chair, his 
head resting against the back, his half-closed eyes following the 
rings of smoke from the cigar that he had just taken from his 
mouth.  Betty waited for him to begin; but as he did not seem 
inclined to open the conversation she remarked quietly: 
</p><p>"Uncle George, will you please give me five hundred dollars?" 
</p><p>The hand that held the cigar dropped nervelessly on the arm 
of the chair, and the cigar fell to the floor.  Muttering 
something about inexcusable carelessness, her uncle stooped down 
and picked it up.  When he straightened, and Betty saw his face, 
she was shocked at its appearance. 
</p><p>"Uncle, are you ill?" she asked, coming to him and bending 
solicitously over him. 
</p><p>"I'm all right, thank you," he replied huskily, and reached 
with a trembling hand for the match-box. 
</p><p>Betty leaned against the edge of the table beside him, and 
watched him doubtfully as he unsteadily applied the light to his 
cigar.  Then she went on: 
</p><p>"Mrs. Maitland Andrews, the chairman of our Red Cross branch, 
is raising money for an ambulance to be sent to France, and I 
promised her five hundred dollars." 
</p><p>Betty made the announcement with the calm assurance of one 
who, never having been denied money in reasonable amounts, did 
not consider a refusal possible.  George Crosby settled even 
deeper in his chair. 
</p><p>"Betty, I'm sorry," he began at last, but until I get your 
father's affairs straightened out, I'm   &mdash;   I'm afraid   &mdash;   it's 
impossible, quite impossible for   &mdash;   me to let you have so   &mdash;   much 
money." 
</p><p>Betty looked at him, her blue eyes round with wonder. 
</p><p>"But, uncle," she expostulated, " father told me just before 
he died that he always kept several thousand dollars on deposit 
for emergencies, and that he never drew on that account." 
</p><p>"There have been some pretty heavy drafts on it lately, 
however   &mdash;   funeral expenses and outstanding bills that you asked me 
to pay at once," he reminded her. 
</p><p>"Yes, I know, Uncle George, but they couldn't have exceeded a 
couple of thousand dollars, and there must have been some income 
from the estate during the past months." 
</p><p>George Crosby's eyes fell before the girl's steady gaze.  He 
examined the end of his cigar carefully. 
</p><p>"Betty," he said at last in a strained, hard voice, "I've 
been meaning to tell you about it for a long time, but I thought 
I would wait until   &mdash;   well, until you had got your strength back 
after the shock and grief of your father's death.  There isn't 
any estate." 
</p><p>"No estate!" echoed Betty incredulously, bending toward him 
the better to see his face. 
</p><p>Her uncle shook his head, his eyes still fixed on his cigar. 
</p><p>"No," he went on.  "Your father made unfortunate investments 
before he died, and practically his entire fortune was lost.  It 
was thought that the shock and disappointment, and all that, were 
the cause of his death." 
</p><p>He replaced the cigar between his lips and drew deeply on it. 
</p><p>"I can't see how it is possible!" exclaimed Betty, clasping 
her hands piteously. 
</p><p>"My dear child"   &mdash;   George Crosby turned his haggard, twitching 
face toward her   &mdash;   "when you've lived as long as I, you'll realize 
that in the financial world it's generally the impossible that 
happens, especially in times such as these.  Your father had the 
reputation of being a clever, hard-headed business man, but since 
I've been going over his affairs I've been surprised, and I may 
say shocked, to find the number of wildcat investments he made. 
Of course, in time some of them may be worth something, but at 
present   &mdash;   "  He paused significantly, and for a fleeting instant 
his eyes sought hers. 
</p><p>"Then I'm a   &mdash;   pauper" faltered Betty, her face white and 
frightened. 
</p><p>"Don't say that, dear child!  You'll always have a home with 
us, of course, and the best we can give you; but I'm afraid 
five-hundred-dollar subscriptions will have to be cut out for the 
present at least.  You understand, I know, that it isn't because 
I <pb n="534"/> don't want you to have the money, don't you, Betty?   &mdash;   but 
simply because it isn't there!" 
</p><p>He rose and put his arm around the drooping figure.  Betty 
raised her white face to him. 
</p><p>"Thank you, Uncle George," she whispered tremulously. 
"You've always been very good to me, and I'm very grateful; but 
what hurts me"   &mdash;   her voice broke   &mdash;   "is that any one should think 
that father was involved in transactions that weren't   &mdash;   quite   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"Don't let that worry you, my dear.  The world is so used to 
heavy jolts after men die that such a thing is no longer even a 
nine days' wonder." 
</p><p>"Oh, but   &mdash;   but father was   &mdash;   different!" interrupted Betty 
almost fiercely.  "He was not like that!  Any one who knew him at 
all must have realized that he wasn't that kind of man.  Why, he 
had the biggest heart and soul of any one I knew!" 
</p><p>"Bigness of heart and soul don't necessarily mean fulness of 
pocket, though," her uncle hastened to assure her, with a dubious 
shake of his head.  "Quite the reverse!  Well, I'll do the best I 
can, and perhaps, as I say, some of the investments will turn out 
better than we anticipate; but in the mean time we'll have to go 
a bit slow." 
</p><p>As if in a dream, Betty crept up to the seclusion of her room 
and sank into a rocking-chair in the deep bay window.  She gazed 
out at the expanse of water roughened into whitecaps under the 
lash of a strong south wind.  Benumbed and heavy-limbed, she 
watched the gulls as they poised against the currents of air, 
hanging suspended and almost motionless for an instant, and then 
with unerring precision swooping down into the dark water and 
reappearing with their prey dangling in their beaks. 
</p><p>Hour after hour she sat as motionless as if a freezing breath 
had turned her into ice.  The shadows crept across the lawn to 
the water's edge, and still she sat with the look of pain 
deepening in her eyes. 
</p><p>It was almost dark when Mrs. Crosby knocked at the door, and 
without waiting for Betty's "Come in!" opened it and entered the 
room.  She had just returned from a bridge-party at Mrs. Peyton 
Grenville's, and an air of antagonism emanated from her, as if 
the afternoon had not been a profitable one. 
</p><p>Mrs. Crosby was one of those people who lay their winnings to 
their own skill and their losings to the malice of fate, against 
which they protest long and loudly.  This afternoon luck had been 
decidedly against her.  She had come directly from the motor to 
her niece's room, and was unaware of Elizabeth's interview with 
her husband; but she had definitely made up her mind that the 
only way out of the difficulties which were closing in about them 
was through the marriage of Elizabeth and Norman.  As Betty had 
long since learned, it was not well to frustrate Mrs. Crosby's 
plans. 
</p><p>"I want to talk to you a little, Betty," she began, sinking 
into the chair that her niece drew up for her and pulling off her 
long, white gloves. 
</p><p>Betty fixed her great eyes on her aunt's face in an almost 
visible effort to concentrate on her words.  Inwardly she shrank 
from what she realized was in store for her; for Mrs. Crosby's 
face had the implacable look that meant: 
</p><p>"There's only one path to follow, and that follows me!" 
</p><p>"It's about Norman, dear," Mrs. Crosby went on.  She was 
trying to untie the dotted veil which so cunningly hid the marks 
that time and worry had left on her face, and Betty jumped to her 
assistance.  "Thank you, dear; you're such a helpful little 
daughter!" 
</p><p>She patted the girl's hand as she took the veil from her. 
Then she continued:  "You know that boy is simply infatuated with 
you, child; he talks of nothing else, and this afternoon, before 
I left for Mrs. Grenville's, he told me again how much your 
influence has done for him." 
</p><p>"I'm very glad, Aunt Maude," murmured Betty dully. 
</p><p>"Men are strange creatures, Betty," her aunt went on. 
"Although they call us the weaker sex, it seems as if we women 
are continually obliged to make allowance for their failings, and 
to strengthen them in their hours of temptation.  And, Betty 
dear, I don't suppose there is any higher vocation for a woman 
than that of saving a man from the purgatory in which he would 
end if it were not for her help."  She stopped to study the 
serious face before her, and added playfully:  "Don't look so 
solemn, child!  A man's love ought to bring joy, happiness, and 
not sadness!" 
<pb n="535"/>  
</p><p>The lines of Betty's face obediently relaxed into a pitiful 
attempt at a smile. 
</p><p>"I am glad, Aunt Maude," she reiterated. 
</p><p>"Then will you let me tell the dear boy so, Betty?" asked 
Mrs. Crosby, an exultant look stealing over her face.  "He thinks 
you don't care.  In fact, he told me so; and I should love to be 
the one to bring him the news that he's wrong!" 
</p><p>"He knows that I care for him, aunt, but   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"But what?" 
</p><p>The question was like the crack of a gun. 
</p><p>"But"   &mdash;   it seemed as if the girl's white lips could not frame 
the words, but after a pleading look into her aunt's relentless 
face Betty went on desperately   &mdash;   "Norman asked me to marry him, 
and I   &mdash;   I can't!" 
</p><p>"Why not?" 
</p><p>Mrs. Crosby's voice was like ice. 
</p><p>"Oh, aunt!" Betty clasped her trembling hands piteously. 
"It's quite impossible   &mdash;   quite; you must see that!" 
</p><p>"I see nothing," answered her aunt uncompromisingly, "except 
that the boy loves you, and you are the one woman who could save 
him from   &mdash;   ruin!" 
</p><p>Mrs. Crosby's voice broke over the last word.  This sign of 
unwonted emotion brought a throb of pity into Betty's throat and 
made her task even more difficult. 
</p><p>"But, Aunt Maude," she faltered, "before he   &mdash;   died, father 
made me promise that I would never marry a man I wasn't sure of 
or that he wouldn't have approved of.  I don't think   &mdash;   in fact, he 
would not have I'm quite certain that wanted me to marry Norman." 
</p><p>"Your father was hardly one to assume the position of judge 
of men, my dear!" 
</p><p>The words came with a cutting emphasis that pierced the 
girl's brain like a knife. 
</p><p>"What do you mean?" she asked hoarsely. 
</p><p>"Just what I say.  Your father's life was not so exemplary 
that he could afford to criticise those who were simply entering 
on the paths that he had already trod!" 
</p><p>Betty shrank back as if seared by a flame. 
</p><p>"Do you mean to insinuate that my father was dishonorable?" 
</p><p>"I insinuate nothing.  I <hi rend="italic">state"</hi>   &mdash;   Mrs. Crosby paused for an 
instant so that the full force of her words should strike home   &mdash;    
"that Randolph Crosby, before he died, was publicly cut by his 
most intimate friends!" 
</p><p>As if unable fully to grasp the import of her aunt's words, 
Betty stared wide-eyed into her face. 
</p><p>"My, father?" she gasped at last, a quiver of incredulous 
pain passing over her ashen face.  "I don't believe it!" 
</p><p>Mrs. Crosby looked at her curiously.  Such suffering as the 
girl exhibited at the assault on her father's name was 
incomprehensible to her.  After all, what did it matter?  But she 
was quick to see the advantage it gave her, and she followed it 
up with ruthless celerity. 
</p><p>"Well, whether you believe it or not, the fact remains that 
after Steadfast was so disgracefully beaten for the Withers Stake 
there was a great deal of talk about foul play, and I myself saw 
Humphrey Welsh and several others refuse to speak to your father. 
It was suspected that he had won a great deal of money on the 
race   &mdash;   much more than enough to offset the loss of the purse!" 
</p><p>All the rancor of the past months over her loss on the race, 
for which she had always blamed Randolph Crosby, came out in the 
bitterness of Mrs. Crosby's words. 
</p><p>Elizabeth drooped further into her chair, and the line of 
pain between her eyebrows deepened.  As a flash of lightning 
reveals a scene in the darkness of the night, the picture of the 
club enclosure after the race rose before her.  She recalled her 
own and Fairfax Cary's doubts as to Steadfast's running, and her 
father's tense face when he came back from his interview with 
Pat. 
</p><p>As a logical sequence came the remembrance of Mrs. 
Hunnewell's peculiar behavior when Trixie had joined them, and 
her insistence that the girl should return to her at once.  There 
was evidently some truth behind her aunt's words, but that her 
father was in any way connected with anything that bore the least 
resemblance to crookedness she resolutely refused to believe. 
</p><p>Mrs. Crosby evidently realized that she had said enough, for 
her manner softened almost to tenderness. 
</p><p>"Forgive me, child, if I've hurt you," she said gently; "but 
your words struck me in a very vulnerable place.  When her only 
son is attacked, a mother naturally resents it.  Your reflections 
on Norman's character goaded me into doing what I long ago 
decided I would never do   &mdash;   let you know the estimation in which 
the world <pb n="536"/>  held your father before his death.  You see, it 
would hardly be possible, under the circumstances, for him to 
object to Norman as a son-in-law!" 
</p><p>She smiled sweetly at the girl; but Betty, her face drawn and 
rigid, continued staring fixedly at her aunt.  She did not relax 
when the older woman rose, and, laying her hand on her niece's 
shoulder, leaned over her and said: 
</p><p>"Well, may I take a little ray of hope to the dear boy?" 
</p><p>In a voice that sounded as if it came from a great distance, 
Betty responded: 
</p><p>"I shall never marry any one   &mdash;   now!" 
</p><p>Mrs. Crosby raised her eyebrows despairingly.  She withdrew 
her hand and moved toward the door. 
</p><p>"I hope in time you'll feel differently," she remarked.  "By 
the bye, Mrs. Goodhue has just returned from Lawrence, and she 
told me this afternoon that your little friend Trixie Hunnewell 
is engaged to Fairfax Cary." 
</p><p>Betty did not reply, so Mrs. Crosby passed out into the hall, 
the perplexed frown lingering around her eyes. 
</p> 
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="7" id="d11"> 
<head>VII</head> 
 
<p>Like a wounded thing stricken unto death, Betty sat alone, 
hardly aware that her aunt had gone.  Her great eyes, distended 
and dark with pain, gazed out into the fading twilight.  She was 
forcing her mind back over the events which just preceded her 
father's death. 
</p><p>Scene after scene presented itself vividly to her, like 
little pieces of mosaic which fitted accurately into one another; 
and at last a completed picture was disclosed which solved 
problems hitherto inexplicable.  The sudden falling away of 
people whom she had thought her friends, and whose unsympathetic 
bearing at the time of her sorrow had puzzled and hurt her beyond 
words; the coolness of others with whom she had unavoidably been 
brought into contact   &mdash;   the revelations of the afternoon explained 
it all. 
</p><p>The twilight deepened into night, and still she sat 
motionless, staring out into the dark, her brain groping through 
the maze of memories for the image of her father.  Her brow 
contracted as she struggled to visualize the presence that always 
seemed to linger near her.  When at last she succeeded, and the 
cold, keen-eyed, rather cynical face was outlined against the 
dark clouds of doubt that her uncle and aunt had raised, her lips 
trembled into a happy smile of restored confidence. 
</p><p>She rose stiffly and switched on the light.  Going to the 
writing-table, on which stood the large picture of her father, 
she took it up and looked tenderly into the stern face. 
Unflinchingly the keen eyes returned her gaze until the 
questioning expression in her eyes turned into one of perfect 
trust, and the taut lines of her face relaxed. 
</p><p>"No matter what they say," she whispered softly, "I shall 
always believe you were as true as steel!" 
</p><p>At her words the eyes seemed to soften into the look of 
tenderness they had always held for her. 
</p><p>Her eyes wandered from the photograph to the dainty things 
about her   &mdash;   the flowered chintses, the tasteful furnishings, the 
pretty French prints, their wires concealed by shirred ribbons 
surmounted by a bow; the glass-topped dressing-table with its 
array of silver-backed toilet articles; the inviting bed where 
she had passed so many restful nights.  The conviction came over 
her that she could no longer remain a member of that household. 
</p><p>But where to go?  She knew her world too well not to 
understand that the homes where the daughter of the prosperous 
Randolph Crosby was so eagerly welcomed would be closed to the 
child of the discredited outcast.  But though no alternative 
suggested itself to her, the fact remained glaringly apparent 
that it was impossible for her to stay at Windy Bluff. 
</p><p>A knock sounded at the door, and Marie, the French maid, 
asked if she could be of any assistance to <hi rend="italic">mademoiselle</hi>.  Betty 
replied that as she had a headache she did not want any dinner 
and would not need her again that night.  Then she locked the 
door quietly, drew out a suit-case from the depths of the closet, 
placed the photograph of her father carefully in it, and began 
hurriedly packing it with things from the closet and drawers. 
Every now and then she glanced at the little gilt clock on the 
mantel, feverishly ticking the minutes away. 
</p><p>She took off the white muslin she had worn all day, and put 
on a black suit and a hat, over which she tied a heavy veil. 
Then, with a final lingering look about the room, <pb n="537"/> she turned 
off the lights, picked up the suitcase, and opened the door. 
</p><p>After listening intently for a moment, she stole along the 
corridor and down the stairs to the large hall below.  Subdued 
voices came from the dining-room, but the drawing-rooms were 
deserted, and Betty made her way unnoticed to the front door. 
Opening it softly, she crept out into the friendly darkness. 
Fearful lest the gravel of the drive should betray her flying 
footsteps, she sped across the lawn toward the entrance gates, 
and with a deep sigh of relief passed between them into the 
highway beyond. 
</p><p>The moisture-laden wind was blowing in fitful gusts that gave 
promise of rain in the near future, and Betty quickened her pace 
once more.  She kept her eyes anxiously alert for a conveyance 
that would take her to her destination, for the suit-case 
increased in weight with every step and seriously impeded her 
progress; but at that hour all the public hacks were in demand to 
take diners-out to the homes of their respective hosts, and Betty 
did not dare to ask a lift in any of the returning private 
motors, for fear that the chauffeurs might recognize her. 
</p><p>Notwithstanding the fact that she was thankful for the 
protection the darkness gave her, she started violently at every 
unusual sound.  Once or twice she had to stop, rest her suit-case 
on the ground, and lean for support against a railing or tree 
until she recovered her breath sufficiently to be able to go on. 
</p><p>It was with an involuntary "Thank Heaven!" that she at last 
spied the bright lights of the wharf, which revealed the shadowy 
hulk of the boat alongside.  A continuous ebbing and flowing 
stream of dark figures passed up and down the gangway, and Betty, 
realizing that not many minutes remained before the hour for 
starting, hastily made her way to the ticket-office and procured 
her passage for New York. 
</p><p>As she passed down the corridor   &mdash;   through which white-coated 
stewards were hurrying, calling vociferously, "All ashore!  All 
ashore!"   &mdash;   she came face to face with Mrs. Maitland Andrews.  Mrs. 
Andrews stared at her doubtfully for a moment, trying to 
penetrate the heavy veil.  Then, as Betty tried to edge past to 
her stateroom, she exclaimed, laying her hand on the girl's 
shoulder: 
</p><p>"Aren't you   &mdash;   why, yes, you <hi rend="italic">are</hi> Betty Crosby!" 
</p><p>Realizing that it was impossible to escape recognition, and 
anxious to explain to Mrs. Andrews her inability to make good her 
promise in regard to a donation for the ambulance, Betty drew the 
older woman into her stateroom. 
</p><p>"Would you mind coming in for a minute?" she pleaded.  "I 
want to tell you   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>Perceiving from the tremulous tones of the faltering voice 
that something was amiss, Mrs. Andrews readily accompanied the 
girl. 
</p><p>"Why, of course, dear," she responded heartily.   "We'll have 
a nice talk   &mdash;   not a soul to interrupt us!" 
</p><p>Betty untied her veil and took it off before she spoke again. 
</p><p>Mrs. Andrews's role of confidante to every sort and condition 
of man occupied almost all the time that she did not spend at the 
board-meetings of the many societies she practically ran and 
supported.  Bishops and newsboys, great financiers and debutant 
girls, poured their difficulties into her sympathetic ears, and 
went away strengthened by her sound counsel.  Betty had always 
been an especial favorite with her, and with open arms she had 
welcomed the girl into the Red Cross work, knowing that it was 
the most effectual means of alleviating her sorrow. 
</p><p>It was with deep concern that she noted the ghastliness of 
the young face and the tightly compressed lips.  She settled 
herself comfortably on the lounge and, in order to give Betty 
time to compose herself   &mdash;   for she saw that the girl had difficulty 
in beginning   &mdash;   remarked beamingly: 
</p><p>"I'm going to New York to order the ambulance.  Isn't it 
splendid?  All the money has been promised, and I want to get it 
off at once." 
</p><p>A tremor passed over Betty's face. 
</p><p>"That's what I want to tell you," she began impulsively, 
laying her hand on Mrs. Andrews's arm.  "I can't   &mdash;   it's impossible 
for me to give you the money I promised this morning." 
</p><p>Mrs. Andrews placed her hand gently over the girl's. 
</p><p>"That's all right, dear; it won't matter in the least.  It 
'll come in from somewhere   &mdash;   it always does.  Please don't fret 
about it!" 
<pb n="538"/>  
</p><p>Two great tears overflowed Betty's eyes and rolled down her 
cheeks. 
</p><p>"I was afraid you wouldn't understand," she whispered 
tremulously.  "I was afraid you might think I wanted to pose as 
being very generous before all those women this morning and then 
back out in private; but I thought I had the money, and   &mdash;   and it 
isn't there!" 
</p><p>She caught her lower lip in her teeth in an attempt to still 
its trembling.  Mrs. Andrews took the girl's hand between hers 
and began stroking it gently. 
</p><p>"Tell me all about it, dear; perhaps I can help you." 
</p><p>But Betty shook her head hopelessly. 
</p><p>"No one can help, as far as the money goes.  It's all gone   &mdash;    
every penny of it.  Apparently father made investments that 
didn't turn out well, and instead of being a rich man he was 
quite the reverse.  I'm on my way to New York now to look for 
something to do." 
</p><p>"Have you left your uncle's for good?" 
</p><p>Betty nodded. 
</p><p>"I couldn't possibly stay   &mdash;   there were conditions that made it 
quite out of the question.  Not that Uncle George wasn't 
perfectly sweet, and told me that they allways expected me to 
make my home with them, but   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"I understand," answered Mrs. Andrews gravely.  "You don't 
want to be under obligations to them.  Sometimes it's like that, 
and the obligations keep mounting up and mounting up until it 
seems as if they would crush you, no matter what you do in 
return.  It's much pleasanter to stand on your own feet, even 
though it means hard work.  What sort of place are you thinking 
of taking?" 
</p><p>Betty turned a wan little face, over which flickered a watery 
smile, to the older woman. 
</p><p>"Beggars can't be choosers," she said bravely.  "I'm ready to 
take anything." 
</p><p>"Have you had any training?" asked Mrs. Andrews. 
"Stenography, typewriting, or any of those things?  So many of 
the girls have been taking them up lately as a sort of fad." 
</p><p>Betty shook her head dispiritedly. 
</p><p>"Father wouldn't let me take up anything like that.  He said 
that I would never have to use it, and that it was a waste of 
time and energy.  The only thing he let me do was a course in Red 
Cross first aid and home nursing, which was a thing he said every 
woman should know; but, of course, that's just the thing that 
won't be of any use to me now, with so many trained nurses 
about!" 
</p><p>A look of deep dejection settled over her, and for a moment 
they sat silent, listening to the ceaseless pulse of the engines 
as the boat forged its way into the dark. 
</p><p>Mrs. Andrews rose and, placing her hands on Elizabeth's 
shoulders as she stood beside her, said gently: 
</p><p>"I'm very glad I ran across you.  I want you to go to bed 
now, and to sleep, mind you   &mdash;   no lying awake thinking and 
worrying!  To-morrow things will look brighter   &mdash;   they always do. 
Promise me!" 
</p><p>Elizabeth's face darkened as if a dense cloud, the forerunner 
of a storm, had passed over it. 
</p><p>"Ah," she said passionately, "you tell me not to worry, but 
how can I help it when people are saying such dreadful things 
about my father?" 
</p><p>"Are they?" asked Mrs. Andrews thoughtfully.  "I haven't 
heard anything, but then I don't often hear slander.  People know 
it isn't exactly in my line."  The even tones were a trifle 
contemptuous.  "Or perhaps," she added whimsically, "they knew it 
wouldn't be any use.  You see, child, I happened to know your 
father!" 
</p><p>She stooped and kissed the girl impulsively.  Betty clung to 
her a moment, unable to speak; then her arms dropped, and she 
smiled bravely into the other's face. 
</p><p>"Good night," she whispered tremulously, "and thank you again 
and again!" 
</p><p>"Now remember, no worrying!" 
</p><p>Mrs. Andrews shook her finger playfully as she disappeared 
through the door.  And, strange to relate, Betty, worn out and 
exhausted, followed her advice and slept peacefully throughout 
the night, a pitiful little smile hovering over her lips. 
</p> 
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="8" id="d12"> 
<head>VIII</head> 
 
<p>It was fully a month after Elizabeth's return to New York 
when Fairfax Cary ran across Major Barry in the Pennsylvania 
Station as they were hurrying to their respective trains.  At the 
risk of missing his connection, the major laid an arresting hand 
on Cary's arm. 
</p><p>"Have you seen Betty Crosby lately?" <pb n="539"/> he asked hurriedly. 
Then, as Fairfax shook his head, he added:  "She's disappeared   &mdash;    
can't be found anywhere.  Her uncle's nearly distracted.  When 
can I see you?" 
</p><p>"To-morrow at eleven, at my office," responded Fairfax, and 
they parted precipitately. 
</p><p>It was only when Fairfax was speeding through the cool tunnel 
under the river that he began to grasp the full import of the 
major's words.  Betty Crosby gone!  Without a trace!  It was 
inconceivable!  Things like that didn't happen in the set in 
which she moved.  After her promise to him, too!  No, he 
absolutely refused to believe it. 
</p><p>But the more he dwelt on the major's news, the deeper grew 
his concern.  That she should leave the uncongenial atmosphere of 
the Crosby home did not surprise him, but that she should go 
without telling any one of her destination gave him, in spite of 
his determination not to credit the report, a feeling of extreme 
disquietude. 
</p><p>"There must have been an upheaval of some sort," he thought 
grimly.  "Mrs. Crosby's a pretty difficult proposition at best, 
and she probably played on the child's nerves like a rasp.  Can't 
say I blame her for cutting it all; but why in thunder didn't she 
let the rest of us know?" 
</p><p>It was this same question that he put to Trixie Hunnewell 
when they met on the club veranda as soon as he had succeeded in 
drawing her away from the group of people with whom he found her; 
for, as he speedily learned, she was in as deep ignorance as 
Major Barry and himself as to Elizabeth's whereabouts. 
</p><p>"She promised me before she left town that she would call on 
me if she was ever in trouble," he said, adding ruefully, half to 
himself:  "As I knew mighty well she would be before long!  And 
Betty Crosby's not one to break a promise." 
</p><p>Trixie eyed the tense, troubled face thoughtfully, and a 
feeling came over her that perhaps, in some way, she had been the 
cause of that broken promise.  She realized that her letters to 
Betty had been full of Fairfax Cary.  It was highly probable that 
Betty had imagined, as she herself had believed, that Cary's 
attentions were of a different significance from what it now 
appeared was their real character.  For Trixie had come to see 
that her attraction for him lay in the fact that she was 
Elizabeth's friend and in constant communication with her. 
</p><p>"If it were really that way with them," she thought 
self-reproachfully, "I'm afraid Betsy felt that I wasn't very 
true to her; but why didn't they tell me?  I certainly had no way 
of guessing!" 
</p><p>But her contrition only added to her concern, and made her 
even more desirous of aiding in the search. 
</p><p>"I shall depend on you to let me know how I can help," she 
told Fairfax when he left her.  "I shall be on tenter-hooks until 
I hear what Major Barry has to tell you to-morrow." 
</p><p>That the intervening hours had been trying for Fairfax, too, 
was evident from the alacrity with which he rose to greet the 
major on his entrance into Cary's private office as the clock 
struck eleven the following morning. 
</p><p>"Sit here, major," he said, indicating a chair on the other 
side of his flat desk. 
</p><p>Major Barry laid his hat and cane carefully on the desk and 
sat down.  His usual cheery expression had given place to one of 
deep seriousness, and he nervously fingered his eye-glasses on 
their broad black ribbon. 
</p><p>"The first intimation I had of this," he began without 
preliminary, "was two days ago, when I met George Crosby at 
Delmonico's.  He looks like an old man.  Have you seen him?" 
Fairfax shook his head, and the major went on:  "You know how the 
Crosbys have always held themselves   &mdash;   as if there wasn't any one 
quite good enough   &mdash;   you know   &mdash;   just manner, of course, but   &mdash;   well, 
it's all gone as far as George is concerned.  He has positively 
crumpled up!  I thought he'd been ill, and stopped to hear about 
it, but he insisted he was all right.  It was only when I 
inquired for Elizabeth   &mdash;   you know I'm her godfather, always was 
very intimate with Randolph and his wife   &mdash;   you knew, of course?" 
</p><p>He fixed his kind, candid eyes on Cary's face.  Fairfax 
nodded understandingly.  He had heard of the major's romance   &mdash;   how 
the two men had loved and courted the beautiful Helen Rogers, and 
how, when Crosby had succeeded in winning her, the major   &mdash;   or 
captain, as he then was   &mdash;   had laid his hand on Randolph's shoulder 
and said: 
</p><p>"You win, old man!  Just as well, I guess; an army post's no 
place for a girl <pb n="540"/> like that!  But if you don't make her 
happy, by gad, sir, you'll have to answer for it to me!" 
</p><p>And when at the end of a year she had died, leaving the 
little flaxen-haired miniature of herself to take her place, the 
two men had accepted the trust that was confided to them and 
lavished the deepest tenderness and care on the little maid. 
</p><p>"She isn't quite sure which is her real father," chuckled 
Randolph when, on her third birthday, Barry had "dropped in as he 
happened to be passing," as he put it, and Betty held out her 
arms to him with a gurgle of delight.  He "happened to be 
passing" so often those days that it had come to be a joke 
between the two men. 
</p><p>"All right, old man, I understand   &mdash;   you just keep on," 
Randolph had said with a slap on the back as he handed the major 
his glass of whisky-and-seltzer.  "Between the two of us she may 
get one fairly decent father!" 
</p><p>And Tod Barry had laughed, and said that he was willing and 
anxious to contribute his share.  So it was evident from the 
major's manner, as he sat in Cary's big chair and twirled his 
eye-glasses, that Betty's lack of confidence had hurt him to the 
quick. 
</p><p>"It is strange she didn't communicate with you," mused 
Fairfax. 
</p><p>"I can't understand it   &mdash;   it makes me afraid the child has come 
to some harm." 
</p><p>Barry moved uneasily, and began beating a tattoo on the edge 
of the desk with his carefully kept nails. 
</p><p>"Did you find out the reason for her leaving?" asked Fairfax 
anxiously. 
</p><p>"Some family trouble, as far as I can make out from what 
George said.  I couldn't really get at the facts, but George 
hinted something about Norman's wanting to marry her.  Evidently 
Betty wouldn't have it   &mdash;   you know what a miserable, dissipated 
little cur he is, and I suppose Mrs. George cut up rusty and made 
it unpleasant for her; so she just left one night, taking a 
suit-case full of clothes, and they haven't heard of her since." 
</p><p>"Well, at all events, there's satisfaction in the knowledge 
that she has plenty of money," commented Cary. 
</p><p>That's just the rub!  Has she? put in the major impatiently. 
"George as good as told me that Randolph's affairs were pretty 
well involved when he died.  He intimated that Elizabeth had gone 
off with the idea of supporting herself.  Imagine   &mdash;   Betty! " 
</p><p>"But I don't understand!" Fairfax exclaimed.  "Randolph 
Crosby's fortune gone?  Why, it's impossible!  I know too well   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>The major looked at him attentively. 
</p><p>"Did you know anything about his investments?" 
</p><p>"Well, not such a great deal.  Mr. Crosby was too reticent a 
man, too self-reliant, to confide anything more than was 
absolutely necessary, even to his lawyer, and of course I did 
only a small part of his legal work.  But, from what I saw of his 
holdings and from my knowledge of the man, I should say that what 
you suggest is a rank impossibility." 
</p><p>The two men eyed each other thoughtfully. 
</p><p>"Is George Crosby sole trustee?" 
</p><p>In his effort to make it unconcerned, the major's voice 
sounded strained and unnatural. 
</p><p>"Sole trustee and guardian, so Miss Crosby told me." 
</p><p>"Humph!"  The major was carefully examining the spring of his 
eye-glasses.  "Cary," he said at last, looking directly into the 
dark, keen face across the desk, "I think it's time Elizabeth 
Crosby's friends took a hand.  As her godfather, I feel a certain 
responsibility in regard to her, and I ask you to assist me in 
whatever search it is necessary to make to determine the child's 
whereabouts and the condition of her affairs." 
</p><p>"I will gladly do anything in my power, Major Barry.  As you 
know, or perhaps you don't know, everything that concerns Miss 
Crosby concerns me very deeply." 
</p><p>Major Barry looked at him sharply. 
</p><p>"Why the dickens, man, didn't you tell her so?" he exclaimed. 
Then all this would have been avoided! 
</p><p>But Fairfax shook his head positively. 
</p><p>"She knew, or at all events she must have guessed; but I 
couldn't ask her to marry me when I had practically nothing to 
offer her." 
</p><p>"Good Lord, Cary, you had a fine young man and a fine old 
name to offer her!  What more could any girl want?" 
</p><p>"Thank you, major.  It's very kind of <pb n="541"/> you; but even if 
it were true, that's not enough for a girl like Elizabeth 
Crosby!" 
</p><p>"It's enough for any girl, especially for one of Betty's 
stamp.  Why, every bit of this would have been avoided!" 
</p><p>"You speak as if you think she would have taken me!" 
</p><p>There was a badly concealed tremor in Cary's voice, and the 
hand that held the pencil with which he was scrawling illegible 
words on the pad before him shook visibly. 
</p><p>"Take you!  Why, man, are you blind?  Self-depreciation is 
one thing, but imbecility   &mdash;   there, there   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>He stopped and looked quickly at Cary, evidently afraid that 
he had gone too far; but the radiant expression on Cary's face 
told him that he could have continued indefinitely in the same 
strain. 
</p><p>"Cary," he asked abruptly, "have you heard anything 
derogatory to Randolph Crosby since he died?" 
</p><p>Fairfax Cary paused for a moment before answering, his eyes 
wandering to the tall buildings pressing closely in on his only 
window, a look of seriousness driving away the happy light in the 
dark eyes.  He turned back to the major and nodded regretfully. 
</p><p>"I was with them when they left the race-track that 
afternoon, and I saw several of Mr. Crosby's friends refuse to 
speak to him.  Afterward I tried to find out the reason for it. 
As far as I could learn, it was pretty generally conceded that 
his horse, Steadfast, had been doctored   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>The major inclined his head. 
</p><p>"And of course the blame was laid on him, in spite of the 
fact that he lost the purse 
</p><p>"They claimed that he had more than offset that." 
</p><p>Again Major Barry nodded. 
</p><p>"Well, of course I don't believe a word of it   &mdash;   don't see how 
any one could who knew the man; but the question is, how can we 
prove it's false?  I'm not satisfied to let the good name of my 
best friend and the father of that child go down to posterity 
blackened.  We've got to clear it, and we've got to find 
Elizabeth!  Now, what do you suggest?" 
</p><p>"Have any steps been taken?" 
</p><p>"George Crosby has employed a private detective, but they're 
so afraid of people's talking, and of a scandal, that they're 
tremendously handicapped.  You see how it was with me   &mdash;   I only 
learned by chance." 
</p><p>"I think I'll go and have a talk with Pat," ruminated 
Fairfax.  "The boy may be able to tell us something.  You know, 
one of the last things Mr. Crosby did before he died was to send 
the boy enough money to make up what he lost on the race.  Pat 
told me about it just after the funeral.  He was all broken up. 
It seems he has a sister who is a bit of a high-flier, from all I 
hear, and he's very anxious to establish her somewhere away from 
the track influences.  He had saved enough money to give her a 
start, but he lost most of it when Steadfast was beaten, so you 
can imagine his gratitude at Mr. Crosby's generosity." 
</p><p>"Just like Rand!"  The major's face twitched.  "Well, let me 
know what you learn." 
</p><p>He rose and took up his hat and stick. 
</p><p>"I will, Major Barry.  Could you meet me at the Sussex Club 
to-night at, say, eleven o'clock?  I can't tell just when I can 
see Pat." 
</p><p>The major assented, and the hands of the two men met in a 
firm clasp. 
</p> 
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="9" id="d13"> 
<head>IX</head> 
 
<p>As soon as he was alone, Fairfax despatched a letter to the 
jockey's headquarters at Sheepshead Bay, and spent the rest of 
the day in impatient perturbation awaiting his reply; but when 
the answer came, it was a hurried scrawl from his sister.</p> 

<p> 
DEAR MR. CARY:<lb/> 
</p><p>Pat's been hurt awful bad in the steeplechase this afternoon. 
Come as quickly as you can. 
                        MOLLY DELANEY.<lb/></p> 

<p>Fairfax grasped his hat and rushed to the elevator.  When he 
reached the street he jumped into a taxi and told the chauffeur 
he would double the fare if he reached the Pennsylvania Station 
in time for the six seventeen train.  Fairfax got his train and 
the man his fare, and the young lawyer settled himself with as 
much patience as he could command to pass the interval which must 
elapse before he could reach Pat. 
</p><p>Molly had evidently left word at the office of his coming, 
for when Cary reached the cheap hotel where the Delaneys had 
their rooms a small boy took him in charge.  The guide conducted 
him at once up the <pb n="542"/> steep stairs and down the narrow hall 
lighted by a flaring gas-jet which disclosed the gilt and green 
wall-paper disfigured by great spots of mold.  The boy indicated 
a door on the right. 
</p><p>"He's in there!" he said in a hoarse, terror-stricken whisper 
and fled precipitately. 
</p><p>Cary knocked softly, and the door was immediately opened by a 
thin youth with furtive eyes. 
</p><p>"It's him!" said this individual in a sepulchral voice and 
disappeared into the corridor. 
</p><p>Cary stepped into the dim room and closed the door.  On the 
iron bedstead he could just distinguish the indistinct outline of 
the jockey's figure.  Out of the bandages that swathed his head 
burned two bright eyes, feverishly restless.  He pressed the 
boy's hand as it lay motionless on the counterpane. 
</p><p>"I'm very sorry for this, Pat!" he said gently. 
</p><p>A little smile stole over the blanched, freckled face. 
</p><p>"The jig's up, I guess, Mr. Cary.  That steeplechasin's 
pretty sure ter git us sooner or later.  Mr. Crosby wouldn't 
never let me do it, but   &mdash;     Well, I'm mighty glad ye got here in 
time.  I've been wantin' ter see ye." 
</p><p>A spasm of pain passed over his face. 
</p><p>"Are they doing everything they can for you?" asked Cary, 
bending solicitously over him. 
</p><p>"Oh, yep!  Sit down, Mr. Cary.  I told Jim ter put a chair 
fer ye; ain't he done it?"  Then, as Cary sat down, Pat went on 
faintly:  "They had a couple of doctors here, an' they patched me 
up some, but there ain't nothin' ter be done, I guess.  Kind o' 
tough, ain't it?  I'd 'most got me pile tergether fer that little 
home fer Molly.  I don't like the way things is goin'!" 
</p><p>For a moment he searched the sympathetic face before him, and 
then, as if satisfied with what he saw, he continued 
confidentially: 
</p><p>"Mr. Norman's begun hangin' round again.  He's in there with 
her now."  With a quick glance of his eyes he indicated the door 
opposite the bed, whence issued the low rumble of a man's voice 
punctuated by the shrill tones of a woman. I  don't like it!" he 
concluded hoarsely.  When gents like him comes followin' up girls 
like Molly, ye kin jest betcher sweet life it ain't fer no good!" 
</p><p>"Has it been going on for long?" asked Cary. 
</p><p>"Off an' on.  He went ter Newport fer a while, an' I wuz 
hopin' it wuz all off, but fer the  past few weeks he ain't 
hardly lef' her fer a minute.  Now ye kin see why I wuz so set on 
gettin' a quiet little place off somewhere.  Race-tracks ain't no 
place fer a girl.  If I could only ha' got that fixed, an' ha' 
felt Steadfast under me once agin, it wouldn't ha' been so hard 
ter go.  Gee, Mr. Cary!"  A film came over the bright eyes.  "Ye 
don't know how I felt ter see that lout Burns ridin' that hoss! 
Why, he's got hands like a plowman!" 
</p><p>"I'm sure it must have been hard," Cary said softly.  "I want 
to ask you about Steadfast and that race for the Withers Stake, 
Pat.  Have you ever suspected that there was anything wrong with 
the horse that day?" 
</p><p>"Yer mean he'd been doped?  I didn't think so then, Mr. Cary; 
but lately, from things Molly's let drop, I've kind o' 
suspicioned   &mdash;   well, I dunno.  Ye see, when a girl gits jealous, 
she says all kinds o' things.  When Mr. Norman went off ter 
Newport, Molly got it inter her nut that he wuz rushin' some 
queen there, an' one night she had sort o' high-strikes, an' she 
said if he wuzn't goin' ter make good she'd peach.  Then she said 
somethin' about what happened before the Withers race; but all of 
a sudden she stopped, an' I couldn't git nuttin' more out o' 
her." 
</p><p>The weak voice trailed off and stopped, and the eyes closed. 
</p><p>A feeling of compunction came over Cary.  He could see that 
the boy's strength was ebbing very fast, but he felt that he must 
do all that he could to get some clue to the mystery of 
Elizabeth's hiding-place. 
</p><p>"Pat," he said, bending over the limp form, "do you know 
where Miss Crosby is now?" 
</p><p>"Miss Crosby?  Miss Betty?"  The blue eyes opened suddenly 
and stared into his. 
</p><p>"Why, ain't she at Newport?" 
</p><p>Cary shook his head. 
</p><p>"She left about a month ago." 
</p><p>"That's queer!  Don't he know?" 
</p><p>Pat glanced meaningly at the door between the two rooms. 
Again Cary shook his head.  Pat stared thoughtfully at him. 
<pb n="543"/>  
</p><p>"Well," he said at last, "it ain't fer the likes o' me ter be 
sizin' up gents like Mr. George Crosby an' Mr. Norman; but in me 
own mind I allays puts 'em in a pretty low class, an' I knows Mr. 
Tutney thinks the same.  I ain't a bit surprised she couldn't 
stan' 'em! " 
</p><p>"Tutney?" repeated Cary.  Barney Tutney?" 
</p><p>"Yep; owns them big diamond-mines in South Africky   &mdash;   least, 
him an' Mr. Crosby does together." 
</p><p>"Where can I find him?" 
</p><p>"Dunno jes' where; he's down there now, wherever they are." 
</p><p>"I wonder how I can get hold of him!" mused Cary. 
</p><p>The boy's head moved restlessly on the pillow.  The short 
twilight had darkened into night, and the little room was 
shrouded in shadows.  Outside, an indistinct murmur of voices 
floated up from the group of youths that Cary had noticed 
standing on the bedraggled plot of grass before the hotel steps, 
but the words were indistinguishable. 
</p><p>"Mr. Cary!" came in a frightened whisper.  "Mr. Cary!  Are ye 
there?" 
</p><p>"Yes, Pat; what is it?" 
</p><p>Cary's hand closed over the cold fingers. 
</p><p>"I thought ye'd gone!"  There was a world of relief in the 
weak voice.  "It's all right   &mdash;   only I wuz kin' o' lonesome.  I 
s'pose I wuz light-headed fer a minute, an' I thought I wuz 
alone.  It's kind o' hard ter die when ye ain't never really 
lived!" 
</p><p>Cary bent over the slight figure, motionless in the glow of 
the electric light which flickered up from the street below. 
</p><p>"Is there anything you'd like me to do for you, Pat?" he 
asked gently. 
</p><p>"If ye could   &mdash;   I don' hardly like ter ask it o' ye, but ye're 
so kind   &mdash;   if ye <hi rend="italic">could"</hi>   &mdash;   there was infinite entreaty in the ashen 
face   &mdash;   "look after Molly a bit?  Ye see, there won't be any one 
after   &mdash;   after   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>With a lump in his throat, Fairfax promised to do everything 
in his power for the girl. 
</p><p>"I've got to go now, Pat," he added regretfully.  "I told 
Major Barry I would meet him at eleven o'clock in town.  He's 
trying to find Miss Betty, too, but I'll be down again the first 
thing in the morning." 
</p><p>The boy's fingers tightened for a moment around the sinewy 
hand; then he released it. 
</p><p>Good-by!" he whispered huskily. "Ye're on the level   &mdash;   I kin 
trust ye.  I've tried ter be straight, too," he added wistfully. 
</p><p>"You've tried, and you've succeeded, Pat!"  Cary stooped over 
him, his voice deep with feeling.  "That's what Mr. Crosby used 
to say   &mdash;   `That boy's as straight as a string; I'd trust him 
anywhere!'" 
</p><p>"Did he say that?" came in a hoarse, eager whisper. 
</p><p>"Often." 
</p><p>"He ain't never said it ter me   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"He will soon, Pat.  I know he's waiting now to tell you." 
</p><p>A slow smile flitted over the boy's face. 
</p><p>"It's kind o' comfortin', ain't it," he faltered, "ter think 
there's some one ye know out there?"  He raised his eyes to the 
window, open at the top to admit as much as possible of the night 
air.  The new moon shone through the blackness, and Pat fixed his 
eyes on it.  "Do ye really think he is?" 
</p><p>"I'm sure of it," answered Cary confidently.  "Now shall I 
call Molly?" 
</p><p>"All right, an' thank ye fer comin'!" 
</p><p>Cary knocked at the door between the two rooms, told Molly 
Delaney that he had to leave, and with a last clasp of Pat's limp 
hand let himself out into the hall.  He glanced at his watch as 
he passed the gas-jet, and, startled at the lateness of the hour, 
hurried down the stairs and through the group of loungers still 
loitering in the front yard.  Jumping into a hack that stood at 
the curb, he directed the driver to make all possible speed to 
the station. 
</p><p>"Wonder if Pat's dead?" remarked one of the group in a hushed 
voice.  "That cove's just lef' him.  Mike said his name is Cary, 
an' he took him up ter see Pat." 
</p><p>"He looked kind o' cut up," answered another of the crowd. 
"I guess he's pretty close ter gone, poor old Pat!" 
</p><p>Cary, in the mean time, was hurrying to the train, which was 
just pulling out as they reached the station.  He darted across 
the platform and swung upon the last car.  He was still panting a 
little when he walked down the aisle and came face to face with 
George Crosby, who had entered the car from the other end. 
</p><p>"Oh   &mdash;   ah   &mdash;   Cary   &mdash;   how-do?" he hesitated and held out his hand. 
"Was it you I saw making that flying leap for the train?" 
</p><p>Crosby was evidently trying to speak with his old-time 
lightness. 
<pb n="544"/>  
</p><p>"Close shave!" replied Cary laconically. 
</p><p>"Come and speak to Mrs. Crosby," continued the other, and 
Fairfax followed him somewhat reluctantly to where Maude Crosby 
sat. 
</p><p>"I thought it was you," she exclaimed as she put out her 
hand; " but I've never seen you in such mad haste before, and I 
couldn't quite reconcile it   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"With my usual Southern laziness?" supplemented Cary, with a 
little laugh. 
</p><p>As usual when he was with Mrs. Crosby, he was possessed by an 
intense desire to irritate her by voicing her insinuations, and 
then watching her discomfiture; but in his present frame of mind 
the mood did not last long. 
</p><p>"I've just come from Pat Delaney," he said quietly to Mr. 
Crosby.  "He's been dreadfully smashed up in a steeplechase, and 
I'm afraid he's done for, poor little chap!" 
</p><p>He looked past Mrs. Crosby to the dim outlines of the plain, 
stretching unbroken and dark to meet the star-flecked sky. 
</p><p>"Too bad!" ejaculated Crosby.  "He was a nice boy." 
</p><p>"Who's that   &mdash;   Randolph's jockey?" asked Mrs. Crosby of her 
husband. 
</p><p>He nodded and sank down beside her. 
</p><p>"How's Miss Crosby?" asked Fairfax in as careless a voice as 
he could command. 
</p><p>"Quite well, thank you," answered Mrs. Crosby quickly.  She 
looked straight into the keen, dark eyes, and added with the 
least possible quiver of her eyelashes:  "It has been a great 
pleasure to have her with us this summer." 
</p><p>"I'm sure of it," agreed Fairfax.  "Will she be with you this 
winter?" 
</p><p>He experienced a curious sensation, almost of admiration, as 
he watched the skill with which she met his thrusts.  Crosby, on 
the contrary, had sunk farther into his seat, and the unnatural 
pallor of his skin had become more accentuated. 
</p><p>"Yes, indeed!" replied Mrs. Crosby.  "We're devoted to the 
child, and can't possibly get along without her!" 
</p><p>"Please remember me to her," said Cary gravely. 
</p><p>With a word of farewell he walked through the car into the 
one ahead, in search of a vacant seat.  He settled himself in it 
with the thought: 
</p><p>"The major's right   &mdash;   George Crosby looks twenty years older 
than he did in June.  Too bad!  Well, it happens that way 
sometimes.  Mrs. Crosby, too, doesn't look quite as youthful as 
she did.  I wonder if they're really so worried over Betty's 
disappearance!  I wouldn't have given them credit for so much 
heart.  They weren't going to let me in on the secret.  They 
evidently thought I didn't know!" 
</p><p>The muscles of the firm chin tightened, and unconsciously he 
straightened his shoulders. 
</p><p>"Well, they're right   &mdash;   I don't know much; but I'm going to 
know more before long!  I'll find Betty Crosby, if I have to 
search every inch of the way between here and San Francisco; and 
when I do, there won't be any more shilly-shallying!  There isn't 
any reason for it, now that the money's gone.  I'm almost glad of 
it!"  A half smile curved the proud lips.  "And if what the major 
says is true, then   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>It still lacked a few minutes to eleven when Cary entered the 
door of the Sussex Club, but, knowing the major's unusual 
punctuality, he went at once to the room where they had arranged 
to meet. 
</p> 
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="10" id="d14"> 
<head>X</head> 
 
<p>When Fairfax Cary entered the lounge of the Sussex Club he 
found young Tony Page, who had just returned from France after 
three months' service as a stretcher-bearer in connection with 
the American Ambulance, holding forth to a good-sized audience. 
</p><p>"But the peach experience of them all," Fairfax heard him 
remark as he passed on his way to the corner where he was to meet 
Major Barry, "was the time I got wounded."  He glanced at his 
arm, which he carried in a sling.  "It was before Verdun, and 
every one had been working his heart out day and night trying to 
get the wounded back.  It was some job, for there were so many 
that every hospital was overflowing, and we stretcher-bearers 
thought we were lucky if we got three hours' sleep out of the 
twenty-four.  Every once in a while one of us would be knocked 
out, and then there would be the dickens, and all to find a man 
to take his place.  Well, that night it seemed as if all Hades 
was let loose.  Generally they talk about a curtain of fire 
behind the force attacked, but this time it seemed as if we were 
in the center of it.  The shrapnel had been falling round us like 
hail, and finally a <pb n="545"/> splinter struck Tom Strawbridge   &mdash;   you 
know Tom   &mdash;   Philadelphia man   &mdash;   polo-player?" 
</p><p>He paused and looked interrogatively at Lindlay Strong, who 
nodded. 
</p><p>"We had a man on the stretcher," Tony went on, "and of course 
we had to take him in; but when we reached the hospital we made 
up our minds we'd get Tom or die in the attempt.  We knew it 
would be frightfully difficult, if not impossible, but we weren't 
going to let that stop us if we could get the extra man. 
Apparently there wasn't one to be found for love or money.  Small 
wonder, too, for it looked like almost certain death to go back 
into that inferno.  Then some one tapped me on the arm.  I turned 
and saw a boy   &mdash;   little chap he was; young, too, from his voice. 
It was dark; I couldn't really get a good look at him, but he 
asked me if he might go with us.  Of course I snapped him up, and 
we jumped on the ambulance and drove like mad to the place where 
we'd left Tom.  That sure was some ride!  The road was all torn 
to bits by heavy traffic and by the shells, and every once in a 
while we would jounce into a pit that seemed as if we would never 
get out of it.  All the time those great, screeching Jack 
Johnsons were crashing around us, exploding with a fury that 
seemed to tear the very insides out of the earth.  It was awful!" 
</p><p>Tony Page stopped and shuddered, and then, as if to emphasize 
the reality of his present surroundings, shook the ice against 
the side of the glass he held in his hand. 
</p><p>"Did you get Tom?" asked Strong anxiously. 
</p><p>"Yes, finally.  He was about all in, but we put him on the 
stretcher and started back to the ambulance.  Those beastly 
shells never let up for a minute, and at last one exploded about 
fifty yards from us, and a great piece of it caught me in the 
arm.  I felt a gush of blood, and knew that a  big vein had been 
cut.  Fortunately we were close to the ambulance,  so we shoved 
Tom in, and then the little chap we'd picked up started to put a 
tourniquet on my arm.  His hands looked awfully small for a 
boy's, and he had the most wonderful touch!  I tried to see his 
face, but his cap was pulled down over his eyes, and I was sort 
of dazed from the shock, so I didn't really care much; but when 
we got back to the hospital, and I was taken into the ward, I 
took a good look at him.  Fellows, who do you suppose it was?" 
</p><p>There was a tense silence, while Tony Page's quick eyes ran 
over the eager faces about him.  Major Barry had come in, and he 
and Fairfax stood a little to one side, listening to the young 
man's story. 
</p><p>"Who?" asked some one. 
</p><p>"Elizabeth Crosby!" 
</p><p>Fairfax Cary caught the back of the armchair behind which he 
stood, as if to steady himself.  Major Barry stepped impulsively 
toward Tony Page. 
</p><p>"Randolph Crosby's daughter?" he ejaculated. 
</p><p>"The same," acquiesced Tony cheerfully.  "She's been working 
in the hospital.  Mrs. Maitland Andrews sent her over and paid 
her expenses; and when Betty heard we were short a man, she took 
the clothes of one of the wounded soldiers and went out with us. 
Pretty sandy, wasn't it?" 
</p><p>"Are you sure?" 
</p><p>Horrified incredulity shone on Major Barry's face, from which 
the ruddy color had fled. 
</p><p>"Am I sure?  Am I sure I'm alive?"  Tony looked significantly 
at his arm.  "Why, of course I'm sure!  That girl saved my life," 
he asserted gratefully.  "I've always known Betty; used to play 
tennis with her a lot at the Country Club and different places. 
I always knew she had grit; but believe me, that night was enough 
to make the nerve of the strongest man crack, much less a 
woman's.  She didn't seem to care, though; she walked through 
that Hades as quietly as if she'd been strolling along Fifth 
Avenue.  I tell you, there was some commotion in that hospital 
when what she'd done got out!" 
</p><p>Fairfax Cary was hanging on every word, his face livid, his 
eyes like coals of fire.  Tony took up a cigarette and held it 
against the match that some one lit for him. 
</p><p>"Paul Townsend's at the head of the hospital.  You remember 
him, don't you?  Big, strapping fellow, looks like Adonis, fair 
hair, very bright blue eyes.  He's a fiend for work, simply eats 
it up, has that hospital humming day and night, and no matter 
what time you bring in a poor wretch he's always on the job. 
Well, he's in love with Betty   &mdash;   absolutely dotty about her.  I 
think it began long before he went to France.  At all events, 
when he found out what she'd done, he went right up in the air   &mdash;    
said he was responsible for the nurses under him, and <pb n="546"/> such a 
thing must never happen, again.  Betty stood there with a quiet 
little smile on her face and asked him what it mattered.  Gee, 
that girl has sand!  You ought to have seen old Paul's face!  He 
was fairly sputtering with rage and excitement!"  Tony chuckled 
delightedly.  "But he made her promise not to do it again.  He 
told her he'd send her home if she did, and that settled it." 
</p><p>Fairfax Cary walked to an armchair in the corner and dropped 
into it.  He covered his eyes with his hand, and Major Barry 
heard him gasp under his breath. 
</p><p>The major laid his hand on Cary's shoulder. 
</p><p>"It's all right, my boy," he said quietly.  She's safe 
enough!" 
</p><p>Cary's hand dropped, and he raised tortured eyes to the 
major. 
</p><p>"But think of her going through that!" 
</p><p>The major's eyebrows were twitching nervously.  He nodded. 
</p><p>"Frightful!  It never should have happened.  I don't know 
what Mrs. Andrews was thinking about.  The front's no place for a 
girl like Betty.  Never stops to think of herself.  She's just as 
apt as not to do it again!" he concluded fearfully, forgetting 
his consoling counsel of a moment before. 
</p><p>Fairfax agreed disconsolately, and they stared anxiously into 
each other's face. 
</p><p>"Tell you what, old man!"  The major emphasized his words by 
bringing down his clenched fist into his open palm.  "One or the 
other of us   &mdash;   or both of us, if necessary   &mdash;   must go over and bring 
that child back!" 
</p><p>Cary nodded gloomily, but his eyes brightened at the 
suggestion. 
</p><p>"Now which shall it be?" the major went on thoughtfully. 
"I'd give half my life to go, but"   &mdash;   a quizzical, rather wistful 
light gleamed in his kind eyes   &mdash;   "I think, Fairfax, perhaps you'd 
have more influence." 
</p><p>It was the first time the major had called him by his 
Christian name, and it seemed to Cary as if in some way it 
brought him nearer to Elizabeth, and gave him a part ownership in 
her.  He impulsively put out his hand and grasped the major's. 
</p><p>"Thank you, major!" be exclaimed a little huskily. 
</p><p>The light in Major Barry's eyes increased until it illumined 
his whole face. 
</p><p>"And, Fairfax," he went on whimsically, "if Betty wants to 
stop in Paris and get her trousseau, tell her it will be my 
wedding-present."  He hesitated before he added softly:  "They 
tell me the Bermudas make an ideal wedding-trip at this time of 
the year!" 
</p><p>The color mounted into Cary's face. 
</p><p>"I'm afraid it isn't going to be as easy as all that," he 
answered with a rueful shake of his head. 
</p><p>"You can't tell, my boy; you can't tell!"  Then the major 
asked abruptly:  "How about this fellow Townsend?" 
</p><p>The flush died out of Cary's face, and was replaced by an 
anxious frown. 
</p><p>"He was at the head of the Rockefeller Institute for a while. 
He's always been a great admirer of Betty." 
</p><p>"Well, the sooner you get off the better."  Major Barry 
reached for the evening paper, which lay on a table near them, 
and, adjusting his eye-glasses carefully, turned to the shipping 
news.  "The Touraine sails tomorrow morning at six thirty.  Can 
you make it?" 
</p><p>"I can!" declared Fairfax so emphatically that the major 
chuckled. 
</p><p>"I'll give you some letters.  It would be useless going 
without the proper credentials.  By the way, did you see Pat?" 
</p><p>"Yes; I've just come back from Sheepshead Bay.  The poor 
little chap met with a bad accident this afternoon, and I'm 
afraid he's done for," Fairfax said sadly. 
</p><p>"Too bad!  I'm sorry to hear that!"  The major's face 
expressed real concern.  "What happened?" 
</p><p>"He got smashed up in a steeplechase.  He was nearly gone 
when I left." 
</p><p>"Too bad!  He was a nice little lad.  Good sort   &mdash;   absolutely 
straight.  No chance for him?" 
</p><p>He looked interrogatively at Fairfax, who shook his head. 
</p><p>"I'm afraid not." 
</p><p>"Shame!  Randolph never would let him ride in those 
steeplechases   &mdash;   said he was too light, and also too good a boy." 
The major paused for a moment before asking:  "Did he say 
anything about the race?" 
</p><p>"Nothing definite; but be seemed to suspect that something 
was wrong with Steadfast, and he intimated that Molly   &mdash;   his 
sister, you know   &mdash;   had information that would throw light on it." 
</p><p>The major raised his eyebrows and pursed his lips under the 
gray mustache. 
<pb n="547"/>  
</p><p>"So?" he asked thoughtfully. 
</p><p>Fairfax went on. 
</p><p>"Norman Crosby seems to be running her pretty hard.  Pat's 
been a good deal worried over it." 
</p><p>"I don't wonder!" commented the major grimly. 
</p><p>"He also told me that Mr. Crosby was interested in some 
diamond-mines in South Africa with a man by the name of Tutney   &mdash;    
do you know him?" 
</p><p>"Tutney?  Oh, yes, I know Tutney.  Randolph was in a lot of 
schemes with him.  He's a keener, all right, but I guess he's 
honest without any question; and he thought a lot of Randolph   &mdash;    
that I'm sure of.  Did Pat say where he was to be found?" 
</p><p>Fairfax shook his head. 
</p><p>"South Africa, somewhere   &mdash;   that was all the information he 
could give me." 
</p><p>"Rather a large order, eh?  Well, all right, old man; I'll 
hunt up the address and cable it to you.  Perhaps that would be 
as good a wedding-trip as the other," he added chaffingly. 
</p><p>Fairfax smiled uncertainly. 
</p><p>"I hope you're a good prophet," he replied, rising and 
pushing back his chair.  "Will you write those letters here or at 
my diggings?" 
</p><p>"I'll come with you, I guess." 
</p><p>The two men walked out of, the room, stopping on the way to 
get the number of Betty's hospital from Tony. 
</p> 
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="11" id="d15"> 
<head>XI</head> 
 
<p>The sun was just rising behind the tall buildings in Brooklyn 
the next morning when Fairfax jumped from a taxi at the wharf of 
the French line.  Picking his way through the bustling throng of 
porters, he boarded the vessel, went at once to his stateroom, 
undressed, and went to bed.  They were well past Fire Island when 
he awoke, to hear the rhythmic throb of the engines as the boat 
plowed her way through the deep waters. 
</p><p>With a feeling that for the present he had done as much as 
lay in his power, he turned over and went to sleep again.  He 
dreamed that the boat had been sunk by a torpedo, and that Betty, 
dressed in a torn, bloodstained khaki uniform, was standing on a 
miraculously floating stretcher, holding out her hands in an 
effort to save him as he struggled in the water. 
</p><p>In a base hospital somewhere in France, Betty, oblivious to 
the commotion her disappearance had caused, toiled night and day, 
stilling the pain of her heart by the ministrations of her hands. 
It was trying, nerve-racking work, which made demands on heart 
and sympathies as well as on muscles, and which sent her to bed 
so nervously and physically exhausted that she perforce must 
sleep.  But at times, when she was on night duty, and the 
occupants of her ward were quiet, a feeling of desolation crept 
over her that made her gaze almost enviously at some gaunt form 
in a near-by bed on whose face dwelt that expression of aloofness 
which showed that he was nearing the shadow-land. 
</p><p>It was after one of those night-watches that Dr. Townsend 
stopped her in the corridor as she was on her way to her room. 
</p><p>As Cary had said, she had known the doctor well in New York, 
and the fact that he was in charge of the hospital had been one 
of the reasons for her acceptance of Mrs. Andrews's suggestion. 
It had also influenced Mrs. Andrews in making the offer to Betty; 
for, knowing the man and his admiration for Betty, she realized 
that the girl would be well looked after.  Indeed, she hoped 
that, in time, in the close association of the work, the feeling 
which she knew existed at least on Townsend's side might develop 
into a stronger attachment which would solve the girl's 
difficulties. 
</p><p>That she had been right in her predictions was apparent from 
the look of concern on the doctor's face as he laid a detaining 
hand on Betty's arm. 
</p><p>"Are we working you too hard, Miss Crosby?" he asked 
solicitously. 
</p><p>"No, indeed"; she answered with an attempt at lightness. 
"Work is what I came over for!" 
</p><p>"I know, but we don't want to overdo it.  You look mighty 
thin to me!"  His eye ran over the almost ethereal lightness of 
the girl's figure. 
</p><p>"I wasn't exactly portly when I arrived!" laughed Betty. 
</p><p>"No, I know," he said sympathetically.  His eyes came back to 
hers with a look of more than concern.  "But I can't run any risk 
of your breaking down." 
</p><p>Betty's eyes dropped. 
</p><p>"No fear of that," she answered resolutely. "I wouldn't allow 
myself to give out, <pb n="548"/> after seeing the wonderful way in which 
you work." 
</p><p>"It's been play since you came!" answered Townsend softly. 
"You've filled the whole place with sunshine, and it seems now as 
if I couldn't get tired.  You've been an inspiration as well as a 
help!" 
</p><p>A deep flush spread over Betty's face. 
</p><p>"It's awfully good of you to be so encouraging," she answered 
gratefully; "for, of course, I realize that I must have failed 
horribly in my work." 
</p><p>"Failed nothing!" retorted Townsend emphatically.  "I can 
tell you that your deft ways and the sight of your sweet face 
have helped many a man to endure without a word tortures that 
have wrung his soul!  And I   &mdash;   well, I simply can't get along 
without you! " 
</p><p>The words sounded extravagant, and Betty raised her eyes with 
a little laugh to his; but the expression on his face caused the 
laugh to die on her lips. 
</p><p>"Tell me I won't have to do without you!" he entreated, 
coming a step nearer to her. 
</p><p>But Betty shrank from him and put out her hand, palm outward. 
</p><p>"Oh, please   &mdash;   please!" she pleaded. 
</p><p>"But, my darling"   &mdash;   the strong hand closed over hers   &mdash;   "I love 
you!  Don't you think in time you could   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>Elizabeth quickly drew away her hand. 
</p><p>"Oh, not now, not now!" she breathed tremulously.  "I 
couldn't possibly, yet!" 
</p><p>She sped up the stairs to her room and, flinging herself face 
down on her bed, sobbed convulsively. 
 
</p><p>With the assistance of Major Barry's letters, which seemed to 
have the effect of magic in making difficult paths straight, 
Fairfax, one afternoon about ten days later, found himself 
wending a tortuous way from Paris in the direction of a great 
smoke-cloud which hung pendent from the sky.  In and out of the 
many vehicles that blocked the road, his chauffeur picked a way 
past huge sign-posts, devastated fields marked with mounds 
bearing little wooden crosses and soldiers' caps, streams 
swarming with bathing soldiers, their horses lining the banks and 
drinking their fill. 
</p><p>The air was choking with dust, white and fine, that sifted 
through and into everything, covering all, yet never seeming to 
rest.  Nearer and nearer to the great smoke-cloud they drew, an 
incessant booming as of thunder roaring in their ears.  Under the 
cloud Fairfax could see the flash of mighty guns, whose 
concussion shook the earth with terrific power. 
</p><p>A sharp scream rang in their ears, and a great black object 
hurled itself past them and buried itself violently in a deep, 
self-made grave.  Cary involuntarily ducked and grasped the side 
of the car, while the chauffeur grinned sardonically at him over 
his shoulder. 
</p><p>They entered the remains of a village.  Tom houses, piles of 
brick and mortar, debris of every kind lay scattered about. 
Desolation and ruin even more marked than that of the forlorn 
countryside through which they had passed emphasized the 
destruction the war had brought. 
</p><p>The chauffeur stopped the car before a long, low building 
over which floated the Red Cross flag.  Fairfax jumped out and, 
entering the doorway, arrested a young man who was dashing 
through the hall.  His hands were full of dressings, and he 
hardly paused long enough to hear Cary out. 
</p><p>"Miss Crosby?" he repeated breathlessly. "Can't say, I'm 
sure, whether you can see her or not.  We're rushed to death this 
morning.  Three hundred wounded came in last night, and we've 
none of us had any sleep.  I'll see  if she can be spared for a 
few minutes." 
</p><p>He vanished up the steep stairs, leaving Fairfax waiting 
impatiently in the bare hall, breathing that indescribable 
atmosphere of suffering induced by the pungent smell of 
anesthetics and disinfectants.  Through half-closed doors he saw 
endless rows of closely packed beds, and in each a figure swathed 
in bandages, the same look of patient suffering carved on each 
face.  Outside, the continuous bursting of shells   &mdash;   dangerously 
near, Fairfax thought   &mdash;   caused his nerves to twitch spasmodically. 
</p><p>He heard a light step behind him, and, turning, saw a slender 
figure in the uniform of a Red Cross nurse coming toward him.  At 
first he did not recognize the pale face that looked out from 
under the white head-dress with its little red emblem.  It was 
only when Betty smiled and stretched out her hand that he saw 
that it was she. 
</p><p>"Betty!" he exclaimed, clasping her hand in both of his. 
<pb n="549"/>  
</p><p>"How did you find me?" she asked quietly. 
</p><p>"I learned from Tony Page, at the Sussex Club.  He was 
telling how you saved his life.  I was waiting for the major and 
happened to overhear him   &mdash;   it was by the merest chance.  Betty, 
why did you do it?" 
</p><p>"What?" asked Betty innocently, the shadow of a smile 
flitting over her face. 
</p><p>Cary dropped her hand abruptly. 
</p><p>"Why did you go off like that and not let any of us know?" 
</p><p>"I didn't think any one would care particularly." 
</p><p>Her tone was hard and cold. 
</p><p>"Care?" repeated Fairfax in a puzzled way.  "Care?  Why, what 
do you mean?" 
</p><p>"Come in here." Betty turned to a little room, half office, 
half reception-room, which happened to be empty.  "Just as I say, 
I didn't think any one would care." 
</p><p>Fairfax looked at her gravely.  Great shadows encircled her 
eyes, and her shoulders drooped wearily. 
</p><p>"Not your uncle or aunt, or Major Barry"   &mdash;   he paused   &mdash;   "or I?" 
</p><p>Betty's chin quivered. 
</p><p>"Dear Uncle Tod!" she murmured regretfully.  "Did he worry?" 
</p><p>Fairfax took a restless turn up and down the room. 
</p><p>"Really, Betty," he said severely, "I don't think you've been 
overkind!" 
</p><p>Betty looked out of the window at the ruins on every side. 
Then she turned back to Fairfax. 
</p><p>"If I'd told Uncle Tod, he would have told Uncle George, who 
would have insisted on my coming back to New York, and that I'm 
not going to do!"  Again she looked out of the window, a 
rebellious light in her eyes.  "I suppose he knows all about it 
now?" she asked impatiently. 
</p><p>"I don't know what the major has done since I left," answered 
Cary stiffly.  "I started a few hours after I heard   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"Why did you come?" asked Betty calmly; but behind the quiet 
words and tone lay an inexorable resolve. 
</p><p>The face before her was like stone. 
</p><p>"To take you home!" 
</p><p>"Home?  Home?" answered Betty.  "I have no home!" 
</p><p>The stern face softened, and Cary came toward her 
impetuously. 
</p><p>"Let me make one for you, Betty!" 
</p><p>Instinctively Betty recoiled from him, and a dark flush 
spread over her face.  "You!" she exclaimed in a horrified voice. 
"You!" 
</p><p>For a moment Fairfax studied the condemning face.  That she 
would refuse him, in spite of the major's predictions, he had 
fully expected; but that she should show such repugnance startled 
him.  Outside the thunder rolled ceaselessly, punctuated now and 
again by the screech of a shell as it tore its way through the 
air. 
</p><p>Betty broke the awkward silence by remarking coldly: 
</p><p>"It was very good of you to come so far, and I assure you I'm 
very grateful for your interest, but it's quite useless.  I'm 
happy here, and Dr. Townsend seems to find me useful, which is 
something   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"Betty," broke in Fairfax impulsively, are you going to marry 
Townsend?" 
</p><p>An expression of anger crossed the girl's face. 
</p><p>"What right have you to ask me that?"  She looked at him in 
cold defiance. 
</p><p>"The right my love for you gives me," retorted Fairfax 
steadily. 
</p><p>"Your love!" repeated Betty scornfully. 
</p><p>"Yes," reiterated Fairfax gravely, "my love   &mdash;   the love I've 
had for you ever since we first met, when I had as little hope of 
ever being able to tell you of it as if you were on a different 
planet.  When conditions changed I thought that perhaps, after 
all, I did have something to offer you that you might be willing 
to accept; and I know that your innate generosity will prompt you 
to tell me whether you have already pledged yourself to another 
man." 
</p><p>The straightforward sincerity of his words caught Betty's 
attention.  She looked long and fixedly into his eyes. 
</p><p>"How is it with you and Beatrix Hunnewell?" she asked at 
last. 
</p><p>"Miss Hunnewell?" repeated Fairfax wonderingly.  "Why, we're 
very good friends   &mdash;   that's all." 
</p><p>Betty took a step nearer to him, her eyes still searching his 
face. 
</p><p>"I heard you were engaged," she said in a low voice. 
</p><p>"Engaged!"  A look of incredulity leaped into the dark eyes. 
"Who told you that?" 
</p><p>"My aunt," answered Betty calmly, her eyes never leaving his 
face. 
</p><p>Well, it's a lie!" The strong jaw <pb n="550"/> snapped.  "There has 
never been anything of that kind between us.  I admire Miss 
Hunnewell beyond words, but   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>He shrugged his shoulders impatiently.  Betty drew another 
step nearer. 
</p><p>"But"   &mdash;   there was a note almost of pleading in her voice   &mdash;    
"you've been seeing a great deal of her this summer?" 
</p><p>"Yes," assented Fairfax gravely, "I have. When you're 
separated from the one who is more to you than life itself, it 
sometimes makes existence easier if once in a while you hear 
something about that person, and Miss Hunnewell was in touch with 
you." 
</p><p>"Oh!" said Betty faintly. 
</p><p>Her face had turned very white, and her lips trembled. 
Fairfax was watching her intently, a hurt look in his sensitive 
eyes. 
</p><p>"What a cad you think me!" he exclaimed bitterly, walking to 
the window, where he stood gazing out, his hands thrust deep in 
his pockets. 
</p><p>Betty impulsively took a step after him.  Her breast, under 
the white kerchief, was rising and falling tumultuously. 
</p><p>"Fairfax!" she whispered timidly. 
</p><p>But the man's shoulders squared themselves resolutely, and 
the dark head proudly refused to turn.  Betty walked quietly 
across the room and slipped her hand through his arm. 
</p><p>"Fairfax, forgive me!" she pleaded softly. 
</p><p>He turned quickly and caught her in his arms. 
</p><p>"Darling!" he whispered passionately, pressing her to him. 
"Don't you care for me just a little?  I love you, dear; I love 
you   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>But Betty struggled to free herself. 
</p><p>"Let me go!  Let me go!" she breathed.  "I mustn't   &mdash;   oh, 
please let me go!" 
</p><p>Fairfax released her reluctantly. 
</p><p>"But some day, Betty?" 
</p><p>Betty stepped back. 
</p><p>"Perhaps some day   &mdash;   perhaps when my father's name is cleared," 
she whispered brokenly.  "I shall never marry any one while any 
stain rests on it." 
</p><p>"Why, Betty!" exclaimed Fairfax impatiently.  "No one 
believes   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"They <hi rend="italic">do!"</hi> she interrupted vehemently.  "A great many 
people believe that he was involved in something dishonorable 
before he died!  When it's proved to be false, then I may think 
of marrying.  Until then   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>She shook her head resolutely.  A nurse appeared in the 
doorway. 
</p><p>"Miss Crosby," she said with a glance at Fairfax, "Dr. 
Townsend wants you." 
</p><p>Betty turned to Fairfax and held out her hand. 
</p><p>"Good-by," she said hurriedly.  "Thank you again for coming 
so far, and give my love to Uncle Tod!" 
</p><p>Fairfax grasped her hand. 
</p><p>"You had better write it to him; I sha'n't see him for some 
time." 
</p><p>"Why, aren't you going back?" 
</p><p>She paused on her way to the door and looked back at him over 
her shoulder. 
</p><p>"By way of South Africa.  I'm going there to see Barney 
Tutney.  He may be able to give me some points." 
</p><p>"Barney Tutney?  Yes!" she mused.  "He would know.  You're 
taking a great deal of trouble," she added softly. 
</p><p>Fairfax laughed. 
</p><p>"Trouble!" he repeated happily.  "Nothing is trouble that I 
do for you.  I consider it a privilege to be able to do any 
service for you or for your father.  You remember, I told you 
that once before." 
</p><p>"I remember.  Thank you again!" 
</p><p>Once more Betty held out her hand; then she passed through 
the door and sped along the hall and up the stairs. 
</p><p>Fairfax got into the motor and hurried back to Paris.  His 
firm mouth was drawn in a straight line, and his keen eyes looked 
unseeing at the tragic scenes through which they passed. 
</p> 
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="12" id="d16"> 
<head>XII</head> 
 
<p>A few days after Cary's visit a number of letters and papers 
reached Elizabeth.  Except for an occasional note from Mrs. 
Andrews, they brought the first news she had had from home since 
her arrival in France, and she took them and ran to her room with 
a little throb of excitement. 
</p><p>Seating herself by the table which stood before the window, 
she spread them out before her.  The letters were from Mrs. 
Crosby, Beatrix Hunnewell, Major Barry, and Fairfax Cary. 
</p><p>Cary's hastily scrawled line, written on the train, she read 
first.  It was very short, and simply stated that he had started 
for Cape Town, and would see her on his way home.  She slipped it 
back into its envelope, a little smile parting her lips, and 
picked up <pb n="551"/>  one addressed in Mrs. Crosby's rather bold hand. 
</p><p>Unconsciously Betty steeled herself.  She opened the letter, 
and at the first words the smiling lips compressed themselves 
into a straight line.  An angry flush spread over her face, and a 
horrified expression widened her blue eyes.  Her face blanched, 
and she turned the page with a hand that trembled. 
</p><p>"Fairfax Cary!" she gasped.  "Never!  It's impossible!  It's 
so inconceivable that it's ridiculous!" 
</p><p>The letter had ended with the sentence: 
 
</p><p>Your uncle and I met him on the train the evening of the 
murder, and he told us he had just left the Delaneys.  His own 
words are an absolutely conclusive proof.  Could any evidence be 
more convincing? 
 
</p><p>Elizabeth unfolded a newspaper clipping which her aunt had 
enclosed, and in great black letters the words jumped at her: 
 
</p><p>Sister of Well-Known jockey Found Murdered in Sheepshead Bay 
Hotel   &mdash;   Prominent Lawyer Suspected   &mdash;   Patrick Delaney Dies in 
Adjoining Room. 
 
</p><p>Her eyes devoured the column of small type which described 
how Molly Delaney's body had been discovered early on Saturday 
morning by the doctor who had come to see Pat.  The boy was dead, 
and Molly was found lying half on the bed, half on the floor of 
her room, a bullet through her heart.  Although the room was in 
great disorder, apparently nothing had been removed, for money 
and jewelry lay scattered about, showing that burglary had not 
been the motive for the crime. 
</p><p>Various clues had been followed, the most conclusive 
centering around Fairfax Cary, who had been seen by a number of 
persons hurriedly leaving the hotel.  That he had been with the 
Delaneys was testified by Michael Frost, the hall-boy, who had 
conducted Cary to Pat Delaney's room shortly after seven o'clock. 
   To make the evidence doubly convincing, a letter from 
Molly Delaney, written on the afternoon before the murder, and 
requesting him to call as soon as possible, had been found in 
Cary's office. 
</p><p>Cary, in the mean time, had disappeared, and no trace of him 
could be found.  It was not thought, however, that he would be 
able to elude the police for very long, for descriptions of him 
had been sent broadcast throughout the country, and his 
apprehension was only a matter of time. 
</p><p>With a gasp of dismay Betty let the paper flutter to the 
table before her.  She rested her elbows on it, and her head 
dropped into her hands.  In spite of the newspaper report, in 
spite of her aunt's biting words, not even the shadow of a doubt 
of Cary's innocence entered her mind.  It was impossible for her 
to believe that the man who had left her so recently, whom her 
father had respected and trusted, could be guilty of this 
atrocious crime.  A hot burst of rage surged over her. 
</p><p>"How could any one connect a man like that with murder?  It's 
wicked!  Brutal!"  Her hands clenched, and she raised her head 
defiantly.  "It's a lie!" 
</p><p>But how to prove it? 
</p><p>Her eves fell on the other letters which had come in the same 
mail.  She opened the major's first and,  glancing hurriedly 
through the first pages filled with tender reproaches, 
concentrated her attention on the words that followed: 
 
</p><p>Fairfax Cary has been implicated in a nasty scandal, out of 
which I'm doing my best to extricate him.  The evidence against 
him, however, is very strong, and I don't know how we're coming 
out.  Whoever murdered Molly Delaney covered his tracks with 
incredible cunning, and now that Pat is gone, it seems almost 
impossible to get at the facts. 
</p><p>Whether or not the boy died before the murder was committed, 
we have been unable to ascertain.  We only know that Cary left 
the hotel at about half past nine.  The question is, was the girl 
alive when he went away?  This only Cary can answer.  Can you 
tell me his whereabouts?  I've cabled to his address in Paris, 
but have had no reply.  We need him and all the help we can get. 
</p><p>Won't you please come home? 
 
</p><p>"Dear Uncle Tod!" thought Betty penitently.  "He's a trump! 
I'm afraid I haven't been very good to him." 
</p><p>She picked up Trixie's note.  It was short and to the point: 
 
DEAR BETSY: 
</p><p>You must come home at once.  We need you to help us to clear 
Fairfax Cary from this dreadful charge that's been brought 
against him.  We shall expect you to stay with us. 
    As ever, affectionately, 
                            TRIXIE. 
 
</p><p>Elizabeth gathered up the papers, dropped <pb n="552"/> them into a 
drawer, and went in search of Dr. Townsend.  Hurriedly, and it 
must be confessed rather incoherently, she explained to him that 
she must return to New York at once. 
</p><p>He gave his consent without comment.  It was only when he 
stood by the motor which was to take her back to Paris that he 
showed what it was costing him to let her go. 
</p><p>"Good-by," he said gently, as he held her hand closely in his 
big clasp.  "Will you come back to us?" 
</p><p>"I want to, and I'll do my best," answered Betty; "but it all 
depends   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"If you don't, I'll come to you," he declared, with a look 
that sent the blood into Betty's face.  "This horror must be over 
soon." 
</p><p>"I hope so," agreed Betty fervently.  "Good-by, and thank you 
again for being so good to me!" 
</p><p>The motor started, and Betty, turning to wave her hand, saw 
him as he stood before the low building, the sunlight glinting on 
the gold of his hair and bringing into high relief the outlines 
of his muscular frame. 
</p><p>"That is a man!" she thought, and a feeling of self-reproach 
came over her at the thought that she was deserting the post of 
duty at the time of greatest need.  "I will surely come back!" 
she hastened to assure herself.  "Only now it seems as if I must 
go home!" 
</p><p>Never before had the trip across the Atlantic seemed of such 
interminable length, and it was almost in a frenzy of impatience 
that Betty stood on the deck as the steamer passed through the 
Narrows into New York Harbor and caught the first glimpse of the 
jagged outlines of the city emerging from the golden October 
haze.  She had cabled Major Barry when to expect her, and as the 
vessel slipped smoothly into its berth, she scanned the waiting 
crowd eagerly for the erect figure and jovial face. 
</p><p>When she at last discovered him, in spite of his expression 
of glad welcome, she saw at once from the anxious look that 
lurked in his eyes that the situation had not improved.   But it 
was not until they were seated in the Hunnewell motor, which 
Trixie had sent for her, that Betty asked the question which she 
had been restraining with difficulty ever since she landed. 
</p><p>"Has the murderer been found?" 
</p><p>Major Barry shook his head gloomily. 
</p><p>"No, I'm sorry to say!" 
</p><p>"And suspicion still rests on   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>The major nodded, and the lips under the close-trimmed 
mustache tightened. 
</p><p>"It's outrageous!" he asserted savagely.  "The evidence is 
purely circumstantial, but they've piled it up, and piled it up, 
until really   &mdash;   "  He shook his head dubiously. 
</p><p>"Have you engaged a lawyer?" asked Betty. 
</p><p>"Oh, yes, of course, right away   &mdash;   Sturgis and Fellows, capital 
men, both of them, and we're not leaving a stone unturned; but if 
I could only get in touch with Cary!  Every minute that he's away 
seems to strengthen the case against him." 
</p><p>"How long will it take him to go to Cape Town and come back?" 
asked Betty. 
</p><p>The conviction was creeping over her that if it had not been 
for her Fairfax could have cleared himself long ago. 
</p><p>It may be a couple of months.  Everything is so unsettled now 
that you can't tell how he'll be delayed." 
</p><p>"Is there any chance of his being arrested there?" 
</p><p>The major shrugged his shoulders. 
</p><p>"You can't tell.  Sometimes, especially when you don't want 
them to be, these detectives are deuced clever at finding things 
out!" 
</p><p>"I wish they'd devote their energies to the situation here!" 
said Betty. 
</p><p>The motor turned into Fifth Avenue and fell into line with 
the endless procession of hurrying cars.  Betty looked at the 
familiar scene with the eyes of an alien.  The well-known faces 
framed in the windows of the swiftly passing limousines, smiling 
and nodding to her in recognition when the traffic paused, gave 
her a feeling of surprise that she should be remembered after the 
long interval which had elapsed since she took her part in the 
drama.  It seemed as if she were looking at the spectacle from a 
great distance, as if it were being presented to her sight 
through the wrong end of an opera-glass. 
</p><p>The hurrying throngs on the streets passing in and out of the 
handsome shops, the same intent, strained look on the faces as 
the swinging doors swallowed or ejected them, forced themselves 
on her consciousness, and a helpless feeling of futility seized 
her.  So lately removed from the scenes of combat where men with 
the courage born <pb n="553"/> of high resolve struggled desperately to 
preserve the highest ideals of civilization   &mdash;   where they fought 
and died that liberty, the most precious heritage of man, might 
be transmitted as of old to the generations yet unborn   &mdash;   the 
picture before her looked crude and cruel in its selfish luxury 
and self-indulgence. 
</p><p>"No one seems to care!" she breathed at last with a little 
catch in her voice. 
</p><p>"It isn't good form to show one's feelings," the major 
reminded her whimsically, perceiving at once the trend of her 
thoughts.  "But they're really not so heartless.  They're most of 
them doing their bit; only, of course, they must have their good 
times, too!" he added indulgently. 
</p><p>"Are Uncle George and Aunt Maude in town?" 
</p><p>"I imagine so.  I saw your uncle at the club yesterday." 
</p><p>"Did he know I was coming back from France?"  An anxious look 
crept into the blue eyes. 
</p><p>"I told him." 
</p><p>I'm not going back to them!" exclaimed Betty, the fire of 
battle in her eyes. 
</p><p>The major looked at her with eyes full of tender interest. 
</p><p>"What are you going to do, my child?" he asked softly. 
</p><p>They had reached the park, and Betty's eyes wandered to the 
avenue of elms stretching their arms high above the path to clasp 
those outstretched to them from the other side. 
</p><p>"I don't know, Uncle Tod.  I can always go back to France." 
</p><p>"Is France more alluring than home just now?" he asked 
anxiously. 
</p><p>"Well, not just now," admitted Betty slowly.  "When some one 
who is sacrificing himself to do something for you gets into 
difficulties himself, you naturally want to do your best to help 
him out; but when it's all straightened out, why, then I'm going 
back." 
</p><p>A frown of disappointment appeared between the major's eyes. 
</p><p>"Well, here we are," he remarked as the motor stopped before 
the broad steps of the Hunnewells' house.  "I think I see Trixie 
at the window." 
</p><p>They passed up the steps and into the hall, and Trixie caught 
Betty in her arms. 
</p><p>"Oh, Betsy!" she exclaimed, a little break in her voice. 
"How could you give us such a scare?" 
</p><p>Betty put her arm around the girl, surprised and touched by 
her exhibition of feeling. 
</p><p>"I never thought it would make such a commotion," she said, 
while a smile which was almost as bright as of old played over 
her face. 
</p><p>"Imagine!" exclaimed Trixie.  "Didn't you know we would care? 
Have you heard anything new?" she asked, turning to the major. 
</p><p>"Not a thing," he replied.  "I'm going down to see Sturgis 
now." 
</p><p>"But you'll come back?" asked Betty anxiously. 
</p><p>"Yes, about five o'clock.  I may have something more to tell 
you then"; and be ran briskly down the steps. 
</p><p>"Come to your room," said Beatrix, drawing Betty toward the 
stairs. 
</p><p>They stopped to speak to Mrs. Hunnewell, who came out of her 
boudoir to greet Elizabeth.  Contrary to Betty's expectations, 
she gave the girl a warm welcome, and seemed to be delighted to 
have her with them. 
</p><p>"We've been hearing your praises sung so loudly for the past 
month," she said, with a teasing glance at Beatrix, " that we're 
overjoyed to have a visit from you." 
</p><p>Elizabeth looked wonderingly at her, but Beatrix drew her up 
the stairs without giving her time to reply. 
</p><p>"Betsy's tired to death," she explained to her mother over 
her shoulder.  "And Major Barry's coming back to tea.  She simply 
must rest!" 
</p><p>But when they reached Elizabeth's room Trixie's solicitude 
for her friend's health seemed to vanish.  After having helped 
Elizabeth to divest herself of her hat and coat, she drew her 
into her own room and closed the door. 
</p><p>"Betsy," she began abruptly, " is Tony Page in love with 
you?" 
</p><p>"Tony Page!  In love with me!" repeated Betty wonderingly. 
"Mercy, no!  What ever put such an idea into your head?" 
</p><p>"Oh, well, I wanted to be sure this time.  He talks 
incessantly about you   &mdash;   how you saved his life and how brave you 
are." 
</p><p>Elizabeth laughed softly. 
</p><p>"Ridiculous!  Even if I did, that doesn't mean he's in love 
with me!  And as to the <pb n="554"/> bravery   &mdash;   "  She paused, and the 
light died suddenly out of her face.  "Trixie, when your life 
isn't worth two cents to you, it doesn't take more than two 
cents' worth of courage to risk it.  And sometimes it takes all 
the courage in the world   &mdash;   much more than you possess   &mdash;   to face the 
prospect the future holds.  No, Trixie, it wasn't courage that 
night; it was just the desire to end it all.  You see, I didn't 
want to live."  The thrushlike voice faltered. 
</p><p>"Is it different now, dear?" 
</p><p>Elizabeth considered for a moment before answering. 
</p><p>"Y-e-s," she hesitated.  " I don't want to die now; at least 
not just yet." 
</p><p>"What changed you, Betsy?" 
</p><p>"I have something to do now   &mdash;   something that I <hi rend="italic">must</hi> do! 
</p><p>"And that?" 
</p><p>"I'm determined to clear the names of my father and Fairfax 
Cary.  I may be wrong, but the conviction is with me day and 
night that when Molly Delaney's murderer is found, the stain on 
my father's memory will be wiped away." 
</p><p>Trixie came very close to Elizabeth and looked earnestly into 
her eyes. 
</p><p>"Betsy, who do you think did it?" 
</p><p>"I don't know, Trixie; I haven't the faintest idea.  But one 
thing I <hi rend="italic">do</hi> know   &mdash;   I know it wasn't Fairfax Cary!" 
</p><p>Beatrix nodded. 
</p><p>"I know that, too," she agreed softly. 
</p><p>Elizabeth looked at her intently. 
</p><p>"Trixie," she said quickly, putting a hand through Trixie's 
arm and drawing her to the lounge, "will you forgive me if I ask 
you something?" 
</p><p>"Why, of course, Betsy, ask anything you like.  I haven't 
anything to hide   &mdash;   at least not yet! 
</p><p>The bright color deepened under the cream of Trixie's skin, 
and unconsciously her eyes strayed to a large photograph that 
stood on her dressing-table.  Betty's eyes followed hers, and she 
looked into Tony Page's smiling face.  For the first time since 
her father's death her vivid smile played over her face. 
</p><p>"I think, on the whole"   &mdash;   the flutelike cadence of her laugh 
rang through the room   &mdash;   "I'll wait till then before I ask you!" 
</p><p>"Why, Betsy!" began Beatrix, startled at the change in the 
girl beside her.  "What do you mean?" 
</p><p>Oh, nothing," replied Betty happily.  Only it's heavenly 
being here with you, Trix!" 
</p><p>"I know it's heavenly having you!" 
</p><p>Trixie leaned over and kissed her warmly. 
</p> 
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="13" id="d17"> 
<head>XIII</head> 
 
<p>Major Barry noticed the change as soon as he entered the 
drawing-room at five o'clock and found the girls busily engaged 
with the tea things. 
</p><p>"What have you been doing to my goddaughter?" he asked, 
smiling at Beatrix as he shook hands. 
</p><p>The intervening hours had apparently had their effect on him, 
too, for he had regained some of his old-time cheeriness. 
</p><p>"Why, nothing special," replied Trixie wonderingly. 
</p><p>"Well, she looks like a different girl, almost as if she had 
anticipated the good news that reached me only a few minutes ago. 
Cary's on his way home," he added joyfully, turning to Elizabeth. 
</p><p>"Oh!" exclaimed Betty, coming eagerly to him.  "When will he 
arrive?" 
</p><p>"That I don't know, but I had a letter from Bordeaux, saying 
that he would sail on the following day on the Rochambeau.  He 
said he ran across Tutney at Madeira.  Odd, wasn't it?  And he 
intimated that he had had a most satisfactory interview with 
him." 
</p><p>"That was strange," agreed Elizabeth. 
</p><p>"Is Tutney coming back, too?" 
</p><p>"I hardly think so   &mdash;   at least not just yet.  He expects to 
come over before long, however, for he wants to make 
investigations himself.  I gleaned from Cary's letter that things 
are not quite to his liking." 
</p><p>"I wonder when the Rochambeau is due?" 
</p><p>Beatrix rang, and when the butler appeared she told him, to 
bring the evening paper.  When it arrived Major Barry took it to 
a lamp on a near-by table. 
</p><p>"She's been sighted off Fire Island!" he exclaimed joyfully. 
</p><p>"That means she'll dock early to-morrow morning." 
</p><p>"You'll be there to meet him, won't you, Uncle Tod?" Betty 
asked anxiously. 
</p><p>"Don't worry your pretty head about that, my dear!  I'll be 
there, if I have to camp out all night on the wharf.  I've kept 
my campaigning outfit and am prepared for all emergencies," he 
added whimsically. 
<pb n="555"/>  
</p><p>He folded the paper carefully and placed it behind the lamp. 
A head-line had caught his eye which he did not care to have 
Betty see.  Evidently the detectives, too, were aware of Cary's 
proximity, and his arrival would doubtless be simultaneous with 
his arrest; but this the major did not think it necessary for 
Betty to know.  As it was, either apprehension or fatigue had 
driven the happy light from her face. 
</p><p>"Have the lawyers learned anything more?" she asked 
fearfully. 
</p><p>The major shook his head. 
</p><p>"Not a thing.  As far as I can make out, it's all up to Cary. 
If he can prove that Molly Delaney was alive when he left the 
hotel, we're all right.  If he can't   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"Well?"  The word was hardly more than a breath. 
</p><p>The major spread out his hands significantly. 
</p><p>"Well!"  He hesitated a moment, then his eyes fell on her 
troubled face.  "We'll have to establish his innocence in some 
other way," he concluded with a hopefulness that he was far from 
feeling. 
</p><p>True to his word, the next morning found Major Barry waiting 
impatiently, in the crisp air that was blowing in from the sea, 
for the great black vessel creeping up the teeming river.  Near 
him stood unobtrusively two men, who evidently considered him an 
object of unusual interest, for they kept him constantly in 
sight.  When he was joined by a short man with quick, alert eyes 
and a pointed nose, they evinced ever-increasing satisfaction. 
</p><p>"That's Sturgis, the lawyer," one of the men remarked in an 
undertone to his companion. 
</p><p>"I guess that settles it!" answered the other, a gleam of 
triumph lighting his keen eyes. 
</p><p>It was he who, when Fairfax Cary came quickly down the 
gangway, stepped forward and said quietly: 
</p><p>"We want you, Mr. Cary," 
</p><p>Fairfax stopped abruptly, and the hand that he had stretched 
out in greeting to Major Barry fell to his side.  He looked at 
the face at his shoulder inquiringly.  The second man appeared on 
the other side. 
</p><p>"Better come quietly, Mr. Cary," he remarked, turning back 
his coat and revealing the shield pinned on his waistcoat. 
"We'll explain later." 
</p><p>Fairfax looked in a perplexed way at Major Barry. 
</p><p>"It's a mistake, Fairfax, my boy, of course; but we'll just 
jump into the taxi with these two gentlemen and talk it over on 
the way.  This is Mr. Sturgis," he added, indicating the man 
beside him. 
</p><p>Fairfax bowed in a dazed way and accompanied the men as they 
led the way to the street. 
</p><p>"What's it all about, major?" he asked as they passed through 
the crowd. 
</p><p>"Something to do with Molly Delaney's murder," answered the 
major, eying him keenly. 
</p><p>"Molly Delaney!  Murdered!" gasped Fairfax.  "Why   &mdash;   who   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"Here we are!" exclaimed the major as they reached the curb. 
"Will you meet us there, Sturgis?" he asked. 
</p><p>A satisfied expression rested on his face, and his voice was 
almost jovial. 
</p><p>The short man assented, and the four took their places in the 
taxi. 
</p><p>When the major walked into the Hunnewells' drawing-room, two 
hours later, he was rubbing his hands delightedly. 
</p><p>"Just as we thought, Betty dear   &mdash;   that boy is no more 
implicated in the murder than I am," he announced joyfully to 
Elizabeth, who had left her seat on the sofa and came to meet 
him.  "Whether he can prove it is another story.  He's convinced 
that Molly was alive when he left.  He says he could distinctly 
hear her talking." 
</p><p>"To whom?" asked Betty quickly. 
</p><p>"Ah, that he didn't say!" 
</p><p>"Does he know?" 
</p><p>"I imagine so, but he didn't tell us." 
</p><p>"Why didn't he?  It may have been   &mdash;   probably was   &mdash;   the man who 
killed her." 
</p><p>The major shrugged his shoulders impatiently. 
</p><p>"Yes, I know; but you know what quixotic ideas of honor Cary 
has, and he didn't actually see the man, couldn't even recognize 
his voice." 
</p><p>Betty wrung her hands desperately. 
</p><p>"When can I see him?" she asked suddenly. 
</p><p>The major started. 
</p><p>"See him?" he ejaculated. 
</p><p>"Yes." 
</p><p>"Oh, you could hardly do that!" 
</p><p>"Why not?" 
</p><p>Betty's fair head went up defiantly. 
<pb n="556"/>  
</p><p>"Why, because   &mdash;   my dear child, he's been arrested!  He's in 
the Tombs!" 
</p><p>"What difference does that make?" 
</p><p>Betty's face was very white, but her eyes gazed unflinchingly 
into the major's. 
</p><p>"Why, you could hardly go there, you know!"  The major 
paused; then he added:  "Of course, if you were his sister or his 
wife, that would be different." 
</p><p>"How different?" argued Betty rebelliously.  "He got into 
this trouble doing something for me, and I insist on seeing him. 
If you won't take me, I shall have to go alone!" 
</p><p>The major groaned inwardly.  The determined expression on 
Betty's face indicated that she was in deadly earnest. 
</p><p>"Well, some time," he temporized. 
</p><p>"This afternoon!" declared Betty emphatically.  "I'm going 
this afternoon!" 
</p><p>"Sturgis is trying to arrange about bail.  Couldn't you wait 
until Cary's out?" pleaded the major. 
</p><p>"I'm going this afternoon," repeated Elizabeth quietly.  "Now 
will you take me?" 
</p><p>The major acquiesced reluctantly. 
</p><p>"Have you seen your aunt and uncle?" he asked on his way to 
the door. 
</p><p>Betty shook her head. 
</p><p>"My dear child," expostulated the major, 
</p><p>I really don't think you're treating them quite right.  After 
all, you know, he's your father's brother, and they were very 
good to you last summer." 
</p><p>"I know," agreed Betty remorsefully.  "I must go.  I'll go 
this afternoon, late.  Now go down and tell Fairfax I'm coming." 
She took hold of the lapels of his coat and, raising herself on 
her toes, kissed his cheek.  "You're such a dear!" she whispered 
tremulously.  "I don't know what I should do without you!" 
</p><p>Major Barry stroked her hair gently. 
</p><p>"There, there," he said tenderly.  "I'm doing nothing at all, 
nothing at all; but don't worry   &mdash;   I'm sure we shall be able to 
straighten things out before long." 
</p><p>But his optimism was all on the surface; for as he sped 
down-town to hear the result of Sturgis's efforts to get Cary out 
on bail, he gave himself over unreservedly to the depression that 
had gradually been closing in on him. 
</p><p>"No matter how hard one may try to put a cheerful face on 
it," he thought gloomily, "the fact remains that the situation is 
extremely grave." 
</p><p>And in this Sturgis agreed when he met him in front of the 
Tombs and they stopped for a few minutes' talk before going in. 
Bail had been refused, and the outlook was far from reassuring. 
</p> 
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="14" id="d18"> 
<head>XIV</head> 
 
<p>But Major Barry had thrown off his air of depression by the 
time he and Sturgis reached Cary's cell.  He patted Fairfax on 
the shoulder as he rose to meet them. 
</p><p>"Well," he began cheerily, "luck's against us for the time 
being, my boy!  The powers that be won't listen to any talk of 
bail." 
</p><p>A quiver passed over the finely chiseled features.  Major 
Barry went on: 
</p><p>"So there's nothing to do but to establish your innocence as 
quickly as possible.  Now, how are we going to do it?" 
</p><p>He and Sturgis sat down on the chairs, and Fairfax dropped 
down on the cot.  Fairfax shrugged his shoulders hopelessly. 
</p><p>"I only know that the girl was alive when I left the hotel. 
As to conjecturing who killed her, you can do that as well as I." 
</p><p>He pressed his hand wearily against the back of his head. 
</p><p>"Who was with her when you left, Mr. Cary?" asked the lawyer. 
</p><p>"That I can't tell you." 
</p><p>"It may give us the clue that will enable us to exonerate 
you." 
</p><p>Cary considered for a moment in silence, while the two men 
searched his face anxiously. 
</p><p>"I prefer not to express an opinion as to who it was," he 
replied at last, "I didn't see the man or recognize his voice." 
</p><p>"Well," said Sturgis, rising, "I know Major Barry has other 
matters to discuss with you, so I'll leave you." 
</p><p>He called to a guard who was passing and disappeared into the 
corridor. 
</p><p>"Now," began the major, drawing his chair closer to Cary, 
"tell me about Tutney.  It was extraordinary your finding him as 
you did!" 
</p><p>Fairfax came out of the abstraction that had fallen on him 
and fixed his dark, penetrating eyes on the major's face. 
</p><p>"Yes," he assented, "it was great luck.  He had just arrived 
from Cape Town, and was, I think, as glad to see me as I was to 
<pb n="557"/> run across him.  He asked me at once about Randolph Crosby's 
affairs.  It seems that he and Mr. Crosby and a number of other 
men had formed a syndicate to develop this diamond-mine, with an 
agreement that no one should sell his interest without first 
giving the other directors a chance to buy it.  Shortly after Mr. 
Crosby's death a large block of the stock was offered at public 
sale.  Tutney, when he heard of it, was naturally a good deal 
upset, and immediately suspected that the stock was Mr. Crosby's. 
He evidently felt pretty badly about it, for he realizes what the 
future of the property will be, and he knew what a mistake it was 
to sell before its true value was reached.  He's a great admirer 
of Miss Crosby, and I know he felt that if his supposition were 
correct, and the stock was her father's, that her executor didn't 
have her best interests at heart." 
</p><p>The major nodded, and remarked ironically: 
</p><p>"He's a man of much perception!" 
</p><p>"He asked me who the trustees were," continued Fairfax; "and 
when I told him that George Crosby was sole executor, he didn't 
seem overpleased.  He said he thought it was a mistake to entrust 
a big estate like that to any one man, even though you had 
unlimited confidence in him.  The chances for mistakes in 
judgment alone were too great." 
</p><p>"Then he thought the property was a large one?" queried the 
major quickly. 
</p><p>"Yes; he said he knew it was.  He scoffed at the idea that 
Mr. Crosby had made unwise investments.  He said any one who knew 
Randolph Crosby at all knew him for a sagacious business man, 
keen, and of remarkable acuteness, while at the same time he had 
an unusual sense of obligation and honor." 
</p><p>"Did you tell him that the entire fortune was gone, and that 
Crosby's daughter was working to support herself?" 
</p><p>Fairfax nodded. 
</p><p>"I asked him if it were possible, and he said not unless the 
trustee had mishandled the estate." 
</p><p>"Just as I thought!"  The major leaned forward and tapped 
Fairfax lightly on the knee.  "Mark my words, boy, George Crosby 
and that precious son of his have made away with that child's 
money!  Now, it's going to be my business to find out where and 
how it has gone."  He straightened up.  "Betty wants to see you," 
he concluded abruptly. 
</p><p>Fairfax started.  He glanced around the bare cell, at the 
stone walls, the iron door, and barred window through which a 
shaft of light slanted and lay in stripes across the cold floor. 
</p><p>"Here?" he breathed, a look of distress coming into his 
haggard eyes. 
</p><p>"Insists on it, my boy," continued the major briskly.  "And, 
Fairfax, when you've known Betty as long as I have, you'll 
realize that when she makes up her mind   &mdash;   "  He spread out his 
hands and shook his head helplessly, an indulgent smile twitching 
at the corners of his mouth.  "You know what an old fool I am 
about her   &mdash;   simply can't refuse her anything.  I don't have to 
tell you that I'm not particularly anxious to have her come here. 
No reflection on you, of course, but   &mdash;   well, it isn't just the 
thing under the circumstances   &mdash;   you understand?" 
</p><p>He looked a little pleadingly into the younger man's face. 
</p><p>"Of course," Fairfax assented gravely.  "I understand 
perfectly." 
</p><p>"Well, she's coming, just the same.  Says she has something 
of the utmost importance to tell you." 
</p><p>"When will she come?" Cary asked huskily. 
</p><p>"This afternoon, about three." 
</p><p>Cary took a turn up and down the cell and stopped before the 
major. 
</p><p>"Has what she is going to tell me got anything to do with Dr. 
Townsend?" 
</p><p>His voice sounded harsh and strained. 
</p><p>"Don't know, I'm sure." 
</p><p>The major looked sympathetically at him.  He did not add that 
Betty had said that she intended shortly to return to France. 
</p><p>"If that's what she's coming to tell him, he'll know it soon 
enough," he thought pityingly.  "I know what the poor boy's going 
through, and suspense, hard as it is to bear, is better than 
despair." 
</p><p>He patted Fairfax on the shoulder and bade him good-by, 
promising to return after luncheon. 
</p><p>If Elizabeth experienced any feelings of trepidation as she 
left the warm sunshine and entered the ominous chill of the 
massive gray building, Major Barry, who was watching her closely, 
failed to detect it.  <pb n="558"/> Even when the door was unlocked and 
they entered the long passage where tier upon tier of cells 
looked down upon them, each with its tragic-faced inmate tense 
with suppressed revolt or huddled in passive lethargy, she 
retained her expression of calm. 
</p><p>The guard stopped before a door and inserted the key.  It 
opened, and Betty stepped into the cell.  The door clanged back 
into place and the lock clicked. 
</p><p>Fairfax rose and turned quickly toward her.  His face was 
very white, but there still clung to him his air of proud 
reserve, and the dark eyes looked out fearless and unashamed from 
under the straight brows. 
</p><p>Betty came quickly to him and held out her hand.  He 
hesitated for a moment, and then, taking it, held it closely in 
his. 
</p><p>"It was very good of you to come," he said in a hushed voice. 
</p><p>Betty laughed a little tremulously. 
</p><p>"Now we're quits!" she exclaimed.  That's what I said to you 
in the hospital!" 
</p><p>A semblance of a smile parted the sensitive lips.  He 
indicated the chair beside which they stood.  After Betty had 
seated herself, he sank once more on the cot and fixed his eyes 
on the shifting bars of light. 
</p><p>Betty pressed her hands tightly together in her lap, and a 
lump rose in her throat.  Her eyes rested pitifully on the bowed, 
dark head.  She swallowed hard; then, rising suddenly, she ran to 
the cot, seated herself beside him, and put her arm around his 
neck. 
</p><p>"Oh, my dear, my dear!" she whispered brokenly, laying her 
cheek against his.  "I didn't tell you the truth that time in 
France.  I do care, Fairfax.  I love you, dear!" 
</p><p>A tremor passed over Fairfax.  He clenched his hands until 
the knuckles showed white. 
</p><p>"Don't!" he breathed hoarsely.  "Don't, for God's sake!" 
</p><p>"Don't what?" Betty drew back, and her great eyes, 
pansy-black in the uncertain light, rested on the white, averted 
face. 
</p><p>"You don't realize what you're doing!" 
</p><p>Betty looked relieved. 
</p><p>"Oh, yes, I do," she asserted.  "I realize perfectly what I'm 
doing.  I'm telling the man I honor above everything on earth 
that I love him.  It's high time that he knew, for I've suddenly 
discovered that I've loved him for a very long time   &mdash;   much longer 
than I had any idea of!" 
</p><p>Cary got up suddenly and, walking with quick, nervous steps 
to the door of his cell, placed his hands on the grating.  He 
shook it slightly; then he turned back to Betty, who had taken a 
step after him. 
</p><p>"It's real!" he whispered huskily.  "Sometimes I think it 
must be a dream, and I have actually to go and feel the locked 
door before I can believe it.  "But now," he went on, the look of 
pain deepening in his eyes, "those bars have begun to press in on 
me closer and closer, until I can feel them on my forehead.  I 
know in time they'll reach my soul, and then I shall never be 
able to wipe away the taint!" 
</p><p>He strode past her and, sinking once more on the cot, buried 
his face in his hands. 
</p><p>"Fairfax!" Betty ran to him, sat down beside him, and put her 
arm around his shoulder.  "You mustn't have such dreadful 
thoughts!  Nothing can taint your soul but sin, and, darling, 
your friends know how far that is from you!" 
</p><p>Again a tremor passed over him. 
</p><p>"You don't know, no one knows until he's been locked in, what 
it means to be caged in a place like this, with the knowledge 
that no power on your part can get you out!  It's hideous, 
horrible!" he whispered hoarsely.  "The iron eats into your 
soul!" 
</p><p>Betty laid her hand on his head and drew it gently to her 
until it rested on her shoulder.  Stooping over, she pressed her 
lips to his forehead. 
</p><p>"Darling," she whispered, "I love you!" 
</p><p>A great sob shook Fairfax.  He raised himself and drew 
resolutely away. 
</p><p>"I should deserve to be kicked if I took what your pity and 
gratitude are prompting you to give!" he said.  "No; I love you 
too dearly to allow you to sacrifice yourself for a man who has 
passed through an ordeal like this!" 
</p><p>Once more the dark head sank into his hands. 
</p><p>"Fairfax, that's absurd!  You wanted to marry me when a stain 
rested on my name   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"That's very different," he broke in.  "The discredit in no 
way reflected on you." 
</p><p>"And if it had, would it have prevented you from loving me?" 
</p><p>"Never!"  The word was sharp and decisive. 
</p><p>"Well," exclaimed Betty, with a little laugh of triumph, 
"then that's settled!" 
<pb n="559"/>  
</p><p>"What's settled?" 
</p><p>"That we're to be married!" 
</p><p>"Miss Crosby, don't you understand   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"Don't call me Miss Crosby!" interrupted Betty imperiously. 
"And as to understanding, why"   &mdash;   her voice softened   &mdash;   "the big fact 
remains that we love each other, dear, and after that nothing 
matters.  Dear heart, you do love me, don't you?" 
</p><p>Fairfax groaned and pressed his hands closer over his eyes. 
</p><p>"You're the most difficult man I ever proposed to," remarked 
Betty, with a tremulous little laugh.  "Well, if you won't be 
nice, I'm going to ask you a question.  Who was in the room with 
Molly Delaney that night when you were talking to Pat?" 
</p><p>Fairfax did not answer. 
</p><p>"Answer me, Fairfax!" 
</p><p>"I don't know.  At least, I'm not sure." 
</p><p>"But you have a strong suspicion?" 
</p><p>"You can't implicate a man in a crime like this on a 
suspicion." 
</p><p>"But if that suspicion led to a correct solution?" 
</p><p>"It might not, and then it would bring unnecessary pain to 
innocent people.  I know too much about that to be willing to 
inflict it on others," he concluded bitterly. 
</p><p>Betty sat for a moment wrapped in thought. 
</p><p>"If we could only get at the motive," she said, half to 
herself, "it might be a clue!  Why should any one want to kill 
the girl?  Do you know any reason?" 
</p><p>Fairfax moved restlessly. 
</p><p>"It's hard to tell," he answered evasively.  "With people 
like that there are so many reasons.  It might have been 
jealousy, fear of exposure, any one of half a dozen things." 
</p><p>"Well, I sha'n't rest night or day till I find out."  Betty 
rose as the guard inserted his key in the lock.  "I'll see you 
again soon." 
</p><p>"Did you learn anything?" asked Major Barry anxiously, when 
she joined him in the waiting-room. 
</p><p>Betty shook her head dejectedly. 
</p><p>"He absolutely refuses to tell who it was.  Uncle Tod, I want 
to go down to Sheepshead Bay and look through those rooms.  I'm 
convinced that there must be something there that will give us a 
clue." 
</p><p>"But, my dear child, the detectives have searched them 
thoroughly." 
</p><p>"Yes, I know," Betty assented obstinately.  "But it may be 
the only chance of saving him!" 
</p><p>She was very pale, but her chin was firm and resolute. 
</p><p>"I'll try to arrange it, but I'm afraid there isn't much 
hope.  Where are you going now?" 
</p><p>"To the Crosbys'.  I want to tell them of my engagement to 
Fairfax." 
</p><p>"What?" 
</p><p>The major stopped in the crowded street along which they were 
walking on their way to the Elevated train and looked aghast at 
the girl's calm face. 
</p><p>"Why, Uncle Tod," she exclaimed, "you don't mean to tell me 
you didn't know?" 
</p><p>"Know!  Know what?" 
</p><p>"Why, that we love each other!" 
</p><p>"I knew that Cary loved you, and I suspected that you cared 
for him; but really, Betty, I hardly think that   &mdash;   at present, if I 
were you   &mdash;   I would   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"You hardly think that now's the time for me to tell the 
world of my belief in Fairfax's innocence?" she said defiantly. 
"You'll have to forgive me for differing with you.  I can't 
imagine any time more appropriate!" 
</p><p>The major looked at her with a gleam of admiration in his 
eyes.  The color had mounted in her cheeks, and her eyes shone 
bright under the level brows. 
</p><p>"Of course, my dear," he answered in a conciliatory voice, 
"we all believe that Fairfax is innocent.  Tell me, how does Cary 
feel about it?" 
</p><p>The dimple under Betty's eye came into play, and she broke 
into a little laugh. 
</p><p>"Oh, he says he won't marry me!" 
</p><p>The major looked relieved. 
</p><p>"He means, of course, not till this mess is straightened 
out." 
</p><p>They crossed the street and passed up the steps to the 
Elevated.  When they were seated in the train Betty answered. 
</p><p>"I don't know what he means," she said.  "I only know that 
I'm going to marry him as soon as possible." 
</p><p>"Well, you modern girls certainly know your own minds!" 
remarked the major.  "Now, in my day if was customary   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"To wait until we were asked?" interposed Betty merrily. 
"Well, things have changed, Uncle Tod; now  it's the other way 
round.  You men don't realize it, but it's <pb n="560"/> really the women 
who do the proposing.  We let the men think the old custom is 
still in force.  It makes them happier, and doesn't alter the 
fact!" 
</p> 
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="15" id="d19"> 
<head>XV</head> 
 
<p>But after she had said good-by to the major at her uncle's 
door and had entered the hall, the happy look faded from 
Elizabeth's face, and was replaced by one of firm resolve.  She 
foresaw a struggle, and with characteristic energy determined to 
have it over as quickly as possible. 
</p><p>She went into the familiar drawing-room, and a slight feeling 
of surprise came over her at finding it exactly as it had been in 
the spring.  The furniture stood in its accustomed places; the 
same photographs looked at her from their silver frames; the same 
copy of Omar Khayyam lay on the table by the same vase, which was 
filled as of old with pink carnations.  Everything was just as 
she had left it; but, in spite of its familiarity, a different 
spirit brooded over the room, subtly conveying an impression of 
suspense, of dread. 
</p><p>"Absurd!" thought Betty, with a little shake of her 
shoulders.  "I'm getting abnormally imaginative!  It's I who have 
changed!" 
</p><p>She heard a step in the hall, and Mrs. Crosby parted the 
portieres and walked into the room.  In spite of the carefully 
shaded light, in spite of her elaborate mauve tea-gown and 
artistic make-up, Betty was shocked at her aunt's appearance. 
</p><p>"Aunt Maude," she exclaimed, deep concern in her voice, 
"you've been ill!" 
</p><p>Mrs. Crosby kissed the girl's cheek mechanically and 
dismissed the question with a wave of her jeweled hand. 
</p><p>"Come into the library," she said.  "Your uncle is there." 
</p><p>They crossed the hall and entered the luxurious room.  George 
Crosby rose from a deep chair by the fire and came slowly toward 
Betty.  He kissed her affectionately and, turning back to the 
fire, dropped again into his seat. 
</p><p>He held out his hands to the blaze.  They were thin and 
wrinkled, and twitched spasmodically, and in the light of the 
fire his face showed gray and haggard. 
</p><p>"You've been gone a long time, Elizabeth," began Mrs. Crosby 
in a curiously restrained voice.  She had seated herself in the 
corner of a sofa, on the other side of the fire, and Betty sank 
down beside her.  "Do you think you have been very kind to us?" 
</p><p>Betty moved uneasily, and did not answer her aunt's question. 
</p><p>"Your uncle has hardly slept or eaten since you left," Mrs. 
Crosby went on plaintively; " and I   &mdash;   "  She paused significantly. 
</p><p>"Oh, I'm so sorry!" exclaimed Betty penitently.  "I had no 
idea you would care!" 
</p><p>George Crosby turned his sunken eyes to her. 
</p><p>"Care?" he repeated dully. 
</p><p>What made you think we wouldn't care?" asked Mrs. Crosby 
reproachfully.  "It has been a dreadful six weeks!  I only hope 
you will never know such suffering and anxiety as you have caused 
us!" 
</p><p>Betty's lip trembled. 
</p><p>"Oh, Aunt Maude," she whispered, "I wasn't happy, either; but 
I couldn't stay   &mdash;   I had to do something!" 
</p><p>"You might at least have told us where you were.  We had no 
idea, and it isn't safe for young girls   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"Yes, I know, aunt.  Believe me, I'm very sorry." 
</p><p>A silence fell on them, broken only by the crackling of the 
flames and the subdued snap of a log as it broke in the middle 
and parted in a shower of sparks. 
</p><p>"Where are you stopping?" asked Mrs. Crosby at last. 
</p><p>"With the Hunnewells." 
</p><p>"Oh!" Mrs. Crosby glanced furtively at the girl's pure 
profile as she gazed past her into the fire.  "I can imagine that 
Mrs. Hunnewell is very happy over Beatrix's escape." 
</p><p>"Escape?" repeated Betty in a bewildered voice and with an 
inquiring look at her aunt. 
</p><p>"Yes   &mdash;   from her engagement to Fairfax Cary." 
</p><p>"Oh!" said Betty slowly.  "That never existed." 
</p><p>"How do you know?" asked Mrs. Crosby sharply. 
</p><p>"Both Trixie and Fairfax told me," answered Betty.  "I am 
going to marry Fairfax Cary," she added quietly. 
</p><p>"What?" exclaimed her uncle and aunt simultaneously. 
</p><p>A happy smile illumined the girl's face. 
<pb n="561"/>  
</p><p>"Yes," she went on, the thrushlike lilt ringing in her voice, 
"he came to see me in France, and asked me to marry him." 
</p><p>"Was this after the murder?" 
</p><p>Betty nodded. 
</p><p>"Yes; he sailed early the following morning, before he knew 
about it." 
</p><p>"Before any one else knew about it," interposed Mrs. Crosby 
bitingly.  "But of course he has absolved you of your promise 
now?" 
</p><p>Betty laughed. 
</p><p>"Oh, I refused to marry him when he asked me; but later I 
found that I loved him and couldn't live without him, so this 
afternoon I told him so." 
</p><p>"Where did you see him?" asked George Crosby. 
</p><p>"At the Tombs," replied Betty calmly.  Uncle Tod took me." 
</p><p>"Tod Barry took you to the Tombs!" exclaimed Mrs. Crosby 
incredulously. 
</p><p>Betty nodded, and again her face was illumined by a bright 
smile. 
</p><p>"So now we're engaged," she concluded happily at least I am 
to him.  I suppose he isn't engaged to me, for he refuses to 
marry me!" 
</p><p>"I'm glad he has some sense of honor left!" 
</p><p>George Crosby sank back into his chair, a relieved expression 
stealing over his face.  Betty's eyes dilated, but her voice was 
quiet and controlled as she replied: 
</p><p>"That's the trouble   &mdash;   he has an exaggerated sense of honor. 
If it were not for that we should know, or at least have a very 
definite idea, who Molly Delaney's murderer is.  Fairfax knows 
who was with her while he was talking to Pat, but he won't tell! 
</p><p>A step had been coming along the hall, and when she finished 
speaking Betty looked up into Norman's livid face. 
</p><p>"Hello, Betty!" he exclaimed in a voice which he was 
evidently struggling to make sound natural.  "So you've left your 
wounded soldiers?" 
</p><p>"Yes," answered Betty gravely, looking searchingly at the 
shrunken figure and restless, glittering eyes.  "I thought just 
now I was needed more here." 
</p><p>"That nursing business has been run into the ground, anyway", 
observed Norman{sic}  He lit a cigarette and inhaled a deep 
breath of the smoke.  "Just a fad!" 
</p><p>"You wouldn't think so if you had ever been in one of those 
hospitals and seen the need!" retorted Betty quickly.  "It's 
terrible!  All that unspeakable agony   &mdash;   sorrow   &mdash;   death   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>The boy started nervously. 
</p><p>"Death!" he exclaimed passionately.  "The whole world's gone 
mad on the subject!  Can't we keep away from it?"  He paced the 
room with quick, short steps.  "It's got to a point where it's a 
morbid obsession with people.  You hear it talked about wherever 
you go!  You read it in every book, magazine, newspaper.  It 
positively jumps at you from every street corner until your 
brain's fairly reeling!  I should think at least in one's own 
home one could keep it out!" 
</p><p>He stopped at a mahogany chest that stood on a small table 
and, taking out a bottle, poured whisky into a glass.  Raising 
the glass high above his head, his eyes burning feverishly, he 
exclaimed hoarsely:  "To hell with death!" and gulped down the 
yellow liquid. 
</p><p>Norman!" exclaimed his mother in a horrified voice.  "What 
<hi rend="italic">is</hi> the matter with you?  I've never seen any one change as you 
have in the past few weeks!"  She looked meaningly at Elizabeth. 
"It's been like this ever since you left us at Newport!" 
</p><p>Norman dropped heavily into a chair by the table. 
</p><p>"Let's go away, mater, somewhere where it's warm and sunny. 
This beastly chill has got into my bones." 
</p><p>He shivered and drove his hands deep into his 
trouser-pockets. 
</p><p>"Come to the fire, dear," urged his mother.  "Where would you 
like to go?" 
</p><p>Don't care, only let's start soon   &mdash;   tomorrow, if you can get 
off." 
</p><p>"Well, hardly to-morrow, dear; there isn't such desperate 
haste as all that, surely.  The next day, perhaps."  She 
considered thoughtfully for a moment and added:  "We might go to 
the Hot Springs." 
</p><p>"For Heaven's sake, don't go where there are a lot of prying, 
gossiping people!" exclaimed Norman hastily.  "Can't we take a 
sea trip to Rio, or some place like that?" 
</p><p>"Mercy!" expostulated Mrs. Crosby.  "That's an interminable 
way off!" 
</p><p>"That's just what I want   &mdash;   an interminable way off.  Come with 
us, Betty!" 
</p><p>Betty shook her head. 
<pb n="562"/>  
</p><p>"No; I've important work to do here," she announced. 
</p><p>"What?" 
</p><p>The boy eyed her narrowly. 
</p><p>"I'm going to find Molly Delaney's murderer." 
</p><p>For a moment no one spoke, and a tense stillness settled over 
the room.  Then, as if unable to bear it, Norman jumped up. 
</p><p>"Well, I wish you luck!" he said huskily and disappeared 
through the door. 
</p><p>"He's been like that ever since you refused to marry him," 
said Mrs. Crosby, looking reproachfully at the pale face beside 
her.  "As I told you at Newport, you could have done everything 
in the world for him, Betty; and now there are times when I'm 
really anxious about him.  Don't you think you could come with us 
on this trip?  It might mean saving the boy from   &mdash;   "  She stopped. 
</p><p>Betty stared into the many-colored flames as they darted up 
the chimney, a feeling of apprehension clutching at her heart. 
This, then, and not the worry over her disappearance, was the 
reason for the atmosphere of anxiety and suspense that hung over 
the household.  But, in spite of the fact that her heart was 
swelling with sympathy, she could not bring herself to leave New 
York just now. 
</p><p>"I'm sorry, Aunt Maude," she faltered.  "If you'll only 
postpone the trip a little I might, but now   &mdash;   it's absolutely 
impossible.  You must see that." 
</p><p>She looked pleadingly at her aunt. 
</p><p>"Do you think yourself cleverer than the police?" asked her 
uncle suddenly. 
</p><p>Betty spread out her hands desperately. 
</p><p>"I don't know, Uncle George.  I only know that I've got to 
stay and do what I can.  You see, I have a feeling that I may be 
able to discover why father   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"Why father what?" asked George Crosby sharply. 
</p><p>"Why people were so unkind to him just before he died, and 
how he came to make such unfortunate investments.  It's all so 
confused and unexplainable now, and I do so want to straighten it 
out!  You must understand how I feel, don't you, Uncle George?" 
</p><p>She turned to him, eager for his sympathy and indorsement; 
but George Crosby did not reply.  He sank deeper into his chair 
and covered his eyes with his shaking hand. 
</p><p>The tall clock in the corner struck six in silvery tones, and 
Betty rose quickly. 
</p><p>"I must go," she announced hurriedly.  "I had no idea it was 
so late!" 
</p><p>"Shall I order the motor for you?" asked her aunt. 
</p><p>"Oh, no, thank you, aunt.  It's only a step to Trixie's." 
</p><p>She kissed them both and passed out into the hall.  Norman 
came out of the drawing-room. 
</p><p>"I'll walk back with you," he said, taking his hat and gloves 
from the hall table. 
</p><p>He opened the door, and they stepped out into the sharp night 
air. 
</p><p>"Betty," he began, as soon as they reached the sidewalk, " I 
wouldn't get mixed up in this Fairfax Cary mess if I were you. 
It won't do any good; and you can't afford   &mdash;   no girl can   &mdash;   to have 
your name connected with a scandal like that." 
</p><p>Betty straightened herself stiffly. 
</p><p>"As I'm going to change my name to Cary before long, I'm 
naturally more anxious to get Fairfax out of this trouble than I 
am to guard the name of Crosby!" she retorted bruskly. 
</p><p>"Betty," exclaimed Norman, stopping abruptly and staring at 
her, "you're <hi rend="italic">not</hi> you're not going to marry that   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"I am," interposed Betty calmly; "so don't make too many 
derogatory remarks about your future cousin!" 
</p><p>"Well, if that's the case, I've nothing further to say!" 
</p><p>They walked on to the Hunnewells' house in silence, and 
Norman rang the bell.  The door was opened, and with a hurried 
good night he raised his hat and ran down the steps, leaving 
Betty to enter the luxurious warmth. 
</p> 
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="16" id="d20"> 
<head>XVI</head> 
 
<p>It was with steps heavy from fatigue that Major Barry entered 
the dark hall of his little apartment that evening, at about half 
past nine o'clock, and switched on the light.  He took off his 
hat and coat in the tiny hall and, going into the sitting-room, 
lit the lamp.  In his hand he held several letters.  He settled 
himself in the comfortable chair by the table and, raising the 
lid of the humidor, took up his pipe and filled it leisurely. 
</p><p>"It certainly is good to have a little quiet at last," he 
said half aloud.  "You must be <pb n="563"/> getting old, Tod; you can't 
stand the pace the way you used to.  This last month has taken it 
out of you, my boy!" 
</p><p>He lit his pipe and, placing his glasses, with their broad, 
black ribbon, on his nose, took up the pile of letters and ran 
over the addresses. 
</p><p>"Wonder whose writing this is?" he soliloquized, gazing 
thoughtfully at one addressed in a tight, cramped hand.  He broke 
open the flap and took out the folded sheet.  It was a short note 
from Barney Tutney, written from the Rossmore Hotel, asking when 
he might see the major. 
</p><p>Major Barry's hand shot out toward the telephone on the table 
beside him.  He gave the number of Tutney's hotel, and in five 
minutes had arranged an immediate interview with him at the 
apartment.  He hung up the receiver, a look of grim resolve on 
his face. 
</p><p>When the bell rang, a little later, he jumped to the door, 
all trace of his fatigue gone.  He grasped Tutney's hand in 
cordial welcome, helped him off with his coat, and drew him into 
the cozy room. 
</p><p>"Sit down, Tutney," he said.  "Do you smoke?"  He opened the 
humidor, and Tutney selected a cigar.  "I'm smoking a pipe," he 
went on.  "I find it great company when I'm alone." 
</p><p>The major held a match to the other man's cigar and studied 
his face as he drew in the smoke. 
</p><p>"I'm very glad you decided to come over so soon," he 
remarked, settling himself back in his chair. 
</p><p>Tutney took the cigar from his mouth and examined the lighted 
end critically. 
</p><p>"I thought it was about time," he answered slowly.  "By the 
bye, I'm mighty sorry about Cary."  He looked sharply at the 
major from under his shaggy eyebrows. 
</p><p>"A bad business!" admitted the major.  He puffed a moment in 
silence, then he added quietly:  "Of course, he had absolutely no 
connection with the murder." 
</p><p>"Of course not," agreed Tutney.  "But, just the same, I guess 
there are people who are glad to have him where he is   &mdash;   out of 
mischief!" 
</p><p>"Perhaps those same people won't be overjoyed to hear of your 
return," remarked the major grimly. 
</p><p>"Probably not   &mdash;   probably not!"  The keen eyes snapped. 
"Things weren't goin' exactly right, and it don't do to let 'em 
get away from you.  It's much better to take a hand in the 
beginnin', and oftentimes you can prevent a landslide." 
</p><p>"Yes," assented the major gravely.  "But in this instance I'm 
afraid we're too late.  I blame myself   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"You couldn't do nothin', Major Barry," interposed the man, 
replacing the cigar in his mouth.  He took a long puff and 
watched the smoke float off into the shadows.  "How could you 
know how things were goin'?  Now, if I'd been here, instead of in 
South Africa, things might have been different.  When that stock 
was put up for sale I could have stepped right in." 
</p><p>"Are you sure it was Crosby's?" 
</p><p>"There ain't no doubt of it.  The transaction was pretty well 
covered up, but I've managed to trace the brokers, and now I have 
my proofs.  George Crosby's been speculatin' pretty heavily the 
last three months; and, besides, he got mixed up in a shyster 
rubber scheme, and from what I can learn, lost a pile of money in 
it." 
</p><p>Tutney stopped, and a great cloud of smoke rose around his 
head. 
</p><p>"Do you think there is any possibility of getting the 
estate   &mdash;   what is left of it   &mdash;   out of his hands?" 
</p><p>"Well, of course that's a question for a lawyer; but from the 
evidence I've been able to gather, I think Miss Crosby has a 
mighty strong case against her uncle.  To my mind, there ain't no 
question but what she can force him to make good.  There'd have 
to be a lawsuit, of course." 
</p><p>"That's the trouble; I don't know whether she would consent 
to it." 
</p><p>"She'll make a big mistake if she don't.  If she waits for 
the three years to be up before she demands an accounting, there 
won't be anything left.  It don't seem possible," Tutney 
ruminated, "that Randolph Crosby's pile should all be gone in 
four months and his daughter workin' for a livin'!  Well, it's 
the first and last time, to my knowledge, that Mr. Crosby got 
fooled in his man.  He thought an awful sight of his brother." 
</p><p>"Which makes George Crosby's behavior just that much more 
reprehensible," said Major Barry indignantly. 
</p><p>Tutney agreed and rose to go, promising to have his testimony 
ready at any time it was needed if a lawsuit were decided upon. 
<pb n="564"/>  
</p><p>For a long while after Tutney left Major Barry sat puffing at 
his pipe and staring into the shadows.  On his usually genial 
face was the expression it had worn when he and his command 
pursued Red Wolf's band after the massacre of Pine Notch. 
If the major had been the judge, in spite of his kindly heart, 
there would be as little clemency shown in this as in the other 
case. 
</p><p>However, he decided to postpone telling Betty of his 
discovery until the web which entangled Fairfax Cary was 
untangled. 
</p><p>"The poor child has quite enough to worry her," he thought 
regretfully as he rose and switched off the light; "and she's 
really fond of her uncle." 
</p><p>Contrary to the major's predictions, he did obtain permission 
to visit the Delaneys' rooms, and the next morning he and Betty 
motored down to the hotel at Sheepshead Bay, where a detective 
met them.  They mounted the steep stairs and passed down the 
narrow hallway, with its unwholesome wall-paper and threadbare 
carpet.  There was a portentous chill in the stale air, and 
Elizabeth shivered a little as the detective stopped before one 
of the closed doors and inserted the key. 
</p><p>The door opened, and they entered the jockey's room, 
evidently untouched since the day after his death.  It looked 
neglected and desolate, with its unmade bed, half-open bureau 
drawers, and scattered papers.  In one corner lay a crumpled 
red-silk shirt next to a stained pair of riding-breeches, and 
standing near was a riding-boot, its mate lying beside it.  By 
the bed stood a small table, its baize cover gray with dust.  In 
the mirror of the ash chiffonier was a snap-shot picture of 
Randolph Crosby. 
</p><p>A sob clutched at Betty's throat, but she resolutely forced 
it back.  She glanced at the door, slightly ajar, which led into 
the adjoining room. 
</p><p>"I should like to go in there first," she said to the 
detective. 
</p><p>"Very well, Miss Crosby!" 
</p><p>He pushed back the door and let her pass.  The men followed, 
and instinctively the major took off his hat. 
</p><p>The room was in great disorder.  A trunk half filled with a 
motley array of garments stood in front of the window.  On a 
chair gaped a suit-case, out of which trailed a worn shirt-waist. 
On the top of the bureau was a mass of toilet articles, 
cosmetics, ribbons, veils, and gloves. 
</p><p>The mantel was littered with photographs of actors and 
actresses, jockeys and trainers.  On one corner of it, on a 
stand, rested Molly's best hat.  It was the one she had worn at 
the races on the afternoon before Randolph Crosby's death, and 
Betty saw once more the girl's audacious face sparkling under the 
crimson feather and purple rose. 
</p><p>The remembrance of that last happy afternoon brought the hot 
tears of regret into Betty's eyes, and to hide them she turned 
quickly to the mantel.  She took up the hat and with gentle 
fingers brushed off the dust which lay thick on the drooping 
feather.  A large photograph that stood behind the stand fell 
forward, disclosing a small, round object set in the wall. 
</p><p>"Why, what is that?" asked Betty. 
</p><p>Grimes, the detective, who had been idly turning over some 
old newspapers on a table near the window, came quickly to her 
side.  Betty pointed to the wall. 
</p><p>"Well, if that don't beat all!" he said under his breath. 
"How do you suppose we came to pass that up?" 
</p><p>"What is it?" 
</p><p>The major left his place by the door, where he had lingered, 
and the expression of extreme distaste which had fixed itself on 
his face turned to one of liveliest interest. 
</p><p>Grimes's fingers ran lovingly over the little round disk. 
</p><p>"That's a dictograph.  I wonder who put it there, and why he 
done it! 
</p><p>The sharp, gray eyes narrowed, and he stepped toward the door 
that led into Pat's room, the major following. 
</p><p>Betty took an irresolute step after them and stopped.  Her 
eyes fell upon the bed against which Molly had been found, and as 
if drawn by a power she could not resist, she walked slowly to 
it.  She stood for a moment gazing down upon it, her imagination 
painting in vivid colors the last scene in the girl's life. 
</p><p>In the weeks of her hospital work, death had in a measure 
lost its horror for her, but this was different; this was death 
in its most revolting form, without the nobility of 
self-sacrifice.  It was sordid, hideous, repulsive!  A shudder 
passed over her, and she turned quickly, as if to rid herself of 
the <pb n="565"/> room and its associations, when her eye was caught by 
the glint of something bright in the space between the mattress 
and the wooden side of the bed. 
</p><p>She stooped down and saw, lying on the slats, a small 
glittering object.  From the other room came the indistinct 
murmur of the men's voices, broken once by an exclamation from 
the detective.  Betty hastily put her hand into the narrow space; 
when she drew it out it held a gold cigarette-case.  The case was 
half open, and the cigarettes under the gold bar were stained and 
dark.  Betty looked at it, her eyes widening in horror. 
</p><p>Steps sounded behind her. 
</p><p>"That was a great find you made, Miss Crosby," said a voice 
at her shoulder.  "Now, if we can discover why it was put there, 
and what went through it the night of the murder, I guess we'll 
have our man, all right!" 
</p><p>Elizabeth started violently and turned quickly, involuntarily 
keeping the hand that held the cigarette-case behind her. 
</p><p>The detective eyed her curiously. 
</p><p>"Have you found anything else?" he asked. 
</p><p>"Oh, no," answered Betty faintly. 
</p><p>Major Barry had joined them, and was standing beside her. 
At the man's words he, too, fastened his eyes on the girl's 
strained face. 
</p><p>"What have you in your hand?" demanded Grimes. 
</p><p>The blood receded from Betty's face, and she turned 
pleadingly to the major. 
</p><p>"Oh, nothing   &mdash;   nothing!  Tell him it isn't anything!" she 
begged piteously. 
</p><p>"Miss Crosby"   &mdash;   the detective spoke impressively   &mdash;   "in the name 
of the law, I ask you to tell me what you have found." 
</p><p>He stepped toward her, and Betty, slowly drawing her hand 
from behind her back, held out the cigarette-case.  Grimes seized 
it and examined it closely. 
</p><p>"Blood!" he exclaimed under his breath. 
</p><p>Where did you find it?" 
</p><p>"There," replied Betty in a hardly audible whisper, pointing 
to the bed. 
</p><p>"Slipped out of his pocket when he stooped over the girl!" 
mused Grimes.  He turned the case over, searching for a mark on 
it.  A monogram stood out in bold relief on the cover.  "C," he 
ruminated.  "Cary   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"No!  Not Cary!" Betty's words rang sharply through the room. 
</p><p>"Who, then?" asked Grimes quickly, his keen eyes fixed on her 
face. 
</p><p>Elizabeth did not answer, and the detective went back to his 
study of the letters. 
</p><p>"N, R, it looks to me; but I can't make it out for sure." 
</p><p>He held out the case to Major Barry for his corroboration; 
but the major shook his head. 
</p><p>"I haven't my glasses," he explained; "but I can see enough 
to know that the initials don't stand for Fairfax, which is Mr. 
Cary's name.  I think this discovery will let him out, don't 
you?" 
</p><p>Grimes shook his head doubtfully, evidently loath to let a 
victim escape out of his net until he had another to take the 
vacant place. 
</p><p>"Maybe," he assented; "but it ain't for me to say.  I'll take 
this to headquarters right off.  You're sure you don't know who 
it belongs to?" 
</p><p>He looked distrustingly at Betty, who shook her head. 
</p><p>"Will this be used as evidence?" she asked. 
</p><p>The detective nodded. 
</p><p>"It's mighty important evidence.  This and the dictograph are 
the best clues we've had yet, and we have you to thank for both 
of them, Miss Crosby.  I dare say they'll clear everything up." 
</p><p>The major put his hand through Betty's arm. 
</p><p>"Come," he said gently.  "Don't you think we might go now?" 
</p> 
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="17" id="d21"> 
<head>XVII</head> 
 
<p>With a hurried good-by to the detective, they passed into the 
hall.  Neither spoke as they walked through the deserted 
corridor, their footsteps echoing desolately against the closed 
doors.  It was only when they were alone in the taxi that Betty's 
self-control gave way.  She clutched the major's arm, her 
horror-stricken eyes devouring his face. 
</p><p>"Oh, Uncle Tod," she gasped, " did you recognize the 
cigarette-case?" 
</p><p>The major took her hand and began stroking it tenderly. 
</p><p>"There, there, my child," he said soothingly.  "You mustn't 
take it so to heart!  You'll make yourself ill!" 
<pb n="566"/>  
</p><p>"Oh, Uncle Tod, don't stop to think about me!  Do you know to 
whom it belongs?" 
</p><p>"Yes, I knew the initials." 
</p><p>Betty's hand tightened on his. 
</p><p>"What shall we do?  Oh, why did it have to be I who found 
it?" 
</p><p>"Nonsense, child; some one was bound to find it sooner or 
later.  As it happens, it is fortunate that it was you, for now 
we may be able to get the boy away before suspicion fastens on 
him.  Will you tell the Crosbys, or shall I?" 
</p><p>"I will, of course," replied Betty hurriedly.  "Oh, how 
ghastly, how awful for them!  Do you really think he did it?" 
</p><p>She looked almost pleadingly into the candid face beside her. 
The major pursed up his lips and stroked his gray mustache 
thoughtfully. 
</p><p>"It's hard to say positively, Betty, but the boy's record is 
against him." 
</p><p>Betty nodded, and once again a tremor passed over her. 
</p><p>"Poor Uncle George!" 
</p><p>Her eyes filled with tears.  Major Barry continued to stroke 
her hand, and began to tell her of the best course to be pursued 
to get Norman away.  He drew a glowing picture of the openings 
for young men in faroff lands, where the boy would be cut off 
from his old associates and temptations.  Gradually he led 
Betty's thoughts away from the horror of the situation, and she 
regained her self-possession. 
</p><p>But it was a very white, tremulous Betty who ascended the 
steps of her uncle's house, before which stood Norman's motor. 
As the major saw her disappear into the hall, he decided that he 
would follow her as soon as he had telephoned his discovery to 
Sturgis, who would convey the news to Cary. 
</p><p>Elizabeth went at once to the library, where she found Norman 
seated in a big chair with newspapers scattered around him.  At 
the sight of her white face he jumped to his feet and came 
quickly to her. 
</p><p>"Betty!" he exclaimed hoarsely.  "What is it?" 
</p><p>Steps sounded in the hall, and Norman glanced fearfully 
toward the door.  A look of relief came into his face as his 
father and mother appeared. 
</p><p>"Has anything been found?" he faltered in a low voice, his 
eyes fixed on Betty's face. 
</p><p>"You must go   &mdash;   quick, Norman, quick!  Don't stop to talk!" 
She was pushing him toward the door.  "Your cigarette-case   &mdash;   it 
was found in Molly Delaney's room.  Oh, Norman, hurry!  Hurry!" 
</p><p>He started toward the door, but Mrs. Crosby laid a 
restraining band on his arm. 
</p><p>"Norman!" she cried.  "What is it?" 
</p><p>He shook her off violently. 
</p><p>"Don't keep me!  They've found   &mdash;   they'll be here for   &mdash;   for   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>He vanished up the stairs. 
</p><p>"Who are they, and what are they coming for?" asked George 
Crosby irascibly, coming toward Betty. 
</p><p>Elizabeth pressed her hands tightly together, and her lips 
quivered. 
</p><p>"Oh, Uncle George!" she moaned, going to him and laying her 
hand gently on his arm.  "It's about Molly Delaney   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>Her voice trailed away into silence. 
</p><p>"Molly Delaney!  Do they connect my son with that?" 
</p><p>Betty did not answer, but the expression on her face seemed 
to give him all the information he needed.  He turned from her 
and, sinking into a big armchair, buried his head in his hands. 
Betty ran to him and put her hand on his shoulder. 
</p><p>"Oh, uncle dear!" she whispered. 
</p><p>A hurried step sounded in the hall, and Mrs. Crosby flew to 
the door. 
</p><p>"Good-by, my boy!" they heard her say. 
</p><p>George Crosby rose and with uncertain feet followed her. 
Betty walked beside him, watching him anxiously.  When they 
reached the hall be put his hand into his breast pocket and, 
drawing out his wallet, took out the money it contained. 
</p><p>"You'll need this," he said huskily, and thrust it into 
Norman's hand. 
</p><p>There was a hurried good-by, the front door opened and 
slammed, and the feverish throb of the motor sounded in their 
ears.  Swaying slightly, George Crosby turned again toward the 
library.  Betty put her arm through his and guided him back to 
the chair by the fire.  He fell into it, and his gray head 
dropped against the back.  Mrs. Crosby followed them and stopped 
beside them. 
</p><p>"What does it all mean?" she asked harshly, turning to Betty. 
</p><p>As gently as she could, Betty told them of the search of 
Molly's room and the resulting discovery. 
<pb n="567"/>  
</p><p>"Who found the cigarette-case?" 
</p><p>Mrs. Crosby's tone was sharp and quick.  Betty hesitated, and 
it seemed as if every drop of blood in her body had flowed back 
to her heart, leaving her numb and cold.  George Crosby raised 
his head and fixed haggard eyes upon her.  The silence closed in 
upon them like the crushing walls of an inquisitional room. 
</p><p>"Was it <hi rend="italic">you?"</hi> 
</p><p>Mrs. Crosby stepped menacingly toward Betty, who shrank from 
the look of implacable rage and hatred in her aunt's face. 
</p><p>"It <hi rend="italic">was</hi> you!" she breathed fiercely. 
</p><p>You   &mdash;   you   &mdash;   traitor!  Living in our house, taking advantage of 
information you got while we were saving you from starvation! 
And now   &mdash;   now"   &mdash;   her voice rose almost to a shriek   &mdash;   "you've hounded 
my boy out of his home!  God only knows where he can go!  Why did 
you do it?  You've brought nothing but misery to us!" 
</p><p>Under the lash of her aunt's words, Betty's eyes had widened 
until they looked like pools of dark water reflecting the 
storm-clouds above.  She wrung her hands piteously. 
</p><p>"I never thought   &mdash;   " she faltered. 
</p><p>"Never thought!  Never thought!" repeated her aunt angrily. 
"No, you never think of any one but yourself and that precious 
lover of yours!" 
</p><p>The scorn in her voice was biting, and it stung Betty beyond 
control. 
</p><p>"And my father!" she supplemented passionately. 
</p><p>"Your father?" sneered Mrs. Crosby. 
</p><p>"Yes!" repeated Betty in a strained voice which she hardly 
recognized as her own.  "If it had not been for the stigma on my 
father's name, I should never have felt justified in entering on 
this search.  As it was   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"And what did you find?" 
</p><p>Mrs. Crosby's thin lips were drawn back in a derisive smile. 
Betty hesitated, and her eyes wandered to the gray head resting 
on the back of the chair.  Her chin trembled a little. 
</p><p>"What did you find?" demanded Mrs. Crosby once more.  "In 
spite of the ruin you've brought on us, you've found nothing that 
clears your father's name, or ever will!" 
</p><p>Major Barry's immaculate figure appeared in the doorway. 
</p><p>"I think you're wrong there," he remarked quietly, after a 
searching look at Elizabeth's quivering face.  "We've been 
looking into Randolph's affairs a bit lately   &mdash;   some of his 
business associates and I   &mdash;   and we've discovered quite a number of 
things." 
</p><p>Mrs. Crosby's face blanched, the two brilliant spots of color 
standing out grotesquely on her cheeks.  George Crosby's eyes 
fixed themselves feverishly on the major's face. 
</p><p>"What do you mean?" 
</p><p>"I mean this, Mrs. Crosby   &mdash;   when Randolph died he left some 
very valuable stock, which has since been sold   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>George Crosby's hand tightened on the arm of his chair until 
even the nails showed white.  His face was livid. 
</p><p>"How do you know?" 
</p><p>"I know through one of the other directors of the concern, in 
which Randolph held a large interest.  This man has traced the 
sale of the stock."  He turned suddenly to George Crosby.  "Do 
you deny it?" 
</p><p>George Crosby sank even deeper into the big chair, and his 
hand went up to his sagging mouth.  Unable to meet the accusing 
eyes fixed on him, his head fell forward until his chin rested on 
his chest.  Betty took a hurried step forward. 
</p><p>"Uncle Tod, what is it?  I don't quite understand   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"My dear, it's simply this   &mdash;   your father died, as we all 
believed, a very rich man.  It is since his death that his money 
has been dissipated." 
</p><p>"Oh!"  The word was hardly more than a sigh.  "Who   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>"That's just it; who could have sacrificed your interests and 
betrayed your father's confidence?  Who had the power?" 
</p><p>Again the major's condemning eyes sought George Crosby's 
stricken figure. 
</p><p>"Uncle George, did you do this thing?"  Betty drew nearer and 
nearer to him, her eyes wide, her mouth quivering.  "You, whom my 
father loved and trusted?  Oh, tell me it isn't true!" 
</p><p>She sank down on her knees beside him and clutched his arm. 
There was a long silence. 
</p><p>"It is true!" came at length, in hollow tones, from the bowed 
head. 
</p><p>Betty drew back slowly, as if still loath to believe what she 
heard. 
<pb n="568"/>  
</p><p>"My father's brother!"  The words seemed drawn from her. 
"And he loved you! 
</p><p>The man before her shuddered. 
</p><p>"Betty!" he groaned.  "I didn't mean   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>As if in hope that he was about to disclaim his culpability, 
Betty stooped eagerly toward him; but he stopped abruptly, and 
once more the gray head fell forward.  A heavy silence wrapped 
itself about them, which at last Mrs. Crosby's harsh voice broke. 
</p><p>"Well, it's all out now!" she said violently.  "I suppose 
you'll send your uncle to join Norman in prison!" 
</p><p>Betty looked at her aunt as if her words were husks void of 
the grain of meaning.  Bending over her uncle's huddled form, she 
stroked his gray head tenderly; then she stooped over and kissed 
him. 
</p><p>"Uncle George, don't worry about it!" she whispered so softly 
that the words hardly reached the others.  "I'm sure it was all a 
mistake.  I don't believe it was for yourself you took the money. 
At all events, it will never make any difference between you and 
me." 
</p><p>A great sob shook the bent shoulders.  George Crosby caught 
her hand and held it to his lips.  Betty kissed him again, and 
then, holding out her hand to Major Barry, drew him out of the 
house. 
</p> 
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="18" id="d22"> 
<head>XVIII</head> 
 
<p>Major Barry's face was glowing with satisfaction as he sat in 
Cary's cell the next morning and rehearsed for his benefit the 
search in the Delaneys' rooms. 
</p><p>"I tell you, that little girl's a wonder, Fairfax!" he 
exclaimed.  "She was in a nasty fix there, with the evidence of 
her cousin's guilt, which she had found herself, in her hand. 
She naturally didn't want to implicate him, and yet she had to 
exonerate you.  I was sorry for the child." 
</p><p>The taut lines of Cary's face had relaxed in a tender smile. 
</p><p>"But you say she wouldn't let it go when the detective 
suggested that the `C' on the case stood for my name?" 
</p><p>The major laughed boyishly. 
</p><p>"No, sir!  She spoke up loud and clear then, all right!  Now, 
the next thing is to discover what was heard through that 
dictograph." 
</p><p>"That seems like an almost hopeless quest, now that Pat's 
gone," answered Fairfax gloomily. 
</p><p>Can't tell, my boy; luck's begun running for us now, and I 
wouldn't be surprised at anything.  It was too bad Sturgis 
couldn't arrange about bail yesterday.  I had hoped, when I 
telephoned, that you would be out last night." 
</p><p>"Apparently it couldn't be done.  There's always so much red 
tape in a case like this." 
</p><p>"I wanted to come down and tell you all about the discovery 
myself, but I knew Sturgis would give you the facts, and I really 
felt that I must go to the Crosbys'.  It was fortunate that I 
did, for that fiend, Maude Crosby, was at poor little Betty neck 
and crop, and, I think, would have rent her asunder if I hadn't 
turned up when I did.  She's a devil, that woman!"  The major's 
shoulders stiffened and his jaw snapped.  "I should like to see 
her brought to her knees!" 
</p><p>Again the tender smile stole over Cary's face. 
</p><p>"And Betty isn't going to bring action against her uncle?" 
</p><p>"Won't consider it for a minute," returned the major. 
"Nothing I could say or do would convince her that she is making 
a mistake.  She won't hear of a lawsuit." 
</p><p>"Well, after all, it's Betty's money, and she's the one to 
decide.  It isn't as if she will really need it now." 
</p><p>"No; there's comfort in that thought.  You're not going to 
let her go back to France, are you, Fairfax?" asked the major, 
eying the other man's face anxiously. 
</p><p>"She's not going out of this country for some time, if I have 
anything to say about it, and she seems to think I have, 
unless"   &mdash;   a light spread over Cary's face   &mdash;   "I can persuade her to 
take that trip to Bermuda that you suggested a while ago!" 
</p><p>"That would be great!  The sooner the better."  Major Barry 
glanced restlessly at his watch.  "It seems to me that Sturgis 
ought to be along pretty soon now." 
</p><p>A guard appeared at the door and unlocked it; but the man who 
was with him was not the alert, keen-eyed lawyer, but a slender 
youth with slack shoulders and narrow, furtive eyes.  The major 
looked inquiringly at Fairfax, who shook his head in answer to 
the unspoken question.  The boy slouched into the cell and 
touched the brim of his hat awkwardly. 
<pb n="569"/>  
</p><p>"Mr.  Cary," he began in a high, shrill voice, "you don't 
remember me, but I'm Jim   &mdash;   Jim Murphy.  I used ter work fer Mr. 
Crosby." 
</p><p>A sudden flash illumined Cary's memory, and he held out his 
hand cordially. 
</p><p>"Why, Jim!" he exclaimed.  "Of course I remember you!  You 
used to take care of Steadfast." 
</p><p>The boy grasped his hand and wrung it. 
</p><p>"I sure did, Mr. Cary!" 
</p><p>"Sit down, Jim, sit down; of course I remember you, and so 
does Major Barry, I'm sure."  The major nodded pleasantly to the 
boy, and Fairfax went on:  "Weren't you with Pat the night he 
died?  I seem to recall seeing you at the hotel." 
</p><p>He looked searchingly into Jim's face. 
</p><p>"Yes, sir; that's what I come ter see ye about.  I wuz with 
Pat till late that night." 
</p><p>Jim was sitting on the edge of his chair, nervously twisting 
his hat around in his big-knuckled hands. 
</p><p>"Then you came back after I went away?" 
</p><p>"Yes, sir." 
</p><p>"Was Molly alive when you left?"  The major asked the 
question eagerly, leaning far out of his seat. 
</p><p>"Yes, sir; she came in two or three times ter see how Pat wuz 
gettin' along." 
</p><p>Mr. Sturgis had arrived in time to hear the boy's words, and 
the three men looked at one another in undisguised pleasure. 
</p><p>"Well," exclaimed the major triumphantly to Fairfax, "that 
lets you out!  I wish we had known this before," he added, 
turning to Murphy. 
</p><p>"I'm sorry, sir, but I didn't know nothin' about what 
happened after I lef' till about a week ago.  The night Pat got 
smashed up I went to Texas with Mr. Vinton's horses.  We wuz on a 
ranch, and didn't often get the newspapers.  I wuz kind o' 
surprised that Molly didn't let me know how Pat wuz, but she an' 
I had had a row, and I s'posed she wuz too mad to write.  It wuz 
only when I had a letter from a friend of mine that I knew"   &mdash;   his 
voice faltered   &mdash;   "that they wuz both dead." 
</p><p>The muscles of his face twitched, and he put his big hand 
over his mouth. 
</p><p>"This is most important evidence!" announced the lawyer. 
</p><p>"I knowed it would be, sir.  I felt awful bad when I heard 
Mr. Cary wuz up fer murder, and I sez ter meself, `You fer the 
Great White Way, Jim!' an' I beats it right on. I should think 
any guy would know <hi rend="italic">he</hi> ain't done it   &mdash;   that is, if they knew him 
at all." 
</p><p>"Who did do it, Jim?" The major's voice was like cold steel. 
</p><p>"Well, when I went away, Mr. Crosby   &mdash;   Mr. Norman Crosby   &mdash;   was 
in the next room with Molly.  He'd been there all evenin', an' 
they'd been havin' it out hot an' heavy.  We could hear 'em, Pat 
an' I, even with the door shut, but we couldn't make out what 
they wuz sayin'.  Fer a long time Pat hadn't liked the way things 
wuz goin', so he rigged up one o' them dictograph things in 
Molly's room and strung the wires into his." 
</p><p>"What was it he suspected?" 
</p><p>The boy moistened his lips. 
</p><p>"He wanted ter find out about the Withers Stake   &mdash;   ye know, 
when Steadfast got licked?"  He glanced interrogatively at Major 
Barry, who nodded.  "Well," he went on, "I'd been givin' Pat some 
dope about what happened just before that race, when he went off 
ter dress, an' then Molly had let drop enough ter put him wise 
that somethin' wuz wrong.  I wuz in the stable all the time Pat 
wuz gone.  Mr. Norman an' Molly didn't know it, but I wuz in the 
stall just the other side of Steadfast's." 
</p><p>He stopped, and his face became ghastly. 
</p><p>"Why did you think   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>Jim swallowed hard. 
</p><p>"Molly an' me had been pals since we wuz kids, an' I wuz kind 
o' sore when she dropped me," he half whispered.  "I knowed Mr. 
Norman wuz rushin' her, an' I wanted ter find out how far things 
had gone, so I hid an' listened." 
</p><p>Jim's big hand clenched, and a red light gleamed in the 
deep-set eyes. 
</p><p>He wuz tellin' her that he loved her, an' he kissed her. 
Then he went inter Steadfast's stall, an' I heard Molly askin' 
him what he wuz doin'.  He said he wuz fixin' things so that he 
an' Molly could go off on a trip an' have a bang-up time.  It wuz 
after I told Pat that that he got the  dictograph; an' the night 
Pat died we heard the whole thing.  Molly told him that she'd 
seen him dope Steadfast, an' there wasn't no use in his denyin' 
it, an' she'd fix him, all right, if he didn't do as he'd 
promised an' marry her.  Pat made me write it all down.  He wuz 
pretty far in, an' he wuz <pb n="570"/> afraid he'd forget somethin'.  He 
said Mr. Cary had promised ter come back in the mornin', an' he 
wanted ter have it fer him.  So I wrote it down an' hid the paper 
under the cover o' the table by the bed, where Pat could reach 
it, an' where Molly wouldn't be apt ter find it.  Then I had ter 
go.  As it was, I nearly missed my train." 
</p><p>"Your testimony will be invaluable in clearing Mr. Cary," 
remarked Sturgis.  "We shall want you to repeat this in court." 
</p><p>"Yes, sir; that's what I come on fer.  I wasn't goin' ter let 
Mr. Cary be put out o' bizness fer what he ain't done.  Mr. 
Cary's on the level, sir!   He's all right, an' I couldn't stand 
by an' see him takin' what ought ter be comin' ter that   &mdash;   " 
</p><p>Jim stopped, and his nostrils quivered. 
</p> 
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="19" id="d23"> 
<head>XIX</head> 
 
<p>It was about four o'clock that afternoon that Fairfax Cary 
ran up the front steps of the Hunnewells' house.  When he entered 
the hall the air was vibrant with the rich chords of the 
"Nocturne in F."  He stood for a moment drinking in its tender 
harmonies.  Wave after wave of the music passed over him, pulsing 
through his veins into his heart, until at last it seemed as if 
his soul had been washed white from the prison taint which, even 
after he left the Tombs, had hovered over him with a sickening 
sense of impurity. 
</p><p>Stronger and more penetrating rose the music, with its 
swelling chords and haunting melody.  Fairfax pushed aside the 
portieres and stepped into the room.  The music stopped abruptly, 
and Betty, with a little cry, rose from the piano.  Her face 
turned very white. 
</p><p>"I didn't know   &mdash;   " she faltered. 
</p><p>He strode across the room and caught her in his arms. 
</p><p>"My dear, my dear!" she sobbed, clinging to him. 
</p><p>He held her to him, and kissed her hungrily with the pent-up 
passion of long months of waiting.  When he half released her to 
gaze into her eyes, he found them full of tears. 
</p><p>"Darling," he expostulated, "you're crying!" 
</p><p>The tears overflowed, and Betty buried her face in his 
shoulder. 
</p><p>"Of course I am!" she cried. 
</p><p>"Will you tell me why?" 
</p><p>"I haven't had time to cry in weeks," answered Betty 
tremulously.  "You don't suppose I could stop to cry when there 
was anything to do, do you?" 
</p><p>Cary's arms tightened around her, and he tenderly kissed the 
drops away. 
</p><p>"My darling!" he whispered.  "Tell me that you love me! " 
</p><p>But she pushed him away with a tremulous little laugh. 
</p><p>"I've been telling you so for weeks.  If you don't believe it 
now, you never will!" 
</p><p>She took his hand and led him to the sofa. 
</p><p>"I sha'n't feel sure of you until we're married," answered 
Fairfax.  "We can be very soon, can't we, dear?" 
</p><p>"I told you in France that I wouldn't marry any one till 
father's name had been cleared." 
</p><p>"Darling, it has been!  Jim Murphy, your father's stable-boy, 
came to see me this morning.  He saw Norman dope Steadfast before 
the Withers race.  Jim will swear to it in court." 
</p><p>"Norman!" exclaimed Betty.  "How dreadful!" 
</p><p>"Molly was with him, and it was after her threat to expose 
the whole thing that he killed her." 
</p><p>"How ghastly, Fairfax!  How perfectly dreadful!  Poor Uncle 
George!" 
</p><p>"So now, darling, you won't keep me waiting any longer, will 
you?" 
</p><p>Betty snuggled closer to him and laid her head on his 
shoulder. 
</p><p>"I'm ready now, as far I can be," she whispered softly.  "I 
can't get a big trousseau, Fairfax.  You know why, don't you, 
dear?  I haven't a cent in the world.  Do you realize that you're 
getting a penniless bride?" 
</p><p>She raised troubled eyes and anxiously studied his face. 
</p><p>Fairfax laughed boyishly. 
</p><p>"Really?" he teased.  "Then I can't marry you, my pretty 
maid!" 
</p><p>"I hate you!" and Betty pressed her lips to his. 
</p> 
<trailer> 
                              THE END
</trailer>
</div1> 
</body> 
<back id="d24"> 
<div1 type="notes" id="d25"> 
<note><p> 
EDITOR'S NOTE   &mdash;   It should have been stated in MUNSEY'S 
MAGAZINE for April last that three of the engravings printed in 
that issue   &mdash;   those on pages 385, 471, and 473.   &mdash;   were from 
photographs by Valentine &amp; Sons, Dundee.</p></note> 
</div1> 
</back> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
