<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="SteHome"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="SteHome">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Letters of a Woman Homesteader</title>
<title type="sort">letters of a woman homesteader</title>
<author>Stewart, Elinore Pruitt</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">266</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">SteHome</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476381</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Letters of a Woman Homesteader</title>
<title type="sort">letters of a woman homesteader</title>
<author>Elinore Pruitt Stewart</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st edition, 3rd printing</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Bison</publisher>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<date value="1967">1967</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>reprint of May 1914 Houghton Mifflin edition</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the
text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1847">1847</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1993-02">February 1993</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Peter J. Kastor, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia;</name>
</respStmt>
<item>TEI tagging, unabiguous line-ends removed</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="1994-08">August 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>updated header</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<front id="d2">

<div1 type="note" id="d3">

<pb n="x"/>

<p>The writer of the following letters is a young
woman who lost her husband in a railroad
accident and went to Denver to seek support
for herself and her two-year-old daughter,
Jerrine.  Turning her hand to the nearest
work, she went out by the day as house-cleaner and laundress.  Later, seeking to
better herself, she accepted employment as a
housekeeper for a well-to-do Scotch cattle-man, Mr. Stewart, who had taken up a
quarter-section in Wyoming.  The letters,
written through several years to a former
employer in Denver, tell the story of her new
life in the new country.  They are genuine
letters, and are printed as written, except for
occasional omissions and the alteration of
some of the names.   May 1914.
</p></div1>
<div1 type="contents" id="d4">
<pb n="xi"/>
	<head>CONTENTS</head>
<list>
<item>
    I.  THE ARRIVAL AT BURNT FORK. . . . . .   3</item><item>
   II.  FILING A CLAIM . . . . . . . . . . .   7</item><item>
  III.  A BUSY, HAPPY SUMMER . . . . . . . .  15</item><item>
   IV.  A CHARMING ADVENTURE AND ZEBULON
          PIKE . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .  23</item><item>
    V.  SEDALIA AND REGALIA. . . . . . . . .  45</item><item>
   VI.  A THANKSGIVING-DAY WEDDING . . . . .  54</item><item>
  VII.  ZEBULON PIKE VISITS HIS OLD HOME . .  60</item><item>
 VIII.  A HAPPY CHRISTMAS. . . . . . . . . .  64</item><item>
   IX.  A CONFESSION . . . . . . . . . . . .  77</item><item>
    X.  THE STORY OF CORA BELLE. . . . . . .  81</item><item>
   XI.  ZEBBIE'S STORY . . . . . . . . . . . 100</item><item>
  XII.  A CONTENTED COUPLE . . . . . . . . . 117</item><item>
 XIII.  PROVING UP . . . . . . . . . . . . . 133</item><item>
  XIV.  THE NEW HOUSE. . . . . . . . . . . . 137</item><item>
   XV.  THE "STOCKING-LEG" DINNER. . . . . . 143</item><item>
  XVI.  THE HORSE-THIEVES. . . . . . . . . . 157</item><item>
 XVII.  AT GAVOTTE'S CAMP. . . . . . . . . . 180</item>
<pb n="xii"/>
<item>
XVIII.  THE HOMESTEADER'S MARRIAGE AND
          LITTLE FUNERAL . . . . . . . . . . 184</item><item>
  XIX.  THE ADVENTURE OF THE CHRISTMAS</item><item>
          TREE . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 193</item><item>
   XX.  THE JOYS OF HOMESTEADING . . . . . . 213</item><item>
  XXI.  A LETTER OF JERRINE'S. . . . . . . . 218</item><item>
 XXII.  THE EFFICIENT MRS. O'SHAUGHNESSY . . 220</item><item>
XXIII.  HOW IT HAPPENED. . . . . . . . . . . 225</item><item>
 XXIV.  A LITTLE ROMANCE . . . . . . . . . . 230</item><item>
  XXV.  AMONG THE MORMONS. . . . . . . . . . 256</item><item>
 XXVI.  SUCCESS. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 279</item>
</list>

<pb n="3"/>

</div1>
</front>

<body id="d5">
<div1 type="chapter" n="1" id="d6">
<head> "THE ARRIVAL AT BURNT FORK"
"BURNT FORK, WYOMING," <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 18, 1909.</head>

<salute>
DEAR MRS. CONEY,&mdash;</salute>
<p>Are you thinking I am lost, like the Babes
in the Wood?  Well, I am not and I'm sure
the robins would have the time of their lives
getting leaves to cover me out here.  I am
'way up close to the Forest Reserve of Utah,
within half a mile of the line, sixty miles
from the railroad.  I was twenty-four hours
on the train and two days on the stage, and
oh, those two days!  The snow was just be-ginning to melt and the mud was about the
worst I ever heard of.
</p><p>The first stage we tackled was just about
<pb n="4"/>
as rickety as it could very well be and I had
to sit with the driver, who was a Mormon and
so handsome that I was not a bit offended
when he insisted on making love all the way,
especially after he told me that he was a
widower Mormon.  But, of course, as I had
no chaperone I looked very fierce (not that
that was very difficult with the wind and
mud as allies) and told him my actual opinion
of Mormons in general and particular.
</p><p>Meantime my new employer, Mr. Stewart,
sat upon a stack of baggage and was dreadfully
concerned about something he calls his
"Tookie," but I am unable to tell you what
that is.  The road, being so muddy, was full
of ruts and the stage acted as if it had the
hiccoughs and made us all talk as though we
were affected in the same way.  Once Mr.
Stewart asked me if I did not think it a "gey
duir trip."  I told him he could call it gay if
he wanted to, but it didn't seem very hilarious
to me.  Every time the stage struck
a rock or a rut Mr. Stewart would "hoot,"
<pb n="5"/>
until I began to wish we would come to a
hollow tree or a hole in the ground so he
could go in with the rest of the owls.
</p><p>At last we "arriv," and everything is just
lovely for me.  I have a very, very comfortable
situation and Mr. Stewart is absolutely
no trouble, for as soon as he has his meals he
retires to his room and plays on his bagpipe,
only he calls it his "bugpeep."  It is "The
Campbells are Coming," without variations,
at intervals all day long and from seven till
eleven at night.  Sometimes I wish they
would make haste and get here.
</p><p>There is a saddle horse especially for me
and a little shotgun with which I am to kill
sage chickens.  We are between two trout
streams, so you can think of me as being
happy when the snow is through melting and
the water gets clear.  We have the finest
flock of Plymouth Rocks and get so many
nice eggs.  It sure seems fine to have all the
cream I want after my town experiences.
Jerrine is making good use of all the good
<pb n="6"/>
things we are having.  She rides the pony to
water every day.
</p><p>I have not filed on my land yet because the
snow is fifteen feet deep on it, and I think
I would rather see what I am getting, so will
wait until summer.  They have just three seasons
here, winter and July and August.  We
are to plant our garden the last of May.
When it is so I can get around I will see about
land and find out all I can and tell you.
</p><p>I think this letter is about to reach thirty-secondly, so I will send you my sincerest love
and quit tiring you.  Please write me when
you have time.
</p><signed>
Sincerely yours,
<lb/>
ELINORE RUPERT.
</signed>
<pb n="7"/>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="2" id="d7">
<head>"FILING A CLAIM" <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 24, 1909</head>
<salute>
DEAR, DEAR MRS. CONEY,&mdash;
</salute>
<p>Well, I have filed on my land and am
now a bloated landowner.  I waited a long
time to even <hi rend="italic">see</hi> land in the reserve, and the
snow is yet too deep, so I thought that as
they have but three months of summer and
spring together and as I wanted the land for
a ranch anyway, perhaps I had better stay
in the valley.  So I have filed adjoining Mr.
Stewart and I am well pleased.  I have a
grove of twelve swamp pines on my place,
and I am going to build my house there.  I
thought it would be very romantic to live on
the peaks amid the whispering pines, but I
reckon it would be powerfully uncomfortable
also, and I guess my twelve can whisper
enough for me; and a dandy thing is, I have
all the nice snow-water I want; a small
<pb n="8"/>
stream runs right through the center of my
land and I am quite near wood.
</p><p>A neighbor and his daughter were going
to Green River, the county-seat, and said I
might go along, so I did, as I could file there
as well as at the land office; and oh, that
trip!  I had more fun to the square inch than
Mark Twain or Samantha Allen <hi rend="italic">ever</hi> provoked.
It took us a whole week to go and
come.  We camped out, of course, for in the
whole sixty miles there was but one house,
and going in that direction there is not a tree
to be seen, nothing but sage, sand, and sheep.
About noon the first day out we came near a
sheep-wagon, and stalking along ahead of us
was a lanky fellow, a herder, going home for
dinner.  Suddenly it seemed to me I should
starve if I had to wait until we got where we
had planned to stop for dinner, so I called
out to the man, "Little Bo-Peep, have you
anything to eat?  If you have, we'd like to
find it."  And he answered, "As soon as I am
able it shall be on the table, if you'll but
<pb n="9"/>
trouble to get behind it."  Shades of
Shakespeare!  Songs of David, the Shepherd Poet!
What do you think of us?  Well, we got behind
it, and a more delicious "it" I never
tasted.  Such coffee!  And out of <hi rend="italic">such</hi> a pot!  I
promised Bo-Peep that I would send him a
crook with pink ribbons on it, but I suspect
he thinks I am a crook without the ribbons.
</p><p>The sagebrush is so short in some places
that it is not large enough to make a fire, so
we had to drive until quite late before we
camped that night.  After driving all day
over what seemed a level desert of sand, we
came about sundown to a beautiful canon,
down which we had to drive for a couple of
miles before we could cross.  In the canon the
shadows had already fallen, but when we
looked up we could see the last shafts of sun-light on the tops of the great bare buttes.
Suddenly a great wolf started from somewhere
and galloped along the edge of the
canon, outlined black and clear by the setting
sun.  His curiosity overcame him at last,
<pb n="10"/>
so he sat down and waited to see what manner of
beast we were.  I reckon he was disappointed
for he howled most dismally.  I
thought of Jack London's "The Wolf."
</p><p>After we quitted the canon I saw the most
beautiful sight.  It seemed as if we were driving
through a golden haze.  The violet shadows were
creeping up between the hills, while
away back of us the snow-capped peaks were
catching the sun's last rays.  On every side
of us stretched the poor, hopeless desert, the
sage, grim and determined to live in spite
of starvation, and the great, bare, desolate
buttes.  The beautiful colors turned to amber
and rose, and then to the general tone, dull
gray.  Then we stopped to camp, and such a
scurrying around to gather brush for the fire
and to get supper!  Everything tasted so good!
Jerrine ate like a man.  Then we raised the
wagon tongue and spread the wagon sheet
over it and made a bedroom for us women.
We made our beds on the warm, soft sand
and went to bed.
<pb n="11"/>
</p><p>It was too beautiful a night to sleep, so I
put my head out to look and to think.  I saw
the moon come up and hang for a while over
the mountain as if it were discouraged with
the prospect, and the big white stars flirted
shamelessly with the hills.  I saw a coyote
come trotting along and I felt sorry for him,
having to hunt food in so barren a place, but
when presently I heard the whirr of wings I
felt sorry for the sage chickens he had disturbed.
At length a cloud came up and I
went to sleep, and next morning was covered
several inches with snow.  It didn't hurt us a
bit, but while I was struggling with stubborn
corsets and shoes I communed with myself,
after the manner of prodigals, and said:
"How much better that I were down in Denver,
even at Mrs. Coney's, digging with a
skewer into the corners seeking dirt which
<hi rend="italic">might</hi> be there, yea, even eating codfish, than
that I should perish on this desert&mdash;of imagination."
So I turned the current of my
imagination and fancied that I was at home
<pb n="12"/>
before the fireplace, and that the backlog
was about to roll down.  My fancy was in
such good working trim that before I knew it
I kicked the wagon wheel, and I certainly got
as warm as the most "sot" Scientist that
ever read Mrs. Eddy could possibly wish.
</p><p>After two more such days I "arrived."
When I went up to the office where I was to
file, the door was open and the most taciturn
old man sat before a desk.  I hesitated at the
door, but he never let on.  I coughed, yet no
sign but a deeper scowl.  I stepped in and
modestly kicked over a chair.  He whirled
around like I had shot him.  "Well?" he
interrogated.  I said, "I am powerful glad of it.
I was afraid you were sick, you looked in
such pain."  He looked at me a minute, then
grinned and said he thought I was a book-agent.  Fancy me, a fat, comfortable widow,
trying to sell books!
</p><p>Well, I filed and came home.  If you will
believe me, the Scot was glad to see me and
didn't herald the Campbells for two hours
<pb n="13"/>
after I got home.  I'll tell you, it is mighty
seldom any one's so much appreciated.
</p><p>No, we have no rural delivery.  It is two
miles to the office, but I go whenever I like.
It is really the jolliest kind of fun to gallop
down.  We are sixty miles from the railroad,
but when we want anything we send by the
mail-carrier for it, only there is nothing to
get.
</p><p>I know this is an inexcusably long letter,
but it is snowing so hard and you know how I
like to talk.  I am sure Jerrine will enjoy the
cards and we will be glad to get them.  Many
things that are a comfort to us out here came
from dear Mrs. &mdash;.  Baby has the rabbit
you gave her last Easter a year ago.  In Denver
I was afraid my baby would grow up
devoid of imagination.  Like all the kindergartners,
she depended upon others to amuse
her.  I was very sorry about it, for my castles
in Spain have been real homes to me.  But
there is no fear.  She has a block of wood she
found in the blacksmith shop which she calls
<pb n="14"/>
her "dear baby."  A spoke out of a wagon
wheel is "little Margaret," and a barrel-stave is "bad little Johnny."
</p><p>Well, I must quit writing before you vote
me a nuisance.  With lots of love to you,
</p>
<signed>Your sincere friend,
<lb/>
ELINORE RUPERT.
</signed>

<pb n="15"/>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="3" id="d8">
<head> "A BUSY, HAPPY SUMMER" <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 11, 1909.</head>
<salute>
DEAR MRS. CONEY,&mdash;
</salute>
<p>This has been for me the busiest, happiest
summer I can remember.  I have worked
very hard, but it has been work that I really
enjoy.  Help of any kind is very hard to get
here, and Mr. Stewart had been too confident
of getting men, so that haying caught him
with too few men to put up the hay.  He had
no man to run the mower and he couldn't
run both the mower and the stacker, so you
can fancy what a place he was in.
</p><p>I don't know that I ever told you, but my
parents died within a year of each other and
left six of us to shift for ourselves.  Our people
offered to take one here and there among
them until we should all have a place, but
we refused to be raised on the halves and so
<pb n="16"/>
arranged to stay at Grandmother's and keep
together.  Well, we had no money to hire men
to do our work, so had to learn to do it ourselves.
Consequently I learned to do many
things which girls more fortunately situated
don't even know have to be done.  Among
the things I learned to do was the way to run
a mowing-machine.  It cost me many bitter
tears because I got sunburned, and my hands
were hard, rough, and stained with machine
oil, and I used to wonder how any Prince
Charming could overlook all that in any girl
he came to.  For all I had ever read of the
Prince had to do with his "reverently kissing
her lily-white hand," or doing some other fool
trick with a hand as white as a snowflake.
Well, when my Prince showed up he didn't
lose much time in letting me know that
"Barkis was willing," and I wrapped my
hands in my old checked apron and took him
up before he could catch his breath.  Then
there was no more mowing, and I almost forgot
that I knew how until Mr. Stewart got
<pb n="17"/>
into such a panic.  If he put a man to mow, it
kept them all idle at the stacker, and he just
couldn't get enough men.  I was afraid to
tell him I could mow for fear he would forbid
me to do so.  But one morning, when he was
chasing a last hope of help, I went down to
the barn, took out the horses, and went to
mowing.  I had enough cut before he got
back to show him I knew how, and as he
came back manless he was delighted as well
as surprised.  I was glad because I really like
to mow, and besides that, I am adding feathers
to my cap in a surprising way.  When you
see me again you will think I am wearing a
feather duster, but it is only that I have been
said to have almost as much sense as a
"mon," and that is an honor I never aspired
to, even in my wildest dreams.
</p><p>I have done most of my cooking at night,
have milked seven cows every day, and have
done all the hay-cutting, so you see I have
been working.  But I have found time to put
up thirty pints of jelly and the same amount
<pb n="18"/>
of jam for myself.  I used wild fruits, gooseberries,
currants, raspberries, and cherries.  I
have almost two gallons of the cherry butter,
and I think it is delicious.  I wish I could get
some of it to you, I am sure you would like it.
</p><p>We began haying July 5 and finished September
8.  After working so hard and so
steadily I decided on a day off, so yesterday
I saddled the pony, took a few things I
needed, and Jerrine and I fared forth.  Baby
can ride behind quite well.  We got away by
sunup and a glorious day we had.  We followed
a stream higher up into the mountains
and the air was so keen and clear at first
we had on our coats.  There was a tang of
sage and of pine in the air, and our horse was
midside deep in rabbit-brush, a shrub just
covered with flowers that look and smell
like goldenrod.  The blue distance promised
many alluring adventures, so we went along
singing and simply gulping in summer.
Occasionally a bunch of sage chickens would fly
up out of the sagebrush, or a jack rabbit
<pb n="19"/>
would leap out.  Once we saw a bunch of
antelope gallop over a hill, but we were out
just to be out, and game didn't tempt us.  I
started, though, to have just as good a time as
possible, so I had a fish-hook in my knapsack.
</p><p>Presently, about noon, we came to a little
dell where the grass was as soft and as green
as a lawn.  The creek kept right up against
the hills on one side and there were groves
of quaking asp and cottonwoods that made
shade, and service-bushes and birches that
shut off the ugly hills on the other side.  We
dismounted and prepared to noon.  We
caught a few grasshoppers and I cut a birch
pole for a rod.  The trout are so beautiful now,
their sides are so silvery, with dashes of old
rose and orange, their speckles are so black,
while their backs look as if they had been
sprinkled with gold-dust.  They bite so well
that it doesn't require any especial skill or
tackle to catch plenty for a meal in a few
minutes.
</p><p>In a little while I went back to where I had
<pb n="20"/>
left my pony browsing, with eight beauties.
We made a fire first, then I dressed my trout
while it was burning down to a nice bed of
coals.  I had brought a frying-pan and a
bottle of lard, salt, and buttered bread.  We
gathered a few service-berries, our trout were
soon browned, and with water, clear, and as
cold as ice, we had a feast.  The quaking
aspens are beginning to turn yellow, but no
leaves have fallen.  Their shadows dimpled
and twinkled over the grass like happy children.
The sound of the dashing, roaring
water kept inviting me to cast for trout, but
I didn't want to carry them so far, so we
rested until the sun was getting low and then
started for home, with the song of the locusts
in our ears warning us that the melancholy
days are almost here.  We would come up
over the top of a hill into the glory of a
beautiful sunset with its gorgeous colors,
then down into the little valley already purpling
with mysterious twilight.  So on, until,
just at dark, we rode into our corral and a
<pb n="21"/>
mighty tired, sleepy little girl was powerfully
glad to get home.
</p><p>After I had mailed my other letter I was
afraid that you would think me plumb bold
about the little Bo-Peep, and was a heap
sorrier than you can think.  If you only knew
the hardships these poor men endure.  They
go two together and sometimes it is months
before they see another soul, and rarely ever
a woman.  I wouldn't act so free in town, but
these men see people so seldom that they are
awkward and embarrassed.  I like to put
them at ease, and it is to be done only by
being kind of hail-fellow-well-met with them.
So far not one has ever misunderstood me
and I have been treated with every courtesy
and kindness, so I am powerfully glad you
understand.  They really enjoy doing these
little things like fixing our dinner, and if my
poor company can add to any one's pleasure
I am too glad.
</p><p>Sincerely yours,
</p><p>ELINORE RUPERT.
<pb n="22"/>
</p><p>Mr. Stewart is going to put up my house
for me in pay for my extra work.
</p><p>I am ashamed of my long letters to you,
but I am such a murderer of language that I
have to use it all to tell anything.
</p><p>Please don't entirely forget me.  Your
letters mean so much to me and I will try to
answer more promptly.
<pb n="23"/>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="4" id="d9">
<head>
"A CHARMING ADVENTURE AND ZEBULON PIKE"
<hi rend="italic">September</hi> 28, 1909.</head>
<salute>
DEAR MRS. CONEY,&mdash;
</salute>
<p>Your second card just reached me and I
am plumb glad because, although I answered
your other, I was wishing I could write you,
for I have had the most charming adventure.
</p><p>It is the custom here for as many women
as care to to go in a party over into Utah to
Ashland (which is over a hundred miles away)
after fruit.  They usually go in September,
and it takes a week to make the trip.  They
take wagons and camp out and of course
have a good time, but, the greater part of the
way, there isn't even the semblance of a road
and it is merely a semblance anywhere.  They
came over to invite me to join them.  I was of
two minds&mdash;I wanted to go, but it seemed
a little risky and a big chance for discomfort,
<pb n="24"/>
since we would have to cross the Uinta
Mountains, and a snowstorm likely any
time.  But I didn't like to refuse outright, so
we left it to Mr. Stewart.  His "Ye're nae
gang" sounded powerful final, so the ladies
departed in awed silence and I assumed a
martyr-like air and acted like a very much
abused woman, although he did only what I
wanted him to do.  At last, in sheer desperation
he told me the "bairn canna stand the
treep," and that was why he was so determined.
I knew why, of course, but I continued to
look abused lest he gets it into his
head that he can boss me.  After he had been
reduced to the proper plane of humility and
had explained and begged my pardon and
had told me to consult only my own pleasure
about going and coming and using his horses,
only not to "expoose" the bairn, why, I forgave
him and we were friends once more.
</p><p>Next day all the men left for the round-up, to be gone a week.  I knew I never could
stand myself a whole week.  In a little while
<pb n="25"/>
the ladies came past on their way to Ashland.
They were all laughing and were so happy
that I really began to wish I was one of the
number, but they went their way and I kept
wanting to go <hi rend="italic">somewhere</hi>.  I got reckless and
determined to do something real bad.  So I
went down to the barn and saddled Robin
Adair, placed a pack on "Jeems McGregor,"
then Jerrine and I left for a camping-out
expedition.
</p><p>It was nine o'clock when we started and
we rode hard until about four, when I turned
Robin loose, saddle and all, for I knew he
would go home and some one would see him
and put him into the pasture.  We had gotten
to where we couldn't ride anyway, so I put
Jerrine on the pack and led "Jeems" for
about two hours longer; then, as I had come
to a good place to camp, we stopped.
</p><p>While we had at least two good hours of
daylight, it gets so cold here in the evening
that fire is very necessary.  We had been
climbing higher into the mountains all day
<pb n="26"/>
and had reached a level tableland where the
grass was luxuriant and there was plenty of
wood and water.  I unpacked "Jeems" and
staked him out, built a roaring fire, and made
our bed in an angle of a sheer wall of rock
where we would be protected against the
wind.  Then I put some potatoes into the
embers, as Baby and I are both fond of
roasted potatoes.  I started to a little spring
to get water for my coffee when I saw a
couple of jack rabbits playing, so I went
back for my little shotgun.  I shot one of the
rabbits, so I felt very like Leather-stocking
because I had killed but one when I might
have gotten two.  It was fat and young, and
it was but the work of a moment to dress it
and hang it up on a tree.  Then I fried some
slices of bacon, made myself a cup of coffee,
and Jerrine and I sat on the ground and ate.
Everything smelled and tasted so good!  This
air is so tonic that one gets delightfully
hungry.  Afterward we watered and restaked
"Jeems," I rolled some logs on to the fire,
<pb n="27"/>
and then we sat and enjoyed the prospect.
</p><p>The moon was so new that its light was
very dim, but the stars were bright.  Presently
a long, quivering wail arose and was
answered from a dozen hills.  It seemed just
the sound one ought to hear in such a place.
When the howls ceased for a moment we
could hear the subdued roar of the creek and
the crooning of the wind in the pines.  So we
rather enjoyed the coyote chorus and were
not afraid, because they don't attack people.
Presently we crept under our Navajos and,
being tired, were soon asleep.
</p><p>I was awakened by a pebble striking my
cheek.  Something prowling on the bluff
above us had dislodged it and it struck me.
By my Waterbury it was four o'clock, so I
arose and spitted my rabbit.  The logs had
left a big bed of coals, but some ends were
still burning and had burned in such a manner
that the heat would go both under and
over my rabbit.  So I put plenty of bacon
<pb n="28"/>
grease over him and hung him up to roast.
Then I went back to bed.  I didn't want to
start early because the air is too keen for
comfort early in the morning.
</p><p>The sun was just gilding the hilltops when
we arose.  Everything, even the barrenness,
was beautiful.  We have had frosts, and the
quaking aspens were a trembling field of gold
as far up the stream as we could see.  We
were 'way up above them and could look far
across the valley.  We could see the silvery
gold of the willows, the russet and bronze of
the currants, and patches of cheerful green
showed where the pines were.  The splendor
was relieved by a background of sober gray-green hills, but even on them gay streaks
and patches of yellow showed where rabbit-brush grew.  We washed our faces at the
spring,&mdash;the grasses that grew around the
edge and dipped into the water were loaded
with ice,&mdash;our rabbit was done to a turn,
so I made some delicious coffee, Jerrine got
herself a can of water, and we breakfasted.
<pb n="29"/>
Shortly afterwards we started again.  We
didn't know where we were going, but we
were on our way.
</p><p>That day was more toilsome than the last,
but a very happy one.  The meadowlarks
kept singing like they were glad to see us.
But we were still climbing and soon got beyond
the larks and sage chickens and up into
the timber, where there are lots of grouse.
We stopped to noon by a little lake, where I
got two small squirrels and a string of trout.
We had some trout for dinner and salted the
rest with the squirrels in an empty can for
future use.  I was anxious to get a grouse and
kept close watch, but was never quick enough.
Our progress was now slower and more difficult,
because in places we could scarcely get
through the forest.  Fallen trees were
everywhere and we had to avoid the branches,
which was powerful hard to do.  Besides, it
was quite dusky among the trees long before
night, but it was all so grand and awe-inspiring.  Occasionally there was an opening
<pb n="30"/>
through which we could see the snowy peaks,
seemingly just beyond us, toward which we
were headed.  But when you get among such
grandeur you get to feel how little you are
and how foolish is human endeavor, except
that which reunites us with the mighty force
called God.  I was plumb uncomfortable,
because all my own efforts have always been
just to make the best of everything and to
take things as they come.
</p><p>At last we came to an open side of the
mountain where the trees were scattered.
We were facing south and east, and the mountain
we were on sheered away in a dangerous
slant.  Beyond us still greater wooded mountains
blocked the way, and in the canon
between night had already fallen.  I began to
get scary.  I could only think of bears and
catamounts, so, as it was five o'clock, we
decided to camp.  The trees were immense.
The lower branches came clear to the ground
and grew so dense that any tree afforded a
splendid shelter from the weather, but I was
<pb n="31"/>
nervous and wanted one that would protect
us against any possible attack.  At last
we found one growing in a crevice of what
seemed to be a sheer wall of rock.  Nothing
could reach us on two sides, and in front two
large trees had fallen so that I could make a
log heap which would give us warmth and
make us safe.  So with rising spirits I unpacked
and prepared for the night.  I soon
had a roaring fire up against the logs and,
cutting away a few branches, let the heat
into as snug a bedroom as any one could wish.
The pine needles made as soft a carpet as
the wealthiest could afford.  Springs abound
in the mountains, so water was plenty.  I
staked "Jeems" quite near so that the fire-light would frighten away any wild thing
that tried to harm him.  Grass was very
plentiful, so when he was made "comfy" I
made our bed and fried our trout.  The
branches had torn off the bag in which I
had my bread, so it was lost in the forest,
but who needs bread when they have good,
<pb n="32"/>
mealy potatoes?  In a short time we were
eating like Lent was just over.  We lost all
the glory of the sunset except what we got by
reflection, being on the side of the mountain
we were, with the dense woods between.  Big
sullen clouds kept drifting over and a wind
got lost in the trees that kept them rocking
and groaning in a horrid way.  But we were
just as cozy as we could be and rest was as
good as anything.
</p><p>I wish you could once sleep on the kind of
bed we enjoyed that night.  It was both soft
and firm, with the clean, spicy smell of the
pine.  The heat from our big fire came in and
we were warm as toast.  It was so good to
stretch out and rest.  I kept thinking how
superior I was since I dared to take such an
outing when so many poor women down in
Denver were bent on making their twenty
cents per hour in order that they could spare a
quarter to go to the "show."  I went to sleep
with a powerfully self-satisfied feeling, but I
awoke to realize that pride goeth before a fall.
<pb n="33"/>
</p><p>I could hardly remember where I was when
I awoke, and I could almost hear the silence.
Not a tree moaned, not a branch seemed to
stir.  I arose and my head came in violent
contact with a snag that was not there when
I went to bed.  I thought either I must have
grown taller or the tree shorter during the
night.  As soon as I peered out, the mystery
was explained.
</p><p>Such a snowstorm I never saw!  The snow
had pressed the branches down lower, hence
my bumped head.  Our fire was burning
merrily and the heat kept the snow from in
front.  I scrambled out and poked up the fire;
then, as it was only five o'clock, I went back
to bed.  And then I began to think how many
kinds of idiot I was.  Here I was thirty or
forty miles from home, in the mountains
where no one goes in the winter and where I
knew the snow got to be ten or fifteen feet
deep.  But I could never see the good of moping,
so I got up and got breakfast while Baby
put her shoes on.  We had our squirrels and
<pb n="34"/>
more baked potatoes and I had delicious
black coffee.
</p><p>After I had eaten I felt more hopeful.  I
knew Mr. Stewart would hunt for me if he
knew I was lost.  It was true, he wouldn't
know which way to start, but I determined
to rig up "Jeems" and turn him loose, for I
knew he would go home and that he would
leave a trail so that I could be found.  I
hated to do so, for I knew I should always
have to be powerfully humble afterwards.
Anyway it was still snowing, great, heavy
flakes; they looked as large as dollars.  I
didn't want to start "Jeems" until the snow
stopped because I wanted him to leave a
clear trail.  I had sixteen loads for my gun
and I reasoned that I could likely kill enough
food to last twice that many days by being
careful what I shot at.  It just kept snowing,
so at last I decided to take a little hunt and
provide for the day.  I left Jerrine happy
with the towel rolled into a baby, and went
along the brow of the mountain for almost
<pb n="35"/>
a mile, but the snow fell so thickly that I
couldn't see far.  Then I happened to look
down into the canon that lay east of us and
saw smoke.  I looked toward it a long time,
but could make out nothing but smoke, but
presently I heard a dog bark and I knew I
was near a camp of some kind.  I resolved to
join them, so went back to break my own
camp.
</p><p>At last everything was ready and Jerrine
and I both mounted.  Of all the times!  If
you think there is much comfort, or even
security, in riding a pack-horse in a snow-storm over mountains where there is no road,
you are plumb wrong.  Every once in a while
a tree would unload its snow down our backs.
"Jeems" kept stumbling and threatening to
break our necks.  At last we got down the
mountain-side, where new danger confronted
us,&mdash;we might lose sight of the smoke or
ride into a bog.  But at last, after what
seemed hours, we came into a "clearing"
with a small log house and, what is rare in
<pb n="36"/>
Wyoming, a fireplace.  Three or four hounds
set up their deep baying, and I knew by
the chimney and the hounds that it was the
home of a Southerner.  A little old man came
bustling out, chewing his tobacco so fast, and
almost frantic about his suspenders, which it
seemed he couldn't get adjusted.
</p><p>As I rode up, he said, "Whither, friend?"
I said, "Hither."  Then he asked, "Air you
spying around for one of them dinged game
wardens arter that deer I killed yisteddy?"
I told him I had never even seen a game
warden and that I didn't know he had killed
a deer.  "Wall," he said, "air you spying
around arter that gold mine I diskivered
over on the west side of Baldy?"  But after
a while I convinced him that I was no more
nor less than a foolish woman lost in the
snow.  Then he said, "Light, stranger, and
look at your saddle."  So I "lit" and looked,
and then I asked him what part of the South
he was from.  He answered, "Yell County,
by gum!  The best place in the United States,
<pb n="37"/>
or in the world, either."  That was my introduction
to Zebulon Pike Parker.
</p><p>Only two "Johnny Rebs" could have
enjoyed each other's company as Zebulon
Pike and myself did.  He was so small and
so old, but so cheerful and so sprightly, and
a real Southerner!  He had a big, open fire-place with backlogs and andirons.  How I
enjoyed it all!  How we feasted on some of the
deer killed "yisteddy," and real corn-pone
baked in a skillet down on the hearth.  He
was so full of happy recollections and had a
few that were not so happy!  He is, in some
way, a kinsman of Pike of Pike's Peak fame,
and he came west "jist arter the wah" on
some expedition and "jist stayed."  He told
me about his home life back in Yell County,
and I feel that I know all the "young
uns."
</p><p>There was George Henry, his only brother;
and there were Phoebe and "Mothie," whose
real name is Martha; and poor little Mary
Ann, whose death was described so feelingly
<pb n="38"/>
that no one could keep back the tears.  Lastly
there was little Mandy, the baby and his
favorite, but who, I am afraid, was a selfish
little beast since she had to have her
prunellas when all the rest of the "young uns"
had to wear shoes that old Uncle Buck made
out of rawhide.  But then "her eyes were blue
as morning-glories and her hair was jist like
corn-silk, so yaller and fluffy."  Bless his
simple, honest heart!  His own eyes are blue
and kind, and his poor, thin little shoulders
are so round that they almost meet in front.
How he loved to talk of his boyhood days!
I can almost see his father and George Henry
as they marched away to the "wah" together,
and the poor little mother's despair
as she waited day after day for some word,
that never came.
</p><p>Poor little Mary Ann was drowned in the
bayou, where she was trying to get waterlilies.
She had wanted a white dress all
her life and so, when she was dead, they
took down the white cross-bar curtains and
<pb n="39"/>
Mother made the little shroud by the light
of a tallow dip.  But, being made by hand,
it took all the next day, too, so that they
buried her by moonlight down back of the
orchard under the big elm where the children
had always had their swing.  And they lined
and covered her grave with big fragrant
water-lilies.  As they lowered the poor little
home-made coffin into the grave the mockingbirds
began to sing and they sang all
that dewy, moonlight night.  Then little
Mandy's wedding to Judge Carter's son Jim
was described.  She wore a "cream-colored
poplin with a red rose throwed up in it,"
and the lace that was on Grandma's wedding
dress.  There were bowers of sweet
Southern roses and honeysuckle and wistaria.
Don't you know she was a dainty
bride?
</p><p>At last it came out that he had not heard
from home since he left it.  "Don't you ever
write?" I asked.  "No, I am not an eddicated
man, although I started to school.
<pb n="40"/>
Yes'm, I started along of the rest, but they
told me it was a Yankee teacher and I was
'fraid, so when I got most to the schoolhouse
I hid in the bushes with my spelling-book, so
that is all the learning I ever got.  But my
mother was an eddicated woman, yes'm, she
could both read and write.  I have the Bible
she give me yit.  Yes'm, you jist wait and
I'll show you."  After some rummaging in
a box he came back with a small leather-bound Bible with print so small it was hard
to read.  After turning to the record of births
and deaths he handed it to me, his wrinkled
old face shining with pride as he said, "There,
my mother wrote that with her own hand."
I took the book and after a little deciphered
that "Zebulon Pike Parker was born Feb.
10, 1830," written in the stiff, difficult style
of long ago and written with pokeberry ink.
He said his mother used to read about some
"old feller that was jist covered with biles,"
so I read Job to him, and he was full of surprise
they didn't "git some cherry bark and
<pb n="41"/>
some sasparilly and bile it good and gin it to
him."
</p><p>He had a side room to his cabin, which was
his bedroom; so that night he spread down
a buffalo robe and two bearskins before
the fire for Jerrine and me.  After making
sure there were no moths in them, I spread
blankets over them and put a sleepy, happy
little girl to bed, for he had insisted on making
molasses candy for her because they happened
to be born on the same day of the
month.  And then he played the fiddle until
almost one o'clock.  He played all the simple,
sweet, old-time pieces, in rather a squeaky,
jerky way, I am afraid, but the music suited
the time and the place.
</p><p>Next morning he called me early and when
I went out I saw such a beautiful sunrise,
well worth the effort of coming to see.  I had
thought his cabin in a canon, but the snow
had deceived me, for a few steps from the
door the mountains seemed to drop down
suddenly for several hundred feet and the
<pb n="42"/>
first of the snow peaks seemed to lie right at
our feet.  Around its base is a great swamp,
in which the swamp pines grow very thickly
and from which a vapor was rising that got
about halfway up the snow peak all around.
Fancy to yourself a big jewel-box of dark
green velvet lined with silver chiffon, the
snow peak lying like an immense opal in its
center and over all the amber light of a new
day.  That is what it looked most like.
</p><p>Well, we next went to the corral, where I
was surprised to find about thirty head of
sheep.  Some of them looked like they should
have been sold ten years before.  "Don't
you ever sell any of your sheep?" I asked.
"No'm.  There was a feller come here once
and wanted to buy some of my wethers, but
I wouldn't sell any because I didn't need
any money."  Then he went from animal to
animal, caressing each and talking to them,
calling them each by name.  He milked his
one cow, fed his two little mules, and then
we went back to the house to cook breakfast.
<pb n="43"/>
We had delicious venison steak, smoking
hot, and hoe-cakes and the "bestest" coffee,
and honey.
</p><p>After breakfast we set out for home.  Our
pack transferred to one of the little mules,
we rode "Jeems," and Mr. Parker rode the
other mule.  He took us another way, down
canon after canon, so that we were able to
ride all the time and could make better
speed.  We came down out of the snow and
camped within twelve miles of home in an
old, deserted ranch house.  We had grouse
and sage chicken for supper.  I was so anxious
to get home that I could hardly sleep,
but at last I did and was only awakened by
the odor of coffee, and barely had time to
wash before Zebulon Pike called breakfast.
Afterwards we fixed "Jeems's" pack so that
I could still ride, for Zebulon Pike was very
anxious to get back to his "critters."
</p><p>Poor, lonely, childlike little man!  He
tried to tell me how glad he had been to
entertain me.  "Why," he said, "I was
<pb n="44"/>
plumb glad to see you and right sorry to have
you go.  Why, I would jist as soon talk to
you as to a nigger.  Yes'm, I would.  It has
been almost as good as talking to old Aunt
Dilsey."  If a Yankee had said the same to
me I would have demanded instant apology,
but I know how the Southern heart longs for
the dear, kindly old "niggers," so I came on
homeward, thankful for the first time that I
can't talk correctly.
</p><p>I got home at twelve and found, to my joy,
that none of the men had returned, so I
am safe from their superiority for a while, at
least.
</p><p>With many apologies for this outrageous
letter, I am</p>
<p>Your ex-Washlady,
</p><p>ELINORE RUPERT.</p>
<pb n="45"/>
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="5" id="d10">
<head>"SEDALIA AND REGALIA"
<hi rend="italic">November</hi> 22, 1909.</head>
<salute>
MY DEAR FRIEND,&mdash;
</salute>
<p>I was dreadfully afraid that my last letter
was too much for you and now I feel plumb
guilty.  I really don't know how to write you,
for I have to write so much to say so little,
and now that my last letter made you sick I
almost wish so many things didn't happen
to me, for I always want to tell you.  Many
things have happened since I last wrote, and
Zebulon Pike is not done for by any means,
but I guess I will tell you my newest experience.
</p><p>I am making a wedding dress.  Don't grin;
it isn't mine,&mdash;worse luck!  But I must
begin at the beginning.  Just after I wrote
you before, there came a terrific storm which
made me appreciate indoor coziness, but as
<pb n="46"/>
only Baby and I were at home I expected to
be very lonely.  The snow was just whirling
when I saw some one pass the window.  I
opened the door and in came the dumpiest
little woman and two daughters.  She asked
me if I was "Mis' Rupit."  I told her that
she had almost guessed it, and then she
introduced herself.  She said she was "Mis'
Lane," that she had heard there was a new
stranger in the country, so she had brought
her twin girls, Sedalia and Regalia, to be
neighborly.  While they were taking off their
many coats and wraps it came out that they
were from Linwood, thirty miles away.  I was
powerful glad I had a pot roast and some
baked beans.
</p><p>After we had put the horses in the barn
we had dinner and I heard the story of the
girls' odd names.  The mother is one of those
"comfy," fat little women who remain happy
and bubbling with fun in spite of hard knocks.
I had already fallen in love with Regalia, she
is so jolly and unaffected, so fat and so plain.
<pb n="47"/>
Sedalia has a veneer of almost uncomfortable
refinement.  She was shocked because Gale
ate all the roast she wanted, and if I had been
very sensitive I would have been in tears,
because I ate a helping more than Gale did.
</p><p>But about the names.  It seemed that
"Mis' Lane" married quite young, was an
orphan, and had no one to tell her things she
should have known.  She lived in Missouri,
but about a year after her marriage the
young couple started overland for the West.
It was in November, and one night when
they had reached the plains a real blue
blizzard struck them.  "Mis' Lane" had been
in pain all day and soon she knew what was
the matter.  They were alone and it was a
day's travel back to the last house.  The
team had given out and the wind and sleet
were seeing which could do the most
meanness.  At last the poor man got a fire started
and a wagon sheet stretched in such a manner
that it kept off the sleet.  He fixed a bed
under the poor shelter and did all he could to
<pb n="48"/>
keep the fire from blowing away, and there,
a few hours later, a little girl baby was born.
They melted sleet in the frying-pan to get
water to wash it.  "Mis' Lane" kept feeling
no better fast, and about the time they got
the poor baby dressed a second little one
came.
</p><p>That she told me herself is proof she didn't
die, I guess, but it is right hard to believe
she didn't.  Luckily the fire lasted until the
babies were dressed and the mother began to
feel better, for there was no wood.  Soon the
wind stopped and the snow fell steadily.  It
was warmer, and the whole family snuggled
up under the wagon sheet and slept.
</p><p>Mr. Lane is a powerful good husband.
He waited two whole days for his wife to
gain strength before he resumed the journey,
and on the third morning he actually carried
her to the wagon.  Just think of it!  Could
more be asked of any man?
</p><p>Every turn of the wheels made poor "Mis'
Lane" more homesick.  Like Mrs. Wiggs of
<pb n="49"/>
the Cabbage Patch, she had a taste for
geographical names, and "Mis' Lane" is very
loyal, so she wanted to call the little first-born "Missouri."  Mr. Lane said she might,
but that if she did he would call the other one
"Arkansas."  Sometimes homesickness would
almost master her.  She would hug up the
little red baby and murmur "Missouri," and
then daddy would growl playfully to "Arkansas."
It went on that way for a long time
and at last she remembered that Sedalia was
in Missouri, so she felt glad and really named
the older baby "Sedalia."  But she could
think of nothing to match the name and was
in constant fear the father would name the
other baby "Little Rock."
</p><p>For three years poor Gale was just
"t'other one."  Then the Lanes went to
Green River where some lodge was having a
parade.  They were watching the drill when
a "bystander that was standing by" said
something about the "fine regalia."  Instantly
"Mis' Lane" thought of her unnamed
<pb n="50"/>
child; so since that time Gale has had
a name.
</p><p>There could be no two people more unlike
than the sisters.  Sedalia is really handsome,
and she is thin.  But she is vain, selfish, shallow,
and conceited.  Gale is not even pretty,
but she is clean and she is honest.  She does
many little things that are not exactly polite,
but she is good and true.  They both went
to the barn with me to milk.  Gale tucked up
her skirts and helped me.  She said, "I just
love a stable, with its hay and comfortable,
contented cattle.  I never go into one without
thinking of the little baby Christ.  I almost
expect to see a little red baby in the straw
every time I peek into a manger."
</p><p>Sedalia answered, "Well, for Heaven's
sake, get out of the stable to preach.  Who
wants to stand among these smelly cows all
day?"
</p><p>They stayed with us almost a week, and
one day when Gale and I were milking she
asked me to invite her to stay with me a
<pb n="51"/>
month.  She said to ask her mother, and left
her mother and myself much together.  But
Sedalia stuck to her mother like a plaster and
I just could not stand Sedalia a whole month.
However, I was spared all embarrassment,
for "Mis' Lane" asked me if I could not
find work enough to keep Gale busy for a
month or two.  She went on to explain that
Sedalia was expecting to be married and that
Gale was so "common" she would really
spoil the match.  I was surprised and indignant,
especially as Sedalia sat and listened
so brazenly, so I said I thought Sedalia would
need all the help she could get to get married
and that I should be glad to have Gale visit
me as long as she liked.
</p><p>So Gale stayed on with me.  One afternoon
she had gone to the post-office when I saw
Mr. Patterson ride up.  He went into the
bunk-house to wait until the men should
come.  Now, from something Gale had said I
fancied that Bob Patterson must be the right
man.  I am afraid I am not very delicate
<pb n="52"/>
about that kind of meddling, and while I had
been given to understand that Patterson was
the man Sedalia expected to marry, I didn't
think any man would choose her if he could
get Gale, so I called him.  We had a long
chat and he told me frankly he wanted Gale,
but that she didn't care for him, and that
they kept throwing "that danged Sedalia"
at him.  Then he begged my pardon for saying
"danged," but I told him I approved of
the word when applied to Sedalia, and broke
the news to him that Gale was staying with
me.  He fairly beamed.  So that night I left
Gale to wash dishes and Bob to help her
while I held Mr. Stewart a prisoner in the
stable and questioned him regarding Patterson's
prospects and habits.  I found both all
that need be, and told Mr. Stewart about my
talk with Patterson, and he said, "Wooman,
some day ye'll gang ploom daft."  But he
admitted he was glad it was the "bonny
lassie, instead of the bony one."  When we
went to the house Mr. Stewart said, "Weel,
<pb n="53"/>
when are you douchy bairns gangin' to the
kirk?"
</p><p>They left it to me, so I set Thanksgiving
Day, and as there is no "kirk to gang to,"
we are going to have a justice of the peace
and they are to be married here.  We are
going to have the dandiest dinner that I can
cook, and Mr. Stewart went to town next
day for the wedding dress, the gayest plaid
outside of Caledonia.  But Gale has lots of
sense and is going to wear it.  I have it
almost finished, and while it doesn't look
just like a Worth model, still it looks plumb
good for me to have made.  The boys are
going up after Zebulon Pike, and Mr. Stewart
is going after "Mis' Lane."  Joy waves are
radiating from this ranch and about Thanksgiving
morning one will strike you.
</p><p>With lots of love and happy wishes,
</p><p>Your ex-Washlady,
</p><p>ELINORE RUPERT.


<pb n="54"/>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="6" id="d11">
<head> "A THANKSGIVING-DAY WEDDING"</head>
<salute>
DEAR MRS. CONEY,&mdash;
</salute>
<p>. . . I think every one enjoyed our
Thanksgiving programme except poor Gale.
She was grieved, I verily believe, because
Mr. Patterson is not Mormon and could not
take Sedalia and herself also.  I suppose it
seemed odd to her to be unable to give way
to Sedalia as she had always done.
</p><p>I had cooked and cooked.  Gale and Zebulon
Pike both helped all they could.  The
wedding was to be at twelve o'clock, so at
ten I hustled Gale into my room to dress.  I
had to lock the door to keep her in, and I
divided my time between the last touches to
my dinner and the finishing touches to Gale's
toilet and receiving the people.  The Lane
party had not come yet, and I was scared to
death lest Sedalia had had a tantrum and
<pb n="55"/>
that Mr. Stewart would not get back in time.
At last I left the people to take care of themselves,
for I had too much on my mind to
bother with them.  Just after eleven Mr.
Stewart, Mis' Lane, Sedalia, and Pa Lane
"arriv" and came at once into the kitchen
to warm.  In a little while poor, frightened
Gale came creeping in, looking guilty.  But
she looked lovely, too, in spite of her plaid
dress.  She wore her hair in a coronet braid,
which added dignity and height, as well as
being simple and becoming.  Her mother
brought her a wreath for her hair, of lilies
of the valley and tiny pink rosebuds.  It
might seem a little out of place to one who
didn't see it, but the effect was really charming.
</p><p>Sedalia didn't know that Mr. Stewart had
given Gale her dress, so, just to be nasty,
she said, as soon as she saw Gale, "Dear me,
when are you going to dress, Gale?  You will
hardly have time to get out of that horse-blanket you are wearing and get into something
<pb n="56"/>
decent."  You see, she thought it was
one of my dresses fixed over for Gale.  Presently
Sedalia asked me if I was invited to the
"function."  She had some kind of rash on
her face and Zebulon Pike noticed the rash
and heard the word "function," so he thought
that was the name of some disease and asked
Mr. Stewart if the "function" was "catching."
Mr. Stewart had heart Sedalia, but
knew "Zebbie" had not heard all that was
said and how he got the idea he had, so he
answered, "Yes, if ye once get the fever."
So Zebulon Pike privately warned every one
against getting the "function" from Sedalia.
There are plenty of people here who don't
know exactly what a function is, myself
among them.  So people edged away from
Sedalia, and some asked her if she had seen
the doctor and what he thought of her case.
Poor girl, I'm afraid she didn't have a very
enjoyable time.
</p><p>At last the "jestice" of the peace came,
and I hope they live happy ever afterward.
<pb n="57"/>
That night a dance was given to celebrate
the event and we began to have dinner
immediately after the wedding so as to get
through in time to start, for dances are never
given in the home here, but in "the hall."
Every settlement has one and the invitations
are merely written announcements posted
everywhere.  We have what Sedalia calls
"homogenous" crowds.  I wouldn't attempt
to say what she means, but as everybody
goes no doubt she is right.
</p><p>Our dinner was a success, but that is not
to be wondered at.  Every woman for miles
around contributed.  Of course we had to
borrow dishes, but we couldn't think of
seating every one; so we set one table for
twenty-four and had three other long tables,
on one of which we placed all the meats,
pickles, and sauces, on another the vegetables,
soup, and coffee, and on the third
the pie, cakes, ice-cream, and other desserts.
We had two big, long shelves, one above the
other, on which were the dishes.  The people
<pb n="58"/>
helped themselves to dishes and neighbors
took turns at serving from the tables, so
people got what they wanted and hunted
themselves a place to sit while they ate.  Two
of the cowboys from this ranch waited upon
the table at which were the wedding party
and some of their friends.  Boys from other
ranches helped serve and carried coffee, cake,
and ice-cream.  The tablecloths were tolerably
good linen and we had ironed them wet
so they looked nice.  We had white lace-paper on the shelves and we used drawn-work paper napkins.  As I said, we borrowed
dishes, or, that is, every woman who called
herself our neighbor brought whatever she
thought we would need.  So after every one
had eaten I suggested that they sort out their
dishes and wash them, and in that way I was
saved all that work.  We had everything done
and were off to the dance by five o'clock.
We went in sleds and sleighs, the snow was
so deep, but it was all so jolly.  Zebbie, Mr.
Stewart, Jerrine, and I went in the bobsled.
<pb n="59"/>
We jogged along at a comfortable pace lest
the "beasties" should suffer, and every now
and then a merry party would fly past us
scattering snow in our faces and yelling like
Comanches.  We had a lovely moon then
and the snow was so beautiful!  We were
driving northward, and to the south and
back of us were the great somber, pine-clad
Uintah Mountains, while ahead and on every
side were the bare buttes, looking like old
men of the mountains,&mdash;so old they had
lost all their hair, beard, and teeth.


<pb n="60"/>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="7" id="d12">
<head> "ZEBULON PIKE VISITS HIS OLD HOME"
<hi rend="italic">December</hi> 28, 1909."</head>
<salute>
DEAR MRS. CONEY,</salute>
<p>&mdash;Our Thanksgiving
affair was the most enjoyable happening I
can remember for a long time.  Zebulon Pike
came, but I had as a bait for him two fat
letters from home.  As soon as I came back
from his place I wrote to Mrs. Carter and
trusted to luck for my letter to reach her.  I
told her all I could about her brother and
how seldom he left his mountain home.  I
asked her to write him all she could in one
letter, as the trips between our place and his
were so few and far between.  So when she
received my letter she wrote all she could
think of, and then sent her letter and mine
to Mothie and Phoebe, who are widows living
in the old home.  They each took turns writing,
so their letters are a complete record of
<pb n="61"/>
the years "Zebbie" has been gone.  The letters
were addressed to me along with a cordial
letter from Mrs. Carter asking me to see
that he got them and to use my judgment in
the delivering.  I couldn't go myself, but
I wanted to read the letters to him and to
write the answers; so I selected one piece of
news I felt would bring him to hear the rest
without his knowing how much there was for
him.
</p><p>Well, the boys brought him, and a more
delighted little man I am sure never lived.
I read the letters over and over, and answers
were hurried off.  He was dreadfully homesick,
but couldn't figure on how he could
leave the "critters," or how he could trust
himself on a train.  Mr. Stewart became interested,
and he is a very resourceful man,
so an old Frenchman was found who had no
home and wanted a place to stay so he could
trap.  He was installed at Zebulon Pike's
with full instructions as to each "critter's"
peculiarities and needs.  Then one of the
<pb n="62"/>
boys, who was going home for Christmas
to Memphis, was induced to wait for Mr.
Parker and to see him safe to Little Rock.
His money was banked for him, and Mr.
Stewart saw that he was properly clothed
and made comfortable for the trip.  Then he
sent a telegram to Judge Carter, who met
Zebulon Pike at Little Rock, and they had a
family reunion in Yell County.  I have had
some charming letters from there, but that
only proves what I have always said, that
I am the luckiest woman in finding really
lovely people and having really happy experiences.
Good things are constantly happening
to me.  I wish I could tell you about my
happy Christmas, but one of my New Year's
resolutions was to stop loading you down
with two-thousand-word letters.
</p><p>From something you wrote I think I must
have written boastingly to you at some time.
I have certainly not intended to, and you
must please forgive me and remember how
ignorant I am and how hard it is for me to
<pb n="63"/>
express myself properly.  I felt after I had
written to Mr. Parker's people that I had
taken a liberty, but luckily it was not thought
of in that way by them.  If you only knew
how far short I fall of my own hopes you
would know I could <hi rend="italic">never</hi> boast.  Why, it
keeps me busy making over mistakes just
like some one using old clothes.  I get myself
all ready to enjoy a success and find that I
have to fit a failure.  But one consolation is
that I generally have plenty of material to
cut generously, and many of my failures have
proved to be real blessings.
</p><p>I do hope this New Year may bring to you
the desire of your heart and all that those
who love you best most wish for you.
</p><p>With lots and lots of love from baby and
myself.
</p><p>Your ex-washlady,
</p><p>ELINORE STEWART.


<pb n="64"/>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="8" id="d13">
<head> "A HAPPY CHRISTMAS"</head>

<salute>DEAR MRS. CONEY,&mdash;</salute>
<p>My happy Christmas resulted from the
ex-sheriff of this county being snowbound
here.  It seems that persons who come from a
lower altitude to this country frequently become
bewildered, especially if in poor health,
leave the train at any stop and wander off
into the hills, sometimes dying before they
are found.  The ex-sheriff cited a case, that
of a young German who was returning from
the Philippines, where he had been discharged
after the war.  He was the only child of his
widowed mother, who has a ranch a few miles
from here.  No one knew he was coming
home.  One day the cook belonging to the
camp of a construction gang went hunting
and came back running, wild with horror.
He had found the body of a man.  The coroner
<pb n="65"/>
and the sheriff were notified, and next
morning went out for the body, but the
wolves had almost destroyed it.  High up in
a willow, under which the poor man had lain
down to die, they saw a small bundle tied in
a red bandanna and fast to a branch.  They
found a letter addressed to whoever should
find it, saying that the body was that of
Benny Louderer and giving them directions
how to spare his poor old mother the awful
knowledge of how he died.  Also there was a
letter to his mother asking her not to grieve
for him and to keep their days faithfully.
"Their days," I afterward learned, were
anniversaries which they had always kept, to
which was added "Benny's day."
</p><p>Poor boy!  When he realized that death
was near his every thought was for the
mother.  Well, they followed his wishes, and
the casket containing the bare, gnawed bones
was sealed and never opened.  And to this
day poor Mrs. Louderer thinks her boy died
of some fever while yet aboard the transport.
<pb n="66"/>
The manner of his death has been kept so secret
that I am the only one who has heard it.
</p><p>I was so sorry for the poor mother that I
resolved to visit her the first opportunity I
had.  I am at liberty to go where I please
when there is no one to cook for.  So, when
the men left, a few days later, I took Jerrine
and rode over to the Louderer ranch.  I had
never seen Mrs. Louderer and it happened
to be "Benny's day" that I blundered in
upon.  I found her to be a dear old German
woman living all alone, the people who do
the work on the ranch living in another house
two miles away.  She had been weeping for
hours when I got there, but in accordance
with her custom on the many anniversaries,
she had a real feast prepared, although no
one had been bidden.
</p><p>She says that God always sends her guests,
but that was the first time she had had a
little girl.  She had a little daughter once
herself, little Gretchen, but all that was left
was a sweet memory and a pitifully small
<pb n="67"/>
mound on the ranch, quite near the house,
where Benny and Gretchen are at rest beside
"der fader, Herr Louderer."
</p><p>She is such a dear old lady!  She made us
so welcome and she is so entertaining.  All
the remainder of the day we listened to stories
of her children, looked at her pictures,
and Jerrine had a lovely time with a wonderful
wooden doll that they had brought with
them from Germany.  Mrs. Louderer forgot
to weep in recalling her childhood days and
showing us her treasures.  And then our
feast,&mdash;for it was verily a feast.  We had
goose and it was <hi rend="italic">so</hi> delicious.  I couldn't tell
you half the good things any more than I
could have eaten some of all of them.
</p><p>We sat talking until far into the night,
and she asked me how I was going to spend
Christmas.  I told her, "Probably in being
homesick."  She said that would never do
and suggested that we spend it together.
She said it was one of their special days and
that the only happiness left her was in making
<pb n="68"/>
some one else happy; so she had thought
of cooking some nice things and going to as
many sheep camps as she could, taking with
her the good things to the poor exiles, the
sheep-herders.  I liked the plan and was glad
to agree, but I never dreamed I should have
so lovely a time.  When the queer old wooden
clock announced two we went to bed.
</p><p>I left quite early the next morning with
my head full of Christmas plans.  You may
not know, but cattle-men and sheep-men
cordially hate each other.  Mr. Stewart is
a cattle-man, and so I didn't mention my
Christmas plans to him.  I saved all the
butter I could spare for the sheep-herders;
they never have any.  That and some jars of
gooseberry jelly was all I could give them.
I cooked plenty for the people here, and two
days before Christmas I had a chance to go
down to Mrs. Louderer's in a buggy, so we
went.  We found her up to her ears in cooking,
and such sights and smells I could never
describe.  She was so glad I came early, for
<pb n="69"/>
she needed help.  I never worked so hard in
my life or had a pleasanter time.
</p><p>Mrs. Louderer had sent a man out several
days before to find out how many camps
there were and where they were located.
There were twelve camps and that means
twenty-four men.  We roasted six geese,
boiled three small hams and three hens.  We
had besides several meat-loaves and links of
sausage.  We had twelve large loaves of the
<hi rend="italic">best</hi> rye bread; a small tub of doughnuts;
twelve coffee-cakes, more to be called fruitcakes,
and also a quantity of little cakes with
seeds, nuts, and fruit in them,&mdash;so pretty to
look at and <hi rend="italic">so</hi> good to taste.  These had a
thick coat of icing, some brown, some pink,
some white.  I had thirteen pounds of butter
and six pint jars of jelly, so we melted the
jelly and poured it into twelve glasses.
</p><p>The plan was, to start real early Christmas
Eve morning, make our circuit of camps, and
wind up the day at Frau O'Shaughnessy's to
spend the night.  Yes, Mrs. O'Shaughnessy
<pb n="70"/>
is Irish,&mdash;as Irish as the pigs in Dublin.
Before it was day the man came to feed and
to get our horses ready.  We were up betimes
and had breakfast.  The last speck was wiped
from the shining stove, the kitchen floor was
scrubbed, and the last small thing put in
order.  The man had four horses harnessed
and hitched to the sled, on which was placed
a wagon-box filled with straw, hot rocks,
and blankets.  Our twelve apostles&mdash;that
is what we called our twelve boxes&mdash;were
lifted in and tied firmly into place.  Then
we clambered in and away we went.  Mrs.
Louderer drove, and Tam O'Shanter and
Paul Revere were snails compared to us.
We didn't follow any road either, but went
sweeping along across country.  No one else
in the world could have done it unless they
were drunk.  We went careening along hill-sides without even slacking the trot.
Occasionally we struck a particularly stubborn
bunch of sagebrush and even the sled-runners
would jump up into the air.  We didn't stop
<pb n="71"/>
to light, but hit the earth several feet in advance
of where we left it.  Luck was with
us, though.  I hardly expected to get through
with my head unbroken, but not even a
glass was cracked.
</p><p>It would have done your heart good to see
the sheep-men.  They were all delighted, and
when you consider that they live solely on
canned corn and tomatoes, beans, salt pork,
and coffee, you can fancy what they thought
of their treat.  They have mutton when it is
fit to eat, but that is certainly not in winter.
One man at each camp does the cooking and
the other herds.  It doesn't make any difference
if the cook never cooked before, and
most of them never did.  At one camp, where
we stopped for dinner, they had a most
interesting collection of fossils.  After
delivering our last "apostle," we turned our faces
toward Frau O'Shaughnessy's, and got there
just in time for supper.
</p><p>Mrs. O'Shaughnessy is a widow, too, and
has quite an interesting story.  She is a
<pb n="72"/>
dumpy little woman whose small nose seems
to be smelling the stars, it is so tip-tilted.
She has the merriest blue eyes and the quickest
wit.  It is really worth a severe bumping
just to be welcomed by her.  It was so warm
and cozy in her low little cabin.  She had her
table set for supper, but she laid plates for
us and put before us a beautifully roasted
chicken.  Thrifty Mrs. Louderer thought it
should have been saved until next day, so
she said to Frau O'Shaughnessy, "We hate
to eat your hen, best you save her till
tomorrow."  But Mrs. O'Shaughnessy answered,
"Oh, 't is no mather, 't is an ould
hin she was annyway."  So we enjoyed the
"ould hin," which was brown, juicy, and
tender.
</p><p>When we had finished supper and were
drinking our "tay," Mrs. O'Shaughnessy
told our fortunes with the tea-leaves.  She told
mine first and said I would die an old maid.
I said it was rather late for that, but she
cheerfully replied, "Oh, well, better late than
<pb n="73"/>
niver."  She predicted for Mrs. Louderer that
she should shortly catch a beau.  "'T is the
next man you see that will come coortin'
you."  Before we left the table some one
knocked and a young man, a sheep-herder,
entered.  He belonged to a camp a few miles
away and is out from Boston in search of
health.  He had been into town and his horse
was lamed so he could not make it into camp,
and he wanted to stay overnight.  He was
a stranger to us all, but Mrs. O'Shaughnessy
made him at home and fixed such a tempting
supper for him that I am sure he was glad of
the chance to stay.  He was very decidedly
English, and powerfully proud of it.  He
asked Mrs. O'Shaughnessy if she was Irish
and she said, "No, ye haythen, it's Chinese
Oi am.  Can't yez tell it be me Cockney
accint?"  Mr. Boutwell looked very much
surprised.  I don't know which was the
funnier, the way he looked or what she said.
</p><p>We had a late breakfast Christmas
morning, but before we were through Mr. Stewart
<pb n="74"/>
came.  We had planned to spend the day
with Mrs. O'Shaughnessy, but he didn't
approve of our going into the sheep district,
so when he found where we had gone he came
after us.  Mrs. Louderer and he are old
acquaintances and he bosses her around like
he tries to boss me.  Before we left, Mrs.
O'Shaughnessy's married daughter came, so
we knew she would not be lonely.
</p><p>It was almost one o'clock when we got
home, but all hands helped and I had plenty
cooked anyway, so we soon had a good dinner
on the table.  Mr. Stewart had prepared
a Christmas box for Jerrine and me.  He
doesn't approve of white waists in the
winter.  I had worn one at the wedding and
he felt personally aggrieved.  For me in the
box were two dresses, that is, the material
to make them.  One is a brown and red
checked, and the other green with a white
fleck in, both outing flannel.  For Jerrine
there was a pair of shoes and stockings, both
stockings full of candy and nuts.  He is very
<pb n="75"/>
bluff in manner, but he is really the kindest
person.
</p><p>Mrs. Louderer stayed until New Year's
day.  My Christmas was really a very happy
one.
</p><p>Your friend,
</p><p>ELINORE RUPERT.

</p><p>. . . An interesting day on this ranch is
the day the cattle are named.  If Mr. Stewart
had children he would as soon think of leaving
them unnamed as to let a "beastie" go
without a name.
</p><p>On the day they vaccinated he came into
the kitchen and told me he would need me
to help him name the "critters."  So he and
I "assembled" in a safe place and took turns
naming the calves.  As fast as a calf was
vaccinated it was run out of the chute and
he or I called out a name for it and it was
booked that way.
</p><p>The first two he named were the "Duke
of Monmouth" and the "Duke of Montrose."
<pb n="76"/>
I called my first "Oliver Cromwell"
and "John Fox."  The poor "mon" had to
have revenge, so the next ugly, scrawny little
beast he called the "Poop of Roome."  And
it was a heifer calf, too.
</p><p>This morning I had the startling news that
the "Poop" had eaten too much alfalfa and
was all "swellit oop," and, moreover, he had
"stealit it."  I don't know which is the more
astonishing, that the Pope has stolen alfalfa,
or that he has eaten it.
</p><p>We have a swell lot of names, but I am
not sure I could tell you which is "Bloody
Mary," or which is "Elizabeth," or, indeed,
which is which of any of them.
</p><p>E. R.


<pb n="77"/>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="9" id="d14">
<head> "A CONFESSION" <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 5,
1910.</head>

<salute>
DEAR MRS. CONEY,&mdash;
</salute>
<p>I find upon re-reading your letter that I
did not answer it at all when I wrote you.
You must think me very indifferent, but I
really don't mean to be.
</p><p>My house joins on to Mr. Stewart's house.
It was built that way so that I could "hold
down" my land and job at the same time.
I see the wisdom of it now, though at first I
did not want it that way.  My boundary
lines run within two feet of Mr. Stewart's
house, so it was quite easy to build on.
</p><p>I think the Pattersons' ranch is about
twenty-five miles from us.  I am glad to tell
you they are doing splendidly.  Gale is just
as thrifty as she can be and Bobby is steady
and making money fast.  Their baby is the
<pb n="78"/>
dearest little thing.  I have heard that
Sedalia is to marry a Mormon bishop, but I
doubt it.  She puts on very disgusting airs
about "our Bobby," and she patronizes Gale
most shamefully; but Gale, bless her unconscious
heart, is so happy in her husband and
son that she doesn't know Sedalia is insulting.
</p><p>My dear old grandmother whom I loved
so much has gone home to God.  I used to
write long letters to her.  I should like a few
addresses of old persons who are lonely as
she was, who would like letters such as I
write.  You know I can't be brief.  I have
tried and cannot.  If you know of any persons
who would not tire of my long accounts and
would care to have them, you will be doing
me a favor to let me know.
</p><p>I have not treated you quite frankly about
something you had a right to know about.
I am ashamed and I regret very much that I
have not told you.  I so dread the possibility
of losing your friendship that I will <hi rend="italic">never</hi> tell
<pb n="79"/>
you unless you promise me beforehand to
forgive me.  I know that is unfair, but it is
the only way I can see out of a difficulty that
my foolish reticence has led me into.  Few
people, perhaps, consider me reticent, but in
some cases I am afraid I am even deceitful.
Won't you make it easy to "'fess" so I may
be happy again?
</p><p>Truly your friend,
</p><p>ELINORE RUPERT.

<hi rend="italic">June</hi> 16, 1910.

MY DEAR FRIEND,&mdash;
</p><p>Your card just to hand.  I wrote you some
time ago telling you I had a confession to
make and have had no letter since, so thought
perhaps you were scared I had done something
too bad to forgive.  I am suffering just
now from eye-strain and can't see to write
long at a time, but I reckon I had better
confess and get it done with.
</p><p>The thing I have done is to marry Mr.
Stewart.  It was such an inconsistent thing
<pb n="80"/>
to do that I was ashamed to tell you.  And,
too, I was afraid you would think I didn't
need your friendship and might desert me.
Another of my friends thinks that way.
</p><p>I hope my eyes will be better soon and
then I will write you a long letter.
</p><p>Your old friend with a new name,
</p><p>ELINORE STEWART.


<pb n="81"/>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="10" id="d15">
<head>"THE STORY OF CORA BELLE"
<hi rend="italic">August</hi> 15, 1910.</head>
<salute>
DEAR MRS. CONEY,&mdash;
</salute>
<p>. . . Grandma Edmonson's birthday is
the 30th of May, and Mrs. O'Shaughnessy
suggested that we give her a party.  I had
never seen Grandma, but because of something
that happened in her family years ago
which a few narrow-heads whom it didn't
concern in the least cannot forgive or forget,
I had heard much of her.  The family consists
of Grandma, Grandpa, and little Cora
Belle, who is the sweetest little bud that ever
bloomed upon the twigs of folly.
</p><p>The Edmonsons had only one child, a
daughter, who was to have married a man
whom her parents objected to solely because
he was a sheep-man, while their sympathies
were with the cattle-men, although they
<pb n="82"/>
owned only a small bunch.  To gain their
consent the young man closed out his interest
in sheep, at a loss, filed on a splendid piece of
land near them, and built a little home for the
girl he loved.  Before they could get to town
to be married Grandpa was stricken with
rheumatism.  Grandma was already almost
past going on with it, so they postponed the
marriage, and as that winter was particularly
severe, the young man took charge of
the Edmonson stock and kept them from
starving.  As soon as he was able he went for
the license.
</p><p>Mrs. O'Shaughnessy and a neighbor were
hunting some cattle that had wandered away
and found the poor fellow shot in the back.
He was not yet dead and told them it was
urgently necessary for them to hurry him
to the Edmonsons' and to get some one to
perform the marriage ceremony as quickly
as possible, for he could not live long.  They
told him such haste meant quicker death
because he would bleed more; but he insisted,
so they got a wagon and hurried all
they could.  But they could not outrun
death.  When he knew he could not live to
reach home, he asked them to witness all he
said.  Everything he possessed he left to the
girl he was to have married, and said he was
the father of the little child that was to come.
He begged them to befriend the poor girl he
had to leave in such a condition, and to take
the marriage license as evidence that he had
tried to do right.  The wagon was stopped
so the jolting would not make death any
harder, and there in the shadow of the great
twin buttes he died.
</p><p>They took the body to the little home he
had made, and Mrs. O'Shaughnessy went to
the Edmonsons' to do what she could there.
Poor Cora Jane didn't know how terrible a
thing wounded pride is.  She told her parents
her misdeeds.  They couldn't see that they
were in any way to blame.  They seemed
to care nothing for her terrible sorrow nor
for her weakened condition.  All they could
<pb n="84"/>
think of was that the child they had almost
worshiped had disgraced them; so they told
her to go.
</p><p>Mrs. O'Shaughnessy took her to the home
that had been prepared for her, where the
poor body lay.  Some way they got through
those dark days, and then began the waiting
for the little one to come.  Poor Cora Jane
said she would die then, and that she wanted
to die, but she wanted the baby to know
it was loved,&mdash;she wanted to leave something
that should speak of that love when the
child should come to understanding.  So Mrs.
O'Shaughnessy said they would make all its
little clothes with every care, and they
should tell of the love.  Mrs. O'Shaughnessy
is the daintiest needleworker I have ever
seen; she was taught by the nuns at St.
Catherine's in the "ould country."  She was
all patience with poor, unskilled Cora Jane,
and the little outfit that was finally finished
was dainty enough for a fairy.  Little Cora
Belle is so proud of it.
<pb n="85"/>
</p><p>At last the time came and Mrs. O'Shaughnessy
went after the parents.  Long before,
they had repented and were only too glad to
go.  The poor mother lived one day and night
after the baby came.  She laid the tiny thing
in her mother's arms and told them to call
her Cora Belle.  She told them she gave them
a pure little daughter in place of the sinful
one they had lost.
</p><p>That was almost twelve years ago, and
the Edmonsons have lived in the new house
all this time.  The deed to the place was made
out to Cora Belle, and her grandfather is her
guardian. . . .
</p><p>If you traveled due north from my home,
after about nine hours' ride you would come
into an open space in the butte lands, and
away between two buttes you would see the
glimmer of blue water.  As you drew nearer
you would be able to see the fringe of willows
around the lake, and presently a low, red-roofed house with corrals and stables.  You
would see long lines of "buck" fence, a flock
<pb n="86"/>
of sheep near by, and cattle scattered about
feeding.  This is Cora Belle's home.  On the
long, low porch you would see two old folks
rocking.  The man is small, and has rheumatism
in his legs and feet so badly that he can
barely hobble.  The old lady is large and fat,
and is also afflicted with rheumatism, but
has it in her arms and shoulders.  They are
both cheerful and hopeful, and you would
get a cordial welcome. . . .
</p><p>When you saw Cora Belle you would see
a stout, square-built little figure with long
flaxen braids, a pair of beautiful brown eyes
and the longest and whitest lashes you ever
saw, a straight nose, a short upper lip, a
broad, full forehead,&mdash;the whole face,
neither pretty nor ugly, plentifully sown
with the brownest freckles.  She is very truly
the head of the family, doing all the house-work and looking after the stock, winter and
summer, entirely by herself.  Three years ago
she took things into her own hands, and since
that time has managed altogether.  Mrs.
<pb n="87"/>
O'Shaughnessy, however, tells her what to
do.
</p><p>The sheep, forty in number, are the result
of her individual efforts.  Mrs. O'Shaughnessy
told her there was more money in raising
lambs than in raising chickens, so she quit
the chickens as a business and went to some
of the big sheep-men and got permission to
take the "dogie" lambs, which they are glad
to give away.  She had plenty of cows, so
she milked cows and fed lambs all day long
all last year.  This year she has forty head of
nice sheep worth four dollars each, and she
doesn't have to feed them the year round
as she would chickens, and the wolves are
no worse to kill sheep than they are to kill
chickens.  When shearing-time came she
went to a sheep-man and told him she would
help cook for his men one week if he would
have her sheep sheared with his.  She said
her work was worth three dollars, that is
what one man would get a day shearing, and
he could easily shear her sheep in one day.
<pb n="88"/>
That is how she got her sheep sheared.  The
man had her wool hauled to town with his,
sold it for her, and it brought sixty dollars.
She took her money to Mrs. O'Shaughnessy.
She wanted some supplies ordered before
she went home, because, as she gravely said,
"the rheumatiz would get all the money she
had left when she got home,"&mdash;meaning
that her grandparents would spend what
remained for medicine.
</p><p>The poor old grandparents read all the
time of wonderful cures that different dopes
accomplish, and they spend every nickel they
can get their hands on for nostrums.  They
try everything they read of, and have to buy
it by the case,&mdash;horrid patent stuff!  They
have rolls of testimonials and believe every
word, so they keep on trying and hoping.
When there is any money they each order
whatever medicine they want to try.  If
Mrs. Edmonson's doesn't seem to help her,
Grandpa takes it and she takes his,&mdash;that is
their idea of economy.  They would spend
<pb n="89"/>
hours telling you about their different remedies
and would offer you spoonful after
spoonful of vile-looking liquid, and be mildly
grieved when you refused to take it.  Grandma's
hands are so bent and twisted that she
can't sew, so dear old Grandpa tries to do it.
</p><p>Mrs. O'Shaughnessy told me that she
helped out when she could.  Three years ago
she made them all a complete outfit, but the
"rheumatiz" has been getting all the spare
money since then, so there has been nothing
to sew.  A peddler sold them a piece of gingham
which they made up for Cora Belle.  It
was broad pink and white stripes, and they
wanted some style to "Cory's" clothes, so
they cut a gored skirt.  But they had no
pattern and made the gores by folding a width
of the goods biasly and cutting it that way.  It
was put together with no regard to matching
the stripes, and a bias seam came in the
center behind, but they put no stay in the
seam and the result was the most outrageous
affair imaginable.
<pb n="90"/>
</p><p>Well, we had a large room almost empty
and Mr. Stewart liked the idea of a party,
so Mrs. Louderer, Mrs. O'Shaughnessy, and
myself planned for the event.  It was to be
a sewing-bee, a few good neighbors invited,
and all to sew for Grandma. . . .  So Mrs.
O'Shaughnessy went to Grandma's and got
all the material she had to make up.  I had
saved some sugar-bags and some flour-bags.
I knew Cora Belle needed underwear, so I
made her some little petticoats of the larger
bags and some drawers of the smaller.  I had
a small piece of white lawn that I had no use
for, and of that I made a dear little sunbonnet
with a narrow edging of lace around, and
also made a gingham bonnet for her.  Two
days before the time, came Mrs. Louderer,
laden with bundles, and Mrs. O'Shaughnessy,
also laden.  We had all been thinking of Cora
Belle.  Mr. Stewart had sent by mail for her
a pair of sandals for everyday wear and a
nice pair of shoes, also some stockings.  Mrs.
Louderer brought cloth for three dresses of
<pb n="91"/>
heavy Dutch calico, and gingham for three
aprons.  She made them herself and she sews
so carefully.  She had bought patterns and
the little dresses were stylishly made, as well
as well made.  Mrs. O'Shaughnessy brought
a piece of crossbar with a tiny forget-me-not polka dot, and also had goods and
embroidery for a suit of underwear.  My
own poor efforts were already completed
when the rest came, so I was free to help
them.
</p><p>Late in the afternoon of the 29th a funny
something showed up.  Fancy a squeaky,
rickety old wagon without a vestige of paint.
The tires had come off and had been "set"
at home; that is done by heating the tires
red-hot and having the rims of the wheels
covered with several layers of burlap, or
other old rags, well wet; then the red-hot
tire is put on and water hurriedly poured on
to shrink the iron and to keep the burlap
from blazing.  Well, whoever had set Cora
Belle's tires had forgotten to cut away the
<pb n="92"/>
surplus burlap, so all the ragtags were merrily
waving in the breeze.
</p><p>Cora Belle's team would bring a smile to
the soberest face alive.  Sheba is a tall, lanky
old mare.  Once she was bay in color, but the
years have added gray hair until now she is
roan.  Being so long-legged she strides along
at an amazing pace which her mate, Balaam,
a little donkey, finds it hard to keep up with.
Balaam, like Sheba, is full of years.  Once
his glossy brown coat was the pride of some
Mexican's heart, but time has added to his
color also, and now he is blue.  His eyes are
sunken and dim, his ears no longer stand up
in true donkey style, but droop dejectedly.
He has to trot his best to keep up with
Sheba's slowest stride.  About every three
miles he balks, but little Cora Belle doesn't
call it balking, she says Balaam has stopped
to rest, and they sit and wait till he is ready to
trot along again.  That is the kind of layout
which drew up before our door that evening.
Cora Belle was driving and she wore her
<pb n="93"/>
wonderful pink dress which hung down in a
peak behind, fully six inches longer than
anywhere else.  The poor child had no shoes.  The
winter had tried the last pair to their utmost
endurance and the "rheumatiz" had long
since got the last dollar, so she came with her
chubby little sunburned legs bare.  Her poor
little scarred feet were clean, her toe-nails
full of nicks almost into the quick, broken
against rocks when she had been herding her
sheep.  In the back of the wagon, flat on the
bottom, sat Grandma and Grandpa, such
bundles of coats and blankets I can't describe.
After a great deal of trouble we got
them unloaded and into the house.  Then
Mrs. Louderer entertained them while Mrs.
O'Shaughnessy and I prepared supper and
got a bath ready for Cora Belle.  We had
a T-bone steak, mashed potatoes, hominy,
hot biscuits and butter, and stewed prunes.
Their long ride had made them hungry and
I know they enjoyed their meal.
</p><p>After supper Cora Belle and I washed the
<pb n="94"/>
dishes while Mrs. O'Shaughnessy laid out
the little clothes.  Cora Belle's clothes were
to be a surprise.  The postmistress here also
keeps a small store and has ribbon, and when
she heard of our plans from Mr. Stewart she
sent up a couple of pairs of hair-ribbon for
Cora Belle.  Soon Mrs. O'Shaughnessy called
us, and Cora Belle and I went into the bedroom
where she was.  I wish you could have
seen that child!  Poor little neglected thing,
she began to cry.  She said, "They ain't for
me, I know they ain't.  Why, it ain't my
birthday, it's Granny's."  Nevertheless, she
had her arms full of them and was clutching
them so tightly with her work-worn little
hands that we couldn't get them.  She
sobbed so deeply that Grandma heard her
and became alarmed.  She hobbled to the
door and pounded with her poor twisted
hands, calling all the while, "Cory, Cory
Belle, what ails you?"  She got so excited
that I opened the door, but Cora Belle told
her to go away.  She said, "They ain't
<pb n="95"/>
for you, Granny, and they ain't for me
either." . . .
</p><p>People here observe Decoration Day
faithfully, and Cora Belle had brought half
a wagon-load of iris, which grows wild here.
Next morning we were all up early, but Cora
Belle's flowers had wilted and she had to
gather more, but we all hurried and helped.
She said as she was going to see her mother
she wanted to wear her prettiest dress, so
Gale and Mrs. O'Shaughnessy helped her to
get ready.  The cemetery is only about two
miles away, so we were all down quite early.
We were obliged to hurry because others
were coming to help sew.  Cora Belle went
at once to the graves where her parents lie
side by side, and began talking to her mother
just as though she saw her.  "You didn't
know me, did you, Mother, with my pretty
new things?  But I am your little girl,
Mamma.  I am your little Cora Belle."  After
she had talked and had turned every way
like a proud little bird, she went to work.
<pb n="96"/>
And, oh, how fast she worked!  Both graves
were first completely covered with pine
boughs.  It looked like sod, so closely were
the little twigs laid.  Next she broke the
stems off the iris and scattered the blossoms
over, and the effect was very beautiful.  Then
we hurried home and everybody got busy.
The men took Grandpa off to another part
of the ranch where they were fanning oats to
plant, and kept him all day.  That was good
for him because then he could be with the
men all day and he so seldom has a chance to
be with men.  Several ladies came and they
all made themselves at home and worked
like beavers, and we all had a fine time. . . .
</p><p>Sedalia was present and almost caused a
riot.  She says she likes unusual words because
they lend distinction to conversation.
Well, they do&mdash;sometimes.  There was another
lady present whose children are very
gifted musically, but who have the bad name
of taking what they want without asking.
The mother can neither read nor write, and
<pb n="97"/>
she is very sensitive about the bad name her
children have.  While we were all busy some
one made a remark about how smart these
children were.  Sedalia thought that a good
time to get in a big word, so she said, "Yes,
I have always said Lula was a progeny."
Mrs. Hall didn't know what she meant and
thought that she was casting reflections on
her child's honesty, so with her face scarlet
and her eyes blazing she said, "Sedalia Lane,
I won't allow you nor nobody else to say my
child is a progeny.  You can take that back
or I will slap you peaked."  Sedalia took it
back in a hurry, so I guess little Lula Hall
is not a progeny.
</p><p>Every one left about four except Gale,
Mrs. O'Shaughnessy, Mrs. Louderer, and the
Edmonsons.  They had farthest to go, so
they stayed over night again.  We worked
until ten o'clock that night over Grandma's
clothes, but everything was thoroughly finished.
Every button was on, every threadend
knotted and clipped, and some tired
<pb n="98"/>
workers lay down to rest, as did a very happy
child and a very thankful old lady.
</p><p>Every one got away by ten o'clock the
next morning.  The last I saw of little Cora
Belle was when they had reached the top of
a long slope and Balaam had "stopped to
rest."  The breeze from the south was playfully
fluttering the rags on the wheels.  Presently
I heard a long "hee-haw, hee-haw," and
I knew Balaam had rested and had started.
</p><p>I have been a very busy woman since I
began this letter to you several days ago.
A dear little child has joined the angels.  I
dressed him and helped to make his casket.
There is no minister in this whole country
and I could not bear the little broken lily-bud to be just carted away and buried, so I
arranged the funeral and conducted the services.
I know I am unworthy and in no way
fitted for such a mission, but I did my poor
best, and if no one else is comforted, I am.
I know the message of God's love and care
has been told once, anyway, to people who
<pb n="99"/>
have learned to believe more strongly in hell
than in heaven.
</p><p>Dear friend, I do hope that this New Year
will bring you and yours fuller joys than you
have ever known.  If I had all the good gifts
in my hands you should certainly be blessed.
</p><p>Your sincere friend,
</p><p>ELINORE RUPERT STEWART.


<pb n="100"/>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="11" id="d16">
<head>"ZEBBIE'S STORY" <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 1, 1910.</head>
<salute>
DEAR MRS. CONEY,&mdash;
</salute>
<p>It was just a few days after the birthday
party and Mrs. O'Shaughnessy was with me
again.  We were down at the barn looking at
some new pigs, when we heard the big corral
gates swing shut, so we hastened out to see
who it could be so late in the day.
</p><p>It was Zebbie.  He had come on the stage
to Burnt Fork and the driver had brought
him on here. . . .  There was so much to tell,
and he whispered he had something to tell
me privately, but that he was too tired then;
so after supper I hustled him off to bed. . . .
</p><p>Next morning . . . the men went off to
their work and Zebbie and I were left to tell
secrets.  When he was sure we were alone he
took from his trunk a long, flat box.  Inside
<pb n="101"/>
was the most wonderful shirt I have ever
seen; it looked like a cross between a night-shirt and a shirt-waist.  It was of homespun
linen.  The bosom was ruffled and tucked, all
done by hand,&mdash;such tiny stitches, such
patience and skill.  Then he handed me an
old daguerreotype.  I unfastened the little
golden hook and inside was a face good to
see and to remember.  It was dim, yet clear
in outline, just as if she were looking out
from the mellow twilight of long ago.  The
sweet, elusive smile,&mdash;I couldn't tell where
it was, whether it was the mouth or the
beautiful eyes that were smiling.  All that
was visible of her dress was the Dutch collar,
just like what is being worn now.  It was
pinned with an ugly old brooch which Zebbie
said was a "breast-pin" he had given her.
Under the glass on the other side was a strand
of faded hair and a slip of paper.  The writing
on the paper was so faded it was scarcely
readable, but it said: "Pauline Gorley, age
22, 1860."
<pb n="102"/>
</p><p>Next he showed me a note written by
Pauline, simply worded, but it held a world
of meaning for Zebbie.  It said, "I spun and
wove this cloth at Adeline's, enough for me a
dress and you a shirt, which I made.  It is
for the wedding, else to be buried in.  Yours,
Pauline."  The shirt, the picture, and the note
had waited for him all these years in Mothie's
care.  And now I will tell you the story.
</p><p>Long, long ago some one did something to
some one else and started a feud.  Unfortunately
the Gorleys were on one side and the
Parkers on the other.  That it all happened
before either Zebbie or Pauline was born
made no difference.  A Gorley must hate a
Parker always, as also a Parker must hate
a Gorley.  Pauline was the only girl, and she
had a regiment of big brothers who gloried
in the warfare and wanted only the slightest
pretext to shoot a Parker.  So they grew up,
and Zebbie often met Pauline at the quiltings
and other gatherings at the homes of non-partisans.  He remembers her so perfectly
<pb n="103"/>
and describes her so plainly that I can picture
her easily.  She had brown eyes and hair.
She used to ride about on her sorrel palfrey
with her "nigger" boy Caesar on behind to
open and shut plantation gates.  She wore
a pink calico sunbonnet, and Zebbie says
"she was just like the pink hollyhocks that
grew by mother's window."  Isn't that a
sweet picture?
</p><p>Her mother and father were both dead,
and she and her brothers lived on their
plantation.  Zebbie had never dared speak
to her until one day he had driven over with
his mothers and sisters to a dinner given on
a neighboring plantation.  He was standing
outside near the wall, when some one dropped
a spray of apple blossoms down upon him
from an upper window.  He looked up and
Pauline was leaning out smiling at him.  After
that he made it a point to frequent places
where he might expect her, and things went
so well that presently Caesar was left at home
lest he should tell the brothers.  She was
<pb n="104"/>
a loyal little soul and would not desert,
although he urged her to, even promising
to go away, "plumb away, clean to Scott
County if she would go."  She told him that
her brothers would go even as far as that to
kill him, so that they must wait and hope.
Finally Zebbie got tired of waiting, and one
day he boldly rode up to the Gorley home
and formally asked for Pauline's hand.  The
bullet he got for his presumption kept him
from going to the war with his father and
brother when they marched away.
</p><p>Some time later George Gorley was shot
and killed from ambush, and although Zebbie
had not yet left his bed the Gorleys believed
he did it, and one night Pauline came
through a heavy rainstorm, with only Caesar,
to warn Zebbie and to beg him, for her
sake, to get away as fast as he could that
night.  She pleaded that she could not live if
he were killed and could never marry him if
he killed her brothers, so she persuaded him
to go while they were all innocent.
<pb n="105"/>
</p><p>Well, he did as she wished and they never
saw each other again.  He never went home
again until last Thanksgiving, and dear little
Pauline had been dead for years.  She herself
had taken her little gifts for Zebbie to
Mothie to keep for him.  Some years later
she died and was buried in the dress she
mentioned.  It was woven at Adeline Carter's,
one of the bitterest enemies of the Gorleys,
but the sacrifice of her pride did her
no good because she was long at rest before
Zebbie knew.  He had been greatly grieved
because no stone marked her grave, only a
tangle of rose-briers.  So he bought a stone,
and in the night before Decoration Day he
and two of Uncle Buck's grandsons went to
the Gorley burying-ground and raised it to
the memory of sweet Pauline.  Some of the
Gorleys still live there, so he came home at
once, fearing if they should find out who
placed the stone above their sister they
would take vengeance on his poor, frail body.
</p><p>After he had finished telling me his story,
<pb n="106"/>
I felt just as I used to when Grandmother
opened the "big chist" to air her wedding
clothes and the dress each of her babies wore
when baptized.  It seemed almost like smelling
the lavender and rose-leaves, and it was
with reverent fingers that I folded the shirt,
the work of love, yellow with age, and laid it
in the box. . . .
</p><p>Well, Mrs. O'Shaughnessy returned, and
early one morning we started with a wagon
and a bulging mess-box for Zebbie's home.
We were going a new and longer route in
order to take the wagon.  Dandelions spread
a carpet of gold.  Larkspur grew waist-high
with its long spikes of blue.  The service-bushes and the wild cherries were a mass of
white beauty.  Meadowlarks and robins and
bluebirds twittered and sang from every
branch, it almost seemed.  A sky of tenderest
blue bent over us and fleecy little clouds
drifted lazily across. . . .Soon we came to
the pineries, where we traveled up deep
gorges and canons.  The sun shot arrows of
<pb n="107"/>
gold through the pines down upon us and
we gathered our arms full of columbines.
The little black squirrels barked and chattered
saucily as we passed along, and we
were all children together.  We forgot all
about feuds and partings, death and hard
times.  All we remembered was that God is
good and the world is wide and beautiful.
We plodded along all day.  Next morning
there was a blue haze that Zebbie said
meant there would be a high wind, so we
hurried to reach his home that evening.
</p><p>The sun was hanging like a great red ball
in the smoky haze when we entered the long
canon in which is Zebbie's cabin.  Already it
was dusky in the canons below, but not a
breath of air stirred.  A more delighted man
than Zebbie I never saw when we finally
drove up to his low, comfortable cabin.
Smoke was slowly rising from the chimney,
and Gavotte, the man in charge, rushed out
and the hounds set up a joyful barking.
Gavotte is a Frenchman, and he was all
<pb n="108"/>
smiles and gesticulations as he said, "Welcome,
welcome!  To-day I am rejoice you
have come.  Yesterday I am despair if you
have come because I am scrub, but to-day,
behold, I am delight."
</p><p>I have heard of clean people, but Gavotte
is the cleanest man I ever saw.  The cabin
floor was so white I hated to step upon it.
The windows shone, and at each there was
a calico curtain, blue-and-white check, unironed
but newly washed.  In one window was
an old brown pitcher, cracked and nicked,
filled with thistles.  I never thought them
pretty before, but the pearly pink and the
silvery green were so pretty and looked so
clean that they had a new beauty.  Above
the fireplace was a great black eagle which
Gavotte had killed, the wings outspread and
a bunch of arrows in the claws.  In one corner
near the fire was a washstand, and behind
it hung the fishing-tackle.  Above one door
was a gun-rack, on which lay the rifle and
shotgun, and over the other door was a pair
<pb n="109"/>
of deer-antlers.  In the center of the room
stood the square home-made table, every
inch scrubbed.  In the side room, which is
the bedroom, was a wide bunk made of pine
plank that had also been scrubbed, then
filled with fresh, sweet pine boughs, and over
them was spread a piece of canvas that had
once been a wagon sheet, but Gavotte had
washed it and boiled and pounded it until it
was clean and sweet.  That served for a sheet.
</p><p>Zebbie was beside himself with joy.  The
hounds sprang upon him and expressed their
joy unmistakably.  He went at once to the
corrals to see the "critters," and every one of
them was safely penned for the night.  "Old
Sime," an old ram (goodness knows <hi rend="italic">how</hi> old!),
promptly butted him over, but he just
beamed with pleasure.  "Sime knows me,
dinged if he don't!" was his happy exclamation.
We went into the cabin and left him
fondling the "critters."
</p><p>Gavotte did himself proud getting supper.
We had trout and the most delicious biscuit.
<pb n="110"/>
Each of us had a crisp, tender head of lettuce
with a spoonful of potato salad in the center.
We had preserves made from canned peaches,
and the firmest yellow butter.  Soon it was
quite dark and we had a tiny brass lamp
which gave but a feeble light, but it was quite
cool so we had a blazing fire which made it
light enough.
</p><p>When supper was over, Zebbie called us
out and asked us if we could hear anything.
We could hear the most peculiar, long-drawn,
sighing wail that steadily grew louder and
nearer.  I was really frightened, but he said
it was the forerunner of the windstorm that
would soon strike us.  He said it was wind
coming down Crag Canon, and in just a few
minutes it struck us like a cold wave and
rushed, sighing, on down the canon.  We
could hear it after it had passed us, and it
was perfectly still around the cabin.  Soon
we heard the deep roaring of the coming
storm, and Zebbie called the hounds in and
secured the door.  The sparks began to fly
<pb n="111"/>
up the chimney.  Jerrine lay on a bearskin
before the fire, and Mrs. O'Shaughnessy and
I sat on the old blue "settle" at one side.
Gavotte lay on the other side of the fire on
the floor, his hands under his head.  Zebbie
got out his beloved old fiddle, tuned up, and
began playing.  Outside the storm was raging,
growing worse all the time.  Zebbie played
and played.  The worse the tumult, the
harder the storm, the harder he played.  I
remember I was holding my breath, expecting
the house to be blown away every moment,
and Zebbie was playing what he called
"Bonaparte's Retreat."  It all seemed to
flash before me&mdash;I could see those poor,
suffering soldiers staggering along in the
snow, sacrifices to one man's unholy ambition.
I verily believe we were all bewitched.
I shouldn't have been surprised to have
seen witches and gnomes come tumbling
down the chimney or flying in at the door,
riding on the crest of the storm.  I glanced at
Mrs. O'Shaughnessy.  She sat with her chin
<pb n="112"/>
in her hand, gazing with unseeing eyes into
the fire.  Zebbie seemed possessed; he could
n't tire.
</p><p>It seemed like hours had passed and the
tumult had not diminished.  I felt like shrieking,
but I gathered Jerrine up into my arms
and carried her in to bed.  Mrs. O'Shaughnessy
came with us.  She touched my elbow
and said, "Child, don't look toward the window,
the banshees are out to-night."  We
knelt together beside the bed and said our
beads; then, without undressing save pulling
off our shoes, we crawled under our blankets
and lay on the sweet, clean pine.  We were
both perfectly worn out, but we could not
sleep.  There seemed to be hundreds of different
noises of the storm, for there are so
many canons, so many crooks and turns,
and the great forest too.  The wind was
shrieking, howling, and roaring all at once.
A deep boom announced the fall of some
giant of the forest.  I finally dozed off even
in that terrible din, but Zebbie was not so
<pb n="113"/>
frenzied as he had been.  He was playing
"Annie Laurie," and that song has always
been a favorite of mine.  The storm began
gradually to die away and "Annie Laurie"
sounded so beautiful.  I was thinking of
Pauline and, I know, to Zebbie, Annie Laurie
and Pauline Gorley are one and the same.
</p><p>I knew no more until I heard Zebbie call
out, "Ho, you sleepy-heads, it's day."  Mrs.
O'Shaughnessy turned over and said she was
still sleepy.  My former visit had taught me
what beauty the early morning would spread
before me, so I dressed hastily and went out-doors.  Zebbie called me to go for a little
walk.  The amber light of the new day was
chasing the violet and amethyst shadows
down the canons.  It was all more beautiful
than I can tell you.  On one side the canon-walls were almost straight up.  It looked as
if we might step off into a very world of
mountains.  Soon Old Baldy wore a crown of
gleaming gold.  The sun was up.  We walked
on and soon came to a brook.  We were washing
<pb n="114"/>
our faces in its icy waters when we heard
twigs breaking, so we stood perfectly still.
>From out the undergrowth of birch and willows
came a deer with two fawns.  They
stopped to drink, and nibbled the bushes.
But soon they scented strangers, and, looking
about with their beautiful, startled eyes,
they saw us and away they went like the
wind.  We saw many great trees uptorn by
the storm.  High up on the cliffs Zebbie
showed me where the eagles built every
year. . . .  We turned homeward and sat
down upon the trunk of a fallen pine to rest
and take another look at the magnificent
view.  Zebbie was silent, but presently he
threw a handful of pebbles down the canon
wall.  "I am not sorry Pauline is dead.  I
have never shed a tear.  I know you think
that is odd, but I have never wanted to
mourn.  I am glad that it is as it is.  I am
happy and at peace because I know she is
mine.  The little breeze is Pauline's own
voice; she had a little caressing way just like
<pb n="115"/>
the gentlest breeze when it stirs your hair.
There is something in everything that brings
back Pauline: the beauty of the morning,
the song of a bird or the flash of its wings.
The flowers look like she did.  So I have not
lost her, she is mine more than ever.  I have
always felt so, but was never quite sure until
I went back and saw where they laid her.
I know people think I am crazy, but I don't
care for that.  I shall not hate to die.  When
you get to be as old as I am, child, everything
will have a new meaning for you."
</p><p>At last we slowly walked back to the cabin,
and at breakfast Zebbie told of the damage
the storm had done.  He was so commonplace
that no one ever would have guessed
his strange fancy. . . .
</p><p>I shall never forget Zebbie as I last saw
him.  It was the morning we started home.
After we left the bench that Zebbie lives on,
our road wound down into a deeper canon.
Zebbie had followed us to where a turn in the
canon should hide us from view.  I looked
<pb n="116"/>
back and saw him standing on the cliffs,
high above us, the early morning sun turning
his snowy hair to gold, the breeze-fingers
of Pauline tossing the scanty locks.  I shall
always remember him so, a living monument
to a dead past.
</p><p>ELINORE STEWART.


<pb n="117"/>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="12" id="d17">
<head> "A CONTENTED COUPLE" <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 6, 1911.
</head>
<salute>
DEAR MRS. CONEY,&mdash;
</salute>
<p>. . . I once "heared" Sedalia Lane telling
some of her experiences, and she said she
"surreptitiously stole along."  One day, when I
thought the coast was clear, I was surreptitiously
examining the contents of the tool-chest with a view toward securing to myself
such hammers, saws, and what else I might
need in doing some carpentry work I had
planned.  The tool-chest is kept in the granary;
both it and the granary are usually kept
locked.  Now the "gude mon" has an idea
that a "wooman" needs no tools, and the use
and misuse of his tools have led to numbers
of inter-household wars.  I was gloating over
my opportunity, and also making the best
of it, when a medley of burring Scotch voices
<pb n="118"/>
brought me to a quick realization that discretion
is the better part of valor.  So I went
into seclusion behind a tall oat-bin.  It
seemed that two neighbors whom I had never
seen were preparing to go to town, and had
come to get some tools and to see if the
Stewart would lend them each a team.  Now
Mr. Stewart must be very righteous, because
he certainly regardeth his beast, although
he doesn't always love his neighbor as himself.
 He was willing, however, for friends
Tam Campbell and Archie McEttrick to use
his teams, but he himself would take a lighter
rig and go along, so as to see that his horses
were properly cared for, and to help out in
case of need.
</p><p>They made their plans, set the day, and
went their ways.  As soon as I could, I made
myself scarce about the granary and very
busy about the house, and, like Josiah Allen,
I was in a very "happyfied" state of mind.
There is nothing Mr. Stewart likes better
than to catch me unprepared for something.
<pb n="119"/>
I had been wanting to go to town, and he had
said I might go with him next time he went,
if I was ready when he was.  I knew I would
not hear one word about the proposed trip,
but that only added to the fun.  I had plenty
of time to make all preparations; so the day
before they were to start found me with all
in readiness.  It was quite early in the spring
and the evenings were quite chilly.  We had
just finished supper, when we heard a great
rumbling, and I knew neighbors Campbell
and McEttrick had arrived on their way to
town; so I began to prepare supper for them.
I hadn't expected a woman, and was surprised
when I saw the largest, most ungainly
person I have ever met come shambling
toward me.
</p><p>She was Aggie McEttrick.  She is tall and
raw-boned, she walks with her toes turned
out, she has a most peculiar lurching gait
like a camel's.  She has skin the color of a
new saddle, and the oddest straggly straw-colored
hair.  She never wears corsets and
<pb n="120"/>
never makes her waists long enough, so there
is always a streak of gray undershirt visible
about her waist.  Her skirts are never long
enough either, and she knits her own stockings.
 Those inclined can always get a good
glimpse of blue-and-white striped hose.  She
said, "I guess you are the Missus."  And
that was every word she said until I had
supper on the table.  The men were busy
with their teams, and she sat with her feet
in my oven, eyeing my every movement.  I
told her we had just had our supper, but she
waited until I had theirs ready before she
announced that neither she nor Archie ate hot
biscuits or steak, that they didn't take tea
for supper, preferred coffee, and that neither
of them could eat peaches or honey.  So all of
my supper was ruled off except the butter
and cream.  She went down to their wagons
and brought up what she wanted, so Tam
Campbell was the only one who ate my
honey and biscuit.
</p><p>Tam is just a Scot with an amazingly close
<pb n="121"/>
fist, and he is very absent-minded.  I had
met Annie, his wife, and their six children.
She told me of his absent-mindedness.  Her
remedy for his trouble when it came to house-hold needs was to repeat the article two or
three times in the list.  People out like we
are buy a year's supply at a time.  So a list
of needed things is made up and sent into
town.  Tam always managed to forget a
great many things.
</p><p>Well, bedtime came.  I offered to show them
to their room, but Aggie said, "We'll nae
sleep in your bed.  We'll jest bide in the
kitchen."  I could not persuade her to change
her mind.  Tam slept at the barn in order
to see after the "beasties," should they need
attention during the night.  As I was preparing
for bed, Aggie thrust her head into
my room and announced that she would be
up at three o'clock.  I am not an early bird,
so I thought I would let Aggie get her own
breakfast, and I told her she would find
everything in the pantry.  As long as I was
<pb n="122"/>
awake I could hear Archie and Aggie talking,
but I could not imagine what about.  I
didn't know their habits so well as I came
to later.  Next morning the rumbling of their
wagons awakened me, but I turned over and
slept until after six.
</p><p>There are always so many things to do before
leaving that it was nine o'clock before
we got started.  We had only gotten about
two miles, when Mr. Stewart remembered
he had not locked the granary, so back we
trotted.  We nooned only a few miles from
home.  We knew we could not catch the
wagons before camping-time unless we drove
very hard, so Mr. Stewart said we would
go by the Edmonsons' and spend the night
there.  I enjoy even the memory of that drive
through the short spring afternoon,&mdash;the
warm red sand of the desert; the Wind River
Mountains wrapped in the blue veil of distance;
the sparse gray-green sage, ugly in
itself, but making complete a beautiful picture;
the occasional glimpse we had of shy,
<pb n="123"/>
beautiful wild creatures.  So much happiness
can be crowded into so short a time.  I was
glad, though, when Cora Belle's home became
a part of our beautiful picture.  It is situated
among great red buttes, and there is a
blue lake back of the house.  Around the
lake is a fringe of willows.  Their house is
a low, rambling affair, with a long, low porch
and a red clay roof.  Before the house is a
cotton-wood tree, its gnarled, storm-twisted
branches making it seem to have the "rheumatiz."
 There is a hop-vine at one end of the
porch.  It had not come out when we were
there, but the dead vine clung hopelessly to
its supports.
</p><p>Little Cora Belle just bubbled with delight,
and her grandparents were scarcely better
than she.  Spring house-cleaning was just
finished, and they have company so seldom
that they made us feel that we were doing
them a favor by stopping.  Poor old "Pa"
hobbled out to help put the team away, and
when they came back, Cora Belle asked me
<pb n="124"/>
out to help prepare supper, so I left Mr.
Stewart with "Granny" and "Pa" to listen
to their recitals and to taste their many
medicines.  Cora Belle is really an excellent
housekeeper.  Her cooking would surprise
many people.  Her bread was delicious, and I
am sure I never tasted anything better than
the roasted leg of lamb she gave us for supper.
I am ashamed to tell you how much I ate of
her carrot jam.  From where I sat I had a
splendid view of the sunset across the lake.
Speaking of things singly, Wyoming has
nothing beautiful to offer.  Taken altogether,
it is grandly beautiful, and at sunrise and
sunset the "heavens declare His glory."
</p><p>Cora Belle is so animated and so straight-forward, so entirely clean in all her thoughts
and actions, that she commands love and
respect at one and the same time.  After supper
her grandfather asked her to sing and
play for us.  Goodness only knows where
they got the funny little old organ that Cora
Belle thinks so much of.  It has spots all over
<pb n="125"/>
it of medicine that has been spilled at different
times, and it has, as Cora Belle said, lost
its voice in spots; but that doesn't set back
Cora Belle at all, she plays away just as if
it was all right.  Some of the keys keep up
a mournful whining and groaning, entirely
outside the tune.  Cora Belle says they
play themselves.  After several "pieces" had
been endured, "Pa" said, "Play my piece,
Cory Belle"; so we had "Bingen on the
Rhine" played and sung from A to izzard.
Dear old "Pa," his pain-twisted old face
just beamed with pride.  I doubt if heaven
will have for him any sweeter music than his
"baby's" voice.  Granny's squeaky, trembly
old voice trailed in after Cora Belle's, always
a word or two behind.  "Tell my friends and
companions when they meet and <hi rend="italic">scrouge</hi>
around"; that is the way they sang it, but no
one would have cared for that, if they had
noticed with what happy eagerness the two
sang together.  The grandparents would like
to have sat up all night singing and telling of
<pb n="126"/>
things that happened in bygone days, but
poor tired little Cora Belle began to nod, so
we retired.  As we were preparing for bed it
suddenly occurred to Mr. Stewart that I had
not been surprised when going to town was
mentioned, so he said, "Wooman, how did it
happen that you were ready when I was to
gae to the toone?"  "Oh," I said, "I knew you
were going."  "Who tell it ye?"  "A little
bird."  "'T was some fool wooman, mayhap."
I didn't feel it necessary to enlighten him,
and I think he is still wondering how I knew.
</p><p>Next morning we were off early, but we
didn't come up with the wagons until almost
camping-time.  The great heavily-loaded
wagons were creaking along over the heavy
sands.  The McEttricks were behind, Aggie's
big frame swaying and lurching with every
jolt of the wagon.  They never travel without
their German socks.  They are great thick
things to wear on the outside of their shoes.
As we came up behind them, we could see
Aggie's big socks dangling and bobbing
<pb n="127"/>
beside Archie's from where they were tied on
the back part of the wagon.  We could hear
them talking and see them gesticulating.
When we came nearer, we found they were
quarreling, and they kept at it as long as I
was awake that night.  After the men had
disposed of their loads, they and Mr. Stewart
were going out of town to where a new coal-mine was being opened.  I intended to go on
the train to Rock Springs to do some shopping.
 Aggie said she was going also.  I suggested
that we get a room together, as we
would have to wait several hours for the
train, but she was suspicious of my motives.
She is greatly afraid of being "done," so she
told me to get my own room and pay for it.
We got into town about three o'clock in the
afternoon, and the train left at midnight.
</p><p>I had gone to my room, and Jerrine and
myself were enjoying a good rest after our
fatiguing drive, when my door was thrown
open and a very angry Aggie strode in.  They
asked us fifty cents each for our rooms.  Aggie
<pb n="128"/>
paid hers under protest and afterward got to
wondering how long she was entitled to its
use.  She had gone back to the clerk about it,
and he had told her for that night only.  She
argued that she should have her room for a
quarter, as she would only use it until midnight.
 When that failed, she asked for her
money back, but the clerk was out of patience
and refused her that.  Aggie was angry all
through.  She vowed she was being robbed.
After she had berated me soundly for submitting
so tamely, she flounced back to her own
room, declaring she would get even with the
robbers.  I had to hurry like everything that
night to get myself and Jerrine ready for the
train, so I could spare no time for Aggie.  She
was not at the depot, and Jerrine and I had
to go on to Rock Springs without her.  It is
only a couple of hours from Green River to
Rock Springs, so I had a good nap and a late
breakfast.  I did my shopping and was back
at Green River at two that afternoon.  The
first person I saw was Aggie.  She sat in the
<pb n="129"/>
depot, glowering at everybody.  She had a
basket of eggs and a pail of butter, which she
had been trying to sell.  She was waiting for
the night train, the only one she could get to
Rock Springs.  I asked her had she overslept.
"No, I didna," she replied.  Then, she proceeded
to tell me that, as she had paid for a
whole night's use of a room, she had stayed
to get its use.  That it had made her plans
miscarry didn't seem to count.
</p><p>After all our business was attended to, we
started for home.  The wagons were half a
day ahead of us.  When we came in sight,
we could see Aggie fanning the air with her
long arms, and we knew they were quarreling.
 I remarked that I could not understand
how persons who hated each other so could
live together.  Clyde told me I had much
to learn, and said that really he knew of no
other couple who were actually so devoted.
He said to prove it I should ask Aggie into
the buggy with me and he would get in with
Archie, and afterwards we would compare
<pb n="130"/>
notes.  He drove up alongside of them, and
Aggie seemed glad to make the exchange.
As we had the buggy, we drove ahead of the
wagons.  It seems that Archie and Aggie are
each jealous of the other.  Archie is as ugly
a little monkey as it would be possible to
imagine.  She bemeaned him until at last I
asked her why she didn't leave him, and
added that I would not stand such crankiness
for one moment.  Then she poured out
the vials of her wrath upon my head, only I
don't think they were vials but barrels.
</p><p>About sundown we made it to where we
intended to camp and found that Mrs.
O'Shaughnessy had established a sheep-camp
there, and was out with her herd herself,
having only Manny, a Mexican boy she had
brought up herself, for a herder.  She welcomed
us cordially and began supper for our
entire bunch.  Soon the wagons came, and all
was confusion for a few minutes getting the
horses put away for the night.  Aggie went
to her wagon as soon as it stopped and made
<pb n="131"/>
secure her butter and eggs against a possible
raid by Mrs. O'Shaughnessy.  Having asked
too high a price for them, she had failed to
sell them and was taking them back.  After
supper we were sitting around the fire, Tam
going over his account and lamenting that
because of his absent-mindedness he had
bought a whole hundred pounds of sugar
more than he had intended, Aggie and
Archie silent for once, pouting I suspect.
Clyde smiled across the camp-fire at me and
said, "Gin ye had sic a lass as I hae, ye might
blither."  "Gin ye had sic a mon as mine&mdash;"
I began, but Mrs. O'Shaughnessy said, "Gin
ye had sic a mon as I hae."  Then we all
three laughed, for we had each heard the
same thing, and we knew the McEttricks
wouldn't fight each other.  They suspected
us of laughing at them, for Archie said to
Aggie, "Aggie, lass, is it sport they are making
of our love?"  "'T is daft they be, Archie,
lad; we'll nae mind their blither."  She arose
and shambled across to Archie and hunkered
<pb n="132"/>
her big self down beside him.  We went to
bed and left them peaceable for once.
</p><p>I am really ashamed of the way I have
treated you, but I know you will forgive me.
I am not strong yet, and my eyes are still
bothering me, but I hope to be all right soon
now, and I promise you a better letter next
time.  Jerrine is very proud of her necklace.
I think they are so nice for children.  I can
remember how proud I was of mine when I
was a child.  Please give your brother our
thanks, and tell him his little gift made my
little girl very happy.
</p><p>I am afraid this letter will seem rather
jumbled.  I still want the address of your
friend in Salem or any other.  I shall find
time to write, and I am not going to let my
baby prevent me from having many enjoyable
outings.  We call our boy Henry Clyde
for his father.  He is a dear little thing, but
he is a lusty yeller for baby's rights.
</p><p>With much love,
</p><p>JERRINE AND HER MAMMA.


<pb n="133"/>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="13" id="d18">
<head> "PROVING UP" <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 14,1911.</head>
<salute>
DEAR MRS. CONEY,&mdash;
</salute>
<p>I think you must be expecting an answer
to your letter by now, so I will try to answer
as many of your questions as I remember.
Your letter has been mislaid.  We have been
very much rushed all this week.  We had the
thresher crew two days.  I was busy cooking
for them two days before they came, and
have been busy ever since cleaning up after
them.  Clyde has taken the thresher on up
the valley to thresh for the neighbors, and
all the men have gone along, so the children
and I are alone.  No, I shall not lose my land,
although it will be over two years before I
can get a deed to it.  The five years in which
I am required to "prove up" will have passed
by then.  I couldn't have held my homestead
<pb n="134"/>
if Clyde had also been proving up, but he
had accomplished that years ago and has his
deed, so I am allowed my homestead.  Also
I have not yet used my desert right, so I am
still entitled to one hundred and sixty acres
more.  I shall file on that much some day
when I have sufficient money of my own
earning.  The law requires a cash payment of
twenty-five cents per acre at the filing, and
one dollar more per acre when final proof is
made.  I should not have married if Clyde
had not promised I should meet all my land
difficulties unaided.  I wanted the fun and
the experience.  For that reason I want to
earn every cent that goes into my own land
and improvements myself.  Sometimes I almost
have a brain-storm wondering how I
am going to do it, but I know I shall succeed;
other women have succeeded.  I know of
several who are now where they can laugh
at past trials.  Do you know?&mdash;I am a firm
believer in laughter.  I am real superstitious
about it.  I think if Bad Luck came along, he
<pb n="135"/>
would take to his heels if some one laughed
right loudly.
</p><p>I think Jerrine must be born for the law.
She always threshes out questions that
arise, to her own satisfaction, if to no one
else's.  She prayed for a long time for her
brother; also she prayed for some puppies.
The puppies came, but we didn't let her
know they were here until they were able to
walk.  One morning she saw them following
their mother, so she danced for joy.  When
her little brother came she was plainly disappointed.
"Mamma," she said, "did God
really make the baby?"  "Yes, dear."  "Then
He hasn't treated us fairly, and I should
like to know why.  The puppies could walk
when He finished them; the calves can, too.
The pigs can, and the colt, and even the
chickens.  What is the use of giving us a half-finished baby?  He has no hair, and no teeth;
he can't walk or talk, nor do anything else
but squall and sleep."
</p><p>After many days she got the question
<pb n="136"/>
settled.  She began right where she left off.
"I know, Mamma, why God gave us such
a half-finished baby; so he could learn our
ways, and no one else's, since he must live
with us, and so we could learn to love him.
Every time I stand beside his buggy he
laughs and then I love him, but I don't love
Stella nor Marvin because they laugh.  So
that is why."  Perhaps that is the reason.
</p><p>Zebbie's kinsfolk have come and taken
him back to Yell County.  I should not be
surprised if he never returned.  The Lanes
and the Pattersons leave shortly for Idaho,
where "our Bobbie" has made some large
investments.
</p><p>I hope to hear from you soon and that you
are enjoying every minute.  With much love,
</p><p>Your friend,
</p><p>ELINORE STEWART.


<pb n="137"/>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="14" id="d19">
<head> "THE NEW HOUSE" <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 1, 1911.</head>
<salute>
DEAR MRS. CONEY,&mdash;
</salute>
<p>I feel just like visiting to-night, so I am
going to "play like" you have come.  It is so
good to have you to chat with.  Please be
seated in this low rocker; it is a present to
me from the Pattersons and I am very proud
of it.  I am just back from the Patterson
ranch, and they have a dear little boy who
came the 20th of November and they call
him Robert Lane.
</p><p>I am sure this room must look familiar to
you, for there is so much in it that was once
yours.  I have two rooms, each fifteen by
fifteen, but this one on the south is my
"really" room and in it are my treasures.
My house faces east and is built up against
a side-hill, or should I say hillside?  Anyway,
<pb n="138"/>
they had to excavate quite a lot.  I had them
dump the dirt right before the house and
terrace it smoothly.  I have sown my terrace
to California poppies, and around my porch,
which is six feet wide and thirty long, I have
planted wild cucumbers.
</p><p>Every log in my house is as straight as a
pine can grow.  Each room has a window and
a door on the east side, and the south room
has two windows on the south with space
between for my heater, which is one of those
with a grate front so I can see the fire burn.
It is almost as good as a fireplace.  The logs
are unhewed outside because I like the rough
finish, but inside the walls are perfectly
square and smooth.  The cracks in the walls
are snugly filled with "daubing" and then
the walls are covered with heavy gray
building-paper, which makes the room very
warm, and I really like the appearance.  I
had two rolls of wall-paper with a bold rose
pattern.  By being very careful I was able to
cut out enough of the roses, which are divided
<pb n="139"/>
in their choice of color as to whether they
should be red, yellow, or pink, to make a border
about eighteen inches from the ceiling.
They brighten up the wall and the gray paper
is fine to hang pictures upon.  Those you
have sent us make our room very attractive.
The woodwork is stained a walnut brown,
oil finish, and the floor is stained and oiled
just like it.  In the corners by the stove and
before the windows we take our comfort.
</p><p>From some broken bamboo fishing-rods I
made frames for two screens.  These I painted
black with some paint that was left from the
buggy, and Gavotte fixed the screens so they
will stay balanced, and put in casters for me.
I had a piece of blue curtain calico and with
brass-headed tacks I put it on the frame of
Jerrine's screen, then I mixed some paste
and let her decorate it to suit herself on
the side that should be next her corner.  She
used the cards you sent her.  Some of the
people have a suspiciously tottering appearance,
perhaps not so very artistic, but they
<pb n="140"/>
all mean something to a little girl whose
small fingers worked patiently to attain satisfactory
results.  She has a set of shelves on
which her treasures of china are arranged.
On the floor is a rug made of two goatskins
dyed black, a present from Gavotte, who
heard her admiring Zebbie's bearskin.  She
has a tiny red rocking-chair which she has
outgrown, but her rather dilapidated family
of dolls use it for an automobile.  For a seat
for herself she has a small hassock that you
gave me, and behind the blue screen is a
world apart.
</p><p>My screen is made just like Jerrine's except
that the cover is cream material with
sprays of wild roses over it.  In my corner I
have a cot made up like a couch.  One of my
pillows is covered with some checked gingham
that "Dawsie" cross-stitched for me.
I have a cabinet bookcase made from an old
walnut bedstead that was a relic of the Mountain
Meadow Massacre.  Gavotte made it for
me.  In it I have my few books, some odds
<pb n="141"/>
and ends of china, all gifts, and a few fossil
curios.  For a floor-covering I have a braided
rug of blue and white, made from old sheets
and Jerrine's old dresses.  In the center of
my room is a square table made of pine and
stained brown.  Over it is a table-cover that
you gave me.  Against the wall near my bed
is my "dresser."  It is a box with shelves
and is covered with the same material as my
screen.  Above it I have a mirror, but it
makes ugly faces at me every time I look
into it.  Upon the wall near by is a match-holder that you gave me.  It is the heads of
two fisher-folk.  The man has lost his nose,
but the old lady still thrusts out her tongue.
The material on my screen and "dresser" I
bought for curtains, then decided to use some
white crossbar I had.  But I wish I had not,
for every time I look at them I think of poor
little Mary Ann Parker.
</p><p>I am going to make you a cup of tea and
wonder if you will see anything familiar
about the teapot.  You should, I think, for it
<pb n="142"/>
is another of your many gifts to me.  Now
I feel that you have a fairly good idea of
what my house looks like, on the inside anyway.
 The magazines and Jerrine's cards and
Mother Goose book came long ago, and Jerrine
and I were both made happy.  I wish
I could do nice things for you, but all I can
do is to love you.
</p><p>Your sincere friend,
</p><p>ELINORE RUPERT.


<pb n="143"/>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="15" id="d20">
<head> "THE STOCKING-LEG DINNER" <hi rend="italic">February</hi>, 1912."</head>
<salute>
DEAR MRS. CONEY,&mdash;
</salute>
<p>. . .  This time I want to tell you about a
"stocking-leg" dinner which I attended not
long ago.  It doesn't sound very respectable,
but it was one of the happiest events I ever
remember.
</p><p>Mrs. Louderer was here visiting us, and
one afternoon we were all in the kitchen
when Gavotte came skimming along on the
first pair of snowshoes I ever saw.  We have
had lots of snow this winter, and many of the
hollows and gullies are packed full.  Gavotte
had no difficulty in coming, and he had come
for the mail and to invite us to a feast of "ze
hose."  I could not think what kind of a
dinner it could be, and I did not believe that
Mr. Stewart would go, but after Gavotte
<pb n="144"/>
had explained how much easier it was now
than at any other time because the hard-packed snow made it possible to go with
bobsleds, I knew he would go.  I can't say I
really wanted to go, but Mrs. Louderer took
it for granted that it would be delightful, so
she and Mr. Stewart did the planning.  Next
morning Gavotte met Mrs. O'Shaughnessy
and invited her.  Then, taking the mail, he
went on ahead to blaze a trail we should
follow with the sleds.  We were to start two
days later.  They planned we could easily
make the trip in a day, as, with the gulches
filled with snow, short cuts were possible,
and we could travel at a good pace, as we
would have a strong team.  To me it seemed
dangerous, but dinner-parties have not been
so plenty that I could miss one.  So, when the
day came on which we were to start, we were
up betimes and had a mess-box packed and
Mr. Stewart had a big pile of rocks hot.  We
all wore our warmest clothes, and the rest
carried out hot rocks and blankets while I
<pb n="145"/>
put the kitchen in such order that the men
left to feed the stock would have no trouble
in getting their meals.  Mr. Stewart carried
out the mess-box, and presently we were off.
We had a wagon-box on bobsleds, and the
box was filled with hay and hot rocks with
blankets on top and more to cover us.  Mr.
Stewart had two big bags of grain in front,
feed for the horses, and he sat on them.
</p><p>It was a beautiful day and we jogged along
merrily.  We had lots of fun, and as we went
a new way, there was much that was new to
Mrs. O'Shaughnessy and myself, and it was
all new to the rest.  Gavotte had told us
where we should noon, and we reached the
place shortly after twelve.  Mr. Stewart
went to lift out the mess-box,&mdash;but he had
forgotten to put it in!  Oh, dear!  We were
a disappointed lot.  I don't think I was ever
so hungry, but there was nothing for it but
to grin and bear it.  It did me some good,
though, to remember how a man misses his
dinner.  The horses had to be fed, so we
<pb n="146"/>
walked about while they were eating.  We
went up a canon that had high cliffs on one
side, and came to a place where, high up on
the rock wall, in great black letters, was this
legend: "Dick fell off of this here clift and
died."  I should think there would be no
question that any one who fell from that
place on to the boulders below <hi rend="italic">would</hi> die.
</p><p>Soon we started again, and if not quite so
jolly as we were before, at least we looked
forward to our supper with a keen relish and
the horses were urged faster than they otherwise
would have been.  The beautiful snow
is rather depressing, however, when there
is snow everywhere.  The afternoon passed
swiftly and the horses were becoming jaded.
At four o'clock it was almost dark.  We had
been going up a deep canon and came upon
an appalling sight.  There had been a snow-slide and the canon was half-filled with snow,
rock, and broken trees.  The whole way was
blocked, and what to do we didn't know, for
the horses could hardly be gotten along and
<pb n="147"/>
we could not pass the snow-slide.  We were
twenty-five miles from home, night was almost
upon us, and we were almost starved.
But we were afraid to stay in that canon lest
more snow should slide and bury us, so sadly
we turned back to find as comfortable a
place as we could to spend the night.  The
prospects were very discouraging, and I am
afraid we were all near tears, when suddenly
there came upon the cold air a clear blast
from a horn.  Mrs. Louderer cried, "Ach, der
reveille!"  Once I heard a lecturer tell of
climbing the Matterhorn and the calls we
heard brought his story to mind.  No music
could have been so beautiful.  It soon became
apparent that we were being signaled; so we
drove in the direction of the sound and found
ourselves going up a wide canon.  We had
passed the mouth of it shortly before we
had come to the slide.  Even the tired horses
took new courage, and every few moments a
sweet, clear call put new heart into us.  Soon
we saw a light.  We had to drive very slowly
<pb n="148"/>
and in places barely crept.  The bugler
changed his notes and we knew he was wondering
if we were coming, so Mr. Stewart
helloed.  At once we had an answer, and
after that we were steadily guided by the
horn.  Many times we could not see the light,
but we drove in the right direction because
we could hear the horn.
</p><p>At last, when it was quite dark and the
horses could go no farther, we drew up before
the fire that had been our beacon light.  It
was a bonfire built out upon a point of rock
at the end of the canon.  Back from it among
the pines was a 'dobe house.  A dried-up
mummy of a man advanced from the fire
to meet us, explaining that he had seen us
through his field-glasses and, knowing about
the snow-slide, had ventured to attract us
to his poor place.  Carlota Juanita was
within, prepared for the <hi rend="italic">senoras</hi>, if they
would but walk in.  If they would!  More
dead than alive, we scrambled out, cold-stiffened and hungry.  Carlota Juanita threw
<pb n="149"/>
open the low, wide door and we stumbled
into comfort.  She hastened to help us off
with our wraps, piled more wood on the
open fire, and busied herself to make us
welcome and comfortable.  Poor Carlota
Juanita!  Perhaps you think she was some
slender, limpid-eyed, olive-cheeked beauty.
She was fat and forty, but not fair.  She had
the biggest wad of hair that I ever saw, and
her face was so fat that her eyes looked
beady.  She wore an old heelless pair of
slippers or sandals that would hardly stay
on, and at every step they made the most
exasperating sliding noise, but she was all
kindness and made us feel very welcome.
The floor was of dirt, and they had the largest
fireplace I have ever seen, with the
widest, cleanest hearth, which was where
they did their cooking.  All their furniture
was home-made, and on a low bench near the
door were three water-jars which, I am sure,
were handmade.  Away back in a corner they
had a small altar, on which was a little statue
<pb n="150"/>
of Mary and the Child.  Before it, suspended
by a wire from the rafters, was a cow's horn
in which a piece of punk was burning, just as
the incense is kept burning in churches.  Supper
was already prepared and was simmering
and smoking on the hearth.  As soon as the
men came in, Carlota Juanita put it on the
table, which was bare of cloth.  I can't say
that I really like Mexican bread, but they
certainly know how to cook meat.  They had
a most wonderful pot-roast with potatoes and
corn dumplings that were delicious.  The roast
had been slashed in places and small bits of
garlic, pepper, bacon, and, I think, parsley,
inserted.  After it and the potatoes and the
dumplings were done, Carlota had poured
in a can of tomatoes.  You may not think
that was good, but I can assure you it was
and that we did ample justice to it.  After
we had eaten until we were hardly able to
swallow, Carlota Juanita served a queer
Mexican pie.  It was made of dried buffalo-berries, stewed and made very sweet.  A
<pb n="151"/>
layer of batter had been poured into a deep
baking-dish, then the berries, and then more
batter.  Then it was baked and served hot
with plenty of hard sauce; and it was powerful
good, too.  She had very peculiar coffee
with goat's milk in it.  I took mine without
the milk, but I couldn't make up my mind
that I liked the coffee.  We sat around the
fire drinking it, when Manuel Pedro Felipe
told us it was some he had brought from
Mexico.  I didn't know they raised it there,
but he told us many interesting things about
it.  He and Carlota Juanita both spoke
fairly good English.  They had lived for
many years in their present home and had
some sheep, a few goats, a cow or two, a few
pigs, and chickens and turkeys.  They had a
small patch of land that Carlota Juanita
tilled and on which was raised the squaw
corn that hung in bunches from the rafters.
Down where we live we can't get sweet corn
to mature, but here, so much higher up, they
have a sheltered little nook where they are
<pb n="152"/>
able to raise many things.  Upon a long shelf
above the fire was an ugly old stone image,
the bottom broken off and some plaster
applied to make it set level.  The ugly thing
they had brought with them from some old
ruined temple in Mexico.  We were all so
very tired that soon Carlota Juanita brought
out an armful of the thickest, brightest rugs
and spread them over the floor for us to sleep
upon.  The men retired to a lean-to room,
where they slept, but not before Manuel
Pedro Felipe and Carlota had knelt before
their altar for their devotions.  Mrs.
O'Shaughnessy and myself and Jerrine,
knowing the rosary, surprised them by
kneeling with them.  It is good to meet with
kindred faith away off in the mountains.  It
seems there could not possibly be a mistake
when people so far away from creeds and
doctrines hold to the faith of their child-hood and find the practice a pleasure after
so many years.  The men bade us goodnight,
and we lost no time in settling ourselves
<pb n="153"/>
to rest.  Luckily we had plenty of
blankets.
</p><p>Away in the night I was awakened by a
noise that frightened me.  All was still, but
instantly there flashed through my mind
tales of murdered travelers, and I was almost
paralyzed with fear when again I heard
that stealthy, sliding noise, just like Carlota
Juanita's old slippers.  The fire had burned
down, but just then the moon came from
behind a cloud and shone through the window
upon Carlota Juanita, who was asleep
with her mouth open.  I could also see a pine
bough which was scraping against the wall
outside, which was perhaps making the noise.
I turned over and saw the punk burning,
which cast a dim light over the serene face
of the Blessed Virgin, so all fear vanished
and I slept as long as they would let me in
the morning.  After a breakfast of <hi rend="italic">tortillas</hi>,
cheese, and rancid butter, and some more of
the coffee, we started again for the stocking-leg dinner.  Carlota Juanita stood in the
<pb n="154"/>
door, waving to us as long as we could see
her, and Manuel P. F. sat with Mr. Stewart
to guide us around the snow-slide.  Under
one arm he carried the horn with which he
had called us to him.  It came from some
long-horned cow in Mexico, was beautifully
polished, and had a fancy rim of silver.  I
should like to own it, but I could not make
it produce a sound.  When we were safe on
our way our guide left us, and our spirits
ran high again.  The horses were feeling
good also, so it was a merry, laughing party
that drew up before Zebbie's two hours
later.
</p><p>Long before I had lent Gavotte a set of
the Leather-Stocking Tales, which he had
read aloud to Zebbie.  Together they had
planned a Leather-Stocking dinner, at which
should be served as many of the viands mentioned
in the Tales as possible.  We stayed
two days and it was one long feast.  We had
venison served in half a dozen different ways.
We had antelope; we had porcupine, or
<pb n="155"/>
hedgehog, as Pathfinder called it; and also
we had beaver-tail, which he found toothsome,
but which I did <hi rend="italic">not</hi>.  We had grouse
and sage hen.  They broke the ice and
snared a lot of trout.  In their cellar they
had a barrel of trout prepared exactly like
mackerel, and they were more delicious than
mackerel because they were finer-grained.
I had been a little disappointed in Zebbie
after his return from home.  It seemed to me
that Pauline had spoiled him.  I guess I was
jealous.  This time he was the same little old
Zebbie I had first seen.  He seemed to thoroughly
enjoy our visit, and I am sure we
each had the time of our lives.  We made
it home without mishap the same day we
started, all of us sure life held something
new and enjoyable after all.
</p><p>If nothing happens there are some more
good times in store for me this summer.
Gavotte once worked under Professor Marsden
when he was out here getting fossils for
the Smithsonian Institution, and he is very
<pb n="156"/>
interesting to listen to.  He has invited us to
go with him out to the Bad-Land hills in
the summer to search for fossils.  The hills
are only a few miles from here and I look
forward to a splendid time.


<pb n="157"/>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="16" id="d21">
<head> "THE HORSE-THIEVES" </head>
<salute>
DEAR MRS. CONEY,&mdash;
</salute>
<p>. . . I am so afraid that you will get an
overdose of culture from your visit to the
Hub and am sending you an antidote of our
sage, sand, and sunshine.
</p><p>Mrs. Louderer had come over to see our
boy.  Together we had prepared supper and
were waiting for Clyde, who had gone to the
post-office.  Soon he came, and after the
usual friendly wrangling between him and
Mrs. Louderer we had supper.  Then they
began their inevitable game of cribbage,
while I sat near the fire with Baby on my lap.
Clyde was telling us of a raid on a ranch
about seventy-five miles away, in which the
thieves had driven off thirty head of fine
horses.  There were only two of the thieves,
<pb n="158"/>
and the sheriff with a large posse was pursuing
them and forcing every man they came
across into the chase, and a regular man-hunt
was on.  It was interesting only because one
of the thieves was a noted outlaw then out
on parole and known to be desperate.  We
were in no way alarmed; the trouble was all
in the next county, and somehow that always
seems so far away.  We knew if the men ever
came together there would be a pitched
battle, with bloodshed and death, but there
seemed little chance that the sheriff would
ever overtake the men.
</p><p>I remember I was feeling sorry for the poor
fellows with a price on their heads,&mdash;the
little pink man on my lap had softened my
heart wonderfully.  Jerrine was enjoying the
pictures in a paper illustrating early days on
the range, wild scenes of roping and branding.
 I had remarked that I didn't believe
there were any more such times, when Mrs.
Louderer replied, "Dot yust shows how much
it iss you do not know.  You shall come to
<pb n="159"/>
mine house and when away you come it shall
be wiser as when you left."  I had kept at
home very closely all summer, and a little
trip seemed the most desirable thing I could
think of, particularly as the baby would be
in no way endangered.  But long ago I learned
that the quickest way to get what I want
is not to want it, outwardly, at least.  So I
assumed an indifference that was not very
real.  The result was that next morning every
one was in a hurry to get me started,&mdash;
Clyde greasing the little old wagon that looks
like a twin to Cora Belle's, and Mrs. Louderer,
who thinks no baby can be properly
brought up without goose-grease, busy greasing
the baby "so as he shall not some cold
take yet."  Mrs. Louderer had ridden over,
so her saddle was laid in the wagon and her
pony, Bismarck, was hitched in with Chub,
the laziest horse in all Wyoming.  I knew
Clyde could manage very well while I should
be gone, and there wasn't a worry to interfere
with the pleasure of my outing.
<pb n="160"/>
</p><p>We jogged along right merrily, Mrs.
Louderer devoting her entire attention to
trying to make Chub pull even with Bismarck,
Jerrine and myself enjoying the ever-changing views.  I wish I could lay it all
before you.  Summer was departing with
reluctant feet, unafraid of Winter's messengers,
the chill winds.  That day was especially
beautiful.  The gleaming snow peaks and
heavy forest south and at our back; west,
north, and east, long, broken lines of the distant
mountains with their blue haze.  Pilot
Butte to the north, one hundred miles away,
stood out clear and distinct as though we
could drive there in an hour or two.  The
dull, neutral-colored "Bad Land" hills nearer
us are interesting only because we know
they are full of the fossil remains of strange
creatures long since extinct.
</p><p>For a distance our way lay up Henry's
Fork valley; prosperous little ranches dotted
the view, ripening grain rustled pleasantly in
the warm morning sunshine, and closely cut
<pb n="161"/>
alfalfa fields made bright spots of emerald
against the dun landscape.  The quaking
aspens were just beginning to turn yellow;
everywhere purple asters were a blaze of
glory except where the rabbit-bush grew in
clumps, waving its feathery plumes of gold.
Over it all the sky was so deeply blue, with
little, airy, white clouds drifting lazily along.
Every breeze brought scents of cedar, pine,
and sage.  At this point the road wound
along the base of cedar hills; some magpies
were holding a noisy caucus among the trees,
a pair of bluebirds twittered excitedly upon
a fence, and high overhead a great black
eagle soared.  All was so peaceful that horse-thieves and desperate men seemed too remote
to think about.
</p><p>Presently we crossed the creek and headed
our course due north toward the desert and
the buttes.  I saw that we were not going
right to reach Mrs. Louderer's ranch, so I
asked where we were supposed to be going.
"We iss going to the mouth of Dry Creek by,
<pb n="162"/>
where it goes Black's Fork into.  Dere mine
punchers holdts five huntert steers.  We shall
de camp visit and you shall come back wiser
as when you went."
</p><p>Well, we both came away wiser.  I had
thought we were going only to the Louderer
ranch, so I put up no lunch, and there was
nothing for the horses either.  But it was too
beautiful a time to let such things annoy us.
Anyway, we expected to reach camp just
after noon, so a little delay about dinner
didn't seem so bad.  We had entered the
desert by noon; the warm, red sands fell
away from the wheels with soft, hissing
sounds.  Occasionally a little horned toad
sped panting along before us, suddenly darting
aside to watch with bright, cunning eyes
as we passed.  Some one had placed a buffalo's
skull beside a big bunch of sage and on
the sage a splendid pair of elk's antlers.  We
saw many such scattered over the sands,
grim reminders of a past forever gone.
</p><p>About three o'clock we reached our destination,
<pb n="163"/>
but no camp was there.  We were
more disappointed than I can tell you, but
Mrs. Louderer merely went down to the
river, a few yards away, and cut an armful of
willow sticks wherewith to coax Chub to a
little brisker pace, and then we took the trail
of the departed mess-wagon.  Shortly, we
topped a low range of hills, and beyond, in a
cuplike valley, was the herd of sleek beauties
feeding contentedly on the lush green grass.
I suppose it sounds odd to hear desert and
river in the same breath, but within a few
feet of the river the desert begins, where
nothing grows but sage and greasewood.  In
oasis-like spots will be found plenty of grass
where the soil is nearer the surface and where
sub-irrigation keeps the roots watered.  In
one of these spots the herd was being held.
When the grass became short they would be
moved to another such place.
</p><p>It required, altogether, fifteen men to take
care of the herd, because many of the cattle
had been bought in different places, some in
<pb n="164"/>
Utah, and these were always trying to run
away and work back toward home, so they
required constant herding.  Soon we caught
the glimmer of white canvas, and knew it
was the cover of the mess-wagon, so we
headed that way.
</p><p>The camp was quite near the river so as
to be handy to water and to have the willows
for wood.  Not a soul was at camp.  The
fire was out, and even the ashes had blown
away.  The mess-box was locked and Mrs.
Louderer's loud calls brought only echoes
from the high rock walls across the river.
However, there was nothing to do but to
make the best of it, so we tethered the horses
and went down to the river to relieve ourselves
of the dust that seemed determined to
unite with the dust that we were made of.
Mrs. Louderer declared she was "so mat as
nodings and would fire dot Herman so soon
as she could see him alreaty."
</p><p>Presently we saw the most grotesque figure
approaching camp.  It was Herman, the
<pb n="165"/>
fat cook, on Hunks, a gaunt, ugly old horse,
whose days of usefulness under the saddle
were past and who had degenerated into a
workhorse.  The disgrace of it seemed to
be driving him into a decline, but he stumbled
along bravely under his heavy load.  A
string of a dozen sage chickens swung on
one side, and across the saddle in front of
Herman lay a young antelope.  A volley of
German abuse was hurled at poor Herman,
wound up in as plain American as Mrs.
Louderer could speak: "And who iss going
to pay de game warden de fine of dot antelope
what you haf shot?  And how iss it that
we haf come de camp by und so starved as
we iss hungry, and no cook und no food?  Iss
dat for why you iss paid?"
</p><p>Herman was some Dutch himself, however.
"How iss it," he demanded, "dat you haf
not so much sense as you haf tongue?  How
haf you lived so long as always in de West
und don't know enough to hunt a bean-hole
when you reach your own camp.  Hey?"
<pb n="166"/>
</p><p>Mrs. Louderer was very properly subdued
and I delighted when he removed the stones
from where the fire had been, exposing a pit
from which, with a pair of pot-hooks, he
lifted pots and ovens of the most delicious
meat, beans, and potatoes.  From the messbox
he brought bread and apricot pie.  From
a near-by spring he brought us a bright, new
pail full of clear, sparkling water, but Mrs.
Louderer insisted upon tea and in a short
time he had it ready for us.  The tarpaulin
was spread on the ground for us to eat from,
and soon we were showing an astonished
cook just how much food two women and a
child could get away with.  I ate a good deal
of ashes with my roast beef and we all ate
more or less sand, but fastidiousness about
food is a good thing to get rid of when you
come West to camp.
</p><p>When the regular supper-time arrived the
punchers began to gather in, and the "boss,"
who had been to town about some business,
came in and brought back the news of the
<pb n="167"/>
man-hunt.  The punchers sat about the fire,
eating hungrily from their tin plates and
eagerly listening to the recital.  Two of the
boys were tenderfeet: one from Tennessee
called "Daisy Belle," because he whistled
that tune so much and because he had
nose-bleed so much,&mdash;couldn't even ride a
broncho but his nose would bleed for hours
afterwards; and the other, "N'Yawk," so
called from his native State.  N'Yawk was a
great boaster; said he wasn't afraid of no
durned outlaw,&mdash;said his father had waded
in bloody gore up to his neck and that he
was a chip off the old block,&mdash;rather hoped
the chase would come our way so he could
try his marksmanship.
</p><p>The air began to grow chill and the sky
was becoming overcast.  Preparations for the
night busied everybody.  Fresh ponies were
being saddled for the night relief, the hard-ridden,
tired ones that had been used that
day being turned loose to graze.  Some poles
were set up and a tarpaulin arranged for
<pb n="168"/>
Mrs. Louderer and me to sleep under.  Mrs.
Louderer and Jerrine lay down on some
blankets and I unrolled some more, which I
was glad to notice were clean, for Baby and
myself.  I can't remember ever being more
tired and sleepy, but I couldn't go to sleep.
I could hear the boss giving orders in quick,
decisive tones.  I could hear the punchers
discussing the raid, finally each of them telling
exploits of his favorite heroes of outlawry.
 I could hear Herman, busy among
his pots and pans.  Then he mounted the
tongue of the mess-wagon and called out,
"We haf for breakfast cackle-berries, first
vot iss come iss served, und those vot iss
sleep late gets nodings."
</p><p>I had never before heard of cackle-berries
and asked sleepy Mrs. Louderer what they
were.  "Vait until morning and you shall
see," was all the information that I received.
</p><p>Soon a gentle, drizzling rain began, and
the punchers hurriedly made their beds, as
they did so twitting N'Yawk about making
<pb n="169"/>
his between our tent and the fire.  "You're
dead right, pard," I heard one of them say,
"to make your bed there, fer if them outlaws
comes this way they'll think you air one of
the women and they won't shoot you.  Just
us <hi rend="italic">men</hi> air in danger."
</p><p>"Confound your fool tongues, how they
goin' to know there's any women here?  I
tell you, fellers, my old man waded in bloody
gore up to his neck and I'm just like him."
</p><p>They kept up this friendly parleying until
I dozed off to sleep, but I couldn't stay
asleep.  I don't think I was afraid, but I certainly
was nervous.  The river was making a
sad, moaning sound; the rain fell gently, like
tears.  All nature seemed to be mourning
about something, happened or going to happen.
 Down by the river an owl hooted dismally.
 Half a mile away the night-herders
were riding round and round the herd.  One
of them was singing,&mdash;faint but distinct
came his song: "Bury me not on the lone
prairie."  Over and over again he sang it.
<pb n="170"/>
After a short interval of silence he began
again.  This time it was, "I'm thinking of
my dear old mother, ten thousand miles
away."
</p><p>Two punchers stirred uneasily and began
talking.  "Blast that Tex," I heard one of
them say, "he certainly has it bad to-night.
What the deuce makes him sing so much?  I
feel like bawling like a kid; I wish he'd shut
up."  "He's homesick; I guess we all are too,
but they ain't no use staying awake and letting
it soak in.  Shake the water off the tarp,
you air lettin' water catch on your side an'
it's running into my ear."
</p><p>That is the last I heard for a long time.  I
must have slept.  I remember that the baby
stirred and I spoke to him.  It seemed to me
that something struck against the guy-rope
that held our tarpaulin taut, but I wasn't
sure.  I was in that dozy state, half asleep,
when nothing is quite clear.  It seemed as
though I had been listening to the tramp of
feet for hours and that a whole army must
<pb n="171"/>
be filing past, when I was brought suddenly
into keen consciousness by a loud voice
demanding, "Hello!  Whose outfit is this?"
"This is the 7 Up,&mdash;Louderer's," the boss
called back; "what's wanted?"  "Is that
you, Mat?  This is Ward's posse.  We been
after Meeks and Murdock all night.  It's so
durned dark we can't see, but we got to keep
going; their horses are about played.  We
changed at Hadley's, but we ain't had a bite
to eat and we got to search your camp."
"Sure thing," the boss answered, "roll off
and take a look.  Hi, there, you Herm, get
out of there and fix these fellers something
to eat."
</p><p>We were surrounded.  I could hear the
clanking of spurs and the sound of the wet,
tired horses shaking themselves and rattling
the saddles on every side.  "Who's in the
wickiup?" I heard the sheriff ask.  "Some
women and kids,&mdash;Mrs. Louderer and a
friend."
</p><p>In an incredibly short time Herman had a
<pb n="172"/>
fire coaxed into a blaze and Mat Watson and
the sheriff went from bed to bed with a lantern.
 They searched the mess-wagon, even,
although Herman had been sleeping there.
The sheriff unceremoniously flung out the
wood and kindling the cook had stored there.
He threw back the flap of our tent and flashed
the lantern about.  He could see plainly
enough that there were but the four of us,
but I wondered how they saw outside where
the rain made it worse, the lantern was so
dirty.  "Yes," I heard the sheriff say, "we've
been pushing them hard.  They're headed
north, evidently intend to hit the railroad
but they'll never make it.  Every ford on the
river is guarded except right along here, and
there's five parties ranging on the other side.
My party's split,&mdash;a bunch has gone on to
the bridge.  If they find anything they're to
fire a volley.  Same with us.  I knew they
couldn't cross the river nowhere but at the
bridge or here."
</p><p>The men had gathered about the fire and
<pb n="173"/>
were gulping hot coffee and cold beef and
bread.  The rain ran off their slickers in little
rivulets.  I was sorry the fire was not better,
because some of the men had on only ordinary
coats, and the drizzling rain seemed
determined that the fire should not blaze
high.
</p><p>Before they had finished eating we heard
a shot, followed by a regular medley of dull
booms.  The men were in their saddles and
gone in less time than it takes to tell it.  The
firing had ceased save for a few sharp reports
from the revolvers, like a coyote's spiteful
snapping.  The pounding of the horse's hoofs
grew fainter, and soon all was still.  I kept
my ears strained for the slightest sound.  The
cook and the boss, the only men up, hurried
back to bed.  Watson had risen so hurriedly
that he had not been careful about his
"tarp" and water had run into his bed.  But
that wouldn't disconcert anybody but a
tenderfoot.  I kept waiting in tense silence
to hear them come back with dead or
<pb n="174"/>
wounded, but there was not a sound.  The
rain had stopped.  Mrs. Louderer struck a
match and said it was three o'clock.  Soon she
was asleep.  Through a rift in the clouds a
star peeped out.  I could smell the wet sage
and the sand.  A little breeze came by,
bringing Tex's song once more:&mdash;
</p>
<lg type="poem">
<l>Oh, it matters not, so I've been told,</l>
<l>How the body lies when the heart grows cold."</l>
</lg>
<p>
Oh, dear! the world seemed so full of sadness.
I kissed my baby's little downy head
and went to sleep.
</p><p>It seems that cowboys are rather sleepy-headed in the morning and it is a part of the
cook's job to get them up.  The next I knew,
Herman had a tin pan on which he was beating
a vigorous tattoo, all the time hollering,
"We haf cackle-berries und antelope steak
for breakfast."  The baby was startled by the
noise, so I attended to him and then dressed
myself for breakfast.  I went down to the
little spring to wash my face.  The morning
was lowering and gray, but a wind had
<pb n="175"/>
sprung up and the clouds were parting.  There
are times when anticipation is a great deal
better than realization.  Never having seen
a cackle-berry, my imagination pictured
them as some very luscious wild fruit, and
I was so afraid none would be left that I
couldn't wait until the men should eat and
be gone.  So I surprised them by joining the
very earliest about the fire.  Herman began
serving breakfast.  I held out my tin plate
and received some of the steak, an egg, and
two delicious biscuits.  We had our coffee in
big enameled cups, without sugar or cream,
but it was piping hot and <hi rend="italic">so</hi> good.  I had
finished my egg and steak and so I told
Herman I was ready for my cackle-berries.
</p><p>"Listen to her now, will you?" he asked.
And then indignantly, "How many cackle-berries does you want?  You haf had so many
as I haf cooked for you."  "Why, Herman, I
haven't had a single berry," I said.  Then
such a roar of laughter.  Herman gazed at
me in astonishment, and Mr. Watson gently
<pb n="176"/>
explained to me that eggs and cackle-berries
were one and the same.
</p><p>N'Yawk was not yet up, so Herman
walked over to his bed, kicked him a few
times, and told him he would scald him if he
didn't turn out.  It was quite light by then.
N'Yawk joined us in a few minutes.  "What
the deuce was you fellers kicking up such
a rumpus fer last night?" he asked.  "You
blamed blockhead, don't you know?" the
boss answered.  "Why, the sheriff searched
this camp last night.  They had a battle
down at the bridge afterwards and either
they are all killed or else no one is hurt.
They would have been here otherwise.  Ward
took a shot at them once yesterday, but I
guess he didn't hit; the men got away, anyway.
 And durn your sleepy head! you just
lay there and snored.  Well, I'll be danged!"
Words failed him, his wonder and disgust
were so great.
</p><p>N'Yawk turned to get his breakfast.  His
light shirt was blood-stained in the back,&mdash;
<pb n="177"/>
seemed to be soaked.  "What's the matter
with your shirt, it's soaked with blood?"
some one asked.  "Then that durned Daisy
Belle has been crawling in with me, that's
all," he said.  "Blame his bleeding snoot.
I'll punch it and give it something to bleed
for."
</p><p>Then Mr. Watson said, "Daisy ain't been
in all night.  He took Jesse's place when he
went to town after supper."  That started
an inquiry and search which speedily showed
that some one with a bleeding wound had
gotten in with N'Yawk.  It also developed
that Mr. Watson's splendid horse and saddle
were gone, the rope that the horse had been
picketed with lying just as it had been cut
from his neck.
</p><p>Now all was bustle and excitement.  It was
plainly evident that one of the outlaws had
lain hidden on N'Yawk's bed while the sheriff
was there, and that afterwards he had saddled
the horse and made his escape.  His own
horse was found in the willows, the saddle
<pb n="178"/>
cut loose and the bridle off, but the poor,
jaded thing had never moved.  By sunup the
search-party returned, all too worn-out with
twenty-four hours in the saddle to continue
the hunt.  They were even too worn-out to
eat, but flung themselves down for a few
hours' rest.  The chase was hopeless anyway,
for the search-party had gone north in the
night.  The wounded outlaw had doubtless
heard the sheriff talking and, the coast being
clear to the southward, had got the fresh
horse and was by that time probably safe in
the heavy forests and mountains of Utah.
His getting in with N'Yawk had been a
daring ruse, but a successful one.  Where his
partner was, no one could guess.  But by
that time all the camp excepting Herman
and Mrs. Louderer were so panicky that we
couldn't have made a rational suggestion.
</p><p>N'Yawk, white around his mouth, approached
Mrs. Louderer.  "I want to quit,"
he said.  "Well," she said, calmly sipping her
coffee, "you haf done it."  "I'm sick," he
<pb n="179"/>
stammered.  "I know you iss," she said, "I
haf before now seen men get sick when they
iss scared to death."  "My old daddy&mdash;" he
began.  "Yes, I know, he waded the creek vone
time und you has had cold feet effer since."
</p><p>Poor fellow, I felt sorry for him.  I had cold
feet myself just then, and I was powerfully
anxious to warm them by my own fire where
a pair of calm blue eyes would reassure me.
</p><p>I didn't get to see the branding that was
to have taken place on the range that day.
The boss insisted on taking the trail of
his valued horse.  He was very angry.  He
thought there was a traitor among the posse.
Who started the firing at the bridge no one
knew, and Watson said openly that it was
done to get the sheriff away from camp.
</p><p>My own home looked mighty good to me
when we drove up that evening.  I don't
want any more wild life on the range,&mdash;not
for a while, anyway.
</p><p>Your ex-Washlady,
</p><p>ELINORE RUPERT STEWART.


<pb n="180"/>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="17" id="d22">
<head> "AT GAVOTTE'S CAMP" <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 16, 1912.</head>
<salute>
MY DEAR FRIEND,&mdash;
</salute>
<p>At last I can write you as I want to.  I am
afraid you think I am going to wait until the
"bairns" are grown up before writing to my
friends, but indeed I shall not.  I fully intend
to "gather roses while I may."  Since God
has given me two blessings, children and
friends, I shall enjoy them both as I go
along.
</p><p>I must tell you why I have not written as I
should have done.  All summer long my eyes
were so strained and painful that I had to let
all reading and writing go.  And I have suffered
terribly with my back.  But now I am
able to be about again, do most of my own
work, and my eyes are much better.  So now
I shall not treat you so badly again.  If you
<pb n="181"/>
could only know how kind every one is to me,
you would know that even ill health has its
compensations out here.  Dear Mrs. Louderer,
with her goose-grease, her bread, and
her delicious "kuchens."  Mrs. O'Shaughnessy,
with her cheery ways, her tireless
friendship, and willing, capable hands.
Gavotte even, with his tidbits of game and
fish.  Dear little Cora Belle came often to see
me, sometimes bringing me a little of Grandpa's
latest cure, which I received on faith,
for, of course, I could not really swallow any
of it.  Zebbie's nephew, Parker Carter, came
out, spent the summer with him, and they
have now gone back to Yell County, leaving
Gavotte in charge again.
</p><p>Gavotte had a most interesting and prosperous
summer.  He was commissioned by a
wealthy Easterner to procure some fossils.
I had had such a confined summer that Clyde
took me out to Gavotte's camp as soon as I
was able to sit up and be driven.  We found
him away over in the bad lands camped in a
<pb n="182"/>
fine little grove.  He is a charming man to
visit at any time, and we found him in a
particularly happy mood.  He had just begun to
quarry a gigantic find; he had piles of specimens;
he had packed and shipped some rare
specimens of fossil plants, but his "beeg
find" came later and he was jubilant.  To
dig fossils successfully requires great care
and knowledge, but it is a work in which
Gavotte excels.  He is a splendid cook.  I
almost believe he could make a Johnny Reb
like codfish, and that night we had a delicious
supper and all the time listening to a learned
discourse about prehistoric things.  I enjoyed
the meal and I enjoyed the talk, but I could
not sleep peacefully for being chased in
my dreams by pterodactyls, dinosaurs, and
iguanodons, besides a great many horrible
creatures whose names I have forgotten.  Of
course, when the ground begins to freeze and
snow comes, fossil-mining is done for until
summer comes, so Gavotte tends the critters
and traps this winter.  I shall not get to go
<pb n="183"/>
to the mountains this winter.  The babies are
too small, but there is always some happy
and interesting thing happening, and I shall
have two pleasures each time, my own enjoyment,
and getting to tell you of them.


<pb n="184"/>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="18" id="d23">
<head> "THE HOMESTEADER'S MARRIAGE AND A LITTLE FUNERAL
<hi rend="italic">December</hi> 2, 1912.</head>
<salute>
DEAR MRS. CONEY,&mdash;
</salute>
<p>Every time I get a new letter from you I
get a new inspiration, and I am always glad
to hear from you.
</p><p>I have often wished I might tell you all
about my Clyde, but have not because of
two things.  One is I could not even begin
without telling you what a good man he is,
and I didn't want you to think I could do
nothing but brag.  The other reason is the
haste I married in.  I am ashamed of that.
I am afraid you will think me a Becky Sharp
of a person.  But although I married in
haste, I have no cause to repent.  That is
very fortunate because I have never had one
bit of leisure to repent in.  So I am lucky all
<pb n="185"/>
around.  The engagement was powerfully
short because both agreed that the trend of
events and ranch work seemed to require
that we be married first and do our "sparking"
afterward.  You see, we had to chink
in the wedding between times, that is, between
planting the oats and other work that
must be done early or not at all.  In Wyoming
ranchers can scarcely take time even
to be married in the springtime.  That having
been settled, the license was sent for by
mail, and as soon as it came Mr. Stewart
saddled Chub and went down to the house of
Mr. Pearson, the justice of the peace and a
friend of long standing.  I had never met any
of the family and naturally rather dreaded
to have them come, but Mr. Stewart was
firm in wanting to be married at home, so
he told Mr. Pearson he wanted him and his
family to come up the following Wednesday
and serve papers on the "wooman i' the
hoose."  They were astonished, of course,
but being such good friends they promised
<pb n="186"/>
him all the assistance they could render.
They are quite the dearest, most interesting
family!  I have since learned to love them
as my own.
</p><p>Well, there was no time to make wedding
clothes, so I had to "do up" what I did have.
Isn't it queer how sometimes, do what you
can, work will keep getting in the way until
you can't get anything done?  That is how
it was with me those few days before the
wedding; so much so that when Wednesday
dawned everything was topsy-turvy and I
had a very strong desire to run away.  But
I always did hate a "piker," so I stood pat.
Well, I had most of the dinner cooked, but it
kept me hustling to get the house into anything
like decent order before the old dog
barked, and I knew my moments of liberty
were limited.  It was blowing a perfect hurricane
and snowing like midwinter.  I had
bought a beautiful pair of shoes to wear on
that day, but my vanity had squeezed my
feet a little, so while I was so busy at work I
<pb n="187"/>
had kept on a worn old pair, intending to put
on the new ones later; but when the Pearsons
drove up all I thought about was getting
them into the house where there was fire, so I
forgot all about the old shoes and the apron
I wore.
</p><p>I had only been here six weeks then, and
was a stranger.  That is why I had no one to
help me and was so confused and hurried.
As soon as the newcomers were warm, Mr.
Stewart told me I had better come over by
him and stand up.  It was a large room I had
to cross, and how I did it before all those
strange eyes I never knew.  All I can remember
very distinctly is hearing Mr. Stewart
saying, "I will," and myself chiming in that
I would, too.  Happening to glance down, I
saw that I had forgotten to take off my apron
or my old shoes, but just then Mr. Pearson
pronounced us man and wife, and as I had
dinner to serve right away I had no time to
worry over my odd toilet.  Anyway the shoes
were comfortable and the apron white, so I
<pb n="188"/>
suppose it could have been worse; and I don't
think it has ever made any difference with
the Pearsons, for I number them all among
my most esteemed friends.
</p><p>It is customary here for newlyweds to give
a dance and supper at the hall, but as I was
a stranger I preferred not to, and so it was a
long time before I became acquainted with
all my neighbors.  I had not thought I should
ever marry again.  Jerrine was always such
a dear little pal, and I wanted to just knock
about foot-loose and free to see life as a
gypsy sees it.  I had planned to see the Cliff-Dwellers' home; to live right there until I
caught the spirit of the surroundings enough
to live over their lives in imagination anyway.
 I had planned to see the old missions
and to go to Alaska; to hunt in Canada.  I
even dreamed of Honolulu.  Life stretched
out before me one long, happy jaunt.  I aimed
to see all the world I could, but to travel unknown
bypaths to do it.  But first I wanted
to try homesteading.
<pb n="189"/>
</p><p>But for my having the grippe, I should
never have come to Wyoming.  Mrs. Seroise,
who was a nurse at the institution for nurses
in Denver while I was housekeeper there, had
worked one summer at Saratoga, Wyoming.
It was she who told me of the pine forests.
I had never seen a pine until I came to
Colorado; so the idea of a home among the
pines fascinated me.  At that time I was
hoping to pass the Civil-Service examination,
with no very definite idea as to what I would
do, but just to be improving my time and
opportunity.  I never went to a public school
a day in my life.  In my childhood days there
was no such thing in the Indian Territory
part of Oklahoma where we lived, so I have
had to try hard to keep learning.  Before the
time came for the examination I was so discouraged
because of the grippe that nothing
but the mountains, the pines, and the clean,
fresh air seemed worth while; so it all came
about just as I have written you.
</p><p>So you see I was very deceitful.  Do you
<pb n="190"/>
remember, I wrote you of a little baby boy
dying?  That was my own little Jamie, our
first little son.  For a long time my heart was
crushed.  He was such a sweet, beautiful boy.
I wanted him so much.  He died of erysipelas.
I held him in my arms till the last agony was
over.  Then I dressed the beautiful little
body for the grave.  Clyde is a carpenter; so
I wanted him to make the little coffin.  He
did it every bit, and I lined and padded it,
trimmed and covered it.  Not that we could
n't afford to buy one or that our neighbors
were not all that was kind and willing; but
because it was a sad pleasure to do everything
for our little first-born ourselves.
</p><p>As there had been no physician to help, so
there was no minister to comfort, and I could
not bear to let our baby leave the world
without leaving any message to a community
that sadly needed it.  His little message to us
had been love, so I selected a chapter from
John and we had a funeral service, at which
all our neighbors for thirty miles around
<pb n="191"/>
were present.  So you see, our union is sealed
by love and welded by a great sorrow.
</p><p>Little Jamie was the first little Stewart.
God has given me two more precious little
sons.  The old sorrow is not so keen now.  I
can bear to tell you about it, but I never
could before.  When you think of me, you
must think of me as one who is truly happy.
It is true, I want a great many things I have
n't got, but I don't want them enough to be
discontented and not enjoy the many blessings
that are mine.  I have my home among
the blue mountains, my healthy, well-formed
children, my clean, honest husband, my kind,
gentle milk cows, my garden which I make
myself.  I have loads and loads of flowers
which I tend myself.  There are lots of chickens,
turkeys, and pigs which are my own
special care.  I have some slow old gentle
horses and an old wagon.  I can load up the
kiddies and go where I please any time.  I
have the best, kindest neighbors and I have
my dear absent friends.  Do you wonder I am
<pb n="192"/>
so happy?  When I think of it all, I wonder
how I can crowd all my joy into one short
life.  I don't want you to think for one
moment that you are bothering me when I
write you.  It is a real pleasure to do so.
You're always so good to let me tell you
everything.  I am only afraid of trying your
patience too far.  Even in this long letter I
can't tell you all I want to; so I shall write
you again soon.  Jerrine will write too.  Just
now she has very sore fingers.  She has been
picking gooseberries, and they have been
pretty severe on her brown little paws.
</p><p>With much love to you, I am
</p><p>"Honest and truly" yours,
</p><p>ELINORE RUPERT STEWART.


<pb n="193"/>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="19" id="d24">
<head> "THE ADVENTURE OF THE CHRISTMAS TREE"
<hi rend="italic">January</hi> 6, 1913.</head>
<salute>
MY DEAR FRIEND,&mdash;
</salute>
<p>I have put off writing you and thanking
you for your thought for us until now so that
I could tell you of our very happy Christmas
and our deer hunt all at once.
</p><p>To begin with, Mr. Stewart and Junior
have gone to Boulder to spend the winter.
Clyde wanted his mother to have a chance
to enjoy our boy, so, as he had to go, he took
Junior with him.  Then those of my dear
neighbors nearest my heart decided to prevent
a lonely Christmas for me, so on December
21st came Mrs. Louderer, laden with an
immense plum pudding and a big <hi rend="italic">"wurst</hi>,"
and a little later came Mrs. O'Shaughnessy
on her frisky pony, Chief, her scarlet sweater
making a bright bit of color against our snow-<pb n="194"/>
wrapped horizon.  Her face and ways are
just as bright and cheery as can be.  When
she saw Mrs. Louderer's pudding and sausage
she said she had brought nothing because
she had come to get something to eat
herself, "and," she continued, "it is a private
opinion of mine that my neighbors are so
glad to see me that they are glad to feed me."
Now wouldn't that little speech have made
her welcome anywhere?
</p><p>Well, we were hilariously planning what
Mrs. O'Shaughnessy called a "widdy"
Christmas and getting supper, when a great
stamping-off of snow proclaimed a newcomer.
 It was Gavotte, and we were powerfully
glad to see him because the hired man
was going to a dance and we knew Gavotte
would contrive some unusual amusement.
He had heard that Clyde was going to have
a deer-drive, and didn't know that he had
gone, so he had come down to join the hunt
just for the fun, and was very much disappointed
to find there was going to be no hunt.
<pb n="195"/>
After supper, however, his good humor re-turned and he told us story after story of big
hunts he had had in Canada.  He worked up
his own enthusiasm as well as ours, and at
last proposed that we have a drive of our own
for a Christmas "joy."  He said he would
take a station and do the shooting if one of
us would do the driving.  So right now I
reckon I had better tell you how it is done.
</p><p>There are many little parks in the mountains
where the deer can feed, although now
most places are so deep in snow that they
can't walk in it.  For that reason they have
trails to water and to the different feeding-grounds, and they can't get through the snow
except along these paths.  You see how easy
it would be for a man hidden on the trail to
get one of the beautiful creatures if some one
coming from another direction startled them
so that they came along that particular path.
</p><p>So they made their plans.  Mrs. O'Shaughnessy
elected herself driver.  Two miles away
is a huge mountain called Phillipeco, and
<pb n="196"/>
deer were said to be plentiful up there.  At
one time there had been a sawmill on the
mountain, and there were a number of deserted
cabins in which we could make ourselves
comfortable.  So it was planned that
we go up the next morning, stay all night,
have the hunt the following morning, and
then come home with our game.
</p><p>Well, we were all astir early the next
morning and soon grain, bedding, and chuck-box were in the wagon.  Then Mrs. Louderer,
the <hi rend="italic">kinder</hi>, and myself piled in; Mrs.
O'Shaughnessy bestrode Chief, Gavotte
stalked on ahead to pick our way, and we
were off.
</p><p>It was a long, tedious climb, and I wished
over and over that I had stayed at home;
but it was altogether on Baby's account.  I
was so afraid that he would suffer, but he
kept warm as toast.  The day was beautiful,
and the views many times repaid us for
any hardship we had suffered.  It was three
o'clock before we reached the old mill camp.
<pb n="197"/>
Soon we had a roaring fire, and Gavotte
made the horses comfortable in one of the
cabins.  They were bedded in soft, dry sawdust,
and were quite as well off as if they had
been in their own stalls.  Then some rough
planks were laid on blocks, and we had our
first meal since breakfast.  We called it supper,
and we had potatoes roasted in the
embers, Mrs. Louderer's <hi rend="italic">wurst</hi>, which she
had been calmly carrying around on her arm
like a hoop and which was delicious with the
bread that Gavotte toasted on long sticks;
we had steaming coffee, and we were all
happy; even Baby clapped his hands and
crowed at the unusual sight of an open fire.
After supper Gavotte took a little stroll and
returned with a couple of grouse for our
breakfast.  After dark we sat around the fire
eating peanuts and listening to Gavotte and
Mrs. Louderer telling stories of their different
great forests.  But soon Gavotte took
his big sleeping-bag and retired to another
cabin, warning us that we must be up early.
<pb n="198"/>
Our improvised beds were the most comfortable
things; I love the flicker of an open fire,
the smell of the pines, the pure, sweet air,
and I went to sleep thinking how blest I was
to be able to enjoy the things I love most.
</p><p>It seemed only a short time until some one
knocked on our door and we were all wide
awake in a minute.  The fire had burned
down and only a soft, indistinct glow from
the embers lighted the room, while through a
hole in the roof I could see a star glimmering
frostily.  It was Gavotte at the door and he
called through a crack saying he had been
hearing queer noises for an hour and he was
going to investigate.  He had called us so
that we need not be alarmed should we hear
the noise and not find him.  We scrambled
into our clothes quickly and ran outdoors to
listen.
</p><p>I can never describe to you the weird
beauty of a moonlight night among the pines
when the snow is sparkling and gleaming,
the deep silence unbroken even by the snapping
<pb n="199"/>
of a twig.  We stood shivering and
straining our ears and were about to go back
to bed when we heard faintly a long-drawn
wail as if all the suffering and sorrow on
earth were bound up in that one sound.  We
couldn't tell which way it came from; it
seemed to vibrate through the air and chill
our hearts.  I had heard that panthers cried
that way, but Gavotte said it was not a
panther.  He said the engine and saws had
been moved from where we were to another
spring across the canon a mile away, where
timber for sawing was more plentiful, but he
supposed every one had left the mill when
the water froze so they couldn't saw.  He
added that some one must have remained
and was, perhaps, in need of help, and if we
were not afraid he would leave us and go see
what was wrong.
</p><p>We went in, made up the fire, and sat in
silence, wondering what we should see or
hear next.  Once or twice that agonized cry
came shivering through the cold moonlight.
<pb n="200"/>
After an age, we heard Gavotte crunching
through the snow, whistling cheerily to reassure
us.  He had crossed the canon to the
new mill camp, where he had found two
women, loggers' wives, and some children.
One of the women, he said, was "so ver'
seek," 't was she who was wailing so, and it
was the kind of "seek" where we could be
of every help and comfort.
</p><p>Mrs. Louderer stayed and took care of the
children while Mrs. O'Shaughnessy and I
followed after Gavotte, panting and stumbling,
through the snow.  Gavotte said he
suspected they were short of "needfuls," so
he had filled his pockets with coffee and
sugar, took in a bottle some of the milk I
brought for Baby, and his own flask of whiskey,
without which he never travels.
</p><p>At last, after what seemed to me hours of
scrambling through the snow, through deepest
gloom where pines were thickest, and out
again into patches of white moonlight, we
reached the ugly clearing where the new
<pb n="201"/>
camp stood.  Gavotte escorted us to the door
and then returned to our camp.  Entering,
we saw the poor, little soon-to-be mother
huddled on her poor bed, while an older
woman stood near warning her that the oil
would soon be all gone and they would be in
darkness.  She told us that the sick one had
been in pain all the day before and much
of the night, and that she herself was worn
completely out.  So Mrs. O'Shaughnessy sent
her to bed and we took charge.
</p><p>Secretly, I felt it all to be a big nuisance
to be dragged out from my warm, comfortable
bed to traipse through the snow at that
time of the night.  But the moment poor little
Molly spoke I was glad I was living, because
she was a poor little Southern girl whose husband
is a Mormon.  He had been sent on a
mission to Alabama, and the poor girl had
fallen in love with his handsome face and
knew nothing of Mormonism, so she had run
away with him.  She thought it would be so
grand to live in the glorious West with so
<pb n="202"/>
splendid a man as she believed her husband
to be.  But now she believed she was going
to die and she was glad of it because she
could not return to her "folks," and she said
she knew her husband was dead because he
and the other woman's husband, both of
whom had intended to stay there all winter
and cut logs, had gone two weeks before to
get their summer's wages and buy supplies.
Neither man had come back and there was
not a horse or any other way to get out of the
mountains to hunt them, so they believed
the men to be frozen somewhere on the road.
Rather a dismal prospect, wasn't it?  Molly
was just longing for some little familiar
thing, so I was glad I have not yet gotten rid
of my Southern way of talking.  No Westerner
can ever understand a Southerner's
need of sympathy, and, however kind their
hearts, they are unable to give it.  Only a
Southerner can understand how dear are our
peculiar words and phrases, and poor little
Molly took new courage when she found I
<pb n="203"/>
knew what she meant when she said she was
just "honin'" after a friendly voice.
</p><p>Well, soon we had the water hot and had
filled some bottles and placed them around
our patient, and after a couple of hours the
tiny little stranger came into the world.  It
had been necessary to have a great fire in
order to have light, so as soon as we got
Baby dressed I opened the door a little to
cool the room and Molly saw the morning
star twinkling merrily.  "Oh," she said,
"that is what I will call my little girlie,&mdash;
Star, dear little Star."
</p><p>It is strange, isn't it? how our spirits will
revive after some great ordeal.  Molly had
been sure she was going to die and saw
nothing to live for; now that she had had a
cup of hot milk and held her red little baby
close, she was just as happy and hopeful as
if she had never left her best friends and
home to follow the uncertain fortunes of
young Will Crosby.  So she and I talked of
ash-hoppers, smoke-houses, cotton-patches,
<pb n="204"/>
goobers, poke-greens, and shoats, until she
fell asleep.
</p><p>Soon day was abroad, and so we went out-doors for a fresh breath.  The other woman
came out just then to ask after Molly.  She
invited us into her cabin, and, oh, the little
Mormons were everywhere; poor, half-clad
little things!  Some sour-dough biscuit and
a can of condensed milk was everything they
had to eat.  The mother explained to us that
their "men" had gone to get things for them,
but had not come back, so she guessed they
had got drunk and were likely in jail.  She
told it in a very unconcerned manner.  Poor
thing!  Years of such experience had taught
her that blessed are they who expect nothing,
for they shall not be disappointed.  She said
that if Molly had not been sick she would
have walked down out of the mountains and
got help.
</p><p>Just then two shots rang out in quick succession,
and soon Gavotte came staggering
along with a deer across his shoulders.  That
<pb n="205"/>
he left for the family.  From our camp he had
brought some bacon and butter for Molly,
and, poor though it may seem, it was a treat
for her.  Leaving the woman to dress the
venison with her oldest boy's aid, we put out
across the canon for our own breakfast.  Beside
our much-beaten trail hung the second
venison, and when we reached our camp and
had our own delicious breakfast of grouse,
bread, butter, and coffee, Gavotte took
Chub and went for our venison.  In a short
time we were rolling homeward.  Of course it
didn't take us nearly so long to get home
because it was downhill and the road was
clearly marked, so in a couple of hours we
were home.
</p><p>Gavotte knew the two loggers were in
Green River and were then at work storing
ice for the railroad, but he had not known
that their wives were left as they were.  The
men actually had got drunk, lost their
money, and were then trying to replace it.
After we debated a bit we decided we could
<pb n="206"/>
not enjoy Christmas with those people in
want up there in the cold.  Then we got busy.
It is sixty miles to town, although our nearest
point to the railroad is but forty, so you
see it was impossible to get to town to get
anything.  You should have seen us!  Every
old garment that had ever been left by men
who have worked here was hauled out, and
Mrs. O'Shaughnessy's deft fingers soon had
a pile of garments cut.  We kept the machine
humming until far into the night, as long as
we could keep our eyes open.
</p><p>All next day we sewed as hard as we could,
and Gavotte cooked as hard as he could.  We
had intended to have a tree for Jerrine, so we
had a box of candles and a box of Christmas
snow.  Gavotte asked for all the bright paper
we could find.  We had lots of it, and I think
you would be surprised at the possibilities
of a little waste paper.  He made gorgeous
birds, butterflies, and flowers out of paper
that once wrapped parcels.  Then he asked
us for some silk thread, but I had none, so he
<pb n="207"/>
told us to comb our hair and give him the
combings.  We did, and with a drop of mucilage
he would fasten a hair to a bird's back
and then hold it up by the hair.  At a few
feet's distance it looked exactly as though
the bird was flying.  I was glad I had a big
stone jar full of <hi rend="italic">fondant</hi>, because we had a
lot of fun shaping and coloring candies.  We
offered a prize for the best representation of
a "nigger," and we had two dozen chocolate-covered things that might have been anything
from a monkey to a mouse.  Mrs.
Louderer cut up her big plum pudding and
put it into a dozen small bags.  These
Gavotte carefully covered with green paper.
Then we tore up the holly wreath that Aunt
Mary sent me, and put a sprig in the top of
each green bag of pudding.  I never had so
much fun in my life as I had preparing for
that Christmas.
</p><p>At ten o'clock, the morning of the 24th,
we were again on our way up the mountain-side.  We took shovels so we could clear a
<pb n="208"/>
road if need be.  We had dinner at the old
camp, and then Gavotte hunted us a way
out to the new, and we smuggled our things
into Molly's cabin so the children should
have a real surprise.  Poor, hopeless little
things!  Theirs was, indeed, a dull outlook.
</p><p>Gavotte busied himself in preparing one
of the empty cabins for us and in making
the horses comfortable.  He cut some pine
boughs to do that with, and so they paid no
attention when he cut a small tree.  In the
mean time we had cleared everything from
Molly's cabin but her bed; we wanted her to
see the fun.  The children were sent to the
spring to water the horses and they were all
allowed to ride, so that took them out of the
way while Gavotte nailed the tree into a box
he had filled with dirt to hold it steady.
</p><p>There were four women of us, and Gavotte,
so it was only the work of a few moments
to get the tree ready, and it was the most
beautiful one I ever saw.  Your largest bell,
dear Mrs. Coney, dangled from the topmost
<pb n="209"/>
branch.  Gavotte had attached a long, stout
wire to your Santa Claus, so he was able to
make him dance frantically without seeming
to do so.  The hairs that held the birds and
butterflies could not be seen, and the effect
was beautiful.  We had a bucket of apples
rubbed bright, and these we fastened to the
tree just as they grew on their own branches.
The puddings looked pretty, too, and we had
done up the parcels that held the clothes as
attractively as we could.  We saved the candy
and the peanuts to put in their little stockings.
</p><p>As soon as it was dark we lighted the
candles and then their mother called the
children.  Oh, if you could have seen them!
It was the very first Christmas tree they had
ever seen and they didn't know what to do.
The very first present Gavotte handed out
was a pair of trousers for eight-years-old
Brig, but he just stood and stared at the tree
until his brother next in size, with an eye to
the main chance, got behind him and pushed
him forward, all the time exclaiming, "Go
<pb n="210"/>
on, can't you!  They ain't doin' nothin' to
you, they's just doin' somethin' for you."
Still Brig would not put out his hand.  He
just shook his tousled sandy head and said he
wanted a bird.  So the fun kept up for an hour.
Santa had for Molly a package of oatmeal, a
pound of butter, a Mason jar of cream, and a
dozen eggs, so that she could have suitable
food to eat until something could be done.
</p><p>After the presents had all been distributed
we put the phonograph on a box and had
a dandy concert.  We played "There were
Shepherds," "Ave Maria," and "Sweet
Christmas Bells."  Only we older people
cared for those, so then we had "Arrah
Wanna," "Silver Bells," "Rainbow," "Red
Wing," and such songs.  How delighted they
were!  Our concert lasted two hours, and by
that time the little fellows were so sleepy that
the excitement no longer affected them and
they were put to bed, but they hung up their
stockings first, and even Molly hung hers up
too.  We filled them with peanuts and candy,
<pb n="211"/>
putting the lion's share of "niggers" into
Molly's stocking.
</p><p>Next morning the happiness broke out in
new spots.  The children were all clean and
warm, though I am afraid I can't brag on the
fit of all the clothes.  But the pride of the
wearers did away with the necessity of a fit.
The mother was radiantly thankful for a
warm petticoat; that it was made of a blanket
too small for a bed didn't bother her, and
the stripes were around the bottom anyway.
Molly openly rejoiced in her new gown, and
that it was made of ugly gray outing flannel
she didn't know or care.  Baby Star Crosby
looked perfectly sweet in her little new
clothes, and her little gown had blue sleeves
and they thought a white skirt only added to
its beauty.  And so it was about everything.
We all got so much out of so little.  I will
never again allow even the smallest thing
to go to waste.  We were every one just as
happy as we could be, almost as delighted as
Molly was over her "niggers," and there was
<pb n="212"/>
very little given that had not been thrown
away or was not just odds and ends.
</p><p>There was never anything more true than
that it is more blessed to give than to receive.
We certainly had a delicious dinner too, and
we let Molly have all she wanted that we
dared allow her to eat.  The roast venison
was so good that we were tempted to let her
taste it, but we thought better of that.  As
soon as dinner was over we packed our belongings
and betook ourselves homeward.
</p><p>It was just dusk when we reached home.
Away off on a bare hill a wolf barked.  A big
owl hooted lonesomely among the pines, and
soon a pack of yelping coyotes went scampering
across the frozen waste.
</p><p>It was not the Christmas I had in mind
when I sent the card, but it was a <hi rend="italic">dandy</hi> one,
just the same.
</p><p>With best wishes for you for a happy,
<hi rend="italic">happy</hi> New Year,
</p><p>Sincerely your friend,
</p><p>ELINORE RUPERT STEWART.


<pb n="213"/>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="20" id="d25">
<head>LTHE JOYS OF HOMESTEADING" <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 23, 1913.</head>
<salute>
DEAR MRS. CONEY,&mdash;
</salute>
<p>I am afraid all my friends think I am very
forgetful and that you think I am ungrateful
as well, but I am going to plead not guilty.
Right after Christmas Mr. Stewart came
down with <hi rend="italic">la grippe</hi> and was so miserable
that it kept me busy trying to relieve him.
Out here where we can get no physician we
have to dope ourselves, so that I had to
be housekeeper, nurse, doctor, and general
overseer.  That explains my long silence.
</p><p>And now I want to thank you for your
kind thought in prolonging our Christmas.
The magazines were much appreciated.  They
relieved some weary night-watches, and the
box did Jerrine more good than the medicine
I was having to give her for <hi rend="italic">la grippe</hi>  She
<pb n="214"/>
was content to stay in bed and enjoy the
contents of her box.
</p><p>When I read of the hard times among the
Denver poor, I feel like urging them every
one to get out and file on land.  I am very
enthusiastic about women homesteading.  It
really requires less strength and labor to
raise plenty to satisfy a large family than it
does to go out to wash, with the added satisfaction
of knowing that their job will not be
lost to them if they care to keep it.  Even if
improving the place does go slowly, it is that
much done to stay done.  Whatever is raised
is the homesteader's own, and there is no
house-rent to pay.  This year Jerrine cut and
dropped enough potatoes to raise a ton of
fine potatoes.  She wanted to try, so we let
her, and you will remember that she is but
six years old.  We had a man to break the
ground and cover the potatoes for her and
the man irrigated them once.  That was all
that was done until digging time, when they
were ploughed out and Jerrine picked them
<pb n="215"/>
up.  Any woman strong enough to go out by
the day could have done every bit of the
work and put in two or three times that
much, and it would have been so much more
pleasant than to work so hard in the city
and then be on starvation rations in the
winter.
</p><p>To me, homesteading is the solution of all
poverty's problems, but I realize that temperament
has much to do with success in
any undertaking, and persons afraid of coyotes
and work and loneliness had better
let ranching alone.  At the same time, any
woman who can stand her own company,
can see the beauty of the sunset, loves growing
things, and is willing to put in as much
time at careful labor as she does over the
washtub, will certainly succeed; will have
independence, plenty to eat all the time, and
a home of her own in the end.
</p><p>Experimenting need cost the homesteader
no more than the work, because by applying
to the Department of Agriculture at Washington
<pb n="216"/>
he can get enough of any seed and as
many kinds as he wants to make a thorough
trial, and it doesn't even cost postage.  Also
one can always get bulletins from there and
from the Experiment Station of one's own
State concerning any problem or as many
problems as may come up.  I would not, for
anything, allow Mr. Stewart to do anything
toward improving my place, for I want the
fun and the experience myself.  And I want to
be able to speak from experience when I tell
others what they can do.  Theories are very
beautiful, but facts are what must be had,
and what I intend to give some time.
</p><p>Here I am boring you to death with things
that cannot interest you!  You'd think I
wanted you to homestead, wouldn't you?
But I am only thinking of the troops of tired,
worried women, sometimes even cold and
hungry, scared to death of losing their places
to work, who could have plenty to eat, who
could have good fires by gathering the wood,
and comfortable homes of their own, if they
<pb n="217"/>
but had the courage and determination to
get them.
</p><p>I must stop right now before you get so
tired you will not answer.  With much love
to you from Jerrine and myself, I am
</p><p>Yours affectionately,
</p><p>ELINORE RUPERT STEWART.


<pb n="218"/>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="21" id="d26">
<head> "A LETTER OF JERRINE'S"
<hi rend="italic">February</hi> 26, 1913.</head>
<salute>
DEAR MRS. CONEY,&mdash;
</salute>
<p>I think you will excuse my mamma for not
writing to thank you for black Beauty when
I tell you why.  I wanted to thank you myself,
and I wanted to hear it read first so I
could very trully thank.  Mama always said
horses do not talk, but now she knows they
do since she read the Dear little book.  I have
known it along time.  My own pony told me
the story is very true.  Many times I have
see men treat horses very badly, but our
Clyde dont, and wont let a workman stay if
He hurts stock.  I am very glad.
</p><p>Mr Edding came past one day with a load
of hay.  he had too much load to pull up hill
and there was much ice and snow but he
think he can make them go up so he fighted
<pb n="219"/>
and sweared but they could not get up.
Mama tried to lend him some horse to help
but he was angry and was termined to make
his own pull it but at last he had to take off
some hay I wish he may read my Black
Beauty.
</p><p>Our Clyde is still away.  We were going to
visit Stella.  Mama was driving, the horses
raned away.  We goed very fast as the wind.
I almost fall out Mama hanged on to the
lines. if she let go we may all be kill.  At last
she raned them into a fence.  they stop and a
man ran to help so we are well but mama
hands and arms are still so sore she cant
write you yet.  My brother Calvin is very
sweet.  God had to give him to us because he
squealed so much he sturbed the angels.  We
are not angels so he Dont sturb us.  I thank
you for my good little book. and I love you
for it too.
</p><p>very speakfully,
</p><p>JERRINE RUPERT.


<pb n="220"/>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="22" id="d27">
<head>"THE EFFICIENT MRS. O'SHAUGHNESSY
 <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 5, 1913.</head>
<salute>
DEAR MRS. CONEY,&mdash;
</salute>
<p>Your letter of April 25 certainly was a surprise,
but a very welcome one.  We are so
rushed with spring work that we don't even
go to the office for the mail, and I owe you
letters and thanks.  I keep promising myself
the pleasure of writing you and keep putting
it off until I can have more leisure, but that
time never gets here.  I am so glad when I
can bring a little of this big, clean, beautiful
outdoors into your apartment for you to enjoy,
and I can think of nothing that would
give me more happiness than to bring the
West and its people to others who could not
otherwise enjoy them.  If I could only take
them from whatever is worrying them and
give them this bracing mountain air, glimpses
<pb n="221"/>
of the scenery, a smell of the pines and the
sage,&mdash;if I could only make them feel the free,
ready sympathy and hospitality of these frontier
people, I am sure their worries would diminish
and my happiness would be complete.
</p><p>Little Star Crosby is growing to be the
sweetest little kid.  Her mother tells me that
she is going "back yan" when she gets a
"little mo' richer."  I am afraid you give me
too much credit for being of help to poor little
Molly.  It wasn't that I am so helpful, but
that "fools rush in where angels fear to
tread."  It was Mrs. O'Shaughnessy who was
the real help.  She is a woman of great courage
and decision and of splendid sense and
judgment.  A few days ago a man she had
working for her got his finger-nail mashed off
and neglected to care for it.  Mrs. O'Shaughnessy
examined it and found that gangrene
had set in.  She didn't tell him, but made
various preparations and then told him she
had heard that if there was danger of bloodpoisoning
it would show if the finger was
<pb n="222"/>
placed on wood and the patient looked
toward the sun.  She said the person who
looked at the finger could then see if there
was any poison.  So the man placed his finger
on the chopping-block and before he could
bat his eye she had chopped off the black,
swollen finger.  It was so sudden and unexpected
that there seemed to be no pain.  Then
Mrs. O'Shaughnessy showed him the green
streak already starting up his arm.  The man
seemed dazed and she was afraid of shock, so
she gave him a dose of morphine and whiskey.
Then with a quick stroke of a razor she laid
open the green streak and immersed the
whole arm in a strong solution of bichloride
of mercury for twenty minutes.  She then
dressed the wound with absorbent cotton
saturated with olive oil and carbolic acid,
bundled her patient into a buggy, and drove
forty-five miles that night to get him to a doctor.
 The doctor told us that only her quick
action and knowledge of what to do saved
the man's life.
<pb n="223"/>
</p><p>I was surprised that you have had a letter
from Jerrine.  I knew she was writing to you
that day, but I was feeling very stiff and sore
from the runaway and had lain down.  She
kept asking me how to spell words until I
told her I was too tired and wanted to sleep.
While I was asleep the man came for the
mail, so she sent her letter.  I have your address
on the back of the writing-pad, so she
knew she had it right, but I suspect that was
all she had right.  She has written you many
letters but I have never allowed her to send
them because she misspells, but that time she
stole a march on me.  The books you sent
her, "Black Beauty" and "Alice in Wonderland,"
have given her more pleasure than
anything she has ever had.  She just loves
them and is saving them, she says, for her
own little girls.  She is very confident that
the stork will one day visit her and leave her
a "very many" little girls.  They are to be of
assorted sizes.  She says she can't see why I
order all my babies little and red and squally,
<pb n="224"/>
&mdash;says she thinks God had just as soon let
me have larger ones, especially as I get so
many from him.
</p><p>One day before long I will get busy and
write you of a visit I shall make to a Mormon
bishop's household.  Polygamy is still practiced.
</p><p>Very truly your friend,
</p><p>ELINORE RUPERT STEWART.


<pb n="225"/>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="23" id="d28">
<head> "HOW IT HAPPENED" <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 12, 1913.</head>
<salute>
DEAR MRS. CONEY,&mdash;
</salute>
<p>Your letter of the 8th to hand, and in order
to catch you before you leave I'll answer at
once and not wait for time.  I always think I
shall do better with more time, but with three
"bairns," garden, chickens, cows, and house-work I don't seem to find much time for
anything.  Now for the first question.  My
maiden name was Pruitt, so when I am putting
on airs I sign Elinore Pruitt Stewart.  I
don't think I have ever written anything that
Clyde would object to, so he can still stay on
the pedestal Scotch custom puts him upon and
remain "the Stewart."  Indeed, I don't think
you are too inquisitive, and I am glad to
tell you how I happened to meet the "gude
mon."
<pb n="226"/>
</p><p>It all happened because I had a stitch in
my side.  When I was housekeeper at the
Nursery, I also had to attend to the furnace,
and, strange but true, the furnace was built
across the large basement from where the
coal was thrown in, so I had to tote the coal
over, and my <hi rend="italic">modus operandi</hi> was to fill a tub
with coal and then drag it across to the hungry
furnace.  Well, one day I felt the catch
and got no better fast.  After Dr. F&mdash;
punched and prodded, she said, "Why, you
have the grippe."  Rev. Father Corrigan had
been preparing me to take the Civil-Service
examination, and that afternoon a lesson
was due, so I went over to let him see how
little I knew.  I was in pain and was so blue
that I could hardly speak without weeping, so
I told the Reverend Father how tired I was of
the rattle and bang, of the glare and the soot,
the smells and the hurry.  I told him what I
longed for was the sweet, free open, and that
I would like to homestead.  That was Saturday
evening.  He advised me to go straight
<pb n="227"/>
uptown and put an "ad" in the paper, so as
to get it into the Sunday paper.  I did so, and
because I wanted as much rest and quiet as
possible I took Jerrine and went uptown and
got a nice quiet room.
</p><p>On the following Wednesday I received a
letter from Clyde, who was in Boulder visiting
his mother.  He was leaving for Wyoming
the following Saturday and wanted an interview,
if his proposition suited me.  I was so
glad of his offer, but at the same time I could
n't know what kind of person he was; so, to
lessen any risk, I asked him to come to the
Sunshine Mission, where Miss Ryan was
going to help me "size him up."  He didn't
know that part of it, of course, but he stood
inspection admirably.  I was under the impression
he had a son, but he hadn't, and
he and his mother were the very last of their
race.  I am as proud and happy to-day as I
was the day I became his wife.  I wish you
knew him, but I suspect I had better not
brag too much, lest you think me not quite
<pb n="228"/>
sincere.  He expected to visit you while he
was in Boulder.  He went to the Stock Show,
but was with a party, so he planned to go
again.  But before he could, the man he left
here, and whom I dismissed for drunkenness,
went to Boulder and told him I was alone, so
the foolish thing hurried home to keep me
from too hard work.  So that is why he was
disappointed.
</p><p>Junior can talk quite well, and even Calvin
jabbers.  The children are all well, and Jerrine
writes a little every day to you.  I have
been preparing a set of indoor outings for
invalids.  Your telling me your invalid friends
enjoyed the letters suggested the idea.  I
thought to write of little outings I take might
amuse them, but wanted to write just as I
took the little trips, while the impressions
were fresh; that is why I have not sent them
before now.  Is it too late?  Shall I send them
to you?  Now this is really not a letter; it is
just a reply.  I must say good-night; it is
twelve o'clock, and I am so sleepy.
<pb n="229"/>
</p><p>I do hope you will have a very happy summer,
and that you will share your happiness
with me in occasional letters.
</p><p>With much love,
</p><p>ELINORE STEWART.

</p><p>In writing I forgot to say that the Reverend
Father thought it a good plan to get a
position as housekeeper for some rancher
who would advise me about land and water
rights.  By keeping house, he pointed out, I
could have a home and a living and at the
same time see what kind of a homestead I
could get.


<pb n="230"/>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="24" id="d29">
<head>"A LITTLE ROMANCE" <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 8, 1913.</head>
<salute>
MY DEAR FRIEND,&mdash;
</salute>
<p>I have had such a happy little peep into
another's romance that I think I should be
cheating you if I didn't tell you.  Help in
this country is extremely hard to get; so when
I received a letter from one Aurelia Timmons,
saying she wanted a job,&mdash;three dollars
a week and <hi rend="italic">not</hi> to be called "Relie,"&mdash;
my joy could hardly be described.  I could
hardly wait until morning to start for Bridger
Bench, where Aurelia held forth.  I was up
before the lark next morning.  It is more
miles to the Bridger Bench country than the
"gude mon" wants his horses driven in a
day; so permission was only given after I
promised to curb my impatience and stay
overnight with Mrs. Louderer.  Under ordinary
<pb n="231"/>
circumstances that would have been a
pleasure, but I knew at least a dozen women
who would any of them seize on to Aurelia
and wrest her from me, so it was only after it
seemed I would not get to go at all that I
promised.
</p><p>At length the wagon was greased, some
oats put in, a substantial lunch and the kiddies
loaded in, and I started on my way.
Perhaps it was the prospect of getting help
that gilded everything with a new beauty.
The great mountains were so majestic, and
the day so young that I knew the night wind
was still murmuring among the pines far up
on the mountain-sides.  The larks were trying
to outdo each other and the robins were so
saucy that I could almost have flicked them
with the willow I was using as a whip.  The
rabbit-bush made golden patches everywhere,
while purple asters and great pink
thistles lent their charm.  Going in that direction,
our way lay between a mountain stream
and the foothills.  There are many ranches
<pb n="232"/>
along the stream, and as we were out so early,
we could see the blue smoke curling from
each house we passed.  We knew that venison
steak, hot biscuit, and odorous coffee would
soon grace their tables.  We had not had the
venison, for the "gude mon" holds to the
letter of the law which protects deer here,
but we begrudged no one anything; we were
having exactly what we wanted.  We jogged
along happily, if slowly, for I must explain
to you that Chub is quite the laziest horse
in the State, and Bill, his partner, is so old he
stands like a bulldog.  He is splay-footed and
sway-backed, but he is a beloved member of
our family, so I vented my spite on Chub, and
the willow descended periodically across his
black back, I guess as much from force of
habit as anything else.  But his hide is thick
and his memory short, so we broke no record
that day.
</p><p>We drove on through the fresh beauty of
the morning, and when the sun was straight
overhead we came to the last good water we
<pb n="233"/>
could expect before we reached Mrs. Louderer's;
so we stopped for lunch.  In Wyoming
quantity has a great deal more to do with
satisfaction than does quality; after half a
day's drive you won't care so much what it is
you're going to eat as you will that there is
enough of it.  That is a lesson I learned long
ago; so our picnic was real.  There were no
ants in the pie, but that is accounted for by
there being no pie.  Our road had crossed the
creek, and we were resting in the shade of a
quaking-asp grove, high up on the sides of
the Bad Land hills.  For miles far below lay
the valley through which we had come.
</p><p>Farther on, the mountains with their dense
forests were all wrapped in the blue haze of
the melancholy days.  Soon we quitted our enchanted
grove whose quivering, golden leaves
kept whispering secrets to us.
</p><p>About three o'clock we came down out of
the hills on to the bench on which the Louderer
ranch is situated.  Perhaps I should explain
that this country is a series of huge terraces,
<pb n="234"/>
each terrace called a bench.  I had just
turned into the lane that leads to the house
when a horseman came cantering toward me.
"Hello!" he saluted, as he drew up beside
the wagon.  "Goin' up to the house?  Better
not.  Mrs. Louderer is not at home, and
there's no one there but Greasy Pete.  He's
on a tear; been drunk two days, I'm tellin'
you.  He's <hi rend="italic">full</hi> of mischief.  'T ain't safe
around old Greasy.  I advise you to go some-'eres else."  "Well," I asked, "where <hi rend="italic">can</hi> I
go?"  "Danged if I know," he replied, "'lessen
it's to Kate Higbee's.  She lives about
six or seven miles west.  She ain't been here
long, but I guess you can't miss her place.
Just jog along due west till you get to Red
Gulch ravine, then turn north for a couple
of miles.  You'll see her cabin up against a
cedar ridge.  Well, so 'long!"  He dug his
spurs into his cayuse's side and rode on.
</p><p>Tears of vexation so blinded me that I
could scarcely see to turn the team, but ominous
sounds and wild yells kept coming from
<pb n="235"/>
the house, so I made what haste I could to
get away from such an unpleasant neighborhood.
 Soon my spirits began to rise.  Kate
Higbee, I reflected, was likely to prove to be
an interesting person.  All Westerners are
likable, with the possible exception of Greasy
Pete.  I rather looked forward to my visit.
But my guide had failed to mention the
buttes; so, although I jogged as west as I
knew how, I found I had to wind around a
butte about ever so often.  I crossed a ravine
with equal frequency, and all looked alike.
It is not surprising that soon I could not
guess where I was.  We could turn back and
retrace our tracks, but actual danger lay
there; so it seemed wiser to push on, as there
was, perhaps, no greater danger than discomfort
ahead.  The sun hung like a big red ball
ready to drop into the hazy distance when
we came clear of the buttes and down on to
a broad plateau, on which grass grew plentifully.
 That encouraged me because the
horses need not suffer, and if I could make
<pb n="236"/>
the scanty remnant of our lunch do for the
children's supper and breakfast, we could
camp in comfort, for we had blankets.  But
we must find water.  I stood up in the wagon
and, shading my eyes against the sun's level
light, was looking out in the most promising
directions when I noticed that the plateau's
farther side was bounded by a cedar ridge,
and, better yet, a smoke was slowly rising,
column-like, against the dun prospect.  That,
I reasoned, must be my destination.  Even
the horses livened their paces, and in a little
while we were there.
</p><p>But no house greeted our eyes,&mdash;just a big
camp-fire.  A lean old man sat on a log-end
and surveyed us indifferently.  On the ground
lay a large canvas-covered pack, apparently
unopened.  An old saddle lay up against a
cedar trunk.  Two old horses grazed near.
I was powerfully disappointed.  You know
misery loves company; so I ventured to say,
"Good-evening."  He didn't stir, but he
grunted, "Hello."  I knew then that he was
<pb n="237"/>
not a fossil, and hope began to stir in my
heart.  Soon he asked, "Are you goin' somewheres
or jist travelin'?"  I told him I had
started somewhere, but reckoned I must be
traveling, as I had not gotten there.  Then he
said, "My name is Hiram K. Hull.  Whose
woman are you?"  I confessed to belonging
to the house of Stewart.  "Which Stewart?"
he persisted,&mdash;"C. R., S. W., or H. C.?"
Again I owned up truthfully.  "Well," he
continued, "what does he mean by letting
you gad about in such onconsequential
style?"
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Sometimes</hi> a woman gets too angry to talk.
Don't you believe that?  No?  Well, they do,
I assure you, for I was then.  He seemed
grown to the log.  As he had made no move
to help me, without answering him I clambered
out of the wagon and began to take
the horses loose.  "Ho!" he said; "are you
goin' to camp here?"  "Yes, I am," I
snapped.  "Have you any objections?"
"Oh, no, none that won't keep," he assured
<pb n="238"/>
me.  It has always been a theory of mine that
when we become sorry for ourselves we make
our misfortunes harder to bear, because we
lose courage and can't think without bias;
so I cast about me for something to be glad
about, and the comfort that at least we were
safer with a simpleton than near a drunken
Mexican came to me; so I began to view the
situation with a little more tolerance.
</p><p>After attending to the horses I began to
make the children comfortable.  My unwilling
host sat silently on his log, drawing long
and hard at his stubby old pipe.  How very
little there was left of our lunch!  Just for
meanness I asked him to share with us, and,
if you'll believe me, he did.  He gravely ate
bread-rims and scraps of meat until there was
not one bit left for even the baby's breakfast.
Then he drew the back of his hand across his
mouth and remarked, "I should think when
you go off on a ja'nt like this you'd have a
well-filled mess-box."  Again speech failed
me.
<pb n="239"/>
</p><p>Among some dwarf willows not far away
a spring bubbled.  I took the kiddies there to
prepare them for rest.  When I returned to
the fire, what a transformation!  The pack
was unrolled and blankets were spread, the
fire had been drawn aside, disclosing a beanhole,
out of which Hiram K. was lifting an
oven.  He took off the lid.  Two of the plumpest,
brownest ducks that ever tempted any
one were fairly swimming in gravy.  Two
loaves of what he called punk, with a box of
crackers, lay on a newspaper.  He mimicked
me exactly when he asked me to take supper
with him, and I tried hard to imitate him in
promptitude when I accepted.  The babies
had some of the crackers wet with hot water
and a little of the gravy.  We soon had the
rest looking scarce.  The big white stars were
beginning to twinkle before we were through,
but the camp-fire was bright, and we all felt
better-natured.  Men are not alone in having
a way to their heart through their stomach.
</p><p>I made our bed beneath the wagon, and
<pb n="240"/>
Hiram K. fixed his canvas around, so we
should be sheltered.  I felt so much better
and thought so much better of him that I
could laugh and chat gayly.  "Now, tell me,"
he asked, as he fastened the canvas to a wheel,
"didn't you think I was an old devil at
first?"  "Yes, I did," I answered.  "Well,"
he said, "I am; so you guessed right."  After
I put the children to bed, we sat by the fire
and talked awhile.  I told him how I happened
to be gadding about in "such onconsequential"
style, and he told me stories of
when the country was new and fit to live in.
"Why," he said, in a burst of enthusiasm,
"time was once when you went to bed you
were not sure whether you'd get up alive and
with your scalp on or not, the Injins were
that thick.  And then there was white men a
durned sight worse; they were likely to plug
you full of lead just to see you kick.  But
now," he continued mournfully, "a bear or an
antelope, maybe an elk, is about all the excitement
we can expect.  Them good old days
<pb n="241"/>
are gone."  I am mighty glad of it; a drunken
Pete is bad enough for me.
</p><p>I was tired, so soon I went to bed.  I could
hear him as he cut cedar boughs for his own
fireside bed, and as he rattled around among
his pots and pans.  Did you ever eat pork and
beans heated in a frying-pan on a camp-fire
for breakfast?  Then if you have not, there is
one delight left you.  But you must be away
out in Wyoming, with the morning sun just
gilding the distant peaks, and your pork and
beans must be out of a can, heated in a disreputable
old frying-pan, served with coffee
<hi rend="italic">boiled</hi> in a battered old pail and drunk from a
tomato-can.  You'll <hi rend="italic">never</hi> want iced melons,
powdered sugar, and fruit, or sixty-nine varieties
of breakfast food, if once you sit Trilbywise
on Wyoming sand and eat the kind of
breakfast we had that day.
</p><p>After breakfast Hiram K. Hull hitched our
horses to the wagon, got his own horses
ready, and then said, "'T ain't more'n half a
mile straight out between them two hills to
<pb n="242"/>
the stage-road, but I guess I had better go
and show you exactly, or you will be millin'
around here all day, tryin' to find it."  In a
very few minutes we were on the road, and
our odd host turned to go.  "S'long!" he
called.  "Tell Stewart you seen old Hikum.
Him and me's shared tarps many's the
nights.  We used to be punchers together,
&mdash;old Clyde and me.  Tell him old Hikum
ain't forgot him."  So saying, he rode away
into the golden morning, and we drove on-ward,
too.
</p><p>We stopped for lunch only a few minutes
that day, and we reached the Bridger community
about two that afternoon.  The much
sought Aurelia had accepted the position of
lifetime housekeeper for a sheep-herder who
had no house to keep, so I had to cast about
for whatever comfort I could.  The roadhouse
is presided over by a very able body of the
clan of Ferguson.  I had never met her, but
formalities count for very little in the West.
She was in her kitchen, having more trouble,
<pb n="243"/>
she said, than a hen whose ducklings were in
swimming.  I asked her if she could accomodate
the children and myself.  "Yes," she
said, "I can give you a bed and grub, but I
ain't got no time to ask you nothing.  I ain't
got no time to inquire who you are nor where
you come from.  There's one room left.  You
can have that, but you'll have to look out for
yourself and young'uns."  I felt equal to that;
so I went out to have the horses cared for and
to unload the kiddies.
</p><p>Leaning against the wagon was a man who
made annual rounds of all the homes in our
community each summer; his sole object was
to see what kind of flowers we succeeded
with.  Every woman in our neighborhood
knows Bishey Bennet, but I don't think
many would have recognized him that afternoon.
 I had never seen him dressed in anything
but blue denim overalls and overshirt
to match, but to-day he proudly displayed
what he said was his dove-colored suit.  The
style must have been one of years ago, for I
<pb n="244"/>
cannot remember seeing trousers quite so
skimpy.  He wore top-boots, but as a concession
to fashion he wore the boot-tops under
the trouser-legs, and as the trousers were
about as narrow as a sheath skirt, they kept
slipping up and gave the appearance of being
at least six inches too short.  Although
Bishey is tall and thin, his coat was two sizes
too small, his shirt was of soft tan material,
and he wore a blue tie.  But whatever may
have been amiss with his costume was easily
forgotten when one saw his radiant face.  He
grasped my hand and wrung it as if it was a
chicken's neck.
</p><p>"What in the world is the matter with
you?" I asked, as I rubbed my abused paw.
"Just you come here and I'll tell you," he
answered.  There was no one to hear but the
kiddies, but I went around the corner of the
house with him.  He put his hand up to his
mouth and whispered that "Miss Em'ly"
was coming, would be there on the afternoon
stage.  I had never heard of "Miss Em'ly,"
<pb n="245"/>
and said so.  "Well, just you go in and set on
the sofy and soon's I see your horses took
care of I'll come in and tell you."  I went into
my own room, and after I rustled some water
I made myself and the kiddies a little more
presentable.  Then we went into the sitting-room and sat on the "sofy."  Presently
Bishey sauntered in, trying to look unconcerned
and at ease, but he was so fidgety he
couldn't sit down.  But he told his story, and
a dear one it is.
</p><p>It seems that back in New York State he
and Miss Em'ly were "young uns" together.
When they were older they planned to marry,
but neither wanted to settle down to the
humdrumness that they had always known.
Both dreamed of the golden West; so Bishey
had gone to blaze the trail, and "Miss Em'ly"
was to follow.  First one duty and then another
had held her, until twenty-five years
had slipped by and they had not seen each
other, but now she was coming, that very
day.  They would be married that evening,
<pb n="246"/>
and I at once appointed myself matron of
honor and was plumb glad there was no other
candidate.
</p><p>I at once took the decorations in hand.
Bishey, Jerrine, and myself went out and
gathered armfuls of asters and goldenrod-like
rabbit-brush.  From the dump-pile we sorted
cans and pails that would hold water, and
we made the sitting-room a perfect bower of
purple and gold beauty.  I put on my last
clean shirt-waist and the children's last clean
dresses.  Then, as there seemed nothing more
to do, Bishey suggested that we walk up the
road and meet the stage; but the day had
been warm, and I remembered my own appearance
when I had come over that same
road the first time.  I knew that journey was
trying on any one's appearance at any time
of the year, and after twenty-five years to be
thrust into view covered with alkali dust and
with one's hat on awry would be too much
for feminine patience; so I pointed out to
Bishey that he'd better clear out and let Miss
<pb n="247"/>
Em'ly rest a bit before he showed up.  At
last he reluctantly agreed.
</p><p>I went out to the kitchen to find what
could be expected in the way of hot water for
Miss Em'ly when she should come.  I found I
could have all I wanted if I heated it myself.
Mrs. Ferguson could not be bothered about
it, because a water company had met there
to vote on new canals, the sheep-men were
holding a convention, there was a more than
usual run of transients besides the regular
boarders, and supper was ordered for the
whole push.  All the help she had was a girl
she just knew didn't have sense enough to
pound sand into a rat-hole.  Under those
circumstances I was mighty glad to help.  I
put water on to heat and then forgot Miss
Em'ly, I was enjoying helping so much, until
I heard a door slam and saw the stage drive
away toward the barn.
</p><p>I hastened to the room I knew was reserved
for Miss Em'ly.  I rapped on the
door, but it was only opened a tiny crack.  I
<pb n="248"/>
whispered through that I was a neighbor-friend of Mr. Bennet's, that I had lots of hot
water for her and had come to help her if
I might.  Then she opened the door, and I
entered.  I found a very travel-stained little
woman, down whose dust-covered cheeks
tears had left their sign.  Her prettiness was
the kind that wins at once and keeps you ever
after.  She was a strange mixture of stiff reticence
and childish trust.  She was in <hi rend="italic">such</hi> a
flutter, and she said she was ashamed to own
it, but she was so hungry she could hardly
wait.
</p><p>After helping her all I could, I ran out to
see about the wedding supper that was to be
served before the wedding.  I found that no
special supper had been prepared.  It seemed
to me a shame to thrust them down among
the water company, the convention, the
regulars, and the transients, and I mentally
invited myself to the wedding supper and
began to plan how we could have a little privacy.
 The carpenters were at work on a long
<pb n="249"/>
room off the kitchen that was to be used as
storeroom and pantry.  They had gone for
the day, and their saw-horses and benches
were still in the room.  It was only the work
of a moment to sweep the sawdust away.
There was only one window, but it was large
and in the west.  It took a little time to wash
that, but it paid to do it.  When a few asters
and sprays of rabbit-brush were placed in
a broken jar on the window-sill, there was a
picture worth seeing.  Some planks were laid
on the saw-horses, some papers over them,
and a clean white cloth over all.  I sorted the
dishes myself; the prettiest the house afforded
graced our table.  I rubbed the glassware
until it shone almost as bright as Bishey's
smile.
</p><p>Bishey had come when he could stay away
no longer; he and Miss Em'ly had had their
first little talk, so they came out to where I
was laying the table.  They were both beaming.
 Miss Em'ly took hold at once to help.
"Bishey," she commanded, "do you go at
<pb n="250"/>
once to where my boxes are open, the one
marked 7; bring me a blue jar you'll find in
one corner."  He went to do her bidding, and
I to see about the kiddies.  When I came
back with them, there was a small willow
basket in the center of our improvised table,
heaped high with pears, apples, and grapes
all a little the worse for their long journey
from New York State to Wyoming, but still
things of beauty and a joy as long as they
lasted to Wyoming eyes and appetites.  We
had a perfectly roasted leg of lamb; we
had mint sauce, a pyramid of flaky mashed
potatoes, a big dish of new peas, a plate of
sponge-cake I will be long in forgetting; and
the blue jar was full of grape marmalade.
Our iced tea was exactly right; the pieces
of ice clinked pleasantly against our glasses.
We took our time, and we were all happy.
We could all see the beautiful sunset, its last
rays lingering on Miss Em'ly's abundant
auburn hair to make happy the bride the sun
shines on.  We saw the wonderful colors&mdash;
<pb n="251"/>
orange, rose, and violet&mdash;creep up and fade
into darker shades, until at last mellow dusk
filled the room.  Then I took the kiddies to
my room to be put to bed while I should wait
until time for the ceremony.
</p><p>Soon the babies were sleeping, and Jerrine
and I went into the sitting-room.  They were
sitting on the "sofy."  She was telling him
that the apples had come from the tree they
had played under, the pears from the tree
they had set out, the grapes from the vine
over the well.  She told him of things packed
in her boxes, everything a part of the past
they both knew.  He in turn told her of his
struggles, his successes, and some of what he
called his failures.  She was a most encouraging
little person, and she'd say to him, "You
did well, Bishey.  I'll say <hi rend="italic">that</hi> for you: you
did well!"  Then he told her about the flowers
he had planted for her.  I understood then
why he acted so queerly about my flowers.
It happens that I am partial to old-time
favorites, and I grow as many of them as I
<pb n="252"/>
can get to succeed in this altitude; so I have
zinnias, marigolds, hollyhocks, and many
other dear old flowers that my mother loved.
Many of them had been the favorites of Miss
Em'ly's childhood, but Bishey hadn't remembered
the names; so he had visited us
all, and when he found a flower he remembered,
he asked the name and how we grew
it, then he tried it, until at last he had about
all.  Miss Em'ly wiped the tears from her eyes
as she remarked, "Bishey, you did well; yes,
you did <hi rend="italic">real</hi> well."  I thought to myself how
well we could <hi rend="italic">all</hi> do if we were so encourage.
   At last the white-haired old justice of the
peace came, and said the words that made
Emily Wheeler the wife of Abisha Bennet.  A
powerfully noisy but truly friendly crowd
wished them well.  One polite fellow asked
her where she was from.  She told him from
New York <hi rend="italic">State</hi>.  "Why," he asked, "do
New Yorkers always say <hi rend="italic">State</hi>?"  "Why, because,"
she answered,&mdash;and her eyes were
<pb n="253"/>
big with surprise,&mdash;<hi rend="italic">"no</hi> one would want to
say they were from New York <hi rend="italic">City</hi>."
</p><p>It had been a trying day for us, so soon
Jerrine and I slipped out to our room.  Ours
was the first room off the sitting-room, and a
long hallway led past our door; a bench sat
against the wall, and it seemed a favorite
roosting-place for people with long discussions.
 First some fellows were discussing the
wedding.  One thought Bishey "cracked"
because he had shipped out an old cooking-stove, one of the first manufactured, all the
way from where he came from, instead of
buying a new one nearer home.  They recalled
instance after instance in which he had
acted queerly, but to me his behavior was no
longer a mystery.  I know the stove belonged
somewhere in the past and that his every act
connected past and future.  After they had
talked themselves tired, two old fellows took
possession of the bench and added a long discussion
on how to grow corn to the general
din.  Even sweet corn cannot be successfully
<pb n="254"/>
grown at this altitude, yet those old men
argued pro and con till I know their throats
must have ached.  In the sitting-room they
all talked at once of ditches, water-contracts,
and sheep.  I was <hi rend="italic">so</hi> sleepy.  I heard a tired
clock away off somewhere strike two.  Some
sheep-men had the bench and were discussing
the relative values of different dips.  I reckon
my ego must have gotten tangled with some
one's else about then, for I found myself
sitting up in bed foolishly saying,&mdash;

</p><p>"Two old herders, unshaved and hairy,
</p><p>Whose old tongues are <hi rend="italic">never</hi> weary,
</p><p>Just outside my chamber-door
</p><p>Prate of sheep dips for <hi rend="italic">ever</hi> more."

</p><p>Next morning it was Bishey's cheerful
voice that started my day.  I had hoped to
be up in time to see them off, but I wasn't.
I heard him call out to Mrs. Bishey, "Miss
Em'ly, I've got the boxes all loaded.  We can
start <hi rend="italic">home</hi> in ten minutes."  I heard her clear
voice reply, "You've done well, Bishey.  I'll
be ready by then."  I was hurriedly dressing,
<pb n="255"/>
hoping yet to see her, when I heard Bishey
call out to bluff old Colonel Winters, who
had arrived in the night and had not known
of the wedding, "Hello!  Winters, have you
met Miss Em'ly?  Come over here and meet
her.  I'm a married man now.  I married Miss
Em'ly last night."  The colonel couldn't
have known how apt was his reply when he
said, "I'm glad for you, Bishey.  You've done
well."  I peeked between the curtains, and
saw Bishey's wagon piled high with boxes,
with Miss Em'ly, self-possessed and happy,
greeting the colonel.  Soon I heard the rattle
of wheels, and the dear old happy pair were
on their way to the cabin home they had
waited twenty-five years for.  Bless the kind
old hearts of them!  I'm sure they've both
"done well."


<pb n="256"/>
</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="25" id="d30">
<head> "AMONG THE MORMONS"
<hi rend="italic">November</hi>, 1913.</head>
<salute>
MY DEAR FRIEND,&mdash;
</salute>
<p>I have wanted to write you for a long time,
but have been so busy.  I have had some visit-ors and have been on a visit; I think you would
like to hear about it all, so I will tell you.
</p><p>I don't think you would have admired my
appearance the morning this adventure began:
I was in the midst of fall house-cleaning
which included some papering.  I am no expert
at the very best, and papering a wall has
difficulties peculiar to itself.  I was up on a
barrel trying to get a long, sloppy strip of
paper to stick to the ceiling instead of to me,
when in my visitors trooped, and so surprised
me that I stepped off the barrel and into a
candy-bucket of paste.  At the same time the
paper came off the ceiling and fell over mine
<pb n="257"/>
and Mrs. Louderer's head.  It was right
aggravating, I can tell you, but my visitors
were Mrs. O'Shaughnessy and Mrs. Louderer,
and no one could stay discouraged with
that pair around.
</p><p>After we had scraped as much paste as we
could off ourselves they explained that they
had come to take me somewhere.  That
sounded good to me, but I could not see how I
could get off.  However, Mrs. Louderer said
she had come to keep house and to take care
of the children while I should go with Mrs.
O'Shaughnessy to E&mdash;.  We should have
two days' travel by sled and a few hours
on a train, then another journey by sled.
I wanted to go powerfully, but the paste-smeared room seemed to forbid.
</p><p>As Mrs. Louderer would stay with the
children, Mr. Stewart thought the trip would
be good for me.  Mrs. O'Shaughnessy knew
I wanted to visit Bishop D&mdash;, a shining
light among the Latter-Day Saints, so she
promised we should stay overnight at his
<pb n="258"/>
house.  That settled it; so in the cold, blue
light of the early morning, Mr. Beeler, a new
neighbor, had driven my friends over in Mrs.
Louderer's big sled, to which was hitched a
pair of her great horses and his own team.  He
is a widower and was going out to the road
for supplies, so it seemed a splendid time to
make my long-planned visit to the Bishop.
Deep snow came earlier this year than usual,
and the sledding and weather both promised
to be good.  It was with many happy anticipations
that I snuggled down among the
blankets and bearskins that morning.
</p><p>Mr. Beeler is pleasant company, and Mrs.
O'Shaughnessy is so jolly and bright, and I
could leave home without a single misgiving
with Mrs. Louderer in charge.
</p><p>The evening sky was blazing crimson and
gold, and the mountains behind us were
growing purple when we entered the little
settlement where the Bishop lives.  We drove
briskly through the scattered, straggling little
village, past the store and the meeting-house,
<pb n="259"/>
and drew up before the dwelling of the
Bishop.  The houses of the village were for
the most part small cabins of two or three
rooms, but the Bishop's was more pretentious.
 It was a frame building and boasted
paint and shutters.  A tithing-office stood
near, and back of the house we could see a
large granary and long stacks of hay.  A bunch
of cattle was destroying one stack, and Mrs.
O'Shaughnessy remarked that the tallow from
those cattle should be used when the olive oil
gave out at their anointings, because it was
the Bishop's cattle eating consecrated hay.
</p><p>We knocked on the door, but got no answer.
 Mr. Beeler went around to the back,
but no one answered, so we concluded we
would have to try elsewhere for shelter.  Mrs.
O'Shaughnessy comforted me by remarking,
"Well, there ain't a penny's worth of difference
in a Mormon bishop and any other Mormon,
and D&mdash; is not the only polygamist
by a long shot."
</p><p>We had just turned out of the gate when a
<pb n="260"/>
lanky, tow-headed boy about fourteen years
of age rode up.  We explained our presence
there, and the boy explained to us that the
Bishop and Aunt Debbie were away.  The
next best house up the road was his "Maw's,"
he said; so, as Mr. Beeler expected to stay
with a friend of his, Mrs. O'Shaughnessy and
I determined to see if "Maw" could accomodate
us for the night.
</p><p>Mr. Beeler offered to help the boy get the
cattle out, but he said, "No, Paw said it
would not matter if they got into the hay,
but that he had to knock off some poles on
another part of the stockyard so that some
horses could get in to eat."
</p><p>"But," I asked, "isn't that consecrated
hay?&mdash;isn't it tithing?"
</p><p>"Yes," he said, "but that won't hurt a
bit, only that old John Ladd always pays his
tithe with foxtail hay and it almost ruins
Paw's horses' mouths."
</p><p>I asked him if his father's stock was supposed
to get the hay.
<pb n="261"/>
</p><p>"No, I guess not," he said, "but they are
always getting in accidental like."
</p><p>We left him to fix the fence so the horses
could get in "accidental like," and drove the
short distance to "the next best house."
</p><p>We were met at the door by a pleasant-faced little woman who hurried us to the fire.
We told her our plight.  "Why, certainly you
must stay with me," she said.  "I am glad
the Bishop and Deb are away.  They keep all
the company, and I so seldom have any one
come; you see Debbie has no children and
can do so much better for any one stopping
there than I can, but I like company, too,
and I am glad of a chance to keep you.  You
two can have Maudie's bed.  Maud is my
oldest girl and she has gone to Ogden to visit,
so we have plenty of room."
</p><p>By now it was quite dark.  She lighted a
lamp and bustled about, preparing supper.
We sat by the stove and, as Mrs. O'Shaughnessy
said, "noticed."
</p><p>Two little boys were getting in wood for
<pb n="262"/>
the night.  They appeared to be about eight
years old; they were twins and were the
youngest of the family.  Two girls, about ten
and twelve years old, were assisting our hostess;
then the boy Orson, whom we met at
the gate, and Maud, the daughter who was
away, made up the family.  They seemed a
happy, contented family, if one judged by
appearance alone.  After supper the children
gathered around the table to prepare next
day's lessons.  They were bright little folks,
but they mingled a great deal of talk with
their studies and some of what they talked
was family history.
</p><p>"Mamma," said Kittie, the largest of the
little girls, "if Aunt Deb does buy a new coat
and you get her old one, then can I have
yours?"
</p><p>"I don't know," her mother replied; "I
should have to make it over if you did take
it.  Maybe we can have a new one."
</p><p>"No, we can't have a new one, I know, for
Aunt Deb said so, but she is going to give me
<pb n="263"/>
her brown dress and you her gray one; she
said so the day I helped her iron.  We'll have
those to make over."
</p><p>For the first time I noticed the discontented
lines on our hostess's face, and it suddenly
occurred to me that we were in the
house of the Bishop's second wife.  Before I
knew I was coming on this journey I thought
of a dozen questions I wanted to ask the
Bishop, but I could never ask that careworn
little woman anything concerning their
peculiar belief.  However, I was spared the
trouble, for soon the children retired and the
conversation drifted around to Mormonism
and polygamy; and our hostess seemed to
want to talk, so I just listened, for Mrs.
O'Shaughnessy rather likes to "argufy"; but
she had no argument that night, only her
questions started our hostess's story.
</p><p>She had been married to the Bishop not
long before the manifesto, and he had been
married several years then to Debbie.  But
Debbie had no children, and all the money
<pb n="264"/>
the Bishop had to start with had been his first
wife's; so when it became necessary for him
to discard a wife it was a pretty hard question
for him because a little child was coming
to the second wife and he had nothing to provide
for her with except what his first wife's
money paid for.  The first wife said she would
content to him starting the second, if she
filed on land and paid her back a small sum
every year until it was all paid back.  So he
took the poor "second," after formally renouncing
her, and helped her to file on the
land she now lives on.  He built her a small
cabin, and so she started her career as a
"second."  I suppose the "first" thought she
would be rid of the second, who had never
really been welcome, although the Bishop
could never have married a "second" without
her consent.
</p><p>"I would <hi rend="italic">never</hi> consent," said Mrs.
O'Shaughnessy.
</p><p>"Oh, yes, you would if you had been raised
a Mormon," said our hostess.  "You see, we
<pb n="265"/>
were all of us children of polygamous parents.
We have been used to plural marriages all
our lives.  We believe that such experience
fits us for our after-life, as we are only preparing
for life beyond while here."
</p><p>"Do you expect to go to heaven, and do
you think the man who married you and then
discarded you will go to heaven too?" asked
Mrs. O'Shaughnessy.
</p><p>"Of course I do," she replied.
</p><p>"Then," said Mrs. O'Shaughnessy, "I am
afraid if it had been mysilf I'd have been
after raising a little hell here intirely."
</p><p>Our hostess was not offended, and there
followed a long recital of earlier-day hard
times that you would scarcely believe any
one could live through.  It seems the first
wife in such families is boss, and while they
do not live in the same homes, still she can
very materially affect the other's comfort.
</p><p>Mrs. O'Shaughnessy asked her if she had
married again.
</p><p>She said, "No."
<pb n="266"/>
</p><p>"Then," said Mrs. O'Shaughnessy, "whose
children are these?"
</p><p>"My own," she replied.
</p><p>Mrs. O'Shaughnessy was relentless.  "Who
is their father?" she asked.
</p><p>I was right sorry for the poor little woman
as she stammered, "I&mdash;I don't know."
</p><p>Then she went on, "Of course I <hi rend="italic">do</hi> know,
and I don't believe you are spying to try
to stir up trouble for my husband.  Bishop
D&mdash; is their father, as he is still my husband,
although he had to cast me off to save
himself and me.  I love him and I see no
wrong in him.  All the Gentiles have against
him is he is a little too smart for them.  'T was
their foolish law that made him wrong the
children and me, and <hi rend="italic">not</hi> his wishes."
</p><p>"But," Mrs. O'Shaughnessy said, "it
places your children in such a plight; they
can't inherit, they can't even claim his name,
they have no status legally."
</p><p>"Oh, but the Bishop will see to that," the
little woman answered.
<pb n="267"/>
</p><p>Mrs. O'Shaughnessy asked her if she had
still to work as hard as she used to.
</p><p>"No, I don't believe I do," she said, "for
since Mr. D&mdash; has been Bishop, things
come easier.  He built this house with his
own money, so Deb has nothing to do with
it."
</p><p>I asked her if she thought she was as happy
as "second" as she would be if she was the
<hi rend="italic">only</hi> wife.
</p><p>"Oh, I don't know," she said, "perhaps
not.  Deb and me don't always agree.  She
is jealous of the children and because I am
younger, and I get to feeling bad when I
think she is perfectly safe as a wife and has
no cares.  She has everything she wants, and
I have to take what I can get, and my children
have to wait upon her.  But it will all
come right somewhere, sometime," she ended
cheerfully, as she wiped her eyes with her
apron.
</p><p>I felt so sorry for her and so ashamed to
have seen into her sorrow that I was really
<pb n="268"/>
glad next morning when I heard Mr. Beeler's
cheerful voice calling, "All aboard!"
</p><p>We had just finished breakfast, and few
would ever guess that Mrs. D&mdash; knew a
trial; she was so cheerful and so cordial as she
bade us good-bye and urged us to stop with
her every time we passed through.
</p><p>About noon that day we reached the railroad.
 The snow had delayed the train farther
north, so for once we were glad to have to
wait for a train, as it gave us time to get
a bite to eat and to wash up a bit.  It was
not long, however, till we were comfortably
seated in the train.  I think a train ride might
not be so enjoyable to most, but to us it
was a delight; I even enjoyed looking at the
Negro porter, although I suspect he expected
to be called Mister.  I found very soon after
coming West that I must not say "Uncle" or
"Aunty" as I used to at home.
</p><p>It was not long until they called the name
of the town at which we wanted to stop.
Mrs. O'Shaughnessy had a few acquaintances
<pb n="269"/>
there, but we went to a hotel.  We were both
tired, so as soon as we had supper we went to
bed.  The house we stopped at was warmer
and more comfortable than the average hotel
in the West, but the partitions were very
thin, so when a couple of "punchers," otherwise
cowboys, took the room next to ours, we
could hear every word they said.
</p><p>It appears that one was English and the
other a tenderfoot.  The tenderfoot was in
love with a girl who had filed on a homestead
near the ranch on which he was employed,
but who was then a waitress in the hotel we
were at.  She had not seemed kind to the
tenderfoot and he was telling his friend about
it.  The Englishman was trying to instruct
him as to how to proceed.
</p><p>"You need to be <hi rend="italic">very</hi> circumspect, Johnny,
where females are concerned, but you must
n't be too danged timid either."
</p><p>"I don't know what the devil to say to her;
I can barely nod my head when she asks me
will I take tea or coffee; and to-night she
<pb n="270"/>
mixed it because I nodded yes when she said,
'tea or coffee,' and it was the dangdest mess I
ever tried to get outside of."
</p><p>"Well," the friend counseled, "you just
get her into a corner some'eres and say to 'er,
'Dearest 'Attie, I hoffer you my 'and hand
my 'eart.'"
</p><p>"But I <hi rend="italic">can't</hi>," wailed Johnny.  "I could
never get her into a corner anyway."
</p><p>"If you can't, you're not hold enough to
marry then.  What the 'ell would you do with
a woman in the 'ouse if you couldn't corner
'er?  I tell 'e, women 'ave to 'ave a master,
and no man better tackle that job until 'e
can be sure 'e can make 'er walk the chalk-line."
   "But I don't want her to walk any line; I
just want her to speak to me."
</p><p>"Dang me if I don't believe you are locoed.
Why, she's got 'e throwed hand 'og-tied now.
What d'e want to make it any worse for?"
</p><p>They talked for a long time and the Englishman
continued to have trouble with his
<pb n="271"/>
<hi rend="italic">h</hi>'s; but at last Johnny was encouraged to
"corner 'er" next morning before they left
for their ranch.
</p><p>We expected to be astir early anyway, and
our curiosity impelled us to see the outcome
of the friend's counsel, so we were almost the
first in the dining-room next morning.  A
rather pretty girl was busy arranging the
tables, and soon a boyish-looking fellow,
wearing great bat-wing chaps, came in and
stood warming himself at the stove.
</p><p>I knew at once it was Johnny, and I saw
"'Attie" blush.  The very indifference with
which she treated him argued well for his
cause, but of course he didn't know that.  So
when she passed by him and her skirt caught
on his big spurs they both stooped at once to
unfasten it; their heads hit together with such
a bump that the ice was broken, although
he seemed to think it was her skull.  I am
sure there ought to be a thaw after all his
apologies.  After breakfast Mrs. O'Shaughnessy
went out to see her friend Cormac
<pb n="272"/>
O'Toole.  He was the only person in town
we could hope to get a team from with which
to continue our journey.  This is a hard country
on horses at best, and at this time of the
year particularly so; few will let their teams
go out at any price, but Mrs. O'Shaughnessy
had hopes, and she is so persuasive that I felt
no one could resist her.  There was a drummer
at breakfast who kept "cussing" the
country.  He had tried to get a conveyance
and had failed; so the cold, the snow, the
people, and everything else disgusted him.
</p><p>Soon Mrs. O'Shaughnessy returned, and
as the drummer was trying to get out to
E&mdash;, and that was our destination also,
she made her way toward him, intending to
invite him to ride with us.  She wore over her
best clothes an old coat that had once belonged
to some one of her men friends.  It had
once been bearskin, but was now more <hi rend="italic">bare</hi>
skin, so her appearance was against her; she
looked like something with the mange.  So
Mr. Drummer did not wait to hear what she
<pb n="273"/>
was going to say but at once exclaimed, "No,
madam, I cannot let you ride out with me.  I
can't get a rig myself in this beastly place."
Then he turned to a man standing near and
remarked, "These Western women are so
bold they don't hesitate to <hi rend="italic">demand</hi> favors."
</p><p>Mrs. O'Shaughnessy's eyes fairly snapped,
but she said nothing.  I think she took a malicious
delight in witnessing the drummer's
chagrin when a few moments later our comfortable
sleigh and good strong team appeared.
</p><p>We were going to drive ourselves, but we
had to drive to the depot for our suit-cases;
but when we got there the ticket-office was
not open, so the agent was probably having
his beauty sleep.  There was a fire in the big
stove, and we joined the bunch of men in the
depot.  Among them we noticed a thin, consumptive-looking
fellow, evidently a stranger.
</p><p>Very soon some men began talking of some
transaction in which a Bishop B&mdash; was
concerned.  It seemed they didn't admire
the Bishop very much; they kept talking of
<pb n="274"/>
his peculiarities and transgressions, and mentioned
his treatment of his wives.  His "second,"
they said, was blind because of cataracts,
and, although abundantly able, he left
her in darkness.  She had never seen her two
last children.  Some one spoke up and said,
"I thought polygamy was no longer practiced."
 Then the man explained that they no
longer contracted plural marriages, but that
many kept <hi rend="italic">all</hi> their wives and B&mdash; still had
both of his.  He went on to say that although
such practice is contrary to law, it was almost
impossible to make a case against them, for
the women would not swear against their
husbands.  B&mdash; had been arrested once,
but his second swore that she didn't know
who her children's father was, and it cost the
sheriff his office the next election.
</p><p>Mrs. O'Shaughnessy spoke to an acquaintance
of hers and mentioned where we were
going.  In a short while we got our suit-cases
and we were off, but as we drove past the
freight depot, the stranger we had noticed
<pb n="275"/>
came down the steps and asked us to let him
ride out with us.  I really felt afraid of him,
but Mrs. O'Shaughnessy thinks herself a
match for any mere man, so she drew up and
the man climbed in.  He took the lines and
we snuggled down under the robes and listened
to the runners, shrill screeching over
the frozen surface.
</p><p>We had dinner with a new settler, and
about two o'clock that afternoon we overtook
a fellow who was plodding along the
road.  His name was B&mdash;, he said, and he
pointed out to us his broad fields and herds.
He had been overseeing some feeders he had,
and his horse had escaped, so he was walking
home, as it was only a couple of miles.  He
talked a great deal in that two-mile trip; too
much for his own good, it developed.
</p><p>For the first time since B&mdash; climbed into
our sleigh, the stranger spoke.  "Can you tell
me where Mrs. Belle B&mdash; lives?" he asked.
</p><p>"Why, yes," our passenger replied.  "She
is a member of our little flock.  She is slightly
<pb n="276"/>
related to me, as you perhaps noticed the
name, and I will show you to her house."
</p><p>"Just how is she related to you?" the
stranger asked.
</p><p>"That," the man replied, "is a matter of
protection.  I have <hi rend="italic">given</hi> her the protection
of my name."
</p><p>"Then she is your wife, is she not?" the
stranger asked.
</p><p>"You must be a stranger in this country,"
the man evaded.  "What is your name?"
</p><p>But the stranger didn't seem to hear, and
just then we came opposite the residence of
the Bishop, and the man we had picked up in
the road said, "That is my home, won't you
get out and warm?  My wife will be glad to
get acquainted with you ladies."
</p><p>We declined, as it was only a short distance
to the house of the man Mrs. O'Shaughnessy
had come to see, so he stayed in the sleigh to
show the stranger to the house of Mrs. Belle
B&mdash;.  I can't say much for it as a house,
and I was glad I didn't have to go in.  The
<pb n="277"/>
stranger and B&mdash; got out and entered the
house, and we drove away.
</p><p>Next morning, as we returned through the
little village, it was all excitement.  Bishop
B&mdash; had been shot the night before, just
as he had left the house of Mrs. Belle B&mdash;,
for what reason or by whom no one knew;
and if the Bishop knew he had not told, for
he either would not or could not talk.
</p><p>They were going to start with him that day
to the hospital, but they had no hopes of his
living.
</p><p>When we came to Mrs. Belle's house, Mrs.
O'Shaughnessy got out of the sleigh and
went into the house.  I could hear her soothing
voice, and I was mighty glad the poor,
forlorn woman had such a comforter.
 .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .
</p><p>I was so <hi rend="italic">very</hi> glad to get home.  How good
it all looked to me!  "Poop o' Roome" has a
calf, and as we drove up to the corral Clyde
was trying to get it into the stall with the
rest.  It is "Poop's" first calf, and she is very
<pb n="278"/>
proud of it, and objected to its being put
away from her, so she bunted at Clyde, and
as he dodged her, the calf ran between his feet
and he sat down suddenly in the snow.  I
laughed at him, but I am powerfully glad he
is no follower of old Joseph Smith.
</p><p>Mrs. Louderer was enjoying herself immensely,
she loves children so much.  She
and Clyde hired the "Tackler"&mdash;so called
because he will tackle <hi rend="italic">any</hi> kind of a job,
whether he knows anything about it or not&mdash;
to paper the room.  He thinks he is a great
judge of the fitness of things and of beauty.
The paper has a stripe of roses, so Tackler
reversed every other strip so that some of
my roses are standing on their heads.  Roses
don't all grow one way, he claims, and so his
method "makes 'em look more nachul like."
</p><p>A little thing like wall-paper put on upside
down don't bother me; but what <hi rend="italic">would</hi> I do
if I were a "second"?</p>
<closer><salute>Your loving friend,</salute>
<signed>ELINORE RUPERT STEWART.</signed></closer>


</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="26" id="d31"><pb n="279"/>
<head> "SUCCESS" <hi rend="italic">November</hi>, 1913.</head>
<salute>
DEAR MRS. CONEY,&mdash;
</salute>
<p>  This is Sunday and I suppose I ought not
to be writing, but I must write to you and
I may not have another chance soon.  Both
your letters have reached me, and now that
our questions are settled we can proceed to
proceed.
</p><p>Now, this is the letter I have been wanting
to write you for a long time, but could not
because until now I had not actually proven
all I wanted to prove.  Perhaps it will not interest
you, but if you see a woman who wants to
homestead and is a little afraid she will starve,
you can tell her what I am telling you.
</p><p>I never did like to theorize, and so this
year I set out to prove that a woman could
ranch if she wanted to.  We like to grow potatoes
<pb n="280"/>
on new ground, that is, newly cleared
land on which no crop has been grown.  Few
weeds grow on new land, so it makes less work.
So I selected my potato-patch, and the man
ploughed it, although I could have done that
if Clyde would have let me.  I cut the potatoes,
Jerrine helped, and we dropped them
in the rows.  The man covered them, and
that ends the man's part.  By that time the
garden ground was ready, so I planted the
garden.  I had almost an acre in vegetables.
I irrigated and I cultivated it myself.
</p><p>We had all the vegetables we could possibly
use, and now Jerrine and I have put in
our cellar full, and this is what we have: one
large bin of potatoes (more than two tons),
half a ton of carrots, a large bin of beets, one
of turnips, one of onions, one of parsnips, and
on the other side of the cellar we have more
than one hundred heads of cabbage.  I have
experimented and found a kind of squash
that can be raised here, and that the ripe
ones keep well and make good pies; also that
<pb n="281"/>
the young tender ones make splendid pickles,
quite equal to cucumbers.  I was glad to
stumble on to that, because pickles are hard
to manufacture when you have nothing to
work with.  Now I have plenty.  They told
me when I came that I could not even raise
common beans, but I tried and succeeded.
And also I raised lots of green tomatoes, and,
as we like them preserved, I made them all up
that way.  Experimenting along another line,
I found that I could make catchup, as delicious
as that of tomatoes, of gooseberries.  I
made it exactly the same as I do the tomatoes
and I am delighted.  Gooseberries were very
fine and very plentiful this year, so I put up
a great many.  I milked ten cows twice a day
all summer; have sold enough butter to pay
for a year's supply of flour and gasoline.  We
use a gasoline lamp.  I have raised enough
chickens to completely renew my flock, and
all we wanted to eat, and have some fryers
to go into the winter with.  I have enough
turkeys for all of our birthdays and holidays.

<pb n="282"/>
</p><p>I raised a great many flowers and I worked
several days in the field.  In all I have told
about I have had no help but Jerrine.  Clyde's
mother spends each summer with us, and she
helped me with the cooking and the babies.
Many of my neighbors did better than I did,
although I know many town people would
doubt my doing so much, but I did it.  I have
tried every kind of work this ranch affords,
and I can do any of it.  Of course I <hi rend="italic">am</hi> extra
strong, but those who try know that strength
and knowledge come with doing.  I just love
to experiment, to work, and to prove out
things, so that ranch life and "roughing it"
just suit me.

</p>
<trailer>THE END</trailer>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
