<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="ThaCycl"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="ThaCycl"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Day of The Cyclone</title>
<title type="sort">day of the cyclone</title>
<author>Thanet, Octave</author>
<respStmt> 
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Charles Keller</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">49</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">ThaCycl</idno> 
<date value="2000">2000</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2000 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476388</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Day of The Cyclone</title>
<title level="m">Scribner`s Magazine</title>
<title type="sort">day of the cyclone</title>
<author>Octave Thanet</author>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>11 pages</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Charles Scribners Sons</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1888">1888</date> 
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: University of Virginia Library AP2 .S4 v.3 1888</idno>
</publicationStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1888">1888</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term> 
<term>prose</term> 
<term>masculine</term> 
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2000-09">September 2000</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Samuel A. Turner</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 
 
<body id="d2"> 
 

 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> <pb n="350"/> 
<head>THE DAY OF THE CYCLONE.<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic">By Octave Thanet</hi>.</head> 
 
<p> 
IT was a warm day. 
Perhaps but for that 
it might not have 
happened, since Captain Barris is a most 
temperate man.  Unluckily the day was 
warm, very warm, 
and Archy was tired with a long ride in 
the "accommodation train:" and a vision of a glass of beer &mdash; cool, foaming, 
pleasantly stinging &mdash; rose before him. 
He had just been stationed at Rock 
Island Arsenal, and all his knowledge of 
the town of Grinnell was the fact that he 
had inherited some property within its 
limits.  Quite innocently, therefore, he 
stared about him for some sign of refreshment. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
The street was like a hundred rural 
streets in the West &mdash; straight, broad, and 
shaded by young trees. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
All the wooden cottages might have 
been designed by the same prosaic architect. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Some of them looked a little rusty; 
many of them shone with new paint. 
They all had trim gardens in front, oases 
of verdure in the midst of the dust. 
Between the dwellings, every now and 
then, there would come a great gap of 
untilled fields where no mower disturbed 
the riotous plantain, and burdock and 
jimson weeds held a kind of squalid revelry over a heap of tin cans.   
The contrast between this unkempt domain and 
the tidiness of the dwellings was queer; 
but it was as Western as the sea of prairie 
around the town, or the fierce sun above. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
No quiver in the hot air blurred the 
shadows of the maple leaves on the side-walks.  A few farmers' wagons crawled 
tediously through the glare.  Just ahead 
of Archy was the solitary other footman 
in sight.  He was a big man, thin, but 
built on the large and sinewy plan. 
Though it was so warm, his gray head 
was covered with a soft black felt hat, 
and he wore the heaviest of boots.  To 
make matters more equal, he carried his 
black coat on his arm and had unbuttoned  
his old-fashioned waistcoat.  He 
walked slowly, with the round shoulders 
and uneven gait of a man accustomed to 
watch the ground. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
So little did Archy know of the interior of Iowa that he marched up to this 
old man and asked where he could get a 
glass of beer. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
His answer was the view of a gaunt 
and weather-beaten visage and a portentous frown. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Kin I tell you where ye kin get a 
glass of beer?" repeated the man, who 
frowned as the keen gray eyes under 
the beetling brows took in Archy's elegant figure, from the white Derby hat of 
the period to his immaculate gaiters. 
"No, young man, I cayn't; and I'd advise you to quit huntin' up beer, or ye 
won't wear sich good clo'se long.  Anyhow, ye won't find no beer in Grinnell." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"What's the trouble with Grinnell?" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"The trouble is, it's a prohibition 
town; and prohibition in Grinnell does 
prohibit.  There ain't a saloon in the 
place.  Ye cayn't git a drop of intoxicatin' liquor, not a drop &mdash; " 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Here his underjaw fell, his eyeballs 
fixed themselves in a dismal stare; and 
the didactic forefinger, which had been 
sawing the air, was paralyzed midway, so 
that it pointed straight at the red-faced 
man reeling round the corner.  The 
look and the swagger of him were unmistakable. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Perhaps <hi rend="italic">he</hi> could tell me," said 
Archy. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
He made the old man a very fine bow 
and walked away, smiling. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
But when he returned to Grinnell, 
a year later, he was more serious.  "I 
daresay Rachel's father is another of 
the same sort," he reflected; "if not &mdash; 
by Jove, that would be too much, 
though!" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
He laughed a little lugubriously.  Rachel  
was beautiful enough, and what was 
better, sweet and good enough to justify 
any man's passion; and he was as much 
in love as a man can well be; but he 
thought of her people with a qualm. 
 
 
<pb n="351"/> 
 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"I grant that Rachel is an angel" &mdash; 
so his mother had talked &mdash; "and the angels  
are above social distinctions; but 
her father and mother?" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Her mother is presumedly an angel, 
too," Archy had replied, "she has been 
dead these ten years." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Well, there are her father and two 
brothers.  And she told me that there 
was a cousin visiting them whom her 
father was going to marry.  <hi rend="italic">She</hi> comes 
from Vermont; but I don't believe the 
boys have ever been out of Grinnell in 
their lives.  You can't judge these people 
by the Ramsays, Archy; the Ramsays 
have been everywhere.  It was only a 
freak of Mr. Ramsay sending Ethel to 
Grinnell.  Archy, I feel sure her people 
are <hi rend="italic">impossible!"</hi> 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"I shan't marry her people," Archy 
had said, lightly. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
But now, with some misgivings, he 
scanned the elderly men coming home 
to their midday dinners, anyone of 
whom might be <hi rend="italic">her</hi> father.  Sedate, 
prosperous-looking men they were, very 
like men of their years in a New England  
village, except for a slight Western 
negligence of dress. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Ramsay is right," mused Archy; 
"Grinnell is a Puritan colony in the 
prairie." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
He was in the College campus, now. 
The ugly, square stone building he 
judged to be the college hall, and from 
the number of heads at the windows he 
surmised that a tall brick building was 
a kind of dormitory.  The pretty cottages  
about must be the professors' 
houses, and the young men and maidens 
among the trees must be the students. 
He thought that the youths had rather 
a rustic air, but some of the girls were 
admirably pretty, and the ripple of their 
gayety spread to the faces of the passers-by. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"But not one of them," was his comment,  
"can compare with Rachel &mdash; 
Hallo! here's the house." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
A door-plate left him in no doubt. 
The house was of wood, of two stories, 
and had two bay-windows and a piazza.   
It was painted gray, and the blinds 
were red.  There was a garden before 
it full of rose-bushes, and the roses were 
in bloom.  Archy grew a little dizzy; 
he had not seen Rachel for a week; he 
would see her in a moment, and being a 
modest, true-hearted young fellow, very 
much in love, his soul abased itself 
before this delicate and radiant creature 
whom he was daring to make his own. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"My white rose," murmured the lover, 
"I am not worthy, but I will try." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Cayn't ye make nobuddy hear ye? 
That gong's intended to ring," remarked 
a harsh, deep voice at his elbow.  An 
old man had come around a bay-window 
to find Archy smiling tenderly at the 
door-plate.  It was the same old man 
whom he had met before. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"I am looking for Mr. Jared Meadowes,"  
said Archy, whose heart sank 
down to his boots. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Well, you've found him." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Inwardly Archy groaned, outwardly 
he bowed and said, "I am Captain 
Barris." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Walk in," said Meadowes, throwing 
the door open, but with no gleam of cordiality  
on his face. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
He strode on before, Archy thinking 
how familiar his back looked, for he was 
in his shirt-sleeves.  He had also dispensed  
with shoes, and his white socks 
glimmered in the obscurity of the hall. 
Archy followed him into a pretty room, 
and took the chair pushed forward.  The 
old man seated himself opposite, planted 
his hands on his knees in the fashion 
of a rustic photograph, and proceeded 
to subject the young officer to a grim 
and leisurely scrutiny.  Decidedly it was 
not a promising welcome. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
However, one cannot sit indefinitely 
staring at one's prospective father-in-law, 
so Archy cleared his throat and began. 
He presumed Mr. Meadowes knew the 
object of his visit.  He had met Miss 
Meadowes at her friend Miss Ramsay's. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Six weeks ago," interrupted the old 
man, "and now ye want to marry her." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
A trifle disconcerted Archy next tried 
to explain his position and prospects. 
"He was in the army, stationed at Rock 
Island Arsenal.  The quarters there &mdash;" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"That's all right," said the old man, 
"I've been on the Island.  Big thing. 
Big arsenal.  But I want to hear 'bout 
<hi rend="italic">you</hi>." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Oh, I?  I am twenty-eight years of 
age.  My father was in the army, General  
Barris.  He was killed in the war. 
It is rather an army family.  My mother 
 
 
<pb n="352"/> 
 
is a Massachusetts woman.  She was a 
Miss Saltonstall." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Dependent on you?" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"She has about half a million dollars 
from her father.  I have one sister, who 
is married and lives in New York.  She 
is not dependent on me either.  My 
mother lives with me.  She &mdash; everybody 
thinks my mother a charming woman." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"But Rachel ain't goin' to marry your 
mother.  Cayn't seem to git ye to talk 
'bout yourself.  Ramsay gives you a fine 
send off in his letter; but things don't 
strike him and I just the same.  I guess 
you're a desirable husband as the world 
looks at things; but I ain't one of the 
world's people.  Never was.  You ain't 
the kind of husband I'd pick out for my 
daughter.  Nor yours ain't the kind of 
life I'd choose for her.  But if you're a 
good man, and likely to make her happy, 
I won't stand in the way.  It's nature, I 
s'pose.  I took her mother off to Kansas, 
'way from her folks, an' now you want 
to take her, an' she's glad to go; but 
'tain't nature I should be glad to have 
her.  Well, now, s'posin' you stop to 
dinner an' give me a chance to sorter 
size ye up; an' if I like the look o' ye 
I'll go down to Rock Island, and if you're 
satisfactory all 'round, it will be time to 
talk of marrying." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"I shall wait until after dinner, then," 
said Archy, smiling. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
No answering smile relaxed the other's 
iron features as he replied: "All right. 
Make yourself to home.  I'll go tell the 
folks." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
He left Archy in a frame of mind 
about equally compounded of irritation, 
amusement, and consternation.  The 
young man could not help laughing as 
he pictured his mother's horror when 
she should see Meadowes.  "Well, anyhow,  
I don't blame him for not wanting 
to give up Rachel," he thought, gazing 
about the room for some trace of this 
one sweet presence.  He rightly judged 
the soft hues of the walls and draperies, 
and the pretty feminine fancies of 
wicker-work and ribbon to be of her 
choosing; but he gave old Meadowes full 
credit for the plaster group representing  
the signing of the Emancipation 
Proclamation, and for a huge, pale engraving  
of Lincoln in the bosom of his 
family.  Above the mantel-piece hung 
a water-color portrait, sumptuously 
framed, with a jar of roses before it 
like an offering before a shrine.  Plainly,  
it was the important object in the 
room.  The portrait was a man's head. 
The features, the brows and the contour 
of the face, which was clean shaven, reminded  
Archy of those multitudinous 
busts in the Vatican.  Like them, also, 
was the singularly calm and determined 
expression.  But the blue eyes were 
mild, sad, and dreamy.  Archy had 
risen for a nearer view when the inmates  
of the house appeared.  They 
were Rachel, her future stepmother, and 
her two brothers.  The future stepmother was introduced as Miss Baker. 
She resembled Rachel in figure and  
carriage, rather than in features or coloring;  
and Archy had a fancy that her 
gentle, faded face looked a good deal as 
the late Mrs. Meadowes's might have 
done at the age of &mdash; say forty.  But, 
naturally, his glance only lingered a 
polite instant before it sought Rachel 
to the wild flowers growing in the clefts 
of New England rocks.  Her extraordinary beauty was of that fragile type 
which has a pathos in its very charm. 
Really, Rachel was both healthy and 
happy, and her father loved to boast of 
her prowess in mathematics at the Grinnell  
College; yet whoever looked on her 
exquisite, pale face, with its wistful eyes 
and sensitive mouth, felt an involuntary 
sympathy, well enough interpreted by 
Archy's mother's remark: "That is the 
kind of girl who can break her heart!" 
She was a creature to whom one is 
gentle by instinct.  Nevertheless, such 
creatures have their own strength.  She 
was graceful because she could not help 
it, and had a natural sense of beauty. 
Archy felt a fond pride as the lovely 
shape approached.  Nothing more than 
a white frock and some red roses; but 
how they suited her. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
By this time he was back in his chair, 
beaming with great friendliness upon 
the two youths, Ossawatomie ("Is he 
named for an Indian chief?" wondered 
Archy) and Jared.  They were twin 
brothers, two years younger than Rachel; 
both tall, slim, and shy; having their sister's  
fascinating combination of bronze 
hair and dark-brown eyes, but with features 
 
<pb n="353"/> 
 
which were a softened copy of 
their father's.  Jared did not open his 
lips; but Ossawatomie made some timid 
advances.  To help on the lagging talk 
Archy spoke of the water-color.  "It 
was painted on East," said Ossawatomie, 
"from a daguerreotype.  It is John 
Brown." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"The Queen's John Brown, or John 
Brown's body?" Archy asked, with his 
fatal levity. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"That, sir," said a deep voice, "is 
John Brown of Ossawatomie, the noblest 
man that ever died for liberty!" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Archy had not seen him approach, 
and who can hear the footfall of socks? 
There he stood in the doorway, fore-finger uplifted, as grim and dark a figure 
as ever sent a witch to the gallows. 
"Well, sir," he continued, "what is <hi rend="italic">your</hi> 
opinion of him?" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"He was a hero, certainly," said Archy, 
"whatever his mistakes." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">"What</hi> mistakes?" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Well, Harper's Ferry.  And that 
Missouri affair where they dragged men 
out of their cabins and shot them in the 
hearing of their wives and children &mdash;" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
The old man interrupted him as usual: 
"Brown wasn't on that raid.  But that 
ain't sayin' he condemned it; he didn't. 
And you needn't waste much pity on 
them men.  They had blood on their 
own hands, every one of them; they had 
murdered Free State men; and they were 
judged, condemned, and killed for it, as 
they had ought to be.  That's all there 
is to that affair.  Those border ruffians 
used to ride over into Kansas, and slay, 
and steal, and burn.  They'd come over 
and vote, and make our laws for us. 
Then they'd shoot us 'cause we objected. 
Didn't ye never hear of the sack of 
Lawrence?  A neighbor of mine was 
shot down, right before his wife, by three 
men.  Three to one, those were their 
odds.  I know all about it, for I was one 
of Brown's men.  I was only a stripling, 
but I had the luck to be in four fights, 
and I got a bullet in my leg that, like's 
not, saved my life, for else I'd a gone off 
with Brown to Harper's Ferry, so I 
guess I owe one good turn to a border 
ruffian.  But, I tell you, I didn't thank 
him for it when I read in the papers how 
those he counted on failed him, and he 
was trapped and lay wounded in prison, 
and then how he &mdash; died.  I'd lay on my 
bed and cry, 'cause I couldn't be there and 
fight it out with him.  Say, sir, you that 
call Harper's Ferry a <hi rend="italic">mistake</hi>, say, did 
you ever read the letters he wrote when 
he was in prison in Charleston?" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"No, I don't think I have; I don't remember  
them," said Archy, meekly. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Then you better, 'fore ye discuss 
Brown and his mistakes again," said 
Brown's old follower.  It was a welcome 
diversion to have Rachel, who had left the 
room for a second, return, to announce 
dinner.  Archy managed to get near 
enough to her for a whisper; but she 
only gave him a frightened glance and 
said, <hi rend="italic">"Please</hi> don't talk about Brown to 
pa until you know more.  Ossie's named 
after him.  Pa thinks the world of him!" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
The meal began ominously.  Archy 
had been praising the pretty town. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"We owe our prosperity to our liquor 
laws," said Mr. Meadowes.  "Humph, 
did ye find any beer that day?" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
So he had remembered!  Archy, blushing  
in spite of himself, said, "No, he 
hadn't tried." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"You drink to home, I s'pose.  Have 
wine on the table?" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Archy confessed to an occasional glass 
of claret with his dinner. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Them boys," said the old man, slanting  
his thumb at the twins, "them boys 
ain't never touched a drop of spirituous 
liquor in their lives." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Indeed," said Archy, trying to throw 
a sympathetic accent into the word. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Yes, sir.  And the majority of the 
boys here have the same habits.  That's 
the great advantage of a prohibitory 
law; it makes a town safe to raise boys 
in.  I wouldn't raise a family in Davenport  
if you gave me my home." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"But Davenport is a delightful place, 
don't you know, Mr. Meadowes; and in 
spite of their saloons, there isn't a town 
in Iowa with a smaller percentage of 
criminal business." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"All the same," Meadowes retorted, 
sardonically,  we'll try to improve it a 
bit.  We are goin' to pass a law that 
will wipe out the saloons all over Iowa. 
P'raps you don't believe sich a law kin 
be enforced?" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Well, it never has been.  Why don't 
you try high license?" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Because I don't believe in compromising 
 
<pb n="354"/> 
 
with evil.  That's why!  I fought 
slavery in my youth, an' I'm fighting 
rum in my old age.  And I've been a 
no-compromise man straight through. 
I learned that from old John Brown. 
There wasn't much compromising about 
<hi rend="italic">him</hi>.  It was a grand thing to see him 
in battle.  And they say it was grander 
to see him die.  And yet there wasn't a 
man was gentler or kinder-hearted.  He 
never took no thought of himself.  Look 
at that letter he wrote his wife from the 
prison, beggin' her not to come to him, 
'cause it would use up all her little stock 
of money, and she might be insulted 
or hard treated.  But I'm wandering. 
Brown's only a fanatic to you.  He was 
not of this world, and the world martyred  
him, an' you compromise men 
stood by consenting unto his blood. 
You're a high-license man yourself, I 
take it.  Believe in doing evil that good 
may come, hey?" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Oh, no," said Archy, smiling.  Somehow  
during the last few moments his 
thoughts had grown kinder to the loyal 
old partisan.  "Oh, no, I merely choose 
between a little evil and a great deal. 
I'll take less than the earth.  But, really,  
Mr. Meadowes, I haven't studied the 
subject enough to discuss it.  Can't you 
ask me something easy?" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Ossie ventured to laugh.  Jared 
frowned.  "What are your politics?" 
said the old man, sternly. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"I am not sure that I have any. 
Sometimes I am a Republican, and sometimes  
a Democrat.  I believe I was a 
Democrat last." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Now, in the interior of Iowa Republicanism  
is, still, a species of religion. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
A gasp of dismay ran through the circle. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Those are your opinions, are they?" 
said the old man, sternly.  "A trimmer.   
Well.  Will you have any more 
meat?" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Archy declined, and Mr. Meadowes 
only spoke to him once again during the 
meal.  The once was when he observed 
Archy shredding his salad with his fork. 
"Ain't ye got no knife?" called he. 
"Lowisa" &mdash; to his red-haired maid &mdash; 
"give Captain Barris a knife." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"He's got a knife," the girl said sharply; "there's your knife!" &mdash; pushing the 
blade at Archy, who silently cut up his 
lettuce.  But Rachel reddened up to her 
eyes. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
The dinner was excellent.  I don't 
know how many hours Rachel and Miss 
Baker had spent in the kitchen with 
"Lowisa."  The linen was dainty, there 
were flowers on the table, and the cut-glass tumblers, and the carafe.  Rachel 
had tripped out of the room with a happy 
smile, thinking: "Archy will see that 
we can have pretty things too." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
But now, seen through a stranger's 
eyes, everything was wofully changed. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
The oilcloth, to which her father clung 
because he had always had an oilcloth on 
his dining-room floor ever since he was 
married; that preposterous sideboard, 
and those portraits of Mr. and Mrs. 
Meadowes which a gifted sign-painter 
had done just before they left Kansas &mdash; 
did Archy notice them, was he laughing 
at them?  Even the table appointments 
were not an unmixed triumph.  Jared 
asked, where was the "water pitcher?" 
"Lowisa" forgot the white apron that had 
been furnished her.  She piled the dishes 
noisily into dizzy towers, and it was almost an interposition of Providence that 
she didn't slay Mr. Meadowes outright, 
as she swung the meat platter above his 
head, with the carving-knife prancing on  
the edge, while he sat below, like an unconscious Damocles.   
It was no use trying  
to catch "Lowisa's" eye; her mind 
was on the sweets in the kitchen, and you 
must speak to the point, and in a good 
round tone, too, or she would glare at 
you and say, <hi rend="italic">"How?"</hi>  Rachel thought 
of Mrs. Barris's dinners, the beautiful 
room, the glittering table, the noiseless 
service.  Every rough gesture of her 
father's was like a blow.  She could have 
groaned when he brandished his knife 
at Archy, in the courage of his opinions, 
or mopped his face with his napkin.  His 
blunt discourtesy was worse than anything  
else.  "How could he? how could 
he?" she kept saying to herself, in a spasm 
of mortification.  Yet, all the while, she 
was angry with her lover.  That indefinable  
thrill of kindred, of the blood 
that is thicker than water, was sending 
hot flushes of mingled shame and indignant  
affection to her cheeks.  What could 
Archy know of her father, of his heroic 
devotion to principle, his honesty, that 
was a proverb in the town, and how 
 
 
<pb n="355"/> 
 
under that harsh exterior was the tenderest,  
faithfullest heart &mdash; why, though 
he talked so fiercely about saloon-keepers,  
he had half supported Gus Timm's 
family after they sold him out and poured 
the barrels into the street!  What did 
Archy know, sitting there so easily, 
sneering at his spiritual betters? 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Meanwhile poor Archy, ignorant of 
this tumult of feeling, was congratulating  
himself on having kept his temper 
so well. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
The dinner, at last, came to an end.  Instantly  
Meadowes spoke to Rachel, "I 
want to see you a minnit, daughter." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
They went out together; Ossie and 
Miss Baker exchanged a sorrowful 
glance; and Miss Baker said, "Won't 
you please step into the parlor, Captain 
Barris?" in much the same tone in 
which one would say, "Won't you walk 
into the silent tomb?" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
The air had grown close and warm. 
Jared flung off his coat without ceremony.   
Ossie sat on the piano-stool 
making aimless half-circles of motion 
and looking dejected.  Miss Baker essayed  
a few commonplaces on the late 
magazines; but her eyes kept wandering  
to the door, and Archy's best efforts 
at sprightliness fell flat; in fact, his listeners  
gazed on him more and more 
compassionately.  It was a distinct relief, 
after half an hour of this, to see old 
Meadowes reappear.  Simultaneously, as 
though they were puppets on a single 
string which he had pulled, the others 
jumped up and filed out of the room. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Archy felt a dismal presentiment.  It 
was no false prophet; in the fewest and 
curtest sentences Meadowes told him 
that his proposal must be rejected. 
"I've looked ye over and ye wun't do," 
said he, "you're a drinkin' man &mdash;" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"I beg your pardon, Mr. Meadowes, 
</p> 
 
<p> 
I was never under the influence of liquor 
in my life.  I don't care for the stuff." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Unconsciously Archy had squared his 
shoulders, he had risen on Mr. Meadowes's  
entrance, and was still standing. 
The old man looked at him &mdash; a gallant 
figure, erect, athletic, with his fair skin 
flushing, his handsome head thrown 
back a little, and his frank blue eyes 
sparkling.  Old Meadowes drew an abrupt  
sigh.  "I didn't say you got drunk," 
he replied; "I said you was a drinkin' 
man, a moderate drinker, if you like 
that expression better &mdash;" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">"Very</hi> moderate." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"I don't take no stock in moderate 
drinkers; if they're too cold-blooded to 
go to perdition themselves, they lead 
other people there, and I ain't sure but 
that's worse.  You are a Democrat and 
an aristocrat.  Ramsay says you ain't a 
professor of religion &mdash; jest a sort of 'piscopal.   
We ain't got an opinion in common." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"I beg your pardon, we have <hi rend="italic">one</hi>, 
your daughter &mdash;" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"That ain't the same thing, even.  You 
think you're in love with her now, but 
when you find her principles interferin' 
with your amusements, and your fine 
friends are laughing at you behind your 
back, you'll git angry with her.  I would 
have more hopes of ye if you'd stood 
up fair and square for the bad things 
you believe in; there'd be some chance 
of convertin' you to righteousness; but 
you're like the Lacedamonians the 'postle  
talks of.  Ye shew what was in ye at 
the dinner-table.  Ye didn't want no disputin';  
oh, no, you was willin' to make 
any concessions, till ye'd got Rachel 
'way; then I guess you'd sing another 
song.  But I tell you, Captain Barris," he 
drew himself up to his full height, his 
countenance grew rigid, and he made a 
single downward stroke with his fore-finger.  "I tell you, I'd ruther see my 
innocent child dead, right here, than 
married to a cold-hearted, unprincipled, 
sneerin' aristocrat that will break her 
heart or else ruin her principles." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"You can hardly expect me to take 
this as final," said Archy, coldly. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Oh! ye kin see Rachel, if ye wanter," 
the old man answered.  All at once he 
looked desperately tired and spoke 
wearily, quite without anger, "It will be 
an additional pain to her; but you've 
both got it to go through, and ye kin 
talk it over together.  I'll call her.  Good-by, Captain Barris.  I expect ye wun't 
care for it, but I'm sorry for you."  He 
extended his hand.  Archy felt the same 
odd movement of friendliness for the 
stanch old soul which he had felt before,  
struggling up to the surface of his 
sensations through all the anger and 
sting of the moment. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"No, Mr. Meadowes," said he, "I 
 
 
<pb n="356"/> 
 
can't shake hands, for I mean to do my 
best to persuade your daughter to marry 
me." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Try," said the old man, stonily, 
walking off. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Then Rachel came.  She looked white 
and miserable and had a package in her 
hands.  Archy would not look at her 
face; he caught her in his arms, whispering,  
"You won't be so cruel, my love, it's 
nonsense my giving you up &mdash; I can't!" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"You <hi rend="italic">must</hi>," said Rachel, trembling, 
but trying to release herself; "please let 
me go, Captain Barris." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
The young man stepped back rather 
an exaggerated distance.  He looked at 
her steadily.  "You don't mean that you 
will throw me over like <hi rend="italic">this</hi>," said he. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Rachel made a great effort and controlled  
her voice.  It was just the soft, 
caressing, plaintive voice that one would 
expect of her; but now it was on that 
level of intonation which comes when 
the will has to hold every word steady 
lest it turn into a sob.  "My father," 
said she, "it's all true what my father 
says; we are altogether different.  The 
people you go with laugh at the things 
I have been taught were the most important.   
They call earnest Christian 
people 'prigs'; and your mother was 
so surprised when I told her I belonged 
to the W. C. T. U., and said, 'Oh, my 
dear, don't; that sort of thing <hi rend="italic">stamps</hi> 
one!'  She made me feel as though I 
had confessed to having been in jail. 
Captain Barris, your mother is ashamed 
of me.  And you would be if you 
married me.  You <hi rend="italic">are</hi> ashamed of my 
folks &mdash;"  She choked with the remembrance  
of the torture of the dinner-table. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Archy looked at her in a confusion of 
anger, pity, and despair.  "But, Rachel," 
he cried, vehemently, "you knew all 
about this before, when you promised to 
marry me.  What does all this r &mdash; stuff 
matter when we love each other?  Come, 
my darling, when you know us better 
you will find we have our principles, too, 
though we may seem to make light of 
them." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"They are different; <hi rend="italic">everything</hi> is 
different.  I was afraid always, but I &mdash; 
You hadn't seen my father, then; I told 
you if he consented.  But he would be 
wretched &mdash;" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"You would rather make <hi rend="italic">me</hi> wretched 
than him?" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Rachel was standing; she sat down 
before she answered, faintly, "Yes." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Then," said he, "when you told me 
that last evening on the island that 
you &mdash;" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Please don't," she whispered; and 
she said aloud, "Jared!" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Archy did not know that she felt herself  
fainting, and her cry to her brother, 
passing by the door, was only because 
of this.  He thought that she wanted to 
cut the interview short.  He was stung 
to the quick. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
He caught up his hat and bowed.  "In 
that case," said he, "I will not prolong 
an interview that seems to distress you. 
I wish you every good fortune, Miss 
Meadowes." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Not daring to raise her eyes she dizzily  
lifted the package in her lap.  But 
he had turned his back.  The poor girl 
had put a few tear-stained words between  
the lids of her Bible, and placed it 
with his notes and the trifling gifts 
which she had allowed him to give her; 
the little bundle slipped from her limp 
fingers, and, just as Archy's footsteps 
pounded along the walk, Rachel's head 
sank on her brother's arm in the first 
swoon of her life. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Archy went striding down the street. 
Well, to this day he has a little tightening  
of the throat recalling the next few 
hours.  He was in a fever of wrath and 
anguish; furious with Rachel, who could 
give him up so tamely, raving at himself 
for flinging up his chance in a fit of temper.   
Then he essayed a cynical gayety, 
and felt his eyes smarting with tears because  
he had remembered some trumpery  
incident of the past weeks and the 
cadence of Rachel's laugh.  Ah! haven't 
the most of us just such moments to remember,  
with their sickening oscillations 
of love and anger and despair!  How 
long Archy walked he could not tell, but 
when he resumed a saner mood enough 
to look about him, he was among the 
low hills, covered with wheat and oats, 
outside the town, and night was falling. 
Clever alienists have their patients walked 
to exhaustion sometimes, and perhaps 
lovers, who are in a measure insane people,  
may be helped the same way.  At 
any rate, by this time Archy's sweet temper 
 
<pb n="357"/> 
 
had acquitted Rachel.  He even had 
a glimmer of the truth, and he began to 
hope again. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
He turned himself about, resolved to 
walk past the Meadowes' house.  He 
would not call, but if by accident &mdash; 
</p> 
 
<p> 
As he passed through the College 
campus he heard a girl's laugh. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"See how funny the sky looks!" she 
said to the young man beside her.  "Look 
&mdash; you are not looking at all!" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"I have something better to look at," 
said he. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Archy brushed past them impatiently. 
Yet it was a strange sky.  Although the 
sun had set, the western sky, up to the 
zenith, burned with a lurid radiance. 
Funnel-shaped clouds, inky black, dipped 
into this unearthly brilliancy.  While 
Archy looked he became aware of the 
utter stillness of the air.  Not a bird's 
chirp, not the hum of an insect.  He had a 
peculiarly ghastly sensation, like one who 
feels for a pulse and there is no throb. 
"What a cursed night!" he muttered. 
It was the night of the 17th of June, 
1882.  He went on.  He passed the 
Meadowes house. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Then he turned, saying to himself that 
he would go to his hotel and write to 
Rachel; he even remembered that he 
had missed his supper, &mdash; when he saw 
Rachel come out of the house.  It was 
too dark to see her face, but he knew her 
figure and a certain blue shawl which she 
used to wear.  Afire now with hope and 
impatience he pursued her.  Suddenly 
that dear form grew dim.  The strange 
light was fading, the black funnels 
dipped lower, lower into the glow, and 
the dark tree-leaves began to rustle. 
Directly, the air vibrated with a horrible 
grinding noise, compared, afterward, to 
many sounds, like them all, yet most appallingly  
different from all.  And then 
&mdash; it came!  Earth and air were rent into  
chaos.  The tall trees swayed, snapped, 
fell.  Houses were swept from their moorings,  
and whirled shivering and crashing 
away.  They were chopped into splinters. 
They were scattered like a handful of 
dust.  There was no more space; the 
air itself was a tumult of darting shapes, 
a horror of woful sounds.  Archy was 
within arm's length of Rachel.  He 
caught her waist; he flung her, or they 
were thrown together, against the roots 
of a great elm.  "Cling!" he shouted; 
"lie flat and hold on for your life!" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Her head and shoulders being in a 
hollow of the roots were partially protected,  
and he could further shield them 
with his own body.  He felt the wind 
of death swaying their limbs; he was 
struck heavy blows, he was flogged, 
battered, stung; his tense muscles were 
ready to snap with the strain, but he 
clung with the immense energy of despair.  The cyclone shot a hundred  
objects over his head &mdash; rafters, branches, 
the marble top of a table, a beast with 
hoofs and horns, the pillows of a bed &mdash; 
there was no counting them.  A house 
to his right was smashed like an egg-shell; a row of houses to his left fell in 
amid frightful screams.  Balls of fire 
were skimming the ground.  A girl's 
face, the face that he had seen a moment 
since, flashed by all white and crooked, 
and vanished.  Not a rod away a man 
ran toward them, screaming.  The wind 
took him and he was gone.  Somewhere 
among the trees a piteous little voice 
cried, "Mamma, tum! mamma, tum!" 
Back of him were some people in sore 
plight who groaned unceasingly, and a 
woman shrieked, "Oh! my baby."  The 
storm went roaring over them, houses, 
barns, trees hurled on either side of its 
track.  It struck the College, levelled the 
brick building like a house of cards, 
peeled roof and upper story off the stone 
building, and flung a shower of blinds, 
glass, shingles, and bricks from the professors' houses. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
But surely now the worst was over; 
they could lie still on the ground, and 
the voices about them were plainer. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"It's over, thank God!" cried a man's 
voice. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Well, it's finished me anyhow," another  
answered; "my legs are both broke, 
and my back too, I guess.  Anybody got 
any legs to get up and look after that 
woman's baby?" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
The cyclone had gone; but the wind 
in its wake was blowing furiously and 
the rain fell as rain never fell in Grinnell  
before; in fact, a water-spout had 
burst.  One could scarcely stand for the 
wind or breathe for the rain.  And the 
darkness was horrible. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Archy managed to get on his feet and 
to raise Rachel.  She held on to his arm, 
 
 
<pb n="358"/> 
 
sobbing, "Oh! my land!  Oh! who is it? 
What has become of them?  Oh!  Captain Barris, what has happened?" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
It was not Rachel's voice. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
At that moment the heavens blazed 
from horizon to horizon, while a clap of 
thunder drowned the multitudinous din 
of human agony.  Who that saw it can 
forget that woful battle-field, struck 
into sight, then swallowed up in blackness &mdash;  
wreck and carnage such as can-not be pictured, and white faces glaring 
out of their death-traps.  Yet Archy 
could only see one object, Miss Baker's 
terrified face.  "For God's sake, where's 
Rachel?" he groaned. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"In the house, and he &mdash; he &mdash;  Oh! 
look; oh! look!" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Through the sheet of rain, as the lightning  
flashed again, they both looked. 
The house was gone. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Miss Baker showed herself the stronger 
of the two now; it was she who suggested  
that they might have reached the 
cellar. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Let us go," said Archy; "but I can't 
leave that baby up in the tree.  Wait a 
moment!" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
The little captive luckily was so wedged 
in the branches (held fast by his frock, 
which was torn in two and rolled round 
a limb as though the cyclone had deliberately  
tied him), that he was merely 
bruised a little, and easily released by 
the simple expedient (suggested by Miss 
Baker) of cutting off the buttons and 
pulling him out of the dress.  Archy 
stumbled across to the cellar, and at the 
first sound of the child's voice a woman 
caught him and wept over him.  She 
said that they were all out of the cellar. 
Only one was badly hurt, and he was 
calling to them to leave him and go to 
others who could be helped. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"I wish we could stay," said Miss 
Baker; "but we must go on, Mrs. Dane. 
Our house is gone.  And Rachel and 
Mr. Meadowes &mdash;" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Oh! God help you," said the woman, 
go, do go!" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Though they used all possible speed 
they had to go slowly, the ground being 
full of great holes where trees had been 
uprooted or fence-posts torn out, and 
encumbered, moreover, with the trunks 
of trees, and rafters and piles of brick, 
and splintered furniture of every kind 
and shape.  Once Archy stumbled over 
a dead horse, very comfortably disposed 
on a feather-bed.  His next stumble 
banged his knees against a kitchen stove. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
A second later a lantern was flashed 
in their eyes, and a wild-faced man 
shouted, "Is Thomas Reynolds's house 
down?" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
They could not tell him, and he ran 
by with his wild face behind his lantern. 
Somehow, this increased their anxiety. 
Indeed there was something very ghastly 
and awful about the way they would be 
suddenly close to a fellow-creature in dire 
misery, and, in the space of a thought, 
he would be gone, and the rain and the 
blackness about them again.  During all 
this while, also, there was no diminution 
of the uproar of shrieks, yells, groans; 
rather its volume was swelled by new 
voices, because helpers were seeking for 
the wounded and the dead, and shouted 
their presence.  Lanterns now twinkled 
in every direction.  The men of Grinnell  
were very generally in the business 
streets when the cyclone came, and this 
part of the town had escaped.  They 
heard the storm and saw it break.  As 
soon as they could stand in the gale they 
were out with lanterns.  A second and a 
third man passed Archy.  The fourth 
man wrested Miss Baker from his arm, 
crying, "God be praised!  Here, hold 
these," he said, thrusting an axe and lantern  
at Archy.  The action, it appeared, 
was to free his arms, that he might embrace  
Miss Baker, which he did most 
tenderly.  Of course it was old Jared 
Meadowes. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Rachel?" gasped Archy. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Rachel's all right, safe and sound, 
thank God," Meadowes replied; "we 
got into the cellar.  But you, Lida &mdash;" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"I should have been killed but for 
Captain Barris," said she, solemnly; "I 
never could have held on but for him." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
The old man wrung Archy's wrist; he 
couldn't wring his hand, since the right 
held the lantern and the left the axe. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"She's to be my wife," said he, hoarsely.   
"I thought I'd lost her." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
He made no other attempt at thanks, 
seeming to think that sentence explained 
everything.  "But my boys, Lida," he 
continued, "they're both up to the College.   
I must go to them.  Kin <hi rend="italic">you</hi> take 
her home?" 
 
 
<pb n="359"/> 
 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Nobody need take me home," said 
Miss Baker, who had acted with unexpected  
spirit and coolness all along.  "I 
know every step of the way, and I ain't a 
mite hurt.  You both go along; you are 
needed here, and I don't need you.  You 
only hinder me; I cayn't hold up my 
dress or nothing, getting over the logs, 
with you 'round!" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
She would not even take the lantern, 
protesting that they would need it in 
their work, which was so much the case 
that they did not insist; and so they parted.   
The two men turned back to the 
College.  They had not proceeded very 
far before Meadowes began to swing his 
lantern, yelling, "Hello, Ossie!  This 
way!" 
</p> 
 
<p> 
A young fellow, bounding recklessly 
over the logs, stopped with a cry of joy; 
palpably Ossie.  He explained hurriedly 
that there were five students under the 
ruins of the brick building, and at least 
three buried under the roof of Central 
College.  He himself had leaped out of 
a window as he felt the building lurch. 
He was bruised and cut, but he came 
down all right by the bell.  Jared's leg 
was hurt.  Ossie got him out somehow, 
and he was picking bricks off the other 
boys; he said that he could do that, since 
his arms were sound.  Ossie must get 
help and find out about the family. 
"Run on, my boy," said the father.  He 
looked in an appealing way at Archy. 
"I guess his eye ain't out, don't you? 
It's only the eyelid got tore, ain't it?  I 
wouldn't stop him to ask." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"It was only the eyelid.  I could see 
plainly." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
The old man drew a deep sigh of relief.   
"Come on," said he, "you've got 
mighty good eyes." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Then ensued a night, the most terrible,  
the most pitiful, and the most noble 
in Grinnell's history.  Well had it been 
named a colony of Puritans; for that 
night, amid desolation and horror, these 
plain people rose to the stature of heroes.   
Fortitude, serenity in danger, 
courage, good sense, magnanimous civic 
devotion, all the rugged virtues of the 
Puritan were there, and with them an 
open-handed generosity and a jocose 
philosophy born of the prairie air. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Archy and old Meadowes worked side 
by side the night through.  They worked 
amid scenes so awful and so piteous that 
all the disguises in which we Anglo-Saxons like to muffle up our hearts were 
torn away. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Archy was prepared to find the old 
John Brown man a cool, long-headed 
fellow, brave and patient, in fine, a good 
comrade; but he did not expect to see 
him as gentle as a woman with the 
wounded, and he opened his eyes over 
the sum which the old man put down on 
the first subscription paper.  "It's a 
thank-offering to the Lord," said he, 
solemnly, "for his mercies to me this 
night." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
The two men had worked in the greatest  
harmony.  Indeed, if anything could 
have amused Archy during those dreadful  
hours he would have been amused to 
observe how Meadowes presently came 
to rely on his quick eyes and strong 
muscles.  Several times the old man 
jerked a gruff word of approval at the 
younger one.  Finally, he tapped him 
on the shoulder, saying, "Had 'bout 
'nuff of this, ain't ye?  I've jest got word 
from Rachel that our barn's all safe, and 
she an' Lida have got an oil-stove up, 
and some hot biscuits and coffee and 
cold ham ready.  It's broad daylight, 
an' I guess we better quit for awhile. 
Jared's there; I'd kinder like to see how 
his leg's comin' on.  An' Lida's waitin' 
to thank you."  His tone changed to one 
of grave and deep feeling.  "I ain't 
rightly thanked ye for that yet, myself," 
said he. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Now, several times during the last 
hours it had occurred to Archy that he 
was sailing into the old man's favor under 
false colors.  There is a well-defined difference  
between risking your life for 
another man's sweetheart and for your 
own. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
It was a temptation; he could see 
Rachel, and the barn, and the steam of 
the coffee, and the turn of her white 
throat as she would look up, and her 
brown eyes shining.  Then he said, sulkily,  
"That's nothing; I &mdash; I ought to tell 
you I mistook Miss Baker for Rachel." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Meadowes's lips twitched with a grin 
of humorous appreciation.  Though a 
Puritan, he was also a Westerner. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"I'll bet a cooky you've been on pins 
and needles," said he, "thinking whether 
you had ought to tell me, or could git 
 
 
<pb n="360"/> 
 
off without."  His face softened.  "Lida 
does feature Rachel, an' they've got the 
same way of walkin'.  'Twas that first 
turned my mind on her."  He hesitated. 
"I guess you'd have done 'bout the same 
if you had known." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Of course," said Archy, indignantly. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"Then I don't see but what the obligation's  
just where it was.  I'm glad ye 
spoke, though; glad ye wouldn't take 
gratitude ye thought didn't b'long to ye. 
My main objection to <hi rend="italic">you</hi>, Barris, was 
your bein' so unprincipled; but I guess 
you've got a conscience, though it's considerable  
darkened.  You've shown yourself  
a man to-night.  I mistrusted you 
hadn't much of a heart either; but when 
I saw you cryin' over that poor little 
blinded baby tryin' to make its dead 
mother hear, an' wipin' your eyes on the 
sly with your fists, not knowin' you was 
leavin' a black mark every time &mdash; oh, ye 
needn't go to rubbin' your face!  Bless 
you, man, you're mud and soot all over, 
and your coat's bu'st down the back. 
Your own mother wouldn't know you! 
But I guess Rachel will.  Come along, 
come along.  You and she will just have 
to settle your concerns yourselves." 
</p> 
 
<p> 
It does not need telling that this settlement  
was satisfactory.  Only it was 
embarrassing that the old man would not 
let him go to the hotel or give him time 
for the rudest toilet. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
But Rachel threw her white arms 
about that dreadful coat with a sob of 
happiness. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
"And you won't send me away again?" 
he whispered.  "We are to settle it ourselves,  
your father says.  He and I are 
great chums.  Though I must admit," he 
added, "it took a cyclone to make us so." 
</p> 
 
</div1> 
 
</body> 
 
</text> 
 
</TEI.2> 
