<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="TorYose"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="TorYose"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">On Foot in the Yosemite</title>
<title type="sort">on foot in the yosemite</title>
<author>Torrey, Bradford</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">39</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">TorYose</idno> 
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476397</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">On Foot in the Yosemite</title>
<title type="sort">on foot in the yosemite</title>
<author>Bradford Torrey</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1910">1910</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 106</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 228-237</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme 
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of  
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1910">1910</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-10">October 1994</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Minimal TEI tagging</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 

<text id="d1">  

<body id="d2"> 
 
<div1 type="article" id="d3"><pb n="228"/> 
<head>Torrey, Bradford.  "On Foot in the Yosemite."  <lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 106 (1910): 228-237.
</head> 

<p>WHEN flocks of wild geese light in the Yosemite, Mr. Muir 
tells us, they have hard work to find their way out again.  
Whatever direction they take, they are soon stopped by the wall, 
the height of which they seem to have an insuperable difficulty in 
gauging.  There is something mysterious about it, they must think.  
The rock looks to be only about so high, but when they should be 
flying far over its top, northward or southward as the season may 
be, here they are once more beating against its stony face; and 
only when, in their bewilderment, they happen to follow the 
downward course of the river, do they hit upon an exit. 
</p><p>Their case is not peculiar.  Dr. Bunnell, in his interesting 
account of the discovery of the Valley, describes the ludicrous 
guesses of his companions and himself as to the height of the rock 
known since that day as El Capitan.  One 'official' estimated it at 
four hundred feet.  A bolder spirit guessed eight hundred, while 
Dr. Bunnell, waxing very courageous, raised the figure to fifteen 
hundred.  The real height is thirty-three hundred feet.  The fact 
seems to be that the eyes of men and geese alike are unaccustomed 
to such perpendicular altitudes.  A mountain three thousand feet 
high is a thing to which they are more or less used, but a vertical 
surface of anything like the same elevation stands quite outside of 
all ordinary experience.  El Capitan is nothing but a cliff, and a 
cliff &mdash; well, any goose knows what a cliff is like.  Rise about so 
far, and you are over it. 
</p><p>For myself, I sympathize with the geese.  The rock was in 
sight from my tent-door for eight weeks, and grand as it was at 
first, and grander still as it became, I could never make it look 
half a mile high.  It was especially alluring to me in the evening 
twilight.  At that hour, the day's tramp over, I loved to lie back 
in my camp-chair and look and look at its noble outline against the 
bright western sky.  Professor Whitney says that it can be seen 
from the San Joaquin Valley, fifty or sixty miles away; but I am 
now farther away than that several times over, and I can see it at 
this minute with all distinctness &mdash; not only the rock itself, but 
the loose fringe of low trees along its top, with the after-glow 
shining through them.  There would be comparatively little profit 
in traveling if we could see things only so long as we remain 
within sight of them. 
</p><p>Comparatively little profit, I say; but in absolute terms a 
great profit, nevertheless, for any man who is an adept in the art 
of living, wise enough to value not only his life, but the days of 
his life.  It is something to spend a happy hour, a happy week or 
month, though that were to be the end of it.  And such a two months 
as I spent in the Yosemite!  Let what will happen to me henceforth, 
so much at least I have enjoyed.  Even if I should never think of 
the place again, though memory should fail me altogether, those 
eight weeks were mine.  While they lasted I lived and was happy.  
Six o'clock every morning saw me at the breakfast-table, and 
<pb n="229"/>  
half an hour later, with bread in my pocket, I was on the 
road, head in air, stepping briskly for warmth, and singing with 
myself over the anticipation of new adventures.  I might be heading 
for Eagle Peak or Nevada Fall, for Glacier Point, or where not.  
What matter?  Here was another day of Sierra sunlight and Sierra 
air, in which to look and look, and listen and listen, and play 
with my thoughts and dreams.  Who was it that said, 'Take care of 
the days, and life will take care of itself'?  Others, men and 
women, old and young, were setting forth on the same holiday 
errand; as we met or passed each other we exchanged cheerful 
greetings; but for my part I was always alone, and, let it sound 
how it will, I liked my company. 
</p><p>Such a feast of walking as the two months gave me!  I shall 
never have another to compare with it.  The Valley itself is four 
thousand feet above sea-level, and many of my jaunts took me nearly 
or quite as much higher.  If the trails were steep, the 
exhilaration was so much the greater.  At the worst I had only to 
stop a minute or two now and then to breathe and look about me, 
upward or downward, or across the way.  There might be a bird near 
by, a solitaire by good luck, or a mountain quail; or two or three 
fox sparrows might be singing gayly from the chaparral; or as many 
pigeons might go by me along the mountain-side, speeding like the 
wind; or, not improbably, a flock of big black swifts would be 
doubling and turning in crazy, lightning-like zigzags over my head.  
Who would not pause a minute to confer with strangers of such 
quality?  And if attractions of this more animated kind failed, 
there would likely enough be broad acres of densely-growing 
manzanita bushes on either side of the way, every one of the 
million branches hanging full of tiny bells, graceful in shape as 
Grecian urns, tinted like the pinkest and loveliest of seashells, 
and fragrant with a reminiscence of the sweetest of all blossoms, 
our darling Plymouth mayflower.  Yes indeed, there was always 
plenty of excuse for a breathing spell. 
</p><p>I began with reasonable moderation, remembering my years.  For 
two or three days I confined my steps to the valley-level; walking 
to Mirror Lake, whither every one goes, though mostly not on foot, 
to see the famous reflections in its unruffled surface just before 
the sunrise; to the foot of Yosemite Fall, or as near it as might 
be without a drenching; and down the dusty road to Capitan bridge 
and the Bridal Veil. 
</p><p>For the time I was contented to <hi rend="italic">look</hi> up, pitching my walk 
low but my prospect high, as some old poet said.  For that, the 
cliffs, the falls, and the wonderful pines, cedars, and firs, many 
of them approaching two hundred feet in height, afforded continual 
inducement.  Sentinel Rock loomed immediately behind my tent, a 
flat, thin, upright slab, &mdash; so it looks at a front view, &mdash; for all 
the world like some ancient giant's gravestone, three thousand feet 
in height.  It was the first thing I saw every morning as I glanced 
up through the ventilator in the gable at the head of my bed, and 
the first thing that I thought of one night when an earthquake 
rocked me out of my sleep. 
</p><p>Eagle Peak, nearly four thousand feet above the Valley, 
peeping over the heads of its two younger brothers, was directly 
opposite as I stood in my door; while I had only to move out of the 
range of a group of pine trees to see the greatest (at that season) 
of the four principal falls: the Yosemite, that is to say, with its 
first stupendous free plunge of fifteen or sixteen hundred feet, a 
height equal (so my Yankee-bred imagination dealt with the matter) 
to that of six or seven Bunker Hill monuments standing 
<pb n="230"/>  
end 
on end.  It was grandeur itself to look at, &mdash; grandeur and beauty 
combined; and to my unaccustomed ears what a noise it made!  As I 
started out for my first stroll, on the noon of my arrival (May 
11), a black cloud overspread the sky in that quarter, from which 
came at intervals a heavy rumbling as of not very distant thunder.  
A passer-by, however, when I questioned him about it, said, &mdash;  
</p><p>'No, it is the fall.' 
</p><p>And so it proved, some momentary shifting of the wind seeming 
now and then to lift the enormous column of water from the cliff, 
and anon let it down again with a resounding crash.  This peculiar 
thundering sound, I was told, would be less frequent later in the 
season, when the warmer days would melt the mountain snow more 
rapidly, and the bulk of the water would be so increased that no 
ordinary wind could lift it.  This, also, was shown to be correct, 
paradoxical as it had sounded, &mdash; the more water, the less noise.  
And after all, when I came to consider the subject, it was only 
giving a new twist to an old proverb, 'Still waters run deep.' 
</p><p>My first considerable climb was an unpremeditated trip to the 
top of Nevada Fall.  I took the trail at the head of the Valley, 
close by the Happy Isles, some three miles from camp, with no 
intention of doing more than try what it might be like; but an 
upward-leading path is of itself an eloquent persuasion, and, one 
turn after another, I kept on, the ravishing wildness of the Merced 
Canyon, and the sight and sound of the Merced River raging among 
the rocks, getting more and more hold upon me, till all at once the 
winding path made a short descent, and behold, I was on a bridge 
over the river; and yonder, all unexpected, only a little distance 
up the foaming rapids, through the loveliest vista of sombre 
evergreens and bright, newly leaved, yellow-green maples, was a 
fall, far less high than the Yosemite, to be sure, but even more 
graceful in its proportions (breadth and height being better 
related), and so wondrously set or framed that no words could begin 
to intimate its beauty.  I looked and looked (but half the time 
must be attending to the mad rush of the river under my feet), and 
then started on.  If this was Vernal Fall, as to which, in my happy 
ignorance, I was uncertain, then I must go far enough to see the 
Nevada. 
</p><p>The trail carried me about and about, past big snow banks and 
along the edge of flowery slopes, with ever-changing views of the 
mighty canyon and the lofty cliffs beyond, till after what may have 
been an hour's work it brought me out upon a mountain shoulder 
whence I looked straight away to another fall, higher and wilder by 
much than the one I had lately seen.  Here, then, was the Nevada, 
to many minds the grandest of the great four, as in truth it must 
be, taking the months together. 
</p><p>Now there was nothing for it, after a few minutes of 
hesitation (still considering my years), but I must keep on, down 
to the river-level again, after all this labor in getting above it, 
and over another bridge, till a final breathless, sharper and 
sharper-angled zigzag brought me to the top, where I stood gazing 
from above at an indescribable, unimaginable sight, &mdash; the plunge of 
the swollen river over a sheer precipice to a huddle of broken 
rocks six hundred feet below. 
</p><p>I happened to be fresh from a few days at Niagara, and 
moreover, I was a man who had all his life taken blame to himself 
as being unwarrantably, almost disgracefully, insensible to the 
charm of falling water.  Nobody would ever stand longer than I to 
muse upon a brook idling through meadows or 
<pb n="231"/>  
gurgling over 
pebbles down a gentle slope; and the narrower it was, the better it 
was, almost, given only some fair measure of clearness, movement 
enough to lend it here and there an eddying dimple, and, most of 
all, a look of being perennial.  I hold in loving recollection two 
or three such streamlets, and at this very minute can seem to see 
and hear them, dipping smoothly over certain well-remembered flat 
boulders, and bearing down a few tufts of wavering sweet-flag 
leaves.  Yes, I see them with all plainness, though the breadth of 
a continent stretches between them and this present dwelling-place 
of mine, where near mountains half circle me about and the Pacific 
surf dashes almost against my doorstep, but where there is never a 
sound of running water all the long summer through.  Often and 
often I say to myself, &mdash;  
</p><p>'If there were only one dear Massachusetts brook, to make the 
charm complete!' 
</p><p>But with all this, as I say, I had always, to my own surprise, 
made strangely small account of our boasted New England cataracts; 
pleasant to look upon they might be, no doubt, but hardly worth 
much running after.  And now these falls of the Merced and its 
larger tributaries had taken me by storm.  Indeed they are 
altogether another story; as little to be compared with anything in 
New Hampshire as Flagstaff Hill on Boston Common is to be set 
beside Mount Washington.  Merely a difference in degree?  Yes, if 
you choose to put it so, but such a difference in degree as amounts 
fairly to a difference in kind.  Imagine the Merrimac tumbling over 
the face of a ledge five hundred, six hundred, fifteen hundred feet 
high!  And the Yosemite Fall, be it remembered, after its first 
plunge of fifteen or sixteen hundred feet, makes at once two others 
of four hundred and six hundred feet respectively.  In other words, 
it drops almost plumb from an altitude nearly as great (as great 
within six hundred feet) as that of the summit of Mount Lafayette 
above the level of Profile Notch.  And furthermore, it is to be 
considered that the water does not slip over the edge of the awful 
cliff, but comes to it at headlong speed, foaming white, having 
been crowded together and rounded up between the rocky walls of its 
steep and narrow bed, exactly as the Niagara River is in the rapids 
above the whirlpool, &mdash; which rapids are to my apprehension, as I 
suppose they are to most men's, hardly a whit less astounding than 
the Horseshoe Fall itself. 
</p><p>This wild outward leap it was that most of all impressed me 
when more than once I stood at the top of the Yosemite Fall, amazed 
and silent.  But that was some time later than the day now spoken 
of, and must be left for mention in its turn. 
</p><p>I had heard before coming to the Valley, and many times since, 
that the one place excelling all others &mdash; of those, that is to say, 
immediately above the Valley wall, and so falling within the range 
of ordinary pedestrians &mdash; was Glacier Point; and now, having given 
my legs and wind a moderate preliminary test, I inquired of the 
camp-manager how difficult the trail to that point might be, as 
compared with the one I had just gone over. 
</p><p>'I should call it twice as difficult,' he said, 'though not so 
long.' 
</p><p>The answer surprised, and for the moment almost discouraged 
me.  Age was never so inopportune, I thought. 
</p><p>'But anyhow,' said I, 'there is no law against my having a 
look at the beginning of the way and judging of its possibilities 
for myself.' 
</p><p>And the very next morning, being apparently in good bodily 
trim, and certainly in good spirits, I made an early start.  The 
trail offered at least 
<pb n="232"/>  
one advantage: it began at my door, 
with no six miles of superfluous valley road such as the previous 
day's jaunt had burdened me with.  As for its unbroken steepness, 
that, I reasoned with myself, was to be overcome by the simple 
expedient of taking it in short steps at a slow pace. 
</p><p>Well, not to boast of what is not at all boastworthy (Mr. 
Galen Clark, ninety-five years old, &mdash; may God bless him, he was 
always showing me kindness, &mdash; had made the descent unaccompanied the 
season before, though you would never hear him tell of it), I 
reached the Point in slow time, but without fatigue, the hours 
having been enlivened by the frequent presence of some jovial 
members of the California Press Club, trailing one behind another, 
who by turns overtook and were overtaken by me (the tortoise having 
sometimes the better of it), till every fresh encounter became 
matter for a jest.  We arrived in company, cutting across lots over 
the hard snow near the top, and then there was no taking of no for 
an answer.  Three of the men were set upon going out upon the 
celebrated overhanging rock &mdash; three thousand feet, more or less, 
over empty space &mdash; to be photographed, and, would he or wouldn't he, 
the old 'Professor,' as with friendly impudence, meaning no 
disrespect, they had dubbed him, must go along and have his picture 
taken with the rest.  And go along the old professor did, keeping, 
to be sure, at a prudent remove from the dizzy edge, though he 
flattered himself, of course, that only for not choosing to play 
the fool, he <hi rend="italic">could</hi> stand as near it as the next man.  This 
pleasing ceremony done with, I was left to go my own gait, and then 
my enjoyment of the marvelous place began. 
</p><p>A good-natured and conversable young driver, who had picked me 
up one day on the road, quizzed me as to what I thought about the 
origin of the Valley; and after I had tried to set forth in outline 
the two principal opinions of geologists upon the subject, not 
suspecting what a philosopher I had to do with, he informed me that 
he took no stock in either of them.  He cared nothing for Whitney 
or Le Conte or Muir.  No subsidence theory or glacial theory for 
him.  <hi rend="italic">He</hi> believed that the place was made so to start with, on 
purpose that people might come from all parts of the world and 
enjoy it.  And to-day, as I moved about the rim of Glacier Point 
for the first time, I was ready to say with equal positiveness, if 
with something less of serious intention, &mdash; This place was made for 
prospects. 
</p><p>If I doubted, I had only to look at the level green valley, 
with the green river meandering through it; at the wall opposite, 
so variously grand and beautiful, from El Capitan to the Half Dome; 
and, best of all, at the Merced Canyon, as seen from the 
neighborhood of the hotel, with my two falls of the day before in 
full sight across it, and beyond them a world of snowy peaks, a 
good half of the horizon studded with them, lonely-looking though 
so many, and stretching away and away and away, till they faded 
into the invisible; a magnificent panorama of the high Sierras, 
minarets and domes, obelisks and battlemented walls; such a 
spectacle as I had never thought to look upon.  It was too bad I 
could not spend the night with it, to see it in other moods; but 
when I was informed that the hotel would be open before many days 
were past, I consoled myself with the promise of another and a 
longer visit. 
</p><p>I was better than my word.  Four times afterward I climbed to 
the Point, once by the 'long trail,' <hi rend="italic">via</hi> Nevada Fall (which, 
with the afternoon descent over the short trail added, really made 
some approximation to a day's 
<pb n="233"/>  
work), and altogether I 
passed six nights there, taking in the splendors of the dawn and 
the sunset, and, for the rest, ranging more or less about the snowy 
woods.  One afternoon (May 23) we were favored with a lively 
snowstorm of several hours' duration, with a single tremendous 
thunder-clap in the midst, which drove three young fellows into the 
hotel-office breathless with a tale of how the lightning had played 
right about their heads till almost they gave themselves up for 
dead men; and when the clouds broke away little by little shortly 
before sunset, the shifting views of the canyon, the falls, and the 
mountain summits near and far, were such as put one or two amateur 
photographers fairly beside themselves, and drove the rest of us to 
silence or to rapturous exclamation according as the powers had 
made us of the quiet or the noisy kind.  Whatever we poor mortals 
made of it, it was a wondrous show. 
</p><p>Thrice I went to the top of Sentinel Dome (eighty-one hundred 
feet), an easy jaunt from the hotel, though just at this time, 
while attempting it in treacherous weather, with the trail, if 
there be one, buried under the winter snow, a young tourist became 
bewildered and lost his life &mdash; vanished utterly, as if the earth had 
swallowed him.  The prospect from the summit is magnificent, if 
inferior, as I think it is, to that from the hotel piazza; and the 
place itself is good to stand on: one of those symmetrical, broadly 
rounded, naked granite domes, so highly characteristic of the 
Sierras, and of which so many are to be seen from any point upon 
the Valley rim.  Some agency or other, once having the pattern, 
seems to have turned them out by the score. 
</p><p>One day I looked down into the Fissures, so called, giddy, 
suicide-provoking rents; and more than once, on the Wawona road, I 
skirted two of those beautiful Sierra Nevada meadows, so feelingly 
celebrated by Mr. Muir, and so surprising and grateful to all new-comers in these parts.  At this moment one of them was starred with 
thousands of greenish-white marsh marigolds &mdash; <hi rend="italic">Caltha 
leptosepala</hi>, as I learned afterward to call them, when good Mr. 
Clark produced, out of his treasures new and old, for my 
enlightenment, a much-desired copy of Brewer and Watson's <hi rend="italic">Botany 
of California</hi>. 
</p><p>After the two trails thus 'negotiated,' to speak a little in 
the Western manner, there remained one that by all accounts was 
steeper and harder still, the trail to Yosemite Point, or, if the 
walker should elect to travel its full length, to Eagle Peak.  As 
to the Peak, I doubted.  The tale of miles sounded long, and as the 
elevation was only seventy-eight hundred feet, substantially the 
same as that of Glacier Point, it appeared questionable whether the 
distance would pay for itself. 
</p><p>'Oh, the trail isn't difficult,' a neighborly-minded, middle-aged tourist had assured me (he spoke of the trail to Yosemite 
Point only); 'we made it between breakfast and luncheon.' 
</p><p>But they had made it on horseback, as came out a minute later, 
which somewhat damaged the argument.  Difficult or easy, however 
(and if there had been forty, or even twenty, less years in my 
pack, all this debate concerning distances and grades would have 
been ridiculous), to Yosemite Point I was determined to go.  Once, 
at least, I must stand upon the rocks at the top of that stupendous 
fall, at which I had spent so many half-hours in gazing.  And stand 
there I did, not once, but thrice; and except for the Glacier Point 
outlook, which must always rank first, I enjoyed no other Yosemite 
experience quite so much.  So I speak; yet sometimes, while 
loitering downward in the late afternoon, 
<pb n="234"/>  
I sang another 
song.  'After all,' I thought, 'these are the best hours.  And 
really there is no reaching any final verdict in matters of this 
nature, so much depending upon mood and circumstance.' 
</p><p>I was walking in the shade of a vertical cliff so near, so 
high, so overpowering in its enormous proportions, that I often 
felt it to be more impressive than El Capitan itself; and, walking 
thus in deep shadow, I looked out upon a world of bright sunlight: 
the fall at my side ('Oh, I say,' an enthusiastic, much-traveled 
man had exclaimed in my hearing, 'it beats Niagara.  Yes, sir, it 
beats Niagara!'), every turn of the path bringing it into view at 
a new angle, and, as it seemed to increased advantage; the shining 
green valley, with its jewel of a river; and yonder, up in the sky, 
all those illuminated snowy Sierra peaks.  Well, I could only stop 
and look, and stop and look again, rejoicing to be alive. 
</p><p>As for Eagle Peak, with its two or three extra miles, before 
the business was over (after the way thither became dry enough to 
be passable without wading) I had paid it four visits.  The Peak 
itself offered no transcendent attraction, but the trail proved to 
be at once so comfortable and so very much to my mind, that, once 
at the end of the sharp zigzags, and on the level of the river 
above the fall, it seemed impossible not to keep on, &mdash; just this 
once more, as I always said; such pleasure I took in the forest of 
stately pines and firs, the multitude of wild flowers by the way, 
and in another and more extensive of those fair mountain meadows 
(natural grassy meads, green as emerald, shining in the sun amidst 
the dark evergreen forest), along the border of which the winding 
trail carried me.  In this were no marsh marigolds, but instead a 
generous sprinkling of sun-bright buttercups, while a pool in the 
midst was covered with lily-pads and yellow spatter-dock lilies, &mdash;  
old New England friends whose homely faces were trebly welcome in 
these far-off California altitudes. 
</p><p>I never approached the meadow &mdash; which melting snowbanks all 
about still rendered impossible of dry-shod exploration &mdash; without 
pleasing anticipations of deer.  They must frequent it, I thought; 
but I looked for them in vain.  The curiously distinctive slow 
drum-taps of an invisible Williamson sapsucker, a true Sierran, 
handsomest of the handsome, were always to be counted upon; 
swallows and swifts went skimming over the grass; robins and 
snowbirds flitted about; but if deer ever came this way, it was not 
down for me to find them. 
</p><p>At the end of the trail, after a tedious gravelly slope, where 
I remember a close bed of the pretty mountain phlox, with thin 
remnants of a snowdrift no more than a rod or two above it, there 
remained a brief clamber over huge boulders, with tufts of gorgeous 
pink pentstemon growing in such scanty deposits of coarse soil as 
the desolate, unpromising situation afforded; the scantier the 
better, as it seemed; for this clever economist is a lover of 
rocks, if there ever was one.  It was to be found in all 
directions, in the valley and on the heights, but never anywhere 
except in the most inhospitable-looking, impossible-looking of 
stony places.  And out of a few grains of powdered granite it 
manages somehow to extract the wherewithal not merely upon which to 
subsist, but for the putting forth of as bright a profusion of 
exquisite bloom as the sun ever shone upon. 
</p><p>The outlook from the topmost boulder of this Titans' cairn, 
for it looked like nothing else, was commanding, &mdash; valley, river, 
and mountain, &mdash; but to me, as I have said, the Peak was mainly of 
<pb n="235"/>  
use as the conclusion of a walk through an enchanting Sierra 
forest; for I, no less than my fellows, have yet to outgrow the 
primitive need of 'a place to go to,' even when I go mostly for 
what is to be enjoyed by the way. 
</p><p>So much for what might be more strictly accounted as climbs to 
the valley rim.  More wearisome, perhaps, because quite as long, 
while without the counterbalancing stimulation which a mountain 
trail seems always, out of its own virtue, to communicate, were an 
indefinite number of jaunts to Inspiration Point (hateful name!) 
and into the forest a mile or two beyond.  Precisely why I expended 
so much labor upon the long miles of this dusty uphill road, it 
might be troublesome to determine; but here, also, there were so 
many things to be looked at, and so many others to be hoped for, 
that the going thither about once in so many days grew little by 
little into something like a habit.  Between the moist riverbanks 
and the dry hillside, what a procession of beautiful and 
interesting wild flowers the progress of the season led before me!  
And if many of them seemed to be the same as I had known in the 
East, they were certain to be the same with a difference: dogwood 
and azalea (azalea hedges by the mile); tall columbines and lilies; 
yellow violets and blue larkspurs; salmonberry and mariposa tulips; 
an odd-looking dwarf convolvulus, not observed elsewhere; the 
famous blood-red snow-plant, which there was reported to be a heavy 
fine for picking; and whole gardens of tiny, high-colored, fairy-like blossoms, kind after kind and color after color, growing 
mostly in separate parterres, ground-flowers in flocks, and 
veritable gems for brightness, over which, in my ignorance, I could 
only stand and wonder. 
</p><p>Of birds, as compared with plants, the walk might offer little 
in the line of novelty, but such as it did offer, taking old and 
new together, they were always enough to keep a man alive: a pair 
of golden eagles, for instance, soaring in the blue, &mdash; a display of 
aviation, as we say in these progressive days, fitted to provoke 
the most earthbound spirit to envy; a pair of violet-green 
swallows, loveliest of the swallow tribe, never so busy, hastening 
in and out of an old woodpecker's hole in a stunted wayside oak; 
tiny hummingbirds, of course, by name Calliope, wearing the 
daintiest of fan-shaped, cherry colored gorgets, true mountaineers, 
every soul of them, fearless of frost and snow, if only the 
manzanita bells would hold out; and, in particular, a sooty grouse, 
who nearly put my neck out of joint before &mdash; after a good half-hour, 
at least &mdash; I finally caught sight of him as he hitched about in his 
leafy hiding-place near the top of a tall pine tree, complaining by 
the hour.  <hi rend="italic">Boom, boom, boom, boo-boom, boom, boom</hi>, so the 
measure ran, with that odd grace note invariably preceding the 
fourth syllable, as if it were a point of conscience with the 
performer that it should stand just there and nowhere else.  A 
forlorn, moping kind of amorous ditty, it sounded to me; most 
unmusical, most melancholy, though perhaps I had no call to 
criticize. 
</p> 
<l>     Hark, from the pines a doleful sound,</l> 
<l>     My ears attend the cry,</l> 
<p> 
my old-fashioned, orthodox memory fell to repeating, while the 
hollow, sepulchral notes grew fainter and fainter with distance as 
I walked away.  Yet I might appropriately enough have envied the 
fellow his altitudinous position, if nothing else, remembering how 
grand and almost grown-up a certain small Massachusetts boy used to 
feel as he surveyed the world from a perch not half so exalted, in 
what to his eyes was about the tallest pine tree in the world, up 
in his father's pasture. 
<pb n="236"/>  
</p><p>The most curiously unique of Yosemite plants, to my thinking, 
is the California nutmeg tree, <hi rend="italic">Torreya Californica</hi>.  I ignore, 
for good reason, the different generic designation adopted in some 
books more recent than the work of Brewer and Watson.  So far as my 
word goes, my distinguished  &mdash;  &mdash; -th cousin shall not be deprived of 
his one genus.  Mr. Clark, who remembered Dr. Torrey's and Dr. 
Gray's visits to the tree, and whose sympathetic account of the 
affectionate relations subsisting between these two scholars was 
deeply interesting, instructed me where to look for the nearest 
examples, at a point below the Cascades, &mdash; some eight miles down the 
El Portal road, &mdash; and I devoted a long day to the making of their 
acquaintance. 
</p><p>It was the twentieth of June, the weather had turned 
summerish, and the road, which had been as dusty as possible &mdash; a 
disgrace to the nation that owns it &mdash; five or six weeks before, when 
I entered the Valley, was by this time very much dustier.  But the 
river, hastening from the mountains to the sea, was close at my 
side, garrulous of thoughts and fancies, histories and dreams, and 
between it and the birds, the trees, and the innumerable wild 
flowers, I must have been a dull stick not to be abundantly 
entertained.  An ouzel, fishing for something on the flat, inclined 
surface of a broad boulder in midstream, just where the rapids were 
wildest, was compelled to spring into the air every minute or so as 
a sudden big wave threatened to carry it away.  It seemed to be 
playing with death; once fairly caught in that mad whirl, nothing 
could save it.  Again and again I looked to see it go, as the angry 
waters clutched at it; but it was always a shaving too quick for 
them.  Syringa and calycanthus ('sweet-shrub' &mdash; faintly ill-scented!) were in blossom, and the brilliant pink godetia &mdash; a name 
which may suggest nothing to the Eastern reader, but which to an 
old Californian like myself stands for all that is brightest and 
showiest in parched wayside gardens &mdash; never made a more effective 
display; and all in all, though I had walked over the longer part 
of the same road within twenty-four hours, the day was a pure 
delight.  If it gains a little something in the retrospect, it is 
all the more like a picture, &mdash; which must be framed and hung at a 
suitable distance before we truly see it. 
</p><p>The trees of which I had come in search were recognizable at 
a glance: the leave, of a remarkably vivid green, bearing a strong 
resemblance to those of the hemlock, but sharp as needles, as if to 
cry 'Hands off!' the flaky gray bark, most incongruously like that 
of some kind of white oak; while the green fruits, prettily spaced 
ornamental pendants, were really for shape and size not a little 
like nutmegs: a surprising crop, surely, to be hanging amid such 
foliage.  The largest of the few examples that I saw (they grow 
plentifully along the road a little farther down, and may be picked 
out readily from a carriage-seat, as I discovered later) might have 
been, I thought, about fifty feet in height. 
</p><p>This tree (the species, I mean), whose only congeners are 
found in Florida, China, and Japan, may be considered as one of 
four that lend a notable distinction to the Californian silva, the 
others being the Torrey pine, the Monterey pine, and the Monterey 
cypress.  No one of them occurs anywhere in the world outside of 
California, and the nutmeg is the only member of the quartette that 
ventures more than a few miles inland.  Stranded species we may 
assume them to be, formerly of wider range, but now &mdash; how or why 
there is none to inform us &mdash; surviving only within these 
extraordinarily narrow limits. 
<pb n="237"/>  
</p><p>I alluded to myself just now as an old Californian, and so far 
as my standing in the Yosemite is concerned I might have said, 
without jesting, that by the time I had been there three weeks I 
had come to be regarded as one of the oldest inhabitants; the 
ordinary stay of visitors being so niggardly brief, &mdash; two or three 
days, perhaps, upon an average. 
</p><p>One man, it is true, gave me what I had to confess might be, 
in his case, a valid reason for brevity.  A Southern gentleman he 
was, as I should have divined at once from the engaging, softly 
musical quality of his voice.  He began with some question about a 
squirrel, &mdash; which had surprised him by running into a hole in the 
ground, &mdash; and after a word or two more called my attention to two or 
three wild roses which he carried in his hand.  They were fragrant, 
he said; had I ever noticed it?  And when I remarked that I should 
have expected them to be common in Tennessee, he explained that at 
home he never went to places where such things were to be looked 
for.  He had discovered the perfume of wild roses as Thoreau 
discovered the sweetness of white-oak acorns, I thought to myself, 
and so far was in good company.  Then he told me that he had 
arrived in the Valley on the noon of the day before, had found it 
grand and beautiful beyond all his dreams, &mdash; 'ravishing' was one of 
his words, &mdash; and was going out again, not of necessity but from 
choice, that very afternoon.  I manifested a natural surprise, and 
he explained that he 'didn't wish to lose the thrill.'  He had seen 
the picture once and, consciously or unconsciously, was following 
Emerson's advice never to look at it again.  So this time, too, he 
was in excellent company. 
</p><p>For my part, I cannot afford to be so sparing in my use of 
good things.  My aesthetic faculty, it would appear, is less prompt 
than other men's.  Its method is not so much an act as a process.  
In the appreciation of natural scenery, at all events, as I have 
before now confessed, I am not apt to get very far, comparatively 
speaking, on the first day.  I must have time, &mdash; time and a liberal 
chance for repetition.  And in the Yosemite, which is as rich in 
modest loveliness as in spectacular grandeur, a fact of which too 
little is made, I know perfectly well that there are countless 
beauties which I have never seen (more and more of them were coming 
to light up to my very last day), as well as countless others that 
I should rejoice to see again, or, better still, to live with.  
Give me the opportunity, say I, and I will cheerfully risk all 
danger of disillusion, or, as my Southern friend of the wild roses 
more feelingly expressed it, the 'loss of the thrill.' 
</p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
