<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="Twa1Sav"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="Twa1Sav"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Our Fellow Savages of the Sandwich Islands (version 1)</title>
<title type="sort">our fellow savages of the sandwich islands version 1</title>
<author>Twain, Mark, 1835-1910</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>  
<name>Stephen Railton</name>  
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">37</num> kilobytes</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>  
<idno type="ETC">Twa1Sav</idno>  
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476405</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>  
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Sandwich Islands Lecture</title>
<title level="m">Mark Twain Speaking</title>
<title type="sort">sandwich islands lecture</title>
<author>Mark Twain, pseud. Samuel Langhorne Clemens</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>  
<name>Fatout, Paul</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>pp. 4-15</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Iowa Press</publisher>  
<pubPlace>Iowa City</pubPlace>  
<date value="1976">1976</date>  
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa Library PS1302.F3 1976 copy 2</idno>
</publicationStmt>  
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>  
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>  
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>  
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>  
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>  
</encodingDesc>  
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1866">1866</date>
</creation>  
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>  
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; non-fiction; fiction</term>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
</profileDesc>  
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-06">June 1997</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Christine Ruotolo</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>  
 
<text id="d1"> 
 

 
<front id="d2"> 
<div1 type="introduction" id="d3">  <pb n="4"/>  
<head> 
.2. 
</head> 
 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">The many versions of the Sandwich Islands lecture evolved from Mark 
Twain's four months' visit to Hawaii in 1866 and his twenty-five letters 
from there published in the Sacramento</hi> Union<hi rend="italic">.  Continually varying 
his delivery, he used the Islands as a lecture topic more often than any 
other: almost one hundred times in the United States and England, usually 
announcing the title as "Our Fellow Savages of the Sandwich Islands."</hi> 
</p> 
</div1> 
</front> 
 
<body id="d4"> 
<div1 type="statement" id="d5"> 
<head> 
Sandwich Islands Lecture<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic">First Given in San Francisco, October 2, 1866; Intermittently Thereafter<lb/> 
Until December 8, 1873</hi> 
</head> 
 
<p>Ladies and gentlemen: The next lecture in this course will be delivered this evening, by Samuel L. 
Clemens, a gentleman whose high character and unimpeachable integrity are only equalled by his 
comeliness of person and grace of manner. And I am the man! I was obliged to excuse the 
chairman from introducing me, because he never compliments anybody and I knew I could do it 
just as well. 
 
</p><p>The Sandwich Islands will be the subject of my lecture&mdash;when I get to it&mdash;and I shall endeavor to 
tell the truth as nearly as a newspaper man can. If I embellish it with a little nonsense, that makes 
no difference; it won't mar the truth; it is only as the barnacle ornaments the oyster by sticking to 
it. That figure is original with me! I was born back from tidewater and don't know as the barnacle 
<hi rend="italic">does</hi> stick to the oyster. 
 
</p><p>Unfortunately, the first object I ever saw in the Sandwich Islands was a repulsive one. It was a 
case of Oriental leprosy, of so dreadful a nature that I have never been able to get it out of my 
mind since. I don't intend that it shall give a disagreeable complexion to this lecture at all, but 
inasmuch as it was the first thing I saw in those islands, it naturally suggested itself when I 
proposed to talk about the islands. It is a very hard matter to get a disagreeable object out of one's 
memory. I discovered that a good while ago. When I made that funeral excursion in the 
<hi rend="italic">Quaker City</hi> they showed me some very interesting objects in a cathedral, and I expected 
to recollect every one of them&mdash;but I didn't.  
   <pb n="5"/>  
I forgot every one of them&mdash;except one&mdash;and that I remembered because it was unpleasant. It was 
a curious piece of ancient sculpture. They don't know where they got it nor how long they have 
had it. It is a stone figure of a man without any skin&mdash;a freshly skinned man showing every vein, 
artery and tissue. It was the heaviest thing, and yet there was something fascinating about it. It 
looked so natural; it looked as if it was in pain, and you know a freshly skinned man would 
naturally look that way. He would unless his attention was occupied with some other matter. It 
was a dreadful object, and I have been sorry many a time since that I ever saw that man. 
Sometimes I dream of him, sometimes he is standing by my bedpost, sometimes he is stretched 
between the sheets, touching me&mdash;the most uncomfortable bedfellow I ever had. 
 
</p><p>I can't get rid of unpleasant recollections. Once when I ran away from school I was afraid to go 
home at night, so I crawled through a window and laid down on a lounge in my father's office. 
The moon shed a ghastly light in the room, and presently I descried a long, dark mysterious shape 
on the floor. I wanted to go and touch it&mdash;but I didn't&mdash;I restrained myself&mdash;I didn't do it. I had a 
good deal of presence of mind&mdash;tried to go to sleep&mdash;kept thinking of it. By and by when the 
moonlight fell upon it, I saw that it was a dead man Iying there with his white face turned up in 
the moonlight. I never was so sick in all my life. I never wanted to take a walk so bad! I went 
away from there. I didn't hurry&mdash;simply went out of the window&mdash;and took the sash along with me. 
I didn't need the sash, but it was handier to take it than to leave it. I wasn't scared, but I was a 
good deal agitated. I have never forgotten that man. He had fallen dead in the street and they 
brought him in there to try him, and they brought him in guilty, too. 
 
</p><p>But I am losing time; what I have been saying don't bear strictly on the Sandwich Islands, but one 
reminiscence leads to another, and I am obliged to bring myself down in this way, on account of 
that unpleasant thing that I first saw there. It is not safe to come to any important matter in an 
entirely direct way. When a young gentleman is about to talk to a young lady about matrimony he 
don't go straight at it. He begins by talking about the weather. I have done that many a time. 
 
</p><p>My next remarks will refer to the Sandwich Islands. Now if an impression has gotten abroad in 
the land that the Sandwich Islands are in South America, that is the error I wish to attack; that is 
the error I wish to combat. To cut the matter short the Sandwich Isles are 2,000 miles southwest 
from San Francisco, but why they were put away out there in the middle of the Pacific, so far 
away from any place and in such an inconvenient locality, is no business of ours&mdash;it was the work of  
   <pb n="6"/>  
providence and is not open to question. The subject is a good deal like many others we should 
like to inquire into, such as, what mosquitoes were made for, etc., but under the circumstances we 
naturally feel a delicacy about doing it. 
 
</p><p>The islands are a dozen in number and their entire area is not greater I suppose than that of Rhode 
Island and Connecticut combined. They are of volcanic origin, of volcanic construction I should 
say. There is not a spoonful of legitimate dirt in the whole group, unless it has been imported. 
Eight of the islands are inhabited, and four of them are entirely girdled with a belt of mountains 
comprising the most productive sugar lands in the world. The sugar lands in Louisiana are 
considered rich, and yield from 500 to 1,700 pounds per acre. A two-hundred-acre crop of wheat 
in the States is worth twenty or thirty thousand dollars; a two-hundred-acre crop of sugar in these 
islands is worth two hundred thousand dollars. You could not do that in this country unless you 
planted it with stamps and reaped it in bonds. I could go on talking about the sugar interest all 
night&mdash;and I have a notion to do it. But I will spare you. It is very interesting to those who are 
interested in it, but I'll drop it now. You will find it all in the Patent Office reports, and I can 
recommend them as the most placid literature in the world. 
 
</p><p>These islands were discovered some eighty or ninety years ago by Captain Cook, though another 
man came very near discovering them before, and he was diverted from his course by a 
manuscript found in a bottle. He wasn't the first man who has been diverted by suggestions got 
out of a bottle. When these islands were discovered the population was about 400,000, but the 
white man came and brought various complicated diseases, and education, and civilization, and all 
sorts of calamities, and consequently the population began to drop off with commendable activity. 
Forty years ago they were reduced to 200,000, and the educational and civilizing facilities being 
increased they dwindled down to 55,000, and it is proposed to send a few more missionaries and 
finish them. It isn't the education or civilization that has settled them; it is the imported diseases, 
and they have all got the consumption and other reliable distempers, and to speak figuratively, 
they are retiring from business pretty fast. When they pick up and leave we will take possession as 
lawful heirs. 
 
</p><p>There are about 3,000 white people in the islands; they are mostly Americans. In fact they are the 
kings of the Sandwich Islands; the monarchy is not much more than a mere name. These people 
stand as high in the scale of character as any people in the world, and some of them who were 
born and educated in those islands don't even know what vice is. A Kanaka or a native is nobody 
unless he has a princely  
   <pb n="7"/>  
income of $75 annually, or a splendid estate worth $100. The country is 
full of office-holders and office-seekers; there are plenty of such noble patriots. Of almost any 
party of three men, two would be office-holders and one an office-seeker. In a little island half the 
size of one of the wards of St. Louis, there are lots of noblemen, princes and men of high degree, 
with grand titles, holding big offices, receiving immense salaries&mdash;such as ministers of war, 
secretaries of the navy, secretaries of state and ministers of justice. They make a fine display of 
uniforms, and are very imposing at a funeral. That's the country for a petty hero to go to, he 
would soon have the conceit taken out of him. There are so many of them that a nobleman from 
any other country would be nobody. They only lionize their own people, and therefore they 
lionize everybody. 
 
</p><p>In color, the natives are a rich, dark brown&mdash;a sort of black and tan. A very pleasing tint. The 
tropical sun and the easy-going ways inherited from their ancestors, have made them rather idle, 
but they are not vicious at all, they are good people. The native women in the rural districts wear 
a loose, magnificent curtain calico garment, but the men don't. Upon great occasions the men 
wear an umbrella, or some little fancy article like that&mdash;further than this they have no inclination 
toward gorgeousness of attire. 
 
</p><p>In the old times the king was absolute, his person was sacred, and if even the shadow of a 
common Kanaka fell upon him the Kanaka had to die. There was no help for him. Whatever the 
king tabooed it was death to touch or speak of. After the king, came the high priests who 
sacrificed human victims; after them came the great feudal chiefs, and then the common Kanakas, 
who were the slaves of all, and wretchedly oppressed. Away down at the bottom of this pyramid 
were the women, the abject slaves of the whole party. They did all the work and were cruelly 
mistreated. It was death for a woman to sit at table with her husband, or to eat of the choice fruits 
of the islands at any time. They seemed to have had a sort of dim knowledge of what came of 
women eating fruit in the Garden of Eden and they didn't feel justified in taking any more chances. 
And it is wisdom&mdash;unquestionably it is wisdom. Adam wasn't strict enough. Eve broke the 
<hi rend="italic">taboo</hi>, and hence comes all this trouble. Can't be too particular about fruit&mdash;with 
women. 
 
</p><p>They were a rusty set all round&mdash;those Kanakas. By and by the American missionaries came and 
they struck off the shackles from the whole race, breaking the power of the kings and chiefs. They 
set the common man free, elevated his wife to a position of equality, and gave a spot of land to 
each to hold forever. The missionaries taught the whole nation to read and write with facility, in 
the native tongue. I  
   <pb n="8"/>  
don't suppose there is today a single uneducated person above eight years of 
age in the Sandwich Islands. It is the best educated country in the world, I believe, not excepting 
portions of the United States. That has all been done by the American missionaries. And in a large 
degree it was paid for by the American Sunday school children with their pennies. We all took 
part in it. True, the system gave opportunities to bad boys. Many a bad boy acquired the habit of 
confiscating pennies of the missionary cause. But it is one of the proudest recollections of my life 
that I never did that&mdash;at least not more than once or twice. I know that I contributed. I have had 
nearly $2 invested there for thirty years. But I don't mind it. I don't care for the money if it has 
been doing good. I don't say this in order to show off, but just mention it as a gentle, humanizing 
fact that may possibly have a benevolent and beneficent effect upon some members of this 
audience. 
 
</p><p>These natives are very hospitable people indeed&mdash;very hospitable. If you want to stay a few days 
and nights in a native's cabin you can stay and welcome. They will do everything they possibly can 
to make you comfortable. They will feed you on baked dog, or poi, or raw fish, or raw salt pork, 
fricasseed cats&mdash;all the luxuries of the season. Everything the human heart can desire, they will set 
before you. Perhaps now, this isn't a captivating feast at first glance, but it is offered in all 
sincerity, and with the best motives in the world, and that makes any feast respectable whether it 
is palatable or not. But if you want to trade, that's quite another matter&mdash;that's business! And the 
Kanucker is ready for you. He is a born trader, and he will swindle you if he can. He will lie 
straight through, from the first word to the last. Not such lies as you and I tell, but gigantic lies, 
lies that awe you with their grandeur, lies that stun you with their imperial impossibility. He will 
sell you a molehill at the market price of a mountain, and will lie it up to an altitude that will make 
it cheap at the money. If he is caught, he slips out of it with an easy indifference that has an 
unmistakable charm about it. 
 
</p><p>One peculiarity of these Kanakas is that nearly every one of them has a dozen mothers&mdash;not 
natural ones&mdash;I haven't got down yet where I can make such a statement as that&mdash;but adopted 
mothers. They have a custom of calling any woman mother they take a liking to&mdash;no matter what 
her color or politics&mdash;and it is possible for one native to have a thousand mothers if his affections 
are liberal and stretchy, and most of them are. This custom breeds some curious incidents. A 
California man went down there and opened a sugar plantation. One of his hands came and said 
he wanted to bury his mother. He gave him permission. Shortly after he came again with the same 
request. "I thought you buried her last week," said the gentleman. "This is  
   <pb n="9"/>  
another one," said the 
native. "AII right," said the gentleman, "go and plant her." Within a month the man wanted to 
bury some more mothers. "Look here," said the planter, "I don't want to be hard on you in your 
affliction, but it appears to me that your stock of mothers holds out pretty well. It interferes with 
business, so clear out, and never come back until you have buried every mother you have in the 
world." 
 
</p><p>They are an odd sort of people, too. They can die whenever they want to. That's a fact. They 
don't mind dying any more than a jilted Frenchman does. When they take a notion to die they die, 
and it don't make any difference whether there is anything the matter with them or not, and they 
can't be persuaded out of it. When one of them makes up his mind to die, he just lays down and is 
just as certain to die as though he had all the doctors in the world hold of him. A gentleman in 
Hawaii asked his servant if he wouldn't like to die and have a big funeral. He said yes, and looked 
happy, and the next morning the overseer came and said, "That boy of yours laid down and died 
last night and said you were going to give him a fine funeral." 
 
</p><p>They are very fond of funerals. Big funerals are their main weakness. Fine grave clothes, fine 
funeral appointments, and a long procession are things they take a generous delight in. Years ago 
a Kanaka and his wife were condemned to be hanged for murder. They received the sentence with 
manifest satisfaction because it gave an opening for a funeral, you know. It makes but little 
difference to them whose it is; they would as soon attend their own funeral as anybody else's. This 
couple were of consequence, and had landed estates. They sold every foot of ground they had and 
laid it out in fine clothes to be hanged in. And the woman appeared on the scaffold in a white satin 
dress and slippers and feathers of gaudy ribbon, and the man was arrayed in a gorgeous vest, blue 
clawhammer coat and brass buttons, and white kid gloves. As the noose was adjusted around his 
neck, he blew his nose with a grand theatrical flourish, so as to show his embroidered white 
handkerchief. I never, never knew of a couple who enjoyed hanging more than they did. 
 
</p><p>They are very fond of dogs, these people&mdash;not the great Newfoundland or the stately mastiff, but a 
species of little mean, contemptible cur that a white man would condemn to death on general 
principles. There is nothing attractive about these dogs&mdash;there is not a handsome feature about 
them, unless it is their bushy tails. A friend of mine said if he had one of these dogs he would cut 
off the tail and throw the rest of the dog away. They feed this dog, pet him, take ever so much 
care of him, and then cook and eat him. I couldn't do that. I would rather go hungry for two days 
than devour an old personal  
   <pb n="10"/>  
friend in that way; but many a white citizen of those islands throws 
aside his prejudices and takes his dinner off one of those puppies&mdash;and after all it is only our 
cherished American sausage with the mystery removed. 
 
</p><p>A Kanaka will eat anything he can bite&mdash;a live fish, scales and all, which must be rather annoying 
to the fish, but the Kanaka doesn't mind that. It used to be said that the Kanakas were cannibals, 
but that was a slander. They didn't eat Captain Cook&mdash;or if they did, it was only for fun. There 
was one instance of cannibalism. A foreigner, from the South Pacific Islands, set up an office and 
did eat a good many Kanakas. He was a useful citizen, but had strong political prejudices and 
used to save up a good appetite forjust before election, so that he could thin out the Democratic 
vote. 
 
</p><p>At this point in my lecture, in other cities, I usually illustrate cannibalism, but I am a stranger here 
and don't feel like taking liberties. Still, if any one in the audience will lend me an infant, I will 
illustrate the matter. But it is of no consequence&mdash;it don't matter. I know children have become 
scarce and high, owing to the inattention they have received since the women's rights movement 
began. I will leave out that part of my program, though it is very neat and pleasant. Yet it is not 
necessary. I am not hungry. 
 
</p><p>Well, that foreign cannibal after a while got tired of Kanakas&mdash;as most anybody would&mdash;and 
thought he would like to try white man with onions. So he captured and devoured a tough old 
whaleship captain, but it was the worst thing he ever did. Of course, he could no more digest that 
old whaler than a keg of nails. There is no telling how much he suffered, with this sin on his 
conscience and the whaler on his stomach. He lingered for a few days and then died. Now I don't 
believe this story myself, and have only told it for its moral. You don't appear to see the moral; 
but I know there is a moral in it, because I have told it thirty or forty times, and never got a moral 
out of it yet! 
 
</p><p>With all these excellent and hospitable ways these Kanakers have some cruel instincts. They will 
put a live chicken in the fire just to see it hop about. In the olden times they used to be cruel to 
themselves. They used to tear their hair and burn their flesh, shave their heads, knock out an eye or 
a couple of front teeth, when a great person or a king died&mdash;just to testify to their sorrow, and if their 
grief was so sore that they couldn't possibly bear it, they would go out and scalp their neighbor, or 
burn his house down. It was an excellent custom, too, for it gave every one a good opportunity to 
square up old grudges. Pity we didn't have it here! They would also kill an infant now and then&mdash;bury 
him alive sometimes; but the missionaries have annihilated infanticide&mdash;for my part I can't see why. 
 
   <pb n="11"/>  
 
</p><p>The ladies of the Sandwich Islands have a great many pleasant customs which I don't know but 
we might practice with profit here. The women all ride like men. I wish to introduce that reform in 
this country. Our ladies ought, by all means to ride like men, these sidesaddles are so dangerous. 
When women meet each other in the road, they ran and kiss and hug each other, and they don't 
blackguard each other behind each other's backs. I would like to introduce that reform, also. I don't 
suppose our ladies do it. But they might. But I believe I am getting on dangerous ground. I won't 
pursue that any further. 
 
</p><p>These people do nearly everything wrong end first. They buckle the saddle on the right side which 
is the wrong side; they mount a horse from the wrong side; they turn out on the wrong side to let you 
go by; they use the same word to say "good-by" and "good morning"; they use "yes" when they mean 
"no"; the women smoke more than the men do; when they beckon to you to come toward them they 
always motion in the opposite direction; the only native bird that has handsome feathers has only two, 
and they are under its wings instead of on top of its head; frequently a native cat has a tail only two 
inches long and has got a knot tied in the end of it; the native duck lives on the dry tops of mountains 
5,000 feet high; the natives always stew chickens instead of baking them; they dance at funerals and 
sing a dismal heartbroken dirge when they are happy; and with atrocious perverseness they wash your 
shirts with a club and iron them with a brickbat. In their playing of the noble American game of 
"seven-up," that's a game, well, I'll explain that by and by. Some of you, perhaps, know all about it, 
and the rest must guess&mdash;but, in their playing of that really noble and intellectual game the dealer deals 
to his right instead of to his left, and what is insufferably worse&mdash;the ten always takes the ace! Now, 
such abject ignorance as that is reprehensible, and, for one, I am glad the missionaries have gone 
there. 
 
</p><p>Now, you see what kind of voters you will have if you take those islands away from these people 
as we are pretty sure to do some day. They will do everything wrong end first. They will make a deal 
of trouble here too. Instead of fostering and encouraging a judicious system of railway speculation, 
and all that sort of thing, they will elect the most incorruptible men to Congress. Yes, they will turn 
everything upside down. 
 
</p><p>In Honolulu they are the most easy-going people in the world. Some of our people are not 
acquainted with their customs. They started a gas company once, and put the gas at $13 a thousand 
feet. They only took in $16 the first month. They all went to bed at dark. They are an excellent 
people. I speak earnestly. They do not even know the name  
   <pb n="12"/>  
of some of the vices in this country. A 
lady called on a doctor. She wanted something for general debility. He ordered her to drink porter. 
She called him again. The porter had done her no good. He asked her how much porter she had 
taken. She said a tablespoonful in a tumbler of water. I wish we could import such blessed ignorance 
into this country. They don't do much drinking there. When they have paid the tax for importing the 
liquor they have got nothing left to purchase the liquor with. They are very innocent and drink 
anything that is liquid&mdash;kerosene, turpentine, hair oil. In one town, on a Fourth of July, an entire 
community got drunk on a barrel of Mrs. Winslow's soothing syrup. 
 
</p><p>The chief glory of the Sandwich Islands is their great volcano. The volcano of Kee-law-ay-oh is 
17,000 feet in diameter, and from 700 to 800 feet deep. Vesuvius is nowhere. It is the largest volcano 
in the world; shoots up flames tremendously high. You witness a scene of unrivaled sublimity, and 
witness the most astonishing sights. When the volcano of Kee-law-ay-oh broke through a few years 
ago, lava flowed out of it for twenty days and twenty nights, and made a stream forty miles in length, 
till it reached the sea, tearing up forests in its awful fiery path, swallowing up huts, destroying all 
vegetation, rioting through shady dells and sinuous canyons. Amidst this carnival of destruction, 
majestic columns of smoke ascended and formed a cloudy murky pall overhead. Sheets of green, blue, 
lambent flames were shot upward, and pierced the vast gloom, making all sublimely grand. 
 
</p><p>The natives are indifferent to volcanic terrors. During the progress of an eruption they ate, drank, 
bought, sold, planted, builded, apparently indifferent to the roar of consuming forests, the startling 
detonations, the hissing of escaping steam, the rending of the earth, the shivering and melting of 
gigantic rocks, the raging and dashing of the fiery waves, the bellowings and unearthly mutterings 
coming up from a burning deep. They went carelessly on, amid the rain of ashes, sand, and fiery 
scintillations, gazing vacantly at the ever-varying appearance of the atmosphere, murky, black, livid, 
blazing, the sudden rising of lofty pillars of flame, the upward curling of ten thousand columns of 
smoke, and their majestic roll in dense and lurid clouds. All these moving phenomena were regarded 
by them as the fall of a shower or the running of a brook; while to others they were as the tokens of 
a burning world, the departing heavens, and a coming judge. There! I'm glad I've got that volcano off 
my mind. 
 
</p><p>I once knew a great, tall gawky country editor, near Sacramento, to whom I sent an ode on the sea, 
starting it with "The long, green swell of the Pacific." The country editor sent back a letter and stated 
I couldn't fool him, and he didn't want any base insinuations from me.   
   <pb n="13"/>  
He knew who I meant when 
I wrote the "long, green swell of the Pacific." 
 
</p><p>There is one thing characteristic of the tropics that a stranger must have, whether he likes it or not, 
and that is the boo-hoo fever. Its symptoms are nausea of the stomach, severe headache, backache 
and bellyache, and a general utter indifference whether school keeps or not. You can't be a full citizen 
of the Sandwich Islands unless you have had the boo-hoo fever. You will never forget it. I remember 
a little boy who had it once there. A New Yorker asked him if he was afraid to die. He said, "No; I 
am not afraid to die of anything, except the boo-hoo fever." 
 
</p><p>The climate of these islands is delightful, it is beautiful. In Honolulu the thermometer stands at 
about 80 or 82 degrees pretty much all the year round&mdash;don't change more than 12 degrees in twelve 
months. In the sugar districts the thermometer stands at 70 and does not change at all. Any kind of 
thermometer will do&mdash;one without any quicksilver is just as good. Eighty degrees by the seashore, and 
70 degrees farther inland, and 60 degrees as you ascend the slope of the mountain, and as you go 
higher 50 degrees, 40, 30, and ever decreasing in temperature, till you get to the top, where it's so 
cold that you can't speak the truth. I know, for I've been there! The climate is wonderfully healthy, 
for white people in particular, so healthy that white people venture on the most reckless imprudence. 
They get up too early: you can see them as early as half-past seven in the morning, and they attend 
to all their business, and keep it up till sundown. It don't hurt 'em, don't kill 'em, and yet it ought to 
do so. I have seen it so hot in California that greenbacks went up to 142 in the shade. 
 
</p><p>These Sandwichers believe in a superstition that the biggest liars in the world have got to visit the 
islands some time before they die. They believe that because it is a fact&mdash;you misunderstand&mdash;I mean 
that when liars get there they stay there. They have several specimens they boast of. They treasure 
up their little perfections, and they allude to them as if the man was inspired&mdash;from below. They had 
a man among them named Morgan. He never allowed anyone to tell a bigger lie than himself, and he 
always told the last one too. When someone was telling about the natural bridge in Virginia, he said 
he knew all about it, as his father had helped to build it. Someone was bragging of a wonderful horse 
he had. Morgan told them of one he had once. While out riding one day a thundershower came on 
and chased him for eighteen miles, and never caught him. Not a single drop of rain dropped onto his 
horse, but his dog was swimming behind the wagon the whole of the way. 
 
</p><p>Once, when the subject of mean men was being discussed, Morgan  
   <pb n="14"/>  
told them of an incorporated 
company of mean men. They hired a poor fellow to blast rock for them. He drilled a hole four feet 
deep, put in the powder, and began to tamp it down around the fuse. I know all about tamping, as 
I have worked in a mine myself. The crowbar struck a spark and caused a premature explosion and 
that man and his crowbar shot up into the air, and he went higher and higher, till he didn't look bigger 
than a boy, and he kept on going higher and higher, until he didn't look bigger than a dog, and he kept 
on going higher and higher, until he didn't look bigger than a bee, and then he went out of sight; and 
presently he came in sight again, looking no bigger than a bee, and he came further and further, until 
he was as big as a dog, and further and further and further, until he was as big as a boy, and he came 
further and further, until he assumed the full size and shape of a man, and he came down and fell right 
into the same old spot and went to tamping again. And would you believe it&mdash;concluded Morgan&mdash;although that poor fellow was not gone more than fifteen minutes, yet that mean company docked 
him for loss of time. 
 
</p><p>The land that I have tried to tell you about lies out there in the midst of the watery wilderness, in 
the very heart of the almost soilless solitudes of the Pacific. It is a dreamy, beautiful, charming land. 
I wish I could make you comprehend how beautiful it is. It is a land that seems ever so vague and 
fairy-like when one reads about it in books, peopled with a gentle, indolent, careless race. 
 
</p><p>It is Sunday land. The land of indolence and dreams, where the air is drowsy and things tend to 
repose and peace, and to emancipation from the labor, and turmoil, and weariness, and anxiety of life.</p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
 
<back id="d6"> 
<div1 type="notes" id="d7"> 
 
<p><hi rend="italic">Text</hi> / Composite, based upon: "Mark Twain at the Mercantile Library Hall," St. Louis  
<hi rend="italic">Democrat</hi>, March 28, 1867; "Mark Twain's Lecture," Providence, Rhode Island, <hi rend="italic">Press</hi>,  
November 10, 1869; "Mark Twain's Lecture," <hi rend="italic">Courant</hi>, November 24 1869; "Mark Twain's Lecture,"  
New Haven, Connecticut, <hi rend="italic">Morning Journal</hi>, December 28, 1869; "Our Fellow Savages of the Sandwich 
Islands," Portland, Maine, <hi rend="italic">Transcript</hi>, January 1, 1870; "Our Fellow Savages of the Sandwich  
Islands," Troy, New York, <hi rend="italic">Times</hi>, January 12, 1870; "Mark Twain, What He Know About the Sandwich  
Islands," Brooklyn <hi rend="italic">Eagle</hi>, February 8, 1873; "Cracking Jokes," London <hi rend="italic">Once a Week</hi>,  
n.s., no. 306 (November 8, 1873):402-5; "The Sandwich Islands," <hi rend="italic">Eloquence</hi>(R), 4:253-59,  
and <hi rend="italic">Eloquence</hi>(T), 13:133-39; "From Mark Twain's First Lecture," <hi rend="italic">MTB</hi>, 4:1601-3. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">introduction</hi> / To circumvent local chairmen who introduced him with lavish praise  
and labored jokes, Mark Twain adopted the practice of introducing himself with 
an extravagant eulogy of his own accomplishments.  One reporter, attempting to capture in print 
the inflated substance and slow delivery, represented them thus:  "Ladies and gentlemen:  
I&mdash;have&mdash;lectured&mdash;many&mdash;years&mdash;and&mdash;in&mdash;many&mdash;towns&mdash;large&mdash;and&mdash;small.  I have  
traveled&mdash;north&mdash;south&mdash;east&mdash;and&mdash;west.  I&mdash;have&mdash;met&mdash;many&mdash;great&mdash;men: <hi rend="italic">very</hi>&mdash;great&mdash;men. 
But&mdash;I&mdash;have&mdash;never&mdash;yet&mdash;in&mdash;all&mdash;ny&mdash;travels&mdash;met&mdash;the&mdash;president&mdash;of&mdash;a&mdash;<hi rend="italic">country</hi>&mdash;lyceum&mdash;who&mdash;could&mdash;introduce&mdash;me&mdash;to&mdash;an&mdash;audience&mdash;with&mdash;that&mdash;<hi rend="italic">distinguished</hi>&mdash;consideration&mdash;which&mdash;my 
<hi rend="italic">merits</hi> deserve."  See Joel Benton, "Reminiscences of Eminent Lecturers," <hi rend="italic">Harper's 
New Monthly Magazine</hi> 96, no. 574 (March 1898):610. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Captain Cook</hi> / James Cook (1728-79). British navigator and explorer.  On a voyage in 
search of the Northwest Passage he came upon the islands in 1778.  He named them Sandwich Islands 
after the earl of Sandwich, first lord of the Admiralty. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Kanaka</hi> / A Polynesian word meaning "man," formerly applied to Hawaiian natives 
and to other South Pacific islanders. 
 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">poi</hi> / A favorite Hawaiian food made of taro root mixed into a paste and allowed to 
ferment.  Mark Twain said, St. Louis <hi rend="italic">Democrat</hi>, March 28, 1867: "Eating poi will cure a 
drunkard.  In order to like poi you must get used to it.  It smells a good deal worse than it 
tastes, and it tastes a good deal worse than it looks." 
 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Kee-law-ay-oh</hi> / Kilauea, an active volcano on the slope of Mauna Loa.  An altitude 
of 4,000 feet and a circumference of eight miles make it one of the largest and most spectacular 
craters in the world.</p> 
 
</div1> 
</back> 
 
   
 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
