<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="Twa2Toa"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 

<TEI.2 id="Twa2Toa">
	<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">1868 Toast To Woman</title>
<title type="sort">1868 toast to woman</title>
<author>Twain, Mark, 1835-1910</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
					<name>Stephen Railton</name>
					<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
					<name>Tom Palombi, Electronic Text Center</name>
					<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
					<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
			<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">12</num> kilobytes</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
				<idno type="ETC">Twa2Toa</idno>
				<date value="1997-09">September 1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476407</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Toast "To Woman"</title>
<title level="j">The Washington Star</title>
<title type="sort">toast to woman</title>
<author>Mark Twain</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
							<name/>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
					<editionStmt>
<p>Twain's toast was delivered to the Washington Correspondents' Club on
							January 11, 1868.</p>
</editionStmt>
					<publicationStmt>
						<date value="1868-01-13">January 13, 1868</date>
						<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted:</idno>
</publicationStmt>
					</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
					word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
				<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general
					use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
				<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
					establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
			</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
			<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; fiction</term>
</keywords>
				</textClass>
</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-09">September 1997</date>
				<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
					<name>Tom Palombi, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
				<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

	<text id="d1">

		<front id="d2">
			<pb/>
			<div1 type="preface" id="d3">
				<head>To Woman: An Irregular Toast</head>

				<p>This toast, delivered 11 January 1868 to a banquet room full of journalists, was
					one of MT's first great public successes in the east. Below is the text, as
					published in the paper the next day and widely reprinted across the country in
					the following weeks, preceded by part of the story of MT's own mixed feelings
					about the address.</p>
			</div1>

			<div1 type="introduction" id="d4">
			<pb/>
				<head>BEHIND THE SCENES</head>

				<p>The <hi rend="italic">Star</hi>'s transcript is a good one, but the paper left
					out two of MT's most risque jokes &mdash; their places are marked in the
					text at left with asterisks, and can be accessed by clicking on the (*). MT was
					initially delighted with both his live performance and the subsequent publicity:
					he sent copies of this article to <hi rend="italic">his</hi> "own mother!" and
					to the <hi rend="italic">Alta California</hi>. Soon, however, he became anxious
					about how well the performance would play with the genteel audiences he was
					trying to adapt his persona to. That audience was, at this point, epitomized by
					Mrs. Mary Fairbanks, the slightly older wife of a Cleveland publisher whom MT
					met on the<hi rend="italic"> Quaker City</hi> tour and was soon calling
					"Mother." To her he wrote on January 24: </p>
				<q>
					<p>Dear Mother &mdash; Don't abuse me on account of that dinner-speech in
						reply to the toast to Woman, if you should see it floating around in the
						papers. &mdash; It had slang in it, but they had no business to report
						it so <hi rend="italic">verbatimly</hi>. . . . I am not going to make any
						more slang speeches in public. You will forgive me, now, won't you? </p>
				</q>

				<p>
					<hi rend="italic">Apparently Mrs. Fairbanks did see the speech, and did abuse
						him for it. On January 30 he wrote:</hi>
				</p>

				<q>
					<p>P.S. &mdash; I confess, humbly, that I deserve all you have said,
						&amp; promise that I will rigidly eschew slang &amp; vulgarity in
						future, even in foolish dinner speeches, when on my guard. </p>
				</q>

				<p>Although the record of the performance seems lost, within a month MT seems to
					addressed himself again "To Woman." This time, he felt, his speech was one
					"Mother" Fairbanks would be pleased with, as he told her in a letter dated
					February 20: </p>

				<q>
					<p>I acknowledge &mdash; I acknowledge &mdash; that I <hi rend="italic"
							>can</hi> be most laceratingly "funny without being vulgar." In proof
						whereof I responded again to the regular toast to Woman at a grand banquet
						night before last, &amp; was frigidly proper in language &amp;
						sentiment. . . . <hi rend="italic">Now</hi> haven't I vindicated myself
						&amp; shed honor upon my teacher &amp; done credit to her teachings?
						With head uncovered, &amp; in attitude suppliant but yet expressive of
						conscious merit, I stand before you in spirit &amp; wait my earned "Well
						done," &amp; augmented emolument of bread &amp; butter &mdash;
						to the end that I may go &amp; slide on the cellar door &amp; be
						happy. </p>
				</q>

				<p>MT knew that people laugh when they are uncomfortable, so he was always working
					right at the line between teasing or provoking his audience and shocking or
					offending them. Except for a few very private performances (<hi rend="italic"
						>1602</hi> and <hi rend="italic">"Some Remarks on the Science of
					Onanism"</hi>) MT made little use of sexual humor &mdash; less, probably,
					than even his repressive culture would have allowed him, and amazingly little by
					the standards of modern comedy. It does not seem that many people besides Mrs.
					Fairbanks would have objected to this 1868 toast, at least as reprinted in
						the<hi rend="italic"> Star </hi>. Apparently his own mother, from a less
					refined realm than Mary Fairbanks, enjoyed it. On the other hand, MT's speech at
					the Whittier Birthday Dinner set off a number of critics. It treated with slang
					and irreverence another of Victorian America's sacred icons &mdash; not
					woman, but the gentleman man-of-letters. </p>
			</div1>

		</front>

		<body id="d5">

			<div1 type="speech" id="d6">
				<pb/>
				<head>The Washington <hi rend="italic">Star</hi><lb/> 13 January 1868<lb/>
					<lb/>Mark Twain's Eulogy of the Fair Sex.</head>

				<p>The Washington Correspondents' Club held its anniversary on Saturday night. Mr.
					Clemens, better known as Mark Twain, responded to the toast "Woman, the pride of
					the professions and the jewel of ours." He said: </p>
				<p>MR. PRESIDENT: I do not know why I should have been singled out to receive the
					greatest distinction of the evening &mdash; for so the office of replying to
					the toast to woman has been regarded in every age. [Applause.] I do not know why
					I have received this distinction, unless it be that I am a trifle less homely
					than the other members of the Club. But, be this as I may, Mr. President, I am
					proud of the position, and you could not have chosen anyone who would have
					accepted it more gladly, or labored with a heartier good will to do the subject
					justice, than I. Because, sir, I love the sex. [Laughter.] I love <hi
						rend="italic">all</hi> the women, sir, irrespective of age or color.
					[Laughter.] </p>
				<p>Human intelligence cannot estimate what we owe to woman, sir. She sews our
					buttons [laughter], she mends our clothes [laughter], she ropes us in at the
					church fairs &mdash; she confides in us; she tells us whatever she can find
					out about the little private affairs of the neighbors &mdash; she gives us
					good advice, and plenty of it &mdash; she gives us a piece of her mind,
					sometimes &mdash; and sometimes all of it &mdash; she soothes our aching
					brows &mdash; she bears our children. In all the relations of life, sir, it
					is but just, and a graceful tribute to woman to say of her that she is a brick.
					[Great laughter.] </p>
				<p>Wheresoever you place woman, sir &mdash; in whatever position or estate
					&mdash; she is an ornament to that place she occupies, and a treasure to the
					world. [Here Mr. Twain paused, looked inquiringly at his hearers and remarked
					that the applause should come in at this point. It came in. Mr. Twain resumed
					his eulogy.] Look at the noble names of history! Look at Cleopatra! look at
					Desdemona! look at Florence Nightengale! look at Joan of Arc! look at Lucretia
					Borgia! [Disapprobriation expressed. "Well," said Mr. Twain, scratching his head
					doubtfully, "suppose we let Lucretia slide."] Look at Joyce Heth! look at Mother
					Eve! I repeat, sir, look at the illustrious names of history! Look at the Widow
					Machree! Look at Lucy Stone! Look at Elizabeth Cady Stanton! Look at George
					Francis Train! [Great laughter.] And, sir, I say with bowed head and deepest
					veneration, look at the mother of Washington! She raised a boy that could not
					lie &mdash; <hi rend="italic">could not lie</hi>. [Applause.] But he <hi
						rend="italic">never had any chance</hi>. It might have been different with
					him if he had belonged to a newspaper correspondent's club. [Laughter, groans,
					hisses, cries of "put him out." Mark looked around placidly upon his excited
					audience and resumed.] </p>
				<p>I repeat, sir, that in whatever position you place a woman she is an ornament to
					society and a treasure to the world. As a sweetheart she has few equals and no
					superiors &mdash; [laughter;] &mdash; as a cousin she is convenient; as
					a wealthy grandmother with an incurable distemper, she is precious; as a wet
					nurse she has no equal among men! [Laughter.] </p>
				<p>What, sir, would the people of this earth be, without woman? They would be
					scarce, sir. Then let us cherish her &mdash; let us protect her &mdash;
					let us give her our support, our encouragement, our sympathies &mdash;
					ourselves, if we get the chance. [Laughter.] </p>
				<p>But, jesting aside, Mr. President, woman is lovable, gracious, kind of heart,
					beautiful &mdash; worthy of all respect, of all esteem, of all deference.
					Not any here will refuse to drink her health right cordially, for each and every
					one of us has personally known, and loved, and honored, the very best one of
					them all &mdash; his own mother! [Applause.] </p>
			</div1>

		</body>

	</text>
</TEI.2>
