<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="Twa6Aro"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="Twa6Aro">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Around the World Letter, No. 6</title>
<title type="sort">around the world letter, no 6</title>
<author>Twain, Mark, 1835-1910</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Steve Railton</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>M. Eleanor Culley, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">13</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">Twa6Aro</idno>
<date value="2001">2001</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2001 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476410</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Around the World Letter, No. 6</title>
<title type="sort">around the world letter, no 6</title>
<author>Mark Twain, pseud. Samuel Langhorne Clemens</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Buffalo Express</publisher>
<date value="1870-01-08">January 8, 1870</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
<term>Mark Twain</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2001-07">July, 2001</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name/>
</respStmt>
<item/>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>





<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="letter" id="d3">
<head>
Buffalo <hi rend="italic">Express</hi>8 January 1869<lb/>
Around the World: Letter No. 6: "Early Days" in Nevada</head>


<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d4">
<head>SILVER LAND NABOBS</head>
<p>
One of the curious features of Pacific Coast life is the startling uncertainty that marks a man's
career in the mines. He may spring from poverty to wealth so suddenly as to turn his hair white
and then after a while he may become poor again so suddenly as to make all that white hair fall
off and leave his head as clean as a billiard ball. The great Nevada silver excitement of '58-'59
was prolific in this sort of vicissitudes.</p>

<p>Two brothers, teamsters, did some hauling for a man in Virginia City, and had to take a small
segregated portion of a silver mine in lieu of $300 cash. They gave an outsider a third to open the
mine, and they went on teaming. But not long. Ten months afterward the mine was out of debt
and paying each owner $8000 to $10,000 a month &mdash; say $100,000 a year. They had that
handsome income for just about two years &mdash; and they dressed in the loudest kind of costumes
and wore mighty diamonds, and played poker for amusement, these men who had seldom had
$20 at one time in all their lives before. One of them is tending bar for wages, now, and the other
is serving his country as Commander-in-Chief of a street car in San Francisco at $75 a month. He
was very glad to get that employment, too.</p>

<p>
One of the earliest nabobs that Nevada was delivered of wore $6000 worth diamonds in his
bosom, and swore he was unhappy because he couldn't spend his money as fast as he made it.
But let us learn from him that persistent effort is bound to achieve success at last. Within a year's
time his happiness was secure; for he hadn't a cent to spend.</p>

<p>
Another Nevada nabob boasted an income that often reached $16,000 a month; and he used to
love to tell how he had worked in the very mine that yielded it, for $5 a day, when he first came
to the country. Three years afterward he attained to the far more exceeding grandeur of working
in it again, at four dollars a day.</p>

<p>
The silver and sage-brush State has knowledge of another of these pets of fortune &mdash; lifted from
actual poverty to affluence almost in a single night &mdash; who was able to offer $100,000 for a
position of high official distinction, shortly afterward, and did offer it &mdash; and a little over a year
ago a friend saw him shoveling snow on the Pacific Railroad for a living, away up on the summit
of the Sierras, some 7,000 feet above the level of comfort and the sea. The friend remarked that it
must be pretty hard work, though, as the snow was twenty-five feet deep, it promised to be a
steady job, at least. Yes, he said, he didn't mind it now, though a month or so ago when it was
sixty-two feet deep and still a snowing, he wasn't so much attached to it. Such is life.</p>

<p>
Then there was John Smith. That wasn't his name, but we will call him that. He was a good,
honest, kind-hearted fellow, born and reared in the lower ranks of life and miraculously ignorant.
He drove a team, and the team belonged to another man. By and bye he married an excellent
woman who owned a small ranch &mdash; a ranch that paid them a comfortable living, for although it
yielded but little hay, what little it did yield was worth from $250 to $500 in gold per ton in the
market. Presently Smith traded a few acres of the ranch for a small undeveloped silver mine in
Gold Hill.  He opened the mine and built a little unpretending ten-stamp mill. Eighteen months
afterward he quit raising hay, for his mining income had reached a most comfortable figure.
Some people said it was $30,000 a month, and others said it was $60,000. Smith was very rich
any how. He built a house out in the desert &mdash; right in the most forbidding and otherwise howling
desert &mdash; and it was currently reported that that house cost him a quarter of a million. Possibly
that was exaggerated somewhat, though it certainly was a fine house and a costly one. The bed
steads cost $400 or $500 apiece.</p>

<p>
And then the Smith went to Europe and traveled. And when they came back Smith was never
tired of telling about the fine hogs he had seen in England, and the gorgeous sheep he had seen in
Spain, and the fine cattle he had noticed in the vicinity of Rome. He was full of the wonder of the
old world, and advised every body to travel. He said a man never imagined what surprising
things there were in the world till he had traveled.</p>
<p>
One day, on board ship, the passengers made up a pool of $500, which was to be the property of
the man who should come nearest to guessing the run of the vessel for the next twenty-four
hours. Next day, toward noon, the figures were all in the purser's hands in sealed envelopes.
Smith was serene and happy, for he had been bribing the engineer. But another party won the
prize! Smith said:
<q>"Here, that won't do! He guessed two miles wider of the mark than I did."</q>

The purser said, <q>"Mr. Smith, you missed it further than any man on board. We traveled two
hundred and eight miles yesterday."</q>

<q>"Well sir," said Smith, "that's just where I've got you, for I guessed two hundred and nine. If
you'll look at my figgers again you'll find a 2 and two naughts, which stands for 200, don't it? &mdash;
and after em your find a 9 (2009), which stands for two hundred and nine. I reckon I'll take that
money, if you please."</q>

Well, Smith is dead. And when he died he wasn't worth a cent. The lesson of all this is, that one
must <hi rend="italic">learn how</hi> to do everything he does &mdash; one must have experience in being rich before
he can <hi rend="italic">remain</hi> rich. The history of California will prove this to your entire satisfaction.
Sudden wealth is an awful misfortune to the average run of men. It is wasting breath to instruct
the reader after this fashion, though, for no man was ever convinced of it yet till he had tried it
himself &mdash; and I am around now hunting for a man who is afraid to try it. I haven't had any luck so
far.</p>

<p>
All the early pioneers of California acquired more or less wealth, but an enormous majority of
them have not got any now. Those that have, got it slowly and by patient toil.</p>

<p>
The reader has heard of the great Gould &amp; Curry silver mine of Nevada. I believe its shares are
still quoted in the stock sales in the New York papers. The claim comprised 1200 feet, if I
remember rightly, or may be it was 800 and I think it all belonged originally to two men whose
name it bears. Mr. Curry owned two-thirds of it &mdash; and he said that he sold it out for twenty-five
hundred dollars in cash, and an old plug horse that ate up his market value in hay and barley in
17 days by the watch. And he said that Gould sold out for a pair of second-hand government
blankets and a bottle of whiskey that killed nine men in three hours, and that an unoffending
stranger that smelt the cork was disabled for life. Four years afterward the mine thus disposed of
was worth on the San Francisco market seven million six hundred thousand dollars in gold
coin.</p>

<p>
In the early days a poverty-stricken Mexican who lived in a canyon right back of Virginia City,
had a stream of water as large as a man's wrist trickling from the hillside on his premises. The
Ophir Company segregated 100 ft. of their mine and swapped it to him for the stream of water.
The 100 ft. proved to be the richest part of the entire mine; four years after the swap, its market
value (including its mill), was $1,500,000. I was down in it about that time, 600 ft. under the
ground, and about half of it caved in over my head &mdash; and yet, valuable as that property was, I
would have given the entire mine to have been out of that. I do not wish to brag &mdash; but I can be
liberal if you take me right.</p>

<p>
An individual who owned 20 feet in the Ophir mine before its great riches were revealed to men,
traded it for a horse, and a very sorry looking brute he was too. A year or so afterward, when
Ophir stock went up to $3000 a foot, this man, who hadn't a cent, used to say he was the most
startling example of magnificence and misery the world had ever seen &mdash; because he was able to
ride a 60,000-dollar horse and yet had to ride him bareback because he couldn't scare up cash
enough to buy a saddle. He said if fortune were to give him another 60,000-dollar horse it would
ruin him.</p>
<p>
The shiftless people I have been talking about have settled sedimentally down to their proper
place on the bottom, but the solid mining prosperity of California and Nevada continues &mdash; the
two together producing some $40,000,000 annually in gold and silver. White Pine is giving birth
to the usual number of suddenly created nabobs, but three years hence nearly every one of them
will be scratching for wages again. Petroleum bred a few of these butterflies for the eastern
market. They don't live long in Nevada. I was worth half a million dollars myself, once, for ten
days &mdash; and now I am prowling around the lecture field and the field of journalism, instructing 
the public for a subsistence. I was just as happy as the other butterflies, and no wiser &mdash; except
that I am sincerely glad that my supernatural stupidity lost me my great windfall before it had a
chance to make a more inspired ass of me than I was before. I am satisfied that I do not know
enough to be wealthy and live to survive it. I had two partners in this brilliant stroke of fortune.
The sensible one is still worth a hundred thousand dollars or so &mdash; he never lost his wits &mdash; but the
other one (and by far the best and worthiest of our trio), can't pay his board.</p>
<p>
I was personally acquainted with the several nabobs mentioned in this letter, and so for old
acquaintance sake, I have swapped their occupations and experiences around in such a way as to
keep the Pacific public from recognizing these once notorious men. I have no desire to drag them
out of their retirement and make them uncomfortable by exhibiting them without mask or
disguise  &mdash; I merely wish to use their fortunes and misfortunes for a moment for the adornment
of this newspaper article. </p>
</div2>
<byline>Mark Twain</byline>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
