<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="TwaChim"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="TwaChim">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Around the World Letter, No. 3</title>
<title type="sort">around the world letter, no 3</title>
<author>Twain, Mark, 1835-1910</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Steve Railton</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>M. Eleanor Culley, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">23</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">TwaChim</idno>
<date value="2001">2001</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2001 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476415</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"How the Chimney-Sweep Got the Ear of the Emperor"</title>
<title type="sort">how the chimney sweep got the ear of the emperor</title>
<author>Mark Twain, pseud. Samuel Langhorne Clemens</author>
<editor>Catherine Tousignant</editor>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: MSS 6314-ao, Alderman Library Special Collections</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Clifton Waller Barrett Collection</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
<term>Mark Twain</term>
<term>Special Collections</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2001-07">July, 2001</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name/>
</respStmt>
<item/>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>



<text id="d1">
<front id="d2">
<div1 type="introduction" id="d3">
<head><bibl><title>Introduction</title><author>Catherine Tousignant</author>
</bibl></head>
<p>A man always fascinated by new technologies, Mark Twain found
typesetting to be the most interesting heir of the industrial age.  In
the 1890's, he nearly bankrupted his family yet again by investing
heavily and poorly in the doomed Paige Typesetter venture.  A journeyman
printer in his youth, he was concerned with questions of type and the
appearance of his texts in print throughout his life.  Indeed, he often
expressed rage and ire toward the publications who often bungled a text
in transmission.  Yet his fervor on this issue seems to abate in his
later career, as he recovered for the Paige disater and began to worry
seriously about providing a solid financial legacy for his family.  In
1899 he contracted with The American Publishing Company to re-release
his works, in an "Authorized Uniform Edition."  This move was intended
to generate quick and substantial cash, rather than to revise and set
his works once and for all.  In the years around the turn of the
century, Twain churned out much writing, many manuscripts left
unfinished, most works, fiction or polemical, of poor quality.  His
biographers take great care to point out his despondency in these years,
his commitment to reform, and his desperate anathema to writing at all. </p>
<p>
Few typed manuscripts survive from this time, or any earlier period in
his career, for that matter. Thus, "How the Chimney-Sweep Got the Ear of
the Emperor," which survives not only in typescript but also in
autograph manuscript at the University of Virginia Library, offers a
rare opportunity to examine Twain's composition habits vis-&agrave;-vis
one of his insignficant stories-cum-commodities, as well as his use of
the relatively new typewriter technology to control the appearance of
his texts in print.  The story was never published as a discrete work of
fiction. It appeared embedded in another story, "The Man With a Message
for the Director-General" under the title "Two Little Tales," first in
1901 in the <hi rend="italic">Century Magazine</hi>.</p>

<p>The story reflects Twain's disgust with medical professionals, who he
believed "killed" his ailing daughter Suzy several years before.  It's
 a rather bittersweet tale, cynical at its core, but illuminated by
Twain's classic faith in simple boyhood wisdom, the magic power of
watermelon, a favorite southern American delicacy which he missed dearly
while he was in Europe. </p>

<p>In the twilight of his life and the waning of his writing career,
Twain seems poised on the edge of the new millenium with mixed feelings
of frustration, moral disgust, and wonder at the modern world around
him.  Likewise, my examination of these various texts in the preparation
of this edition has revealed the author at his easiest and best with
an old-fashioned pen in hand; yet embracing new technology to infiltrate
the typesetting process.  Alas, when the story does appear in print, we
find that publishers took as many liberties setting from a typed
manuscript as from a raw hand, both to adjust for cultural conventions
which the typewritten manuscript actually highlighted, and to whitewash
the very details that distinguish Twain's masterful dialogue in the
interest of preserving the common denominator in a journal of
mass-circulation.</p>
</div1>
</front>

<body id="d4">

<div1 type="story" id="d5">
<head><bibl><title>HOW THE CHIMNEY-SWEEP GOT THE EAR OF THE EMPEROR</title><author>Mark Twain</author></bibl></head>

<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d6">
<head>I.</head> 

<p>Summer was come, and all the strong were bowed by the 
burden of the awful heat, and many of the weak were prostrate 
and dying.  For weeks the army had been wasting away with a 
plague of dysentery, that scourge of the soldier, and there 
was but little help.  The doctors were in despair; such 
efficacy as their drugs and their science had once had&mdash;and  
it was not much, at its best&mdash;was a thing of the past, 
and promised to remain so.
</p><p>
The Emperor commanded the physicians of greatest renown 
to appear before him for a consultation, for he was profoundly 
disturbed.  He was very severe with them, and called them to 
account for letting his soldiers die; and asked them if they 
knew their trade, or didn't; and were they properly healers, 
or merely assassins?  Then the principal assassin, who was 
also the oldest doctor in the land and the most venerable in 
appearance, answered and said&mdash;
</p><p>
"We have done what we could, your Majesty, and for a good 
reason it has been little: no medicine and no physician can 
cure that disease; only Nature and a good constitution can 
do it.  I am old, and I know.  No doctor and no medicine 
can cure it&mdash;I repeat it and I emphasize it;  sometimes they 
seem to help Nature a little&mdash;a very little&mdash;but as a rule 
they merely do damage."
</p>
<p>The Emperor was a profane and passionate man, and he 
deluged the doctors with rugged and unfamiliar names and drove 
them from his presence.  Within a day he was attacked by that 
fell disease himself. The news flew from mouth to mouth, and 
carried consternation with it all over the land.  All the talk 
was about this awful disaster, and there was general depression, 
for few had hope.  The Emperor himself was very melancholy, 
and sighed and said&mdash;
</p><p>"The will of God be done.  Send for the assassins again, 
and let us get over with it."
</p><p>
They came, and felt his pulse, and looked at his tongue, 
and fetched the drugstore and emptied it into him, and sat 
down patiently to wait&mdash;for they were not paid by the job, 
but by the year.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d7">
<head>II.</head>

<p>Tommy was sixteen and a bright lad, but he was not in 
society.  His rank was too humble for that, and his employment 
too base; in fact it was the lowest of all employments, 
for he was second in command to his father, who emptied cesspools 
and drove a night-cart.  Tommy's closest friend was 
Jimmy the chimney-sweep, a slim little fellow of fourteen, 
who was honest and industrious, and had a good heart and 
supported a bed-ridden mother by his dangerous and unpleasant 
trade. </p>
<p>About a month after the Emperor fell ill, 
these two lads met one evening about nine.  Tommy was 
on his way to his night-work, and of course was not in his 
Sundays, but in his dreadful work-clothes, and not smelling 
very well;  Jimmy was on his way home from his day's labor, 
and was blacker than any other object imaginable, and he had 
his brushes on his shoulder and his soot-bag at his waist, 
and no feature of his sable face was distinguishable except 
his lively eyes.</p>
<p>They sat down on the curbstone to talk; and of course 
it was upon the one subject&mdash;the nation's calamity, the 
Emperor's disorder.  Jimmy was full of a great project, and 
burning to unfold it.  He said&mdash;
</p><p>"Tommy, I can cure his Majesty! I know how to do it."
</p><p>
Tommy was surprised.
</p><p>
"What? You?"
</p><p>"Yes, I."
</p><p>"Why, you little fool, the best doctors can't."
</p><p>"I don't care, I can do it.  I can cure him in fifteen 
minutes."
</p><p>"Oh, come off!  What are you giving me?"</p><p>
"The facts&mdash;that's all."

</p><p>Jimmy's manner was so serious that it sobered Tommy, who 
said&mdash;
</p><p>"I believe you are in earnest, Jimmy.  Are you in earnest?"
</p><p>"I give you my word."</p>
<p>"What is the plan?  How'll you cure him?"
</p><p>"Tell him to eat a slice of ripe watermelon."

It caught Tommy rather suddenly, and he was shouting with 
laughter at the absurdity of the idea before he could put on a 
stopper.  But he sobered down when he saw that Jimmy was 
wounded.  He patted Jimmy's knee affectionately, not minding 
the soot, and said&mdash;
</p><p>"I take the laugh all back  I didn't mean any harm, 
Jimmy, and I won't do it again.  You see, it seemed so funny, 
because wherever there's a soldier-camp and dysentery, the 
doctors always put up a sign saying anybody caught bringing 
watermelons there will be flogged with the cat till he can't 
stand."
</p><p>"I know it&mdash;the idiots!" 
said Jimmy, with both tears and anger in his voice.  
</p><p>"There's plenty of watermelons, 
and not one of all those soldiers ought to have died."
</p><p>"But Jimmy, what put the notion in your head?"

</p><p>"It isn't a notion, it's a fact.  Do you know that old 
gray-headed Zulu?  Well, this long time back he has been 
curing a lot of our friends, and my mother has seen him do 
it, and so have I.  It takes only one or two slices of melon, 
and it don't make any difference whether the disease is new 
or old, it cures it."
</p><p>"It's very odd.  But Jimmy, if it is so, the Emperor 
ought to be told of it."

</p><p>"Of course; and my mother has told people, hoping they 
could get the word to him;  but they are poor working-folks 
and ignorant, and don't know how to manage it."

</p><p>"Of course they don't, the blunderheads," said Tommy, 
scornfully;  <hi rend="italic">"I'll</hi> get it to him!"
</p><p>

</p><p>"You? you night-cart polecat!" and it was Jimmy's turn 
to laugh;  but Tommy retorted sturdily&mdash;

</p><p>"Oh, laugh if you like&mdash;but I'll <hi rend="italic">do</hi> it!"
</p><p>
It had such an assured and confident sound that it made 
an impression, and Jimmy asked, gravely&mdash;
</p><p>
"Do you know the Emperor?"
</p><p>
"Do <hi rend="italic">I</hi> know him?  Why, how you talk!  Of course I don't."
</p><p>
"Then how'll you do it?"
</p><p>
"It's very simple, and very easy.  Guess.  How would <hi rend="italic">you</hi> 
do it, Jimmy?"
</p><p>
"Send him a letter.  I never thought of it till this 
minute.  But I'll bet that's your way."
</p><p>
"I'll bet it ain't.  Tell me&mdash;how would you send it?"
</p><p>
"Why, through the mail, of course."
</p><p>
Tommy overwhelmed him with scoffings, and said&mdash; 

</p><p>
"Now don't you suppose every crank in the Empire is doing 
the same thing?  Do you mean to say you haven't thought of 
that?"
</p><p>
"Well  no," said Jimmy, abashed.
</p><p>
"You <hi rend="italic">might</hi> have thought of it, if you weren't so young 
and inexperienced.  Why Jimmy, when even a common <hi rend="italic">General</hi>, 
or a poet, or an actor, or anybody that's a little famous 
gets sick, all the cranks in the kingdom load up the mails 
with certain-sure quack-cures for him.  And so, what's bound 
to happen when it's the Emperor?"
</p><p>
"I suppose it's worse," said Jimmy, sheepishly.
</p><p>
"Well, I should think so.  Look here, Jimmy, every single 
night we cart off as many as six loads of that kind of letters 
from the back yard of the palace where they're thrown.  Eighty 
thousand letters in one night!  Do you reckon anybody reads 
them?  Sho!  not a single one.  It's what would happen to your 
letter if you wrote it&mdash;which you won't, I reckon?"
</p><p>
"No," sighed Jimmy, crushed.
</p><p>
"But it's all right, Jimmy, don't you fret, there's more 
than one way to skin a cat: <hi rend="italic">I'll</hi> get the word to him."
</p><p>
"Oh, if you only <hi rend="italic">could</hi>, Tommy!  I should love you for 
ever!"
</p><p>
"I'll do it, I tell you.  Don't you worry; you depend 
on me."
</p><p>
"Indeed I will, Tommy, for you do know so much.  You're 
not like other boys;  they never know anything.  How'll you 
manage, Tommy?"
</p><p>
Tommy was greatly pleased.  He settled himself for reposeful 
talk, and said&mdash;
</p><p>
"Do you know that ragged poor thing that thinks he's a 
butcher because he goes around with a basket and sells cat's-meat 
and rotten livers?  Well, to begin with, I'll tell <hi rend="italic">him</hi>."
</p><p>
Jimmy was deeply disappointed and chagrined, and said&mdash;
</p><p>
"Now Tommy, it's a shame to talk so.  You know my heart's 
in it, and it's not right."
</p><p>
Tommy gave him a love-pat and said&mdash;
</p><p>
"Don't you be troubled, Jimmy, I know what I'm about. 
Pretty soon you'll see.  That half-breed butcher will tell 
the old woman that sells chestnuts at the corner of the lane&mdash;
she's his closest friend, and I'll ask him to.  Then&mdash;by 
request&mdash;she'll tell her rich aunt that keeps the little 
fruit shop on the corner, two blocks above;  and that one will 
tell her particular friend the man that keeps the game-shop, 
and he will tell his friend the sergeant of police, and the 
sergeant will tell his captain, and the captain will tell the 
magistrate, and the magistrate will tell his brother-in-law 
the county judge, and the county judge will tell the sheriff, 
and the sheriff will tell the Lord Mayor, and the Lord Mayor 
will tell the President of the Council, and the President of 
the Council will tell&mdash;"
</p><p>
"By George, but it's a wonderful scheme, Tommy!  How ever 
<hi rend="italic">did</hi> you&mdash;"
</p><p>
"&mdash;Rear Admiral, and the Rear will tell the Vice, and the 
Vice will tell the Admiral of the Blue, and the Blue will tell 
the Red, and the Red will tell the White, and the White will 
tell the First Lord of the Admiralty, and the First Lord will 
tell the Speaker of the House, and the Speaker&mdash;"
</p><p>
"Go it Tommy, you're 'most there!"
</p><p>
"&mdash;will tell the Master of the Hounds, and the Master will 
tell the Head Groom of the Stables, and the Head Groom will 
tell the Chief Equerry, and the Chief Equerry will tell the 
First Lord in Waiting, and the First Lord will tell the Lord 
High Chamberlain, and the Lord High Chamberlain will tell the 
Master of the Household, and the Master of the Household will 
tell the little pet page that fans the flies off the Emperor, 
and the page will get down on his knees and whisper it to his 
Majesty&mdash;and the game's made!"
</p><p>
"I've <hi rend="italic">got</hi> to get up and hurrah a couple of times, Tommy, 
it's the grandest idea that ever was.  What ever put it into 
your head?"
</p><p>
"Sit down and listen, and I'll give you some wisdom&mdash;
and don't you ever forget it as long as you live.  Now then, 
who is the closest friend you've got, and the one you couldn't 
and wouldn't ever refuse anything in the world to?"
</p><p>
"Why, it's you, Tommy&mdash;you know that."
</p><p>
"Suppose you wanted to ask a pretty large favor of the 
cat's-meat man.  Well, you don't know him, and he would tell 
you to go to thunder, for he is that kind of a person; but he 
is my next best friend after you, and would run his legs off 
to do me a kindness&mdash;<hi rend="italic">any</hi> kindness  he don't care what it is.
Now I'll ask you: Which is the most common-sensible&mdash;for you to go 
and ask him to tell the chestnut-woman about your watermelon 
cure, or for you to get me to do it for you?"
</p><p>
"To get you to do it for me, of course.  I wouldn't ever 
have thought of that, Tommy&mdash;it's splendid."
</p><p>
"It's a <hi rend="italic">philosophy</hi>, you see.  Mighty good word&mdash;and 
large.  It goes on this idea:  everybody in the world, little 
and big, has one <hi rend="italic">special</hi> friend, a friend that he's <hi rend="italic">glad</hi> to do 
favors to&mdash;not sour about it, but <hi rend="italic">glad</hi>&mdash;glad clear to the 
marrow.  And so I don't care where you start, you can get 
at anybody's ear that you want to  I don't care how low you 
are nor how high he is.  And it's so simple:  you've only to 
find the <hi rend="italic">first</hi> friend, that is all; that ends your part of the 
work; he finds the next friend himself, and that one finds the 
third, and so on, friend after friend, link after link, like a 
chain, and you can go up it or down it, as high as you like or 
as low as you like."
</p><p>
"It's just beautiful, Tommy."
</p><p>
"It's as simple and easy as A B C; but did you ever hear
of anybody trying it?  No, everybody is a fool.  He goes to a 
stranger, without any introduction, or writes a letter, 
and of course he strikes a cold wave&mdash;and serves him gorgeously 
right.  Now the Emperor don't know me, but that's no matter&mdash;
he'll eat his watermelon to-morrow.  You'll see.  Hi-hi&mdash;stop! 
It's the cat's-meat man.  Good-bye, Jimmy, I'll overtake him."
</p><p>
He did overtake him, and said&mdash;
</p><p>
"Say&mdash;will you do me a favor?"
</p><p>
<hi rend="italic">"Will</hi> I?  Well, I should <hi rend="italic">say</hi>!  I'm your man&mdash;name it, 
and see me fly!"
</p><p>
"Go tell the chestnut-woman to put down everything and 
carry this message to her first-best friend and tell the friend 
to pass it along."  He worded the message, and said, "Now 
then, rush!"
</p><p>
The next moment the chimney-sweep's word to the Emperor 
was on its way.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="3" id="d8">
<head>III.</head>

<p>The next evening, toward midnight, the doctors sat while whispering 
together in the imperial sick-room, and they were in 
deep trouble, for the Emperor was in very bad case.  They 
could not hide it from themselves that every time they emptied 
a fresh drugstore into him he got worse.  It saddened them, 
for they were expecting that result.  The poor emaciated 
Emperor lay motionless, with his eyes closed, and the page 
that was his darling was fanning the flies away and crying 
softly.  Presently the boy heard the silken rustle of a 
porti&egrave;re, and turned and saw the Lord High Great Master of 
the Household peering in at the door and excitedly motioning 
to him to come.  Lightly and swiftly the page tip-toed his 
way to his dear and worshipped friend the Master, who said&mdash;
</p><p>
"Only you can persuade him and oh, don't fail to do it! 
Take this&mdash;make him eat it, and he is saved."
</p><p>
"On my head be it.  He shall eat it!"
</p><p>
It was a couple of great slices of ruddy fresh watermelon. 

</p><p>
</p><p>
</p><p>
The next morning the news flew everywhere that the Emperor 
was sound and well again, and had hanged the doctors.  A wave 
of joy swept the land, and frantic preparations were made to 
illuminate.
</p><p>
After breakfast his Majesty sat meditating.  His gratitude 
was unspeakable, and he was trying to devise a reward 
rich enough to properly testify it to his benefactor.  He 
got it arranged in his mind, and called the page, and asked 
him if he had invented that cure.  The boy said no&mdash;he got 
it from the Master of the of the Household.
</p><p>
He was sent away, and the Emperor went to devising again. 
The Master was an Earl; he would make him a Duke, and give him 
a vast estate which belonged to a member of the Opposition.  
He had him called, and asked him if he was the inventor of 
the remedy.  But the Master was an honest man, and said he 
got it of the Grand Chamberlain.  He was sent away, and the 
Emperor thought some more.  The Chamberlain was a Viscount; 
he would make him an Earl, and give him a large income.  But 
the Chamberlain referred him to the First Lord in Waiting, 
and there was some more thinking.  His Majesty thought out a smaller 
reward.  But the First Lord in Waiting referred  him back 
further, and he had to sit down and think out a further and 
becomingly and suitably smaller reward.
</p><p>

Then,to break the tediousness of the inquiry and hurry the business, he
sent for the Grand High Chief Detective, and
commanded him to trace the cure to the bottom, so that he 
could properly reward his benefactor.
</p><p>
At nine in the evening the High Chief Detective brought 
the word.  He had traced the cure down to a lad named Jimmy, 
a chimney-sweep.  The Emperor said, with deep feeling&mdash;
</p><p>
"Brave boy, he saved my life, and shall not regret it!"
</p><p>
And sent him a pair of his own boots;  and the next best 
ones he had, too.  They were too large for Jimmy, but they 
fitted the Zulu, so it was all right, and everything as it 
should be.
</p>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
