<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="TwaPlym"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="TwaPlym"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Plymouth Rock and the Pilgrims</title>
<title type="sort">plymouth rock and the pilgrims</title>
<author>Twain, Mark, 1835-1910</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>  
<name>Stephen Railton</name>  
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>  
<name/>  
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>Text prepared by the 1997-98 J. Wallace Sieg Graduate Fellow Jennifer 
Easley for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">34</num> kilobytes</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>  
<idno type="ETC">TwaPlym</idno>  
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476427</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>  
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Plymouth Rock and the Pilgrims</title>
<title level="m">Mark Twain's Speeches</title>
<title type="sort">plymouth rock and the pilgrims</title>
<author>Mark Twain, pseud. Samuel Langhorne Clemens</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>  
<name/>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>17-24</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harper &amp; Brothers</publisher>  
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>  
<date value="1910">1910</date>  
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: PS1322.S5 1910</idno>
</publicationStmt>  
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>  
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>  
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>  
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>  
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>  
</encodingDesc>  
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1881">1881</date>
</creation>  
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>  
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; non-fiction</term>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
</profileDesc>  
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-09">September, 1997</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Jennifer Easley, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>  
 
<text id="d1"> 
<front id="d2"> 
<div1 type="preface" id="d3"> 
<head> 
<hi rend="bold">"I rise to protest"</hi> 
</head> 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">To me this speech, besides being my favorite, is the best 
performance to look at to see what MT could and couldn't achieve 
morally as a humorist.  It was delivered at the first annual 
dinner of Philadelphia's New England Society (the same kind of 
occasion as his 1882 toast "To Woman," although New York's New 
England Society was 77 years older).  The various New England 
Societies scattered across the country (there was even one in 
Charleston) met on the anniversary of the arrival of an 
immigrant group &mdash; the landing of the Pilgrims at Plymouth Rock 
&mdash; yet one of the forces behind the spread of these Societies 
throughout the nineteenth century was a reactionary resistance 
to the recurring waves of immigration from non-Anglo-Saxon 
ethnic groups.  While the many speakers at these annual dinners 
paid homage to the Pilgrim Fathers, their filio-piety also 
nurtured their self-righteous belief that the descendants of 
such fathers were the "true" America, the legitimate heirs to 
the nation's places of privilege, the guardians of American 
culture across the dislocations of space and time.</hi> 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="italic">This was a major theme of the keynote address at this 
dinner, as you can see by reading the account of the banquet 
from the</hi> Philadelphia Press<hi rend="italic">. MT gave his speech last, 
after a number of other toasts to New England and 
the "sons" who had gathered to pay homage to the legacy of the 
"fathers."  MT's speech was the only one to notice all the other 
native sons and daughters who had been excluded from the 
Society's version of America: native Americans, slaves, women 
and Others.  As with Huck Finn's voice, MT here chooses to 
occupy and speak from a place at the denigrated margins of 
society.  He re-views American history in a way that profoundly 
anticipates the revisionist historicism of our times.  But he 
does so always as a comedic performance.  As humor, this 
"protest" shocked and entertained its audience &mdash; at the same 
time.  When they stopped laughing, would the sons of the 
Puritans in his audience have felt the need to do anything else 
about the pattern of injustice M.T. articulates?</hi> 
</p> 
</div1> 
 
<div1 type="report" id="d4">  
<head> 
NEW ENGLAND'S SONS.<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic">FIRST FESTIVAL OF PENNSYLVANIA'S</hi><lb/> 
<hi rend="italic">PILGRIM DESCENDENTS</hi><lb/> 
A Notable Dinner at the Continental Hotel &mdash;<lb/> 
Addresses by President Rollins, Senator Frye,<lb/> 
Gov. Hoyt, President Hopkins, and Mark Twain. <lb/> 
from the Philadelphia Press,<lb/> 
23 December 1881 
</head> 
 
<note n="1"><p> 
<hi rend="italic">[This story, which included the complete text of MT's speech, 
occupied the lead position on page one. Reproduced here is about 
one-third of the article. Even this is long, but it provides a dramatic 
sense of the immediate context in which MT spoke his "protest."]</hi> 
</p></note> 
<p> 
The main dining-room of the Continental Hotel presented a 
beautiful and picturesque scene last night on the occasion of the First 
Annual Festival of the New England Society of Pennsylvania. The society 
was formed a few weeks since by residents of this city who are natives 
of or descendants from good old Puritan stock. The object of the 
association is good-fellowship and the honoring of a worthy ancestry, of 
which all the sons of New England are justly proud. The day fixed for 
the annual festival, the 22nd of December, is "Forefathers' Day," the 
anniversary of the landing of the Pilgrim Fathers. The society 
determined to make their first festival a notable one, and to that end 
invited many notable descendants of the Eastern States, who showed their 
appreciation by attending in person.  The dinner hour was fixed last 
evening at six o'clock, and notwithstanding the stormy weather, the 
members and guests began to arrive promptly on time. They were ushered 
into Parlor C, where the president of the society, E.A. Rollins, and 
Gov. Hoyt, a vice-president, held an informal reception. Never was there 
seen a more solid and respectable gathering of business men, leaders of 
the bench and bar, newspaper editors and proprietors, clergymen and 
college professors, all gathered to do honor to their native section of 
country.  The tall form of President Hopkins, of Williams College, was 
seen in the throng as he conversed with Admiral George H.  Preble. 
Senator Frye, of Maine, stood chatting with Governor Hoyt. Mark Twain 
stood in one corner uttering drolleries which caused his auditors to 
guffaw in a manner highly reprehensible in staid and sober citizens. 
John Welsh conversed with Frederick Fraley, and Rev. H.  Clay Trumbull, 
secretary of the society, darted hither and thither, arranging things 
generally for the event. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="bold">THE GENTLEMEN PRESENT.</hi>
</p><p> 
At seven o'clock the line was 
formed, and headed by President E.A.  Rollins and Professor Hopkins, of 
Williams College, the members and guests proceeded to the dining-room. 
President Rollins took his seat at the centre of the north table. On his 
right were Professor Hopkins, Professor Daniel E. Goodwin, D.D., LL. D., 
one of the society's vice-presidents; John Welsh, Rear-Admiral Geo. H. 
Preble, Frederick Fraley, Henry Winsor, Clayton McMichael, James L. 
Claghorn, Calvin Wells, of Pittsburg; Charles Emory Smith, of THE PRESS, 
and Rev. H. Clay Trumbull, secretary. On his left were Senator W.P. 
Frye, of Maine; Governor Hoyt, Samuel L. Clemens (Mark Twain), 
Lieutenant Thackara, U.S.N.; Rev. W.N.  McVickar, Judge Allison, Rev. 
George Dana, Boardman Chaplain, and Clarence H. Clark, treasurer of the 
society. 
</p><p> 
Among the other prominent persons seated at the tables 
were E. Dunbar Lockwood, who talked reform with Amos R. Little. H.W. 
Pitkin and other members of the Committee of One Hundred; Rev. Charles 
G. Amos, the noted Unitarian clergyman; Francis D.  Lewis, A.G.  Heaton. 
The Reading Railroad was represented by President Frank S. Bond, 
Secretary Kinsley, Receiver Stephen A. Caldwell, directors George F. 
Tyler, E.W. Clark, and the company attorneys, Samuel Dickson, Judge 
Asbhel Green, of New Jersey, the McCalmont brothers' counsel also 
chatted with the party.  Some of the others were: A.C.  Hetherington, 
General McCartney, E.P.  Borda, George Russell, H.W. Bartol, B.H. 
Atwood, N.P.  Storey, Joseph P.  Mumford, Dr. H.M. Howe, John P. Thayer, 
Sidney Tyler, Dr. Forrest, E.W.  Clark and B.B.  Comegys, the bankers, 
Chas. M. Jackson, C.A. Kingsbury, J.C. Collins, T.B. Merrick, Frank O. 
Allen, G.A. Bigelow, C.E. Morgan, Jr., Walter McMichael, Nelson F. 
Evans, C.F.  Richardson, G. Cornish, John Welsh Dulles, C.H. Brush, 
Robert N. Wilson, Walter H. Tilden, Charles P. Turner, Dr. J.F. Stone, 
and J.E. Graff. Altogether one hundred and fifty gentleman sat down. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="bold">THE BANQUETTING ROOM.</hi>
</p><p> 
The room was elegantly and most appropriately 
decorated. The chandeliers were festooned with smilax. Hanging-baskets 
were suspended along the walls and before the windows. At the eastern 
end of the room were stately palms, graceful camelias and rare plants 
perfuming the air with fragrance. A magnificent design composed of 
immortelles in red, yellow and purple, was prominent at this end of the 
hall. It bore in large letters the inscription: 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="center">December 22,<lb/> 1620-1881</hi> 
</p><p> Along the north 
end of the hall a long table was ranged, at which the officers and 
distinguished guests were seated as given above. Extending transversely 
from this were several other long tables, around which were placed the 
members. 
</p><p> 
Beside each plate lay a toast list, printed on 
hand-made paper of the style of two centuries ago.  There was also a 
menu of the most artistic and original design. It was printed in 
chocolate-colored ink, and bore on the first page a representation of 
the Mayflower making her perilous voyage, with the Pilgrim Fathers on 
board. On the last page was a portrait of John Alden's Priscilla, one of 
whose descedants was present at the festival.  The bill of fare was 
printed in antique type, and was as follows: 
</p>
<p> 
<hi rend="center"> 
THE FIRST ANNUAL FESTIVAL<lb/> 
&mdash;OF&mdash;<lb/> 
THE NEW ENGLAND SOCIETY<lb/> 
&mdash;OF&mdash;<lb/> 
PENNSILVANIA,<lb/> 
Thursday Eveninge, December 22, 1881.<lb/> 
YE LISTE OF DISHES FOR YE FESTIVAL.<lb/> 
Oysters from Chasepack Bay in their Shells.<lb/> 
Green Turtle Soupe.<lb/> 
Boyled Salmon with Sauce of Shrimps.<lb/> 
Cucumbers.<lb/> 
*Pates a la Reine.<lb/> 
Fillet of Beef Garnyshed with Mushrooms.<lb/> 
Roaste Turkey from Cape Cod, with Cranberries.<lb/> 
Potatoes. Strynge Beans. Pease.<lb/> 
Pork and Beans. Stewed Terrapin.<lb/> 
1620 1881<lb/> 
Sherbot. Cigarettes.<lb/> 
Canvas-back Duck. Partridge.<lb/> 
Lettuce Salading Dressed in Oyle.<lb/> 
Puddings with Plumbs.<lb/> 
Mince Pie. Pumpkin Pie.<lb/> 
Frozen Sweete Thynges, also Jellies and Cakes.<lb/> 
Several Sorts of Nuts and Fruits.<lb/> 
Coffee. 
</hi> 
</p>

<p> 
*Lyttle Pies such as the Queen of France doth love. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="bold">PRESIDENT ROLLINGS' ADDRESS.</hi>
</p><p> 
As soon as the members and guests reached their places President Rollins 
requested Rev. W.  Nelson McVikar to offer up prayer, which he did in an 
impressive manner.  The dinner was then served and full justice done to 
it. After an unlucky member had been threatened with expulsion because 
he preferred stewed terrapin to pork and beans President Rollins arose 
to welcome those present. He stood in an easy, graceful attitude, and 
spoke without using notes. His neat, humorous remarks were frequently 
interrupted by loud laughter and his patriotic sentiments were heartily 
applauded. He spoke as follows: 
</p><p> 
Fathers, brothers, uncles, nephews, cousins, as descendants of New 
England, we are all relatives. I congratulate you heartily upon the 
comfortable landing we have made here this evening. Upon my honor I do 
half believe, that if the Pilgrim Fathers had known of this good 
hostelry with its canvas back and terrapin, they would themselves have 
landed here. But I will not do them this rank injustice &mdash; never were 
men lured less by love of pleasure or constrained by higher motives. 
</p><p> 
We here in Philadelphia, in connection with local politics, have heard 
much of a Committee of a Hundred, but that Committee of a Hundred men, 
women and children which sailed from Plymouth, in September, 1620, and 
which in journeying often, in perils of waters, in perils of their own 
countrymen, in perils by the heathen, in perils in the wilderness, in 
perils in the sea, in weariness and painfulness in watchings often, in 
hunger and thirst, in fastings often, in cold and nakedness, gave its 
politics to this North American continent, and for all time and through 
their descendants, largely to that of South America as well, was the 
grandest committee of which history has made record. 
</p><p> 
On the 22d of November, in the harbor of Provincetown, in the cabin of 
the Mayflower, they adopted their form of Government &mdash; signed their 
compact, and chose John Carver Governor.  At that election every man who 
was authorized to do so cast his ballot I believe &mdash; cast it once and 
had it counted. That was the New England "idea" and it remains so unto 
this day. 
</p><p> 
On Monday, the 22d of December, 261 years ago, when the sun had just 
entered its winter solstice and the days were the shortest and the 
nights the longest and the cold the bitterest of all the year, having 
rested Sunday that they might not descecrate it but keep it holy unto 
the Lord, the Pilgrims landed on Plymouth Rock, placed for their feet, 
apparently, by the hand of God himself, for their was not another like 
it &mdash; not of the same material even, for miles and miles &mdash; a stone of 
only a few tons weight &mdash; a few feet only this was, and this a 
stepping-stone &mdash; but not the philosopher's stone &mdash; nor the Moabite 
stone &mdash; nor Jacob's stone in the chapel of Ednam, the confessor in 
Westminster Abbey, on which the Kings of Scotland and afterwards the 
United Kingdom, have received their crowns for a thousand years, nor 
that wondrous stone, which travelers kiss, high up in Blarney Castle &mdash; 
not one or all of them together, have enriched this world so much as 
Plymouth Rock. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="center">THE COMPACT OF SELF-GOVERNMENT.</hi> 
</p><p> 
The compact which the Pilgrims signed, and with which they landed and 
under which they lived, and which they have transmitted to their 
children and their children's children, was that of self-government, the 
government of the people by the people for the people. Out of that grand 
principle the Constitution of the United States was builded and when in 
after years the rains descended, and the floods came, and the winds 
blew, and beat upon that house &mdash; it fell not, for it was founded upon a 
rock. My friends, here is a piece of Plymouth Rock, which was kindly 
given to me by an old resident of Plymouth, and now a member of this 
society and present with us, Mr. T.E. Cornish. For three and a half 
months from that landing and during all the perils and horrors of that 
awful winter the Mayflower rocked at anchor in the harbor, and when, on 
the 5th of April following, she 
<q> 
"Took the wind upon her quarter, and stood for the open Atlantic," 
</q> 
not one of the 100 pilgrims returned in her. 
</p><p> 
Why? 
</p><p> 
Possibly John Alden staid because of his Priscilla &mdash; mayhap also on her 
account. Miles Standish also and Priscilla may have stayed for both. In 
saying this I trust that our member, Mr.  Watters, would remember that I 
would not speak lightly of his country.  Probably, however, few were 
sea-sick coming over, and so wisely enough determined to make the rest 
of their earthly pilgrimage by land. But making due allowance for all 
this, when we remember that of the one hundred who were living in 
December almost one-half, from exposure and disease, were dead; that all 
the living who had strength enough gathered on the bluff and saw the 
little ship go back without one thought of going back themselves; that 
food, strength, health, life itself gave out, but courage, heroism, 
devotion to their great cause, never &mdash; we remember that not at 
Thermopylae, nor Marathon, nor Bannochburn, nor Marston Moor, nor any 
other battlefield, has the world witnessed such a marvelous exhibition 
of the grandeur of human nature as on that day at Plymouth. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="center">THE MARCH OF PIE.</hi> 
</p><p> 
Only six months and a little more and after that the Plymouth Colonists 
celebrate their first Thanksgiving. I don't know what pies they had nor 
what pork and beans on that occasion, but these things and Thanksgiving 
Day itself are the gift of the Pilgrims, and through their descendants 
they have spread all over the land. I think it was Mark Twain, and if it 
were not I hope nobody will correct me, who first called the attention 
of the moral and hygenic world to the great pie zone which then extended 
from about where we sit due west to the Pacific. North of it was one 
vast sea of pie. South of it there was not one sporadic pie, but the 
zone moved on and Sherman's triumphant march to the sea was not more 
certain and inevitable than the march of pie and beans from the Canadas 
to the Gulf. The Pilgrims' Thanksgiving has become the National festival 
of the mightiest, freest, and, thanking God, I believe most united 
people the sun shines on. 
</p><p> 
The hundred Pilgrims headed the procession of 20,000 English men and 
English women who came to New England in the next twenty years, and 
before the meeting of the Long Parliament, and there were only about a 
thousand afterwards for nearly one hundred and fifty years, nor until 
the Revolutionary War. Those 20,000 made New England what she was and 
largely what she is. As late as 1858 Dr. Palfrey in a carefully prepared 
statement in his first volume of the History of New England, in speaking 
of New Englanders and their modes says: "There is probably not a county 
in England occupied by a population of purer English blood than theirs, 
and I presume there is one-third of the people of these United States, 
wheresoever now residing, who could peruse this volume without reading 
the history of his own progenitors." 
</p><p> 
The sons of New England are scattered throughout our wide domain and 
everywhere they are at home: for over the home of every man in this 
broad land, seen or unseen, floats the dear old flag of his childhood. 
They have carried with them not alone a love for their peculiar food, 
and of their honored feast-day, but as well their enterprise, their 
courage and power of endurance, their school system and their high 
estimate of education, their conscience and their freedom to worship God 
according to its dictates, and their worship of Him also, and to-day the 
people of every State and territory, and every town and hamlet in these 
United States are a better people, and their Government is a better 
Government, because of the Pilgrim Fathers. To the casual observer it 
might seem that in something I have said, I have trenched somewhat upon 
the first subject in our intellectual menu, which is, "The Pilgrims and 
Their Creation, New England," but I haven't, for the subject is as 
inexhaustible as filial affection, and its aspects are as various and 
numberless as the leaves of an autumnal forest in the good old State of 
Maine. 
</p> 
<note n="2"><p> 
<hi rend="italic">[Between Rollins' address and MT's there were six toasts, mostly 
quoted in full:</hi><lb/> 
<hi rend="italic">"New England," given by Senator Frye;</hi><lb/> 
<hi rend="italic">"Pennsylvania," Governor Hoyt;</hi><lb/> 
<hi rend="italic">"The Army and Navy of the United States," Rear-Admiral George Henry 
Peble;</hi><lb/> 
<hi rend="italic">"New England and Education," Rev. Mark Hopkins;</hi><lb/> 
<hi rend="italic">"The Mission of New England," Rev. George Dana Boardman;</hi><lb/> 
<hi rend="italic">"The Press of New England," Charles Emory Smith.</hi><lb/> 
<hi rend="italic">There were humorous moments in all these toasts, though the dominant 
tone was sanctimonious. The account concluded with MT's address, introduced in 
this way:]</hi> 
</p></note> 
<p> 
<hi rend="bold">MARK TWAIN'S SPEECH.</hi> 
</p><p> 
Mr. Rollins said that the next speaker, while not born in New England, 
had done the best he could, for he had his children born there and thus 
had made himself a New England ancestor.  He thus introduced Mark Twain, 
who sat to the left of Governor Hoyt. Mr.  Clemens rose and in a 
peculiar, sleepy manner began his remarks by thanking the company for 
the deserved compliment to himself and to his posterity. "I shall 
continue to do my best," drawled out the speaker, who continued as 
follows: 
</p> 
</div1> 
</front> 
 
<body id="d5"> 
<div1 type="speech" id="d6"> 
<head> 
<hi rend="bold">PLYMOUTH ROCK AND THE PILGRIMS</hi><lb/> 
ADDRESS AT THE FIRST ANNUAL DINNER, N. E. SOCIETY<lb/> 
PHILADELPHIA, DECEMBER 22, 1881 
</head> 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">On calling upon Mr. Clemens to make response, President 
Rollins said:</hi> 
</p><p> 
<q><hi rend="italic">"This sentiment has been assigned to one 
who was never</hi> exactly<hi rend="italic"> born in New England, nor, perhaps, 
were any of his ancestors. He is not</hi> technically<hi rend="italic">, 
therefore, of New England descent. Under the painful 
circumstances in which he has found himself, however, he has 
done the best he could &mdash; he has had all his children born 
there, and has made of</hi> himself<hi rend="italic"> a New England 
</hi>ancestor<hi rend="italic">. He is a self-made man. More than this, and 
better even, in cheerful, hopeful, helpful literature he is of 
New England</hi> ascent<hi rend="italic">. To</hi> ascend<hi rend="italic"> there in anything 
that's reasonable is difficult, for &mdash; confidentially, with the 
door shut &mdash; we all know that they are the brightest, ablest 
sons of that goodly land who never leave it, and it is among and 
above</hi> them<hi rend="italic"> that Mr.  Twain has made his brilliant and 
permanent ascent &mdash; become a man of mark."</hi></q> 
</p><p> 
I RISE to protest. I have kept still for 
years, but really I think there is no sufficient justification 
for this sort of thing. What do you want to celebrate those 
people for ?-those ancestors of yours of 1620 &mdash; the 
<hi rend="italic">Mayflower</hi> tribe, I mean.  What do you want to celebrate 
<hi rend="italic">them</hi> for? Your pardon: the gentleman at my left assures 
me that you are not celebrating the Pilgrims themselves, but the 
landing of the Pilgrims at Plymouth Rock on the 22d of December. 
So you are celebrating their landing. Why, the other pretext was 
thin enough, but this is thinner than ever;  the other was 
tissue, tinfoil, fish-bladder, but this is gold-leaf. 
Celebrating their landing! What was there remarkable about it, I 
would like to know? What can you be thinking of? Why, those 
Pilgrims had been at sea three or four months. It was the very 
middle of winter: it was as cold as death off Cape Cod there. 
Why shouldn't they come ashore? If they <hi rend="italic">hadn't</hi> landed 
there would be some reason for celebrating the fact. It would 
have been a case of monumental leatherheadedness which the world 
would not willingly let die. If it had been <hi rend="italic">you</hi>, 
gentlemen, you probably wouldn't have landed, but you have no 
shadow of right to be celebrating, in your ancestors, gifts 
which they did not exercise, but only transmitted. Why, to be 
celebrating the mere landing of the Pilgrims &mdash; to be trying to 
make out that this most natural and simple and customary 
procedure was an extraordinary circumstance &mdash; a circumstance to 
be amazed at, and admired, aggrandized and glorified, at orgies 
like this for two hundred and sixty years &mdash; hang it, a horse 
would have known enough to land; a horse &mdash; Pardon again; the 
gentleman on my right assures me that it was not merely the 
landing of the Pilgrims that we are celebrating, but the 
Pilgrims themselves. So we have struck an inconsistency here one 
says it was the landing, the other says it was the Pilgrims. It 
is an inconsistency characteristic of your intractable and 
disputatious tribe, for you never agree about anything but 
Boston. Well, then, what do you want to celebrate those Pilgrims 
for? They were a mighty hard lot &mdash; you know it. I grant you, 
without the slightest unwillingness, that they were a deal more 
gentle and merciful and just than were the people of Europe of 
that day; I grant you that they are better than their 
predecessors. But what of that? &mdash; that is nothing. People 
always progress. You are better than your fathers and 
grandfathers were (this is the first time I have ever aimed a 
measureless slander at the departed, for I consider such things 
improper). Yes, those among you who have not been in the 
penitentiary, if such there be, are better than your fathers and 
grandfathers were; but is that any sufficient reason for getting 
up annual dinners and celebrating you?  No, by no means &mdash; by no 
means. Well, I repeat, those Pilgrims were a hard lot. They took 
good care of themselves, but they abolished everybody else's 
ancestors. I am a border-ruffian from the State of Missouri. I 
am a Connecticut Yankee by adoption. In me, you have Missouri 
morals, Connecticut culture; this, gentlemen, is the combination 
which makes the perfect man. But where are my ancestors? Whom 
shall I celebrate? Where shall I find the raw material? 
</p><p> 
My first American ancestor, gentlemen, was 
an Indian &mdash; an early Indian. Your ancestors 
skinned him alive, and I am an orphan. Not one 
drop of my blood flows in that Indian's veins today. I stand here, 
lone and forlorn, without an 
ancestor. They skinned him! I do not object 
to that, if they needed his fur; but alive, gentlemen &mdash; alive! 
They skinned him alive &mdash; and before 
company! That is what rankles. Think how he 
must have felt; for he was a sensitive person 
and easily embarrassed. If he had been a bird, 
it would have been all right, and no violence 
done to his feelings, because he would have been 
considered "dressed." But he was not a bird, 
gentlemen, he was a man, and probably one of 
the most undressed men that ever was. I ask 
you to put yourselves in his place. I ask it as a 
favor; I ask it as a tardy act of justice; I ask it 
in the interest of fidelity to the traditions of your 
ancestors; I ask it that the world may contemplate, 
with vision unobstructed by disguising 
swallow-tails and white cravats, the spectacle 
which the true New England Society ought to 
present. Cease to come to these annual orgies 
in this hollow modern mockery &mdash; the surplusage of 
raiment. Come in character; come in the 
summer grace, come in the unadorned simplicity, 
come in the free and joyous costume which your 
sainted ancestors provided for mine. 
</p><p> 
Later ancestors of mine were the Quakers William 
Robinson, Marmaduke Stevenson, et al. 
Your tribe chased them out of the country for their 
religion's sake; promised them death if they came 
back; for your ancestors had forsaken the homes 
they loved, and braved the perils of the sea, the 
implacable climate, and the savage wilderness, 
to acquire that highest and most precious of 
boons, freedom for every man on this broad 
continent to worship according to the dictates 
of his own conscience &mdash; and they were not going 
to allow a lot of pestiferous Quakers to interfere 
with it. Your ancestors broke forever the chains 
of political slavery, and gave the vote to every 
man in this wide land, excluding none! &mdash; none 
except those who did not belong to the orthodox 
church. Your ancestors &mdash; yes, they were a hard  
lot; but, nevertheless, they gave us religious 
liberty to worship as they required us to worship, 
and political liberty to vote as the church 
required; and so I the bereft one, I the forlorn one, 
am here to do my best to help you celebrate them 
right. 
</p><p> 
The Quaker woman Elizabeth Hooton was an 
ancestress of mine. Your people were pretty 
severe with her &mdash; you will confess that. But, 
poor thing! I believe they changed her opinions 
before she died, and took her into their fold; and 
so we have every reason to presume that when 
she died she went to the same place which your 
ancestors went to. It is a great pity, for she was 
a good woman. Roger Williams was an ancestor 
of mine. I don't really remember what your 
people did with him. But they banished him to 
Rhode Island, anyway. And then, I believe, 
recognizing that this was really carrying harshness 
to an unjustifiable extreme, they took pity 
on him and burned him. They were a hard lot! 
All those Salem witches were ancestors of mine! 
Your people made it tropical for them. Yes 
they did; by pressure and the gallows they made 
such a clean deal with them that there hasn't 
been a witch and hardly a halter in our family 
from that day to this, and that is one hundred 
and eighty-nine years. The first slave brought 
into New England out of Africa by your progenitors 
was an ancestor of mine &mdash; for I am of a 
mixed breed, an infinitely shaded and exquisite 
Mongrel. I'm not one of your sham meerschaums 
that you can color in a week. No, my complexion 
is the patient art of eight generations. Well, in 
my own time, I had acquired a lot of my kin &mdash; by 
purchase, and swapping around, and one way 
and another &mdash; and was getting along very well. 
Then, with the inborn perversity of your lineage, 
you got up a war, and took them all away from me. 
And so, again am I bereft, again am I forlorn; 
no drop of my blood flows in the veins of 
any living being who is marketable. 
</p><p> 
O my friends, hear me and reform! I seek 
your good, not mine. You have heard the speeches. 
Disband these New England societies &mdash; nurseries 
of a system of steadily augmenting laudation and 
hosannaing, which, if persisted in uncurbed, may 
some day in the remote future beguile you into 
prevaricating and bragging. Oh, stop, stop, 
while you are still temperate in your appreciation 
of your ancestors! Hear me, I beseech you; get 
up an auction and sell Plymouth Rock! The Pilgrims 
were a simple and ignorant race. They 
never had seen any good rocks before, or at least 
any that were not watched, and so they were excusable 
for hopping ashore in frantic delight and 
clapping an iron fence around this one. But you, 
gentlemen, are educated; you are enlightened; 
you know that in the rich land of your nativity, 
opulent New England, overflowing with rocks, 
this one isn't worth, at the outside, more than 
thirty-five cents. Therefore, sell it, before it is 
injured by exposure, or at least throw it open to 
the patent-medicine advertisements, and let it 
earn its taxes. 
</p><p> 
Yes, hear your true friend &mdash; your only true 
friend &mdash; list to his voice. Disband these societies, 
hotbeds of vice, of moral decay &mdash; perpetuators of 
ancestral superstition. Here on this board I see 
water, I see milk, I see the wild and deadly 
lemonade. These are but steps upon the downward 
path. Next we shall see tea, then chocolate, then 
coffee-hotel coffee. A few more years &mdash; all too 
few, I fear &mdash; mark my words, we shall have cider! 
Gentlemen, pause ere it be too late. You are on 
the broad road which leads to dissipation, physical 
ruin, moral decay, gory crime and the gallows! 
I beseech you, I implore you, in the name 
of your anxious friends, in the name of your suffering 
families, in the name of your impending 
widows and orphans, stop ere it be too late. Disband 
these New England societies, renounce these 
soul-blistering saturnalia, cease from varnishing 
the rusty reputations of your long-vanished 
ancestors &mdash; the super-high-moral old iron-clads of 
Cape Cod, the pious buccaneers of Plymouth 
Rock-go home, and try to learn to behave! 
However, chaff and nonsense aside, I think I 
honor and appreciate your Pilgrim stock as much 
as you do yourselves, perhaps; and I endorse and 
adopt a sentiment uttered by a grandfather of 
mine once &mdash; a man of sturdy opinions, of sincere 
make of mind, and not given to flattery. He 
said: "People may talk as they like about that 
Pilgrim stock, but, after all's said and done, it 
would be pretty hard to improve on those people; 
and, as for me, I don't mind coming out flatfooted 
and saying there ain't any way to improve on 
them &mdash; except having them born in Missouri!" 
</p> 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
