<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="TwaQuin"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="TwaQuin">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Arousing More Interest</title>
<title type="sort">arousing more interest</title>
<author>Twain, Mark, 1835-1910</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Steve Railton</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>J. Nathaniel Goldsmith, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">5</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">TwaQuin</idno>
<date value="2001">2001</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2001 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476428</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Arousing More Interest</title>
<title type="sort">arousing more interest</title>
<author>Mark Twain, pseud. Samuel Langhorne Clemens</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Quincy Herald</publisher>
<pubPlace>Quincy</pubPlace>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
<term>Mark Twain</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2001-07">July, 2001</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name/>
</respStmt>
<item/>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">
<div1 type="letter" id="d3">
<head>Arousing More Interest</head>

<p>JOHN SMITH, ESQ. &mdash;
Dear Sire: It gratifies me, more than tongue can express, to receive this kind attention at your
hand, and I hasten to reply to your flattering note.  I am filled with astonishment to find you here,
John Smith.  I am astonished, because I thought you were in San Francisco.  I am almost certain I
left you there.  I am almost certain it was you, and I know if it was not you, it was a man whose
name is similar.</p>

<p>I am surprised to find you here, John Smith.  And yet I ought not to be, either, because I
found you in New York, most unexpectedly; and I stumbled on you in Boston; and was amazed to
discover you in New Orleans; and thunderstruck to run across you in St. Louis.  You must
certainly be a sort of roving disposition, John Smith.  You certainly are, John, and you know that
a rolling stone gathers no moss.  And a rolling Smith never gathers any moss.  There is no real use
in anybody's gathering moss, John, because it isn't worth any more in the market than sawdust is,
and hardly as much &mdash; but then, if we want to get along pleasantly with the world, we must respect
the world's little whims and caprices; and you know that the world has a foolish prejudice in favor
of a man's gathering moss.  So you had better locate, John, and go to gathering some.  It is no 
credit to you, John Smith, that you are always sure to turn up wherever a man goes.  It may be &mdash;
no, it cannot be possible &mdash; that there are two John Smiths.  The idea is absurd.</p>

<p>However, I always liked you, Smith, and I am right glad to come across you again, moss or
no moss.  I am proud to be asked to lecture for you and shall always treasure the recollection of
that compliment with peculiar fondness; but you see I have already agreed to lecture for the
Encore Club, and so of course I have to decline your kind offer.  But do not let this provoke a
coolness, John; on the contrary, let it bind us together more tenderly than ever in the common
bonds of our rolling and mossless good fellowship.</p>

<p>Come to National Hall Tuesday night, 9th inst., John, and bring some of your relations.  I
would say bring all of them, John, and say it with all my heart, too, but the hall only covers one
acre of ground, and your Smith family is a large one, John.</p>

<closer>Yors tenderly,
<signed>MARK TWAIN</signed>
</closer>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
