<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="TwaRou2"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="TwaRou2">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Roughing It Lecture, version 2</title>
<title type="sort">roughing it lecture, version 2</title>
<author>Twain, Mark, 1835-1910</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Steve Railton</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>J. Nathaniel Goldsmith, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">37</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">TwaRou2</idno>
<date value="2001">2001</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2001 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476430</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Roughing It Lecture, version 2</title>
<title type="sort">roughing it lecture, version 2</title>
<author>Mark Twain, pseud. Samuel Langhorne Clemens</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The State Republican</publisher>
<pubPlace>Lansing, Michigan</pubPlace>
<date value="1871-12-21">21 December 1871</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
<term>Mark Twain</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2001-07">July, 2001</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name/>
</respStmt>
<item/>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">

<div1 type="section" id="d3">

<p>LADIES AND GENTLEMEN: By request, I will ask leave to introduce the lecturer 
of the evening, Mr. Clemens, otherwise Mark Twain &mdash; a gentleman whose great 
learning, whose historical accuracy, whose devotion to science, and whose 
veneration for the truth, are only equaled by his high moral character and 

his majestic presence. I refer in these vague and general terms to myself. 
I am a little opposed to the custom of ceremoniously introducing a lecturer
to an audience, partly because it seems to me that it is not entirely 
necessary, I would much rather make it myself. Then I can get in all the 
facts.</p>

<p>But it is not really the introduction that I care for &mdash; I don't care about
that &mdash; that don't discommode me &mdash; but it's the compliments that sometimes go 
with it. That's what <hi rend="italic">hurts</hi>. It would hurt anybody. The idea of a young lady 
being introduced into society as the sweetest singer or the finest 

conversationalist! You might as well knock her in the head at once. I never 
had but one public introduction that seemed to me just exactly the thing &mdash; an 
introduction brimful of grace. Why, it was a sort of inspiration. And yet the 
man who made it wasn't acquainted with me; but he was sensible to the backbone, 
and he said to me: "Now you don't want any compliments?" Of course I did not want 

any compliments at all. He said: Ladies and gentlemen &mdash; I shan't fool away any 
unnecessary time in this introduction. I don't know anything about this man; at 
least I only know two things: One is, that he has never been in the penitentiary; 
and the other is, I don't know why." Such an introduction as that puts a man at 
his ease right off.</p>

<p>I must not forget to make the announcement of the next lecture, the second of 
course, to be delivered by President Angell of the State University on Tuesday 
evening, the 26th of December. I don't know what his subject is going to be, but 
it will be good and well handled no doubt. In fact I forgot to ask what the 
subject is going to be.</p>

<p>Now when I first started out on this missionary expedition, I had a lecture
which I liked very well, but by-and-by I got tired of telling that same old 
stuff over and over again, and then I got up another lecture, and after that 
another one, and I am tired of that: so I just thought tonight I would try 
something fresh, if you are willing. I don't suppose you care what a lecturer 

talks about if he only tells the truth &mdash; at intervals. Now I have got a book in 
press (it will be out pretty soon), over 600 octavo pages, and illustrated after 
the fashion of the Innocents Abroad. Terms &mdash; however I am not around canvassing 
for the work. I should like to talk a little of that book to you tonight. It is
very fresh in my mind, as it is not more than three months since I wrote it. 
Say 30 or 40 pages &mdash; or if you prefer it the whole 600.</p>

<p>Ten or twelve years ago, I crossed the continent from Missouri to California,
in the old overland stagecoach, a good while before the Pacific Railway was built. 
Over 1,900 miles. It was a long ride, day and night, through sagebrush, over 
sand and alkali plains, wolves and Indians, starvation and smallpox &mdash; everything 

to make the journey interesting. Had a splendid time, a most enjoyable pleasure 
trip, in that old stagecoach. We were bound for Nevada, which was then a bran'
new Territory nearly or about as large as the state of Ohio. It was a desolate, 
barren, sterile, mountainous, unpeopled country, sagebrush and deserts of alkali.
You could scarcely cast your eye in any direction but your gaze would be met by
one significant object, and that was the projecting horns of a dried, shrunken 

carcass of an ox, preaching eloquent sermons of the hardships suffered by those 
emigrants, where a soil refused to clothe its nakedness, except now and then a 
little rill (or, as you might call it, a river) goes winding through the plain. 
Such is the Carson River, which clothes the valley with refreshing and fragrant 
hayfields. However, hay is a scant crop, and with all the importations from 

California the price of that article has never come under $300 per ton. In the 
winter the price reaches $800, and once went up to $1,200 per ton, and then the 
cattle were turned out to die, and it is hardly putting the figure too strong 
to say that the valleys were paved with the remains of these cattle.</p>

<p>It is a land where the winters are long and rigorous, where the summers are hot 
and scorching, and where not a single drop of rain ever falls during eleven 
tedious months; where it never thunders, and never lightens; where no river 

finds its way to the sea or empties its waters into the great lakes that have 
no perceptible outlet, and whose surplus waters are spirited away through 
mysterious channels down into the ground. A territory broad and ample, but 
which has not yet had a population numbering 30,000, yet a country that 
produced $20,000,000 of silver bullion in the year 1863, and produces $12,000,000 
to $16,000,000 every year, yet the population has fallen away until now it does 

not number more than 15,000 or 18,000. Yet that little handful of people vote 
just as strongly as they do anywhere, are just as well represented in the Senate 
of the United States as Michigan, or the great state of New York with her 
3,000,000 or 4,000,000 of people. That is equality in representation.</p>

<p>I spoke of the sagebrush. That is a particular feature of the country 
out there. It's an interesting sort of shrub. You see no other sort of 
vegetable, and clear from Pike's Peak to California's edge the sagebushes 
stand from three to six feet apart, one vast greenish-gray sea of sage brush. 
It was the emigrant's fast friend, his only resource for fuel. In its appearance
it resembles a venerable live oak with its rough bark and knotty trunk, 
everything twisted and dwarfed, covered with its thick foliage. I think the 

sagebrush are beautiful &mdash; one at a time is, anyway. Of course,
when you see them as far as the eye can reach, seven days and a half in the week, 
it is different. I am not trying to get up an excitement over sagebrush, but 
there are many reasons why it should have some mention from an appreciative 
friend. I grant you that as a vegetable for table use sagebrush is a failure. 
Its leaves taste like our ordinary sage; you can make sage tea of it; but 
anybody in this audience who has ever been a boy or a girl, or both, in a 
country where doctors were scarce and measles and grandmothers plenty, don't 
hanker after sage tea. And yet after all there was a manifest providence in 

the creation of the sagebrush, for it is food for the mules and donkeys, and 
therefore many emigrant trains are enabled to pull through with their loads 
where ox teams would lie down and die of starvation. That a mule will eat 
sagebrush don't prove much, because I know a mule will eat anything. He don't 
give the toss up of a copper between oysters, lead pipe, brick dust, or even 
patent office reports. He takes whatever he can get most of.</p>

<p>In our journey we kept climbing and climbing for I don't know how many days 
and nights. At last we reached the highest eminence &mdash; the extreme summit of the 
great range of the Rocky Mountains, and entered the celebrated South Pass. 
Now the South Pass is more suggestive of a straight road than a suspension 

bridge hung in the clouds though in one place it suggests the latter. One 
could look below him on the diminishing crags and canyons lying down, down, 
down, away to the vague plain below, with a crooked thread in it which was 
the road, and tufts of feathers in it which were trees &mdash; the whole country 
spread out like a picture, sleeping in the sunlight, and darkness stealing  
over it, blotting out feature after feature under the frown of a gathering 
storm &mdash; not a film or shadow to mar the spectator's gaze. I could watch that 

storm break forth down there; could see the lightnings flash, the sheeted 
rain drifting along the canyon's side, and hear the thunder crash upon crash 
reverberating among a thousand rocky cliffs. This is a familiar experience 
to traveling people. It was a miracle of sublimity to a boy like me, who 
could hardly say that he had ever been away from home a single day in his 
life before.</p>

<p>We visited Salt Lake City in our journey. Carson City, the capital of 
Nevada, had a wild harem-scarem population of editors, thieves, lawyers, 
in fact all kinds of blacklegs. Its desperadoes, gamblers, and silver 
miners went armed to the teeth, every one of them dressed in the roughest 
kind of costumes, which looked strange and romantic to me and I was 
fascinated.</p>

<p>Now, instead of making a tedious description, I will say that they 
had a curious and peculiar breed of horses out there. I will give you 
the main points in regard to a little personal adventure which I had 
with one of these horses, leaving your imaginations to do the rest. 
Everybody rode horseback there. They were most magnificent riders. I 
thought so at least. I soon learned to tell a horse from a cow, and I 
was just burning with impatience to learn more. I was determined to 

have a horse to ride, and just as the thought was rankling in my mind 
an auctioneer came along on a beast crying him for sale, going at 22, 22, 
horse, saddle, and bridle. I could hardly resist. There was a man standing 
there. I was not acquainted with him (he turned out to be the auctioneer's 
brother). He observed to me, "That is a remarkable horse to be going at that 
price." I said I had half a notion to buy it. He said: "I know that horse &mdash; know 
him perfectly well. You are a stranger, and you may think that he is an 
American horse. He's nothing of the kind; he's a genuine Mexican plug; 
that's what he is." Well, I didn't know what a "genuine Mexican plug" was, 

but there was something about that man's way of saying it that I made up my
mind to have that horse if it took every cent I had, and I said: "Has he 
any other advantages?" Well, he just hooked his forefinger into the breast 
pocket of my army shirt, led me off one side, and said in a low tone that 
no one else could hear, said: "He can outbuck any horse in this part of the
country. Yes," he repeated, "he can outbuck any horse in America." The 
auctioneer was crying him at 24, 24, going at 24. I said, 27 &mdash; "and sold." I took
the "genuine Mexican plug," paid for him, put him in the livery stable, 

had him fed, then I let him rest until after dinner, when I brought him out 
into the plaza, where some of the citizens held him by the head while others 
held him down by the tail, and I got on him. As soon as they had let go, he put 
all his feet together in a bunch. He let his back sag down and then he arched 
it suddenly and shot me 180 yards into the air. I wasn't used to such things, 
and I came down and lit in the saddle, then he sent me up again and this time 

I came down astride his neck, but I managed to slide backward until I got into
the saddle again. He then raised himself almost straight up on his hind
legs and walked around awhile, like a member of Congress, then he came down 
and went up the other way, and just walked about on his hands as a schoolboy 
would, and all the time kept kicking at the sky. While he was in this position

I heard a man say to another, "But don't he buck!" So that was "bucking." 
I was very glad to know it. Not that I was particularly enjoying it, but I was 
somewhat interested in it and naturally wanted to know what the name of it was. 
While this performance was going on, a sympathizing crowd had gathered around, 
and one of them remarked to me: "Stranger, you have been taken in. That's a genuine 

Mexican plug," and another one says: "Think of it! You might have bought 
an American horse, used to all kinds of work, for a very little more money." 
Well I didn't want to talk. I didn't have anything to say. I sat down. 
I was so jolted up, so internally, externally, and eternally mixed up, 
gone all to pieces. I put one hand on my forehead, the other on my stomach; 
and if I had been the owner of 16 hands I could have found a place for 
every one of them. If there is a Californian in this audience he knows 
what a Mexican plug is, and he knows that I have hardly exaggerated that 
exasperating creature.</p>

<p>Now if you would see the noblest, loveliest inland lake in the world, you 
should go to Lake Tahoe. It is just on the boundary line between California 
and Nevada. I have seen some of the world's celebrated lakes and they bear no 

comparison with Tahoe. There it is, a sheet of perfectly pure, limpid water, 
lifted up 6,300 feet above the sea &mdash; a vast oval mirror framed in a wall of snowclad
mountain peaks above the common world. Solitude is king, and in that realm 
calm silence is brooding always. It is the home of rest and tranquility and gives
emancipation and relief from the griefs and plodding cares of life. Could 
you but see the morning breaking there, gilding those snowy summits and 

then creeping gradually along the slopes until it sets, the lake and 
woodlands, free from mist, all agleam, you would see old Nature, the master 
artist, painting these dissolving views on the still water and finally 
grouping all these features into a complete picture. Every little dell, the 
mountains with their dome-turned pinnacles, the cataracts and drifting 
clouds, are all exquisitely photographed on the burnished surface of the 
lake, suffused with the softest and richest color. This lake is ten miles 
from Carson City, and in company with a friend we used to foot it out there, 

taking along provisions and blankets &mdash; camp out on the lake shore two or three 
weeks at a time; not another human being within miles of us. We used to loaf 
about in the boat, smoke and read, sometimes play seven-up to strengthen 
the mind. It's a sinful game, but it's mighty nice. We'd just let the boat drift
and drift wherever it wanted to. I can stand a deal of such hardship and 
suffering when I'm healthy. And the water was so wonderfully clear. 
Where it was 80 feet deep the pebbles on the bottom were just as distinct as 

if you held them in your hand; and in that clear white atmosphere it seemed 
as if the boat was drifting through the air. Out in the middle it was a deep 
dark indigo blue, and the official measurement made by the State Geologist 
of California shows it to be 1,525 feet deep in the center. You can imagine that 
it would take a great many churches and steeples piled one upon another before they 
would be perceptible above its surface. You might use up a great deal of 
ecclesiastical architecture in that way. Now, notwithstanding that lake is 

lifted so high up among the clouds, surrounded by the everlasting 
snowcapped mountain-peaks, with its surface higher than Mt. Washington in the 
East, and notwithstanding the water is pretty shallow around the edges, yet 
the coldest winter day in the recollection of humanity was never known to form 
ice upon its surface. It has no feeders but the little mountain rills, yet it 
never rises nor falls. Donar Lake, close by, freezes hard every 
winter.Why Lake Tahoe does not is a question which no scientist has ever been 
able to explain.</p>

<p>If there are any consumptives here I urge them to go out there, renew their 
age, make their bodies hale and hearty, in the pure, magnificent air of Lake 
Tahoe. If it don't cure you I'll bury you at my own expense. It will cure you. 
I met a man there &mdash; he had been a man once, but now he was only a shadow, and a 
very poor sort of shadow at that. That man took the thing very deliberately. He 

had fixed up things comfortable while he did stay, but he was in dead earnest. 
Thought he was going to die sure, but he made a sickly failure of it. He had 
brought along a plan of his private graveyard, some drawings of different kinds 
of coffins, and he never did anything but sit around all day and cipher over 
these plans, to get things to suit him, and try to find out which coffin 
would be the most becoming. Well, I met that man three months afterward. He was 
chasing mountain sheep over mountains seven miles high with a Sharp's rifle. 
He didn't get them, but he was chasing them just the same. He had used up his 

graveyard plans for wadding and had sent home for some more. Such a cure as 
that was! Why, when I first saw that man his clothes fitted him about as a 
circus tent fits the tentpole; now they were snug to him; they stuck to him 
like postage stamps, and he weighed a ton. Yes, he weighed more than a ton, 
but I will throw in the odd ounces, I'm not particular about that, eleven I 
think it was. I know what I am talking about, for I took him to the hay scales 
and weighed him myself. A lot of us stood on there with him. But I hope you 
won't mind my nonsense about it. It was really a wonderful cure, and if I can 

persuade any consumptive to go out there I shall feel at any rate that I have 
done one thing worth having lived to accomplish. And if there is a consumptive 
in this house I want to say to him: Shoulder your gun, go out there and hunt. 
It's the noblest hunting ground on earth. You can hunt there a year and never
find anything &mdash; except mountain sheep; but you can't get near enough to them to 
shoot one. You can see plenty of them with a spyglass. Of course you can't shoot 
mountain sheep with a spyglass. It is our American Shamwah (I believe that is 
the way that word is pronounced &mdash; I don't know), with enormous horns, inhabiting 
the roughest mountain fastnesses, so exceedingly wild that it is impossible to 

get within rifleshot of it. There was no other game in that country when I 
was there &mdash; except seven-up; though one can see a California quail now and then &mdash; 
a proud, stately, beautiful bird, with a curved and graceful plume on top of its 
head. But you can't shoot one. You might as well try to kill a cast-iron dog. 
They don't mind a mortal wound any more than a man would mind a scratch.</p>

<p>I had supposed in my innocence that silver mining was nice, easy business, 
and that of course all you had to do was to pick it up, and that you could tell 
it from any other substance on account of its brightness and its white metallic 
look. Then came my disenchantment; for I found that silver was merely scattered 
through quartz rock. Gold is found in cement veins, in quartz veins, loosely 

mingled with the earth, in the sand in beds of rivers, but I never heard of 
any other house or home for silver to live in than quartz rock. This rock is 
of a dull whitish color faintly marbled with blue veins. A fine powder of 
silver ore makes these blue veins and this yields $30 in bullion. A little 
dab of silver that I could crowd in my mouth came out of this 2,000 pounds of 
solid rock. I found afterward that $30 rock was mighty profitable. Then they 
showed me some more rock which was a little more clouded, that was worth $50 a

ton. The bluer and darker the rock the richer it was. Sometimes you could 
find it worth $400, $500, and $600 a ton. At rare intervals rock can be 
found that is worth $1,500 and $2,000 per ton, and at rarer intervals you 
would see a piece of quartz that had a mass of pure silver in its grip, 
large as a child's head &mdash; more than pure, because it always had a good deal 

of gold mixed up in its composition. The wire silver is Nature's 
aristocratic jewelry. The quartz crystallizes and becomes perfectly clear, 
just as clear and faultless as the diamond, and almost as radiant in beauty. 
Nature, down there in the depths of the earth, takes one of these quartz 
rocks, shapes a cavity, and right in its heart imprisons a delicate little 
coil of serpentine, pure white, aristocratic silver.</p>

<p>It was uphill work, this silver mining. There were plenty of mines but it 
required a fortune to work one; for tons of worthless rock must be ground to 
powder to get at the silver. I was the owner of a hundred silver mines, yet I 
realized that I was the poorest man on earth. Couldn't sell to anybody; 

couldn't pay my board; so I had to go to work in a quartz mill at ten dollars 
per week. I was glad to get that berth, but I couldn't keep it. I don't know 
why; I was the most careful workman they ever had. They said so. I took more 
pains with my work than anybody else. I was shoveling sand-tailings as they 
call it. It is silver bearing rock that has been ground up and worked over 

once. It is then saved and worked over again. I was so particular about it 
that I have sat still for one hour and a half and studied about the best way 
to shovel that sand; and if I couldn't cipher it out in my mind I wouldn't 
go shoveling around recklessly &mdash; I would leave it alone until the next day. 
Many a time when I have been carrying sand from one pile to another 30 or 40 

feet apart I would get started with a pailful when a splendid idea would 
strike me and I would carry that sand right back and sit down and think about 
it. Like as not I would get so absorbed in it as to go to sleep. I most always 
go to sleep when I am excited.</p>

<p>I knew there was a tiptop splendid way to move that sand from one pile to 
another and I told the boss so. "Well," he replied, "I am all-fired glad to 
hear it," and you never saw a man so kind of uplifted as he was. He seemed as 
if a load had been lifted from his breast &mdash; a load of sand.</p>

<p>I said to him: "What you want now is to get a cast-iron pipe about 14 
feet in diameter &mdash; boiler iron will do &mdash; and about 42 feet long. Have one end 
raised up 35 or 40 feet, and then you want to have a revolving belt. Work 
it with the waste steam from the engine. Have a chair fastened to that 
belt and let me sit in that chair. Have a Chinaman to load up that big box, 

pass it to me as I come around, and I will up it into that pipe." You never 
saw a man so overcome with admiration. He discharged me on the spot. He 
said I had too much talent to be fooling away my time in a quartz mill.</p>

<p>If you will permit me, I would like to illustrate the ups and downs of 
fortune in the mining country with just a little personal experience of my
own. I had a cabinmate by the name of Higby &mdash; a splendid good fellow. One 
morning the camp was thrown into a fearful state of excitement, for the 

"Wide West" had struck a lead black with native silver and yellow with 
gold. The butcher had been dunning us a week or two. Higby went up and 
brought a handful away and he sat studying and examining it, now and then 
soliloquizing in this manner: "That stuff never came out of the Wide West 
in the world." I told him it did, because I saw them hoist it out of the 

shaft. Higby went away by himself, and came back in a couple of hours 
perfectly overcome with excitement. He came in, closed the door, went and 
looked out of the window to make sure there was nobody in the neighborhood, 
and said to me, "We are worth a million of dollars. The Wide West be 
hanged &mdash; that's a blind lead." Said I: "Higby, are you <hi rend="italic">really</hi> in earnest? 
Say it again: say it strong, Higby." He replied: "Just as sure as I am 

standing here, it's a blind lead. We're rich." Poverty had vanished and 
we could buy that town and pay for it, and six more just like it. A blind
lead is one that doesn't crop out above the ground like an ordinary quartz
lead. The Wide West had simply tapped it in their shaft and we had discovered
it. It belonged to us. It was our property and there wouldn't anybody in 
the camp dispute that fact. We took into partnership the foreman of the 

Wide West, and the Wide West had to stop digging. We were the lions of 
Esmeralda. People wanted to lend us money; other people wanted to sell 
us village lots on time; and the butcher brought us meat enough for a 
barbecue and went away without his pay.</p>

<p>Now there is a rule that a certain amount of work must be done on a new 
claim within the first ten days, or the claim is forfeited to any one who 
may first take it up. Now I was called away to nurse an old friend who was 
dangerously ill up at the Nine Mile Ranch, and I just wrote a note and threw 
it into the window telling Higby where I was gone. The fellow I went to nurse 

was an irascible sort of fellow, and while carrying him from the vapor bath 
because I let my end of him fall we had a quarrel and I started for home. 
When I reached there, I saw a vast concourse of people over at the claim 
and the thought struck me that we were richer than ever, probably worth two 
million certain. Presently I met Higby looking like a ghost, and says I: 

"What on earth is the matter." "Well," he says, "you didn't do the work on 
the mine. I depended on you. The foreman's mother dying in California, he 
didn't do the work, our claim is forfeited and we are ruined. We haven't a 
cent." We went home to the cabin. I looked down at the floor. There was my 
note, and beside it was a note from Higby, telling me that he was going 
away to look for another mine which wouldn't have amounted to anything even 
if he had found it, in comparison with our claim.</p>

<p>It don't seem possible that there could be three as big fools in one 
small town, but we were there, and I was one of them. For once in my life 
I was absolutely a millionaire for just ten days by the watch.  I was just 
ready to go into all kinds of dissipation and I am really thankful that 

this was a chapter in the history of my life, although at the time of 
course I did a great deal of weeping and gnashing my teeth. When I lost 
that million my heart was broken and I wanted to pine away and die, but 
I couldn't borrow money enough to live on while I did so, and I had to 
give that up. Everything appeared to go against me. Of course, I might 
have suicided, but that was kind of disagreeable.</p>

<p>I had written a few letters for the press, and just in the nick of time 
I received a letter from the Virginia City <hi rend="italic">Daily Enterprise</hi> offering me $25
a week to go and be a reporter on that paper. I could hardly believe it, 
but this was no time for foolishness and I was in for anything. I never 

had edited anything, but if I had been offered the job of translating 
Josephus &mdash; from the original Hebrew &mdash; I should have taken it. If I had 
translated Josephus I would have thrown in as many jokes as I could for 
the money and made him readable. I would have had a variety, if I had 
to write him all up new.</p>

<p>Well, I walked that 130 miles in pretty quick time and took the berth. 
Have you ever considered what straits reporters are sometimes pushed to
in furnishing the public with news? Why, the first day items were so 
scarce, I couldn't find an item anywhere and just as I was on the verge
of despair, as luck would have it, there came in a lot of emigrants 
with their wagon trains. They had been fighting with the Indians and 

got the worst of it. I got the names of their killed and wounded, and 
then by-and-by there was another train came in. They hadn't had any 
trouble and of course I was disappointed, but I did the best I could 
under the circumstances. I cross-questioned that boss emigrant and 
found that they were going right on through and wouldn't come back 
to make trouble, so I got his list of names and added to my killed 
and wounded, and I got ahead of all the other papers. I put that 
wagon train through the bloodiest Indian fight ever seen on the 
plains. They came out of the conflict covered with glory. The chief 
editor said he didn't want any better reporter than I was. I said: 

"You just bring on your Indians and fetch out your emigrants, leave 
me alone, and I will make the fur fly. I will hang a scalp on every 
sagebush between here and the Missouri border." That was all first 
rate, but by-and-by items got low again and I was downhearted. I was 
miserable, because I couldn't strike an item. At last fortune favored 
me again. A couple of dear delightful desperadoes got into a row right 
before me and one of them shot the other. I stepped right up there and 
got the victim to give me his last words exclusively for the Enterprise, 

and I added some more to them so as to be sure and get ahead of the 
other papers, and then I turned to the desperado. Said I, "You are a 
stranger to me, sir, but you have done me a favor which I can never 
sufficiently thank you for. I shall ever regard you as a benefactor." 
And I asked him if he could lend me half a dollar. We always borrowed 
a piece whenever we could &mdash; it was a public custom. The thought then 
struck me that I could raise a mob and hang the other

desperado, but the officers got ahead of me and took him into custody. 
They were down on us and would always do any little mean thing like 
that, to spite us. And so I was fairly launched in literature, in the 
business of doing good. I love to do good. It is our duty. I think 
when a man does good all the time his conscience is so clear. I like 
to do right and be good, though there is a deal more fun in the other 
thing.</p>

<p>Now you see by my sort of experience a man may go to bed at night not 
worth a cent and wake up in the morning to find himself immensely wealthy, 
and very often he is a man who has a vast cargo of ignorance. To illustrate 
my point I will give you a story about a couple of these fresh nabobs 

whose names were colonels Jim and Jack. Colonel Jim had seen considerable 
of the world, but Colonel Jack was raised down in the backwoods of Arkansas. 
These gentlemen after their good luck suddenly determined on a pleasure 
trip to New York; so they went to San Francisco, took a steamer, and in 
due time arrived in the great metropolis. While passing along the street, 
Colonel Jack's attention was attracted by the hacks and splendid equipages 
he saw, and he says: "Well I've heard about these carriages all my life 
and I mean to have a ride in one. I don't care what it costs." So Colonel 
Jim stepped to the edge of the sidewalk and ordered a handsome carriage. 

Colonel Jack says: "No, you don't. None of your cheap turnouts for me. 
I'm here to have a good time, and money's no object. I'm going to have 
the best rig this country affords. You stop that yellow one there with 
the pictures on it." So they got into the empty omnibus and sat down. 
Colonel Jack says: "Well! ain't it gay? Ain't it nice? Windows and pictures 
and cushions, till you can't rest. What would the boys think of this if 
they could see us cut such a swell in New York? I wish they could see us. 
What is the name of this." Colonel Jim told him it was a barouche. After

a while he poked his head out in front and said to the driver, "I say, 
Johnny, this suits me. We want this shebang all day. Let the horses go."
The driver loosened the strap and passed his hand in for the fare. 
Colonel Jack, thinking that he wanted to shake hands, shook him heartily
and said: "You understand me. You take care of me and I'll take care 
of you." He put a $20 gold piece into the driver's hand. The driver 
says: "I can't change that." Colonel Jack replied: "Put it into your 
pocket, I don't want any change. We're going to ride it out." In a few

minutes the bus stopped and a young lady got in. Colonel Jack stared 
at her. Pretty soon she got out her money to pay the driver. Colonel 
Jack says: "Put up your money, Miss; you are perfectly welcome to ride 
here just as long as you want to, but this barouche is chartered and 
we can't let you pay." Soon an old lady got in. Colonel Jack told her 
to "sit down. Don't be at all uneasy, everything is paid for and as 
free as if you were in your own turnout, but you can't pay a cent." 
Pretty soon two or three gentlemen got in, and ladies with children.</p>

<p>Colonel Jack says, "Come right along. Don't mind  us. Free blowout." 
By and by the crowd filled all the seats and were standing up, while 
others climbed up on top. He nudged Colonel Jim and says: "Colonel, what 
kind of cattle do they have here? If this don't bang anything I ever saw. 
Ain't they friendly, and so awful cool about it, but they ain't sociable." 
But I have related enough of that circumstance to illustrate the enormous 
simplicity of these unfledged biddies of fortune.</p>

<p>When I told the chairman of the society this evening that I wanted to 
change my subject he said it was a little risky; he didn't know about it, 
but I pleaded so hard and said the only reason was I didn't want to talk 
that Artemus Ward lecture because it had been printed in the papers. I told 
him that I	would put in a little scrap from that Artemus Ward lecture, 
just enough to cover the advertisement, and then I wouldn't be telling any 
lies. Besides this anecdote had a moral to it. Well, the moral got him.</p>

<p>As nearly as I can cipher it out, the newspaper reporter has got us 
lecturers at a disadvantage. He can either make a synopsis or do most 
anything he wants to. He ought to be generous, and praise us or abuse us,
but not print our speeches. Artemus Ward was bothered by a shorthand 
reporter and he begged him not to do him the injustice to garble his 

speech. He says, "You can't take it all down as I utter it." The 
reporter said, "If you utter anything I can't take down I will 
agree not to print the speech." Along in	the lecture he tipped 
the reporter the wink and then he told the following anecdote:</p>

<p>(Whistle wherever the stars occur. If you can't, get somebody 
that can.)</p>

<p>He said that several gentlemen were conversing in a hotel parlor
and one man sat there who didn't have anything to say. By and by, 
the gentlemen all went out except one of the number and the silent 
man. Presently the silent man reached out and touched the gentleman
and says: "** I think, Sir, I	have seen you somewhere before. I am

not ** sure where it was or ** when it was ** but I know I have 
seen you,"	The gentleman says: "Very likely: but what do you 
whistle for?"	** I'll tell you all about it ** I used to 
stammer ** fearfully and I courted a **	girl ** and she 
wouldn't ** have me because I was afflicted with such an **
infirmity. I went to a doctor and ** he ** told me that every 
time I went to stammer ** that I must whistle, which I	did, 

and it completely cured me. But don't you know that ** girl **
wouldn't have me at last, for she ** said that **she wouldn't
talk to a man that whistled as I did. ** She'd as soon hold a 
conversation with a wheelbarrow that wanted ** greasing."</p>

<p>Ladies and gentlemen, For three or four days I have had it in my 
mind to throw away that other lecture, but I never had the pluck to 
do it until tonight.  The audience seemed to look friendly, and as 
I had been here before I felt a little acquainted.  I thought I 
would make the venture.  I sincerely thank you for the help you 
have given me, and I bid you goodnight.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
