<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="TwaRou1"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="TwaRou1">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Roughing it Lecture, version 1</title>
<title type="sort">roughing it lecture, version 1</title>
<author>Twain, Mark, 1835-1910</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Steve Railton</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>J. Nathaniel Goldsmith, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">29</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">TwaRou1</idno>
<date value="2001">2001</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2001 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476429</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Roughing it Lecture, version 1</title>
<title type="sort">roughing it lecture, version 1</title>
<author>Mark Twain, pseud. Samuel Langhorne Clemens</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Chicago Tribune</publisher>
<pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
<date value="1871-12-20">20 December 1871</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
<term>Mark Twain</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2001-07">July, 2001</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name/>
</respStmt>
<item/>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="article" id="d3">
<head>The Chicago Tribune<lb/>
20 December 1871<lb/>
[<hi rend="italic">Transcribed text of MT lecture, given 18 December 1871.</hi>]<lb/>
"MARK TWAIN."<lb/>
Sketch of the Great American Humorist's Lecture, 
Delivered in the Michigan Avenue Baptist Church &mdash;
An Original Introduction &mdash; Mark's Experience with
a "Genuine Mexican Plug" &mdash; Reportorial Experience
at Virginia City &mdash; Remarkable Exploits as a Duellist.</head>

<div2 type="introduction" id="d4">

<p>"Mark Twain" delivered his new lecture, which contains his Nevada experience, on 
Monday evening at the Michigan Avenue Baptist Church, and last evening at the Union 
Park Congregational Church. Both places were crowded. Mr. Clemens is a youngish looking 
man of perhaps thirty-five, not handsome, but having a bright, intelligent look, 
and an eye with a humorous twinkle that put him at once <hi rend="italic">en rapport</hi> with an
audience. There is nothing finical about his style of dress. He is clean shaven, 
and his manner of wearing his hair, which is abundant, shows that he is his own 
tonsorial artist. His clothing, upon the platform, was, on Monday evening, a black 
suit, the upper garment being a black frock coat, closely buttoned. His style of
oratorical delivery is like that of Artemas Ward. He has the same dry, hesitating,
stammering manner, and his face, aside from the merry light in his eyes, is as grave
and solemn as the visage of an undertaker when screwing down a coffin-lid. He always
introduces himself, for reasons which he gives his audiences. On Monday night he
prefaced his lecture with the following remarks:</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" id="d5">

<p>LADIES AND GENTLEMEN. By request of the Chairman of the committee, who has been 
very busy, and is very tired, I suppose, I ask leave to introduce to you the lecturer 
of the evening, Mr. Clemens, otherwise Mark Twain, a gentleman whose great learning, 
whose historical accuracy, whose devotion to science, and whose veneration for the 
truth [laughter] are only equalled by his moral character and his majestic presence. 
[Renewed laughter.] I refer these vague general terms to myself. [Giggling.] I am a 

little opposed to the custom of ceremoniously introducing the lecturer to the audience, 
because it seems to me unnecessary where the man has been properly advertised [laughter], 
and besides it is very uncomfortable for the lecturer. But where it is the custom, an 
introduction ought to be made, and I had rather make it myself in my own case, and then 
I can rely on getting in all the facts. [Continued laughter.] It is not a simple 
introduction that I mind. I don't really care for that at all, but it is the 

compliments that sometimes go with it &mdash; that is what hurts. It would make anyone 
uncomfortable. You can fancy a young lady introduced to a parlor-full of company 
as the best conversationalist, the best model in every way in her section of the 
country. You might just as well knock her in the head. She could not say a word the 
rest of the evening.</p>

<p>I never had but one public introduction that seemed exactly the thing; that 
seemed to be a very inspiration in the way of an introduction. The gentleman had 
a good head, and he said he supposed I didn't want any compliments. I said he was 
exactly right, I didn't want any compliments. And when he introduced me he said, 

"Ladies and gentlemen, I shall not waste any unnecessary time in the introduction. 
I don't know anything about this man; [laughter] at least I only know two things 
about him; one is that he has never been in the Penitentiary, and the other is I 
can't imagine why." [Prolonged laughter.] Now such an introduction puts a man right 
at ease. [Laughter.] </p>

<p>The speaker alluded to the various lectures which he had delivered the present 
season. He had prepared several; got tired of them, and cast them aside. He really 
supposed that his audience didn't care what the lecturer talked about. [Laughter.] 
The present address was part of a volume of 600 octavo pages, now in press, which 

detailed his experience in Nevada. He would give them thirty or forty pages of it, 
or the whole 600, just as they preferred. "There's nothing mean about me," said Mark, 
with a sudden flush of innocence. </p>

<p>He then proceeded to describe an overland trip as it was twelve or fifteen years 
ago, before the days of Pacific railroads. He and his party were bound for Nevada. 
A description of that territory followed, with the characteristics of soil, climate, 

productions which it presents, and the peculiarities of life and population which it 
there presented. Its mountains, its valleys, its cloudless skies, were all well 
depicted. The Territory never has possessed 30,000 inhabitants, and yet it sends 
two senators to Congress, and has all the national influence that attends upon a 
Commonwealth. Equal representation was something which he believed one's ancestors 

contended for at the time of the revolution, although he was not certain, not having 
been present. He spent considerable time while in Nevada, at Carson City. Here he had 
a peculiar adventure, which was given to the audience in the form of a narrative. We 
give it nearly in the speaker's own words: </p>

<p>Everybody rode horseback in that town. I never saw such magnificent horsemanship as 
that displayed in Carson streets every day, and I did envy them, though I was not much 
of a horseman. But I had soon learned to tell a horse from a cow [laughter], and was 
burning with impatience	to learn more.	I was determined to have a horse and ride 

myself. Whilst this thought was rankling in my mind, the auctioneer came scouring 
through the plaza on a black beast, that was humped, and &mdash; like a dromedary, 
and fearfully homely. He was going at "twenty, twenty-two-two dollars, for horse, 
saddle, and bridle." </p>

<p> A man standing near me &mdash; whom I didn't know, &mdash; but who turned out to be the 
auctioneer's brother, noticed the wistful look in my eye, and observed that that 
was a remarkable horse to be going at such a price, let alone the saddle and 
bridle. I said I had half a notion to bid.  "Now," he says, "I know that horse. 

I know him well. You are a stranger, I take it. You might think he is an American 
horse, but he is not anything of the kind. He is a Mexican plug &mdash; that's what he 
is &mdash; a genuine Mexican plug," but there was something else about that man's way of 
saying it, that made me just determine that I would own a genuine Mexican plug &mdash; if 
it took every cent I had. And I said, "Has he any other advantages?" He hooked 

his forefinger in the locket of my army shirt and led me to one side, and uttered, 
"Sh! don't say a word! He can outbuck any horse in America; he can out-buck 
any horse in the world" [laughter.] Just then the auctioneer came along. 
"Twenty-four, twenty-four dollars, for the horse, saddle. and bridle." I said 
"Twenty-seven!" "Sold." [laughter.] </p>

<p>I took the genuine Mexican plug, paid for him, put him in a livery stable, let 
him get something to eat, and get rested, and then in the afternoon I brought him 
out in the plaza, and some of the citizens held him by the head, and others held 
him down to the earth by the tail, and I got on him. And as soon as those people 

let go [laughter], he put all his feet in a bunch together, let his back sag 
down, and then he arched it up [laughter] suddenly [laughter], and shot me one 
hundred and eighty yards [great laughter]; and I came down again, straight down, 
and lighted in the saddle, and went up again. And when I came down the next time I
lit on his neck, and seized him, and slid back into the saddle, and held on. Then he 
raised himself straight up in the air on his hind feet, and just stepped around like 
a member of Congress [convulsive laughter], and then he came down and went up the 

other way, and just walked around on his hands, just as a schoolboy would. Then he 
came down on all fours again with the same old process of shooting me up in the 
air, and the third time I went up I heard a man say "O, don't he buck!"
[Loud laughter.] So that was "bucking." I was very glad to know it. Not that I 
was enjoying it, but then I had been taking a general sort of interest in it 
[laughter], and had naturally desired to know what the name of it was. And whilst 
I was up somebody hit the horse a whack with a strap, and when I got down again the 
genuine bucker was gone. [Roars of laughter.] </p>

<p> At this point of the interesting scene, a kindhearted stranger came to the rider, 
told him that he had been taken in, explained the mysterious terms, and gave him the 
comforting information that anybody in town could have told him all about the 
horse if he had inquired. </p>

<p> A description of Lake Tahoe followed, which showed considerable literary skill. 
This is a sheet of water, beautifully clear and deep, which never freezes, and has 
wonderful curative properties. </p>

<p> The mining adventures of the speaker, with his hopes, fears, poverty, and 
afflictions, were detailed at some length. Minute descriptions were given of 
the silver mines, the appearance of the various ores, and the ups and downs 

of mining life. But, quite unexpectedly, he received an invitation one day from 
a newspaper in Virginia City, with which he had been corresponding, to come 
and be a reporter on that journal, at a salary of $25 a week in gold. He went, 
and remained three years. The life of a reporter was described in the following 
terms: </p>

<p> I reported on that morning newspaper three years, and it was pretty hard work. 
But I enjoyed its attractions. Reporting is the best school in the world to get a 
knowledge of human beings, human nature, and human ways. A nice, gentlemanly  
reporter &mdash; I make no references &mdash; is well treated by everybody. Just think of the wide 
range of his acquaintanceship, his experience of life and society! No other 

occupation brings a man into such familiar sociable relations with all grades and 
classes of people. The last thing at night &mdash; midnight &mdash; he goes browsing around after 
items among police and jail-birds, in the lock-up, questioning the prisoners, and 
making pleasant and lasting friendships with some of the worst people in the world. 
[Laughter.] And the very next evening he gets himself up regardless of expense, 
puts on all the good clothes his friends have got &mdash; [laughter] goes and takes dinner 

with the Governor or the Commander-in-Chief of the District, the United States 
Senator, and some more of the upper crust of society. He is on good terms with 
all of them, and is present at every public gathering, and has easy access to every 
variety of people. Why I breakfasted almost every morning with the Governor, dined
with the principal clergyman, and slept in the Station House. [Laughter.] </p>

<p> A reporter has to lie a little, of course, or they would discharge him. 
That is the only drawback to the profession. That is why I left it. [Laughter.] 
I am different from Washington; I have a higher and grander standard of principle. 
Washington could not lie. I <hi rend="italic"> can </hi> lie, but I <hi rend="italic"> won't </hi>. [Prolonged laughter.] 

Reporting is fascinating, but then it is distressing to have to lie so. Lying is 
bad &mdash; lying is very bad. Every individual in this house knows that by experience. 
I think that for a man to tell a lie when he can't make anything by it, is wrong. 
[Laughter.] </p>
</div2>

<div2 type="conclusion" id="d6">

<p> A description of Virginia City followed. </p>

<p> After the reportorial experience of Mr. Clemens was ended, he became 
editor-in-chief of the paper on which he was working. He kept his position 
one week. The reason for this extreme brevity of time was that, according to the 
code of ethics of Virginia City, if you injured a man you were expected to challenge 
him. Duels accumulated rapidly on his hands. The first three of four he did 
not notice, as it was thought the persons would not fight. But at length he had 
trouble with the editor of the rival sheet, and a challenge passed. The boys were 

delighted, especially Steve, a near and dear friend. His friends took him out in 
the woods to practice with a revolver, that being the favorite duelling weapon. 
His opponent was a long, lean fellow, and not brilliant. A target for practice was 
made by leaning a rail against a stable-door to represent his antagonist, and putting 
on a squash for a head. The rail was a little too much of a caricature, but the 
squash did very well. He could not hit the rail, or even the stable-door. To make 
it more uncomfortable they could hear this antagonist with his friends practicing 
in a neighboring valley. Steve, being a dead shot, killed a bird, and the other party 

coming over to see what was the matter, the credit of this shot was given to Mark, and 
the party were informed that he could do the same thing nine times out of ten. When 
Mark and his friends got home that night they found a note declining the honor of a duel. 
All the other duels were declined with thanks, and Steve got them much to his delight. 
But accidentally hearing of his powers, they were all off, whereat that belligerent 
party was greatly grieved.</p>

<p> The lecture closed with some amusing moral reflections regarding the sins of duelling.</p>
</div2>
</div1>

<div1 type="article" id="d7">
<head>The Chicago Tribune<lb/>
24 December 1871<lb/>
"MARK TWAIN."<lb/>
A Few More Passages from the Great Humorist's 
Lecture at the Michigan Avenue Baptist Church &mdash; Lake
Tahoe and Camp Life in Its Vicinity &mdash; Remarkable Recovery
of an Invalid &mdash; Hunting Rocky Mountain Sheep &mdash; Mark's
Great Sand Shifter &mdash; Duelling at Virginia City.</head>

<div2 type="introduction" id="d8">

<p> We have already given liberal extracts from the lecture which Mark Twain delivered 
in this city on Monday evening. The matter pans out so well, both in a literary and 
humorous point of view, that we append a few more passages taken from the copious 
notes of our reporter: </p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" id="d9">


<div3 type="subsection" id="d10">
<head>LAKE TAHOE.</head>

<p> One of the most attractive portions of the lecture, and also one of the most 
polished, was a description of Lake Tahoe in Nevada. It is situated many thousand 
feet above the level of the sea, and yet it never freezes. Not the thinnest film of 
ice is ever seen upon its surface. And yet Lake Donner, which is at about the same 

altitude, and not far distant, is covered thickly with ice every winter. Here is a nut 
for scientists to crack, said the humorist. The question is not why Lake Donner freezes, 
but why Lake Tahoe does not freeze. Silver mining, not furnishing the seeker after wealth
very steady employment, a large portion of the time was spent in a boat on this beautiful 
lake. It was so clear that the pebbles on its bottom were visible at a great depth. 
The extreme depth of the water was about one-fourth of a mile. The audience was 

asked to imagine the number of church spires that could be placed one above the other 
before the surface was reached. The curative properties of the water, and the 
atmosphere of this region are most remarkable. Every consumptive invalid was urged to 
throw physic to the dogs and make their systems strong and perfect by a little camp 
life at Lake Tahoe. Said the speaker: </p>

<p> "If it don't cure them, I will bury them. I shall be glad to bury them &mdash; I shall 
be glad to do it. I will give them a funeral that will be a comfort to them as long 
as they live. But it will cure them. I met a man there &mdash; he had been a man once &mdash; 
now he was nothing but a shadow and a very poor shadow at that &mdash; and that man had

come there deliberately to die, and what a sickly failure he made of it! He was in dead 
earnest. He had heard that this air was easy and soothing to breathe, as God knows it is; 
and he had simply come there to have what comfort he might whilst life ebbed away. 
And he had brought along a plan of his private graveyard, and pictures and drawings 
of different kinds of coffins and hearses, and such things, and he never did anything 
but sit around and study that graveyard, and figure at coffins, and such things, 

trying to make up his mind which kind he liked best, or which kind would be most 
becoming. And when I saw that man three months afterward he was chasing mountain 
sheep over a mountain seven miles high, with a Sharp's rifle. He did not get them, 
but be chased them all the same. And he has used up all his graveyards, and coffins &mdash; all 
his plans and pictures, for wadding &mdash; and sent for more. </p>

<p> "When I first saw him, his clothes hung about him &mdash; why, they did not fit him 
any more than a circus tent fits the tent poles, but now they clung to him like court 
plaster. He could hardly breathe without starting a seam. He weighed a ton &mdash; he 
weighed more than a ton. I throw in the odd ounces &mdash; eleven, I think it was. 
But I know what I am talking about, because I took him to the hay scales myself. 
There was a lot of us stood on there with him. </p>

<p> "But, really, that was a remarkable cure. I have exaggerated it a little. 
You might not have noticed it. But still it was a cure and a very remarkable one. 
I wish you would not heed my nonsense, but simply take note of my earnest word. 
I think if I could only persuade one invalid to go there I should feel as if I 
had done one thing worth having accomplished. I am really sincere about that." </p>
</div3>

<div3 type="subsection" id="d11">
<head>ROCKY MOUNTAIN SHEEP.</head>

<p> "If there is a sportsman is this audience, I say to him, shoulder your gun and go 
out there. It is the best hunting place on the face of the earth. You can hunt there 
year after year, and not find anything. You can find mountain sheep, but you cannot get 

near them. You can see plenty of them with a spy-glass. But that was the only game I 
saw that was worth speaking of, when I was there, except 'seven-up.' [For the sake of 
convenience, we omit the laughter, only stating that it was incessant. &mdash; REPORTER.] 
I will here remark that the mountain sheep is our American chamois &mdash; French pronunciation!
He is the same kind they make the chamois leather of in other countries. We would here 

if we could catch him. He has enormous horns, and is a pretty large animal, too. 
He is so shy, so very shy, that it's almost impossible to get within rifle-shot of him. 
He inhabits the rockiest fastnesses of the mountains." </p>
</div3>

<div3 type="subsection" id="d12">
<head>SHOVELLING SAND.</head>

<p> "I had to go to work in a quartz mill at $10 a week. A nice place, truly, for the 
proprietor of a hundred silver mines! But I was glad to get that berth. But I could 
not keep it. They did not want me. I did'nt know why. I was the most careful workman
they had ever had. They said so. I took more pains with my work. I was shovelling sand. 

The technical term is "tailing." The silver rock is ground over once or twice and
they clean it up and work it over again. Whenever I had a lot of that sand to shovel 
I was so particular that I would sit down for an hour and a half and think about the 
best way to shovel that sand. And if I could not cipher it out in my mind just so, 
I would not go shovelling it around heedless. I would leave it alone until next day.
Many a time when I would be carrying a bucket full of sand from one pile to another, 

thirty or forty feet off, right in the middle, suddenly, a new idea would strike me, 
and I would carry that sand back, and sit down and think about it, and like enough get 
so wrought up, and absorbed in it, that I would go to sleep. Why, I always knew there 
must be some tip-top, first-rate way to move that sand. At last I discovered it. I went 
to the boss, and told him that I had got just the thing, the very best and quickest way to 
get that sand from one pile to the other. And he says, 'I am awful glad to hear it.' 

You never saw a man so uplifted as he was. It appeared to take a load off his breast &mdash; a 
load of sand, I suppose. And I said &mdash; 'What you want now is a cast iron pipe about 13 or 
14 feet in diameter, and, say, 42 feet long. And you want to prop one end of that pipe 
up, about 35 or 40 feet off the ground. And then you want a revolving belt &mdash; just work it 
with the waste steam from the engine &mdash; a revolving belt with a revolving chair to it. I 
am to sit in that chair, and have a Chinaman down there to till up the bucket with sand, 
and pass it up as I come around, [illustrates with gestures] and I am just to soar up there 
and tilt it into that pipe, and there you are. It is as easy as rolling off a log. </p>

<p> "You never saw a man so overcome with admiration &mdash; so overwhelmed. Before he 
knew what he was about he discharged me." </p>
</div3>

<div3 type="subsection" id="d13">
<head>THE CODE DUELLO.</head>

<p> From Esmarelda, the scene of his mining exploits, Mark went to Virginia City. 
Here he held a reportorial position on one of the papers for three years. After 
deserting the mining speculation, and the collapse that followed it, he said:
"That was a singular town. They had some of the strangest customs &mdash; some of the 

most curious customs. When I finished reporting on that paper they made me chief editor. 
I lasted just a week. I edited that paper six days, and then I had five duels on my hands. 
I wouldn't have minded that if it had been the custom for those other people to challenge 
me. Then I would have simply have declined with thanks. But it was not so. If you 
abused a man in the paper, if you called him names &mdash; they had no rights there such 
as we have here &mdash; it the men didn't like it, you had to challenge him, and shoot him.

Of course I didn't want to do this, but the publisher said it was the custom &mdash; society 
must be protected. If I could not do the duties of my position, he would have to hire 
somebody else. </p>

<p> "I didn't mind the first three or four men; but the other man &mdash; I was after him. 
I knew he didn't want to fight so I was going to make all the reputation out of him I 
could. He got touched at something I said about him &mdash; I don't know what it was now &mdash; 

I called him a thief, perhaps. He fought very shy of me at first, and so I plied him 
with bloodthirsty challenges all the more. At last be began to take an interest in this 
thing. It seemed as though he really was going to enter into it at last. All our boys 
were delighted at the prospect, but I was not. This was not a turn I was expecting 
in things. </p>

<p> "I had taken for my second a fiery, peppery little fellow, named Steve, full of fight, 
and anxious to have this thing fixed up right away. He took me over into a little ravine 
beyond the town to practice. It was the custom to fight with Colt's navy revolvers at 
five steps. We borrowed a stable door for a mark from a gentleman who was absent. 

We set up that stable door, and	then we propped a fence rail up against the middle of 
it to represent my antagonist, and put a squash on it to represent his head.  He was a
very light thin man, <hi rend="italic"> very </hi> thin &mdash; the poorest kind of material for a duel &mdash; you 
could not expect to do anything with a scattering shot at all.	But he made a splendid 
line shot, and it was the line that that I practiced principally. </p>

<p> "But there was no success about it. I could not hit the rail, and there was no need 
that I should hit the rail; the rail did not really represent him. It was a little too 
thin and narrow. But the squash was all right. Well, I could not hit the rail, and I 

could not hit the squash, and, finally, when I found I could not hit the door either, 
I got a little discouraged.  But when I noticed that I crippled one of the boys 
occasionally, I thought it was not so bad &mdash; I was dangerous with a pistol, but 
not reliable. </p>

<p> "Finally, we heard some shooting going on over in the other ravine. We knew what 
that meant. The other party was practicing. I didn't feel comfortable. They might 
straggle over the ridge, and see what was going	on, and when they saw no bullet-hole in
that barn door, it would be too much encouragement for them. Just then a little bird, 
a little larger than a sparrow, lit on a sage bush near by. Steve whipped out his 

revolver and shot its head off. The boys picked up the bird, and were talking about it, 
when the other duelling party came over the ridge, and came down to see what was
going on. When the second saw the bird he said, 'How far off was that?' Steve said 
about thirty steps. 'Who did that?' 'Why, Twain, my man, of course.' 'Did he, indeed! 
can he do that often?' 'Well, he can do that about four times in five.' </p>

<p> "I knew that little rascal was lying, but I didn't like to tell him so. I was one 
of those kind of men that don't like to be too frank or too familiar in a matter like 
that, so I didn't say anything.  But it was a comfort to see those fellows under

jaws drop; to see them turn blue about the gills and look sick. They went off, and 
got their man and took him home, and when I got home I found a little note from these
parties, peremptorily declining to fight. How sore the boys were! How indignant they 
were! And so was I!  But I was not distressed about it.	I thought I could stand
it, perhaps. </p>


<p> "Well, I was out of that scrape, and I didn't want to got into anymore of them.
I turned the other four duels over to Steve, who wanted them. But when those 
people found out afterward that he did that shooting, he didn't get any good out
of his duels. They wouldn't fight him. </p>

<p> "All that was in my younger days, when I didn't know much &mdash; which I do now. 
I didn't know any better then, but now I am bitterly opposed to duelling. I won't 
have anything to do with duelling. I think that duelling is immoral, and has a 

bad tendency, and I think it is every man's duty to frown down and discourage duelling.  
I do. I discourage it on all occasions.	If a man were to challenge me  now, I would go 
and take that man by the hand, and lead him to a quiet, private room &mdash; and kill him!</p>

<p>"Ladies and gentlemen, after thanking you very heartily for the attention you have given me this evening, I desire to wish you a very pleasant good night, and at the same time assure you earnestly that I have told nothing but the truth to-night, and I have hardly exaggerated that."  [Laughter and applause.]</p>
</div3>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
