<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="TwaStlo"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;

]>
<TEI.2 id="TwaStlo">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Arousing Interest</title>
<title type="sort">arousing interest</title>
<author>Twain, Mark, 1835-1910</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Steve Railton</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>J. Nathaniel Goldsmith, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">7</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">TwaStlo</idno>
<date value="2001">2001</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2001 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476432</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Arousing Interest</title>
<title type="sort">arousing interest</title>
<author>Mark Twain, pseud. Samuel Langhorne Clemens</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Sacramento Union</publisher>
<pubPlace>Sacramento</pubPlace>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
<term>Mark Twain</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2001-07">July, 2001</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name/>
</respStmt>
<item/>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="letter" id="d3">
<head>Arousing Interest</head>

<p>EDITOR, Sunday <hi rend="italic">Republican</hi>: You may not know that I am
going to lecture at Mercantile Hall tomorrow night for the benefit of the South St. Louis Mission
Sunday School, but I am.  I do not consider any apology necessary.  I would like to have a
Sunday School of my own, but I would not be competent to run it, you know, because I have not
had experience, and so I have thought that the next most gratifying thing I could do would be to
give somebody else's Sunday School a lift.  I used to go to Sunday School myself, a long time
ago, and it is on that account that I have always taken a powerful interest in such institutions
since.  I even rose to be a teacher in one once, but they discharged me because they said the
information I imparted was of too general a character.</p>

<p>I have done some good in my time though.  When I was elected to the Chief Magistry of the
Burlesque Government of the territory of Nevada, I delivered my annual message to the
Legislature for the benefit of a church, and charged double admission.  The proceeds enabled
them to put a new roof on that church, and everybody said that that roof would cave in, some
time or other, and mash the congregation, because I was one of those sinful newspaper men, but it
never did.  Ever since that I have been ambitious to put a roof on a Sunday School and see if it
could stand it, and now I got a chance.  I feel a little proud about it, and I wish you would
mention in your paper that I am going to lecture for the benefit of a Sunday School, so that they
will see it in California, because, you know, if I were merely to say it myself, without any
endorsement, they would copper it.  (That is a Californian poetical simile; when they don't believe
a statement there, they say copper it.)</p>

<p>I want this Sunday School experiment of mine to be a success, now that I have got this
opening, and so I offer the following splendid prizes to encourage an interest among the public. 
(One has got to turn everything into a lottery now-a-days, to make it popular.  However, there is
no harm in it maybe, because even the church festivals have their little lottery arrangements, you
know.)</p>

<p>For the best conundrum, first prize, a beautiful elephant. <hi rend="italic">N.B.</hi> He is a little
cadaverous, now, but a few tons of hay and confectionery would soon feed him up to a condition
of symmetry and vivacity that would render him a favorite at the fireside, and the pet of the
household.  It is far better to have an elephant around than a cat, because cats sleep on the bed,
but an elephant never.</p>

<p>For the best poem on Summer or Summer Complaint (option with the author), the second
prize, consisting of eighteen hundred Auger Holes, will be awarded.  These auger holes are really
magnificent specimens of the carpenter's beautiful art, and have elicited the wildest burst of
admiration wherever they have been exhibited, both in America and among the crowned heads of
Europe.  QueenVictoria observed of them that she only wanted to see these auger holes once
more and then die.  Competitors for this prize may crawl around and look through them free of
charge, if they desire it.  They will be found to possess as many virtues as any auger holes.</p>

<p>For the most splendid essay on Female Suffrage the Third prize, consisting of that splendid
piece of property known as Lafayette Park, is offered.  This beautiful park lies out toward
Compton Hill, and is tastefully laid out in walks, and bridges, and holes in the ground, and piles of
dirt, and has neat legible signs to tell you where the grass is when there is any there.</p>

<p>The iron fence around it is a gem in itself.  Few people can contemplate it without emotion,
and nobody can climb it without stilts.  Lafayette Park would cut up handsomely for city lots, and
bring enormous prices.  The winner of the Third prize will be awarded it.  The diversion he will
experience in trying to get possession of the property, must be a fortune in itself, and will afford
him the liveliest entertainment as long as he lives.</p>

<p>How's that?</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">N.B.</hi> This moral lecture on the Sandwich Islands, which I am going to deliver, is a
separate institution all by itself, and is not connected with any other circus.</p>

<closer>
<signed>MARK TWAIN</signed>
</closer>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
