<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="TylSeki"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="TylSeki"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Sekidera Komachi</title>
<title type="sort">sekidera komachi</title>
<author>Tyler, Royall</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>  
<name>Winnie Chan</name>  
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>  
<name/>  
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">33</num> kilobytes</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>  
<idno type="ETC">TylSeki</idno>  
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476439</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>  
<seriesStmt>
<p>Japanese Text Initiative</p>
</seriesStmt>  
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Copyright 1978 Royall Tyler. Except for brief quotations in a review, no part of this 
text may be reproduced or utilized in any form or by any means, 
electronic or mechanical, including photocopying and recording, or by 
any information storage or retrieval system, without permission in 
writing from the author. Please address inquiries to Royall Tyler in 
care of East Asia Program, Cornell University, 140 Uris Hall, Ithaca, NY 
14853-7601.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>  
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Komachi at the Gateway Temple (Sekidera Komachi: a woman play or a miscellaneous play)</title>
<title level="m">Pining Wind: a Cycle of N&omacr; Plays</title>
<title type="sort">komachi at the gateway temple sekidera komachi a woman play or a miscellaneous play</title>
<author>Royall Tyler</author>
</titleStmt>  
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt>  
<extent>pp. 104-117</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Cornell China-Japan Program</publisher>  
<pubPlace>Ithaca, New York</pubPlace>  
<date value="1978">1978</date>  
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa Library call number PL 782 .E5 P55 v.1</idno>
</publicationStmt>  
<seriesStmt>
<p>Cornell University East Asia Papers, number 17</p>
</seriesStmt>  
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Copyright 1978 Royall Tyler. From <hi rend="italic">Pining Wind: A Cycle of Noh 
Plays</hi> (English translation). Cornell East Asia Series no. 
17, 204 pp., 0-939657-17-1, $12 paper.  East Asia Program, Cornell 
University, 140 Uris Hall, Ithaca, NY 14853-7601 (ph.  607-255-6222; 
fax: 607-255-1388, kks3@cornell.edu).</p>
</note>  
<note>
<p>CAUTION: Except for brief quotations in a review, no part of this 
text may be reproduced or utilized in any form or by any means, 
electronic or mechanical, including photocopying and recording, or by 
any information storage or retrieval system, without permission in 
writing from the author. Please address inquiries to Royall Tyler in 
care of East Asia Program, Cornell University, 140 Uris Hall, Ithaca, NY 
14853-7601.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>  
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>  
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>  
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>  
<p>Spacing in print source has been preserved. Natural line breaks have been removed, and the trailing part of a verse has been joined to the preceding line.</p>  
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>  
</encodingDesc>  
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1978">1978</date>
</creation>  
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>  
<language id="rj">Romaji</language>
</langUsage>  
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>drama; prose; poetry</term>  
<term>Literature in Translation</term>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
</profileDesc>  
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-09">September 1997</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added milestones to correspond with ZeaSeki.</item>
</change>  
<change>
<date value="1997-02">February 1997</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Winnie Chan</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>  
 
 
<text id="d1"> 
 
<front id="d2"> 
 
 <pb n="104" id="TylSeki104"/>  
 
<div1 type="introduction" id="d3"> 
 
<head> 
KOMACHI AT GATEWAY TEMPLE<lb/> 
(<hi rend="italic">Sekidera Komachi</hi>: a woman play or a 
miscellaneous play) 
</head> 
 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">Komachi at Gateway Temple</hi> takes place on the seventh night 
of the seventh moon of the year. This is the night of Tanabata, a festival 
which is still celebrated in Japan. Nowadays Tanabata is on the night of 
July 7, in the height of summer. In the lunar calendar, however, the 
seventh day of the seventh moon falls several weeks later, at the start of 
fall. A month in the solar calendar is not the same as a 'moon.' Nor 
indeed was an 'hour' in pre-modern Japan the same as one of our hours. Day 
and night were divided into six periods each, no matter what the season, 
so that each period waxed and waned in length through the year. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
On Tanabata, or Seventh Night, the two celestial lovers meet: the Herd-Boy 
star (Altair) crosses the River of Heaven (the Milky Way) to the Weaver 
star (Vega) over a bridge formed of the joyously-linked wings of magpies. 
In this play, a celebration is being offered at Gateway Temple for the 
occasion. There is to be music and dancing, and many bamboo wands tied 
with streamers of five colors. These wands are prayer sticks, to pray for 
various blessings including skill in poetry. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
To hear more about poetry, some priests and children from the temple go to 
visit an old lady who lives nearby. She turns out to be Ono no Komachi, 
who in her youth was a peerless beauty and a great poet. Now she is only a 
year short of one hundred, the forgotten ruin of a woman. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
The historical Ono no Komachi was active in the mid-ninth century,  
   
 
 <pb n="105" id="TylSeki105"/>  
and left behind her a vivid legend. There is no other record of her having 
retired to Gateway Temple, below the eastern slope of Osaka Pass, but it 
is fitting that at the gates of death, she should live in such a place. 
Osaka Pass was indeed the gateway from Miyako toward what were in 
Komachi's time the wilds of the east and north, and it was famous for 
painful separations. 
</p> 
 
<p> 
Several passages of <hi rend="italic">Komachi at Gateway Temple</hi> are taken 
from the preface to the <hi rend="italic">Kokinsh&umacr;</hi>, which was the 
canonical statement on poetry. It is this preface which singles out the 
'Naniwa Harbor' and 'Mount Asaka' poems for special comment. Naniwa was a 
port on the site of modern Osaka, and the poem goes, 'At Naniwa Harbor it 
blooms! this flower winter-long shut in, now spring is here it blooms! 
this flower.' The 'Mount Asaka' poem can be roughly translated: 'Mount 
Asaka, reflecting you the rocky pool's shallow this heart is not in 
desire.' The ancient story goes that when the King of Kazuraki visited 
northern Japan, he felt poorly received and refused to eat or drink until 
a serving girl came up to him with a full wine cup, tapped him on the 
knee, and recited this verse; everything went smoothly from then on. It is 
also the <hi rend="italic">Kokinsh&umacr;</hi> preface that describes Komachi's 
poetry as 'affecting, but not strong.' 
</p> 
 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">Komachi at Gateway Temple</hi> mentions 'cloud walkers,' meaning 
the nobles of the imperial court, for the Emperor's own palace is known as 
the 'cloud dwelling.' Figuratively speaking, all of Japan was one 
mountain, on top of which was the Imperial Seat&mdash;this is the meaning 
of the word <hi rend="italic">miyako</hi> which became the common 
name for the Capital. One always traveled 'up' to Miyako, and 'down' from 
it. 
</p> 
   
 
 <pb n="107" id="TylSeki107"/>  
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">Komachi at Gateway Temple</hi> is held to be the loftiest play 
in the repertoire, and only a senior and distinguished actor would dare to 
perform its main role. Some say the role is so difficult and so lofty 
because Komachi does not move at all during the first hour or so of the 
play&mdash;as though loftiness were measured by the obligation to 
tolerate, toward some esoteric end, intolerable boredom. There is some 
truth in this, but surely the real loftiness comes from the play's 
transparent simplicity of tone. There are masterpieces, but this is a 
past-masterpiece, beyond praise. Zeami, who may possibly have written it, 
says that an old actor who has truly mastered the 'flower' of the art will 
always be perfectly fresh even though he is long past the age for 
brilliance. His acting will be like blossoms on an old bough. In 
<hi rend="italic">Komachi at Gateway Temple</hi>, this image is applied to Komachi 
herself, as she dances at last. The whole play, though, is actually like 
that. Beside an old, old woman whose age has brought her out of the world 
into a second innocence, one sees the children, dressed in their best, 
gravely dancing for the Stars. 
</p> 
</div1> 
   

</front> 
 
<body id="d4"> 

<div1 type="play" id="d5"><pb n="108"/>
 
 
<stage> 
Komachi's hut stands before drums. From it hang a few slips of paper for 
writing poems. 
</stage> 
 
<p>SHIDAI</p>
 
<stage> 
Sideman and Sideman's Second enter, preceded by Child. They line up down 
front, with Sideman and Sideman's Second facing each other. 
</stage> 

 
<p>SHIDAI<lb/> on-str</p>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki1"/>
<sp> 
<speaker>Sideman and Side Second</speaker> 
<lg> 
<l>The waiting ends </l>  
<l>now fall's rejoined</l>   
<l>the waiting ends </l>  
<l>now fall's rejoined </l>  
<l>the Stars: hasten their feast! </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 

 
<p>NANORI<lb/> off-sp</p>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki2"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Sideman</speaker> 
<p> 
<stage>facing front</stage> 
You have before you the head priest of Gateway Temple in the land of 
&Omacr;mi. Today being the seventh day of the seventh month, we're all 
going into the garden of the Lecture Hall, to celebrate Seventh Night. But 
now, an old woman has put together a hut under this mountain, and I 
understand she's a master of the Way of Song; so I'm taking the young 
people with me to hear what she has to say. 
</p> 
</sp> 

 
<p>SASHI<lb/> off-str</p>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki3"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Sideman and Side Second</speaker> 

<stage> 
face to face 
</stage> <lg> 
<l>'Hiss and sigh </l>  
<l>the chilling winds </l>  
<l>and wilting hairs </l>  
<l>converge at start of fall,' </l>  
<l>and evening of </l>  
<l>the seventh day </l>  
<l>so soon has come. </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki4"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Sideman</speaker> 

<stage> 
facing front 
</stage> <lg> 
<l>This Seventh Night </l>  
<l>we've offerings: </l>  
<l>strings, pipes tuned</l>   
<l>to modes and scales </l>  
<l>many-hued </l>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki5"/>
<l>words urge we forth </l>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki6"/>
<l>for Blessed Isles' </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 

 
<p> 
AGEUTA<lb/> 
on-str 
</p>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki7"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Sideman and Side Second</speaker> 
 
<stage> 
face to face 
</stage> <lg>
<l>Way our prayer </l>  
<l>threads streaming bright </l>  
<l>Way our prayer </l>  
<l>threads streaming bright </l>  
<l>oh, weave brocade</l>   
<l>loom the flags of </l>  
<l>pampas grasses, </l>  
<l>flowers too </l>  
<l>and autumn weeds </l>  
<l>dew-spangled sing,</l>   
<l>so gently plays </l>  
<l>the pining wind, </l>
</lg> 
 
<stage> 
Sideman takes a few steps and returns to his place by start of next 
passage. 
</stage> 
   
 
 <pb n="108" id="TylSeki108"/>  
<lg> 
<l>itself perfect</l>   
<l>offering </l>  
<l>this wondrous night </l>  
<l>offering </l>  
<l>this wondrous night! </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 

 
<p> 
TSUKI-ZERIFU<lb/> 
off-sp 
</p>
 
<sp> 
<speaker>Sideman</speaker> 
<p> 
<stage> 
facing front 
</stage> 
You wait here a moment, while I inquire within the hut. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<stage> 
All go to sit near Sideman's spot. Stage hand removes cover from the hut, 
revealing Doer seated inside. She wears the 
<hi rend="italic">r&omacr;jo</hi>, or Old Woman, mask. 
</stage> 

 
<p> 
SASHI<lb/> 
off-w 
</p>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki8"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Doer</speaker> 
<lg> 
<l>Though mornings I get not one bowl, seek food I cannot; </l>  
<l>though grass wraps, nights, hide not my flesh I have nothing more. </l>   
<l>Flowers, as rains go by, lose their scarlet youth; </l>  
<l>willows, as breezes lure them, let the green fronds droop. </l>  
<l>Man is not young again: at last he's old, </l>  
<l>and though spring come with warblers'</l>   
<l>hundred carolings, no fall goes back</l>   
<l>to yesteryear. </l>  
<l>Oh the old days, </l>  
<l>I miss them so! </l>
</lg> 
 
<stage> 
She gently checks tears. 
</stage> 
 
<lg> 
<l>Oh the old days, </l>
<l>I miss them so! </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 
 
<stage> 
Sideman stands, and has Child stand also. 
</stage> 

 
<p> 
MONDO<lb/> 
off-w* 
</p>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki9"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Sideman</speaker> 
<p> 
<stage><hi rend="super">sp</hi></stage> 
Old lady, I beg your pardon, but I'd like to speak with you. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<sp> 
<speaker>Doer</speaker> 
<p> 
Who is it? 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<sp> 
<speaker>Sideman</speaker> 
<p> 
I'm from Gateway Temple. The children of the temple are studying poetry, 
and they've been asking about the old lady. So I've brought them along to 
ask you how to compose songs, and to listen to whatever you have to say. 
</p> 
</sp> 
   
 
 <pb n="109" id="TylSeki109"/>  
<stage> 
Sideman and Child move closer to Doer. 
</stage> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki10"/>
<sp> 
<speaker>Doer</speaker> 
<lg> 
<l>You do astonish me! A buried stump disowned by men, that's what I 
am:</l>   
<l>no longer shall </l>  
<l>plumed pampas grass </l>  
<l>burst into fruit. Just make the heart your seed, and dip the flowers of 
your speech in hue and fragrance. If you do, then how should you fail to 
grasp true style? </l>
 </lg>
<stage> 
turning to Child 
</stage> <p>
How lovely that all this should appeal to you young people! 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki11"/>
<sp> 
<speaker>Sideman</speaker> 
<p> 
One that everyone praises right off is the 'Naniwa Harbor' song, and I 
understand it's to be considered the first model for learners. Isn't that 
so? 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki12"/>
<sp> 
<speaker>Doer</speaker> 
<p> 
Very definitely. Song, you see, began in the Age of Gods, but the count of 
letters then kept changing, and likely enough the heart of the matter was 
difficult to make out. Now we're in the Age of Men; and it's because the 
poem celebrates a happy Imperial accession that people make much of the 
'Naniwa Harbor' song. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki13"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Sideman</speaker> 
<p> 
And the 'Mount Asaka' song is a very happy poem too, since it soothed the 
heart of a king! 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki14"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Doer</speaker> 
<p> 
Yes, you understand perfectly. With these two songs as mother and father 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki15"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Sideman</speaker> 
<stage><hi rend="super">s</hi></stage> 
 <lg> 
<l>and first model </l>
<l>for all learners, </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki16"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Doer</speaker>
 <stage><hi rend="super">sp</hi></stage> 
<lg> 
<l>men high and low, </l>  
<l>of all degrees, </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki17"/>
<sp> 
<speaker>Sideman</speaker> 
 <stage><hi rend="super">s</hi></stage> 
<lg> 
<l>town and country, </l>
<l>rustic folk </l>
<l>of furthest lands, </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki18"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Doer</speaker> 
<lg> 
<l>plain people even,</l>
<l>like ourselves, </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki19"/>
<sp> 
<speaker>Sideman</speaker> 
<p> 
sweet delight do 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki20"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Doer</speaker> 
<p> 
Sea of &Omacr;mi 
</p> 
</sp> 

 
<p> 
AGEUTA<lb/> 
on-w 
</p>
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki21"/>
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<lg> 
<l>ripples o! </l>  
<l>Sands of the shore </l>
<l>may reach an end </l>  
<l>sands of the shore </l>  
<l>may reach an end;</l>   
<l>words of song, though, </l>  
<l>never shall.</l>   
<l>Greenwillow fronds</l>   
<l>flow on  </l>
   
 
 <pb n="110" id="TylSeki110"/>  
<l>always, </l>  
<l>pine needles </l>  
<l>do not fall and die. </l>  
<l>Know then that the seed's the heart! </l>  
<l>And though times change,</l>   
<l>though all things pass, </l>  
<l>so long as words </l>  
<l>of these songs last,</l>   
<l>so long shall</l>   
<l>the bird prints run </l>  
<l>so long shall</l>   
<l>the bird prints run. </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 

 
<p> 
MONDO<lb/> 
off-w* 
</p>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki22"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Sideman</speaker>
 <stage>sp</stage>
<lg>  
<l>Thank you. The old poets have left us many words, but songs by women are 
rare. There are few like you, old lady! 'My own love </l>  
<l>this night shall come:</l>   
<l>little spider </l>  
<l>with her web </l>  
<l>weaves me a sign!' Is that a woman's song? </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki23"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Doer</speaker> 
<p> 
That's a song by Princess Sot&omacr;ri, of the old days. She was the 
consort of Emperor Ingy&omacr;. In form, at least, it's her style I 
followed. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki24"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Sideman</speaker> 
<p> 
Well now, you say you followed Princess Sot&omacr;ri's style? Ono no 
Komachi herself, who's so much heard of in recent years, 
</p> 
 
<stage> 
Doer lowers her head. 
</stage> 
 
<lg> 
<l>is said to work in Princess Sot&omacr;ri's style. 'So forlorn I 
grieve, </l>  
<l>pondweed root-cut and drifting; </l>  
<l>should some stream</l>   
<l>stir to woo me now </l>  
<l>I'd go, I know!' There's a song by Komachi! </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki25"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Doer</speaker> 
<p> 
<stage> 
lifting head 
</stage> 
<stage><hi rend="super">s</hi></stage> 
Yes, &Omacr;e no Koreaki had had a change of heart, and I was very 
downcast.  
<stage><hi rend="super">sp</hi></stage> 
Then Fun'ya no Yasuhide, on his way down as Governor of Mikawa, suggested 
I come with him. 'Do please find solace in my country dwelling,' said he,  
<stage> 
turning to Sideman 
</stage> 
and that was why I made the song. 
</p> 
</sp> 

 
<p> 
SAGEUTA<lb/> 
on-w 
</p>

<sp> 
 <stage>turning front again</stage> 
<lg> 
<l>I'd forgotten </l>  
<l>through the years,</l>   
<l>but listening now, </l>  
<l>tears fall for old </l>
   
 
 <pb n="111" id="TylSeki111"/>  
<l>things </l>  
<l>brought to mind </l>  
<l>alas, with sorrow! </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 
 
<stage> 
Doer checks tears. 
</stage> 

 
<p> 
MONDO<lb/> 
off-w* 
</p>
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki26"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Sideman</speaker> 
<p> 
<stage><hi rend="super">sp</hi></stage> 
How strange! I hear you say that it's you who made the song, 'So forlorn I 
grieve' and your statement that you followed Princess Sot&omacr;ri's style 
sounds like Komachi too. In fact, as I consider the age. . . You, old 
lady, say you're a hundred; then even if Komachi were much changed, she 
might well still be alive. No, there's no longer any doubt: you yourself 
are what is left of Komachi!  
<stage><hi rend="super">s</hi></stage> 
I tell you, hide it no longer! 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki27"/>
<sp> 
<speaker>Doer</speaker> 
<p> 
No, hearing 'Komachi' I'm ashamed 
</p> 
 
<stage> 
She lifts her head, turns to Sideman. 
</stage> 
 
<p> 
'Hues all unseen. . .' though then I sang, 
</p> 
</sp> 

 
<p> 
AGEUTA<lb/> 
on-w 
</p>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki28"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<lg> 
<l>'. . . it shifts and fades, </l>  
<l>a worldly one's heart flower. . .' </l>  
<l>ah, now seen! I'm ashamed! </l>
</lg> 
 
<stage> 
She lowers her head, turns front again. 
</stage> 
 
<lg> 
<l>'So forlorn I grieve, </l>  
<l>pondweed root-cut and drifting, should some stream </l>  
<l>stir to woo me: </l>  
<l>even now I'd go, I know!' </l>  
<l>I'm ashamed! </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 
 
<stage> 
Doer lifts her head once more. Sideman and Child go back to sit at 
Sideman's spot. 
</stage> 

 
<p> 
KURI<lb/> 
off-weak 
</p>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki29"/>  
<sp> 
<lg> 
<l>Indeed,</l>   
<l>'screen them I do,</l>   
<l>yet from these sleeves spill shining drops, </l>  
<l>of eyes that see thee not the tears,' reigning </l>  
<l>memories sow seeds </l>  
<l>of passion grasses' </l>  
<l>bloom now wilted </l>  
<l>I, until the end,</l>   
<l>shall hold&mdash;but why?&mdash; </l>  
<l>with shining dews </l>  
<l>to days long since gone. </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 

   
 
 <pb n="112" id="TylSeki112"/>  
<p> 
SASHI<lb/> 
off-weak 
</p>
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki30"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Doer</speaker> 
<lg> 
<l>Yes, 'Absorbed in love</l>   
<l>I lie me down </l>  
<l>and he appears!' </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki31"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<lg> 
<l>sang I, though now</l>   
<l>it suits me ill; </l>  
<l>so long they've come,</l>   
<l>the moons and years </l>  
<l>I send off, greet, </l>  
<l>as spring and fall</l>   
<l>with dews trip in </l>  
<l>and pass with frost, </l>  
<l>for leaves of grass change, </l>  
<l>insect cries</l>   
<l>have died away.</l> 
</lg> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki32"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Doer</speaker> 
<lg> 
<l>Already life</l> 
<l>is at its term, </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 

 
<p> 
KUSE<lb/> 
on-weak 
</p>
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki34"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<lg> 
<l>just like the rose of Sharon's </l>  
<l>one glorious day. </l>  
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki35"/> 
<l>'The living die, </l>  
<l>the dead gain ever more </l>  
<l>in this my life </l>  
<l>alas, how long </l>  
<l>am I bound to mourn?' </l>  
<l>That too I sang, </l>  
<l>oh how long </l>  
<l>the ivy vine, </l>  
<l>flowers falling,</l>   
<l>leaves all dropping, </l>  
<l>lingers in dewdrop life! </l>
</lg> 
<stage> 
She lowers her head, lost in memories. 
</stage> 
 
<lg> 
<l>Oh the old days,</l>   
<l>I miss them so! </l>  
<l>Each time I feel</l>   
<l>one with the past </l>  
<l>I so recall, old things capture me, </l>  
<l>till now, again, </l>
</lg> 
 
<stage>		 
She lifts her head, checks tears. 
</stage> 
 
<lg> 
<l>I am in love </l>  
<l>with those first years </l>  
<l>of old age. </l>  
<l>Most piteous my plight! </l>  
<l>In the old days </l>  
<l>the very room </l>  
<l>I lodged in </l>  
<l>a single night</l>   
<l>was decked with tortoiseshell; </l>  
<l>the fence hung with</l>   
<l>golden blossoms;</l>   
<l>doorways dripped rock crystal; </l>  
<l>Imperial Car, </l>  
<l>court carriages</l>   
<l>in radiant silks</l>   
<l>of proudest hues </l>  
<l>smooth-spread </l>  
<l>pillows enhanced</l>   
<l>the lovers' chamber </l>  
<l>where, within,</l>   
<l>I took my ease</l>   
<l>on flower-brocaded cushions. </l>
</lg> 
 
<stage> 
She lowers her head. 
</stage> 
   
 
 <pb n="113" id="TylSeki113"/>  
<lg> 
<l>Now, a mud-daub hut's</l>   
<l>my jeweled couch! </l>
</lg> 
 
<stage> 
She lifts her head, listens to bell. 
</stage> 
</sp> 
 
<sp> 
<speaker>Doer</speaker> 
<lg> 
<l>Gateway Temple's</l> 
<l>bell tolls </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 
 
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<lg> 
<l>'All things must pass'; </l>  
<l>these old ears hear </l>  
<l>but learn nothing. </l>  
<l>Winds sweep down </l>
</lg> 
 
<stage> 
She looks into distance to her right. 
</stage> 
 
<lg> 
<l>Osaka Pass: </l>  
<l>'All born must die,' </l>  
<l>they say; </l>  
<l>oh, if I knew! </l>  
<l>When petals fly </l>  
<l>and leaves fall, then, </l>  
<l>each time, </l>  
<l>for my delight, </l>  
<l>here at my wattled door </l>
</lg> 
 
<stage> 
She takes one of the poem slips in her left hand, then uses fan to mime 
dipping a writing brush in ink. She writes, dips brush again, 
writes some more as Chorus sings on. 
</stage> 
 
<lg> 
<l>the inkstone I make sing, </l>  
<l>stain the brush, and </l>  
<l>salt sea tangle </l>  
<l>trace out leaves of speech </l>  
<l>soon withered quite. </l>
</lg> 
 
<stage> 
She gazes at the slip she has been writing on. 
</stage> 
 
<lg> 
<l>'Most affecting, but not strong.' </l>  
<l>Not strong because</l>  
<l>a woman's songs . . . </l>
</lg> 
 
<stage> 
Weakly puts the poem slip down, and checks tears. 
</stage> 
 
<lg> 
<l>So terribly </l>  
<l>in my old age </l>  
<l>I've grown weak, </l>  
<l>till all that's left </l>  
<l>is sorrow. </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 

 
<p> 
MONDO<lb/> 
off-sp 
</p>
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki36"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Sideman</speaker> 
<p> 
<stage> 
to Sideman's Second 
</stage> 
You know, it's getting late for the feast of Seventh Night. Do invite the 
old lady to come along with us. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<sp> 
<speaker>Side Second</speaker> 
<p> 
By all means. 
</p> 
 
<stage> 
Sideman's Second stands and moves a few steps toward Doer. 
</stage> 
   
 <pb n="114" id="TylSeki114"/>  

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki37"/>  
<p> 
I beg your pardon, old lady, but what harm could it do? Do please come and 
have a look at the celebration we're offering for Seventh Night. 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki38"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Doer</speaker> 
<p> 
Oh no, an old woman shouldn't impose that way. I wouldn't think of it. 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<stage> 
Sideman's Second goes back to his place and sits. Sideman stands. 
</stage> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki39"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Sideman</speaker> 
<p> 
No, no, old lady, we'll be glad to have you. 
</p> 
 
<stage> 
He goes up to Doer and touches her. She picks up her staff. 
</stage> 
 
<p> 
Don't worry! Just come with us! 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<stage> 
Doer stands, aided by Sideman, and emerges from the hut. At 'Komachi,' she 
goes to main spot while Sideman retires to Sideman's spot. 
</stage> 

 
<p> 
AGEUTA<lb/> 
on-w 
</p>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki40"/>  
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<lg> 
<l>Seventh Night:</l>   
<l>weave streamer wands </l>  
<l>to offer up </l>  
<l>how many years </l>  
<l>gone shadow sere </l>  
<l>Ono no Komachi's touched </l>  
<l>one hundred, </l>  
<l>overhead </l>  
<l>Heaven's own congress of stars </l>  
<l>with cloud walkers </l>  
<l>quite at ease </l>
</lg> 
 
<stage> 
Now Doer gazes at her sleeves. At 'poor woman,' she sits wearily, leaning 
on her staff, and lowers her head. 
</stage> 
 
<lg> 
<l>did she brush sleeves,  </l> 
<l>now hempen-clad, </l>  
<l>poor woman! </l>  
<l>Oh painful fate! </l>  
<l>A sight not to be borne! </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 
 
<stage> 
Sideman opens his fan, holds it like a sake ladle, and faces Child. As 
Chorus sings on, Child opens his fan and holds it like a cup. He receives 
the liquor from Sideman, then goes before Doer and pours for her. At 
'streamer wands,' he stands and begins to dance: at 'round cups go,' moves 
to mark post, then sweeps left up to drums; at 'oh lovely,' comes to 
center, opens. 
</stage> 

 
<p> 
UTA<lb/> 
on-w 
</p>
 
<sp> 
<lg> 
<l>Ah yes, this night </l>  
<l>for Seventh Night</l>   
<l>ah yes, this night </l>  
<l>for Seventh Night </l>  
<l>offerings we have </l>
   
 
 <pb n="115" id="TylSeki115"/>  
<l>diverse, </l>  
<l>some, streamer wands </l>  
<l>twirling round</l>   
<l>and round cups go </l>  
<l>while moon snow lights </l>  
<l>on dancing children's sleeves, </l>  
<l>oh lovely scene! </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 

 
<p> 
EI<lb/> 
off-w 
</p>
 
<sp> 
<lg> 
<l>Fine bamboo wands</l> 
<l>with which we feast the Stars </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki41"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Doer</speaker> 
<lg> 
<l>age to age jointed </l>  
<l>live on, headed hence </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 
 
<stage> 
Child returns to Sideman's spot, does a leftright, and sits. Doer, as 
though unconsciously, beats time with fan. 
</stage> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki42"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<lg> 
<l>to what eternities, </l>
<l>Ten Thousand Years! </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 

 
<p>*<lb/> 
off-w* 
</p>
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki43"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Doer</speaker> 
<stage><hi rend="super">sp</hi></stage> 
 <lg>
<l>Oh, lovely </l>  
<l>they were just now, </l>  
<l>the dancing children's sleeves! </l>  
<l>Long ago</l>   
<l>at Harvest Vigil </l>  
<l>the girls of the Five Measure Dance </l>  
<l>twirled their sleeves </l>  
<l>yes, five times it was;  </l>
 </lg>
<stage><hi rend="super">s</hi></stage>
 <lg>
<l>sleeves offered now</l>   
<l>for Seventh Night </l>
<l>should be turned seven times.  </l>
</lg> 
<stage><hi rend="super">sp</hi></stage> 
 <p>
When a madman runs, they say, the sane run after him. Now, lured by the 
dancing children's sleeves, 
 </p>
 
<stage><hi rend="super">s</hi></stage>
<l> the madman's going to run.</l>
</sp> 
 
<stage> 
With the aid of her staff she stands, then taps beat once. 
</stage> 

 
<p> 
WAKA<lb/> 
off-w 
</p>
 

<sp> 
<p> 
One hundred years 
</p> 
</sp> 

 
<p> 
MAI 
</p>
 
<stage> 
She begins to dance, very slowly. Some way into the dance she lays down 
her staff, to pick it up again near the end. She stops at last at main 
spot and, as text resumes, strikes fan high pose. 
</stage> 

 
<p> 
WAKA<lb/> 
off-w 
</p>

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki44"/>  
<sp> 
<lg> 
<l>One hundred years </l>
<l>snug in a flower </l> 
<l>now dances the butterfly. </l>
</lg> 
 
<stage> 
Now she continues dancing, staff in hand. At 'touching sight,' she does a 
leftright; at 'skirts,' moves to mark post; at'wandering,' 
displays  
   
 
 <pb n="116" id="TylSeki116"/>  
open fan; at 'scarves,' turns left up to center; at 'sleeves,' looks at 
sleeves.) 
</stage> 
</sp> 

 
<p> 
NORIJI<lb/> 
onori-w 
</p>
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki45"/>
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<lg> 
<l>Oh touching sight! </l>  
<l>Oh touching sight! </l>  
<l>The old tree bough </l>  
<l>blossoms 
</l></lg> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki46"/>
<sp> 
<speaker>Doer</speaker> 
<lg> 
<l>nod, swinging sleeves</l> 
<l>move how forgotten</l> 
</lg> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki47"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<p> 
skirts keep feeble step, 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki48"/>
<sp> 
<speaker>Doer</speaker> 
<p> 
a wandering wave's 
</p> 
</sp> 

<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki49"/> 
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<lg> 
<l>up and dancing </l>  
<l>scarves toss round </l>  
<l>but no sleeves these </l>  
<l>to turn back the old days! </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 
 
<milestone unit="speech" n="Seki50"/>
<sp> 
<speaker>Doer</speaker>
 <stage><hi rend="super">off</hi></stage>  
<lg> 
<l>Oh the past, </l>  
<l>I miss it so! </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 
 
<stage> 
She sits at center, staff held over left shoulder, and hides tears. At 
'all the while,' she lifts her head; then gazes up to the eastern sky; 
then listens to temple bell and to cockcrow; at 'caught me,' lowers head. 
</stage> 

 
<p> 
NORIJI<lb/> 
onori-w 
</p>
 
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<lg> 
<l>All the while</l>   
<l>the short night</l>   
<l>of early fall </l>  
<l>begins to break, </l>  
<l>Gateway Temple's bell, </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 
 
<sp> 
<speaker>Doer</speaker> 
<p> 
cocks a-crowing 
</p> 
</sp> 
 
<sp> 
<speaker>Chorus</speaker> 
<lg> 
<l>tell abroad dawn's</l>  
<l>caught me, ah, </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 
 
<sp> 
<speaker>Doer</speaker> 
<p> 
the Forest of Vergogne 
</p> 
 
<stage> 
She stands, leaning on her staff. 
</stage> 
 
<p> 
never will hide me now. 
</p> 
 
<stage> 
She bows her head toward Sideman, then makes her way toward hut. 
</stage> 
 
<lg> 
<l>Farewell, </l>  
<l>I'm going back, </l>  
<l>says she, </l>  
<l>leans on her staff </l>  
<l>and totters home </l>  
<l>to the straw hut </l>  
<l>whence she came; </l>
</lg> 
 
<stage> 
She enters hut and sits facing front, with staff over her right shoulder. 
</stage> 
   
 
 <pb n="117" id="TylSeki117"/>  
<lg> 
<l>a hundred-year-old crone </l>  
<l>is she called now, </l>  
<l>the ruin of Komachi </l>
</lg> 
 
<stage> 
She checks tears. 
</stage> 
 
<lg> 
<l>is she called now, </l> 
<l>the ruin of Komachi. </l>
</lg> 
</sp> 
 
<stage> 
While music is still playing, she comes out of hut and stands motionless. 
</stage> 
 
 

</div1> 
  
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
 
