<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="VeaShak"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>
<TEI.2 id="VeaShak"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Was Shakespeare a Barber? The Secret of the Bard's Private Life 
Revealed at Last</title>
<title type="sort">was shakespeare a barber the secret of the bards private life revealed at last</title>
<author>Veatch, Charles</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>creation of machine-readable version</resp> 
<name>Charles Keller</name>  
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">22</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">VeaShak</idno> 
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476443</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Was Shakespeare a Barber? The Secret of the Bard's Private Life 
Revealed at Last</title>
<title type="sort">was shakespeare a barber the secret of the bards private life revealed at last</title>
<author>Charles Veatch</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Munsey's Magazine</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1916">1916</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume LIX November, 1916 Number II pp. 319-323</p>
</seriesStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme 
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of 
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1914">1914</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-06">June 1994</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Steve Shoemaker</name>
</respStmt>
<item>TEI header and basic markup</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 

<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2"> 

<div1 type="section" id="d3"> <pb n="319" id="VeaShak319"/> 
<head>I</head>
<p> The versatility of the greatest of all dramatists is conceded by 
every one familiar with his plays.  The many-sidedness of that 
masterful genius who "walked in every path of human life, felt 
every passion," is the world's wonder. 
</p><p>Students have devoted much valuable time and consumed many 
gallons of midnight oil in efforts to prove that Shakespeare 
followed most of the vocations open to mankind.  It has been 
shown that he was a finished actor &mdash; not a "strutting player whose 
conceit lies in his hamstring," but an artist competent to hold 
the mirror up to nature.  His attainments as an attorney, "versed 
in strict statutes and most biting laws," have been ably set 
forth. 
</p><p>That he was a warrior, a "manifold linguist, and incomparable 
soldier," can scarcely be doubted; while his achievements as a 

physician, his knowledge of anatomy, and his profound 
accomplishments as an alienist and neurologist have been duly 
exploited by many writers.  He was, moreover, a gardener cunning 
in the lore of plants as well as a subtle discerner of the secret 
springs of emotion; an ardent angler, who could sit all day upon 
a rock in the hot sun, like Patience on a monument, waiting to 
</p> 
<lg><l>See the fish</l> 
<l>Cut with her golden oars the silver stream</l> 
<l>And greedily devour the treacherous bait.</l> 
</lg> 
 
<p>Shakespeare, too, was a skilled metaphysician and an expert 
logician.  He was  a courtier of rare grace, a diplomat, a 
<pb n="320" id="VeaShak320"/>man of the world, a lawyer's clerk, a pedagogue with a 
rod in pickle for the youngster "creeping like a snail 
unwillingly to school."  Some investigators in this fertile field 
have proved to their satisfaction that the poet was a butcher; 
and it has even been suggested that he conducted an intelligence 
office, from <hi rend="italic">Pistol's</hi> remark in "Henry IV": 
</p> 
<lg> 
<l>Have we not <hi rend="italic">Hiren</hi> here?</l> 
</lg> 
 
<p>In fact, Shakespeare seems to have been not only a jack of 
all trades but complete master thereof.  A character in "Macbeth" 
remarks: 
</p> 
<lg> 
<l>I had thought to have let in some of all professions.</l> 
</lg> 
 
<p>Undoubtedly, when those words were penned, the poet must have 
had the barber's trade in mind.  For I shall now proceed to prove 
that if internal evidence counts for anything, Shakespeare was a 
barber of skill and experience, possessing a thorough knowledge 
of his craft. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d4"> 
<head>AN HONORABLE CALLING</head> 
 
<p>My revelation will in nowise lower this "myriad-minded man" 
in the just estimation of the world.  The mystery of shaving is 
not only ancient but honorable.  In the poet's time it was 
counted as one of the learned professions, inasmuch as the barber 
was often called upon to perform the duties of a surgeon, such as 
bleeding a customer &mdash; apart from any accidental slip of the 
razor &mdash; and occasionally extracting a troublesome molar.  That 
Shakespeare was familiar with both these operations may be shown 
by countless citations from his plays, such as the famous line in 
"Julius Caesar": 
</p> 
<lg> 
<l>This was the most unkindest cut of all &mdash; </l> 
</lg> 
<p> 
and the following from "Much Ado About Nothing": 
</p> 
<lg> 
<l>I have the toothache, draw it.</l> 
</lg> 
<p>Nor does the calling of a barber offer any obstacle to the 
exercise of the poetic faculty.  On the contrary, it may develop 
and foster the divine afflatus, as witness Jacques Jasmin of 
Gascony, Folez, the German poet, Burchiello, the Italian 
sonneteer, and Allan Ramsay, all reputed barbers whose effusions 
shed a golden glory over the tonsorial gild. 
</p><p>Shakespeare must have spent much of his time in a barber-shop.  His plays are so full of allusions to the craft, and his 
<hi rend="italic">dramatis personae</hi> exhibit such familiar knowledge of hair and 
whiskers, that it is difficult to avoid the thought that the 
"sweet swan of Avon" learned to shave before he began to sing. 
As he was not indifferent to those "attributes of awe and majesty 
wherein doth sit the dread and fear of kings," it cannot be urged 
that he would consider barbering beneath his dignity, especially 
when royalty set the example.  Note this passage from "Henry V": 
 </p>
<lg> 
<l>It is no English treason to cut French crowns, and to-morrow</l> 
<l>the king himself will be a clipper.</l> 
</lg> 
 
<p>In considering the theory that Shakespeare was a barber, it 
should be borne in mind that his father was a wool-comber &mdash; 
manifestly a calling closely akin to that of the hair-cutter. 
Here we have strong circumstantial evidence; for in early times 
trades commonly descended from sire to son.  Perhaps the poet was 
articled to his father, for he says somewhere: 
 </p>
<lg> 
<l>Must I not serve a long apprenticehood?</l> 
</lg> 
 
<p>Among the almost innumerable ways of spelling the poet's name 
we find "Shaxberd" and "Shakberd," variants possessing peculiar 
significance in the present discussion.  Nothing could be 
plainer, even to a wayfaring man, that in the unsettled 
orthography of the period these are simply forms of 
"Shakebeard" &mdash; a descriptive appellation needing no comment.  It 
points as directly to the barber-shop as does "Smith" to the 
smithy. </p>
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d5"> 
<head>TWO STRIKING CRYPTOGRAMS</head> 
 
<p>At this juncture it will be necessary to allude momentarily 
to the well-nigh moribund and altogether tiresome Bacon-<pb n="321" id="VeaShak321"/> 
Shakespeare controversy &mdash; not to establish any truth of history, 
but to point a way out to misguided enthusiasts who, in their 
efforts to filch the poet's good name, find themselves deeply 
floundering in cryptogrammic mire. 
</p><p>Remembering that surnames were in many instances derived from 
occupations followed by their owners, we find the <hi rend="italic">King</hi> in 
"Hamlet" saying: 
 </p>
<lg> 
<l>You must not think</l> 
<l>That we are made of stuff so flat and dull</l> 
<l>That we can let our <hi rend="italic">beard</hi> be <hi rend="italic">shook</hi>.</l> 
</lg> 
<p> 
Again, this is from "King Lear": 
</p> 
<lg> 
<l>If you did wear a beard upon your chin,</l> 
<l>I'd <hi rend="italic">shake</hi> it upon this quarrel.</l> 
</lg> 
 
<p>These fateful lines contain two transparent cryptograms, 
wherein the real author's name is so thinly veiled that he who 
runs may read, swift Baconite though he be.  It requires no 
arbitrary juggling with figures, no biliteral alphabets, no 
devious approaches by ways that are dark and tricks that are vain 
to show from these two passages that "Shakebeard"  (Shakberd-Shaxberd-Shakespeare) is the only genuine "concealed poet," the 
mighty master who was not of an age but for all time. 
</p><p>Here is a revelation that shines like a good deed in a 
naughty world.  In an instant, in the twinkling of an eye, as it 
were, the foundations of the flimsy Baconian structure are swept 
away, and the edifice, built up with so much care by its 
ingenious architects, vanishes like the baseless fabric of a 
vision, leaving not a rack behind. 
</p><p>After reading George Meredith's "Shaving of Shagpat," Dante 
Gabriel Rossetti declared that he was strongly reminded of 
Shakespeare.  No doubt the suggestive alliteration of the title 
had something to do with the remark, but Rossetti had probably 
been already convinced that Shakespeare was a barber, after 
carefully studying the cumulative evidence of the plays.  It is 
significant that "Shagpat" so closely resembles "Shagsper," one 
of the variant spellings of the poet's name. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d6"> 
<head>TONSORIAL PHRASES IN THE PLAYS</head> 
 
<p>Although &mdash; perhaps owing to the great dramatist's personal 
modesty &mdash; no barbers appear in the throng of people who crowd 
Shakespeare's stage, there is no lack of the lingo of that 
profession.  Kings and queens, lords and ladies, knights, fools, 
and country louts all use tonsorial phrases with an ease and 
gusto attainable only through expert knowledge. 
</p><p>"Did I not pluck thee by the nose?" says <hi rend="italic">Lucio</hi> &mdash; a 
familiarity common to the fraternity at the present day.  In 
"Coriolanus," <hi rend="italic">Marcius</hi> exclaims with professional yearning, "Oh, 
let me clip ye" &mdash; whereat one is reminded of <hi rend="italic">Petruchio's</hi> "Here's 
snip and nip and cut and slit and slash." 
</p><p>"Comb down his hair," suggests <hi rend="italic">Cardinal Beaufort</hi>, and 
<hi rend="italic">Antonio</hi>, of "The Tempest," longs for the day when newborn chins 
be rough and razorable."  The gay gallant in Shakespeare's time, 
"trimmed like a younker," went "prancing to his love, while his 
chin, new-reaped, showed like a stubble-field at harvest home." 
</p><p>There must have been shampooing in Shakespeare's shop.  To 
prove it, there is <hi rend="italic">Iago's</hi> boast: 
 </p>
<lg> 
<l>I have rubbed this young quat almost to the sense.</l> 
</lg> 
 
<p><hi rend="italic">Hamlet's</hi> "Aye, there's the rub," expressed his satisfaction 
in the soothing process.  As the barber hastened his knotted and 
combined locks to part, mayhap he fell asleep, "perchance to 
dream," under the soporific touch of nimble digits.  Yet even in 
a simple shampoo the poet points a moral, as when he makes the 
poor <hi rend="italic">Queen</hi> in "Richard III" say: 
 </p>
<lg> 
<l>The world is full of rubs.</l> 
</lg> 
 
<p>It is generally believed that singeing the ends of the hair 
or beard, to stimulate growth, is a modern invention; yet this 
seems to have been a common practise <pb n="322" id="VeaShak322"/>in Shakespeare's shop. 
<hi rend="italic">Hamlet</hi> tried it, for he speaks of "singeing his pate," and 
<hi rend="italic">Lear</hi> exclaims: 
</p> 
<lg> 
<l>Singe my white head.</l> 
</lg> 
<p>On one occasion, at least, the operation met with a 
disastrous ending; in the "Comedy of Errors" mention is made of 
one "whose beard they have singed off." 
</p>
</div1>
 
<div1 type="section" id="d7">
<head>EVIDENCE HEAPED ON EVIDENCE</head> 
 
<p>As an expert craftsman, Shakespeare assuredly took a laudable 
pride in, his trade, but he was not blind to certain foibles of 
the profession.  For instance, one of his characters thus refers 
to the barber's well-known penchant for putting the shaving-brush 
in a patron's mouth: 
</p> 
<lg> 
<l>I will not ope my lips so wide that a bristle may enter,</l> 
</lg> 
 
<p>As for hair-dye, Buckingham remarks: 
</p> 
<lg> 
<l>That dye is on me which makes my whitest part black.</l> 
</lg> 
 
<p>It was no doubt with full technical knowledge of dyes and 
restoratives that <hi rend="italic">Henry</hi> V declared: 
</p> 
<lg> 
<l>A black beard will turn white, and a curled pate will grow</l> 
<l>bald.</l> 
</lg> 
 
<p>As it is now generally conceded that there is nothing new 
under the sun, the "lady barber" is of course an old story. 
Shakespeare mentions several, among them <hi rend="italic">Helen of Troy</hi>. 
<hi rend="italic">Pandarus</hi>, happening into the shop one day, noticed that famous 
damsel scrutinizing the fifty-two hairs in the sparse beard of 
<hi rend="italic">Troilus</hi>, and he "could not choose but laugh to think how she 
tickled his chin with her marvelous white hand." 
</p><p>The shrewish <hi rend="italic">Kate</hi> ranks high as a barberess.  Especially is 
she noted for the introduction of certain novelties in the 
business, such as combing <hi rend="italic">Hortensio's</hi> noddle with a three-legged stool, a proceeding well calculated to make each 
particular hair stand on end "like quills upon the fretful 
porpentine."  Another, less famous, was <hi rend="italic">Bianca</hi>, but the poet 
throws little light upon the lady's professional qualifications. 
The only hint to show that she was connected with the trade is 
her expression in "Othello": 
</p> 
<lg> 
<l>Come, you are next.</l> 
</lg> 
 
<p>If further evidence should be needed to establish the theory 
herein advanced, it can be found in Shakespeare's requirements 
for a first-class shop.  "Have napkins about you" is the advice 
in "Macbeth," and <hi rend="italic">Grumio's</hi> command is: 
</p> 
<lg> 
<l>Let the heads be sleekly combed and the blue coats brushed.</l> 
</lg> 
 
<p>Every barber has an "oily palm," of course, and, like 
<hi rend="italic">Richard III</hi>, is often "at charges for a lookin &mdash; glass."  Other 
specifications for the poet's shop are "best water brought by 
conduits" and "all the perfumes of Arabia," together with 
unguents with whose sweet smell the air shall be perfumed." 
Emblazoned upon the walls might be seen <hi rend="italic">Perdita's</hi> friendly 
greeting: 
</p> 
<lg> 
<l>You are welcome to our shearing.</l> 
</lg>  
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d8"> 
<head>THE BARD AND THE LABOR QUESTION</head> 
 
<p>In these days of industrial unrest it will be of interest to 
learn Shakespeare's position on the labor question.  Not only do 
the dramas testify to the fact that he was a barber, but they 
contain evidence of his membership in a barbers' union.  In 
"Richard III" a disgruntled party asks: 
</p> 
<lg> 
<l>Shall I strike?</l> 
</lg> 
 
<p><hi rend="italic">Hamlet's</hi> query, "Is thy union here?" and old <hi rend="italic">Polonius's</hi> 
mention of a "walkout" are significant indications that organized 
labor had secured a foothold in the poet's time.  Moreover, in 
addition to many other corroborative passages in the plays, one 
of the speakers complains of a "sore injunction," and another 
declares: 
</p> 
<lg> 
<l>At these injunctions every one doth swear.</l> 
</lg> 
 
<p>The big commentators have unaccountably missed a point here. 
<hi rend="italic">"To</hi> these injunctions" is the reading in most texts, and 
probably would have remained so but for an erudite member of 
<pb n="323" id="VeaShak323"/> 
a local union, who suggested the emendation as above. 
The ingenious substitution of "at" for "to" lends new force to the 
lines, and will doubtless be adopted as a happy rendering of an 
otherwise obscure statement. 
</p><p>Such forceful expressions make it reasonably apparent that 
the attitude of the unions toward this legal process has not 
changed since Shakespeare's day, and are curiously prophetic of 
present conditions.  Even the matter of Sunday closing did not 
escape the poet's attention, for he avows a, brotherly sympathy 
for the barber "whose sore task does not divide the Sunday from 
the week." 
</p><p>Truly, "the barber's chair fits all," and many of the great 
bard's immortals have reclined therein.  "I must to the barber-shop," says the peerless <hi rend="italic">Bottom</hi>, "for methinks I am marvelous 
hairy about the face."  We have <hi rend="italic">Falstaff's</hi> word for it that 
<hi rend="italic">Bardolph</hi> was shaved at least once, "and lost many a hair."  His 
face, all whelks and knobs, would have been a grievous task for 
an artist even of Shakespeare's skill.  It is pleasant to think 
of that arrant rogue with basin beneath his chin, his wonderful 
nose shedding a lurid glare, like a Pharos, over the wide expanse 
of snowy lather, and wincing under a dull razor amid the ribald 
gibes of <hi rend="italic">Fat Jack</hi> and bombastic <hi rend="italic">Pistol.</hi> 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d9"> 
<head>THE SHAVEN AND THE UNSHAVEN</head> 
 
<p><hi rend="italic">Marc Antony</hi> was a steady patron of the shop, and a stickler 
for a close shave, being "barbered ten times o'er" prior to a 
call upon <hi rend="italic">Cleopatra</hi>."  I could not endure a husband with a 
beard," said <hi rend="italic">Beatrice</hi>, whereon <hi rend="italic">Benedick</hi> hiked to the shop, 
and the "old ornament of his cheek" went to stuff tennis-balls. 
</p><p>For the most part, Shakespeare's characters were well-groomed 
in this respect, but some of them exhibited a marked antipathy to 
razors and shears.  There is no evidence that <hi rend="italic">Sir Andrew 
Aguecheek</hi>, whose excellent head of hair hung like flax from a 
distaff, was ever tonsured.  <hi rend="italic">Pericles</hi>, too "swore never to wash 
his face nor comb his hairs," nor must we forget our old military 
friend, "the soldier, bearded like the pard," who was so busy 
seeking bubbles that he had little time to think of a barber. 
</p><p>Another was a certain lover whose "browny locks did hang in 
crooked curls," while a most persistent offender was <hi rend="italic">Young 
Gobbo</hi>, who sported "more hair on his chin than Dobbin had on his 
tail." 
</p><p>In his own shop Shakespeare was urbane and obliging to every 
patron, and so generous that he would not "quarrel with a man 
that hath a hair more or a hair less in his beard."  This would 
be high praise for a journeyman working by the day, but when it 
can be said of an artist doing piece-work it is strong evidence 
to show that the confidence of the ages in Shakespeare's nobility 
of mind has not been misplaced.  And in this respect what a 
marked contrast between the poet and the impatient <hi rend="italic">Hotspur</hi>, who 
stood ready to meet all comers, even to cavil over the ninth part 
of a hair." 
</p><p>We may rest serenely confident that Master Will Shakespeare 
had a good and lucrative business.  As for his customers, he 
could say, with <hi rend="italic">Marie</hi>, in "Twelfth Night": 
 
</p>
<lg> 
<l>I have them at my fingers' ends.</l> 
</lg> 

</div1> 
<div1 type="poem" id="d10"> 

<lg>
<head>EFFICIENCY</head> 
 
<l>ALL things are changing.  Sudden gone from me 
</l><l>The gods of prudence and propriety &mdash; 
</l><l>Those little gods whose law was fear; 
</l><l>The god of dauntless souls is here! 
</l><l>Nor fast nor fawning will his favor gain; 
</l><l>The weakling offers prayers to him in vain. 
</l><l>But one commandment his:  "Succeed!" 
</l><l>"Do!" is his law, "I dare!" his creed. 
</l></lg> 
<signed>Lannie Haynes Martin</signed> 
 
<trailer>[The end] </trailer>

</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2>
