<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="VebBarb"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="VebBarb"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Barbarian Status of Women</title>
<title type="sort">barbarian status of women</title>
<author>Veblen, Thorstein, 1857-1929</author>
<editor>Small, Albion W.</editor>
<respStmt> 
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>McMaster University</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">31</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">VebBarb</idno> 
<date value="2001">2001</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2001 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476444</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Barbarian Status of Women</title>
<title level="j">The American Journal of Sociology</title>
<title type="sort">barbarian status of women</title>
<author>Thorstein Veblen</author>
<editor>Albion W. Small</editor>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>pp. 503-514</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher> 
<pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace> 
<date value="1898">1898-99</date> 
<idno type="callNo">source copy consulted: UVa Alderman library, call number HM 1 .A7 v.4 1898-99</idno>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Pages in the original source have been replaced with xerox copies, pages 497-512.  Reason unknown.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1898">1898</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term> 
<term>prose</term> 
<term>masculine</term> 
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2001-06">June 2001</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Jayme Schwartzberg, Etext center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>added TEI header and tags</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 

<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="503"/> <head>The Barbarian Status of Women</head> 
<div2 type="section" id="d4"> 
<p>It seems altogether probable that in the primitive groups of 
mankind, when the race first took to a systematic use of tools 
and so emerged upon the properly human plane of life, there was 
but the very slightest beginning of a system of status, with 
little of invidious distinction between classes and little of a 
corresponding division of employments. In an earlier paper, 
published in this JOURNAL,<ref target="n1">[1]</ref> it has been argued that the early 
division of labor between classes comes in as the result of an 
increasing efficiency of labor, due to a growing effectiveness in 
the use of tools. When, in the early cultural development, the 
use of tools and the technical command of material forces had 
reached a certain degree of effectiveness, the employments which 
occupy the primitive community would fall into two distinct 
groups -(a) the honorific employments, which involve a large 
element of prowess, and (b) the humiliating employments, which 
call for diligence and into which the sturdier virtues do not 
enter. An appreciable advance in the use of tools must precede 
this differentiation of employments, because (1) without 
effective tools (including weapons) men are not sufficiently 
formidable in conflict with the ferocious beasts to devote 
themselves so exclusively to the hunting of large game as to 
develop that occupation into a conventional mode of life reserved 
for a distinct class; (2) without tools of some efficiency, 
industry is not productive enough to support a dense population, 
and therefore the groups into which the population gathers will 
not come into such a habitual hostile contact with one another as 
would give rise to a life of warlike prowess; (3) until 
industrial methods and knowledge have made some advance, the work 
of getting a livelihood is too exacting to admit of the 
consistent exemption of any portion of the community from vulgar 
labor; 
 
<pb n="504"/> 
 
(4) the inefficient primitive industry yields no such 
disposable surplus of accumulated goods as would be worth 
fighting for, or would tempt an intruder, and therefore there is 
little provocation to warlike prowess. 
</p><p>With the growth of industry comes the possibility of a 
predatory life; and if the groups of savages crowd one another in 
the struggle for subsistence, there is a provocation to 
hostilities, and a predatory habit of life ensues. There is a 
consequent growth of a predatory culture, which may for the 
present purpose be treated as the beginning of the barbarian 
culture. This predatory culture shows itself in a growth of 
suitable institutions. The group divides itself conventionally 
into a fighting and a peace-keeping class, with a corresponding 
division of labor. Fighting, together with other work that 
involves a serious element of exploit, becomes the employment of 
the able-bodied men; the uneventful everyday work of the group 
falls to the women and the infirm. 
</p><p>In such a community the standards of merit and propriety rest 
on an invidious distinction between those who are capable 
fighters and those who are not. Infirmity, that is to say 
incapacity for exploit, is looked down upon. One of the early 
consequences of this deprecation of infirmity is a tabu on women 
and on women's employments. In the apprehension of the archaic, 
animistic barbarian, infirmity is infectious. The infection may 
work its mischievous effect both by sympathetic influence and by 
transfusion. Therefore it is well for the able-bodied man who is 
mindful of his virility to shun all undue contact and 
conversation with the weaker sex and to avoid all contamination 
with the employments that are characteristic of the sex. Even the 
habitual food of women should not be eaten by men, lest their 
force be thereby impaired. The injunction against womanly 
employments and foods and against intercourse with women applies 
with especial rigor during the season of preparation for any work 
of manly exploit, such as a great hunt or a warlike raid, or 
induction into some manly dignity or society or mystery. 
Illustrations of this seasonal tabu abound in the early history 
of all peoples that have had a warlike or barbarian past.  
 
<pb n="505"/> 
 
The women, their occupations, their food and clothing, their habitual 
place in the house or village, and in extreme cases even their 
speech, become ceremonially unclean to the men. This imputation 
of ceremonial uncleanness on the ground of their infirmity has 
lasted on in the later culture as a sense of the unworthiness or 
levitical inadequacy of women; so that even now we feel the 
impropriety of women taking rank with men, or representing the 
community in any relation that calls for dignity and ritual 
competency,. as for instance, in priestly or diplomatic offices, 
or even in representative civil offices, and likewise, and for a 
like reason, in such offices of domestic and body servants as are 
of a seriously ceremonial character -footmen, butlers, etc. 
</p><p>The changes that take place in the everyday experiences of a 
group or horde when it passes from a peaceable to a predatory 
habit of life have their effect on the habits of thought 
prevalent in the group. As the hostile contact of one group with 
another becomes closer and more habitual, the predatory activity 
and the bellicose animus become more habitual to the members of 
the group. Fighting comes more and more to occupy men's everyday 
thoughts, and the other activities of the group fall into the 
background and become subsidiary to the fighting activity. In the 
popular apprehension the substantial core of such a group -that 
on which men's thoughts run when the community and the 
community's life is thought of -is the body of fighting men. The 
collective fighting capacity becomes the most serious question 
that occupies men's minds, and gives the point of view from which 
persons and conduct are rated. The scheme of life of such a group 
is substantially a scheme of exploit. There is much of this point 
of view to be found even in the common-sense views held by modern 
populations. The inclination to identify the community with its 
fighting men comes into evidence today whenever warlike interests 
occupy the popular attention in an appreciable degree. 
</p><p>The work of the predatory barbarian group is gradually 
specialized and differentiated under the dominance of this ideal 
of prowess, so as to give rise to a system of status in which the 
non- 
<pb n="506"/> 
 
fighters fall into a position of subservience to the 
fighters. The accepted scheme of life or consensus of opinions 
which guides the conduct of men in such a predatory group and 
decides what may properly be done, of course comprises a great 
variety of details; but it is, after all, a single scheme -a 
more or less organic whole so that the life carried on under its 
guidance in any case makes up a somewhat consistent and 
characteristic body of culture. This is necessarily the case, 
because of the simple fact that the individuals between whom the 
consensus holds are individuals. The thinking of each one is the 
thinking of the same individual, on whatever head and in whatever 
direction his thinking may run. Whatever may be the immediate 
point or object of his thinking, the frame of mind which governs 
his aim and manner of reasoning in passing on any given point of 
conduct is, on the whole, the habitual frame of mind which 
experience and tradition have enforced upon him. Individuals 
whose sense of what is right and good departs widely from the 
accepted views suffer some repression, and in case of an extreme 
divergence they are eliminated from the effective life of the 
group through ostracism. Where the fighting class is in the 
position of dominance and prescriptive legitimacy, the canons of 
conduct are shaped chiefly by the common sense of the body of 
fighting men. Whatever conduct and whatever code of proprieties 
has the authentication of this common sense is definitively right 
and good, for the time being. and the deliverances of this common 
sense are, in their turn, shaped by the habits of life of the 
able-bodied men. Habitual conflict acts, by selection and by 
habituation, to make these male members tolerant of any 
infliction of damage and suffering. Habituation to the sight and 
infliction of suffering, and to the emotions that go with fights 
and brawls, may even end in making the spectacle of misery a 
pleasing diversion to them. The result is in any case a more or 
less consistent attitude of plundering and coercion on the part 
of the fighting body, and this animus is incorporated into the 
scheme of life of the community. The discipline of predatory life 
makes for an attitude of mastery on the part of the able-bodied 
men in all their relations with the weaker members of the group, 
and especially in their  
 
<pb n="507"/> 
 
relations with the women. Men who are 
trained in predatory ways of life and modes of thinking come by 
habituation to apprehend this form of the relation between the 
sexes as good and beautiful. 
</p><p>All the women in the group will share in the class repression 
and depreciation that belongs to them as women, but the status of 
women taken from hostile groups has an additional feature. Such a 
woman not only belongs to a subservient and low class, but she 
also stands in a special relation to her captor. She is a trophy 
of the raid, and therefore an evidence of exploit, and on this 
ground it is to her captor's interest to maintain a peculiarly 
obvious relation of mastery toward her. And since, in the early 
culture, it does not detract from her subservience to the life of 
the group, this peculiar relation of the captive to her captor 
will meet but slight, if any, objection from the other members of 
the group. At the same time, since his peculiar coercive relation 
to the woman serves to mark her as a trophy of his exploit, he 
will somewhat jealously resent any similar freedom taken by other 
men, or any attempt on their part to parade a similar coercive 
authority over her, and so usurp the laurels of his prowess, very 
much as a warrior would under like circumstances resent a 
usurpation or an abuse of the scalps or skulls which he had taken 
from the enemy. 
</p><p>After the habit of appropriating captured women has hardened 
into custom, and so given rise on the one hand to a form of 
marriage resting on coercion, and on the other hand to a concept 
of ownership,<ref target="n2">[2]</ref> a development of certain secondary features of 
the institution so inaugurated is to be looked for. In time this 
coercive ownership-marriage receives the sanction of the popular 
taste and morality. It comes to rest in men's habits of thought 
as the right form of marriage relation, and it comes at the same 
time to be gratifying to men's sense of beauty and of honor. The 
growing predilection for mastery and coercion, as a manly trait, 
together with the growing moral and aesthetic approbation of 
marriage on a basis of coercion and ownership,  
 
<pb n="508"/> 
 
will affect the 
tastes of the men most immediately and most strongly; but since 
the men are the superior class, whose views determine the current 
views of the community, their common sense in the matter will 
shape the current canons of taste in its own image. The tastes of 
the women also, in point of morality and of propriety alike, will 
presently be affected in the same way. Through the precept and 
example of those who make the vogue, and through selective 
repression of those who are unable to accept it, the institution 
of ownership-marriage makes its way into definitive acceptance as 
the only beautiful and virtuous form of the relation. As the 
conviction of its legitimacy grows stronger in each succeeding 
generation, it comes to be appreciated unreflectingly as a 
deliverance of common sense and enlightened reason that the good 
and beautiful attitude of the man toward the woman is an attitude 
of coercion. "None but the brave deserve the fair." 
</p><p>As the predatory habit of life gains a more unquestioned and 
undivided sway, other forms of the marriage relation fall under a 
polite odium. The masterless, unattached woman consequently loses 
caste. It becomes imperative for all men who would stand well in 
the eyes of their fellows to attach some woman or women to 
themselves by the honorable bonds of seizure. In order to a 
decent standing in the community a man is required to enter into 
this virtuous and honorific relation of ownership-marriage, and a 
publicly acknowledged marriage relation which has not the 
sanction of capture becomes unworthy of able-bodied men. But as 
the group increases in size, the difficulty of providing wives by 
capture becomes very great, and it becomes necessary to find a 
remedy that shall save the requirements of decency and at the 
same time permit the marriage of women from within the group. To 
this end the status of women married from within the group is 
sought to be mended by a mimic or ceremonial capture. The 
ceremonial capture effects an assimilation of the free woman into 
the more acceptable class of women who are attached by bonds of 
coercion to some master, and so gives a ceremonial legitimacy and 
decency to the resulting marriage relation. The probable motive 
for adopting the free women into the honorable  
 
<pb n="509"/> 
 
class of bond 
women in this way is not primarily a wish to improve their 
standing or their lot, but rather a wish to keep those good men 
in countenance who, for dearth of captives, are constrained to 
seek a substitute from among the home-bred women of the group. 
The inclinations of men in high standing who are possessed of 
marriageable daughters would run in the same direction. It would 
not seem right that a woman of high birth should irretrievably be 
outclassed by any chance-comer from outside. 
</p><p>According to this view, marriage by feigned capture within 
the tribe is a case of mimicry -"protective mimicry," to borrow 
a phrase from the naturalists. It is substantially a case of 
adoption. As is the case in all human relations where adoption is 
practiced, this adoption of the free women into the class of the 
unfree proceeds by as close an imitation as may be of the 
original fact for which it is a substitute. And as in other cases 
of adoption, the ceremonial performance is by no means looked 
upon as a fatuous make-believe. The barbarian has implicit faith 
in the efficiency of imitation and ceremonial execution as a 
means of compassing a desired end. The entire range of magic and 
religious rites is testimony to that effect. He looks upon 
external objects and sequences naively, as organic and individual 
things, and as expressions of a propensity working toward an end. 
The unsophisticated common sense of the primitive barbarian 
apprehends sequences and events. in terms of will-power or 
inclination. As seen in the light of this animistic 
preconception, any process is substantially teleological, and the 
propensity imputed to it will not be thwarted of its legitimate 
end after the course of events in which it expresses itself has 
once fallen into shape or got under. way. It follows logically, 
as a matter of course, that if once the motions leading to a 
desired consummation have been rehearsed in the accredited form 
and sequence, the same substantial result will be attained as 
that produced by the process imitated. This is the ground of 
whatever efficiency is imputed to ceremonial observances on all 
planes of culture, and it is especially the chief element in 
formal adoption and initiation. Hence, probably, the practice of 
mock-seizure or  
 
<pb n="510"/> 
 
mock-capture, and hence the formal profession of 
fealty and submission on the part of the woman in the marriage 
rites of peoples among whom the household with a male head 
prevails. This form of the household is almost always associated 
with some survival or reminiscence of wife-capture. In all such 
cases, marriage is, by derivation, a ritual of initiation into 
servitude. In the words of the formula, even after it has been 
appreciably softened under the latter-day decay of the sense of 
status, it is the woman's place to love, honor, and obey. 
</p><p>According to this view, the patriarchal household, or, in 
other words, the household with a male head, is an outgrowth af 
emulation between the members of a warlike community. It is, 
therefore, in point of derivation, a predatory institution. The 
ownership and control of women is a gratifying evidence of 
prowess and high standing. In logical consistency, therefore, the 
greater the number of women so held, the greater the distinction 
which their possession confers upon their master. Hence the 
prevalence of polygamy, which occurs almost universally at one 
stage of culture among peoples which have the male household. 
There may, of course, be other reasons for polygamy, but the 
ideal development of polygamy which is met with in the harems of 
very powerful patriarchal despots and chieftains can scarcely be 
explained on other grounds. But whether it works out in a system 
of polygamy or not, the male household is in any case a detail of 
a system of status under which the women are included in the 
class of unfree subjects. The dominant feature in the 
institutional structure of these communities is that of status, 
and the groundwork of their economic life is a rigorous system of 
ownership. 
</p><p>The institution is found at its best, or in its most 
effectual development, in the communities in which status and 
ownership prevail with the least mitigation; and with the decline 
of the sense of status and of the extreme pretensions of 
ownership, such as has been going on for some time past in the 
communities of the western culture, the institution of the 
patriarchal household has also suffered something of a 
disintegration. There has been some weakening and slackening of 
the bonds, and this  
 
<pb n="511"/> 
 
deterioration is most visible in the 
communities which have departed farthest from the ancient system 
of status, and have gone farthest in reorganizing their economic 
life on the lines of industrial freedom. And the deference for an 
indissoluble tie of ownership-marriage, as well as the sense of 
its definitive virtuousness, has suffered the greatest decline 
among the classes immediately engaged in the modern industries. 
So that there seems to be fair ground for saying that the habits 
of thought fostered by modern industrial life are, on the whole, 
not favorable to the maintenance of this institution or to that 
status of women which the institution in its best development 
implies. The days of its best development are in the past, and 
the discipline of modern life -if not supplemented by a prudent 
inculcation of conservative ideals -will scarcely afford the 
psychological basis for its rehabilitation. 
 
</p><p>This form of marriage, or of ownership, by which the man 
becomes the head of the household, the owner of the woman, and 
the owner and discretionary consumer of the household's output of 
consumable goods, does not of necessity imply a patriarchal 
system of consanguinity. The presence or absence of maternal 
relationship should, therefore, not be given definite weight in 
this connection. The male household, in some degree of 
elaboration, may well coexist with a counting of relationship in 
the female line, as, for instance, among many North American 
tribes. But where this is the case it seems probable that the 
ownership of women, together with the invidious distinctions of 
status from which the practice of such an ownership springs, has 
come into vogue at so late a stage of the cultural development 
that the maternal system of relationship had already been 
thoroughly incorporated into the tribe's scheme of life. The male 
household in such cases is ordinarily not developed in good form 
or entirely free from traces of a maternal household. The traces 
of a maternal household which are found in these cases commonly 
point to a form of marriage which disregards the man rather than 
places him under the surveillance of the woman. It may well be 
named the household of the unattached woman. This condition of 
things argues that the tribe or race in question  
 
<pb n="512"/> 
 
has entered upon 
a predatory life only after a considerable period of peaceable 
industrial life, and after having achieved a considerable 
development of social structure under the regime of peace and 
industry, whereas the unqualified prevalence of the patriarchate, 
together-with the male household, may be taken to indicate that 
the predatory phase was entered early, culturally speaking. 
</p><p>Where the patriarchal system is in force in fully developed 
form, including the paternal household, and hampered with no 
indubitable survivals of a maternal household or a maternal 
system of relationship, the presumption would be that the people 
in question has entered upon the predatory culture early, and has 
adopted the institutions of private property and class 
prerogative at an early stage of its economic development. On the 
other hand, where there are well-preserved traces of a maternal 
household, the presumption is that the predatory phase has been 
entered by the community in question at a relatively late point 
in its life history, even if the patriarchal system is, and long 
has been, the prevalent system of relationship. In the latter 
case the community, or the group of tribes, may, perhaps for 
geographical reasons, not have independently attained the 
predatory culture in accentuated form, but may at a relatively 
late date have contracted the agnatic system and the paternal 
household through contact with another, higher, or 
characteristically different, culture, which has included these 
institutions among its cultural furniture. The required contact 
would take place most effectually by way of invasion and conquest 
by an alien race occupying the higher plane or divergent line of 
culture. Something of this kind is the probable explanation, for 
instance, of the equivocal character of the household and 
relationship system in the early Germanic culture, especially as 
it is seen in such outlying regions as Scandinavia. The evidence, 
in this latter case, as in some other communities lying farther 
south, is somewhat obscure, but it points to a long-continued 
coexistence of the two forms of the household; of which the 
maternal seems to have held its place most tenaciously among the 
subject or lower classes of the population, while the  
 
<pb n="513"/> 
 
paternal 
was the honorable form of marriage in vogue among the superior 
class. In the earliest traceable situation of these tribes there 
appears to have been a relatively feeble, but growing, 
preponderance of the male household throughout the community. 
This mixture of marriage institutions, as well as the correlative 
mixture or ambiguity of property institutions associated with it 
in the Germanic culture, seems most easily explicable as being 
due to the mingling of two distinct racial stocks, whose 
institutions differed in these respects. The race or tribe which 
had the maternal household and common property would probably 
have been the more numerous and the more peaceable at the time 
the mixing process began, and would fall into some degree of 
subjection to its more warlike consort race. 
 
</p><p>No attempt is hereby made to account for the various forms of 
human marriage, or to show how the institution varies in detail 
from place to place and from time to time, but only to indicate 
what seems to have been the range of motives and of exigencies 
that have given rise to the paternal household, as it has been 
handed down from the barbarian past of the peoples of the western 
culture. To this end, nothing but the most general features of 
the life history of the institution have been touched upon, and 
even the evidence on which this much of generalization is based 
is, per force, omitted. The purpose of the argument is to point 
out that there is a close connection, particularly in point of 
psychological derivation, between individual ownership, the 
system of status, and the paternal household, as they appear in 
this culture. 
</p><p>This view of the derivation of private property and of the 
male household, as already suggested, does not imply the prior 
existence of a maternal household of the kind in which the woman 
is the head and master of a household group and exercises a 
discretionary control over her husband or husbands and over the 
household effects. Still less does it imply a prior state of 
promiscuity. What is implied by the hypothesis and by the scant 
evidence at hand is rather the form of the marriage relation 
above characterized as the household of the unattached woman. The 
characteristic feature of this marriage seems to  
 
<pb n="514"/> 
 
have been an 
absence of coercion or control in the relation between the sexes. 
The union (probably monogamic and more or less enduring) seems to 
have been terminable at will by either party, under the 
constraint of some slight conventional limitations. The 
substantial difference introduced into the marriage relation on 
the adoption of ownership-marriage is the exercise of coercion by 
the man and the loss on the part of the woman of the power to 
terminate the relation at will. Evidence running in this 
direction, and in part hitherto unpublished, is to be found both 
in the modern and in the earlier culture of Germanic communities. 
</p><p>It is only in cases where circumstances have, in an 
exceptional degree, favored the development of ownership-marriage 
that we should expect to find the institution worked out to its 
logical consequences. Wherever the predatory phase of social life 
has not come in early and has not prevailed in unqualified form 
for a long time, or wherever a social group or race with this 
form of the household has received a strong admixture of another 
race not possessed of the institution, there the prevalent form 
of marriage should show something of a departure from this 
paternal type. And even where neither of these two conditions is 
present, this type of the marriage relation might be expected in 
the course of time to break down with the change of 
circumstances, since it is an institution that has grown up as a 
detail of a system of status, and, therefore, presumably fits 
into such a social system, but does not fit into a system of a 
different kind. It is at present visibly breaking down in modern 
civilized communities, apparently because it is at variance with 
the most ancient habits of thought of the race, as well as with 
the exigencies of a peaceful, industrial mode of life. There may 
seem some ground for holding that the same reassertion of ancient 
habits of thought which is now apparently at work to disintegrate 
the institution of ownership-marriage may be expected also to 
work a disintegration of the correlative institution of private 
property; but that is perhaps a question of speculative curiosity 
rather than of urgent theoretical interest.</p> 
 
<trailer> THE UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO. 
<lb/> 
THORSTEIN VEBLEN. </trailer> 
</div2> 
 
<div2 type="notes" id="d5"> 
<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">1.</seg> <p>"The Instinct of Workmanship and the Irksomeness of Labor," 
September 1898, pp. 187-210.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n2"><seg type="note-symbol">2.</seg> <p>For a more detailed discussion of this point see a paper on 
"The Beginnings of Ownership" in this JOURNAL for November, 1898.</p></note> 
</div2> 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
