<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="VilNegr"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

 
<TEI.2 id="VilNegr"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Negro in the Regular Army</title>
<title type="sort">negro in the regular army</title>
<author>Villard, Oswald Garrison</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">35</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">VilNegr</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476447</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Negro in the Regular Army</title>
<title type="sort">negro in the regular army</title>
<author>Oswald Garrison Villard</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher> 
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace> 
<date value="1903">1903</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>91</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Villard, Oswald Garrison.  "The Negro in the Regular Army."  
<hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 91 (1903): 721-729.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1903">1903</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term> 
<term>African American</term>
<term>American Civil War</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-08">August 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added header, Tagged with TEI.2-compatible SGML, Parsed against "teilite" dtd</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 

<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="721"/>
	<head>THE NEGRO IN THE REGULAR ARMY.</head> 
 
<p>WHEN the Fifty-fourth Massachusetts Regiment stormed Fort 
Wagner July 18, 1863, only to be driven back with the loss of its 
colonel, Robert Gould Shaw, and many of its rank and file, it 
established for all time the fact that the colored soldier would 
fight and fight well.  This had already been demonstrated in 
Louisiana by colored regiments under the command of General Godfrey 
Weitzel in the attack upon Port Hudson on May 27 of the same year.  
On that occasion regiments composed for the greater part of raw 
recruits, plantation hands with centuries of servitude under the 
lash behind them, stormed trenches and dashed upon cold steel in 
the hands of their former masters and oppressors.  After that there 
was no more talk in the portion of the country of the "natural 
cowardice" of the negro.  But the heroic qualities of Colonel Shaw, 
his social prominence and that of his officers, and the comparative 
nearness of their battlefield to the North, attracted greater and 
more lasting attention to the daring and bravery of their exploit, 
until it finally became fixed in many minds as the first real 
baptism of fire of colored American soldiers. 
</p><p>After Wagner the recruiting of colored regiments, originally 
opposed by both North and South, went on apace, particularly under 
the Federal government, which organized no less than one hundred 
and fifty-four, designated as "United States Colored Troops."  
Colonel Shaw's raising of a colored regiment aroused quite as much 
comment in the North because of the race prejudice it defied, as 
because of the novelty of the new organization.  General Weitzel 
tendered his resignation the instant General B. F. Butler assigned 
black soldiers to his brigade, and was with difficulty induced to 
serve on.  His change of mind was a wise one, and not only because 
these colored soldiers covered him with glory at Port Hudson.  It 
was his good fortune to be the central figure in one of the 
dramatic incidents of a war that must ever rank among the most 
thrilling and tragic the world has seen.  The black cavalrymen who 
rode into Richmond, the first of the Northern troops to enter the 
Southern capital, went in waving their sabres and crying to the 
negroes on the sidewalks, "We have come to set you free!"  They 
were from the division of Godfrey Weitzel, and American history has 
no more stirring moment. 
</p><p>In the South, notwithstanding the raising in 1861 of a colored 
Confederate regiment by Governor Moore of Louisiana (a magnificent 
body of educated colored men which afterwards became the First 
Louisiana National Guards of General Weitzel's brigade and the 
first colored regiment in the Federal Army), the feeling against 
negro troops was insurmountable until the last days of the 
struggle.  Then no straw could be overlooked.  When, in December, 
1863, Major-General Patrick R. Cleburne, who commanded a division 
of Hardee's Corps of the Confederate Army of the Tennessee,<pb n="722"/>  
sent in a paper in which the employment of the slaves as soldiers 
of the South was vigorously advocated, Jefferson Davis indorsed it 
with the statement, "I deem it inexpedient at this time to give 
publicity to this paper, and request that it be suppressed."  
General Cleburne urged that "freedom within a reasonable time" be 
granted to every slave remaining true to the Confederacy, and was 
moved to this action by the valor of the Fifty-fourth 
Massachusetts, saying, "If they [the negroes] can be made to face 
and fight bravely against their former masters, how much more 
probable is it that with the allurement of a higher reward, and led 
by those masters, they would submit to discipline and face 
dangers?" 
</p><p>With the ending of the civil war the regular army of the 
United States was reorganized upon a peace footing by an act of 
Congress dated July 28, 1866.  In just recognition of the bravery 
of the colored volunteers six regiments, the Ninth and Tenth 
Cavalry and the Thirty-eighth, Thirty-ninth, Fortieth, and Forth-first Infantry, were designated as colored regiments.  When the 
army was again reduced in 1869, the Thirty-eighth and Forty-first 
became the Twenty-fourth Infantry, and the Thirty-ninth and 
Fortieth became the Twenty-fifth.  This left four colored regiments 
in the regular army as it was constituted from 1870 until 1901.  
There has never been a colored artillery organization in the 
regular service. 
</p><p>To these new regiments came a motley mixture of veterans of 
volunteer organizations, newly released slaves, and some freedmen 
of several years' standing but without military experience.  They 
were eager to learn, and soon showed the same traits which 
distinguish the black regiments to-day,&mdash;loyalty to their officers 
and to their colors, sobriety and courage, and a notable pride in 
the efficiency of their corps.  But if ever officers had to "father 
and mother" their soldiers they were the company officers of these 
regiments.  The captains in particular had to be bankers, 
secretaries, advisers, and judges for their men.  As Lieutenant 
Grote Hutcheson has stated it, "The men knew nothing, and the non-commissioned officers but little more.  From the very circumstances 
of their preceding life it could not be otherwise.  They had no 
independence, no self-reliance, not a thought except for the 
present, and were filled with superstition."  Yet the officers were 
determined to prove the wisdom of the experiment.  To do this they 
were forced to give their own attention to the minutest details of 
military administration, and to act as non-commissioned officers.  
The total lack of education among the men necessitated an enormous 
amount of writing by the officers.  In the Ninth Cavalry only one 
man was found able to write well enough to be sergeant-major, and 
not for several years was it possible to obtain troop clerks.  When 
the Tenth Cavalry was being recruited an officer was sent to 
Philadelphia with the express purpose of picking up educated 
colored men for the non-commissioned positions.  Difficult as the 
tasks of the officers thus were, most of them felt well repaid for 
their unusual labors by the affectionate regard in which they were 
held by their soldiers, and by the never-failing good humor with 
which the latter went about their duties. 
</p><p>As the years passed the character of the colored soldiers 
naturally changed.  In place of the war veterans, and of the men 
whose chains of servitude had just been struck off, came young men 
from the North and East with more education and more self-reliance.  
They depended less upon their officers, both in the barracks and in 
the field, yet they reverenced and cared for them as much as did 
their predecessors.  Their greatest faults then as now were 
gambling and quarreling.  On the other hand, the negro regiments 
speedily became favorably known because of greater sobriety and of 
<pb n="723"/>  fewer desertions than among the white soldiers.  It was the 
Ninth Cavalry which a few years ago astonished the army by 
reporting not a single desertion in twelve months, an unheard-of 
and perhaps undreamed-of record.  In all that goes to make a good 
soldier, in drill, fidelity, and smartness, the negro regular from 
the first took front rank. 
</p><p>Nor was there ever any lack of the fighting quality which had 
gratified the nation at Fort Wagner, or at Fort Blakely, Ala., 
where the Seventy-third Colored Infantry, under Colonel Henry C. 
Merriam, stormed the enemy's works, in advance of orders, in one of 
the last actions of the war.  It soon fell to the lot of the Ninth 
and Tenth Cavalry to prove that the negroes could do as well under 
fire in the Indian wars as they had when fighting for the freedom 
of their race.  While the Twenty-fourth and Twenty-fifth Infantry 
had merely garrison work to do, the Ninth and Tenth Cavalry scouted 
for years against hostile Indians in Texas, New Mexico, Colorado, 
and Kansas, always acquitting themselves honorably.  In September, 
1868, a little over two years after their organization, three 
troops of the Ninth Cavalry did well in an action against Indians 
at Horsehead Hills, Texas.  When General George A. Forsyth and his 
detachment of fifty scouts were surrounded and "corralled" by seven 
hundred Indians on an island in the Republican River, it was the 
troop of Captain Louis H. Carpenter, of the Tenth Cavalry, which 
first came to their rescue.  Similarly when Major T. T. Thornburg's 
command was nearly wiped out by Utes in 1879, it was Captain F. S. 
Dodge's Troop D of the Ninth which succeeded in reaching it in 
time, losing all its horses in so doing.  This regiment alone took 
part in sixty Indian fights between 1868 and 1890, during which 
time it lost three officers and twenty-seven men killed, and had 
three officers and thirty-four men wounded.  The Tenth Cavalry's 
casualties were also heavy during this same period, and it fought 
for many years over a most difficult country in New Mexico and 
Arizona, taking a conspicuous part in running to earth Geronimo's 
and Victoria's bands of Apaches. 
</p><p>On one of these campaigns Lieutenant Powhatan H. Clarke gave 
effective proof of the affection which the officers of colored 
regiments have for their men.  In the fight in the Pineto Mountains 
with a portion of Geronimo's forces this young Southerner risked 
his life to save a colored sergeant who had fallen wounded in an 
open space where both he and his rescuer were easy marks for the 
Apaches.  For this gallant act Lieutenant Clarke rightly received 
a medal of honor.  The Twenty-fourth Infantry, on the other hand, 
has contributed a striking instance of the devotion of colored 
soldiers to their officers.  When Major Joseph W. Wham, paymaster, 
was attacked by robbers on May 11, 1889, his colored escort fought 
with such gallantry that every one of the soldiers was awarded a 
medal of honor or a certificate of merit.  Some of them stood their 
ground although badly wounded, notably Sergeant Benjamin Brown, who 
continued to fight and to encourage his men until shot through both 
arms.  In a fight against Apaches in the Cuchilo Negro Mountains of 
New Mexico on August 16, 1881, Moses Williams, First Sergeant of 
Troop I, Ninth Cavalry, displayed such gallantry that he was given 
a medal of honor by common consent.  When the only officer with the 
detachment, Lieutenant Gustavus Valois, had his horse shot under 
him, and was cut off from his men, Sergeant Williams promptly 
rallied the detachment, and conducted the right flank in a running 
fight for several hours with such coolness, bravery, and 
unflinching devotion to duty that he undoubtedly saved the lives of 
at least three comrades.  His action in standing by and rescuing 
Lieutenant Valois was the more noteworthy because he and his men 
were subjected, in an exposed position, to a heavy fire <pb n="724"/>  
from a large number of Indians.  For splendid gallantry against 
Indians, while serving as sergeant of Troop K, Ninth Cavalry, on 
May 14, 1880, and August 12, 1881, George Jordan was also given a 
medal of honor.  Five of the medal of honor men now in the service 
are colored soldiers, while fifteen others have "certificates of 
merit" also awarded for conspicuous deeds of bravery. 
</p><p>It was not until the battle of Santiago, however, that the 
bulk of the American people realized that the standing army 
comprised regiments composed wholly of black men.  Up to that time 
only one company of colored soldiers had served at a post east of 
the Mississippi.  Even Major, later Brigadier-General, Guy V. 
Henry's gallop to the rescue of the Seventh Cavalry on December 30, 
1890, with four troops of the Ninth Cavalry, attracted but little 
attention.  This feat was the more remarkable because Major Henry's 
command had just completed a march of more than one hundred miles 
in twenty-four hours.  But in the battle at Santiago, the four 
colored regiments won praise from all sides, particularly for their 
advance upon Kettle Hill, in which the Rough Riders also figured.  
>From the very beginning of the movement of the army after its 
landing, the negro troops were in the front of the fighting, and 
contributed largely to the successful result.  Although they 
suffered heavy losses, especially in officers, the men fought with 
the same gallantry they had displayed on the plains, as is attested 
by the honors awarded.  In every company there were instances of 
personal gallantry.  The first sergeants especially lived up to the 
responsibilities placed upon them.  The color sergeant of the Tenth 
Cavalry, Adam Houston, bore to the front not only his own flags, 
but those of the Third Cavalry when the latter's color sergeant was 
shot down.  In several emergencies where troops or companies lost 
their white officers, the senior sergeants took command and handled 
their men in a faultless manner, notably in the Tenth Cavalry. 
</p><p>Indeed, the conduct of these men has done much to dispel the 
old belief that colored soldiers will fight only when they have 
efficient white officers.  This may well have been true at one 
period of the civil war when the colored race as a whole had never 
even had the responsibilities attaching to free men.  It is growing 
less and less true as time passes and better educated men enter the 
ranks.  in recognition of their achievements at Santiago a number 
of these black non-commissioned officers were made commissioned 
officers in several of the so-called "immune" regiments of United 
States Volunteers raised in July, 1898.  None of these 
organizations were in service long enough to become really 
efficient, and a few were never properly disciplined.  
Nevertheless, a majority of the officers promoted from the colored 
regulars bore themselves well under exceedingly trying 
circumstances.  Some of them, and a number of regular sergeants and 
corporals who had succeeded to their former places, were made 
lieutenants and captains in the Forty-eighth and Forty-ninth 
Volunteer Infantry, which served in the Philippines for two years, 
and to which we shall recur later. 
</p><p>At Santiago the characteristic cheerfulness of the negro 
soldiers was as striking as their bravery.  In his little book 
called The Nth Foot In War, Lieutenant M. B. Stewart says of them:--</p><p>"The negro troops were in a high good humor.  They had made 
the charge of the day; they had fought with a dash and vigor which 
forever established their reputation as fighters, and which would 
carry them down in the pages of history.  To have heard them that 
night no one would have ever thought that they had lived for twelve 
mortal hours under a galling fire.  They were laughing and joking 
over the events of the day, in the same manner they would have done 
had they been returning from a picnic. <pb n="725"/>  
</p><p>"'Golly,' laughed a six-foot sergeant, 'dere was music in de 
air sho' nuff.  Dat lead was flying around in sheets, I tell you.  
I seen a buzzard flying around in front of our line, and I says to 
myself, "Buzzard, you is in a mighty dangerous position.  You 
better git out uf dat, 'cause dey ain't room out dar for a 
muskeeter."'  Another remarked, 'Say, did you see dat man Brown; 
pity dat man been killed.  He'd a been a corporal, sho.' 
</p><p>"In the utter exhaustion of the moment all race and social 
distinctions were forgotten.  Officers lay down among their men and 
slept like logs.  The negro troops sought out soft places along the 
sides of the road and lay down with their white comrades.  There 
was a little commotion among the latter, and an officer was heard 
to yell: 'Here, you man, take your feet off my stomach.  Well, I'll 
be damned if it ain't a nigger.  Get out, you black rascal.'  As 
the commotion subsided, the negro was heard to remark, 'Well, if 
dat ain't de mos' particler man I ever see.'" 
</p><p>Characteristic also is a story of the negro cavalryman who, 
returning to the rear, said to some troops anxious to get to the 
front: "Dat's all right, gemmen; don't git in a sweat; dere's lots 
of it lef' for you.  You wants to look out for dese yere 
sharpshooters, for dey is mighty careless with dere weapons, and 
dey is specially careless when dey is officers aroun'." 
</p><p>As soon as the army settled down in the trenches before 
Santiago, smuggled musical instruments&mdash;guitars, banjos, mouth 
organs, and what not&mdash;appeared among the negro troops as if by 
magic, and they were ever in use.  It was at once a scene of 
cheerfulness and gayety, and the officers had their usual trouble 
in making the men go to sleep instead of spending the night in 
talking, singing, and gaming.  In the peaceful camp of the Third 
Alabama, in that state, the scenes were similar.  There was always 
"a steady hum of laughter and talk, dance, song, shout, and the 
twang of musical instruments."  It was "a scene full of life and 
fun, of jostling, scuffling, and racing, of clown performances and 
cake-walks, of impromptu minstrelsy, speech-making, and preaching, 
of deviling, guying, and fighting, both real and mimic."  The 
colonel found great difficulty in getting men to work alone.  Two 
would volunteer for any service.  "Colonel," said a visitor to the 
camp, "your sentinels are sociable fellows.  I saw No. 5 over at 
the end of his beat entertaining No. 6 with some fancy manual of 
arms.  Afterwards, with equal amiability, No. 6 executed a most 
artistic cake-walk for his friend."  It must be remembered here 
that this colonel's men were typical Southern negroes, literate and 
illiterate, and all new to military life. 
</p><p>In addition to the Forty-eighth and Forty-ninth Volunteers, 
the four regular colored regiments have served in the Philippines.  
Here the work was particularly trying and the temptations to 
misconduct many.  The Filipino women were especially attractive to 
the men because of their color, and it is on record that several 
soldiers were tempted from their allegiance to the United States.  
Two of these, whose sympathy and liking for the Filipinos overcame 
their judgment, paid the full penalty of desertion, being hanged by 
their former comrades.  Both belonged to the Ninth Cavalry.  On the 
other hand, in a remarkable order issued by General A. S. Burt in 
relinquishing command of the Twenty-fifth Infantry, on April 17, 
1902, on his promotion to brigadier-general, he was able to quote 
the Inspector-General of the army as saying: "The Twenty-fifth 
Infantry is the best regiment I have seen in the Philippines."  
General Burt praised highly the excellent conduct of the enlisted 
men while in the Archipelago, which proved to his mind that the 
American negroes are "as law-abiding as any race in the world." 
</p><p>Three of General Burt's sergeants, <pb n="726"/>  Russell, McBryar, 
and Hoffman, were promoted to the Forty-eighth and Forty-ninth 
Volunteers, and served, as lieutenants, for several months with 
their old regiment, the Twenty-fifth, until the arrival of their 
new regiments in Manila.  During this time they were frequently 
under fire.  General Burt bore high testimony to their soldierly 
bearing, their capacity and ability, and expressed great regret 
when he was forced to let them go.  McBryar had won a medal of 
honor for gallantry against Indians in Arizona in 1890.  In the 
Forty-ninth Volunteers, Company L, composed wholly of colored men, 
and commanded by Captain Edward L. Baker, a colored veteran of 
Santiago, who had served for seventeen years in the Ninth and Tenth 
Cavalry and in the Tenth "Immunes," made a wonderful record.  
According to a statement which was widely published at the time and 
never denied, this company had on its rolls during a period of 
twelve months one hundred and six men who were fit for duty at all 
times and never lost a day on account of sickness.  No white 
company remotely approached this record.  More extraordinary still 
is the fact that during this same period not one of these men ever 
went before a court-martial.  This is surely a striking 
illustration of what can be done by colored officers.  It is 
noticeable, too, that neither the officers nor the men of any 
colored regiment have figured in the charges and counter-charges 
arising out of the use of the water-torture, except one man who at 
the time of his offense was not with his regiment.  The Forty-ninth 
Volunteers was a very unhappy regiment during its brief life, but 
its troubles were largely due to its white officers.  One of these, 
a major, was dismissed for misconduct, and his place was filled by 
the senior captain, a colored man.  Several other white officers 
and one colored captain got into serious trouble, the last being 
dismissed.  The Forty-eighth was, on the contrary, a contented 
organization in which the colored officers were treated in a kindly 
and courteous manner by their white associates and superiors.  The 
two regiments afford a striking illustration of Napoleon's saying, 
"There are no such things as poor regiments,&mdash;only poor colonels." 
</p><p>The negro regiment unquestionably calls for different 
treatment from that which would be accorded to white troops, just 
as the Indian troops of King Edward's army require different 
handling from that called for in the case of the King's Royal 
Rifles.  Yet as fighting machines, the Indian soldiers may be the 
equals if not the superiors of the Englishmen.  Major Robert L. 
Bullard, Twenty-eighth United States Infantry who commanded the 
colored Third Alabama Volunteers, already referred to, during the 
war with Spain, discusses in a remarkable paper published in the 
United Service Magazine for July, 1901, the differences between 
negro and white soldiers.  They are so great, he says, as to 
require the military commander to treat the negro as a different 
species.  He must fit his methods of instruction and discipline to 
the characteristics of the race.  Major Bullard adds that 
"mistakes, injustices, and failures would result from his making 
the same rules and methods apply to the two races without regard to 
how far apart set by nature or separated by evolution."  But Major 
Bullard would unquestionably concede that these differences in no 
way require a treatment of the negro soldier which implies that he 
is an inferior being and which ever impresses upon him his 
inferiority.  Yet this seems to have been the case in the Forty-ninth United States Volunteers. 
</p><p>In the regular army, as well as in the volunteers, officers 
have frequently appealed with success to the negroes' pride of 
race, and have urged them on to greater efficiency and better 
behavior by reminding them that they have the honor of their people 
in their hands.  To <pb n="727"/>  such appeals there is ever a prompt 
response.  One of the most effective ways of disciplining an 
offender is by holding him up to the ridicule of his fellows.  The 
desire of the colored soldiers to amuse and to be amused gives the 
officers an easy way of obtaining a hold upon them and their 
affections.  The regimental rifle team, the baseball nine, the 
minstrel troupe, and the regimental band offer positions of 
importance for which the competition is much keener than in the 
white regiments.  There is also a friendly rivalry between 
companies, which is much missed elsewhere in the service.  The 
negroes are natural horsemen and riders.  It is a pleasure to them 
to take care of their mounts, and a matter of pride to keep their 
animals in good condition.  Personally they are clean and neat, and 
they take the greatest possible pride in their uniforms.  In no 
white regiment is there a similar feeling.  With the negroes the 
canteen question is of comparatively slight importance, not only 
because the men can be more easily amused within their barracks, 
but because their appetite for drink is by no means as strong as 
that of the white men.  Their sociability is astonishing.  They 
would rather sit up and tell stories and crack jokes than go to 
bed, no matter how hard the day has been. 
</p><p>The dark sides are, that the negro soldiers easily turn 
merited punishment into martyrdom, that their gambling propensities 
are almost beyond control, that their habit of carrying concealed 
weapons is incurable, and that there is danger of serious fighting 
when they fall out with one another.  Frequent failure to act 
honorably toward a comrade in some trifling matter is apt to cause 
scuffling and fighting until the men are well disciplined.  Women 
are another cause of quarrels, and are at all times a potent 
temptation to misconduct and neglect of duty.  It is very difficult 
to impress upon the men the value of government property, and duty 
which requires memorizing of orders is always the most difficult to 
teach.  For the study of guard duty manuals or of tactics they have 
no natural aptitude.  The non-commissioned officers are of very 
great importance, and in the regulars they are looked up to and 
obeyed implicitly, much more so than is the case with white troops.  
It is necessary, however, for the officers to back up the sergeants 
and corporals very vigorously, even when they are slightly in the 
wrong.  Then colored men are more easily "rattled" by poor officers 
than are their white comrades.  There was a striking instance of 
this two or three years ago when a newly appointed and wholly 
untrained white officer lost his head at a post in Texas.  His 
black subordinates, largely recruits, followed suit, and in 
carrying out his hysterical orders imperiled many lives in the 
neighboring town.  Selections for service with colored troops 
should therefore be most carefully made.  Major Bullard declares 
that the officer of negro troops "must not only be an officer and 
a gentleman, but he must be considerate, patient, laborious, self-sacrificing, a man of affairs, and he must have knowledge and 
wisdom in a great lot of things not really military." 
</p><p>If the position of a white officer is a difficult one, that of 
the colored officer is still more so.  He has not the self-assumed 
superiority of the white man, naturally feels that he is on trial, 
and must worry himself incessantly about his relations to his white 
comrades of the shoulder straps.  While the United States Navy has 
hitherto been closed to negroes who aspire to be officers, the army 
has pursued a wiser and more just policy.  The contrast between the 
two services is really remarkable.  On almost every war vessel 
white and black sailors sleep and live together in crowded quarters 
without protest or friction.  But the negro naval officer is kept 
out of the service by hook or by crook for <pb n="728"/>  the avowed 
reason that the cramped quarters of the wardroom would make 
association with him intolerable.  In the army, on the other hand, 
the experiment of mixed regiments has never been tried.  A good 
colored soldier can nevertheless obtain a commission by going 
through West Point, or by rising from the ranks, or by being 
appointed directly from civil life. 
</p><p>Since the foundation of the Military Academy there have been 
eighteen colored boys appointed to West Point, of whom fifteen 
failed in their preliminary examinations, or were discharged after 
entering because of deficiency in studies.  Three were graduated 
and commissioned as second lieutenants of cavalry, Henry Ossian 
Flipper, John Hanks Alexander, and Charles Young.  Of these, 
Lieutenant Flipper was dismissed June 30, 1882, for "conduct 
unbecoming an officer and a gentleman."  The other two proved 
themselves excellent officers, notably Young, who is at this 
writing a captain, and a most efficient one, in the Ninth Cavalry, 
with which he recently served in the Philippines.  Lieutenant 
Alexander died suddenly in 1894.  In announcing his death in a 
regimental order his colonel spoke of him in terms of high praise, 
and did not use the customary stereotyped phrases of regret.  His 
fellow white officers all had good words for him.  There never was 
more striking testimony to the discipline and spirit of fairness at 
West Point than was afforded by the sight of Cadet Charles Young, 
who is of very dark complexion, commanding white cadets.  Nothing 
else has impressed foreign visitors at West Point half so much. 
</p><p>An equally remarkable happening, and one which speaks even 
more for the democratic spirit in the army, was the commissioning 
in 1901 of Sergeant-Major Benjamin O. Davis, Ninth Cavalry, and of 
Corporal John E. Green, Twenty-fourth Infantry.  Both these men 
were examined by boards of white officers, who might easily have 
excluded them because of color prejudice, in which case there would 
have been no appeal from their findings.  Lieutenant Davis's former 
troop commander, a West Pointer, openly rejoiced at his success, 
and predicted that he would make an excellent officer.  These are 
the first two colored men to rise from the ranks, but there will be 
many more if the same admirable spirit of fair play continues to 
rule in the army and is not altered by outside prejudice.  It was 
thought that there would be a severe strain upon discipline when a 
colored officer rose to the rank of captain and to the command of 
white officers.  But in Captain Young's case his white subordinates 
seem to have realized that it is the position and rank that they 
are compelled to salute and obey, and not the individual.  This 
principle is at the bottom of all discipline.  Only too frequently 
do subordinates throughout the army have to remind themselves of 
this when obeying men for whose social qualities and character they 
have neither regard nor respect.  During the war with Spain Captain 
Young commanded a negro battalion from Ohio, which was pronounced 
the best drilled organization in the large army assembled at Camp 
Alger near Washington.  In addition to these officers, Captain John 
R. Lynch, formerly a Congressman from Mississippi, and four colored 
chaplains represent their race on the commissioned rolls of the 
army.  All of these men are doing well.  One colored chaplain was 
dismissed for drunkenness in 1894.  Beyond this their record is 
unblemished. 
</p><p>Despite the fairness shown in these appointments, there has 
been considerable very just criticism of the War Department for its 
failure to appoint to the regulars any of the colored officers who 
did well in the Forty-eighth and Forty-ninth Volunteers.  Every 
colonel of volunteers was allowed to designate for examination for 
appointment to the regular army the best officers in his regiment 
<pb n="729"/>  Hundreds of white officers were selected in this way, but 
not a single colored officer was given an examination,&mdash;not even 
Lieutenant McBryar, with his medal of honor, or Captain Baker.  
Similarly fault has been found with Secretary Root because no new 
colored regiments were established under the law of February 2, 
1901, increasing the army by five regiments of infantry, five of 
cavalry, and a large number of companies of artillery.  The excuse 
most often heard is that the negroes already have sufficient 
representation in comparison with the percentage of negroes to 
white persons within the borders of the United States.  But the 
sterling characteristics of the colored soldiers, their loyalty to 
the service as shown by the statistics of desertion, and, above 
all, their splendid service in Cuba, should have entitled them to 
additional organizations.  To say the least, the decision of the 
War Department smacks considerably of ingratitude.  Nevertheless, 
the negro regiments have come to stay, both in the regulars and in 
the volunteers.  The hostilities of the last five years have 
dispelled any doubt which may have existed upon this point. 
</p><signed>                         <hi rend="italic"> Oswald Garrison Villard.</hi></signed> 
 
 
</div1>
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
 
