<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WasReli"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
<TEI.2 id="WasReli"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Religious Life of the Negro.</title>
<title type="sort">religious life of the negro</title>
<author>Washington, Booker T.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">13</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WasReli</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476462</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Religious Life of the Negro.</title>
<title type="sort">religious life of the negro</title>
<author>Booker T. Washington</author>
</titleStmt> 
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>North American Review</publisher> 
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace> 
<date value="1905">1905</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">North American Review</hi> 181 (July 1905): 20-23.</p>
</seriesStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of 
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1905">1905</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term> 
<term>democracy</term> 
<term>religion</term>
</keywords> 
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-12">December 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Deirdre Johnson, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Header added, basic TEI markup added</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2"> 

<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="20"/> 
	<head>THE RELIGIOUS LIFE OF THE NEGRO.<lb/> 
BY BOOKER T. WASHINGTON, PRINCIPAL OF THE TUSKEGEE NORMAL<lb/> 
AND INDUSTRIAL INSTITUTE.</head> 
 
<p>IN everything that I have been able to read about the 
religious life of the Negro, it has seemed to me that writers have 
been too much disposed to treat of it as something fixed and 
unchanging.  They have not sufficiently emphasized the fact that 
the Negro people, in respect to their religious life, have been, 
almost since they landed in America, in a process of change and 
growth. 
</p><p>The Negro came to America with the pagan idea of his African 
ancestors; he acquired under slavery a number of Christian ideas, 
and at the present time he is slowly learning what those ideas mean 
in practical life.  He is learning, not merely what Christians 
believe, but what they must do to be Christians. 
</p><p>The religious ideas which the Negroes brought with them to 
America from Africa were the fragments of a system of thought and 
custom, which, in its general features, is common to most barbarous 
people.  What we call "fetichism" is, I suppose, merely the 
childish way of looking at and explaining the world, which did not, 
in the case of the people of West Africa, preclude a belief in the 
one true God, although He was regarded by them as far away and not 
interested in the little affairs of men. 
</p><p>But the peculiarity of their primitive religion, as I have 
learned from a very interesting book written by one who has been 
many years a missionary in Africa, consists in this, that it sought 
for its adherents a purely "physical salvation." 
</p><p>In the religion of the native African there was, generally 
speaking, no place of future reward or punishment, no heaven and no 
hell, as we are accustomed to conceive them.  For this reason, the 
Negro had little sense of sin.  He was not tortured by doubts and 
fears, which are so common and, we sometimes feel, 
<pb n="21"/> 
so necessary a part of the religious experiences of Christians.  The 
evils he knew were present and physical. 
</p><p>During the period of servitude in the New World, the Negro 
race did not wholly forget the traditions and habits of thought 
that it brought from Africa.  But it added to its ancestral stock 
certain new ideas. 
</p><p>Slavery, with all its disadvantages, gave the Negro race, by 
way of recompense, one great consolation, namely, the Christian 
religion and the hope and belief in a future life.  The slave, to 
whom on this side of the grave the door of hope seemed closed, 
learned from Christianity to lift his face from earth to heaven, 
and that made his burden lighter.  In the end, the hope and 
aspiration of the race in slavery fixed themselves on the vision of 
the resurrection, with its "long white robes and golden slippers." 
</p><p>This hope and this aspiration, which are the theme of so many 
of the old Negro hymns, found expression in the one institution 
that slavery permitted to the Negro people&mdash;the Negro Church.  It 
was natural and inevitable that the Negro Church, coming into 
existence as it did under slavery, should permit the religious life 
of the Negro to express itself in ways almost wholly detached from 
morality.  There was little in slavery to encourage the sense of 
personal responsibility. 
</p><p>The attitude of some Negro communities in this respect is very 
clearly illustrated in the story of the slave who was a "professor" 
of religion, in the current phrase of the time, but made his master 
so much trouble by his persistence in certain immoral practices 
that it was finally necessary to call in a clergyman to try to 
reform him.  The clergyman made the attempt, and sought to bring 
the terrors of the law to bear upon the slave's conscience. 
</p><p>"Look yeah, Massa," said the culprit, "don't de Scripture say, 
Dem who b'lieves an' is baptize' shall be saved?" 
</p><p>"Certainly," was the reply, and the clergyman went on to 
explain the passage to him, but the slave interrupted him again. 
</p><p>"Jus' you tell me now, Massa, don't de good book say dese 
words: 'Dem as b'lieve and is baptize' shall be saved?'" 
</p><p>"Yes, but&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Dat's all I want to know, sar.  Now, wat's de use of talkin' 
to me.  You ain't ago'n to make me believe wat de blessed Lord say 
ain't so, not if you tries forever." 
</p><p>This illustrates one of the difficulties that we have to 
contend 
<pb n="22"/> 
with to-day.  In our Tuskegee Negro Conference, we 
have constantly to insist that the people draw moral distinctions 
within the limits of their own communities, that they get rid of 
immoral ministers and school-teachers, and refuse to associate with 
people whom they know to be guilty of immoral practices. 
</p><p>It has been said that the trouble with the Negro Church is 
that it is too emotional.  It seems to me that what the Negro 
Church needs is a more definite connection with the social and 
moral life of the Negro people.  Could this connection be effected 
in a large degree, it would give to the movement for the upbuilding 
of the race the force and inspiration of a religious motive.  It 
would give to the Negro religion more of that missionary spirit, 
the spirit of service, that it needs to purge it of some of the 
worst elements that still cling to it. 
</p><p>The struggle to attain a higher level of living, to get land, 
to build a home, to give their children an education, just because 
it demands more earnestness and steadfastness of purpose, gives a 
steadiness and a moral significance to the religious life, which is 
the thing the Negro people need at present. 
</p><p>A large element of the Negro Church must be recalled from its 
apocalyptic vision back to the earth; the members of the Negro race 
must be taught that mere religious emotion that is guided by no 
definite idea and is devoted to no purpose is vain. 
</p><p>It is encouraging to notice that the leaders of the different 
denominations of the Negro Church are beginning to recognize the 
force of the criticism made against it, and that, under their 
leadership, conditions are changing.  In one of these 
denominations, the A. M. E. Zion Church alone, &dollar;2,000,000 was 
raised, from 1900 to 1904, for the general educational, moral and 
material improvement of the race.  Of this sum, &dollar;1,000,000 was 
contributed for educational purposes alone.  The A. M. E. Church 
and the Baptists did proportionally as well. 
</p><p>The mere fact that this amount of money has been raised for 
general educational purposes, in addition to the sum expended in 
each local community for teachers, for building schoolhouses and 
supplementing the State appropriations for schools, shows that the 
colored people have spent less money in saloons and dispensaries; 
that less has been squandered on toys and gimcracks that are of no 
use.  It shows that there has been more saving, more thought for 
the future, more appreciation of the real value of life. 
<pb n="23"/> 
</p><p>In this connection, it is well to have in mind that the 
industrial schools have performed a great and useful service, in so 
far as they have impressed upon the young men who go out from these 
schools as preachers the importance of learning a trade, something 
of agriculture, so that they can give the members of their 
congregations an example of industrial thrift. 
</p><p>At Tuskegee Institute, we insist upon the importance of 
service.  Every student in this department is expected to do, in 
connection with his other work either as a teacher or preacher, 
some part of the social and religious work that is carried on under 
the direction of the Bible Training School in the surrounding 
country.  We are seeking to imbue these young men who are going 
forth as leaders of their people with the feeling that the great 
task of uplifting the race, though it may be for others merely a 
work of humanity, for them, and every other member of the Negro 
race, is a work of religion. 
</p><p>In this great modern world, where every individual has so many 
interests and life is so complicated there is a tendency to let 
religion and life drift apart.  I meet men every day who, honest 
and upright though they be, have lost in their daily lives this 
connection with religion, and are striving vainly to regain it. 
There is no one great dominating motive in their lives which enters 
into every task and gives it significance and zest. 
</p><p>It is one of the compensations which hardships bring, that the 
race problem is a thing so real and so present to the Negro people 
that it enters, as a motive, into everything they do.  It is this 
that makes it possible for them to realize that the acts of every 
individual have an importance far beyond the measure in which they 
make or mar his or her personal fortunes. 
</p><p>So soon as a man, white or black, really learns to comprehend 
that fact, he will cease to whine and complain, and he will be 
content to do his best, humble though it be, to improve his own 
condition, and to help his less fortunate fellows. 
</p><p>Slowly but surely, and in ever larger numbers, the members of 
my race are learning that lesson; they are realizing that God has 
assigned to their race a man's part in the task of civilization; 
they are learning to understand their duty, and to face 
uncomplainingly and with confidence the destiny that awaits them. 
</p> 
<signed>BOOKER T. WASHINGTON.</signed> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
