<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WelCran"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]>
<TEI.2 id="WelCran"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Stephen Crane. From an English Standpoint</title>
<title type="sort">stephen crane from an english standpoint</title>
<author>Crane review: Wells, H. G.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>creator of electronic version</name> 
<resp>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</resp> 
<name>creator of image(s)</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">28</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WelCran</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476467</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Stephen Crane. From an English Standpoint.</title>
<title type="sort">stephen crane from an english standpoint</title>
<author>Crane review: H. G. Wells</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>North American Review Publishing Company</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York: Franklin Square</pubPlace> 
<date value="1900-08">August, 1900</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>North American Review, Vol CLXXI, No. DXXV, August, 
1900, pp. 233-242</p>
</seriesStmt>  
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center 
scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1900-08">August, 1900</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-12">December, 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Bryson Clevenger, Jr.</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Minimal TEI tagging, TEI header</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="article" id="d3">  <pb n="233" id="WelCran233"/>
<head>Wells, H. G.  "Stephen Crane, from an English Standpoint."<lb/> 
     <hi rend="italic">North American Monthly Review</hi> 171 (Aug. 1900): 233-242. 
</head> 

 
<p>THE untimely death at thirty of Stephen Crane robs English 
literature of an interesting and significant figure, and the little 
world of those who write, of a stout friend and a pleasant comrade. 
</p><p> 
For a year and more he had been ailing.  The bitter hardships of 
his Cuban expedition had set its mark upon mind and body alike, and 
the slow darkling of the shadow upon him must have been evident to 
all who were not blinded by their confidence in what he was yet to 
do.  Altogether, I knew Crane for less than a year, and I saw him 
for the last time hardly more than seven weeks ago.  He was then in 
a hotel at Dover, lying still and comfortably wrapped about, before 
an open window and the calm and spacious sea.  If you would figure 
him as I saw him, you must think of him as a face of a type very 
typically American, long and spare, with very straight hair and 
straight features and long, quiet hands and hollow eyes, moving 
slowly, smiling and speaking slowly, with that deliberate New 
Jersey manner he had, and lapsing from speech again into a quiet 
contemplation of his ancient enemy.  For it was the sea that had 
taken his strength, the same sea that now shone, level waters 
beyond level waters, with here and there a minute, shining ship, 
warm and tranquil beneath the tranquil evening sky.  Yet I felt 
scarcely a suspicion then that this was a last meeting.  One might 
have seen it all, perhaps.  He was thin and gaunt and wasted, too 
weak for more than a remembered jest and a greeting and good 
wishes.  It did not seem to me in any way credible that he would 
reach his refuge in the Black Forest only to die at the journey's 
end.  It will be a long time yet before I can fully realize that he 
is no longer a contemporary of mine; that the last I saw of him 
was, indeed, final and complete.  
<pb n="234" id="WelCran234"/>
</p><p>Though my personal acquaintance with Crane was so soon 
truncated, I have followed his work for all the four years it has 
been known in England.  I have always been proud, and now I am 
glad, that, however obscurely, I also was in the first chorus of 
welcome that met his coming.  It is, perhaps, no great distinction 
for me; he was abundantly praised; but, at least, I was early and 
willing to praise him when I was wont to be youthfully jealous of 
my praises.  His success in England began with "The Red Badge of 
Courage," which did, indeed, more completely than any other book 
has done for many years, take the reading public by storm.  Its 
freshness of method, its vigor of imagination, its force of color 
and its essential freedom from many traditions that dominate this 
side of the Atlantic, came&mdash;in spite of the previous shock of Mr. 
Kipling&mdash;with a positive effect of impact.  It was a new thing, in 
a new school.  When one looked for sources, one thought at once of 
Tolstoi; but, though it was clear that Tolstoi had exerted a 
powerful influence upon the conception, if not the actual writing, 
of the book, there still remained something entirely original and 
novel.  To a certain extent, of course, that was the new man as an 
individual; but, to at least an equal extent, it was the new man as 
a typical young American, free at last, as no generation of 
Americans have been free before, of any regard for English 
criticism, comment or tradition, and applying to literary work the 
conception and theories of the cosmopolitan studio with a quite 
American directness and vigor.  For the great influence of the 
studio on Crane cannot be ignored; in the persistent selection of 
the essential elements of an impression, in the ruthless exclusion 
of mere information, in the direct vigor with which the selected 
points are made, there is Whistler even more than there is Tolstoi 
in "The Red Badge of Courage."  And witness this, taken almost 
haphazard: 
 
</p><p>"At nightfall the column broke into regimental pieces, and 
the 
fragments went into the fields to camp.  Tents sprang up like 
strange plants.  Camp fires, like red, peculiar blossoms, dotted 
the night. * * *  From this little distance the many fires, with 
the black forms of men passing to and fro before the crimson rays, 
made weird and satanic effects." 
 
</p><p>And here again; consider the daring departure from all 
academic requirements, in this void countenance: 
 
</p><p>"A warm and strong hand clasped the youth's languid fingers 
for an instant, and then he heard a cheerful and audacious 
whistling as  
<pb n="235" id="WelCran235"/>

the man strode away.  As he who had so 
befriended him was thus passing out of his life, it suddenly 
occurred to the youth that he had not once seen his face." 
 
</p><p>I do not propose to add anything here to the mass of 
criticism 
upon this remarkable book.  Like everything else which has been 
abundantly praised, it has occasionally been praised "all wrong;" 
and I suppose that it must have been said hundreds of times that 
this book is a subjective study of the typical soldier in war.  But 
Mr. George Wyndham, himself a soldier of experience, has pointed 
out in an admirable preface to a re-issue of this and other of 
Crane's war studies, that the hero of the "Red Badge" is, and is 
intended to be, altogether a more sensitive and imaginative person 
than the ordinary man.  He is the idealist, the dreamer of boastful 
things brought suddenly to the test of danger and swift occasions 
and the presence of death.  To this theme Crane returned several 
times, and particularly in a story called "Death and the Child" 
that was written after the Greek war.  That story is considered by 
very many of Crane's admirers as absolutely his best.  I have 
carefully re-read it in deference to opinions I am bound to 
respect, but I still find it inferior to the earlier work.  The 
generalized application is, to my taste, a little too evidently 
underlined; there is just that touch of insistence that prevails so 
painfully at times in Victor Hugo's work, as of a writer not sure 
of his reader, not happy in his reader and seeking to drive his 
implication (of which also he is not quite sure) home.  The child 
is not a natural child; there is no happy touch to make it 
personally alive; it is THE CHILD, something unfalteringly big; a 
large, pink, generalized thing, I cannot help but see it, after the 
fashion of a Vatican church.  The fugitive runs panting to where, 
all innocent of the battle about it, it plays; and he falls down 
breathless to be asked, "Are you a man?"  One sees the intention 
clearly enough; but in the later story it seems to me there is a 
new ingredient that is absent from the earlier stories, an 
ingredient imposed on Crane's natural genius from without&mdash;a 
concession to the demands of a criticism it had been wiser, if less 
modest, in him to disregard&mdash;criticism that missed this quality of 
generalization and demanded it, even though it had to be 
artificially and deliberately introduced. 
</p><p>Following hard upon the appearance of "The Red Badge of 
Courage" in England came reprints of two books, "Maggie" and  
<pb n="236" id="WelCran236"/>

"George's Mother," that had already appeared in America six 
years earlier.  Their reception gave Crane his first taste of the 
peculiarities of the new public he had come upon.  These stories 
seem to me in no way inferior to the "Red Badge;" and at times 
there are passages, the lament of Maggie's mother at the end of 
"Maggie," for example, that it would be hard to beat by any passage 
from the later book.  But on all hands came discouragement or tepid 
praise.  The fact of it is, there had been almost an orgie of 
praise&mdash;for England, that is; and ideas and adjectives and phrases 
were exhausted.  To write further long reviews on works displaying 
the same qualities as had been already amply discussed in the 
notices of the "Red Badge" would be difficult and laborious; while 
to admit an equal excellence and deny an equal prominence would be 
absurd.  But to treat these stories as early work, to find them 
immature, dismiss them and proceed to fresher topics, was obvious 
and convenient.  So it was, I uncharitably imagine, that these two 
tales have been overshadowed and are still comparatively unknown.  
Yet, they are absolutely essential to a just understanding of 
Crane.  In these stories, and in these alone, he achieved 
tenderness and a compulsion of sympathy for other than vehement 
emotions, qualities that the readers of "The Third Violet" and "On 
Active Service," his later love stories, might well imagine beyond 
his reach. 
</p><p>And upon the appearance of these books in England came what, 
in my present mood, I cannot but consider as the great blunder and 
misfortune of Crane's life.  It is a trait of the public we writers 
serve, that to please it is to run the gravest risk of never 
writing again.  Through a hundred channels and with a hundred 
varieties of seduction and compulsion, the public seeks 
to induce its favorite to do something else&mdash;to act, to lecture, to 
travel, to jump down volcanoes or perform in music halls, to do 
anything, rather than to possess his soul in peace and to pursue 
the work he was meant to do.  Indeed, this modern public is as 
violently experimental with its writers as a little child with a 
kitten.  It is animated, above all things, by an insatiable desire 
to plunge its victim into novel surroundings, and watch how he 
feels.  And since Crane had demonstrated, beyond all cavil, that he 
could sit at home and, with nothing but his wonderful brain and his 
wonderful induction from recorded things, build up the truest and 
most convincing picture of war; since he was a fastidious 
<pb n="237" id="WelCran237"/>
and careful worker, intensely subjective in his mental habit; since 
he was a man of fragile physique and of that unreasonable courage 
that will wreck the strongest physique; and since, moreover, he was 
habitually a bad traveller, losing trains and luggage and missing 
connections even in the orderly circumstances of peace, it was 
clearly the most reasonable thing in the world to propose, it was 
received with the applause of two hemispheres as a most right and 
proper thing, that he should go as a war correspondent, first to 
Greece and then to Cuba.  Thereby, and for nothing but 
disappointment and bitterness, he utterly wrecked his health.  He 
came into comparison with men as entirely his masters in this work 
as he was the master of all men in his own; and I read even in the 
most punctual of his obituary notices the admission of his 
journalistic failure.  I have read, too, that he brought back 
nothing from these expeditions.  But, indeed, even not counting his 
death, he brought back much.  On his way home from Cuba he was 
wrecked, and he wrote the story of the nights and days that 
followed the sinking of the ship with a simplicity and vigor that 
even he cannot rival elsewhere. 
</p><p>"The Open Boat" is to my mind, beyond all question, the 
crown 
of all his work.  It has all the stark power of the earlier 
stories, with a new element of restraint; the color is as full and 
strong as ever, fuller and stronger, indeed; but those chromatic 
splashes that at times deafen and confuse in "The Red Badge," those 
images that astonish rather than enlighten, are disciplined and 
controlled.  "That and 'Flanagan'," he told me, with a 
philosophical laugh, "was all I got out of Cuba."  I cannot say 
whether they were worth the price, but I am convinced that these 
two things are as immortal as any work of any living man.  And the 
way "The Open Boat" begins, no stress, plain&mdash;even a little gray 
and flattish: 
 
</p><p>"None of them knew the color of the sky.  Their eyes glanced 
level, and were fastened upon the waves that swept toward them.  
These waves were of the hue of slate, save for the tops, which were 
of foaming white, and all of the men knew the color of the sea.  
The horizon narrowed and widened, and dipped and rose, and at all 
times its edge was jagged with waves that seemed thrust up in 
points like rocks. 
</p><p>"Many a man ought to have a bath-tub larger than the boat 
which here rode upon the sea.  These waves were most wrongfully and 
barbarously abrupt and tall, and each froth-top was a problem in 
small-boat navigation.  
<pb n="238" id="WelCran238"/>
</p><p>"The cook squatted in the bottom, and looked with both eyes 
at 
the six inches of gunwale which separated him from the ocean.  His 
sleeves were rolled over his fat forearms, and the two flaps of his 
unbuttoned vest dangled as he bent to bail out the boat.  Often he 
said, 'Gawd!  That was a narrow clip.'  As he remarked it, he 
invariably gazed eastward over the broken sea. 
</p><p>"The oiler, steering with one of the two oars in the boat, 
sometimes raised himself suddenly to keep clear of the water that 
swirled in over the stern.  It was a thin little oar and it seemed 
often ready to snap. 
</p><p>"The correspondent, pulling at the other oar, watched the 
waves and wondered why he was there." 
 
</p><p>From that beginning, the story mounts and mounts over the 
waves, wave frothing after wave, each wave a threat, and the men 
toil and toil and toil again; by insensible degrees the day lights 
the waves to green and olive, and the foam grows dazzling.  Then as 
the long day draws out, they come toward the land. 
 
</p><p>"'Look!  There's a man on the shore!' 
</p><p>"'Where?' 
</p><p>"'There!  See 'im?' 
</p><p>"'Yes, sure!  He's walking along.' 
</p><p>"'Now he's stopped.  Look!  He's facing us!' 
</p><p>"'So he is, by thunder!' 
</p><p>"'Ah, now we're all right!  Now we're all right!  There'll 
be 
a boat out here for us in half-an-hour.' 
</p><p>"'He's going on.  He's running.  He's going up to that home 
there.' 
</p><p>"The remote beach seemed lower than the sea, and it required 
a searching glance to discern the little black figure.  The captain 
saw a floating stick and they rowed to it.  A bath-towel was by 
some weird chance in the boat, and, tying this on the stick, the 
captain waved it.  The oarsman did not dare turn his head, so he 
was obliged to ask questions. 
</p><p>"'What's he doing now?' 
</p><p>"'He's standing still again.  He's looking, I think. . . .  
There he goes again.  Towards the house.  Now he's stopped again.' 
</p><p>"'Is he waving at us?' 
</p><p>"'No, not now! he was, though.' 
</p><p>"'Look!  There comes another man!' 
</p><p>"'He's running.' 
</p><p>.      .      .      .      .      .      .      .      . 
</p><p>"'Well, I wish I could make something out of those signals.  
What do you suppose he means!' 
</p><p>"'He don't mean anything.  He's just playing.' 
</p><p>"'Well, if he'd just signal us to try the surf again, or to 
go 
to sea and wait, or go north, or go south, or go to hell&mdash;there 
would be some reason in it.  But look at him.  He just stands there 
and keeps his coat revolving like a wheel.  The ass!' 
</p><p>"'There come more people.' 
</p><p>"'Now there's quite a mob.  Look!  Isn't that a boat?' 
</p><p>"'Where?  Oh, I see where you mean.  No, that's no boat.'  
 
<pb n="239" id="WelCran239"/>
</p><p>"'That fellow is still waving his coat.' 
</p><p>"'He must think we like to see him do that.  Why don't he 
quit 
it?  It don't mean anything.' 
</p><p>"'I don't know.  I think he is trying to make us go north.  
It 
must be that there's a life saving station there somewhere.' 
</p><p>"'Say, he ain't tired yet.  Look at 'im wave.' 
</p><p>.      .      .      .      .      .      .      .      . 
</p><p>"'Holy smoke!' said one, allowing his voice to express his 
impious mood.  'If we keep on monkeying out here!  If we've got to 
flounder out here all night!' 
</p><p>"'Oh, we'll never have to stay here all night!  Don't you 
worry.  They've seen us now, and it won't be long before they'll 
come chasing out after us.' 
</p><p>"The shore grew dusky.  The man waving a coat blended 
gradually into this gloom, and it swallowed in the same manner the 
omnibus and the group of people.  The spray, when it dashed 
uproariously over the side, made the voyagers shrink and swear like 
men who were being branded. 
</p><p>"'I'd like to catch the chump who waved the coat.  I feel 
like 
soaking him one, just for luck.' 
</p><p>"'Why?  What did he do?' 
</p><p>.      .      .      .      .      .      .      .      . 
</p><p>"In the meantime the oiler rowed, and then the correspondent 
rowed, and then the other rowed.  Grey-faced and bowed forward, 
they mechanically, turn by turn, piled the leaden oars.  The form 
of the lighthouse had vanished from the southern horizon, but 
finally a pale star appeared, just lifting from the sea.  The 
streaked saffron in the west passed before the all-merging 
darkness, and the sea to the east was black.  The land had 
vanished, and was expressed only by the low and dread thunder of 
the surf." 
 
</p><p>"The Open Boat" gives its title to a volume containing, in 
addition to that and "Flanagan," certain short pieces.  One of 
these others, at least, is also to my mind a perfect thing, "The 
Wise Men."  It tells of the race between two bar-tenders in the 
city of Mexico, and I cannot imagine how it could possibly have 
been better told.  And in this volume, too, is that other 
masterpiece&mdash;the one I deny&mdash;"Death and the Child." 
</p><p>Now I do not know how Crane took the reception of this book, 
for he was not the man to babble of his wrongs; but I cannot 
conceive how it could have been anything but a grave disappointment 
to him.  To use the silly phrase of the literary shopman, "the 
vogue of the short story" was already over; rubbish, pure rubbish, 
provided only it was lengthy, had resumed its former precedence 
again in the reviews, in the publishers' advertisements and on the 
library and book-seller's counters.  The book was taken as a 
trivial by-product, its author was exhorted to abandon this 
production 
 
<pb n="240" id="WelCran240"/>

of "brilliant fragments"&mdash;anything less than fifty 
thousand words is a fragment to the writer of literary columns&mdash;and 
to make that "sustained effort," that architectural undertaking, 
that alone impresses the commercial mind.  Of course, the man who 
can call "The Open Boat" a brilliant fragment would reproach Rodin 
for not completing the edifice his brilliant fragments of statuary 
are presumably intended to adorn, and would sigh, with the late Mr. 
Ruskin for the day when Mr. Whistler would "finish" his pictures.  
Moreover, he was strongly advised&mdash;just as they have advised Mr. 
Kipling&mdash;to embark upon a novel.  And from other quarters, where a 
finer wisdom might have been displayed, he learned that the things 
he had written were not "short stories" at all; they were 
"sketches" perhaps, "anecdotes"&mdash;just as they call Mr. Kipling's 
short stories "anecdotes;" and it was insinuated that for him also 
the true, the ineffable "short story" was beyond his reach.  I 
think it is indisputable that the quality of this reception, which 
a more self-satisfied or less sensitive man than Crane might have 
ignored, did react very unfavorably upon his work.  They put him 
out of conceit with these brief intense efforts in which his 
peculiar strength was displayed. 
</p><p>It was probably such influence that led him to write "The 
Third Violet."  I do not know certainly, but I imagine, that the 
book was to be a demonstration, and it is not a successful 
demonstration, that Crane could write a charming love story.  It is 
the very simple affair of an art student and a summer boarder, with 
the more superficial incidents of their petty encounters set forth 
in a forcible, objective manner that is curiously hard and 
unsympathetic.  The characters act, and on reflection one admits 
they act, <hi rend="italic">true</hi>, but the play of their emotions goes on 
behind the curtain of the style, and all the enrichments of 
imaginative appeal that make love beautiful are omitted.  Yet, 
though the story as a whole fails to satisfy, there are many 
isolated portions of altogether happy effectiveness, a certain ride 
behind an ox cart, for example.  Much more surely is "On Active 
Service" an effort, and in places a painful effort, to fit his 
peculiar gift to the uncongenial conditions of popular acceptance.  
It is the least capable and least satisfactory of all Crane's work. 
</p><p>While these later books were appearing, and right up to his 
last fatal illness, Crane continued to produce fresh war pictures 
that show little or no falling off in vigor of imagination and 
 
<pb n="241" id="WelCran241"/>

handling; and, in addition, he was experimenting with verse.  
In that little stone-blue volume, "War is Kind," and in the earlier 
"Black Riders," the reader will find a series of acute and vivid 
impressions and many of the finer qualities of Crane's descriptive 
prose, but he will not find any novel delights of melody or cadence 
or any fresh aspects of Crane's personality.  There remain some 
children's stories to be published and an unfinished romance.  With 
that the tale of his published work ends, and the career of one of 
the most brilliant, most significant and most distinctively 
American of all English writers comes to its unanticipated 
<hi rend="italic">finis</hi>. 
</p><p>It would be absurd, here and now, to attempt to apportion 
any 
relativity of importance to Crane, to say that he was greater than 
A. or less important than B.  That class-list business is, indeed, 
best left forever to the newspaper plebiscite and the library 
statistician; among artists, whose sole, just claim to recognition 
and whose sole title to immortality must necessarily be the 
possession of unique qualities, that is to say, of unclassifiable 
factors, these gradations are absurd.  Suffice it that, even before 
his death, Crane's right to be counted in the hierarchy of those 
who have made a permanent addition to the great and growing fabric 
of English letters was not only assured, but conceded.  To define 
his position in time, however, and in relation to periods and modes 
of writing will be a more reasonable undertaking; and it seems to 
me that, when at last the true proportions can be seen, Crane will 
be found to occupy a position singularly cardinal.  He was a New 
Englander of Puritan lineage, and the son of a long tradition of 
literature.  There had been many Cranes who wrote before him.  He 
has shown me a shelf of books, for the most part the pious and 
theological works of various antecedent Stephen Cranes.  He had 
been at some pains to gather together these alien products of his 
kin.  For the most part they seemed little, insignificant books, 
and one opened them to read the beaten <hi rend="italic">cliches</hi>, the battered 
outworn phrases, of a movement that has ebbed.  Their very size and 
binding suggested a dying impulse, that very same impulse that in 
its prime had carried the magnificence of Milton's imagery and the 
pomp and splendors of Milton's prose.  In Crane that impulse was 
altogether dead.  He began stark&mdash;I find all through this brief 
notice I have been repeating that in a dozen disguises, "freedom 
from tradition," "absolute directness" and the like&mdash;as though he 
came into the world of letters without ever a predecessor. 
<pb n="242" id="WelCran242"/>
In style, in method and in all that is distinctively <hi rend="italic">not</hi> 
found in his books, he is sharply defined, the expression in 
literary art of certain enormous repudiations.  Was ever a man 
before who wrote of battles so abundantly as he has done, and never 
had a word, never a word from first to last, of the purpose and 
justification of the war?  And of the God of Battles, no more than 
the battered name; "Hully Gee!"&mdash;the lingering trace of the Deity!  
And of the sensuousness and tenderness of love, so much as one can 
find in "The Third Violet!"  Any richness of allusion, any melody 
or balance of phrase, the half quotation that refracts and softens 
and enriches the statement, the momentary digression that opens 
like a window upon beautiful or distant things, are not merely 
absent, but obviously and sedulously avoided.  It is as if the 
racial thought and tradition had been razed from his mind and its 
site ploughed and salted.  He is more than himself in this; he is 
the first expression of the opening mind of a new period, or, at 
least, the early emphatic phase of a new initiative&mdash;beginning, as 
a growing mind must needs begin, with the record of impressions, a 
record of a vigor and intensity beyond all precedent.</p> 

<signed>H. G. WELLS.</signed>
 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
