<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WelSecr"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="WelSecr"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The New Secret Service of the United States</title>
<title type="sort">new secret service of the united states</title>
<author>Welliver, Judson C.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Charles E. Keller</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">25</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">WelSecr</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476472</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The New Secret Service of the United States</title>
<title type="sort">new secret service of the united states</title>
<author>Judson C Welliver</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Munsey's Magazine</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1916-02">February 1916</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume LVII Number 1</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text 
Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center 
scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the 
text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for
page one of Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1916">1916</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-03">March 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>SGML markup</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="33"/>  
<head>The NEW SECRET SERVICE of the UNITED STATES</head>
 
<p>SEVERAL months ago a great railway bridge which spanned one of the 
boundary rivers between the United States and Canada was seriously 
damaged by the explosion of a huge charge of dynamite. 
</p><p>Not many hours later a roughly dressed man was found in the 
woods on the American side and arrested on suspicion.  Under 
examination be confessed.  Yes, he had blown up the bridge.  He 
was willing to admit it.  He was a most engagingly frank person, 
this dynamiter who had tried to put an international railway trunk 
line out of business, and had been perfectly willing to wreck 
trains and kill scores of people in doing it. 
</p><p>The story of this crime, of the over-willing confession of the 
perpetrator, and of the subsequent procedure by which the Secret 
Service men learned the facts that finally enabled them to send 
the criminal to prison gives a particularly graphic illustration 
of the difficulties with which the service has to grapple. 
</p><p>The prisoner declared that he was a reserve officer of the 
German army, and insisted that he had committed, on Canadian soil, 
an act of war against Canada, in the interest of his own country.  
He denied that he had committed any crime whatever, and 
particularly denied that he had in any way offended against the 
peace, dignity, or laws of the United States.  On his theory, he 
was merely a soldier who had been making war against the British 
Empire, and had escaped to American territory.  Being captured 
there, he was entitled to be regarded, not as a common criminal, 
but as a soldier subject to internment by the neutral government 
of the United States. 
</p><p>The Canadian railways, he argued, were carrying both war 
supplies and soldiers from the interior to the Atlantic seaboard, 
and anything that would hinder their operation, and perhaps 
destroy some of these necessaries of war, would be a service to 
Germany. 
</p><p>He had concluded, therefore, to conduct a one-man invasion of 
Canada and, if possible, to blow up a railroad bridge where it 
would do the most damage to the country's transportation system.  
He said that he had no particular difficulty in getting into 
Canada.  He left the train at the first station on the Canadian 
side and walked back along the track toward the international 
boundary.  It had been arranged in advance, according to his tale, 
that between the railway-station and the bridge-head he would meet 
an Irishman carrying a suitcase.  As they approached each other he 
was to address the Irishman: 
</p><p>"Hello, Tommy!" 
</p><p>"Hello yourself," Tommy was to reply. 
</p><p>Thereupon Tommy was to turn over the suit-case to the 
reservist and disappear into the woods.  In the suit-case was 
eighty-five pounds of dynamite, with fuses and other necessary 
paraphernalia for exploding it. 
</p><p>All this, according to the "confession" of the dynamiter, took 
place precisely as had been arranged.  He received the bag of 
explosives and infernal mechanism from Tommy, walked out on the 
bridge, placed 
<pb n="34"/> the dynamite, and set the fuse, being 
careful to keep on the Canadian side of the boundary-line.  Then, 
he said, he went on across the bridge to the American side, and 
disappeared into the forest, having planned to walk to a village 
several miles away, where he thought he could appear without 
exciting suspicion and escape on a train. 
</p><p>It was a particularly well-organized and attractive story.  
The Secret Service men were not satisfied with it, but through 
many hours of questioning and cross-questioning they failed to 
lead the prisoner into any substantial modification of his 
narrative.  What they wanted was to prove that he had committed an 
offense against the laws of the United States. 
</p><p>The most palpable flaw in his story was its introduction of 
the mysterious Tommy.  This particular yarn was of a type with 
which the Secret Service people were thoroughly familiar; and they 
early concluded that Tommy was a fiction introduced in order to 
account for the dynamiter's possession of the explosives.  They 
believed that he had, in fact, brought the suit-case full of 
dynamite with him from the United States; and if this were true 
there was a chance to prosecute him for the statutory crime of 
transporting explosives on a train carrying passengers. 
</p><p>Having made up their minds that this was the correct theory, 
the officers set about to find evidence supporting it.  They were 
helped by the fact that the prisoner had made a curious mistake in 
framing his plans.  When arrested he was arrayed in the costume of 
a working man.  A description of the costume and of the prisoner 
was furnished to the railroad authorities of every line that might 
have brought him from New York.  Conductors, porters, ticket-agents, 
and employees generally were questioned as to whether they 
had seen the man, when he had ridden on any of the trains, and 
what baggage he carried. 
</p><p>This drag-net very quickly brought the desired information.  
The man had left New York carrying a heavy suit-case, and had 
traveled by way of Boston in one of the best trains of the New 
Haven Railroad.  On that train, because his rough clothing was 
incongruous with his mode of travel, he had been noted and 
remarked upon by both officials and fellow passengers. 
</p><p>With this information in their possession, the officers were 
still unable to complete their case against him, because, while 
they were morally certain that he had carried the explosives with 
him from New York, nobody had actually seen the inside of his 
suit-case.  The prisoner still clung to the story of the 
mysterious Tommy, and it was very doubtful whether a jury could be 
induced to convict him in the face of his own seemingly frank and 
circumstantial narrative; so a ruse was resorted to for the 
purpose of breaking down his story and getting a real confession 
instead of a bogus one. 
</p><p>This part of the story illustrates how the skilled operators 
of the Secret Service work to get information from unwilling 
witnesses.  The officials do not attempt any "third degree" method 
of forcing confessions.  It has been found too frequently that 
statements thus extorted are likely to be worthless.  Instead, the 
effort is made to discover some sentimental trait in the 
prisoner's character, through which he can be led, in spite of 
himself, to tell the truth. 
</p><p>During their repeated conversations with the dynamiter the 
investigators had discovered that be was particularly proud of his 
status as a German army officer.  He had referred more than once 
to the honor of his profession, and had strenuously insisted that 
he had acted as a soldier, not as a criminal. 
</p><p>Accordingly, one of the detectives sat down with him and took 
his dictation of the confession on which he stood.  It was written 
out with the utmost care, and he was permitted to correct and sign 
it. 
</p><p>Then came the appeal which broke down the entire fabrication.  
Having signed the statement, the prisoner handed it across the 
table to the Secret Service man who had helped prepare it.  The 
latter picked it up, hesitated a few moments, and then, producing 
a fountain pen, wrote, immediately following the prisoner's 
signature: 
 
</p><p>I certify that the foregoing is a true and complete statement, 
on my honor as a gentleman and an officer of the German army. 
 
</p><p>With this addendum, the memorandum was passed back to the 
prisoner, 
</p><p>"Now," said the investigator, "just accommodate me by signing 
that, and this part of our business will be finished." 
</p><p>The prisoner picked up the memorandum and eyed it with some 
curiosity.  He read the addendum.  Then he turned back to the 
beginning of the statement and perused <pb n="35"/> it with a new care and 
interest.  He turned it over in his hands several times, and read 
it once more.  Finally he laid it down on the table, smiled grimly 
at his <hi rend="italic">vis-a-vis</hi>, and slowly shook his head. 
</p><p>The Secret Service man took out his watch, glanced at it a 
little impatiently, as if the delay was annoying, and said: 
</p><p>"Well?" 
</p><p>"I guess I can't sign that," admitted the prisoner 
lugubriously. 
</p><p>"What's the matter with it?  You've already signed it once." 
</p><p>The prisoner shook his head again, this time more decisively. 
</p><p>"No, I can't sign that." 
</p><p>"But why not?" persisted the investigator. 
</p><p>"Tommy!" 
</p><p>Nothing more was said for a full minute, the two men watching 
each other closely.  Then the official spoke: 
</p><p>"You don't care to declare, on your honor as a gentleman and 
an officer of the German army, that there was any Tommy in the 
case?" 
</p><p>The prisoner burst into a hearty laugh. 
</p><p>"Well," he said, "anyhow, I've got those Canadians up there 
still looking for Tommy!  No, there wasn't any Tommy." 
</p><p>The government had perfected its case.  On the trial it was 
proved that the dynamiter had calmly walked through the Grand 
Central Station in New York carrying nearly one hundred pounds of 
dynamite in his bag, bought his railroad ticket, climbed into a 
Pullman car, chucked his bagful of destruction under a lower 
berth, and himself scrambled into the upper berth. 
</p><p>The prisoner testified, with some evidences of gleeful 
satisfaction, that he enjoyed an excellent night's sleep.  Perhaps 
the man in the lower berth would not have done so well if he had 
known all about his traveling companion; his testimony is not at 
hand. 
</p><p>This little story has been told because it illustrates the 
methods employed by the Secret Service.  The good, old-fashioned, 
dime-novel methods of heroic sleuths who are pictured carrying 
young arsenals on their persons and doing lightning-change acts 
with wigs and false mustaches, are not being affected now in the 
best circles of Secret Service society.  An old-school detective 
of the <hi rend="italic">Nick Carter</hi> type would be about as useful and appropriate 
in the organization of the present Secret Service as a forty-two-centimeter gun at a peace parliament.  They aren't doing it that 
way nowadays. 
</p><p>It is perhaps not generally known that there are now two 
distinct branches of the United States Secret Service.  The older 
branch has been in existence for many years, and is a division of 
the Treasury Department, commissioned to prevent counterfeiting 
and to investigate one or two other classes of offenses, such as 
fraudulent bounty claims.  Prior to 1908 this was the only 
detective agency of the government.  The Department of justice, 
though charged with the prosecution of criminal cases, had no 
means of investigation save inquiries by district attorneys and 
Federal grand juries. 
</p><p>On request of a district attorney, it was customary for the 
Secret Service to loan operatives to the Department of justice to 
make a particular investigation.  In cases involving violation of 
the national banking laws, the department would borrow the 
services of national bank examiners, who were experts in banking 
and accounting methods, to help secure evidence of illegal acts.  
But in general there was no organized bureau or service designed 
for general use in detecting violations of Federal laws. 
</p><p>Early in 1908 the charge was made in Congress that Secret 
Service operatives had been employed to inquire into the conduct 
of members of Congress.  This caused much indignation, and, as a 
result, there was inserted in one of the appropriation bills of 
that year a proviso that thereafter the Secret Service of the 
Treasury Department should be employed only for enforcement of the 
laws against counterfeiting and for the protection of the 
President, and in no other way whatever; also that no Secret 
Service officer should be paid from any other than the regular 
Secret Service appropriation.  This meant that the other 
government departments were not to be permitted thereafter to 
borrow investigators from the Treasury. 
</p><p>These restrictions on the established Secret Service made it 
necessary for the Department of justice to equip itself with some 
sort of investigating instrumentality of its own, which could be 
used to secure evidence in land-fraud, revenue, peonage, and other 
classes of cases.  At that time the department had a corps of 
attorney examiners, as they were called, and this <pb n="36"/> corps was 
expanded into the Bureau of Investigation of the Department of 
justice, which is now the general Secret Service of the United 
States.  The bureau was organized with a force of thirty or forty 
men, and Stanley W. Finch, who had been chief examiner of the 
department, was placed at its head. 
</p><p>Mr. Finch was not afflicted with any lurid notions about the 
spectacular aspects of a detective organization.  He engaged good, 
bright, clever lawyers, accountants, bank experts, and a number of 
the veteran operatives who had been discharged from the old Secret 
Service of the Treasury Department when its field of activity was 
circumscribed by the proviso that has been explained. 
</p><p>The present head of the service is A. Bruce Bielaski, a young 
man who entered official life as a laborer in the Department of 
Justice, worked his way through law school by studying out of 
business hours, demonstrated a peculiar capacity for the business 
of investigation, was assigned to this bureau, and in a remarkably 
short time rose to be its chief. 
</p><p>Mr. Bielaski would be more likely to be taken for a clergyman 
than for a detective.  He conducts his service on the simple and 
rather obvious theory that the best way to get information is to 
go to the people who have it, and ask them for it.  Sometimes they 
will frankly disclose it.  Sometimes they will try to conceal it, 
but will tell more than they intend or realize.  Sometimes they 
will try to suppress things which the investigators know they 
could tell if they chose; and that is one of the most unwise 
things a man can do when the representatives of Uncle Sam ask him 
for information. 
</p><p>It is the experience of the Secret Service people that when a 
crime has been done it is commonly useless to attempt shadowing 
people who are suspected.  Instead, it is found more effective to 
hunt up people who have played minor parts in the criminal 
transaction, usually without knowing the significance of what they 
were doing.  The Secret Service man goes to such a person, frankly 
explains what he wants to know, and asks for information. 
</p><p>There is no buncombe, no effort at disguising the matter in 
hand, no attempt to gain the confidence of the person who is being 
questioned by employing misrepresentations.  Instead, he is 
advised that his own interest is to be perfectly frank with the 
government and to help it. 
</p><p>In nearly all cases this procedure is effective.  A Secret 
Service man of long experience and intimate understanding of human 
nature declares that most people are pretty persistent liars about 
every-day affairs, but that very few of them will attempt lying 
when an officer asks for information.  They prefer to tell the 
truth, in the hope that it will keep them out of embarrassing 
complications.  More-over, despite their proneness to lie, most 
people do it very badly, and the man who attempts it usually 
confounds himself early in the game. 
</p><p>Crimes against the Federal laws almost invariably involve a 
considerable number of people.  This does not necessarily mean a 
large or elaborate conspiracy; but it does mean that there must be 
a pretty widely extended net of circumstances in which a good many 
people are involved, most of whom play unwitting parts that give 
them information the significance of which they are likely not to 
understand. 
</p><p>Persons in this position are likely to be very willing 
witnesses, because of their desire to make plain that they are 
entirely innocent.  Thus the officers, starting at the margin of 
the net of circumstances, are able to unravel it bit by bit, 
increasing their knowledge as they travel inward toward the real 
malefactors at the center. 
</p><p>It is frequently found useful to know all about the character 
and antecedents of a person before he is questioned, because this 
knowledge frequently indicates the method of most effective 
appeal.  How many detectives of the old-fashioned <hi rend="italic">Nick Carter</hi> 
school would have realized, for instance, the value of appealing 
to the honor of an officer and a gentleman in order to get a 
bridge dynamiter to confess? 
</p><p>One of the commonest and most effective ways of tracing 
criminals is by watching the mails.  A bank teller disappears from 
his home town, and it is discovered that he has looted the bank.  
There may be absolutely no clue to his whereabouts, but it is 
almost certain that before very long he will write to somebody&mdash;to 
his family or his friends.  The circle of intimates to whose 
discretion he could be expected thus to trust himself is 
necessarily small and easily conjectured. 
</p><p>Even in cases of this kind it is not permitted to open first-class mail; but the <pb n="37"/> post-office authorities cooperate with the 
service officials in tracing the courses of mail when proper 
request is made.  The missing banker will, of course, write in a 
disguised hand, and perhaps will also have an arrangement for 
relaying his mail; but the officers are perfectly familiar with 
all these methods. 
</p><p>When a suspected letter is reported, it is traced back to the 
point of origin.  Before long it is possible to determine whether 
that point is a relay point, and, if so who is the person to whom 
the fugitive is sending communications.   After this the 
unraveling of the scheme is commonly rather a simple affair. 
</p><p>Another very useful means of detecting criminals is through 
the records that telegraph and telephone corporations keep of 
their messages and calls.  If some friend in a bad scrape calls 
you on the long-distance phone, or sends you a mysterious message, 
you are likely to be surprised at the promptness with which an 
insinuating gentleman from the Secret Service will call on you and 
urge you to explain the circumstances.  Likewise, you probably 
will be surprised at the desire which will suddenly seize you to 
give him all possible information.  You will want the insinuating 
gentleman distinctly to understand that you are not helping a 
criminal to escape. 
</p><p>It is almost an invariable rule not to attempt any deception 
of the person from whom information is desired.  Experience has 
proved that when an investigator tries to fool a witness the 
witness generally succeeds in fooling him.  Perfect straight-forwardness is generally the effective method. 
</p><p>It is part of the policy of the Bureau of Investigation not to 
let it be known how many people are actually in its service.  The 
officials admit that there is not much point to this bit of 
mystery, because anybody can read the appropriation bill passed by 
Congress, which provides the money, and can see that the present 
appropriation is half a million dollars per annum from which to 
pay both the salaries and expenses of the employees.  Manifestly, 
it cannot be a very large personnel that attempts to cover the 
whole country at such an expense. 
</p><p>Since the passage of the so-called White Slave Act, the 
enforcement of which is under this service, a good many local 
police officers have been engaged on a fee basis to assist the 
work of the Federal officials.  These men are enlisted with a view 
to getting the best possible knowledge from such centers as 
railroad-stations, hotels, and the like. 
</p><p>The Bureau of Investigation has grown rapidly since its 
establishment, and is likely to grow still faster in the near 
future, because of the importance of its work in connection with 
plots against the neutrality of the United States.  There has 
always been a profound prejudice among Americans against anything 
like a system of espionage, and there is not the least danger that 
anything like the systems maintained in certain European countries 
will ever develop here.  No Congress would pass a law providing 
for any such intimate scheme of watching and card-indexing people 
as is in vogue in countries like Russia and Germany. 
</p><p>There, of course, close espionage is justified by the 
government's fears of revolutionary plots and military spying in 
the interest of hostile neighbors.  In our own country we have 
possibly gone to an extreme in protecting individual liberty in 
these regards. 
</p><p>An alien may come to the United States, map our harbors, make 
charts of fortifications, and generally familiarize himself with 
anything of possible interest, without any fear of apprehension 
and punishment, simply because there is no law to prevent such 
things.  Again, offenses against American neutrality, by the means 
of blowing up industrial establishments, dynamiting railway 
bridges, and the like, are offenses against the State in which 
they are committed, rather than against the United States. 
</p><p>There is thus presented a difficult and anomalous situation.  
The Federal government possesses the only means with which to 
combat such attacks, and yet has no law under which to prosecute 
them. 
</p><p>The need of more direct and efficient laws to empower the 
Federal authorities to deal with new classes of offenses is coming 
to be generally recognized, and it is believed these will be 
passed without much delay.  But nobody imagines that any general 
espionage system will ever be attempted in the United States.  
There is no need for it, and, except under stress of great and 
imminent national peril, the public would never consent to it. 
</p> 
<trailer>[The end] </trailer>
</div1>
 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
