<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaDile"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
 
<TEI.2 id="WhaDile"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Dilettante.</title>
<title type="sort">dilettante</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">26</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WhaDile</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476489</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Dilettante.</title>
<title type="sort">dilettante</title>
<author>Edith Wharton</author>
</titleStmt> 
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harper's Monthly</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York City</pubPlace> 
<date value="1903">1903</date>
</publicationStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Verification made against printed text.</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1903">1903</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-04">April 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Kelly Moulton</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>TEI tagging</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 


<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
<head>Wharton, Edith.  "The Dilettante."  <lb/> 
<hi rend="italic"> Harper's Monthly</hi> 108  (Dec. 1903): 139-43.<lb/> 
</head> 
 

 
<pb n="139"/>  
 
<p>IT was on an impulse hardly needing the arguments he found himself 
advancing in its favor, that Thursdale, on his way to the club, 
turned as usual into Mrs. Vervain's street.</p><p> 
     The "as usual" was his own qualification of the act; a 
convenient way of bridging the interval&mdash;in days and other 
sequences&mdash;that lay between this visit and the last.  It was 
characteristic of him that he instinctively excluded his call two 
days earlier, with Ruth Gaynor, from the list of his visits to 
Mrs. 
Vervain: the special conditions attending it had made it no more 
like a visit to Mrs. Vervain than an engraved dinner invitation 
is 
like a personal letter.  Yet it was to talk over his call with 
Miss 
Gaynor that he was now returning to the scene of that episode; 
and 
it was because Mrs. Vervain could be trusted to handle the 
talking 
over as skilfully as the interview itself that, at her corner, he 
had felt the dilettante's irresistible craving to take a last 
look 
at a work of art that was passing out of his possession.</p><p> 
     On the whole, he knew no one better fitted to deal with the 
unexpected than Mrs. Vervain.  She excelled in the rare art of 
taking things for granted, and Thursdale felt a pardonable pride 
in 
the thought that she owed her excellence to his training.  Early 
in 
his career Thursdale had made the mistake, at the outset of his 
acquaintance with a lady, of telling her that he loved her and 
exacting the same avowal in return.  The latter part of that 
episode had been like the long walk back from a picnic, when one 
has to carry all the crockery one has finished using: it was the 
last time Thursdale ever allowed himself to be encumbered with 
the 
debris of a feast.  He thus incidentally learned that the 
privilege 
of loving her is one of the least favors that a charming woman 
can 
accord; and in seeking to avoid the pitfalls of sentiment he had 
developed a science of evasion in which the woman of the moment 
became a mere implement of the game.  He owed a great deal of 
delicate enjoyment to the cultivation of this art.  The perils 
from 
which it had been his refuge became naively harmless: was it 
possible that he who now took his easy way along the levels had 
once preferred to gasp on the raw heights of emotion?  Youth is a 
high-colored season; but he had the satisfaction of feeling that 
he 
had entered earlier than most into that chiar'oscuro of sensation 
where every half-tone has its value.</p><p> 
     As a promoter of this pleasure no one he had known was 
comparable to Mrs. Vervain.  He had taught a good many women not 
to 
betray their feelings, but he had never before had such fine 
material to work in.  She had been surprisingly crude when he 
first 
knew her; capable of making the most awkward inferences, of 
plunging through thin ice, of recklessly undressing her emotions; 
but she had acquired, under the discipline of his reticences and 
evasions, a skill almost equal to his own, and perhaps more 
remarkable in that it involved keeping time with any tune he 
played 
and reading at sight some uncommonly difficult passages.</p><p> 
     It had taken Thursdale seven years to form this fine talent; 
but the result justified the effort.  At the crucial moment she 
had 
been perfect: her way of greeting Miss Gaynor had made him regret 
that he had announced his engagement by letter.  it was an 
evasion 
that confessed a difficulty; a deviation implying an obstacle, 
where, by common consent, it was agreed to see none; it betrayed, 
in short, a lack of confidence in the completeness of his method. 
 
It had been his pride never to put himself in a position which 
had 
to be quitted, as it were, by the back door; but here, as he 
perceived, the main portals would have opened for him of their 
own 
accord.  All this, and much more, he read in the finished 
naturalness with which Mrs. Vervain had <pb n="140"/>  met 
Miss Gaynor.  
He had never seen a better piece of work: there was no over-eagerness, no suspicious warmth, above all (and this gave her art 
the grace of a natural quality) there were none of those damnable 
implications whereby a woman, in welcoming her friend's 
betrothed, 
may keep him on pins and needles while she laps the lady in 
complacency.  So masterly a performance, indeed, hardly needed 
the 
offset of Miss Gaynor's door-step words&mdash;"To be so kind to me, 
how 
she must have liked you!"&mdash;though he caught himself wishing it 
lay 
within the bounds of fitness to transmit them, as a final 
tribute, 
to the one woman he knew who was unfailingly certain to enjoy a 
good thing.  It was perhaps the one drawback to his new situation 
that it might develop good things which it would be impossible to 
hand on to Margaret Vervain.</p><p> 
     The fact that he had made the mistake of underrating his 
friend's powers, the consciousness that his writing must have 
betrayed his distrust of her efficiency, seemed an added reason 
for 
turning down her street instead of going on to the club.  He 
would 
show her that he knew how to value her; he would ask her to 
achieve 
with him a feat infinitely rarer and more delicate than the one 
he 
had appeared to avoid.  Incidentally, he would also dispose of 
the 
interval of time before dinner: ever since he had seen Miss 
Gaynor 
off, an hour earlier, on her return journey to Buffalo, he had 
been 
wondering how he should put in the rest of the afternoon.  It was 
absurd, how he missed the girl. . . .  Yes, that was it; the 
desire 
to talk about her was, after all, at the bottom of his impulse to 
call on Mrs. Vervain!  It was absurd, if you like&mdash;but it was 
delightfully rejuvenating.  He could recall the time when he had 
been afraid of being obvious: now he felt that this return to the 
primitive emotions might be as restorative as a holiday in the 
Canadian woods.  And it was precisely by the girl's candor, her 
directness, her lack of complications, that he was taken.  The 
sense that she might say something rash at any moment was 
positively exhilarating: if she had thrown her arms about him at 
the station he would not have given a thought to his crumpled 
dignity.  It surprised Thursdale to find what freshness of heart 
he 
brought to the adventure; and though his sense of irony prevented 
his ascribing his intactness to any conscious purpose, he could 
but 
rejoice in the fact that his sentimental economies had left him 
such a large surplus to draw upon.</p><p> 
     Mrs. Vervain was at home&mdash;as usual.  When one visits the 
cemetery one expects to find the angel on the tombstone, and it 
struck Thursdale as another proof of his friend's good taste that 
she had been in no undue haste to change her habits.  The whole 
house appeared to count on his coming; the footman took his hat 
and 
overcoat as naturally as though there had been no lapse in his 
visits; and the drawing-room at once enveloped him in that 
atmosphere of tacit intelligence which Mrs. Vervain imparted to 
her 
very furniture.</p><p> 
     It was a surprise that, in this general harmony of 
circumstances, Mrs. Vervain should herself sound the first false 
note.</p><p> 
     "You?" she exclaimed; and the book she held slipped from her 
hand.</p><p> 
     It was crude, certainly; unless it were a touch of the 
finest 
art.  The difficulty of classifying it disturbed Thursdale's 
balance.</p><p> 
     "Why not?" he said, restoring the book.  "Isn't it my hour?" 
 
And as she made no answer, he added gently, "Unless it's some one 
else's?"</p><p> 
     She laid the book aside and sank back into her chair.  
"Mine, 
merely," she said.</p><p> 
     "I hope that doesn't mean that you're unwilling to share 
it?"</p><p> 
     "With you?  By no means.  You're welcome to my last 
crust."</p><p> 
     He looked at her reproachfully.  "Do you call this the 
last?"</p><p> 
     She smiled as he dropped into the seat across the hearth.  
"It's a way of giving it more flavor!"</p><p> 
     He returned the smile.  "A visit to you doesn't need such 
condiments."</p><p> 
     She took this with just the right measure of retrospective 
amusement.</p><p> 
     "Ah, but I want to put into this one a very special taste," 
she confessed.</p><p> 
     Her smile was so confident, so reassuring, that it lulled 
him 
into the imprudence of saying, "Why should you want it to be 
different from what was always so perfectly right?"</p><p> 
     She hesitated.  "Doesn't the fact that it's the last 
constitute a difference?"</p><p> 
     "The last&mdash;my last visit to you?"  
<pb n="141"/> </p><p> 
     "Oh, metaphorically, I mean&mdash;there's a break in the 
continuity."</p><p> 
     Decidedly, she was pressing too hard: unlearning his arts 
already!</p><p> 
     "I don't recognize it," he said.  "Unless you make me&mdash;" he 
added, with a note that slightly stirred her attitude of languid 
attention.</p><p> 
     She turned to him with grave eyes.  "You recognize no 
difference whatever?"</p><p> 
     "None&mdash;except an added link in the chain."</p><p> 
     "An added link?"</p><p> 
     "In having one more thing to like you for&mdash;your letting Miss 
Gaynor see why I had already so many."  He flattered himself that 
this turn had taken the least hint of fatuity from the 
phrase.</p><p> 
     Mrs. Vervain sank into her former easy pose.  "Was it that 
you 
came for?" she asked, almost gaily.</p><p> 
     "If it is necessary to have a reason&mdash;that was one."</p><p> 
     "To talk to me about Miss Gaynor?"</p><p> 
     "To tell you how she talks about you."</p><p> 
     "That will be very interesting&mdash;especially if you have seen 
her since her second visit to me."</p><p> 
     "Her second visit?"  Thursdale pushed his chair back with a 
start and moved to another.  "She came to see you again?"</p><p> 
     "This morning, yes&mdash;by appointment."</p><p> 
     He continued to look at her blankly.  "You sent for 
her?"</p><p> 
     "I didn't have to&mdash;she wrote and asked me last night.  But 
no 
doubt you have seen her since."</p><p> 
     Thursdale sat silent.  He was trying to separate his words 
from his thoughts, but they still clung together inextricably.  
"I 
saw her off just now at the station."</p><p> 
     "And she didn't tell you that she had been here 
again?"</p><p> 
     "There was hardly time, I suppose&mdash;there were people 
about&mdash;" 
he floundered.</p><p> 
     "Ah, she'll write, then."</p><p> 
     He regained his composure.  "Of course she'll write: very 
often, I hope.  You know I'm absurdly in love," he cried 
audaciously.</p><p> 
     She tilted her head back, looking up at him as he leaned 
against the chimney-piece.  He had leaned there so often that the 
attitude touched a pulse which set up a throbbing in her throat.  
"Oh, my poor Thursdale!" she murmured.</p><p> 
     "I suppose it's rather ridiculous," he owned; and as she 
remained silent, he added, with a sudden break&mdash;"Or have you 
another reason for pitying me?"</p><p> 
     Her answer was another question.  "Have you been back to 
your 
rooms since you left her?"</p><p> 
     "Since I left her at the station?  I came straight 
here."</p><p> 
     "Ah, yes&mdash;you <hi rend="italic">could:</hi> there was no reason&mdash;"  Her 
words 
passed into a silent musing.</p><p> 
     Thursdale moved nervously nearer.  "You said you had 
something 
to tell me?"</p><p> 
     "Perhaps I had better let her do so.  There may be a letter 
at 
your rooms."</p><p> 
     "A letter?  What do you mean?  A letter from <hi rend="italic">her?</hi>  
What 
has happened?"</p><p> 
     His paleness shook her, and she raised a hand of 
reassurance.  
"Nothing has happened&mdash;perhaps that is just the worst of it.  You 
always <hi rend="italic">hated</hi>, you know," she added incoherently, "to have 
things happen: you never would let them."</p><p> 
     "And now&mdash;?"</p><p> 
     "Well, that was what she came here for: I supposed you had 
guessed.  To know if anything had happened."</p><p> 
     "Had happened?"  He gazed at her slowly.  "Between you and 
me?" he said with a rush of light.</p><p> 
     The words were so much cruder than any that had ever passed 
between them that the color rose to her face; but she held his 
startled gaze.</p><p> 
     "You know girls are not quite as unsophisticated as they 
used 
to be.  Are you surprised that such an idea should occur to 
her?"</p><p> 
     His own color answered hers: it was the only reply that came 
to him.</p><p> 
     Mrs. Vervain went on, smoothly: "I supposed it might have 
struck you that there were times when we presented that 
appearance."</p><p> 
     He made an impatient gesture.  "A man's past is his 
own!"</p><p> 
     "Perhaps&mdash;it certainly never belongs to the woman who has 
shared it.  But one learns such truths only by experience; and 
Miss 
Gaynor is naturally inexperienced."</p><p> 
     "Of course&mdash;but&mdash;supposing her act a natural one&mdash;" he 
floundered lamentably among his innuendoes&mdash;"I still don't 
see&mdash;how 
there was anything&mdash;"</p><p> 
     "Anything to take hold of?  There wasn't&mdash;"  
<pb n="142"/> </p><p> 
     "Well, then&mdash;?" escaped him, in crude satisfaction; but as 
she 
did not complete the sentence he went on with a faltering laugh: 
"She can hardly object to the existence of a mere friendship 
between us!"</p><p> 
     "But she does," said Mrs. Vervain.</p><p> 
     Thursdale stood perplexed.  He had seen, on the previous 
day, 
no trace of jealousy or resentment in his betrothed: he could 
still 
hear the candid ring of the girl's praise of Mrs. Vervain.  If 
she 
were such an abyss of insincerity as to dissemble distrust under 
such frankness, she must at least be more subtle than to bring 
her 
doubts to her rival for solution.  The situation seemed one 
through 
which one could no longer move in a penumbra, and he let in a 
burst 
of light with the direct query: "Won't you explain what you 
mean?"</p><p> 
     Mrs. Vervain sat silent, not provokingly, as though to 
prolong 
his distress, but as if, in the attenuated phraseology he had 
taught her, it was difficult to find words robust enough to meet 
his challenge.  It was the first time he had ever asked her to 
explain anything; and she had lived so long in dread of offering 
elucidations which were not wanted, that she seemed unable to 
produce one on the spot.</p><p> 
     At last she said slowly: "She came to find out if you were 
really free."</p><p> 
     Thursdale colored again.  "Free?" he stammered, with a sense 
of physical disgust at contact with such crassness.</p><p> 
     "Yes&mdash;if I had quite done with you."  She smiled in 
recovered 
security.  "It seems she likes clear outlines; she has a passion 
for definitions."</p><p> 
     "Yes&mdash;well?" he said, wincing at the echo of his own 
subtlety.</p><p> 
     "Well&mdash;and when I told her that you had never belonged to 
me, 
she wanted me to define <hi rend="italic">my</hi> status&mdash;to know exactly where I 
had 
stood all along."</p><p> 
     Thursdale sat gazing at her intently; his hand was not yet 
on 
the clue.  "And even when you had told her that&mdash;"</p><p> 
     "Even when I had told her that I had <hi rend="italic">had</hi> no 
status&mdash;that 
I had never stood anywhere, in any sense she meant," said Mrs. 
Vervain, slowly&mdash;"even then she wasn't satisfied, it 
seems."</p><p> 
     He uttered an uneasy exclamation.  "She didn't believe you, 
you mean?"</p><p> 
     "I mean that she <hi rend="italic">did</hi> believe me: too 
thoroughly."</p><p> 
     "Well, then&mdash;in God's name, what did she want?"</p><p> 
     "Something more&mdash;those were the words she used."</p><p> 
     "Something more?  Between&mdash;between you and me?  Is it a 
conundrum?"  He laughed awkwardly.</p><p> 
     "Girls are not what they were in my day; they are no longer 
forbidden to contemplate the relation of the sexes."</p><p> 
     "So it seems!" he commented.  "But since, in this case, 
there 
wasn't any&mdash;" he broke off, catching the dawn of a revelation in 
her gaze.</p><p> 
     "That's just it.  The unpardonable offence has been&mdash;in our 
not offending."</p><p> 
     He flung himself down despairingly.  "I give it up!&mdash;What 
did 
you tell her?" he burst out with sudden crudeness.</p><p> 
     "The exact truth.  If I had only known," she broke off with 
a 
beseeching tenderness, "won't you believe that I would still have 
lied for you?"</p><p> 
     "Lied for me?  Why on earth should you have lied for either 
of 
us?"</p><p> 
     "To save you&mdash;to hide you from her to the last!  As I've 
hidden you from myself all these years!"  She stood up with a 
sudden tragic import in her movement.  "You believe me capable of 
that, don't you?  If I had only guessed&mdash;but I have never known a 
girl like her; she had the truth out of me with a spring."</p><p> 
     "The truth that you and I had never&mdash;"</p><p> 
     "Had never&mdash;never in all these years!  Oh, she knew why&mdash;she 
measured us both in a flash.  She didn't suspect me of having 
haggled with you&mdash;her words pelted me like hail.  'He just took 
what he wanted&mdash;sifted and sorted you to suit his taste.  Burnt 
out 
the gold and left a heap of cinders.  And you let him&mdash;you let 
yourself be cut in bits'&mdash;she mixed her metaphors a little&mdash;'be 
cut 
in bits, and used or discarded, while all the while every drop of 
blood in you belonged to him!  But he's Shylock&mdash;and you have 
bled 
to death of the pound of flesh he has cut out of you.'  But she 
despises me the most, you know&mdash;far the most&mdash;" Mrs. Vervain 
ended.</p><p> 
     The words fell strangely on the scented stillness of the 
room: 
they seemed out of harmony with its setting of afternoon 
intimacy, 
the kind of intimacy on which <pb n="143"/>  at any moment, 
a visitor 
might intrude without perceptibly lowering the atmosphere.  It 
was 
as though a grand opera-singer had strained the acoustics of a 
private music-room.</p><p> 
     Thursdale stood up, facing his hostess.  Half the room was 
between them, but they seemed to stare close at each other now 
that 
the veils of reticence and ambiguity had fallen.</p><p> 
     His first words were characteristic.  "She <hi rend="italic">does</hi> 
despise 
me, then?" he exclaimed.</p><p> 
     "She thinks the pound of flesh you took was a little too 
near 
the heart."</p><p> 
     He was excessively pale.  "Please tell me exactly what she 
said of me."</p><p> 
     "She did not speak much of you: she is proud.  But I gather 
that while she understands love or indifference, her eyes have 
never been opened to the many intermediate shades of feeling.  At 
any rate, she expressed an unwillingness to be taken with 
reservations&mdash;she thinks you would have loved her better if you 
had 
loved some one else first.  The point of view is original&mdash;she 
insists on a man with a past!"</p><p> 
     "Oh, a past&mdash;if she's serious&mdash;I could rake up a past!" he 
said with a laugh.</p><p> 
     "So I suggested: but she has her eyes on his particular 
portion of it.  She insists on making it a test case.  She wanted 
to know what you had done to me; and before I could guess her 
drift 
I blundered into telling her."</p><p> 
     Thursdale drew a difficult breath.  "I never supposed&mdash;your 
revenge is complete," he said slowly.</p><p> 
     He heard a little gasp in her throat.  "My revenge?  When I 
sent for you to warn you&mdash;to save you from being surprised as 
<hi rend="italic">I</hi> 
was surprised?"</p><p> 
     "You're very good&mdash;but it's rather late to talk of saving 
me."  
He held out his hand in the mechanical gesture of 
leave-taking.</p><p> 
     "How you must care!&mdash;for I never saw you so dull," was her 
answer.  "Don't you see that it's not too late for me to help 
you?"  
And as he continued to stare, she brought out sublimely: "Take 
the 
rest&mdash;in imagination!  Let it at least be of that much use to 
you.  
Tell her I lied to her&mdash;she's too ready to believe it!  And so, 
after all, in a sense, I sha'n't have been wasted."</p><p> 
     His stare hung on her, widening to a kind of wonder.  She 
gave 
the look back brightly, unblushingly, as though the expedient 
were 
too simple to need oblique approaches.  It was extraordinary how 
a 
few words had swept them from an atmosphere of the most complex 
dissimulations to this contact of naked souls.</p><p> 
     It was not in Thursdale to expand with the pressure of fate; 
but something in him cracked with it, and the rift let in new 
light.  He went up to his friend and took her hand.</p><p> 
     "You would do it&mdash;you would do it!"</p><p> 
     She looked at him, smiling, but her hand shook.</p><p> 
     "Good-by," he said, kissing it.</p><p> 
     "Good-by?  You are going&mdash;?"</p><p> 
     "To get my letter."</p><p> 
     "Your letter?  The letter won't matter, if you will only do 
what I ask."</p><p> 
     He returned her gaze.  "I might, I suppose, without being 
out 
of character.  Only, don't you see that if your plan helped me it 
could only harm her?"</p><p> 
     "Harm <hi rend="italic">her?"</hi></p><p> 
     "To sacrifice you wouldn't make me different.  I shall go on 
being what I have always been&mdash;sifting and sorting, as she calls 
it.  Do you want my punishment to fall on <hi rend="italic">her?"</hi></p><p> 
     She looked at him long and deeply.  "Ah, if I had to choose 
between you&mdash;!"</p><p> 
     "You would let her take her chance?  But I can't, you see.  
I 
must take my punishment alone."</p><p> 
     She drew her hand away, sighing.  "Oh, there will be no 
punishment for either of you."</p><p> 
     "For either of us?  There will be the reading of her letter 
for me."</p><p> 
     She shook her head with a slight laugh.  "There will be no 
letter."</p><p> 
     Thursdale faced about from the threshold with fresh life in 
his look.  "No letter?  You don't mean&mdash;"</p><p> 
     "I mean that she's been with you since I saw her&mdash;she's seen 
you and heard your voice.  If there <hi rend="italic">is</hi> a letter, she has 
recalled it&mdash;from the first station, by telegraph."</p><p> 
     He turned back to the door, forcing an answer to her smile.  
"But in the mean while I shall have read it," he said.</p><p> 
     The door closed on him, and she hid her eyes from the 
dreadful 
emptiness of the room.</p> 
 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
