<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaGrav"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="WhaGrav"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"The Angel at the Grave."</title>
<title type="sort">the angel at the grave</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">41</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">WhaGrav</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476495</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>"[time]" inserted where it seemed to be omitted on 
line 3 of page 159; "[sic]" inserted after "built" where 
it should read "build" in line 10 of the 2nd full paragraph on page 
163 and after "interventing" in line 13 of the 3rd full paragraph 
on page 165.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"The Angel at the Grave."</title>
<title type="sort">the angel at the grave</title>
<author>Edith Wharton</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner's Magazine</publisher>
<date value="1995"/>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>Scribner's Magazine 29 (Feb. 1901): 158-166.</p>
</seriesStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Verification made against printed text</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of  
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1901-02">Feb. 1901</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">Jan 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Lorrie S. Chisholm, Electronic Text Ctr., University of Virginia 
Library System.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added in header.</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
<head> 
Wharton, Edith.  "The Angel at the Grave."   
<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic"> Scribner's Magazine</hi> 29 (Feb. 1901): 158-166. 
</head> 
<pb n="158"/>  
<p> 
THE House stood a few yards back from the elm-shaded village 
street, in that semi-publicity sometimes cited as a democratic 
protest against old-world standards of domestic exclusiveness.  
This candid exposure to the public eye is more probably a result of 
the gregariousness which, in the New England bosom, oddly coexists 
with a shrinking from direct social contact; most of the inmates of 
such houses preferring that furtive intercourse which is the result 
of observations through shuttered windows and a categorical 
acquaintance with the neighboring clothes-lines.  The House, 
however, faced its public with a difference.  For sixty years it 
had written itself with a capital letter, had self-consciously 
squared itself in the eye of an admiring nation.  The most 
searching inroads of village intimacy hardly counted in a household 
that opened on the universe; and a lady whose door-bell was at any 
moment liable to be rung by visitors from London or Vienna was not 
likely to flutter up-stairs when she observed a neighbor "stepping 
over." 
</p><p>The solitary inmate of the Anson House owed this induration of 
the social texture to the most conspicuous accident in her annals: 
the fact that she was the only grand-daughter of the great Orestes 
Anson.  She had been born, as it were, into a museum, and cradled 
in a glass case with a label; the first foundations of her 
consciousness being built on the rock of her grand-father's 
celebrity.  To a little girl who acquires her earliest knowledge of 
literature through a <hi rend="italic"> Reader</hi> embellished with fragments of her 
ancestor's prose, that personage necessarily fills an heroic space 
in the foreground of life.  To communicate with one's Past through 
the impressive medium of print, to have, as it were, a footing in 
every library in the country, and an acknowledged kinship with that 
world-diffused clan, the descendants of the great, was to be 
pledged to a standard of manners that amazingly simplified the 
lesser relations of life.  The village street on which Paulina 
Anson's youth looked out led to all the capitals of Europe; and 
over the roads of intercommunication unseen caravans bore back to 
the elm-shaded House the tribute of an admiring world. 
</p><p>Fate seemed to have taken a direct share in fitting Paulina 
for her part as the custodian of this historic dwelling.  It had 
long been secretly regarded as a "visitation" by the great man's 
family that he had left no son and that his daughters were not 
"intellectual."  The ladies themselves were the first to lament 
their deficiency, to own that nature had denied them the gift of 
making the most of their opportunities.  A profound veneration for 
their parent and an unswerving faith in his doctrines had not 
amended their congenital incapacity to understand what he had 
written.  Laura, who had her moments of mute rebellion against 
destiny, had sometimes thought how much easier it would have been 
if their progenitor had been a poet; for she could recite with 
feeling portions of "The Culprit Fay" and of the poems of Mrs. 
Hemans; and Phoebe, who was more conspicuous for memory than 
imagination, kept an album filled with "selections."  But the great 
man was a philosopher; and to both daughters respiration was 
difficult on the cloudy heights of metaphysic.  The situation would 
have been intolerable but for the fact that, while Phoebe and Laura 
were still at school, their father's fame had passed from the open 
ground of conjecture to the chill privacy of certitude.  Dr. Anson 
had in fact achieved one of those anticipated immortalities not 
uncommon at a time when people were apt to base their literary 
judgments on their emotions, and when to affect plain food and 
despise England went a long way toward establishing a man's 
intellectual pre-eminence.  Thus, when the daughters were called on 
to strike a filial attitude about their parent's pedestal there was 
little to do but to pose <pb n="159"/>  gracefully and point upward; and 
there are spines to which the immobility of worship is not a 
strain.  A legend had by this [time] crystallized about the great 
Orestes, and it was more immediate interest to the public to hear 
what brand of tea he drank, and whether he took off his boots in 
the hall, than to rouse the drowsy echo of his dialectic.  A great 
man never draws so near his public as when it has become 
unnecessary to read his books and is still interesting to know what 
he eats for breakfast. 
</p><p>As recorders of their parent's domestic habits, as pious 
scavengers of his wastepaper basket, the Misses Anson were 
unexcelled.  They always had an interesting anecdote to impart to 
the literary pilgrim, and the tact with which, in later years, they 
intervened between the public and the growing inaccessibility of 
its idol, sent away many an enthusiast satisfied to have touched 
the veil before the sanctuary.  Still it was felt, especially by 
old Mrs. Anson, who survived her husband for some years, that 
Phoebe and Laura were not worthy of their privileges.  There had 
been a third daughter so unworthy of hers that she had married a 
distant cousin, who had taken her to live in a new Western 
community where the <hi rend="italic"> Works of Orestes Anson</hi> had not yet become 
a part of the civic consciousness; but of this daughter little was 
said, and she was tacitly understood to be excluded from the family 
heritage of fame.  In time, however, it appeared that the 
traditional penny with which she had been cut off had been invested 
to unexpected advantage; and the interest on it, when she died, 
returned to the Anson House in the shape of a granddaughter who was 
at once felt to be what Mrs. Anson called a "compensation."  It was 
Mrs. Anson's firm belief that the remotest operations of nature 
were governed by the centripetal force of her husband's greatness; 
and that Paulina's exceptional intelligence could be explained only 
on the ground that she was designed to act as the guardian of the 
family temple. 
</p><p>The House, by the time Paulina came to live in it, had already 
acquired the publicity of a place of worship; not the perfumed 
chapel of a romantic idolatry, but the cold clean empty meeting-house of ethical enthusiasms.  The ladies lived on its outskirts, 
as it were, in cells that left the central fane undisturbed.  The 
very position of the furniture had come to have a ritual 
significance; the sparse ornaments were the offerings of kindred 
intellects, the steel engravings by Raphael Morghen marked the Via 
Sacra of a European tour, and the black-walnut desk with its bronze 
inkstand modelled on the Pantheon was the altar of this bleak 
temple of thought. 
</p><p>To a child compact of enthusiasms, and accustomed to pasture 
them on the scanty herbage of a new social soil, the atmosphere of 
the old house was full of floating nourishment.  In the compressed 
perspective of Paulina's outlook it stood for a monument of ruined 
civilizations, and its white portico opened on legendary distances.  
Its very aspect was impressive to eyes that had first surveyed life 
from the jig-saw "residence" of a raw-edged Western town.  The 
high-ceilinged rooms, with their panelled walls, their polished 
mahogany, their portraits of triple-stocked ancestors and of 
ringleted "females" in crayon, furnished the child with the 
historic scenery against which a young imagination constructs its 
vision of the past.  To other eyes the cold spotless thinly 
furnished interior might have suggested the shuttered mind of a 
maiden-lady who associates fresh air and sunlight with dust and 
discoloration; but it is the eye which supplies the coloring-matter, and Paulina's brimmed with the richest hues. 
</p><p>Nevertheless, the House did not immediately dominate her.  She 
had her confused out-reachings toward other centres of sensation, 
her vague intuition of a heliocentric system; but the attraction of 
habit, the steady pressure of example, gradually fixed her roving 
allegiance and she bent her neck to the yoke.  Vanity had a share 
in her subjugation; for it had early been discovered that she was 
the only person in the family who could read her grandfather's 
works.  The fact that she had perused them with delight at an age 
when (even presupposing a metaphysical bias) it was impossible for 
her to understand them, seemed to her aunts and grandmother sure 
evidence of predestination.  Paulina was to be the interpreter of 
the oracle, and the philosophic fumes so vertiginous to meaner 
minds would throw her into the needed condition of clairvoyance.  
Noth-<pb n="160"/> ing could have been more genuine than the emotion on 
which this theory was based.  Paulina, in fact, delighted in her 
grandfather's writings.  His sonorous periods, his mystic 
vocabulary, his bold flights into the rarefied air of the abstract, 
were thrilling to a fancy unhampered by the need of definitions.  
This purely verbal pleasure was supplemented later by the 
excitement of gathering up crumbs of meaning from the rhetorical 
board.  What could have been more stimulating than to construct the 
theory of a girlish world out of the fragments of this Titanic 
cosmogony?  Before Paulina's opinions had reached the stage when 
ossification sets in, their form was fatally predetermined. 
</p><p>The fact that Dr. Anson had died and that his apotheosis had 
taken place before his young priestess's induction to the temple, 
made her ministrations easier and more inspiring.  There were no 
little personal traits&mdash;such as the great man's manner of helping 
himself to salt, or the guttural cluck that started the wheels of 
speech&mdash;to distract the eye of young veneration from the central 
fact of his divinity.  A man whom one knows only through a crayon 
portrait and a dozen yellowing tomes on free-will and intuition is 
at least secure from the belittling effects of intimacy. 
</p><p>Paulina thus grew up in a world readjusted to the fact of her 
grandfather's greatness; and as each organism draws from its 
surroundings the kind of nourishment most needful to its growth, so 
from this somewhat colorless conception she absorbed warmth, 
brightness, and variety.  Paulina was the type of woman who 
transmutes thought into sensation and nurses a theory in her bosom 
like a child. 
</p><p>In due course Mrs. Anson "passed away"&mdash;no one died in the 
Anson vocabulary&mdash;and Paulina became more than ever the foremost 
figure of the commemorative group.  Laura and Phoebe, content to 
leave their father's glory in more competent hands, placidly lapsed 
into needlework and fiction, and their niece stepped into immediate 
prominence as the chief "authority" on the great man.  Historians 
who were "getting up" the period wrote to consult her and to borrow 
documents; ladies with inexplicable yearnings begged for an 
interpretation of phrases which had "influenced" them, but which 
they had not quite understood; critics applied to her to verify 
some doubtful citation or to decide some disputed point in 
chronology; and the great tide of thought and investigation kept up 
a continuous murmur on the quiet shores of her life. 
</p><p>An explorer of another kind disembarked there one day in the 
shape of a young man to whom Paulina was primarily a kissable girl, 
with an after-thought in the shape of a grandfather.  From the 
outset it had been impossible to fix Hewlett Winsloe's attention on 
Dr. Anson.  The young man behaved with the innocent profanity of 
infants sporting on a tomb.  His excuse was that he came from New 
York, a Cimmerian outskirt which survived in Paulina's geography 
only because Dr. Anson had gone there once or twice to lecture.  
The curious thing was that she should have thought it worth while 
to find excuses for young Winsloe.  The fact that she did so had 
not escaped the attention of the village; but people, after a gasp 
of awe, said it was the most natural thing in the world that a girl 
like Paulina Anson should think of marrying.  It would certainly 
seem a little odd to see a man in the House, but young Winsloe 
would of course understand that the Doctor's books were not to be 
disturbed, and that he must go down to the orchard to smoke.  The 
village had barely framed this <hi rend="italic"> modus vivendi</hi> when it was 
convulsed by the announcement that young Winsloe declined to live 
in the House on any terms.  Hang going down to the orchard to 
smoke!  He meant to take his wife to New York.  The village drew 
its breath and watched. 
</p><p>Did Persephone, snatched from the warm fields of Enna, peer 
half-consentingly down the chasm that opened at her feet?  Paulina, 
it must be owned, hung a moment over the black gulf of temptation.  
She would have found it easy to cope with a deliberate disregard of 
her grandfather's rights; but young Winsloe's unconsciousness of 
that shadowy claim was as much a natural function as the falling of 
leaves on a grave.  His love was an embodiment of the perpetual 
renewal which to some tender spirits seems a crueller process than 
decay. 
</p><p>On women of Paulina's mould this piety toward implicit 
demands, toward the ghosts of dead duties walking unappeased  
<pb n="161"/>  among usurping passions, has a stronger hold than any tangible 
bond.  People said that she gave up young Winsloe because her aunts 
disapproved of her leaving them; but such disapproval as reached 
her was an emanation from the walls of the House, from the bare 
desk, the faded portraits, the dozen yellowing tomes that no hand 
but hers ever lifted from the shelf. 


</p><p>                           II 

</p><p>AFTER that the House possessed her.  As if conscious of its 
victory it imposed a conqueror's claims.  It had once been 
suggested that she should write a life of her grandfather, and the 
task from which she had shrunk as from a too-oppressive privilege 
now shaped itself into a justification of her course.  In a burst 
of filial pantheism she tried to lose herself in the vast ancestral 
consciousness.  Her one refuge from scepticism was a blind faith in 
the magnitude and the endurance of the idea to which she had 
sacrificed her life, and with a passionate instinct of self-preservation she labored to fortify her position. 
</p><p>The preparations for the <hi rend="italic"> Life</hi> led her through byways that 
the most scrupulous of the previous biographers had left 
unexplored.  She accumulated her material with a blind animal 
patience, unconscious of fortuitous risks.  The years stretched 
before her like some vast blank page spread out to receive the 
record of her toil; and she had a mystic conviction that she would 
not die till her work was accomplished. 
</p><p>The aunts, sustained by no such high purpose, withdrew in turn 
to their respective divisions of the Anson "plot," and Paulina 
remained alone with her task.  She was forty when the book was 
completed.  She had travelled little in her life, and it had become 
more and more difficult to her to leave the House even for a day; 
but the dread of entrusting her document to a strange hand made her 
decide to carry it herself to the publisher.  On the way to Boston 
she had a sudden vision of the loneliness to which this last 
parting condemned her.  All her youth, all her dreams, all her 
renunciations lay in that neat bundle on her knee.  It was not so 
much her grandfather's life as her own that she had written; and 
the knowledge that it would come back to her in all the 
glorification of print was of no more help than, to a mother's 
grief, the assurance that the lad she must part with will return 
with epaulets. 
</p><p>She had naturally addressed herself to the firm which had 
published her grandfather's works.  Its founder, a personal friend 
of the philosopher's, had survived the Olympian group of which he 
had been a subordinate member long enough to bestow his 
octogenarian approval on Paulina's pious undertaking.  But he had 
died soon afterward; and Miss Anson found herself confronted by his 
grandson, a person with a brisk commercial view of his trade, who 
was said to have put "new blood" into the firm. 
</p><p>This gentleman listened attentively, fingering her manuscript 
as though literature were a tactile substance; then, with a 
confidential twist of his revolving chair, he emitted the verdict: 
"We ought to have had this ten years sooner." 
</p><p>Miss Anson took the words as an allusion to the repressed 
avidity of her readers.  "It has been a long time for the public to 
wait," she solemnly assented. 
</p><p>The publisher smiled.  "They haven't waited," he said. 
</p><p>She looked at him strangely.  "Haven't waited?" 
</p><p>"No&mdash;they've gone off; taken another train.  Literature's like 
a big railway station now, you know: there's a train starting every 
minute.  People are not going to hang round the waiting-room.  If 
they can't get to a place when they want to they go somewhere 
else." 
</p><p>The application of this parable cost Miss Anson several 
minutes of throbbing silence.  At length she said: "Then I am to 
understand that the public is no longer interested in&mdash;in my 
grandfather?"  She felt as though heaven must blast the lips that 
risked such a conjecture. 
</p><p>"Well, it's this way.  He's a name still, of course.  People 
don't exactly want to be caught not knowing who he is; but they 
don't want to spend two dollars finding out, when they can look him 
up for nothing in any biographical dictionary." 
</p><p>Miss Anson's world reeled.  She felt <pb n="162"/>  herself adrift 
among mysterious forces, and no more thought of prolonging the 
discussion than of opposing an earthquake with argument.  She went 
home carrying the manuscript like a wounded thing.  On the return 
journey she found herself traveling straight toward a fact that had 
lurked for months in the background of her life, and that now 
seemed to await her on the very threshold: the fact that fewer 
visitors came to the House.  She owned to herself that for the last 
four or five years the number had steadily diminished.  Engrossed 
in her work, she had noted the change only to feel thankful that 
she had fewer interruptions.  There had been a time when, at the 
travelling season, the bell rang continuously, and the ladies of 
the House lived in a chronic state of "best silks" and expectation.  
It would have been impossible then to carry on any consecutive 
work; and she now saw that the silence which had gathered round her 
task had been the hush of death. 
</p><p>Not of <hi rend="italic"> his</hi> death!  The very walls cried out against the 
implication.  It was the world's enthusiasm, the world's faith, the 
world's loyalty that had died.  A corrupt generation that had 
turned aside to worship the brazen serpent.  Her heart yearned with 
a prophetic passion over the lost sheep straying in the wilderness.  
But all great glories had their interlunar periods; and in due time 
her grandfather would once more flash full-orbed upon a darkling 
world. 
</p><p>The few friends to whom she confided her adventure reminded 
her with tender indignation that there were other publishers less 
subject to the fluctuations of the market; but much as she had 
braved for her grandfather, she could not again brave that 
particular probation.  She found herself, in fact, incapable of any 
immediate effort.  She had lost her way in a labyrinth of 
conjecture where her worst dread was that she might put her hand 
upon the clew. 
</p><p>She locked up the manuscript and sat down to wait.  If a 
pilgrim had come just then the priestess would have fallen on his 
neck; but she continued to celebrate her rites alone.  It was a 
double solitude; for she had always thought a great deal more of 
the people who came to see the House than of the people who came to 
see her.  She fancied that the neighbors kept a keen eye on the 
path to the house; and there were days when the figure of a 
stranger strolling past the gate seemed to focus upon her the 
scorching sympathies of the village.  For a time she thought of 
travelling; of going to Europe, or even to Boston; but to leave the 
House now would have seemed like deserting her post.  Gradually her 
scattered energies centred themselves in the fierce resolve to 
understand what had happened.  She was not the woman to live long 
in an unmapped country or to accept as final her private 
interpretation of phenomena.  Like a traveller in unfamiliar 
regions, she began to store for future guidance the minutest 
natural signs.  Unflinchingly she noted the accumulating symptoms 
of indifference that marked her grandfather's descent toward 
posterity.  She passed from the heights on which he had been 
grouped with the sages of his day to the lower level where he had 
come to be "the friend of Emerson," "the correspondent of 
Hawthorne," or (later still) "the Dr. Anson" mentioned in their 
letters.  The change had taken place as slowly and imperceptibly as 
a natural process.  She could not say that any ruthless hand had 
stripped the leaves from the tree: it was simply that, among the 
evergreen glories of his group, her grandfather's had proved 
deciduous. 
</p><p>She had still to ask herself why.  If the decay had been a 
natural process, was it not the very pledge of renewal?  It was 
easier to find such arguments than to be convinced by them.  Again 
and again she tried to drug her solicitude with analogies; but at 
last she saw that such expedients were but the expression of a 
growing incredulity.  The best way of proving her faith in her 
grandfather was not to be afraid of his critics.  She had no notion 
where these shadowy antagonists lurked; for she had never heard of 
the great man's doctrine being directly combated.  Oblique assaults 
there must have been, however, Parthian shots at the giant that 
none dared face; and she thirsted to close with such assailants.  
The difficulty was to find them.  She began by re-reading the <hi rend="italic"> 
Works;</hi> thence she passed to the writers of the same school, those 
whose rhetoric bloomed perennial in <hi rend="italic"> First Read-</hi>
<pb n="163"/> 
<hi rend="italic"> ers</hi> 
from which her grandfather's prose had long since faded.  Amid that 
clamor of far-off enthusiasms she detected no controversial note.  
The little knot of Olympians held their views in common with an 
early-Christian promiscuity.  They were continually proclaiming 
their admiration for each other, the public joining as chorus in 
this guileless antiphon of praise; and she discovered no traitor in 
their midst. 
</p><p>What then had happened?  Was it simply that the main current 
of thought had set another way?  Then why did the others survive?  
Why were they still marked down as tributaries to the philosophic 
stream?  This question carried her still farther afield, and she 
pressed on with the passion of a champion whose reluctance to know 
the worst might be construed into a doubt of his cause.  At 
length&mdash;slowly but inevitably&mdash;an explanation shaped itself.  Death 
had overtaken the doctrines about which her grandfather had draped 
his cloudy rhetoric.  They had disintegrated and been reabsorbed, 
adding their little pile to the dust drifted about the mute lips of 
the Sphinx.  The great man's contemporaries had survived not by 
reason of what they taught, but of what they were; and he, who had 
been the mere mask through which they mouthed their lesson, the 
instrument on which their tune was played, lay buried deep among 
the obsolete tools of thought. 
</p><p>The discovery came to Paulina suddenly.  She looked up one 
evening from her reading, and it stood before her like a ghost.  It 
had entered her life with stealthy steps, creeping close before she 
was aware of it.  She sat in the library, among the carefully 
tended books and portraits; and it seemed to her that she had been 
walled alive into a tomb hung with the effigies of dead ideas.  She 
felt a desperate longing to escape into the outer air, where people 
toiled and loved, and living sympathies went hand in hand.  It was 
the sense of wasted labor that oppressed her; of two lives consumed 
in that ruthless process that uses generations of effort to built 
[sic] a single cell.  There was a dreary parallel between her 
grandfather's fruitless toil and her own unprofitable sacrifice.  
Each in turn had kept vigil by a corpse. 


</p><p>                           III 

</p><p>THE bell rang&mdash;she remembered it afterward&mdash;with a loud 
thrilling note.  It was what they used to call the "visitor's 
ring"; not the tentative tinkle of a neighbor dropping in to borrow 
a sauce-pan or discuss parochial incidents, but a decisive summons 
from the outer world. 
</p><p>Miss Anson put down her knitting and listened.  She sat 
upstairs now, making her rheumatism an excuse for avoiding the 
rooms below.  Her interests had insensibly adjusted themselves to 
the perspective of her neighbors' lives, and she wondered&mdash;as the 
bell re-echoed&mdash;if it could mean that Mrs. Heminway's baby had 
come.  Conjecture had time to ripen into certainty, and she was 
limping toward the closet where her cloak and bonnet hung, when her 
little maid fluttered in with the announcement: "A gentleman to see 
the house." 
</p><p>"The <hi rend="italic"> House?"</hi> 
</p><p>"Yes, m'm.  I don't know what he means," faltered the 
messenger, whose memory did not embrace the period when such 
announcements were a daily part of the domestic routine. 
</p><p>Miss Anson glanced at the proffered card.  The name it 
bore&mdash;Mr. George Corby&mdash;was unknown to her, but the blood rose to 
her languid cheek.  "Hand me my Mechlin cap, Katy," she said, 
trembling a little, as she laid aside her walking-stick.  She put 
the cap on before the mirror, with rapid unsteady touches.  "Did 
you draw up the library blinds?" she breathlessly asked. 
</p><p>She had gradually built up a wall of commonplace between 
herself and her illusions, but at the first summons of the past 
filial passion swept away the frail barriers of expediency. 
</p><p>She walked downstairs so hurriedly that her stick clicked like 
a girlish heel; but in the hall she paused, wondering nervously if 
Katy had put a match to the fire.  The autumn air was cold and she 
had the reproachful vision of a visitor with elderly ailments 
shivering by her inhospitable hearth.  She thought instinctively of 
the stranger as a survivor of the days when such a visit was a part 
of the young enthusiast's itinerary. <pb n="164"/>  
</p><p>The fire was unlit and the room forbiddingly cold; but the 
figure which, as Miss Anson entered, turned from a lingering 
scrutiny of the book-shelves, was that of a fresh-eyed sanguine 
youth clearly independent of any artificial caloric.  She stood 
still a moment, feeling herself the victim of some anterior 
impression that made this robust presence an insubstantial thing; 
but the young man advanced with an air of genial assurance which 
rendered him at once more real and more reminiscent. 
</p><p>"Why this, you know," he exclaimed, "is simply immense!" 
</p><p>The words, which did not immediately present themselves as 
slang to Miss Anson's unaccustomed ear, echoed with an odd 
familiarity through the academic silence. 
</p><p>"The room, you know, I mean," he explained with a 
comprehensive gesture.  "These jolly portraits, and the books&mdash; 
that's the old gentleman himself over the mantelpiece, I suppose?&mdash; 
and the elms outside, and&mdash;and the whole business.  I do like a 
congruous background&mdash;don't you?" 
</p><p>His hostess was silent.  No one but Hewlett Winsloe had ever 
spoken of her grandfather as "the old gentleman." 
</p><p>"It's a hundred times better than I could have hoped," her 
visitor continued, with a cheerful disregard of her silence.  "The 
seclusion, the remoteness, the philosophic atmosphere&mdash;there's so 
little of that kind of flavor left!  I should have simply hated to 
find that he lived over a grocery, you know.  I had the deuce of a 
time finding out where he <hi rend="italic"> did</hi> live," he began again, after 
another glance of parenthetical enjoyment.  "But finally I got on 
the trail through some old book on Brook Farm.  I was bound I'd get 
the environment right before I did my article." 
</p><p>Miss Anson, by this time, had recovered sufficient self-possession to seat herself and assign a chair to her visitor. 
</p><p>"Do I understand," she asked slowly, following his rapid eye 
about the room, "that you intend to write an article about my 
grandfather?" 
</p><p>"That's what I'm here for," Mr. Corby genially responded; 
"that is, if you're willing to help me; for I can't get on without 
your help," he added with a confident smile. 
</p><p>There was another pause, during which Miss Anson noticed a 
fleck of dust on the faded leather of the writing-table and a fresh 
spot of discoloration in the right-hand upper corner of Raphael 
Morghen's "Parnassus." 
</p><p>"Then you believe in him?" she said, looking up.  She could 
not tell what had prompted her; the words rushed out irresistibly. 
</p><p>"Believe in him?" Corby cried, springing to his feet.  
"Believe in Orestes Anson?  Why, I believe he's simply the 
greatest&mdash;the most stupendous&mdash;the most phenomenal figure we've 
got!" 
</p><p>The color rose to Miss Anson's brow.  Her heart was beating 
passionately.  She kept her eyes fixed on the young man's face, as 
though it might vanish if she looked away. 
</p><p>"You&mdash;you mean to say this in your article?" she asked. 
</p><p>"Say it?  Why, the facts will say it," he exulted.  "The 
baldest kind of a statement would make it clear.  When a man is as 
big as that he doesn't need a pedestal!" 
</p><p>Miss Anson sighed.  "People used to say that when I was 
young," she murmured.  "But now&mdash;" 
</p><p>Her visitor stared.  "When you were young?  But how did they 
know&mdash;when the thing hung fire as it did?  When the whole edition 
was thrown back on his hands?" 
</p><p>"The whole edition&mdash;what edition?"  It was Miss Anson's turn 
to stare. 
</p><p>"Why, of his pamphlet&mdash;<hi rend="italic"> the</hi> pamphlet&mdash;the one thing that 
counts, that survives, that makes him what he is!  For heaven's 
sake," he tragically adjured her, "don't tell me there isn't a copy 
of it left!" 
</p><p>Miss Anson was trembling slightly.  "I don't think I 
understand what you mean," she faltered, less bewildered by his 
vehemence than by the strange sense of coming on an unexplored 
region in the very heart of her dominions. 
</p><p>"Why, his account of the <hi rend="italic"> amphioxus</hi>, of course!  You can't 
mean that his family didn't know about it&mdash;that <hi rend="italic"> you</hi> don't know 
about it?  I came across it by the merest accident myself, in a 
letter of vindication that he wrote in 1830 to an old scientific 
paper; but I understood there were journals&mdash;early journals; there 
must be refer-<pb n="165"/> ences to it somewhere in the 'twenties.  He 
must have been at least ten or twelve years ahead of Yarrell; and 
he saw the whole significance of it, too&mdash;he saw where it led to.  
As I understand it, he actually anticipated in his pamphlet Saint 
Hilaire's theory of the universal type, and supported the 
hypothesis by describing the notochord of the amphioxus as a 
cartilaginous vertebral column.  The specialists of the day jeered 
at him, of course, as the specialists in Goethe's time jeered at 
the plant-metamorphosis.  As far as I can make out, the anatomists 
and zoologists were down on Dr. Anson to a man; that was why his 
cowardly publishers went back on their bargain.  But the pamphlet 
must be here somewhere&mdash;he writes as though, in his first 
disappointment, he had destroyed the whole edition; but surely 
there must be at least one copy left?" 
</p><p>His scientific jargon was as bewildering as his slang; and 
there were even moments in his discourse where Miss Anson ceased to 
distinguish between them; but the suspense with which he continued 
to gaze on her acted as a challenge to her scattered thoughts. 
</p><p>"The <hi rend="italic"> amphioxus</hi>," she murmured, half-rising.  "It's an 
animal, isn't it&mdash;a fish?  Yes, I think I remember."  She sank back 
with the inward look of one who retraces some lost line of 
association. 
</p><p>Gradually the distance cleared, the details started into life.  
In her researches for the biography she had patiently followed 
every ramification of her subject, and one of these overgrown paths 
now led her back to the episode in question.  The great Orestes's 
title of "Doctor" had in fact not been merely the spontaneous 
tribute of a national admiration; he had actually studied medicine 
in his youth, and his diaries, as his granddaughter now recalled, 
showed that he had passed through a brief phase of anatomical ardor 
before his attention was diverted to super-sensual problems.  It 
had indeed seemed to Paulina, as she scanned those early pages, 
that they revealed a spontaneity, a freshness of feeling somehow 
absent from his later lucubrations&mdash;as though this one emotion had 
reached him directly, the others through some interventing [sic] 
medium.  In the excess of her commemorative zeal, she had even 
struggled through the unintelligible pamphlet to which a few lines 
in the journal had bitterly directed her.  But the subject and the 
phraseology were alien to her, and unconnected with her conception 
of the great man's genius; and after a hurried perusal she had 
averted her thoughts from the episode as from a revelation of 
failure.  At length she rose a little unsteadily, supporting 
herself against the writing-table.  She looked hesitatingly about 
the room; then she drew a key from her old-fashioned reticule and 
unlocked a drawer beneath one of the book-cases.  Young Corby 
watched her breathlessly.  With a tremulous hand she turned over 
the dusty documents that seemed to fill the drawer.  "Is this it?" 
she said, holding out a thin discolored volume. 
</p><p>He seized it with a gasp.  "Oh, by George," he said, dropping 
into the nearest chair. 
</p><p>She stood observing him strangely as his eye devoured the 
mouldy pages. 
</p><p>"Is this the only copy left?" he asked at length, looking up 
for a moment as a thirsty man lifts his head from his glass. 
</p><p>"I think it must be.  I found it long ago, among some old 
papers that my aunts were burning up after my grandmother's death.  
They said it was of no use&mdash;that he'd always meant to destroy the 
whole edition and that I ought to respect his wishes.  But it was 
something <hi rend="italic"> he</hi> had written; to burn it was like shutting the door 
against his voice&mdash;against something he had once wished to say, and 
that nobody had listened to.  I wanted him to feel that I was 
always here, ready to listen, even when others hadn't thought it 
worth while; and so I kept the pamphlet, meaning to carry out his 
wish and destroy it before my death." 
</p><p>Her visitor gave a groan of retrospective anguish.  "And but 
for me&mdash;but for to-day&mdash;you would have?" 
</p><p>"I should have thought it my duty." 
</p><p>"Oh, by George&mdash;by George," he repeated, subdued afresh by the 
inadequacy of speech. 
</p><p>She continued to watch him in silence.  At length he jumped up 
and impulsively caught her by both hands. 
</p><p>"He's bigger and bigger!" he almost shouted.  "He simply leads 
the field!  You'll help me go to the bottom of this, <pb n="166"/>  won't 
you?  We must turn out all the papers&mdash;letters, journals, 
memoranda.  He must have made some notes.  He must have left some 
record of what led up to this.  We must leave nothing unexplored.  
By Jove," he cried, looking up at her with his bright convincing 
smile, "do you know you're the granddaughter of a Great Man?" 
</p><p>Her color flickered like a girl's.  "Are you&mdash;sure of him?" 
she whispered, as though putting him on his guard against a 
possible betrayal of trust. 
</p><p>"Sure!  Sure!  My dear lady&mdash;" he measured her again with his 
quick confident glance.  "Don't <hi rend="italic"> you</hi> believe in him?" 
</p><p>She drew back with a confused murmur.  "I&mdash;used to."  She had 
left her hands in his: their pressure seemed to send a warm current 
to her heart.  "It ruined my life!" she cried with sudden passion.  
He looked at her perplexedly. 
</p><p>"I gave up everything," she went on wildly, "to keep <hi rend="italic"> him</hi> 
alive.  I sacrificed myself&mdash;others&mdash;I nursed his glory in my 
bosom, and it died&mdash;and left me&mdash;left me here alone."  She paused 
and gathered her courage with a gasp.  "Don't make the same 
mistake!" she warned him. 
</p><p>He shook his head, still smiling.  "No danger of that!  You're 
not alone, my dear lady.  He's here with you&mdash;he's come back to you 
to-day.  Don't you see what's happened?  Don't you see that it's 
your love that has kept him alive?  If you'd abandoned your post 
for an instant&mdash;let things pass into other hands&mdash;if your wonderful 
tenderness hadn't perpetually kept guard&mdash;this might have been&mdash; 
must have been&mdash;irretrievably lost."  He laid his hand on the 
pamphlet.  "And then&mdash;then he <hi rend="italic"> would</hi> have been dead!" 
</p><p>"Oh," she said, "don't tell me too suddenly!"  And she turned 
away and sank into a chair. 
</p><p>The young man stood watching her in an awed silence.  For a 
long time she sat motionless, with her face hidden, and he thought 
she must be weeping. 
</p><p>At length he said, almost shyly: "You'll let me come back, 
then?  You'll help me work this thing out?" 
</p><p>She rose calmly and held out her hand.  "I'll help you," she 
declared. 
</p><p>"I'll come to-morrow, then.  Can we get to work early?" 
</p><p>"As early as you please." 
</p><p>"At eight o'clock, then," he said briskly.  "You'll have the 
papers ready?" 
</p><p>"I'll have everything ready."  She added with a half-playful 
hesitancy: "And the fire shall be lit for you." 
</p><p>He went out with his bright nod.  She walked to the window and 
watched his buoyant figure hastening down the elm-shaded street.  
When she turned back into the empty room she looked as though youth 
had touched her on the lips. 
</p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
