<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaPret"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="WhaPret"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Pretext</title>
<title type="sort">pretext</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text 
Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">71</num> kilobytes</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>  
<idno type="ETC">WhaPret</idno>  
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476508</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>  
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Pretext</title>
<title type="sort">pretext</title>
<author>Edith Wharton</author>
</titleStmt>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner's</publisher>  
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>  
<date value="1908-08">August 1908</date>
</publicationStmt>  
<seriesStmt>
<p>Scribner's Magazine</p>
</seriesStmt>  
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>  
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>  
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>  
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme   
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>  
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's  
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of   
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>  
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1908">1908</date>
</creation>  
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>  
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>  
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-02">February 1995</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Monique Dull, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>conversion to basic TEI-conformant markup</item>
</change>  
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>  
<text id="d1">   
<body id="d2"> 
 
<div1 type="section" n="1" id="d3"> <pb n="173"/>   
<head>  Wharton, Edith.  "The Pretext."<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic"> Scribner's Magazine</hi>  44 (Aug. 1908): 173-187. <lb/> 
                                 I </head> 
 
<p> 
     MRS. RANSOM, when the front door had closed on her visitor,  
passed with a spring from the drawing-room to the narrow hall, 
and  
thence up the narrow stairs to her bedroom. </p><p> 
     Though slender, and still light of foot, she did not always  
move so quickly: hitherto, in her life, there had not been much 
to  
hurry for, save the recurring domestic tasks that compel haste  
without fostering elasticity; but some impetus of youth revived,  
communicated to her by her talk with Guy Dawnish, now found  
expression in her girlish flight upstairs, her girlish impatience 
 
to bolt herself into her room with her throbs and her blushes. 
</p><p> 
     Her blushes?  Was she really blushing? </p><p> 
     She approached the cramped "Colonial" mirror above her plain 
 
prim dressing-table: just such a meagre concession to the 
weakness  
of the flesh as every old-fashioned house in Wentworth counted  
among its heirlooms.  The face reflected in this unflattering  
surface&mdash;for even the mirrors of Wentworth erred on the side of  
depreciation&mdash;did not seem, at first sight, a suitable theatre 
for  
the display of the tenderer emotions, and its owner blushed more  
deeply as the fact was forced upon her. </p><p> 
     Her fair hair had grown too thin&mdash;it no longer quite hid the 
 
blue veins in her candid forehead&mdash;a forehead that one seemed to  
see turned toward professorial desks, in large bare halls where a 
 
snowy winter light fell uncompromisingly on rows of "thoughtful  
women."  Her mouth was thin, too, and a little strained; her lips 
 
were too pale; and there were lines in the corners of her eyes.  
It  
was a face which had grown middle-aged while it waited for the 
joys  
of youth. </p><p> 
     Well&mdash;but if she could still blush?  Instinctively she drew  
back a little, so that her scrutiny became less microscopic, and  
the pretty lingering pink threw a veil over her pallor, the 
hollows  
in her temples, the faint wrinkles of inexperience about her lips 
 
and eyes.  How a little colour helped!  It made her eyes so deep  
and shining.  She saw now why bad women rouged. . . .  Her 
redness  
deepened at the thought. </p><p> 
     But suddenly she noticed for the first time that the collar 
of  
her dress was cut too low.  It showed the shrunken lines of the  
throat.  She rummaged feverishly in a tidy scentless drawer, and  
snatching out a bit of black velvet, bound it about her neck.   
Yes&mdash;that was better.  It gave her the relief she needed.   
Relief&mdash;contrast&mdash;that was it!  She had never had any, either in  
her appearance or in her setting.  She was as flat as the pattern 
 
of the wall-paper&mdash;and so was her life.  And all the people about 
 
her had the same look.  Wentworth was the kind of place where  
husbands and wives gradually grew to resemble each other&mdash;one or  
two of her friends, she remembered, had told her lately that she  
and Ransom were beginning to look alike. . . . </p><p> 
     But why had she always, so tamely, allowed her aspect to  
conform to her situation?  Perhaps a gayer exterior would have  
provoked a brighter fate.  Even now&mdash;she turned back to the 
glass,  
loosened the tight strands of hair above her brow, ran the fine 
end  
of the comb under them with a rapid frizzing motion, and then  
disposed them, more lightly and amply, above her eager face.  
Yes&mdash;  
it was really better; it made a difference.  She smiled at 
herself  
with a timid coquetry, and her lips seemed rosier as she smiled.  
 
Then she laid down the comb and the smile faded.  It made a  
difference, certainly&mdash;but was it right to try to make one's hair 
 
look thicker and wavier than it really was?  Between that and  
rouging the ethical line seemed almost impalpable, and the 
spectre  
of her rigid New England ancestry rose reprovingly before her.  
She  
was sure that none of her grandmothers had ever simulated a curl 
or  
encouraged a blush.  <pb n="174"/>  A blush, indeed!  What 
had any of them  
ever had to blush for in all their frozen lives?  And what, in  
Heaven's name, had she?  She sat down in the stiff mahogany  
rocking-chair beside her work-table and tried to collect herself.  
 
>From childhood she had been taught to "collect herself"&mdash;but 
never  
before had her small sensations and aspirations been so widely  
scattered, diffused over so vague and uncharted an expanse.   
Hitherto they had lain in neatly sorted and easily accessible  
bundles on the high shelves of a perfectly ordered moral  
consciousness.  And now&mdash;now that for the first time they   
<hi rend="italic"> needed</hi> collecting&mdash;now that the little winged and 
scattered bits  
of self were dancing madly down the vagrant winds of fancy, she  
knew no spell to call them to the fold again.  The best way, no  
doubt&mdash;if only her bewilderment permitted&mdash;was to go back to the  
beginning&mdash;the beginning, at least, of to-day's visit&mdash;to  
recapitulate, word for word and look for look. . . . </p><p> 
     She clasped her hands on the arms of the chair, checked its  
swaying with a firm thrust of her foot, and fixed her eyes upon 
the  
inward vision. . . . </p><p> 
     To begin with, what had made to-day's visit so different 
from  
the others?  It became suddenly vivid to her that there had been  
many, almost daily, others, since Guy Dawnish's coming to  
Wentworth.  Even the previous winter&mdash;the winter of his arrival  
from England&mdash;his visits had been numerous enough to make 
Wentworth  
aware that&mdash;very naturally&mdash;Mrs. Ransom was "looking after" the  
stray young Englishman committed to her husband's care by an  
eminent Q. C. whom the Ransoms had known on one of their brief  
London visits, and with whom Ransom had since maintained  
professional relations.  All this was in the natural order of  
things, as sanctioned by the social code of Wentworth.  Every one 
 
was kind to Guy Dawnish&mdash;some rather importunately so, as 
Margaret  
Ransom had smiled to observe&mdash;but it was recognized as fitting 
that  
she should be kindest, since he was in a sense her property, 
since  
his people in England, by profusely acknowledging her kindness, 
had  
given it the domestic sanction without which, to Wentworth, any  
social relation between the sexes remained unhallowed and to be  
viewed askance.  Yes!  And even this second winter, when the 
visits  
had become so much more frequent, so admitted a part of the day's 
 
routine, there had not been, from any one, a hint of surprise or 
of  
conjecture. . . . </p><p> 
     Mrs. Ransom smiled with a faint bitterness.  She was 
protected  
by her age, no doubt&mdash;her age and her past, and the image her  
mirror gave back to her. . . . </p><p> 
     Her door-handle turned suddenly, and the bolt's resistance 
was  
met by an impatient knock. </p><p> 
     "Margaret!" </p><p> 
     She started up, her brightness fading, and unbolted the door 
 
to admit her husband. </p><p> 
     "Why are you locked in?  Why, you're not dressed yet!" he  
exclaimed. </p><p> 
     It was possible for Ransom to reach his dressing-room by a  
slight circuit through the passage; but it was characteristic of  
the relentless domesticity of their relation that he chose, as a  
matter of course, the directer way through his wife's bedroom.  
She  
had never before been disturbed by this practice, which she  
accepted as inevitable, but had merely adapted her own habits to  
it, delaying her hasty toilet till he was safely in his room, or  
completing it before she heard his step on the stair; since a  
scrupulous traditional prudery had miraculously survived this  
massacre of all the privacies. </p><p> 
     "Oh, I shan't dress this evening&mdash;I shall just have some tea 
 
in the library after you've gone," she answered absently.  "Your  
things are laid out," she added, rousing herself. </p><p> 
     He looked surprised.  "The dinner's at seven.  I suppose the 
 
speeches will begin at nine.  I thought you were coming to hear  
them." </p><p> 
     She wavered.  "I don't know.  I think not.  Mrs. Sperry's 
ill,  
and I've no one else to go with." </p><p> 
     He glanced at his watch.  "Why not get hold of Dawnish?   
Wasn't he here just now?  Why didn't you ask him?" </p><p> 
     She turned toward her dressing-table, and straightened the  
comb and brush with a nervous hand.  Her husband had given her,  
that morning, two tickets for the ladies' gallery in Hamblin 
Hall,  
where the great public dinner of the evening was to take place&mdash;a 
 
banquet offered by the faculty of Wentworth to visitors of aca-<pb n="175"/> demic eminence&mdash;and she had meant to ask 
Dawnish to go with  
her: it had seemed the most natural thing to do, till the end of  
his visit came, and then, after all, she had not spoken. . . . 
</p><p> 
     "It's too late now," she murmured, bending over her pin  
cushion. </p><p> 
     "Too late?  Not if you telephone him." </p><p> 
     Her husband came toward her, and she turned quickly to face  
him, lest he should suspect her of trying to avoid his eye.  To  
what duplicity was she already committed! </p><p> 
     Ransom laid a friendly hand on her arm: "Come along, 
Margaret.   
You know I speak for the bar."  She was aware, in his voice, of a 
 
little note of surprise at his having to remind her of this. 
</p><p> 
     "Oh, yes.  I meant to go, of course&mdash;" </p><p> 
     "Well, then&mdash;"  He opened his dressing-room door, and caught 
 
a glimpse of the retreating house-maid's skirt.  "Here's Maria 
now.   
Maria!  Call up Mr. Dawnish&mdash;at Mrs. Creswell's, you know.  Tell  
him Mrs. Ransom wants him to go with her to hear the speeches 
this  
evening&mdash;the <hi rend="italic"> speeches</hi>, you understand?&mdash;and he's to call 
for  
her at a quarter before nine." </p><p> 
     Margaret heard the Irish "Yessir" on the stairs, and stood  
motionless, while her husband added loudly: "And bring me some  
towels when you come up."  Then he turned back into his wife's  
room. </p><p> 
     "Why, it would be a thousand pities for Guy to miss this.   
He's so interested in the way we do things over here&mdash;and I don't 
 
know that he's ever heard me speak in public."  Again the slight  
note of fatuity!  Was it possible that Ransom was a fatuous man? 
</p><p> 
     He paused in front of her, his short-sighted unobservant  
glance concentrating itself unexpectedly on her face. </p><p> 
     "You're not going like that, are you?" he asked, with 
glaring  
eye-glasses. </p><p> 
     "Like what?" she faltered, lifting a conscious hand to the  
velvet at her throat. </p><p> 
     "With your hair in such a fearful mess.  Have you been  
shampooing it?  You look like the Brant girl at the end of a  
tennis-match." </p><p> 
     The Brant girl was their horror&mdash;the horror of all right-thinking Wentworth; a laced, whale-boned, frizzle-headed, high-heeled daughter of iniquity, who came&mdash;from New York, of 
course&mdash;on  
long, disturbing, tumultuous visits to a Wentworth aunt, working  
havoc among the freshmen, and leaving, when she departed, an 
angry  
wake of criticism that ruffled the social waters for weeks.    
<hi rend="italic"> She</hi>, too, had tried her hand at Guy&mdash;with ludicrous 
unsuccess.   
And now, to be compared to her&mdash;to be accused of looking "New  
Yorky!"  Ah, there are times when husbands are obtuse; and 
Ransom,  
as he stood there, thick and yet juiceless, in his dry legal 
middle  
age, with his wiry dust-coloured beard, and his perpetual <hi rend="italic"> 
pince-nez</hi>, seemed to his wife a sudden embodiment of this 
traditional  
attribute.  Not that she had ever fancied herself, poor soul, a 
<hi rend="italic">"  
femme incomprise</hi>."  She had, on the contrary, prided herself 
on  
being understood by her husband, almost as much as on her own  
complete comprehension of him.  Wentworth laid a good deal of  
stress on "motives"; and Margaret Ransom and her husband had 
dwelt  
in a complete community of motive.  It had been the proudest day 
of  
her life when, without consulting her, he had refused an offer of 
 
partnership in an eminent New York firm because he preferred the  
distinction of practising in Wentworth, of being known as the 
legal  
representative of the University.  Wentworth, in fact, had always 
 
been the bond between the two; they were united in their 
veneration  
for that estimable seat of learning, and in their modest yet 
vivid  
consciousness of possessing its tone.  The Wentworth "tone" is  
unmistakable: it permeates every part of the social economy, from 
 
the <hi rend="italic"> coiffure</hi> of the ladies to the preparation of the 
food.  It  
has its sumptuary laws as well as its curriculum of learning.  It 
 
sits in judgment not only on its own townsmen but on the rest of  
the world&mdash;enlightening, criticising, ostracizing a heedless  
universe&mdash;and non-conformity to Wentworth standards involves  
obliteration from Wentworth's consciousness. </p><p> 
     In a world without traditions, without reverence, without  
stability, such little expiring centres of prejudice and 
precedent  
make an irresistible appeal to those instincts for which a  
democracy has neglected to provide.  Wentworth, with its "tone,"  
its backward references, its inflexible aversions and  
condemnations, its hard moral outline preserved intact against a  
whirling background of experiment, had been all the poetry and  
history of Margaret Ransom's life.  Yes, what she had really   
<pb n="176"/>  esteemed in her husband was the fact of his 
being so intense  
an embodiment of Wentworth; so long and closely identified, for  
instance, with its legal affairs, that he was almost a part of 
its  
university existence, that of course, at a college banquet, he  
would inevitably speak for the bar! </p><p> 
     It was wonderful of how much consequence all this had seemed 
 
till now. . . .  
  
 </p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="2" id="d4"> 
<head> 
                                II </head> 
<p> 
     WHEN, punctually at ten minutes to seven, her husband had  
emerged from the house, Margaret Ransom remained seated in her  
bedroom, addressing herself anew to the difficult process of 
self-collection.  As an aid to this endeavour, she bent forward and  
looked out of the window, following Ransom's figure as it receded 
 
down the elm-shaded street.  He moved almost alone between the 
prim  
flowerless grass-plots, the white porches, the protrusion of  
irrelevant shingled gables, which stamped the empty street as 
part  
of an American college town.  She had always been proud of living 
 
in Hill Street, where the university people congregated, proud to 
 
associate her husband's retreating back, as he walked daily to 
his  
office, with backs literary and pedagogic, backs of which it was  
whispered, for the edification of duly-impressed visitors: "Wait  
till that old boy turns&mdash;that's so-and-so." </p><p> 
     This had been her world, a world destitute of personal  
experience, but filled with a rich sense of privilege and  
distinction, of being not as those millions were who, denied the  
inestimable advantage of living at Wentworth, pursued elsewhere  
careers foredoomed to futility by that very fact. </p><p> 
     And now&mdash;! </p><p> 
     She rose and turned to her work-table where she had dropped, 
 
on entering, the handful of photographs that Guy Dawnish had left 
 
with her.  While he sat so close, pointing out and explaining, 
she  
had hardly taken in the details; but now, on the full tones of 
his  
low young voice, they came back with redoubled distinctness.  
This  
was Guise Abbey, his uncle's place in Wiltshire, where, under his 
 
grandfather's rule, Guy's own boyhood had been spent: a long 
gabled  
Jacobean facade, many-chimneyed, ivy-draped, overhung (she felt  
sure) by the boughs of a venerable rookery.  And in this other  
picture&mdash;the walled garden at Guise&mdash;that was his uncle, Lord  
Askern, a hale gouty-looking figure, planted robustly on the  
terrace, a gun on his shoulder and a couple of setters at his 
feet.   
And here was the river below the park, with Guy "punting" a girl 
in  
a flapping hat&mdash;how Margaret hated the flap that hid the girl's  
face!  And here was the tennis-court, with Guy among a jolly 
cross-legged group of youths in flannels, and pretty girls about the 
tea-table under the big lime: in the centre the curate handing bread  
and butter, and in the middle distance a footman approaching with 
 
more cups. </p><p> 
     Margaret raised this picture closer to her eyes, puzzling, 
in  
the diminished light, over the face of the girl nearest to Guy  
Dawnish&mdash;bent above him in profile, while he laughingly lifted 
his  
head.  No hat hid this profile, which stood out clearly against 
the  
foliage behind it. </p><p> 
     "And who is that handsome girl?" Margaret had said, 
detaining  
the photograph as he pushed it aside, and struck by the fact 
that,  
of the whole group, he had left only this member unnamed. </p><p> 
     "Oh, only Gwendolen Matcher&mdash;I've always known her&mdash;.  Look 
at  
this: the almshouses at Guise.  Aren't they jolly?" </p><p> 
     And then&mdash;without her having had the courage to ask if the  
girl in the punt were also Gwendolen Matcher&mdash;they passed on to  
photographs of his rooms at Oxford, of a cousin's studio in  
London&mdash;one of Lord Askern's grandsons was "artistic"&mdash;of the 
rose-hung cottage in Wales to which, on the old Earl's death, his  
daughter-in-law, Guy's mother, had retired. </p><p> 
     Every one of the photographs opened a window on the life  
Margaret had been trying to picture since she had known him&mdash;a 
life  
so rich, so romantic, so packed&mdash;in the mere casual vocabulary of 
 
daily life&mdash;with historic reference and poetic allusion, that she 
 
felt almost oppressed by this distant whiff of its air.  The very 
 
words he used fascinated and bewildered her.  He seemed to have  
been born into all sorts of connections, political, historical,  
official, that made the Ransom situation at Wentworth as  
featureless as the top shelf of a dark closet.  Some one in the  
family had "asked for the Chiltern Hundreds"&mdash;one uncle was an  
Elder Brother of the Trinity House&mdash;some  <pb n="177"/>  one 
else was the  
Master of a College&mdash;some one was in command at Devonport&mdash;the  
Army, the Navy, the House of Commons, the House of Lords, the 
most  
venerable seats of learning, were all woven into the dense  
background of this young man's light unconscious talk.  For the  
unconsciousness was unmistakable.  Margaret was not without  
experience of the transatlantic visitor who sounds loud names and 
 
evokes reverberating connections.  The poetry of Guy Dawnish's  
situation lay in the fact that it was so completely a part of 
early  
associations and accepted facts.  Life was like that in 
England&mdash;in  
Wentworth of course (where he had been sent, through his uncle's  
influence, for two years' training in the neighbouring electrical 
 
works at Smedden)&mdash;in Wentworth, though "immensely jolly," it was 
 
different.  The fact that he was qualifying to be an electrical  
engineer&mdash;with the hope of a secretaryship at the London end of 
the  
great Smedden Company&mdash;that, at best, he was returning home to a  
life of industrial "grind," this fact, though avowedly a bore, 
did  
not disconnect him from that brilliant pinnacled past, that many- 
faceted life in which the brightest episodes of the whole body of 
 
English fiction seemed collectively reflected.  Of course he 
would  
have to work&mdash;younger sons' sons almost always had to&mdash;but his  
uncle Askern (like Wentworth) was "immensely jolly," and Guise  
always open to him, and his other uncle, the Master, a capital 
old  
boy too&mdash;and in town he could always put up with his clever aunt, 
 
Lady Caroline Duckett, who had made a "beastly marriage" and was  
horribly poor, but who knew everybody jolly and amusing, and had  
always been particularly kind to him. </p><p> 
     It was not&mdash;and Margaret had not, even in her own thoughts, 
to  
defend herself from the imputation&mdash;it was not what Wentworth 
would  
have called the "material side" of her friend's situation that  
captivated her.  She was austerely proof against such appeals: 
her  
enthusiasms were all of the imaginative order.  What subjugated 
her  
was the unexampled prodigality with which he poured for her the  
same draught of tradition of which Wentworth held out its little  
teacupful.  He besieged her with a million Wentworths in one&mdash;  
saying, as it were: "All these are mine for the asking&mdash;and I  
choose you instead!" </p><p> 
     For this, she told herself somewhat dizzily, was what it 
came  
to&mdash;the summing-up toward which her conscientious efforts at 
self-collection had been gradually pushing her: with all this in 
reach,  
Guy Dawnish was leaving Wentworth reluctantly. </p><p> 
     "I <hi rend="italic"> was</hi> a bit lonely here at first&mdash;but <hi rend="italic"> now!"</hi>  
And  
again: "It will be jolly, of course, to see them all again&mdash;but  
there are some things one doesn't easily give up. . . ." </p><p> 
     If he had known only Wentworth, it would have been wonderful 
 
enough that he should have chosen her out of all Wentworth&mdash;but 
to  
have known that other life, and to set her in the balance against 
 
it&mdash;poor Margaret Ransom, in whom, at the moment, nothing seemed 
of  
weight but her years!  Ah, it might well produce, in nerves and  
brain, and poor unpractised pulses, a flushed tumult of 
sensation,  
the rush of a great wave of life, under which memory struggled in 
 
vain to reassert itself, to particularize again just what his 
last  
words&mdash;the very last&mdash;had been. . . .  
 </p><p> 
     When consciousness emerged, quivering, from this 
retrospective  
assault, it pushed Margaret Ransom&mdash;feeling herself a mere leaf 
in  
the blast&mdash;toward the writing-table from which her innocent and  
voluminous correspondence habitually flowed.  She had a letter to 
 
write now&mdash;much shorter but more difficult than any she had ever  
been called on to indite. </p><p> 
     "Dear Mr. Dawnish," she began, "since telephoning you just 
now  
I have decided not&mdash;" </p><p> 
     Maria's voice, at the door, announced that tea was in the  
library: "And I s'pose it's the brown silk you'll wear to the  
speaking?" </p><p> 
     In the usual order of the Ransom existence, its mistress's  
toilet was performed unassisted; and the mere enquiry&mdash;at once  
friendly and deferential&mdash;projected, for Margaret, a strong light 
 
on the importance of the occasion.  That she should answer: "But 
I  
am not going," when the going was so manifestly part of a 
household  
solemnity about which the thoughts below stairs fluttered in 
proud  
participation; that in face of such participation she should 
utter  
a word implying indifference or hesitation&mdash;nay, revealing 
herself  
the transposed, uprooted thing she had been on the verge of  
becoming; to do this was&mdash;well! infinitely harder 
<pb n="178"/> 
than to  
perform the alternative act of tearing up the sheet of note-paper 
 
under her reluctant pen. </p><p> 
     Yes, she said, she would wear the brown silk. . . .  
  
 </p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="3" id="d5"><head> 
                                III</head> 
<p> 
     ALL the heat and glare from the long illuminated table, about  
which the fumes of many courses still hung in a savoury fog, seemed  
to surge up to the ladies' gallery, and concentrate themselves in  
the burning cheeks of a slender figure withdrawn behind the  
projection of a pillar. </p><p> 
     It never occurred to Margaret Ransom that she was sitting in 
 
the shade.  She supposed that the full light of the chandeliers 
was 
beating on her face&mdash;and there were moments when it seemed as  
though all the heads about the great horse-shoe below, bald,  
shaggy, sleek, close-thatched, or thinly latticed, were equipped  
with an additional pair of eyes, set at an angle which enabled 
them  
to rake her face as relentlessly as the electric burners. </p><p> 
     In the lull after a speech, the gallery was fluttering with  
the rustle of programmes consulted, and Mrs. Sheff (the Brant  
girl's aunt) leaned forward to say enthusiastically: "And now 
we're  
to hear Mr. Ransom!" </p><p> 
     A louder buzz rose from the table, and the heads (without  
relaxing their upward vigilance) seemed to merge, and flow  
together, like an attentive flood, toward the upper end of the  
horse-shoe, where all the threads of Margaret Ransom's  
consciousness were suddenly drawn into what seemed a small speck, 
 no more&mdash;a black speck that rose, hung in air, dissolved into  
gyrating gestures, became distended, enormous, 
preponderant&mdash;became  
her husband "speaking." </p><p> 
     "It's the heat&mdash;" Margaret gasped, pressing her handkerchief 
 
to her whitening lips, and finding just strength enough left to  
push back farther into the shadow. </p><p> 
     She felt a touch on her arm.  "It <hi rend="italic"> is</hi> horrible&mdash;shall 
we  
go?" a voice suggested; and, "Yes, yes, let us go," she 
whispered,  
feeling, with a great throb of relief, <hi rend="italic"> that</hi> to be the 
only  
possible, the only conceivable, solution.  To sit and listen to 
her  
husband <hi rend="italic"> now</hi>&mdash;how could she ever have thought she could 
survive  
it?  Luckily, under the lingering hubbub from below, his opening  
words were inaudible, and she had only to run the gauntlet of  
sympathetic feminine glances, shot after her between waving fans  
and programmes, as, guided by Guy Dawnish, she managed to reach 
the  
door.  It was really so hot that even Mrs. Sheff was not much  
surprised&mdash;till long afterward. . . .  
 </p><p> 
     The winding staircase was empty, half dark and blessedly  
silent.  In a committee room below Dawnish found the inevitable  
water jug, and filled a glass for her, while she leaned back,  
confronted only by a frowning college President in an emblazoned  
frame.  The academic frown descended on her like an anathema when 
 
she rose and followed her companion out of the building. </p><p> 
     Hamblin Hall stands at the end of the long green "Campus" 
with  
its sextuple line of elms&mdash;the boast and the singularity of  
Wentworth.  A pale spring moon, rising above the dome of the  
University library at the opposite end of the elm-walk, diffused 
a  
pearly mildness in the sky, melted to thin haze the shadows of 
the  
trees, and turned to golden yellow the lights of the college  
windows.  Against this soft suffusion of light the Library cupola 
 
assumed a Bramantesque grace, the white steeple of the  
congregational church became a campanile topped by a winged 
spirit,  
and the scant porticoes of the older halls the colonnades of  
classic temples. </p><p> 
     "This is better&mdash;" Dawnish said, as they passed down the 
steps  
and under the shadow of the elms. </p><p> 
     They moved on a little way in silence before he began again: 
 
"You're too tired to walk.  Let us sit down a few minutes." 
</p><p> 
     Her feet, in truth, were leaden, and not far off a group of  
park benches, encircling the pedestal of a patriot in bronze,  
invited them to rest.  But Dawnish was guiding her toward a 
lateral  
path which bent, through shrubberies, toward a strip of turf  
between two of the buildings. </p><p> 
     "It will be cooler by the river," he said, moving on without 
 
waiting for a possible protest.  None came: it seemed easier, for 
 
the moment, to let herself be led without any conventional feint 
of  
resistance.  And besides, there was nothing wrong about <hi rend="italic"> 
this</hi>&mdash;  
the wrong would have been in sitting up there in the glare,  
pretending to listen to her husband, a dutiful wife among her 
kind.  
. . . <pb n="179"/>  </p><p> 
     The path descended, as both knew, to the chosen, the  
inimitable spot of Wentworth: that fugitive curve of the river,  
where, before hurrying on to glut the brutal industries of South  
Wentworth and Smedden, it simulated for a few hundred yards the  
leisurely pace of an ancient university stream, with willows on 
its  
banks and a stretch of turf extending from the grounds of Hamblin 
 
Hall to the boat houses at the farther bend.  Here too were  
benches, beneath the willows, and so close to the river that the  
voice of its gliding softened and filled out the reverberating  
silence between Margaret and her companion, and made her feel 
that  
she knew why he had brought her there. </p><p> 
     "Do you feel better?" he asked gently as he sat down beside  
her. </p><p> 
     "Oh, yes.  I only needed a little air." </p><p> 
     "I'm so glad you did.  Of course the speeches were  
tremendously interesting&mdash;but I prefer this.  What a good night!" 
</p><p> 
     "Yes." </p><p> 
     There was a pause, which now, after all, the soothing  
accompaniment of the river seemed hardly sufficient to fill. 
</p><p> 
     "I wonder what time it is.  I ought to be going home,"  
Margaret began at length. </p><p> 
     "Oh, it's not late.  They'll be at it for hours in there&mdash;  
yet." </p><p> 
     She made a faint inarticulate sound.  She wanted to say: 
"No&mdash;  
Robert's speech was to be the last&mdash;" but she could not bring  
herself to pronounce Ransom's name, and at the moment no other 
way  
of refuting her companion's statement occurred to her. </p><p> 
     The young man leaned back luxuriously, reassured by her  
silence. </p><p> 
     "You see it's my last chance&mdash;and I want to make the most of 
 
it." </p><p> 
     "Your last chance?"  How stupid of her to repeat his words 
on  
that cooing note of interrogation!  It was just such a lead as 
the  
Brant girl might have given him. </p><p> 
     "To be with you&mdash;like this.  I haven't had so many.  And  
there's less than a week left." </p><p> 
     She attempted to laugh.  "Perhaps it will sound longer if 
you  
call it five days." </p><p> 
     The flatness of that, again!  And she knew there were people 
 
who called her intelligent.  Fortunately he did not seem to 
notice  
it; but her laugh continued to sound in her own ears&mdash;the  
coquettish chirp of middle age!  She decided that if he spoke  
again&mdash;if he <hi rend="italic"> said anything</hi>&mdash;she would make no farther 
effort at  
evasion: she would take it directly, seriously, frankly&mdash;she 
would  
not be doubly disloyal. </p><p> 
     "Besides," he continued, throwing his arm along the back of  
the bench, and turning toward her so that his face was like a 
dusky  
bas-relief with a silver rim&mdash;"besides, there's something I've 
been  
wanting to tell you." </p><p> 
     The sound of the river seemed to cease altogether: the whole 
 
world became silent. </p><p> 
     Margaret had trusted her inspiration farther than it 
appeared  
likely to carry her.  Again she could think of nothing happier 
than  
to repeat, on the same witless note of interrogation: "To tell 
me?" </p><p> 
     "You only." </p><p> 
     The constraint, the difficulty, seemed to be on his side 
now:  
she divined it by the renewed shifting of his attitude&mdash;he was  
capable, usually, of such fine intervals of immobility&mdash;and by a  
confusion in his utterance that set her own voice throbbing in 
her  
throat. </p><p> 
     "You've been so perfect to me," he began again.  "It's not 
my  
fault if you've made me feel that you would understand 
everything&mdash;  
make allowances for everything&mdash;see just how a man may have held  
out, and fought against a thing&mdash;as long as he had the strength. 
.  
. .  This may be my only chance; and I can't go away without  
telling you." </p><p> 
     He had turned from her now, and was staring at the river, so 
 
that his profile was projected against the moonlight in all its  
beautiful young dejection. </p><p> 
     There was a slight pause, as though he waited for her to  
speak; then she leaned forward and laid her hand on his. </p><p> 
     "If I have really been&mdash;if I have done for you even the 
least  
part of what you say . . . what you imagine . . . will you do for 
 
me, now, just one thing in return?" </p><p> 
     He sat motionless, as if fearing to frighten away the shy  
touch on his hand, and she left it there, conscious of her 
gesture  
only as part of the high ritual of their farewell. </p><p> 
     "What do you want me to do?" he asked in a low tone. </p><p> 
     <hi rend="italic">" Not</hi> to tell me!" she breathed on a deep note of 
entreaty. </p><p> 
     <hi rend="italic">" Not</hi> to tell you&mdash;?" <pb n="180"/>  </p><p> 
     "Anything&mdash;<hi rend="italic"> anything</hi>&mdash;just to leave our . . . our  
friendship . . . as it has been&mdash;as&mdash;as a painter, if a friend  
asked him, might leave a picture&mdash;not quite finished, perhaps . . 
 
. but all the more exquisite. . . ." </p><p> 
     She felt the hand under hers slip away, recover itself, and  
seek her own, which had flashed out of reach in the same 
instant&mdash;  
felt the start that swept him round on her as if he had been 
caught  
and turned about by the shoulders. </p><p> 
     "You&mdash;<hi rend="italic"> you</hi>&mdash;?" he stammered, in a strange voice full 
of  
fear and tenderness; but she held fast, so centred in her  
inexorable resolve that she was hardly conscious of the effect 
her  
words might be producing. </p><p> 
     "Don't you see," she hurried on, "don't you <hi rend="italic"> feel</hi> how 
much  
safer it is&mdash;yes, I'm willing to put it so!&mdash;how much safer to  
leave everything undisturbed . . . just as . . . as it has grown 
of  
itself . . . without trying to say: 'It's this or that' . . . ?   
It's what we each choose to call it to ourselves, after all, 
isn't  
it?  Don't let us try to find a name that . . . that we should 
both  
agree upon . . . we probably shouldn't succeed."  She laughed  
abruptly.  "And ghosts vanish when one names them!" she ended 
with  
a break in her voice. </p><p> 
     When she ceased her heart was beating so violently that 
there  
was a rush in her ears like the noise of the river after rain, 
and  
she did not immediately make out what he was answering.  But as 
she  
recovered her lucidity she said to herself that, whatever he was  
saying, she must not hear it; and she began to speak again, half  
playfully, half appealingly, with an eloquence of entreaty, an  
ingenuity in argument, of which she had never dreamed herself  
capable.  And then, suddenly, strangling hands seemed to reach up 
 
from her heart to her throat, and she had to stop. </p><p> 
     Her companion remained motionless.  He had not tried to 
regain  
her hand, and his eyes were away from her, on the river.  But his 
 
nearness had become something formidable and exquisite&mdash;something 
 
she had never before imagined.  A flush of guilt swept over her&mdash; 
 
vague reminiscences of French novels and of opera plots.  This 
was  
what such women felt, then . . . this was "shame." . . .  Phrases 
 
of the newspaper and the pulpit danced before her. . . .  She 
dared  
not speak, and his silence began to frighten her.  Had ever a 
heart  
beat so wildly before in Wentworth? </p><p> 
     He turned at last, and taking her two hands, quite simply,  
kissed them one after the other. </p><p> 
     "I shall never forget&mdash;" he said in a confused voice, unlike 
 
his own. </p><p> 
     A return of strength enabled her to rise, and even to let 
her  
eyes meet his for a moment. </p><p> 
     "Thank you," she said, simply also. </p><p> 
     She turned away from the bench, regaining the path that led  
back to the college buildings, and he walked beside her in 
silence.   
When they reached the elm walk it was dotted with dispersing  
groups.  The "speaking" was over, and Hamblin Hall had poured its 
 
audience out into the moonlight.  Margaret felt a rush of relief, 
 
followed by a receding wave of regret.  She had the distinct  
sensation that her hour&mdash;her one hour&mdash;was over. </p><p> 
     One of the groups just ahead broke up as they approached, 
and  
projected Ransom's solid bulk against the moonlight. </p><p> 
     "My husband," she said, hastening forward; and she never  
afterward forgot the look of his back&mdash;heavy, round-shouldered, 
yet  
a little pompous&mdash;in a badly fitting overcoat that stood out at 
the  
neck and hid his collar.  She had never before noticed how he  
dressed.  
  
 </p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="4" id="d6"><head> 
                                IV </head> 
<p> 
     THEY met again, inevitably, before Dawnish left; but the 
thing  
she feared did not happen&mdash;he did not try to see her alone. 
</p><p> 
     It even became clear to her, in looking back, that he had  
deliberately avoided doing so; and this seemed merely an added  
proof of his "understanding," of that deep undefinable communion  
that set them alone in an empty world, as if on a peak above the  
clouds. </p><p> 
     The five days passed in a flash; and when the last one came, 
 
it brought to Margaret Ransom an hour of weakness, of profound  
disorganization, when old barriers fell, old convictions faded&mdash;  
when to be alone with him for a moment became, after all, the one 
 
craving of her heart.  She knew he was coming that afternoon to 
say  
"good-by"&mdash;and she knew also that Ransom was to be away at South  
Wentworth.  She waited alone in her pale little drawing-<pb n="181"/> room, with its scant kakemonos, its one or two 
chilly  
reproductions from the antique, its slippery Chippendale chairs.  
 
At length the bell rang, and her world became a rosy 
blur&mdash;through  
which she presently discerned the austere form of Mrs. Sperry, 
wife  
of the Professor of palaeontology, who had come to talk over with 
 
her the next winter's programme for the Higher Thought Club.  
They  
debated the question for an hour, and when Mrs. Sperry departed  
Margaret had a confused impression that the course was to deal 
with  
the influence of the First Crusade on the development of European 
 
architecture&mdash;but the sentient part of her knew only that Dawnish 
 
had not come. </p><p> 
     He "bobbed in," as he would have put it, after 
dinner&mdash;having,  
it appeared, run across Ransom early in the day, and learned that 
 
the latter would be absent till evening.  Margaret was in the 
study  
with her husband when the door opened and Dawnish stood there.   
Ransom&mdash;who had not had time to dress&mdash;was seated at his desk, a  
pile of shabby law books at his elbow, the light from a hanging  
lamp falling on his grayish stubble of hair, his sallow forehead  
and spectacled eyes.  Dawnish, towering higher than usual against 
 
the shadows of the room, and refined by his unusual pallor, hung 
a  
moment on the threshold, then came in, explaining himself  
profusely&mdash;laughing, accepting a cigar, letting Ransom push an 
arm-chair forward&mdash;a Dawnish she had never seen, ill at ease,  
ejaculatory, yet somehow more mature, more obscurely in command 
of  
himself. </p><p> 
     Margaret drew back, seating herself in the shade, in such a  
way that she saw her husband's head first, and beyond it their  
visitor's, relieved against the dusk of the book shelves.  Her  
heart was still&mdash;she felt no throbbing in her throat or temples:  
all her life seemed concentrated in the hand that lay on her 
knee,  
the hand he would touch when they said good-by.  
 </p><p> 
     Afterward her heart rang all the changes, and there was a 
mood  
in which she reproached herself for cowardice&mdash;for having  
deliberately missed her one moment with him, the moment in which  
she might have sounded the depths of life, for joy or anguish.  
But  
that mood was fleeting and infrequent.  In quieter hours she  
blushed for it&mdash;she even trembled to think that he might have  
guessed such a regret in her.  It seemed to convict her of a lack 
 
of fineness that he should have had, in his youth and his power, 
a  
tenderer, surer sense of the peril of a rash touch&mdash;should have  
handled the case so much more delicately. </p><p> 
     At first her days were fire and the nights long solemn 
vigils.   
Her thoughts were no longer vulgarized and defaced by any notion 
of  
"guilt," of mental disloyalty.  She was ashamed now of her shame.  
 
What had happened was as much outside the sphere of her marriage 
as  
some transaction in a star.  It had simply given her a secret 
life  
of incommunicable joys, as if all the wasted springs of her youth 
 
had been stored in some hidden pool, and she could return there 
now  
to bathe in them. </p><p> 
     After that there came a phase of loneliness, through which 
the  
life about her loomed phantasmal and remote.  She thought the 
dead  
must feel thus, repeating the vain gestures of the living beside  
some Stygian shore.  She wondered if any other woman had lived to 
 
whom <hi rend="italic"> nothing had ever happened?</hi>  And then his first 
letter  
came. . . . </p><p> 
     It was a charming letter&mdash;a perfect letter.  The little 
touch  
of awkwardness and constraint under its boyish spontaneity told 
her  
more than whole pages of eloquence.  He spoke of their 
friendship&mdash;  
of their good days together. . . .  Ransom, chancing to come in  
while she read, noticed the foreign stamps; and she was able to  
hand him the letter, saying gaily: "There's a message for you," 
and  
knowing all the while that <hi rend="italic"> her</hi> message was safe in her 
heart. </p><p> 
     On the days when the letters came the outlines of things 
grew  
indistinct, and she could never afterward remember what she had  
done or how the business of life had been carried on.  It was  
always a surprise when she found dinner on the table as usual, 
and  
Ransom seated opposite to her, running over the evening paper. 
</p><p> 
     But though Dawnish continued to write, with all the English  
loyalty to the outward observances of friendship, his  
communications came only at intervals of several weeks, and 
between  
them she had time to repossess herself, to regain some sort of  
normal contact with life.  And the customary, the recurring,  
gradually reclaimed her, the net of habit tightened again&mdash;her   
<pb n="182"/>  daily life became real, and her one momentary 
escape from it  
an exquisite illusion.  Not that she ceased to believe in the  
miracle that had befallen her: she still treasured the reality of 
 
her one moment beside the river.  What reason was there for  
doubting it?  She could hear the ring of truth in young Dawnish's 
 
voice: "It's not my fault if you've made me feel that you would  
understand everything. . . ."  No! she believed in her miracle, 
and  
the belief sweetened and illumined her life; but she came to see  
that what was for her the transformation of her whole being might 
 
well have been, for her companion, a mere passing explosion of  
gratitude, of boyish good-fellowship touched with the pang of  
leave-taking.  She even reached the point of telling herself that 
 
it was "better so": this view of the episode so defended it from  
the alternating extremes of self-reproach and derision, so  
enshrined it in a pale immortality to which she could make her  
secret pilgrimages without reproach. </p><p> 
     For a long time she had not been able to pass by the bench  
under the willows&mdash;she even avoided the elm walk till autumn had  
stripped its branches.  But every day, now, she noted a step 
toward  
recovery; and at last a day came when, walking along the river, 
she  
said to herself, as she approached the bench: "I used not to be  
able to pass here without thinking of him; <hi rend="italic"> and now I am not  
thinking of him at all!"</hi> </p><p> 
     This seemed such convincing proof of her recovery that she  
began, as spring returned, to permit herself, now and then, a 
quiet  
session on the bench&mdash;a dedicated hour from which she went back  
fortified to her task. </p><p> 
     She had not heard from her friend for six weeks or more&mdash;the 
 
intervals between his letters were growing longer.  But that was  
"best" too, and she was not anxious, for she knew he had obtained 
 
the post he had been preparing for, and that his active life in  
London had begun.  The thought reminded her, one mild March day,  
that in leaving the house she had thrust in her reticule a letter 
 
from a Wentworth friend who was abroad on a holiday.  The 
envelope  
bore the London post mark, a fact showing that the lady's face 
was  
turned toward home.  Margaret seated herself on her bench, and  
drawing out the letter began to read it. </p><p> 
     The London described was that of shops and museums&mdash;as 
remote  
as possible from the setting of Guy Dawnish's existence.  But  
suddenly Margaret's eye fell on his name, and the page began to  
tremble in her hands. </p><p> 
     "I heard such a funny thing yesterday about your friend Mr.  
Dawnish.  We went to a tea at Professor Bunce's (I do wish you 
knew  
the Bunces&mdash;their atmosphere is so <hi rend="italic"> uplifting</hi>), and there 
I met  
that Miss Bruce-Pringle who came out last year to take a course 
in  
histology at the Annex.  Of course she asked about you and Mr.  
Ransom, and then she told me she had just seen Mr. Dawnish's 
aunt&mdash;  
the clever one he was always talking about, Lady Caroline  
something&mdash;and that they were all in a dreadful state about him.  
 
I wonder if you knew he was engaged when he went to America?  He  
never mentioned it to <hi rend="italic"> us</hi>.  She said it was not a positive 
 
engagement, but an understanding with a girl he has always been  
devoted to, who lives near their place in Wiltshire; and both  
families expected the marriage to take place as soon as he got  
back.  It seems the girl is an heiress (you know <hi rend="italic"> how low</hi> 
the  
English ideals are compared with ours), and Miss Bruce-Pringle 
said  
his relations were perfectly delighted at his 'being provided 
for,'  
as she called it.  Well, when he got back he asked the girl to  
release him; and she and her family were furious, and so were his 
 
people; but he holds out, and won't marry her, and won't give a  
reason, except that he has 'formed an unfortunate attachment.'  
Did  
you ever hear anything so peculiar?  His aunt, who is quite wild  
about it, says it must have happened at Wentworth, because he  
didn't go anywhere else in America.  Do you suppose it <hi rend="italic"> 
could</hi>  
have been the Brant girl?  But why 'unfortunate' when everybody  
knows she would have jumped at him?" </p><p> 
     Margaret folded the letter and looked out across the river.  
 
It was not the same river, but a mystic current shot with  
moonlight.  The bare willows wove a leafy veil above her head, 
and  
beside her she felt the nearness of youth and tempestuous  
tenderness.  It had all happened just here, on this very seat by  
the river&mdash;it had come to her, and passed her by, and she had not 
 
held out a hand to detain it. . . . </p><p> 
     Well!  Was it not, by that very abstention, made more deeply 
 
and ineffaceably hers?  She could argue thus while she had 
  
<pb n="183"/>   
thought the episode, on his side, a mere transient effect of  
propinquity; but now that she knew it had altered the whole 
course  
of his life, now that it took on substance and reality, asserted 
a  
separate existence outside of her own troubled consciousness&mdash;now 
 
it seemed almost cowardly to have missed her share in it. </p><p> 
     She walked home in a dream.  Now and then, when she passed 
an  
acquaintance, she wondered if the pain and glory were written on  
her face.  But Mrs. Sperry, who stopped her at the corner of  
Maverick Street to say a word about the next meeting of the 
Higher  
Thought Club, seemed to remark no change in her. </p><p> 
     When she reached home Ransom had not yet returned from the  
office, and she went straight to the library to tidy his writing- 
table.  It was part of her daily duty to bring order out of the  
chaos of his papers, and of late she had fastened on such small  
recurring tasks as some one falling over a precipice might snatch 
 
at the weak bushes in its clefts. </p><p> 
     When she had sorted the letters she took up some pamphlets 
and  
newspapers, glancing over them to see if they were to be kept.   
Among the papers was a page torn from a London <hi rend="italic"> Times</hi> of 
the  
previous month.  Her eye ran down its columns and suddenly a  
paragraph flamed out. </p><p> 
     "We are requested to state that the marriage arranged 
between  
Mr. Guy Dawnish, son of the late Colonel the Hon. Roderick 
Dawnish,  
of Malby, Wilts, and Gwendolen, daughter of Samuel Matcher, Esq. 
of  
Armingham Towers, Wilts, will not take place." </p><p> 
     Margaret dropped the paper and sat down, hiding her face  
against the stained baize of the desk.  She remembered the  
photograph of the tennis-court at Guise&mdash;she remembered the  
handsome girl at whom Guy Dawnish looked up, laughing.  A gust of 
 
tears shook her, loosening the dry surface of conventional 
feeling,  
welling up from unsuspected depths.  She was sorry&mdash;very sorry, 
yet  
so glad&mdash;so ineffably, impenitently glad.  
 
</p> 
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="5" id="d7"><head> 
                                 V </head> 
<p> 
     THERE came a reaction in which she decided to write to him.  
 
She even sketched out a letter of sisterly, almost motherly,  
remonstrance, in which she reminded him that he "still had all 
his  
life before him."  But she reflected that so, after all, had she; 
 
and that seemed to weaken the argument. </p><p> 
     In the end she decided not to send the letter.  He had never 
 
spoken to her of his engagement to Gwendolen Matcher, and his  
letters had contained no allusion to any sentimental disturbance 
in  
his life.  She had only his few broken words, that night by the  
river, on which to build her theory of the case.  But illuminated 
 
by the phrase "an unfortunate attachment" the theory towered up,  
distinct and immovable, like some high landmark by which 
travellers  
shape their course.  She had been loved&mdash;extraordinarily loved.   
But he had chosen that she should know of it by his silence 
rather  
than by his speech.  He had understood that only on those terms  
could their transcendant communion continue&mdash;that he must lose 
her  
to keep her.  To break that silence would be like spilling a cup 
of  
water in a waste of sand.  There would be nothing left for her  
thirst. </p><p> 
     Her life, thenceforward, was bathed in a tranquil beauty.  
The  
days flowed by like a river beneath the moon&mdash;each ripple caught  
the brightness and passed it on.  She began to take a renewed  
interest in her familiar round of duties.  The tasks which had 
once  
seemed colourless and irksome had now a kind of sacrificial  
sweetness, a symbolic meaning into which she alone was initiated.  
 
She had been restless&mdash;had longed to travel; now she felt that 
she  
should never again care to leave Wentworth.  But if her desire to 
 
wander had ceased, she travelled in spirit, performing invisible  
pilgrimages in the footsteps of her friend.  She regretted that 
her  
one short visit to England had taken her so little out of 
London&mdash;  
that her acquaintance with the landscape had been formed chiefly  
through the windows of a railway carriage.  She threw herself 
into  
the architectural studies of the Higher Thought Club, and  
distinguished herself, at the spring meetings, by her fluency, 
her  
competence, her inexhaustible curiosity on the subject of the  
growth of English Gothic.  She ransacked the shelves of the 
college  
library, she borrowed photographs of the cathedrals, she pored 
over  
the folio pages of "The Seats of Noblemen and Gentlemen."  She 
was  
like some banished princess who learns that she 

<pb n="184"/> 
has inherited a domain in her own country, who knows that she will  
never see it, yet feels, wherever she walks, its soil beneath her 
 
feet. </p><p> 
     May was half over, and the Higher Thought Club was to hold 
its  
last meeting, previous to the college festivities which, in early 
 
June, agreeably disorganized the social routine of Wentworth.  
The  
meeting was to take place in Margaret Ransom's drawing-room, and 
on  
the day before she sat upstairs preparing for her dual duties as  
hostess and orator&mdash;for she had been invited to read the final  
paper of the course.  In order to sum up with precision her  
conclusions on the subject of English Gothic she had been 
rereading  
an analysis of the structural features of the principal English  
cathedrals; and she was murmuring over to herself the phrase: 
"The  
longitudinal arches of Lincoln have an approximately elliptical  
form," when there came a knock on the door, and Maria's voice  
announced: "There's a lady down in the parlour." </p><p> 
     Margaret's soul dropped from the heights of the shadowy  
vaulting to the dead level of an afternoon call at Wentworth. 
</p><p> 
     "A lady?  Did she give no name?" </p><p> 
     Maria became confused.  "She only said she was a lady&mdash;" and 
 
in reply to her mistress's look of mild surprise: "Well, ma'am, 
she  
told me so three or four times over." </p><p> 
     Margaret laid her book down, leaving it open at the  
description of Lincoln, and slowly descended the stairs.  As she  
did so, she repeated to herself: "The longitudinal arches are  
elliptical." </p><p> 
     On the threshold below, she had the odd impression that her  
bare and inanimate drawing-room was brimming with life and 
noise&mdash;  
an impression produced, as she presently perceived, by the 
resolute  
forward dash&mdash;it was almost a pounce&mdash;of the one small figure  
restlessly measuring its length. </p><p> 
     The dash checked itself within a yard of Margaret, and the  
lady&mdash;a stranger&mdash;held back long enough to stamp on her hostess a 
 
sharp impression of sallowness, leanness, keenness, before she  
said, in a voice that might have been addressing an unruly  
committee meeting: "I am Lady Caroline Duckett&mdash;a fact I found it 
 
impossible to make clear to the young woman who let me in." 
</p><p> 
     A warm wave rushed up from Margaret's heart to her throat 
and  
forehead.  She held out both hands impulsively.  "Oh, I'm so 
glad&mdash;  
I'd no idea&mdash;" </p><p> 
     Her voice sank under her visitor's impartial scrutiny. 
</p><p> 
     "I don't wonder," said the latter drily.  "I suppose she  
didn't mention, either, that my object in calling here was to see 
 
Mrs. Ransom?" </p><p> 
     "Oh, yes&mdash;won't you sit down?"  Margaret pushed a chair  
forward.  She seated herself at a little distance, brain and 
heart  
humming with a confused interchange of signals.  This dark sharp  
woman was his aunt&mdash;the "clever aunt" who had had such a hard 
life,  
but had always managed to keep her head above water.  Margaret  
remembered that Guy had spoken of her kindness&mdash;perhaps she would 
 
seem kinder when they had talked together a little.  Meanwhile 
the  
first impression she produced was of an amplitude out of all  
proportion to her somewhat scant exterior.  With her small flat  
figure, her shabby heterogeneous dress, she was as dowdy as any  
Professor's wife at Wentworth; but her dowdiness (Margaret 
borrowed  
a literary analogy to define it), her dowdiness was somehow "of 
the  
centre."  Like the insignificant emissary of a great power, she 
was  
to be judged rather by her passports than her person. </p><p> 
     While Margaret was receiving these impressions, Lady 
Caroline,  
with quick bird-like twists of her head, was gathering others 
from  
the pale void spaces of the drawing-room.  Her eyes, divided by a 
 
sharp nose like a bill, seemed to be set far enough apart to see 
at  
separate angles; but suddenly she bent both of them on Margaret. 
</p><p> 
     "This <hi rend="italic"> is</hi> Mrs. Ransom's house?" she asked, with an 
emphasis  
on the verb that gave a distinct hint of unfulfilled 
expectations. </p><p> 
     Margaret assented. </p><p> 
     "Because your American houses, especially in the provincial  
towns, all look so remarkably alike, that I thought I might have  
been mistaken; and as my time is extremely limited&mdash;in fact I'm  
sailing on Wednesday&mdash;" </p><p> 
     She paused long enough to let Margaret say: "I had no idea 
you  
were in this country." </p><p> 
     Lady Caroline made no attempt to take this up.  "And so much 
 
of it," she carried 
<pb n="185"/>  on her sentence, "has 
been wasted in  
talking to people I really hadn't the slightest desire to see, 
that  
you must excuse me if I go straight to the point." </p><p> 
     Margaret felt a sudden tension of the heart.  "Of course," 
she  
said while a voice within her cried: "He is dead&mdash;he has left me 
a  
message." </p><p> 
     There was another pause; then Lady Caroline went on, with  
increasing asperity: "So that&mdash;in short&mdash;if I <hi rend="italic"> could</hi> see 
Mrs.  
Ransom at once&mdash;" </p><p> 
     Margaret looked up in surprise.  "I am Mrs. Ransom," she 
said. </p><p> 
     The other stared a moment, with much the same look of 
cautious  
incredulity that had marked her inspection of the drawing-room.   
Then light came to her. </p><p> 
     "Oh, I beg your pardon.  I should have said that I wished to 
 
see Mrs. <hi rend="italic"> Robert</hi> Ransom, not Mrs. Ransom.  But I 
understood that  
in the States you don't make those distinctions."  She paused a  
moment, and then went on, before Margaret could answer: "Perhaps, 
 
after all, it's as well that I should see you instead, since 
you're  
evidently one of the household&mdash;your son and his wife live with  
you, I suppose?  Yes, on the whole, then, it's better&mdash;I shall be 
 
able to talk so much more frankly."  She spoke as if, as a rule,  
circumstances prevented her giving rein to this propensity.  "And 
 
frankness, of course, is the only way out of this&mdash;this extremely 
 
tiresome complication.  You know, I suppose, that my nephew 
thinks  
he's in love with your daughter-in-law?" </p><p> 
     Margaret made a slight movement, but her visitor pressed on  
without heeding it.  "Oh, don't fancy, please, that I'm 
pretending  
to take a high moral ground&mdash;though his mother does, poor dear!  
I  
can perfectly imagine that in a place like this&mdash;I've just been  
driving about it for two hours&mdash;a young man of Guy's age would   
<hi rend="italic"> have</hi> to provide himself with some sort of distraction, 
and he's  
not the kind to go in for anything objectionable.  Oh, we quite  
allow for that&mdash;we should allow for the whole affair, if it 
hadn't  
so preposterously ended in his throwing over the girl he was  
engaged to, and upsetting an arrangement that affected a number 
of  
people besides himself.  I understand that in the States it's  
different&mdash;the young people have only themselves to consider.  In 
 
England&mdash;in our class, I mean&mdash;a great deal may depend on a young 
 
man's making a good match; and in Guy's case I may say that his  
mother and sisters (I won't include myself, though I might) have  
been simply stranded&mdash;thrown overboard&mdash;by his freak.  You can  
understand how serious it is when I tell you that it's that and  
nothing else that has brought me all the way to America.  And my  
first idea was to go straight to your daughter-in-law, since her  
influence is the only thing we can count on now, and put it to 
her  
fairly, as I'm putting it to you.  But, on the whole, I dare say  
it's better to see you first&mdash;you might give me an idea of the 
line  
to take with her.  I'm prepared to throw myself on her mercy!" 
</p><p> 
     Margaret rose from her chair, outwardly rigid in proportion 
to  
her inward tremor. </p><p> 
     "You don't understand&mdash;" she began. </p><p> 
     Lady Caroline brushed the interruption aside.  "Oh, but I 
do&mdash;  
completely!  I cast no reflection on your daughter-in-law.  Guy 
has  
made it quite clear to us that his attachment is&mdash;has, in short,  
not been rewarded.  But don't you see that that's the worst part 
of  
it?  There'd be much more hope of his recovering if Mrs. Robert  
Ransom had&mdash;had&mdash;" </p><p> 
     Margaret's voice broke from her in a cry.  "I am Mrs. Robert 
 
Ransom," she said. </p><p> 
     If Lady Caroline Duckett had hitherto given her hostess the  
impression of a person not easily silenced, this fact added  
sensibly to the effect produced by the intense stillness which 
now  
fell on her. </p><p> 
     She sat quite motionless, her large bangled hands clasped  
about the meagre fur boa she had unwound from her neck on 
entering,  
her rusty black veil pushed up to the edge of a "fringe" of  
doubtful authenticity, her thin lips parted on a gasp that seemed 
 
to sharpen itself on the edges of her teeth.  So overwhelming and 
 
helpless was her silence that Margaret began to feel a motion of  
pity beneath her indignation&mdash;a desire at least to facilitate the 
 
excuses which must terminate their disastrous colloquy.  But when 
 
Lady Caroline found voice she did not use it to excuse herself. 
</p><p> 
     "You <hi rend="italic"> can't</hi> be," she said, quite simply. </p><p> 
     "Can't be?" Margaret stammered, with a flushing cheek. 
</p><p> 
     "I mean, it's some mistake.  Are there <hi rend="italic"> two</hi> Mrs. 
Robert  
Ransoms in the same town?  Your family arrangements are so  
extremely puzzling."  She had a farther <pb n="186"/>  rush 
of  
enlightenment.  "Oh, I <hi rend="italic"> see!</hi>  I ought of course to have 
asked  
for Mrs. Robert Ransom 'Junior'!" </p><p> 
     The idea sent her to her feet with a haste which showed her  
impatience to make up for lost time. </p><p> 
     "There is no other Mrs. Robert Ransom at Wentworth," said  
Margaret. </p><p> 
     "No other&mdash;no 'Junior'?  Are you <hi rend="italic"> sure?"</hi>  Lady 
Caroline  
fell back into her seat again.  "Then I simply don't see," she  
murmured helplessly. </p><p> 
     Margaret's blush had fixed itself on her throbbing forehead.  
 
She remained standing, while her strange visitor continued to 
gaze  
at her with a perturbation in which the consciousness of  
indiscretion had evidently as yet no part. </p><p> 
     "I simply don't see," she repeated. </p><p> 
     Suddenly she sprang up, and advancing to Margaret laid an  
inspired hand on her arm.  "But, my dear woman, you can help us 
out  
all the same; you can help us to find out <hi rend="italic"> who it is</hi>&mdash;and 
you  
will, won't you?  Because, as it's not you, you can't in the 
least  
mind what I've been saying&mdash;" </p><p> 
     Margaret, freeing her arm from her visitor's hold, drew back 
 
a step; but Lady Caroline instantly rejoined her. </p><p> 
     "Of course, I can see that if it <hi rend="italic"> had</hi> been, you might 
have  
been annoyed: I dare say I put the case stupidly&mdash;but I'm so  
bewildered by this new development&mdash;by his using you all this 
time  
as a pretext&mdash;that I really don't know where to turn for light on 
 
the mystery&mdash;" </p><p> 
     She had Margaret in her imperious grasp again, but the 
latter  
broke from her with a more resolute gesture. </p><p> 
     "I'm afraid I have no light to give you," she began; but 
once  
more Lady Caroline caught her up. </p><p> 
     "Oh, but do please understand me!  I condemn Guy most 
strongly  
for using your name&mdash;when we all know you'd been so amazingly 
kind  
to him!  I haven't a word to say in his defence&mdash;but of course 
the  
important thing now is: <hi rend="italic"> who is the woman, since you're 
not?"</hi> </p><p> 
     The question rang out loudly, as if all the pale puritan  
corners of the room flung it back with a shudder at the speaker.  
 
In the silence that ensued Margaret felt the blood ebbing back to 
 
her heart; then she said, in a distinct and level voice: "I know  
nothing of the history of Mr. Dawnish." </p><p> 
     Lady Caroline gave a stare and a gasp.  Her distracted hand  
groped for her boa and she began to wind it mechanically about 
her  
long neck. </p><p> 
     "It would really be an enormous help to us&mdash;and to poor  
Gwendolen Matcher," she persisted pleadingly.  "And you'd be 
doing  
Guy himself a good turn." </p><p> 
     Margaret remained silent and motionless while her visitor 
drew  
on one of the worn gloves she had pulled off to adjust her veil.  
 
Lady Caroline gave the veil a final twitch. </p><p> 
     "I've come a tremendously long way," she said, "and, since 
it  
isn't you, I can't think why you won't help me. . . ."  
 </p><p> 
     When the door had closed on her visitor Margaret Ransom went 
 
slowly up the stairs to her room.  As she dragged her feet from 
one  
step to another, she remembered how she had sprung up the same  
steep flight after that visit of Guy Dawnish's when she had 
looked  
in the glass and seen on her face the blush of youth. </p><p> 
     When she reached her room she bolted the door as she had 
done  
that day, and again looked at herself in the narrow mirror above  
her dressing-table.  It was just a year since then&mdash;the elms were 
 
budding again, the willows hanging their green veil above the 
bench  
by the river.  But there was no trace of youth left in her face&mdash; 
 
she saw it now as others had doubtless always seen it.  If it  
seemed as it did to Lady Caroline Duckett, what look must it have 
 
worn to the fresh gaze of young Guy Dawnish? </p><p> 
     A pretext&mdash;she had been a pretext.  He had used her name to  
screen some one else&mdash;or perhaps merely to escape from a 
situation  
of which he was weary.  She did not care to conjecture what his  
motive had been&mdash;everything connected with him had grown so 
remote  
and alien.  She felt no anger&mdash;only an unspeakable sadness, a  
sadness which she knew would never be appeased. </p><p> 
     She looked at herself long and steadily; she wished to clear 
 
her eyes of all illusions.  Then she turned away and took her 
usual  
seat beside her work-table.  From where she sat she could look 
down  
the empty elm-shaded street, up which, at this hour every day, 
she  
was sure to see her husband's figure advancing.  She would see it 
 
presently&mdash;she would see it for many years to come.  She had a  
sudden aching sense of the length  <pb n="187"/>  of the 
years that  
stretched before her.  Strange that one who was not young should  
still, in all likelihood, have so long to live! </p><p> 
     Nothing was changed in the setting of her life, perhaps  
nothing would ever change in it.  She would certainly live and 
die  
in Wentworth.  And meanwhile the days would go on as usual,  
bringing the usual obligations.  As the word flitted through her  
brain she remembered that she had still to put the finishing  
touches to the paper she was to read the next afternoon at the  
meeting of the Higher Thought Club.  The book she had been 
reading  
lay face downward beside her, where she had left it an hour ago.  
 
She took it up, and slowly and painfully, like a child 
laboriously  
spelling out the syllables, she went on with the rest of the  
sentence: </p><p> 
     &mdash;"and they spring from a level not much above that of the  
springing of the transverse and diagonal ribs, which are so  
arranged as to give a convex curve to the surface of the vaulting 
conoid."  
 
 
</p>  
  
</div1>  
</body>  
</text>  
</TEI.2>
 
