<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaR1Md"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="WhaR1Md"> 

<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mrs. Wharton's "Madame de Treymes"</title>
<title type="sort">mrs whartons madame de treymes</title>
<author>Wharton review: Moss, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">9</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WhaR1Md</idno> 
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476515</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mrs. Wharton's "Madame De Treymes"</title>
<title level="j">Bookman</title>
<title type="sort">mrs whartons madame de treymes</title>
<author>Mary Moss</author>
</titleStmt> 
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition.</p>
</editionStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Dodd, Mead and Company</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York, N. Y.</pubPlace> 
<date value="1907">1907</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Bookman</hi> 25 (May 1907): 303-04.</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>UVa ed. AP2.B78</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p> 
<p>Spell-check and verification made 
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1907">1907</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
<term>prose</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-03">March 1996</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Deirdre A. Johnson, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added header and basic TEI markup</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 

<body id="d2"> 


<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> <pb n="303"/> 
<head>MRS. WHARTON'S "MADAME DE TREYMES" <lb/>
[Madame de Treymes. By Edith Wharton. New York: Charles Scribner's Sons.]</head>
 
<p>Since such crude early attempts as Theodore Fay's preposterous 
<hi rend="italic">Norman Leslie</hi> deserve scant consideration, Mr. Henry James 
may safely claim to have discovered the international episode as a 
motive for American fiction. In spite of many competitors, he has 
hitherto kept an easy supremacy in this field, with such 
masterpieces as <hi rend="italic">Daisy Miller, The American, The Princess 
Casamassima, The Ambassadors, The Golden Bowl</hi>, not to mention 
a host of short stories. But among this brilliant company, Mrs. 
Wharton's <hi rend="italic">Madame de Treymes</hi> must instantly take undisputed 
place. In fact, the author fairly challenges comparison by 
choosing a theme almost identical with that of <hi rend="italic">The American</hi>&mdash; 
the clash between a spirited outsider and the intangible 
resistance of Old World traditions and standards. And to be frank, 
her latest story excels Mr. James's early one in the matter of 
probability. For my part I have never been quite satisfied that a 
man of Newman's imaginative force would not have broken through the 
network of obstacles, if only by not appreciating them, and have 
ended by carrying off the object of his homage. 
</p><p>Curiously enough, it is by an even greater subtlety than Mr. 
James's that Mrs. Wharton reaches a fine simplicity. Where he 
merely shows a picture of his American baffled by the Faubourg, 
Mrs. Wharton gives in addition the point at which the Faubourg 
miscalculates the rules governing our trans-Atlantic Code. 
</p><p>John Durham wishes to marry Madame de Malrive, whom he had 
known in New York as Fanny Frisbee. This lady lives in Paris with 
the family of a husband from whom the French law has granted her a 
separation. A divorce is fully within her rights. It is a 
question of persuading the de Malrive not to contest the case, so 
that the divorce may be awarded without trailing the scandal of a 
cause celebre over the life of Fanny's young son. The story 
narrows down into a game played between John Durham and a French 
sister-in-law, Christiane de Treymes. Having gone so far, a review 
must perforce stop, for fear of blemishing the reader's delight in 
following the series of infinitely delicate touches by which the 
contest for Fanny's freedom is unfolded. 
</p><p>At the very start, Mrs. Wharton succeeds in mastering the 
greatest technical difficulty in fiction, that of introducing her 
situation without confusion, and without a hint of clumsy 
retrospect. So few words are used&mdash;the whole is the fruit of such 
discreet elimination&mdash;that one short chapter puts you in full 
possession of every essential fact; yet nothing could be less 
marred by haste. Giving in simplest form the last product of her 
own elaborate mental processes, Mrs. Wharton keeps that air of 
leisure proper to fiction which deals with states of mind rather 
than with bodily adventure. 
</p><p>From whatever point you look the story shows no flaw. The 
author brings out her three types of women with the utmost 
clearness. Durham's sisters, with their "'handsome' haphazard 
clothes," fresh from New York and not altogether unlike the Fanny 
Frisbee of old New York days&mdash;Fanny herself&mdash;"the same, but so 
mysteriously changed . . . with the mystery, the sense of unprobed 
depths of initiation which drew him to her as her freshness had 
never drawn him"&mdash;and above all Madame de Treymes, whose 
unfathomable completeness puts even Fanny's finish of mind and 
person in a slightly secondary place. 
</p><p>It is with this last creation of elegance and depravity that 
Durham must contend for his right to marry. The duel between these 
two runs through a series of astonishingly brilliant scenes. Mrs. 
Wharton falls into no cheap errors. Durham makes war with force, 
intelligence, and common sense; he is neither intimidated by the 
powers arrayed against him, nor does he underrate them. He commits 
none of the absurdities by which novel heroes are wont to create 
and sustain difficult situations. The real subtlety lies&mdash;

<pb n="304" id="WhaR1Md304"/> 

where it belongs&mdash;in the situation itself, not in the ingenuity 
with which it is prolonged. Moreover, the fact that Mrs. Wharton 
lets the conclusion turn upon a fundamental moral issue gives a 
solidity to the whole story, placing it on a more durable ground 
than any sketch of contrasted nationalities, since it touches the 
permanent human questions of honour and duty. It is true that she 
touches these questions lightly, rather with brilliancy than with 
a heat, which would be alien to her own nature. She neither 
harrows you by describing Fanny in transports of despair, nor drags 
you through Madame de Treymes's equivocal pleasures. Her supreme 
skill lies in bringing you face to face with these women as they 
are after the past has moulded them. Gyp herself could not more 
firmly convince you of the French woman's tragic perfidy, yet the 
detail is barely indicated. You only have the result in pure 
essence. 
</p><p>By sacrificing a possible long novel (for which <hi rend="italic">Madame de 
Treymes</hi> contains ample material) through a miracle of 
condensation, in matter, in form, and by an unimpeachable 
distinction of style, Mrs. Wharton has written a short story which 
stands entirely above criticism.</p> 
<closer><signed><hi rend="italic">Mary Moss.</hi></signed> </closer> 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
