<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaRead"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
 
<TEI.2 id="WhaRead"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Vice of Reading</title>
<title type="sort">vice of reading</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">24</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WhaRead</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476523</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Vice of Reading</title>
<title type="sort">vice of reading</title>
<author>Edith Wharton</author>
</titleStmt> 
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>North American Review</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1903">1903</date>
</publicationStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic 
Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Verification made against printed text.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text 
Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1903">1903</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
<term>prose</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-05">May 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Kelly Moulton</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>TEI tagging</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 

<div1 type="article" id="d3"> <pb n="513"/>  
<head>Wharton, Edith.  "The Vice of Reading."<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic"> North American Review</hi> 177 (Oct. 1903): 513-21.<lb/> 
</head> 


 
      
 
<p>  THAT "diffusion of knowledge" commonly classed with 
steam-heat 
and universal suffrage in the category of modern improvements, 
has 
incidentally brought about the production of a new vice&mdash;the vice 
of reading.</p><p> 
     No vices are so hard to eradicate as those which are 
popularly 
regarded as virtues.  Among these the vice of reading is 
foremost.  
That reading trash is a vice is generally conceded; but reading 
<hi rend="italic"> 
per se</hi>&mdash;the habit of reading&mdash;new as it is, already ranks 
with 
such seasoned virtues as thrift, sobriety, early rising and 
regular 
exercise.  There is, indeed, something peculiarly aggressive in 
the 
virtuousness of the sense-of-duty reader.  By those who have kept 
to the humble paths of precept he is revered as following a 
counsel 
of perfection.  "I wish I had kept up my reading as you have," 
the 
unlettered novice declares to this adept in the supererogatory; 
and 
the reader, accustomed to the incense of uncritical applause, not 
unnaturally looks on his occupation as a noteworthy intellectual 
achievement.</p><p> 
     Reading deliberately undertaken&mdash;what may be called 
volitional 
reading&mdash;is no more reading than erudition is culture.  Real 
reading is reflex action; the born reader reads as unconsciously 
as 
he breathes; and, to carry the analogy a degree farther, reading 
is 
no more a virtue than breathing.  Just in proportion as it is 
considered meritorious does it become unprofitable.  What is 
reading, in the last analysis, but an interchange of thought 
between writer and reader?  If the book enters the reader's mind 
just as it left the writer's&mdash;without any of the additions and 
modifications inevitably produced by contact with a new body of 
thought&mdash;it has been read to no purpose.  In such cases, of 
course, 
the reader is not always to blame.  There are books that 
<pb n="514"/>  
are always the same&mdash;incapable of modifying or of being 
modified&mdash; 
but these do not count as factors in literature.  The value of 
books is proportionate to what may be called their plasticity&mdash; 
their quality of being all things to all men, of being diversely 
moulded by the impact of fresh forms of thought.  Where, from one 
cause or the other, this reciprocal adaptability is lacking, 
there 
can be no real intercourse between book and reader.  In this 
sense 
it may be said that there is no abstract standard of values in 
literature: the greatest books ever written are worth to each 
reader only what he can get out of them.  The best books are 
those 
from which the best readers have been able to extract the 
greatest 
amount of thought of the highest quality; but it is generally 
from 
these books that the poor reader gets least.</p><p> 
     To be a poor reader may therefore be considered a 
misfortune; 
but it is certainly not a fault.  Why should we all be readers?  
We 
are not all expected to be musicians; but read we must; and so 
those that cannot read creatively read mechanically&mdash;as though a 
man who had no aptitude for the violin were to regard the 
grinding 
of a barrel-organ as an equivalent accomplishment!  It must be 
understood at the outset that, in the matter of reading, the real 
offenders are not those who restrict themselves to recognized 
trash.  There is little harm in the self-confessed devourer of 
foolish fiction.  He who feasts upon "the novel of the day" does 
not seriously impede the development of literature.  The cast of 
mind which discerns in the natural divisions of the melon an 
indication that it is meant to be eaten <hi rend="italic">en famille</hi>, might 
even 
look upon certain works&mdash;the penny-in-the-slot or 
touch-the-button 
books, which require no effort beyond turning the pages and using 
one's eyes&mdash;as especially designed for the consumption of the 
mechanical reader.  Providence turns out an unfailing supply of 
authors whose obvious mission it is thus to protect literature 
from 
the ravages of the unintelligent; and it is only when he strays 
from his predestined pastures that the mechanical reader becomes 
a 
danger to the body of letters.  The idea that reading is a moral 
quality has unhappily led many conscientious persons to renounce 
their innocuous dalliance with light literature for more 
strenuous 
intercourse.  These are the persons who "make it a rule to read." 
 
The "platform" of the more ambitious actually includes the large 
resolve to keep up with all that is being written!  The desire to 
keep up is apparently the <pb n="515"/>  strongest incentive 
to this class 
of readers: they seem to regard literature as a cable-car that 
can 
be "boarded" only by running; while many a born reader may be 
found 
unblushingly loitering in the tea-cup times of stage-coach and 
posting-chaise, without so much as being aware of the new means 
of 
locomotion.</p><p> 
     It is when the mechanical reader, armed with this high 
conception of his duty, invades the domain of letters&mdash;discusses, 
criticises, condemns, or, worse still, praises&mdash;that the vice of 
reading becomes a menace to literature.  Even so, it might seem 
in 
questionable taste to resent an intrusion prompted by motives so 
respectable, were it not that the incorrigible self-sufficiency 
of 
the mechanical reader makes him a fair object of attack.  The man 
who grinds the barrel-organ does not challenge comparison with 
Paderewski, but the mechanical reader never doubts his 
intellectual 
competency.  As grace gives faith, so zeal for self-improvement 
is 
supposed to confer brains.</p><p> 
     To read is not a virtue; but to read well is an art, and an 
art that only the born reader can acquire.  The gift of reading 
is 
no exception to the rule that all natural gifts need to be 
cultivated by practice and discipline; but unless the innate 
aptitude exist the training will be wasted.  It is the delusion 
of 
the mechanical reader to think that intentions may take the place 
of aptitude.</p><p> 
     So far is this from being the case that there are certain 
generic signs by which the born reader detects his manufactured 
copy under whatever guise the latter may assume.  One of these 
idiosyncrasies is the habit of regarding reading objectively.  
The 
mechanical reader, as he always reads consciously, knows exactly 
how much he reads, and will tell you so with the pride of the 
careful housekeeper who has calculated to within half an ounce 
the 
daily consumption of food in her household.  As the housekeeper 
is 
apt to go to market every day at a certain hour, so the 
mechanical 
reader has often a fixed time for laying in his intellectual 
stores; and not infrequently he reads for just so many hours a 
day.  
The statement in one of Hamerton's youthful diaries&mdash;"I shall now 
commence a course of poetical reading, beginning with 50 hours of 
Chaucer, and as I gave him 1 1/2 last night it leaves me exactly 
48 
1/2"&mdash;is a good example of this kind of reading.  It follows that 
he who reads by time often "has no time to read"; a plight 
unknown 
to the born reader, whose reading forms a continuous undercurrent 
to all his other occupations. <pb n="516"/> </p><p> 
     The mechanical reader is the slave of his book-mark: if he 
lose his place he is under the irksome necessity of beginning 
again 
at the beginning; and a story is told of one such reader whom a 
flippant relative kept for a year at "Fire and Sword in the 
Soudan" 
by the unfeeling stratagem of shifting the marker every night.  
The 
born reader is his own book-mark.  He instinctively remembers at 
what stage in the argument he laid his book down, and the pages 
open of themselves at the point for which he is looking.  It is 
due 
to the mechanical reader to say that he is uniformly scrupulous 
in 
the performance of his task: it is one of his rules <hi rend="italic"> never to 
skip a word</hi>, and he can always meet with a triumphant 
affirmative 
Dr. Johnson's immortal "Do <hi rend="italic"> you</hi> read books <hi rend="italic"> 
through?"</hi>  This 
inexorable principle is doubtless based on the fact that the 
mechanical reader is incapable of discerning intuitively whether 
a 
book is worth reading or not.  In fact, until he has read the 
last 
line of a book he is unable to form any opinion of it; nor can he 
give any adequate reasons for his opinion when formed.  Viewing 
all 
books from the outside, and having no point of contact with the 
author's mind, he makes no allowances for temperament or 
environment; for that process of transposition and selection that 
makes the most impersonal book the product of unique 
conditions.</p><p> 
     It is obvious that the mechanical reader, taking each book 
separately as an entity suspended in the inane, must miss all the 
by-paths and cross-cuts of his subject.  He is like a tourist who 
drives from one "sight" to another without looking at anything 
that 
is not set down in Baedeker.  Of the delights of intellectual 
vagrancy, of the improvised chase after a fleeting allusion, 
suggested sometimes by the turn of a phrase or by the mere 
complexion of a word, he is serenely unaware.  With him the 
book's 
the thing: the idea of using it as the keynote of unpremeditated 
harmonies, as the gateway into some <hi rend="italic"> paysage choisi</hi> of the 
spirit, is beyond his ken.</p><p> 
     The mechanical reader considers it his duty to read every 
book 
that is talked about; a duty rendered less onerous by the fact 
that 
he can judge beforehand, from the material dimensions of each 
book, 
how much space it will take up in his head: there is no need to 
allow for expansion.  To the mechanical reader, books once read 
are 
not like growing things that strike root and intertwine branches, 
but like fossils ticketed and put away in the <pb n="517"/>  
drawers of a 
geologist's cabinet; or rather, like prisoners condemned to 
lifelong solitary confinement.  In such a mind the books never 
talk 
to each other.</p><p> 
     The course of the mechanical reader is guided by the <hi rend="italic"> vox 
populi</hi>.  He makes straight for the book that is being talked 
about, and his sense of its importance is in proportion to the 
number of editions exhausted before publication, since he has no 
means of distinguishing between the different classes of books 
talked about, nor between the voices that do the talking.</p><p> 
     It is a part of the whole duty of the mechanical reader to 
pronounce an opinion on every book he reads, and he is sometimes 
driven to strange shifts in the conscientious performance of this 
task.  It is his nature to mistrust and dislike every book he 
does 
not understand.  "I cannot read and therefore wish all books 
burned."  In his heart of hearts the mechanical reader may 
sometimes echo this wish of Envy in Doctor Faustus; but, it being 
also a part of his duty to be "fond of reading," he is obliged to 
repress his bibliocidal impulse, and go through the form of 
trying 
the case, when lynching would have been so much simpler.</p><p> 
     It is only natural that the reader who looks on reading as a 
moral obligation should confound moral and intellectual 
judgments.  
Here is a book that every one is talking about; the number of its 
editions is an almost unanswerable proof of its merit; but to the 
mechanical reader it is cryptic, and he takes refuge in 
disapproval.  He admits the cleverness, of course; but one of the 
characters is "not nice"; <hi rend="italic"> ergo</hi>, the book is not nice; he 
is 
surprised that you should have cared to read it.  The mechanical 
reader, after a few such experiments, learns the potency of 
disapproval as a critical weapon, and it soon becomes his chief 
defence against the irritating demand to admire what he cannot 
understand.  Sometimes his disapprobation is tempered by 
philosophic concessions to human laxity: as in the case of the 
lady 
who could not approve of Balzac's novels, but was of course 
willing 
to admit that "they were written in the most beautiful French."  
A 
fine instance of this temperate disapproval is furnished by Mrs. 
Barbauld's verdict upon The Ancient Mariner: she "pronounced it 
improbable."</p><p> 
     The obligation of expressing an opinion on every book which 
is 
being talked about has led to the reprehensible but natural habit 
of borrowing opinions.  Any one who frequents a group of 
<pb n="518"/>  
mechanical readers soon becomes accustomed to their socialistic 
use 
of certain formulas, and to the rapid process of erosion and 
distortion undergone by much-borrowed opinions.  There have been 
known persons heartless enough to find pleasure in taking the 
mechanical reader unawares with the demand for an opinion; and it 
must be owned that the result sometimes justifies the theory that 
no sports are so diverting as those which are seasoned with 
cruelty.  In such extremities, the expedients resorted to by 
mechanical readers often do justice to their inventiveness; as 
when 
a lady, on being suddenly asked what she thought of <hi rend="italic"> "Quo 
Vadis,"</hi> replied that she had no fault to find with the book 
except 
that "nothing happened in it."</p><p> 
     Thus far the subject has dealt only with what may be called 
the average mechanical reader: a designation embracing the 
immense 
majority of book-consumers.  There is, however, another and more 
striking type of mechanical reader&mdash;he who, wearying of the 
Philistine diversion of "understanding the obvious," boldly 
threads 
his way "amid the bitterness of things occult."  
Transcendentalism 
owes much of its perennial popularity to a reverence for the 
unintelligible, and its disciples are largely recruited from the 
class of readers who consider it as great an intellectual feat to 
read a book as to understand it.  But these votaries of the 
esoteric are too few in number to be harmful.  It is the average 
mechanical reader who really endangers the integrity of letters; 
this may seem a curious charge to bring against that voracious 
majority.  How can those who create the demand for the hundredth 
thousand be accused of malice toward letters?</p><p> 
     In that acute character-study, "Manoeuvring," Miss Edgeworth 
says of one of her characters: "Her mind had never been 
overwhelmed 
by a torrent of wasteful learning.  That the stream of literature 
had passed over it was apparent only from its fertility."  There 
could hardly be a happier description of those who read 
intuitively; and its antithesis as fitly portrays the mechanical 
reader.  His mind is devastated by that torrent of wasteful 
learning which his demands have helped to swell.  It is probable 
that if no one read but those who know how to read, none would 
produce books but those who know how to write; but it is the 
least 
offence of the mechanical reader to have encouraged the 
mechanical 
author.  The two were made for each other and may prey on one 
another with impunity. <pb n="519"/> </p><p> 
     The harmfulness of the mechanical reader is fourfold.  In 
the 
first place, by bringing about the demand for mediocre writing, 
he 
facilitates the career of the mediocre author.  The crime of 
luring 
creative talent into the ranks of mechanical production is in 
fact 
the gravest offence of the mechanical reader.</p><p> 
     Secondly, by his passion for "popular" renderings of 
abstruse 
and difficult subjects, by confounding the hastiest <hi rend="italic"> 
rechauffe</hi> 
of scientific truisms with the slowly-matured conceptions of the 
original thinker, he retards true culture and lessens the 
possible 
amount of really abiding work.</p><p> 
     The habit of confusing moral and intellectual judgments is 
the 
third cause of his harmfulness to literature.  The inadequacy of 
"art for art's sake" as a literary creed has long been conceded.  
It is not by requiring that the imaginative writer shall be 
touched 
"to fine issues" that the mechanical reader interferes with the 
production of masterpieces, but by his own inability to discern 
the 
"fine issues" of any book, however great, which presents some 
incidental stumbling-block to his vision.  To those who regard 
literature as a criticism of life, nothing is more puzzling than 
this incapacity to distinguish between the general tendency of a 
book&mdash;its technical and imaginative value as a whole&mdash;and its 
merely episodical features.  That the mechanical reader should 
confound the unmoral with the immoral is perhaps natural; he may 
be 
pardoned for an erroneous classification of such books as <hi rend="italic"> "La 
Chartreuse de Parme"</hi> or the "Life of Benvenuto Cellini"; his 
harmfulness to literature lies in his persistent ignorance of the 
fact that any serious portrayal of life must be judged not by the 
incidents it presents but by the author's sense of their 
significance.  The harmful book is the trivial book: it depends 
on 
the writer, and not on the subject, whether the contemplation of 
life results in Faust or Faublas.  To gauge the absence of this 
perception in the average reader, one must turn to the ordinary 
"improper" book of current English and American fiction.  In 
these 
works, enjoyed under protest, with the plea that they are 
"unpleasant, but so powerful," one sees the reflection of the 
image 
which the great portrayals of life leave on the minds of the 
mechanical reader and his novelist.  There is the collocation of 
"painful" incidents; but the rest, being unperceived, is left 
out.</p><p> 
     Finally, the mechanical reader, by his demand for peptonized 
<pb n="520"/>  literature, and his inability to distinguish 
between the 
means and the end, has misdirected the tendencies of criticism, 
or 
rather, has produced a creature in his own image&mdash;the mechanical 
critic.  The London correspondent of a New York paper recently 
quoted a "well-known English reviewer" as saying that people no 
longer had time to read critical analyses of books&mdash;that what 
they 
wanted was a <hi rend="italic"> resume</hi> of the contents.  It is of course an 
open 
question (and hardly within the scope of this argument) how much 
literature is benefited by criticism; but to speak as though the 
analysis of a book were one kind of criticism and the cataloguing 
of its contents another, is a manifest absurdity.  The born 
reader 
may or may not wish to hear what the critics have to say of a 
book; 
but if he cares for any criticism he wants the only kind worthy 
of 
the name&mdash;an analysis of subject and manner.  He who has no time 
for such criticism will certainly spare none to the summing-up of 
the contents of a book: an inventory of its incidents, ending up 
with the conventional "But we will not spoil the reader's 
enjoyment 
by revealing, etc."  It is the mechanical reader who demands such 
inventories and calls them criticisms; and it is because the 
mechanical reader is in the majority that the mechanical plot-extractor is fast superseding the critic.  Whether real criticism 
be of service to literature or not, it is clear that this pseudo-reviewing is harmful, since it places books of very different 
qualities on the same dead level of mediocrity, by ignoring their 
true purport and significance.  It is impossible to give an idea 
of 
the value of any book, except perhaps a detective-story, by the 
recapitulation of its contents; and even those qualities which 
differentiate the good from the bad detective-story lie not so 
much 
in the collocation of incidents as in the handling of the subject 
and the choice of means used for producing a given effect.  All 
forms of art are based on the principle of selection, and where 
that principle is held of no account in the sum-total of any 
intellectual production, there can be no genuine 
criticism.</p><p> 
     It is thus that the mechanical reader systematically works 
against the best in literature.  Obviously, it is to the writer 
that he is most harmful.  The broad way that leads to his 
approval 
is so easy to tread and so thronged with prosperous fellow-travellers that many a young pilgrim has been drawn into it by 
the 
mere craving for companionship; and perhaps it is not until the 
<pb n="521"/>  journey's end, when he reaches the Palace of 
Platitudes and 
sits down to a feast of indiscriminate praise, with the 
scribblers 
he has most despised helping themselves unreproved out of the 
very 
dish prepared in his honor, that his thoughts turn longingly to 
that other way&mdash;the strait path leading "To The Happy Few."</p> 
<signed>                                             EDITH WHARTON.</signed> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
