<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaView"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>


<TEI.2 id="WhaView"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mrs. Manstey's View.</title>
<title type="sort">mrs mansteys view</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">27</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">WhaView</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476534</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mrs. Manstey's View.</title>
<title type="sort">mrs mansteys view</title>
<author>Edith Wharton</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner's Magazine</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1891-07">July 1891</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 10</p>
</seriesStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Verification made against printed text</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of  
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1891">1891</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman and Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 

<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 

<head> 
Wharton, Edith.  "Mrs. Manstey's View."   
<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic"> Scribner's Magazine</hi> 10 (July 1891): 117-122. 
</head> 

<pb n="117"/>  

<p>THE view from Mrs. Manstey's window was not a striking one, but to 
her at least it was full of interest and beauty.  Mrs. Manstey 
occupied the back room on the third floor of a New York boarding-house, in a street where the ash-barrels lingered late on the 
sidewalk and the gaps in the pavement would have staggered a 
Quintus Curtius.  She was the widow of a clerk in a large wholesale 
house, and his death had left her alone, for her only daughter had 
married in California, and could not afford the long journey to New 
York to see her mother.  Mrs. Manstey, perhaps, might have joined 
her daughter in the West, but they had now been so many years apart 
that they had ceased to feel any need of each other's society, and 
their intercourse had long been limited to the exchange of a few 
perfunctory letters, written with indifference by the daughter, and 
with difficulty by Mrs. Manstey, whose right hand was growing stiff 
with gout.  Even had she felt a stronger desire for her daughter's 
companionship, Mrs. Manstey's increasing infirmity, which caused 
her to dread the three flights of stairs between her room and the 
street, would have given her pause on the eve of undertaking so 
long a journey; and without perhaps, formulating these reasons she 
had long since accepted as a matter of course her solitary life in 
New York. 
</p><p>She was, indeed, not quite lonely, for a few friends still 
toiled up now and then to her room; but their visits grew rare as 
the years went by.  Mrs. Manstey had never been a sociable woman, 
and during her husband's lifetime his companionship had been all-sufficient to her.  For many years she had cherished a desire to 
live in the country, to have a hen-house and a garden; but this 
longing had faded with age, leaving only in the breast of the 
uncommunicative old woman a vague tenderness for plants and 
animals.  It was, perhaps, this tenderness which made her cling so 
fervently to her view from her window, a view in which the most 
optimistic eye would at first have failed to discover anything 
admirable. 
</p><p>Mrs. Manstey, from her coign of vantage (a slightly projecting 
bow-window where she nursed an ivy and a succession of unwholesome-looking bulbs), looked out first upon the yard of her own dwelling, 
of which, however, she could get but a restricted glimpse.  Still, 
her gaze took in the topmost boughs of the ailanthus below her 
window, and she knew how early each year the clump of dicentra 
strung its bending stalk with hearts of pink. 
</p><p>But of greater interest were the yards beyond.  Being for the 
most part attached to boarding-houses they were in a state of 
chronic untidiness <pb n="118"/>  and fluttering, on certain days of the 
week, with miscellaneous garments and frayed table-cloths.  In 
spite of this Mrs. Manstey found much to admire in the long vista 
which she commanded.  Some of the yards were, indeed, but stony 
wastes, with grass in the cracks of the pavement and no shade in 
spring save that afforded by the intermittent leafage of the 
clothes-lines.  These yards Mrs. Manstey disapproved of, but the 
others, the green ones, she loved.  She had grown used to their 
disorder; the broken barrels, the empty bottles and paths unswept 
no longer annoyed her; hers was the happy faculty of dwelling on 
the pleasanter side of the prospect before her. 
</p><p>In the very next enclosure did not a magnolia open its hard 
white flowers against the watery blue of April?  And was there not, 
a little way down the line, a fence foamed over every May be lilac 
waves of wistaria?  Farther still, a horse-chestnut lifted its 
candelabra of buff and pink blossoms above broad fans of foliage; 
while in the opposite yard June was sweet with the breath of a 
neglected syringa, which persisted in growing in spite of the 
countless obstacles opposed to its welfare. 
</p><p>But if nature occupied the front rank in Mrs. Manstey's view, 
there was much of a more personal character to interest her in the 
aspect of the houses and their inmates.  She deeply disapproved of 
the mustard-colored curtains which had lately been hung in the 
doctor's window opposite; but she glowed with pleasure when the 
house farther down had its old bricks washed with a coat of paint.  
The occupants of the houses did not often show themselves at the 
back windows, but the servants were always in sight.  Noisy 
slatterns, Mrs. Manstey pronounced the greater number; she knew 
their ways and hated them.  But to the quiet cook in the newly 
painted house, whose mistress bullied her, and who secretly fed the 
stray cats at nightfall, Mrs. Manstey's warmest sympathies were 
given.  On one occasion her feelings were racked by the neglect of 
a housemaid, who for two days forgot to feed the parrot committed 
to her care.  On the third day, Mrs. Manstey, in spite of her gouty 
hand, had just penned a letter, beginning: "Madam, it is now three 
days since your parrot has been fed," when the forgetful maid 
appeared at the window with a cup of seed in her hand. 
</p><p>But in Mrs. Manstey's more meditative moods it was the 
narrowing perspective of far-off yards which pleased her best.  She 
loved, at twilight, when the distant brown-stone spire seemed 
melting in the fluid yellow of the west, to lose herself in vague 
memories of a trip to Europe, made years ago, and now reduced in 
her mind's eye to a pale phantasmagoria of indistinct steeples and 
dreamy skies.  Perhaps at heart Mrs. Manstey was an artist; at all 
events she was sensible of many changes of color unnoticed by the 
average eye, and dear to her as the green of early spring was the 
black lattice of branches against a cold sulphur sky at the close 
of a snowy day.  She enjoyed, also, the sunny thaws of March, when 
patches of earth showed through the snow, like ink-spots spreading 
on a sheet of white blotting-paper; and, better still, the haze of 
boughs, leafless but swollen, which replaced the clear-cut tracery 
of winter.  She even watched with a certain interest the trail of 
smoke from a far-off factory chimney, and missed a detail in the 
landscape when the factory was closed and the smoke disappeared. 
</p><p>Mrs. Manstey, in the long hours which she spent at her window, 
was not idle.  She read a little, and knitted numberless stockings; 
but the view surrounded and shaped her life as the sea does a 
lonely island.  When her rare callers came it was difficult for her 
to detach herself from the contemplation of the opposite window-washing, or the scrutiny of certain green points in a neighboring 
flower-bed which might, or might not, turn into hyacinths, while 
she feigned an interest in her visitor's anecdotes about some 
unknown grandchild.  Mrs. Manstey's real friends were the denizens 
of the yards, the hyacinths, the magnolia, the green parrot, the 
maid who fed the cats, the doctor who studied late behind his 
mustard-colored curtains; and the confidant of her tenderer musings 
was the church-spire floating in the sunset. 
</p><p>One April day, as she sat in her usual place, with knitting 
cast aside and eyes <pb n="119"/>  fixed on the blue sky mottled with 
round clouds, a knock at the door announced the entrance of her 
landlady.  Mrs. Manstey did not care for her landlady, but she 
submitted to her visits with ladylike resignation.  To-day, 
however, it seemed harder than usual to turn from the blue sky and 
the blossoming magnolia to Mrs. Sampson's unsuggestive face, and 
Mrs. Manstey was conscious of a distinct effort as she did so. 
</p><p>"The magnolia is out earlier than usual this year, Mrs. 
Sampson," she remarked, yielding to a rare impulse, for she seldom 
alluded to the absorbing interest of her life.  In the first place 
it was a topic not likely to appeal to her visitors and, besides, 
she lacked the power of expression and could not have given 
utterance to her feelings had she wished to. 
</p><p>"The what, Mrs. Manstey?" inquired the landlady, glancing 
about the room as if to find there the explanation of Mrs. 
Manstey's statement. 
</p><p>"The magnolia in the next yard&mdash;in Mrs. Black's yard," Mrs. 
Manstey repeated. 
</p><p>"Is it, indeed?  I didn't know there was a magnolia there," 
said Mrs. Sampson, carelessly.  Mrs. Manstey looked at her; she did 
not know that there was a magnolia in the next yard! 
</p><p>"By the way," Mrs. Sampson continued, "speaking of Mrs. Black 
reminds me that the work on the extension is to begin next week." 
</p><p>"The what?" it was Mrs. Manstey's turn to ask. 
</p><p>"The extension," said Mrs. Sampson, nodding her head in the 
direction of the ignored magnolia.  "You knew, of course, that Mrs. 
Black was going to build an extension to her house?  Yes, ma'am.  
I hear it is to run right back to the end of the yard.  How she can 
afford to build an extension in these hard times I don't see; but 
she always was crazy about building.  She used to keep a boarding-house in Seventeenth Street, and she nearly ruined herself then by 
sticking out bow-windows and what not; I should have thought that 
would have cured her of building, but I guess it's a disease, like 
drink.  Anyhow, the work is to begin on Monday." 
</p><p>Mrs. Manstey had grown pale.  She always spoke slowly, so the 
landlady did not heed the long pause which followed.  At last Mrs. 
Manstey said: "Do you know how high the extension will be?" 
</p><p>"That's the most absurd part of it.  The extension is to be 
built right up to the roof of the main building; now, did you 
ever?" 
</p><p>"Mrs. Manstey paused again.  "Won't it be a great annoyance to 
you, Mrs. Sampson?" she asked. 
</p><p>"I should say it would.  But there's no help for it; if people 
have got a mind to build extensions there's no law to prevent 'em, 
that I'm aware of."  Mrs. Manstey, knowing this, was silent.  
"There is no help for it," Mrs. Sampson repeated, "but if I <hi rend="italic"> am</hi> 
a church member, I wouldn't be so sorry if it ruined Eliza Black.  
Well, good-day, Mrs. Manstey; I'm glad to find you so comfortable." 
</p><p>So comfortable&mdash;so comfortable!  Left to herself the old woman 
turned once more to the window.  How lovely the view was that day!  
The blue sky with its round clouds shed a brightness over 
everything; the ailanthus had put on a tinge of yellow-green, the 
hyacinths were budding, the magnolia flowers looked more than ever 
like rosettes carved in alabaster.  Soon the wistaria would bloom, 
then the horse-chestnut; but not for her.  Between her eyes and 
them a barrier of brick and mortar would swiftly rise; presently 
even the spire would disappear, and all her radiant world be 
blotted out.  Mrs. Manstey sent away untouched the dinner-tray 
brought to her that evening.  She lingered in the window until the 
windy sunset died in bat-colored dusk; then, going to bed, she lay 
sleepless all night. 
</p><p>Early the next day she was up and at the window.  It was 
raining, but even through the slanting gray gauze the scene had its 
charm&mdash;and then the rain was so good for the trees.  She had 
noticed the day before that the ailanthus was growing dusty. 
</p><p>"Of course I might move," said Mrs. Manstey aloud, and turning 
from the window she looked about her room.  She might move, of 
course; so might she be flayed alive; but she was not likely to 
survive either operation.  The room, though far less important to 
her happiness than the view, was as much a part <pb n="120"/>  of her 
existence.  She had lived in it seventeen years.  She knew every 
stain on the wall-paper, every rent in the carpet; the light fell 
in a certain way on her engravings, her books had grown shabby on 
their shelves, her bulbs and ivy were used to their window and knew 
which way to lean to the sun.  "We are all too old to move," she 
said. 
</p><p>That afternoon it cleared.  Wet and radiant the blue 
reappeared through torn rags of cloud; the ailanthus sparkled; the 
earth in the flower-borders looked rich and warm.  It was Thursday, 
and on Monday the building of the extension was to begin. 
</p><p>On Sunday afternoon a card was brought to Mrs. Black, as she 
was engaged in gathering up the fragments of the boarders' dinner 
in the basement.  The card, black-edged, bore Mrs. Manstey's name. 
</p><p>"One of Mrs. Sampson's boarders; wants to move, I suppose.  
Well, I can give her a room next year in the extension.  Dinah," 
said Mrs. Black, "tell the lady I'll be upstairs in a minute." 
</p><p>Mrs. Black found Mrs. Manstey standing in the long parlor 
garnished with statuettes and antimacassars; in that house she 
could not sit down. 
</p><p>Stooping hurriedly to open the register, which let out a cloud 
of dust, Mrs. Black advanced on her visitor. 
</p><p>"I'm happy to meet you, Mrs. Manstey; take a seat, please," 
the landlady remarked in her prosperous voice, the voice of a woman 
who can afford to build extensions.  There was no help for it; Mrs. 
Manstey sat down. 
</p><p>"Is there anything I can do for you, ma'am?" Mrs. Black 
continued.  "My house is full at present, but I am going to build 
an extension, and&mdash;" 
</p><p>"It is about the extension that I wish to speak," said Mrs. 
Manstey, suddenly.  "I am a poor woman, Mrs. Black, and I have 
never been a happy one.  I shall have to talk about myself first 
to&mdash;to make you understand." 
</p><p>Mrs. Black, astonished but imperturbable, bowed at this 
parenthesis. 
</p><p>"I never had what I wanted," Mrs. Manstey continued.  "It was 
always one disappointment after another.  For years I wanted to 
live in the country.  I dreamed and dreamed about it; but we never 
could manage it.  There was no sunny window in our house, and so 
all my plants died.  My daughter married years ago and went away&mdash; 
besides, she never cared for the same things.  Then my husband died 
and I was left alone.  That was seventeen years ago.  I went to 
live at Mrs. Sampson's, and I have been there ever since.  I have 
grown a little infirm, as you see, and I don't get out often; only 
on fine days, if I am feeling very well.  So you can understand my 
sitting a great deal in my window&mdash;the back window on the third 
floor&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Well, Mrs. Manstey," said Mrs. Black, liberally, "I could 
give you a back room, I dare say; one of the new rooms in the ex&mdash;" 
</p><p>"But I don't want to move; I can't move," said Mrs. Manstey, 
almost with a scream.  "And I came to tell you that if you build 
that extension I shall have no view from my window&mdash;no view!  Do 
you understand?" 
</p><p>Mrs. Black thought herself face to face with a lunatic, and 
she had always heard that lunatics must be humored. 
</p><p>"Dear me, dear me," she remarked, pushing her chair back a 
little way, "that is too bad, isn't it?  Why, I never thought of 
that.  To be sure, the extension <hi rend="italic"> will</hi> interfere with your view, 
Mrs. Manstey." 
</p><p>"You do understand?" Mrs. Manstey gasped. 
</p><p>"Of course I do.  And I'm real sorry about it, too.  But 
there, don't you worry, Mrs. Manstey.  I guess we can fix that all 
right." 
</p><p>Mrs. Manstey rose from her seat, and Mrs. Black slipped toward 
the door. 
</p><p>"What do you mean by fixing it?  Do you mean that I can induce 
you to change your mind about the extension?  Oh, Mrs. Black, 
listen to me.  I have two thousand dollars in the bank and I could 
manage, I know I could manage, to give you a thousand if&mdash;"  Mrs. 
Manstey paused; the tears were rolling down her cheeks. 
</p><p>"There, there, Mrs. Manstey, don't you worry," repeated Mrs. 
Black, soothingly.  "I am sure we can settle it.  I am sorry that 
I can't stay and talk about it any longer, but this is such a busy 
time of day, with supper to get&mdash;" <pb n="121"/>  
</p><p>Her hand was on the door-knob, but with sudden vigor Mrs. 
Manstey seized her wrist. 
</p><p>"You are not giving me a definite answer.  Do you mean to say 
that you accept my proposition?" 
</p><p>"Why, I'll think it over, Mrs. Manstey, certainly I will.  I 
wouldn't annoy you for the world&mdash;" 
</p><p>"But the work is to begin to-morrow, I am told," Mrs. Manstey 
persisted. 
</p><p>Mrs. Black hesitated.  "It shan't begin, I promise you that; 
I'll send word to the builder this very night."  Mrs. Manstey 
tightened her hold. 
</p><p>"You are not deceiving me, are you?" she said. 
</p><p>"No&mdash;no," stammered Mrs. Black.  "How can you think such a 
thing of me, Mrs. Manstey?" 
</p><p>Slowly Mrs. Manstey's clutch relaxed, and she passed through 
the open door.  "One thousand dollars," she repeated, pausing in 
the hall; then she let herself out of the house and hobbled down 
the steps, supporting herself on the cast-iron railing. 
</p><p>"My goodness," exclaimed Mrs. Black, shutting and bolting the 
hall-door, "I never knew the old woman was crazy!  And she looks so 
quiet and ladylike, too." 
</p><p>Mrs. Manstey slept well that night, but early the next morning 
she was awakened by a sound of hammering.  She got to her window 
with what haste she might and, looking out saw that Mrs. Black's 
yard was full of workmen.  Some were carrying loads of brick from 
the kitchen to the yard, others beginning to demolish the old-fashioned wooden balcony which adorned each story of Mrs. Black's 
house.  Mrs. Manstey saw that she had been deceived.  At first she 
thought of confiding her trouble to Mrs. Sampson, but a settled 
discouragement soon took possession of her and she went back to 
bed, not caring to see what was going on. 
</p><p>Toward afternoon, however, feeling that she must know the 
worst, she rose and dressed herself.  It was a laborious task, for 
her hands were stiffer than usual, and the hooks and buttons seemed 
to evade her. 
</p><p>When she seated herself in the window, she saw that the 
workmen had removed the upper part of the balcony, and that the 
bricks had multiplied since morning.  One of the men, a coarse 
fellow with a bloated face, picked a magnolia blossom and, after 
smelling it, threw it to the ground; the next man, carrying a load 
of bricks, trod on the flower in passing. 
</p><p>"Look out, Jim," called one of the men to another who was 
smoking a pipe, "if you throw matches around near those barrels of 
paper you'll have the old tinder-box burning down before you know 
it."  And Mrs. Manstey, leaning forward, perceived that there were 
several barrels of paper and rubbish under the wooden balcony. 
</p><p>At length the work ceased and twilight fell.  The sunset was 
perfect and a roseate light, transfiguring the distant spire, 
lingered late in the west.  When it grew dark Mrs. Manstey drew 
down the shades and proceeded, in her usual methodical manner, to 
light her lamp.  She always filled and lit it with her own hands, 
keeping a kettle of kerosene on a zinc-covered shelf in a closet.  
As the lamp-light filled the room it assumed its usual peaceful 
aspect.  The books and pictures and plants seemed, like their 
mistress, to settle themselves down for another quiet evening, and 
Mrs. Manstey, as was her wont, drew up her armchair to the table 
and began to knit. 
</p><p>That night she could not sleep.  The weather had changed and 
a wild wind was abroad, blotting the stars with close-driven 
clouds.  Mrs. Manstey rose once or twice and looked out of the 
window; but of the view nothing was discernible save a tardy light 
or two in the opposite windows.  These lights at last went out, and 
Mrs. Manstey, who had watched for their extinction, began to dress 
herself.  She was in evident haste, for she merely flung a thin 
dressing-gown over her night-dress and wrapped her head in a scarf; 
then she opened her closet and cautiously took out the kettle of 
kerosene.  Having slipped a bundle of wooden matches into her 
pocket she proceeded, with increasing precautions, to unlock her 
door, and a few moments later she was feeling her way down the dark 
staircase, led by a glimmer of gas from the lower hall.  At length 
she reached the bottom of the stairs and began the more <pb n="122"/>  
difficult descent into the utter darkness of the basement.  Here, 
however, she could move more freely, as there was less danger of 
being overheard; and without much delay she contrived to unlock the 
iron door leading into the yard.  A gust of cold wind smote her as 
she stepped out and groped shiveringly under the clothes-lines. 
</p><p>That morning at three o'clock an alarm of fire brought the 
engines to Mrs. Black's door, and also brought Mrs. Sampson's 
startled boarders to their windows.  The wooden balcony at the back 
of Mrs. Black's house was ablaze, and among those who watched the 
progress of the flames was Mrs. Manstey, leaning in her thin 
dressing-gown from the open window. 
</p><p>The fire, however, was soon put out, and the frightened 
occupants of the house, who had fled in scant attire, reassembled 
at dawn to find that little mischief had been done beyond the 
cracking of window panes and smoking of ceilings.  In fact, the 
chief sufferer by the fire was Mrs. Manstey, who was found in the 
morning gasping with pneumonia, a not unnatural result, as everyone 
remarked, of her having hung out of an open window at her age in a 
dressing-gown.  It was easy to see that she was very ill, but no 
one had guessed how grave the doctor's verdict would be, and the 
faces gathered that evening about Mrs. Sampson's table were 
awestruck and disturbed.  Not that any of the boarders knew Mrs. 
Manstey well; she "kept to herself," as they said, and seemed to 
fancy herself too good for them; but then it is always disagreeable 
to have anyone dying in the house and, as one lady observed to 
another: "It might just as well have been you or me, my dear." 
</p><p>But it was only Mrs. Manstey; and she was dying, as she had 
lived, lonely if not alone.  The doctor had sent a trained nurse, 
and Mrs. Sampson, with muffled step, came in from time to time; but 
both, to Mrs. Manstey, seemed remote and unsubstantial as the 
figures in a dream.  All day she said nothing; but when she was 
asked for her daughter's address she shook her head.  At times the 
nurse noticed that she seemed to be listening attentively for some 
sound which did not come; then again she dozed. 
</p><p>The next morning at daylight she was very low.  The nurse 
called Mrs. Sampson and as the two bent over the old woman they saw 
her lips move. 
</p><p>"Lift me up&mdash;out of bed," she whispered. 
</p><p>They raised her in their arms, and with her stiff hand she 
pointed to the window. 
</p><p>"Oh, the window&mdash;she wants to sit in the window.  She used to 
sit there all day," Mrs. Sampson explained.  "It can do her no 
harm, I suppose?" 
</p><p>"Nothing matters now," said the nurse. 
</p><p>They carried Mrs. Manstey to the window and placed her in her 
chair.  The dawn was abroad, a jubilant spring dawn; the spire had 
already caught a golden ray, though the magnolia and horse-chestnut 
still slumbered in shadow.  In Mrs. Black's yard all was quiet.  
The charred timbers of the balcony lay where they had fallen.  It 
was evident that since the fire the builders had not returned to 
their work.  The magnolia had unfolded a few more sculptural 
flowers; the view was undisturbed. 
</p><p>It was hard for Mrs. Manstey to breathe; each moment it grew 
more difficult.  She tried to make them open the window, but they 
would not understand.  If she could have tasted the air, sweet with 
the penetrating ailanthus savor, it would have eased her; but the 
view at least was there&mdash;the spire was golden now, the heavens had 
warmed from pearl to blue, day was alight from east to west, even 
the magnolia had caught the sun. 
</p><p>Mrs. Manstey's head fell back and smiling she died. 
</p><p>That day the building of the extension was resumed. 
</p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
