<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaWild"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="WhaWild"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Hermit and the Wild Woman</title>
<title type="sort">hermit and the wild woman</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">57</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">WhaWild</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476536</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Hermit and the Wild Woman</title>
<title type="sort">hermit and the wild woman</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner's Magazine</publisher>
<pubPlace>new York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1906-02">Feb. 1906</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Volume 39</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Verification made against printed text</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of  
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1906">1906</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman and Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 

<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
<head> 
Wharton, Edith.  "The Hermit and the Wild Woman."   
<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic"> Scribner's Magazine</hi> 39 (Feb. 1906): 145-56. 
</head> 

<pb n="145"/>  

<p>THE Hermit lived in a cave in the hollow of a hill.  Below him was 
a glen, with a stream in a coppice of oaks and alders, and on the 
farther side of the valley, half a day's journey distant, another 
hill, steep and bristling, which raised aloft a little walled town 
with Ghibelline swallow-tails notched against the sky. 
</p><p>When the Hermit was a lad, and lived in the town, the 
crenellations of the walls had been square-topped, and a Guelf lord 
had flown his standard from the keep.  Then one day a steel-coloured line of men-at-arms rode across the valley, wound up the 
hill and battered in the gates.  Stones and Greek fire rained from 
the ramparts, shields clashed in the streets, blade sprang at blade 
in passages and stairways, pikes and lances dripped above huddled 
flesh, and all the still familiar place was a stew of dying bodies.  
The boy fled from it in horror.  He had seen his father go forth 
and not come back, his mother drop dead from an arquebuse shot as 
she leaned from the platform of the tower, his little sister fall 
with a slit throat across the altar steps of the chapel&mdash;and he 
ran, ran for his life, through the slippery streets, over warm 
twitching bodies, between legs of soldiers carousing, out of the 
gates, past burning farmsteads, trampled wheat-fields, orchards 
stripped and broken, till the still woods received him and he fell 
face down on the unmutilated earth. 
</p><p>He had no wish to go back.  His longing was to live hidden 
from life.  Up the hillside he found a hollow in the rock, and 
built before it a porch of boughs bound together with withies.  He 
fed on nuts and roots, and on trout which he caught with his hands 
under the stones in the stream.  He had always been a quiet boy, 
liking to sit at his mother's feet and watch the flowers grow on 
her embroidery frame, while the chaplain read aloud the histories 
of the Desert Fathers from a great silver-clasped volume.  He would 
rather have been bred a clerk and scholar than a knight's son, and 
his happiest moments were when he served mass for the chaplain in 
the early morning, and felt his heart flutter up and up like a 
lark, up and up till it was lost in infinite space and brightness.  
Almost as happy were the hours when he sat beside the foreign 
painter who came over the mountains to paint the chapel, and under 
whose brush celestial faces grew out of the rough wall as if he had 
sown some magic seed which flowered while you watched it.  With the 
appearing of every gold-rimmed face the boy felt he had won another 
friend, a friend who would come and bend above him at night, 
keeping off the ugly visions which haunted his pillow&mdash;visions of 
the gnawing monsters about the church-porch, evil-faced bats and 
dragons, giant worms and winged bristling hogs, a devil's flock who 
crept down from the stone-work at night and hunted the souls of 
sinful children through the town.  With the growth of the picture 
the bright mailed angels thronged so close about the boy's bed that 
between their interwoven wings not a snout or a claw could force 
itself; and he would turn over sighing on his pillow, which felt as 
soft and warm as if it had been lined with down from those 
sheltering pinions. 
</p><p>All these thoughts came back to him now in his cave on the 
cliff-side.  The stillness seemed to enclose him with wings, to 
fold him away from life and evil.  He was never restless or 
discontented.  He loved the long silent empty days, each one as 
like the other as pearls in a well-matched string.  Above all he 
liked to have time to save his soul.  He had been greatly troubled 
about his soul since a band of Flagellants had passed through the 
town, exhibiting their gaunt scourged bodies and exhorting the 
people to turn from soft raiment and delicate fare, from marriage 
and money-getting and dancing and games, and think only how they 
might escape the devil's talons and the great red blaze of hell.  
For days that red blaze hung on the edge of the boy's thoughts like 
the light of a <pb n="146"/>  burning city across a plain.  There seemed 
to be so many pitfalls to avoid&mdash;so many things were wicked which 
one might have supposed to be harmless.  How could a child of his 
age tell?  He dared not for a moment think of anything else.  And 
the scene of sack and slaughter from which he had fled gave shape 
and distinctness to that blood-red vision.  Hell was like that, 
only a million million times worse.  Now he knew how flesh looked 
when devils' pincers tore it, how the shrieks of the damned 
sounded, and how roasting bodies smelled.  How could a Christian 
spare one moment of his days and nights from the long long struggle 
to keep safe from the wrath to come? 
</p><p>Gradually the horror faded, leaving only a tranquil pleasure 
in the minute performance of his religious duties.  His mind was 
not naturally given to the contemplation of evil, and in the 
blessed solitude of his new life his thoughts dwelt more and more 
on the beauty of holiness.  His desire was to be perfectly good, 
and to live in love and charity with his fellow-men; and how could 
one do this without fleeing from them? 
</p><p>At first his life was difficult, for in the winter season he 
was put to great straits to feed himself; and there were nights 
when the sky was like an iron vault, and a hoarse wind rattled the 
oakwood in the valley, and a great fear came on him that was worse 
than any cold.  But in time it became known to his townsfolk and to 
the peasants in the neighbouring valleys that he had withdrawn to 
the wilderness to lead a godly life; and after that his worst 
hardships were over, for pious persons brought him gifts of oil and 
dried fruit, one good woman gave him seeds from her garden, another 
spun for him a hodden gown, and others would have brought him all 
manner of food and clothing, had he not refused to accept anything 
but for his bare needs.  The good woman who had given him the seeds 
showed him also how to build a little garden on the southern ledge 
of his cliff, and all one summer the Hermit carried up soil from 
the streamside, and the next he carried up water to keep his garden 
green.  After that the fear of solitude quite passed from him, for 
he was so busy all day long that at night he had much ado to fight 
off the demon of sleep, which Saint Arsenius the Abbot has 
denounced as the chief foe of the solitary.  His memory kept good 
store of prayers and litanies, besides long passages from the Mass 
and other offices, and he marked the hours of his day by different 
acts of devotion.  On Sundays and feast days, when the wind was set 
his way, he could hear the church bells from his native town, and 
these helped him to follow the worship of the faithful, and to bear 
in mind the seasons of the liturgical year; and what with carrying 
up water from the river, digging in the garden, gathering fagots 
for his fire, observing his religious duties, and keeping his 
thoughts continually upon the salvation of his soul, the Hermit 
knew not a moment's idleness. 
</p><p>At first, during his night vigils, he had felt a great fear of 
the stars, which seemed to set a cruel watch upon him, as though 
they spied out the frailty of his heart and took the measure of his 
littleness.  But one day a wandering clerk, to whom he chanced to 
give a night's shelter, explained to him that, in the opinion of 
the most learned doctors of theology, the stars were inhabited by 
the spirits of the blessed, and this thought brought great 
consolation to the Hermit.  Even on winter nights, when the eagle's 
wings clanged among the peaks, and he heard the long howl of wolves 
about the sheep-cotes in the valley, he no longer felt any fear, 
but thought of those sounds as representing the evil voices of the 
world, and hugged himself in the solitude of his cave.  Sometimes, 
to keep himself awake, he composed lauds in honour of Christ and 
the saints, and they seemed to him so pleasant that he feared to 
forget them, so after much debate with himself he decided to ask a 
friendly priest from the valley, who sometimes visited him, to 
write down the lauds; and the priest wrote them down on comely 
sheepskin, which the Hermit dried and prepared with his own hands.  
When the Hermit saw them written down they appeared to him so 
beautiful that he feared to commit the sin of vanity if he looked 
at them too often, so he hid them between two smooth stones in his 
cave, and vowed that he would take them out only once in the year, 
at Easter, when our Lord has risen and it is meet that Christians 
should rejoice.  And this vow he faithfully kept; but, alas, when 
Easter drew near, he found he was looking forward to the blessed 
festival less because of our Lord's rising than because he should 
then be able to read his pleasant lauds <pb n="147"/>  written on fair 
sheepskin; and thereupon he took a vow that he would not look upon 
the lauds till he lay dying. 
</p><p>So the Hermit, for many years, lived to the glory of God and 
in great peace of mind. 


</p><p>                           II 

</p><p>ONE day he resolved to set forth on a visit to the Saint of 
the Rock, who lived on the other side of the mountains.  Travellers 
had brought the Hermit report of this solitary, how he lived in 
great holiness and austerity in a desert place among the hills, 
where snow lay all winter, and in summer the sun beat down cruelly.  
The Saint, it appeared, had vowed that he would withdraw from the 
world to a spot where there was neither shade nor water, lest he 
should be tempted to take his ease and think less continually upon 
his Maker; but wherever he went he found a spreading tree or a 
gushing spring, till at last he climbed up to the bare heights 
where nothing grows, and where the only water comes from the 
melting of the snow in spring.  Here he found a tall rock rising 
from the ground, and in it he scooped a hollow with his own hands, 
labouring for five years and wearing his fingers to the bone.  Then 
he seated himself in the hollow, which faced the west, so that in 
winter he should have small warmth of the sun and in summer be 
consumed by it; and there he had sat without moving for years 
beyond number. 
</p><p>The Hermit was greatly drawn by the tale of such austerities, 
which in his humility he did not dream of emulating, but desired, 
for his soul's good, to contemplate and praise; so one day he bound 
sandals to his feet, cut an alder staff from the stream, and set 
out to visit the Saint of the Rock. 
</p><p>It was the pleasant spring season, when seeds are shooting and 
the bud is on the tree.  The Hermit was troubled at the thought of 
leaving his plants without water, but he could not travel in winter 
by reason of the snows, and in summer he feared the garden would 
suffer even more from his absence.  So he set out, praying that 
rain might fall while he was away, and hoping to return again in 
five days.  The peasants labouring in the fields left their work to 
ask his blessing; and they would even have followed him in great 
numbers had he not told them that he was bound on a pilgrimage to 
the Saint of the Rock, and that it behoved him to go alone, as one 
solitary seeking another.  So they respected his wish, and he went 
on and entered the forest.  In the forest he walked for two days 
and slept for two nights.  He heard the wolves crying, and foxes 
rustling in the covert, and once, at twilight, a shaggy brown man 
peered at him through the leaves and galloped away with a soft 
padding of hoofs; but the Hermit feared neither wild beasts nor 
evil-doers, nor even the fauns and satyrs who linger in unhallowed 
forest depths where the Cross has not been raised; for he said: "If 
I die, I die to the glory of God, and if I live it must be to the 
same end."  Only he felt a secret pang at the thought that he might 
die without seeing his lauds again.  But the third day, without 
misadventure, he came out on another valley. 
</p><p>Then he began to climb the mountain, first through brown woods 
of beech and oak, then through pine and broom, and then across red 
stony ledges where only a pinched growth of lentisk and briar 
spread in patches over the rock.  By this time he thought to have 
reached his goal, but for two more days he fared on through the 
same scene, with the sky close over him and the green valleys of 
earth receding far below.  Sometimes for hours he saw only the red 
glistering slopes tufted with thin bushes, and the hard blue heaven 
so close that it seemed his hand could touch it; then at a turn of 
the path the rocks rolled apart, the eye plunged down a long pine-clad defile, and beyond it the forest flowed in mighty undulations 
to a plain shining with cities and another mountain-range many 
days' journey away.  To some eyes this would have been a terrible 
spectacle, reminding the wayfarer of his remoteness from his kind, 
and of the perils which lurk in waste places and the weakness of 
man against them; but the Hermit was so mated to solitude, and felt 
such love for all things created, that to him the bare rocks sang 
of their Maker and the vast distance bore witness to His greatness.  
So His servant journeyed on unafraid. 
</p><p>But one morning, after a long climb over steep and difficult 
slopes, the wayfarer halted suddenly at a bend of the way; for 
beyond the defile at his feet there was no plain shining with 
cities, but a bare expanse of shaken silver that reached away to 
the rim of the world; and the Hermit knew it was the <pb n="148"/>  sea.  
Fear seized him then, for it was terrible to see that great plain 
move like a heaving bosom, and, as he looked on it, the earth 
seemed also to heave beneath him.  But presently he remembered how 
Christ had walked the waves, and how even Saint Mary of Egypt, who 
was a great sinner, had crossed the waters of Jordan dry-shod to 
receive the Sacrament from the Abbot Zosimus; and then the Hermit's 
heart grew still, and he sang as he went down the mountain: "The 
sea shall praise Thee, O Lord." 
</p><p>All day he kept seeing it and then losing it; but toward night 
he came to a cleft of the hills, and lay down in a pine-wood to 
sleep.  He had now been six days gone, and once and again he 
thought anxiously of his herbs; but he said to himself: "What 
though my garden perish, if I see a holy man face to face and 
praise God in his company?"  So he was never long cast down. 
</p><p>Before daylight he was afoot under the stars; and leaving the 
wood where he had slept, began climbing the face of a tall cliff, 
where he had to clutch the jutting ledges with his hands, and with 
every step he gained, a rock seemed thrust forth to hurl him back.  
So, footsore and bleeding, he reached a little stony plain as the 
sun dropped to the sea; and in the red light he saw a hollow rock, 
and the Saint sitting in the hollow. 
</p><p>The Hermit fell on his knees, praising God; then he rose and 
ran across the plain to the rock.  As he drew near he saw that the 
Saint was a very old man, clad in goatskin, with a long white 
beard.  He sat motionless, his hands on his knees, and two red eye-sockets turned to the sunset.  Near him was a young boy in skins 
who brushed the flies from his face; but they always came back, and 
settled on the rheum which ran from his eyes. 
</p><p>He did not appear to hear or see the approach of the Hermit, 
but sat quite still till the boy said: "Father, here is a pilgrim." 
</p><p>Then he lifted up his voice and asked angrily who was there 
and what the stranger sought. 
</p><p>The Hermit answered: "Father, the report of your holy 
practices came to me a long way off, and being myself a solitary, 
though not worthy to be named with you for godliness, it seemed 
fitting that I should cross the mountains to visit you, that we 
might sit together and speak in praise of solitude." 
</p><p>The Saint replied: "You fool, how can two sit together and 
praise solitude, since by so doing they put an end to the thing 
they pretend to honour?" 
</p><p>The Hermit, at that, was sorely abashed, for he had thought 
his speech out on the way, reciting it many times over; and now it 
appeared to him vainer than the crackling of thorns under a pot. 
</p><p>Nevertheless he took heart and said: "True, Father; but may 
not two sinners sit together and praise Christ, who has taught them 
the blessings of solitude?" 
</p><p>But the other only answered: "If you had really learned the 
blessings of solitude you would not squander them in idle 
wandering."  And, the Hermit not knowing how to reply, he said 
again: "If two sinners meet they can best praise Christ by going 
each his own way in silence." 
</p><p>After that he shut his lips and continued motionless while the 
boy brushed the flies from his eye-sockets; but the Hermit's heart 
sank, and for the first time he felt all the weariness of the way 
he had fared, and the great distance dividing him from home. 
</p><p>He had meant to take counsel with the Saint concerning his 
lauds, and whether he ought to destroy them; but now he had no 
heart to say another word, and turning away he began to descend the 
mountain.  Presently he heard steps running behind him, and the boy 
came up and pressed a honey-comb in his hand. 
</p><p>"You have come a long way and must be hungry," he said; but 
before the Hermit could thank him he had hastened back to his task.  
So the Hermit crept down the mountain till he reached the wood 
where he had slept before; and there he made his bed again, but he 
had no mind to eat before sleeping, for his heart hungered more 
than his body; and his salt tears made the honey-comb bitter. 


</p><p>                           III 

</p><p>ON the fourteenth day he came to the valley below his cliff, 
and saw the walls of his native town against the sky.  He was 
footsore and heavy of heart, for his long pilgrimage had brought 
him only weariness and humiliation, and as no drop of <pb n="149"/>  rain 
had fallen he knew that his garden must have perished.  So he 
climbed the cliff heavily and reached his cave at the angelus. 
</p><p>But there a great wonder awaited him.  For though the scant 
earth of the hillside was parched and crumbling, his garden-soil 
reeked with moisture, and his plants had shot up, fresh and 
glistening, to a height they had never before attained.  More 
wonderful still, the tendrils of the gourd had been trained about 
his door, and kneeling down he saw that the earth had been loosened 
between the rows of sprouting vegetables, and that every leaf 
sparkled with drops as though the rain had but newly ceased.  Then 
it appeared to the Hermit that he beheld a miracle, but doubting 
his own deserts he refused to believe himself worthy of such grace, 
and went within doors to ponder on what had befallen him.  And on 
his bed of rushes he saw a young woman sleeping, clad in an 
outlandish garment, with strange amulets about her neck. 
</p><p>The sight was very terrifying to the Hermit, for he recalled 
how often the demon, in tempting the Desert Fathers, had taken the 
form of a woman for their undoing; but he reflected that, since 
there was nothing pleasing to him in the sight of this female, who 
was brown as a nut and lean with wayfaring, he ran no great danger 
in looking at her.  At first he took her for a wandering Egyptian, 
but as he looked he perceived, among the heathen charms, an Agnus 
Dei in her bosom; and this so surprised him that he bent over and 
called on her to wake. 
</p><p>She sprang up with a start, but seeing the Hermit's gown and 
staff, and his face above her, lay quiet and said to him: "I have 
watered your garden daily in return for the beans and oil that I 
took from your store." 
</p><p>"Who are you, and how do you come here?" asked the Hermit. 
</p><p>She said: "I am a wild woman and live in the woods." 
</p><p>And when he pressed her again to tell him why she had sought 
shelter in his cave, she said that the land to the south, whence 
she came, was full of armed companies and bands of marauders, and 
that great license and bloodshed prevailed there; and this the 
Hermit knew to be true, for he had heard of it on his homeward 
journey.  The Wild Woman went on to tell him that she had been 
hunted through the woods like an animal by a band of drunken men-at-arms, Lansknechts from the north by their barbarous dress and 
speech, and at length, starving and spent, had come on his cave and 
hidden herself from her pursuers.  "For," she said, "I fear neither 
wild beasts nor the woodland people, charcoal burners, Egyptians, 
wandering minstrels or chapmen; even the highway robbers do not 
touch me, because I am poor and brown; but these armed men flown 
with blood and wine are more terrible than wolves and tigers." 
</p><p>And the Hermit's heart melted, for he thought of his little 
sister lying with her throat slit across the altar steps, and of 
the scenes of blood and rapine from which he had fled away into the 
wilderness.  So he said to the stranger that it was not meet he 
should house her in his cave, but that he would send a messenger to 
the town across the valley, and beg a pious woman there to give her 
lodging and work in her household.  "For," said he, "I perceive by 
the blessed image about your neck that you are not a heathen 
wilding, but a child of Christ, though so far astray from Him in 
the desert." 
</p><p>"Yes," she said, "I am a Christian, and know as many prayers 
as you; but I will never set foot in city walls again, lest I be 
caught and put back into the convent." 
</p><p>"What," cried the Hermit with a start, "you are a runagate 
nun?"  And he crossed himself, and again thought of the demon. 
</p><p>She smiled and said: "It is true I was once a cloistered 
woman, but I will never willingly be one again.  Now drive me forth 
if you like; but I cannot go far, for I have a wounded foot, which 
I got in climbing the cliff with water for your garden."  And she 
pointed to a deep cut in her foot. 
</p><p>At that, for all his fear, the Hermit was moved to pity, and 
washed the cut and bound it up; and as he did so he bethought him 
that perhaps his strange visitor had been sent to him not for his 
soul's undoing but for her own salvation.  And from that hour he 
earnestly yearned to save her. 
</p><p>But it was not fitting that she should remain in his cave; so, 
having given her water to drink and a handful of lentils, he raised 
her up and putting his staff in her hand guided her to a hollow not 
far off in the face of the cliff.  And while he was doing this he 
heard the sunset bells ring across the valley, and set about 
reciting the <hi rend="italic"> Angelus Domini nuntiavit Mariae</hi>; and she <pb n="150"/>  
joined in very piously, with her hands folded, not missing a word. 
</p><p>Nevertheless the thought of her wickedness weighed on him, and 
the next day when he went to carry her food he asked her to tell 
him how it came about that she had fallen into such abominable sin.  
And this is the story she told. 


</p><p>                           IV 

</p><p>I WAS born (said she) in the north country, where the winters 
are long and cold, where snow sometimes falls in the valleys, and 
the high mountains for months are white with it.  My father's 
castle is in a tall green wood, where the winds always rustle, and 
a cold river runs down from the ice-gorges.  South of us was the 
wide plain, glowing with heat, but above us were stony passes where 
the eagle nests and the storms howl; in winter great fires roared 
in our chimneys, and even in summer there was always a cool air off 
the gorges.  But when I was a child my mother went southward in the 
great Empress's train and I went with her.  We travelled many days, 
across plains and mountains, and saw Rome, where the Pope lives in 
a golden palace, and many other cities, till we came to the great 
Emperor's court.  There for two years or more we lived in pomp and 
merriment, for it was a wonderful court, full of mimes, magicians, 
philosophers and poets; and the Empress's ladies spent their days 
in mirth and music, dressed in light silken garments, walking in 
gardens of roses, and bathing in a great cool marble tank, while 
the Emperor's eunuchs guarded the approach to the gardens.  Oh, 
those baths in the marble tank, my Father!  I used to lie awake 
through the whole hot southern night, and think of that plunge at 
sunrise under the last stars.  For we were in a burning country, 
and I pined for the tall green woods and the cold stream of my 
father's valley; and when I had cooled my limbs in the tank I lay 
all day in the scant cypress shade and dreamed of my next bath. 
</p><p>My mother pined for the coolness till she died; then the 
Empress put me in a convent and I was forgotten.  The convent was 
on the side of a bare yellow hill, where bees made a hot buzzing in 
the thyme.  Below was the sea, blazing with a million shafts of 
light; and overhead a blinding sky, which reflected the sun's 
glitter like a huge baldric of steel.  Now the convent was built on 
the site of an old pleasure-house which a holy Princess had given 
to our Order; and a part of the house was left standing with its 
court and garden.  The nuns had built all about the garden; but 
they left the cypresses in the middle, and the long marble tank 
where the Princess and her ladies had bathed.  The tank, however, 
as you may conceive, was no longer used as a bath; for the washing 
of the body is an indulgence forbidden to cloistered virgins; and 
our Abbess, who was famed for her austerities, boasted that, like 
holy Sylvia the nun, she never touched water save to bathe her 
finger-tips before receiving the Sacrament.  With such an example 
before them, the nuns were obliged to conform to the same pious 
rule, and many, having been bred in the convent from infancy, 
regarded all ablutions with horror, and felt no temptation to 
cleanse the filth from their flesh; but I, who had bathed daily, 
had the freshness of clear water in my veins, and perished slowly 
for want of it, like your garden herbs in a drought. 
</p><p>My cell did not look on the garden, but on the steep mule-path 
leading up the cliff, where all day long the sun beat as if with 
flails of fire, and I saw the sweating peasants toil up and down 
behind their thirsty asses, and the beggars whining and scraping 
their sores in the heat.  Oh, how I hated to look out through the 
bars on that burning world!  I used to turn away from it, sick with 
disgust, and lying on my hard bed, stare up by the hour at the 
ceiling of my cell.  But flies crawled in hundreds on the ceiling, 
and the hot noise they made was worse than the glare.  Sometimes, 
at an hour when I knew myself unobserved, I tore off my stifling 
gown, and hung it over the grated window, that I might no longer 
see the shaft of hot sunlight lying across my cell, and the dust 
dancing in it like fat in the fire.  But the darkness choked me, 
and I struggled for breath as though I lay at the bottom of a pit; 
so that at last I would spring up, and dragging down the dress, 
fling myself on my knees before the Cross, and entreat our Lord to 
give me the gift of holiness, that I might escape the everlasting 
fires of hell, of which this heat was like an awful foretaste.  For 
if I could not <pb n="151"/>  endure the scorching of a summer's day, with 
what constancy could I meet the thought of the flame that dieth 
not? 
</p><p>This longing to escape the heat of hell made me apply myself 
to a devouter way of living, and I reflected that if my bodily 
distress were somewhat eased I should be able to throw myself with 
greater zeal into the practice of vigils and austerities.  And at 
length, having set forth to the Abbess that the sultry air of my 
cell induced in me a grievous heaviness of sleep, I prevailed on 
her to lodge me in that part of the building which overlooked the 
garden. 
</p><p>For a few days I was quite happy, for instead of the dusty 
mountainside, and the sight of the sweating peasants and their 
asses, I looked out on dark cypresses and rows of budding 
vegetables.  But presently I found I had not bettered myself.  For 
with the approach of midsummer the garden, being all enclosed with 
buildings, grew as stifling as my cell.  All the green things in it 
withered and dried off, leaving trenches of bare red earth, across 
which the cypresses cast strips of shade too narrow to cool the 
aching heads of the nuns who sought shelter there; and I began to 
think sorrowfully of my former cell, where now and then there came 
a sea-breeze, hot and languid, yet alive, and where at least I 
could look out upon the sea.  But this was not the worst; for when 
the dog-days came I found that the sun, at a certain hour, cast on 
the ceiling of my cell the reflection of the ripples on the garden-tank; and to say how I suffered from this sight is not within the 
power of speech.  It was indeed agony to watch the clear water 
rippling and washing above my head, yet feel no solace of it on my 
limbs: as though I had been a senseless brazen image lying at the 
bottom of a well.  But the image, if it felt no refreshment, would 
have suffered no torture; whereas every inch of my skin throbbed 
with thirst, and every vein was a mouth of Dives praying for a drop 
of water.  Oh, Father, how shall I tell you the grievous pains that 
I endured?  Sometimes I so feared the sight of the mocking ripples 
overhead that I hid my eyes from their approach, lying face down on 
my burning bed till I knew that they were gone; yet on cloudy days, 
when they did not come, the heat was even worse to bear. 
</p><p>By day I hardly dared trust myself in the garden, for the nuns 
walked there, and one fiery noon they found me hanging so close 
above the tank that they snatched me away, crying out that I had 
tried to destroy myself.  The scandal of this reaching the Abbess, 
she sent for me to know what demon had beset me; and when I wept 
and said, the longing to bathe my burning body, she broke into 
great anger and cried out: "Do you not know that this is a sin 
well-nigh as great as the other, and condemned by all the greatest 
saints?  For a nun may be tempted to take her life through excess 
of self-scrutiny and despair of her own worthiness; but this desire 
to indulge the despicable body is one of the lusts of the flesh, to 
be classed with concupiscence and adultery."  And she ordered me to 
sleep every night for a month in my heavy gown, with a veil upon my 
face. 
</p><p>Now, Father, I believe it was this penance that drove me to 
sin.  For we were in the dog-days, and it was more than flesh could 
bear.  And on the third night, after the portress had passed, and 
the lights were out, I rose and flung off my veil and gown, and 
knelt in my window fainting.  There was no moon, but the sky was 
full of stars.  At first the garden was all blackness; but as I 
looked I saw a faint twinkle between the cypress-trunks, and I knew 
it was the starlight on the tank.  The water!  The water!  It was 
there close to me&mdash;only a few bolts and bars were between us. 
</p><p>The portress was a heavy sleeper, and I knew where her keys 
hung, on a nail just within the door of her cell.  I stole thither, 
unlatched the door, seized the keys and crept barefoot down the 
corridor.  The bolts of the cloister-door were stiff and heavy, and 
I dragged at them till the veins in my wrists were bursting.  Then 
I turned the key and it cried out in the ward.  I stood still, my 
whole body beating with fear lest the hinges too should have a 
voice&mdash;but no one stirred, and I pushed open the door and slipped 
out.  The garden was as airless as a pit, but at least I could 
stretch my arms in it; and, oh, my Father, the sweetness of the 
stars!  The stones in the path cut my feet as I ran, but I thought 
of the joy of bathing them in the tank, and that made the wounds 
sweet to me. . . .  My Father, I have heard of the temptations 
which in times past assailed the holy Solitaries of the desert, 
flattering the reluctant <pb n="152"/>  flesh beyond resistance; but none, 
I think, could have surpassed in ecstasy that first touch of the 
water on my limbs.  To prolong the joy I let myself slip in slowly, 
resting my hands on the edge of the tank, and smiling to see my 
body, as I lowered it, break up the shining black surface and 
shatter the starbeams into splinters.  And the water, my Father, 
seemed to crave me as I craved it.  Its ripples rose about me, 
first in furtive touches, then in a long embrace that clung and 
drew me down; till at length they lay like kisses on my lips.  It 
was no frank comrade like the mountain pools of my childhood, but 
a secret playmate compassionating my pains and soothing them with 
noiseless hands.  From the first I thought of it as an accomplice&mdash; 
its whisper seemed to promise me secrecy if I would promise it 
love.  And I went back and back to it, my Father; all day I lived 
in the thought of it; each night I stole to it with fresh thirst. 
. . . 
</p><p>But at length the old portress died, and a young lay-sister 
took her place.  She was a light sleeper, and keen-eared; and I 
knew the danger of venturing to her cell.  I knew the danger, but 
when darkness came I felt the water drawing me.  The first night I 
fought on my bed and held out; but the second I crept to her door.  
She made no motion when I entered, but rose up secretly and stole 
after me; and the second night she warned the Abbess, and the two 
came on me as I stood by the tank. 
</p><p>I was punished with terrible penances: fasting, scourging, 
imprisonment, and the privation of drinking water; for the Abbess 
stood amazed at the obduracy of my sin, and was resolved to make me 
an example to my fellows.  For a month I endured the pains of hell; 
then one night the Saracen pirates fell on our convent.  On a 
sudden the darkness was full of flames and blood; but while the 
other nuns ran hither and thither, clinging to the Abbess's feet or 
shrieking on the steps of the altar, I slipped through an unwatched 
postern and made my way to the hills.  The next day the Emperor's 
soldiery descended on the carousing heathen, slew them and burned 
their vessels on the beach; the Abbess and nuns were rescued, the 
convent walls rebuilt, and peace restored to the holy precincts.  
All this I heard from a shepherdess of the hills, who found me in 
my hiding, and brought me honeycomb and water.  In her simplicity 
she offered to lead me home to the convent; but while she slept I 
laid off my wimple and scapular, and stealing her cloak fled away 
lest she should betray me.  And since then I have wandered alone 
over the face of the world, living in woods and desert places, 
often hungry, often cold and sometimes fearful; yet resigned to any 
hardship, and with a front for any peril, if only I may sleep under 
the free heaven and wash the dust from my body in cool water. 


</p><p>                            V 

</p><p>THE Hermit, as may be supposed, was much perturbed by this 
story, and dismayed that such sinfulness should cross his path.  
His first motion was to drive the woman forth, for he knew the 
heinousness of the craving for water, and how Saint Jerome, Saint 
Augustine and other holy doctors have taught that they who would 
purify the soul must not be distraught by the vain cares of bodily 
cleanliness; yet, remembering the lust that drew him to his lauds, 
he dared not judge his sister's fault too harshly. 
</p><p>Moreover he was moved by the Wild Woman's story of the 
hardships she had suffered, and the godless company she had been 
driven to keep&mdash;Egyptians, jugglers, outlaws and even sorcerers, 
who are masters of the pagan lore of the East, and still practice 
their dark rites among the simple folk of the hills.  Yet she would 
not have him think wholly ill of this vagrant people, from whom she 
had often received food and comfort; and her worst danger, as he 
learned with shame, had come from the <hi rend="italic"> girovaghi</hi> or wandering 
monks, who are the scourge and dishonour of Christendom; carrying 
their ribald idleness from one monastery to another, and leaving on 
their way a trail of thieving, revelry and worse.  Once or twice 
the Wild Woman had nearly fallen into their hands; but had been 
saved by her own quick wit and skill in woodcraft.  Once, so she 
assured the Hermit, she had found refuge with a faun and his 
female, who fed and sheltered her in their cave, where she slept on 
a bed of leaves with their shaggy nurslings; and in this cave she 
had seen a stock or idol of wood, extremely seamed and ancient, 
before which the wood-creatures, when they <pb n="153"/>  thought she 
slept, laid garlands and the wild bees' honey-comb. 
</p><p>She told him also of a hill-village of weavers, where she 
lived many weeks, and learned to ply their trade in return for her 
lodging; and where wayfaring men in the guise of cobblers, 
charcoal-burners or goatherds came and taught strange doctrines at 
midnight in the poor hovels.  What they taught she could not 
clearly tell, save that they believed each soul could commune 
directly with its Maker, without need of priest or intercessor; 
also she had heard from some of their disciples that there are two 
Gods, one of good and one of evil, and that the God of evil has his 
throne in the Pope's palace in Rome.  But in spite of these dark 
teachings they were a mild and merciful folk, full of loving-kindness toward poor persons and wayfarers; so that her heart 
grieved for them when one day a Dominican monk appeared in the 
village with a company of soldiers, and some of the weavers were 
seized and dragged to prison, while others, with their wives and 
babes, fled to the winter woods.  She fled with them, fearing to be 
charged with their heresy, and for months they lay hid in desert 
places, the older and weaker, who fell sick from want and exposure, 
being devoutly ministered to by their brethren, and dying in the 
sure faith of heaven. 
</p><p>All this she related modestly and simply, not as one who joys 
in a godless life, but as having been drawn into it through 
misadventure; and she told the Hermit that when she heard the sound 
of church bells she never failed to say an Ave or a Pater; and that 
often, as she lay in the midnight darkness of the forest, she had 
hushed her fears by reciting the versicles from the Evening Hour: 
</p><p>Keep us, O Lord, as the apple of the eye, 
</p><p>Protect us under the shadow of Thy wings. 
</p><p>The wound in her foot healed slowly; and the Hermit, while it 
was mending, repaired daily to her cave, reasoning with her in love 
and charity, and exhorting her to return to the cloister.  But this 
she persistently refused to do; and fearing lest she attempt to fly 
before her foot was healed, and so expose herself to hunger and 
ill-usage, he promised not to betray her presence, or to take any 
measures toward restoring her to her Order. 
</p><p>He began indeed to doubt whether she had any calling to the 
life enclosed; yet her gentleness and innocency of mind made him 
feel that she might be won back to holy living, if only her freedom 
were assured.  So after many inward struggles (since his promise 
forbade his taking counsel with any concerning her) he resolved to 
let her remain in the cave till some light should come to him.  And 
one day, visiting her about the hour of Nones (for it became his 
pious habit to say the evening office with her), he found her 
engaged with a little goatherd, who in a sudden seizure had fallen 
from a rock above her cave, and lay senseless and full of blood at 
her feet.  And the Hermit saw with wonder how skilfully she bound 
up his cuts and restored his senses, giving him to drink of a 
liquor she had distilled from the wild simples of the mountain; 
whereat the boy opened his eyes and praised God, as one restored by 
heaven.  Now it was known that this lad was subject to possessions, 
and had more than once dropped lifeless while he heeded his flock; 
and the Hermit, knowing that only great saints or unclean 
necromancers can loosen devils, feared that the Wild Woman had 
exorcised the spirits by means of unholy spells.  But she told him 
that the goatherd's sickness was caused only by the heat of the 
sun, and that, such seizures being common in the hot countries 
whence she came, she had learned from a wise woman how to stay them 
by a decoction of the <hi rend="italic"> carduus benedictus</hi>, made in the third 
night of the waxing moon, but without the aid of magic. 
</p><p>"But," she continued, "you need not fear my bringing scandal 
on your holy retreat, for by the arts of the same wise woman my own 
wound is well-nigh healed, and tonight at sunset I set forth on my 
travels." 
</p><p>The Hermit's heart grew heavy as she spoke, and it seemed to 
him that her own look was sorrowful.  And suddenly his perplexities 
were lifted from him, and he saw what was God's purpose with the 
Wild Woman. 
</p><p>"Why," said he, "do you fly from this place, where you are 
safe from molestation, and can look to the saving of your soul?  Is 
it that your feet weary for the road, and your spirits are heavy 
for lack of worldly discourse?" 
</p><p>She replied that she had no wish to travel, and felt no 
repugnance to solitude.  "But," said she, "I must go forth to beg 
my bread, since in this wilderness there is <pb n="154"/>  none but 
yourself to feed me; and moreover, when it is known that I have 
healed the goatherd, curious folk and scandal-mongers may seek me 
out, and, learning whence I come, drag me back to the cloister." 
</p><p>Then the Hermit answered her and said: "In the early days, 
when the faith of Christ was first preached, there were holy women 
who fled to the desert and lived there in solitude, to the glory of 
God and the edification of their sex.  If you are minded to embrace 
so austere a life, contenting you with such sustenance as the 
wilderness yields, and wearing out your days in prayer and vigil, 
it may be that you shall make amends for the great sin you have 
committed, and live and die in the peace of the Lord Jesus." 
</p><p>He spoke thus, knowing that if she left him and returned to 
her roaming, hunger and fear might drive her to fresh sin; whereas 
in a life of penance and reclusion her eyes might be opened to her 
iniquity, and her soul snatched back from ruin. 
</p><p>He saw that his words moved her, and she seemed about to 
consent, and embrace a life of holiness; but suddenly she fell 
silent, and looked down on the valley at their feet. 
</p><p>"A stream flows in the glen below us," she said.  "Do you 
forbid me to bathe in it in the heat of summer?" 
</p><p>"It is not I that forbid you, my daughter, but the laws of 
God," said the Hermit; "yet see how miraculously heaven protects 
you&mdash;for in the hot season, when your lust is upon you, our stream 
runs dry, and temptation will be removed from you.  Moreover on 
these heights there is no excess of heat to madden the body, but 
always, before dawn and at the angelus, a cool breeze which 
refreshes it like water." 
</p><p>And after thinking long on this, and again receiving his 
promise not to betray her, the Wild Woman agreed to embrace a life 
of reclusion; and the Hermit fell on his knees, worshipping God and 
rejoicing to think that, if he saved his sister from sin, his own 
term of probation would be shortened. 


</p><p>                           VI 

</p><p>THEREAFTER for two years the Hermit and the Wild Woman lived 
side by side, meeting together to pray on the great feast-days of 
the year, but on all other days dwelling apart, engaged in pious 
practices. 
</p><p>At first the Hermit, knowing the weakness of woman, and her 
little aptitude for the life apart, had feared that he might be 
disturbed by the nearness of his penitent; but she faithfully held 
to his commands, abstaining from all sight of him save on the Days 
of Obligation; and when they met, so modest and devout was her 
demeanour that she raised his soul to fresh fervency.  And 
gradually it grew sweet to him to think that, near by though 
unseen, was one who performed the same tasks at the same hours; so 
that, whether he tended his garden, or recited his chaplet, or rose 
under the stars to repeat the midnight office, he had a companion 
in all his labours and devotions. 
</p><p>Meanwhile the report had spread abroad that a holy woman who 
cast out devils had made her dwelling in the Hermit's cliff; and 
many sick persons from the valley sought her out, and went away 
restored by her.  These poor pilgrims brought her oil and flour, 
and with her own hands she made a garden like the Hermit's, and 
planted it with corn and lentils; but she would never take a trout 
from the brook, or receive the gift of a snared wild-fowl, for she 
said that in her vagrant life the wild creatures of the wood had 
befriended her, and as she had slept in peace among them, so now 
she would never suffer them to be molested. 
</p><p>In the third year came a plague, and death walked the cities, 
and many poor peasants fled to the hills to escape it.  These the 
Hermit and his penitent faithfully tended, and so skilful were the 
Wild Woman's ministrations that the report of them reached the town 
across the valley, and a deputation of burgesses came with rich 
offerings, and besought her to descend and comfort their sick.  The 
Hermit, seeing her depart on so dangerous a mission, would have 
accompanied her, but she bade him remain and tend those who fled to 
the hills; and for many days his heart was consumed in prayer for 
her, and he feared lest every fugitive should bring him word of her 
death. 
</p><p>But at length she returned, wearied-out but whole, and covered 
with the blessings of the townsfolk; and thereafter her name for 
holiness spread as wide as the Hermit's. 
</p><p>Seeing how constant she remained in her chosen life, and what 
advance she had made in the way of perfection, the Hermit now felt 
that it behoved him to exhort her again to return to the convent; 
and more <pb n="155"/>  than once he resolved to speak with her, but his 
heart hung back.  At length he bethought him that by failing in 
this duty he imperilled his own soul, and thereupon, on the next 
feast-day, when they met, he reminded her that in spite of her good 
works she still lived in sin and excommunicate, and that, now she 
had once more tasted the sweets of godliness, it was her duty to 
confess her fault and give herself up to her superiors. 
</p><p>She heard him meekly, but when he had spoken she was silent 
and her tears ran over; and looking at her he wept also, and said 
no more.  And they prayed together, and returned each to his cave. 
</p><p>It was not till late winter that the plague abated; and the 
spring and early summer following were heavy with rains and great 
heat.  When the Hermit visited his penitent at the feast of 
Pentecost, she appeared to him so weak and wasted that, when they 
had recited the <hi rend="italic"> Veni, sancte spiritus</hi>, and the proper psalms, 
he taxed her with too great rigour of penitential practices; but 
she replied that her weakness was not due to an excess of 
discipline, but that she had brought back from her labours among 
the sick a heaviness of body which the intemperance of the season 
no doubt increased.  The evil rains continued, falling chiefly at 
night, while by day the land reeked with heat and vapours; so that 
lassitude fell on the Hermit also, and he could hardly drag himself 
down to the spring whence he drew his drinking-water.  Thus he fell 
into the habit of going down to the glen before cockcrow, after he 
had recited Matins; for at that hour the rain commonly ceased, and 
a faint air was stirring.  Now because of the wet season the stream 
had not gone dry, and instead of replenishing his flagon slowly at 
the trickling spring, the Hermit went down to the waterside to fill 
it; and once, as he descended the steep slope of the glen, he heard 
the covert rustle, and saw the leaves stir as though something 
moved behind them.  As he looked silence fell, and the leaves grew 
still; but his heart was shaken, for it seemed to him that what he 
had seen in the dusk had a human semblance, such as the wood-people 
wear.  And he was loth to think that such unhallowed beings haunted 
the glen. 
</p><p>A few days passed, and again, descending to the stream, he saw 
a figure flit by him through the covert; and this time a deeper 
fear entered into him; but he put away the thought, and prayed 
fervently for all souls in temptation.  And when he spoke with the 
Wild Woman again, on the feast of the Seven Maccabees, which falls 
on the first day of August, he was smitten with fear to see her 
wasted looks, and besought her to cease from labouring and let him 
minister to her in her weakness.  But she denied him gently, and 
replied that all she asked of him was to keep her steadfastly in 
his prayers. 
</p><p>Before the feast of the Assumption the rains ceased, and the 
plague, which had begun to show itself, was stayed; but the ardency 
of the sun grew greater, and the Hermit's cliff was a fiery 
furnace.  Never had such heat been known in those regions; but the 
people did not murmur, for with the cessation of the rain their 
crops were saved and the pestilence banished; and these mercies 
they ascribed in great part to the prayers and macerations of the 
two holy anchorets.  Therefore on the eve of the Assumption they 
sent a messenger to the Hermit, saying that at daylight on the 
morrow the townspeople and all the dwellers in the valley would 
come forth, led by their Bishop, who bore the Pope's blessing to 
the two solitaries, and who was mindful to celebrate the Mass of 
the Assumption in the Hermit's cave in the cliffside.  At the 
blessed word the Hermit was well-nigh distraught with joy, for he 
felt this to be a sign from heaven that his prayers were heard, and 
that he had won the Wild Woman's grace as well as his own.  And all 
night he prayed that on the morrow she might confess her fault and 
receive the Sacrament with him. 
</p><p>Before dawn he recited the psalms of the proper nocturn; then 
he girded on his gown and sandals, and went forth to meet the 
Bishop in the valley. 
</p><p>As he went downward daylight stood on the mountains, and he 
thought he had never seen so fair a dawn.  It filled the farthest 
heaven with brightness, and penetrated even to the woody crevices 
of the glen, as the grace of God had entered into the obscurest 
folds of his heart.  The morning airs were hushed, and he heard 
only the sound of his own footfall, and the murmur of the stream 
which, though diminished, still poured a swift current between the 
rocks; but as he reached the bottom of the <pb n="156"/>  glen a sound of 
chanting came to him, and he knew that the pilgrims were at hand.  
His heart leapt up and his feet hastened forward; but at the 
streamside they were suddenly stayed, for in a pool where the water 
was still deep he saw the shining of a woman's body&mdash;and on a stone 
hard by lay the Wild Woman's gown and sandals. 
</p><p>Fear and rage possessed the Hermit's heart, and he stood as 
one smitten speechless, covering his eyes from the shame.  But the 
song of the approaching pilgrims swelled ever louder and nearer, 
and finding voice he cried to the Wild Woman to come forth and hide 
herself from the people. 
</p><p>She made no answer, but in the dusk he saw her limbs sway with 
the swaying of the water, and her eyes were turned to him as if in 
mockery.  At the sight blind fury filled him, and clambering over 
the rocks to the pool's edge he bent down and caught her by the 
shoulder.  At that moment he could have strangled her with his 
hands, so abhorrent to him was the touch of her flesh; but as he 
cried out on her, heaping her with cruel names, he saw that her 
eyes returned his look without wavering; and suddenly it came to 
him that she was dead.  Then through all his anger and fear a great 
pang smote him; for here was his work undone, and one he had loved 
in Christ laid low in her sin, in spite of all his labours. 
</p><p>One moment pity possessed him; the next he bethought him how 
the people would find him bending above the body of a naked woman, 
whom he had held up to them as holy, but whom they might now well 
take for the secret instrument of his undoing; and beholding how at 
her touch all the slow edifice of his holiness was demolished, and 
his soul in mortal jeopardy, he felt the earth reel round him and 
his sight grew red. 
</p><p>Already the head of the procession had entered the glen, and 
the stillness shook with the great sound of the <hi rend="italic"> Salve Regina</hi>.  
When the Hermit opened his eyes once more the air was quivering 
with thronged candle-flames, which glittered on the gold thread of 
priestly vestments, and on the blazing monstrance beneath its 
canopy; and close above him was bent the Bishop's face. 
</p><p>The Hermit struggled to his knees. 
</p><p>"My Father in God," he cried, "behold, for my sins I have been 
visited by a demon&mdash;"  But as he spoke he perceived that those 
about him no longer heeded him, and that the Bishop and all his 
clergy had fallen on their knees about the pool.  Then the Hermit, 
following their gaze, saw that the brown waters of the pool covered 
the Wild Woman's limbs as with a garment, and that about her 
floating head a great light floated; and to the utmost edges of the 
throng a cry of praise went up, for many were there whom the Wild 
Woman had healed and comforted, and who read God's mercy in this 
wonder.  But fresh fear fell on the Hermit, for he had cursed a 
dying saint, and denounced her aloud to all the people; and this 
new anguish, coming so close upon the other, smote down his 
weakened frame, so that his limbs failed him and he sank once more 
to the ground. 
</p><p>Again the earth reeled about him, and the bending faces grew 
remote; but as he forced his weak voice once more to proclaim his 
sins he felt the blessed touch of absolution, and the holy oils of 
the last voyage laid on his lips and eyes.  Peace returned to him 
then, and with it a great longing to look once more upon his lauds, 
as he had dreamed of doing at his last hour; but he was too far 
gone to make this longing known, and so tried to banish it from his 
mind.  Yet in his weakness the wish held him, and the tears ran 
down his face. 
</p><p>Then, as he lay there, feeling the earth slip from under him, 
and the Everlasting Arms replace it, he heard a great peal of 
voices that seemed to come down from the sky and mingle with the 
singing of the throng; and the words of the chant were the words of 
his own lauds, so long hidden in the secret of his breast, and now 
rejoicing above him through the spheres.  And his soul rose on the 
chant, and soared with it to the seat of mercy. 
</p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
