<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WilSavi"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
 
<TEI.2 id="WilSavi"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Lord Arthur Savile's Crime</title>
<title type="sort">lord arthur saviles crime</title>
<author>Wilde, Oscar</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">76</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WilSavi</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476554</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">From The Picture of Dorian Gray and Selected Stories</title>
<title type="sort">from the picture of dorian gray and selected stories</title>
<author>Oscar Wilde</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Signet Classic; New American Library of World Literature,   
Inc.</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1962">1962</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Lord Arthur Savile's Crime from Lord Arthur Savile's 
Crime and Other Stories, Methuen &amp; Co., 1909</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Spell-check and verification made 
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions 
for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1909">1909</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction, prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-07">July 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Lorrie S. Chisholm, Electronic Text Center, University of 
Virginia Library System.</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Updated header</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="1994-02">February 1994</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>minimal TEI tagging; unambiguous line-end hyphenation removed; 
spellchecked</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1">  
 
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="1" id="d3"> 
<pb n="264"/>  
<head>Lord Arthur Savile's Crime</head> 
 
<p>IT was Lady Windermere's last reception before Easter, 
and Bentinck House was even more crowded than 
usual.  Six cabinet ministers had come on from the Speaker's 
Levee in their stars and ribands, all the pretty 
women wore their smartest dresses, and at the end of the 
picture-gallery stood the Princess Sophia of Carlsruhe, a 
heavy Tartar-looking lady, with tiny black eyes and wonderful 
emeralds, talking bad French at the top of her 
voice and laughing immoderately at everything that was 
said to her.  It was certainly a wonderful medley of people.  
Gorgeous peeresses chattered affably to violent Radicals, 
popular preachers brushed coat-tails with eminent sceptics, 
a perfect bevy of bishops kept following a stout prima 
donna from room to room, on the staircase stood several 
royal academicians, disguised as artists, and it was said 
that at one time the supper-room was absolutely crammed 
with geniuses.  In fact, it was one of Lady Windermere's 
best nights, and the Princess stayed till nearly half-past 
eleven. 
</p><p>As soon as she had gone, Lady Windermere returned 
to the picture-gallery, where a celebrated political economist 
was solemnly explaining the scientific theory of music 
to an indignant virtuoso from Hungary, and began to talk 
to the Duchess of Paisley.  She looked wonderfully beautiful 
with her grand ivory throat, her large, blue, forget-me-not eyes, and her heavy coils of golden hair.  Or pur 
they were &mdash; not that pale straw colour that nowadays 
<pb n="265"/>  
usurps the gracious name of gold, but such gold as is 
woven into sunbeams or hidden in strange amber &mdash;  
and they gave to her face something of the frame of a 
saint, with not a little of the fascination of a sinner.  She 
was a curious psychological study.  Early in life she had 
discovered the important truth that nothing looks so like 
innocence as an indiscretion, and by a series of reckless 
escapades, half of them quite harmless, she had acquired 
all the privileges of a personality.  She had more than once 
changed her husband &mdash; indeed, Debrett credits her with 
three marriages &mdash; but as she had never changed her lover, 
the world had long ago ceased to talk scandal about her.  
She was now forty years of age, childless, and with that 
inordinate passion for pleasure which is the secret of remaining 
young. 
</p><p>Suddenly she looked eagerly round the room, and said, 
in her clear contralto voice, "Where is my cheiromantist?" 
</p><p>"Your what, Gladys?" exclaimed the duchess, giving an 
involuntary start. 
</p><p>"My cheiromantist, Duchess; I can't live without him 
at present." 
</p><p>"Dear Gladys! you are always so original," murmured 
the duchess, trying to remember what a cheiromantist 
really was, and hoping it was not the same as a cheiropodist. 
</p><p>"He comes to see my hand twice a week regularly," 
continued Lady Windermere, "and is most interesting 
about it." 
</p><p>"Good heavens!" said the duchess to herself, "he is a 
sort of cheiropodist after all.  How very dreadful.  I hope 
he is a foreigner at any rate.  It wouldn't be quite so bad 
then." 
</p><p>"I must certainly introduce him to you." 
</p><p>"Introduce him!" cried the duchess; "you don't mean 
to say he is here?" and she began looking about for a 
small tortoise-shell fan and a very tattered lace shawl, so 
as to be ready to go at a moment's notice. 
</p><p>"Of course he is here; I would not dream of giving a 
party without him.  He tells me I have a pure psychic 
hand, and that if my thumb had been the least little 
<pb n="266"/>  
bit shorter, I should have been a confirmed pessimist and 
gone into a convent." 
</p><p>"Oh, I see!" said the duchess, feeling very much relieved; 
"he tells fortunes, I suppose?" 
</p><p>"And misfortunes, too," answered Lady Windermere; 
"any amount of them.  Next year, for instance, I am in 
great danger, both by land and sea, so I am going to live 
in a balloon and draw up my dinner in a basket every 
evening.  It is all written down on my little finger, or on 
the palm of my hand &mdash; I forget which" 
</p><p>"But surely that is tempting Providence, Gladys." 
</p><p>"My dear Duchess, surely Providence can resist temptation 
by this time.  I think every one should have their 
hands told once a month, so as to know what not to do.  
Of course, one does it all the same, but it is so pleasant 
to be warned.  Now, if some one doesn't go and fetch 
Mr. Podgers at once, I shall have to go myself." 
</p><p>"Let me go, Lady Windermere," said a tall, handsome 
young man who was standing by, listening to the conversation 
with an amused smile. 
</p><p>"Thanks so much, Lord Arthur; but I am afraid you 
wouldn't recognize him." 
</p><p>"If he is as wonderful as you say, Lady Windermere, 
I couldn't well miss him.  Tell me what he is like, and I'll 
bring him to you at once." 
</p><p>"Well, he is not a bit like a cheiromantist.  I mean be is 
not mysterious, or esoteric, or romantic-looking.  He is 
a little, stout man, with a funny bald head, and great 
gold-rimmed spectacles &mdash; something between a family doctor 
and a country attorney.  I'm really very sorry, but it 
is not my fault.  People are so annoying.  All my pianists 
look exactly like poets, and all my poets look exactly like 
pianists; and I remember last season asking a most dreadful 
conspirator to dinner, a man who had blown up ever 
so many people, and always wore a coat of mail, and 
carried a dagger up his shirt-sleeve; and do you know that 
when he came he looked just like a nice old clergyman, 
and cracked jokes all the evening? Of course, he was 
very amusing and all that, but I was awfully disappointed; 
and when I asked him about the coat of mail, he only 
laughed and said it was far too cold to wear in England.  
Ah, here is Mr. Podgers! Now, Mr. Podgers, I want you 
<pb n="267"/>  
to tell the Duchess of Paisley's hand.  Duchess, you must 
take your glove off.  No, not the left hand, the other." 
</p><p>"Dear Gladys, I really don't think it is quite right," said 
the duchess, feebly unbuttoning a rather soiled kid glove. 
</p><p>"Nothing interesting ever is," said Lady Windermere: 
"on a fait le monde ainsi.  But I must introduce you.  Duchess, 
this is Mr. Podgers, my pet cheiromantist.  Mr. Podgers, 
this is the Duchess of Paisley, and if you say that 
she has a larger mountain of the moon than I have, I 
will never believe in you again." 
</p><p>"I am sure, Gladys, there is nothing of the kind in 
my hand," said the duchess gravely. 
</p><p>"Your Grace is quite right," said Mr. Podgers, glancing 
at the little fat hand with its short square fingers, 
"the mountain of the moon is not developed.  The line of 
life, however, is excellent.  Kindly bend the wrist.  Thank 
you.  Three distinct lines on the rascette! You will live to 
a great age, Duchess, and be extremely happy.  Ambition 
 &mdash; very moderate, line of intellect not exaggerated, line 
of heart &mdash; " 
</p><p>"Now, do be indiscreet, Mr. Podgers," cried Lady 
Windermere. 
</p><p>"Nothing would give me greater pleasure," said Mr. 
Podgers, bowing, "if the duchess ever had been, but I am 
sorry to say that I see great permanence of affection, combined 
with a strong sense of duty." 
</p><p>"Pray go on, Mr. Podgers," said the duchess, looking 
quite pleased. 
</p><p>"Economy is not the least of your Grace's virtues," continued 
Mr. Podgers, and Lady Windermere went off into 
fits of laughter. 
</p><p>"Economy is a very good thing," remarked the duchess 
complacently; "when I married Paisley, he had eleven 
castles and not a single house fit to live in." 
</p><p>"And now he has twelve houses and not a single castle," 
cried Lady Windermere. 
</p><p>"Well, my dear," said the Duchess, "I like &mdash; " 
</p><p>"Comfort," said Mr. Podgers, "and modern improvements, 
and hot water laid on in every bedroom.  Your 
Grace is quite right.  Comfort is the only thing our civilization 
can give us." 
</p><p>"You have told the duchess's character admirably, 
<pb n="268"/>  
Mr. Podgers, and now you must tell Lady Flora's"; and 
in answer to a nod from the smiling hostess, a tall girl, 
with sandy Scotch hair and high shoulder-blades, stepped 
awkwardly from behind the sofa and held out a long 
bony hand with spatulate fingers. 
</p><p>"Ah, a pianist! I see," said Mr. Podgers, "an excellent 
pianist, but perhaps hardly a musician.  Very reserved, 
very honest, and with a great love of animals." 
</p><p>"Quite true!" exclaimed the duchess, turning to Lady 
Windermere, "absolutely true! Flora keeps two dozen collie 
dogs at Macloskie, and would turn our town house 
into a menagerie if her father would let her." 
</p><p>"Well, that is just what I do with my house every Thursday 
evening," cried Lady Windermere, laughing, "only I 
like lions better than collie dogs." 
</p><p>"Your one mistake, Lady Windermere," said Mr. Podgers, 
with a pompous bow. 
</p><p>"If a woman can't make her mistakes charming, she is 
only a female," was the answer.  "But you must read some 
more hands for us.  Come, Sir Thomas, show Mr. Podgers 
yours"; and a genial-looking old gentleman, in a white 
waistcoat, came forward and held out a thick rugged 
hand with a very long third finger. 
</p><p>"An adventurous nature; four long voyages in the past, 
and one to come.  Been shipwrecked three times.  No, 
only twice, but in danger of a shipwreck your next journey. 
A strong Conservative, very punctual, and with a 
passion for collecting curiosities.  Had a severe illness between 
the ages of sixteen and eighteen.  Was left a fortune 
when about thirty.  Great aversion to cats and Radicals." 
</p><p>"Extraordinary!" exclaimed Sir Thomas; "you must 
really tell my wife's hand, too." 
</p><p>"Your second wife's," said Mr. Podgers quietly, still 
keeping Sir Thomas's hand in his.  "Your second wife's.  I 
shall be charmed"; but Lady Marvel, a melancholy-looking 
woman, with brown hair and sentimental eyelashes, entirely 
declined to have her past or her future exposed; 
and nothing that Lady Windermere could do would induce 
Monsieur de Koloff, the Russian ambassador, even 
to take his gloves off.  In fact, many people seemed afraid 
to face the odd little man with his stereotyped smile, 
<pb n="269"/>  
his gold spectacles, and his bright beady eyes; and when 
he told poor Lady Fermor, right out before every one, 
that she did not care a bit for music, but was extremely 
fond of musicians, it was generally felt that cheiromancy 
was a most dangerous science, and one that ought not to 
be encouraged, except in a tete-a-tete. 
</p><p>Lord Arthur Savile, however, who did not know anything 
about Lady Fermor's unfortunate story, and who 
had been watching Mr. Podgers with a great deal of interest, 
was filled with an immense curiosity to have his 
own hand read, and feeling somewhat shy about putting 
himself forward, crossed over the room to where Lady 
Windermere was sitting and, with a charming blush, 
asked her if she thought Mr. Podgers would mind. 
</p><p>"Of course he won't mind," said Lady Windermere; 
"that is what he is here for.  All my lions, Lord Arthur, 
are performing lions, and jump through hoops whenever 
I ask them.  But I must warn you beforehand that 
I shall tell Sybil everything.  She is coming to lunch with 
me to-morrow to talk about bonnets, and if Mr. Podgers 
finds out that you have a bad temper, or a tendency to 
gout, or a wife living in Bayswater, I shall certainly let 
her know all about it." 
</p><p>Lord Arthur smiled and shook his head.  "I am not 
afraid," he answered.  "Sybil knows me as well as I know 
her." 
</p><p>"Ah! I am a little sorry to hear you say that.  The 
proper basis for marriage is a mutual misunderstanding.  
No, I am not at all cynical, I have merely got experience, 
which, however, is very much the same thing.  Mr. Podgers, 
Lord Arthur Savile is dying to have his hand read.  Don't 
tell him that he is engaged to one of the most beautiful 
girls in London, because that appeared in the Morning 
Post a month ago." 
</p><p>"Dear Lady Windermere," cried the Marchioness of 
Jedburgh, "do let Mr. Podgers stay here a little longer.  
He has just told me I should go on the stage, and I am 
so interested." 
</p><p>"If he has told you that, Lady Jedburgh, I shall certainly 
take him away.  Come over at once, Mr. Podgers, 
and read Lord Arthur's hand." 
</p><p>"Well," said Lady Jedburgh, making a little moue as 
<pb n="270"/>  
she rose from the sofa, "if I am not to be allowed to go 
on the stage, I must be allowed to be part of the audience 
at any rate." 
</p><p>"Of course; we are all going to be part of the audience," 
said Lady Windermere; "and now, Mr. Podgers, be sure 
and tell us something nice.  Lord Arthur is one of my 
special favourites." 
</p><p>But when Mr. Podgers saw Lord Arthur's hand, he 
grew curiously pale and said nothing.  A shudder seemed 
to pass through him, and his great bushy eyebrows 
twitched convulsively, in an odd, irritating way they had 
when he was puzzled.  Then some huge beads of perspiration 
broke out on his yellow forehead, like a poisonous 
dew, and his fat fingers grew cold and clammy. 
</p><p>Lord Arthur did not fail to notice these strange signs 
of agitation, and, for the first time in his life, he himself 
felt fear.  His impulse was to rush from the room, but 
he restrained himself.  It was better to know the worst, 
whatever it was, than to be left in this hideous uncertainty. 
</p><p>"I am waiting, Mr. Podgers," he said. 
</p><p>"We are all waiting," cried Lady Windermere, in her 
quick impatient manner, but the cheiromantist made no 
reply. 
</p><p>"I believe Arthur is going on the stage," said Lady 
Jedburgh, "and that, after your scolding, Mr. Podgers 
is afraid to tell him so." 
</p><p>Suddenly Mr. Podgers dropped Lord Arthur's right 
hand and seized hold of his left, bending down so low 
to examine it that the gold rims of his spectacles seemed 
almost to touch the palm.  For a moment his face became 
a white mask of horror, but he soon recovered his sang-froid and, looking up at Lady Windermere, said with a 
forced smile, "It is the hand of a charming young man." 
</p><p>"Of course it is!" answered Lady Windermere, "but will 
he be a charming husband? That is what I want to know." 
</p><p>"All charming young men are," said Mr. Podgers. 
</p><p>"I don't think a husband should be too fascinating," 
murmured Lady Jedburgh pensively; "it is so dangerous." 
</p><p>"My dear child, they never are too fascinating," cried 
Lady Windermere.  "But what I want are details.  Details 
<pb n="271"/>  
are the only things that interest.  What is going to happen 
to Lord Arthur?" 
</p><p>"Well, within the next few months Lord Arthur will 
go on a voyage &mdash; " 
</p><p>"Oh yes, his honeymoon, of course!" 
</p><p>"And lose a relative." 
</p><p>"Not his sister, I hope?" said Lady Jedburgh, in a piteous 
tone of voice. 
</p><p>"Certainly not his sister," answered Mr. Podgers, with 
a deprecating wave of the hand, "a distant relative 
merely." 
</p><p>"Well, I am dreadfully disappointed," said Lady Windermere. 
"I have absolutely nothing to tell Sybil tomorrow. 
No one cares about distant relatives nowadays.  They 
went out of fashion years ago.  However, I suppose she had 
better have a black silk by her; it always does for church, 
you know.  And now let us go to supper.  They are sure 
to have eaten everything up, but we may find some hot 
soup.  Francois used to make excellent soup once but 
he is so agitated about politics at present that I never 
feel quite certain about him.  I do wish General Boulanger 
would keep quiet.  Duchess, I am sure you are 
tired?" 
</p><p>"Not at all, dear Gladys," answered the duchess, waddling 
towards the door.  "I have enjoyed myself immensely, 
and the cheiropodist &mdash; I mean the cheiromantist &mdash; is most 
interesting.  Flora, where can my tortoise-shell fan be? 
Oh, thank you, Sir Thomas, so much.  And my lace shawl, 
Flora? Oh, thank you, Sir Thomas, very kind, I'm sure"; 
and the worthy creature finally managed to get downstairs 
without dropping her scent-bottle more than twice. 
</p><p>All this time Lord Arthur Savile had remained standing 
by the fire-place, with the same feeling of dread over 
him, the same sickening sense of coming evil.  He smiled 
sadly at his sister as she swept past him on Lord Plymdale's 
arm, looking lovely in her pink brocade and pearls, 
and he hardly heard Lady Windermere when she called 
to him to follow her.  He thought of Sybil Merton, and the 
idea that anything could come between them made his 
eyes dim with tears. 
</p><p>Looking at him, one would have said that Nemesis had 
<pb n="272"/>  
stolen the shield of Pallas and shown him the Gorgon's 
head.  He seemed turned to stone, and his face was like 
marble in its melancholy.  He had lived the delicate and 
luxurious life of a young man of birth and fortune, a 
life exquisite in its freedom from sordid care, its beautiful 
boyish insouciance, and now for the first time he became 
conscious of the terrible mystery of destiny, of the 
awful meaning of doom. 
</p><p>How mad and monstrous it all seemed! Could it be that 
written on his hand, in characters that he could not read 
himself, but that another could decipher, was some fearful 
secret of sin, some blood-red sign of crime? Was there 
no escape possible? Were we no better than chessmen, 
moved by an unseen power, vessels the potter fashions 
at his fancy, for honour or for shame? His reason revolted 
against it, and yet he felt that some tragedy was hanging 
over him, and that he had been suddenly called upon 
to bear an intolerable burden.  Actors are so fortunate.  
They can choose whether they will appear in tragedy or 
in comedy, whether they will suffer or make merry, laugh 
or shed tears.  But in real life it is different.  Most men 
and women are forced to perform parts for which they 
have no qualifications.  Our Guildensterns play Hamlet for 
us, and our Hamlets have to jest like Prince Hal.  The 
world is a stage, but the play is badly cast. 
</p><p>Suddenly Mr. Podgers entered the room.  When he saw 
Lord Arthur, he started, and his coarse fat face became 
a sort of greenish-yellow colour.  The two men's eyes met, 
and for a moment there was silence. 
</p><p>"The duchess has left one of her gloves here, Lord 
Arthur, and has asked me to bring it to her," said Mr. 
Podgers finally.  "Ah, I see it on the sofa! Good evening." 
</p><p>"Mr. Podgers, I must insist on your giving me a straight-forward answer to a question I am going to put to you." 
</p><p>"Another time, Lord Arthur, but the duchess is anxious. 
I am afraid I must go." 
</p><p>"You shall not go.  The duchess is in no hurry." 
</p><p>"Ladies should not be kept waiting, Lord Arthur," said 
Mr. Podgers, with his sickly smile.  "The fair sex is apt 
to be impatient." 
</p><p>Lord Arthur's finely chiselled lips curled in petulant 
<pb n="273"/>  
disdain.  The poor duchess seemed to him of very little 
importance at that moment.  He walked across the room 
to where Mr. Podgers was standing, and held his hand out. 
</p><p>"Tell me what you saw there," he said.  "Tell me the 
truth.  I must know it.  I am not a child." 
</p><p>Mr. Podgers's eyes blinked behind his gold-rimmed spectacles, 
and he moved uneasily from one foot to the other, 
while his fingers played nervously with a flash watch-chain. 
</p><p>"What makes you think that I saw anything in your 
hand, Lord Arthur, more than I told you?" 
</p><p>"I know you did, and I insist on your telling me what 
it was.  I will pay you.  I will give you a cheque for a 
hundred pounds." 
</p><p>The green eyes flashed for a moment, and then became 
dull again. 
</p><p>"Guineas?" said Mr. Podgers at last, in a low voice. 
</p><p>"Certainly.  I will send you a cheque to-morrow.  What 
is your club?" 
</p><p>"I have no club.  That is to say, not just at present.  
My address is &mdash; but allow me to give you my card"; and 
producing a bit of gilt-edge pasteboard from his waistcoat 
pocket, Mr. Podgers handed it, with a low bow, to 
Lord Arthur, who read on it 
     Mr. SEPTIMUS R. PODGERS<lb/> 
    Professional Cheiromantist<lb/> 
      103a West Moon Street<lb/> 
</p><p>"My hours are from ten to four," murmured Mr. Podgers 
mechanically, "and I make a reduction for families." 
</p><p>"Be quick," cried Lord Arthur, looking very pale and 
holding his hand out. 
</p><p>Mr. Podgers glanced nervously round and drew the 
heavy partiere across the door. 
</p><p>"It will take a little time, Lord Arthur.  You had better 
sit down." 
</p><p>"Be quick, sir," cried Lord Arthur again, stamping his 
foot angrily on the polished floor. 
<pb n="274"/>  
</p><p>Mr. Podgers smiled, drew from his breast-pocket a 
small magnifying glass, and wiped it carefully with his 
handkerchief. 
</p><p>"I am quite ready," he said. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="2" id="d4"> 
<pb n="275"/>  
<p>TEN minutes later, with face blanched by terror and eyes 
wild with grief, Lord Arthur Savile rushed from Bentinck 
House, crushing his way through the crowd of fur-coated footmen that stood round the large striped awning, 
and seeming not to see or hear anything.  The night was 
bitter cold, and the gas-lamps round the square flared and 
flickered in the keen wind, but his hands were hot with 
fever and his forehead burned like fire.  On and on he 
went, almost with the gait of a drunken man.  A policeman 
looked curiously at him as he passed, and a beggar, who 
slouched from an archway to ask for alms, grew frightened, 
seeing misery greater than his own.  Once he stopped 
under a lamp and looked at his hands.  He thought he 
could detect the stain of blood already upon them, and a 
faint cry broke from his trembling lips. 
</p><p>Murder! That is what the cheiromantist had seen there.  
Murder! The very night seemed to know it, and the desolate 
wind to howl it in his ear.  The dark corners of the 
streets were full of it.  It grinned at him from the roofs 
of the houses. 
</p><p>First he came to the park, whose sombre woodland 
seemed to fascinate him.  He leaned wearily up against 
the railings, cooling his brow against the wet metal and 
listening to the tremulous silence of the trees.  "Murder! 
murder!" he kept repeating, as though iteration could dim 
the horror of the word.  The sound of his own voice made 
him shudder, yet he almost hoped that Echo might hear 
<pb n="276"/>  
him and wake the slumbering city from its dreams.  He 
felt a mad desire to stop the casual passerby and tell 
him everything. 
</p><p>Then he wandered across Oxford Street into narrow 
shameful alleys.  Two women with painted faces mocked 
at him as he went by.  From a dark court-yard came a 
sound of oaths and blows, followed by shrill screams, and, 
huddled upon a damp door-step, he saw the crook-backed 
forms of poverty and eld.  A strange pity came over him.  
Were these children of sin and misery predestined to their 
end, as he to his? Were they, like him, merely the puppets 
of a monstrous show? 
</p><p>And yet it was not the mystery, but the comedy of 
suffering that struck him; its absolute uselessness, its grotesque 
want of meaning.  How incoherent everything 
seemed! How lacking in all harmony! He was amazed at 
the discord between the shallow optimism of the day 
and the real facts of existence.  He was still very young. 
</p><p>After a time he found himself in front of Marylebone 
Church.  The silent roadway looked like a long riband of 
polished silver, flecked here and there by the dark arabesques 
of waving shadows.  Far into the distance curved the 
line of flickering gas-lamps, and outside a little walled-in 
house stood a solitary hansom, the driver asleep inside.  
He walked hastily in the direction of Portland Place, now 
and then looking round, as though he feared that he was 
being followed.  At the corner of Rich Street stood two 
men, reading a small bill upon a hoarding.  An odd feeling 
of curiosity stirred him, and he crossed over.  As he came 
near, the word "Murder," printed in black letters, met his 
eye.  He started, and a deep flush came into his cheek.  
It was an advertisement offering a reward for any information 
leading to the arrest of a man of medium height, 
between thirty and forty years of age, wearing a billycock 
hat, a black coat, and check trousers, and with a scar 
upon his right cheek.  He read it over and over again, and 
wondered if the wretched man would be caught, and how 
he had been scarred.  Perhaps, some day, his own name 
might be placarded on the walls of London.  Some day, 
perhaps, a price would be set on his head also. 
</p><p>The thought made him sick with horror.  He turned on 
his heel and hurried on into the night. 
<pb n="277"/>  
</p><p>Where he went he hardly knew.  He had a dim memory 
of wandering through a labyrinth of sordid houses, of 
being lost in a giant web of sombre streets, and it was 
bright dawn when he found himself at last in Piccadilly 
Circus.  As he strolled home towards Belgrave Square, he 
met the great waggons on their way to Covent Garden.  
The white-smocked carters, with their pleasant sunburned 
faces and coarse curly hair, strode sturdily on, cracking 
their whips and calling out now and then to each other; 
on the back of a huge grey horse, the leader of a jangling 
team, sat a chubby boy, with a bunch of primroses in 
his battered hat, keeping tight hold of the mane with his 
little hands and laughing; and the great piles of vegetables 
looked like masses of jade against the morning sky, 
like masses of green jade against the pink petals 
of some marvellous rose.  Lord Arthur felt curiously affected, 
he could not tell why.  There was something in 
the dawn's delicate loveliness that seemed to him inexpressibly 
pathetic, and he thought of all the days that break 
in beauty and that set in storm.  These rustics, too, with 
their rough, good-humoured voices and their nonchalant 
ways, what a strange London they saw! A London free 
from the sin of night and the smoke of day, a pallid 
ghostlike city, a desolate town of tombs! He wondered 
what they thought of it, and whether they knew anything 
of its splendour and its shame, of its fierce, fiery-coloured 
joys and its horrible hunger, of all it makes and mars 
from morn to eve.  Probably it was to them merely a mart 
where they brought their fruits to sell, and where they 
tarried for a few hours at most, leaving the streets still 
silent, the houses still asleep.  It gave him pleasure to 
watch them as they went by.  Rude as they were, with 
their heavy hob-nailed shoes and their awkward gait, they 
brought a little of Arcady with them.  He felt that they 
had lived with Nature and that she had taught them 
peace.  He envied them all that they did not know. 
</p><p>By the time he had reached Belgrave Square, the sky 
was a faint blue and the birds were beginning to twitter 
in the gardens. 
</p>  
</div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="3" id="d5"> 
<pb n="278"/>  
<p>WHEN Lord Arthur woke it was twelve o'clock, and 
the midday sun was streaming through the ivory-silk 
curtains of his room.  He got up and looked out of the 
window.  A dim haze of heat was hanging over the great 
city, and the roofs of the houses were like dull silver.  In 
the flickering green of the square below, some children 
were flitting about like white butterflies, and the pavement 
was crowded with people on their way to the park.  Never 
had life seemed lovelier to him; never had the things of 
evil seemed more remote. 
</p><p>Then his valet brought him a cup of chocolate on a 
tray.  After he had drunk it, he drew aside a heavy portiere 
of peach-coloured plush and passed into the bathroom. 
The light stole softly from above, through thin 
slabs of transparent onyx, and the water in the marble 
tank glimmered like a moonstone.  He plunged hastily in, 
till the cool ripples touched throat and hair, and then 
dipped his head right under, as though he would have 
wiped away the stain of some shameful memory.  When he 
stepped out, he felt almost at peace.  The exquisite physical 
conditions of the moment had dominated him &mdash; as, indeed, 
often happens in the case of very finely wrought 
natures, for the senses, like fire, can purify as well as 
destroy. 
</p><p>After breakfast, he flung himself down on a divan and 
lit a cigarette.  On the mantel-shelf, framed in dainty old 
brocade, stood a large photograph of Sybil Merton, as he 
<pb n="279"/>  
had seen her first at Lady Noel's ball.  The small, exquisitely 
shaped head drooped slightly to one side, as 
though the thin reedlike throat could hardly bear the burden 
of so much beauty; the lips were slightly parted, and 
seemed made for sweet music; and all the tender purity 
of girlhood looked out in wonder from the dreaming eyes.  
With her soft clinging dress of crepe-de-chine and her 
large, leaf-shaped fan, she looked like one of those delicate 
little figures men find in the olive-woods near Tanagra; 
and there was a touch of Greek grace in her pose 
and attitude.  Yet she was not petite.  She was simply 
perfectly proportioned &mdash; a rare thing in an age when so 
many women are either over life-size or insignificant. 
</p><p>Now as Lord Arthur looked at her, he was filled with 
the terrible pity that is born of love.  He felt that to marry 
her, with the doom of murder hanging over his head, 
would be a betrayal like that of Judas, a sin worse than 
any the Borgia had ever dreamed of.  What happiness 
could there be for them when at any moment he might 
be called upon to carry out the awful prophecy written in 
his hand? What manner of life would be theirs while Fate 
still held this fearful fortune in the scales? The marriage 
must be postponed, at all costs.  Of this he was quite resolved. 
Ardently though he loved the girl &mdash; and the mere 
touch of her fingers, when they sat together, made each 
nerve of his body thrill with exquisite joy &mdash; he recognized 
none the less clearly where his duty lay, and was fully 
conscious of the fact that he had no right to marry until 
he had committed the murder.  This done, he could stand 
before the altar with Sybil Merton and gave his life into 
her hands without terror of wrong-doing.  This done, he 
could take her to his arms, knowing that she would never 
have to blush for him, never have to hang her head in 
shame.  But done it must be first; and the sooner the 
better for both. 
</p><p>Many men in his position would have preferred the 
primrose path of dalliance to the steep heights of duty, 
but Lord Arthur was too conscientious to set pleasure 
above principle.  There was more than mere passion in his 
love, and Sybil was to him a symbol of all that is good 
and noble.  For a moment he had a natural repugnance 
against what he was asked to do, but it soon passed away. 
<pb n="280"/>  
His heart told him that it was not a sin, but a sacrifice; 
his reason reminded him that there was no other course 
open.  He had to choose between living for himself and 
living for others, and terrible though the task laid upon 
him undoubtedly was, yet he knew that he must not suffer 
selfishness to triumph over love.  Sooner or later we are 
all called upon to decide on the same issue &mdash; of us all, 
the same question is asked.  To Lord Arthur it came 
early in life &mdash; before his nature had been spoiled by the 
calculating cynicism of middle age, or his heart corroded 
by the shallow fashionable egotism of our day, and he 
felt no hesitation about doing his duty.  Fortunately also, 
for him, he was no mere dreamer, or idle dilettante.  Had 
he been so, he would have hesitated, like Hamlet, and let 
irresolution mar his purpose.  But he was essentially practical. 
Life to him meant action, rather than thought.  He 
had that rarest of all things, common sense. 
</p><p>The wild turbid feelings of the previous night had by 
this time completely passed away, and it was almost with 
a sense of shame that he looked back upon his mad 
wanderings from street to street, his fierce emotional agony.  
The very sincerity of his sufferings made them seem unreal 
to him now.  He wondered how he could have been 
so foolish as to rant and rave about the inevitable.  The 
only question that seemed to trouble him was, whom to 
make away with; for he was not blind to the fact that 
murder, like the religions of the pagan world, requires a 
victim as well as a priest.  Not being a genius, he had no 
enemies; and, indeed, he felt that this was not the time 
for the gratification of any personal pique or dislike, the 
mission in which he was engaged being one of great and 
grave solemnity.  He accordingly made out a list of his 
friends and relatives on a sheet of note-paper, and after 
careful consideration, decided in favour of Lady Clementina 
Beauchamp, a dear old lady who lived in Curzon 
Street and was his own second cousin by his mother's 
side.  He had always been very fond of Lady Clem, as 
every one called her, and as he was very wealthy himself &mdash;  
having come into all Lord Rugby's property when 
he came of age &mdash; there was no possibility of his deriving 
any vulgar monetary advantage by her death.  In fact, 
the more he thought over the matter, the more she seemed 
<pb n="281"/>  
to him to be just the right person, and, feeling that any 
delay would be unfair to Sybil, he determined to make 
his arrangements at once. 
</p><p>The first thing to be done was, of course, to settle 
with the cheiromantist; so he sat down at a small Sheraton 
writing-table that stood near the window, drew a 
cheque for L105 payable to the order of Mr. Septimus 
Podgers, and, enclosing it in an envelope, told his valet 
to take it to West Moon Street.  He then telephoned to the 
stables for his hansom, and dressed to go out.  As he 
was leaving the room, he looked back at Sybil Merton's 
photograph and swore that, come what may, he would 
never let her know what he was doing for her sake, but 
would keep the secret of his self-sacrifice hidden always 
in his heart. 
</p><p>On his way to the Buckingham, he stopped at a florist's, 
and sent Sybil a beautiful basket of narcissus, with 
lively white petals and staring pheasants' eyes, and on arriving 
at the club, went straight to the library, rang the 
bell, and ordered the waiter to bring him a lemon-and-soda, and a book on toxicology.  He had fully decided that 
poison was the best means to adopt in this troublesome 
business.  Anything like personal violence was extremely 
distasteful to him, and besides, he was very anxious not 
to murder Lady Clementina in any way that might attract 
public attention, as he hated the idea of being lionized 
at Lady Windermere's, or seeing his name figuring in the 
paragraphs of vulgar society newspapers.  He had also to 
think of Sybil's father and mother, who were rather old-fashioned people, and might possibly object to the marriage 
if there was anything like a scandal, though he felt 
certain that if he told them the whole facts of the case 
they would be the very first to appreciate the motives 
that had actuated him.  He had every reason, then, to decide 
in favour of poison.  It was safe, sure, and quiet, and 
did away with any necessity for painful scenes, to which, 
like most Englishmen, he had a rooted objection. 
</p><p>Of the science of poisons, however, he knew absolutely 
nothing, and as the waiter seemed quite unable to find 
anything in the library but Ruff's Guide and Bailey's 
Magazine, he examined the book-shelves himself, and 
finally came across a handsomely bound edition of the 
<pb n="282"/>  
Pharmacopoeia and a copy of Erskine's Toxicology, edited 
by Sir Mathew Reid, the President of the Royal College 
of Physicians and one of the oldest members of the 
Buckingham, having been elected in mistake for somebody 
else &mdash; a contretemps that so enraged the Committee 
that when the real man came up they blackballed him 
unanimously.  Lord Arthur was a good deal puzzled at 
the technical terms used in both books, and had begun to 
regret that he had not paid more attention to his classics 
at Oxford, when in the second volume of Erskine, he 
found a very interesting and complete account of the 
properties of aconitine, written in fairly clear English.  It 
seemed to him to be exactly the poison he wanted.  It 
was swift &mdash; indeed, almost immediate in its effect &mdash; perfectly 
painless, and when taken in the form of a gelatine 
capsule, the mode recommended by Sir Mathew, not by 
any means unpalatable.  He accordingly made a note, 
upon his shirt-cuff, of the amount necessary for a fatal 
dose, put the books back in their places, and strolled up 
St. James's Street to Pestle and Humbey's, the great 
chemists.  Mr. Pestle, who always attended personally on 
the aristocracy, was a good deal surprised at the order, 
and in a very deferential manner murmured something 
about a medical certificate being necessary.  However, as 
soon as Lord Arthur explained to him that it was for a 
large Norwegian mastiff that he was obliged to get rid of, 
as it showed signs of incipient rabies and had already 
bitten the coachman twice in the calf of the leg, he expressed 
himself as being perfectly satisfied, complemented 
Lord Arthur on his wonderful knowledge of toxicology, 
and had the prescription made up immediately. 
</p><p>Lord Arthur put the capsule into a pretty little silver 
bonbonniere that he saw in a shop window in Bond 
Street, threw away Pestle and Humbey's ugly pill-box, and 
drove off at once to Lady Clementina's. 
</p><p>"Well, monsieur le mauvais sujet," cried the old lady as 
he entered the room, "why haven't you been to see me 
all this time?" 
</p><p>"My dear Lady Clem, I never have a moment to myself," 
said Lord Arthur, smiling. 
</p><p>"I suppose you mean that you go about all day long 
with Miss Sybil Merton, buying chiffons and talking 
<pb n="283"/>  
nonsense? I cannot understand why people make such a 
fuss about being married.  In my day we never dreamed of 
billing and cooing in public, or in private for that matter." 
</p><p>"I assure you I have not seen Sybil for twenty-four 
hours, Lady Clem.  As far as I can make out, she belongs 
entirely to her milliners." 
</p><p>"Of course; that is the only reason you come to see 
an ugly old woman like myself.  I wonder you men don't 
take warning.  On a fait des folies pour moi, and here I 
am, a poor rheumatic creature with a false front and a 
bad temper.  Why, if it were not for dear Lady Jansen, 
who sends me all the worst French novels she can find, I 
don't think I could get through the day.  Doctors are no 
use at all, except to get fees out of one.  They can't even 
cure my heartburn." 
</p><p>"I have brought you a cure for that, Lady Clem," said 
Lord Arthur gravely.  "It is a wonderful thing, invented 
by an American." 
</p><p>"I don't think I like American inventions, Arthur.  I 
am quite sure I don't.  I read some American novels 
lately, and they were quite nonsensical." 
</p><p>"Oh, but there is no nonsense at all about this, Lady 
Clem! I assure you it is a perfect cure.  You must promise 
to try it"; and Lord Arthur brought the little box out of 
his pocket and handed it to her. 
</p><p>"Well, the box is charming, Arthur.  Is it really a present? 
That is very sweet of you.  And is this the wonderful 
medicine? It looks like a bonbon.  I'll take it at once." 
</p><p>"Good heavens! Lady Clem," cried Lord Arthur, catching 
hold of her hand, "you mustn't do anything of the 
kind.  It is a homoeopathic medicine, and if you take it 
without having heartburn, it might do you no end of harm.  
Wait till you have an attack, and take it then.  You will 
be astonished at the result." 
</p><p>"I should like to take it now," said Lady Clementina, 
holding up to the light the little transparent capsule, with 
its floating bubble of liquid aconitine.  "I am sure it is 
delicious.  The fact is that, though I hate doctors, I love 
medicines.  However, I'll keep it till my next attack." 
</p><p>"And when will that be?" asked Lord Arthur eagerly.  
"Will it be soon?" 
<pb n="284"/>  
</p><p>"I hope not for a week.  I had a very bad time yesterday 
morning with it.  But one never knows." 
</p><p>"You are sure to have one before the end of the 
month then, Lady Clem?" 
</p><p>"I am afraid so.  But how sympathetic you are to-day, 
Arthur! Really, Sybil has done you a great deal of good.  
And now you must run away, for I am dining with some 
very dull people who won't talk scandal, and I know that 
if I don't get my sleep now I shall never be able to keep 
awake during dinner.  Good-bye, Arthur.  Give my love to 
Sybil, and thank you so much for the American medicine." 
</p><p>"You won't forget to take it, Lady Clem, will you?" 
said Lord Arthur, rising from his seat. 
</p><p>"Of course I won't, you silly boy.  I think it is most 
kind of you to think of me, and I shall write and tell 
you if I want any more." 
</p><p>Lord Arthur left the house in high spirits and with a 
feeling of immense relief. 
</p><p>That night he had an interview with Sybil Merton.  He 
told her how he had been suddenly placed in a position 
of terrible difficulty, from which neither honour nor duty 
would allow him to recede.  He told her that the marriage 
must be put off for the present, as until he had got 
rid of his fearful entanglements, he was not a free man.  
He implored her to trust him, and not to have any doubts 
about the future.  Everything would come right, but patience 
was necessary. 
</p><p>The scene took place in the conservatory of Mr. Merton's 
house, in Park Lane, where Lord Arthur had dined 
as usual.  Sybil had never seemed more happy, and for a 
moment Lord Arthur had been tempted to play the coward's 
part, to write to Lady Clementina for the pill, and 
to let the marriage go on as if there was no such person 
as Mr. Podgers in the world.  His better nature, however, 
soon asserted itself, and even when Sybil flung herself 
weeping into his arms, he did not falter.  The beauty that 
stirred his senses had touched his conscience also.  He felt 
that to wreck so fair a life for the sake of a few months' 
pleasure would be a wrong thing to do. 
</p><p>He stayed with Sybil till nearly midnight, comforting 
<pb n="285"/>  
her and being comforted in turn, and early the next 
morning he left for Venice, after writing a manly, firm 
letter to Mr. Merton about the necessary postponement of 
the marriage. 
</p>  
</div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="4" id="d6"> 
<pb n="286"/>  
<p>IN Venice he met his brother, Lord Surbiton, who happened 
to have come over from Corfu in his yacht.  The 
two young men spent a delightful fortnight together.  In 
the morning they rode on the Lido, or glided up and 
down the green canals in their long black gondola; in the 
afternoon they usually entertained visitors on the yacht; 
and in the evening they dined at Florian's and smoked 
innumerable cigarettes on the Piazza.  Yet somehow Lord 
Arthur was not happy.  Every day he studied the obituary 
column in the Times, expecting to see a notice of Lady 
Clementina's death, but every day he was disappointed.  
He began to be afraid that some accident had happened 
to her, and often regretted that he had prevented her 
taking the aconitine when she had been so anxious to 
try its effect.  Sybil's letters, too, though full of love, and 
trust, and tenderness, were often very sad in their tone, 
and sometimes he used to think that he was parted from 
her for ever. 
</p><p>After a fortnight Lord Surbiton got bored with Venice 
and determined to run down the coast to Ravenna, as 
he heard that there was some capital cock-shooting in 
the Pinetum.  Lord Arthur at first refused absolutely to 
come, but Surbiton, of whom he was extremely fond, 
finally persuaded him that if he stayed at Danielli's by 
himself he would be moped to death, and on the morning 
of the 15th they started, with a strong nor'-east wind 
<pb n="287"/>  
blowing and a rather choppy sea.  The sport was excellent 
and the free open-air life brought the colour back to 
Lord Arthur's cheek, but about the 22nd be became 
anxious about Lady Clementina, and, in spite of Surbiton's 
remonstrances, came back to Venice by train. 
</p><p>As he stepped out of his gondola on to the hotel 
steps, the proprietor came forward to meet him with a 
sheaf of telegrams.  Lord Arthur snatched them out of 
his hand and tore them open.  Everything had been successful. 
Lady Clementina had died quite suddenly on the 
night of the 17th! 
</p><p>His first thought was for Sybil, and he sent her off a 
telegram announcing his immediate return to London.  He 
then ordered his valet to pack his things for the night 
mail, sent his gondoliers about five times their proper 
fare, and ran up to his sitting-room with a light step and 
a buoyant heart.  There he found three letters waiting 
for him.  One was from Sybil herself, full of sympathy and 
condolence.  The others were from his mother and from 
Lady Clementina's solicitor.  It seemed that the old lady 
had dined with the duchess that very night, had delighted 
every one by her wit and esprit, but had gone home 
somewhat early, complaining of heartburn.  In the morning 
she was found dead in her bed, having apparently 
suffered no pain.  Sir Mathew Reid had been sent for at 
once, but, of course, there was nothing to be done, and 
she was to be buried on the 22nd at Beauchamp Chalcote. 
A few days before she died she had made her will, 
and left Lord Arthur her little house in Curzon Street 
and all her furniture, personal effects, and pictures, with 
the exception of her collection of miniatures, which was 
to go to her sister, Lady Margaret Rufford, and her 
amethyst necklace, which Sybil Merton was to have.  The 
property was not of much value, but Mr. Mansfield, the 
solicitor, was extremely anxious for Lord Arthur to return 
at once, if possible, as there were a great many bills 
to be paid, and Lady Clementina had never kept any regular 
accounts. 
</p><p>Lord Arthur was very much touched by Lady Clementina's 
kind remembrance of him, and felt that Mr. Podgers 
had a great deal to answer for.  His love of Sybil, however, 
<pb n="288"/>  
dominated every other emotion, and the consciousness 
that he had done his duty gave him peace and comfort. 
When he arrived at Charing Cross, he felt perfectly 
happy. 
</p><p>The Mertons received him very kindly.  Sybil made him 
promise that he would never again allow anything to 
come between them, and the marriage was fixed for the 
7th June.  Life seemed to him once more bright and 
beautiful, and all his old gladness came back to him 
again. 
</p><p>One day, however, as he was going over the house in 
Curzon Street, in company with Lady Clementina's solicitor 
and Sybil herself, burning packages of faded letters 
and turning out drawers of odd rubbish, the young 
girl suddenly gave a little cry of delight. 
</p><p>"What have you found, Sybil?" said Lord Arthur, 
looking up from his work and smiling. 
</p><p>"This lovely little silver bonbonniere, Arthur.  Isn't 
it quaint and Dutch? Do give it to me! I know amethysts 
won't become me till I am over eighty." 
</p><p>It was the box that had held the aconitine. 
</p><p>Lord Arthur started, and a faint blush came into his 
cheek.  He had almost entirely forgotten what he had 
done, and it seemed to him a curious coincidence that 
Sybil, for whose sake he had gone through all that terrible 
anxiety, should have been the first to remind him of 
it. 
</p><p>"Of course you can have it, Sybil.  I gave it to poor 
Lady Clem myself." 
</p><p>"Oh! thank you, Arthur; and may I have the bonbon 
too? I had no notion that Lady Clementina liked sweets.  I 
thought she was far too intellectual." 
</p><p>Lord Arthur grew deadly pale, and a horrible idea 
crossed his mind. 
</p><p>"Bonbon, Sybil? What do you mean?" he said in a slow 
hoarse voice. 
</p><p>"There is one in it, that is all.  It looks quite old and 
dusty, and I have not the slightest intention of eating 
it. What is the matter, Arthur? How white you look!" 
</p><p>Lord Arthur rushed across the room and seized the 
box.  Inside it was the amber-coloured capsule, with its 
<pb n="289"/>  
poison-bubble.  Lady Clementina had died a natural 
death after all! 
</p><p>The shock of the discovery was almost too much for 
him.  He flung the capsule into the fire, and sank on the 
sofa with a cry of despair. 
</p>  
</div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="5" id="d7"> 
<pb n="290"/>  
<p>MR. MERTON was a good deal distressed at the second 
postponement of the marriage, and Lady Julia, 
who had already ordered her dress for the wedding, did 
all in her power to make Sybil break off the match.  
Dearly, however, as Sybil loved her mother, she had 
given her whole life into Lord Arthur's hands, and nothing 
that Lady Julia could say could make her waver in her 
faith.  As for Lord Arthur himself, it took him days to 
get over his terrible disappointment, and for a time his 
nerves were completely unstrung.  His excellent common 
sense, however, soon asserted itself, and his sound practical 
mind did not leave him long in doubt about what 
to do.  Poison having proved a complete failure, dynamite, 
or some other form of explosive, was obviously the 
proper thing to try. 
</p><p>He accordingly looked again over the list of his 
friends and relatives, and, after careful consideration, 
determined to blow up his uncle, the Dean of Chichester.  
The Dean, who was a man of great culture and learning, 
was extremely fond of clocks, and had a wonderful collection 
of timepieces, ranging from the fifteenth century 
to the present day, and it seemed to Lord Arthur that this 
hobby of the good Dean's offered him an excellent opportunity 
for carrying out his scheme.  Where to procure 
an explosive machine was, of course, quite another matter. 
The London Directory gave him no information on the 
point, and he felt that there was very little use in going 
<pb n="291"/>  
to Scotland Yard about it, as they never seemed to know 
anything about the movements of the dynamite faction 
till after an explosion had taken place, and not much 
even then. 
</p><p>Suddenly he thought of his friend Rouvaloff, a young 
Russian of very revolutionary tendencies, whom he had 
met at Lady Windermere's in the winter.  Count Rouvaloff 
was supposed to be writing a life of Peter the Great, 
and to have come over to England for the purpose of studying 
the documents relating to that Tsar's residence in this 
country as a ship carpenter, but it was generally suspected 
that he was a nihilist agent, and there was no doubt 
that the Russian Embassy did not look with any favour 
upon his presence in London.  Lord Arthur felt that he 
was just the man for his purpose, and drove down one 
morning to his lodgings in Bloomsbury to ask his 
advice and assistance. 
</p><p>"So you are taking up politics seriously?" said Count 
Rouvaloff, when Lord Arthur had told him the object of 
his mission; but Lord Arthur, who hated swagger of any 
kind, felt bound to admit to him that he had not the 
slightest interest in social questions and simply wanted 
the explosive machine for a purely family matter, in 
which no one was concerned but himself. 
</p><p>Count Rouvaloff looked at him for some moments in 
amazement, and then seeing that he was quite serious, 
wrote an address on a piece of paper, initialled it, and 
handed it to him across the table. 
</p><p>"Scotland Yard would give a good deal to know this 
address, my dear fellow." 
</p><p>"They shan't have it," cried Lord Arthur, laughing; 
and after shaking the young Russian warmly by the hand, 
he ran downstairs, examined the paper, and told the 
coachman to drive to Soho Square. 
</p><p>There he dismissed him, and strolled down Greek 
Street till he came to a place called Bayle's Court.  He 
passed under the archway, and found himself in a curious 
cul-de-sac that was apparently occupied by a French 
laundry, as a perfect network of clothes-lines was 
stretched across from house to house and there was a 
flutter of white linen in the morning air.  He walked 
right to the end and knocked at a little green house. 
<pb n="292"/>  
After some delay, during which every window in the 
court became a blurred mass of peering faces, the door 
was opened by a rather rough-looking foreigner, who 
asked him in very bad English what his business was.  
Lord Arthur handed him the paper Count Rouvaloff had 
given him.  When the man saw it, he bowed and invited 
Lord Arthur into a very shabby front parlour on the 
ground floor, and in a few moments Herr Winckelkopf, as 
he was called in England, bustled into the room, with a 
very wine-stained napkin round his neck and a fork in 
his left hand. 
</p><p>"Count Rouvaloff has given me an introduction to 
you," said Lord Arthur, bowing, "and I am anxious to 
have a short interview with you on a matter of business.  
My name is Smith, Mr. Robert Smith, and I want you 
to supply me with an explosive clock." 
</p><p>"Charmed to meet you, Lord Arthur," said the genial 
little German, laughing.  "Don't look so alarmed; it is 
my duty to know everybody, and I remember seeing you 
one evening at Lady Windermere's.  I hope her ladyship is 
quite well.  Do you mind sitting with me while I finish my 
breakfast? There is an excellent pate, and my friends 
are kind enough to say that my Rhine wine is better than 
any they get at the German Embassy," and before Lord 
Arthur had got over his surprise at being recognized, 
he found himself seated in the back-room, sipping the 
most delicious Marcobrunner out of a pale yellow hock-glass marked with the Imperial monogram and chatting 
in the friendliest manner possible to the famous conspirator. 
</p><p>"Explosive clocks," said Herr Winckelkopf, "are not 
very good things for foreign exportation, as, even if they 
succeed in passing the Custom House, the train service is 
so irregular that they usually go off before they have 
reached their proper destination.  If, however, you want 
one for home use, I can supply you with an excellent 
article, and guarantee that you will be satisfied with the 
result.  May I ask for whom it is intended? If it is for the 
police, or for any one connected with Scotland Yard, 
I am afraid I cannot do anything for you.  The English 
detectives are really our best friends, and I have always 
<pb n="293"/>  
found that by relying on their stupidity, we can do exactly 
what we like.  I could not spare one of them." 
</p><p>"I assure you," said Lord Arthur, "that it has nothing 
to do with the police at all.  In fact, the clock is intended 
for the Dean of Chichester." 
</p><p>"Dear me! I had no idea that you felt so strongly 
about religion, Lord Arthur.  Few young men do nowadays." 
</p><p>"I am afraid you overrate me, Herr Winckelkopf," 
said Lord Arthur, blushing.  "The fact is, I really know 
nothing about theology." 
</p><p>"It is a purely private matter then?" 
</p><p>"Purely private." 
</p><p>Herr Winckelkopf shrugged his shoulders and left 
the room, returning in a few minutes with a round 
cake of dynamite about the size of a penny and a pretty 
little French clock surmounted by an ormolu figure of 
Liberty trampling on the hydra of Despotism. 
</p><p>Lord Arthur's face brightened up when he saw it.  
"That is just what I want," he cried; "and now tell me 
how it goes off." 
</p><p>"Ah! there is my secret," answered Herr Winckelkopf, 
contemplating his invention with a justifiable look of 
pride; "let me know when you wish it to explode, and 
I will set the machine to the moment." 
</p><p>"Well, to-day is Tuesday, and if you could send it 
off at once &mdash; " 
</p><p>"That is impossible; I have a great deal of important 
work on hand for some friends of mine in Moscow.  Still, 
I might send it off to-morrow." 
</p><p>"Oh, it will be quite time enough!" said Lord Arthur 
politely, "if it is delivered to-morrow night or Thursday 
morning.  For the moment of the explosion, say Friday 
at noon exactly.  The dean is always at home at that 
hour." 
</p><p>"Friday, at noon," repeated Herr Winckelkopf, and he 
made a note to that effect in a large ledger that was lying 
on a bureau near the fireplace. 
</p><p>"And now," said Lord Arthur, rising from his seat, 
"pray let me know how much I am in your debt." 
</p><p>"It is such a small matter, Lord Arthur, that I do not 
care to make any charge.  The dynamite comes to seven 
<pb n="294"/>  
and sixpence, the clock will be three pounds ten, and the 
carriage about five shillings.  I am only too pleased to 
oblige any friend of Count Rouvaloff's." 
</p><p>"But your trouble, Herr Winckelkopf?" 
</p><p>"Oh, that is nothing! It is a pleasure to me.  I do not 
work for money; I live entirely for my art." 
</p><p>Lord Arthur laid down L4, 2s. 6d. on the table, 
thanked the little German for his kindness, and, having 
succeeded in declining an invitation to meet some Anarchists 
at a meat-tea on the following Saturday, left 
the house and went off to the park. 
</p><p>For the next two days he was in a state of the greatest 
excitement, and on Friday at twelve o'clock he drove 
down to the Buckingham to wait for news.  All the afternoon 
the stolid hall-porter kept posting up telegrams from 
various parts of the country giving the results of horse-races, the verdicts in divorce suits, the state of the 
weather, and the like, while the tape ticked out wearisome 
details about an all-night sitting in the House of Commons 
and a small panic on the Stock Exchange.  At four 
o'clock the evening papers came in, and Lord Arthur disappeared 
into the library with the Pall Mall, the St. 
James's, the Globe, and the Echo, to the immense indignation 
of Colonel Goodchild, who wanted to read the 
reports of a speech he had delivered that morning at 
the Mansion House on the subject of South African Missions 
and the advisability of having black Bishops in 
every province, and for some reason or other had a 
strong prejudice against the Evening News.  None of the 
papers, however, contained even the slightest allusion to 
Chichester, and Lord Arthur felt that the attempt must 
have failed.  It was a terrible blow to him, and for a time 
he was quite unnerved.  Herr Winckelkopf, whom he 
went to see the next day, was full of elaborate apologies, 
and offered to supply him with another clock free of 
charge, or with a case of nitroglycerine bombs at cost 
price.  But he had lost all faith in explosives, and Herr 
Winckelkopf himself acknowledged that everything is so 
adulterated nowadays that even dynamite can hardly be 
got in a pure condition.  The little German, however, 
while admitting that something must have gone wrong 
with the machinery, was not without hope that the clock 
<pb n="295"/>  
might still go off, and instanced the case of a barometer 
that he had once sent to the military governor at Odessa 
which, though timed to explode in ten days, had not 
done so for something like three months.  It was quite 
true that when it did go off, it merely succeeded in blowing 
a housemaid to atoms, the governor having gone out 
of town six weeks before, but at least it showed that 
dynamite, as a destructive force, was, when under the 
control of machinery, a powerful, though a somewhat 
unpunctual agent.  Lord Arthur was a little consoled 
by this reflection, but even here he was destined to 
disappointment, for two days afterwards, as he was 
going upstairs, the duchess called him into her boudoir 
and showed him a letter she had just received from the 
Deanery. 
</p><p>"Jane writes charming letters," said the duchess; "you 
must really read her last.  It is quite as good as the novels 
Mudie sends us." 
</p><p>Lord Arthur seized the letter from her hand.  It ran as 
follows: 
THE DEANERY, CHICHESTER,<lb/> 
27th May.<lb/> 
My Dearest Aunt,<lb/> 
</p><p>Thank you so much for the flannel for the Dorcas 
Society, and also for the gingham.  I quite agree with you 
that it is nonsense their wanting to wear pretty things, 
but everybody is so Radical and irreligious nowadays, 
that it is difficult to make them see that they should not 
try and dress like the upper classes.  I am  sure I don't 
know what we are coming to.  As Papa has  often said in 
his sermons, we live in an age of unbelief. 
</p><p>We have had great fun over a clock that an unknown 
admirer sent Papa last Thursday.  It arrived  in a wooden 
box from London, carriage paid, and Papa  feels it must 
have been sent by some one who had read his remarkable 
sermon, "Is Licence Liberty?" for on the top of the clock 
was a figure of a woman, with what Papa said was the 
cap of Liberty on her head.  I didn't think it very becoming 
myself, but Papa said it was historical, so I suppose it is 
all right.  Parker unpacked it, and Papa put it on the mantelpiece 
in the library, and we were all sitting there on 
<pb n="296"/>  
Friday morning when, just as the clock struck twelve, 
we heard a whirring noise, a little puff of smoke came 
from the pedestal of the figure, and the goddess of Liberty 
fell off and broke her nose on the fender! Maria 
was quite alarmed, but it looked so ridiculous that James 
and I went off into fits of laughter, and even Papa was 
amused.  When we examined it, we found it was a sort of 
alarum clock, and that, if you set it to a particular hour, 
and put some gunpowder and a cap under a little 
hammer, it went off whenever you wanted.  Papa said it 
must not remain in the library, as it made a noise, so 
Reggie carried it away to the schoolroom and does nothing 
but have small explosions all day long.  Do you think 
Arthur would like one for a wedding present? I suppose 
they are quite fashionable in London.  Papa says they 
should do a great deal of good, as they show that Liberty 
can't last, but must fall down.  Papa says Liberty was invented 
at the time of the French Revolution.  How awful it 
seems! 
</p><p>I have now to go to the Dorcas, where I will read 
them your most instructive letter.  How true, dear Aunt, 
your idea is, that in their rank of life they should wear 
what is unbecoming.  I must say it is absurd, their anxiety 
about dress, when there are so many more important 
things in this world and in the next.  I am so glad your 
flowered poplin turned out so well, and that your lace 
was not torn.  I am wearing my yellow satin, that you so 
kindly gave me, at the Bishop's on Wednesday, and think 
it will look all right.  Would you have bows or not? Jennings 
says that every one wears bows now, and that the 
under-skirt should be frilled.  Reggie has just had another 
explosion, and Papa has ordered the clock to be sent to 
the stables.  I don't think Papa likes it so much as he did 
at first, though he is very flattered at being sent such a 
pretty and ingenious toy.  It shows that people read his 
sermons and profit by them. 
</p><p>Papa sends his love, in which James, and Reggie, and 
Maria all unite, and, hoping that Uncle Cecil's gout is 
better, believe me, dear Aunt, ever your affectionate 
niece, 
JANE PERCY.<lb/> 
<pb n="297"/>  
</p><p>PS. &mdash; Do tell me about the bows.  Jennings insists they 
are the fashion. 
</p><p>Lord Arthur looked so serious and unhappy over the 
letter that the duchess went into fits of laughter. 
</p><p>"My dear Arthur," she cried, "I shall never show you a 
young lady's letter again! But what shall I say about the 
clock? I think it is a capital invention, and I should like 
to have one myself." 
</p><p>"I don't think much of them," said Lord Arthur, with 
a sad smile, and, after kissing his mother, he left the 
room. 
</p><p>When he got upstairs, he flung himself on a sofa, and 
his eyes filled with tears.  He had done his best to commit 
this murder, but on both occasions he had failed, and 
through no fault of his own.  He had tried to do his duty, 
but it seemed as if Destiny herself had turned traitor.  
He was oppressed with the sense of the barrenness of 
good intentions, of the futility of trying to be fine.  Perhaps 
it would be better to break off the marriage altogether. 
Sybil would suffer, it is true, but suffering could 
not really mar a nature so noble as hers.  As for himself, 
what did it matter? There is always some war in which a 
man can die, some cause to which a man can give his 
life, and as life had no pleasure for him, so death had no 
terror.  Let Destiny work out his doom.  He would not 
stir to help her. 
</p><p>At half-past seven he dressed and went down to the 
club.  Surbiton was there with a party of young men, and 
he was obliged to dine with them.  Their trivial conversation 
and idle jests did not interest him, and as soon as 
coffee was brought he left them, inventing some engagement 
in order to get away.  As he was going out of the 
club, the hall-porter handed him a letter.  It was from Herr 
Winckelkopf, asking him to call down the next evening 
and look at an explosive umbrella that went off as soon 
as it was opened.  It was the very latest invention, and 
had just arrived from Geneva.  He tore the letter up into 
fragments.  He had made up his mind not to try any more 
experiments.  Then he wandered down to the Thames Embankment 
and sat for hours by the river.  The moon 
peered through a mane of tawny clouds, as if it were a 
<pb n="298"/>  
lion's eye, and innumerable stars spangled the hollow 
vault, like gold dust powdered on a purple dome.  Now 
and then a barge swung out into the turbid stream and 
floated away with the tide, and the railway signals changed 
from green to scarlet as the trains ran shrieking across 
the bridge.  After some time, twelve o'clock boomed from 
the tall tower at Westminster, and at each stroke of the 
sonorous bell the night seemed to tremble.  Then the 
railway lights went out, one solitary lamp left gleaming 
like a large ruby on a giant mast, and the roar of the 
city became fainter. 
</p><p>At two o'clock he got up and strolled towards Blackfriars. 
How unreal everything looked! How like a 
strange dream! The houses on the other side of the 
river seemed built out of darkness.  One would have 
said that silver and shadow had fashioned the world 
anew.  The huge dome of St. Paul's loomed like a bubble 
through the dusky air. 
</p><p>As he approached Cleopatra's Needle he saw a man 
leaning over the parapet, and as he came nearer the man 
looked up, the gas-light falling full upon his face. 
</p><p>It was Mr. Podgers, the cheiromantist! No one could 
mistake the fat flabby face, the gold-rimmed spectacles, 
the sickly feeble smile, the sensual mouth. 
</p><p>Lord Arthur stopped.  A brilliant idea flashed across 
him, and he stole softly up behind.  In a moment he had 
seized Mr. Podgers by the legs and flung him into the 
Thames.  There was a coarse oath, a heavy splash, and 
all was still.  Lord Arthur looked anxiously over, but 
could see nothing of the cheiromantist but a tall hat, 
pirouetting in an eddy of moonlit water.  After a time it 
also sank, and no trace of Mr. Podgers was visible.  Once 
he thought that he caught sight of the bulky misshapen 
figure striking out for the staircase by the bridge, and 
a horrible feeling of failure came over him, but it turned 
out to be merely a reflection, and when the moon shone 
out from behind a cloud, it passed away.  At last he 
seemed to have realized the decree of destiny.  He heaved 
a deep sigh of relief, and Sybil's name came to his lips. 
</p><p>"Have you dropped anything, sir?" said a voice behind 
him suddenly. 
<pb n="299"/>  
</p><p>He turned round and saw a policeman with a bull's-eye lantern. 
</p><p>"Nothing of importance, Sergeant," he answered, 
smiling, and hailing a passing hansom, he jumped in 
and told the man to drive to Belgrave Square. 
</p><p>For the next few days he alternated between hope and 
fear.  There were moments when he almost expected Mr. 
Podgers to walk into the room, and yet at other times 
he felt that Fate could not be so unjust to him.  Twice 
he went to the cheiromantist's address in West Moon 
Street, but he could not bring himself to ring the bell.  
He longed for certainty, and was afraid of it. 
</p><p>Finally it came.  He was sitting in the smoking-room of 
the club, having tea and listening rather wearily to Surbiton's 
account of the last comic song at the Gaiety, 
when the waiter came in with the evening papers.  He 
took up the St. James's, and was listlessly turning over 
its pages, when this strange heading caught his eye: 
SUICIDE OF A CHEIROMANTIST<lb/> 
</p><p>He turned pale with excitement and began to read.  The 
paragraph ran as follows: 
</p><p>Yesterday morning, at seven o'clock, the body of Mr. Septimus 
R. Podgers, the eminent cheiromantist, was washed on 
shore at Greenwich, just in front of the Ship Hotel.  The 
unfortunate gentleman had been missing for some days, and 
considerable anxiety for his safety had been felt in cheiromantic 
circles.  It is supposed that he committed suicide under the 
influence of a temporary mental derangement, caused by 
overwork, and a verdict to that effect was returned this 
afternoon by the coroner's jury.  Mr. Podgers had just completed 
an elaborate treatise on the subject of the human 
hand that will shortly be published, when it will no doubt 
attract much attention.  The deceased was sixty-five years of 
age, and does not seem to have left any relations. 
</p><p>Lord Arthur rushed out of the club with the paper still 
in his hand, to the immense amazement of the hall-porter who tried in vain to stop him, and drove at once 
to Park Lane.  Sybil saw him from the window, and something 
told her that he was the bearer of good news.  She 
<pb n="300"/>  
ran down to meet him, and when she saw his face, she 
knew that all was well. 
</p><p>"My dear Sybil," cried Lord Arthur, "let us be 
married to-morrow!" 
</p><p>"You foolish boy! Why, the cake is not even ordered!" 
said Sybil, laughing through her tears. 
</p>  
</div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="6" id="d8"> 
<pb n="301"/>  
<p>WHEN the wedding took place some three weeks later, 
St. Peter's was crowded with a perfect mob of smart 
people.  The service was read in the most impressive 
manner by the Dean of Chichester, and everybody 
agreed that they had never seen a handsomer couple 
than the bride and bridegroom.  They were more than 
handsome, however &mdash; they were happy.  Never for a single 
moment did Lord Arthur regret all that he had suffered 
for Sybil's sake, while she, on her side, gave him 
the best things a woman can give to any man &mdash; worship, 
tenderness, and love.  For them romance was not killed 
by reality.  They always felt young. 
</p><p>Some years afterwards, when two beautiful children 
had been born to them, Lady Windermere came down on a 
visit to Alton Priory, a lovely old place that had been 
the duke's wedding present to his son; and one afternoon 
as she was sitting with Lady Arthur under a lime-tree in the garden, watching the little boy and girl as 
they played up and down the rose-walk, like fitful sunbeams, 
she suddenly took her hostess's hand in hers, 
and said, "Are you happy, Sybil?" 
</p><p>"Dear Lady Windermere, of course I am happy.  Aren't 
you?" 
</p><p>"I have no time to be happy, Sybil.  I always like the 
last person who is introduced to me; but, as a rule, as 
soon as I know people, I get tired of them." 
</p><p>"Don't your lions satisfy you, Lady Windermere?" 
<pb n="302"/>  
</p><p>"Oh dear, no! Lions are only good for one season.  
As soon as their manes are cut, they are the dullest creatures 
going.  Besides, they behave very badly, if you are 
really nice to them.  Do you remember that horrid Mr. 
Podgers? He was a dreadful impostor.  Of course, I 
didn't mind that at all, and even when he wanted to 
borrow money I forgave him, but I could not stand his 
making love to me.  He has really made me hate cheiromancy. 
I go in for telepathy now.  It is much more amusing." 
</p><p>"You mustn't say anything against cheiromancy here, 
Lady Windermere; it is the only subject that Arthur does 
not like people to chaff about.  I assure you he is 
quite serious over it." 
</p><p>"You don't mean to say that he believes in it, Sybil?" 
</p><p>"Ask him, Lady Windermere, here he is"; and Lord 
Arthur came up the garden with a large bunch of yellow 
roses in his hand, and his two children dancing round him. 
</p><p>"Lord Arthur?" 
</p><p>"Yes, Lady Windermere." 
</p><p>"You don't mean to say that you believe in cheiromancy?" 
</p><p>"Of course I do," said the young man, smiling. 
</p><p>"But why?" 
</p><p>"Because I owe to it all the happiness of my life," he 
murmured, throwing himself into a wicker chair. 
</p><p>"My dear Lord Arthur, what do you owe to it?" 
</p><p>"Sybil," he answered, handing his wife the roses and 
looking into her violet eyes. 
</p><p>"What nonsense!" cried Lady Windermere.  "I never 
heard such nonsense in all my life." 
</p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2>  
 
