<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WilThre"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
 
<TEI.2 id="WilThre"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Three Old Sisters and the Old Beau</title>
<title type="sort">three old sisters and the old beau</title>
<author>Wilkins, Mary E.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp> 
<name>creator of image(s)</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">11</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WilThre</idno> 
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476555</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"The Three Old Sisters and the Old Beau."</title>
<title type="sort">the three old sisters and the old beau</title>
<author>Wilkins, Mary E.</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt> 
<date value="1896">1896</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>Harper's New Monthly Magazine 92 (May 1896): 
854-855.</p>
</seriesStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1896">1896</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-03">Mar. 1996</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Jan Horner</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>TEI header &amp; footer added</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
  

<div1 type="story" id="d3"><head>              THE THREE OLD SISTERS AND THE OLD BEAU.  
 <lb/> 
                        BY MARY E. WILKINS.  
 </head> 
 <pb n="854"/> 
<p>THE three old sisters, Rachel and Nancy and Camilla, lived in the  
house in which they had been born.  They were very old in  
years&mdash;the youngest was nearly seventy&mdash;but they were, after all,  
the most youthful maidens in the village.  Not a child dragging her  
doll-carriage past their windows, not a young girl strolling by in  
the twilight on her lover's arm, was as young as they, for the  
youth in them had actually triumphed over age, and gained, as it  
were, a species of immortality in this world.  
</p><p>Did not Camilla and Nancy, the two younger, really play at  
grace-hoops sometimes of an evening?  The fantastic old shadows,  
with stiff rheumatic gestures, apeing the free motions of youth,  
and the flying hoops, had been plainly seen on the window curtains  
after the candles were lighted.  The hoops themselves, wound with  
faded ribbons, the relics of a graceful sport of their graceful  
girlhood, hung conspicuously over the mahogany table in their front  
hall.  
</p><p>In this same front hall, large and square, hung with old  
greenish landscape paper, with a spiral stair winding slowly upward  
from its midst, the three old sisters were wont to sit in the cool  
of summer afternoons.  At five o'clock the front door, topped with  
bull's-eyes of dull green glass, was thrown open, and the three  
appeared, sitting in state with their embroidery-work.  They still  
embroidered, bending their spectacled eyes painfully over scallops  
and sprigs and eyelet-holes.  They had never outgrown the  
occupations of their youth, as they had scarcely outgrown its  
amusements.  It did not seem impossible that Camilla, the youngest,  
sometimes nursed her ancient doll in her withered bosom.  
</p><p>However, the strongest evidence of the youth which still  
survived in their hearts, and answered to their conceptions of  
themselves and one another, was in their costumes.  The three old  
sisters, Rachel, Nancy, and Camilla, sat in their front hall  
arrayed in bygone silks and muslins, made after the fashions of  
their girlhood days, with no alterations.  
</p><p>Scanty ruffled skirts clinging to their wasted limbs the three  
wore, and low bodices and elbow sleeves, displaying pitilessly  
their withered necks and arms, from which all the sweet curves of  
youth had departed.  
</p><p>Their gray and scanty locks were arranged in ringlets, and  
garnished with shell combs, and sometimes a wreath of faded  
artificial flowers.  
</p><p>It was inconceivable how one, surveying the others, as they  
sat there in their gay array, could not have seen in their faces,  
if not in her looking-glass, the loss of her youth; but if she did,  
she made no sign.  Not one of them seemed to have a suspicion that  
these old costumes did not become them as fairly as ever, and  
nobody knew if their illusions ever failed them at the sight of one  
another's parchment skins, and the hollows between their poor old  
bones.  
</p><p>Always on a pleasant summer afternoon, as they sat there in  
their front hall, <pb n="855"/>  the old Beau came stepping across the way  
from his old house, half hidden behind a little grove of pine-trees.  He was as old as the eldest sister, but not at all feeble.   
He carried his handsome white head proudly above his old-fashioned  
high stock, and had a military set-back to his shoulders.  
</p><p>The old Beau, while looking, in his morning attire, not so  
very different from the modern man, clung always to his old  
costumes of state.  When he crossed the road to the sisters of an  
afternoon he wore always his silk bell hat and blue swallow-tail  
coat, with bright brass buttons, and swung, with a fine courtly  
flourish of the past, an ancient ivory-headed cane.  No one knew  
which of the sisters possessed the warmest affection of his  
faithful old heart.  He had stepped across the road to visit them  
ever since people could remember.  He had never had any other  
sweetheart, and they had never had any other beau.  
</p><p>One and then another of the sisters had been supposed to  
devote her virgin heart to him, and been pining over his long  
courtship.  Nancy, the middle sister, was the one popularly  
considered to have especially favored him.  There were vague  
whispers of more particular attentions paid her in years gone by.   
Moreover, she had been the beauty of the family.  Tall and willowy  
in figure, with long brown curls drooping over rose-leaf cheeks,  
with gentle blue eyes had Nancy been in her youth.  
</p><p>It seemed probable that she had crept the closest to the heart  
of the old Beau, but no one really knew.  He was a close man, and  
quite a student; he lived in his old library, walled in with musty  
books, and wrote with his quill pen pages of fine crabbed letters,  
which no one ever read, nor knew what their subject was.  His one  
outside diversion was his afternoon call upon the three sisters.  
</p><p>Then, seated, in summer-time, in a carved arm-chair in their  
front hall, and in the winter in their parlor, with a damask napkin  
over his thin knees, he partook of tea in a blue china cup, and  
pound-cake in a blue china plate.  The sisters' maidservant always  
passed around a tea-tray in the afternoon&mdash;an old and genteel  
custom which prevailed nowhere else in the village.  
</p><p>Nancy, the middle sister, died first&mdash;of old age, the town  
record said, although that seemed impossible, and the other sisters  
insisted that it was of a cold upon the lungs.  "Consumption is in  
our mother's family, and Nancy was always delicate.  I never  
expected she would live to be old," Rachel told the minister when  
he called.  
</p><p>After Nancy's death the old Beau drank tea with the other  
sisters for another summer, then Rachel died, and there was only  
Camilla left.  He did not make his call every afternoon after that.   
It was understood that she had doubts about the strict propriety of  
such solitary visits, and had prohibited them.  
</p><p>Then it was that the old Beau manifested symptoms of  
uneasiness.  At the hour when he had been accustomed to call upon  
his friends he strolled aimlessly about the roads, switching the  
way-side weeds with his cane.  People thought that he was ageing  
fast.  
</p><p>About three months after Rachel's death, one midsummer Sunday,  
the old Beau and Camilla walked down the road together to meeting,  
and it was said that they had gone to the minister's that morning  
and been married.  
</p><p>The Bridegroom wore his old dress costume of bell hat and blue  
swallow-tail coat, and held up his handsome white head like a  
prince in his high stock, and the Bride minced gently at his side  
in an ample bridal array of a long-past fashion and cut.  A white  
bride-bonnet, white-veiled and crowned with white plumes, adorned  
the old Bride, and she wore a lustrous white satin gown with a low  
bodice, a white Canton crape shawl, and white satin shoes.  That  
bridal costume had, beyond doubt, been prepared years and years  
gone by for one of the sisters, in anticipation of youthful love  
and wedded bliss; but for which?  No one ever knew.  Some, indeed,  
fancied that the white satin breadths were over-long for Camilla,  
and would better have suited Nancy, who had been taller, but who  
could say with certainty, since Camilla stooped with age, and must  
have lost somewhat of her youthful stature?  
</p><p>The old Bride passed up the aisle with her old Bridegroom, and  
a smile of youth that triumphed over age and memory shone on her  
old face through her white veil, and no one ever knew whether she  
wore her own or her sister's wedding-gown, or had wedded her own or  
her sister's old Beau.  
  
</p>
</div1>
</body> 
  
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
