<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="ZitImpr"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>        
 
<TEI.2 id="ZitImpr"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Impressions of an Indian Childhood</title>
<title type="sort">impressions of an indian childhood</title>
<author>Zitkala-Sa</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">42</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">ZitImpr</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476567</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Impressions of an Indian Childhood</title>
<title level="j">Atlantic Monthly</title>
<title type="sort">impressions of an indian childhood</title>
<author>Zitkala-Sa</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 85, pp. 37-47</p>
</seriesStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the 
text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term> 
<term>Native American</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
<term>Young Readers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-08">August 1994</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Kelly Tetterton, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>TEI tagging</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 

<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="section" n="1" id="d3"> 
<head type="divisional">Zitkala-Sa.  "Impressions of an Indian Childhood." 
<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 85 (1900): 37-47.</head> <pb n="37"/>  


<head type="main">MY MOTHER.</head> 
 
<p>A WIGWAM of weather-stained canvas stood at the base of some 
irregularly ascending hills.  A footpath wound its way gently down 
the sloping land till it reached the broad river bottom; creeping 
through the long swamp grasses that bent over it on either side, it 
came out on the edge of the Missouri. 
</p><p>Here, morning, noon, and evening, my mother came to draw water 
from the muddy stream for our household use.  Always, when my 
mother started for the river, I stopped my play to run along with 
her.  She was only of medium height.  Often she was sad and silent, 
at which times her full arched lips were compressed into hard and 
bitter lines, and shadows fell under her black eyes.  Then I clung 
to her hand and begged to know what made the tears fall. 
</p><p>"Hush; my little daughter must never talk about my tears;" and 
smiling through them, she patted my head and said, "Now let me see 
how fast you can run to-day."  Whereupon I tore away at my highest 
possible speed, with my long black hair blowing in the breeze. 
</p><p>I was a wild little girl of seven.  Loosely clad in a slip of 
brown buckskin, and light-footed with a pair of soft moccasins on 
my feet, I was as free as the wind that blew my hair, and no less 
spirited than a bounding deer.  These were my mother's pride, &mdash; my 
wild freedom and overflowing spirits.  She taught me no fear save 
that of intruding myself upon others. 
</p><p>Having gone many paces ahead I stopped, panting for breath, 
and laughing with glee as my mother watched my every movement.  I 
was not wholly conscious of myself, but was more keenly alive to 
the fire within.  It was as if I were the activity, and my hands 
and feet were only experiments for my spirit to work upon. 
</p><p>Returning from the river, I tugged beside my mother, with my 
hand upon the bucket I believed I was carrying.  One time, on such 
a return, I remember a bit of conversation we had.  My grown-up 
cousin, Warca-Ziwin (Sunflower), who was then seventeen, always 
went to the river alone for water for her mother.  Their wigwam was 
not far from ours; and I saw her daily going to and from the river.  
I admired my cousin greatly.  So I said: "Mother, when I am tall as 
my cousin Warca-Ziwin, you shall not have to come for water.  I 
will do it for you." 
</p><p>With a strange tremor in her voice which I could not 
understand, she answered, "If the paleface does not take away from 
us the river we drink." 
</p><p>"Mother, who is this bad paleface?" I asked. 
</p><p>"My little daughter, he is a sham, &mdash; a sickly sham!  The 
bronzed Dakota is the only real man." 
</p><p>I looked up into my mother's face while she spoke; and seeing 
her bite her lips, 
<pb n="38"/>  
I knew she was unhappy.  This aroused 
revenge in my small soul.  Stamping my foot on the earth, I cried 
aloud, "I hate the paleface that makes my mother cry!" 
</p><p>Setting the pail of water on the ground, my mother stooped, 
and stretching her left hand out on the level with my eyes, she 
placed her other arm about me; she pointed to the hill where my 
uncle and my only sister lay buried. 
</p><p>"There is what the paleface has done!  Since then your father 
too has been buried in a hill nearer the rising sun.  We were once 
very happy.  But the paleface has stolen our lands and driven us 
hither.  Having defrauded us of our land, the paleface forced us 
away. 
</p><p>"Well, it happened on the day we moved camp that your sister 
and uncle were both very sick.  Many others were ailing, but there 
seemed to be no help.  We traveled many days and nights; not in the 
grand happy way that we moved camp when I was a little girl, but we 
were driven, my child, driven like a herd of buffalo.  With every 
step, your sister, who was not as large as you are now, shrieked 
with the painful jar until she was hoarse with crying.  She grew 
more and more feverish.  Her little hands and cheeks were burning 
hot.  Her little lips were parched and dry, but she would not drink 
the water I gave her.  Then I discovered that her throat was 
swollen and red.  My poor child, how I cried with her because the 
Great Spirit had forgotten us! 
</p><p>"At last, when we reached this western country, on the first 
weary night your sister died.  And soon your uncle died also, 
leaving a widow and an orphan daughter, your cousin Warca-Ziwin.  
Both your sister and uncle might have been happy with us to-day, 
had it not been for the heartless paleface." 
</p><p>My mother was silent the rest of the way to our wigwam.  
Though I saw no tears in her eyes, I knew that was because I was 
with her.  She seldom wept before me. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="2" id="d4"> 
<head>THE LEGENDS.</head> 
 
<p>During the summer days, my mother built her fire in the shadow 
of our wigwam. 
</p><p>In the early morning our simple breakfast was spread upon the 
grass west of our tepee.  At the farthest point of the shade my 
mother sat beside her fire, toasting a savory piece of dried meat.  
Near her, I sat upon my feet, eating my dried meat with unleavened 
bread, and drinking strong black coffee. 
</p><p>The morning meal was our quiet hour, when we two were entirely 
alone.  At noon, several who chanced to be passing by stopped to 
rest, and to share our luncheon with us, for they were sure of our 
hospitality. 
</p><p>My uncle, whose death my mother ever lamented, was one of our 
nation's bravest warriors.  His name was on the lips of old men 
when talking of the proud feats of valor; and it was mentioned by 
younger men, too, in connection with deeds of gallantry.  Old women 
praised him for his kindness toward them; young women held him up 
as an ideal to their sweethearts.  Every one loved him, and my 
mother worshiped his memory.  Thus it happened that even strangers 
were sure of welcome in our lodge, if they but asked a favor in my 
uncle's name. 
</p><p>Though I heard many strange experiences related by these 
wayfarers, I loved best the evening meal, for that was the time old 
legends were told.  I was always glad when the sun hung low in the 
west, for then my mother sent me to invite the neighboring old men 
and women to eat supper with us.  Running all the way to the 
wigwams, I halted shyly at the entrances.  Sometimes I stood long 
moments without saying a word.  It was not any fear that made me so 
dumb when out upon such a happy errand; nor was it that I wished to 
<pb n="39"/>  
withhold the invitation, for it was all I could do to 
observe this very proper silence.  But it was a sensing of the 
atmosphere, to assure myself that I should not hinder other plans.  
My mother used to say to me, as I was almost bounding away for the 
old people: "Wait a moment before you invite any one.  If other 
plans are being discussed, do not interfere, but go elsewhere." 
</p><p>The old folks knew the meaning of my pauses; and often they 
coaxed my confidence by asking, "What do you seek, little 
granddaughter?" 
</p><p>"My mother says you are to come to our tepee this evening," I 
instantly exploded, and breathed the freer afterwards. 
</p><p>"Yes, yes, gladly, gladly I shall come!" each replied.  Rising 
at once and carrying their blankets across one shoulder, they 
flocked leisurely from their various wigwams toward our dwelling. 
</p><p>My mission done, I ran back, skipping and jumping with 
delight.  All out of breath, I told my mother almost the exact 
words of the answers to my invitation.  Frequently she asked, "What 
were they doing when you entered their tepee?"  This taught me to 
remember all I saw at a single glance.  Often I told my mother my 
impressions without being questioned. 
</p><p>While in the neighboring wigwams sometimes an old Indian woman 
asked me, "What is your mother doing?"  Unless my mother had 
cautioned me not to tell, I generally answered her questions 
without reserve. 
</p><p>At the arrival of our guests I sat close to my mother, and did 
not leave her side without first asking her consent.  I ate my 
supper in quiet, listening patiently to the talk of the old people, 
wishing all the time that they would begin the stories I loved 
best.  At last, when I could not wait any longer, I whispered in my 
mother's ear, "Ask them to tell an Iktomi story, mother." 
</p><p>Soothing my impatience, my mother said aloud, "My little 
daughter is anxious to hear your legends."  By this time all were 
through eating, and the evening was fast deepening into twilight. 
</p><p>As each in turn began to tell a legend, I pillowed my head in 
my mother's lap; and lying flat upon my back, I watched the stars 
as they peeped down upon me, one by one.  The increasing interest 
of the tale aroused me, and I sat up eagerly listening for every 
word.  The old women made funny remarks, and laughed so heartily 
that I could not help joining them. 
</p><p>The distant howling of a pack of wolves or the hooting of an 
owl in the river bottom frightened me, and I nestled into my 
mother's lap.  She added some dry sticks to the open fire, and the 
bright flames leaped up into the faces of the old folks as they sat 
around in a great circle. 
</p><p>On such an evening, I remember the glare of the fire shone on 
a tattooed star upon the brow of the old warrior who was telling a 
story.  I watched him curiously as he made his unconscious 
gestures.  The blue star upon his bronzed forehead was a puzzle to 
me.  Looking about, I saw two parallel lines on the chin of one of 
the old women.  The rest had none.  I examined my mother's face, 
but found no sign there. 
</p><p>After the warrior's story was finished, I asked the old woman 
the meaning of the blue lines on her chin, looking all the while 
out of the corners of my eyes at the warrior with the star on his 
forehead.  I was a little afraid that he would rebuke me for my 
boldness. 
</p><p>Here the old woman began: "Why, my grandchild, they are 
signs, &mdash; secret signs I dare not tell you.  I shall, however, tell 
you a wonderful story about a woman who had a cross tattooed upon 
each of her cheeks." 
</p><p>It was a long story of a woman whose magic power lay hidden 
behind the marks upon her face.  I fell asleep before the story was 
completed. 
<pb n="40"/>  
</p><p>Ever after that night I felt suspicious of tattooed people.  
Whenever I saw one I glanced furtively at the mark and round about 
it, wondering what terrible magic power was covered there. 
</p><p>It was rarely that such a fearful story as this one was told 
by the camp fire.  Its impression was so acute that the picture 
still remains vividly clear and pronounced. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="3" id="d5"> 
<head>THE BEADWORK.</head> 
 
<p>Soon after breakfast, mother sometimes began her beadwork.  On 
a bright clear day, she pulled out the wooden pegs that pinned the 
skirt of our wigwam to the ground, and rolled the canvas part way 
up on its frame of slender poles.  Then the cool morning breezes 
swept freely through our dwelling, now and then wafting the perfume 
of sweet grasses from newly burnt prairie. 
</p><p>Untying the long tasseled strings that bound a small brown 
buckskin bag, my mother spread upon a mat beside her bunches of 
colored beads, just as an artist arranges the paints upon his 
palette.  On a lapboard she smoothed out a double sheet of soft 
white buckskin; and drawing from a beaded case that hung on the 
left of her wide belt a long, narrow blade, she trimmed the 
buckskin into shape.  Often she worked upon small moccasins for her 
small daughter.  Then I became intensely interested in her 
designing.  With a proud, beaming face, I watched her work.  In 
imagination, I saw myself walking in a new pair of snugly fitting 
moccasins.  I felt the envious eyes of my playmates upon the pretty 
red beads decorating my feet. 
</p><p>Close beside my mother I sat on a rug, with a scrap of 
buckskin in one hand and an awl in the other.  This was the 
beginning of my practical observation lessons in the art of 
beadwork.  From a skein of finely twisted threads of silvery sinews 
my mother pulled out a single one.  With an awl she pierced the 
buckskin, and skillfully threaded it with the white sinew.  Picking 
up the tiny beads one by one, she strung them with the point of her 
thread, always twisting it carefully after every stitch. 
</p><p>It took many trials before I learned how to knot my sinew 
thread on the point of my finger, as I saw her do.  Then the next 
difficulty was in keeping my thread stiffly twisted, so that I 
could easily string my beads upon it.  My mother required of me 
original designs for my lessons in beading.  At first I frequently 
ensnared many a sunny hour into working a long design.  Soon I 
learned from self-inflicted punishment to refrain from drawing 
complex patterns, for I had to finish whatever I began. 
</p><p>After some experience I usually drew easy and simple crosses 
and squares.  These were some of the set forms.  My original 
designs were not always symmetrical nor sufficiently 
characteristic, two faults with which my mother had little 
patience.  The quietness of her oversight made me feel strongly 
responsible and dependent upon my own judgment.  She treated me as 
a dignified little individual as long as I was on my good behavior; 
and how humiliated I was when some boldness of mine drew forth a 
rebuke from her! 
</p><p>In the choice of colors she left me to my own taste.  I was 
pleased with an outline of yellow upon a background of dark blue, 
or a combination of red and myrtle-green.  There was another of red 
with a bluish gray that was more conventionally used.  When I 
became a little familiar with designing and the various pleasing 
combinations of color, a harder lesson was given me.  It was the 
sewing on, instead of beads, some tinted porcupine quills, 
moistened and flattened between the nails of the thumb and 
forefinger.  My mother cut off the prickly ends and burned them at 
once in the centre fire.  These sharp points were 
<pb n="41"/>  
poisonous, 
and worked into the flesh wherever they lodged.  For this reason, 
my mother said, I should not do much alone in quills until I was as 
tall as my cousin Warca-Ziwin. 
</p><p>Always after these confining lessons I was wild with surplus 
spirits, and found joyous relief in running loose in the open 
again.  Many a summer afternoon, a party of four or five of my 
playmates roamed over the hills with me.  We each carried a light 
sharpened rod about four feet long, with which we pried up certain 
sweet roots.  When we had eaten all the choice roots we chanced 
upon, we shouldered our rods and strayed off into patches of a 
stalky plant under whose yellow blossoms we found little crystal 
drops of gum.  Drop by drop we gathered this nature's rock-candy, 
until each of us could boast of a lump the size of a small bird's 
egg.  Soon satiated with its woody flavor, we tossed away our gum, 
to return again to the sweet roots. 
</p><p>I remember well how we used to exchange our necklaces, beaded 
belts, and sometimes even our moccasins.  We pretended to offer 
them as gifts to one another.  We delighted in impersonating our 
own mothers.  We talked of things we had heard them say in their 
conversations.  We imitated their various manners, even to the 
inflection of their voices.  In the lap of the prairie we seated 
ourselves upon our feet; and leaning our painted cheeks in the 
palms of our hands, we rested our elbows on our knees, and bent 
forward as old women were most accustomed to do. 
</p><p>While one was telling of some heroic deed recently done by a 
near relative, the rest of us listened attentively, and exclaimed 
in undertones, "Han! han!" (yes! yes!) whenever the speaker paused 
for breath, or sometimes for our sympathy.  As the discourse became 
more thrilling, according to our ideas, we raised our voices in 
these interjections.  In these impersonations our parents were led 
to say only those things that were in common favor. 
</p><p>No matter how exciting a tale we might be rehearsing, the mere 
shifting of a cloud shadow in the landscape near by was sufficient 
to change our impulses; and soon we were all chasing the great 
shadows that played among the hills.  We shouted and whooped in the 
chase; laughing and calling to one another, we were like little 
sportive nymphs on that Dakota sea of rolling green. 
</p><p>On one occasion, I forgot the cloud shadow in a strange notion 
to catch up with my own shadow.  Standing straight and still, I 
began to glide after it, putting out one foot cautiously.  When, 
with the greatest care, I set my foot in advance of myself, my 
shadow crept onward too.  Then again I tried it; this time with the 
other foot.  Still again my shadow escaped me.  I began to run; and 
away flew my shadow, always just a step beyond me.  Faster and 
faster I ran, setting my teeth and clenching my fists, determined 
to overtake my own fleet shadow.  But ever swifter it glided before 
me, while I was growing breathless and hot.  Slackening my speed, 
I was greatly vexed that my shadow should check its pace also.  
Daring it to the utmost, as I thought, I sat down upon a rock 
imbedded in the hillside. 
</p><p>So! my shadow had the impudence to sit down beside me! 
</p><p>Now my comrades caught up with me, and began to ask why I was 
running away so fast. 
</p><p>"Oh, I was chasing my shadow!  Didn't you ever do that?" I 
inquired, surprised that they should not understand. 
</p><p>They planted their moccasined feet firmly upon my shadow to 
stay it, and I arose.  Again my shadow slipped away, and moved as 
often as I did.  Then we gave up trying to catch my shadow. 
</p><p>Before this peculiar experience I have no distinct memory of 
having recognized any vital bond between myself and my 
<pb n="42"/>  
own 
shadow.  I never gave it an afterthought. 
</p><p>Returning our borrowed belts and trinkets, we rambled 
homeward.  That evening, as on other evenings, I went to sleep over 
my legends. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="4" id="d6"> 
<head>THE COFFEE-MAKING.</head> 
 
<p>One summer afternoon, my mother left me alone in our wigwam, 
while she went across the way to my aunt's dwelling. 
</p><p>I did not much like to stay alone in our tepee, for I feared 
a tall, broad-shouldered crazy man, some forty years old, who 
walked loose among the hills.  Wiyaka-Napbina (Wearer of a Feather 
Necklace) was harmless, and whenever he came into a wigwam he was 
driven there by extreme hunger.  He went nude except for the half 
of a red blanket he girdled around his waist.  In one tawny arm he 
used to carry a heavy bunch of wild sunflowers that he gathered in 
his aimless ramblings.  His black hair was matted by the winds, and 
scorched into a dry red by the constant summer sun.  As he took 
great strides, placing one brown bare foot directly in front of the 
other, he swung his long lean arm to and fro. 
</p><p>Frequently he paused in his walk and gazed far backward, 
shading his eyes with his hand.  He was under the belief that an 
evil spirit was haunting his steps.  This was what my mother told 
me once, when I sneered at such a silly big man.  I was brave when 
my mother was near by, and Wiyaka-Napbina walking farther and 
farther away. 
</p><p>"Pity the man, my child.  I knew him when he was a brave and 
handsome youth.  He was overtaken by a malicious spirit among the 
hills, one day, when he went hither and thither after his ponies.  
Since then he cannot stay away from the hills," she said. 
</p><p>I felt so sorry for the man in his misfortune that I prayed to 
the Great Spirit to restore him.  But though I pitied him at a 
distance, I was still afraid of him when he appeared near our 
wigwam. 
</p><p>Thus, when my mother left me by myself that afternoon, I sat 
in a fearful mood within our tepee.  I recalled all I had ever 
heard about Wiyaka-Napbina; and I tried to assure myself that 
though he might pass near by, he would not come to our wigwam 
because there was no little girl around our grounds. 
</p><p>Just then, from without a hand lifted the canvas covering of 
the entrance; the shadow of a man fell within the wigwam, and a 
large roughly moccasined foot was planted inside. 
</p><p>For a moment I did not dare to breathe or stir, for I thought 
that could be no other than Wiyaka-Napbina.  The next instant I 
sighed aloud in relief.  It was an old grandfather who had often 
told me Iktomi legends. 
</p><p>"Where is your mother, my little grandchild?" were his first 
words. 
</p><p>"My mother is soon coming back from my aunt's tepee," I 
replied. 
</p><p>"Then I shall wait awhile for her return," he said, crossing 
his feet and seating himself upon a mat. 
</p><p>At once I began to play the part of a generous hostess.  I 
turned to my mother's coffeepot. 
</p><p>Lifting the lid, I found nothing but coffee grounds in the 
bottom.  I set the pot on a heap of cold ashes in the centre, and 
filled it half full of warm Missouri River water.  During this 
performance I felt conscious of being watched.  Then breaking off 
a small piece of our unleavened bread, I placed it in a bowl.  
Turning soon to the coffeepot, which would never have boiled on a 
dead fire had I waited forever, I poured out a cup of worse than 
muddy warm water.  Carrying the bowl in one hand and cup in the 
other, I handed the light luncheon to the old warrior.  I offered 
them to him 
<pb n="43"/>  
with the air of bestowing generous hospitality. 
</p><p>"How! how!" he said, and placed the dishes on the ground in 
front of his crossed feet.  He nibbled at the bread and sipped from 
the cup.  I sat back against a pole watching him.  I was proud to 
have succeeded so well in serving refreshments to a guest all by 
myself.  Before the old warrior had finished eating, my mother 
entered.  Immediately she wondered where I had found coffee, for 
she knew I had never made any, and that she had left the coffeepot 
empty.  Answering the question in my mother's eyes, the warrior 
remarked, "My granddaughter made coffee on a heap of dead ashes, 
and served me the moment I came." 
</p><p>They both laughed, and mother said, "Wait a little longer, and 
I shall build a fire."  She meant to make some real coffee.  But 
neither she nor the warrior, whom the law of our custom had 
compelled to partake of my insipid hospitality, said anything to 
embarrass me.  They treated my best judgment, poor as it was, with 
the utmost respect.  It was not till long years afterward that I 
learned how ridiculous a thing I had done. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="5" id="d7"> 
<head>THE DEAD MAN'S PLUM BUSH.</head> 
 
<p>One autumn afternoon, many people came streaming toward the 
dwelling of our near neighbor.  With painted faces, and wearing 
broad white bosoms of elk's teeth, they hurried down the narrow 
footpath to Haraka Wambdi's wigwam.  Young mothers had their 
children by the hand, and half pulled them along in their haste.  
They overtook and passed by the bent old grandmothers who were 
trudging along with crooked canes toward the centre of excitement.  
Most of the young braves galloped hither on their ponies.  
Toothless warriors, like the old women, came more slowly, though 
mounted on lively ponies.  They sat proudly erect on their horses.  
They wore their eagle plumes, and waved their various trophies of 
former wars. 
</p><p>In front of the wigwam a great fire was built, and several 
large black kettles of venison were suspended over it.  The crowd 
were seated about it on the grass in a great circle.  Behind them 
some of the braves stood leaning against the necks of their ponies, 
their tall figures draped in loose robes which were well drawn over 
their eyes. 
</p><p>Young girls, with their faces glowing like bright red autumn 
leaves, their glossy braids falling over each ear, sat coquettishly 
beside their chaperons.  It was a custom for young Indian women to 
invite some older relative to escort them to the public feasts.  
Though it was not an iron law, it was generally observed. 
</p><p>Haraka Wambdi was a strong young brave, who had just returned 
from his first battle, a warrior.  His near relatives, to celebrate 
his new rank, were spreading a feast to which the whole of the 
Indian village was invited. 
</p><p>Holding my pretty striped blanket in readiness to throw over 
my shoulders, I grew more and more restless as I watched the gay 
throng assembling.  My mother was busily broiling a wild duck that 
my aunt had that morning brought over. 
</p><p>"Mother, mother, why do you stop to cook a small meal when we 
are invited to a feast?" I asked, with a snarl in my voice. 
</p><p>"My child, learn to wait.  On our way to the celebration we 
are going to stop at Chanyu's wigwam.  His aged mother-in-law is 
lying very ill, and I think she would like a taste of this small 
game." 
</p><p>Having once seen the suffering on the thin, pinched features 
of this dying woman, I felt a momentary shame that I had not 
remembered her before. 
</p><p>On our way, I ran ahead of my mother, and was reaching out my 
hand to 
<pb n="44"/>  
pick some purple plums that grew on a small bush, 
when I was checked by a low "Sh!" from my mother. 
</p><p>"Why, mother, I want to taste the plums!" I exclaimed, as I 
dropped my hand to my side in disappointment. 
</p><p>"Never pluck a single plum from this bush, my child, for its 
roots are wrapped around an Indian's skeleton.  A brave is buried 
here.  While he lived, he was so fond of playing the game of 
striped plum seeds that, at his death, his set of plum seeds were 
buried in his hands.  From them sprang up this little bush." 
</p><p>Eyeing the forbidden fruit, I trod lightly on the sacred 
ground, and dared to speak only in whispers, until we had gone many 
paces from it.  After that time, I halted in my ramblings whenever 
I came in sight of the plum bush.  I grew sober with awe, and was 
alert to hear a long-drawn-out whistle rise from the roots of it.  
Though I had never heard with my own ears this strange whistle of 
departed spirits, yet I had listened so frequently to hear the old 
folks describe it that I knew I should recognize it at once. 
</p><p>The lasting impression of that day, as I recall it now, is 
what my mother told me about the dead man's plum bush. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="6" id="d8"> 
<head>THE GROUND SQUIRREL.</head> 
 
<p>In the busy autumn days, my cousin Warca-Ziwin's mother came 
to our wigwam to help my mother preserve foods for our winter use.  
I was very fond of my aunt, because she was not so quiet as my 
mother.  Though she was older, she was more jovial and less 
reserved.  She was slender and remarkably erect.  While my mother's 
hair was heavy and black, my aunt had unusually thin locks. 
</p><p>Ever since I knew her, she wore a string of large blue beads 
around her neck, &mdash; beads that were precious because my uncle had 
given them to her when she was a younger woman.  She had a peculiar 
swing in her gait, caused by a long stride rarely natural to so 
slight a figure.  It was during my aunt's visit with us that my 
mother forgot her accustomed quietness, often laughing heartily at 
some of my aunt's witty remarks. 
</p><p>I loved my aunt threefold: for her hearty laughter, for the 
cheerfulness she caused my mother, and most of all for the times 
she dried my tears and held me in her lap, when my mother had 
reproved me. 
</p><p>Early in the cool mornings, just as the yellow rim of the sun 
rose above the hills, we were up and eating our breakfast.  We 
awoke so early that we saw the sacred hour when a misty smoke hung 
over a pit surrounded by an impassable sinking mire.  This strange 
smoke appeared every morning, both winter and summer; but most 
visibly in midwinter it rose immediately above the marshy spot.  By 
the time the full face of the sun appeared above the eastern 
horizon, the smoke vanished.  Even very old men, who had known this 
country the longest, said that the smoke from this pit had never 
failed a single day to rise heavenward. 
</p><p>As I frolicked about our dwelling, I used to stop suddenly, 
and with a fearful awe watch the smoking of the unknown fires.  
While the vapor was visible, I was afraid to go very far from our 
wigwam unless I went with my mother. 
</p><p>From a field in the fertile river bottom my mother and aunt 
gathered an abundant supply of corn.  Near our tepee, they spread 
a large canvas upon the grass, and dried their sweet corn in it.  
I was left to watch the corn, that nothing should disturb it.  I 
played around it with dolls made of ears of corn.  I braided their 
soft fine silk for hair, and gave them blankets as various as the 
scraps I found in my mother's workbag. 
</p><p>There was a little stranger with a black-and-yellow-striped 
coat that used 
<pb n="45"/>  
to come to the drying corn.  It was a little 
ground squirrel, who was so fearless of me that he came to one 
corner of the canvas and carried away as much of the sweet corn as 
he could hold.  I wanted very much to catch him, and rub his pretty 
fur back, but my mother said he would be so frightened if I caught 
him that he would bite my fingers.  So I was as content as he to 
keep the corn between us.  Every morning he came for more corn.  
Some evenings I have seen him creeping about our grounds; and when 
I gave a sudden whoop of recognition, he ran quickly out of sight. 
</p><p>When mother had dried all the corn she wished, then she sliced 
great pumpkins into thin rings; and these she doubled and linked 
together into long chains.  She hung them on a pole that stretched 
between two forked posts.  The wind and sun soon thoroughly dried 
the chains of pumpkin.  Then she packed them away in a case of 
thick and stiff buckskin. 
</p><p>In the sun and wind she also dried many wild fruits, &mdash;  
cherries, berries, and plums.  But chiefest among my early 
recollections of autumn is that one of the corn drying and the 
ground squirrel. 
</p><p>I have few memories of winter days, at this period of my life, 
though many of the summer.  There is one only which I can recall. 
</p><p>Some missionaries gave me a little bag of marbles.  They were 
all sizes and colors.  Among them were some of colored glass.  
Walking with my mother to the river, on a late winter day, we found 
great chunks of ice piled all along the bank.  The ice on the river 
was floating in huge pieces.  As I stood beside one large block, I 
noticed for the first time the colors of the rainbow in the crystal 
ice.  Immediately I thought of my glass marbles at home.  With my 
bare fingers I tried to pick out some of the colors, for they 
seemed so near the surface.  But my fingers began to sting with the 
intense cold, and I had to bite them hard to keep from crying. 
</p><p>From that day on, for many a moon, I believed that glass 
marbles had river ice inside of them. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="7" id="d9"> 
<head>THE BIG RED APPLES.</head> 
 
<p>The first turning away from the easy, natural flow of my life 
occurred in an early spring.  It was my eighth year; in the month 
of March, I afterward learned.  At this age I knew but one 
language, and that was my mother's native tongue. 
</p><p>From some of my playmates I heard that two paleface 
missionaries were in our village.  They were from that class of 
white men who wore big hats and carried large hearts, they said.  
Running direct to my mother, I began to question her why these two 
strangers were among us.  She told me, after I had teased much, 
that they had come to take away Indian boys and girls to the East.  
My mother did not seem to want me to talk about them.  But in a day 
or two, I gleaned many wonderful stories from my playfellows 
concerning the strangers. 
</p><p>"Mother, my friend Judewin is going home with the 
missionaries.  She is going to a more beautiful country than ours; 
the palefaces told her so!" I said wistfully, wishing in my heart 
that I too might go. 
</p><p>Mother sat in a chair, and I was hanging on her knee.  Within 
the last two seasons my big brother Dawee had returned from a three 
years' education in the East, and his coming back influenced my 
mother to take a farther step from her native way of living.  First 
it was a change from the buffalo skin to the white man's canvas 
that covered our wigwam.  Now she had given up her wigwam of 
slender poles, to live, a foreigner, in a home of clumsy logs. 
</p><p>"Yes, my child, several others besides 
<pb n="46"/>  
Judewin are 
going away with the palefaces.  Your brother said the missionaries 
had inquired about his little sister," she said, watching my face 
very closely. 
</p><p>My heart thumped so hard against my breast, I wondered if she 
could hear it. 
</p><p>"Did he tell them to take me, mother?" I asked, fearing lest 
Dawee had forbidden the palefaces to see me, and that my hope of 
going to the Wonderland would be entirely blighted. 
</p><p>With a sad, slow smile, she answered: "There!  I knew you were 
wishing to go, because Judewin has filled your ears with the white 
men's lies.  Don't believe a word they say!  Their words are sweet, 
but, my child, their deeds are bitter.  You will cry for me, but 
they will not even soothe you.  Stay with me, my little one!  Your 
brother Dawee says that going East, away from your mother, is too 
hard an experience for his baby sister." 
</p><p>Thus my mother discouraged my curiosity about the lands beyond 
our eastern horizon; for it was not yet an ambition for Letters 
that was stirring me.  But on the following day the missionaries 
did come to our very house.  I spied them coming up the footpath 
leading to our cottage.  A third man was with them, but he was not 
my brother Dawee.  It was another, a young interpreter, a paleface 
who had a smattering of the Indian language.  I was ready to run 
out to meet them, but I did not dare to displease my mother.  With 
great glee, I jumped up and down on our ground floor.  I begged my 
mother to open the door, that they would be sure to come to us.  
Alas!  They came, they saw, and they conquered! 
</p><p>Judewin had told me of the great tree where grew red, red 
apples; and how we could reach out our hands and pick all the red 
apples we could eat.  I had never seen apple trees.  I had never 
tasted more than a dozen red apples in my life; and when I heard of 
the orchards of the East, I was eager to roam among them.  The 
missionaries smiled into my eyes, and patted my head.  I wondered 
how mother could say such hard words against them. 
</p><p>"Mother, ask them if little girls may have all the red apples 
they want, when they go East," I whispered aloud, in my excitement. 
</p><p>The interpreter heard me, and answered: "Yes, little girl, the 
nice red apples are for those who pick them; and you will have a 
ride on the iron horse if you go with these good people." 
</p><p>I had never seen a train, and he knew it. 
</p><p>"Mother, I'm going East!  I like big red apples, and I want to 
ride on the iron horse!  Mother, say yes!" I pleaded. 
</p><p>My mother said nothing.  The missionaries waited in silence; 
and my eyes began to blur with tears, though I struggled to choke 
them back.  The corners of my mouth twitched, and my mother saw me. 
</p><p>"I am not ready to give you any word," she said to them.  "To-morrow I shall send you my answer by my son." 
</p><p>With this they left us.  Alone with my mother, I yielded to my 
tears, and cried aloud, shaking my head so as not to hear what she 
was saying to me.  This was the first time I had ever been so 
unwilling to give up my own desire that I refused to hearken to my 
mother's voice. 
</p><p>There was a solemn silence in our home that night.  Before I 
went to bed I begged the Great Spirit to make my mother willing I 
should go with the missionaries. 
</p><p>The next morning came, and my mother called me to her side.  
"My daughter, do you still persist in wishing to leave your 
mother?" she asked. 
</p><p>"Oh, mother, it is not that I wish to leave you, but I want to 
see the wonderful Eastern land," I answered. 
</p><p>My dear old aunt came to our house that morning, and I heard 
her say, "Let her try it." 
</p><p>I hoped that, as usual, my aunt was 
<pb n="47"/>  
pleading on my 
side.  My brother Dawee came for mother's decision.  I dropped my 
play, and crept close to my aunt. 
</p><p>"Yes, Dawee, my daughter, though she does not understand what 
it all means, is anxious to go.  She will need an education when 
she is grown, for then there will be fewer real Dakotas, and many 
more palefaces.  This tearing her away, so young, from her mother 
is necessary, if I would have her an educated woman.  The 
palefaces, who owe us a large debt for stolen lands, have begun to 
pay a tardy justice in offering some education to our children.  
But I know my daughter must suffer keenly in this experiment.  For 
her sake, I dread to tell you my reply to the missionaries.  Go, 
tell them that they may take my little daughter, and that the Great 
Spirit shall not fail to reward them according to their hearts." 
</p><p>Wrapped in my heavy blanket, I walked with my mother to the 
carriage that was soon to take us to the iron horse.  I was happy.  
I met my playmates, who were also wearing their best thick 
blankets.  We showed one another our new beaded moccasins, and the 
width of the belts that girdled our new dresses.  Soon we were 
being drawn rapidly away by the white man's horses.  When I saw the 
lonely figure of my mother vanish in the distance, a sense of 
regret settled heavily upon me.  I felt suddenly weak, as if I 
might fall limp to the ground.  I was in the hands of strangers 
whom my mother did not fully trust.  I no longer felt free to be 
myself, or to voice my own feelings.  The tears trickled down my 
cheeks, and I buried my face in the folds of my blanket.  Now the 
first step, parting me from my mother, was taken, and all my 
belated tears availed nothing. 
</p><p>Having driven thirty miles to the ferryboat, we crossed the 
Missouri in the evening.  Then riding again a few miles eastward, 
we stopped before a massive brick building.  I looked at it in 
amazement and with a vague misgiving, for in our village I had 
never seen so large a house.  Trembling with fear and distrust of 
the palefaces, my teeth chattering from the chilly ride, I crept 
noiselessly in my soft moccasins along the narrow hall, keeping 
very close to the bare wall.  I was as frightened and bewildered as 
the captured young of a wild creature. 
</p>
<signed>
                              <hi rend="italic">Zitkala-Sa.</hi>
</signed> 
 
</div1> 

</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
