<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AdaPois"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;


]>
<TEI.2 id="AdaPois">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Poison Bugaboo</title>
<title type="sort">poison bugaboo</title>
<author>Adams, Samuel Hopkins</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Charles Keller</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">40</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AdaPois</idno>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475655</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Poison Bugaboo</title>
<title level="j">Everybody's Magazine, vol. XXIII, no. 4</title>
<title type="sort">poison bugaboo</title>
<author>Samuel Hopkins Adams</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pages 518-525</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Ridgway Company Publishers</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York City, Spring and Macdougal Streets</pubPlace>
<date value="1910-10">October 1910</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa library, call no.: AP Z.E9</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1910-10">1910 October</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-08">August 1997</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Gregory Murray, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" n="1" id="d3">
	<head>The Poison Bugaboo.<lb/>
		<lb/>
		By<lb/>
		SAMUEL HOPKINS ADAMS<lb/>
		<lb/>
		AUTHOR OF<lb/>
		"THE GREAT AMERICAN FRAUD," "THE MYSTERY"<lb/>
		(WITH STEWART EDWARD WHITE), ETC.<lb/></head>
	<div2 type="introduction" id="d4">
	<pb n="518" id="AdaPois518"/>
<head>[Introduction]</head>
<p>ROMANCE revels in the peril of the unknown. Lapped about with the
armor-plate of civilization, the modern citizen muses relishingly, like
a child beguiling himself with ogre tales, upon the terrors which lie
just beyond his ken. To his mind,</p>
	
<lg type="verse">
<l>A stone's throw out on either hand,</l>
<l>And all the world is wild and strange.</l>
</lg>

<p>Avid for sensation, he peoples the remoteness of forest and
mountain with malign and destructive creatures, whence has grown up an
extensive and astonishing literature of snake and insect poison lore.

</p><p>"Deadly" is the master word of the cult.  The rattlesnake is
"deadly." The copperhead and moccasin are "deadly." So is the wholly
mythical puff adder. In hardly less degree is the tarantula "deadly,"
while varying lethal capacities are ascribed to the centipede, the
scorpion, the kissing-bug, and sundry other forms of insect life. The
whole matter is based upon the slenderest foundations. I don't mean, by
this, that these ill-famed species are wholly innocuous. It would be
highly inadvisable to snatch a kiss from a copperhead or to stroke a
tarantula's fur the wrong way. But one could do it and live to boast of
the achievement. Pseudoscience to the contrary notwithstanding, there is
no living thing within the boundaries of the United States of America
whose bite or sting is sure death or (with one possible exception) even
probable death.

</p><p>There are five varieties of venomous serpents in this country:
three of them Crotalids, and two belonging to the Elaps family.  The
Elaps are rather rare. The Crotalids (rattlesnake, moccasin, and
copperhead) are common, and of the widest geographical distribution.
Yet, on the basis of actual evidence, the amazing fact stands out that
only about eighty persons, so far as is ascertainable, have ever died
from snake bite in the United States.  Nowhere in the Civil War records
does a death from this cause appear, though hundreds of thousands of men
were living "on the country," and at a time when the serpent clan was
much more numerous than now.

</p><p>Estimates vary as to the proportion of deaths to bites. Prentiss
Willson believes that something over ten per cent. of all persons bitten
by venomous snakes in the United States die. As to how many of these
succumb, not to the venom, but to the misdirected efforts of misguided
friends at treatment&mdash;an extremely important differentiation&mdash;he lacks
the data upon which to base a reckoning. S. Weir Mitchell's figures
indicate 8.7 per cent. mortality for rattlesnake bite. This would make
the venom about as dangerous as the toxin of typhoid fever, which is not
generally regarded as a necessarily "deadly" disease.  Other writers go
as high as fifteen per cent. for the rattlesnake and as low as one per
cent. for the copperhead.

</p><p>All general estimates seem to me to leave one basic element out
of consideration&mdash;the unnoted, non-fatal snake bites. That a bite
resulting in death will eventually get itself reported is reasonably
certain. On the other hand, I am satisfied, from talking with plantation
owners in the South, with ranchmen in the West, and with woodsmen and
hunters all over the country, that, in the remoter regions, many
instances of poisoning by copperheads and the smaller rattlesnakes never
attain the dignity of being listed, so insignificant are they in their
effects. Were all these to be recorded, I believe that the mortality
ratio would fall notably.

</p><p>Although I have been interested in the subject for many years, I
have never met a man

   <pb n="519" id="AdaPois519"/>

who has seen a fatal case of snake bite.  More than this, my friend Mr.
Stewart Edward White, a noted hunter and explorer of untrodden ground in
regions infested by reptiles, has known of but one case terminating in
death which he believes to be authentic. Dr.  J. A. Mitchell, of
Victoria, Texas, one of the most experienced of field observers, has
never met with an instance of fatality from this cause. Dr. Mitchell
believes that horses always, and dogs almost always, recover from
rattlesnake bite. He confirms, from observation, the mysterious fact
that hogs exhibit absolute immunity from the venom.</p>
	</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d5">
<head>WHISKY VS. SNAKEBITE</head>

<p>Be it remembered always that death following snake bite is not
necessarily the same thing as death from snake bite. Error in treatment
plays no small part in vitiating the statistics.  For "error" read
"whisky." Whoever is primarily responsible for the hoary superstition
that liquor in huge doses is useful in snake poisoning has many a life
to answer for. Apart from any adventitious aid whatsoever, whether from
a snake or any other source, a whole bottle of raw whisky forced down
the throat of a man unaccustomed to alcohol is pretty likely to kill
him, and is absolutely certain to cause grave poisoning. Add to this
that it is given, often, in such a manner that the reaction from it
comes contemporaneously with the heart collapse caused by the venom, and
a telling commentary upon the method is suggested. It is a question
whether alcohol should ever be given in such cases without the advice of
a physician.  Certain it is that it should not be poured into the victim
in quantities limited only by the flask-contents of the bystanders.

</p><p>Several years ago I saw two interestingly contrasted cases of
copperhead bite. The first patient was a powerful, full-blooded,
temperate, Irish day-laborer who, while road-mending, was bitten on the
back of the hand between two fingers. His fellows hustled him off to a
room over a neighboring saloon, where they proceeded to administer the
classic treatment. Before the doctor arrived they had introduced a quart
and a half of whisky into a stomach unused to anything stronger than
beer in small quantities. Six hours later, when I saw the man through
the wreckage of chairs, tables, and bedding, four battered friends were
trying to hold him down. They thought he was having convulsions from the
snake venom. He wasn't.  He was having delirium tremens from the whisky.
His arm and shoulder were purple and swollen. Later he collapsed

</p><p>"Will he die?" I asked the doctor.

</p><p>"He won't die of the bite, but I think he will of the whisky,"
replied the disgusted practitioner.

</p><p>But he didn't. His splendid physique pulled him through. It was
long, however, before he wholly recovered from the effects of the two
poisons.

</p><p>This was in a Hudson River town. Only a few miles away a negro
boy, shortly after, was struck by a copperhead on the bare leg. The
wound was a deep, double-fanged puncture.  While the boy's father rushed
for whisky, his mother ran for the doctor. The doctor got there first.
He opened up the wound and rubbed in permanganate of potash to oxidize
the venom and destroy its toxic properties.  When I talked with the boy,
two days later, he was hobbling about on a crutch, and the swelling had
almost subsided. Setting the boy's lesser age and resistant power
against the fact of the laborer's being bitten in a worse place (for
crotaline venom is much more effective in an upper limb or extremity
than in a lower), we have a fairly illustrative instance of the relative
merits of alcoholic and non-alcoholic measures.</p>

</div2><div2 type="section" n="3" id="d6">
<head>WHEN RATTLESNAKES KILL</head>

<p>Thirteen cases of death following rattlesnake and copperhead bite
in which satisfactory clinical data were obtainable, are given by
Prentiss Willson. Of the victims, five were young children, one was a
fourteen-year-old boy, one a chronic drunkard, and one a leper who
submitted to the stroke of a captive rattlesnake in the mad hope that it
would cure his affliction. It did&mdash;in twenty-four hours. Of the
remaining five, three were dosed with alcohol in large quantities. In
several of the cases, notably those of the children, there seemed to be
at least an even chance of recovery, when the ligatures binding the
affected limb were loosened to relieve the pain, with quickly fatal
results. Two of the fatalities were attributed, not immediately to the
venom, but to the secondary blood-poisoning, this being the case with
the only copperhead bite in the list.

</p><p>Death resulting typically from crotaline poisoning occurred in
two instances, one the fourteen-year-old boy, who was struck by a

   <pb n="520" id="AdaPois520"/>

large rattlesnake and died in six hours, despite skilled and prompt
medical attendance; the other, a Dr. Post, into whose veins, it would
appear, the poison entered immediately, since a jet of blood spurted
from the wound inflicted by the captive rattlesnake.  The man passed
from great agony into coma, from which he never rallied, death ensuing
in five hours after the bite. There is nothing in these data to indicate
that a full-grown man in normal health, and with proper treatment, will
succumb to crotaline poisoning unless the venom enters a vein, direct.

</p><p>In the matter of the comparative potency of snake poisons, there
are apparent contradictions.  In the order of recorded fatalities, the
rattlesnake ranks easily first, with the water moccasin a rather distant
second, and the copperhead a very poor third. Yet experiments upon
animals indicate that moccasin venom is five times as powerful as
rattlesnake, though only three times as powerful as copperhead. Taking
the cobra as the basis of estimate, it requires only twice as much
moccasin venom as it does cobra poison to kill a guinea pig, whereas it
requires six times as much copperhead and ten times as much rattlesnake
virus. Why, then, is the rattler pre-eminent over its more virulent
cousins?  Probably for two reasons&mdash;the greater amount of venom
secreted, and the superior power with which the rattler drives its fangs
home.</p>

</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="4" id="d7">
<head>NO VIPERS IN THIS COUNTRY</head>

<p>Fully as much terror attaches, in the country districts, to the
puff adder or sand viper as to the rattlesnake or copperhead. This is a
suggestive bit of superstition, since there's no such thing as an adder
or viper on the Western hemisphere and never has been one, unless it
came, carefully pickled, in a jar.  What passes for the supposedly
deadly reptile is the common hog-nosed or bull snake. It is about as
dangerous as an infuriated rabbit.  But it puts up one of the best
"bluffs" known to natural history. When caught at its favorite
occupation of basking in the open, without convenient avenue of escape,
it flattens its head, and strikes right and left, blowing and hissing
with an aspect much more terrifying than that of the truly venomous
species.  Then, when the objects of its fury have taken to trees or
adjacent fences, it glides quietly away into the grass and effaces
itself. Any one who has the nerve to look it between the eyes may
uncover its pretense. For by this token may be known the real Crotalids
from the mock: a small but distinct pit between eye and nostril. Lacking
this mark, no ventral crawler in the land of the free need cause a
flutter in the most timid breast, with one notable exception.</p>

</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="5" id="d8">
<head>BEWARE THE ELAPS</head>

<p>Shun, as you would a rabid dog, a pretty little red-and-black
banded serpent about as thick as your thumb. If any living creature
whose habitat is the United States deserves the epithet "deadly," it is
the Elaps. Two species are known; the harlequin snake, which ranges
throughout the Gulf states to Texas and up the Mississippi River to
Ohio, and the Sonoran coral snake, found in the Southwest only. By a
strange perversion of facts, while the harmless hog-nosed snake enjoys a
repute of terror, the Elaps, most dangerous of all American reptiles, is
commonly regarded as harmless.  Partly this is due to its slight and
graceful prettiness, partly to its innocent-appearing head, which shows
no flattening (the popularly understood mark of the venomous species),
and partly to its lethargic and peaceful disposition. Experimenters
wishing to secure the venom of the Elaps often find it difficult to
rouse the snake to striking wrath.

</p><p>Very few instances are known of Elaps bite, but those few
unquestionably set this ornamental creature in a class by itself, among
American Ophidia, for "results." Out of eight well-authenticated cases
of Elaps bite, six of the victims died. This is believed to indicate a
falsely large percentage, however, the scientific estimate of mortality
being somewhere between twenty-five and fifty per cent.

</p><p>A government scientist tells me of a curious result from
coral-snake bite which came under his notice. The victim, who was
handling the reptile preparatory to photographing it, apparently
overstepped the bounds of its habitual forbearance, for it fastened upon
his finger with such determination that it had to be pried off. The man
soon became unconscious, but rallied, and, after three days of dubious
condition, recovered. Every year since, at about the anniversary of the
bite, an ulcer forms upon the finger and the nail sloughs off. I have
heard of similar recurrent effects from crotaline poisoning, but none
scientifically attested, as is this phenomenon.

</p><p>Before passing from the subject of snakes,

   <pb n="521" id="AdaPois521"/>

let me make one point clear. While the venomous snakes of this country
are by no means "deadly" in the ordinary sense of the term, their bite
is always serious, both in its immediate effects and in the possibility
of after effects. The bitten person should get to a physician at once.
The immediate treatment is prompt incision and sucking of the wound.
Permanganate of potash for rubbing into the bitten place should always
be carried by persons traveling in a snake-infested country.  If the
bite is on a limb, a light ligature will check the spread of the venom.
Use whisky sparingly, if at all, and then only in case of complete
collapse.

</p><p>The local treatments are most effective while the venom is still
around the site of the bite, and will reduce the injurious effects
considerably. But after half an hour or so the absorption of the venom
becomes more general and the local treatments ineffective.  When the
venom once enters into general circulation no chemicals or medication
can neutralize its effects, except a specific antivenin, such as has
been prepared by Dr. Noguchi at the Rockefeller Institute in New York.
Antivenin is the only antidote that can counteract the action of venom
anywhere in the body. It finds the venom wherever it is present and
neutralizes it there, without producing any ill effects on the
system.</p>

</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="6" id="d9">
<head>GILA MONSTER NOT SO MONSTROUS</head>

<p>Dissension and discussion have raged for years about the hideous
head of the Gila monster. This great lizard of the Southwest has been
pronounced absolutely deadly by one set of partisans, and absolutely
harmless by another. Somewhere between lies the truth. If any human
being has actually been bitten by a heloderma, the event has either
escaped notice or has been so hedged about with obstructive legend as to
have forfeited scientific credence.  But the saurian itself has been
studied and dissected, and its venom has been analyzed.  The venom is
related to snake poison, but is neither crotaline nor elapine. From
animal experiments it is thought that it might be fatal to man under
unfavorable conditions. There are no fangs proper. The poison gland is
in the lower jaw, instead of in the upper, as in snakes, and its product
is projected through small ducts which open in the gums outside the
teeth. The Gila monster has the grip of a bulldog. Torture will not
loosen its hold, once fastened on. It is through this intimate contact
that the venom works into the wounds.

</p><p>Fortunately, the lizard is slow to anger, and prefers flight to
battle, so it is likely to be long before science has an opportunity of
studying the effect of its envenomed jaw-clamp upon man. There are a few
vaguely rumored reports of prospectors having perished, in the desert,
of Gila monster poison, but these are so confused with symptoms
suspiciously resembling alcoholic poisoning as to lead Dr. R. W.
Shufeldt, an authority upon the Reptilia, to remark that "a quart of raw
whisky, practically given at one dose, may prove more fatal than the
bite of ten helodermas."

</p><p>Almost any kind of an insect bite or sting <hi
rend="italic">may</hi> prove fatal. So may a pin scratch, if the
blood of the subject be in bad enough condition.  There is a
well-substantiated case of a trained nurse who died from blood poisoning
following a mosquito bite. Ant bite has resulted fatally, as has a
single sting from the common wasp. No one, however, considers these
everyday insects as "deadly." But substitute "scorpion" for "ant," and
"centipede" for "wasp," and shrieks of dismay rise from the general
throat. Yet perhaps there is no other variety of harmful creature whose
reputation rests upon so meager a foundation as that of these two.

</p><p>True, an El Paso report claims that a man stung by a whip
scorpion died in twelve hours; but the details are so vague as to be in
a high degree unconvincing. Dr. Eugene Murray-Aaron, a witness of
unimpeachable scientific competency, describes the sting, after several
personal encounters with the vigorous tropical species, as no worse than
that of a large hornet. Dr. L. B. Rowland, of Florida, says:  "My wife
has been stung several times [by the common scorpion]. It is like a wasp
sting, only."</p>

</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="7" id="d10">
<head>THE SCORPION'S STING</head>

<p>The Mexican scorpion enjoys an evil repute, which, from personal
observation, I consider greatly exaggerated. Stewart Edward White was so
obliging as to afford me excellent opportunity of judging, in the course
of a recent hunting trip which we took together in a hot and remote
Mexican desert. Mr. White, in the process of disrobing, sat down upon a
brown scorpion, an inch and a half long.  The scorpion punctured Mr.
White twice.  I noted his symptoms. They were chiefly surprise and
indignation. Within half an hour

   <pb n="522" id="AdaPois522"/>

he was asleep, and on the following day he was riding a mule. The
scorpion, however, died.

</p><p>With respect to the centipede, satisfactory data are difficult to
obtain. Some scientists whose observations are worthy of note state that
the legs of this curious creature secrete a poison, and that their trail
over human flesh is marked by a sort of rash, sometimes followed by
fever. As showing that this is not an invariable phenomenon, I may set
the circumstantial account given me by Captain Robert Kemp Wright, who,
at his place at Pitch Lake, Trinidad, saw a good-sized centipede crawl
across the forehead of his sleeping son. Not daring to make a move, as
the centipede is supposed to strike very swiftly, Captain Wright was
compelled to stand still while it slowly made its way to the pillow and
thence to the floor, where it was killed. The boy, who had neither waked
nor moved, showed absolutely no trace of the reptile's course.</p>

</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="8" id="d11">
<head>THE DEADLY TARANTULA&mdash;IN PRINT</head>

<p>The only direct evidence which has come to me regarding the bite
of the hundred-legged crawler was from an English naturalist whom I met
in Venezuela. He was bitten on the ankle by a centipede nearly a foot
long. So severe was the laceration that his sock was clotted with blood
before he could get it off.  The two punctures were marked. Almost
immediately the ankle began to swell. The pain he describes as being
equal to a bad toothache. It kept him awake all that night.  He had some
fever, which, however, he attributes rather to the loss of sleep than to
any specific action of the poison, as there were no other general
symptoms. In the morning the pain had abated a good deal, and he
believes that he could have gone about his pursuits had he been able to
get his sock and shoe on. He noted some discoloration about the wound.
Late in the afternoon he was hobbling about.  A week in a carpet slipper
was the extent of disability which he suffered. On these evidences it
would seem just, for the present, to set down the scorpion and the
centipede as painful, rather than dangerous, assailants.

</p><p>Diseased imagination could invent no creature more horrific of
appearance than the tarantula. Its bristling and hostile aspect, the
swift ferocity of its rush, its great size, and its enthusiastic
preference for combat as against flight, are sufficient to account for
the fear and respect in which it is generally held.  But, though several
species of the huge spider are native to the United States, and others
frequently drop out of banana bunches from South or Central America, to
the discomfiture of the unsuspecting grocer, no authentic instance of
death from tarantula poison in this country is obtainable. St. Louis
papers please copy, particularly that one which, several years ago,
announced in appropriately black headlines:<lb/>

<lb/>
<hi rend="bold">IN TWO WEEKS<lb/>
Three Men Have Died From Bites of Tarantulas,</hi><lb/>
<lb/>

proceeding to explain that the victims were banana handlers in the
wholesale fruit district. No names were supplied&mdash;a common phenomenon in
this class of obituary notice.  Search in the coroner's records failed
to bring to light any case of the sort, and an exhaustive inquiry in the
fruit district was equally unproductive. The report was a pure fake.

</p><p>Apparently of the same nature is the "news story" of a
Californian who, presumably mistaking a tarantula for a fragrant
floweret, was bitten on the nose and "died in great agony."  That, of
course, is the proper way to die under such circumstances. They all do
it&mdash;in print.

</p><p>Now let us see about the "agony." Herbert H. Smith, the
naturalist and collector, saw a man bitten on the bare foot by a
tarantula (Mygale) so hard as to draw blood.  There was very little
swelling, and the man paid no heed to the occurrence, but went on with
his work.

</p><p>I have talked with a Southern Pacific Railroad fireman who was
jabbed on the wrist by a large tarantula. Some years before, he had been
stung on the cheek by a "bald" hornet.  He wasn't inclined to make any
choice between the two except that the tarantula (not the wound) "looked
a d&mdash; sight more scary." He didn't let the bite interfere with his
job, even for the day.

</p><p>On the other hand, Dr. Murray-Aaron records serious symptoms
following two bites upon the hand by a large female trapdoor tarantula;
pain comparable to that of the worst earache, involuntary twitching of
arms, legs, lips, and tongue, great swelling and discoloration of the
hand and forearm, and considerable suffering for four days, with
occasionally recurrent pains for a month. This, however, was in Haiti.
And even there, he believes, death never follows tarantula bite unless
the subject is in a depleted state of resistance from blood-disease or
other cause.

   <pb n="523" id="AdaPois523"/>

</p><p>Under the heading "Fatal Spider Bite" there is a considerable and
interesting newspaper bibliography. The details do not analyze well.
Often the name of the supposed victim doesn't appear; and where names
and specifications are given, the evidence is hardly sufficient, as a
rule, to convict the insect of any crime more serious than mayhem. For
example, a young woman in Brooklyn awoke one morning to find a swollen
spot on her body. On the bed was (according to allegation) a spider.
Some ten days later she died.  For a long period she had been in ill
health.  Yet the death was credited to the spider, though specific
symptoms of venomous poisoning were lacking.

</p><p>The instance of a young woman in an Eastern state is significant.
Thrusting her foot into an old slipper, she felt a sharp jab upon the
point of her index digit.  Upon hasty removal of the footgear, she saw,
or supposed she saw, a large and ferocious spider dart forth. This, to
her mind, was evidence both conclusive and damning. Seizing upon the
carving knife, she promptly cut off her perfectly good toe, bound up the
wound, and sent for the doctor, thereby blossoming out in next day's
print as a "Heroine who had Saved her own life by her Marvelous Presence
of Mind." The thoughtful will wonder, however, whether the lady wouldn't
have got at the real root of the matter by cutting off her head instead
of her toe.</p>

</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="9" id="d12">
<head>SPIDER HYSTERIA</head>

<p>Imagination and terror undoubtedly account for certain general
symptoms in this class of injury. Colonel Nicholas Pike, a competent
observer, records a case of a man slapping his hand down upon a window
sill and feeling a lively stab in the palm. At the same moment a small
spider ran across the back of his fingers and was captured. There was a
distinct puncture in the hand. Here, then, was a definite case, where
the wound and the insect were both in evidence. But examination of the
arachnid's fangs satisfied Colonel Pike that they were far too small and
weak to penetrate the tough skin where the wound was. Meantime the
victim exhibited the classic symptoms of venomous poisoning:  numbness,
nausea, chills, and threatened collapse. A physician, being summoned,
examined both the victim and the accused, and took Colonel Pike's view
that the spider was innocent. The man was wrathful, with the indignation
of terror. He said he guessed he knew whether he was bitten or not, and
that the physician's business was to eschew idle speculations and go
ahead and save his life if it wasn't already too late. Thereupon the
doctor opened up the wound and extracted a section of a fine needle. The
other half was found sticking in the window sill where a careless
seamstress had fixed it. The spider had been a fortuitous arrival. The
man made one of the quickest recoveries recorded.</p>

</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="10" id="d13">
<head>THE "RED-SPOT"&mdash;DANGEROUS</head>

<p>Strangely enough, the one really dangerous spider on the American
continent is small, obscure, and practically unknown to popular or
journalistic hysteria. Latrodectus mactans is its scientific name. It is
about the size of a large pea, black with a red spot on the back&mdash;a
useful danger signal&mdash;and spins a small web in outhouses or around
wood-piles. So far as is known, its poison is the most virulent and
powerful, drop for drop, secreted by any living creature. Cobra virus,
in the minute quantity which the Latrodectus's glands contain, would
probably have no appreciable effect upon man; whereas the tiny spider's
venom, in the volume injected by the cobra's stroke, would slay a herd
of elephants. Were this little-known crawler as large as the common
black hunting spider of our gardens and lawns, its bite would be almost
invariably fatal. Happily, the "red-spot's" fangs, being small and weak,
can with difficulty penetrate the skin, and are able to inject venom in
dangerous quantity only when the bite is inflicted upon some
tender-skinned portion of the body. Nevertheless, fatalities consequent
upon the bite of this insect are sufficiently well attested to take rank
as established scientific facts.

</p><p>One of the most detailed comes from an intelligent farmer of
Greensboro, North Carolina. A workman in his employ, while hauling wood,
brushed at something crawling upon his neck and felt a sharp, stinging
sensation.  He found a small, black spider with a red spot.  This was at
8.30 A.M. Presently, ten small white pimples appeared about the bitten
spot, though no puncture was visible and there was no swelling. The pain
soon passed, but returned in three hours and became general, finally
settling in the abdomen and producing violent cramps. At one o'clock the
man had a spasmodic attack. Two hours later he had so far recovered as
to be able to go back to

   <pb n="524" id="AdaPois524"/>

work, for an hour. Then the spasms took him again; he sank into coma,
and died between ten and eleven o'clock that evening, about fourteen
hours after the bite. At no time were there local symptoms or swelling,
other than the slight eruption, but the neck, left arm, and breast are
reported as having assumed a stonelike hardness.

</p><p>The same farmer had seen, three years previous, a negro who had
been bitten upon the ankle by a "red-spot" and who suffered from
diminishingly severe spasmodic attacks for three weeks. The white
pimples appeared in this case also. The negro recovered, but the
eruption reappeared for years thereafter whenever he was overheated.

</p><p>Recoveries from Latrodectus bite are much more common, in the
records, than deaths.  Dr. Corson, of Savannah, Georgia, reports six
cases, characterized by agonizing pains, spasmodic contractions like
those of tetanus, and grave general symptoms. All recovered.  From
Anaheim, California, a fatal case is reported by Dr. Bickford, death
occurring twenty hours after the bite. William A. Ball, of San
Bernardino, California, gives a vivid account of his sensations after
being bitten on the groin by a red-spotted spider, the data being
attested by his physician. Shortly after being bitten, he began to
suffer great agony, with convulsive contractions of the muscles.

</p><p>"The pains in my hip-joints, chest, and thighs grew rapidly more
violent, until it seemed that the bones in these parts of my body were
being crushed to fragments." He was seriously ill for ten days.</p>

</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="11" id="d14">
<head>WORSE THAN THE "DEADLY" COPPERHEAD</head>

<p>It may be that only under certain uncomprehended conditions is
the venom of the Latrodectus effective. Inoculation of guinea pigs with
the poison has been without any resultant symptoms. Scientific
experimenters have suffered themselves to be bitten and have experienced
no ill effects. The foreign cousins of the American species, however,
have as evil a repute as the "mactans." The "katipo," found in sedges on
the beach of New Zealand, is dreaded by the Maoris, who traditionally
refuse to sleep nearer than half a stone's throw from the water, that
being the extent of range of the spider. The Latrodecti of Corsica,
Algeria, and France are infamous in the lore of the country folk, which
fact must be regarded as strongly evidential, when their insignificant
appearance is taken into account.

</p><p>Only in America is there no popular fear of this really
formidable little creature. Yet it is found in almost every part of the
United States, though by no means one of the commoner spiders. In the
past five years I have seen two specimens at my country place in central
New York, and have heard of a dozen others. If people understood
generally that this rather ornamental insect is both more perilous to
life and health, and rather more prone to attack human beings, than the
superstitiously dreaded "deadly" copperhead, there would probably be a
heavy mortality in the Latrodectus family at the hands of energetic
house-cleaners.</p>

</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="12" id="d15">
<head>THE RISE OF THE KISSING-BUG</head>

<p>Years ago the United States Bureau of Entomology received from an
exasperated clergyman in Georgia a dead insect, enclosed in this note:

</p><p>"Prof. Riley: What is this devil? He sailed down on my hedge. I
took hold of his lone front leg, and as quick as lightning he speared me
under my thumb nail and I dropped him. My thumb and whole arm are still
paining me . . . "

</p><p>The miscreant was a fine specimen of Reduvius personatus, the
cone-nosed blood-sucker, soon thereafter to achieve heights of newspaper
notoriety together with its cousin, Melanolestes picipes, as the
"kissing-bug."  How many persons died (in type) from kissing-bug bites
in the year of enlightened civilization, 1899, will never be known. But
from far and near, from California and Connecticut and the Carolinas,
from Minnesota and Maryland and Maine, came startling reports of this
hitherto unfamed creature's depredations upon the human countenance.
Thereby the spider family was relieved of much unmerited odium, for it
is more than suspected by entomologists that a large proportion of
so-called spider bites are really the work of the more vicious but less
formidable-appearing kissing-bug, as is often evidenced by the nature of
the puncture.

</p><p>The kissing-bug is about half an inch in length, flat-backed,
shaped in geometrically regular angles, and armed with a large, hard
beak. It is this beak which does the damage, for the kissing-bug is a
fighter and will risk a prod at anything that gives it cause of offense.
Testimony is not lacking that it sometimes punctures the human epidermis
with a view

   <pb n="525" id="AdaPois525"/>

to obtaining blood at first hand instead of
from its natural prey.

</p><p>But the curious feature of the kissing-bug's bite is its after
effect. Neither the southern Reduvius nor the northern Melanolestes
possesses any venom apparatus. Now, an insect without fangs (or sting),
duct, and poison gland, can no more envenom the object of its attack
than a fish can kick a man to death.  Yet we find such authorities as
Dr. L. O.  Howard, the United States Entomologist, Professor Le Conte,
Mr. Charles Drury, of Cincinnati, and others, including a mass of
medical witnesses, declaring from first-hand observation that the
kissing-bug bite causes much swelling and severe pain. Le Conte, indeed,
compares the effect to snake bite, and states that people are seriously
affected for a week. A case is recorded from Holland, South Carolina,
where there were vomiting and marked weakness. Mr. Schwartz, an expert
of the Bureau of Entomology at Washington, was bitten twice upon the
hand and testifies to the painful effects. In 1899, when the species was
very common in Washington, the Emergency Hospital had a long list of
patients who appeared on the records under the heading, "Insect
Bite."</p>

</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="13" id="d16">
<head>THE DECLINE OF THE KISSING-BUG</head>

<p>Thus was started the general "scare," a reporter with a keen nose
for news having made a legitimate "sensation" from the repeated entries
on the hospital roster.  From Washington it spread over the country, and
became the topic of the day, until any insect bite or sting&mdash;mosquito,
hornet, bedbug, or whatnot&mdash;was magnified by the hysteria of the patient
and the credulousness of the public into a "dangerous" instance of
kissing-bug poisoning. Reports of fatal cases, however, invariably
proved to be canards.

</p><p>For explanation of the marked local symptoms resultant upon
attack by the insect, science has been hard put to it. The general
symptoms, observed in a few cases, where violent, may probably be
ascribed to shock and nervousness. But the marked swelling and pain
cannot be thus dismissed. Medical men believe that the insect, in its
various prowlings for food, thrusts its exploring beak into decaying
animal and vegetable matter and thus, in a sense, so poisons it that
when it comes into contact with human blood, a rapid local infection is
set up&mdash;not through any specific poison, as in spider bite or bee sting,
but by the agency of the putrefactive germs collected on the weapon.

</p><p>Not the least interesting phase of the kissing-bug scare is the
rapidity and completeness of its decadence. It is but ten years ago that
the newspapers rang with it; that victims of the bite, in every city,
were fleeing, white-faced and racked with forebodings, to doctor or
hospital. To-day, both the Melanolestes and the "conenose" are abroad in
the land.  Doubtless, upon provocation, they are "spearing" others as
they speared the outraged clergyman. But that's all. The bepunctured
ones do not seek the consolations of medical or journalistic attention.
They put a little wet mud or peroxide on the place and let it go at
that. Exit another bogy!</p>

</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="14" id="d17">
<head>OUR REAL POISON PERIL</head>


<p>One venomous creature there is in this country which may justly
be termed a public peril, in the widest sense. Proportionately to
population, more victims fall to it yearly in the United States than to
the dreaded cobra in India. Some twelve thousand Americans are killed
every year by its bite. Three hundred thousand more are made seriously
ill from the after effects. Unfortunately, the virus works so slowly
that alarm is stilled. The victims do not sicken at once. The bite is
forgotten; but ten days or two weeks after, the subject falls into a
fever. His blood is poisoned within him. Eventually, in extreme cases,
he becomes delirious, succumbs to a stupor, and dies.

</p><p>Yet, because there is nothing horrific to the sensation-loving
imagination in the malaria-bearing mosquito, public inertia or ignorance
tolerates it with a grin and permits it to breed in city and country
alike throughout the length and breadth of the nation. Compared with it,
as a real menace, all the combined brood of snakes, scorpions,
centipedes, tarantulas, and other pet bugaboos of our childish
romanticism are utterly negligible; are as figment to reality, as shadow
to substance. It is perhaps characteristic of our wryly humorous
American temperament that we should have invested the unimportant danger
with all the shuddering attributes of horror, and have made of the real
peril a joke to be perennially hailed with laughter in a thousand
thoughtless prints.</p>

</div2>
</div1>



</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

