<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AndDoor"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;

]>

<TEI.2 id="AndDoor">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Door of the Trap</title>
<title type="sort">door of the trap</title>
<author>Anderson, Sherwood, 1876-1941</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">27</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AndDoor</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475670</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Door Trap</title>
<title level="j">The Dial</title>
<title type="sort">door trap</title>
<author>Sherwood Anderson</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Dial Publishing Co. Inc.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1920">1920</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Text originally appeared in the May, 1920 issue
of The Dial, Volume 68, No. 5</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions
for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1920-05">May, 1920</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-04">April, 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Matthew G. Kirschenaum, University of Virginia Library
Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI.2-conformant header and tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="work" id="d3">
	<pb n="567"/>
<head>THE DOOR OF THE TRAP.<lb/>
BY SHERWOOD ANDERSON</head>

     <p>WINIFRED WALKER understood some things clearly enough.  She
understood that when a man is put behind iron bars he is in prison.
Marriage was marriage to her.</p>
     <p>It was that to her husband Hugh Walker, too, as he found out.
Still he didn't understand.  It might have been better had he
understood.  Then he might at least have found himself.  He didn't.
After his marriage five or six years passed like shadows of wind-blown trees playing on a wall.  He was in a drugged, silent state.
In the morning and evening every day he saw his wife.  Occasionally
something happened within him and he kissed her.  Three children
were born.  He taught mathematics in the little college at Union
Valley, Illinois, and waited.</p>
     <p>For what?  He began to ask himself that question.  It came to
him at first faintly like an echo.  Then it became an insistent
question.  "I want answering," the question seemed to say.  "Stop
fooling along.  Give your attention to me."</p>
     <p>Hugh walked through the streets of the Illinois town.  "Well,
I'm married.  I have children," he muttered.</p>
     <p>He went home to his own house.  He did not have to live within
his income from the little college and so the house was rather
large and comfortably furnished.  There was a negro woman who took
care of his children and another who cooked and did housework.  One
of the women was in the habit of crooning low soft negro songs.
Sometimes Hugh stopped at the house door and listened.  He could
see through the glass in the door into the room where his family
was gathered.  Two children played with blocks on the floor.  His
wife sat sewing.  The old negress sat in a rocking chair with his
youngest child, a baby, in her arms.  The whole room seemed under
the spell of the crooning voice.  Hugh fell under the spell.  He
waited in silence.  The voice carried him far away somewhere, into
forests, along the edges of swamps.  There was nothing very
definite about his thinking.  He would have given a good deal to be
able to be definite.</p>
<pb n="568"/>
     <p>He went inside the house.  "Well, here I am," his mind seemed
to say, "here I am.  This is my house, these are my children."</p>
     <p>He looked at his wife Winifred.  She had grown a little plump
since their marriage.  "Perhaps it is the mother in her coming out,
she has had three children," he thought.</p>
     <p>The crooning old negro woman went away, taking the youngest
child with her.  He and Winifred held a fragmentary conversation.
"Have you been well to-day, dear?" she asked.  "Yes," he answered.
     </p><p>If the two older children were intent on their play his chain
of thought was not broken.  His wife never broke it as the children
did when they came running to pull and tear at him.  Throughout the
early evening, after the children went to bed, the surface of the
shell of him was not broken at all.  A brother college professor
and his wife came in or he and Winifred went to a neighbour's
house.  There was talk.  Even when he and Winifred were alone
together in the house there was talk.  "The shutters are becoming
loose," she said.  The house was an old one and was furnished with
green shutters.  They were continually coming loose and at night
blew back and forth on their hinges making a loud banging noise.
     </p><p>Hugh made some remark.  He said he would see a carpenter about
the shutters.  Then his mind began playing away out of his wife's
presence, out of the house, in another sphere.  "I am a house and
my shutters are loose," his mind said.  He thought of himself as a
living thing inside a shell, trying to break out.  To avoid
distracting conversation he got a book and pretended to read.  When
his wife had also begun to read he watched her closely, intently.
Her nose was so and so and her eyes so and so.  She had a little
habit with her hands.  When she became lost in the pages of a book
the hand crept up to her cheek, touched it and then was put down
again.  Her hair was not in very good order.  Since her marriage
and the coming of the children she had not taken good care of her
body.  When she read her body slumped down in the chair.  It became
bag-like.  She was one whose race has been run.
     </p><p>Hugh's mind played all about the figure of his wife but did
not really approach the woman who sat before him.  It was so with
his children.  Sometimes, just for a moment, they were living
things to him, things as alive as his own body.  Then for long
periods they seemed to go far away like the crooning voice of the
negress. </p><pb n="569"/>
     <p>It was odd that the negress was always real enough.  He felt
an understanding existed between himself and the negress.  She was
outside his life.  He could look at her as at a tree.  Sometimes in
the evening when she had been putting the children to bed in the
upper part of the house and when he sat with a book in his hand
pretending to read, the old black woman came softly through the
room, going toward the kitchen.  She did not look at Winifred, but
at Hugh.  He thought there was a strange, soft light in her old
eyes.  "I understand you, my son," her eyes seemed to say.
     </p><p>Hugh was determined to get his life cleaned up if he could
manage it.  "All right, then," he said, as though speaking to a
third person in the room.  He was quite sure there was a third
person there and that the third person was within himself, inside
his body.  He addressed the third person.
     </p><p>"Well, there is this woman, this person I married, she has the
air of something accomplished," he said, as though speaking aloud.
Sometimes it almost seemed to him he had spoken aloud and he looked
quickly and sharply at his wife.  She continued reading, lost in
her book.  "That may be it," he went on.  "She has had these
children.  They are accomplished facts to her.  They came out of
her body, not out of mine.  Her body has done something.  Now it
rests.  If she is becoming a little bag-like, that's all right."
     </p><p>He got up and making some trivial excuse got out of the room
and out of the house.  In his youth and young manhood the long
periods of walking straight ahead through the country, that had
come upon him like visitations of some recurring disease, had
helped.  Walking solved nothing.  It only tired his body, but when
his body was tired he could sleep.  After many days of walking and
sleeping something occurred.  The reality of life was in some queer
way re-established in his mind.  Some little thing happened.  A man
walking in the road before him threw a stone at a dog that ran
barking out of a farm-house.  It was evening perhaps, and he walked
in a country of low hills.  Suddenly he came out upon the top of
one of the hills.  Before him the road dipped down into darkness
but to the west, across fields, there was a farm-house.  The sun
had gone down, but a faint glow lit the western horizon.  A woman
came out of the farm-house and went toward a barn.  He could not
see her figure distinctly.  She seemed to be carrying something, no
doubt a milk pail; she was going to a barn to milk a cow.</p><pb n="570"/>
     <p>The man in the road who had thrown the stone at the farm dog
had turned and seen Hugh in the road behind him.  He was a little
ashamed of having been afraid of the dog.  For a moment he seemed
about to wait and speak to Hugh and then was overcome with
confusion and hurried away.  He was a middle-aged man, but quite
suddenly and unexpectedly he looked like a boy.
     </p><p>As for the farm woman, dimly seen going toward a distant barn,
she also stopped and looked toward him.  It was impossible she
should have seen him.  She was dressed in white and he could see
her but dimly against the blackish green of the trees of an orchard
behind her.  Still she stood looking and seemed to look directly
into his eyes.  He had a queer sensation of her having been lifted
by an unseen hand and brought to him.  It seemed to him he knew all
about her life, all about the life of the man who had thrown the
stone at the dog.
     </p><p>In his youth when life had stepped out of his grasp Hugh had
walked and walked until several such things had occurred and then
suddenly he was all right again and could again work and live among
men.
     </p><p>After his marriage and after such an evening as the one here
described he started walking rapidly as soon as he left the house.
As quickly as possible he got out of town and struck out along a
road that led over the rolling prairie.  "Well, I can't walk for
days and days as I did once," he thought.  "There are certain facts
in life and I must face facts.  Winifred, my wife, is a fact, and
my children are facts.  I must get my fingers on facts.  I must
live by them and with them.  It is the way lives are lived."
     </p><p>Hugh got out of town and on to a road that ran between
cornfields.  He was an athletic-looking man and wore loose-fitting
clothes.  He went along distraught and puzzled.  In a way he felt
like a man capable of taking a man's place in life and in another
way he didn't at all.
     </p><p>The country spread out, wide, in all directions.  It was
always night when he walked thus and he could not see, but the
realization of distances was always with him.  "Everything goes on
and on but I stand still," he thought.  He had been a professor in
the little college for six years.  Young men and women had come
into a room and he had taught them.  It was nothing.  Words and
figures had been played with.  An effort had been made to arouse
minds.<pb n="571"/>
     </p><p>For what?
     </p><p>There was the old question, always coming back, always wanting
answering as a little animal wants food.  Hugh gave up trying to
answer.  He walked rapidly, trying to grow physically tired.  He
made his mind attend to little things in the effort to forget
distances.  One night he got out of the road and walked completely
around a cornfield.  He counted the stalks in each hill of corn and
computed the number of stalks in a whole field.  "It should yield
twelve hundred bushels of corn, that field," he said to himself
dumbly, as though it mattered to him.  He pulled a little handful
of cornsilk out of the top of an ear of corn and played with it.
He tried to fashion himself a yellow moustache.  "I'd be quite a
fellow with a trim yellow moustache," he thought.
     </p><p>One day in his class-room Hugh suddenly began to look with new
interest at his pupils.  A young girl attracted his attention.  She
sat beside the son of a Union Valley merchant and the young man was
writing something on the back of a book.  She looked at it and then
turned her head away.  The young man waited.
     </p><p>It was winter and the merchant's son had asked the girl to go
with him to a skating party.  Hugh, however, did not know that.  He
felt suddenly old.  When he asked the girl a question she was
confused.  Her voice trembled.
     </p><p>When the class was dismissed an amazing thing happened.  He
asked the merchant's son to stay for a moment and when the two were
alone together in the room he grew suddenly and furiously angry.
His voice was, however, cold and steady.  "Young man," he said,
"you do not come into this room to write on the back of a book and
waste your time.  If I see anything of the kind again I'll do
something you don't expect.  I'll throw you out through a window,
that's what I'll do."
     </p><p>Hugh made a gesture and the young man went away, white and
silent.  Hugh felt miserable.  For several days he thought about
the girl who had quite accidentally attracted his attention.  "I'll
get acquainted with her.  I'll find out about her," he thought.
     </p><p>It was not an unusual thing for professors in the college at
Union Valley to take students home to their houses.  Hugh decided
he would take the girl to his home.  He thought about it several
days and late one afternoon saw her going down the college hill
ahead of him.<pb n="572"/>
     </p><p>The girl's name was Mary Cochran and she had come to the
school but a few months before from a place called Huntersburg,
Illinois, no doubt just such another place as Union Valley.  He
knew nothing of her except that her father was dead, her mother
too, perhaps.  He walked rapidly down the hill to overtake her.
"Miss Cochran," he called, and was surprised to find that his voice
trembled a little.  "What am I so eager about," he asked himself.

     </p><p>A new life began in Hugh Walker's house.  It was good for the
man to have some one there who did not belong to him and Winifred
Walker, and the children accepted the presence of the girl.
Winifred urged her to come again.  She did come several times a
week.
     </p><p>To Mary Cochran it was comforting to be in the presence of a
family of children.  On winter afternoons she took Hugh's two sons
and a sled and went to a small hill near the house.  Shouts arose.
Mary Cochran pulled the sled up the hill and the children followed.
Then they all came tearing down together.
     </p><p>The girl, developing rapidly into womanhood, looked upon Hugh
Walker as something that stood completely outside her own life.
She and the man who had become suddenly and intensely interested in
her had little to say to each other and Winifred Walker seemed to
have accepted her without question as an addition to the household.
Often in the afternoon when the two negro women were busy she went
away leaving the two older children in Mary's charge.
     </p><p>That was in the late afternoon and perhaps Hugh had walked
home with Mary from the college.  In the spring he worked in the
neglected garden.  It had been plowed and planted, but he took a
hoe and rake and puttered about.  The children played about the
house with the college girl.  Hugh did not look at them but at her.
"She is one of the world of people with whom I live and with whom
I am supposed to work here," he thought.  "Unlike Winifred and
these children she does not belong to me.  I could go to her now,
touch her fingers, look at her and then go away and never see her
again."
     </p><p>That thought was a comfort to the distraught man.  In the
evening when he went out to walk the sense of distance that lay all
about him did not tempt him to walk and walk, going half insanely
forward for hours, trying to break through an intangible wall.
     </p><p>He thought about Mary Cochran.  She was a girl from a
country
<pb n="573"/>  town.  She must be like millions of American girls.  He
wondered what went on in her mind as she sat in his class-room, as
she walked beside him along the streets of Union Valley, as she
played with the children in the yard beside his house.
     </p><p>In the winter, when in the growing darkness of a late
afternoon Mary and the children built a snow man in the yard, he
went upstairs and stood in the darkness to look out a window.  The
tall straight figure of the girl, dimly seen, moved quickly about.
"Well, nothing has happened to her.  She may be anything or
nothing.  Her figure is like a young tree that has not borne
fruit," he thought.  He went away to his own room and sat for a
long time in the darkness.  That night when he left the house for
his evening's walk he did not stay long but hurried home and went
to his own room.  He locked the door.  Unconsciously he did not
want Winifred to come to the door and disturb his thoughts.
Sometimes she did that.
     </p><p>All the time she read novels.  She read the novels of Robert
Louis Stevenson.  When she had read them all she began again.
     </p><p>Sometimes she came upstairs and stood talking by his door.
She told some tale, repeated some wise saying that had fallen
unexpectedly from the lips of the children.  Occasionally she came
into the room and turned out the light.  There was a couch by a
window.  She went to sit on the edge of the couch.  Something
happened.  It was as it had been before their marriage.  New life
came into her figure.  He also went to sit on the couch and she put
up her hand and touched his face.
     </p><p>Hugh did not want that to happen now.  He stood within the
room for a moment and then unlocked the door and went to the head
of the stairs.  "Be quiet when you come up, Winifred.  I have a
headache and am going to try to sleep," he lied.
     </p><p>When he had got back in his own room and locked the door again
he felt safe.  He did not undress but threw himself on the couch
and turned out the light.
     </p><p>He thought about Mary Cochran, the school girl, but was sure
he thought about her in a quite impersonal way.  She was like the
woman going to milk cows he had seen across hills when he was a
young fellow and walked far and wide over the country to cure the
restlessness in himself.  In his life she was like the man who
threw the stone at the dog.
     </p><p>"Well, she is unformed; she is like a young tree," he told
himself<pb n="574"/>  again.  "People are like that.  They just grow up
suddenly out of childhood.  It will happen to my own children.  My
little Winifred that cannot yet say any words will suddenly be like
this girl.  I have not selected her to think about for any
particular reason.  For some reason I have drawn away from life and
she has brought me back.  It might have happened when I saw a child
playing in the street or an old man going up a stairway into a
house.  She does not belong to me.  She will go away out of my
sight.  Winifred and the children will stay on and on here and I
will stay on and on.  We are imprisoned by the fact that we belong
to each other.  She is free, or at least she is free as far as this
prison is concerned.  No doubt she will after a while make a prison
of her own and live in it, but I will have nothing to do with the
matter."
     </p><p>By the time Mary Cochran was in her third year in the college
at Union Valley she had become a kind of fixture in the Walker
household.  Still she did not know Hugh.  She knew the children
better than he did, perhaps better than their mother.  In the fall
she and the two boys went to the woods to gather nuts.  In the
winter they went skating on a little pond near the house.
     </p><p>Winifred accepted her as she accepted everything, the service
of the two negroes, the coming of the children, the habitual
silence of her husband.
     </p><p>And then quite suddenly and unexpectedly Hugh's silence, that
had lasted all through his married life, was broken up.  He walked
homeward with a German who had the chair of modern languages in the
school and got into a violent quarrel.  He stopped to speak to men
on the street.  When he went to putter about in the garden he
whistled and sang.
     </p><p>One afternoon in the fall he came home and found the whole
family assembled in the living room of the house.  The children
were playing on the floor and the negress sat in the chair by the
window with his youngest child in her arms crooning one of the
negro songs.
     </p><p>Mary Cochran was there.  She sat reading a book.
     </p><p>Hugh walked directly toward her and looked over her shoulder.
At that moment Winifred came into the room.  He reached forward and
snatched the book out of the girl's hands.  She looked up startled.
With an oath he threw it into the fire that burned in an open grate
at the side of the room.  A flood of words ran from him.  He cursed
books and people and schools.  "Damn it all," he said.</p>
<pb n="575"/>
<p>"What makes you want to read about life?  What makes people want to
think about life?  Why don't they live?  Why don't they leave books
and thoughts and schools alone?"
     </p><p>He turned to look at his wife who had grown pale and stared at
him with a queer fixed uncertain stare.  The old negro woman got up
and went quickly away.  The two older children began to cry.  Hugh
was miserable.  He looked at the startled girl in the chair who
also had tears in her eyes, and at his wife.  His fingers pulled
nervously at his own coat.  To the two women he looked like a boy
who had been caught stealing food in a pantry.  "I am having one of
my silly irritable spells," he said looking at his wife but in
reality addressing the girl.  "You see I am more serious than I
pretend to be.  I was not irritated by your book but by something
else.  I see so much that can be done in life and I do so little."
     </p><p>He went upstairs to his own room wondering why he had lied to
the two women, why he continually lied to himself.
     </p><p>Did he lie to himself?  He tried to answer the question but
couldn't.  He was like one who walks in the darkness of the hallway
of a house and comes to a blank wall.  The old desire to run away
from life, to wear himself out physically, came back upon him like
a madness.
     </p><p>For a long time he stood in the darkness inside his own room.
The children stopped crying and the house became quiet again.  He
could hear his wife's voice speaking softly and presently the back
door of the house banged and he knew the schoolgirl had gone away.
     </p><p>Life in the house began again.  Nothing happened.  Hugh ate
his dinner in silence and went for a long walk.  For two weeks Mary
Cochran did not come to his house and then one day he saw her on
the college grounds.  She was no longer one of his pupils.  "Please
do not desert us because of my rudeness," he said.  The girl
blushed and said nothing.  When he got home that evening she was in
the yard beside the house playing with the children.  He went at
once to his own room.  A hard smile came and went on his face.
"She isn't like a young tree any more.  She is almost like
Winifred.  She is almost like a person who belongs here, who
belongs to me and my life," he thought.

     </p><p>Mary Cochran's visits to the Walker household came to an end
very abruptly.  One evening when Hugh was in his room she
came<pb n="576"/>  up the stairway with the two boys.  She had dined with
the
family and was putting the two boys into their beds.  It was a
privilege she claimed when she dined with the Walkers.
     </p><p>Hugh had hurried upstairs immediately after dining.  He knew
where his wife was.  She was downstairs, sitting under a lamp,
reading one of the books of Robert Louis Stevenson.
     </p><p>For a long time Hugh could hear the voices of his children on
the floor above.  Then the thing happened.
     </p><p>Mary Cochran came down the stairway that led past the door of
his room.  She stopped, turned back and climbed the stairs again to
the room above.  Hugh arose and stepped into the hallway.  The
schoolgirl had returned to the children's room because she had been
suddenly overtaken with a hunger to kiss Hugh's oldest boy, now a
lad of nine.  She crept into the room and stood for a long time
looking at the two boys, who unaware of her presence had gone to
sleep.  Then she stole forward and kissed the boy lightly.  When
she went out of the room Hugh stood in the darkness waiting for
her.  He took hold of her hand and led her down the stairs to his
own room.
     </p><p>She was terribly afraid and her fright in an odd way pleased
him.  "Well," he whispered, "you can't understand now what is going
to happen here but some day you will.  I'm going to kiss you and
then I am going to ask you to go out of this house and never come
back."
     </p><p>He held the girl against his body and kissed her upon the
cheeks and lips.  When he led her to the door she was so weak with
fright and with new, strange, trembling desires that she could with
difficulty make her way down the stairs and into his wife's
presence.  "She will lie now," he thought, and heard her voice
coming up the stairs like an echo to his thoughts.  "I have a
terrible headache.  I must hurry home," he heard her voice saying.
The voice was dull and heavy.  It was not the voice of a young
girl.
     </p><p>"She is no longer like a young tree," he thought.  He was glad
and proud of what he had done.  When he heard the door at the back
of the house close softly his heart jumped.  A strange quivering
light came into his eyes.  "She will be imprisoned but I will have
nothing to do with it.  She will never belong to me.  My hands will
never build a prison for her," he thought with grim pleasure.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
