<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AntWoma"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="AntWoma">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Woman's Half-Century of Evolution</title>
<title type="sort">womans half century of evolution</title>
<author>Anthony, Susan B. (Susan Brownell), 1820-1906</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">32</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AntWoma</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475694</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>In the original, footnotes were marked with asterisk, dagger and double dagger. For ease in reading, notes in the electronic text have been moved to the end and marked with consecutive numbers.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Woman's Half-Century of Evolution.</title>
<title level="j">The North American Review.</title>
<title type="sort">womans half century of evolution</title>
<author>Susan B. Anthony</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The North American Review Publishing Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1902">1902</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">North American Review</hi> 175 (Dec. 1902): 800-810.</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1902">1902</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
<language id="fre">French</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term>
<term>democracy</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-02">February 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Deirdre A. Johnson, Electronic Text Center, University of
Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header and basic TEI markup</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">



<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="800"/>
<head>           WOMAN'S HALF-CENTURY OF EVOLUTION.<lb/>

                  BY SUSAN B. ANTHONY.</head>

<p>THE status of woman in the United States fifty years ago, the
progressive steps by which it has been improved, present
conditions, future probabilities&mdash;in fact, a resume of the great
movement in which Elizabeth Cady Stanton has been the central
figure through two generations&mdash;this is the subject assigned me to
consider in the brief space of one magazine article!
</p><p>The title I claim for Mrs. Stanton is that of leader of women.
Women do not enjoy one privilege to-day beyond those possessed by
their foremothers, which was not demanded by her before the present
generation was born.  Her published speeches will verify this
statement.  In the light of the present, it seems natural that she
should have made those first demands for women; but at the time it
was done the act was far more revolutionary than was the
Declaration of Independence by the colonial leaders.  There had
been other rebellions against the rule of kings and nobles; men
from time immemorial had been accustomed to protest against
injustice; but for women to take such action was without a
precedent and the most daring innovation in all history.  Men of
old could emphasize their demands by the sword, and in the present
century they have been able to do so by the ballot.  While they
might, indeed, put their lives in peril, they were always supported
by a certain amount of sympathy from the public.  Women could
neither fight nor vote; they were not sustained even by those of
their own sex; and, while they incurred no physical risk, they
imperilled their reputation and subjected themselves to mental and
spiritual crucifixion.  Therefore I hold that the calling of that
first Women's Rights Convention in 1848 by Mrs. Stanton, Lucretia
Mott and two or three other brave Quaker women, was one of the most
courageous acts on record. <pb n="801"/>
</p><p>It must be remembered that at this time a woman's convention
never had been heard of, with the exception of the few which had
been called, early in the anti-slavery movement, by the women who
had been driven out of the men's meetings and had formed their own
society; but even these were almost wholly managed by men.  A few
individual women had publicly advocated equality of rights&mdash;the
number could be more than counted on one's fingers&mdash;but a
convention for this purpose and an organized demand had been till
then undreamed of.  The vigor and scope of the Declaration of
Sentiments which was presented and adopted at this memorable
meeting, held at Mrs. Stanton's home, in Seneca Falls, New York,
are in nowise diminished by comparison with the Declaration of the
forefathers proclaimed exactly seventy-two years before.  It began,
indeed, with the preamble of the Declaration of Independence,
substituting "women" for "men" and "colonies"; and it continued:</p>
<p>"The history of mankind is a history of repeated injuries and
usurpations on the part of man toward woman, having in direct
object the establishment of an absolute tyranny over her.  To prove
this, let facts be submitted to a candid world:
</p><p>"He has never permitted her to exercise her inalienable right
to the elective franchise.
</p><p>"He has compelled her to submit to laws in the formation of
which she had no voice.
</p><p>"He has withheld from her rights which are given to the most
ignorant and degraded men&mdash;both natives and foreigners.
</p><p>"Having deprived her of this first right of a citizen, the
elective franchise, thereby leaving her without representation in
the halls of legislation, he has oppressed her on all sides.
</p><p>"He has made her, if married, in the eye of the law, civilly
dead.
</p><p>"He has taken from her all right in property, even to the
wages she earns.
</p><p>"He has made her morally an irresponsible being, as she can
commit many crimes with impunity, provided they be done in the
presence of her husband.  In the covenant of marriage, she is
compelled to promise obedience to her husband, he becoming, to all
intents and purposes, her master&mdash;the law giving him power to
deprive her of her liberty and to administer chastisement.
</p><p>"He has so framed the laws of divorce, as to what shall be the
proper causes, and to whom the guardianship of the children shall
be given, as to be wholly regardless of the happiness of woman&mdash;the
law, in all cases, going upon a false supposition of the supremacy
of man, and giving all power into his hands.
</p><p>"After depriving her of all rights as a married woman, if
single and <pb n="802"/>  the owner of property, he has taxed her to
support a government which recognizes her only when her property
can be made profitable to it.
</p><p>"He has monopolized nearly all the profitable employments, and
from those she is permitted to follow, she receives but a scanty
remuneration.
</p><p>"He has closed against her all the avenues to wealth and
distinction which he considers most honorable to himself.  In
theology, medicine, and law she is not known.
</p><p>"He has denied her the facilities for obtaining a thorough
education&mdash;all colleges being closed against her.
</p><p>"He allows her in Church, as well as State, but a subordinate
position, claiming Apostolic authority for her exclusion from the
ministry, and, with some exceptions, from any public participation
in the affairs of the Church.
</p><p>"He has created a false public sentiment by giving to the
world a different code of morals for men and women, by which moral
delinquencies which exclude women from society are not only
tolerated but deemed of little account in man.
</p><p>"He has usurped the prerogative of Jehovah himself, claiming
it as his right to assign for her a sphere of action, when that
belongs to her conscience and to her God.
</p><p>"He has endeavored, in every way that he could to destroy her
confidence in her own powers, to lessen her self-respect and to
make her willing to lead a dependent and abject life.
</p><p>"Now, in view of this entire disfranchisement of one-half the
people of this country, their social and religious degradation&mdash;in
view of the unjust laws above mentioned, and because women do feel
themselves aggrieved, oppressed and fraudulently deprived of their
most sacred rights, we insist that they have immediate admission to
all the rights and privileges which belong to them as citizens of
the United States.
</p><p>"In entering upon the great work before us we anticipate no
small amount of misconception, misrepresentation and ridicule; but
we shall use every instrumentality within our power to effect our
object.  We shall employ agents, circulate tracts, petition the
State and national Legislatures, and endeavor to enlist the pulpit
and the press in our behalf.  We hope this Convention will be
followed by a series of Conventions, embracing every part of the
country."
</p><p>"Firmly relying upon the final triumph of the Right and the
True, we do this day affix our signatures to this Declaration."</p>

<p>To emphasize these most radical sentiments the following
resolutions also were adopted:</p>

<p>"The great precept of nature is conceded to be, 'that man
shall pursue his own true and substantial happiness.'  Blackstone,
in his Commentaries, remarks, that this law of Nature being coeval
with mankind and dictated by God himself, is of course superior in
obligation to any other.  It is binding over all the globe, in all
countries, and at all times; no human laws are of any validity if
contrary to this, and such of them <pb n="803"/>  as are valid derive all
their force and all their validity and all their authority,
mediately and immediately, from this original; therefore,
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Resolved</hi>, That such laws as conflict, in any way, with
the true and substantial happiness of woman, are contrary to the
great precept of nature and of no validity; for this is 'superior
in obligation to any other.'
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Resolved</hi>, That all laws which prevent woman from
occupying such a station in society as her conscience shall
dictate, or which place her in a position inferior to that of man,
are contrary to the great precept of nature and therefore of no
force or authority.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Resolved</hi>, That woman is man's equal&mdash;was intended to
be so by the Creator&mdash;and the highest good of the race demands that
she should be recognized as such.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Resolved</hi>, That the women of this country ought to be
enlightened in regard to the laws under which they live, that they
may no longer publish their degradation by declaring themselves
satisfied with their present position, nor their ignorance by
asserting that they have all the rights they want.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Resolved</hi>, That inasmuch as man, while claiming for
himself intellectual superiority, does accord to woman moral
superiority, it is preeminently his duty to encourage her to speak
and teach, as she has an opportunity, in all religious assemblies.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Resolved</hi>, That the same amount of virtue, delicacy and
refinement of behavior that is required of woman in the social
state should also be required of man, and the same transgressions
should be visited with equal severity on both man and woman.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Resolved</hi>, That the objection of indelicacy and
impropriety, which is so often brought against woman when she
addresses a public audience, comes with a very ill-grace from those
who encourage by their attendance her appearance on the stage, in
the concert or in feats of the circus.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Resolved</hi>, That woman has too long rested satisfied in
the circumscribed limits which corrupt customs and a perverted
application of the Scriptures have marked out for her, and that it
is time she should move in the enlarged sphere which her great
Creator has assigned her.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That it is the duty of the women of this
country to secure to themselves their sacred right to the elective
franchise.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Resolved</hi>, That the equality of human rights results
necessarily from the fact of the identity of the race in
capabilities and responsibilities.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Resolved</hi>, therefore, That, being invested by the
Creator with the same capabilities and the same consciousness of
responsibility for their exercise, it is demonstrably the right and
duty of woman, equally with man, to promote every righteous cause
by every righteous means; and especially in regard to the great
subjects of morals and religion, it is self-evidently her right to
participate with her brother in teaching them, both in private and
in public, by writing and by speaking, by any instrumentalities
proper to be used and in any assemblies proper to be held; and this
being a self-evident truth, growing out of the divinely implanted
principles of human nature, any custom or authority adverse <pb n="804"/>
to it, whether modern or wearing the hoary sanction of antiquity,
is to be regarded as a self-evident falsehood and at war with the
interests of mankind."</p>

<p>In all the conventions which have been held during the past
fifty-four years, the impassioned addresses made, the resolutions
presented, the hearings before legislative bodies, there has been
nothing to add to these declarations made by a woman only thirty-three years old, born and bred in the midst of the most rigid
social, civil and religious conservatism.  They illustrate vividly
the conditions which existed in that day, when the simplest
rudiments of education were deemed sufficient for women; when only
a half-dozen remunerative employments were open to them and any
work outside the home placed a stigma on the worker; when a woman's
right to speak in public was more bitterly contested than her right
to the suffrage is to-day.  The storm of ridicule and denunciation
which broke over the heads of the women who took part in this
convention never has been exceeded in the coarsest and most
vituperative political campaign ever conducted.  The attacks were
led by the pulpit, whose influence fifty years ago was far greater
than at present and whose power over women was supreme.  The press
of the country did not suffer itself to be outdone; but, taking its
cue from the metropolitan papers of New York, contributed its full
quota of caricature and misrepresentation.
</p><p>At the beginning of 1848, the English Common Law was in force
practically everywhere in the United States.  Its treatment of
women was a blot on civilization only equalled in blackness by the
slavery of the negro.  The latter, technically at least, has now
disappeared.  The former dies slowly, because it cannot be
eradicated by fire and sword.  Lord Coke called this Common Law
"the perfection of reason."  Under its provisions the position of
the wife was thus stated by Blackstone:</p>

<p>"The very being or existence of the woman is suspended during
the marriage, or at least is incorporated and consolidated into
that of the husband, under whose wing, protection and covert she
performs everything.  She is, therefore, called in our Law-French
a <foreign lang="fre"><hi rend="italic">femme-covert</hi></foreign>, is said to be <foreign lang="fre"><hi rend="italic">covert-baron</hi></foreign>, or under
the protection and influence of her husband, her baron or lord.
</p><p>"The husband also, by the old law, might give his wife
moderate correction.  For, as he is to answer for her misbehavior,
the law thought it reasonable to intrust him with this power of
restraining her by domestic <pb n="805"/>  chastisement in the same
moderation that a man is allowed to correct his apprentices or
children.  But this power of correction was confined within
reasonable bounds, and the husband was prohibited from using any
violence to his wife, except as lawfully and reasonably belongs to
a husband for the sake of governing and disciplining his wife.  The
Civil Law gave the husband the same or a larger authority over his
wife, allowing him for some misdemeanors to beat his wife severely
with whips and cudgels; for others only to administer moderate
chastisement."<ref target="n1">1</ref> </p>

<p>Other provisions of this law were as follows:</p>

<p>"By marriage, the husband and wife are one person in law; that
is, the legal existence of the woman is merged in that of her
husband.  He is her baron or lord, bound to supply her with
shelter, food, clothing and medicine, and is entitled to her
earnings and the use and custody of her person, which he may seize
wherever he may find it."<ref target="n2">2</ref> </p>

<p>"The husband, being bound to provide for his wife the
necessaries of life, and being responsible for her morals and the
good order of the household, may choose and govern the domicile,
select her associates, separate her from her relatives, restrain
her religious and personal freedom, compel her to cohabit with him,
correct her faults by mild means, and, if necessary, chastise her
with moderation, as though she was his apprentice or child.  This
is in respect to the terms of the marriage contract and the
infirmity of the sex."<ref target="n3">3</ref>  </p>

<p>It does not seem necessary to add further particulars as to
the condition of women in the middle of the century just closed and
at the time Elizabeth Cady Stanton began the almost superhuman task
of setting them free from the bondage of centuries.  The first
cleft in the infamy of the Common Law was made almost
simultaneously by the Legislatures of New York, and Pennsylvania,
in the spring of 1848, by special statutes giving a married woman
the right to hold property.  This was the first glimmer of freedom
from legal slavery which ever had appeared to women; and it is not
surprising that it scarcely penetrated the darkness in which they
had been enveloped for untold ages, or that they rejected with
scorn those who came to deliver them.
</p><p>The beginning of my friendship and work with Mrs. Stanton
dates from the summer of 1851.  I was at that time thirty-one years
old and had been teaching since I was eighteen.  My father was
deeply interested in the anti-slavery cause; and Garrison,
Phillips, Pillsbury, Channing, Frederick Douglass and other noted
reformers were often guests in our home.  The school-room


<pb n="806"/>
had grown insupportably narrow.  I had no personal grievances, as
my own family, in common with all the Friends, or Quakers,
recognized the equality of woman in all the relations of life; but
I was stirred by the terrible injustice which I saw meted out to
women on every hand, and I realized the especial need of their
voice and influence in the two great causes of temperance and anti-slavery.  The necessity for the ballot had not appealed to me, as,
in those days, Quaker men were not in the habit of voting.  But in
October, 1850, my consciousness was awakened by reading in the
<hi rend="italic">New York Tribune</hi> a full and favorable account of a Woman's
Rights Convention held in Worcester, Massachusetts.  The next year
I became acquainted with Mrs. Stanton, and she soon fired my soul
with all her own zeal for the right of the suffrage.  Among my old
papers is the following appeal, which, as Secretary of the New York
State Temperance Society, I sent out in the spring of 1852,
accompanying petitions for what was then known as the Maine Law:

</p><p>"Women, and mothers in particular, should feel it their right
and duty to extend their influence beyond the circumference of the
home circle, and to say what circumstances shall surround children
when they go forth from under the watchful guardianship of the
mother's love; for certain it is that if the customs and laws of
society remain corrupt as they now are, the best and wisest of the
mother's teachings will soon be counteracted. . . .  Woman has so
long been accustomed to non-intervention with law making, so long
considered it man's business to regulate the liquor traffic, that
it is with much cautiousness she receives the new doctrine which we
preach&mdash;the doctrine that it is her right and duty to speak out
against the traffic and all men and institutions that in any way
sanction, sustain or countenance it; and, since she can not vote,
to duly instruct her husband, son, father or brother how she would
have him vote, and, if he longer continue to misrepresent her, take
the right to march to the ballot-box and deposit a vote indicative
of her highest ideas of practical temperance."

</p><p>This was my first declaration for woman suffrage, which I have
since repeated in season and out of season at every possible
opportunity for fifty years.  In a short time the conviction became
so dominant that the franchise was the lever with which women could
lift all other reform movements, that I abandoned everything else
and devoted the whole force of my being to securing this
fundamental power for women.  The only departure from this rule was
made during the Civil War, when every issue but one was held in
abeyance.  Mrs. Stanton and I sent out a call <pb n="807"/>  for a mass
meeting in Dr. Cheever's church, New York, where the Woman's Loyal
League was formed, on May 14th, 1863.  Nearly 400,000 signatures to
petitions for emancipation were secured, and Charles Sumner and
Henry Wilson wrote us repeatedly that these petitions formed the
bulwark of their demand for Congressional action to abolish
slavery.
</p><p>The moment the war was over&mdash;in 1865, when the Fourteenth
Amendment was under discussion and it was proposed to introduce the
word "male" in the National Constitution for the first time&mdash;I
resumed my efforts for woman suffrage and have never deviated from
the straight and narrow path which leads to this goal.  During late
years Mrs. Stanton has held that, as the suffrage movement is
steadily going forward by its own momentum, women should take up
other public questions which so evidently need the combined wisdom
of men and women in their solution.  I have maintained my original
attitude, believing that for the leaders of the work for woman
suffrage to identify themselves with the other issues of the day is
to create animosities and alienate supporters of a cause which can
achieve victory only through the assistance of all religious bodies
and political parties.  I have sympathized thoroughly, however,
with Mrs. Stanton's rebelliousness against that condition of
dependence which compels women to remain mute and inactive in the
great movements of the time, as the only means of achieving freedom
to speak and act effectively in the future.
</p><p>To follow in detail the steps by which women have reached
their present position of comparative social, educational,
financial and legal independence, would be to write a chapter for
each of the fifty years which have intervened since the first few
brave souls dared lift up their voices in a cry for liberty.  The
organized movement for the emancipation of women began in earnest
soon after the close of the Civil War.  Every one of the past
thirty-five years has witnessed the breaking of a link in the
chain.  The going forth of hundreds of thousands of men from the
farm, the work-shop, the factory, the store&mdash;from every field of
employment&mdash;to swell the ranks of the army, made it absolutely
necessary for women to step into their places in order that the
countless wheels of the world's work should not stop.  The
vacancies left by those who never returned, and the rapidly-growing
tendency to remove domestic products from the home to the factory,
practically set-<pb n="808"/> tled the question of woman's entering the
wage-earning occupations.
</p><p>The period immediately after the War was marked by the speedy
increase and enlargement of State Universities and the admission of
women.  Their example was followed by many of the other colleges
and universities of the country, and in 1890 by the founding of the
two great endowed institutions, Stanford and Chicago, with the
admission of women to every department.  Although the latter has
just made the egregious blunder of modifying its original plan,
this action represents only the individual scheme of one man and
not a reactionary tendency.  The question of the higher education
of woman may be regarded as decided in her favor.
</p><p>The right of women to organize for public work is now
universally recognized and approved.  They have at present in the
United States over one hundred national organizations, with
thousands of local clubs and societies comprising millions of
members, and their influence over the general conditions of the
various communities is beyond computation.  The right of women to
speak in public is not only everywhere conceded but, given a man
and a woman with equal abilities, the average audience would prefer
to hear the latter.
</p><p>The legal features of the revolution have been quite as marked
as its other phases.  An examination, doubtless, would show that in
not one State does the Common Law now prevail in its entirety.  In
many of them it has been largely obliterated by special statutes.
There has been no retrogressive legislation with respect to the
status of women before the law.  In the majority of the States, a
married woman may now own and control property, carry on business
and possess her earnings, make a will and a contract, bring suit in
her own name, act as administrator and testify in the courts.  In
one-fifth of the States, she has equal guardianship with the father
over the minor children.  Where formerly there was but one cause
for divorce, the wife may now obtain a divorce in almost every
State for habitual drunkenness, cruelty, failure to provide and
desertion on the part of the husband; and he can no longer, as of
old even though the guilty party, retain sole possession of the
children and the property.  The general tendency of legislation for
women is progressive, and there is not a doubt that this will
continue to be the case. <pb n="809"/>
</p><p>I do not wish to be understood for a moment, however, as
maintaining that woman stands on a perfect equality with man in any
of the above-mentioned departments&mdash;in the industries, education,
organization, public speaking or the laws.  She simply has made
immense gains in all, and her standing has been completely
revolutionized since Mrs. Stanton announced the beginning of a new
Reformation.  Woman never will have equality of rights anywhere,
she never will hold those she now has by an absolute tenure, until
she possesses the fundamental right of self-representation.  This
fact is so obvious as to need no argument.  Had this right been
conceded at the start, the others would have speedily followed; and
the leaders among women, instead of spending the last half-century
in a constant struggle to obtain their civil and political rights,
might have contributed their splendid services to the general
upbuilding and strengthening of the Government.  The effort for
this most important of rights has had to content not only, like the
rest, with the obstinate prejudices and customs of the ages, but
also with the still more stubborn condition of its hard and fast
intrenchment in constitutional law.  It is not merely a board of
trustees or a body of legislators who must be converted to the
justice of extending this right to women, but also the great masses
of men, including the ignorant, the foreign-born, the small-minded
and the vicious.  A majority of the men in every State must give
their consent at the ballot box for women to come into possession
of this paramount right.  Such has not been the case with any other
step in the progress of women.
</p><p>It is not necessary to consider the minor reasons why the
enfranchisement of women has been so long deferred; but, in spite
of the almost insuperable obstacles, there has been considerable
progress in this direction.  In some States, the Legislatures
themselves can confer a fragmentary suffrage without the
ratification of the voters.  This has been done in about half of
them, Kansas granting the municipal franchise, Louisiana, Montana
and New York a taxpayer's franchise, and twenty-two States a vote
on matters connected with the public schools.  Within the last
twelve years, four States have conferred the full suffrage on
women&mdash;Wyoming and Utah by placing it in the constitutions under
which they entered Statehood; Colorado and Idaho through a
submission of the question to the voters.  There is a strong basis
<pb n="810"/>  for believing that within a few years several other States
will take similar action.
</p><p>The effect upon women themselves of these enlarged
opportunities in every direction has been a development which is
almost a regeneration.  The capability they have shown in the realm
of higher education, their achievements in the business world,
their capacity for organization, their executive power, have been
a revelation.  To set women back into the limited sphere of fifty
years ago would be to arrest the progress of the whole race.  Their
evolution has been accompanied by a corresponding development in
the moral nature of man, his ideas of temperance and chastity, his
sense of justice, his relations to society.  In no department of
the world's activities are the higher qualities so painfully
lacking as in politics, and this is the only one from which women
are wholly excluded.  Is it not perfectly logical to assume that
their influence would be as beneficial here as it has been
everywhere else?  Does not logic also justify the opinion that, as
they have been admitted into every other channel, the political
gateways must inevitably be opened?
</p><p>There cannot be a doubt in the reasoning and unbiased mind
that woman suffrage ultimately will prevail in every State in the
Union.  It will be the legitimate outcome of the spirit of our
institutions, which is the direct expression of individual opinion.
A deep feeling of regret always will prevail that the Liberator of
woman, Elizabeth Cady Stanton, could not live to see the complete
triumph of her cause, as did those other great emancipators,
Lincoln, Garrison and Phillips; but she died in the full knowledge
that the day of its victory is clearly marked on the calendar of
the near future. </p>
<signed>                                        SUSAN B. ANTHONY.</signed>

</div1>
</body>

<back id="d4">
<div1 type="notes" id="d5">
<p><note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">Blackstone's</seg> <p>Commentaries, I., 356, 366.</p></note>
<note id="n2"><seg type="note-symbol">Id.,</seg> <p>444.</p></note>
<note id="n3"><seg type="note-symbol">Id.,</seg> <p>442.</p></note>

</p>
</div1>
</back>
</text>
</TEI.2>
