<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AusAhLe"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="AusAhLe">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Conversion of Ah Lew Sing</title>
<title type="sort">conversion of ah lew sing</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">18</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AusAhLe</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475698</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>illustrations are not yet included</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Conversion of Ah Lew Sing</title>
<title level="j">Overland Monthly</title>
<title type="sort">conversion of ah lew sing</title>
<author>Mary Austin</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>A. Roman &amp; Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>San Francisco</pubPlace>
<date value="1897-10">October 1897</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>30</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Austin, Mary.  "The Conversion of Ah Lew Sing."  <hi rend="italic">Overland
Monthly</hi> n.s. 30 (Oct. 1897): 307-312.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1897-10">October 1897</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Native American</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-04">April 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header; Tagged with TEI.2-compatible SGML; Parsed against
local "teilite" dtd.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">


<front id="d2">
<titlePage id="d3"><pb n="307"/>
<docTitle><titlePart type="main">
THE CONVERSION OF AH LEW SING
</titlePart></docTitle>
<byline>
BY <docAuthor>M. AUSTIN</docAuthor>
</byline>
<epigraph><lg type="epigraph"><l>"The heathen Chinee is peculiar."</l></lg></epigraph>
</titlePage>
</front>
<body id="d4">
<div1 type="story" id="d5">
<p>AH LEW SING was the proprietor of a vegetable garden between the stock yard
and the rail-road bridge, on the farther side of the Summerfield canal.  He was the
lankest, obliquest-eyed celestial that ever combined an expression of childlike
innocence with the appearance of having fallen into a state of permanent
disrepair, an outward seeming that much belied the inner man.
</p><p>Previous to his conversion, his ideas, if he had any, in regard to the Deity,
were hazy in the extreme; but his convictions on the subject of devils were
concise and dogmatic.  There were about three hundred, according to Lew Sing's
computation; all of the most malevolent type.
</p><p>If the potatoes rotted, if the celery rusted, if the cabbages failed to head, or
the blight got his early peas, Lew Sing was at no loss where to lay the blame.  All
of these things frequently happened, notwithstanding that he burned punk at the
four corners of his fields, and at all the foot-bridges that crossed his irregular
ditches, which were so narrow and low that no sort of a devil could cross without
wetting his feet,&mdash;a thing to which Chinese devils are very much averse.
</p><p>
But in spite of the devils and a brisk competition in the vegetable trade,
Lew Sing was able to put by a moiety of his earnings, which he further increased
by judicious speculation with his friends Chock Sin, Sam Kee, and Foo Chou,
choice spirits all.  Chock Sin was more ignorant and cunning than Lew Sing; Sam
Kee was worse than Chock Sin, and Foo Chou was the epitome of highbinderism.
When Foo Chou could dupe his friends, he did so; when he could not, he
consoled himself that none of them would ever be able to fleece him.  But in this
he reckoned without Lew Sing.
</p><p>The speculations of Foo Chou were various, including by preference
anything sufficiently lawless and dangerous to make other people afraid of doing
it.  One of these chances of fortune put him in possession of the person of Li
Choi, whose father had previously sold her for a sixteenth interest in a tea store
on Dupont street.  Li Choi had very small feet and very large ear-rings, and
smooth glistening bands of hair with an astonishing number of jade ornaments
stuck in them.  Foo Chou expected to make as much as three hundred dollars on
her, and Foo Chou was a judge of marketable women.  But the cunningest of
speculators comes to grief now and then, and Foo Chou made the mistake of his
life when he brought his three friends to the close red-curtained room where his
property was sequestered, and permitted them to gaze through the hole he had cut
in the door to display the charms of Li Choi.
</p><p>The eyes of Lew Sing had no sooner beheld her than the heart of Lew Sing
was consumed by love.  Forthwith he began to suffer the pangs of disappointed
affection, for his potato crop, owing perhaps to the devils, perhaps to a superfluity
of water, was a failure, and the purse of Lew Sing did not contain an equivalent
for so much loveliness.  While he debated the possibility of inducing that
hardened piece of rascality to abate the price for friendship's sake, Foo Chou was
growing morose.  No purchaser was forthcoming for the lovely Li Choi, and she
was costing him dear for her keep, besides wasting her loveliness with secret
tears.
</p><p>It was not because of any lack of appreciation of her charms that Foo
Chou did not espouse her himself.
</p><p>In the gambling dens of Summerfield's Chinatown, Foo Chou was known
as the most inveterate and unluckiest gambler of them all, and no profitable
villanies being at hand, nothing but a cash price for Li Choi could replenish his
failing fortunes.
<pb n="308"/>

</p><p>What maiden fears and childish terrors and dread of outraged womanhood
were endured in that little red-curtained room no one knew.  No one, unless,
perhaps Ah Foo, who was grandfather at large to all the little pig-tailed celestials
in Chinatown.  He might have heard her crying as he squatted under her window
while his shaved and sandaled little charges made a skipping rope of his grizzled
queue, which was pieced out an extra length for that especial accommodation.
</p><p>The pretty face of Li Choi looked out between the curtains at the
wrinkled, kindly visage of Ah Foo and took heart of hope.  Foo Chou, coming one
morning to take stock of his property, found a strange key in the door and the
room empty.  Great was the wrath of Foo Chou, and such the questioning and
gesticulating and running to and fro that grandfather Foo had to move his charges
quite two blocks away to escape being trodden upon.  Later, word came to Foo
Chou that his property had taken refuge at the mission, whose gray walls towered
at least a story and a half above the shabby roofs that sheltered Chinatown.
</p><p>Foo Chou and his kind looked with marked disfavor on the mission and its
mistress, whose success in luring profitable females from their rightful masters
was looked upon as an unwarrantable interference in trade.  The friends of Foo
Chou advised an appeal to the law for the recovery of his property.  Not of course
that the law of this enlightened country recognized the lovely Li Choi as a legal
chattel, but any number of respectable merchants in Chinatown were ready to
swear to being the husband, father, brother, or otherwise legal guardian, praying
her restoration on his loving protection.  The thing had been done before, but Foo
Chou deemed it inadvisable for several reasons, chief of which was the
recollection of a recent encounter with the law on his own account in a little
operation connected with the opium trade in which Foo Chou had come hardly
off.
</p><p>For the present until some better plan could be devised Li Choi must
remain where she was.  True, she might be converted to Christianity, but she was
safe against any other chance and cost him nothing.  As for Christianity, Foo
Chou had never seen a case of it so bad it could not be cured with two or three
judicious beatings, nevertheless, he must keep as close a watch as circumstances
permitted over the recreant Li Choi.  Obviously this must be done by deputy,
since the villanous face of Foo Chou, if recognized, would bring about the very
thing he feared,&mdash;namely: the removal of Li Choi to a mission in another part of
the State, where she might be hopelessly lost to the proprietor.
</p><p>
In his perplexity he bethought himself of the guileless front of his friend
Lew Sing.  Then it was that Lew Sing congratulated himself that he had never
confessed his tender attachment to Foo Chou, and his smile was blank enough to
have deceived the Father of mischief himself, as he purchased a primer and
joined the night class at the mission.  Faithfully for a week he poured over the
intricacies of c-a-t and d-o-g, but never once did he catch a glimpse of the bright
eyes of Li Choi nor hear the pat-pat of her entrancing little feet.  Now the mission
school is but a trap to catch converts, and that the shrewd celestial knows as well
as anybody, and is wary to avoid its pitfalls,&mdash;but the conversion of Ah Lew Sing
dated from the day when he discovered that the converts of both sexes
participated in the religious exercises.
</p><p>From that time on his growth in grace was astonishing.  Within a week it
carried him from a back seat near the door to the
<pb n="309"/>
front row of shining examples beside Li Choi, who in the grateful promptings of
her simple heart believed whatever she thought would please the matron of the
mission, Miss Campbell.
</p><p>When they stood around the organ and sang, "O how I love Jesus!" Li
Choi looked at Miss Campbell and Lew Sing looked at Li Choi.
</p><p>"Me velly happy," was Lew Sing's unfailing testimony.
</p><p>So Ah Sing kept watch over Li Choi while Foo Chou perfected his plans.
If the law, he reasoned, did not recognize his proprietary interest in the person of
Li Choi, it could not deny his right to the jade ornaments which had been no
inconsiderable item of the purchase price.  Foo Chou
<pb n="310"/>  meant to swear out
a warrant for the arrest of Li Choi for the theft of certain earrings, hair ornaments,
and armlets, which she did feloniously abstract from the residence of Foo Chou.
While the arrest was in progress the friends of Foo Chou would rush to the rescue
of the distressed Li Choi and bear her away from the cruel arms of the law.  Foo
Chou thought for a sufficient sum the constable might even permit himself to be
knocked down in defense of his prisoner.  Foo Chou, for reasons before
mentioned, being averse to appearing on the scene in person, it was agreed that
the rescue should be conducted by Chock Sin and Sam Kee, and that Lew Sing
should convey the prisoner to the safe place in the country to which the wily Foo
Chou should retire after arranging for the arrest.
</p><p>It must be said to Foo Chou's credit that he left the management of an
affair of such importance in the hands of his friends with reluctance; however,
there was no help for it and he trusted to his well known reputation for blood-thirstiness to ensure the fidelity of Chock Sin, Sam Kee, and Lew Sing.  He meant
to stay quietly in the country until the affair had had time to blow over, and then
he hoped to get safely off to Sacramento, where the traffic in small feet and bright
eyes was flourishing.
</p><p>The arrest took place exactly as prescribed.  At an hour when all
Chinatown smoked its pipe and the charges of Father Foo napped in the shade,
the constable rapped at the door and presented his warrant for Li Choi.  Miss
Campbell demurred, hesitated, and was lost; for while she suspected the design of
Foo Chou, still the thing might have been contrived to lure her away from other
charges, more than one of whom was the alleged property of some enterprising
celestial.  While she debated, the tearful Li Choi was hurried out of reach.
</p><p>The rescue was the most successful affair of the kind ever carried on in
Chinatown.  When Chock Sin and Sam Kee crept out of the cellar in which they
had lain quiet during the perfunctory search carried on by the profane but not
over-zealous officer, they glowed with honest pride to find nothing else talked of
in the tea shops and laundries.  Lew Sing was not molested by the officers, for
nobody testified to the bundle of quilted petticoat which was hurried under the
canvas cover of his vegetable wagon waiting innocently around the corner.
</p><p>What happened in the interim between the rescue and the return of Foo
Chou on the third day, exceedingly wroth at what he supposed to be the total
failure of his plans, can never be accurately known; whether the heart of Lew
Sing, meditating long and tenderly on the charms of Li Choi, had yielded to an
overwhelming temptation, or whether his childlike countenance covered more
duplicity than even Foo Chou gave him credit for, is open to debate.  Perhaps the
demure Li Choi did not greatly resist the manifest destiny of her sex.  It is not to
be supposed that she was unaware of all these devoted glances when they stood
up in Sunday School and shared the same Gospel Hymn book.  Certainly Li Choi
did not want to be handed over to Foo Chou, neither did she want to go to jail,
and although a Chinaman in a vegetable wagon is not exactly an ideal knight
errant, rescuing a distressed maiden, it might have appeared so to Li Choi.  At any
rate he carried her away to his own domicile with a serene disregard of
consequences that did credit to his courage.  But the courage paled visibly before
the information brought by the friendly Ah Foo that Foo Chou had learned the
real state of affairs and was coming with a very big knife to kill Lew Sing and cut
off his queue, and carry Li Choi away.  All of which might have come to pass,
had not Lew Sing consulted with his friend, the flagman at the railroad crossing.
</p><p>"What you want to do to keep anybody from touching your wife is to get
married, alle samee white man.  Sabee?"
</p><p>Lew Sing reflected: to get married "alle samee white man" might make Li
Choi secure, but it might also make it difficult if he should ever wish to get rid of
her.  But then Lew Sing did not believe that he should ever want to get rid of Li
Choi.  Such is the reckless enthusiasm of love.  Besides, Foo Chou was coming
with his knife.
</p><p>The flagman scribbled a line on the back of an old letter.  "You takee this
to the City Hall, give him to Mr. McGee, he fix him all right."
</p><p>Half an hour later, while Foo Chou was furiously searching the premises
of Ah Lew Sing, that worthy was helping his pretty
<pb n="311"/>


<pb n="312"/>

bride up the steps of the City Hall, her parasol awry
and her embroidered sandals sadly the worse for their hasty flight across lots.

</p><p>Ah Sing in the swelling of commendable pride, at having outwitted the
most notorious highbinder in Chinatown, built him a house that was quite large
enough to swing a cat in, and as gorgeous inside as a joss house, and quite as
dingy without, with the wisdom of Confucius done in very large characters on
very red paper pasted all about the front door.  He has returned to his old
occupation of fighting devils.  A three hundred dollar wife must be supported in a
style to correspond with her worth,&mdash;besides there is a little Lew Sing who is
expected to grow up and become a mandarin with a green button on his hat and
must be looked after accordingly.
</p><p>Ah Lew Sing never went back to the mission, although Miss Campbell
visited him as soon as she heard of the wedding and exhorted him to hold fast to
the faith that he had.  His wife goes sometimes and sits in her old seat but it is
only an act of grateful remembrance like the nice stale duck eggs and packages of
roasted watermelon seeds that find their way occasionally to Grandfather Foo.
</p><p>As for Foo Chou he departed for regions unknown.  He might have
devised new rascalities to compensate for the loss of his property, but to be
overreached by a mere vegetable gardener, a man who worked for a living!  After
that no self-respecting highbinder could hold up his head.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>


