<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AusAnte"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="AusAnte">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Last Antelope</title>
<title type="sort">last antelope</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">20</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AusAnte</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475699</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Last Antelope</title>
<title type="sort">last antelope</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Edited by</resp>
<name/>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<date value="1903">1903</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Vol. 92</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Verification made against printed text</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1903">1903</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman and Kelly Tetterton, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header, basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head> Austin, Mary.  "The Last Antelope."
<lb/>
<hi rend="italic"> Atlantic Monthly</hi> 92 (1903): 24-28.</head>

<pb n="24"/>

<p>THERE were seven notches in the juniper by the Lone Tree
Spring for the seven seasons that Little Pete had summered there,
feeding his flocks in the hollow of the Ceriso.  The first time of
coming he had struck his axe into the trunk meaning to make
firewood, but thought better of it, and thereafter chipped it in
sheer friendliness, as one claps an old acquaintance, for by the
time the flock has worked up the treeless windy stretch from the
Little Antelope to the Ceriso, even a lone juniper has a friendly
look.  And Little Pete was a friendly man, though shy of demeanor,
so that with the best will in the world for wagging his tongue, he
could scarcely pass the time of day with good countenance; the soul
of a jolly companion with the front and bearing of one of his own
sheep.
</p><p>He loved his dogs as brothers; he was near akin to the wild
things; he communed with the huddled hills, and held intercourse
with the stars, saying things to them in his heart that his tongue
stumbled over and refused.  He knew his sheep by name, and had
respect to signs and seasons; his lips moved softly as he walked,
making no sound.  Well&mdash;what would you? a man must have fellowship
in some sort.
</p><p>Whoso goes a-shepherding in the desert hills comes to be at
one with his companions, growing brutish or converting them.
Little Pete humanized his sheep.  He perceived lovable qualities in
them, and differentiated the natures and dispositions of inanimate
things.
</p><p>Not much of this presented itself on slight acquaintance, for
in fact he looked to be of rather less account than his own dogs.
He was undersized and hairy, and had a roving eye; probably he
washed once a year at the shearing as the sheep were washed.  About
his <pb n="25"/>  body he wore a twist of sheepskin with the wool outward,
holding in place the tatters of his clothing.  On hot days when he
wreathed leaves about his head, and wove him a pent of twigs among
the scrub in the middle of his flock, he looked a faun or some wood
creature come out of pagan times, though no pagan, as was clearly
shown by the medal of the Sacred Heart that hung on his hairy
chest, worn open to all weathers.  Where he went about sheep camps
and shearings, there was sly laughter and tapping of foreheads, but
those who kept the tale of his flocks spoke well of him and
increased his wage.
</p><p>Little Pete kept to the same round year by year, breaking away
from La Liebre after the spring shearing, south around the foot of
Pinos, swinging out to the desert in the wake of the quick, strong
rains, thence to Little Antelope in July to drink a bottle for <hi rend="italic">
La Quatorze</hi>, and so to the Ceriso by the time the poppy fires were
burned quite out and the quail trooped at noon about the tepid
pools.  The Ceriso is not properly mesa nor valley, but a long
healed crater miles wide, rimmed about with the jagged edge of the
old cone.
</p><p>It rises steeply from the tilted mesa, overlooked by Black
Mountain, darkly red as the red cattle that graze among the honey-colored hills.  These are blunt and rounded, tumbling all down from
the great crater and the mesa edge toward the long, dim valley of
Little Antelope.  Its outward slope is confused with the outlines
of the hills, tumuli of blind cones, and the old lava flow that
breaks away from it by the west gap and the ravine of the spring;
within, its walls are deeply guttered by the torrent of winter
rains.
</p><p>In its cuplike hollow, the sink of its waters, salt and bitter
as all pools without an outlet, waxes and wanes within a wide
margin of bleaching reeds.  Nothing taller shows in all the Ceriso,
and the wind among them fills all the hollow with an eerie
whispering.  One spring rills down by the gorge of an old flow on
the side toward Little Antelope, and, but for the lone juniper that
stood by it, there is never a tree until you come to the foot of
Black Mountain.
</p><p>The flock of Little Pete, a maverick strayed from some rodeo,
a prospector going up to Black Mountain, and a solitary antelope
were all that passed through the Ceriso at any time.  The antelope
had the best right.  He came as of old habit; he had come when the
lightfoot herds ranged from here to the sweet, mist-watered canons
of the Coast Range, and the bucks went up to the windy mesas what
time the young ran with their mothers, nose to flank.  They had
ceased before the keen edge of slaughter that defines the frontier
of men.
</p><p>All that a tardy law had saved to the district of Little
Antelope was the buck that came up the ravine was the buck that
came up the ravine of the Lone Tree Spring at the set time of the
year when Little Pete fed his flock in the Ceriso, and Pete averred
that they were glad to see one another.  True enough they were each
the friendliest thing the other found there, for the law ran as far
as the antelope ranged, there were hill dwellers who took no
account of it, namely, the coyotes.  They hunted the buck in season
and out, bayed him down from the feeding grounds, fended him from
the pool, pursued him by relay races, ambushed him in the pitfalls
of the black rock.
</p><p>There were seven coyotes ranging the east side of the Ceriso
at the time when Little Pete first struck his axe into the juniper
tree, slinking, sly-footed, and evil-eyed.  Many an evening the
shepherd watched them running lightly in the hollow of the crater,
the flash-flash of the antelope's white rump signaling the progress
of the chase.  But always the buck outran or outwitted them, taking
to the high broken ridges where no split foot could follow his
seven-leagued bounds.  Many a morning Little Pete, tending his
cooking pot by a quavering <pb n="26"/>  sagebrush fire, saw the antelope
feeding down toward the Lone Tree Spring, and looked his
sentiments.  The coyotes had spoken theirs all in the night with
derisive voices; never was there any love lost between a shepherd
and a coyote.  The pronghorn's chief recommendation to an
acquaintance was that he could outdo them.
</p><p>After the third summer, Pete began to perceive a reciprocal
friendliness in the antelope.  Early mornings the shepherd saw him
rising from his lair, or came often upon the warm pressed hollow
where he had lain within cry of his coyote-scaring fire.  When it
was mid-day in the misty hollow and the shadows drawn close, stuck
tight under the juniper and the sage, they went each to his nooning
in his own fashion, but in the half light they drew near together.
</p><p>Since the beginning of the law the antelope had half forgotten
his fear of man.  He looked upon the shepherd with steadfastness,
he smelled the smell of sheep and the unhandled earth, and the
smell of wood smoke was in his hair.  They had companionship
without speech; they conferred favors silently after the manner of
those who understand one another.  The antelope led to the best
feeding grounds, and Pete kept the sheep from muddying the spring
until the buck had drunk.  When the coyotes skulked in the scrub by
night to deride him, the shepherd mocked them in their own tongue,
and promised the best of his lambs for the killing; but to hear
afar off their hunting howl stirred him out of sleep to curse with
great heartiness.  At such times he thought of the antelope and
wished him well.
</p><p>Beginning with the west gap opposite the Lone Tree Spring
about the first of August, Pete would feed all around the broken
rim of the crater, up the gullies and down, and clean through the
hollow of it in a matter of two months, or if the winter had been
a wet one, a little longer, and in seven years the man and the
antelope grew to know each other very well.  Where the flock fed
the buck fed, keeping farthest from the dogs, and at last he came
to lie down with it.
</p><p>That was after a season of scant rains, when the feed was poor
and the antelope's flank grew thin; the rabbits had trooped down to
the irrigated lands, and the coyotes, made more keen by hunger,
pressed him hard.  One of those smoky, yawning days when the sky
hugged the earth, and all sound fell back from a woolly atmosphere
and broke dully in the scrub, about the usual hour of their running
between twilight and mid-afternoon, the coyotes drove the tall
buck, winded, desperate, and foredone, to refuge among the silly
sheep, where for fear of the dogs and the man the howlers dared not
come.  He stood at bay there, fronting the shepherd, brought up
against a crisis greatly needing the help of speech.
</p><p>Well&mdash;he had nearly as much gift in that matter as Little
Pete.  Those two silent ones understood each other; some assurance,
the warrant of a free given faith, passed between them.  The buck
lowered his head and eased the sharp throbbing of his ribs; the
dogs drew in the scattered flocks; they moved, keeping a little
cleared space nearest the buck; he moved with them; he began to
feed.  Thereafter the heart of Little Pete warmed humanly toward
the antelope, and the coyotes began to be very personal in their
abuse.  That same night they drew off the shepherd's dogs by a ruse
and stole two of his lambs.
</p><p>The same seasons that made the friendliness of the antelope
and Little Pete wore the face of the shepherd into a keener
likeness to the weathered hills, and the juniper flourishing
greenly by the spring bade fair to outlast them both.  The line of
ploughed lands stretched out mile by mile from the lower valley,
and a solitary homesteader built him a cabin at the foot of the
Ceriso.
</p><p>In seven years a coyote may learn <pb n="27"/>  somewhat; those of
the Ceriso learned the ways of Little Pete and the antelope.  Trust
them to have noted, as the years moved, that the buck's flanks were
lean and his step less free.  Put it that the antelope was old, and
that he made truce with the shepherd to hide the failing of his
powers; then if he came earlier or stayed later than the flock, it
would go hard with him.  But as if he knew their mind in the
matter, the antelope delayed his coming until the salt pool shrunk
to its innermost ring of reeds, and the sun-cured grasses crisped
along the slope.  It seemed the brute sense waked between him and
the man to make each aware of the other's nearness.  Often as
Little Pete drove in by the west gap he would sight the prongs of
the buck rising over the barrier of black rocks at the head of the
ravine.  Together they passed out of the crater, keeping fellowship
as far as the frontier of evergreen oaks.  Here Little Pete turned
in by the cattle fences to come at La Liebre from the north, and
the antelope, avoiding all man-trails, growing daily more remote,
passed into the wooded hills on unguessed errands of his own.
</p><p>Twice the homesteader saw the antelope go up to the Ceriso at
that set time of the year.  The third summer when he sighted him,
a whitish speck moving steadily against the fawn-colored background
of the hills, the homesteader took down his rifle and made haste
into the crater.  At that time his cabin stood on the remotest edge
of settlement, and the grip of the law was loosened in so long a
reach.
</p><p>"In the end the coyotes will get him.  Better that he fall to
me," said the homesteader.  But, in fact, he was prompted by the
love of mastery, which for the most part moves men into new lands,
whose creatures they conceive given over into their hands.
</p><p>The coyote that kept the watch at the head of the ravine saw
him come, and lifted up his voice in the long-drawn dolorous whine
that warned the other watchers in their unseen stations in the
scrub.  The homesteader heard also, and let a curse softly under
his breath, for besides that they might scare his quarry, he
coveted the howler's ears, in which the law upheld him.  Never a
tip nor a tail of one showed above the sage when he had come up
into the Ceriso.
</p><p>The afternoon wore on, the homesteader hid in the reeds, and
the coyotes had forgotten him.  Away to the left in a windless blur
of dust the sheep of Little Pete trailed up toward the crater's
rim.  The leader, watching by the spring, caught a jack rabbit and
was eating it quietly behind the black rock.
</p><p>In the meantime the last antelope came lightly and securely,
by the gully, by the black rock and the lone juniper into the
Ceriso.  The friendliness of the antelope for Little Pete betrayed
him.  He came with some sense of home, expecting the flock and
protection of man-presence.  He strayed witlessly into the open,
his ears set to catch the jangle of the bells.  What he heard was
the snick of the breech bolt as the homesteader threw up the sight
of his rifle, and a small demoniac cry that ran from gutter to
gutter of the crater rim, impossible to gauge for numbers or
distance.
</p><p>At that moment Little Pete worried the flock up the outward
slope where the ruin of the old lava flows gave sharply back the
wrangle of the bells.  Three weeks he had won up from the Little
Antelope, and three by way of the Sand Flat, where there was great
scarcity of water, and in all that time none of his kind had hailed
him.  His heart warmed toward the juniper tree and the antelope
whose hoof-prints he found in the white dust of the mesa trail.
Men had small respect by Little Pete, women he had no time for: the
antelope was the noblest thing he had ever loved.  The sheep poured
through the gap and spread fan-wise down the gully; behind them
Little Pete twirled his staff, and made merry wordless noises in
his throat in anticipation of friendliness.  "Ehu!" he <pb n="28"/>  cried
when he heard the hunting howl, "but they are at their tricks
again," and then in English he voiced a volley of broken,
inconsequential oaths, for he saw what the howlers were about.
</p><p>One imputes a sixth sense to that son of a thief misnamed the
coyote, to make up for speech, persuasion, concerted movement, in
short, the human faculty.  How else do they manage the terrible
relay races by which they make quarry of the fleetest footed?  It
was so they plotted the antelope's last running in the Ceriso: two
to start the chase from the black rock toward the red scar of a
winter torrent, two to leave the mouth of the wash when the first
were winded, one to fend the ravine that led up to the broken
ridges, one to start out of the scrub at the base of a smooth
upward sweep, and, running parallel to it, keep the buck well into
the open; all these when their first spurt was done to cross
leisurely to new stations to take up another turn.  Round they went
in the hollow of the crater, velvet-footed and sly even in full
chase, and biding their time.  It was a good running, but it was
almost done when away by the west gap the buck heard the voice of
Little Pete raised in adjuration and the friendly blether of the
sheep.  Thin spirals of dust flared upward from the moving flocks
and signaled truce to chase.  He broke for it with wide panting
bounds and many a missed step picked up with incredible eagerness,
the thin rim of his nostrils oozing blood.  The coyotes saw and
closed in about him, chopping quick and hard.  Sharp ears and sharp
muzzles cast up at his throat, and were whelmed in a press of gray
flanks.  One yelped, one went limping from a kick, and one went
past him, returning with a spring upon the heaving shoulder, and
the man in the reeds beside the bitter water rose up and fired.
</p><p>All the luck of that day's hunting went to the homesteader,
for he had killed an antelope and a coyote with one shot, and
though he had a bad quarter of an hour with a wild and loathly
shepherd, who he feared might denounce him to the law, in the end
he made off with the last antelope, swung limp and graceless across
his shoulder.  The coyotes came back to the killing ground when
they had watched him safely down the ravine and were consoled with
what they found.  As they pulled the body of the dead leader about
before they began upon it, they noticed that the homesteader had
taken the ears of that also.
</p><p>Little Pete lay in the grass and wept simply; the tears made
pallid traces in the season's grime.  He suffered the torture, the
question extraordinary of bereavement.  If he had not lingered so
long in the meadow of Los Robles, if he had moved faster on the
Sand Flat trail,&mdash;but, in fact, he had come up against the
inevitable.  He had been breathed upon by that spirit which goes
before cities like an exhalation and dries up the gossamer and the
dew.
</p><p>From that day the heart had gone out of the Ceriso.  It was a
desolate hollow, reddish-hued and dim, with brackish waters, and
moreover the feed was poor.  His eyes could not forget their trick
of roving the valley at all hours; he looked by the rill of the
spring for hoof-prints that were not there.
</p><p>Fronting the west gap there was a spot where he would not
feed, where the grass stood up stiff and black with what had dried
upon it.  He kept the flocks to the ridgy slopes where the limited
horizon permitted one to believe the crater was not quite empty.
His heart shook in the night to hear the long-drawn hunting howl,
and shook again remembering that he had nothing to be fearing for.
After three weeks he passed out on the other side and came that way
no more.  The juniper tree stood greenly by the spring until the
homesteader cut it down for firewood.  Nothing taller than the
rattling reeds stirs in all the hollow of the Ceriso.
</p>
<signed>                              <hi rend="italic"> Mary Austin.</hi></signed>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
