<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AusCoyo"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="AusCoyo">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Little Coyote</title>
<title type="sort">little coyote</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">21</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AusCoyo</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475702</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Little Coyote</title>
<title type="sort">little coyote</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Edited by</resp>
<name>editor</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<date value="1902">1902</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Vol. 89</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Verification made against printed text</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1902">1902</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman and Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head>
Austin, Mary.  "The Little Coyote."
<lb/>
<hi rend="italic"> Atlantic Monthly</hi> 89  (1902): 249-254.
</head>
<pb n="249"/>

<p>WITHOUT doubt a man's son is his son, whether the law has
spoken or no, and that the Little Coyote was the son of Moresco was
known to all Maverick and the Campoodie beyond it.  In the course
of time it became known to the Little Coyote.  His mother was
Choyita, who swept and mended for Moresco in the room behind the
store, which was all his home.  In those days Choyita was young,
light of foot, and pretty,&mdash;very pretty for a Piute.
</p><p>The Little Coyote was swart and squat, well-knit but slow-moving, reputed dull of wit, though that, people said, he did not
get from Moresco.  Moresco was a Hebrew of the Hebrews, and sharp,
so that they said at Maverick "as sharp as Moresco," and there was
an end of comparison.  Land and goods gravitated to Moresco.  His
Bed Rock Emporium was the centre of their commercial world, running
out threads of influence to the farthest corners of <pb n="250"/>  the
desert hills.  Everybody at Maverick owed or had owed Moresco, and
would be glad, if opportunity offered, to owe him again.
</p><p>Moresco dealt in merchandise and miners' supplies at a profit
that made men swear as they continued to buy.  Moresco grubstaked
prospectors, and outfitted miners for the working of prospect
holes, for a lion's share of the findings.  To do him justice, if
there were no findings he was not heard to complain.  Moresco had
always the cash in hand for the backing of new enterprises, for a
consideration.  In short, Moresco was the burning glass that
focused at Maverick whatever of bustle and trade was left in the
depleted hills.
</p><p>What the people perceived chiefly was, that as the country
grew poorer Moresco waxed richer, and they grumbled accordingly.
But the real sore spot in Maverick was his relation to the
Campoodie.
</p><p>It was said, and believed, that Moresco dealt brotherly by the
Piutes.  He gave them plain terms, forbore to haggle, preferred
them for small employments, warmed them at his fire, gave them
good-morrow and good-night.  The fact was, Moresco had the
instincts of a patriarch.  To outwit Maverick was business, to
despoil the Gentile might be religion; but the hapless, feckless
people who dwelt gingerly beside them were his dependents, his
beneficiaries,&mdash;in a word, his children.  In reality they cost him
very little.  He was amused, he was diverted, he expanded with
paternal graciousness.  For their part, the Indians revered him,
and Choyita was envied of the women to have borne him a son.
</p><p>Not that Moresco admitted anything of the kind, but there are
no secrets in a Campoodie.  Choyita left the child behind when she
went to clean and mend for Moresco.  What was she or her son that
her lord should be mindful of them?  Once, when the child was about
a year old, and she sat with the Mahalas by the sun-warmed wall,
watching the daily pageant of white life as it passed through the
streets of Maverick, Moresco called her into the store, and gave
her a pair of shoes for the child, and red calico for a frock.
Thereafter Choyita walked proudly.  To her mind the child was
acknowledged, and so it was received in the Campoodie.  Happy was
she among women, though her son should be called the Coyote.
</p><p>Among Piutes, Coyote as a name to be called by is a matter for
laughter or killing, as the case may be.  For the coyote, though
evilly bespoken, is of all beasts the most gullible; the butt, the
cat's-paw, the Simple Simon, of four-footed things,&mdash;the Jack
Dullard of Piute folk lore.  So from the time he stumbled witlessly
about the Campoodie on his fat, bowed legs, Choyita's son was the
Little Coyote; and the time is past when a man may win a new name
for himself,&mdash;long past with the time when there were deeds worth
naming.  The Little Coyote he remained when he was come to his full
size, which was something short of the stature of a man.
</p><p>By that time, Choyita, who had lost her prettiness and grown
fat, had gone to keep house for a miner down Panniment way, and
Moresco had married a wife, who bore him only daughters, and spent
much of her time and most of his money in San Francisco.  By that
time, too, the Coyote knew whose son he was.  It came to him as a
revelation, about the time his slow wit perceived that the other
children mocked him for his tainted blood.
</p><p>"Nana," he asked, when the savory smell of the cooking pots
drew the children in from their long day's playing,&mdash;"Nana, whose
son am I?"
</p><p>"Moresco's," she answered, and there fell a long silence
between them.  If she had said the alpenglow had fathered him, he
would not have been more amazed.  It lay all about them now, the
diurnal benediction of high altitudes, the transfiguration of the
rifted hills, and the boy at the heart of it <pb n="251"/>  thought of
Moresco,&mdash;Moresco, who stood for power and pleasance, the
quintessence of all things desired or feared, the little god of the
Piutes.
</p><p>"Moresco, Moresco," he repeated softly, under his breath.  He
did not call him "father," and he told no man, but he never forgot.
</p><p>When the Little Coyote was, as nearly as he could guess, about
seventeen, he killed his first big game.  It was a deer, shot at
the time of pinons, when all the tribe went up to the annual
harvest.  The Coyote made next to nothing of it, for he had the
good manners of his tribe; but he put by the best cut, wrapped in
fern leaves, and the next day walked the eleven miles to Maverick
that he might bring it to Moresco.  He stood at the door of the Bed
Rock Emporium until the merchant noticed him.
</p><p>"Vell, Kyode, vat you wandt?" said Moresco."
</p><p>"That you should have this," said the Coyote, and then he went
away.
</p><p>A few days later the merchant called him into the store, and
gave him a box of sardines and two tins of corn.  Nobody understood
the etiquette of present-giving better than Moresco.
</p><p>After that, when it began to be observed there was a
kindliness between the Hebrew and the Coyote, people crooked one
finger to the curve of an aquiline nose and winked slyly.
</p><p>Although Maverick could not deny Moresco's ultimate winnings
in the financial game, it permitted itself the luxury of
questioning the several moves by which he achieved them.  Never, in
the opinion of Maverick, had he behaved more foolishly than in the
matter of Jean Rieske's sheep.  Jean Rieske was a sheep-owner in a
small way, shepherding his own flock in the windy passes of the
hills, made his exclusive pasture by the strip of barrenness that
encompassed them.  Jean Rieske had been several other things in a
small way, and had thoughts other than belong properly to sheep-herding.  He collected bits of ledges and outcrops, and carried
them to Maverick to be assayed, until at last he conceived that he
had made a "strike."  Forthwith he would be a miner.
</p><p>Making a mine out of a prospect hole is an expensive business,
but if Moresco was willing to risk the money, Jean Rieske would
risk his sheep.  He worked at it ten months, and at the end of that
time he discovered that he had no mine and no flock.  So he went a-shepherding again, and to the same flock, but as a hireling, not an
owner,&mdash;at which he considered himself aggrieved, and was comforted
with strong waters.  At the end of other ten months Moresco
discharged him, and gave his place to the Little Coyote.
</p><p>Whatever Jean Rieske swore and Maverick prophesied, the Coyote
proved himself born for it.  He knew the hills; he scented pasture
from afar; he had an instinct for short cuts like a homing pigeon;
he was weather-wise as&mdash;an Indian.  The flock prospered.  The
Little Coyote was happy: he did a man's work, and he served
Moresco.  Two or three times in a year he came in to replenish his
stores and to make report.  He stood at the door of the store,
grave and still, until Moresco came out and spoke to him: "Vell,
vat you wandt, Kyode?"  The shepherd gave the tale of his flock in
straight-spoken words and few, with long pauses.  When he had quite
done, Moresco would say, with his hand withdrawn from his left
breast pocket, "Take a cigar, Kyode."  Then he would light his own,
and they smoked together, the man and his son, for a sign of good
understanding, and went each his own way.
</p><p>The flock increased and became notable.  Moresco trusted his
shepherd.  It was a responsible employment, and there were men in
Maverick who coveted it.  Persons who felt the situation to be
indefensible probed it a little, gingerly.  Why should the likes of
that job fall to a Piute, when there <pb n="252"/>  were better men
wanting it?  "Vell, for one ting, id is cheaber," said the
merchant, with his bland, inclusive smile.  And that was as much as
most people got out of Moresco.
</p><p>Three, four, five years the Little Coyote worked the flock
from Keynot across the summit to Rose Springs, and in all the
foodful hollows that lie between.  He saw little of men, and missed
them not at all.  If in the wickiups beyond Maverick there were
young breasts and bright, desirous eyes, he took no thought of
them: he thought only of Moresco and the flock, how he might
prosper it.  All the slow heat of his being burned in a passion of
service for the man who treated him as if he were white.  He ran at
the head of his flock; he lay down with it by night; he carried the
lambs in his bosom.  He lived as simply as one of his own sheep,
and looked a young god, walking clear on the skyline with the
nimble flock, or coming up out of streams on summer mornings, with
the sun shining on his fine gold-colored limbs.  And oh, but he was
a silent one, was the Little Coyote.  He had no pipes to play, nor
any song; but at times, as he walked in the full tide of the
spring, near naked and unashamed, throwing up the tall stalk of
some hillside flower and catching it, his lips moved in the minor
croon of his people, the <hi rend="italic">" he-na, ah-na, ha-na</hi>," that is the
burden of their songs,&mdash;an old word of a forgotten tongue, never to
be laid aside.  It seemed as if the morning prime of earth
persisted in him with that word.
</p><p>By this time the flock had trebled, and the Coyote, going down
to make report, so far forgot his Indian training as to admit his
pride.
</p><p>"Id is too much for you, Kyode," said Moresco.  "I vill ged
Chopo to helb you."
</p><p>"Chopo is a fool," said the Coyote.  "I would rather have
another dog."
</p><p>"Two dogs, if you like," returned Moresco.
</p><p>The Coyote considered.  "No," he said, "one, if I may choose
him."
</p><p>So Moresco's shepherd had one of the famous dogs of Del Mar,
and Maverick outdid itself guessing the price Moresco paid for it.
Maverick had other things to talk about before the season was over,
for that was the winter of the "great snow."  Snows came
occasionally to Maverick, in the wake of storms fleeting over from
ridge to crest.  They whitened the hills, crusted the streams, and
snuggled away into the roots of the pines by the bare rock gullies.
They came in a swirl of wind sometimes, that packed them deep in
the canons, and left the high places bare to days of twinkling
cold, but afforded nothing by way of contrast to the great snow.
For two days the sky lowered and brooded and the valleys filled and
filled with a white murk, dry, and warmer than should be for the
time of year.  The moon of nights showed sickly white and cast no
shadow.
</p><p>The Little Coyote smelled snow in the air, and began to move
the flock toward the Marionette.  The Marionette was the hole in
the ground that Jean Rieske hoped would turn out a mine.  It was a
deep, wide gouge in the face of the hill, at the head of a steep
gully.  The Coyote had built corrals in the gully, and used it at
lambing time.  The Indian's instinct proved him right.  The third
morning snow fell, wet and clogging.  It increased with the day,
and grew colder.  The man and the dogs put all their skill to the
proof, but the sheep huddled and stumbled.  They were half a day's
journey from the mine in the best of weather, and every hour the
storm thickened.  Crossing Cedar Flat, two miners, going hastily
down from a far, solitary mine, gave the Coyote a friendly hail.
</p><p>"Leave the sheep to the dogs, and get out of this!" they
cried.  "It's going to be a hell of a storm."
</p><p>But that the cold had stiffened his face into immobility the
Coyote would <pb n="253"/>  smiled.  They to talk to him of the weather
and the sheep!
</p><p>He saw what his work was to be, and settled to it.  He
lightened the camp burro of his pack and let him go.  The little
beast trudged doggedly beside him, until presently they came to a
wind-tilted cedar in the lee of a hill.  The burro considered; he
looked at the shepherd, and put his nose to the thick, sodden snow;
he backed under the cedar and dropped his head.  It was a hard
shift, but he would see what came of it.  The shepherd spoke to his
dogs: they lagged and whimpered, but they heard his voice.  He who
had been chary of words grew voluble: he shouted, he urged, he
adjured them, he wrestled with them in the white silence of the
snow.  The Piute had none of the white man's gift for expedients to
save himself and as many of the sheep as he could.  The sheep were
Moresco's, and Moresco trusted him: he must bring them all in.  If
one halted and stumbled, the Coyote carried it until it was warmed
and rested a little.  They floundered in a drift, and he lifted
them out upon his shoulders, the dogs whining a confession of
helplessness.  It grew dark, and the snow still fell, sharp, and
fine, and most bitter cold.  The wind came up and snatched his
breath from him; but there was no longer any need for crying out,&mdash;
the dogs understood.  They had passed the first revolt of physical
terror, and remembered their obligations; their spirits touched the
man's spirit and grappled with their work.  They were no longer
dogs, but heroes.  Moreover, they knew now where they went, and
helped him with their finer sense.  Happen what would to the man
and the dogs, the sheep would all come in.
</p><p>Late, late they found the ravine of the Marionette.  The
Little Coyote had lost all sense of time and feeling.  He drowsed
upon his feet, but moved steadily about the flock.  The dogs bayed,
and he heard the sharper clang of the bells given back by the rocks
as the sheep began to pour into the cavern of the mine.  His head
floated in space; he was warm and comforted, and he knew what these
things might mean.  His feet slipped in the yielding drifts.
</p><p>"Moresco!  Moresco!" he cried, as a man might call, in
extremity, on God.

</p><p>The morning broke steely blue and cold upon a white wonder.
At Maverick, people looked up from their path-shoveling to ask if
the men from the mines had all come in, and what was to be done for
those who had not.  Two miners, arriving late the previous day, had
told redoubtable tales of the trail and the wind and the snow.
Incidentally, they mentioned having seen the Little Coyote.  By ten
o'clock it was known in all the saloons that Moresco was offering
inducements for men to go to the rescue of his shepherd.  Opinion
gained ground that the Coyote was a fool for not looking out for
himself better, and that cold never hurt a Piute anyway, and if he
was at the Marionette he was all right.
</p><p>"Yes," said a man nursing a frozen foot,&mdash;"yes, if he got in."
</p><p>Within an hour there were three found willing to start,&mdash;Salty
Bill, an Indian called Jim, and one Duncan, a miner from Panniment
way,&mdash;and who else but Moresco!  People said it was ridiculous;
Moresco was short and fat, and turned fifty.  The barkeeper at the
Old Corner wanted to know if anybody thought Moresco would trust
the counting of his sheep to any other.
</p><p>It is fifteen miles from Maverick to the Marionette, and all
uphill.  By the time they came to the turn of the trail they were
knee-deep in the snow.  It was soft and shifty, and balled
underfoot.  They kept as much as possible to the high places; this
avoided the drifts, but made more climbing.  Crossing the flats
they floundered hip-deep, wide of the trail.  Perspiration rolled
from their foreheads and froze upon their beards.  Their bodies
were warm <pb n="254"/>  and wet, and their lungs wheezing; they had lost
the sense of their feet under them.  The sun on the snow made them
blind and sick.  They had been out four hours, and were little more
than halfway.  The white men cursed with what breath they had; only
the Indian kept a stolid front.  Moresco was purple and gasping.
</p><p>"Give up," cried Salty Bill,&mdash;"give up, Moresco!  We'll never
make it.  Such a peck of trouble about a Piute and a parcel of
sheep.  Better for the Coyote to freeze than us four.  Give up, I
say."
</p><p>"Ah yes, der Kyode," said Moresco, dazed and feebly,&mdash;"der
Liddle Kyode.  He vas my son," and he burrowed on through the snow.
</p><p>The men stared, but they followed.  Salty Bill kept the lead;
he was in a ferment to have the thing over with, that he might go
home and tell his wife.
</p><p>Six hours out, quite spent, and drunk with fatigue, they came
to the ravine of the Marionette.  They heard the sheep bleat and
the dogs yelp, trailing frozen-footed across the snow.  At the foot
of the gully a white heap lay, covered but well defined, spread out
in the symbol of a sacrifice that the Hebrew repudiated and the
Indian had never known.  Moresco brushed the snow from it with his
hands, and, as he stooped above it, tears fell upon a face grown
white in death and strangely like his own.  It was the Little
Coyote.
</p>
<signed>                              <hi rend="italic"> Mary Austin.</hi></signed>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
