<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AusTown"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="AusTown">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Little Town of the Grape Vines</title>
<title type="sort">little town of the grape vines</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">17</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AusTown</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475720</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Little Town of the Grape Vines</title>
<title type="sort">little town of the grape vines</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Edited by</resp>
<name>editor</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<date value="1903">1903</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Vol. 91</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Verification made against printed text</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1903">1903</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="article" id="d3">
<head>
Austin, Mary.  "The Little Town of the Grape Vines."
<lb/> <hi rend="italic"> Atlantic Monthly</hi> 91 (1903): 822-25.
</head>

<pb n="822"/>

<p>THERE are still some places in the West where the quail cry,
<hi rend="italic">" Cuidado;"</hi> where all the speech is soft, all the manners
gentle; where all the dishes have <hi rend="italic"> chile</hi> in them, and they make
more of the Sixteenth of September than they do of the Fourth of
July.  I mean in particular El Pueblo de Los Vinos Uvas.  Where it
lies, how to come at it, you will not get from me; rather would I
show you the heron's nest in the Tulares.  It has a peak behind it,
glinting above the Tamarack pines; above, a breaker of ruddy hills
that have a long slope valley-wards, and the shore-ward steep of
waves toward the Sierras.
</p><p>Below the Town of the Grape Vines, which shortens to Los Vinos
for common use, the land dips away to the river pastures and the
Tulares.  It shrouds under a twilight thicket of vines, under a
dome of cottonwood trees, drowsy and murmurous as a hive.
Hereabout are some strips of tillage and the headgates that dam up
the creek for the village weirs; upstream you catch the growl of
the <hi rend="italic"> arrastra</hi>.  Wild vines that begin among the willows lap over
to the orchard rows, and take the trellis and rooftree.
</p><p>There is another town above Los Vinos that merits some
attention, a town of arches and airy crofts, full of linnets,
blackbirds, fruit-birds, small, sharp hawks, and mocking-birds that
sing by night.  They pour out piercing, unendurably sweet cavatinas
above the fragrance of bloom and musky smell of fruit.  Singing is
in fact the business of the night at Los Vinos, as sleeping is for
midday.  When the moon comes over the mountain wall new washed from
the sea, and the shadows lie like lace on the stamped floors of the
patios, from recess to recess of the vine tangle run the thrum of
guitars and the voice of singing.
</p><p>At Los Vinos they keep up all the good customs brought out of
Old Mexico, or bred in a lotus-eating land: drink and are merry,
and look out for something to eat afterward; have children, nine or
ten to a family; have cock-fights, keep the siesta, smoke
cigarettes, and wait for the sun to go down.  And always they
dance, at dusk, on the smooth adobe floors, afternoons, under the
trellises, where the earth is damp and has a fruity smell.  A
betrothal, a wedding, or a christening, or the mere proximity of a
guitar, is sufficient occasion; and if the occasion lacks, send for
the guitar and dance anyway.
</p><p>All this requires explanation.  Antonio Sevadra, drifting this
way from Old Mexico with the flood that poured into the Tappan
district after the first notable strike, discovered La Golondrina.
It was a generous lode, and Tony a good fellow; to work it he
brought in all the Sevadras, even to the twice removed, all the
Castros, who were his wife's family, all the Saises, Romeros, and
Eschobars, the relations of his relations-in-law.  There you have
the beginning of a pretty considerable town.  To these accrued much
of the Spanish California float swept out of the Southwest by
Eastern enterprise.  They slacked away again when the price of
silver went down and the ore dwindled in La Golondrina.  All the
hot eddy of mining life swept away from that corner of the hills,
but there were always those too idle, too poor to move, or too
easily content with El Pueblo de Los Vinos Uvas.
</p><p>Nobody comes nowadays to the Town of the Grape Vines except,
as we say, "with the breath of crying," but of these enough.  All
the low sills run over with small heads.  Ah, ah!  There is a kind
of pride in that if you did but know it,&mdash;to have your baby every
year <pb n="823"/>  or so as the time sets, and keep a full breast.  So
great a blessing as marriage is easily come by.  It is told of Ruy
Garcia that when he went for his marriage license he lacked a
dollar of the clerk's fee, but borrowed it of the sheriff, who
expected reelection, and exhibited thereby a commendable thrift.
</p><p>Of what account is it to lack meal or meat when you may have
it of any neighbor?  Besides there is sometimes a point of honor in
these things.  Jesus Romero, father of ten, had a job sacking ore
in the Marionette, which he gave up of his own accord.  "Eh, why?"
said Jesus, "for my fam'ly."
</p><p>"It is so, Senora," he said solemnly.  "I go to the
Marionette; I work, I eat meat&mdash;pie&mdash;frijoles&mdash;good, ver' good.  I
come home Sad'day nigh'; I see my fam'ly.  I play a lil' game poker
with the boys, have lil' drink wine, my money all gone.  My fam'ly
they have no money, nothing eat.  All time I work at mine I eat
good, ver' good grub.  I think sorry for my fam'ly.  No, no,
Senora, I no work no more that Marionette; I stay with my fam'ly."
The wonder of it is, I think, that the family had the same point of
view.
</p><p>Every house in the Town of the Vines has its garden plot, corn
and brown beans, and a row of peppers reddening in the sun, and in
damp borders of the irrigating ditches clumps of <hi rend="italic"> yerba santa</hi>,
horehound, catnip, and spikenard, wholesome herbs and curative, but
if no peppers then nothing at all.  You will have for a holiday
dinner in Los Vinos soup with meat balls and chile in it, chicken
with chile, rice with chile, fried beans with more chile,
enchilads, which is corn cake with a sauce of chile and tomatoes,
onion, grated cheese and olives, and for a relish chile <hi rend="italic"> pepinos</hi>
passed about in a dish; all of which is comfortable and corrective
to the stomach.  You will have wine which every man makes for
himself, of good body and inimitable bouquet, and sweets that are
not nearly so nice as they look.
</p><p>There are two occasions when you may count on that kind of a
meal; always on the Sixteenth of September, and on the two-yearly
visits of Father Shannon.  It is absurd of course that El Pueblo de
Los Vinos Uvas should have an Irish priest, but Black Rock, Minton,
Jimville, and all that country round do not find it so.  Father
Shannon visits them all, waits by the Red Butte to confess the
shepherds who go through with their flocks, carries blessing to
small and isolated mines, and so in the course of a year or so
works around to Los Vinos to bury and marry and christen.  Then all
the little graves in the Campo Santo are brave with tapers, the
brown pine head-boards blossom like Aaron's rod with paper roses
and bright cheap prints of Our Lady of Sorrows.  Then the Senora
Sevadra, who thinks herself elect of heaven for that office,
gathers up the original sinners, the little Elijias, Lolas,
Manuelitas, Joses, and Felipes, by dint of adjurations and sweets
smuggled into small perspiring palms, to fit them for the
Sacrament.
</p><p>I used to peek in at them, never so softly, in Dona Ina's
living-room; Raphael-eyed little imps, going sidewise on their
knees to rest them from the bare floor; candles lit on the mantel
to give a religious air, and a great sheaf of wild bloom before the
Holy Family.  Come Sunday, they set out the altar in the
schoolhouse, with the fine drawn altar cloths, the beaten silver
candlesticks, and the wax images, chief glory of Los Vinos, brought
up muleback from Old Mexico forty years ago.  All in white the
communicants go up two and two in a hushed sweet awe to take the
body of their Lord, and Tomaso, who is priest's boy, tries not to
look unduly puffed up by his office.  After that, you have dinner
and a bottle of wine that ripened on the sunny slope of Escondito.
All the week Father Shannon has shriven his people, who bring clean
consciences to the betterment of appetite, <pb n="824"/>  and the father
sets them an example.  Father Shannon is rather big about the
middle, to accommodate the large laugh that lives in him, but a
most shrewd searcher of hearts.  It is reported that one derives
much comfort from his confessional, and I for my part believe it.
</p><p>The celebration of the Sixteenth, though it comes every year,
takes as long to prepare for as Holy Communion.  The Senoritas have
each a new dress, the Senoras a new <hi rend="italic"> rebosa</hi>.  The young
gentlemen have new silver trimmings to their sombreros, unspeakable
ties, silk handkerchiefs, and new leathers to their spurs.  At this
time, when the peppers glow in the gardens and the young quail cry,
"Cuidado," "Have a care!" you can hear the <hi rend="italic"> plump, plump</hi> of the
<hi rend="italic"> metate</hi> from the alcoves of the vines, where comfortable old
dames, whose experience gives them the touch of art, are pounding
out corn for <hi rend="italic"> tamales</hi>.
</p><p>Schoolteachers from abroad have tried before now at Los Vinos
to have school begin on the first of September, but get nothing
else to stir in the heads of the little Castros, Garcias, and
Romeros but feasts and cockfights until after the Sixteenth.
Perhaps you need to be told that this is the anniversary of the
Republic, when Liberty awoke and cried in the provinces of Old
Mexico.  You are roused at midnight to hear them shouting in the
streets, <hi rend="italic">" Vive la Libertad!"</hi> answered from the houses and the
recesses of the vines, <hi rend="italic">" Vive la Mexico!"</hi>  At sunrise shots are
fired commemorating the tragedy of unhappy Maximilian, and then
music, the noblest of national hymns, as the great flag of Old
Mexico floats up the flagpole in the bare little plaza of shabby
Los Vinos.  The sun over Pine Mountain greets the eagle of
Montezuma before it touches the vineyards and the town, and the day
begins with a great shout.  By and by there will be a reading of
the Declaration of Independence and an address punctured by
<hi rend="italic">vives;</hi> all the town in its best dress, and some exhibits of
horsemanship that make lathered bits and bloody spurs; also a
cockfight.
</p><p>By night there will be dancing, and such music! old Santos to
play the flute, a little lean man with a saintly countenance, young
Garcia, whose guitar has a soul, and Carrasco with the violin.
They sit on a high platform above the dancers in the candle-flare,
backed by the red, white, and green of Old Mexico, and play
fervently such music as you will not hear elsewhere.
</p><p>At midnight the flag comes down.  Count yourself at a loss if
you are not moved by that performance.  Pine Mountain watches
whitely overhead, shepherd fires glow strongly on the gloomy hills,
the plaza, the bare glistening pole, the dark folk, and the bright
dresses are lit ruddily by a bonfire.  It leaps up to the eagle
flag, dies down, the music begins softly, and aside.  They play
airs of old longing and exile; slowly out of the dark the flag
drops, bellying and falling with the midnight draft.  Sometimes a
hymn is sung, always there are tears.  The flag is down; Tony
Sevadra has received it in his arms.  The music strikes a barbaric
swelling tune; another flag begins a slow ascent,&mdash;it takes a
breath or two to realize that they are both, flag and tune, the
Star-Spangled Banner,&mdash;a volley is fired, we are back, if you
please, in California of America.  Every youth who has the blood of
patriots in him lays hold on Tony Sevadra's flag, happiest if he
can get a corner of it.  The music goes before, the folk fall in
two and two, singing.  They sing everything,&mdash;America, the
Marseillaise, for the sake of the French shepherds hereabout, the
hymn of Cuba, and the Chilean national air, to comfort two families
of that country.  The flag goes to Dona Ina's, with the
candlesticks and the altar cloths; then Los Vinos eats tamales and
dances the sun up the slope of Pine Mountain.
</p><p>You are not to suppose that they do <pb n="825"/>  not keep the
Fourth, Washington's Birthday, and Thanksgiving at the Town of the
Grape Vines.  These make excellent occasions for quitting work and
dancing, but the Sixteenth is the holiday of the heart.  On
Memorial Day the graves have garlands and new pictures of the
saints tacked to the headboards.  There is great virtue in an <hi rend="italic">
ave</hi> said in the Camp of the Saints.  I like that name which the
Spanish-speaking people give to the garden of the dead, Campo
Santo, as if it might be some bed of healing from which blind souls
and sinners rise up whole and praising God.  Sometimes the speech
of simple folk hints at truth the understanding does not reach.  I
am persuaded only a complex soul can get any good of a plain
religion.  Your earthborn is a poet and a symbolist.  We breed in
an environment of asphalt pavement a body of people whose creeds
are chiefly restrictions against other people's way of life, who
have kitchens and latrines under the same roof that houses their
God.  Such as these go to church to be edified, but at Los Vinos
they go only for pure worship, and to entreat their God.  The
logical conclusion of the faith that every good gift cometh from
God is the open hand and the finer courtesy.  The meal done without
buys a candle for the neighbor's dead child.  You do foolishly to
suppose that the candle does no good.
</p><p>At Los Vinos every house is a piece of the earth,&mdash;thick-walled, whitewashed adobe that keeps the even temperature of a
cave; every man is an accomplished horseman and consequently bow-legged; every family keeps dogs, flea-bitten mongrels that loll on
the earthen floors.  The people speak a purer Castilian than
obtains in like villages of Mexico, and the way they count
relationship everybody is more or less akin.  There is not much
villainy among them.  What incentive to thieving or killing can
there be when there is little wealth, and that to be had for the
borrowing?  If they love too hotly, as we say, "take their meat
before grace," so do their betters.  Eh, what! shall a man be a
saint before he is dead?  And besides, Holy Church takes it out of
you one way and another before all is done.  Come away, you who are
possessed with your own importance in the scheme of things, and
have got nothing you did not sweat for, come away by the brown
valleys and full-bosomed hills, to the even-breathing days, to the
kindliness, earthiness, ease of El Pueblo de Los Vinos Uvas.
</p><p>                              <hi rend="italic"> Mary Austin.</hi>
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
