<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AusWooi"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="AusWooi">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Wooing of the Se&ntilde;orita</title>
<title type="sort">wooing of the senorita</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">19</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AusWooi</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475723</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Wooing of the Se&ntilde;orita</title>
<title level="j">Overland Monthly</title>
<title type="sort">wooing of the senorita</title>
<author>Mary Austin</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>A. Roman &amp; Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>San Francisco</pubPlace>
<date value="1897-03">March 1897</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>29</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Austin, Mary.  "The Wooing of the Se&ntilde;orita."
<hi rend="italic">Overland Monthly</hi> n.s. 29 (Mar. 1897): 258-263.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1897-03">March 1897</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Native American</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-04">April 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header; Tagged with TEI.2-compatible SGML; Parsed against
teilite.dtd.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="258"/>
<head><bibl>
THE WOOING OF THE SEN&Ntilde;ORITA.
</bibl></head>

<p>MILLARD TRAVIS was a man of ideas; he was also very young.  This
was not so bad as it might have been, for his ideas were of the toy pistol sort,&mdash;a
nuisance to everybody, but only occasionally hurtful to the holder.  The idea
which made Travis particularly odious to his fellow men was less original than
unexpected.  He merely held that all this peep-show performance of modern
affairs was a progression towards emptiness, that there was nothing sound or
wholesome, but naked, unblushing savagery, and his <hi rend="italic">vade mecum</hi> was
"our progenitor, Adam."
</p><p>As he was born in Boston of a long line of Doctor-of-Divinity and
Professor-of-Moral-Science ancestry, it may be inferred that his opportunities for
observation were limited.  As may be also imagined his peculiar views had not
endeared him to his friends.  Miss Vandeventer went so far as to say she thought
Adam must have been a stupid fellow, he had so few experiences.  But then Miss
Vandeventer lived in New York, where the tinsel glitter manifestations of this
decried civilization are particularly seductive.
</p><p>Travis's conceit, however, was polemical rather than personal, and he
continued to conduct himself faultlessly by the canons of cultivated society, and
fed his theories until they waxed big and obnoxious.  Then lest he should grow
inflated past all usefulness, fate pricked the bubble of his queer conceit, and the
manner of his downfall is worth relating.

</p><p>He had been holding forth at the club, <pb n="259"/>  where his ideas were
neither popular nor well received, and had been told incontinently to shut up.  It is
not gratifying to talk to a man who thinks you would appear to better advantage in
red paint and a breech-cloth.  There was a visiting stranger at the club, a
ruminative little man from the West, who might be conceived as forgiving
himself the too evident rotundity of his vest because of its increased facilities for
the display of gold link chain and jeweled fob.  The Western man wanted to know
if Travis had ever seen a Digger Indian, or a Comanche, or a Piute?  Travis had
not.  He had a complacent acquaintance with the most notable institutions of this
evanescent fabric of human affairs, but he had never seen raw humanity at home.
He had never seen a Digger, nor a Piute.
</p><p>"Wait until you do," said the man from the West.
</p><p>This suggestion, tipped with an air of superior knowledge, had the
immediate effect of closing the discussion, the club rejoicing greatly thereat.
</p><p>When the other man has seen what you have only thought about, there is
really nothing more to be said.  Conning over this rebuff, Travis conceived the
idea of putting his theories to the test of personal observation.  A month later saw
Travis on his way to California to engage in the study of raw humanity.  He was
bound for Los Vinos, a cattle ranch in the San Joaquin valley.  He had met the
owner of Los Vinos on an Atlantic steam-ship the summer before, the Californian
being on his way to secure the co-operation of English financiers in his pet
irrigation scheme.
</p><p>Travis had procured him some fortunate introductions and the rancher had
extended an invitation with all the effusion of Western landed interests toward
Eastern capital.  The Californian had told him that the work on his ranch was
done by Indians.  Travis was humble, and recognized his limitations.  He would
begin with the Indians at Los Vinos, who might be supposed to have suffered a
diminution of their naturalness, and work himself into a state of sympathy with
raw humanity.
</p><p>He found Los Vinos with very little trouble, a cattle range skilfully gerry-mandered over the best grazing land in three counties.  On the way there he saw
Diggers and Piutes, he also smelt them and realized that a course of esoteric
culture is not the best preparation for the study of aboriginal humanity.  At Los
Vinos he found Piutes and Greasers and degenerate half-breeds,&mdash;not exactly what
he came to see, but sufficiently raw for his purpose.  It was snowing when the
train pulled out of Boston, but at Los Vinos woolly clouds rolled up the
ca&ntilde;ons from blossomy acres of white, mellowed and bordered with gold,
and all intoxicating delights exhaled in the sensuous atmosphere.  He declined the
hospitality of the superintendent at the ranch house and sought bed and board
with Juan Romero, head vaquero.  Romero's house was an old stage station, a
long low adobe structure set on the slope where the valley rises to meet the hills,
some miles below the ranch headquarters and close to the stream that leaped
whitening from the ca&ntilde;on as far as it could or dared, to the plain below.
</p><p>A row of poplars ran as far up the slope to the mountain as the stream ran
down to the valley.  Behind the house the water foamed and curdled under a
twilight thicket of grape-vines, whose twisted stems, riding the ridge of the roof
like some green old man of the sea, dropped pendulous fingers to the eaves of the
low veranda that looked full on the glare of the leopard-colored plain.
</p><p>The chief of the vaqueros welcomed Travis to this ancient hostelry with
the <pb n="260"/>  air of an hidalgo, and the Se&ntilde;ora Romero was very good to
him.  The proprietor of Los Vinos was still abroad and the superintendent was a
man of many cares.  Travis purchased a saddle and a sombrero and resigned
himself to the impulse of the hour.
</p><p>He spent the first two weeks hunting fleas and learning to like villainous
messes of <hi rend="italic">chile con carne</hi>.  At the end of that time he had become
accustomed to both, and all but forgotten previous states of existence.  He rode
with the vaqueros after he had learned to manage their vicious little broncos, and
had borne with becoming humility the amusement his fashionable-riding-school
ignorance of the art provoked.  He liked the wild rush through the chaparral and
the hazardous scurrying down steep hillsides, and exulted in the bellowing
m&ecirc;l&eacute;e of the rodeo.  Much more he delighted to sleep unhoused
between the earth and sky.  A new sense stirred within him in the wakeful pauses
of the night, a sense of gladsome multitudinous existences peopling the sentient
earth.  The domestic life he found less interesting, it was so undeniably dirty; but
there were phases of it that filled him with unmixed delight.
</p><p>The women, for instance, were charming.  That the most charming were
found sooner or later to be of doubtful origin was to be regretted, but the most
aboriginal, if she were anything less than middle-aged, seldom failed of the
picturesque.  He was never weary of watching the Se&ntilde;ora Romero and the
felicity of her compromises between the indolent instincts of race and what she
felt to be due to her position as wife of the man who could rope and tie more
cattle in a day than any man in Los Vinos.
</p><p>In the fourth week of his enchantment, when the grape vines were misty
with bloom, came to Los Vinos the Se&ntilde;orita De Silvierra.  She said she
was Spanish.  She was the daughter of a tamale man in San Jos&eacute;, and bore
some unexplained relation to Juan's wife, to whom she had come on a visit.  The
Se&ntilde;ora Romero, it may be remarked in passing, belonged to that race who
had not found it incompatible with a state of undiluted human nature to draw
rations from the government.  But that could hardly account for the general
irresistibility which Travis acknowledged in her young relative.  Brown, passive,
and inscrutable, she held him with a charm that escaped definition, just as the soft
illusions of her speech eluded his tongue trained to the prim syllabification of
Bostonese.  After the Se&ntilde;orita came he rode less often with the vaqueros
and cared less interestedly for the indolent simplicity of life in the wickiups.
After the Se&ntilde;orita came he neglected his correspondence and began to
learn the vernacular.
</p><p>The great valley smiled for a brief season and lay still, fainting under the
stress of summer suns.  All day the light beat down the hollow of the valley, and
pulsed back to the translucent dome, but Travis no longer noted the recurrent
phases of the day.  Long afternoons the Se&ntilde;orita sat on the veranda with
her interminable drawn-work, while Travis smoked cigarettes, which the
Se&ntilde;orita rolled for him, and found his appreciation of the curves of her
lithe young body in no wise diminished by the cut of her greasy frock, with half
the buttons off.  When the light failed the Se&ntilde;orita tinkled the strings of
her guitar, while the wind shook small mysterious patterings and more mysterious
silences out of the poplar trees, and the warm earth turned duskily to the yellow
California moon, which is not projected on a glassy sky, <pb n="261"/>  [illustration
omitted] but hangs full orbed upon the verge of space.
</p><p>About this time Travis began to take his Sunday dinner with the
superintendent at the ranch house.  On Sundays there came to Romero's, in the
unmitigated ugliness of cheap calicoes and "store clothes," the youth of Los
Vinos, and the Se&ntilde;orita was very glad to see them.  She laced her soft
young curves into her only pair of stays under a pink and purple frock, and
became at once ordinary and unlovely.  There came also from Tuniwai, beyond
Salt Creek, one Hawker, a villainous half-white, gross and indolent, but not
without good points, or what passed for such at Los Vinos; an audacious air, a
skin less swart than might have been expected, and a talent for existing without
labor.
</p><p>Now mark the inconsistencies of human nature.  Los Vinos admired
Hawker in proportion as the white strain was uppermost, and in like degree Travis
found him odious, especially as the half-breed began to discover an attitude of
mind that, considering the errand on which he had come, the Bostonian had no
manner of right to resent.  It is one thing to entertain the belief that society is used
up and another to find yourself regarded as the product of its effeteness.  Travis
acknowledged a diminished personality in the presence of the Se&ntilde;orita,
but he did not want Hawker to tell her so.
</p><p>Sitting on the veranda with the company adjusting its behavior to the half-breed's opinion of his deserts, he experienced the disgust of a masquerading
monarch who finds his incognito more of a <pb n="262"/>  disguise than he intended.  It
was then that he remembered his proxy host, whom up to this time he had
somewhat neglected.  The superintendent had been nine years at Los Vinos and
had but one opinion of the inhabitants, he said.  When Travis thought of Hawker
he was inclined to agree with him, but he remembered the Se&ntilde;orita and
withheld judgment.
</p><p>Events of late had not softened the asperity of the superintendent's temper.
From time to time marked discrepancies in the count of the Los Vinos herds were
found to correspond with the appearance in the market of hides and cattle bearing
a mutilated brand.  And the nuisance did not abate, notwithstanding the whole
population of Los Vinos bent itself with alacrity to hunting down the culprit.
</p><p>When Travis had been two months at Los Vinos, Romero took another
boarder, a shy, silent man who had received permission to prospect the Los Vinos
grant for minerals.  Travis was at first drawn towards the stranger, but the event
proved him a man of no discrimination, for before a week was out he
fellowshiped with Hawker like a brother.  Travis returned to the veranda, his
cigarette, and his Se&ntilde;orita.
</p><p>One of those unnumbered languorous days the stranger disappeared in the
vaporous distance down the valley toward Summerfield.  When he came again he
wore the badge of a sheriff's deputy, and the sheriff was with him.  They dropped
wearily from their saddles in the white, palpitant glare of afternoon, before the
dismantled bar room at Romero's, where Travis and the superintendent had worn
out the morning with cribs and cigars.
</p><p>Travis surveyed their grim and war-like aspect with humorous
appreciation not unmixed with personal satisfaction, for the much sought-for
cattle thief whom they had come to arrest was none other than the half-breed,
Hawker.  Half an hour later, leaving them to their plans, Travis, passing out of the
low dim room, came suddenly on Hawker and the Se&ntilde;orita crouched
listening under the window.  A dismayed sense of the situation translated itself
from eye to eye with the swiftness of thought.
</p><p>The sheriff's strident voice reached them through the open window, and
the water gurgled continuously among the rocks.  How the recollection of those
long afternoons of inconsequent dalliance smote him in the vulgar complacency
of the girl's confidence in her power over him.
</p><p>She was not looking at him, but at her lover in triumphant assurance.  The
half-breed, calculating the chances between jealousy and fear, watched him with
his hand thrust backward in a menace the Bostonian did not understand.  Ten
steps away his host plotted with the officers of the law to rid himself of a
nuisance, and Travis was a party to his intention.  In common courtesy he could
do no less than raise his voice in alarm.  He saw himself withheld from this by the
Se&ntilde;orita's interpretation of his attitude toward her, doubly withheld by the
half-breed's mocking distrust of his intention.
</p><p>The Bostonian walked out of the dilemma as instantly as he had walked
in, suddenly aware, as he went, of the rank smell of rawhide crisping in the sun,
and Romero's flea-bitten dogs sprawling on the kitchen floor.  Hawker let down
his bridle rein from a broken trellis among the vines, and stepped cautiously down
the deep wash of the stream that furrowed the plain far below the summer limit of
its waters.
</p><p>If the sheriff and his party had looked back as they climbed the long slope
of the hill to Tuniwai, they might have seen <pb n="263"/>  the diminished figure of a
horseman spurring rapidly across the vari-colored plain.  Travis did not meet
them, two days later, when they rode back bootless, weary, and profane.
Important business, so Romero said, had called him home.

</p><p>Travis's friends all declared him much improved by his brief sojourn in
the West.
</p><p>He never mentioned this episode to any one, not even to Miss
Vandeventer, whom he married the following winter; perhaps because he cannot
for the life of him tell what he has done.  He is troubled at times over his breach
of good faith to his host, but he does not know how he could have consoled the
Se&ntilde;orita, having robbed her of her lover.  If she has married him since, no
doubt he has made her suffer for having permitted a rival's devotion to reach the
point of making her husband his debtor for life.
</p><p>At all times he sees himself compounding a felony; but he need not
trouble himself about his breach of good faith with the superintendent.  If he had
raised the alarm the half-breed would probably have shot one or both of them, a
contingency that has not occurred to him.

</p><p>Shortly after his return Travis wrote some clever sketches of California
life which were much admired, but from beginning to end there was not one word
in them of the dirty but adorable Se&ntilde;orita de Silvierra.
</p>
<trailer> <hi rend="italic">M. Austin.</hi></trailer>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
