<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AusWill"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="AusWill">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Return of Mr. Wills</title>
<title type="sort">return of mr wills</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">18</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AusWill</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475722</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Return of Mr. Wills</title>
<title type="sort">return of mr wills</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Edited by</resp>
<name>editor</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Century Magazine</publisher>
<date value="1907">1907</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Vol. 74</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Verification made against printed text</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1907">1907</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman and Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head>Austin, Mary.  "The Return of Mr. Wills."
<lb/>
<hi rend="italic"> Century Magazine</hi> 74 (1907): 244-247.<lb/>

Author of "Isidro," etc.
</head>
<pb n="244"/>

<p>
MRS. WILLS had lived seventeen years with Mr. Wills, and when he
left her for three, those three were so much the best of her
married life that she wished he had never come back.  The only real
trouble with Mr. Wills was that he should never have moved West.
Back East, I suppose, they breed such men because they need them,
but they ought really to keep them there.
</p><p>I am quite certain that when Mr. Wills was courting Mrs. Wills
he parted his hair in the middle and the breast pocket of his best
suit had a bright silk lining which Mr. Wills pulled up to simulate
a silk handkerchief.  Mrs. Wills had a certain draggled prettiness
and a way of tossing her head, that came back to her after Mr.
Wills left, which made one think she might have been the prettiest
girl of her town.  They were happy enough at first when Mr. Wills
was a grocery clerk, assistant Sunday school superintendent, and
they owned a cabinet organ and four little Willses.  It might have
been that Mr. Wills thought he could go right on being the same
sort of man in the West&mdash;he was clerk at the Bed Rock Emporium and
had brought the organ and the children&mdash;or it might have been he
thought himself at bottom a very different sort of man, and meant
to be it if he got a chance.
</p><p>There is a sort of man bred up in close communities, who is
like a cask, to whom the church, public opinion, the social note,
are hoops to hold him in serviceable shape.  Without these there
are a good many ways of going to pieces.  Mr. Wills's way was lost
mines.
</p><p>Being clerk at the Emporium, where miners and prospectors
bought their supplies, he heard a lot of talk about mines, and was
too new to it to understand that the man who has the most time to
stop and talk about it has the least to do with mining.  And of all
he heard, the most fascinating to Mr. Wills, who was troubled with
an imagination, was of the lost mines, incredibly rich ledges,
touched, and not found again.  To go out into the unmapped hills on
the mere chance of coming across something was, on the face of it,
a risky business; but to look for a mine once located, sampled, and
proved, definitely situated in a particular mountain range or a
certain canon, had a smack of plausibility.  Besides that, an
ordinary prospect might or might not prove workable, but the lost
mines were always amazingly rich.
</p><p>Of all the ways in the West in which a man may go to pieces
this is the most insidious.  Out there beyond the towns the long
wilderness lies brooding, imperturbable; she puts out to
adventurous minds glittering fragments of fortune or romance, like
the lures men use to catch antelopes.  <hi rend="italic"> Clip!</hi> then she has them.
If Mr. Wills had gambled or drank, his wife could have gone to the
minister about it, his friends could have done something.  There
was a church in Maverick of twenty-seven members, and the Willses
had brought letters to it; but except for the effect it had on Mrs.
Wills it would not be worth mentioning.  Though he might never have
found it out in the East, Mr. Wills belonged to the church not
because of what it meant to him, but for what it meant to other
people.  Back East it had meant social standing, repute, moral
impeccability.  To other people in Maverick it meant a weakness
which was excused in you so long as you did not talk about it.  Mr.
Wills did not because <pb n="245"/>  there was so much else to talk about
in connection with lost mines.
</p><p>He began by grub-staking Pedro Ruiz to look for the lost ledge
of Fisherman's Peak, and that was not so bad, for it had not been
lost more than thirty years, the peak was not a hundred miles from
Maverick, and, besides, I have a piece of the ore myself.  Then he
was bitten by the myth of the "Gunsight," of which there was never
any thing more tangible than a dime's worth of virgin silver,
picked up by a Jayhawker, hammered into a sight for a gun; and you
had to take the gun on faith at that, for it and the man who owned
it had quite disappeared.  Afterward it was the Duke o' Wild Rose,
which was never a mine at all, but merely an arrow-mark on a map
left by a penniless lodger, found dead in a San Francisco hotel.
Grub-staking is expensive even to a clerk at the Bed Rock Emporium,
getting discounts on the grub, and grub-staked prospectors are
about as dependable as the dreams they chase, often pure fakes,
lying up at seldom visited waterholes while the stake lasts, and
returning with wilder tales and more alluring clues.
</p><p>It was a late conviction that led Mr. Wills, when he put the
last remnant of his means into the search for the White Cement
Mines, to resign his clerkship and go in charge of the expedition
himself.  There is no doubt whatever that there is a deposit of
cement on Bald Mountain, with lumps of gold sticking out of it like
plums in a pudding.  It lies at the bottom of a small gulch near
the middle fork of Owens's River, and is overlaid by pumice.  There
is a camp-kit buried somewhere near, and two skeletons.  There was
also an Indian in that vicinity who was thought to be able to point
out the exact location, if he would.  It was quite the sort of
thing to appeal to the imagination of Mr. Wills, and he spent two
years proving that he could not find it.  After that he drifted out
toward the Lee district to look for Lost Cabin mine, because a man
who had immediate need of twenty dollars had, for that amount,
offered Wills some exact and unpublished information as to its
location.  By that time Wills's movements had ceased to interest
anybody in Maverick.  He could be got to believe anything about any
sort of a prospect, provided it was lost.
</p><p>The only visible mark left by all this was on Mrs. Wills.
Everybody in a mining town except the minister and professional
gamblers, who wear frock-coats, dresses pretty much alike, and
Wills very soon got to wear on his face the guileless, trustful
fixity of the confirmed prospector.  It seemed as if the desert had
overshot him and struck at Mrs. Wills, and Richard Wills, Esther
Wills, Benjy Wills, and the youngest Wills, who was called Mugsey.
Desertness attacked the door-yard and the house; even the cabinet
organ had a weathered look.  During the time of the White Cement
obsession the Wills family looked to be in need of a grub-stake
themselves.  Mrs. Wills's eyes were like the eyes of trail-weary
cattle.  Her hands grew to have that pitiful way of catching the
front of her dress of the woman not so much a slattern as hopeless.

It was when her husband went out after Lost Cabin, that she fell
into the habit of sitting down to a cheap novel, with the dishes
unwashed, a sort of drugging of despair common among women of the
camps.
</p><p>All this time Mr. Wills was drifting about from camp to camp
of the desert borders, working when it could not be avoided, but
mostly on long, fruitless trudges among the unmindful ranges.  I do
not know if the man was honest with himself, or if he knew by this
time that the clue of a lost mine was the baldest of excuses merely
to be out and away from everything that savored of definiteness and
responsibility.  The fact was, the desert had got him.  All the
hoops were off the cask.  The mind of Mr. Wills faded out at the
edges like the desert horizon, which melts in mists and mirages,
and finally he went on an expedition from which he did not come
back.
</p><p>He had been gone nearly a year when Mrs. Wills gave up
expecting him.  She had grown so used to the bedraggled crawl of
life that she might never have taken any notice of the
disappearance of Mr. Wills had not the Emporium refused to make any
more charges in his name.  There had been a great many dry
waterholes on the desert that year and more than the usual
complement of sun-dried corpses.  In a general way this accounted
<pb n="246"/>  for Mr. Wills, though there was nothing of sufficient
definiteness to justify Mrs. Wills in putting on a widow's dress,
and, anyway, she could not have afforded it.
</p><p>Mrs. Wills and the children went to work, and work was about
the only thing in Maverick of which there was more than enough.  It
was a matter of a very few months when Mrs. Wills made the
remarkable discovery that after the family bills were paid at the
end of the month there was a little over&mdash;a very little.  Mrs.
Wills had lived so long with the tradition that a husband is a
natural provider that it took some months longer to realize that
she not only did not need Mr. Wills, but got on better without him.

This was about the time she was able to have the sitting-room
repapered and to put up lace curtains.  And the next spring the
children planted roses in the front yard.  All up and down the wash
of Salt Creek there were lean coyote mothers and wild folk of every
sort that could have taught her that nature never makes the mistake
of neglecting to make the child-bearer competent to provide.  But
Mrs. Wills had not been studying life in the lairs.  She had most
of her notions of it from the church and her parents, and, under
the new sense of independence and power, she had an ache of
forlornness and neglect.  As a matter of fact, she filled out, grew
stronger, had a spring in her walk.  She was not pining for Mr.
Wills; the desert had him, though for whatever conceivable use, it
was more than Mrs. Wills could put him to.  Let the desert keep
what it had got.
</p><p>It was in the third summer that she regained a certain air
that made one think she must have been pretty when Mr. Wills
married her.  And no woman in a mining town can so much as hint at
prettiness without its being found out.  Mrs. Wills had a good many
prejudices left over from the time when Mr. Wills had been
assistant superintendent of the Sunday school, and would not hear
of divorce.  Yet, as the slovenliness of despair fell away from
her, as she held up her head and began to have company to tea, it
is certain somebody would have broached it to her before the summer
was over; but by that time Mr. Wills came back.
</p><p>It happened that Benjy Wills, who was fourteen and driving the
Bed Rock delivery-wagon, had a runaway accident in which he had
behaved very handsomely and got a fractured skull.  News of it went
by way of the local paper to Tonopah and from there drifted south
to the Funeral Mountains and the particular prospect that Mr. Wills
was working on a grub-stake.  He had come to that.  Perhaps as much
because he had found there was nothing in it as from paternal
anxiety, he came home the evening of the day the doctor had
declared the boy out of danger.
</p><p>It was my turn to sit up that night, I remember, and Mrs.
Meyer, who had the turn before, was telling me about the medicines.

A neighbor woman, who had come in by the back door with a bowl of
custard, and the doctor, standing in the sitting-room with Mrs.
Wills, were present, when Mr. Wills came in through the black block
of the doorway with his hand before his face to ward off the light--and perhaps some shamefacedness: who knows?
</p><p>I saw Mrs. Wills quiver, and her hand went up to her bosom as
if some one had struck her.  I have seen horses start and check
like that as they came over the pass and the hot blast of the
desert took them fairly.  It was the stroke of desolation.  I
remember turning quickly, at the doctor's curt signal, to shut the
door between the sitting-room and Benjy.
</p><p>"Don't let the boy see you to-night, Wills," said the doctor,
with no hint of a greeting; "he's not to be excited."  With that he
got himself off as quickly as possible, and the neighbor woman and
I went out and sat on the back steps a long time, and tried to talk
about everything but Mr. Wills.  When I went in at last he was
sitting in the Morris chair, which had come with soap wrappers,
explaining to Mrs. Meyer about the rich prospect he had left to
come to his darling boy.  But he did not get so much as a glimpse
of his darling boy while I was in charge.
</p><p>Mr. Wills settled on his family like a blight.  For a man who
has prospected lost mines to so great an extent is positively not
good for anything else.  It was not only as though the desert had
sucked the life out of him and cast him back, but as though it
would have Mrs. Wills in his room.  As the weeks went on, one
<pb n="247"/>  could see a sort of dinginess creeping up from her dress to
her hair and her face, and it spread to the house and the doorway.
Mr. Wills had enjoyed the improved condition of his home, though he
missed the point of it; his wife's cooking tasted good to him after
miner's fare, and he was proud of his boys.  He didn't want any
more of the desert, not he.  "There's no place like home," said Mr.
Wills, or something to that effect.
</p><p>But he had brought the desert with him on his back.  If it had
been at any other time than when her mind was torn with anxiety for
Benjy, Mrs. Wills might have made a fight against it.  But the only
practical way to separate the family from the blight was to divorce
Mr. Wills, and the church to which Mrs. Wills belonged admitted
divorce only in the event of there being another woman.
</p><p>Mrs. Wills rose to the pitch of threatening, I believe, about
the time Mr. Wills insisted on his right to control the earnings of
his sons.  But the minister called; the church put out its hand
upon her poor staggered soul, which sunk back.  The minister
himself was newly from the East, and did not understand that the
desert is to be dealt with as a woman and a wanton.  He was
thinking of it as a place on the map.  Therefore he was not of the
slightest use to Mrs. Wills, which did not prevent him from
commanding her behavior.  And the power of the Wilderness lay like
a wasting sickness on the home.
</p><p>About that time Mrs. Wills took to novel-reading again; the
eldest son drifted off up Tonopah way, and Benjy began to keep back
a part of the wages he brought home.  Mr. Wills is beginning to
collect misinformation about the exact locality where Peg-leg Smith
is supposed to have found the sunburned nuggets.  He does not
mention the matter often, being, as he says, done with mines, but
whenever Peg-leg comes up in talk, I can see Mrs. Wills chirk up a
little, her gaze wandering to the inscrutable grim spaces, not with
the hate you might suppose, but with something like hope in her
eye&mdash;as if she had guessed what I am certain of, that in time its
insatiable spirit will reach out and take Mr. Wills again.
</p><p>And this time, if I know Mrs. Wills, he will not come back.
</p></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
