<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="BakNegr"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="BakNegr">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Negro Suffrage in a Democracy</title>
<title type="sort">negro suffrage in a democracy</title>
<author>Baker, Ray Stannard</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">29</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">BakNegr</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475726</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Negro Suffrage in a Democracy</title>
<title type="sort">negro suffrage in a democracy</title>
<author>Ray Stannard Baker</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1910">1910</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 106</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 612-619</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1910">1910</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction; prose</term>
<term>African American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-08">August 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>minimal TEI tagging</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="article" id="d3">
<head>Baker, Ray Stannard.  "Negro Suffrage in a Democracy."
<hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 106 (1910): 612-619.</head>
<pb n="612"/>

<p>IN this paper I endeavor to lay down the fundamental
principles which should govern the Negro franchise in a democracy,
and to outline a practical programme for the immediate treatment of
the problem.
</p><p>As I see it, the question of Negro suffrage in the United
States presents two distinct aspects: &mdash;
</p><p><hi rend="italic">First:</hi> the legal aspect.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Second:</hi> the practical aspect.
</p><p>It will be admitted, I think, without argument, that all
governments do and of a necessity must exercise the right to limit
the number of people who are permitted to take part in the weighty
responsibilities of the suffrage.  Some governments allow only a
few men to vote; in an absolute monarchy there is only one voter;
other governments, as they become more democratic, permit a larger
proportion of the people to vote.
</p><p>Our own government is one of the freest in the world in the
matter of suffrage; and yet we bar out, in most states, all women;
we bar out Mongolians, no matter how intelligent; we bar out
Indians, and all foreigners who have not passed through a certain
probationary stage and have not acquired a certain small amount of
education.  We also declare &mdash; for an arbitrary limit must be placed
somewhere &mdash; that no person under twenty-one years of age may
exercise the right to vote, although some boys of eighteen are to-day better equipped to pass intelligently upon public questions
than many grown men.  We even place adult white men on probation
until they have resided for a certain length of time, often as
<pb n="613"/>
much as two years, in the state or the town where they wish to
cast their ballots.  Our registration and ballot laws eliminate
hundreds of thousands of voters; and finally, we bar out everywhere
the defective and criminal classes of our population.  We do not
realize, sometimes, I think, how limited the franchise really is,
even in America.  We forget that out of nearly ninety million
people in the United States, fewer than fifteen million cast their
votes for President in 1908 &mdash; or about one in every six.
</p><p>Thus the practice of a restricted suffrage is very deeply
implanted in our system of government.  It is everywhere recognized
that even in a democracy lines must be drawn, and that the ballot,
the precious instrument of government, must be hedged about with
stringent regulations.  The question is, where shall these lines be
drawn in order that the best interests, not of any particular
class, but of the whole nation, shall be served.
</p><p>Upon this question, we, as free citizens, have the absolute
right to agree or disagree with the present laws regulating
suffrage; and if we want more people brought in as partakers in
government, or some people who are already in, barred out, we have
a right to organize, to agitate, to do our best to change the laws.
Powerful organizations of women are now agitating for the right to
vote; there is an organization which demands the suffrage for
Chinese and Japanese who wish to become citizens.  It is even
conceivable that a society might be founded to lower the suffrage
age-limit from twenty-one to nineteen years, thereby endowing a
large number of young men with the privileges, and therefore the
educational responsibilities, of political power.  On the other
hand, a large number of people, chiefly in our Southern States,
earnestly believe that the right of the Negro to vote should be
curtailed, or even abolished.
</p><p>Thus we disagree, and government is the resultant of all these
diverse views and forces.  No one can say dogmatically how far
democracy should go in distributing the enormously important powers
of active government.  Democracy is not a dogma; it is not even a
dogma of free suffrage.  Democracy is a life, a spirit, a growth.
The primal necessity of any sort of government, democracy or
otherwise, whether it be more unjust or less unjust toward special
groups of its citizens, is to exist, to be a going concern, to
maintain upon the whole a stable and peaceful administration of
affairs.  If a democracy cannot provide such stability, then the
people go back to some form of oligarchy.  Having secured a fair
measure of stability, a democracy proceeds with caution toward the
extension of the suffrage to more and more people &mdash; trying
foreigners, trying women, trying Negroes.
</p><p>And no one can prophesy how far a democracy will ultimately go
in the matter of suffrage.  We know only the tendency.  We know
that in the beginning, even in America, the right to vote was a
very limited matter.  In the early years, in New England, only
church-members voted; then the franchise was extended to include
property-owners; then it was enlarged to include all white adults;
then to include Negroes; then, in several Western States, to
include women.
</p><p>Thus the line has been constantly advancing, but with many
fluctuations, eddies, and back-currents &mdash; like any other stream of
progress.  At the present time the fundamental principles which
underlie popular government, and especially the whole matter of
popular suffrage, are much in the public mind.  The tendency of
government throughout the entire civilized
<pb n="614"/>
world is
strongly in the direction of placing more and more power in the
hands of the people.  In our own country we are enacting a
remarkable group of laws providing for direct primaries in the
nomination of public officials, for direct election of United
States Senators, and for direct legislation by means of the
initiative and referendum; and we are even going to the point, in
many cities, of permitting the people to recall an elected official
who is unsatisfactory.  The principle of local option, which is
nothing but that of direct government by the people, is being
everywhere accepted.  All these changes affect, fundamentally, the
historic structure of our government, making it less republican and
more democratic.
</p><p>Still more important and far-reaching in its significance is
the tendency of our government, especially our Federal Government,
to regulate or to appropriate great groups of business enterprises
formerly left wholly in private hands.  More and more, private
business is becoming public business.
</p><p>Now, then, as the weight of responsibility upon the popular
vote is increased, it becomes more and more important that the
ballot should be jealously guarded and honestly exercised.  In the
last few years, therefore, a series of extraordinary new
precautions have been adopted: the Australian ballot, more
stringent registration systems, the stricter enforcement of
naturalization laws to prevent the voting of crowds of unprepared
foreigners, and the imposition by several states, rightly or
wrongly, of educational and property tests.  It becomes a more and
more serious matter every year to be an American citizen, more of
an honor, more of a duty.
</p><p>At the close of the Civil War, in a time of intense idealistic
emotion, some three-quarters of a million of Negroes, the mass of
them densely ignorant and just out of slavery, with the iron of
slavery still in their souls, were suddenly given the political
rights of free citizens.  A great many people, and not in the South
alone, thought then, and still think, that it was a mistake to
bestow the high powers and privileges of a wholly unrestricted
ballot &mdash; a ballot which is the symbol of intelligent self-government &mdash; upon the Negro.  Other people, of whom I am one,
believe that it was a necessary concomitant of the revolution; it
was itself a revolution, not a growth, and like every other
revolution it has had its fearful reaction.  Revolutions, indeed,
change names, but they do not at once change human relationships.
Mankind is reconstructed not by proclamations, or legislation, or
military occupation, but by time, growth, education, religion,
thought.  At that time, then, the nation drove down the stakes of
its idealism in government far beyond the point it was able to
reach in the humdrum activities of everyday existence.  A reaction
was inevitable; it was inevitable and perfectly natural that there
should be a widespread questioning as to whether all Negroes, or
indeed any Negroes, should properly be admitted to full political
fellowship.  That questioning continues to this day.
</p><p>Now, the essential principle established by the Fifteenth
Amendment to the Constitution was not that all Negroes should
necessarily be given an unrestricted access to the ballot; but that
the right to vote should not be denied or abridged 'on account of
race, color, or previous condition of servitude.'  This amendment
wiped out the color-line in politics so far as any written law
could possibly do it.
</p><p>Let me here express my profound conviction that the principle
of political equality then laid down is a sound, valid, and
absolutely essential principle
<pb n="615"/>
in any free government; that
restrictions upon the ballot, when necessary, should be made to
apply equally to white and colored citizens; and that the Fifteenth
Amendment ought not to be, and cannot be repealed.  Moreover, I am
convinced that the principle of political equality is more firmly
established to-day in this country than it was forty years ago,
when it had only Northern bayonets behind it.  For now, however
short the practice falls of reaching the legal standard, the
principle is woven into the warp and woof of Southern life and
Southern legislation.  Many Southern white leaders of thought are
to-day <hi rend="italic">convinced</hi>, not <hi rend="italic">forced</hi> believers in the principle;
and that is a great omen.
</p><p>Limitations have come about, it is true, and were to be
expected as the back-currents of the revolution.  Laws providing
for educational and property qualifications as a prerequisite to
the exercise of the suffrage have been passed in all the Southern
States, and have operated to exclude from the ballot large numbers
of both white and colored citizens, who on account of ignorance or
poverty are unable to meet the tests.  These provisions, whatever
the opinion entertained as to the wisdom of such laws, are well
within the principle laid down by the Fifteenth Amendment.  But
several Southern States have gone a step further, and by means of
the so-called 'grandfather laws,' have exempted certain ignorant
white men from the necessity of meeting the educational and
property tests.  These unfair 'grandfather laws,' however, in some
of the states adopting them, have now expired by limitation.
</p><p>Let me then lay down this general proposition: &mdash;
</p><p>Nowhere in the South to-day is the Negro cut off <hi rend="italic">legally</hi>,
as a Negro, from the ballot.  Legally, to-day, any Negro who can
meet the comparatively slight requirements as to education, or
property, or both, can cast his ballot on a basis of equality with
the white man.  I have emphasized the word legally, for I know the
<hi rend="italic">practical</hi> difficulties which confront the Negro votes in many
parts of the South.  The point I wish to make is that legally the
Negro is essentially the political equal of the white man; but that
practically, in the enforcement of the law, the legislative ideal
is still pegged out far beyond the actual performance.
</p><p>Now, then, if we are interested in the problem of democracy,
we have two courses open to us.  We may think the laws are unjust
to the Negro, and incidentally to the 'poor white' man as well.  If
we do, we have a perfect right to agitate for changes; and we can
do much to disclose, without heat, the actual facts regarding the
complicated and vexatious legislative situation in the South, as
regards the suffrage.  Every change in the legislation upon this
subject should, indeed, be jealously watched, that the principle of
political equality between the races be not legally curtailed.  The
doctrine laid down in the Fifteenth Amendment must, at any hazard,
be maintained.
</p><p>But, personally, &mdash; and I am here voicing a profound
conviction, &mdash; I think our emphasis at present should be laid upon
the practical rather than upon the legal aspect of the problem; I
think we should take advantage of the widely prevalent feeling in
the South that the question of suffrage has been settled, legally,
for some time to come: of the desire on the part of many Southern
people, both white and colored, to turn aside from the discussion
of the political status of the Negro.
</p><p>In short, let us for the time being accept the laws as they
are, and build upward from that point.  Let us turn our attention
to the practical task of finding out why it is that the laws we
<pb n="616"/>
already have are not enforced, and how best to secure an
honest vote for every Negro and equally for every 'poor white' man,
who is able to meet the requirements, but who for one reason or
another does not or cannot now exercise his rights.  I include the
disfranchised white man as well as the Negro, because I take it
that we are interested, first of all, in democracy, and unless we
can arouse the spirit of democracy, South and North, we can hope
for justice neither for Negroes, nor for the poorer class of white
men, nor for the women of the factories and shops, nor for the
children of the cottonmills.
</p><p>Taking up this side of the problem we shall discover two
entirely distinct difficulties: &mdash;
</p><p>First, we shall find many Negroes, and indeed hundreds of
thousands of white men as well, who might vote, but who, through
ignorance, or inability or unwillingness to pay the poll-taxes, or
from mere lack of interest, disfranchise themselves.
</p><p>The second difficulty is peculiar to the Negro.  It consists
in open or concealed intimidation on the part of the white men who
control the election machinery.  In many places in the South to-day
no Negro, how well qualified, would dare to present himself for
registration; when he does, he is rejected for some trivial or
illegal reason.
</p><p>Thus we have to meet a vast amount of apathy and ignorance and
poverty on the one hand, and the threat of intimidation on the
other.
</p><p>First of all, for it is the chief injustice as between white
and colored men with which we have to deal, &mdash; an injustice which the
law already makes illegal and punishable, &mdash; how shall we meet the
matter of intimidation?  As I have already said, the door of the
suffrage is everywhere legally open to the Negro, but a certain
sort of Southerner bars the passage-way.  He stands there and, law
or no law, keeps out many Negroes who might vote; and he represents
in most parts of the South the prevailing public opinion.
</p><p>Shall we meet this situation by force?  What force is
available?  Shall the North go down and fight the South?  You and
I know that the North to-day has no feeling but friendship for the
South.  More than that &mdash; and I say it with all seriousness, because
it represents what I have heard wherever I have gone in the North
to make inquiries regarding the Negro problem &mdash; the North, wrongly
or rightly, is to-day more than half convinced that the South is
right in imposing some measure of limitation upon the franchise.
There is now, in short, no disposition anywhere in the North to
interfere in internal affairs in the South &mdash; not even with the force
of public opinion.
</p><p>What other force, then, is to be invoked?  Shall the Negro
revolt?  Shall he migrate?  Shall he prosecute his case in the
courts?  The very asking of these questions suggests the inevitable
reply.
</p><p>We might as well, here and now, dismiss the idea of force,
express or implied.  There are times of last resort which call for
force; but this is not such a time.
</p><p>What other alternatives are there?
</p><p>Accepting the laws as they are, then, there are two methods of
procedure, neither sensational nor exciting.  I have no quick cure
to suggest, but only old and tried methods of commonplace growth.
</p><p>The underlying causes of the trouble in the country being
plainly ignorance and prejudice, we must meet ignorance and
prejudice with their antidotes, education and association.
</p><p>Every effort should be made to extend free education among
both Negroes
<pb n="617"/>
and white people.  A great extension of
education is now going forward in the South.  The Negro is not by
any means getting his full share; but, as certainly as sunshine
makes things grow, education in the South will produce tolerance.
That there is already such a growing tolerance no one who has
talked with the leading white men in the South can doubt.  The old
fire-eating, Negro-baiting leaders of the Tillman-Vardaman type are
swiftly passing away: a far better and broader group is coming into
power.
</p><p>In his last book, Mr. Edgar Gardner Murphy, of Alabama,
expresses this new point of view when he says, &mdash;
</p><p>'There is no question here as to the unrestricted admission
[to the ballot] of the great masses of our ignorant and semi-ignorant blacks.  I know no advocate of such admission.  But the
question is as to whether the individuals of the race, upon
conditions or restrictions legally imposed and fairly administered,
shall be admitted to adequate and increasing representation in the
electorate.  And as that question is more seriously and more
generally considered, many of the leading publicists of the South,
I am glad to say, are quietly resolved that the answer shall be in
the affirmative.'
</p><p>From an able Southern white man, a resident of New Orleans, I
received recently a letter containing these words: &mdash;
</p><p>'I believe we have reached the bottom, and a sort of quiescent
period.  I think it most likely that from now on there will be a
gradual increase of the Negro vote.  And I honestly believe that
the less said about it, the surer the increase will be.'
</p><p>Education &mdash; and by education I mean education of all sorts,
industrial, professional, classical, in accordance with each man's
talents &mdash; will not only produce breadth and tolerance, but will help
to cure the apathy which now keeps so many thousands of both white
men and Negroes from the polls: for it will show them that it is
necessary for every man to exercise all the political rights within
his reach.  If he fails voluntarily to take advantage of the rights
he already has, how shall he acquire more rights?
</p><p>And as ignorance must be met by education, so prejudice must
be met with its antidote, which is association.  Democracy does not
consist in mere voting, but in association, the spirit of common
effort, of which the ballot is a mere visible expression.  When we
come to know one another we soon find that the points of likeness
are much more numerous than the points of difference.  And this
human association for the common good, which is democracy, is
difficult to bring about anywhere, whether among different classes
of white people, or between white people and Negroes.  As one of
the leaders of the Negro race, Dr. Du Bois, has said, &mdash;
</p><p>'Herein lies the tragedy of the age.  Not that men are poor:
all men know something of poverty.  Not that men are wicked: who is
good?  Not that men are ignorant: what is truth?  Nay, but that men
know so little of each other.'
</p><p>After the Atlanta riot I attended a number of conferences
between leading white men and leading colored men.  It is true
those meetings bore evidence of awkwardness and embarrassment, for
they were among the first of the sort to take place in the South,
but they were none the less valuable.  A white man told me after
one of the meetings, &mdash;
</p><p>'I did not know that there were any such sensible Negroes in
the South.'
</p><p>And a Negro told me that it was the first time in his life
that he had ever heard a Southern white man reason in
<pb n="618"/>
a
friendly way with a Negro concerning their common difficulties.
</p><p>More and more these associations of white and colored men, at
certain points of contact, must and will come about.  Already, in
connection with various educational and business projects in the
South, white and colored men meet on common grounds, and the way
has been opened to a wider mutual understanding.  And it is common
enough now, where it was unheard of a few years ago, for both white
men and Negroes to speak from the same platform in the South.  I
have attended a number of such meetings.  Thus slowly &mdash; awkwardly,
at first, for two centuries of prejudice are not immediately
overcome &mdash; the white man and Negro will come to know one another,
not merely as master and servant, but as co-workers.  These things
cannot be forced.
</p><p>One reason why the white man and the Negro have not got
together more rapidly in the South than they have, is because they
have tried always to meet at the sorest points.  When sensible
people, who must live together whether or no, find that there are
points at which they cannot agree, it is the part of wisdom to
avoid these points, and to meet upon other and common interests.
Upon no other terms, indeed, can a democracy exist, for in no
imaginable future state will individuals cease to disagree with one
another upon something less than half of all the problems of life.
</p><p>'Here we all live together in a great country,' say the
apostles of this view; 'let us all get together and develop it.
Let the Negro do his best to educate himself, to own his own land,
and to buy and sell with the white people in the fairest possible
way.'
</p><p>It is wonderful, indeed, how close together men who are
stooping to a common task soon come.
</p><p>Now, buying and selling, land ownership and common material
pursuits, may not be the highest points of contact between man and
man, but they are real points, and help to give men an idea of the
worth of their fellows, white or black.  How many times, in the
South, I heard white men speak in high admiration of some Negro
farmer who had been successful, or of some Negro blacksmith who was
a worthy citizen, or of some Negro doctor who was a leader of his
race.
</p><p>It is curious, once a man (any man, white or black) learns to
do his job well, how he finds himself in a democratic relationship
with other men.  I remember asking a prominent white citizen of a
town in Central Georgia if he knew anything about Tuskegee.  He
said, &mdash;
</p><p>'Yes: I had rather a curious experience last fall.  I was
building a hotel and couldn't get any one to do the plastering as
I wanted it done.  One day I saw two Negro plasterers at work in a
new house that a friend of mine was building.  I watched them for
an hour.  They seemed to know their trade.  I invited them to come
over and see me.  They came, took the contract for my work, hired
a white man to carry mortar at a dollar a day, and when they got
through it was the best job of plastering in town.  I found that
they had learned their trade at Tuskegee.  They averaged four
dollars a day each in wages.  We tried to get them to locate in our
town, but they went back to school.'
</p><p>When I was in Mississippi a prominent banker showed me his
business letter-heads.
</p><p>'Good job, isn't it?' he said.  'A Negro printer did it.  He
wrote to me asking if he might bid on my work.  I replied that
although I had known him a long time I couldn't give him the job
merely because he was a Negro.

<pb n="619"/>
He told me to forget his
color, and said that if he couldn't do as good a job and do it as
reasonably as any white man could, he didn't want it.  I let him
try, and now he does most of our printing.'
</p><p>Out of such points of contact, then, encouraged by such wise
leaders as Booker T. Washington, will grow an ever finer and finer
spirit of association and of common and friendly knowledge.  And
that will inevitably lead to an extension upon the soundest
possible basis of the Negro franchise.  I know cases where white
men have urged intelligent Negroes to come and cast their ballots,
and have stood sponsor for them, out of genuine respect.  As a
result, to-day, the Negroes who vote in the South are, as a class,
men of substance and intelligence, fully equal to the tasks of
citizenship.
</p><p>Thus, I have boundless confidence not only in the sense of the
white men of the South, but in the innate capability of the Negro,
and that once these two come really to know each other, not at sore
points of contact, but as common workers for a common country, the
question of suffrage will gradually solve itself along the lines of
true democracy.
</p><p>Another influence also will tend to change the status of the
Negro as a voter.  That is the pending break-up of the political
solidarity of the South.  All the signs point to a political
realignment upon new issues in this country, both South and North.
Old party names may even pass away.  And that break-up, with the
attendant struggle for votes, is certain to bring into politics
thousands of Negroes and white men now disfranchised.  The result
of a real division on live issues has been shown in many local
contests in the South, as in the fight against the saloons, when
every qualified Negro voter, and every Negro who could qualify, was
eagerly pushed forward by one side or the other.  With such a
division on new issues the Negro will tend to exercise more and
more political power, dividing, not on the color line, but on the
principles at stake.
</p><p>Thus in spite of the difficulties which now confront the
Negro, I cannot but look upon the situation in a spirit of
optimism.  I think sometimes we are tempted to set a higher value
upon the ritual of a belief than upon the spirit which underlies
it.  The ballot is not democracy: it is merely the symbol or ritual
of democracy, and it may be full of passionate social, yes, even
religious significance, or it may be a mere empty and dangerous
formalism.  What we should look to, then, primarily, is not the
shadow, but the substance of democracy in this country.  Nor must
we look for results too swiftly; our progress toward democracy is
slow of growth and needs to be cultivated with patience and watered
with faith.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
