<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="BarStep"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;

]>


<TEI.2 id="BarStep">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A note on Stephen Crane</title>
<title type="sort">note on stephen crane</title>
<author>Crane review: Barry, John D.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">8</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">BarStep</idno>
<date value="1996-05">May, 1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475729</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Some British spellings such as "humour," "organisation,"
"characterised," and "favourably."</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Note on Stephen Crane</title>
<title level="j">The Bookman: An Illustrated Journal of Literature and
Life</title>
<title type="sort">note on stephen crane</title>
<author>Crane review: John D. Barry</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Dodd Mead &amp; Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1901-04">April, 1901</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Vol 13 (April 1901): 148</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using
WordPerfect spell checker.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1901-04">April, 1901</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-05">May, 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Bryson Clevenger, Jr.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Minimal TEI tagging, Spellchecking, and adding header.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="article" id="d3">

<head>
Barry, John D.  "A Note on Stephen Crane.<hi rend="italic">"Bookman</hi> 13
     (April 1901): 148.</head>

<pb n="148" id="BarStep148"/>

<p>   Not long ago, the New York <hi rend="italic">Evening Post</hi>, in an editorial
discussing "The Decay of Decadence," grouped the late Stephen
Crane, as a poet, with the Symbolists of France and England.  I was
struck by the association, for the reason that I happened to be
familiar with the peculiar circumstances under which <hi rend="italic">The Black
Riders and Other Lines</hi>, from which a quotation is made in the
editorial, had come to be written.  As a matter of fact, at the
time of writing that volume it is probable that Mr. Crane had never
even heard of the Symbolists; if he had heard of them, it is pretty
certain that he had never read them.  He was then about twenty-one
years of age, and he was woefully ignorant of books.  Indeed, he
deliberately avoided reading from a fear of being influenced by
other writers.  He had already published <hi rend="italic">Maggie</hi>, his first
novel, and by sending it to Mr. Hamlin Garland he had made an
enthusiastic friend.  Through Mr. Garland he met several other
writers, among them Mr. W. D. Howells.  One evening while receiving
a visit from Mr. Crane, Mr. Howells took from his shelves a volume
of Emily Dickinson's verses and read some of these aloud.  Mr.
Crane was deeply impressed, and a short time afterward he showed me
thirty poems in manuscript, written, as he explained, in three
days.  These furnished the bulk of the volume entitled <hi rend="italic">The Black
Riders</hi>.  It was plain enough to me that they had been directly
inspired by Miss Dickinson, who, so far as I am aware, has never
been classed with the Symbolists.  And yet, among all the critics
who have discussed the book, no one, to my knowledge, at any rate,
has called attention to the resemblance between the two American
writers.  It is curious that this boy, feeling his way toward
expression as he was then doing, should have been stimulated by so
simple and so sincere a writer as Miss Dickinson into unconscious
cooperation with the decadent writers of Europe.  Perhaps an
explanation may be suggested by the association of Mr. Crane at
this period with a group of young American painters, who had
brought from France the impressionistic influences, which with him
took literary form.
</p><p>   <hi rend="italic">The Black Riders</hi> received comparatively little attention,
though it was favourably noticed in THE BOOKMAN and in other
periodicals, and it was ridiculed in several.  Its publishers
apparently made no effort to take advantage of the success achieved
by Mr. Crane a few months later with <hi rend="italic">The Red Badge of Courage</hi>.
Few readers are now aware of its existence.  Whatever may be
thought of its qualities as verse, no one can dispute its being a
curiosity of literature.
</p><p>   While writing of Mr. Crane, it may not be amiss to give ** or
two of his life which I have not seen in print.  His bent toward
the writer's career probably came from his mother, who, he once
told me, had been a newspaper writer.  It was his mother who
secured for him his first chance to write regularly for money as a
New Jersey correspondent for the New York <hi rend="italic">Tribune</hi>.  I think he
said that she had held the post herself.  I have a distinct
recollection of Crane's remarking, with a humour made grim by his
poverty at the time, that he had been discharged from the position
of correspondent because he had given offence to some organisation
of workingmen by writing satirically of one of their parades.  For
the <hi rend="italic">Tribune</hi> he wrote some sketches which had all the qualities
of observation, humour, and grotesque originality of expression
that characterised much of his later work.  At the time of his
death he was acquiring from the world the education he had missed
in his brief experience at college.  Among other things, he was
learning new words, fine words, the words that most writers know
and never use.  He snatched at them as a child snatches at bits of
flashing jewelry, and he stuck them into his stories with a
splendid disregard of their fitness.  <hi rend="italic">Whilomville Stories</hi>, one
of his latest books, instead of being written in the simple
language suitable to the child-life described, is full of such
words; they fairly stick out of the page.  If Mr. Crane had lived
a few years longer, he would undoubtedly have stored those words in
his memory, kept them shut up there, and returned to plain speech.
</p>                                 <signed><hi rend="italic">John D. Barry.</hi></signed>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

