<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="BeeEssa"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % UVAsupp SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/uva-supp.ent"> %UVAsupp;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>
<TEI.2 id="BeeEssa">
	<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">An essay on slavery and abolitionism, with reference to the duty of
					American females. By Catharine E. Beecher</title>
<title type="sort">essay on slavery and abolitionism, with reference to the duty of american females by catharine e beecher</title>
<author>Beecher, Catharine E.</author>
<respStmt>
					<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
					<name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name>
					<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
					<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
			<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">181</num> kilobytes</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
				<idno type="ETC">BeeEssa</idno>
				<date value="1998">1998</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1998 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475730</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">An essay on slavery and abolitionism, with reference to the duty of
							American females. By Catharine E. Beecher</title>
<title type="sort">essay on slavery and abolitionism, with reference to the duty of american females by catharine e beecher</title>
<author>Beecher, Catharine E.</author>
</titleStmt>
					<editionStmt>
<p>2nd ed.</p>
</editionStmt>
					<extent>151 p. 15 cm.</extent>
					<publicationStmt>
<publisher>H. Perkins; Perkins &amp; Marvin</publisher>
						<pubPlace>Philadelphia ; Boston</pubPlace>
						<date value="1837">1837</date>
						<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted:</idno>
</publicationStmt>
					</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
					word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
				<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to
					aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
			</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1837">1837</date>
</creation>
			<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
			<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
					<term>prose</term>
					<term>feminine</term>
					<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
				</textClass>
</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1998">1998</date>
				<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
					<name>Stephen Ramsay</name>
</respStmt>
				<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
			<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
				<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
					<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
				<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
	<text id="d1">
		<front id="d2">


			<titlePage id="d3">
				<pb/>
				<docTitle>
					<titlePart type="main"> AN ESSAY ON SLAVERY AND ABOLITIONISM, </titlePart>
					<pb/>
					<titlePart type="sub"> WITH REFERENCE TO THE DUTY OF AMERICAN FEMALES.
					</titlePart>
				</docTitle>
				<byline> BY <docAuthor>CATHARINE E. BEECHER.</docAuthor>
				</byline>
				<docImprint>
					<pubPlace>Philadelphia;</pubPlace>
					<publisher>HENRY PERKINS, 134 CHESTNUT STREET. PERKINS &amp; MARVIN, BOSTON.</publisher>
					<docDate>1837.</docDate> Entered according to the Act of Congress, in the year
					1837, by <hi rend="italic">Henry Perkins,</hi> in the Clerk's Office of the
					District Court of the Eastern District of Pennsylvania. 1. ASHMEAD AND CO.
					PRINTERS. </docImprint>
			</titlePage>

			<div1 type="preface" id="d4">
			<pb n="003"/>
				<head>PREFACE.</head>
				<p> </p>


				<p><hi rend="small-caps">The</hi> following are the circumstances which occasioned
					the succeeding pages. A gentleman and a friend, requested the writer to assign
					reasons why he should not join the Abolition Society. While preparing a reply to
					this request, <hi rend="small-caps">Miss Grimke's</hi> Address was presented,
					and the information communicated, of her intention to visit the North, for the
					purpose of using her influence among northern ladies to induce them to unite
					with Abolition Societies. The writer then began a private letter to Miss
					Grimk&eacute; as a personal friend. But by the wishes and advice of others,
					these two efforts were finally combined in the following Essay, to be presented
					to the public.</p>

				<pb n="004"/>
				<p> </p>

				<p>The honoured and beloved name which that lady bears, so associated as it is at
					the South, North, and West, with all that is elegant in a scholar, refined in a
					gentleman, and elevated in a Christian, &mdash; the respectable sect with
					which she is connected, &mdash; the interesting effusions of her pen,
					&mdash; and her own intellectual and moral worth, must secure respect for
					her opinions and much personal influence. This seems to be a sufficient apology
					for presenting to the public some considerations in connexion with her name;
					considerations which may exhibit in another aspect the cause she advocates, and
					which it may be appropriate to consider. As such, they are respectfully
					commended to the public, and especially to that portion of it for which they are
					p articularly designed.</p>
			</div1>
		</front>


		<body id="d5">

			<div1 type="essay" id="d6">
				<pb n="005"/>
				<head>ESSAY ON SLAVERY AND ABOLITIONISM.</head>

				<div2 type="letter" id="d7">
					<head>ADDRESSED TO MISS A. D. GRIMKE.</head>
					<opener>
						<salute>
							<hi rend="small-caps">My dear Friend,</hi>
						</salute>
					</opener>

					<p>Your public address to Christian females at the South has reached me, and I
						have been urged to aid in circulating it at the North. I have also been
						informed, that you contemplate a tour, during the ensuing year, for the
						purpose of exerting your influence to form Abolition Societies among ladies
						of the non-slave-holding States.</p>
					<p>Our acquaintance and friendship give me a claim to your private ear; but
						there are reasons why it seems more desirable to address you, who now stand
						before the public <pb n="006"/> as an advocate of Abolition measures, in a
						more public manner.</p>
					<p>The object I have in view, is to present some reasons why it seems unwise and
						inexpedient for ladies of the non-slave-holding States to unite themselves
						in Abolition Societies; and thus, at the same time, to exhibit the
						inexpediency of the course you propose to adopt.</p>
					<p>I would first remark, that your public address leads me to infer, that you
						are not sufficiently informed in regard to the feelings and opinions of
						Christian females at the North. Your remarks seem to assume, that the <hi
							rend="italic">principles</hi> held by Abolitionists on the subject of
						slavery, are peculiar to them, and are not generally adopted by those at the
						North who oppose their <hi rend="italic">measures</hi>. In this you are not
						correctly informed. In the sense in which Abolitionists expla in the terms
						they employ, there is little, if any, difference between them and most
						northern persons. Especially is this true of northern persons of religious
						principles. I know not where to look for northern Christians, who would deny
							<pb n="007"/> that every slave-holder is bound to treat his slaves
						exactly as he would claim that his own children ought to be treated in
						similar circumstances; that the holding of our fellow men as property, or
						the withholding any of the rights of freedom, for mere purposes of gain, is
						a sin, and ought to be immediately abandoned; and that where the laws are
						such, that a slave-holder cannot <hi rend="italic">legally</hi> emancipate
						his slaves, without throwing them into worse bondage, he is bound to use all
						his influence to alter those laws, and, in the meantime, to treat his
						slaves, as nearly as he can, <hi rend="italic">as if </hi> they were free.</p>
					<p>I do not suppose there is one person in a thousand, at the North, who would
						dissent from these principles. They would only differ in the use of terms
						and call this the doctrine of <hi rend="italic">gradual emancipation,</hi>
						while Abolitionists would call it the doctrine of <hi rend="italic"
							>immediate emancipation</hi>.</p>
					<p>As this is the state of public opinion at the North, there is no necessity
						for using any influence with northern ladies, in order that they may adopt
						your <hi rend="italic">principles</hi> on the subject<pb n="008"/> of
						slavery; for they hold them in common with yourself, and it would seem
						unwise, and might prove irritating, to approach them as if they held
						opposite sentiments.</p>
					<p>In regard to the duty of making efforts to bring the people of the Southern
						States to adopt these principles, and act on them, it is entirely another
						matter. On this point you would find a large majority opposed to your views.
						Most persons in the non-slave-holding States have considered the matter of
						Southern slavery, as one in which they were no more called to interfere,
						than in the abolition of the press-gang system in England, or the tythe
						system of Ireland. Public opinion may have been wrong on this point, and yet
						have been right on all those great principles of rectitude and justice
						relating to slavery, which Abolitionists claim as their <hi rend="italic"
							>distinctive </hi> peculiarities.</p>
					<p>The distinctive peculiarity of the Abolition Society is this: it is a
						voluntary association in one section of the country, designed to awaken
						public sentiment against a moral evil existing in another section of the
						country, <pb n="009"/> and the principal point of effort seems to be, to
						enlarge the numbers of this association as a means of influencing public
						sentiment. The principal object of your proposed tour, I suppose, is to
						present facts, arguments, and persuasions to influence northern ladies to
						enrol themselves as members of this association.</p>
					<p>I will therefore proceed to present some of the reasons which may be brought
						against such a measure as the one you would urge.</p>
					<p>In the first place, the main principle of action in that society rests wholly
						on a false deduction from past experience. Experience has shown, that when
						certain moral evils exist in a community, efforts to awaken public sentiment
						against such practices, and combinations for the exercise of personal
						influence and example, have in various cases tended to rectify these evils.
						Thus in respect to intemperance; &mdash; the collecting of facts, the
						labours of public lecturers and the distribution of publications, have had
						much effect in diminishing the evil. So in reference to the slave-trade and
						slavery in England. The <pb n="010"/> English nation possessed the power of
						regulating their own trade, and of giving liberty to every slave in their
						dominions; and yet they were entirely unmindful of their duty on this
						subject. Clarkson, Wilberforce, and their coadjutors, commenced a system of
						operations to arouse and influence public sentiment, and they succeeded in
						securing the suppression of the slave trade, and the gradual abolition of
						slavery in the English colonies. In both these cases, the effort was to
						enlighten and direct public sentiment in a community, of which the actors
						were a portion, in order to lead them to rectify an evil existing among
						THEMSELVES, which was entirely under their control.</p>
					<p>From the success of such efforts, the Abolitionists of this country have
						drawn inferences, which appear to be not only illogical, but false. Because
						individuals in <hi rend="italic">their own</hi> community have aroused their
						fellow citizens to correct their own evils, therefore they infer that
						attempts to convince their fellow-citizens of the faults of <hi
							rend="italic">another</hi> community will lead that community to forsake
							<pb n="011"/> their evil practices. An example will more clearly
						illustrate the case. Suppose two rival cities, which have always been in
						competition, and always jealous of each other's reputation and prosperity.
						Certain individuals in one of these cities become convinced, that the sin of
						intemperance is destroying their prosperity and domestic happiness. They
						proceed to collect facts, they arrange statistics, they call public
						meetings, they form voluntary associations, they use arguments, entreaties
						and personal example, and by these means they arrest the evil.</p>
					<p>Suppose another set of men, in this same community, become convinced that
						certain practices in trade and business in the rival city, are dishonest,
						and have an oppressive bearing on certain classes in that city, and are
						injurious to the interests of general commerce. Suppose also, that these are
						practices, which, by those who allow them, are considered as honourable and
						right. Those who are convinced of their immorality, wish to alter the
						opinions and the practices of the citizens of their rival city, and to do
						this, <pb n="012"/> they commence the collection of facts, that exhibit the
						tendencies of these practices and the evils they have engendered. But
						instead of going among the community in which the evils exist, and
						endeavouring to convince and persuade them, they proceed to form voluntary
						associations among their neighbours at home, and spend their time, money and
						efforts to convince their fellow citizens that the inhabitants of their
						rival city are guilty of a great sin. They also publish papers and tracts
						and send out agents, not to the guilty city, but to all the neighbouring
						towns and villages, to convince them of the sins of the city in their
						vicinity. And they claim that they shall succeed in making that city break
						off its sins, by these measures, because other men succe eded in banishing
						intemperance by labouring among their own friends and fellow citizens. Is
						not this example exactly parallel with the exertions of the Abolitionists?
						Are not the northern and southern sections of our country distinct
						communities, with different feelings and interests? Are they not rival, and
						jealous in feeling? Have the northern States the power to rectify evils <pb
							n="013"/>
						<milestone unit="collation" n="B"/> at the South, as they have to remove
						their own moral deformities; or have they any such power over the southern
						States as the British people had over their own trade and their dependent
						colonies in the West Indies? Have not Abolitionists been sending out papers,
						tracts, and agents to convince the people of the North of the sins of the
						South? Have they not refrained from going to the South with their facts,
						arguments, and appeals, because they feared personal evils to themselves?
						And do not Abolitionists f ound their hopes of success in their project, on
						the success which crowned the efforts of British philanthropists in the case
						of slavery, and on the success that has attended efforts to banish
						intemperance? And do not these two cases differ entirely from the Abolition
						movement in this main point, that one is an effort to convince men of <hi
							rend="italic">their own</hi> sins, and the other is an effort to
						convince men of the sins of <hi rend="italic">other persons?</hi></p>
					<p>The second reason I would urge against joining the Abolition Society is, that
						its character and measures are not either peaceful <pb n="014"/> or
						Christian in tendency, but they rather are those which tend to generate
						party spirit, denunciation, recrimination, and angry passions.</p>
					<p>But before bringing evidence to sustain this position, I wish to make a
						distinction between the <hi rend="italic">men</hi> who constitute an
						association, and the <hi rend="italic">measures</hi> which are advocated and
						adopted.</p>
					<p>I believe, that as a body, Abolitionists are men of pure morals, of great
						honesty of purpose, of real benevolence and piety, and of great activity in
						efforts to promote what they consider the best interests of their fellow
						men. I believe, that, in making efforts to abolish slavery, they have taken
						measures, which they supposed were best calculated to bring this evil to an
						end, with the greatest speed, and with the least danger and suffering to the
						South. I do not believe they ever designed to promote disunion, or
						insurrection, or to stir up strife, or that they suppose that their measures
						can be justly characterized by the peculiarities I have specified. I believe
						they have been urged forward by a <pb n="015"/> strong feeling of
						patriotism, as well as of religious duty, and that they have made great
						sacrifices of feeling, character, time, and money to promote what they
						believed to be the cause of humanity and the service of God. I regard
						individuals among them, as having taken a bold and courageous stand, in
						maintaining the liberty of free discussion, the liberty of speech and of the
						press; though this however is somewhat abated by the needless provocations
						by which they caused those difficulties and hazards they so courageously
						sustained. In speaking thus of Abolitionists as a body, it is not assumed
						that there are not bad men found in this party as well as in every other;
						nor that among those who are good men, there are not those who may have
						allowed party spirit to take the place of Christian principle; men who have
						exhibited a mournful destitution of Christian charity; who have indulged in
						an overbearing, denouncing, and self-willed pertinacity as to measures. Yet
						with these reservations, I believe that the above is no more than a fair and
						just exhibition of that class of men <pb n="016"/> who are embraced in the
						party of Abolitionists. And all this can be allowed, and yet the objection I
						am to urge against joining their ranks may stand in its full force.</p>
					<p>To make the position clearer, an illustration may be allowed. Suppose a body
						of good men become convinced that the inspired direction, &ldquo;them
						that sin, rebuke before all, that others may fear,&rdquo; imposes upon
						them the duty of openly rebuking every body whom they discover in the
						practice of any sin. Suppose these men are daily in the habit of going into
						the streets, and calling all by-standers around them, pointing out certain
						men, some as liars, some as dishonest, some as licentious, and then bringing
						proofs of their guilt and rebuking them before all; at the same time
						exhorting all around to point at them the finger of scorn.</p>
					<p>They persevere in this course till the whole community is thrown into an
						uproar; and assaults, and even bloodshed ensue. They then call on all good
						citizens to protect their persons from abuse, and to maintain the liberty of
						speech and of free opinion.</p>
					<pb n="017"/>
					<p> </p>
					<milestone unit="collation" n="B 2"/>
					<p>Now the men may be as pure in morals, as conscientious and upright in
						intention, as any Abolitionist, and yet every one would say, that their
						measures were unwise and unchristian.</p>
					<p>In like manner, although Abolitionists may be lauded for many virtues, still
						much evidence can be presented, that the character and measures of the
						Abolition Society are not either peaceful or christian in tendency, but that
						they are in their nature calculated to generate party spirit, denunciation,
						recrimination, and angry passions.</p>
					<p>The first thing I would present to establish this, is the character of the
						leaders of this association. Every combined effort is necessarily directed
						by leaders; and the spirit of the leaders will inevitably be communicated to
						their coadjutors, and appear in the measures of the whole body.</p>
					<p>In attempting to characterize these leaders, I would first present another
						leader of a similar enterprise, the beloved and venerated <hi
							rend="small-caps">Wilberforce</hi>. It is thus that his prominent traits
						are delineated by an intimate friend.</p>
					<pb n="018"/>
					<p> </p>
					<p>&ldquo;His extreme benevolence contributed largely to his success. I have
						heard him say, that it was one of his constant rules, and on the question of
						slavery especially, never to provoke an adversary &mdash; to allow him
						credit fully for sincerity and purity of motive &mdash; to abstain from
						all irritating expressions &mdash; to avoid even such political attacks
						as would indispose his opponents for his great cause. In fact, the
						benignity, the gentleness, the kind-heartedness of the man, disarmed the
						bitterest foes. Not only on this question did he restrain himself, but
						generally. Once he had been called during a whole debate `the religious
						member,' in a kind of scorn. He remarked afterwards, that he was much
						inclined to have retorted; by calling his opponent the <hi rend="italic"
							>irreligious</hi> member, but that he refrained, as it would have been a
						returning of evil for evil. Next to his general consistency, and love of the
						Scriptures, the <hi rend="italic">humility</hi> of his character always
						appeared remarkable. The modest, shrinking, simple Christian statesman and
						friend always appeared in him. And the nearer you approached<pb n="019"/>
						him, the more his habit of mind obviously appeared to be modest and lowly.
						His <hi rend="italic">charity in judging of others,</hi> is a farther trait
						of his Christian character. Of his benevolence I need not speak, but his <hi
							rend="italic">kind construction of doubtful actions,</hi> his <hi
							rend="italic">charitable language</hi> toward those with whom he most
						widely differed, his thorough forgetfulness of little affronts, were fruits
						of that general benevolence which continually appeared.&rdquo;</p>
					<p>This was the leader, both in and out of Parliament, of that body of men who
						combined to bring to an end slavery and the slave trade, in the dominions of
						Great Britain. With him, as principal leaders, were associated <hi
							rend="small-caps">Clarkson, Sharpe, Macauley,</hi> and others of a
						similar spirit. These men were all of them characterized by that mild,
						benevolent, peaceful, gentlemanly and forbearing spirit, which has been
						described as so conspicuous in Wilberforce. And when their measures are
						examined, it will be found that they were eminently mild, peaceful, and
						forbearing. Though no effort that is to encounter the selfish interests of
						men, can escape <pb n="020"/> without odium and opposition, from those who
						are thwarted, and from all whom they can influence, these men carefully took
						those measures that were calculated to bring about their end with the least
						opposition and evil possible. They avoided prejudices, strove to conciliate
						opposers, shunned every thing that would give needless offence and
						exasperation, began slowly and cautiously, with points which could be the
						most easily carried, and advanced toward others only as public sentiment
						became more and more enlightened. They did not beard the lion in full face,
						by coming out as the first thing with the maxim, that all slavery ought and
						must be abandoned immediately. They began with &ldquo;inquiries as to
						the <hi rend="italic">impolicy</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">slave
						trade,</hi>&rdquo; and it was years before they came to the point of the
						abolition of slavery. And they carried their measures through, without
						producing warring parties among <hi rend="italic">good men, </hi> who held
						common principles with themselves. As a general fact, the pious men of Great
						Britain acted harmoniously in this great effort.</p>
					<pb n="021"/>
					<p> </p>
					<p>Let us now look at the leaders of the Abolition movement in America. The man
						who first took the lead was William L. Garrison, who, though he professes a
						belief in the Christian religion, is an avowed opponent of most of its
						institutions. The character and spirit of this man have for years been
						exhibited in &ldquo;the Liberator,&rdquo; of which he is the editor.
						That there is to be found in that paper, or in any thing else, any evidence
						of his possessing the peculiar traits of Wilberforce, not even his warmest
						admirers will maintain. How many of the opposite traits can be found, those
						can best judge who have read his paper. Gradually others joined themselves
						in the effort commenced by Garrison; but for a long time they consisted
						chiefly of men who would fall into one of these three classes; either good
						men who were so excited by a knowledge of the enormous evils of slavery,
						that <hi rend="italic">any thing</hi> was considered better than entire
						inactivity, or else men accustomed to a contracted field of observation, and
						more qualified to judge of immediate results than of general tendencies, <pb
							n="022"/> or else men of ardent and impulsive temperament, whose
						feelings are likely to take the lead, rather than their judgment.</p>
					<p>There are no men who act more efficiently as the leaders of an enterprise
						than the editors of the periodicals that advocate and defend it. The editors
						of the Emancipator, the Friend of Man, the New York Evangelist, and the
						other abolition periodicals, may therefore be considered as among the chief
						leaders of the enterprise, and their papers are the mirror from which their
						spirit and character are reflected.</p>
					<p>I wish the friends of these editors would cull from their papers all the
						indications they can find of the peculiarities that distinguished
						Wilberforce and his associates; all the evidence of &ldquo;a modest and
						lowly spirit,&rdquo; &mdash; all the exhibitions of
						&ldquo;charity in judging of the motives of those who oppose their
						measures,&rdquo; &mdash; all the &ldquo;indications of
						benignity, gentleness, and kind-heartedness,&rdquo; &mdash; all the
						&ldquo;kind constructions of doubtful actions,&rdquo; &mdash;
						all the &ldquo;charitable language used toward those who differ in
						opinion or measures,&rdquo; &mdash; all the <pb n="023"/>
						&ldquo;thorough forgetfulness of little affronts,&rdquo; &mdash;
						all the cases where &ldquo;opponents are allowed full credit for purity
						and sincerity of motive,&rdquo; &mdash; all cases where they have
						been careful &ldquo;never to provoke an adversary,&rdquo;
						&mdash; all cases where they have &ldquo;refrained from all
						irritating expressions,&rdquo; &mdash; all cases where they have
						avoided every thing that would &ldquo;indispose their opponents for
						their great cause,&rdquo; and then compare the result with what may be
						found of an opposite character, and I think it would not be unsafe to infer
						that an association whose measures, on an exciting subject, were guided by
						such men, would be more likely to be aggressive than peaceful. The position
						I would establish will appear more clearly, by examining in detail some of
						the prominent measures which have been adopted by this association.</p>
					<p>One of the first measures of Abolitionists was an attack on a benevolent
						society, originated and sustained by some of the most pious and devoted men
						of the age. It was imagined by Abolitionists, that the influence and
						measures of the Colonization Society tended to <pb n="024"/> retard the
						abolition of slavery, and to perpetuate injurious prejudices against the
						coloured race. The peaceful and christian method of meeting this difficulty
						would have been, to collect all the evidence of this supposed hurtful
						tendency, and privately, and in a respectful and conciliating way, to have
						presented it to the attention of the wise and benevolent men, who were most
						interested in sustaining this institution. If this measure did not avail to
						convince them, then it would have been safe and justifiable to present to
						the public a temperate statement of facts, and of the deductions based on
						them, drawn up in a respectful and candid manner, with every charitable
						allowance which truth could warrant. Instead of this, when the attempt was
						first made to turn public opinion against the Colonization Society, I met
						one of the most influential supporters of that institution, just after he
						had had an interview with a leading Abolitionist. This gentleman was most
						remarkable for his urbanity, meekness, and benevolence, and his remark to me
						in reference to this interview, shows what was its nature. <pb n="025"/>
						<milestone unit="collation" n="C"/> &ldquo;I love truth and sound
						argument,&rdquo; said he, &ldquo;but when a man comes at me with a
						sledge hammer, I cannot help dodging.&rdquo; This is a specimen of their
						private manner of dealing. In public, the enterprise was attacked as a plan
						for promoting the selfish interests and prejudices of the whites, at the
						expense of the coloured population; and in many cases, it was assumed that
						the conductors of this association were aware of this, and accessory to it.
						And the style in which the thing was done was at once offensive,
						inflammatory, and exasperating. Denunciation, sneers, and public rebuke,
						were bestowed indiscriminately upon the conductors of the enterprise, and of
						course they fell upon many sincere, upright, and conscientious men, whose
						feelings were harrowed by a sense of the injustice, the indecorum, and the
						unchristian treatment, they received. And when a temporary impression was
						made on the public mind, and its opponents supposed they had succeeded in
						crushing this society, the most public and triumphant exultation was not
						repressed. Compare this method of carrying a point, with that <pb n="026"/>
						adopted by Wilberforce and his compeers, and I think you will allow that
						there was a way that was peaceful and christian, and that this was not the
						way which was chosen.</p>
					<p>The next measure of Abolitionism was an attempt to remove the prejudices of
						the whites against the blacks, on account of natural peculiarities. Now,
						prejudice is an <hi rend="italic">unreasonable</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
							>groundless</hi> dislike of persons or things. Of course, as it is
						unreasonable, it is the most difficult of all things to conquer, and the
						worst and most irritating method that could be attempted would be, to attack
						a man as guilty of sin, as unreasonable, as ungenerous, or as proud, for
						allowing a certain prejudice.</p>
					<p>This is the sure way to produce anger, <orig reg="self-justification"
							>self-justification</orig>, and an increase of the strength of
						prejudice, against that which has caused him this rebuke and irritation.</p>
					<p>The best way to make a person like a thing which is disagreeable, is to try
						in some way to make it agreeable; and if a certain class of persons is the
						subject of unreasonable prejudice, the peaceful and christian way of
						removing it would be to endeavour to render <pb n="027"/> the unfortunate
						persons who compose this class, so useful, so humble and unassuming, so kind
						in their feelings, and so full of love and good works, that prejudice would
						be supplanted by complacency in their goodness, and pity and sympathy for
						their disabilities. If the friends of the blacks had quietly set themselves
						to work to increase their intelligence, their usefulness, their
						respectability, their meekness, gentleness, and benevolence, and then had
						appealed to the pity, generosity, and christian feelings of their fellow
						citizens, a very different result would have appeared. Instead of this,
						reproaches, rebukes, and sneers, were employed to convince the whites that
						their prejudices were sinful, and without any just cause. They were accused
						of pride, of selfish indifference, of unchristian neglect. This tended to
						irritate the whites, and to increase their prejudice against the blacks, who
						thus were made the causes of rebuke and exasperation. Then, on the other
						hand, the blacks extensively received the Liberator, and learned to imbibe
						the spirit of its conductor.</p>
					<pb n="028"/>
					<p> </p>
					<p>They were taught to feel that they were injured and abused, the objects of a
						guilty and unreasonable prejudice &mdash; that they occupied a lower
						place in society than was right &mdash; that they ought to be treated as
						if they were whites; and in repeated instances, attempts were made by their
						friends to mingle them with whites, so as to break down the existing
						distinctions of society. Now, the question is not, whether these things,
						that were urged by Abolitionists, were true. The thing maintained is, that
						the method taken by them to remove this prejudice was neither peaceful nor
						christian in its tendency, but, on the contrary, was calculated to increase
						the evil, and to generate anger, pride, and recrimination, on one side, and
						envy, discontent, and revengeful feelings, on the other.</p>
					<p>These are some of the general measures which have been exhibited in the
						Abolition movement. The same peculiarities may be as distinctly seen in
						specific cases, where the peaceful and quiet way of accomplishing the good
						was neglected, and the one most calculated to excite wrath and strife was
						chosen. <pb n="029"/>
						<milestone unit="collation" n="C 2"/> Take, for example, the effort to
						establish a college for coloured persons. The quiet, peaceful, and christian
						way of doing such a thing, would have been, for those who were interested in
						the plan, to furnish the money necessary, and then to have selected a
						retired place, where there would be the least prejudice and opposition to be
						met, and there, in an unostentatious way, commenced the education of the
						youth to be thus sustained. Instead of this, at a time when the public mind
						was excited on the subject, it was noised abroad that a college for blacks
						was to be founded. Then a city was selected for its location, where was
						another college, so large as to demand constant effort and vigilance to
						preserve quiet subordination; where contests with &ldquo;sailors and
						town boys&rdquo; were barely kept at bay; a college embracing a large
						proportion of southern students, who were highly excited on the subject of
						slavery and emancipation; a college where half the shoeblacks and waiters
						were coloured men. Beside the very walls of this college, it was proposed to
						found a college for coloured young <pb n="030"/> men. Could it be otherwise
						than that opposition, and that for the best of reasons, would arise against
						such an attempt, both from the faculty of the college and the citizens of
						the place? Could it be reasonably expected that they would not oppose a
						measure so calculated to increase their own difficulties and liabilities,
						and at the same time so certain to place the proposed institution in the
						most unfavourable of all circumstances? But when the measure was opposed,
						instead of yielding meekly and peaceably to such reasonable objections, and
						soothing the feelings and apprehensions that had been excited, by putting
						the best construction on the matter, and seeking another place, it was
						claimed as an evidence of opposition to the interests of the blacks, and as
						a mark of the force of sinful prejudice. The worst, rather than the best,
						motives were ascribed to some of the most respectable, and venerated, and
						pious men, who opposed the measure; and a great deal was said and done that
						was calculated to throw the community into an angry ferment.</p>
					<p>Take another example. If a prudent and <pb n="031"/> benevolent female had
						selected almost any village in New England, and commenced a school for
						coloured females, in a quiet, appropriate, and unostentatious way, the world
						would never have heard of the case, except to applaud her benevolence, and
						the kindness of the villagers, who aided her in the effort. But instead of
						this, there appeared public advertisements, (which I saw at the time,)
						stating that a seminary for the education of young ladies of colour was to
						be opened in Canterbury, in the state of Connecticut, where would be taught
						music on the piano forte, drawing, &amp;c., together with a course of
						English education. Now, there are not a dozen coloured families in New
						England, in such pecuniary circumstances, that if they were whites it would
						not be thought ridiculous to attempt to give their daughters such a course
						of education, and Canterbury was a place where but few of the wealthiest
						families ever thought of furnishing such accomplishments for their children.
						Several other particulars might be added that were exceedingly irritating,
						but this may serve as a specimen of <pb n="032"/> the method in which the
						whole affair was conducted. It was an entire disregard of the prejudices and
						the proprieties of society, and calculated to stimulate pride, anger,
						ill-will, contention, and all the bitter feelings that spring from such
						collisions. Then, instead of adopting measures to soothe and conciliate,
						rebukes, sneers and denunciations, were employed, and Canterbury and
						Connecticut were held up to public scorn and rebuke for doing what most
						other communities would probably have done, if similarly tempted and
						provoked.</p>
					<p>Take another case. It was deemed expedient by Abolitionists to establish an
						Abolition paper, first in Kentucky, a slave State. It was driven from that
						State, either by violence or by threats. It retreated to Ohio, one of the
						free States. In selecting a place for its location, it might have been
						established in a small place, where the people were of similar views, or
						were not exposed to dangerous popular excitements. But Cincinnati was
						selected; and when the most intelligent, the most reasonable, and th e most
						patriotic of <pb n="033"/> the citizens remonstrated, &mdash; when they
						represented that there were peculiar and unusual liabilities to popular
						excitement on this subject, &mdash; that the organization and power of
						the police made it extremely dangerous to excite a mob, and almost impo
						ssible to control it, &mdash; that all the good aimed at could be
						accomplished by locating the press in another place, where there were not
						such dangerous liabilities, &mdash; when they kindly and respectfully
						urged these considerations, they were disregarde d. I myself was present
						when a sincere friend urged upon the one who controlled that paper, the
						obligations of good men, not merely to avoid breaking wholesome laws
						themselves, but the duty of regarding the liabilities of others to
						temptation; and that wh ere Christians could foresee that by placing certain
						temptations in the way of their fellow-men, all the probabilities were, that
						they would yield, and yet persisted in doing it, the tempters became
						partakers in the guilt of those who yielded to the tempt ation. But these
						remonstrances were ineffectual. The paper must not only be printed and
						circulated, but it must <pb n="034"/> be stationed where were the greatest
						probabilities that measures of illegal violence would ensue. And when the
						evil was perpetrated, and a mob destroyed the press, then those who had
						urged on these measures of temptation, turned upon those who had advised and
						remonstrated, as the guilty authors of the violence, because, in a season of
						excitement, the measures adopted to restrain and control the mob, were not
						such as were deemed suitable and right.</p>
					<p>Now, in all the above cases, I would by no means justify the wrong or the
						injudicious measures that may have been pursued, under this course of
						provocation. The greatness of temptation does by no means release men from
						obligation; but Christians are bo und to remember that it is a certain
						consequence of throwing men into strong excitement, that they will act
						unwisely and wrong, and that the tempter as well as the tempted are held
						responsible, both by God and man. In all these cases, it cannot but appear
						that the good aimed at might have been accomplished in a quiet, peaceable,
						and <pb n="035"/> christian way, and that this was not the way which was
						chosen.</p>
					<p>The whole system of Abolition measures seems to leave entirely out of view,
						the obligation of Christians to save their fellow men from all needless
						temptations. If the thing to be done is only lawful and right, it does not
						appear to have been a matter of effort to do it in such a way as would not
						provoke and irritate; but often, if the chief aim had been to do the good in
						the most injurious and offensive way, no more certain and appropriate
						methods could have been devised.</p>
					<p>So much has this been the character of Abolition movements, that many have
						supposed it to be a deliberate and systematized plan of the leaders to do
						nothing but what was strictly a <hi rend="italic">right</hi> guaranteed by
						law, and yet, in such a man ner, as to provoke men to anger, so that unjust
						and illegal acts might ensue, knowing, that as a consequence, the opposers
						of Abolition would be thrown into the wrong, and sympathy be aroused for
						Abolitionists as injured and persecuted men. It is a fact, that
						Abolitionists have taken the course most <pb n="036"/> calculated to awaken
						illegal acts of violence, and that when they have ensued, they have seemed
						to rejoice in them, as calculated to advance and strengthen their cause. The
						violence of mobs, the denunciations and unreasonable requirements of the
						South, th e denial of the right of petition, the restrictions attempted to
						be laid upon freedom of speech, and freedom of the press, are generally
						spoken of with exultation by Abolitionists, as what are among the chief
						means of promoting their cause. It is not so m uch by exciting feelings of
						pity and humanity, and Christian love, towards the oppressed, as it is by
						awakening indignation at the treatment of Abolitionists themselves, that
						their cause has prospered. How many men have declared or implied, that in
						joinin g the ranks of Abolition, they were influenced, not by their
						arguments, or by the wisdom of their course, but because the violence of
						opposers had identified that cause with the question of freedom of speech,
						freedom of the press, and civil liberty.</p>
					<p>But when I say that many have supposed that it was the deliberate intention
						of the Abolitionists<pb n="037"/>
						<milestone unit="collation" n="D"/> to foment illegal acts and violence, I
						would by no means justify a supposition, which is contrary to the dictates
						of justice and charity. The leaders of the Abolition Society disclaim all
						such wishes or intentions; they only act apparently on the assumpt ion that
						they are exercising just rights, which they are not bound to give up,
						because other men will act unreasonably and wickedly.</p>
					<p>Another measure of Abolitionists, calculated to awaken evil feelings, has
						been the treatment of those who objected to their proceedings.</p>
					<p>A large majority of the philanthropic and pious, who hold common views with
						the Abolitionists, as to the sin and evils of slavery, and the duty of using
						all appropriate means to bring it to an end, have opposed their measures,
						because they have believe d them not calculated to promote, but rather to
						retard the end proposed to be accomplished by them. The peaceful and
						Christian method of encountering such opposition, would have been to allow
						the opponents full credit for purity and integrity of motive, t o have
						avoided all <pb n="038"/> harsh and censorious language, and to have
						employed facts, arguments and persuasions, in a kind and respectful way with
						the hope of modifying their views and allaying their fears. Instead of this,
						the wise and good who opposed Abolition measures, have bee n treated as
						though they were the friends and defenders of slavery, or as those who, from
						a guilty, timid, time-serving policy, refused to take the course which duty
						demanded. They have been addressed either as if it were necessary to
						convince them that s lavery is wrong and ought to be abandoned, or else, as
						if they needed to be exhorted to give up their timidity and selfish
						interest, and to perform a manifest duty, which they were knowingly
						neglecting.</p>
					<p>Now there is nothing more irritating, when a man is conscientious and acting
						according to his own views of right, than to be dealt with in this manner.
						The more men are treated as if they were honest and sincere &mdash; the
						more they are treated with re spect, fairness, and benevolence, the more
						likely they are to be moved by evidence and arguments. <pb n="039"/> On the
						contrary, harshness, uncharitableness, and rebuke, for opinions and conduct
						that are in agreement with a man's own views of duty and rectitude, tend to
						awaken evil feelings, and indispose the mind properly to regard evidence.
						Abolitionists have not only taken this course, but in many cases, have
						seemed to act on the principle, that the abolition of Slavery, in the
						particular mode in which they were aiming to accomplish it, was of such
						paramount importance, that every thing must be overthrown that s tood in the
						way.</p>
					<p>No matter what respect a man had gained for talents, virtue, and piety, if he
						stood in the way of Abolitionism, he must be attacked as to character and
						motives. No matter how important an institution might be, if its influence
						was against the measures of Abolitionism, it must be attacked openly, or
						sapped privately, till its influence was destroyed. By such measures, the
						most direct means have been taken to awaken anger at injury, and resentment
						at injustice, and to provoke retaliation on those who inf lict the wrong.
						All the partialities of personal friendship; all the feelings<pb n="040"/>
						of respect accorded to good and useful men; all the interests that cluster
						around public institutions, entrenched in the hearts of the multitudes who
						sustain them, were outraged by such a course.</p>
					<p>Another measure of Abolitionists, which has greatly tended to promote wrath
						and strife, is their indiscreet and incorrect use of terms.</p>
					<p>To make this apparent, it must be premised, that words have no inherent
						meaning, but always signify that which they are commonly <hi rend="italic"
							>understood</hi> to mean. The question never should be asked, what <hi
							rend="italic">ought</hi> a word t o mean? but simply, what is the
						meaning generally attached to this word by those who use it? Vocabularies
						and standard writers are the proper umpires to decide this question. Now if
						men take words and give them a new and peculiar use, and are consequently
						misunderstood, they are guilty of a species of deception, and are
						accountable for all the evils that may ensue as a consequence.</p>
					<p>For example; if physicians should come out and declare, that it was their
						opinion that they <pb n="041"/>
						<milestone unit="collation" n="D 2"/> ought to poison all their patients,
						and they had determined to do it, and then all the community should be
						thrown into terror and excitement, it would be no justification for them to
						say, that all they intended by that language was, that they should admin
						ister as medicines, articles which are usually called poisons.</p>
					<p>Now Abolitionists are before the community, and declare that all slavery is
						sin, which ought to be immediately forsaken; and that it is their object and
						intention to promote the <hi rend="italic">immediate emancipation</hi> of
						all the slaves in this n ation.</p>
					<p>Now what is it that makes a man cease to be a slave and become free? It is
						not kind treatment from a master; it is not paying wages to the slave; it is
						not the intention to bestow freedom at a future time; it is not treating a
						slave as if he were free; it is not feeling toward a slave as if he were
						free. No instance can be found of any dictionary, or any standard writer,
						nor any case in common discourse, where any of these significations are
						attached to the word as constituting its peculiar and appropr iate meaning.
						It always <pb n="042"/> signifies <hi rend="italic">that legal act,</hi>
						which, by the laws of the land, changes a slave to a freeman.</p>
					<p>What then is the <hi rend="italic">proper</hi> meaning of the language used
						by Abolitionists, when they say that all slavery is a sin which ought to be
						immediately abandoned, and that it is their object to secure the immediate
						emancipation of all slav es?</p>
					<p>The true and only proper meaning of such language is, that it is the duty of
						every <orig reg="slave-holder">slave-holder</orig> in this nation, to go
						immediately and make out the legal instruments, that, by the laws of the
						land, change all his slaves t o freemen. If their maxim is true, no
						exception can be made for those who live in States where the act of
						emancipation, by a master, makes a slave the property of the State, to be
						sold for the benefit of the State; and no exception can be made for those,
						who, by the will of testators, and by the law of the land, have no power to
						perform the legal act, which alone can emancipate their slaves.</p>
					<p>To meet this difficulty, Abolitionists affirm, that, in such cases, men are
						physically unable to emancipate their slaves, and of course are <pb n="043"
						/> not bound to do it; and to save their great maxim, maintain that, in such
						cases, the slaves are not slaves, and the slave-holders are not
						slave-holders, although all their legal relations remain unchanged.</p>
					<p>The meaning which the Abolitionist attaches to his language is this, that
						every man is bound to treat his slaves, as nearly as he can, like freemen;
						and to use all his influence to bring the system of slavery to an end as
						soon as possible. And they all ow that when men do this they are free from
						guilt, in the matter of slavery, and undeserving of censure.</p>
					<p>But men at the North, and men at the South, understand the language used in
						its true and proper sense; and Abolitionists have been using these terms in
						a new and peculiar sense, which is inevitably and universally misunderstood,
						and this is an occasion of much of the strife and alarm which has prevailed
						both at the South and at the North. There are none but these defenders of
						slavery who maintain that it is a relation justifiable by the laws of the
						Gospel, who differ from Abolitionists in <pb n="044"/> regard to the real
						thing which is meant. The great mistake of Abolitionists is in using terms
						which inculcate the immediate annihilation of the relation, when they only
						intend to urge the Christian duty of treating slaves according to the gospel
						rules of justice and benevolence, and using all lawful and appropriate means
						for bringing a most pernicious system to a speedy end.</p>
					<p>If Abolitionists will only cease to teach that <hi rend="italic">all</hi>
						slave-holding is a sin which ought to be <hi rend="italic">immediately
							abolished</hi>; if they will cease to urge their plan as one of <hi
							rend="italic">immediate emancipation ,</hi> and teach simply and exactly
						that which they do mean, much strife and misunderstanding will cease. But so
						long as they persevere in using these terms in a new and peculiar sense,
						which will always be misunderstood, they are guilty of a species of d
						eception and accountable for the evils that follow.</p>
					<p>One other instance of a similar misuse of terms may be mentioned. The word
							&ldquo;<orig reg="man-stealer">man-stealer</orig>&rdquo; has one
						peculiar signification, and it is no more synonymous with
						&ldquo;slave-holder&rdquo; than it is with &ldquo;shee
						p-stealer.&rdquo; But Abolitionists<pb n="045"/> show that a
						slave-holder, in fact, does very many of the evils that are perpetrated by a
						man-stealer, and that the crime is quite as evil in its nature, and very
						similar in character, and, therefore, he calls a slave-holder a man-stealer.</p>
					<p>On this principle there is no abusive language that may not be employed to
						render any man odious &mdash; for every man commits sin of some kind,
						and every sin is like some other sin, in many respects, and in certain
						aggravated cases, may be bad, or even worse, than another sin with a much
						more odious name. It is easy to show that a man who neglects all religious
						duty is very much like an atheist, and if he has had great advantages, and
						the atheist very few, he may be much more guilty than an atheist. And so,
						half the respectable men in our religious communities, may be called
						atheists, with as much propriety as a slave-holder can be called a
						man-stealer. Abolitionists have proceeded on this principle, in their
						various publications, until the terms of odi um that have been showered upon
						slave-holders, would form a large page <pb n="046"/> in the vocabulary of
						Billingsgate. This method of dealing with those whom we wish to convince and
						persuade, is as contrary to the dictates of common sense, as it is to the
						rules of good breeding and the laws of the gospel.</p>
					<p>The preceding particulars are selected, as the evidence to be presented, that
						the character and measures of the Abolition Society are neither peaceful nor
						Christian in their tendency; but that in their nature they are calculated to
						generate party-spiri t, denunciation, recrimination, and angry passions. If
						such be the tendency of this institution, it follows, that it is wrong for a
						Christian, or any lover of peace, to be connected with it.</p>
					<p>The assertion that Christianity itself has led to strife and contention, is
						not a safe method of evading this argument. Christianity is a system of <hi
							rend="italic">persuasion,</hi> tending, by kind and gentle influences,
						to make men <hi rend="italic">willing</hi> to leave off their sins
						&mdash; and it comes, not to convince those who are not sinners, but to
						sinners themselves.</p>
					<p>Abolitionism, on the contrary, is a system of <hi rend="italic">coercion</hi>
						by public opinion; and in its present<pb n="047"/> operation, its influence
						is not to convince the erring, but to convince those who are not guilty, of
						the sins of those who are.</p>
					<p>Another prominent peculiarity of the Abolitionists, (which is an objection to
						joining this association,) is their advocacy of a principle, which is wrong
						and very pernicious in its tendency. I refer to their views in regard to
						what is called &ldquo;the doctrine of expediency.&rdquo; Their
						difficulty on this subject seems to have arisen from want of a clear
						distinction between the duty of those who are guilty of sin, and the duty of
						those who are aiming to turn men from their sins. The principle is assu med,
						that because certain men ought to abandon every sin immediately, therefore,
						certain other men are bound <hi rend="italic">immediately</hi> to try and
						make them do it. Now the question of expediency does not relate to what men
						are bound to do, who ar e in the practice of sin themselves &mdash; for
						the immediate relinquishment of sin is the duty of all; but it relates to
						the duty of those who are to make efforts to induce others to break off
						their wickedness.</p>
					<p>Here, the wisdom and rectitude of a given <pb n="048"/> course, depend
						entirely on the <hi rend="italic">probabilities of success</hi>. If a father
						has a son of a very peculiar temperament, and he knows by observation, that
						the use of the rod will make him more irritable and more liable to a certain
						fault, an d that kind arguments, and tender measures will more probably
						accomplish the desired object, it is a rule of expediency to try the most
						probable course. If a companion sees a friend committing a sin, and has,
						from past experience, learned that remonstranc es excite anger and
						obstinacy, while a look of silent sorrow and disapprobation tends far more
						to prevent the evil, expediency and duty demand silence rather than
						remonstrance.</p>
					<p>There are cases also, where differences in age, and station, and character,
						forbid all interference to modify the conduct and character of others.</p>
					<p>A nursery maid may see that a father misgoverns his children, and ill-treats
						his wife. But her station makes it inexpedient for her to turn reprover. It
						is a case where reproof would do no good, but only evil.</p>
					<pb n="049"/>
					<p> </p>
					<milestone unit="collation" n="E"/>
					<p>So in communities, the propriety and rectitude of measures can be decided,
						not by the rules of duty that should govern those who are to renounce sin,
						but by the probabilities of good or evil consequence.</p>
					<p>The Abolitionists seem to lose sight of this distinction. They form voluntary
						associations in free States, to convince their fellow citizens of the sins
						of other men in other communities. They are blamed and opposed, because
						their measures are deemed i nexpedient, and calculated to increase, rather
						than diminish the evils to be cured.</p>
					<p>In return, they show that slavery is a sin which ought to be abandoned
						immediately, and seem to suppose that it follows as a correct inference,
						that they themselves ought to engage in a system of agitation against it,
						and that it is needless for them t o inquire whether preaching the truth in
						the manner they propose, will increase or diminish the evil. They assume
						that whenever sin is committed, not only ought the sinner immediately to
						cease, but all his fellow-sinners are bound to take measures to make him
						cease, <pb n="050"/> and to take measures, without any reference to the
						probabilities of success.</p>
					<p>That this is a correct representation of the views of Abolitionists
						generally, is evident from their periodicals and conversation. All their
						remarks about preaching the truth and leaving consequences to God
						&mdash; all their depreciation of the doctrine of expediency, are
						rendered relevant only by this supposition.</p>
					<p>The impression made by their writings is, that God has made rules of duty;
						that all men are in all cases to remonstrate against the violation of those
						rules; and that God will take the responsibility of bringing good out of
						this course; so that we ours elves are relieved from any necessity of
						inquiring as to probable results.</p>
					<p>If this be not the theory of duty adopted by this association, then they
						stand on common ground with those who oppose their measures, viz: that the
						propriety and duty of a given course is to be decided by <hi rend="italic"
							>probabilities as to its resu lts;</hi> and these probabilities<pb
							n="051"/> are to be determined by the <hi rend="italic">known laws of
							mind,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">records of past experience</hi>.</p>
					<p>For only one of two positions can be held. Either that it is the duty of all
						men to remonstrate at all times against all violations of duty, and leave
						the consequences with God; or else that men are to use their judgment, and
						take the part of remonstra nce only at such a time and place, and in such a
						manner, as promise the best results.</p>
					<p>That the Abolitionists have not held the second of these positions, must be
						obvious to all who have read their documents. It would therefore be unwise
						and wrong to join an association which sustains a principle false in itself,
						and one which, if acted out, would tend to wrath and strife and every evil
						word and work.</p>
					<p>Another reason, and the most important of all, against promoting the plans of
						the Abolitionists, is involved in the main question &mdash; <hi
							rend="italic">what are the probabilities as to the results of their
							movements?</hi> The only way to judge of t he future results of certain
						measures is, by <pb n="052"/> the known laws of mind, and the recorded
						experience of the past.</p>
					<p>Now what is the evil to be cured?</p>
					<p>
						<hi rend="small-caps">Slavery in this nation.</hi>
					</p>
					<p>That this evil is at no distant period to come to an end, is the unanimous
						opinion of all who either notice the tendencies of the age, or believe in
						the prophecies of the Bible. All who act on Christian principles in regard
						to slavery, believe that in a given period (variously estimated) it will
						end. The only question then, in regard to the benefits to be gained, or the
						evils to be dreaded in the present agitation of the subject, relates to the
							<hi rend="italic">time</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">ma nner</hi> of
						its extinction. The Abolitionists claim that their method will bring it to
						an end in the shortest time, and in the safest and best way. Their opponents
						believe, that it will tend to bring it to an end, if at all, at the most
						distant period, a nd in the most dangerous way.</p>
					<p>As neither party are gifted with prescience, and as the Deity has made no
						revelations as to the future results of any given measures, all the means of
						judging that remain<pb n="053"/>
						<milestone unit="collation" n="E 2"/> to us, as before stated, are the laws
						of mind, and the records of the past.</p>
					<p>The position then I would aim to establish is, that the method taken by the
						Abolitionists is the one that, according to the laws of mind and past
						experience, is least likely to bring about the results they aim to
						accomplish. The general statement is th is.</p>
					<p>The object to be accomplished is:</p>
					<p>First. To convince a certain community, that they are in the practice of a
						great sin, and</p>
					<p>Secondly, To make them willing to relinquish it.</p>
					<p>The method taken to accomplish this is, by voluntary associations in a
						foreign community, seeking to excite public sentiment against the
						perpetrators of the evil; exhibiting the enormity of the crime in full
						measure, without palliation, excuse or sympa thy, by means of periodicals
						and agents circulating, not in the community committing the sin, but in that
						which does not practise it.</p>
					<p>Now that this method may, in conjunction with other causes, have an influence
						to bring <pb n="054"/> slavery to an end, is not denied. But it is believed,
						and from the following considerations, that it is the least calculated to do
						the <hi rend="italic">good,</hi> and that it involves the greatest evils.</p>
					<p>It is a known law of mind first seen in the nursery and school, afterwards
						developed in society, that a person is least likely to judge correctly of
						truth, and least likely to yield to duty, when excited by passion.</p>
					<p>It is a law of experience, that when wrong is done, if repentance and
						reformation are sought, then love and kindness, mingled with remonstrance,
						coming from one who has a <hi rend="italic">right</hi> to speak, are more
						successful than rebuke and scorn from others who are not beloved, and who
						are regarded as impertinent intruders.</p>
					<p>In the nursery, if the child does wrong, the finger of scorn, the taunting
						rebuke, or even the fair and deserved reproof of equals, will make the young
						culprit only frown with rage, and perhaps repeat and increase the injury.
						But the voice of maternal love, or even the gentle remonstrances of an elder
							<pb n="055"/> sister, may bring tears of sorrow and contrition.</p>
					<p>So in society. Let a man's enemies, or those who have no interest in his
						welfare, join to rebuke and rail at his offences, and no signs of penitence
						will be seen. But let the clergyman whom he respects and loves, or his bosom
						friend approach him, with kindness, forbearance and true sincerity, and all
						that is possible to human agency will be effected.</p>
					<p>It is the maxim then of experience, that when men are to be turned from
						evils, and brought to repent and reform, those only should interfere who are
						most loved and respected, and who have the best right to approach the
						offender. While on the other hand , rebuke from those who are deemed
						obtrusive and inimical, or even indifferent, will do more harm than good.</p>
					<p>It is another maxim of experience, that such dealings with the erring should
						be in private, not in public. The moment a man is publicly rebuked, shame,
						anger, and pride <pb n="056"/> of opinion, all combine to make him defend
						his practice, and refuse either to own himself wrong, or to cease from his
						evil ways.</p>
					<p>The Abolitionists have violated all these laws of mind and of experience, in
						dealing with their southern brethren.</p>
					<p>Their course has been most calculated to awaken anger, fear, pride, hatred,
						and all the passions most likely to blind the mind to truth, and make it
						averse to duty.</p>
					<p>They have not approached them with the spirit of love, courtesy, and
						forbearance.</p>
					<p>They are not the persons who would be regarded by the South, as having any
							<hi rend="italic">right </hi> to interfere; and therefore, whether they
						have such right or not, the probabilities of good are removed. For it is not
						only demanded for the benefit of the offender, that there should really be a
						right, but it is necessary that he should feel that t here is such a right.</p>
					<p>In dealing with their brethren, too, they have not tried silent, retired,
						private measures. It has been public denunciation of crime and shame in
						newspapers, addressed <pb n="057"/> as it were to by-standers, in order to
						arouse the guilty.</p>
					<p>In reply to this, it has been urged, that men could not go to the South
						&mdash; that they would be murdered there &mdash; that the only way
						was, to convince the North, and excite public odium against the sins of the
						South, and thus gradually conviction, re pentance, and reformation would
						ensue.</p>
					<p>Here is another case where men are to judge of their duty, by estimating
						probabilities of future results; and it may first be observed, that it
						involves the principle of expediency, in just that form to which
						Abolitionists object.</p>
					<p>It is allowed that the immediate abolition of slavery is to be produced by
						means of &ldquo;light and love,&rdquo; and yet it is maintained as
						right to withdraw personally from the field of operation, because of <hi
							rend="italic">consequences;</hi> bec ause of the probable danger of
						approaching. &ldquo;If we go to the South, and present truth, argument,
						and entreaty, <hi rend="italic">we shall be slain,</hi> and therefore we are
						not under obligation to go.&rdquo; If this justifies Abolitionists in
						thei r neglect <pb n="058"/> of their offending brethren, because they fear
						evil results to themselves, it also justifies those who refuse to act with
						Abolitionists in their measures, because they fear other evil results.</p>
					<p>But what proof is there, that if the Abolitionists had taken another method,
						the one more in accordance with the laws of mind and the dictates of
						experience, that there would have been at the South all this violence?
						Before the abolition movement comme nced, both northern and southern men,
						expressed their views freely at the South. The dangers, evils, and mischiefs
						of slavery were exhibited and discussed even in the legislative halls of
						more than one of the Southern States, and many minds were anxiously devising
						measures, to bring this evil to an end.</p>
					<p>Now let us look at some of the records of past experience. Clarkson was the
						first person who devoted himself to the cause of Abolition in England. His
						object was to convince the people of England that they were guilty of a
						great impolicy, and great <pb n="059"/> sin, in permitting the slave-trade.
						He was to meet the force of public sentiment, and power, and selfishness,
						and wealth, which sustained this trafic, in that nation. What were his
						measures? He did not go to Sweden, or Russia, or France, to awaken public
						sentiment against the sins of the English. &mdash; He began by first
						publishing an inquiry in England whether it was right to seize men, and make
						them slaves. He went unostentatiously to some of the best and most pious men
						there, and endeavoured to interes t them in the inquiry.</p>
					<p>Then he published an article on the impolicy of the slave-trade, showing its
						disadvantages. Then he collected information of the evils and enormities
						involved in the traffic, and went quietly around among those most likely to
						be moved by motives of hum anity and Christianity. In this manner he toiled
						for more than fourteen years, slowly implanting the leaven among the good
						men, until he gained a noble band of patriots and Christians, with
						Wilberforce at their head.</p>
					<p>The following extract from a memoir of <pb n="060"/> Clarkson discloses the
						manner and spirit in which he commenced his enterprise, and toiled through
						to its accomplishment.</p>
					<p>&ldquo;In 1785 Dr. Peckhard, Vice-Chancellor of the University, deeply
						impressed with the iniquity of the slave-trade, announced as a subject for a
						Latin Dissertation to the Senior Bachelors of Arts: <hi rend="italic">`Anne
							liceat invitos in servitute m dare?'</hi> `Is it right to make slaves of
						others against their will?' However benevolent the feelings of the
						Vice-Chancellor, and however strong and clear the opinions he held on the
						inhuman traffic, it is probable that he little thought that this disc ussion
						would secure for the object so dear to his own heart, efforts and advocacy
						equally enlightened and efficient, that should be continued, until his
						country had declared, not that the slave-trade only, but that slavery itself
						should cease.</p>
					<p>&ldquo;Mr. Clarkson, having in the preceding year gained the first prize
						for the Latin Dissertation, was naturally anxious to maintain his honourable
						position; and no efforts were spared, during the few intervening weeks, in
							<pb n="061"/>
						<milestone unit="collation" n="F"/> collecting information and evidence.
						Important facts were gained from Anthony Benezet's Historical Account of
						Guinea, which Mr. Clarkson hastened to London to purchase. Furnished with
						these and other valuable information, he commenced his difficult task. How
						it was accomplished, he thus informs us.</p>
					<p>&ldquo; 'No person,' he states,<ref target="n1">*</ref> 'can tell the
						severe trial which the writing of it proved to me. I had expected pleasure
						from the invention of the arguments, from the arrangement of them, from the
						putting of them together, and from the thought, in the interim, that I was
						engaged in an innocent contest for literary honour. But all my pleasure was
						damped by the facts which were now continually before me. It was but one
						gloomy subject from morning to night. In the day-time I was uneasy; in the
						night I ha d little rest. I sometimes never closed my eyelids for grief. It
						became now not so much a trial for academical reputation, as for <pb n="062"
						/> the production of a work which might be useful to injured Africa. And
						keeping this idea in my mind ever after the perusal of Benezet, I always
						slept with a candle in my room, that I might rise out of bed, and put down
						such thoughts as might occur to me in the night, if I judged them valuable,
						conceiving that no arguments of any moment should be lost in so great a
						cause. Having at length finished this painful task, I sent my Essay to the
						Vice-Chancellor, and soon afterwards found myself honoured, as before , with
						the first prize.</p>
					<p>&ldquo; `As it is usual to read these essays publicly in the senate-house
						soon after the prize is adjudged, I was called to Cambridge for this
						purpose. I went, and performed my office. On returning, however, to London,
						the subject of it almost wholly e ngrossed my thoughts. I became at times
						very seriously affected while upon the road. I stopped my horse
						occasionally, and dismounted, and walked. I frequently tried to persuade
						myself in these intervals that the contents of my Essay could not be true.
						The more, <pb n="063"/> however, I reflected upon them, or rather upon the
						authorities on which they were founded, the more I gave them credit. Coming
						in sight of Wade's Mill, in Hertfordshire, I sat down disconsolate on the
						turf by the road-side, and held my horse. Here a thoug ht came into my mind,
						that if the contents of the Essay were true, it was time some person should
						see these calamities to their end. Agitated in this manner, I reached home.
						This was in the summer of 1785.</p>
					<p>&ldquo; `In the course of the autumn of the same year I experienced
						similar impressions. I walked frequently into the woods, that I might think
						on the subject in solitude, and find relief to my mind there. But there the
						question still recurred, `Are th ese things true?' Still the answer followed
						as instantaneously, &mdash; `They are.' Still the result accompanied it;
						`Then, surely, some person should interfere.' I then began to envy those who
						had seats in parliament, and who had great riches, and widely e xtended
						connexions, which would enable them to take up this cause. Finding scarcely
						any one at that <pb n="064"/> time who thought of it, I was turned
						frequently to myself. But here many difficulties arose. It struck me, among
						others, that a young man of only twenty-four years of age could not have
						that solid judgment, or knowledge of men, manners, and things, which were
						requisite to qualify him to undertake a task of such magnitude and
						importance: and with whom was I to unite? I believed also, that it looked so
						much like one of the feigned labours of Hercules, that my understanding
						would be suspected if I proposed i t. On ruminating, however, on the
						subject, I found one thing at least practicable, and that this was also in
						my power. I could translate my Latin Dissertation. I could enlarge it
						usefully. I could see how the public received it, or how far they were likel
						y to favour any serious measures, which should have a tendency to produce
						the abolition of the slave-trade. Upon this, then, I determined; and in the
						middle of the month of November, 1785, I began my work.'</p>
					<p>&ldquo;Such is the characteristic and ingenuous account given by Clarkson
						of his introduction<pb n="065"/>
						<milestone unit="collation" n="F 2"/> to that work to which the energies of
						his life were devoted, and in reference to which, and to the account whence
						the <orig reg="fore-going">fore-going</orig> extract has been made, one of
						the most benevolent and gifted writers of our country<ref target="n2"
						>*</ref> has justly observed, &mdash; </p>
					<p>&ldquo; `This interesting tale is related, not by a descendant, but a
						cotemporary; not by a distant spectator, but by a participator of the
						contest; and of all the many participators, by the man confessedly the most
						efficient; the man whose unparallele d labours in this work of love and
						peril, leave on the mind of a reflecting reader the sublime doubt, which of
						the two will have been the greater final gain to the moral world,
						&mdash; the removal of the evil, or the proof, thereby given, what
						mighty effect s single good men may realize by <orig reg="self-devotion"
							>self-devotion</orig> and perseverance.'</p>
					<p>&ldquo;When Mr. Clarkson went to London to publish his book, he was
						introduced to many friends of the cause of Abolition, who aided in giving it
						extensive circulation. Whilst <pb n="066"/> thus employed, he received an
						invitation, which he accepted, to visit the Rev. James Ramsay, vicar of
						Teston, in Kent, who had resided nineteen years in the island of St.
						Christopher.</p>
					<p>&ldquo;Shortly afterwards, dining one day at Sir Charles Middleton's,
						(afterwards Lord Barham,) the conversation turned upon the subject, and Mr.
						Clarkson declared that he was ready to devote himself to the cause. This
						avowal met with great encourageme nt from the company, and Sir C. Middleton,
						then Comptroller to the Navy, offered every possible assistance. The friends
						of Mr. Clarkson increased, and this encouraged him to proceed. Dr. Porteus,
						then Bishop of Chester, and Lord Scarsdale, were secured in the House of
						Lords. Mr. Bennet Langton, and Dr. Baker, who were acquainted with many
						members of both houses of parliament; the honoured Granville Sharpe, James
						and Richard Phillips, could be depended upon, as well as the entire body of
						the Society of Fri ends, to many of whom he had been introduced by Mr.
						Joseph Hancock, his fellow-townsman. <pb n="067"/> Seeking information in
						every direction, Mr. Clarkson boarded a number of vessels engaged in the
						African trade, and obtained specimens of the natural productions of the
						country. The beauty of the cloth made from African cotton, &amp;c.
						enhanced his estimat e of the skill and ingenuity of the people, and gave a
						fresh stimulus to his exertions on their behalf. He next visited a
						slave-ship; the rooms below, the gratings above, and the barricade across
						the deck, with the explanation of their uses, though the si ght of them
						filled him with sadness and horror, gave new energy to all his movements. In
						his indefatigable endeavours to collect evidence and facts, he visited most
						of the sea-ports in the kingdom, pursuing his great object with invincible
						ardour, althoug h sometimes at the peril of his life. The following
						circumstance, among others, evinces the eminent degree in which he possessed
						that untiring perseverance, on which the success of a great enterprise often
						depends.</p>
					<p>&ldquo;Clarkson and his friends had reason to fear that slaves brought
						from the interior of <pb n="068"/> Africa by certain rivers, had been
						kidnapped; and it was deemed of great importance to ascertain the fact. A
						friend one day mentioned to Mr. Clarkson, that he had, above twelve months
						before, seen a sailor who had been up these rivers. The name of the sai lor
						was unknown, and all the friend could say was, that he was going to, or
						belonged to, some man-of-war in ordinary. The evidence of this individual
						was important, and, aided by his friend Sir Charles Middleton, who gave him
						permission to board all the s hips of war in ordinary, Mr. Clarkson
						commenced his search: &mdash; beginning at Deptford, he visited
						successfully Woolwich, Chatham, Sheerness, and Portsmouth; examining in his
						progress the different persons on board upwards of two hundred and sixty
						vessel s, without discovering the object of his search. The feelings under
						which the search was continued, and the success with which it was crowned,
						he has himself thus described: &mdash; </p>
					<p>&ldquo; `Matters now began to look rather disheartening. &mdash; I
						mean as far as my grand object was concerned. There was but one <pb n="069"
						/> other port left, and this was between two and three hundred miles
						distant. I determined, however, to go to Plymouth. I had already been more
						successful in this tour, with respect to obtaining general evidence, than in
						any other of the same length; and the probability was, that as I should
						continue to move among the same kind of people, my success would be in a
						similar proportion, according to the number visited. These were great
						encouragements to me to proceed. At length I arrived at the place of my last
						hope. On my first day's expedition I boarded forty vessels, but found no one
						in these who had been on the coast of Africa in the slave-trade. One or two
						had been there in king's ships; but they never had been on shore. Things
						were now drawing near to a cl ose; and notwithstanding my success, as to
						general evidence, in this journey, my heart began to beat. I was restless
						and uneasy during the night. The next morning I felt agitated again between
						the alternate pressure of hope and fear; and in this state I e ntered my
						boat. The fifty-seventh vessel I boarded was the <pb n="070"/> Melampus
						frigate. &mdash; One person belonging to it, on examining him in the
						captain's cabin, said he had been two voyages to Africa; and I had not long
						discoursed with him, before I found, to my inexpressible joy, that he was
						the man. I found, too, that h e unravelled the question in dispute precisely
						as our inferences had determined it. He had been two expeditions up the
						river Calabar, in the canoes of the natives. In the first of these they came
						within a certain distance of a village: they then concealed themselves under
						the bushes, which hung over the water from the banks. In this position they
						remained during the day-light; but at night they went up to it armed, and
						seized all the inhabitants who had not time to make their escape. They
						obtained forty-f ive persons in this manner. In the second, they were out
						eight or nine days, when they made a similar attempt, and with nearly
						similar success. They seized men, women, and children, as they could find
						them in the huts. They then bound their arms, and drov e them before them to
						the canoes. The name of the person thus discovered<pb n="071"/> on board of
						the Melampus was Isaac Parker. On inquiring into his character, from the
						master of the division, I found it highly respectable. I found also
						afterward that he had sailed with Captain Cook, with great credit to
						himself, round the world. It was also remarkable, that my brother, on seeing
						him in London, when he went to deliver his evidence, recognized him as
						having served on board the Monarch, man-of-war, and as one of the most
						exemplary men in that ship.'</p>
					<p>&ldquo;Mr. Clarkson became, early in his career, acquainted with Mr.
						Wilberforce. At their first interview, the latter frankly stated, `that the
						subject had often employed his thoughts, and was near his heart,' and
						learning his visiter's intention to d evote himself to this benevolent
						object, congratulated him on his decision; desired to be made acquainted
						with his progress, expressing his willingness, in return, to afford every
						assistance in his power. In his intercourse with members of parliament, Mr.
						Clarkson was now frequently associated with Mr. Wilberforce, who daily <pb
							n="072"/> became more interested in the fate of Africa. The intercourse
						of the two philanthropists was mutually cordial and encouraging; Mr.
						Clarkson imparting his discoveries in the custom-houses of London,
						Liverpool, and other places; and Mr. Wilberforce communic ating the
						information he had gained from those with whom he associated.</p>
					<p>&ldquo;In 1788, Mr. Clarkson published his important work on the Impolicy
						of the <orig reg="Slave-Trade">Slave-Trade</orig>.</p>
					<p>&ldquo;In 1789, this indefatigable man went to France, by the advice of
						the Committee which he had been instrumental in forming two years before;
						Mr. Wilberforce, always solicitous for the good of the oppressed Africans,
						being of opinion that advantage might be taken of the commotions in that
						country, to induce the leading persons there to take the slave-trade into
						their consideration, and incorporate it among the abuses to be removed.
						Several of Mr. Clarkson's friends advised him to travel by another name, as
						accounts had arrived in England of the excesses which had taken place in
						Paris; but <pb n="073"/>
						<milestone unit="collation" n="G"/> to this he could not consent. On his
						arrival in that city he was speedily introduced to those who were favourable
						to the great object of his life; and at the house of M. Necker dined with
						the six deputies of colour from St. Domingo, &mdash; who had been sen t
						to France at this juncture, to demand that the free people of colour in
						their country might be placed upon an equality with the whites. Their
						communications to the English philanthropist were important and interesting;
						they hailed him as their friend, a nd were abundant in their commendations
						of his conduct.</p>
					<p>&ldquo;Copies of the Essay on the Impolicy of the Slave-Trade, translated
						into French, with engravings of the plan and section of a slave ship, were
						distributed with apparent good effect. The virtuous Abb&eacute;
						Gregoire, and several members of the Na tional Assembly, called upon Mr.
						Clarkson. The Archbishop of Aix was so struck with horror, when the plan of
						the slave ship was shown to him, that he could scarcely speak; and Mirabeau
						ordered a model of it in wood to be placed in his dining-room.</p>
					<pb n="074"/>
					<p> </p>
					<p>&ldquo;The circulation of intelligence, although contributing to make
						many friends, called forth the extraordinary exertions of enemies.
						Merchants, and others interested in the continuance of the slave-trade,
						wrote letters to the Archbishop of Aix, bes eeching him not to ruin France;
						which they said he would inevitably do, if, as the president, he were to
						grant a day for hearing the question of the abolition. Offers of money were
						made to Mirabeau, if he would totally abandon his intended motion. Books w
						ere circulated in opposition to Mr. Clarkson's; resort was had to the public
						papers, and he was denounced as a spy. The clamour raised by these efforts
						pervaded all Paris, and reached the ears of the king. M. Necker had a long
						conversation with his royal master upon it, who requested to see the Essay,
						and the specimens of African manufactures, and bestowed considerable time
						upon them, being surprised at the state of the arts there. M. Necker did not
						exhibit the section of the slave ship, thinking that as the king was
						indisposed, he might be too much affected by <pb n="075"/> it. Louis
						returned the specimens, commissioning M. Necker to convey his thanks to Mr.
						Clarkson, and express his gratification at what he had seen.</p>
					<p>&ldquo;No decided benefit appears at this time to have followed the
						visit: but though much depressed by his ill success in France, Mr. Clarkson
						continued his labours, till excess of exertion, joined to repeated and
						bitter disappointments, impaired his health, and, after a hard struggle,
						subdued a constitution, naturally strong and vigorous beyond the lot of men
						in general, but shattered by anxiety and fatigue, and the sad probability,
						often forced upon his understanding, that all might at last have bee n in
						vain. Under these feelings, he retired in 1794 to the beautiful banks of
						Ulleswater; there to seek that rest which, without peril to his life, could
						no longer be delayed.</p>
					<p>&ldquo;For seven years he had maintained a correspondence with four
						hundred persons; he annually wrote a book upon the subject of the abolition,
						and travelled more than <orig reg="thirty-five">thirty-five</orig> thousand
						miles in search of evidence, <pb n="076"/> making a great part of these
						journeys in the night. `All this time,' Mr. Clarkson writes, `my mind had
						been on the stretch; it had been bent too to this one subject; for I had not
						even leisure to attend to my own concerns. The various instances of barbari
						ty, which had come successively to my knowledge within this period, had
						vexed, harassed, and afflicted it. The wound which these had produced was
						rendered still deeper by the reiterated refusal of persons to give their
						testimony, after I had travelled hun dreds of miles in quest of them. But
						the severest stroke was that inflicted by the persecution begun and pursued
						by persons interested in the continuance of the trade, of such witnesses as
						had been examined against them; and whom, on account of their depe ndent
						situation in life, it was most easy to oppress. As I had been the means of
						bringing them forward on these occasions, they naturally came to me, as the
						author of their miseries and their ruin.<ref target="n3">*</ref> These
						different circumstances, <pb n="077"/>
						<milestone unit="collation" n="G 2"/> by acting together, had at length
						brought me into the situation just mentioned; and I was, therefore, obliged,
						though very reluctantly, to be borne out of the field where I had placed the
						great honour and glory of my life.' &rdquo;</p>
					<p>It was while thus recruiting the energies exhausted in the conflict, that
						Clarkson, and the compatriot band with which he had been associated in the
						long and arduous struggle, were crowned with victory, and received the
						grateful reward of their honoura ble toil in the final abolition of the
						slave-trade by the British nation, in 1807, the last but most glorious act
						of the Grenville administration.</p>
					<p>The preceding shows something of the career of Clarkson while labouring to
						convince the people of Great Britain of the iniquity of <hi rend="italic"
							>their own</hi> trade, a trade which they had the power to abolish.
						During all this time, Clarkson, Wil berforce, and their associates <pb
							n="078"/> avoided touching the matter of <hi rend="italic">slavery</hi>.
						They knew that one thing must be gained at a time, and they as a matter of
						expediency, avoided discussing the duty of the British nation in regard to
						the system of slavery in their colonies w hich was entirely under their own
						control. During all the time that was employed in efforts to end the
						slave-trade, slavery was existing in the control of the British people, and
						yet Clarkson and Wilberforce decided that it was right to let that matter en
						tirely alone.</p>
					<p>The following shows Clarkson's proceedings after the British nation had
						abolished the slave-trade.</p>
					<p>&ldquo;By the publication of his Thoughts on the Abolition of Slavery,
						Mr. Clarkson showed that neither he nor those connected with him, considered
						their work as accomplished, when the laws of his country clasped with its
						felons those engaged in the ne farious traffic of slaves. But the efforts of
						Mr. Clarkson were not confined to his pen. In 1818, he proceeded to Aix la
						Chapelle, at the time when the sovereigns of Europe met in congress.<pb
							n="079"/> He was received with marked attention by the Emperor of
						Russia, who listened to his statements (respecting the <hi rend="italic"
								><orig reg="slave-trade">slave-trade</orig>,</hi>) and promised to
						use his influence with the assembled monarchs, to secure t he entire
						suppression of the trade in human beings, as speedily as possible.
						Describing his interview with this amiable monarch, in which the subject of
						peace societies, as well as the abolition of the slave-trade was discussed,
						Mr. Clarkson, in a letter to a friend, thus writes:</p>
					<p>&ldquo; `It was about nine at night, when I was shown into the emperor's
						apartment. I found him alone. He met me at the door, and shaking me by the
						hand, said, `I had the pleasure of making your acquaintance at Paris.' He
						then led me some little way in to the room, and leaving me there, went
						forward and brought me a chair with his own hand, and desired me to sit
						down. This being done, he went for another chair, and bringing it very near
						to mine, placed himself close to me, so that we sat opposite to eac h other.</p>
					<pb n="080"/>
					<p> </p>
					<p>&ldquo; `I began the conversation by informing the emperor that as I
						supposed the congress of Aix la Chapelle might possibly be the last congress
						of sovereigns for settling the affairs of Europe, its connexions and
						dependencies, I had availed myself of the kind permission he gave me at
						Paris, of applying to him in behalf of the oppressed Africans, being
						unwilling to lose the last opportunity of rendering him serviceable to the
						cause.</p>
					<p>&ldquo; `The emperor replied, that he had read both my letter and my
						address to the sovereigns, and that what I asked him and the other
						sovereigns to do, was only reasonable.</p>
					<p>&ldquo; `Here I repeated the two great propositions in the address
						&mdash; the necessity of bringing the Portuguese time for continuing the
						trade (which did not expire till 1825, and then only with a condition,) down
						to the Spanish time, which expired in 1820; and secondly, when the two times
						should legally have expired, (that is, both of them in 1820,) then to make
						any farther continuance <hi rend="italic">piracy</hi>. I entreated him not
						to be deceived by any other propositions; for that Mr. Wilberfor ce, <pb
							n="081"/> myself, and others, who had devoted our time to this subject,
						were sure that no other measure would be effectual.</p>
					<p>&ldquo; `He then said very feelingly in these words, `By the providence
						of God, I and my kingdom have been saved from a merciless tyranny, (alluding
						to the invasion of Napoleon,) and I should but ill repay the blessing, if I
						were not to do every thing in my power to protect the poor Africans against
						their oppression also.'</p>
					<p>&ldquo; `The emperor then asked if he could do any thing else for our
						cause. I told him he could; and that I should be greatly obliged to him if
						he would present one of the addresses to the Emperor of Austria, and another
						to the King of Prussia, <hi rend="italic">with his own hand</hi>. I had
						brought two of them in my pocket for the purpose. He asked me why I had not
						presented them before. I replied that I had not the honour of knowing either
						of those sovereigns as I knew him; nor any of their ministers; and that I
						was not only fearful lest these addresses would not be presented to them,
						but even if they were, that <pb n="082"/> coming into their hands without
						any recommendation, they would be laid aside and not read; on the other
						hand, if he (the emperor,) would condescend to present them, I was sure they
						would be read, and that coming from him, they would come with a weight of
						influence, which would secure an attention to their contents. Upon this, the
						emperor promised, in the most kind and affable manner, that he would perform
						the task I had assigned to him.</p>
					<p>&ldquo; `We then rose from our seats to inspect some articles of
						manufacture, which I had brought with me as a present to him, and which had
						been laid upon the table. We examined the articles in leather first, one by
						one, with which he was uncommonly g ratified. He said they exhibited not
						only genius but taste. He inquired if they tanned their own leather, and
						how: I replied to his question. He said he had never seen neater work,
						either in Petersburg or in London. He then looked at a dagger and its scab
						bard or sheath. I said the sheath was intended as a further, but more
						beautiful specimen of the <pb n="083"/> work of the poor Africans in
						leather; and the blade of their dagger as a specimen of their work in iron.
						Their works in cotton next came under our notice. There was one piece which
						attracted his particular notice, and which was undoubtedly very beautiful.
						It called from him this observation, `Manchester,' said he, `I think is your
						great place for manufactures of this sort &mdash; do you think they
						could make a better piece of cotton there?' I told him I had never seen a
						better piece of workmanship of the ki nd any where. Having gone over all the
						articles, the emperor desired me to inform him whether he was to understand
						that these articles were made by the Africans in their own country, that is,
						in their native villages, or <hi rend="italic">after they had arrived in
							America,</hi> where they would have an opportunity of seeing European
						manufactures, and experienced workmen in the arts? I replied that such
						articles might be found in every African village, both on the coast and in
						the interior, and that they were samples of their own ingenuity, without any
						connexion with Europeans.<pb n="084"/> `Then,' said the emperor, `you
						astonish me &mdash; you have given me a new idea of the state of these
						poor people. I was not aware that they were so advanced in society. The
						works you have shown me are not the works of brutes &mdash; but of men,
						endued with rational and intellectual powers, and capable of being brought
						to as high a degree of proficiency as any other men. <hi rend="italic"
							>Africa ought to have a fair chance of raising her character in the
							scale of the civilized world</hi>.' I replied that it was this cruel
						traffic alone, which had prevented Africa from rising to a level with other
						nations; and that it was only astonishing to me that the natives there had,
						under its impeding influence, arrived at the perfection which had displayed
						itself in t he specimens of workmanship he had just seen.' &rdquo;</p>
					<p>Animated by a growing conviction of the righteousness of the cause in which
						he was engaged, and encouraged by the success with which past endeavours had
						been crowned, Mr. Clarkson continued his efficient co-opetion with the
						friends of Abolition, advoca ting its claims on all suitable occasions.</p>
					<pb n="085"/>
					<p> </p>
					<milestone unit="collation" n="H"/>
					<p>It would be superfluous to recount the steps by which, even before the
						venerated Wilberforce was called to his rest, this glorious event was
						realized, and Clarkson beheld the great object of his own life, and those
						with whom he had acted, triumphantly achieved. The gratitude cherished
						towards the Supreme Ruler for the boon thus secured to the oppressed
						&mdash; the satisfaction which a review of past exertions afforded, were
						heightened by the joyous sympathy of a large portion of his countrymen.<ref
							target="n1">*</ref></p>
					<p>The History of the Abolition of the <orig reg="Slave-trade"
						>Slave-trade</orig>, by Clarkson himself, presents a more detailed account
						of his own labours and of the labours of others, and whoever will read it,
						will observe the following particulars in w hich this effort differed from
						the Abolition movement in America.</p>
					<p>In the first place, it was conducted by some of the wisest and most talented
						statesmen, as well as the most pious men, in the British nation.<pb n="086"
						/> Pitt, Fox, and some of the highest of the nobility and bishops in
						England, were the firmest friends of the enterprise from the first. It was
						conducted by men who had the intellect, knowledge, discretion, and wisdom
						demanded for so great an enterprise.</p>
					<p>Secondly. It was conducted slowly, peaceably, and by eminently judicious
						influences.</p>
					<p>Thirdly. It included, to the full extent, the doctrine of expediency
						denounced by Abolitionists.</p>
					<p>One of the first decisions of the &ldquo;Committee for the Abolition of
						the Slave-trade,&rdquo; which conducted all Abolition movements, was
						that <hi rend="italic">slavery</hi> should not be attacked, but only the <hi
							rend="italic">slave-trade;</hi> and Clarkson expressly says, that it was
						owing to this, more than to any other measure, that success was gained.</p>
					<p>Fourthly. Good men were not divided, and thrown into contending parties.
						&mdash; The opponents to the measure, were only those who were
						personally interested in the perpetuation of slavery or the slave-trade.</p>
					<p>Fifthly. This effort was one to convince men of their <hi rend="italic"
						>own</hi> obligations, and not an effort <pb n="087"/> to arouse public
						sentiment against the sinful practices of another community over which they
						had no control.</p>
					<p>I would now ask, why could not some southern gentleman, such for example as
						Mr. Birney, whose manners, education, character, and habits give him
						abundant facilities, have acted the part of Clarkson, and quietly have gone
						to work at the South, collectin g facts, exhibiting the impolicy and the
						evils, to good men at the South, by the fire-side of the planter, the known
						home of hospitality and chivalry. Why could he not have commenced with the
						most vulnerable point, the <hi rend="italic">domestic slave-tr ade,</hi>
						leaving emancipation for a future and more favourable period? What right has
						any one to say that there was no southern Wilberforce that would have
						arisen, no southern Grant, Macaulay or Sharpe, who, like the English
						philanthropists, would have s tood the fierce beating of angry billows, and
						by patience, kindness, arguments, facts, eloquence, and Christian love,
						convinced the skeptical, enlightened the ignorant, excited the benevolent,
						and finally have carried the <pb n="088"/> day at the South, by the same
						means and measures, as secured the event in England? All experience is in
						favour of the method which the Abolitionists have rejected, because it
						involves <hi rend="italic">danger to themselves</hi>. The cause they have
						selec ted is one that stands alone. &mdash; No case parallel on earth
						can be brought to sustain it, with probabilities of good results. No
						instance can be found, where exciting the public sentiment of one community
						against evil practices in another, was ever mad e the means of eradicating
						those evils. All the laws of mind, all the records of experience, go against
						the measures that Abolitionists have taken, and in favour of the one they
						have rejected. And when we look still farther ahead, at results which time
						is to develope, how stand the probabilities, when we, in judging, again
						take, as data, the laws of mind and the records of experience?</p>
					<p>What are the plans, hopes, and expectations of Abolitionists, in reference to
						their measures? They are now labouring to make the North a great Abolition
						Society, &mdash; to convince every northern man that slavery at the <pb
							n="089"/>
						<milestone unit="collation" n="H 2"/> South is a great sin, and that it
						ought immediately to cease. Suppose they accomplish this to the extent they
						hope, &mdash; so far as we have seen, the more the North is convinced,
						the more firmly the South rejects the light, and turns from the truth.</p>
					<p>While Abolition Societies did not exist, men could talk and write, at the
						South, against the evils of slavery, and northern men had free access and
						liberty of speech, both at the South and at the North. But now all is
						changed. Every avenue of approach to the South is shut. No paper, pamphlet,
						or preacher, that touches on that topic, is admitted in their bounds. Their
						own citizens, that once laboured and remonstrated, are silenced; their own
						clergy, under the influence of the exasperated feelings of the ir people,
						and their own sympathy and sense of wrong, either entirely hold their peace,
						or become the defenders of a system they once lamented, and attempted to
						bring to an end. This is the record of experience as to the tendencies of
						Abolitionism, as thu s far developed. The South are now in just that state
							<pb n="090"/> of high exasperation, at the sense of wanton injury and
						impertinent interference, which makes the influence of truth and reason most
						useless and powerless.</p>
					<p>But suppose the Abolitionists succeed, not only in making northern men
						Abolitionists, but also in sending a portion of light into the South, such
						as to form a body of Abolitionists there also What is the thing that is to
						be done to end slavery at the S outh? It is to <hi rend="italic">alter the
							laws,</hi> and to do this, a small minority must begin a long, bitter,
						terrible conflict with a powerful and exasperated majority. Now if, as the
						Abolitionists hope, there will arise at the South such a minority , it will
						doubtless consist of men of religious and benevolent feelings, &mdash;
						men of that humane, and generous, and upright spirit, that most keenly feel
						the injuries inflicted on their fellow men. Suppose such a band of men begin
						their efforts, sustain ed by the northern Abolitionists, already so odious.
						How will the exasperated majority act, according to the known laws of mind
						and of experience? Instead of lessening the evils of slavery, they will
						increase them. The <pb n="091"/> more they are goaded by a sense of
						aggressive wrong without, or by fears of dangers within, the more they will
						restrain their slaves, and diminish their liberty, and increase their
						disabilities. They will make laws so unjust and oppressive, not only to sl
						aves, but to their Abolitionist advocates, that by degrees such men will
						withdraw from their bounds. Laws will be made expressly to harass them, and
						to render them so uncomfortable that they must withdraw. Then gradually the
						righteous will flee from the d evoted city. Then the numerical proportion of
						whites will decrease, and the cruelty and unrestrained wickedness of the
						system will increase, till a period will come when the physical power will
						be so much with the blacks, their sense of suffering so incre ased, that the
						volcano will burst, &mdash; insurrection and servile wars will begin.
						Oh, the countless horrors of such a day! And will the South stand alone in
						that burning hour? When she sends forth the wailing of her agonies, shall
						not the North and the W est hear, and lift up together the voice of wo? Will
						not fathers hear the cries <pb n="092"/> of children, and brothers the cries
						of sisters? Will the terrors of insurrection sweep over the South, and no
						Northern and Western blood be shed? Will the slaves be cut down, in such a
						strife, when they raise the same p&aelig;an song of liberty and human
						rights, that was the watchword of our redemption from far less dreadful
						tyranny, and which is now thrilling the nations and shaking monarchs on
						their thrones &mdash; will this be heard, and none of the sons of
						liberty be found to appear on their side? This is no picture of fancied
						dangers, which are not near. The day has come, when already the feelings are
						so excited on both sides, that I have heard intelligent men, good men,
						benevolent and pious men, in moments of excitement, declare themselves ready
						to ta ke up the sword &mdash; some for the defence of the master, some
						for the protection and right of the slave. It is my full conviction, that if
						insurrection does burst forth, and there be the least prospect of success to
						the cause of the slave, there will be men from the North and West, standing
							<pb n="093"/> breast to breast, with murderous weapons, in opposing
						ranks.</p>
					<p>Such apprehensions many would regard as needless, and exclaim against such
						melancholy predictions. But in a case where the whole point of duty and
						expediency turns upon the probabilities as to results, those probabilities
						ought to be the chief subjects of inquiry. True, no one has a right to say
						with confidence what will or what will not be; and it has often amazed and
						disturbed my mind to perceive how men, with so small a field of vision,
						&mdash; with so little data for judging, &mdash; with so few years,
						and so little experience, can pronounce concerning the results of measures
						bearing upon the complicated relations and duties of millions, and in a case
						where the wisest and best are dismayed and baffled. It sometimes has seemed
						to me that the prescience of Deity alone should dare to take such positions
						as are both carelessly assumed, and pertinaciously defended, by the
						advocates of Abolitionism.</p>
					<p>But if we are to judge of the wisdom or folly of any measures on this
						subject, it must <pb n="094"/> be with reference to future results. One
						course of measures, it is claimed, tends to perpetuate slavery, or to end it
						by scenes of terror and bloodshed. Another course tends to bring it to an
						end sooner, and by safe and peaceful influences. And the whole discussion of
						duty rests on these probabilities. But where do the laws of mind and
						experience oppose the terrific tendencies of Abolitionism that have been
						portrayed? Are not the minds of men thrown into a ferment, and excited by
						those passions which blin d the reason, and warp the moral sense? Is not the
						South in a state of high exasperation against Abolitionists? Does she not
						regard them as enemies, as reckless madmen, as impertinent intermeddlers?
						Will the increase of their numbers tend to allay this ex asperation? Will
						the appearance of a similar body in their own boundaries have any tendency
						to soothe? Will it not still more alarm and exasperate? If a movement of a
						minority of such men attempt to alter the laws, are not the probabilities
						strong that st ill more unjust and oppressive measures will be adopted?
						&mdash; <pb n="095"/> measures that will tend to increase the hardships
						of the slave, and to drive out of the community all humane, conscientious
						and pious men? As the evils and dangers increase, will not the alarm
						constantly diminish the proportion of whites, and make it more and more
						needful to increase such disabilities and restraints as will chafe and
						inflame the blacks? When this point is reached, will the blacks, knowing, as
						they will know, the sympathies of their Abolition friends, refrain from
						exerting their physical p ower? <hi rend="italic">The Southampton
							insurrection occurred with far less chance of sympathy and success</hi>.</p>
					<p>If that most horrible of all scourges, a servile war, breaks forth, will the
						slaughter of fathers, sons, infants, and of aged, &mdash; will the cries
						of wives, daughters, sisters, and kindred, suffering barbarities worse than
						death, bring no fathers, bro thers, and friends to their aid, from the North
						and West?</p>
					<p>And if the sympathies and indignation of freemen can already look such an
						event in the face, and feel that it would be the slave, rather than the
						master, whom they would <pb n="096"/> defend, what will be the probability,
						after a few years' chafing shall have driven away the most christian and
						humane from scenes of cruelty and inhumanity, which they could neither
						alleviate nor redress? I should like to see any data of past experience,
						that will show that these results are not more probable than that the South
						will, by the system of means now urged upon her, finally be convinced of her
						sins, and voluntarily bring the system of slavery to an end. I claim not
						that the predictions I presen t will be fulfilled. I only say, that if
						Abolitionists go on as they propose, such results are <hi rend="italic"
						>more</hi> probable than those they hope to attain.</p>
					<p>I have not here alluded to the probabilities of the severing of the Union by
						the present mode of agitating the question. This may be one of the results,
						and, if so, what are the probabilities for a Southern republic, that has
						torn itself off for the pu rpose of excluding foreign interference, and for
						the purpose of perpetuating slavery? Can any Abolitionist suppose that, in
						such a state of things, the great cause of emancipation is as likely to <pb
							n="097"/>
						<milestone unit="collation" n="I"/> progress favourably, as it was when we
						were one nation, and mingling on those fraternal terms that existed before
						the Abolition movement began?</p>
					<p>The preceding are some of the reasons which, on the general view, I would
						present as opposed to the proposal of forming Abolition Societies; and they
						apply equally to either sex. There are some others which seem to oppose
						peculiar objections to the act ion of females in the way you would urge.</p>
					<p>To appreciate more fully these objections, it will be necessary to recur to
						some general views in relation to the place woman is appointed to fill by
						the dispensations of heaven.</p>
					<p>It has of late become quite fashionable in all benevolent efforts, to shower
						upon our sex an abundance of compliments, not only see what they have done,
						but also for what they can do; and so injudicious and so frequent, are these
						oblations, that while I feel an increasing respect for my countrywomen, that
						their good sense has not been decoyed by these appeals to their vanity and
						ambition, I cannot but apprehend that there is some need <pb n="098"/> of
						inquiry as to the just bounds of female influence, and the times, places,
						and manner in which it can be appropriately exerted.</p>
					<p>It is the grand feature of the Divine economy, that there should be different
						stations of superiority and subordination, and it is impossible to
						annihilate this beneficent and immutable law. On its first entrance into
						life, the child is a dependent on parental love, and of necessity takes a
						place of subordination and obedience. As he advances in life these new
						relations of superiority and subordination multiply. The teacher must be the
						superior in station, the pupil a subordinate. The master of a famil y the
						superior, the domestic a subordinate &mdash; the ruler a superior, the
						subject a subordinate. Nor do these relations at all depend upon superiority
						either in intellectual or moral worth. However weak the parents, or
						intelligent the child, there is no reference to this, in the immutable law.
						However incompetent the teacher, or superior the pupil, no alteration of
						station can be allowed. However unworthy the master or worthy the servant,
						while their mutual relations<pb n="099"/> continue, no change in station as
						to subordination can be allowed. In fulfilling the duties of these
						relations, true dignity consists in conforming to all those relations that
						demand subordination, with propriety and cheerfulness. When does a man,
						howeve r high his character or station, appear more interesting or dignified
						than when yielding reverence and deferential attentions to an aged parent,
						however weak and infirm? And the pupil, the servant, or the subject, all
						equally sustain their own claims to s elf-respect, and to the esteem of
						others, by equally sustaining the appropriate relations and duties of
						subordination. In this arrangement of the duties of life, Heaven has
						appointed to one sex the superior, and to the other the subordinate station,
						and t his without any reference to the character or conduct of either. It is
						therefore as much for the dignity as it is for the interest of females, in
						all respects to conform to the duties of this relation. And it is as much a
						duty as it is for the child to fu lfil similar relations to parents, or
						subjects to rulers. But while woman holds a subordinate<pb n="100"/>
						relation in society to the other sex, it is not because it was designed that
						her duties or her influence should be any the less important, or
						all-pervading. But it was designed that the mode of gaining influence and of
						exercising power should be altogeth er different and peculiar.</p>
					<p>It is Christianity that has given to woman her true place in society. And it
						is the peculiar trait of Christianity alone that can sustain her therein.
						&ldquo;Peace on earth and good will to men&rdquo; is the character
						of all the rights and privileges, the influence, and the power of woman. A
						man may act on society by the collision of intellect, in public debate; he
						may urge his measures by a sense of shame, by fear and by personal interest;
						he may coerce by the combination of public sentiment; he may d rive by
						physical force, and he does not outstep the boundaries of his sphere. But
						all the power, and all the conquests that are lawful to woman, are those
						only which appeal to the kindly, generous, peaceful and benevolent
						principles.</p>
					<p>Woman is to win every thing by peace <pb n="101"/>
						<milestone unit="collation" n="I 2"/> and love; by making herself so much
						respected, esteemed and loved, that to yield to her opinions and to gratify
						her wishes, will be the free-will offering of the heart. But this is to be
						all accomplished in the domestic and social circle. There let every woman
						become so cultivated and refined in intellect, that her taste and judgment
						will be respected; so benevolent in feeling and action; that her motives
						will be reverenced; &mdash; so unassuming and unambitious, that
						collision and competition will be banis hed; &mdash; so
						&ldquo;gentle and easy to be entreated,&rdquo; as that every heart
						will repose in her presence; then, the fathers, the husbands, and the sons,
						will find an influence thrown around them, to which they will yield not only
						willingly but proudly . A man is never ashamed to own such influences, but
						feels dignified and ennobled in acknowledging them. But the moment woman
						begins to feel the promptings of ambition, or the thirst for power, her
						&aelig;gis of defence is gone. All the sacred protection of religion,
						all the generous promptings of chivalry, all the poetry of romantic
						gallantry, depend upon woman's retaining<pb n="102"/> her place as dependent
						and defenceless, and making no claims, and maintaining no right but what are
						the gifts of honour, rectitude and love.</p>
					<p>A woman may seek the aid of co-operation and combination among her own sex,
						to assist her in her appropriate offices of piety, charity, maternal and
						domestic duty; but whatever, in any measure, throws a woman into the
						attitude of a combatant, either fo r herself or others &mdash; whatever
						binds her in a party conflict &mdash; whatever obliges her in any way to
						exert coercive influences, throws her out of her appropriate sphere. If
						these general principles are correct, they are entirely opposed to the plan
						o f arraying females in any Abolition movement; because it enlists them in
						an effort to coerce the South by the public sentiment of the North; because
						it brings them forward as partisans in a conflict that has been begun and
						carried forward by measures that are any thing rather than peaceful in their
						tendencies; because it draws them forth from their appropriate retirement,
						to expose themselves<pb n="103"/> to the ungoverned violence of mobs, and to
						sneers and ridicule in public places; because it leads them into the arena
						of political collision, not as peaceful mediators to hush the opposing
						elements, but as combatants to cheer up and carry forward the mea sures of
						strife.</p>
					<p>If it is asked, &ldquo;May not woman appropriately come forward as a
						suppliant for a portion of her sex who are bound in cruel
						bondage?&rdquo; It is replied, that, the rectitude and propriety of any
						such measure, depend entirely on its probable results . If petitions from
						females will operate to exasperate; if they will be deemed obtrusive,
						indecorous, and unwise, by those to whom they are addressed; if they will
						increase, rather than diminish the evil which it is wished to remove; if
						they will be the o pening wedge, that will tend eventually to bring females
						as petitioners and partisans into every political measure that may tend to
						injure and oppress their sex, in various parts of the nation, and under the
						various public measures that may hereafter <pb n="104"/> be enforced, then
						it is neither appropriate nor wise, nor right, for a woman to petition for
						the relief of oppressed females.</p>
					<p>The case of Queen Esther is one often appealed to as a precedent. When a
						woman is placed in similar circumstances, where death to herself and all her
						nation is one alternative, and there is nothing worse to fear, but something
						to hope as the other alte rnative, then she may safely follow such an
						example. But when a woman is asked to join an Abolition Society, or to put
						her name to a petition to congress, for the purpose of contributing her
						measure of influence to keep up agitation in congress, to promot e the
						excitement of the North against the iniquities of the South, to coerce the
						South by fear, shame, anger, and a sense of odium to do what she has
						determined not to do, the case of Queen Esther is not at all to be regarded
						as a suitable example for imi tation.</p>
					<p>In this country, petitions to congress, in reference to the official duties
						of legislators, seem, <hi rend="small-caps">in all cases,</hi> to fall
						entirely without the sphere of female duty. Men are the <pb n="105"/> proper
						persons to make appeals to the rulers whom they appoint, and if their female
						friends, by arguments and persuasions, can induce them to petition, all the
						good that can be done by such measures will be secured. But if females
						cannot influence their n earest friends, to urge forward a public measure in
						this way, they surely are out of their place, in attempting to do it
						themselves.</p>
					<p>There are some other considerations, which should make the American females
						peculiarly sensitive in reference to any measure, which should even <hi
							rend="italic">seem</hi> to draw them from their appropriate relations in
						society.</p>
					<p>It is allowed by all reflecting minds, that the safety and happiness of this
						nation depends upon having the <hi rend="italic">children</hi> educated, and
						not only intellectually, but morally and religiously. There are now nearly
						two millions of childr en and adults in this country who cannot read, and
						who have no schools of any kind. To give only a small supply of teachers to
						these destitute children, who are generally where the population is sparse,
						will <pb n="106"/> demand <hi rend="italic">thirty thousand teachers;</hi>
						and <hi rend="italic">six thousand</hi> more will be needed every year,
						barely to meet the increase of juvenile population. But if we allow that we
						need not reach this point, in order to save ourse lves from that destruction
						which awaits a people, when governed by an ignorant and unprincipled
						democracy; if we can weather the storms of democratic liberty with only
							<orig reg="one-third">one-third</orig> of our ignorant children properly
						educated, stil l we need <hi rend="italic">ten thousand</hi> teachers at
						this moment, and an addition of <hi rend="italic">two thousand every
						year</hi>. Where is this army of teachers to be found? Is it at all probable
						that the other sex will afford even a moderate po rtion of this supply? The
						field for enterprise and excitement in the political arena, in the arts, the
						sciences, the liberal professions, in agriculture, manufactures, and
						commerce, is opening with such temptations, as never yet bore upon the mind
						of any nation. Will men turn aside from these high and exciting objects to
						become the patient labourers in the school-room, and for only the small
						pittance that rewards such toil? <pb n="107"/> No, they will not do it. Men
						will be educators in the college, in the high school, in some of the most
						honourable and lucrative common schools, but the <hi rend="italic"
						>children,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">little children</hi> of this nation
						must, to a wide extent, be taught by females, or remain untaught. The
						drudgery of education, as it is now too generally regarded, in this country,
						will be given to the female hand. And as the value of education rises in the
						public mind, and the importance of a teac her's office is more highly
						estimated, women will more and more be furnished with those intellectual
						advantages which they need to fit them for such duties.</p>
					<p>The result will be, that America will be distinguished above all other
						nations, for <orig reg="well-educated">well-educated</orig> females, and for
						the influence they will exert on the general interests of society. But if
						females, as they approach the other sex, in intellectual elevation, begin to
						claim, or to exercise in any manner, the peculiar prerogatives of that sex,
						education will prove a doubtful and dangerous blessing. But this will never
						be the result. For the more intelligent<pb n="108"/> a woman becomes, the
						more she can appreciate the wisdom of that ordinance that appointed her
						subordinate station, and the more her taste will conform to the graceful and
						dignified retirement and submission it involves.</p>
					<p>An ignorant, a narrow-minded, or a stupid woman, cannot feel nor understand
						the rationality, the propriety, or the beauty of this relation; and she it
						is, that will be most likely to carry her measures by tormenting, when she
						cannot please, or by petul ent complaints or obtrusive interference, in
						matters which are out of her sphere, and which she cannot comprehend.</p>
					<p>And experience testifies to this result. By the concession of all travellers,
						American females are distinguished above all others for their general
						intelligence, and yet they are complimented for their retiring modesty,
						virtue, and domestic faithfulnes s, while the other sex is as much
						distinguished for their respectful kindness and attentive gallantry. There
						is no other country where females have so much public respect and kindness
						accorded to them <pb n="109"/>
						<milestone unit="collation" n="K"/> as in America, by the concession of all
						travellers. And it will ever be so, while intellectual culture in the female
						mind, is combined with the spirit of that religion which so strongly
						enforces the appropriate duties of a woman's sphere.</p>
					<p>But it may be asked, is there nothing to be done to bring this national sin
						of slavery to an end? Must the internal slave-trade, a trade now ranked as
						piracy among all civilized nations, still prosper in our bounds? Must the
						very seat of our government stand as one of the chief slave-markets of the
						land; and must not Christian females open their lips, nor lift a finger, to
						bring such a shame and sin to an end?</p>
					<p>To this it may be replied, that Christian females may, and can say and do
						much to bring these evils to an end; and the present is a time and an
						occasion when it seems most desirable that they should know, and appreciate,
						and <hi rend="italic">exercise </hi> the power which they do possess for so
						desirable an end.</p>
					<p>And in pointing out the methods of exerting female influence for this object,
						I am <pb n="110"/> inspired with great confidence, from the conviction that
						what will be suggested, is that which none will oppose, but all will allow
						to be not only practicable, but safe, suitable, and Christian.</p>
					<p>To appreciate these suggestions, however, it is needful previously to
						consider some particulars that exhibit the spirit of the age and the
						tendencies of our peculiar form of government.</p>
					<p>The prominent principle, now in development, as indicating the spirit of the
						age, is the perfect right of all men to entire freedom of opinion. By this I
						do not mean that men are coming to think that &ldquo;it is no matter
						what a man believes, if he is only honest and sincere,&rdquo; or that
						they are growing any more lenient towards their <orig reg="fellow-men"
							>fellow-men</orig>, for the evil consequences they bring on themselves
						or on others for believing wrong.</p>
					<p>But they are coming to adopt the maxim, that no man shall be forced by pains
						and penalties to adopt the opinions of other minds, but that every man shall
						be free to form his <pb n="111"/> own opinions, and to propagate them by all
						lawful means.</p>
					<p>At the same time another right is claimed, which is of necessity involved in
						the preceding, &mdash; the right to oppose, by all lawful means, the
						opinions and the practices of others, when they are deemed pernicious either
						to individuals or to the commun ity, <hi rend="italic">Facts, arguments</hi>
						and <hi rend="italic">persuasions</hi> are, by all, conceded to be lawful
						means to employ in propagating our own views, and in opposing the opinions
						and practices of others.</p>
					<p>These fundamental principles of liberty have in all past ages been restrained
						by coercive influences, either of civil or of ecclesiastical power. But in
						this nation, all such coercive influences, both of church and state, have
						ceased. Every man may thi nk what he pleases about government, or religion,
						or any thing else; he may propagate his opinions, he may contrevert opposite
						opinions, and no magistrate or ecclesiastic can in any legal way restrain or
						punish.</p>
					<p>But the form of our government is such, that every measure that bears upon
						the public <pb n="112"/> or private interest of every citizen, is decided by
							<hi rend="italic">public sentiment</hi>. All laws and regulations in
						civil, or religious, or social concerns, are decided by the <hi
							rend="italic">majority of votes</hi>. And the present is a time when
						every doctrine, every principle, and every practice which influences the
						happiness of man, either in this, or in a future life, is under discussion.
						The whole nation is thrown into parties about almost every possible
						question, and every man is stimulated in his efforts to promote his own
						plans by the conviction that success depends entirely upon bringing his
						fellow citizens to think as he does. Hence every man is fierce in
						maintaining his own right of free discussion, his own right to propagate his
						opini ons, and his own right to oppose, by all lawful means, the opinions
						that conflict with his own.</p>
					<p>But the difficulty is, that a right which all men claim for themselves, with
						the most sensitive and pertinacious inflexibility, they have not yet learned
						to accord to their fellow men, in cases where their own interests are
						involved. Every man is sayin g, &ldquo;let me have <pb n="113"/>
						<milestone unit="collation" n="K 2"/> full liberty to propagate my opinions,
						and to oppose all that I deem wrong and injurious, but let no man take this
						liberty with my opinions and practices. Every man may believe what he
						pleases, and propagate what he pleases, provided he takes care not to attack
						any thing which belongs to me.&rdquo;</p>
					<p>And how do men exert themselves to restrain this corresponding right of their
						fellow men? Not by going to the magistrate to inform, or to the spiritual
						despot to obtain ecclesiastical penalties, but he resorts to methods, which,
						if successful, are in e ffect the most severe pains and penalties that can
						restrain freedom of opinion.</p>
					<p>What is dearer to a man than <hi rend="italic">his character,</hi> involving
						as it does, the esteem, respect and affection of friends, neighbours and
						society, with all the confidence, honour, trust and emolument that flow from
						general esteem? How sens itive is every man to any thing that depreciates
						his intellectual character! What torture, to be ridiculed or pitied for such
						deficiencies! How cruel the suffering, when his moral delinquencies are held
						up <pb n="114"/> to public scorn and reprehension! Confiscation, stripes,
						chains, and even death itself, are often less dreaded.</p>
					<p>It is this method of punishment to which men resort, to deter their
						fellow-men from exercising those rights of liberty which they so tenaciously
						claim for themselves. Examine now the methods adopted by almost all who are
						engaged in the various conflict s of opinion in this nation, and you will
						find that there are certain measures which combatants almost invariably
						employ.</p>
					<p>They either attack the intellectual character of opponents, or they labour to
						make them appear narrow-minded, illiberal and bigoted, or they impeach their
						honesty and veracity, or they stigmatize their motives as mean, selfish,
						ambitious, or in some ot her respect unworthy and degrading. Instead of
						truth, and evidence, and argument, personal depreciation, sneers,
						insinuations, or open abuse, are the weapons employed. This method of
						resisting freedom of opinions, by pains and penalties, arises in part fr om
						the natural selfishness of man, and in part from want of clear <pb n="115"/>
						distinctions as to the rights and duties involved in freedom of opinion and
						freedom of speech.</p>
					<p>The great fundamental principle that makes this matter clear, is this, that a
						broad and invariable distinction should ever be preserved between the <hi
							rend="italic">opinions</hi> and <hi rend="italic">practices</hi> that
						are discussed, and the <hi rend="italic">advocates</hi> of these opinions
						and practices.</p>
					<p>It is a sacred and imperious duty, that rests on every human being, to exert
						all his influence in opposing every thing that he believes is dangerous and
						wrong, and in sustaining all that he believes is safe and right. And in
						doing this, no compromise is to be made, in order to shield country, party,
						friends, or even self, from any just censure. Every man is bound by duty to
						God and to his country, to lay his finger on every false principle, or
						injurious practice, and boldly say, &ldquo;this is wrong &mdash;
						this is dangerous &mdash; this I will oppose with all my influence,
						whoever it may be that advocates or practises it.&rdquo; And every man
						is bound to use his efforts to turn public sentiment against all that he
						believes <pb n="116"/> to be wrong and injurious, either in regard to this
						life, or to the future world. And every man deserves to be respected and
						applauded, just in proportion as he fearlessly and impartially, and in a <hi
							rend="italic">proper spirit, time</hi> and <hi rend="italic">manner,
						</hi> fulfils this duty.</p>
					<p>The doctrine, just now alluded to, that it is &ldquo;no matter what a man
						believes, if he is only honest and sincere,&rdquo; is as pernicious, as
						it is contrary to religion and to common sense. It is as absurd, and as
						impracticable, as it would be to urge on the mariner the maxim,
						&ldquo;no matter which way you believe to be north, if you only steer
						aright.&rdquo; A man's character, feelings, and conduct, all depend upon
						his opinions. If a man can reason himself into the belief that it is right
						to take the property of others and to deceive by false statements, he will
						probably prove a thief and a liar. It is of the greatest concern, therefore,
						to every man, that his fellow-men should <hi rend="italic">believe
						right,</hi> and one of his most sacred duties is to use all his influence to
						promote correct opinions.</p>
					<p>But the performance of this duty, does by no means involve the necessity of
						attacking <pb n="117"/> the character or motives of the <hi rend="italic"
							>advocates</hi> of false opinions, or of holding them up, individually,
						to public odium.</p>
					<p>Erroneous opinions are sometimes the consequence of unavoidable ignorance, or
						of mental imbecility, or of a weak and erring judgment, or of false
						testimony from others, which cannot be rectified. In such cases, the
						advocates of false opinions are to be pitied rather than blamed; and while
						the opinions and their tendencies may be publicly exposed, the men may be
						objects of affection and kindness.</p>
					<p>In other cases, erroneous opinions spring from criminal indifference, from
						prejudice, from indolence, from pride, from evil passions, or from selfish
						interest. In all such cases, men deserve blame for their pernicious
						opinions, and the evils which flow from them.</p>
					<p>But, it may be asked, how are men to decide, when their fellow-men are guilty
						for holding wrong opinions; when they deserve blame, and when they are to be
						regarded only with pity and commiseration by those who believe them to be in
						the wrong? Here, surely, <pb n="118"/> is a place where some correct
						principle is greatly needed.</p>
					<p>Is every man to sit in judgment upon his fellow-man, and decide what are his
						intellectual capacities, and what the measure of his judgment? Is every man
						to take the office of the Searcher of Hearts, to try the feelings and
						motives of his fellow-man? Is that most difficult of all analysis, the
						estimating of the feelings, purposes, and motives, which every man, who
						examines his own secret thoughts, finds to be so complex, so recondite, so
						intricate; is this to be the basis, not only of individual opinion, but of
						public reward and censure? Is every man to constitute himself a judge of the
						amount of time and interest given to the proper investigation of truth by
						his fellow-man? Surely, this cannot be a correct principle.</p>
					<p>Though there may be single cases in which we can know that our fellow-men are
						weak in intellect, or erring in judgment, or perverse in feeling, or misled
						by passion, or biased by selfish interest, as a general fact we <pb n="119"
						/> are not competent to decide these matters, in regard to those who differ
						from us in opinion.</p>
					<p>For this reason it is manifestly wrong and irrelevant, when discussing
						questions of duty or expediency, to bring before the public the character or
						the motives of the individual advocates of opinions.</p>
					<p>But, it may be urged, how can the evil tendencies of opinions or of practices
						be investigated, without involving a consideration of the character and
						conduct of those who advocate them? To this it may be replied, that the
						tendencies of opinions and practices can never be ascertained by discussing
						individual character. It is <hi rend="italic">classes</hi> of persons, or
						large <hi rend="italic">communities,</hi> embracing persons of all varieties
						of character and circumstances, that are the only proper subjects of
						investigation for this object. For example, a community of Catholics, and a
						community of Protestants, may be compared, for the purpose of learning the
						moral tendencies of their different opinions. Scotland and New England,
						where the principles opposite to Catholicism have most prevailed, may
						properly be compared with <pb n="120"/> Spain and Italy, where the Catholic
						system has been most fairly tried. But to select certain individuals who are
						defenders of these two different systems, as examples to illustrate their
						tendencies, would be as improper as it would be to select a kernel of grain
						to prove the good or bad character of a whole crop.</p>
					<p>To illustrate by a more particular example. The doctrines of the Atheist
						school are now under discussion, and Robert Owen and Fanny Wright have been
						their prominent advocates.</p>
					<p>In agreement with the above principles, it is a right, and the duty of every
						man who has any influence and opportunity, to show the absurdity of their
						doctrines, the weakness of their arguments, and the fatal tendencies of
						their opinions. It is right to show that the <hi rend="italic"
						>practical</hi> adoption of their principles indicates a want of common
						sense, just as sowing the ocean with grain and expecting a crop would
						indicate the same deficiency. If the advocates of these doctrines carry out
						their principles into practice, in any such way as to <pb n="121"/>
						<milestone unit="collation" n="L"/> offend the taste, or infringe on the
						rights of others, it is proper to express disgust and disapprobation. If the
						female advocate chooses to come upon a stage, and expose her person, dress,
						and elocution to public criticism, it is right to express disgust at
						whatever is offensive and indecorous, as it is to criticise the book of an
						author, or the dancing of an actress, or any thing else that is presented to
						public observation. And it is right to make all these things appear as
						odious and reprehensible to others as they do to ourselves.</p>
					<p>But what is the private character of Robert Owen or Fanny Wright? Whether
						they are ignorant or weak in intellect; whether they have properly examined
						the sources of truth; how much they have been biased by pride, passion, or
						vice, in adopting their opinions; whether they are honest and sincere in
						their belief; whether they are selfish or benevolent in their aims, are not
						matters which in any way pertain to the discussion. They are questions about
						which none are qualified to judge, except those in close and intimate
							communion<pb n="122"/> with them. We may inquire with propriety as to
						the character of a <hi rend="italic">community </hi> of Atheists, or of a
						community where such sentiments extensively prevail, as compared with a
						community of opposite sentiments. But the private character, feelings, and
						motives of the individual advocates of these doctrines, are not proper
						subjects of investigation in any public discussion.</p>
					<p>If, then, it be true, that attacks on the character and motives of the
						advocates of opinions are entirely irrelevant and not at all necessary for
						the discovery of truth; if injury inflicted on character is the most severe
						penalty that can be employed to restrain freedom of opinions and freedom of
						speech, what are we to say of the state of things in this nation?</p>
					<p>Where is there a party which does not in effect say to every man,
						&ldquo;if you dare to oppose the principles or practices we sustain, you
						shall be punished with personal odium?&rdquo; which does not say to
						every member of the party, &ldquo;uphold your party, right or wrong;
						oppose all that is adverse to your party, right or wrong, or else suffer the
						penalty of having <pb n="123"/> your motives, character, and conduct,
						impeached?&rdquo;</p>
					<p>Look first at the political arena. Where is the advocate of any measure that
						does not suffer sneers, ridicule, contempt, and all that tends to depreciate
						character in public estimation? Where is the partisan that is not attacked,
						as either weak in intellect, or dishonest in principle, or selfish in
						motives? And where is the man who is linked with any political party, that
						dares to stand up fearlessly and defend what is good in opposers, and
						reprove what is wrong in his own party?</p>
					<p>Look into the religious world. There, even those who take their party name
						from their professed liberality, are saying, &ldquo;whoever shall adopt
						principles that exclude us from the Christian church, and our clergy from
						the pulpit, shall be held up either as intellectually degraded, or as
						narrow-minded and bigoted, or as ambitious, partisan and persecuting in
						spirit. No man shall believe a creed that excludes us from the pale of
						Christianity, under penalty of all the odium we can inflict.&rdquo;</p>
					<pb n="124"/>
					<p> </p>
					<p>So in the Catholic controversy. Catholics and their friends practically
						declare war against all free discussion on this point. The decree has gone
						forth, that &ldquo;no man shall appear for the purpose of proving that
						Catholicism is contrary to Scripture, or immoral and anti-republican in
						tendency, under penalty of being denounced as a dupe, or a hypocrite, or a
						persecutor, or a narrow-minded and prejudiced bigot.</p>
					<p>On the contrary, those who attack what is called liberal Christianity, or who
						aim to oppose the progress of Catholicism, how often do they exhibit a
						severe and uncharitable spirit towards the individuals whose opinions they
						controvert. Instead of loving the men, and rendering to them all the offices
						of Christian kindness, and according to them all due credit for whatever is
						desirable in character and conduct, how often do opposers seem to feel, that
						it will not answer to allow that there is any thing good, either in the
						system or in those who have adopted it. &ldquo;Every thing about my
						party is right, and every thing in the opposing party is wrong,&rdquo;
						seems to be <pb n="125"/>
						<milestone unit="collation" n="L 2"/> the universal maxim of the times. And
						it is the remark of some of the most intelligent foreign travellers among
						us, and of our own citizens who go abroad, that there is no country to be
						found, where freedom of opinion, and freedom of speech is more really
						influenced and controlled by the fear of pains and penalties, than in this
						land of boasted freedom. In other nations, the control is exercised by
						government, in respect to a very few matters; in this country it is
						party-spirit that rules with an iron rod, and shakes its scorpion whips over
						every interest and every employment of man.</p>
					<p>From this mighty source spring constant detraction, gossiping, tale-bearing,
						falsehood, anger, pride, malice, revenge, and every evil word and work.</p>
					<p>Every man sets himself up as the judge of the intellectual character, the
						honesty, the sincerity, the feelings, opportunities, motives, and
						intentions, of his fellow-man. And so they fall upon each other, not with
						swords and spears, but with the tongue, &ldquo;that unruly <pb n="126"/>
						member, that setteth on fire the course of nature, and is set on fire of
						hell.&rdquo;</p>
					<p>Can any person who seeks to maintain the peaceful, loving, and gentle spirit
						of Christianity, go out into the world at this day, without being bewildered
						at the endless conflicts, and grieved and dismayed at the bitter and
						unhallowed passions they engender? Can an honest, upright and Christian man,
						go into these conflicts, and with unflinching firmness stand up for all that
						is good, and oppose all that is evil, in whatever party it may be found,
						without a measure of moral courage such as few can command? And if he
						carries himself through with an unyielding integrity, and maintains his
						consistency, is he not exposed to storms of bitter revilings, and to
						peltings from both parties between which he may stand?</p>
					<p>What is the end of these things to be? Must we give up free discussion, and
						again chain up the human mind under the despotism of past ages? No, this
						will never be. God designs that every intelligent mind shall be governed,
						not by coercion, but by reason, and <pb n="127"/> conscience, and truth. Man
						must reason, and experiment, and compare past and present results, and hear
						and know all that can be said on <hi rend="italic">both</hi> sides of every
						question which influences either private or public happiness, either for
						this life or for the life to come.</p>
					<p>But while this process is going on, must we be distracted and tortured by the
						baleful passions and wicked works that unrestrained party-spirit and
						ungoverned factions will bring upon us, under such a government as ours?
						Must we rush on to disunion, and civil wars, and servile wars, till all
						their train of horrors pass over us like devouring fire?</p>
					<p>There is an influence that can avert these dangers &mdash; a spirit that
						can allay the storm &mdash; that can say to the troubled winds and
						waters, &ldquo;peace, be still.&rdquo;</p>
					<p>It is that spirit which is gentle and easy to be entreated, which thinketh no
						evil, which rejoiceth not in iniquity, but rejoiceth in the truth, which is
						not easily provoked, which hopeth all things, which beareth all things. Let
						this spirit be infused into the mass of the nation, and then truth may be
						sought, defended,<pb n="128"/> and propagated, and error detected, and its
						evils exposed; and yet we may escape the evils that now rage through this
						nation, and threaten us with such fiery plagues.</p>
					<p>And is there not a peculiar propriety in such an emergency, in looking for
						the especial agency and assistance of females, who are shut out from the
						many temptations that assail the other sex, &mdash; who are the
						appointed ministers of all the gentler charities of life, &mdash; who
						are mingled throughout the whole mass of the community, &mdash; who
						dwell in those retirements where only peace and love ought ever to enter,
						&mdash; whose comfort, influence, and dearest blessings, all depend on
						preserving peace and good will among men?</p>
					<p>In the present aspect of affairs among us, when everything seems to be
						tending to disunion and distraction, it surely has become the duty of every
						female instantly to relinquish the attitude of a partisan, in every matter
						of clashing interests, and to assume the office of a mediator, and an
						advocate of peace. And to do this, it is not necessary that a woman should
						in any manner relinquish <pb n="129"/> her opinion as to the evils or the
						benefits, the right or the wrong, of any principle or practice. But, while
						quietly holding her own opinions, and calmly avowing them, when conscience
						and integrity make the duty imperative, every female can employ her
						influence, not for the purpose of exciting or regulating public sentiment,
						but rather for the purpose of promoting a spirit of candour, forbearance,
						charity, and peace.</p>
					<p>And there are certain prominent maxims which every woman can adopt as
						peculiarly belonging to her, as the advocate of charity and peace, and which
						it should be her especial office to illustrate, enforce, and sustain, by
						every method in her power.</p>
					<p>The first is, that every person ought to be sustained, not only in the right
						of propagating his own opinions and practices, but in opposing all those
						principles and practices which he deems erroneous. For there is no opinion
						which a man can propagate, that does not oppose some adverse interest; and
						if a man must cease to advocate his own views of truth and rectitude,
						because he opposes the <pb n="130"/> interest or prejudices of some other
						man or party, all freedom of opinion, of speech, and of action, is gone. All
						that can be demanded is, that a man shall not resort to falsehood, false
						reasoning, or to attacks on character, in maintaining his own rights. If he
						states things which are false, it is right to show the falsehood,
						&mdash; if he reasons falsely, it is right to point out his sophistry,
						&mdash; if he impeaches the character or motives of opponents, it is
						right to express disapprobation and disgust; but if he uses only facts,
						arguments, and persuasions, he is to be honoured and sustained for all the
						efforts he makes to uphold what he deems to be right, and to put down what
						he believes to be wrong.</p>
					<p>Another maxim, which is partially involved in the first, is, that every man
						ought to allow his own principles and practices to be freely discussed, with
						patience and magnanimity, and not to complain of persecution, or to attack
						the character or motives of those who claim that he is in the wrong. If he
						is belied, if his character is impeached, if his motives are assailed, if
						his intellectual capabilities are <pb n="131"/> made the objects of sneers
						or commiseration, he has a right to complain, and to seek sympathy as an
						injured man; but no man is a consistent friend and defender of liberty of
						speech, who cannot bear to have his own principles and practices subjected
						to the same ordeal as he demands should be imposed on others.</p>
					<p>Another maxim of peace and charity is, that every man's own testimony is to
						be taken in regard to his motives, feelings, and intentions. Though we may
						fear that a fellowman is mistaken in his views of his own feelings, or that
						he does not speak the truth, it is as contrary to the rules of good breeding
						as it is to the laws of Christianity, to assume or even insinuate that this
						is the case. If a man's word cannot be taken in regard to his own motives,
						feelings, and intentions, he can find no redress for the wrong that may be
						done to him. It is unjust and unreasonable in the extreme to take any other
						course than the one here urged.</p>
					<p>Another most important maxim of candour and charity is, that when we are to
						assign motives<pb n="132"/> for the conduct of our fellow-men, especially of
						those who oppose our interests, we are obligated to put the best, rather
						than the worst construction, on all they say and do. Instead of assigning
						the worst as the probable motive, it is always a duty to <hi rend="italic"
							>hope</hi> that it is the best, until evidence is so unequivocal that
						there is no place for such a hope.</p>
					<p>Another maxim of peace and charity respects the subject of <hi rend="italic"
							>retaliation</hi>. Whatever may be said respecting the literal
						construction of some of the rules of the gospel, no one can deny that they
						do, whether figurative or not, forbid retaliation and revenge; that they do
						assume that men are not to be judges and executioners of their own wrongs;
						but that injuries are to be borne with meekness, and that retributive
						justice must be left to God, and to the laws. If a man strikes, we are not
						to return the blow, but appeal to the laws. If a man uses abusive or
						invidious language, we are not to return railing for railing. If a man
						impeaches our motives and attacks our character, we are not to return the
						evil. If a man sneers and ridicules, we are not to retaliate<pb n="133"/>
						<milestone unit="collation" n="M"/> with ridicule and sneers. If a man
						reports our weaknesses and failings, we are not to revenge ourselves by
						reporting his. No man has a right to report evil of others, except when the
						justification of the innocent, or a regard for public or individual safety,
						demands it. This is the strict law of the gospel, inscribed in all its
						pages, and meeting in the face all those unchristian and indecent violations
						that now are so common, in almost every conflict of intellect or of
						interest.</p>
					<p>Another most important maxim of peace and charity imposes the obligation to
						guard our fellow-men from all unnecessary temptation. We are taught daily to
						pray, &ldquo;lead us not into temptation;&rdquo; and thus are
						admonished not only to avoid all unnecessary temptation ourselves, but to
						save our fellow-men from the danger. Can we ask our Heavenly Parent to
						protect us from temptation, while we recklessly spread baits and snares for
						our fellow-men? No, we are bound in every measure to have a tender regard
						for the weaknesses and liabilities of all around, and ever to be ready to
						yield even our just rights, <pb n="134"/> when we can lawfully do it, rather
						than to tempt others to sin. The generous and <orig reg="high-minded"
							>high-minded</orig> Apostle declares, &ldquo;if meat make my brother
						to offend, I will eat no flesh while the world standeth;&rdquo; and it
						is the spirit of this maxim that every Christian ought to cultivate. There
						are no occasions when this maxim is more needed, than when we wish to modify
						the opinions, or alter the practices of our fellow-men. If, in such cases,
						we find that the probabilities are, that any interference of ours will
						increase the power of tempation, and lead to greater evils than those we
						wish to remedy, we are bound to forbear. If we find that one mode of
						attempting a measure will increase the power of temptation, and another will
						not involve this danger, we are bound to take the safest course. In all
						cases we are obligated to be as careful to protect our fellow-men from
						temptation, as we are to watch and pray against it in regard to ourselves.</p>
					<p>Another maxim of peace and charity requires a most scrupulous regard to the
						reputation, character, and feelings of our <orig reg="fellow-men"
							>fellow-men</orig>,<pb n="135"/> and especially of those who are opposed
						in any way to our wishes and interests. Every man and every woman feels that
						it is wrong for others to propagate their faults and weakness through the
						community. Every one feels wounded and injured to find that others are
						making his defects and infirmities the subject of sneers and ridicule. And
						what, then, is the rule of duty? &ldquo;As ye would that men should do
						to you, do ye even so to them.&rdquo; With this rule before his eyes and
						in his mind, can a man retail his neighbour's faults, or sneer at his
						deficiencies, or ridicule his infirmities, with a clear conscience? There
						are cases when the safety of individuals, or public justice, demands that a
						man's defects of character, or crimes, be made public; but no man is
						justified in communicating to others any evil respecting any of his
						fellow-men, when he cannot appeal to God as his witness that he does it from
						benevolent interest in the welfare of his fellow-men &mdash; from a
						desire to save individuals or the public from some evil &mdash; and not
						from a malevolent or gossiping propensity. Oh, that this law of love and <pb
							n="136"/> charity could find an illustration and an advocate in every
						female of this nation! Oh, that every current slander, and every injurious
						report, might stand abashed, whenever it meets the notice of a woman!</p>
					<p>These are the maxims of peace and charity, which it is in the power of the
						females of our country to advocate, both by example and by entreaties. These
						are the principles which alone can protect and preserve the right of free
						discussion, the freedom of speech, and liberty of the press. And with our
						form of government, and our liabilities to faction and party-spirit, the
						country will be safe and happy only in proportion to the prevalence of these
						maxims among the mass of the community. There probably will never arrive a
						period in the history of this nation, when the influence of these principles
						will be more needed, than the present. The question of slavery involves more
						pecuniary interests, touches more private relations, involves more
						prejudices, is entwined with more sectional, party, and political interests,
						than any other which can ever again arise. It is a matter <pb n="137"/>
						<milestone unit="collation" n="M 2"/> which, if discussed and controlled
						without the influence of these principles of charity and peace, will shake
						this nation like an earthquake, and pour over us the volcanic waves of every
						terrific passion. The trembling earth, the low murmuring thunders, already
						admonish us of our danger; and if females can exert any saving influence in
						this emergency, it is time for them to awake.</p>
					<p>And there are topics that they may urge upon the attention of their friends,
						at least as matters worthy of serious consideration and inquiry.</p>
					<p>Is a woman surrounded by those who favour the Abolition measures? Can she not
						with propriety urge such inquiries as these?</p>
					<p>Is not slavery to be brought to an end by free discussion, and is it not a
						war upon the right of free discussion to impeach the motives and depreciate
						the character of the opposers of Abolition measures? When the opposers of
						Abolition movements claim that they honestly and sincerely believe that
						these measures tend to perpetuate slavery, or to bring it to an end by
						servile wars, and civil <pb n="138"/> disunion, and the most terrific
						miseries &mdash; when they object to the use of their pulpits, to the
						embodying of literary students, to the agitation of the community, by
						Abolition agents &mdash; when they object to the circulation of such
						papers and tracts as Abolitionists prepare, because they believe them most
						pernicious in their influence and tendencies, is it not as much persecution
						to use invidious insinuations, depreciating accusation and impeachment of
						motive, in order to intimidate, as it is for the opposers of Abolitionism to
						use physical force? Is not the only method by which the South can be brought
						to relinquish slavery, a conviction that not only her <hi rend="italic"
							>duty,</hi> but her highest <hi rend="italic">interest,</hi> requires
						her to do it? And is not <hi rend="italic">calm, rational Christian</hi>
						discussion the only proper method of securing this end? Can a community that
						are thrown into such a state of high exasperation as now exists at the
						South, ever engage in such discussions, till the storm of excitement and
						passion is allayed? Ought not every friend of liberty and of free
						discussion, to take every possible means to soothe exasperated feelings, and
						to <pb n="139"/> avoid all those offensive peculiarities that in their
						nature tend to inflame and offend?</p>
					<p>Is a woman among those who oppose Abolition movements? She can urge such
						inquiries as these: Ought not Abolitionists to be treated as if they were
						actuated by the motives of benevolence which they profess? Ought not every
						patriot and every Christian to throw all his influence against the
						impeachment of motives, the personal detraction, and the violent measures
						that are turned upon this body of men, who, however they may err in judgment
						or in spirit, are among the most exemplary and benevolent in the land? If
						Abolitionists are censurable for taking measures that exasperate rather than
						convince and persuade, are not their opponents, who take exactly the same
						measures to exasperate Abolitionists and their friends, as much to blame? If
						Abolitionism prospers by the abuse of its advocates, are not the authors of
						this abuse accountable for the increase of the very evils they deprecate?</p>
					<p>It is the opinion of intelligent and well informed men, that a very large
						proportion of <pb n="140"/> the best members of the Abolition party were
						placed there, not by the arguments of Abolitionists, but by the abuse of
						their opposers. And I know some of the noblest minds that stand there,
						chiefly from the influence of those generous impulses that defend the
						injured and sustain the persecuted, while many others have joined these
						ranks from the impression that Abolitionism and the right of free discussion
						have become identical interests. Although I cannot perceive why the right of
						free discussion, the right of petition, and other rights that have become
						involved in this matter, cannot be sustained without joining an association
						that has sustained such injurious action and such erroneous principles, yet
						other minds, and those which are worthy of esteem, have been led to an
						opposite conclusion.</p>
					<p>The South, in the moments of angry excitement, have made unreasonable demands
						upon the non-slave-holding States, and have employed overbearing and
						provoking language. This has provoked re-action again at the North, and men,
						who heretofore were <pb n="141"/> unexcited, are beginning to feel
						indignant, and to say, &ldquo;Let the Union be sundered.&rdquo; Thus
						anger begets anger, and unreasonable measures provoke equally unreasonable
						returns.</p>
					<p>But when men, in moments of excitement rush on to such results, little do
						they think of the momentous consequences that may follow. Suppose the South
						in her anger unites with Texas, and forms a Southern <orig
							reg="slave-holding">slave-holding</orig> republic, under all the
						exasperating influences that such an avulsion will excite? What will be the
						prospects of the slave then, compared with what they are while we dwell
						together, united by all the ties of brotherhood, and having free access to
						those whom we wish to convince and persuade?</p>
					<p>But who can estimate the mischiefs that we must encounter while this
						dismemberment, this tearing asunder of the joints and members of the body
						politic, is going on? What will be the commotion and dismay, when all our
						sources of wealth, prosperity, and comfort, are turned to occasions for
						angry and selfish strife?</p>
					<pb n="142"/>
					<p> </p>
					<p>What agitation will ensue in individual States, when it is to be decided by
						majorities which State shall go to the North and which to the South, and
						when the discontented minority must either give up or fight! Who shall
						divide our public lands between contending factions? What shall be done with
						our navy and all the various items of the nation's property? What shall be
						done when the post-office stops its steady movement to divide its efforts
						among contending parties? What shall be done when public credit staggers,
						when commerce furls her slackened sail, when property all over the nation
						changes its owners and relations? What shall be done with our canals and
						railways, now the bands of love to bind us, then the causes of contention
						and jealousy? What umpire will appear to settle all these questions of
						interest and strife, between communities thrown asunder by passion, pride,
						and mutual injury?</p>
					<p>It is said that the American people, though heedless and sometimes reckless
						at the approach of danger, are endowed with a strong <pb n="143"/> and
						latent principle of common sense, which, when they fairly approach the
						precipice, always brings them to a stand, and makes them as wise to devise a
						remedy as they were rash in hastening to the danger. Are we not approaching
						the very verge of the precipice? Can we not already hear the roar of the
						waters below? Is not now the time, if ever, when our stern principles and
						sound common sense must wake to the rescue?</p>
					<p>Cannot the South be a little more patient under the injurious action that she
						feels she has suffered, and cease demanding those concessions from the
						North, that never will be made? For the North, though slower to manifest
						feeling, is as sensitive to her right of freedom of speech, as the South can
						be to her rights of property.</p>
					<p>Cannot the North bear with some unreasonable action from the South, when it
						is remembered that, as the provocation came from the North, it is wise and
						Christian that the aggressive party should not so strictly <pb n="144"/>
						hold their tempted brethren to the rules of right and reason?</p>
					<p>Cannot the South bear in mind that at the North the colour of the skin does
						not take away the feeling of brotherhood, and though it is a badge of
						degradation in station and intellect, yet it is oftener regarded with pity
						and sympathy than with contempt? Cannot the South remember their generous
						feelings for the Greeks and Poles, and imagine that some such feelings may
						be awakened for the African race, among a people who do not believe either
						in the policy or the right of slavery?</p>
					<p>Cannot the North remember how jealous every man feels of his domestic
						relations and rights, and how sorely their Southern brethren are tried in
						these respects? How would the husbands and fathers at the North endure it,
						if Southern associations should be formed to bring forth to the world the
						sins of Northern men, as husbands and fathers? What if the South should send
						to the North to collect all the sins and neglects of Northern husbands and
						fathers, to retail them at the South in <pb n="145"/>
						<milestone unit="collation" n="N"/> tracts and periodicals? What if the
						English nation should join in the outcry, and English females should send
						forth an agent, not indeed to visit the offending North, but to circulate at
						the South, denouncing all who did not join in this crusade, as the defenders
						of bad husbands and bad fathers? How would Northern men conduct under such
						provocations? There is indeed a difference in the two cases, but it is not
						in the nature and amount of irritating influence, for the Southerner feels
						the interference of strangers to regulate his domestic duty to his servants,
						as much as the Northern man would feel the same interference in regard to
						his wife and children. Do not Northern men owe a debt of forbearance and
						sympathy toward their Southern brethren, who have been so sorely tried?</p>
					<p>It is by urging these considerations, and by exhibiting and advocating the
						principles of charity and peace, that females may exert a wise and
						appropriate influence, and one which will most certainly tend to bring to an
						end, not only slavery, but unnumbered other evils <pb n="146"/> and wrongs.
						No one can object to such an influence, but all parties will bid God speed
						to every woman who modestly, wisely and benevolently attempts it.</p>
					<p>I do not suppose that any Abolitionists are to be deterred by any thing I can
						offer, from prosecuting the course of measures they have adopted. They
						doubtless will continue to agitate the subject, and to form voluntary
						associations all over the land, in order to excite public sentiment at the
						North against the moral evils existing at the South. Yet I cannot but hope
						that some considerations may have influence to modify in a degree the spirit
						and measures of some who are included in that party.</p>
					<p>Abolitionists are men who come before the public in the character of <hi
							rend="italic">reprovers</hi>. That the gospel requires Christians
						sometimes to assume this office, cannot be denied; but it does as
						unequivocally point out those qualifications which alone can entitle a man
						to do it. And no man acts wisely or consistently, unless he can satisfy
						himself that he possesses <pb n="147"/> the qualifications for this duty,
						before he assumes it.</p>
					<p>The first of these qualifications is more than common exemption from the
						faults that are reproved. The inspired interrogatory, &ldquo;thou
						therefore which teachest another, teachest thou not thyself?&rdquo;
						enforces this principle; and the maxim of common sense, that
						&ldquo;reprovers must have clean hands,&rdquo; is no less
						unequivocal. Abolitionists are reprovers for the violation of duties in the
						domestic relations. Of course they are men who are especially bound to be
						exemplary in the discharge of all their domestic duties. If a man cannot
						govern his temper and his tongue; if he inflicts that moral castigation on
						those who cross his will, which is more severe than physical stripes; if he
						is overbearing or exacting with those under his control; if he cannot secure
						respect for a kind and faithful discharge of all his social and relative
						duties, it is as unwise and improper for him to join an Abolition Society,
						as it would be for a drunkard to preach temperance, or a slave-holder
						Abolitionism.</p>
					<pb n="148"/>
					<p> </p>
					<p>Another indispensable requisite for the office of reprover is a character
						distinguished for humility and meekness. There is nothing more difficult
						than to approach men for the purpose of convincing them of their own
						deficiencies and faults; and whoever attempts it in a self-complacent and
						dictatorial spirit, always does more evil than good. However exemplary a man
						may be in the sight of men, there is abundant cause for the exercise of
						humility. For a man is to judge of himself, not by a comparison with other
						men, but as he stands before God, when compared with a perfect law, and in
						reference to all his peculiar opportunities and restraints. Who is there
						that in this comparison, cannot find cause for the deepest humiliation? Who
						can go from the presence of Infinite Purity after such an investigation, to
						&ldquo;take his brother by the throat?&rdquo; Who rather, should not
						go to a brother, who may have sinned, with the deepest sympathy and love, as
						one who, amid greater temptations and with fewer advantages, may be the
						least offender of the <pb n="149"/> two? A man who goes with this spirit,
						has the best hope of doing good to those who may offend. And yet even this
						spirit will not always save a man from angry retort, vexatious insinuation,
						jealous suspicion, and the misconstruction of his motives. A reprover,
						therefore, if he would avoid a quarrel and do the good he aims to secure,
						must be possessed of that meekness which can receive evil for good, with
						patient benevolence. And a man is not fitted for the duties of a reprover,
						until he can bring his feelings under this control.</p>
					<p>The last, and not the least important requisite for a reprover, is <hi
							rend="italic">discretion</hi>. This is no where so much needed as in
						cases where the domestic relations are concerned, for here is the place
						above all others, where men are most sensitive and unreasonable. There are
						none who have more opportunities for learning this, than those who act as
						teachers, especially if they feel the responsibility of a Christian and a
						friend, in regard to the moral interests of pupils, A teacher who shares <pb
							n="150"/> with parents the responsibilities of educating their children,
						whose efforts may all be rendered useless by parental influences at home;
						who feels an affectionate interest in both parent and child, is surely the
						one who might seem to have a right to seek, and a chance of success in
						seeking, some modifications of domestic influences. And yet teachers will
						probably testify, that it is a most discouraging task, and often as likely
						to result in jealous alienation and the loss of influence over both parent
						and child, as in any good. It is one of the greatest compliments that can be
						paid to the good sense and the good feeling of a parent to dare to attempt
						any such measure. This may show how much discretion, and tact, and delicacy,
						are needed by those who aim to rectify evils in the domestic relations of
						mankind.</p>
					<p>The peculiar qualifications, then, which make it suitable for a man to be an
						Abolitionist are, an exemplary discharge of all the domestic duties;
						humility, meekness, delicacy, tact, and discretion, and these should
							especially<pb n="151"/> be the distinctive traits of those who take the
						place of <hi rend="italic">leaders</hi> in devising measures.</p>
					<p>And in performing these difficult and <orig reg="self-denying"
						>self-denying</orig> duties, there are no men who need more carefully to
						study the character and imitate the example of the Redeemer of mankind. He,
						indeed, was the searcher of hearts, and those reproofs which were based on
						the perfect knowledge of &ldquo;all that is in man,&rdquo; we may
						not imitate. But we may imitate him, where he with so much gentleness,
						patience, and pitying love, encountered the weakness, the rashness, the
						selfishness, the worldliness of men. When the young man came with such
						self-complacency to ask what more he could do, how kindly he was received,
						how gently convinced of his great deficiency! When fire would have been
						called from heaven by his angry followers, how forbearing the rebuke! When
						denied and forsaken with oaths and curses by one of his nearest friends,
						what was it but a look of pitying love that sent the disciple out so
						bitterly to weep? When, in his last extremity<pb n="152"/> of sorrow, his
						friends all fell asleep, how gently he drew over them the mantle of love! Oh
						blessed Saviour, impart more of thy own spirit to those who profess to
						follow thee!</p>
					<trailer> THE END. </trailer>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="notes" id="d8">
					<note place="end" id="n1" n="n1">
						<seg type="note-symbol">*</seg>
						<p>History of the Abolition of the Slave Trade.</p>
					</note>
					<note place="end" id="n2" n="n2">
						<seg type="note-symbol">*</seg>
						<p>Coleridge.</p>
					</note>
					<note place="end" id="n3" n="n3">
						<seg type="note-symbol">*</seg>
						<p>The father of the late Samuel Whitbread, Esq., generously undertook, in
							order to make Mr. Clarkson's mind easy upon the subject, &ldquo;to
							make good all injuries which any individuals might suffer from such
							persecution; and he honourably and nobly fulfilled his engagement.</p>
					</note>
					<note place="end" id="n4" n="n4">
						<seg type="note-symbol">*</seg>
						<p>This account of Clarkson, and the preceding one of Wilberforce, are taken
							from the Christian Keepsake of 1836 and 1837.</p>
					</note>
				</div2>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
