<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="BesLett"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="BesLett">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Letter: Boston, April 20th, 1773.</title>
<title type="sort">letter boston, april 20th 1773</title>
<author>Bestes, Peter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Readex &mdash; a division of NewsBank Inc.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">8</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">BesLett</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475733</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Documentary Sources Database.  American Multiculturalism
Series.  Unit one.  Documenting the African American Experience.</p>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Boston, April 20th, 1773. Sir, The efforts made by the legislative
[sic] of this province in their last sessions to free themselves from
slavery, gave us, who are in that deplorable state, a high degree of
satisfaction. ... We cannot but wish and hope, sir, that you will have
the same grand object, we mean civil and religious liberty, in view of
your next session. ...</title>
<title type="sort">boston, april 20th 1773 sir the efforts made by the legislative sic of this province in their last sessions to free themselves from slavery gave us who are in that deplorable state a high degree of satisfaction we cannot but wish and hope sir that you will have the same grand object we mean civil and religious liberty in view of your next session</title>
<author>Peter Bestes [and three others].</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) ; 38 x 25 cm.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>s.n.</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
<date value="1773">[1773]</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Early American Imprints, 1st series, no. 42416
(filmed)</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Circular letter; signed: In behalf of our fellow slaves in this
province, and by order of their committee. Peter Bestes [and three
others]. For the representatives of the town of [blank].</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared by TextBase in consultation with David Seaman,
University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>milestone tag records a pagination number that runs consecutively
for the whole project.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1773">1773</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term type="references">Bristol B3534.</term>
<term type="references">Shipton &amp; Mooney 42416.</term>
<term type="references">Ford, W.C.  Broadsides, 1649.</term>
<term type="subjects">Slavery&mdash;Massachusetts.</term>
<term type="subjects">Slavery&mdash;Emancipation.</term>
<term type="genres">Broadsides.</term>
<term type="additional">Bestes, Peter.</term>
<term type="printer">sine nomine</term>
<term type="pubplace">United States&mdash;Massachusetts&mdash;Boston.</term>
<term type="record">w005115</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-02">February 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Matthew G. Kirschenbaum, Electronic Text Center, University of
Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI.2-compatible header and tagging</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="letter" id="d3">
<pb/>
<milestone unit="seriespage" n="000086"/>
<head><hi rend="italic">BOSTON</hi>, APRIL 20<hi rend="italic">th</hi>,
1773.</head>

<salute>
<hi rend="italic">SIR,</hi>
</salute>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">THE</hi> efforts made by the legislative of this province in their last
sessions to free themselves from slavery, gave us, who are in that deplorable state, a high
degree of satisfacton. We expect great things from men who have made such a noble
stand against the designs of their <hi rend="italic">fellow-men</hi> to enslave them. We
cannot but wish and hope Sir, that you will have the same grand object, we mean civil
and religious liberty, in view in your next session. The divine spirit of
<hi rend="italic">freedom</hi>, seems to fire every humane breast on this continent, except
such as are bribed to assist in executing the execrable plan.
</p><p>
WE are very sensible that it would be highly detrimental to our present masters, if we
were allowed to demand all that of <hi rend="italic">right</hi> belongs to us for past
services; this
we disclaim. Even the <hi rend="italic">Spaniards</hi>, who have not those sublime ideas
of freedom that English men have, are conscious that they have no right to all the service
of their fellow-men, we mean the <hi rend="italic">Africans</hi>, whom they have
purchased with
their money; therefore they allow them one day in a week to work for themselve, to
enable them to earn money to purchase the residue of their time, which they have a
right to demand in such portions as they are able to pay for (a due appraizment of their
services being first made, which always stands at the purchase money.) We do not
pretend to dictate to you Sir, or to the honorable Assembly, of which you are a
member: We acknowledge our obligations to you for what you have already done, but
as the people of this province seem to be actuated by the principles of equity and
justice, we cannot but expect your house will again take our deplorable case into
serious consideration, and give us that ample relief which, <hi rend="italic">as men</hi>,
we have
a natural right to.
</p><p>
BUT since the wise and righteous governor of the universe, has permitted our fellow
men to make us slaves, we bow in submission to him, and determine to behave in such
a manner, as that we may have reason to expect the divine approbation of, and
assistance in, our peaceable and lawful attempts to gain our freedom.
</p><p>
WE are willing to submit to such regulations and laws, as may be made relative to us,
until we leave the province, which we determine to do as soon as we can from our
joynt labours procure money to transport ourselves to some part of the coast of
<hi rend="italic">Africa</hi>, where we propose a settlement. We are very desirous that
you should
have instructions relative to us, from your town, therefore we pray you to
communicate this letter to them, and ask this favor for us.
</p><p>
In behalf of our fellow slaves in this province, And by order of their Committee.
</p>
<list>
<item>PETER BESTES,</item>
<item>SAMBO FREEMAN,</item>
<item>FELIX HOLBROOK</item>
<item>CHESTER JOIE</item>
</list>
<trailer>For the REPRESENTATIVE of the town of [?]</trailer>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
