<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="BicPugn"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="BicPugn">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Pugnacious Style</title>
<title type="sort">pugnacious style</title>
<author>Bicknell, Percy F.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name/>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">16</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">BicPugn</idno>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475735</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Pugnacious Style</title>
<title level="j">The Dial</title>
<title type="sort">pugnacious style</title>
<author>Percy F. Bickell</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>353-356</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Henry O. Shepard Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
<date value="1915-10-28">October 28, 1915</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: U. Va. Library, Call No. AP2.D48, Vol. 59, No. 704, October 28, 1915</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Reprinted 1966 by Kraus Reprint Corporation, New York, with permission of James S. Watson, Jr. and Scofield Thayer.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1915">1915</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose, non-fiction</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-08">August 1997</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Christopher Fennell, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and SGML tagging</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
	<pb n="353"/>
<head><hi rend="italic">THE PUGNACIOUS STYLE.</hi></head>

<p>It is the nature of man to love a good hater; at any rate, a
considerable part of mankind pays him the tribute of admiration for
the vigor and constancy of his animosity.  In like manner the
reading world enjoys the aggressive energy and the keen stabs, or
sledge-hammer blows, of him who writes with the intent of
annihilating a foe or exploding a false doctrine; and this in spite of
the fact that little of worth in the cause of truth and justice has ever
been effected by passionate vehemence of style, no wrong-headed
person has ever been bullied into reasonableness, and no enemy has
ever been crushed by mere force of vituperation.  As is illustrated
every week and every day in the heated discussions that in these
fevered times claim so much space in our newspapers and
magazines, and even in our books, the controversialist falls easily
into the error of hurting his cause by undue warmth of manner, and
repels by intemperance of speech where he might win by
moderation and restraint.  If it be true, as experience inclines one to
believe, that nobody was ever convinced by argument who was not
already more than half persuaded, it is doubly true that no
prejudiced person was ever induced by vituperation to renounce his
prejudice and alter his opinions.

</p><p>Intellectual independence is dear to every one of us, and the
faintest suspicion that an author is assailing that independence is
enough to erect a barrier against the cogency of his reasoning.  But
if the controversialist can so state his case as to seem to leave his
readers entire freedom of choice between acceptance and rejection
of his views, he stands a good chance of making converts; and if,
employing a somewhat subtler art, he can cause the reader to
imagine himself a little more acute or a little more logical than the
author, and can tickle him with the illusion of seeing important
points that had escaped the other's duller perceptions (though it was
just these points that the writer had adopted this artful means of
making manifest), then the case is won, and the pleader is willing
enough to renounce the glory of victory for its more substantial
fruits.

   <pb n="354"/>

But the partisan pamphleteer of these fiery times is prone to begin
his polemic by antagonizing the very persons he wishes to conciliate,
and so his purpose is often defeated before he has fairly begun his
argument.  He commonly writes in a lively and spicy and highly
readable style, and is therefore followed with immense satisfaction by
those who are already on his side, or who are not positively opposed
to him.  The pugnacious style in itself, such is erring human nature,
appeals to most readers when it does not chance to be directed too
pointedly and personally against them; it keeps them awake, pleases
them with a sense of taking part in laying low an army of stupid or
malicious adversaries who needed only this unanswerable demonstration
of the matter to induce them to confess the futility of further
opposition; and it is delightful to serve the cause of truth and
righteousness in this easy fashion, when all that is just and virtuous
and noble is so manifestly on our side, and all that is false and
wicked and perverse and abominable so evidently on the other.

</p><p>The immense vogue enjoyed by such contributions to so-called
popular science as Professor Haeckel's widely-read solution of "The
Riddle of the Universe" is no doubt largely due to the confidently
aggressive air with which he exposes the folly of all those
philosophers who pretend to see in the scheme of created things
some element other than matter and mechanism.  How vastly
superior one feels to Plato and Emerson and the whole tribe of
mystics and dreamers when one has taken a hand with the Jena
professor in their demolition and has arrived at the point where one
can say with this sturdy foe to every form of transcendental
nonsense, "The supreme and all-pervading law of nature, the true
and only cosmological law, is, in my opinion, the <hi rend="italic">law of
substance</hi>," and can regard with him the belief in the soul's
immortality as the "highest point of superstition."  But what if one
happens to be a Platonist and a dreamer to begin with?  Will the
controversial tone of "The Riddle of the Universe" work a change of
heart and win a new convert to the Haeckelian doctrine?  Hardly.

</p><p>A long-recognized master of the pugnaciously vituperative
style, and one whom it is an unending delight to read, even though
the reader be wise enough not to yield entire assent to what affords
him this intellectual refreshment, is found in the author of that
history of England which in the middle of the last century rivalled
in popularity the novels of Dickens and Thackeray.  It has been said
of Macaulay's style that it is admirable for almost every purpose but
telling the truth.  Certainly it is an admirable style to adopt when
one wishes not to spoil a good story in the telling.  With what an
array of rhetorical weapons Macaulay has assailed the luckless
monarch who was the last of the Stuarts to sit on the throne of
England, all the world knows.  His merciless handling of that king's
infamous tool, the bloodthirsty chief justice whose name has
become synonymous with judicial severity, is almost as notorious.
Jeffreys, as we are now warranted in believing, was not absolutely
devoid of humanity, though a reading of Macaulay or of Campbell
would incline a credulous person to regard him as a veritable
monster of malice and cruelty.  Mr. H. B. Irving, not many years
ago, showed us the man as a human being.  When Macaulay,
trusting to authorities that have since his time become more or less
discredited, speaks of Jeffreys as "constitutionally prone to
ignorance and to the angry passions," he is but just beginning the
list of the chief justice's evil qualities.  In his early practice at the
bar of the Old Bailey, "daily conflicts with prostitutes and thieves
called out and exercised his powers so effectually that he became
the most consummate bully ever known in his profession.  All
tenderness for the feelings of others, all self-respect, all sense of the
becoming were obliterated from his mind. . .  The profusion of
maledictions and vituperative epithets which composed his
vocabulary could hardly have been rivalled in the fish-market or the
bear-garden. . .  There was a fiendish exultation in the way in which
he pronounced sentence on offenders.  Their weeping and imploring
seemed to titillate him voluptuously; and he loved to scare them
into fits by dilating with luxuriant amplification on all the details of
what they were to suffer."  This lavishing of the historian's wealth
of rhetoric upon one who was doubtless equally liberal in airing his
vocabulary in the courts of law does not, to say the least, make for
somnolence in the reader.  As the popular opinion of "Bloody
Jeffreys" was already far from complimentary when Macaulay's
work appeared, this valiant thwacking of the odious wretch gave
untold satisfaction to thousands of readers.

   <pb n="355"/>


</p><p>For vituperative energy, combined with all the resources of
erudition and reinforced by the weight of a commanding personality,
there is little in our literature to compare with Milton's famous
reply, in his "Defense of the People of England," to Salmasius, the
noted Leyden professor whose espousal of the cause of Charles I. had
stirred the wrath of the Latin Secretary to the Commonwealth.  When
Milton says of his adversary's work, "I persuaded myself, the
extemporary rhymes of some antic jack-pudding may better deserve
printing," he is at his mildest; and even when he calls Salmasius "a
vain and flashy man," and addresses him as "thou superlative fool," he
does not attain the pitch of abuse to which he subsequently lashes
himself.  But in his very first paragraph he is sufficiently heated to
write such sentences as this: "I would advise you not to have so good
an opinion of yourself (for nobody else has of you) as to imagine that
you are able to speak well upon any subject, who can neither play the
part of an orator, nor an historian, nor express yourself in a style
that would not be ridiculous even in a lawyer; but like a mountebank's
juggler, with big swelling words in your preface, you raised our
expectations, as if some mighty matter were to ensue; in which your
design was not so much to introduce a true narrative of the king's
story, as to make your own empty intended flourishes go off the
better."  And a little further on he adds: "I will tell you what the
matter is with you.  In the first place, you find yourself affrighted
and astonished at your own monstrous lies; and then you find that
empty head of yours not encompassed, but carried round, with so many
trifles and fooleries, that you not only now do not, but never did,
know what was fit to be spoken, and in what method."  This vigorous
polemic was written, it is true, in Latin, in which it presents an
appearance of perhaps greater seemliness and dignity than in the
vernacular rendering; but it illustrates a style no longer in vogue in
our controversial literature, though whether it has given place to
anything more worthy of admiration may be open to dispute.

</p><p>An eminent living writer has declared that no one should
expect to accomplish anything in literature until he has first ruined
his digestion.  How much of Carlyle's fame he owes to his
dyspepsia, one cannot accurately determine; but his works contain
an excess of invective that probably would have had no place there
if he had been a eupeptic person.  In all this amazingly fluent and
varied and picturesque tirade, however, there is a quality of artistic
detachment, of humorous gusto even, without which these
atrabilious outpourings would be offensive, or merely wearisome,
instead of entertaining and stimulating.  In his "Latter-Day
Pamphlets," with what wealth of disparaging language the doughty
pamphleteer exposes the ineptitude of Downing Street!  If he had
been born on the west instead of the east side of St. Patrick's
Channel he could scarcely have been more uncompromisingly "agin
the government" &mdash; as may appear from a few random sentences.
Concerning the solemn mummeries of the "strange Entities" in
Downing Street he says, with characteristic opulence of imagery:
"How the tailors clip and sew, in that sublime sweating
establishment of theirs, we know not: that the coat they bring us out
is the sorrowfulest fantastic mockery of a coat, a mere intricate
artistic network of traditions and formalities, an embroiled
reticulation made of web-listings and superannuated thrums and
tatters, endurable to no grown Nation as a coat, is mournfully
clear!"  The one invariable attribute of those who are set in high
places to govern those beneath them, is stupidity.  "For empires or
for individuals there is but one class of men to be trembled at; and
that is the Stupid Class, the class that cannot see, who alas are they
mainly that will not see.  A class of mortals under which as
administrators, kings, priests, diplomatists, etc., the interests of
mankind in every European country have sunk overloaded, as under
universal nightmare, near to extinction; and are indeed at this
moment convulsively writhing, decided either to throw off the
unblessed super-incumbent nightmare, or roll themselves and it to
the Abyss."

</p><p>Among more recent masters of the pugnacious style, one of the
most enjoyable to read, and one in whom an irresistible drollery of
humor never fails to mask any possible sub-stratum of malevolence,
is the author of that spirited defence of Harriet Shelley which was
evoked by Dowden's admired biography of this unhappy lady's
poet-husband.  Mark Twain, when moved to anger by any
exhibition of arrogance or inhumanity, was capable of showing
himself an antagonist whose pen was to be feared.

   <pb n="356"/>

</p><p>Our brilliant and ever-entertaining contemporaries, Mr.
Bernard Shaw and Mr. G. K. Chesterton, naturally come to mind in
this connection as notable exponents of the literary style here under
consideration.  Perhaps the dominant note of these two, especially
of Mr. Shaw, might be indicated by the misquotation from Pope,
"Whatever is, is wrong."  The world is all at fault and needs to be
scolded and ridiculed and paradoxed into right conduct.  Mr.
Chesterton's recent vigorous onslaught on the Prussians leaves no
doubt as to his mastery of incisiveness.  Mr. Shaw's infinity of
resource when the perversities and asininities of his fellow-men
require castigation at his hands is too well known to call for
comment or illustration.

</p><p>Although little of lasting value is ever accomplished by
unbridled vehemence of invective, yet it may be assumed as certain
that not until human nature shall cease to be what it now is, and not
until the occurrence of a dog-fight in the street shall fail to draw an
eager crowd of spectators, will the pugnacious style, as employed
by a master of sarcastic vituperation, cease to be accounted an
agreeable stimulus to the jaded senses, provided only one be not the
conscious object against which this battery of abuse is directed.</p>

<closer>PERCY F. BICKNELL.</closer>

</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

