<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="BlaJack"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="BlaJack">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Jack London</title>
<title type="sort">jack london</title>
<author>Bland, Henry Meade</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">20</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">BlaJack</idno>
<date value="2000">2000</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2000 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475737</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Jack London</title>
<title level="j">The Overland Monthly</title>
<title type="sort">jack london</title>
<author>Henry Meade Bland</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>California Pub. Co., 1883-1923</publisher>
<pubPlace>San Francisco</pubPlace>
<date value="1904-05">May 1904</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Source copy consulted: Micfilm S-147 reel 35-50.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>American periodical series: 1850-1900 ; 35-50.</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Microfilm. Ann Arbor, Mich. : University Microfilms, [n.d.]. 16 microfilm reels ; 35 mm. (American periodical series: 1850-1900 ; 35-50)</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1904">1904</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2001-04">April 2001</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Karen Wikander</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
<head>JACK LONDON<lb/>
&mdash;<lb/>
BY HENRY MEADE BLAND</head>

<pb n="370"/>

<p>JACK LONDON has, perhaps as no other American author, put his own
life into his books.  He has lived his art.  It is this feature of
London's work that makes one ready to prophesy that his sojourn as war
correspondent at the seat of the great conflict between Russia and Japan
will result in, unless the drudgery of newspaper hack-work interferes,
at least one new volume of powerful delineation of life.

</p><p>London's first series of personal adventure was aboard a whaler
on the seas northeast of Japan.  Perhaps his return to Japan means an
Oriental sea-story.  London has already in mind a striking title, which
the writer of this article is sworn not to reveal, but which, it is
permitted to say, indicates a tale of the deep.

</p><p>At any rate, we may rest assured that the author of "The Call of
the Wild" is now building a new and important epoch in the long list of
his startling experiences.  That these experiences mean another book is
merely the logic of London's life.  It is this relation between his own
active life and his literary art that makes his biography intensely
fascinating.

</p><p>Jack London is a native son of California.  His father and mother
have resided in California for more than thirty years.  Mr. London,
senior, was a Civil War veteran, and while in the service contracted
diseases, which, after entailing much expense and hardship on the entire
family, ultimately carried him to his grave.

</p><p>Livermore, Oakland, Alameda and San Francisco have at various
times been the family residence.  Jack was born twenty-eight years ago
on the twelfth of last January.

</p><p>The mother of the boy aided in bread-getting by giving music
lessons; and it may, very probably, be that her keen sense of musical
rhythm contributed largely to form in her son that instinct for the
harmonious which often appears in his prose.

</p><p>The boy was a great reader, and often said in a childish way:
"When I am a man I'm going to have a whole house full of books."  This
love of reading is a first step in the development of literary genius.
He attended the public school and completed its work.  The increasing
age and illness of his father, however, made it necessary for a time
after he left the common schools to contribute in earnest to the family
living, and he was initiated into a life of toil.

</p><p>It was at this time that his thirst for adventure showed itself.
He chose work which took him on San Francisco Bay.  He was employed to
patrol the oyster beds in search of oyster pirates.  This work seems to
have been eminently to his liking, although he was but fourteen years
old, and the work carried with it much hardship.

</p><p>A year or more later, he was sent to sea by his parents, who
wished to satisfy his longing for adventure,

<pb n="371"/>

as well as to get him out of what
they feared were evil influences.

</p><p>He went with a whaling crew on the seas to the North and
Northeast of Japan.  In this Pacific cruise he touched the Orient at
Yokohama.  His stay on the islands at this time was but three weeks,
when he put to sea again on the whaler.  While on the broad seas the
crew mutinied.  The captain of the whaler attempted to pay the sailors
in foreign coin.  The men rebelled, as the foreign money was at a
discount, and to accept it would involve a loss.  All the men, even the
youngster Jack, took part against the captain, who was brought to terms.

</p><p>In such experiences as these London was gaining an insight into
human nature and thus laying a foundation to his life work.

</p><p>On his return to California, new and more startling adventures
were in store for him.  His love for literary work had lead him to join
a debating society, "The Henry Clay," which afterwards proved to be an
important element in his education.  "The Henry Clay" had planned an
open debate, and in this London was to take a prominent part.  When the
day before the debate was to occur came, Jack could nowhere be found.
He had followed Coxey's army of the unemployed off to Washington.  A
strong instinctive sympathy with humanity had wakened in him a vital
interest in the unfortunate men who composed the army, many of whom were
union men out of employment.  After Coxey had been gone several days
from Oakland, London suddenly concluded to follow.  Allying himself with
an ordinary tramp, the two riding brake-beams and roaming after the
manner of ordinary wanderers, found themselves with a few of "army's"
stragglers at Buffalo, New York.

</p><p>Here arrested for vagrancy with a bunch of twenty-four tramps,
rounded up by the Buffalo police, he was railroaded into jail with but
the shadow of a trial.  His sentence was for three months.  The whole
proceeding was a rude shock to London's ideas of American justice.  He
was, however, made a trusty by the prison authorities, so that his term
in jail was not an exceedingly hard one.  He succeeded in hiding thirty
dollars which he had in his pocket when arrested.  With this to go on
after his release he continued his strange tour of the East, visiting
all the large cities, sometimes sojourning with relatives, at other
times wholly adrift among strangers; but all the time gathering up the
fund of experience which was afterwards woven into his books.  He
returned to California, by way of the Canadian Pacific, still riding the
brake-beam most of the way.

</p><p>The passion for literary expression grew rapidly in him during
this stay in the East, and once again home he began to write.  Many
short stories were produced with the net result that the author only had
good practice in composing them.

</p><p>During the Eastern trip the motive, an intense interest in the
wrongs and sufferings of humanity, which has since most largely swayed
his destinies, took permanent hold of him.  He felt the need of a better
education, and when once again in Oakland, he laid plans to secure a
formal scholastic training.  He entered the Oakland High School.  Here
he wrote a number of times for the school paper, the "Aegis."

</p><p>His aim was now firmly fixed on preparation for college, but he
was in a hurry to get through the preliminary work.  He decided that the
high school was too slow.  Leaving it to gain time, he entered
Anderson's academy, and studied there three months.  The private school
was too expensive, besides being tedious.  He therefore determined to
prepare himself by private study for the university.

<pb n="372"/>

</p><p>He was still a moving spirit in the "Henry Clay" debating
society.  The membership of this society at one time reached
twenty-five, and its debaters without doubt did much to strengthen
London's power of expression.

</p><p>His self-preparation for the university was rapidly progressing,
and after three months of incessant toil, in which he covered more than
a year of ordinary work, he readily passed the entrance examinations to
the college at Berkeley.

</p><p>London's course in the university lasted but a short time.  The
most conspicuous influence upon him came in his reading of Carlyle's
"French Revolution."  He studied the Scotch philosopher with an
increasing interest and rejoiced in the vigorous portrayals of the
scenes of the Revolution.  In his study of history he became confirmed
in his already growing belief in socialism.  The conservative economic
views current at the university were very unsatisfactory to him, and the
young thinker was often in open war against the college propaganda.  Nor
did London get in his English studies at the University what he said he
afterward sorely needed in the production of his books.

</p><p>During all the time he was working for an education, scarcity of
money necessitated constant toil outside the lines of study for a
livelihood.

</p><p>He undertook anything at hand to do, even if the wages in payment
were small.  When the inspiration seized him to write, though, he threw
everything aside and buried himself in his manuscript.  Sorrow and
suffering at this time were the lot of the London family, as the
father's life had slowly ebbed away as a result of the illness
contracted during the war, and he now lay at death's door.

</p><p>When the Klondike gold fever broke out, London went with the
crowd to the North.  On this trip he got inspiration for the best books
he has written.  As far as moneymaking went, the Klondike adventure was
a failure.  He spent most

<pb n="373"/>

of his time reading the scant literature obtainable in the new land,
and prospected but little.  Yet all of
the time he was filling his brain
with the life pictures which he afterwards put into his stories of the
Northland.

</p><p>On his way from the Klondike back to civilization he drifted with
three other men down the Yukon on a raft.  After many perilous escapes
among the river rapids all were finally taken from the raft by a steamer
and conveyed to St. Michael's.  In order that he might save the small
sum of money that he had left over from his expense account in the North
when he was ready to return to California he shipped as coal-heaver and
worked his passage home.

</p><p>The passion to write on his return fell upon him, and every spare
moment he was busy with his pen.  He was slowly and by dogged
persistence winning his way in his art.

</p><p>He was now close to the door of fame.  One after another, in
rapid succession, he sent the products of his pen to various
publications; but he made no great strike until "The White Silence" was
mailed to the Overland Monthly, which had already published one of his
short stories, "To the Man on the Trail."

</p><p>When "The White Silence" arrived at the Overland office the
editor-in-chief, James Bridge, was in the East.  The assistant editor,
Charles S. Greene, had in his chief's absence, accepted the manuscript
and the tale appeared in print.  Mr.  Bridge saw the story while on the
train on his way home, having purchased a number of his own magazine
from the newsboy.  He read the story and declared it "great."  On the
editor's return to San Francisco negotiations were entered upon with the
author, who agreed to contribute a serial to the magazine.  This duly
appeared in the following Overland numbers, and the tales thus published
have been collected with others into one volume, "The Son of the Wolf."
London was thus for the first time launched on his career as an author.

</p><p>Miss Elizabeth Maddern in the spring of nineteen hundred became
the novelist's wife and since their marriage two children, both girls,
have been borne to them.  It was about this time that a number of visits
were made to the "sun-kissed" valley of the Santa Clara; and the
beautiful groves around College Park seemed to have formed the
environment which gave a strong impetus to the contemplative thought
which is so marked in "The Call of the Wild."  These were sunny times in
the author's life.

</p><p>Mr. London's close friend, Mr.  Louis Bond, son of Judge Bond,
who was the original of "Judge Miller" in "The Call of the Wild," lives
in the town of Santa Clara near College Park.  London's acquaintance
with Mr. Louis Bond began in the Klondike, and the prototype of the
genial Louis without doubt appears in "The Son of the Wolf" in the
character of Stanley Prince.  The original of Buck, the dog hero of "The
Call of the Wild," belonged to Louis Bond.  Buck was a beautiful
long-haired animal with a Scotch collie and Saint Bernard ancestry
behind him.  Any one who has strolled in the picturesque grounds around
Judge Bond's home will appreciate London's description of Buck's home,
and will certainly take more delight in the opening chapters of "The
Call of the Wild."

</p><p>During the Boer troubles in South Africa Mr. London received a
call from the American Press Association to interview the Boer
commanders.  But on his way to the Transvaal, when in New York, he was
informed of the censorship at that time established over war news from
the Cape, and was obliged to change his plans.

</p><p>Instead of returning home he went to England, and after a short
rest in London, during which he saw the coronation ceremonies of

<pb n="374"/>

Edward VII, he began a study of
the London slums.  The product of
this work he had previously agreed
to furnish to a new socialistic magazine of New York.  He was, according to his contract with the
magazine, to tell the whole truth
about what he saw among the poor
of the great city.

</p><p>He was to tell the truth even if it did make those in high places
cringe at the knowledge of the awful conditions which might be brought
to light, and for which they might be held responsible.

</p><p>When the manuscript of this study was finished the magazine which
was to publish it failed.  The work was then published in book form with
the title, "The People of the Abyss."

</p><p>Of the books London has written, "The Son of the Wolf," "The God
of his Fathers," "A Daughter of the Snows," and "The Children of the
Frost," all grow out of his experiences in the North.  "The Cruise of
the Dazzler," a boys' story, recites in the main the story of his own
adventures as a boy on San Francisco bay.

</p><p>"The Call of the Wild" is a story of Northern gold-fields&mdash;an
animal story; and a story of wonderful effect it is.  Its very first
reading in manuscript brought tears to the eyes of the usually
imperturbable reader of Macmillan &amp; Company, to whom it had been
assigned to determine its worthiness for publication.  Its success was
assured from the time Manager Brett received the report of this reading.

</p><p>For the manuscript of this book the author received but seven
hundred dollars.  The publishers have sold over two hundred thousand
copies of "The Call."  This is a conservative estimate of the sales.  It
is said that the publishers are paying this gifted writer a royalty in
addition to the mere pittance first received for the manuscript.  In all
London has received about five

<pb n="375"/>

thousand dollars for "The Call of
the Wild."

</p><p>The volume known as "A Daughter of the Snows" was written at the
request of the Macmillan Company, who advanced the author one hundred
and fifty dollars per month, in order that he might write continuously
on the story.  This was London's first successful novel.

</p><p>In personal appearance London is not especially striking.  He has
light curly hair, blue eyes, square face, firm-set chin, and rather
prominent cheek bones.  He is of medium height, and now weighs about one
hundred and sixty pounds.  He is agile and strong, his training on the
seas having strongly developed the athletic in him.  In dress he is not
fastidious, and is very averse to social functions.  He cannot be coaxed
into a dress suit.  His favorite costume is the bicycle suit with
sweater or neglige shirt.

</p><p>There are two striking features of Jack London's career.  The one
is the tenacity with which, even in the most adverse circumstances, he
worked his ideal as a literary artist.  The other is his wonderful
success in putting a romantic and checkered experience into books so
acceptable to the reading public.

</p><p>Throughout his works are to be found unmistakable traces of the
motive of his work.  There is a growing sympathy with humanity.  There
is hatred of sham and pretense, of meanness and selfishness.  While he
consciously portrays the horrible, and uses it as a means of arousing
the interest of his readers, yet, in his extended novels, the good and
the true find ultimately a setting of peace and happiness.  While the
selfish as Mercedes, Hal, and Charles in "The Call of the Wild," or
Carter Wetherbee and Percy Cuthfert in "The Son of a Wolf" go down to
the miserable deaths which their meanness had prepared for them, yet
London always has a noble touch for the strong, rough, good-hearted
characters of the Northland.  One feels that it is a righteous will that
permits Buck of "The Call of the Wild" to earn the life of bliss which
finally came to him as leader of the wild wolfpack of the Northland.

</p><p>There is a deep spiritual significance in the mysterious voice
that beckoned the great, shaggy Buck back to the land of primordial
life.  In this call do we not ourselves hear a voice from out the
illimitable deep, a voice for those who possess the "restless,
unsatisfied longing," who have the eternal aspiration for the life that
now lives for us only in shadowy dreams, the life that is to be?

</p><p>Jack London himself has this infinite aspiration, this longing
for the unattainable.  It is this which marks him as a strong writer in
the new school of literature which is the product of the twentieth
century.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

