<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="BonMast"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;

]>


<TEI.2 id="BonMast">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Master Sold by a Slave</title>
<title type="sort">master sold by a slave</title>
<author>Bonner, John Stuart</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">8</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">BonMast</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475742</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>The print version was not illustrated.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Master Sold by a Slave</title>
<title type="sort">master sold by a slave</title>
<author>John Stuart Bonner</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
<name/>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>McClure's</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1897">1897</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">McClure's</hi> 9 (June 1897): 709.</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1897">1897</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>African American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-12">December 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Deirdre Johnson, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header added, basic TEI markup added.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="709"/>
<head type="main">A MASTER SOLD BY A SLAVE.</head>
<head type="sub">BY JOHN STUART BONNER.</head>
<p>
ONE of the most successful negro speculators on the Peninsula in
the forties was a man named James Hubbard, who lived upon his own
estate near Yorktown, and was accounted one of the wealthiest men
in those parts.  He was a man of powerful physique and coarse
manners.  His hair and eyes were intensely black, and his
complexion so swarthy that he would have suffered by comparison
with many of the human chattels he dealt in.
</p><p>About the year 1845 James Murder, a young man, last in the
male line of one of the old colonial families, died suddenly,
leaving his large estate so involved that it was necessary to sell
off everything to satisfy his creditors.  Among his slaves was a
body-servant called "Mack," who was nearly the same age as his
deceased master.  The two had been reared together from infancy,
the slave had enjoyed the same advantages as the master, and
through association with the best society of many countries had
acquired an ease of manner and fluency of speech which, combined
with his handsome person, would have made him an ornament to any
circle.  There was little negro blood in his veins, and he would
have passed as a white man anywhere.  He was held in high esteem by
all of Murder's friends.
</p><p>It was therefore determined that in the sale of Murder's
slaves Mack should be saved from the hands of the speculators, and
a number of gentlemen attended at the court-house in Williamsburg
prepared to pay a large price for the young negro.  James Hubbard
was also there, and he swore an oath that he would have "that
nigger" if it cost him his fortune.  For Hubbard had a twofold
grudge to gratify.  Many a time before, the Williamsburg men had
prevented him from securing a "bargain"; and he was very bitter
against them also because of the social ostracism which his
business had brought upon his family.  The result was that Mack was
knocked down to Hubbard for a price seldom paid for a slave in
Virginia.  A few days later Hubbard started South with a band of
negroes, taking Mack with him as a body-servant.
</p><p>On their arrival at New Orleans Hubbard soon disposed of his
negroes to good advantage, but, either because he could not find a
buyer at the high figure he had paid or because he had taken a
fancy to him, he retained Mack in his personal service.  Mack had
some money of his own, and, as a matter of pride as well as
business, Hubbard dressed him like a gentleman, and also allowed
him much liberty.
</p><p>Keeping carefully out of his master's way, Mack frequented the
various fashionable saloons and gaming houses, where he easily
passed as a Virginia planter, and contrived to form a considerable
acquaintance among the fast set of the day.  He was walking the
street one evening with one of these acquaintances, when his master
passed by on the opposite side.  "See that boy over there?" said
he, carelessly, indicating Hubbard.  "I brought him down here with
me, but he's got so independent that I've got to sell him."
</p><p>"What will you take for him?"
</p><p>"Why, he ought to bring me fifteen hundred quick, but I'll
take a thousand if it can be arranged quietly."
</p><p>In less than twenty-four hours they had come to terms, and
Hubbard was sold by his own slave.  The papers were regularly made
out and transferred, and the money paid over, Mack only stipulating
that the buyer should take his property quietly.
</p><p>When Hubbard was seized, of course there was trouble.  He
fought like a wildcat, but was finally overpowered and taken from
the fashionable hotel where he was staying, amid the jeers of his
quondam friends.  He appealed to the law; but not until three well-known citizens of Williamsburg, properly fortified with papers of
identification from the authorities, made the long trip to New
Orleans was he released.  The trial cost him thousands of dollars,
and consumed a great deal of time.  Meanwhile Mack, well supplied
with money by the sale, had got beyond pursuit.  Large rewards were
offered for his apprehension, and the best detectives were
employed, but without avail.  He was never traced beyond the wharf
where he took passage for the North.  He is supposed, however, to
have gone to France, where he had lived during his former master's
student days.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

