<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="BouHist"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>


<TEI.2 id="BouHist">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"The Negro's Place in History"</title>
<title type="sort">the negros place in history</title>
<author>Boughton, Willis, 1854-1942</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>Jennifer Hanna University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">27</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">BouHist</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475745</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This article first appeared in <hi rend="italic">The Arena</hi> 16 (Sept. 1896): 612&mdash;621.</p>
</note>
<note>
<p>Copy consulted: UVa. Library call number: AP 2 .A6</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"The Negro's Place in History"</title>
<title level="j">The Arena</title>
<title type="sort">the negros place in history</title>
<author>by Prof. Willis Boughton of Ohio State University</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>41 v. : ill. ; 26 cm.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Arena Publishing Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston, MA</pubPlace>
<date value="1896">1896</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This article appeared in vol. 16 (June-Nov. 1896),
p. 612-621.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1896">1896</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>African American</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>LCSH</term>
<term>Afro-Americans|xSocial conditions|y19th century.</term>
<term>Social change|zUnited States|xHistory|y19th century.</term>
<term type="Field651">United States|xSocial conditions|y1865-1918.</term>
<term>Slavery|zUnited States|xHistory|y19th century.</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-10-01">Oct. 1, 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Cataloger</resp>
<name>Jackie Shieh, University of Virginia Library, Cataloging
Services Dept.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>TEI header revised.  Access points and subject headings
added.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="1995-11-27">November 27, 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Jennifer Hanna</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI compatible header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
	<pb n="612"/>
<head type="main">THE NEGRO'S PLACE IN HISTORY.</head>
<head type="sub">BY PROF. WILLIS BOUGHTON OF OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY.</head>

<p>During the life of mankind every generation has been
confronted with one or more grave social questions the solution of
which seemed, at the time, to be of vital importance to the
progress of civilization.  So, too, every age has had its
alarmists, who have preached wars and desolation and the utter
destruction of existing institutions.  But civilization has moved
onward.  Every age and every generation has indeed proved equal to
its emergencies.  Though the champions of a principle be tried by
the crucial test of wars, though French revolutions and American
rebellions enact their bloody scenes, the fittest survives, the
most vigorous principle conquers, the world advances in culture.
Only the extreme pessimist will deny that the world is to-day
better than it has ever been before, that people are more cultured,
more humane, more Christ-like.  The nations of our day are better
able to grapple with difficult social problems than were their
ancestors.  Under the most threatening portents there is no
occasion for undue alarm.  Regulated by the laws of universal
progress, the right principle will, in the end, prevail, for
mankind will not rush madly onward to the destruction of cherished
institutions.
</p><p>Honest agitators are necessary to the solution of any social
problem; but the negro question has been the hobby of the American
alarmist ever since the first cargo of black slaves was landed at
Jamestown.  There is, however, a bright side to the entire history
of the American negro.  The African is brought to our shores as a
rude, uncultured savage; he is forced into the most intimate social
relations with a highly civilized class of whites; he imbibes much
from contact with the culture of one of the most enlightened
nations of the world; the females become the mothers of numbers of
half-white slave children; the race itself, under the moulding
influence of peculiar environment, becomes a new race, lighter in
color, stronger in intellect, superior in culture&mdash;"the Afro-American race." </p>
<pb n="613"/>

<p>By the abolishment of slavery our country made a great stride
in the line of progress.  That cursed institution removed, the
whole land seemed to rise from the ashes of war with phoenix-like
vigor, to flourish with a lusty strength unknown under the blight
of slavery, and to lead the world in enterprising undertakings.
But what a great change for the negro!  Just at the right moment,
when the slave had risen as high in culture as he could under the
restraining laws of bondage, when the dusky savage had become a new
being, the fetters of servitude were stricken asunder, and a future
was opened to the Afro-American whereby he might aspire to the
highest attainable condition of enlightenment.
</p><p>Having been made a free man and an American citizen, the
progress of the negro has been phenomenal.  Without original
capital even to the amount of that unfortunate one talent, many
individual members of this despised race are accumulating fortunes;
forbidden to learn to read or write, thousands are becoming as
proficient in those accomplishments as are their white neighbors;
taught that laws of marriage and of morality had no place in the
social creed of the slave, there are now thousands who are leading
purer and more moral lives than are numbers of our own proud,
superior race; born, every one of them, bastards, there is now not
a greater percentage of illegitimate births among the negro
population of the black belt of Alabama than there is among the
inhabitants of the kingdom of Bavaria.  (Mayo in Mohonk Conference
Report, 1890, page 44.)  Surely the alarmist must look elsewhere
for material with which to intimidate the thoughtful.
</p><p>But pass for a moment into details.  It may be said without
charge of hyperbole that the progress of these negroes during their
quarter of a century of freedom has been phenomenal.  "The colored
people of the South," says Judge Tourgee in a recent speech, "have
accomplished more in twenty-five years, from an industrial point of
view, than any people on the face of the earth ever before achieved
under anything like such unfavorable conditions."  Biddle
University, North Carolina, was built under the management of a
colored master carpenter.  Though both white and colored laborers
were employed, he was of all by far the best workman.  As a penman
the negro excels.  One of the two teachers of penmanship employed
in the Cincinnati public schools is a colored man, and he is
universally liked and
<pb n="614"/>
respected by the white pupils who
come under his instruction.  There is a very successful colored
physician in Nashville.  In Atlanta there is a colored dentist,
many of whose patrons are prominent white people.  W. E. Dubois has
not only won the first oratorical prize, but a three-hundred-dollar
scholarship as well&mdash;and this too at Harvard, "where the
contestants are the <hi rend="italic">elite</hi> students of the white race in that
ancient seat of learning."  But still more encouraging is the
astonishing fact that there are sixteen thousand negro school
teachers employed in the South in the work of educating their
fellows.  These are only ripples, but they harbinger the flood that
is to follow, or rather prove the current that flows deep and
strong beneath.
</p><p>In the midst of such proofs of the progressive tendency of the
race arises the question of the fitness of the negro for United
States citizenship.  The ballot has undoubtedly been one of the
greatest educators of the colored people.  In order to cast the
ballot with a degree of intelligibility equal to that of the
whites, numbers have been induced to sacrifice many comforts in
order to learn to read and write.  Others, realizing that the
avenues to power are open to the educated only, have sought a
preparation that would fit them, as well as members of the more
favored race, for positions of honor or of power.  Great numbers
are now qualified intelligently to exercise the right of suffrage,
while the masses are just as capable of voting as are the ruling
elements in our great cities.  Indeed, it can be no more galling to
the white man of the black belt of the South to submit to negro
rule, than it is for the truly conscientious American citizen in
our great cities to realize that his precinct is controlled by the
votes of the vicious from the scum of European life.  The policy of
our government in giving the negro the ballot has not been a
mistaken one.  It was best for these colored people to receive at
once their freedom and the ballot; it is still best for them to
remain full citizens of our country; it will ennoble their future
and make them a race of men.  They are deserving of the full rights
of citizenship.  "You cannot find one dynamiter among them, you
cannot find a single socialist or anarchist among them, nor a
secret society of any kind whose object is to undermine our
Christian institutions.  You have these classes all over your
northern country.  These eight million colored men are loyal to our
government."  (Mohonk Conference Report, 1890, page 17.)
</p>
<pb n="615"/>

<p>In our own country, then, the negro race has proved itself
progressive without limitation.  Advancement in culture has been
continuous ever since the first handful was landed on our shores&mdash;
and that too under discouragements such as no other people have
encountered.  Thus far we can rejoice in the happy solution of one
of our most difficult social problems.  The hand that has guided
these people has not led them astray.  Their paths have been dark,
but the day dawns.  The alarmist, however, does not care to recall
the past; he prefers to view, with a disordered imagination, the
future, and his visions are painted with the gloomiest forebodings.
Let us, then, look into the future.  But in order to realize the
capabilities of the negro race, we must fully understand the remote
past history of the blacks as a race.
</p><p>The question "Has the negro race at any period of time or in
any country on the globe been a factor in the history-making of the
world?" has, in the course of the agitation of the race question,
been asked repeatedly.  Most assuredly he has been an important
element in the history-making of the entire globe.  Though such a
statement be surprising to some and contrary to the commonly
accepted belief, it is nevertheless true.  Whenever the above
question is asked, the imagination of man forthwith pictures the
naked savage in the heart of the African continent as an example of
the negro at the summit of his attainments in all that goes to make
what we call civilization.  So even, with just as great a claim to
reason, may the Chinese mandarin point to the semi-savage Galchan
of the Hindu Kush region to illustrate the highest type of Aryan
culture, because this child of the mountains may have redder hair
and whiter skin than the ordinary representative of the Aryan race
in southern Europe.
</p><p>The black race has a history.  In fact all history is full of
traces of the black element.  It is now usually recognized as the
oldest race of which we have any knowledge.  The wanderings of
these people since prehistoric history began have not been confined
to the African continent.  In Paleolithic times the black man
roamed at will over all the fairer portions of the Old World.
Europe as well as Asia and Africa acknowledged his sway.  No white
man had as yet appeared to dispute his authority in the vine-clad
valleys of France or Germany or upon the classic hills of Greece or
Rome.  The black man preceded all others and
<pb n="616"/>
carried Paleolithic culture to its very height.  But the history of all
lands has been only a record of succeeding races.  Old races have
often been supplanted by those of inferior culture but of superior
energy.  More often, however, by fusion of different racial types
and by the mingling of various tribes and peoples, have been
evolved new races superior to any of the original types.
</p><p>The blacks were a fundamental element in the origin not only
of the primitive races of southern Europe, but of the civilized
races of antiquity as well.  History may be said to begin in
ancient Egypt, and recede into the dim past just as far as records
and inscriptions lend us light; still in the Nile valley we find a
civilization that has drawn from all succeeding ages expressions of
wonder and admiration.  This first example of a civilization was an
isolated one; it had evolved right there in that wondrously happy
region.  Surely these ancient Egyptians were a remarkable people;
but who were they?  The ruling tribes are called Hamites&mdash;the
"sunburnt" family according to Dr. Winchell; of Negritic origin,
says Canon Rawlinson.  But back of these ruling Hamites were a
"light-hearted" people,&mdash;"gay," "good-natured," "pleasant,"
"sportive," "witty," "droll," "amorous,"&mdash;such are the descriptive
terms used in telling the story of those primitive tribes who, Dr.
Taylor says, lived peaceably in those regions for two thousand
years before the advent of Asiatic invaders.  Suggestive as they
may seem, such terms are truly descriptive of the inhabitants whom
we would expect to find in the Nile valley in ancient times.  They
were probably as purely Negritic as are the great mass of our own
Afro-Americans.
</p><p>If the colored Egyptian, beginning at the zero point of
culture, could independently evolve a civilization, having had no
model, what can we not hope from the American negro, who has for a
model the highest civilization that the world has ever seen and who
has already proved himself such an apt scholar?  Let no one, then,
visit Egypt and view her pyramids, her obelisks, her temples, her
tombs, her sphinx, and still claim that the blacks have no place in
history.  They furnish the almost isolated example of a
civilization developed without a model, even though other racial
factors may have entered into that civilization.
</p><p>When the Hamites and their kindred were at the height of their
power, their influence extended to far greater limits
<pb n="617"/>
than is ordinarily supposed.  They pressed toward the confines of
Europe; they entered and took possession of the land.  "The
Iberians," says Dr. Winchell (<hi rend="italic">North American Review</hi>,
September, 1884), "entered by the Pillars of Hercules.  They came
from northern Africa at a time when the Hamitic Berbers were
gaining possession.  They overran the Spanish peninsula, founded
cities, built a navy, carried on commerce, extended their empire
over Italy, as Sicanes, when Rome was founded, long before the sack
of Troy, and from Italy passed into Sicily. . . .  The Pelasgic
empire was at its meridian as early as 2500 B. C.  This people came
from the islands of the AEgean, and more remotely from Asia Minor.
They were originally a branch of the sunburnt Hamitic stock, that
laid the basis of civilization in Canaan and Mesopotamia, destined
later to be Semitized. . . .  Rome itself was Pelasgian from the
fourteenth century to 428 B. C.  But in Italy and Greece the
Hamitic stock was displaced and absorbed by Aryan, as in Asia it
had been by Semitic."
</p><p>The Hellenes were the Aryans first to be brought into contact
with these sunburnt Hamites, who, let it be remembered, though
classed as whites, were probably as strongly Negritic as are the
Afro-Americans.  These Hellenes were savages or barbarians.  But
Aryan strength and energy were thus brought into contact with
Hamitic culture.  Then occurred that great struggle of centuries
for social equality between the blond Aryan and the Pelasgian, the
dark child of the soil.  Greece thus had her race social question
to settle, and it was settled by <hi rend="italic">fusion</hi>.  Had it not been
for that mixture of dark blood in the Greek composition, that race
of poets, artists, and philosophers would never have existed.
</p><p>Rome, even, had her race social problem.  There was also a
struggle between the white and the dark races.  The oppressed
Plebeians finally seceded to the Sacred Mount until their wrongs
were in a measure redressed.  Intermarriage, or fusion, at last
settled the question.  Such, too, is the story that Spanish
ethnology tells.  "Clearly there does not exist in Europe a nation
of tolerably pure ethnic character, nor do national boundaries mark
the limits of such ethnic strains as remain discoverable.  The
figment of a German nationality or a French, in any ethnic sense,
is as baseless as that of an Austrian, a British, or an American.
The mixture
<pb n="618"/>

is a conglomerate, not an alloy.  Ethnic
peculiarities are everywhere protrusive; they refuse to be
obliterated."  (Dr. Winchell, <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>)  Those drops of cursed
black blood were just as necessary to produce the ethnic character
of the Spaniard or Roman as were the white, and generations
probably passed away before it was noticeable as to which element
predominated.  Still it would be deemed the height of discourtesy
sneeringly to inquire, What makes the Greek, the Italian, or the
Spaniard dark in color?  It is fitting that we realize, however,
how great a factor the negro has been in the history-making of the
world.
</p><p>In our own country this race social question began under
conditions somewhat different.  Ignorant and even barbarous blacks,
from the uncultured regions of Africa, were made the slaves of an
enlightened race of whites.  In slave times fusion became so rapid
that, at their emancipation, there were great numbers in whose
veins the blood of white and black mingled in about equal
proportions.  Nor has this fusion ceased.  "The number of light-complexioned people of color," says the <hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi> (May 25,
1889), "one sees everywhere in the South suggests painful
reflections; and the fact that many of the light-complexioned are
children shows that the process of miscegenation still goes on."
There is nothing strange or surprising in this; it is simply God's
way of creating a new race.  Two races have never yet dwelt
together for any length of time without commingling; and fusion
will no doubt be the final solution of the race problem in our
country.
</p><p>Though the above view of the question is unpopular and even
repulsive, though some one has said that the "horror of
amalgamation may be dismissed as a misbegotten goblin of folly and
prejudice" (<hi rend="italic">Andover Review</hi>, December, 1889), theory points
to the experience of the past, while practice seems to be
confirming the inevitable teachings of history.  There is no
occasion, however, for sounding the alarm.  Fusion has thus far
gone on simply at the will of those parties who have found pleasure
in such mingling.  It is very evident that a great many otherwise
respectable white men have not found the idea of illegal fusion
repulsive.  Is that man who could, in slave times, so deaden the
instinctive tenderness of the parent as to send his own half-breed
children to the auction block, degraded by becoming the lawful
companion of the negro woman whom he compelled to minister
<pb n="619"/>
to his brutal nature?  Is that man who can, shamelessly and often
openly, pass his leisure in the presence of his colored mistress,
too supreme a being to be that woman's legal husband?  Is it more
honorable for him to rear about him a brood of bastard offspring
than to be the husband of the woman of his choice and the legal
father of his children?  Which is the more repulsive?
</p><p>In this matter of fusion there is no compulsion.  In a country
like our own it is optional to every white man or woman to
associate with the negro or not.  If any one finds gratification in
such an alliance, why should those who differ from him in taste
become horrified at his seeming depravity?  Even carrion is not
repulsive to the buzzard.
</p><p>Still the cry of the alarmist sounds in our ears, and he would
have us believe that fusion will be complete within a generation or
two.  Nothing of the kind.  It is a slow process; it has been in
operation in southern Europe for twenty-five centuries, and still
it is incomplete.  Eternity is long enough to produce this result.
Five centuries hence, no doubt, the census enumerator will find
thousands whom he shall be obliged to designate as "black," though
it is hoped that the stigma attached thereto shall have been
removed.  There is evolving in our land an American race&mdash;a race
that shall be the product of more peoples mingled than have ever
before met in any region of the earth.  Perhaps this alloy of negro
blood is an essential element in our race formation, and has been
placed here by the Creator to be used in producing a people that
shall, in its day, be as peculiarly gifted as were the Greeks or
Romans in their time.
</p><p>In their ignorance and foolishness those who most deplore the
social degradation of the times are removing the natural barriers
against fusion.  In some of the southern States "there still exists
an immoral and absurd law making penal the marriage of a white man
with a colored woman&mdash;immoral, because it encourages concubinage;
absurd, because it utterly fails to hinder that mixture of races
which it is designed to prevent."  (<hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi>, May 25,
1889.)  The very social ostracism into which it is intended to cast
these unfortunate people will operate against those who profess to
despise the negro.  So long as the negro race is made to feel that
it is "despised and rejected of all men," so long will
<pb n="620"/>
the colored woman feel that she is socially elevating herself and her
children by association with a white man, no matter if the
connection be irregular according to the dictates of our Christian
institutions.  So long as a "cultured Christian woman," chagrined
at the knowledge that negro blood flows in her veins, can exclaim,
"I would lie down and be flayed without a murmur, if I might only
rise up white," so long are the whites holding out the strongest
possible temptation to every colored woman, for her children's
sake, to seek an alliance, however illicit, with a white man.
</p><p>The barriers are being removed, though unconsciously, in other
ways.  The negroes are becoming, through education, fitted for all
positions and departments of life.  Individuals are even now
attaining positions of rank and distinction.  Let a colored man
reach a position of influence, and the road is open at once, if he
so chooses, for his marriage with a very respectable white woman.
Recall, if you will, a few years since, in our national capital,
the marriage of the greatest of Afro-Americans.  Such examples are
rare, but others of scarcely less note are known.
</p><p>Were the alarmist to seek for a sign more foreboding than any
other, he might find it in the rapidity with which this despised
race is accumulating property.  Gold will remove even the curse of
blood.  Let the negro become wealthy, and the doors of social
equality will soon be thrown open for his entrance.  Had the
colored maiden a dower of a few thousand dollars, there is many a
white man who would fall at her feet and offer her legal marriage.
Individual negroes are rapidly accumulating fortunes, and the above
conditions are extremely probable.  The time may come when the
American white girl, proud of her pure Teutonic lineage, will find
the wealthy brunette of doubtful lineage a winning competitor in
the purchase, for a husband, of a broken-down foreign nobleman.  So
long as money is the chief consideration, such misalliance in
either case would be revolting to the true American.
</p><p>Foreign immigration will have a tendency to break down the
barriers between the races.  The foreigner does not feel,
naturally, an aversion toward such an alliance as does the
American, who remembers the days of slavery.  Even the English
emigrant who returns to his native land with a colored bride does
not seem to be socially ostracized.  The Afro-American, modified by
the peculiar environment of our
<pb n="621"/>
civilization, bleached by
a semi-fusion already completed, educated, enlightened, above all
possessed of some property, will become a fit subject for the
cupidity of the great bulk of foreigners who become immigrants to
our shores.  The one forms an alliance with a more highly respected
race; the other obtains at once the gold for which he is so greedy.
</p><p>Is there anything alarming or horrifying in this view of the
question?  It is simply a matter of choice on the part of every
individual who forms a misalliance.  Our own generation or the next
will see no great change.  Let the work of education and
enlightenment go forward; let the negro be fully prepared for
places of distinction; let all laws forbidding the marriage of
whites and blacks be swept from the statute books, so that whatever
unions are formed may be legal and whatever children are born may
be legitimate.  Then, should fusion take place, the colored element
need not be totally degenerating.  This great question will be
solved only when all men can say with Dr. Hall (Mohonk
Conference Report, 1890): "I do not care whether a man is black or
white or yellow or chocolate-colored, if he has in himself the idea
of Christ, of doing as Christ did when He sat by the well in this
low world of ours.  If he has time to visit the hungry and the
weary and the sad, he is good enough for me."</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
