<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="BraType"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>


<TEI.2 id="BraType">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Strange Tale of a Type-Writer</title>
<title type="sort">strange tale of a type writer</title>
<author>Brackett, Anna C.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">22</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">BraType</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475750</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Strange Tale of a Type-Writer</title>
<title>Harper's New Monthly Magazine</title>
<title type="sort">strange tale of a type writer</title>
<author>Anna C. Brackett</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harper</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1890-10">Oct 1890</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>81</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Brackett, Anna C.  "The Strange Tale of a Type-Writer."
<hi rend="italic">Harper's New Monthly Magazine</hi> 81 (Oct. 1890): 679-682.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1890-10">October 1890</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction ; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-11">November 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Checked for completeness; Added header; Tagged with TEI.2-compatible
SGML; Verified that text parses against "teilite" dtd.
Made following changes according to print text:
page 682 changed "is his own language" to "in his own language"</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">


<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" id="d3">
	<pb n="679"/>	
<head>THE STRANGE TALE OF A TYPE-WRITER.<lb/>
BY ANNA C. BRACKETT.</head>
<p>I HAD  a favorite type-writer &mdash; I will not say of whose
manufacture &mdash; with which, through much use of it, I became very
intimate.  That expression I use boldly, because everybody knows
already that many among modern machines have a definite character,
and that even individual character is observed in those of the same
sort.  The engine-driver, for example, will tell you that each
locomotive of a lot made to be precisely similar will be found to
have, so to speak, its own temperament and manner, and that he
becomes attached to his own engine as to a person.
</p><p> So my type-writer became to me individual, and even
intelligent.  It had moods, captious or sunny, and sometimes it
seemed even humorous.  And as for intelligence, even before the
really wonderful thing happened that I am about to relate, I had
from time to time a strange though slight feeling that the machine
was acquiring that faculty; that the currents of thought passing
through it were stimulating its powers, developing its slight
individuality, and making orderly its fitful, irregular motions of
quasi-intelligence.  The machine, through much speaking, seemed to
be learning to think.  In what I may call its highest moments, it
seemed to meet or even to anticipate my action; outrunning the
pressure of my fingers, and recording sometimes, as I thought of
its own motion, the next following letter &mdash; not always the designed
one, but never, I believe, a letter which, taken with the preceding
ones, failed to spell correctly some word, though, perhaps, not the
word that I intended.  These appearances I took for accident
compounded with idle whimsies of my mind, since naturally I did not
suspect the truth.
</p><p> But at last, when the type-writer had been for a good period
in very hard use, and had acted, I know, more than ever as if it
had a daemon of its own, I was compelled to leave town for a few
days.  On my return, coming into my house with the comfortable
feeling which possesses one always on getting again among his own
belongings after any absence, it was, perhaps, the indulgence of
this feeling, as I made my way after a few minutes toward my work-room, that at first hindered me from noticing a slight clicking
sound, which, however, presently became clearly audible.  Upon
entering the first of two rooms, the second of which was the work-room, it was plain to me that some person was at work on my beloved
type-writer &mdash; a vast impertinence, since the rule of the house was
that no hands but mine should touch it.  But my vexation did not
make me incautious.  I advanced across the room too quietly to
afford notice of my approach, and looked through the half-open door
into the interior apartment.  I know myself to be very steady in
face of danger &mdash; the presence of anything to be done or to be
avoided is a tonic to me &mdash; and I am as far removed as most men from
craven fear, but I should not like to feel again the cold sensation
that came upon me when I discovered nobody in the room, and nothing
peculiar, save the type-writer working diligently by itself.
</p><p> I should mention, before I go any farther, that just before my
departure I had been experimenting with an invention of mine which
is intended to obviate the necessity of stopping to change the
sheets of paper when one has reached the bottom of a page.  It will
be evident that I cannot go into particulars on this invention, as
I have not yet secured the patent, and I might by so doing lose the
reasonable certainty of becoming at least a United States Senator
in a few years by a judicious use of the large fortune which I
shall, no doubt, have poured into my hands when the patent has been
once acquired.  Suffice it to say, then, that before being summoned
away, I had arranged a number of sheets of paper in my type-writer,
all ready for a little novelette which I had planned after the old
style of fairy stories, and I had already written the words, "Once
upon a time," when the telegram which called me away was put into
my hand.  My papyro-positor, as it is to be called, was not
attached to the machine when it began to write, and consequently
the sheets had not been gathered up as they would have been had
that been the case, but had dropped off as they were written, and
were lying loosely scattered on the floor and the table, just
<pb n="680"/>  where they had happened to fall as they had reeled off from
the type-writer.
</p><p> As I fairly caught sight of what was going on in the room, I
saw one of the sheets gradually slide off from the rack and fall
slowly to the table.  I have no idea for how long a time I stood,
but at last another partly written sheet fluttered to the floor,
and the machine ceased its motion.  In time &mdash; some time; I cannot
say how soon it was &mdash; I gathered up the scattered pages.  They
contained the following matter of the type-writer's own composing &mdash;
a sketch, a story, a little fantasy &mdash; one may name it as he pleases;
but there is nothing mechanical about it.  It has little breaks
here and there, as though for a moment the machine had been out of
order; but as to the substance of it, it shows invention,
constructive power, and delicate satire, with an airy audacity
entirely charming.
</p><p> When afterward, with some awe, I returned to use of the
machine, I found in it a distinct change of manner.  No less
intelligent or tractable than before, it was more quiet, less
impatient.  I have not known it once since to outrun my own
motions, nor has it ever again undertaken the task of original
production.  I think it is waiting to see its matter in print, and
when that occurs, I shall look with keen expectation for another
effort at composition, and shall give days and nights to watching
for this.  What now is troubling me is the question how, if the
type-writer should produce perhaps a masterpiece of literature,
could it get copyright, even in America?
</p><p> Here is the story which I found on the paper:

</p><p>                  "A TYPE-WRITER FANTASY.

</p><p> "Once upon a time there lived in a little house on the edge of
a thick wood an old woman who never had read any of Balzac's
novels.  It was not because she had not learned to read, for when
she was young she had gone for five weeks to the public schools of
New York; and that time, as everybody knows, is quite enough to
gain any branch of knowledge, since the schools are, as one may
say, absolutely perfect, so that even the children who try not to
learn are really compelled to absorb knowledge through the
atmosphere which has been successively diffused through all of them
by the high character of the Boards of Edcation.  I should have
said 'Education,' but such a trivial mistake is of no consequence.
The main reason why this old woman never had read Balzac's novels
was, to tell the truth, because there were absolutely none in the
country in which her house was situated.  And the reason for this
strange fact, which nevertheless was a fact, was that in the said
country there was a high protective tariff, so high as to be really
prohibitory.  And the highest duty of all in this tariff was,
strange to say, on French novels.  But this old woman had a cousin
on her mother's side who had been in France and Germany, and
although he could not remember whether it had been in France or
Germany that he had read Balzac, yet he was sure that it was in one
of the two.  The reason why he could not be sure was because he
spoke and read both these languages perfectly, so that he never
knew which he was reading or speaking.  This is one danger in
learning any language perfectly, even your own; and though this
last remark may seem absurd, it really is not so.  If we only
reflect a moment, we shall readily see that the more difficulty any
one has in saying anything the less likely is he to forget what he
has said.  This is why all good teachers always insist upon having
a child hunt for the places mentioned in his geography.
</p><p> "Though the young man could not remember, as I have said,
whether he had read Balzac's stories in French or in German, yet he
had been profoundly impressed by them; so profoundly, in fact, that
he could talk of nothing else after his arrival at his cousin's
house, and as the old woman was very anxious to make herself
agreeable, being naturally of a kind disposition, she became
convinced that if she was to maintain any part in the conversation
she must know something about the famous French writer.  But how to
find out, in the first place, to what country to go in order to
purchase the books?  That was the great question.  However, she
considered that a man is more likely to dream in the language that
he knows best, so she went to the police station and hired a
policeman for a year.  She did this because she knew that it is
always dangerous to generalize too hastily, as men generally do,
and that she should therefore be obliged to have reports from a
large number of dreams.  Moreover, her cousin being a thoroughly
healthy man, <pb n="681"/>  and having no business, might not dream every
night; and besides, she found she could get a policeman much
cheaper by the year than by the day.  (This is the reason why
Tammany keeps the New York policemen in its pay all the year
round.)
</p><p> "The experiment began, and every night the constant policeman
sat patiently at the bedside of the unconscious man, watching for
his slightest utterance.  At his side he had pen and paper, and
every syllable was carefully taken down.  At the end of the year
all the utterances were carefully examined, but when they came to
make out the required statistics, they could find nothing but
English words, and even those were much confused and broken, so
that it became necessary to send to New York for the services of
one of the public-school teachers there, who was accustomed to
making sense out of nonsense, and to calculating percentages, in
order to derive any benefit from the experiment.
</p><p> "The teacher came, and for the space of about five weeks spent
her entire time tabulating and calculating.  At the close of her
investigations she announced it as the profound conviction of her
mind, fortified by a long experience in the schools, that under the
supposition that the gentleman had spoken in German and French
instead of in English, as he had, he would have used fifty per
cent. of German words and fifty per cent. of French words.  She had
gone through this difficult calculation because the old woman had
especially desired her not to leave out of consideration any
possible element which might, under any circumstances, affect the
outcome.  There was naturally a little disappointment at this
somewhat ambiguous result, and disappointment was by no means
confined to the house where the experiment had taken place, for by
this time the whole village on the edge of which was the above-mentioned thick wood had become interested in the solution of the
question, so much so, indeed, that it had become necessary to
engage the services of an additional person to write off a bulletin
every hour as the calculation of the percentages progressed, in
order to satisfy public curiosity.  In fact, many of the wealthier
citizens of the village combined together and sent to the
neighboring city for the best electrician then known, and had him
construct a telegraph line from the old woman's house to their
homes in the village.  In this way they kept themselves informed at
every minute just how the calculations stood.  Those who could not
afford such a luxury used to send a special messenger at a given
time, when they were sure to find a bulletin hung up on the door of
the house, for the rings at the bell became so incessant that the
whole time of the old woman's servants was occupied in going to the
door to answer inquiries.  After the bulletin became an
institution, things grew a little better.  The old woman employed
a small boy whose whole duty it was to take care of the bulletin-board and to answer the questions of those who came to the door,
and so the servants could go on with their work.
</p><p> "Now, however, it had become evident that, if she was to find
out about Balzac, she must employ some other way.  She turned it
over and over in her head, for the difficulties she had encountered
had by no means diminished her desire to read the famous writer
about whom she had heard so much.  At last she said, 'I will go and
find out for myself.'  So she went to the city to buy a steamer
ticket; but when she was obliged to tell the ticket agent her
destination, she was not at all able to say where it was that she
wanted to go.  The ticket agent was polite but firm, so, in
despair, at last the old lady exclaimed, 'I will take a ticket for
both countries, and settle the matter that way.'  At this happy
solution of the difficulty the agent beamed with satisfaction, and
the old lady went home in comparatively a comfortable frame of
mind.  When she came to get ready for the voyage, she began to
wonder how she was to go on two steamers at once; or if not, how
she was to decide.  The whole matter seemed to be still involved in
difficulties, and she began almost to wish that her mother had
never been born at all, because then she never should have had a
cousin on her side, and never should have heard of Balzac.  But
this thought seeming somewhat impious, she banished it from her
mind, and confined herself to the milder wish that her cousin had
gone to visit some other relative than herself.  That did not seem
so wrong.
</p><p> "But as the interest on the two tickets she had bought kept
mounting up, she decided that she must do something; so she went to
see the agents of the two steamship lines, and at last succeeded in
indu-<pb n="682"/> cing them to start on the same day and at the same
hour.
</p><p> "The day came at last, and the two steamers swung out from
their berths.  The pier was black with people, among whom were all
the newspaper reporters of the neighboring city, and many from
other places in the country, who looked on with wonder, not unmixed
with admiration, as the ponderous vessels slowly went on their way,
bearing between them, suspended in a rude but strong steel hammock,
the woman to whose desire for knowledge, persistence, and
indomitable courage the whole idea was due.  It was feared by some
of those who are always ready to raise objections to any scheme,
however desirable, that some difficulty might arise at the opening
of the English Channel, where it would become necessary, according
to the usual order, for the two vessels to separate; but by this
time the community had acquired such abounding faith in the
ingenuity of the old woman, and such admiration for her pluck, that
they waited, not without doubt certainly, but without any real
fear, the outcome of the arrangements which they were sure she
would be able to make when the proper time should come.  One result
of the plans already carried out was that the old woman did not
suffer at all from sea-sickness, for it was found, to the great
astonishment of the passengers, that the motion of one vessel
completely neutralized the motion of the other; so that while the
other passengers suffered much from the tossing of the sea, which
was unusually rough for that time of year, the indomitable old
woman voyaged in the most perfect calm.  At this sight many of the
more wealthy of them, who were also some of the more sea-sick,
ventured to ask if she would not rent a few feet of her hammock to
them, and as the old woman had more room than she absolutely needed
for herself, except at meal-times, she gladly acceded to their
request, and by that means gained more than enough to pay for the
expenses of her voyage, laying up sufficient at the same time to
purchase a complete edition of Balzac's works.  There was one
little difficulty here, because she was not sure whether to lay up
this money in napoleons or in gulden.  But she finally decided till
she arrived at her destination before doing this, because, as she
remarked to one of her tenants, 'You see, I don't really know
positively where I am going.'
</p><p> "As the ships approached the English Channel, expectation
deepened into a state of feverish anxiety, and the steward found
that the passengers did not eat so much as formerly.  But they
might have saved themselves any trouble, and the old lady had been
quite right in waiting to change her extra money, for just as they
sighted the Scilly Islands they perceived a large vessel bearing
down upon them.  The flag that she carried was unknown to the
captain, who therefore regarded her with considerable anxiety.  It
represented, as well as they could make it out, a large eagle,
hovering in a ground of different colors, and was of enormous size.
The captain ran up a signal of distress, which was soon answered by
the strange vessel's coming alongside.  The excitement was at its
highest pitch when an officer, dressed in a uniform like the flag,
leaped from one deck to the other, and at once proceeded to the
captain's state-room.  Here he remained for but a short time, when
both officers relieved all anxiety by returning with smiling faces,
smoking amicably one cigar, which was lighted at the middle.
</p><p> "After a short pause, full of an uncertain joy on the part of
the passengers, the captain announced that France had been so
impressed with the character of the young German Emperor that she
had thought herself probably safer under his rule than under that
of any Frenchman.  She had accordingly made an offer of herself to
the Germans, who had joyfully accepted the offer, and the two
countries were formally united under the name of 'The Franco-German
Republic.'  Everybody was pleased at this news, especially the old
lady, all of whose difficulties had thus been happily removed, and
the wisdom of whose course in not changing sooner her spare cash
was now fully manifest.  Of course, as the two countries had become
finally one, it made no practical difference to her whether Balzac
had written in French or German, especially as now she happened to
remember that she could read neither language.  She returned safely
home in the next steamer, much improved by her trip, and a full
account of the whole affair was printed in a large octavo volume,
which appropriately bore for its motto, 'Always read an author in
his own language.'"
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
