<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="BroBach"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="BroBach">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Bachelor's Fancy</title>
<title type="sort">bachelors fancy</title>
<author>Brown, Alice</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Charles Keller</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">33</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">BroBach</idno>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475751</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Bachelor's Fancy</title>
<title level="j">The Atlantic Monthly: A Magazine of Literature, Science, Art, and Politics. Vol. 93, no. 555.</title>
<title type="sort">bachelors fancy</title>
<author>Alice Brown</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pages 37-45</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Houghton, Mifflin and Company. | The Riverside Press.</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston and New York. | Cambridge, Mass.</pubPlace>
<date value="1904-01">January 1904</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa library, call no.: AP2.A8</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1904">1904</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; fiction</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-10">October 1997</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">



<div1 type="story" id="d3">
	<pb n="37"/>
<head>BACHELOR'S FANCY.</head>

<p>CYNTHIA GALE sat by the window in
the long shed chamber, her hands at momentary
ease. She was a slight, sweet
creature. with a delicate skin, and hair
etherealized by ashen coverts. Her eyes
were dark, and beauty throbbed into
them with drifting thoughts. Cynthia
was tired. She had been at work at
the loom since the first light of day, and
now she had given up to the languor of
completed effort, her head thrown back,
her arms along the arms of the chair,
in an attitude of calm. Her hair had
slipped from its coil, and fallen on
either side of her face in gentle disarray.
She was very lovely.
</p><p>The room, the scene of her toil and
resting, was dark with age and significant
in tokens of a disused art. The
loom stood well in the centre, its great
upright beams obstructing the light
from window to window. All about
were the lesser implements of a weaver's
trade: the linen wheel, the reels
and swifts. On a chest were skeins of
indigo-blue yarn Cynthia had dyed, and
near by, the flaxen thread she had
unearthed from an ancient hoard under
the rafters. At last, she knew how to
weave. She had walked a weary way
in the pursuit of her trade, and now she
had reached the first of many goals.
</p><p>The stillness of the autumn day made
a great world about her where everything
was happy because everything was
busy. A woodpecker settled on the
locust outside, and began drumming.
She looked out at him from the idleness
of a well-earned rest, and smiled.
It seemed to her a wonderful earth
where there was so much to do. From
first to last, she saw, creation moved
and toiled, and she moved with it.
Without conscious thought, she felt the
strength and beauty of the twisting
chain.
</p><p>Cynthia had come to happiness by a
<milestone unit="column"/>
long road. Her first memories were of
the poorhouse near the sea, where her
mother, a sad waif out of the drift of
life, had been swept, to die. Cynthia
knew nothing about her father, except
that he drank and played the violin.
People said he invented things, what
things she never heard. He was clever
with his hands and brain; but nothing he
had was used to his own advantage. He
was one of life's pensioners. Cynthia,
growing up at the poorhouse, seemed to
have no more to do with life as it is than
he. She did the housework set her as
her portion with an absent care, and
then escaped into the open for some
mysterious sustenance that she understood
as little as the people who watched
her ways. There were hours when,
tramping inland, she lay prone under
the pines in the pasture, smelling at life
and very happy. There were more when
she sat looking at a great island of fern,
entranced by something she could not
apprehend, and had no need to, because
feeling was enough. Though she did
her tasks, she was called lazy, and she
lived, in a sense, apart from people until
one day Andrew Gale, driving about
to buy cattle, met her in the country
road as she was coming home like Ruth
from her gleaning, only that Cynthia's
arms were piled with golden-rod instead
of grain. Her eyes were brimming
with still happiness. Her cheeks had
a bloom over their summer tan. Andrew
caught his breath and stared again.
The next day, after patient watching,
he found her by the sea, and again he
met her when she went to gather grapes.
In a month he married her and took her
home to the great house where he had
lived alone since his mother's death,
with only old Hannah to do the work
in a perfect fashion that left him lonelier
than before, in the solitude made
by her deaf ears.
   <pb n="38"/>
</p><p>Cynthia blossomed like a flower, and
from some inner secret of being she felt
like one. This was like growing in a
garden with fructifying soil, the sun
upon her and gentle rains, and one great
tree to shade her from too strong effulgence.
Andrew was the tree. He was
a silent creature, the emotion in him
hidden by a fine reserve; but he tended
and protected her until she grew worshipful
of him in a way neither of them
quite realized. All Cynthia's capacity
for love bloomed out in a fervor that
made her vivid, with a charm added to
her beauty. When they had been married
a few months, old Hannah died, and
then Cynthia, shrinking from a new presence
in their intimate solitude, did the
work alone. She threw it off easily
enough, without heart or fancy, and very
swiftly, to give her time to be with
Andrew in the fields or during his trips
over the countryside. Housework, to
her mind, was a dull means to life, only
made tolerable because Andrew was satisfied
with everything she did. It was
devoid of grace, not, like weaving, a
road to happy fantasy. In spite of it,
she kept the purely untrammeled habit
of life which lies in a perfect freedom,
with love at the end of each day's work.
Again her estate seemed to her like
that of the flowers of the field. She
had nothing to do but live and bloom.
</p><p>When she had been married a year,
her own individual passion came upon
her. One day she went up into the
shed chamber in search of an old saddle
Andrew remembered as one of the
family holdings, and found herself in a
mysterious workshop. This was the
weaving room. It had a strange look
of waiting, of holding secrets it was
ready to divulge, of keeping a strange
silence it might some time break. Instant
recognition laid hold on her. At
first it seemed curiosity; then it grew
into something more piquing. Thrown
upon a bench, as if the last weaver had
left it there, was a book written in a
delicate yet unformed hand, in faded
<milestone unit="column"/>
ink upon a yellowed page. She turned
it swiftly. There were the patterns for
weaving the old blue coverlets of which
the house already had a store. The
names made her breathless with their
sound of homely poesy: Bachelor's
Fancy, Girl's Love, Primrose and
Diamonds, Chariot Wheels and Church
Windows, Pansies and Roses in the
Wilderness. There were full directions
in the faded hand, and the patterns had
been made in the careful drawing of
one who rules her lines and works from a
pathetic ignorance. Cynthia ran downstairs
tumultuously, and unfurled the
book before Andrew where he sat mending
the harness.
</p><p>"See here!" she cried. "See what
I 've found."
</p><p>Andrew looked up with an abstracted
interest.
</p><p>"Oh," said he, "that's Argentine's
book."
</p><p>"Who was Argentine?"
</p><p>"She was great-grandmother Pyncheon's
sister. She was a great weaver.
She stuck to it when everybody else had
give it up. She was goin' to be married,
but he was lost at sea, an' after
that she never did much but weave.
Them coverlets you set such store by
were all hers."
</p><p>Cynthia had treasured the coverlets
with an unreasoning love. Their pattern
pleased her. The close firm weave
awoke respect, beside more modern fabrics.
New passion stirred in her from
that first interest.
</p><p>"O Andrew!" she breathed, "do you
s'pose I could weave coverlets?"
</p><p>It was not Andrew's custom to deny
anything in their little world.
</p><p>"I guess so," said he indulgently.
"I guess you could do anything you set
out to. Mebbe old Foss could put you
on the road."
</p><p>Old Foss lived a mile away, in a little
house filled with treasures of ancient
usage which he seemed to prize only
because collectors came at intervals and
fixed a market value in his mind. Next
   <pb n="39"/>
day Andrew hitched up and went down
to borrow him; but Foss clung to his
hearthstone. He could weave, he said,
but weaving had gone out. He guessed
with cotton cloth as cheap as it was
now, there's no need of wastin'
anybody's time over a loom. Next day,
Cynthia herself went down with her
book of patterns, and he gave her a few
grudging rules. Then she started on
her ignorant way, and to-day was the
culmination of long desire. Bachelor's
Fancy was in process of growth. It
was only a question of time when she
should have a coverlet of her own to
hoard with Argentine's.
</p><p>The silence in the shed chamber grew
more drowsy with the mounting day.
Suddenly Cynthia was aware that she
was more than half asleep, nodding
over the verge of something almost tangible,
it was so deep and still. She was
hungry, too, but that she scarcely knew.
A slice of bread and a cup of milk had
made her early breakfast, and since then
this breathless achievement had lifted
her outside the pale of daily needs.
But now she rose and went swaying
down the stairs, her eyelids heavy.
The house below was still. Andrew
had been away a week with the threshing
machine, leaving the next neighbor
to milk and "feed the critters." Cynthia
had half promised to go over to the
neighbor's house to sleep, but the passion
for weaving had so engrossed her
that now she scarcely knew light from
darkness, and the short intervals in her
work it seemed foolish to spend away
from home. Besides, she missed Andrew
less if she stayed in their familiar
places, where the walls were reminiscent
of him. In the bottom of her heart was
always a crying hunger for him, an
aching loneliness. But she could bear
it. She had the weaving and a child's
eager hope to bring him the work of
her own hands.
</p><p>Down there in the kitchen she looked
about and smiled a sleepy smile at
its disorder. Her plate and cup were
<milestone unit="column"/>
on the table, and there was a pile of
dishes in the sink. Even the milk
pails were unwashed, and she did shrink
momentarily under the guilt of that.
</p><p>"O my soul!" said she.
</p><p>Ashes had blown across the hearth,
and the kitten had rolled an egg from
the table to the rug. Through the open
bedroom door her unmade bed was
yawning. It was sweet and clean.
The sun lay brightly on the tick, and the
autumn breeze blew on snowy sheets.
Yet it was disorder, and Cynthia knew
it, as any housewife would know, or
any man used to the rigor of routine.
She was a slattern. Her house tattled
the tale even to her own eyes. Nevertheless,
she had achieved Bachelor's
Fancy, and her mouth curled in a smile
that widened to a pretty yawn. She
stretched herself out on the lounge and
went to sleep.
</p><p>There was a step on the threshold,
impatient, swift. Cynthia opened her
eyes from deep beatitude to a flood of
noon sunlight in the disordered room,
and a figure standing in the midst of
it. She rose to her elbow, pushing back
her hair. Then she gave a cry:&mdash;
</p><p>"Andrew! Andrew! O Andrew!"
She was on her feet, on tiptoe to fly to
him, but his face arrested her. "Andrew!"
she called, "what is it?"
</p><p>He had had a hard week. A man had
failed them, and he had been doing double
work, feeding the machine in dust
and heat and for two days with a beard
of barley in his eye. They had taken
the threshing by the job and he had put
it through madly, to get home to Cynthia,
spurred always by the certainty of
her loneliness, and half ashamed of his
childish worry over her. He was dead
tired, he was hungry, dirty, hot. Even
his face was blackened from the dust,
and little moist runners had streaked
and whitened it. The sight of him
amazed her, and she stood there a-wing,
ready to go to him, her child's cheeks
creased with drowsiness and her great
eyes dark. But something about his set
   <pb n="40"/>
mouth and glowing eyes forbade her
nearer greeting.
</p><p>"O Andrew!" she breathed again,
"I didn't think you'd come."
</p><p>"You didn't think I'd come? Why
didn't you?"
</p><p>Instantly there flashed into her mind
a story she had heard about the Gale
temper. Andrew was a slow man, the
neighbors said, "till you got him
roused. Then you better stan' from
under." Andrew had owned it to her
once, with a shamefaced grin. But after
his confession they had both laughed,
and she had felt his arms about her in
that mutual understanding which was
more than human trust, but a something
ineffable neither could define.
Now for the first time in her life there
was a barrier between them, invisible
but potent. She did not dare approach
him.
</p><p>"Why didn't you think so?" he repeated.
</p><p>She faltered in her answer. "You
said 't would be a week."
</p><p>"It's been a week. I said I'd be
here Thursday noon."
</p><p>"Yes"&mdash;she opened her mouth in
futile protest and then closed it. But
the truth came to her, and she told it
with a childlike confidence that it would
be the same to Andrew as to her. "I
got weaving. I forgot."
</p><p>"You got weaving!" he repeated.
Then he looked about the room, and its
disorder made satirical commentary on
her words. But Cynthia had gained
courage. The mention of her new triumph
reminded her that she had a joy
to bring him.
</p><p>"O Andrew!" she breathed, "I've
learned it. I've learned Bachelor's
Fancy. Mine's as good as Argentine's."
</p><p>Andrew stood looking at her for a
moment, her distended eyes, her pretty
mouth where the smile was just beginning,
and would come if he invited it.
But at that moment the smile was not
for him. It meant a child's absorption
<milestone unit="column"/>
in a foolish game, and oblivion of him
for whom there was hard work and
barley beards. He turned abruptly.
</p><p>"Well," he announced, "I've got
no more to say."
</p><p>He had taken a step toward the open
door, but her voice followed him. It
was sharp with quick alarm.
</p><p>"Andrew, where you goin'?"
</p><p>He turned upon her.
</p><p>"I'll tell you where I'm goin'. I'm
goin' on to Trumbull's with the thrashers,
an' get a meal o' victuals."
</p><p>"But, Andrew, I'll get dinner. I
can, in no time. There's eggs. You
like eggs, Andrew."
</p><p>"Mebbe you don't remember what
we said that last mornin' I set off. I
told ye I'd bring Miles an' t'other men
to dinner. It ain't been out o' my
mind a minute. For two days I've
been houndin' 'em to finish up, so's
we could git here this noon. What do
you s'pose I wanted to do it for? I
wanted to show off. I wanted to let
'em see how well we were fixed. An'
this kitchen don't look as if there'd
been a meal o' victuals cooked in it
sence the time o' Noah. It ain't a
kitchen; it's a hurrah's nest."
</p><p>"O Andrew!" She backed piteously
away from him, with a sudden,
alien sense of a house not her own.
She seemed to herself in that instant
to be not his wife, but a guest by whom
his hospitality had been abused. Then
again she trembled into speech. "Maybe
you've done with me, Andrew.
Maybe you don't want me to stay here
any more."
</p><p>"I don't care what ye do nor where
ye go," said Andrew blindly. "I'm
goin' to Trumbull's." He strode out
and away down the path, and she heard
him hailing the threshers at the gate.
They answered jovially, and then the
heavy team went grinding on.
</p><p>She sat down upon the couch and
looked about her. The sun came cruelly
in at the window, and showed the
room in all its dusty disarray. The
   <pb n="41"/>
dazed spot in her brain cleared, like a
lifting sedative, and left her vulnerable
to pain. She saw his house as he had
seen it, and for the instant felt how he
had hated it and her. With that certainty
she met also the ultimate pang
of youth which knows when its hour is
spoiled, and says, "This is the end."
There was but one thing to do. She
must take herself away. She went to
the cupboard and reached to the upper
shelf where old Hannah used to
keep her toothache drops. There was
laudanum enough in them, Andrew had
said, to kill an army. It would kill
her. But as she stood there in the
stillness with the bottle in her hand,
distaste came upon her for the ugliness
of such a death, and that moment,
sounding in her ears, she heard the sea.
Whether it was because she had begun
her life by it or through some quickness
of the mind, running over the possibilities
of a decent death, she remembered
a little mate of hers who had been playing
in a dory when the anchor slipped,
and had drifted out, never to be seen
again. And now the sea was calling
her.
</p><p>"You gimme a match, won't ye?"
called old Nancy Hutchens from the
door. "I won't come in. I'm all
over muck from the swamp down there.
I crossed by the willers, to save steps."
</p><p>Cynthia tucked the bottle back in its
place and crossed the kitchen swiftly,
taking a card of matches as she went.
Old Nancy stood there on the doorstone,
a squat figure with one shoulder
higher than the other. She had the
imposing equipment of an aquiline nose
and sound white teeth at seventy.
Her thick gray hair was drawn back
into a knot, and the lines in her brown
face were crisp and deep. A life solitary
in itself, and yet spent among people
in a drifting way, had touched her
face with little quizzical shades of
meaning. Her cold pipe was in her
hand, waiting to be filled.
</p><p>"Here's the matches," said Cynthia.
<milestone unit="column"/>
</p><p>Nancy took them with a mechanical
touch, and remained looking at her.
</p><p>"Law!" said she, "'t ain't wuth it."
</p><p>"What ain't?" repeated Cynthia.
</p><p>"What you've got on your mind,
whatever 't is. Wait a day an' it 'll be
a thing o' the past. If 't ain't in a
day, 't will be in a year, or ten year,
or a lifetime. Wait long enough, an'
the whole on us 'll be underground."
</p><p>"Yes," said Cynthia, "we shall be
underground." But her mind was not
with the old woman, but on her own
preparations for flight. The tawdry
room still troubled her, the slatternly
picture he must find when he came
home. She would leave his house in
order for him. "Look here, Nancy,"
said she suddenly, "you stay the rest
o' the day an' help me clean."
</p><p>Nancy smiled satirically. She looked
up at the blue sky, sown with flying
white, and then over the line of upland
where her fate, every day renewed, was
waiting for her.
</p><p>"I don't clean for myself," she
said. "My bed ain't been made nor
slep' in for a fortnight. I been trampin'
the countryside."
</p><p>"I'll give you a dollar!"
</p><p>"I ain't got much use for dollars till
winter time, an' then I guess I shall be
provided for. I got a passel o' herbs
to sell this fall." But she was searching
Cynthia's face with her impersonal
glance, and her mind altered. "Law,
yes!" said she. "It's as good a way
o' passin' time as any other. You let
me pull off these muddy boots. You
got a pair o' rubbers I can scuff round
in? Where you goin' to begin?"
</p><p>With the word, she had caught up
an old pair of Andrew's shoes beside
the shed door, and slipped her feet into
them. Cynthia left her, and went flying
upstairs with an unregarding haste.
She went first to the shed chamber, and,
without a glance at her precious handiwork,
closed the door upon it. Then,
running to the other rooms in turn, she
breathed dull satisfaction at finding
   <pb n="42"/>
them in comfortable array. There was
the west chamber; she had put that in
order when aunt Patten had been expected,
a week before, to spend the
night, and the other rooms had to match
it because aunt Patten would go mousing
round. Cynthia had laughed with
Andrew, in the doing, over so patently
setting her scene for a meddler. But
aunt Patten had diverged, on her visiting
way, and Cynthia's pains had
seemed unnecessary.
</p><p>At the foot of the stairs Nancy was
awaiting her. She had an air of large
leisure; yet in some subtle fashion her
man's attitude showed the reserve
strength in her and inspired content.
</p><p>"What be I goin' to fly at fust?"
she asked indulgently, as at a madness
not her own.
</p><p>"You sweep the sittin'-room," returned
Cynthia. "When the dust is
settled, you can do the winders. I 'll
begin on the bedroom."
</p><p>Cynthia did not, it seemed to her,
think at all as she went about her work,
doing it swiftly and still with the far-off sound of the sea in her ears. She
was simply a different creature from
that other happy woman who had been
weaving coverlets that morning. She
had brought upon herself a colossal
punishment. She never stopped to wonder
whether the punishment were just.
It was simply there.
</p><p>At one she and Nancy had some eggs
and tea, and in mid afternoon they met
in the kitchen, each about her task.
Cynthia was baking now, cream o' tartar
biscuits and custard pie, and Nancy
was cleaning the woodwork with great
sweeps of her lean arm.
</p><p>"I didn't know you was such a
driver," she said at length, as she sat
on the top of the step-ladder, taking a
pull at her pipe.
</p><p>"I guess I ain't been," said Cynthia,
her pretty brows in a painstaking
frown over the scalloped edges of the
pie. "I ain't done much housework."
</p><p>"You like it?" asked Nancy.
<milestone unit="column"/>
</p><p>A swift terror fled across Cynthia's
face, like a beating wing. At that moment
she liked housework better than
anything on earth. It was not a cold
routine. It had at last a poignant
meaning. It meant Andrew and her
home. But she answered stolidly, "I
guess so."
</p><p>"If you've took it on yourself,
you've got to like it," said Nancy
philosophically, rising and knocking the
ashes from her pipe. "You hand me
up that bar soap. That's the wust o'
menfolks. Once you've got 'em, you
got to slave for 'em. Lug 'em or leave
'em! But don't git 'em, I say. Look
here, now! Fifty year ago come November,
I said I'd marry a man down
Sudleigh way. I went to stay a spell
with his mother. Well, sir! I come
home an' I broke it off. `I ain't a-goin'
to spend my days makin' sugar gingerbread,'
says I. `No, sir! Nor cuttin'
it out in an oak-leaf pattern,&mdash;not by
a long chalk!' "
</p><p>"He likes sugar gingerbread," said
Cynthia to herself. "I guess I got
time to make some."
</p><p>"I warrant ye the colored pop'lation
never felt freer 'n I did when I see him
walkin' away down the path arter I
told him 't was broke off," chuckled
Nancy, moving the step-ladder along.
"I never had a minute's sorrer over it,&mdash;not a second."
</p><p>"I guess I'll put in a mite o' ginger,"
said Cynthia, stirring breathlessly.
"Do you use ginger, Nancy?"
</p><p>"Law! I dunno what ye do, it's
so long sence I've tried any. I don't
concern myself with sweet trade. I
can make as good a meal as I want out
o' crackers an' cheese an' wash it down
with a drink o' water out o' the well.
Look here! did it ever come into your
head that everybody ain't called to
preach, an' everybody ain't called to
marry?"
</p><p>"Some ain't fit," said Cynthia bitterly,
her passionate mind on her own
defects, "they ain't fit to marry."
   <pb n="43"/>
</p><p>"'T ain't only that,&mdash;they're like a
bird in a cage. You look here! menfolks
think they're dull sometimes, settled
down in a pint measure with one
woman. Lordymighty! the women's
dull, too, on'y they don't let on. Pious
little devils! they go round washin'
dishes an' moppin' up under the sto',
and half on 'em wants to be trampin'
like me, an' t'other half dunno what
they want. Keep out on 't, I say! keep
out on 't!"
</p><p>Nancy lifted her voice in a tuneful
stave, the words satirically fit, but Cynthia
was not listening. The notes fell
upon her like a patter of unregarded
rain, as she creased her gingerbread
and beat her mind back from futile
wonderment over her own plight when
Andrew should be here alone.
</p><p>"The house has got to be jes' so,"
pursued Nancy. "The woman's got
to be jes' so. They can come home all
over gurry, but she's got to have on a
clean apron an' her hair slicked up to
the nines. They can set all the evenin'
huskin' together an' hootin' over
old stories, an' come stumblin' in when
they git ready, an' find doughnuts an'
pie set out complete. What's fair for
one's fair for another, I say."
</p><p>"No, it ain't!" cried Cynthia, suddenly
awakened. She stood straight and
slender in the middle of her kitchen.
Defensive fires burned hotly in her
eyes. "Nancy, I ain't goin' to have
such talk in here. I can't stand it.
You think of him gettin' all over dust
an' dirt workin' like a dog. You think
of it, Nancy! It's his house. It's
no more 'n right he should have it the
way he wants it. I should like to know
if he ain't goin' to have anything the
way he wants it?" Her voice choked
in passionate championship of the man
whose pride was hurt.
</p><p>But Nancy only gave a derisive
chuckle. "Law!" said she. "You
needn't worry. I guess they'll look
out for themselves. I never see a man
yet but had time enough for that."
<milestone unit="column"/>
</p><p>At five o'clock the house was in
order and Nancy had started on her
homeward way, a dollar in her pocket,
and, despite some ruthless indifference
on her part, a basket of food in her
hand. Cynthia dismissed her with an
unwitting solemnity.
</p><p>"Good-by, Nancy," said she.
"You've been a real help to me. I
don't know how I should have got
through it if it hadn't been for you."
</p><p>"It's clean as a ribbin," Nancy
called back cheerfully. "But land!
cleanin' up's nothin'. Trouble is to
keep it so. Well, I'll be pokin'
along."
</p><p>Cynthia stood and watched her well-knit figure swinging on between the
willows that marked the road. Then
she turned back to her clean house for
a last look and the renewed certainty
of its perfect state. She walked delicately
about the kitchen, lest a grain of
dust should be tracked upon the speckless
floor. The food not yet cooled from
the oven was in the pantry. All through
the lower rooms there was the fragrance
of cake and bread. It was a house set
in order, and finding it perfect, she made
herself sweet and clean, and changed
her working dress for a crisper calico.
In the doing, she thought solemnly how
she had once helped bathe a child that
had died at the poorhouse, and prepare
it for burial. This body of hers was
also being prepared, and though she had
no words to say so, it seemed to her
the body of her love. And all the time
the sea kept calling her, with its assurances
of manifold and solemn refuge.
</p><p>Presently she was ready to go. She
had made the clothing she had slipped
off into a little bundle, to leave none
but fresh things behind her, and now she
took it in her hand and stepped out at
the front door. That she closed, but
the windows were still open. It was
better that storms should invade the
house than that he should find it
inhospitably shut. Day and night could be
trusted with their welcome to him.
   <pb n="44"/>
But turning from the door, she smelled
her garden, and its autumn bitterness of
breath awoke in her a final pang of
homesickness. She laid down her bundle
and hurried round to the well, to
draw bucket after bucket of water and
drench the roots she had kept tended
since the spring. It was a separate good-by to every one. Here were the delicate
firstlings whose day had long been
over, and the hollyhocks that had made
the summer gay. Dahlias and asters
were the ones to keep this later watch,
but she sprinkled them impartially,
whether they were to bloom again or
wither till the winter's spell. The moon
was rising behind the wooded hill, and
there was suddenly a prophetic touch of
frost in the air. She stood for a moment
listening to the stillness, recognizing
life as if it all came flooding in on her
at once, only to retreat like a giant
wave and wash some farther shore.
Her brain apprehended what her tongue
could never say. She understood the
meaning of service and harmonious living.
It was no more dull to her now
than daily sunrise. She looked at Andrew's
house, builded by another Gale
over a hundred years ago. It meant
more than a shelter. It was the roof
of love, the nest of springing hopes.
Yet being a child at heart, she could
not stay after he had found her for one
day unworthy, and she was too young
to know how storms may pass.
</p><p>The man came heavily along the darkened
road and reached the gate as she
did. She saw him and dropped her bundle
in the shade of the lilac at the fence.
Andrew did not speak. He threw open
the gate, stepped in, and put his arms
about her. He held her to him as we
hold what is almost lost us through our
own lax grasp; but when he spoke to
her, she did not hear, and when he loosed
his clasp to look at her, she sank down
and would have fallen.
</p><p>"Cynthy, for God's sake!" he cried,
and his voice recalled her. Then she
gained her feet, he helping her.
<milestone unit="column"/>
</p><p>"What is it, dear? what is it, dear?"
he kept saying, and she answered him
with her tremulous breath upon his
cheek. Presently they went up the path
together, and in at the closed door.
"By George, don't it smell good!" said
Andrew. His voice, in nervous joviality,
was shaking, like his hands. "Le'
me git a light, honey. I've got to
look at you. Got to make sure you're
here!"
</p><p>The blaze from the shining lamp
struck full on her, and Andrew caught
his breath. Cynthia looked like the
angel of herself. Her tired face, overlaid
by joy, was like that of a child
awakened from sleep to unexpected welcome.
She seemed an adoring handmaid,
incredulous of the beauty of her
task. Andrew felt the wistfulness of
her air, the presence of things unknown
to him. He went over to her and drew
her nearer.
</p><p>"You knew I'd come," he said.
"You knew I couldn't stan' it after
I'd been ugly to you. Look at this
house! You fixed all up, an' made it
neat as wax. I started just as they set
down to supper, an' put for home. I've
been scairt 'most to death all the afternoon.
I dunno what I thought would
happen to you, but I had to come."
</p><p>"I've cleaned the house," said Cynthia,
like a child. "I got old Nancy."
</p><p>"Yes, dear, yes," he soothed her.
"You knew I'd come. You knew I
wouldn't stay away a night after I
broke your heart. You tell about your
weavin', dear. I want to hear it now."
</p><p>"My weavin'?" repeated Cynthia
vaguely. The words roused her a little
from her happy dream, and for one
luminous instant she felt the significance
of all the threads that make the
web of life. She laughed. "'Twas
only Bachelor's Fancy," she said. "I
learned it, that's all. There's lots o'
things I'd ruther do. You go in the
pantry, dear, an' look."
</p><p>Andrew left her with a kiss that was like meeting, not good-by.
But as
   <pb n="45"/>
he took the lamp from the table, Cynthia
slipped out at the front door.
</p><p>"Where you goin'?" he called.
</p><p>"Only out to the lilac," she answered
throbbingly. "I dropped somethin'
there."
</p><p>While he lingered for her, she came
<milestone unit="column"/>
back and, as she ran, tossed her little bundle into the closet under the
stairs.  The hues of youth were on her face.  Her eyes were wet and
glad.
</p><p>"I'm terrible hungry, too," she told him. "Come! there's sugar
gingerbread."
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Alice Brown</hi>.
</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

