<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="BurMere"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>


<TEI.2 id="BurMere">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">M&egrave;re Giraud's Little Daughter</title>
<title type="sort">mere girauds little daughter</title>
<author>Burnett, Frances Hodgson</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Charles Keller</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">38</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">BurMere</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475765</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">M&egrave;re Giraud's Little Daughter</title>
<title>Scribner's Monthly</title>
<title type="sort">mere girauds little daughter</title>
<author>Frances Hodgson Burnett</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Frances Hart &amp; Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1876-11">November, 1876</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Scribner's Monthly, Vol. 13, no. 1, pp. 108-115</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic
Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding
line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text
Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed
of the text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in
AusEmma1 for page one of Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1876-11">November, 1876</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
<language id="fre">French</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
<term>Young Readers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-11">November, 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Bryson Clevenger, Jr.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>TEI header, minimal TEI tagging</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">



<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="108"/>
<head>
MERE GIRAUD'S LITTLE DAUGHTER.<lb/>
by Frances Hodgson Burnett<lb/>
SCRIBNER'S MONTHLY<lb/>
VOL. XIII.<lb/>           NOVEMBER, 1876.<lb/>              NO.
1.<lb/>
pp. 108-115</head>

<p>"Prut!" said Annot, her sabots clattering loudly on the brick
floor as
she moved more rapidly in her wrath.  "Prut!  Madame Giraud,
indeed!  There
was a time, and it was but two years ago, that she was but plain
Mere Giraud,
and no better than the rest of us; and it seems to me, neighbors,
that it is
not well to show pride because one has the luck to be favored by
fortune.
Where, forsooth, would our `Madame' Giraud stand if luck had not
given her a
daughter pretty enough to win a rich husband?"
</p><p>"True, indeed!" echoed two of the gossips who were her
admiring
listeners, "True, beyond doubt.  Where, indeed?"
</p><p>But the third, a comely, fresh-skinned matron, who leaned
against the
door, and knitted a stout gray stocking with fast-clashing
needles, did not
acquiesce so readily.
</p><p>"Well, well, neighbors," she said, "for my part, I do not
see so much
to complain of.  Mere Giraud&mdash;she is still Mere Giraud to me&mdash;is
as honest and
kindly a soul as ever.  It is not she who has called herself
Madame Giraud; it
is others who are foolish enough to fancy that good luck must
change one's old
ways.  If she had had the wish to be a grand personage, would she
not have
left our village before this and have joined Madame Legrand in
Paris.  On the
contrary, however, she remains in her cottage, and is as good a
neighbor as
ever, even though she is fond of talking of the carriages and
jewels of Madame
Legrand and her establishment on the Boulevard Malesherbes.  In
fact, I ask
you, who of us would not rejoice also to be the mother of a
daughter whose
fortune had been so good?"
</p><p>"That also is true," commented the amiable couple, nodding
their white-capped heads with a sagacious air.  "True, without
doubt."
</p><p>But Annot replied, with a contemptuous shrug of her
shoulders:
</p><p>"Wait until Madame Giraud is invited to visit the
Boulevard Malesherbes," she said.  "We have not heard that this
has happened yet."
</p><p>She would not go if she were, at least not to remain.  Her
heart has
grown to the old place she bore her children in, and she has
herself said to
me most sensibly:  `Laure is young, and will learn easily the
ways of the
great world; I am old, and cannot; I am better at home among my
neighbors.'
Doubtless, however, in course of time she will pay Madame Legrand
a visit at her home in Paris, or at the Chateau which Monsieur
Legrand of course possesses, as the rich and aristocratic always
do."
    "Doubtless!" said Annot, grimly; "doubtless "
</p><p>Honest Jeanne Tallot passed the sneer by, and went on with
stout gravity of demeanor:
</p><p>"There is only one thing for which I somewhat blamed Mere
Giraud, and
that is that I think she has scarcely done her duty toward
Valentin.  He
disappointed her by being an ugly lad instead of a pretty girl,
and she had
not patience with him.  Laure was the favorite.  Whatever Laure
did was right,
and it was not so with the other, though I myself know that
Valentin was a
good lad, and tender-hearted."
</p><p>"Once," put in a white cap, "I saw her beat him severely
because he
fell with the little girl in his arms and scratched her cheek,
and it was not
his fault.  His foot slipped upon a stone.  He was carrying the
child
carefully and tenderly enough.  You are right in calling him a
good lad,
neighbor Tallot.  He was a good lad,&mdash;Valentin Giraud,&mdash;and fond
of his
mother, notwithstanding that she was not fond of him."
</p><p>"Yes," added her companion; "but it is a truth that he was
a great
contrast to the girl.  <hi rend="italic"> Mon dieu!</hi> his long limbs and
awkward body,
his great sad eyes and ugly face!  While Laure,&mdash;was she not tall
and slender
and white, like a lily in a garden?  And her voice was like the
ringing of
silver, and her eyes so soft and large.  As an infant, she
reminded one of the
little Jesu as one sees him in the churches.  No wonder that Mere
Giraud
fretted at the difference between the two.  And Valentin was her
first, and
what mother does not look for great things in her first?  We
cannot help
feeling that something must come of one's own charms if one has
any, and Mere
Giraud was a handsome bride.  An ugly bantling seems to offer one
a sort of
insult, particularly at first, when one is young and vain."
</p><p>"There was no more beautiful young girl than Laure Giraud
at sixteen,"
said Jeanne Tallot.
</p><p>"And none more useless," said Annot
<pb n="109"/> loudly.  "Give
me a young girl who is industrious and honest.  My Margot is
better provided
for than Laure Giraud was before her marriage; but her hands are
not white,
nor is her waist but a span around.  She has too much work to do.
She is not
a tall, white, swaying creature who is too good to churn and tend
the
creatures who give her food.  I have heard it said that Laure
would have
worked if her mother had permitted it, but I don't believe it.
She had not a
working look.  Mademoiselle Laure was too good for the labor of
humble people;
she must go to Paris and learn a fine, delicate trade."
</p><p>"But good came of it," put in Jeanne Tallot.  "It proved
all the better
for her."
</p><p>"Let her mother thank the Virgin, then," cried Annot,
contemptuously.
"It might not have proved the better; it might have proved the
worse; evil
might have come of it instead of good.  Who among us has not
heard of such
things?  Did not Marie Gautier go to Paris too?"
</p><p>"Ah, poor little one, indeed!" sighed the white caps.
</p><p>"And in two years," added Annot, <hi rend="italic">" her</hi> mother
died of a
broken heart."
</p><p>"But," said cheerful Jeanne, somewhat dryly, "Laure's
mother is not
dead yet, so let us congratulate ourselves that to go to Paris
has brought
luck to one of our number at least, and let us deal charitably
with Mere
Giraud, who certainly means well, and is only naturally proud of
her
daughter's grandeur.  For my part, I can afford to rejoice with
her."
</p><p>She rolled up her stout stocking into a ball, and stuck
her needles
through it, nodding at the three women.
</p><p>"I promised I would drop in and spend a few minutes with
her this
morning," she said; "so I will bid you good-day," and she stepped
across the
threshold and trudged off in the sunshine, her wooden shoes
sounding bravely
upon the path.
</p><p>It was only a little place,&mdash;St. Croix, as we will call it
for want of
a better name,&mdash;a little village of one street, and of many
vines, and roses,
and orchards, and of much gossip.  Simple people inhabited
it,&mdash;simple,
ignorant folk, who knew one another, and discussed one another's
faults and
grape-crops with equal frankness, worked hard, lived frugally,
confessed
regularly and slept well.  Devout people, and ignorant, who
believed that the
little shrines they erected in their vineyards brought blessings
upon their
grapes, and who knew nothing of the great world beyond, and spoke
of Paris
with awe, and even a shade of doubt.  Living the same lives
generation after
generation, tilling the same crops, and praying before the same
stone altar in
the small, quaint church, it is not to be wondered at that when a
change
occurred to any one of their number, it was regarded as a sort of
social era.
There were those in St. Croix who had known Mere Giraud's
grandfather, a slow-spoken, kindly old peasant, who had drunk his <hi rend="italic"> vin
ordinaire</hi>, and
smoked his pipe with the poorest; and there was not one who did
not well know
Mere Giraud herself, and who had not watched the growth of the
little Laure,
who had bloomed into a beauty not unlike the beauty of the white
Provence
roses which climbed over and around her mother's cottage door.
"Mere Giraud's
little daughter," she had been called, even after she grew into
the
wonderfully tall and wonderfully fair creature she became before
she left the
village, accompanying her brother Valentin to Paris.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">" Ma foi!"</hi> said the men, "but she is truly a
beauty, Mere
Giraud's little daughter!"
</p><p>"She should be well looked to," said the wiseacres,&mdash;"Mere
Giraud's
little daughter."
</p><p>"There is one we must always give way before," said the
best-natured
among the girls, "and that one is Mere Giraud's little daughter."
</p><p>The old <hi rend="italic"> Cure</hi> of the parish took interest in
her, and gave
her lessons, and, as Mere Giraud would have held her strictly to
them, even if
she had not been tractable and studious by nature, she was better
educated and
more gently trained than her companions.  The fact was, however,
that she had
not many companions.  Some element in her grace and beauty seemed
to separate
her from the rest of her class.  Village sports and festivities
had little
attraction for her, and, upon the whole, she seemed out of place
among them.
Her stature, her fair, still face, and her slow, quiet movements,
suggested
rather embarrassingly to the humble feasters the presence of some
young
princess far above them.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">" Pouf!"</hi> said a sharp-tongued belle one day, "I
have no
patience with her.  She is so tall, this Laure, that one must be
forever
looking up to her, and I, for one, do not care to be forever
looking up."
</p><p>The hint of refined pride in her demeanor was Mere
Giraud's greatest
glory.
</p><p>"She is not like the rest, my Laure," she would say to her
son.  "One
can see it in the way in which she holds her head.  She
<pb n="110"/> has
the quiet, grave air of a great personage."
</p><p>There were many who wondered that Valentin showed no
jealousy or
distaste at hearing his sister's praises sounded so frequently to
his own
detriment.  There was no praise for him.  The poor fond mother's
heart was too
full of Laure.  Her son had been a bitter disappointment to her,
and, to her
mind, was fitted for nothing but to make himself an adoring slave
to his
sister's beauty; and this the gentle, generous fellow certainly
was.  He was
always ready to serve her; always affectionate; always faithful;
and Mere
Giraud, who was blind to, or careless of, all his loving,
constant labor for
her own comfort, deigned to see that he did his duty toward
Laure.
</p><p>"He has at least the sense to appreciate her as far as he
is able," she
said.
</p><p>So when Valentin, who had a curious talent for engraving,
was
discovered by some one who understood his genius, and could make
use of it,
and was offered a place in the great, gay city, Mere Giraud
formed an
ambitious plan.  He should take Laure and find her a position
also; she had
the fingers of a fair magician, and could embroider marvelously.
So she
trusted Laure to him, and the two bade farewell to St. Croix and
departed
together.  A month passed, and then there came a letter
containing good news.
Valentin was doing well, and Laure also.  She had found a place
in a great
family where she was to embroider and wait upon a young lady.
They were rich
people, and were kind, and paid her well, and she was happy.
</p><p>"When they first saw her, they were astonished," wrote the
simple,
tender Valentin.  "I went with her to present herself.  My
employer had
recommended her.  There is a son who is past his youth, and who
has evidently
seen the world.  He is aristocratic and fair, and slightly bald,
but extremely
handsome still.  He sat holding a newspaper in his long, white
fingers, and
when we entered, he raised his eyes above it and looked at Laure,
and I heard
him exclaim under his breath, `<hi rend="italic"> Mon Dieu!</hi>' as if her
beauty fairly
startled him."
</p><p>When the <hi rend="italic"> Cure</hi>, to whom the proud mother showed
the letter,
read this part, he did not seem as rejoiced as Mere Giraud had
expected.  On
the contrary, he looked a little grave, and rubbed his forehead.
</p><p>"Ah! ah!" he said; "there lies the danger."
</p><p>"Danger!" exclaimed Mere Giraud, starting.
</p><p>He turned, and regarded her with a rather hesitant air, as
if he were
at once puzzled and fearful,&mdash;puzzled by her simplicity, and
fearful of
grieving her unnecessarily.
</p><p>"Valentin is a good lad," he said.  "Valentin will be
watchful,&mdash;though
perhaps he is too good to suspect evil."
</p><p>Mere Giraud put her hand to her heart.
</p><p>"You are not afraid?" she said, quite proudly, beginning
at last to
comprehend.  "You are not afraid of evil to Laure?"
</p><p>"No, no, no," he answered; "surely not."
</p><p>He said no more then, but he always asked to see the
letters, and read
them with great care, sometimes over and over again.  They came
very regularly
for six or seven months, and then there was a gap of a few weeks,
and then
came a strange, almost incomprehensible, letter from Valentin,
containing news
which almost caused Mere Giraud's heart to burst with joy and
gratitude.
Laure was married, and had made such a marriage as could scarcely
have been
dreamed of.  A rich aristocrat, who had visited her employers,
had fallen in
love with her, and married her.  He had no family to restrain
him, and her
beauty had won him completely from the first hour.  He had
carried her away
with him to make a prolonged tour.  The family with whom she had
lived had
been lavish in their gifts and kindness, but they had left, Paris
also and
were voyaging.  The name of Laure's bridegroom was Legrand, and
there came
messages from Laure, and inclosed was a handsome present of
money.
</p><p>Mere Giraud was overwhelmed with joy.  Before three hours
had passed,
all St. Croix knew the marvelous news.  She went from house to
house showing
the letter and the money, and it was not until night that she
cooled down
sufficiently to labor through a long epistle to Valentin.
</p><p>It was a year before Laure returned to Paris, and during
that time she
wrote but seldom; but Valentin wrote often, and answered all his
mother's
questions, though not as fluently, nor with so many words as she
often wished.
Laure was rich, and beautiful as ever; her husband adored her,
and showered
gifts and luxuries upon her; she had equipages and jewels; she
wore velvet and
satin and lace every day; she was a great lady, and had a house
like a palace.
Laure herself did not say so much.  In her secret heart, Mere
Giraud often
longed for more, but she was a discreet and far-seeing woman.
</p><p>"What would you?" she said.  "She
<pb n="111"/> must drive out in
her equipage, and she must dress and receive great people, and I
am not so
blind a mother as not to see that she will have many things to
learn.  She has
not time to write long letters,&mdash;and see how she cares for
me,&mdash;money, see
you, by every letter, and a silk dress and lace cap she herself
has chosen in
the Boulevard Capucines.  And I must care for myself, and furnish
the cottage
prettily, and keep a servant.  Her wealth and great fortune have
not rendered
her undutiful,&mdash;my Laure."
</p><p>So she talked of Madame Legrand, and so all St. Croix
talked of Madame
Legrand, and some, of course, were envious and prophesied that
the end had not
come yet, and Mere Giraud would find herself forgotten some fine
day; and
others rejoiced with her, and congratulated themselves that they
knew so
aristocratic a person as Madame Legrand.
</p><p>Jeanne Tallot was of those who sympathized with her in all
warm-heartedness and candor.  With her knitting in her hand ready for
action, and
with friendly unceremoniousness, she presented herself at the
cottage door one
morning, nodding and speaking before she had crossed the
threshold.
</p><p>"Good-day, neighbor Giraud.  Any letters from Laure this
morning?"
</p><p>Mere Giraud, who sat before the window under the swinging
cage of her
bird, looked up with an air a little more serious than usual.
</p><p>"Ah!" she said, "I am glad it is you, Jeanne.  I have been
wishing to
see you."  Jeanne seated herself, smiling.
    "Then," said she, "it is well I came."
</p><p>But immediately she noticed the absent look of her friend,
and
commented upon it.
</p><p>"You do not look at your best this morning," she said.
"How does it
occur?"
</p><p>"I am thinking," said Mere Giraud with some importance of
manner; "I am
thinking of going to Paris."
    "To Paris!"
</p><p>"I am anxious," shaking her head seriously.  "I had last
night a bad
dream.  I wish to see Laure."
</p><p>Then she turned and looked at Jeanne almost wistfully.
</p><p>"It is a long time since I have seen her," she said.
</p><p>"Yes," answered Jeanne in a little doubt; "but Paris is a
long way
off."
</p><p>"Yes," said Mere Giraud; "but it appears that all at once
I realize how
long it is since I have seen my child.  I am getting old, you
see.  I was not
very young when she was born, and, as one grows older, one
becomes more uneasy
and obstinate in one's fancies.  This morning I feel that I must
see my Laure.
My heart yearns for her, and"&mdash;hastily&mdash;"she will undoubtedly be
rejoiced to
see me.  She has often said that she wished she might lay her
head upon my
breast again."
</p><p>It seemed that she was resolved upon the journey.  She was
in a
singular, uneasy mood, and restless beyond measure.  She who had
never been
twenty miles from St. Croix had made up her mind to leave it at
once and
confront all the terrors of a journey to Paris,&mdash;for there were
terrors in
such a journey to the mind of a simple peasant who had so far
traveled but in
one groove.  She would not even wait to consult <hi rend="italic"> Monsieur le
Cure</hi>,
who was unfortunately absent.  Jeanne discovered to her
astonishment that she
had already made her small preparations, had packed her best
garments in a
little wooden box, laying the silk gown and lace cap at the top
that they
might be in readiness.
</p><p>"I will not interfere at all, and I shall not remain
long," she said.
"Only long enough to see my Laure, and spend a few days with her
quietly.  It
is not Paris I care for, or the great sights; it is that I must
see my child."
</p><p>St. Croix was fairly bewildered at the news it heard the
next day.
Mere Giraud had gone to Paris to visit Madame Legrand&mdash;had
actually gone,
sending her little servant home, and shutting up her small trim
cottage.
</p><p>"Let us hope that Madame Legrand will receive her as she
expects to be
received," said Annot.  "For my part I should have preferred to
remain in St.
Croix.  Only yesterday Jeanne Tallot told us that she had no
intention of
going."
</p><p>"She will see wonderful things," said the more simple and
amiable.  "It
is possible that she may be invited to the Tuileries, and without
doubt she
will drive to the Bois de Boulogne in Madame Legrand's carriage,
with servants
in livery to attend her.  My uncle's sister's son, who is a <hi rend="italic">
valet de
place</hi> in a great family, tells us that the aristocracy drive
up and down
the Champs Elysees every afternoon, and the sight is
magnificent."
</p><p>But Mere Giraud did not look forward to such splendors as
these.  "I
shall see my Laure as a great lady," she said to herself.  "I
shall hold her
white hands and kiss her cheeks."

<pb n="112"/>
</p><p>The roar of vehicles, and the rush and crowd and bustle
bewildered her;
the brightness and the rolling wheels dazzled her old eyes, but
she held
herself bravely.  People to whom she spoke smiled at her <hi rend="italic">
patois</hi> and
her innocent questions, but she did not care.
</p><p>She found a <hi rend="italic"> fiacre</hi> which took her to her
destination; and
when, after she had paid the driver, he left her, she entered the
wide doors
with a beating heart, the blood rising on her cheek, and glowing
through the
withered skin.
</p><p>"Madame Legrand," she said a little proudly to the
<hi rend="italic"> concierge</hi>, and the woman stared at her as she led her
up the
staircase.  She was so eager that she scarcely saw the beauty
around her,&mdash;the
thick soft carpets, the carved balustrades, the superb lamps.
But when they
stopped before a door she touched the <hi rend="italic"> concierge</hi> upon
the arm.
</p><p>"Do not say my name," she said.  "I am her mother."
</p><p>The woman stared at her more than ever.
</p><p>"It is not my place to announce you," she said.  "I only
came up
because I thought you would not find the way."
</p><p>She could not have told why it was or how it happened, but
when at last
she was ushered into the <hi rend="italic"> salon</hi> a strange sense of
oppression fell
upon her.  The room was long and lofty, and so shadowed by the
heavy curtains
falling across the windows that it was almost dark.
</p><p>For a few seconds she saw nobody, and then all at once
some one rose
from a reclining chair at the farther end of the apartment and
advanced a few
steps toward her&mdash;a tall and stately figure, moving slowly.
</p><p>"Who&mdash;?" she heard a cold soft voice say, and then came
a sharp cry,
and Laure's white hands were thrown out in a strange, desperate
gesture, and
she stopped and stood like a statue of stone.
"Mother&mdash;mother&mdash;mother!" she
repeated again and again, as if some indescribable pain shook
her.
</p><p>If she had been beautiful before, now she was more
beautiful still.
She was even taller than ever,&mdash;she was like a queen.  Her long
robe was of
delicate gray velvet, and her hair and throat and wrists were
bound with
pearls and gold.  She was so lovely and so stately that for a
moment Mere
Giraud was half awed, but the next it was as if her strong mother
heart broke
loose.
</p><p>"My Laure!" she cried out.  "Yes, it is I, my child&mdash;it is
I, Laure;"
and she almost fell upon her knees as she embraced her, trembling
for very
ecstasy.
</p><p>But Laure scarcely spoke.  She was white and cold, and at
last she
gasped forth three words.
    "Where is Valentin?"
</p><p>But Mere Giraud did not know.  It was not Valentin she
cared to see.
Valentin could wait, since she had her Laure.  She sat down
beside her in one
of the velvet chairs, and she held the fair hand in her own.  It
was covered
with jewels, but she did not notice them; her affection only told
her that it
was cold and tremulous.
</p><p>"You are not well, Laure?" she said.  "It was well that my
dream warned
me to come.  Something is wrong."
</p><p>"I am quite well," said Laure.  "I do not suffer at all."
</p><p>She was so silent that if Mere Giraud had not had so much
to say she
would have been troubled; as it was, however, she was content to
pour forth
her affectionate speeches one after another without waiting to be
answered.
</p><p>"Where is Monsieur Legrand?" she ventured at last.
</p><p>"He is," said Laure, in a strange hesitant voice,&mdash;"he is
in Normandy."
</p><p>"Shall I not see him?" asked Mere Giraud.
</p><p>"I am afraid not, unless your visit is a long one.  He
will be absent
for some months."
</p><p>She did not speak with any warmth.  It was as if she did
not care to
speak of him at all,&mdash;as if the mention of him even embarrassed
her a little.
    Mere Giraud felt a secret misgiving.
</p><p>"I shall not stay long," she said; "but I could not remain
away.  I
wished so eagerly to see you, and know that you were happy.  You
are happy, my
Laure?"
</p><p>Laure turned toward her and gave her long look&mdash;a look
which seemed
unconsciously to ask her a question.
</p><p>"Happy!" she answered slowly and deliberately, "I suppose
so.&mdash;Yes."
</p><p>Mere Giraud caressed her hand again and again.  "Yes," she
said, "it
must be so.  The good are always happy; and you, my Laure, have
always been
dutiful and virtuous, and consequently you are rewarded.  You
have never
caused me a grief, and now, thank the good God! you are
prosperous."  She
looked at her almost adoringly, and at last touched the soft
thick gray velvet
of her drapery with reverence.  "Do you wear such things as this
every day?"
she asked.

<pb n="113"/>
    "Yes," Laure answered, "every day."
</p><p>"Ah!" sighed the happy mother, "How Monsieur Legrand must
adore you!"
</p><p>At length she found time to ask a few questions concerning
Valentin.
</p><p>"I know that he is well and as prosperous as one could
expect him to
be; but I hope"&mdash;bridling a little with great seriousness&mdash;"I
hope he conducts
himself in such a manner as to cause you no embarrassment, though
naturally
you do not see him often."
</p><p>"No," was the answer,&mdash;they did not see him often.
</p><p>"Well, well," began Mere Giraud, becoming lenient in her
great
happiness, "he is not a bad lad&mdash;Valentin.  He means well&mdash;"
</p><p>But here she stopped,&mdash;Laure checked her with a swift,
impassioned
movement.
</p><p>"He is what we cannot understand," she said in a hushed
strained voice.
"He is a saint.  He has no thought for himself.  His whole life
is a
sacrifice.  It is not I you should adore&mdash;it is Valentin."
    "Valentin!" echoed Mere Giraud.
</p><p>It quite bewildered her, the mere thought of adoring
Valentin.
</p><p>"My child," she said when she recovered herself, "it is
your good heart
which says this."
</p><p>The same night Valentin came.  Laure went out into the
antechamber to
meet him, and each stood and looked at the other with pale face
and anguished
eyes.  Valentin's eyes were hollow and sunken as if with some
great sorrow,
and his large awkward frame seemed wasted.  But there was no
reproach mingled
with the indescribable sadness of his gaze.
</p><p>"Your note came to me," he said.  "Our mother&mdash;"
</p><p>"She is in there," said Laure in a low, hurried, shaken
voice, and she
pointed to the <hi rend="italic"> salon</hi>.  "She has come to embrace me, to
make sure
that I am happy.  Ah, my God!" and she covered her deathly face
with her
hands.
</p><p>Valentin did not approach her.  He could only stand still
and look on.
One thought filled his mind.
</p><p>"We have no time to weep, Laure," he said gently.  "We
must go on as we
have begun.  Give me your hand."
</p><p>This was all, and then the two went in together, Laure's
hand upon her
brother's arm.
</p><p>It was a marvelous life Mere Giraud lived during the next
few days.
Certainly she could not complain that she was not treated with
deference and
affection.  She wore the silk dress every day; she sat at the
wonderful table,
and a liveried servant stood behind her chair; she drove here and
there in a
luxurious carriage; she herself, in fact, lived the life of an
aristocrat and
a great lady.  Better than all the rest, she found her Laure as
gracious and
dutiful as her fond heart could have wished.  She spent every
hour with her;
she showed her all her grandeurs of jewelry and <hi rend="italic">
toilette</hi>; she was
not ashamed of her mother, untutored and simple as she might be.
</p><p>"Only she is very pale and quiet," she remarked to
Valentin once; "even
paler and more quiet than I should have expected.  But then we
know that the
rich and aristocratic are always somewhat reserved.  It is only
the peasantry
and provincials who are talkative and florid.  It is natural that
Laure should
have gained the manner of the great world."
</p><p>But her happiness, poor soul, did not last long, and yet
the blow God
sent was a kindly one.
</p><p>One morning as they went out to their carriage, Laure
stopped to speak
to a woman who crouched upon the edge of the pavement with a
child in her
arms.  She bent down and touched the little one with her hand,
and Mere
Giraud, looking on, thought of pictures she had seen of the
Blessed Virgin,
and of lovely saints healing the sick.
</p><p>"What is the matter?" asked Laure.
</p><p>The woman looked down at the child and shivered.
</p><p>"I do not know," she answered hoarsely.  "Only we are ill,
and God has
forsaken us.  We have not tasted food for two days."
</p><p>Laure took something from her purse and laid it silently
in the child's
small, fevered hand.  The woman burst into tears.
</p><p>"Madame," she said, "it is a twenty-franc piece."
</p><p>"Yes," said Laure gently.  "When it is spent come to me
again," and she
went to her carriage.
</p><p>"My child," said Mere Giraud, "it is you who are a saint.
The good God
did wisely in showering blessings upon you."
</p><p>A few days longer she was happy, and then she awakened
from her sleep
one night and found Laure standing at her bedside looking down at
her and
shuddering.  She started up with an exclamation of terror.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">" Mon Dieu!"</hi> she said.  "What is it?"
</p><p>She was answered in a voice she had never heard
before,&mdash;Laure's, but
hoarse and VOL. XIII.&mdash;8.
<pb n="114"/> shaken.  Laure had fallen upon
her knees, and grasped the bedclothes, hiding her face in the
folds.
</p><p>"I am ill," she answered in this strange, changed tone.
"I am&mdash;I am
cold and burning&mdash;I am&mdash;dying."
</p><p>In an instant Mere Giraud stood upon the floor holding her
already
insensible form in her arms.  She was obliged to lay her upon the
floor while
she rang the bell to alarm the servants.  She sent for Valentin
and a doctor.
The doctor, arriving, regarded the beautiful face with manifest
surprise and
alarm.  It was no longer pale, but darkly flushed, and the stamp
of terrible
pain was upon it.
</p><p>"She has been exposed to infection," he said.  "This is
surely the
case.  It is a malignant fever."
</p><p>Then Mere Giraud thought of the poor mother and child.
</p><p>"O my God!" she prayed, "do not let her die a martyr."
</p><p>But the next day there was not a servant left in the
house; but
Valentin was there, and there had come a Sister of Mercy.  When
she came,
Valentin met her, and led her into the <hi rend="italic"> salon</hi>.  They
remained
together for half an hour, and then came out and went to the
sick-room, and
there were traces of tears upon the Sister's face.  She was a
patient, tender
creature, who did her work well, and she listened with untiring
gentleness to
Mere Giraud's passionate plaints.
</p><p>"So beautiful, so young, so beloved," cried the poor
mother; "and
Monsieur absent in Normandy, though it is impossible to say
where!  And if
death should come before his return, who could confront him with
the truth?
So beautiful, so happy, so adored!"
</p><p>And Laure lay upon the bed, sometimes wildly delirious.
sometimes a
dreadful statue of stone,&mdash;unhearing, unseeing, unmoving,&mdash;death
without
death's rest,&mdash;life in death's bonds of iron.
</p><p>But while Mere Giraud wept, Valentin had no tears.  He was
faithful,
untiring, but silent even at the worst.
</p><p>"One would think he had no heart," said Mere Giraud; "but
men are often
so,&mdash;ready to work, but cold and dumb.  Ah! it is only a mother
who bears the
deepest grief."
</p><p>She fought passionately enough for a hope at first, but it
was forced
from her grasp in the end.  Death had entered the house and
spoken to her in
the changed voice which had summoned her from her sleep.
</p><p>"Madame," said the doctor one evening as they stood over
the bed while
the sun went down, "I have done all that is possible.  She will
not see the
sun set again.  She may not see it rise."
</p><p>Mere Giraud fell upon her knees beside the bed, crossing
herself and
weeping.
</p><p>"She will die," she said, "a blessed martyr.  She will die
the death of
a saint."
</p><p>That very night&mdash;only a few hours later&mdash;there came to
them a friend,&mdash;
one they had not for one moment even hoped to see,&mdash;a gentle,
grave old man,
in a thin, well-worn black robe,&mdash;the <hi rend="italic"> Cure</hi> of St.
Croix.
</p><p>Him Valentin met also, and when the two saw each other,
there were
barriers that fell away in their first interchange of looks.
</p><p>"My son," said the old man, holding out his hands, "tell
me the truth."
</p><p>Then Valentin fell into a chair and hid his face.
</p><p>"She is dying," he said, "and I cannot ask that she should
live."
</p><p>"What was my life&mdash;" he cried passionately, speaking
again&mdash;"What was
my life to me that I should not have given it to have her,&mdash;to
save her to her
beauty and honor, and her mother's love!  I would have given it
cheerfully,&mdash;a
thousand times,&mdash;a thousand times again and again.  But it was
not to be; and,
in spite of my prayers, I lost her Oh, my God!" with a sob of
agony, "if to-night she were in St. Croix and I could hear the neighbors call
her again as
they used, `Mere Giraud's little daughter!'"
</p><p>The eyes of the <hi rend="italic"> Cure</hi> had tears in them also.
</p><p>"Yesterday I returned to St. Croix and found your mother
absent," he
said.  "I have had terrible fears for months, and when I found
her house
closed, they caused me to set out upon my journey at once."
</p><p>He did not ask any questions.  He remembered too well the
man of whom
Valentin had written; the son who was "past his youth, and had
evidently seen
the world;" the pale aristocrat, who had exclaimed <hi rend="italic">" Mon
Dieu!</hi> at
the sight of Laure's wondrous beauty.
</p><p>"When the worst came to the worst," said Valentin, "I
vowed myself to
the labor of sparing our mother.  I have worked early and late to
sustain
myself in the part I played.  It was not from Laure the money
came.  My God!
Do you think I would have permitted my mother's hand to have
touched a gift of
hers?  She wrote the letters, but the money I had earned
honestly.

<pb n="115"/> Heaven will justify me for my falsehood since I have
suffered so much."
</p><p>"Yes," responded the <hi rend="italic"> Cure</hi>, looking at his bent
form with
gentle, pitying eyes; "Heaven will justify you, my son."
</p><p>They watched by Laure until the morning, but she did not
see them; she
saw nothing; tonight it was the statue of marble which lay before
them.  But
in the early morning, when the sky was dappled with pink and
gold, and the air
was fresh and cool, and a silence, even more complete than that
of the night,
seemed to reign, there came a change.  The eyes they had seen
closed for so
many hours were opened, and the soft voice broke in upon the
perfect stillness
of the room:
</p><p>"The lilies in the garden are in bloom to-day.  The were
never so tall,
and white, and fair before.  I will gather them&mdash;for the
altar&mdash;to give to the
Virgin&mdash;at my confession.  <hi rend="italic"> Mea culpa&mdash;Mea</hi>&mdash;" and all
was over,
and Mere Giraud fell upon her knees again, crying, as she had
cried before,
amid a passion of sobs and tears:
</p><p>"She has died, my child, the death of a blessed martyr."

</p><p>It was rather strange, the villagers said, that Madame
Legrand should
have been buried in the little grave-yard at St. Croix instead of
in some fine
tomb at <hi rend="italic"> Pere la Chaise</hi>; but&mdash;it was terribly sad!&mdash;her
husband was
away, they knew not where, and it was Valentin's wish, and Mere
Giraud's heart
yearned so over her beloved one.  So she was laid there, and a
marble cross
was placed at her head&mdash;a tall, beautiful cross&mdash;by Monsieur
Legrand, of
course.  Only it was singular that he never came, though perhaps
that is the
way of the great&mdash;not to mourn long or deeply even for those who
have been
most lovely, and whom they have most tenderly loved.

</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

