<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="BysEngl"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="BysEngl">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Art of English Poetry</title>
<title type="sort">art of english poetry</title>
<author>Bysshe, Edward</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>The Electronic Text Center</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">100</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">BysEngl</idno>
<date value="2000">2000</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2000 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475776</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Art of English Poetry</title>
<title type="sort">art of english poetry</title>
<author>Edward Bysshe</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>38 pages</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Printed for R. Knaplock At the Angel in St. Paul`s Church-Yard; E. Castle next Scotland-Yard-Gate by White-Hall; and B.
Tooke at the Middle-Temple-Gate in Fleetstreet</publisher>
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
<date value="1702">1702</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:   Alderman Library PE 1519.B9 1702a</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>/web/data/ENEC982</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1702">1702</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2001-02">February, 2001</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Andrew Rouner, The Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item/>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<front id="d2">

<titlePage id="d3">
	<pb/>
<titlePart type="main">
THE<lb/>
ART<lb/>
OF<lb/>
ENGLISH POETRY<lb/>
<lb/><lb/>
CONTAINING,
</titlePart>
<titlePart type="sub">
I. Rules for making Verses.<lb/>
II. A Dictionary of Rhymes.<lb/>
III. A Collection of the most Natural, <lb/>
Agreeable, and Noble <hi rend="italic">Thoughts</hi>, <lb/>
viz. Allusions, Similes, Descriptions, and <lb/>
Characters, of Persons and Things; that are <lb/>
to be found in the best <hi rend="italic">English Poets</hi>.
</titlePart>

<byline>BY
<docAuthor>
<hi rend="italic">By</hi> EDW. BYSSHE, <hi rend="italic">Gent.</hi>
</docAuthor>
</byline>

<epigraph>
<cit><q><lg type="stanza"><l>
<hi rend="italic">Munus &amp; Officium, nil scribens ipse, docebo;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Unde parentur opes; quit alat, formetque Poetam:</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Quid deceat, quid non: quo Virtus, quo ferat Error.</hi></l>
</lg></q>
<bibl>Horat.</bibl>
</cit></epigraph>

<docImprint>
<pubPlace>LONDON</pubPlace>,<lb/>
Printed for R. <unclear>Knaplock</unclear> At the <hi rend="italic">Angel</hi>
in St. <hi rend="italic">Paul's Church-Yard; E. Castle</hi> next
<hi rend="italic">Scotland-Yard-Gate</hi> by <hi rend="italic">White-Hall;</hi>
and <hi rend="italic">B. Tooke</hi> at the <hi rend="italic">Middle-Temple-Gate</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Fleetstreet</hi>, <date value="1702">1702</date>.
</docImprint>
</titlePage>

<div1 type="dedication" id="d4">
<pb/>
<head>TO<lb/>
EDMUND DUNCH, <hi rend="italic">Esq</hi>;<lb/>
OF<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Little Wittenham ,</hi><lb/>
IN<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">BERKSHIRE.</hi>
</head>

<salute><hi rend="bold"> SIR</hi>,</salute>
<p><hi rend="italic">I Have not presum'd to make you this Publick Address,
without reflecting, that of all Writers those who treat of Poetry ought to
be the most scrupulous in their Choice of a Patron. For, a Man to whom a Book
is Dedicated either in Law, Divinity, or Physick, may have made that Subject
his Profession, and then he is suppos'd of Course to be a proper Judge of it;
or if it treat of History, Ethicks, or Politicks; those are Subjects that fall
within the reach of Good Sense;</hi> <hi rend="italic">in any of these Cases
therefore People seldom </hi>

<pb n="ii"/>

<hi rend="italic">give themselves the trouble of inquiring into the Merits
of the Patron: But the Publick are not a little inquisitive about the Person
to whom a Book of Poetry is inscrib'd, for indeed, there go so many excellent
Qualifications to the making of a good Judge of Poetry, that he that is possess'd
of them is well worth inquiring after</hi>; <hi rend="italic">few being ignorant
that such a Man must be of an elevated Mind, founded on a great Compass of
Knowledge, on a generous Education, on reading of the best Authors, and on a
Conversation with Men of the first Rank and Fortunes</hi>: <hi rend="italic">All
which must concur to give him that Readiness and Clearness of Apprehension, that
Fine and Just Taste of what is Natural and Great, that Elegance and Depth of
Thought</hi>; <hi rend="italic">in a Word, that happy Turn of Soul and Race of
Judgment, which distinguish him from the Vulgar in every thing he Speaks and Acts.
This, Sir, is the Character that you have gain'd among the most accomplish'd and
discerning Part of Mankind, and which has drawn upon you this Dedication; but would
have protected you from it; had any considerable Part of the Work, been mine. The
Share I have in it may be of some Use and Entertainment to others, tho I do not
think </hi>

<pb n="iii"/>

<hi rend="italic">it worth mentioning to you. But I perswade my Self, that
what is made up by other Hands cannot be an unwelcome Present to you. The
Minds of meaner Men are seldom in a due Situation to relish the Charm of
good Verse; the Poets therefore always chose to be read by Men in such a flow
of Happiness as you are blest with.</hi>
</p>

<lg type="stanza"><l>
Non tu Corpus eras fine Pectore. Di tibi formam, </l><l>
Di tibi Divitias dederunt, artemque fruendi.</l></lg>
<bibl><hi rend="italic">Horat.</hi></bibl>

<p>
<hi rend="italic">The</hi> Melange<hi rend="italic"> of so many different
Subjects, and such a Variety of Thoughts upon them (which, if I am not
deceiv'd, give an agreeable</hi> Go&ucirc;t <hi rend="italic">to the Whole)
may not satisfie you so well as a Composition perfect in its kind on one intire
Subject; but possibly it may divert and amuse you better, for here is no thread
of Story, nor connexion of one Part with another, to keep the Mind intent, and
constrain you to any length of Reading; This is a Book that may be taken up and
laid down at Pleasure, and would rather choose to lye about in a With-drawing-Room,
or a Grove, than be set up in a Closet.</hi>
</p>

<pb n="iii"/>

<p>
<hi rend="italic">But that I may not trespass upon your Patience in this
Dedication; when I pretend to have consulted your Ease in the Book; I will
conclude, with professing my self,</hi><lb/>
SIR,
</p>

<closer>
Your most Obedient<lb/>
Humble Servant,<lb/>
<signed>
E. Bysshe.
</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

<div1 type="contents" id="d5">
<pb n="1"/>
<head>RULES<lb/>
For making<lb/>
ENGLISH VERSE.</head>

<p><hi rend="small-caps">In</hi> the English Versification there are Two
Things chiefly to be consider'd;</p>

<list type="ordered">
<item n="1">1. The Verses.</item>
<item n="2">2. The several Sorts of Poems or Compositions in Verse.</item>
</list>

<p>
But because in the Verses there are also two Things to be observ'd; The
Structure of the Verse; and the Rhyme, this Treatise shall be divided into
three Chapters:
</p>

<list type="ordered">
<item n="1">I. Of the Structure of English Verses.</item>
<item n="2">II. Of Rhyme.</item>
<item n="3">III. Of the several Sorts of Poems and Compositions in Verse.</item>
</list>

</div1>
</front>

<body id="d6">
<div1 type="chapter" n="1" id="d7">
<head>CHAP. I.<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Of the Structure of English Verses.</hi>
</head>
<div2 type="section" id="d8">


<p>
<hi rend="small-caps">The</hi> Structure of our Verses, whether Blank or
in Rhyme, consists in a certain Number of Syllables; and not in Feet compos'd
of long and short syllables, as the Verses of the Greeks and Romans. And tho'
some Ingenious Persons formerly puzzled themselves in prescribing Rules for
the quantity of English Syllables, and, in Imitation of the Latins, compos'd
Verses by the measure of <hi rend="italic">Spondees, Dactyls,</hi> &amp;c;
yet the

<pb n="2"/>

Success of their Undertaking has fully evinc'd the Vainness of their Attempt,
and given ground to suspect that they had not thoroughly weigh'd what the
Genius of our Language would bear; nor reflected that each Tongue has its
peculiar Beauties, and that what is agreeable and natural to one, is very
often disagreeable, nay, inconsistent with another. But that Design being
now wholly exploded, it is sufficient to have mention'd it.
</p><p>
Our Verses therefore consist in a certain Number of Syllables; but the Verses
of double Rhyme require a Syllable more than those of single Rhyme. Thus in a
Poem, whose Verses consist of ten Syllables, those of the same Poem that are
accented upon the last save one, which we call Verses of double Rhyme, must
have Eleven; as may be seen by these Verses.
</p>

<lg type="stanza"><l>
<hi rend="italic">A Man so various that he seem'd to be</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Not one, but all Mankind's Epitome :</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Stiff in Opinions, always in the Wrong,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Was ev'ry thing by starts, and nothing long :</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">But, in the course of one revolving Moon,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Was Fidler, Chymist, Statesman, and Buffoon.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Then all for Women, Painting, Rhyming, Drinking</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Besides Ten thousand Freaks that dy'd in Thinking.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Praising and railing were his usual Themes,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And both, to shew his Judgment, in extreams.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">So over violent or over Civil,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">That every Man with him was God or Devil.</hi></l>
</lg><lb/>
<bibl>Dryd.</bibl>

<p>
Where the 4 Verses that are accented on the <hi rend="italic">Penultima </hi>
have 11 Syllables, the others, accented upon the last, but 10.
</p><p>
In a Poem whose Verses consist of 8, the double Rhymes require 9. as,
</p>

<lg type="stanza"><l>
<hi rend="italic">When hard Words, Jealousies and Fears,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Set Folks together by the Ears;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And made 'em fight, like mad, or drunk,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">For Dame Religion, as for Punk;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Whose Honesty they all durst swear for,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Tho' not a Man of 'em knew wherefore.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Then did Sir Knight abandon dwelling,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And out he rode a Collonelling.</hi></l>
</lg><lb/>
<bibl>Hud.</bibl>

<pb n="3"/>

<p>
In a Poem whose Verses consist of 7, the double Rhymes require 8. as,
</p>

<lg type="stanza"><l>
<hi rend="italic">All thy Verse is softer far</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Than the Downy Feathers are</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Of my Wings, or of my Arrows,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Of my Mother's Doves or Sparrows.</hi></l></lg><lb/>
<bibl>Cowl.</bibl>

<p>
This must also be observ'd in Blank Verse.
</p>

<lg type="stanza"><l>
<hi rend="italic">Yet not for those,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Nor what the Potent Victor in his Rage</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Can else inflict, do I repent or change,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Tho' chang'd in outward Lustre: that fix'd Mind</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And High Disdain from sense of Injur'd Merit,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">That with the Mightiest rais'd me to contend,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And to the fierce Contention brought along</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Innumerable Force of Spirits arm'd,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">That durst dislike his Reign, and me preferring</hi></l>
</lg><lb/>
<bibl>(Milt.</bibl>

<p>
And this Verse of the same Poet,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Void of all Succour and needful Comfort,</hi></l></lg>

<p>
wants a Syllable; for, being accented on the last save one, it ought to have
Eleven, as two Verses of the preceeding Example have: But if we transpose
the Words thus,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Of Succour, and all needful Comfort void,</hi></l></lg>

<p>
it becomes a true Verse, and wants nothing of its due Measure, because
it is accented on the last Syllable.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d9">
<head>SECT. I.</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Of the several sorts of Verses, and first of those of 10
Syllables, and of the due Observation of the</hi> Accent,<hi rend="italic">
and of the</hi> Pause.
</p>

<p>
Our Poetry admits for the most part but of three sorts of Verses; that is
to say, of Verses of 10, 8, or 7 Syllables: Those of 4, 6, 9, 11, 12, and 14,
are generally imploy'd in Masks and Operas, and in the Stanzas of Lyrick and
Pindarick Odes, and we have few intire Poems compos'd in any of those sorts
of Verses. But those of 12 and 14 Syllables

<pb n="4"/>

are frequently inserted in our Poems in Heroick Verse, and when rightly made
use of, carry a peculiar Grace with them. See <hi rend="italic">Sect</hi>. 2.
towards the end.
</p><p>
The Verses of 10 Syllables, which are our Heroick, are us'd in Heroick Poems,
in Tragedies, Comedies, Pastorals, Elegies, &amp;c. and sometimes in Burlesque.
</p><p>
In these Verses two things are chiefly to be consider'd.
</p>

<list>
<item n="1">1. The Seat of the Accent. </item>
<item n="2">2. The Pause. </item>
</list>

<p>For, 'tis not enough that Verses have their just Number of Syllables: the
true Harmony of them depends on a due Observation of the Accent and Pause.
</p><p>
The Accent is an Elevation of the Voice on a certain Syllable of a Word.
</p><p>
The Pause is a Rest or Stop that is made in pronouncing the Verse, and that
divides it, as it were, into two parts; each of which is call'd an Hemistich,
or half Verse.
</p><p>
But this Division is not always equal, that is to say, one of the Half-verses
does not always contain the same Number of Syllables as the other: and this
Inequality proceeds from the Seat of the Accent that is strongest, and prevails
most in the first Half-verse. For, the Pause must be observ'd at the end of the
Word where such Accent happens to be, or at the end of the following Word, as
shall be shewn immediately.
</p><p>
Now in a Verse of 10 Syllables, this Accent must
be either on the 2d, 4th, or 6th; which produces 5 several Pauses, that is to
say at the 3d,4th, 5th, 6th, or 7th Syllables of the Verse; For,
</p><p>
When it happens to be on the 2d, the Pause will be either at the 3d, or 4th.
</p><p>
At the 3d in two manners;
</p>

<list>
<item n="1">1. When the Syllable of the Accent happens to be the last save
one of a Word; as,
</item></list>
<lg><l><hi rend="italic">As Busy&mdash;as Intentive Emmets are;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Or Cities&mdash;whom unlook'd for Sieges scare.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Dav.</bibl><lb/>

<list>
<item n="2">2. Or, when the Accent is on the last of a Word, and that the
next be a Monosyllable that may be sunk in its Pronunciation, and whose
Construction is Govern'd by that word on which the Accent is; as,<lb/>
</item></list>
<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Despise it,</hi>&mdash;<hi rend="italic">And more
noble Thoughts pursue.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Dryd.</bibl>

<pb n="5"/>

<p>
When the Accent falls on the 2d Syllable of the Verse, and the last save
two of a Word, the Pause will be at the 4th; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">The Covetous</hi>&mdash;<hi rend="italic">toil long
for an Estate.</hi></l></lg>

<p>
When the Accent is on the 4th of a Verse, the Pause will be either at the
same Syllable, or at the 5th or 6th.
</p>

<p>
At the same, when the Syllable of the Accent happens to be the last of a
Word; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Such huge Extreams&mdash;inhabit thy great
Mind,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">God-like, unmov'd,&mdash;and yet like Woman,
kind.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl>

<p>
At the 5th in 2 manners.
</p>

<list>
<item n="1">1. When it happens to be the last save one of a Word , as,
</item></list>

<lg type="stanza"><l>
<hi rend="italic">Light Bright Aurora&mdash;whose refulgent Ray</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Foretells the Fervour&mdash;of ensuing Day,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And warns the Shepherd&mdash;with his Flocks, retreat</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">To leafy shadows&mdash;from the threaten'd Heat.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl><lb/>

<list>
<item n="2">2. Or the last of the Word, and that the following one be a
Monosyllable govern'd by it, and that may be lower'd in its Pronunciation; as,
</item></list>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">So fresh the Wound is&mdash; and the Grief so
vast.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl>

<p>
At the 6th, when the Syllable of the Accent happens to be the last save
two of a Word; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Those Seeds of Luxury&mdash;Debate and Pride.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl>

<p>
Lastly, When the Accent is upon the 6th Syllable of the Verse, the Pause
will be either at the same Syllable, or at the 7th.
</p><p>
At the same, when the Syllable of the Accent happens tobe the last of a Word;
as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">She meditates Revenge&mdash;resolv'd to dye.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl>

<p>
At the 7th in two manners.
</p>

<list>
<item n="1">1. When it happens to be the last save one of a Word; as,
</item></list>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Mirrors are taught to flatter</hi>&mdash;
<hi rend="italic">but our Springs.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl><lb/>

<list>
<item n="2">2. Or the last of a Word, if the following one be a
Monosyllable that may be funk in pronouncing, and whose Construction
depends on the preceeding Word on which the Accent is; as,
</item></list>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">And since he could not save her</hi>&mdash;
<hi rend="italic">with her dy'd.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Dryd.</bibl>


<pb n="6"/>

<p>
From all this it appears, that the Pause is determined by the Seat of the Accent, but if
it should happen that the Accents on the 2d, 4th,or 6th Syllable of a Verse be equally
strong, the Sence and Construction of the Words must then guide to the observance of
the Pause: For Example; In the Verse I cited as an Instance of it at the 7th Syllable.
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Mirrors are taught&mdash;to flatter, but our
Springs,</hi></l></lg>

<p>
The Accent is as strong on <hi rend="italic">Taught,</hi> as on the first
Syllable of <hi rend="italic">Flatter,</hi> and if the Pause were observ'd
at the 4th Syllable of the Verse, it would have nothing disagreable in its
Sound; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Mirrors are taught&mdash;to flatter, but our
Springs,</hi></l></lg>

<p>
Which tho' it be no Violence to the Ear, yet it is to the Sense, and that ought always
carefully to be avoided in repeating Verses.
</p>

<p>
For this Reason it is, that the Construction or Sence should never end, at a Syllable
where the Pause ought not to be made; as at the 8th and 2d in the two
following Verses:
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Bright Hesper twinkles from afar:&mdash;Away</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">My Kids!&mdash;for you have had a Feast to day.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Staff.</bibl>

<p>
Which Verses have nothing disagreeable in their Structure but the Pause, which in the
first of them must be observ'd at the 8th Syllable, in the 2d at the 2d, and so unequal a
Division can produce no true Harmony.
</p>

<p>
The foregoing Rules ought indispensably to be follow'd in all our Verses of 10
Syllables, and the observation of them, like that of Right Time in Musick, will
produce Harmony; the neglect of them Harshness and Discord, as appears by the
following Verses,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">None think Rewards render'd worthy their Worth,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And both Lovers, both thy Disciples were.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Dav.</bibl>

<p>
Where tho' the true Number of Syllables be observ'd, yet neither of them have
so much as the sound of a Verse: Now their disagreeableness proceeds from the
undue Seat of the Accent: For Example, the first of them is accented on the 5th
and 7th Syllables; but if we change the Words, and remove the Accent from thence,
the Verse will become smooth and easie; as,
</p>

<pb n="6"/>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">None think Rewards are equal to their Worth.</hi></l></lg>

<p>
<hi rend="italic"></hi> The harshness of the last of them proceeds from its being
accented on the 3d Syllable, which may be mended thus, by transposing only one
Word;
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">And Lovers both, both thy Disciples were.</hi></l></lg>

<p>
In like manner the following Verses
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">To be Massacred, not in Battle stain.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Blac.</bibl>
<lg><l><hi rend="italic">But forc'd, harsh, and uneasie unto all.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowl.</bibl>
<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Against the Insults of the Wind and Tide.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Blac.</bibl>
<lg><l><hi rend="italic">A second Essay will the Pow'rs appease.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Blac.</bibl>
<lg><l><hi rend="italic">With</hi> Scythians <hi rend="italic">expert in
the Dart and Bow.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Dryd.</bibl>

<p>
are rough, because the foregoing Rules are not observ'd in their Structure; for
Example, the first, where the Pause is the 5th Syllable, and the Accent at the 3d, is
contrary to the Rule that says, that the Accent that determines the Pause must be on
the 2d, 4th, or 6th Syllable of the Verse; and to mend that Verse we need only place
the Accent on the 4th, and then the Pause at the 5th will have nothing disagreeable,
as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Thus to be murder'd, not in Battle stain.</hi></l></lg>

<p>
The Second Verse is accented on the 3d Syllable, and the Pause is there too;
which makes it indeed the thing it expresses, forc'd, harsh, and uneasie; it
may be mended thus,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">But forc'd and harsh, uneasie unto all.</hi></l></lg>

<p>
The 3d, 4th, and 6th of those Verses have like faults, for the Pauses are at the 5th, and
the Accent there too, which is likewise contrary to the foregoing Rules: Now they will
become smooth and flowing, by taking the Accent from the 5th, and altering the Seat
of the Pause; as
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Against th' Insults both of the Wind and Tide.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">A Second Tryal will the Pow'rs appease.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">With</hi> Scythians <hi rend="italic">skilful in the
Dart and Bow.</hi></l></lg>

<p>
From whence we may gather, that in all Verses of 10 Syllables, the most
prevailing Accents ought to be on the 2d, 4th, and 6th Syllables; for if
they are on the 3d, 5th, or 7th, the Verse will be rough and disagreeable,
ashas been prov'd by the preceeding Instances.
</p>

<pb n="8"/>

<p>
In short, the wrong placing of the Accent is as great a fault in our
Versification, as false Quantity was in that of the Ancients, and therefore
we ought to take an equal care to avoid it, and endeavour to to dispose the
Words as may create a certain Melody in the Ear, without Labour to the Tongue,
or Violence to the Sence.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d10">
<head>SECT. II.</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Of the other sorts of Verses that are us'd in our
Poetry.</hi>
</p>

<p>
After the Verses of 10 Syllables, those of 8 are most frequent, and we have many
intire Poems compos'd in them.
</p><p>
In the Structure of these Verses, as well as of those of <hi rend="italic">7</hi>
Syllables, we must take care that the most prevailing Accent be neither on the 3d, nor
5th Syllables of them.
</p><p>
They also require a Pause to be observ'd in pronouncing them, which is generally at
the 3d, 4th, or 5th Syllable; and the true Seat of it may be discover'd by the Rules
already prescrib'd in the preceeding Section.
</p><p>
The Verses of Nine, and of Eleven Syllables, are of two sorts; one of those that are
accented upon the last save one, which are only the Verses of double Rhyme that
belong to those of 8 and 10 Syllables, of which Examples have already been given.
The other of those that are accented on the last Syllable, which are employ'd only in
Musical Compositions, and in the lowest sort of Burlesque Poetry, the
disagreeableness of their Measure, having wholy excluded
them from grave and serious Subjects. Those who desire to see Examples of them,
may find some scatter'd here and there in our Masques, and Operas, and in our
Burlesque Writers. I will give you but two.
</p>

<lg><l>Hilas, O Hilas, <hi rend="italic">why sit we mute?</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Now that each Bird saluteth the Spring.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Apart let me view then each Heavenly Fair,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">For three at a time there's no Mortal can bear.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Congr.</bibl>

<pb n="9"/>

<p>
The Verses of 12 Syllables are truly Heroick, both in their Measure and Sound; tho
we have no intire Works compos'd in them; and they are so far from being a Blemish
to the Poems they are in, that on the contrary, when rightly imploy'd, they conduce
not a little to the Ornament pf them; particularly in the following Rencounters.
</p>

<list>
<item n="1">1. When they conclude an Episode in an Heroick Poem: Thus <hi rend="italic">Stafford</hi> ends his Translation of that of <hi
rend="italic">Camilla</hi> from the 11th &AElig;neid, by a Verse of 12 Syllables,
</item></list>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">The ling'ring Soul th' unwelcom Doom receives,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And murm'ring with Disdain&mdash;the beauteous Body
leaves.</hi></l></lg>

<list>
<item n="2">2. When they conclude a Triplet and full Sence together, as,
</item></list>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Millions of opening Mouths to Fame belong;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And every Mouth is furnish'd with a Tongue;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And round with list'ning Ears&mdash;the flying Plague is hung.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>(Dryd.</bibl>

<p>
(But here we may observe by the way, that whenever a Triplet is made use of in an
Heroick Poem, it is a fault not to close the Sence at the end of the Triplet, but to
continue it on to the beginning of the next Line , as <hi rend="italic">Dryden</hi>
has done in his Translation of the 11th &AElig;neid in these Lines:
</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">With Olives Crown'd the Presents they shall bear</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">A Purple Robe, a Royal Iv'ry Chair,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And all the Marks of Sway, that</hi> Latian
<hi rend="italic">Monarchs wear,</hi> </l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And Sums of Gold,</hi> &amp;c.</l></lg>

<p>
And in the 7th &AElig;neid he has committed the like fault.
</p>

<lg type="stanza"><l>
<hi rend="italic">Then they, whose Mothers, Frantick with their Fear,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">In Woods and Wilds the Flags of Bacchus bear,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And lead his Dances with dishevel'd Hair,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Increase the Clamour</hi></l></lg>

<p>
But the Sence is not confin'd to the Couplet, for the Close of it may fall into the
middle of the next Verse, that is the Third, and sometimes farther off. Examplesof this
are so frequent, that it is needless to give any.)
</p>

<pb n="10"/>

<list>
<item n="3">
3. When they conclude the Stanzas of Lyrick or Pindarick Odes; Examples
of which are frequently seen in <hi rend="italic">Dryden,</hi> and others.
</item></list>

<p>
In these Verses the Pause ought to be at the 6th Syllable, as may be seen in
the foregoing Examples.
</p><p>
We sometimes find it, tho' very rarely, at the 7th; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">That such a cursed Creature&mdash;lives so long a
space,</hi></l></lg>

<p>
When it is at the 4th, the Verse will be rough; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">And Midwife Time&mdash;the ripen'd Plot to Murder
brought.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Dry.</bibl>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Like a swoln Flood&mdash;from some steep Mountain
pours along.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cow.</bibl>

<p>
In the last of which it is very apparent, that if the Sence and Construction
would allow us to make the Pause at the 6th Syllable,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Like a swoln Flood from some&mdash;steep Mountain
pours along.</hi></l></lg>

<p>
the Verse would be much more flowing and easie.
</p>

<p>
The Verses of 14 Syllables are less frequent than those of 12;<hi rend="italic">,
</hi> they are likewise inserted in Heroick Poems, &amp;c. and are agreeable
enough when they conclude a Triplet and Sence, and follow a Verse of 12; as,
</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">For Thee the Land in fragrant Flow'rs is drest;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">For Thee the Ocean smiles, and smooths her wavy Breast,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And Heav'n it self with more serene and purer Light is blest.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>(Dryd.</bibl>

<p>
But if they follow one of 10 Syllables, the Inequality of
the Measure renders them less agreeable; as,</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">While all thy Province, Nature, I survey,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And sing to</hi> Memmius <hi rend="italic">an Immortal Lay</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Of Heav'n and earth; and every where thy wondrous (Pow'r display. </hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Dryd.</bibl>

<p>
Especially if it be the last of a Couplet only; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">With Court Informers haunts and Royal Spies,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Things done relates, not done she feigns, and mingles Truth with
Lies.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Dryd.</bibl>

<pb n="11"/>

<p>
But this is only in Heroicks, for in Pindaricks and Lyricks Verses of 12 or 14
Syllables are frequently and gracefully plac'd after those that are not only of 12,
or 10, but even of any other number of Syllables whatsoever.
</p><p>
The Verses of 4 and 6 Syllables have nothing worth observing, and therefore I shall
content my self with having made mention of them. They are as I said before, us'd
only in Operas, and Masks, and in Lyrick and Pindarick Odes. Take one Example of
them,
</p>

<lg type="stanza"><l>
<hi rend="italic">A Mind that's truly brave</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Stands despising,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Storms arising,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And can't be made a Slave.</hi></l></lg>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="3" id="d11">
<head>SECT. III.</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Several Rules conducing to the beauty of our Versification.</hi>
</p>

<p>
Our Poetry being very much polish'd and refin'd since the Days of
<hi rend="italic">Chaucer</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Spencer</hi>, and
the other Ancient Poets, some Rules which they neglected, and that conduce
very much to the Ornament of it, have beep practis'd by the best of the Moderns.
</p><p>
The first is, to avoid as much as possible the Concourse of Vowels, which occasions
a certain ill-sounding Gaping, call'd by the Latins <hi rend="italic">Hiatus,</hi>
and which they thought so disagreeable to the Ear, that, to avoid it, whenever a Word
ended in a Vowel, and the next began by one, they never, even in Prose, sounded the
Vowel of the first Word, but lost it in the Pronunciation, and it is a fault in our
Poets not to do the like, whenever our Language will admit of it.
</p><p>
For this Reason the <hi rend="italic">e</hi> of the Particle <hi rend="italic">
The,</hi> ought always to be cut off before the Words that begin by a
Vowel;  as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">With weeping Eyes she heard th' unwelcome News. </hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Dryd.</bibl>

<p>
And it is a fault to make <hi rend="italic">The</hi> and the first Syllable of the
following word two distinct Syllables, as in this:
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Restrain'd a while by the unwelcome Night.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl>

<pb n="12"/>

<p>
A second sort of <hi rend="italic">Hiatus</hi>, and that ought no less to be
avoided, is, when a Word that ends in a Vowel that cannot be cut off, is plac'd
before one that begins by the same Vowel, or one that has the like Sound; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Should thy Iambicks swell into a Book.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl>

<p>
The second Rule is, to contract the two last Syllables of the Preter-Perfect
Tenses of all the Verbs that will admit of it; which are all the Regular Verbs
whatsoever, except only those in D and T, and in DE and TE. And it is a fault to
make <hi rend="italic">Amazed</hi> of three Syllables, and <hi rend="italic">
Loved</hi> of two; instead of <hi rend="italic">Amaz'd</hi> of two, and
<hi rend="italic">Lov'd</hi> of one.
</p><p>
And the second Person of the Present and Preterperfect Tenses of all Verbs
ought to be contracted in like manner, as <hi rend="italic">Thou Lov'st</hi>,
for <hi rend="italic">thou lovest</hi>, &amp;c.
</p><p>
The third Rule is, not to make use of several Words in a Verse, that begin by the same
Letter; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">The Court he knew to steer in Storms of State.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Dav.</bibl>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">He in these Miracles Design Discern'd.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Dryd.</bibl>

<p>
The fourth is, to avoid ending a Verse by an Adjective whose Substantive begins the
following one; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Some lost their quiet Rivals, some their kind Parents,</hi>
&amp;c.</l></lg>
<bibl>Dav.</bibl>

<p>
Or, by a Preposition when the Case it governs begins the Verse that follows; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">The daily less'ning of our Life shews by</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">A little dying, how outright to dye.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl>

<p>
The fifth is to avoid the frequent use of Words of many Syllables, which are proper
enough to Prose, but come not into Verse without a certain Violence altogether
disagreeable; particularly those whose Accent is on the fourth Syllable
from the last.
</p><pb n="13"/>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="4" id="d12">
<head>SECT. IV.</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Doubts concerning the Number of Syllables of certain
Words.</hi>
</p>

<p>
There is no Language whatsoever that so often joyns several Vowels together to make
Dipthongs of them as ours; this appears from our having several compos'd of three
different Vowels: as EAU, and EOU in <hi rend="italic">Beauteous</hi>:  IOU in
<hi rend="italic">Glorious,</hi> UAI in <hi rend="italic">Acquaint,</hi> and
several others.
</p><p>
Now from hence may arise some Difficulties concerning the true Pronunciation of
those Vowels: Whether they ought to be founded separately in two Syllables, or
joyntly in one.
</p><p>
The Ancient Poets made them sometimes of two Syllables, sometimes but of one,
as the Measure of their Verse requir'd ; but they are now become to be but of
one, and it is a fault to make them of two: From whence we may draw this general
Rule;
</p><p>
That whenever one Syllable of a Word ends in a Vowel, and the next begins by
one, provided the first of those Syllables be not that on which the Word is
accented; those two Syllables ought in Verse to be contracted and made but one.
Thus <hi rend="italic">Beauteous</hi> is but of two Syllables, <hi rend="italic">
Victorious</hi> but of three, and it is a fault in <hi rend="italic">Dryden,</hi>
to make it of four, as he has done in this Verse:
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Your Arms are on the</hi> Rhine <hi rend="italic">
Victorious.</hi></l></lg>

<p>
To prove that this Verse wants a Syllable of its due Measure, we have but to add
one to it, as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Tour Arms are on thee</hi> Rhine <hi rend="italic">Victorious now.</hi></l></lg>

<p>
Where tho' the Syllable <hi rend="italic">now</hi> be added to the Verse, it
has no more than its due number of Syllables, which plainly proves the other
wanted it.
</p><p>
But if the Accent be upon the first of these Syllables, they cannot be
contracted to make a Dipthong, but must be computed as two distinct Syllables:
Thus <hi rend="italic">Poet, Lyon, Quiet</hi>, and the like, must always be of
two Syllables: <hi rend="italic">Poetry</hi> and the like, of three.
</p>

<pb n="14"/>

<p>
And it is a fault to make <hi rend="italic">Riot</hi>, (for Example,) but of
one Syllable, as <hi rend="italic">Milton</hi> has done in this Verse.
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Their Riot ascends above their lofty Tow'rs</hi>.</l></lg>

<p>
And the same Poet has in another place made use of the same Word twice in one
Verse, and made it of two Syllables each time.
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">With Riot upon Riot, Rout on Rout.</hi></l></lg>

<p>
And any Ear may discover that this last has its true Measure, the other not.
</p><p>
But there are some words that may be excepted; as <hi rend="italic">Diamond,
Violet, Violent, Diadem,</hi> and perhaps some others, which though they are
accented upon the first Vowel, are sometimes us'd but as two Syllables, as in
the following Verses,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">From Diamond Quarries hewn, and Rocks of Gold.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Milt.</bibl>
<lg><l><hi rend="italic">With Poppies, Daffadils, and Violets joyn'd.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Tate.</bibl>
<lg><l><hi rend="italic">With Vain, but Violent Force their Darts they flung.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowl.</bibl>
<lg><l><hi rend="italic">His Ephod, Mitre, well-cut Diadem on.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowl.</bibl>

<p>
Sometimes three; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">A Mount of Rocky Diamond did rise.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Blac.</bibl>
<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Hence the blue Violet and blushing Rose.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Gar.</bibl>

<p>
But this Contraction is not always made of Syllables of the same Word; for the
Particle <hi rend="italic">A</hi> being plac'd after a Word that ends in a Vowel,
will sometimes admit of the like Contradiction: For Example, after the Word
<hi rend="italic">Many</hi>; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">I have attended many a Winter Night.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Dryd.</bibl>
<lg><l><hi rend="italic">They many a Trophy gain'd with many a Wound.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Dav.</bibl>

<p>
After <hi rend="italic">To</hi>; as
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Can he to a Friend, to a Son so bloody grow.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowl.</bibl>

<pb n="15"/>

<p>
After <hi rend="italic">They</hi>; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">From thee their long-known King they a King desire.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowl.</bibl>

<p>
After <hi rend="italic">By</hi>; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">When we by a foolish Figure say.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowl.</bibl>

<p>
And perhaps after some others.
</p>

<p>
There are also many other Words whose Syllables are sometimes contracted,
sometimes not: As <hi rend="italic">Bower</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Heaven,
Prayer, Nigher, Towards</hi>, and many other of the like nature: But they generally
ought to be us'd but as one Syllable; and then they suffer an Elision of the e that
preceedes their final Consonant, and ought to be written thus: <hi
rend="italic">Pow'r,</hi> <hi rend="italic">Heav'n, Pray'r, </hi>&amp;c.
</p><p>
The Termination ISM is always us'd but as one Syllable; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Where griefly Schism and raging Strife appear.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowl.</bibl>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">And Rhumatisms I send to rack the Joynts.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Dryd.</bibl>

<p>
And, indeed, considering that it has but one Vowel, it may seem absurd to assert that
it ought to be reckon'd two Syllables; and yet in my Opinion, those Verses seem to
have a Syllable more than their due Measure, and would run better if we took a
Syllable from them; as,
</p>

<l><hi rend="italic">Where griefly Schism, raging Strife appear,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">I Rhumatisms send to rack the Joynts.</hi></l>

<p>
But this Opinion being contrary to the constant practice of our Poets, I shall
not presume to advance it as a Rule for others to follow, but propose it only to
the consideration of such as are better Judges of Poetical Numbers, and whose Ears
are more Musical than mine. The like too may be said of the Terminations ASM and OSM.
</p><pb n="16"/>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="5" id="d13">
<head>SECT. V.</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Of the Elisions that are admitted in our Versification.</hi>
</p>

<p>
Our Verses consisting only of a certain Number of Syllables, nothing can be of more
ease, or greater use to our Poets than the retaining or cutting off a Syllable from a
Verse, according as the measure of it requires; and therefore it will be requisite to
treat of the Elisions that are allowable in our Poetry, some of which have been already
taken notice of in the preceeding Article.
</p><p>
By Elision I mean the cutting off one or more Letters from a. Word, whereby two
Syllables come to be contracted into one, or the taking away an entire Syllable; Now
when in a Word of more than two Syllables, which is accented upon the last save two,
any of the Liquids L, M, N, or R, happen to be between two Vowels, that which
preceedes the Liquid admits of an Elision. Of this nature are all the Words in LOUS,
MOUS, NOUS, and ROUS preceded by a Vowel; as <hi rend="italic">Fabulous,
Amorous,</hi> which are Words of three Syllables, and often us'd as such in Verse:
But they may also be contracted into two, by cutting off the Vowel that preceedes the
Liquid; as <hi rend="italic">Fab'lous, Am'rous.</hi>
</p><p>
Observe, that I said accented upon the last save two, for if the Word be accented on
the last save one; that is to say, upon the Vowel that precedes the Liquid, that Vowel
may not be cut off. And therefore it is a fault in some Poets to make, for Example, <hi
rend="italic">Sonorous</hi> of two Syllables, as in this Verse;
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">With Son'rous Metals wak'd the drowsie Day.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Blac.</bibl>

<p>
Which always ought to be of three; as in this,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Sonorous Metals blowing Martial Sounds.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Milt.</bibl>

<p>
There are also many Words in RY, that admit of the like Elisions; as <hi
rend="italic">Vot'ry, Vict'ry,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Votary, Victory,</hi>
&amp;c.
</p><p>
To these may be added the Gerunds of all Verbs whose Infinitives end in any of the
Liquids, preceeded by a Vowel or Dipthong, and that are accented upon the last save
one,

<pb n="17"/>

for the Gerunds being form'd by adding the Syllable ING to the Infinitive, the Liquid,
that was their final Letter, comes thereby to be between two Vowels, and the Accent
that was upon the last save one of the Infinitive, comes to be on the last save two of
the Gerund, and therefore the Vowel or Dipthong that preceeds the Liquid may be cut
off, by means whereof the Gerund of three Syllables comes to be but of two, as from
<hi rend="italic">Travel, Travelling,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Trav'ling,</hi>
from <hi rend="italic">Endeavour, Endeavouring,</hi> or <hi
rend="italic">Endeav'ring,</hi> and many others.
</p><p>
But if the Accent be upon the last Syllable of such a Verb, its Gerund will not
suffer such an Elision: Thus the Gerund of <hi rend="italic">Devour</hi> must
always be of 3 Syllables, <hi rend="italic">Devouring,</hi>not <hi rend="italic">
Dev'ring,</hi> because all Derivatives still retain the Accent of their Primitives,
that is, upon the same Syllable, and the Accent always obliges the Syllable upon
which it is to remain intire.
</p><p>
Whenever the Letter S happens to be between two Vowels in words of the like Nature,
that is to say, that are Accented upon the last save one, one of the Vowels will
admit of the like Elision; as <hi rend="italic">Pris'ner, Bus'ness,</hi> &amp;c.
</p><p>
Or the Letter C when it is sounded like S, that is to say, whenever it preceeds
the Vowels <hi rend="italic">e</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">i,</hi> as, <hi
rend="italic">Med'cine</hi> for <hi rend="italic">Medicine,</hi> &amp;c.
</p><p>
Whenever V Consonant happens to be between two Vowles, the last of them may be
cut off, as <hi rend="italic">Ev'n, Ev'ry</hi>, &amp;c. But <hi
rend="italic">Never, Ever, Over,</hi> lose their Consonant, and are contracted
thus: <hi rend="italic">Ne'er, E'er, O'er.</hi>
</p><p>
Lastly, to these may be added the Gerunds of the Verbs in OW, that are Accented
upon the last save one, as <hi rend="italic">Follow, Wallow,</hi> &amp;c. All
which will suffer an Elision of the O that preceeds the W; as <hi
rend="italic">Foll'wing, Wall'wing,</hi> &amp;c.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="6" id="d14">
<head>SECT. VI.</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Some other Elisions that are frequently us'd in our
Versification; and particularly of the Particles</hi> It, Is, To, Are,
Will, He, She, We, Would, Have, His, Am, Not, In, The, Who, By.
</p>

<p>
The Particle <hi rend="italic">It</hi> admits of an Elision of its I, when
it is plac'd after any word that ends in a Vowel ; as <hi rend="italic">by't</hi>
for <hi rend="italic">by it,</hi> <hi rend="italic">do't</hi> for <hi rend="italic">
do it,</hi> &amp;c. Or that ends in any of the Consonants

<pb n="18"/>

that can be pronounc'd after the Letter T, as <hi rend="italic">Was't</hi> for
<hi rend="italic">Was it, In't</hi> for <hi rend="italic">In it</hi>, and the
like.
</p><p>
Or when it is plac'd before any Word. that begins by a Vowel, or by any of
the Consonants that the Letter T can be sounded before, as <hi rend="italic">`Tis</hi>
for <hi rend="italic">It is</hi>, <hi rend="italic">T'wouId</hi> for
<hi rend="italic">It would,</hi> &amp;c.
</p><p>
The Particle <hi rend="italic">Is</hi> may lose its I after any Word that ends
in a Vowel, or in any of the Consonants after which the 'Letter S may be sounded;
<hi rend="italic">she's</hi> for <hi rend="italic">she is</hi>: The
<hi rend="italic">Air's</hi> for the <hi rend="italic">Air is,</hi> &amp;c.
</p><p>
<hi rend="italic">To</hi> (sign of the Infinitive) may lose its O before any
Word that begins by a Vowel; as <hi rend="italic">T' amaze, t' undo</hi>, &amp;c.
</p><p>
<hi rend="italic">Are</hi> may lose its A after the Pronouns Personal <hi
rend="italic">We, You, They,</hi> as <hi rend="italic">We're, You're,
They're</hi>: And thus it is that this Elision ought to be made, and not as some do,
by cutting offthe Final Vowels of the Pronouns Personal; <hi rend="italic">W'are,
Y'are</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> Th'are</hi>: It also loses its A after <hi
rend="italic">Who</hi>: <hi rend="italic">Who're</hi> for <hi
rend="italic">Who are</hi>.
</p><p>
<hi rend="italic">Will</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Would</hi> may lose all their
first Letters, and retain only their final one, after any of the Pronouns Personal; as <hi
rend="italic">I'll</hi> for I will, <hi rend="italic">He'd</hi> for <hi
rend="italic">He would,</hi> &amp;c. or after <hi rend="italic">Who,</hi> as
<hi rend="italic">who'll</hi> for <hi rend="italic">who will, who'd</hi> for <hi
rend="italic">who would.</hi>
</p><p>
<hi rend="italic">He, She, We,</hi> may lose their E before any Verb that begins
by a Vowel; as <hi rend="italic">Sh' exposes</hi>, <hi
rend="italic">W'aim</hi>,&amp;c. And sometimes before other words, as in this
Verse of <hi rend="italic">Cowley.</hi>
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Shame and Woe to us, if w' our Wealth obey.</hi></l></lg>

<p>
<hi rend="italic">Have</hi>, may lose its two first Letters after
<hi rend="italic">I, You, We, They</hi>; as <hi rend="italic">I've, You've,
We've, They've.</hi>
</p><p>
<hi rend="italic">Not,</hi> loses its two first Letters after can; <hi
rend="italic">Can't</hi> for <hi rend="italic">Can not.</hi>
</p><p>
<hi rend="italic">Am,</hi> may lose its A after I: <hi rend="italic">I'm</hi> for
<hi rend="italic">I am.</hi>
</p><p>
<hi rend="italic">Us</hi>, its U after Let, <hi rend="italic">Let's</hi> for <hi
rend="italic">let us.</hi>
</p><p>
<hi rend="italic">Taken</hi>, its K, as <hi rend="italic">Ta'en</hi>, for so it
ought to be writ not <hi rend="italic">ta'ne.</hi>
</p><p>
In some of our Poets we find the Particle <hi rend="italic">His</hi> lose its two
first Letters after any word that ends in a Vowel; as <hi rend="italic">To's</hi>,
<hi rend="italic">by's,</hi> &amp;c. for <hi rend="italic">to his, by his,</hi>
&amp;c. Or after any word that ends in a Consonant, after which the Letter S can be
pronounc'd, as <hi rend="italic">In's, for's,</hi> for <hi rend="italic">In his, for
his, </hi>&amp;c This is frequent in <hi rend="italic">Cowley,</hi> who I must
confess often makes Contractions that are scarce allowable; as <hi rend="italic">t'
your</hi> for <hi rend="italic">to your, t' which</hi> for <hi rend="italic">to
which,</hi> and many others; In which we must be cautious of following his
Example: But the Contracting the Particle <hi rend="italic">His</hi> in the manner
I have mention'd, is not wholly to be Condemn'd.
</p><p>
We sometimes find the word <hi rend="italic">Who,</hi> contracted before words
that begin by a Vowel; As,
</p>

<pb n="19"/>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Wh' expose to scorn and hate both them and it.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowley.</bibl>

<p>
And the Preposition <hi rend="italic">By</hi> in like manner; As,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">B' unequal Fate, and Providence's Crime.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Dryd.</bibl>

<p>
But these and the like Contractions are very rare in our most Correct Poets, and
ought but sparingly to be follow'd.
</p><p>
I have already spoken of the Contraction of the Particle <hi rend="italic">The</hi>
before Vowels, in the Third Section of this Chapter, but it will be requisite to take
notice that it sometimes loses its Vowel when it is before a Word that begins by a
ConSonant; and then its two remaining Letters are join'd to the preceeding word; as
<hi rend="italic">to th' Wall,</hi> for <hi rend="italic">to the Wall, by th'
Wall.</hi> for <hi rend="italic">by the Wall,</hi> &amp;c.
</p><p>
It may also be cut off before words that begin by the Letter H, when it is not
strongly aspir'd, and particularly, when the H is follow'd by another E; As,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Th' Heroick Prince's Courage or his Love.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Th' Hesperean Fruit and made the Dragon sleep.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl>

<p>
The Particles <hi rend="italic">In, of,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">on,</hi> and
some others of like Nature sometimes lose their Consonants, and are join'd to the
Particle <hi rend="italic">The</hi> in like manner; as <hi rend="italic">i'th',
o'th',</hi> for <hi rend="italic">In the, of the.</hi>
</p><p>
Some words admit of an Elision of their first Syllable; as <hi rend="italic">`Tween,
`Twixt, `Mong, `Mongst, `Gainst, `Bove, `cause, `fore, `gins, `gan,</hi> for<hi
rend="italic"></hi> for <hi rend="italic">Between, Betwixt, Among, Amongst,
Because, Before, Begins, Began, </hi> and perhaps some others that may be observ'd
in reading our Poets.
</p>
</div2>
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="2" id="d15">
<head>CHAP. II.<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Of Rhyme.</hi>
</head>

<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d16">
<head>SECT. I.</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">What Rhyme is, and the several sorts of it.</hi>
</p>

<p>
Rhyme is only a sameness of sound at the end of words. I say, of Sound,
not of Letters; for as the Office of Rhyme is to content and please the
Ear, and not the Eye, the sound only is to be regarded, not the Writing:
Thus <hi rend="italic">Maid</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Perswade</hi>,
<hi rend="italic">Laugh</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Quaff</hi>, tho'
they differ in

<pb n="20"/>

Writing, Rhyme very well: But <hi rend="italic">Plough</hi> and <hi
rend="italic">Cough, Chang'd</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Hang'd,</hi> tho'
written alike, Rhyme not at all.
</p><p>
In our Versification we may observe 3 several sorts of Rhyme; Single, Double, and
Treble.
</p><p>
The single Rhyme is of two sorts: One of the words that are accented upon the last
Syllable: Another, of those that have their Accent upon the last save two.
</p><p>
The words accented upon the last Syllable, if they end in a Consonant or mute E,
oblige the Rhyme to begin at the Vowel that preceeds their last Consonant, and to
continue to the end of the word: In a Consonant; As,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Here might be seen that Beauty, Wealth and Wit,</hi>
<hi rend="italic">And Prowess to the Pow'r of Love Submit.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Dryd.</bibl>

<p>
In mute E; As,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">A spark of Virtue, by the deepest shade</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Of sad Adversity, is fairer made.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl>

<p>
But if a Dipthong preceed the last Consonant, the Rhyme
must begin at that Vowel of it whose sound most prevails; As,                .
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Next to the Pow'r of making Tempests cease,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Was in that Storm to have so calm a Peace.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl>

<p>
If the words accented upon the last Syllable end in any of the Vowels, except mute E,
or in a Dipthong, the Rhyme is made only to that Vowel or Dipthong, to the Vowel; As,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">So wing'd with praise we penetrate the Sky,</hi> </l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Teach Clouds and Stars to praise him as we fly.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl>

<p>
To the Dipthong; As,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">So hungry Wolves, tho' greedy of their Prey,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Stop when they find a Lyon in the way.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl>

<p>
The other sort of single Rhyme is of the words that have their Accent upon the last
Syllable, save two; And these Rhyme to each other in the same manner as the former;
that is to say, if they end in any of the Vowels, except mute E, the Rhyme is made
only to that Vowel; As,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">So seems to speak the Youthful Deity;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Voice, Colour, Hair, and all like Mercury.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl>

<p>
But if they end in a Consonant or mute E, the Rhyme must begin at the Vowel that
preceeds that Consonant, and continue to the end of the word.
</p><p>
But we must take notice that all the words that are accented upon the last save two,
will Rhyme not only to one another, but also to all the words whose Terminations
have

<pb n="21"/>

the same sound, tho' they are accented upon the last Syllable. Thus <hi rend="italic">
Tenderness</hi> Rhymes not only to <hi rend="italic">Poetess, Wretchedness</hi> and
the like, that are accented upon the last save two, but also to <hi rend="italic">
Confess, Express, </hi>&amp;c. that are accented upon the last; As,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Thou art my Father now, these words confess</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">That Name, and that indulgent Tenderness.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Dryd.</bibl>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d17">
<head>SECT. II.</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Of Double and Treble Rhymes.</hi>
</p>

<p>All words that are accented on the last save one, require the Rhyme to begin
at the Vowel of that Syllable, and to continue to the end of the word, and
this is what we call Double Rhyme; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Then all for Women, Painting, Rhyming, Drinking,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Besides ten Thousand freaks that dy'd in thinking.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Dryd.</bibl>

<p>
But it is convenient to take notice that the Ancient Poets have not always
observ'd this Rule, and took care only that the last Syllable of the words
should be alike in sound, without any regard to the Seat of the Accent. Thus
<hi rend="italic">Nation</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Affection, Tenderness</hi>
and <hi rend="italic">Hapless, Villany</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Gentry,
Follow</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Willow,</hi> and the like were allow'd as
Rhymes to each other, in the Days of <hi rend="italic">Chaucer, Spencer,</hi>
and the rest of the Ancients; but this is now become a fault in our Versification;
and these two Verses of <hi rend="italic">Cowley</hi> Rhyme not at all.
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">A clean and lively brown was</hi> Merab's
<hi rend="italic">Dye</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Such as the proudest Colours might envy.</hi></l></lg>

<p>
Nor these of <hi rend="italic">Dryden.</hi>
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Thus Air was void of light and Earth unstable,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And Waters dark Abyss unnavigable.</hi></l></lg>

<p>
Because we may not place an Accent on the last Syllable of <hi rend="italic">
Envy,</hi> nor on the last save one of <hi rend="italic">Unnavigable;</hi> which
nevertheless we must be oblig'd to do, if we make the first of them Rhyme to
<hi rend="italic">Dye,</hi> the last to <hi rend="italic">Unstable.</hi>
</p><p>
But we must take notice that in Burlesque Poetry, it is permitted to place an
Accent upon a Syllable that naturally has none; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">When Pulpit, Drum Ecclesiastick,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Was beat with fist instead of a stick.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Hudib.</bibl>

<pb n="22"/>

<p>
Where unless we pronounce the Particle A with a strong Accent upon it,
and make it sound like the Vowel A. in the last Syllable but one of
<hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastick;</hi> the Verse will lose all its Beauty
and Rhyme. But this is allowable in Burlesque Poetry only.
</p><p>
Observe that these double Rhymes may be Compos'd of two several words; provided
the Accent be upon the last Syllable of the first of them; as in these Verses of
<hi rend="italic">Cowley</hi>, speaking of Gold,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">A Curse on him who did refine it,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">A Curse on him who first did coin it.</hi></l></lg>

<p>
Or one of the Verses may end in an intire word, and the Rhyme to it be Compos'd of
several; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Tho' stor'd with Deletery Med'cines,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Which whosoever took is dead since.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Hudib.</bibl>

<p>
The Treble Rhyme is, when in words Accented upon the last save two we
begin the Rhyme at the Vowel of that Syllable, and continue it to the
end of the word. Thus <hi rend="italic">Charity</hi> and <hi rend="italic">
Parity</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Tenderness</hi> and <hi rend="italic">
Slenderness</hi>, &amp;c. are treble Rhymes; And there too, as well as
the double; may be composed of several words; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">There was an Ancient sage Philosopher,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">That had read</hi> Alexander Ross <hi rend="italic">
over</hi>.</l></lg>
<bibl>Hudib.</bibl>

<p>
The Treble Rhyme is very seldom us'd, and ought wholy to be excluded from
serious subjects; for it has a certain flatness, unworthy the gravity requir'd
in Heroick Verse. In which <hi rend="italic">Dryden</hi> was of opinion that
even the double Rhymes ought very cautiously to find place; and in all his
Translation of <hi rend="italic">Virgil</hi> he has, I think, made use of
none except only in such words as admit of a Contraction, and therefore cannot
properly be said to be double Rhymes; as <hi rend="italic">Giv'n</hi>,
<hi rend="italic">Driv'n</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Tow'r</hi>, <hi rend="italic">
Pow'r</hi>, and the like. And indeed, considering that their measure is different
from that of an Heroick Verse, which consists but of 10 Syllables, they ought not
to be too frequently us'd in Heroick Poems; but they are very graceful in the
Lyrick, to which, as well as to the Burlesque, those Rhymes more properly belong.
</p><pb n="23"/>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="3" id="d18">
<head>SECT. III.</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Some other Instructions concerning the Rhyme.</hi>
</p>

<p>
<hi rend="italic"></hi>The Consonants, that preceed the Vowels where the
Rhyme begins, must be different in sound, and not the same; for then the Rhyme
will be too perfect; as <hi rend="italic">Light, Delight</hi>; <hi rend="italic">
Vice, Advice,</hi> and the like; for tho' such Rhymes were allowable in the Days
of <hi rend="italic">Spencer</hi> and the other old Poets, they are not so now;
nor can there be any Musick in one single Note. <hi rend="italic">Cowley</hi>
himself owns, that they ought not to be employ'd except in Pindarick Odes, which
is a free sort of Poetry, and there too very sparingly, and not without a third
Rhyme to Answer to both; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">In Barren Age wild and unglorious lye,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And boast of past fertility,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">The poor Relief of present poverty.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowley.</bibl>

<p>
Where the words <hi rend="italic">Fertility</hi> and <hi rend="italic">
Poverty</hi> Rhyme very well to the last Word of the first Verse,
<hi rend="italic">Ly</hi> ; but cannot Rhyme to each other, because the
Consonants that preceed the last Vowel are the same, both in writing and
sound. But this is yet less allowable if the Accent be upon the Syllable
of the Rhyme; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Her Language melts Omnipotence, arrests</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">His hand, and thence the vengeful Lightning wrests.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Blac.</bibl>

<p>
From hence it follows that a word cannot Rhyme to it self, tho' the
signification be different; as <hi rend="italic">He Leaves</hi> to
<hi rend="italic">The Leaves,</hi> &amp;c.
</p><p>
Nor the words that differ both in Writing and Sence, if they have the same
sound, as <hi rend="italic">Maid</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Made, Prey</hi>
and <hi rend="italic">Pray</hi>, <hi rend="italic">to Bow</hi> and <hi
rend="italic">a Bough</hi>: as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">How Gawdy Fate may be in Presents sent</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And creep insensibly by touch or scent.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Oldh.</bibl>

<p>
Nor a Compound to its simple; as <hi rend="italic">Move</hi> to <hi
rend="italic">Remove</hi>, <hi rend="italic">taught</hi> to <hi
rend="italic">untaught,</hi> &amp;c.
</p><p>
Nor the Compounds of the same words to one another; as <hi rend="italic">
Disprove</hi> to <hi rend="italic">Approve</hi>, and the like. All which
proceeds from what I said before, because the Consonants chat preceed the
Vowel where the Rhyme begins, must not be the same in sound, but different.
</p>

<pb n="24"/>

<p>
We must take care not to place a word at the middle of the Verse, that
Rhymes to the last word of it; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">So young in show, as if he still should grow.</hi></l></lg>

<p>
But this fault is yet more inexcusable, if the second Verse Rhyme to the
middle and end of the first; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Knowledge he only sought, and so soon caught,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">As if for him Knowledge had rather sought.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowl.</bibl>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Here Passion sways; but there the Muse shall raise</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Eternal Monuments of louder Praise.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl>

<p>
Or both the middle and end of the second to the last word of the first; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Farewell, she cry'd, my Sister, thou dear Part,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Thou sweetest part of my divided Heart.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Dryd.</bibl>

</div2>
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="3" id="d19">
<head>CHAP. III.<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Of the several sorts of Poems, or Compositions in Verse.</hi>
</head>
<p>
All our Poems may be divided into two sorts; the first of those that are
Compos'd in Couplets; the second of those that are Compos'd in Stanzas
consisting of several Verses.
</p>

<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d20">
<head>SECT. I.</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Of the Poems compos'd in Couplets.</hi>
</p>

<p>
In the Poems Compos'd in Couplets, the Rhymes follow one another and end
at each Couplet, that is to say, the 2d Verse Rhymes to the 1st, the 4th to
the 3d, the 6th to the 5th, and in like manner to the end of the Poem. The
Verses employ'd in this sort of Poems, are either Verses of 10 Syllables; as,
</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">Oh! Could I flow like thee, and make thy Stream</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">My Great Example, as it is my Theme;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Tho' deep, yet clear; to' gentle, yet not dull:</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Strong, without Rage, without o'erflowing, full.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Denh.</bibl>

<pb n="25"/>

<p>Or of 8; as</p>

<lg type="stanza"><l>
<hi rend="italic">Anger in hasty Words or Blows</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">It self discharges on our Foes:</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And Sorrow too finds some Relief</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">In Tears that wait upon our Grief;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Thus every Passion, but fond Love,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Unto its own Redress does move, </hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl>

<p>Or of 7; as</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">Phillis, why should we delay</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Pleasures shorter than the day;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Could we, which we never can,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Stretch our Lives beyond their Span.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Beauty like a Shadow flies,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And our Youth before us dies,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Or would Youth and Beauty stay,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Love has Wings and will away, &amp;c.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl>

<p>
But the second Verse of the Couplet does not always contain a like
number of Syllables with the first; as
</p>

<lg type="stanza"><l>
<hi rend="italic">What shall I do to be for ever known,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And make the Age to come my own.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">I shall like Beasts and common People dye,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Unless you write my Elegy, &amp;c.</hi></l></lg>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d21">
<head>SECT. II.</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Of the Poems compos'd in Stanzas: And First, of the
Stanzas consisting of three and of four Verses.</hi>
</p>

<p>
In the Poems compos'd in Stanzas, each Stanza contains a certain
number of Verses compos'd for the most part of a different number of
Syllables: And a Poem that is in several Stanzas, we generally call
an Ode, and this is Lyrick Poetry.
</p><p>
But we must not forget to observe that our Ancient Poets frequently made use
of intermixt Rhyme in their Heroick Poems, which they dispos'd into Stanzas and
Cantos. Thus the <hi rend="italic">Troilus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Cressida
</hi>of<hi rend="italic"> Chaucer</hi> is compos'd in Stanzas consisting of 7
Verses;<hi rend="italic"></hi> the <hi rend="italic">Fairy Queen</hi> of<hi
rend="italic"> Spencer</hi> in Stanzas of 9, &amp;c. And this they took from the
Italians, whose Heroick Poems generally consist in Stanzas of 8. But this is now
wholly laid aside and <hi rend="italic">Davenant,</hi> who compos'd

<pb n="26"/>

his <hi rend="italic">Gondibert,</hi> in Stanzas of 4 Verses in Alternate Rhyme,
was the last that follow'd their Example of intermingling Rhymes in Heroick Poems.
</p><p>
The Stanzas employ'd in our Poetry cannot consist of less than three, and seldom
of more than 12 Verses, except in Pindarick Odes, where the Stanzas are different
from one another in number of Verses, as shall be shewn hereafter.
</p><p>
But to treat of all the different Stanzas that are employ'd, or may be admitted
in our Poetry, would be a labour no less tedious than useless, it being easie to
demonstrate that they may be vary'd almost to an Infinity, that would be different
from one another, either in the Number of the Verses of each Stanza, or in the Number
of the Syllables of each Verse, or lastly, in the various intermingling of the Rhyme.
I shall therefore confine my self to mention only such as are most frequently us'd by
the best of our Modern Poets. And first of the Stanzas consisting of three Verses.
</p><p>
In the Stanzas of three Verses, or Triplets, the Verses of each Stanza rhyme to one
another, and are either Herorick; as
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Nothing, thou Elder Brother ev'n to shade!</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Thou hadst a being e'er the World was made;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And, (well-fix'd) art alone of ending not afraid.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Roch.</bibl>

<p>
Or else they consist of 8 Syllables; as these of <hi
rend="italic">Waller,</hi> Of a fair Lady playing with a Snake.
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Strange that such Horrour and such Grace</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Should dwell together in one place,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">A Fury's Arm, an Angel's Face.</hi></l></lg>

<p>
In the Stanzas of 4 Verses the Rhyme may be intermixt in two different
manners: For either the 1st and 3d Verse may rhyme to each other, and by
consequence the 2d and 4th, and this is call'd Alternate Rhyme; or the 1st
and 4th may rhyme, and by consequence the 2d and 3d.
</p><p>
But there are some Poems in Stanzas of four Verses, where the Rhymes follow
one another, and the Verses differ in number of Syllables only; as in <hi rend="italic">
Cowley's</hi> Hymn to the Light, which begins thus:
</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">First born of</hi> Chaos!<hi rend="italic"> Who so
fair didst come</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">From the old</hi> Negro's<hi rend="italic"> darksome
Womb:</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Which when it saw the lovely Child,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">The melancholly Mass put on kind Looks and smil'd.</hi></l></lg>

<p>
But these Stanzas are generally in Alternate Rhymes, and

<pb n="27"/>

the Verses consist either of 10 Syllables, as
</p>

<lg type="stanza"><l>
<hi rend="italic">She ne'er saw Courts, but Courts could have undone</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">With untaught Looks, and an unpractis'd Heart:</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Her Nets the most prepar'd could never shun;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">For Nature spread them in the scorn of Art.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Dav.</bibl>

<p>Or of 8, as </p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">Had Echo with so sweet a Grace,</hi></l><l>
Narcissus <hi rend="italic">loud complaints return'd;</hi>
<hi rend="italic">Not for Reflection of his Face,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">But of his Voice the Boy had burn'd.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl>

<p>
Or of 10 and 8, that is to say, the 1st and 3d of 10; the 2d and 4th of 8; as
</p>

<lg type="stanza"><l>
<hi rend="italic">Love from Time's Wings has stol'n the Feathers sure,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">He has, and put them to his own:</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">For Hours of late as long as Days endure,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And very Minutes Hours are grown.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowl.</bibl>

<p>Or of 8 and 6 in the like manner; as </p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">Then ask not Bodies doom'd to dye</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">To what abode they go:</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Since Knowledge is but Sorrow's Spy,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">`Tis better not to know.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Dav.</bibl>

<p>Or of 7; as </p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">Not the silver Doves that fly,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Yoak'd in</hi> Cytherea's <hi rend="italic">Car;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Nor the Wings that lift so high,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And convey her Son so far.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Are so lovely sweet and fair,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Or do more ennoble Love;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Are so choicely match'd a pair,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Or with more consent do move.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl>

<p>
<hi rend="italic">Note,</hi> That it is absolutely necessary that both the
Construction and Sence should end with the Stanza, and not fall into the beginning of
the following one, as it does in the laft Example, which is a fault wholly to be
avoided.
</p></div2>

<div2 type="section" n="3" id="d22">
<head>SECT. III.</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Of the Stanzas of Six Verses.</hi>
</p>

<p>
The Stanzas of 6 Verses are generally only one of the before-mention'd
Quadrans or Stanzas of 4 Verses, with two Verses at the end that rhyme to
one another; as
</p>

<pb n="28"/>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">A Rural Judge dispos'd of Beautie's Prize,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">A simple Shepherd was prefer'd to</hi> Jove<hi rend="italic">;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Down to the Mountains from the Partial Skies</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Came</hi> Juno<hi rend="italic">,</hi> Pallas<hi rend="italic">,
and the Queen of Love,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">To plead for that which was so justly giv'n</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">To the bright Carlisle of the Courts of Heav'n.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl>

<p>
Where the 4 first Verses are only a Quadran, whose Verses consist of 10 Syllables in
Alternate Rhyme. The following Stanza in like manner is compos'd of a Quadran,
whose Verses consist of 8 Syllables, and to which 2, Verses that rhyme to one another
are added at the end, as
</p>

<lg type="stanza"><l>
<hi rend="italic">Hope waits upon the flowry Prime,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And Summer, tho' it be less gay,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Yet is not look'd on as a time</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Of Declination and Decay,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">For with a full Hand that does bring</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">All that was promis'd by the Spring.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl>

<p>
Sometimes the Quadran ends the Stanza; and the two Lines of the same Rhyme
begin it; as
</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">Here's to thee Dick, this whining Love despise:</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Pledge me my Friend, and drink till thou be'st wise.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">It sparkles brighter far than she;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">`Tis pure and right without Deceit;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And such no Woman e'er can be;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">No, they are all Sophisticate.</hi></l></lg>

<p>
Or as in these where the first and last Verses of the Stanza consist of 10
Syllables;
</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">When Chance or cruel Bus'ness parts us two,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">What do our Souls, I wonder do?</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">While steep does our dull Bodies tie,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Methinks at home they should not stay</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Content with Dreams, but boldly fly</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Abroad, and meet each other half the way.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowl.</bibl>

<p>
Or as in the following Stanza, where the 4th and 5th Verses rhyme to each
other, and the 3d and 6th.
</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">While what I write I do not see,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">I dare thus even to you write Poetry,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Ah foolish Muse! That dost so high aspire,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And knows't her Judgment well,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">How much it does thy Power excel;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Yet dar'st be read by thy just doom the fire.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowl.</bibl>

<p>
(<hi rend="italic">Written in Juice of Lemon.</hi>
</p><p>
But in some of these Stanzas the Rhymes follow one another; as
</p>

<pb n="29"/>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">I came, I saw, and was undone;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Lightning did through my Bones and Marrow run</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">A pointed Pain peirc'd deep my Heart;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">A swift cold trembling seiz'd on ev'ry part.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">My Head turn'd round, nor could it bear</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">The Poison that was enter'd there.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowl.</bibl>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="4" id="d23">
<head>SECT. IV.</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Of the Stanzas of 8 Verses.</hi>
</p>

<p>
I have already said that the Italians compose their Heroick Poems in Stanzas of 8
Verses, where the Rhyme is dispos'd as follows; the 1st 3d and 5th Verses rhyme to
each other, and the 2d 4th and 6th, the two last always rhyme to one another. Now our
Translators of their Heroick Poems have observed the same Stanza and Disposition of
Rhyme; of which take the following Example from <hi rend="italic">Fairfax's
</hi>Translation of <hi rend="italic">Tasso's</hi> Goffredo, <hi
rend="italic">Cant. </hi>1. Stan. 3d.
</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">Thither thou know'st the world is best inclin'd,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Where luring</hi> Parnass <hi rend="italic">most his Beams imparts;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And Truth convey'd in Verse of gentlest kind,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">To read sometimes, will move the dullest Hearts.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">So we, if Children Young diseas'd we find,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Anoint with Sweets the Vessels foremost parts,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">To make them taste the Potions sharp we give;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">They drink deceiv'd and so deceiv'd they live.</hi></l></lg>

<p>
But our Poets seldom imploy this Stanza in Compositions of their own; where
the following ones of 8 Verses are most frequent.
</p>

<lg type="stanza"><l>
<hi rend="italic">Some others may with safety tell</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">The mod'rate Flames which in them dwell;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And either find some Med'cine there,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Or cure themselves ev'n by despair.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">My Love's so great, that it might prove</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Dang'rous to tell her that I love.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">So tender is my Wound, it cannot bear</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Any Salute, tho' of the kindest Air.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowl.</bibl>

<p>
Where the Rhymes follow one another, and the Six first Verses consist of 8
Syllables each, the two last of 10.
</p><p>
We have another sort of Stanza of 8 Verses, where the 4th rhymes to the 1st, the 3d to
the 2d, and the four last

<pb n="30"/>

are two Couplets; and where the 1st, 4th, 6th and 8th, are of 10 Syllables each, the 4
others but of 8; as
</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">I've often wish'd to love: What shall I do?</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Me still the cruel Boy does spare;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And I a double task must bear,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">First to wooe him, and then a Mistress too.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Come at last, and strike for shame</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">If thou art any thing besides a Name;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">I'll think thee else no God to be,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">But Poets, rather, Gods, who first created thee.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowley.</bibl>

<p>
Another when the 2 first and 2 last Verses consist of 10 Syllables each, and Rhyme
to one another, the 4 other but of 8 in alternate Rhyme.
</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">Tho' you be absent hence, I needs must say,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">The Trees as beauteous are and Flow'rs as gay,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">As ever they were wont to be:</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Nay the Birds rural Musick too</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Is as melodious and free,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">As if they sung to pleasure you.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">I saw a Rose bud ope this Morn; I'll swear</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">The Blushing Morning open'd not more fair.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowley.</bibl>

<p>
Another where the 4 first Verses are two Couplets, the 4 last in
alternate Rhyme; as in <hi rend="italic">Cowley's</hi> Ode, Of a Lady
that made Posies for Rings.
</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">I little thought the time would ever be</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">That I should wit in dwarfish Posies see.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">As all words in few Letters live,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Thou to few words all sence dost give.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">`Twas Nature taught you this rare Art,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">In such a little much to shew;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Who all the Good she did impart</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">To Womankind Epitomiz'd in you.</hi></l></lg>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="5" id="d24">
<head>SECT. V.</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Of the Stanzas of 10 and 12 Verses.</hi>
</p>

<p>
The Stanzas of 10 and it Verses are seldom employ'd in our Poetry,
it being very difficult to confine our selves to a certain Disposition
of Rhyme, and measure of Verse for so many lines together; for which
Reason those of 4, 6, and 8 Verses are the most frequent. However we
sometimes find

<pb n="31"/>

some of 10 and 12; as in <hi rend="italic">Cowley's</hi> Ode which he
calls, <hi rend="italic">Verses</hi> <hi rend="italic">lost upon a
Wager</hi>, where the Rhymes follow one another, but the Verses differ
in Number of Syllables.
</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">As soon hereafter will I lay</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">`Gainst what an Oracle shall say.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Fool that I was to venture to deny</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">A Tongue so us'd to Victory.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">A Tongue so blest by nature and by Art,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">That never yet it spoke, but gain'd a heart.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Tho' what you said had not been true</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">If spoke by any else but you:</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Your Speech will govern Destiny,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And Fate will change rather than you should ly.</hi></l></lg>

<p>
The same Poet furnishes us with an Example of a Stanza of 12 Verses in
the Ode he calls <hi rend="italic">the Prophet</hi>, where the Rhymes are
observ'd in the same manner as in the former  Example:
</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">Teach me to Love! Go teach thy self more wit:</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">I chief Professor am of it.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Teach Craft to</hi> Scots<hi rend="italic">, and thrift to
</hi>Jews<hi rend="italic">,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Teach boldness to the</hi> Stews<hi rend="italic">.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">In Tyrants Courts teach supple flattery,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Teach</hi> Jesuits <hi rend="italic">that have Travell'd far to
ly.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Teach Fire to burn, and Winds to blow,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Teach restless Fountains how to flow.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Teach the dull Earth fixt to abide,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Teach Womankind Inconstancy and Pride.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">See if your diligence there will useful prove;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">But, prithee, teach not me to love.</hi></l></lg>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="6" id="d25">
<head>SECT. VI.</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Of the Stanzas that consist of an odd Number of Verses.</hi>
</p>

<p>
We have also Stanzas that consist of an odd number of Verses, as of 5, 7, 9,
and 11, in all which it of necessity follows that three Verses of the Stanza
must rhyme to one another, or that one of them must be a blank Verse.
</p><p>
In the Stanzas of 5 Verses, the 1st and 3d may rhyme, and the 2d and two
last; as,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Sees not my Love how Time resumes</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">The Glory which he lent these Flow'rs:</hi></l></lg>

<pb n="31"/>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Tho' none should taste of their Perfumes,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Yet they must live but some few Hours:</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Time, what we forbear, devours.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl>

<p>
Which is only a Stanza of 4 Verses in Alternate Rhyme, to which a 5th
Verse is added that rhymes to the 2d and 4th.
</p><p>
See also an Instance of a Stanza of 5 Verses where the Rhymes are intermix'd
in the same manner as the former, but the 1st and 3d Verses are compos'd but
of 4 Syllables each
</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">Go lovely Rose,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Tell her that wastes her time and me,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">That now she knows,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">When I resemble her to thee,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">How sweet and fair she seems to be.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Wall.</bibl>

<p>
In the following Example the two first Verses rhyme, and the three last.
</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">`Tis well, `tis well with them, said I,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Whose short-liv'd passions with themselves can dy.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">For none can be unhappy, who</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">`Midst all his ills a Time does know,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Tho' ne'er so long, when he shall not be so.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowl.</bibl>

<p>
In this Stanza, the 2 first and the last, and the 3d and 4th, Rhyme to
one another.
</p>

<lg type="stanza"><l>
<hi rend="italic">It is enough, enough of time and pain</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Hast thou consum'd in vain:</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Leave, wretched</hi> Cowley, <hi rend="italic">leave,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Thy self with shadows to deceive.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Think that already lost which thou must never gain.</hi></l></lg>

<p>
The Stanzas of 7 Verses are frequent enough in our Poetry, especially among the
Ancients, who compos'd many of their Poems in this sort of Stanza: See an Example
of one of them taken from <hi rend="italic">Spencer</hi> in <hi rend="italic">the
Ruins of time,</hi> where the 1st and 3d Verse rhyme to One another, the 2d, 4th,
and 5th, and the two last.
</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">But Fame with golden Wings aloft doth fly</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Above the reach of ruinous decay,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And with brave Plumes does beat the Azure Sky;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Admir'd of baseborn Men from far away;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Then whoso will with virtuous Deeds essay</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">To mount to Heav'n, on</hi> Pegasus <hi rend="italic">must
ride,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And in sweet Poets Verse be glorify'd.</hi></l></lg>

<pb n="33"/>

<p>
I have the rather chosen to take notice of this Stanza, because that Poet
and <hi rend="italic">Chaucer</hi> have made use of it in many bf their
Poems, but have not been follow'd by any of the Moderns; whose Stanzas of 7
Verses are commonly compos'd as follows.
</p><p>
Either the four first Verses are a Quadran in Alternate Rhymes, and the
three last rhyme to one another, as
</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">Now by my Love, the greatest Oath that is,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">None loves you half so well as I,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">I do not ask your love for this,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">But for Heaven's sake believe me or I dye.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">No Servant e'er but did deserve</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">His Master should believe that he did serve;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And I'll ask no more Wages tho' I starve.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowl.</bibl>

<p>
Or the four first are two Couplets, and the three last a Triplet; as
</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">Indeed I must confess,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">When Souls mix `tis a Happiness,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">But not compleat till Bodies too combine,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And closely as our Minds together joyn.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">But half of Heav'n the Souls in Glory taste;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Till by Love in Heav'n at last,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Their Bodies too are plac'd.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Now by my Love, the greatest Oath that is,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">None loves you half so well as I,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">I do not ask your love for this,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">But for Heaven's sake believe me or I dye.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowl.</bibl>

<p>
Or, on the contrary, the three first may rhyme, and the four last be in Rhymes
that follow one another; as
</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">From Hate, Fear, Hope, Anger, and Envy free,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And all the Passions else that be,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">In vain I boast of Liberty:</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">In vain this State a Freedom call,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Since I have Love, and Love is all.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Sot that I am! who think it fit to brag</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">That I have no Disease besides the Plague.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowl.</bibl>

<p>
Or the 1st may rhyme to the two last, the 2d to the 5th, and the 3d
and 4th to one another; as
</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">In vain thou Drowsie God I thee invoke,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">For thou who dost from Fumes arise,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Thou who Man's Soul dost overshade</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">With a thick Cloud, by Vapours made,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Canst have no pow'r to shut his Eyes,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Or passage of his Spirits to choak,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Whose Flame's so pure, that it sends up no smoke.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowl.</bibl>

<pb n="34"/>

<p>
Or lastly, the four first and two last may be in following Rhyme, and
the 5th a blank Verse; as
</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">Thou rob'st my days of Bus'ness and Delights,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Of Sleep thou rob'st my Nights:</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Ah lovely Thief! what wilt thou do?</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">What, rob me of Heav'n too!</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Thou ev'n my Pray'rs dost from me steal,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And I with wild Idolatry</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Begin to God, and end them all in thee.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowl.</bibl>

<p>
The Stanzas of 9 and of 11 Syllables are not so frequent as those of 5 and of 7, <hi
rend="italic">Spencer</hi> has compos'd his <hi rend="italic">Fairy Queen</hi>
in Stanzas of 9 Verses, where the 1st rhymes to the 3d, the 2d to the 4th, 5th, and 7th;
and the 6th to the two last. But this Stanza is very difficult to maintain, and the
unlucky choice of it reduc'd him often to the necessity of making use of many
exploded Words; nor has he, I think, been follow'd in it by any of the Moderns;
whose 6 first Verses of the Stanzas that consist of 9, are generally in Rhymes that
follow one another, and the three last a Triplet; as
</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">Beauty, thou wild fantastick Ape,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Who dost in ev'ry Country change thy Shape:</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Here Black, there Brown, here Tawny, and there White,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Thou Flatt'rer which comply'st with ev'ry sight.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Thou</hi> Babel<hi rend="italic"> which confound'st the Eye</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">With unintelligible Variety:</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Who hast no certain What nor Where,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">But vary'st still, and dost thy self declare</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Inconstant, as thy She-Professors are.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowl.</bibl>

<p>
In the following Example the like Rhyme is observ'd, but the Verses differ in
Measure from the former.
</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">Beneath this gloomy Shade,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">By Nature only for my Sorrows made,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">I'll spend this Voice in Cries;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">In Tears I'll waste these Eyes,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">By Love so vainly fed,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">So Lust of old the Deluge punished.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Ah wretched youth! said I;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Ah wretched Youth! twice did I sadly cry;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Ah wretched Youth! the Fields and Floods reply.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowl.</bibl>

<p>
The Stanzas consisting of 11 Verses are yet less frequent than those
of 9, and have nothing particular to be observ'd

<pb n="35"/>

in them. See an Example of one of them, where the 8 first Verses are
in following Rhyme, the three last rhyme to one another, and where
the 4th, 7th, and the last Verse are of 10 Syllables each, the others of 8.
</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">No, to what purpose should I speak?</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">No wretched Heart, swell till you break:</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">She cannot love me if she would;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And, to say Truth, `twere pity that she should.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">No, to the Grave thy Sorrows bear,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">As silent as they will be there:</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Since that lov'd Hand this mortal Wound does give,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">So handsomly the thing contrive,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">That she may guitless of it live:</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">So perish, that her killing thee</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">May a chance-medley, and no Murther be.</hi></l></lg>
<bibl>Cowl.</bibl>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="7" id="d26">
<head>SECT. VII.</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Of Pindarick Odes, and Poems in Blank Verse.</hi>
</p>

<p>
The Stanzas of Pindarick Odes are neither confin'd to a certain number
of Verses, nor the Verses to a certain number of Syllables, nor the Rhyme
to a certain Distance. Some Stanzas contain 50 Verses or more, others not
above 10: Some Verses 14, nay 16 Syllables, others not above 4: Sometimes
the Rhymes follow one another for several Couplets together, sometimes they
are remov'd 6 Verses from each other; and all this in the same Stanza.
<hi rend="italic">Cowley</hi> was the first who introduc'd this sort of
Poetry into our Language, nor can the Nature of it be better describ'd than
he himself has done it, in one of the Stanzas of the Ode he has written upon
<hi rend="italic">Liberty,</hi> which I will transcribe, not as an Example,
for none can properly be said to be given, where no Rule can be prescribed,
but to give an Idea of the Nature of this sort of Poetry.
</p>

<lg type="stanza"><l>
<hi rend="italic">If Life should a well-order'd Poem be,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">In which he only hits the White,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Who joyns true Profit with the best Delight,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">The more Heroick Strain let others take,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Mine the Pindarick way I'll make,</hi></l>

<pb n="36"/>

<l><hi rend="italic">The Matter shall be Grave, the Numbers loose and free;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">It shall not keep one setled pace of Time,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">In the same Tune it shall not always chime,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Nor shall each day just to his Neighbour rhyme.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">A thousand Liberties it shall dispence,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And yet shall manage all without Offence,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Or to the sweetness of the Sound, or greatness of the Sence,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Nor shall it never from one Subject start,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Nor seek Transitions to depart:</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Nor its set way oe'r Stiles and Bridges make,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Nor thro' Lanes a Compass take,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">As if it fear'd some Trespass to commit,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">When the wide Air's a Road for it.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">So the Imperial Eagle does not stay</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Till the whole Carcass he devour,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">That's fallen into its Pow'r,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">As if his generous Hunger understood,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">That he can never want plenty of Food,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">He only sucks the tastful Blood,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And to fresh Game flies chearfully away;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">To Kites and meaner Birds he leaves the mangled Prey.</hi></l></lg>

<p>
This sort of Poetry is employ'd in all manner of Subjects; in Pleasant,
in Grave, in Amorous, in Heroick, in Philosophical, in Mortal and in Divine.
</p><p>
Blank Verse is where the Measure is exactly kept without Rhyme; and it was
<hi rend="italic">Shakespear,</hi> who to avoid the troublesome constraint
of Rhyme, first invented it; our Poets since him have made use of it in many
of their Tragedies and Comedies; but the most celebrated Poem in this kind of
Verse is the Paradise Lost of <hi rend="italic">Milton;</hi> from the 5th
Book of which I have taken the following Lines for an example of Blank Verse.
</p>

<lg type="stanza">
<l><hi rend="italic">These are thy glorious Works, Parent of Good!</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Almighty! thine this Universal Frame,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Thus wondrous fair! thy self how wondrous then!</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Speak you, who best can tell, ye Sons of Light,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Angels! for you behold him, and with Songs,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And Choral Symphonies, Day without Night</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Circle his Throne rejoycing, you in Heaven.</hi></l>

<pb n="37"/>

<l><hi rend="italic">On Earth, joyn all ye Creatures, to extol</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Him first, him last, him midst, and without end.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Fairest of Stars! last in the Train of Night;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">If better thou belong'st not to the Dawn,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Sure Pledge of day that crown'st the smiling Morn,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">With thy bright Circlet, raise him in thy Sphere,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">While Day arises, that sweet Hour of Prime.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Thou Sun! of this Great World; both Eye and Soul,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Acknowledge him thy Greater, sound his Praise</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">In thy Eternal Course, both when thou climb'st</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And when high Noon hast gain'd, and when thou fall'st.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Moon! that now meet'st the Orient Sun, now fly'st</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">With the fixt Stars, fixt in their Orb that flies,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And ye five other wand'ring Fires! that move</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">In Mystick Dance, not without Song, resound</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">His Praise, who out of Darkness call'd up Light.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Air! and ye Elements! the eldest Birth</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Of Nature's Womb, that in Quaternion run</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Perpetual Circle, multiform; and mix</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">And nourish all things, let your ceaseless Change</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Vary to our Great Maker still new Praise.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Ye Mists and Exhalations! that now rise</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">From Hill or steaming Lake, Dusky or Grey,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Till the Sun paint your fleecy Skirts with Gold,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">In honour to the World's great Author rise,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Whether to deck with Clouds th' uncolour'd Sky,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Or wet the thirsty Earth with falling Showers,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Rising or falling, still advance his Praise.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">His Praise, ye Winds! that from four Quarters blow,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Breathe soft or loud; and wave your Tops, ye Pines!</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">With ev'ry Plant, in sign of Worship, wave.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Fountains! and ye that warble as you flow</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Melodious Murmurs, warbling tune his Praise.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Joyn Voices all ye living Souls, ye Birds!</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">That singing, up to Heaven's high Gate ascend,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Bear on your Wings, and in your Notes his Praise.</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Ye that in Waters glide! and ye that walk,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">The Earth! and stately Tread, or lowly Creep;</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Witness if I be silent, Ev'n or Morn,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">To Hill or Valley, Fountain or fresh Shade,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Made Vocal by my Song, and taught his Praise.</hi></l></lg>

<pb n="38"/>

<p>
Thus I have given a short Account of all the sorts of Poems, that are
most us'd in our Language, The Acrosticks, Emblems, Anagrams, &amp;c.
deserve not to be mention'd, and we may say of them what an Ancient Poet
said long ago,
</p>

<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Stultum est difficiles habere Nugas,</hi></l><l>
<hi rend="italic">Et stultus Labor est ineptiarum.</hi></l></lg>

<trailer>FINIS.</trailer>

</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
