<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CahYoun"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="CahYoun">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Younger Russian Writers</title>
<title type="sort">younger russian writers</title>
<author>Cahan, Abraham</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">29</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CahYoun</idno>
<date value="1998">1998</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1998 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475779</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Younger Russian Writers</title>
<title level="j">The Forum, Vol. XXVIII (Sept. 1899)</title>
<title type="sort">younger russian writers</title>
<author>A. Cahan</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 119-128</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Forum Publishing Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVA Library call number AP2 .F8 v. 28 1899-1900</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1998-05">May, 1998</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Carol Osborne, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI tags and header</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="article" id="d3"> <pb n="119"/>
<head>THE YOUNGER RUSSIAN WRITERS.</head>

<p>RUSSIAN critics never cease lamenting the dearth of good
literature.  Turgeneff, Dostoyevsky, Pisemsky, Goncharoff, and
Pomialovsky are dead; Tolstoy, the only survivor of the great
constellation of the sixties and seventies, is a very old man and has
"sworn off;" while the younger generation of novelists has so far failed to
produce a single work of lasting value.  The productions of the masters
were inspired by the noble enthusiasms of their time: they were the
&aelig;sthetic offspring of the abolitionist movement and of the
renaissance which followed the emancipation of the serfs.  "Does the
poverty of our literature of to-day denote a lack of ideals?" ask the critics.
</p><p>This literary famine, however, is limited to the novel; for the list of
short story-tellers in Russia is considerable in length, and includes
several men of uncommon power, some of whom deserve a place in the
foremost ranks of modern authors.  Of these younger Russian writers
Vladimir Korolenko is perhaps, the only one
with whom English-speaking readers are more or less
familiar; Chekhoff, Potapenko, Gorki,
and Veresayeff being almost unknown in Anglo-Saxon countries.
</p><p>All these are realists.  Indeed, no other species of fiction would be
considered literature in Russia, where the story of adventure and plot is
looked upon as the &aelig;sthetic diet of children, and where "decadent"
influences have never been able to obtain even a temporary footing.
Lifelikeness clothed in the simplest forms of expression, and artistic
sincerity reflecting the self-criticisms and the melancholy moods of the
Russian people &mdash; which the critics have taught the public to exact from
its story-writers since Pushkin &mdash; are still the <hi rend="italic">sine qua non</hi> of
literature.</p>

<q>"One thing is immortal in art as well as in life, and that is
<hi rend="italic">truth</hi>," reads a recent testimonial addressed to Modest Ivanovitch
Pisareff, the St. Petersburg actor.  "The love of truth is the hall-mark of
real talent.  You, Modest Ivanovitch, are truly Russian in your art.  The
whole character of our nation, with all our merits and faults, rises lifelike
in your artistic interpretation.  The stormy passions of the Russian's soul,
his reckless pluck and abandon, his self-lashings and his sadness &mdash; the
characteristic sadness of the Russian people &mdash; all this has found in you a
fruitful and talented impersonator.

   <pb n="120"/>

You are one of those to whom the truth is dearer than
applause.  Guard it, then, from all that is insincere and garish."

</q><p>The testimonial was signed by some of the leading Russian writers
of to-day; and the note which rings through it is the keynote of the
Russian short story as well as of the Russian drama.
</p><p>The list of living authors, omitting the name of Count Tolstoy, is
headed by Vladimir Galaktionovitch Korolenko and Anton Pavlovitch
Chekhoff; and the relative standing of these two men, better than
anything else, perhaps, illustrates the general literary situation of their
country.  Korolenko is popular for his views on the social question;
Chekhoff, in spite of his having none.
</p><p>The peculiar conditions under which Russian literature has grown
up have brought about a close intimacy between the political ideals of the
cultured classes, on the one hand, and their fiction, on the other.
Silenced by the censor, the reformer is forced to call upon the novel to
convey his message.  This is the characteristic feature of Russian letters.
It involves a point of view which countries otherwise circumstanced may
find it difficult to appreciate, and that accounts for the unusual
seriousness with which the educated Russian takes his fiction.
</p><p>No nation has a theory of art so clearly defined, nor one so firmly
imbedded in the traditions of the intelligent classes, as is the theory
which forms the underlying principle of Russian criticism; and one of the
essential points of this theory is, that a work of art must also be a work of
education.  "Art for art's sake" is out of the question in a country where
the poem must take the place of the editorial, and where the story-teller,
who does not make his fiction a criticism of life, is looked upon as
something like a public officer who betrays his trust.
</p><p>A literary creed such as this would seem to be fatal to art, and the
fiction based upon it doomed to degenerate into that species of
sermon-novel which is a bad sermon and a worse novel.  Yet, so far as Russia is
concerned, the curse has turned out to be a blessing.  Sermonizing is just
what the censor will not allow; so the novelist must try to make his
pictures talk, to let life expose its own wounds.  For, like those well-bred
ladies of whom Thackeray tells us that they did not mind looking at the
trousers of hundreds of men, though they would have been shocked to
hear the word uttered, the censor, as a rule, does not prevent a subject of
the Czar from painting a spade, but he will not let him call it by its name.
</p><p>To make a story such a vehicle of expression two things are
necessary.  It must be a faithful transcript of life, and it must be a work of

   <pb n="121"/>

art; that is, not a dead "protocol" of events, nor yet a series of re-touched
photographs, but a picture vivified by the breath of genius and carrying
the illusion of pulsating reality.  A "purpose novel," where the sails of the
narrative are trimmed to suit the wind which blows in the direction of the
author's preconceived moral, is in Russia in far worse odor than it is here.
Indeed, this sort of fiction usually defeats its own "purpose;" for it is
prevented, by its artificiality, and made-to-order effect, from directing
attention to the phase of life in question, so that, instead of exclaiming,
"How true!" the reader exclaims, "Oh, it's only a story!"

</p><q>"A work of art," says Dobroluboff, the great critic of the sixties &mdash;
those palmy days of the Russian novel &mdash; "may be the exponent of an
idea, not because the author conceives this idea upon addressing himself
to his task, but because he has been struck by those facts of life from
which the idea follows as a natural inference. . .  The office of literature
is one of propaganda, and its value depends on what and how it
propagates. . .  Thinking, as we do, that to educate is the chief function of
literature, we require of it one thing, without which it can have no worth
whatever, and that is truth."

</q><p>This is the sum and substance of the literary doctrine which holds
sway over the great Northern Empire.  Like Moli&egrave;re's "Le
Bourgeois Gentilhomme," who was agreeably surprised to discover that
what he had spoken all his life was prose, Russia had been writing
realism long before she was acquainted with the term.  While in France,
for example, this school of fiction made its appearance in the natural
course of literary evolution, in Russia it was forced upon the enlightened
classes by the political conditions of their country.
</p><p>In the above sense Turgeneff was a propagandist.  His every novel
was written with a purpose; and yet they are anything but "novels with a
purpose," as the term is used in American and English criticism.
Turgeneff's works are the artistic incarnation of social ideas; so are
Pisemsky's, Tolstoy's, Dostoyevsky's, Ostrovsky's; and so are the stories
and sketches of Vladimir Korolenko.
</p><p>Korolenko is of an affectionate, self-sacrificing nature.  He thinks
the present order of things in his country unjust, and his heart goes out to
every victim of it.  He has suffered for the sympathies which form the
groundwork of his art; and the public and the critics love him as much
for his sacrifices as for his talent.  In short, Korolenko is a radical; and
the "facts of life which strike him" most keenly, and which he portrays in
his works, are such as, according to the critics, contain his advanced
views.  Not so Chekhoff, who is neither a radical nor a conservative, but
a man without convictions, who writes for no

   <pb n="122"/>

other "purpose" than the pleasure which he takes in his work.  As a
result, the applause which his genius received in the early days of his
career was half-hearted and accompanied by howls of disapproval.
</p><p>He made his bow to the public in the latter part of the eighties as a
writer of short sketches for newspapers; and he had not been known a
year, before it became evident that a great, new star had appeared on the
literary horizon of Russia.  But then he was a man without social ideas;
so the critics took a tone with him which made it appear as if they
begrudged him his powers and challenged his title to them.  That he has
overcome all the obstacles in his way to fame, and has been universally
recognized as the greatest master of the Russian short story and the most
powerful living writer in his country after Tolstoy, is one of the proofs of
the magnitude of his genius.
</p><p>Speaking of Chekhoff's earlier sketches, Skabichevsky, in his
"History of Recent Russian Literature," remarks that they
</p><q>
"reveal a vigorous talent and bristle with art and humor, but suffer from
one vital shortcoming, and that is their lack of a unifying idea.  The
author abandons himself to fleeting impressions which he hastens to
convey within the space of some two hundred newspaper lines.  The
upshot of it is that next to a heart-wringing life-drama he will offer you a
series of vaudeville scenes obviously written for the sole purpose of
making his readers laugh.  His longer stories, as, for example, 'The
Steppe' and 'Flames,' are characterized by the same kaleidoscopic quality
and by the absence of any central idea."

</q><p>Since 1892, when the above passage was written, Chekhoff has
taken himself more seriously.  His "Ward No. 6," where a country
physician &mdash; a lonely thinker and passionate reader, misunderstood by his
neighbors &mdash; is locked up as a madman by his rival physician; "The Black
Friar," which portrays the picturesque hallucinations of an overworked
professor and his misery upon recovering from his blissful megalomania;
"The Butterfly," which is the quiet tragedy of a good-natured man of
science married to an unsuccessful painter, who, unable to appreciate her
husband's gifts and the importance of his work, is abandoned to the
recklessness of Bohemian life till she violates her plighted troth; "The
Kiss," which a shy bachelor received in a dark room from a charming
woman, who mistook him for her lover, and the tragic-comic effect it had
upon his psychology; "The Peasants," where the grim truth of village life
in Russia is laid bare &mdash; these and many other short stories and sketches
are irresistible works of art, strong, deep, true, and beautiful.  But they,
too, are devoid of "underlying ideas;" and so, while the critics have come
to agree that the appearance of a new story by Chekhoff is an important
event in the

   <pb n="123"/>

literary history of Russia, they still frown upon him as a kind of political
heathen.
</p><p>Nicolai Constantinovitch Michailovsky, the leading critical
authority of the present generation, who is one of the irreconcilable
literary enemies of the younger master, points to the following passage in
"A Dull Story," by Chekhoff, as true of the author himself.

</p><q>"In all my ideas and feelings of men and things," says the hero of
the narrative, "there is a lack of that unifying something which might link
them into an organic whole.  Each sensation and each thought lives in me
by itself, and all my reasonings upon science, literature, the drama, as
well as all the images in my mind, are detached and independent of one
another; so that the most ingenious analyst would fail to discover in them
that which is called 'unifying idea' or 'the God in the living man.'  Now,
where this is lacking all real interest in life is lacking."

</q><p>"Chekhoff has talent and the power of observation," declares
Michailovsky, "but he lacks 'that which is called unifying idea or the God
in the living man.'  This is the key to the riddle why we all, who respect
his gifts, are firmly convinced that he will never develop them to the full
extent of their potential vigor."
</p><p>The hero of "A Dull Story" and his author are representatives of a
type which is quite common in Russia and Poland.  Turgeneff has
portrayed several varieties of this <hi rend="italic">Hamlet</hi> of our times in his
stories; and Sienkewitcz has made him the subject of his best
psychological novel, "Without Dogma."  As to Chekhoff, his "Dull
Story" is not the only production in which his leading character is a man
without a dogma.  Several of his other tales have this type for their
central figures.  The rest treat of other types; each story "living by itself,"
and all of them reflecting the state of mind which is characteristic of their
time.
</p><p>Another critic who finds fault with Chekhoff's social views
observes apropos his "Peasants:"

</p><q>"But Chekhoff becomes a really remarkable master when, casting
all ideas to the winds and obeying his artistic instincts alone, he sets out
to paint life in his own objective and simple way.  It is a long time since
Russian literature congratulated itself upon the appearance of a piece of
art like 'The Peasants.'"

</q><p>Verisimilitude, then, is a first consideration; and no amount of
cleverness and fine writing can atone for the lack of it.  To win the
attention of the educated Russian, it is absolutely necessary that the
author should have the gift of making things seem real.  Chekhoff
possesses this gift in a marvellous degree.  One of the striking features of
his stories is their absolute naturalness.  Korolenko, Potapenko,

   <pb n="124"/>

Gorki, and a score of lesser lights are endowed with a sense of character
and can draw a lifelike picture; but Chekhoff, of all Russian writers of
the younger generation, seems to tell a true story.  It is impossible to read
half a dozen sentences in any of his tales without beginning to feel that
all was only spirited gossip about people with whom author and reader
are personally acquainted.  Chekhoff seems to be too keenly interested in
these people, and too anxious to tell you about them, to indulge in a
prettily turned phrase, a jest, or a piece of rhetoric.  Indeed, his works
teem with irresistible humor; his style is a model of grace; a few simple
words sketch off the character so that it lives and moves before the
reader; and, above all, almost every sentence exposes to view some
interesting nook of the human soul.  But all these results are achieved in
a most casual way.  The author enjoys his gossip too intensely to be
aware of his own cleverness.
</p><p>The stories mentioned, except "The Peasants," have been selected,
because they belong to those of Chekhoff's productions in which
something happens, so that the "point" or the simple little plot can be
presented in a nutshell.  The typical Chekhoff story, however, the one
which shows his genius at its best, is so absolutely storyless that there is
not enough even to fill a nutshell.  From five to ten thousand words are
bestowed upon the most trivial bit of every-day life.  But then it is life
itself, not a mere <hi rend="italic">r&eacute;chauff&eacute;</hi> of it; and the plain,
hum-drum people and things, to whom nothing out of the ordinary
happens, turn out to be thrillingly interesting.
</p><p>The great point of Chekhoff's genius is his wonderful artistic
memory for the caprices and fleeting trifles of reality &mdash; for the wanton
dissimilarities as well as for the similarities of life.  Almost everything
the author says sets the reader wondering how it ever occurred to him to
mention such a thing at all.  It seems to have so little in common with
what writers, good or bad, usually put in their descriptions or dialogues.
It is one of those evanescent flinders of life which one can neither
remember nor invent, and which are as fresh and unexpected, in every
instance, as they are characteristic of the period and place to which they
relate.  His stories are full of these little surprises, and the illusion is
entrancingly complete.  Tolstoy is the only writer who possesses this
quality in a higher degree for psychical analysis; but even he yields first
place to Chekhoff in the description of external phenomena.
</p><p>It is ordinary, commonplace conditions, too, which have furnished
Korolenko, the humane prose-poet of Russian literature of to-day,

   <pb n="125"/>

with some of his most fascinating creations; but, like Gorki, he
sometimes departs from this realism <hi rend="italic">sans phrases</hi> to write a
species of fairy tales or fables.  These, however, can hardly be called
romance in the sense in which the term is applied to the novels of
Crockett, Weyman, or Anthony Hope; for while the English romancer
will make it his business to put ordinary mortals through experiences that
are anything but ordinary, the fantasies referred to deal with actualities
under the guise of the supernatural, in common mortals masked as
fairies, devils, or angels.  Korolenko's "Judgment Day," which is a satire
upon the government's discriminative policy regarding the Jews, is,
perhaps, the best example of this class of realistic poetry.  The devil of
the story is a pretty human sort of devil, just as Makar's "Dream" of his
experiences after death is quite a wakeful vision of throbbing earthly life.
</p><p>Korolenko's natural bent seems to be in the direction of the
mysterious and the weird.  He is indisputably the greatest master of
Russian composition since Turgeneff and Goncharoff.  His style is rich in
color and exquisitely finished; but instead of the soft, enravishing
splendor of Turgeneff's diction, it has a lethargic, uncanny glow which
pleases but does not move.  Were he an Englishman his art would,
perhaps, have developed some of the qualities of Stevenson and Du
Maurier.  As it is, he often seeks for the quaint and the bizarre in real life;
now penetrating the depths of a "Rustling Forest" for a story of old
serfdom days; now descending into the subterranean refuge of beggars to
study the feelings of a boy "In Bad Company;" now ascending to the bell-tower
of a village church where a superannuated, life-long "Bell-ringer"
gasps his last amid the reverberations of his own chimes.
</p><p>Korolenko is best known to English readers as the author of "The
Blind Musician," which it is customary to call his masterpiece.  This is
scarcely fair to the gifted writer; for, with all its high merits, this story is
not altogether free from a certain premeditated effect which is absent
from his other works, notably, "In Bad Company."  This tale treats of life
among the drink-crazed outcasts of a southern town, and of the touching
friendship between the young son of the local judge and the sickly little
daughter of one of the social waifs.  Abandoned to his gnawing grief
over the loss of his wife, the judge neglects his motherless boy; letting
him roam around the streets, make excursions to the vaults of the
abandoned castle, and visit the church where the tramps of the town find
shelter.  The lonely little nobleman thirsts for the caressing hand of a
parent; and in his yearnings he finds consolation

   <pb n="126"/>

in his secret devotion to the beggar girl.  The story is thoroughly
convincing, and offers a striking example of a disagreeable subject made
beautiful through artistic truth inspired by human sympathy.  The several
outcasts in the story are among the strongest creations in modern
literature.
</p><p>Korolenko's later stories have all appeared in "Russkoye Bogatstvo"
(Russian Riches), of which he and Michailovsky, the critic, are the
editors.  His contributions are rather far between.  So are Chekhoff's.
The most prolific of the noted writers of short stories is Ignati
Nicola&iuml;evitch Potapenko.  This, however, has anything but an
enviable effect upon his literary status.  He has written several tales
which should entitle him to a place in the front rank.  "The Private
Secretary of His Excellency" is an inimitable portrait of a man who wears
out his nerves and dies of heart-failure; overworking himself for the glory
of his worthless time-server of an employer; "Practical Common Sense"
may not be a model of construction, but it is full of human interest and
irresistible humor.  Besides these two, Potapenko has written a dozen or
so of other stories and sketches which have in them the elements of
enduring literature; but all these are lost in scores of "potboilers" quite
unworthy of his talent.
</p><p>All his stories, without exception, are, however, extremely
readable; and running through them all there is a chord of human
sympathy and of an undimmed optimism, coupled with that spirit of
criticism which is a necessary element of success in Russian fiction.
Sometimes the humanitarian idea is given expression in a species of
semi-idealized images, whose flesh and blood are of a questionable
quality, as is the case in his "General's Daughter" and "Active Service;"
at other times it betrays him into false notes like those which jar upon the
reader of his story of newspaper life in Odessa; but in his happier moods
he is free from all these faults.  At his best he is very good indeed.
Unfortunately, however, he is too often at his worst.
</p><p>The clerical and the Bohemian world are his specialty; but he has a
close acquaintance with almost every walk of life, particularly in the
southern provinces; and the ten or twelve volumes of short stories he has
published cover the widest range of type and circumstance.  He has
neither the tender-hearted poetry of Korolenko nor the divine
clairvoyance of Chekhoff; but he knows the world thoroughly, and has a
lively sense of its comedies and tragedies.  One of the secrets of his wide
popularity is his inexhaustible stock of most interesting themes.  As the
reader lays down a new story by Potapenko, he thinks it curious

   <pb n="127"/>

that the subject should so long have been overlooked by literature.  It
seems just the thing to make a story of, and, at the same time, it is such a
familiar phase of our every-day experience, that one cannot help
wondering how it escaped the notice of all other writers.
</p><p>As to Gorki and Veresayeff, they "arrived" so recently that their
position has not yet been clearly defined.  Both are endowed with the
power of description, and both have sense of character; but while
Veresayeff has attracted attention as a promising disciple of Turgeneff,
Gorki has sprung into sudden prominence through his most original and
extremely vigorous sketches of life among social waifs.  His "unifying
idea" strongly suggests Nietzsche.
</p><p>Piotr Dmitrievitch Boborykin, who trains his literary camera upon
the latest tendencies and fads of his country, and Dmitri Nikanorovitch
Mamin, who hunts for "local color" among the tribes of the Ural
Mountains and Western Siberia, are novelists.  Both have the art of
projecting their figures, and both are widely read &mdash; particularly
Boborykin, who belongs to an older generation.  But neither of them is
capable of arousing enthusiasm in a country where the word novelist is
associated in the public mind with the names of Tolstoy, Turgeneff,
Dostoyevsky, and Goncharoff.
</p><p>Of the young women who contribute stories to the leading
magazines, Viera Mikoulich has attracted considerable notice.  Other
young writers, also, have done good work; and, like those mentioned
above, they draw their themes from the actualities of their own
environment.
</p><p>The peculiar history of Russian literature, from Pushkin, Gogol,
and Lermontoff down to our time, and the "characteristic sadness" and
introspective, "self-lashing" propensities of the educated classes have
developed a passionate interest in the artistic study of character and
human motive.  The five or six magazines published in the two capitals,
and the influential newspapers of the Empire, give much space to this
kind of literature.  Not contented with the home product, they also print a
translation of anything to be found in the way of realistic fiction in
foreign countries; provided the realism is art, and the analysis is not a
long-drawn-out discussion, but a "picture of the soul."
</p><p>But then the Russian magazines will also give space to stories of
foreign authors who are not realists.  Generally speaking, they are far
more tolerant with writers of the "decaying West" than they are with their
own.  They limit themselves, however, to the best representatives

   <pb n="128"/>

of literature in each country; so that, upon the whole, the
fiction printed in the Russian magazines is of an unusually high order.
This would not be the case, perhaps, if the magazine-reading public in
Russia were as large as it is in countries where education is much more
evenly distributed than it is in the dominions of the Czar.  But the
Russian monthlies cater to a small, intellectual minority &mdash; the circulation
of the "Messenger of Europe," the best-established magazine in St.
Petersburg, is, according to its own figures, from 7,000 to 8,000 &mdash; and
the average of tastes they have to deal with is exceedingly high.
</p><p>The publications in question are all of the "Revue des Deux
Mondes" type; each combining the elements of a review, such as THE
FORUM, and a literary magazine.  In Russia they are, broadly speaking,
the substitutes for political parties.  Not that the matter published is
limited by any definite programme or necessarily colored by partisan bias
&mdash; for, indeed, topics covering the widest range of thought are given fair
and exhaustive treatment, and the fiction, though often saddled with a
purpose, is in the majority of instances good literature &mdash; but the writers
grouped about a magazine are, for the most part, banded together by the
ties of political persuasion; and their belief, more or less directly
advocated in special articles, crops out in the trend of the literary
discussions as well as in the stories and the poetry.</p>
<closer>
<signed>A. CAHAN.</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

