<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CanMaid"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="CanMaid">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Poet and Scullery-Maid / By Dorothy Canfield</title>
<title type="sort">poet and scullery maid by dorothy canfield</title>
<author>Canfield, Dorothy</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">14</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CanMaid</idno>
<date value="1999">1999</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1999 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475784</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Poet and Scullery-Maid</title>
<title level="j">Munsey`s Magazine.</title>
<title type="sort">poet and scullery maid</title>
<author>Dorothy Canfield</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>New York.</pubPlace>
<date value="1906">1906.</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Alderman Library AP2.M8 v.35 1906.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1906">1906</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>feminine</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1999-05">May 1999</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Matthew Gibson, Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
	<pb n="253"/>
	<head>Poet and Scullery-Maid</head>



<p>ONCE upon a time there was a little
scullery-maid, who, like all scullery-maids, spent most of her time in a kitchen.
It was the kitchen of a boarding-house,
and you can imagine what a disagreeable
place it was &mdash; full of unpleasant smells,
and usually piled high with dirty dishes
which the scullery-maid must wash.  It
was dark, it was greasy, the cook had a
bad temper, and the chimney smoked.
</p><p>You would have thought the little
scullery-maid would have been glad to
get out of it the instant her work was
done, even though the only place to which
she could go was one corner of an attic
on the top floor.  But, oddly enough,
she often left her attic room and slipped
back down to the kitchen after every one
had gone.
</p><p>For, much as she hated the kitchen,
there was one thing about it she loved.  It
overhung a rippling little river, which
ran down from the mountains above the
city, and which was always talking to
itself and to any one else who would
listen.  All day long it talked, but then its
voice was drowned in the rattle of pots
and pans and the angry commands of the
bad-tempered cook.  The scullery-maid
sometimes went out on a little platform,
directly over the water, where she sat and
peeled a mountain of potatoes.  There


<pb n="254"/>

she could hear the river much more
plainly; and she was always deeply disappointed when the cook decided to have
the potatoes boiled in their jackets, for
on those days she had no opportunity to
hear even for a moment the singing voice
of the clear stream.
</p><p>But at night &mdash; that was the time!  The
kitchen was quiet then, and although the
door to the platform was locked, she
could put her head out of the window and
see and hear the dear little river almost
as if she were floating on its surface in
a boat.  She came to know every one of
its moods, and how it looked and how
it sang in fair weather and in foul.
Sometimes it was as merry as a child,
and went along laughing and chuckling
to itself till a smile came on the scullery-maid's dirty face in answer.  Sometimes,
on dark nights, it whispered something
mournful and yet so sweet that she felt
her heart swell.  On moonlight nights it
glided smoothly along like a moonbeam,
with only a gentle lapping where it passed
the pillars of the platform, and a low,
happy murmur from the other bank.
</p><p>But under the stars it was the best of
all.  Then it sang so gallant and heartening a song that the little scullery-maid
forgot how she hated the kitchen and the
greasy dishes, forgot that she had no
friends and no sweetheart.  She only felt
glad that she was alive, and faced bravely
a long future of bad-tempered cooks and
unpleasant smells.
</p><p>Now one of the people who lived in
the boarding-house was a poet &mdash; a really,
truly poet, although people did not know
it yet, for he was only a young man and
looked like any one else, except that he
often forgot to shave himself.  One evening he was invited out to a fashionable
late supper &mdash; a great event with him, for
he was very poor.  When he dressed, he
noticed that as usual he had not shaved
for two or three days, so that a blond
stubble bristled all over his cheeks and
chin.  It was too late to ring for anything,
so he took his little pitcher and went
downstairs to the kitchen to get some
warm water.
</p><p>He had very old slippers on his feet,
and they were so worn and soft that they
made no noise as he walked; so that the
little scullery-maid, leaning out of the
window, did not hear him, any more than
he saw her in the dark room.  As he
dipped his pitcher in the reservoir of
water, he caught his sleeve on a pan and
it came crashing down on the stove.  It
was a question which was more startled,
the girl or the poet.  They stood and
stared at each other in the dusk.  He saw
a very dirty little maid with a plain face
and no figure at all, and she saw a very
handsome young man, for it was so dark
that she could not see that he needed to
shave.
</p><p>"Who in the world are you?" asked
the poet.
</p><p>"I am the scullery-maid," she said.
</p><p>"Good heavens, do you have to stay
in this awful place at night as well as
by day?"
</p><p>The poet was like other poets, and
could not bear to think of unpleasant
things, although he was glad enough to
be benefited by their results.
</p><p>"No, I don't have to stay here."
</p><p>"Why under the sun do you come back,
then?"
</p><p>Now the scullery-maid was very ignorant and simple-minded &mdash; you can imagine
how much so from the fact that she could
not think of anything to say but the truth.
</p><p>"I come back to listen to the river," she
said.
</p><p>The poet stared.
</p><p>"Why do you do that?" he asked.
</p><p>"I do not know exactly why.  I &mdash; I
like it."
</p><p>There was a long silence, in which the
poet heard the gallant song of the little
river rushing past under the stars, hurrying along it knew not whither, but still
happy and sure that its path was safe.
Tears came into his eyes, and he set the
pitcher of hot water down on the stove.
He had a sudden realization of what the
voice of the stream meant to the ugly
little scullery-maid.  After the manner of
poets, he knew at once, much better than
she did, what it said to her.  He felt a
whole poem chanting in his heart.
</p><p>"You poor child!" he said, and laid
his hand on her shoulder.  His voice
was very soft.  Nobody else had ever
spoken to her so before.  "You poor
child!  <hi rend="italic">I</hi> know why you like to hear it."
</p><p>And with that he went up-stairs and
wrote the loveliest poem you can imagine
&mdash; all about the little scullery-maid, and
how she hated the kitchen, and her ugly,


<pb n="255"/>

unhappy life, and yet how sweetly the
little river sang to her and told her to be
brave.  The tears were in his eyes many
times as he wrote, and he forgot all about
the supper to which he had been invited,
for he was a real poet.
</p><p>The scullery-maid stood still exactly
where he had left her.  For once she did
not hear the voice of the river.  She heard
some one saying, "You poor child!  You
poor child!"  It seemed to her she must
have dreamed it, and yet there was the
pot of hot water, glimmering white in
the dusk.  There it was in the morning,
too, although of course the water had
grown cold.
</p><p>The poet sent the poem he had written
in the night to a great editor &mdash; one who
had refused every single thing the poet
had written before.  The editor was as
bad-tempered as he was great, but he
wiped his eyes after he had read the poem
about the dirty little scullery-maid and
the song of the river, and sent for the poet
at once, to tell him to write more like it.
This the poet was already doing.  He had
forgotten everything else, and imagined
that he too was a maid and lived in a
greasy kitchen with only the sound of a
river for comfort.
</p><p>For that is the way with a poet.  If he
gets interested in somebody's point of
view, he steps in and pushes the owner
out of the way and lives his life for a
while.  The scullery-maid below stairs
did not know that the blond young man
on the fourth floor was washing her
dishes, peeling her potatoes, and dreading
with her the harsh voice of the cook; but
so he was.  In the evening he stood beside her as she listened to the song of the
river; and he stole her simple, ignorant
thoughts, one by one, and carried away
on the tip of his pen the love for the little
stream which filled her heart.
</p><p>When he had taken them all, and written them down so beautifully that he
made himself cry many times, he put them
all in a book.  Then he forgot about them
and fell to imagining he was some one
else.  For that is the way with a poet.
</p><p>But the editor did not forget, nor did
any one who read the poems.  Everywhere in the city people were moved to
tears by the beauty of the river's song
and the sadness of the little scullery-maid.
Gray-haired business folk, lovely ladies
of society, unhappy young men and old
women &mdash; all imagined, while they read
the poems, that they, too, were scullery-maids and that the river sang to them;
and they faced whatever was unhappy or
ugly in their own lives with more courage
because of what it said.  They did not
say much in praise of the little book,
but they dried their eyes when they had
finished it, and went to buy another copy
to send to a friend.  Most remarkable of
all, they treated their own scullery-maids
with more kindness, which is a tremendous thing for a poem to have accomplished.  The editor who had recognized
before any one else how lovely the poems
were was surer than ever that he was a
great man.
</p><p>Scullery-maids were quite heroines,
and even the ugly little one in the kitchen
of the boarding-house seemed so important that the grocer's boy tried to be
her sweetheart.  He was a good fellow,
and wished to be kind to her, but she
would have none of him, because he was
not blond, and did not put his hand on
her shoulder and say in a tender voice,
"You poor child!" &mdash; in other words, because he was not a poet; whereas, if she
had but known it, it was a lucky thing for
her that he was not.
</p><p>She was so ignorant and neglected that
she had never learned to read, and she was
almost the only one in the city who did
not have the joy of the poems about her
river.  She found out where the poet's
room was, and whenever she could she
would slip away to try and catch a
glimpse of him.  But though he passed
her several times on the stairs, he did not
notice her.  He was so busy living the
life of an old, old woman whom he had
seen on the other side of town that he
could think of nothing else.  Still, it was
a joy to the scullery-maid even to see him,
and as she sat on the platform, peeling
potatoes, she thought how yellow his hair
was, and how blue his eyes, instead of
listening to the river which had comforted her so long.
</p><p>And then, one day, the poet got so
much money from the sale of his little
book that he decided to move away to a
better boarding-place.  When the little
scullery-maid heard the news, as she
washed the dishes in the greasy kitchen,
something snapped inside her head, and


<pb n="256"/>

she could no longer hear any sound of
the river at all.
</p><p>That day, as she sat peeling the potatoes, the little river flowed past, silently,
silently, and yet with so dizzying a gleam
that, as she looked long and miserably at
it, she lost her balance and fell into the
water and was drowned.  It was probably
the best thing that could have happened
to her.  For when one can no longer hear
any sound of brave song through the
hateful noise of dreary toil, when one has
lost one's singing river, there is not much
to live for, is there?
</p><p>She was carried down the current and
cast ashore on the beach where the river
runs into the sea.  The poet, walking on
the beach, saw her lying there, and
straightway fell to imagining the most
romantic ideas about an unhappy love
story.  The tears came to his eyes,
although that was nothing surprising for
him.  A beautiful poem sang in his heart,
so that he forgot all about the poor little
scullery-maid lying dead at his feet.  For
that is the way with a poet.
</p> <p> <hi rend="italic">Dorothy Canfield</hi>
</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
