<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CanPort"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="CanPort">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Portrait of a Philosopher</title>
<title type="sort">portrait of a philosopher</title>
<author>Canfield, Dorothy</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">33</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CanPort</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475787</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Portrait of a Philosopher</title>
<title type="sort">portrait of a philosopher</title>
<author>Canfield, Dorothy</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner's Magazine</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1911-04">April 1911</date>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1911">1911</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-02">February 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>updated header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="1995-02">February 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Monique Dull</name>
</respStmt>
<item>conversion to basic TEI-conformant markup</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">
	<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head>PORTRAIT OF A PHILOSOPHER </head>



<div2 type="chapter" n="1" id="d4">
	<pb n="447"/>
<head>I</head>

<p>THE news of Professor Gridley's death filled Middletown
College with consternation.  Its one claim to distinction was gone,
for in spite of the excessive quiet of his private life, he had
always cast about the obscure little college the shimmering aura of
greatness.  There had been no fondness possible for the austere old
thinker, but Middletown village, as well as the college, had been
touched by his fidelity to the very moderate attractions of his
birthplace.  When, as often happened, some famous figure was seen
on the streets, people used to say first, "Here to see old Grid, I
suppose," and then, "Funny how he sticks here.  They say he was
offered seven thousand at the University of California."  In the
absence of any known motive for this steadfastness, the village
legend-making instinct had evolved a theory that he did not wish to
move away from a state of which his father had been governor, and
where the name of Gridley was like a patent of nobility.
</p><p>And now he was gone, the last of the race.  His disappearance
caused the usual amount of reminiscent talk among his neighbors.
The older people recalled the by-gone scandals connected with his
notorious and popular father and intimated with knowing nods that
there were plenty of other descendants of the old governor who were
not entitled legally to bear the name; but the younger ones, who
had known only the severely ascetic life and cold personality of
the celebrated scholar, found it difficult to connect him with such
a father.  In their talk they brought to mind the man himself, his
queer shabby clothes, his big stooping frame, his sad black eyes,
absent almost to vacancy as though always fixed on high and distant
thoughts; and those who had lived near him told laughing stories
about the crude and countrified simplicity of his old aunt's
housekeeping&mdash;it was said that the president of Harvard had been
invited to join them once in a Sunday evening meal of crackers and
milk&mdash;but the general tenor of feeling was, as it had been during
his life, of pride in his great fame and in the celebrated people
who had come to see him.
</p><p>This pride warmed into something like affection when, the day
after his death, came the tidings that he had bequeathed <pb n="448"/>  to
his college the Gino Sprague Falleres portrait of himself.  Of
course, at that time, no one in Middletown had seen the picture,
for the philosopher's sudden death had occurred, very dramatically,
actually during the last sitting.  He had, in fact, had barely one
glimpse of it himself, as, according to Falleres's invariable rule,
no one, not even the subject of the portrait, had been allowed to
examine an unfinished piece of work.  But, though Middletown had no
first-hand knowledge of the picture, there could be no doubt about
the value of the canvas.  As soon as it was put on exhibition in
London, from every art-critic in the three nations who claimed
Falleres for their own, there rose a wail that this masterpiece was
to be buried in an unknown college in an obscure village in
barbarous America.  It was confidently stated that it would be
saved from such an unfitting resting-place by strong action on the
part of an International Committee of Artists; but Middletown,
though startled by its own good fortune, clung with Yankee tenacity
to its rights.  Raphael Collin, of Paris, commenting on this in the
<hi rend="italic">Revue des Deux Mondes</hi>, cried out whimsically upon the woes of
an art-critic's life, "as if there were not already enough
wearisome pilgrimages necessary to remote and uncomfortable places
with jaw-breaking names, which must nevertheless be visited for the
sake of a single picture!"  And a burlesque resolution to carry off
the picture by force was adopted at the dinner in London given in
honor of Falleres the evening before he set off for America to
attend the dedicatory exercises with which Middletown planned to
install its new treasure.
</p><p>For the little rustic college rose to its one great occasion.
Bold in their confidence in their dead colleague's fame, the
college authorities sent out invitations to all the great ones of
the country.  Those to whom Gridley was no more than a name on
volumes one never read, came because the portrait was by Falleres,
and those who had no interest in the world of art came to honor the
moralist whose noble clear-thinking had simplified the intimate
problems of modern life.  There was the usual residuum of those who
came because the others did, and, also as usual, they were among
the most brilliant figures in the procession which filed along, one
October morning, under the old maples of Middletown campus.
</p><p>It was a notable celebration.  A bishop opened the exercises
with prayer, a United States senator delivered the eulogy of the
dead philosopher, the veil uncovering the portrait was drawn away
by the mayor of one of America's largest cities, himself an ardent
Gridleyite, and among those who spoke afterward were the presidents
of three great universities.  The professor's family was
represented but scantily.  He had had one brother, who had
disappeared many years ago under a black cloud of ill report, and
one sister who had married and gone West to live.  Her two sons,
middle-aged merchants from Ohio, gave the only personal note to the
occasion by their somewhat tongue-tied and embarrassed presence,
for Gridley's aunt was too aged and infirm to walk with the
procession from the Gymnasium, where it formed, to the Library
building where the portrait was installed.
</p><p>After the inevitable photographers had made their records of
the memorable gathering the procession began to wind its many-colored way back to the Assembly Hall, where it was to lunch.
Every one was feeling relieved that the unveiling had gone off so
smoothly, and cheerful at the prospect of food.  The undergraduates
began lustily to shout their college song, which was caught up by
the holiday mood of the older ones.  This cheerful tumult gradually
died away in the distance, leaving the room of the portrait
deserted in an echoing silence.  A janitor began to remove the rows
of folding chairs.  The celebration was over.
</p><p>Into the empty room there now limped forward a small, shabby
old woman with a crutch.  "I'm his aunt, that lived with him," she
explained apologetically, "and I want to see the picture."
</p><p>She advanced, peering near-sightedly at the canvas.  The
janitor continued stacking up chairs until he was stopped by a cry
from the new-comer.  She was a great deal paler than when she came
in.  She was staring hard at the portrait and now beckoned him
wildly to do the same.  "Look at it!  Look at it!"
</p><p>Surprised, he followed the direction of her shaking hand.
"Sure, it's Professor Grid to the life!" he said admiringly.
<pb n="449"/>  [illustration omitted]
</p><p>"Look at it!  Look at it!"  She seemed not to be able to find
any other words.
</p><p>After a prolonged scrutiny he turned to her with a puzzled
line between his eyebrows.  "Since you've spoken of it, ma'am, I
will say that there's a something about the expression of the eyes
. . . and mouth, maybe . . . that ain't just the professor.  He was
more absent-like.  It reminds me of somebody else . . . of some
face I've seen . . ."
</p><p>She hung on his answer, her mild, timid old face drawn like a
mask of tragedy.  "Who?  Who?" she prompted him.
</p><p>For a time he could not remember, staring at the new portrait
and scratching <pb n="450"/>  his head.  Then it came to him suddenly:
"Why, sure, I ought to ha' known without thinkin', seeing the other
picture as often as every time I've swep' out the president's
office.  And Professor Grid always looked like him some, anyhow."
</p><p>The old woman leaned against the wall, her crutch trembling in
her hand.  Her eyes questioned him mutely.
</p><p>"Why, ma'am, who but his own father, to be sure . . . the old
governor."
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="2" id="d5">
<head> II </head>
<p>WHILE they had been duly sensible of the lustre reflected upon
them by the celebration in honor of their distinguished uncle,
Professor Gridley's two nephews could scarcely have said truthfully
that they enjoyed the occasion.  As one of them did say to the
other, the whole show was rather out of their line.  Their line was
wholesale hardware and, being eager to return to it, it was with a
distinct feeling of relief that they waited for the train at the
station.  They were therefore as much displeased as surprised by
the sudden appearance to them of their great-aunt, very haggard,
her usual extreme timidity swept away by overmastering emotion.
She clutched at the two merchants with a great sob of relief:
"Stephen!  Eli!  Come back to the house," she cried, and before
they could stop her was hobbling away.  They hurried after her,
divided between the fear of losing their train and the hope that
some inheritance from their uncle had been found.  They were not
mercenary men, but they felt a not unnatural disappointment that
Professor Gridley had left not a penny, not even to his aunt, his
one intimate.
</p><p>They overtook her, scuttling along like some frightened and
wounded little animal.  "What's the matter, Aunt Amelia?" they
asked shortly.  "We've got to catch this train."
</p><p>She faced them.  "You can't go now.  You've got to make them
take that picture away."
</p><p>"Away!"  Their blankness was stupefaction.
</p><p>She raged at them, the timid, harmless little thing, like a
creature distraught.  "Didn't you see it?  Didn't you <hi rend="italic">see</hi> it?"
</p><p>Stephen answered: "Well, no, not to have a good square look at
it.  The man in front of me kept getting in the way."
</p><p>Eli admitted: "If you mean you don't see anything in it to
make all this hurrah about, I'm with you.  It don't look half
finished.  I don't like that slap-dash style."
</p><p>She was in a frenzy at their denseness.  "Who did it look
like?" she challenged them.
</p><p>"Why, like Uncle Grid, of course.  Who else?"
</p><p>"Yes, yes," she cried; "who else?  Who else?"
</p><p>They looked at each other, afraid that she was crazed, and
spoke more gently: "Why, I don't know, I'm sure, who else.  Like
Grandfather Gridley, of course; but then Uncle Grid always did look
like his father."
</p><p>At this she quite definitely put it out of their power to
leave her by fainting away.
</p><p>They carried her home and laid her on her own bed, where one
of them stayed to attend her while the other went back to rescue
their deserted baggage.  As the door closed behind him the old
woman came to herself.  "Oh, Stephen," she moaned, "I wish it had
killed me, the way it did your uncle."
</p><p>"What <hi rend="italic">is</hi> the matter?" asked her great-nephew wonderingly.
"What do you think killed him?"
</p><p>"That awful, awful picture!  I know it now as plain as if I'd
been there.  He hadn't seen it all the time he was sitting for it,
though he'd already put in his will that he wanted the college to
have it, and when he did see it&mdash;" she turned on the merchant with
a sudden fury: "How <hi rend="italic">dare</hi> you say those are your uncle's eyes!"
</p><p>He put his hand soothingly on hers.  "Now, now, Aunt 'Melia,
maybe the expression isn't just right, but the color is <hi rend="italic">fine</hi> .
. . just that jet-black his were . . . and the artist has got in
exact that funny stiff way uncle's hair stood up over his
forehead."
</p><p>The old woman fixed outraged eyes upon him.  "Color!" she
said.  "And hair!  Oh Lord, help me!"
</p><p>She sat up on the bed, clutching her nephew's hand, and began
to talk rapidly.  When, a half-hour later, the other brother
returned, neither of them heard him enter the house.  It was only
when he called <pb n="451"/>  [illustration omitted] at the foot of the
stairs that they both started and Stephen ran down to join him.
</p><p>"You'll see the president . . . you'll fix it?" the old woman
cried after him.
</p><p>"I'll see, Aunt 'Melia," he answered pacifyingly as he drew
his brother out of doors.  He looked quite pale and moved, and drew
a long breath before he could begin.  "Aunt Amelia's been telling
me a lot of things I never knew, Eli.  It seems that . . . say, did
you ever hear that Grandfather Gridley, the governor, was such a
bad lot?"
</p><p>"Why, mother never said much about her father one way or the
other, but I always sort of guessed he wasn't all he <pb n="452"/>  might
have been from her never bringing us on to visit here until after
he died.  She used to look queer, too, when folks congratulated her
on having such a famous man for father.  All the big politicians of
his day thought a lot of him.  He <hi rend="italic">was</hi> as smart as chain-lightning!"
</p><p>"He was a disreputable old scalawag!" cried his other
grandson.  "Some of the things Aunt Amelia has been telling me make
me never want to come back to this part of the country again.  Do
you know why Uncle Grid lived so poor and scrimped and yet left no
money?  He'd been taking care of a whole family grandfather had
beside ours; and paying back some people grandfather did out of a
lot of money on a timber deal fifty years ago; and making it up to
a little village in the backwoods that grandfather persuaded to
bond itself for a railroad that he knew wouldn't go near it."
</p><p>The two men stared at each other an instant, reviewing in a
new light the life that had just closed.  "That's why he never
married," said Eli, finally.
</p><p>"No, that's what I said, but Aunt Amelia just went wild when
I did.  She said . . . gee!" he passed his hand over his eyes with
a gesture of mental confusion.  "Ain't it strange what can go on
under your eyes and you never know it.  Why, she says Uncle Grid
was just like his father."
</p><p>The words were not out of his mouth before the other's face of
horror made him aware of his mistake.  "No!  No!  Not that!
Heavens, no!  I mean . . . made like him . . . <hi rend="italic">wanted</hi> to be
that kind, specially drink . . ." his tongue, unused to phrasing
abstractions, stumbled and tripped in his haste to correct the
other's impression.  "You know how much Uncle Grid used to look
like grandfather . . . the same black hair and broad face and thick
red lips and a kind of knob on the end of his nose?  Well, it seems
he had his father's insides too . . . <hi rend="italic">but his mother's
conscience!</hi>  I guess, from what Aunt Amelia says, that the
combination made life about as near Tophet for him . . . !  She's
the only one to know anything about it, because she's lived with
him always, you know, took him when grandmother died and he was a
child.  She says when he was younger he was like a man fighting a
wild beast . . . he didn't dare let up or rest.  Some days he
wouldn't stop working at his desk all day long, not even to eat,
and then he'd grab up a piece of bread and go off for a long
tearing tramp that'd last 'most all night.  You know what a
tremendous physique all the Gridley men have had.  Well, Uncle Grid
turned into work all the energy the rest of them spent in deviltry.
Aunt Amelia said he'd go on like that day after day for a month,
and then he'd bring out one of those essays folks are so crazy
about.  She said she never could bear to <hi rend="italic">look</hi> at his books . .
. seemed to her they were written in his blood.  She told him so
once and he said it was the only thing to do with blood like his."
</p><p>He was silent, while his listener made a clucking noise of
astonishment.  "My!  My!  I'd have said that there never was
anybody more different from grandfather than uncle.  Why, as he got
on in years he didn't even look like him any more."
</p><p>This reference gave Stephen a start.  "Oh, yes, that's what
all this came out for.  Aunt Amelia is just wild about this
portrait.  It's just a notion of hers, of course, but after what
she told me I could see, easy, how the idea would come to her.  It
looks this way, she says, as though Uncle Grid inherited his
father's physical make-up complete, and spent all his life fighting
it . . . and won out!  And here's this picture making him look the
way he would if he'd been the worst old . . . as if he'd been like
the governor.  She says she feels as though she was the only one to
defend uncle . . . as if it could make any difference to him!  I
guess the poor old lady is a little touched.  Likely it's harder
for her, losing uncle, than we realized.  She just about worshipped
him.  Queer business, anyhow, wasn't it?  Who'd ha' thought he was
like that?"
</p><p>He had talked his unwonted emotion quite out, and now looked
at his brother with his usual matter-of-fact eye.  "Did you tell
the station agent to hold the trunk?"
</p><p>The other, who was the younger, looked a little abashed.
"Well, no; I found the train was so late I thought maybe we could
. . . you know there's that business to-morrow . . .!"
</p><p>His senior relieved him of embarrassment.  "That's a good
idea.  Sure we can. <pb n="453"/>  There's nothing we could do if we
stayed.  It's just a notion of Aunt 'Melia's, anyhow.  I agree with
her that it don't look so awfully like Uncle Grid, but, then, oil-portraits are never any good.  Give me a photograph!"
</p><p>"It's out of our line, anyhow," agreed the younger, looking at
his watch.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="3" id="d6">
<head>III </head>
<p>THE president of Middletown College had been as much relieved
as pleased by the success of the rather pretentious celebration he
had planned.  His annoyance was correspondingly keen at the
disturbing appearance in the afternoon reception before the new
portrait, of the late professor's aunt, "an entirely insignificant
old country woman," he hastily assured M. Falleres after she had
been half forced, half persuaded to retire, "whose criticisms were
as negligible as her personality."
</p><p>The tall, Jove-like artist concealed a smile by stroking his
great brown beard.  When it came to insignificant country people,
he told himself, it was hard to draw lines in his present company.
He was wondering whether he might not escape by an earlier train.
</p><p>To the president's remark he answered that no portrait-painter
escaped unreasonable relatives of his sitters.  "It is an axiom
with our guild," he went on, not, perhaps, averse to giving his
provincial hosts a new sensation, "that the family is never
satisfied, and also that the family has no rights.  A sitter is a
subject only, like a slice of fish.  The only question is how it's
done.  What difference does it make a century from now, if the
likeness is good?  It's a work of art or it's nothing."  He
announced this principle with a regal absence of explanation and
turned away; but his thesis was taken up by another guest, a New
York art critic.
</p><p>"By Jove, it's inconceivable, the ignorance of art in
America!" he told the little group before the portrait.  "You find
every one so incurably personal in his point of view . . . always
objecting to a masterpiece because the watch-chain isn't the kind
usually worn by the dear departed."
</p><p>Some one else chimed in.  "Yes, it's incredible that any one,
even an old village granny, should be able to look at that canvas
and not be struck speechless by its quality."
</p><p>The critic was in Middletown to report on the portrait and he
now began marshalling his adjectives for that purpose.  "I never
saw such use of pigment in my life . . . it makes the Whistler
'Carlyle' look like burnt-out ashes . . . the luminous richness of
the blacks in the academic gown, the masterly generalization in the
treatment of the hair, the placing of those great talons of hands
on the canvas carrying out the vigorous lines of the composition,
and the unforgetable felicity of those brutally red lips as the one
ringing note of color.  As for life-likeness, what's the old dame
talking about!  I never saw such eyes!  Not a hint of meretricious
emphasis on their lustre and yet they fairly flame."
</p><p>The conversation spread to a less technical discussion as the
group was joined by the professor of rhetoric, an ambitious young
man with an insatiable craving for sophistication, who felt himself
for once entirely in his element in the crowd of celebrities.
"It's incredibly good luck that our little two-for-a-cent college
should have so fine a thing," he said knowingly.  "I've been
wondering how such an old skinflint as Gridley ever got the money
loose to have his portrait done by . . ."
</p><p>A laugh went around the group at the idea.  "It was
Mackintosh, the sugar king, who put up for it.  He's a great
Gridleyite, and persuaded him to sit."
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Persuade</hi> a man to sit to Falleres!"  The rhetoric
professor was outraged at the idea.
</p><p>"Yes, so they say.  The professor was dead against it from the
first.  Falleres himself had to beg him to sit.  Falleres said he
felt a real inspiration at the sight of the old fellow . . . knew
he could make a good thing out of him.  He <hi rend="italic">was</hi> a good subject!"
</p><p>The little group turned and stared appraisingly at the
portrait hanging so close to them that it seemed another living
being in their midst.  The rhetoric professor was asked what kind
of a man the philosopher had been personally, and answered briskly:
"Oh, nobody knew him personally . . . the silent old codger.  He
was a dry-as-dust, bloodless, secular monk . . ." <pb n="454"/>
</p><p>He was interrupted by a laugh from the art critic, whose eyes
were still on the portrait.
</p><p>"Excuse me for my cynical mirth," he said, "but I must say he
doesn't look it.  I was prepared for any characterization but that.
He looks like a powerful son of the Renaissance, who might have
lived in that one little vacation of the soul after mediaevalism
stopped hag-riding us, and before the modern conscience got its
claws on us.  And you say he was a blue-nosed Puritan!"
</p><p>The professor of rhetoric looked an uneasy fear that he was
being ridiculed.  "I only repeated the village notion of him," he
said airily.  "He may have been anything.  All I know is that he
was as secretive as a clam, and about as interesting personally."
</p><p>"Look at the picture," said the critic, still laughing;
"you'll know all about him!"
</p><p>The professor of rhetoric nodded.  "You're right, he doesn't
look much like my character of him.  I never seem to have had a
good, square look at him before.  I've heard several people say the
same thing, that they seemed to understand him better from the
portrait than from his living face.  There was something about his
eyes that kept you from thinking of anything but what he was
saying."
</p><p>The critic agreed.  "The eyes are wonderful . . . ruthless in
their power . . . fires of hell."  He laughed a deprecating apology
for his over-emphatic metaphor and suggested: "It's possible that
there was more to the professorial life than met the eye.  Had he
a wife?"
</p><p>"No; it was always a joke in the village that he would never
look at a woman."
</p><p>The critic glanced up at the smouldering eyes of the portrait
and smiled.  "I've heard of that kind of a man before," he said.
"Never known to drink, either, I suppose?"
</p><p>"Cold-water teetotaler," laughed the professor, catching the
spirit of the occasion.
</p><p>"Look at the color in that nose!" said the critic.  "I fancy
that the ascetic moralist. . . ."
</p><p>A very young man, an undergraduate who had been introduced as
the junior usher, nodded his head.  "Yep, a lot of us fellows
always thought old Grid a little too good to be true."
</p><p>An older man with the flexible mouth of a politician now
ventured a contribution to a conversation no longer bafflingly
aesthetic: "His father, old Governor Gridley, wasn't he . . .
Well, I guess you're right about the son.  No halos were handed
down in <hi rend="italic">that</hi> family!"
</p><p>The laugh which followed this speech was stopped by the
approach of Falleres, his commanding presence dwarfing the
president beside him.  He was listening with a good-natured
contempt to the apparently rather anxious murmurs of the latter.
</p><p>"Of course I know, Mr. Falleres, it is a great deal to ask,
but she is so insistent . . . she won't go away and continues to
make the most distressing spectacle of herself . . . and several
people, since she has said so much about it, are saying that the
expression is not that of the late professor.  Much against my will
I promised to speak to you . . ."
</p><p>His mortified uneasiness was so great that the artist gave him
a rescuing hand.  "Well, Mr. President, what can I do in the
matter?  The man is dead.  I cannot paint him over again, and if I
could I would only do again as I did this time, choose that aspect
which my judgment told me would make the best portrait.  If his
habitual vacant expression was not so interesting as another not so
permanent a habit of his face . . . why, the poor artist must be
allowed some choice.  I did not know I was to please his
grandmother, and not posterity."
</p><p>"His aunt," corrected the president automatically.
</p><p>The portrait-painter accepted the correction with his tolerant
smile.  "His aunt," he repeated.  "The difference is considerable.
May I ask what it was you promised her?"
</p><p>The president summoned his courage.  It was easy to gather
from his infinitely reluctant insistence how painful and compelling
had been the scene which forced him to action.  "She wants you to
change it . . . to make the expression of the . . ."
</p><p>For the first time the artist's equanimity was shaken.  He
took a step backward.  "Change it!" he said, and although his voice
was low the casual chat all over the <pb n="455"/>  room stopped short as
though a pistol had been fired.
</p><p>"It's not <hi rend="italic">my</hi> idea!" the president confounded himself in
self-exoneration.  "I merely promised, to pacify her, to ask you if
you could not do some little thing that would . . ."
</p><p>The critic assumed the role of conciliator.  "My dear sir, I
don't believe you quite understand what you are asking.  It's as
though you asked a priest to make just a little change in the
church service and leave out the Not in the commandments."
</p><p>"I only wished to know Mr. Falleres's attitude," said the
president stiffly, a little nettled by the other's note of
condescension.  "I presume he will be willing to take the
responsibility of it himself and explain to the professor's aunt
that <hi rend="italic">I</hi> have done . . ."
</p><p>The artist had recovered from his lapse from Olympian calm and
now nodded smiling: "Dear me, yes, Mr. President, I'm used to irate
relatives."
</p><p>The president hastened away and the knots of talkers in other
parts of the room, who had been looking with expectant curiosity at
the group before the portrait, resumed their loud-toned chatter.
When their attention was next drawn in the same direction, it was
by a shaky old treble, breaking and quavering with weakness.  A
small, shabby old woman, leaning on a crutch, stood looking up
imploringly at the tall painter.
</p><p>"My dear madam," he broke in on her with a kindly impatience,
"all that you say about Professor Gridley is much to his credit,
but what has it to do with me?"
</p><p>"You painted his portrait," she said with a simplicity that
was like stupidity.  "And I am his aunt.  You made a picture of a
bad man.  I know he was a good man."
</p><p>"I painted what I saw," sighed the artist wearily.  He looked
furtively at his watch.
</p><p>The old woman seemed dazed by the extremity of her emotion.
She looked about her silently, keeping her eyes averted from the
portrait that stood so vividly like a living man beside her.  "I
don't know what to do!" she murmured with a little moan.  "I can't
<hi rend="italic">bear</hi> it to have it stay here&mdash;people forget so.  Everybody'll
think that Gridley looked like <hi rend="italic">that!</hi>  And there isn't anybody
but me.  He never had anybody but me."
</p><p>The critic tried to clear the air by a roundly declaratory
statement of principles.  "You'll pardon my bluntness, madam; but
you must remember that none but the members of Professor Gridley's
family are concerned in the exact details of his appearance.  Fifty
years from now nobody will remember how he looked, one way or the
other.  The world is only concerned with portraits as works of
art."
</p><p>She followed his reasoning with a strained and docile
attention and now spoke eagerly as though struck by an unexpected
hope: "If that's all, why put his name to it?  Just hang it up, and
call it anything."
</p><p>She shrank together timidly and her eyes reddened at the
laughter which greeted this naive suggestion.
</p><p>Falleres looked annoyed and called his defender off.  "Oh,
never mind explaining me," he said, snapping his watch shut.
"You'll never get the rights of it through anybody's head who
hasn't himself sweat blood over a composition only to be told that
the other side of the sitter's profile is usually considered the
prettier.  After all, we have the last word, since the sitter dies
and the portrait lives."
</p><p>The old woman started and looked at him attentively.
</p><p>"Yes," said the critic, laughing, "immortality's not a bad
balm for pin-pricks."
</p><p>The old woman turned very pale and for the first time looked
again at the portrait.  An electric thrill seemed to pass through
her as her eyes encountered the bold, evil ones fixed on her.  She
stood erect with a rigid face, and "Immortality!" she said, under
her breath.
</p><p>Falleres moved away to make his adieux to the president, and
the little group of his satellites straggled after him to the other
end of the room.  For a moment there was no one near the old woman
to see the crutch furiously upraised, hammer-like, or to stop her
sudden passionate rush upon the picture.
</p><p>At the sound of cracking cloth, they turned back, horrified.
They saw her, with an insane violence, thrust her hands into the
gaping hole that had been the portrait's
<pb n="456"/>  face and, tearing
the canvas from end to end, fall upon the shreds with teeth and
talon.
</p><p>All but Falleres flung themselves toward her, dragging her
away.  With a movement as instinctive he rushed for the picture,
and it was to him, as he stood aghast before the ruined canvas,
that the old woman's shrill treble was directed, above the loud
shocked voices of those about her: "There ain't anything immortal
but souls!" she cried.
</p>

</div2>
		</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
