<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CanPian"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="CanPian">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Piano / By Dorothy Canfield; Author of "The Rescue," "The Story of Ralph Miller," ETC.</title>
<title type="sort">piano by dorothy canfield author of the rescue, the story of ralph miller etc</title>
<author>Canfield, Dorothy</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">22</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CanPian</idno>
<date value="1999">1999</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1999 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475786</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Piano</title>
<title level="m">Munsey`s Magazine.</title>
<title type="sort">piano</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>New York.</pubPlace>
<date value="1907">1906-1907.</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Alderman Library AP2.M8 v.36 1906-1907.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1907">1907</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>feminine</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1999-04">April, 1999</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Matthew Gibson, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<pb n="542"/>

<head>THE PIANO<lb/>
BY DOROTHY CANFIELD<lb/>
AUTHOR OF "THE RESCUE," "THE STORY OF RALPH MILLER," ETC.<lb/></head>

<div2 type="part" n="1" id="d4">

<p>IT was characteristic of Frederika's
relentlessly keen self-analysis that one
of the most intolerable elements of her
misery was the banality of the situation.
Following every step of the wretchedly
familiar mental pilgrimage came the
conviction of the total lack of novelty in
her sensation.  It was as though the
aridity of her outward life penetrated
to the center of her being, and she could
not even suffer but in a worn-out and
threadbare fashion.
</p><p>The very setting of the scene was platitudinously appropriate, she reflected, as
she looked about the little room, bare
but for the grand piano, and noted that
the fire at her husband's feet had smoldered out into white ashes.  Her thin,
handsome face did not move from its
expression of lassitude as this detail
claimed her attention, although her unspoken comment was acrid: "Just the
thing a second-rate French novelist
would put in as a cheap and trivial bit
of symbolism."
</p><p>Her eyes rested long on her husband
after this, in a distastefully minute survey of his figure, relaxed in his armchair, his neck bulging out in a red roll
in spite of the unloosened collar of his
uniform.  She noticed how the straight,
severe lines of his officer's tunic brought
out the ugly lines of a too large waist,
and she remembered, still with no outward change in her spiritless face, that
ten years ago she had thought a uniform
a becoming garment, which gave color
and character to military life, alone in
a commercial age.
</p><p>And yet she had not been a young
girl, ignorant and inexperienced, when
she married.  She had thought that she
recognized unmistakably the call of love
as stronger than the rights of her art,
that the humanity in her was more vital
than music.  She had fancied that she
knew life and that she could weigh what
she was going to give up, definitely,
against what she was getting.  The dry,
commercial aspect of her phrase suddenly came to her, and her inexorable
sense of justice, even to herself, made
her retract.  It was not only what she
was to get from Dick that had influenced
her, it was what she could give the
rough, silent giant; it was the great and
joyous sacrifice of a brilliant musical
career to his interests; it was the rare
and romantic chance to prove herself
worthy of a mighty love and capable of
returning it by giving up all that meaner
folk hold precious &mdash; ease, variety, money,
reputation, success, her name golden for
all music-loving souls.  She had thought
all that of little avail beside the inextinguishable fire of affection and devotion she felt within her for Richard Farrington.  At this for the first time her
mouth twisted into a wry smile, and she
looked again at the heap of white and
gray between the andirons.
</p><p>And how equally insignificant was the
extinguishing of either fire to the sleeping man!  Another, even if he slept,
would awake, shivering, and feel the
chilly desolation of the room and of her
heart, but Dick would rouse himself only
to go to bed so that he could be fresh
for reveille in the morning, that hateful
call to action in the bald light of dawn
which had grown so unbearable to her.
And then he would be out all day on the
drill-ground, blustering paternally over
his recruits, and filling in vacant moments with the childishly detailed accounts of every breath drawn on the
little remote Western post which the
government at Washington exacted and
Dick delighted to make out.  And in the
evening he would come back to the ill-constructed

<pb n="543"/>

officers' quarters, eat his
dinner with a robust disregard for what
it was, drop heavily into his armchair in
front of the fire, dutifully ask his wife
to play to him, and doze off as he had
to-night, not noticing that she sat in
silence.
</p><p>For herself, as though in an ingenious
contrivance of many-angled mirrors, she
saw her drooping figure wherever she
looked, sitting as she now sat, before a
cold hearth, her long musician's fingers
idle in her lap and her self-contemptuous
thoughts busy behind her impassive face.
She told herself impatiently that she
envied unreasonable women who could
get a perverse satisfaction out of blaming conditions for what they themselves
were responsible for.  That would be a
variation from the hopelessly clear sight
which turned her thoughts inexorably
back upon herself.
</p><p>She could not blame Dick for being
exactly what he was.  When she married
him, he had steadily and honestly told
her that he was a rough, inert, half-complete creature, all soldier and but
half-man, his heart going out in a
foolishly recurrent impulse to one after
another of the groups of sodden, fumbling animals who were given him to
make soldiers of.  She remembered how
he had been moved to a blind fear by
her passion and the greatness of her
sacrifice to marry him, and had striven
inarticulately to tell her that she was
mistaken in him; that, although his love
for her was all of his personality outside
his profession, still it was not worthy of
her love for him &mdash; her love made up of
such fine, subtle insight and clear, bright
confidence.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="part" n="2" id="d5"><head>II</head>

<p>SHE stirred restlessly in her chair,
pricked through her apathetic disgust
with herself and the world by a sudden
stab of mortification.  How foolishly
they had talked when they were engaged!
She could not tell how it had happened.
It seemed like a fantastic dream; and
now she was awake and yawning in a
deadly and eternal ennui, and Dick &mdash;
She looked at him again.  His head
hung more heavily toward his shoulder
than before, and his breathing was
louder.  With each outward respiration
his lips puffed out with a faint, unpleasant whistling sound.  In about five
minutes he would begin to snore.  She
would wake him, he would look up, nod,
perhaps pat her hand, and settle down in
a new position to snore again.  Nor
could she blame him for it.  A day of
active exercise out of doors in that eversweeping wind &mdash; what could she expect?
</p><p>That was not the point.  What had
she expected?  What <hi rend="italic">could</hi> she have expected?  With a qualm of self-suspicion
she wondered if she was so paltry as to
be disappointed because Dick was too
good an officer with recruits and common soldiers ever to be advanced to more
spectacular positions.
</p><p>Had she perhaps dreamed of being a
general's wife, of having social rank and
prestige in some metropolitan society?
Remembering her incongruous school-girl admiration for Dick's uniform, she
searched her mind for traces of another
vein of cheapness in her discontent.
There was even a cessation of the dull
ache of dejection as she drove this new
inquiry home to the innermost fastnesses
of her heart; but in a moment she drew
a long breath and again shifted her
position.
</p><p>No, she was not so low as that.  There
was no such positive element as disappointed ambition in the flat negation of
her depression.  She had married Dick
because she loved him, and because that
love meant more to her than her art;
and now she did not love him, and her
art was lost to her.  She held her hand
up to shield her eyes from the lamp, and
noticed how steadily it stood as she admitted that she no longer loved her husband.  The most terrifying cataclysm of
a woman's life was upon her, and she
acknowledged it to herself so languidly
that her hand did not quiver.
</p><p>There were, in fact, no positive aspects of her condition to make her
quiver.  She said dryly to herself that
in one respect at least she differed from
the unpleasant and familiar heroine of
the well-worn French novel.  She did
not crave any other love, having lost
her first.  She had lost not only her love
for her husband but her love for love.
She shuddered at the thought of ever
again putting herself in that maze of
self-illusion, of ever again feeling that


<pb n="544"/>

feverish insanity of emotion.  She was
cured once and for all &mdash; "a burned child."
</p><p>She recalled without a tremor, so unmoved did it leave her, the sudden outburst of passion of a young lieutenant
at the post where they had been last stationed, and remembered with a half
smile how his fervor had been frozen
into a sort of terror of her unearthly
remoteness.  Not even his sudden shame
had made him mistake her attitude for
conscious virtue.  He had called her inhuman &mdash; an epithet, she reflected, which
was truer than most of those of amorous
and disappointed youth, and probably a
great deal truer than he at all realized.
His ardent, impudent love-making had
not moved her.  She settled a ring on a
long, strong finger with the reflection
that nothing could move her.
</p><p>And yet as the next gust of wind
brought a sudden patter of autumn rain
upon the tin roof, she sprang to her feet,
and ran across the room like a girl, to
close the window above the piano, passing an anxious hand across the polished
surface to detect dampness.  There <hi rend="italic">was</hi>
something that could move her, and she
gave a little gasp of thankfulness to feel
her heart beating high.  She was still
alive, although imprisoned in a tomb.
But the thing that kept her alive was an
emotion forever unsatisfied.  She looked
at the great piano, sprawling its ungainly bulk across most of the tiny
room, with unreasoning, half-hysterical
devotion.  It had saved the life of her
soul, she thought to herself, and a knot
came in her throat at the cool, smooth
touch of the keys.  The piles of music
on the little table by its side were like
so many tongues, calling out to her that
beauty still lived in the world.  But they
also cried out that she was lost to it, and
it to her.
</p><p>In the passionate lament over her
realization that she was missing all that
life meant for her she exonerated herself
proudly from much personal vanity and
selfish disappointment.  She was not
thinking of the brilliant future her
teachers had promised her, of the international reputation which had been within her grasp.  She was not so poor a
thing as to regret her name in large
letters on posters.  What rent her with
an intolerable sense of rebellion against
fate was the thought of all the lovely
realm of joy which she might have made
for herself and a thousand thousand
hearers; the inspiriting consciousness of
the actuality, the power, the invincible
might of beauty she might have given
them.
</p><p>And it was still hers, in blessed moments, thanks to the ugly black monster
before her.  Even in her rising emotion
she gave an honest thought to the man
before the hearth &mdash; how he had always
toiled and contrived and mastered circumstance so that she might have her
genie with her; and always with so vacant and good-natured an incapacity to
understand one tittle of what it meant
to her, that his sacrifice was of no
avail &mdash; was even hateful to her &mdash; a profanation!
</p><p>She sat down before the piano, shivering with a prescience of emotion to come,
and laid her hands fondly upon the keys.
As she swung into the first movement of the Beethoven sonata in F
minor, she felt her listless weariness break and fade away.  The last
scudding wisp of it, which for a
moment blinded her to the glorious ether
whither the music swept her, was the
sardonic reflection that the only outward
value of her talent now was that she
would wake her husband, so that he
could shift to an easier position, by the
crash of chords instead of a hand on his
shoulder.
</p><p>And then, while the sonata lasted,
she was transfigured &mdash; translated by a
happy magic into a world all joy, where
every pain is beautiful.  Like a viewless
column the music rose up solemnly and
shut her into a fairy tower of safety
from herself.
</p><p>The last movement ended, the last
chord was struck, the last echo died
away, and down from about her melted
the fleeting bulwarks of her soul.  She
sat shivering on the stool, waiting for her
husband's never-failing, cheerful, ignorant admiration.  She did not look up at
him, but she knew precisely the aspect of
his face, vacuous with fatigue and faintly colored with an absent and conscientious interest in her art.  He did not
speak.  She turned sharply about to have
the incident over with, and saw him


<pb n="545"/>

sitting as she had last noticed him, but
with his head now hanging completely
on his shoulder.  It made him look like
a man who has been hanged.
</p><p>"Dick!" she called peremptorily.
</p><p>He did not stir.  Something about the
look of his hand, fallen from the chair-arm and hanging heavily &mdash;  She held
her breath, and heard stertorous gasps
that turned her faint.  She flung herself
toward the chair, and dropped back appalled at the blue-lipped mask of horror
which hung upon her husband's shoulder.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="part" n="3" id="d6"><head>III</head>

<p>AFTER the last desperate expedient
had been tried, it seemed to Frederika
that an hour of agonized suspense passed
before the doctor lifted his white head
from the sick man's breast.  In answer
to the haggard question in her eyes he
nodded and drew a long breath.
</p><p>"He'll pull through &mdash; this time!
He'll probably be conscious in a few
minutes.  Get around to this side.  He'll
want to see you first."
</p><p>Still with his eyes bent on the face of
the prostrate man, with one hand on the
heart and one on the pulse, he went on:
"I've been afraid of something of this
sort ever since he came to the post.  I
warned him about his heart only a few
months ago, and told him to keep as
quiet as he could, but he &mdash;"
</p><p>The woman interrupted him, a keen
edge of apprehension in her voice.
"Oh, doctor, it won't mean his having to
give up and go back to Washington or
New York?  It would break his heart to
give up his active life!  He's all soldier,
you know!"
</p><p>She spoke with an accent of pride
which broke into a yearning quiver as
she continued: "But, oh, what does it
matter now that he's safe!  Now that I
have him again!  Oh, doctor, don't let
him die!  He's all that I have in the
world."
</p><p>This last she said in a tone of such
simple and heartfelt conviction that the
doctor found no answer to make, and
they sat silent, one on each side of the
sick man.
</p><p>The fire blazing high at his feet threw
a strong flickering light into every corner
of the disordered room, littered with
sick-room appliances assembled in the
most frenzied haste.  The piano, as almost the only article of furniture besides the chairs, was laden with a
strange array.  Basins of hot water with
cloths hanging over the side, a heap of
broken ice, an overturned bottle from
whose open mouth a thick black liquid
was dripping slowly upon the keys, a
pile of wet flannel rags still sending up
faint wisps of steam, and a broken flask
of ammonia whose contents had left a
white trail across the polished wood.
</p><p>Frederika's hair hung in a disordered
maze about her shoulders.  Her hands,
swollen and red with manipulating hot
cloths, were clasped across her breast as
though to keep her heart in her bosom,
and her deep eyes never for a moment
left her husband's face.
</p><p>The bluish tinge was gradually fading from his lips.  As his countenance
relaxed into lines of peace she bent over
him in a frenzy of attention, but when
he opened his eyes and looked at her
recognizingly, she began to cry quietly,
like a little child.
</p><p>He put out his hand weakly, his first
impulse being to comfort her.
</p><p>"Don't cry, Freddie, dear," he whispered.  "I won't do it if you don't like
to have me &mdash;"
</p><p>He stopped, his voice failing him,
suddenly realizing his situation and trying vainly to lift his head.  His wife
caught up his hand and held it to her
lips, as the doctor came briskly to the
explanation.
</p><p>"Don't stir, old man.  We've had
trouble enough with you as it is.  You've
had one of those attacks I prophesied to
you.  It's come, but you're none the
worse for it, thanks to about the hardest
two hours I ever put in &mdash; but mostly
thanks to your wife.  She's missed her
vocation.  She should have been a
trained nurse."
</p><p>The sick man smiled, his swollen lips
twisting in a grotesque and pathetic
grimace.
</p><p>"There's nothing she can't do,
doctor."  And then with a sudden accent of horror, "Oh, Freddie, darling,
what have you done to your piano?  It'll
be ruined!"
</p><p>He tried to raise himself, a distracted
anxiety in his voice.
</p><p>The fire blazed high and in a flickering

<pb n="546"/>

leap brought the wild confusion of
the instrument close to them.  The
musician surveyed it for a moment with
unseeing eyes &mdash; blank and inattentive.
Then she turned back impatiently to her
husband, put her arms about him, and
still sobbing a little, laid her head on
his shoulder.  A moment later she sought
blindly for his lips and kissed his
feverish, swollen mouth with so profound a fervor that the doctor turned
away.
</p><p>"Come, Mrs. Farrington," he said as
he came back to the hearth, "pleasurable
emotions won't hurt our patient, but we
mustn't let him worry.  The piano's all
right, captain; and now, my dear lady, if
I may have a glass of just plain cold
water I guarantee to have him ready for
bed in half an hour.  These attacks pass
as quickly as they come."
</p><p>The woman rose alertly from her
knees and went to the door.  As she
passed the piano her skirt caught on a
pail of water standing near the stool,
and stooping to free herself she brushed
one hand against the keys.  At the touch
she stood suddenly erect, electrified,
looking at the piano as though she saw
it for the first time.
</p><p>"Oh!" she said in a low tone, with
a sharp, indrawn breath, and she gazed
at it with a fierce attention.  Her voice
went up an octave.  <hi rend="italic">"Oh!"</hi> she cried
with an enigmatic intonation, and turning, she fixed her eyes on her husband
with a strange and ambiguous expression
of wonder.  She looked at the piano
again, and then going swiftly to the fire,
she knelt by the sick man and taking his
large square hand in hers she kissed it.
</p><p>The doctor followed her out of the
room with his eyes.  "Captain Farrington, heart failure or not, I envy you.
Through all the excitement of the last
two hours the thought which has been
uppermost in my mind has been that you
are a very lucky man.  It's positive
cruelty to show a loveless old bachelor
such depths of affection!  It makes me
feel as though I were dying of cold in
sight of a blazing fire."
</p><p>The soldier smiled humbly.  "What
she ever saw in me &mdash;"
</p><p>"It's not only what she saw in you
then, it's what she continues to see in
you now.  You don't begin to deserve it
&mdash; and yet somehow you must!  I'd
never dare to marry a woman like that.
I'd be sure I never could keep her affection.  Good God!  To see her look at
you as you were coming to &mdash; after ten
years of married life!"
</p><p>Captain Farrington spoke with a
grave and boyish solemnity.  "You
can't know what it is &mdash; no man who is
not married can!  It's not just the passion of a moment of anxiety.  It's the
never-wavering, never-faltering quality
of a true woman's love.  A man who is
married to a good woman who loves him
is in a haven of peace which heaven
can't better.  The surety of it &mdash; the
blessed certainty!"
</p><p>The doctor rose to his feet and began
dropping the bottles in his medicine-case
back to their sockets.
</p><p>"Yes, I know," he quoted sententiously in the tone of one who utters a
self-evident axiomatic truth.  "'Man's
love is of man's life a thing apart; 'tis
woman's whole existence!'"
</p>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
