<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CheGoop"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="CheGoop">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Goophered Grapevine</title>
<title type="sort">goophered grapevine</title>
<author>Chesnutt, Charles Waddell, 1858-1932</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">28</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CheGoop</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475804</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Goophered Grapevine</title>
<title type="sort">goophered grapevine</title>
<author>Charles W. Chesnutt</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<date value="1887">1887</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>60</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 254-260</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>All dates in letters have been standardized in the yyyymmdd
format.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text
Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of
the text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in
SpeFQue1 for page one of Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
<p>The N attribute for each DIV carries a composite of its value and
the value of the DIV one level up. For example, the N attribute for
the second DIV1 in the first DIV0 will have the value "1.2".</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1887">1887</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-03">March 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Timothy Jarrett</name>
</respStmt>
<item>minimal TEI markup</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<pb n="254"/>
<p>ABOUT ten years ago my wife was in poor health, and our family
doctor, in whose skill and honesty I had implicit confidence, advised a
change of climate.  I was engaged in grape-culture in northern Ohio, and
decided to look for a locality suitable for carrying on the same business
in some Southern State.  I wrote to a cousin who had gone into the
turpentine business in central North Carolina, and he assured me that no
better place could be found in the South than the State and neighborhood
in which he lived: climate and soil were all that could be asked for, and
land could be bought for a mere song.  A cordial invitation to visit him
while I looked into the matter was accepted.  We found the weather
delightful at that season, the end of the summer, and were most
hospitably entertained.  Our host placed a horse and buggy at our
disposal, and himself acted as guide until I got somewhat familiar with
the country.</p>
<p>I went several times to look at a place which I thought might suit
me.  It had been at one time a thriving plantation, but shiftless
cultivation had well-night exhausted the soil.  There had been a vineyard
of some extent on the place, but it had not been attended to since the
war, and had fallen into utter neglect.  The vines &mdash; here partly supported
by decayed and broken-down arbors, there twining themselves among the
branches of the slender saplings which had sprung up among them &mdash;
grew in wild and unpruned luxuriance, and the few scanty grapes which
they bore were the undisputed prey of the first comer.  The site was
admirably adapted to grape-raising; the soil, with a little attention, could
not have been better; and with the native grape, the luscious
scuppernong, mainly to rely upon, I felt sure that I could introduce and
cultivate successfully a number of other varieties.</p>
<p>One day I went over with my wife, to show her the place.  We
drove between the decayed gate-posts &mdash; the gate itself had long since
disappeared &mdash; and up the straight, sandy lane to the open space where a
dwelling-house had once stood.  But the house had fallen a victim to the
fortunes of war, and nothing remained of it except the brick pillars upon
which the sills had rested.  We alighted, and walked about the place for
a while; but on Annie's complaining of weariness I led the way back to
the yard, where a pine log, lying under a spreading elm, formed a shady
though somewhat hard seat.  One end of the log was already occupied by
a venerable-looking colored man.  He held on his knees a hat full of
grapes, over which he was smacking his lips with great gusto, and a pile
of grape-skins near him indicated that the performance was no new
thing.  He respectfully rose as we approached, and was moving away,
when I begged him to keep his seat.</p>
<p>"Don't let us disturb you," I said.  "There's plenty of room for us
all." </p>

<pb n="255"/>
<p>He resumed his seat with somewhat of embarrassment.</p>
<p>"Do you live around here?" I asked, anxious to put him at his
ease.</p>
<p>"Yas, suh.  I lives des ober yander, behine de nex' san'-hill, on de
Lumberton plank-road."</p>
<p>"Do you know anything about the time when this vineyard was
cultivated?"</p>
<p>"Lawd bless yer, suh, I knows all about it.  Dey ain' na'er a man
in dis settlement w'at won' tell yer ole Julius McAdoo 'uz bawn an'
raise' on dis yer same plantation.  Is you de Norv'n gemman w'at's
gwine ter buy de ole vimya'd?"</p>
<p>"I am looking at it," I replied; "but I don't know that I shall care
to buy unless I can be reasonably sure of making something out of
it."</p>
<p>"Well, suh, you is a stranger ter me, en I is a stranger ter you, en
we is bofe strangers ter one anudder, but 'f I 'uz in yo' place, I wouldn'
buy dis vimya'd."</p>
<p>"Why not?" I asked.</p>
<p>"Well, I dunner whe'r you b'lieves in cunj'in er not, &mdash; some er de
w'ite folks don't, er says dey don't, &mdash; but de truf er de matter is dat dis
yer ole vimya'd is goophered."</p>
<p>"Is what?" I asked, not grasping the meaning of this unfamiliar
word.</p>
<p>"Is goophered, cunju'd, bewitch'."</p>
<p>He imparted this information with such solemn earnestness, and
with such an air of confidential mystery, that I felt somewhat interested,
while Annie was evidently much impressed, and drew closer to
me.</p>
<p>"How do you know it is bewitched?" I asked.</p>
<p>"I wouldn' spec' fer you ter b'lieve me 'less you know all 'bout de
fac's.  But ef you en young miss dere doan' min' lis'n'in' ter a ole
nigger run on a minute er two w'ile you er restin', I kin 'splain to yer
how it all happen'."</p>
<p>We assured him that we would be glad to hear how it all
happened, and he began to tell us.  At first the current of his memory --or imagination &mdash; seemed somewhat sluggish; but as his embarrassment
wore off, his language flowed more freely, and the story acquired
perspective and coherence.  As he became more and more absorbed in
the narrative, his eyes assumed a dreamy expression, and he seemed to
lose sight of his auditors, and to be living over again in monologue his
life on the old plantation.</p>
<p>"Ole Mars Dugal' McAdoo bought dis place long many years befo'
de wah, en I 'member well w'en he sot out all dis yer part er de
plantation in scuppernon's.  De vimes growed monst'us fas', en Mars
Dugal' made a thousan' gallon er scuppernon' wine eve'y year.</p>
<p>"Now, ef dey's an'thing a nigger lub, nex' ter 'possum, en
chick'n, en watermillyums, it's scuppernon's.  Dey ain' nuffin dat kin
stan' up side'n de scuppernon' fer sweetness; sugar ain't a suckumstance
ter scuppernon'.  W'en de season is nigh 'bout ober, en de grapes begin
ter swivel up des a little wid de wrinkles er ole age, &mdash; w'en de skin git
sof' en brown, &mdash; den de scuppernon' make you smack yo' lip en roll yo'
eye en wush fer mo'; so I reckon it ain' very 'stonishin' dat niggers lub
scuppernon'.</p>
<p>"Dey wuz a sight er niggers in de naberhood er de vimya'd.  Dere
wuz ole Mars Henry Brayboy's niggers, en ole Mars Dunkin McLean's
niggers, en Mars Dugal's own niggers; den dey wuz a settlement er free
niggers en po' buckrahs down by de Wim'l'ton Road, en Mars Dugal'
had de only vimya'd in de naberhood.  I reckon it ain' so much so
nowadays, but befo' de wah, in slab'ry times, er nigger didn' mine goin'
fi' er ten mile in a night, w'en dey wuz sump'n good ter eat at de yuther
een.</p>
<p>"So atter a w'ile Mars Dugal' begin ter miss his scuppernon's.
Co'se he 'cuse' de niggers er it, but dey all 'nied it ter de las'.  Mars
Dugal' sot spring

<pb n="256"/>  guns en steel traps, en he en de oberseah sot up nights
once't er twice't, tel one night Mars Dugal' &mdash; he 'uz a monst'us keerless
man &mdash; got his leg shot full er cow-peas.  But somehow er nudder dey
couldn' nebber ketch none er de niggers.  I dunner how it happen, but it
happen des like I tell yer, en de grapes kep' on a-goin des de
same.</p>
<p>"But bimeby ole Mars Dugal' fix' up a plan ter stop it.  Dey 'uz a
cunjuh 'ooman livin' down mongs' de free niggers on de Wim'l'ton
Road, en all de darkies fum Rockfish ter Beaver Crick wuz feared uv
her.  She could wuk de mos' powerfulles' kind er goopher, &mdash; could
make people hab fits er rheumatiz, er make 'em des dwinel away en die;
en dey say she went out ridin' de niggers at night, for she wuz a witch
'sides bein' a cunjuh 'ooman.  Mars Dugal' hearn 'bout Aun' Peggy's
doin's, en begun ter 'flect whe'r er no he couldn' git her ter he'p him
keep de niggers off'n de grapevimes.  One day in de spring er de year,
ole miss pack' up a basket er chick'n en poun'-cake, en a bottle er
scuppernon' wine, en Mars Dugal' tuk it in his buggy en driv ober ter
Aun' Peggy's cabin.  He tuk de basket in, en had a long talk wid Aun'
Peggy.  De nex' day Aun' Peggy come up ter de vimya'd.  De niggers
seed her slippin' 'roun', en dey soon foun' out what she 'uz doin' dere.
Mars Dugal' had hi'ed her ter goopher de grapevimes.  She sa'ntered
'roun' mongs' de vimes, en tuk a leaf fum dis one, en a grape-hull fum
dat one, en a grape-seed fum anudder one; en den a little twig fum here,
en a little pinch er dirt fum dere, &mdash; en put it all in a big black bottle,
wid a snake's toof en a speckle' hen's gall en some ha'rs fum a black
cat's tail, en den fill' de bottle wid scuppernon' wine.  W'en she got de
goopher all ready en fix', she tuk 'n went out in de woods en buried it
under de root uv a red oak tree, en den come back en tole one er de
niggers she done goopher de grapevimes, en a'er a nigger w'at eat dem
grapes 'ud be sho ter die inside'n twel' mont's.</p>
<p>"Atter dat de niggers let de scuppernon's 'lone, en Mars Dugal'
didn' hab no 'casion ter fine no mo' fault; en de season wuz mos' gone,
w'en a strange gemman stop at de plantation one night ter see Mars
Dugal' on some business; en his coachman, seein' de scuppernon's
growin' so nice en sweet, slip 'roun' behine de smoke-house, en et all
de scuppernon's he could hole.  Nobody didn' notice it at de time, but
dat night, on de way home, de gemman's hoss runned away en kill' de
coachman.  W'en we hearn de noos, Aun' Lucy, de cook, she up 'n say
she seed de strange nigger eat'n' er de scuppernon's behine de
smoke-house; en den we knowed de goopher had b'en er wukkin.  Den
one er de nigger chilluns runned away fum de quarters one day, en got
in de scuppernon's, en died de nex' week.  W'ite folks say he die' er de
fevuh, but de niggers knowed it wuz de goopher.  So you k'n be sho de
darkies didn' hab much ter do wid dem scuppernon' vimes.</p>
<p>"W'en de scuppernon' season 'uz ober fer dat year, Mars Dugal'
foun' he had made fifteen hund'ed gallon er wine; en one er de niggers
hearn him laffin' wid de oberseah fit ter kill, en sayin' dem fifteen
hund'ed gallon er wine wuz monst'us good intrus' on de ten dollars he
laid out on de vimya'd.  So I 'low ez he paid Aun' Peggy ten dollars fer
to goopher de grapevimes.</p>
<p>"De goopher didn' wuk no mo' tel de nex' summer, w'en 'long
to'ds de middle er de season one er de fiel' han's died; en ez dat lef'
Mars Dugal' sho't er han's, he went off ter town fer ter buy anudder.
He fotch de noo nigger home wid 'im.  He wuz er ole nigger, er de
color er a gingy-cake, en ball ez a hoss-apple on de top er his head.  He
wuz a peart ole nigger, do', en could do a big day's wuk.</p>
<p>"Now it happen dat one er de niggers on de nex' plantation, one er
ole

<pb n="257"/>  Mars Henry Brayboy's niggers, had runned away de
day befo', en tuk ter de swamp, en ole Mars Dugal' en some er de
yuther nabor w'ite folks had gone out wid dere guns en dere dogs fer ter
he'p 'em hunt fer de nigger; en de han's on our own plantation wuz all
so flusterated dat we fuhgot ter tell de noo han' 'bout de goopher on de
scuppernon' vimes.  Co'se he smell de grapes en see de vimes, an atter
dahk de fus' thing he done wuz ter slip off ter de grapevimes 'dout
sayin' nuffin ter nobody.  Nex' mawnin' he tole some er de niggers
'bout de fine bait er scuppernon' he et de night befo'.</p>
<p>"W'en dey tole 'im 'bout de goopher on de grapevimes, he 'uz dat
tarrified dat he turn pale, en look des like he gwine ter die right in his
tracks.  De oberseah come up en axed w'at 'uz de matter; en w'en dey
tole 'im Henry be'n eatin' er de scuppernon's, en got de goopher on 'im,
he gin Henry a big drink er w'iskey, en 'low dat de nex' rainy day he
take 'im ober ter Aun' Peggy's, en see ef she wouldn' take de goopher
off'n him, seein' ez he didn' know nuffin erbout it tel he done et de
grapes.</p>
<p>"Sho nuff, it rain de nex' day, en de oberseah went ober ter Aun'
Peggy's wid Henry.  En Aun' Peggy say dat bein' ez Henry didn' know
'bout de goopher, en et de grapes in ign'ance er de quinseconces, she
reckon she mought be able fer ter take de goopher off'n him.  So she
fotch out er bottle wid some cunjuh medicine in it, en po'd some out in a
go'd fer Henry ter drink.  He manage ter git it down; he say it tas'e like
whiskey wid sump'n bitter in it.  She 'lowed dat 'ud keep de goopher
off'n him tel de spring; but w'en de sap begin ter rise in de grapevimes
he ha' ter come en see her agin, en she tell him w'at e's ter do.</p>
<p>"Nex' spring, w'en de sap commence' ter rise in de scuppernon'
vime, Henry tuk a ham one night.  Whar'd he git de ham?  <hi rend="italic">I</hi>
doan know; dey wa'nt no hams on de plantation 'cep'n' w'at 'uz in de
smoke-house, but <hi rend="italic">I</hi> never see Henry 'bout de smoke-house.
But ez I wuz a-sayin', he tuk de ham ober ter Aun' Peggy's; en Aun'
Peggy tole 'im dat w'en Mars Dugal' begin ter prume de grapevimes, he
mus' go en take 'n scrape off de sap whar it ooze out'n de cut een's er
de vimes, en 'n'int his ball head wid it; en ef he do dat once't a year de
goopher wouldn' wuk agin 'im long ez he done it.  En bein' ez he fotch
her de ham, she fix' it so he kin eat all de scuppernon' he want.</p>
<p>"So Henry 'n'int his head wid de sap out'n de big grapevime des
ha'f way 'twix' de quarters en de big house, en de goopher nebber wuk
agin him dat summer.  But de beatenes' thing you eber see happen ter
Henry.  Up ter dat time he wuz ez ball ez a sweeten' 'tater, but des ez
soon ez de young leaves begun ter come out on de grapevimes de ha'r
begun ter grow out on Henry's head, en by de middle er de summer he
had de bigges' head er ha'r on de plantation.  Befo' dat, Henry had
tol'able good ha'r 'roun de aidges, but soon ez de young grapes begun
ter come Henry's ha'r begun ter quirl all up in little balls, des like dis
yer reg'lar grapy ha'r, en by de time de grapes got ripe his head look
des like a bunch er grapes.  Combin' it didn' do no good; he wuk at it
ha'f de night wid er Jim Crow<note n="1"><p>A small card, resembling a
curry-comb in construction, and used by negroes in the rural districts
instead of a comb</p></note>, en think he git it straighten' out, but in de
mawnin' de grapes 'ud be dere des de same.  So he gin it up, en tried
ter keep de grapes down by havin' his ha'r cut sho't.</p>
<p>"But dat wa'nt de quares' thing 'bout de goopher.  When Henry
come ter de plantation, he wuz gittin' a little ole an stiff in de j'ints.  But
dat summer he got des ez spry en libely ez any young nigger on de
plantation; fac' he got so biggity dat Mars Jackson, de oberseah,

<pb n="258"/>  ha' ter th'eaten ter whip 'im, ef he didn' stop cuttin'
up his didos en behave hisse'f.  But de mos' cur'ouses' thing happen' in
de fall, when de sap begin ter go down in de grapevimes.  Fus', when
de grapes 'uz gethered, de knots begun ter straighten out'n Henry's h'ar;
en w'en de leaves begin ter fall, Henry's ha'r begin ter drap out; en
w'en de vimes 'uz b'ar, Henry's head wuz baller 'n it wuz in de spring,
en he begin ter git ole en stiff in de j'ints ag'in, en paid no mo' tention
ter de gals dyoin' er de whole winter.  En nex' spring, w'en he rub de
sap on ag'in, he got young ag'in, en so soopl en libely dat none er de
young niggers on de plantation couldn' jump, ner dance, ner hoe ez
much cotton ez Henry.  But in de fall er de year his grapes begun ter
straighten out, en his j'ints ter git stiff, en his ha'r drap off, en de
rheumatiz begin ter wrastle wid 'im.</p>
<p>"Now, ef you'd a knowed ole Mars Dugal' McAdoo, you'd a
knowed dat it ha' ter be a mighty rainy day when he couldn' fine sump'n
fer his niggers ter do, en it ha' ter be a mighty little hole he couldn'
crawl thoo, en ha' ter be a monst'us cloudy night w'en a dollar git by
him in de dahkness; en w'en he see how Henry git young in de spring en
ole in de fall, he 'lowed ter hisse'f ez how he could make mo' money
outen Henry dan by wukkin' him in de cotton fiel'.  'Long de nex'
spring, atter de sap commence' ter rise, en Henry 'n'int 'is head en
commence fer ter git young en soopl, Mars Dugal' up 'n tuk Henry ter
town, en sole 'im fer fifteen hunder' dollars.  Co'se de man w'at bought
Henry didn' know nuffin 'bout de goopher, en Mars Dugal' didn' see no
'casion fer ter tell 'im.  Long to'ds de fall, w'en de sap went down,
Henry begin ter git ole again same ez yuzhal, en his noo marster begin
ter git skeered les'n he gwine ter lose his fifteen-hunder'-dollar nigger.
He sent fer a mighty fine doctor, but de med'cine didn' 'pear ter do no
good; de goopher had a good holt.  Henry tole de doctor 'bout de
goopher, but de doctor des laff at 'im.</p>
<p>"One day in de winter Mars Dugal' went ter town, en wuz
santerin' 'long de Main Street, when who should he meet but Henry's
noo marster.  Dey said 'Hoddy,' en Mars Dugal' ax 'im ter hab a
seegyar; en atter dey run on awhile 'bout de craps en de weather, Mars
Dugal' ax 'im, sorter keerless, like ez ef he des thought of it, &mdash; </p>
<p>"'How you like de nigger I sole you las' spring?'</p>
<p>"Henry's marster shuck his head en knock de ashes off'n his
seegyar.</p>
<p>"'Spec' I made a bad bahgin when I bought dat nigger.  Henry
done good wuk all de summer, but sence de fall set in he 'pears ter be
sorter pinin' away.  Dey ain' nuffin pertickler de matter wid 'im &mdash;
leastways de doctor say so &mdash; 'cep'n' a tech er de rheumatiz; but his ha'r
is all fell out, en ef he don't pick up his strenk mighty soon, I spec' I'm
gwine ter lose 'im."</p>
<p>"Dey smoked on awhile, en bimeby ole mars say, 'Well, a
bahgin's a bahgin, but you en me is good fren's, en I doan wan' ter see
you lose all de money you paid fer dat digger [sic]; en ef w'at you say is
so, en I ain't 'sputin' it, he ain't wuf much now.  I spec's you wukked
him too ha'd dis summer, er e'se de swamps down here don't agree wid
de san'-hill nigger.  So you des lemme know, en ef he gits any wusser
I'll be willin' ter gib yer five hund'ed dollars fer 'im, en take my
chances on his livin'.'</p>
<p>"Sho nuff, when Henry begun ter draw up wid de rheumatiz en it
look like he gwine ter die fer sho, his noo marster sen' fer Mars Dugal',
en Mars Dugal' gin him what he promus, en brung Henry home ag'in.
He tuk good keer uv 'im dyoin' er de winter, &mdash; give 'im w'iskey ter rub
his rheumatiz, en terbacker ter smoke, en all he want ter eat, &mdash; 'caze a
nigger w'at he could make a thousan' dollars a year off'n didn' grow on
eve'y huckleberry bush.</p>

<pb n="259"/>
<p>"Nex' spring, w'en de sap ris en Henry's ha'r commence' ter
sprout, Mars Dugal' sole 'im ag'in, down in Robeson County dis time;
en he kep' dat sellin' business up fer five year er mo'.  Henry nebber
say nuffin 'bout de goopher ter his noo marsters, 'caze he know he
gwine ter be tuk good keer uv de nex' winter, w'en Mars Dugal' buy
him back.  En Mars Dugal' made 'nuff money off'n Henry ter buy
anudder plantation ober on Beaver Crick.</p>
<p>"But long 'bout de een' er dat five year dey come a stranger ter
stop at de plantation.  De fus' day he 'uz dere he went out wid Mars
Dugal' en spent all de mawnin' lookin' ober de vimya'd, en atter dinner
dey spent all de evenin' playin' kya'ds.  De niggers soon 'skiver' dat he
wuz a Yankee, en dat he come down ter Norf C'lina fer ter learn de
w'ite folks how to raise grapes en make wine.  He promus Mars Dugal'
he cud make de grapevimes b'ar twice't ez many grapes, en dat de noo
wine-press he wuz a-sellin' would make mo' d'n twice't ez many gallons
er wine.  En ole Mars Dugal' des drunk it all in, des 'peared ter be
bewitched wit dat Yankee.  W'en de darkies see dat Yankee runnin'
'roun de vimya'd en diggin' under de grapevimes, dey shuk dere heads,
en 'lowed dat dey feared Mars Dugal' losin' his min'.  Mars Dugal' had
all de dirt dug away fum under de roots er all de scuppernon' vimes, an'
let 'em stan' dat away fer a week er mo'.  Den dat Yankee made de
niggers fix up a mixtry er lime en ashes en manyo, en po' it roun' de
roots er de grapevimes.  Den he 'vise' Mars Dugal' fer ter trim de vimes
close't, en Mars Dugal' tuck 'n done eve'ything de Yankee tole him ter
do.  Dyoin' all er dis time, mind yer, 'e wuz libbin' off'n de fat er de
lan', at de big house, en playin' kyards wid Mars Dugal' eve'y night; en
dey say Mars Dugal' los' mo'n a thousan' dollars dyoin' er de week dat
Yankee wuz a runnin' de grapevimes.</p>
<p>"W'en de sap ris nex' spring, ole Henry 'n'inted his head ez
yuzhal, en his ha'r commence' ter grow des de same ez it done eve'y
year.  De scuppernon' vimes growed monst's fas', en de leaves wuz
greener en thicker dan dey eber be'n dyowin my rememb'ance; en
Henry's ha'r growed out thicker dan eber, en he 'peared ter git younger
'n younger, en soopler 'n soopler; en seein' ez he wuz sho't er han's dat
spring, havin' tuk in consid'able noo groun', Mars Dugal' 'cluded he
wouldn' sell Henry 'tel he git de crap in en de cotton chop'.  So he kep'
Henry on de plantation.</p>
<p>"But 'long 'bout time fer de grapes ter come on de scuppernon'
vimes, dey 'peared ter come a change ober dem; de leaves wivered en
swivel' up, en de young grapes turn' yaller, en bimeby eve'ybody on de
plantation could see dat de whole vimya'd wuz dyin'.  Mars Dugal' tuck
'n water de vimes en done all he could, but 't wan' no use: dat Yankee
done bus' de watermillyum.  One time de vimes picked up a bit, en
Mars Dugal' thought dey wuz gwine ter come out ag'in; but dat Yankee
done dug too close unde' de roots, en prune de branches too close ter de
vime, en all dat lime en ashes done burn' de life outen de vimes, en dey
des kep' a with'in' en a swivelin'.</p>
<p>"All dis time de goopher wuz a-wukkin'.  W'en de vimes
commence' ter wither, Henry commence' ter complain er his rheumatiz,
en when de leaves begin ter dry up his ha'r commence' ter drap out.
When de vimes fresh up a bit Henry 'ud git peart agin, en when de
vimes wither agin Henry 'ud git ole agin, en des kep' gittin' mo' en mo'
fitten fer nuffin; he des pined away, en fine'ly tuk ter his cabin; en when
de big vime whar he got de sap ter 'n'int his head withered en turned
yaller en died, Henry died too, &mdash; des went out sorter like a cannel.  Dey
didn't 'pear ter be nuffin de matter wid 'im, 'cep'n de rheumatiz, but his
strenk des dwinel'

<pb n="260"/>
away 'tel he didn' hab ernuff lef' ter draw his bref.
De goopher had got de under holt, en th'owed Henry fer good en all dat
time.</p>
<p>"Mars Dugal' tuk on might'ly 'bout losin' his vimes en his nigger
in de same year; en he swo' dat ef he could git hold er dat Yankee he'd
wear 'im ter a frazzle, en den chaw up de frazzle; en he'd done it, too,
for Mars Dugal' 'uz a monst'us brash man w'en he once git started.  He
sot de vimya'd out ober agin, but it wuz th'ee er fo' year befo' de vimes
got ter b'arin' any scuppernon's.</p>
<p>"W'en de wah broke out, Mars Dugal' raise' a comp'ny, en went
off ter fight de Yankees.  He saw he wuz mighty glad dat wah come, en
he des want ter kill a Yankee fer eve'y dollar he los' 'long er dat
grape-raisin' Yankee.  En I 'spec' he would a done it, too, ef de
Yankees hadn' s'picioned sump'n, en killed him fus'.  Atter de s'render
ole miss move' ter town, de niggers all scattered 'way fum de plantation,
en de vimya'd ain' be'n cultervated sence."</p>
<p>"Is that story true?" asked Annie, doubtfully, but seriously, as the
old man concluded his narrative.</p>
<p>"It's des ez true ez I'm a-settin' here, miss.  Dey's a easy way ter
prove it: I kin lead de way right ter Henry's grave ober yander in de
plantation buryin'-groun'.  En I tell yer w'at, marster, I wouldn' 'vise
yer to buy dis yer ole vimya'd, 'caze de goopher's on it yit, en dey ain'
no tellin' w'en it's gwine ter crap out."</p>
<p>"But I thought you said all the old vines died."</p>
<p>"Dey did 'pear ter die, but a few ov 'em come out ag'in, en is
mixed in mongs' de yuthers.  I ain' skeered ter eat de grapes, 'caze I
knows de old vimes fum de noo ones; but wid strangers dey ain' no
tellin' w'at might happen.  I wouldn' 'vise yer ter buy dis
vimya'd."</p>
<p>I bought the vineyard, nevertheless, and it has been for a long time
in a thriving condition, and is referred to by the local press as a striking
illustration of the opportunities open to Northern capital in the
development of Southern industries.  The luscious scuppernong holds
first rank among our grapes, though we cultivate a great many other
varieties, and our income from grapes packed and shipped to the
Northern markets is quite considerable.  I have not noticed any
developments of the goopher in the vineyard, although I have a mild
suspicion that our colored assistants do not suffer from want of grapes
during the season.</p>
<p>I found, when I bought the vineyard, that Uncle Julius had
occupied a cabin on the place for many years, and derived a respectable
revenue from the neglected grapevines.  This, doubtless, accounted for
his advice to me not to buy the vineyard, though whether it inspired the
goopher story I am unable to state.  I believe, however, that the wages I
pay him for his services are more than an equivalent for anything he lost
by the sale of the vineyard.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
