<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="ChoOzem"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>


<TEI.2 id="ChoOzem">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Ozeme's Holiday</title>
<title type="sort">ozemes holiday</title>
<author>Chopin, Kate</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">19</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">ChoOzem</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475819</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Ozeme's Holiday</title>
<title type="sort">ozemes holiday</title>
<author>Kate Chopin</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Century Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1896-08">August, 1896</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>The Century Illustrated Monthly Magazine,
52 (n.s.30) (Aug. 1896): 629-31.</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Copy consulted: Alderman Library AP2.C4.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1896">1896</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction, prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-05">May 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Lorrie Chisholm, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia
Library System.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Minimal TEI tagging, removed unambiguous line-end hyphenation
and ran electronic spell-check.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="629"/>
<head>OZ&Egrave;ME'S HOLIDAY.</head>

<p>OZ&Egrave;ME often wondered why there was not a special dispensation
of providence to do away with the necessity for work.  There seemed
to him so much created for man's enjoyment in this world, and so
little time and opportunity to profit by it.  To sit and do nothing
but breathe was already a pleasure to Oz&egrave;me; but to sit in the
company of a few choice companions, including a sprinkling of
ladies, was even a greater delight; and the joy which a day's
hunting or fishing or picnicking afforded him is hardly to be
described.  Yet he was by no means indolent.  He worked faithfully
on the plantation the whole year long, in a sort of methodical way;
but when the time came around for his annual week's holiday, there
was no holding him back.  It was often decidedly inconvenient for
the planter that Oz&egrave;me usually chose to take his holiday during
some very busy season of the year.
</p><p>He started out one morning in the beginning of October.  He
had borrowed Mr. Laballi&egrave;re's buckboard and Padue's old gray mare,
and a harness from the negro S&eacute;v&eacute;rin.  He wore a light-blue suit
which had been sent all the way from St. Louis, and which had cost
him ten dollars; he had paid almost as much again for his boots;
and his hat was a broad-rimmed gray felt which he had no cause to
be ashamed of.  When Oz&egrave;me went &laquo;broading,&raquo; he dressed&mdash;well,
regardless of cost.  His eyes were blue and mild; his hair was
light, and he wore it rather long; he was clean shaven, and really
did not look his thirty-five years.
</p><p>Oz&egrave;me had laid his plans weeks beforehand.  He was going
visiting along Cane River; the mere contemplation thrilled him with
pleasure.  He counted upon reaching Fr&eacute;deaus' about noon, and he
would stop and dine there.  Perhaps they would ask him to stay all
night.  He really did not hold to staying all night, and was not
decided to accept if they did ask him.  There were only the two old
people, and he rather fancied the notion of pushing on to
Beltrans', where he would stay a night, or even two, if urged.  He
was quite sure there would be something agreeable going on at
Beltrans', with all those young people&mdash;perhaps a fish-fry, or
possibly a ball!
</p><p>Of course he would have to give a day to Tante Sophie and
another to Cousine Victoire; but none to the St. Annes unless
entreated&mdash;after St. Anne reproaching him last year with being a
<hi rend="italic">fain&eacute;ant</hi> for broading at such a season!  At Cloutierville,
where he would linger as long as possible, he meant to turn and
retrace his course, zigzagging back and forth across Cane River so
as to take in the Duplans, the Velcours, and others that he could
not at the moment recall.  A week seemed to Oz&egrave;me a very, very
little while in which to crowd so much pleasure.
</p><p>There were steam-gins at work; he could hear them whistling
far and near.  On both sides of the river the fields were white
with cotton, and everybody in the world seemed busy but Oz&egrave;me.
This reflection did not distress or disturb him in the least; he
pursued his way at peace with himself and his surroundings.
</p><p>At Lam&eacute;rie's cross-roads store, where he stopped to buy a
cigar, he learned that there was no use heading for Fr&eacute;deaus', as
the two old people had gone to town for a lengthy visit, and the
house was locked up.  It was at Fr&eacute;deaus' that Oz&egrave;me had intended
to dine.
</p><p>He sat in the buckboard, given up to a moment or two of
reflection.  The result was that he turned away from the river, and
entered the road that led between two fields back to the woods and
into the heart of the country.  He had determined upon taking a
short cut to the Beltrans' plantation, and on the way he meant to
keep an eye open for old Aunt Tildy's cabin, which he knew lay in
some remote part of this cut-off.  He remembered that Aunt Tildy
could cook an excellent meal if she had the material at hand.  He
would induce her to fry him a chicken, drip a cup of coffee, and
turn him out a pone of corn-bread, which he felt would be sumptuous
enough fare for the occasion.
</p><p>Aunt Tildy dwelt in the usual log cabin of one room, with its
chimney of mud and sticks and its shallow gallery formed by the
jutting of the roof.  In close proximity to the cabin was a small
cotton-field, which from a little distance looked like a field of
snow.  The cotton was bursting and overflowing foam-like from bolls
on the drying stalk.  On the lower branches it was hanging ragged
and tattered, and much of it had already fallen to the ground.
There were a few chinaberry-trees in the yard before the hut, and
under one of them an ancient and rusty-looking mule was eating corn
from a rude trough.  Some common

<pb n="630"/>
little creole chickens
were scratching about the mule's feet and snatching at the grains
of corn that occasionally fell from the trough.
</p><p>Aunt Tildy was hobbling across the yard when Oz&egrave;me drew up
before the gate.  One hand was confined in a sling; in the other
she carried a tin pan, which she let fall noisily to the ground
when she recognized him.  She was broad, black, and misshapen, with
her body bent forward almost at an acute angle.  She wore a blue
cottonade of large plaids, and a bandana awkwardly twisted around
her head.
</p><p>&laquo;Good land, man!  Whar you come from?&raquo; was her startled
exclamation at beholding him.
</p><p>&laquo;F'om home, Aunt Tildy; w'ere else do you expec'?&raquo; replied
Oz&egrave;me, dismounting composedly.
</p><p>He had not seen the old woman for several years&mdash;since she was
cooking in town for the family with which he boarded at the time.
She had washed and ironed for him, atrociously, it is true, but her
intentions were beyond reproach if her washing was not.  She had
also been clumsily attentive to him during a spell of illness.  He
had paid her with an occasional bandana, a calico dress, or a
checked apron, and they had always considered the account between
themselves square, with no sentimental feeling of gratitude
remaining on either side.
</p><p>&laquo;I like to know,&raquo; remarked Oz&egrave;me, as he took the gray
mare
from the shafts, and led her up to the trough where the mule was&mdash;
&laquo;I like to know w'at you mean by makin' a crop like that an' then
lettin' it go to was'e?  Who you reckon's goin' to pick that
cotton?  You think maybe the angels goin' to come down an' pick it
fo' you, an' gin it an' press it, an' then give you ten cents a
poun' fo' it, <hi rend="italic">hein?</hi>&raquo;
</p><p>&laquo;Ef de Lord don' pick it, I don' know who gwine pick it, Mista
Oz&egrave;me.  I tell you, me an' Sandy we wuk dat crap day in an' day
out; it's him done de mos' of it.&raquo;
</p><p>&laquo;Sandy?  That little&mdash;&raquo;
</p><p>&laquo;He ain' dat li'le Sandy no mo' w'at you ric'lec's; he 'mos'
a man, an' he wuk like a man too.  He wuk mo' 'an fittin' fo' his
strenk, an' now he layin' in dah sick&mdash;God A'mighty knows how sick.
An' me wid a risin' twell I 'bleeged to walk de flo' o' nights, an'
don' know ef I ain' gwine to lose de han' atter all.&raquo;
</p><p>&laquo;W'y, in the name o' conscience, you don' hire somebody to
pick?&raquo;
</p><p>&laquo;Whar I got money to hire?  An' you knows well as me ev'y
chick an' chile is pickin' roun' on de plantations an' gittin' good
pay.&raquo;
</p><p>The whole outlook appeared to Oz&egrave;me very depressing, and even
menacing, to his personal comfort and peace of mind.  He foresaw no
prospect of dinner unless he should cook it himself.  And there was
that Sandy&mdash;he remembered well the little scamp of eight, always at
his grandmother's heels when she was cooking or washing.  Of course
he would have to go in and look at the boy, and no doubt dive into
his traveling-bag for quinine, without which he never traveled.
</p><p>Sandy was indeed very ill, consumed with fever.  He lay on a
cot covered up with a faded patchwork quilt.  His eyes were half
closed, and he was muttering and rambling on about hoeing and
bedding and cleaning and thinning out the cotton; he was hauling it
to the gin, wrangling about weight and bagging and ties and the
price offered per pound.  That bale or two of cotton had not only
sent Sandy to bed, but had pursued him there, holding him through
his fevered dreams, and threatening to end him.  Oz&egrave;me would never
have known the black boy, he was so tall, so thin, and seemingly so
wasted, lying there in bed.
</p><p>&laquo;See yere, Aunt Tildy,&raquo; said Oz&egrave;me,
after he had, as was usual with him when in doubt, abandoned
himself to a little reflection; &laquo;between us&mdash;you an'
me&mdash;we got to manage to kill an' cook one o' those chickens
I see scratchin' out yonda, fo' I'm jus'about starved.  I reckon you
ain't got any quinine in the house?
No; I didn' suppose an instant you had.  Well, I'm goin' to give
Sandy a good dose o' quinine to-night, an' I'm goin' stay an' see
how that'll work on 'im.  But sun-up, min' you, I mus' get out o'
yere.&raquo;
</p><p>Oz&egrave;me had spent more comfortable nights than the one passed
in Aunt Tildy's bed, which she considerately abandoned to him.
</p><p>In the morning Sandy's fever was somewhat abated, but had not
taken a decided enough turn to justify Oz&egrave;me in quitting him
before noon, unless he was willing &laquo;to feel like a dog,&raquo; as he told
himself.  He appeared before Aunt Tildy stripped to the undershirt,
and wearing his second-best pair of trousers.
</p><p>&laquo;That's a nice pickle o' fish you got me in, ol' woman.  I
guarantee, nex' time I go abroad, 't ain't me that'll take any cut-off.  W'ere's that cotton-basket an' cotton-sack o' yo's?&raquo;
</p><p>&laquo;I knowed it!&raquo; chanted Aunt Tildy&mdash;&laquo;I knowed de Lord war
gwine
sen' somebody to holp me out.  He warn' gwine let de crap was'e
atter he give Sandy an' me de strenk to make hit.  De Lord gwine
shove you 'long de row, Mista Oz&egrave;me.  De Lord gwine give you
plenty mo' fingers an' han's to pick dat cotton nimble an' clean.&raquo;

<pb n="631"/>
</p><p>&laquo;Neva you min' w'at the Lord's goin' to do; go get me that
cotton-sack.  An' you put that poultice like I tol' you on yo'
han', an' set down there an' watch Sandy.  It looks like you are
'bout as helpless as a' ol' cow tangled up in a potato-vine.&raquo;
</p><p>Oz&egrave;me had not picked cotton for many years, and he took to it
a little awkwardly at first; but by the time he had reached the end
of the first row the old dexterity of youth had come back to his
hands, which flew rapidly back and forth with the motion of a
weaver's shuttle; and his ten fingers became really nimble in
clutching the cotton from its dry shell.  By noon he had gathered
about fifty pounds.  Sandy was not then quite so well as he had
promised to be, and Oz&egrave;me concluded to stay that day and one more
night.  If the boy were no better in the morning, he would go off
in search of a doctor for him, and he himself would continue on
down to Tante Sophie's; the Beltrans' was out of the question now.
</p><p>Sandy hardly needed a doctor in the morning.  Oz&egrave;me's
doctoring was beginning to tell favorably; but he would have
considered it criminal indifference and negligence to go away and
leave the boy to Aunt Tildy's awkward ministrations just at the
critical moment when there was a turn for the better; so he stayed
that day out, and picked his hundred and fifty pounds.
</p><p>On the third day it looked like rain, and a heavy rain just
then would mean a heavy loss for Aunt Tildy and Sandy, and Oz&egrave;me
again took to the field, this time urging Aunt Tildy before him to
do what she might with her one sound hand.
</p><p>&laquo;Aunt Tildy,&raquo; called out Oz&egrave;me to the bent old woman
moving
ahead of him between the white rows of cotton, &laquo;if the Lord gets me
safe out o' this ditch, 't ain't to-morrow I'll fall in anotha with
my eyes open, I bet you.&raquo;
</p><p>&laquo;Keep along, Mista Oz&egrave;me; don' grumble, don' stumble; de
Lord's a-watchin' you.  Look at yo' Aunt Tildy; she doin' mo' wid
her one han' 'an you doin' wid yo' two, man.  Keep right along,
honey.  Watch dat cotton how it fallin' in yo' Aunt Tildy's bag.&raquo;
</p><p>&laquo;I am watchin' you, ol' woman; you don' fool me.  You got to
work that han' o' yo's spryer than you doin', or I'll take the
rawhide.  You done fo'got w'at the rawhide tas'e like, I reckon&raquo;&mdash;a
reminder which amused Aunt Tildy so powerfully that her big negro
laugh resounded over the whole cotton-patch, and even caused Sandy,
who heard it, to turn in his bed.
</p><p>The weather was still threatening on the succeeding day, and
a sort of dogged determination or characteristic desire to see his
undertakings carried to a satisfactory completion urged Oz&egrave;me to
continue his efforts to drag Aunt Tildy out of the mire into which
circumstances seemed to have thrust her.
</p><p>One night the rain did come, and began to beat softly on the
roof of the old cabin.  Sandy opened his eyes, which were no longer
brilliant with the fever flame.  &laquo;Granny,&raquo; he whispered, &laquo;de rain!
Des listen, granny; de rain a-comin', an' I ain' pick dat cotton
yit.  W'at time it is?  Gi' me my pants&mdash;I got to go&mdash;&raquo;
</p><p>&laquo;You lay whar you is, chile alive.  Dat cotton put aside clean
and dry.  Me an' de Lord an' Mista Oz&egrave;me done pick dat cotton.&raquo;
</p><p>Oz&egrave;me drove away in the morning looking quite as spick and
span as the day he left home in his blue suit and his light felt
drawn a little over his eyes.
</p><p>&laquo;You want to take care o' that boy,&raquo; he instructed Aunt Tildy
at parting, &raquo;an' get 'im on his feet.  An', let me tell you, the
nex' time I start out to broad, if you see me passin' in this yere
cut-off, put on yo' specs an' look at me good, because it won't be
me; it'll be my ghos', ol' woman.&raquo;
</p><p>Indeed, Oz&egrave;me, for some reason or other, felt quite
shamefaced as he drove back to the plantation.  When he emerged
from the lane which he had entered the week before, and turned into
the river road, Lamerie, standing in the store door, shouted out:
</p><p>&raquo;<hi rend="italic">H&eacute;</hi>, Oz&egrave;me! you had good times yonda?  I
bet you
danced holes in the sole of them new boots.&raquo;
</p><p>&raquo;Don't talk, La&eacute;rie,&raquo; was Oz&egrave;me's rather
ambiguous reply,
as he flourished the remainder of a whip over the old gray mare's
sway-back, urging her to a gentle trot.
</p><p>When he reached home, Bod&eacute;, one of Padue's boys, who was
assisting him to unhitch, remarked:
</p><p>&raquo;How come you didn' go yonda down the coas' like you said,
Mista Oz&egrave;me?  Nobody didn' see you in Cloutierville, an' Mailitte
say you neva cross' de twenty-fo'-mile ferry, an' nobody didn' see
you no place.&raquo;
</p><p>Oz&egrave;me returned, after his customary moment of reflection:
</p><p>&raquo;You see, it's 'mos' always the same thing on Cane Riva, my
boy; a man gets tired o' that <hi rend="italic">&agrave; la fin</hi>.  This time I went
back in the woods, 'way yonda in the Fr&eacute;deau cut-off; kin' o'
campin' an' roughin' like, you might say.  I tell you, it was
sport, Bod&eacute;&raquo;
</p>

<signed><hi rend="italic">Kate Chopin.</hi></signed>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
