<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="ColCurr"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="ColCurr">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Massachusetts` Currency Reform Act (1749) / by Massachusetts</title>
<title type="sort">massachusetts currency reform act 1749 by massachusetts</title>
<author>Brock: Massachusetts</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Ronald Michener, University of Virginia</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">26</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">ColCurr</idno>
<date value="2000">2000</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2000 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475824</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>This text is part of the collection for the Leslie Brock Center for the Study of Colonial Currency.</p>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Massachusetts Currency Reform Act (1749)</title>
<title level="m">The acts and resolves, public and private, of the Province of the Massachusetts Bay: to which are prefixed the
charters of the province: with historical and explanatory notes, and an appendix</title>
<title type="sort">massachusetts currency reform act 1749</title>
<author>Massachusetts</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>12 pages</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Wright &amp; Potter</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
<date value="1749">1749</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Alderman Library, University of Virginia, Micfilm 7219</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Sources of Massachusetts legal history; no. 5</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Footnotes in the original text have not been included in this electronic version.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1749">1749</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2000-05">May, 2000</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Cynthia Filer, The Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<front id="d2">
<div1 type="introduction" id="d3">

<p>The text of the currency reform act,
reproduced below, can be found in <hi rend="italic">Acts and Resolves of the Province
of Massachusetts-Bay</hi>, Vol. III, pp. 430-441 or in Evans Imprints.
The act was passed on January 26, 1749.</p>
</div1>
</front>

<body id="d4">


<div1 type="resolution" id="d5">
	<head>AN ACT FOR DRAWING IN THE BILLS OF CREDIT OF
		THE SEVERAL DENOMINATIONS WHICH HAVE AT ANY TIME BEEN ISSUED BY THIS
		GOVERNMENT AND ARE STILL OUTSTANDING, AND FOR ASCERTAINING THE RATE OF
		COIN'D SILVER IN THIS PROVINCE FOR THE FUTURE.</head>
<pb n="430"/>

<p>WHEREAS the sum of one hundred and eighty-three thousand six hundred
and forty-nine pounds two shillings and sevenpence halfpenny sterling
money, has been  granted by the
parliament
of Great Britain, for reimbursing to this province their expences in
taking and securing Cape Breton, &mdash; </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Be it enacted by the Governour, Council and House of
Representatives.</hi> </p>

<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d6">
<head>[SECT. 1.]</head>
<p>That the Honourable Sir Peter Warren, Knight of the Bath, William
Bollan, Esq., agent for this province, and Eliakim Palmer, Esq., of
London, merchant, they or two of them, &mdash; the said William Bollan,
agent, as aforesaid, except in case of his death, always to be one, &mdash;
be and are hereby authorized and impowred to give a full discharge to
the right honourable the lords commissioners of the treasury, for the
sum granted as aforesaid, whensoever the same shall have been issued; or
to the Bank of England, in case the same shall have been there
deposited; or to any person or persons in whose possession or custody
soever the same is or shall be; to prefer the humble address of the
general court of this province to the king's most excellent majesty,
that he would be graciously pleased to order the said sum to be
transported to this government in foreign coin'd silver, on board some
one or more of his majesty's ships; and to pursue such instructions as
the said general court shall judge necessary concerning the
transportation of the said granted sum to this province.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">And be it further enacted</hi>,</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d7">
<head>[SECT. 2.]</head>
<p>That the treasurer of the province for the time being, be and hereby
is fully authorized and impowred to demand and receive the whole and
every part of the money aforesaid from the commander of any vessel or
vessels on board of which the same shall be ship'd, upon the arrival
thereof within this government. </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">And be it further enacted</hi>,</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="3" id="d8">
<head>[SECT. 3.]</head>
<p>That from and after the thirty-first day of March, which shall be in
the year of our Lord one thousand seven hundred and fifty, the possessor
and possessors of each and every of the bills of credit of this province
which shall then be outstanding, upon bringing such bill or bills to the
treasurer aforesaid, shall be intitled to and receive, in exchange for
every such bill or bills, silver at the rate following; viz., for change
of every such bill or bills, silver at the rate following; viz., for
every forty-five shillings in bills commonly known and understood by
bills of the old form and tenor, one piece of eight; and for every
eleven shillings and three pence in bills of the new form and tenor, and
also of the middle form and tenor, one piece of eight; and so
proportionably for a greater or less sum in the bills of each and any of
the forms and tenors aforesaid: <hi rend="italic">provided, nevertheless</hi>, that if the
possessors aforesaid shall not offer such bills in exchange within one
year from and after the said thirty-first day of March, one thousand
seven hundred and fifty, all right or claim to the redemption or
exchange thereof shall determine and cease.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Provided always</hi>, &mdash; </p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="4" id="d9">
<head>[SECT. 4.]</head>
<p>That such of the bills of credit of this province as shall be the
property of the inhabitants of Connecticut, New Hampshire and

<pb n="431"/>
Rhode Island, may and shall be redeemed or exchanged by the bills of
credit of each of those governments, respectively, that may be in the
hands of the inhabitants of this government; anything in this act to the
contrary notwithstanding. </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">And whereas</hi> all debts, dues, demands, bargains and contracts
whatsoever, unless otherwise specially agreed or contracted, are now
understood to be payable and may be discharged by the publick bills of
credit of this province; and upon any action or actions being brought in
the courts of judicature within this province, and judgment being made
upon such action, and execution issued; such execution may be now
satisfied and discharged by the publick bills of credit as aforesaid,
with the addition of a greater or less sum according to the time when
such debts were contracted, &mdash; </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Be it enacted</hi>,</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="5" id="d10">
<head>[SECT. 5.]</head>
<p>That from and after the thirty-first day of March, which shall be in
the year of our Lord one thousand seven hundred and fifty, all debts,
dues, demands, bargains and contracts payable in bills of credit as
aforesaid, shall be understood to be payable in coin'd silver only; and
all executions in consequence of any judgment of court in all actions
heretofore brought or that may at any time hereafter be brought for the
recovery of such debts, dues, demands, bargains and contracts made and
contracted as aforesaid, shall and may be then discharged by silver at
the rate following; viz., every forty-five shillings of such debts, dues
or demands which were payable or might be discharged by bills of the old
tenor, shall and may be discharged by one mill'd piece-of-eight, with
such addition, according to the time of contracting, as the laws of this
province do or shall require; and so proportionably of any debt or
demand of greater or less value.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">And whereas</hi> in and by the several clauses in the acts of
this government for issuing the public bills of credit, provision has
been made for drawing said bills into the publick treasury again by
certain taxes which it is provided by said acts shall be laid on the
several towns in this government in each of the several years from this
present year until the year one thousand seven hundred and sixty, &mdash;</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Be it further enacted</hi>,</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="6" id="d11">
<head>[SECT. 6.]</head>
<p>That the several clauses in the acts aforesaid, providing for the
bringing into the province treasury, by taxes, the several sums, in
bills of credit issued by virtue of such acts, be and hereby are
repealed, and declared null and void. </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">And whereas</hi> the sum granted by parliament as aforesaid, may
prove insufficient to redeem or exchange the whole sum which is now
outstanding in said bills of credit, at the rates aforesaid, &mdash;</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Be it further enacted</hi>,</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="7" id="d12">
<head>[SECT. 7.]</head>
<p>That there be and hereby is granted unto his most excellent majesty,
a tax of seventy-five pounds, to be levied on polls, and estates both
real and personal, within this province, according to such rules and in
such proportions on the several towns and districts within the same, as
shall be agreed upon and ordered by this court at their session in May,
one thousand seven hundred and forty-nine, to be paid into the publick
treasury on or before the last of December then next ensuing; and the
tax aforesaid is hereby declared to be payable in bills of the new form
and tenor, or of the middle form and tenor, according to their
respective denominations, or in bills of the old

<pb n="432"/>
tenor, accounting four
for one, or in Spanish mill'd dollars at the Rate of eleven Shillings
and three Pence each.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">And be it further enacted,</hi></p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="8" id="d13">
<head>[SECT. 8.]</head>
<p>That in case the general court shall not
at their sessions in May and before the twentieth of June, one thousand
seven hundred and forty-nine, agree and conclude upon an act
apportioning the sum which by this act is engaged shall be in said year
apportioned assessed and levied, that then and in such case each town
and district within this province shall pay, by a tax to be levied on
the polls, and estates both real and personal, within their districts) the
same proportion of the said sum as the said towns and districts shall
have been taxed by the general court in the tax-act then last
preceeding; and the province treasurer is hereby fully impowred and
directed some time in the month of June in the year one thousand seven
Hundred and forty nine, to issue and send forth his warrants directed to
the selectmen or assessors of each town and district within this
province, requiring them to assess the polls, and estates both real and
personal, within their several towns and districts for their respective
part and proportion of the sum before directed, and engaged to be
assessed, and the assessors as

<pb n="433"/>
also persons assessed, shall observe, be
governed by and subject to all such rules and directions as shall have
been given in the last preceeding tax-act; and if their be any
surplusage it shall remain a stock in the treasury. </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">And whereas</hi> it is provided by this act that the whole sum now
outstanding in bills of credit which have been the medium and instrument
of trade and commerce for many years past, shall be sunk, partly by a
tax, and partly by being exchanged for the sum granted by parliament as
aforesaid,&mdash;which sum may prove sufficient to serve as a medium instead
of said bills,&mdash;and it being of great importance that all possible means
should be us'd for establishing an invariable silver currency for the
future: </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Be it enacted,</hi></p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="9" id="d14">
<head>[SECT. 9.]</head>
<p>That all bargains and contracts, debts and dues
whatsoever which shall be agreed, contracted or made after the
thirty-first day of March, one thousand seven hundred and fifty, shall be
understood

<pb n="434"/>
and are hereby declared to be in silver at six shillings and
eightpence per ounce, and all Spanish mill'd pieces of eight, of full
weight, shall be accounted taken and paid at the rate of six shillings
per piece, for the discharge of any contracts or bargains to be made
after the said thirty-first day of March, one thousand seven hundred and
fifty, the half's quarters and other less pieces of the same coin, to be
accounted received taken or paid in the same proportion; and if any
person shall for the discharge of any such contracts or bargains account
receive, take or pay any silver coin, or any of the said pieces at any
greater or higher rate than that at which the same is hereby regulated
and allowed, every such person so accounting, receiving, taking or paying
the same, shall forfeit the sum of fifty pounds for every offence, one
moiety thereof to his majesty, his heirs and successors, to and for the
use of this government, the other moiety to him or them that shall sue
for the same, to be recovered with full costs of suit, by action of debt,
bill, plaint, or information, in any of his majesty's courts of record
within this province, or by presentment of the grand jury; and all
persons whatsoever are hereby required to conform their books and
accounts according to the regulation aforesaid, any former usage to the
contrary notwithstanding; and any books and accounts which shall not be
made to conform to the said regulation, shall not be admitted or allowed
to be produced in evidence for the recovery of any debt in any of his
majesty's courts within this province.</p>

<pb n="435"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">And whereas</hi> bills of credit have been the only medium of
trade within this government for many years past, and the bills of
Connecticut, New Hampshire and Rhode Island, have passed promiscuously
with the bills of this government, and the inhabitants of this
government will be liable to greater evils than they have ever yet
suffered if the bills of those governments continue current within this
province,&mdash; </p>

<pb n="436"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">Be it further enacted</hi>,</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="10" id="d15">
<head>[SECT. 10.]</head>
<p>That if any person, from and after the thirty-first day of March, one
thousand seven hundred and fifty, shall account, receive, take or pay
any bill or bills of credit of either of the governments of Connecticut,
New Hampshire or Rhode Island, in discharge of any contract or bargain,
or for any valuable consideration whatsoever, every such person so
accounting, receiving, taking or paying the same, shall forfeit the sum
of fifty pounds for every offence, to be recovered and applied in like
manner with the forfeiture or penalty for receiving or paying silver
coin at a higher rate than is regulated by this act.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">And be it further enacted</hi>, </p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="11" id="d16">
<head>[SECT. 11.]</head>
<p>That from and after the last day of March, which shall be in the year
of our Lord one thousand seven hundred and fifty, until the last day of
March, which shall be in the year of our Lord one thousand seven hundred
and fifty-four, every person who shall be chosen to serve in any office
in any of the towns of this province, shall, before his entrance upon
said office, take the following oath, to be administered by a justice of
the peace, or where no justice of the peace shall be present, by the
town clerk, who is hereby impowred to administer the same; viz: &mdash; </p>

<p>You, A.B., do, in the presence of God, solemnly declare, that you
have not, since the last day of March, 1750, wittingly and willingly,
directly or indirectly,

<pb n="437"/>
either by yourself or any for or under you, been
concerned in receiving or paying, within this government, any bill or
bills of credit of either of the governments of Connecticut, New
Hampshire or Rhode Island. So help you God. </p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="12" id="d17">
<head>[SECT. 12.]</head>
<p>And where any person chosen as aforesaid, shall refuse or neglect to
take the oath aforesaid on tendering the same, the town shall proceed to
the choice of another person in his room; and where any person shall be
elected during the term aforesaid, by any town into any office, to the
non-acceptance or refusal whereof a penalty is by law annexed, such
person neglecting or refusing to take the oath aforesaid, shall be
liable to the same penalty as is by law provided for the non-acceptance
or refusal of such office.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">And be it further enacted</hi>,</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="13" id="d18">
<head>[SECT. 13.]</head>
<p>That when any person, during the term aforesaid, shall be chosen to
represent any town within this province, in the general court or
assembly, such person so chosen shall take the oath aforesaid, and
return shall be made by the selectmen upon the back of the precept, that
the person so chosen has taken the oath required in the act made and
passed in the twenty-second year of his majesty King George the second,
intitled, &ldquo;An act for drawing in the bills of credit of the several
denominations which have at any time been issued by this government, and
are still outstanding, and for ascertaining the rate of coin'd silver in
this province for the future;&rdquo; and if any person so chosen shall
refuse or neglect to take the oath aforesaid, such refusal or neglect
shall

<pb n="438"/>
be deem'd a refusal to serve as a representative, and the town
shall proceed to the choice of another person in his room.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">And be it further enacted</hi>,</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="14" id="d19">
<head>[SECT. 14.]</head>
<p>That the oath aforesaid shall be administered to each of the members
of his majesty's council every year during the term aforesaid, at the
same time when the usual oaths required to be taken by the said members
of his majesty's council shall be administered; and all officers, civil
and military, within this government, who shall be nominated or
appointed during the term aforesaid, shall, before they receive their
respective commissions, take the oath aforesaid, and their respective
commissions shall otherwise be void; and all persons elected into any
office during the term aforesaid, by the general assembly, shall be
deem'd not qualified to enter upon the execution of their respective
offices until they have taken the oath aforesaid; and all officers,
civil and military, appointed by this government, who shall be in
commission in the month of June, one thousand seven hundred and
fifty-three, shall, some time in said month, take the oath aforesaid;
and in case of neglect thereof, their respective commissions shall
become and are hereby declared to be void.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">And be it further enacted,</hi></p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="15" id="d20">
<head>[SECT. 15.]</head>
<p>That no execution shall be issued, during the term aforesaid, from
the office of any clerk of any of the inferiour courts of common pleas,
or of the superiour courts of judicature, for any sum whatsoever, unless
the plaintiff or plaintiffs, suing in his or their own right, and

<pb n="439"/>
dwelling within this province, shall first take the oath aforesaid, and
certificate thereof shall be made on such execution; and if any
execution shall issue or go forth during the term aforesaid without such
certificate, the same shall be and is hereby declared to be void.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="16" id="d21">
<head>[SECT. 16.]</head>
<p>And no licence shall be granted to, nor any recognizance taken from,
any taverner, innholder or retailer, by the justices of any of the
courts of sessions within this province during the term aforesaid, until
such taverner, innholder or retailer shall have taken said oath in
presence of the court, or certificate of his having so done, from a
justice of peace, shall be presented to the court. </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Provided always</hi>, &mdash; </p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="17" id="d22">
<head>[SECT. 17.]</head>
<p>That when any inhabitant of this province shall be sued or have his
person or estate taken by mean process, or in execution, for any debt
contracted before the thirty-first day of March, one thousand seven
hundred and fifty, with any of the inhabitants of either of the

<pb n="440"/>
governments aforesaid, upon making oath that he was possess'd of any sum
in bills of credit of the government to which his creditor belongs,
before the said thirty-first day of March, one thousand seven hundred
and fifty, and has continu'd to be so possess'd, he shall have liberty
to tender the same; and the creditor shall be oblig'd to accept the same
towards payment or discharge of such debt, in like manner as if this act
had never pass'd.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Provided also, and it is accordingly to be understood</hi>, &mdash; </p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="18" id="d23">
<head>[SECT. 18.]</head>
<p>That if the bills of credit of said governments of Connecticut, New
Hampshire and Rhode Island, shall be drawn in and sunk, and the paper
currency of said governments shall be brought to an end, and cease, at
any time before the said thirty-first day of March, one thousand seven
hundred and fifty-four, then, and in such case, the three last
preceeding enacting clauses of this act shall become void and have no
further effect.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">And whereas</hi> the sum of one hundred and eighty-three thousand
six hundred and forty-nine pounds two shillings and sevenpence
halfpenny, sterling, granted by parliament as aforesaid, and the further
sum of seventy-five thousand pounds, now granted to be assess'd in bills
of credit in the year one thousand seven hundred and forty-nine, on the
polls and estates of the inhabitants of this province, are by this act
become the sole fund and security for the whole sum in bills of credit
outstanding, and in case the said sterling sum, granted as aforesaid, be
not imported into this province before the said thirty-first day of
March, one thousand seven hundred and fifty, the exchanging the bills of
credit as is above intended will be rendered impracticable, and, the
former funds or securities being made void, there will remain a fund for
seventy-five

<pb n="441"/>
thousand pounds only, and the remainder of the said bills
of credit will become of no value to the possessors:</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Be it therefore provided</hi>,</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="19" id="d24">
<head>[SECT. 19.]</head>
<p>And it is accordingly hereafter enacted, that if the sum granted by
parliament as aforesaid, shall not be received within this government on
or before the thirty-first day of March, one thousand seven hundred and
fifty, then, and in such case, the several acts of this province for
drawing in the said bills, and all and every part of said acts, shall be
and continue in full force, anything in this act to the contrary
notwithstanding, and all and every part of this act shall be void and
have no further effect. </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Saving always</hi>, that whereas the sum of one hundred and thirty
thousand five hundred pounds in said bills of credit, is engaged by said
acts to be drawn in by a tax in the year one thousand seven hundred and
forty-nine, and by this act provision is made for drawing seventy-five
thousand pounds, part of said sum only, in said year, which part of this
act may have had its effect, and the time will be elapsed for drawing in
the remaining part of said one hundred and thirty thousand five hundred
pounds,&mdash; </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Be it therefore hereby enacted and declared</hi>,</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="20" id="d25">
<head>[SECT. 20.]</head>
<p>That in such case the sum of fifty-five thousand five hundred pounds the
remaining part of said sum of one hundred and thirty thousand five
hundred pounds, shall be and hereby is added to the tax of thirty five
thousand pounds, engag'd to be assess'd in the year one thousand seven
hundred and fifty; and the inhabitants of this province shall be
assess'd for said sum at the same time and in like manner and proportion
as is by law provided that they shall be assess'd for said thirty-five
thousand pounds; and the treasurer is hereby required to issue his
warrants accordingly. [<hi rend="italic">Passed January </hi>26, 1748-49.</p>

</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
