<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CraKick"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="CraKick">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Kicking Twelfth</title>
<title type="sort">kicking twelfth</title>
<author>Crane, Stephen, 1871-1900</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">27</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CraKick</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475843</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Print source not available at time of tagging.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Kicking Twelfth</title>
<title level="j">Ainslee's Magazine, 6 August 1900</title>
<title type="sort">kicking twelfth</title>
<author>Stephen Crane</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Ainslee's Magazine</publisher>
<date value="1900-08">August 1900</date>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic TextCenter.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the
text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for
page one of Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-09">September, 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Tom Lukas</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Tagged according to TEI-2</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">



<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="47"/>
<head>THE KICKING TWELFTH<lb/>
BY STEPHEN CRANE<lb/>
Author of "The Red Badge of Courage," "The Open Boat," etc., etc.</head>

<p>THE Spitzenberg army was backed by traditions of centuries of victory.
In its chronicles, occasional defeats were not printed in italics, but were
likely to appear as glorious stands against overwhelming odds.  A
favorite way to dispose of them was to attribute them frankly to the
blunders of the civilian heads of government.  This was very good for the
army, and probably no army had more self-confidence.
</p><p>When it was announced that an expeditionary force was to be sent
to Rostina to chastise an impudent people, a hundred barrack squares
filled with excited men and a hundred sergeant-majors hurried silently
through the groups and succeeded in looking as if they were the
repositories of the secrets of empire.  Officers on leave sped joyfully
back to their harness, and recruits were abused with unflagging devotion
by every man from colonels to privates of experience.
</p><p>The Twelfth Regiment of the Line&mdash;the Kicking Twelfth&mdash;was
consumed with a dread that it was not to be included in the expedition,
and the regiment formed itself into an informal indignation meeting.  Just
as they had proved that a great outrage was about to be perpetrated,
warning orders arrived to hold themselves in readiness for active service
abroad in Rostina, in fact.  The barrack yard was in a flash transformed
into a blue and buff pandemonium, and the official bugle itself hardly
had the power to quell the glad disturbance.
</p><p>Thus it was that early in the spring the Kicking Twelfth&mdash;1,600 men
in service equipment&mdash;found itself crawling along a road in Rostina.
They did not form part of the main force, but belonged to a column of
four regiments of foot, two batteries of field guns, a battery of mountain
howitzers, a regiment of horse and a company of engineers.  Nothing had
happened.  The long column had crawled without amusement of any kind
through a broad green valley.  Big white farm houses dotted the slopes,
but there was no sign of man or beast, and no smoke came from the
chimneys.  The column was operating from its own base, and its general
was expected to form a junction with the main body at a given point.
</p><p>A squadron of the cavalry was fanned out ahead, scouting, and day
by day the trudging infantry watched the blue uniforms of the horsemen
as they came and went.  Sometimes there would sound the faint thuds of
a few shots, but the cavalry was unable to find anything to engage
seriously.
</p><p>The Twelfth had no record of foreign service, and it could hardly be
said that it had served as a unit in the great civil war when His Majesty
the King had whipped the Pretender.  At that time the regiment had
suffered from two opinions.  So that it was impossible for either side to
depend upon it.  Many men had deserted to the standard of the Pretender,
and a number of officers had drawn their swords for him.  When the
King, a thorough soldier, looked at the remnant he saw that they lacked
the spirit to be of great help to him in the tremendous battles which he
was waging for his throne.  And so this emaciated Twelfth was sent off
to a corner of the kingdom to guard a dockyard, where some of the
officers so plainly expressed their disapproval of this policy that the
regiment received its steadfast name, the Kicking Twelfth.
</p><p>At the time of which I am writing the Twelfth had a few veteran
officers and well-bitten sergeants, but the body of the regiment was
composed of men who had never heard a shot fired excepting on the rifle
range.  But it was an experience for which they longed and with it came
the moment for the corps' cry, "Kim up the Kickers"&mdash;there was not likely
to be a man who would not go tumbling after his leaders.
</p><p>Young Timothy Lean was a second lieutenant in the first company
of the third battalion, and just at this time he was pattering along at the
flank of the men, keeping a fatherly lookout for boots that hurt and packs
that sagged.  He was extremely bored.  The mere faraway sound of
desultory shooting was not war as he had been led to believe it.
</p><p>It did not appear that behind that freckled face and under that red
hair there was a mind which dreamed of blood.  He was not extremely
anxious to kill somebody, but he was very fond of soldiering&mdash;it had been
the
<pb n="48"/>
career of his father and of his grandfather&mdash;and he understood
that the profession of arms lost much of its point unless a man shot at
people, and had people shoot at him.  Strolling in the sun through a
practically deserted country might be a proper occupation for a divinity
student on a vacation, but the soul of Timothy Lean was in revolt at it.
Sometimes in the camp at night he would go morosely to the camp of the
cavalry and hear the infant subalterns laughingly exaggerate the comedy
side of adventures which they had had when out with small patrols far
ahead.  Lean would sit and listen in glum silence to these tales, and
dislike the young officers&mdash;many of them old military-school friends&mdash;for
having had experience in modern warfare.  "Anyhow," he said, savagely,
"presently you'll be getting into a lot of trouble, and then the Foot will
have to come along and pull you out.  We always do.  That's history."
</p><p>"Oh, we can take care of ourselves," said the cavalry, with good-natured understanding of his mood.
</p><p>But the next day even Lean blessed the cavalry, for excited troopers
came whirling back from the front, bending over their speeding horses
and shouting wildly and hoarsely for the infantry to clear the way.  Men
yelled at them from the roadside as courier followed courier, and from
the distance ahead sounded in quick succession six booms from field
guns.  The information possessed by the couriers was no longer precious.
Everybody knew what a battery meant when it spoke.  The bugles cried
out, and the long column jolted into a halt.  Old Colonel Sponge went
bouncing in his saddle back to steer the general, and the regiment sat
down in the grass by the roadside, and waited in silence.  Presently the
second squadron of the cavalry trotted off along the road in a cloud of
dust, and in due time old Colonel Sponge came bouncing back and
palavered his three majors and his adjutant.  Then there was a bit more
talk by the majors, and gradually through the correct channels spread
information, which in due time reached Timothy Lean.  The enemy,
5,000 strong, occupied a pass at the head of the valley some four miles
beyond.  They had three batteries well posted.  Their infantry was
intrenched.  The ground in their front was crossed and lined with many
ditches and hedges, but the enemy's batteries were so posted that it was
doubtful if a ditch would ever prove convenient as shelter for the
Spitzenberg infantry.  There was a fair position for the Spitzenberg
artillery 2,300 yards from the enemy.  The cavalry had succeeded in
driving the enemy's skirmishers back upon the main body, but of course
had only tried to worry them a little.  The position was almost
inaccessible on the enemy's right, owing to high, steep hills which had
been crowned by small parties of infantry.  The enemy's left, although
guarded by a much larger force, was approachable and might be flanked.
This was what the cavalry had to say, and it added briefly a report of two
troopers killed and five wounded.
</p><p>Whereupon, Major-General Richie, commanding a force of 7,500
men of His Majesty of Spitzenberg, set in motion with a few simple
words the machinery which would launch his army at the enemy.  The
Twelfth understood the orders when they saw the smart young aide
approaching old Colonel Sponge, and they rose as one man, apparently
afraid that they would be late.  There was a clank of accoutrements.  Men
shrugged their shoulders tighter against their packs, and thrusting their
thumbs between their belts and their tunics, they wriggled into a closer fit
with regard to the heavy ammunition equipment.  It is curious to note that
almost every man took off his cap and looked contemplatively into it as if
to read a maker's name.  Then they replaced their caps with great care.
There was little talking, and it was not observable that a single soldier
handed a token or left a comrade with a message to be delivered in case
he should be killed.  They did not seem to think of being killed; they
seemed absorbed in a desire to know what would happen, and what it
would look like when it was happening.  Men glanced continually at their
officers in a plain desire to be quick to understand the very first order that
would be given, and officers looked gravely at their men, measuring
them, feeling their temper, worrying about them.
</p><p>A bugle called: there were sharp cries; and the Kicking Twelfth was
off to battle.
</p><p>The regiment had the right of the line in the infantry brigade, and as
the men tramped noisily along the white road every eye was strained
ahead, but, after all, there was nothing to be seen but a dozen farms&mdash;in
short, a country-side.  It resembled the scenery in Spitzenberg; every man
in the Kicking Twelfth had often confronted a dozen such farms with a
composure which amounted to indifference.  But still down the road
there came galloping troopers, who delivered information to Colonel
Sponge and
<pb n="49"/>
then galloped on.  But in time the Twelfth came to
the top of a rise, and below them, on a plain, was the heavy black streak
of a Spitzenberg squadron, and back of the squadron loomed the gray
bare hill of the Rostina position.  There was a little of skirmish firing.
The Twelfth reached a knoll which the officers easily recognized as the
place described by the cavalry as suitable for the Spitzenberg guns.  The
men swarmed up it in a peculiar formation.  They resembled a crowd
coming off a race-track, but, nevertheless, there were no stray sheep.  It is
simply that the ground on which actual battles are fought is not like a
chessboard.  And after them came swinging a six-gun battery, the guns
wagging from side to side as the long line turned out of the road, and the
drivers using their whips as the leading guns scrambled at the hill.  The
halted Twelfth lifted its voice and spake amiably but with point to the
battery: "Go on, guns!  We'll take care of you.  Don't be afraid.  Give it to
them."  The teams&mdash;lead, swing and wheel&mdash;struggled and slipped over
the steep and uneven ground, and the gunners, as they clung to their
springless positions, wore their usual and natural air of unhappiness.
They made no reply to the infantry.  Once upon the top of the hill,
however, these guns were unlimbered in a flash, and directly the infantry
could hear the loud voice of an officer drawling out the time for the
fuses.  A moment later the first three-point-two bellowed out, and there
could be heard the swish and the snarl of a fleeting shell.  Colonel
Sponge and a number of officers climbed to the battery's position, but the
men of the regiment sat in the shelter of the hill like so many blind-folded people and wondered what they would have been able to see if
they had been officers.  Sometimes the shells of the enemy came
sweeping over the top of the hill and burst in great brown explosions in
the fields to the rear.  The men looked after them and laughed.  To the
rear could be seen also the mountain battery coming at a comic trot with
every man obviously in a deep rage with every mule.  If a man can put in
long service with a mule battery, and come out of it with an amiable
disposition, he should be presented with a medal weighing many ounces.
After the mule battery came a long, black, winding thing which was three
regiments of Spitzenberg infantry, and back of them and to the right was
an inky square, which was the remaining Spitzenberg guns.  General
Richie and his staff clattered up to the hill.  The blindfolded Twelfth sat
still.  The inky square suddenly became a long racing line.  The howitzers
joined their little bark to the thunder of the guns on the hill, and the three
regiments of infantry came on.  The Twelfth sat still.
</p><p>Of a sudden a bugle rang its warning, and the officers shouted.
Some used the old cry, "Attention!  Kim up the Kickers!" and the
Twelfth knew that it had been told to go in.  The majority of the men
expected to see great things as soon as they rounded the shoulder of the
hill, but there was nothing to be seen save a complicated plain and the
gray knolls occupied by the enemy.  Many company commanders in low
voices worked at their men and said things which do not appear in the
written reports.  They talked soothingly; they talked indignantly, and they
talked always like father.  And the men heard no sentence completely.
They heard no specific direction, these wide-eyed men.  They understood
that there was being delivered some kind of exhortation to do as they had
been taught, and they also understood that a superior intelligence was
anxious over their behavior and welfare.
</p><p>There was a great deal of floundering through hedges, a climbing of
walls, a jumping of ditches.  Curiously original privates try to find new
and easier ways for themselves instead of following the men in front of
them.  Officers had short fits of fury over these people.  The more
originality they possessed the more likely they were to become separated
from their companies.  Colonel Sponge was making an exciting progress
on a big charger.  When the first faint song of the bullets came from
above, the men wondered why he sat so high.  The charger seemed as tall
as the Eiffel Tower.  But if he was high in the air, he had a fine view, and
that is supposedly why people ascend the Eiffel Tower.  Very often he
had been a joke to them, but when they saw this fat old gentleman so
coolly treating the strange new missiles which hummed in the air, it
struck them suddenly that they had wronged him seriously, and a man
who could attain the command of a Spitzenberg regiment was entitled to
general respect.  And they gave him a sudden quick affection, an
affection that would make them follow him heartily, trustfully, grandly&mdash;this fat old gentleman, seated on a too-big horse.  In a flash, his touseled
gray head, his short, thick legs, even his paunch had become specially
and humorously endeared to them.  And this is the way of soldiers.
<pb n="50"/>
</p><p>But still the Twelfth had not yet come to the place where tumbling
bodies begin their test of the very heart of a regiment.  They backed
through more hedges, jumped more ditches, slid over more walls.  The
Rostina artillery had seemed to have been asleep, but suddenly the guns
aroused like dogs from their kennels and around the Twelfth there began
a wild, swift screeching.  There arose cries to hurry, to come on, and as
the rifle bullets began to plunge into them, the men saw the high,
formidable hills of the enemy's right, and perfectly understood that they
were doomed to storm them.  The cheering thing was the sudden
beginning of a tremendous uproar on the enemy's left.
</p><p>Every man ran, hard, tense, breathless.  When they reached the foot
of the hills they thought they had won the charge already, but they were
electrified to see officers above them waving their swords and yelling
with anger, surprise and shame.  With a long, murmurous outcry, the
Twelfth began to climb the hill.  And as they went and fell, they could
hear frenzied shouts.  "Kim up the Kickers."  The pace was slow.  It was
like the rising of a tide.  It was determined, almost relentless in its
appearance, but it was slow.  If a man fell, there was a chance that he
would land twenty yards below the point where he was hit.  The Kickers
crawled, their rifles in their left hands as they pulled and tugged
themselves up with their right hands.  Ever arose the shout, "Kim up the
Kickers."  Timothy Lean, his face flaming, his eyes wild, yelled it back as
if he was delivering the gospel.
</p><p>The Kickers came up.  The enemy&mdash;they had been in small force,
thinking the hills safe enough from attack&mdash;retreated quickly from this
preposterous advance, and not a bayonet in the Twelfth saw blood.
Bayonets very seldom do.
</p><p>The homing of this successful charge wore an unromantic aspect.
About twenty windless men suddenly arrived and threw themselves upon
the crest of the hill and breathed.  And these twenty were joined by
others and still others until almost 1,100 men of the Twelfth lay upon the
hilltop.  The regiment's track was marked by body after body, in groups
and singly.  The first officer&mdash;perchance, the first man&mdash;one never can be
certain&mdash;the first officer to gain the top of the hill was Timothy Lean, and
such was the situation that he had the honor to receive his colonel with a
bashful salute.
</p><p>The regiment knew exactly what it had done.  It did not have to
wait to be told by the Spitzenberg newspapers.  It had taken a formidable
position with the loss of about 500 men, and it knew it.  It knew, too, that
it was a great glory for the Kicking Twelfth, and as the men lay rolling on
their bellies, they expressed their joy in a wild cry.  "Kim up the
Kickers."  For a moment there was nothing but joy, and then suddenly
company commanders were besieged by men who wished to go down the
path of the charge and look for their mates.  The answers were without
the quality of mercy.  They were short, snapped quick words:
</p><p>"No, you can't."
</p><p>The attack on the enemy's left was sounding in great rolling
crashes.  The shells in their flight through the air made a noise as of red-hot iron plunged into water, and stray bullets nipped near the ears of the
Kickers.
</p><p>The Kickers looked and saw.  The battle was below them.  The
enemy was indicated by a long, noisy line of gossamer smoke, although
there could be seen a toy battery with tiny men employed at the guns.  All
over the field the shrapnel was bursting, making quick bulbs of white
smoke.  Far away two regiments of Spitzenberg infantry were charging,
and at the distance this charge looked like a casual stroll.  It appeared that
small black groups of men were walking meditatively toward the Rostina
entrenchments.
</p><p>There would have been orders given sooner to the Twelfth, but
unfortunately Colonel Sponge arrived on top of the hill without a breath
of wind in his body.  He could not have given an order to save the
regiment from being wiped off the earth.  Finally he was able to gasp out
something and point at the enemy.  Timothy Lean ran along the line
yelling to the men to sight at 800 yards, and like a slow and ponderous
machine, the regiment again went to work.  The fire flanked a great part
of the enemy's trenches.
</p><p>It could be said that there were only two prominent points of view
expressed by the men after their victorious arrival on the crest.  One was
defined in the exulting use of the corps' cry.  The other was a grief-stricken murmur which is invariably heard after a hard fight: "My God,
we're all cut to pieces!"
</p><p>Colonel Sponge sat on the ground and impatiently waited for his
wind to return.  As soon as it did, he arose and cried out, "Form up and
we'll charge again!  We will win this battle as soon as we can hit them!"
The shouts of the officers sounded wild like men yelling on shipboard in
a gale.  And the
<pb n="51"/>
obedient Kickers arose for their task.  It was
running down hill this time.  The mob of panting men poured over the
stones.
</p><p>But the enemy had not been at all blind to the great advantage
gained by the Twelfth, and they now turned upon them a desperate fire of
small arms.  Men fell in every imaginable way, and their accoutrements
rattled on the rocky ground.  Some landed with a crash, floored by some
tremendous blow; others dropped gently down like sacks of meal; with
others it would positively appear that some spirit had suddenly seized
them by the ankles and jerked their legs from under them.  Many officers
were down, but Colonel Sponge, stuttering and blowing, was still
upright.  He was almost the last man in the charge, but not to his shame,
rather to his stumpy legs.  At one time it seemed that the assault would be
lost.  The effect of the fire was somewhat as if a terrible cyclone was
blowing in the men's faces.  They wavered, lowering their heads and
shouldering weakly as if it were impossible to make headway against the
wind of battle.  It was the moment of despair, the moment of the heroism
which comes to the chosen of the war god.  The colonel's cry broke and
screeched absolute hatred.  Other officers simply howled, and the men
silent, debased, seemed to tighten their muscles for one last effort.  Again
they pushed against this mysterious power of the air, and once more the
regiment was charging.  Timothy Lean, agile and strong, was well in
advance, and afterward he reflected that the men who had been nearest to
him were an old grizzled sergeant, who would have gone to hell for the
honor of the regiment, and a pie-faced lad who had been obliged to lie
about his age in order to get into the army.
</p><p>There was no shock of meeting.  The Twelfth came down on a
corner of the trenches, and as soon as the enemy had ascertained that the
Twelfth was certain to arrive, they scuttled out, running close to the earth
and spending no time in glances backward.  In these days it is not
discreet to wait for a charge to come home.  You observe the charge, you
attempt to stop it, and if you find that you can't, it is better to retire
immediately to some other place.  The Rostina soldiers were not heroes,
perhaps, but they were men of sense.  A maddened and badly frightened
mob of Kickers came tumbling into the trench and shot at the backs of
fleeing men.  And at that very moment the action was won, and won by
the Kickers.  The enemy's flank was entirely crumpled, and, knowing
this, he did not await further and more disastrous information.  The
Twelfth looked at themselves, and knew that they had a record.  They sat
down and grinned patronizingly as they saw the batteries galloping to
advance positions to shell the retreat, and they really laughed as the
cavalry swept tumultuously forward.
</p><p>The Twelfth had no more concern with the battle.  They had won it,
and the subsequent proceedings were only amusing.
</p><p>There was a call from the flank, and the men wearily came to
attention as General Richie and his staff came trotting up.  The young
general, cold-eyed, stern and grim as a Roman, looked with his straight
glance at a hammered and thin and dirty line of figures which was His
Majesty's Twelfth Regiment of the Line.  When opposite old Colonel
Sponge, a pudgy figure standing at attention, the general's face set in still
more grim and stern lines.  He took off his helmet.  "Kim up the
Kickers," said he.  He replaced his helmet and rode off.  Down the
cheeks of the little fat colonel rolled tears.  He stood like a stone for a
long moment, and then wheeled in supreme wrath upon his surprised
adjutant.  "Delahaye, you damn fool, don't stand there staring like a
monkey.  Go tell young Lean I want to see him."  The adjutant jumped as
if he was on springs, and went after Lean.  That young officer presented
himself directly, his face covered with disgraceful smudges, and he had
also torn his breeches.  He had never seen the colonel in such a rage.
"Lean, you young whelp, you&mdash;you're a good boy."  And even as the
general had turned away from the colonel, the colonel turned away from
the lieutenant.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
