<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CraShra"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="CraShra">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Shrapnel of their Friends</title>
<title type="sort">shrapnel of their friends</title>
<author>Crane, Stephen, 1871-1900</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>Tom Lukas, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">16</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CraShra</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475850</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Shrapnel of Their Friends</title>
<title level="j">Ainslee's</title>
<title type="sort">shrapnel of their friends</title>
<author>Stephen Crane</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Ainslee's Magazine</publisher>
<date value="1900-05-05">5 May 1900</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp.303-305</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the
text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for
page one of Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-09">September 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Tom Lukas</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Tagged in accordance with TEI-2</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="story" id="d3">
	<pb n="303"/>
<head>THE SHRAPNEL OF THEIR FRIENDS<lb/>
BY STEPHEN CRANE</head>

<p>FROM far over the knolls came the tiny sound of a cavalry bugle
singing out the recall, and later, detached parties of His Majesty's
Second Hussars came trotting back to where the Spitzenbergen
infantry sat complacently on the captured Rostina position.  The
horsemen were well pleased, and they told how they had ridden
thrice through the helter-skelter of the fleeing enemy.  They had
ultimately been checked by the great truth that when an enemy runs
away in daylight he sooner or later finds a place where he fetches up
with a jolt and turns to face the pursuit&mdash;notably if it is a cavalry
pursuit.  The Hussars had discreetly withdrawn, displaying no
foolish pride of corps.</p>
    <p>There was a general admission that the Kicking Twelfth had
taken the chief honors of the day, but the Artillery added that if the
guns had not shelled so accurately the Twelfth's charge could not
have been made so successfully, and the three other regiments of
infantry, of course, did not conceal their feeling that their attack on
the enemy's left had withdrawn many rifles that otherwise would
have been pelting at the Twelfth.  The Cavalry simply said that but
for them the victory would not have been complete.</p>
    <p>Corps prides met each other face to face at every step, but the
Kickers smiled easily and indulgently.  A few recruits bragged, but
they bragged because they were recruits.  The older men did not
wish it to appear that they were surprised and rejoiced at the
performance of the regiment.  If they were congratulated they
simply smirked, suggesting that the ability of the Twelfth had long
been known to them and that the charge had been a little thing, you
know, just turned off in the way of an afternoon's work.  Major-General Richie encamped his troops on the position which they had
taken from the enemy.  Old Colonel Sponge, of the Twelfth,
redistributed his officers, and the losses had been so great that
Timothy Lean got command of a company.  It was not too much of
a company.  Forty-seven smudged and sweating men faced their
new commander.  The company had gone into action with a
strength of eighty-six.  The heart of Timothy Lean beat high with
pride.  He intended to be, some day, a general, and if he ever
became a general, that moment of promotion was not equal in joy to
the moment when he looked at his new possession of forty-seven
vagabonds.  He scanned the faces and recognized with satisfaction
one old sergeant and two bright young corporals.  "Now," said he to
himself, "I have here a snug little body of men with which I can do
something."  In him burned the usual fierce fire to make them the
best company in the regiment.  He had adopted them; they were his
men.  "I will do what I can for you," he said.  "Do you the same for
me."</p>
    <p>The Twelfth bivouacked on the ridge.  Little fires were built,
and there appeared among the men innumerable blackened tin-cups,
which were so treasured that a faint suspicion in connection with
the loss of one could bring on the grimmest of fights.  Meantime
certain of the privates silently re-adjusted their kits as their names
were called out by the sergeants.  These were the men condemned
to picket duty after a hard day of marching and fighting.  The dusk
came slowly, and the color of the countless fires, spotting the ridge
and the plain, grew in the falling darkness.  Far away pickets fired at
something.</p>
<p>One by one the men's heads were lowered to the earth until the
ridge was marked by two long, shadowy rows of men.  Here and
there an officer sat musing in his dark cloak with the ray of a
weakening fire gleaming on his sword hilt.  From the plain there
came at times the sound of battery horses moving restlessly at their
tethers, and one could imagine he heard the throaty grumbling curse
of the aroused drivers.  The moon dived swiftly through flying light
clouds.  Far away pickets fired at something.</p>
    <p>In the morning the infantry and guns
<pb n="304"/>
breakfasted to the music of a racket between the cavalry and the enemy which was
taking place some miles up the valley.  The ambitious Hussars had
apparently stirred some kind of a hornet's nest, and they were
having a good fight with no officious friends near enough to
interfere.  The remainder of the army looked toward the fight
musingly over the tops of tin cups.  In time the column crawled
lazily forward to see.  The Twelfth, as it crawled, saw a regiment
deploy to the right, and saw a battery dash to take position.  The
cavalry jingled back, grinning with pride and expecting to be greatly
admired.  Presently the Twelfth was bidden to take seat by the
roadside and await its turn.  Instantly the wise men&mdash;and there were
more than three&mdash;came out of the east and announced that they had
divined the whole plan.  The Kicking Twelfth was to be held in
reserve until the critical moment of the fight, and then they were to
be sent forward to win a victory.  In corroboration they pointed to
the fact that the general in command was sticking close to them in
order, they said, to give the word quickly at the proper moment.
And, in truth, on a small hill to the right Major-General Richie sat
his horse and used his glasses, while back of him his staff and the
orderlies bestrode their champing, dancing mounts.</p>
<p>It is always good to look hard at a general, and the Kickers
were transfixed with interest.  The wise men again came out of the
east and told what was inside the Richie head, but even the wise
men wondered what was inside the Richie head.
</p><p>Suddenly, an exciting thing happened.  To the left and ahead
was a pounding Spitzbergen battery, and a toy suddenly appeared
on the slope behind the guns.  The toy was a man with a flag&mdash;the
flag was white save for a square of red in the centre.  And this toy
began to wig-wag, wig-wag, and it spoke to General Richie under
the authority of the captain of the battery.  It said: "The Eighty-eighth are being driven on my centre and right."
</p><p>Now, when the Kicking Twelfth had left Spitzbergen there was
an average of six signal-men in each company.  A proportion of
these signalers had been destroyed in the first engagement, but
enough remained so that the Kicking Twelfth read, as a unit, the
news of the Eighty-eighth.  The word ran quickly.  "The eighty-eighth are being driven on my centre and right."
</p><p>Richie rode to where Colonel Sponge sat aloft, on his big
horse, and a moment later a cry rang along the column.  "Kim up
the Kickers."  A large number of the men were already in the road,
hitching and twisting at their belts and packs.  The Kickers moved
forward.
</p><p>They deployed and passed in a straggling line through the
battery and to the left and right of it.  The gunners called out to
them cheerfully, telling them not to be afraid.
</p><p>The scene before them was startling.  They were facing a
country cut up by many steep-sided ravines, and over the resultant
hills were retreating little squads of the Eighty-eighth.  The Twelfth
laughed in its exultation.  The men could now tell by the volume of
fire that the Eighty-eighth were retreating for reasons which were
not sufficiently expressed in the noise of the Rostina shooting.
Held together by the bugle, the Kickers swarmed up the first hill
and laid on its crest.  Parties of the Eighty-eighth went through their
lines, and the Twelfth told them coarsely its several opinions.  The
sights were clicked up to 600 yards, and with a crashing volley the
regiment entered its second battle.
</p><p>A thousand yards away on the right, the cavalry and a regiment
of infantry were creeping onward.  Sponge decided not to be
backward, and the bugle told the Twelfth to go ahead once more.
The Twelfth charged, followed by a rabble of rallied men of the
Eighty-eighth, who were crying aloud that it had been all a mistake.
</p><p>A charge in these days is not a running match.  Those splendid
pictures of leveled bayonets dashing at headlong pace towards the
closed ranks of the enemy are absurd as soon as they are mistaken
for the actuality of the present.  In these days charges are likely to
cover at least the half of a mile, and, to go at the pace exhibited in
the pictures, a man would be obliged to have a little steam engine
inside of him.
</p><p>The charge of the Kicking Twelfth somewhat resembled the
advance of a great crowd of beaters, who for some reason
passionately desired to start the game.  Men stumbled; men fell;
men swore.  There were cries: "This way!  Come this way!  Don't go
that way!  You can't get up that way."  Over the rocks the Twelfth
scrambled, red in the face, sweating and angry.  Soldiers fell
because they were struck by bullets and because they had not an
ounce of strength left in them.  Colonel Sponge, with a face like a
red cushion, was being dragged windless up the steps by devoted
and athletic men.  Three of the older captains lay afar back, and
<pb n="305"/>
swearing with their eyes because their tongues were
temporarily out of service.
</p><p>And yet&mdash;and yet the speed of the charge was slow.  From the
position of the battery, it looked as if the Kickers were taking a walk
over some extremely difficult country.
</p><p>The regiment ascended a superior height and found trenches
and dead men.  They took seat with the dead, satisfied with this
company until they could get their wind.  For thirty minutes, purple-faced stragglers re-joined from the rear.  Colonel Sponge looked
behind him and saw that Richie, with his staff, had approached by
another route, and had evidently been near enough to see the full
extent of the Kickers' exertions.  Presently Richie began to pick a
way for his horse toward the captured position.  He disappeared in a
gully between two hills.
</p><p>Now, it came to pass that a Spitzbergen battery on the far right
took occasion to mistake the identity of the Kicking Twelfth, and
the captain of these guns, not having anything to occupy him in
front, directed his six 3.2's upon the ridge where the tired Kickers
lay side by side with the Rostina dead.  A shrapnel, of course,
scattered forward, hurting nobody.  But a man screamed out to his
officer, "By God, sir, that is one of our own batteries."  The whole
line quivered with fright.  Five more shells streamed overhead, and
one flung its hail into the middle of the third battalion's line, and the
Kicking Twelfth shuddered to the very centre of its heart&mdash;and arose
like one man&mdash;and fled.
</p><p>Colonel Sponge, fighting, frothing at the mouth, dealing blows
with his fist right and left, found himself confronting a fury on
horseback.  Richie was as pale as death, and his eyes sent out
sparks.  "What does this conduct mean?" he flashed out from
between his fastened teeth.
</p><p>Sponge could only gurgle, "The battery&mdash;the battery&mdash;the
battery&mdash;"
</p><p>"The battery?" cried Richie in a voice which sounded like
pistol shots.  "Are you afraid of the guns you almost took yesterday?
Go back there, you white-livered cowards! you swine! you dogs!
curs! curs! curs!  Go back there!"
</p><p>Most of the men halted and crouched under the lashing tongue
of their maddened general.  But one man found desperate speech,
and he yelled: "General, it is our own battery that is firing on us!"
</p><p>Many say that the general's face tightened until it looked like a
mask.  The Kicking Twelfth retired to a comfortable place where
they were only under the fire of the Rostina artillery.  The men saw
a staff officer riding over the obstructions in a manner calculated to
break his neck directly.
</p><p>The Kickers were aggrieved, but the heart of the old colonel
was cut in twain.  He even babbled to his majors, talking like a man
who is about to die of simple rage.  "Did you hear what he said to
me?  Did you hear what he called us?  <hi rend="italic">Did you hear what he
called us?"</hi>
</p><p>The majors searched their minds for words to heal a deep
wound.
</p><p>The Twelfth received orders to go into camp upon the hill
where they had been insulted.  Old Sponge looked as if he were
about to knock the aide out of the saddle, but he saluted and took
the regiment back to the temporary companionship of the Rostina
dead.
</p><p>Major-General Richie never apologized to Colonel Sponge.
When you are a commanding officer you do not adopt the custom
of apologizing for the wrong done to your subordinates.  You ride
away.  And they understand and are confident of the restitution to
honor.  Richie never opened his stern young lips to Sponge in
reference to the scene near the hill of the Rostina dead, but in time
there was General Order No. 20, which spoke definitely of the
gallantry of His Majesty's Twelfth Regiment of the Line and its
colonel.  In the end Sponge was given a high decoration because he
had been badly used by Richie on that day.  Richie knew that it is
hard for men to withstand the shrapnel of their friends.  A few days
later the Kickers, marching in column on the road, came upon their
friend, the battery, halted in a field.  And they addressed the battery.
And the captain of the battery blanched to the tips of his ears.  But
the men of the battery told the Kickers to go to the devil&mdash;frankly&mdash;freely, placidly, told the Kickers to go to the devil.
</p><p>And this story proves that it is sometimes better to be a
private.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
