<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CraVete"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="CraVete">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Veteran</title>
<title type="sort">veteran</title>
<author>Crane, Stephen, 1871-1900</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">14</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CraVete</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475853</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Veteran</title>
<title type="sort">veteran</title>
<author>Stephen Crane</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The S. S. McClure Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>McClure's Magazine Illustrated.; Vol. VII; August,
1896; pp. 222-224</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Some dialect in dialogue, e.g., "our'n" for "our
own,"  "th'" for "the," "'em" for "them," "'peared" for "appeared,"
"medder" for "meadow," "fulness" for "fullness."</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions
for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1896-08">August, 1896</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-12">December, 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Bryson Clevenger, Jr.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Minimal TEI tagging, TEI header, Spell-checking against print
version</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head>
Crane, Stephen.  "The Veteran." <lb/> <hi rend="italic">McClure's</hi> 7 (Aug. 1896): 222-224.
<lb/>
 Author of "The Red Badge of Courage," "The Little Regiment," etc.
</head>
<pb n="222"/>


<p>
OUT of the low window could be seen three hickory trees placed
irregularly in a meadow that was resplendent in spring-time green.
Farther away, the old dismal belfry of the village church loomed
over the pines.  A horse meditating in the shade of one of the
hickories lazily swished his tail.  The warm sunshine made an
oblong of vivid yellow on the floor of the grocery.
</p><p>"Could you see the whites of their eyes?" said the man who was
seated on a soap-box.
</p><p>"Nothing of the kind," replied old Henry warmly.  "Just a lot
of flitting figures, and I let go at where they 'peared to be the
thickest.  Bang!"
</p><p>"Mr. Fleming," said the grocer&mdash;his deferential voice
expressed somehow the old man's exact social weight&mdash;"Mr. Fleming,
you never was frightened much in them battles, was you?"
</p><p>The veteran looked down and grinned.  Observing his manner,
the entire group tittered.  "Well, I guess I was," he answered
finally.  "Pretty well scared, sometimes.  Why, in my first battle
I thought the sky was falling down.  I thought the world was coming
to an end.  You bet I was scared."
</p><p>Every one laughed.  Perhaps it seemed strange and rather
wonderful to them that a man should admit the thing, and in the
tone of their laughter there was probably more admiration than if
old Fleming had declared that he had always been a lion.  Moreover,
they knew that he had ranked as an orderly sergeant, and so their
opinion of his heroism was fixed.  None, to be sure, knew how an
orderly sergeant ranked, but then it was understood to be somewhere
just shy of a major-general's stars.  So when old Henry admitted
that he had been frightened, there was a laugh.
</p><p>"The trouble was," said the old man, "I thought they were all
shooting at me.  Yes, sir, I thought every man in the other army
was aiming at me in particular, and only me.  And it seemed so
darned unreasonable, you know.  I wanted to explain to 'em what an
almighty good fellow <pb n="223"/>  I was, because I thought then they
might quit all trying to hit me.  But I couldn't explain, and they
kept on being unreasonable&mdash;blim!&mdash;blam!&mdash;bang!  So I run!"
</p><p>Two little triangles of wrinkles appeared at the corners of
his eyes.  Evidently he appreciated some comedy in this recital.
Down near his feet, however, little Jim, his grandson, was visibly
horror-stricken.  His hands were clasped nervously, and his eyes
were wide with astonishment at this terrible scandal, his most
magnificent grandfather telling such a thing.
</p><p>"That was at Chancellorsville.  Of course, afterward I got
kind of used to it.  A man does.  Lots of men, though, seem to fell
all right from the start.  I did, as soon as I 'got on to it,' as
they say now; but at first I was pretty flustered.  Now, there was
young Jim Conklin, old Si Conklin's son&mdash;that used to keep the
tannery&mdash;you none of you recollect him&mdash;well, he went into it from
the start just as if he was born to it.  But with me it was
different.  I had to get used to it."
</p><p>When little Jim walked with his grandfather he was in the
habit of skipping along on the stone pavement in front of the three
stores and the hotel of the town and betting that he could avoid
the cracks.  But upon this day he walked soberly, with his hand
gripping two of his grandfather's fingers.  Sometimes he kicked
abstractedly at dandelions that curved over the walk.  Any one
could see that he was much troubled.
</p><p>"There's Sickles's colt over in the medder, Jimmie," said the
old man.  "Don't you wish you owned one like him?"
</p><p>"Um," said the boy, with a strange lack of interest.  He
continued his reflections.  Then finally he ventured: "Grandpa&mdash;
now&mdash;was that true what you was telling those men?"
</p><p>"What?" asked the grandfather.  "What was I telling them?"
</p><p>"Oh, about your running."
</p><p>"Why, yes, that was true enough, Jimmie.  It was my first
fight, and there was an awful lot of noise, you know."
</p><p>Jimmie seemed dazed that this idol, of its own will, should so
totter.  His stout boyish idealism was injured.
</p><p>Presently the grandfather said: "Sickles's colt is going for
a drink.  Don't you wish you owned Sickles's colt, Jimmie?"
</p><p>The boy merely answered: "He ain't as nice as our'n."  He
lapsed then into another moody silence.

</p><p>One of the hired men, a Swede, desired, to drive to the
county-seat for purposes of his own.  The old man loaned a horse
and an unwashed buggy.  It appeared later that one of the purposes
of the Swede was to get drunk.
</p><p>After quelling some boisterous frolic of the farm-hands and
boys in the garret, the old man had that night gone peacefully to
sleep, when he was aroused by clamoring at the kitchen door.  He
grabbed his trousers, and they waved out behind as he dashed
forward.  He could hear the voice of the Swede, screaming and
blubbering.  He pushed the wooden button, and, as the door flew
open, the Swede, a maniac, stumbled inward, chattering, weeping,
still screaming.  "De barn fire!  Fire!  Fire!  De barn fire!
Fire!  Fire!  Fire!"
</p><p>There was a swift and indescribable change in the old man.
His face ceased instantly to be a face; it became a mask, a gray
thing, with horror written about the mouth and eyes.  He hoarsely
shouted at the foot of the little rickety stairs, and immediately,
it seemed, there came down an avalanche of men.  No one knew that
during this time the old lady had been standing in her night-clothes at the bed-room door, yelling: "What's th' matter?  What's
th' matter?  What's th' matter?"
</p><p>When they dashed toward the barn it presented to their eyes
its usual appearance, solemn, rather mystic in the black night.
The Swede's lantern was overturned at a point some yards in front
of the barn doors.  It contained a wild little conflagration of its
own, and even in their excitement some of those who ran felt a
gentle secondary vibration of the thrifty part of their minds at
sight of this overturned lantern.  Under ordinary circumstances it
would have been a calamity.
</p><p>But the cattle in the barn were trampling, trampling,
trampling, and above this noise could be heard a humming like the
song of innumerable bees.  The old man hurled aside the great
doors, and a yellow flame leaped out at one corner and sped and
wavered frantically up the old gray wall.  It was glad, terrible,
this single flame, like the wild banner of deadly and triumphant
foes.
</p><p>The motley crowd from the garret had come with all the pails
of the farm.  They flung themselves upon the well.  It was a
leisurely old machine, long dwelling in indolence.  It was in the
habit of giving out water with a sort of reluctance.  The men
stormed at it, cursed it; but it continued to allow the buckets to
be filled only after <pb n="224"/>  the wheezy windlass had howled many
protests at the mad-handed men.
</p><p>With his opened knife in his hand old Fleming himself had gone
headlong into the barn, where the stifling smoke swirled with the
air-currents, and where could be heard in its fulness the terrible
chorus of the flames, laden with tones of hate and death, a hymn of
wonderful ferocity.
</p><p>He flung a blanket over an old mare's head, cut the halter
close to the manger, led the mare to the door, and fairly kicked
her out to safety.  He returned with the same blanket, and rescued
one of the work-horses.  He took five horses out, and then came out
himself, with his clothes bravely on fire.  He had no whiskers, and
very little hair on his head.  They soused five pailfuls of water
on him.  His eldest son made a clean miss with the sixth pailful,
because the old man had turned and was running down the decline and
around to the basement of the barn, where there were the stanchions
of the cows.  Some one noticed at the time that he ran very lamely,
as if one of the frenzied horses had smashed his hip.
</p><p>The cows, with their heads held in the heavy stanchions, had
thrown themselves, strangled themselves, tangled themselves: done
everything which the ingenuity of their exuberant fear could
suggest to them.
</p><p>Here, as at the well, the same thing happened to every man
save one.  Their hands went mad.  They became incapable of
everything save the power to rush into dangerous situations.
</p><p>The old man released the cow nearest the door, and she, blind
drunk with terror, crashed into the Swede.  The Swede had been
running to and fro babbling.  He carried an empty milk-pail, to
which he clung with an unconscious, fierce enthusiasm.  He shrieked
like one lost as he went under the cow's hoofs, and the milk-pail,
rolling across the floor, made a flash of silver in the gloom.
</p><p>Old Fleming took a fork, beat off the cow, and dragged the
paralyzed Swede to the open air.  When they had rescued all the
cows save one, which had so fastened herself that she could not be
moved an inch, they returned to the front of the barn and stood
sadly, breathing like men who had reached the final point of human
effort.
</p><p>Many people had come running.  Someone had even gone to the
church, and now, from the distance, rang the tocsin note of the old
bell.  There was a long flare of crimson on the sky, which made
remote people speculate as to the whereabouts of the fire.
</p><p>The long flames sang their drumming chorus in voices of the
heaviest bass.  The wind whirled clouds of smoke and cinders into
the faces of the spectators.  The form of the old barn was outlined
in black amid these masses of orange-hued flames.
</p><p>And then came this Swede again, crying as one who is the
weapon of the sinister fates.  "De colts!  De colts!  You have
forgot de colts!"
</p><p>Old Fleming staggered.  It was true; they had forgotten the
two colts in the box-stalls at the back of the barn.  "Boys," he
said, "I must try to get 'em out."  They clamored about him then,
afraid for him, afraid of what they should see.  Then they talked
wildly each to each.  "Why, it's sure death!"  "He would never get
out!"  "Why, it's suicide for a man to go in there!"  Old Fleming
stared absent-mindedly at the open doors.  "The poor little
things," he said.  He rushed into the barn.
</p><p>When the roof fell in, a great funnel of smoke swarmed toward
the sky, as if the old man's mighty spirit, released from its body--a little bottle&mdash;had swelled like the genie of fable.  The smoke
was tinted rose-hue from the flames, and perhaps the unutterable
midnights of the universe will have no power to daunt the color of
this soul.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
