<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CroSubs"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="CroSubs">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Subscription Books</title>
<title type="sort">subscription books</title>
<author>Crocker, S. R.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Stephen Railton</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">7</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CroSubs</idno>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475855</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Subscription Books</title>
<title level="j">The Literary World</title>
<title type="sort">subscription books</title>
<author>S. R. Crocker</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>p. 40</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>S. R. Crocker</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
<date value="1874-08-01">August 1, 1874</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVA Library call number Micfilm S-147 reel 155</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1874">1874</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; non-fiction</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-06">June 1997</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Carol Osborne, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="article" id="d3">
	<pb n="40" id="CroSubs40"/>
	<head>Subscription Books.<lb/>
[By S. R. Crocker]</head>
<p>[from <hi rend="italic">The Literary World</hi>, Boston, 1 August 1874]</p>
<p>We are sorry to see an increasing tendency on the part of some of our best writers to appeal
to the public through the agency of publishers of subscription books, so called.  The recent
example of Mr. Warner [<hi rend="bold">MT's co-author of</hi> <hi rend="italic">The Gilded Age</hi>] has had a bad effect
upon his contemporaries, and scores of the latter are saying to themselves, "Why shall not I, too,
have my books published by a subscription house, and thereby get great gain?"</p>

<p>Authors as a class are not satisfied with the pecuniary reward given them by publishers, which
is generally ten per cent on the retail price of the book.  They think, and not unreasonably, that four
hundred and fifty dollars &mdash; which would represent the author's share of the profits on a one-dollar-and-fifty book which reached a sale of 3,000 copies &mdash; is not a sufficient payment for the
labor of six months, or, it may be, a year.  Few of them &mdash; Gail Hamilton and perhaps one or two
others must be excepted &mdash; complain that publishers receive more than a fair share of the profits;
but they do think that those profits ought to be larger.  The subscription plan offers certain
important advantages, the chief of which is in the fact that a book is pushed into currency by the
combined personal efforts of many experienced and dauntless men, while a book published in the
regular way must depend mainly upon its own merits for its success.  A subscription publisher,
having agreed to publish a certain book, that would be sold by the regular trade at one dollar and
a half, makes it up in such a way &mdash; with thick paper, large type, and cheap illustrations &mdash; that it
will bear the price of three dollars.  Through the efforts of his agents, he sells from four to twenty
times as many copies as the regular dealer would sell; and of course he can afford to allow the
author a larger royalty.  It would seem, in view of these facts, that the subscription plan was the
only true way of publishing books.  But several considerations are to be taken into account.
Subscription books are in bad odor, and cannot possibly circulate among the best classes of
readers, owing to the general and not unfounded prejudice against them as a class.</p>

<p>Consequently, an author of established reputation, who resorts to the subscription plan for the
sake of making more money, descends to a constituency of a lower grade and inevitably loses
caste, just as Edwin Booth would lose caste, if, induced by the promise of greater pecuniary gain,
he should "play to" the pit, instead of the parquet.  For this loss no money could compensate.
</p>

<p>But the injury resulting from the adoption of the subscription plan by our best writers would
not be limited to themselves, but would affect seriously our whole literature.  This plan operates
directly against the principle that the sale of a book should be proportioned to its merits, and
makes these quite subordinate to the arts of importunity and trickery, which Mr. Perkins has so
well described in "Scrope," and of which almost every reader has had personal experience, as
characteristic of the book-canvasser. </p>

</div1>


</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

