<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DavElec"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="DavElec">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Elected Mother</title>
<title type="sort">elected mother</title>
<author>Daviess, Maria Thompson</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Charles E. Keller</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">27</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">DavElec</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475861</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Elected Mother: A Story of Woman's Equal Rights</title>
<title type="sort">elected mother a story of womans equal rights</title>
<author>Maria Thompson Daviess</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Bobbs-Merrill Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>Indianapolis</pubPlace>
<date value="1912">1912</date>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text
Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of
the text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in
SpeFQue1 for page one of Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1912">1912</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-03">March 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Timothy Jarrett</name>
</respStmt>
<item>minimal TEI markup</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<front id="d2">


<titlePage id="d3"><pb/>
<docTitle><titlePart type="main">THE<lb/>
ELECTED MOTHER<lb/>
<lb/>
A STORY OF WOMAN'S<lb/>
EQUAL RIGHTS</titlePart></docTitle>

<byline>By<lb/>
Maria Thompson Daviess
<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Author of</hi><lb/>
The Road to Providence<lb/>
The Melting of Molly, etc.</byline>

<docImprint>
	<pubPlace>Indianapolis</pubPlace><lb/>
<publisher>The Bobbs-Merrill Company</publisher><lb/>
Publishers
<lb/>
Copyright <docDate>1912</docDate><lb/>
<publisher>The Bobbs-Merrill Company</publisher><lb/>
<lb/>
REPRINTED FROM A VOLUME OF SHORT STORIES<lb/>
AND PUBLISHED BY REQUEST<lb/>
<lb/>
WITH THE GREATEST CONFIDENCE<lb/>
IN THEM AND THEIR FUTURE,<lb/>
I DEDICATE THIS BOOK TO THE<lb/>
SMALL DAUGHTERS OF MY FRIENDS</docImprint></titlePage>


</front>
<body id="d4">
<div1 type="story" id="d5">
<pb n="1"/>
<p> "Yes, and one of the very nicest parts about getting home is to
find the astonishing faithfulness of Pa," said Mrs. Pettibone as her eyes
roamed over the garden, the yard, down the long arbor and across the
meadow bars to return to the wistaria {sic} on the side porch, which was
riotous with the bumble of bees and blooms. </p>
<p> "Why, you didn't expect to find anything else, did you?"
demanded Mrs. Ezra Spain, who sat on the porch steps with a pan of
snap beans in her lap which she was industriously and expectantly
snapping. </p>
<p> "Oh, no, I don't suppose I
  <pb n="2"/>
really did, but for fifty miles or more in the cars coming
home I kept a-doubting of him and a-mistrusting as to the June peas and
the front walk and the yellow-legged domineck in the setting-house.  I
always like to get her off the nest by April twentieth, for she's so
heavy-feathered it makes her nervous to set in hot weather.  But for a
<hi rend="italic">man</hi>, Pa has attended to the important things surprising &mdash;
surprising.  I'm right down thankful that I find I can trust him with such
like &mdash; it'll make me feel freer to go and come after this." </p>
<p> "Where in the world do you expect to be going and coming from
any more, soon?" asked Mrs. Ez with astonishment in her wide eyes.
"We can't spare you again.  You've visited the boys this spring
  <pb n="3"/>

&mdash; Mr.  Pettibone is bettern'n the common run of men,
but I don't believe he'll let &mdash; " </p>
<p> "Well, I don't know as I'll ask him when I get a travel-notion
again," responded Mrs. Pettibone placidly as she began to take the husks
off a bowl of extra large nasturtium seeds, to make ready for a sundown
planting. </p>
<p> "What?" demanded Mrs. Ezra in an awe-struck voice as she
looked at Mrs. Pettibone's tranquil face. </p>
<p> "Yes," answered Mrs. Pettibone in a matter-of-fact tone, "Yes,
I'm thinking of beginning all over with Pa.  I've been married to him
forty-three years next November, and I'm afraid it will go kinder hard
with him, but he will have to be led easy and blind-like to the fact that
woman's day has dawned.
<pb n="4"/>
She's been downtrodden, geared up uneven, stalled up in
a house over a cook stove, poked fun at by love-making and things of
that kind until she is such a poor weak creature she is in danger of just
going on permitting it and being happy in spite of it.  Child, don't you
know about woman's suffrage when you hear it mentioned in such
feeling terms as those?" </p>
<p> "Yes," answered Mrs. Ez contentedly, "but I never took any
interest in such doings and I didn't know you &mdash; " </p>
<p> "I never did before," answered Mrs. Pettibone as she shooed an
inquisitive bee away with a gentle but determined hand.  "I've been so
busy that I hadn't got 'round to it.  You see, the raising of five boys into
being good God-fearing men and proper husbands for five

<pb n="5"/> likely girls that some other women have been putting in
licks on to get ready for them, has taken up a lot of my time.  I could
just make out to get them warm-covered, proper-fed and catechism-instructed, give a little attention to making a good-husband example out
of Pa for them, meet the calls that Old Zion church laid on me as a
member, do my duty by the sick and get up love enough for the doing of
it all to make me sing the number of songs I think the good Lord stints
out by the day to all us women to be sung before it's time to put out the
cat and the lamp.  It's different now &mdash;  I've got time to feel my
<hi rend="italic">wrongs</hi>." </p>
<p> "But what has happened?  You've got no wrongs, Mis' Pettibone.
The boys and Mr. Pettibone fairly &mdash; "    </p>
  <pb n="6"/>
<p> "Oh, they haven't done anything to me!  Pais a none-such
husband and every boy I've got is a God's blessing and married to a
good woman, as managing most of them as I would ask for my sons'
welfare; but I have waked up to the fact that I'm <hi rend="italic">injured</hi>, or
could be if anybody wanted to injure me, which they don't.  I'm glad
you came over this morning, for I want to tell you of the astonishing
things I have experienced out to Wahoo City on this visit to Tom and
Elviry.  I can't tell Pa, for I'm keeping him blind until I can get time to
commence on his reformation and my emancipation."  As she spoke
Mrs. Pettibone's eyes twinkled and her rosy cheeks drew up into a series
of crinkled dimples which tickled Mrs. Spain's risibles to the extent of
making her emit a
  <pb n="7"/>

deep-voiced chuckle.  The bees buzzed resentfully at her
merriment and one dusty old fellow bumbled in real temper about her
head. </p>
<p> "Lawsy me," she laughed, "you scared me!  I thought you were
serious.  I was just beginning to get sorry for Mr. Pettibone and &mdash; "
</p>
<p> "I <hi rend="italic">am</hi> serious, child; that is, I've come from a place
where such things are so serious that there is no time to do or think
about anything else.  They've got a club in Wahoo City that's just for
women to go to and discuss <hi rend="italic">wrongs</hi> and <hi rend="italic">wants</hi>
and it's a revelation to hear 'em do it.  I went with Elviry the very
second day after I got there and I came away as mad and cross as a wet
hen, and I had got over about half that missing of Pa that
  <pb n="8"/>
always spoils my visits to the boys and their families.
</p>
<p> "'Elviry,' I said, 'I don't see how you can listen so calm and
peaceful when you bear that in all but ten of these United States a
woman's children don't belong to her at all, but to some
good-for-nothing man who can do just as he pleases with them and her
too.  How can you stand it, and you a mother with &mdash;  ' </p>
<p> "'Why, Mother Pet,' she said kinder astonished-like at me, 'my
children are Tom's children.  I want him to do just as he sees fit with all
of us.  If he does it I will know it is for the best and &mdash; ' </p>
<p> "'Fiddlesticks,' I said real cross, for the way Elviry does spoil
Tom is sinful.  She's so in love with him that it would be pitiful if he
wasn't worse than she is

<pb n="9"/> in love sickness.  'I don't trust Tom not to be just as
much of a brute as any of those other men they tell about.  They're all
<hi rend="italic">men</hi>, I say.' </p>
<p> "With that Elviry laughed and we got on the street-car.  I was still
so upset that I glared at a nice young man, who stood to give me a seat
as polite as you please.  Elviry introduced him to me and I must say his
pleasantness soothed me down some and when I got off the car I said I
would be glad to have him call round to see me, as he was such a
particular friend of Tom's.  He said he would come right away and bring
his wife.  He looked kinder proud and sheepish when he mentioned her
and I wondered if she was that young a bride.  But Elviry told me about
it as we walked home.  She was the

<pb n="10"/> woman that was running for mayor on the reform ticket,
and all that meeting I had heard, had been brought about by a kind of
caucus held to do something toward her election.  I didn't pay much
attention because I couldn't make out the straight of it, but it seems over
there is one of the places where women <hi rend="italic">do</hi> vote and they
were doing it for fare-youwell.  A man, who had stolen a whole lot of
money from the City, was out against her for reelection and the things
he was resorting to to beat her were most shameful. </p>
<p> "But Elviry said that the women in the town were all up and
doing and that a lot of the men were for her and determined to see her
have a fair show.  She said she was a splendid woman and a fine speaker
and was something or other titled

<pb n="11"/> from two or three colleges.  She promised to take me to
hear her speak the very next night, which would be the last speech she
would make before the election.  I was just as excited as could be though
a funny little feeling hit me when I thought of that young fellow so
proud and shy &mdash; but, anyway, by that time we were at home and ready
for dinner. </p>
<p> "At the table I read Tom one good long lecture on the rights of
woman, and I didn't allow him to answer back, either.  He said he
hadn't had such a fine time since the Sunday evenings I uster spend with
all my boys in the front parlor teaching them who made them and for
what purpose.  He laughed and laughed and hugged first Elviry and then
me, and then made us come up with him and look at

<pb n="12"/> the two children to see if I thought they had grown as
much as they oughter.  Tom's a lot like Pa, and a good bit of my
homesickness for my husband came back before bedtime, but I went to
sleep thinking about how I would enjoy hearing that fine young woman
make a speech.  Still that clean-shaved young man would keep coming
into my dreams and I felt a kind of pity mixing up with him. </p>
<p> "But my! I tell you that next night was glorious!  We sat in good
front seats and could see and hear without any strain.  When I saw her
come down the aisle between the committees on both sides of the
platform and take her stand behind the long heavy table like is in the
court-house, my heart just kinder stopped beating with excitement.  She
was a tall, upstanding,

<pb n="13"/>  young woman with great sky-colored eyes and the most
beautiful head set on her strong shoulders you ever saw anywhere.  On
her black hair was one of her college square-top-and-tassel caps, and a
long black silk gown was over her white dress.  She looked like one of
those pictures of judges and lawyers on the bench in the court-house over
in England.  I just loved her on sight and would have liked to stretch out
my hands to her. </p>
<p> "She stood still for a second and let her eyes rove around hunting
for something and then there was a little flash of a smile over to a place
behind us where something told me without looking <hi rend="italic">who</hi> was
there.  That smile killed the last bit of that pity feeling I'd been hatching
up in my mind for <hi rend="italic">him</hi>.</p>

<pb n="14"/>
<p>"What did she say?  Well, I just can't remember one word of it,
but I know it was grand and noble.  It was about the duty of being
citizens in a town and it wasn't any raving about anybody's wrongs.
Everybody sat still and listened to the very end and then they just tore up
the house with their hollering and cheering.  The women waved their
handkerchiefs and the men clapped and clapped.  She waited and smiled
down at everybody, and, honey, the blush on that woman's face, who
had just stood up and took what is called a man's part, was as sweet as
coulder been the one Eve mustered when Adam introduced her to the
animal friends in the garden.  As I said, it was all just
<hi rend="italic">glorious</hi>. </p>
<p> "Oh, yes, I got acquainted with her.  Tom and Elviry and I
waited

<pb n="15"/> for her and her husband and they came home with us in
Tom's abomination of an automobile, what scares me to death the very
sight of, to have supper.  They live just down the street from my folks
and they neighbor almost like we do out here in Glenrose, Harpeth
Valley. </p>
<p> "And between her and me it was one of those cases of love at first
sight that the dear Lord sometimes sends to settle like a lovely pink
cloud of warm feelings between two women, which never floats away
from them, but rests a benediction and a protection.  She was like a
beautiful ruby woman out of the Proverbs, last chapter, tenth verse, and
you could see that the heart of her husband was '<hi rend="italic">safely
trusting</hi>.' </p>
<p> "While Elviry was cooking some

<pb n="16"/> outrageous but good-smelling food in her silver parlor
skillet, chafing-dish she called it, Tom undertook to tell the sweet child
about what he called my 'high vault to the woman side of the fence.'  Of
course they all laughed and he made it worse and more outrageous with
making up about what I was planning to do to Pa when I got back home
and the like, but when I waited until there was a pause in the high jinks
and asked him straight out how he'd like to have little Elviry's future
husband get mad at her and take her children away if he wanted to,
whether or not, and she with the law against her, I felt strong soft arms
creep around my neck from behind and her lovely voice half whispered,
half laughed, into my ear as she said:

<pb n="17"/>  </p>
<p> "'Never mind, Mrs. Pettibone, I'm coming in to-morrow to have
a talk with you and then at dinner you can straighten Tom's conviction
out with no trouble at all.' </p>
<p> "Then we all ate and laughed and parted good friends, though
going up-stairs Tom cut his weather eye at me as if he was still afraid of
a peach-tree switch hid in my skirts.  I just ignored him completely, but
took Elviry into my room with me for a minute.  There I put the
question that was troubling me to her fairly. </p>
<p> "'Yes, Mother Pet,' she answered in a kind of blush herself, 'but
it's six weeks off and all this excitement will be over then.  She had
pledged herself to accept the nomination and started the campaign before
she knew of her condition.  She has felt it her duty to

<pb n="18"/> keep on with it because one of the arguments that is
continually being brought up on the woman question is that the very fact
of &mdash; of such a contingency unfits women for the responsibilities of
administration, and holding office and &mdash; ' </p>
<p> "'Fiddlesticks!' I answered, all that caucus-meeting feeling
rushing over me at once, 'it don't unfit them for cooking, washing and
ironing, tending the toddlers, mending and sewing, working the garden,
milking the cow, churning the butter, and any number of extras thrown
in, so why should it unfit them for being mayors and presidents and
such?  Most candidates from governors to sheriff take a week off any
time in a campaign to get on a spree, and why shouldn't a woman
quietly and in

<pb n="19"/> the fear of God have her baby and go on with the good
work?'  I was real het up, and showed it. </p>
<p> "'Oh, Mother Pet, if you'll just say that to her in exactly that tone
of voice and manner to-morrow I believe you will save the day,' said
Elviry, divided between laughing and crying.  'She hasn't any mother
and neither have I, and she gets scared sometimes and I try to comfort
her, but I'm not like you &mdash; ' </p>
<p> "'I'll attend to this comforting business from now on, daughter,' I
said to Elviry as I lent her my best pocket-handkerchief to wipe her
eyes. </p>
<p> "'Has she all her baby fixings ready ?' </p>
<p> "'No,' said Elviry, smiling through her tears.  'She's been so
busy; I've done a lot for her, but &mdash; '

<pb n="20"/>  </p>
<p> "'Now,' said I positively, 'that sort of thing won't do.  She must
attend to all that right away and not neglect it, mayor or no mayor, and
I'll start her first thing in the morning.' </p>
<p> "And I did, and never in my life have I seen a sweeter sight than
that lovely grand woman seated by my side hemming a flannel band, the
telephone ringing at her elbow constant with some politics question or
other to settle right off the minute.  She'd give her commands and decide
what to do in short quick words, then go on printing her stitches in a
little night-gown about as big as a minute slow and careful.  And for a
week those infant first-aid caucuses went on every morning and it looked
like to me I was being born all over into a new and most

<pb n="21"/> disturbing world.  We'd first talk safety-pins and
crocheted socks and then about the dreadful sweatshops and what they do
to women.  Then we'd veer from short petticoats to the property laws
what let a woman work her life out helping her husband buy a farm and
then at his death be sold out of it on account of having only a dower
interest.  We'd plan a little silk coat and end up with a prayer for the
noble women teachers that a he-school board makes work longer hours
than any little whipper-snapper college boy that's teaching for a stepping-stone, and for much less pay.  And all the time she was as gentle and
noble, but as firm as a rock and well-nigh inspired in her talk about what
<hi rend="italic">had</hi> to come for women.  And with each decision she would
say that she knew

<pb n="22"/> it would be best for all women because she wanted it for
her daughter.  The way she planned the conditions she wanted that child
to face when she had grown to her woman's estate sounded like a psalm
of life written in Revelation style. </p>
<p> "So it was, she sitting at my feet learning the way of women who
had been, and I at hers learning the way of the women who were to be,
until the Monday of the election came.  And that morning was just the
same as the others, only we had about finished up most of the needful
jobs and were packing them in a little blue and white hamper.  Elviry
had gone to be one of the counters at one of the polls and the children
were both across the street at the kindergarten.  The house was quiet

<pb n="23"/> and still and I must say that it, was as clean and neat as
a pin, and Elviry with only one girl in the kitchen, but with management
and kindness to help that girl to do the work of three and have time off.
She had put the dinner in the fireless cooker &mdash; I'll tell you about that
later &mdash; and gone down to the drug store to vote before time to bring the
children home for their lunch.  The sweet child and me had things to
ourselves and was enjoying the quiet communion. </p>
<p> "'Mother Pet,' she said as she looked up with stars in her eyes
from a box of little silk shirts I had had her sew tapes on, 'tell me true,
am I going to be any less <hi rend="italic">her</hi> mother because I have given so
much of my time and my strength to this work &mdash; that &mdash; the world still
says is a man's?  Would

<pb n="24"/> it have been better for me to have sat quietly and
dreamed a clean, wide-streeted, beautified city for her with no dark
corners where women are wronged, no "open doors" for the young men
from which she is to choose her husband?  Should I have waited the
generations ?' </p>
<p> "'No, child,' I answered, looking her full in the face.  'It is not
every woman who could do what you have done and it won't be that
most of them can ever run their woman-jobs and take up these cares of
state, as they are rightly called, but neither could most men or can they
ever.  We'll just go on having homes which are man guarded and
woman tended and the great few among both sexes can meet and settle
what is best for all concerned.  Run a piece of

<pb n="25"/> blue ribbon in this sleeve before you fold it.' </p>
<p> "'And, Mother Pet,' this time the rose color spread all over her
cheeks in a flame even up into her dark hair, 'my husband &mdash; you don't
think, do you, the doing what I have done, in any way brings upon him
the charge of incompetency?  He thinks as I do &mdash; he knows that the time
has come for women to be legislated for and not against and that the men
have failed them.  The real sacrifice was made by him.  That is what has
hurt me &mdash; have I taken anything from him that wrongs him?  Do I bring
anything back from my public life into his home that injures the
sacredness of it?  Am I a lesser wife for a good man because I seek to
better the condition of the wife of the bad?  Am I &mdash; '</p>

<pb n="26"/>
<p> "'Honey,' I said to kinder interrupt her, for the tears were
swimming deep over the violets in her eyes and I didn't want her to get
upset.  'That husband of yours is no more disqualified by your being a
good mayor of this town than I am by Tom's being president of that
bank, country boy that he is and always surprising me and Pa by his
gumption.  Your man looks as happy to me all the time as a man who's
got his ticket to Salvation bought with a stopover at every pleasant place
along the way.  Don't worry about him; he's got a "ruby" wife and he
knows it.  Now you must go home and rest, for I want you to be ready
to enjoy the rally after the vote is all counted.' </p>
<p> "And just then the telephone rang and she was the cool mayor-
<pb n="27"/> self again with the mother-wife tears still wet on her
cheeks. </p>
<p> "And after lunch at Elviry's I went into my room to lie down and
get forty winks against another all-night frolic, for it does seem to me
that city people get less real sleep than is scarcely believable, with their
junketings and doings which Tom is always just thick into. </p>
<p> "I must have slept some into hours when I heard the telephone
ring, which I'm not much used to answering, but will when pushed to,
and I took it up kinder ginger. </p>
<p> "'Mrs. Pettibone, can you come down here quick &mdash; she &mdash; she
needs you,' and that was all; but I knew that boy's voice and what the
trouble was, so I put on my bonnet and got the camphire bottle and left
in short order.</p>

<pb n="28"/>
<p> "Yes, Mrs. Ezra, it's the God's blessed truth I'm telling you.
While all the women, and what proved to be the majority of the men in
Wahoo City, were down town a-voting for that sweet child to be the
mayor of the town, she and him and me was up at her house a-having
her baby. </p>
<p> "'Well,' I said first thing cheerful-like, 'daughter wants to get
here in time to cast her vote before the polls close.' </p>
<p> "And in the due course of time it all came right in the most
natural and peaceable way possible.  Along about the time the counts
from the different wards began to come in and we could hear the
cheering from the flash-light reports down the street at the drugstore
corner, I had got the little blossom all tucked out in flannel

<pb n="29"/> and linen and lace; and a finer child I never saw.  But I
sat with it across my lap for quite a spell just a-thinking how on earth I
was going to break the news of the calamity to her.  She had been so
brave and patient and lovely that I couldn't bear to think of her
disappointment, and I made out to myself that I oughter put another little
shawl inside the blanket, just to give myself more time. </p>
<p> "Then I made a resolve &mdash; I sent the nurse to tell <hi rend="italic">him</hi>
to come to me.  He came in looking more sheepish than I almost ever
saw on such an occasion.  But there was a pride there, too, and a power
of awe. </p>
<p> "'Yes,' I said firmly, 'it's true and you have got to tell her.
Now, be careful and lay the child in her arms before you break it to
her.'</p>

<pb n="30"/>
<p> "'Come with me,' he said pitiful-like, and I followed him. </p>

<p> "And if I thought she looked grand and noble as she stood before
the audience a-championing her weak sisters for all the world to hear, in
my heart I knelt down before her as she took the little thing into her
lovely strong arms and laid it against her deep breast. </p>
<p> "'Dear,' said the man gently and quietly, with both sorrow and
courage in his voice, 'she's your &mdash; <hi rend="italic">son</hi>.' </p>
<p> "'Oh,' she said as a glory that was like the sun-dawn spread over
her face and neck and white breast, 'oh &mdash; a man &mdash; I'm glad!  Glad!'
And about that time I saw that I could come away. </p>
<p> "Oh, yes, I stayed to see her take her oath of office &mdash; that's

<pb n="31"/> what made me two weeks behind-hand coming home.  I
hated to disappoint Pa about my promise to be here on April the third,
but I decided that it was best for him to begin to find out how much I
meant to use my own mind.  Oh, no, I'm not going to be savigorus
about it, still I'm going to lead him up to my idea gentle but firm.  But
now, who'd have thought he would have followed my mind so faithful
about the peas and the domineck? </p>
<p> "No, Mrs. Spain, I don't think so!  Somehow I have a feeling that
when all this ruckus gets men's strongness and faithfulness mixed with
women's courage and chastity in the future folks, His Kingdom is
a-going to come in about two generations from then.  And may I be
there to see!"</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

