<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DosOrph"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="DosOrph">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Little Orphan</title>
<title type="sort">little orphan</title>
<author>Dostoevsky, Fyodor</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">14</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">DosOrph</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475876</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>The spelling of the author's name has been changed in the
header from Theodore Dostoivsky to Fyodor Dostoevsky, the standard
used by the UVA Library</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Little Orphan</title>
<title level="j">The Cosmopolitan</title>
<title type="sort">little orphan</title>
<author>Fyodor Dostoevsky</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>Volume II</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>pp 390-392.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Schlicht &amp; Field, Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>Rochester, N.Y.</pubPlace>
<date value="1887-02">February 1887</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Electronic text checked against microfilm, UVA Library call
number s-147, reel 660</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1887">1887</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Literature in Translation</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-06">June 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Catherine Tousignant</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI-compatible header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" id="d3"> <pb n="390"/>
<head>THE LITTLE ORPHAN.<ref target="n1">1</ref><lb/>
BY THEODORE DOSTOIVSKY.</head>

<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d4">
<head>I.</head>

<p>IN a large city, on Christmas eve in the biting cold, I see a young child,
still quite young, six years old, perhaps even less; yet too young to be
sent on the street begging, but assuredly destined to be sent in a year or
two.

</p><p>This child awakes one morning in a damp and frosty cellar.  He is
wrapped in a kind of squalid dressing-gown and is shivering.  His breath
issues from between his lips in white vapor; he is seated on a trunk; to
pass the time he blows the breath from his mouth, and amuses himself in
seeing it escape.  But he is very hungry.  Several times since morning he
has drawn near the bed covered with a straw mattress as thin as gauze,
where his mother lies sick, her head resting on a bundle of rags instead of
a pillow.

</p><p>How did she come there?  She came probably from a strange city
and has fallen ill.  The proprietress of the miserable lodging was arrested
two days ago, and carried to the police station; it is a holiday to-day, and
the other tenants have gone out.  However, one of them has remained in
bed for the last twenty-four hours, stupid with drink, not having waited
for the holiday.

</p><p>From another corner issue the complaints

   <pb n="391"/>

of an old woman of eighty years, laid up with rheumatism.  This old
woman was formerly a children's nurse somewhere; now she is dying all
alone.  She whines, moans, and growls at the little boy, who begins to
be afraid to come near the corner where she lies with the death rattle
in her throat.  He has found something to drink in the hallway, but he
has not been able to lay his hand on the smallest crust of bread, and
for the tenth time he comes to wake his mother.  He finishes by
getting frightened in this darkness.

</p><p>The evening is already late, and no one comes to kindle the fire.
He finds, by feeling around, his mother's face, and is astonished that she
no longer moves and that she has become as cold as the wall.

</p><p>"It is so cold!" he thinks.

</p><p>He remains some time without moving, his hand resting on the
shoulder of the corpse.  Then he begins to blow in his fingers to warm
them, and, happening to find his little cap on the bed, he looks softly for
the door, and issues forth from the underground lodging.

</p><p>He would have gone out sooner had he not been afraid of the big
dog that barks all the day up there on the landing before their neighbor's
door.

</p><p>Oh! what a city! never before had he seen anything like it.  Down
yonder from where he came, the nights are much darker.  There is only
one lamp for the whole street; little low wooden houses, closed with
shutters; in the street from the time it grows dark, no one; every one shut
up at home: only a crowd of dogs that howl, hundreds, thousands of
dogs, that howl and bark all the night.  But then, it used to be so warm
there!  And he got something to eat.  Here, ah! how good it would be to
have something to eat!  What a noise here, what an uproar!  What a great
light, and what a crowd of people!  What horses, and what carriages!
And the cold, the cold!  The bodies of the tired horses smoke with frost
and their burning nostrils puff white clouds; their shoes ring on the
pavement through the soft snow.  And how every body hustles every
body else!  "Ah! how I would like to eat a little piece of something.  That
is what makes my fingers ache so."</p>

</div2><div2 type="section" n="2" id="d5">
<head>II.</head>

<p>A POLICEMAN just passes by, and turns his head so as not to see
the child.

</p><p>"Here is another street.  Oh! how wide it is!  I shall be crushed to
death here, I know; how they all shout, how they run, how they roll
along!  And the light, and the light!  And that, what is that?  Oh! what a
big window pane!  And behind the pane, a room, and in the room a tree
that goes up to the ceiling; it is the Christmas tree.  And what lights under
the tree!  Such papers of gold, and such apples!  And all around dolls and
little hobby-horses.  There are little children well-dressed, nice, and
clean; they are laughing and playing, eating and drinking things.  There is
a little girl going to dance with the little boy.  How pretty she is!  And
there is music.  I can hear it through the glass."

</p><p>The child looks, admires, and even laughs.  He feels no longer any
pain in his fingers or feet.  The fingers of his hand have become all red,
he cannot bend them any more, and it hurts him to move them.  But all at
once, he feels that his fingers ache; he begins to cry, and goes away.  He
perceives through another window another room, and again trees and
cakes of all sorts on the table, red almonds and yellow ones.  Four
beautiful ladies are sitting down, and when any body comes he is given
some cake: and the door opens every minute, and many gentlemen enter.
The little fellow crept forward, opened the door of a sudden, and went in.
Oh! what a noise was made when they saw him, what confusion!
Immediately a lady arose, put a kopeck in his hand, and opened herself
the street door for him.  How frightened he was!</p>

</div2><div2 type="section" n="3" id="d6">
<head>III.</head>

<p>THE kopeck has fallen from his hands, and rings on the steps of the
stairs.  He was not able to tighten his little fingers enough to hold the
coin.  The child went out running, and walked fast, fast.  Where was he
going?  He did not know.  And he runs, runs, and blows in his hands.  He
is troubled.  He feels so lonely, so frightened!  And suddenly, what is that
again!  A crowd of people stand there and admire.

</p><p>"A window! behind the pane, three pretty dolls attired in wee red
and yellow dresses, and just exactly as though they were alive!  And that
little old man sitting down, who seems to play the fiddle.  There are two
others, too, standing up, who play on tiny violins, keeping time with their
heads to the

   <pb n="392"/>

music.  They look at each other and their lips move.
And they really speak?  Only they cannot be heard through the glass."

</p><p>And the child first thinks that they are living, and when he
comprehends that they are only dolls, he begins to laugh.  Never had he
seen such dolls before, and he didn't know that there were any like that!
He would like to cry, but those dolls are just too funny!</p>

</div2><div2 type="section" n="4" id="d7">
<head>IV.</head>

<p>SUDDENLY he feels himself seized by the coat.  A big rough boy
stands near him, who gives him a blow of his fist on the head, snatches
his cap, and trips him up.

</p><p>The child falls.  At the same time there is a shout; he remains a
moment paralyzed with fear.  Then he springs up with a bound and runs,
runs, darts under a gateway somewhere and hides himself in a court-yard
behind a pile of wood.  He cowers and shivers in his fright; he can hardly
breathe.

</p><p>And suddenly he feels quite comfortable.  His little hands and feet
don't hurt any more; he is warm, warm as though near a stove, and all his
body trembles.

</p><p>"Ah!  I am going asleep! how nice it is to have a sleep!  I shall stay
a little while and then I will go and see the dolls again," thought the little
fellow, and he smiled at the recollection of the dolls.  "They looked just
as though they were alive!"

</p><p>Then he hears his mother's song.  "Mamma, I am going to sleep.
Ah! how nice it is here for sleeping!"

</p><p>"Come to my house, little boy, to see the Christmas tree," said a
soft voice.

</p><p>He thought at first it was his mother; but no, it was not she.

</p><p>Then who is calling him?  He does not see.  But some one stoops
over him, and folds him in his arms in the darkness: and he stretches out
his hand and&mdash;all at once&mdash;oh! what light!  Oh! what a Christmas tree!
No, it is not a Christmas tree; he has never seen the like of it!

</p><p>Where is he now?  All is resplendent, all is radiant, and dolls all
around; but no, not dolls, little boys, little girls; only they are very bright.
All of them circle round him; they fly.  They hug him, they take him and
carry him away, and he is flying too.  And he sees his mother looking at
him and laughing joyfully.

</p><p>"Mamma! mamma! ah! how nice it is here!" cries her little boy to
her.

</p><p>And again he embraces the children, and would like very much to
tell them about the dolls behind the window pane.  "Who are you, little
girls?" he asks, laughing and fondling them.

</p><p>It is the Christmas tree at Jesus's.

</p><p>At Jesus's, that day, there is always a Christmas tree for little
children that have none themselves.

</p><p>And he learned that all these little boys and girls were children like
himself, who had died like him.  Some had died of cold in the baskets
abandoned at the doors of the public functionaries of St. Petersburg;
others had died out at nurse in the foul hovels of the Tchaukhnas; others
of hunger at the dry breasts of their mothers during the famine.  All were
here now, all little angels now, all with Jesus, and He Himself among
them, spreading his hands over them, blessing them and their sinful
mothers.

</p><p>And the mothers of these children are there too, apart, weeping;
each recognizes her son or her daughter, and the children fly towards
them, embrace them, wipe away the tears with their little hands, and beg
them not to weep.

</p><p>And below on the earth, the concierge in the morning found the
wee corpse of the child, who had taken refuge in the courtyard.  Stiff and
frozen behind the pile of wood it lay.

</p><p>The mother was found too.  She died before him; both are reunited
in Heaven in the Lord's house.</p>

<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">This</seg> <p>story is an excellent example of the style of M. Dostoivsky,
the great Russian novelist, whose works are attracting so much attention
in France.  It is without plot, like most of his stories, but it is a very
powerful and realistic sketch.  The repetition of words and phrases
noticeable in this story is common to Russian stories.  It is particularly
noticeable in Count Leon Tolstoi's "Search for Happiness," a volume of
short stories written for the Russian peasants.</p></note>
</div2>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

