<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DouFutu"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
]>
<TEI.2 id="DouFutu">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Future of the Colored Race</title>
<title type="sort">future of the colored race</title>
<author>Douglass, Frederick, 1817?-1895</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">11</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">DouFutu</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475882</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Future of the Colored Race</title>
<title type="sort">future of the colored race</title>
<author>Frederick Douglass</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
<name>James Russell Lowell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>Boston, MA</pubPlace>
<date value="1886-05">May 1886</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>North American Review (142)</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1886-05">May 1886</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term>
<term>democracy</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>African American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-12">December 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Monique Dull, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to basic TEI.2-conformant markup; edited TEI.2 header;
checked bibliographic information with print edition, University of
Virginia Library AP 2.N7 v.142 1886</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
	<pb n="437"/>
<head>THE FUTURE OF THE COLORED RACE.</head>
<p>It is quite impossible, at this early date, to say with any
decided emphasis what the future of the colored people will be.
Speculations of that kind, thus far, have only reflected the mental
bias and education of the many who have essayed to solve the
problem.
</p><p>We all know what the negro has been as a slave.  In this
relation we have his experience of two hundred and fifty years
before us, and can easily know the character and qualities he has
developed and exhibited during this long and severe ordeal.  In his
new relation to his environments, we see him only in the twilight
of twenty years of semi-freedom; for he has scarcely been free long
enough to outgrow the marks of the lash on his back and the fetters
on his limbs.  He stands before us, to-day, physically, a maimed
and mutilated man.  His mother was lashed to agony before the birth
of her babe, and the bitter anguish of the mother is seen in the
countenance of her offspring.  Slavery has twisted his limbs,
shattered his feet, deformed his body and distorted his features.
He remains black, but no longer comely.  Sleeping on the dirt floor
of the slave cabin in infancy, cold on one side and warm on the
other, a forced circulation of blood on the one side and chilled
and retarded circulation on the other, it has come to pass that he
has not the vertical bearing of a perfect man.  His lack of
symmetry, caused by no fault of his own, creates a resistance to
his progress which cannot well be overestimated, and should be
taken into account, when measuring his speed in the new race of
life upon which he has now entered.  As I have often said before,
we should not measure the negro from the heights which the white
race has attained, but from the depths from which he has come.  You
will not find Burke, Grattan, Curran and O'Connell among the
oppressed and famished poor of the famine-stricken districts of
Ireland.  Such men come of comfortable antecedents and sound
parents.</p><pb n="438"/>
<p>Laying aside all prejudice in favor of or against race,
looking at the negro as politically and socially related to the
American people generally, and measuring the forces arrayed against
him, I do not see how he can survive and flourish in this country
as a distinct and separate race, nor do I see how he can be removed
from the country either by annihilation or expatriation.
</p><p>Sometimes I have feared that, in some wild paroxysm of rage,
the white race, forgetful of the claims of humanity and the
precepts of the Christian religion, will proceed to slaughter the
negro in wholesale, as some of that race have attempted to
slaughter Chinamen, and as it has been done in detail in some
districts of the Southern States.  The grounds of this fear,
however, have in some measure decreased, since the negro has
largely disappeared from the arena of Southern politics, and has
betaken himself to industrial pursuits and the acquisition of
wealth and education, though even here, if over-prosperous, he is
likely to excite a dangerous antagonism; for the white people do
not easily tolerate the presence among them of a race more
prosperous than themselves.  The negro as a poor ignorant creature
does not contradict the race pride of the white race.  He is more
a source of amusement to that race than an object of resentment.
Malignant resistance is augmented as he approaches the plane
occupied by the white race, and yet I think that that resistance
will gradually yield to the pressure of wealth, education, and high
character.
</p><p>My strongest conviction as to the future of the negro
therefore is, that he will not be expatriated nor annihilated, nor
will he forever remain a separate and distinct race from the people
around him, but that he will be absorbed, assimilated, and will
only appear finally, as the Phoenicians now appear on the shores of
the Shannon, in the features of a blended race.  I cannot give at
length my reasons for this conclusion, and perhaps the reader may
think that the wish is father to the thought, and may in his wrath
denounce my conclusion as utterly impossible.  To such I would say,
tarry a little, and look at the facts.  Two hundred years ago there
were two distinct and separate streams of human life running
through this country.  They stood at opposite extremes of
ethnological classification: all black on the one side, all white
on the other.  Now, between these two extremes, an intermediate
race has arisen, which is neither white nor black, neither
Caucasian nor <pb n="439"/>  Ethiopian, and this intermediate race is
constantly increasing.  I know it is said that marital alliance
between these races is unnatural, abhorrent and impossible; but
exclamations of this kind only shake the air.  They prove nothing
against a stubborn fact like that which confronts us daily and
which is open to the observation of all.  If this blending of the
two races were impossible we should not have at least one-fourth of
our colored population composed of persons of mixed blood, ranging
all the way from a dark-brown color to the point where there is no
visible admixture.  Besides, it is obvious to common sense that
there is no need of the passage of laws, or the adoption of other
devices, to prevent what is in itself impossible.
</p><p>Of course this result will not be reached by any hurried or
forced processes.  It will not arise out of any theory of the
wisdom of such blending of the two races.  If it comes at all, it
will come without shock or noise or violence of any kind, and only
in the fullness of time, and it will be so adjusted to surrounding
conditions as hardly to be observed.  I would not be understood as
advocating intermarriage between the two races.  I am not a
propagandist, but a prophet.  I do not say that what I say
<hi rend="italic">should</hi> come to pass, but what I think is likely to come to
pass, and what is inevitable.  While I would not be understood as
advocating the desirability of such a result, I would not be
understood as deprecating it.  Races and varieties of the human
family appear and disappear, but humanity remains and will remain
forever.  The American people will one day be truer to this idea
than now, and will say with Scotia's inspired son:
</p>
<lg type="citation">
<l>              "A man's a man for a' that."</l>
</lg>
<p>When that day shall come, they will not pervert and sin
against the verity of language as they now do by calling a man of
mixed blood, a negro; they will tell the truth.  It is only
prejudice against the negro which calls every one, however nearly
connected with the white race, and however remotely connected with
the negro race, a negro.  The motive is not a desire to elevate the
negro, but to humiliate and degrade those of mixed blood; not a
desire to bring the negro up, but to cast the mulatto and the
quadroon down by forcing him below an arbitrary and hated color
line.  Men of mixed blood in this country apply the name
<hi rend="italic">"negro"</hi> to themselves, not because it is a correct
ethnological description, <pb n="440"/>  but to seem especially devoted to
the black side of their parentage.  Hence in some cases they are
more noisily opposed to the conclusion to which I have come, than
either the white or the honestly black race.  The opposition to
amalgamation, of which we hear so much on the part of colored
people, is for most part the merest affectation, and, will never
form an impassable barrier to the union of the two varieties.
</p>
<trailer>FREDERICK DOUGLASS.</trailer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
