<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DouReco"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="DouReco">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Reconstruction</title>
<title type="sort">reconstruction</title>
<author>Douglass, Frederick, 1817?-1895</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">20</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">DouReco</idno>
<date value="1993">1993</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1993 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475885</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Reconstruction</title>
<title type="sort">reconstruction</title>
<author>Frederick Douglass</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<date value="1866">1866</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 18</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 761-765</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>spell-check and verification made against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1866">1866</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term>
<term>democracy</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>African American</term>
<term>American Civil War</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-02">February 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>changed COCOA tags to TEI tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader><text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
<pb n="761"/>
<head>
Douglass, Frederick.  "Reconstruction."  <lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 18 (1866): 761-765.
</head>
<p>THE assembling of the Second Session of the Thirty-ninth
Congress may very properly be made the occasion of a few earnest
words on the already much-worn topic of reconstruction.
</p><p>Seldom has any legislative body been the subject of a
solicitude more intense, or of aspirations more sincere and ardent.
There are the best of reasons for this profound interest.
Questions of vast moment, left undecided by the last session of
Congress, must be manfully grappled with by this.  No political
skirmishing will avail.  The occasion demands statesmanship.
</p><p>Whether the tremendous war so heroically fought and so
victoriously ended shall pass into history a miserable failure,
barren of permanent results, &mdash; a scandalous and shocking waste of
blood and treasure, &mdash; a strife for empire, as Earl Russell
characterized it, of no value to liberty or civilization, &mdash; an
attempt to re-establish a Union by force, which must be the merest
mockery of a Union, &mdash; an effort to bring under Federal authority
States into which no loyal man from the North may safely enter, and
to bring men into the national councils who deliberate with daggers
and vote with revolvers, and who do not even conceal their deadly
hate of the country that conquered them; or whether, on the other
hand, we shall, as the rightful reward of victory over treason,
have a solid nation, entirely delivered from all contradictions and
social antagonisms, based upon loyalty, liberty, and equality, must
be determined one way or the other by the present session of
Congress.  The last session really did nothing which can be
considered final as to these questions.  The Civil Rights Bill and
the Freedmen's Bureau Bill and the proposed constitutional
amendments, with the amendment already adopted and recognized as
the law of the land, do not reach the difficulty, and cannot,
unless the whole structure of the government is changed from a
government by States to something like a despotic central
government, with power to control even the municipal regulations of
States, and to make them conform to its own despotic will.  While
there remains such an idea as the right of each State to control
its own local affairs, &mdash; an idea, by the way, more
<pb n="762"/>
deeply
rooted in the minds of men of all sections of the country than
perhaps any one other political idea, &mdash; no general assertion of
human rights can be of any practical value.  To change the
character of the government at this point is neither possible nor
desirable.  All that is necessary to be done is to make the
government consistent with itself, and render the rights of the
States compatible with the sacred rights of human nature.
</p><p>The arm of the Federal government is long, but it is far too
short to protect the rights of individuals in the interior of
distant States.  They must have the power to protect themselves, or
they will go unprotected, spite of all the laws the Federal
government can put upon the national statute-book.
</p><p>Slavery, like all other great systems of wrong, founded in the
depths of human selfishness, and existing for ages, has not
neglected its own conservation.  It has steadily exerted an
influence upon all around it favorable to its own continuance.  And
to-day it is so strong that it could exist, not only without law,
but even against law.  Custom, manners, morals, religion, are all
on its side everywhere in the South; and when you add the ignorance
and servility of the ex-slave to the intelligence and accustomed
authority of the master, you have the conditions, not out of which
slavery will again grow, but under which it is impossible for the
Federal government to wholly destroy it, unless the Federal
government be armed with despotic power, to blot out State
authority, and to station a Federal officer at every cross-road.
This, of course, cannot be done, and ought not even if it could.
The true way and the easiest way is to make our government entirely
consistent with itself, and give to every loyal citizen the
elective franchise, &mdash; a right and power which will be ever present,
and will form a wall of fire for his protection.
</p><p>One of the invaluable compensations of the late Rebellion is
the highly instructive disclosure it made of the true source of
danger to republican government.  Whatever may be tolerated in
monarchical and despotic governments, no republic is safe that
tolerates a privileged class, or denies to any of its citizens
equal rights and equal means to maintain them.  What was theory
before the war has been made fact by the war.
</p><p>There is cause to be thankful even for rebellion.  It is an
impressive teacher, though a stern and terrible one.  In both
characters it has come to us, and it was perhaps needed in both.
It is an instructor never a day before its time, for it comes only
when all other means of progress and enlightenment have failed.
Whether the oppressed and despairing bondman, no longer able to
repress his deep yearnings for manhood, or the tyrant, in his pride
and impatience, takes the initiative, and strikes the blow for a
firmer hold and a longer lease of oppression, the result is the
same, &mdash; society is instructed, or may be.
</p><p>Such are the limitations of the common mind, and so thoroughly
engrossing are the cares of common life, that only the few among
men can discern through the glitter and dazzle of present
prosperity the dark outlines of approaching disasters, even though
they may have come up to our very gates, and are already within
striking distance.  The yawning seam and corroded bolt conceal
their defects from the mariner until the storm calls all hands to
the pumps.  Prophets, indeed, were abundant before the war; but who
cares for prophets while their predictions remain unfulfilled, and
the calamities of which they tell are masked behind a blinding
blaze of national prosperity?
</p><p>It is asked, said Henry Clay, on a memorable occasion, Will
slavery never come to an end?  That question, said he, was asked
fifty years ago, and it has been answered by fifty years of
unprecedented prosperity.  Spite of the eloquence of the earnest
Abolitionists, &mdash; poured out against slavery during thirty years, &mdash;
even they must confess, that, in all the probabilities of the case,
that system of barbarism would
<pb n="763"/>
have continued its horrors
far beyond the limits of the nineteenth century but for the
Rebellion, and perhaps only have disappeared at last in a fiery
conflict, even more fierce and bloody than that which has now been
suppressed.
</p><p>It is no disparagement to truth, that it can only prevail
where reason prevails.  War begins where reason ends.  The thing
worse than rebellion is the thing that causes rebellion.  What that
thing is, we have been taught to our cost.  It remains now to be
seen whether we have the needed courage to have that cause entirely
removed from the Republic.  At any rate, to this grand work of
national regeneration and entire purification Congress must now
address Itself, with full purpose that the work shall this time be
thoroughly done.  The deadly upas, root and branch, leaf and fibre,
body and sap, must be utterly destroyed.  The country is evidently
not in a condition to listen patiently to pleas for postponement,
however plausible, nor will it permit the responsibility to be
shifted to other shoulders.  Authority and power are here
commensurate with the duty imposed.  There are no cloud-flung
shadows to obscure the way.  Truth shines with brighter light and
intenser heat at every moment, and a country torn and rent and
bleeding implores relief from its distress and agony.
</p><p>If time was at first needed, Congress has now had time.  All
the requisite materials from which to form an intelligent judgment
are now before it.  Whether its members look at the origin, the
progress, the termination of the war, or at the mockery of a peace
now existing, they will find only one unbroken chain of argument in
favor of a radical policy of reconstruction.  For the omissions of
the last session, some excuses may be allowed.  A treacherous
President stood in the way; and it can be easily seen how reluctant
good men might be to admit an apostasy which involved so much of
baseness and ingratitude.  It was natural that they should seek to
save him by bending to him even when he leaned to the side of
error.  But all is changed now.  Congress knows now that it must go
on without his aid, and even against his machinations.  The
advantage of the present session over the last is immense.  Where
that investigated, this has the facts.  Where that walked by faith,
this may walk by sight.  Where that halted, this must go forward,
and where that failed, this must succeed, giving the country whole
measures where that gave us half-measures, merely as a means of
saving the elections in a few doubtful districts.  That Congress
saw what was right, but distrusted the enlightenment of the loyal
masses; but what was forborne in distrust of the people must now be
done with a full knowledge that the people expect and require it.
The members go to Washington fresh from the inspiring presence of
the people.  In every considerable public meeting, and in almost
every conceivable way, whether at court-house, school-house, or
cross-roads, in doors and out, the subject has been discussed, and
the people have emphatically pronounced in favor of a radical
policy.  Listening to the doctrines of expediency and compromise
with pity, impatience, and disgust, they have everywhere broken
into demonstrations of the wildest enthusiasm when a brave word has
been spoken in favor of equal rights and impartial suffrage.
Radicalism, so far from being odious, is not the popular passport
to power.  The men most bitterly charged with it go to Congress
with the largest majorities, while the timid and doubtful are sent
by lean majorities, or else left at home.  The strange controversy
between the President and the Congress, at one time so threatening,
is disposed of by the people.  The high reconstructive powers which
he so confidently, ostentatiously, and haughtily claimed, have been
disallowed, denounced, and utterly repudiated; while those claimed
by Congress have been confirmed.
</p><p>Of the spirit and magnitude of the canvass nothing need be
said.  The
<pb n="764"/>
appeal was to the people, and the verdict was
worthy of the tribunal.  Upon an occasion of his own selection,
with the advice and approval of his astute Secretary, soon after
the members of the Congress had returned to their constituents, the
President quitted the executive mansion, sandwiched himself between
two recognized heroes, &mdash; men whom the whole country delighted to
honor, &mdash; and, with all the advantage which such company could give
him, stumped the country from the Atlantic to the Mississippi,
advocating everywhere his policy as against that of Congress.  It
was a strange sight, and perhaps the most disgraceful exhibition
ever made by any President; but, as no evil is entirely unmixed,
good has come of this, as from many others.  Ambitious,
unscrupulous, energetic, indefatigable, voluble, and plausible, &mdash; a
political gladiator, ready for a "set-to" in any crowd, &mdash; he is
beaten in his own chosen field, and stands to-day before the
country as a convicted usurper, a political criminal, guilty of a
bold and persistent attempt to possess himself of the legislative
powers solemnly secured to Congress by the Constitution.  No
vindication could be more complete, no condemnation could be more
absolute and humiliating.  Unless reopened by the sword, as
recklessly threatened in some circles, this question is now closed
for all time.
</p><p>Without attempting to settle here the metaphysical and
somewhat theological question (about which so much has already been
said and written), whether once in the Union means always in the
Union, &mdash; agreeably to the formula, Once in grace always in grace, &mdash;
it is obvious to common sense that the rebellious States stand to-day, in point of law, precisely where they stood when, exhausted,
beaten, conquered, they fell powerless at the feet of Federal
authority.  Their State governments were overthrown, and the lives
and property of the leaders of the Rebellion were forfeited.  In
reconstructing the institutions of these shattered and overthrown
States, Congress should begin with a clean slate, and make clean
work of it.  Let there be no hesitation.  It would be a cowardly
deference to a defeated and treacherous President, if any account
were made of the illegitimate, one-sided, sham governments hurried
into existence for a malign purpose in the absence of Congress.
These pretended governments, which were never submitted to the
people, and from participation in which four millions of the loyal
people were excluded by Presidential order, should now be treated
according to their true character, as shams and impositions, and
supplanted by true and legitimate governments, in the formation of
which loyal men, black and white, shall participate.
</p><p>It is not, however, within the scope of this paper to point
out the precise steps to be taken, and the means to be employed.
The people are less concerned about these than the grand end to be
attained.  They demand such a reconstruction as shall put an end to
the present anarchical state of things in the late rebellious
States, &mdash; where frightful murders and wholesale massacres are
perpetrated in the very presence of Federal soldiers.  This
horrible business they require shall cease.  They want a
reconstruction such as will protect loyal men, black and white, in
their persons and property; such a one as will cause Northern
industry, Northern capital, and Northern civilization to flow into
the South, and make a man from New England as much at home in
Carolina as elsewhere in the Republic.  No Chinese wall can now be
tolerated.  The South must be opened to the light of law and
liberty, and this session of Congress is relied upon to accomplish
this important work.
</p><p>The plain, common-sense way of doing this work, as intimated
at the beginning, is simply to establish in the South one law, one
government, one administration of justice, one condition to the
exercise of the elective franchise, for men of all races and colors
alike.  This great measure is sought as earnestly
<pb n="765"/>
by loyal
white men as by loyal blacks, and is needed alike by both.  Let
sound political prescience but take the place of an unreasoning
prejudice, and this will be done.
</p><p>Men denounce the negro for his prominence in this discussion;
but it is no fault of his that in peace as in war, that in
conquering Rebel armies as in reconstructing the rebellious States,
the right of the negro is the true solution of our national
troubles.  The stern logic of events, which goes directly to the
point, disdaining all concern for the color or features of men, has
determined the interests of the country as identical with and
inseparable from those of the negro.
</p><p>The policy that emancipated and armed the negro &mdash; now seen to
have been wise and proper by the dullest &mdash; was not certainly more
sternly demanded than is now the policy of enfranchisement.  If
with the negro was success in war, and without him failure, so in
peace it will be found that the nation must fall or flourish with
the negro.
</p><p>Fortunately, the Constitution of the United States knows no
distinction between citizens on account of color.  Neither does it
know any difference between a citizen of a State and a citizen of
the United States.  Citizenship evidently includes all the rights
of citizens, whether State or national.  If the Constitution knows
none, it is clearly no part of the duty of a Republican Congress
now to institute one.  The mistake of the last session was the
attempt to do this very thing, by a renunciation of its power to
secure political rights to any class of citizens, with the obvious
purpose to allow the rebellious States to disfranchise, if they
should see fit, their colored citizens.  This unfortunate blunder
must now be retrieved, and the emasculated citizenship given to the
negro supplanted by that contemplated in the Constitution of the
United States, which declares that the citizens of each State shall
enjoy all the rights and immunities of citizens of the several
States, &mdash; so that a legal voter in any State shall be a legal voter
in all the States.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
