<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DubNegr"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="DubNegr">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Negro Schoolmaster in the New South</title>
<title type="sort">negro schoolmaster in the new south</title>
<author>Du Bois, W. E. Burghardt</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">25</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">DubNegr</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475898</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Negro Schoolmaster in the New South</title>
<title type="sort">negro schoolmaster in the new south</title>
<author>W. E. Burghardt Du Bois</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 83</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 99-104</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>All dates in letters have been standardized in the yyyymmdd
format.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text
Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of
the text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in
SpeFQue1 for page one of Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term>
<term>democracy</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction; prose</term>
<term>African American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-04">April 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Timothy Jarrett</name>
</respStmt>
<item>minimal TEI markup</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">
<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
<pb n="99"/>

<p>ONCE upon a time I taught school in the hills of Tennessee, where
the broad dark vale of the Mississippi begins to roll and crumple to greet
the Alleghanies.  I was a Fisk student then, and all Fisk men think that
Tennessee &mdash; beyond the Veil &mdash; is theirs alone, and in vacation time they
sally forth in lusty bands to meet the county school commissioners.
Young and happy, I too went, and I shall not soon forget that summer,
ten years ago.</p>
<p>First, there was a teachers' Institute at the county-seat; and there
distinguished guests of the superintendent taught the teachers fractions
and spelling and other mysteries, &mdash; white teachers in the morning,
Negroes at night.  A picnic now and then, and a supper, and the rough
world was softened by laughter and song.  I remember how &mdash;   But I
wander.</p>
<p>There came a day when all the teachers left the Institute, and
began the hunt for schools.  I learn from hearsay (for my mother was
mortally afraid of firearms) that the hunting of ducks and bears and men
is wonderfully interesting, but I am sure that the man who has never
hunted a country school has something to learn of the pleasures of the
chase.  I see now the white, hot roads lazily rise and fall and wind
before me under the burning July sun; I feel the deep weariness of heart
and limb, as ten, eight, six miles stretch relentlessly ahead; I feel my
heart sink heavily as I hear again and again, "Got a teacher?  Yes."  So I
walked on and on, &mdash;  horses were too expensive, &mdash; until I had wandered
beyond railways, beyond stage lines, to a land of "varmints" and
rattlesnakes, where the coming of a stranger was an event, and men lived
and died in the shadow of one blue hill.</p>
<p>Sprinkled over hill and dale lay cabins and farmhouses, shut out
from the world by the forests and the rolling hills toward the east.
There I found at last a little school.  Josie told me of it; she was a thin,
homely girl of twenty, with a dark brown face and thick, hard hair.  I
had crossed the stream at Watertown, and rested under the great
willows; then I had gone to the little cabin in the lot where Josie was
resting on her way to town.  The gaunt farmer made me welcome, and
Josie, hearing my errand, told me anxiously that they wanted a school
over the hill; that but once since the war had a teacher been there;

<pb n="100"/>  that she herself longed to learn, &mdash; and thus she ran on,
talking fast and loud, with much earnestness and energy.</p>
<p>Next morning I crossed the tall round hill, lingered to look at the
blue and yellow mountains stretching toward the Carolinas; then I
plunged into the wood, and came out at Josie's home.  It was a dull
frame cottage with four rooms, perched just below the brow of the hill,
amid peach trees.  The father was a quiet, simple soul, calmly ignorant,
with no touch of vulgarity.  The mother was different, &mdash; strong,
bustling, and energetic, with a quick, restless tongue, and an ambition to
live "like folks."  There was a crowd of children.  Two boys had gone
away.  There remained two growing girls; a shy midget of eight; John,
tall, awkward, and eighteen; Jim, younger, quicker, and better looking;
and two babies of indefinite age.  Then there was Josie herself.  She
seemed to be the centre of the family: always busy at service or at home,
or berry-picking; a little nervous and inclined to scold, like her mother,
yet faithful, too, like her father.  She had about her a certain fineness,
the shadow of an unconscious moral heroism that would willingly give
all of life to make life broader, deeper, and fuller for her and hers.  I
saw much of this family afterward, and grew to love them for their
honest efforts to be decent and comfortable, and for their knowledge of
their own ignorance.  There was with them no affectation.  The mother
would scold the father for being so "easy;" Josie would roundly rate the
boys for carelessness; and all knew that it was a hard thing to dig a
living out of a rocky side hill.</p>
<p>I secured the school.  I remember the day I rode horseback out to
the commissioner's house, with a pleasant young white fellow, who
wanted the white school.  The road ran down the bed of a stream; the
sun laughed and the water jingled, and we rode on.  "Come in," said the
commissioner, &mdash; "come in.  Have a seat.  Yes, that certificate will do.
Stay to dinner.  What do you want a month?"  Oh, thought I, this is
lucky; but even then fell the awful shadow of the Veil, for they ate first,
then I &mdash; alone.</p>
<p>The schoolhouse was a log hut, where Colonel Wheeler used to
shelter his corn.  It sat in a lot behind a rail fence and thorn bushes, near
the sweetest of springs.  There was an entrance where a door once was,
and within, a massive rickety fireplace; great chinks between the logs
served as windows.  Furniture was scarce.  A pale blackboard crouched
in the corner.  My desk was made of three boards, reinforced at critical
points, and my chair, borrowed from the landlady, had to be returned
every night.  Seats for the children, &mdash; these puzzled me much.  I was
haunted by a New England vision of neat little desks and chairs, but,
alas, the reality was rough plank benches without backs, and at times
without legs.  They had the one virtue of making naps dangerous, &mdash;
possibly fatal, for the floor was not to be trusted.</p>
<p>It was a hot morning late in July when the school opened.  I
trembled when I heard the patter of little feet down the dusty road, and
saw the growing row of dark solemn faces and bright eager eyes facing
me.  First came Josie and her brothers and sisters.  The longing to
know, to be a student in the great school at Nashville, hovered like a star
above this child woman amid her work and worry, and she studied
doggedly.  There were the Dowells from their farm over toward
Alexandria: Fanny, with her smooth black face and wondering eyes;
Martha, brown and dull; the pretty girl wife of a brother, and the
younger brood.  There were the Burkes, two brown and yellow lads, and
a tiny haughty-eyed girl.  Fat Reuben's little chubby girl came, with
golden face and old gold hair, faithful and solemn.  'Thenie was on hand
early, &mdash; a jolly, ugly, good-hearted girl, who slyly dipped snuff and
looked

<pb n="101"/>  after her little bow-legged brother.  When her mother
could spare her, 'Tildy came, &mdash; a midnight beauty, with starry eyes and
tapering limbs; and her brother, correspondingly homely.  And then the
big boys: the hulking Lawrences; the lazy Neills, unfathered sons of
mother and daughter; Hickman, with a stoop in his shoulders; and the
rest.</p>
<p>There they sat, nearly thirty of them, on the rough benches, their
faces shading from a pale cream to a deep brown, the little feet bare and
swinging, the eyes full of expectation, with here and there a twinkle of
mischief, and the hands grasping Webster's blue-back spelling-book.  I
loved my school, and the fine faith the children had in the wisdom of
their teacher was truly marvelous.  We read and spelled together, wrote
a little, picked flowers, sang, and listened to stories of the world beyond
the hill.  At times the school would dwindle away, and I would start out.
I would visit Mun Eddings, who lived in two very dirty rooms, and ask
why little Lugene, whose flaming face seemed ever ablaze with the dark
red hair uncombed, was absent all last week, or why I missed so often
the inimitable rags of Mack and Ed.  Then the father, who worked
Colonel Wheeler's farm on shares, would tell me how the crops needed
the boys; and the thin, slovenly mother, whose face was pretty when
washed, assured me that Lugene must mind the baby.  "But we'll start
them again next week."  When the Lawrences stopped, I knew that the
doubts of the old folks about book-learning had conquered again, and
so, toiling up the hill, and getting as far into the cabin as possible, I put
Cicero pro Archia Poeta into the simplest English with local applications,
and usually convinced them &mdash; for a week or so.</p>
<p>On Friday nights I often went home with some of the children;
sometimes to Doc Burke's farm.  He was a great, loud, thin Black, ever
working, and trying to buy the seventy-five acres of hill and dale where
he lived; but people said that he would surely fail, and the "white folks
would get it all."  His wife was a magnificent Amazon, with saffron face
and shining hair, uncorseted and barefooted, and the children were
strong and beautiful.  They lived in a one-and-a-half-room cabin in the
hollow of the farm, near the spring.  The front room was full of great fat
white beds, scrupulously neat; and there were bad chromos on the walls,
and a tired centre-table.  In the tiny back kitchen I was often invited to
"take out and help" myself to fried chicken and wheat biscuit, "meat"
and corn pone, string beans and berries.  At first I used to be a little
alarmed at the approach of bed-time in the one lone bedroom, but
embarrassment was very deftly avoided.  First, all the children nodded
and slept, and were stowed away in one great pile of goose feathers;
next, the mother and the father discreetly slipped away to the kitchen
while I went to bed; then, blowing out the dim light, they retired in the
dark.  In the morning all were up and away before I thought of awaking.
Across the road, where fat Reuben lived, they all went outdoors while
the teacher retired, because they did not boast the luxury of a
kitchen.</p>
<p>I liked to stay with the Dowells, for they had four rooms and
plenty of good country fare.  Uncle Bird had a small, rough farm, all
woods and hills, miles from the big road; but he was full of tales, &mdash; he
preached now and then, &mdash; and with his children, berries, horses, and
wheat he was happy and prosperous.  Often, to keep the peace, I must
go where life was less lovely; for instance, 'Tildy's mother was
incorrigibly dirty, Reuben's larder was limited seriously, and herds of
untamed bedbugs wandered over the Eddingses' beds.  Best of all I loved
to go to Josie's, and sit on the porch, eating peaches, while the mother
bustled and talked: how Josie had bought the sewing-machine; how

<pb n="102"/>  Josie worked at service in winter, but that four dollars
a month was "mighty little" wages; how Josie longed to go away to
school, but that it "looked like" they never could get far enough ahead to
let her; how the crops failed and the well was yet unfinished; and,
finally, how "mean" some of the white folks were.</p>
<p>For two summers I lived in this little world; it was dull and
humdrum.  The girls looked at the hill in wistful longing, and the boys
fretted, and haunted Alexandria.  Alexandria was "town," &mdash; a straggling,
lazy village of houses, churches, and shops, and an aristocracy of Toms,
Dicks, and Captains.  Cuddled on the hill to the north was the village of
the colored folks, who lived in three or four room unpainted cottages,
some neat and homelike, and some dirty.  The dwellings were scattered
rather aimlessly, but they centred about the twin temples of the hamlet,
the Methodist and the Hard-Shell Baptist churches.  These, in turn,
leaned gingerly on a sad-colored schoolhouse.  Hither my little world
wended its crooked way on Sunday to meet other worlds, and gossip,
and wonder, and make the weekly sacrifice with frenzied priest at the
altar of the "old-time religion."  Then the soft melody and mighty
cadences of Negro song fluttered and thundered.</p>
<p>I have called my tiny community a world, and so its isolation
made it; and yet there was among us but a half-awakened common
consciousness, sprung from common joy and grief, at burial, birth, or
wedding; from a common hardship in poverty, poor land, and low
wages; and, above all, from the sight of the Veil that hung between us
and Opportunity.  All this caused us to think some thoughts together; but
these, when ripe for speech, were spoken in various languages.  Those
whose eyes thirty and more years before had seen "the glory of the
coming of the Lord" saw in every present hindrance or help a dark
fatalism bound to bring all things right in His own good time.  The mass
of those to whom slavery was a dim recollection of childhood found the
world a puzzling thing: it asked little of them, and they answered with
little, and yet it ridiculed their offering.  Such a paradox they could not
understand, and therefore sank into listless indifference, or shiftlessness,
or reckless bravado.  There were, however, some such as Josie, Jim,
and Ben, &mdash; they to whom War, Hell, and Slavery were but childhood
tales, whose young appetites had been whetted to an edge by school and
story and half-awakened thought.  Ill could they be content, born without
and beyond the World.  And their weak wings beat against their barriers,
&mdash; barriers of caste, of youth, of life; at last, in dangerous moments,
against everything that opposed even a whim. </p>
<p>The ten years that follow youth, the years when first the realization
comes that life is leading somewhere, &mdash; these were the years that passed
after I left my little school.  When they were past, I came by chance
once more to the walls of Fisk University, to the halls of the chapel of
melody.  As I lingered there in the joy and pain of meeting old school
friends, there swept over me a sudden longing to pass again beyond the
blue hill, and to see the homes and the school of other days, and to learn
how life had gone with my school-children; and I went.</p>
<p>Josie was dead, and the gray-haired mother said simply, "We've
had a heap of trouble since you've been away."  I had feared for Jim.
With a cultured parentage and a social caste to uphold him, he might
have made a venturesome merchant or a West Point cadet.  But here he
was, angry with life and reckless; and when Farmer Durham charged
him with stealing wheat, the old man had to ride fast to escape the stones
which the furious fool hurled after him.  They told

<pb n="103"/>  Jim to run away; but he would not run, and the
constable came that afternoon.  It grieved Josie, and great awkward John
walked nine miles every day to see his little brother through the bars of
Lebanon jail.  At last the two came back together in the dark night.  The
mother cooked supper, and Josie emptied her purse, and the boys stole
away.  Josie grew thin and silent, yet worked the more.  The hill became
steep for the quiet old father, and with the boys away there was little to
do in the valley.  Josie helped them sell the old farm, and they moved
nearer town.  Brother Dennis, the carpenter, built a new house with six
rooms; Josie toiled a year in Nashville, and brought back ninety dollars
to furnish the house and change it to a home.</p>
<p>When the spring came, and the birds twittered, and the stream ran
proud and full, little sister Lizzie, bold and thoughtless, flushed with the
passion of youth, bestowed herself on the tempter, and brought home a
nameless child.  Josie shivered, and worked on, with the vision of
schooldays all fled, with a face wan and tired,&mdash;
worked until, on a
summer's day, some one married another; then Josie crept to her mother
like a hurt child, and slept &mdash; and sleeps.</p>
<p>I paused to scent the breeze as I entered the valley.  The
Lawrences have gone; father and son forever, and the other son lazily
digs in the earth to live.  A new young widow rents out their cabin to fat
Reuben.  Reuben is a Baptist preacher now, but I fear as lazy as ever,
though his cabin has three rooms; and little Ella has grown into a
bouncing woman, and is ploughing corn on the hot hillside.  There are
babies a plenty, and one half-witted girl.  Across the valley is a house I
did not know before, and there I found, rocking one baby and expecting
another, one of my schoolgirls, a daughter of Uncle Bird Dowell.  She
looked somewhat worried with her new duties, but soon bristled into
pride over her neat cabin, and the tale of her thrifty husband, the horse
and cow, and the farm they were planning to buy.</p>
<p>My log schoolhouse was gone.  In its place stood Progress, and
Progress, I understand, is necessarily ugly.  The crazy foundation stones
still marked the former site of my poor little cabin, and not far away, on
six weary boulders, perched a jaunty board house, perhaps twenty by
thirty feet, with three windows and a door that locked.  Some of the
window glass was broken, and part of an old iron stove lay mournfully
under the house.  I peeped through the window half reverently, and
found things that were more familiar.  The blackboard had grown by
about two feet, and the seats were still without backs.  The county owns
the lot now, I hear, and every year there is a session of school.  As I sat
by the spring and looked on the Old and the New I felt glad, very glad,
and yet &mdash; </p>
<p>After two long drinks I started on.  There was the great double log
house on the corner.  I remembered the broken, blighted family that used
to live there.  The strong, hard face of the mother, with its wilderness of
hair, rose before me.  She had driven her husband away, and while I
taught school a strange man lived there, big and jovial, and people
talked.  I felt sure that Ben and 'Tildy would come to naught from such
a home.  But this is an odd world; for Ben is a busy farmer in Smith
County, "doing well, too," they say, and he had cared for little 'Tildy
until last spring, when a lover married her.  A hard life the lad had led,
toiling for meat, and laughed at because he was homely and crooked.
There was Sam Carlon, an impudent old skinflint, who had definite
notions about niggers, and hired Ben a summer and would not pay him.
Then the hungry boy gathered his sacks together, and in broad daylight
went into Carlon's corn; and when the hard-fisted farmer set upon him,
the angry boy flew at him

<pb n="104"/>  like a beast.  Doc Burke saved a murder and a
lynching that day.</p>
<p>The story reminded me again of the Burkes, and an impatience
seized me to know who won in the battle, Doc or the seventy-five acres.
For it is a hard thing to make a farm out of nothing, even in fifteen
years.  So I hurried on, thinking of the Burkes.  They used to have a
certain magnificent barbarism about them that I liked.  They were never
vulgar, never immoral, but rather rough and primitive, with an
unconventionality that spent itself in loud guffaws, slaps on the back, and
naps in the corner.  I hurried by the cottage of the misborn Neill boys.
It was empty, and they were grown into fat, lazy farm hands.  I saw the
home of the Hickmans, but Albert, with his stooping shoulders, had
passed from the world.  Then I came to the Burkes' gate and peered
through; the inclosure looked rough and untrimmed, and yet there were
the same fences around the old farm save to the left, where lay
twenty-five other acres.  And lo! the cabin in the hollow had climbed the
hill and swollen to a half-finished six-room cottage.</p>
<p>The Burkes held a hundred acres, but they were still in debt.
Indeed, the gaunt father who toiled night and day would scarcely be
happy out of debt, being so used to it.  Some day he must stop, for his
massive frame is showing decline.  The mother wore shoes, but the
lionlike physique of other days was broken.  The children had grown up.
Rob, the image of his father, was loud and rough with laughter.  Birdie,
my school baby of six, had grown to a picture of maiden beauty, tall and
tawny.  "Edgar is gone," said the mother, with head half bowed, &mdash;
"gone to work in Nashville; he and his father couldn't agree."</p>
<p>Little Doc, the boy born since the time of my school, took me
horseback down the creek next morning toward Farmer Dowell's.  The
road and the stream were battling for mastery, and the stream had the
better of it.  We splashed and waded, and the merry boy, perched behind
me, chattered and laughed.  He showed me where Simon Thompson had
bought a bit of ground and a home; but his daughter Lana, a plump,
brown, slow girl, was not there.  She had married a man and a farm
twenty miles away.  We wound on down the stream till we came to a
gate that I did not recognize, but the boy insisted that it was "Uncle
Bird's."  The farm was fat with the growing crop.  In that little valley
was a strange stillness as I rode up; for death and marriage had stolen
youth, and left age and childhood there.  We sat and talked that night,
after the chores were done.  Uncle Bird was grayer, and his eyes did not
see so well, but he was still jovial.  We talked of the acres bought, &mdash;
one hundred and twenty-five, &mdash; of the new guest chamber added, of
Martha's marrying.  Then we talked of death: Fanny and Fred were
gone; a shadow hung over the other daughter, and when it lifted she was
to go to Nashville to school.  At last we spoke of the neighbors, and as
night fell Uncle Bird told me how, on a night like that, 'Thenie came
wandering back to her home over yonder, to escape the blows of her
husband.  And next morning she died in the home that her little
bow-legged brother, working and saving, had bought for their widowed
mother.</p>
<p>My journey was done, and behind me lay hill and dale, and Life
and Death.  How shall man measure Progress there where the dark-faced Josie lies?  How many heartfuls of sorrow shall balance a bushel
of wheat?  How hard a thing is life to the lowly, and yet how human and
real!  And all this life and love and strife and failure, &mdash; is it the twilight
of nightfall or the flush of some faint-dawning day?</p>
<p>Thus sadly musing, I rode to Nashville in the Jim Crow car.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

