<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="EasMadn"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="EasMadn">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Madness of Bald Eagle</title>
<title type="sort">madness of bald eagle</title>
<author>Eastman, Charles Alexander, 1858-1939</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">11</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">EasMadn</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475906</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Judy Boss has made the following changes: p. 143: to day] to-day</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Madness of Bald Eagle</title>
<title level="j">The Southern Workman</title>
<title type="sort">madness of bald eagle</title>
<author>Charles A. Eastman</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 141-143</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Hampton Institute</publisher>
<pubPlace>Hampton, Va.</pubPlace>
<date value="1905-03">March 1905</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVA library call no. LC2701 .S7</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Southern Workman 34 (Mar. 1905): 141-143</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1905">1905</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-11">November 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Michele Ierardi</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="141"/>
<head>The Madness of Bald Eagle<lb/>
CHARLES A. EASTMAN
</head>
<p>IT was many years ago, when I was only a child, began White
Ghost, the patriarchal old chief of the Yanktonnais Sioux, that our
band was engaged in a desperate battle with the Rees and Mandans.
The cause of the fight was a peculiar one.  I will tell you about it.
And he laid aside his long-stemmed pipe and settled himself to the
recital.
</p><p>At that time the Yanktonnais numbered a little over forty
families.  We were nicknamed by the other bands Shunkikoheka, or
Domestic Dogs, because of our owning large numbers of these
animals.  My father was the head chief.
</p><p>Our favorite wintering place was a timbered tract near the
mouth of the Grand River, and it was here that we met the
Blackfoot Sioux in the fall hunt.  On the opposite side of the river
from our camp was the permanent village of the Rees and Mandans,
whose houses were of dirt and partly underground.  For a hundred
years before this time they had planted large gardens, and we were
accustomed to buy of them corn, beans, and pumpkins.  From time
to time our people had made treaties of peace with them.  Each
family of the Rees had one or two buffalo boats&mdash;not round as the
Sioux made them, but two or three skins long.  In these boats they
brought quantities of dried beans and other vegetables to trade with
us for jerked buffalo meat.
</p><p>It was a great gathering and a time of general festivity and
hospitality.  The Sioux young men were courting the Ree girls, and
the Ree braves were courting our girls, while the old people bartered
their produce.  All day the river was alive with canoes and its banks
rang with the laughter of the youths and maidens.
</p><p>My father's younger brother, whose name was Big Whip, had a
close friend, a young man who ever after the event of which I am
<pb n="142"/>
about to tell you, was known as Bald Eagle.  They were both
daring young men and very ambitious for distinction.  They had
been following the Ree girls to their canoes as they returned to their
homes in the evening.
</p><p>Big Whip and his friend stood upon the river bank at sunset,
one with a quiver full of arrows upon his back while the other
carried a gun under his blanket.  Nearly all the people of the other
village had crossed the river, and the chief of the Rees, whose name
was Bald Eagle, went home with his wife last of all.  It was about
dusk as they entered their bull-hide boat, and the two Sioux stood
there looking at them.
</p><p>Suddenly Big Whip exclaimed: "Friend, let us kill the chief.  I
dare you to kill and scalp him!"  His friend replied:&mdash;
</p><p>"It shall be as you say.  I will stand by you in all things.  I am
willing to die with you."
</p><p>Accordingly Bald Eagle pulled out his gun and shot the Ree
dead.  From that day he took his name.  The old man fell backward
into his boat and the old woman screamed and wept as she rowed
him across the river.  The other young man shot an arrow or two at
the wife, but she continued to row until she reached the other bank.
</p><p>There was great excitement on both sides of the river as soon
as the people saw what had happened.  There were two camps of
Sioux, the Blackfoot Sioux and the Yanktonnais, or our people.  Of
course the Mandans and Rees greatly outnumbered us; their camp
must have numbered two or three thousand, which was more than
we had in our combined camps.
</p><p>There was a Sioux whose name was Black Shield, who had
inter-married among the Rees.  He came down to the opposite bank
of the Missouri and shouted to us:&mdash;
</p><p>"Of which one of your bands is the man who killed Bald
Eagle?"
</p><p>One of the Blackfoot Sioux replied:
</p><p>"It is a man of the Yanktonnais Sioux who killed Bald Eagle."
</p><p>Then he said: "The Rees wish to do battle with them; you had
better withdraw from their camp."
</p><p>Accordingly the Blackfeet retired about a mile from us upon
the bluffs and pitched their tents, while the Yanktonnais remained
on the flats.  The two bands had been great rivals in courage and the
art of war, so we did not ask for help from our kinsfolk, but during
the night we dug trenches about the camp, the inner one for the
women and children, and the outer one for the men to stay in and do
battle.
</p><p>The next morning at daybreak the enemy landed and
approached our camp in great numbers.  Some of their women and
old men came also, and sat upon the bluffs to watch the fight and to
carry off their dead and wounded.  The Blackfeet likewise were
watching the battle from the bluffs, and just before the fight began
one Blackfoot came in with his wife and joined us.  His name was
Red Dog's Track, but
<pb n="143"/>
from that day he was called He-Came-Back.  His wife was a Yanktonnais, and he had said to her:
"If I don't join your tribe to-day, my brothers-in-law will call me a
coward."
</p><p>The Sioux were well entrenched and well armed with guns and
arrows, and their aim was deadly, so that the Rees crawled up
gradually and took every opportunity to pick off any Sioux who
ventured to show his head above the trenches.  In like manner every
Ree who exposed himself was sure to die.
</p><p>Up to this time no one had seen the two men who made all the
trouble.  There was a natural hollow in the bank, concealed by
buffalo berry bushes, very near where they stood when Bald Eagle
shot the Ree.
</p><p>"Friend," said Big Whip, "it is likely that our own people will
punish us for this deed.  They will pursue and kill us wherever they
find us.  They have the right to do this.  The best thing is to drop
into this washout and remain there until they cease to look for us."
</p><p>They did so, and remained hidden during the night.  But after
the fight began, Big Whip said again: "Friend, we are the cause of
the deaths of many brave men this day.  We committed the act to
show our bravery.  We dared each other to do it.  It will now
become us as warriors to join our band."
</p><p>Then both stripped, and taking their weapons in hand ran
toward the camp.  They had to pass directly through the enemy's
lines, but they were not recognized till they had fairly passed them.
Then they were between two fires.  When they had almost reached
the entrenchment, they faced about and fired at the Rees, jumping
about incessantly to avoid being hit, as is the Indian fashion.
Bullets and arrows were flying all about them like hail, but at last
they dropped back unhurt into the Sioux trenches.  Thus the two
men saved their reputation for bravery, and their people never
openly reproached them for the events of that day.  Young men are
often rash, but it is not well to reprove one for a brave deed lest he
become a coward.
</p><p>Many were killed but more of the Rees than of our band.
About the middle of the afternoon there came a cold rain.  It was in
the fall of the year.  The bow-strings were wet, and the guns were
only flint-locks.  You know when the flint becomes wet it is useless,
and it looked as if the fight must be with knives.
</p><p>But the Rees were much disheartened.  They had lost many.
The women were all the time carrying off the wounded, and there
were the Blackfoot Sioux watching them from the hills.  They
turned and fled toward the river.  The Sioux followed like crazy
wolves, tomahawking the tired and slow ones.  Many were killed at
the boats, and some of the boats were punctured with shot and sank.
Some carried a load of Sioux arrows back across the river.  That
was the greatest battle ever fought by our band, the old man
concluded, with a deep sigh of mingled satisfaction and regret.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

