<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="GalWoma"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="GalWoma">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"The Woman Behind the Man"</title>
<title type="sort">the woman behind the man</title>
<author>Le Gallienne, Richard</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Charles Keller</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">37</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">GalWoma</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475976</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"The Woman Behind the Man"</title>
<title type="sort">the woman behind the man</title>
<author>Richard Le Gallienne</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Munsey's Magazine</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1916-03">March 1916</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Vol. 57, Num. 2, pp. 260-267</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Checked against University of Virginia library copy: AP2 M8 v.
LVII</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1916">1916</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-06">June 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header and minimal TEI tagging</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<front id="d2">
<titlePage id="d3">
	<pb/>
<docImprint>
MUNSEY'S MAGAZINE<lb/>

VOLUME LVII<lb/>

March, 1916<lb/>
Number 2<lb/>
pp. 260-267<lb/>
</docImprint>
</titlePage>
</front>


<body id="d4">

<div1 type="article" id="d5"><pb n="260"/>
<head>
The Woman<lb/>
Behind the Man<lb/>
by Richard Le Gallienne<lb/>
</head>

<p><hi rend="italic">Thus is a man created &mdash; to do all his work for some woman,
Do it for her and her only, only to lay at her feet;
Yet in his talk to pretend, shyly and fiercely maintain it,
That all is for love of the work &mdash; toil just for love of the toil.
Yet was there never a battle, but side by side with the soldiers,
Stern like the serried corn, fluttered the souls of the women,
As in and out through the corn go the blue-eyed shapes of the flowers;
Yet was there never a strength but a woman's softness upheld it,
Never a Thebes of our dreams but it rose to the music of woman &mdash;
Iron and stone it might stand, but the women had breathed on the building;
Yea, no man shall make or unmake, ere some woman hath made him a
man.</hi></p>

<p>GREAT men are impossible without great women.  Behind all
masculine greatness there is always present some woman as a
part of the process.
</p><p>Sometimes it is a woman who might well have been great on
her own account, had she not preferred to submerge her own
gifts and ambitions in those of son, husband, or brother.
Into the mysterious crucible of genius she has chosen to throw
as a most precious ingredient her own heart's blood, and too
often her tears.  She has been content to be the unseen oil
that feeds the glittering flame, and far too often this
ministry of hers has been taken for granted by its
beneficiaries, or has been acknowledged in some patronizing
foot-note in the biographies of the great.
</p><p>Some great men, such as Goethe or Byron, might be said to
be devourers of women.  They have absorbed their essences into
themselves as so much celestial food, ruthlessly used up their
devotion, and cast them aside like empty vessels.  Perhaps
neither the devourer; nor the world that worships them have
realized the nature and the all-importance of this sacrificial
gift of woman.  Possibly they have considered it as
accidental, and not really necessary; have considered that
they themselves were great anyway.  If so, theirs was a
grievous and most ungrateful illusion.
</p><p>No man has ever been great merely by his own strength.
The greatest brain would lie idle without woman to supply it
with motive power, either by her beauty, or her goodness, or
her own spiritual and intellectual influence.  Creation even
in the world of the mind is a dual process.  However solitary
the thinker, his thought is not born of himself alone.  The
brain of man would seem to need the impregnation of feminine
influence in some form or another before it can give birth to
its brain-children.
</p><p>"Without women nothing is possible," wrote Castiglione,
himself inspired by Elisabetta Gonzaga, one of the great women
of the Italian Renaissance, "either in military courage, or
art, or poetry, or music, or philosophy, or even religion.
God is truly seen only through them."
</p><p>And in our own time John Stuart Mill formulated, from his
own experience with his remarkable and dearly loved wife,
this

<pb n="261"/>
theory of the genesis of thought by feminine
suggestion:

</p><p>Who can tell how many of the original thoughts put forth
by male writers belong to a woman by suggestion, to themselves
only by verifying and working out?  If I may judge by my own
case, a very large proportion indeed.

</p><p>The noble dedication to his great book "On Liberty" makes
this inspiring acknowledgment of his indebtedness:

</p><p>To the beloved and deplored memory of her who was the
inspirer, and in part the author, of all that is best in my
writings &mdash; the friend and wife whose exalted sense of truth and
right was my strongest incitement, and whose approbation was
my chief reward &mdash; I dedicate this volume.  Like all that I have
written for many years, it belongs as much to her as to me.
</p><p>Were I but capable of interpreting to the world one-half
the great thoughts and noble feelings which are buried in her
grave, I should be the medium of a greater benefit to it than
is ever likely to arise from anything I can write, unprompted
and unassisted by her all but unrivaled wisdom.

</p><p>This must not be taken merely as a burst of affection.
There is no doubt that it represented the actual experience of
one whose life from childhood had been an unusual training in
hard thinking; and it may be taken as representative, rather
than exceptional, in the history of men of genius.
</p><p>No less lofty a scientist than Galileo owed a debt
scarcely less great to a well-loved daughter, a vivacious
young nun, Sister Celeste, whose delightful letters to her
father were published in 1891.
</p><p>"I pride myself," she says in one of these, "that I love
and revere my dearest father more, by far, than others love
their fathers, and I clearly perceive that, in return, he far
surpasses the greater part of other fathers in the love which
he has for me, his loved daughter."
</p><p>The letters are not merely full of gay daughterly
tenderness and womanly "mothering" touches, but reveal, too,
the active intellectual sympathy between father and daughter,
and the very real strength and inspiration she brought him in
dark hours, when, but for her, he might have faltered before
the menacing superstitions he was to destroy.  Her death
clearly revealed how much he had leaned upon her, and his own
soon followed.
</p><p>"I continually hear," he wrote to a friend, "myself called
by my dearly beloved daughter."
</p><p>For my present purpose, I prefer to set aside, as
suffering from no lack of full acknowledgment, the part played
by woman's beauty in the processes of greatness.  It is indeed
rather irrelevant to my theme; for beauty is an impersonal
quality, a quality which woman shares with the moon, a serious
rival, and many other objects and aspects of nature.  Woman's
beauty shines alike on the just and the unjust, and makes
poets and artists and murderers with a divine indifference.
</p><p>Though the beauty of Lais and Phryne made great sculptors
of Apelles and Praxiteles, the obligation of those great
artists to those fair women is not the kind I am thinking of.
The inspiration and influence I mean is a more human thing, a
generously exerted sympathy and comradeship, an inexhaustible
treasure of succor and self-sacrifice; the kind of help, as we
are speaking of the women of antiquity, that Aspasia brought
to Pericles, the kind of help that Aurelia, as mother brought
to Julius Caesar, that Livia, as wife, brought to Augustus,
and, as mother, brought to Tiberius; that Octavia, as sister,
brought to Augustus also; the kind of help that even a mother-in-law has sometimes given, as in the case of Cicero and his
mother-in-law, Laelia.
</p><p>How much have great statesmen, from Pericles to Gladstone
and Disraeli, owed to the devotion and intellectual
fraternalism, so to say, of women!  Even Bismarck attributed
his successes to his wife, Johanna von Puttkammer.  The men of
iron and the men of the moon alike have been eager to admit
that it was woman that made them, and not they themselves.  It
is more than likely that Columbus would never have discovered
America had it not been for the championship of Queen Isabella
of Castile; and such wisdom as was in the pompous head of
Louis XIV was rather Mme. de Maintenon's than his own.
</p><p>Mothers, wives, sweethearts, and sisters &mdash; as history over
and over again illustrates &mdash; it is to these angels that nature
has given charge concerning those strange children, its men of
genius; be they soldiers, statesmen, poets, artists, or even
saints.
</p><p>Saints no less illustrious than St. Jerome and St. Francis
were enabled to accomplish their momentous life-work only by
what might well be called the celestial inspiration and
assistance of pious and learned women.  St. Jerome's Latin
version of the Scriptures,, known as the Vulgate-as also

<pb n="262"/>
the Latin Psalter &mdash; was made literally in collaboration
with two Roman ladies, Paula and Eustochium, whose knowledge
of Hebrew, Greek, and Latin was at least equal to the saint's
own.  To them he submitted his first drafts for their
criticisms and emendations, and he made acknowledgment of his
indebtedness in eloquent dedications, classing them with those
"holy women of the Gospel" who were ministering angels to
Christ himself, and the noble women who inspired the sages of
antiquity.
</p><p>What Paula and Eustochium were to St. Jerome was the
Italian maiden, Chiara Schiffi of Assisi, known as St. Clara,
to St. Francis.
</p><p>"She defended Francis," says the saint's biographer
Sabatier, "not only against others, but against himself.  In
those hours of dark discouragement which so often and so
profoundly disturb the noblest souls and sterilize the
grandest efforts, she was beside him to show the way.  When he
doubted his mission and thought of fleeing to the heights of
repose and solitary prayer, it was she who showed him the
ripening harvest with no reapers to gather it in, men going
astray with no shepherd to herd them, and drew him once again
into the train of the Galilean, into the number of those who
give their lives as a ransom for many."
</p><p>Similar is the story of St. Benedict and his twin sister
Scholastica.
</p><p>Another son of the church, whose estrangement from her was
more superficial than fundamental, and whose criticism of the
letter of Christianity has long since resulted in an
aggrandizement of its spirit, Ernest Renan, would never have
been able even to begin his life-work had it not been for the
devotion of another "sister friend," his own elder sister
Henriette.  One of the most beautiful things in literature is
Renan's record of that devotion in his memoir of her,
accompanied by their letters to each other.
</p><p>"Although," he says, "lives nobly lived stand in no need
of recollection, save by God himself, I should be all the more
to blame were I to leave this duty to my sister Henriette
unperformed, because I alone know all the treasures of that
elect, soul.  Her timidity, her reserve, her fixed opinion
that a woman's life should be a hidden one, cast a veil over
her rare qualities which few were permitted to lift.  Her
existence was one succession of acts of devotion, destined to
remain unknown."
</p><p>Henriette was twelve years old when Ernest Renan was born,
and their father's death, when she was but seventeen, left the
upbringing of her little brother almost entirely to her.  She
also took upon her heroic young shoulders the liquidation of
her father's debts, to provide for which, and for her
brother's education, she became a school-teacher, finally
exiling herself for many years as a governess in Poland.
Though thus separated from him, she kept a constant eye upon
Ernest's intellectual and spiritual training, encouraging him
in his first aspirations toward the priesthood, though her own
mind was already in that path of freedom which he was later to
find for himself.
</p><p>When, finally, at the age of twenty-three, he left the
seminary of St. Sulpice, unable any longer to reconcile his
conscience with his chosen vocation, Henriette returned to
Paris, and the two set up house together, thus beginning that
idyl of sister-and-brother friendship which was to last,
unbroken even by his marriage, till her death.  Not only did
she take upon herself the management of their domestic
affairs, but her fine scholarship enabled her to assist him
materially in all branches of his work, and he has paid a
special tribute to her influence upon that literary style
which was one of the most effective of his accomplishments.
The picture he gives of their tranquil lives together in "a
small apartment at the bottom of a garden near the Val de
Grace" is full of charm:

</p><p>She had the extremest respect for my work; I have known
her sit of an evening for hours by my side, holding her breath
lest she should disturb me.  Yet she liked to see me, and the
door between our two rooms was always open.  So perfect was
the union of our minds that we scarcely needed to communicate
our thoughts.  She surpassed me in knowledge on many points of
modern history, which she had studied at the fountainhead.
</p><p>The general plan of my career, the scheme of inflexible
sincerity I had mapped out, was so essentially the combined
product of our two consciences, that, had I been tempted to
fail in any particular of it, she, like a second self, would
have been found beside me to call me back to duty.  Thus her
influence in my mental sphere was very great.  She was my
incomparable amanuensis.  She copied all my works, and
understood them so thoroughly that I could trust to her as to
the living index of my own intelligence.

</p><p>The friendship of brother and sister is perhaps the most
perfect of human relationships,

<pb n="263"/>
and the part played by
devoted sisters in the lives of great men surpasses even that
of mothers and wives.
</p><p>Some brothers and sisters are as inseparable in their
immortality as in their lives.  Charles and Mary Lamb, for
example, whose names come together as naturally on our tongues
as the names of two members of the same firm.  "Bridget Elia"
is as well-known to us as "Elia" himself, and their story has
appealed the more to humanity because the brother's self-sacrificing love for the sister has at least as large a share
in it as the sister's affection for the brother.  When that
tragic cloud of madness fell over his sister's mind, a cloud
that was intermittently to shadow their joint lives till the
end, Charles, in devoting his life to her care, to the extent
even of putting from his thoughts forever the possible love of
wife and children, felt that he was but repaying Mary for the
care she had first given him as a lonely boy, for Mary was ten
years his senior.  Says he in one of his poems:</p>

	<l>    Thou to me didst ever show</l>
	<l>Fondest affection, and would ofttimes lend</l>
	<l>An ear to my desponding, love-sick lay,</l>
	<l>Weeping my sorrows with me, who repay</l>
	<l>But ill the mighty debt of love I owe,</l>
	<l>Mary, to thee, my sister and my friend.</l>

<p>His great friend, Wordsworth, was similarly blessed with a
sister who fostered a genius for which the world was far from
bringing a ready welcome; and she, like Mary Lamb, had no
small literary gifts of her own.  Wordsworth, indeed, owed
much to the women of his household.  His nephew has put it on
record thus:

</p><p>If Providence had not blessed him with a wife, a sister, a
wife's sister, and a daughter, whose lives were bound up in
his life, as his was in theirs, and who felt what the world
was slow in admitting &mdash; that his poems were destined for
immortality, and that it was no small privilege to be
instrumental in conveying them to posterity &mdash; it is probable
that many of his verses, muttered by him on the roads, or on
the hills, or on the terrace-walks of his own garden, would
have been scattered to the winds.

</p><p>Literary men seem to have been particularly fortunate in
their sisters.  Their indebtedness to the adoring and
understanding sister is incalculable.  The reader may recall
the absurd <hi rend="italic">_Mr. Sapsea</hi>_ in Charles Dickens's "Edwin
Drood," and remember how his wife, in an attitude of abject
admiration, used to address him as "O thou!"  Well, all great
men, in the adolescent stage, stand in need, as a vital
condition of their development, of such nutritive worship.
Men grow great &mdash; at the beginning, at all events &mdash; by being told
that they are great.  A certain egoism is inseparable from
greatness.  Nothing is done without a belief in oneself, and
in the early stages of greatness, before a confirming audience
has been won, that self-belief has often to fight hard for its
existence against despondency and discouragement.  How
priceless, then, at  that period to the man of genius is the
devoted being who believes in him, the  divining love,
prophetic in its admiration of the future fame, ever ready
with that inspiring "O thou!"
</p><p>How many darling, self-effacing sisters have been thus
ready with their "O thou! for their big, important brothers
through the ages.
</p><p>Another such sister was she who had Sir Philip Sidney for
brother &mdash; Mary Sidney, Countess of Pembroke, for whom Ben
Jonson wrote so splendid an epitaph:</p>

	<l>    Underneath this sable hearse</l>
	<l>    Lies the subject of all verse &mdash; </l>
	<l>    Sidney's sister, Pembroke's mother.</l>
	<l>    Death, ere thou hast slain another</l>
	<l>    Learned and fair and good as she,</l>
	<l>    Time shall throw a dart at thee.</l>

<p>The shaping of one of the rarest of English souls was
undoubtedly Mary Sidney's, and the picture of the noble sister
and brother together in the old manor-house garden at Wilton &mdash;
Philip at work on his famous romance of "Arcadia," undertaken
at her bidding &mdash; is one of those perfect historic memories that
help to keep pure the heart of Time.  So identified with each
other were brother and sister that when the "Arcadia" was
published it was described on the title-page as "The Countess
of Pembroke's Arcadia."
</p><p>Another conspicuous monument of literature nearer to our
own time, Macaulay's "History of England," is ours partly
because Macaulay, who never married, found his lifelong friend
in his sister Hannah, Lady Trevelyan.  Hannah long kept house
for the historian, and so deep was his attachment to her that
her marriage, when at last it came, fell upon him like a
bereavement.  Yet it did not separate them, and on her great
brother's death it was still this sister's task to remain his
editor, for no one but she could read his difficult

<pb n="264"/>
manuscript, and the complete and final edition of his
works is hers.
</p><p>A great American historian, Francis Parkman, was still
more dependent than Macaulay on the love of a young sister,
Eliza, who, when his eyesight failed him, became for him both
eyes and pen.
</p><p>"She may truly be said," one reads, "to have literally
written six of the volumes of his history, inditing each word
as it fell from the historian's lips as he sat shading his
eyes from the light before his study fire, while she wrote
rapidly at the table in the window."
</p><p>Miss Parkman never married.  One wonders if a renounced
love may not lie beneath the foundations of her brother's
history; but whether or not in her case such sacrifice was
made, there is no doubt that many such buried hopes
voluntarily foregone by sisters and other sacrificial women do
lie at the base of no little human greatness.  It somewhat
gruesomely reminds one of those dedicatory human victims said
to be enclosed in the foundations of medieval bridges and
other ancient buildings.
</p><p>The comparison is, of course, as extreme as it is painful,
and is, it is to be hoped of but limited application.  Those
sacrificial women have perhaps seldom been conscious of their
sacrifice, and have been happy, rather, in their sense of
collaborating with an inspired friend in a great endeavor.
This was surely the case with Caroline Herschel, sister of the
great astronomer, from whose biography Professor Mozans in his
fascinating book on "Woman in Science" quotes this inspiring
passage:

</p><p>She became his assistant in the workshop; she helped him
to grind and polish his mirrors; she stood beside his
telescope in the nights of midwinter, to write down his
observations when the very ink was frozen in the bottle.  She
kept him alive by her care; thinking nothing of herself, she
lived for him.  She loved him and believed in him, and helped
him with all her heart and with all her strength.  She might
have become a distinguished woman on her own account, for with
the seven-foot Newtonian sweeper given her by her brother she
discovered eight comets, first and last.

</p><p>A brother-and-sister friendship, in which, again, the
element of self-sacrifice did not surely press heavily was
that of John and Elizabeth Whittier.  Theirs was indeed a love
filled with that peace which passeth all understanding.
</p><p>"It seems almost a profanation to speak of it," said one
writer, "so sacred was the love between the two."
</p><p>Thoreau, again, was blessed with two sisters, Helen and
Sophia, on whom their worship of their famous brother sat
lightly.
</p><p>It was a very different genius who wrote this to a sister
on the death of her husband:

</p><p>Oh, my sister, in this hour of overwhelming affliction my
thoughts are only for you.  I have no wife, I have no
betrothed; nor, since I have been better acquainted with my
own mind and temper, have I sought them.  Live, then, my
heart's treasure, for one who has ever loved you with a
surpassing love, and who would cheerfully have yielded his own
existence to have saved you the bitterness of this letter.
Yes, my beloved, be my genius, my solace, my companion, my
joy.  We will never part, and if I cannot be to you all our
lost friend was, at least we will feel that life can never be
a blank while gilded by the perfect love of a sister and a
brother.

</p><p>The reader will scarcely have suspected the writer of this
impassioned tenderness to be that Machiavellian statesman,
Benjamin Disraeli.  Disraeli was no less fortunate in his wife
than in his sister.  Just before their marriage he had written
to her:

</p><p>I shall always have the refuge of your sweet heart in
sorrow or disappointment, and your quick and accurate sense to
guide me in prosperity and triumph.

</p><p>And the prophecy was fulfilled, as few such prenuptial
prophecies are, though in many respects it was a marriage of
opposites, as Mrs. Disraeli made fun out of emphasizing in a
quaint document to be found in her husband's biography.  In
parallel columns she placed their opposing qualities after
this fashion &mdash; Disraeli's in the first column, hers in the
second:</p>
<list>
<item>Very calm.						Very effervescent</item><lb/>
<item>Manners grave and almost sad.				Gay and happy-looking when speaking.</item><lb/>
<item>Never irritable.						Very irritable.</item><lb/>
<item>Bad-humored.						Good-humored.</item><lb/>
<item>Very patient.						No patience.</item><lb/>
<item>Very studious.						Very idle.</item><lb/>
<item>Very generous.						Only generous to those she loves.</item><lb/>
<item>No vanity.						Much vanity.</item><lb/>
<item>Conceited.						No conceit.</item><lb/>
<item>He is seldom amused.					Everything amuses her.</item><lb/>
<item>He is a genius.						She is a dunce.</item><lb/>
<item>He is to be depended on to a certain degree.		She is not to be depended on.</item><lb/>
<item>His whole soul is devoted to politics and ambition.	She has no ambition and hates politics.</item><lb/>
</list>

<pb n="265"/>
<p>Disraeli's great rival, Gladstone, was even more
fortunate in a wife who was his wonderful helpmeet through his
life.  After sixty years of married happiness the old man
wrote:

</p><p>It would not be possible to unfold in words the value of
the gifts which the bounty of Providence has conferred upon me
through her.

</p><p>She had great skill as doctor and nurse, and was the ever-watchful guardian of her husband's health through the long
strain of his strenuous parliamentary career.  She was also
his wise and outspoken critic, as one may judge by this note
in Lord Morley's journal of a holiday he spent with the
Gladstones, in 1892, Gladstone being, then eighty-two:

</p><p>After breakfast Mrs. Gladstone came to my room and said
how glad she was that I had not scrupled to put unpleasant
points; that Mr. Gladstone must not be shielded and sheltered
as some great people are, who hear all the pleasant things and
none of the unpleasant; that the perturbation from what is
disagreeable only lasts an hour.

</p><p>Mrs. Gladstone, born Catherine Glynne, lived to see her
great man safely at rest from his labors, and herself followed
him two years later.
</p><p>Men of science seem to have been particularly fortunate in
their wives.  Huxley's wife, according to his son, was his
"help and stay for forty years; the critic whose judgment he
valued almost above any, and whose praise be cared most to
win."  He "invariably submitted his writings to the criticism
of his wife before they were seen by any other eye.  To her
judgment was due the toning down of many a passage which erred
by excess of vigor, and the clearing up of phrases which would
be obscure to the public.  In fact, if any essay met with her
approval, he felt sure it would not fail of its effect when
published."
</p><p>The astronomer Kepler would have counted his wife as his
greatest discovery, and the debt of Pasteur to his wife and
daughter is dwelt on by all his biographers.
</p><p>"It is impossible," says one of them, rightly to
appreciate Pasteur's life without some understanding of the
immense assistance which he received in his home.  Whether in
discussing forms of crystals, watching over experiments,
shielding her husband from all the daily fret of life, or busy
at the customary evening task of writing to his dictation,
Mme. Pasteur was at once his most devoted assistant and
incomparable companion."  Another writer gives a very human
picture of the great scientist running up from his laboratory,
after making one of his discoveries, to announce it to his
wife and daughter, embracing them as he did so, with the tears
running down his cheeks.
</p><p>Agassiz and his wife were such close fellow workers that
in the preface to "A journey in Brazil" we find them saying:

</p><p>Our separate contributions have become so closely
interwoven that we should hardly know how to disconnect them.

</p><p>Another great traveler, Livingstone, had an intrepid wife
by his side in all his explorations till that last one in
which he had to dig her grave in the valley of the Zambezi,
and go on alone through "Darkest Africa" indeed.
</p><p>Literary men, for the most part, do not seem to have been
fortunate in their wives &mdash; though their wives might perhaps
prefer the matter stated to the effect that they have seldom
been fortunate in their husbands.  So, perhaps, Mrs. Carlyle
might have put it, though one cannot but feel that honors were
even in that tragic misalliance.  It was to a mother and
sister that the sad, difficult soul of the author of "Sartor
Resartus" turned for sympathy and understanding not in vain.
</p><p>Browning, as we know, was one of the happy exceptions.  In
that perfect union, where each inspired and was inspired by
the other, it would be hard to say which gave most.  To be at
once muse, wife, and poet has perhaps never again happened to
woman &mdash; each the other's poet and each eager to acclaim the
other as the greater.
</p><p>"She has genius; I am only a painstaking fellow," said
Browning once.  "Can't you imagine a clever sort of angel who
plots and plans and tries to build up something &mdash; he wants to
make you see it as he sees it &mdash; shows you one point of view,
carries you off to another, hammering into your head the thing
he wants you to understand; and while this bother is going on,
God Almighty turns you off a little star &mdash; that's the
difference between us.  The true creative power is hers, not
mine."
</p><p>Browning's other inspirer, Shelley, tragic as was his
first love, found in his second wife, Mary Godwin, one of the
heroic women of the world.  Poe's ill-starred life knew one
happiness, that of his beautiful, adored

<pb n="266"/>
child-wife; and
American men of letters generally seem to have been happier in
this respect than their European fellows.  What a true comrade
had Hawthorne in his wife, and who does not know the anecdote
of his coming home from his office, downcast with the news
that his post in the custom-house had been taken from him &mdash; how
his wife, far from showing concern, briskly lit a fire in his
study, arranged paper and pens, then laughingly sat him down
at his desk, saying:
</p><p>"Now, you can write your book!"
</p><p>Of Emerson's life with "Lidian" &mdash; his pet name for his
second wife, Lydia &mdash; it has been said that it was as if "two
angels had set up housekeeping together."  In the delicate art
of living with a transcendental philosopher, Mrs. Emerson was
more than matched by Mrs. Bronson Alcott, wife of probably the
most helpless idealist ever brought face to face with this
perplexing world.  It is laughable as well as pitiful to think
what would have become of the gentle founder of "Fruitlands" &mdash;
Alcott's vegetarian community near        Concord &mdash; without the
common-sense "mothering" of his wife and of that daughter
whose literary gift, first displayed in "Little Women," was
afterward to support her whole family.
</p><p>One would like to dwell on Louisa Alcott's part of the
story.  Of course, the father was such an absent-minded angel
that it was impossible to be angry with him.  A story is told
of his returning from a lecturing trip, having, to the dismay
of his family, lost his overcoat and with it all the eagerly
anticipated proceeds, except one dollar.
</p><p>"I call that doing very well," said the kind wife.  "Since
you are safely home, dear, we don't ask anything more!"
</p><p>And this characteristic passage in one of the daughter's
letters to her sister speaks volumes:

</p><p>I feel very moral to-day, having done a big wash alone,
baked, swept the house, picked the hops, got dinner, and
written a chapter in "Moods."

</p><p>What musicians owe to women would fill many volumes &mdash; and
how women have fared at the hands of musicians would make a
prodigious supplement.  Behind all the music of Mozart,
Mendelssohn, Schubert, Beethoven, Schumann, Chopin, Wagner,
Liszt, Gounod, Grieg, as some master lays his bow upon the
violin, or his fingers on the piano, or the sea of sound
surges and floats up from the orchestra like a storm gathering
in a forest, with low plaining as of breaking hearts, or
sudden sweeping volume of passionate melody, there seem to
rise at times, like wraiths borne on the wind, the starry
souls of women, who loved and gave and suffered &mdash; </p>

	<l>   She was only a woman, famished for loving,</l>
	<l>       Mad with devotion, and such slight things;</l>
	<l>   But he was a very great musician,</l>
	<l>       Grimacing and fingering his fiddle-strings.</l>

<p>In that cloud of witnessing women are not merely the women
who inspired the tumultuous passions that create a "Tristan
und Isolde" or a Chopin "Fantaisie," but sometimes it is a
devoted sister like Fanny Mendelssohn, or a tender mother like
the mother of Richard Wagner, to whom we find the great sound-compeller writing indeed, as he himself says, like a lover to
a sweetheart:

</p><p>Now I have left you, the feeling of thanks for that grand
love of yours toward your child, which you displayed to him so
warmly and so tenderly again the other day, so overpowers me
that I fain would write, nay, tell you of it in accents soft
as of a lover to his sweetheart.  Yes, and still softer &mdash; for
is not a mother's love far greater, far more untainted, than
all other?

</p><p>Behind the monuments of masculine genius, whatever their
nature, there is always to be seen, hovering like a spiritual
presence, the soul of some woman.  Behind the marbles of
Michelangelo rises the stately form of the noble and pious
Vittoria Colonna.  Through her Michelangelo became poet as
well as sculptor, as his lofty sonnets to her bear witness.
</p><p>"Without wings," he wrote to her, "I fly with your wings;
by your genius I am raised to the skies; in your soul my
thought is born."
</p><p>Behind the dialogues of Plato it is not only Socrates we
see, but Aspasia too, and those other learned women of Athens
who were his most ardent disciples.  Of Dante it is scarcely
necessary to speak, for the pure girl-star that was Beatrice
has become the symbol for all time of the uplifting and
transmuting influence of woman &mdash; of the mere thought and dream
of a loved woman.  For in Dante's case it was no more than a
dream that inspired and sustained him through all his bitter
pilgrimage.

<pb n="267"/>
</p><p>There is no need, either, to speak of Petrarch and his
Laura, to whom he attributed all his inspiration:</p>

	<l>   Thus if in me is nursed</l>
	<l>   Any good fruit, from you the seed came first;</l>
	<l>   To you, if such appear, the praise is due;</l>
	<l>   Barren myself till fertilized by you.</l>

<p>And there is not a poet from Petrarch to the latest
hatched of present-day nightingales that has not, or could
not, say the same thing.  Nor is there a successful business
man, lawyer, statesman, man of affairs, who would not say it,
too.  When there is a George Washington there is always a
Martha Washington, and every James Madison has his "Dolly."
Always behind the achievement, whatever its nature, there are
the love and the enthusiasm of some unselfish woman, making
the purpose and ambition of "her man" her only object in life,
dreaming planning, cheering, praising, ever on the watch to
keep him up to his best endeavor, the jealous guardian of his
strength and peace, his muse, his mother, his wife, his
sister, his nurse, his incredibly good friend.
</p><p>How infinitely tender, almost unearthly, is this quality
in women!  I find it nowhere more sensitively expressed in
words than in some letters to Edwin Booth by the wonderful
young wife, Mary Devlin, who was to be his for so short a
time &mdash; for she died at twenty-three.  Booth was despondent and
hesitating about his career, and this is how she writes to
"the being God has given me to influence and cherish":

</p><p>We must ever dwell above the thunder, treading beneath our
feet the black clouds of dissension.  You are too great ever
to descend to discord.  I have too high an appreciation of the
divine spark God has gifted you with, and which you entrust to
my care, ever to cause you to seek another sphere than your
natural one.

</p><p>And, again:

</p><p>If my love is selfish, you will never be great.  Part of
you belongs to the world.  I must remember this, and assist in
its blossoming, if I would taste of the ripe fruit.  That will
prove a rich reward.

</p><p>How touching is this divine proprietorship of women &mdash; "the
being God has given me to influence and cherish."
</p><p>It is not so with men.    No, not even with the best of
them!
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
