<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="GriWild"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="GriWild">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Wild Indian</title>
<title type="sort">wild indian</title>
<author>Grinnell, George Bird</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">40</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">GriWild</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476012</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Wild Indian</title>
<title level="j">Atlantic Monthly</title>
<title type="sort">wild indian</title>
<author>George Bird Grinnell</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 83, pp. 20-29</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the
text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term> 
<term>Native American</term>
<term>Young Readers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-04">April 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Timothy Jarrett, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>TEI markup</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="essay" id="d3">

<pb n="20"/>

<p>IF after a long period the Indian problem remains a problem still,
it is because we have no sufficient knowledge of the people we are
striving to teach.  The solution of the problem is not to be reached until
the stronger race shall understand the weaker, and, in the light of that
understanding, shall deal with it wisely and well.  I say this with the
more confidence because for many years I have lived with the plains
people in their homes, engaging in their pursuits, sharing their joys and
sorrows, standing toward them in all essentials as one of themselves.  I
have thus learned to think and feel as an Indian thinks and feels, and to
see things as he sees them and from his point of view.</p>
<p>To contribute in some measure to a better comprehension of the
Indian as a man, and thus to an appreciation of the real nature of the
Indian problem in its present phase, I shall attempt to show very briefly
what the Indian was and is; to describe the old-time savage in his old
home and his old free life twenty-five years ago, and then the new
Indian, who, amid surroundings but dimly comprehended, is staggering
under the heavy burdens which civilization has laid upon him. </p>
<p>The wild Indian exists no longer.  The game on which he lived has
been destroyed; the country over which he roamed has been taken up;
and his tribes, one by one, have been compelled to abandon the old
nomadic life, and to settle down within the narrow confines of
reservations.  This change, by which an entire race has been called to
give over the ways of wanderers, and to adapt itself to the life of a
people of fixed abodes, is most momentous.  The magnitude of it is
equaled only by the suddenness with which it has been wrought, and by
its completeness.  The transition is not material alone, but intellectual.
To fit himself to it, the Indian of middle age must become literally as a
little child, that he may think new thoughts.</p>
<p>The plains Indian on the reservation of to-day is a
"reconcentrado," taken from his old home and shut up within narrow
limits beyond which he may not pass.  He is ignorant unless he be
taught, helpless unless he be helped.  His is the problem of conforming
to unwonted conditions, of adjusting himself to the ways of a new life,
of meeting its exactions, reconciling himself to its privations,
comprehending the larger opportunities it offers, proving its
compensations and winning its rewards.  Ours is the problem of helping
him in the new life.  The responsibility is one we can neither evade nor
escape.  We shall assume it the more intelligently and discharge it the
more successfully when we know the real character of the natural Indian,
and understand the influence which his former wild life must have upon
the life he is now living on the reservation.  We cannot deal with the
Indian of to-day unless we know the Indian of yesterday.  The average
man seldom thinks about Indians, and when he does he thinks of them
either with entire indifference or with contemptuous dislike.  He is
moved in part by that narrowness which leads us to despise those who in
appearance or by birth or tradition are different from ourselves,&mdash;the
feeling which leads many a white man to speak with contempt of negroes
or Chinamen.  More weighty than this feeling, however, is the inherited
one that the Indian is an enemy, who from the time he was first known
has been hostile to us.  Even nowadays most people seem to think of the
Indian only as a warrior, who is chiefly occupied in killing women and
children,

<pb n="21"/>
burning homes and torturing captives.  From the days
when Indians fought the Pilgrim Fathers, and then the settlers of the
Ohio Valley, and later still the emigrants crossing the plains, nine tenths
of all that has appeared in print about them has treated them with
prejudiced ignorance; and the newspapers, which now constitute so large
a portion of the reading matter of the American public, seldom print
anything about Indians except in connection with massacres and
uprisings.  The effect of all this literature on the popular estimation in
which the race is held has been very great.</p>
<p>The popular impressions are entirely erroneous.  The Indian was a
fighter, yet war was only an incident of his life.  Like any other human
being he is many-sided, and he did not always wear his war paint.  If
certain of his characteristics repel us, there are other aspects of his
nature which are pleasing.  If in some relations he may appear to the
civilized man ferocious and hateful, in others he seems kindly and
helpful.  The soldier sees the Indian from one point of view only, the
missionary from another, the traveler from a third, the agent from a
fourth.  Each of these is impressed by some salient feature of his
character, yet each sees that one only or chiefly, and the image shown is
imperfect, ill-proportioned, and misleading.  Only the man who for
years has shared the Indian's home, who has seen him under all the
varying conditions of his life, who has learned what motives govern him
and how he feels and thinks and reasons, can, in the present mood of
almost universal prejudice, form a just estimate of him; only one so well
acquainted with the Indian can look at things as he looks at them, and so
can fairly judge in what respects he differs from a white man and what
his needs really are.  Knowledge such as this can be had at first hand
only by one who has had a long association with him.  You learn him as
in the first instance you learn any other human being,&mdash;by living with
him.  And after you have lived with him for a time you will see that if
he is a savage, he is also a man.  The same wind that freezes you chills
him; he is warmed by the same sun, rejoices in the same kind of
success, resists when he is ill treated, and when trouble comes is
downhearted and depressed.  He is a man, but one in the child stage of
development, in which passions and impulses are stronger and reasoning
powers are more feeble than they are with civilized men.</p>
<p>Perhaps the first thing that impressed the visitor to the old-time
Indian camp was its picturesqueness; for whether one viewed him with
eyes friendly or hostile the wild Indian was always picturesque.  It was a
fine sight to watch him on his fleet pony, charging down upon you,
when with long hair, feather-decked, streaming in the wind, and weapon
ready for instant use, he swept toward you, a perfect master of horse and
seat.  And it was not less fine to ride in the midst of five hundred such
men&mdash;your friends&mdash;in the hurly-burly of the charge on the buffalo herd,
when you felt yourself part of a confused blur of dust, flying pebbles,
great brown beasts, naked men, and straining horses.  As striking,
though in a different way, was the long line of the marching camp, as in
slow procession, stretched out over a mile or two of prairie, it wound its
course among the hills.  Viewed from a distance, it looked like a long
ribbon, spotted here and there with bright bits of color; but if you were a
part of it, as it advanced, you saw that it was made up of groups of
silent men with bows and quivers at their backs, of women riding or
leading patient pack ponies that dragged their travois, of racing boys, of
loose horses, and of vagrant dogs.  The barking, the neighing, the
shouting, the scolding, that fell on your ear, told something of the
vitality that animated the component parts of the procession. </p>

<pb n="22"/>
<p>Hardly less picturesque were the quiet scenes of the Indian's home
life, when you lived with him in his village of conical skin tents.  Sitting
in the shade of the lodge when the sun was hot, you smoked the
long-stemmed pipe and talked with your friends, while all about you the
people came and went.  Men returned from the hunt, riding horses
heavily laden with fresh meat and hides; women were at work pegging
out the skins or dressing them; from neighboring lodges men were
shouting invitations to the feast; all about there were little groups like
your own, smoking, chatting, and laughing.  For the Indian is not, as the
popular idea figures him, stolid, taciturn, or even sullen in his every-day
life.  He may be shy and silent in the presence of strangers, but in his
home life he is talkative,&mdash;eager to give and receive the news, and to
gossip about it.  He is merry and laughter-loving, and likes to make
good-natured fun of another's personal peculiarities.  Thus, one of her
companions may jeeringly call a very slender woman the shadow of a
moccasin string.  Once, on the prairie, in the bright hot sunlight, I heard
one Indian say to another who was very stout, "My friend, stand still for
a little while.  I want to sit down in the shade and cool off."</p>
<p>Some years ago I was on the reservation of a tribe known as the
Big Bellies&mdash;Gros Ventres&mdash;at Fort Belknap, Montana; and while I was
there a new agent came to them.  He was a fat man, and one of the
Indians, who met the agent for the first time in my presence, said, as he
shook hands with him, "Ah, you are one of our own people.  You, too,
are a Big Belly."</p>
<p>It is true that Indians are savages and have savage vices; but they
also have savage virtues, many of which are admirable, among them
honesty, bravery, hospitality, consideration for their neighbors, family
affection, and fidelity,&mdash;the keeping of pledged faith even with an enemy.
These people have a respect for their promises which seems remarkable
to a white man.  A liar is regarded with contempt, and when a man has
once been detected in an untruth it is almost impossible for him to regain
his reputation.  Often when I ask a man to tell me a sacred story, he sits
silent for a while, to arrange his ideas.  Then he holds his palms up
toward the sun, and passes them over his head, arms, and body, rubs
them on the ground, and again passes them over his head, arms, and
body.  Then he prays: "O Wise One Above, listen.  Earth, listen.  All
you Spiritual Powers, listen.  Take pity on me.  Help me.  I am going to
talk to this man.  I am going to tell him a story of ancient times, of the
things which used to happen a long time ago.  Help me to talk straight to
him.  Watch me, and do not let me tell a lie.  Make me tell these things
just as they used to be.  Listen carefully, and make me tell him the
truth."</p>
<p>A striking example of the faithfulness with which the Indians keep
their engagements was shown by the northern Cheyennes, who in 1879
surrendered, as prisoners of war, to General Miles, and immediately
afterward enlisted under him as scouts.  For four years, as prisoners of
war and mindful of the promises they had made, they faithfully served
the government, scouting by themselves over hundreds of miles of
territory, and fighting hard against hostile tribes, often against their own
people.  Instances even more impressive occur at intervals among the
civilized tribes of the Indian Territory.  Among these people, if a man
kills one of his fellows, he is tried by the tribal court, and if convicted is
sentenced to be shot.  The day for his execution having been fixed, he is
released on parole and goes away, promising to be present at the place of
execution at the appointed time.  He is always there.  In a case recently
reported, the convict was a member of a famous ball team which

<pb n="23"/>
had engagements running through the summer.  He was
sentenced to die early in August, but in view of the inconvenience which
his death would cause to the ball team he was reprieved until the last
days of October, so that he might fulfill his engagements with the team.
After being sentenced, he married the girl on whose account he had
killed his rival, set his affairs in order, played the different games of
ball, and on the morning set for his execution went alone to the ground
and paid the penalty of death.</p>
<p>Nowhere in the world was property more safe than in the old-time
Indian camp.  To take what belonged to his neighbor was something that
could no more have occurred to an Indian than it would occur to a guest
at dinner to pocket the spoons and forks from the table of his hostess.
This perhaps is not to be imputed to the Indian for righteousness: the
very idea of theft was wholly foreign to him; he was never exposed to
the temptation.  If in the camp you lost any piece of property, such as
your knife or your pipe, and if at your request the old crier shouted
through the village that you had lost something, the article, if found by
any one in the camp, would be returned to you immediately.  Several
years ago my brother and I, with an interpreter, visited a camp, took up
our quarters in the lodge assigned to us, and unpacked our things there.
When we went out, we left our possessions scattered about.  Just after
leaving the lodge, my brother, who was new to Indian camps, said to the
interpreter, "Bill, I left all my things lying on my bed.  Will they be
safe?"  "Safe," returned Bill, "sure; they'll be safe all right.  There ain't
a white man within thirty miles of here."  The Indians of to-day have
picked up from white people many of the white people's ways, and are
not always honest, but they do not yet take things from one another or
from their guests.</p>
<p>Like ourselves, Indians are fathers and mothers, husbands and
wives, brothers and sisters.  In order to exist with any comfort, they
must live on good terms with their neighbors; they love, their wives,
their children, their friends, their tribe.  Their lives are wholly devoted
to securing the welfare, first of the immediate family, then of the tribe.
No people are more patriotic.  They love their tribe as we love our
country; an Indian believes that his own people are better than any
others.  Though so intensely loyal&mdash;true clansmen&mdash;they are yet
sufficiently fair-minded to see the qualities, good and bad, of alien and
hostile peoples.  I have heard the Cheyennes&mdash;one of the bravest tribes of
the plains&mdash;speak in highest praise of the courage and fighting qualities of
tribes who were their enemies, and with contempt of others who might
perhaps be their friends.  Thus of the Sioux they say that to fight them
was like chasing buffalo cows; for the Sioux ran away so fast that the
Cheyennes had to ride hard to overtake them before they could kill them.
But of the Pawnees and the Crows they say that when they met either of
these in battle, the contest was like that between two buffalo bulls
fighting: they would come together with a great shock, and push and
push, yielding this way and that, and presently one body of men would
push harder than the other and would drive their opponents back, and
then the latter would make a supreme effort and drive the others a little
way; and so the battle might sway backward and forward for hours,
before either party gained the victory.</p>
<p>In daily intercourse within the tribe Indians might teach many
white people lessons of patience, courtesy, and generosity toward their
fellows, and of family affection and consideration for the comfort of
wives and children.  When a number of men are sitting together,
discussing some subject, each speaker is listened to with the same grave
patience,

<pb n="24"/>
whether he is the wisest and most important or the most
foolish and least considered of the group.  He is never interrupted, but is
allowed to finish his remarks.  Even if he should lose the thread of his
speech and stop short, striving to remember something he wished to say,
no one smiles or laughs or moves.  All sit quiet, and wait until he
signifies that he has finished what he has to say.  If one individual in an
assembly begins to pray, all the others are silent until the prayer is
ended.  No one speaks, no one whispers.  When the prayer is over,
conversation may begin again.  Indians are not ashamed to show their
affection for one another.  Close friends who have been separated for
any length of time, when they meet, put their arms around and hug and
kiss one another.  Often two young men will be seen standing or sitting
close together and holding hands, or with the arm of one about the neck
of the other.  When we meet after a long absence, my old father among
the Blackfeet puts his arms around me and hugs me.  The purely social
side of life in an Indian camp could not fail to interest any one who
might be introduced to it.  The gatherings of mature men for discussion
of subjects affecting the general welfare, the assembling of old women
for gossip and of middle-aged women for gambling, the active games of
young men and women, the visiting, the dancing, and the feasting, all
remind us as closely as possible of what is going on about us in our own
surroundings every day; in fact, these represent our round of town
meetings, mutual improvement clubs, whist clubs, and golf meetings,
calls and afternoon teas and dances and dinners.</p>
<p>In the family relation the Indian shows a side which is attractive.
He loves his wife and family as we love ours, and he thinks of them
before thinking of himself.  But besides the natural affection that any
animal has for its young the Indian cares for his children for another
reason.  He is intensely patriotic.  His pride in his tribe and its
achievements is very strong.  He glories in the prowess of its braves and
the wisdom of its chiefs; his soul thrills as he hears told over and over
again the stories of the victories which his people have won over their
enemies; he rejoices at the return of a successful war party.  In the
children growing up in the camp, in the boys shooting their blunt-headed
arrows at blackbirds and ground squirrels, or yelling and shouting with
excitement in the mimic warfares which constitute a part of their sport,
and in the girls nursing their puppies or helping their mothers at their
work, he recognizes those who a few years hence must bear the
responsibilities of the tribe, uphold its past glories or protect it from
danger, as he and his ancestors have done.  No wonder he loves
them.</p>
<p>Indians seldom punish their children, yet usually they are well
trained, though chiefly by advice and counsel.  When a tiny little boy,
who has just received his first bow and arrows, starts out of the lodge to
play with his fellows, his mother is likely to say to him, "Be careful,
now; do not do anything bad, do not hit any one, do not shoot any one
with your arrows.  You may hurt people with these things, if you are not
careful.  Pay attention to what I say."</p>
<p>If older people are sitting in the lodge, and a child comes in, it sits
down by its mother and remains quiet.  It seldom speaks or makes any
noise or disturbance.  If a very small child comes in and begins to talk,
its mother lifts up her finger and says <hi rend="italic">Sh!</hi> and at once it is
quiet.  I have never seen children who seemed to be better behaved at
home.  Out of doors they are as full of animal spirits, as boisterous, and
as fond of playing in the dirt as healthy children are the world over.
The boys hunt birds, engage in sham battles, and go in swimming.  The
girls play with their

<pb n="25"/>
dolls, make clothing for them, and pitch or move their
mimic camps.  Some of the older people enjoy the society of the
children.  The father delights to play with his little boys, and the
grandfather pets the tiny child, perhaps painting its face or hanging about
its neck some cherished charm or ornament that he himself has long
worn.  Here is the advice given by a poor Pawnee widow to her young
son who was growing to manhood.  Her precepts of industry, courage,
singleness of purpose, charity, and devotion to friends might worthily
have been spoken by any woman of the highest civilization.</p>
<p>"You must always trust in God.<ref target="GriWiln1">1</ref>
He made us, and through him
we live.  When you grow up you must be a man.  Be brave and face
whatever danger may meet you.  Do not forget, when you look back to
your young days, that I have raised you and always supported you.  You
had no father to do it.  Your father was a chief, but you must not think
of that.  Because he was a chief it does not follow that you will be one.
It is not the man who stays in the lodge that becomes great.  It is the
man who works, who sweats, who is always tired from going on the
warpath.  When you get to be a man, remember that it is his ambition
that makes the man.  If you go on the warpath, do not turn around when
you have gone part way, but go on as far as you were going, and then
come back.  If I should live to see you become a man, I want you to
become a great man.  I want you to think about the hard times we have
been through.  Take pity on people who are poor, because we have been
poor, and people have taken pity on us.  If I live to see you a man, and
to go off on the warpath, I should not cry if I were to hear that you had
been killed in battle.  That is what makes a man,&mdash;to fight and to be
brave.  I should be sorry to see you die from sickness.  If you are killed,
I would rather have you die in the open air, so that the birds will eat
your flesh, and the wind will breathe on you and blow over your bones.
It is better to be killed in the open air than to be smothered in the earth.
Love your friend and never desert him.  If you see him surrounded by
the enemy, do not run away.  Go to him, and if you cannot save him be
killed with him and let your bones lie side by side.  Be killed on a hill,
high up.  Your grandfather said it is not manly to be killed in a hollow.
It is not a man who is talking to you, advising you; yet heed my words,
even if I am a woman." </p>

<p>Though the Indian woman&mdash;like her husband&mdash;works hard in behalf
of her family she is not the slave which popular fancy pictures her.  If it
is true among civilized people that the hand that rocks the cradle rules
the world, in an Indian village it is not less true that the hand that
scrapes the parfleche rules the camp.  The impression is firmly fixed in
the popular mind that in an Indian camp the woman does all the work,
yet I have seen no place in the world where woman was better able to
take care of herself then there.  In many tribes it is the woman who
owns the property.  In some tribes women are the chiefs.  In all they are
treated with respect, receive consideration from men, and possess great
influence.  In former times young and unmarried women sometimes went
off with a war party, usually not as warriors, but as helpers.  When they
did this, they were treated with the utmost respect and consideration by
every member of the party.</p>
<p>Just as in a white community, in an Indian tribe the man is the
provider, the woman cares for the household.  Among the plains tribes it
was the duty of the man to keep his wife supplied with food for the
lodge, and with skins for clothing or shelter.  He strove to add to the
consideration in which he and his family were held by going to war

<pb n="26"/>
and exposing himself to danger, gaining glory and
wealth by killing enemies or capturing property.  As among white
people, the wife cooks for her husband, prepares clothing for the family,
attends to the packing up when the village is moved, and, in the case of
agricultural people, helps to cultivate and gather the crops.  White
people look upon hunting and war in the light of pastimes or recreations,
but with Indians each of these occupations was a serious one.  Often in
winter, if food were scarce, men traveled many miles to get buffalo; and
they were obliged to go, no matter what the weather was.  Though the
cold were bitter and the fine snow flying in level clouds over the prairie,
his family must eat, and the man must hunt.  After he had killed the
game, he had to skin and pack his meat; though often before he got it on
his horse it might be frozen solid.  He might get lost in the storm, and
have to lie out for two or three nights, freezing hands or feet, or even
perishing.  Perhaps the buffalo might disappear from a district, and
young men might be obliged, in the worst of weather, to make long
journeys, scouting to see where food could be obtained.</p>
<p>The men's toil on the warpath was more severe.  The party started
out on foot, carrying upon their backs heavy loads of food, extra
moccasins and arms.  They might be forced to go two or three hundred
miles before turning back, every day exposed to discovery and death by
the enemies through whose country they were passing.  If they made a
successful trip and captured a herd of horses, they were obliged, in order
to escape pursuit, to ride these naked animals for two or three days,
literally without stopping, except to change from tired horses to fresh
ones.  No one who has not lived the hard life of the plains can imagine
what such a journey was.  It was far more laborious than anything that
the women had to do, and besides it was full of danger.</p>
<p>While the men were engaged in this hard and dangerous work, the
women were at home in the comfortable lodges, and had no labor to
perform more arduous than cutting and collecting a supply of fuel, which
occupied them only for an hour each day.  In mild and pleasant days
they often worked at the dressing of robes, but in the severest weather
they did little or nothing at this.  In some sheltered place among the
timber they would clear away the weeds and undergrowth from a
considerable space, and hanging up about this robes or lodge-skins to
serve as wind-breaks, would build a great fire in the middle and work at
their tasks before it.  Such a place was comfortable, almost like the
inside of a lodge, except that it was open at the top.</p>
<p>The Indian woman does not stand in awe of her husband.  On the
contrary, if in her presence he says something with which she does not
agree, she is very likely to correct him, and tell him that he knows little
about the matter.  I have seen an angry woman enter a lodge in which
were sitting half a dozen of the wisest old men and bravest warriors of
the tribe, and, irritated by some innocent remark, turn on them and rate
them with high-pitched scoldings, until one by one they drew their
blankets over their heads and fled from the lodge to escape her clamor.
If you wish to have anything done in an Indian camp, and can get the
women on your side, you will obtain your desires.  At the same time,
they are conservative and opposed to change.  They sometimes hold the
tribe back when the men are willing to make a step in advance and
abandon an old custom for the ways of civilization.  They are good
wives and mothers, and devotedly attached to their families.  Frequently
the tie of affection between husband and wife is remarkably strong, and
this not only between young couples, but even between the middle-aged
and the old.  Often the

<pb n="27"/>
two accompany each other everywhere, and are seldom
seen apart.  If you stop an old man to talk with him, his wife stops too,
and very soon she begins to take part in the conversation.  In other
words, in a very large proportion of cases the sexes stand on an
equality.</p>
<p>This family affection is one of the most striking characteristics of
the Indian, and permeates all his legend and folklore.  It is the motive
which induces many a hero to start off on his travels, striving to
accomplish some great thing.  Numerous examples might be cited from
the literature of those tribes whose stories have been recorded, which
exemplify the truth that the family relation among the buffalo savages of
the plains is essentially the same that holds good among civilized people.
Stories having this motive are Comanche Chief and the Ghost Wife in
Pawnee, and Scarface and the Origin of the Worm Pipe in Blackfoot
literature.  An abstract of this last tale will give an idea of its character,
and incidentally show its resemblance to one of the most familiar
classical myths.</p>
<p>There was once a man who was very fond of his wife.  After they
had been married for some time they had a little boy.  After that the
woman fell sick and did not get well.  The young man loved his wife so
dearly that he did not wish to take a second wife.  She grew worse and
worse.  Doctoring did not seem to do her any good, and at last she died.
The man used to take his baby on his back and travel out from the camp,
walking over the hills crying.  He kept away from the village.  After
some time he said to his child, "My little boy, you will have to go and
live with your grandmother.  I am going to try to find your mother and
bring her back."  He took the baby to his mother's lodge and asked her
to take care of it and left it with her.  Then he started off to look for his
wife, not knowing where he was going nor what he was going to do.  He
traveled toward the land of the dead; and after long journeyings, by the
assistance of helpers who had spiritual power, he reached it.  The old
woman who helped him to get there told him how hard it was to
penetrate to the ghosts' country, and made him understand that the
shadows would try to scare him by making fearful noises and showing
him strange and terrible things.  At last he reached the ghosts' camp,
and as he passed through it the ghosts tried to scare him by all kinds of
fearful sights and sounds, but he kept up a brave heart.  He reached a
lodge, and the man who owned it came out and asked him where he was
going.  He said, "I am looking for my dead wife.  I mourn for her so
much that I cannot rest.  My little boy, too, keeps crying for his mother.
They have offered to give me other wives, but I do not want them.  I
want only the one for whom I am searching."</p>
<p>The ghost said to him: "It is a fearful thing that you have come
here.  It is very likely that you will never get away.  There never was a
person here before."  But the ghost asked him to come into the lodge,
and he entered.  Then this chief ghost said to him: "You shall stay here
for four nights, and you shall see your wife; but you must be very
careful or you will never go back.  You will die right here."</p>
<p>Then the chief went outside and called for a feast, inviting this
man's father-in-law and other relations who were in the camp, saying,
"Your son-in-law invites you to a feast," as if to say that their son-in-law
was dead, and had become a ghost, and had arrived at the ghosts' camp.
Now when these invited people, the relations and some of the principal
men of the camp, had reached the lodge, they did not like to go in.
They called out, "There is a person here!"  It seemed that there was
something about him that they could not bear the smell of.  The ghost
chief

<pb n="28"/>
burned sweet pine in the fire, which took away this
smell, and the people came in and sat down.  Then the host said to them:
"Now pity this son-in-law of yours.  He is seeking his wife.  Neither
the great distance nor the fearful sights that he has seen here have
weakened his heart.  You can see for yourselves he is tender-hearted.
He not only mourns for his wife, but mourns also because his little boy
is now alone, with no mother; so pity him and give him back his
wife."</p>
<p>After consultation the ghosts determined that they would give him
back his wife, who should become alive again.  They also gave him a
sacred pipe.  And at last, after many difficulties, the man and his wife
reached their home. </p>
<p>I have thus briefly indicated some of the more striking personal
traits of the Indian in the old time, from which his character may be
judged.  He was childlike in his simplicity, in his eagerness to revenge a
wrong, in his shyness, and in his fear of things that he did not
understand.  A creature of quick impulses, he could endure the keenest
sufferings and the greatest dangers, yet was subject to groundless panics,
when, like one of a herd of stampeded animals, he fled in headlong
terror from he knew not what.  So with the Indian of to-day.  His
powers of observation are highly trained, yet on matters without the
range of his limited experience he reasons like a child.  On the prairie,
from the appearance of the sky, the direction of the wind, the actions of
birds or animals, or of people at a distance, he will make predictions
whose accuracy will startle you; but if you attempt to explain to him
some of the most ordinary events and methods of civilized life, he fails
to comprehend you and seems quite unable to use his wits.  A little
investigation will show you that you are talking over his head and about
something which is utterly strange to him, and that you are using terms
for which his vocabulary has no equivalents.  Most of the processes of
civilization are as obscure to him as is the art of writing to a
four-year-old child, and, like a child, the Indian must have
instruction&mdash;often repeated&mdash;before he can comprehend these processes,
and much practice before he can perform them.</p>
<p>The old-time Indian had the stature of a man with the experiences
and reasoning powers of a child.  He was a nomad, a free wanderer,
limited in his ordinary hunting journeys only by his natural range, and in
war roaming without limits.  In summer he followed the game or the
fish, accumulating a store of provisions to carry him through the winter.
Among the buffalo tribes the winter hunt usually took place during
November and December, when the robes were at their best and the
buffalo fat, and before the weather became very cold and stormy.  When
really severe weather came he retreated to his permanent village, or, if
his tribe was one that had no permanent habitation, he chose some
sheltered place where wood was abundant and remained there with the
camp.  Except in case of necessity the men did not venture far nor hunt
much in bad winter weather, but if the food supply ran low they were
forced to brave the storm.</p>
<p>Until about fifteen years ago the old free life still prevailed over
much of the Western country.  Fifteen years earlier than this it had first
in some degree been interrupted by the building of a transcontinental
railroad, and every railroad built afterward imposed new and stronger
limits on the freedom of the old-time dwellers of the West.  The
railroads brought hunters and settlers, and made a market for the flesh
and skins of the wild beasts on which the Indians subsisted, and so
caused extermination of this food supply.  With the railroads, too, came
the speedier movement

<pb n="29"/>
of troops, and the punishment and gathering in of hostile
or vagrant camps.  Thus little by little the Indians were collected on
reservations; the wild West began to be settled, and of a sudden was
wild no longer.  The Indian ceased to wander.</p>
<p>He has ceased to wander, but he has not forgotten.  The fierce joys
of the warpath still live in his mind: the long weary marches under a sun
like fire, the stealthy approach, the successful charge, and the long
flight.  Sometimes in memory he feels again the sense of swelling
triumph that filled his heart as, with blackened face and bearing his
trophies, he rode over the hills and swiftly passed on down toward the
village; he sees as if but yesterday the people streaming out from the
lodges to meet his party, singing for joy and shouting out the names of
the fortunate warriors, his name among the rest; he recalls how old men
praised him and old women danced before him, singing a song in his
honor, and how all the people, old and middle-aged and young, down to
the tiniest children, honored him as one of those to whom the tribe owed
its triumph.  Nor does he forget the pleasures of the more peaceful
pursuits of the old life.  Often he recalls his scouting as a young man
after buffalo, when the camp was hungry, and each scout prayed that he
might be the one who should find food and bring life and happiness to
the people.  He remembers the times when he was successful, and how,
when he brought the good news, they said that he was smart and had
good luck; how his name was called through the camp, and every one
was glad that he, and not another, had been sent out; and he remembers,
too, how, on one of these triumphant returns, that young woman&mdash;now
the mother of his children&mdash;had heard about it, and the next time he met
her, instead of looking at the ground, she raised her eyes to his face and
smiled.</p>
<p>There were many buffalo chases to remember, even from the time
when he was a little boy; the shouts of the criers saying that the tribe
should hunt, the orders to men and women, the start, the control
exercised by the soldiers, the headlong race of the final charge, all the
active life and quick changes of the pursuit, and the confusion of the
killing; then the happiness that came of plenty in the camp, when the
drying-scaffolds hung red and white with sheets of meat and of rich
backfat, and the feast shout had no end.</p>
<p>This was the old life in the free days, the life which moulded the
Indian and made him what he was and is.  No marvel then that to the
older men of the tribe, though but a memory growing dim, that old life
is yet more real than this new existence on the reservation, with its
limitations and perplexities, its white man's ways, which the centuries of
his training have made it so hard for the Indian to assume.
</p>

<note id="GriWiln1"><seg type="note-symbol">1</seg> <p>Atius Tirawa==Spirit Father, or Father Above.</p></note>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
