<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HadMobi"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;

]>
<TEI.2 id="HadMobi">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Television and the Mobilization of a New Christian Right Family Policy</title>
<title type="sort">television and the mobilization of a new christian right family policy</title>
<author>Hadden, Jeffrey</author>
<editor>D`Antonio, William and Joan Aldous</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Compiler</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>religiousbroadcasting.lib.virginia.edu/pubs</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">57</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HadMobi</idno>
<date value="2002">2002</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2002 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476016</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Television and the Mobilization of a New Christian Right Family Policy</title>
<title type="sort">television and the mobilization of a new christian right family policy</title>
<author>Jeffrey Hadden</author>
<editor>Willian V. D'Antonio and Joan Aldous</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Compiler</resp>
<name/>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>20 pp.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Sage Publications</publisher>
<pubPlace>Beverly Hills, CA</pubPlace>
<date value="1983">1983</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Private copy</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1983">1983</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term>
<term>democracy</term>
<term>religion</term>
<term>sociology</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2002-11">November 2002</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Irene Oh</name>
</respStmt>
<item/>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
<head>
Television and the Mobilization of a New
Christian Right Family Policy
</head>
<div2 type="section" id="d4">

<p>In 1933, William F. Ogburn published a paper entitled
"The Family and Its Functions" in a volume that resulted from the first
presidentially commissioned social science investigation. Ogburn identified
six primary functions of the family: economic, protective, religious,
recreational, educational, and status conferring. The family's role in the
performance of each of these functions, he argued, was eroding in modern
industrial society.</p>


<p>By contemporary social science research standards
Ogburn's mustering of evidence to support his conclusion was seriously
deficient (see, for example, Caplow et al., 1981). Nevertheless, for nearly
fifty years, his forecast of the demise of the family has been part of the
taken-for-granted stock of knowledge of scholars and popular writers
alike.</p>

<p>Notwithstanding the considerable attention Ogburn's paper
received at the time, it did not lead to governmental policy with respect
to the family. The family has long been exalted by presidents and other
politicians as the cornerstone of society, but, strangely, it has never
been much of a political issue per se. In fact, Jimmy Carter was the first
president ever to attempt to create an explicit family policy (Steiner
1981). And his efforts to do so may well have been a significant factor in
the mobilization of evangelical Christians who disagreed with his
policies.</p>

<p>An evangelical Christian himself, Jimmy Carter believed
American families were experiencing "steady erosion and weakening
(Steiner, 1981: 3). If elected, candidate Carter promised to "construct an
administration that will reverse the trends we have seen toward the
breakdown of family in our country" (Steiner, 1981: 3).</p>

<p>President Carter believed there was an inexorable
relationship between government and the family. Strong families contribute
to the</p>

<pb n="248"/>


<p>strength of a good government; weak families add yet more
burdens to the government. " If we want less government," Carter told a New
Hampshire audience in 1976, "we must have stronger families, for government
steps in by necessity when families have failed" (Steiner 1981: 5). Carter
was determined to create a family policy that would aid families in need of
assistance and, at the same time, selfconsciously seek to eliminate and
avoid regulations and laws that might have deleterious effects on the
family (for example, tax laws that tax a working couple at a higher rate
than an unmarried couple or a couple with only one person in the labor
force).</p>

<p>President Carter substantially failed to achieve his goal
of creating a systematic government policy on the family, but he succeeded
in making the family a highly obstreperous political issue. One important
reason for his failure was the absence of consensus regarding what would
constitute a sound profamily policy. Liberal philosophy would provide
economic assistance and social services to families in need. Conservatives
see such policies as creating dependence rather than self-reliance. Thus,
conservatives see the good intentions of strengthening the family through
economic assistance and social services as likely to have the exact
opposite effect and weaken the family.</p>


<p>The White House Conference on the Family convened during
the last year of the Carter administration, and the underlying ideological
conflict regarding what measures might strengthen the family came to the
fore. At that point, the " New Christian Right" emerged as a vocal
dissident against the more liberal philosophies of the administration
Outmaneuvered in their bid for significant representation at the White
House Conference. The New Christian Right went public and had considerable
success in persuading a significant proportion of conservative Americans
that the conference was dominated by voices dedicated to destroying rather
than revitalizing the family.<ref target="n1">[1]</ref></p>

<p>In the waning days of the Carter administration, the
White House Conference on the Family issued a report with a series of
recommendations about what government could do to buoy up the presumed
fast-fading fortunes of the American family. But the report was too late
The sweeping victories conservatives had scored in 1980 and the popular
assumption of the effectiveness of the New Christian Right in those
victories assured that the recommendations of the White House Conference
would not be acted upon. At the same time, the issue of the family in
American life would continue to demand attention.</p>

<p>In the first year of his administration, Ronald Reagan
concentrated on putting his economic programs in place. Some of his New
Christian Right supporters felt his failure to move simultaneously on
social programs signaled a betrayal of their conservative goals.</p>

<pb n="249"/>


<p>Reagan continued to move cautiously on "pro-family
programs in 1982 precisely because they were even more controversial than
his economic recovery measures. Still, his commitment to a social policy
paralleling the goals of the New Christian Right is abundantly
clear.</p>


<p>In his address before the National Affairs Briefing
sponsored by the Religious Roundtable in Dallas on August 22,1980, Reagan
told a wildly cheering crowd: "The office of the presidency must ensure
that the awesome power of government respects the rights of parents and the
integrity of the family" (Reagan, 1980: 4). Then, later in that address, he
said that we should help families "to care for one another, rather than
driving their members into impersonal dependence upon government program
and government institutions."</p>

<p>It was President Reagan's close friend and campaign
manager in both 1976 and 1980, Senator Paul Laxalt, who introduced the
Family Protection Act in 1980. An omnibus bill, the proposed legislation
covered some 38 distinct measures dealing with education, welfare, First
Amendment guarantees, taxation, and domestic relations. When Senator Laxalt
first introduced the bill, it was not considered by most Washington
analysts to be a serious piece of legislation. Not so when the Family
Protection Act was reintroduced in 1981 with cosponsorship from Senator
Roger Jepsen and Representative Albert Lee Smith.</p>

<p>President Reagan (1982) told the conservative National
Religious Broadcasters that "rebuilding America begins with restoring
family strength and preserving family values." In that same address, in a
gesture of support to the New Christian Right leadership, he stated, " I do
not agree with those who accuse you of trying to impose your views on
others." The Family Protection Act, along with other legislation judged by
conservatives to be profamily, received considerable attention in 1982
although it failed to be enacted into law.</p>


<p><hi rend="bold">TV PREACHERS AS THE VANGUARD OF THE NEW CHRISTIAN
RIGHT</hi></p>

<p>The New Christian Right is a coalescence of a range
of diverse and previously only loosely connected groups. Many are single
issue groups fighting abortion and ERA, such as the Pro Family Forum, the
Right to Life Commission and the Eagle Forum. Some have been on the
political scene for a long time, such as the Institute for Christian
Economics. Others, such as the Moral Majority, Christian Voice, and the
Christian Roundtable, are newcomers to the political process.</p>

<p>While they have diverse interests and goals, these groups
share an anger about what is happening to America. American culture has
moved significantly in directions that seriously affront their
personal</p>


<pb n="250"/>

<p>beliefs, which are grounded in evangelical faith.
Explicit sex in print and broadcast media are morally wrong, they feel, and
there is a clear causal relationship between this development and the
soaring divorce rate, living together out of wedlock, casual sex, and so
on. In their view, abortion is the taking of human life. To speak of the
right of a woman to determine whether to carry a pregnancy is to hide the
truth that millions of unborn babies have been murdered.</p>

<p>But these issues represent only the tip of the iceberg.
Anger and moral indignation run deep, and resentment about what is
happening in and to America has been growing for a long time. Perhaps what
angers these groups most is that they do not believe that the rest of
society and, particularly, the government have taken them seriously. They
are tired of being treated as a lunatic fringe or just another interest
group that is not strong enough to be factored into political decisions.
Partly because their own values have held politics to be dirty and partly
because the political process has discounted their importance, they have
developed feelings of powerlessness and second-class
citizenship.</p>

<p>From the vantage point of these groups, this nation has
fallen from greatness because it has turned its back on God. " Getting
right with God" requires repentance and cleaning up of a lot of individual
and collective sin. Substantial segments of this belief system have been
shared by evangelicals for many years. Billy Graham's crusades have not
strayed very far from these themes in a quarter of a century.</p>



<p>
However, two new ingredients make this emerging coalition important. The
first is the
belief that it is the <hi rend="italic">responsibility, </hi>indeed the
<hi rend="italic">duty, </hi>of Christians to engage in the political process as a means to
bring America back to God. While the notion that religion and politics
do not mix is historically a myth, it has guided the consciousness of
most evangelical Christians in recent history. The old beliefs had to be
undone. Ironically, it was Jimmy Carter's public profession that he
was a "born again" Christian that began to challenge conventional
Bible Belt wisdom about the separation of church and state. By 1980
many evangelicals who supported Carter in 1976 were disillusioned
with him, but not with the political process. Like the liberals of the
1950s and 1960s, they had come to believe that morality can be
legislated; hence it is important to get the right people elected to office
(see VanderJagt, 1980)
</p>

<p>The second factor that makes the emerging New Christian
Right coalition important is involvement of the television preachers. These
are the dynamos behind the thrust of born-again politics. While only a few
of the "televangelists" have engaged in direct advocacy of political
involvement, latent political messages are present in the</p>


<pb n="251"/>

<p>
messages of the large majority. They
constantly remind their audiences of the collective sins of the nation and
of the need to repent and bring America back to God.</p>

<p>There are now some <hi rend="italic">95</hi> syndicated religious
television programs being monitored by Arbitron. This does not include most
of the programs that are telecast via satellite to a burgeoning cable
system in America. There are approximately 600 commercial stations that
offer exclusively religious programming, and a total of 1000 that offer at
least 14 hours per week of religious content.</p>


<p>The reason the electronic church is important, the reason
it has captured the concern of America, is not found in audience size or
budgets or air time. It is found in the potential clout of these people to
reshape American culture. Unlike the smorgasbord of religious pluralism
that one can find in virtually every American community, the menu of
spiritual messages on the airwaves is substantially limited to
fundamentalist and evangelical offerings. While it would be naive and
foolish to fail to see the diversity within the fundamentalist and
evangelical camps, there is considerable homogeneity in the conservative
theological emphasis. And, as repeated social science investigations have
demonstrated, there are clear links between conservative theology and
conservative political ideology. Only a few radio and television preachers
have publicly pronounced the wedding of conservative theology and
conservative politics. The latent link, however, is present in almost all
of the conservative traditions.</p>


<p>From a long tradition of circuit riders, tent preachers
and Elmer Gantry-like revivalists, the evangelist, now the televangelists
have come a long way. No longer are they simply safeguarding the moral an
spiritual character of their private constituency. No longer are they
satisfied with Sister Lou or Brother Jim finding the Lord and being bor
again. For, while salvation may still be their goal, the sinner is not you
and me anymore it's America. And to save America takes a lot of believers
a lot of money, and a lot of power.</p>

<p>The power of the televangelists lies in their potential
to mobilize large masses of everyday Christians. Various polls have
estimated the number of evangelicals all the way from 30 to <hi rend="italic">85
</hi>million, depending on the defining criteria. What proportion of this
group can be mobilized to support the political objectives of the New
Christian Right depends on the political sophistication with which the
develop their campaign.</p>

<p>Religious broadcasters represent a nascent social
movement. One of the critical components of a successful social movement is
access to media. Every important social movement since television has been
waged via mass communications. Marches and demonstrations are</p>

<pb n="252"/>

<p>means to gain the attention of the news media and thereby
bring the causes of social movement leaders into America's living rooms on
the evening news and in the morning newspapers.</p>


<p>The New Christian Right does not have to draw a crowd to
attract the attention of the media. They have merely to turn on their
television cameras. They already have access to large audiences, and they
have developed proven methods to raise the money to retain access. The
audiences they are reaching are not nearly as large as they claim, but they
are sufficiently large to develop powerful social movement organizations.
And when they want the rest of the country to pay attention, they can use
their access to the airwaves to organize events such as "Washington for
Jesus." Furthermore, as we have seen through the person of Jerry Falwell
they have considerable potential to capture the attention of even larger
audiences via access to the secular media. Astutely mobilized, this
potential power base will not be easily checked.</p>

<p>Yet another factor that gives this nascent social
movement so much potential power is its mastery of the ancillary technology
of television, which pivots around the computer. Direct mail, targeted to
audiences likely to be sympathetic to a cause, is the foundation. It is
proven way to raise big money and mobilize people to a cause.</p>

<p>Still another component of a successful social movement
is the cause or causes pursued. Virtually all social movements begin with
no more than a small percentage of the general population in favor of the
positions being advocated by social movement activists. To gain support
they must eventually convince the general public of the legitimacy of their
cause. There are a variety of ways to legitimize a cause, but all major
social movements must ultimately legitimize their activities and goals at a
cosmological level. The causes they advocate and the activities in which
they engage are pursued because it is the will of the Almighty.</p>

<p>The civil rights movement owed its success in no small
measure to its ability to identify brotherhood and justice as goal
ordained by God. The leaders of the New Christian Right have carved out
four basic issues they hope to define as God given and, therefore, self
evident: family, life, morality, and country. Of these four, the family is
fast emerging as the master issue. Let us examine next how they have used
the old prophecy of the death of the family to weave together their broad
agenda to save America.</p>


<p><hi rend="bold">TELEVANGELIST MESSAGES ABOUT THE AILING AMERICA
FAMILY</hi></p>
<p>Jerry Falwell is not the intellectual leader of the New
Christian Right, but he is easily its most visible spokesperson. As the
Moral</p>
<pb n="253"/>

<p>Majority has evolved, Falwell has elaborated the list of
things for which the organization stands. Most of the issues that the Moral
Majority addresses can be seen as elaborations on four initial issues. The
Moral Majority is (1) traditional profamily, (2) prolife, (3) promorality,
and (4) pro-America.</p>


<p>Affirmation of the "traditional" family is a rejection of
all forms of family life other than the marriage of a man to a woman.
Implicit in this affirmation is a rejection of divorce, because marriage is
for life. Homosexual and common-law marriages are rejected explicitly.
Rejection of the ERA can also be subsumed under the affirmation of the
traditional family, for the ERA constitutes a threat to traditional sex
roles and the division of labor between husband and wife.</p>


<p>A "prolife" stand is a stand in opposition to
abortion under any circumstances. The Moral Majority rejects the 1973
Supreme Court decision that legalized abortion, and they are prepared to
work for legislation and/or a constitutional amendment to outlaw
abortion.</p>


<p>Promorality focuses mainly on opposition to pornography
although opposition to illegal drug traffic is also included. To date, the
Moral Majority has devoted much more energy to fighting pornography than to
fighting drugs.</p>

<p>All of these issues, in one way or another, deal with the
Moral Majority's perception of the "traditional" family. Pornography, print
and broadcast, destroys families by filling minds with lust, which leads to
disobedience of God's commandments about sex. Even the affirmation of
strong America is rooted in the alleged demise of the family. As members of
the Moral Majority see it, sinister forces are at work to topple America
from greatness. The strategy America's enemies have chosen for the
accomplishment of this goal is the destruction of the traditional
family.</p>

<p>What is presented as a set of positive affirmations by
the Moral Majority thus turns out to be a rejection of "nontraditional"
lifestyles and values.</p>

<p>It is important to stress that while the New Christian
Right is a loose coalition, there is rather considerable consensus about
the centrality of the family in its agenda of social concerns. There is
also the same strong negativism that is found in the writings and sermons
of Falwell. Most of the members of the New Christian Right see enemies of
the family everywhere, working to destroy this holy of holy institutions
The strong element of defensiveness can be gleaned from the titles of their
books: <hi rend="italic">Attack on the Family, The Battle for the Family, </hi>and <hi rend="italic">How
to Protect the Family.</hi></p>

<p>But what do the New Christian Right leaders affirm
about the family? Writes Falwell (1981: 110):</p>

<p><q>The family is the fundamental building block and
basic unit of our society, and its continued health is a prerequisite for a
healthy and prosperous nation.
</q></p>

<pb n="254"/>


<p>James Robison (1980: 7) a fiery televangelist from Texas
and vice-president of the Christian Roundtable, agrees:</p>

<p>All that America has become a strong, thriving nation,
full of creativity, variety, and uniqueness owes itself to the foundational
influence of marriage and the family.</p>

<p>Charles Stanley, pastor of the First Baptist Church in
Atlanta, the home base for his

television ministry called " In Touch, " also concurs. Speaking to the
"Washington for Jesus"
rally on April 20, 198O, Stanley said:</p>

<q><p>[The] home is the most important institution in
America today No nation has ever survived the collapse of its home life.

The home is established by God, and the home is to be the foundation of
society.</p></q>

<p>Similar affirmations of the centrality of the family to
the well-being of the country can be found in the sermons and tracts of
virtually all of the televangelists whether or not they cross over into the
political arena with Falwell.</p>


<p>But what about the family itself? What about the positive
roles of nurture, love, and support? One can infer from the sermons of the
leaders of the New Christian Right, and from short passages in their books
that the family is a loving, supporting institution. But relatively little
space or time is devoted to elaboration of these positive dimensions of the
family. The overwhelming message that comes across in their printed and
audiovisual messages is that the family is an institution for which the
primary function is the exercise of social control over the base impulses
of human beings. And, at this moment in history, it stands in perilous
danger of losing the battle.</p>

<p>There is virtual consensus among the televangelists that
the American family is under attack as never before in the nation's
history. The attackers are diffuse, but evangelical theology allows that
Satan is behind the onslaught. (In contrast to main-line Christian
theology, demonic forces are very much alive in fundamentalistevangelical
theology). In the 1950s, Satan's instrument to destroy America was
unabashedly the atheistic communists. They are still around. Falwell (1980:
82-96) has a chapter on "the threat of communism" in his book, <hi rend="italic">Liste
America. </hi>James Robison (1980: 9-11) writes about "the collectivists" in
his book, <hi rend="italic">Attack on the Family, </hi>and cites (inaccurately) content
from <hi rend="italic">The Communist Manifesto </hi>to identify their goals. But the scare
tactics of a "commie in every</p>

<pb n="255"/>

<p>closet" and "better dead than red," which characterize
the era of Joseph McCarthy, are largely missing.</p>

<p>The communists who in the 1950s threatened to infiltrate
and take over our government have been replaced by new enemies who have
already infiltrated our government, media, and educational institutions. In
many instances, the new enemies mean well, but their minds have been
corrupted by the awesome arsenal of Satanic forces. If they are diverse in
their motives, these enemies stand united in their intent to destroy the
family. And what better way to destroy America than to erode the family the
foundation upon which this godly nation was built?</p>


<p>Tim LaHaye, pastor of one of the largest churches in the
country founder and president of Family Seminars, and one of the three
members of the board of directors of the Moral Majority, gave the new
enemies a name. In his best-selling book, <hi rend="italic">The Battle for the Mind,
</hi>LaHaye (1980) details how the <hi rend="italic">secular humanists </hi>have plotted to
take over America. Beginning with only a tiny cadre early in this century,
they have profoundly influenced media, education, and public policy. Even
today, according to LaHaye, there are only about a quarter of a million
dedicated secular humanists. But they have so influenced how we think and
what we think that they have impact far beyond their number.</p>

<p>Through the skillful use of the media, the secular
humanists are said to promote world views that erode commitment to
traditional family values. Abortion, adultery, premarital sex, free love,
divorce and remarriage, and rebellion against authority, to name but a few
issues, have become commonplace subjects in the media. To deal with these
issues without moral protestation is to render them legitimate. In the name
of fairness and openness to alternative viewpoints, thus, the media have
sanctioned rebellion against God's commandments.</p>


<p>Falwell believes the media have been instrumental in
promoting the "cult of the playboy." He sees this philosophy as the "most
dangerous" factor in the "war against the family." "This . . . philosophy,
writes Falwell (1980: 123-124), "tells men that they do not have to be
committed to their wife and to their children.... It is more than just
revolution of dirty magazines. It represents a life style that ultimately
corrupts the family." Kennedy (1981: 2) echoes Falwell on this point: "The
'playboy philosophy' promotes a life style that says 'up with lust, down
with the family.'"</p>


<p>Education, too, has become a sanctuary for advocating
rebellion against God's word. "Creation versus evolution" has become
another rallying cry of the fundamentalists. But the heart of the
issue</p>
<pb n="256"/>

<p>is not what the public schools teach about how the world
was created. The problem is that public schools socialize young people to
all sorts of values that run contrary to fundamentalist doctrine, not the
least of which is the legitimacy of developing independent thought and the
questioning of authority.</p>

<p>The Christian school movement may once have received support from
persons whose primary motive was the avoidance of desegregation. Today
the issue is not racial segregation, but segregation of children from
public school systems that threaten the values of these fundamentalist
Christians. Let it be noted that this movement is not without precedent.
Virtually every sectarian school movement in the history of this nation
has been motivated by the desire to socialize children to a particular
group's world view.</p>


<p>
According to the New Christian Right, the media and our public
education system have molded a cultural value system that is
anchored in secular humanism rather than godly principles. Secular
humanism has penetrated the halls of Congress, the courts, and the
executive office. The goal of the New Christian Right is to change the
composition of all branches of government, replacing those who
willfully or unwittingly have fallen prey to the secular humanist
philosophy.
</p>

<p>The armies of the New Christian Right, like the loyal
supporters of Senator McCarthy, know that their enemies are everywhere. The
true believers among their troops, like the dedicated forces in any social
movement, know that the world can be divided between those who are for them
and those who serve the pernicious secular humanists. This reasoning is
captured in a fundamentalist bumper sticker that reads: "God said it. I
believe it. That settles it." Either you are for them in every painstaking
detail or you serve secular humanism.</p>

<p>Alarm about the rise of the New Christian Right has
generated a predictable countermobilization of persons who stand in
opposition to the group's beliefs. In fact, there is something approaching
a state of hysteria about the implications of fundamentalist Christian
becoming as zealous about their politics as they are about their faith.
Those who believe that the New Christian Right constitutes a threat to our
pluralistic culture are busy creating organizations and putting new life
into old organizations in an effort to combat its influence.</p>


<p>In the final section of this chapter, I examine the
potential of the New Christian Right to exert significant political
influence and thereby impose on America its viewpoints about the
family.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">ASSESSING THE POWER OF THE NEW CHRISTIAN
RIGHT</hi>
</p>
<pb n="257"/>

<p>The single most important fact in assessing the rise of
the New Christian Right is that its power has been grossly exaggerated
Prior to the 1980 National Republican Convention in Detroit, the New
Christian Right was virtually unknown to the media and, hence, America.
When Jerry Falwell and his Moral Majority showed up in force, the media
took note. When they learned a few weeks later that Ronald Reagan was to
address a gathering of born-again politicians in Dallas, the press showed
up in force more than 250 strong.</p>


<p>From that date forward, the involvement of right-wing
Christians in the election was one of the big campaign stories. By election
time, the country was braced for the election of a former second-rate
cowboy movie star to the White House, but the stunning defeat of many
liberal senators and house members required explanation.</p>


<p>Jerry Falwell, whose name became practically a household
word during the campaign, wasted no time in stepping forward to claim
responsibility for the political upsets in the name of the Moral Majority
and other New Christian Right organizations. Pollster Louis Harris agreed
with Falwell's assessment. So did several of the defeated senators and
members of Congress. It seemed and the media played up the idea that the
televangelists had created a force to be reckoned with.</p>


<p>Skeptics thought that Jerry Falwell and the Moral
Majority would go away after the election. They were wrong. Not everybody
bought Falwell's claims about being a central figure in the outcome of the
elections, but neither were his claims seriously challenged. At age 47,
with nearly 25 years of experience in front of television cameras, Falwell
proved to be very adept at gaining media attention.</p>

<p>Much of what was written about Falwell and his followers
was not very favorable, but people kept writing. A year after the
elections, Falwell was in the news more than he was during the 1980
campaign. Through a combination of luck and skillful media manipulation
Falwell kept himself in the limelight in the role of emerging power
broker.</p>


<p>Shortly after the national elections, the Moral Majority
joined forces with a little group called the Coalition for Better
Television. They threatened to boycott sponsors of programs that "promote
sex, violence and profanity." They called off the boycott during the summer
of 1981, claiming a major victory, when Procter and Gamble announced
withdrawal of sponsorship of network programs that did</p>
<pb n="258"/>

<p>not meet its program guidelines. This was hailed as
great victory and evidence of the group's political power. No one
challenged the ability of the Moral Majority and its allies to stage a
successful boycott.</p>

<p>Liberals did a lot to help Falwell's cause. Even before
the elections, Norman Lear (1980), creator of several of the most
successful television situation comedies of the 1970s, organized People for
the American Way to combat the "pernicious danger" of "fascism masquerading
as Christianity." After his defeat, former Senator George McGovern
organized another group called Americans for Common Sense. The ACLU wastes
little time in sounding an alert about the assault on civil liberties being
orchestrated by the Moral Majority. Common Cause (1981) also joined the
campaign, claiming that Falwell and other New Christian Right leaders were
trying to "radically change our Constitutional system of checks and
balances."</p>

<p>Many individuals joined in sounding the alarm. Yale
University President A. Bartlett Giamatti sent a letter to the entering
freshman class in the fall of 1981 warning against the radical assault on
freedom coming from the Moral Majority and other New Christian Right
organizations. Wrote Giamatti (1981: 28):</p>

<p>Angry at change, rigid in the application of chauvinistic
slogans, absolutistic in morality, they threaten through political pressure
or public denunciation whoever dares to disagree with their authoritarian
positions. Using television, direct mail and economic boycott, they would
sweep before them anyone who holds a different opinion.</p>

<p>Several other college presidents quickly followed suit,
publicly denouncing Falwell and his followers. For months there was an
almost never-ending outpouring of attacks on Falwell. Each public outcry
resulted in at least two news stories: one an account of the criticism and
another a report of a rebuttal from Falwell or his spokesman.</p>

<p>Falwell's friends also helped to keep him visible. When
Israeli Prime Minister Menachem Begin bombed the Saudi nuclear power plant
he called Falwell and asked him to rally Americans in support of this act.
And later that year, when Begin visited Washington, he warmly received
Falwell and a group of the Moral Majority leader's friends at Blair House.
President Reagan also gave credence to the image of Falwell as an important
spokesman for conservatives when he called Falwell to ask for his support
when he nominated Sandra O'Connor to be the first woman Supreme Court
justice. And Falwell's initial feisty defiance made him seem all the
stronger.</p>


<pb n="259"/>


<p>The only problem with the unfolding political drama
portraying Jerry Falwell as the powerful leader of many emerging New
Christian Right organizations was that the press and the politicians did
not bother to check the facts.</p>

<p>Jerry Falwell is not alone when it comes to exaggerating
the size of his television audience. Virtually all the televangelists do
just as itinerant evangelists are prone to exaggerate the number of souls
that were saved in their last crusade down the road. It is an accepted part
of fundamentalist folk culture.</p>

<p>In June 1981, two independently published reports, one
using Arbitron data, the other Nielson data, reported Jerry Falwell's
audience to be about 1.5 million, not the 25 or 50 million variously
claimed by Falwell (Hadden and Swann, 1981; Martin, 1981). The false claim
about audience size proved to be a popular news item around the country for
several months. Still, there seemed to be a reluctance to accept the
implications of this datum: If Falwell had lied about his TV following, is
it not possible that he had also uttered misleading statements about both
his Moral Majority following and its political accomplishments?</p>

<p>The answer is an emphatic yes. The first significant
evidence pointing to the conclusion that America had overestimated th
power of the evangelical involvement in the elections was presented in an
article by Lipset and Raab published in <hi rend="italic">Commentary </hi>in March 1981
Having examined a mass of polling and election data, Lipset and Raab (1981:
30) conclude: "What all these findings seem to indicate is that the effort
to mobilize a religious constituency for political purposes in America had
<hi rend="italic">no measurable effect </hi>on the 1980 elections" (emphasis added). Lipset
and Raab (1981: 30) continue:</p>

<q><p>Instead, the available evidence appears to
sustain the thesis that the
electoral swing toward conservatism and the emergence of a
political evangelical movement will parallel developments which
have been mutually reinforcing rather than related to one another as
cause and effect.</p></q>


<p>Lipset and Raab (1980: 30) further warn that the danger
of giving groups such as the Moral Majority "more credit than they deserve
[is] to run the risk of self-furfilling prophecy.... If politicians become
convinced that the Moral Majority is a decisive force in American life,
they are likely to treat it as such, just to be on the safe
side."</p>

<p>In <hi rend="italic">Prime Time Preachers</hi> (1981), Charles Swann and
I wrote about the <hi rend="italic">great potential </hi>evangelicals have to amass
political power, but we cautioned against interpreting the 1980 election
outcomes as evidence of power achieved. And we presented substantial data
to support our</p>
<pb n="260"/>


<p>caution. Some of our data paralleled evidence presented
by Lipset and Raab, but we used independent data sources.</p>


<p>Evidence challenging the assumption of the great power
and influence of Jerry Falwell and the Moral Majority continues to mount. A
<hi rend="italic">Washington Post </hi>ABC News poll conducted in June 1981 found that only
49 percent of the American public had heard or read about the Moral
Majority (Peterson and Sussman, 1981). This, even after the enormous amount
of publicity Falwell and the organization had received over the previous
ten months. Of those who had heard of the Moral Majority, 37 percent said
they generally approved of the group's positions. But this figure is very
misleading. Almost half who said they generally approved of Moral Majority
positions also favored the Equal Rights Amendment. And 40 percent approving
Moral Majority positions agreed with the proposition that "homosexuals and
lesbians should be allowed to teach in public schools, and that homosexual
relations between consenting adults should be legal" (Peterson and Sussman
1981). The Moral Majority stands in strong opposition to the ERA and the
homosexual propositions. The 37 percent approval of Moral Majority
positions thus must be interpreted as a very soft number. The truth is that
a lot of people do not know where the Moral Majority stands on a lot of
issues.</p>

<p>One might assume that Falwell would have both greater
recognition and a greater following close to home. These assumptions are
not supported by two independent polls conducted during the Virginia
gubernatorial race during the fall of 1981. A <hi rend="italic">Richmond Times-Dispatch
(1981</hi>: 1) poll revealed that only 13 percent of Virginians approved of
the Moral Majority's goals, while 49 percent said they disapproved. Right
in his home state, thus, almost 4 out of 10 citizens did not know or had no
opinion about Falwell's Moral Majority. An even more telling indicator or
Falwell's political strength in Virginia is revealed by the <hi rend="italic">Times-
Dispatch </hi>poll: Only 4 percent of those surveyed said they would be more
inclined to vote for a candidate endorsed by Falwell, while 24 percent said
they would be less likely to do so (Richmond Times-Dispatch, 1981
1).</p>

<p>The second Virginia poll, conducted for the <hi rend="italic">Virginia
Pilot </hi>(1981: 27) in Norfolk, found that only 10 percent of those
surveyed had positive evaluations of Falwell while 54 percent had negative
evaluations.</p>


<p>A survey conducted in the Dallas-Fort Worth metropolita
area during the same time span affirms other evidence of the limited
influence of the New Christian Right (Shupe and Stacey, 1981). Only 14
percent of those surveyed in the metropolis supported the Moral Majority.
And, as in the <hi rend="italic">Washington Post </hi>poll, many who said they supported
the Moral Majority did not support Moral Majority po-</p>

<pb n="261"/>

<p>sitions: 34 percent disagreed with the proposition "Abortion is a sin
against God's law," and 41 percent supported the ERA to guarantee women
equal rights.<ref target="n2">[2]</ref></p>

<p>An examination of the social and demographic
characteristics of the supporters of the Moral Majority leads sociologist
Shupe and Stacey (1981: 28) to conclude that the New Christian Right "is a
social movement whose membership/support base is preponderantly composed o
fundamentalist Christians rather than some interdenominational or
ecumenical population."</p>


<p>If the preponderance of data runs counter to the widely
held assumption that the evangelical Christians have already amassed
enormous power and are now positioned to take over America, extreme caution
should be exercised in shifting to the opposite conclusion that they are
totally lacking in a power base. There are several reasons this is
so.</p>

<p>The first reason is the group's unique access to mass
media. No other social movement has ever had the kind of access to media
that they do. Even after we discount Falwell's exaggerated audience claims,
he is still talking to approximately 1.5 million persons each week. And
there are a lot of other televangelists reaching significant audiences with
messages that, though not blatantly political, are generally supportive of
the proposition that America must return to godly principles. Furthermore,
the televangelists have command of the ancillary technology of the
electronic church that is so critical to the raising of large sums of
money. Media access and money are clearly two of the most important
ingredients of a successful social movement.</p>

<p>A second important reason that the New Christian Right is
not to be dismissed is that their potential constituency is very large. To
date, no more than one-third to one-half of the religiously conservative
Protestants in America could be counted as sympathetic to the Moral
Majority or some other New Christian Right organization. If mobilized, they
would represent a significant political minority in America.</p>


<p>A recently released study of American values found that
26 percent of those over age 14 are "highly religious" (Pollock, 1981: 43).
That amounts to 45 million adults. While it is theoretically possible to
score "high" on the study's eight-item scale of religiosity without being
theologically conservative, it is unlikely. Of those aged 65 or over, 46
percent were "highly religious." This fact has long-range implications as
our nation gradually ages.</p>


<p>In addition to the potential to mobilize evangelicals and
fundamentalists, there are a lot of conservative persons who are only
marginally religious. While not institutionally involved in
religion,</p>
<pb n="262"/>


<p>they stand ready to "vote" for religion. A 1978 George
Gallup survey estimated the number of unchurched Americans at 61 million.
What most impressed Gallup in his examination of the characteristics of the
unchurched was their similarity to the churched. They pray. They believe in
Jesus Christ. They believe in the resurrection. "With a few distinct
variations ... the unchurched claim the church as the churched except they
are <hi rend="italic">not </hi>attending, supporting, or belonging to a congregation of the
visible church" (Gallup and Poling, 1980: 89). Furthermore, the unchurched,
like the churched, affirm traditional family values (Gallup and Poling
1980: 82).</p>

<p>The Shupe and Stacey (1981) study also demonstrates the
potential for support among the nominally religious. Of the persons they
surveyed in the Dallas-Fort Worth area, 44 percent reported church
attendance of only "now and then" or less.<ref target="n3">[3]</ref>
Still, 87 percent of their
sample believed that prayer should be allowed in the schools, and 73
percent favored teaching the Biblical account of creation in public schools.
<ref target="n4">[4]</ref></p>

<p>Social movements are first and foremost in the business
of shaping public opinion. Almost always they begin from minority positions
and gradually develop support for their causes. To sustain a movement, they
need a solid core of supporters. The mass of public support can be soft so
long as it constitutes a majority and responds affirmatively to the
questions posed by the pollsters. How people respond to questions depend
on how the questions are raised. This means that the success of a social
movement depends, in part, on shaping the questions so that it is easy for
people to agree with them.</p>

<p>By selecting the family as one of its central concerns,
the New Christian Right has aligned itself with a plurality issue. No on
is against the family or hardly anyone. The strategic issue is <hi rend="italic">how
</hi>the group aligns itself with the family. To date, the moral absolutism
of the New Christian Right has deprived it of a lot of potential support.
The abortion issue illustrates the matter well. Even the most liberal
Protestant leaders in America have difficulty supporting unrestricted
abortion. It is an agonizing issue that defies a satisfactory moral
position. By taking an absolute and uncompromising position on abortion as
murder, the New Christian Right deprives itself of many potential
supporters. The same can be said of almost every other issue that troubles
the New Christian Right.</p>


<p>All social movements are caught between holding on to
hard core of "true believers" and reaching out to build larger
constituencies. It can be a precarious and dangerous line to walk. What we
have learned thus far about the New Christian Right is that it has not
strayed very far from the old issues of personal morality that have
bothered and periodically rallied conservative Christians for a long time.
And as a result, it has not broadened the base of its
constituency.</p>
<pb n="263"/>

<p>As long as the New Christian Right defines issues <hi rend="italic">only
</hi>in absolutist principles, it will be perceived as an extremist element
in society and will not sign)ficantly increase its following. The Moral
Majority may become a very vocal minority in America, but it is not likely
to build a significant following until it succeeds in presenting its
concerns in ways that can <hi rend="italic">be perceived </hi>as reasonable by much large
sectors of society.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">TOWARD UNDERSTANDING THE REAL PROBLEMS OF THE
FAMILY
</hi></p>

<p>The American family is a troubled institution. Few will
deny this proposition. Ogburn's (1933) analysis of the demise of the family
a half-century ago was not based on speculation alone. The critical flaw is
his analysis, however, was not very different from the error in reasoning
of the modern-day "family fixers." Both Ogburn and the New Christian Right
leadership confuse change with demise. Certainly change produces disruption
in processes that over time come to be defined as "normal." But this is no
necessarily synonymous with demise.</p>

<p>The disruptions that are occurring in the American family
result from both <hi rend="italic">changing social structures </hi>and <hi rend="italic">changing values
</hi>The changing size and composition of the nuclear family is an example
of structural change. One of the most important comparisons that can be
made between the mid-nineteenth- and mid-twentieth-century American family
is that the former had an average of six children, in contrast to only two
for the latter (U.S. Bureau of the Census, 1974). The mid-nineteenth-
century mother spent virtually her entire adult life in a nuclear family
with children present; on the average, there was a period of only 1.8 years
between the marriage of the last child and the mother's death. By contrast
the mid-twentieth-century mother can expect an empty nest for fully three
decades, and can expect to survive her spouse by nearly a
decade.</p>

<p>Choosing to have fewer children or the female's choice to
pursue a career are examples of changing patterns. Whether husband and wife
pursue dual careers, or the female enters the labor force out of boredom,
the need for a second paycheck, or the desire for extra earnings to enhance
leisure lifestyle activities, the movement of women into the labor force
alters the division of labor and the mutual expectations husbands and wives
have one for another. This is very likely to create tension.</p>

<p>The New Christian Right leadership would interpret this
tension as resulting from a violation of the fundamental and God
ordained</p>
<pb n="264"/>

<p>division of labor between the husband and wife. In their
view, although there may be exceptions, in the final analysis the woman's
place is in the home as mother, wife and homemaker. To assert that women
have the right to pursue a career is to utter the heresy of feminism,
godless ideology grounded in secular humanism.</p>

<p>The New Christian Right is seriously lacking in any
systematic analysis or appreciation of structural and value changes that
are taking place in American society. They seek scapegoats that can explain
complex phenomena with simple labels. A case in point is LaHaye's (1982)
treatment of the phenomenon of women in the labor force. LaHaye, executive
committee member of the Moral Majority and one of the "intellectual
leaders of the New Christian Right, offers several reasons, including
economic necessity, for the presence of women in the labor force. Then he
proceeds to chip away at the legitimacy of each of these reasons and
concludes, in the final analysis, that it is "the feminist movement, which
has agitated careerism, . . . based on humanist commitment to self
actualization" that is responsible for women in the labor force (LaHaye
1982: 176).</p>

<p>LaHaye's book <hi rend="italic">The Battlefor the Family </hi>(1982),
like his earlier best seller, <hi rend="italic">The Battlefor the Mind </hi>(1980), is
diatribe about what is wrong with American society from the
fundamentalist's perspective. Only tangentially does the book deal with the
family. His laundry list of things that ail America closely parallels Jerry
Falwell's. How these ills are related to the family is often not clear. We
are told that social ills are destroying the family, while, in almost the
same breath, we are told that the breakdown of traditional Christian values
is what has permitted the social ills to flourish. Careful reading of the
books and sermons of these men fails to reveal any systematic cause-and-
effect analysis.</p>

<p>So long as Jerry Falwell, Tim LaHaye. Pat Robertson,
James Robison, and the other New Christian Right leaders possess the
"truth" about what ails the family, we are probably safe from the most
pernicious acts they might commit in the name of fixing the family. This is
not to say they will not be mischievous. They will. But their views are
simply too far afield from the mainstream of American values to garner
aufficient political strength to impose their family policy package on this
nation.</p>


<p>In his 1933 assessment of the status of the family
Ogburn identifies a seventh function. which he calls, a bit awkwardly.
"personality." Somewhat timidly. Ogburn argues that the decline in the
other functions, especially the economic functions, of the family is
shifting the central role of the family toward personal development and
socioemotional fulfillment. Had Oghurn been bold enough to
pursue</p>


<pb n="265"/>


<p>this, he might have analyzed how love, rather than
economic necessity, functions as the glue that holds the family
together.</p>

<p>If the New Christian Right were to grasp this important
fact about the modern American family, much of its contrived rhetoric
against feminists and secular humanists could be eschewed and replaced with
a gospel of love. A theology that emphasizes how love can overcome the
tensions and contradictions of modern life could establish a much firmer
foundation to build a <hi rend="italic">real </hi>moral majority.</p>


<p>Jerry Falwell and his New Christian Right friends appeal
to be engaging in pugnacious resistance to compromise their social agenda.
While chiding unrelenting fundamentalists like Bob Jones, Falwell seems
more preoccupied with looking over his shoulder to see if the likes of
Jones are following him than with charting a course of accommodation that
would permit him to build a broader constituency.</p>

<p>If and when the Moral Majority sets its mind on becoming
a real majority, America will be faced with a great opportunity as well as
great peril. The danger is that the group will enhance its political skills
and abilities to manipulate the media without altering its agenda. This
possibility must be taken seriously. If groups such as Norman Lear's People
for the American Way have overreacted to any real and immediate danger
they nevertheless serve an important role in guarding against political
excesses from the right.</p>


<p>On the other hand, there is nothing to fear from a Moral
Majority that can learn to temper its rhetoric and change its mind in the
face of evidence. To date, the members of the New Christian Right appear to
have treated the family as a symbol of all that troubles them about
American society. But the family is the locus of real problems that are
crying for understanding and solutions. Opportunity rests in the prospect
of liberals and conservatives joining in the honest pursuit of real
solutions to real problems.</p>

</div2>
<div2 type="notes" id="d5">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">[1]For</seg> <p>arguments regarding the exaggerated strength of
the New Christian Right. see Hadden and Swann (1981) and Lipset and Raab
(1981).</p></note>


<note id="n2"><seg type="note-symbol">[2]The</seg> <p>figures cited here were computed from Shupe and
Stacey (1981: 19, Table 3).</p></note>

<note id="n3"><seg type="note-symbol">[3]See</seg> <p>note 2.</p></note>

<note id="n4"><seg type="note-symbol">[4]See</seg> <p>note 2.</p></note>

</div2>
<div2 type="bibliography" id="d6">
<head>REFERENCES</head>
<p>Caplow, T. E. et al. (1981) Middletown Families: 50 Years
of Change and Continuity. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press.</p>


<pb n="266"/>


<p>Common Cause (1981) Advertisement in the New York Times
October 11.</p>

<p>Falwell, J. (1981) The Fundamentalist Phenomenon: The
Resurgence of Conservative Christianity. (Edited with E. Dobson and E.
Hindson.) Garden City, NY: Doubleday.</p>

<p>(1980) Listen America. Garden City, NY:
Doubleday.</p>


<p>Gallup, G., Jr., and D. Poling (1980) The Search for
America's Faith. Nashville: Abingdon.</p>

<p>Gallup Opinion Index (1978) Survey of the Unchurched
American. Princeton, NJ: American Institute of Public Opinion.</p>


<p>Giamatti, A.B. (1981) "Liberal education and the new
coercion." Yale Alumni Magazine (October): 27-29.</p>

<p>Hadden, J. K. and C. E. Swann (1981) Prime Time
Preachers. Reading, MA: Addison-Wesley.</p>


<p>Kennedy, D. J. (1981) " Assault on the family.
Messenger 3 (September): 1981.</p>

<p>LaHaye, T. (1982) The Battle for the Family. Old Tappan,
NJ: Fleming H. Revell.</p>


<p>(1980) The Battle for the Mind. Old Tappan, NJ: Fleming
H. Revell.</p>

<p>Lear, N. (1980) People for the American Way direct mail
letter, October.</p>


<p>Lipset, S. M. and E. Raab (1981) "The election and the
evangelicals." Commentary 71 (March): 25-31.</p>

<p>Martin, W. C. (1981) "The birth of a media myth."
Atlantic (June): 9-11, 16.</p>


<p>Ogburn, W. F. with the assistance of C. Tibbits (1933)
"The family and its functions," pp. 661-708 in Recent Social Trends in the
United States. New York: McGraw- Hill.</p>


<p>Peterson, B. and B. Sussman (1981) " Moral Majority is
growing in recognition, but it remains unknown to half the public."
Washington Post (June 13).</p>


<p>Pollock, J. C. (1981) The Connecticut Mutual Life Report
on American Values in the '80s: The Impact of Belief. Hartford: Connecticut
Mutual Life Insurance.</p>


<p>Reagan, R. (1982) Address to the National Religious
Broadcasters, Washington, D. C., February 9.</p>

<p>(1980) Address to the Roundtable National Affairs
Briefing, Dallas, August 22.</p>


<p>Richmond Times- Dispatch (1981) September 27
1.</p>

<p>Robison, J. (1980) Attack on the Family. Wheaton, IL:
Tyndale House.</p>


<p>Shupe, A. D:, Jr., and W. A. Stacey (1981) " A
assessment of grass roots support for the new religious right." Department
of Sociology, University of Texas, Arlington. (unpublished)</p>

<p>Stanley, C. (1980) Address to Washington for Jesus rally
Washington, D.C., April 29.</p>

<p>Steiner, G. Y. (1981) The Futility of Family Policy.
Washington, DC: Brookings.</p>


<p>U.S. Bureau of the Census (1974) Fertility Histories an
Birth Expectations of American Women: June 1971. Current Population
Reports, Series P-20, No. 263. Washington, DC: Government Printing
Office.</p>

<p>Vander Jagt, G. (1980) Address to the Roundtable National
Affairs Briefing, Dallas, August 21.</p>


<p>Virginia Pilot (1981) October 4: 27.</p>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
