<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HadWhyk"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;

]>
<TEI.2 id="HadWhyk">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Why Jerry Falwell Killed the Moral Majority</title>
<title type="sort">why jerry falwell killed the moral majority</title>
<author>Hadden, Jeffrey K.; Shupe, Anson; Hawdon, James</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>www.religiousbroadcasting.org; religiousbroadcasting.lib.virginia.edu/pubs/</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">39</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HadWhyk</idno>
<date value="2004">2004</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2004 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476020</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Illustrations have been included from the original source.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Why Jerry Fallwell Killed the Moral Majority</title>
<title type="sort">why jerry fallwell killed the moral majority</title>
<author>Jeffrey K. Hadden, Anson Shupe, James Hawdon</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>196 pp.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Bowling Green State University Popular Press</publisher>
<pubPlace>Bowling Green, Ohio</pubPlace>
<date value="1987">1987</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: University of Virginia Library BV 3780.G63 1987</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1987">1987</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
<term>CORD</term>
<term>religion</term>
<term>sociology</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>LCSH, Religion, Sociology</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2004-07">July 2004</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jason Smick, University of Virginia E-text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item/>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
<head>Why Jerry Falwell Killed the Moral Majority</head>
<div2 type="introduction" id="d4">

<p>
The emergence of the New Christian Right was one of the important
stories of the 1980 presidential campaign, and for most of this
decade, one man (Jerry Falwell) and his organization (the Moral
Majority) monopolized media coverage of the growing political
consciousness among conservative Christians.
</p><p>
After an initial period of awe over his apparent power, the mass
media challenged his credibility and forecast his early demise from
the national political scene. Despite repeated pronouncements of his
demise, Falwell has refused to fade like a morning glory in the
noon-day sun. Wherever he has gone, whatever he has done, he has
commanded media attention with perhaps as much skill as anyone in
America with the exception of the incumbent of the White House.
</p><p>
In January of 1986, without any advance warnings, Falwell boldly
announced the creation of a new political arm which would go by the
name of Liberty Federation. This new organization would <hi rend="italic">continue</hi> the
activities and interests of the Moral Majority, <hi rend="italic">while</hi> also <hi rend="italic">pursuing a
broader agenda.</hi> "We want to continue to be the standard bearer for
traditional American values. But it's time to broaden our horizons as
well" Falwell said in a press announcement.
</p><p>
This dramatic move to kill the Moral Majority bore some
resemblance to killing the goose that laid the golden egg. For over
six years the name Moral Majority, as much as the brilliantly
combative persona of Jerry Falwell, had served as a cannon and a
lightning rod -- both dishing it out and taking the heat. The name
Moral Majority served also as a battle cry arousing conservative
Christians and encouraging them to become involved in the political
process. And it also sent tremors of fear and indignation into the
hearts of millions of liberals.
</p>
<pb n="102"/>
<p>
How could Jerry Falwell decide to kill such an important symbol
and communications instrument? From the beginning of high public
visibility both Falwell and the Moral Majority have been
controversial. Neither the man nor the organization has ever ranked
very high in polls of public approval. In deciding to kill the name
Moral Majority, Falwell apparently reasoned that he had reached a
point where there was more to be gained by jettisoning the negative
aspects of the name than in carrying the liabilities that had accrued
to the name. That rationale seemed paramount in his press
statement:
</p>
<q>
...the press for six years has bloodied and beaten the
name, Moral Majority. There are a lot of people who will say yes
to everything we are saying, but they dare not stand with us on
particular policies for fear of getting tarred, hurt -- that is,
picking up baggage the media has dumped on us.
</q>
<p>
Hence, like a giant corporation deciding a new name would be good
for business, Falwell said his political arm would henceforth be
known as the Liberty Federation, not the Moral Majority.
</p><p>
Most commentators responded to Falwell's change of name with
seeming indifference. Considering the tens of thousands of column
inches of print on the Moral Majority over the previous six years,
there was only brief notice and little analysis of the reasoning
behind the change to Liberty Federation. "...[E]xtremism
never does very well for very long in this country" wrote <hi rend="italic">Washington
Post</hi> columnist Mary McGrory. America had become fed-up with Falwell's
"holier-than-thou" behavior. "[I]f Falwell wishes to realize
his goal of making this a 'Christian nation,'" she stated with
confidence, "it will not be enough to change the name of the Moral
Majority to Liberty Federation. He must change his own."
</p><p>
Most of the media had long believed that Falwell and his band of
"religious zealots" were neither moral nor a majority. So, without
much pause for reflection or analysis, they seemed to accept the name
change as an admission of failure and moved on to another story. Pat
Robertson's interest in running for president quickly became the
focal point of news about conservative religion and politics.
</p><p>
Before the Moral Majority is forgotten completely, or we witness
its resurrection without remembering that it died, it is useful to
examine more carefully Falwell's rationale for the name change.
</p><p>
The thesis we shall advance is that Falwell had very good reason
to kill the Moral Majority, but that reason was not the one he
advanced, i.e., unloading the negative baggage that had accrued as a
result of so much tarring and feathering from the media. Contrary to
the general media impression that the name chance represented
admission of failure,
<pb n="103"/>
we argue that it was success that led to the slaying of the goose
that laid the golden egg.
</p><p>
Our conclusions are reached through a circuitous route and are not
without ambiguity and irony. The <hi rend="italic">circuitous</hi> route takes us through
the yellowing pages of back issues of the <hi rend="italic">Moral Majority Report,</hi> the
official news publication of the Moral Majority. They reveal secrets
of suspected organizational impotence -- unobtrusive measures as
real as the dental records of a deceased mortal.
</p><p>
The <hi rend="italic">ambiguity</hi> of the story is that we will never be able to assess
empirically the degree to which the Moral Majority was responsible
for stimulating political action by conservative Christians in
America. One of the oldest propositions in sociological lore is that
when people believe something to be real, it becomes real in its
consequences. Notwithstanding considerable evidence of a gigantic
hoax, the media and people from every walk of political life from the
far right to the far left believed the Moral Majority to be a well
organized and significant social movement organization. As a result
of this widely held belief, the Moral Majority was significant. But
there was scarcely any social movement organization there at all.
</p><p>
The <hi rend="italic">irony</hi> of the story, hence, is that Jerry Falwell's requiem for
the giant he slew was probably not very far from an accurate
assessment:
</p>
<q>
"...we [the Moral Majority], more than any other
organization in America, have been responsible for the
conservative turn around in this country in the past six years."
</q>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d5">
<head>ASSESSING THE MORAL MAJORITY'S STRENGTH:<lb/>A LITERATURE REVIEW</head>
<p>
Assessing the real organizational strength of the Moral Majority
has been a matter of interest to virtually everyone involved in
understanding the political process in America. Ronald Reagan
concluded early that Jerry Falwell had a significant following and he
has acted accordingly during his presidency. Now, George Bush's
advisors, as well as Republican operatives across the country, are
debating the assets and liabilities of Falwell's support. Liberal
Democrats have a serious interest in assessing whether the Moral
Majority is really a threat to their value preferences and political
power or, as many of them believe, merely a "paper tiger." Students
of social movements too are interested in forecasting the strength
and the potential of the conservative movement in America, and where
the Moral Majority fits into this broader movement.
</p><p>
Social movement organizations typically provide little
organizational data. What they do offer is likely to be self-serving
and, thus, must be treated with caution. It is virtually a truism
that SMOs systematically
<pb n="104"/>
"fudge" organizational numbers to exaggerate their power. And
since memberships, financial data, and other organizational records
are not readily accessible for public inspection, SMOs typically
utilize made-up statistics to create impressions of much greater
organizational strength than they actually have. Few people have
worked the magic of made-up organizational figures more skillfully
than Jerry Falwell. (An insider joke among people who work for
Falwell is that "Jerry never lies...he just remembers big.")
</p><p>
In the absence of reliable data, how can we assess the
organizational strength of SMOs generally and the Moral Majority
specifically? The answer is that we must rely on indirect measures.
Two broad classes of data have been utilized to try to get a better
picture of the size and strength of the Moral Majority.
</p><p>
The first class of data involves a variety of <hi rend="italic">indirect measures of
support</hi> for the Moral Majority. What do people think about the Moral
Majority? Where is the general public viz. the value preferences of
the Moral Majority?
</p><p>
Studies which attempt to measure support for Falwell and the Moral
Majority are fairly consistent in recording low rates of approval. A
1981 Gallup Poll found that 40% of the respondents of a national
sample had heard of the Moral Majority while only 8% approved of the
organization (Gallup Report, 1981: 60). In 1982, Gallup found that
recognition of the Moral Majority had increased to 55% and approval
had grown to 12%, with 5% expressing an interest in joining (Gallup
Report, 1982: 170). But Gallup polling in subsequent years failed to
reveal any appreciable increase in Moral Majority popularity.
</p><p>
In Dallas-Fort Worth, which Shupe and Stacey call the heart of the
Bible-Belt, they found that only 16% expressed favorable attitudes
toward the Moral Majority while 31% expressed hostile feelings toward
the organization (1983). In Indiana, Johnson and Tamney conducted two
separate studies in "Middletown" and support for the Moral Majority
declined from a slim 16% in 1981 to 14% in 1982 (1983: xx; 1984:
189).
</p><p>
In a national study, Buell and Sigelman found about 3% outright
support for the Moral Majority and another 6% were classified as
sympathetic with the Moral Majority. In sharp contrast, fully
two-thirds (69%) were either hostile or critical of the organization
and their beliefs (1985: 431).
</p>
<pb n="106"/>
<p>
On the other hand, studies which have attempted to estimate Moral
Majority support by determining what proportion of the population
support views consistent with the organization's position have
produced much higher support. Analyzing <hi rend="italic">New York Times/CBS</hi>
News poll data, for example, Yankelovich (1981:5) concluded that
67 million Americans were potential Moral Majority supporters. And
Simpson (1983: 188-190) analyzed NORC data and found 30% of the
population were in agreement with the Moral Majority in disapproving
homosexuality, the women's liberation movement, abortion, and
federally mandated legislation restricting school prayer. On
individual items, support for the Moral Majority position ran even
higher.
</p><p>
This latter class of data supports Falwell's claim of having a
significant proportion of the population with him on the issues but
still unwilling to express sympathy for his organization. These data
in conjunction with the low support obtained when the Moral Majority
name is mentioned suggest Falwell may have acted with considerable
wisdom in getting rid of the name--at least if his goal is to
move toward "respectability" and broaden the base of organizational
support.
</p><p>
A second broad class of data deal specifically with the actual
<hi rend="italic">organization</hi> of the Moral Majority. The number of studies in
this second class is not large. Typically, they have utilized unobtrusive
measures to glean insights about the size and character of the
organization.
</p><p>
During the 1980 presidential campaign, Falwell claimed the Moral
Majority had two to three million members. Hadden and Swann (1981:
137, 164-5) were able to pull together a number of organizational
indicators from which they inferred that this size claim had to be
significantly exaggerated. Among other things, they noted that the
claimed circulation of the <hi rend="italic">Moral Majority Report</hi> was only 482,000.
Why don't all the members of the Moral Majority receive its official
publication, they asked. They learned also from the Executive
Director of the Washington state Moral Majority that his chapter had
12,000 members. The national office of Moral Majority confirmed that
Washington state had the largest membership of any state. Simple
arithmetic led to the conclusion that the total size of the national
organization had to be much smaller than Falwell was boasting.
</p><p>
Probably the most perceptive glimpse into the organizational
character of the Moral Majority was offered by Liebman (1983). From
the onset, Falwell claimed that the Moral Majority represented a
broad ecumenical base of Protestants, Catholics and Jews. Utilizing
the directory of state chairman published in the <hi rend="italic">Moral Majority
Report,</hi> Liebman went to local telephone directories, and a variety of
other resources, to
<pb n="107"/>
see if this claim could be substantiated in terms of
organizational leadership. He was able to identify <hi rend="italic">forty-five of the
fifty state chairman as Baptist ministers.</hi> Furthermore, twenty-eight
of them were affiliated with a small alliance of independent Baptists
called the Bible Baptist Fellowship.
</p><p>
Liebman's data seriously challenged the claim of broad based
ecumenicity. Furthermore, he uncovered an important clue as to how
Falwell was able to put together a national organization so quickly.
The Moral Majority merely, but ingeniously, linked an already
existing national communications network of conservative ministers,
spread its umbrella over them, and gave them a name. From its origin,
the Moral Majority had a running start with an already existing
nascent national federation along with an extensive array of mailing
lists.
</p><p>
Utilizing existing networks and organizational structures has
liabilities as well as assets. As Liebman notes:
</p>
<q>
while the availability of pre-existing networks lowers
the cost of mobilization, social movements organizations may have
to pay a stiff price when they incorporate previously organized
constituencies (73).
</q>
<p>
One important liability for the Moral Majority was the necessity
of structuring the organization so that state charters were
quasi-autonomous. Falwell claimed that local autonomy was an asset,
but the record suggests there were significant liabilities as well.
There were several incidents where people far to the right of Falwell
engaged in activities and made statements that were so outrageous
that Falwell had to publicly repudiate or disassociate himself from
them.
</p><p>
A more significant liability was the problem of motivating people,
already highly successful in their own right, to organize their own
time and projects in the name of the Moral Majority. From the
beginning, the Board of Directors consisted of pastors of "super
churches" and only one of these persons actively pursued projects in
the name of the Moral Majority. The others basically "lent" their
names and otherwise went about their own business.
</p><p>
Such liabilities do not necessarily preclude the development of a
strong national organization, or coalition of loosely networked state
organizations under a national umbrella. But this knowledge should
serve as a warning that Falwell would likely encounter difficulties
in building a solid grass-roots organization. In the absence of
substantiated evidence, one should approach claims of organization
success with some skepticism. Development is not likely to be easy,
and it should not be
<pb n="108"/>
assumed, simply on the basis of unsubstantiated claims, that these
liabilities have been overcome.
</p><p>
Just how successful Falwell may have been in building a strong
grass roots SMO has been the subject of much speculation and debate,
but there has generally been an absence of systematic efforts to find
indicators of organizational strength. This paper is offered as a
modest effort to fill that gap.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d6">
<head>CONTENT ANALYSIS OF MORAL MAJORITY REPORT</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Statement of Assumptions and Research Methods.</hi> As noted in our
literature review above, the popularity of an SMO or its leader(s) is
not a very useful indicator of organizational strength. We argue that
a more useful technique for assessing organizational strength is to
examine its activities. What are an organization's goals and
projects? Is there evidence to indicate that the organization is
engaged in activities aimed at achieving its stated goals?
</p><p>
The <hi rend="italic">Moral Majority Report</hi> is a monthly newspaper offered "at no
cost as an extension of the Moral Majority Foundation" (11/85
masthead, pg. 2). This is the only regularly scheduled publication of
Moral Majority and, as such, offers the best possible public record
of Moral Majority activities.
</p><p>
We do not assume that <hi rend="italic">MMR</hi> reports all activities of the Moral
Majority. Some activities, such as lobbying, may be more effective if
they remain low-keyed or even private information. Similarly, active
SMO leaders are often too busy engaging in movement activities to
stop and provide a chronicle of what they do. Thus, we would expect
some underreporting of organizational activity. But it is also
reasonable to assume:
</p>
<list type="ordered">
<item n="1">(1) that the national organization has an interest in
promoting itself to its "members" and other readers of <hi rend="italic">MMR</hi>;</item>
<item n="2">(2) that significant activities, whether carried out by the
national or state organizations, will not go unknown to the
tabloid and, thus;</item>
<item n="3">(3) most significant activities will be reported in the pages
of <hi rend="italic">MMR</hi>.</item>
</list>
<p>
A corollary assumption is that the absence of <hi rend="italic">reports</hi> of
organizational activity can be interpreted as an indicator of the
lack of organizational activities.
</p><p>
In order to assess the nature and magnitude of Moral Majority
activities, we conducted a content analysis of all issues of the <hi rend="italic">MMR</hi>
for the calendar years of 1984 and 1985. The <hi rend="italic">Report</hi> appears in
tabloid newspaper form, typically 24 pages in length.
</p>
<pb n="109"/>
<p>
A typical issue of <hi rend="italic">MMR</hi> features some topic of interest to the New
Christian Right, e.g., pornography, homosexuality, abortion, school
prayer, etc. In addition to this feature section, <hi rend="italic">MMR</hi> carries columns
of several conservative writers, news stories of interest to
conservative Christians, an insert about Liberty University and some
commercial advertising.
</p><p>
Another regular feature of the newspaper during the time period of
our examination was called "Moral Majority Reports." This section
included reports from the "National Officers" as well as
"State-By-State" reports. This section seemed ideally suited for our
efforts to chronicle the activities of the Moral Majority.
</p><p>
Before deciding to focus on the "Moral Majority Reports" section
of the newspaper, however, we conducted a global survey of the entire
content of the newspaper. For the two year period under
investigation, we concluded that the pages of <hi rend="italic">MMR</hi> provide no evidence
of sustained ongoing activities or projects that can be uniquely
attributed to the Moral Majority. We expected that the Moral Majority
would have programatic activities dealing with each of the topics
featured in the newspaper, but we found little news about Moral
Majority <hi rend="italic">activities</hi> per se that would document specific
organizational activities.
</p><p>
With this global evidence, we turned to a systematic analysis of
the section of the news tabloid entitled "Moral Majority Reports." A
cursory examination of the reports of the National Leaders revealed
evidence that they, as individuals, were engaged in various
activities, speaking, lobbying, etc. But again we found an absence of
specificity regarding <hi rend="italic">organizational activities.</hi>
</p><p>
Hence, we decided to concentrate our analysis on the
"State-By-State" reports. The Moral Majority claims to be a
grass-roots network of local and state organizations. If the
organization is functioning well at this level, the state reports
should provide good evidence of the nature and extent of grass roots
activities.
</p><p>
The unit of analysis for this investigation, thus, is the
State-By-State reports. Our strategy for analysis is to record all
<hi rend="italic">activities</hi> reported. An activity was very broadly defined as any
event (general or specific) reported in the State-By-State
sub-section of the Moral Majority Reports. Each activity was
classified in terms of <hi rend="italic">nature</hi> of the activity and the <hi rend="italic">issue content</hi>
of the activities. <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> refers to what was done, e.g.
demonstrating, registering voters, monitoring legislators, lobbying,
etc. <hi rend="italic">Issue content</hi> refers to the substantive matter of the activity,
e.g., pornography, abortion, homosexuality, etc. In addition we coded
<pb n="110"/>
a number of demographic variables such as state, region, who
participated, how many, the time frame, the target group, etc.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d7">
<head>RESULTS</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Who Reported</hi>? The Moral Majority claims chapters in all
fifty states. Ten states (20%) submitted no report at all during the
two year time period of 1984-1985 which we studied. Eleven state
chapters (22%) submitted one report, fourteen (28%) reported twice,
and fifteen (30%) reported more than twice. Overall, there were a
total of 104 reports published, including the District of Columbia.
That amounts to an average of one report per year per state for the
two year period examined.
</p><p>
Falwell has claimed strong support for the Moral Majority in all
states and regions of the country, but the presence and absence of
reports by state suggests a <hi rend="italic">strong regional character.</hi> More than half
(54%) of all the reports came from the South, states considered to
constitute the Bible Belt. Of the ten states that failed to report,
all were outside the Bible Belt region. The Northeast industrial
complex (New England and Middle Atlantic) accounted for only 11% of
all reports.
</p><p>
The distinctively regional character of Moral Majority activity is
further evidenced by the proportion of states within each region that
reported. All but one Southern state reported (94%) while
approximately one third of the states in the East and West never
reported. Furthermore, 81% of the Southern regional states reported
more than once while only 44% and 39% respectively of the Eastern and
Western region states did so.
</p><p>
We also observed that states were much more likely to report in
1984 (78%) than in 1985 (38%). The higher rate of activity in 1984
can partially be accounted for by the fact that it was an election
year. This fact, however, cannot account for a dramatic drop in all
kinds of activities between 1984 and 1985. (We'll return to
interpreting this statistic in our conclusions. )
</p><p>
<hi rend="italic">Activities Reported.</hi> The forty states plus the District of
Columbia reported a total of 244 activities. Leading the list of
activities is "lobbying," 17% of all activities. This is followed
closely by "voter registration" which comprises 16% of all
activities. "Monitoring" constituted 11% of all activities, but
seldom did we find evidence indicating how a situation was being
monitored. This led us to suspect that "monitoring" might constitute
a certain "fudge factor," i.e., something to report when nothing was
otherwise happening. "Meetings" comprised 9% of all activities,
"demonstrations" 8% and "rallies" made up 4%. We identified a
total.
</p>
<pb n="111"/>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Who are the actors?</hi> Thirty-eight percent of all activities
reported are claimed solely as Moral Majority activities. Forty-two
percent of the time, the writer explicitly indicates that the
activity is being carried out by Moral Majority in cooperation with
some other group. Rather frequently, 12% of the time, the person
writing the report uses the first person singular to describe the
activity, e.g., "I spoke," "I appeared on a TV program," etc. Eight
percent of the time the actors are another group, or actors who are
unspecified.
</p><p>
We think it significant that more than half of all activities
reported are things that would usually be done by a single
individual. In this context, we also find the large proportion of
joint activities (42%) suggestive of a broad class of MM activities.
If Jerry Falwell appears as a speaker at a rally or meeting, we
suspect that activity would likely be considered a <hi rend="italic">joint</hi> Moral
Majority activity even though the MM may not have been involved in
organization and management of the meeting.
</p><p>
<hi rend="italic">Time frame for activity.</hi> The time frame for which
activities were reported also proved to be quite revealing. Of the
244 activities recorded, 105, or 43%, were identified in the <hi rend="italic">future
tense.</hi> That is to say, nearly half of the time the authors of the
state reports are writing about things they plan to do, rather than
things they have done or are doing. For the future tense activities
reported in 1984, we attempted to follow up and see if the author
later reported that the activity had happened. This involved a total
of 76 projected activities. Of this group, we could not positively
confirm that any of these projected activities actually happened.
</p><p>
<hi rend="italic">Activity Content.</hi> What were the substantive issues which
the Moral Majority activities addressed? In our coding we had some
difficulty differentiating between <hi rend="italic">type of activity</hi> and <hi rend="italic">activity
content.</hi> This was particularly apparent with two general categories
of activities -- election related tasks and "organizational
maintenance." And these two issues topped our list of recorded
activity content. More than a quarter of all activities (28%) dealt
with election related matters. Matters pertaining to the organization
of Moral Majority were the second most frequently recorded activity
content, accounting for 14% of all activities. Together, they account
for 42% of all activity content.
</p><p>
Part of our difficulty results from certain conceptual ambiguities
that arise in differentiating between "type" and "content" of
activity. But it is also evident that many of the reports simply do
not report a substantive content. We clearly had a coding bias that
was evident only after we completed the task. In the absence of
content, we were prone to record type of activity as a substitute for
content.
</p>
<pb n="112"/>
<p>
If we eliminate the election and organizational maintenance
activities from consideration, we have a total of 147 coded
substantive issues. Topping the list of concerns are issues relating
to education with a total of 26% of all the contents recorded. The
substance of the education mentions breaks down almost equally
between matters relating to private and public schools. This is
followed by abortion which constitutes 22% of all mentions and
pornography with 18% of the mentions. Other issues include
homosexuality (9%), drinking (5%), and church and state issues (5%).
Other issues receiving less than 5% mention included patriotism,
defense, ERA and family.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d8">
<head>ASSESSING THE IMPLICATIONS OF THE DATA</head>
<p>
One of the rationales Jerry Falwell offered for creating the
Liberty Federation was that he wanted to broaden the base of issues
which he addressed. Those who have listened to Falwell over the past
half-dozen years probably feel that he has never seemed constrained
when it comes to speaking out on matters pertaining to national
defense and foreign policy.
</p><p>
But the data here show that to the extent that the Moral Majority
has been addressing issues, they have focused extensively on matters
of personal morality to the exclusion of social-structural issues.
Developing concern for this broader range of issues among his
followers would seem to require new organizational and educational
initiatives. In this context, Falwell's bold initiative in giving the
Moral Majority the axe takes on new meaning.
</p><p>
The creation of a new organization with a new image and a broader
mission can be seen both as an initiative to rid himself of the
negative sentiments that have accrued to the name Moral Majority as
well as an effort to form a new conservative Christian alliance that
he could move beyond the issues of personal morality.
</p><p>
Contrary to the old adage that data speak for themselves, the data
we have extracted from the <hi rend="italic">Moral Majority Report</hi> don't make much
sense at all except as they are interpreted. First and foremost, we
think the data here amassed point to the absence of a flourishing
grass-roots organizational structure.
</p><p>
If there were a significant grass-roots organizational structure
out across America, there would be abundant evidence of this in the
form of reports of projects and activities. What we find, rather, is
something more nearly approaching a facade. The state activity
reports represent a form of impression management. The Editor of <hi rend="italic">MMR</hi>
found it increasingly difficult to maintain the facade because State
Chairmen,
<pb n="113"/>
who weren't doing much, were increasingly unwilling to cooperate
in providing accounts which revealed how little they were actually
doing.
</p><p>
The Moral Majority really was a goose with a golden egg. Falwell
chose to use the glitter of the egg to attract the attention of the
media and thereby promote his cause in the press rather than
investing the egg in building grass-roots organization clout.
Perhaps, from the beginning, Falwell was content to sound the trumpet
calling evangelical Christians to action. It may never have been his
goal to build a grassroots structure. Or, perhaps he didn't
understand that grass-roots organizations don't just happen -- they
must be staffed and built with the same discipline that goes into
building any other effective organization.
</p><p>
Whatever may have been Falwell's intentions, he has served well
the conservative Christian movement in America by raising
consciousness and giving millions hope that their vision of America
might be restored. He has masterfully created awareness of issues and
ignited fires of hope.
</p><p>
Falwell has cries-crossed the country delivering hundreds of
speeches and sermons which have aroused fundamentalists Christians.
He has also quite self-consciously done combat with the press and
with a select groups of liberals in America -- e.g., Norman Lear,
Ted Kennedy, Walter Mondale, Phil Donahue, etc. By arousing their
wrath, he has brought attention to the conservative Christian
movement. The hostility exhibited by liberals has served to move
conservative Christians closer toward mobilization even though they
may not particularly like Falwell.
</p><p>
If Falwell has made one strategic error, it is his incessant
bragging about his millions of followers and Herculean
accomplishments. For the most part, the press has been amazingly
uncritical of him, seldom submitting his made-up statistics to
careful scrutiny. Herein, we find the horns of the dilemma which led
him to slay the golden goose.
</p><p>
The Moral Majority was primarily an organization for grabbing
media attention, built and supported by direct-mail technology. As
such, it was Increasingly In the precarious position of having the
press scrutinize Falwell's boastful claims. Like the final revealing
of the Wizard of Oz, Falwell has been ever vulnerable to the
likelihood that Dorothy and her trio of companions on the Yellow
Brick Road would one day step around behind the curtain to discover
that the Great Oz's powers were largely a facade -- more amplified
voice and lightening machine than substance. That is always the risk
when a social movement is predicated too closely on media
imagery.
</p>
<pb n="114"/>
<p>
During the summer of 1985 Falwell lost his two vice presidents who
had been the backbone of the Moral Majority since its founding. Cal
Thomas, the quick-witted, sharp-tongued VP for Communications,
decided to stride out on his own as a syndicated columnist and
freelance journalist, and Ron Godwin, MM's Executive VP, was seduced
by big bucks to become a VP with the <hi rend="italic">Washington Times.</hi> These near
simultaneous developments provided Falwell with an opportunity to
slip out from under the weight of his shaky Moral Majority
edifice.
</p><p>
Charles Judd, a former national GOP fund-raiser who was hired by
Falwell in April 1984 was promoted to head the organization. Judd's
goal, with Falwell's blessing, was to engage in building the
grass-roots organization that had not previously been accomplished.
In November Judd claimed that the Moral Majority was now "a lot more
substance than hype." In contrast to the Falwell model, Judd claimed
"...our purpose is not to be a lightning rod. Our purpose is to
mobilize the conservative. We don't need to be that visible to be
effective."
</p><p>
These events, thus, set the stage for Falwell to climb out from
under the Moral Majority. It had served its purpose, and the purpose
of the New Christian Right, well. But it had run its course. Falwell
himself had established sufficient national and international
visibility and didn't need the organization to promote himself. In
fact, as the data we have here reviewed suggests, Falwell's own
image, over the long haul, might well be improved by killing the
Moral Majority.
</p><p>
Thus in January 1986 did Jerry Falwell announce the passing of the
Moral Majority and the birth of Liberty Federation.
</p><p>
There are lots of possible explanations for these developments.
We've argued that it was success and not capitulation to the
pressures of negative criticism that led Jerry Falwell to kill the
Moral Majority. Like a lot of other decisions he has made, he saw a
window of opportunity and went with it.
</p><p>
There are other factors that may also have contributed to the
decision. Falwell is committed to building Liberty University into a
class institution for the higher education of conservative
Christians. His announced goal of 50,000 students may be another one
of his whopping made-up statistics.
</p><p>
Falwell has also recently purchased a cable television network. He
began feeding the <hi rend="italic">Old-Time Gospel Hour</hi> onto the cable system via
satellite in 1986, and has plans to begin regular extended
broadcasting in 1987. In addition to broadcasting a lot of live
events from Liberty University, Falwell will host a daily talk-show
with lines open to the audience. Even some of his closest friends and
associates don't think he has a chance of building a network that can
compete with Pat
<pb n="115"/>
Robertson's or Jim Bakker's networks. But they also note that they
would never have dreamed that he could have built a university with
6,500 students and with the quality of Liberty University in less
than a decade.
</p><p>
Between the development of Liberty University and the Liberty
Broadcasting Network, Falwell has two good reasons to settle down and
stay home more. He also has reason to begin to soften the tongue that
so infuriates liberal Americans. But those reasons may not prove to
be compelling. Upon considered reflection, it may become evident that
softening the tongue and cleaning up his image are not likely to
increase the chances that liberals will send their kids to school in
Lynchburg, nor their bucks to support his network.
</p><p>
Jerry Falwell got where he is today by his instincts, energy, wit,
and sharp tongue. It seems pretty obvious that he rather likes the
idea of everything in his organization coming up LIBERTY. But Falwell
is also smart and pragmatic. If Liberty doesn't work for all
occasions, he can try something else. And if Charlie Judd doesn't
turn Liberty Federation into a grass-roots organization that is
paying dividends he may be working for the Republican Party again,
and we may well see that after the life and death of the Moral
Majority comes its resurrection.
</p>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

