<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HagMini"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="HagMini">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Ancient Mining on the Shores of Lake Superior</title>
<title type="sort">ancient mining on the shores of lake superior</title>
<author>Hagar, Albert D.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">31</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HagMini</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476021</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Ancient Mining on the Shores of Lake Superior</title>
<title type="sort">ancient mining on the shores of lake superior</title>
<author>Albert D. Hagar</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1865-03">March 1865</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 15, pp. 308-315</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the
text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1865">1865</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-08">August 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>TEI tagging</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">


<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="308"/>
<head>Hagar, Albert D.  "Ancient Mining on the Shores of Lake Superior."<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 15 (Mar. 1865): 308-315.</head>

<p>IN the month of March, 1848, Samuel O. Knapp and J. B. Townsend
discovered, from tracks in the snow, that a hedgehog had taken up
his winter-quarters in a cavity of a ledge of rocks, about twelve
miles from Ontonagon, Lake Superior, in the neighborhood of the
Minnesota Copper Mine.  In order to capture their game, they
procured a pick and shovel, and commenced an excavation by removing
the vegetable mould and rubbish that had accumulated about the
mouth of what proved to be a small cavern in the rock.  At the
depth of a few feet they discovered numerous stone hammers or
mauls; and they saw that the cavern was not a natural one, but had
been worked out by human agency, and that the stone implements,
found in great profusion in and about it, were the tools used in
making the excavation.  Further examination developed a well-defined vein of native copper running through the rock; and it was
evidently with a view of getting this metal that this extensive
opening had been made.
</p><p>This was the first instance where "ancient diggings" &mdash; as they
are familiarly called in the Lake Superior region &mdash; were ever
recognized as such; and this artificial cavern presents the most
conclusive proofs that a people in the remote past worked those
mines.  Upon the discovery of this mine, attention was at once
directed to numerous other cavities and depressions in the surface
of the earth at this and other points, and the result was that
nearly a hundred ancient pits were found, and in all of them
mining-tools of various kinds.  These ancient mines or pits are not
restricted to one locality, but extend over the entire length of
the copper region, from the eastern extremity of Keweenaw Point to
the Porcupine Mountains, a distance of nearly one hundred miles.
</p><p>In some of the ancient diggings, the stone hammers have the
marks of hard usage, fractured or battered faces, and a large
proportion of them are broken and unfit for use; but in other pits
the hammers are all sound, and many of them have the appearance of
never having been used.  These hammers, or mauls, which are of
various sizes, and not uniform in shape, are water-worn stones, of
great hardness, similar in all respects to those that are found in
abundance on the shore of the Lake, or in the gravel-banks of that
region.  They are generally trap-rock, embracing the varieties of
gray, porphyritic, hornblendic, sienitic, and amygdaloidal trap,
and appear to have had no labor expended upon them except the
chiseling of a groove around the middle for the purpose of
attaching a withe to serve as a handle.  In a few instances, I have
noticed small hammers, usually egg-shaped, without a groove; and
the battered or worn appearance at one end was all that induced the
belief that they were ever used for hammering.
</p><p>These hammers are usually from six to eight inches in length,
and from eight to twelve inches in circumference, and
<pb n="309"/>
weigh from four to eight pounds; but I have measured specimens that were
twenty-four inches in circumference at the groove, and would weigh
thirty pounds.  It seems hardly probable that one man could wield
so ponderous a tool; and from the fact that some of the large mauls
have two grooves around them, it is presumed that two men were
employed in using them.
</p><p>Stone hammers are found in all the ancient diggings, and in
some instances the number is almost incredible.  From the pits near
the Minnesota mines it is estimated that ten cart-loads have been
removed; I was informed that a well there was entirely stoned up
with them, and from the great number still remaining I am inclined
to believe the report.  A still greater number are said to have
been found at the Mesnard and Pontiac Mines, in the Portage Lake
district.  Farther east, in the vicinity of the Cliff and Central
Mines, they are also abundant; and it would seem, from the
circumstance of their being invariably found in the pits, that the
law among the ancient miners was similar to the one adopted by the
adventurers in California a few years since, who established their
claims by leaving their tools upon the land or in the pits where
they were digging for gold.
</p><p>In addition to the stone implements, copper chisels, wedges,
or "gads," are often found in the abandoned mines; and in the
vicinity, as well as in places more remote, other copper relics are
found, consisting of knives, spear-points, and rings, like the
bracelets of the present day.  In a collection at the Douglas
House, in Houghton, Portage Lake, are ornaments of this kind, and
also some spear-heads, nicely wrought and similar in shape and size
to the blade of a spontoon.  But I have never seen a copper relic
that had the appearance of having been melted.  They invariably
appear to have been cut and hammered into shape from a mass of
native copper.
</p><p>Colonel Charles Whittlesey, of Cleveland, Ohio, who has
examined these "ancient diggings," has several interesting relics,
some of which he has figured and described in the thirteenth volume
of the "Smithsonian Contributions to Knowledge."  In the Vermont
State Cabinet is a spear-head of native copper, about six inches
long, which was found in Williston, Vermont, in 1843.
</p><p>It may be proper here to remark, that the copper in these
relics is tougher than that which has been fused, and so is the
native copper of Lake Superior; and occasionally in these copper
relics blotches and grains of native silver are found.  These
circumstances serve to establish the fact, that the material of
which the implements were made was obtained at Lake Superior; for
there, and nowhere else in America, is native silver found in
grains, and sometimes in considerable masses, imbedded in a matrix
of native copper.  I well remember, when a boy, reading an article
relating to the "Lost Arts," in which the fact was stated, that a
piece of metal consisting of pure copper and silver had been found
in Hamilton County, Ohio, and that a copper knife had been found in
one of the ancient mounds at Marietta, which had distinct blotches
of pure silver in it.  The writer of the article claimed that the
people who manufactured that knife were in the possession of an
art, now lost, by which copper and silver could be melted and
indiscriminately mixed, but upon cooling would separate and remain
distinct and pure, instead of forming an alloy.  The discovery of
native copper and silver similarly associated in the Lake Superior
mines has not only destroyed this theory, but has established
beyond a doubt the locality whence that copper knife, and other
relics found in the ancient mounds and elsewhere, were obtained.
</p><p>Billets of wood that bear the marks of a tolerably sharp-cutting tool are often found in the old mines where water has been
suffered to remain since their abandonment.  In the Waterbury Mine
wooden shovels were found about three and one half feet long, some
of
<pb n="310"/>
which were much worn upon the blade, and appeared as
though they had been used for scraping together and throwing out
the refuse rock and dirt from the mine.*  At the same locality a
wooden bowl was found, the side being so worn as to show
conclusively that it had been used for baling water from the mine.
Similar implements have been found at the mines in the Portage Lake
and Ontonagon districts.  When first found, these wooden implements
appear sound, and being thoroughly saturated with water are heavy
and can be handled without breaking; but when dried they often
crack and warp so as to retain little of their original form and
appearance.  It is to be regretted that but few of these wooden
relics were saved and properly preserved by those who found them.
In a few instances the wooden withe or handle has been found
attached to the hammers, but upon being dried they usually fall to
pieces.
</p><p>At the Hilton Mine in the Ontonagon district, in October,
1863, as the men were removing the vegetable mould that had
accumulated in one of the old pits, they found at the depth of
about nine feet a leather bag, which was eleven inches long and
seven inches wide.  It was lying upon a mass of native copper which
the ancient miners had unsuccessfully attempted to remove from its
parent vein.  The bag was in a remarkable state of preservation,
the leather being quite pliable and as though as sheepskin.  It was
made up with the hair inside, was sewed across the bottom and up
one side with a leather string, and near the top holes were cut and
a leather string inserted to close the mouth by drawing it
together.  The bag was empty, but from its appearance I judged that
it had been used for transporting copper or other mineral, &mdash; the
leather in places showing marks of much service, and the hair being
almost entirely worn off.  I was unable to determine what kind of
skin it was, but inclined to the belief that it was from the
walrus, as the short, stubby hairs more closely resembled those of
that animal than of any other with which I am acquainted.  At the
time I saw the bag, &mdash; the day after it was discovered, &mdash; it was in
the possession of C. M. Sanderson, Esq., the agent of the Knowlton
Mine; but I hear it has since been taken to Boston and sold.
</p><p>In several of the ancient mines considerable masses of pure
copper detached from the main lode have been found, which were left
there by those who mined it.  At the Central Mine, not far from
Eagle Harbor, a mass of copper was found in one of these old pits
that weighed forty-six tons.  Every portion of the surface was
smooth, and appeared as though it had been hammered by those who
detached it from its original vein.  In the Mesnard Mine, in the
Portage Lake district, a detached mass of copper was found that
weighed eighteen tons, hammered smooth like the mass before named.
</p><p>But the most interesting specimen was found in an old pit near
the Minnesota Mine.  In removing the accumulated leaves and
vegetable mould, the workmen, at the depth of eighteen feet,
discovered a mass of copper ten feet long, three feet wide, and
more than a foot thick, weighing six tons.  On removing the earth
around the mass, it was found to rest upon skids, or timbers, piled
up to the height of about five feet.  These timbers, having been
constantly covered with water, were in a good state of
preservation, and at the ends showed plainly the marks of the tool
used in cutting them.  It was thought by those who saw the billets
when they were plump, that they were a species of oak; but the few
remaining pieces which I have seen were so cracked and shrivelled
that I have been unable to form an opinion as to the kind of wood.
This mass of copper, like all others found in those ancient pits,
was divested of all its ragged points, and hammered perfectly
smooth.  There was nothing in its appearance to show that it had
ever been cut from another mass; but upon clearing
<pb n="311"/>
out the rubbish from the bottom of the mine, which was about twenty-six
feet below the surface, a vein of pure metal was found from which
this had evidently been taken.
</p><p>A few unfinished jobs have been found in these ancient pits,
which throw some light upon the manner in which the work was
carried on.  In two instances there were projecting masses somewhat
resembling urns, or inverted short-necked bottles, and completely
smoothed by hammering, especially at the thinner portion or neck.
It appears that the ancient miners first removed the rock from
around the veins of copper.  This was done by building fires upon
or about it, and, when heated, crumbling it by throwing on water.
By means of stone mauls the fragments were broken up and removed.
When the vein was sufficiently exposed on all sides, a point was
selected where the copper was thinner or narrower than the average
of the vein.  Here they commenced cutting off a mass, and by
patient and long-continued hammering severed the two portions of
the vein.  In all the ancient mines which I have visited there is
abundant evidence that fire was extensively used in the removal of
rock; for not only do the rocks give proof of having been heated,
but charcoal and ashes are invariably found at the bottom of all
the rock excavations.
</p><p>In general, the mining was done by surface openings along the
line of the outcrop of the vein; but occasionally adits are driven
into the rock, similar to the one first discovered at the Minnesota
Mine before alluded to.
</p><p>The surface mines are usually nearly filled with leaves and
vegetable mould that have accumulated during the centuries that
have elapsed since their abandonment, and till within a few years
a heavy growth of timber covered the land; hence the numerous
slight depressions that occurred along the line of the vein excited
no suspicion that they were artificial excavations.  By the closest
observers they were regarded as natural depressions, caused either
by the disintegration of the underlying rock or the peculiar manner
in which the overlying drift was deposited.  In many of these
depressions, which have proved to be abandoned mines, trees of
enormous size are found growing, some of which are ascertained, by
counting their concentric rings, to be four hundred years old.  At
the Hilton Mine, directly over the leather bag before alluded to,
there was a hemlock-tree about three feet in diameter.  I noticed
the stump of a tree nearly four feet in diameter in a gap near the
Rockland Mine, where a hill had been actually cut asunder by these
ancient miners, and a deep valley formed by the removal of the
rock.  Until very recently this valley was not recognized as an
ancient mine; for, being ten rods in width, and cutting nearly at
right angles across the strata of the rock that formed the hill, it
was considered too extensive to have been made by human hands, and
was supposed to be the result of natural causes.  But about two
years since, during a very dry time, a destructive fire swept
through the woods, and so completely burned up all the vegetable
matter accumulated there as to expose the underlying rock, and
reveal its true character.  After the fire had done its work, it
was found that copper veins, which had been worked, ran through the
rock in the gap, and that the great bank upon the south side of the
hill, which was supposed to be a terraced gravel bank, proved to be
a vast accumulation of "attle," or refuse stone, that had been
taken from the artificial gap and deposited there.  The stones
forming this immense pile are generally small, and appear to have
been broken up by heating to facilitate their removal from the
mine, and possibly may have been again broken, with the hope of
finding copper in them.  In the midst of the pile I noticed several
stone hammers, or mauls, some of them measuring twenty inches in
girth around their grooves, and one I brought away weighing thirty
pounds.
</p><p>When examining this locality, I was struck with a significant
fact, tending
<pb n="312"/>
to show the long time that must have elapsed
since the abandonment of these mines.  I noticed in many instances
that the artificial groove around the hammers was nearly
obliterated upon the upper side, while upon the lower side, less
exposed to the abrading agency of the atmosphere and rains, the
groove presented a comparatively fresh appearance, and even the
slight markings made by the tool that cut them were quite distinct.
When I removed the overlying rock, and found a grooved maul in a
protected spot, the groove was generally as fresh as though it had
been made but a few months before.  The compact nature of the stone
of which these hammers are made, and their ability to resist the
action of weather and moisture, prove conclusively that much time
has been required to disintegrate their surface so as to obliterate
the artificial work which has been expended upon them.
</p><p>I feel unwilling to leave this subject without instituting an
inquiry relative to the time when these mines were wrought, and the
people who worked them.  Many who have been taught to regard the
present roving tribes of Indians as instinctively wise in matters
of medicine and mining are ready to award to that race the credit
of having worked these mines; but, inasmuch as even a traditional
knowledge of their existence was unknown to the Indians at the time
the Jesuit missionaries visited that region in the sixteenth
century, we incline to the opinion that another and distinct race
worked them.  I am unable to see why the descendants of a people
residing in the same country, and subject to the same wants, should
abandon the half-worked mines which their ancestors had opened, and
even fail to hand down to their posterity a tradition of their
existence.  If copper was in such demand that the ancestors of the
present race of Chippeways were induced to work so perseveringly to
obtain it, why did not the children continue to work, at least
enough to finish the jobs already commenced by their progenitors?
We cannot consistently attribute the Herculean labor expended on
these mines to the ancestors of the indolent race of North American
Indians.  We incline, rather, to the opinion that the miners were
the mound-builders, who resided south of the mines, and ultimately
found a home in Mexico.  The condition in which the mines were left
favors this theory; for in many instances unfinished jobs are
found, &mdash; as in the case of the mass of copper upon skids at the
Minnesota Mine, and the half-severed veins in other mines.  May we
not reasonably suppose that the miners came from the South, and
worked during the summer months, returning to their homes in
winter?  The circumstance that no traces of their habitations or
burial-places have ever been discovered in the immediate vicinity
of the mines leads to the inference that they came from a distance;
and the fact that copper rings, chisels, and knives, and
occasionally stone hammers, are found in the ancient mounds that
extend in an unbroken line from Ohio to Mexico, induces the belief
that the ancient miners and the ancient mound-builders were the
same people.
</p><p>It is said that artificial mounds are found in British
America; and I was informed of one upon the banks of the Ontonagon
River, about six miles from its mouth, but was unable to visit the
spot.  It is well known that they are quite abundant in Wisconsin,
and extend the entire length of the Mississippi Valley.
</p><p>It is a noticeable fact that as we proceed south we find the
mounds generally larger and more symmetrical than those in more
northern latitudes.  It would seem that the people who constructed
those in British America, in moving southward, (for we strongly
suspect that this people originally crossed Behring's Strait from
Asia,) improved in their style of building, and, on arriving at the
Ohio River, had so far improved as to be able to construct those
interesting works at Marietta, Moundville, and other points in that
region.  It was not till about the time they reached
<pb n="313"/>
the Ohio Valley that they manufactured pottery.  In that valley, and
thence to Mexico, fragments of earthen ware are very common; and in
the mounds entire vessels are not unfrequently found.  Upon
reaching Mexico, the mounds are seen to be still further improved
in size and form, and specimens of ancient pottery are more
abundant.  The great mound or pyramid at Cholula, which is a fair
type of the mounds in Mexico, is fourteen hundred and twenty-three
feet square at the base, and one hundred and seventy-seven feet
high, being larger than the celebrated pyramids of Egypt.  This
immense structure is said to have been built by the Toltecs, a
people who, according to tradition, as communicated to the
Spaniards, entered Mexico from the North in the year A. D. 648, and
established their capital on the northern confines of the great
valley of Mexico, at Tula, the remains of which city were visible,
and a record made of them, at the time of the Conquest by Cortes.
</p><p>This people were said to have possessed a good knowledge of
agriculture, and were well instructed in many useful mechanic arts.
They mixed gold and copper, and were experts in working these
metals.  For a period of four hundred years they occupied the
territory of Mexico or Anahuac; but secession, and the attendant
evils of war, pestilence, and famine, greatly reduced their
numbers, and the race disappeared from the land to give place to
their successors, the Aztecs, who also emigrated from the North.
Remnants of the Toltec race are said to have migrated still farther
south, and to have spread over Central America; and the remarkable
correspondence of dates inclines us to the belief that the famous
Manco Capac, whom the Peruvians worshipped as the founder of their
empire, may have been a wanderer from that once happy, but then
unfortunate people.  The useful arts, which he made known to the
semi-barbarous people among whom he settled, instead of originating
in the great luminary of the day, and being brought to earth by a
"child of the Sun," as they were taught, are far more likely to
have been cultivated by the Toltecs in the days of their
prosperity, and, on the dissolution of their government,
transmitted by those who, fearing the result, had fled and taken
refuge with the credulous Peruvians.  Whether the stupendous ruins
of temples found at Mitla, Palenque, and Uxmal were the work of the
Toltecs or the Aztecs, is immaterial.  It is sufficient for the
purposes of this paper to show that a people inhabited Mexico prior
to and at the time of the Conquest, who were far in advance of the
roving tribes of Indians that subsisted in the more northern and
eastern portions of North America.
</p><p>At the time of the conquests of Mexico and Peru, numerous
cities were found in those countries, and magnificent temples and
palaces abounded, some of which were richly decorated with massive
images of solid gold, others ornamented with fantastic and
sometimes hideous figures carved out of the solid rock.  But what
is remarkable, no <hi rend="italic">iron</hi> implements were used, nor did the
inhabitants have the least knowledge of its use, notwithstanding
iron ore was plentifully distributed through the country in which
they lived.  Not a trace of iron has ever been found in those grand
ruins of Yucatan visited by Stephens and Catherwood; nor do the
ruins of the holy city, Cuzco, give evidence that implements of
iron were used in its construction.  But the people of these
countries were acquainted with many of the metals, and the Spanish
invaders found numerous silver, tin, and copper mines that had been
worked by them.  All the deep, winding galleries of these mines
were driven without the aid of iron, steel, or gunpowder.  It is
said that an alloy of tin and copper was used for their edge-tools;
and with the aid of a silicious sand or dust, they were enabled to
cut and polish amethysts, emeralds, porphyry, and other hard
substances.  With these implements the elaborate carving in the
stone temples of Palenque and the other ruined cities of Central
America was executed.  The
<pb n="314"/>
great calendar-stone, which in
1790 was disinterred in the city of Mexico, was nicely wrought out
of a block of dark porphyry, that is estimated to have weighed
fifty tons, and must have been transported several leagues; for the
nearest point where porphyry of that character is found is upon the
shores of Lake Chalco, many miles distant from the city of Mexico.
In the absence of iron, some tough metal would be in requisition
for the tools and machinery necessary in the execution and removal
of such a gigantic and elaborate work.  In many abandoned quarries
in Mexico and Central America unfinished blocks of granite and
porphyry are found, which are supposed to have been the work of the
Toltecs, and abandoned by them at the time of the invasion of the
fierce Aztec.  Assuming this to be the fact, we can readily
conceive why the half-raised mass of copper in the Minnesota Mine
should also be abandoned; for a people suddenly scattered as the
Toltecs were &mdash; so suddenly as to leave temples half finished, and
blocks of stone half hewn &mdash; would have no further use for copper
tools; and hence the raw material would no longer have a value.  In
the abandoned quarries near Mitla, amid fragments of pillars and
architraves and half-finished block of granite, copper axes,
chisels, and wedges were found in abundance; but the same
inordinate love of money that prompted adventurers to flock to
Chiriqui, a few years since, to rob the ancient burying-grounds of
their golden idols, induced others to search the old quarries and
mines of Mexico and Central America, and take from them any relics
that were intrinsically valuable.
</p><p>In Mexico, the mounds were built so that their summits were
visible from every portion of the surrounding city, in order that
the inhabitants might continually have in view the sacred fires
that were ever kept burning on each side of the sacrificial altar.
The same is strikingly true of the mounds at the West; for they are
invariably placed so that their summits occupy a commanding
position, &mdash; a circumstance that has induced many to suppose them to
have been built for military purposes, and to have served as watch-towers.  But when we reflect that the attacks of savage or half-civilized peoples are usually made in the night-time, we shall
hardly suppose these structures were raised for any such purpose.
The Pyramid of Cholula is composed of alternate layers of brick and
clay, or possibly of burnt and unburnt brick; and others in Mexico
are built of unburnt brick.  Many of the mounds in the West are of
clay, &mdash; perhaps of unburnt brick, &mdash; in situations where clay is not
so abundant as other earths.
</p><p>I recollect visiting Circleville, Ohio, when it was really a
<hi rend="italic">Circle</hi>-ville.  An octagonal court-house stood upon an ancient
mound, and the dwellings and stores were built upon an ancient
circular wall of earth that encompassed an area around the mound.
South of this circular inclosure, and joining it, was a square
inclosure of several acres, surrounded by a wall about ten feet
high.  What is remarkable, this square wall &mdash; and we presume the
same is true also of the mound and circular wall &mdash; was built of
clay, perhaps of unburnt brick, that must have been transported a
considerable distance; for no clay exists upon that alluvial
bottom, and the nearest point where it is found is three fourths of
a mile distant, across a considerable creek.  On a subsequent visit
to this place, I found the people using the clay from the wall of
the square inclosure for making brick, and streets had been cut
across the circular inclosure, so that the city is no longer
entitled to the name of Circleville.  In many instances, the ruined
cities of Central America have inclosures resembling those at
Circleville, surrounding the Teocallis, or sacred temples, which
almost invariably stand upon mounds, or, as they are commonly
called, pyramids.
</p><p>With these many points of resemblance, the conclusion is
irresistible, that the mounds of the West were but the germs of the
more symmetrical pyramids
<pb n="315"/>
of Mexico and Central America,
and that the people who constructed them were, in intelligence and
civilization, far in advance of the roving tribes of North American
Indians who inhabited the country at the time of its discovery.
</p><p>If it be true, as tradition informs us, that the Toltecs were
a cultivated race, even more advanced than the Aztecs who occupied
Mexico at the time of the Conquest, we may reasonably suppose that
a metal so valuable to them as copper would be in great demand, and
that mines of it, even at a remote distance, would be worked by a
people, the construction of whose religious temples and royal
palaces, and, it would seem, their nationality even, depended upon
its possession.
</p><p>Other evidence might be adduced to show that the extensive
mining-pits on the shores of Lake Superior were not the work of the
indolent and untutored race of Indians who now inhabit that region,
nor of their ancestors, but of a people comparatively well
acquainted with the mechanic arts.  Our article, however, has
already extended beyond the limits contemplated.  I therefore leave
the subject, with the hope that the few hints here thrown out may
awaken other and abler minds to its investigation.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
