<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HarChie"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="HarChie">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Three Noted Chiefs of the Sioux</title>
<title type="sort">three noted chiefs of the sioux</title>
<author>Anonymous</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">10</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HarChie</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476026</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Three Noted Chiefs of the Sioux</title>
<title level="j">Harper's Weekly</title>
<title type="sort">three noted chiefs of the sioux</title>
<author>Anonymous</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harper's Weekly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1890-10-20">20 October 1890</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 34, pp. 995</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the
text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1890">1890</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-08">August 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>TEI tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">
<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
<head>"Three Noted Chiefs of the Sioux."
<lb/><hi rend="italic">Harper's Weekly</hi> 34, 20 Oct. 1890: 995.</head>

<pb id="HarChie995" n="995"/>

<p>THE delusion of the coming of the Messiah among the Indians of
the Northwest, with the resulting ceremony known as the ghost
dance, is indicative of greater danger of an Indian war in that
region than has existed since 1876.  Never before have diverse
Indian tribes been so generally united upon a single idea.  The
conspiracy of Pontiac and the arrayment of savage forces by
Tecumseh are insignificant by comparison.  The conditions do not
exist that ordinarily have led to wars upon the Western frontier.
The peril of the situation lies in the fanaticism which may carry
the superstitious and excitable Indian to the point of hostilities
in defiance of all hope of ultimate success; and the uncertainty of
this element baffles the judgment of the oldest frontiersman, in
the effort to determine the extent of the danger.  A single spark
in the tinder of excited religious gatherings may precipitate an
Indian war more sanguinary than any similar war that has ever
occurred.  The hope of peace lies in the judicious display of
force, united with conciliation, by the United States authorities,
helped by the coming of severely cold weather, which would make an
outbreak obviously hopeless, and allow time for the delusion to
dissipate.
</p><p>In the present state of affairs the noted Sioux chief Sitting
Bull, who has already been the source of so much trouble in the
course of Indian affairs, appears once more as a prominent figure.
This time he does not have the fair pretext under which he incited
the war in 1876, which led to the defeat and massacre of General
Custer's command on Little Big Horn River, and terminated with the
escape of Sitting Bull and his immediate followers into British
territory.  Since his surrender through the mediation of the
Dominion officials in 1880, and his return to the Standing Rock
Reservation in 1883, he has found his authority greatly diminished
among the Dakota Sioux.  This authority he has endeavored to regain
by identifying himself with every element of hostility to the
whites and opposition to the innovations of civilization, and has
been so far successful that at the conference at Standing Rock,
Dakota, in July and August, 1888, he influenced his tribe to refuse
to relinquish their lands by purchase.
</p><p>Contrary to the general estimate concerning him, this famous
chief is a man of mediocre ability, not noted for bravery as a
warrior, and inferior as a commander and an intelligence to some of
his lieutenants.  Sheer obstinacy, stubborn tenacity of purpose,
and low cunning, with an aptitude for theatrical effect and for
working on the superstitions of his people, are the attributes by
which he has acquired and retained influence among the Northwest
tribes.  Personally he is pompous, vain, boastful, licentious, and
untrustworthy.  He has constantly been a disturbing element at the
agency since his return from confinement as a military prisoner
seven years ago, and has grown worse in this respect as he has felt
his authority and importance departing.
</p><p>The dangerous elements that this chief has called around him
do not represent the most noted Indians who fought under his
leadership in the Sioux war fourteen years ago and followed him in
his exile across the British frontier.  Those warriors have
realized the futility of warfare with the whites, and are sincerely
desirous not to incur its evils again.  The Indians of whom Sitting
Bull is the representative comprise the irreconcilables &mdash; warriors
who adhere to the old aboriginal usages and chiefs jealous of their
authority, which wanes in proportion as their followers advance in
civilization.  This small but dangerous faction are ready at any
time for war.  In sympathy with their desire are many young men
ambitious for a chance to distinguish themselves as warriors.
</p><p>The chiefs of the greatest influence among the majority of the
Indians are men of strong will and good sense, who have accepted
the situation, and are willing to adapt themselves to the new
condition of things.  They could control their people by their own
influence unaided if the scene of the gatherings was not so near
exposed settlements, which tempt lawless Indians to make trouble in
hope of booty.  The present excitement is fanned to some extent by
unscrupulous white persons desirous of a war with the hope that it
shall bring them emolument, and end in throwing open the
reservation lands for settlement.
</p><p>Foremost among the Indians who have taken the side of peace
and safety, and have made every effort to break up the delusion
which finds expression in the ghost dances, are chiefs Gall and
John Grass, both warriors held in great respect for wisdom and
bravery, who took a prominent part as followers of Sitting Bull in
the war that brought about the massacre at the Little Big Horn.
The change in them in the fourteen years since both these chiefs
were on the war-path in the equipments of savagery &mdash; the war
bonnets, the braided hair pieced out with buffalo tails, and the
array of weapons &mdash; is remarkable.  The difference between the good
and the bad Indian is indicated in the countenance even more
obviously than among the civilized whites.  The strong faces of
these two chiefs indicate their character, which, unlike that of
Sitting Bull, is fearless, upright, bright, and progressive.
</p><p>The foremost leader among the Sioux is Chief Gall, who stands
above all other chiefs in their estimation.  Many persons familiar
with the situation say that he planned the campaign of 1876, which
made Sitting Bull famous as a commander and strategist, and affirm
that no serious outbreak among the Northwest tribes will occur so
long as he remains friendly to the government.
</p><p>This famous war chief is one of the best farmers at the
Standing Rock Agency.  His family are all members of the
Episcopalian Church.  He takes no part in the ghost dance, nor does
he lend his sanction to it.  He feels that the Indians fail to
appreciate the benefits of their present surroundings, and want old
times, which have been magnified in their imagination by tradition,
to return.  "I think it better," he said, at the conclusion of a
conference he and John Grass had with Major James McLaughlin, the
United States agent at Standing Rock, "for us to live as we are
living rather than create trouble, not knowing how it will end."
</p><p>An element of great value in the preservation of order upon
the reservation, and conspicuously useful in the present disturbed
condition of affairs at the agency, is the Indian police.  At
Standing Rock the force is thirty in number, commanded by a captain
and a lieutenant.  For the adjudication of affairs occurring upon
the reservation an Indian court has been established at the agency.
Two of the judges are members of the police force, and the third
one is John Grass, who speaks English.  The impartiality and
excellent judgment displayed in the conduct of this court have been
noteworthy, and its decisions have almost invariably been accepted
without complaint.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
