<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HawLege"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="HawLege">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Legends of the Province House</title>
<title type="sort">legends of the province house</title>
<author>Hawthorne, Nathaniel, 1804-1864</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Charles Keller</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">120</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HawLege</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476053</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Legends of the Province House</title>
<title level="m">The Complete Novels and Selected Tales of Nathaniel Hawthorne</title>
<title type="sort">legends of the province house</title>
<author>Nathaniel Hawthorne</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
<name>Norman Holmes Pearson</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>Modern Library Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>pp 952-990.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Random House, Inc.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1937">1937</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa Library call number PS 1850 1937</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1837">1837</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-09">September 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="book" id="d3"> <pb n="952"/>
<head>LEGENDS OF THE PROVINCE HOUSE</head>
<div2 type="story" id="d4">
<head>I<lb/>
HOWE'S MASQUERADE</head>

<p>ONE afternoon, last summer, while walking along Washington Street,
my
eye was attracted by a signboard protruding over a narrow archway,
nearly opposite the Old South Church. The sign represented the
front of
a
stately edifice, which was designated as the ``OLD PROVINCE HOUSE,
kept
by Thomas Waite.'' I was glad to be thus reminded of a purpose,
long entertained, of visiting and rambling over the mansion of the
old
royal governors of Massachusetts; and entering the arched passage,
which
penetrated through the middle of a brick row of shops, a few steps
transported
me from the busy heart of modern Boston into a small and secluded
court-yard. One side of this space was occupied by the square front
of
the Province House, three stories high, and surmounted by a cupola,
on the
top of
which a gilded Indian was discernible, with his bow bent and his
arrow on
the string, as if aiming at the weathercock on the spire of the Old
South.
The figure has kept this attitude for seventy years or more, ever
since
good Deacon Drowne, a cunning carver of wood, first stationed him
on
his long sentinel's watch over the city.
</p><p>The Province House is constructed of brick, which seems
recently to
have been overlaid with a coat of light-colored paint. A flight of
red freestone steps, fenced in by a balustrade of curiously wrought
iron,
ascends
from the court-yard to the spacious porch, over which is a balcony,
with
an iron balustrade of similar pattern and workmanship to that
beneath.
These letters and figures&mdash;16 P.S. 79&mdash;are wrought into the iron
work of
the balcony, and probably express the date of the edifice, with the
initials
of its founder's name. A wide door with double leaves admitted me
into
the hall or entry, on the right of which is the entrance to the
bar-room.
</p><p>It was in this apartment, I presume, that the ancient
governors held
their levees, with vice-regal pomp, surrounded by the military men,
the
councillors, the judges, and other officers of the crown, while all
the loyalty of the province thronged to do them honor. But the
room, in
its present condition, cannot boast even of faded magnificence. The
panelled
wainscot is covered with dingy paint, and acquires a duskier hue
from
   <pb n="953"/>
the deep shadow into which the Province House is thrown by the
brick
block that shuts it in from Washington Street. A ray of sunshine
never
visits this apartment any more than the glare of the festal
torches, which
have been extinguished from the era of the Revolution. The most
venerable and ornamental object is a chimney-piece set round with
Dutch
tiles
of blue-figured China, representing scenes from Scripture; and, for
aught
I know, the lady of Pownall or Bernard may have sat beside this
fireplace, and told her children the story of each blue tile. A bar
in
modern
style, well replenished with decanters, bottles, cigar boxes, and
net-work
bags of lemons, and provided with a beer pump, and a soda fount,
extends along one side of the room. At my entrance, an elderly
person
was
smacking his lips with a zest which satisfied me that the cellars
of the
Province House still hold good liquor, though doubtless of other
vintages
than were quaffed by the old governors. After sipping a glass of
port sangaree, prepared by the skilful hands of Mr. Thomas Waite,
I besought
that
worthy successor and representative of so many historic personages
to
conduct me over their time honored mansion.
</p><p>He readily complied; but, to confess the truth, I was forced
to draw
strenuously upon my imagination, in order to find aught that was
interesting in a house which, without its historic associations,
would
have
seemed merely such a tavern as is usually favored by the custom of
decent
city boarders, and old-fashioned country gentlemen. The chambers,
which were probably spacious in former times, are now cut up by
partitions, and subdivided into little nooks, each affording scanty
room
for the
narrow bed and chair and dressing-table of a single lodger. The
great
staircase, however, may be termed, without much hyperbole, a
feature of
grandeur and magnificence. It winds through the midst of the house
by
flights of broad steps, each flight terminating in a square
landing-place,
whence the ascent is continued towards the cupola. A carved
balustrade,
freshly painted in the lower stories, but growing dingier as we
ascend,
borders the staircase with its quaintly twisted and intertwined
pillars,
from top to bottom. Up these stairs the military boots, or
perchance the
gouty shoes, of many a governor have trodden, as the wearers
mounted to
the cupola, which afforded them so wide a view over their
metropolis and
the surrounding country. The cupola is an octagon, with several
windows,
and a door opening upon the roof. From this station, as I pleased
myself
with imagining, Gage may have beheld his disastrous victory on
Bunker
Hill (unless one of the tri-mountains intervened), and Howe have
marked
the approaches of Washington's besieging army; although the
buildings
since erected in the vicinity have shut out almost every object,
save the
steeple of the Old South, which seems almost within arm's length.
Descending from the cupola, I paused in the garret to observe the
ponderous white-oak framework, so much more massive than the frames
of
modern houses, and thereby resembling an antique skeleton. The
brick
walls,
the materials of which were imported from Holland, a d the timbers
of
the mansion, are still as sound as ever; but the floors and other
interior
parts being greatly decayed, it is contemplated to gut the whole,
and build
   <pb n="954"/>
a new house within the ancient frame and brick work. Among other
inconveniences of the present edifice, mine host mentioned that any
jar or
motion was apt to shake down the dust of ages out of the ceiling of
one
chamber upon the floor of that beneath it.
</p><p>We stepped forth from the great front window into the
balcony, where,
in old times, it was doubtless the custom of the king's
representative to
Show himself to a loyal populace, requiting their huzzas and
tossed-up
hats with stately bendings of his dignified person. In those days
the front
of the Province House looked upon the street; and the whole site
now
occupied by the brick range of stores, as well as the present
court-yard,
was laid out in grass plats, overshadowed by trees and bordered by
a
wrought-iron fence. Now, the old aristocratic edifice hides its
time-worn
visage behind an upstart modern building; at one of the back
windows I
observed some pretty tailoresses, sewing and chatting and laughing,
with
now and then a careless glance towards the balcony. Descending
thence,
we again entered the bar-room, where the elderly gentleman above
mentioned, the smack of whose lips had spoken so favorably for Mr.
Waite's
good liquor, was still lounging in his chair. He seemed to be, if
not a
lodger, at least a familiar visitor of the house, who might be
supposed to
have his regular score at the bar, his summer seat at the open
window,
and his prescriptive corner at the winter's fireside. Being of a
sociable aspect, I ventured to address him with a remark calculated
to draw
forth his
historical reminiscences, if any such were in his mind; and it
gratified me
to discover, that, between memory and tradition, the old gentleman
was
really possessed of some very pleasant gossip about the Province
House.
The portion of his talk which chiefly interested me was the outline
of the
following legend. He professed to have received it at one or two
removes
from an eye-witness; but this derivation, together with the lapse
of time,
must have afforded opportunities for many variations of the
narrative; so
that despairing of literal and absolute truth, I have not scrupled
to make
such further changes as seemed conducive to the reader's profit and
delight.

</p><p>&mdash;
</p><p>At one of the entertainments given at the Province House,
during the
latter part of the siege of Boston, there passed a scene which has
never yet
been satisfactorily explained. The officers of the British army,
and the
loyal gentry of the province, most of whom were collected within
the beleaguered town, had been invited to a masked ball; for it was
the
policy
of Sir William Howe to hide the distress and danger of the period,
and the
desperate aspect of the siege, under an ostentation of festivity.
The spectacle of this evening, if the oldest members of the
provincial
court circle
might be believed, was the most gay and gorgeous affair that had
occurred
in the annals of the government. The brilliantly-lighted apartments
were
thronged with figures that seemed to have stepped from the dark
canvas
of historic portraits, or to have flitted forth from the magic
pages of romance, or at least to have flown hither from one of the
London
theatres,
   <pb n="955"/>
without a change of garments. Steeled knights of the Conquest,
bearded
statesmen of Queen Elizabeth, and high-ruffled ladies of her court,
were
mingled with characters of comedy, such as a party-colored Merry
Andrew, jingling his cap and bells; a Falstaff, almost as
provocative
of
laughter as his prototype; and a Don Quixote, with a bean pole for
a
lance, and a pot lid for a shield.
</p><p>But the broadest merriment was excited by a group of figures
ridiculously dressed in old regimentals, which seemed to have been
purchased
at a military rag fair, or pilfered from some receptacle of the
cast-off
clothes of both the French and British armies. Portions of their
attire had
probably been worn at the siege of Louisburg, and the coats of most
recent cut might have been rent and tattered by sword, ball, or
bayonet, as
long ago as Wolfe's victory. One of these worthies&mdash;a tall, lank
figure,
brandishing a rusty sword of immense longitude&mdash;purported to be no
less
a personage than General George Washington; and the other principal
officers of the American army, such as Gates, Lee, Putnam,
Schuyler,
Ward and Heath, were represented by similar scarecrows. An
interview in
the mock heroic style, between the rebel warriors and the British
commander-in-chief, was received with immense applause, which came
loudest of all from the loyalists of the colony. There was one of
the
guests,
however, who stood apart, eyeing these antics sternly and
scornfully, at
once with a frown and a bitter smile.
</p><p>It was an old man, formerly of high station and great repute
in the
province, and who had been a very famous soldier in his day. Some
surprise had been expressed that a person of Colonel Joliffe's
known
whig
principles, though now too old to take an active part in the
contest, should
have remained in Boston during the siege, and especially that he
should
consent to show himself in the mansion of Sir William Howe. But
thither
he had come, with a fair granddaughter under his arm; and there,
amid
all the mirth and buffoonery, stood this stern old figure, the best
sustained character in the masquerade, because so well representing
the antique spirit of his native land. The other guests affirmed
that
Colonel
Joliffe's black puritanical scowl threw a shadow round about him;
although in spite of his sombre influence their gayety continued to
blaze
higher, like&mdash;(an ominous comparison)&mdash;the flickering brilliancy of
a
lamp which has but a little while to burn. Eleven strokes, full
half an
hour ago, had pealed from the clock of the Old South, when a rumor
was
circulated among the company that some new spectacle or pageant was
about to be exhibited, which should put a fitting close to the
splendid festivities of the night.
</p><p>``What new jest has your Excellency in hand?'' asked the
Rev. Mather
Byles, whose Presbyterian scruples had not kept him from the
entertainment. ``Trust me, sir, I have already laughed more than
beseems my
cloth
at your Homeric confabulation with yonder ragamuffin General of the
rebels. One other such fit of merriment, and I must throw off my
clerical
wig and band.''
</p><p>``Not so, good Doctor Byles,'' answered Sir William Howe;
``if mirth
   <pb n="956"/>
were a crime, you had never gained your doctorate in divinity. As
to this
new foolery, I know no more about it than yourself; perhaps not so
much.
Honestly now, Doctor, have you not stirred up the sober brains of
some
of your countrymen to enact a scene in our masquerade?''
</p><p>``Perhaps,'' slyly remarked the granddaughter of Colonel
Joliffe, whose
high spirit had been stung by many taunts against New
England,&mdash;``perhaps we are to have a mask of allegorical figures.
Victory, with
trophies
from Lexington and Bunker Hill&mdash;Plenty, with her overflowing horn,
to
typify the present abundance in this good town&mdash;and Glory, with a
wreath for his Excellency's brow.''
</p><p>Sir William Howe smiled at words which he would have
answered with
one of his darkest frowns had they been uttered by lips that wore
a beard.
He was spared the necessity of a retort, by a singular
interruption. A
sound of music was heard without the house, as if proceeding from
a full
band of military instruments stationed in the street, playing not
such a
festal strain as was suited to the occasion, but a slow funeral
march. The
drums appeared to be muffled, and the trumpets poured forth a
wailing
breath, which at once hushed the merriment of the auditors, filling
all
with wonder, and some with apprehension. The idea occurred to many
that either the funeral procession of some great personage had
halted in
front of the Province House, or that a corpse, in a velvet-covered
and gorgeously-decorated coffin, was about to be borne from the
portal.
After
listening a moment, Sir William Howe called, in a stern voice, to
the
leader of the musicians, who had hitherto enlivened the
entertainment
with gay and lightsome melodies. The man was drum-major to one of
the
British regiments.
</p><p>``Dighton,'' demanded the general, ``what means this
foolery? Bid your
band silence that dead march&mdash;or, by my word, they shall have
sufficient
cause for their lugubrious strains! Silence it, sirrah!''
</p><p>``Please your honor,'' answered the drum-major, whose
rubicund visage
had lost all its color, ``the fault is none of mine. I and my band
are all
here together, and I question whether there be a man of us that
could play
that march without book. I never heard it but once before, and that
was
at the funeral of his late Majesty, King George the Second.''
</p><p>``Well, well!'' said Sir William Howe, recovering his
composure&mdash;``it is
the prelude to some masquerading antic. Let it pass.''
</p><p>A figure now presented itself, but among the many fantastic
masks that
were dispersed through the apartments none could tell precisely
from
whence it came. It was a man in an old-fashioned dress of black
serge
and having the aspect of a steward or principal domestic in the
household
of a nobleman or great English landholder. This figure advanced to
the
outer door of the mansion, and throwing both its leaves wide open,
withdrew a little to one side and looked back towards the grand
staircase as if
expecting some person to descend. At the same time the music in the
street sounded a loud and doleful summons. The eyes of Sir William
Howe and his guests being directed to the staircase, there
appeared, on
the uppermost landing-place that was discernible from the bottom,
several
   <pb n="957"/>
personages descending towards the door. The foremost was a man
of
stern visage, wearing a steeple-crowned hat and a skull-cap beneath
it; a
dark cloak, and huge wrinkled boots that came half-way up his legs.
Under his arm was a rolled-up banner, which seemed to be the banner
of
England, but strangely rent and torn; he had a sword in his right
hand,
and grasped a Bible in his left. The next figure was of milder
aspect, yet
full of dignity, wearing a broad ruff, over which descended a
beard, a
gown of wrought velvet, and a doublet and hose of black satin. He
carried a roll of manuscript in his hand. Close behind these two
came
a
young man of very striking countenance and demeanor, with deep
thought and contemplation on his brow, and perhaps a flash of
enthusiasm in his eye. His garb, like that of his predecessors, was
of an
antique
fashion, and there was a stain of blood upon his ruff. In the same
group
with these were three or four others, all men of dignity and
evident command, and bearing themselves like personages who were
accustomed to
the gaze of the multitude. It was the idea of the beholders that
these figures went to join the mysterious funeral that had halted
in front
of the
Province House; yet that supposition seemed to be contradicted by
the
air of triumph with which they waved their hands, as they crossed
the
threshold and vanished through the portal.
</p><p>``In the devil's name what is this?'' muttered Sir William
Howe to a
gentleman beside him; ``a procession of the regicide judges of King
Charles the martyr?''
</p><p>``These,'' said Colonel Joliffe, breaking silence almost for
the first time
that evening,&mdash;``these, if I interpret them aright, are the Puritan
governors&mdash;the rulers of the old original Democracy of
Massachusetts.
Endicott, with the banner from which he had torn the symbol of
subjection,
and Winthrop, and Sir Henry Vane, and Dudley, Haynes, Bellingham,
and Leverett.''
</p><p>``Why had that young man a stain of blood upon his ruff?''
asked Miss
Joliffe.
</p><p>``Because, in after years,'' answered her grandfather, ``he
laid down
the wisest head in England upon the block for the principles of
liberty.''
</p><p>``Will not your Excellency order out the guard?'' whispered
Lord
Percy, who, with other British officers, had now assembled round
the General. ``There may be a plot under this mummery.''
</p><p>``Tush! we have nothing to fear,'' carelessly replied Sir
William Howe.
``There can be no worse treason in the matter than a jest, and that
somewhat of the dullest. Even were it a sharp and bitter one, our
best
policy
would be to laugh it off. See&mdash;here come more of these gentry.''
</p><p>Another group of characters had now partly descended the
staircase.
The first was a venerable and white-bearded patriarch, who
cautiously
felt his way downward with a staff. Treading hastily behind him,
and
stretching forth his gauntleted hand as if to grasp the old man's
shoulder,
came a tall, soldier-like figure, equipped with a plumed cap of
steel, a
bright breastplate, and a long sword, which rattled against the
stairs.
Next was seen a stout man, dressed in rich and courtly attire, but
not of
   <pb n="958"/>
courtly demeanor; his gait had the swinging motion of a seaman's
walk,
and chancing to stumble on the staircase, he suddenly grew
wrathful, and
was heard to mutter an oath. He was followed by a noble-looking
personage in a curled wig, such as are represented in the portraits
of
Queen
Anne's time and earlier; and the breast of his coat was decorated
with an
embroidered star. While advancing to the door, he bowed to the
right
hand and to the left, in a very gracious and insinuating style; but
as he
crossed the threshold, unlike the early Puritan governors, he
seemed to
wring his hands with sorrow.
</p><p>``Prithee, play the part of a chorus, good Doctor Byles,''
said Sir William Howe. ``What worthies are these?''
</p><p>``If it please your Excellency they lived somewhat before my
day,'' answered the doctor; ``but doubtless our friend, the
Colonel, has
been hand
and glove with them.''
</p><p>``Their living faces I never looked upon,'' said Colonel
Joliffe, gravely;
``although I have spoken face to face with many rulers of this
land, and
shall greet yet another with an old man's blessing ere I die. But
we talk of
these figures. I take the venerable patriarch to be Bradstreet, the
last of
the Puritans, who was governor at ninety, or thereabouts. The next
is Sir
Edmund Andros, a tyrant, as any New England school-boy will tell
you;
and therefore the people cast him down from his high seat into a
dungeon. Then comes Sir William Phipps, shepherd, cooper,
sea-captain,
and
governor&mdash;may many of his countrymen rise as high from as low an
origin! Lastly, you saw the gracious Earl of Bellamont, who ruled
us under King William.''
</p><p>``But what is the meaning of it all?'' asked Lord Percy.
</p><p>``Now, were I a rebel,'' said Miss Joliffe, half aloud, ``I
might fancy
that the ghosts of these ancient governors had been summoned to
form
the funeral procession of royal authority in New England.''
</p><p>Several other figures were now seen at the turn of the
staircase. The
one in advance had a thoughtful, anxious, and somewhat crafty
expression of face, and in spite of his loftiness of manner, which
was
evidently
the result both of an ambitious spirit and of long continuance in
high stations, he seemed not incapable of cringing to a greater
than
himself. A
few steps behind came an officer in a scarlet and embroidered
uniform,
cut in a fashion old enough to have been worn by the Duke of
Marlborough. His nose had a rubicund tinge, which, together with
the
twinkle of
his eye, might have marked him as a lover of the wine cup and good
fellowship; notwithstanding which tokens he appeared ill at ease,
and
often
glanced around him as if apprehensive of some secret mischief. Next
came
a portly gentleman, wearing a coat of shaggy cloth, lined with
silken velvet; he had sense, shrewdness, and humor in his face, and
a folio
volume
under his arm; but his aspect was that of a man vexed and tormented
beyond all patience, and harassed almost to death. He went hastily
down,
and was followed by a dignified person, dressed in a purple velvet
suit
with very rich embroidery; his demeanor would have possessed much
stateliness, only that a grievous fit of the gout compelled him to
hobble
   <pb n="959"/>
from stair to stair, with contortions of face and body. When Dr.
Byles beheld this figure on the staircase, he shivered as with an
ague, but
continued to watch him steadfastly, until the gouty gentleman had
reached
the threshold, made a gesture of anguish and despair, and vanished
into
the outer gloom, whither the funeral music summoned him.
</p><p>``Governor Belcher!&mdash;my old patron!&mdash;in his very shape and
dress!''
gasped Doctor Byles. ``This is an awful mockery!''
</p><p>``A tedious foolery, rather,'' said Sir William Howe, with
an air of indifference. ``But who were the three that preceded
him?''
</p><p>``Governor Dudley, a cunning politician&mdash;yet his craft once
brought
him to a prison,'' replied Colonel Joliffe. ``Governor Shute,
formerly a Colonel under Marlborough, and whom the people
frightened out of the
province; and learned Governor Burnet, whom the legislature
tormented
into a mortal fever.''
</p><p>``Methinks they were miserable men, these royal governors of
Massachusetts,'' observed Miss Joliffe. ``Heavens, how dim the
light
grows!''
</p><p>It was certainly a fact that the large lamp which
illuminated the stair-case now burned dim and duskily: so that
several figures, which
passed
hastily down the stairs and went forth from the porch, appeared
rather
like shadows than persons of fleshly substance. Sir William Howe
and his
guests stood at the doors of the contiguous apartments, watching
the
progress of this singular pageant, with various emotions of anger,
contempt, or half-acknowledged fear, but still with an anxious
curiosity. The
shapes which now seemed hastening to join the mysterious procession
were recognized rather by striking peculiarities of dress, or broad
characteristics of manner, than by any perceptible resemblance of
features to
their prototypes. Their faces, indeed, were invariably kept in deep
shadow. But Doctor Byles, and other gentlemen who had long been
familiar
with the successive rulers of the province, were heard to whisper
the
names of Shirley, of Pownall, of Sir Francis Bernard, and of the
well-remembered Hutchinson; thereby confessing that the actors,
whoever
they might be, in this spectral march of governors, had succeeded
in putting on some distant portraiture of the real personages. As
they
vanished
from the door, still did these shadows toss their arms into the
gloom of
night, with a dread expression of woe. Following the mimic
representative
of Hutchinson came a military figure, holding before his face the
cocked
hat which he had taken from his powdered head; but his epaulettes
and
other insignia of rank were those of a general officer, and
something in his
mien reminded the beholders of one who had recently been master of
the
Province House, and chief of all the land.
</p><p>``The shape of Gage, as true as in a looking-glass,''
exclaimed Lord
Percy, turning pale.
</p><p>``No, surely,'' cried Miss Joliffe, laughing hysterically;
``it could not be
Gage, or Sir William would have greeted his old comrade in arms!
Perhaps he will not suffer the next to pass unchallenged.''
</p><p>``Of that be assured, young lady,'' answered Sir William
Howe, fixing
his eyes, with a very marked expression, upon the immovable visage
of
   <pb n="960"/>
her grandfather. ``I have long enough delayed to pay the ceremonies
of a
host to these departing guests. The next that takes his leave shall
receive
due courtesy.''
</p><p>A wild and dreary burst of music came through the open door.
It
seemed as if the procession, which had been gradually filling up
its ranks,
were now about to move, and that this loud peal of the wailing
trumpets,
and roll of the muffled drums, were a call to some loiterer to make
haste.
Many eyes, by an irresistible impulse, were turned upon Sir William
Howe, as if it were he whom the dreary music summoned to the
funeral or
departed power.
</p><p>``See!&mdash;here comes the last!'' whispered Miss Joliffe,
pointing her tremulous finger to the staircase.
</p><p>A figure had come into view as if descending the stairs;
although so
dusky was the region whence it emerged, some of the spectators
fancied
that they had seen this human shape suddenly moulding itself amid
the
gloom. Downward the figure came, with a stately and martial tread,
and
reaching the lowest stair was observed to be a tall man, booted and
wrapped in a military cloak, which was drawn up around the face so
as to
meet the flapped brim of a laced hat. The features, therefore, were
completely hidden. But the British officers deemed that they had
seen
that
military cloak before, and even recognized the frayed embroidery on
the
collar, as well as the gilded scabbard of a sword which protruded
from
the folds of the cloak, and glittered in a vivid gleam of light.
Apart from
these trifling particulars, there were characteristics of gait and
bearing
which impelled the wondering guests to glance from the shrouded
figure
to Sir William Howe, as if to satisfy themselves that their host
had not
suddenly vanished from the midst of them.
</p><p>With a dark flush of wrath upon his brow they saw the
General draw
his sword and advance to meet the figure in the cloak before the
latter had
stepped one pace upon the floor.
</p><p>``Villain, unmuffle yourself!'' cried he. ``You pass no
farther!''
</p><p>The figure, without blenching a hair's breadth from the
sword which
was pointed at his breast, made a solemn pause and lowered the cape
of
the cloak from about his face, yet not sufficiently for the
spectators to
catch a glimpse of it. But Sir William Howe had evidently seen
enough.
The sternness of his countenance gave place to a look of wild
amazement,
if not horror, while he recoiled several steps from the figure. and
let fall
his sword upon the floor. The martial shape again drew the cloak
about
his, features and passed on; but reaching the threshold, with his
back towards the spectators, he was seen to stamp his foot and
shake his
clinched
hands in the air. It was afterwards affirmed that Sir William Howe
had
repeated that selfsame gesture of rage and sorrow, when, for the
last time,
and as the last royal governor, he passed through the portal of the
Province House.
</p><p>``Hark!&mdash;the procession moves,'' said Miss Joliffe.
</p><p>The music was dying away along the street, and its dismal
strains were
mingled with the knell of midnight from the steeple of the Old
South, and
   <pb n="961"/>
with the roar of artillery, which announced that the beleaguering
army of
Washington had intrenched itself upon a nearer height than before.
As
the deep boom of the cannon smote upon his ear, Colonel Joliffe
raised
himself to the full height of his aged form, and smiled sternly on
the
British General.
</p><p>``Would your Excellency inquire further into the mystery of
the pageant?'' said he.
</p><p>``Take care of your gray head!'' cried Sir William Howe,
fiercely,
though with a quivering lip. ``It has stood too long on a traitor's
shoulders!''
</p><p>``You must make haste to chop it off, then,'' calmly replied
the Colonel;
``for a few hours longer, and not all the power of Sir William
Howe, nor
of his master, shall cause one of these gray hairs to fall. The
empire of
Britain in this ancient province is at its last gasp
to-night;&mdash;almost while
I speak it is a dead corpse;&mdash;and methinks the shadows of the old
governors are fit mourners at its funeral!''
</p><p>With these words Colonel Joliffe threw on his cloak, and
drawing his
granddaughter's arm within his own, retired from the last festival
that a
British ruler ever held in the old province of Massachusetts Bay.
It was
supposed that the Colonel and the young lady possessed some secret
intelligence in regard to the mysterious pageant of that night.
However this
might be, such knowledge has never become general. The actors in
the
scene have vanished into deeper obscurity than even that wild
Indian
band who scattered the cargoes of the tea ships on the waves, and
gained
a place in history, yet left no names. But superstition, among
other legends of this mansion, repeats the wondrous tale, that on
the
anniversary
night of Britain's discomfiture the ghosts of the ancient governors
of
Massachusetts still glide through the portal of the Province House.
And,
last of all, comes a figure shrouded in a military cloak, tossing
his clinched
hands into the air, and stamping his iron-shod boots upon the broad
freestone steps, with a semblance of feverish despair, but without
the
sound
of a foot-tramp.

</p><p>&mdash;
</p><p>When the truth-telling accents of the elderly gentleman were
hushed, I
drew a long breath and looked round the room, striving, with the
best
energy of my imagination, to throw a tinge of romance and historic
grandeur over the realities of the scene. But my nostrils snuffed
up a
scent of
cigar smoke, clouds of which the narrator had emitted by way of
visible
emblem, I suppose, of the nebulous obscurity of his tale. Moreover,
my
gorgeous fantasies were wofully disturbed by the rattling of the
spoon in a
tumbler of whiskey punch, which Mr. Thomas Waite was mingling for
a
customer. Nor did it add to the picturesque appearance of the
panelled
walls that the slate of the Brookline stage was suspended against
them,
instead of the armorial escutcheon of some far-descended governor.
A
stage-driver sat at one of the windows, reading a penny paper of
the day
   <pb n="962"/>
&mdash;the Boston Times&mdash;and presenting a figure which could nowise be
brought into any picture of ``Times in Boston'' seventy or a
hundred
years ago. On the window seat lay a bundle, neatly done up in brown
paper, the direction of which I had the idle curiosity to read.
``MISS
SUSAN HUGGINS, at the PROVINCE HOUSE.'' A pretty chambermaid, no
doubt. In truth, it is desperately hard work, when we attempt to
throw
the spell of hoar antiquity over localities with which the living
world, and
the day that is passing over us, have aught to do. Yet, as I
glanced at the
stately staircase down which the procession of the old governors
had descended, and as I emerged through the venerable portal whence
their
figures had preceded me, it gladdened me to be conscious of a
thrill
of awe.
Then, diving through the narrow archway, a few strides transported
me
into the densest throng of Washington Street.</p>


</div2>
<div2 type="story" id="d5">
<head>II<lb/>
EDWARD RANDOLPH'S PORTRAIT</head>

<p>THE old legendary guest of the Province House abode in my
remembrance from midsummer till January. One idle evening last
winter,
confident that he would be found in the snuggest corner of the
bar-room, I resolved to pay him another visit, hoping to deserve
well of my
country by
snatching from oblivion some else unheard-of fact of history. The
night
was chill and raw, and rendered boisterous by almost a gale of
wind,
which whistled along Washington Street, causing the gas-lights to
flare
and flicker within the lamps. As I hurried onward, my fancy was
busy
with a comparison between the present aspect of the street and that
which
it probably wore when the British governors inhabited the mansion
whither I was now going. Brick edifices in those times were few,
till a
succession of destructive fires had swept, and swept again, the
wooden
dwellings
and warehouses from the most populous quarters of the town. The
buildings stood insulated and independent, not, as now, merging
their
separate
existences into connected ranges, with a front of tiresome
identity,&mdash;but
each possessing features of its own, as if the owner's individual
taste had
shaped it,&mdash;and the whole presenting a picturesque irregularity,
the absence of which is hardly compensated by any beauties of our
modern
architecture. Such a scene, dimly vanishing from the eye by the ray
of
here and there a tallow candle, glimmering through the small panes
of
scattered windows, would form a sombre contrast to the street as I
beheld
it, with the gas-lights blazing from corner to corner, flaming
within the
   <pb n="963"/>
shops, and throwing a noonday brightness through the huge plates of
glass.
</p><p>But the black, lowering sky, as I turned my eyes upward,
wore, doubtless, the same visage as when it frowned upon the
ante-revolutionary New
Englanders. The wintry blast had the same shriek that was familiar
to
their ears. The Old South Church, too, still pointed its antique
spire into
the darkness, and was lost between earth and heaven; and as I
passed, its
clock, which had warned so many generations how transitory was
their
lifetime, spoke heavily and slow the same unregarded moral to
myself.
``Only seven o'clock,'' thought I. ``My old friend's legends will
scarcely
kill the hours 'twixt this and bedtime.''
</p><p>Passing through the narrow arch, I crossed the court-yard,
the confined
precincts of which were made visible by a lantern over the portal
of the
Province House. On entering the bar-room, I found, as I expected,
the old
tradition monger seated by a special good fire of anthracite,
compelling
clouds of smoke from a corpulent cigar. He recognized me with
evident
pleasure; for my rare properties as a patient listener invariably
make me
a favorite with elderly gentlemen and ladies of narrative
propensities.
Drawing a chair to the fire, I desired mine host to favor us with
a glass
apiece of whiskey punch, which was speedily prepared, steaming hot,
with a slice of lemon at the bottom, a dark-red stratum of port
wine upon
the surface, and a sprinkling of nutmeg strewn over all. As we
touched
our glasses together, my legendary friend made himself known to me
as
Mr. Bela Tiffany; and I rejoiced at the oddity of the name, because
it
gave his image and character a sort of individuality in my
conception.
The old gentleman's draught acted as a solvent upon his memory, so
that
it overflowed with tales, traditions, anecdotes of famous dead
people, and
traits of ancient manners, some of which were childish as a nurse's
lullaby, while others might have been worth the notice of the grave
historian. Nothing impressed me more than a story of a black
mysterious
picture, which used to hang in one of the chambers of the Province
House,
directly above the room where we were now sitting. The following is
as
correct a version of the fact as the reader would be likely to
obtain from
any other source, although, assuredly, it has a tinge of romance
approaching to the marvellous.

</p><p>&mdash;
</p><p>In one of the apartments of the Province House there was
long preserved an ancient picture, the frame of which was as black
as
ebony, and
the canvas itself so dark with age, damp, and smoke, that not a
touch of
the painter's art could be discerned. Time had thrown an
impenetrable
veil over it, and left to tradition and fable and conjecture to say
what had
once been there portrayed. During the rule of many successive
governors,
it had hung, by prescriptive and undisputed right, over the
mantel-piece
of the same chamber; and it still kept its place when
Lieutenant-Governor
Hutchinson assumed the administration of the province, on the
departure
of Sir Francis Bernard.
   <pb n="964"/>
</p><p>The Lieutenant-Governor sat, one afternoon, resting his head
against
the carved back of his stately armchair, and gazing up thoughtfully
at the
void blackness of the picture. It was scarcely a time for such
inactive musing, when affairs of the deepest moment required the
ruler's
decision, for
within that very hour Hutchinson had received intelligence of the
arrival
of a British fleet, bringing three regiments from Halifax to
overawe the
insubordination of the people. These troops awaited his permission
to occupy the fortress of Castle William, and the town itself. Yet,
instead of
affixing his signature to an official order, there sat the
Lieutenant-Governor, so carefully scrutinizing the black waste of
canvas that his
demeanor
attracted the notice of two young persons who attended him. One,
wearing a military dress of buff, was his kinsman, Francis Lincoln,
the
Provincial Captain of Castle William; the other, who sat on a low
stool
beside
his chair, was Alice Vane, his favorite niece.
</p><p>She was clad entirely in white, a pale, ethereal creature,
who, though a
native of New England, had been educated abroad, and seemed not
merely a stranger from another clime, but almost a being from
another
world.
For several years, until left an orphan, she had dwelt with her
father in
sunny Italy, and there had acquired a taste and enthusiasm for
sculpture
and painting which she found few opportunities of gratifying in the
undecorated dwellings of the colonial gentry. It was said that the
early productions of her own pencil exhibited no inferior genius,
though,
perhaps,
the rude atmosphere of New England had cramped her hand, and dimmed
the glowing colors of her fancy. But observing her uncle's
steadfast gaze,
which appeared to search through the mist of years to discover the
subject of the picture, her curiosity was excited.
</p><p>``Is it known, my dear uncle,'' inquired she, ``what this
old picture once
represented? Possibly, could it be made visible, it might prove a
masterpiece of some great artist&mdash;else, why has it so long held
such a
conspicuous place?''
</p><p>As her uncle, contrary to his usual custom (for he was as
attentive to
all the humors and caprices of Alice as if she had been his own
best-beloved child), did not immediately reply, the young Captain
of
Castle William took that office upon himself.
</p><p>``This dark old square of canvas, my fair cousin,'' said he,
``has been an
heirloom in the Province House from time immemorial. As to the
painter,
I can tell you nothing; but, if half the stories told of it be
true, not one of
the great Italian masters has ever produced so marvellous a piece
of work
as that before you.''
</p><p>Captain Lincoln proceeded to relate some of the strange
fables and
fantasies which, as it was impossible to refute them by ocular
demonstration, had grown to be articles of popular belief, in
reference to
this old
picture. One of the wildest, and at the same time the best
accredited, accounts, stated it to be an original and authentic
portrait of the
Evil One,
taken at a witch meeting near Salem; and that its strong and
terrible resemblance had been confirmed by several of the
confessing wizards
and
witches, at their trial, in open court. It was likewise affirmed
that a famaliar
   <pb n="965"/>
spirit or demon abode behind the blackness of the picture,
and had
shown himself, at seasons of public calamity, to more than one of
the
royal governors. Shirley, for instance, had beheld this ominous
apparition, on the eve of General Abercrombie's shameful and bloody
defeat
under the walls of Ticonderoga. Many of the servants of the
Province
House had caught glimpses of a visage frowning down upon them, at
morning or evening twilight,&mdash;or in the depths of night, while
raking up
the fire that glimmered on the hearth beneath; although, if any
were bold
enough to hold a torch before the picture, it would appear as black
and
undistinguishable as ever. The oldest inhabitant of Boston
recollected
that his father, in whose days the portrait had not wholly faded
out of
sight, had once looked upon it, but would never suffer himself to
be questioned as to the face which was there represented. In
connection
with such
stories, it was remarkable that over the top of the frame there
were some
ragged remnants of black silk, indicating that a veil had formerly
hung
down before the picture, until the duskiness of time had so
effectually
concealed it. But, after all, it was the most singular part of the
affair that
so many of the pompous governors of Massachusetts had allowed the
obliterated picture to remain in the state chamber of the Province
House.
</p><p>``Some of these fables are really awful,'' observed Alice
Vane, who had
occasionally shuddered, as well as smiled, while her cousin spoke.
``It
would be almost worth while to wipe away the black surface of the
canvas, since the original picture can hardly be so formidable as
those which
fancy paints instead of it.''
</p><p>``But would it be possible,'' inquired her cousin, ``to
restore this dark
picture to its pristine hues?''
</p><p>``Such arts are known in Italy,'' said Alice.
</p><p>The Lieutenant-Governor had roused himself from his
abstracted
mood, and listened with a smile to the conversation of his young
relatives.
Yet his voice had something peculiar in its tones when he undertook
the
explanation of the mystery.
</p><p>``I am sorry, Alice, to destroy your faith in the legends of
which you
are so fond,'' remarked he; ``but my antiquarian researches have
long
since made me acquainted with the subject of this picture&mdash;if
picture it
can be called&mdash;which is no more visible, nor ever will be, than the
face of
the long buried man whom it once represented. It was the portrait
of Edward Randolph, the founder of this house, a person famous in
the
history
of New England.''
</p><p>``Of that Edward Randolph,'' exclaimed Captain Lincoln,
``who obtained the repeal of the first provincial charter, under
which our
forefathers had enjoyed almost democratic privileges! He that was
styled the
arch-enemy of New England, and whose memory is still held in
detestation as the destroyer of our liberties!''
</p><p>``It was the same Randolph,'' answered Hutchinson, moving
uneasily
in his chair. ``It was his lot to taste the bitterness of popular
odium.''
</p><p>``Our annals tell us,'' continued the Captain of Castle
William, ``that
the curse of the people followed this Randolph where he went, and
   <pb n="966"/>
wrought evil in all the subsequent events of his life, and that its
effect was
seen likewise in the manner of his death. They say, too, that the
inward
misery of that curse worked itself outward, and was visible on the
wretched man's countenance, making it too horrible to be looked
upon.
If so, and if this picture truly represented his aspect, it was in
mercy that
the cloud of blackness has gathered over it.''
</p><p>``These traditions are folly to one who has proved, as I
have, how little
of historic truth lies at the bottom,'' said the
Lieutenant-Governor. ``As
regards the life and character of Edward Randolph, too implicit
credence
has been given to Dr. Cotton Mather, who&mdash;I must say it, though
some
of his blood runs in my veins&mdash;has filled our early history with
old women's tales, as fanciful and extravagant as those of Greece
or
Rome.''
</p><p>``And yet,'' whispered Alice Vane, ``may not such fables
have a moral?
And, methinks, if the visage of this portrait be so dreadful, it is
not without a cause that it has hung so long in a chamber of the
Province
House.
When the rulers feel themselves irresponsible, it were well that
they
should be reminded of the awful weight of a people's curse.''
</p><p>The Lieutenant-Governor started, and gazed for a moment at
his niece,
as if her girlish fantasies had struck upon some feeling in his own
breast,
which all his policy or principles could not entirely subdue. He
knew, indeed, that Alice, in spite of her foreign education,
retained the
native
sympathies of a New England girl.
</p><p>``Peace, silly child,'' cried he, at last, more harshly than
he had ever
before addressed the gentle Alice. ``The rebuke of a king is more
to be
dreaded than the clamor of a wild, misguided multitude. Captain
Lincoln,
it is decided. The fortress of Castle William must be occupied by
the
royal troops. The two remaining regiments shall be billeted in the
town,
or encamped upon the Common. It is time, after years of tumult, and
almost rebellion, that his majesty's government should have a wall
of
strength about it.''
</p><p>``Trust, sir&mdash;trust yet awhile to the loyalty of the
people,'' said Captain Lincoln; ``nor teach them that they can ever
be on other terms
with
British soldiers than those of brotherhood, as when they fought
side by
side through the French War. Do not convert the streets of your
native
town into a camp. Think twice before you give up old Castle
William, the
key of the province, into other keeping than that of true-born New
Englanders.''
</p><p>``Young man, it is decided,'' repeated Hutchinson, rising
from his chair.
``A British officer will be in attendance this evening, to receive
the necessary instructions for the disposal of the troops. Your
presence
also will be
required. Till then, farewell.''
</p><p>With these words the Lieutenant-Governor hastily left the
room, while
Alice and her cousin more slowly followed, whispering together, and
once
pausing to glance back at the mysterious picture. The Captain of
Castle
William fancied that the girl's air and mien were such as might
have belonged to one of those spirits of fable-fairies, or
creatures of a
more antique mythology&mdash;who sometimes mingled their agency with
mortal affairs,
   <pb n="967"/>
half in caprice, yet with a sensibility to human weal or
woe. As he
held the door for her to pass, Alice beckoned to the picture and
smiled.
</p><p>``Come forth, dark and evil Shape!'' cried she. ``It is
thine hour!''
</p><p>In the evening, Lieutenant-Governor Hutchinson sat in the
same chamber where the foregoing scene had occurred, surrounded by
several
persons whose various interests had summoned them together. There
were
the Selectmen of Boston, plain, patriarchal fathers of the people,
excellent representatives of the old puritanical founders, whose
sombre
strength had stamped so deep an impress upon the New England
character. Contrasting with these were one or two members of
Council,
richly
dressed in the white wigs, the embroidered waistcoats and other
magnificence of the time, and making a somewhat ostentatious
display of
courtier-like ceremonial. In attendance, likewise, was a major of
the
British
army, awaiting the Lieutenant-Governor's orders for the landing of
the
troops, which still remained on board the transports. The Captain
of
Castle William stood beside Hutchinson's chair with folded arms,
glancing rather haughtily at the British officer, by whom he was
soon to
be
superseded in his command. On a table, in the centre of the
chamber,
stood a branched silver candlestick, throwing down the glow of half
a
dozen wax-lights upon a paper apparently ready for the
Lieutenant-Governor's signature.
</p><p>Partly shrouded in the voluminous folds of one of the window
curtains,
which fell from the ceiling to the floor, was seen the white
drapery of a
lady's robe. It may appear strange that Alice Vane should have been
there at such a time; but there was something so childlike, so
wayward, in
her singular character, so apart from ordinary rules, that her
presence did
not surprise the few who noticed it. Meantime, the chairman of the
Selectmen was addressing to the Lieutenant-Governor a long and
solemn
protest against the reception of the British troops into the town.
</p><p>``And if your Honor,'' concluded this excellent but somewhat
prosy old
gentleman, ``shall see fit to persist in bringing these mercenary
sworders
and musketeers into our quiet streets, not on our heads be the
responsibility. Think, sir, while there is yet time, that if one
drop of blood
be shed,
that blood shall be an eternal stain upon your Honor's memory. You,
sir,
have written with an able pen the deeds of our forefathers. The
more to
be desired is it, therefore, that yourself should deserve honorable
mention,
as a true patriot and upright ruler, when your own doings shall be
written
down in history.''
</p><p>``I am not insensible, my good sir, to the natural desire to
stand well in
the annals of my country,'' replied Hutchinson, controlling his
impatience
into courtesy, ``nor know I any better method of attaining that end
than
by withstanding the merely temporary spirit of mischief, which,
with
your pardon, seems to have infected elder men than myself. Would
you
have me wait till the mob shall sack the Province House, as they
did my
private mansion? Trust me, sir, the time may come when you will be
glad
to flee for protection to the king's banner, the raising of which
is now so
distasteful to you.''
   <pb n="968"/>
</p><p>``Yes,'' said the British major, who was impatiently
expecting the Lieutenant-Governor's orders. ``The demagogues of
this Province have
raised
the devil and cannot lay him again. We will exorcise him, in God's
name
and the king's.''
</p><p>``If you meddle with the devil, take care of his claws!''
answered the
Captain of Castle William, stirred by the taunt against his
countrymen.
</p><p>Craving your pardon, young sir,'' said the venerable
Selectman, ``let
not an evil spirit enter into your words. We will strive against
the oppressor with prayer and fasting, as our forefathers would
have done.
Like
them, moreover, we will submit to whatever lot a wise Providence
may
send us,&mdash;always, after our own best exertions to amend it.''
</p><p>And there peep forth the devil's claws!'' muttered
Hutchinson, who
well understood the nature of Puritan submission. ``This matter
shall be
expedited forthwith. When there shall be a sentinel at every
corner, and a
court of guard before the town house, a loyal gentleman may venture
to
walk abroad. What to me is the outcry of a mob, in this remote
province
of the realm? The king is my master, and England is my country!
Upheld
by their armed strength, I set my foot upon the rabble, and defy
them!''
</p><p>He snatched a pen, and was about to affix his signature to
the paper
that lay on the table, when the Captain of Castle William placed
his hand
upon his shoulder. The freedom of the action, so contrary to the
ceremonious respect which was then considered due to rank and
dignity,
awakened general surprise, and in none more than in the
Lieutenant-Governor himself. Looking angrily up, he perceived that
his young
relative
was pointing his finger to the opposite wall. Hutchinson's eye
followed the
signal; and he saw, what had hitherto been unobserved, that a black
silk
curtain was suspended before the mysterious picture, so as
completely to
conceal it. His thoughts immediately recurred to the scene of the
preceding afternoon; and, in his surprise, confused by indistinct
emotions, yet
sensible that his niece must have had an agency in this phenomenon,
he
called loudly upon her.
</p><p>``Alice!&mdash;come hither, Alice!''
</p><p>No sooner had he spoken than Alice Vane glided from her
station, and
pressing one hand across her eyes, with the other snatched away the
sable
curtain that concealed the portrait. An exclamation of surprise
burst
from every beholder; but the Lieutenant-Governor's voice had a tone
of
horror.
</p><p>``By Heaven!'' said he, in a low, inward murmur, speaking
rather to
himself than to those around him, ``if the spirit of Edward
Randolph were
to appear among us from the place of torment, he could not wear
more of
the terrors of hell upon his face!''
</p><p>``For some wise end,'' said the aged Selectman, solemnly,
``hath Providence scattered away the mist of years that had so long
hid this
dreadful
effigy. Until this hour no living man hath seen what we behold!''
</p><p>Within the antique frame, which so recently had inclosed a
sable waste
of canvas, now appeared a visible picture, still dark, indeed, in
its hues
and shadings, but thrown forward in strong relief. It was a
half-length
   <pb n="969"/>
figure of a gentleman in a rich but very old-fashioned dress of
embroidered velvet, with a broad ruff and a beard, and wearing a
hat, the
brim of
which overshadowed his forehead. Beneath this cloud the eyes had a
peculiar glare, which was almost lifelike. The whole portrait
started
so distinctly out of the background, that it had the effect of a
person
looking
down from the wall at the astonished and awe-stricken spectators.
The
expression of the face, if any words can convey an idea of it, was
that of a
wretch detected in some hideous guilt, and exposed to the bitter
hatred
and laughter and withering scorn of a vast surrounding multitude.
There
was the struggle of defiance, beaten down and overwhelmed by the
crushing weight of ignominy. The torture of the soul had come forth
upon
the
countenance. It seemed as if the picture, while hidden behind the
cloud of
immemorial years, had been all the time acquiring an intenser depth
and
darkness of expression, till now it gloomed forth again, and threw
its evil
omen over the present hour. Such, if the wild legend may be
credited, was
the portrait of Edward Randolph, as he appeared when a people's
curse
had wrought its influence upon his nature.
</p><p>`` 'T would drive me mad&mdash;that awful face!'' said
Hutchinson, who
seemed fascinated by the contemplation of it.
</p><p>``Be warned, then!'' whispered Alice. ``He trampled on a
people's
rights. Behold his punishment&mdash;and avoid a crime like his!''
</p><p>The Lieutenant-Governor actually trembled for an instant;
but, exerting his energy&mdash;which was not, however, his most
characteristic
feature
&mdash;he strove to shake off the spell of Randolph's countenance.
</p><p>``Girl!'' cried he, laughing bitterly as he turned to Alice,
``have you
brought hither your painter's art&mdash;your Italian spirit of
intrigue&mdash;your
tricks of stage effect&mdash;and think to influence the councils of
rulers and
the affairs of nations by such shallow contrivances? See here!''
</p><p>``Stay yet a while,'' said the Selectman, as Hutchinson
again snatched
the pen; ``for if ever mortal man received a warning from a
tormented
soul, your Honor is that man!''
</p><p>``Away!'' answered Hutchinson fiercely. ``Though yonder
senseless picture cried `Forbear!'&mdash;it should not move me!''
</p><p>Casting a scowl of defiance at the pictured face (which
seemed at that
moment to intensify the horror of its miserable and wicked look),
he
scrawled on the paper, in characters that betokened it a deed of
desperation, the name of Thomas Hutchinson. Then, it is said, he
shuddered, as
if that signature had granted away his salvation.
</p><p>``It is done,'' said he; and placed his hand upon his brow.
</p><p>``May Heaven forgive the deed,'' said the soft, sad accents
of Alice
Vane, like the voice of a good spirit flitting away.
</p><p>When morning came there was a stifled whisper through the
household,
and spreading thence about the town, that the dark, mysterious
picture
had started from the wall, and spoken face to face with
Lieutenant-Governor Hutchinson. If such a miracle had been wrought,
however, no
traces
of it remained behind, for within the antique frame nothing could
be discerned save the impenetrable cloud, which had covered the
canvas
since
   <pb n="970"/>
the memory of man. If the figure had, indeed, stepped forth, it had
fled
back, spirit-like, at the daydawn, and hidden itself behind a
century's obscurity. The truth probably was, that Alice Vane's
secret for
restoring the
hues of the picture had merely effected a temporary renovation. But
those
who, in that brief interval, had beheld the awful visage of Edward
Randolph, desired no second glance, and ever afterwards trembled at
the recollection of the scene, as if an evil spirit had appeared
visibly
among
them. And as for Hutchinson, when, far over the ocean, his dying
hour
drew on, he gasped for breath, and complained that he was choking
with
the blood of the Boston Massacre; and Francis Lincoln, the former
Captain of Castle William, who was standing at his bedside,
perceived
a likeness in his frenzied look to that of Edward Randolph. Did his
broken
spirit feel, at that dread hour, the tremendous burden of a
People's curse?

</p><p>&mdash;
</p><p>At the conclusion of this miraculous legend, I inquired of
mine host
whether the picture still remained in the chamber over our heads;
but Mr.
Tiffany informed me that it had long since been removed, and was
supposed to be hidden in some out-of-the-way corner of the New
England
Museum. Perchance some curious antiquary may light upon it there,
and,
with the assistance of Mr. Howorth, the picture cleaner, may supply
a not
unnecessary proof of the authenticity of the facts here set down.
During
the progress of the story a storm had been gathering abroad, and
raging
and rattling so loudly in the upper regions of the Province House,
that it
seemed as if all the old governors and great men were running riot
above
stairs while Mr. Bela Tiffany babbled of them below. In the course
of generations, when many people have lived and died in an ancient
house,
the
whistling of the wind through its crannies, and the creaking of its
beams
and rafters, become strangely like the tones of the human voice, or
thundering laughter, or heavy footsteps treading the deserted
chambers.
It is
as if the echoes of half a century were revived. Such were the
ghostly
sounds that roared and murmured in our ears when I took leave of
the
circle round the fireside of the Province House, and plunging down
the
door steps, fought my way homeward against a drifting snow-storm.</p>

</div2>
<div2 type="story" id="d6">
<head>III<lb/>
LADY ELEANORE'S MANTLE</head>

<p>MINE excellent friend, the landlord of the Province House, was
pleased,
the other evening, to invite Mr. Tiffany and myself to an oyster
supper.
This slight mark of respect and gratitude, as he handsomely
observed,
   <pb n="971"/>
was far less than the ingenious tale-teller, and I, the humble
note-taker of
his narratives, had fairly earned, by the public notice which our
joint
lucubrations had attracted to his establishment. Many a cigar had
been
smoked within his premises&mdash;many a glass of wine, or more potent
aqua
vit&aelig;, had been quaffed&mdash;many a dinner had been eaten by
curious strangers, who, save for the fortunate conjunction of Mr.
Tiffany and me,
would
never have ventured through that darksome avenue which gives access
to
the historic precincts of the Province House. In short, if any
credit be due
to the courteous assurances of Mr. Thomas Waite, we had brought his
forgotten mansion almost as effectually into public view as if we
had
thrown down the vulgar range of shoe shops and dry goods stores,
which
hides its aristocratic front from Washington Street. It may be
unadvisable, however, to speak too loudly of the increased custom
of the
house,
lest Mr. Waite should find it difficult to renew the lease on so
favorable
terms as heretofore.
</p><p>Being thus welcomed as benefactors, neither Mr. Tiffany nor
myself
felt any scruple in doing full justice to the good things that were
set before us. If the feast were less magnificent than those same
panelled walls
had witnessed in a by-gone century,&mdash;if mine host presided with
somewhat less of state than might have befitted a successor of the
royal Governors,&mdash;if the guests made a less imposing show than the
bewigged
and
powdered and embroidered dignitaries, who erst banqueted at the
gubernatorial table, and now sleep, within their armorial tombs on
Copp's Hill,
or round King's Chapel,&mdash;yet never, I may boldly say, did a more
comfortable little party assemble in the Province House, from Queen
Anne's
days to the Revolution. The occasion was rendered more interesting
by
the presence of a venerable personage, whose own actual
reminiscences
went back to the epoch of Gage and Howe, and even supplied him with
a
doubtful anecdote or two of Hutchinson. He was one of that small,
and
now all but extinguished, class, whose attachment to royalty, and
to the
colonial institutions and customs that were connected with it, had
never
yielded to the democratic heresies of after times. The young queen
of
Britain has not a more loyal subject in her realm&mdash;perhaps not one
who
would kneel before her throne with such reverential love&mdash;as this
old
grandsire, whose head has whitened beneath the mild sway of the
Republic, which still, in his mellower moments, he terms a
usurpation.
Yet prejudices so obstinate have not made him an ungentle or
impracticable
companion. If the truth must be told, the life of the aged loyalist
has been of
such a scrambling and unsettled character,&mdash;he has had so little
choice of
friends and been so often destitute of any,&mdash;that I doubt whether
he
would refuse a cup of kindness with either Oliver Cromwell or John
Hancock,&mdash;to say nothing of any democrat now upon the stage. In
another
paper of this series I may perhaps give the reader a closer glimpse
of his
portrait.
</p><p>Our host, in due season, uncorked a bottle of Madeira, of
such exquisite
perfume and admirable flavor that he surely must have discovered it
in
an ancient bin, down deep beneath the deepest cellar, where some
jolly
   <pb n="972"/>
old butler stored away the Governor's choicest wine, and forgot to
reveal
the secret on his death-bed. Peace to his red-nosed ghost, and a
libation to
his memory! This precious liquor was imbibed by Mr. Tiffany with
peculiar zest; and after sipping the third glass, it was his
pleasure
to give us
one of the oddest legends which he had yet raked from the
storehouse
where he keeps such matters. With some suitable adornments from my
own fancy, it ran pretty much as follows.

</p><p>&mdash;
</p><p>Not long after Colonel Shute had assumed the government of
Massachusetts Bay, now nearly a hundred and twenty years ago, a
young
lady
of rank and fortune arrived from England, to claim his protection
as her
guardian. He was her distant relative, but the nearest who had
survived
the gradual extinction of her family; so that no more eligible
shelter could
be found for the rich and high-born Lady Eleanore Rochcliffe than
within the Province House of a transatlantic colony. The consort of
Governor
Shute, moreover, had been as a mother to her childhood, and was now
anxious to receive her, in the hope that a beautiful young woman
would
be exposed to infinitely less peril from the primitive society of
New England than amid the artifices and corruptions of a court. If
either
the Governor or his lady had especially consulted their own
comfort, they
would
probably have sought to devolve the responsibility on other hands;
since,
with some noble and splendid traits of character, Lady Eleanore was
remarkable for a harsh, unyielding pride, a haughty consciousness
of
her
hereditary and personal advantages, which made her almost incapable
of
control. Judging from many traditionary anecdotes, this peculiar
temper
was hardly less than a monomania; or, if the acts which it inspired
were
those of a sane person, it seemed due from Providence that pride so
sinful
should be followed by as severe a retribution. That tinge of the
marvellous, which is thrown over so many of these half-forgotten
legends,
has
probably imparted an additional wildness to the strange story of
Lady
Eleanore Rochcliffe.
</p><p>The ship in which she came passenger had arrived at Newport,
whence
Lady Eleanore was conveyed to Boston in the Governor's coach,
attended
by a small escort of gentlemen on horseback. The ponderous equipage
with its four black horses, attracted much notice as it rumbled
through
Cornhill, surrounded by the prancing steeds of half a dozen
cavaliers,
with swords dangling to their stirrups and pistols at their
holsters.
Through the large glass windows of the coach, as it rolled along,
the
people could discern the figure of Lady Eleanore, strangely
combining an
almost queenly stateliness with the grace and beauty of a maiden in
her
teens. A singular tale had gone abroad among the ladies of the
province,
that their fair rival was indebted for much of the irresistible
charm of her
appearance to a certain article of dress&mdash;an embroidered
mantle&mdash;which
had been wrought by the most skilful artist in London, and
possessed
even magical properties of adornment. On the present occasion,
however,
   <pb n="973"/>
she owed nothing to the witchery of dress, being clad in a riding
habit of
velvet, which would have appeared stiff and ungraceful on any other
form.
</p><p>The coachman reined in his four black steeds, and the whole
cavalcade
came to a pause in front of the contorted iron balustrade that
fenced the
Province House from the public street. It was an awkward
coincidence
that the bell of the Old South was just then tolling for a funeral;
so that,
instead of a gladsome peal with which it was customary to announce
the
arrival of distinguished strangers, Lady Eleanore Rochcliffe was
ushered
by a doleful clang, as if calamity had come embodied in her
beautiful
person.
</p><p>``A very great disrespect!'' exclaimed Captain Langford, an
English
officer, who had recently brought dispatches to Governor Shute.
``The funeral should have been deferred, lest Lady Eleanore's
spirits be
affected
by such a dismal welcome.''
</p><p>``With your pardon, sir,'' replied Doctor Clarke, a
physician, and a famous champion of the popular party, ``whatever
the heralds may
pretend,
a dead beggar must have precedence of a living queen. King Death
confers high privileges.''
</p><p>These remarks were interchanged while the speakers waited a
passage
through the crowd, which had gathered on each side of the gateway,
leaving an open avenue to the portal of the Province House. A black
slave in
livery now leaped from behind the coach, and threw open the door;
while
at the same moment Governor Shute descended the flight of steps
from
his mansion, to assist Lady Eleanore in alighting. But the
Governor's
stately approach was anticipated in a manner that excited general
astonishment. A pale young man, with his black hair all in
disorder,
rushed
from the throng, and prostrated himself beside the coach, thus
offering his
person as a footstool for Lady Eleanore Rochcliffe to tread upon.
She held
back an instant, yet with an expression as if doubting whether the
young
man were worthy to bear the weight of her footstep, rather than
dissatisfied to receive such awful reverence from a fellow-mortal.
</p><p>``Up, sir,'' said the Governor, sternly, at the same time
lifting his cane
over the intruder. ``What means the Bedlamite by this freak?''
</p><p>``Nay,'' answered Lady Eleanore playfully, but with more
scorn than
pity in her tone, ``your Excellency shall not strike him. When men
seek
only to be trampled upon, it were a pity to deny them a favor so
easily
granted&mdash;and so well deserved!''
</p><p>Then, though as lightly as a sunbeam on a cloud, she placed
her foot
upon the cowering form, and extended her hand to meet that of the
Governor. There was a brief interval, during which Lady Eleanore
retained
this attitude; and never, surely, was there an apter emblem of
aristocracy
and hereditary pride trampling on human sympathies and the kindred
of
nature, than these two figures presented at that moment. Yet the
spectators were so smitten with her beauty, and so essential did
pride
seem to
the existence of such a creature, that they gave a simultaneous
acclamation of applause.
   <pb n="974"/>
</p><p>``Who is this insolent young fellow?'' inquired Captain
Langford, who
still remained beside Doctor Clarke. ``If he be in his senses, his
impertinence demands the bastinado. If mad, Lady Eleanore should be
secured
from further inconvenience, by his confinement.''
</p><p>``His name is Jervase Helwyse,'' answered the Doctor; ``a
youth of no
birth or fortune, or other advantages, save the mind and soul that
nature
gave him; and being secretary to our colonial agent in London, it
was his
misfortune to meet this Lady Eleanore Rochcliffe. He loved her&mdash;and
her
scorn has driven him mad.''
</p><p>``He was mad so to aspire,'' observed the English officer.
</p><p>``It may be so,'' said Doctor Clarke, frowning as he spoke.
``But I tell
you, sir, I could well-nigh doubt the justice of the Heaven above
us if no
signal humiliation overtake this lady, who now treads so haughtily
into
yonder mansion. She seeks to place herself above the sympathies of
our
common nature, which envelops all human souls. See, if that nature
do
not assert its claim over her in some mode that shall bring her
level with
the lowest!''
</p><p>``Never!'' cried Captain Langford indignantly&mdash;``neither in
life, nor
when they lay her with her ancestors.''
</p><p>Not many days afterwards the Governor gave a ball in honor
of Lady
Eleanore Rochcliffe. The principal gentry of the colony received
invitations, which were distributed to their residences, far and
near, by
messengers on horseback, bearing missives sealed with all the
formality of
official dispatches. In obedience to the summons, there was a
general
gathering of rank, wealth, and beauty; and the wide door of the
Province
House had seldom given admittance to more numerous and honorable
guests than on the evening of Lady Eleanore's ball. Without much
extravagance of eulogy, the spectacle might even be termed
splendid;
for,
according to the fashion of the times, the ladies shone in rich
silks and
satins, outspread over wide-projecting hoops; and the gentlemen
glittered
in gold embroidery, laid unsparingly upon the purple, or scarlet,
or sky-blue velvet, which was the material of their coats and
waistcoats.
The latter article of dress was of great importance, since it
enveloped
the wearer's body nearly to the knees, and was perhaps bedizened
with the
amount
of his whole year's income, in golden flowers and foliage. The
altered taste
of the present day&mdash;a taste symbolic of a deep change in the whole
system of society&mdash;would look upon almost any of those gorgeous
figures as
ridiculous; although that evening the guests sought their
reflections in
the pier-glasses, and rejoiced to catch their own glitter amid the
glittering
crowd. What a pity that one of the stately mirrors has not
preserved a
picture of the scene, which, by the very traits that were so
transitory,
might have taught us much that would be worth knowing and
remembering!
</p><p>Would, at least, that either painter or mirror could convey
to us some
faint idea of a garment, already noticed in this legend,&mdash;the Lady
Eleanore's embroidered mantle,&mdash;which the gossips whispered was
invested
with magic properties, so as to lend a new and untried grace to her
figure
   <pb n="975"/>
each time that she put it on! Idle fancy as it is, this mysterious
mantle
has thrown an awe around my image of her, partly from its fabled
virtues,
and partly because it was the handiwork of a dying woman, and,
perchance, owed the fantastic grace of its conception to the
delirium
of approaching death.
</p><p>After the ceremonial greetings had been paid, Lady Eleanore
Rochcliffe stood apart from the mob of guests, insulating herself
within a small
and distinguished circle, to whom she accorded a more cordial favor
than
to the general throng. The waxen torches threw their radiance
vividly
over the scene, bringing out its brilliant points in strong relief;
but she
gazed carelessly, and with now and then an expression of weariness
or
scorn, tempered with such feminine grace that her auditors scarcely
perceived the moral deformity of which it was the utterance. She
beheld the
spectacle not with vulgar ridicule, as disdaining to be pleased
with the
provincial mockery of a court festival, but with the deeper scorn
of one
whose spirit held itself too high to participate in the enjoyment
of other
human souls. Whether or no the recollections of those who saw her
that
evening were influenced by the strange events with which she was
subsequently connected, so it was that her figure ever after
recurred
to them
as marked by something wild and unnatural,&mdash;although, at the time,
the
general whisper was of her exceeding beauty, and of the
indescribable
charm which her mantle threw around her. Some close observers,
indeed,
detected a feverish flush and alternate paleness of countenance,
with corresponding flow and revulsion of spirits, and once or twice
a
painful and
helpless betrayal of lassitude, as if she were on the point of
sinking to the
ground. Then, with a nervous shudder, she seemed to arouse her
energies
and threw some bright and playful yet half-wicked sarcasm into the
conversation. There was so strange a characteristic in her manners
and
sentiments that it astonished every right-minded listener; till
looking
in her
face, a lurking and incomprehensible glance and smile perplexed
them
with doubts both as to her seriousness and sanity. Gradually, Lady
Eleanore Rochcliffe's circle grew smaller, till only four gentlemen
remained
in it. These were Captain Langford, the English officer before
mentioned;
a Virginian planter, who had come to Massachusetts on some
political errand; a young Episcopal clergyman, the grandson of a
British earl;
and,
lastly, the private secretary of Governor Shute, whose
obsequiousness had
won a sort of tolerance from Lady Eleanore.
</p><p>At different periods of the evening the liveried servants of
the Province
House passed among the guests, bearing huge trays of refreshments
and
French and Spanish wines. Lady Eleanore Rochcliffe, who refused to
wet
her beautiful lips even with a bubble of Champagne, had sunk back
into a
large damask chair, apparently overwearied either with the
excitement of
the scene or its tedium, and while, for an instant, she was
unconscious of
voices, laughter and music, a young man stole forward, and knelt
down at
her feet. He bore a salver in his hand, on which was a chased
silver goblet, filled to the brim with wine, which he offered as
reverentially as to a
crowned queen, or rather with the awful devotion of a priest doing
sacrifice
   <pb n="976"/>
to his idol. Conscious that some one touched her robe, Lady
Eleanore
started, and unclosed her eyes upon the pale, wild features and
dishevelled hair of Jervase Helwyse.
</p><p>``Why do you haunt me thus?'' said she, in a languid tone,
but with a
kindlier feeling than she ordinarily permitted herself to express.
``They
tell me that I have done you harm.''
</p><p>``Heaven knows if that be so,'' replied the young man
solemnly. ``But,
Lady Eleanore, in requital of that harm, if such there be, and for
your
own earthly and heavenly welfare, I pray you to take one sip of
this holy
wine, and then to pass the goblet round among the guests. And this
shall
be a symbol that you have not sought to withdraw yourself from the
chain
of human sympathies&mdash;which whoso would shake off must keep company
with fallen angels.''
</p><p>``Where has this mad fellow stolen that sacramental
vessel?'' exclaimed
the Episcopal clergyman.
</p><p>This question drew the notice of the guests to the silver
cup, which was
recognized as appertaining to the communion plate of the Old South
Church; and, for aught that could be known, it was brimming over
with
the consecrated wine.
</p><p>``Perhaps it is poisoned,'' half whispered the Governor's
secretary.
</p><p>``Pour it down the villain's throat!'' cried the Virginian
fiercely.
</p><p>``Turn him out of the house!'' cried Captain Langford,
seizing Jervase
Helwyse so roughly by the shoulder that the sacramental cup was
over-turned, and its contents sprinkled upon Lady Eleanore's
mantle.
``Whether knave, fool, or Bedlamite, it is intolerable that the
fellow
should go
at large.
</p><p>``Pray, gentlemen, do my poor admirer no harm,'' said Lady
Eleanore
with a faint and weary smile. ``Take him out of my sight, if such
be your
pleasure; for I can find in my heart to do nothing but laugh at
him;
whereas, in all decency and conscience, it would become me to weep
for
the mischief I have wrought!''
</p><p>But while the by-standers were attempting to lead away the
unfortunate young man, he broke from them, and with a wild,
impassioned
earnestness, offered a new and equally strange petition to Lady
Eleanore. It
was no other than that she should throw off the mantle, which,
while he
pressed the silver cup of wine upon her, she had drawn more closely
around her form, so as almost to shroud herself within it.
</p><p>``Cast it from you!'' exclaimed Jervase Helwyse, clasping
his hands in
an agony of entreaty. ``It may not yet be too late! Give the
accursed garment to the flames!''
</p><p>But Lady Eleanore, with a laugh of scorn, drew the rich
folds of the
embroidered mantle over her head, in such a fashion as to give a
completely new aspect to her beautiful face, which&mdash;half hidden,
half
revealed&mdash;seemed to belong to some being of mysterious character
and
purposes.
</p><p>``Farewell, Jervase Helwyse!'' said she. ``Keep my image in
your remembrance, as you behold it now.''
   <pb n="977"/>
</p><p>``Alas, lady!'' he replied, in a tone no longer wild, but
sad as a funeral
bell. ``We must meet shortly, when your face may wear another
aspect&mdash;and that shall be the image that must abide within me.''
</p><p>He made no more resistance to the violent efforts of the
gentlemen and
servants, who almost dragged him out of the apartment, and
dismissed
him roughly from the iron gate of the Province House. Captain
Langford,
who had been very active in this affair, was returning to the
presence of
Lady Eleanore Rochcliffe, when he encountered the physician, Doctor
Clarke, with whom he had held some casual talk on the day of her
arrival. The Doctor stood apart, separated from Lady Eleanore by
the
width of the room, but eying her with such keen sagacity that
Captain
Langford involuntarily gave him credit for the discovery of some
deep
secret.
</p><p>``You appear to be smitten, after all, with the charms of
this queenly
maiden,'' said he, hoping thus to draw forth the physician's hidden
knowledge.
</p><p>``God forbid!'' answered Doctor Clarke, with a grave smile;
``and if
you be wise you will put up the same prayer for yourself. Woe to
those
who shall be smitten by this beautiful Lady Eleanore! But yonder
stands
the Governor&mdash;and I have a word or two for his private ear. Good
night!''
</p><p>He accordingly advanced to Governor Shute, and addressed him
in so
low a tone that none of the by-standers could catch a word of what
he
said, although the sudden change of his Excellency's hitherto
cheerful
visage betokened that the communication could be of no agreeable
import. A very few moments afterwards it was announced to the
guests
that
an unforeseen circumstance rendered it necessary to put a premature
close to the festival.
</p><p>The hall at the Province House supplied a topic of
conversation for the
colonial metropolis for some days after its occurrence, and might
still
longer have been the general theme, only that a subject of
all-engrossing
interest thrust it, for a time, from the public recollection. This
was the
appearance of a dreadful epidemic, which, in that age and long
before and
afterwards, was wont to slay its hundreds and thousands on both
sides of
the Atlantic. On the occasion of which we speak, it was
distinguished by a
peculiar virulence, insomuch that it has left its traces&mdash;its
pit-marks, to
use an appropriate figure&mdash;on the history of the country, the
affairs of
which were thrown into confusion by its ravages. At first, unlike
its ordinary course, the disease seemed to confine itself to the
higher
circles of
society, selecting its victims from among the proud, the well-born,
and
the wealthy, entering unabashed into stately chambers, and lying
down
with the slumberers in silken beds. Some of the most distinguished
guests
of the Province House even those whom the haughty Lady Eleanore
Rochcliffe had deemed not unworthy of her favor&mdash;were stricken by
this
fatal scourge. It was noticed, with an ungenerous bitterness of
feeling,
that the four gentlemen&mdash;the Virginian, the British officer, the
young
clergyman, and the Governor's secretary&mdash;who had been her most
devoted attendants on the evening of the ball, were the foremost of
whom
   <pb n="978"/>
the plague stroke fell. But the disease, pursuing its onward
progress, soon
ceased to be exclusively a prerogative of aristocracy. Its red
brand was
no longer conferred like a noble's star, or an order of knighthood.
It
threaded its way through the narrow and crooked streets, and
entered the
low, mean, darksome dwellings, and laid its hand of death upon the
artisans and laboring classes of the town. It compelled rich and
poor to
feel themselves brethren then; and stalking to and fro across the
Three
Hills, with a fierceness which made it almost a new pestilence,
there was
that mighty conqueror&mdash;that scourge and horror of our
forefathers&mdash;the
Small-Pox!
</p><p>We cannot estimate the affright which this plague inspired
of yore, by
contemplating it as the fangless monster of the present day. We
must remember, rather, with what awe we watched the gigantic
footsteps of
the
Asiatic cholera, striding from shore to shore of the Atlantic, and
marching like destiny upon cities far remote which flight had
already
half depopulated. There is no other fear so horrible and
unhumanizing as
that
which makes man dread to breathe heaven's vital air lest it be
poison, or
to grasp the hand of a brother or friend lest the gripe of the
pestilence
should clutch him. Such was the dismay that now followed in the
track of
the disease, or ran before it throughout the town. Graves were
hastily dug,
and the pestilential relics as hastily covered, because the dead
were enemies of the living, and strove to draw them headlong, as it
were,
into their
own dismal pit. The public councils were suspended, as if mortal
wisdom
might relinquish its devices, now that an unearthly usurper had
found his
way into the ruler's mansion. Had an enemy's fleet been hovering on
the
coast, or his armies trampling on our soil, the people would
probably have
committed their defence to that same direful conqueror who had
wrought
their own calamity, and would permit no interference with his sway.
This
conquerer had a symbol of his triumphs. It was a blood-red flag,
that
fluttered in the tainted air, over the door of every dwelling into
which the
Small-Pox had entered.
</p><p>Such a banner was long since waving over the portal of the
Province
House; for thence, as was proved by tracking its footsteps back,
had all
this dreadful mischief issued. It had been traced back to a lady's
luxurious
chamber&mdash;to the proudest of the proud&mdash;to her that was so delicate,
and
hardly owned herself of earthly mould&mdash;to the haughty one, who took
her
stand above human sympathies&mdash;to Lady Eleanore! There remained no
room for doubt that the contagion had lurked in that gorgeous
mantle,
which threw so strange a grace around her at the festival. Its
fantastic
splendor had been conceived in the delirious brain of a woman on
her
death-bed, and was the last toil of her stiffening fingers, which
had interwoven fate and misery with its golden threads. This dark
tale,
whispered
at first, was now bruited far and wide. The people raved against
the Lady
Eleanore, and cried out that her pride and scorn had evoked a
fiend, and
that, between them both, this monstrous evil had been born. At
times,
their rage and despair took the semblance of grinning mirth; and
whenever the red flag of the pestilence was hoisted over another
and
yet another
   <pb n="979"/>
door, they clapped their hands and shouted through the
streets, in
bitter mockery: ``Behold a new triumph for the Lady Eleanore!''
</p><p>One day, in the midst of these dismal times, a wild figure
approached
the portal of the Province House, and folding his arms, stood
contemplating the scarlet banner which a passing breeze shook
fitfully, as if
to fling
abroad the contagion that it typified. At length, climbing one of
the pillars by means of the iron balustrade, he took down the flag
and
entered
the mansion, waving it above his head. At the foot of the staircase
he met
the Governor, booted and spurred, with his cloak drawn around him,
evidently on the point of setting forth upon a journey.
</p><p>``Wretched lunatic, what do you seek here?'' exclaimed
Shute, extending his cane to guard himself from contact. ``There is
nothing here
but
Death. Back&mdash;or you will meet him!''
</p><p>``Death will not touch me, the banner-bearer of the
pestilence!'' cried
Jervase Helwyse, shaking the red flag aloft. ``Death, and the
Pestilence,
who wears the aspect of the Lady Eleanore, will walk through the
streets
to-night, and I must march before them with this banner!''
</p><p>``Why do I waste words on the fellow?'' muttered the
Governor, drawing his cloak across his mouth. ``What matters his
miserable life,
when
none of us are sure of twelve hours' breath? On, fool, to your own
destruction!''
</p><p>He made way for Jervase Helwyse, who immediately ascended
the
staircase, but, on the first landing place, was arrested by the
firm grasp of
a hand upon his shoulder. Looking fiercely up, with a madman's
impulse
to struggle with and rend asunder his opponent, he found himself
powerless beneath a calm, stern eye, which possessed the mysterious
property
of quelling frenzy at its height. The person whom he had now
encountered was the physician, Doctor Clarke, the duties of whose
sad
profession had led him to the Province House, where he was an
infrequent
guest in more prosperous times.
</p><p>``Young man, what is your purpose?'' demanded he.
</p><p>``I seek the Lady Eleanore,'' answered Jervase Helwyse,
submissively.
</p><p>``All have fled from her,'' said the physician. ``Why do you
seek her
now? I tell you, youth, her nurse fell death-stricken on the
threshold of
that fatal chamber. Know ye not, that never came such a curse to
our
shores as this lovely Lady Eleanore?&mdash;that her breath has filled
the air
with poison?&mdash;that she has shaken pestilence and death upon the
land,
from the folds of her accursed mantle?''
</p><p>``Let me look upon her!'' rejoined the mad youth, more
wildly. ``Let me
behold her, in her awful beauty, clad in the regal garments of the
pestilence! She and Death sit on a throne together. Let me kneel
down
before
them!''
</p><p>``Poor youth!'' said Doctor Clarke; and, moved by a deep
sense of human weakness, a smile of caustic humor curled his lip
even then.
``Wilt
thou still worship the destroyer and surround her image with
fantasies
the more magnificent, the more evil she has wrought? Thus man doth
ever to his tyrants. Approach, then! Madness, as I have noted, has
that
   <pb n="980"/>
good efficacy, that it will guard you from contagion&mdash;and perchance
its
own cure may be found in yonder chamber.''
</p><p>Ascending another flight of stairs, he threw open a door and
signed to
Jervase Helwyse that he should enter. The poor lunatic, it seems
probable, had cherished a delusion that his haughty mistress sat in
state, unharmed herself by the pestilential influence, which, as by
enchantment,
she scattered round about her. He dreamed, no doubt, that her
beauty was
not dimmed, but brightened into superhuman splendor. With such
anticipations, he stole reverentially to the door at which the
physician
stood,
but paused upon the threshold, gazing fearfully into the gloom of
the
darkened chamber.
</p><p>``Where is the Lady Eleanore?'' whispered he.
</p><p>``Call her,'' replied the physician.
</p><p>``Lady Eleanore!&mdash;Princess!&mdash;Queen of Death!'' cried Jervase
Helwyse, advancing three steps into the chamber. ``She is not here!
There
on yonder table, I behold the sparkle of a diamond which once she
wore
upon her bosom. There''&mdash;and he shuddered&mdash;``there hangs her
mantle,
on which a dead woman embroidered a spell of dreadful potency. But
where is the Lady Eleanore?''
</p><p>Something stirred within the silken curtains of a canopied
bed; and a
low moan was uttered, which, listening intently, Jervase Helwyse
began
to distinguish as a woman's voice, complaining dolefully of thirst.
He
fancied, even, that he recognized its tones.
</p><p>``My throat!&mdash;my throat is scorched,'' murmured the voice.
``A drop
of water!''
</p><p>``What thing art thou?'' said the brain-stricken youth,
drawing near
the bed and tearing asunder its curtains. ``Whose voice hast thou
stolen
for thy murmurs and miserable petitions, as if Lady Eleanore could
be
conscious of mortal infirmity? Fie! Heap of diseased mortality, why
lurkest thou in my lady's chamber?''
</p><p>``O Jervase Helwyse,'' said the voice&mdash;and as it spoke the
figure contorted itself, struggling to hide its blasted
face&mdash;``look not now
on the
woman you once loved! The curse of Heaven hath stricken me, because
I would not call man my brother, nor woman sister. I wrapped myself
in
PRIDE as in a MANTLE, and scorned the sympathies of nature; and
therefore has nature made this wretched body the medium of a
dreadful
sympathy. You are avenged&mdash;they are all avenged&mdash;Nature is
avenged&mdash;for
I am Eleanore Rochcliffe!''
</p><p>The malice of his mental disease, the bitterness lurking at
the bottom
of his heart, mad as he was, for a blighted and ruined life, and
love that
had been paid with cruel scorn, awoke within the breast of Jervase
Helwyse. He shook his finger at the wretched girl, and the chamber
echoed,
the curtains of the bed were shaken, with his outburst of insane
merriment.
</p><p>``Another triumph for the Lady Eleanore!'' he cried. ``All
have been
her victims! Who so worthy to be the final victim as herself?''
</p><p>Impelled by some new fantasy of his crazed intellect, he
snatched the
   <pb n="981"/>
fatal mantle and rushed from the chamber and the house. That night
a
procession passed, by torchlight, through the streets, bearing in
the midst
the figure of a woman, enveloped with a richly embroidered mantle;
while
in advance stalked Jervase Helwyse, waving the red flag of the
pestilence.
Arriving opposite the Province House, the mob burned the effigy,
and a
strong wind came and swept away the ashes. It was said that, from
that
very hour, the pestilence abated, as if its sway had some
mysterious connection, from the first plague stroke to the last,
with Lady
Eleanore's
Mantle. A remarkable uncertainty broods over that unhappy lady's
fate.
There is a belief, however, that in a certain chamber of this
mansion a female form may sometimes be duskily discerned, shrinking
into the
dark.
est corner and muffling her face within an embroidered mantle.
Supposing the legend true, can this be other than the once proud
Lady
Eleanore?

</p><p>&mdash;
</p><p>Mine host and the old loyalist and I bestowed no little
warmth of applause upon this narrative, in which we had all been
deeply
interested;
for the reader can scarcely conceive how unspeakably the effect of
such
a tale is heightened when, as in the present case, we may repose
perfect
confidence in the veracity of him who tells it. For my own part,
knowing
how scrupulous is Mr. Tiffany to settle the foundation of his
facts, I
could not have believed him one whit the more faithfully had he
professed
himself an eye-witness of the doings and sufferings of poor Lady
Eleanore.
Some sceptics, it is true, might demand documentary evidence, or
even
require him to produce the embroidered mantle, forgetting
that&mdash;Heaven
be praised&mdash;it was consumed to ashes. But now the old loyalist,
whose
blood was warmed by the good cheer, began to talk, in his turn,
about the
traditions of the Province House, and hinted that he, if it were
agreeable,
might add a few reminiscences to our legendary stock. Mr. Tiffany,
having no cause to dread a rival, immediately besought him to favor
us
with a
specimen; my own entreaties, of course, were urged to the same
effect;
and our venerable guest, well pleased to find willing auditors,
awaited
only the return of Mr. Thomas Waite, who had been summoned forth to
provide accommodations for several new arrivals. Perchance the
public&mdash;but be this as its own caprice and ours shall settle the
matter&mdash;may read
the result in another Tale of the Province House.</p>

   <pb n="982"/>

</div2>
<div2 type="story" id="d7">
<head>IV<lb/>
OLD ESTHER DUDLEY</head>

<p>OUR host having resumed the chair, he, as well as Mr. Tiffany and
myself;
expressed much eagerness to be made acquainted with the story to
which
the loyalist had alluded. That venerable man first of all saw fit
to moisten
his throat with another glass of wine, and then, turning his face
towards
our coal fire, looked steadfastly for a few moments into the depths
of its
cheerful glow. Finally, he poured forth a great fluency of speech.
The
generous liquid that he had imbibed, while it warmed his
age-chilled
blood, likewise took off the chill from his heart and mind, and
gave him
an energy to think and feel, which we could hardly have expected to
find
beneath the snows of fourscore winters. His feelings, indeed,
appeared to
me more excitable than those of a younger man; or at least, the
same degree of feeling manifested itself by more visible effects
than if
his judgment and will had possessed the potency of meridian life.
At the
pathetic
passages of his narrative he readily melted into tears. When a
breath of
indignation swept across his spirit the blood flushed his withered
visage
even to the roots of his white hair; and he shook his clinched fist
at the
trio of peaceful auditors, seeming to fancy enemies in those who
felt
very kindly towards the desolate old soul. But ever and anon,
sometimes
in the midst of his most earnest talk, this ancient person's
intellect would
wander vaguely, losing its hold of the matter in hand, and groping
for it
amid misty shadows. Then would he cackle forth a feeble laugh, and
express a doubt whether his wits&mdash;for by that phrase it pleased our
ancient
friend to signify his mental powers&mdash;were not getting a little the
worse
for wear.
</p><p>Under these disadvantages, the old loyalist's story required
more revision to render it fit for the public eye than those of the
series
which have
preceded it; nor should it be concealed that the sentiment and tone
of the
affair may have undergone some slight, or perchance more than
slight,
metamorphosis, in its transmission to the reader through the medium
of
a thorough-going democrat. The tale itself is a mere sketch, with
no involution of plot, nor any great interest of events, yet
possessing,
if I have
rehearsed it aright, that pensive influence over the mind which the
shadow
of the old Province House flings upon the loiterer in its
court-yard.

</p><p>&mdash;
</p><p>The hour had come&mdash;the hour of defeat and humiliation&mdash;when
Sir
William Howe was to pass over the threshold of the Province House,
and
   <pb n="983"/>
embark, with no such triumphal ceremonies as he once promised
himself,
on board the British fleet. He bade his servants and military
attendants
go before him, and lingered a moment in the loneliness of the
mansion, to
quell the fierce emotions that struggled in his bosom as with a
death throb.
Preferable, then, would he have deemed his fate, had a warrior's
death
left him a claim to the narrow territory of a grave within the soil
which
the King had given him to defend. With an ominous perception that,
as
his departing footsteps echoed adown the staircase, the sway of
Britain
was passing forever from New England, he smote his clinched hand on
his brow, and cursed the destiny that had flung the shame of a
dismembered empire upon him.
</p><p>``Would to God,'' cried he, hardly repressing his tears of
rage, ``that the
rebels were even now at the doorstep! A blood-stain upon the floor
should
then bear testimony that the last British ruler was faithful to his
trust.''
</p><p>The tremulous voice of a woman replied to his exclamation.
</p><p>``Heaven's cause and the King's are one,'' it said. ``Go
forth, Sir William Howe, and trust in Heaven to bring back a Royal
Governor in
triumph.''
</p><p>Subduing, at once, the passion to which he had yielded only
in the
faith that it was unwitnessed, Sir William Howe became conscious
that
an aged woman, leaning on a gold-headed staff, was standing betwixt
him
and the door. It was old Esther Dudley, who had dwelt almost
immemorial years in this mansion, until her presence seemed as
inseparable from
it as the recollections of its history. She was the daughter of an
ancient
and once eminent family, which had fallen into poverty and decay,
and
left its last descendant no resource save the bounty of the King,
nor any
shelter except within the walls of the Province House. An office in
the
household, with merely nominal duties, had been assigned to her as
a pre-text for the payment of a small pension, the greater part of
which
she expended in adorning herself with an antique magnificence of
attire.
The
claims of Esther Dudley's gentle blood were acknowledged by all the
successive Governors; and they treated her with the punctilious
courtesy
which it was her foible to demand, not always with success, from a
neglectful world. The only actual share which she assumed in the
business
of the mansion was to glide through its passages and public
chambers,
late at night, to see that the servants had dropped no fire from
their
flaring torches, nor left embers crackling and blazing on the
hearths.
Perhaps it was this invariable custom of walking her rounds in the
hush
of midnight that caused the superstition of the times to invest the
old
woman with attributes of awe and mystery; fabling that she had
entered the portal of the Province House, none knew whence, in the
train of
the first Royal Governor, and that it was her fate to dwell there
till the
last should have departed. But Sir William Howe, if he ever heard
this
legend, had forgotten it.
</p><p>``Mistress Dudley, why are you loitering here?'' asked he,
with some
severity of tone. ``It is my pleasure to be the last in this
mansion of the
King.''
   <pb n="984"/>
</p><p>``Not so, if it please your Excellency,'' answered the
time-stricken
woman. ``This roof has sheltered me long. I will not pass from it
until they
bear me to the tomb of my forefathers. What other shelter is there
for old
Esther Dudley, save the Province House or the grave?''
</p><p>``Now Heaven forgive me!'' said Sir William Howe to himself.
``I was
about to leave this wretched old creature to starve or beg. Take
this, good
Mistress Dudley,'' he added, putting a purse into her hands. ``King
George's head on these golden guineas is sterling yet, and will
continue so,
I warrant you, even should the rebels crown John Hancock their
king.
That purse will buy a better shelter than the Province House can
now
afford.''
</p><p>``While the burden of life remains upon me, I will have no
other shelter
than this roof,'' persisted Esther Dudley, striking her staff upon
the floor
with a gesture that expressed immovable resolve. ``And when your
Excellency returns in triumph, I will totter into the porch to
welcome you.''
</p><p>``My poor old friend!'' answered the British General,&mdash;and
all his
manly and martial pride could no longer restrain a gush of bitter
tears.
``This is an evil hour for you and me. The Province which the King
intrusted to my charge is lost. I go hence in misfortune&mdash;perchance
in disgrace&mdash;to return no more. And you, whose present being is
incorporated
with the past&mdash;who have seen Governor after Governor, in stately
pageantry, ascend these steps&mdash;whose whole life has been an
observance
of
majestic ceremonies, and a worship of the King&mdash;how will you endure
the
change? Come with us! Bid farewell to a land that has shaken off
its allegiance, and live still under a royal government, at
Halifax.''
</p><p>``Never, never!'' said the pertinacious old dame. ``Here
will I abide;
and King George shall still have one true subject in his disloyal
Province.''
</p><p>``Beshrew the old fool!'' muttered Sir William Howe, growing
impatient of her obstinacy, and ashamed of the emotion into which
he
had
been betrayed. ``She is the very moral of old-fashioned prejudice,
and
could exist nowhere but in this musty edifice. Well, then, Mistress
Dudley, since you will needs tarry, I give the Province House in
charge to
you. Take this key, and keep it safe until myself, or some other
Royal
Governor, shall demand it of you.''
</p><p>Smiling bitterly at himself and her, he took the heavy key
of the Province House, and delivering it into the old lady's hands,
drew his
cloak
around him for departure. As the General glanced back at Esther
Dudley's antique figure, he deemed her well fitted for such a
charge,
as being
so perfect a representative of the decayed past&mdash;of an age gone by,
with
its manners, opinions, faith and feelings, all fallen into oblivion
or scorn
&mdash;of what had once been a reality, but was now merely a vision of
faded
magnificence. Then Sir William Howe strode forth, smiting his
clinched
hands together, in the fierce anguish of his spirit; and old Esther
Dudley
was left to keep watch in the lonely Province House, dwelling there
with
memory; and if Hope ever seemed to flit around her, still was it
Memory
in disguise.
   <pb n="985"/>
</p><p>The total change of affairs that ensued on the departure of
the British
troops did not drive the venerable lady from her stronghold. There
was
not, for many years afterwards, a Governor of Massachusetts; and
the
magistrates, who had charge of such matters, saw no objection to
Esther
Dudley's residence in the Province House, especially as they must
otherwise have paid a hireling for taking care of the premises,
which
with her
was a labor of love. And so they left her the undisturbed mistress
of the
old historic edifice. Many and strange were the fables which the
gossips
whispered about her, in all the chimney corners of the town. Among
the
time-worn articles of furniture that had been left in the mansion
there was
a tall, antique mirror, which was well worthy of a tale by itself,
and perhaps may hereafter be the theme of one. The gold of its
heavily-wrought
frame was tarnished, and its surface so blurred, that the old
woman's
figure, whenever she paused before it, looked indistinct and
ghost-like.
But it was the general belief that Esther could cause the Governors
of the
overthrown dynasty, with the beautiful ladies who had once adorned
their
festivals, the Indian chiefs who had come up to the Province House
to
hold council or swear allegiance, the grim Provincial warriors, the
severe
clergymen&mdash;in short, all the pageantry of gone days&mdash;all the
figures that
ever swept across the broad plate of glass in former times&mdash;she
could
cause the whole to reappear, and people the inner world of the
mirror
with shadows of old life. Such legends as these, together with the
singularity of her isolated existence, her age, and the infirmity
that each
added
winter flung upon her, made Mistress Dudley the object both of fear
and
pity; and it was partly the result of either sentiment that, amid
all the
angry license of the times, neither wrong nor insult ever fell upon
her unprotected head. Indeed, there was so much haughtiness in her
demeanor
towards intruders, among whom she reckoned all persons acting under
the new authorities, that it was really an affair of no small nerve
to look
her in the face. And to do the people justice, stern republicans as
they had
now become, they were well content that the old gentlewoman, in her
hoop petticoat and faded embroidery, should still haunt the palace
of
ruined pride and overthrown power, the symbol of a departed system,
embodying a history in her person. So Esther Dudley dwelt year
after
year in the Province House, still reverencing all that others had
flung
aside, still faithful to her King, who, so long as the venerable
dame yet
held her post, might be said to retain one true subject in New
England,
and one spot of the empire that had been wrested from him.
</p><p>And did she dwell there in utter loneliness? Rumor said, not
so. Whenever her chill and withered heart desired warmth, she was
wont to
summon a black slave of Governor Shirley's from the blurred mirror,
and
send him in search of guests who had long ago been familiar in
those deserted chambers. Forth went the sable messenger, with the
starlight
or
the moonshine gleaming through him, and did his errand in the
burial
ground, knocking at the iron doors of tombs, or upon the marble
slabs
that covered them, and whispering to those within: ``My mistress,
old
Esther Dudley, bids you to the Province House at midnight.'' And
punctually
   <pb n="986"/>
as the clock of the Old South told twelve came the shadows of
the
Olivers, the Hutchinsons, the Dudleys, all the grandees of a
by-gone generation, gliding beneath the portal into the well-known
mansion,
where
Esther mingled with them as if she likewise were a shade. Without
vouching for the truth of such traditions, it is certain that
Mistress
Dudley
sometimes assembled a few of the stanch, though crestfallen, old
tories,
who had lingered in the rebel town during those days of wrath and
tribulation. Out of a cobwebbed bottle, containing liquor that a
royal
Governor might have smacked his lips over, they quaffed healths to
the
King,
and babbled treason to the Republic, feeling as if the protecting
shadow
of the throne were still flung around them. But, draining the last
drops
of their liquor, they stole timorously homeward, and answered not
again
if the rude mob reviled them in the street.
</p><p>Yet Esther Dudley's most frequent and favored guests were
the children of the town. Towards them she was never stern. A
kindly and
loving
nature, hindered elsewhere from its free course by a thousand rocky
prejudices, lavished itself upon these little ones. By bribes of
gingerbread
of her own making, stamped with a royal crown, she tempted their
sunny
sportiveness beneath the gloomy portal of the Province House, and
would
often beguile them to spend a whole play-day there, sitting in a
circle
round the verge of her hoop petticoat, greedily attentive to her
stories of
a dead world. And when these little boys and girls stole forth
again from
the dark, mysterious mansion, they went bewildered, full of old
feelings
that graver people had long ago forgotten, rubbing their eyes at
the world
around them as if they had gone astray into ancient times, and
become
children of the past. At home, when their parents asked where they
had
loitered such a weary while, and with whom they had been at play,
the
children would talk of all the departed worthies of the Province,
as far
back as Governor Belcher and the haughty dame of Sir William
Phipps.
It would seem as though they had been sitting on the knees of these
famous personages, whom the grave had hidden for half a century,
and
had
toyed with the embroidery of their rich waistcoats, or roguishly
pulled
the long curls of their flowing wigs. ``But Governor Belcher has
been dead
this many a year,'' would the mother say to her little boy. ``And
did you
really see him at the Province House?'' ``Oh yes, dear mother!
yes!'' the
half-dreaming child would answer. ``But when old Esther had done
speaking about him he faded away out of his chair.'' Thus, without
affrighting
her little guests, she led them by the hand into the chambers of
her own
desolate heart, and made childhood's fancy discern the ghosts that
haunted there.
</p><p>Living so continually in her own circle of ideas, and never
regulating
her mind by a proper reference to present things, Esther Dudley
appears
to have grown partially crazed. It was found that she had no right
sense
of the progress and true state of the Revolutionary War, but held
a constant faith that the armies of Britain were victorious on
every
field, and
destined to be ultimately triumphant. Whenever the town rejoiced
for a
battle won by Washington, or Gates, or Morgan or Greene, the news,
in
   <pb n="987"/>
passing through the door of the Province House, as through the
ivory
gate of dreams, became metamorphosed into a strange tale of the
prowess
of Howe, Clinton, or Cornwallis. Sooner or later it was her
invincible belief the colonies would be prostrate at the footstool
of the King.
Sometimes she seemed to take for granted that such was already the
case. On
one occasion, she startled the towns-people by a brilliant
illumination of
the Province House, with candles at every pane of glass, and a
transparency of the King's initials and a crown of light in the
great
balcony
window. The figure of the aged woman in the most gorgeous of her
mildewed velvets and brocades was seen passing from casement to
casement,
until she paused before the balcony, and flourished a huge key
above her
head. Her wrinkled visage actually gleamed with triumph, as if the
soul
within her were a festal lamp.
</p><p>``What means this blaze of light? What does old Esther's joy
portend?''
whispered a spectator. ``It is frightful to see her gliding about
the chambers, and rejoicing there without a soul to bear her
company.''
</p><p>``It is as if she were making merry in a tomb,'' said
another.
</p><p>``Pshaw! It is no such mystery,'' observed an old man, after
some brief
exercise of memory. ``Mistress Dudley is keeping jubilee for the
King of
England's birthday.''
</p><p>Then the people laughed aloud, and would have thrown mud
against
the blazing transparency of the King's crown and initials, only
that they
pitied the poor old dame, who was so dismally triumphant amid the
wreck
and ruin of the system to which she appertained.
</p><p>Oftentimes it was her custom to climb the weary staircase
that wound
upward to the cupola, and thence strain her dimmed eyesight seaward
and countryward, watching for a British fleet, or for the march of
a grand
procession, with the King's banner floating over it. The passengers
in the
street below would discern her anxious visage, and send up a shout,
``When the golden Indian on the Province House shall shoot his
arrow,
and when the cock on the Old South spire shall crow, then look for
a
Royal Governor again!''&mdash;for this had grown a byword through the
town.
And at last, after long, long years, old Esther Dudley knew, or
perchance
she only dreamed, that a Royal Governor was on the eve of returning
to
the Province House, to receive the heavy key which Sir William Howe
had committed to her charge. Now it was the fact that intelligence
bearing some faint analogy to Esther's version of it was current
among
the
townspeople. She set the mansion in the best order that her means
allowed, and, arraying herself in silks and tarnished gold, stood
long before
the blurred mirror to admire her own magnificence. As she gazed,
the gray
and withered lady moved her ashen lips, murmuring half aloud,
talking to
shapes that she saw within the mirror, to shadows of her own
fantasies,
to the household friends of memory, and bidding them rejoice with
her
and come forth to meet the Governor. And while absorbed in this
communion, Mistress Dudley heard the tramp of many footsteps in the
street,
and, looking out at the window, beheld what she construed as the
Royal
Governor's arrival.
   <pb n="988"/>
</p><p>``O happy day! O blessed, blessed hour!'' she exclaimed.
``Let me but
bid him welcome within the portal, and my task in the Province
House,
and on earth, is done!''
</p><p>Then with tottering feet, which age and tremulous joy caused
to tread
amiss, she hurried down the grand staircase, her silks sweeping and
rustling as she went, so that the sound was as if a train of
spectral
courtiers
were thronging from the dim mirror. And Esther Dudley fancied that
as
soon as the wide door should be flung open, all the pomp and
splendor of
by-gone times would pace majestically into the Province House, and
the
gilded tapestry of the past would be brightened by the sunshine of
the
present. She turned the key&mdash;withdrew it from the lock&mdash;unclosed
the
door&mdash;and stepped across the threshold. Advancing up the court-yard
appeared a person of most dignified mien, with tokens, as Esther
interpreted
them, of gentle blood, high rank, and long-accustomed authority,
even in
his walk and every gesture. He was richly dressed, but wore a gouty
shoe
which, however, did not lessen the stateliness of his gait. Around
and behind him were people in plain civic dresses, and two or three
war-worn
veterans, evidently officers of rank, arrayed in a uniform of blue
and buff.
But Esther Dudley, firm in the belief that had fastened its roots
about
her heart, beheld only the principal personage, and never doubted
that
this was the long-looked-for Governor, to whom she was to surrender
up
her charge. As he approached, she involuntary sank down on her
knees
and tremblingly held forth the heavy key.
</p><p>``Receive my trust! take it quickly!'' cried she, ``for
methinks Death is
striving to snatch away my triumph. But he comes too late. Thank
Heaven for this blessed hour! God save King George!''
</p><p>``That, Madam, is a strange prayer to be offered up at such
a moment,''
replied the unknown guest of the Province House, and courteously
removing his hat, he offered his arm to raise the aged woman.
``Yet,
in reverence for your gray hairs and long-kept faith, Heaven forbid
that
any
here should say you nay. Over the realms which still acknowledge
his
sceptre, God save King George!''
</p><p>Esther Dudley started to her feet, and hastily clutching
back the key
gazed with fearful earnestness at the stranger; and dimly and
doubtfully,
as if suddenly awakened from a dream, her bewildered eyes half
recognized his face. Years ago she had known him among the gentry
of the
province. But the ban of the King had fallen upon him! How, then,
came
the doomed victim here? Proscribed, excluded from mercy, the
monarch's most dreaded and hated foe, this New England merchant had
stood
triumphantly against a kingdom's strength; and his foot now trod
upon
humbled Royalty, as he ascended the steps of the Province House,
the
people's chosen Governor of Massachusetts.
</p><p>``Wretch, wretch that I am!'' muttered the old woman, with
such a
heart-broken expression that the tears gushed from the stranger's
eyes
``Have I bidden a traitor welcome? Come, Death! come quickly!''
</p><p>``Alas, venerable lady!'' said Governor Hancock, tending her
his support with all the reverence that a courtier would have shown
to a
queen.
   <pb n="989"/>
</p><p>``Your life has been prolonged until the world has changed
around you.
You have treasured up all that time has rendered worthless&mdash;the
principles, feelings, manners, modes of being and acting, which
another
generation has flung aside&mdash;and you are a symbol of the past. And
I,
and
these around me&mdash;we represent a new race of men&mdash;living no longer
in
the past, scarcely in the present&mdash;but projecting our lives forward
into
the future. Ceasing to model ourselves on ancestral superstitions,
it is our
faith and principle to press onward, onward! Yet,'' continued he,
turning
to his attendants, ``let us reverence, for the last time, the
stately and
gorgeous prejudices of the tottering Past!''
</p><p>While the Republican Governor spoke, he had continued to
support the
helpless form of Esther Dudley; her weight grew heavier against his
arm;
but at last, with a sudden effort to free herself, the ancient
woman sank
down beside one of the pillars of the portal. The key of the
Province
House fell from her grasp, and clanked against the stone.
</p><p>``I have been faithful unto death,'' murmured she. ``God
save the
King!''
</p><p>``She hath done her office!'' said Hancock solemnly. ``We
will follow
her reverently to the tomb of her ancestors; and then, my
fellow-citizens,
onward&mdash;onward! We are no longer children of the Past!''

</p><p>&mdash;
</p><p>As the old loyalist concluded his narrative, the enthusiasm
which had
been fitfully flashing within his sunken eyes, and quivering across
his
wrinkled visage, faded away, as if all the lingering fire of his
soul were
extinguished. Just then, too, a lamp upon the mantel-piece threw
out a
dying gleam, which vanished as speedily as it shot upward,
compelling our
eyes to grope for one another's features by the dim glow of the
hearth.
With such a lingering fire, methought, with such a dying gleam, had
the
glory of the ancient system vanished from the Province House, when
the
spirit of old Esther Dudley took its flight. And now, again, the
clock of
the Old South threw its voice of ages on the breeze, knolling the
hourly
knell of the Past, crying out far and wide through the
multitudinous city,
and filling our ears, as we sat in the dusky chamber, with its
reverberating
depth of tone. In that same mansion&mdash;in that very chamber&mdash;what a
volume of history had been told off into hours, by the same voice
that
was
now trembling in the air. Many a Governor had heard those midnight
accents, and longed to exchange his stately cares for slumber. And
as
for
mine host and Mr. Bela Tiffany and the old loyalist and me, we had
babbled about dreams of the past, until we almost fancied that the
clock was
still striking in a bygone century. Neither of us would have
wondered,
had a hoop-petticoated phantom of Esther Dudley tottered into the
chamber, walking her rounds in the hush of midnight, as of yore,
and
motioned
us to quench the fading embers of the fire, and leave the historic
precincts to herself and her kindred shades. But as no such vision
was
vouch-safed, I retired unbidden, and would advise Mr. Tiffany to
lay hold
of
   <pb n="990"/>
another auditor, being resolved not to show my face in the Province
House for a good while hence&mdash;if ever.</p>

</div2>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

