<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HimPlan"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="HimPlan">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Plan of Paradise Lost</title>
<title type="sort">plan of paradise lost</title>
<author>Himes, John A.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">39</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HimPlan</idno>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476080</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Plan of Paradise Lost</title>
<title level="j">The New Englander, vol. 42</title>
<title type="sort">plan of paradise lost</title>
<author>John A. Himes</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>196-211</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<date value="1883-03">March 1883</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa library, Micfilm S-10 reel 910</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1883">1883</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
<language id="la">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-08">August 1997</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Gregory Murray, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
 <pb n="196"/>
<head>ARTICLE IV. &mdash; THE PLAN OF PARADISE LOST.</head>

<p>IN all the attempts to trace the origin of <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi> to
the Caedmon, to Andreini, to Grotius, to Du Bartas, and to a score of
others, no claim, so far as I am aware, has been advanced to having
found in any, or in all, of them the entire plan upon which Milton
worked and which he filled out.  Caedmon is said to have helped here,
Andreini there, and Du Bartas in a third place, but no one of them and
not all of them together give in any just sense an explanation of the
existence of the great English epic.</p>

<p>During an extended study of <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi>, the results of
which were published in 1878, I became convinced that there remained a
point of view from which the poem would show a better unity than it is
commonly supposed to have.  This point of view I found, accidentally, it
must be admitted, shortly after the publication of my essay, and at once
and without any difficulty I wrote out the substance of what I am here
about to give.  Reviewing my material after an interval of nearly five
years, during which much thought has been expended upon the poem, I am
more than ever convinced of its value in explanation of the poet's
method.</p>

<p>Milton is no exception to the rule that great poets find rather than
make their plans.  There is a narrative exactly coincident with the
story of the poem in its beginning, breadth, and end.  It is found where
Milton would naturally look for his plan.  It conforms to the poet's
classical taste.  As commonly understood, it accords with Milton's early
religious training and political sympathies.  It is highly figurative,
and therefore just what a poet's soul would delight to interpret.  In
the last-named characteristic we find the chief reason why Milton's
selection of the passage as the foundation of his poem has not sooner
been discovered.</p>

<p>St. John's vision of the seven trumpets in the Apocalypse
is a vision of Judgment covering the entire course of angelic
and human transgression.  It begins before the Creation, takes

   <pb n="197"/>

in the whole reach of time, and ends with the final disposition
of things for eternity.  It is a view of the origin and the final
punishment of evil.  What else could be said of <hi rend="italic">Paradise
Lost?</hi>  Its scope and purpose are the same, its method is the
same, and we shall find that every distinct feature of the
prophecy can be found in the poem.</p>

<p>The prophet's vision and the poet's may best be compared first in
their general features.  In the former a part of the action is
extra-mundane and a part intra-mundane, and the transition from the one
to the other is marked by the warning cry between the fourth and the
fifth trumpet: "Woe to the inhabiters of the earth by reason of the
other voices of the trumpet of the three angels which are yet to sound!"
Magnificent opportunity for an epic poet meditating this subject in the
way of an opening leading at once <foreign lang="la">in medias
res!</foreign> Milton was not slow to see and take advantage of such a
feature.  At this point of time, near the sounding of the fifth trumpet,
he enters upon the narrative, and from this looks before and after.
Raphael is brought from Heaven to narrate the past, Michael to foretell
the future.  Two angels, unnamed, likewise appeared to St. John: the
first, seen "flying through the midst of Heaven," is identical with
Raphael, who, charged with a warning to man, similarly sprang up and
"flew through the midst of Heaven" (v. 251); the second is Michael,
having the same radiant form as he, and clothed, like him, with a cloud
and a rainbow (xi. 229, 244).</p>

<p>It will be observed that the angels who sound the trumpets are
stationed in Heaven, while the judgments following are executed in some
other place.  The last three are separated from the rest as alone
executed upon the earth; and it is most natural to infer that the other
four are to be referred to Hell, the place of punishment, which is
unmistakably prominent in the passage.  In <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi>, six
soundings of the trumpet in Heaven are explicitly mentioned, and the
remaining one is with sufficient clearness implied.  Two of the
soundings occur on the first day of the war in Heaven.  On the morning
of that day, as a sign of wrath awaked for the first time in celestial
history, "the loud ethereal trumpet from on high gan blow" (vi. 60).  It
announced the approaching combat between

   <pb n="198"/>

Faith, represented in Abdiel, and Unbelief, embodied
in Satan.  Again, just as the two armies were about to engage
in a general battle,</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>"Michael bid sound
</l><l>The archangel trumpet.  Through the vast of Heaven
</l><l>It sounded, and the faithful armies rung
</l><l>Hosanna to the Highest" <bibl>(vi. 202)</bibl>.</l></lg>

<p>It was the signal for the conflict between the Letter and the Spirit of
the Law, such as took place when Michael contended with Satan for the
body of Moses (Jude 9).  The third sounding was at the dawning of the
second day, when</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>"Up rose the victor angels, and to arms
</l><l>The matin trumpet sung" <bibl>(vi. 526)</bibl>.</l></lg>

<p>Following this came the fierce and doubtful encounter which symbolizes
the struggle between the Flesh and the Spirit, or between Desire and
Duty.  Another sounding on the morning of the third day is naturally
looked for, but instead thereof the chariot of the Messiah then rushes
forth "with whirlwind sound."  What reason is there for believing this
to be a substitute for the fourth sounding of the trumpet, and its
equivalent?</p>

<p>Note the features of the third day's conflict.  They are such as the
Sacred Writings associate with the Final Judgment.  The unexpected
appearance of the Messiah on his throne in the clouds accompanied by his
saints and his portentous heavenly ensign; his renewal of the disordered
celestial territory, as he will finally renew the earth; his approval of
the faithful; his affliction of the disobedient, until they call for the
mountains to fall upon them and shield them from his wrath; his
expulsion of his enemies, as a flock of timorous goats, from Heaven; his
imprisonment of them in the dungeon of despair, form together a scene of
unmistakable significance.  Matthew and Paul mention the sounding of a
trumpet as announcing the Judgment, but Mark and Luke omit it, and Peter
speaks only of "a great noise."  The Old Testament writers frequently
connect a whirlwind with their Judgment scenes, and at least one (Zech.
ix. 14) includes both the sounding of a trumpet and a whirlwind.  The
poet, then, may be allowed to choose as to whether he will mention the
trumpet

   <pb n="199"/>

again, or, by substituting the whirlwind, bring out with additional
distinctness the meaning of the whole scene.  Like the sound of a
whirlwind in the natural world, the sound of the Judgment trumpet
proclaims the impending doom and over-throw of those who have "sowed
the wind."</p>

<p>The weight of these considerations being admitted, the only
difficulty has vanished.  The next trumpet sounded when
Michael prepared to descend to drive Adam and Eve out of
Paradise; and the sounding of the sixth and the seventh is
foretold in the same sentence in which this is announced.</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>"He ended, and the Son gave signal high
</l><l>To the bright Minister that watched.  He blew
</l><l>His trumpet, heard in Oreb since perhaps
</l><l>When God descended, and perhaps once more
</l><l>To sound at general doom."
</l></lg>

<p>This passage, when its leadings are carefully followed, furnishes a clew
to the whole poem.  Why should Milton interrupt his narrative at such a
juncture with the sounding of a trumpet?  For speaking of a trumpet at
Oreb and at "general doom" he had authority in the Sacred Scriptures;
had he any for this? had he any for the soundings in the sixth book?
Step by step such questions lead us to the vision of the trumpets in the
Apocalypse, where we find thus divided into seven divine eras the
history of evil and its punishment.</p>

<p>It is in order next to inquire whether there is in <hi rend="italic">Paradise
Lost</hi> anything that agrees with the judgments described as following
the several soundings of the trumpets.  That we may proceed
intelligently, it is necessary to have a firm hold upon Milton's
principle of interpretation.  The comprehension of one fact will greatly
help our progress &mdash; the fact that the fallen spirits number one-third
of the original inhabitants of Heaven; and whenever St. John speaks of
one-third of any class of objects, Milton understands him to refer to
the devils.  We read of judgments upon the third part of the trees, of
the creatures in the sea, of the ships, of the rivers, of the waters,
and of the stars.  To justify his belief that under all these terms the
devils are referred to, Milton might have pointed to the epistle of
Jude, where "the angels which kept not their first estate" are
designated as "clouds without water," "trees

   <pb n="200"/>

whose fruit withereth," "raging waves of the sea, foaming out
their own shame," "wandering stars, to whom is reserved the
blackness of darkness forever."  That this method of denoting
the evil spirits was not uncommon in apostolic times is evident
from 2 Pet. ii. 17, where nearly the same language is used as
that just quoted from Jude.  In strict harmony with the
apostles, Milton compares the devils to <hi rend="italic">trees</hi>, "the forest oaks
or mountain pines" (i. 613), to the <hi rend="italic">"starry</hi> flock" led by Lucifer
(v. 708, 709), and more obscurely to <hi rend="italic">rivers</hi> or <hi rend="italic">streams</hi> of water
&mdash; serpents formed from the blood of Gorgon, the storm-cloud
(x. 527).  Satan, a representative spirit, is likened to that <hi rend="italic">sea-beast</hi> Leviathan (i. 200), to the <hi rend="italic">sun</hi> or the morning <hi rend="italic">star</hi> (in
many places), to a <hi rend="italic">cloud</hi> without water (iv. 813-819), to a <hi rend="italic">ship</hi>
or <hi rend="italic">fleet</hi> (ii. 636, 1043).</p>

<p>The "hail and fire mingled with blood" that followed the sounding
of the first trumpet are the "sulphurous hail" and the "red lightning"
(i. 171, 175) remembered by Satan as having been ingredients of the
terrible storm which pursued the fleeing castaways through the Deep.
The earth upon which the storm fell is not this planet of ours, but
the land portions of Hell, burned, and desolated, and changed by a
curse into those "dry places" over which the evil spirits are said to
wander.  Standing on this barren soil, the evil spirits are like
trees, not such as grow along the heavenly rivers of water,
flourishing and bearing fruit, but such as have been swept through
with fires, showing bare and lifeless branches and a "singed top."
This judgment of the singed top, implying intellectual loss, is a fit
reward for the willful unbelief manifested in the first day's fight in
Heaven, and agrees perfectly with St. John's statement that "the third
part of the trees was burnt up."</p>

<p>The judgments following the second trumpet are that "a
great mountain burning the fire was cast into the sea, and the
third part of the sea became blood."  In reproducing this
scene, as in the preceding, Milton takes the word "blood" to
designate only the color and not the essence of the thing so
represented, and is evidently at pains to make his description
of the Lake of Fire consistent with this verse.  The "fiery
waves" and the "inflamed sea" might seem enough to represent

   <pb n="201"/>

the color suggested in the Apocalyptic vision, but in addition
the whole body of "liquid fire" is compared to the <hi rend="italic">Red</hi> Sea (i.
306).  Still further, there is the very precise statement that the
"hue" of the shore is like the color of the ground, whence</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>"The force
</l><l>Of subterranean wind transports a hill
</l><l>Torn from Pelorus, or the shattered side
</l><l>Of thundering Etna."
</l></lg>

<p>A number of the minor cones of Etna have received such names as Monte
Rossi and Monte Arso, from the redness of the ashes and cinders of
which they are mainly composed; and it is not an unusual thing for
such cones to fall into the crater (<hi rend="italic">Encyc. Brit.</hi>, vol. viii.,
pp. 629, 630).  Mount Sinai, the mountain where the Law was given,
often typifies, with its thunders and lightnings, the penalty of the
Law broken.  The "great mountain burning with fire" that was cast into
the sea is no other than Sinai in its terrific spiritual meaning, and
symbolizes the punishment of those who fought against Michael, the
representative of the Law, after the second trumpet of the first day
in Heaven.</p>

<p>"The third part of the creatures which were in the sea, and had
life died; and the third part of the ships were destroyed."  These
"ships" and "creatures," according to Milton's principle of
interpretation, are simply the fallen spirits again presented under
new figures consistent with their changed relations.  St.  John says
of the "ships" that they "were destroyed," and of the "creatures" that
they "died."  Milton likewise describes the devils as laid low "in
horrible destruction," "as far as gods and heavenly essences can
perish."  They remained in their state of inactivity, or "confusion"
nine days and nights; just as long as the mythical Latona (Leto=Death)
labored at the birth of her children, Apollo and Diana; and likewise
as long as from the beginning of the creative week in Genesis to the
creation of Eve.  At the end of that period, Satan and Beelzebub, who,
as will hereafter appear, are identical with the twin children of
Latona, rise from the fiery lake, the bonds of death having been
broken.  Death is with perfect consistency represented as the special
doom for resisting Michael, the

   <pb n="202"/>

genius of the Law, because "the soul that sinneth, it shall
die."</p>

<p>Connected with the sounding of the third angel is the fall of a
"great star" from Heaven.  Milton treats this star as identical with
that which falls from Heaven to Earth after the sounding of the fifth
angel; and he personifies what it represents in the form of Sin
sitting at Hell gates.  The description of Sin as "a great star
burning as it were a lamp" sets forth the consuming nature of Lust
which feeds upon the soul as the flame upon oil.  Milton's Sin is an
impersonation not so much of lawlessness as of carnal Pleasure &mdash; the
Venus of Paradise Lost, dressed in deceitful beauty.  In common with
the star whose name is Wormwood, she proves herself, as her cheated
devotees invariably experience, "a bitter morsel" (ii. 808).  But one
fact of itself would establish the identity of Sin with the star, &mdash;
the fact that "the key of the bottomless pit," which St. John assigns
to the star is by Milton given to Sin.  The star fell upon "the third
part of the rivers and fountains of waters;" that is, it caused in all
the rebellious spirits the bitterness of remorse.  Afterward the sin
and the remorse came also among men through the agency of the evil
spirits.  Following the trumpet which announced the celestial
encounter between Duty and Pleasure, comes fitly the fall of Sin into
Hell, and then the birth of Death.</p>

<p>Consequent upon the sounding of the fourth angel is the smiting of
the third part of the Sun, the Moon, and the Stars.  Milton's angels
are very often described under images and forms of expression drawn
from, and applicable to, the celestial orbs.  The poet's custom is
sanctioned by the usage of Scripture, where the righteous in Heaven
are directly compared to the stars and the sun (Dan. xii. 3; Matt.
xiii. 43).  Of the fallen angels Satan is the solar spirit, Beelzebub
the lunar spirit, and the others are the stellar spirits.  Their
smiting is their loss of glory so impressively described in the first
book of Paradise Lost.  But there is loss not only in them, but on
account of them; for "the day shone not for a third part of it, and
the night likewise."  There is loss in Heaven, because of the Divine
curse which in the third day's fight stripped them of their splendor
and expelled them from Heaven.</p>

   <pb n="203"/>

<p>Before the fifth trumpet sounds, the scene of action is transferred
to this world.  The evil spirits have already risen in the smoke of
the Pit in clouds, like the locusts of Egypt, which darkened the land
(i. 343).  Hell-gates have been thrown open by Sin, and have begun to
cast forth their furnace smoke and flame.  Satan has accomplished his
journey through Chaos into the world, a precursor of the irruption of
devils that was later to take place.  After announcing the fifth
trumpet, St. John gives a very particular description of the locusts,
or devils, who are soon to invade the world.  They have faces like men,
hair like women, bodies like war-horses, and tails like scorpions; the
other features are properties rather than essentials.  What meaning
did Milton take out of this description?  Long familiarity with the
poet's habits of thought encourages me to venture a reply.</p>

<p>The poet, I think, understands the seer to be giving a visible
picture of something in fact immaterial and invisible.  Evil has its
starting-point in desire, which persuades the will and produces the
wrong purpose, that in turn gives birth to the wrong act.  Wrong acts
always work injustice and cause conflict between the sufferers and the
doers of the wrong.  The conflict fully carried out ends in death.
This is what the Apostle James means by saying: "When lust hath
conceived, it bringeth forth sin; and sin, when it is finished,
bringeth forth death."  The back part of the head with its woman's
hair represents lust, the front with its man's face is will, the
agreement of the two is the formation of the purpose.  The body, that
of a war-horse, represents the wars and fightings that come from lust
(James iv. 1); the tail with its scorpion sting represents death,
which is the end of all.  The whole process of evil is illustrated in
the history of the antediluvian world, when the sons of God were
joined to the daughters of men and begat those giants and men of
renown who filled earth with violence and led to the destruction of
the race in the Deluge.  The crowns of gold on these spiritual figures
denote the universal power of evil over men, and the lion-like teeth
suggest its devouring greediness.  Not one of these features has been
overlooked by the poet.  The spiritual facts are fundamental
throughout the poem, and the symbol appropriate

   <pb n="204"/>

to each is sooner or later brought to notice in a striking simile
or metaphor.</p>

<p>But of nothing else in the whole prophetic vision does Milton make
such constant use as of the identification of the king of these fallen
spirits, Satan or Lucifer, with the Apollyon or Apollo of the Greeks.
Let it be noted that Milton here has Scriptural authority, not merely
for comparing Satan to Apollo, but for treating him as the same.  He
whom the Greeks call Apollo is the chief of the devils.  The
recognition of this fact is essential to the comprehension of Milton's
plan, at the same time that it exposes the blunder of such as hold
with Dr. Johnson that "the mythological allusions have been justly
censured as not being always used with notice of their vanity."  To
believers of the earlier centuries those myths were far from vain;
they contained the true history of beings who were at the same time
the gods of the Pagan and the demons or angels of the Christian.
Besides, those beings stand for actual facts and principles in the
physical and moral constitution of the world.  That the Satan of
Paradise Lost is intended to be no other than the Apollo of mythology
is evident from the frequency of his association with solar phenomena;
from his possession of the characteristics and his performance of the
functions of Apollo; and from the similarity of his adventures to
those of the powerful sun-god.</p>

<p>Standing for the first time after their fall at the head of his
legions, Satan is like the sun new-risen in a cloudy sky (i. 591-600);
sitting upon his gorgeous throne in Pandemonium, he reminds one of the
same luminary nearing its zenith (ii. 1-5); about to depart on a long
journey and encompassed with "a globe of fiery seraphim," he is again
explicitly compared to the radiant sun taking his farewell from a
clear evening sky (ii. 486-495).  The sight of the natural sun in this
world of ours is hateful to him, because it brings to his remembrance
from what state he fell (iv. 32-40); and when we inquire what the
splendor of that heavenly state was, we are shown "the Apostate in his
sun-bright chariot,"</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>"Idol of majesty divine, enclosed
</l><l>With flaming cherubim and golden shields."
</l></lg>

<p>Satan manifests Apollo's oracular power in predicting the

   <pb n="205"/>

creation of the world and of man, in misleading angels and
men by awaking deceitful hopes of good to be derived from a
course of evil, and in giving birth to the sorceress, Sin.  He
executes the office of Apollo as god of medicine in ministering
to the diseased minds of his adherents and reviving their
drooping spirits.  He discharges the function of Apollo as
god of music in effecting this spiritual cure by means of "flutes
and soft recorders," such as have</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>"Power to mitigate and swage
</l><l>With solemn touches troubled thoughts, and chase
</l><l>Anguish and doubt and fear and sorrow and pain
</l><l>From mortal or immortal minds."
</l></lg>

<p>At the same time he follows Apollo's profession of a shepherd
in controling and guiding his followers, who are spoken of as
"bleating herds" (ii. 494), as a "starry flock" (v. 709), and as
a "herd of goats or timorous flock" (vi. 856).</p>

<p>There is an equal coincidence in the events of Satan's and those of
Apollo's existence.  The circumstances attending Apollo's birth from
Latona (Death) are like those of Satan's recovery from the deadly
stupor of nine nights and days.  As Satan had Pandemonium built for
himself by the labor of Mammon and Mulciber, near the "mountain of
metals," so Apollo had his temple at Delphi built under the
superintendence of the brothers Agamedes and Trophonius, at the foot of
Mount Parnassus.  As Satan encounters Death on the threshold of Hell,
so Apollo encountered Thanatos in the house of Admetus.  As Satan was
driven out of Heaven, so Apollo was exiled from Olympus.  As Apollo
was enamored of Daphne, so Satan was momentarily smitten with passion
at sight of Eve in her likeness to one of "Delia's train."  In
addition to this, Satan's doings are very frequently modeled after
those of Hector, Sarpedon, and other Homeric leaders who are favorites
of Apollo and inspired by him.  Taking all this into account I am led
to question whether there is anything in the history of Milton's
Arch-fiend which cannot be traced directly or indirectly in the Pagan
Apollo.</p>

<p>On the day when Michael descended (the day of the fifth
trumpet), Death entered the world with Sin.  From this time
until the giving of the Law on Mount Sinai, from Adam to

   <pb n="206"/>

Moses, between the fifth and sixth trumpets, the reign of Death is
conspicuous.  "And in those days shall men seek death, and shall not
find it; and shall desire to die, and death shall flee from them," is
the language of St. John.  In the eleventh book of Milton's poem also,
Adam is invited by Michael to behold the effects which the first man's
crime wrought in his descendants "who never touched the excepted
tree," or in the words of St. Paul, who "had not sinned after the
similitude of Adam's transgression."  A vast tragedy, rising through
more and more appalling events and culminating in the Deluge, is
presented before Adam's vision; and in that tragedy is a terrible
scene evidently drawn from the words of St. John just quoted.  The
poet pictures to the view a vast lazar-house, gives a long catalogue
of the diseases to which the inmates are subject, and then adds:</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>"Dire was the tossing, deep the groans; Despair
</l><l>Tended the sick, busiest from couch to couch;
</l><l>And over them triumphant Death his dart
</l><l>Shook, but delayed to strike, though oft invoked
</l><l>With vows, as their chief good and final hope."
</l></lg>

<p>The five months' torment spoken of by the apostle was probably
understood by the poet to refer to the Deluge itself, the waters of
which "prevailed [increased] upon the earth a hundred and fifty days"
(Gen. vii. 24), and within that time brought upon all mankind, except
those who had "the seal of God upon their foreheads" (Noah and his
family), the pangs of dissolution.</p>

<p>The sounding of the sixth trumpet heralded the giving of the Law on
Mount Sinai.  A part of what was there promulgated related to civil
justice, and this part, written in the beginning on the nature of man,
must remain operative while human beings live in the world.  Another
part, consisting in rites and ceremonies, was first ordained at Sinai,
and was intended only for temporary use in the way of discipline.  At
the death of Christ it was abrogated, and after that Christians were
even reproved for continuing to observe these "days and months and
times and years" (Gal. iv. 10).  Such observance is afterward spoken
of as the bondage of the Law, which may,

   <pb n="207"/>

perhaps, not unfitly be represented by the "four angels bound
in the great river Euphrates."  Milton's account is as follows:</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>"So Law appears imperfect, and but given
</l><l>With purpose to resign them, in full time,
</l><l>Up to a better covenant, disciplined
</l><l>From shadowy types to truth, from flesh to spirit,
</l><l>From imposition of strict laws to free
</l><l>Acceptance of large grace, from servile fear
</l><l>To filial, works of law to works of faith."
</l></lg>

<p>The four angels were loosed, as Milton seems to have understood it,
while the Ceremonial Law was in force; they represent a mere literal
unintelligent obedience to that Law, and assist in the condemnation
and destruction of men by preventing its effectiveness for
discipline.  The Euphrates, in which the four angels are bound, is the
river of Babylon, and the Babylon, Sodom or Egypt of the Apocalypse is
Rome, where Milton saw lifeless ceremony and ritual enough during his
visit to Italy.</p>

<p>The giving of the Law was signalized by an increased
activity among the evil spirits.  A vast army of two hundred
millions of horsemen comes upon the earth, to inflict spiritual,
as the locusts had inflicted bodily, death.  They represent at
once the spirit of hostility to the Law and the retribution
which follows a breaking of the Law.  They are, therefore, in
array of battle and armed with the weapons which their war-god,
Moloch, had proposed in the council in Pandemonium to
use against Heaven.  He wished,</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>"Armed with Hell-flames and fury, all at once
</l><l>O'er Heaven's high towers to force resistless way,
</l><l>Turning our tortures into horrid arms
</l><l>Against the Torturer; when, to meet the noise
</l><l>Of his almighty engine, he shall hear
</l><l>Infernal thunder, and, for lightning, see
</l><l>Black fire and horror shot with equal rage
</l><l>Among his angels, and his throne itself
</l><l>Mixed with Tartarean sulphur and strange fire,
</l><l>His own invented torments."
</l></lg>

<p>We now see how it was that the devils might turn the inventions of the
Almighty against himself.  He had established laws, but even the most
faithful ones had at some time violated

   <pb n="208"/>

them, made enemies of them and stood under their curse:  and
Christ himself, as the bearer of his people's sins, was numbered among
the transgressors, and felt the vengeance of the Law which thus
reached even to the Divine throne.  The horsemen of St. John's vision
were armed just as Moloch proposed to arm the devils: "And thus I saw
the horses in the vision, and them that sat on them, having
breast-plates of fire, and of jacinth [smoke, or something dark in
hue], and brimstone: and the heads of the horses were as the heads of
lions; and out of their mouths issued fire and smoke and brimstone.
By these three was the third part of men killed, by the fire, and by
the smoke, and by the brimstone which issued out of their mouths."</p>

<p>If further evidence is needed of the reasonableness of Milton's
conclusion that the events following the sounding of the sixth trumpet
are very intimately connected with the giving of the Law, it is only
necessary to quote the last two verses of the ninth chapter: "And the
rest of the men which were not killed by these plagues yet repented
not of the works of their hands, that they should not worship devils,
and idols of gold, and silver, and brass, and stone, and of wood;
which neither can see, nor hear, nor walk; neither repented they of
their murders, nor of their sorceries, nor of their fornication, nor of
their thefts."  In these verses we have a pretty complete catalogue of
the representative sins against which the Law is directed.</p>

<p>The tenth chapter of the Apocalypse is taken up with an account of
the descent and the message of "another mighty angel," who becomes the
Michael of Paradise Lost.  The angel gave to John a little book,
which, as he devoured it, was in his mouth "sweet as honey," but
afterward it made his "belly bitter."  When Michael narrated to Adam
the future history of the world, the tale was animating and
enchanting, but the patriarch's subsequent experience of the same was
painful.  Men enjoy, the poet and the seer remind us, a rehearsal or
representation of the great events of time, the most tragic parts
most, just as they might watch the unfolding of a powerful drama; but
to act one's part on the great stage of life, to experience its
losses, passions, sorrows, sin, remorse, is indeed

   <pb n="209"/>

bitter.  This bitterness began in Adam, when, hand in hand,
he and Eve, having turned their backs on Paradise, "with
wandering steps and slow, through Eden took their solitary
way."</p>

<p>The remainder of the Apocalyptic vision which Milton has been
following clearly has reference to events that are to happen near the
end of the world.  The measurement of the temple which the Seer is
directed to make shows the extent of the true Christian Church.  The
outer court, which the Gentiles profane, but in which God's two
Witnesses are to prophesy, embraces the limits of so-called
Christendom where the light of the Gospel shines but is not heeded.
The two Witnesses preach here for a time with success, but their
message is afterward despised, and they themselves are overcome and
killed by the beast from the Pit.  Faith and Truth, enlightened by the
Holy Spirit and Conscience are represented by Milton as going through
a somewhat similar course of maltreatment.  The poet tells us that in
the closing scenes of the world's history,</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>"Heavy persecution shall arise
</l><l>On all who in the worship persevere
</l><l>Of Spirit and Truth: the rest, far greater part,
</l><l>Will deem in outward rites and specious forms
</l><l>Religion satisfied; Truth shall retire
</l><l>Bestruck with slanderous darts, and works of Faith
</l><l>Rarely be found."
</l></lg>

<p>This degeneracy of the Church into "outward rites and
specious forms" may very well be represented as an exposure
to shame of the dead bodies of Truth and Faith, after the life
has departed.  Moreover they are to be exposed "in the street
of the great city, which spiritually is called Sodom and Egypt."
Milton understood this to refer to Rome, the seat of the great
hierarchy, whose names, places, titles, and secular power are
used to force spiritual laws upon the conscience.</p>

<p>The absence of Truth and the lack of Faith seem to hurry
on the closing scenes of the world's history.  Two woes out of
the three that were to fall upon the earth are past, and "the
third woe cometh quickly."  The seventh, and last, trumpet
sounds, and heavenly voices are heard praising the Messiah,
and saying: "We give thee thanks, O Lord God Almighty,

   <pb n="210"/>

which art, and wast, and art to come; because thou hast taken to thee
thy great power, and hast reigned.  And the nations were angry, and
thy wrath is come, and the time of the dead, that they should be
judged, and that thou shouldest give reward unto thy servants the
prophets, and to the saints, and them that fear thy name, small and
great; and shouldest destroy them which destroy the earth."  Just to
this consummation does the archangel Michael in the poem likewise
pursue his narrative; and just here, at "the world's great period,"
does he pause, having told how the Messiah will come,</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>"When this world's dissolution shall be ripe,
</l><l>With glory and power, to judge both quick and dead &mdash;
</l><l>To judge the unfaithful dead, but to reward
</l><l>His faithful, and receive them into bliss."
</l></lg>

<p>Long before the poet had decided to make his masterpiece an epic, and
while he was yet considering the suitableness of various subjects for a
dramatic composition, he published his opinion that "the Apocalypse of
St. John is the majestic image of a high and stately tragedy shutting up
and intermingling her solemn scenes and acts with a sevenfold chorus of
hallelujahs and harping symphonies."  Here is strong external
probability to join with the unlimited internal evidence that
<hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi> is founded upon the passage of Revelation which we
have been considering.  A clearer case, it seems to me, we could not
have, unless the poet had taken the awkward step of explaining his own
work to the world.</p>

<p>Other portions of the Apocalypse, indeed I might say almost the
whole of it, are incorporated in the poem.  Considerable portions of
other books, &mdash; Canticles, the Proverbs, the Psalms, the Gospels, the
Epistles, the Historical books, and the Prophecies are to be found.
Indeed, a minute and careful examination, clause by clause, of nearly
the whole poem almost warrants me in believing that every idea in it,
however apparently remote, was meant by Milton to set forth some
Scriptural truth.  But nowhere, not even in the first of Genesis, do I
find any plan which can at all be regarded as co&euml;xtensive with
that of <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi> except the plan of the vision of the seven
trumpets.  The Fall of Man, more than any other event, is the central
and important fact in this history of disobedience to

   <pb n="211"/>

the Sovereign of the Universe, Adam and Eve are indeed nowhere
mentioned by name in the vision, but they are inseparably associated
with that fall of the Wormwood Star, symbolizing the introduction of
Sin upon the earth.  To human beings, for whom St. John's vision was
recorded, the first four soundings of the trumpet had no direct
relation; and it is at the fifth that the Seer begins to expand his
narrative into greater particularity.  It is right that the poet also
should at the same point labor upon that long and careful analysis of
the human nature in Adam and Eve, and that minute description of their
state, environment and temptations which occupies so much of the
work.  The very full account of the Creation seems at first somewhat
remote from the main subject, but it can scarcely be regarded as a
violation of unity in this way to give prominence to the great
transition, in the midst of the story, from Hell to this world.
Indeed, if the poem is examined in the light of its relation to the
Apocalyptic vision, one cannot fail to be impressed with its perfect
unity and logical coherence.</p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

