<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HowNorr"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="HowNorr">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Frank Norris</title>
<title type="sort">frank norris</title>
<author>Howells, W. D.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">26</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HowNorr</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476090</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Frank Norris</title>
<title level="j">North American Review</title>
<title type="sort">frank norris</title>
<author>W. D. Howells</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>North American Review Publishing Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1902-12">December 1902</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This article appeared in The North American Review,
Volume 175 (December 1902), pp. 769-778.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions
for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1902-12">December 1902</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-02-20">February 20, 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jennifer Hanna</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI-compatible header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">


<body id="d2">
	<div1 type="story" id="d3">
	<pb n="769"/>
<head>
                           FRANK NORRIS.<lb/>
                         BY W. D. HOWELLS.</head>


<div2 type="introduction" id="d4">
<head>[Introduction]</head>

<p>THE projection which death gives the work of a man against the
history of his time, is the doubtful gain we have to set against
the recent loss of such authors as George Douglas, the Scotchman,
who wrote "The House with the Green Shutters," and Frank Norris,
the American, who wrote "McTeague" and "The Octopus," and other
novels, antedating and postdating the first of these, and less
clearly prophesying his future than the last.  The gain is
doubtful, because, though their work is now freed from the cloud of
question which always involves the work of a living man in the mind
of the general, if his work is good (if it is bad they give it no
faltering welcome), its value was already apparent to those who
judge from the certainty within themselves, and not from the
uncertainty without.  Every one in a way knows a thing to be good,
but the most have not the courage to acknowledge it, in their
sophistication with canons and criterions.  The many, who in the
tale of the criticism are not worth minding, are immensely unworthy
of the test which death alone seems to put into their power.  The
few, who had the test before, were ready to own that Douglas's
study of Scottish temperaments offered a hope of Scottish fiction
freed the Scottish sentimentality which had kept it provincial; and
that Norris's two mature novels, one personal and one social,
imparted the assurance of an American fiction so largely
commensurate with American circumstance as to liberate it from the
casual and the occasional, in which it seemed lastingly trammelled.
But the parallel between the two does not hold much farther.  What
Norris did, not merely what he dreamed of doing, was of vaster
frame, and inclusive of imaginative intentions far beyond those of
the only immediate contemporary to be <pb n="770"/>  matched with him,
while it was of as fine and firm an intellectual quality, and of as
intense and fusing an emotionality.</p>
</div2>


<div2 type="chapter" n="1" id="d5">
<head>I</head>
<p>In several times and places, it has been my rare pleasure to
bear witness to the excellence of what Norris had done, and the
richness of his promise.  The vitality of his work was so abundant,
the pulse of health was so full and strong in it, that it is
incredible it should not be persistent still.  The grief with which
we accept such a death as his is without the consolation that we
feel when we can say of some one that his life was a struggle, and
that he is well out of the unequal strife, as we might say when
Stephen Crane died.  The physical slightness, if I may so suggest
one characteristic of Crane's vibrant achievement, reflected the
delicacy of energies that could be put forth only in nervous
spurts, in impulses vivid and keen, but wanting in breadth and bulk
of effect.  Curiously enough, on the other hand, this very lyrical
spirit, whose freedom was its life, was the absolute slave of
reality.  It was interesting to hear him defend what he had
written, in obedience to his experience of things, against any
change in the interest of convention.  "No," he would contend, in
behalf of the profanities of his people, "that is the way they
<hi rend="italic">talk</hi>.  I have thought of that, and whether I ought to leave
such things out, but if I do I am not giving the thing as I
<hi rend="italic">know</hi> it."  He felt the constraint of those semi-savage
natures, such as he depicted in "Maggie," and "George's Mother,"
and was forced through the fealty of his own nature to report them
as they spoke no less than as they looked.  When it came to "The
Red Badge of Courage," where he took leave of these simple
aesthetics, and lost himself in a whirl of wild guesses at the fact
from the ground of insufficient witness, he made the failure which
formed the break between his first and his second manner, though it
was what the public counted a success, with every reason to do so
from the report of the sales.
</p><p>The true Stephen Crane was the Stephen Crane of the earlier
books, the earliest book; for "Maggie" remains the best thing he
did.  All he did was lyrical, but this was the aspect and accent as
well as the spirit of the tragically squalid life he sang, while
"The Red Badge of Courage," and the other things that followed it,
were the throes of an art failing with material to which it could
<pb n="771"/>  not render an absolute devotion from an absolute knowledge.
He sang, but his voice erred up and down the scale, with occasional
flashes of brilliant melody, which could not redeem the errors.
New York was essentially his inspiration, the New York of suffering
and baffled and beaten life, of inarticulate or blasphemous life;
and away from it he was not at home, with any theme, or any sort of
character.  It was the pity of his fate that he must quit New York,
first as a theme, and then as a habitat; for he rested nowhere
else, and wrought with nothing else as with the lurid depths which
he gave proof of knowing better than any one else.  Every one is
limited, and perhaps no one is more limited than another; only, the
direction of the limitation is different in each.  Perhaps George
Douglas, if he had lived, would still have done nothing greater
than "The House with the Green Shutters," and might have failed in
the proportion of a larger range as Stephen Crane did.  I am not
going to say that either of these extraordinary talents was of
narrower bound than Frank Norris; such measures are not of the map.
But I am still less going to say that they were of finer quality
because their achievement seems more poignant, through the sort of
physical concentration which it has.  Just as a whole unhappy world
agonizes in the little space their stories circumscribe, so what is
sharpest and subtlest in that anguish finds its like in the epical
breadths of Norris's fiction.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="2" id="d6">
<head>II</head>
<p>At the other times when I so gladly owned the importance of
this fiction, I frankly recognized what seemed to me the author's
debt to an older master; and now, in trying to sum up my sense of
it in an estimate to which his loss gives a sort of finality for
me, I must own again that he seemed to derive his ideal of the
novel from the novels of Zola.  I cannot say that, if the novels of
Zola had not been cast in the epic mould, the novels of Frank
Norris would not have been epical.  This is by no means certain;
while it is, I think, certain that they owe nothing beyond the form
to the master from whom he may have imagined it.  Or they owe no
more to him, essentially, than to the other masters of the time in
which Norris lived out his life all too soon.  It is not for
nothing that any novelist is born in one age, and not another,
unless we are to except that aoristic freak, the historical
novelist; and by what Frank Norris wrote one might easily know what
he had <pb n="772"/>  read.  He had read, and had profited, with as much
originality as any man may keep for himself, by his study of the
great realists whose fiction has illustrated the latter part of the
nineteenth century beyond any other time in the history of fiction;
and if he seemed to have served his apprenticeship rather more to
one of them than to another, this may be the effect of an
inspiration not finally derived from that one.  An Italian poet
says that in Columbus "the instinct of the unknown continent
burned;" and it may be that this young novelist, who had his
instincts mostly so well intellectualized, was moved quite from
within when he imagined treating American things in an epical
relation as something most expressive of their actual relation.  I
am not so sure that this is so, but I am sure that he believed it
so, and that neither in material nor in treatment are his novels
Zolaesque, though their form is Zolaesque, in the fashion which
Zola did not invent, though he stamped it so deeply with his nature
and his name.
</p><p>I may allow also that he was like Zola in his occasional
indulgence of a helpless fondness for the romantic, but he quite
transcended Zola in the rich strain of poetry coloring his thought,
and the mysticism in which he now and then steeped his story.  I do
not care enough, however, for what is called originality in any
writer to fatigue myself greatly in the effort to establish that of
a writer who will avouch his fresh and vigorous powers to any one
capable of feeling them.  I prefer, in the presence of a large
design left unfulfilled, to note the generous ideal, the ample
purpose, forecast in the novel forming the first of the trilogy he
imagined.
</p><p>In one of those few meetings which seem, too late, as if they
might have been so many, but which the New York conditions of
overwork for all who work at all begrudge, I remember how he
himself outlined his plan.  The story of the Wheat was for him the
allegory of the industrial and financial America which is the real
America, and he had begun already to tell the first part of this
story in the tragedy of the railroad-ridden farms of California,
since published as "The Octopus."  The second part, as he then
designed, was to carry the tale to Chicago, where the distribution
of the Wheat was to be the theme, as its production had already
been the theme in the first.  The last part was to find its scene
in Europe, among the representative cities where the consumption of
the Wheat was to form the motive.  Norris believed himself
peculiarly qualified for the work by the accidents <pb n="773"/>  of his
life; for he was born in Chicago and had lived there till he was
fifteen years old; then he had gone to California, and had grown up
into the knowledge of the scene and action which he has portrayed
so powerfully; later, he had acquainted himself with Europe, by
long sojourn; and so he argued, with an enthusiasm tempered by a
fine sense of his moral and artistic responsibility, that he had
within himself the means of realizing the whole fact to the
reader's imagination.  He was aware that such a plan could be
carried out only by years of ardent and patient study, and he
expected to dedicate the best part of his strong young life to it.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="3" id="d7">
<head>III</head>
<p>Those who know "The Octopus" know how his work justified his
faith in himself; but those who had known "McTeague" could not have
doubted but he would do what he had undertaken, in the spirit of
the undertaking.  Norris did give the time and toil to the right
documentation of his history.  He went to California and renewed
his vital knowledge of his scene; he was in California again,
studying the course of the fact which was to bring him to Chicago,
when death overtook him and ended his high emprise.  But in the
meantime he had given us "The Octopus," and before that he had
given us "McTeague," books not all so unlike in their nature as
their surfaces might suggest.  Both are epical, though the one is
pivoted on the common ambition of a coarse human animal, destined
to prevail in a half-quackish triumph, and the other revolves about
one of the largest interests of modern civilization.  The author
thought at first of calling "McTeague," as he told me, "The Golden
Tooth," which would have been more significant of the irregular
dentist's supremacy in the story, and the ideal which inspired him;
but perhaps he felt a final impossibility in the name.  Yet, the
name is a mere mask; and when one opens the book, the mask falls,
and the drama confronts us with as living a physiognomy as I have
seen in fiction.  There is a bad moment when the author is overcome
by his lingering passion for the romantic, and indulges himself in
a passage of rank melodrama; but even there he does nothing that
denies the reality of his characters, and they are always of a
reality so intense that one lives with them in the grotesquely
shabby San Francisco street where, but for the final episode, the
action passes. <pb n="774"/>
</p><p>What is good is good, it matters not what other things are
better or worse; and I could ask nothing for Norris, in my sense of
his admirable achievement, but a mind freed to criticism absolute
and not relative.  He is of his time, and, as I have said, his
school is evident; and yet I think he has a right to make his
appeal in "The Octopus" irrespective of the other great canvases
beside which that picture must be put.  One should dissociate it as
far as possible from the work of his masters&mdash;we all have masters;
the masters themselves had them&mdash;not because it is an imitation,
and would suffer from the comparison, but because it is so
essentially different, so boldly and frankly native, that one is in
danger of blaming it for a want of conformity to models, rather
than for too close a following.  Yet this, again, does not say
quite the right thing, and what I feel, and wish others to feel, in
regard to it, is the strong security of its most conscientious and
instructed art.  Here is nothing of experiment, of protest, of
rebellion; the author does not break away from form in any
sprawling endeavor for something newly or incomparably American,
Californian, Western, but finds scope enough for his powers within
the limits where the greatest fiction of our period "orbs about."
The time, if there ever was one, for a prose Walt Whitman was past;
and he perceived that the indigenous quality was to be imparted to
his work by the use of fresh material, freshly felt, but used in
the fashion and the form which a world-old art had evolved in its
long endeavor.
</p><p>"McTeague" was a personal epic, the Odyssey of a simple, semi-savage nature adventuring and experiencing along the low social
levels which the story kept, and almost never rose or fell from.
As I review it in the light of the first strong impressions, I must
own it greater than I have ever yet acknowledged it, and I do this
now with the regret which I hope the critic is apt to feel for not
praising enough when praise could have helped most.  I do not think
my strictures of it were mistaken, for they related to the limits
which certain facts of it would give it with the public, rather
than to the ethical or aesthetic qualities which would establish it
with the connoisseur.  Yet, lest any reader of mine should be left
without due sense of these, I wish now to affirm my strong sense of
them, and to testify to the value which this extraordinary book has
from its perfectly simple fidelity: from the truthfulness in which
there is no self-doubt and no self-excuse. </p><pb n="775"/>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="4" id="d8">
<head>IV</head>
<p>But, with all its power, "McTeague" is no such book as "The
Octopus," which is the Iliad to its Odyssey.
</p><p>It will not be suggesting too much for the story to say, that
there is a kind of Homeric largeness in the play of the passions
moving it.  They are not autochthons, these Californians of the
great Wheat farms, choking in the folds of the railroad, but
Americans of more than one transplantation; yet there is something
rankly earthy and elemental in them, which gives them the pathos of
tormented Titans.  it is hard to choose any of them as the type, as
it is hard to chose* any scene as the representative moment.  If we
choose Annixeter, growing out of an absolute, yet not gross,
materiality, through the fire of a purifying love, into a kind of
final spirituality, we think, with misgiving for our decision, of
Magnus Derrick, the high, pure leader of the rebellion against the
railroad, falling into ruin, moral and mental, through the use of
the enemy's bad means for his good cause.  Half a score of other
figures, from either camp, crowd upon the fancy to contest the
supreme interest, men figures, women figures; and, when it comes to
choosing this episode or that as the supreme event, the confusion
of the critic is even greater.  If one were to instance the fight
between the farmers and the sheriff's deputies, with the
accompanying evictions, one must recall the tremendous passages of
the train-robbery by the crazy victim of the railroad's treachery,
taking his revenge in his hopeless extremity.  Again, a half score
of other scenes, other episodes rise from the remembered pages, and
defy selection.
</p><p>The story is not less but more epical, in being a strongly
inter-wrought group of episodes.  The play of an imagination fed by
a rich consciousness of the mystical relations of nature and human
nature, the body and the soul of earthly life, steeps the whole
theme in an odor of common growth.  It is as if the Wheat sprang
out of the hearts of men, in the conception of the young poet who
writes its Iliad, and who shows how it overwhelms their lives, and
germinates anew from their deaths.  His poem, of which the terms
are naked prose, is a picture of the civilization, the society, the
culture which is the efflorescence of the wheaten prosperity; and
the social California, rank, crude, lusty, which he depicts is as
convincing as the agricultural California, which is the ground of
his work.  It will be easily believed that in the handling <pb n="776"/>
nothing essential to the strong impression is blinked; but nothing,
on the other hand, is forced in.  The episode of Venamee and
Angele, with its hideous tragedy, and the long mystical epilogue
ending almost in anti-climax, is the only passage which can be
accused of irrelevance, and it is easier to bring than to prove
this accusation.
</p><p>As I write, and scarcely touch the living allegory here and
there, it rises before me in its large inclusion, and makes me feel
once more how little any analysis of a work of art can represent
it.  After all the critic must ask the reader to take his word for
it that the thing is great, and entreat him to go see for himself:
see, in this instance, the breadth and the fineness, the beauty and
the dread, the baseness and the grandeur, the sensuality and the
spirituality, working together for the effect of a novel unequalled
for scope and for grasp in our fiction.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="5" id="d9">
<head>V</head>
<p>Fine work we have enough of and to spare in our fiction.  No
one can say it is wanting in subtlety of motive and delicate grace
of form.  But something still was lacking, something that was not
merely the word but the deed of commensurateness.  Perhaps, after
all, those who have demanded Continentality of American literature
had some reason in their folly.  One thinks so, when one considers
work like Norris's, and finds it so vast in scope while so fine and
beautiful in detail.  Hugeness was probably what those poor fellows
were wanting when they asked for Continentality; and from any fit
response that has come from them one might well fancy them dismayed
and puzzled to have been given greatness instead.  But
Continentality he also gave them.
</p><p>His last book is a fragment, a part of a greater work, but it
is a mighty fragment, and it has its completeness.  In any time but
this, when the air is filled with the fizz and sputter of a
thousand pin-wheels, the descent of such a massive aerolite as "The
Octopus" would have stirred all men's wonder, but its light to most
eyes appears to have seemed of one quality with those cheap
explosives which all the publishing houses are setting off, and
advertising as meteoric.  If the time will still come for
acknowledgment of its greatness, it will not be the time for him
who put his heart and soul into it.  That is the pity, but that in
the human condition is what cannot be helped.  We are here to do
something, we <pb n="777"/>  do not know why; we think it is for
ourselves, but it is for almost anyone but ourselves.  If it is
great, some one else shall get the good of it, and the doer shall
get the glory too late; if it is mean, the doer shall have the
glory, but who shall have the good?  This would not be so bad if
there were life long enough for the processes of art; if the artist
could outlive the doubt and the delay into which every great work
of art seems necessarily to plunge the world anew, after all its
experience of great work.
</p><p>I am not saying, I hope, that Frank Norris had not his
success, but only that he had not success enough, the success which
he would have had if he had lived, and which will still be his too
late.  The two novels he has left behind him are sufficient for his
fame, but though they have their completeness and their adequacy,
one cannot help thinking of the series of their like that is now
lost to us.  It is Aladdin's palace, and yet,
<q><lg type="verse"><l>"The unfinished window in Aladdin's palace</l>
<l rend="indent">Unfinished must remain,"</l></lg></q>
and we never can look upon it without an ache of longing and
regret.
</p><p>Personally, the young novelist gave one the impression of
strength and courage that would hold out to all lengths.  Health
was in him always as it never was in that other rare talent of ours
with whom I associate him in my sense of the irretrievable, the
irreparable.  I never met him but he made me feel that he could do
it, the thing he meant to do, and do it robustly and quietly,
without the tremor of "those electrical nerves" which imparted
itself from the presence of Stephen Crane.  With him my last talk
of the right way and the true way of doing things was saddened by
the confession of his belief that we were soon to be overwhelmed by
the rising tide of romanticism, whose crazy rote he heard afar, and
expected with the resignation which the sick experience with all
things.  But Norris heard nothing, or seemed to hear nothing, but
the full music of his own aspiration, the rich diapason of purposes
securely shaping themselves in performance.
</p><p>Who shall inherit these, and carry forward work so instinct
with the Continent as his?  Probably, no one; and yet good work
shall not fail us, manly work, great work.  One need not be
overhopeful to be certain of this.  Bad work, false, silly,
ludicrous <pb n="778"/>  work, we shall always have, for the most of those
who read are so, as well as the most of those who write; and yet
there shall be here and there one to see the varying sides of our
manifold life truly and to say what he sees.  When I think of Mr.
Brand Whitlock and his novel of "The Thirteenth District," which
has embodied the very spirit of American politics as American
politicians know them in all the Congressional districts; when I
think of the author of "The Spenders," so wholly good in one half
that one forgets the other half is only half good; when I think of
such work as Mr. William Allen White's, Mr. Robert Herrick's, Mr.
Will Payne's&mdash;all these among the younger men&mdash;it is certainly not
to despair because we shall have no such work as Frank Norris's
from them.  They, and the like of them, will do their good work as
he did his.
</p><signed>
W. D. HOWELLS.</signed>

</div2>
	</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
