<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="HowTrue"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="HowTrue">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The True Story of the Wallowa Campaign</title>
<title type="sort">true story of the wallowa campaign</title>
<author>Howard, General O. O.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>Text prepared by the 1997-98 J. Wallace Sieg Graduate Fellow Lisa Spiro
for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">31</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">HowTrue</idno>
<date value="1998">1998</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1998 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476091</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The True Story of the Wallowa Campaign</title>
<title level="j">North American Review, vol. 129</title>
<title type="sort">true story of the wallowa campaign</title>
<author>General O. O. Howard, U.S. Army</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>D. Appleton and Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1879-07">1879 July</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: University of Virginia Library call number AP 2 .N7 vol. 129</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1879">1879</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1998-06">June 1998</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Lisa Spiro, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> <pb n="53"/><head>
IV.
<lb/>
THE TRUE STORY OF THE WALLOWA
CAMPAIGN.
</head>

<p>ON reading in the "North American Review" for April the
article entitled "An Indian's View of Indian Affairs," I was so
pleased with Joseph's statement &mdash; necessarily <hi rend="italic">ex parte</hi>
though it was, and naturally inspired by resentment toward me as a
supposed enemy &mdash; that at first I had no purpose of making a
rejoinder.  But when I saw in the "Army and Navy Journal" long
passages quoted from Joseph's tale, which appeared to reflect
unfavorably upon my official conduct, to lay upon me the blame of
the atrocious murders committed by the Indians, and to convict me
of glaring faults where I had deemed myself worthy only of
commendation, I addressed to the editor of that journal a
communication (which has been published) correcting
misstatements, and briefly setting forth the facts of the case.
</p><p>Now I find Eastern newspapers insisting that, if Joseph's
statements are borne out by the facts of history, General Howard
should be removed from his department.
</p><p>May I say that I am profoundly concerned about this subject of
the management of Indian affairs; and, if I am an obstacle in the
way of order, justice, obedience to law, and the advancement of
civilization among the Indians, I deserve to be deprived of
command?  But is it not a strange idea that the army commander
who is subject to the requisition of the Indian Department, of which
he forms no part; who on that requisition is ordered to use the force
under his command to stop citizens and Indians in armed array
against each other from fighting; to put bands of roaming and
nomadic Indians on reservations set apart for them; and, finally, to
restore the peace where fiendish murders have already begun &mdash; is it
not a strange idea that he should be held accountable for all the

   <pb n="54"/>

mischief that has been brewing; for the depredations of the nomads,
for the quarrels between the citizens and Indians; for the
dispositions of the Indian Department, and for the horrid murders
that inaugurate the war?  This is a very unfair distribution of power
and accountability.  If I had had the power and the management
entirely in my hands, I believe I could have healed that old sore, and
established peace and amity with Joseph's Indians.  It could only
have been done, first, by a retrocession of Wallowa (already
belonging to Oregon) to the United States, and then setting that
country apart for ever for the Indians without the retention of any
Government authority whatever; and, second, by the removal
therefrom of every white settler, making to each a proper
remuneration for his land and improvements.  But this power I did
not have, and the Indian management did not belong to my
department.
</p><p>There were two ways in which I was brought into this matter
as department commander: first, by the yearly appeal of the
scattered white people for protection against the depredations,
misconduct, and threats of the Indians; these appeals, coming from
an alarmed population and taking official form, had to be met.
Second, the requisition of the Indian Department through its several
channels, resulting in positive military orders.
</p><p>Now permit me to present a few simple facts which will show
whether, in manner or matter, I have failed to meet the requirements
of the situation.  These facts I wrote and published when the whole
subject was fresh in memory, and will endeavor before long to place
again at the disposal of the public, in book form, with a more
complete account of this notable Indian war.
</p><p>Governor Stevens and Joel Palmer, in 1855, made a treaty with
the Nez Perc&eacute;s, including all the different bands.  Joseph's
band were parties to the treaty, and Joseph's father signed it.  This
ceded and relinquished to the United States all land that the Nez
Perc&eacute;s claimed outside of the limits then fixed and agreed
upon.
</p><p>This treaty, be it remembered, included Wallowa and Imnaha
Valleys.  In 1863 the United States, by their commissioners, made
another treaty with the Nez Perc&eacute;s &mdash; fifty-one chiefs
participating.  This treaty reduced the limits so as to constitute the
reservation in Lapwai, as it now is, and ceded all the land outside to
the United States.  Wallowa and Imnaha were left out.
</p><p>Joseph's band, and a few other bands, now known as the
Salmon River or White Bird's band, lived east of the reservation,
and the

   <pb n="55"/>

Palouse or Hush-hush-cute's band, west of the same.  These, with a
few more, on and off the reserve, constitute what are called "non-treaties."  The vast majority who made the treaty have kept good
faith, and are called "treaty Indians."  James Lawyer, the present
head chief, is an excellent man; dresses as a white man, and has a
good house and farm.  Now, notice the difference: Joseph says,
"Governor Stevens urged my father to sign the treaty (1855), but he
refused"; and then he goes on to give us a graphic account of this
refusal and its consequences.  He "cautioned his people to take no
presents."  He "was invited to many councils, and they tried hard to
make him sign the treaty, but he was firm as the rock and would not
sign away his home," etc.  Now, all this is very fine; yet his father
did sign the treaty.  His name is the third on the list, and there are
eleven white witnesses, besides the makers of the instrument.
</p><p>Governor Grover says in his message, "The reservation named
became the common property of the whole tribe."  Joseph and his
band acknowledged these conclusions also, by accepting the benefit
of the treaty of 1855.
</p><p>Such is the record of history, in precise contradiction to Young
Joseph's traditional statement.  But he states truly the <hi rend="italic">claim</hi>
(based on the treaty of 1863) of the United States to Wallowa, and
Joseph's constant <hi rend="italic">demurrer</hi> thereto.  The underlying cause of
all the troubles, finally resulting in the war, is Joseph's assumption
that, as sub-chief, he is not bound by this last treaty, inasmuch as he
has ever refused to sign it.  This disputed territory was finally
surveyed, and is within the limits of Oregon.  Stockmen began to
pasture portions of it, and enterprising frontiersmen settled in and
near one of the valleys.  They took up land and gained their titles to
homesteads in the usual way.  Again and again the Government
tried to convince the Indians that they all had common right inside
of the Lapwai Reserve, but that "the Indian title was extinguished"
for those Oregon lands.
</p><p>Nothing but restlessness and dissatisfaction resulted for a
while &mdash; no serious outbreak, though the quarrels with settlers,
especially in the Salmon River country, were perpetual, several
times resulting in loss of life.
</p><p>Again, the account of Joseph concerning his father's death, and
his home, is beautiful and quite affecting.  I dislike to mar the effect
of it, yet it is a known fact that when the United States agents
sought to make some definite arrangement, proposing to give this

   <pb n="56"/>

land to the tribe as a <hi rend="italic">home</hi>, the offer was refused.  The
Governor of Oregon writes in 1873: "This small band wish the
possession of this large section of Oregon simply to gratify a wild,
roaming disposition, and <hi rend="italic">not for a home</hi>."  And even up to
the last peace council the objection was not that "you take from us
our <hi rend="italic">home"</hi> (for they intended to live part of the year with the
remainder of the tribe), but "you take away our liberty; fix bounds
to our habitation, and give law to us.  The land is ours, and not
yours."
</p><p>Joseph's pictures of frontier troubles between whites and Indians
are graphic and true.  The killing of a member of his tribe by a white
man he refers to.  This came near causing an outbreak.  The troops
intervened between the settlers and the Indians and the latter
quieted down.  But the slow process of the civil law, and the
prejudice against Indians in all frontier courts, almost invariably
prevent the punishment of crimes against Indians.  I did what I
could to further the ends of justice, in bringing the guilty to trial; but
my efforts in this case resulted in nothing.  The Indian has a
complaint against us (army and agents) because we can and do
punish <hi rend="italic">him</hi>, but do not and can not punish <hi rend="italic">white
men</hi> who steal the Indian's property and take life.
</p><p>"But no war was made on my people until General Howard
came to our country two years ago," etc.  This has all the summary
brevity of Shakespeare's history, but is not more accurate.  The facts
are, that I had been in command of the department since the fall of
1874, and had had many dealings with Joseph and his people.
</p><p>The "non-treaties" became suspiciously restless during the
Modoc troubles.  This was quieted by my worthy predecessor, by
sending a considerable force among them just after the Modoc war.
</p><p>General Davis, speaking of a large gathering of Indians that
boded difficulty at the Wee-ipe, says: "The troops did not interfere
with the council (twelve hundred Indians), but their presence there
for about ten days had the effect to disperse it.  General
dissatisfaction, however, seemed to prevail among the 'non-treaty
Nez Perc&eacute;s.'  This was particularly the case with Joseph's
band, the claimants of Wallowa Valley."
</p><p>Again, the <hi rend="italic">same year</hi> (1874), these Indians were so
restless and threatening that Major John Green, First Cavalry, was
sent to Wallowa Valley with two companies, and remained till the
Indians left for their winter quarters.
</p><p>The next year (1875) I say in my report: "The troubles at Lapwai

   <pb n="57"/>


and Wallowa Valley have not thus far resulted in bloodshed;
but it has been prevented by great carefulness and provision on the
part of Government agents."
</p><p>The year following (1876) my report goes into the trouble
quite at length, mentioning the grave fact that "an Indian was killed
by a white man in a dispute concerning some stock," and winds up
with these words: "And renew my recommendation of a
Commission to hear and settle the whole matter, before war is even
thought of."  The Commission was at last ordered, but not till after
blood had been shed &mdash; not till after the Indians had stood up in
battle array against armed citizens in Wallowa; and a conflict was
averted only by the intervention of regular troops.  The Commission
came, held its memorable sessions at Lapwai in November of 1876,
and labored hard and long to get the consent of the disaffected
"non-treaty Indians" to some measures of adjustment.
</p><p>Here are a few of the facts developed by this Commission:
"The Dreamers, among other pernicious doctrines, teach that the
earth being created by God complete, should not be disturbed by
man; and that any cultivation of the soil or other improvements to
interfere with its natural productions; any voluntary submission to
the control of the Government; any improvement in the way of
schools, churches, etc., are crimes from which they shrink.  This
fanaticism is kept alive by the superstition of these Dreamers, who
industriously teach that if they continue steadfast in their present
belief a leader will be raised up (in the East) who will restore all the
dead Indians to life, who will unite with them in expelling the
whites from their country, when they will again enter upon and
repossess the lands of their ancestors.
</p><p>"Influenced by such belief, Joseph and his band firmly
declined to enter into any negotiations, or make any arrangements
that looked to a final settlement of the question pending between
him and the Government; . . . yet, in view of the fact that these
Indians do not claim simply this [rights of occupancy], but set up an
absolute title to the lands, an absolute and independent sovereignty,
and refuse even to be limited in their claim and control, necessity,
humanity, and good sense constrain the Covernment to set metes
and bounds and give regulations to these non-treaty Indians. . . .
And if the principle usually applied by the Government, of holding
that the Indians with whom they have treaties are bound by
majorities, is here applied, Joseph should be required to live within
the limits of the present reservation."

   <pb n="58"/>

</p><p>The Commission, though firm and strong in the expression of
its opinion, was very patient with and kind to the Indians.  I was a
member of this Commission, and earnestly desired peace.  I took
Joseph's brother by himself and showed him how much it would be
for the Indians' advantage to come to some settlement, and spent a
long time giving him and his brother, in the kindest manner, the
benefit of my counsel.  They appeared at one time almost on the
point of yielding, but bad advice intervened to renew the Dreamer
sophistry.  The Commission promised that they should annually
visit Wallowa, and so recommended.  But here are a few closing
words: "If these Indians overrun land belonging to the whites and
commit depredations on their property, disturb the peace by threats
or otherwise, or commit any other overt acts of hostility, we
recommend the employment of sufficient force to bring them into
subjection, and to place them upon the Nez Perc&eacute;
reservation.  The Indian agent at Lapwai should be fully instructed
to carry into execution these suggestions, relying at all times upon
the department commander for aid when necessary."
</p><p>Now, there was nothing like precipitancy in all this; so that the
wonderfully abrupt advent of General Howard, with a fear of the
laughter of white men in his heart, and a threat of violence on his
tongue, is all a fiction.
</p><p>Doubtless Joseph was told what the Commission had
recommended, "that Wallowa should be held by military
occupation," to <hi rend="italic">prevent</hi> and not to make war, and that I
should have the work to do.
</p><p>This Commission's report was approved at Washington.  The
Indian Agent, Mr. Monteith, did all that lay in his power to carry out
the recommendations at first without military aid.
</p><p>The Indians called me to an interview first at Walla Walla,
afterward at Lapwai.  At Walla Walla the talk with Joseph's brother,
Ollicut, was exceedingly pleasant.  I write of it, "The old Medicineman
looks happy, and Ollicut believes we shall have no trouble. . . .
</p><p>I made the appointment for Lapwai in twelve days, but I went
to Lewiston immediately to meet the officers of Fort Lapwai, and
Indian Agent Monteith, to read to them carefully the full
instructions from the Honorable Secretary of War, General
Sherman, and the commanding general of the military division, in
relation especially to the agency the military was to have in placing
the Indians upon the reservations."

   <pb n="59"/>

</p><p>I made a visit to Wallula, and then returned by stage to meet
the non-treaties at Lapwai the 3d of May (1877).  This is the council
to which Joseph invited me, and not I him, as he alleges.
</p><p>Before giving points in this interview in answer to Joseph's
statements, I must state that Mr. Monteith, Indian Agent, had been
instructed by his chief at Washington to bring the "non-treaty Nez
Perc&eacute;s" upon their reservation.  He had made his official
demand upon me.  I had been positively ordered to give the
essential aid.  There was now nothing left to parley about, yet, to
please the Indians, I had promised to meet them again, and I did.
</p><p>These picturesque people came in sight, after keeping us
waiting long enough for effect.  They drew near to the hollow
square of the post and in sight of us, the small company to be
interviewed.  They struck up their song.  They were not armed,
except with a few tomahawk-pipes "that could be smoked with the
peaceful tobacco or penetrate the skull-bone of an enemy, at the
will of the holder"; yet somehow this wild song produces a strange
effect.  Our ladies, thinking it a war-song, ask with some show of
trepidation, "Do you think Joseph means to fight?"  The Indians
sweep around outside the fence and make the entire circuit, still
keeping up the song as they ride, the buildings breaking the refrain
into irregular bubblings of sound till the ceremony was completed.
</p><p>After all had finally gathered at the tent, and Father Cataldo
had opened by a prayer in the Nez Perc&eacute; language, I turned
to Joseph and said through Mr. Whitman (the interpreter): "I heard
from your brother Ollicut, twelve days ago at Walla Walla, that you
wished to see me.  I am now here to listen to what you have to say."
</p><p>Joseph then told me of other Indians coming, and said, "You
must not be in a hurry to go till all get in, to have a talk."
</p><p>I replied: "Mr. Monteith, the Indian Agent, and I have our
instructions from Washington.  They send us to your people.  If you
decide at once to comply with the wishes of the Government, you
can have the first pick of vacant land.  We will wait for White Bird
if you desire it.  Instructions to him are the same as to you.  He can
take his turn."  And an old Dreamer intimating that they wished a
long talk, the answer is: "Mr. Monteith and I wish to hear what you
have to say, whatever time it may take; but you may as well know at
the outset that, in any event, the Indians must obey the orders of the
Government of the United States."
</p><p>Mr. Monteith then read his instructions from the Indian
Bureau

   <pb n="60"/>

to the Indians, and had them carefully interpreted to them, and also
explained how he had already informed them of the orders to come
on the reservation through Reuben (then head-chief at Lapwai), and
that they had scorned his message.  "Now you <hi rend="italic">must</hi> come,
and there is no getting out of it.  Your Indians, and White Bird's, can
pick up your horses and cattle and come on the reservation. . . .
General Howard will stay till matters are settled."
</p><p>Ollicut replied at length, objecting to considering matters
settled.
</p><p>I rejoined: "Joseph, the agent Mr. Monteith, and myself are
under the same Government.  What it commands us to do, that we
must do.  The Indians are to come on the reservation first;
<hi rend="italic">then</hi> they may have privileges, as the agent has shown, to
hunt and to fish in the Imnaha Valley.  If the Indians hesitate to
come to the reservation, the Government directs that soldiers be
used to bring them hither.  Joseph and Ollicut know that we are
friends to them, and that if they comply there will be no trouble."
</p><p>Everybody at this council was in good humor except two old
Dreamers who tried to make a disturbance.  I told them pointedly to
give good advice.  My manner I will not judge of.  It is my usual
manner, proceeding from the kindest of feelings, and from an
endeavor to behave as a gentleman to the weakest or most ignorant
human being.  The Indians, excepting the two I have named, made
no angry remarks.  We shook hands and separated, to wait as Joseph
had requested.
</p><p>Joseph has turned this right about in the article published in
the "Review," where it is stated that he said, "I am ready to talk to-day,"
 etc. (page 421), and that General Howard would not.  His
account runs two days' interviews into one.  Joseph never made that
interesting speech ending with "I do not believe that the Great Spirit
Chief gave one kind of men the right to tell another kind of men
what they must do."  And I did never reply, "You want to dictate to
me, do you?"  We always treated each other with the most marked
courtesy.
</p><p>On May 4th Joseph made a brief speech: "This is White Bird; I
spoke to you of him; this is the first time he has seen you and you
him.  I want him and his Indians to understand what has been said
to us."
</p><p>White Bird was a demure-looking Indian, about five feet eight
inches in height.  His face assumed the condition of impassibility

   <pb n="61"/>

while in council; he kept his ceremonial hat on, and placed a large
eagle's wing in front of his eyes and nose.
</p><p>The sub-chief and Dreamer, Too-hool-hool-suit, was
broad-shouldered, deep-chested, thick-necked, five feet ten in height, had
a deep, guttural voice, and betrayed in every word a strong and
settled hatred of all Caucasians.  This man the Indians now put
forward to speak for them &mdash; not that they had already decided to
endorse his sentiments, but because he always counseled war: they
evidently desired to see what effect his public utterance would
produce upon us.
</p><p>Now, instead of the mild and respectful speech attributed to
this surly Indian by Joseph, a speech that was followed by my
causeless loss of temper, Mr. Monteith and I heard him patiently,
for quite a length of time, asserting his independence and uttering
rebellious speeches against the Washington authority.  We replied
firmly and kindly as before, explaining everything and showing the
imperative nature of our instructions.
</p><p>The White-Bird Indians were very tired that day, and Joseph
asked again for delay.  The record reads: "Let the Indians take time;
let them wait till Monday morning, and meanwhile talk among
themselves.  So, with pleasant faces and cordial handshaking, the
second interview broke up."
</p><p>How different this is from Joseph's account of the affair, in
which he condenses the whole narrative into the arrest of
Too-hool-hool-suit upon his first appearance, and without provocation.
</p><p>Now (Monday, May 7th) we came together again.  The "non-treaties"
had received large accessions.  The display (previous to
seating themselves) gave them great boldness.  Our garrison was but
a handful, and the manner of the Indians was now defiant.  Mr.
Monteith began in the kindest manner to show the Indians that their
religion would not be interfered with, nor their ceremonies, unless
the peace was disturbed by excessive drumming.
</p><p>Then Too-hool-hool-suit began in the most offensive style.
We listened to the oft-repeated Dreamer nonsense with no
impatience, till finally he accused us of speaking untruthfully about
the chieftainship of the earth.
</p><p>I thought the time had come to check his tirade.  I was not in
the least angry, if I recall my mood with accuracy, did not lose my
temper, but I did assume a severity of tone sufficient to show that I
understood the drift of the council, and that we were not to be
intimidated.  My first words were: "I do not want to interfere

   <pb n="62"/>

with your religion, but you must talk about practicable things.
Twenty times over I hear that the earth is your mother, and about
the chieftainship of the earth; I want to hear it no more, but to come
to business at once."
</p><p>He then talked against the treaty Indians, and said they had no
law, or their law was born of to-day; then against us white people
for attempting to divide the earth, and defiantly asking, "What do
you mean?"
</p><p>Mr. Monteith explained: "The law is, you must come to the
reservation.  The law is made in Washington; we don't make it."
Then, again, the Dreamer goes over the same ground and becomes
fiercer and fiercer.  The crowd of Indians are becoming excited, and
I saw that I must act, and that very promptly.  The record is: "The
rough old fellow, in his most provoking tone, says something in a
short sentence, looking fiercely at me.  The interpreter quickly says:
'He demands what person pretends to divide the land and put me on
it?'  In the most decided voice I said: 'I am the man; I stand here for
the President, and there is no spirit, good or bad, that will hinder
me.  My orders are plain and will be executed.  I hoped that the
Indians had good sense enough to make me their friend and not
their enemy.'"
</p><p>From various unmistakable signs (I am no novice with
Indians) I saw that immediate trouble was at hand.  Joseph, White
Bird, and Looking-Glass endorsed and encouraged this malcontent.
I must somehow put a wedge between them; so I turned to this
Dreamer and said, "Then you do not propose to comply with the
orders of the Government?"
</p><p>After considerable more growling and impudence of manner,
he answered with additional fierceness, "The Indians may do what
they like, but I am not going on the reservation."  After telling the
Indians that this bad advice would be their ruin, I asked the chiefs to
go with me to look at their land.  "The old man shall not go.  I will
leave him with Colonel Perry."  He says, "Do you want to scare me
with reference to my body?"  I said, "I will leave your body with
Colonel Perry."  I then arose and led him out of the council, and
gave him into the charge of Colonel Perry.
</p><p>The whole tone of the Indians now changed, and they readily
agreed to go with me to look at their new homes.  They may have
thought of killing me then and there; but a bold, quick, unexpected
action will often save you in extreme peril.  Joseph's manner was
never defiant.  He rode with me to look at what Mr.

   <pb n="63"/>

Monteith had intended for him.  A few Indians and some white
sojourners would have to remove to other lands, to put Joseph's
people together.  We lunched together at Mr. Colwell's, and then
returned to the fort.  White Bird and Looking-Glass appeared to be
happy and contented.  They pleaded for the release of Too-hool-hool-suit; but I told them to wait till I had shown them their land
which Mr. Monteith would designate.  The next day we rode to
Kamiah (sixty-five miles), and the next went to the lands intended.
White Bird picked his near Looking-Glass's farms, and then we
returned to Kamiah, and the next day following to Lapwai.
</p><p>Too-hool-hool-suit was released on the pledge of Looking-Glass
and White Bird, and on his own earnest promise to behave
better and give good advice.
</p><p>Now we have our final interview, May 14th.  Joseph
concluded to go to near Kamiah with the rest.  The promises were
put in writing.  No objection was made to thirty days, except by
Hush-hush-cute.  I gave him thirty-five days, because he had not
had so early notice of removal.
</p><p>I withheld the protection papers from Hush-hush-cute because
of something that he said, which indicated that he was attempting to
conceal his intentions.  So I left his papers with the agent.  There
was general joy among treaty Indians, non-treaty Indians, and
whites, at the peaceful outcome of the councils, and I returned to
Portland.
</p><p>This idea that General Howard caused the war is an after
thought.
</p><p>That story that Joseph asked me for more time is not true.
That I sent orders to the soldiers to drive them out on their return to
Wallowa is of course untrue; that would have disconcerted
everything: on the contrary, the officers and soldiers were simply to
occupy Wallowa in the interest of peace, and not use constraint
unless forced to do so.
</p><p>The statements with reference to our losses and those of the
Indians are all wrong, and Joseph does not tell how his own Indians,
White Bird and his followers, who treacherously escaped, after the
terms of the surrender had been agreed upon between us at General
Miles's battle-field, being permitted by himself, did in fact utterly
break and make void the said terms of surrender.
</p><p>These Indians were to return to Idaho, not because of any
promise, but because of General McDowell's orders requiring all the
Nez Perc&eacute; prisoners to be kept in my department.  This
order was changed by General Sherman, or at Washington.

   <pb n="64"/>

</p><p>Should the Indians return to the scene of their horrid outrages,
they could have no peace.  There is not an Indian there now.  The
Bitter Root country puts them at the throat of our Eastern
connections, and makes another war very probable.
</p><p>Let them settle down, and keep quiet, in the Indian Territory,
as the Modocs have done, and they will thrive as they do.
</p>
    <closer>
<signed><name type="person">O. O. HOWARD.
</name>
</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

