<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="JewFore"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>


<TEI.2 id="JewFore">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Foreigner</title>
<title type="sort">foreigner</title>
<author>Jewett, Sarah Orne</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">60</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">JewFore</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476113</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Foreigner</title>
<title type="sort">foreigner</title>
<author>Sarah Orne Jewett</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly (Houghton, Mifflin, and Company)</publisher>
<pubPlace>Cambridge, Mass</pubPlace>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 86</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Jewett, Sarah Orne.  "The Foreigner."  <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 86 (1900): 152-167.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions
for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction ; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-07">July 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header; Tagged text with TEI2-compatible SGML; Parsed text against
"teilite" dtd; All other major changes</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">


<body id="d2">

<div1 type="chapter" n="1" id="d3"><pb n="152"/><head>I</head>

<p>ONE evening, at the end of August, in Dunnet Landing, I heard
Mrs. Todd's firm footstep crossing the small front entry outside my
door, and her conventional cough which served as a herald's
trumpet, or a plain New England knock, in the harmony of our
fellowship.
</p><p>"Oh, please come in!" I cried, for it had been so still in the
house that I supposed my friend and hostess had gone to see one of
her neighbors.  The first cold northeasterly storm of the season
was blowing hard outside.  Now and then there was a dash of great
raindrops and a flick of wet lilac leaves against the window, but
I could hear that the sea was already stirred to its dark depths,
and the great rollers were coming in heavily against the shore.
One might well believe that Summer was coming to a sad end that
night, in the darkness and rain and sudden access of autumnal cold.
It seemed as if there must be danger offshore among the outer
islands.
</p><p>"Oh, there!" exclaimed Mrs. Todd, as she entered.  "I know
nothing ain't ever happened out to Green Island since the world
began, but I always do worry about mother in these great gales.
You know those tidal waves occur sometimes down to the West Indies,
and I get dwellin' on 'em so I can't set still in my chair, not
knit a common row to a stocking.  William might get mooning, out in
his small bo't, and not observe how the sea was making, an' meet
with some accident.  Yes, I thought i'd come in and set with you if
you wa'n't busy.  No, I never feel any concern about 'em in winter
'cause then they're prepared, and all ashore and everything snug.
William ought to keep help, as I tell him; yes, he ought to keep
help."
</p><p>I hastened to reassure my anxious guest by saying that Elijah
Tilley had told me in the afternoon, when I came along the shore
past the fish houses, that Johnny Bowden and the Captain were out
at Green Island; he had seen them beating up the bay, and thought
they must have put into Burnt Island cove, but one of the
lobstermen brought word later that he saw them hauling out at Green
Island as he came by, and Captain Bowden pointed ashore and shook
his head to say that he did not mean to try to get in.  "The old
Miranda just managed it, but she will have to stay at home a day or
two and put new patches in her sail," I ended, not without pride in
so much circumstantial evidence.
</p><p>Mrs. Todd was alert in a moment.  "Then they'll all have a
very pleasant evening," she assured me, apparently dismissing all
fears of tidal waves and other sea-going disasters.  "I was urging
Alick Bowden to go ashore some day and see mother before cold
weather.  He's her own nephew; she sets a great deal by him.  And
Johnny's a great chum o' William's; don't you know the first day we
had Johnny out 'long of us, he took an' give William his money to
keep for him that he'd been a-savin', and William showed it to me
an' was so affected, I thought he was goin' to shed tears?  'Twas
a dollar an' eighty cents; yes, they'll have a beautiful evenin'
all together, and like's not the sea'll be flat as a doorstep come
morning."
</p><p>I had drawn a large wooden rocking-chair before the fire, and
Mrs. Todd was sitting there jogging herself a little, knitting
fast, and wonderfully placid of countenance.  There came a fresh
gust of wind and rain, and we could feel the small wooden house
rock and hear it creak as if it were a ship at sea.
</p><p>"Lord, hear the great breakers!" ex-<pb n="153"/> claimed Mrs. Todd.
"How they pound!&mdash;there, there!  I always run of an idea that the
sea knows anger these nights and gets full o' fight.  I can hear
the rote o' them old black ledges way down the thoroughfare.  Calls
up all those stormy verses in the Book o' Psalms; David he knew how
old sea-goin' folks have to quake at the heart."
</p><p>I thought as I had never thought before of such anxieties.
The families of sailors and coastwise adventurers by sea must
always be worrying about somebody, this side of the world or the
other.  There was hardly one of Mrs. Todd's elder acquaintances,
men or women, who had not at some time or other made a sea voyage,
and there was often no news until the voyagers themselves came back
to bring it.
</p><p>"There's a roaring high overhead, and a roaring in the deep
sea," said Mrs. Todd solemnly, "and they battle together nights
like this.  No, I couldn't sleep; some women folks always goes
right to bed an' to sleep, so's to forget, but 'taint my way.
Well, it's a blessin' we don't all feel alike; there's hardly any
of our folks at sea to worry about, nowadays, but I can't help my
feelin's, an' I got thinking of mother all alone, if William had
happened to be out lobsterin' and couldn't make the cove gettin'
back."
</p><p>"They will have a pleasant evening," I repeated.  "Captain
Bowden is the best of good company."
</p><p>"Mother'll make him some pancakes for his supper, like's not,"
said Mrs. Todd, clicking her knitting needles and giving a pull at
her yarn.  Just then the old cat pushed open the unlatched door and
came straight toward her mistress's lap.  She was regarded severely
as she stepped about and turned on the broad expanse, and then made
herself into a round cushion of fur, but was not openly admonished.
There was another great blast of wind overhead, and a puff of smoke
came down the chimney.
</p><p>"This makes me think o' the night Mis' Cap'n Tolland died,"
said Mrs. Todd, half to herself.  "Folks used to say these gales
only blew when somebody's a-dyin', or the devil was a-comin' for
his own, but the worst man I ever knew died a real pretty mornin'
in June."
</p><p>"You have never told me any ghost stories," said I; and such
was the gloomy weather and the influence of the night that I was
instantly filled with reluctance to have this suggestion followed.
I had not chosen the best of moments; just before I spoke we had
begun to feel as cheerful as possible.  Mrs. Todd glanced
doubtfully at the cat and then at me, with a strange absent look,
and I was really afraid that she was going to tell me something
that would haunt my thoughts on every dark stormy night as long as
I lived.
</p><p>"Never mind now; tell me to-morrow by daylight, Mrs. Todd," I
hastened to say, but she still looked at me full of doubt and
deliberation.
</p><p>"Ghost stories!" she answered.  "Yes, I don't know but I've
heard a plenty of 'em first an' last.  I was just sayin' to myself
that this is like the night Mis' Cap'n Tolland died.  'Twas the
great line storm in September all of thirty, or maybe forty, year
ago.  I ain't one that keeps much account o' time."
</p><p>"Tolland?  That's a name I have never heard in Dunnet," I
said.
</p><p>"Then you haven't looked well about the old part o' the
buryin' ground, no'theast corner," replied Mrs. Todd.  "All their
women folks lies there; the sea's got most o' the men.  They were
a known family o' shipmasters in early times.  Mother had a mate,
Ellen Tolland, that she mourns to this day; died right in her bloom
with quick consumption, but the rest o' that family was all boys
but one, and older than she, an' they lived hard seafarin' lives
an' all died hard.  They were called very smart seamen.  I've heard
that when the
<pb n="154"/>  youngest went into one o' the old shippin'
houses in Boston, the head o' the firm called out to him: 'Did you
say Tolland from Dunnet?  That's recommendation enough for any
vessel!'  There was some o' them old shipmasters as tough as iron,
an' they had the name o' usin' their crews very severe, but there
wa'n't a man that wouldn't rather sign with 'em an' take his
chances, than with the slack ones that didn't know how to meet
accidents."



</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="2" id="d4"><head>II</head>

<p>There was so long a pause, and Mrs. Todd still looked so
absent-minded, that I was afraid she and the cat were growing
drowsy together before the fire, and I should have no reminiscences
at all.  The wind struck the house again, so that we both started
in our chairs and Mrs. Todd gave a curious, startled look at me.
The cat lifted her head and listened too, in the silence that
followed, while after the wind sank we were more conscious than
ever of the awful roar of the sea.  The house jarred now and then,
in a strange, disturbing way.
</p><p>"Yes, they'll have a beautiful evening out to the island,"
said Mrs. Todd again; but she did not say it gayly.  I had not seen
her before in her weaker moments.
</p><p>"Who was Mrs. Captain Tolland?" I asked eagerly, to change the
current of our thoughts.
</p><p>"I never knew her maiden name; if I ever heard it, I've gone
an' forgot; 'twould mean nothing to me," answered Mrs. Todd.
</p><p>"She was a foreigner, an' he met with her out in the Island o'
Jamaica.  They said she'd been left a widow with property.  Land
knows what become of it; she was French born, an' her first husband
was a Portugee, or somethin'."
</p><p>I kept silence now, a poor and insufficient question being
worse than none.
</p><p>"Cap'n John Tolland was the least smartest of any of 'em, but
he was full smart enough, an' commanded a good brig at the time, in
the sugar trade; he'd taken out a cargo o' pine lumber to the
islands from somewheres up the river, an' had been headin' for home
in the port o' Kingston, an' had gone ashore that afternoon for his
papers, an' remained afterwards 'long of three friends o' his, all
shipmasters.  They was havin' their suppers together in a tavern;
'twas late in the evenin' an' they was more lively than usual, an'
felt boyish; and over opposite was another house full o' company,
real bright and pleasant lookin', with a lot o' lights, an' they
heard somebody singin' very pretty to a guitar.  They wa'n't in no
go-to-meetin' condition, an' one of 'em, he slapped the table an'
said, 'Le''s go over 'n' hear that lady sing!' an' over they all
went, good honest sailors, but three sheets in the wind, and
stepped in as if they was invited, an' made their bows inside the
door, an' asked if they could hear the music; they were all
respectable well-dressed men.  They saw the woman that had the
guitar, an' there was a company a-listenin', regular highbinders
all of 'em; an' there was a long table all spread out with big
candlesticks like little trees o' light, and a sight o' glass an'
silver ware; an' part o' the men was young officers in uniform, an'
the colored folks was steppin' round servin' 'em, an' they had the
lady singin'.  'Twas a wasteful scene, an' a loud talkin' company,
an' though they was three sheets in the wind themselves there
wa'n't one o' them cap'ns but had sense to perceive it.  The others
had pushed back their chairs, an' their decanters an' glasses was
standin' thick about, an' they was teasin' the one that was singin'
as if they'd just got her in to amuse 'em.  But they quieted down;
one o' the young officers had beautiful manners, an' invited the
four cap'ns to join 'em, very polite; 'twas a kind of public house,
and
<pb n="155"/>  after they'd all heard another song, he come to consult
with 'em whether they wouldn't git up and dance a hornpipe or
somethin' to the lady's music.
</p><p>They was all elderly men an' shipmasters, and owned property;
two of 'em was church members in good standin'," continued Mrs.
Todd loftily, "an' they wouldn't lend theirselves to no such kick-shows as that, an' spite o' bein' three sheets in the wind, as I
have once observed, they waved aside the tumblers of wine the young
officer was pourin' out for 'em so freehanded, and said they should
rather be excused.  An' when they all rose, still very dignified,
as I've been well informed, and made their partin' bows and was
goin' out, them young sports got round 'em an' tried to prevent
'em, and they had to push an' strive considerable, but out they
come.  There was this Cap'n Tolland and two Cap'n Bowdens, and the
fourth was my own father."  (Mrs. Todd spoke slowly, as if to
impress the value of her authority.)  "Two of them was very
religious, upright men, but they would have their night off
sometimes, all o' them old-fashioned cap'ns, when they was free of
business and ready to leave port.
</p><p>"An' they went back to their tavern an' got their bills paid,
an' set down kind o' mad with everybody by the front window,
mistrusting some o' their tavern charges, like's not, by that time,
an' when they got tempered down, they watched the house over
across, where the party was.
</p><p>"There was a kind of a grove o' trees between the house an'
the road, an' they heard the guitar a-goin' an' a-stoppin' short by
turns, and pretty soon somebody began to screech, an' they saw a
white dress come runnin' out through the bushes, an' tumbled over
each other in their haste to offer help; an' out she come, with the
guitar, cryin' into the street, and they just walked off four
square with her amongst 'em, down toward the wharves where they
felt more to home.  They couldn't make out at first what 'twas she
spoke,&mdash;Cap'n Lorenzo Bowden was well acquainted in Havre an'
Bordeaux, an' spoke a poor quality o' French, an' she knew a little
mite o' English, but not much; and they come somehow or other to
discern that she was in real distress.  Her husband and her
children had died o' yellow fever; they'd all come up to Kingston
from one o' the far Wind'ard Islands to get passage on a steamer to
France, an' a negro had stole their money off her husband while he
lay sick o' the fever, an' she had been befriended some, but the
folks that knew about her had died too; it had been a dreadful run
o' the fever that season, an' she fell at last to playin' an'
singin' for hire, and for what money they'd throw to her round them
harbor houses.
</p><p>'Twas a real hard case, an' when them cap'ns made out about
it, there wa'n't one that meant to take leave without helpin' of
her.  They was pretty mellow, an' whatever they might lack o'
prudence they more'n made up with charity: they didn't want to see
nobody abused, an' she was sort of a pretty woman, an' they stopped
in the street then an' there an' drew lots who should take her
aboard, bein' all bound home.  An' the lot fell to Cap'n Jonathan
Bowden who did act discouraged; his vessel had but small
accommodations, though he could stow a big freight, an' she was a
dreadful slow sailer through bein' square as a box, an' his first
wife, that was livin' then, was a dreadful jealous woman.  He threw
himself right onto the mercy o' Cap'n Tolland."
</p><p>Mrs. Todd indulged herself for a short time in a season of
calm reflection.
</p><p>"I always thought they'd have done better, and more
reasonable, to give her some money to pay her passage home to
France, or wherever she may have wanted to go," she continued.
</p><p>I nodded and looked for the rest of the story.
<pb n="156"/>
</p><p>"Father told mother," said Mrs. Todd confidentially, "that
Cap'n Jonathan Bowden an' Cap'n John Tolland had both taken a
little more than usual; I wouldn't have you think, either, that
they both wasn't the best o' men, an' they was solemn as owls, and
argued the matter between 'em, an' waved aside the other two when
they tried to put their oars in.  An' spite o' Cap'n Tolland's
bein' a settled old bachelor they fixed it that he was to take the
prize on his brig; she was a fast sailer, and there was a good
spare cabin or two where he'd sometimes carried passengers, but
he'd filled 'em with bags o' sugar on his own account an' was
loaded very heavy beside.  He said he'd shift the sugar an' get
along somehow, an' the last the other three cap'ns saw of the party
was Cap'n John handing the lady into his bo't, guitar and all, an'
off they all set tow'ds their ships with their men rowin' 'em in
the bright moonlight down to Port Royal where the anchorage was,
an' where they all lay' goin' out with the tide an' mornin' wind at
break o' day.  An' the others thought they heard music of the
guitar, two o' the bo'ts kept well together, but it may have come
from another source."
</p><p>"Well; and then?" I asked eagerly after a pause.  Mrs. Todd
was almost laughing aloud over her knitting and nodding
emphatically.  We had forgotten all about the noise of the wind and
sea.
</p><p>"Lord bless you! he come sailing into Portland with his sugar,
all in good time, an' they stepped right afore a justice o' the
peace, and Cap'n John Tolland come paradin' home to Dunnet Landin'
a married man.  He owned one o' them thin, narrow-lookin' houses
with one room each side o' the front door, and two slim black
spruces spindlin' up against the front windows to make it gloomy
inside.  There was no horse nor cattle of course, though he owned
pasture land, an' you could see rifts o' light right through the
barn as you drove by.  And there was a good excellent kitchen, but
his sister reigned over that; she had a right to two rooms, and
took the kitchen an' a bedroom that led out of it; an' bein' given
no rights in the kitchen had angered the cap'n so they weren't on
no kind o' speakin' terms.  He preferred his old brig for comfort,
but now and then, between voyages he'd come home for a few days,
just to show he was master over his part o' the house, and show
Eliza she couldn't commit no trespass.
</p><p>"They stayed a little while; 'twas pretty spring weather, an'
I used to see Cap'n John rollin' by with his arms full o' bundles
from the store, lookin' as pleased and important as a boy; an' then
they went right off to sea again, an' was gone a good many months.
Next time he left her to live there alone, after they'd stopped at
home together some weeks, an' they said she suffered from bein' at
sea, but some said that the owners wouldn't have a woman aboard.
'Twas before father was lost on that last voyage of his, an' he
said mother went up once or twice to see them.  Father said there
wa'n't a mite o' harm in her, but somehow or other a sight o'
prejudice arose; it may have been caused by the remarks of Eliza
an' her feelin's tow'ds her brother.  Even my mother had no regard
for Eliza Tolland.  But mother asked the cap'n's wife to come with
her one evenin' to a social circle that was down to the meetin'-house vestry, so she'd get acquainted a little, an' she appeared
very pretty until they started to have some singin' to the
melodeon.  Mari' Harris an' one o' the younger Caplin girls
undertook to sing a duet, an' they sort o' flatted, an' she put her
hands right up to her ears, and give a little squeal, an' went
quick as could be an' give 'em the right notes, for she could read
the music like plain print, an' made 'em try it over again.  She
was real willin' an' pleasant, but that didn't suit, an' she made
faces
<pb n="157"/>  when they got it wrong.  An' then there fell a dead
calm, an' we was all settin' round prim as dishes, an' my mother,
that never expects ill feelin', asked her if she wouldn't sing
somethin', an up she got,&mdash;poor creatur', it all seems so different
to me now,&mdash;an' sung a lovely little song standin' in the floor; it
seemed to have something gay about it that kept a-repeatin', an'
nobody could help keepin' time, an' all of a sudden she looked
round at the tables and caught up a tin plate that somebody'd
fetched a Washin'ton pie in, an' she begun to drum on it with her
fingers like one o' them tambourines, an' went right on singin'
faster an' faster, and next minute she begun to dance a little
pretty dance between the verses, just as light and pleasant as a
child.  You couldn't help seein' how pretty 'twas; we all got to
trottin' a foot, an' some o' the men clapped their hands quite
loud, a-keepin' time, 'twas so catchin', an' seemed so natural to
her.  There wa'n't one of 'em but enjoyed it; she just tried to do
her part, an' some urged her on, till she stopped with a little
twirl of her skirts an' went to her place again by mother.  And I
can see mother now, reachin' over an' smilin' an' pattin' her hand.
</p><p>"But next day there was an awful scandal goin' in the parish,
an' Mari' Harris reproached my mother to her face, an' I never
wanted to see her since, but I've had to a good many times.  I said
Mis' Tolland didn't intend no impropriety,&mdash;I reminded her of
David's dancin' before the Lord; but she said such a man as David
never would have thought o' dancin' right there in the Orthodox
vestry, and she felt I spoke with irreverence.
</p><p>"And next sunday Mis' Tolland come walkin' into our meeting,
but I must say she acted like a cat in a strange garret, and went
right out down the aisle with her head in air, from the pew Deacon
Caplin had showed her into.  'Twas just in the beginning of the
long prayer.  I wish she'd stayed through, whatever her reasons
were.  Whether she'd expected somethin' different, or misunderstood
some o' the pastor's remarks, or what 'twas, I don't really feel
able to explain, but she kind o' declared war, at least folks
thought so, an' war 'twas from that time.  I see she was cryin', or
had been, as she passed by me; perhaps bein' in meetin' was what
had power to make her feel homesick and strange.
</p><p>"Cap'n John Tolland was away fittin' out; that next week he
come home to see her and say farewell.  He was lost with his ship
in the Straits of Malacca, and she lived there alone in the old
house a few months longer till she died.  He left her well off;
'twas said he hid his money about the house and she knew where
'twas.  Oh, I expect you've heard that story told over an' over
twenty times, since you've been here at the Landin'?"
</p><p>"Never one word," I insisted.
</p><p>"It was a good while ago," explained Mrs. Todd, with
reassurance.  "Yes, it all happened a great while ago."



</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="3" id="d5"><head>III</head>

<p>At this moment, with a sudden flaw of the wind, some wet twigs
outside blew against the window panes and made a noise like a
distressed creature trying to get in.  I started with sudden fear,
and so did the cat, but Mrs. Todd knitted away and did not even
look over her shoulder.
</p><p>"She was a good-looking woman; yes, I always thought Mis'
Tolland was good-looking, though she had, as was reasonable, a sort
of foreign cast, and she spoke very broken English, no better than
a child.  She was always at work about her house, or settin' at a
front window with her sewing; she was a beautiful hand to
embroider.  Sometimes, summer evenings, when the windows was
<pb n="158"/>
open, she'd set an' drum on her guitar, but I don't know as I
ever heard her sing but once after the cap'n went away.  She
appeared very happy about havin' him, and took on dreadful at
partin' when he was down here on the wharf, going back to Portland
by boat to take ship for that last v'y'ge.  He acted kind of
ashamed, Cap'n John did; folks about here ain't so much accustomed
to show their feelings.  The whistle had blown an' they was waitin'
for him to get aboard, an' he was put to it to know what to do and
treated her very affectionate in spite of all impatience; but
mother happened to be there and she went an' spoke, and I remember
what a comfort she seemed to be.  Mis' Tolland clung to her then,
and she wouldn't give a glance after the boat when it had started,
though the captain was very eager a-wavin' to her.  She wanted
mother to come home with her an' wouldn't let go her hand, and
mother had just come in to stop all night with me an' had plenty o'
time ashore, which didn't always happen, so they walked off
together, an' 'twas some considerable time before she got back.
</p><p>"'I want you to neighbor with that poor lonesome creatur','
says mother to me, lookin' reproachful.  'She's a stranger in a
strange land,' says mother.  'I want you to make her have a sense
that somebody feels kind to her.'
</p><p>"'Shy, since that time she flaunted out o' meetin', folks have
felt she liked other ways better'n our'n,' says I.  I was provoked,
because I'd had a nice supper ready, an' mother'd let it wait so
long 'twas spoiled.  'I hope you'll like your supper!' I told her.
I was dreadful ashamed afterward of speakin' so to mother.
</p><p>"'What consequence is my supper?' says she to me; mother can
be very stern,&mdash;'or your comfort or mine, beside letting a foreign
person an' a stranger feel so desolate; she's done the best a woman
could do in her lonesome place, and she asks nothing of anybody
except a little common kindness.  Think if 'twas you in a foreign
land!'
</p><p>"And mother set down to drink her tea, an' I set down humbled
enough over by the wall to wait till she finished.  An' I did think
it all over, an' next day I never said nothin', but I put on my
bonnet, and went to see Mis' Cap'n Tolland, if 'twas only for
mother's sake.  'Twas about three quarters of a mile up the road
here, beyond the schoolhouse.  I forgot to tell you that the cap'n
had bought out his sister's right at three or four times what 'twas
worth, to save trouble, so they'd got clear o' her, an' I went
round into the side yard sort o' friendly an' sociable, rather than
stop an' deal with the knocker an' the front door.  It looked so
pleasant an' pretty I was glad I come; she had set a little table
for supper, though 'twas still early, with a white cloth on it,
right out under an old apple tree close by the house.  I noticed
'twas same as with me at home, there was only one plate.  She was
just coming out with a dish; you couldn't see the door nor the
table from the road.
</p><p>"In the few weeks she'd been there she'd got some bloomin'
pinks an' other flowers next the doorstep.  Somehow it looked as if
she'd known how to make it homelike for the cap'n.  She asked me to
set down; she was very polite, but she looked very mournful, and I
spoke of mother, an' she put down her dish and caught holt o' me
with both hands an' said my mother was an angel.  When I see the
tears in her eyes 'twas all right between us, and we were always
friendly after that, and mother had us come out and make a little
visit that summer; but she come a foreigner and she went a
foreigner, and never was anything but a stranger among our folks.
She taught me a sight o' things about herbs I never knew before nor
since; she was well acquainted with the virtues o' plants.  She'd
act awful
<pb n="159"/>  secret about some things too, an' used to work
charms for herself sometimes, an' some o' the neighbors told to an'
fro after she died that they knew enough not to provoke her, but
'twas all nonsense; 'tis the believin' in such things that causes
'em to be any harm, an' so I told 'em," confided Mrs. Todd
contemptuously.  "That first night I stopped to tea with her she'd
cooked some eggs with some herb or other sprinkled all through, and
'twas she that first led me to discern mushrooms; an' she went
right down on her knees in my garden here when she saw I had my
different officious herbs.  Yes, 'twas she that learned me the
proper use o' parsley too; she was a beautiful cook."
</p><p>Mrs. Todd stopped talking, and rose, putting the cat gently in
the chair, while she went away to get another stick of apple-tree
wood.  It was not an evening when one wished to let the fire go
down, and we had a splendid bank of bright coals.  I had always
wondered where Mrs. Todd had got such an unusual knowledge of
cookery, of the varieties of mushrooms, and the use of sorrel as a
vegetable, and other blessings of that sort.  I had long ago
learned that she could vary her omelettes like a child of France,
which was indeed a surprise in Dunnet Landing.



</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="4" id="d6"><head>IV</head>

<p>All these revelations were of the deepest interest, and I was
ready with a question as soon as Mrs. Todd came in and had well
settled the fire and herself and the cat again.
</p><p>"I wonder why she never went back to France, after she was
left alone?"
</p><p>"She come here from the French islands," explained Mrs. Todd.
"I asked her once about her folks, an' she said they were all dead;
'twas the fever took 'em.  She made this her home, lonesome as
'twas; she told me she hadn't been in France since she was 'so
small,' and measured me off a child o' six.  She'd lived right out
in the country before, so that part wa'n't unusual to her.  Oh yes,
there was something very strange about her, and she hadn't been
brought up in high circles nor nothing o' that kind.  I think she'd
been really pleased to have the cap'n marry her an' give her a good
home, after all she'd passed through, and leave her free with his
money an' all that.  An' she got over bein' so strange-looking to
me after a while, but 'twas a very singular expression: she wore a
fixed smile that wa'n't a smile; there wa'n't no light behind it,
same's a lamp can't shine if it ain't lit.  I don't know just how
to express it, 'twas a sort of made countenance."
</p><p>One could not help thinking of Sir Philip Sidney's phrase, "A
made countenance, between simpering and smiling."
</p><p>"She took it hard, havin' the captain go off on that last
voyage," Mrs. Todd went on.  "She said somethin' told her when they
was partin' that he would never come back.  He was lucky to speak
a home-bound ship this side o' the Cape o' Good Hope, an' got a
chance to send her a letter, an' that cheered her up.  You often
felt as if you was dealin' with a child's mind, for all she had so
much information that other folks hadn't.  I was a sight younger
than I be now, and she made me imagine new things, and I got
interested watchin' her an' findin' out what she had to say, but
you couldn't get to no affectionateness with her.  I used to blame
me sometimes; we used to be real good comrades goin' off for an
afternoon, but I never give her a kiss till the day she laid in her
coffin and it come to my heart there wa'n't no one else to do it."
</p><p>"And Captain Tolland died," I suggested after a while.
</p><p>"Yes, the cap'n was lost," said Mrs. Todd, "and of course word
didn't come for a good while after it happened.  The letter come
from the owners to my uncle, Cap'n Lorenzo Bowden, who was
<pb n="160"/>
in charge of Cap'n Tolland's affairs at home, and he come right up
for me an' said I must go with him to the house.  I had known what
it was to be a widow, myself, for near a year, an' there was plenty
o' widow women along this coast that the sea had made desolate, but
I never saw a heart break as I did then.
</p><p>"'Twas this way: we walked together along the road, me an'
uncle Lorenzo.  You know how it leads straight from just above the
schoolhouse to the brook bridge, and their house was just this side
o' the brook bridge on the left hand; the cellar's there now, and
a couple or three good-sized gray birches growin' in it.  And when
we come near enough I saw that the best room, this way, where she
most never set, was all lighted up, and the curtains up so that the
light shone bright down the road, and as we walked, those lights
would dazzle and dazzle in my eyes, and I could hear the guitar a-goin', an' she was singin'.  She heard our steps with her quick
ears and come running to the door with her eyes a-shinin', an' all
that set look gone out of her face, an' begun to talk French, gay
as a bird, an' shook hands and behaved very pretty an' girlish,
sayin' 'twas her fete day.  I didn't know what she meant then.  And
she had gone an' put a wreath o' flowers on her hair an' wore a
handsome gold chain that the cap'n had given her; an' there she
was, poor creatur', makin' believe have a party all alone in her
best room; 'twas prim enough to discourage a person, with too many
chairs set close to the walls, just as the cap'n's mother had left
it, but she had put sort o' long garlands on the walls, droopin'
very graceful, and a sight of green boughs in the corners, till it
looked lovely, and all lit up with a lot o' candles."
</p><p>"Oh dear!" I sighed.  "Oh, Mrs. Todd, what did you do?"
</p><p>"She beheld our countenances," answered Mrs. Todd solemnly.
"I expect they was telling everything plain enough, but Cap'n
Lorenzo spoke the sad words to her as if he had been her father;
and she wavered a minute and then over she went on the floor before
we could catch hold of her, and then we tried to bring her to
herself and failed, and at last we carried her upstairs, an' I told
uncle to run down and put out the lights, and then go fast as he
could for Mrs. Begg, being very experienced in sickness, an' he so
did.  I got off her clothes and her poor wreath, and I cried as I
done it.  We both stayed there that night, and the doctor said
'twas a shock when he come in the morning; he'd been over to Black
Island an' had to stay all night with a very sick child."
</p><p>"You said that she lived alone some time after the news came,"
I reminded Mrs. Todd then.
</p><p>"Oh yes, dear," answered my friend sadly, "but it wa'n't what
you'd call livin'; no, it was only dyin', though at a snail's pace.
She never went out again those few months, but for a while she
could manage to get about the house a little, and do what was
needed, an' I never let two days go by without seein' her or
hearin' from her.  She never took much notice as I came an' went
except to answer if I asked her anything.  Mother was the one who
gave her the only comfort."
</p><p>"What was that?" I asked softly.
</p><p>"She said that anybody in such trouble ought to see their
minister, mother did, and one day she spoke to Mis' Tolland, and
found that the poor soul had been believin' all the time that there
weren't any priests here.  We'd come to know she was a Catholic by
her beads and all, and that had set some narrow minds against her.
And mother explained it just as she would to a child; and uncle
Lorenzo sent word right off somewheres up river by a packet that
was bound up the bay, and the first o' the week a priest come by
the boat, an' uncle Lorenzo was on the wharf 'tendin' to some
business; so they just come
<pb n="161"/>  up for me, and I walked with
him to show him the house.  He was a kind-hearted old man; he
looked so benevolent an' fatherly I could ha' stopped an' told him
my own troubles; yes, I was satisfied when I first saw his face,
an' when poor Mis' Tolland beheld him enter the room, she went
right down on her knees and clasped her hands together to him as if
he'd come to save her life, and he lifted her up and blessed her,
an' I left 'em together, and slipped out into the open field and
walked there in sight so if they needed to call me, and I had my
own thoughts.  At last I saw him at the door; he had to catch the
return boat.  I meant to walk back with him and offer him some
supper, but he said no, and said he was comin' again if needed, and
signed me to go into the house to her, and shook his head in a way
that meant he understood everything.  I can see him now; he walked
with a cane, rather tired and feeble; I wished somebody would come
along, so's to carry him down to the shore.
</p><p>"Mis' Tolland looked up at me with a new look when I went in,
an' she even took hold o' my hand and kept it.  He had put some oil
on her forehead, but nothing anybody could do would keep her alive
very long; 'twas his medicine for the soul rather 'n the body.  I
helped her to bed, and next morning she couldn't get up to dress
her, and that was Monday, and she began to fail, and 'twas Friday
night she died."  (Mrs. Todd spoke with unusual haste and lack of
detail.)  "Mrs. Begg and I watched with her, and made everything
nice and proper, and after all the ill will there was a good number
gathered to the funeral.  'Twas in Reverend Mr. Bascom's day, and
he done very well in his prayer, considering he couldn't fill in
with mentioning all the near connections by name as was his habit.
He spoke very feeling about her being a stranger and twice widowed,
and all he said about her being reared among the heathen was to
observe that there might be roads leadin' up to the New Jerusalem
from various points.  I says to myself that I guessed quite a
number must ha' reached there that wa'n't able to set out from
Dunnet Landin'!"
</p><p>Mrs. Todd gave an odd little laugh as she bent toward the
firelight to pick up a dropped stitch in her knitting, and then I
heard a heartfelt sigh.
</p><p>'Twas most forty years ago," she said; "most everybody's gone
a'ready that was there that day."



</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="5" id="d7"><head>V</head>

<p>Suddenly Mrs. Todd gave an energetic shrug of her shoulders,
and a quick look at me, and I saw that the sails of her narrative
were filled with a fresh breeze.
</p><p>"Uncle Lorenzo, Cap'n Bowden that I have referred to"&mdash;
</p><p>"Certainly!" I agreed with eager expectation.
</p><p>"He was the one that had been left in charge of Cap'n John
Tolland's affairs, and had now come to be of unforeseen importance.
</p><p>"Mrs. Begg an' I had stayed in the house both before an' after
Mis' Tolland's decease, and she was now in haste to be gone, having
affairs to call her home; but uncle come to me as the exercises was
beginning, and said he thought I'd better remain at the house while
they went to the buryin' ground.  I couldn't understand his
reasons, an' I felt disappointed, bein' as near to her as most
anybody; 'twas rough weather, so mother couldn't get in, and didn't
even hear Mis' Tolland was gone till next day.  I just nodded to
satisfy him, 'twa'n't no time to discuss anything.  Uncle seemed
flustered; he'd gone out deep-sea fishin' the day she died, and the
storm I told you of rose very sudden, so they got blown off way
down the coast beyond Monhegan, and he'd just got back in time to
dress himself and come.
<pb n="162"/>
</p><p>"I set there in the house after I'd watched her away down the
straight road far's I could see from the door; 'twas a little short
walkin' funeral an' a cloudy sky, so everything looked dull an'
gray, an' it crawled along all in one piece, same's walking
funerals do, an' I wondered how it ever come to the Lord's mind to
let her begin down among them gay islands all heat and sun, and end
up here among the rocks with a north wind blowin'.  'Twas a gale
that begun the afternoon before she died, and had kept blowin' off
an' on ever since.  I'd thought more than once how glad I should be
to get home an' out o' sound o' them black spruces a-beatin' an'
scratchin' at the front windows.
</p><p>"I set to work pretty soon to put the chairs back, an' set
outdoors some that was borrowed, an' I went out in the kitchen, an'
I made up a good fire in case somebody come an' wanted a cup o'
tea; but I didn't expect any one to travel way back to the house
unless 'twas uncle Lorenzo.  'Twas growin' so chilly that I fetched
some kindlin' wood and made fires in both the fore rooms.  Then I
set down an' begun to feel as usual, and I got my knittin' out of
a drawer.  You can't be sorry for a poor creatur' that's come to
the end o' all her troubles; my only discomfort was I thought I'd
ought to feel worse at losin' her than I did; I was younger then
than I be now.  And as I set there, I begun to hear some long notes
o' dronin' music from upstairs that chilled me to the bone."
</p><p>Mrs. Todd gave a hasty glance at me.
</p><p>"Quick's I could gather me, I went right upstairs to see what
'twas," she added eagerly, "an 'twas just what I might ha' known.
She'd always kept her guitar hangin' right against the wall in her
room; 'twas tied by a blue ribbon, and there was a window left wide
open; the wind was veerin' a good deal, an' it slanted in and
searched the room.  The strings was jarrin' yet.
</p><p>"'Twas growin' pretty late in the afternoon, an' I begun to
feel lonesome as I shouldn't now, and I was disappointed at having
to stay there, the more I thought it over, but after a while I saw
Cap'n Lorenzo polin' back up the road all alone, and when he come
nearer I could see he had a bundle under his arm and had shifted
his best black clothes for his every-day ones.  I run out and put
some tea into the teapot and set it back on the stove to draw, an'
when he come in I reached down a little jug o' spirits,&mdash;Cap'n
Tolland had left his house well provisioned as if his wife was
goin' to put to sea same's himself, an' there she'd gone an' left
it.  There was some cake that Mis' Begg an' I had made the day
before.  I thought that uncle an' me had a good right to the
funeral supper, even if there wa'n't any one to join us.  I was
lookin' forward to my cup o' tea; 'twas beautiful tea out of a
green lacquered chest that I've got now."
</p><p>"You must have felt very tired," said I, eagerly listening.
</p><p>"I was 'most beat out, with watchin' an' tendin' and all,"
answered Mrs. Todd, with as much sympathy in her voice as if she
were speaking of another person.  "But I called out to uncle as he
came in, 'Well, I expect it's all over now, an' we've all done what
we could.  I thought we'd better have some tea or somethin' before
we go home.  Come right out in the kitchen, sir,' says I, never
thinking but we only had to let the fires out and lock up
everything safe an' eat our refreshment, an' go home.
</p><p>"'I want both of us to stop here to-night,' says uncle,
looking at me very important.
</p><p>"'Oh, what for?' says I, kind o' fretful.
</p><p>"'I've got my proper reasons,' says uncle.  'I'll see you well
satisfied, Almira.  Your tongue ain't so easy-goin' as some o' the
women folks, an' there's property here to take charge of that you
don't know nothin' at all about.' <pb n="163"/>

</p><p>"'What do you mean?' says I.
</p><p>"'Cap'n Tolland acquainted me with his affairs; he hadn't no
sort o' confidence in nobody but me an' his wife, after he was
tricked into signin' that Portland note, an' lost money.  An' she
didn't know nothin' about business; but what he didn't take to sea
to be sunk with him he's hid somewhere in this house.  I expect
Mis' Tolland may have told you where she kept things?' said uncle.
</p><p>"I see he was dependin' a good deal on my answer," said Mrs.
Todd, "but I had to disappoint him; no, she had never said nothin'
to me.
</p><p>"'Well, then, we've got to make a search,' says he, with
considerable relish; but he was all tired and worked up, and we set
down to the table, an' he had somethin', an' I took my desired cup
o' tea, and then I begun to feel more interested.
</p><p>"'Where you goin' to look first?' says I, but he give me a
short look an' made no answer, and begun to mix me a very small
portion out of the jug, in another glass.  I took it to please him;
he said I looked tired, speakin' real fatherly, and I did feel
better for it, and we set talkin' a few minutes, an' then he
started for the cellar, carrying an old ship's lantern he fetched
out o' the stairway an' lit.
</p><p>"'What are you lookin' for, some kind of a chist?' I inquired,
and he said yes.  All of a sudden it come to me to ask who was the
heirs; Eliza Tolland, Cap'n John's own sister, had never demeaned
herself to come near the funeral, and uncle Lorenzo faced right
about and begun to laugh, sort o' pleased.  I thought queer of it'
'twa'n't what he'd taken, which would be nothin' to an old
weathered sailor like him.
</p><p>"'Who's the heir?' says I the second time.
</p><p>"'Why, it's <hi rend="italic">you</hi>, Almiry,' says he; and I was so took
aback I set right down on the turn o' the cellar stairs.
</p><p>"'Yes, 'tis,' said uncle Lorenzo.  'I'm glad of it too.  Some
thought she didn't have no sense but foreign sense, an' a poor
stock o' that, but she said you was friendly to her, an' one day
after she got news of Tolland's death, an' I had fetched up his
will that left everything to her, she said she was goin' to make a
writin', so's you could have things after she was gone, an' she
give five hundred to me for bein' executor.  Square Pease fixed up
the paper, an' she signed it; it's all accordin' to law.'  There,
I begun to cry," said Mrs. Todd; "I couldn't help it.  I wished I
had her back again to do somethin' for, an' to make her know I felt
sisterly to her more'n I'd ever showed, an' it come over me 'twas
all too late, an' I cried the more, till uncle showed impatience,
an' I got up an' stumbled along down cellar with my apern to my
eyes the greater part of the time.
</p><p>"'I'm goin' to have a clean search,' says he; 'you hold the
light.'  An' I held it, and he rummaged in the arches an' under the
stairs, an' over in some old closet where he reached out bottles
an' stone jugs an' canted some kags an' one or two casks, an'
chuckled well when he heard there was somethin' inside,&mdash;but there
wa'n't nothin' to find but things usual in a cellar, an' then the
old lantern was givin' out an' we come away.
</p><p>"'He spoke to me of a chist, Cap'n Tolland did,' says uncle in
a whisper.  'He said a good sound chist was as safe a bank as there
was, an' I beat him out of such nonsense, 'count o' fire an' other
risks.'  'There's no chist in the rooms above,' says I'; 'no,
uncle, there ain't no sea-chist, for I've been here long enough to
see what there was to be seen.'  Yet he wouldn't feel contented
till he'd mounted up into the toploft; 'twas one o' them single,
hip-roofed houses that don't give proper accommodation for a real
garret, like Cap'n Littlepage's down here at the Landin'.  There
was broken furniture and rubbish, an' he let down a <pb n="164"/>
terrible sight o' dust into the front entry, but sure enough there
wasn't no chist.  I had it all to sweep up next day.
</p><p>"'He must have took it away to sea,' says I to the cap'n, an'
even then he didn't want to agree, but we was both beat out.  I
told him where i'd always seen Mis' Tolland get her money from, and
we found much as a hundred dollars there in an old red morocco
wallet.  Cap'n John had been gone a good while a'ready, and she had
spent what she needed.  'Twas in an old desk o' his in the settin'
room that we found the wallet."
</p><p>"At the last minute he may have taken his money to sea," I
suggested.
</p><p>"Oh yes," agreed Mrs. Todd.  "He did take considerable to make
his venture to bring home, as was customary, an' that was drowned
with him as uncle agreed; but he had other property in shipping,
and a thousand dollars invested in Portland in a cordage shop, but
'twas about the time shipping begun to decay, and the cordage shop
failed, and in the end I wa'n't so rich as I thought I was goin' to
be for those few minutes on the cellar stairs.  There was an
auction that accumulated something.  Old Mis' Tolland, the cap'n's
mother, had heired some good furniture from a sister: there was
above thirty chairs in all, and they're apt to sell well.  I got
over a thousand dollars when we come to settle up, and I made uncle
take his five hundred; he was getting along in years and had met
with losses in navigation, and he left it back to me when he died,
so I had a real good lift.  It all lays in the bank over to
Rockland, and I draw my interest fall an' spring, with the little
Mr. Todd was able to leave me; but that's kind o' sacred money;
'twas earnt and saved with the hope o' youth, an' I'm very
particular what I spend it for.  Oh yes, what with ownin' my house,
I've been enabled to get along very well, with prudence!" said Mrs.
Todd contentedly.
</p><p>"But there was the house and land," I asked,&mdash;"what became of
that part of the property?"
</p><p>Mrs. Todd looked into the fire, and a shadow of disapproval
flitted over her face.
</p><p>"Poor old uncle!" she said, "he got childish about the matter.
I was hoping to sell at first, and I had an offer, but he always
run of an idea that there was more money hid away, and kept wanting
me to delay; an' he used to go up there all alone and search, and
dig in the cellar, empty an' bleak as 'twas in winter weather or
any time.  An' he'd come and tell me he'd dreamed he found gold
behind a stone in the cellar wall, or somethin'.  And one night we
all see the light o' fire up that way, an' the whole Landin' took
the road, and run to look, and the Tolland property was all in a
light blaze.  I expect the old gentleman had dropped fire about; he
said he'd been up there to see if everything was safe in the
afternoon.  As for the land, 'twas so poor that everybody used to
have a joke that the Tolland boys preferred to farm the sea
instead.  It's 'most all grown up to bushes now, where it ain't
poor water grass in the low places.  There's some upland that has
a pretty view, after you cross the brook bridge.  Years an' years
after she died, there was some o' her flowers used to come up an'
bloom in the door garden.  I brought two or three that was unusual
down here; they always come up and remind me of her constant as the
spring.  But I never did want to fetch home that guitar, some way
or 'nother; I wouldn't let it go at the auction, either.  It was
hangin' right there in the house when the fire took place.  I've
got some o' her other little things scattered about the house: that
picture on the mantelpiece belonged to her."
</p><p>I had often wondered where such a picture had come from, and
why Mrs. Todd had chosen it; it was a French <pb n="165"/>  print of the
statue of the Empress Josephine in the Savane at old Fort Royal, in
Martinique.



</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="6" id="d8"><head>VI</head>

<p>Mrs. Todd drew her chair closer to mine; she held the cat and
her knitting with one hand as she moved, but the cat was so warm
and so sound asleep that she only stretched a lazy paw in spite of
what must have felt like a slight earthquake.  Mrs. Todd began to
speak almost in a whisper.
</p><p>"I ain't told you all," she continued; "no, I haven't spoken
of all to but very few.  The way it came was this," she said
solemnly, and then stopped to listen to the wind, and sat for a
moment in deferential silence, as if she waited for the wind to
speak first.  The cat suddenly lifted her head with quick
excitement and gleaming eyes, and her mistress was leaning forward
toward the fire with an arm laid on either knee, as if they were
consulting the glowing coals for some augury.  Mrs. Todd looked
like an old prophetess as she sat there with the firelight shining
on her strong face; she was posed for some great painter.  The
woman with the cat was as unconscious and as mysterious as any
sibyl of the Sistine Chapel.
</p><p>"There, that's the last struggle o' the gale," said Mrs. Todd,
nodding her head with impressive certainty and still looking into
the bright embers of the fire.  "You'll see!"  She gave me another
quick glance, and spoke in a low tone as if we might be overheard.
</p><p>"'Twas such a gale as this the night Mis' Tolland died.  She
appeared more comfortable the first o' the evenin'; and Mrs. Begg
was more spent than I, bein' older, and a beautiful nurse that was
the first to see and think of everything, but perfectly quiet an'
never asked a useless question.  You remember her funeral when you
first come to the Landing?  And she consented to goin' an' havin'
a good sleep while she could, and left me one o' those good little
pewter lamps that burnt whale oil an' made plenty o' light in the
room, but not too bright to be disturbin'.
</p><p>"Poor Mis' Tolland had been distressed the night before, an'
all that day, but as night come on she grew more and more easy, an'
was layin' there asleep; 'twas like settin' by any sleepin' person,
and I had none but usual thoughts.  When the wind lulled and the
rain, I could hear the seas, though more distant than this, and I
don' know's I observed any other sound than what the weather made;
'twas a very solemn feelin' night.  I set close by the bed; there
was times she looked to find somebody when she was awake.  The
light was on her face, so I could see her plain; there was always
times when she wore a look that made her seem a stranger you'd
never set eyes on before.  I did think what a world it was that her
an' me should have come together so, and she have nobody but Dunnet
Landin' folks about her in her extremity.  'You're one o' the stray
ones, poor creatur',' I said.  I remember those very words passin'
through my mind, but I saw reason to be glad she had some comforts,
and didn't lack friends at the last, though she'd seen misery an'
pain.  I was glad she was quiet; all day she'd been restless, and
we couldn't understand what she wanted from her French speech.  We
had the window open to give her air, an' now an' then a gust would
strike that guitar that was on the wall and set it swinging by the
blue ribbon, and soundin' as if somebody begun to play it.  I come
near takin' it down, but you never know what'll fret a sick person
an' put 'em on the rack, an' that guitar was one o' the few things
she'd brought with her."
</p><p>I nodded assent, and Mrs. Todd spoke still lower.
</p><p>"I set there close by the bed; I'd <pb n="166"/>  been through a good
deal for some days back, and I thought I might's well be droppin'
asleep too, bein' a quick person to wake.  She looked to me as if
she might last a day longer, certain, now she'd got more
comfortable, but I was real tired, an' sort o' cramped as watchers
will get, an' a fretful feeling begun to creep over me such as they
often do have.  If you give way, there ain't no support for the
sick person; they can't count on no composure o' their own.  Mis'
Tolland moved then, a little restless, an' I forgot me quick
enough, an' begun to hum out a little part of a hymn tune just to
make her feel everything was as usual an' not wake up into a poor
uncertainty.  All of a sudden she set right up in bed with her eyes
wide open, an' I stood an' put my arm behind her; she hadn't moved
like that for days.  And she reached out both her arms toward the
door, an' I looked the way she was lookin', an' I see some one was
standin' there against the dark.  No, 'twa'n't Mis' Begg; 'twas
somebody a good deal shorter than Mis' Begg.  The lamplight struck
across the room between us.  I couldn't tell the shape, but 'twas
a woman's dark face lookin' right at us; 'twa'n't but an instant I
could see.  I felt dreadful cold, and my head begun to swim; I
thought the light went out; 'twa'n't but an instant, as I say, an'
when my sight come back I couldn't see nothing there.  I was one
that didn't know what it was to faint away, no matter what
happened; time was I felt above it in others, but 'twas somethin'
that made poor human natur' quail.  I saw very plain while I could
see; 'twas a pleasant enough face, shaped somethin' like Mis'
Tolland's, and a kind of expectin' look.
</p><p>"No, I don't expect I was asleep," Mrs. Todd assured me
quietly, after a moment's pause, though I had not spoken.  She gave
a heavy sigh before she went on.  I could see that the recollection
moved her in the deepest way.
</p><p>"I suppose if I hadn't been so spent an' quavery with long
watchin', I might have kept my head an' observed much better," she
added humbly; "but I see all I could bear.  I did try to act calm,
an' I laid Mis' Tolland down on her pillow, an' I was a-shakin' as
I done it.  All she did was to look up to me so satisfied and sort
o' questioning, an I looked back to her.
</p><p>"'You saw her, didn't you?' she says to me, speakin' perfectly
reasonable.  ''Tis my mother,' she says again, very feeble, but
lookin' straight up at me, kind of surprised with the pleasure, and
smiling as if she saw I was overcome, an' would have said more if
she could, but we had hold of hands.  I see then her change was
comin', but I didn't call Mis' Begg, nor make no uproar.  I felt
calm then, an' lifted to somethin' different as I never was since.
She opened her eyes just as she was goin'&mdash;
</p><p>"'You saw her, didn't you?' she said the second time, an' I
says, '<hi rend="italic">Yes, dear, I did; you ain't never goin' to feel strange
an' lonesome no more</hi>.'  An' then in a few quiet minutes 'twas
all over.  I felt they'd gone away together.  No, I wa'n't alarmed
afterward; 'twas just that one moment I couldn't live under, but I
never called it beyond reason I should see the other watcher.  I
saw plain enough there was somebody there with me in the room.



</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="7" id="d9"><head>VII</head>

<p>"'Twas just such a night as this Mis' Tolland died," repeated
Mrs. Todd, returning to her usual tone and leaning back comfortably
in her chair as she took up her knitting.  "'Twas just such a night
as this.  I've told the circumstances to but very few; but I don't
call it beyond reason.  When folks is goin' 'tis all natural, and
only common things can jar upon the mind.  You know plain enough
there's somethin' beyond this <pb n="167"/>  world; the doors stand wide
open.  'There's somethin' of us that must still live on; we've got
to join both worlds together an' live in one but for the other.'
The doctor said that to me one day, an' I never could forget it; he
said 'twas in one o' his old doctor's books."

</p><p>We sat together in silence in the warm little room; the rain
dropped heavily from the eaves, and the sea still roared, but the
high wind had done blowing.  We heard the far complaining fog horn
of a steamer up the Bay.
</p><p>"There goes the Boston boat out, pretty near on time," said
Mrs. Todd with satisfaction.  "Sometimes these late August
storms'll sound a good deal worse than they really be.  I do hate
to hear the poor steamers callin' when they're bewildered in thick
nights in winter, comin' on the coast.  Yes, there goes the boat;
they'll find it rough at sea, but the storm's all over."
</p><signed>                        <hi rend="italic">Sarah Orne Jewett.</hi></signed>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
