<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="JewWill"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="JewWill">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">William's Wedding</title>
<title type="sort">williams wedding</title>
<author>Jewett, Sarah Orne</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">29</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">JewWill</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476122</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">William's Wedding</title>
<title type="sort">williams wedding</title>
<author>Sarah Orne Jewett</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly (Houghton, Mifflin &amp; Co.)</publisher>
<pubPlace>Cambridge, Mass</pubPlace>
<date value="1910">1910</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>106</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Jewett, Sarah Orne.  "William's Wedding."  <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 106 (1910): 33-40.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions
for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1910">1910</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction ; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-07">July 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header; Tagged with TEI2-compatible SGML markup; Parsed against
"teilite" dtd.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">


<front id="d2">
<div1 type="preface" id="d3"><pb n="33"/>
<head> WILLIAM'S WEDDING <lb/>
BY SARAH ORNE JEWETT </head>

<p>[After the publication of 'A Dunnet Shepherdess' in the
<hi rend="italic">Atlantic</hi> for December, 1899, and its subsequent appearance
in a volume of collected stories, Miss Jewett received many appeals
to bring William Blackett's lifelong love of Esther Hight, 'the
shepherdess,' who had given the better part of her days to the care
of her stricken mother, to a happy termination.  The story of
'William's Wedding' was written, but the manuscript was mislaid,
and has only just been found.  Miss Jewett had hoped to give to it
an hour or two of final revision to make it conform more perfectly
to her fastidious taste, but few lovers of her work will find any
flaw.
</p><p>The two chief characters are thus described in earlier
stories:&mdash;
</p><p>'I turned, startled in the silence of the wide field, and saw
an elderly man, bent in the shoulders as fishermen often are, gray-headed and clean-shaven, and with a timid air.  It was William. .
. .  He was about sixty, and not young-looking for his years.  Yet
so undying is the spirit of youth, and bashfulness has such a power
of survival, that I felt all the time as if one must try to make
the occasion easy for some one who was young and new to the affairs
of the social world.' (<hi rend="italic">The Country of the Pointed Firs</hi>.)
'As for Esther, she might have been Jeanne d'Arc returned to her
sheep, touched with age, and gray with the ashes of a great
remembrance.  She wore the simple look of sainthood and unfeigned
devotion.  My heart was moved by the sight of her plain sweet face,
weather-worn and gentle in its looks, her thin figure in its close
dress, and the strong hand that clasped a shepherd's staff. . . .
She had lived in sunshine and rain among her silly sheep, and been
refined instead of coarsened, while her touching patience with a
ramping old mother, stung by the sense of defeat, and mourning her
lost activities, had given back a lovely self-possession and habit
of sweet temper. . . .  I love to remember her worn face and her
young blue eyes.'  ('A Dunnet Shepherdess,' in <hi rend="italic">The Queen's Twin</hi>)</p>
<signed>&mdash; THE EDITORS.]</signed>

</div1>
</front>
<body id="d4">
<div1 type="chapter" n="1" id="d5">
<head>        I </head>

<p>THE hurry of life in a large town, the constant putting aside
of preference to yield a most unsatisfactory activity, began to vex
me, and one day I took the train, and only left it for the
eastward-bound boat.  Carlyle says somewhere that the only
happiness a man ought to ask for is happiness enough to get his
work done; and against this the complexity and futile ingenuity of
social life seems a conspiracy.  But the first salt wind from the
east, the first sight of a lighthouse set boldly on its outer rock,
the flash of a gull, the waiting procession of seaward-bound firs
on an island, made me feel solid and definite again, instead of a
poor, incoherent being.  Life was resumed, and anxious living blew
away as if it had not been.  I could not breathe deep enough or
long enough.  It was a return to happiness.
</p><p>The coast had still a wintry look; it was far on in May, but
all the shore looked cold and sterile.  One was conscious of going
north as well as east, and as the day went on the sea grew colder,
and all the warmer air and bracing strength and stimulus of the
autumn weather, and storage of the heat of summer, were quite gone.
I was very cold and very tired when I came at evening up the lower
bay, and saw the white houses of Dunnet Landing climbing the hill.
They had a friendly look, these little houses, not as if they were
<pb n="34"/>  climbing up the shore, but as if they were rather all coming
down to meet a fond and weary traveler, and I could hardly wait
with patience to step off the boat.  It was not the usual eager
company on the wharf.  The coming-in of the mail-boat was the one
large public event of a summer day, and I was disappointed at
seeing none of my intimate friends but Johnny Bowden, who had
evidently done nothing all winter but grow, so that his short sea-smitten clothes gave him a look of poverty.
</p><p>Johnny's expression did not change as we greeted each other,
but I suddenly felt that I had shown indifference and inconvenient
delay by not coming sooner; before I could make an apology he took
my small portmanteau, and walking before me in his old fashion he
made straight up the hilly road toward Mrs. Todd's.  Yes, he was
much grown&mdash;it had never occurred to me the summer before that
Johnny was likely, with the help of time and other forces, to grow
into a young man; he was such a well-framed and well-settled chunk
of a boy that nature seemed to have set him aside as something
finished, quite satisfactory and entirely completed.
</p><p>The wonderful little green garden had been enchanted away by
winter.  There were a few frost-bitten twigs and some thin
shrubbery against the fence, but it was a most unpromising small
piece of ground.  My heart was beating like a lover's as I passed
it on the way to the door of Mrs. Todd's house, which seemed to
have become much smaller under the influence of winter weather.
</p><p>'She hasn't gone away?' I asked Johnny Bowden with a sudden
anxiety just as we reached the doorstep.
</p><p>'Gone away!' he faced me with blank astonishment,&mdash;'I see her
settin' by Mis' Caplin's window, the one nighest the road, about
four o'clock!'  And eager with suppressed news of my coming he made
his entrance as if the house were a burrow.
</p><p>Then on my homesick heart fell the voice of Mrs. Todd.  She
stopped, through what I knew to be excess of feeling, to rebuke
Johnny for bringing in so much mud, and I dallied without for one
moment during the ceremony; then we met again face to face.



</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="2" id="d6"><head>       II </head>

<p>'I dare say you can advise me what shapes they are going to
wear.  My meetin'-bunnit ain't going to do me again this year; no!
I can't expect 'twould do me forever,' said Mrs. Todd, as soon as
she could say anything.  'There! do set down and tell me how you
have been!  We've got a weddin' in the family, I s'pose you know?'
</p><p>'A wedding!' said I, still full of excitement.
</p><p>'Yes; I expect if the tide serves and the line-storm don't
overtake him they'll come in and appear out on Sunday.  I shouldn't
have concerned me about the bunnit for a month yet, nobody would
notice, but havin' an occasion like this I shall show consider'ble.
'Twill be an ordeal for William!'
</p><p>'For <hi rend="italic">William!</hi>' I exclaimed.  'What do you mean, Mrs.
Todd?'
</p><p>She gave a comfortable little laugh.  'Well, the Lord's seen
reason at last an' removed Mis' Cap'n Hight up to the farm, an' I
don't know but the weddin's going to be this week.  Esther's had a
great deal of business disposin' of her flock, but she's done extra
well&mdash;the folks that owns the next place goin' up country are well
off.  'Tis elegant land north side o' that bleak ridge, an' one o'
the boys has been Esther's right-hand man of late.  She instructed
him in all matters, and after she markets the early lambs he's
goin' to take the farm <pb n="35"/>  on halves, an' she's give the refusal
to him to buy her out within two years.  She's reserved the
buryin'-lot, an' the right o' way in, an'&mdash;'
</p><p>I couldn't stop for details.  I demanded reassurance of the
central fact.
</p><p>'William going to be married?' I repeated; whereat Mrs. Todd
gave me a searching look that was not without scorn.
</p><p>'Old Mis' Hight's funeral was a week ago Wednesday, and 'twas
very well attended,' she assured me after a moment's pause.
</p><p>'Poor thing!' said I, with a sudden vision of her helplessness
and angry battle against the fate of illness; 'it was very hard for
her.'
</p><p>'I thought it was hard for Esther!' said Mrs. Todd without
sentiment.



</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="3" id="d7"><head>       III </head>

<p>I had an odd feeling of strangeness: I missed the garden, and
the little rooms, to which I had added a few things of my own the
summer before, seemed oddly unfamiliar.  It was like the hermit
crab in a cold new shell,&mdash;and with the windows shut against the
raw May air, and a strange silence and grayness of the sea all that
first night and day of my visit, I felt as if I had after all lost
my hold of that quiet life.
</p><p>Mrs. Todd made the apt suggestion that city persons were prone
to run themselves to death, and advised me to stay and get properly
rested now that I had taken the trouble to come.  She did not know
how long I had been homesick for the conditions of life at the
Landing the autumn before&mdash;it was natural enough to feel a little
unsupported by compelling incidents on my return.
</p><p>Some one has said that one never leaves a place, or arrives at
one, until the next day!  But on the second morning I woke with the
familiar feeling of interest and ease, and the bright May sun was
streaming in, while I could hear Mrs. Todd's heavy footsteps
pounding about in the other part of the house as if something were
going to happen.  There was the first golden robin singing
somewhere close to the house, and a lovely aspect of spring now,
and I looked at the garden to see that in the warm night some of
its treasures had grown a hand's breadth; the determined spikes of
yellow daffies stood tall against the doorsteps, and the bloodroot
was unfolding leaf and flower.  The belated spring which I had left
behind farther south had overtaken me on this northern coast.  I
even saw a presumptuous dandelion in the garden border.

</p><p>It is difficult to report the great events of New England;
expression is so slight, and those few words which escape us in
moments of deep feeling look but meagre on the printed page.  One
has to assume too much of the dramatic fervor as one reads; but as
I came out of my room at breakfast-time I met Mrs. Todd face to
face, and when she said to me, 'This weather'll bring William in
after her; 'tis their happy day!' I felt something take possession
of me which ought to communicate itself to the least sympathetic
reader of this cold page.  It is written for those who have a
Dunnet Landing of their own: who either kindly share this with its
writer, or possess another.
</p><p>'I ain't seen his comin' sail yet; he'll be likely to dodge
round among the islands so he'll be the less observed,' continued
Mrs. Todd.  'You can get a dory up the bay, even a clean new
painted one, if you know as how, keepin' it against the high land.'
She stepped to the door and looked off to sea as she spoke.  I
could see her eye follow the gray shores to and fro, and then a
bright light spread over her calm face.  'There <pb n="36"/>  he comes,
and he's striking right in across the open bay like a man!' she
said with splendid approval.  'See, there he comes!  Yes, there's
William, and he's bent his new sail.'
</p><p>I looked too, and saw the fleck of white no larger than a
gull's wing yet, but present to her eager vision.
</p><p>I was going to France for the whole long summer that year, and
the more I thought of such an absence from these simple scenes the
more dear and delightful they became.  Santa Teresa says that the
true proficiency of the soul is not in much thinking, but in much
loving, and sometimes I believed that I had never found love in its
simplicity as I had found it at Dunnet Landing in the various
hearts of Mrs. Blackett and Mrs. Todd and William.  It is only
because one came to know them, these three, loving and wise and
true, in their own habitations.  Their counterparts are in every
village in the world, thank heaven, and the gift to one's life is
only in its discernment.  I had only lived in Dunnet until the
usual distractions and artifices of the world were no longer in
control, and I saw these simple natures clear.  'The happiness of
life is in its recognitions.  It seems that we are not ignorant of
these truths, and even that we believe them; but we are so little
accustomed to think of them, they are so strange to us&mdash;'

</p><p>'Well now, deary me!' said Mrs. Todd, breaking into
exclamation; 'I've got to fly round&mdash;I thought he'd have to beat;
he can't sail far on that tack, and he won't be in for a good hour
yet&mdash;I expect he's made every arrangement, but he said he shouldn't
go up after Esther unless the weather was good, and I declare it
did look doubtful this morning.'
</p><p>I remembered Esther's weather-worn face.  She was like a
Frenchwoman who had spent her life in the fields.  I remembered her
pleasant look, her child-like eyes, and thought of the astonishment
of joy she would feel now in being taken care of and tenderly
sheltered from wind and weather after all these years.  They were
going to be young again now, she and William, to forget work and
care in the spring weather.  I could hardly wait for the boat to
come to land, I was so eager to see his happy face.
</p><p>'Cake an' wine I'm goin' to set 'em out!' said Mrs. Todd.
'They won't stop to set down for an ordered meal, they'll want to
get right out home quick's they can.  Yes, I'll give 'em some cake
an' wine&mdash;I've got a rare plum-cake from my best receipt, and a
bottle o' wine that the old Cap'n Denton of all give me, one of
two, the day I was married, one we had and one we saved, and I've
never touched it till now.  He said there wa'n't none like it in
the State o' Maine.'
</p><p>It was a day of waiting, that day of spring; the May weather
was as expectant as our fond hearts, and one could see the grass
grow green hour by hour.  The warm air was full of birds, there was
a glow of light on the sea instead of the cold shining of chilly
weather which had lingered late.  There was a look on Mrs. Todd's
face which I saw once and could meet again.  She was in her highest
mood.  Then I went out early for a walk, and when I came back we
sat in different rooms for the most part.  There was such a thrill
in the air that our only conversation was in her most abrupt and
incisive manner.  She was knitting, I believe, and as for me I
dallied with a book.  I heard her walking to and fro, and the door
being wide open now, she went out and paced the front walk to the
gate as if she walked a quarterdeck.
</p><p>It is very solemn to sit waiting for <pb n="37"/>  the great events
of life&mdash;most of us have done it again and again&mdash;to be expectant
of life or expectant of death gives one the same feeling.
</p><p>But at the last Mrs. Todd came quickly back from the gate, and
standing in the sunshine at the door, she beckoned me as if she
were a sibyl.
</p><p>'I thought you comprehended everything the day you was up
there,' she added with a little more patience in her tone, but I
felt that she thought I had lost instead of gained since we parted
the autumn before.
</p><p>'William's made this pretext o' goin' fishin' for the last
time.  'Twouldn't done to take notice, 'twould scared him to death!
but there never was nobody took less comfort out o' forty years
courtin'.  No, he won't have to make no further pretexts,' said
Mrs. Todd, with an air of triumph.
</p><p>'Did you know where he was going that day?' I asked with a
sudden burst of admiration at such discernment.
</p><p>'I did!' replied Mrs. Todd grandly.
</p><p>'Oh! but that pennyroyal lotion,' I indignantly protested,
remembering that under pretext of mosquitoes she had besmeared the
poor lover in an awful way&mdash;why, it was outrageous!  Medea could
not have been more conscious of high ultimate purposes.
</p><p>'Darlin',' said Mrs. Todd, in the excitement of my arrival and
the great concerns of marriage, 'he's got a beautiful shaped face,
and they pison him very unusual&mdash;you wouldn't have had him present
himself to his lady all lop-sided with a mosquito-bite?  Once when
we was young I rode up with him, and they set upon him in concert
the minute we entered the woods.'  She stood before me
reproachfully, and I was conscious of deserved rebuke.  'Yes,
you've come just in the nick of time to advise me about a bunnit.
They say large bows on top is liable to be worn.'



</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="4" id="d8"><head>       IV </head>

<p>The period of waiting was one of direct contrast to these high
moments of recognition.  The very slowness of the morning hours
wasted that sense of excitement with which we had begun the day.
Mrs. Todd came down from the mount where her face had shone so
bright, to the cares of common life, and some acquaintances from
Black Island for whom she had little natural preference or liking
came, bringing a poor, sickly child to get medical advice.  They
were noisy women with harsh, clamorous voices, and they stayed a
long time.  I heard the clink of teacups, however, and could detect
no impatience in the tones of Mrs. Todd's voice; but when they were
at last going away, she did not linger unduly over her leave-taking, and returned to me to explain that they were people she had
never liked, and they had made an excuse of a friendly visit to
save their doctor's bill; but she pitied the poor little child, and
knew beside that the doctor was away.
</p><p>'I had to give 'em the remedies right out,' she told me; 'they
wouldn't have bought a cent's worth o' drugs down to the store for
that dwindlin' thing.  She needed feedin' up, and I don't expect
she gets milk enough; they're great butter-makers down to Black
Island, 'tis excellent pasturage, but they use no milk themselves,
and their butter is heavy laden with salt to make weight, so that
you'd think all their ideas come down from Sodom.'
</p><p>She was very indignant and very wistful about the pale little
girl.  'I wish they'd let me kept her,' she said.  'I kind of
advised it, and her eyes was so wishful in that pinched face when
she heard me, so that I could see what was the matter with her, but
they said she wa'n't prepared.  Prepared!'  And Mrs. Todd snuffed
like an offended war-<pb n="38"/> horse, and departed; but I could hear
her still grumbling and talking to herself in high dudgeon an hour
afterward.
</p><p>At the end of that time her arch enemy, Mari' Harris, appeared
at the side-door with a gingham handkerchief over her head.  She
was always on hand for the news, and made some formal excuse for
her presence,&mdash;she wished to borrow the weekly paper.  Captain
Littlepage, whose housekeeper she was, had taken it from the post-office in the morning, but had forgotten, being of failing memory,
what he had done with it.
</p><p>'How is the poor old gentleman?' asked Mrs. Todd with
solicitude, ignoring the present errand of Maria and all her
concerns.
</p><p>I had spoken the evening before of intended visits to Captain
Littlepage and Elijah Tilley, and I now heard Mrs. Todd repeating
my inquiries and intentions, and fending off with unusual
volubility of her own the curious questions that were sure to come.
But at last Maria Harris secured an opportunity and boldly inquired
if she had not seen William ashore early that morning.
</p><p>'I don't say he wasn't,' replied Mrs. Todd; 'Thu'sday's a very
usual day with him to come ashore.'
</p><p>'He was all dressed up,' insisted Maria&mdash;she really had no
sense of propriety.  'I didn't know but they was going to be
married?'
</p><p>Mrs. Todd did not reply.  I recognized from the sounds that
reached me that she had retired to the fastnesses of the kitchen-closet and was clattering the tins.
</p><p>'I expect they'll marry soon anyway,' continued the visitor.
</p><p>'I expect they will if they want to,' answered Mrs. Todd.  'I
don't know nothing' 'tall about it; that's what folks say.'  And
presently the gingham handkerchief retreated past my window.
</p><p>'I routed her, horse and foot,' said Mrs. Todd proudly, coming
at once to stand at my door.  'Who's coming now?' as two figures
passed inward bound to the kitchen.
</p><p>They were Mrs. Begg and Johnny Bowden's mother, who were
favorites, and were received with Mrs. Todd's usual civilities.
Then one of the Mrs. Caplins came with a cup in hand to borrow
yeast.  On one pretext or another nearly all our acquaintances came
to satisfy themselves of the facts, and see what Mrs. Todd would
impart about the wedding.  But she firmly avoided the subject
through the length of every call and errand, and answered the final
leading question of each curious guest with her non-committal
phrase, 'I don't know nothin' 'tall about it; that's what folks
say!'
</p><p>She had just repeated this for the fourth or fifth time and
shut the door upon the last comers, when we met in the little front
entry.  Mrs. Todd was not in a bad temper, but highly amused.
'I've been havin' all sorts o' social privileges, you may have
observed.  They didn't seem to consider that if they could only
hold out till afternoon they'd know as much as I did.  There wa'n't
but one o' the whole sixteen that showed real interest, the rest
demeaned themselves to ask out o' cheap curiosity; no, there wa'n't
but one showed any real feelin'.'
</p><p>'Miss Maria Harris you mean?' and Mrs. Todd laughed.
</p><p>'Certain, dear,' she agreed, 'how you do understand poor human
natur'!'
</p><p>A short distance down the hilly street stood a narrow house
that was newly painted white.  It blinded one's eyes to catch the
reflection of the sun.  It was the house of the minister, and a
wagon had just stopped before it; a man was helping a woman to
alight, and they stood side by side for a mo-<pb n="39"/> ment, while
Johnny Bowden appeared as if by magic, and climbed to the wagon-seat.  Then they went into the house and shut the door.  Mrs. Todd
and I stood close together and watched; the tears were running down
her cheeks.  I watched Johnny Bowden, who made light of so great a
moment by so handling the whip that the old white Caplin horse
started up from time to time and was inexorably stopped as if he
had some idea of running away.  There was something in the back of
the wagon which now and then claimed the boy's attention; he leaned
over as if there were something very precious left in his charge;
perhaps it was only Esther's little trunk going to its new home.
</p><p>At last the door of the parsonage opened, and two figures came
out.  The minister followed them and stood in the doorway, delaying
them with parting words; he could not have thought it was a time
for admonition.
</p><p>'He's all alone; his wife's up to Portland to her sister's,'
said Mrs. Todd, in a matter-of-fact voice.  'She's a nice woman,
but she might ha' talked too much.  There! see, they're comin'
here.  I didn't know how 'twould be.  Yes, they're comin' up to see
us before they go home.  I declare, if William ain't lookin' just
like a king!'
</p><p>Mrs. Todd took one step forward, and we stood and waited.  The
happy pair came walking up the street, Johnny Bowden driving ahead.
I heard a plaintive little cry from time to time to which in the
excitement of the moment I had not stopped to listen; but when
William and Esther had come and shaken hands with Mrs. Todd and
then with me, all in silence, Esther stepped quickly to the back of
the wagon, and unfastening some cords returned to us carrying a
little white lamb.  She gave a shy glance at William as she fondled
it and held it to her heart, and then, still silent, we went into
the house together.  The lamb had stopped bleating.  It was lovely
to see Esther carry it in her arms.
</p><p>When we got into the house, all the repression of Mrs. Todd's
usual manner was swept away by her flood of feeling.  She took
Esther's thin figure, lamb and all, to her heart and held her
there, kissing her as she might have kissed a child, and then held
out her hand to William and they gave each other the kiss of peace.
This was so moving, so tender, so free from their usual fetters of
self-consciousness, that Esther and I could not help giving each
other a happy glance of comprehension.  I never saw a young bride
half so touching in her happiness as Esther was that day of her
wedding.  We took the cake and wine of the marriage feast together,
always in silence, like a true sacrament, and then to my
astonishment I found that sympathy and public interest in so great
an occasion were going to have their way.  I shrank from the
thought of William's possible sufferings, but he welcomed both the
first group of neighbors and the last with heartiness; and when at
last they had gone, for there were thoughtless loiterers in Dunnet
Landing, I made ready with eager zeal and walked with William and
Esther to the water-side.  It was only a little way, and kind faces
nodded reassuringly from the windows, while kind voices spoke from
the doors.  Esther carried the lamb on one arm; she had found time
to tell me that its mother had died that morning and she could not
bring herself to the thought of leaving it behind.  She kept the
other hand on William's arm until we reached the landing.  Then he
shook hands with me, and looked me full in the face to be sure I
understood how happy he was, and stepping into the boat held out
his arms to Esther&mdash;at last she was his own. <pb n="40"/>
</p><p>I watched him make a nest for the lamb out of an old sea-cloak
at Esther's feet, and then he wrapped her own shawl round her
shoulders, and finding a pin in the lapel of his Sunday coat he
pinned it for her.  She looked at him fondly while he did this, and
then glanced up at us, a pretty, girlish color brightening her
cheeks.
</p><p>We stood there together and watched them go far out into the
bay.  The sunshine of the May day was low now, but there was a
steady breeze, and the boat moved well.
</p><p>'Mother'll be watching for them,' said Mrs. Todd.  'Yes,
mother'll be watching all day, and waiting.  She'll be so happy to
have Esther come.'
</p><p>We went home together up the hill, and Mrs. Todd said nothing
more; but we held each other's hand all the way.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

