<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="KniReal"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="KniReal">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Real Artemus Ward</title>
<title type="sort">real artemus ward</title>
<author>Knight, Enoch</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">30</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">KniReal</idno>
<date value="2000">2000</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2000 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476144</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Real Artemus Ward</title>
<title level="j">The Overland monthly</title>
<title type="sort">real artemus ward</title>
<author>Enoch Knight</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>California Pub. Co., 1883-1923</publisher>
<pubPlace>San Francisco</pubPlace>
<date value="1891-07">July 1891</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Micfilm S-147 reel 35-50.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>American periodical series: 1850-1900 ; 35-50.</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Microfilm. Ann Arbor, Mich. : University Microfilms, [n.d.]. 16 microfilm reels ; 35 mm. (American periodical series: 1850-1900 ; 35-50)</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1891">1891</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2001-04">April 2001</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Karen Wikander</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI-header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
<head>THE REAL ARTEMUS WARD</head>
<pb n="54"/>


<epigraph>
<q>"Rest, loved one, rest."</q>
<l>&mdash;</l>
<lg type="epitaph"><l>"CHARLES F. BROWNE,</l>
<l>Known to the world as</l>
<l>'ARTEMUS WARD,'</l></lg>
<lg><l>Died in Southampton, Eng.,</l>
<l>March 6, 1867,</l>
<l>Aged, 33 years.</l></lg>

<lg><l><q>His name will live as</q></l>
<l><q>A sweet and unfading recollection."</q></l></lg>
</epigraph>



<p>THE above epitaph, written by the genial humorist's mother, one may
read on a marble slab in the little cemetery at Waterford, Oxford
County, Maine,&mdash; "Water-ford near Rum-ford," as he used to say, "the
little village that nestled amongst the hills and never did anything but
nestle."  It is a charming spot where rest the remains of Charles Farrar
Browne, looking out upon the little lake, and hard by the edge of a
beech and maple wood,<lb/>

<q>Where ruddy children tumbled in their play,<lb/>
   And lovers came to woo,</q>

in the days when I first knew the place.  Born in the same year and in
the same neighborhood as himself, and all the scenes of his early life
being as dear and familiar to me as the songs of the birds or the crests
of the bordering hills, it has seemed partly a duty, as well as a
privilege and pleasure, to add my little contribution to the literature
his career has called forth.

</p><p>Even to those who knew him intimately throughout, his real life
seems to have begun just where the great world first heard of him, upon
his early pilgrimage westward.  Major Armstrong tells how the green
youth of twenty-three, in long linen duster, came to him in 1857 in the
little city of Tiffin, Ohio, and wanted to set type on the only
newspaper in town; how he took him into the hotel and gave him his first
leisurely meal for many a day; how he "set locals out of his head" for
four dollars a week till Riley put him on the local staff of the
<hi rend="italic">Toledo Commercial</hi>, and paid him the munificent stipend of a
collar a day.  Here his witticisms attracted the attention of Mr. Gray,
the veteran editor of the Cleveland <hi rend="italic">Plain Dealer</hi>, and to that
city the young journalist went, and soon found fame and the beginning of
good fortune.  In fact, Cleveland was always more a home to him than any
other place, and he who goes thither to this day can learn from the lips
of many warm and willing witnesses with what peculiar pride and
affection his memory is cherished.  The rickety chair and the old pine
table he used in the <hi rend="italic">Plain Dealer</hi> office are preserved with
great care in the Western Reserve Historical Society.

</p><p>The "show" had taken possession of him from his very boyhood, and
showmen were always his admiration.  "Artemus Ward," the showman he
clothed with flesh and blood early in his <hi rend="italic">Plain Dealer</hi> work,
was a faithful development and no accident.  The "3 moral bares" were
born of the same idea that evolved the caravan of the boy of ten, in his
little Oxford County home, in which his mother's cow, decked with fancy
bed quilt, was the elephant.

</p><p>Nearly three years were spent in Cleveland, when he went to New
York to assist in the making of <hi rend="italic">Vanity Fair</hi>.  But in all this
time his fragmentary newspaper work was only preparatory to entering
upon a career that had been the dream of his life.  It is curious to
note that nearly all his newspaper friends tried to dissuade him from
his purpose to attempt lecturing.  Major Bone, the present managing
editor of the <hi rend="italic">Plain Dealer</hi>, having once gotten hold of a string
of matter that appeared to have


<pb n="55"/>

been put together for use on the platform, made a personal appeal to Browne
to give up the venture, as it would be
sure to be a sorry failure.  But he was
persistent, even stubborn, (though always amiably so,) in his purpose, though
in other things he had been vacillating
and inconstant.  He had heard his sayings retailed in minstrel halls and elsewhere, and if they were good, if they
were merchandise, why should he not
come to his own, since he was poor?

</p><p>The public is tolerably familiar with his first ventures,
"Ghosts," "Sixty Minutes in Africa," and the "Babes in the Wood."  He
was determined to lecture, and on a plan of his own, a plan it took some
time and money to effect.  It was the golden age of the platform, but
there had never been a humorous lecture, in any broad sense.  To
entertain, with pure frolic, audiences thus educated, was indeed an
audacious undertaking.  But Artemus never seemed to have the slightest
doubt of his success, which shows how completely he had mastered the
subject.  It was not, however, till his California trip and what came
out of it that his full ideal was to be realized,&mdash;a lecture that should
have a thread of narrative, or a series of pictures, or both, which he
could use as the framework of his incomparable fun.

</p><p>In more ways than one the California journey in the season of
1863-64 proved of great consequence.  His reception all along the route
was wonderfully cordial.  In Virginia City the miners took charge of his
lecture, refusing to have tickets sold, but invited in the crowd, and
then a committee passed among the audience and collected sixteen hundred
dollars!  One hat broke through with its load of gold.  Everybody wanted
to see the tenderfoot who, on being requested to reply by wire what he
would take for forty nights in California, instantly answered "Brandy
and water."  His wit was quicker than the lightning, and his kindliness
and humor simply measureless.

</p><p>But this terribly trying trip in "the little den on wheels," as
he called the stage, brought on a serious illness upon his return by way
of Utah; and yet, as has been hinted, it all turned out to be one of the
greatest bits of good fortune.  His enforced stay among the Mormons gave
him an opportunity to study the inside history and working of their
institution, and thus furnish him what he had so long desired,&mdash;the
subject of an illustrated lecture, which in those days meant a panorama
or other series of actual pictures, instead of the modern stereopticon.
On his reaching New York, in the spring of '64, he at once set about his
ideal plan, and was soon "on the road" with the most unique
entertainment ever offered to the public.

</p><p>I shall never forget my meeting him in Baltimore the following
winter, the last year of the war, when he was giving his new Mormon
lecture in the quaint old "Maryland Institute."  I had not seen him for
three years, and his first greeting was to thrust into my hand the
program of his lecture, and a ticket inscribed, "Admit the bearer and
one wife."  This ticket, the program, and autograph on an invitation to
admit all my acquaintances, together with woodcuts of the lecturer, and
other curious mementoes of my old friend, gathered later, I keep among
my treasures.

</p><p>From this time until the date of his leaving for England in the
summer of 1866, I had great opportunities to observe and study him.
There was something very fascinating in his presence.  Never was a man
more misunderstood.  He had not one trace of coarseness or real
awkwardness.  Though far from handsome, he had a fine, lithe figure,
with smooth, light hair, teeth white and delicate, and the most
beautiful hands.  His voice was peculiarly soft, and his whole demeanor
was that of a finely bred, sensitive, and modest gentleman.  Even his
most intimate friends could hardly understand why nothing of the

<pb n="56"/>

clown ever cropped out in facial or bodily
contortion, when he was saying his odd
things; but surely it never did, and this
self poise and grave mien on all these
occasions no one who knew him can ever
for a moment forget.  It is not strange
that the great public always thought of
him beforehand as a bumptious and
rather uncouth specimen of the traveling showman, and it was their disappointment on seeing him that added
greatly to the amusement of his entertainment.  A London reporter relates
that when he made his appearance in the
evening on the stage, a large part of the
audience that had never seen him supposed that he was the genteel manager
who had come out to make some preliminary announcement.  But the real fact
is that Artemus Ward was not even affected by local coloring or prejudice, nor
was his speech marked by a single provincialism.  He was a cosmopolitan gentleman in every relation of life.  And
this is what was the beginning of the
power he had over his audiences, that
they at once saw he was not to attempt
to amuse them by antics, but by quietly
saying things worth saying.  And half
the fun of the entertainment lay in the
successive, or rather cumulative bursts
of laughter that followed his best points.
The bright few were ready to laugh on
the instant; then a slower section of
the audience would "catch on," and
finally all would be tumult for minutes
together.

</p><p>The program of this Mormon lecture, precisely the same in England
as here, was a wonderful creation; and the very music in it showed the
genius of the artist.  It was at a time when the community was gorged
with sentimental songs, and these were imitated and paraphrased by him,
one of the pieces being entitled, "Dearest, When Thou Sleepest, Dostest
Dreamest of Me?"  And yet Artemus was not a frivolous person.  He had a
deep and appreciative sentiment.  More than this, he had reverence, and
it was because of these that he detested shallow and unworthy persons
and cheats.  It was because he had real sentiment that he ridiculed
gush.  He was up to the intellectual standard of his audiences.  It is a
mistake to suppose he was in any way an inferior man.  He knew men and
he knew public affairs most correctly and thoroughly.  One of his
English critics has said of him that he knew as much about England as
most Englishmen knew; and "To him the Tower of London was the history of
England in stone and mortar."

</p><p>I saw him the last time on the eve of his departure for London,
where he was to face a critical and expectant public in the metropolis
of England.  He never seemed to doubt the entire safety of this venture,
and was gleeful as a child over the prospect.  Exactly as he had planned
it, he delivered his opening lecture November 13th, 1866, in Egyptian
Hall, which had been made famous by many literary talkers.  The notables
among artists, actors, the club men, in fact, the representatives of all
social and literary London, were there,&mdash;all by invitation, the paying
public not being admitted.  On this first night, as I have said, it was
the lecture on the Mormons.  There was "the little picture shop, with
its central curtain of green baize, the piano hidden from view, some
pictures to be unrolled, a few good, but mostly very bad; while the
music was what the lecturer's whim might suggest.

</p><p>When at the last moment, a spare figure in full evening dress,
holding in his delicate handsome hand the dainty little riding whip to
point out the details of his pictures, appeared upon the stage in front
of the curtain, there was a depressed and disappointed feeling all
through the audience that somehow there was a mistake,&mdash;nearly everybody
having the impression that, though well meant, it must be a dismal
failure.  But Artemus soon ended all that.  In that quiet, quaint way
that no man has

<pb n="57"/>

ever equaled, and no man can half represent, hesitating, and even apparently
stammering and blushing just a little, in
his effort to say the exact and conscientious thing, seemingly so diffident that
he would apparently get wholly confused
and incapable of getting back to what
he had marked out to say, he began: "I
hope my little picture shop will please
you.  The pictures are by some of the
oldest masters I could find.  I am not an
artist myself, but I have always been
more or less mixed up with art.  Once a
sculpist wanted to make a burst of me,
but I was too modest to let him do it.  I
knew everybody would want one, and it
would get very trying to be constantly
meeting everywhere the educated classes
taking bursts of me to their families."
And then he told them a roundabout
story of something that happened to him
once when he had undertaken to be a
manager; how he had engaged a celebrated living skeleton in New York to
exhibit in Australia.  "He was a splendid skeleton, one of the most reliable
skeletons I had ever met.  But do you
know that very soon after getting to sea
that unprincipled creature began to eat
dreadfully?  Between meals he would
wander around amongst the freight, and
eat everything he could get his hands
on.  He said he thought the salt air
agreed with him!  When we arrived at
Melbourne that dreadful, that perfidious
skeleton weighed seventy-three pounds
more than I did!"  And then he would
apologize for introducing the incident,
and thus keep the audience waiting by
something like this, though never twice
the same.  "I know that this story has
nothing to do with my entertainment,
but one of the principal features of my
entertainment is that it contains so many
things that don't have anything to do
with it."  By this time the audience
would be all alive to try and catch what
he meant by it all.  The very next thing
would be apparently the most childlike
statement about his show.  "I always
try to get the best without much regard
to expense.  I pay my orchestra five
pounds a week, and do his washing!"
Think of the audacity of a man who
could look into the face of John Bright
and the Honorable Robert Lowe, who,
as a London paper of the next day said,
sat in one of the front rows of seats, and
say such things!

</p><p>A considerable portion of this lecture was a really creditable
and worthy piece of description, and some of the illustrations from the
panorama were excellent.  But it was all only a background for the fun
of the showman, and he was supreme master of it.  However much the
audience might laugh, even to a tumult of merriment that would often
last a minute or two, or perhaps longer, Artemus stood with the gravest
mien and unmoved face.  He could not help laughing while writing or
planning a good thing, but no necromancer was ever more selfpoised when
he stood before his audience.

</p><p>The lecture showed much shrewd observation of the Mormons, who
were then at the height of their power.  He knew Brigham Young
personally, as well as Heber C. Kimball, and always spoke of the
latter's wives as the queens of Heber.  But the greatest fun of the
whole was the manipulation of the panorama itself.  Things would go
wrong every now and then, and the audience would fairly scream with
laughter, supposing it was a mistake; while as a matter of fact Artemus
was always at the bottom of it all.  For instance, the prairie fire
would go down at the wrong time, and then break out again when the scene
it was to illustrate had wholly passed, the lecturer meantime apparently
nearly overcome with vexation and despair, that made the whole effect
irresistibly ludicrous.  Then the wrong music would be played, and the
house would break out into roars of laughter, as when he touched upon
one really pathetic recital the piano ground out "Poor Mary Ann."

<pb n="58"/>

</p><p>In the midst of a most instructive talk on the complications of
the Mormon question, or an impressive description of the mountain
scenery in Salt Lake City, he would call attention to an animal in the
foreground of one of the pictures, and remark that it was a horse, as he
had that very morning learned from his artist; and he thought no man had
a right to keep such a fact from the public.  In another moment he would
become seemingly lost to everything about him as he related some
startling and absorbing incident, turning it to ridicule in the next
breath by incidentally remarking, "I did not see this myself, but I had
it from a man-that-is-just-as-<hi rend="italic">relible</hi>-as-I-am!"

</p><p>Of a piece with this was his reference to a very touching speech
he once made, ending by exclaiming, "If Cicero were alive&mdash;" and then,
as if suddenly stricken with a sharp sense of a recent personal
bereavement, he would add, "but he is not; he is dead,&mdash;he is gone from
us."  It usually took two or three minutes for the audience to
straighten itself out after this scene, but all the while the lecturer
stood as if deprecating the whole thing as an unexpected interruption.

</p><p>Humor must have fact, and very familiar fact, as a basis of
interpretation by grotesque and incongruous comparisons.  The fact and
the whimsical statement about it must have a very close relation.  The
whole fun of the pun or the answer to the conundrum lies in its being so
very easy; so that he who keeps nearest to the truth, even in fun, is
most effective.  Nobody understood this better than Artemus, who rarely
made a mistake.  It is true, he led up to the joke by the most elaborate
art,&mdash;but it was always a surprise when it came, and never an
unwholesome one.  Sometimes there would be a most effective and needed
hit at the foibles of the times in his little byplays.  As for instance,
when he pointed out how people who had settled a certain Western town
had prospered; "I know," said he, "a young man who was the son of poor
parents, who had hardly any education, who went there and started in
business without a cent of capital, and at the end of two years he left
the place, owing over two hundred thousand dollars!"  In cold type there
is nothing very funny about this, which must be said of many things that
have amused us; but this man had the power, at any moment, to take hold
of the average audience at any given point, and play with them till they
shrieked with laughter,&mdash;a thing I never saw done before, and never
expect to see again.

</p><p>I have spoken of this particular entertainment thus somewhat at
length, and both as I have seen it many times, and as it has been
described in its London presentation by some personal friends and in the
public press.  The marvel of it seems to be that it was such a success
with the audiences at Egyptian Hall, before a matter-of-fact people, who
have never been supposed capable of great interest in our most
pronounced types of American humor.  But the praise of it was very
great, even from the most cautious authorities.  I subjoin the notice of
it in the London <hi rend="italic">Times</hi>, on the morning after the first
presentation:-
</p><p>Before a large audience, comprising an extraordinary number of
literary celebrities, Mr. Artemus Ward, the noted American humorist,
made his first appearance here as a public lecturer Tuesday evening.
His very first sentences and the way they were received amply sufficed
to prove that his success was certain.  His dialect bears a less evident
mark of the Western world than that of many American actors; but his
jokes are of that true transatlantic type to which no nation beyond the
limits of the States can offer any parallel.  These jokes he lets fall
with an air of profound unconsciousness,&mdash;we may almost say
melancholy,&mdash;which is irresistibly droll.  And he has found an audience
by whom his caustic humor is thoroughly appreciated.  Not one of the odd
pleasantries, slipped out with such imperturbable gravity, misses its
mark, and scarcely a minute elapses at the end of which the sedate
Artemus is not forced to pause till the roar of mirth has subsided;
which shows that the Englishman, puzzled by Yankee politics, is capable
of relishing Yankee jokes, though they are not in the least like his
own.


</p><p>After making several excellent points

<pb n="59"/>

of criticism, all in words of genuine appreciation, the article ends thus:-
</p><p>We can therefore state that the lecture is entertaining to such a
degree that, to those who seek amusement, its brevity is its only fault;
that it is wholly free from offence, though the opportunities for
offence given by the subject of Mormonism are obviously many; and that
it is interspersed not only with irresistible jokes, but with shrewd
remarks, proving that Artemus Ward is a man of reflection as well as a
consummate humorist.


</p><p>But the curtain fell for the last time before his little "picture
shop," on the night of January 23d, 1867, the lecture of that evening
being abruptly broken off by the sudden illness of the lecturer, the
fitful flame of whose life had long been flickering.  Exactly one month
later he made his will, a copy of which lies before me as I write, and
in another week came the end.  Never a man had such friends.  They took
him to the Isle of Jersey, with the hope that the sea breezes might
strengthen him, but it was too late.  They started to take him back to
London, but he could not bear the journey farther than Southampton,
where he died on Wednesday, March 6th, at the age of thirty-three, with
the regret upon his lips that he could not look into his mother's eyes
once more.  To the very last his new friends were around him, one London
club by agreement detailing two of its members at a time to keep him
company and minister to him, although he never knew the arrangement, so
delicately was it managed; and when it was all over they buried him in
Kensal Green.  Afterwards his remains were brought back to his Oxford
County home, and laid to rest beside his father and brother; and only a
little while ago, his mother, too, joined them in the village cemetery,
and over her grave, when I saw it, the blades of new grass were
quivering in the June sun.

</p><p>And thus I have tried to sketch, with the help of notes by Mr.
Hingston and others, in a way that befits truthfulness, and a sincere
friendship as well, the career of a young man who was known to the world
less than ten years, and to the platform only six, and yet who made for
himself a world-wide fame, by very force of his genius; for while other
men have been wits and humorists in a provincial and restricted sense,
and in special and peculiar modes and directions, and have had skill and
art, this man had nothing less than genius; and best of all, it was able
to interpret and illumine the tenderest and most lovable side of human
life.

</p><p>I have purposely avoided any attempt herein to write a mere
biographical sketch.  I have not even desired to tell a new anecdote of
the man, though there are many which I could relate, that, so far as I
know, have never been recorded.  But I have felt that not everything
which has been said and thought of him has been appreciative or just;
and so I have written this, my contribution to the history of the
humorous literature of the country, of which he was unquestionably the
best exponent.  He was greater than all the rest in most ways, and
especially in this: He was a natural interpreter and exponent of the
truest type of distinctively American humor, and yet it never even
tended to coarseness, indirectly or remotely.  He led a merry, and
somewhat whimsical life, but his humor had such a phase and such a
setting that it at once enlarged and illuminated the tender human side.
He himself was broader and manlier for it all.  It did not mar or narrow
him.  It was not strained or unduly cultivated; and so it ministered
naturally and inevitably to his own happiness.  He made a business of
humorous lecturing for these few years, and yet he was always something
more&mdash;at least to his friends&mdash;than a professional funny man.  So far
from there being any abnormal or even undue development of this phase of
fun, his whole make-up was sound and symmetrical.  He was not one man on
the stage and another off.  He was the same everywhere and always, for
his fun was healthy and legitimate.  He

<pb n="60"/>

laughed over his first squibs in the <hi rend="italic">Plain
Dealer</hi> office in Cleveland; he laughed
over the good things he had read or
"thought up" in his boyhood; and he
laughed with his friends and the world
from first to last, because the world was
all beautiful and healthful to him.  He
never did a cheap thing.  He never made
a contortion or a grimace in his life.  His
fun was never intermittent.  It was a
fountain that never had to be forced but
always bubbled.  "You should go to the
pantomime.  You should be made to
laugh.  You should see Harlequin,"
cheerily said old Doctor Abernethy, who
had just come from the play, to the dejected looking patient who stood before
him.&mdash;"See Harlequin!  My God, Doctor, I <hi rend="italic">am</hi> Harlequin, and I am dying from
melancholy!"&mdash;Not so with Artemus
Ward.  The more he could make others
laugh the blither was he, the very gravity of his face at times being the curtain
for his incomparable fun.

</p><p>How many times, since I determined to write this little sketch,
has the picture of the old town where Artemus was born come up before
me.  My own early home was close by, and I knew it as a schoolboy knows
the picture in the book he daily studies.  I knew all its people, young
and old, for I dwelt among them, and taught the children in the schools.
There was the overhanging mountain in the west, that was at once a
bulwark and a shade for the one little street of the village, whose row
of square white houses looked out upon the lake that washed the very
edges of their gardens.  There was the quaint little church with the fan
windows, where Parson Douglass preached for more than fifty years, and
is buried in its shadow.  There was the great white house of the
'Squire, with the long L, and stable with green doors, the heavy
gate-posts in front, and arched portal through which many a lover has
walked with the 'Squire's daughters as they came in from their long
strolls beneath the winter stars.  There was the little white office of
the village Lawyer on the edge of the green, with only a single room,
whose floor was of soft, pale brick, and with the great flaring
fireplace, where more than one statesman had begun his professional and
political career and laid the foundation of his future fortune.  There
was the old Doctor's office, precisely like the other only that it was
painted yellow and had a rough flagstone step, with the skull upon the
mantel over the fireplace, and the skeleton in the closet by the
woodbox, where as a student one of the most celebrated surgeons of his
time came daily from his old home three miles away, and burned the
old-fashioned whale-oil lamp till into the morning hours.  All these and
many more familiar pictures come up to me like the faces of old friends.

</p><p>But in the midst of it all, most potent and pathetic is the
memory of Charles F. Browne, the gentlest and most loyal of friends,
with a tenderness surpassing the love of woman, whose gifts were the
very essence and form of genius, who has touched every note of pathos
and humor in the gamut of the human passions, and who never by deed or
word knowingly brought a feather's weight of sorrow to any human
heart.</p>

<byline>Enoch Knight.</byline>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
