<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="LonPaul"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="LonPaul"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Paul Revere`s Ride</title>
<title type="sort">paul revere s ride</title>
<author>Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1807-1882</author>
<respStmt> 
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>wiretap.spies.com via Alex Catalog Electronic Texts</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">10</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">LonPaul</idno> 
<date value="2000">2000</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2000 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476158</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Paul Revere`s Ride</title>
<title type="parallel">The Landlord`s Tale</title>
<title level="m">Tales of a wayside inn</title>
<title type="sort">paul revere s ride</title>
<author>Henry Wadsworth Longfellow</author>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>8 pages</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Ticknor and Fields</publisher> 
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace> 
<date value="1864">1864</date> 
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: University of Virginia Library PS2269 .A1 1864</idno>
</publicationStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1864">1864</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term> 
<term>poetry</term> 
<term>masculine</term> 
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2000-09">September 2000</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Samuel A. Turner</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
 
<text id="d1"> 
 
<body id="d2"> 
 
<div1 type="poem" id="d3"> 
<head>The Landlord's Tale<lb/> 
Paul Revere's Ride</head> 
 
<lg type="stanza"> 
<l>Listen my children and you shall hear</l> 
<l>Of the midnight ride of Paul Revere,</l> 
<l>On the eighteenth of April, in Seventy-five;</l> 
<l>Hardly a man is now alive</l> 
<l>Who remembers that famous day and year.</l> 
</lg> 
 
<lg type="stanza">  
<l>He said to his friend, "If the British march</l> 
<l>By land or sea from the town to-night,</l> 
<l>Hang a lantern aloft in the belfry arch</l> 
<l>Of the North Church tower as a signal light,&mdash;</l> 
<l>One if by land, and two if by sea;</l> 
<l>And I on the opposite shore will be,</l> 
 
<pb n="19"/> 
 
<l>Ready to ride and spread the alarm</l> 
<l>Through every Middlesex village and farm,</l> 
<l>For the country folk to be up and to arm."</l> 
</lg> 
 
<lg type="stanza">  
<l>Then he said "Good-night!" and with muffled oar</l> 
<l>Silently rowed to the Charlestown shore,</l> 
<l>Just as the moon rose over the bay,</l> 
<l>Where swinging wide at her moorings lay</l> 
<l>The Somerset, British man-of-war;</l> 
<l>A phantom ship, with each mast and spar</l> 
<l>Across the moon like a prison bar,</l> 
<l>And a huge black hulk, that was magnified</l> 
<l>By its own reflection in the tide.</l> 
</lg> 
 
<lg type="stanza">  
<l>Meanwhile, his friend through alley and street</l> 
<l>Wanders and watches, with eager ears,</l> 
<l>Till in the silence around him he hears</l> 
<l>The muster of men at the barrack door,</l> 
<l>The sound of arms, and the tramp of feet,</l> 
 
<pb n="20"/> 
 
<l>And the measured tread of the grenadiers,</l> 
<l>Marching down to their boats on the shore.</l> 
</lg> 
 
<lg type="stanza">  
<l>Then he climbed the tower of the Old North Church,</l> 
<l>By the wooden stairs, with stealthy tread,</l> 
<l>To the belfry chamber overhead,</l> 
<l>And startled the pigeons from their perch</l> 
<l>On the sombre rafters, that round him made</l> 
<l>Masses and moving shapes of shade,&mdash;</l> 
<l>By the trembling ladder, steep and tall,</l> 
<l>To the highest window in the wall,</l> 
<l>Where he paused to listen and look down</l> 
<l>A moment on the roofs of the town</l> 
<l>And the moonlight flowing over all.</l> 
</lg> 
 
<lg type="stanza">  
<l>Beneath, in the churchyard, lay the dead,</l> 
<l>In their night encampment on the hill,</l> 
<l>Wrapped in silence so deep and still</l> 
<l>That he could hear, like a sentinel's tread,</l> 
<l>The watchful night-wind, as it went</l> 
 
<pb n="21"/> 
 
<l>Creeping along from tent to tent,</l> 
<l>And seeming to whisper, "All is well!"</l> 
<l>A moment only he feels the spell</l> 
<l>Of the place and the hour, and the secret dread</l> 
<l>Of the lonely belfry and the dead;</l> 
<l>For suddenly all his thoughts are bent</l> 
<l>On a shadowy something far away,</l> 
<l>Where the river widens to meet the bay,&mdash;</l> 
<l>A line of black that bends and floats</l> 
<l>On the rising tide like a bridge of boats.</l> 
</lg> 
 
<lg type="stanza">  
<l>Meanwhile, impatient to mount and ride,</l> 
<l>Booted and spurred, with a heavy stride</l> 
<l>On the opposite shore walked Paul Revere.</l> 
<l>Now he patted his horse's side,</l> 
<l>Now he gazed at the landscape far and near,</l> 
<l>Then, impetuous, stamped the earth,</l> 
<l>And turned and tightened his saddle girth;</l> 
<l>But mostly he watched with eager search</l> 
<l>The belfry tower of the Old North Church,</l> 
 
<pb n="22"/> 
 
<l>As it rose above the graves on the hill,</l> 
<l>Lonely and spectral and sombre and still.</l> 
<l>And lo! as he looks, on the belfry's height</l> 
<l>A glimmer, and then a gleam of light!</l> 
<l>He springs to the saddle, the bridle he turns,</l> 
<l>But lingers and gazes, till full on his sight</l> 
<l>A second lamp in the belfry burns.</l> 
</lg> 
 
<lg type="stanza">  
<l>A hurry of hoofs in a village street,</l> 
<l>A shape in the moonlight, a bulk in the dark,</l> 
<l>And beneath, from the pebbles, in passing, a spark</l> 
<l>Struck out by a steed flying fearless and fleet;</l> 
<l>That was all! And yet, through the gloom and the light,</l> 
<l>The fate of a nation was riding that night;</l> 
<l>And the spark struck out by that steed, in his flight,</l> 
<l>Kindled the land into flame with its heat.</l> 
 
<pb n="23"/> 
 
 
<l>He has left the village and mounted the steep,</l> 
<l>And beneath him, tranquil and broad and deep,</l> 
<l>Is the Mystic, meeting the ocean tides;</l> 
<l>And under the alders that skirt its edge,</l> 
<l>Now soft on the sand, now loud on the ledge,</l> 
<l>Is heard the tramp of his steed as he rides.</l> 
</lg> 
 
<lg type="stanza">  
<l>It was twelve by the village clock</l> 
<l>When he crossed the bridge into Medford town.</l> 
<l>He heard the crowing of the cock,</l> 
<l>And the barking of the farmer's dog,</l> 
<l>And felt the damp of the river fog,</l> 
<l>That rises after the sun goes down.</l> 
</lg> 
 
<lg type="stanza">  
<l>It was one by the village clock,</l> 
<l>When he galloped into Lexington.</l> 
<l>He saw the gilded weathercock</l> 
<l>Swim in the moonlight as he passed,</l> 
<l>And the meeting-house windows, black and bare,</l> 
 
<pb n="24"/> 
 
<l>Gaze at him with a spectral glare,</l> 
<l>As if they already stood aghast</l> 
<l>At the bloody work they would look upon.</l> 
</lg> 
 
<lg type="stanza">  
<l>It was two by the village clock,</l> 
<l>When he came to the bridge in Concord town.</l> 
<l>He heard the bleating of the flock,</l> 
<l>And the twitter of birds among the trees,</l> 
<l>And felt the breath of the morning breeze</l> 
<l>Blowing over the meadow brown.</l> 
<l>And one was safe and asleep in his bed</l> 
<l>Who at the bridge would be first to fall,</l> 
<l>Who that day would be lying dead,</l> 
<l>Pierced by a British musket ball.</l> 
</lg> 
 
<lg type="stanza">  
<l>You know the rest. In the books you have read</l> 
<l>How the British Regulars fired and fled,&mdash;</l> 
<l>How the farmers gave them ball for ball,</l> 
<l>From behind each fence and farmyard wall,</l> 
 
<pb n="25"/> 
 
<l>Chasing the redcoats down the lane,</l> 
<l>Then crossing the fields to emerge again</l> 
<l>Under the trees at the turn of the road,</l> 
<l>And only pausing to fire and load.</l> 
</lg> 
 
<lg type="stanza">  
<l>So through the night rode Paul Revere;</l> 
<l>And so through the night went his cry of alarm</l> 
<l>To every Middlesex village and farm,&mdash;</l> 
<l>A cry of defiance, and not of fear,</l> 
<l>A voice in the darkness, a knock at the door,</l> 
<l>And a word that shall echo for evermore!</l> 
<l>For, borne on the night-wind of the Past,</l> 
<l>Through all our history, to the last,</l> 
<l>In the hour of darkness and peril and need,</l> 
<l>The people will waken and listen to hear</l> 
<l>The hurrying hoof-beats of that steed,</l> 
<l>And the midnight message of Paul Revere.</l> 
</lg> 
 
</div1> 
 
</body> 
 
</text> 
 
</TEI.2> 
