<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="McnPoor"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="McnPoor">
	<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Poor Little Eddie</title>
<title type="sort">poor little eddie</title>
<author>McNutt, William Slavens</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
					<name>Charles E. Keller</name>
					<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
					<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
			<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">45</num> kilobytes</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
				<idno type="ETC">McnPoor</idno>
				<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476178</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Poor Little Eddie</title>
<title type="sort">poor little eddie</title>
<author>William Slavens McNutt</author>
</titleStmt>
					<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Munsey's Magazine</publisher>
						<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
						<date value="1916">1916</date>
</publicationStmt>
					<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 59</p>
</seriesStmt>
					<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 37-42</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
				<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
					word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
				<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid
					in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
			<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's unique
					cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of Spenser's
					Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1916">1916</date>
</creation>
			<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
			<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-03">March 1994</date>
				<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
					<name>Timothy Jarrett</name>
</respStmt>
				<item>Converted COCOA markings to TEI markings</item>
</change>
			<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
				<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
					<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
				<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

	<text id="d1">
		<body id="d2">

			<div1 type="part" n="1" id="d3">
				<pb n="37"/>
				<head>Part I</head>

				<p>Be helpless &mdash; that's what wins. Be a harmless, wide-eyed boob, and you
					won't have to rise early to get the money. No! All you have to do is lie in bed
					and wait for some sympathetic moneyed person to bring you plenty on a tray.</p>
				<p>Let George do it &mdash; that's the idea. If you can't, there's always some
					George that will. Sure!</p>
				<p>Of course, helpless stupidity is like every other accomplishment &mdash;
					you've got to be perfect to get the best results. You can't expect to have a
					silver spoon rammed down your throat if you're capable of guiding it to your
					lips by your own efforts. Oh, no! Nobody drops pennies into a cup held by a man
					owning one perfectly good eye. A blind man must be totally so to go into
					business for himself.</p>
				<p>Same way with a boob that grows fat on his own folly &mdash; he must be a
					Simon-pure simp. He must believe politicians before an election and
					patent-medicine advertisements when he's sick. </p>
				<p>Absolutely! He must be of the order of intelligence that derives no amusement
					from political editorials in partizan{sic} newspapers. He must be the kind of a
					fellow that stops on a moonlight evening when a pretty girl tells him to.</p>
				<p>If you know any man as foolish as all that, cultivate his friendship while he's
					young and accessible, because later on he'll have money to lend and so many
					office-boys as a body-guard in front of his door that no card but that of a very
					old friend or a millionaire can get through to him.</p>
				<p>Brains are a misfortune, I tell you. If you have brains, you have to use them,
					and the use of brains is work, and work is a curse. Therefore, brains being a
					curse, the lack of them must necessarily be a blessing.</p>
				<p>And good looks? Hub! If a man's good-looking, some girl with no more sense than
					to marry him just because he's handsome, will. Then, if he's a gentleman, he's
					got to work like a dog for the rest of his life, to make enough to atone, so far
					as he can with money &mdash; which is some distance &mdash; for the
					irreparable mistake his manly cow-lick caused her to make.</p>
				<p>And money? Why, if you've got money to start with, you're nothing but shark-bait.
					You can't be friends with anybody. No! You're either an opportunity or a pest.
					The first time you knock at a man's door you're opportunity, and he comes on the
					run at the first tap and borrows money from you. <pb n="38"/> The next time you
					knock you're a pest, and he's not in.</p>
				<p>If a man laughs at a funny story you tell, you don't get any pleasure from
					listening to his mirth. You're wondering how much it will cost you when he gets
					you alone and tells you his funny one about the check that should have been in
					the day before, but probably got lost in the mail. Isn't that right? Absolutely!</p>
				<p>And, girls! Why, if you've got money, and a pretty girl tells you that you're
					different from any man she's ever known, and sits over a few inches nearer, you
					get a thrill all right, but it's not a thrill of ecstasy. It's apprehension that
					makes you shiver. You recall that you've told her she waltzes nicely, and you
					call your lawyer out of bed to ask him how much she can collect on the strength
					of that remark. Isn't that right? Absolutely!</p>
				<p>But a mouse-haired, fish-eyed, pigeon-toed, bow-legged, brain-shy,
					poverty-stricken boob is immune. He hasn't got anything that anybody wants,
					whereas everybody has something that be needs.</p>
				<p>Everything comes his way. The law of supply and demand, I suppose; but it's
					discouraging to an industrious striver like myself, who's been brought up in a
					humble but Presbyterian atmosphere, to believe that the early bird gets the
					worm, when I sit by and see a worm too stupid to know when it's time to get up,
					fall out of his bole in the late afternoon, and gobble the classiest bird on the
					lawn! </p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="part" n="2" id="d4">
				<head>Part II</head>
				<p>I have Eddie May in mind when I speak of a boob. He's the model from which I draw
					my description.</p>
				<p>And yet, come to think of it, Eddie's not so bad. He's not ugly enough to attract
					attention, nor bow-legged enough to be called deformed. His feet are cross-eyed,
					but not to such an extent but what his toes point in the general direction of
					his immediate destination. He knows that Christopher Columbus discovered
					America, and he can count and read, and vote, and perform other little parlor
					tricks indicative of the possession of a certain something akin to human
					intelligence.</p>
				<p>It's a bit hard to explain just what it is about Eddie that makes him such a
					perfect boob. I think, perhaps, it's the consistency of his low average. He can
					do almost anything not very well.</p>
				<p>I remember him chiefly as a sort of concrete absence. He was flesh-and-blood
					substance, and yet you could sit in the room with him for hours and act as if
					you were alone without effort. If you wanted to talk, he was something that had
					the capacity to listen, and if you didn't you could just mentally erase him. If
					you didn't go out of your way to notice him, he wouldn't register on your
					consciousness at all.</p>
				<p>The little shrimp roomed with me and Dick Scanlon at college. He was welcome,
					because we could remember him when the rent came due just long enough to collect
					his share of it, and then forget him for the rest of the time.</p>
				<p>Of course, he did occupy a certain amount of space, but he didn't bother us any
					more than a bureau or desk that would have taken up the same room. Why, I'd ask
					Dick to run out and leave me alone for a time, and then, when he was gone, I'd
					compose love-letters under the inspiration of complete solitude, with Eddie
					sitting on the sofa watching me all the time.</p>
				<p>There was only one thing that Dick and me had as little of as Eddie. That was
					money!</p>
				<p>Our youth was the only license we had for being out of the poorhouse. Of course
					Dick and I had great futures. We've still got 'em. Poor Eddie didn't even have
					the promise of a brilliant career to cheer him while he worked the college for
					his way through.</p>
				<p>Teaching was the only hope Eddie's very best friends had for him. Funny! Nobody
					ever advises a blind man to try for a position as a guide, but an educated boob
					who doesn't know enough to <pb n="39"/> get by at anything else is unanimously
					elected to teach.</p>
				<p>Things financial got steadily worse with Eddie and Dick and me for three years.
					We started with nothing and went in debt. By the end of our junior year we all
					had plenty of debts, but no credit. It was up to us to coin our vacation or
					vacate permanently.</p>
				<p>Dick and I might have booked up with some beach as life-guards, and there was
					always the possibility of Eddie getting on as a waiter in a summer hotel; but
					after figuring a bit we decided that that wouldn't do. Life-savers get very
					little, whether they operate in the surf or the dining-room.</p>
				<p>"Well, what 'll we do?" Eddie piped up, after Dick and I had settled what not to
					do. Eddie never suggested; he always asked.</p>
				<p>"We'll use a little sense," Dick said. Of course we didn't, but he said we would.
					"Who is it," he asked, "that makes the most money &mdash; the man who does
					things or the man who sells things?"</p>
				<p>"Cinch!" I told him. "The winner is the man who sells things that other people
					produce. Am I right?"</p>
				<p>You're as right as the city-hall clock," Dick complimented me. "We're going to
					sell things that other people produce."</p>
				<p>"What things?" Eddie asked.</p>
				<p>He was that way &mdash; a slave to petty details. He had no breadth of
					vision. His mind always dealt with little things.</p>
				<p>"Anything," Dick told him. "It isn't the thing you have for sale that counts,
					it's the way you offer it. Now get that into your head, Eddie," he said. "It
					doesn't make any difference whether you've got ice in the Arctic or
					steam-heating plants in Panama. If you're a salesman, you'll sell 'em. If you're
					not a salesman, you couldn't sell gum-drops to an Eskimo. People don't buy what
					they need; they buy what the salesman makes them think they want. And if you can
					hypnotize them into buying one thing they haven't any use for, you can another.
					I don't know or particularly care what we're going to sell this summer; we're
					going to sell something to somebody for more than it cost us to buy it from
					somebody else. That's success!"</p>
				<p>So we weren't as careful in selecting our article of commerce as we might have
					been. Dick suggested books, but I balked. I pointed out to Dick that while I was
					willing to practise ordinary business dishonesty to get along in the world,
					there were depths of deceit I didn't feel capable of dropping to. After three
					years in college, I knew I couldn't look a man in the eye and advise him to buy
					a book. That was too much!</p>
				<p>Dick argued that there was no sentiment in business, and that we shouldn't allow
					our personal prejudices, or likes and dislikes, to color our salesmanship in any
					way, or to affect our choice of an article to sell.</p>
				<p>"You know, we're not going to buy ourselves something to keep," Dick told me.
					"We're going to buy something to get rid of. Doesn't it seem reasonable to
					believe that you could more easily sell something you have an aversion to than
					something you like? You've had your nose in some sort of a book for so long that
					your idea of a perfectly happy man is one who doesn't know the letters of the
					alphabet. Suppose you had books with you this summer. Wouldn't you work all the
					harder to get rid of them, feeling as you do?"</p>
				<p>It seemed reasonable to believe that, but I didn't. I thought it would be nice to
					arrange with some motor company to act as automobile salesmen, and have them
					furnish us a sample car to travel around the country in and demonstrate with.
					Dick agreed with me, but no motor-car company would; so we compromised on patent
					potato-peelers. </p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="part" n="3" id="d5">
				<head>Part III</head>
				<p>We were all genuinely enthusiastic about the merits of those machines. During our
					freshman year we'd all done our bit of barbering spuds at Mrs. Rariden's <pb
						n="40"/> respectable boarding-house, in return for a pallid meal now and
					then; so we were capable of appreciating the fine points of Popple's Patent
					Potato-Peeler.</p>
				<p>It was a sort of an adaptation of the safety-razor idea. A child, or even a
					cooking-school graduate, could handle it. It took all the art out of
					potato-peeling. You just took the instrument in one hand and the spud in the
					other, and thought about something else for a while. Then you glanced casually
					down at the spud, and &mdash; presto, you found it shaved as smooth as a con
					man's lip!</p>
				<p>We figured on making quite a cleanup out of those vegetable safety-razors. In
					fact, Dick and I felt that if we were lucky we might make enough to afford a
					room without Eddie during our senior year. We both of us liked Eddie in a way,
					but we looked upon him as a sort of youthful frivolity. We felt that the loss of
					him would add to our dignity, and you know how prospective seniors have to
					reckon on those things.</p>
				<p>But what do the common people care about progress, science, art, political
					economy? Nothing! That's why they're common. I talked to some of the commonest
					people during the first week we were on the road with those spud-skinners.
					Common people? I was just like a candidate to 'em; and all that any of them gave
					me was a pain!</p>
				<p>Pay two bits for a little article absolutely indispensable to the successful
					conduct of any well-run household? Kick in with the price of a hair-cut for an
					invention as necessary to the orderly development of culinary science as
					strangers to Broadway? Part with twenty-five ordinary pennies, five nickels, two
					dimes and a jitney, the mere fourth part of an insignificant dollar, to save
					wife or cook from the danger of a lacerated hand and probable death from
					poisoning thereby?</p>
				<p>Common people? Don't argue with me! I know the answer. I proved it to my own
					disgust. Say, if the fountain of youth was a potato-peeler and Ponce de Leon was
					the common people, he wouldn't give a worthy young college man a postal-card to
					write home for money in exchange for a whole gross of them!</p>
				<p>Sell Popple's Patent Potato-Peelers? Why, we couldn't trade 'em for their weight
					in skimmed milk at a dairy-farm! Don't ever tell me farmers are suckers. If
					they're sea-food, they're crabs. Why, I used every form of argument from pure,
					cold, business logic to a consumptive cough, and all I got for my work was a
					variety of negative answers. A farmer can think up more mean ways of saying no
					than a total abstainer!</p>
				<p>Dick and I at least held our own. If we couldn't lift the price of a patent
					potato-peeler from a wayside farm, we didn't stop off and try to lift the
					mortgage. Do you know what Eddie did? Just to show you &mdash; he let a
					woman up in northern Massachusetts tell him why she couldn't buy one of his
					patent potato-peelers to help a poor boy get a college education.</p>
				<p>It was a sad story, mates. The year of the big wind it hadn't rained enough, and
					the year of the big rain there hadn't been any wind. Both years there hadn't
					been any crops. The only things she'd been able to raise on her little farm were
					nine kids and one hog. Her husband drank vile liquor and had the rheumatism. He
					and the hog had both been sick, and the old lady's luck ran true to form. It was
					the boy that died.</p>
				<p>Well, Eddie loaned her his ears, and after she'd poured them full he gave her the
					ten dollars he had left. Then he hunted Dick and me up, and tried to make us
					weep with a second-hand version of the story he went broke on. That was Eddie
					&mdash; boob to the bone!</p>
				<p>Dick and I had already decided to go to Paskamatqua Beach, a summer resort on the
					Maine coast about forty miles distant. A college man with a crease in his
					trousers and no pride can always make some sort of a living at a Maine beach. We
					had no intention of leaving <pb n="41"/> Eddie alone with himself, but we
					thought a good scare might instil into him a proper regard for the gentle art of
					self-preservation, and teach him the value of a deaf ear when impecunious ladies
					with rheumatic husbands and no hog tell hard-luck stories.</p>
				<p>"I'm sorry you're broke, Eddie," I told him. "Dick and I would both like to help
					you out, but neither of us can. We're practically broke, too. We made a mistake
					in bringing patent potato-peelers with us; what we need is some kind of a
					scalpel to peel the surrounding farmer away from his money. Dick and I are going
					to Paskamatqua Beach to make a living. We've only got money enough between us
					for two tickets, so you see how it is."</p>
				<p>"But what am I going to do?" Eddie asked. He spoke in such a pitiful way that I
					almost felt sorry for him. Eddie could arouse sympathy. "I haven't a cent, and I
					don't know where I can get one. You won't leave me alone, will you?"</p>
				<p>"You might go back to the lady you gave the ten to, and ask her for a job," Dick
					suggested. "There ought to be some leftovers now that the hog is dead. The
					prodigal son got by on husks."</p>
				<p>"But he had an address to wire to when they disagreed with him," Eddie pointed
					out. "I haven't."</p>
				<p>"Try beating your way to the beach, Eddie," I advised him. "We'll help you. You
					get on the train with us, and we'll turn two seats together. You scrooch down on
					the floor between them, and we'll pile our suit-cases around you. Then we'll put
					our coats over you and take a chance."</p>
				<p>"You'll take a chance!" Eddie said. "You! What chance do you take?"</p>
				<p>"Why, think of the embarrassment we should suffer if we're found in the company
					of a hobo," Dick explained. "We're taking all the chances; you're not taking
					any. You've got nothing to lose. If they catch you, all they can do is to put
					you off the train. Wherever they dump you, you won't be any worse off than you
					are here. You can't lose!"</p>
				<p>So Eddie got on the train with us and huddled up between the seats. We stacked
					the suit-cases around him and spread our coats over them.</p>
				<p>The other passengers in the car were interested in watching us. One fat,
					red-faced fellow right across the aisle, with a diamond in his tie the size of
					an early strawberry, was particularly curious. Dick tapped his forehead, to
					indicate that our traveling-companion was suffering from an absence of tenants
					on the upper floor.</p>
				<p>Then the conductor came along, and Dick showed him three tickets to Paskamatqua
					Beach. The conductor looked at Dick, and then at me, and then at the three
					tickets.</p>
				<p>Who's the other ticket for?" he asked.</p>
				<p>Dick took the coats off the top of the suit-cases and pointed at poor little
					Eddie, all doubled up on the floor and looking at the conductor like a rabbit in
					a trap sizing up a hungry dog. The conductor leaned over and looked down at him.</p>
				<p>What's be doing down there on the floor?" he asked.</p>
				<p>"He's peculiar," Dick explained. "He likes to ride that way."</p>
				<p>"Well, there's no law against it," the conductor admitted; "but if he gets
					violent I shall hold you two responsible for him!"</p>
				<p>Eddie never did have a sense of humor. He couldn't see anything funny in the
					situation, even after we explained it to him in detail; but I thought the fat,
					red-faced fellow across the aisle would melt himself laughing. I actually feared
					for him.</p>
				<p>Eddie was mad at all of us, but particularly so at the fat fellow who was having
					hysterics. The fat fellow saw how Eddie felt about it, and gave him some good
					advice.</p>
				<p>"Don't get mad, my boy," he said in the tone of a man giving a baccalaureate <pb
						n="42"/> address. "I can tell by the look of you that you haven't the
					faculty for entering into the spirit of things. That's bad! Be a mixer. I have
					to be in my business, and I know the commercial value of it. Always be ready to
					appreciate a good joke, whether it's on the other fellow or on you. Never be
					discomfited and grouchy!"</p>
				<p>And just then &mdash; whango! The train we were on started an argument over
					the issue of right of way with another train coming in the opposite direction on
					the same track. </p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="part" n="4" id="d6">
				<head>Part IV</head>
				<p>To us, in the coaches, the collision seemed like the production of an imaginative
					person's conception of the end of the world. I bounced around between the floor
					and the roof until what was left of the thing that had been a train once more
					established a comparative equilibrium. Then I crawled out through a ragged
					absence of floor, and took a look at the corn-field we had entered and broken.
					We hadn't plowed quite as much of that field as the farmer had, but we'd gone
					deeper. I gave thanks for my deliverance and resolved to start going to church
					again.</p>
				<p>Just then Dick crawled beside me.</p>
				<p>"Eddie's pinned down," he gasped.</p>
				<p>"Give me a hand with him!"</p>
				<p>So I crawled back inside, and we started trying to lift things off poor Eddie.
					There was an awful lot on him. And what a screaming came from underneath! It
					sent the shivers up and down my spine to hear it.</p>
				<p>"Don't yell so, Eddie!" I begged.</p>
				<p>"We'll have you out in a minute."</p>
				<p>We had taken enough carpentry and upholstery off him by that time to enable him
					to twist his head around. He looked up at me and said:</p>
				<p>"I'm not yelling. What you hear is this humorist under me laughing at another
					joke."</p>
				<p>It was the fat man! Eddie was bedded down on him as comfortable as a Persian
					princess on forty-seven sofa-pillows. The fat man was speaking extemporaneously,
					and the form of his remarks was an argument for the use of a manuscript. The
					tenor of his speech was something like this:</p>
				<p>"Save me! Save me! Help! Help! Take your foot out of my eye! You're gouging my
					ear off! Oh, Lord, I'm dying! Now I lay me down to sleep &mdash; quit
					digging your knee into my stomach, will you? If I ever get up out of this I'll
					knock your block! Oh, Lord, I'm dying! Help!</p>
				<p>There wasn't a thing holding him down but Eddie. As soon as we got Eddie loose
					the fat one could have got up all right; but I thought of the big diamond in his
					tie, and of my own destitute condition. When I lifted Eddie off him, I slipped a
					stray seat-back on, and knelt on it to give it weight.</p>
				<p>"Are you in much pain?" I asked him.</p>
				<p>"I'm dying!" he said. "I can feel myself getting weaker. Can't you save me?"</p>
				<p>"There's a heavy timber across your back," I told him. "We'll do our best. Have
					courage! We won't desert you."</p>
				<p>"I just want a crack at that sharp-angled fool who used me for a mattress," he
					wailed. "Oh, Lord, I'm dying! Help! Save me!"</p>
				<p>After I'd sat for a while on the seat-back I'd laid across him, in order to make
					the rescue seem more difficult, and Dick and I had both heaved and groaned as if
					we were straining our ligaments to free him from the death-trap in which he was
					imprisoned, I got up and we saved him.</p>
				<p>He wasn't much hurt. Between cussing Eddie and praying, he'd injured his vocal
					chords somewhat; but aside from that and a few bruises he was all right. He was
					peeved because we wouldn't let him lick Eddie.</p>
				<p>"The little rabbit used my face for a foot-rest," he complained. "When the crash
					came, he picked out my softest spots and settled down on 'em. Don't tell <pb
						n="43"/> me he didn't do it purposely! If he'd had an osteopath's map of my
					anatomy he couldn't have picked out the tender places better. It was
					cold-blooded, scientific, intentional torture, I tell you!"</p>
				<p>But we finally cooled him off and he introduced himself. He was Roland B. Kemmer,
					proprietor of the Bonavita Hotel at Paskamatqua Beach.</p>
				<p>"You gentlemen saved my life," he told Dick and me. "Any time I can do anything
					for you, just let me know."</p>
				<p>I spoke for our side. I didn't dictate or even suggest just what he should do for
					us, but I intimated that almost anything would be welcome, and that there was no
					time like the present.</p>
				<p>"It's fate!" Kemmer declared. "I can use you two boys to our mutual advantage. We
					need presentable young men at the beach &mdash; young college men who can
					dance and play tennis, handle a canoe conservatively, and flirt discreetly.
					We've been frightfully shy of men this year. That's bad, very bad! Where there
					are no men, the women leave; and where the women have left, no men will come.
					The absence of men at a summer hotel is apt to be the first link in a chain of
					misfortune that leads directly to bankruptcy. Come with me! I'll give you free
					room and board at the hotel, all the privileges of the place, and a salary of
					&mdash; say twenty dollars a week for the summer. In return you have a good
					time, and see to it that the young ladies stopping at my hostelry do the same.
					Agreeable?"</p>
				<p>Agreeable? Could he ask such a question and keep a straight face? I looked at
					Dick, and Dick looked at me, and then we both looked at Eddie. That was a
					mistake. If we hadn't looked at him we might have been able to leave him. Poor
					little Eddie!</p>
				<p>His expression of pitiful appeal would have made a cat stay in a dog-kennel. I
					wanted to leave him, but I couldn't. His utter helplessness preyed on my
					conscience. </p>
				<p>What would he do if we left him? Starve, probably! Sit out in the open and
					patiently wait for death, like the boob he was! If he'd had just a modicum of
					sense &mdash; enough, say, to know better than to waste his time pounding
					sand in a rat-hole, I could have laughed harshly and done my duty by myself; but
					he didn't. There he stood, a helpless, hopeless, pitiful boob, waiting to be
					left to his fate.</p>
				<p>The claim for protection that his helplessness presented compelled me to take a
					chance with the first law of nature.</p>
				<p>"Will it be possible for you to make use of our friend in some way?" I asked
					Kemmer. "He's with us, and I feel responsible for him in a way."</p>
				<p>"Use him?" Kemmer shouted. "Him? I'll give him good money to hang by the heels
					and let me use him for a punching-bag! He deliberately stuck his foot in my eye,
					I tell you! Use him? I'll pay his way if he'll go down to old man Carlson's
					hotel, at the other end of the beach from us and hoodoo the place!"</p>
				<p>I didn't try to defend Eddie. What was the use? There's no sense in arguing that
					two and two don't make four.</p>
				<p>"I know," I said. "But he doesn't mean any harm, and he's with us, you see. We
					can't very well leave him."</p>
				<p>"Admirable!" Kemmer said. "Shows a splendid spirit of loyalty. Too bad it's
					wasted on such a poor cause! Well, if he'll obey my orders, I'll give him his
					board and room, but no salary. We have some elderly ladies at the Bonavita who
					enjoy croquet and leisurely strolls. I can use him as an escort for them. They
					frequently require some one to carry their lunches and camp-stools for them."</p>
				<p>"I'm sure you can depend upon me to do my best," Eddie said humbly.</p>
				<p>"I'm sorry I put my foot in your eye, sir."</p>
				<p>"If you didn't have two good friends to intercede for you, you'd be a darn sight
					sorrier!" Kemmer blustered. "I don't want you around, but I'm going to <pb
						n="44"/> try and put up with you as a favor to your two friends, who saved
					my life while you were trying to murder me."</p>
				<p>So the three of us went with Kemmer to the Bonavita Hotel at Paskamatqua Beach.
					Dick and I got right into the swim as regular bathers, and Eddie took up his
					duties as the old ladies' life-guard. While Dick and I swam and played tennis
					and golf and danced and canoed with as fine a bunch of peacherinoes as ever
					troubled a boarding-school, Eddie carried chairs and tables for the hens who had
					ceased to cackle when they laid a birthday, and did his bit with croquet-mallets
					and parasols. Between times he sat on the veranda and read nice novels out loud
					to his flock. </p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="part" n="5" id="d7">
				<head>Part V</head>
				<p>The first week in July, Clarice Claremont, the musical-comedy star, arrived at
					the Bonavita. She said she'd come for a rest, but Dick and I didn't give her
					any. She was a corking good fellow, and we had some great times together for a
					couple of weeks. Dick and I had cooperated up to the time when she arrived, but
					she developed a certain amount of competition between us.</p>
				<p>Then Kemmer's niece, Helen Ardsley, arrived from the West, and our friendship
					entirely ceased. So did our attentions to Miss Claremont.</p>
				<p>Miss Ardsley was an orphan, and while it was evident from the way she dressed and
					acted that she was more or less of a poor relation, we both noticed that Kemmer
					was very fond of her. There was a strong probability that he might do pretty
					well by the man who married his niece.</p>
				<p>Not that that had anything whatever to do with my feelings, or Dick's &mdash;
					positively not! With both of us it was a case of love at first sight, and fair
					play go bang! She was about twenty, a tall, quiet, reserved girl, with light
					hair and big, blue eyes, and as pretty as &mdash; oh, what's the use? She
					was to her sex what Shelley is to poets. Turn your imagination loose with that
					for a tip. You can't go too far.</p>
				<p>Within a week Dick and I were as popular with all the rest of the girls at the
					place as a divorced husband at his ex-wife's second wedding. When Dick was out
					with Miss Ardsley, I was too miserable to bother with anybody else. When I was
					out with her, Dick would sit in his room and read Poe.</p>
				<p>Several of the girls we'd been attentive to left the hotel in somewhat of a huff,
					and in my rare, lucid moments, when I was temporarily able to forget Miss
					Ardsley, it occurred to me that Kemmer had a kick coming. However, he seemed
					satisfied with the way things were going. He was fond of his niece, and I
					suppose he was gratified by the court we paid her, even if it did cost him a few
					guests.</p>
				<p>Miss Claremont was the only one of our former playmates who didn't get offended.
					She was so nice and sympathetic that I used to hunt her up and knock Dick when
					he had Miss Ardsley out. Dick employed the same means of solace when I was the
					lucky one. She'd tell me what Dick said about me, and then tell Dick what I said
					about him. She was nice that way.</p>
				<p>After a few days Dick and I quit speaking to each other, and only conversed
					through her. Then she asked me to do her a favor.</p>
				<p>"Anything," I promised fervently. "Anything you ask."</p>
				<p>Isn't it funny? When a man's in love he'll promise anything fervently, not only
					to the one he's in love with, but to anybody else. Love seems to be a kind of
					promissory mood, doesn't it?</p>
				<p>"I want you to help me in a little press-agent stunt," she said. "My husband's
					coming on Monday &mdash; "</p>
				<p>"Your husband!" I said, with a foolish expression. "Your husband!"</p>
				<p>Yes," she said. "Didn't you know I was married? I thought every one knew that.
					Jack's a dear! Don't you remember reading how he horsewhipped <pb n="45"/> that
					Italian count who was attentive to me? No? The story went all over the country.
					Jack's supposed to be murderously jealous of me. Of course, he's not &mdash;
					he knows he's the only man in the world I ever give a thought to &mdash; but
					it makes good press stuff. Now, I want you to take me out sailing on Monday
					morning. We'll sail out beyond the reef to Perch Island, and go ashore there for
					a few hours. Jack will arrive a little before noon, and will ask for me. When he
					finds out I've gone sailing with you, he'll storm around and make a terrible
					disturbance. Then he'll pace up and down the beach, waiting for us to come back.
					We'll get back about sunset, and Jack will make a most frightful scene."</p>
				<p>I was as dumb as a man in love usually is.</p>
				<p>"But if you know he's coming, why get caught?" I asked.</p>
				<p>Press stuff, silly!" she said. "Well-known actress &mdash; ardent college boy
					&mdash; jealous husband &mdash; don't you see it?"</p>
				<p>"I see the scene," I told her, "but not with myself as any part of the scenery!"</p>
				<p>"But you said you'd do anything for me," she reminded me.</p>
				<p>"Anything but that," I qualified my proffer of assistance.</p>
				<p>I was thinking of Miss Ardsley. I'd have a fine chance with her after being mixed
					up in a mess like that, wouldn't I? Thinking of Miss Ardsley naturally reminded
					me of Dick, who was playing tennis with her at the time.</p>
				<p>"Ask Dick," I advised Miss Claremont.</p>
				<p>"I did," Miss Claremont said. "He recommended you."</p>
				<p>The unprincipled trickster! Trying to get me in wrong with Helen Ardsley!</p>
				<p>Then I had an inspiration. Eddie! Why not? Of course, Eddie had a perfectly good
					reputation, but it didn't do him a particle of good. It was reasonable to assume
					that the loss of it wouldn't do him any harm, wasn't it? Absolutely!</p>
				<p>So I nominated Eddie, and Miss Claremont and I elected him unanimously. We
					decided not to tell him what his duties would be.</p>
				<p>"Why worry him?" I asked Miss Claremont. "If he doesn't know what's coming off,
					he'll act the part all the better. He'll be more convincing in it. Then it 'll
					be fun to watch him when he thinks he's in danger of being murdered by an irate
					husband!"</p>
				<p>"I'd better be seen with him as much as possible between now and Monday," Miss
					Claremont said. "Sort of work up Jack's entrance, you know." </p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="part" n="6" id="d8">
				<head>Part VI</head>
				<p>Work it up? She exploded it! Woof! I've heard some scandal in my time, but never
					any as juicy as the gossip resulting from the friendship that suddenly sprang up
					between Miss Claremont and poor little Eddie.</p>
				<p>Of course, the friendship didn't really spring up; Miss Claremont reared it
					&mdash; carefully. And, also of course, it wasn't a friendship; it was a
					combination of hypnotic terror and business expediency. Eddie was hypnotized and
					terrified, while Miss Claremont was simply working at her trade.</p>
				<p>And the things that were said of Miss Claremont! Tell me, why do all women hate
					an actress? Oh, yes, they do! All women hate actresses they've met. I know they
					write notes to some they've never seen off the stage, but after they once get as
					much as an introduction they write notes about them. Why? Sour grapes?</p>
				<p>Anyhow, what the ladies at the Bonavita, married, single, young, and otherwise,
					said about Miss Claremont after she took up with Eddie would have scorched the
					ears of an asbestos idol.</p>
				<p>She was delighted with the way people had taken notice.</p>
				<p>"It couldn't be better," she told me. "Poor little Eddie's been the old ladies'
					friend for so long that his sudden attachment to a wicked actress stirs up <pb
						n="46"/> real talk. You know," she said, "if a bartender marries a burlesque
					queen, it's hardly worth a mention; but if a Methodist minister elopes with a
					show-girl, it's good for columns, and the A. P. wires get all choked up with the
					horrible details. Of course, Eddie isn't a minister, but be ought to be. He's
					the shyest man! I have to locate him every morning by keen deduction, and kidnap
					him by force. If he could escape me by guile or main strength, he would. If he's
					ever been kissed, some female brute must have sneaked up on him when he wasn't
					looking, and held him helpless. I'm only afraid he'll run out on me before Jack
					gets here!"</p>
				<p>Helen Ardsley was as indignant over poor little Eddie's capture by the Thespian
					enemy as anybody. She besought me to do something about it before it was too
					late.</p>
				<p>"He seems such a nice boy," she said. "It's a shame! I know he hasn't taken up
					with that woman of his own accord. She's hypnotized him. Heretofore he's always
					been so courteous and attentive to the elderly ladies at the hotel, and now he
					spends his entire time with that hussy! And I know he doesn't do it willingly,
					either. I can see by his expression when he's with her that he's ashamed."</p>
				<p>"It 'll do Eddie good," I assured her. "He needs experience. Poor little Eddie! I
					don't think he ever went twice with the same girl before; never could find one
					foolish enough to repeat the mistake of going out with him. He's all right, but
					he's simple."</p>
				<p>I didn't realize how simple he was till he came to me with his trouble.</p>
				<p>"I don't love Miss Claremont, old man," he said, as solemn as a sign-painter
					talking about art. "And I'm afraid she's becoming attached to me. I wouldn't
					cause her pain for the world. I've tried to make her see that I can never return
					her love, but she insists on my going about with her. I simply can't marry her."</p>
				<p>"Why not?" I asked him. "She seems a nice girl."</p>
				<p>"I love another," he said, like a man making his last statement. "I love
					another."</p>
				<p>That was the first time I ever had a real case of hysterics.</p>
				<p>"I didn't know you'd ever had a girl, Eddie," I said, when I'd recovered
					sufficiently to speak. "I never saw you twice with the same one."</p>
				<p>"I am poor," Eddie said. "I am unworthy. I have never told her of my love; but I
					love her!"</p>
				<p>That was like him! If he ever loved a girl, he wouldn't tell her. He'd keep it a
					secret. Boob to the bone, I tell you &mdash; absolutely! </p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="part" n="7" id="d9">
				<head>Part VII</head>
				<p>Dick had a date with Helen Ardsley on the morning of the Monday when husband Jack
					was to arrive and yell for lover Eddie's gore, so I rose early and went for a
					long, lone walk to nurse black thoughts and hatred for the double-dyed villain
					who had once been my friend.</p>
				<p>I got back to the hotel a little before noon, in order to be on hand for Jack's
					entrance. Miss Claremont met me on the veranda.</p>
				<p>"It's all off!" she told me sorrowfully. "Eddie ran out on me. He promised to
					take me sailing this morning as per schedule, but he's gone!"</p>
				<p>"Must be around some place," I said. "I'll hunt him up. There's still time for
					him to take you sailing before your husband gets here."</p>
				<p>Miss Claremont shook her head.</p>
				<p>"He's gone, I tell you. Think I haven't hunted for him? He took the train for
					Portsmouth last night. A good story all gone to pot!"</p>
				<p>Just then Dick came up and looked me over as if I were a sickness he was afraid
					of having.</p>
				<p>"Pretty smart, aren't you?" he sneered.</p>
				<p>"Yes," I admitted. "You just find it out?"</p>

				<pb n="47"/>
				<p>"I've just found out that you're treacherous!" he said. You knew that I had a
					date with Miss Ardsley this morning."</p>
				<p>"Certainly," I said. "What of it?"</p>
				<p>"Where is she?" he asked.</p>
				<p>"How do I know?" I returned.</p>
				<p>"Didn't she go walking with you?" Dick inquired.</p>
				<p>"No," I said. "Didn't she go with you?"</p>
				<p>"No," Dick replied.</p>
				<p>Then the house automobile from the noon train drove up, and we found out where
					Helen Ardsley was. She was right there &mdash; with Eddie.</p>
				<p>We knew before he told us. A man looks as foolish as that only once in a
					lifetime, unless he's married twice.</p>
				<p>"My wife!" Eddie blatted. "My wife! We were married last night in Portsmouth."</p>
				<p>We followed them inside and watched Kemmer get his shock. I was looking for him
					to rave at Eddie, but he was strangely amiable. I didn't understand it then, but
					I did later.</p>
				<p>"I'm so happy, boys!" Helen Ardsley &mdash; I mean Mrs. May, dog-gone it!
					&mdash; told us. "Do you know, I proposed to Eddie! I suppose I ought to be
					ashamed of that, but as a matter of fact I'm proud of it! I knew he loved me all
					the time, and I also knew that he was too bashful to speak. He's the finest man
					in the world, but he lacks self-confidence. He doesn't realize what a perfectly
					splendid fellow he is. He felt himself unworthy of me, and wouldn't court me at
					all. Wasn't that silly of him? I have that horrible Miss Claremont to thank for
					my happiness. If it hadn't been for her shameless attempt to win him, I should
					never have got up the courage to speak; but I wasn't going to stand by and see
					the man whom I loved, and who I knew loved me, dragged down by that dreadful
					person! Oh, boys, I'm so happy about everything! I could almost forgive Miss
					Claremont. You know, I'm really the first and only woman Eddie ever loved. He's
					such a dear! And so modest! Oh!</p>
				<p>Well, that was about all that I could stand at one time. I drifted out on the
					veranda, and Dick followed me. We'd just got done shaking hands and renewing our
					friendship when Kemmer came up.</p>
				<p>He looked awfully blue &mdash; almost as blue as I felt. I didn't blame him.
					Terrible thing to have a pill like Eddie married on you!</p>
				<p>"Between us we sort of spilled the beans, boys," he said gloomily. "I was rather
					hoping one of you two would catch on with my niece."</p>
				<p>"We were rather hoping the same thing," I admitted. "I suppose you'll have to
					give Eddie something to do around the hotel to support him. He hasn't a thing,
					you know."</p>
				<p>Give him something to do around the hotel?" Kemmer gasped. "Give him &mdash;
					you're crazy! I get a salary for running this place. My brother-in-law
					&mdash; my niece's father &mdash; put this hotel up before he died, just
					to give me something to do. Not a nickel's worth of it belongs to me. She owns
					it, and this is only a little plaything of hers. It would take an expert
					accountant six months to figure up all she owns. Why, you boobs, I'm only a poor
					relation of hers! I was hoping she might marry one of you two boys, because I
					thought you might be friendly to me afterward. Give Eddie something to do around
					the hotel? Why, I'm scared stiff for fear he'll remember some of the things I've
					said to him, and have me fired!"</p>
				<p>Be a boob, I tell you &mdash; that's what wins. I admit I have brains and
					good looks, and I still have my future, but &mdash; ah, but! Eddie's in
					Florida at his winter home. I'm in debt at my tailor's, and haven't got any home
					that I can lay claim to if I miss paying the rent for a week.</p>
				<p>Be a boob, I tell you. Be helpless &mdash; that's the idea. Poor little
					Eddie! Waugh!</p>

			</div1>

		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
