<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="NewArti"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;

]>
<TEI.2 id="NewArti">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Articles of Confederation of the United Colonies of England (May 19, 1643)</title>
<title type="sort">articles of confederation of the united colonies of england may 19, 1643</title>
<author>New England Confederation</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/avalon.htm</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">20</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">NewArti</idno>
<date value="2002">2002</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2002 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476253</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Articles of Confederation of the United Colonies of England (May 19, 1643)</title>
<title type="sort">articles of confederation of the united colonies of england may 19, 1643</title>
<editor>Francis Newton Thorpe</editor>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>Original source used by The Avon Project: "The Federal and State Constitutions Colonial Charters, and Other Organic Laws of the
States, Territories, and Colonies New or Heretofore Forming the United States of America, Copiled and Edited Under the Act of
Congress of June 30, 1906.</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
<date value="1909">1909</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: University of Virginia, Alderman Library E173.P93 1893</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1643">1643</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term>
<term>democracy</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2002-08">August 2002</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Irene Oh, University of Virginia, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item/>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="decree" id="d3">
<head>
The Articles of Confederation
of the United Colonies of New England
(May 19, 1643)
</head>
<div2 type="preface" id="d4">
<p>The Articles of Confederation between
the Plantations under the Government of the Massachusetts, the
Plantations under the Government of New Plymouth, the Plantations
under the Government of Connecticut, and the Government of New Haven
with the Plantations in Combination therewith:</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="statement" id="d5">
<p>Whereas we all came<lb/>
into these parts of America with one and the same end and aim, namely,
to advance the Kingdom of our Lord Jesus Christ and to enjoy the
liberties of the Gospel in purity with peace; and whereas in our
settling (by a wise providence of God) we are further dispersed upon
the sea coasts and rivers than was at first intended, so that we can
not according to our desire with convenience communicate in one
government and jurisdiction; and whereas we live encompassed with
people of several nations and strange languages which hereafter may
prove injurious to us or our posterity. And forasmuch as the natives
have formerly committed sundry Insolence and outrages upon several
Plantations of the English and have of late combined themselves
against us: and seeing by reason of those sad distractions in England
which they have heard of, and by which they know vie are hindered from
that humble way of seeking advice, or reaping those comfortable fruits
of protection, which at other times we might well expect.  We
therefore do conceive it our bounder duty, without delay to enter into
a present Consociation amongst ourselves, for mutual help and strength
in all our future concernments: That, as in nation and religion, so in
other respects, we be and continue one according to the tenor and true
meaning of the ensuing articles: Wherefore it is fully agreed and
concluded by and between the parties or Jurisdictions above named, and
they jointly and severally do by these presents agree and conclude
that they all be and henceforth be called by the name of the United
Colonies of New England.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="decree" id="d6"><p>2. The said United
Colonies for themselves and their posterities do jointly and severally
hereby enter into a firm and perpetual league of friendship and amity
for offence and defence, mutual advice and succor upon all just
occasions both for preserving and propagating the truth and liberties
of the Gospel and for their own mutual safety and welfare.
</p></div2>

<div2 type="decree" id="d7"><p>3. It is further agreed
that the Plantations which at present are or hereafter shall be
settled within the limits of the Massachusetts shall be forever under
the Massachusetts and shall have peculiar jurisdiction among
themselves in all cases as an entire body, and that Plymouth,
Connecticut, and New Haven shall each of them have like peculiar
jurisdiction and government within their limits; and in reference to
the Plantations which already are settled, or shall hereafter be
erected, or shall settle within their limits respectively; provided no
other Jurisdiction shall hereafter be taken in as a distinct head or
member of this Confederation, nor shall any other Plantation or
Jurisdiction in present being, and not already in combination or under
the jurisdiction of any of these Confederates, be received by any of
them; nor shall any two of the Confederates join in one Jurisdiction
without consent of the rest, which consent to be interpreted as is
expressed in the sixth article ensuing.  </p>
</div2>
	<div2 type="decree" id="d8"><p>4. It is by these
Confederates agreed that the charge of all just wars, whether
offensive or defensive, upon what part or member of this Confederation
soever they fall, shall both in men, provisions and all other
disbursements be borne by all the parts of this Confederation in
different proportions according to their different ability in manner
following, namely, that the Commissioners for each Jurisdiction from
time to time, as there shall be occasion, bring a true account and
number of all their males in every Plantation, or any way belonging to
or under their several Jurisdictions, of what quality or condition
soever they be, from sixteen years old to threescore, being
inhabitants there. And that according to the different numbers which
from time to time shall be found in each Jurisdiction upon a true and
just account, the service of men and all charges of the war be borne
by the poll: each Jurisdiction or Plantation being left to their own
just course and custom of rating themselves and people according to
their different estates with due respects to their qualities and
exemptions amongst themselves though the Confederation take no notice
of any such privilege: and that according to their different charge of
each Jurisdiction and Plantation the whole advantage of the war (if it
please God so to bless their endeavors) whether it be in lands, goods,
or persons, shall be proportionately divided among the said
Confederates. </p>
	</div2>
		<div2 type="decree" id="d9"><p>5. It is further agreed,
that if any of these Jurisdictions or any Plantation under or in
combination with them, be invaded by any enemy whomsoever, upon notice
and request of any three magistrates of that Jurisdiction so invaded,
the rest of the Confederates without any further meeting or
expostulation shall forthwith send aid to the Confederate in danger
but in different proportions; namely, the Massachusetts an hundred men
sufficiently armed and provided for such a service and journey, and
each of the rest, forty-five so armed and provided, or any less
number, if less be required according to this proportion. But if such
Confederate in danger may be supplied by their next Confederates, not
exceeding the number hereby agreed, they may crave help there, and
seek no further for the present: the charge to be borne as in this
article is expressed: and at the return to be victualled and supplied
with powder and shot for their journey (if there be need) by that
Jurisdiction which employed or sent for them; but none of the
Jurisdictions to exceed these numbers until by a meeting of the
Commissioners for this Confederation a greater aid appear necessary.
And this proportion to continue till upon knowledge of greater numbers
in each Jurisdiction which shall be brought to the next meeting, some
other proportion be ordered. But in any such case of sending men for
present aid, whether before or after such order or alteration, it is
agreed that at the meeting of the Commissioners for this
Confederation, the cause of such war or invasion be duly considered:
and if it appear that the fault lay in the parties so invaded then
that Jurisdiction or Plantation make just satisfaction, both to the
invaders whom they have injured, and bear all the charges of the war
themselves, without requiring any allowance from the rest of the
Confederates towards the same.  And further that if any Jurisdiction
see any danger of invasion approaching, and there be time for a
meeting, that in such a case three magistrates of the Jurisdiction may
summon a meeting at such convenient place as themselves shall think
meet, to consider and provide against the threatened danger; provided
when they are met they may remove to what place they please; only
whilst any of these four Confederates have but three magistrates in
their Jurisdiction, their requests, or summons, from any two of them
shall be accounted of equal force with the three mentioned in both the
clauses of this article, till there be an increase of magistrates
there. </p>
		</div2>
			<div2 type="decree" id="d10"><p>6. It is also agreed, that
for the managing and concluding of all Stairs and concerning the whole
Confederation two Commissioners shall be chosen by and out of each of
these four Jurisdictions:  namely, two for the Massachusetts, two for
Plymouth, two for Connecticut, and two for New Haven, being all in
Church-fellowship with us, which shall bring full power from their
several General Courts respectively to hear, examine, weigh, and
determine all affairs of our war, or peace, leagues, aids, charges,
and numbers of men for war, division of spoils and whatsoever is
gotten by conquest, receiving of more Confederates for Plantations
into combination with any of the Confederates, and all things of like
nature, which are the proper concomitants or consequents of such a
Confederation for amity, offense, and defence: not intermeddling with
the government of any of the Jurisdictions, which by the third article
is preserved entirely to themselves. But if these eight Commissioners
when they meet shall not all agree yet it [is] concluded that any six
of the eight agreeing shall have power to settle and determine the
business in question.  But if six do not agree, that then such
propositions with their reasons so far as they have been debated, be
sent and referred to the four General Courts; namely, the
Massachusetts, Plymouth, Connecticut, and New Haven; and if at all the
said General Courts the business so referred be concluded, then to be
prosecuted by the Confederates and all their members. It is further
agreed that these eight Commissioners shall meet once every year
besides extraordinary meetings (according to the fifth article) to
consider, treat, and conclude of all affairs belonging to this
Confederation, which meeting shall ever be the first Thursday in
September.  And that the next meeting after the date of these
presents, which shall be accounted the second meeting, shall be at
Boston in the Massachusetts, the third at Hartford, the fourth at New
Haven, the fifth at Plymouth, the sixth and seventh at Boston; and
then Hartford, New Haven, and Plymouth, and so n course successively,
if in the meantime some middle place be not found out and agreed on,
which may be commodious for all the Jurisdictions. </p>
			</div2>
				<div2 type="decree" id="d11"><p>7. It is further agreed
that at each meeting of these eight Commissioners, whether ordinary or
extraordinary, they or six of them agreeing as before, may choose
their President out of themselves whose office work shall be to take
care and direct for order and a comely carrying on of all proceedings
in the present meeting: but he shall be invested with no such power or
respect, as by which he shall hinder the propounding or progress of
any business, or any way cast the scales otherwise than in the
precedent article is agreed. </p>
				</div2>
					<div2 type="decree" id="d12"><p>8. It is also agreed that
the Commissioners for this Confederation hereafter at their meetings,
whether ordinary or extraordinary, as they may have commission or
opportunity, do endeavor to frame and establish agreements and orders
in general cases of a civil nature, wherein all the Plantations are
interested, for preserving of peace among themselves, for preventing
as much as may be all occasion of war or differences with others, as
about the free and speedy passage of justice in every Jurisdiction, to
all the Confederates equally as to their own, receiving those that
remove from one Plantation to another without due certificate, how all
the Jurisdictions may carry it towards the Indians, that they neither
grow insolent nor be injured without due satisfaction, lest war break
in upon the Confederates through such miscarriages. It is also agreed
that if any servant run away from his master into any other of these
confederated Jurisdictions, that in such case, upon the ceritficate of
one magistrate in the Jurisdiction out of which the said servant fled,
or upon other due proof; the said servant shall be delivered, either
to his master, or any other that pursues and brings such certificate
or proof. And that upon the escape of any prisoner whatsoever, or
fugitive for any criminal cause, whether breaking prison, or getting
from the officer, or otherwise escaping, upon the certificate of two
magistrates of the Jurisdiction out of which the escape is made, that
he was a prisoner, or such an offender at the time of the escape, the
magistrates, or some of them of that Jurisdiction where for the
present the said prisoner or fugitive abideth, shall forthwith grant
such a warrant as the case will bear, for the apprehending of any such
person, and the delivery of him into the hands of the officer or other
person who pursues him. And if there be help required, for the safe
returning of any such offender, then it shall be granted to him that
craves the same, he paying the charges thereof. </p>
					</div2>
						<div2 type="decree" id="d13"><p>9. And for that the justest
wars may be of dangerous consequence, especially to the smaller
Plantations in these United Colonies, it is agreed that neither the
Massachusetts, Plymouth, Connecticut, nor New Haven, nor any of the
members of them, shall at any time hereafter begin, undertake, or
engage themselves, or this Confederation, or any part thereof in any
war whatsoever (sudden exigencies, with the necessary consequents
thereof excepted), which are also to be moderated as much as the case
will permit, without the consent and agreement of the forementioned
eight Commissioners, or at least six of them, as in the sixth article
is provided: and that no charge be required of any of the
Confederates, in case of a defensive war, till the said Commissioners
have met, and approved the justice of the war, and have agreed upon
the sum of money to be levied, which sum is then to be paid by the
several Confederates in proportion according to the fourth article
</p>
						</div2>
							<div2 type="decree" id="d14"><p>10. That in extraordinary
occasions, when meetings are summoned by three magistrates of any
Jurisdiction, or two as in the fifth article, ii) any of the
Commissioners come not, due warning being given or sent, it is agreed
that four of the Commissioners shall have power to direct a war which
cannot be delayed, and to send for due proportions of men out of each
Jurisdiction, as well as six might do if all met; but not less than
six shall determine the justice of the war, or allow the demands or
bills of charges, or cause any levies to be made for the same.
</p>
							</div2>
							<div2 type="decree" id="d15"><p>11. It is further agreed
that if any of the Confederates shall hereafter break any of these
present articles, or be any other ways injurious to any one of the
other Jurisdictions; such breach of agreement or injury shall be duly
considered and ordered by the Commissioners for the other
Jurisdictions, that both peace and this present Confederation may be
entirely preserved without violation. </p>
							</div2>
								<div2 type="decree" id="d16"><p>12. Lastly, this perpetual
Confederation, and the several articles and agreements thereof being
read and seriously considered, both by the General Court for the
Massachusetts, and by the Commissioners for Plymouth, Connecticut, and
New Haven, were fully allowed and confirmed by three of the forenamed
Confederates, namely, the Massachusetts, Connecticut, and New Haven;
only the Commissioners for Plymouth having no commission to concludes
desired respite until they might advise with their General Court;
whereupon it was agreed and concluded by the said Court of the
Massachusetts, and the Commissioners for the other two Confederates,
that, if Plymouth consent, then the whole treaty as it stands in these
present articles is, and shall continue, firm and stable without
alteration: but if Plymouth come not in yet the other three
Confederates do by these presents confirm the whole Confederation, and
all the articles thereof; only in September next when the second
meeting of the Commissioners is to be at Boston, new consideration may
be taken of the sixth article, which concerns number of Commissioners
for meeting and concluding the affairs of this Confederation to the
satisfaction of the Court of the Massachusetts, and the Commissioners
for the other two Confederates, but the rest to stand unquestioned.
</p>
								</div2>
									<div2 type="decree" id="d17"><p>In testimony whereof, the
General Court of the Massachusetts by their Secretary, and the
Commissioners for Connecticut and New Haven, have subscribed these
present articles of this nineteenth of the third month, commonly
called <date value="1643-05">May, Anno Domini 1643</date>. </p>

<p>At a meeting of the Commissioners for the Confederation held at
Boston the 7th of September, it appearing that the General Court of New
Plymouth and the several townships thereof have read, considered, and
approved these Articles of Confederation, as appeareth by commission of
their General Court bearing date the <date value="1643-08-29">29th of August, 1643</date>,
to Mr.  Edward Winslow and Mr. William Collier to ratify and confirm the
same on their behalf: we therefore, the Commissioners for the
Massachusetts, Connecticut, and New Haven, do also from our several
Governments subscribe unto them.
</p>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>


