<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="NurLaw3"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">

]>
<TEI.2 id="NurLaw3">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Rebecca Nurse Collection:
Rev. Lawson's Narrative of the Examinations of Rebecca Nurse &amp; Dorcas Good</title>
<title type="sort">rebecca nurse collection rev lawsons narrative of the examinations of rebecca nurse &amp; dorcas good</title>
<author>Nurse, Rebecca</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Carolyn Fay, Electronic Text Center</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">7</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
	<idno type="ETC">NurLaw3</idno>
<date value="1998">1998</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1998 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476603</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This document is part of a collection of documents pertaining to the Rebecca Nurse witchcraft trial of 1692 in Salem Village, Massachusetts, collected and edited by Richard B. Trask in "The Devil hath been raised." This electronic collection is a pilot project that is part of a larger digital enterprise which will collect together all of the documents pertaining to the Salem witchcraft trials. This enterprise is a project undertaken by the Electronic Text Center. Benjamin C. Ray, professor of Religious Studies, is the project supervisor.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Rebecca Nurse Collection:
Rev. Lawson's Narrative of the Examinations of Rebecca Nurse &amp; Dorcas Good</title>
<title level="m">"The Devil hath been raised:" A Documentary History of the Salem Village Witchcraft Outbreak of March 1692</title>
<title type="sort">rebecca nurse collection rev lawsons narrative of the examinations of rebecca nurse &amp; dorcas good</title>
<author>Rebecca Nurse</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
<name>Richard B. Trask</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>Revised Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>p. 52</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Yeoman Press</publisher>
<pubPlace>Danvers, Mass.</pubPlace>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: personal copy</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1692-03-24">1692-03-24</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>feminine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1998-07">July 1998</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Carolyn Fay, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="statement" n="1692-03-24" id="d3">
<head>
<hi rend="bold">Rev. Lawson's Narrative of the Examinations
of Rebecca Nurse &amp; Dorcas Good</hi>
</head>
<p>

On Thursday the Twenty fourth of march, (being in course the Lecture
Day, at the Village,) Goodwife N. [urse] was brought before the
Magistrates Mr. Hathorne and Mr.  Corwin, about Ten of Clock, in the
Fore Noon, to be Examined in the Meeting House, the Reverend Mr. Hale,
begun with Prayer, and the Warrant being read, she was required to give
answer, Why she aflicted those persons? she pleaded her owne innocency
with earnestness.Thomas Putmans Wife, Abigail Williams and Thomas
Putmans daughter accused her that she appeared to them, and afflicted
them in their fitts: but some of the other said, that they had seen her,
but knew not that ever she had hurt them; amongst which was Mary Walcut,
who was presently after she had so declared bitten, and cryed out of her
in the meeting-house; producing the Marks of teeth on her wrist. It was
so disposed, that I had not leisure to attend the whole time of
Examination, but both Magistrates and Ministers, told me, that the
things alledged, by the afflicted, and defences made by her, were much
after the same manner, as the former was. And her motions, did produce
like effects as to, Biteing, Pinching, Bruising, Tormenting, at their
Breasts, by her Leaning, and when, bended Back, were as if their Backs
was broken. The afflicted persons said, the Black Man, whispered to her
in the Assembly, and therefore she could not hear what the Magistrates
said unto her. They said also that she did then ride by the
Meeting-house, behind the Black Man. Thomas Putman's wife had a grievous
Fit, in the time of Examination, to the very great Impairing of her
strength, and wasting of her spirits, insomuch as she could hardly move
hand, or foot, when she was carryed out. Others also were there
grievously afflicted, so that there was once such an hideous scrietch
and noise, (which I heard as I walked, at a little distance from the
Meeting house,) as did amaze me, and some that were within, told me the
whole assembly was struck with consternation, and they were afraid, that
those that sate next to them, were under the influence of Witchcraft.
This woman also was that day committed to Salem Prison. The Magistrates
and Ministers also did informe me, that they apprehended a child of
Sarah G. [ood] and Examined it, being between 4 and 5 years of Age And
as to matter of Fact, they did Unanimously affirm, that when this Child,
did but cast its eye upon the afflicted persons, they were tormented,
and they held her Head, and yet so many as her eye could fix upon were
afflicted. Which they did several times make careful observation of the
afflicted complained, they had often been Bitten by this child, and
produced the marks of a small set of teeth, accordingly, this was also
committed to Salem Prison, the child looked hail, and well as other
Children. I saw it at Lieut. Ingersols. After the commitment of Goodw.
N. Tho: Putmans wife was much better, and had no violent fits at all
from that 24th of March, to the 5th of April.  Some others also said
they had not seen her so frequently appear to them, to hurt them.
</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

