<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="NurLaw2"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">

]>
<TEI.2 id="NurLaw2">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Rebecca Nurse Collection:
Rev. Lawson Visits the Thomas Putnam House</title>
<title type="sort">rebecca nurse collection rev lawson visits the thomas putnam house</title>
<author>Nurse, Rebecca</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Carolyn Fay, Electronic Text Center</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">7</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
	<idno type="ETC">NurLaw2</idno>
<date value="1998">1998</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1998 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476602</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This document is part of a collection of documents pertaining to the Rebecca Nurse witchcraft trial of 1692 in Salem Village, Massachusetts, collected and edited by Richard B. Trask in "The Devil hath been raised." This electronic collection is a pilot project that is part of a larger digital enterprise which will collect together all of the documents pertaining to the Salem witchcraft trials. This enterprise is a project undertaken by the Electronic Text Center. Benjamin C. Ray, professor of Religious Studies, is the project supervisor.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Rebecca Nurse Collection:
Rev. Lawson Visits the Thomas Putnam House</title>
<title level="m">"The Devil hath been raised:" A Documentary History of the Salem Village Witchcraft Outbreak of March 1692</title>
<title type="sort">rebecca nurse collection rev lawson visits the thomas putnam house</title>
<author>Rebecca Nurse</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
<name>Richard B. Trask</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>Revised Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>p. 49</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Yeoman Press</publisher>
<pubPlace>Danvers, Mass.</pubPlace>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: personal copy</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1692-03-23">1692-03-23</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>feminine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1998-07">July 1998</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Carolyn Fay, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="statement" n="1692-03-23" id="d3">
<head>
<hi rend="bold">WEDNESDAY,  <date value="1692-03-23">MARCH 23, 1692</date><lb/>

Rev. Lawson Visits the Thomas Putnam House</hi>
</head>
<p>
On Wednesday the 23 of March, I went to Thomas Putmans, on purpose to
see his Wife:  I found her lying on the Bed, having had a sore fit a
little before, she spake to me, and said, she was glad to see me; her
Husband and she, both desired me to pray with her, while she was
sensible; which I did, though the Apparition said, I should not go to
Prayer. At the first beginning she attended; but after a little time,
was taken with a fit: yet continued silent, and seemed to be Asleep:
when Prayer was done, her Husband going to her, found her in a Fit; he
took her off the Bed, to set her on his Knees; but at first she was so
stiff, she could not be bended; but she afterwards set down; but quickly
began to strive violently with her Arms and Leggs; she then began to
Complain of, and as it were to Converse personally with, Goodw.
N.[urse], saying, "Goodw. N. Be gone! Be gone!  Be gone! are you not
ashamed, a Woman of your Profession, to afflict a poor Creature so? what
hurt did I ever do you in my life! you have but two years to live, and
then the Devil will torment your Soul, for this your Name is blotted out
of Gods Book, and it shall never be put in Gods Book again, be gone for
shame, are you not afraid of that which is coming upon you? I Know, I
know, what will make you afraid; the wrath of an Angry God, I am sure
that will make you afraid; be gone, do not tourment me, I know what you
would have (we judged she meant, her Soul) but it is out of your reach;
it is Clothed with the white Robes of Christs Righteousness." After
this, she seemed to dispute with the Apparition about a particular Text
of Scripture. The Apparition seemed to deny it; (the Womans eyes being
fast closed all this time) she said, She was sure there was such a Text;
and she would tell it; and then the Shape would be gone, for said she,
"I am sure you cannot stand before that Text!" then she was sorely
Afflicted; her mouth drawn on one side, and her body strained for about
a minute, and then said, "I will tell, I will tell; it is, it is, it
is!" three or four times, and then was afflicted to hinder her from
telling, at last she broke forth and said, "It is the third Chapter of
the Revelations." I did something scruple the reading it, and did let my
scruple appear, lest Satan should make any, Superstitious he to improve
the Word of the Eternal God. However, tho' not versed in these things, I
judged I might do it this once for an Experiment. I began to read, and
before I had near read through the first verse, she opened her eyes, and
was well; this fit continued near half an hour. Her Husband and the
Spectators told me, she had often been so relieved by reading Texts that
she named, something pertinent to her Case; as Isa. 40. 1. Isa. 49.1.
Isa. 50.1 and several others.

</p><p>
<hi rend="italic">(Deodat Lawson,</hi> A Brief and True Narrative<hi rend="italic">
[Boston, 1692] p. 5-6)</hi>
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

