<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="OslDecl"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;

]>
<TEI.2 id="OslDecl">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Olso Declaration on Freedom of Religion or Belief (1998)</title>
<title type="sort">olso declaration on freedom of religion or belief 1998</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>www.angelfire.com/co/JeStFi/oslodecl.html</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">8</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">OslDecl</idno>
<date value="2001">2001</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2001 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476272</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Illustrations have been included from the original source.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Oslo Declaration on Freedom of Religion or Belief</title>
<title type="sort">oslo declaration on freedom of religion or belief</title>
</titleStmt>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Oslo Conference on Freedom of Religion or Belief</publisher>
<pubPlace>Oslo, Norway</pubPlace>
<date value="1998">1998</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: University of Virginia, Alderman Library BL.H78 L47 2000</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1998">1998</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term>
<term>democracy</term>
<term>religion</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2002-08">August 2002</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Irene Oh, University of Virginia, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item/>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="decree" id="d3">
<head>
THE OSLO DECLARATION
on
FREEDOM OF RELIGION OR BELIEF (1998)</head>

<p><hi rend="italic">Whereas</hi> the Oslo Conference on Freedom of Religion or Belief,
meeting in celebration of the fiftieth anniversary of the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights, reaffirms that every person has the right to
freedom of religion or belief;</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">And whereas</hi> participants in the Oslo Conference have accepted the
challenge to build an international coalition and to develop a strategic
plan of action to achieve substantial progress in and give practical
support to the implementation of Article 18 of the Universal Declaration
of Human Rights, Article 18 of the International Covenant on Civil and
Political Rights, and the 1981 United Nations Declaration of the
Elimination of All Forms of Intolerance and of Discrimination Based on
Religion or Belief;</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Therefore</hi>, we the participants in the Oslo Conference:</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Recognize</hi> that religions and beliefs teach peace and good
will;</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Recognize</hi> that religions and beliefs may be misused to cause
intolerance, discrimination and prejudice, and have all too often been
used to deny the rights and freedoms of others;</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Affirm</hi> that every human being has a responsibility to condemn
discrimination and intolerance based on religion or belief, and to apply
religion or belief in support of human dignity and peace;</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Consider</hi> the founding of the United Nations and the adoption of the
Universal Declaration of Human Rights to be watershed events, in which the
world community recognized for the first time that the existence of human
rights transcends the laws of sovereign states;</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Confirm</hi> that Article 18 of both the Universal Declaration of Human
Rights and of the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights
together with other instruments create both a mandate for freedom of
religion or belief and a universal standard around which we wish to
rally;</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Recognize</hi> that the U.N. has made significant accomplishments in
strengthening this universal standard by passage of the 1981 U.N.
Declaration on the Elimination of All Forms of Intolerance and of
Discrimination Based on Religion or Belief, by the appointments of a
Special Rapporteur to monitor its implementation, and by further defining
freedom of religion or belief in the General Comment on Article 18 of the
International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights;</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Recommend</hi> that the U.N. Commission on Human Rights change the title
of the Rapporteur to Special Rapporteur on Freedom of Religion or
Belief;</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Urge</hi> increased financial and personnel support to the U.N. to
implement the work of the Special Rapporteur and his
recommendations;</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Request</hi> the U.N. High Commissioner for Human Rights to develop a
coordinated plan to focus resources of the United Nations, including all
specialized agencies such as UNESCO, ILO, UNDP, and UNHCR on problems
involving freedom of religion or belief;</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Recognize</hi> the importance of UNESCO's work for peace through
religious and cultural dialogue and call for intensified cooperation with
in this field;</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Urge</hi> scholars and teachers to study and apply Article 18 of the
International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights and the 1981
Declaration as universal standards on freedom of religion or belief and as
a way to solve problems of intolerance and discrimination caused by
competing beliefs;</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Challenge</hi> religious bodies, interfaith associations,
non-governmental organizations and academic institutions to create
educational programs using the 1981 Declaration as a universal standard to
build a culture of tolerance and understanding and respect between people
of diverse beliefs;</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Further urge</hi> U.N. member states to use the 1981 Declaration and
other relevant instruments to mediate, negotiate, and resolve intolerance,
discrimination, injustice and violence in conflicts where religion or
belief plays a role;</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Support</hi> research and development of other informational resources
and methodologies for collecting information, monitoring compliance and
initiating comparative country studies to strengthen the work of the
United Nations and protect freedom of religion or belief;</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Urge</hi> the organizers and sponsors of the Oslo Conference, in
consultation with Conference participants:</p>

<p>to review the discussions and recommendations of the Conference, with
the purpose of creating an "Oslo Coalition on Freedom of Religion or
Belief," inviting support and participation by governments, religious or
belief communities, academic institutions and non-governmental
organizations; and</p>

<p>to develop a strategic plan of action and seek funding to carry out
programs and projects based on its recommendations, in cooperation with
the United Nations.</p>

<p><date value="1998-08-15">August 15, 1998</date></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
