<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="OuiLitt"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="OuiLitt">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Little Thief</title>
<title type="sort">little thief</title>
<author>Ouida, 1839-1908</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">16</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">OuiLitt</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476273</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Little Thief</title>
<title type="sort">little thief</title>
<author>Ouida [Marie Louis de la Ram&eacute;e]</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Schlicht &amp; Field</publisher>
<pubPlace>Rochester, New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1900-03">March, 1900</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Cosmopolitan; March, 1900; Vol. XXVII, No. 5, pp.
552-555</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG
versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center
scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of
the text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in
AusEmma1 for page one of  Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1900-03">March, 1900</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-12">December, 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Bryson Clevenger, Jr.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Minimal TEI tagging, TEI header, and spellchecking against
print version</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="552"/>
<head>
Ouida.  "A Little Thief."<lb/> <hi rend="italic">Cosmopolitan</hi> 28 (Mar. 1900):
    552-554.
</head>


<p>IT was a warm night in February; there was the scent of
narcissus and violets already on the air, and the Arno was silvered
by the light of a full moon, as it flowed under the arches of the
Ponte Vecchio.
</p><p> A small boy was leaning over the parapet and gazing at the
water when he ought to have been in bed.  But his bed was only a
bit of sacking, with some dead maize leaves underneath it; and he
liked better the radiant moonlight and the movements of the fresh,
clear, pungent night air.
</p><p> His family name was a fine and ancient one, but he was
called only Lillino now.  His parents were dead; he had only an old
great-grandmother, bedridden in the one room in Oltrarno, where he
lived with her.  He kept her and himself by selling matches, and he
was as thin as a match himself, but was a pretty boy, with his
great brown eyes and his loose auburn curls, and such a wistful,
pleading smile that hardly any girl or woman passed him without
buying, and no dog without a kindly dab of the tongue.
</p><p> His mother had died at his birth, and his father had shot
himself after losing all he possessed at a gambling club; the off-spring of a secret marriage, the child was left to his foster-mother, a good woman, who cultivated a little farm on the hills
above Impruneta.
</p><p> She and her spouse maintained him for seven years; then the
husband deserted her and emigrated, and a year later she was killed
by the steam-tram near the Gelsomino, and there was only her old
mother left, the aged creature whom he called his "Nonna."
</p><p> She was turned out of their little farm, and clinging to
the child, and the child to her, they went down into the city to
live, and she mended silken hose and he sold matches.
</p><p> It was only in this last year, his tenth year, that the
veins of her legs swelled so much that they kept her bedridden, and
her sight failed her also, and the matches became their only
support.  One by one all the little objects that his Nonna had
brought with her into the town were sold, and there remained
nothing but the ragged clothes which covered them both and a few
miserable
necessary things.  They would have died of hunger and of cold but
for the charity of those who were not much better off than
themselves, and for the occasional alms which ladies, passing in
the streets, arrested by the pathetic beauty of Lillino's face, put
into his small thin hand.  This was not begging, for every one took
a box of matches, knowing that if they did not they would cause him
trouble with the police, for in theory begging is forbidden.
</p><p> Lillino's body was in the streets, but his soul was in the
country.  It was three years since he had seen it, but he had never
ceased to think of it.  "Let us go back, Nonna.  Let us go back,"
he said continually.  But the poor old bedridden woman could only
cry feebly and answer: "Oh, my dearie, who would take us there?
Who would keep us when we got there?  We are here, and here we must
abide.  Perhaps if the saints would kill me outright somebody would
be kinder to you and carry you out of this cruel place&mdash;all stones
and noise and clatter, and full of food and drink for those whose
bellies are full already, and never a bit or drop for those who
starve in it."
</p><p> "Do not die, Nonna," said Lillino, clasping his arms about
her.  "Do not die and go away into the earth.  Pray, pray, do not.
I have only you."
</p><p> "My poor little one, and what good am I?" she murmured,
laying her hand in blessing on his head.  "An old log, not even
good for burning, for I have no sap left in me.  Alas! alas!"
</p><p> But she was all he had to care for, this bundle of rags
under her rugged coverlet, and he had known her all his life; she
had been always exceedingly good to him, and in that time, though
already aged, had been a strong and hearty woman and his earliest
memories had been of merrily running beside her, with his hand on
her skirt, to cut water-cresses in the ditches, <pb n="553"/>
or drive the ducks to the rivulet, or gather olives, chestnuts,
blackberries, wood-strawberries, or do any one of those other
lighter labors which occupy the old people and the young children
in the fields and woods, and make everybody useful from three years
old to ninety.
</p><p> Now Nonna was of use no more and Lillino tried with all his
might to do his utmost to be of use enough for two.  He never
doubted that he belonged to her, or rather he never thought about
it; he had always seen her near him, and he had always heard Mamma
Rosa, whom he had been taught to believe was his mother, call her
grandmother.  No one had ever told him that he had patrician blood
in his veins.  This poor old creature, scarcely alive, except in
the warmth of her affections and the pains of her limbs, was all he
had on earth, and he clung to her with the tenacity of a tender and
timid nature.  His idea was that if only he could get Nonna back to
the country she would become well and strong once more, and able to
walk out in those green places and amongst those grassy streamlets
which neither she nor he had ever forgotten.
</p><p> "I am sure she would get well," he thought, as he leaned
over the stone parapet and watched the river glide away under the
moon. </p><p> But how to carry her there?  She was like a log, as
she said, with limbs which were wholly useless, without power to
move any part of her except her lips, dependent on her neighbors
for every bit and drop.  Nothing but a miracle could ever raise her
again on her feet; but Lillino believed in miracles, or, more truly
speaking, miracles seemed natural to him&mdash;a constant part of daily
life.
</p><p> True, he saw them no more in the streets and the homes, but
he saw them in the frescoes, in the sculptures, in the carvings in
the churches, and he thought the halt and the blind and the sick
could all be cured if Some One unseen and unknown would be good
enough to do it.  But all he saw and heard in the unkind streets
began to make him feel that the real meaning of miracles was money--that strange, dirty, ugly paper thing which was, he saw, so
powerful in such amazing ways.  What was it, if not a miracle, that
a scrap of soiled paper, crumpled and dog-eared, could procure
bread for the hungry and wine for the weak?  Even those black-rimmed bronze coins&mdash;how much they could do, only passing from hand
to hand!  Lillino had not much understanding, and Mamma Rosa had
been too busy herself all day long to attend to his education,
either moral or mental.  He groped his way as he could to his few
ideas, and his thoughts were confused and tangled.  But these two
were clear to him: Nonna would get well if she went back to the
country, and with money she could be taken there, carried, he was
not sure how, but in some way, back to those vineyards and pastures
and running brooks where his babyhood had been spent, and her whole
life had passed.  But the extremely scanty means he ever gained did
not even suffice to keep life in himself and her, and pay for their
one room under the roof.
</p><p> This night, as he leaned over the river wall, the moon was
at the full, and the water was high; it had a strange attraction
for him as it flowed toward the weir reflecting the long double
lines of the lamps.  He came away from it reluctantly, not to be
scolded by the person of the house for being out too late.
</p><p> The garret which he and the old woman rented was a mere
nook under the eaves of an old house.  As he drew near it, on the
moonlit flags of the old street he saw an object shining: his feet
touched it, he picked it up; it was a little bag of golden
chainwork with a gold snap; he opened it; he saw it was full of
coins&mdash;such coins as he had never seen in his life, except in
little bowls in money-changers' windows.  The Madonna or Mamma Rosa
had sent it.  Nothing else occurred to him.  It was a miracle!  An
answer to his prayer!
</p><p> He slipped his hand which had closed on it into his ragged
shirt, and took his homeward way, his ears singing and his brain
turning, and his heart throbbing in his persuasion that Some One in
heaven, Some One had heard and answered his prayer!  Surely it was
Mamma Rosa, sitting now beside the Madonna!
</p><p> Mamma Rosa had always taught him, indeed, that what was
other people's property he must never touch or take, but this thing
was no one's; it was lying in his <pb n="554"/>  path; it was
plainly put there by some merciful hand; it was a miraculous gift,
a gift of the heavenly host, who were so much kinder than these on
earth. </p><p> He climbed the steep stone stairs, ninety-three from
the basement to the attic, dark, slippery, foul-smelling, full of
dust and mud and cobwebs; he hugged the little purse in his breast,
he smiled to himself radiantly as he climbed up the steps one by
one with tired, aching feet.  He opened the wooden door by its
latch and gently entered the room, for Nonna might be asleep, and
it would harm her to startle her, even to tell her such good
tidings. </p><p> Noiselessly he ran across the brick floor and sat
down on his own bit of sacking, and began to think.  Now he had all
this money it would be easy to move his Nonna out of the city and
carry her up, up, up, along the green and gracious ascent of the
hills, and never stop until she could be set down under the peach
boughs and the walnut leaves where the little brimming brooks were
running amidst the grass.
</p><p> He opened the pretty bag again and poured the gold coins
out upon the sacking.  The moon-rays shone also upon them.  There
were twenty.  What they were worth he did not know; but a great
deal, he felt sure.  With them Nonna would be able to buy their
farm, and they could live happily there, both of them forever,
seeing the blossoms and the fruits come and go.
</p><p> He longed to wake her, but he dared not; one of the women
had told him never to disturb her when she slept.  How glad she
would be when she did awake and heard that they could both go home!
There was a carter who lived in the house; he would take them up
into the hills, making a couch of hay in the cart for Nonna; that
would be easy to do, when once they could give him a shining gold-piece for his trouble.  Once there, all the rest would follow of
itself.  When once she could see the green grass again, and see the
buds on the fruit-trees, she would begin to move her limbs and get
back her strength, and they would pay to have a mass said every day
in the church up above amongst the olives, a mass of thanksgiving
to the Madonna and Mamma Rosa.
</p><p> He had eaten only a bit of black bread all the day, and his
brain was a little dim, and his thoughts were not very clear.  He
had been walking about on the stones ever since morning.  His head
ached and his feet ached, and his brow and lips were hot and dry,
but he was so happy.  The moon looked at him over the trees and
seemed to smile; he lay down with his arms outstretched, so that
they embraced the motionless body of his only friend, and his
hands, clasping the little purse, rested upon the rags which
covered her.
</p><p> "She will be so glad when she awakes," he thought; "when
she awakes and hears we can go home."
</p><p> Then he, too, fell asleep and dreamed of angels and
fountains of gold, and little red-throated birds singing amongst
flowering fruit-trees, and grassy paths beneath the vines, and
brown rippling rivulets, and Mamma Rosa standing smiling with the
sun about her feet, and saying, "Our Lady sent me."
</p><p> Then his sleep became too deep for dreams, and he breathed
deeply, unconsciously, whilst the moon passed upward and its light
ceased to shine upon his face and that of his Nonna.
</p><p> The trampling of feet on the brick floor aroused him; a
rude hand clutched his shoulder and another hand seized the gold.
"Here is the thief," said a brutal voice, "and here is the lady's
purse." </p><p> "The little heartless wretch!" said a voice as
rude.  "Look!  He is safe here, he thinks, because the old woman is
dead!" </p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
