<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="PeaMoza"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="PeaMoza"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mozart: A Fantasy</title>
<title type="sort">mozart a fantasy</title>
<author>Peattie, Elia Wilkinson, 1862-1935</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>  
<name>Judy Boss</name>  
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>  
<name/>  
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>Stephen Ramsay, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">12</num> kilobytes</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>  
<idno type="ETC">PeaMoza</idno>  
<date value="1998">1998</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1998 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476285</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>  
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mozart: A Fantasy</title>
<title level="j">The Atlantic Monthly : A Magazine of Literature, Science, Art, and Politics.</title>
<title type="sort">mozart a fantasy</title>
<author>Elia W. Peattie</author>
</titleStmt>  
<editionStmt>
<p>Volume 90, No. 541</p>
</editionStmt>  
<extent>pp. 634-636</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Houghton Mifflin</publisher>  
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>  
<date value="1902-11">November 1902</date>  
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa Library, Call Number: AP 2 .A8 1902</idno>
</publicationStmt>  
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>  
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>  
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>  
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>  
</encodingDesc>  
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1902">1902</date>
</creation>  
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>  
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>  
<term>prose</term>  
<term>masculine</term>  
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
</profileDesc>  
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1998-09">September 1998</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Stephen Ramsay, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>  
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>  
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
 <pb n="634"/> 
<head>MOZART: A FANTASY.</head> 
 
<p>WHEN the winds of the morning were first loosed by God, 
they leaped like hounds from the leash, harking through the spaces 
between the worlds in search of the Things That Are.  In their 
adventurings they came upon All Things, &mdash; stars that were blue as 
forged steel, those red as blood, the ringed worlds, the crimson and 
the yellow suns in their solitudes, scintillant seas of star dust, the 
reservoirs of man's knowledge; the amazing chaos of the Things 
That Were Yet to Be. 
</p><p>Also they came upon the place of the Birth of Waters; and a 
very strange place of great dimness, where was only the Silence of 
Nothingness.  There, huddling in the chill was a lair of monstrous 
creatures, Discords, waiting for the chiding of human beings that 
they might find a medium for their voices.  They writhed there, 
through the &aelig;ons, torn and tortured for lack of outcry. 
</p><p>A comet's journey from this place, drifting in long shafts from 
the centremost sun, were other creatures, very wonderful and of 
potential loveliness, known to all the stars as Harmonies.  They, 
likewise, waited for the lifting of the stillness.  They watched with 
holy eagerness for souls to voice that which broke from them 
against the Walls of Silence in impetuous waves. 
</p><p>Not a spirit hurried from the Place of Souls through the white 
Vast toward the habitations of men, but all the band set on it, 
struggling for the mastery.  The Harmonies went with the swiftness 
of light; but the Discords had within them the strength of the 
Powers of Darkness, and only once in a full round of time did a 
Harmony break through their black band and merge into Life.  The 
victory was with the Discord for a time and times. 
</p><p>So it came about that soul after soul sped to the body which 
was to house it, hectored with a dinning Discord which clung to it as 
tentacled creatures of the nether deep cling to drowned men.  The 
spirits in this abject case were doomed to the deliberate and cruel 
sins, to quarrelings, to narrowness of vision, to greed and doubt; 
their faces grew craven, their eyes were accursed with the evasive 
glance. 
</p><p>When, by the chance of a chance, a Harmony gained the 
mastery, it made life lovely for the being it inhabited, and men 
found fair names by which to denominate such a one, &mdash; poet, or 
liberator, or maker of songs. 
</p><p>The winds learned all this in their excursions, &mdash; they learned 
all things, &mdash; and they came in time to take their part in this mystic 
war.  The black winds of destruction and of night leagued 
themselves with the Discords; the blossom-bursting winds, the 
white and perfumed servitors of the dawn, the gallant winds from 
mountains and from mesas, enlisted with the Harmonies. 
</p><p>A century and half a century of yesterdays, a swift soul, 
dropping between the spheres toward Earth, was set upon by these 
contending spirits.  In the Vast, among the stellar solitudes they 
fought, and in the scorching nebula of a yet 
 
 
<pb n="635"/>  
 
unrounded star the conflict reached its height.  Then came a great 
white wind from the farthest chamber of the East and smote the 
Discords, till they mingled with that molten world; and from the 
confusion of the warring creatures the gentle soul went on its way 
tremblingly toward Earth. 
</p><p>Seven Harmonies swept after it, &mdash; seven Harmonies, wild with 
impatience for utterance.  One Harmony was for song and one for 
reeds, one for horns, one for instruments of the drawn strings, and 
one for keys of ivory on resonant boards of brass; one for harmony 
of thought; and one, serene, past man's divinest dreams, for 
harmony of life.  All these swung downward with the gentle soul, 
and made such sweetness in their going that men, a-toiling on the 
Earth, listened, amazed, thinking that after years of yearning they 
heard the spheres. 
</p><p>The seven Harmonies, the gentle soul, and a delicate fresh-born body became as one, &mdash; a vibrating entity, a man-child with a 
mystic power, a lyric babe, smiling at unheard melodies. 
</p><p>"This little child," the old nurse said, "seems to be in the 
company of angels.  It cannot be that he has long to live." 
</p><p>The Harmonies within him were too eager for articulation to 
wait in patience for his body to grow.  Five years of dreams made 
him a master of the instruments.  But if he was spared the need of 
study, he was refused the meed of rest.  He was scourged with 
beauty; the thongs of his spirit goaded him day and night.  He was 
the servitor of the creatures that had come from the shafts of the 
central sun; and they, knowing that in the brief term of a man's life 
there was not a tithe of the time required to express their intent; 
knowing, too, that it might be cycles before they would again have 
domination over a willing soul, clamored &mdash; as with the sonorous 
clamoring of many high-swung bells &mdash; for the use of his hands, his 
eyes, his voice, his brain and heart. 
</p><p>"I have such a sense of religion," he wrote, "that I shall never 
do anything I would not do before the whole world." 
</p><p>Poverty was with him, if he had noticed it.  Love was his, for 
his sanctifying.  Riches he passed by, absently smiling.  Loyalty was 
his, because he was without cognizance of treason. 
</p><p>By reason that the Harmonies loved order, sequence, and 
technique as much as ecstasy, it was a part of his toil to develop the 
science as well as the emotion of his art.  Praise, happiness, 
concord, these he knew for forms of law, which he formulated into 
a code.  To express and illustrate it, he worked when others slept, &mdash; 
when others danced.  He forgot the material necessities of the body.  
He sung out his soul in masses; he whispered of love in lyrics; he 
expressed the storm and stress of his spirit in operas, sonatas, 
symphonies.  He had no choice but to write as if each line were to 
be dedicated to the Most High.  Always, the fair Harmony of 
beautiful living kept him unspotted from the world. 
</p><p>He was a monarch, with no need for sceptre or for crown.  
Lesser kings were forgotten when his name was mentioned.  Others 
enriched themselves by means of his genius; but as for him, he 
often went from his bare lodgings to pawn for bread the jewels 
which had been flung at him in idle appreciation.  It was not 
permitted him to take thought of wealth, or place, or peace.  He was 
an instrument, fashioned for the playing; he was the vehicle of holy 
passions; he bent his will and did not question. 
</p><p>Whatever is most exquisite is most sad.  It is the law of nature 
that rapture, vibrating round its perfect circle, shall meet with pain.  
Love, at its best, melts in tears; tears at their bitterest find God's 
pure joy.  Thus it came about that the Harmonies, ever striving 
through this body for their ultimate utterance, reached at the climax 
the great moan called Mozart's Requiem Mass. 
</p><p>It is the processional to which souls, 
 
 
<pb n="636"/>  
 
cassocked for Death, march forth into the Presence.  It is a ladder of 
song by which the sorrowful may climb from the grief of the grave 
to the peace of it. 
</p><p>One night came a stranger, knocking, and commanded: &mdash; 
</p><p>"Write me a mass for the dead." 
</p><p>"Surely my hour is almost come," said the musician.  "I must 
write." 
</p><p>And again came the stranger in the night and asked: &mdash; 
</p><p>"Is the mass for the dead ready for the playing?" 
</p><p>The tension of toil was tightened.  The Harmonies, filled with 
such rapture as only immortal spirits know, did their utmost.  The 
musician lay dead, with the Requiem Mass in his hand. 
</p><p>The next night came the stranger querying: &mdash; 
</p><p>"Is the mass for the dead complete?" 
</p><p>In the wonder and majesty of the stars the seven Harmonies 
went their way.  Their flight left a quiver of light like that a burning 
meteor streaks across the affrighted sky.  The soul of Wolfgang 
Amadeus Mozart winged back to the Place of Souls, and the body 
was tumbled fin a pauper's grave, &mdash; a grave in which two others 
rested, very humble and much worn with toil.  No stone marks the 
spot.  The place has been forgotten. 
</p><p>But the labors of the Harmonies are among the deathless 
things.  And whenever a man can fittingly reproduce them, all 
discord dies in the air and in the soul, and those who listen are as 
little children lifted into a world where sin and greed are not, and 
where Harmony is perfect, &mdash; the Harmony which includes all 
things. 
</p> 
 
<closer> 
 
<signed><hi rend="italic">Elia W. Peattie.</hi></signed> 
 
</closer> 
 
</div1> 
 
 
 
</body> 
 
</text> 
 
</TEI.2> 
