<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="PoeBere"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="PoeBere"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Berenice</title>
<title type="sort">berenice</title>
<author>Poe, Edgar Allan, 1809-1849</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">25</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">PoeBere</idno> 
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476302</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>First created by Judy Boss; the text then went to Tom Almy's 
Bitter Butter Better BBS, where he removed the pagination, and then to 
The Internet Wiretap.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Tales of Mystery and Imagination</title>
<title type="sort">tales of mystery and imagination</title>
<author>Edgar Allan Poe</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>J. M. Dent &amp; Sons</publisher> 
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace> 
<date value="1912">1912</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Source copy consulted: Call no. PS 2612 A1 1912, Alderman Library, University of Virginia</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme 
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of 
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1835">1835</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language> 
<language id="lat">Latin</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-11">November 1994</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Repaginated because Judy Boss identified the source of the text; 
updated tags and header</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="1993-07">July 1993</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Minimal TEI tagging; note that this text is from an unknown 
edition, so the text has been paginated to The Complete Works of Edgar 
Allan Poe, ed. by James A. Harrison, vol. 2, New York: Thomas Y. 
Crowell and Company, 1902; unambiguous line-end hyphenation has been 
removed by Internet Wiretap</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 

<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
<head>Berenice</head> 
<pb n="175"/>  

<epigraph>
<q> 
Dicebant mihi sodales, si sepulchrum amicae visitarem, curas meas<lb/> 
aliquantulum fore levatas.   &mdash; IBN ZAIAT
</q> 
</epigraph> 

 

<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d4">
 
<p>Misery is manifold.  The wretchedness of earth is multiform. 
Overreaching the wide horizon as the rainbow, its hues are as 
various as the hues of the arch, &mdash; as distinct too, yet as 
intimately blended.  Overreaching the wide horizon as the 
rainbow.  How is it that from beauty I have derived a type of 
unloveliness? &mdash; from the covenant of peace a simile of sorrow? 
But as, in ethics, evil is a consequence of good, so, in fact, 
out of joy is sorrow born.  Either the memory of past bliss is 
the anguish of to-day, or the agonies which <hi rend="italic">are</hi> have their 
origin in the ecstasies which <hi rend="italic">might have been</hi>. 
</p><p>My baptismal name is Egaeus; that of my family I will not 
mention.  Yet there are no towers in the land more time-honoured 
than my gloomy, grey, hereditary halls.  Our line has been called 
a race of visionaries; and in many striking particulars &mdash; in the 
character of the family mansion &mdash; in the frescoes of the chief 
saloon &mdash; in the tapestries of the dormitories &mdash; in the chiselling 
of some buttresses in the armory &mdash; but more especially in the 
gallery of antique paintings &mdash; in the fashion of the library 
chamber &mdash; and, lastly, in the very peculiar nature of the 
library's contents, there is more than sufficient evidence to 
warrant the belief. 
</p><p>The recollections of my earliest years are connected with 
that chamber, and with its volumes &mdash; of which latter I will say no 
more.  Here died my mother.  Herein was I born.  But it is mere 
idleness to say that I had not lived before &mdash; that the soul has no 
previous existence.  You deny it? &mdash; let us not argue the matter. 
Convinced myself, I seek not to convince.  There is however, a 
remembrance of aerial forms &mdash; of spiritual and meaning eyes &mdash; of 
sounds, musical yet sad &mdash; a remembrance which will not be 
excluded; a memory like a shadow, vague, variable, indefinite, 
unsteady; and like a shadow, too, in the impossibility of my 
getting rid of it while the sunlight of my reason shall exist. 
</p><p>In that chamber was I born.  Thus awaking from the long 
night of what seemed, but was not, nonentity, at once into the 
very regions of fairy-land &mdash; into a palace of imagination &mdash; into 
<pb n="176"/>  
the wild dominions of monastic thought and erudition &mdash; it is not 
singular that I gazed around me with a startled and ardent eye &mdash; 
that I loitered away my boyhood in books, and dissipated my youth 
in reverie; but it <hi rend="italic">is</hi> singular that as years rolled away, and 
the noon of manhood found me still in the mansion of my fathers &mdash; 
it is wonderful what stagnation there fell upon the springs of my 
life &mdash; wonderful how total an inversion took place in the 
character of my commonest thought.  The realities of the world 
affected me as visions, and as visions only, while the wild ideas 
of the land of dreams became, in turn, &mdash; not the material of my 
every-day existence &mdash; but in very deed that existence utterly and 
solely in itself. 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d5">
<head> * </head> 
 
<p>Berenice and I were cousins, and we grew up together in my 
paternal halls.  Yet differently we grew &mdash; I ill of health, and 
buried in gloom &mdash; she agile, graceful, and overflowing with 
energy; hers the ramble on the hill-side &mdash; mine the studies of the 
cloister &mdash; I living within my own heart, and addicted body and 
soul to the most intense and painful meditation &mdash; she roaming 
carelessly through life with no thought of the shadows in her 
path, or the silent flight of the raven-winged hours.  Berenice! &mdash; 
I call upon her name &mdash; Berenice! &mdash; and from the grey ruins of 
memory a thousand tumultuous recollections are startled at the 
sound!  Ah! vividly is her image before me now, as in the early 
days of her light-heartedness and joy!  Oh! gorgeous yet 
fantastic beauty!  Oh! sylph amid the shrubberies of Arnheim! 
Oh! Naiad among its fountains! &mdash; and then &mdash; then all is mystery and 
terror, and a tale which should not be told.  Disease &mdash; a fatal 
disease &mdash; fell like the simoom upon her frame, and, even while I 
gazed upon her, the spirit of change swept over her, pervading 
her mind, her habits, and her character, and, in a manner the 
most subtle and terrible, disturbing even the identity of her 
person!  Alas! the destroyer came and went, and the victim &mdash; where 
was she?  I knew her not &mdash; or knew her no longer as Berenice. 
</p><p>Among the numerous train of maladies superinduced by that 
fatal and primary one which effected a revolution of so horrible 
a kind in the moral and physical being of my cousin, may be 
mentioned as the most distressing and obstinate in its nature, a 
species of epilepsy not unfrequently terminating in <hi rend="italic">trance</hi> 
itself &mdash; trance very nearly resembling positive dissolution, and 
from which her manner of recovery was, in most instances, 
<pb n="177"/>  
startlingly abrupt.  In the meantime my own disease &mdash; for I have 
been told that I should call it by no other appellation &mdash; my own 
disease, then, grew rapidly upon me, and assumed finally a 
monomaniac character of a novel and extraordinary form &mdash; hourly 
and momently gaining vigour &mdash; and at length obtaining over me the 
most incomprehensible ascendancy.  This monomania, if I must so 
term it, consisted in a morbid irritability of those properties 
of the mind in metaphysical science termed the <hi rend="italic">attentive</hi>.  It 
is more than probable that I am not understood; but I fear, 
indeed, that it is in no manner possible to convey to the mind of 
the merely general reader, an adequate idea of that nervous 
<hi rend="italic">intensity of interest</hi> with which, in my case, the powers of 
meditation (not to speak technically) busied and buried 
themselves, in the contemplation of even the most ordinary 
objects of the universe. 
</p><p>To muse for long unwearied hours with my attention riveted 
to some frivolous device on the margin, or in the typography of a 
book; to become absorbed for the better part of a summer's day, 
in a quaint shadow falling aslant upon the tapestry, or upon the 
door; to lose myself for an entire night in watching the steady 
flame of a lamp, or the embers of a fire; to dream away whole 
days over the perfume of a flower; to repeat monotonously some 
common word, until the sound, by dint of frequent repetition, 
ceased to convey any idea whatever to the mind; to lose all sense 
of motion or physical existence, by means of absolute bodily 
quiescence long and obstinately persevered in; &mdash; such were a few 
of the most common and least pernicious vagaries induced by a 
condition of the mental faculties, not, indeed, altogether 
unparalleled, but certainly bidding defiance to anything like 
analysis or explanation. 
</p><p>Yet let me not be misapprehended. &mdash; The undue, earnest, and 
morbid attention thus excited by objects in their own nature 
frivolous, must not be confounded in character with that 
ruminating propensity common to all mankind, and more especially 
indulged in by persons of ardent imagination.  It was not even, 
as might at first be supposed, an extreme condition, or 
exaggeration of such propensity, but primarily and essentially 
distinct and different.  In the one instance, the dreamer, or 
enthusiast, being interested by an object usually <hi rend="italic">not</hi> 
frivolous, imperceptibly loses sight of this object in a 
wilderness of deductions and suggestions issuing therefrom, 
until, at the conclusion of a day-dream <hi rend="italic">often replete with 
luxury</hi>, he finds the <hi rend="italic">incitamentum</hi> or first cause of his 
musings entirely vanished 
<pb n="178"/>  
and forgotten.  In my case the primary 
object was <hi rend="italic">invariably frivolous</hi>, although assuming, through 
the medium of my distempered vision, a refracted and unreal 
importance.  Few deductions, if any, were made; and those few 
pertinaciously returning in upon the original object as a centre. 
The meditations were <hi rend="italic">never</hi> pleasurable; and, at the 
termination of the reverie, the first cause, so far from being 
out of sight, had attained that supernaturally exaggerated 
interest which was the prevailing feature of the disease.  In a 
word, the powers of mind more particularly exercised were, with 
me, as I have said before, the <hi rend="italic">attentive</hi>, and are, with the 
day-dreamer, the <hi rend="italic">speculative</hi>. 
</p><p>My books, at this epoch, if they did not actually serve to 
irritate the disorder, partook, it will be perceived, largely, in 
their imaginative and inconsequential nature, of the 
characteristic qualities of the disorder itself.  I well 
remember, among others, the treatise of the noble Italian Coelius 
Secundus Curio, <hi rend="italic">De Amplitudine Beati Regni Dei</hi>; St Austin's 
great work, <hi rend="italic">The City of God</hi>; and Tertullian, <hi rend="italic">De Carne 
Christi</hi>, in which the paradoxical sentence, '<hi rend="italic">Mortuus est Dei 
filius; credibile est quia ineptum est: et sepultus resurrexit; 
certum est quia impossibile est</hi>', occupied my undivided time, 
for many weeks of laborious and fruitless investigation. 
</p><p>Thus it will appear that, shaken from its balance only by 
trivial things, my reason bore resemblance to that ocean-crag 
spoken of by Ptolemy Hephestion, which, steadily resisting the 
attacks of human violence, and the fiercer fury of the waters and 
the winds, trembled only to the touch of the flower called 
Asphodel.  And although, to a careless thinker, it might appear a 
matter beyond doubt, that the alteration produced by her unhappy 
malady, in the <hi rend="italic">moral</hi> condition of Berenice, would afford me 
many objects for the exercise of that intense and abnormal 
meditation whose nature I have been at some trouble in 
explaining, yet such was not in any degree the case.  In the 
lucid intervals of my infirmity, her calamity, indeed, gave me 
pain, and, taking deeply to heart that total wreck of her fair 
and gentle life, I did not fail to ponder frequently and bitterly 
upon the wonder-working means by which so strange a revolution 
had been so suddenly brought to pass.  But these reflections 
partook not of the idiosyncrasy of my disease, and were such as 
would have occurred, under similar circumstances, to the ordinary 
mass of mankind.  True to its own character, my disorder revelled 
in the less important but more startling changes 
<pb n="179"/>  
wrought in the 
<hi rend="italic">physical</hi> frame of Berenice &mdash; in the singular and most 
appalling distortion of her personal identity. 
</p><p>During the brightest days of her unparalleled beauty, 
most surely I had never loved her.  In the strange anomaly of my 
existence, feelings with me <hi rend="italic">had never been</hi> of the heart, and 
my passions <hi rend="italic">always were</hi> of the mind.  Through the grey of the 
early morning &mdash; among the trellised shadows of the forest at 
noonday &mdash; and in the silence of my library at night, she had 
flitted by my eyes, and I had seen her &mdash; not as the living and 
breathing Berenice, but as the Berenice of a dream &mdash; not as a 
being of the earth, earthy, but as the abstraction of such a 
being &mdash; not as a thing to admire, but to analyse &mdash; not as an object 
of love, but as the theme of the most abstruse although desultory 
speculation.  And <hi rend="italic">now</hi> &mdash; now I shuddered in her presence, and 
grew pale at her approach; yet bitterly lamenting her fallen and 
desolate condition, I called to mind that she had loved me long, 
and, in an evil moment, I spoke to her of marriage. 
</p><p>And at length the period of our nuptials was approaching, 
when, upon an afternoon in the winter of the year, &mdash; one of those 
unseasonably warm, calm, and misty days which are the nurse of 
the beautiful Halcyon,<ref target="P1">1</ref> &mdash; I sat 
(and sat, as I thought, alone) in the 
inner apartment of the library.  But uplifting my eyes I saw that 
Berenice stood before me. 
</p><p>Was it my own excited imagination &mdash; or the misty influence of 
the atmosphere &mdash; or the uncertain twilight of the chamber &mdash; or the 
grey draperies which fell around her figure &mdash; that caused in it so 
vacillating and indistinct an outline?  I could not tell.  She 
spoke no word, and I &mdash; not for worlds could I have uttered a 
syllable.  An icy chill ran through my frame; a sense 
of insufferable anxiety oppressed me; a consuming curiosity pervaded 
my soul; and sinking back upon the chair, I remained for some 
time breathless and motionless, with my eyes riveted upon her 
person.  Alas! its emaciation was excessive, and not one vestige 
of the former being lurked in any single line of the contour.  My 
burning glances at length fell upon the face. 
</p><p>The forehead was high, and very pale, and singularly placid; 
and the once jetty hair fell partially over it, and overshadowed 
the hollow temples with innumerable ringlets now of a vivid 
yellow, and jarring discordantly, in their fantastic character, 
<pb n="180"/>  
with the reigning melancholy of the countenance.  The eyes were 
lifeless, and lustreless, and seemingly pupil-less, and I shrank 
involuntarily from their glassy stare to the contemplation of the 
thin and shrunken lips.  They parted; and in a smile of peculiar 
meaning, <hi rend="italic">the teeth</hi> of the changed Berenice disclosed 
themselves slowly to my view.  Would to God that I had never 
beheld them, or that, having done so, I had died! 
</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="3" id="d6">
<head> * </head> 
<p>
 
The shutting of a door disturbed me, and, looking up, I found 
that my cousin had departed from the chamber.  But from the 
disordered chamber of my brain, had not, alas! departed, and 
would not be driven away, the white and ghastly <hi rend="italic">spectrum</hi> of 
the teeth.  Not a speck on their surface &mdash; not a shade on their 
enamel &mdash; not an indenture in their edges &mdash; but what that period of 
her smile had sufficed to brand in upon my memory.  I saw them 
<hi rend="italic">now</hi> even more unequivocally than I beheld them <hi rend="italic">then</hi>.  The 
teeth! &mdash; the teeth! &mdash; they were here, and there, and everywhere, 
and visibly and palpably before me; long, narrow, and excessively 
white, with the pale lips writhing about them, as in the very 
moment of their first terrible development.  Then came the full 
fury of my <hi rend="italic">monomania</hi>, and I struggled in vain against its 
strange and irresistible influence.  In the multiplied objects of 
the external world I had no thoughts but for the teeth.  For 
these I longed with a phrenzied desire.  All other matters and 
all different interests became absorbed in their single 
contemplation.  They &mdash; they alone were present to the mental eye, 
and they, in their sole individuality, became the essence of my 
mental life.  I held them in every light.  I turned them in every 
attitude.  I surveyed their characteristics.  I dwelt upon their 
peculiarities.  I pondered upon their conformation.  I mused upon 
the alteration in their nature.  I shuddered as I assigned to 
them in imagination a sensitive and sentient power, and even when 
unassisted by the lips, a capability of moral expression.  Of 
Mad'selle Salle it has been well said, '<hi rend="italic">que tous ses pas 
etaient des sentiments</hi>', and of Berenice I more seriously 
believed <hi rend="italic">que toutes ses dents etaient des idees.  Des idees!</hi> &mdash; 
ah here was the idiotic thought that destroyed me!  <hi rend="italic">Des 
idees!</hi> &mdash; ah <hi rend="italic">therefore</hi> it was that I coveted them so madly!  I 
felt that their possession could alone ever restore me to peace, 
in giving me back to reason. 
</p><p>And the evening closed in upon me thus &mdash; and then the 
darkness came, and tarried, and went &mdash; and the day again dawned &mdash; 
and the mists of a second night were now gathering around &mdash; 
<pb n="181"/>  
and 
still I sat motionless in that solitary room; and still I sat 
buried in meditation, and still the <hi rend="italic">phantasma</hi> of the teeth 
maintained its terrible ascendancy as, with the most vivid and 
hideous distinctness, it floated about amid the changing lights 
and shadows of the chamber.  At length there broke in upon my 
dreams a cry as of horror and dismay; and thereunto, after a 
pause, succeeded the sound of troubled voices, intermingled with 
many low moanings of sorrow, or of pain.  I arose from my seat 
and, throwing open one of the doors of the library, saw standing 
out in the antechamber a servant maiden, all in tears, who told 
me that Berenice was &mdash; no more.  She had been seized with epilepsy 
in the early morning, and now, at the closing in of the night, 
the grave was ready for its tenant, and all the preparations for 
the burial were completed. 
 
</p><p>I found myself sitting in the library, and again sitting there 
alone.  It seemed that I had newly awakened from a confused and 
exciting dream.  I knew that it was now midnight, and I was well 
aware that since the setting of the sun Berenice had been 
interred.  But of that dreary period which intervened I had no 
positive &mdash; at least no definite comprehension.  Yet its memory was 
replete with horror &mdash; horror more horrible from being vague, and 
terror more terrible from ambiguity.  It was a fearful page in 
the record of my existence, written all over with dim, and 
hideous, and unintelligible recollections.  I strived to decipher 
them, but in vain; while ever and anon, like the spirit of a 
departed sound, the shrill and piercing shriek of a female voice 
seemed to be ringing in my ears.  I had done a deed &mdash; what was it? 
I asked myself the question aloud, and the whispering echoes of 
the chamber answered me, '<hi rend="italic">what was it</hi>?' 
</p><p>On the table beside me burned a lamp, and near it lay a 
little box.  It was of no remarkable character, and I had seen it 
frequently before, for it was the property of the family 
physician; but how came it <hi rend="italic">there</hi>, upon my table, and why did 
I shudder in regarding it?  These things were in no manner to be 
accounted for, and my eyes at length dropped to the open pages of 
a book, and to a sentence underscored therein.  The words were 
the singular but simple ones of the poet Ebn Zaiat, '<hi rend="italic">Dicebant 
mihi sodales si sepulchrum amicae visitarem, curas meas 
aliquantulum fore levatas</hi>.'  Why then, as I perused them, did 
the hairs of my head erect themselves on end, and the blood of my 
body become congealed within my veins? 
<pb n="182"/>  
</p><p>There came a light tap at the library door, and pale as the 
tenant of a tomb, a menial entered upon tiptoe.  His looks were 
wild with terror, and he spoke to me in a voice tremulous, husky, 
and very low.  What said he? &mdash; some broken sentences I heard.  He 
told of a wild cry disturbing the silence of the night &mdash; of the 
gathering together of the household &mdash; of a search in the direction 
of the sound; &mdash; and then his tones grew thrillingly distinct as he 
whispered me of a violated grave &mdash; of a disfigured body 
enshrouded, yet still breathing, still palpitating, still 
<hi rend="italic">alive</hi>! 
</p><p>He pointed to my garments; &mdash; they were muddy and clotted with 
gore.  I spoke not, and he took me gently by the hand; &mdash; it was 
indented with the impress of human nails.  He directed my 
attention to some object against the wall; &mdash; I looked at it for 
some minutes; &mdash; it was a spade.  With a shriek I bounded to the 
table, and grasped the box that lay upon it.  But I could not 
force it open; and in my tremor it slipped from my hands, and 
fell heavily, and burst into pieces; and from it, with a rattling 
sound, there rolled out some instruments of dental surgery, 
intermingled with thirty-two small, white and ivory-looking 
substances that were scattered to and fro about the floor. 
</p> 
 



<note id="P1"><seg type="note-symbol">1.</seg> <p>For as Jove, during 
the winter season, gives twice seven days of warmth, men have called 
this clement and temperate time the nurse of the beautiful Halcyon. <lb/> 
&mdash; SIMONIDES. 
</p></note> 


</div2>
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
