<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="PoePerv"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="PoePerv"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Imp of the Perverse</title>
<title type="sort">imp of the perverse</title>
<author>Poe, Edgar Allan, 1809-1849</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">19</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">PoePerv</idno> 
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476320</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>First created by Judy Boss; the text then went to Tom Almy's 
Bitter Butter Better BBS, where he removed the pagination, and then to 
The Internet Wiretap.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Tales of Mystery and Imagination</title>
<title type="sort">tales of mystery and imagination</title>
<author>Edgar Allan Poe</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>edited by</resp>
<name/>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>J. M. Dent &amp; Sons</publisher> 
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace> 
<date value="1912">1912</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Source copy consulted: Call no. PS 2612 A1 1912, Alderman Library, University of Virginia</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme 
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of 
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1845">1845</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-12">December 1994</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>repaginated because Judy Boss identified the source of the text; 
updated tags and header</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="1993-06">June 1993</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>minimal TEI tagging; italics included; pagination came 
with the text, but it remains unclear what edition this text 
originated from</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
 
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
<head>The Imp of the Perverse</head> 
<pb n="361"/>   
<p>In the consideration of the faculties and impulses &mdash; of the 
<hi rend="italic">prima mobilia</hi> of the human soul, the phrenologists have failed to 
make room for a propensity which, although obviously existing as a 
radical, primitive, irreducible sentiment, has been equally 
overlooked by all the moralists who have preceded them.  In the 
pure arrogance of the reason, we have all overlooked it.  We have 
suffered its existence to escape our senses solely through want of 
belief &mdash; of faith; &mdash; whether it be faith in Revelation, or faith in 
the Kabbala.  The idea of it has never occurred to us, simply 
because of its supererogation.  We saw no <hi rend="italic">need</hi> of impulse &mdash; for 
the propensity.  We could not perceive its necessity.  We could not 
understand, that is to say, we could not have understood, had the 
notion of this <hi rend="italic">primum mobile</hi> ever obtruded itself; &mdash; we could 
not have understood in what manner it might be made to further the 
objects of humanity, either temporal or eternal.  It cannot be 
denied that phrenology and, in great measure, all metaphysicianism 
have been concocted <hi rend="italic">a priori</hi>.  The intellectual or logical man, 
rather than the understanding or observant man, set himself to 
imagine designs &mdash; to dictate purposes to God.  Having thus fathomed, 
to his satisfaction, the intentions of Jehovah, out of these 
intentions he built his innumerable systems of mind.  In the matter 
of phrenology, for example, we first determined, naturally enough, 
that it was 
<pb n="362"/>  
the design of the Deity that man should eat.  We then 
assigned to man an organ of alimentiveness, and this organ is the 
scourge with which the Deity compels man, will-I nill-I, into 
eating.  Secondly, having settled it to be God's will that man 
should continue his species, we discovered an organ of amativeness, 
forthwith.  And so with combativeness, with ideality, with 
causality, with constructiveness, &mdash; so, in short, with every organ, 
whether representing a propensity, a moral sentiment, or a faculty 
of the pure intellect.  And in these arrangements of the 
<hi rend="italic">principia</hi> of human action, the Spurzheimites, whether right or 
wrong, in part, or upon the whole, have but followed, in principle, 
the footsteps of their predecessors; deducing and establishing 
everything from the preconceived destiny of man, and upon the 
ground of the objects of this Creator. 
</p><p>It would have been wiser, it would have been safer, to 
classify (if classify we must) upon the basis of what man usually 
or occasionally did, and was always occasionally doing, rather than 
upon the basis of what he took it for granted the Deity intended 
him to do.  If we cannot comprehend God in his visible works, how 
then in his inconceivable thoughts, that call the works into being? 
If we cannot understand him in his objective creatures, how then in 
his substantive moods and phases of creation? 
</p><p>Induction, <hi rend="italic">a posteriori</hi>, would have brought phrenology to 
admit, as an innate and primitive principle of human action, a 
paradoxical something, which we may call <hi rend="italic">perverseness</hi>, for want 
of a more characteristic term.  In the sense I intend, it is, in 
fact, a <hi rend="italic">mobile</hi> without motive, a motive not <hi rend="italic">motivirt</hi>. 
Through its promptings we act without comprehensible object; or, if 
this shall be understood as a contradiction in terms, we may so far 
modify the proposition as to say, that through its promptings we 
act, for the reason that we should <hi rend="italic">not</hi>.  In theory, no reason 
can be more unreasonable; but, in fact, there is none more strong. 
With certain minds, under certain conditions it becomes absolutely 
irresistible.  I am not more certain that I breathe, than that the 
assurance of the wrong or error of any action is often the one 
unconquerable <hi rend="italic">force</hi> which impels us, and alone impels us to its 
prosecution.  Nor will this overwhelming tendency to do wrong for 
the wrong's sake, admit of analysis, or resolution into ulterior 
elements.  It is radical, a primitive impulse &mdash; elementary.  It will 
be said, I am aware, that when we persist in acts because we feel 
we should <hi rend="italic">not</hi> persist in them, our conduct is but a 
modification of that which 
<pb n="363"/>  
ordinarily springs from the 
<hi rend="italic">combativeness</hi> of phrenology.  But a glance will show the fallacy 
of this idea.  The phrenological combativeness has, for its 
essence, the necessity of self-defence.  It is our safeguard 
against injury.  Its principle regards our well-being; and thus the 
desire to be well is excited simultaneously with its development. 
It follows, that the desire to be well must be excited 
simultaneously with any principle which shall be merely a 
modification of combativeness, but in the case of that something 
which I term <hi rend="italic">perverseness</hi>, the desire to be well is 
not only aroused, but a strongly antagonistical sentiment exists. 
</p><p>An appeal to one's own heart is, after all, the best reply to 
the sophistry just noticed.  No one who trustingly consults and 
thoroughly questions his own soul, will be disposed to deny the 
entire radicalness of the propensity in question.  It is not more 
incomprehensible than distinctive.  There lives no man who at some 
period has not been tormented, for example, by an earnest desire to 
tantalize a listener by circumlocution.  The speaker is aware that 
he displeases, he has every intention to please; he is usually 
curt, precise, and clear; the most laconic and luminous language is 
struggling for utterance upon his tongue; it is only with 
difficulty that he restrains himself from giving it flow; he dreads 
and deprecates the anger of him whom he addresses; yet, the thought 
strikes him, that by certain involutions and parentheses this anger 
may be engendered.  That single thought is enough.  The impulse 
increases to a wish, the wish to a desire, the desire to an 
uncontrollable longing, and the longing (to the deep regret and 
mortification of the speaker, and in defiance of all consequences) 
is indulged. 
</p><p>We have a task before us which must be speedily performed.  We 
know that it will be ruinous to make delay.  The most important 
crisis of our life calls, trumpet-tongued, for immediate energy and 
action.  We glow, we are consumed with eagerness to commence the 
work, with the anticipation of whose glorious result our whole 
souls are on fire.  It must, it shall be undertaken to-day, and yet 
we put it off until to-morrow; and why?  There is no answer, except 
that we feel <hi rend="italic">perverse</hi>, using the word with no comprehension of 
the principle.  To-morrow arrives, and with it a more impatient 
anxiety to do our duty, but with this very increase of anxiety 
arrives, also, a nameless, a positively fearful, because 
unfathomable, craving for delay.  This craving gathers strength as 
the moments fly.  The last hour for action is at hand.  We tremble 
with the violence of the 
<pb n="364"/>  
conflict within us, &mdash; of the definite with 
the indefinite &mdash; of the substance with the shadow.  But, if the 
contest has proceeded thus far, it is the shadow which prevails &mdash; we 
struggle in vain.  The clock strikes, and is the knell of our 
welfare.  At the same time, it is the chanticleer-note to the ghost 
that has so long overawed us.  It flies &mdash; it disappears &mdash; we are 
free. The old energy returns.  We will labour <hi rend="italic">now</hi>. Alas, it is 
<hi rend="italic">too late</hi>! 
</p><p>We stand upon the brink of a precipice.  We peer into the 
abyss &mdash; we grow sick and dizzy.  Our first impulse is to shrink from 
the danger.  Unaccountably we remain.  By slow degrees our sickness 
and dizziness and horror become merged in a cloud of unnamable 
feeling.  By gradations, still more imperceptible, this cloud 
assumes shape, as did the vapour from the bottle out of which arose 
the genius in the <hi rend="italic">Arabian Nights</hi>.  But out of this <hi rend="italic">our</hi> 
cloud upon the precipice's edge, there grows into palpability, a 
shape, far more terrible than any genius or any demon of a tale, 
and yet it is but a thought, although a fearful one, and one which 
chills the very marrow of our bones with the fierceness of the 
delight of its horror.  It is merely the idea of what would be our 
sensations during the sweeping precipitancy of a fall from such a 
height.  And this fall &mdash; this rushing annihilation &mdash; for the very 
reason that it involves that one most ghastly and loathsome of all 
the most ghastly and loathsome images of death and suffering which 
have ever presented themselves to our imagination &mdash; for this very 
cause do we now the most vividly desire it.  And because our reason 
violently deters us from the brink, <hi rend="italic">therefore</hi> do we the most 
impetuously approach it.  There is no passion in nature so 
demoniacally impatient as that of him who, shuddering upon the edge 
of a precipice, thus meditates a plunge.  To indulge, for a moment, 
in any attempt at <hi rend="italic">thought</hi>, is to be inevitably lost; for 
reflection but urges us to forbear, and <hi rend="italic">therefore</hi> it is, I say, 
that we <hi rend="italic">cannot</hi>.  If there be no friendly arm to check us, or if 
we fail in a sudden effort to prostrate ourselves backward from the 
abyss, we plunge, and are destroyed. 
</p><p>Examine these and similar actions as we will, we shall find 
them resulting solely from the spirit of the <hi rend="italic">Perverse</hi>.  We 
perpetrate them merely because we feel that we should <hi rend="italic">not</hi> 
Beyond or behind this there is no intelligible principle; and we 
might, indeed, deem this perverseness a direct instigation of the 
arch-fiend, were it not occasionally known to operate in 
furtherance of good. 
</p><p>I have said thus much, that in some measure I may answer 
<pb n="365"/>  
your 
question &mdash; that I may explain to you why I am here &mdash; that I may 
assign to you something that shall have at least the faint aspect 
of a cause for my wearing these fetters, and for my tenanting this cell 
of the condemned.  Had I not been thus prolix, you 
might either have misunderstood me altogether, or, with the rabble, 
have fancied me mad.  As it is, you will easily perceive that I am 
one of the many uncounted victims of the Imp of the Perverse. 
</p><p>It is impossible that any deed could have been wrought with a 
more thorough deliberation.  For weeks, for months, I pondered upon 
the means of the murder.  I rejected a thousand schemes, because 
their accomplishment involved a <hi rend="italic">chance</hi> of detection.  At 
length, in reading some French memoirs, I found an account of a 
nearly fatal illness that occurred to Madame Pilau, through the 
agency of a candle accidentally poisoned.  The idea struck my fancy 
at once.  I knew my victim's habit of reading in bed.  I knew, too, 
that his apartment was narrow and ill-ventilated.  But I need not 
vex you with impertinent details.  I need not describe the easy 
artifices by which I substituted, in his bed-room candle stand, a 
wax-light of my own making for the one which I there found.  The 
next morning he was discovered dead in his bed, and the coroner's 
verdict was &mdash; 'Death by the visitation of God.' 
</p><p>Having inherited his estate, all went well with me for years. 
The idea of detection never once entered my brain.  Of the remains 
of the fatal taper I had myself carefully disposed.  I had left no 
shadow of a clue by which it would be possible to convict, or even 
suspect, me of the crime.  It is inconceivable how rich a sentiment 
of satisfaction arose in my bosom as I reflected upon my absolute 
security.  For a very long period of time I was accustomed to revel 
in this sentiment.  It afforded me more real delight than all the 
mere worldly advantages accruing from my sin.  But there arrived at 
length an epoch, from which the pleasurable feeling grew, by 
scarcely perceptible gradations, into a haunting and harassing 
thought.  It harassed me because it haunted.  I could scarcely get 
rid of it for an instant.  It is quite a common thing to be thus 
annoyed with the ringing in our ears, or rather in our memories, of 
the burthen of some ordinary song, or some unimpressive snatches 
from an opera.  Nor will we be the less tormented if the song in 
itself be good, or the opera air meritorious.  In this manner, at 
last, I would perpetually catch myself pondering upon my security, 
and repeating, in a low under-tone, the phrase, 'I am safe.' 
<pb n="366"/>  
</p><p>One day, whilst sauntering along the streets, I arrested 
myself in the act of murmuring, half aloud, these customary 
syllables.  In a fit of petulance I re-modelled them thus: 'I am 
safe &mdash; I am safe &mdash; yes &mdash; if I be not fool enough to make open 
confession.' 
</p><p>No sooner had I spoken these words, than I felt an icy chill 
creep to my heart.  I had had some experience in these fits of 
perversity (whose nature I have been at some trouble to explain), 
and I remembered well that in no instance I had successfully 
resisted their attacks.  And now my own casual self-suggestion, 
that I might possibly be fool enough to confess the murder of which 
I had been guilty, confronted me, as if the very ghost of him whom 
I had murdered &mdash; and beckoned me on to death. 
</p><p>At first, I made an effort to shake off this nightmare of the 
soul.  I walked vigorously &mdash; faster &mdash; still faster &mdash; at length I ran. 
I felt a maddening desire to shriek aloud.  Every succeeding wave 
of thought overwhelmed me with new terror, for, alas! I well, too 
well, understood that to <hi rend="italic">think</hi>, in my situation, was to be 
lost.  I still quickened my pace.  I bounded like a madman through 
the crowded thoroughfares.  At length, the populace took the alarm 
and pursued me.  I felt <hi rend="italic">then</hi> the consummation of my fate. 
Could I have torn out my tongue, I would have done it &mdash; but a rough 
voice resounded in my ears &mdash; a rougher grasp seized me by the 
shoulder.  I turned &mdash; I gasped for breath.  For a moment I 
experienced all the pangs of suffocation; I became blind, and deaf, 
and giddy; and then some invisible fiend, I thought, struck me with 
his broad palm upon the back.  The long-imprisoned secret burst 
forth from my soul. 
</p><p>They say that I spoke with a distinct enunciation, but with 
marked emphasis and passionate hurry, as if in dread of 
interruption before concluding the brief but pregnant sentences 
that consigned me to the hangman and to hell. 
</p><p>Having related all that was necessary for the fullest judicial 
conviction, I fell prostrate in a swoon. 
</p><p>But why shall I say more?  To-day I wear these chains, and am 
<hi rend="italic">here</hi>!  To-morrow I shall be fetterless! &mdash; <hi rend="italic">but where</hi>? 
</p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
