<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="PokSupe"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

 
<TEI.2 id="PokSupe"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Indian Superstitions and Legends.</title>
<title type="sort">indian superstitions and legends</title>
<author>Pokagon, Simon</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">35</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">PokSupe</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476327</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Indian Superstitions and Legends.</title>
<title type="sort">indian superstitions and legends</title>
<author>Simon Pokagon</author>
</titleStmt> 
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
<hi rend="italic">Forum</hi>
</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York, N.Y.</pubPlace> 
<date value="1898">1898</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>25</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Forum</hi> 25 (July 1898): 618-629.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1898">1898</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term> 
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-08">August 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Deirdre Johnson, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Header added, basic TEI markup added</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="section" n="1" id="d3"> <pb n="618"/>  
<head> INDIAN SUPERSTITIONS AND LEGENDS.</head> 
 
    <p> UNTIL twelve years old I could speak only <hi rend="italic">nin-gaw odaw-naw-naw</hi> 
(my mother-tongue).  Before then I had bitter thoughts of 
the white men; regarding them as robbers of the worst sort, and 
destitute of all love or sympathy for our race.  When I saw them I 
fled and hid myself, like the young partridge from the hawk. 
    </p><p> About that time I became acquainted with Edward Coles, a 
travelling Indian missionary, who frequently called at our wigwam 
in Pokagon, my father's village, in Southwestern Michigan.  He had 
had a fair English education, and was a fine Christian teacher.  He 
saw how bitterly I felt toward the dominant race, and often told me 
that the better class were as good as our own people, and that I 
was very prejudiced.  No doubt this was the case, and was due to 
the fact, that the white men who generally came in contact with the 
Indians were the worst of their kind.  He also said that numbers of 
white men believed in Kigi Manito,&mdash;the God we worshipped,&mdash;and 
that many, many years before, He had sent from Waw-kwi (Heaven) to 
their forefathers His son Jesus, whom they murdered, and that He 
arose from the dead, and ascended to Heaven; that He now there 
stood, with open arms, ready to receive all who put their trust in 
Him; and that when life was ended here, they would dwell with Him 
in Waw-kwi forever.  I could not understand how white men could be 
so good as red men, and yet be guilt of taking the life of a noble 
chief who had come to save them.  I inquired of him if those white 
men who had brought ruin upon our people, by selling them fire-water, would be permitted to enter the garden of Waw-kwi.  He 
claimed that if they would quit their accursed business, and humbly 
repent, and try to repair the great wrong they had done, it was 
barely possible they might enter the land of promise.  This noble 
Christian missionary greatly impressed me with the wonderful things 
white men could do, through the mighty inventions and discoveries 
they had made; and these so excited my love of the marvellous, that 
my youthful heart thirsted night and day to drink from the fountain 
of knowledge at the white man's school. 
    </p><p> About this time my dear father died; and, soon after, my 
mother, <pb n="619"/>  on the advice of one of the Catholic Fathers, sent 
me to Notre Dame School, near South Bend, Indiana, where I remained 
four or five years.  But, desiring a more liberal education than I 
was likely to get there, I sought out my old missionary friend 
Coles, and laid before him my great anxiety to go to school at 
Oberlin, Ohio, where race and color were disregarded.  The good man 
finally persuaded my mother to send me to that school.  I was about 
to leave home, when, to my surprise, some of the older members of 
the Pokagon band objected to my going to the white man's school; 
believing it would displease the Great Spirit for a son of the 
Great Chief, who had passed into the hunting-ground beyond, to 
attend the Pale-face school. 
    </p><p> I listened to their admonitions and advice; well knowing their 
objection was too weak for consideration.  Yet, I must confess that 
their words lingered about my heart, and worried me, in spite of 
all my reasoning; and I said to myself, "Pokagon, such superstition 
you must inherit from your race."  I was troubled; for I thought I 
should not be able to compete in my studies with white class-mates, 
who would have better sense than to worry over that which they did 
not believe. 
    </p><p> A short time after this I mentioned to one of the most 
intelligent of my class-mates, that on the following day I was 
going into an advanced class.  He replied, "You had better wait 
until Monday."  "Why so?" I asked.  "Because," said he, "to-morrow 
is Friday&mdash;an unlucky day&mdash;and very likely, if you start then, you 
will always be at the tail-end of your class."  This foolish 
suggestion, coming from such a source, fairly staggered me; and yet 
it encouraged me to know that my rival had weak points like those 
which had lessened my faith in myself. 
    </p><p> Notwithstanding the superstitions of our Algonquin fathers, 
they were no idol-worshippers.  Their "religion" taught them that 
each mountain, stream, and lake had its spirit that governed and 
ruled over it.  They also believed that some deity controlled the 
winds and waves, and rode upon the clouds; commanding the storm, 
and guiding the whirlwind in its course. 
    </p><p> They believed in four sister-deities, who controlled the four 
seasons of the year.  Bi-bon (Winter) brought down from the north 
<hi rend="italic">agon</hi> (the snow), and, with her chilly fingers, touched the 
lakes and streams; leaving them ice-bound, until her sister Sig-wan 
(Spring) came.  She, with her warm breath, melted the snow and ice; 
letting the imprisoned lakes and streams go free, clothing the 
naked trees in robes of green, covering the earth with grass and 
fragrant flowers, filling the air with <pb n="620"/>  song-birds and 
insect life, and the waters with fish, and working with might and 
main until the arrival of her sister Ne-bin (Summer) on hasty 
wings, to help on the work Sig-wan had so well begun.  Man, beasts, 
and fowls sought the shade, to avoid the scorching sunshine of her 
face.  Last of all, the oldest sister, Baw-waw-gi (Autumn), came to 
ripen all the fruit, grain, and nuts; painting in gold and red the 
forest leaves, which for a few short days flaunted their glories in 
the breeze, then shed themselves, leaving their parent branches to 
combat with the winter's storms. 
    </p><p> Our forefathers did not grasp the grand idea of an infinite, 
all-wise being whose presence is everywhere.  Hence they believed 
that these deities, scattered throughout the world, were the agents 
of a mighty chief, one Mi-chi Ogaw-maw, who ruled all the rest.  
They saw the beauty of his face in the rainbow; the majesty of his 
eyes flashed in the clouds; the terror of his voice thundered in 
the storm, rumbled in the earthquake, and roared in the sea.  They 
taught their children, that Ke-sus (the sun) represented the eyes 
of this mighty Kigi Manito by day; that Te-bik Kesus and Anong (the 
moon and stars) were his eyes by night; and that they could not 
hide their words or acts from him.<note n="1"><p>Indians never swear in their own language; and, as they 
generally believe all white men to be Christians, they do not 
understand why so many should indulge in profanity.</p></note> 
</p>  
    <p> Our traditions show most clearly that the children were 
obedient to their parents, kind to the old and unfortunate, and 
respectful to all.  They had no cigarettes to smoke, no fire-water 
to drink, no saloons to lounge in.  As a race they were held in 
great Nature's lap, close to her heart: they listened to her words, 
and obeyed, as they understood them.  All believed in the 
immortality of the soul. 
    </p><p> I never saw nor heard of an Indian atheist.  Their Heaven was 
not paved with gold and precious stones; but it was a grand, 
romantic paradise of forests and wide, extended plains,&mdash;filled 
with beasts and birds, with lakes and streams swarming with fish 
close to shore,&mdash;where want never came, and where all were 
contented and happy. 
    </p><p> Among the most ancient traditions of our race is one that our 
first parents found themselves here surrounded by beasts of prey 
without number, whose physical strength far exceeded theirs, and 
whose young had greater strength and more knowledge than the Indian 
children.  Stones and clubs were used for weapons, until the bow 
and arrow were invented; and but for the fact, that a <hi rend="italic">manito</hi> 
was impressed upon the human countenance, before which the fiercest 
brute stood in awe, our <pb n="621"/>  first parents and their children 
would have been destroyed from off the face of the earth.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="2" id="d4"> 
<head>THE GREAT FLOOD.</head> 
 
<p>   One very remarkable character reported in our legends, dimly 
seen through the mist of untold centuries, is Kwi-wi-sens Nenaw-bo-zhoo, meaning, in Algonquin dialect, "The greatest clown-boy in the 
world."  When he became a man, he was not only a great prophet 
among his people, but a giant of such marvellous strength, that he 
could wield his war-club with force enough to shatter in pieces the 
largest pine-tree.  His hunting-dog was a monstrous black wolf, as 
large as a full-grown buffalo, with long, soft hair, and eyes that 
shone in the night like the moon.  The deity of the sea saw the 
charming beauty of this wolf-dog, and was so extremely jealous of 
him, that he was determined to take his life.  So he appeared 
before him in the form of a deer; and as the dog rushed to seize 
him, he was grasped by the deity and drowned in the depths of the 
sea.  He then made a great barbecue and invited as his guests 
whales, serpents, and all the monsters of the deep, that they might 
exult and rejoice with him that he had slain the dog of the 
prophet. 
    </p><p> When the seer-clown learned of the fate of his noble dog, 
through cunning Waw-goosh (the fox), whose keen eyes saw the 
deception that cost the wolf-dog his life, he sought to take 
revenge upon the sea-god.  So he went at once to the place where 
the latter was accustomed to come on land with his monster servants 
to bathe in the sunshine, and there concealed himself among the 
tall rushes until the "caravan of the deep" came ashore.  When they 
had fallen fast asleep, he drew his giant bow, twice as long as he 
was tall, and shot a poisoned arrow that pierced Neben Manito, the 
water-god, through the heart.  Neben Manito rolled into the sea, 
and cried, "Revenge!  Revenge!"  Then all the assembled monsters of 
the deep rushed headlong after the slayer of their king.  The 
prophet fled in consternation before the outraged creatures that 
hurled after him mountains of water, which swept down the forests 
like grass before the whirlwind.  He continued to flee before the 
raging flood, but could find no dry land.  In sore despair he then 
called upon the God of Heaven to save him, when there appeared 
before him a great canoe, in which were pairs of all kinds of land-beasts and birds, being rowed by a most beautiful maiden, who let 
down a rope and drew him up into the boat. 
    </p><p> The flood raged on; but, though mountains of water were 
continually<pb n="622"/> being hurled after the prophet, he was safe.  
When he had floated on the water many days, he ordered Aw-milk (the 
beaver) to dive down and, if he could reach the bottom, to bring up 
some earth.  Down the latter plunged, but in a few minutes came 
floating to the surface lifeless.  The prophet pulled him into the 
boat, blew into his mouth, and he became alive again.  He then said 
to Waw-jashk (the musk-rat), "You are the best diver among all the 
animal creation.  Go down to the bottom and bring me up some earth, 
out of which I will create a new world; for we cannot much longer 
live on the face of the deep." 
    </p><p> Down plunged the musk-rat; but, like the beaver, he, too, soon 
came to the surface lifeless, and was drawn into the boat, 
whereupon the prophet blew into <hi rend="italic">his</hi> mouth, and he became 
alive again.  In his paw, however, was found a small quantity of 
earth, which the prophet rolled into a small ball, and tied to the 
neck of Ka-ke-gi (the raven), saying, "Go thou, and fly to and fro 
over the surface of the deep, that dry land may appear."  The raven 
did so; the waters rolled away; the world resumed its former shape; 
and, in course of time, the maiden and prophet were united and 
repeopled the world.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="3" id="d5"> 
<head> PICTURES OF GOD BEFORE AND AFTER HE MADE THE WORLD.</head> 
 
<p>     About forty years ago two Indians, who were cutting cord-wood 
near Little Traverse village, one day returned in great haste, pale 
and excited, to Kaw-kee, their employer, saying, "Oh Kaw-kee, we 
cut down this morning a large maple-tree; and when we had sawn off 
the butt cut, behold, we found painted on the end of the log a 
figure of God before He made the world!  It seemed so strange and 
wonderful that we dared not stay longer on the work; feeling sure 
that something awful would happen if we did."  I will complete the 
story as it was told me by Kaw-kee about the time it occurred: 
    </p><p> "Well," said he, "I laughed at them for such foolish 
superstition.  They then tried to get me to return with them and 
examine the strange picture.  I was sick at the time, and persuaded 
them to go back and saw off a thin piece of the log, and bring it 
to me, that I might see the picture for myself. 
    </p><p> They started off very reluctantly.  Returning in about two 
hours more excited than before, they exclaimed, 'Oh Kaw-kee, we 
have cut off the end of the log as you requested; and, as it fell 
picture-side to the ground&mdash;<hi rend="italic">Na!  Mash-kee!</hi>  On the other 
side was a plain figure of God after He had made the world.  And we 
do not dare to meddle further with it, for we feel that something 
dreadful will happen if we do.'  On <pb n="623"/>  the following day I 
went with them to see what had so alarmed them, and to soothe their 
fears, if possible. 
    </p><p> I must confess that as we approached the fallen tree I felt a 
curious sort of awe about my heart.  I picked up the slice of wood 
which they had sawn off, and looked it carefully over on both 
sides.  I was indeed astonished; for on each side Nature had traced 
a wonderful picture!" 
    </p><p> At this point I became so intensely interested in his 
wonderful story, that I said, "Kaw-kee, what has become of that 
piece of wood?" 
    </p><p> "Here it is," he replied; handing it to me as he stepped to 
one corner of his wigwam. 
    </p><p> It was indeed a natural curiosity, well calculated to deceive 
anyone.  On one side appeared the figure of a man with folded arms, 
and with a blanket wrapped about him, standing in what appeared to 
be the outlines of the segment of a rainbow.  This had been 
regarded as a picture of God <hi rend="italic">before</hi> He made the world.  On 
the other side, appeared the same figure, with the right arm 
extended at full length, holding in his right hand a large ball, 
apparently in the act of throwing it.  This had been considered to 
be a picture of God <hi rend="italic">after</hi> He had made the world. 
    </p><p> On close inspection, I saw that these pictures were caused in 
some way by the growth of the timber.  The heart, or red part, of 
the wood forming the figures was surrounded by the white of the 
wood, which made the outlines clear.  As I looked first at one 
side, and then at the other, I said to myself, "Those pictures 
might deceive the very elect."</p></div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="4" id="d6"> 
<head>                       INDIAN SPIRITUALISM.</head> 
 
<p>     There is a tradition among the Ottawa branch of the great 
Algonquin family, believed to this day, that, centuries ago, their 
first parents migrated westward from the sea-coast, near the mouth 
of the St. Lawrence River, and settled in the valley of the Ottawa 
River in Canada, where they lived for untold centuries, and that 
their main village was at a place they named Ke-tchi-nebis-sing, 
which name it still bears.  There a daughter of the chief of the 
village went down to the lake to bathe one morning; leaving her 
infant boy tied to a flat piece of wood, as was the custom.  On 
returning to the spot where she had left her child, he could 
nowhere be found.  Distracted, she ran back to the village; 
frantically screaming that her child had been stolen.  The 
villagers turned out and searched long and well; but not a trace of 
the child could be found. <pb n="624"/>  
    </p><p> A few days after this two young lovers sat on a mound near the 
spot where the child had been lost; and while they were kissing and 
making love, they were startled by hearing, deep in the ground 
beneath them, an infant crying and sobbing as if its heart would 
break.  They ran in great haste to the village, and reported what 
they had heard.  All the inhabitants believed that it was the lost 
child which had been heard crying underground.  The old chief 
called together all the magicians,&mdash;as is the custom to this day, 
where the Indians are not under the influence of Christianity,&mdash;to 
hold a <hi rend="italic">seance</hi>, for communion with the unseen spirits, to 
divine what had become of the child.  I will here briefly describe 
the manner in which Indians proceed to receive communications from 
the spiritual world, as I have myself witnessed. 
    </p><p> Poles, ten to twelve feet high, are set in the ground, in the 
form of a circle from six to eight feet in diameter.  The top of 
the lodge is left open.  The sides are tightly covered with birch-bark, or the skins of animals.  A fire is built close to the ledge 
for the purpose of enabling the spectators to light their pipes, as 
they generally smoke during the strange performance.  All being 
ready, a low, tinkling sound is heard, like several small bells at 
a distance.  With a rush, on comes the leading performer, carrying 
a magician's little, flat rattle-box, somewhat like a tambourine.  
He sits down by the fire, and begins by telling his audience how he 
can call up spirits of the dead, as well as of those yet living in 
the world, and that any present can ask them questions and receive 
true answers thereto.  He next sings a peculiar song, which can 
scarcely be understood.  He then either goes into the lodge by 
crawling under, or sits outside with the audience; throwing his 
blanket or some other clothing over the top of it.  Immediately the 
lodge begins to shake, like a creature of life with an ague chill.  
Then is heard in the lodge a sound like that of a distant, strong 
wind sweeping through leafless trees, and intermingled with strange 
voices.  When questions are asked by anyone present they are always 
answered in an unknown tongue; but, luckily, among the spirits 
there is always a special interpreter to explain what the spirits 
say. 
    </p><p> According to the tradition above referred to, when the 
performance closed a party was sent to the lake to dig near where 
the lost child was left by its mother.  They did so; and, as deep 
down in the ground as they were tall, they found the remains of the 
child in a cavern, from which fled, through an underground channel 
into the lake, a spirit monster.  The magicians then declared that 
the country was ruled by Mau-tchi Manito, the evil one, who was an 
enemy seeking to do them all the <pb n="625"/>  harm possible; that all 
the misfortunes which had befallen them came from that source 
alone; and that their only means of safety was to seek a new land 
toward the setting sun.  Thus it was, that those tribes of the 
great valley of the Ottawa moved westward along the northern limits 
of Lake Huron and Lake Michigan and all about Ot-chip-we-ki-tchi-gami (Lake Superior), where many of them remain to this day.</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="5" id="d7"> 
<head>  ORIGIN OF OUR TRIBAL FLOWER&mdash;THE TRAILING ARBUTUS.</head> 
 
<p>    Many, many moons ago, there lived an old man alone in his 
lodge beside a stream in the thick woods.  He was heavily clad in 
furs; for it was winter, and all the world was covered with snow 
and ice.  The winds swept through the woods; searching every bush 
and tree for birds to chill, and chasing evil spirits over high 
hills, through tangled swamps, and valleys deep.  The old man went 
about, and peered vainly in the deep snow for pieces of wood to 
sustain the fire in his lodge.  Sitting down by the last dying 
embers, he cried to Kigi Manito Waw-kwi (the God of Heaven) that he 
might not perish.  The winds howled, and blew aside the door of his 
lodge, when in came a most beautiful maiden.  Her cheeks were like 
red roses; her eyes were large, and glowed like the fawn's in the 
moonlight; her hair was long and black as the raven's plumes, and 
touched the ground as she walked; her hands were covered with 
willow-buds; on her head were wreaths of wild flowers; her clothing 
was sweet grass and ferns; her moccasons were fair white lilies; 
and, when she breathed, the air of the lodge became warm and 
fragrant.  The old man said, "My daughter, I am indeed glad to see 
you.  My lodge is cold and cheerless; yet it will shield you from 
the tempest.  But tell me who you are, that you should come to my 
lodge in such strange clothing.  Come, sit down here, and tell me 
of thy country and thy victories, and I will tell thee of my 
exploits.  For I am Manito."  He then filled two pipes with 
tobacco, that they might smoke together as they talked.  When the 
smoke had warmed the old man's tongue, again he said, "I am Manito.  
I blow my breath, and the lakes and streams become flint."  The 
maiden answered, "I breathe, and flowers spring up on all the 
plains."  The old man replied, "I breathe, and the snow covers all 
the earth."  "I shake my tresses," returned the maiden, "and warm 
rains fall from the clouds."  "When I walk about," answered the old 
man, "leaves wither and fall from the trees.  At my command the 
animals hide themselves in the ground, and the fowls forsake the 
waters and fly <pb n="626"/>  away.  Again I say, 'I am Manito.'"  The 
maiden made answer: "When I walk about, the plants lift up their 
heads, and the naked trees robe themselves in living green; the 
birds come back; and all who see me sing for joy.  Music is 
everywhere."  As they talked the air became warmer and more 
fragrant in the lodge; and the old man's head drooped upon his 
breast, and he slept.  Then the sun came back, and the bluebirds 
came to the top of the lodge and sang, "We are thirsty.  We are 
thirsty."  And Sebin (the river) replied, "I am free.  Come, come 
and drink."  And while the old man was sleeping, the maiden passed 
her hand over his head; and he began to grow small.  Streams of 
water poured out of his mouth; very soon he became a small mass 
upon the ground; and his clothing turned to withered leaves. 
    </p><p> Then the maiden kneeled upon the ground, took from her bosom 
the most precious pink and white flowers, and, hiding them under 
the faded leaves, and breathing upon them, said: "I give you all my 
virtues, and all the sweetness of my breath; and all who would pick 
thee shall do so on bended knees." 
    </p><p> Then the maiden moved away through the woods and over the 
plains; all the birds sang to her; and wherever she stepped, and 
nowhere else, grows our tribal flower&mdash;the trailing arbutus.</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="6" id="d8"> 
<head>                     GOD'S KETTLE.</head> 
 
<p>     About two hundred and fifty years ago Weme-gen-debay, a noted 
chief and a great hunter, discovered, while hunting in the 
wilderness east of Traverse Bay, Michigan, a great kettle made of 
pure copper.  It was nearly covered with earth; and the roots of 
large trees had grown over and around it.  When taken out of the 
ground it had the appearance of never having been used.  The kettle 
was so large that a full-grown bear could be cooked whole in it.  
It was regarded as <hi rend="italic">Manito aukick</hi> (God's kettle).  Hence it 
was considered a sacred relic, was treated with a sort of 
reverential awe, and was kept securely hidden in a wild retreat 
unfrequented by man; never being used except when Tchi-bekan-kewin 
(the feast for the dead) was celebrated. 
    </p><p> When the Indians in the Grand Traverse region became civilized 
this magic kettle lost its sacred influence, and was used to boil 
maple sap to sugar, instead of for cooking bear at feasts.  
Blackbird, a noted Indian now living at Harbor Springs, Michigan, 
as late as 1840, made a bail for this kettle while he was at work 
in the Government blacksmith-shop at the old Mission on Grand 
Traverse Bay.  When I asked him, <pb n="627"/>  a short time since, what 
had become of that magic kettle, he replied, "I do not know, but 
must believe Manito has taken it home; for it disappeared as 
mysteriously as it came."</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="7" id="d9"> 
      <head>     THANKSGIVING FEASTS, AND FEASTS FOR THE DEAD.</head> 
 
<p>     In the spring-time of each year our forefathers held Ma-gosh-e-win&mdash;a religious feast of prayer and thanksgiving,&mdash;rejoicing 
that winter had passed, and that all nature was alive again.  At 
such times they erected in the centre of their camping-ground a 
high pole, on which they hung all their old, cast-off garments.  
Around this pole men, women, and children would sing and dance.  
The prayer of their song was, that Kigi Manito, who had brought 
back Ke-sus, the sun,&mdash;melting the snow and unlocking the ice-bound 
lakes and streams,&mdash;would look down upon his dependent children 
with love and compassion, and give them peace and plenty through 
another year.  After the close of this feast they celebrated the 
feast for the dead. 
    </p><p> All would march among the camp-fires; shaking hands whenever 
they met, singing in plaintive tones, "Ne-baw-baw-tchi-baw-yew ash-an-dis-win at-chak ne-bod" ("We are wandering about as spirits 
feeding the souls of the dead"), and at the same time eating, and 
throwing part of their food into the fire.  This practice of 
feasting the dead, and of burying their weapons and utensils with 
them, was done in the same spirit as that in which the dominant 
race provides clothing, flowers, and marble for its dead.  I 
believe there is no race on earth that has more reverence for its 
dead than ours.  Our greatest sorrow, in being driven from our 
homes, has been our separation from the graves of our fathers, 
which we loved so much. 
    </p><p> No greater insult can be given to Indians than to speak evil 
of their dead; for, say they, "The dead cannot speak for 
themselves; and the living that will not defend them are worse than 
Mau-tchi Manito (the Devil)."</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="8" id="d10"> 
      <head>                  LOVE AND MARRIAGE.</head> 
 
<p>     My feelings have often been mortified in reading in American 
histories that it was a custom among our people to marry for so 
many moons.  There never was a greater misstatement.  All our 
traditions most clearly show that, in our primitive state, we were 
a very virtuous people.  Love and marriage were regarded as of 
divine origin.  The false reports quoted in histories were made by 
white fur-traders, who, in early days, came among us, and, in order 
to get in closer touch with <pb n="628"/>  our people, intermarried.  They 
afterward deserted their Indian wives and children; returning to 
their own people, and branding us with the lie in order to hide 
their own shame. 
    </p><p> When our boys and girls become warmly attached to each other, 
they confidentially talk the matter over with their parents, who 
always sympathize with them in their love affairs; for, believe me, 
our children are never laughed at and tormented, as is the case 
with white people, as though it were a crime to fall in love. 
    </p><p> When lovers are married they repeat, generally in presence of 
both families, the following: "We now marry each other for life, 
before all our friends, now here assembled, by the command of the 
Great Spirit, who has united our hearts in one." 
    </p><p> Then the lovers simply join hands; their lips in mutual 
concert meet, and the marriage-knot is tied for life.</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="9" id="d11"> 
      <head>                THE SACRED WHITE DEER.</head> 
 
<p>     There is a very old superstition, still extant among our 
people, that white, or albino deer&mdash;which are very rare&mdash;are 
sacred.  They have for time out of mind been called <hi rend="italic">Manito 
sucsee wabe</hi> ("the sacred white deer"). 
    </p><p> It is believed that if anyone should shoot at and miss a white 
deer, he would be sick in consequence; and, that should he kill 
one, death would soon be the result.  I once encamped while hunting 
with a white man for partner.  Returning to our lodge one night, I 
told him how, during the day, I had had a chance to kill a most 
beautiful white buck, having the most perfect antlers I had ever 
seen, but that I had not had the heart to take his life, for I had 
always heard our old hunters say that the white deer was sacred, 
and that they never knew a hunter who killed one to live long.  He 
called me many hard names, and among other things, said: "Pokagon, 
you are as superstitious as an uneducated redskin.  Don't you know 
anything?  Why, we could have sold that deer for more than fifty 
dollars!" 
    </p><p> Yet this same man, a few days later, when we had started on 
our morning hunt, went back to the lodge, a distance of at least 
half a mile, to get an old horse-chestnut which he claimed had 
brought him good luck for years. 
     He would not hunt on Friday; fearing he might get shot.  I 
suggested to him one Friday morning that, if he should fill his 
pockets with chestnuts, he would be perfectly safe.  He talked very 
eloquently to me for some time; but he did not thank me for my 
advice.</p><pb n="629"/>  
  <p> In conclusion, permit Pokagon to say that he once thought that 
man's proneness to trust in superstitions was such a reflection on 
his natural ability, as to declare him unworthy of being considered 
spiritual and immortal.  But, after having associated with the 
dominant race, as well as his own, for more than fifty years, and 
after having learned that trust in superstitions creeps into the 
hearts of all races, whether savage, or civilized and enlightened, 
he has been forced to a contrary opinion; and he now believes with 
all his heart, that such trust in superstitions most emphatically 
declares that man is spiritual and immortal, and has a higher life 
beyond the grave.  In fact, it appears to him just as natural for 
man to trust in some intelligence higher than himself, who he 
believes brought him into being, as it is for children to trust in 
their parents. 
    </p><p> As reasonable beings, without prejudice, we cannot for a 
moment believe that heathen who bow down to idols, or savages who 
trust in totums, or the civilized who have faith in mascots, 
believe there is any power in the object itself, but simply that 
there is somehow or other, a spiritual intelligence connected with 
it, which they cannot understand or explain, independent of the 
thing itself.  They only know that it satisfies their nature to 
confide in it.  As beings of common sense, we cannot believe 
otherwise than that their feelings are akin to those of the little 
girl who pets and caresses her doll, sleeps with it; and embraces 
it with all the tenderness of a devoted mother, and yet not for a 
moment believes it real.  She is actuated to love and caress it in 
order to satisfy that parent love born in her own soul, which the 
God of nature has so wisely implanted in the breast of all human-kind. 
    </p><p> Those mother-like caresses of the little girl, as she plays 
with her doll, declare no more emphatically to our reason that she 
inherits maternal love, than do those acts of rational beings who 
idolize totums and mascots declare that they are spiritual beings 
connected in some way with a higher Intelligence, who created them 
and governs all, and to whom all are accountable in this life and 
in the life to come.  Pokagon does not wish to be understood, 
because he has reasoned by way of analogy in proof of spirituality, 
that he wishes to encourage idol-worship, after the relation 
between God and man has been revealed to men.  Nor can he 
understand how it is possible for true Christians to trust or 
confide in anything this side of eternity beyond the revealed God 
of Heaven, to satisfy their spiritual wants.</p>
<signed>SIMON POKAGON.</signed>

</div1></body>
</text>
</TEI.2> 
