<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="RouPoli"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="RouPoli"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Discourse on Political Economy</title>
<title type="sort">discourse on political economy</title>
<author>Rousseau, Jean-Jacques, 1712-1778</author>
<editor>Cole, G. D. H.</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Translator</resp> 
<name/> 
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>www.constitution.org</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">94</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">RouPoli</idno> 
<date value="2002">2002</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2002 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476351</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Social Contract and Discourses</title>
<title type="sort">social contract and discourses</title>
<author>Jean Jacques Rousseu</author>
<editor>G. D. H. Cole</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Translator</resp> 
<name/>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>E.P. Dutton and Company, Inc</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1950">1950</date> 
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:   Univeristy of Virginia, Alderman Library JC179R.85 1950</idno>
</publicationStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1755">1755</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language> 
<language id="grc">Greek</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term> 
<term>democracy</term> 
<term>philosophy</term> 
<term>sociology</term>
</keywords> 
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term> 
<term>prose</term> 
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2002-07">July 2002</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Irene Oh, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item/>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and/or corrected tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1"> 
 
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> 
<head> 
A DISCOURSE<lb/> 
ON POLITICAL ECONOMY<lb/> 
Jean Jacques Rousseau<lb/> 
<date value="1755">1755 
</date> 
</head> 
 
<p> 
 
THE word Economy, or &OElig;conomy, is derived from <hi rend="italic"> <foreign 
lang="grc">oikos</foreign>, a house</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"><foreign 
lang="grc">vomos</foreign>, law</hi>, and meant originally only the wise 
and legitimate government of the house for the common good of the whole 
family. The meaning of the term was then extended to the government of 
that great family, the State. To distinguish these two senses of the 
word, the latter is called <hi rend="italic">general</hi> or <hi rend="italic">political</hi> 
economy, and the former domestic or particular economy. The first only 
is discussed in the present discourse.</p> 
 
<p>Even if there were as close an analogy as many authors maintain 
between the State and the family, it would not follow that the rules of 
conduct proper for one of these societies would be also proper for the 
other. They differ too much in extent to be regulated in the same 
manner; and there will always be a great difference between domestic 
government, in which a father can see everything for himself, and civil 
government, where the chief sees hardly anything save through the eyes 
of others. To put both on an equality in this respect, the talents, 
strength, and all the faculties of the father would have to increase in 
proportion to the size of his family, and the soul of a powerful monarch 
would have to be, to that of an ordinary man, as the extent of his 
empire is to that of a private person's estate.</p> 
 
<p>But how could the government of the State be like that of the family, 
when the basis on which they rest is so different? The father being 
physically stronger than his children, his paternal authority, as long 
as they need his protection, may be reasonably said to be established by 
nature. But in the great family, all the members of which are naturally 
equal, the political authority, being purely arbitrary as far as its 
institution is concerned, can be founded only on conventions, and the 
Magistrate can have no authority over the rest, except by virtue of the 
laws. The duties of a father are dictated to him by natural feelings, 
and in a manner that seldom allows him to neglect them. For rulers there 
is no such principle, and they are really obliged to the people only by 
what they themselves have promised to do, and the people have therefore 
a right to require of them. Another more important difference is that 
since the children have nothing but what they receive from their father, 
it is plain that all the rights of property belong to him, or emanate 
from him; but quite the opposite is the case in the great family, where 
the general administration is established only to secure individual 
property, which is antecedent to it. The principal object of the work of 
the whole house is to preserve and increase the patrimony of the father, 
in order that he may be able some day to distribute it among his 
children without impoverishing them; whereas the wealth of the exchequer 
is only a means, often ill understood, of keeping the individuals in 
peace and plenty. In a word, the little family is destined to be 
extinguished, and to resolve itself some day into several families of a 
similar nature; but the great family, being constituted to endure for 
ever in the same condition, need not, like the small one, increase for 
the purpose of multiplying, but need only maintain itself; and it can 
easily be proved that any increase does it more harm than good.</p> 
 
<p>In the family, it is clear, for several reasons which lie in its very 
nature, that the father ought to command. In the first place, the 
authority ought not to be equally divided between father and mother; the 
government must be single, and in every division of opinion there must 
be one preponderant voice to decide. Secondly, however lightly we may 
regard the disadvantages peculiar to women, yet, as they necessarily 
occasion intervals of inaction, this is a sufficient reason for 
excluding them from this supreme authority: for when the balance is 
perfectly even, a straw is enough to turn the scale. Besides, the 
husband ought to be able to superintend his wife's conduct, because it 
is of importance for him to be assured that the children, whom he is 
obliged to acknowledge and maintain, belong to no one but himself. 
Thirdly, children should be obedient to their father, at first of 
necessity, and afterwards from gratitude: after having had their wants 
satisfied by him during one half of their lives, they ought to 
consecrate the other half to providing for his. Fourthly, servants owe 
him their services in exchange for the provision he makes for them, 
though they may break off the bargain as soon as it ceases to suit them. 
I say nothing here of slavery, because it is contrary to nature, and 
cannot be authorised by any right or law.</p> 
 
<p>There is nothing of all this in political society, in which the chief 
is so far from having any natural interest in the happiness of the 
individuals, that it is not uncommon for him to seek his own in their 
misery. If the magistracy is hereditary, a community of men is often 
governed by a child. If it be elective, innumerable inconveniences arise 
from such election; while in both cases all the advantages of paternity 
are lost. If you have but a single ruler, you lie at the discretion of a 
master who has no reason to love you: and if you have several, you must 
bear at once their tyranny and their divisions. In a word, abuses are 
inevitable and their consequences fatal in every society where the 
public interest and the laws have no natural force, and are perpetually 
attacked by personal interest and the passions of the ruler and the 
members.</p> 
 
<p>Although the functions of the father of a family and those of the 
chief magistrate ought to make for the same object, they must do so in 
such different ways, and their duty and rights are so essentially 
distinct, that we cannot confound them without forming very false ideas 
about the fundamental laws of society, and falling into errors which are 
fatal to mankind. In fact, if the voice of nature is the best counsellor 
to which a father can listen in the discharge of his duty, for the 
Magistrate it is a false guide, which continually prevents him from 
performing his, and leads him on sooner or later to the ruin of himself 
and of the State, if he is not restrained by the most sublime virtue. 
The only precaution necessary for the father of a family is to guard 
himself against depravity, and prevent his natural inclinations from 
being corrupted; whereas it is these themselves which corrupt the 
Magistrate. In order to act aright, the first 
 has only to consult his heart; the other becomes a traitor the moment 
he listens to his. Even his own reason should be suspect to him, nor 
should he follow any rule other than the public reason, which is the 
law. Thus nature has made a multitude of good fathers of families; but 
it is doubtful whether, from the very beginning of the world, human 
wisdom has made ten men capable of governing their peers.</p> 
 
<p>From all that has just been said, it follows that <hi rend="italic">public</hi> 
economy, which is my subject, has been rightly distinguished from 
<hi rend="italic">private</hi> economy, and that, the State having nothing in common 
with the family except the obligations which their heads lie under of 
making both of them happy, the same rules of conduct cannot apply to 
both. I have considered these few lines enough to overthrow the 
detestable system which Sir Robert Filmer has endeavoured to establish 
in his <hi rend="italic">Patriarcha</hi>; a work to which two celebrated writers have 
done too much honour in writing books to refute it. Moreover, this error 
is of very long standing; for Aristotle himself thought proper to combat 
it with arguments which may be found in the first book of his 
<hi rend="italic">Politics</hi>.</p> 
 
<p>I must here ask my readers to distinguish also between <hi rend="italic">public 
economy</hi>, which is my subject and which I call <hi rend="italic">government</hi>, 
and the supreme authority, which I call <hi rend="italic">Sovereignty</hi>; a 
distinction which consists in the fact that the latter has the right of 
legislation, and in certain cases binds the body of the nation itself, 
while the former has only the right of execution, and is binding only on 
individuals.</p> 
 
<p>I shall take the liberty of making use of a very common, and in some 
respects inaccurate, comparison, which will serve to illustrate my 
meaning.</p> 
 
<p>The body politic, taken individually, may be considered as an 
organised, living body, resembling that of man. The sovereign power 
represents the head; the laws and customs are the brain, the source of 
the nerves and seat of the understanding, will and senses, of which the 
Judges and Magistrates are the organs: commerce, industry, and 
agriculture are the mouth and stomach which prepare the common 
subsistence; the public income is the blood, which a prudent 
<hi rend="italic">economy</hi>, in performing the functions of the heart, causes to 
distribute through the whole body nutriment and life: the citizens are 
the body and the members, which make the machine live, move and work; 
and no part of this machine can be damaged without the painful 
impression being at once conveyed to the brain, if the animal is in a 
state of health.</p> 
 
<p>The life of both bodies is the self common to the whole, the 
reciprocal sensibility and internal correspondence of all the parts. 
Where this communication ceases, where the formal unity disappears, and 
the contiguous parts belong to one another only by juxtaposition, the 
man is dead, or the State is dissolved.</p> 
 
<p>The body politic, therefore, is also a moral being possessed of a 
will; and this general will, which tends always to the preservation and 
welfare of the whole and of every part, and is the source of the laws, 
constitutes for all the members of the State, in their relations to one 
another and to it, the rule of what is just or unjust: a truth which 
shows, by the way, how idly some writers have treated as theft the 
subtlety prescribed to children at Sparta for obtaining their frugal 
repasts, as if everything ordained by the law were not lawful.</p> 
 
<p>It is important to observe that this rule of justice, though certain 
with regard to all citizens, may be defective with regard to foreigners. 
The reason is clear. The will of the State, though general in relation 
to its own members, is no longer so in relation to other States and 
their members, but becomes, for them, a particular and individual will, 
which has its rule of justice in the law of nature. This, however, 
enters equally into the principle here laid down; for in such a case, 
the great city of the world becomes the body politic, whose general will 
is always the law of nature, and of which the different States and 
peoples are individual members. From these distinctions, applied to each 
political society and its members, are derived the most certain and 
universal rules, by which we can judge whether a government is good or 
bad, and in general of the morality of all human actions.</p> 
 
<p>Every political society is composed of other smaller societies of 
different kinds, each of which has its interests and its rules of 
conduct:  but those societies which everybody perceives, because they 
have an external and authorised form, are not the only ones that 
actually exist in the State: all individuals who are united by a common 
interest compose as many others, either transitory or permanent, whose 
influence is none the less real because it is less apparent, and the 
proper observation of whose various relations is the true knowledge of 
public morals and manners. The influence of all these tacit or formal 
associations causes, by the influence of their will, as many different 
modifications of the public will. The will of these particular societies 
has always two relations; for the members of the association, it is a 
general will; for the great society, it is a particular will; and it is 
often right with regard to the first object, and wrong as to the second. 
An individual may be a devout priest, a brave soldier, or a zealous 
senator, and yet a bad citizen. A particular resolution may be 
advantageous to the smaller community, but pernicious to the greater. It 
is true that particular societies being always subordinate to the 
general society in preference to others, the duty of a citizen takes 
precedence of that of a senator, and a man's duty of that of a citizen: 
but unhappily personal interest is always found in inverse ratio to 
duty, and increases in proportion as the association grows narrower, and 
the engagement less sacred; which irrefragably proves that the most 
general will is always the most just also, and that the voice of the 
people is in fact the voice of God.</p> 
 
<p>It does not follow that the public decisions are always equitable; 
they may possibly, for reasons which I have given, not be so when they 
have to do with foreigners. Thus it is not impossible that a Republic, 
though in itself well governed, should enter upon an unjust war. Nor is 
it less possible for the Council of a Democracy to pass unjust decrees, 
and condemn the innocent; but this never happens unless the people is 
seduced by private interests, which the credit or eloquence of some 
clever persons substitutes for those of the State: in which case the 
general will will be one thing, and the result of the public 
deliberation another. This is not contradicted by the case of the 
Athenian Democracy; for Athens was in fact not a Democracy, but a very 
tyrannical Aristocracy, governed by philosophers and orators. Carefully 
determine what happens in every public deliberation, and it will be seen 
that the general will is always for the common good; but very often 
there is a secret division, a tacit confederacy, which, for particular 
ends, causes the natural disposition of the assembly to be set at 
nought. In such a case the body of society is really divided into other 
bodies, the members of which acquire a general will, which is good and 
just with respect to these new bodies, but unjust and bad with regard to 
the whole, from which each is thus dismembered.</p> 
 
<p>We see then how easy it is, by the help of these principles, to 
explain those apparent contradictions, which are noticed in the conduct 
of many persons who are scrupulously honest in some respects, and cheats 
and scoundrels in others, who trample under foot the most sacred duties, 
and yet are faithful to the death to engagements that are often 
illegitimate.  Thus the most depraved of men always pay some sort of 
homage to public faith; and even robbers, who are the enemies of virtue 
in the great society, pay some respect to the shadow of it in their 
secret caves.</p> 
 
<p>In establishing the general will as the first principle of public 
<hi rend="italic">economy</hi>, and the fundamental rule of government, I have not 
thought it necessary to inquire seriously whether the Magistrates belong 
to the people, or the people to the Magistrates; or whether in public 
affairs the good of the State should be taken into account, or only that 
of its rulers. That question indeed has long been decided one way in 
theory, and another in practice; and in general it would be ridiculous 
to expect that those who are in fact masters will prefer any other 
interest to their own. It would not be improper, therefore, further to 
distinguish public <hi rend="italic">economy</hi> as popular or tyrannical. The former 
is that of every State, in which there reigns between the people and the 
rulers unity of interest and will:  the latter will necessarily exist 
wherever the government and the people have different interests, and, 
consequently, opposing wills. The rules of the latter are written at 
length in the archives of history, and in the satires of Machiavelli. 
The rules of the former are found only in the writings of those 
philosophers who venture to proclaim the rights of humanity.</p> 
 
<p>I. The first and most important rule of legitimate or popular 
government, that is to say, of government whose object is the good of 
the people, is therefore, as I have observed, to follow in everything 
the general will. But to follow this will it is necessary to know it, 
and above all to distinguish it from the particular will, beginning with 
one's self: this distinction is always very difficult to make, and only 
the most sublime virtue can afford sufficient illumination for it. As, 
in order to will, it is necessary to be free, a difficulty no less great 
than the former arises; that of preserving at once the public 
liberty and the authority of government. Look into the motives which 
have induced men, once united by their common needs in a general 
society, to unite themselves still more intimately by means of civil 
societies: you will find no other motive than that of assuring the 
property, life and liberty of each member by the protection of all. But 
can men be forced to defend the liberty of any one among them, without 
trespassing on that of others?  And how can they provide for the public 
needs, without alienating the individual property of those who are 
forced to contribute to them? With whatever sophistry all this may be 
covered over, it is certain that if any constraint can be laid on my 
will, I am no longer free, and that I am no longer master of my own 
property, if any one else can lay a hand on it.  This difficulty, which 
would have seemed insurmountable, has been removed, like the first, by 
the most sublime of all human institutions, or rather by a divine 
inspiration, which teaches mankind to imitate here below the 
unchangeable decrees of the Deity. By what inconceivable art has a means 
been found of making men free by making them subject; of using in the 
service of the State the properties, the persons and even the lives of 
all its members, without constraining and without consulting them; of 
confining their will by their own admission; of overcoming their refusal 
by that consent, and forcing them to punish themselves, when they act 
against their own will? How can it be that all should obey, yet nobody 
take upon him to command, and that all should serve, and yet have no 
masters, but be the more free, as, in apparent subjection, each loses no 
part of his liberty but what might be hurtful to that of another? These 
wonders are the work of law. It is to law alone that men owe justice and 
liberty. It is this salutary organ of the will of all which establishes, 
in civil right, the natural equality between men. It is this celestial 
voice which dictates to each citizen the precepts of public reason, and 
teaches him to act according to the rules of his own judgment, and not 
to behave inconsistently with himself. It is with this voice alone that 
political rulers should speak when they command; for no sooner does one 
man, setting aside the law, claim to subject another to his private 
will, than he departs from the state of civil society, and confronts him 
face to face in the pure state of nature, in which obedience is 
prescribed solely by necessity.</p> 
 
<p>The most pressing interest of the ruler, and even his most 
indispensable duty, therefore, is to watch over the observation of the 
laws of which he is the minister, and on which his whole authority is 
founded. At the same time, if he exacts the observance of them from 
others, he is the more strongly bound to observe them himself, since he 
enjoys all their favour.  For his example is of such force, that even if 
the people were willing to permit him to release himself from the yoke 
of the law, he ought to be cautious in availing himself of so dangerous 
a prerogative, which others might soon claim to usurp in their turn, and 
often use to his prejudice.  At bottom, as all social engagements are 
mutual in nature, it is impossible for any one to set himself above the 
law, without renouncing its advantages; for nobody is bound by any 
obligation to one who claims that he is under no obligations to others. 
For this reason no exemption from the law will ever be granted, on any 
ground whatsoever, in a well-regulated government. Those citizens who 
have deserved well of their country ought to be rewarded with honours, 
but never with privileges: for the Republic is at the eve of its fall, 
when any one can think it fine not to obey the laws. If the nobility or 
the soldiery should ever adopt such a maxim, all would be lost beyond 
redemption.</p> 
 
<p>The power of the laws depends still more on their own wisdom than on 
the severity of their administrators, and the public will derives its 
greatest weight from the reason which has dictated it. Hence Plato 
looked upon it as a very necessary precaution to place at the head of 
all edicts a preamble, setting forth their justice and utility. In fact, 
the first of all laws is to respect the laws: the severity of penalties 
is only a vain resource, invented by little minds in order to substitute 
terror for that respect which they have no means of obtaining. It has 
constantly been observed that in those countries where legal punishments 
are most severe, they are also most frequent; so that the cruelty of 
such punishments is a proof only of the multitude of criminals, and, 
punishing everything with equal severity, induces those who are guilty 
to commit crimes, in order to escape being punished for their 
faults.</p> 
 
<p>But though the government be not master of the law, it is much to be 
its guarantor, and to possess a thousand means of inspiring the love of 
it. In this alone the talent of reigning consists. With force in one's 
hands, there is no art required to make the whole world tremble, nor 
indeed much to gain men's hearts; for experience has long since taught 
the people to give its rulers great credit for all the evil they abstain 
from doing it, and to adore them if they do not absolutely hate it. A 
fool, if he be obeyed, may punish crimes as well as another: but the 
true statesman is he who knows how to prevent them: it is over the 
wills, even more than the actions, of his subjects that his honourable 
rule is extended. If he could secure that every one should act aright, 
he would no longer have anything to do; and the masterpiece of his 
labours would be to be able to remain unemployed. It is certain, at 
least, that the greatest talent a ruler can possess is to disguise his 
power, in order to render it less odious, and to conduct the State so 
peaceably as to make it seem to have no need of conductors.</p> 
 
<p>I conclude, therefore, that, as the first duty of the legislator is 
to make the laws conformable to the general will, the first rule of 
public <hi rend="italic">economy</hi> is that the administration of justice should be 
conformable to the laws. It will even be enough to prevent the State 
from being ill governed, that the Legislator shall have provided, as he 
should, for every need of place, climate, soil, custom, neighbourhood, 
and all the rest of the relations peculiar to the people he had to 
institute. Not but what there still remains an infinity of details of 
administration and economy, which are left to the wisdom of the 
government: but there are two infallible rules for its good conduct on 
these occasions; one is, that the spirit of the law ought to decide in 
every particular case that could not be foreseen; the other is that the 
general will, the source and supplement of all laws, should be consulted 
wherever they fail. But how, I shall be asked, can the general will be 
known in cases in which it has not expressed itself? Must the whole 
nation be assembled together at every unforeseen event? Certainly not. 
It ought the less to be assembled, because it is by no means certain 
that its decision would be the expression of the general will; besides, 
the method would be impractible in a great people, and is hardly ever 
necessary where the government is well-intentioned: for the rulers well 
know that the general will is always on the side which is most 
favourable to the public interest, that is to say, most equitable; so 
that it is needful only to act justly, to be certain of following the 
general will. When this is flouted too openly, it makes itself felt, in 
spite of the formidable restraint of the public authority. I shall cite 
the nearest possible examples that may be followed in such cases.</p> 
 
<p>In China, it is the constant maxim of the Prince to decide against 
his officers, in every dispute that arises between them and the people. 
If bread be too dear in any province, the Intendant of that province is 
thrown into prison. If there be an insurrection in another, the Governor 
is dismissed, and every Mandarin answers with his head for all the 
mischief that happens in his department. Not that these affairs do not 
subsequently undergo a regular examination; but long experience has 
caused the judgment to be thus anticipated. There is seldom any 
injustice to be repaired; in the meantime, the Emperor, being satisfied 
that public outcry does not arise without cause, always discovers, 
through the seditious clamours which he punishes, just grievances to 
redress.</p> 
 
<p>It is a great thing to preserve the rule of peace and order through 
all the parts of the Republic; it is a great thing that the State should 
be tranquil, and the law respected: but if nothing more is done, there 
will be in all this more appearance than reality; for that government 
which confines itself to mere obedience will find difficulty in getting 
itself obeyed. If it is good to know how to deal with men as they are, 
it is much better to make them what there is need that they should be. 
The most absolute authority is that which penetrates into a man's inmost 
being, and concerns itself no less with his will than with his actions. 
It is certain that all peoples become in the long run what the 
government makes them; warriors, citizens, men, when it so pleases: or 
merely populace and rabble, when it chooses to make them so. Hence every 
prince who despises his subjects, dishonours himself, in confessing that 
he does not know how to make them worthy of respect. Make men, 
therefore, if you would command men: if you would have them obedient to 
the laws, make them love the laws, and then they will need only to know 
what is their duty to do it. This was the great art of ancient 
governments, in those distant times when philosophers gave laws to men, 
and made use of their authority only to render them wise and happy. 
Thence arose the numerous sumptuary laws, the many regulations of 
morals, and all the public rules of conduct which were admitted or 
rejected with the greatest care. Even tyrants did not forget this 
important part of administration, but took as great pains to corrupt the 
morals of their slaves, as Magistrates took to correct those of their 
fellow-citizens. But our modern governments, which imagine they have 
done everything when they have raised money, conceive that it is 
unnecessary and even impossible to go a step further.</p> 
 
<p>II. The second essential rule of public economy is no less important 
than the first. If you would have the general will accomplished, bring 
all the particular wills into conformity with it; in other words, as 
virtue is nothing more than this conformity of the particular wills with 
the general will, establish the reign of virtue.</p> 
 
<p>If our politicians were less blinded by their ambition, they would 
see how impossible it is for any establishment whatever to act in the 
spirit of its institution, unless it is guided in accordance with the 
law of duty; they would feel that the greatest support of public 
authority lies in the hearts of the citizens, and that nothing can take 
the place of morality in the maintenance of government. It is not only 
upright men who know how to administer the laws; but at bottom only good 
men know how to obey them. The man who once gets the better of remorse, 
will not shrink before punishments which are less severe, and less 
lasting, and from which there is at least the hope of escaping: whatever 
precautions are taken, those who only require impunity in order to do 
wrong will not fail to find means of eluding the law, and avoiding its 
penalties. In this case, as all particular interests unite against the 
general interest, which is no longer that of any individual, public 
vices have a greater effect in enervating the laws than the laws in the 
repression of such vices: so that the corruption of the people and of 
their rulers will at length extend to the government, however wise it 
may be. The worst of all abuses is to pay an apparent obedience to the 
laws, only in order actually to break them with security. For in this 
case the best laws soon become the most pernicious; and it would be a 
hundred times better that they should not exist. In such a situation, it 
is vain to add edicts to edicts and regulations to regulations. 
Everything serves only to introduce new abuses, without correcting the 
old. The more laws are multiplied, the more they are despised, and all 
the new officials appointed to supervise them are only so many more 
people to break them, and either to share the plunder with their 
predecessors, or to plunder apart on their own. The reward of virtue 
soon becomes that of robbery; the vilest of men rise to the greatest 
credit; the greater they are the more despicable they become; their 
infamy appears even in their dignities, and their very honours dishonour 
them. If they buy the influence of the leaders or the protection of 
women, it is only that they may sell justice, duty, and the State in 
their turn: in the meantime, the people, feeling that its vices are not 
the first cause of its misfortunes, murmurs and complains that all its 
misfortunes come solely from those whom it pays to protect it from such 
things.</p> 
 
<p>It is under these circumstances that the voice of duty no longer 
speaks in men's hearts, and their rulers are obliged to substitute the 
cry of terror, or the lure of an apparent interest, of which they 
subsequently trick their creatures. In this situation they are compelled 
to have recourse to all the petty and despicable shifts which they call 
<hi rend="italic">rules of State</hi> and <hi rend="italic">mysteries of the cabinet</hi>. All the 
vigour that is left in the government is used by its members in ruining 
and supplanting one another, while the public business is neglected, or 
is transacted only as personal interest requires and directs. In short, 
the whole art of those great politicians lies in so mesmerising those 
they stand in need of, that each may think he is labouring for his own 
interest in working for theirs: I say <hi rend="italic">theirs</hi> on the false 
supposition that it is the real interest of rulers to annihilate a 
people in order to make it subject, and to ruin their own property in 
order to secure their possession of it.</p> 
 
<p>But when the citizens love their duty, and the guardians of the 
public authority sincerely apply themselves to the fostering of that 
love by their own example and assiduity, every difficulty vanishes; and 
government becomes so easy that it needs none of that art of darkness, 
whose blackness is its only mystery. Those enterprising spirits, so 
dangerous and so much admired, all those great ministers, whose glory is 
inseparable from the miseries of the people, are no longer regretted: 
public morality supplies what is wanting in the genius of the rulers; 
and the more virtue reigns, the less need there is for talent. Even 
ambition is better served by duty than by usurpation: when the people is 
convinced that its rulers are labouring only for its happiness, its 
deference saves them the trouble of labouring to strengthen their power: 
and history shows us, in a thousand cases, that the authority of one who 
is beloved over those whom he loves is a hundred times more absolute 
than all the tyranny of usurpers. This does not mean that the government 
ought to be afraid to make use of its power, but that it ought to make 
use of it only in a lawful manner. We find in history a thousand 
examples of pusillanimous or ambitious rulers, who were ruined by their 
slackness or their pride; not one who suffered for having been strictly 
just. But we ought not to confound negligence with moderation, or 
clemency with weakness. To be just, it is necessary to be severe; to 
permit vice, when one has the right and the power to suppress it, is to 
be oneself vicious.</p> 
 
<p>It is not enough to say to the citizens, <hi rend="italic">be good</hi>; they must 
be taught to be so; and even example, which is in this respect the first 
lesson, is not the sole means to be employed; patriotism is the most 
efficacious: for, as I have said already, every man is virtuous when his 
particular will is in all things conformable to the general will, and we 
voluntarily will what is willed by those whom we love. It appears that 
the feeling of humanity evaporates and grows feeble in embracing all 
mankind, and that we cannot be affected by the calamities of Tartary or 
Japan, in the same manner as we are by those of European nations. It is 
necessary in some degree to confine and limit our interest and 
compassion in order to make it active. Now, as this sentiment can be 
useful only to those with whom we have to live, it is proper that our 
humanity should confine itself to our fellow-citizens, and should 
receive a new force because we are in the habit of seeing them, and by 
reason of the common interest which unites them. It is certain that the 
greatest miracles of virtue have been produced by patriotism: this fine 
and lively feeling, which gives to the force of self-love all the beauty 
of virtue, lends it an energy which, without disfiguring it, makes it 
the most heroic of all passions. This it is that produces so many 
immortal actions, the glory of which dazzles our feeble eyes; and so 
many great men, whose old-world virtues pass for fables now that 
patriotism is made mock of. This is not surprising; the transports of 
susceptible hearts appear altogether fanciful to any one who has never 
felt them; and the love of one's country, which is a hundred times more 
lively and delightful than the love of a mistress, cannot be conceived 
except by experiencing it. But it is easy to perceive in every heart 
that is warmed by it, in all the actions it inspires, a glowing and 
sublime ardour which does not attend the purest virtue, when separated 
from it. Contrast Socrates even with Cato; the one was the greater 
philosopher, the other more of the citizen. Athens was already ruined in 
the time of Socrates, and he had no other country than the world at 
large.  Cato had the cause of his country always at heart; he lived for 
it alone, and could not bear to outlive it. The virtue of Socrates was 
that of the wisest of men; but, compared with Caesar and Pompey, Cato 
seems a God among mortals. Socrates instructed a few individuals, 
opposed the Sophists, and died for truth: but Cato defended his country, 
its liberty and its laws, against the conquerors of the world, and at 
length departed from the earth, when he had no longer a country to 
serve. A worthy pupil of Socrates would be the most virtuous of his 
contemporaries; but a worthy follower of Cato would be one of the 
greatest. The virtue of the former would be his happiness; the latter 
would seek his happiness in that of all. We should be taught by the one, 
and led by the other; and this alone is enough to determine which to 
prefer: for no people has ever been made into a nation of philosophers, 
but it is not impossible to make a people happy.</p> 
 
<p>Do we wish men to be virtuous? Then let us begin by making them love 
their country: but how can they love it, if their country be nothing 
more to them than to strangers, and afford them nothing but what it can 
refuse nobody? It would be still worse, if they did not enjoy even the 
privilege of social security, and if their lives, liberties and property 
lay at the mercy of persons in power, without their being permitted, or 
it being possible for them, to get relief from the laws. For in that 
case, being subjected to the duties of the state of civil society, 
without enjoying even the common privileges of the state of nature, and 
without being able to use their strength in their own defence, they 
would be in the worst condition in which freemen could possibly find 
themselves, and the word <hi rend="italic">country</hi> would mean for them something 
merely odious and ridiculous. It must not be imagined that a man can 
break or lose an arm, without the pain being conveyed to his head: nor 
is it any more credible that the general will should consent that any 
one member of the State, whoever he might be, should wound or destroy 
another, than it is that the fingers of a man in his senses should 
wilfully scratch his eyes out. The security of individuals is so 
intimately connected with the public confederation that, apart from the 
regard that must be paid to human weakness, that convention would in 
point of right be dissolved, if in the State a single citizen who might 
have been relieved were allowed to perish, or if one were wrongfully 
confined in prison, or if in one case an obviously unjust sentence were 
given. For the fundamental conventions being broken, it is impossible to 
conceive of any right or interest that could retain the people in the 
social union; unless they were restrained by force, which alone causes 
the dissolution of the state of civil society.</p> 
 
<p>In fact, does not the undertaking entered into by the whole body of 
the nation bind it to provide for the security of the least of its 
members with as much care as for that of all the rest? Is the welfare of 
a single citizen any less the common cause than that of the whole State? 
It may be said that it is good that one should perish for all. I am 
ready to admire such a saying when it comes from the lips of a virtuous 
and worthy patriot, voluntarily and dutifully sacrificing himself for 
the good of his country: but if we are to understand by it, that it is 
lawful for the government to sacrifice an innocent man for the good of 
the multitude, I look upon it as one of the most execrable rules tyranny 
ever invented, the greatest falsehood that can be advanced, the most 
dangerous admission that can be made, and a direct contradiction of the 
fundamental laws of society. So little is it the case that any one 
person ought to perish for all, that all have pledged their lives and 
properties for the defence of each, in order that the weakness of 
individuals may always be protected by the strength of the public, and 
each member by the whole State. Suppose we take from the whole people 
one individual after another, and then press the advocates of this rule 
to explain more exactly what they mean by the <hi rend="italic">body of the 
State</hi>, and we shall see that it will at length be reduced to a 
small number of persons, who are not the people, but the officers of the 
people, and who, having bound themselves by personal oath to perish for 
the welfare of the people, would thence infer that the people is to 
perish for their own.</p> 
 
<p>Need we look for examples of the protection which the State owes to 
its members, and the respect it owes to their persons? It is only among 
the most illustrious and courageous nations that they are to be found; 
it is only among free peoples that the dignity of man is realised. It is 
well known into what perplexity the whole republic of Sparta was thrown, 
when the question of punishing a guilty citizen arose.</p> 
 
<p>In Macedon, the life of a man was a matter of such importance, that 
Alexander the Great, at the height of his glory, would not have dared to 
put a Macedonian criminal to death in cold blood, till the accused had 
appeared to make his defence before his fellow-citizens, and had been 
condemned by them. But the Romans distinguished themselves above all 
other peoples by the regard which their government paid to the 
individual, and by its scrupulous attention to the preservation of the 
inviolable rights of all the members of the State. Nothing was so sacred 
among them as the life of a citizen; and no less than an assembly of the 
whole people was needed to condemn one. Not even the Senate, nor the 
Consuls, in all their majesty, possessed the right; but the crime and 
punishment of a citizen were regarded as a public calamity among the 
most powerful people in the world. So hard indeed did it seem to shed 
blood for any crime whatsoever, that by the Lex Porcia, the penalty of 
death was commuted into that of banishment for all those who were 
willing to survive the loss of so great a country. Everything both at 
Rome, and in the Roman armies, breathed that love of fellow-citizens one 
for another, and that respect for the Roman name, which raised the 
courage and inspired the virtue of every one who had the honour to bear 
it. The cap of a citizen delivered from slavery, the civic crown of him 
who had saved the life of another, were looked upon with the greatest 
pleasure amid the pomp of their triumphs; and it is remarkable that 
among the crowns which were bestowed in honour of splendid actions in 
war, the civic crown and that of the triumphant general alone were of 
laurel, all the others being merely of gold. It was thus that Rome was 
virtuous and became the mistress of the world. Ambitious rulers! A 
herdsman governs his dogs and cattle, and yet is only the meanest of 
mankind. If it be a fine thing to command, it is when those who obey us 
are capable of doing us honour. Show respect, therefore, to your 
fellow-citizens, and you will render yourselves worthy of respect; show 
respect to liberty, and your power will increase daily. Never exceed 
your rights, and they will soon become unlimited.</p> 
 
<p>Let our country then show itself the common mother of her citizens; 
let the advantages they enjoy in their country endear it to them; let 
the government leave them enough share in the public administration to 
make them feel that they are at home; and let the laws be in their eyes 
only the guarantees of the common liberty. These rights, great as they 
are, belong to all men: but without seeming to attack them directly, the 
ill-will of rulers may in fact easily reduce their effect to nothing. 
The law, which they thus abuse, serves the powerful at once as a weapon 
of offence, and as a shield against the weak; and the pretext of the 
public good is always the most dangerous scourge of the people. What is 
most necessary, and perhaps most difficult, in government, is rigid 
integrity in doing strict justice to all, and above all in protecting 
the poor against the tyranny of the rich. The greatest evil has already 
come about, when there are poor men to be defended, and rich men to be 
restrained. It is on the middle classes alone that the whole force of 
the law is exerted; they are equally powerless against the treasures of 
the rich and the penury of the poor. The first mocks them, the second 
escapes them. The one breaks the meshes, the other passes through 
them.</p> 
 
<p>It is therefore one of the most important functions of government to 
prevent extreme inequality of fortunes; not by taking away wealth from 
its possessors, but by depriving all men of means to accumulate it; not 
by building hospitals for the poor, but by securing the citizens from 
becoming poor. The unequal distribution of inhabitants over the 
territory, when men are crowded together in one place, while other 
places are depopulated; the encouragement of the arts that minister to 
luxury and of purely industrial arts at the expense of useful and 
laborious crafts; the sacrifice of agriculture to commerce; the 
necessitation of the tax-farmer by the mal-administration of the funds 
of the State; and in short, venality pushed to such an extreme that even 
public esteem is reckoned at a cash value, and virtue rated at a market 
price: these are the most obvious causes of opulence and of poverty, of 
public interest, of mutual hatred among citizens, of indifference to the 
common cause, of the corruption of the people, and of the weakening of 
all the springs of government. Such are the evils, which are with 
difficulty cured when they make themselves felt, but which a wise 
administration ought to prevent, if it is to maintain, along with good 
morals, respect for the laws, patriotism, and the influence of the 
general will.</p> 
 
<p>But all these precautions will be inadequate, unless rulers go still 
more to the root of the matter. I conclude this part of public economy 
where I ought to have begun it. There can be no patriotism without 
liberty, no liberty without virtue, no virtue without citizens; create 
citizens, and you have everything you need; without them, you will have 
nothing but debased slaves, from the rulers of the State downwards. To 
form citizens is not the work of a day; and in order to have men it is 
necessary to educate them when they are children. It will be said, 
perhaps, that whoever has men to govern, ought not to seek, beyond their 
nature, a perfection of which they are incapable; that he ought not to 
desire to destroy their passions; and that the execution of such an 
attempt is no more desirable than it is possible. I will agree, further, 
that a man without passions would certainly be a bad citizen; but it 
must be agreed also that, if men are not taught not to love some things, 
it is impossible to teach them to love one object more than another; to 
prefer that which is truly beautiful to that which is deformed. If, for 
example, they were early accustomed to regard their individuality only 
in its relation to the body of the State, and to be aware, so to speak, 
of their own existence merely as a part of that of the State, they might 
at length come to identify themselves in some degree with this greater 
whole, to feel themselves members of their country, and to love it with 
that exquisite feeling which no isolated person has save for himself; to 
lift up their spirits perpetually to this great object, and thus to 
transform into a sublime virtue that dangerous disposition which gives 
rise to all our vices. Not only does philosophy demonstrate the 
possibility of giving feeling these new directions; history furnishes us 
with a thousand striking examples. If they are so rare among us moderns, 
it is because nobody troubles himself whether citizens exist or not, and 
still less does anybody think of attending to the matter soon enough to 
make them. It is too late to change our natural inclinations, when they 
have taken their course, and egoism is confirmed by habit: it is too 
late to lead us out of ourselves when once the human Ego, concentrated 
in our hearts, has acquired that contemptible activity which absorbs all 
virtue and constitutes the life and being of little minds. How can 
patriotism germinate in the midst of so many other passions which 
smother it? And what can remain, for fellow-citizens, of a heart already 
divided between avarice, a mistress, and vanity?</p> 
 
<p>From the first moment of life, men ought to begin learning to deserve 
to live; and, as at the instant of birth we partake of the rights of 
citizenship, that instant ought to be the beginning of the exercise of 
our duty. If there are laws for the age of maturity, there ought to be 
laws for infancy, teaching obedience to others: and as the reason of 
each man is not left to be the sole arbiter of his duties, government 
ought the less indiscriminately to abandon to the intelligence and 
prejudices of fathers the education of their children, as that education 
is of still greater importance to the State than to the fathers: for, 
according to the course of nature, the death of the father often 
deprives him of the final fruits of education; but his country sooner or 
later perceives its effects. Families dissolve, but the State 
remains.</p> 
 
<p>Should the public authority, by taking the place of the father, and 
charging itself with that important function, acquire his rights by 
discharging his duties, he would have the less cause to complain, as he 
would only be changing his title, and would have in common, under the 
name of <hi rend="italic">citizen</hi>, the same authority over his children, as he 
was exercising separately under the name of <hi rend="italic">father</hi>, and would 
not be less obeyed when speaking in the name of the law, than when he 
spoke in that of nature. Public education, therefore, under regulations 
prescribed by the government, and under magistrates established by the 
Sovereign, is one of the fundamental rules of popular or legitimate 
government. If children are brought up in common in the bosom of 
equality; if they are imbued with the laws of the State and the precepts 
of the general will; if they are taught to respect these above all 
things; if they are surrounded by examples and objects which constantly 
remind them of the tender mother who nourishes them, of the love she 
bears them, of the inestimable benefits they receive from her, and of 
the return they owe her, we cannot doubt that they will learn to cherish 
one another mutually as brothers, to will nothing contrary to the will 
of society, to substitute the actions of men and citizens for the futile 
and vain babbling of sophists, and to become in time defenders and 
fathers of the country of which they will have been so long the 
children.</p> 
 
<p>I shall say nothing of the Magistrates destined to preside over such 
an education, which is certainly the most important business of the 
State. It is easy to see that if such marks of public confidence were 
conferred on slight grounds, if this sublime function were not, for 
those who have worthily discharged all other offices, the reward of 
labour, the pleasant and honourable repose of old age, and the crown of 
all honours, the whole enterprise would be useless and the education 
void of success. For wherever the lesson is not supported by authority, 
and the precept by example, all instruction is fruitless; and virtue 
itself loses its credit in the mouth of one who does not practise it. 
But let illustrious warriors, bent under the weight of their laurels, 
preach courage: let upright Magistrates, grown white in the purple and 
on the bench teach justice. Such teachers as these would thus get 
themselves virtuous successors, and transmit from age to age, to 
generations to come, the experience and talents of rulers, the courage 
and virtue of citizens, and common emulation in all to live and die for 
their country.</p> 
 
<p>I know of but three peoples which once practised public education, 
the Cretans, the Lacedemonians, and the ancient Persians: among all 
these it was attended with the greatest success, and indeed it did 
wonders among the two last. Since the world has been divided into 
nations too great to admit of being well governed, this method has been 
no longer practicable, and the reader will readily perceive other 
reasons why such a thing has never been attempted by any modern people. 
It is very remarkable that the Romans were able to dispense with it; but 
Rome was for five hundred years one continued miracle which the world 
cannot hope to see again. The virtue of the Romans, engendered by their 
horror of tyranny and the crimes of tyrants, and by an innate 
patriotism, made all their houses so many schools of citizenship; while 
the unlimited power of fathers over their children made the individual 
authority so rigid that the father was more feared than the Magistrate, 
and was in his family tribunal both censor of morals and avenger of the 
laws.</p> 
 
<p>Thus a careful and well-intentioned government, vigilant incessantly 
to maintain or restore patriotism and morality among the people, 
provides beforehand against the evils which sooner or later result from 
the indifference of the citizens to the fate of the Republic, keeping 
within narrow bounds that personal interest which so isolates the 
individual that the State is enfeebled by his power, and has nothing to 
hope from his good-will. Wherever men love their country, respect the 
laws, and live simply, little remains to be done in order to make them 
happy; and in public administration, where chance has less influence 
than in the lot of individuals, wisdom is so nearly allied to happiness, 
that the two objects are confounded.</p> 
 
<p>III. It is not enough to have citizens and to protect them, it is 
also necessary to consider their subsistence. Provision for the public 
wants is an obvious inference from the general will, and the third 
essential duty of government. This duty is not, we should feel, to fill 
the granaries of individuals and thereby to grant them a dispensation 
from labour, but to keep plenty so within their reach that labour is 
always necessary and never useless for its acquisition. It extends also 
to everything regarding the management of the exchequer, and the 
expenses of public administration. Having thus treated of general 
economy with reference to the government of persons, we must now 
consider it with reference to the administration of property.</p> 
 
<p>This part presents no fewer difficulties to solve, and contradictions 
to remove, than the preceding. It is certain that the right of property 
is the most sacred of all the rights of citizenship, and even more 
important in some respects than liberty itself; either because it more 
nearly affects the preservation of life, or because, property being more 
easily usurped and more difficult to defend than life, the law ought to 
pay a greater attention to what is most easily taken away; or finally, 
because property is the true foundation of civil society, and the real 
guarantee of the undertakings of citizens: for if property were not 
answerable for personal actions, nothing would be easier than to evade 
duties and laugh at the laws. On the other hand, it is no less certain 
that the maintenance of the State and the government involves costs and 
outgoings; and as every one who agrees to the end must acquiesce in the 
means, it follows that the members of a society ought to contribute from 
their property to its support. Besides, it is difficult to secure the 
property of individuals on one side, without attacking it on another; 
and it is impossible that all the regulations which govern the order of 
succession, will, contracts, etc., should not lay individuals under 
some constraint as to the disposition of their goods, and should not 
consequently restrict the right of property.</p> 
 
<p>But besides what I have said above of the agreement between the 
authority of law and the liberty of the citizen, there remains to be 
made, with respect to the disposition of goods, an important observation 
which removes many difficulties. As Puffendorf has shown, the right of 
property, by its very nature, does not extend beyond the life of the 
proprietor, and the moment a man is dead his goods cease to belong to 
him. Thus, to prescribe the conditions according to which he can dispose 
of them, is in reality less to alter his right as it appears, than to 
extend it in fact.</p> 
 
<p>In general, although the institution of the laws which regulate the 
power of individuals in the disposition of their own goods belongs only 
to the Sovereign, the spirit of these laws, which the government ought 
to follow in their application, is that, from father to son, and from 
relation to relation, the goods of a family should go as little out of 
it and be as little alienated as possible. There is a sensible reason 
for this in favour of children, to whom the right of property would be 
quite useless, if the father left them nothing, and who besides, having 
often contributed by their labour to the acquisition of their father's 
wealth, are in their own right associates with him in his right of 
property. But another reason, more distant, though not less important, 
is that nothing is more fatal to morality and to the Republic than the 
continual shifting of rank and fortune among the citizens: such changes 
are both the proof and the source of a thousand disorders, and overturn 
and confound everything; for those who were brought up to one thing find 
themselves destined for another; and neither those who rise nor those 
who fall are able to assume the rules of conduct, or to possess 
themselves of the qualifications requisite for their new condition, 
still less to discharge the duties it entails. I proceed to the object 
of public finance.</p> 
 
<p>If the people governed itself and there were no intermediary between 
the administration of the State and the citizens, they would have no 
more to do than to assess themselves occasionally, in proportion to the 
public needs and the abilities of individuals: and as they would all 
keep in sight the recovery and employment of such assessments, no fraud 
or abuse could slip into the management of them; the State would never 
be involved in debt, or the people over-burdened with taxes; or at least 
the knowledge of how the money would be used would be a consolation for 
the severity of the tax. But things cannot be carried on in this manner: 
on the contrary, however small any State may be, civil societies are 
always too populous to be under the immediate government of all their 
members. It is necessary that the public money should go through the 
hands of the rulers, all of whom have, besides the interests of the 
State, their own individual interests, which are not the last to be 
listened to. The people, on its side, perceiving rather the cupidity and 
ridiculous expenditure of its rulers than the public needs, murmurs at 
seeing itself stripped of necessaries to furnish others with 
superfluities; and when once these complaints have reached a certain 
degree of bitterness, the most upright administration will find it 
impossible to restore confidence. In such a case, voluntary 
contributions bring in nothing, and forced contributions are 
illegitimate. This cruel alternative of letting the State perish, or of 
violating the sacred right of property, which is its support, 
constitutes the great difficulty of just and prudent economy.</p> 
 
<p>The first step which the founder of a republic ought to take after 
the establishment of laws, is to settle a sufficient fund for the 
maintenance of the Magistrates and other Officials, and for other public 
expenses.  This fund, if it consist of money, is called <hi rend="italic">ararium</hi> 
or <hi rend="italic">fisc</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">public demesne</hi> if it consist of lands. 
This, for obvious reasons, is much to be preferred. Whoever has 
reflected on this matter must be of the opinion of Bodin, who looks upon 
the public demesne as the most reputable and certain means of providing 
for the needs of the State.  It is remarkable also that Romulus, in his 
division of lands, made it his first care to set apart a third for the 
use of the State. I confess it is not impossible for the produce of the 
demesne, if it be badly managed, to be reduced to nothing; but it is not 
of the essence of public demesnes to be badly administered.</p> 
 
<p>Before any use is made of this fund, it should be assigned or 
accepted by an assembly of the people, or of the estates of the country, 
which should determine its future use. After this solemnity, which makes 
such funds inalienable, their very nature is, in a manner, changed, and 
the revenues become so sacred, that it is not only the most infamous 
theft, but actual treason, to misapply them or pervert them from the 
purpose for which they were destined. It reflects great dishonour on 
Rome that the integrity of Cato the censor was something so very 
remarkable, and that an Emperor, on rewarding the talents of a singer 
with a few crowns, thought it necessary to observe that the money came 
from his own private purse, and not from that of the State. But if we 
find few Galbas, where are we to look for a Cato? For when vice is no 
longer dishonourable, what chiefs will be so scrupulous as to abstain 
from touching the public revenues that are left to their discretion, and 
even not in time to impose on themselves, by pretending to confound 
their own expensive and scandalous dissipations with the glory of the 
State, and the means of extending their own authority with the means of 
augmenting its power? It is particularly in this delicate part of the 
administration that virtue is the only effective instrument, and that 
the integrity of the Magistrate is the only real check upon his avarice. 
Books and auditing of accounts, instead of exposing frauds, only conceal 
them; for prudence is never so ready to conceive new precautions as 
knavery is to elude them. Never mind, then, about account books and 
papers; place the management of finance in honest hands: that is the 
only way to get it faithfully conducted.</p> 
 
<p>When public funds are once established, the rulers of the State 
become of right the administrators of them: for this administration 
constitutes a part of government which is always essential, though not 
always equally so. Its influence increases in proportion as that of 
other resources is diminished; and it may justly be said that a 
government has reached the last stage of corruption, when it has ceased 
to have sinews other than money. Now as every government constantly 
tends to become lax, this is enough to show why no State can subsist 
unless its revenues constantly increase.</p> 
 
<p>The first sense of the necessity of this increase is also the first 
sign of the internal disorder of the State; and the prudent 
administrator, in his endeavours to find means to provide for the 
present necessity, will neglect nothing to find out the distance cause 
of the new need; just as a mariner when he finds the water gaining on 
his vessel, does not neglect, while he is working the pumps, to discover 
and stop the leak.</p> 
 
<p>From this rule is deduced the most important rule in the 
administration of finance, which is, to take more pains to guard against 
needs than to increase revenues. For, whatever diligence be employed, 
the relief which only comes after, and more slowly than, the evil, 
always leaves some injury behind. While a remedy is being found for one 
evil, another is beginning to make itself felt, and even the remedies 
themselves produce new difficulties: so that at length the nation is 
involved in debt and the people oppressed, while the government loses 
its influence and can do very little with a great deal of money. I 
imagine it was owing to the recognition of this rule that such wonders 
were done by ancient governments, which did more with their parsimony 
than ours do with all their treasures; and perhaps from this comes the 
common use of the word <hi rend="italic">economy</hi>, which means rather the prudent 
management of what one has than ways of getting what one has not.</p> 
 
<p>But apart from the public demesne, which is of service to the State 
in proportion to the uprightness of those who govern, any one 
sufficiently acquainted with the whole force of the general 
administration, especially when it confines itself to legitimate 
methods, would be astonished at the resources the rulers can make use of 
for guarding against public needs, without trespassing on the goods of 
individuals. As they are masters of the whole commerce of the State, 
nothing is easier for them than to direct it into such channels as to 
provide for every need, without appearing to interfere. The distribution 
of provisions, money, and merchandise in just proportions, according to 
times and places, is the true secret of finance and the source of 
wealth, provided those who administer it have foresight enough to suffer 
a present apparent loss, in order really to obtain immense profits in 
the future. When we see a government paying bounties, instead of 
receiving duties, on the exportation of corn in time of plenty, and on 
its importation in time of scarcity, we must have such facts before our 
eyes if we are to be persuaded of their reality. We should hold such 
facts to be idle tales, if they had happened in ancient times. Let us 
suppose that, in order to prevent a scarcity in bad years, a proposal 
were made to establish public granaries; would not the maintenance of so 
useful an institution serve in most countries as an excuse for new 
taxes? At Geneva, such granaries, established and kept up by a prudent 
administration, are a public resource in bad years, and the principal 
revenue of the State at all times. <hi rend="italic">Alit et ditat</hi> is the 
inscription which stands, rightly and properly, on the front of the 
building. To set forth in this place the economic system of a good 
government, I have often turned my eyes to that of this Republic, 
rejoicing to find in my own country an example of that wisdom and 
happiness which I should be glad to see prevail in every other.</p> 
 
<p>If we ask how the needs of a State grow, we shall find they generally 
arise, like the wants of individuals, less from any real necessity than 
from the increase of useless desires, and that expenses are often 
augmented only to give a pretext for raising receipts: so that the State 
would sometimes gain by not being rich, and apparent wealth is in 
reality more burdensome than poverty itself would be. Rulers may indeed 
hope to keep the peoples in stricter dependence, by thus giving them 
with one hand what they take from them with the other; and this was in 
fact the policy of Joseph towards the Egyptians: but this political 
sophistry is the more fatal to the State, as the money never returns 
into the hands it went out of. Such principles only enrich the idle at 
the expense of the industrious.</p> 
 
<p>A desire for conquest is one of the most evident and dangerous causes 
of this increase. This desire, occasioned often by a different species 
of ambition from that which it seems to proclaim, is not always what it 
appears to be, and has not so much, for its real motive, the apparent 
desire to aggrandise the Nation as a secret desire to increase the 
authority of the rulers at home, by increasing the number of troops, and 
by the diversion which the objects of war occasion in the minds of the 
citizens.</p> 
 
<p>It is at least certain, that no peoples are so oppressed and wretched 
as conquering nations, and that their successes only increase their 
misery.  Did not history inform us of the fact, reason would suffice to 
tell us that, the greater a State grows, the heavier and more burdensome 
in proportion its expenses become: for every province has to furnish its 
share to the general expense of government, and besides has to be at the 
expense of its own administration, which is as great as if it were 
really independent. Add to this that great fortunes are always acquired 
in one place and spent in another. Production therefore soon ceases to 
balance consumption, and a whole country is impoverished merely to 
enrich a single town.</p> 
 
<p>Another source of the increase of public wants, which depends on the 
foregoing, is this. There may come a time when the citizens, no longer 
looking upon themselves as interested in the common cause, will cease to 
be the defenders of their country, and the Magistrates will prefer the 
command of mercenaries to that of free-men; if for no other reason than 
that, when the time comes, they may use them to reduce free-men to 
submission. Such was the state of Rome towards the end of the Republic 
and under the Emperors: for all the victories of the early Romans, like 
those of Alexander, had been won by brave citizens, who were ready, at 
need, to give their blood in the service of their country, but would 
never sell it.  Only at the siege of Veii did the practice of paying the 
Roman infantry begin. Marius, in the Jugurthine war, dishonoured the 
legions by introducing freedmen, vagabonds and other mercenaries. 
Tyrants, the enemies of the very people it was their duty to make happy, 
maintained regular troops, apparently to withstand the foreigner, but 
really to enslave their countrymen. To form such troops, it was 
necessary to take men from the land; the lack of their labour then 
diminished the amount of provisions, and their maintenance introduced 
those taxes which increased prices. This first disorder gave rise to 
murmurs among the people; in order to suppress them, the number of 
troops had to be increased, and consequently the misery of the people 
also got worse; and the growing despair led to still further increases 
in the cause in order to guard against its effects. On the other hand, 
the mercenaries, whose merit we may judge of by the price at which they 
sold themselves, proud of their own meanness, and despising the laws 
that protected them, as well as their fellows whose bread they ate, 
imagined themselves more honoured in being Caesar's satellites than in 
being defenders of Rome. As they were given over to blind obedience, 
their swords were always at the throats of their fellow-citizens, and 
they were prepared for general butchery at the first sign. It would not 
be difficult to show that this was one of the principal causes of the 
ruin of the Roman Empire.</p> 
 
<p>The invention of artillery and fortifications has forced the princes 
of Europe, in modern times, to return to the use of regular troops, in 
order to garrison their towns; but, however lawful their motives, it is 
to be feared the effect may be no less fatal. There is no better reason 
now than formerly for depopulating the country to form armies and 
garrisons, nor should the people be oppressed to support them; in a 
word, these dangerous establishments have increased of late years with 
such rapidity in this part of the world, that they evidently threaten to 
depopulate Europe, and sooner or later to ruin its inhabitants.</p> 
 
<p>Be this as it may, it ought to be seen that such institutions 
necessarily subvert the true economic system, which draws the principal 
revenue of the State from the public demesne, and leave only the 
troublesome resource of subsidies and imposts; with which it remains to 
deal.</p> 
 
<p>It should be remembered that the foundation of the social compact is 
property; and its first condition, that every one should be maintained 
in the peaceful possession of what belongs to him. It is true that, by 
the same treaty, every one binds himself, at least tacitly, to be 
assessed toward the public wants: but as this undertaking cannot 
prejudice the fundamental law, and presupposes that the need is clearly 
recognised by all who contribute to it, it is plain that such 
assessment, in order to be lawful, must be voluntary; it must depend, 
not indeed on a particular will, as if it were necessary to have the 
consent of each individual, and that he should give no more than just 
what he pleased, but on a general will, decided by vote of a majority, 
and on the basis of a proportional rating which leaves nothing arbitrary 
in the imposition of the tax.</p> 
 
<p>That taxes cannot be legitimately established except by the consent 
of the people or its representatives, is a truth generally admitted by 
all philosophers and jurists of any repute on questions of public right, 
not even excepting Bodin. If any of them have laid down rules which seem 
to contradict this, their particular motives for doing so may easily be 
seen; and they introduce so many conditions and restrictions that the 
argument comes at bottom to the same thing: for whether the people has 
it in its power to refuse, or the Sovereign ought not to exact, is a 
matter of indifference with regard to right; and if the point in 
question concerns only power, it is useless to inquire whether it is 
legitimate or not.  Contributions levied on the people are two kinds; 
real, levied on commodities, and personal, paid by the head. Both are 
called taxes or subsidies: when the people fixes the sum to be paid, it 
is called subsidy; but when it grants the product of an imposition, it 
is called a tax. We are told in <hi rend="italic">The Spirit of the Laws</hi> that a 
capitation tax is most suited to slavery, and a real tax most in 
accordance with liberty. This would be incontestable, if the 
circumstances of every person were equal; for otherwise nothing can be 
more disproportionate than such a tax; and it is in the observations of 
exact proportions that the spirit of liberty consists. But if a tax by 
heads were exactly proportioned to the circumstances of individuals, as 
what is called the capitation tax in France might be, it would be the 
most equitable and consequently the most proper for freemen.</p> 
 
<p>These proportions appear at first very easy to note, because, being 
relative to each man's position in the world, their incidence is always 
public: but proper regard is seldom paid to all the elements that should 
enter into such a calculation, even apart from deception arising from 
avarice, fraud and self-interest. In the first place, we have to 
consider the relation of quantities, according to which, <hi rend="italic">ceteris 
paribus</hi>, the person who has ten times the property of another man 
ought to pay ten times as much to the State. Secondly, the relation of 
the use made, that is to say, the distinction between necessaries and 
superfluities. He who possesses only the common necessaries of life 
should pay nothing at all, while the tax on him who is in possession of 
superfluities may justly be extended to everything he has over and above 
mere necessaries. To this he will possibly object that, when his rank is 
taken into account, what may be superfluous to a man of inferior station 
is necessary for him. But this is false: for a grandee has two legs just 
like a cow-herd, and, like him again, but one belly. Besides, these 
pretended necessaries are really so little necessary to his rank, that 
if he should renounce them on any worthy occasion, he would only be the 
more honoured. The populace would be ready to adore a Minister who went 
to Council on foot, because he had sold off his carriages to supply a 
pressing need of the State. Lastly, to no man does the law prescribe 
magnificence; and propriety is no argument against right.</p> 
 
<p>A third relation, which is never taken into account, though it ought 
to be the chief consideration, is the advantage that every person 
derives from the social confederacy; for this provides a powerful 
protection for the immense possessions of the rich, and hardly leaves 
the poor man in quiet possession of the cottage he builds with his own 
hands. Are not all the advantages of society for the rich and powerful? 
Are not all lucrative posts in their hands? Are not all privileges and 
exemptions reserved for them alone? Is not the public authority always 
on their side? If man of eminence robs his creditors, or is guilty of 
other knaveries, is he not always assured of impunity? Are not the 
assaults, acts of violence, assassinations, and even murders committed 
by the great, matters that are hushed up in a few months, and of which 
nothing more is thought? But if a great man himself is robbed or 
insulted, the whole police force is immediately in motion, and woe even 
to innocent persons who chance to be suspected. If he has to pass 
through any dangerous road, the country is up in arms to escort him. If 
the axle-tree of his chaise breaks, everybody flies to his assistance. 
If there is a noise at his door, he speaks but a word, and all is 
silent. If he is incommoded by the crowd, he waves his hand and every 
one makes way. If his coach is met on the road by a wagon, his servants 
are ready to beat the driver's brains out, and fifty honest pedestrians 
going quietly about their business had better be knocked on the head 
than an idle jackanapes be delayed in his coach. Yet all this respect 
costs him not a farthing: it is the rich man's right, and not what he 
buys with his wealth. How different is the case of the poor man! the 
more humanity owes him, the more society denies him. Every door is shut 
against him, even when he has a right to its being opened: and if ever 
he obtains justice, it is with much greater difficulty than others 
obtain favours. If the militia is to be raised or the highway to be 
mended, he is always given the preference; he always bears the burden 
which his richer neighbour has influence enough to get exempted from. On 
the least accident that happens to him, everybody avoids him: if his 
cart be overturned in the road, so far is he from receiving any 
assistance, that he is lucky if he does not get horse-whipped by the 
impudent lackeys of some young Duke; in a word, all gratuitous 
assistance is denied to the poor when they need it, just because they 
cannot pay for it. I look upon any poor man as totally undone, if he has 
the misfortune to have an honest heart, a fine daughter, and a powerful 
neighbour.</p> 
 
<p>Another no less important fact is that the losses of the poor are 
much harder to repair than those of the rich, and that the difficulty of 
acquisition is always greater in proportion as there is more need for 
it.  "Nothing comes out of nothing," is as true of life as in 
physics: money is the seed of money, and the first guinea is sometimes 
more difficult to acquire than the second million. Add to this that what 
the poor pay is lost to them for ever, and remains in, or returns to, 
the hands of the rich: and as, to those who share in the government or 
to their dependents, the whole produce of the taxes must sooner or later 
pass, although they pay their share, these persons have always a 
sensible interest in increasing them.</p> 
 
<p>The terms of the social compact between these two estates of men may 
be summed up in a few words. You have need of me, because I am 
rich and you are poor. We will therefore come to an agreement. I will 
permit you to have the honour of serving me, on condition that you 
bestow on me the little you have left, in return for the pains I shall 
take to command you.</p> 
 
<p>Putting all these considerations carefully together, we shall find 
that, in order to levy taxes in a truly equitable and proportionate 
manner, the imposition ought not to be in simple ratio to the property 
of the contributors, but in compound ratio to the difference of their 
conditions and the superfluity of their possessions. This very important 
and difficult operation is daily made by numbers of honest clerks, who 
know their arithmetic; but a Plato or a Montesquieu would not venture to 
undertake it without the greatest diffidence, or without praying to 
Heaven for understanding and integrity.</p> 
 
<p>Another disadvantage of personal taxes is that they may be too much 
felt or raised with too great severity. This, however, does not prevent 
them from being frequently evaded; for it is much easier for persons to 
escape a tax than for their possessions.</p> 
 
<p>Of all impositions, that on land, or real taxation, has always been 
regarded as most advantageous in countries where more attention is paid 
to what the tax will produce, and to the certainty of recovering the 
product, than to securing the least discomfort for the people. It has 
been even maintained that it is necessary to burden the peasant in order 
to rouse him from indolence, and that he would never work if he had no 
taxes to pay. But in all countries experience confutes this ridiculous 
notion. In England and Holland the farmer pays very little, and in China 
nothing: yet these are the countries in which the land is best 
cultivated. On the other hand, in those countries where the husbandman 
is taxed in proportion to the produce of his lands, he leaves them 
uncultivated, or reaps just as much from them as suffices for bare 
subsistence. For to him who loses the fruit of his labour, it is some 
gain to do nothing. To lay a tax on industry is a very singular 
expedient for banishing idleness.</p> 
 
<p>Taxes on land or corn, especially when they are excessive, lead to 
two results so fatal in their effect that they cannot but depopulate and 
ruin, in the long run, all countries in which they are established.</p> 
 
<p>The first of these arises from the defective circulation of specie; 
for industry and commerce draw all the money from the country into the 
capitals: and as the tax destroys the proportion there might otherwise 
be between the needs of the husbandman and the price of his corn, money 
is always leaving and never returning. Thus the richer the city the 
poorer the country. The product of the taxes passes from the hands of 
the Prince or his financial officers into those of artists and traders; 
and the husbandman, who receives only the smallest part of it, is at 
length exhausted by paying always the same, and receiving constantly 
less. How could a human body subsist if it had veins and no arteries, or 
if its arteries conveyed the blood only within four inches of the heart? 
Chardin tells us that in Persia the royal dues on commodities are paid 
in kind:  this custom, which, Herodotus informs us, prevailed long ago 
in the same country down to the time of Darius, might prevent the evil 
of which I have been speaking. But unless intendants, directors, 
commissioners, and warehousemen in Persia are a different kind of people 
from what they are elsewhere, I can hardly believe that the smallest 
part of this produce ever reaches the king, or that the corn is not 
spoilt in every granary, and the greater part of the warehouses not 
consumed by fire.</p> 
 
<p>The second evil effect arises from an apparent advantage, which 
aggravates the evil before it can be perceived. That is that corn is a 
commodity whose price is not enhanced by taxes in the country producing 
it, and which, in spite of its absolute necessity, may be diminished in 
quantity without the price being increased. Hence, many people die of 
hunger, although corn remains cheap, and the husbandman bears the whole 
charge of a tax, for which he cannot indemnify himself by the price of 
his corn. It must be observed that we ought not to reason about a 
land-tax in the same manner as about duties laid on various kinds of 
merchandise; for the effect of such duties is to raise the price, and 
they are paid by the buyers rather than the sellers. For these duties, 
however heavy, are still voluntary, and are paid by the merchant only in 
proportion to the quantity he buys; and as he buys only in proportion to 
his sale, he himself gives the law its particular application; but the 
farmer who is obliged to pay his rent at stated times, whether he sells 
or not, cannot wait till he can get his own price for his commodity: 
even if he is not forced to sell for mere subsistence, he must sell to 
pay the taxes; so that it is frequently the heaviness of the tax that 
keeps the price of corn low.</p> 
 
<p>It is further to be noticed that the resources of commerce and 
industry are so far from rendering the tax more supportable through 
abundance of money, that they only render it more burdensome. I shall 
not insist on what is very evident; i.e., that, although a greater or 
less quantity of money in a State may give it the greater or less credit 
in the eye of the foreigner, it makes not the least difference to the 
real fortune of the citizens, and does not make their condition any more 
or less comfortable.  But I must make these two important remarks: 
first, unless a State possesses superfluous commodities, and abundance 
of money results from foreign trade, only trading cities are sensible of 
the abundance; while the peasant only becomes relatively poorer. 
Secondly, as the price of everything is enhanced by the increase of 
money, taxes also must be proportionately increased; so that the farmer 
will find himself still more burdened without having more resources.</p> 
 
<p>It ought to be observed that the tax on land is a real duty on the 
produce. It is universally agreed, however, that nothing is so dangerous 
as a tax on corn paid by the purchaser: but how comes it we do not see 
that it is a hundred times worse when the duty is paid by the cultivator 
himself? Is not this an attack on the substance of the State at its very 
source? Is it not the directest possible method of depopulating a 
country, and therefore in the end ruining it? For the worst kind of 
scarcity a nation can suffer from is lack of inhabitants.</p> 
 
<p>Only the real statesman can rise, in imposing taxes, above the mere 
financial object: he alone can transform heavy burdens into useful 
regulations, and make the people even doubtful whether such 
establishments were not calculated rather for the good of the nation in 
general, than merely for the raising of money.</p> 
 
<p>Duties on the importation of foreign commodities, of which the 
natives are fond, without the country standing in need of them; on the 
exportation of those of the growth of the country which are not too 
plentiful, and which foreigners cannot do without: on the productions of 
frivolous and all too lucrative arts; on the importation of all pure 
luxuries; and in general on all objects of luxury; will answer the 
two-fold end in view. It is by such taxes, indeed, by which the poor are 
eased, and the burdens thrown on the rich, that it is possible to 
prevent the continual increase of inequality of fortune; the subjection 
of such a multitude of artisans and useless servants to the rich, the 
multiplication of idle persons in our cities, and the depopulation of 
the country-side.</p> 
 
<p>It is important that the value of any commodity and the duties laid 
on it should be so proportioned that the avarice of individuals may not 
be too strongly tempted to fraud by the greatness of the possible 
profit. To make smuggling difficult, those commodities should be singled 
out which are hardest to conceal. All duties should be rather paid by 
the consumer of the commodity taxed than by him who sells it: as the 
quantity of duty he would be obliged to pay would lay him open to 
greater temptations, and afford him more opportunities for fraud.</p> 
 
<p>This is the constant custom in China, a country where the taxes are 
greater and yet better paid than in any other part of the world. There 
the merchant himself pays no duty; the buyer alone, without murmuring or 
sedition, meets the whole charge; for as the necessaries of life, such 
as rice and corn, are absolutely exempt from taxation, the common people 
is not oppressed, and the duty falls only on those who are well-to-do. 
Precautions against smuggling ought not to be dictated so much by the 
fear of it occurring, as by the attention which the government should 
pay to securing individuals from being seduced by illegitimate profits, 
which first make them bad citizens, and afterwards soon turn them into 
dishonest men.</p> 
 
<p>Heavy taxes should be laid on servants in livery, on equipages, rich 
furniture, fine clothes, on spacious courts and gardens, on public 
entertainments of all kinds, on useless professions, such as dancers, 
singers, players, and in a word, on all that multiplicity of objects of 
luxury, amusement and idleness, which strike the eyes of all, and can 
the less be hidden, as their whole purpose is to be seen, without which 
they would be useless. We need be under no apprehension of the produce 
of these taxes being arbitrary, because they are laid on things not 
absolutely necessary. They must know but little of mankind who imagine 
that, after they have been once seduced by luxury, they can ever 
renounce it: they would a hundred times sooner renounce common 
necessaries, and had much rather die of hunger than of shame. The 
increase in their expense is only an additional reason for supporting 
them, when the vanity of appearing wealthy reaps its profit from the 
price of the thing and the charge of the tax. As long as there are rich 
people in the world, they will be desirous of distinguishing themselves 
from the poor, nor can the State devise a revenue less burdensome or 
more certain than what arises from this distinction.</p> 
 
<p>For the same reason, industry would have nothing to suffer from an 
economic system which increased the revenue, encouraged agriculture by 
relieving the husbandman, and insensibly tended to bring all fortunes 
nearer to that middle condition which constitutes the genuine strength 
of the State. These taxes might, I admit, bring certain fashionable 
articles of dress and amusement to an untimely end; but it would be only 
to substitute others, by which the artificer would gain, and the 
exchequer suffer no loss. In a word, suppose the spirit of government 
was constantly to tax only the superfluities of the rich, one of two 
things must happen:  either the rich would convert their superfluous 
expenses into useful ones, which would redound to the profit of the 
State, and thus the imposition of taxes would have the effect of the 
best sumptuary laws, the expenses of the State would necessarily 
diminish with those of individuals, and the treasury would not receive 
so much less as it would gain by having less to pay; or, if the rich did 
not become less extravagant, the exchequer would have such resources in 
the product of taxes on their expenditure as would provide for the needs 
of the State. In the first case the treasury would be the richer by what 
it would save, from having the less to do with its money; and in the 
second, it would be enriched by the useless expenses of individuals.</p> 
 
<p>We may add to all this a very important distinction in matters of 
political right, to which governments, constantly tenacious of doing 
everything for themselves, ought to pay great attention. It has been 
observed that personal taxes and duties on the necessaries of life, as 
they directly trespass on the right of property, and consequently on the 
true foundation of political society, are always liable to have 
dangerous results, if they are not established with the express consent 
of the people or its representatives. It is not the same with articles 
the use of which we can deny ourselves; for as the individual is under 
no absolute necessity to pay, his contribution may count as voluntary. 
The particular consent of each contributor then takes the place of the 
general consent of the whole people: for why should a people oppose the 
imposition of a tax which falls only on those who desire to pay it? It 
appears to me certain that everything, which is not proscribed by law, 
or contrary to morality, and yet may be prohibited by the government, 
may also be permitted on payment of a certain duty. Thus, for example, 
if the government may prohibit the use of coaches, it may certainly 
impose a tax on them; and this is a prudent and useful method of 
censuring their use without absolutely forbidding it. In this case, the 
tax may be regarded as a sort of fine, the product of which compensates 
for the abuse it punishes.</p> 
 
<p>It may perhaps be objected that those, whom Bodin calls 
<hi rend="italic">impostors</hi>, i.e., those who impose or contrive the taxes, being 
in the class of the rich, will be far from sparing themselves to relieve 
the poor. But this is quite beside the point. If, in every nation, those 
to whom the Sovereign commits the government of the people, were, from 
their position, its enemies, it would not be worth while to inquire what 
they ought to do to make the people happy.</p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
