<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="SchSiou"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="SchSiou">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Sun-Dance of the Sioux</title>
<title type="sort">sun dance of the sioux</title>
<author>Schwatka, Frederick</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">20</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">SchSiou</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476358</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Sun-Dance of the Sioux</title>
<title type="sort">sun dance of the sioux</title>
<author>Frederick Schwatka</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Century Magazine</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1890">1889-1890</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 39</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 753-759</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1890">1889-1890</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-10">October 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Minimal TEI tagging</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
	
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
<pb n="753"/>
<head>Schwatka, Frederick.  "The Sun-Dance of the Sioux."  <hi rend="italic">Century
Magazine</hi> 39 (1889-1890): 753-759.</head>

<p>A FEW years ago it was the good fortune of the writer to witness,
at the Spotted Tail Indian Agency, on Beaver Creek, Nebraska, the
ceremony of the great sun-dance of the Sioux.  Perhaps eight
thousand Brule Sioux were quartered at the agency at that time, and
about forty miles to the west, near the head of the White River,
there was another reservation of Sioux, numbering probably a
thousand or fifteen hundred less Ordinarily each tribe or
reservation has its own celebration of the sun-dance; but owing to
the nearness of these two
<pb n="754"/>
agencies it was this year thought
best to join forces and celebrate the savage rites with unwonted
splendor and barbarity.  Nearly half way between the reservations
the two forks of the Chadron (or Shadron) creek form a wide plain,
which was chosen as the site of the great sun-dance.
</p><p>In general it is almost impossible for a white man to gain
permission to view this ceremony in all its details; but I had in
Spotted Tail, the chief, and in Standing Elk, the head warrior, two
very warm friends, and their promise that I should behold the rites
in part slowly widened and allowed me to obtain full view of the
entire proceedings.
</p><p>It was in June that the celebration was to be held, and for
many days before the first ceremonies took place the children of
the prairies began to assemble, not only from the two agencies most
interested, but from many distant bands of Sioux to which rumors of
the importance of this meeting had gone.  Everywhere upon the
plains were picturesque little caravans moving towards the level
stretch between the branches of the Chadron &mdash; ponies dragging the
lodge-poles of the tepees, with roughly constructed willow baskets
hanging from the poles and filled with a confusion of pots and
puppies, babies and drums, scalps and kindling-wood and rolls of
jerked buffalo meat, with old hags urging on the ponies, and gay
young warriors riding.  Fully twenty thousand Sioux were present,
the half-breeds and the "squaw-men" of the two agencies said, when
the opening day arrived.  Probably fifteen thousand would be more
correct.  It was easier to believe the statement of the Indians
that it was the grandest sun-dance within the memory of the oldest
warriors; and as I became fully convinced of this assertion, I left
no stone unturned that would keep me fast in the good graces of my
friends, Spotted Tail and Standing Elk.
</p><p>When all had assembled and the medicine-men had set the day
for the beginning of the great dance dedicated to the sun, the
"sun-pole" was selected.  A handsome young pine or fir, forty or
fifty feet high, with the straightest and most uniformly tapering
trunk that could be found within a reasonable distance, was chosen.
The selection is always made by some old woman, generally the
oldest one in the camp, if there is any way of determining, who
leads a number of maidens gaily dressed in the beautiful beaded
buckskin gowns they wear on state occasions; the part of the
maidens is to strip the tree of its limbs as high as is possible
without felling it.  Woe to the girl who claims to be a maiden, and
joins the procession the old squaw forms, against whose claims any
reputable warrior or squaw may publicly proclaim.  Her punishment
is swift and sure, and her degradation more cruel than interesting.
</p><p>The selection of the tree is the only special feature of the
first day's celebration.  After it has been stripped of its
branches nearly to the top, the brushwood and trees for a
considerable distance about it are removed, and it is left standing
for the ceremony of the second day.
</p><p>Long before sunrise the eager participants in the next great
step were preparing themselves for the ordeal; and a quarter of an
hour before the sun rose above the broken hills of white clay a
long line of naked young warriors, in gorgeous war-paint and
feathers, with rifles, bows and arrows, and war-lances in hand,
faced the east and the sun-pole, which was from five to six hundred
yards away.  Ordinarily this group of warriors numbers from fifty
to possibly two hundred men.  An interpreter near me estimated the
line I beheld as from a thousand to twelve hundred strong.  Not far
away, on a high hill overlooking the barbaric scene, was an old
warrior, a medicine-man of the tribe, I think, whose solemn duty it
was to announce by a shout that could be heard by every one of the
expectant throng the exact moment when the tip of the morning sun
appeared above the eastern hills.  Perfect quiet rested upon the
line of young warriors and upon the great throng of savage
spectators that blacked the green hills overlooking the arena.
Suddenly the old warrior, who had been kneeling on one knee, with
his extended palm shading his scraggy eyebrows, arose to his full
height, and in a slow, dignified manner waved his blanketed arm
above his head.  The few warriors who were still unmounted now
jumped hurriedly upon their ponies; the broken, wavering line
rapidly took on a more regular appearance; and then the old man,
who had gathered himself for the great effort, hurled forth a yell
that could be heard to the uttermost limits of the great throng.
The morning sun had sent its commands to its warriors on earth to
charge.
</p><p>The shout from the hill was reechoed by the thousand men in
the valley; it was caught up by the spectators on the hills as the
long line of warriors hurled themselves forward towards the sun-pole, the objective point of every armed and naked savage in the
yelling line.  As they converged towards it the slower ponies
dropped out, and the weaker ones were crushed to the rear.  Nearer
and nearer they came, the long line becoming massed until it was
but a surging crowd of plunging horses and yelling, gesticulating
riders.  When the leading warriors had reached a point within a
hundred yards of the sun-pole, a sharp report of rifles sounded
along the line, and a
<pb n="755"/>
[illustration omitted]
<pb n="756"/>
moment
later the rushing mass was a sheet of flame, and the rattle of
rifle-shots was like the rapid beat of a drum resounding among the
hills.  Every shot, every arrow, and every lance was directed at
the pole, and bark and chips were flying from its sides like
shavings from the rotary bit of a planer.  When every bullet had
been discharged, and every arrow and lance had been hurled, the
riders crowded around the pole and shouted as only excited savages
can shout.
</p><p>Had it fallen in this onslaught, another pole would have been
chosen and another morning devoted to this performance.  Though
this seldom happens, it was thought that the numerous assailants of
this pole might bring it to the ground.  They did not, however,
although it looked like a ragged scarecrow, with chips and bark
hanging from its mutilated sides.
</p><p>That such a vast, tumultuous throng could escape accident in
all that wild charging, firing of shots, hurling of lances and
arrows, and great excitement would be bordering on a miracle, and
no miracle happened.  One of the great warriors was trampled upon
in the charge and died late that evening, and another Indian was
shot.  The bruises, sprains, and cuts that might have been spoken
of in lesser affairs were here unnoticed, and nothing was heard of
them.
</p><p>Later in the day the sun-pole was cut down and taken to the
center of the great plain between the two forks of the Chadron,
about a mile away.  Here a slight excavation was made, and into it
the butt of the sun-pole was put, and the tree, the bushy top
having now disappeared, was held upright by a number of ropes made
of buffalo thongs diverging from its top.  At their outer ends,
probably from seventy to eighty feet away from the sun-pole, they
were fastened to the tops of stakes seven or eight feet in length.
These, with a large number of stakes of similar size driven in
close together, formed a circular cordon around the sun-pole, and
over these stakes were stretched elk-skins and buffalo-robes,
canvas and blankets, and a wattling of willows and brush.
Sometimes canvas, blankets, and light elk-skins are thrown over the
supporting ropes to ward off in a slight way the fierce rays of the
noonday sun.  To one approaching by the road that led over the
winding hills which hem in the broad plain between the two forks of
the Chadron the affair looked not unlike a circus tent, the top of
which has been ruthlessly torn away by a cyclone.
</p><p>All day, from the closing of the ceremony of shooting at the
sun-pole, the attention of the Indians was occupied in constructing
this inclosure, where, within a day or two after its completion,
they performed those barbarous rites and ceremonies of cruelty and
self-torture that have placed the sun-dance of the Sioux on a level
with the barbarisms of any of the far more famed devotees of
Juggernaut.
</p><p>Early on the morning of the third or fourth day the true
worship of the sun, if it can be strictly so called, was begun.  So
far all that that luminary had done was to signal the charge of the
young warriors on the sun-pole.  It now entered into the
calculation of every minute, almost of every second, of the
barbarous proceedings.  Those who were to torture themselves,
probably forty or fifty in a sun-dance of this size, were, as near
as I could judge, young warriors from twenty to twenty-five years
of age, all of them the very finest specimens of savage manhood in
the great tribe.
</p><p>I was told that these fine fellows fast for a number of days
before they go through the self-torture, one informant saying that
before the ordeal takes place it is required of them to abstain
from food for seven days and from water for two.  While their
condition did not indicate such abstemiousness as this, I think it
true that some fasting precedes the more barbarous ceremonies.
</p><p>The third day was mostly consumed in dancing and in exercises
that did not vary greatly from the dances and exercises usually
seen at any time in large Indian villages.  On this day, however,
the sun-dance began.  Within the arena were from six to twelve
young warriors, still in war-costume of paint and feathers,
standing in a row, and always facing the sun, however brightly it
shone in their eyes; with fists clenched across the breast, like a
foot racer in a contest of speed, they jumped up and down in
measured leaps to the monotonous beating of the tom-toms and the
accompanying yi-yi-yi-yis of the assembled throng.  The dancers
occasionally vary the proceedings with savage music or with
whistles made of bone.  Now and then a similar row of young maidens
would appear in another part of the arena, and their soprano voices
would break in pleasantly on the harsher voices of the men.  The
dancing continued for intervals of from ten minutes to a quarter of
an hour, broken by rests of about equal length, and lasted from
sunrise to sunset.
</p><p>Many trifling ceremonies took place while the important ones
were proceeding.  Horses and ponies were brought into the arena,
and the medicine-men, with incantations, dipped their hands into
colored earth and besmeared the sides of the animals with it.  As
these animals were evidently the best war-ponies, the ceremony was
doubtless a blessing or a consecration to war.
</p><p>On the fourth day of the Chadron sun-dance the self-torture
began, and I was told that those who were to submit themselves to
the great
<pb n="757"/>
ordeal were the same young warriors who had been
dancing the day before.  Those who began the dance on the fourth
day took the final ordeal on the fifth, and so for four or five
days the dancers of one day became the sufferers of the tortures of
the next.
</p><p>The row of dancers took their places promptly at sunrise, but
it was not before nine or ten that the tortures began.
</p><p>Then each one of the young men presented himself to a
medicine-man, who took between his thumb and forefinger a fold of
the loose skin of the breast, about half way between the nipple and
the collar-bone, lifted it as high as possible, and then ran a very
narrow-bladed but sharp knife through the skin underneath the hand.
In the aperture thus made, and before the knife was withdrawn, a
stronger skewer of bone, about the size of a carpenter's pencil was
inserted.  Then the knife-blade was taken out, and over the
projection of this skewer, backwards and forwards, alternately
right and left, was thrown a figure-of-eight noose with a strong
thong of dressed skin.  This was tied to a long skin rope fastened,
at its other extremity, to the top of the sun-pole in the center of
the arena.  Both breasts are similarly punctured, the thongs from
each converging and joining the rope which hangs from the pole.
The whole object of the devotee is to break loose from these
fetters.  To liberate himself he must tear the skewers through the
skin, a horrible task that even with the most resolute may require
many hours of torture.  His first attempts are very easy, and seem
intended to get him used to the horrible pain he must yet endure
before he breaks loose from the thongs.  As he increases his
efforts his shouts increase, huge drops of perspiration pour down
his greasy, painted skin, and every muscle stands out on his body
in tortuous ridges, his swaying frame, as he throws his whole
weight wildly against the
<pb n="758"/>
fearful fetters, being convulsed
with shudders.  All the while the beating of the tom-toms and the
wild, weird chanting of the singers near him continue.  The
wonderful strength and extensibility of the human skin is most
forcibly and fearfully displayed in the strong struggles of the
quivering victims.  I have seen these bloody pieces of bone
stretched to such a length from the devotee that his outstretched
arms in front of him would barely allow his fingers to touch them.
</p><p>I know it is not pleasant to dwell long upon this cruel
spectacle.  Generally in two or three hours the victim is free, but
there are many cases where double and even triple that time is
required.  Oftentimes there are half a dozen swinging wildly from
the pole, running towards it and then moving backwards with the
swiftness of a war-horse and the fierceness of a lion in their
attempts to tear the accursed skewers from their wounded flesh.
Occasionally some over-ambitious youth will erect four stakes
within the arena, and fastening skewers to both breasts and to both
shoulders will throw himself backwards and forwards against the
four ropes that hold the skewers to the stakes.
</p><p>Faintings are not uncommon even among these sturdy savages;
but no forfeit, opprobrium, censure, or loss of respect in any way
seems to follow.  The victim is cut loose and placed on the floor
of some lodge near by and left in charge of his nurses.  The only
attempt I saw to break loose from double skewers in front and
behind terminated in this manner.  Whether the men ever afterwards
enter the cruel contest after having thus failed I do not know.  It
may be possible that some exceedingly ambitious warrior may enter
the lists year after year to show his prowess, but I understand
that it is supposed to be done but once in a lifetime.  It is not
obligatory, and by far
<pb n="759"/>
the greater number grow up sensibly
abstaining from such savage luxuries.  When the day is almost over,
and the solar deity is nearly down in the west, the self-tortured
warriors file from the inclosed arena, one by one, and just outside
the doors, deeply covered with handsomely painted buffalo-robes,
they kneel, and with arms crossed over their bloody breasts and
with bowed heads face the setting sun and rise only when it has
disappeared.
</p><p>Many other horrible variations have been reported to me; such
as tying a saddle or a buffalo's skull to the end of the long rope
fastened to the skewer and running over the prairie and through the
timber, the saddle or skull bounding after the victim until he
liberates himself; or, when fainting, to draw the tortured man
clear of the ground by the ropes until his weight overcame the
strength of the distended skin.  My informants told me that no two
of the ceremonies were alike, the self-torture in some form being
the one common link in all.  The consecration of the sun-pole, much
of the dancing and singing, the double efforts of ambitious youths,
and other ceremonies might be left out entirely or others
substituted.  I describe it only as I saw it.  I will add that this
sun-dance was called the greatest the Sioux had ever held; the
greatest self-sacrifice of the greatest native nation within our
boundaries.  Within a year they had checked, at the Rosebud Hills
in Montana, the largest army we had ever launched against the
American Indians in a single fight; had retired successfully to the
Little Big Horn, a few miles away, and there, a week later, had
wiped Custer's fine command from the face of the earth; had held
Reno for two days upon a hill; had never lost a battle worthy of
the name in the war which led to their subjugation; and had proved
the utter worthlessness of victory to a savage race contending
against civilization.
</p>
<signed>Frederick Schwatka.</signed>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
