<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="ScoPsyc"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="ScoPsyc">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Psychology of Advertising</title>
<title type="sort">psychology of advertising</title>
<author>Scott, Walter Dill, 1869-1955</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Charles Keller</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">35</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">ScoPsyc</idno>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476359</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Psychology of Advertising</title>
<title level="j">The Atlantic Monthly: A Magazine of Literature, Science, Art, and Politics. Vol. 93, no. 555.</title>
<title type="sort">psychology of advertising</title>
<author>Walter D. Scott</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pages 29-36</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Houghton, Mifflin and Company. | The Riverside Press.</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston and New York. | Cambridge, Mass.</pubPlace>
<date value="1904">1904</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa library, call no.: AP2.A8</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1904">1904</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; non-fiction</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-10">October 1997</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<front id="d2">

 <pb n="29"/>

<div1 type="note" id="d3">
<p>[This article, the first of a series of studies of Modern Advertising,
has been written by Walter D. Scott, Assistant Professor of Psychology in
Northwestern University.&mdash;THE EDITORS.]
</p>
</div1>

</front>
<body id="d4">

<div1 type="essay" id="d5">
<head>THE PSYCHOLOGY OF ADVERTISING.</head>

<p>THE only method of advertising known to the ancients was the word of
mouth.  The merchant who had wares to offer brought them to the gate of
a city and there cried aloud, making the worth of his goods known to
those who were entering the city, and who might be induced to turn aside
and purchase them. We are not more amused by the simplicity of the
ancients than we are amazed at the magnitude of the modern systems of
advertising. From the day when Boaz took his stand by the gate to
advertise Naomi's parcel of land by crying, "Ho, . . . turn aside," to
the day when Barnum billed the towns for his three-ringed circus, the
evolution in advertising had been gradual, but it had been as great as
that from the anthropoid ape to P. T. Barnum himself.

</p><p>As soon as printed symbols were invented the advertising man made
use of them to give publicity to his merchandise.  We find
advertisements engraved on walls and tombs, written on parchment and
papyrus, and printed by the first printing presses. Although these
various forms of advertising were employed, but little thought and care
seem to have been expended upon them. Posters, painted signs, street-car
placards, booklets, calendars, almanacs, handbills, magazine and
newspaper advertising have now become forms of advertising so well
established that we look upon them as a necessity, and are surprised to
learn that most of them are modern innovations.

</p><p>The first advertisement printed in English appeared in the
Imperial Intelligencer in March, 1648. Advertising in magazines was not
begun until comparatively recent times. For instance, the first
advertisement appeared

<milestone unit="column"/>

in Harper's Magazine in 1864. In this magazine more space has been
devoted to advertising during the past year than the sum total of space
for the twenty-four years from 1864 to 1887, inclusive.  Indeed,
advertising may be said to have been in its swaddling clothes until
about the year 1887. The most rapid development has taken place during
the last fifteen years. The change has been so great that the leading
advertisers say that in comparison with to-day there was in existence
fifteen years ago no advertising worthy of the name.

</p><p>The gain in the quantity of advertising can be seen by observing
the increase in the number of pages devoted to advertisements in any of
our publications.  The month of October is regarded as the typical
month, therefore we present the number of pages devoted to
advertisements for the month of October in Harper's Magazine for each
year from the first appearance of advertisements in that magazine to the
present time,&mdash;1864, 3&frac14;; '65, 2; '66, 3; '67, 6; '68, 7&frac13;;
'69, 5&frac13;; '70, 4&frac12;; '71, 3&frac12;; '72, 2; '73, 1; '74, 0;
'75, 0; '76, 0; '77, 0; '78,0; '79, 0; '80, 0; '81, 0; '82, 1&frac12;;
'83, 8&frac12;; '84, 8; '85, 11&frac12;; '86, 20; '87, 37; '88, 54; '89,
48; '90, 73; '91, 80&frac12;; '92, 87; '93, 77&frac12;; '94, 75&frac34;;
'95, 78&frac14;; '96, 73; '97, 80&frac34;; '98, 81&frac34;; '99,
106&frac34;; 1900, 97&frac12;; '01, 93&frac12;; '02, 128; '03, 141.

</p><p>It will be noticed in the data as given above that during the
years of special prosperity there was a very great increase in the
volume of advertising while there was but a slight falling off following
a financial depression. The increase was not pronounced until about
1887, but from that time on it has been very marked, not only in
Harper's, but in almost all of our publications.

   <pb n="30"/>

</p><p>There has not only been an increase in the number of advertising
pages in the individual publications, but the number of publications has
increased enormously of recent years. The increase of population in the
United States has been rapid during the last fifty years, but the
increase in the total number of copies of the different publications has
been many fold greater. Thus the distribution of the copies of these
periodicals to each individual was as follows:&mdash;

</p><p>In 1850 each individual received on the average 18 copies from
one or more of these periodicals; in 1860, 29; in 1870, 39; in 1880, 41;
in 1890, 74; in 1900, 107.

</p><p>A significant cause of this increase is the reduction in the
subscription price which is made possible because of the profit accruing
to such publications from their advertisements. The total income secured
from subscriptions for all these publications last year was less than
the amount paid for the advertising pages.  We have this current year
about 20,000 periodicals carrying advertisements, each with a constantly
increasing number of pages devoted to them, and with a rapidly advancing
rate secured for each advertisement.  In addition to this, the increase
is phenomenal in the use of booklets, posters, painted signs, street-car
placards, almanacs, and many other forms of advertising. One firm is
supposed to have distributed 25,000,000 almanacs in a single year.

</p><p>The expense connected with these various forms of printed
advertising reaches far into the millions. One authority puts the total
annual expense of printed forms of advertising at six hundred million
dollars. This sum does not seem to be an exaggeration. Mr. Post spends
as much as six hundred thousand dollars annually in advertising his food
products. One million dollars was spent last year in advertising Force.
Over six hundred thousand dollars is spent annually in advertising
Ayer's remedies;

<milestone unit="column"/>

and over one million dollars in advertising Peruna.

</p><p>The advertising rate has been advanced repeatedly in many
magazines during the last few years. Firms which formerly paid but one
hundred dollars for a full-page advertisement in the Century Magazine
now pay two hundred and fifty dollars for the same amount of space. The
Ladies' Home Journal has increased its advertising rate to six dollars
for a single agate line (there are fourteen agate lines to the inch),
the width of one column, for a single insertion.  The cost of a full
page for a single issue is four thousand dollars. The Procter &amp; Gamble
Co. have made a three years' contract for a single page in each issue,
to be devoted to the advertisement of Ivory Soap. For this space they
pay four thousand dollars a month, forty-eight thousand dollars a year,
and one hundred and forty-four thousand dollars for the term of three
years. Think of the risk a firm runs in investing four thousand dollars
in a single page advertisement!  How can they expect to get back the
equivalent of such a sum of money from a single advertisement?

</p><p>There are very many advertisements that do not pay. One man has
roughly estimated that seventy-five per cent of all advertisements do
not pay; yet the other twenty-five per cent pay so well that there is
scarcely a business man who is willing to stand idly by and allow his
competitors to do the advertising.  The expense connected with
advertising has increased; the competition between rival firms has
become keener; and consequently the demand for good advertising has
become imperative. The number of unsuccessful advertisements are many,
and yet the loss incurred in an unsuccessful advertising campaign is so
great that many firms stand aghast at the thought of such an
undertaking. Many merchants see the necessity of advertising their
business, but feel unable to enter the arena and compete with successful
rivals.

   <pb n="31"/>

</p><p>The day of reckless, sporadic, haphazard advertising is rapidly
coming to an end so far as magazine advertising is concerned. Although
the number of pages devoted to advertising in our best magazines has
increased during the last ten years, the number of firms advertising in
these same magazines has decreased.  The struggle has been too fierce
for any but the strongest. The inefficient advertisers are gradually
being eliminated, and the survival of the fittest seems to be a law of
advertising as it is of everything else that develops.

</p><p>The leaders of the profession feel that their work has grown till
it is beyond their control and comprehension. They have been successful,
and hardly know how it has all come about. The men who have been the
most successful are often the ones who feel most deeply their inability
to meet new emergencies. They believe that there should be some
underlying principles which could help them in analyzing what they have
already accomplished, and assist them in their further efforts. As their
entire object is to produce certain effects on the minds of possible
customers, it is not strange that they have turned to psychology in
search of such principles. Traditionally the practical business man
scouts at theory.  Psychology, to the popular mind, is something devoid
of all practical application, related to metaphysics, and suited only to
the recluse and the hermit. If ever there was ground to expect sarcastic
and pessimistic prophecies from the hard-headed business man, it was
when it was proposed to establish advertising on a theoretical basis
deduced from psychology.  Such adverse criticism has, however, been the
exception. The American business man is not afraid of theories. He wants
them, and the more the better.

</p><p>The best thought of the advertising world finds expression in the
advertising journals and in the addresses delivered by various experts
at gatherings of professional advertisers. In 1895 in one

<milestone unit="column"/>

of the leading advertising journals appeared the following editorial:
"Probably when we are a little more enlightened, the advertisement
writer, like the teacher, will study psychology. For, however diverse
their occupations may at first sight appear, the advertisement writer
and the teacher have one great object in common&mdash;to influence the human
mind. The teacher has a scientific foundation for his work in that
direction, but the advertisement writer is really also a psychologist.
Human nature is a great factor in advertising success; and he who writes
advertisements without reference to it is apt to find that he has
reckoned without his host." The man who penned this editorial was a
practical advertiser, but he admitted of no incongruity between the
practical and the theoretical.

</p><p>In Publicity, for March, 1901, appeared a leading article on
psychology and advertising. The following is a quotation from it:&mdash;

</p><p>"The time is not far away when the advertising writer will find
out the inestimable benefits of a knowledge of psychology.  The
preparation of copy has usually followed the instincts rather than the
analytical functions. An advertisement has been written to describe the
articles which it was wished to place before the reader; a bit of
cleverness, an attractive cut, or some other catchy device has been
used, with the hope that the hit or miss ratio could be made as
favorable as possible. But the future must needs be full of better
methods than these to make advertising advance with the same rapidity as
it has during the latter part of the last century. And this will come
through a closer knowledge of the psychological composition of the mind.
The so-called `students of human nature' will then be called successful
psychologists, and the successful advertisers will be likewise termed
psychological advertisers. The mere mention of psychological terms,
habit, self,

   <pb n="32"/>

conception, discrimination, association, memory, imagination and
perception, reason, emotion, instinct and will, should create a flood of
new thought that should appeal to every advanced consumer of advertising
space."

</p><p>In an address before the Agate Club of Chicago the speaker said:
"As advertisers, all your efforts have been to produce certain effects
on the minds of possible customers. Psychology is, broadly speaking, the
science of the mind. Art is the doing and science is the understanding
how to do, or the explanation of what has been done. If we are able to
find and to express the psychological laws upon which the art of
advertising is based, we shall have made a distinct advance, for we
shall have added the science to the art of advertising."

</p><p>In a recent address before the Atlas Club of Chicago the speaker
said: "In passing to the psychological aspect of our subject,
advertising might properly be defined as the art of determining the will
of possible customers.... Our acts are the resultants of our motives,
and it is your function in commercial life to create the motives that
will effect the sale of the producer's wares."

</p><p>In response to this felt need on the part of the advertiser,
several students of psychology have tried to select those principles of
psychology which might be of benefit to the advertiser, and to present
them to the advertising world through
pamphlets, <ref target="n1">[1]</ref>
magazine articles,<ref target="n2">[2]</ref>
public addresses,<ref target="n3">[3]</ref> and, in one case at least,
by means of a book.<ref target="n4">[4]</ref>

</p><p>The method employed by the psychologist in attempting to give
advertising a theoretical basis has been quite uniform.  He has first
analyzed the human mind into its various activities, then analyzed

<milestone unit="column"/>

advertisements to discover what there is in them that may or may not
awaken the activity desired. This method can best be understood from an
example. For an illustration we shall consider Mental Imagery as
understood by the psychologist and in its application to advertising.

</p><p>The man who is born blind is not only unable to see objects, but
he is equally unable to imagine how they look. After we have looked at
objects we can see them in our mind's eye with more or less
distinctness, even if our eyes are closed or the object is far removed
from us. When we imagine how an absent object looks we are said to have
a <hi rend="italic">visual image</hi> of it.  We cannot imagine how a thing looks unless
we have actually seen it in our previous experience. The imagination can
take the data of former experience and unite them into new forms, but
all the details of the new formation must be taken from the former
experience of the individual.

</p><p>The man who is born deaf can neither hear nor imagine what sounds
are like.  Whatever we have heard, we can live over again in
imagination,&mdash;we can form <hi rend="italic">auditory images</hi> of it. We cannot
imagine any sound which we have not actually heard, although we can
unite into new combinations the sounds and tones which we have
experienced.

</p><p>I can imagine how beefsteak tastes, but I cannot imagine the
taste of hashish, for in all my past experience I never have tasted it,
and do not even know which one of my former experiences it is like. If I
knew that it tasted like pepper, or like pepper and vinegar mixed, I
could form some sort of an image of its taste; but as it is I am
perfectly helpless when I try to imagine it. I can, with more or less
success, imagine how

   <pb n="33"/>

everything tastes which I have eaten, but I cannot imagine the taste of
a thing which I have not touched to my tongue.  Analogous descriptions
could be given of images of movements, of smell, of touch, of heat, of
cold, of pressure, and of pain.

</p><p>We have no direct knowledge of the minds of our neighbors; we
assume that their thinking is very much like ours, for their
actions&mdash;outward expressions of thought&mdash;are so similar to ours. It was
formerly assumed that, given any particular object of thought, all
normal minds would reach the same conclusion concerning it, and,
furthermore, the different stages in the line of thought and the "mind
stuff" would be the same throughout. Such a conception is wholly false.
Normal minds reach different conclusions under apparently identical
outward circumstances, but there is a greater difference in the terms of
thought, or the mind stuff with which the thinking is done. One man
thinks in terms of sight. He is said to be "eye-minded."  His thinking
is a rapid succession of pictures. When he thinks of a violin he thinks
rather how it looks than how it sounds.

</p><p>Another man thinks in terms of sound.  He is "ear-minded." His
thinking is a succession of sounds. When he thinks of his friends he
hears their voices, but cannot possibly imagine how they look.  He does
not know that there are other possible forms of thought, and so assumes
that all people think in terms of sound as he does. If he should
describe a battle his description would be full of the roar and tumult
of the strife. Another man is "motor-minded." He thinks in terms of
movements. Even when he looks at a painting he whispers inaudibly to
himself a description of the painting. Later when he describes the
picture to a friend he may do it in the terms which he whispered to
himself when he was looking at the picture.

</p><p>Thus it has been found that there are great personal differences
in normal individuals

<milestone unit="column"/>

in their ability to form certain classes of mental images.

</p><p>All persons seem to be able to form at least unclear and
indistinct visual images; most persons seem to have some ability in
forming auditory images; very many can imagine movements with some
degree of satisfaction. There are many who cannot imagine how pickles
taste; others cannot imagine the odor of a flower. There are persons who
have a limited ability to form all sorts of images, but most persons
have a very decided ability for one class and a corresponding weakness
for others. This difference in the ease with which certain classes of
images can be formed, as well as the difference in individuals in
imagining different classes of sensations, is followed with practical
consequences.

</p><p>In a former age the seller, the buyer, and the commodity were
brought together.  The seller described and exhibited his wares. The
buyer saw the goods, heard of them, tasted them, smelt them, felt, and
lifted them. He tested them by means of every sense organ to which they
could appeal. In this way the buyer became acquainted with the goods.
His perception of them was as complete as it could be made. In these
latter days the market-place has given way to the office. The consequent
separation of buyer, seller, and commodity made the commercial traveler
with his sample case seem a necessity. But, with the growing volume of
business, and with the increased need for more economical forms of
transacting business, the printed page, as a form of advertisement, has
superseded the market-place, and is, in many cases, displacing the
commercial traveler. In this transition from the market-place and the
commercial traveler to the printed page, the advertiser must be on his
guard to preserve as many as possible of the good features of the older
institutions.  In the two older forms of barter all the senses of the
purchaser were appealed to, if possible, and in addition to this the

   <pb n="34"/>

word of mouth of the seller was added to increase the impressions, and
to call special attention to the strong features of the commodity. In
the printed page the word of mouth is the only feature which is of
necessity entirely absent.  Indeed, the printed page cannot appeal
directly to any of the senses except the eye, but the argument may be of
such a nature that the reader's senses are appealed to indirectly
through his imagination.

</p><p>The function of our nervous system is to make us aware of the
sights, sounds, feelings, tastes, etc., of the objects in our
environment, and the more sensations we receive from an object the
better we know it. The nervous system which does not respond to sound or
to any other of the sensible qualities is a defective nervous system.
Advertisements are sometimes spoken of as the nervous system of the
business world. That advertisement of musical instruments which contains
nothing to awaken images of sound is a defective advertisement. That
advertisement of foods which contains nothing to awaken images of taste
is a defective advertisement. As our nervous system is constructed to
give us all the possible sensations from objects, so the advertisement
which is comparable to the nervous system must awaken in the reader as
many different kinds of images as the object itself can excite.

</p><p>A person can be appealed to most easily and most effectively
through his dominating imagery. Thus one who has visual images that are
very clear and distinct appreciates descriptions of scenes.  The one who
has strong auditory imagery delights in having auditory images awakened.
It is in general best to awaken as many different classes of images as
possible, for in this way variety is given, and each reader is appealed
to in the sort of imagery which is the most pleasing to him, in which he
thinks most readily, and by means of which he is most easily influenced.

<milestone unit="column"/>

</p><p>One of the great weaknesses of the present
day advertising is found in the fact
that the writer of the advertisement fails
to appeal thus indirectly to the senses.
How many advertisers describe a piano
so vividly that the reader can <hi rend="italic">hear</hi> it?
How many food products are so described
that the reader can <hi rend="italic">taste</hi> the food? How
many advertisements describe a perfume
so that the reader can <hi rend="italic">smell</hi> it? How
many describe an undergarment so that
the reader can <hi rend="italic">feel</hi> the pleasant contact
with his body? Many advertisers seem
never to have thought of this, and make
no attempt at such descriptions.

</p><p>The cause of this deficiency is twofold.  In the first place, it
is not easy in type to appeal to any other sense than that of sight.
Other than visual images are difficult to awaken when the means employed
is the printed page. In the second place, the individual writers are
deficient in certain forms of mental imagery, and therefore are not
adepts in describing articles in terms which to themselves are not
significant. This second ground for failure in writing effective
advertisements will be made clear by the examples taken from current
advertisements which are quoted below.

</p><p>A piano is primarily not a thing to look at or an object for
profitable investment, but it is a <hi rend="italic">musical</hi>
instrument. It might be beautiful and cheap, but still be very
undesirable. The chief thing about a piano is the quality of its tone.
Many advertisers of pianos do not seem to have the slightest
appreciation of this fact.

</p><p>When they attempt to describe a piano they seem as men groping in
the dark. Their statements are general and meaningless. As an example of
such a failure the advertisement of the Knabe Piano is typical:&mdash;

</p><p><hi rend="italic">The</hi> KNABE<lb/>

<hi rend="italic">Its successful growth and experience
of nearly seventy years guarantees
to new friends the greatest

   <pb n="35"/>

degree to tried and tested <hi rend="bold">excellence</hi>,
judged from any standpoint
of criticism or comparison</hi>.
</p><p>WM. KNABE &amp; CO.<lb/>
NEW YORK BALTIMORE WASHINGTON

</p><p>This is a half-page advertisement, but it contains no
illustration, makes no reference to tone or to any other quality of
music, and does not even suggest that the Knabe is a musical instrument
at all.  Many advertisers describe the appearance and durability of the
case or the cost of the entire instrument, but ordinarily their
statements are so general that the advertisement could be applied
equally well to perfumes, fountain pens, bicycles, automobiles, snuff,
or sausages, but would be equally inefficient if used to advertise any
of them. They do not describe or refer in any way to the essential
characteristics of a piano. They awaken no images of sound; they do not
make us hear a piano in our imagination.

</p><p>The following is a quotation in full of an advertisement of the
Vose Piano, but with the words "sewing machine" substituted for "piano."
This advertisement, like the one quoted above, contains no illustration,
and it will be noted that there is nothing in the text which does not
apply equally well to a sewing machine.

</p><p>VOSE<lb/>
SEWING MACHINES<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Have been Established over 51 Years</hi>
</p><p>They are perfect examples of sewing
machine strength. The Construction of
the <hi rend="italic">Vose</hi> is the result of fifty years of
development and the application of the
highest mechanical skill to the production
of each separate part.
</p><p>By our easy payment plan, every family in
moderate circumstances can own a fine sewing
machine. We allow a liberal price for old
instruments in exchange, and deliver the sewing
machine in your house free of expense. You
can deal with us at a distant point the same as
in Boston. <hi rend="italic">Send for our descriptive catalogue H,
which gives full information</hi>.
</p><p>VOSE &amp; SONS SEWING MACHINE CO.<lb/>
161 BOYLSTON STREET, BOSTON, MASS.

</p><p>Many of the advertisements of the Emerson, Weber, Everett, and of
a few other piano firms are equally poor attempts to present the
desirable features of pianos.

</p><p>In recent advertisements of the Blasius piano an attempt is made
to present a piano as a <hi rend="italic">musical</hi> instrument.
A music score is used as the background of the advertisement; there is a
cut of a young lady playing the piano; and in the text appear these
expressions: "Excellent tone," "the sweetest tone I ever heard," "sweet
and melodious in tone," "like a grand church organ for power and volume:
and a brilliant, sweet-toned piano in one." Thus the background, the
illustration, and the text all unite to awaken images of sound, and to
suggest that about a piano which is the real ground for desiring such an
instrument.

</p><p>In determining which foods I shall eat it is a matter of some
importance to know how the goods are manufactured, what the prices are,
how they are prepared for the table, and whether they are nourishing or
harmful to my system. The one essential element, however, is the
<hi rend="italic">taste</hi>.  When I look over a bill of fare I choose
what I think will taste good. When I order groceries I order what
pleases and tickles my palate. I want the food that makes me smack my
lips, that makes my mouth water. Under these circumstances all other
considerations are minimized to the extreme.

</p><p>In advertisements of food products it is surprising to note that
many foods are advertised as if they had no taste at all.  One would
suppose that the food was to be taken by means of a hypodermic
injection, and not by the ordinary process of taking the food into the
mouth and hence into contact with the organ of taste. The advertisers
seem to be at a loss to know what to say about their foods, and so have,
in many cases, expressed themselves in such general terms that their
advertisements could be applied to any product whatever.

   <pb n="36"/>

</p><p>The following is the complete text of a full-page advertisement
which appeared in recent magazines. The only change is that here we have
substituted "scouring soap" for the name of the commodity:

</p><p> "The grocer's smile. The smile that wont come off.<lb/>
More scouring soap the grocer said,<lb/>
No other brand will do instead;<lb/>
And o'er his kindly features spread<lb/>
The smile that won't come off.<lb/>
Look for the coupon in the package."

</p><p>The illustration was that of a grocer looking at a package which
might as well have been scouring soap as Quaker Oats.  There is nothing
to suggest taste.

</p><p>Some advertisers of food are evidently chronic dyspeptics, and
take it for granted that all others are in the same condition.  They
have nothing to say about their foods except that they have wonderful
medicinal properties. To me a food which is only healthful savors of
hospitals and sickrooms, and is something which a well man would not
want.

</p><p>There are other advertisers who appreciate the epicurean tendency
of the ordinary man and woman. They describe food in such a way that we
immediately want what they describe. The man who wrote the following
advertisement belongs to this class: "That very old proverb about
reaching the heart of a man is best exemplified with Nabisco sugar
wafers. A fairy sandwich with an upper and a lower crust of
indescribable delicacy, separated with a creamy flavor of lemon, orange,
chocolate, vanilla, strawberry, raspberry, or mint. Ask for your
favorite flavor." The picture represents a beautiful young lady
presenting a gentleman with the commodity described.

</p><p>This advertisement has character and individuality. Its
statements could not be applied to anything but foods, and, indeed, to
nothing but Nabisco. They do not say that Nabisco is healthy, but

<milestone unit="column"/>

when I read them I feel sure that Nabisco would agree with me.

</p><p>This illustration of the way in which one chapter of psychology
(Mental Imagery) can be applied to advertising is but one of a score of
illustrations which could be given. Psychology has come to be one of the
most fascinating of all the sciences, and bids fair to become of as
great practical benefit as physics and chemistry. As these latter form
the theoretical basis for all forms of industry which have to do with
matter, so psychology must form the theoretical basis for all forms of
endeavor which deal with mind.

</p><p>The householder in glancing through his morning paper has his
attention caught by the more attractive advertisements.  The mechanic in
going to and from his place of employment whiles away his time in
looking at the display cards in the trolley or the elevated cars.  The
business man can scarcely pass a day without being forced to look at the
advertisements which stare at him from the bill boards. The members of
the family turn over the advertising pages in their favorite magazine,
not because they are forced to, but because they find the advertisements
so interesting and instructive.  These persons are oblivious to the
enormous expense which the merchant has incurred in securing these
results.  They are unconscious of the fact that the results secured are
the ones sought for, and that in planning the advertising campaign the
merchant has made a study of the minds of these same householders,
mechanics, business men, and members of the family. Advertising is an
essential factor in modern business methods, and to advertise wisely the
business man must understand the workings of the minds of his customers,
and must know how to influence them effectively,&mdash;he must know how to
apply psychology to advertising.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Walter D. Scott.</hi>
</p>

<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">[1]</seg> <p><hi rend="italic">On the Psychology of Advertising</hi>. Professor
HARLOW GALE, author and publisher:
Minneapolis, Minn. 1900.</p></note>

<note id="n2"><seg type="note-symbol">[2]</seg> <p><hi rend="italic">Mahin's Magazine</hi>, Chicago. This magazine
contains monthly articles on The Psychology
of Advertising.</p></note>

<note id="n3"><seg type="note-symbol">[3]</seg> <p>Found in the published proceedings of the
various advertising clubs.</p></note>

<note id="n4"><seg type="note-symbol">[4]</seg> <p><hi rend="italic">The Theory of Advertising</hi>. By WALTER
DILL SCOTT. Boston: Small, Maynard &amp; Co 1903.</p></note>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

