<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="ShaDost"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="ShaDost">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Dostoievsky's Mystical Terror</title>
<title type="sort">dostoievskys mystical terror</title>
<author>Shaw, Charles Gray</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">29</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">ShaDost</idno>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476361</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Dostoievsky's Mystical Terror</title>
<title level="j">The North American Review</title>
<title type="sort">dostoievskys mystical terror</title>
<author>Charles Gray Shaw</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>246-256</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>North American Review Corporation</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1918">1918</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: U. Va. Library, Call No. AP2.N7, Vol. 207, Jan.-June 1918</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1918">1918</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
<language id="fr">French</language>
<language id="la">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose, non-fiction</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-08">August 1997</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Christopher Fennell, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and SGML tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> <pb n="246"/>
<head>DOSTOIEVSKY'S MYSTICAL TERROR <lb/>BY CHARLES GRAY SHAW</head>

<p>IT is a terrible thing to fall into the hands of the living God,
but that is what happened to Fydor Dostoievsky.  It was not Russia,
vast, fantastic, terrible, but real existence as such which wrung from
his soul his tales of self-inquisition.  "Reality has caught me upon a
hook"; this chance expression in one of his romances of reality is the
confessed secret of the anguished author.  Dostoievsky is Russia, and
"the Russian soul is a dark place."  Having said this of his own land,
Dostoievsky, without playing upon Amiel's pretty epigram, "the landscape
is a state of the soul," proceeds to show us how the outer darkness
pervades his own soul.  He knows not why, but at dusk there comes over
him an oppressive and agonizing state of mind difficult to define, but
recognizable in the form of "mystical terror."  Because of his
pessimistic realism, Dostoievsky is not to be understood by any attempt
to force his stubborn thought into the pens of conventional literature;
"standard authors" afford us no analogies, so that it is only by
relating the Russian to Job, Ezekiel, and the author of the Apocalypse
that we are able to make headway in reading Dostoievsky.  Hoffmann, Poe,
and Baudelaire played with the terrible as a boy plays with toy spiders
and snakes; but their soul-states knew no Siberias, their mental hides
escaped the hooks of reality.

</p><p>With the several volumes of Dostoievsky weighing one's
book-shelves down or with the ponderous pages spread
out before perplexed eyes, the reader cannot comprehend
Dostoievsky as artist unless the reader is prepared to look
upon art as absolute.  Style is swallowed up in significance,
technique surrenders to subject; for the story <hi rend="italic">is</hi> something,
not about something.  As architecture and music are arts
which refuse to represent something other than themselves,

   <pb n="247"/>

but are real and representative together, so the art of Dostoievsky,
instead of being pictorial and imitative, is so much reality spread out
before one's gaze.  The idea becomes fact, the mental solidifies, and
that which is said is no more, no less, than that which took place.  The
story is a stream which carries river-bank and river-bed along with it,
while huge cakes of reality float upon the surface.  Some of this
Russian realism Dostoievsky learned from Gogol, and, like many another
ardent Slav, he beheld the troika of Russia speeding its nocturnal way
like a thunderbolt from Heaven upon some mad mission of God.  But
Dostoievsky had no one to guide him when in his Slavonic demonism he
turned "Russian" into an adjective capable of qualifying things most
absolute.  In this spirit, he speaks of "Russian sympathy" as if to
suggest that the human heart has resources of compassion which man
outside Russia has not been permitted to feel.  Only the Russian nation
is "god-bearing"; in such a land alone may one say, "an atheist can't be
a Russian."  In his egregious zeal for the Slavonic mood, Dostoievsky
goes so far as to speak of "the Russian God," who, he admits, is in
danger of being overcome by cheap vodka.

</p><p>It is imperative to consider Dostoievsky's art from an intensive
standpoint as so much psychology, but a psychology which would strain
one of our modern laboratories, while its Russian aspects would
disconcert what is popularly known as "sociology."  The Russian writer
chooses to style it "double-edged psychology," whose methods of analysis
are so painful to the subject that he cries out, "Don't rummage in my
soul; cursed be all those who pry into the human heart."  Dostoievsky's
fascinating fear of psychology was probably due to the fact that his
most precious moments of introspection were enjoyed in connection with
his experience as an epileptic.  In the midst of his mystical terror,
the spirit rends his soul, while he screams as though another person
were crying out within his own soul.  Nevertheless, this epileptic
experience has its heights of transfiguration, since the sufferer with
his "special, sudden idea" is able to behold the "highest synthesis of
life."  Entering in true Russian fashion, without knocking, Reality
informs him that such an exalted moment is worth one's whole life, while
it further conveys the tidings that, after all, the whole world is
lovely, like trees, flowers,

   <pb n="248"/>

and children.  Reduced to exact formulation, as though a
moral maxim were concealed in that which is epileptic and
existential, this real moment persuades the sufferer that
"compassion is the only law of human existence," just as
it gives him apocalyptical assurance that time shall be no
more.  This eternal love of All comes in blinding flashes,
but from the tangled light-rays he weaves a web of moral
and religious meaning.

</p><p>However vague and disconnected the soul-states of Dostoievsky may
appear, it is doubtful whether his readers can deny that they are wholly
free from such "special, sudden ideas."  In practically every mind, no
matter how much common sense there may be, there are occasional
whirlpools and explosions which show how untamed are human ideas and
impulses.  At heart, all tend to feel somewhat of Dostoievsky's mystic
terror, even when they have the mystical tendencies and their better
natures pretty well under control.  As an exceptional psychologist of
the dark Russian soul, Dostoievsky is fond of rearing unexpected islands
in the stream of consciousness.  Every plan for the murder carefully
made, Raskolnikov, the hero in <hi rend="italic">Crime and Punishment</hi>, lies down to
wait for the coming of the necessary darkness.  The resolution to kill
his victim has been forged; the hatchet is by his side.  Now, in this
moment of waiting, he is as it were in Egypt on some palm-dotted oasis;
camel and caravan rest quietly, man and beast drink alike from the
murmuring stream as it flows over the many-colored stones and golden
spangles of the sandy bottom.  Between the idea of diabolical
preparation and the impulse which leads to the bloody execution of his
plan does this remote and charming picture pass in the mind of the
murderer.  Another example of unexpected abstraction occurs in <hi rend="italic">The
Idiot</hi>, where Lebedev, the money lender, who is just bereft of his
wife, spends the night upon his knees, but praying for the repose of the
Countess Du Barry's soul.  Dmitri Karamazov, about to leap from the
darkness and murder his father, notes with great care how the light from
the window of the paternal mansion intensifies the red of the berries
upon the near-by bush; in the criminal court where he undergoes
searching examination, he is fascinated by the amethyst in the
prosecutor's ring.  Instead of following a scientific psychology, which
would make the soul-state a mere appendage to the event in nature,
Dostoievsky is

   <pb n="249"/>

persuaded that consciousness has tides which rise and fall
in response to an unearthly influence.

</p><p>Two general principles seem to guide Dostoievsky's contemplation
of life: one is anthropological in its attempt to define man and place
him in a habitat; the other is racial, and seeks to analyze the Russian
soul.  As an anthropologist, Dostoievsky refuses to subsume man under
the genus home, just as he is unwilling to assign him to earth as his
home.  "Man," said Pascal, "is neither beast nor angel &mdash;
<foreign lang="fr"><hi rend="italic">ni b&ecirc;te, ni ange</hi></foreign>."  According to
Dostoievsky's calculation, <hi rend="italic">man is either beast or angel</hi>, since
he is never merely man; or, to use his own language, man is a "diamond
set in the dirty background of life."  Wholly wanting in Laodicean
conceptions of life, the artist prefers to regard man in Gadarean
fashion, a beast demonized from without.  "It has always been a mystery
to me," says he, "and I have marvelled a thousand times at that faculty
in man (and in the Russian, I believe, more especially) of cherishing
in his soul his loftiest ideal side by side with the most abject
baseness, and all quite sincerely."  In his mystic intuition of life,
Dostoievsky could behold nothing between the black, barren earth and
the endless shining of the sky; from which follows the fact that, as
he says, "the man with the ideal of Sodom in his soul does not
renounce the ideal of the Madonna."  The climax of this crass view
occurs in the clever but unhappy twist given to the words of the Latin
humanist: <foreign lang="la"><hi rend="italic">Satan sum et nihil humani me alienum
puto</hi></foreign>.

</p><p>The anthropology which makes of man a beast-angel is accompanied
by an exalted sociology which makes of Russia a peculiar blending of
Tartar and Buddhist.  With the Russian, there is no such thing as mere
living; man must either assert or deny the will to live.  For this
reason, the interpretation of Dostoievsky must be carried on in the
courts of a super-psychology and a major morality; if the reader clings
to his traditional ideas of man as a creature of common consciousness
and proper morality, he will soon be floundering in the flotsam of
Dostoievsky's turbid soul-stuff.  Schiller, whom he admired, looked
upon man as a chemical combination of sense and reason finely
synthesized through &aelig;sthetic education; but Dostoievsky himself
can concoct no plan suitable for uniting the Tartar beast with the
Buddhist angel; hence, he says of his Russian,
<foreign lang="fr"><hi rend="italic">'Grattez le russe et vous verrez le tartare.'
</hi></foreign> Catalogue the characters

   <pb n="250"/>

which move about in the romances of this Slavonic apostle, and you will
find, never a human being, but always an animal or an angel.  Out of
such a social appreciation of his own race, he extracts an opposed pair
of moral categories wholly distinct from the ethical presumptions of
extra-Russian moralists; they are those of strength and weakness, of
super-strength which makes man worse than bad, of victorious weakness
which makes the man better than the good.

</p><p>Enthralled by the idea of a super-strong consciousness which
turns human blood to lava or moulten iron, Dostoievsky makes Milton's
Satan and Nietzsche's blond beast appear quite amateurish and
unconvincing; the strong Slav is a reality in the artistic experience
of the writer.  "Strong natures," says he, "often find it difficult to
bear the burden of their strength."  Prominent among these strong ones
is Raskolnikov, who raises his nervous will to the
n<hi rend="super">th</hi> power of human volition; strictly speaking,
Raskolnikov has no will, but a volition-channel through which the
vicious assertiveness of the Tartar rushes like a spring freshet.  The
most systematic treatment of undue strength is found in <hi rend="italic">The
Brothers Karamazov</hi>, which celebrates the "primitive force of the
Karamazovs, a crude, unbridled earth-force, a thirst for life
regardless of everything."  Other nations, he tells us, may have their
Hamlets, but the Russians have their Karamazovs.  Dostoievsky's strong
one turns to crime to cleanse his soul of the sense of power whose
superabundance has become a burden to him.  In this spirit, Rogozhin,
in <hi rend="italic">The Idiot</hi>, with a garden-knife slays a family of six for
the sake of killing them, from which act of disinterested deviltry he
turns to the murder of his beautiful bride.  Prince Harry, in <hi rend="italic">The
Possessed</hi>, that Gadarean swine story, bites off the ear of the
old count who in his deafness is trying to hear what the youth has to
say.  Famous among Dostoievsky's tales of terror is that of the two
peasants who go to bed in the same room, whereupon one cuts the
other's throat because of the silver watch which his friend carries,
although the murderer has neither need of nor desire for the
time-piece.  To make the matter still more unearthly, the artist
assures us that the foul act was accompanied by a fervid prayer on the
part of the bloodthirsty man, who ejaculates, "God, forgive me for
Christ's sake."  Again, a young girl reads the story of a Jew who,
having cut off

   <pb n="251"/>

the fingers of a child, crucifies it with no regret save that the
Golgothan period of the child's suffering was limited to a paltry four
hours.  Not content with absorbing this touch of Sadism, the fair maid
often imagines that she herself is the Jew, while she adds a personal
touch to the story by expressing the idea that, had she done the deed,
she should want to sit by the cross <hi rend="italic">"eating pineapple compote</hi>."
According to Dostoievsky's amiable psychology of strength, everybody
loves crime, just as everybody in the Karamazov community loved Dmitri,
who was believed to have killed his father.  To such a murderous major
premise, the artist adds a minor one to the effect that, as a matter of
fact, one always wants to kill one's father.  Astounded as one may well
be by such tales and such interpretations, one should consider that the
news which keeps journalism alive is habitually pessimistic, since it is
made up of columns of human sin and human sorrow, just as one may recall
the further fact that the Man of the Evangel warned His disciples that
out of the heart of man come such things as wickedness, deceit,
foolishness, murder.

</p><p>Side by side with such frank frightfulness, for which even the
German U-boat fleet can hardly prepare us, Dostoievsky loves to place
accompanying tales of excessive want and extravagant self-abasement.
From tropic to poles his art passes without literary inconsistency.  In
his hands, the story shifts from the Slavonic to the Sanskrit, while a
word from him turns the Cossack into a Buddhist.  Meanwhile, we are kept
wondering just when man in the European and American sense will make his
appearance.  The underlying philosophy of Dostoievsky puzzles the eyes
of reading-room and magazine-people, because this philosophy puts the
negation of life upon a par with life-assertion.  "The law of
self-preservation and the law of self-destruction," says he, "are
equally strong in humanity."  Thus the Hindu becomes the match for the
Tartar, while the Buddhist hypnotizes the Cossack.  Walking side by side
with the ferocious characters and enjoying their crimson confidence too
are so many gentle souls whose sense of want and whose capacity for
compassion make them strange bed-fellows.  Prominent among these
amateur angels appear Vanya, in <hi rend="italic">Injured and Insulted</hi>, Prince
Myshkin, the "idiot," and Alesha, of the family Karamazov.  With such,
the need of negation and the nostalgia for the Nought

   <pb n="252"/>

expresses itself quite frankly in connection with suicide as a fine art.
Self-destruction is not at all uncommon; fear of dishonor, disappointed
love, and even the high cost of living instruct the coroner in his
search for causes.  However, Shakespeare and Schopenhauer have indulged
in the casuistry of self-destruction, so that suicide is a topic about
which we are, as it were, pretty well informed.  But, according to
Dostoievsky, no one has a right to take his life for a cause; if there
must be suicide, it must be for no reason at all.  In this manner,
Kraft, in <hi rend="italic">Injured and Insulted</hi>, takes his own precious and
promising life, because the science of craniology and anthropology have
led him to the conclusion that the Russians are a second-rate race, so
that to live as a Russian is not worth while.  The young consumptive in
<hi rend="italic">The Idiot</hi> contemplates but does not consummate suicide, not
because of his malady, but simply because the spectacle of life appears
in itself repulsive.  Stavrogin, in <hi rend="italic">The Possessed</hi>, is perfectly
willing to slip the noose about his neck, but fears that such a display
of courage may create the impression of a soul-greatness which he did
not possess.  Kirollov, the practical and successful man of affairs, is
anxious to take his useful life simply because he has no reason for so
doing.  "The highest point of self-will," so he argues, "is to kill
myself with my own hands.  To do this without any cause at all I shall
be the only one."  For himself, Dostoievsky concludes that life is at
its best when its tides are at their lowest ebb, its colors of an
infra-red tint.  The best man is the least of men, a kind of idiot who
possesses just enough volition and ideation to continue diplomatic
relations with life.  Good and bad, life and death are one; at the same
time, all souls are open to the one world; the endless publicity of
Siberian existence had taught Dostoievsky that bitter lesson.  "In
truth," he says, "we are each responsible for all, and it's only men who
don't know this.  If they did, the earth would be a paradise at once."
This oneness of human life on earth is the source of the artist's
sympathism; all may be walled in, but there are no separating
partitions.  Sorrow is sacred, hence the monk, in <hi rend="italic">The Brothers
Karamazov</hi>, bows in reverence before the suffering in store for the
young villain.  More striking and better known than this episode is the
incident in <hi rend="italic">Crime and Punishment</hi> where Raskolnikov kisses the
feet of the despised street-girl, and says, "I do

   <pb n="253"/>

not bow down to you personally, but to suffering humanity
in your person."  Such a text is the essence of the Russian
novel.

</p><p>Dostoievsky's theology is neither the latitudinarianism of
Berlin nor the anthropomorphism of the Kaiser.  Instead of accepting
the idea of God, he finds no possible way of rejecting the notion.
The Psalmist admitted that the fool might say,
<foreign lang="la"><hi rend="italic">non est deus</hi></foreign>, even when he did not think
it; but Dostoievsky cannot admit the possibility of the atheistic
<foreign lang="la"><hi rend="italic">dixit</hi></foreign>.  The atheist, he thinks,
"will always be talking about something else."  Like his favorite
character, Alesha Karamazov, Dostoievsky seems to say, "I am not
rebelling against God; I simply don't accept his world."
Dostoievsky's rejection of the world is due to the pessimistic
perception that the planet is the place of disorder, which fact makes
possible the art of the Russian, even when his &aelig;sthetic
capitalization of the cosmic chaos is not quite the same as that of
the munition-maker's.  That which gave Dostoievsky his deepest wound
was the thought that, when the Man appeared, the earth had no place
for Him except Golgotha.  It was indeed for the sake of the Man that
all things were made, and without Him all were madness; yet the fact
that the laws of the planet did not spare Him proves that "the very
laws of the planet are a lie, and the vaudeville of Devils."  There
are places in the art of Thomas Hardy where the condemnation of the
planet is no less strident; but Hardy proceeds to his bitter
conclusions in a spirit less tender and less evangelical.  Of the
Russian it may be said that this is perhaps the only place in his
&aelig;sthetic system where the mystic becomes malicious; even here
his indignation assumes no more threatening an aspect than that of the
"suffering smile."

</p><p>If atheists are always talking about something else than the
Deity whose existence they would deny, Dostoievsky showed his
willingness to listen to their rash utterances; it was as a mere
listener at Fourier meetings that he was condemned and exiled.  These
atheists who pour henbane into the ear seem to have reduced the cosmic
proportions of the Deity until God became little more than a magnified
Man, and as such an undesirable citizen.  Much of this fervent
anthropomorphism may be traced to the Hegelianism of Feuerbach and
others whom nihilists like Turgeniev had studied in Germany; some of it
was elaborated upon a quasipolitical

   <pb n="254"/>

basis, as if God were a sort of Czar.  This "god," so
Dostoievsky hears, is to be deposed and exiled; "then they will divide
history into two parts: from the gorilla to the annihilation of God, and
from the annihilation of God to the transformation of the earth and of
man."  Convinced that atheism cannot be fact, thought, or even word,
Dostoievsky further has compassion for "God," as for all other
unfortunates.  In this spirit, he makes the convict say, "If they drive
God from earth, we will shelter Him underground; and then we men
underground will sing from the bowels of earth a glorious hymn to God."
In general, Dostoievsky's art is a subterranean song, his religion the
bowels of cosmic compassion.  God torments him with inner calamities as
He used to torment the patriarch Job, but Dostoievsky still trusts; the
world seems like the Devil's vaudeville, yet he stoops to kiss the black
earth.  Man is naked and a beggar rejected by both heaven and earth, but
man may walk in the light, and while he <hi rend="italic">is</hi> nothing he may see
everything.

</p><p>It was Dostoievsky's fate to be possessed of a primitive and
patriarchal spirit and be called upon to display this in an age of
industry.  Place him in the world when creation was fresh and when the
newest winds of Heaven fanned faces not yet furrowed by doubt and care,
and your Dostoievsky had been fit and ready to join Enoch as he walked
with God.  But, finding himself in a world where economic systems have
become superior to things and men, Dostoievsky could not help invoking
the spirit of nihilism, even when he repudiated nihilistic politics as
such.  Confronted by the spectacle of his Russia engaged in industrial
activity, Dostoievsky can only condemn business and rejoice in the fact
that there are so few practical men in Russia.  In the midst of an
animated discussion on the subject of railways as the saviours of
Russia, Dostoievsky allows his 'idiot' to lisp something to this effect:
"I believe that beauty will save the world."

</p><p>Along with this spiritual nihilism which condemns the railway as
a soteriological principle goes Dostoievsky's repudiation of science.
He feels that science is selfish and tends to forbid pity, whence it
will be folly to put one's trust in its princes, just as Gorky admitted
that science was a divine beverage, but that up to the present time it
resembled Russian vodka, in that its ultimate yield was nothing

   <pb n="255"/>

but headache.  "Science," says Dostoievsky, "has ever given the
solution by the fist.  This is particularly characteristic of the
half-truths of science, the most terrible scourge of humanity, unknown
until the last (eighteenth) century, and worse than plague, famine, or
war."  Science, he believes, could not exist were it not for beauty,
while the contrast between the &aelig;sthetical and the scientific makes
it possible for one to conclude that "Shakespeare is better than boots,
Raphael greater than petroleum, the Sistine Madonna finer than a
pencil."  The Russian God may have survived the emancipation of the
serfs, but it is a question whether He can stand out against the
railways.

</p><p>Such epileptic exaggerations are more likely to occasion a smile
than to cause wrath, but it cannot be denied that there is in them the
implicit criticism of a philosophy which the thoughtful and
semi-thoughtful person of the day carries around with him.  All such
philosophers are interested in the exterior perfection of humanity as
this is to be found in the proper assembling and organizing of the sons
of men, just as they are mildly concerned about the elaboration of an
inner and intensive humanism as this is to appear in their own
individual hearts.  This is, of course, bourgeois, but better than
nothing; it sprouts up in labor-unions, in charity organizations here,
in free libraries and women's clubs there.  Now, can we deny that our
creeds begin with, 'I believe in railways'?  Our freight-rebates and
eight-hour-per-day strikes may distill some doubt about our new god,
but the Apostles worried along with the bag-holding Judas, and we ought
to be able to pull through in spite of our modern men from Kerioth.
Adam Smith and Herbert Spencer have formulated our new creeds for us, so
that we are beginning to feel quite at home in our new temples, which
like some new railway stations resemble the old Dorics and Gothics.
Dostoievsky may not have found the integrating principle which shall not
only bring men together, but persuade them that they belong together,
but he has been of some service in showing us that our hope in horses
and chariots, in steel cars and automobiles, is a vain and far-fetched
consolation.

</p><p>As to the terrified mystic himself, the reader of his unique
works may close the several volumes with the conviction that, no matter
what science may say about him, no matter what society may do to him,
man exists.  There must

   <pb n="256"/>

be some better way of describing the freedom of man in the world than to
do as Dostoievsky and Gorky do when they liken the present aimlessness
of human life to the meanderings of a "cockroach."  There must be some
superior way of evincing the spiritual character of man's inner self, so
that one will no longer need to follow Dostoievsky through all the
perturbed ramifications of the stricken soul.  While this philosophy of
man is being elaborated, we may keep in mind Dostoievsky's idea that
man, far from being a brick in the industrial wall or a cell in the
social organism, is an inner world-order, fantastic, terrible, yet
beautiful. . . .  According to the words of the apostle Jude, "Of
some have compassion, making a difference."  Dostoievsky
was "different."</p>

<closer><hi rend="small-caps">Charles Gray Shaw</hi>.</closer>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

