<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="SpoNeme"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="SpoNeme">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Nemesis of Motherhood</title>
<title type="sort">nemesis of motherhood</title>
<author>Spofford, Harriet Prescott</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">25</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">SpoNeme</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476375</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Nemesis of Motherhood</title>
<title level="j">Cosmopolitan</title>
<title type="sort">nemesis of motherhood</title>
<author>Harriet Prescott Spofford</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>International Magazine Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1899-04">April 1899</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This story appeared in Cosmopolitan Magazine, Volume
26 (April 1899), pp. 692-696.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions
for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899-04">April 1899</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-02-20">February 20, 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jennifer Hanna</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI-compatible header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="692"/>
<head>THE NEMESIS OF MOTHERHOOD.<lb/>
                   BY HARRIET PRESCOTT SPOFFORD.</head>

<epigraph>
<l>           "There are two moments in a diver's life: </l>
<l>            One, when a beggar he prepares to plunge, </l>
<l>            One, when a prince he rises with his pearl. </l>
<l>            Festus, I plunge."&mdash;<hi rend="italic">Browning.</hi> </l> </epigraph>

<div2 type="part" n="I" id="d4"> 

<p>THE hospital of the prison was little more than a whitewashed
corridor with bald daylight coming through the high gratings.  The
nurse was neither soft-footed nor soft-hearted.
</p><p>But the woman occupying one of the cots there was as oblivious
of outer circumstances as if she were in the middle of a cloud.  It
was, in fact, thick cloud that swathed her, body and soul, in black
shadow, as she lay there with her baby three days old.  If she
herself had ever been fair to see, there was small reason to
suspect the possibility now; and the little dark atom of humanity
she held would perhaps have given any but its mother a feeling of
repulsion.
</p><p>She had been sentenced to a term of years at hard labor for
her crime.  Although a young woman, she was an old offender.  It
was held among the officials that there was nothing so bad or so
vile that she might not be a part of its wickedness.  She had lived
on the plane of an animal, an exceedingly cunning and rather
vicious animal.  Her memories, could she have awakened them, would
have revolted any listener however abandoned, and have hardened the
heart of an angel.
</p><p>Yet as she lay there and felt the little new being at her
breast, two great tears welled from under her closed eyelids and
paused upon her cheeks; a sunbeam through the grating touched them
and painted in them the reflection of all heaven.  The nurse saw
the sunbeam, and drew the shade down; no one looked for any
reflection of heaven in that woman's tears.
</p><p>She was suffering little from her physical troubles, although
prostrate from weakness.  She knew that everything was wrong with
her; but that did not trouble her; she had been in hell too long,
she would have said, to fear now; and, to her, death, not birth,
seemed a sleep and a forgetting.  But through all her varied
experience, this was her first child; and the condition where she
found herself was a new hell, and one undreamed of before.  This
little creature, drawing her life into itself, was something for
which she felt a fierce protecting instinct&mdash;an unspeakable and
angry need of interposing herself between it and the cruelty of the
world.  Her child&mdash;it was foreordained by fate that it must suffer.
Her daughter&mdash;there was not power enough in the universe to hinder
her from sharing her mother's lot.  The child must grow up in the
alleys, in the gutters.  Her first words would be oaths; little
criminals would be her companions; sin must be her daily sight,
evil must be her atmosphere; she the bantling of a ribald moment,
and by right of descent possessor of her mother's indecency.  Wrong
would come to her earlier than it had come to herself&mdash;she
remembered sharply the first stirring of the vicious impulses in
herself, the first temptation; the first yielding; the bad, bitter
joy; the end in wretchedness, in despair, in ruin.  He had gone
free&mdash;and where there was one of her there were ten of him&mdash;and she
felt the multitude of him lying in wait for this girl drawing now
from her veins the impulse, the yielding, the riot, the rage; and
once more the fierce instinct of protection made her clasp the
child so closely that it cried out with a feeble cry.
</p><p>The nurse came and looked at her curiously and saw the tear
and went away.  The child dropped off to sleep.  But far from sleep
was the mother, with a fire ravaging her brain.  She saw the way
marked out for this child; she saw not only that, but the bleeding
feet with which she must tread it.
</p><p>But yet&mdash;it was not impossible&mdash;she could be saved from all
that.  There were people who could take her out and away, who could
surround her with the things of a different life&mdash;she who was
innocent now. <pb n="693"/>
</p><p>Innocent?  Was she innocent, this child born with an injured
body, with a diseased soul?  No intelligence, no cunning, no
benevolence, could evade the inevitable.  For what she was, that
her child was.  You do not gather figs from thistles.  What she had
made herself, she had made her child; what she had become, that her
child became also.  In being born, the child became all that.  This
soft and shapeless lip was ready for the lie; those tiny clutching
fingers for the theft; those helpless hands for the secret murder;
that body would grow lithe and supple for all sin, and would one
day wither in the fire of pain.  Born vile, to wallow in slime, the
child would take only what was given to it&mdash;from the unknown,
nameless father corruption; from the mother the blackness of
shameless things of midnight.  All that the mother had done she
would do; all that the mother had suffered she would suffer.  Had
there been any happiness in her part?  Not one jot.  The child
would live to curse the day she saw the light.
</p><p>She rose on one arm and looked at it.  She laid her thin hand
on its thin cheek.  Her heart suddenly stood still with a wild,
unused sensation&mdash;could it be love for the child?  She fell back on
her pillow a chill sweat of horror covering her.  All this evil she
had given her child in giving it life.
</p><p>There was something else she could give it.
</p><p>In the morning the nurse and the doctor could not say that the
mother had not overlain the child in sleep.  It did not seem best
to make any search into the affair, since for this mother's child
death was so much better than life.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" n="II" id="d5"> 

<p>Every sound in the large and lovely room was muffled by the
rich rugs, the silk-hung walls, the heavy curtains.  A fire burnt
low on the hearth and sent a ruby shadow here and there, flickering
over the alabaster vase, the ivory carving, the water-color on the
panel, the blue silk coverlet and the billowy lace about the bed.
The room was full of the fragrance of a hundred roses.  An
attendant, velvet-shod, carried away a small gold tray with a bowl
of china as translucent as a flower; another nurse sat by the fire
and dreamed over the pillow that lay across her knee.  All seemed
well with the young mother; all seemed well with the child.
</p><p>She rested deep among her pillows, in a sleepy content; but
quite determined on no more experience of this sort.  Why could not
the race have been continued in some other way?  It really seemed
as if there were some malevolence toward women.  How much she had
missed since they forbade her to dance or to ride.  The idea of her
foregoing all her pleasures for this&mdash;and life so short at the
best!  She would be on a horse again the moment she was able,
before the frosty weather was all gone.  She had lost the Hunt
Ball, as it was.  Well, here was the heir, anyway; and he would
have to do.
</p><p>A gush of music came through an opening door or window, a
thrill of violins and flutes; there was a small and early german in
the next house&mdash;how vexatious to be here!  And all the rehearsals
for the theatricals were over without her; and every one had
declared there could never be such a Cleopatra as she; and she had
ropes and ropes of pearls to wear, and miles of rose-colored gauzes
half to hide and half to reveal the rose-colored tights.  Very
likely there would have been a fuss; but what was the use of being
beautiful all to yourself?  At all events, the gauzes would do for
the skirt-dances they were going to give for the Blenheim Spaniel
Hospital.
</p><p>There would be some cotillions, anyway, before Lent.  She
hoped she wasn't going to come out of all this with her color gone.
And her figure&mdash;it would be a pity if the gowns that had just come
from Paris shouldn't fit her now.  She would have the boxes opened
to-morrow and the gowns spread out for inspection&mdash;one of them
ought to be simply exquisite&mdash;cherry-colored satin, the front
embroidered with seed-pearls, cut very low, but with a high ruff,
and clouds of old Venice point.  Lester van Dycke always said when
she wore that shade that Watteau should have painted her.  Poor
Lester&mdash;she couldn't understand why there should have been any
feeling about that little flirtation; he was only teaching her how
to smoke a cigarette like Carmen.  And then it was diverting to see
just how far you could go and <pb n="694"/>  stop.  And really she had
been awfully hard up when he lost that money to her at poker.
Thank goodness, it was all paid back before he was sent off on that
whaling voyage to break up his drinking.  How people do slip in and
out of your life.&mdash;What was that woman doing now?  Oh, indeed&mdash;they
needn't bring that baby to her; she didn't want him.
</p><p>The nurse, a wise woman as nurses were in the days of Pharaoh,
turned down the silken sheet and laid on the mother's arm the
bundle of soft wool and filmy lace, baring the little pink face.
"I never supposed babies looked like that.  Isn't he comical?  And
you needn't think I'm going to nurse him," she meant to say aloud,
but really said only to herself.  "He can be brought up by hand; or
you may get all the foster-mothers you please.  I won't be tied
down by a chain two or three hours long, and grow a fright into the
bargain!"
</p><p>"We can't let the little man starve," the nurse was saying.
"At any rate, just for the present," she urged.  "Till the doctor
comes again and we can get just what is wanted."
</p><p>Were all nurses like this?  Wasn't she compelling?  A sort of
civilized <hi rend="italic">She</hi>.  Well, if she must.  But not to keep it up.
How absurd!  How perfectly ridiculous!  But they were not to think
she was going on with it and forego the races and the yachting and
everything else.  "Don't you know," she said in her thoughts to the
baby, "that you're dreadfully in my way?"
</p><p>The baby smiled&mdash;the vacuous little grimace of a baby&mdash;and
opened his eyes.  "Dear me," she said.  "How interesting!  Do you
imagine he sees me?  Fancy!  And look at the fingers&mdash;aren't they
quite perfect?  And his eyes&mdash;why, they're really&mdash;just look at the
little fine corners!  Do you suppose he knows I'm his mother?  Oh,
I <hi rend="italic">am</hi> his mother!"  And the little head had snuggled into
place.  She gazed at him in a bewildered wonder: something seemed
to be taking hold of her very heart-strings.  Oh, this scrap of a
creature was part of her life itself!  She had made him!  She had
struck this spark of a soul into a being!  The idea!  But why?  The
dear person had a soul, of course.  And she fell to wondering what
kind of soul it was.  What kind of a soul&mdash;why, didn't people say
the son was the avatar of the mother?  A soul like hers, to be
sure.  My gracious, what kind of a soul was hers?
</p><p>It seemed suddenly to be growing black everywhere about her,
whether owing to the new sensations and to exhaustion, or to the
too illuminating thought.  All along the dusky wall she saw written
in letters of flame, Mene, mene, tekel upharsin.  She half laughed
to think it should be in plain, every-day characters instead of
Persian script.  Thou art weighed in the balance&mdash;and found
wanting.
</p><p>What did it mean?  What was weighed?  What was found wanting?
And what was this blackness?  Was she fainting?  Or, oh, was she
dying!
</p><p>Heavens!  Was this dying?  Was she sinking, failing, letting
go of life?  Don't let her die!  Oh, don't let her die!  She didn't
want to leave all these pleasant things.  She was afraid.  For, oh,
she was not fit to die!  She must have made some exclamation, for
the nurse was sprinkling her face.  "It is all right," the woman
was saying.  "She is coming to.  It's not unusual."  Yes; it was no
longer black about her: she was in the middle of a great light; she
seemed to be withering in it, like a leaf in the fire.  In the
middle of the great light she saw herself for what she was.  In
that unknown and vast beyond, her little worthless soul would be
lost.  That was the kind of soul she had&mdash;a little, worthless,
paltering one.
</p><p>That was the kind of soul, then, she had given to her boy.  He
was to grow up in this great moving world as trifling, as light-minded, as slight as she, she who cared only for the pleasures that
waste the body and starve the soul!  His little velvet cheek lay on
her breast&mdash;oh, how dear he was; how sweet he was, the little new
person!  And she had made him as useless, as light as a bubble.
She recalled a deceit she had practised just before his birth&mdash;a
scandal she had stimulated; the case that had been laid before her
of bringing out a poor man's family for just the money that would
buy the emerald cross she wanted, and she had taken refuge behind
the immigration laws, and there were the emeralds in her jewel-case; her face burnt to remember<pb n="695"/>  the champagne she drank
the night she first wore those emeralds&mdash;heaven knows what silly
things she said!  Yes, yes; there was no help for it, this son of
hers would want ease, glitter, wine, bibelots!  Pleasures that had
been follies in her would be follies in him, too, and worse than
follies.  Her frivolity would be in him effeminacy, her idleness
would have made him a voluptuary.  He would know nothing and care
less for the sin and sorrow on his right hand and his left; he
would not waste an hour of his laughing life on any of the grief
and pain that made discord in the music.  A silken sybarite, he
would yield to every temptation; every gaiety would allure him.
The thrones of the world might rock, he would not know it if his
clubs were sound.  His ambitions would be in his clothes, in his
horses.  He would have no strength to fight the forces of evil&mdash;he
would be a part of them.  Insufficient, of no purpose in the great
scheme of the growth of the race&mdash;oh, was she thinking of her boy,
her little son, the dear new, tender life?  And then again that
sinking, that slipping into outer darkness.
</p><p>No, no, she must overcome it; she must not die; there was
something for her to do; she could not afford to die!  She could
not have him, when his time came, go out into the dark the trumpery
thing she was herself, as he needs must if she did not live to
hinder it.  He would be without strength to resist the press of
evil, for she had given him no strength; he would be without
impulse to do good, for she had given him no impulse; he would be
without value in the scales of the universe, for she had given him
no value.  She must live to lead him past the temptation, for she
would recognize it; to bid him to see the pitfall; to find,
herself, and show to him, the shining mark beyond; to help him in
all those straits and perils where being her son, he must otherwise
be helpless.  That other woman whom the doctor was to bring, that
foster-mother, she must go away again.  They should give her
something for her own baby; but she could not have this one.  She
might be a better woman; he might draw force and will from her; but
from his own mother he would draw love, and the love should keep
him safe.
</p><p>The fire fell, and all was still in the room.  The nurse
drowsed in her chair.  The very roses seemed to hush themselves in
dropping now and then a petal lest they wake the mother and the
child from their deep, sweet, regenerating sleep.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="part" n="III" id="d6"> 

<p>There was but one room in the log-cabin of the forest
clearing.  The summer moonlight poured in a flood of pale-green
silver through the open door and the windows, glorifying all the
place.
</p><p>The young mother, lying there with her first-born beside her,
had done what she could to make the spot homelike till something
better should replace it; and it wore a certain reminiscence of
castle halls in the tapestry of skins, in the huge antlers, in the
crossed arms.
</p><p>The woman, who had come from a dozen miles away to be with her
now&mdash;one to whose help she had gone herself when the forest-fever
smote the household there, was in the lean-to with the doctor.  The
husband was out hunting, unaware of the imminence of the event; and
the two lads were with him.  There was no one in the room but the
mother and her child.
</p><p>No one?  What was this shape in the moonlight&mdash;this shining
mist&mdash;the winged shape of a great angel, gleaming obscurely in the
bloom of the broad glow?  What the darker shape of another that
seemed the shadow of the first?  Or were they shapes at all, or
more than the phantasmagoria of a failing brain?
</p><p>She was too weak to note anything closely; but she felt in
long thrills through all her frame the soft, slow breathing of the
baby at her side, and her soul was full of a rapture of gladness.
She felt, moreover, vaguely conscious of a certain dim sense of
triumph, for although her father's holdings had gone in a distant
branch to the heir male, she knew that she, inheriting of her
father, that her son, inheriting of her, truly represented the
race&mdash;not that son of many alien mothers who now had name and
place.
</p><p>Left dowerless, through mishap, she had married a man of
adventurous spirit, and had come out here, a pioneer, to begin
fresh life; her son was to be one of the <pb n="696"/>  makers of the new
world.  But of none of this she thought now or was aware, save as
a dull undercurrent.  She faintly remembered thinking before he was
born that this child was to be the flower of his race; that his
mother must make him so; that his mother's father had already made
him so&mdash;that father in whom there had been no taint of dishonor, of
self-seeking, of uncleanness, of distemper of mind or body.
Perhaps the nobility had lain dormant in herself; she had feared
that; she had tried to rouse it&mdash;but on the whole had given herself
small time to dwell upon it.  There had been far too much to do to
think if she possessed virtues and graces.  She had had plans, in
the early days, of great work among the prisons she would visit,
and the help she would give the convict people; of the way in which
she would bring pleasure to certain of the insane; and, when war
broke out, of the help she might be as an army nurse&mdash;she familiar
with sick-rooms.  But she had had no chance to bring herself to
proof; for her father had needed her every hour.  And when he had
died, she had married a poor man, a prince among poor men as she
felt, and she had come out with him to build a new home under new
conditions.  As, upon the voyage, she had looked over at those in
the steerage, her heart had swelled with pity, and with a sense of
being in reality one of them, with no right to more ease; she had
gone in among them, and an old woman there had died in her arms,
and to the child of a poor young wife she had rendered the first
offices.  And as her foot touched shore her heart had swelled
again, but with a sort of ecstasy, thinking of the great promise
this land gave to the oppressed of all the earth.  On the train
across the country she had found two little lads whose people had
died and who were bewildered at their homeless condition; and she
and her husband had taken them to their home in the wilderness.
</p><p>Over here life had not been easy; but she had given no sign.
It had been beyond her strength; but she had never faltered.  She
was making home and happiness and she had found a vivid joy in it.
She had been lonesome in the long days of necessary solitude; but
no one knew it.  She had been home-sick for old sights, old faces,
old luxuries; but there was always a smile on her lip when any one
looked.  Sometimes her husband took her with him on his errands to
the distant town, and as she saw the busy people going to and fro
a great love swept from her to one and all of them.  And when her
child was coming, she was so glad of him that that love for others
seemed only to have opened the way for an inexhaustible fountain of
love flowing to him and through him.  She had a sort of smiling
memory that it took generations to make a gentleman&mdash;it had meant
generations of mothers, of course; and after all was a gentleman in
the first place other than a man of the people who loved his
people?  Fate must have begun in season with her child.  She
searched herself, if by mischance any hidden sin in her could come
to light in him; she had prayed almost hourly that he might have
truth, courage, a pure heart, a generous hand, a selfless spirit,
and that, when the ordeal came, if one must go, the child should
stay and have his share of the joy of the world that she had found
so sweet, unwitting that her very prayer gave him all the loftiness
she craved for him.
</p><p>And now the son had been born to her and slept beside her, a
strong and lusty boy, the builder, possibly, of a new race; surely,
as she had dreamed, the last richness of an old one.  She lay with
indistinct, half-wandering fancies, looking into the pouring
moonlight.  For a moment she was quite sure she saw them&mdash;the two
great angels; and then the eyelids dropped dreamily, and she saw no
more.
</p><p>"It is a child," said the shadowy angel, hovering over the
bed, "whose mother had given him the strength that becomes a man,
who has a place to take in the world, a work to do, and a will to
do it.  The race needs him.  He is yours."
</p><p>"It is a mother," said the shining angel, "who has already
given her child the welcome that makes a joyous soul.  He shall not
miss her smile.  He is what she is.  He will need love since he
will give so much.  And she is all compact of love.  She is one of
the forces of Life.  Death, I cannot surrender her."
</p><p>And the dark angel fled away into the moonlight, and the
shining one fanned sleeping mother and child with his wings.</p>

</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
