<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="ThoQues"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="ThoQues"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Question "How?"</title>
<title type="sort">question how</title>
<author>Thomson, William Hanna</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>  
<name>Charles Keller</name>  
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>  
<name/>  
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">18</num> kilobytes</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>  
<idno type="ETC">ThoQues</idno>  
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476390</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>  
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Question "How?"</title>
<title level="j">Everybody's Magazine, vol. XXIII, no.2</title>
<title type="sort">question how</title>
<author>William Hanna Thomson</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>  
<name>John O'Hara Cosgrave</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>pages 205-208</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Ridgway Company Publishers</publisher>  
<pubPlace>New York City, Spring and Macdougal Streets</pubPlace>  
<date value="1910-08">August 1910</date>  
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa library, call no.: AP 2.E9</idno>
</publicationStmt>  
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>  
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>  
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>  
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>  
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>  
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>  
</encodingDesc>  
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1910">1910</date>
</creation>  
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>  
<language id="la">Latin</language>
</langUsage>  
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
</profileDesc>  
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-08">August 1997</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Gregory Murray, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>  
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>  
 
 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
	<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
<head> 
THE QUESTION "HOW?"<lb/> 
<lb/> 
By WILLIAM HANNA THOMSON, M.D., LL.D.<lb/> 
Author of " Brain and Personality," "What is Physical Life?" etc.<lb/> 
<lb/> 
Physician to the Roosevelt Hospital; Consulting Physician to the 
New York 
State Manhattan Hospital for the Insane; formerly Professor of 
the Practice of 
Medicine and Diseases of the Nervous System, New York University 
Medical College; Ex-President of the New York Academy of 
Medicine, etc. 
</head> 
 

 
<div2 type="section" id="d4"> 
  <pb n="205"/>   
<p>IN one of Carlyle's earliest productions, 
dealing with the philosophy of Clothes, 
he showed that a man quite plainly reveals 
his inner self by what he wears. So we would 
now discuss what the being, Man, reveals 
about himself by his eternal question, 
"How?" 
 
</p><p>As language is a lofty endowment and, 
moreover, on this earth exclusively human, 
we would lead up to the subject by stating 
what the parts of speech are. 
 
</p><p>According to the Arabs, who surpass all other peoples in the 
study of language&mdash;for they claim that they have twenty-five thousand 
books on grammar in their literature&mdash;the parts of speech are three; 
and, as one of their old scholars states, this threefold division of 
speech is not confined to one language, but is universal, because human 
speech does not differ with the difference of human tongues. These three 
parts are: first, nouns&mdash;the names of things; second, verbs&mdash;the names 
of events; and, third, the partitives&mdash;or the words which express the 
relations of things to events. Thus the most abstract of verbs, "to be," 
refers to an event; for when a man says, "I am," he is mentioning an 
event in the history of the universe which did not occur till he 
existed. 
 
</p><p>This division, however, necessitates that 
the adjectives should be regarded as nouns; 
and so they are classed in all Semitic 
languages, as the Hebrew, the Arabic, the Syriac, 
etc. The writers of the New Testament, 
therefore, could not write Greek without 
continually falling into their native Hebrew 
idiom; so that if the passages were translated 
literally, some modern expositions 
would have to be much modified. Thus, 
"Who created the worlds by the word of his 
power" means "Who created the worlds by 
his powerful word." "The body of our 
humiliation" is "our humiliating body." 
"Who shall deliver me from the body of this 
death?" is "from this deadly body," as the 
context of the passage clearly shows. In 
each case the second noun is the adjective 
modifying the first. 
 
</p><p>Moreover, the most interesting deduction 
from this division of the parts of speech is that 
the partitives are far the highest in rank 
among words, because they express pure 
relations, which only the royal mind of man 
can so distinctly perceive as to make words 
for them. Thus, a dog can learn his own 
name, and understand the verbs "go" and 
"come," especially with the imperative tone 
of his master; but he could never understand 
the words "outgoing year" or "incoming 
year." 
 
</p><p>Prepositions belong to the partitives, and, 
with different prepositions attached to one 
and the same thing or noun, the human mind 
can step through the vast regions of thought 
as easily as the ether can vibrate through 
space. Thus the Latin <foreign lang="la">scriptio</foreign>, the name of 
a thing, a writing, gives us the following 
changes, according to the preposition: An 
<hi rend="italic">a</hi>scription is not a <hi 
rend="italic">con</hi>scription, by any means; 
nor does a conscription mean anything like 
a <hi rend="italic">des</hi>cription; nor is that the same 
thing with 
an <hi rend="italic">in</hi>scription; nor when we <hi 
rend="italic">pre</hi>scribe for 
 
   <pb n="206"/>   
 
a man are we <hi rend="italic">pro</hi>scribing him; and 
every one 
of us knows, when the agent of a worthy 
cause enters, what the difference is between 
a <hi rend="italic">sub</hi>scription and a <hi 
rend="italic">super</hi>scription. 
</p><p>To the adverbs, however, must be given 
the pre&euml;minence among all human words. 
But even here there are gradations in rank. 
Thus the adverb, "Why?" may be nothing 
but a question of curiosity, and hence its idea 
may be suggested to an inquisitive monkey. 
But it is not so with the question, "How?" 
"Why?" may be answered by an affirmation, 
but "How?" can be answered only by a 
demonstration. Now, as our object is to call speech 
to witness as to what is in man, or, in other 
words, what man is himself, we will proceed 
to analyze the testimony of this word, 
"How?"</p> 
 
 
</div2><div2 type="section" id="d5"> 
<head>"HOW" FINDS A PLANET</head> 
 
<p>First: It does not refer to anything which 
appears on the surface. Instead, it seeks to 
find the hidden and the unknown by following 
up one clue after another. When the 
astronomer, Leverrier, found that the planets 
Saturn and Uranus did not come to time, he 
asked himself how that could be. Meanwhile, 
the answer to any number of "hows" 
must have been previously demonstrated by 
him and by other astronomers before the 
movements of these great and distant heavenly 
bodies could be shown as not according 
to the clock-like regularity of planets in their 
courses. He reasoned that only one probable 
"how" could account for the facts; namely, 
another planet of just such a size and weight, 
and moving at just such a distance, would 
suffice thus to hold back Saturn and Uranus 
in their orbits. And so he calculated how 
large this heavenly body was, how heavy it 
was, and then just where it was, until, by this 
human but sure detective system, astronomers 
caught sight of Neptune&mdash;after Leverrier 
told them where to look for it. 
 
</p><p>But, after all, to decide how the vast 
heavenly bodies move in space is easy compared 
with finding out how to make a sewing 
machine go. For a needle to thread itself 
and then rapidly proceed to sew without the 
help of fingers calls for the discovery of more 
"hows" than are needed to explain Laplace's 
"M&eacute;canique c&eacute;leste." Mass and gravity suffice 
for the one, but only a Yankee's mind 
could have created the other. 
 
</p><p>We have now come to a great word&mdash;"create." A creator is a being who gives 
origin to things which would not exist but for 
his intelligent purpose and design. Now, 
man has simply filled this earth with his own 
creations, all due to himself alone and to none 
other, and all again by pondering the question, 
"How?" He began, for instance, by putting 
a hole through a flint hatchet, and ended with 
putting a hole through the Alps. In this last, 
an engineer stood at the foot of the great 
mountain and asked himself how he could 
tunnel it for nations to pass through. He 
saw a small stream dashing down the mountainside 
and at once found his desired "how," 
for he made that stream work big drills by 
compressed air, till the everlasting rocks 
themselves had to give in. 
 
</p><p>But man is an infinite creator&mdash;by which 
we mean that his creative capacity is limitless 
and inexhaustible. No sooner does he create 
one thing than he turns to create another 
thing totally different from it. A locomotive 
thundering past with a long train has no 
resemblance to a telegraph line, nor that, in 
turn, to a great printing press. Man coolly 
sets at defiance the most fundamental laws of 
physical science. 
 
</p><p>Thus, a heavy load of passengers, sitting 
in no less heavy cars, if put on a smooth 
inclined plane must slide down faster and faster 
to the bottom, or Vulcan would be confounded. 
But man strings a thin wire overhead, 
which would snap instantly if the load 
gave it one pull; but something which, some 
"how," man causes to pass along that wire, 
makes the trolley with its live freight go 
uphill faster than a horse can run.</p> 
 
 
</div2><div2 type="section" id="d6"> 
<head>THE ETHER ENSLAVED</head> 
 
<p>And what about that mysterious ether? 
It can neither be seen, heard, felt, handled, 
smelt, nor tasted. Nevertheless, man has 
learned so much about its "how" that he is 
turning it into as menial a servant, obedient 
to his wishes, as he has made of electricity, 
the cause of sublime thunder; for man bids 
the ether carry his stock quotations or any 
other message of his to the ends of the earth. 
 
</p><p>These are great doings, but really no greater 
than his small doings, for the least of these 
is just as impossible for other earthly creatures 
as are an Alpine tunnel or a battleship. 
A large convention of chimpanzees could not 
combine to make one pin or one sleeve-button, 
if they tried. 
 
</p><p>All this is because man is native to the 
world of relations, which no other earthly beings 
 
   <pb n="207"/>   
 
are, because they cannot go beyond the 
information provided by their bodily senses. 
Man, on the contrary, gains infinitely more 
knowledge than his bodily senses can afford. 
By studying the relations of abstract points 
to abstract lines, he becomes a mathematician. 
Following up the many "hows" of 
chemistry, he talks about molecules, atoms, 
and ions as fluently as: if he had seen or 
handled them.</p> 
 
 
</div2><div2 type="section" id="d7"> 
<head>MAN IS INVISIBLE</head> 
 
<p>This explains how man can and does create. 
Every great invention existed first in the 
mind of the inventor. So the great engineer 
who made the Brooklyn Bridge never had to 
handle one of the materials used in its 
construction, for every stone, wire, and bolt was 
provided for in that engineer's mind before 
any part of that tremendous mass of matter 
could be seen on the earth. 
 
</p><p>Moreover, this great human creator is as 
invisible as the Divine Creator Himself. 
People are continually saying that they will 
not believe in a thing till they can see it, thus 
pinning their faith to the testimony of that 
one of our senses which makes more mistakes 
than do all our other senses put together. 
When a man six feet high is a mile off, it says 
that he is only six inches high. The eye can 
see nothing of the vast microscopic living 
world which lies within six inches of the eyeball, 
and so we have had to invent a microscope 
to make up for this serious deficiency. 
But what would the Russian Witte not have 
given if he could have telegraphed to St. 
Petersburg that he had actually <hi rend="italic">seen</hi> 
the 
Japanese Komura while they were talking 
about making peace at Portsmouth, New 
Hampshire, and that he knew just what the 
courteous Jap thought and proposed! All 
that he saw was the Asiatic's smiling face 
and other things of his outside. Every 
human personality belongs to the real world, 
the world of the Unseen, and cannot be 
known except as he chooses to reveal himself.</p> 
 
 
</div2><div2 type="section" id="d8"> 
<head>BRAIN NOT THE MAN</head> 
 
<p>Some persons might object here that the brain is both visible and 
tangible in man, and that man is in his brain, and, therefore, the brain 
is man. Medical science, however, shows that the brain no more thinks 
than the hand and foot do, but is simply the instrument of the invisible 
thinker. The proof of this is that we have two brains, just as we have 
two eyes and two ears, but that only one of our two brain hemispheres is 
the instrument for talking, thinking, or knowing. Which one of the two 
hemispheres will be the mental one will depend altogether on how it has 
been <hi rend="italic">taught</hi> by the invisible thinker, who 
will begin to teach the left hemisphere if he is right-handed, or the 
right hemisphere if he is left-handed. He will leave the other 
hemisphere in each case wholly speechless or thoughtless, and concerned 
only with the business of governing the muscles or receiving the bodily 
sensations of its corresponding side. If brain matter really itself 
thought, we should have two thinking and speaking hemispheres&mdash;and this 
the first case of loss of speech by an apoplectic clot would disprove. 
 
</p><p>"By thy words thou shalt be judged." 
This means that man is to be judged by his 
own creations, for it is only men who create 
words. By their words they show what is in 
them, both intellectually and morally. We 
have demonstrated that the being who can 
ask the question, "How?" naturally belongs 
to the universe. Already he knows what 
stuff inconceivably distant stars are made of; 
and the "how" to know that he found in a 
small glass prism.</p> 
 
 
</div2><div2 type="section" id="d9"> 
<head>THE MORAL "HOW"</head> 
 
<p>It would seem, therefore, as if it were by 
some temporary accident that he is held to 
this little material speck of matter called the 
earth. And this impression grows upon us 
as we study the greatest facts of human life. 
We enter this world knowing nothing and 
not nearly so well equipped to take care of 
ourselves as are other animals. There is no 
helplessness like that of a babe. But 
wonderfully early he begins to ask the question, 
"How?" A little boy will ask more questions 
in a day than his father will ask in a week; 
nor can he be stopped or deceived, because 
the question, "Why?" you can answer as you 
please, but not "How?" 
 
</p><p>He who can ask "How?" can be a learner 
as long as he exists, whether here or hereafter. 
In his life here he may become either 
a great financier or a great statesman, but 
certainly not either unless he knows how. 
Any education, in fact, is simply learning 
how. 
 
</p><p>What is true in the intellectual world is still 
more true in the moral world. Whenever 
a question bearing on morals enters, every 
 
   <pb n="208"/>   
 
one should stop and ask, "How?" A mistake 
here is like entering the wrong gate in 
a large railroad station. The longer you stay 
in its corresponding train, the farther it will 
take you from where you should go. For 
example, there are some who say that the 
human will is not free, but that our actions 
are all, in the last analysis, according to our 
make-up. In other words, we are machines 
which must go as they are made to go. There 
is, therefore, no right nor wrong in human 
conduct, for machines cannot be held responsible 
for conduct or the way they go&mdash;there 
can be no sinful automobile or wicked windmill. 
 
</p><p>According to these reasoners, therefore, when human law punishes 
one who has robbed a widow of all she had, or has seduced the daughter 
of a friend, or committed a cold-blooded murder, the law is wholly 
illogical in punishing him, because, since he is a machine, his 
punishment is like throwing a clock out of a window if it does not keep 
good time.  The only answer to such a talker should be, "Get out!" with 
particular emphasis on the "out."</p> 
</div2> 
		</div1>
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
