<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="TilKnow"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="TilKnow"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Knowledge is Power</title>
<title type="sort">knowledge is power</title>
<author>Tilden, Freeman</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Charles E. Keller</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">36</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">TilKnow</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476392</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Knowledge is Power</title>
<title type="sort">knowledge is power</title>
<author>Freeman Tilden</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Munsey's Magazine</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1916-05">May 1916</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume LVII pp. 649-656</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme 
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the
text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of 
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1916">1916</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-03">March 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs</name>
</respStmt>
<item>SGML markup</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2"> 
  
<div1 type="chapter" n="1" id="d3"><pb n="649"/><head>I</head>
<p>NO we don't want no more books!" cried Mr. Caleb Coppins in a 
tone of belligerent finality. 
</p><p>At the same time he attempted to slam the front door in the 
enthusiastic face of the young man who stood outside.  But the 
young man, who was no chicken at canvassing, had taken due 
precautions in expectation of just such an event.  He had neatly  
inserted his foot between the door-casing and the jamb. 
</p><p>"Just a minute, Mr. Coppins," he pleaded. 
</p><p>"Take your foot out of there, or I'll bust it for you!" 
replied the head of the household. 
</p><p>The young man regarded his victim with something of pity, 
mingled with subdued joy.  He had tamed many a householder like 
Mr. Coppins, and his thin nose quivered with the excitement of 
approaching combat. 
</p><p>"You may slam the door, Mr. Coppins," he said earnestly.  "You 
may amputate my foot; but my severed foot will remain inside with 
you to extol the glory of the eighth wonder of the world &mdash; the 
`Pan-Continental Encyclopedic Dictionary,' the steam-engine of 
intellect, the book that will make your name a byword for wisdom 
and your home the rendezvous of the intellectual elite." 
</p><p>The canvasser's eloquence was not without effect.  Mr. Caleb 
Coppins's set jaw relaxed.  He ceased to push against the inserted 
foot. 
</p><p>"You've got nerve, young feller," he admitted.  "Come in!  But 
you can't sell it to me, no matter what it is.  We've got books 
cluttering up the whole house.  I can't turn around now without 
knocking against a book, and I haven't read half of 'em, nor a 
quarter.  And I get the `Agricultural Year-Book' every year from 
our Congressman." 
</p><p>The canvasser for the "Pan-Continental" followed silently into 
the musty-smelling parlor, and, at the bidding of the owner, sat 
down.  As Mr. Coppins threw open the door of the seldom-used room 
the odor of decaying heirlooms nearly gagged the book-agent.  With 
a quick glance he surveyed the chamber of horrors, from the 
horsehair-covered chairs to the tall bookcase of black walnut, 
stuffed with dusty volumes that dated from the period when "Vanity 
Fair" was thought to be a little off color. 
</p><p>I am not surprised to see so many books," said the canvasser, 
with a subtle feigning of rapture.  "I find it worth while to 
visit only the true lovers of good literature.  Ah, Mr. Coppins, 
how little the average man knows the rare pleasure that we 
bibliophiles get from our printed treasures!" 
</p><p>The fact was, as the canvasser very well understood, that Mr. 
Coppins had led him
 
<pb n="650"/> 
into the parlor not with the idea of 
doing him honor, but merely to intimidate him &mdash; to prove that the 
house was already supplied with books. 
</p><p>Mr. Coppins, however, hearing himself described as a 
bibliophile, and surmising that a bibliophile must be a person of 
some importance, permitted himself the luxury of remarking that he 
<hi rend="italic">was</hi> a bibliophile &mdash; a forty-third-degree bibliophile.  In fact, 
though he was firm in his resolve not to buy any more books just 
then, he pastured himself on these green and luscious fields of 
flattery like a half-starved cow from a rocky hillside. 
</p><p>"It's a pleasure to visit a man like you, Mr. Coppins," 
resumed the canvasser.  "Believe me, I appreciate it.  My eye 
sparkled when I saw that bookcase.  Maybe you saw it sparkle?  
Exactly!  `Here is a man of parts,' I said to myself. `Here is a 
man who knows.  I would rather talk with a man like this man, and 
not sell my books, than sell a cart-load of books to the vulgar 
crowd who cannot appreciate them.'" 
</p><p>The canvasser paused, and Mr. Coppins nodded appreciatively. 
</p><p>"Don't try to tell me that you don't read these books," 
continued the canvasser.  "I admire your modesty, but I know you 
gorge yourself on them in the long winter evenings.  I'll bet you 
could recite half of them from memory!" 
</p><p>Mr. Coppins, who spent most of the long winter evenings 
shooting Kelly pool in a stuffy room at the rear of the 
barber-shop, assented to this indictment with dreamy 
self-approval. 
</p><p>Suddenly the manner of the canvasser changed.  He became 
violently agitated, for no apparent reason.  His eyes took on a 
gleam of high exultation.  He began to pace up and down excitedly 
in the open space between the what-not and the table full of 
artificial flowers in glass.  Then he stopped and pointed a long 
finger at Mr. Coppins so suddenly that that gentleman winced. 
</p><p>"You are a man of parts, Mr. Coppins!" he repeated furiously.  
"Your name was sent to me from the home office in New York &mdash; in New 
York, understand?  You know what books are worth.  You know that 
knowledge is power!  You know that a man can rule the world, if he 
knows enough.  Well, then, let me tell you something.  You have 
made one mistake.  You have dabbled.  Your information has been 
sound, but spread too thin.  I can prove it to you.  Shall I?" 
</p><p>Mr. Coppins was fascinated.  He nodded feeble assent. 
</p><p>The canvasser's voice became more shrill and cutting.  He 
launched another finger in the direction of the householder's 
half-scared face. 
</p><p>"Can you tell me," he demanded with emphasis that cut like a 
Damascene blade, "what was the population of the city of Joliet, 
Illinois, in 1900?  Can you tell me the name of the heaviest 
element in nature?  How much does the earth weigh, down to the 
fraction of an ounce?  Can you go right out into company and tell 
the names of the opposing generals in the first Punic War?  Or 
what makes sugar crystallize?  Or why the sky is blue?  Do you 
know these things?" 
</p><p>"No, I don't," replied Caleb Coppins hoarsely. 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"I</hi> know!" shouted the canvasser victoriously.  "I can tell 
you the colors of the solar spectrum, backward and forward.  I can 
tell you what the interest on one dollar, compounded semiannually 
at six per cent for a thousand years, would amount to.  I can tell 
you the name of the right-hand man of the Egyptian monarch Rameses 
II, and the inscription on the tomb of Numa the Lawgiver.  What 
was the first message ever sent over the electric telegraph?  Can 
you tell me that, Mr. Coppins?" 
</p><p>"No, I can't," replied the abashed bibliophile.  And then he 
added, with a ray of wicked hope flickering in his eyes:  "Can 
you?" 
</p><p>"You can bet your best hat I can!  The telegraph was invented 
by Samuel F. B. Morse, and the first message that was flashed over 
the wire was:  `What hath God wrought!'" 
</p><p>Mr. Coppins shrank back from this prodigy of learning, and his 
hands trembled nervously. 
</p><p>Again the accusing finger shot forth toward the head of the 
householder. 
</p><p>"What," cried the canvasser, "is telekinesis?  What is 
arteriosclerosis?  Who discovered the X-ray?  What is the present 
price of radium per milligram?  What is a milligram?  What is the 
coldest place in the United States?  Where is Omsk?  Who owns the 
most expensive dog in the world?" 
</p>
<pb n="651"/>  

<p>"Calkins the grocer has a darned expensive dog," ventured Mr. 
Coppins.  "He bit a lawyer last week!" 
</p><p>"That is not worthy of you," challenged the canvasser, 
flushing deeply.  "That is trivial.  We are dealing in all 
seriousness with the greater truths.  Is there a single book in 
your excellent library that can tell you the precise nutritive 
value of the Lima bean?" 
</p><p>"No," admitted Mr. Coppins. 
</p><p>"There you are!" the canvasser shot back swiftly.  "You've got 
lots of books, but if you wanted to find any of these important 
things in them it would be like hunting for a needle in a 
haystack.  Suppose any one should ask you to give the origin and 
uses of caoutchouc?  Could you do it?  No.  Could you spell it?  
No.  There is an old Latin proverb, `<hi rend="italic">Scire ubi aliquid invenias 
magna pars eruditionis est</hi>.'  You recall it?" 
</p><p>"Perfectly," responded Mr. Coppins, trying to look as much as 
possible like an ancient Roman. 
</p><p>"Of course you do.  You know that it means, `To know where to 
lay hands on a fact is a great part of learning.'  Well, Mr. 
Coppins, here you are!  The `Pan-Continental Encyclopedic 
Dictionary' &mdash; the greatest book ever issued from the 
printing-press &mdash; the book that cost two hundred thousand dollars 
before a single page was printed &mdash; the book that called for the 
brains of one thousand of the world's greatest savants.  Will you 
have it in cloth, in buckram, or in limp leather?  Don't choose 
cloth, Mr. Coppins.  I beg you won't give way to your first 
mercenary impulse and choose cloth." 
</p><p>"Why not choose cloth, if it comes cheaper?" asked Mr. 
Coppins, in one last defensive effort. 
</p><p>"Because," concluded the canvasser, you look, act, and talk 
like a limp leather man!  Sign here &mdash; on this line, please.  That's 
right!" 
</p><p>"How much?" queried Mr. Coppins, after he had committed 
himself.  Already he was breathing more freely, like a man 
emerging from a trance. 
</p><p>"Ninety-six dollars and fifty cents," was the soothing reply.  
"The books are worth a thousand dollars to you.  One-half the 
amount down and the rest in monthly instalments{sic}.  With these 
books you can become a walking fund of learning.  You can override 
the village like a Roman conqueror in his triumphal chariot.  You 
can be an oracle, a magnate.  Knowledge is power!" 
</p><p>"Ninety-six fifty!" groaned the bibliophile.  "I don't know 
whether to be glad or sorry I didn't shut the door and amputate 
your foot." 
</p><p>The day will come when you will remember me with a heart full 
of gratitude, Mr. Coppins.  We prepay freight charges.  Your check 
is just as good as your money.  Thank you!" 
</p><p>"Durn his hide!" said Caleb Coppins, when the nimble figure 
had flattened itself against the expanse of distance.  "Ninety-six 
fifty!  I feel like I had been mesmerized and robbed.  But them 
books may be wuth it!" 
</p> 
</div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="2" id="d4"> 
<head>II</head> 
 
<p>THE "Pan-Continental Encyclopedic Dictionary" came by fast 
freight.  Mr. Coppins bore the treasures to his room, and 
manufactured a number of reasonable excuses for being in 
possession of them when Mrs. Coppins should make the inevitable 
inquiries.    He entered the item on his check-stub as 
"investment," for the benefit of his wife's splendid eyesight; and 
then he began to absorb knowledge, which is power. 
</p><p>Down in the rear of the barbershop the game of Kelly pool was 
proceeding with the usual abandon.  Mr. Coppins was not present.  
The twelve ball got the money; the six ball captured the ten-cent 
stakes; the ivory cue-ball left the table and went into the corner 
of the room with its accustomed vigor; but Mr. Coppins was not 
there. 
</p><p>There was a light burning in Mr. Coppins's favorite corner of 
the house at night.  There was a man absorbing the truths of the 
universe from limp-leather volumes.  There was a man accumulating 
a fund of deathless information.  There was a man trying to wring 
ninety-six dollars and fifty cents' worth of knowledge out of 
twenty-one volumes that sprang from the brains of one thousand of 
the world's greatest savants. 
</p><p>The man was Caleb Coppins.  The volumes were the 
"Pan-Continental Encyclopedic Dictionary." 
</p><p>One bright morning Mr. Coppins emerged from his home with an 
eager look in his eye.  He pounded down Main Street until he got 
as far as Calkins's Cash Grocery, 

<pb n="652"/> 
where he met Mr. Hemingway, manager of the canning-factory. 
</p><p>"Morning, Caleb," was the latter's salutation. 
</p><p>Mr. Coppins nodded and then took the other man by the 
coat-collar and spoke to him crisply. 
</p><p>"What is the temperature of the ocean at a depth of three 
thousand fathoms?" he asked. 
</p><p>Mr. Hemingway backed off to a safe distance. 
</p><p>"What difference does it make?" he parried. 
</p><p>"How much is a fathom?" continued Mr. Coppins, cocking his 
head on one side knowingly. 
</p><p>"I don't know." 
</p><p>Mr. Coppins gave a triumphal snort. 
</p><p>"You <hi rend="italic">ought</hi> to know, Alec," he said.  "A man in your 
position!" 
</p><p>Then he proceeded on his way.  He had already picked out 
another victim.  It was the principal of the high school, on his 
way to duty. 
</p><p>Before he received that box of books by fast freight Mr. 
Coppins had always regarded this man &mdash; Sterling Wendell &mdash; with awe.  
Now he stepped up to him with an air of affable ease and said: 
</p><p>"Mr. Wendell, do you happen to know what is the Algonquin 
Indian word for summer squash?" 
</p><p>"Why, I don't recall it just this minute," replied the 
schoolmaster, as if it had slipped from his mind during the last 
few seconds. 
</p><p>"Perhaps you can tell me what is the chemical symbol for 
ice-cream?" suggested Mr. Coppins. 
</p><p>"Really, Caleb, I'm a little late for school as it is.  I'll 
be glad to talk over those matters with you some evening.  By the 
way, do <hi rend="italic">you</hi> know the chemical symbol for ice-cream?" 
</p><p>"I should say I do!" replied Mr. Coppins, hastening onward 
with a serene heart. 
</p><p>Then Mr. Coppins entered the butcher-shop, 
</p><p>"What can I do for you this morning?" asked the butcher, "Some 
mighty fine pork just came in." 
</p><p>"Wells," said Caleb sharply, "probably you can tell me the 
meaning of the word `endosperm'?" 
</p><p>"I'm afraid I can't this morning, Mr. Coppins," replied the 
butcher reluctantly.  "Did you say you'd have a shoulder or a loin 
roast?" 
</p><p>"No, I didn't.  At what temperature would water boil at an 
altitude of nineteen thousand feet above sea-level?" 
</p><p>Mr. Wells was silent. 
</p><p>"You don't know?" prodded the man of parts. 
</p><p>The butcher shook his head. 
</p><p>"You <hi rend="italic">ought</hi> to know, in your business," was the commiserating 
retort. 
</p><p>"I s'pose you know," said the butcher. 
</p><p>"Pretty likely I do!" replied Caleb Coppins, in triumph. 
</p><p>Mr. Coppins visited the bank, and asked to be informed as to 
the date of the discovery of argon.  He also requested information 
concerning the treatment of anthrax.  The cashier threw up his 
hands and hid behind his card-index. 
</p><p>Mr. Coppins then assailed the clothing-store employees, 
clamoring for the specific gravity of dried prunes.  The employees 
fell down wofully {sic} on this problem.  Mr. Coppins smiled 
genially. 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"I</hi> know!" he said. 
</p><p>Then he went home.  He felt that things were coming his way.  
He knew that before supper he would be the talk of the village.  
He felt that there would be a movement on foot to deal with him.  
He was equally sure that he could be dealt with only at the 
expense of the dealer. 
</p><p>"The feller was right," ruminated Mr. Coppins.  "I've got 'em 
all thinking.  Knowledge is power!" 
 
</p> 
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="3" id="d5"> 
<head>III</head> 
 
<p>HIS sudden flare of erudition gained for Mr. Coppins all the 
popularity of a game-warden.  Not since the smallpox epidemic of 
1871 had Brookfield been visited by such a pest.  The male 
residents of voting age learned how to disappear around corners or 
into doorways when they saw Caleb Coppins approaching.  The 
principal of the high school discovered a circuitous route from 
his home to the school that took only ten minutes longer to 
travel.  Children instinctively shunned this prodigy of 
information, because Caleb had been reduced, once or twice, to the 
necessity of holding them up and demanding an answer to the 
question: 
</p><p>"Which is the longest bridge in the world?" 
</p><p>But the thing that most envenomed Mr. Coppins's former 
associates of the stuffy 

<pb n="653"/> 
room at the rear of the barber-shop 
was the fact that Caleb had gained no small credit with the 
feminine part of Brookfield society.  Local hostesses who had run 
short of attractions took him up.  He became a lion.  The proper 
thing to do, it developed, was to serve some small refreshments, 
and then, after the dishes had been spirited away from the parlor, 
to turn to some harried young male victim and say: 
</p><p>"Mr. Peters, wouldn't you like to ask Mr. Coppins a question?" 
</p><p>In such cases Mr. Coppins would sit back comfortably into the 
upholstery and cock his head attentively, while Mr. Peters would 
shrink to the size of a dwarfed child, cough nervously, and ask to 
be excused from such a wild adventure.  Whereupon the 
forty-third-degree bibliophile would say nonchalantly: 
</p><p>"Oh, go on, Peters, ask me something difficult!" 
</p><p>And then, failing to arouse the fighting spirit of his paltry 
opponent, Mr. Coppins would ask himself questions and answer them 
with careless celerity. 
</p><p>Down at the pool-table, one night, Mr. Calkins paused over his 
shot and remarked to the smoke-embalmed gathering: 
</p><p>"Say, what do you think of this feller Coppins, anyway?" 
</p><p>"I think he's a big bluff," responded a slender youth.  "I 
been thinking it over, and I come to the conclusion that he don't 
know the answers to half the questions he asks.  You notice he 
always <hi rend="italic">says</hi> he knows, but he never tells what it is." 
</p><p>"Well, why don't you call his bluff?" asked Mr. Calkins. 
</p><p>The slender youth hitched nervously and replied: 
</p><p>"Aw, what's the use?" 
</p><p>"He's making a great hit with the women," said another man.  
"You can't go to a party, or anything, these days, without having 
Coppins rubbed under your nose.  We got to do something to that 
wise gent, or he'll have us back in the peg-top class, or rolling 
hoop, or something!" 
</p><p>"Where'd he get all that information?" asked some one. 
</p><p>"Gosh, I dunno," replied the grocer.  "He never used to know 
beans; and all of a sudden he launches out as a regular college 
president!" 
</p><p>"Somebody's got to call his bluff, if he's bluffing.  If he 
isn't, somebody's got to inveigle him into a vacant lot and wallop 
him," said the grocer. 
</p><p>"He's bluffing, all right," affirmed the slender youth. 
</p><p>"Well, who's going to call him?" 
</p><p>The slender youth thought for a moment and then replied: 
</p><p>"What do you say we get young Harold Hussey?" 
</p><p>"Harold Hussey!" echoed half a dozen sneering, raucous voices.  
"That little shrimp?" 
</p><p>"He may be a shrimp," was the reply; "but what makes him a 
shrimp?  Ain't it because he studies too much?  Ain't it because 
he spends so much time playing the piano and reading magazines and 
things?  Ain't it because his head is so loaded with information 
that he don't have any time for the pleasures of life?  What more 
do you want?" 
</p><p>"By thunder, he's right!" admitted Calkins.  "Harold is the 
boy.  If there's any one in this town that can hand it to Caleb, 
it's little Harold Hussey.  But will he do it?  Harold hasn't got 
the nerve of a chipmunk." 
</p><p>"He'll do it," continued the slender youth, "if you can get 
him on a subject he's interested in.  You just mention music, and 
you'll see his eyes looking almost human.  He knows more about 
music and musicians than Caleb Coppins could learn in the rest of 
his lifetime.  Me for Harold Hussey!" 
</p><p>"Somebody go get him," said the grocer.  "He won't be in bed 
yet, I guess.  It's only quarter of eight.  Bring him here to talk 
it over." 
</p><p>"No, he couldn't stand the atmosphere of this room," objected 
Wells, the butcher.  "He'd faint.  We'd better appoint a 
delegation to wait on Harold and groom him for the occasion.  
We'll promise him a box of the best fudge if he'll do it." 
</p><p>"There's a great chance coming the night after to-morrow," 
said the slender youth.  "Mrs. Hastings is going to have a 
surprise party for George Hastings, and everybody's going to turn 
out to see George try to look surprised.  You see, George was the 
one that thought of the idea.  Everybody that comes is supposed to 
bring something to eat, and it 'll stock up the Hastingses with 
pie and cake enough for a month, at least.  That's the time to 
spring little Harold Hussey on Coppins." 

<pb n="654"/>  
</p><p>Half an hour later a couple of the men returned to the 
barber-shop with the glad news that Harold had consented to 
propound a number of questions on the momentous occasion.  At 
least, Harold's mother had consented to permit Harold to consent, 
which was just as good, if not better. 
</p><p>Whereupon a dozen strong men, each shouldering a cue, formed 
in line and marched around the pool-table, pausing now and then to 
slap one another on the back and utter some horrible imprecation 
against Caleb Coppins. 
</p> 
</div1><div1 type="chapter" n="4" id="d6"> 
<head>IV</head> 
 
<p>HAROLD HUSSEY had a watery blue eye, tapering fingers, 
manicured nails, and a slight lisp.  It was said that Mrs. Hussey 
had been disappointed because Harold, her only child, was not a 
girl.  At all events, she had since done all that she could to 
rectify nature's unfortunate mistake.  The only additional shame 
she could possibly have saddled upon the nineteen-year-old youth 
would have been to make him wear earrings. 
</p><p>He called his mother "mommy," and she usually referred to him 
as "my angel."  She withheld from Harold the only possibility by 
which he might have gained some good repute from the rest of his 
fellows &mdash; she wouldn't let him learn to play ragtime on the piano. 
</p><p>You can't keep a scheme like that quiet in a place like 
Brookfield.  It came to Caleb's ears that Harold Hussey was going 
to be used against him at the Hastings surprise party, and Mr. 
Coppins nearly exploded with subdued laughter. 
</p><p>He knew that Harold's knowledge was practically confined to 
one subject.  Now, Mr. Coppins knew nothing about music.  But he 
got to work under his kerosene lamp.  He absorbed everything in 
the "Pan-Continental" that looked as if it might have the taint of 
harmony.  He delved for dates and nourished himself on names. 
</p><p>He arrived at the Hastings home with a glint of vulpine 
shrewdness in his eyes.  He was not perturbed by the surreptitious 
whispering that went on around him.  He picked out the best chair 
in the crowded rooms, and threw himself into the preliminary 
course of ice-cream, sandwiches, and cake.  Once in a while he 
cast a withering glance at Harold Hussey, who had been placed 
opposite to him, and Harold nearly choked upon a mouthful of 
frosted cake, Mrs. Hussey patted her pride and hope upon his back 
and spoke soothing words to him. 
</p><p>Mr. Coppins deliberately put away his dishes and drew himself 
into a dignified attitude of scholastic reflection.  Suddenly he 
remarked: 
</p><p>"I tell you, folks, it's only when a man really begins to 
learn something that he realizes how much there is to learn.  Now, 
friends, there was a time when I felt pretty sure I knew 
everything.  But I didn't &mdash; not then!" 
</p><p>"I suppose you do now," retorted an untactful guest, out of 
his heart of writhing hate. 
</p><p>"Oh, no," replied Caleb complacently; "not everything.  But 
little by little I'm accumulating a fund of knowledge.  Knowledge 
is power!  I tell you what, it makes a man feel like a real man.  
It's the little facts that count.  How many of you here could tell 
me, for instance, the length, in American measure, of a Swedish 
mile?  You ought to know, folks.  It's important to know those 
things.  How many of you could tell me what language the ancient 
Egyptians spoke, or who deciphered the first cuneiform 
inscriptions dug from the great desert near the Nile?  You ought 
to know.  Everybody ought to know.  Those things are important.  
Now, <hi rend="italic">you</hi>," concluded Caleb, pointing at the untactful young man 
who had opened the subject, "suppose you ask me some question &mdash; any 
question.  Go ahead &mdash; make it a hard one!" 
</p><p>The untactful young man glowered at the enemy and swallowed 
hard.  He took four reefs in his forehead, and the veins stood out 
on his temples in his effort to think of a poser.  Finally he 
gasped and lay back in his chair, helpless.  He couldn't think of 
a question to save his life! 
</p><p>Mr. Coppins laughed softly and stroked his chin. 
</p><p>"Anybody else?" he said airily. 
</p><p>"Wait a minute!" cried the untactful one, suddenly coming to 
life with a wild gleam of joy.  "Tell us &mdash; tell us &mdash; who discovered 
the &mdash; monkey-wrench!" 
</p><p>A titter went around the room, and a dozen male mouths opened 
with cordial expectation that Caleb Coppins would be crushed to 
earth.  For a second he looked at the ceiling.  Then, in a chant 
that was <pb n="655"/> suspiciously like that of a parrot, he warbled: 
</p><p>"Certainly!  The monkey-wrench is not, as some may suppose, an 
instrument to monkey with; nor indeed has it any connection with 
the simian tribe.  It should really be called a <hi rend="italic">moncky</hi>-wrench, 
for it was invented by a Baltimore mechanic named Charles Moncky.  
Got any other question to ask?" 
</p><p>The youth who propounded the query faded into the background 
and deftly pulled the background over his naked shame.  There was 
generous applause from the ladies. 
</p><p>"I've got one!" said another brave candidate.  "Who discovered 
glue?" 
</p><p>"Glue!" repeated Mr. Coppins.  "Now there's a question!  Who 
discovered glue?  I like to have questions like that thrown at me.  
Glue is an important substance, and everybody should know the 
answer to that question.  Now, glue &mdash; " 
</p><p>Mr. Coppins stopped.  Of course, he did not know who 
discovered glue, and he had not the wit to frame a satisfactory 
answer to what was in reality an unfair question.  It would have 
been almost as reasonable to inquire who invented bread. 
</p><p>His only hope was a swift diversion. 
</p><p>"Harold," he said, pulling himself together, "you are a 
musician.  I'll bet you anything you don't know all a musician 
should know about the famous author of `Parsifal.'  You don't know 
how old he was when he died, or where he was born, or where he 
died, or any of those important data." 
</p><p>"You mean Wagner?" replied Harold. 
</p><p>"I mean Vogner," replied Mr. Coppins, severely precise.  
"Those who do not know call him Wagner.  I call him Vogner, as his 
fellow countrymen did.  The German language is not like our 
language, you must understand.  Now I ask the question, where was 
that great composer born; and I answer it myself &mdash; he was born in 
Leipsic, Germany." 
</p><p>"Is that right, Harold?" asked a score of eager voices.  "Do 
you know?" 
</p><p>"That'th right," was the feeble and disappointed reply.  
"Leipthic is right." 
</p><p>"You see!" said Mr. Coppins, with a broad smile at the 
company.  "Another important question!" continued Caleb, rubbing 
his hands gleefully.  "A very important question!  Where did the 
great composer die?  Shake off the mortal coil, as one might say?  
I will answer &mdash; at Baireuth.  Pronounced `Byroit,' you will please 
observe." 
</p><p>"Is that right, Harold?" challenged the same palpitating 
voices. 
</p><p>"No, thir," was the reply.  "It ith not!" 
</p><p>"What?" shouted Caleb Coppins menacingly.  "Do you mean to 
tell me, Harold, that I am wrong?  Think again, boy, think again!" 
</p><p>"He died in Venice," persisted Harold in feeble exultation and 
reaching for his mother's hand. 
</p><p>"He did not!" retorted Mr. Coppins. 
</p><p>"He did so," Harold insisted. 
</p><p>"The boy's got you," said Calkins, the grocer.  "Give up, 
Caleb.  You're stung!" 
</p><p>"He died in Byroit," said Caleb.  "Mind what I tell you.  I 
know!" 
</p><p>"Venice," said Harold Hussey feebly but doggedly. 
</p><p>Mr. Calkins, with a cunning look in his eye, took Harold by 
the arm and led him aside. 
</p><p>"Are you sure about it, son?" he asked. 
</p><p>"That'th what my book sayth," lisped Harold.  "Besides, I know 
that Wagner died in an old palace on the Grand Canal in Venice." 
</p><p>Calkins turned swiftly upon Caleb.  "The boy's got you," he 
laughed.  "Give up; you're stung, Caleb!" 
</p><p>"Nonsense!" said Caleb. 
</p><p>I'll bet you one hundred dollars the boy's right," cried the 
grocer.  "Put up or shut up!" 
</p><p>Mr. Calkins evidently had little idea that Caleb would put up.  
He paled visibly when Mr. Coppins replied confidently: 
</p><p>"I'll go you!" 
</p><p>"I &mdash; I haven't got that much cash with me," stammered the 
grocer.  "But here are witnesses.  I say Harold is right." 
</p><p>"I really hate to take your money," replied Caleb coolly.      
"It doesn't seem fair, honestly; but you can't blame me.  One 
hundred dollars!  I'm your man." 
</p><p>"Really, you mustn't bet money," interrupted Mrs. Hastings, 
thinking of the dignity of her position as hostess, but secretly 
hoping that it would be disregarded. 
</p><p>"Let 'em go ahead!" cried the men.  "This has been coming to 
Caleb for a long time." 
 &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  &mdash;  
</p><p>EDITOR'S NOTE &mdash; The erroneous statement that Richard Wagner 
died at Baireuth is actually to be found in a well-known and 
usually very accurate work of reference. 
 
<pb n="656"/>  
</p><p>"I can prove it by my book," averred Harold.  "I'll go right 
home and get it thith minute." 
</p><p>"Books talk," returned Caleb.  "I'll be back in half a jiffy.  
Then you'll hand me a check for that hundred, Calkins! 
</p> 
</div1><div1 type="chapter" n="5" id="d7"> 
<head>V</head> 
 
<p>TEN awful minutes of suspense passed over the heads of the 
company.  Calkins perspired in a corner and accepted the 
congratulations of the crowd with a clammy and uncertain hand. 
</p><p>There was a shuffling of feet outside.  In another moment 
Caleb Coppins entered with a large volume bound in limp leather.  
He opened it and laid it on the table.  Then he pressed his finger 
on a certain spot and threw back his head haughtily.  As many as 
could gather around the evidence regarded the fatal words and 
groaned.  In his corner Mr. Calkins shivered.  It was plain: 
 
</p><p>WAGNER, Richard, German composer, born at Leipsic, 1813; died 
at Baireuth, 1883. 
 
</p><p>Another scraping of feet outside, and Mrs. Hussey entered with 
Harold.  Harold also had a book.  Mr. Coppins deigned to glance at 
his antagonist's evidence, and his eyebrows lifted somewhat.  
Harold also had a volume of the "Pan-Continental Encyclopedic 
Dictionary"! 
</p><p>Then Caleb smiled.  All the better &mdash; the same volume to tell 
the same story! 
</p><p>Mr. Coppins saw Mr. Calkins pounce wolfishly upon Harold's 
book and whip the pages over.  Presently the search ended, and 
young Hussey pointed to a passage which Mr. Calkins eagerly read.  
Then the grocer strode toward Caleb with a countenance which 
somehow made the bibliophile wonder if he had forgotten anything.  
With a bold front, however, he turned upon Mr. Calkins and asked 
confidently: 
</p><p>"Is there any other question you'd like to ask me?" 
</p><p>There was a tense moment of hush in the room.  A glint of 
wicked guile that sparked from Calkins's eyes brought a pale spot 
under each of Caleb's ears.  Then he heard these words: 
</p><p>"Yes, Caleb, there are two questions I'd like to ask you.  One 
of them is:  Have you seen <hi rend="italic">this</hi>?" 
</p><p>He planked down before Caleb Harold's volume of the 
"Pan-Continental" and glued his finger to a pink slip of paper 
inserted in front of the title-page.  Then, in a loud and cheerful 
voice, he read the following into Caleb's ear: 
 
</p><p>"ERRATUM &mdash; On page 301 of this volume, under `WAGNER, Richard,' 
for `died at Baireuth,' read `died at Venice, Italy.'" 
 
</p><p>Defeated, stricken dumb, Mr. Coppins did not even attempt a 
reply.  After a moment of dead silence the triumphant voice of Mr. 
Calkins went on: 
</p><p>"Yes, Caleb, and here's the second question &mdash; have you that 
hundred in your jeans?"</p> 
</div1> 
</body> 
<back id="d8"> 
<div1 type="poem" id="d9">
<head>ROSES &mdash; FOR A SONG</head>
<lg type="stanza">  
<l>Buy me roses for my garden,"</l> 
<l>    Said the lady whose least word</l> 
<l>Blends the iron of a mandate</l> 
<l>    With the sweetness of a bird.</l> 
</lg>
<lg type="stanza">  
<l>"But I have no golden money;</l> 
<l>Scarce have I a silver crown!"</l> 
<l>"Buy them with Catullian honey,</l> 
<l>Sweet as wild bees' dripping down.</l> 
</lg>
<lg type="stanza">  
<l>"Take some golden words to market;</l> 
<l>Don't you think the merchant knows</l> 
<l>Beauty always is good barter,</l> 
<l>Rose is fair exchange for rose?</l> 
</lg>
<lg type="stanza">  
<l>"Then, when next time in my garden</l> 
<l>By my side you walk along,</l> 
<l>You shall see how words look growing &mdash; </l> 
<l>Buy me roses with a song!"</l> 
</lg>
<p><hi rend="italic">Richard Franklin</hi> </p>
 
</div1>
</back> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
