<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="TruNegr"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
 
<TEI.2 id="TruNegr"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Negro Minstrelsy &mdash; Ancient and Modern</title>
<title type="sort">negro minstrelsy &mdash; ancient and modern</title>
<author>Trux, J. J.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">40</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">TruNegr</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476401</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Judy Boss adds that she made the following changes to the text: on p. 
75, par. 1, "Tennesse" to "Tennessee"; "river in in" to "river in."</p>
</note>
</notesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Negro Minstrelsy &mdash; Ancient and Modern</title>
<title type="sort">negro minstrelsy &mdash; ancient and modern</title>
<author>J. J. Trux</author>
</titleStmt> 
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt> 
<publicationStmt> 
<pubPlace>New York, NY</pubPlace> 
<date value="1855-01">January 1855</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>Putnam's Monthly Magazine</p>
</seriesStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1855-01">January 1855</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term> 
<term>African American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-12">December 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Monique Dull, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Converted to basic TEI.2-conformant markup; scanning of print 
illustration; composed figure description; edited TEI.2 header;  
checked bibliographic information with print edition, University of  
Virginia Library AP 2.97 v.5 1855</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 

<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="72"/>
	<head>NEGRO MINSTRELSY&mdash;ANCIENT AND MODERN.</head> 
 
<p>It is now some eighteen or twenty years since an enterprising 
Yankee, actuated, it is but charitable to suppose, by the purest 
love of musical art, by the enthusiasm of the discoverer, or by a 
proper and praiseworthy desire for posthumous fame, produced upon 
the boards of one of our metropolitan theatres, a musical sketch 
entitled "Jim Crow."  Beyond the simple fact of its production by 
the estimable gentleman above referred to, the origin of this 
ancient and peculiar melody is beyond the reach of modern 
antiquarian lore.  Whether it was first sung upon the banks of the 
Alatamaha, the Alabama, or the Mississippi; or, whether it is pre-American, and a relic of heathen rites in Congo, or in that 
mysterious heart of Africa, which foot of civilized man has never 
trod, is a problem whose solution must be left to the zeal and 
research of some future Ethiopian Oldbuck.  It is sufficient for 
the present disquisition to know that it appeared in the manner 
above stated.  To those (if there can be any such) who are 
unacquainted with its character and general scope, it may be proper 
to remark that "Jim Crow" is what may be called a dramatic song, 
depending for its success, perhaps more than any play ever written 
for the stage, upon the action and mimetic powers of the performer.  
Its success was immediate and marked.  It touched a chord in the 
American heart which had never before vibrated, but which now 
responded to the skilful fingers of its first expounder, like the 
music of the Bermoothes to the magic wand of Prospero.  The 
schoolboy whistled the melody on his unwilling way to his daily 
tasks.  The ploughman checked his oxen in mid-furrow, as he reached 
its chorus, that the poetic exhortation to "do just so," might have 
the action suited to the word.  Merchants and staid professional 
men, to whom a joke was a sin, were sometimes seen by the eyes of 
prying curiosity in private to unbend their dignity to that weird 
and wonderful posture, now, alas! seldom seen but in historic 
pictures, or upon the sign of a tobacconist; and of the thoroughly 
impressive and extraordinary sights which the writer of this 
article has in his lifetime beheld, the most memorable and 
noteworthy was that of a young lady in a sort of inspired rapture, 
throwing her weight alternately upon the tendon Achillis of the 
one, and the toes of the other foot, her left hand resting upon her 
hip, her right, like that of some prophetic sybil, extended aloft, 
gyrating as the exigencies of the song required, and singing Jim 
Crow at the top of her voice.  Popularity like this laughs at 
anathemas from the pulpit, or sneers from the press.  The song 
which is sung in the parlor, hummed in the kitchen, and whistled in 
the stable, may defy oblivion.  But such signal and triumphant 
success can produce but one result.  Close upon the heels of Jim 
Crow, came treading, one after the other, "Zip Coon," "Long-tailed 
Blue," "Ole Virginny neber tire," "Settin' on a Rail," and a host 
of others, all of superior merit, though unequal alike in their 
intrinsic value, and in their participation in public approval.  
The golden age of negro literature had commenced.  Thenceforward 
for several years the appearance of a new melody was an event whose 
importance can hardly be appreciated by the coming generation.  It 
flew from mouth to mouth, and from hamlet to hamlet, with a 
rapidity which seemed miraculous.  The stage-driver dropped a stave 
or two of it during a change of the mails at some out of the way 
tavern; it was treasured up and remembered, and added to from day 
to day, till the whole became familiar as household words.  Yankee 
Doodle went to town with a load of garden vegetables.  If upon his 
ears there fell the echo of a new plantation song, barter and 
sight-seeing were secondary objects till he had mastered both its 
words and music.  Thereafter, and until supplanted by some equally 
enthusiastic and enterprising neighbor, Yankee Doodle was the hero 
of his native vale, of Todd Hollow.  Like the troubadours and 
minstrels of ancient days, he found open doors and warm hearts 
wherever he went.  Cider, pumpkin pie, and the smiles of the fair 
were bestowed upon him with an unsparing hand.  His song was for 
the time to him the wand of Fortunatus. 
</p><p>The prevailing characteristics of the melodies which this 
period produced are their perfect and continual lightness, spirit, 
and good humor; but the true secret of their favor with the world 
is to be found in the fact that they 
<pb n="73"/>  are genuine and real.  
They are no senseless and ridiculous imitations forged in the dull 
brain of some northern self-styled minstrel, but the veritable 
tunes and words which have lightened the labor of some weary negro 
in the cotton fields, amused his moonlight hours as he fished, or 
waked the spirits of the woods as he followed in the track of the 
wary racoon.  It is as impossible to counterfeit, or successfully 
imitate, one of these songs, as it would be for a modern poet to 
produce a border ballad like Chevy Chase or Lord Jamie Douglas.  It 
is not alone the patient and laborious student of negro minstrelsy 
that can detect the ring of the false metal.  The shameless 
imitations carry their imposture upon their face.  Walpole, with 
all his credulity, would never have been deceived, had Chatterton 
turned his attention to manufacturing plantation songs. 
</p><p>The allusion to ancient English and Scottish ballads cannot 
fail to bring to the mind of the poetical scholar, the striking 
similarity that exists between many of the "specimens" of Percy, 
Ritson and others, and the most approved poetry of the African 
school.  In the terseness and fitness of the language, the oft 
repeated idiomatic expressions, the occasional looseness and 
negligence in respect to rhyme, the carelessness and license in the 
metre, and, above all, in the incoherence of the constantly 
recurring refrain; the lover of negro minstrelsy is continually 
reminded of the old, plain songs which Shakespeare loved, and "the 
spinsters and the knitters in the sun" did use to chant.  I quote 
almost at random from Motherwell.</p> 

<lg type="citation"> 
<l>  "Oh!  I never saw my love before</l> 
<l>     With a hey lilelu and a how lo lan;</l> 
<l>   Till I saw her through an auger bore,</l> 
<l>     And the birk and the brume blooms bonnie.</l> 
 
<l>"And she gave to me a gay gold ring,</l> 
<l>     With a hey lilelu and a how lo lan;</l> 
<l>   With three shining diamonds set therein,</l> 
<l>   And the birk and the brume blooms bonnie."</l> 
</lg> 

<p>Let the words peculiarly Scottish in Hynd Horn, the ballad 
from which the above is taken, or in almost any other ancient 
ballad, be literally translated into the African dialect, and we 
have at once a plantation song.  The birk and the brume may be more 
alliterative, but they are certainly not more poetic trees than the 
gum and the persimmon.  In further illustration of this subject I 
cannot forbear quoting a portion of a banjo song from a volume now 
lying before me.  Its genuineness, no one at all familiar with 
negro literature will presume to question, while its intrinsic 
worth and excellence will be perceived by the most indifferent or 
prejudiced observer.  It is hardly possible to peruse it without 
thinking of Gil Maurice or Syr Charles Bawdin.  Not inferior to the 
former in its simplicity and truthfulness, it is far above the 
feeble imitation of Chatterton in dramatic effect and artistic 
construction.</p> 

<lg type="citation"> 
<l>  "Oh, my boys I'm bound to tell you;</l> 
<l>                     Oh!  Oh!</l> 
<l>   Listen a while, and I will tell you;</l> 
<l>                     Oh!  Oh!</l> 
<l>   I'll tell you little 'bout Uncle Gabriel;</l> 
<l>   Oh, boys, I've just begun.</l> 
<l>   Hard times in old Virginny.</l> 
 
<l>"Oh, don't you know old Uncle Gabriel?</l> 
<l>                     Oh!  Oh!</l> 
<l>   Oh, he was a darkey General,</l> 
<l>                     Oh!  Oh!</l> 
<l>   He was the chief of the insurgents,</l> 
<l>   Way down in Southampton.</l> 
<l>   Hard times in old Virginny.</l> 
 
<l>"It was a little boy betrayed him,</l> 
<l>                     Oh!  Oh!</l> 
<l>   A little boy by the name of Daniel</l> 
<l>                     Oh!  Oh!</l> 
<l>   Betrayed him at the Norfolk landing;</l> 
<l>   Oh, boys I'm getting done.</l> 
<l>   Hard Times in old Virginny.</l> 
 
<l>"Says he, How d'ye do, my Uncle Gabriel?</l> 
<l>                     Oh!  Oh!</l> 
<l>   I am not your Uncle Gabriel,</l> 
<l>                     Oh!  Oh!</l> 
<l>   My name it is Jim McCullen;</l> 
<l>   Some they calls me Archy Mullin.</l> 
<l>   Hard times in old Virginny.</l> 
 
<l>      *    *    *    *    *    * </l>
 
<l>"They took him down to the gallows,</l> 
<l>                     Oh!  Oh!</l> 
<l>   They drove him down with four grey horses,</l> 
<l>                     Oh!  Oh!</l> 
<l>   Brice's Ben, he drove the wagon,</l> 
<l>   Oh, boys, I am most done.</l> 
<l>   Hard times in old Virginny.</l> 
 
<l>"And there they hung him and they swung him,</l> 
<l>                     Oh!  Oh!</l> 
<l>   And they swung him and they hung him,</l> 
<l>                     Oh!  Oh!</l> 
<l>   And that was the last of the darkey General;</l> 
<l>   Oh, boys I'm just done.</l> 
<l>   Hard times in old Virginny."</l> 
</lg> 
<p>Those of us who have for so many years been looking anxiously 
forward to <pb n="74"/>  the advent of the coming poet who is to take away 
from America the sin and the shame of never having produced an 
epic, or a lyric, commensurate with Niagara and the Rocky 
Mountains, will do well to get up a subscription and buy the author 
of this song, if his owner can be persuaded to part with him.  His 
noble, poetic nature must chafe in the cotton field like Pegasus in 
harness.  The specimen above given, is simple, grand, and 
expressive.  The picture it presents to the imagination is natural 
and life-like.  The stream of song runs in a straight channel, and 
conducts us swiftly and directly to the catastrophe.  There is no 
turning aside for flowery metaphors, or forcible expressions&mdash;no 
straining for effect&mdash;no lugubrious whining over the hero's 
downfall&mdash;no moralizing his unhappy fate.  Even the jingle of rhyme 
is wanting.  And yet, for severe beauty, perfect dramatic 
structure, and succinct impressive narration, it would be difficult 
in the whole range of ancient and modern ballad poetry, to find a 
worthy rival to "Uncle Gabriel." 
</p><p>The lightness and prevailing good humor of the negro songs, 
have been before remarked upon.  A true southern melody is seldom 
sentimental, and never melancholy.  And this results directly from 
the character and habits of the colored race.  No hardships or 
troubles can destroy, or even check their happiness and levity.  As 
I pen these words, the grinning image of the boy Quash rises up 
before me like a phantom.  Light-hearted, witty, and gay, he was 
the very type of his race.  His jests, his laughter, and his songs 
linger with me yet, though many a long year has passed since I 
gazed upon his shining face.  It is but fitting that I should 
embalm his memory in these pages.  Watching one day the embarkation 
of a few bales of cotton, I noticed Quash in the shadow of the 
steamboat as she lay alongside the dock.  A foolish whim induced me 
to say, "Quash, what is the name of that boat?"  Quash stepped 
deliberately up to the side of the boat, gazed knowingly at the 
large black letters on the wheel-house, shaded his eyes with his 
hand, and looked again, dropped his head between his shoulders, and 
peered earnestly into the unknown characters, stepped a few paces 
back, and went through the same manoeuvres, and at last turned to 
me with an arch leer upon his face. "I 'clar Maussa," replied he, 
"I'se so near-sighted, dis mornin', I can't 'stinguish de letters." 
</p><p>Reading Othello one warm and quiet afternoon, in the shade of 
a spreading fig-tree, I became suddenly aware of the bright eyes of 
Quash, which were turned with a curious gaze upon me and my book, 
as if he were wondering at that strange and awful science, which 
discloses to us the thoughts and feelings of the dead.  "Quash," 
said I, wishing to get, from a mind totally unbiased by the 
conflicting opinions of critics, a "first impression" upon a 
disputed passage, "which reading to you prefer, 'Put out the light, 
and then&mdash;Put out the light,' or, 'Put out the light, and then&mdash;put 
out <hi rend="italic">the</hi> light'?"  Quash scratched his woolly head, and 
putting on that same indescribable leer again, solved the 
difficulty at once.  "I tink, Maussa," replied he, "I should make 
um blow de light out de fuss time."  If the student of Shakespeare 
ponders as long and as deeply upon this answer as I did, the covert 
satire and the AEsopian wisdom which it displays will not be lost 
upon him.  Alexander's solution of the Gordian knot was not more 
witty or more wise.  But that rascal Quash is at his old trick, 
again, I find, of causing me to neglect my business.  Let us 
return. 
</p><p>In or about the year 1841, a descriptive ballad, entitled "Ole 
Dan Tucker," first made its appearance, and speedily acquired a 
renown and popularity hardly excelled, even by that of "Jim Crow."  
This may be partly attributable to the fact that less histrionic 
talent is required to give it a fitting interpretation, and partly 
to its intrinsic worth.  In some respects Ole Dan Tucker may be 
regarded as the best of what I have denominated the ancient negro 
ballads.  The <ref target="n1"> melody*</ref> was far superior to anything that had 
preceded it.  In its vivacity and liveliness, the music 
occasionally reminds us of some of Donizetti's happiest efforts, 
while its simplicity and quaintness at times breathe of Auber.  The 
words, too, came more dearly home to the heart of the American 
people than those of its predecessors.  The song, it is needless to 
say, consists of a series of vivid pictures, disconnected in 
themselves, varying as rapidly as the changes in a kaleidoscope, 
and yet presenting 
<pb n="75"/>  
to us the character of the hero, as a most artistic 
whole.  The most searching test of popularity can be applied to 
"Ole Dan Tucker" with perfect confidence.  It has been sung, 
perhaps, oftener than any melody ever written. 
</p><p>I have said that this was in some aspects the best of these 
songs.  It was the last.  With that ballad African minstrelsy may 
be said to have culminated.  From that period its decline and fall 
was rapid and saddening.  Hardly a song has been produced since 
that time which does not present the most glaring marks of 
barefaced and impudent imposition.  The zealous student of this 
species of literature, as he wanders amongst the decaying ruins of 
its former grandeur, may well sigh at the rank and mildewed 
vegetation which is fast overspreading those noble relics of 
antiquity.  If a buttress or a cornice of beauty meets his eye, he 
finds it but a portion of the old edifice degraded to a new 
position.  If a gleam of the former light occasionally sparkles in 
his path, it is but the phosphoric glimmer which beams from 
loathsome and decaying putrescence.  Vile parodies, sentimental 
love songs, dirges for dead wenches who are generally sleeping 
under the willow, on the bank of some stream, and melancholy 
reminiscences of negroic childhood fill the places once allotted to 
the grand old ballads of former days.  From the volume before 
mentioned, I have not been able, after a most critical examination, 
to select more than ten which bear any trace of the cotton-field 
afflatus, and these ten, with only one exception, have been so 
patched and dressed up for drawing-room inspection, that they look 
like a bumpkin who has suddenly come into possession of a fortune.  
They have lost their country grace without acquiring a city polish.  
This inundation of trash has swept away in its might all the 
ancient landmarks of song.  It is mortifying to be obliged to 
confess that I have searched unsuccessfully from Appleton's to the 
book stand in the rear of the post-office, for a copy of the 
original Jim Crow.  The names, even, have lost their marked 
significance.  The questionable taste which has given birth to 
appellations like Fanny Fern, Lotty Lee, Minnie Myrtle, and their 
long retinue of vegetable alliterations, has crept into this 
department of poetry and exhibits itself in such Africo-romantic 
fancies as Rosa Lee, Lily Dale, Flora May, Nelly Bell or <ref  
target="n2">Etty Way*</ref>. Poetasters who never saw an alligator,  
or smelt the magnolia blossom in their lives, sit coolly down to  
write an African ditty as a pleasant after-dinner pastime, or a  
daily task; and, as a natural consequence of this reprehensible  
assumption, we find the banana growing wild in Tennessee, South  
Carolina slaves gorging themselves with pumpkin pie, a deceased  
negress buried upon the Lawrence river in the midst of a furious  
snow, and a Kentucky sugar mill in full blast in the month of June. 
</p><p>But ludicrous anachronisms, and unpardonable ignorance of 
topography, are not the worst evils of which we have to complain.  
Instead of the lyrics which once stirred the heart of the nation, 
our wives and children are daily and nightly compelled to listen to 
some such horrible parody as this&mdash;</p> 
<lg type="citation"> 
<l>"In a lone cypress swamp, where the <hi rend="italic">wild-roaring</hi>bullfrog,</l> 
<l>   The echoes <hi rend="italic">awake</hi> with his deep thrilling tones&mdash;</l> 
<l> Old Pompey lies there, and the plantation watch-dog</l> 
<l>   A requiem howls o'er his deep sunken bones."</l> 
</lg> 
<p>or sentimental trash like this&mdash;</p> 
<lg type="citation">  
<l>"Etty was so gentle, kind, and good to all,</l> 
<l>She played the old banjo which hung upon de wall;</l> 
<l>Etty's voice was low and sweet, like de little bird;</l> 
<l>Them soft and gentle tones dat I've so often heard."</l> 
</lg> 
<p>or this&mdash;</p> 
<lg type="citation">   
<l>          "Oh!  I ne'er can lub anudder</l> 
<l>             So fond, so true, again;</l> 
<l>          I'm thine, and thine forebber,</l> 
<l>             My charming Kate Loraine."</l> 
</lg> 
<p>They are fortunate if they get to bed without being wearied 
and disgusted with some crude burlesque on a popular opera, served 
up with vulgar caricatures of the style and manner of well-known 
<pb n="76"/> artists; and commended to popular favor by the vilest puns, 
of which "Lend her de Sham-money," or "Lucy did lam a Moor," are 
not exaggerated specimens.  Now, all this may serve to make the 
unskilful laugh, but it cannot fail to make the judicious grieve.  
It is from the purpose of negroic minstrelsy, whose end at the 
first was, and now ought to be, to present to the lovers of 
original poetry and music, a class of songs, peculiar, genuine, and 
unadulterated.  A thoughtful, reflective man, can hardly leave one 
of the temples devoted to such barbaric sacrifices, without 
reasonable and just despondency and alarm.  The decay of Athens and 
Rome was as marked and as melancholy in their literature as in 
their <ref target="n3">government*</ref>.  The poet, the orator, and the statesman, went 
down hand in hand into the shadowy valley, and disappeared together 
in the clouds of ignorance and superstition that veil for ever the 
Dark Ages.  Is it treasonable to hint, for the warning of American 
minstrels and politicians, that there is something more than a 
striking coincidence in this simultaneous decline; and that the 
present diseased taste in popular poetry, may be but the first 
faint symptoms of another dark period, in which America shall be 
hidden from the gaze of the world; never, perhaps, to emerge to her 
pristine dignity and splendor?  I am no alarmist, and yet it seems 
to me that, in these views, the patriot may find matter for deep 
and serious consideration. 
</p><p>A proper diagnosis of the disease, however, is of no effect, 
unless a remedy is applied.  Fortunately, in this case, we are not 
left without hope.  The mine from which Jim Crow and Ole Dan Tucker 
were dug, is not yet exhausted, and a resort to it will be alike 
easy and successful.  Why need we groan and grumble under the 
inflictions of ignorant and self-conceited song-writers, when every 
cotton-field teems with melody, and every slave hut, throughout the 
Southern country, has its little list of genuine ballads, which 
only need to be known, in order to be received to the heart of a 
nation.  We talk with vague regrets and sentimental longings, of 
the forgotten strains of Tasso, once chanted so commonly by the 
shrill-voiced gondoliers of Venice.  Poets have mused dejectedly 
over the songless boatmen, travellers have feelingly bewailed the 
silence and desolation of those once gay canals; romancists and 
serenaders are gradually ceasing to adjure us to "list to the voice 
of the gay gondolier."  That malice which delights to slander the 
unresisting dead, has begun to deny both the gaiety of the 
gondolier, and the purity of his voice.  He shares the fate of 
Memnon.  Ever since the hush of those mysterious sounds which were 
wont to greet the dawn, there have not been wanting travelled 
Gradgrinds to assure us that the song from his lips was a humbug 
and a sham; and to degrade that majestic statue into a vulgar 
shoemaker with a musical lapstone, upon which the morning hymn was 
hammered by his knavish priests.  So we are asked to believe that 
the voice of the gondolier was harsh and unmusical, and that 
"Tasso's echoes," chanted alternately, were but such polite and 
complimentary remarks as may be heard to this day among the drivers 
on the Erie Canal.  But as I seat myself in imagination, on this 
calm and moonlight night, by a certain wayside in the South, I 
leave these discussions to the prosy antiquary, and care not for 
the songs of Venice, or the music of Memnon.  Up from the Sound 
comes a gentle south wind, rippling the water, and fanning my 
whiskers; the shore surge whispers low at my feet; afar in the 
distance I hear the hum of the plantation.  The tumultuous harmony 
of the stock, mingled and blending with the faint shouts and cries 
of the "people," and the nameless and varied sounds of insect life 
lull my senses like the gentle susurrus of Tityrus.  And now, 
faintly heard far over the water, I distinguish the soft thump of 
oars in the rowlock of an approaching boat.  I listen with 
attentive ears&mdash;for I know by experience the gratification in store 
for me&mdash;and soon catch the distant tones of the human voice&mdash;now 
more faintly heard, and now entirely lost.  A few minutes pass, and 
the breeze once more wafts to me the swelling notes of the chorus 
half buried in the measured cadence of the oars.  The wind dies 
away, and my straining ears again hear nothing but the measured 
beat of the rowers, and the plashing of the restless sea.  But now, 
anew, I hear the sound of those manly negro voices swelling up upon 
the evening gale.  Nearer and nearer comes the boat, higher and 
higher rises the melody, till it overpowers and subdues the noise 
of the oars, which in their turn become subservient 
<pb n="77"/> to the song, and mark its time with harmonious beating.  
And now the boat is so near, that every word and every tone comes 
to my ear, over the water, with perfect distinctness, and I 
recognize the grand old triumphal chorus of the stirring patriotic 
melody of "Gen'el Jackson":</p> 
<lg type="citation">  
<l>     "Gen'el Jackson, mighty man&mdash;</l> 
<l>        Whaw, my kingdom, fire away;</l> 
<l>      He fight on sea, and he fight on land,</l> 
<l>        Whaw, my kingdom, fire away.</l> 
  
<l>     "Gen'el Jackson gain de day&mdash;</l> 
<l>        Whaw, my kingdom, fire away,</l> 
<l>      He gain de day in Floraday,</l> 
<l>        Whaw, my kingdom, fire away.</l> 
  
<l>     "Gen'el Jackson fine de trail,</l> 
<l>        Whaw, my kingdom, fire away,</l> 
<l>      He full um fote wid cotton bale,</l> 
<l>        Whaw, my kingdom, fire away."</l> 
</lg> 
<p>But the boat touches the beach; the negroes with a wild cry 
quit their singing, tumble out into the shallow water, drag their 
dug-out up high and dry upon the sand, and I am left once more with 
the evening breeze and the quieter harmony of nature. 
</p><p>The song, a part of which I have just quoted, is fresh from 
the sable mint in which it was coined.  Its originality and 
genuineness every one familiar with plantation life will at once 
perceive; while some Georgians may even be able to point to the 
very river on which the dusky troubadours still chant it.  I am 
well aware that in depriving the words of their appropriate music, 
I rob it of much of its attractiveness, and still it is no bad 
sample of what may be called the Historic Plantation Ballad.  The 
particular naval battle in which Old Hickory was engaged, I have 
not been able to discover; but the allusion to the bales of cotton 
in the third stanza may not be without its effect in settling one 
of the vexed questions relating to the defence of New Orleans; and 
it adds another to the many examples of the superiority of oral 
tradition over contemporaneous written history. 
</p><p>It is not alone, however, on the water that these quaint songs 
are produced.  The annual corn-shucking season has its own peculiar 
class of songs, never heard but on that festival; their rhythmical 
structure or caesural pauses not being adapted to the measured 
cadence of the oars.  Standing at a little distance from the corn 
heap, on some dark and quiet night, watching the sable forms of the 
gang, illuminated at intervals by the flashes of the lightwood 
knot, and listening to the wild high notes of their harvest songs, 
it is easy to imagine ourselves unseen spectators of some secret 
aboriginal rite or savage festival.  Snatches of one or two songs 
which on such occasions I have heard, recur to me.  Could I in the 
following specimen give you any idea of the wild grandeur and 
stirring music of the refrain, I should need no apology for 
presenting it to my readers.</p> 
<lg type="citation">  
<l>          "De ladies in de parlor,</l> 
<l>             Hey, come a rollin' down&mdash;</l> 
<l>           A drinking tea and coffee;</l> 
<l>             Good morning ladies all.</l> 
  
<l>          "De gemmen in de kitchen,</l> 
<l>             Hey come a rollin' down&mdash;</l> 
<l>           A drinking brandy toddy;</l> 
<l>             Good morning, ladies all."</l> 
</lg> 
<p>I place the above in a class to which I have given the name of 
descriptive songs.  By this I do not mean to be understood as 
hinting that it is an accurate description of a "whitefolks," 
party.  On the contrary, it probably originated in the tipsy brain 
of its dusky author; or, perhaps, in a moment of discontent may 
have been composed as an exaggerated satire.  The allusion to the 
kitchen, as the place where the gentlemen are engaged in their 
pleasing and congenial occupation goes to show that the minstrel 
had in his view a colored party, which I am inclined to think was 
in fact the case.  But at this stage of our critical knowledge on 
the subject of negro literature, such speculations are alike 
tedious and unprofitable. 
</p><p>The comic ballads of the South, form a large and highly 
interesting class of songs, more especially as they are of a sort 
most readily transplanted, and most grateful to the public taste.  
Apart from their fun, however, they lack the merit which 
distinguishes many other kinds of African composition.  The negro 
is humorous rather than witty, and his comic songs consist of 
ludicrous images, instead of witty conceits.  I do not remember, in 
the whole course of my investigations, to have met with anything 
like a pun in a genuine plantation melody.  The following shucking 
song has nothing to recommend it to public attention, save the 
questionable rhyme to "supper."  The lovers of "Ole Dan Tucker" 
will be pleased and interested with a coincidence in which there 
cannot be the slightest ground for a suspicion of plagiarism.</p> 
<pb n="78"/>  
<lg type="citation">   
<l>          "Cow bog on middle e' island&mdash;</l> 
<l>             Ho! meleety, ho!</l> 
<l>           Cow boy on middle e' island&mdash;</l> 
<l>             Ho! meleety, ho!</l> 
   
<l>          "Missis eat de green persimmon,</l> 
<l>             Ho! meleety, ho! [<hi rend="italic">Repeat.</hi>]</l>   
   
<l>          "Mouf all drawd up in a pucker,</l> 
<l>             Ho! meleety, ho! [<hi rend="italic">Repeat.</hi>]</l> 
   
<l>          "Staid so till she went to supper,</l> 
<l>             Ho! meleety, ho!" [<hi rend="italic">Repeat.</hi>]</l>  
</lg> 
<p>The main obstacle which the enthusiastic collector of these 
songs will have to contend against, will be the difficulty of 
thoroughly comprehending the negro dialect.  So peculiar is it, 
that those even who have been familiar with it from their infancy, 
are often times at a loss to interpret such passages as the chorus 
in the last specimen.  No assistance can be expected in such 
matters from the negroes, who, when called upon to repeat slowly 
and distinctly a line which they have just sung, will declare with 
the utmost gravity and solemnity that they have utterly forgotten 
it.  I used to think that they were unwilling to show to the world 
the richest treasures of their literature; but subsequent 
investigations induced me to believe their assertion, and to 
conclude that their intellects could only retain the words when 
assisted by the music.  An intelligent friend to whom I applied, 
suggested, though not without doubt, that the line in question was 
"Oh! my lady, oh!"  And the fact that the ballad is principally 
devoted to the misfortune of the "mistress," gives some countenance 
to this interpretation.  With the line "He full um fote wid cotton 
bale," in the ballad of Gene'l Taylor, I had an amount of trouble 
which will hardly be appreciated by those who see the line in 
print.  I suppose it is hardly necessary to observe that "full um 
fote" means "filled" <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, constructed "his fort." 
</p><p>Autobiographic ballads hold a prominent position among 
Southern melodies; but as they are usually sung exclusively by 
their authors, and are regarded in a measure as private property, 
I do not feel at liberty to transfer any specimens to these pages; 
more especially as at this moment I find it impossible to bring any 
to my recollection.  One melancholy chorus, "The long summer's 
day," I still remember.  Its perpetually recurring sound never 
failed to have a singularly saddening and depressing effect upon 
me, whenever I heard it. 
</p><p>In speaking of this kind of literature the improvisations of 
the negroes must not be forgotten, but as they are usually but a 
running commentary on matters passing under the immediate notice of 
the minstrel, they possess but a local and transitory interest, and 
a single stanza taken at random will suffice.  The reader will 
notice the chorus, which was a favorite one with the improvisator, 
and has served to string many thousand lines together.</p> 
<lg type="citation">   
<l>"Ole Maus William, he gone to legislatur;</l> 
<l>   Ah! chogaloga, chogaloga, chogalog.</l> 
<l>Young Maus John, he done come home from college,</l> 
<l>   Ah! chogaloga, chogaloga, chagolog."</l> 
</lg> 
<p>Those who are familiar with Southern life, and especially 
those who have participated in its hunting delights, will perhaps 
understand, without any explanation, that the foregoing refrain is 
intended to be an imitation of the gobble of the wild turkey.  I 
have performed many orthographical experiments, in order to 
represent the sound more nearly on paper, but without success, and 
I am aware that no words can express the rich, unctuous, guttural 
flow of the line, when uttered in perfect time by a full gang at 
their corn-shucking task.  An approximation to it, however, may be 
made by pronouncing the words rapidly in a deep tone, and at the 
same time violently agitating the body in a perpendicular 
direction.  Having on one or two occasions essayed this mode with 
considerable satisfaction to myself, and no little commendation 
from a few privileged spectators, I am enabled to make this 
assertion with some confidence; but, as the movement is slightly 
fatiguing, and totally devoid of grace, I do not wish to be 
understood as recommending it either to invalids or ladies.  It is, 
however, the only feasible method of "talking turkey," that I have 
yet been able to discover. 
</p><p>I have thus attempted, as calmly and dispassionately as my own 
strong feelings of the importance of the subject will permit, to 
call the public attention to a serious and growing evil, and 
humbly, as becomes me, to point out some means for its removal.  My 
task is finished, and my duty accomplished.  Henceforth, the duty 
of guiding or correcting the public taste in these matters will 
devolve upon other pens than mine.  I have endeavored to discharge 
my obligations to society fearlessly and sincerely.<pb n="79"/>   For 
this courage and sincerity alone I desire credit.  If the 
considerations which I have presented shall have the effect of 
awakening public attention to the subject, I shall be sufficiently 
rewarded; if not, the consciousness of duty performed will sustain 
me.  It is earnestly to be desired that collections of genuine 
plantation songs may be made.  The grateful incense of posterity 
would embalm the memory of him who should hand down to them 
authentic ballads, which another generation may sweep from the face 
of the earth forever.  There are men whose birth or long residence 
in the South, whose knowledge of the negro dialect, and whose taste 
and accomplishments in polite literature, seem to have especially 
fitted them for this service.  For the few and imperfect specimens 
which I have given above, I have been indebted to a treacherous 
memory of a few months' sojourn in Georgia some six or seven years 
ago, when I had no reason to suppose that I should ever feel called 
upon to pen this article.  Could I have foreseen its necessity, the 
collection would have been greatly larger and more perfect.  But 
enough has been presented to show how much may be effected by a 
zealous scholar under more advantageous circumstances.  Upon a 
rough calculation, made with no statistics to refer to, I have 
concluded that there are, at least, thirty thousand slave 
plantations in the United States.  Is it unreasonable to suppose 
that, on each of these plantations, one song may be found of 
undisputed genuineness and excellence?  It will be a proud day for 
America when these thirty thousand songs are collected into several 
volumes, handsomely bound in Turkey morocco, and superbly 
embellished.  Then negro minstrelsy will take its proper place in 
literature; then Ethiopian Serenaders, and Congo Minstrels will 
draw crowded houses at three dollars a seat, and one dollar for a 
promenade ticket; and then&mdash;but long ere that time the hand that 
writes these lines will have mouldered and become dust&mdash;will the 
eye of the student and antiquary linger reverently and delightedly 
over some time-worn manuscript as he deciphers the title "Jim 
Crow," or "Uncle Gabriel?" 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="notes" id="d4"> 
<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">*</seg> <p>I have hitherto given to the word <hi rend="italic">melody</hi> its 
technical signification of <hi rend="italic">a negroic song</hi>.  Of course, here, 
it has its ordinary meaning.</p></note> 
<note id="n2"><seg type="note-symbol">*</seg> <p>Rosa Lee, if such a personage had ever existed, would have 
been known as "Massa Lee's Rosa."  The prevailing ignorance at the 
North on the subject of negro names is remarkable and amusing. 
They seldom have pretty or common appellations, as they impose on 
their owners the office&mdash;on some plantations no sinecure&mdash;of 
dispensing the nomenclature; and as the gentlemen are naturally 
unwilling to confer upon a slave a name borne by some member of the 
family or some friend.  The fruitfulness of the women on the place 
of a planter whom I once visited, had on one occasion exhausted his 
vocabulary.  "Please Massa," said a hand to him one morning before 
he was out of bed, "Clementine sent me to ask you for a name.  She 
had a little boy, last night."  "Call him Last Night," said my 
friend, lazily catching at the last words; and "Last Night" he is, 
and will remain until the shadows of the last night of all shall 
gather round him.  He blacked my boots, and it struck me as a 
curious anomaly to rise in the morning, and call for Last Night. 
It seemed as if, like the last poet out, I was "summoning before me 
the dark past."</p></note> 
<note id="n3"><seg type="note-symbol">*</seg> <p>Hallam's Middle Ages, Chapter ix, Part 1.</p></note> 

</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
