<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="TurVisi"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="TurVisi"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Visions&mdash;A Phantasy</title>
<title type="sort">visions&mdash;a phantasy</title>
<author>Turgenev, Ivan</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>  
<name>Judy Boss</name>  
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>  
<name/>  
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">64</num> kilobytes</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>  
<idno type="ETC">TurVisi</idno>  
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476404</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>  
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Visions&mdash;A Phantasy</title>
<title level="j">The Galaxy</title>
<title type="sort">visions&mdash;a phantasy</title>
<author>Ivan Turgenev</author>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>pp 108-121</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Sheldon &amp; Company</publisher>  
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>  
<date value="1872-07">July 1872</date>  
<idno type="callNo">Print Copy Consulted: AP2 .G2</idno>
</publicationStmt>  
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>The Galaxy, Vol. 14, No. 1, July 1872.</p>
</note>  
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>  
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>  
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>  
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>  
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>  
</encodingDesc>  
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1872">1872</date>
</creation>  
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>  
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>  
<term>Literature in Translation</term>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
</profileDesc>  
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-09">September 1996</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Stephen Ramsay, Electronic Text center</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>  
<text id="d1">  
 
<body id="d2">   
 
<div1 type="chapter" n="1" id="d3"><pb n="108"/><head>  I.</head> 
 
<p>FOR a long time I tried in vain to sleep and kept tossing from side 
to side.  "The devil take all this nonsense of tipping tables," I 
said to myself, "it certainly shakes the nerves."  At length, 
however, drowsiness began to get the upper hand. 
</p><p>Suddenly it seemed to me that a harp-string twanged feebly in 
my chamber.  I lifted my head.  The moon was low in the sky and 
shone full in my face; its light lay like a chalk-mark on the 
carpet.  The strange sound was distinctly repeated.  I raised 
myself on my elbow, my heart beat forcibly.  A minute passed so&mdash; 
another&mdash;then in the distance a cock crowed and a second answered 
him from yet further. 
</p><p>My head fell back on the pillow.  "It comes even to that," I 
thought, "my ears are fairly ringing." 
</p><p>In a moment more I was asleep, or seemed to myself to be 
sleeping.  I had a singular dream.  I thought that I was in my own 
chamber, in my own bed, wide awake.  Suddenly I hear the noise 
again.  I turn.  The moonbeam on the floor begins to waver, to 
rise, to take shape, stands motionless before me like the white 
figure of a woman, transparent as mist. 
</p><p>"Who are you?" I ask, trying to retain my composure. 
</p><p>A voice resembling the soughing of the wind among tree-tops 
answers me.  "It is I&mdash;I&mdash;I.  I am come for you." 
</p><p>"For me?  But who are you?" 
</p><p>"Come at nightfall to the old oak tree at the edge of the 
wood.  I will be there." 
</p><p>I wish to see more closely the features of this mysterious 
being; an involuntary cold shudder runs through me.  I find myself 
not lying, but in a sitting posture on my bed, and where the 
appearance of the figure was there is a long pale moon streak on 
the floor. 
 
 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="2" id="d4"><head>II.</head> 
 
<p>I do not know how the next day passed.  I tried, I remember, 
to read and to work a little, but could accomplish nothing.  Night 
fell; my heart beat as if I had been expecting some one.  I went to 
bed and turned my face to the wall. 
</p><p>"Why did you not come?"  The whisper was plainly audible in 
the chamber. 
</p><p>Hastily I turned my head. 
</p><p>There was the form again, the mysterious being with fixed eyes 
in its rigid countenance, and an expression of woe. 
</p><p>"Come?" I heard faintly. 
</p><p>"I will come," I answered with uncontrollable terror.  The 
shape wavered, sank into itself like a puff of smoke, and once more 
it was only the wan moonlight that lay on the smooth floor. 
 
 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="3" id="d5"><head>III.</head> 
 
<p>I passed the day in excitement.  At tea I nearly emptied a 
bottle of wine, and for a moment stood hesitating at the open door, 
but almost immediately turned back and threw myself upon my couch.  
The blood rushed at fever-speed through my veins. 
</p><p>Again I heard the tones.  I shrank, but would not look up.  
Then suddenly I felt myself tightly clasped by something, and a 
whisper in my very ear, "Come, come, come!"  Trembling with fright 
I stammered, "I will come," and raised myself upright. 
</p><p>The woman's form was bending over the head of my bed.  It 
smiled slightly, and faded, but not before I had been able to 
distinguish the features.  It seemed to me that I had seen them 
before, but where&mdash;when?  It was late when I rose, and I spent 
almost the whole day in the fresh air, went to the old oak tree at 
the edge of the wood and regarded it thoroughly.  Toward evening I 
seated myself beside the open window in my study.  My housekeeper 
brought me a cup of tea, but I was unable to taste it.  All sorts 
of thoughts besieged me, and I asked myself seriously whether I was 
not on the road to madness.  It was just after sunset, and not only 
the sky but the whole atmosphere was suddenly suffused with a 
supernatural 
<pb n="109"/>  
purple light; leaves and weeds, smooth as if 
freshly varnished, were alike motionless, there was something 
singular, almost mysterious, in this absolute quiet, this dazzling 
sharpness of outline, this combination of intense glow with the 
stillness of death itself.  A large gray bird flew noiselessly 
toward me and settled itself upon the balustrade of my balcony.  I 
looked at it and it looked at me, its head sideways, with its 
round, dusky eye.  "Are you sent to remind me?" I thought. 
</p><p>The bird spread its wings and flew away as silently as it had 
come.  I remained at the window for some time longer, but no longer 
absorbed in thought.  I seemed to be under a spell, a gentle but 
irresistible power controlled me, as the boat is swept on by the 
current long before the cataract is in sight.  When I regained 
possession of myself the glow was gone from the sky which had grown 
dark and the enchanted stillness had ceased.  A light breeze had 
sprung up, the moon rode bright and brighter through the blue 
expanse, and in her cold light the trees shimmered, half dusk half 
silver.  My old servant entered with a lamp, but the draught from 
the window extinguished the flame.  I waited no longer, thrust my 
hat on my head and hurried to the old oak tree at the edge of the 
wood. 
 
 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="4" id="d6"><head>IV.</head> 
 
<p>YEARS ago this oak had been struck by lightning; its top was 
shivered and entirely blasted, but the trunk had still vigor for 
coming centuries.  As I approached, a filmy cloud drew over the 
moon; blackest shadow lay under the broad branches.  At first I was 
not conscious of anything unusual, but as I glanced to one side my 
heart throbbed&mdash;a white form was standing motionless by a tall 
sapling between me and the tree.  My hair stood on end, but I 
plucked up courage and walked steadily on. 
</p><p>Yes, it was she, my nightly visitant.  As I drew near, the 
moon shone out in full splendor.  The figure seemed woven, as it 
were, out of a half transparent milky cloud; through the face I 
could see a twig that stirred with the wind, only the hair and the 
eyes were of a somewhat darker coloring, and on one finger of the 
folded hands I saw the faint glimmer of a narrow ring.  I remained 
standing before it and attempted to speak to it, but my voice died 
in my throat; although I was no longer sensible of fear.  Its 
glance was full upon me, the expression was neither of grief nor of 
gladness but a rigid, unlife-like attention.  I waited to be 
addressed, but it kept immovable and silent with its death-like 
stare fixed on me.  Again I felt my self-possession failing. 
</p><p>"I am come," I said at last with a mighty effort.  My voice 
was hollow and unnatural. 
</p><p>"I love you," returned a whisper. 
</p><p>"You love me?" I asked in amazement. 
</p><p>"Give yourself to me," was answered, still in the same tone. 
</p><p>"Give myself to you? You are only a ghost.  You have no bodily 
existence."  A peculiar excitement had taken possession of me.  
"What are you?  Smoke&mdash;air&mdash;vapor?  Give myself up to you?  First 
answer me&mdash;who are you?  Have you lived on earth?  And whence do 
you now come?" 
</p><p>"Give yourself to me.  I will do you no ill.  Say but two 
words: 'take me.'" 
</p><p>I looked at it attentively.  "What is it talking about?" I 
thought.  "What does it all mean?  How can it take me?  Shall I 
venture?" 
</p><p>"Very good," I answered so that it should hear, with 
unexpected loudness indeed as if some one had hit me from behind, 
"Take me!" 
</p><p>I had hardly pronounced the syllables when the form bent 
forward with a smile so that the features trembled for a moment, 
and slowly extended its arms.  I would fain have drawn back but 
found it already out of my power.  It twined about me, my body was 
caught up a yard from the ground, and gently and not too rapidly I 
floated over the still and dewy grass. 
 
 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="5" id="d7"><head>V.</head> 
 
<p>MY head swam.  Involuntarily I closed my eyes, only to open 
them, however, the next moment.  We were still floating upward.  
But the wood was no longer to be seen.  Under us lay a wide plain, 
flecked here and there with shadow.  With horror I realized that we 
had gained a fearful height. 
<pb n="110"/>  
</p><p>"I am lost.  I am in the Devil's clutches," was the thought 
that shot lightning-like through my brain.  Till this moment the 
idea of demoniacal interference in my undertaking had not occurred 
to me.  We were borne constantly farther and took our flight higher 
and higher as it appeared. 
</p><p>"Where are you taking me?" burst from me at length. 
</p><p>"Wherever you will," answered my guide.  It clung closer and 
closer to me, its face almost touching my own.  Yet I could not 
feel the contact. 
</p><p>"Take me back to the earth.  This height makes me giddy. 
</p><p>"Good; only shut your eyes and hold your breath." 
</p><p>I followed this counsel and found myself immediately sinking 
like a stone, the wind fairly whistling through my hair.  When I 
recovered myself we were hovering just above the ground, so that we 
stirred the tops of the grass-blades. 
</p><p>"Put me down," I said, "on my feet.  I have had enough of 
flying.  I am no bird." 
</p><p>"I believed it would be pleasant to you.  We have no other 
power." 
</p><p>"We?  Who are you, then?" 
</p><p>No answer. 
</p><p>"Can't you tell me anything?" 
</p><p>A woful tone, like that which had wakened me the first night 
trembled at my ear.  All this while we had been moving almost 
imperceptibly through the damp night air. 
</p><p>"Set me down," I repeated.  My guide moved quietly aside, and 
I stood upon my feet.  It remained before me again with folded 
hands.  I had regained my composure and looked closely in its face.  
There was the same expression of a melancholy not human. 
</p><p>"Where are we?" I inquired, for I did not recognize my 
surroundings. 
</p><p>"You are far from home, but in a moment you may be there." 
</p><p>"What?  Must I trust myself to you again?" 
</p><p>"I have done you no harm and will let none come to you.  We 
can fly till dawn, not later.  I can take you wherever you may 
desire&mdash;to the ends of the earth.  Resign yourself to me; say once 
more, 'take me.'" 
</p><p>"Then&mdash;'take me.'" 
</p><p>Again she clasped me.  I was lifted from the ground and we 
floated in air. 
 
 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="6" id="d8"><head>VI.</head> 
 
<p>"WHITHER?" she asked me. 
</p><p>"On, straight on." 
</p><p>"But here are trees." 
</p><p>"Rise above them&mdash;only gingerly." 
</p><p>We soared upward and took once more an onward course.  Instead 
of grass, the tops of the trees waved under our feet.  The wood, 
seen from above, presented a singular appearance with its moon-lighted, prickly back.  It was like some monstrous sleeping 
creature, and the low, steady rustling of the leaves, like measured 
breath, carried the resemblance yet farther.  Now and then we 
passed above a little clearing, along whose edge a charmingly 
indented line of shadow lay.  Occasionally we heard below us the 
plaintive cry of a hare, nearer, the hoot of owls rang dolefully; 
the air was full of wild and piny smells; on all sides the 
moonlight lay absolute and cold, and high above our heads shone the 
Pleiades.  Speedily we left the wood behind us, and debouched upon 
a plain through which some stream ran like a ribbon of mist.  We 
flew along its bank over bushes that were still and heavy with 
dampness.  Here the little waves swelled blue on the river, there 
they rose dark and threatening.  Sometimes a fine faint fragrance 
rose in a wonderful fashion, as if the water were taking life and 
soul; it was where the water-lilies unfolded their white petals in 
a maidenly splendor, conscious that no hand could reach them.  The 
whim seized me to gather one of these, and behold me already at the 
surface of the stream.  There was an unpleasant sensation of 
moisture in my face as I broke the tough stem of a great flower.  
We flew from shore to shore like the jack-o'-lanthorns which we saw 
glittering about us, and which we seemed to chase.  At times we hit 
upon whole families of wild ducks squatting in a circle in a hollow 
of the reeds, but they did not stir; it was a chance if one or 
another would drowsily withdraw its head from its wing, look about 
it, and hasten to bury its beak again in the soft down, or make a 
feeble cackling accompanied by a shake of the whole body.  We 
roused a heron; he emerged from a clump of willows, stretched his 
legs, spread his clumsy wings, and flapped heavily away.  Nowhere 
did a fish leap in the water, apparently they also slept.  I had by 
this time become accustomed to the sensation of flying, and even 
<pb n="111"/>  
began to find it agreeable; every one who has dreamed 
of 
flying will understand this.  I began to scrutinize the wonderful 
being who bore me, and whom I had to thank for these incredible 
experiences. 
 
 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="7" id="d9"><head>VII.</head> 
 
<p>IT had the appearance of a woman with delicate, not Russian, 
features.  Grayish-white, nearly transparent, with scarcely 
perceptible shading, it reminded me of an alabaster vase, and once 
more seemed suddenly, strangely familiar to me. 
</p><p>"May I talk to you?" I asked it. 
</p><p>"Speak." 
</p><p>"I see a ring on your finger.  You have lived on earth then, 
have been married?" 
</p><p>I stopped, but there was no answer. 
</p><p>"What is your name, or rather what was your name?" 
</p><p>"You may call me Ellis." 
</p><p>"Ellis!  That is an English name.  Are you an Englishwoman?  
Have you known me before?" 
</p><p>"No." 
</p><p>"Why have you appeared to me then?" 
</p><p>"I love you." 
</p><p>"Well&mdash;does this satisfy you?" 
</p><p>"Yes; we are flying and circling together in pure space." 
</p><p>"Ellis!" I cried, "can it be that you are a lost soul?" 
</p><p>My companion's head sank.  "I do not understand," she 
whispered. 
</p><p>"I conjure you in the name of God"&mdash;I began. 
</p><p>"What are you saying?" she asked, bewildered.  And I fancied 
that the arm that surrounded me like a chill girdle, trembled 
slightly. 
</p><p>"Do not fear, my beloved," Ellis said, "do not fear."  Her 
face turned to mine and approached it closely, and I felt a curious 
sensation on my lips, like the prick of a fine needle. 
 
 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="8" id="d10"><head>VIII.</head> 
 
<p>I LOOKED down.  We had again ascended to a tremendous height 
and were flying over a large city unknown to me, which was built on 
the side of a high hill.  Church-spires rose here and there from 
the dark mass of roofs and gardens, a bridge arched the river-bend, 
everything lay in the deepest stillness, bound in sleep.  Domes and 
crosses glimmered faintly in the peaceful light; a gray-white road 
ran still and straight as an arrow from one end of the city and 
vanished still and straight in the dim distance among the 
monotonous fields. 
</p><p>"What is this city?" I asked. 
</p><p>"&mdash;sow." 
</p><p>"&mdash;sow is in the &mdash;schen province, is it not?" 
</p><p>"Yes." 
</p><p>"Then we are a long way from home." 
</p><p>"For us distance is not." 
</p><p>"Truly?"  A sudden recklessness awoke in me.  Take me to South 
America then." 
</p><p>"To America&mdash;there I cannot.  There it is day." 
</p><p>"So, we are birds o' night then, both of us.  Well, wherever 
you can, only let it be right far." 
</p><p>"Shut your eyes and hold your breath," was Ellis's response, 
and we began to move with the swiftness of a hurricane.  With 
stunning violence the wind rushed past my ears. 
</p><p>We stopped, but the rushing sound did not cease.  On the 
contrary, it increased to a frightful roar, like a thunder peal. 
</p><p>"Now you can open your eyes," Ellis said. 
 
 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="9" id="d11"><head>IX.</head> 
 
<p>I OBEYED.  Good Heavens, where am I? 
</p><p>Over me heavy clouds are hurrying across the sky like a herd 
of angry beasts, and below is another monster, the sea, in wildest 
rage.  White foam is spouting and seething madly, waves tower 
mountain-high and dash themselves with hoarse fury against a 
gigantic, pitch-black reef.  Everywhere the howling of the tempest, 
the icy breath of the revolted elements, the hollow roar of the 
breakers, through which at times I caught something like loud 
lamentations, distant cannon and the peal of bells; ear-splitting 
grate and crunch of the chalk cliffs, the sudden cry of an unseen 
gull, and against the gray horizon the outline of a reeling 
vessel&mdash;everywhere confusion, horror, and death.  My head swam, my 
heart stopped; I closed my eyes anew. 
</p><p>"What is that and where are we?" 
</p><p>"Off the southerly coast of the Isle of Wight, before the 
Blackgang Rock where so many vessels are lost," replied Ellis, this 
time with great distinctness of tone, and, as I fancied, a shade of 
joyous excitement. 
<pb n="112"/>  
</p><p>"Take me away&mdash;away from here&mdash;home." 
</p><p>I shrank into myself and pressed my hands over my eyes.  I 
could feel that we were moving more swiftly than before; already 
the wind ceased to howl and shriek, it blew evenly in my face, but 
so strongly that I could hardly breathe. 
</p><p>"Take your foot-hold," I heard Ellis say. 
</p><p>I made a mighty effort to regain my full consciousness and the 
mastery of myself.  I felt the ground beneath my feet, but could 
hear no more than if everything about me lay dead; only on my own 
temples the veins throbbed violently, unevenly, and with a little 
inward ringing; I was still half fainting.  But I stood up and 
opened my eyes. 
 
 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="10" id="d12"><head>X.</head> 
 
<p>WE were on the bank of my own pond.  Straight before me I 
could see through the slender willow leaves the glassy surface of 
the water, dappled here and there with mist.  On the right was a 
ryefield in tremulous motion, on the left rose steady and dewy-wet 
the trees of my garden.  The morning had already breathed on them.  
In the empty gray sky a pair of narrow clouds hung like smoke-wreaths; they were russet, the first faint hint of dawn had reached 
them, God knows how; the eye could not distinguish as yet any spot 
on the wide horizon where the daylight should break.  The stars 
were gone, there was no stir yet in the magical half-light 
everything drew consciously to its awakening. 
</p><p>"Morning, morning is here!" Ellis murmured in my ear.  
"Farewell till to-morrow." 
</p><p>I turned to her.  She rose, lightly swaying, from the ground, 
and lifted both arms above her head.  Head, arms, and shoulders 
were suddenly suffused with a warm, rosy flesh tint, the fire of 
life glowed in the shadowy eyes, a smile of secret joy played over 
the scarlet lips, it was a charming woman all at once who stood 
before me.  But almost instantly she sank back as if exhausted, and 
melted away like mist. 
</p><p>I stood motionless. 
</p><p>When things about me had reassumed the aspects of ordinary 
life, I looked round and it seemed to me as if the rosy glow that 
had irradiated the form of my shadowy companion had not faded, but 
still permeated the air and surrounded me on every side.  It was 
the Dawn.  An irresistible languor crept over me, and I went to the 
house.  As I was passing the hennery my ear caught the first 
morning gabble of the young geese (of all winged creatures these 
are the earliest to stir) and I saw the jackdaws perched on the 
ridge-pole busily preening their feathers and outlined sharply 
against the milky-colored sky.  From time to time they all flew off 
simultaneously and after a short flight settled again silently in 
their old places.  From the wood at hand sounded twice or thrice 
the shrill cry of a mountain cock that had alighted in the dewy 
grass to seek for berries there.  With a slight chilliness in all 
my limbs I reached my own bed and sank at once into a profound 
sleep. 
 
 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="11" id="d13"><head>XI.</head> 
 
<p>ON the following night as I neared the oak tree, Ellis glided 
to meet me as toward a familiar friend.  Nor did I experience the 
horror of yesterday in her presence, indeed I was almost glad to 
see her; I did not even speculate on what might happen, but only 
desired to be taken to some great distance and to some interesting 
places. 
</p><p>Ellis placed her arm about me and our flight began. 
</p><p>"Fly with me to Italy," I whispered in her ear. 
</p><p>"Where you will, my beloved," answered Ellis in low glad 
tones, and turned her face to mine with a gentle caressing 
movement.  She did not seem so nebulous as on the previous night; 
more substantial, more womanly, she brought to my recollection the 
beautiful creature who had vanished from me in the dawn. 
</p><p>"To-night is a festal night," she continued.  "It falls but 
seldom; when seven times thirteen&mdash;" 
</p><p>Here some words escaped me. 
</p><p>"On this night one can see things hidden at other times." 
</p><p>"Ellis!" I entreated, "who are you then?  Tell me at last!" 
</p><p>But she silently raised one white arm above her head. 
</p><p>There in the dark sky where her finger pointed, a comet 
gleamed like a red ribbon among the stars. 
<pb n="113"/>  
</p><p>"Who am I to understand you?" I began.  "Do you mean that as 
yonder comet wanders forever between stars and planets, you wander 
between men and&mdash;what other race, Ellis?" 
</p><p>Ellis's hand covered my eyes.  It seemed to me as if a thick 
river-fog veiled them. 
</p><p>"To Italy! to Italy!" she whispered.  "This is a festal 
night." 
 
 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="12" id="d14"><head>XII.</head> 
 
<p>THE mist before my face parted; I saw a vast plain under me.  
Already I could perceive by the warm, soft air which fanned my 
cheek that I was no longer in Russia, nor did the plain which I saw 
bear any resemblance to our Russian steppes.  This was a vast dark 
expanse, apparently quite waste, not even grass-grown, with here 
and there pools of stagnant water which shone like the fragments of 
a shattered mirror, and in the far distance I vaguely recognized 
the still unrippled sea.  Large stars shone through the rents of 
the clouds; a ceaseless thousand-voiced, yet not a loud hum, rose 
up on all sides; wonderfully it rang, this pervading, drowsy 
murmur, this night voice of the wilderness. 
</p><p>"The Pontine Marshes," Ellis said.  "Do you hear the frogs?  
Do you smell the sulphur?" 
</p><p>"The Pontine Marshes!"  I repeated with a sudden sense of 
depression.  "Why should we loiter over so dreary a place?  Let us 
hasten to Rome." 
</p><p>"Rome is not far," Ellis replied; "prepare yourself!" 
</p><p>Our flight was along the old road from Latium.  A wild ox 
lazily stretched his rough, shapeless head with its shaggy mane and 
its curving horns up from the sticky slime.  He glared about him 
with his little evil eyes and blew a cloud of steam from his wet 
nostrils, as if he were defiantly conscious of our presence. 
</p><p>"We are nearing Rome!" whispered Ellis.  "Look, look up!"  I 
raised my eyes. 
</p><p>What is the black line there at the world's edge?  Are those 
the high arches of a giant bridge?  What is the stream that flows 
beneath?  Why is it broken here and there?  No, this is no bridge, 
it is an old aqueduct.  Round us lies the sacred Campagna; there in 
the distance are the Alban Hills, the rising moon gilds their 
summits and softens the ridge-line of the acqueduct. 
</p><p>We checked ourselves abruptly, and hung poised in the air 
above a lonely ruin.  No one could have declared its use in other 
times, whether palace, strong-hold or mausoleum.  Black ivy clung 
to it on every side with its fatal embrace; the half-crumbled walls 
yawned like a vengeance below us.  A damp odor of decay rose from 
this heap of thickset stones, from which the coating of plaster had 
long since mouldered away. 
</p><p>"Here!" Ellis said, and stretched out her hand.  "Here!  Say 
three times loudly, the name of the great Roman." 
</p><p>"What will follow?" 
</p><p>"You will see." 
</p><p>I reflected for a moment.  "Divus Caius Julius C&aelig;sar!" 
I shouted suddenly, "Divus Caius Julius C&aelig;sar," I repeated 
yet more loudly, "C&aelig;sar!" 
 
 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="13" id="d15"><head>XIII.</head> 
 
<p>SCARCELY had the echo of my last word died away when I 
perceived&mdash; 
</p><p>I can with difficulty express what it was.  At first I heard 
something like a vague, hardly distinguishable, yet ceaselessly 
repeated clamor of trumpets and applause.  It seemed as if 
somewhere, in an unfathomable depth, at a measureless distance, I 
could hear the tumult of a mighty throng, swelling and subsiding, 
one calling to another with faint cries as in dreams.  The air was 
set in motion; a new kind of darkness brooded over the ruin.  And 
next I seemed to see myriads of shadowy figures, millions of 
shapes, some round like helmets, some long extended spears; in the 
moonlight these spears and helmets glittered like blue sparks, and 
the whole immense troop swarmed ever nearer and nearer, more and 
more distinct grew the stormy sounds.  An impalpable force, strong 
enough to move the world in space, appeared to impel the throng 
onward, but as yet no single form stood plainly out.  Suddenly a 
thrill seemed to pass through the whole great body; it parted in 
monstrous waves and made room&mdash;"C&aelig;sar, C&aelig;sar venit!" 
rang the voices with a sound like a wind-swept forest, and a pale, 
stern face, the eyelids drooping, the forehead crowned with a 
laurel wreath, gradually detached itself to my vision.  The head of 
the Imperator! 
<pb n="114"/>  
</p><p>Language has no words to express the frenzy or horror that I 
felt at this sight.  I believe that I must have died, had this head 
raised its eyes or opened its lips. 
</p><p>"Ellis!" I groaned, "I will not&mdash;I cannot!  Away from this 
awful place, in God's name, away!" 
</p><p>"Faint heart!" she murmured, but our flight began.  The 
brazen, and this time, the thunderous cry of the legions rose 
again, but behind me, and then the darkness swallowed all. 
 
 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="14" id="d16"><head>XIV.</head> 
 
<p>"LOOK round you," said Ellis, "and calm yourself." 
</p><p>I obeyed and the first impression was so exquisite that I gave 
a sigh of relief.  A soft silvery radiance&mdash;or was it mist? 
surrounded me completely.  At first I could distinguish nothing, 
the blue light blinded me, but soon the outlines of beautiful 
mountains and forests began to stand out; a sheet of water lay 
widespread under us with the stars glittering, reflected in its 
depths, and with ripples that caressed, murmuring, the shore.  The 
perfume of orange blossoms stole up to me, and like the wave beats 
and at first blended with them, the fresh, pure tones of a woman's 
voice pulsed the air.  The odor, the sound drew me downward; I let 
myself sink to a stately marble chateau that gleamed white in a 
grove of cypresses.  The singer's voice streamed out of the wide-set windows, the water washed softly under the very walls of the 
building, and just opposite, completely mantled with orange and 
laurel shrubs, flooded with moonlight and tricked with many a fair 
statue and slender column, a round high island rose from the 
water's lap. 
</p><p>"Isola Bella," Ellis told me.  "Lago Maggiore." 
</p><p>An "ah!" was my only answer; I sank lower and lower down.  
Louder and clearer the woman's voice sounded from the chateau; it 
compelled me irresistibly, I must see the face of the singer who 
filled with such strains such a night.  We stopped before one of 
the windows. 
</p><p>In the middle of a room decorated in the Pompeiian manner and 
resembling an old temple more than a modern salon, filled with 
Greek statues, Etruscan vases, exotic flowers, rare and costly 
stuffs, a young girl sat at a piano full in the light of two lamps 
that burned softly overhead in their alabaster vases.  With head 
slightly thrown back and eyes half closed, she sang an Italian 
aria; she sang and smiled, yet at the same time her features wore 
an expression of glowing earnestness, token of the intensest 
enjoyment.  She smiled, and it seemed as if the lusty young Faun of 
Praxiteles smiled back to her out of his corner behind the 
oleanders through the thin smoke that curled up from a brazen 
censer on a tripod.  The beauty was alone.  Entranced by the song, 
by the light, by the splendor and fragrance, and stirred to the 
depth of my soul by the sight of this young, tranquil, perfect 
happiness, I had entirely forgotten my companion and the 
extraordinary wise in which I had become the witness of a life so 
foreign and so far from my own, and I made a movement to step 
within the window and to speak. 
</p><p>Instantly my whole frame thrilled with a heavy electric shock.  
I turned, Ellis's face, spite of its transparency, was gloomy and 
menacing; in her suddenly wide-opened eyes gleamed wrathful fires. 
</p><p>"Come!" she said in an angry whisper, and again I felt 
tempest-speed, darkness, and the sensation of swooning.  But this 
time it was not the cry of the legions but the voice of the 
songstress broken off at a high note that lingered in my ears. 
</p><p>We paused.  The same high note rang steadily, continued, 
though I was conscious of another air and quite a different odor.  
A fresh, invigorating breeze, like one blowing over a large body of 
water, and the smell of hay, smoke, and hemp, met me.  A second 
long-sustained note followed the first, then a third, and with an 
expression so simple, a modulation so familiar and homely, that I 
said to myself on the spot, "That is one of Russia's sons who sings 
a Russian ballad."  In the same instant everything about me grew 
clear. 
 
 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="15" id="d17"><head>XV.</head> 
 
<p>WE found ourselves over a flat shore.  To the left extended 
endlessly, mown meadows with enormous hay-stacks here and there; to 
the right, just as endlessly, spread the glassy surface of a broad 
stream.  A little way out from shore some boats swung duskily at 
their moorings, 
<pb n="115"/>  
their slender masts swaying to and fro like 
idly pointing fingers.  From one of these boats came the tones of 
the pathetic song that had fallen on my ear.  On the same boat a 
fire was burning, whose long red reflection quivered along the 
water like a snake.  Here and there, both on the water and on the 
land, but whether far or near the eye could not determine, was the 
glow of other fires; sometimes low, sometimes brilliantly blazing.  
Countless crickets were chirping away, recalling without resembling 
the noise of the frogs in the Pontine Marshes, and from time to 
time the dim, low-bending heavens rang with the mystical cry of 
some unfamiliar bird. 
</p><p>"We are in Russia?" I asked of Ellis. 
</p><p>"That is the Volga," she replied. 
</p><p>We pursued our way along its shore.  "Why did you snatch me 
away from that glorious spot?" I began.  "What was your grudge?  It 
is not possible that you were jealous?" 
</p><p>Ellis's lips moved a little, and there was a threatening flash 
of her eye.  But her features took directly their usual fixed 
expression. 
</p><p>"Take me home," I demanded. 
</p><p>"Nay, wait," Ellis said, imploringly.  "To-night is a night of 
marvels, and the opportunity will not soon return.  You shall 
witness&mdash;only wait." 
</p><p>And we took sudden flight obliquely across the Volga, low, 
close to the water and darting like two swallows before a storm.  
Under us surged the billows, a cutting wind struck us in powerful 
gusts, and soon the lofty bank began to ride before us.  Steep 
cliffs, jagged with deep ravines appeared, to one of which we drew 
near. 
</p><p>"Shout 'Sarin Nakitschu'!"<ref target="n115">[note]</ref> 
breathed Ellis in my ear. 
</p><p>I thought of the panic that I had experienced at the 
appearance of the Roman legions; I felt, besides, weariness and a 
curious sense of gloom, and I struggled to resist the saying of the 
fatal words, sure beforehand that at their repetition something 
alarming would come to pass.  But half against my will my lips 
unclosed and I called in the same unwilling manner, with a voice 
that was weak and thin "'Sarin Nakitschu'!" 
 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="16" id="d18"><head>XVI.</head> 
 
<p>FOR a moment there was no change, as it had been before the 
Roman ruin, but suddenly a boisterous <hi rend="italic">burlakisches</hi> 
<ref target="n115a">[note]</ref> laughter 
pealed close beside me, and something fell with a splash and began 
to gasp.  I started, there was nothing to be seen, yet the sound 
was echoed loudly from the bank, and in another instant a deafening 
tumult had arisen on every side.  What sound was that mingled in 
this chaos?  Shriek and moan, curses and laughter, laughter 
dominating all, stroke of oar and hatchet, crashing sounds as of 
doors and chests broken in, the creak of cordage and pulleys, the 
stamping of horses, clanking of chains, whistling of the wind, 
hollow roar and crackling of a conflagration, drunken songs, 
confused cries, passionate weeping, despairing entreaties, 
imperious commands, the death-rattle, shrill piping of orders, 
screeches, and the tramp of many feet.  "Strike!  To the yard-arm!  
Overboard with him!  Off with his head!  Good!  Good!  No quarter!"  
It was all perfectly distinct, even to the panting of the 
breathless, hurrying men; yet all around, as far as the eye could 
reach, everything remained the same, the waves rolled gloomily by 
the desolate, bare shore&mdash;that was all. 
</p><p>I turned to Ellis, but she laid her finger on her lips. 
</p><p>"Stepan Timopheitch!  Stepan Timopheitch comes!" rose a shout, 
"our captain, our benefactor, our father!"  And although there was 
nothing visible, I knew that a gigantic form was advancing toward 
me.  "Frolka!  Dog!  Where art thou?" thundered a terrible voice.  
"So!  Fire it on every side and out with your axes!" 
</p><p>I felt the heat of a fire close at hand, and a suffocating 
smell of tar and smoke reached me; at the same time something warm 
like blood sprinkled my hands and face.  Wild laughter burst forth 
on every side. 
</p><p>Consciousness forsook me.  When I came to myself, Ellis and I 
were floating quietly along the familiar edge of my own woodland, 
straight to the old oak tree. 
</p><p>"Do you see that path?" Ellis said to me.  "The one yonder, 
dim in the moonlight, where two young birches let their branches 
hang?  Will you enter it?" 
</p> 
<pb n="116"/>  
<p>I felt myself so shaken, so exhausted, that I could only sigh, 
"Home, home." 
</p><p>"You are at home," answered Ellis. 
</p><p>In fact I stood directly in front of my own door and alone.  
Ellis had vanished.  The watch-dog approached me, snuffed at me 
distrustfully, and ran howling away. 
</p><p>I dragged myself heavily to my bed, threw myself upon it 
without undressing, and slept. 
 
 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="17" id="d19"><head>XVII.</head> 
 
<p>THE next morning I had a headache so severe that I could 
hardly stir, yet my bodily pain was the lightest; regret and 
vexation gnawed at me. 
</p><p>I was extremely annoyed at myself.  "Fainthearted!" I 
ceaselessly repeated.  "Yes, Ellis was right.  Why did I fear?  How 
could I let the chance slip by un-used?  I might have seen 
C&aelig;sar himself&mdash;and was half dead with fright&mdash;must need 
screech and hide my face like a child afraid of a whipping.  Stenka 
Rasin&mdash;that was a different matter.  As a nobleman and a 
landholder&mdash;but even here was it worth while to be so 
panicstricken?  O fainthearted! fainthearted! 
</p><p>"Is it possible that I have only dreamed all this?" I queried 
at last.  I called my housekeeper. 
</p><p>"Marfa, when did I go to bed last night, do you remember?" 
</p><p>"But who can tell that, gracious master?  It must have been 
late enough.  At twilight you left the house and after midnight you 
were running round your chamber.  Decidedly it must have been near 
morning; yes, decidedly.  And so the night before last.  Ah! some 
care must lie heavy on you?" 
</p><p>"Lo!" I thought.  "No doubt about the expedition then.  Well, 
how do I look to-day?" I added aloud. 
</p><p>"How do you look?  Na, let us see.  But weak.  And you are 
pale, gracious little master, not the smallest trace of color in 
your cheeks." 
</p><p>I shrank a little and sent Marfa away. 
</p><p>"This will certainly bring a man to suicide or to madness," I 
said to myself, sitting at my window.  "I must drive it all out of 
my head.  The experiment is too dangerous.  And now I can feel that 
my heart is beating in a very unusual way.  And I remember that 
while I am flying it seems as if some one were sucking the blood 
out of it, something trickling out of it, as in spring the sap runs 
out of a fir tree that is cut.  It is a pity.  And then Ellis&mdash;she 
plays with me as a cat does with a mouse&mdash;it is beyond a question 
that she is evilly inclined.  I will trust myself to her for the 
last time, will see my fill and then&mdash;.  But suppose that she 
really sucks my blood?  That is a horrible idea!  Besides it is 
impossible that motion so rapid should not be hurtful.  I have 
heard that in England it is forbidden by statute to travel more 
than one hundred and twenty versts an hour on the railways." 
</p><p>And so forth.  I reasoned with myself all day, and at nine 
o'clock I stood waiting at the oak. 
 
 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="18" id="d20"><head>XVIII.</head> 
 
<p>THE night was dull and overcast, with a small rain in the air.  
To my amazement there was no one at the tree.  I walked round it 
several times, went to the edge of the wood, returned, peered 
sharply into the shadows; no one to be seen.  For awhile I waited, 
then I called Ellis by name, softly at first, then more and more 
loudly, but she did not make her appearance.  I was disappointed, 
aggrieved even; my earlier suspicions had vanished and only the 
thought remained that my companion might return no more. 
</p><p>"Ellis!  Ellis!  Will you not come to me?" I cried for the 
last time. 
</p><p>A raven that my voice had disturbed from sleep, began to stir 
in the top of a tree near me; he hopped from twig to twig and 
flapped his wings.  Ellis came not. 
</p><p>I turned back to the house with head hanging.  Before me rose 
black the clump of willows at the brink of my pond, and the light 
in my study flickered through the trees; flickered a moment and 
went out, as if it had been the eye of some one watching me who 
found himself discovered.  All of a sudden there was a swift, 
rushing sound behind me as if the air were cloven, and something 
seized and lifted me in very much the same way that a hawk pounces 
upon a chicken.  It was Ellis who had swooped upon me thus.  I felt 
her cheek against mine, her arm encircled my body like a girdle, 
and like a sharply cold breeze her whisper reached  
<pb n="117"/>  
my ear: 
"I am come."  I was startled and delighted at once.  We floated 
along at no great height from the ground. 
</p><p>"Did you not mean to come to-night?" I asked. 
</p><p>"Did you desire me?  Do you love me?  O you are my very own!" 
</p><p>Ellis's words made me a little uncomfortable.  I did not know 
how to reply. 
</p><p>"They kept me," continued she.  "They watched me." 
</p><p>"Who watched you?" 
</p><p>"Where will you go?" asked Ellis, leaving my question 
unanswered, after her usual fashion. 
</p><p>"Take me to Italy, to that lake&mdash;you remember?" 
</p><p>Ellis moved a little away from me and shook her head, denying 
this.  When first I discovered that she had ceased to be 
transparent, and that her face had also gained coloring; a clear, 
rosy tint was spread over the mist white.  I looked into her eyes 
and had an uneasy sensation; in these eyes something seemed to stir 
with the slow, continuous, uncanny motion of a chilled snake that 
is beginning to return to life under the rays of the sun. 
</p><p>"Ellis," I cried, "who are you?  Tell me who are you?" 
</p><p>But Ellis only shrugged her shoulders. 
</p><p>It vexed me.  I resolved to have my revenge upon her, and the 
idea came suddenly to me that she should take me to Paris.  "You 
shall have food enough for your jealousy," I thought.  "Ellis," I 
said aloud, "do great cities terrify you.  Paris, for example?" 
</p><p>"No." 
</p><p>"No?  Not even the places where it is as light as the 
Boulevards are?" 
</p><p>"It is not the light of day." 
</p><p>"That is fortunate.  You shall take me then to the Boulevard 
des Italiens." 
</p><p>Ellis threw one end of her wide flowing sleeve over my head.  
A curious faint smell, like poppies, overpowered me, and everything 
vanished, light, even consciousness itself.  Only the assurance of 
living remained in some way; nor was there anything disagreeable in 
the rest. 
</p><p>By and by the odor was withdrawn abruptly as Ellis freed my 
head from her drapery, and I saw beneath me a mass of buildings 
closely packed together, brilliant light, motion, bustle&mdash;it was 
Paris on which I looked down. 
 
 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="19" id="d21"><head>XIX.</head> 
 
<p>I HAD been in Paris and at once I recognized the place to 
which Ellis had directed our course.  It was the garden of the 
Tuileries, with the old chestnuts, iron gratings, the moat, and the 
brutal Zouaves at their posts.  Past the palace and the church of 
St. Roche, on whose steps the first Napoleon spilled French blood 
for the first time, we stayed our flight high above the Boulevard 
des Italiens where the third Napoleon did the same thing and with 
the same results.  Crowds of people, fops, young and old, workmen, 
women gayly apparelled, thronged the promenades; restaurants, and 
caf&eacute;s were brilliantly lighted, cabs and carriages of every 
sort and appearance rolled along the Boulevard; wherever the eye 
fell it was on glare and bustle.  Yet, strange as it may seem, I 
felt no desire to leave my pure, dim, airy height to mingle with 
these human ant-swarms.  Life was too crowded; it seemed to ascend 
to us, a heavy, heated, redly-glowing vapor, half fragrant, half 
nauseous.  I was still hesitating what to do when suddenly, sharp 
as the clash of steel on steel, the voice of a street lorette 
reached my ear.  Like a poisonous tongue it darted up and stung me.  
I pictured to myself the sharp, greedy, shallow French face with 
vicious eyes, rouged and powdered, hair crimped, and a bouquet of 
artificial flowers, nails like claws, and a deformity of crinoline.  
Then I thought in turn of one of my own countrymen in his foolish 
gambols after this coy damsel.  I imagined him disconcerted to 
boorishness and confused by the rapid nasal speech, wearied by the 
effort to attain the elegant manners of the waiters at Vefour's; 
whispering, fluttering about her, seeking to ingratiate himself; 
and I was seized with disgust.  "No," I thought, "small cause for 
Ellis to be jealous here." 
</p><p>Meanwhile, I became aware that we were sinking, and that Paris 
with all its tumult and confusion, was coming near and nearer. 
</p><p>"Stop!" I said, turning to Ellis.  "Do you not feel a sense of 
feverish oppression here?" 
</p><p>"You yourself bade me bring you hither." 
</p><p>"I have changed my mind.  I recall the wish.  Take me away, 
Ellis, I entreat you.  Look, there is at this moment Prince 
Kulmametow sauntering along the Boulevard, 
<pb n="118"/>  
and there is his 
friend Serge Waraxin who is beckoning with his delicately-gloved 
hand and calling, 'Ivan Stepanitsch! <hi rend="italic">allons souper vite, j'ai 
engag&eacute; Rigolboche en person</hi>.'  Yes, take me away from 
this Mabille, these maisons Dor&eacute;es, from Gandin's and the 
Biches, from the Jockey-club and Figaro, these smooth shaven 
soldier faces and these smooth plastered barracks, from the 
sergents de ville with their goatees, from the domino-players in 
the caf&eacute;s and the players at the Bourse; from the red 
ribbons in coats and palet&ocirc;ts, from M. de Foy the inventor 
'<hi rend="italic">de la sp&eacute;cialit&eacute; de mariage</hi>,' and the 
consultations gratis of Dr. Charles Albert; from liberal journals 
and official brochures, from French comedy and French opera, French 
wit and French witnesses&mdash;away! away!" 
</p><p>"Look down," Ellis answered quietly.  "You are no longer over 
Paris." 
</p><p>I turned my glance to earth.  It was true.  A dusky plain, 
streaked here and there with white highways, seemed to be flying 
from under us, and far behind us on the horizon, like the glare of 
a monstrous conflagration, lay the wide reflection of the lights of 
the world's capital. 
 
 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="20" id="d22"><head>XX.</head> 
 
<p>AGAIN a mist before my eyes; again my senses failed me.  
Finally it cleared. 
</p><p>What is it now below me?  What is that park with its avenues 
of trimmed lindens, its firs standing singly and cut fan-shaped, 
its summer-houses &agrave; la Pompadour, its statues of nymphs and 
satyrs after Bernini's school; its rococo tritons in winding 
artificial lakes which are kept within their borders by a marble 
rim?  Can it be Versailles?  No, Versailles it is not.  A tiny 
palace, also rococo, is half hidden behind a group of gnarled oaks.  
The moon, covered with light clouds, shines but dimly, and a thin 
mist spreads over the ground; the eye cannot distinguish if it is 
moonlight or vapor.  Swans are asleep in the basins, their long 
backs gleam frostily, and glowworms glitter like diamonds in the 
blue shadow at the statues' bases. 
</p><p>"We are at Mannheim," Ellis said; "that is the park of 
Schwetzingen." 
</p><p>"In Germany then," I thought, and listened for some sound.  
Silence; only that from somewhere came the dull murmur of a 
waterfall.  It seemed to be repeating one strain; "Yes, yes, yes; 
forever yes."  All at once I believed that I saw in one of the 
avenues between the formal hedge rows, a cavalier in red-heeled 
shoes with gold-embroidered coat, lace ruffles, and poignard; on 
his arm hung a dame with powdered hair and many-colored silken 
gown.  Wondrous pale faces which I am eager to scrutinize closely, 
but they fade, and only the water murmurs as before. 
</p><p>"Those are ghosts that are walking," Ellis whispered.  
"Yesterday you could have seen many more of them.  But to-day they 
shun mortal eyes.  Let us go on." 
</p><p>We ascended and flew on.  So still and even was our flight, 
that I could hardly persuade myself that it was we who moved, and 
not the earth which sped beneath us.  Dark and billowy, some 
forest-clad mountains came in sight; they loomed up before us, 
swept toward us.  Already they are passed with all their curves, 
their ravines, the glimmering lights in the sleep-bound villages, 
the rushing brooks in the valleys, and before us yet other hills 
swell and sink behind.  We are in the midst of a wilderness. 
</p><p>Mountains and yet more mountains appear: and forests, 
beautiful, old far-reaching.  The night is so clear that I can 
distinguish easily the different trees; the silver firs, with their 
straight, shining stems, are the loveliest of all.  Now and again 
deer peep out of their covert, slender and alert they stand and 
listen, turning their delicate ears from side to side continually.  
On the summit of a naked rock an old castle rears its dismal, 
shattered walls; how peacefully the stars shine above the ruins.  
>From a small dark lake rises like a lamentation the croak of frogs; 
it seems to me that I can hear yet other long-drawn tones, mournful 
as those of an &AElig;olian harp.  It is the land of romance.  The 
same fine, moonlit mist that had charmed me in Schwetzingen covers 
everything here, and the more remote the mountains the thicker 
their veil.  I can count five or six distinct gradations of shadow 
on the mountain-slopes, and over all this soundless variety the 
moon reigns in melancholy splendor.  The wind is soft and light.  
My mood is also equable and gently melancholy. 
</p><p>"Ellis, is not this place dear to you?" 
</p><p>"Nothing is dear to me." 
<pb n="119"/>  
</p><p>"Indeed?  And I&mdash;?" 
</p><p>"You&mdash;yes;" is her tranquil answer. 
</p><p>I fancy that her arm clasps me more closely than before. 
</p><p>"On! on!" she says with a kind of cold exaltation. 
</p><p>"On!" I repeat. 
 
 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="21" id="d23"><head>XXI.</head> 
 
<p>SOME strong, clear, shrill tones make their way to us of a 
sudden; first above, then somewhat in advance of us. 
</p><p>"Those are belated cranes flying northward," Ellis said.  
"Would you like to join them?" 
</p><p>"By all means." 
</p><p>Upwards we swung and in a moment more found ourselves near the 
moving troop. 
</p><p>They were large and beautiful birds, thirteen in all.  Their 
flight was in the shape of a triangle, firm and measured the broad 
wings beat the air.  With head and legs stretched stiff, and 
proudly opposing breasts, they flew on, steadily and so swiftly 
that they made a whistling in the air.  It was a curious sight to 
see this warm, strong life, this unbending will at such a height 
and such a distance from any breathing thing.  Victorious and 
pauseless the cranes parted the air, now and then exchanging a cry 
with their leader; there was something proud and grave, a certain 
unwavering self-reliance in this call, this interchange of speech 
in the cloud confines.  "We will, at any cost, reach our goal," 
they seemed to encourage each other in turn.  The thought rose 
involuntarily that there were but few people in Russia&mdash;yet why 
should I say Russia alone?&mdash;in the whole world there but few who 
would bear a comparison with these birds. 
</p><p>"We are flying in the direction of Russia," breathed Ellis.  
It was not the first time that I had noticed that she seemed to 
divine my thoughts.  "Shall we turn?" 
</p><p>"Yes, let us turn back&mdash;or stay; I have been in Paris, take me 
now to St. Petersburg." 
</p><p>"At once?" 
</p><p>"At once.  But cover my head with your mantle or I shall be 
giddy." 
</p><p>Ellis extended her arm, but before the mist veiled me I felt 
on my lips the prick of a firm, sharp needle. 
 
 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="22" id="d24"><head>XXII.</head> 
 
<p>"AT-TENTION!" fell on my ear with long drawn cry.  "At-tention!" a second answered it from a distance.  "At-tention!" a 
third died away somewhere at the very end of the world.  I aroused 
myself.  A lofty gilded spire met my eye, and I recognized the 
fortress Petropawlowsk. 
</p><p>Pallid, northern night!  Is it really night and not rather a 
wan and sickly day?  I have never liked the nights of St. 
Petersburg, but this time I experienced actual fear; Ellis's 
features vanished utterly; she melted like a morning mist before 
July sun, and I saw distinctly my own body as it floated alone in 
air with all its weight, at a height equal to the Alexander column.  
So here is St. Petersburg.  Yes, not to be mistaken.  These gray, 
broad, empty streets, these whitish-yellow houses, plaster-covered 
and with plaster peeling from them, with their deep-set windows and 
glaring sign-boards, with sheet-iron pent-houses over the entrances 
and the miserable huckster stalls; these gables, inscriptions, 
sentry boxes; the gilded dome of St. Isaac's Church, the gay 
Exchange, overloaded with ornament, the granite walls of the 
fortress; the boats laden with hay or wood, this mingled smell of 
dust, cabbages, tan, and stables; these hostlers apparently 
petrified in their sheepskins before the house-doors, and coachmen 
sound asleep upon their waiting droschkas; yes, it is unmistakably 
our northern Palmyra.  Everything is easily to be recognized; 
everything is unnaturally distinct and clear, and everything lies 
in sombre sleep.  The twilight glow, a kind of swooning redness, is 
not yet gone and will not vanish before morning from the white 
starless heavens; it is reflected in long streaks on the mirror-like surface of the Neva, that hardly seems to move, so quietly its 
cold blue waters flow. 
</p><p>"Let us fly hence?" Ellis implored me. 
</p><p>And without waiting for an answer she bore me over the Neva to 
the Palace yard.  We heard steps and voices under us, and up the 
street came a little party of young fellows with haggard faces, 
still talking over the night's exploits.  "Second Lieutenant 
Stolpatof, No. 7!" called suddenly a half-asleep soldier on watch 
beside a pile of rusty cannon-balls.  Somewhat further, at the open 
window of a house, I saw a girl in a fanciful silken garb, 
<pb n="120"/>  
sleeveless, with a string of pearls in her hair and a cigarette in 
her mouth.  She was completely absorbed in a book, one of the 
productions of our latest Juvenal. 
</p><p>"Let us leave this," I said to Ellis. 
</p><p>An instant later and we were already passing the dismal fir-forests and swamps that environ St. Petersburg.  We held our way 
straight south.  Heaven and earth took momently a darker coloring.  
The unwholesome day, the unwholesome night, the unwholesome city, 
all were left behind. 
 
 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="23" id="d25"><head>XXIII.</head> 
 
<p>OUR flight was less rapid than usual, and I could follow with 
my eye the unfamiliar aspect of the familiar ground as it unrolled 
like an endless panorama before me.  Woods, bushes, fields, 
ravines, streams, occasionally villages and churches; then fields, 
woods, bushes, and ravines again.  I had a feeling of sadness and 
also of indifference, almost of ennui; but not in the least because 
it was Russia over which we were taking our flight.  No; the earth 
in and for itself; this flat plain that spread beneath me, the 
whole planet with its short-lived, helpless races, oppressed with 
poverty, sickness and care, chained to a clod of dust; this rough 
and brittle crust, this sediment upon our planet's fiery core on 
which a mould is grown that we call by the high-sounding title of 
the vegetable world; these men-flies, a hundred times less useful 
than the flies themselves, with their dwellings of clay and the 
fugitive trace of their little monotonous lives, their eternal 
strife against the inevitable and the immutable&mdash;how it shocked me!  
My heart beat heavily in my bosom; the desire to contemplate any 
longer these unmeaning pictures had entirely left me.  Yes, it was 
ennui that I felt, but something sharper than ennui as well.  Not 
once did I feel pity for my fellow-men; every other thought was 
swallowed up in one that I hardly dare to name; it was loathing, 
and the profoundest, deepest loathing of all was&mdash;for myself. 
</p><p>"O cease," breathed Ellis, "cease your thoughts, else it will 
be impossible for me to carry you.  You are too heavy." 
</p><p>"Home!" I cried to her with the tone in which I had summoned 
my driver once when at four o'clock in the morning I took leave of 
the friends at Moskow with whom I had been discussing Russia's 
future.  "Home!" I repeated and closed my eyes. 
 
 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="24" id="d26"><head>XXIV.</head> 
 
<p>IT was not long till I opened them.  Ellis began to nestle 
against me in a singular way; she nearly stifled me.  I turned my 
eyes upon her and the blood curdled in my veins.  Every one will 
understand me who has ever chanced to catch an expression of 
extreme terror on a stranger's face without any suspicion of its 
cause.  A transport of horror drew and distorted Ellis's pallid, 
almost blotted-out features.  Never had I seen the like on mortal 
face; here was a bodiless, nebulous ghost, a shadow, and such 
rigidity of fear! 
</p><p>"Ellis!  What is the matter with you?" I asked at last. 
</p><p>"He!  It is he!"  With difficulty she brought the words forth. 
</p><p>"He?  Who is he?" 
</p><p>"Do not name him, do not name him," Ellis stammered in haste.  
"We must seek some refuge, else it is all at an end, and forever.  
Look!  There!" 
</p><p>I turned my head to the side where her shuddering finger was 
pointing, and was conscious of Something&mdash;something that was indeed 
awful to look upon. 
</p><p>This something was the more frightful that it had no decided 
form.  A clumsy, horrible, dark-yellow Thing, spotted like a 
lizard's belly, neither cloud nor smoke, was crawling snake-like 
over the earth.  Its motion was measured, broad-sweeping from above 
to below and from below to above, like the ill-omened flight of a 
bird of prey that seeks its booty; from time to time it swooped 
upon the earth in an indescribable, hideous way; so the spider 
pounces upon the entrapped fly.  Who or what art thou, grewsome 
Shape?  Under its influence&mdash;I saw and felt this&mdash;everything 
shrivelled and grew rigid.  A foul, pestilential chill spread 
upward.  I felt myself fainting; my sight grew dim, my hair stood 
on end.  It was a Power that was approaching; a power that knows no 
obstacle, that subjects everything to itself; that, blind and 
formless and senseless, sees everything, knows everything, controls 
everything; like a vulture selects its prey, like a snake crushes 
it and licks it with its deadly tongue. 
</p><p>"Ellis, Ellis," I shrieked like a madman, "That is Death!  The 
very, living Death himself!" 
<pb n="121"/>  
</p><p>The lamentable sound that I had heard before escaped Ellis's 
lips, only this time it was far more like a mortal cry of despair; 
and we flew on.  Our flight was singularly and frightfully 
unsteady; Ellis turned over and over in the air, plunged first in 
one direction then in the other, like a partridge that, wounded 
unto death, still endeavors to distract the dog from her brood.  
But in the meanwhile long feelers, like extended arms, or rather 
lassos, had disengaged themselves from the lump, and were 
stretching out after us with groping movements.  And then of a 
sudden it rose into the gigantic shape of a shrouded figure on a 
pale horse.  It grew, filling the Heavens themselves.  More 
agitated, more desperate became Ellis's flight.  "He has seen me&mdash; 
it is all over&mdash;I am lost," I caught in broken whispers.  "O 
miserable that I am!  The opportunity so close!  Life within my 
grasp! and now&mdash;nothingness&mdash;nothingness!" 
</p><p>I could bear it no longer.  Consciousness left me. 
 
 
</p></div1><div1 type="chapter" n="25" id="d27"><head>XXV.</head> 
 
<p>WHEN I came to myself I was lying on my back in the grass, and 
I felt all through my body a dull ache as if after a heavy fall.  
Morning flickered in the sky.  I could clearly distinguish my 
surroundings.  Not far off there was a willow-fringed road that ran 
beside a birch wood.  The region seemed familiar.  I began to 
recall what had happened to me, and could not repress a shudder as 
I remembered the last awful spectacle. 
</p><p>"But what can have terrified Ellis?" I thought.  "Can she be 
subject to his power?  Is she not immortal?  How is it possible 
that she can be doomed to annihilation?" 
</p><p>A low moan sounded not far away.  I hastily turned my head in 
that direction, and there, two paces from me, lay the motionless 
form of a young woman in a white garment, with thick, unbound hair, 
and shoulders bared.  One arm was over head, the other had fallen 
across her bosom, the eyelids were closed, and the tightly-compressed lips were stained slightly with a reddish froth.  Could 
it be Ellis?  But Ellis was a ghost, and it was a real woman whom 
I saw.  I crawled over to her and bent above her.  "Ellis, is it 
you?" I cried.  The eyelids quivered, slowly uplifted; dark, 
expressive eyes fixed themselves earnestly on my face, and in the 
next instant a warm, moist, fragrant mouth was pressed to mine, 
slender, strong arms clasped themselves round my neck, a hot breast 
swelled against my own.  "Farewell! farewell!" the dying voice 
said, and everything disappeared. 
</p><p>I staggered to my feet like a drunken man, passed my hand 
across my forehead, and looked about me.  I found myself on the 
&mdash;schen road, two versts from my country-seat.  Before I reached 
home the sun had risen. 
 
</p><p>For some nights following this I waited, let me confess it, 
not altogether without fear, for the return of my companion, but 
she came no more.  One evening, indeed, I stationed myself at the 
old place, at the old hour, but nothing unusual occurred.  After 
all, I could not regret the end of so singular an intimacy.  I 
pondered much and earnestly upon this inexplicable, 
incomprehensible experience, and had to come to the conclusion that 
not only positive science is in no condition to handle it, but that 
it is out of the range of legends and fairy tales even.  Indeed, 
what was Ellis?  A ghost, a wandering soul, an evil spirit, a 
sylph, a vampire, finally?  At times the fancy possessed me that 
Ellis was in truth a woman whom I had known; and I ransacked my 
memory to find where I might have seen her before.  Hold! a moment 
more and I have it!  But it never came.  Everything grew confused 
like a dream.  Yes, I have thought much and, as is very often the 
case, have arrived at no conclusion.  I could not bring myself to 
ask the advice or the opinion of others, for fear of being taken 
for a madman.  At last I gave up all my gropings; to tell the 
truth, I had other things to think of.  First, the emancipation of 
the serfs and the equal distribution of lands, etc., intervened; 
then the condition of my health, that has received a shock; I have 
pain in my chest, cough much, and suffer from sleeplessness.  I am 
visibly growing thin.  I am as yellow as a mummy.  The doctor 
assures me that I suffer from consumption of the blood, calls my 
complaint by a Greek name, <hi rend="italic">"an&aelig;mie</hi>," and declares that 
I must go to Gastein.</p> 
         <signed>IVAN TURGENIEV.</signed> 
 
</div1> 
<div1 type="notes" id="d28"> 
<note id="n115"><seg type="note-symbol">[note]The</seg> <p>cry of the pirates of the Volga on 
attacking a vessel.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n115a"><seg type="note-symbol">[note]"Burlak"</seg> <p>is the name given to the sailors on 
river craft, especially on the Volga.</p></note> 
</div1> 
 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
