<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="TwaArt1"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="TwaArt1">
	<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">REMINISCENCES OF SOME UNCOMMONPLACE CHARARACTERS I HAVE CHANCED TO
					MEET (Artemus Ward version 1)</title>
<title type="sort">reminiscences of some uncommonplace chararacters i have chanced to meet artemus ward version 1</title>
<author>Twain, Mark, 1835-1910</author>
<respStmt>
					<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
					<name>Steve Railton</name>
					<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
					<name>J. Nathaniel Goldsmith, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
						Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
			<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">8</num> kilobytes</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
				<idno type="ETC">TwaArt1</idno>
				<date value="2001">2001</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2001 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476413</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">REMINISCENCES OF SOME UNCOMMONPLACE CHARARACTERS I HAVE CHANCED TO
							MEET (Artemus Ward version 1)</title>
<title type="sort">reminiscences of some uncommonplace chararacters i have chanced to meet artemus ward version 1</title>
<author>Mark Twain, pseud. Samuel Langhorne Clemens</author>
</titleStmt>
					<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Philadelphia Enquirer</publisher>
						<pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
						<date value="1871-11-21">21 November 1871</date>
						<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:</idno>
</publicationStmt>
					</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a
					word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
				<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to
					aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
			</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
			<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
					<term>prose</term>
					<term>masculine</term>
					<term>Mark Twain</term>
</keywords>
				</textClass>
</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2001-07">July, 2001</date>
				<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
					<name/>
</respStmt>
				<item/>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

	<text id="d1">

		<body id="d2">
			<div1 type="article" id="d3">
				<head>The Philadelphia Inquirer<lb/> 1871: November 21<lb/> MARK TWAIN.<lb/>
					"REMINISCENCES OF SOME UNCOMMONPLACE CHARARACTERS I HAVE CHANCED TO MEET."</head>

				<p>This formed the title of the lecture delivered last evening at the Academy of
					Music, by Mark Twain. Despite the inclemency of the weather the house was
					densely crammed; in fact, it contained the largest audience ever assembled
					within its walls to listen to a lecture.</p>

				<p>Those present had evidently come to hear something good and quaint. In this they
					were not disappointed. Just before the lecturer was introduced, Mrs. Susan
					Galton Kelleher sang "The Skylark" sweetly, and received an encore. Upon the
					conclusion of this the lecturer came forward and said:&mdash;</p>

				<p>Ladies and Gentlemen:&mdash;I ask leave to introduce to you the lecturer of
					the evening, Mr. Clemens, otherwise "Mark Twain," a gentleman whose great
					learning, whose accuracy of language, whose devotion to science, whose
					veneration for the truth and infelicitious harmonies are equal to his high moral
					character and the majesty of his benign presence. I refer in these vague general
					terms to myself. It is not the custom here, I believe, for lecturers to
					introduce themselves to the audience. I thought, perhaps, that it would be
					better for me to do this myself and then I could get in all the facts.</p>

				<p>Well, this lecture is about Artemus Ward. Before I come to the heavier part of my
					subject I will make a little skeleton of it, an outline of the history of Mr.
					Ward. I do not propose to load you down with important information, so that you
					can go home with it. It would weigh you down. I rather illustrate the character
					of the man by personal examination than by didactics.</p>

				<p>When I first started out to make this lecture I thought that I would put three or
					four persons into it, but as I got on I found I could not get them all into the
					compass of one lecture. Consequently, three or four were left out. There is no
					place for John Bunyan, Martin Luther and John Knox. Before I got the lecture
					done I could hardly squeeze Artemus Ward in so small a compass. I tried to get
					all of Artemus in, but I couldn't do it. Well, Artemus was perhaps the greatest
					showman and humorist of the time, but his sudden elevation was due more to his
					matter than to his manner. His speeches in print were flat, but his talk was
					interesting. It was unkind to report him. There was more in his pauses than in
					his words, and so no reporter's pen could do him justice.</p>

				<p>Artemus had one favorite device in his speeches, and that was a sudden transition
					in the statement of sublime facts to a rehearsal of something decidedly
					ridiculous. The climax was spoiled, but the laugh came in, and that was just
					what was needed.</p>

				<p>The wit of Mr. Ward was very lively. He was a great humorist, nevertheless. True,
					he must not be compared with Holmes or Lowell. These men have a refinement that
					he did not possess; but this does not detract from the great showman's ability
					to create fun for the million.</p>

				<p>In his youthful days Artemus Ward hated work. It grieved his heart to see others
					work. He did not like to see convicts work upon a tread-mill. One time he
					proposed to the authorities a plan to run the tread-mill by steam. The father of
					Artemus had a farm, and tried to make the son scare the crows away by firing a
					shot-gun at them; but the boy was too indolent for this; he loaded the gun and
					the father fired it. The report was like a young earthquake.</p>

				<p>Old Mr. Ward was laid up for a week. The senile gentleman, upon recovering, asked
					his son to come forward. He questioned him about the loading of the fowling
					piece &mdash; why he didn't make a report. The precocious youth replied that
					he supposed the gun would make a report for itself, and so it did. That was
					enough.</p>

				<p>Artemus' health was never good. He never had that strong constitution peculiar to
					those hardy men of his native state &mdash; Maine.</p>

				<p>The lecturer traced at length the career of the great showman and lecturer
					through America and England, relating a number of his favorite and amusing
					anecdotes. A beautiful tribute was paid to the deceased humorist.</p>

				<p>Throughout the entire lecture the audience was kept in a continuous roar of
					laughter; and, if Artemus Ward could create fun for the million, as stated by
					the lecturer, the latter certainly demonstrated his ability to do the same.</p>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
