<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="TwaObit"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="TwaObit"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Twain, Mark: Selected Obituaries</title>
<title type="sort">twain, mark selected obituaries</title>
<author>Twain, Mark, 1835-1910</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Stephen Railton, University of Virginia</name> 
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp> 
<name>Stephen Railton, University of Virginia</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>Ann Steinhart University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">190</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">TwaObit</idno> 
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476426</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Illustrations have been included from the print version.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Twain, Mark: Selected Obituaries</title>
<title type="sort">twain, mark selected obituaries</title>
<author>Anonymous</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Compiler</resp> 
<name>Stephen Railton, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Various</publisher> 
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted:</idno>
</publicationStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p> 
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1910">1910</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>Prose, non-fiction</term>
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d3"> 
<head>Mark Twain From the <hi rend="italic">Baltimore Sun</hi><lb/> 
April 22, 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous]</head> 
 
 
<p>It will be many a day before the people of the United States forget 
Mark Twain, the man. Since far back in the 70's he had been one of our 
national celebrities, and perhaps the greatest of the clan, beaming, 
expansive and kindly: a star at all great public feasts; the friend of 
Presidents and millionaires, of archbishops and actors, welcome 
everywhere and always in good humor, a fellow of infinite jest. As the 
years passed his picturesque figure grew more and more familiar and 
lovable. Every town of any pretensions knew him. He was in ceaseless 
motion, making a speech here, taking a degree there, and always dripping 
fun. The news that he was to be present was enough to make a success of 
anything, from a bacchanal of trust magnates to a convocation of 
philologists.</p> 
 
<p>So much for the Mark Twain of banquet hall and popular fancy. He will 
recede slowly, but recede he must, for there is something pitifully 
insubstantial about fame of that sort. The new generation will have its 
own philosophers and its own comedians, and their pressing reality will 
make poor Mark's white dress suit, his chrysanthemum of white hair and 
his eternal cigar grow faint and wavering. Oldsters will chuckle and wag 
their heads when they think of him, but as a living figure he will sink 
into the past. In that human certainty, however, there is no need for 
mourning, for there remains the Mark Twain of literature, in stature 
vastly above the post-prandial wit &mdash; a Mark Twain whose place among the 
immortals is generally conceded &mdash; a Mark Twain whose life work as 
satirist, humorist and philosopher is measured in the estimation of many 
critics by that of Cervantes, Thackeray and Fielding, Aristophanes and 
Moli&#232;re.</p> 
 
<p>There is great temptation, of course, to overestimate a man in the 
presence of his death, but here, we believe, there is no such 
extravagance. More than 15 years ago the true rank of Samuel Langhorne 
Clemens began to impress itself upon the more discerning of his 
contemporaries. It was the late Sir Walter Besant who first made earnest 
and effective protest against the popular tendency to regard him as a 
funny man, and as a funny man only.  To show the absurdity of this 
error, Sir Walter entered upon an elaborate analysis of "Huckleberry 
Finn," as one who might claim expert knowledge of the literary craft and 
its problems, pointing out its marvelously accurate characterizations, 
its vivid picture of a civilization, its Homeric sweep and throb. Here, 
said Sir Walter, was a literary feat of the first magnitude, for a grown 
man had entered into the soul of a boy and looked at the world through 
that boy's eyes. The result, he thought, was the greatest novel ever 
written by an American, if not the greatest ever written in English.</p> 
 
<p>Enthusiasm seemed to color this revolutionary judgment, but it won 
unexpected support and in unexpected places. The English critics, 
strangely enough, were the first to say aye with hearty good will. While 
we were still roaring over "The Jumping Frog," as over some masterpiece 
of empty clowning, they were comparing "A Connecticut Yankee" to "Don 
Quixote" and "Gulliver's Travels," and setting up "A Tramp Abroad" as 
unique and incomparable. The Germans followed the English and the French 
came after, and then at last we Americans began to realize that a truly 
great man was among us &mdash; a man who would be remembered when some of our 
Presidents were forgotten. In 1891, when Yale University made Mr. 
Clemens a doctor of letters, this turn of the tide was publicly marked. 
He lost, after that, nothing of his popular vogue, but he began to gain 
the less noisy but more lasting fame of an artist of world rank. Honors 
came thick and fast, and in 1907, when he was called to Oxford to 
receive the doctorate of that ancient university, England received him 
with almost royal pomp.</p> 
 
<p>The Mark Twain of the last phase was little more than a shadow of the 
Mark Twain who wrote "Huckleberry Finn." There was still abundant 
foolery in him, but his old Rabelaisian joy in the human comedy seemed 
to be gone. He no longer got beneath the surface; he was no longer the 
universal satirist, dealing with broad types and touching the heart as 
well as the midriff. He was old, and maybe a bit weary. But the world 
will not take account of these weak echoes of his former self when it 
comes to reckon his worth, any more than it considers "Lovell the 
Widower" when it judges Thackeray. He must be estimated by his best, as 
Cervantes and the others are estimated. And that best will give delight 
so long as the English of today remains a living tongue.</p> 
 
<p>Let us take leave of him here. The time is not one for elaborate 
essays. He had the great human qualities. Reading him, one came to love 
him, as one loves Chaucer, Fielding and Ben Jonson. For all his war upon 
shams and frauds, there was a vast benevolence in him, a genial 
tolerance, a deep human note. Truly a great man has gone from among 
us.</p> 
  </div1> 
 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d4"> 
<head> 
Chief of American Men of Letters<lb/> 
MARK TWAIN IS DEAD.<lb/> 
From the <hi rend="italic">New York American</hi><lb/> 
April 22, 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous] 
</head> 
 
<p>It would be hard to frame four other words that could carry a message 
of personal bereavement to so many Americans.</p> 
 
<p>He was easily the chief of our writers, by the only valid test. He 
could touch the emotional centre of more lives than any other.</p> 
 
<p>He was curiously and intimately American. No other author has such a 
tang of the soil &mdash; such a flavor of the average national mind.</p> 
 
<p>Europeans who complain that we denied Walt Whitman, misunderstood 
Emerson and have admired only those who write in old world fashions 
should be satisfied at least with Mark Twain, and with our unwavering 
taste for him.</p> 
 
<p>He was our very own, and we gathered him to our hearts.</p> 
 
<p>In ages to come, if historians and archaeologists would know the 
thoughts, the temper, the characteristic psychology of the American of 
the latter half of the nineteenth century, he will need only to read 
"Innocents Abroad," "Tom Sawyer," and "Huckleberry Finn."</p> 
 
<p>Mr. Clemens's books were the transcripts of his life. And that life 
was the kind of life that the average American man of his time has 
believed in and admired.</p> 
 
<p>He was the man that rose from the ranks without envy or 
condescension.</p> 
 
<p>The man that hated dogmas and philosophies and loved a flash of 
intellectual light.</p> 
 
<p>He was the man that cared much to get rich, yet would sweat blood to 
pay his debts.</p> 
 
<p>The man of boundless optimism, who has never troubled to understand 
the great tragedies of nations.</p> 
 
<p>The deepening sense of the twentieth century &mdash; with its feeling that 
there are social problems that cannot be resolved by pleasantries &mdash; has 
somehow left our dear prophet, with all his delicate and tender ironies 
and his merry quips, a little in the rear.</p> 
 
<p>Mark Twain was never fortunate in his polemics. He was not effective 
as the champion of a cause. What he wrote of the Congo was hardly more 
creditable or convincing than his crusade against Mrs. Eddy.</p> 
 
<p>He had no natural acerbity, and consequently no real talent for 
satire.</p> 
 
<p>His genius was full of bravery and brightness and the joy of 
life.</p> 
 
<p>And in the strength of his serene and laughing spirit generations of 
Americans will go forth to do deeds that he himself could never have 
conceived.</p> 
 
</div1> 
 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d5"> 
<head> 
Mark Twain: An American Pioneer in Man's Oldest Art<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">Collier's</hi>, 45<lb/> 
April 30, 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous]
 </head> 
<div2 type="section" id="d6">
<head>Note</head> 
<p>[<hi rend="italic">Both these appreciations appeared in the April 30th edition of 
</hi>Collier's<hi rend="italic">, the first on the magazine's editorial page, the second 
among the articles.</hi>]</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="section" id="d7"> 
<head>Mark Twain</head> 
 
<p>A Gentle Man, if that abused title may have any significance restored 
to it, was Mark Twain.  Good and ill fortune made trial of his finely 
tempered spirit, and success could not spoil nor adversity embitter him. 
His humor might play like summer lightning over the range of human 
weakness, but his compassion was warm and universal as the rain. 
America has lost as much in the man as in the writer.</p> 
 
<p>His pen knew neither fear nor reverence, yet he dipped it tenderly in 
the heart of childhood.  He asked for no exceptions from human hardship, 
and he gave out in the last year of his life, when a great sorrow came 
to him, a glow as of a spirit about to be released.</p> 
 
<p>To call Mark Twain a humorist merely would be to describe Shakespeare 
as a strolling player.  More than one generation has drunk at the 
well-head of his tonic and sane philosophy.</p> 
 
<p>A letter written a few weeks before his death showed him 
notwithstanding his courage to have felt that darkness was closing in. 
He wrote from Bermuda:  "There is not another orphan who is so wrecked, 
so ruined, so forsaken, as I am.  Just a battered old derelict washing 
about the wastes of the great seas, with nobody on the bridge."</p> 
 
<p>America is poorer, in Mr. Clemen's death, by the loss of great and 
gracious personality: there is a void, not to be filled, in the hearts 
of those whom he surrounded with his friendship: but who shall say he 
has not earned that honorable and anxiously awaited resting-place beside 
Jean and Susie and their mother?  He has left to those he loved a 
stainless memory and to this nation a lasting heritage of smiles and 
tears.</p> 
</div2> 
 
<div2 type="section" id="d8"> 
<head>Mark Twain: An American Pioneer in Man's Oldest Art,<lb/> 
Whose Death Is Mourned by the World at Large</head> 
 
<p>Happy among creative artists is the humorist. He strikes as deep into 
life as his neglected brothers who deal in pain and tragedy. But he 
alone carries the people with him. He has their good will, while he 
interprets their life to them. And only at his death is there sadness 
because of him. The more he made them merry, the richer the grief. And 
there are few peoples to-day on the earth where there is no sense of 
loss because MARK TWAIN died.  He would have been seventy-five years old 
in November, and in the final months had suffered much pain.</p> 
 
<p>Printer's devil and Mississippi pilot, cub reporter, pioneer, miner, 
and tramp royal, he knew life, and got the rough stuff out of which to 
spin his cloth of gold from reality itself. He had lived the life from 
nocessity, and then wrote it out.</p> 
 
<p>His sense of the vast innate humor of things was beaten into the 
fiber of him by the Nevada years, when he was territorial secretary in 
the State of Nevada. Those were great days. It was a life that couldn't 
stand the swiftest theatrical show for ten minutes running, but in its 
panting restlessness clamored for poker and drink and dancing and 
barbaric music. Partly a glorified picnic, full of easy nuggets and 
dramatic high lights, and then again tragic and bitter, where sweat and 
blood dropped free.</p> 
 
<p>A Western man has said of him: "A good many people think MARK TWAIN 
is a natural-born humorist. He isn't. He simply described the things he 
saw in Nevada and got the habit."</p> 
 
<p>The tumult of that life never forsook him. It passed into the color 
and startling suddenness of his prose. A land that was unexpected and 
vast, and men who were irreverent, ironic, fearless and sincere, what 
was left to do but hive the honey from those unreaped fields?</p> 
 
<p>In the teeth of the schools, he broke away from the gentle 
reminiscent New England tradition, and struck out a trail as new and 
sure as that of ABRAHAM LINCOLN in statecraft. He was an American in 
every line of his mirthful copy, and it was a generation before the 
critics caught up and knew it for literature, and ANDREW LANG called it 
Homeric.</p> 
 
<p>Leaping into the public eye with the overburdened life of the 
Calaveras frog who couldn't jump because of his meal of buckshot, he hit 
his public yet harder with "Innocents Abroad," which showed the ignorant 
and unashamed American tourist thrust upon the shrines of Europe, who 
forthwith dramatizes his own innocence, and is unaware of COLUMBUS, but 
weeps at the grave of ADAM. He finds the old masters a clutter of paint, 
and refuses to be moved by the cant of embryo Cookists. He turns a 
fresh, untroubled face on Europe, and asks that it make its own 
impression sincerely and first-hand.</p> 
 
<p>That manhandling of the holy places and hoar traditions was the key 
to MARK TWAIN, who faced life itself in the same naked way. Background, 
and atmosphere and the accumulations of convention were nonexistent for 
him, who asked them only to give up their reality and what of vital 
spark they still possessed for him. This trait of the unabashed 
accounted for some of his more doubtful ventures, as when he entered the 
lists of the Shakespeare controversy.</p> 
 
<p>The books which will safeguard his fame longer than a library of 
solemn and academic tomes are "Tom Sawyer" and its greater sequel 
"Huckleberry Finn," wherein the boy in literature is first discovered 
and celebrated. All the Boytowns and Bad Boys since owe a goodly debt to 
the clean sweep of those adventures, where boys whitewash fences, run 
away from home, and exhibit their naked souls in a leaping narrative, 
brimmed with undying laughter, and poignant with such touches of pathos 
as the unsuspected deafness of poor black Jim's little girl. The humor 
of those early books persists through many languages, and is little 
time-worn by forty years.</p> 
 
<p>To see things with fresh eyes, and find nothing sacred simply because 
other men had removed their shoes &mdash; it was in this spirit that he invaded 
the medieval realm, and plucked the comic out of the forest rides of 
knights and ladies and the renowned jousts. He called it "A Yankee at 
the Court of King Arthur." He had already written "The Prince and the 
Pauper" to show that tenderness and reverence could be accorded.</p> 
 
<p>In his "Joan of Arc" he dealt tenderly with the lovely lady in proof 
that he knew how to kneel as well as strike.</p> 
 
<p>He made a few swift sorties into literary criticism in the same 
masculine, forthright way &mdash; notably in his bitter attack on SHELLEY for 
the treatment of the poor drowned HARRIET, and in the paper on COOPER, 
whom he pilloried for committing the 57 varieties of literary sin in 
plot construction and style.</p> 
 
<p>He did not flinch from facing the popular good will, which was so 
largely his, and attacked the national policy of imperialism in his 
eloquent "To Them That Sit in Darkness," and the acrid drive at General 
FUNSTON.  FUNSTON thought of replying, and the author in the pride of 
conscious power, advised him to beware or he would hand him out some 
"man-talk."</p> 
 
<p>He was free of prejudices, and wrote a fine, strong article on the 
Jews, where the unfailing sympathy of it included some earnest 
criticism.</p> 
 
<p>The external facts are few after the early hard years which grounded 
him in reality. The books sold like "The Pilgrim's Progress." His 
lectures were always thronged.</p> 
 
<p>In old age he met a sudden financial loss to himself &mdash; and to those 
who had invested with him in a publishing house of his founding &mdash; by a 
recurrence of energy on the lecture platform, which cleared every cent 
of the indebtedness. He exactly repeated the intrepid and honorable feat 
of WALTER SCOTT, which had enriched literary history for a hundred 
years.</p> 
 
<p>In his later years he was moved by the pathos of life &mdash; the ceaseless 
striving game. His manner was affectionate and playful, and the 
impression of him on the spirit was tender and pathetic. He was simple 
and offhand, never forcing the note. His conversation was made up of 
short, easy words, never aiming at wit or cleverness. Sometimes, too, 
there was music on his lips, as when, on his birthday celebration, he 
spoke of Pier 70, and the laughter and songs of the young men in the 
streets at midnight, no more to be heard.</p> 
 
<p>With the fearless poise of the head of white hair, he would be 
watched by a theater audience more closely than the star actor on the 
stage. Ten thousand men rose to their feet when he entered the open-air 
auditorium at the Yale bicentennial.</p> 
</div2> 
 
 </div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d9"> 
<head> 
Mark Twain<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">Dial</hi>, 48<lb/> 
May 1, 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous]
</head> 
 
<p>The report of Mark Twain's death on the 21st of April, this time not 
"greatly exaggerated" but sadly and literally true, was the occasion of 
heart-felt grief to the entire nation, we may almost say to the whole 
world.  No American of our time was more widely known; no other American 
writer lately among the living had endeared himself to so large and 
cosmopolitan an audience. His life, ended midway in its seventy-fifth 
year, had been rich in human experience, had fulfilled the season of 
mellow fruitfulness, and had given literary expression, as few other 
lives have done, to the qualities of buoyancy and independence so 
characteristic of the typical American temperament. It was also a life 
which, in its personal aspects, revealed the qualities of manliness and 
sympathy, was admirable in its public and private relations, and bore 
with fortitude the buffets of ill-fortune. These are tests of character 
which few men can suffer without some show of weakness; his character 
they served only to sweeten and strengthen.</p> 
 
<p>Mark Twain's life may be divided into two nearly equal parts. Of the 
first part, which includes his boyhood days, his experiences as a 
journeyman printer and editor, his brief career as a Mississippi pilot, 
his briefer career as a Confederate soldier, and his adventures in the 
mining-camps and rude settlements of the West, we have the most vivid of 
records in his books &mdash; in "Tom Sawyer" and "Huckleberry Finn" and 
"Roughing It," and in the countless short stories and sketches which 
began with "The Jumping Frog" and are probably not yet at an end, for 
only a part of the work which he humorously styles his "Autobiography" 
has been put into print. Those early days left him with a fund of 
recollections upon which his drafts were honored &mdash; as was similarly the 
case with Bret Harte &mdash; for long years after the experiences themselves 
had become old (although not unhappy) far off things. As the recorder of 
these phases of pioneer life which he knew at first hand, and of which 
he almost alone has preserved for us the very form and pressure, we are 
immeasurably in his debt. There are few things that we know as well as 
what it was to be a bay in a Missouri country town, a futile skirmisher 
in the early days of the Civil War, and a traveller on the lower 
Mississippi, few bygone types that are as real to us as the miners and 
stage-coach drivers and politicians and barroom loafers of the untutored 
West of the midcentury. The writings in which these things have been 
preserved for us are Mark Twain's best, because they are his raciest and 
least self-conscious.</p> 
 
<p>The next best group of his books is provided by "The Innocents 
Abroad," "A Tramp Abroad," and "Following the Equator," the three 
extensive records of unconventional travel. Yet in these the touch of 
sophistication is seen, and becomes progressively pronounced with each 
succeeding narrative. The second is not as good as the first, and the 
third is distinctly weaker than the second, more artificial in its 
conception and more forced in its humor. When the author transplanted 
himself to the East for permanent residence in the seventies, he 
abandoned the primal sources of his inspiration, and never developed 
others of comparable importance.  Going farther and farther afield in 
search of fresh material, he illustrated anew the myth of Antaeus, and 
displayed a pitiable weakness. Over some of his later flounderings in 
the alien elements of literary criticism, history, and metaphysics, it 
were best discreetly to draw a veil. There was in him a streak of the 
Philistine which might have remained undetected had he "kept to his 
last," but which was sharply revealed when he infringed upon the domain 
of intellectual and scholarly concerns.</p> 
 
<p>The present is not, however, the best occasion for dwelling upon Mark 
Twain's limitations, or for emphasizing the ephemeral character of a 
considerable part of his work. A fair share of that work, at least, 
stands upon a level so high as to be in no danger of passing out of 
sight. Up to an advanced point in his career, he grew steadily in power 
and wisdom; his sympathies became ever broader and deeper, and his 
expressive faculty kept pace with the larger demands that were made upon 
it. From the exuberant journalist who gave us entertainment in his 
earlier days he developed into something like a sage to whom we came to 
look no less for counsel than for amusement. We learned to detect in his 
homely speech the movings of a fine spirit, instinct with the nobler 
promptings of democracy, hating shams and ostentatious vulgarity, gentle 
and gracious in its quieter moods, but fanned to burning indignation 
when facing some monstrous wickedness, such as the corruption of our 
political life, or the dastardly act of the American soldier in the 
Philippines who betrayed his rescuer and shamelessly boasted of the 
shameful deed, or the infamy of the royal libertine who distilled a 
fortune from the blood of the miserable natives of the Congo. Even more 
than by his strictly literary work, he earned our gratitude for the 
brave words which he spoke upon such themes as these, words that cleared 
the moral atmosphere and made us see things in the light of naked 
truth.</p> 
 
<p>Nor should we, in our tribute to the man, forget the silent heroism 
with which he endured loss of fortune in his advancing years, and 
shouldered the burden of a debt incurred by the rascality of his 
associates, a debt for which he was only indirectly responsible, and 
which he might have evaded without serious impairment of his reputation. 
The strenuous labors of the years of lecturing and writing which enabled 
him to discharge in full the shadowy obligations which he then assumed 
took their toll of his vitality, but won for him an esteem higher than 
is ever the reward of the artist alone. This action ranks with the 
similar examples set by Scott and Curtis; it is one of those shining 
deeds that reveal the man himself, in contradistinction to the works by 
which most men of creative genius are contented to be known.</p> 
 
<p>The attitude of criticism toward Mark Twain as a writer has undergone 
a slow but complete change during the past thirty years. From being 
thought of simply as a "funny man," of the kin of Josh Billings and 
Artemus Ward, he has gradually come to be recognized as one of our 
foremost men of letters. This is a profoundly significant transformation 
of opinion, and to account for it fully would require a more careful 
analysis than we here have space to undertake. The recognition has been 
unduly delayed, partly because so much of his output has been utterly 
unworthy of his best self, and partly because his work in its totality 
is of so nondescript a character.  The conventional way to distinction 
in literature is by the fourfold path of the poem, the play, the novel, 
and the essay. Occasionally, also, an historian compels literary 
recognition. But Mark Twain was neither a poet nor a playwright nor an 
historian. he was hardly a novelist, either, for his share in "The 
Gilded Age" does not seriously count, and his work in the form of 
fiction is not remarkable as story-telling pure and simple. If we are to 
group him at all, it must be with the essayists, using that term 
elastically enough to include with him our own Irving, and such 
Englishmen as Swift and Carlyle. We must either do this, of fall back 
upon the <hi rend="italic">sui generis</hi> solution of the problem. Again, if we make a 
subdivision of the essayist class for the humorists alone, we encounter 
the difficulty offered by our obstinate association of that term with 
mere fun-making and the appeal to the lighter interests of human nature. 
Obviously, our subdivision must take yet another step, and admit that, 
on the one hand, there are humorists who make us laugh and have hardly 
any other influence over us, and humorists who are also creative 
artists, and critics of life in the deeper sense, and social 
philosophers whose judgments are of weight and import. If we are to 
classify Mark Twain at all, it must be with the latter distinguished 
company; and his title to kinship with the three English writers above 
mentioned, and even with such alien prototypes as Aristophanes and 
Rabelais and Cervantes, is at least not scornfully to be put aside.</p> 
 
  </div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d10"> 
<head> 
The Death of Mark Twain<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">Chautauquan</hi>, 59<lb/> 
June, 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous] 
</head> 
 
<p>Samuel L. Clemens died on April 21 alter a brief illness at the age 
of seventy-four. A great career, characteristically American, was then 
closed.  Literature, humor, humanitarianism, intellectual and moral 
progress suffered a severe loss.</p> 
 
<p>Many glowing tributes have been paid to Mark Twain since his death by 
men and women of distinction, both of Europe and America. It is a source 
of satisfaction to know that in his rather sad old age, a period of 
personal bereavement and loneliness, Mark Twain knew that he had the 
affection, gratitude, admiration of legions of readers, young and old. 
He had been signally honored by Oxford and English literary and educated 
bodies; he had won ample recognition not as a "mere humorist" but as one 
of the most original and gifted men of letters of America.</p> 
 
<p>Mark Twain's humor, rich and delicious as it was, was always 
fundamentally serious. It was the humor of a deep thinker, a gentle but 
penetrating observer, a philosopher who loved mankind while seeing all 
its weaknesses. Mark Twain was racy, playful, whimsical, extravagant; 
but he was never guilty of deliberate coarseness, and as President Taft 
has remarked, "he never wrote a line that a father could not read to a 
daughter." And this in spite of the fact that he wrote much about rough 
men, hard and primitive conditions, pioneering, the taming of nature and 
the lower elements in man. He was breezy, vital, candid, colloquial, 
"western;" but the civilization, ideas and manners he expressed and 
expounded were essentially sound. Geniality, charity, unselfishness, 
informed and inspired every utterance.</p> 
 
<p>Mark Twain wrote in several styles and contributed to several forms 
of literature. He is best known, perhaps, for his earliest works, 
"Adventures of Tom Sawyer," "Huckleberry Finn," "Jumping Frog," etc., 
and certainly his studies of bay nature are wonderfully acute and 
entertaining. But he wrote excellent history, biography, criticism, 
disguised philosophy. "Is Shakespeare Dead?" the latest work, dealt with 
the controversy over the authorship of the plays attributed to "the 
immortal bard," and was keen and suggestive, if not original or 
scholarly. "Joan of Arc" and "Christian Science" were notable books of 
their respective kinds. It was impossible for Mark Twain not to be 
humorous, stimulating, inimitable, but in his most exuberant and 
irrepressible moments of mirth-making he was no boisterous jester.</p> 
 
<p>The cause of political morality, freedom, human equality, honest 
government, democracy had in him a staunch and courageous defender. He 
took a deep interest in the social and industrial reforms of the day, 
and supported children's theaters, social settlements and similar 
welfare work.  He was an enemy of snobbery, solemn pedantry, cant and 
corruption in public and commercial life. His death removed a salutary, 
beneficent force, a rare, if not unique, personality.</p> 
 
  </div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d11"> 
<head> 
Serious Humorists<lb/> 
</head> 
<div2 type="section" id="d12"> 
<head>Note</head>
<p>[The Nation <hi rend="italic">published two obituary notices, six weeks apart.  The 
second may have been intended as a kind of corrective of the first  &mdash;  at 
least, in the first Stuart Sherman writes that</hi> Innocents Abroad 
<hi rend="italic">seems to be "of appalling seriousness," while in the second Simeon 
Stransky says that he won't "attempt to classify the writer" who could offer 
such an assessment.</hi>]</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="section" id="d13"> 
<head> 
MARK TWAIN<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">Nation</hi>, 90<lb/> 
May 12, 1910<lb/>   
[Stuart P. Sherman]</head> 
 
<div3 type="chapter" id="d14"> 
<head>I.</head> 
 
<p>No American writer has ever enjoyed a more purely democratic 
reputation than Mark Twain.  From village celebrity to international 
renown, he has been advanced stage after stage by popular suffrage.  The 
plain, unbookish burgess holding both his sides at a public lecture has 
helped roar him into eminence.  The freckled, brown-legged pirate who 
finds Tom Sawyer nearer to his business and his bosom than Robinson 
Crusoe has played no negligible part in the campaign.  The vote of a 
retired merchant reading "A Tramp Abroad" in preparation for a European 
holiday told decisively in his favor before the tardy voice of the 
professional critic assented.  When an overwhelming majority of his 
fellow countrymen had established his position, the universities 
recognized the fact, so that one day not long ago, he strolled into the 
Sheldonian Theatre, clad in scarlet, and, after a "very satisfactory 
hurrah" from the audience, was created doctor of letters by the 
University of Oxford.</p> 
 
<p>During the last few years of his life, he attained a still higher 
honor.  It is to be hoped that no one will attempt to distinguish the 
customary "three periods" of his development, because, contrary to 
custom, he was essentially the same in all parts of his career.  One may 
distinguish, however, three aspects of his reputation.  Like a political 
orator making his maiden speech or invading hostile territory, he broke 
through the reserve of his audience with a string of irresistible 
stories.  Handicapped by uproarious laughter, he produced two or three 
pieces of fiction which demanded serious attention; but his leonine head 
had grown gray before he lived down his reputation as a "platform 
humorist."  At his seventieth birthday he obtained a reconsideration of 
his case, and the highest tribunals decided that he indubitably belonged 
in the history of literature, if, indeed, he was not "the foremost 
American man of letters."  After that, national feeling about him 
crystallized rapidly.  He appeared in white flannels in midwinter, 
declaring that white was the only wear for a man with seventy years 
behind him; we were significantly pleased.  After our newspapers had 
made one of their little breaks, he sent word to us that reports of his 
death were "greatly exaggerated."  It was a phrase that we all envied, 
from the President down; we saw that he was not mere literary man  &mdash;  he 
was a public man.  When he died, we abandoned the last reservation.  We 
said with one voice: He was an American.</p> 
 
<p>To the foreign critic this ultimate tribute may seem perplexingly 
cheap and anticlimactic.  That is, of course, due to the mistaken notion 
that we number some four score millions of Americans.  As a matter of 
fact, we number our Americans on our ten fingers; the rest of us are 
merely citizens of the United States.  Any one who will take a little 
pains with the alphabet may become a citizen; to become an American 
demands other talents.  We are more than doubtful about Washington. 
Lowell said that Lincoln was the first American, but he forgot about 
Franklin.  There have been one or two since Lincoln's time.  From 
certain indications, it looks as if Mr. Roosevelt might turn out to be 
an American.  Only the other day he sent us a message to this effect: "I 
know that the American people will agree that I could have acted in no 
other way than I did act."  The American is a man of destiny.  His word 
and deed flow inevitably out of the American character.  On the one 
hand, he does a thing because it is right; on the other hand, the thing 
is right because he does it.  Revising the thought of Henry V, we may 
say, Nice customs curtsy to great Americans.</p> 
</div3> 
<div3 type="chapter" id="d15">  
<head>II.</head> 
 
<p>The point is strikingly illustrated by a story which Mark Twain tells 
on himself in one of the chapters of his autobiography.  It was in 1877, 
before a company including all the leading geniuses of New England, 
banqueting in honor of Whittier's birthday.  When Mark Twain's turn 
came, he rose and entered upon a fictitious "reminiscence."  Out in 
southern California he had knocked at a miner's cabin and announced 
himself as a literary man.  The miner replied with marked ill-humor that 
he had just got rid of three of them, "Mr. Longfellow, Mr. Emerson, Mr. 
Oliver Wendell Holmes  &mdash;  consound the lot. . . . Mr. Emerson was a seedy 
little bit of a chap, red headed; Mr. Holmes was as fat as a balloon; he 
weighed as much as three hundred, and had double chins all the way down 
to his stomach.  Mr.  Longfellow was built like a prizefighter. . . . 
They had been drinking, I could see that."  And so on.</p> 
 
<p>At the words "consound the lot," Twain had expected a peal of 
laughter, but to his amazement "the expression of interest in the faces 
turned to a sort of black frost."  The whole story was a dismal failure; 
it was years before the author recovered from the shame of it.  Speaking 
as a mere reader of Lamb, Jane Austen, Thackeray, O.W. Holmes, I am not 
in the least surprised at the New England frost.  I know very well that 
Congreve or Addison or George Meredith would have agreed with the New 
England geniuses that Mark Twain's reminiscence was a piece of crude, 
heavy, intellectual horse-play  &mdash;  an impudent affront offered to Puritan 
aristocracy by a rough-handed plebian jester from Missouri.  But hear 
Mark Twain thirty years later:</p> 
 
<p><q>I have read it twice, and unless I am an idiot, it hasn't 
a single defect in it from the first word to the last.  It is just as 
good as can be.  It is smart; it is saturated with humor.  There isn't a 
suggestion of coarseness or vulgarity in it anywhere.  What could have 
been the matter with that house? . . . If I had those beloved and 
revered old literary immortals back here . . . I would melt them till 
they'd run all over that stage!</q></p> 
 
<p>In his mellow Indian summer Mark Twain himself grew conscious that he 
had become an American.  He knew, therefore, that the speech was right, 
<hi rend="italic">because he had made it</hi>.  I confess to a doubt whether those "old 
literary immortals" would laugh at it even now; if they would not, as a 
countryman of Lincoln I should be ashamed of them.  The man who cannot 
laugh with Twain must be either better or worse than the "overwhelming 
majority" of his fellow-citizens.  To accept him is almost equivalent to 
accepting the American flag.  When once you have sworn allegiance, you 
may find fault with both for the rest of your life without impeachment 
of your patriotism.  "I paint myriads of heads," cried Walt Whitman, 
"but I paint no head without its nimbus of gold-colored light."  He was 
prophesying the golden mean, which he called the "divine average," and 
which he knew was actually rarer than either extreme.  He was 
prophesying Mark Twain.  "Who are you, indeed," he exclaims, "who would 
talk or sing in America?"  The antiphonal voice replies:</p> 
 
<p><q>I swear I will have each quality of my race in 
myself,<lb/> Talk as you like, he only suits These States whose manners 
favor the audacity and sublime turbulence of The 
States.</q></p> 
 
</div3> 
<div3 type="chapter" id="d16"> 
<head>III.</head> 
 
<p>Humor, it is agreed, consists in contrasts and incongruities, and the 
essence of Mark Twain's most characteristic humor consists in 
contrasting this typical, nimbused American, compacted of golden 
mediocrities, against the world  &mdash;  consists in showing the incongruity 
of the rest of the world with this nimbused American.  It necessarily 
follows that the heights and depths of humor are beyond the reaches of 
Mark Twain's soul.  It necessarily follows that his laughter is burly, 
not fine; broad, nor profound; national, not universal.  When he that 
sitteth in the heavens laughs, he is not constrasting the year 1910 with 
the year 1300, nor the President of the United States with Louis XVI, 
nor the uncrowned sovereigns of Missouri with the serfs of Russia, 
Germany, or England.  The comparison is intolerable  &mdash;  let us mark a 
lowlier difference.  When Puck, in the "Midsummer Night's Dream," 
looking out upon the bewildered lovers exclaims, "Lord, what fools these 
mortals be"; when Titania, waking from magical sleep, murmurs drowsily, 
"Methought I was enamoured of an ass"  &mdash;  the mirth of these subtle 
creatures is kindled by the contrast between sentimental and bottom 
humanity, respectively, and the exquisite manners and passions of 
elfland.  If Twain had written the play, he would have put Puck into 
overalls and Titania into a hoop-skirt.  For he ignored the ethereal 
hunger which troubled the creator of Falstaff, and never entered into 
the secret laughter of the idealist.  Let us descend once more.  It is 
said that the last book Mark Twain read was Carlyle's "French 
Revolution."  I suppose he loved it incidentally for its picturesque and 
savage energy, but mainly because it proclaims that a man's a man for 
all that.  He shows traces both of its style and of its central thought 
in his own work.  But so far as I know, he never shows a trace of its 
heart-searching irony, of that universal world-humor which arises when 
the upstart, red-blooded pageant of time's latest hour is confronted 
with the grim, dim phantasms of eternity  &mdash; </p> 
 
<p><q>Charlemagne sleeps at Salzburg, with truncheon grounded, 
only fable expecting that he will waken.  Charles the Hammer, Pepin 
Bow-legged, where now is their eye of menace, their voice of command? 
Rollo and his shaggy Northmen cover not the Seine with ships, but have 
sailed off on a longer voyage.  The hair of Tow-head (Tete d'etoupes) 
now needs no combing; Iron-cutter (Taillefer) cannot cut a cobweb; 
shrill Fredegonda, shrill Brunhilda, have had out their hot life-scold, 
and lie silent, their hot life-frenzy cooled. . . . They are all gone; 
sunk  &mdash;  down, down with the tumult they made; and the rolling and 
trampling of ever new generations passed over them; and they hear it not 
anymore forever.</q></p> 
 
<p>Carlyle makes ducks and drakes of Charlemagne and shrill Fredegonda, 
but he laughs with a by-gone eternity.  When Whitman asks that 
stupendous question, "Whom have you slaughtered lately, European 
headsman?"  millions of strange shadows tend on him.  He, too, is a 
humorist, and a grave one.  He makes ducks and drakes of the "old 
literary immortals," for he laughs with an eternity to come.  Mark Twain 
cannot be persuaded that we are such stuff as dreams are made of; 
looking neither before nor after, he laughs with the present hour; and 
he cannot stand the comparison.</p> 
</div3> 
<div3 type="chapter" id="d17"> 
<head>IV.</head> 
 
<p>Not by his subtlety, then, nor his depth, nor his elevation, but by 
his understanding and his unflinching assertion of the ordinary self of 
the ordinary American did Mark Twain becomes our "foremost man of 
letters."</p> 
 
<p>He was geographically an American; he knew his land and its idioms at 
first hand  &mdash;  Missouri, the Mississippi River and its banks, Nevada, 
California, New England, New York, the great cities.  It is 
insufficiently recognized that to love one's country intelligently one 
must know its body, as well as its mind.  He had the good fortune to be 
born in the West; so that, of course, he had to go East  &mdash;  otherwise he 
might, instead of becoming an American, have remained a Bostonian or New 
Yorker all his life, and never have learned to love Chicago and San 
Francisco at all.  At various times and places, he was pilot, printer, 
editor, reporter, miner, lecturer, author, and publisher.  But during 
the first half of his life, he went most freely with "powerful 
uneducated persons, and with the young, and with the mothers of 
families."  The books in which he embodies his early experiences  &mdash;  "Tom 
Sawyer," "Roughing It," "Huckleberry Finn"  &mdash;  are almost entirely 
delightful.  They breathe the spirit of eternal boyhood, they are richly 
provincial, they spring out of the fresh earth.  There is a touch of 
melodrama in the first, and more than a touch of farce in the last, but 
in the main, they are as native as a bluff to the Mississippi or a pine 
tree to a red spur of the Rockies.</p> 
 
<p>It is when an American carries his virtues abroad that the lines of 
his character become salient.  Mark Twain was a self made man, of small 
Latin and less Greek, indifferent to abstractions, deficient in 
historical sympathy and imagination, insensitive to delicate social 
differences, content and at home in modern workaday realities.  I 
confess with great apprehension that I do not much care for his books of 
foreign travel.  Like the story told on Whittier's birthday, they are 
"smart and saturated with humor"; but for some almost indefinable reason 
my emotions fail to enter into the spirit of the occasion.  An uneasy 
doubt about the point of view binds my mirth as with a "black frost."  I 
find myself concerned for my fellow-citizen, the author behind the 
books; beneath the surface gayety, the whole affair seems to be of 
appalling seriousness for us both.  Ostensibly light-hearted burlesques 
of the poetical and sentimental volumes of travel, these books are in 
reality an amazingly faithful record of the way Europe and the Orient 
strike the "divine average"  &mdash;  the typical American  &mdash;  the man for whom 
the world was created in 1776.  Wandering through the exhumed Pompeii, 
he peoples its solemn ruins with the American proletariat, and fancies 
that he sees upon the wall of its theatre the placard, "Positively No 
Free List, Except Members of the Press."  He digresses from an account 
of the ascent of Vesuvius to compare the prices of gloves, linen shirts, 
and dress suits in Paris and in Italy.  At length arrived at the summit 
of the mountain, he describes its crater as a "circular ditch"; some of 
the party light their cigars in the fissures; he descends, observing 
that the volcano is a poor affair compared with Kilauea, in the Sandwich 
Islands.  He visits the Parthenon in the night; obviously, the memorable 
feature of the expedition was robbing the vineyards on the way back to 
the ship.  The most famous picture galleries of Europe are hung with 
"celebrated rubbish"; the immemorial Mosque of St. Sophia is the 
"mustiest barn in heathendom"; the Sea of Gallilee is nothing to Lake 
Tahoe. The Mississippi pilot, homely, naive, arrogantly candid, refuses 
to sink his identity in the object contemplated  &mdash;  that, as Corporal Nym 
would have said, is the humor of it.  He is the kind of travelling 
companion that makes you wonder why you went abroad.  He turns the Old 
World into a laughing-stock by shearing it of its storied humanity  &mdash;  
simply because there is nothing in him to respond to the glory that was 
Greece, to the grandeur that was Rome  &mdash;  simply because nothing is 
holier to him than a joke.  He does not throw comic light upon 
counterfeit enthusiasm; he laughs at art, history, and antiquity from 
the point of view of one who is ignorant of them and mightily well 
satisfied with his ignorance.  And, unless I am very much mistaken, the 
"overwhelming majority" of his fellow-citizens  &mdash;  those who made the 
success of "Innocents Abroad" and "A Tramp Abroad"  &mdash;  have laughed with 
him, not at him.  So, too, unquestionably, in the nearly parallel case 
of that bludgeoning burlesque, "A Connecticut Yankee at King Arthur's 
Court."</p> 
</div3> 
<div3 type="chapter" id="d18"> 
<head>V.</head> 
 
<p>What endears a public man to us is what he has in common with  
us  &mdash;  not his occasional supereminences.  It does not damage Franklin to say 
that he was not so graceful as Lord Chesterfield; nor Lincoln to say 
that he was not so handsome as Count D'Orsay; nor Mr. Roosevelt to say 
that one misses in his literary style I know not what that one finds in 
the style of Walter Savage Landor.  Writing from Khartum, the hunter 
tells us that, in consequence of hard service in camp, his pigskin books 
were "stained with blood, sweat, gun oil, dust, and ashes."  We have a 
mystical feeling that this is very appropriate and beautiful  &mdash;  that a 
good American's books ought to be stained with gun oil and ashes.  "Fear 
grace  &mdash;  fear delicatesse," cries the author of "Chants Democratic."  It 
does not damage Mark Twain to say that there was not a drop of the 
aristocrat in his veins.</p> 
 
<p>In politics he was an intelligent but unspeculative democrat, 
committed to the principles of the preamble to the Constitution, 
preserving a tang of Tom Paine's contempt for kings, and not without a 
suggestion of the republican insolence caricatured by Dickens in "Martin 
Chuzzlewit."  I do not think that he gave a "square deal" either to 
Europe or to the Arthurian realm; but within his own territory he had a 
very genuine sense of the brotherhood of man.  He was not, like some 
more exquisite men of letters, a democrat in his study and a snob in his 
drawing room; he was of the people and for the people at all times.  His 
tender regard for the social contract permeated his humor.  It will be 
remembered that Pudd'nhead Wilson earned his nickname and ruined his 
chances as a lawyer for twenty years by an incomprehensible remark about 
a howling dog.  "I wish I owned half of that dog," said Wilson.  "Why?" 
somebody asked.  "Because I would kill my half."  No one understood him 
 &mdash;  the sensitive, symbolic democracy of the expression was too compact 
for their intelligence, and they fell into a delicious discussion of how 
one-half could be killed without injury to the other half.  That, to be 
sure, is also one of the problems of democracy; but Wilson's 
implications were, I believe, both simpler and deeper than that.  In not 
molesting another man's dog, he showed the American reverence for 
property.  The American desire to be moderately well-to-do (Mr. 
Roosevelt's "neither rich nor poor") he indicated by desiring to own 
only half the dog.  In saying that he would kill his half he expressed 
his sacred and inalienable right to dispose of his own property as he 
chose, while at the same time he recognized his neighbor's sacred and 
inalienable right to let his half of the property howl.  Indeed, I am 
not sure that he did not recognize that the dog itself had a certain 
property right in howling.</p> 
 
<p>With almost every qualification for a successful political career, 
Mark Twain could never have aspired to the Presidency, for he was not a 
regular attendant at church  &mdash;  a short-coming, by the way, which 
interfered seriously with Mr. Taft's campaign till his former pastor 
testified in the public prints that once at a church social taken the 
part of a fairy.  In religion, Twain appeared to be a mugwump, or, more 
classically speaking, an agnostic over whom had fallen the shadow of 
Robert Ingersoll of pious memory.  The irreligion of that generation is 
touched with a raw, philistine rationalism, but is thoroughly honest. 
Like all Americans, the author of "Tom Sawyer" received his religious 
culture in the Sunday-school, but stumbled over the book of Genesis and 
kindred difficulties, and was "emancipated."  The loss of faith which, 
in proper conditions, is a terrible bereavement, was to him a blessed 
relief; when the God of the Sunday-school and camp meeting ceases to 
terrify, he ordinarily becomes a deadly bore.  Having never known the 
magnificent poetry of faith, he never knew the magnificent melancholy of 
unbelief.  His experience was typical, however, and his very 
unspirituality was social.  In his examination of Christian Science, he 
admitted that every man is entitled to his own favorite brand of 
insanity, and insisted that he himself was an insane as anybody.  That 
was enough to assure most of us that he was sound on "all 
essentials."</p> 
 
<p>"Be good and you will be lonesome" is, I suppose, one of Mark Twain's 
most widely quoted utterances on moral topics.  At first thought one may 
wonder why this apparently Bohemian apothegm should have taken such hold 
upon the heart of a nation which above all things else adores virtue. 
But the difficulty disappears the instant one reflects that these seven 
words express as in a nutshell precisely the kind and temper of virtue 
that the nation adores.  Like Wilson's observation on the dog, the 
saying is cryptic and requires explication.  Twain tells us in his 
autobiography that when he was a boy his mother always allowed about 
thirty per cent. on what he said for "embroidery" and so "struck his 
average."  The saying means, as I take it, first of all, don't lose your 
sense of humor as those do who become infatuated with their own 
particular hobbies in goodness.  Calculate to keep about in the middle 
of the road, but make allowances for all reasonable shades of difference 
in taste and opinion.  Don't be too good or you will find yourself in a 
barren and uninfluential minority of one.  In America, whatever is not 
social is not virtue.  When he put his shoulder under the debts of his 
bankrupt publishing house, the author of the apothegm himself explained 
its meaning.  Natively fond of strong language, careless of 
peccadilloes, tolerant of all human frailties though he was  &mdash;  
kin-making touches of nature  &mdash;  his feet were "mortised and tenoned" in 
domestic rectitude and common morality.</p> 
 
<p>"We cannot live always on the cold heights of the sublime  &mdash;  the thin 
air stifles"  &mdash;  I have forgotten who said it.  We cannot flush always 
with the high ardor of the signers of the Declaration, nor remain at the 
level of the address at Gettysburg, nor cry continually, "O Beautiful! 
My country!"  Yet, in the long dull interspaces between these sacred 
moments we need someone to remind us that we are a nation.  For in the 
dead vast and middle of the years insidious foes are stirring  &mdash;  anaemic 
refinements, cosmopolian decadencies, the egotistic and usurping pride 
of great cities, the cold sickening of the heart at the reiterated 
exposures of giant fraud and corruption.  When our countrymen migrate 
because we have no kings or castles, we are thankful to anyone who can 
tell us what we can count on.  When they complain that our soil lacks 
the humanity essential to great literature, we are grateful even for the 
firing of a national joke heard round the world.  And when Mark Twain, 
robust, big-hearted, gifted with the divine power to use words, makes us 
all laugh together, builds true romances with prairie fire and Western 
clay, and shows us that we are at one on all the main points, we feel 
that he has been appointed by Providence to see to it that the precious 
ordinary self of the Republic shall suffer no harm.</p> 
 
<p>STUART P. SHERMAN.<lb/> 
Urbana, Ill.</p> 
</div3> 
</div2> 
 
<div2 type="section" id="d19"> 
<head> 
Serious Humorists<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">Nation</hi>, 90<lb/> 
June 30, 1910<lb/>   
[Simeon Stransky]
</head> 
 
<p>Mark Twain's memory may suffer from a certain paradoxical habit we 
have fallen into when passing judgment on the illustrious dead. The 
habit consists in picking out for particular commendation in the man 
what one least expects. If the world thinks of him as a great humorist, 
the point to make is that at bottom he was really a philosopher. If his 
shafts struck at everybody and everything, the thing to say is that he 
liked best what he hit hardest. If one of his books sold five thousand 
copies, the attempt is made to base his future fame on the comparatively 
unknown book. The motive behind such reasoning is commendable enough. It 
is the desire not to judge superficially, the desire to get at the 
"real" man behind the mask which all of us, according to tradition, wear 
in life. It is a praiseworthy purpose, but, in the hands of the 
unskilled or the careless, a perilous one. And worse than either is the 
intellectual snob whose business it is constitutionally to disagree with 
the obvious. We make no attempt to classify the writer who has declared 
that Mark Twain, when he wrote "Innocents Abroad," was terribly in 
earnest; that he set out to satirize and was funny only because he could 
not help it. This represents the extreme of a tendency that is made 
manifest on every side, to turn Mark Twain into everything but what he 
was &mdash; a great compeller of laughter.</p> 
 
<p>One gets dreadfully weary of such topsy-turvy criticism. There are 
times when one would like to believe that Napoleon will be remembered 
because he won Austerlitz and Marengo, and not because he divided up 
France into a vast number of small peasant holdings; that Lincoln was a 
great man because he signed the Proclamation of Emancipation and wrote 
the Gettysburg address, and not because he kept his temper under 
criticism and in adversity. It is well to try to pierce behind the veil 
of Maya, but no amount of analysis can do away with the popularly 
accepted beliefs that mothers are primarily maternal, that actresses' 
talents lie in the direction of the stage, that joyful people laugh, and 
that people who make wry faces are either pessimists or dyspeptics. What 
use is there in trying to make a serious book out of the "Innocents 
Abroad," when we know well that the Mark Twain who wrote it was 
primarily a fun-maker? For ourselves, we confess that we have been 
unable to find any grave purpose in the "Jumping Frog of Calaveras." We 
recall the Hawaiian stranger whom Mark Twain kissed for his mother's 
sake before robbing him of his small change. We recall the horse he rode 
in Honolulu; it had many fine points, and our traveller hung his hat 
upon one of them. We recall that other horse behind which he went 
driving one Sunday with the lady of his choice; it was a milk-dealer's 
horse on week-days, and it persisted in travelling diagonally across the 
street and stopping before every gate. These adventures are easy to 
recall, but the hidden serious purpose within them remains hidden from 
us.</p> 
 
<p>The serious element in Mark Twain the man and the writer, it would, 
of course, be futile to deny. His hatred of sham, his hatred of cruelty, 
his hatred of oppression, appear in the "Innocents Abroad," as they do 
in his "Connecticut Yankee" and in his bitter assaults on the Christian 
Scientists and the American missionaries in China of the Boxer days. But 
to say that Mark Twain was a great humorist because he was an intensely 
serious man is not true, whatever truth there may be in the formula that 
humorists are humorists because they are men of sorrow. We would reverse 
the formula.  We would say that humorists are often sad because they are 
humorists, and that from much laughing the rebound must necessarily be 
towards much grief. If it is commonly asserted that the humorist laughs 
because of the incongruities of life, it is, nevertheless, just as sale 
to maintain that the man born to laughter will be driven by his 
instincts to search for incongruities.  There was no fundamental 
pessimism in Mark Twain. As Mr. Howells brings out in his chapter of 
reminiscences in the last <hi rend="italic">Harper's</hi>, Mr. Clemens had the soul of 
untamed boyishness. He was boyish in his exuberance of manner, in his 
taste for extraordinary clothes, and in his glee at earning a great deal 
of money:</p> 
 

<p><q>The postals [announcing his share of the daily profits from the 
"Gilded Age"] used to come about dinner-time, and Clemens would read 
them aloud to us in wild triumph. $150 &mdash; $200 &mdash; $300, were the gay figures 
which they bore, and which he flaunted in the air before he sat down at 
table, or rose from it to brandish, and then, flinging his napkin into 
his chair, walked up and down to exult in.</q></p>  
 
<p>One thing there was in Mark Twain that was not apparently boyish or 
simple. Mr. Howells asserts positively that in his later years Twain 
believed neither in the Christian theology, in God, nor in 
immortality:</p> 
 
 
<p><q>All his expressions to me were of a courageous renunciation of any 
hope of living again, or elsewhere seeing those he had lost. He suffered 
terribly in their loss, and he was not fool enough to try ignoring his 
grief. He knew that for that there were but two medicines; that it would 
wear itself out with the years, and that meanwhile there was nothing for 
it but those respites in which the mourner forgets himself in slumber. I 
remember that in a black hour of my own when I was called down to see 
him, as he thought from sleep, he said, with an infinite, an exquisite 
compassion, "Oh, did I wake you, did I <hi rend="italic">wake</hi> you?" Nothing more, 
but the look, the voice, were everything; and while I live they cannot 
pass from my sense.</q></p>  
 
<p>Here at last we have the disillusion that is said to dwell in the 
innermost soul of the great humorist. But here, too, we seem to feel 
that the gray vision of the future was with him not a cause, but a 
result. When the buoyant soul sinks back upon itself it is apt to feel 
the riddle of life very keenly indeed.</p> </div2>
 
</div1> 
 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d20"> 
<head> Boston Globe Obituary<lb/> Editorial Points </head> 
 
<div2 type="section" id="d21"> 
<head> From <hi rend="italic">Boston Daily Globe</hi><lb/> 
22 April 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous]</head> 
 
<p>People who speak of Mark Twain simply as a humorist do not realize 
how much serious work he did. He had securely held the place of the 
leading American author for a long time before he died.</p> 
</div2> 

<div2 type="section" id="d22"> 
<head> 
From <hi rend="italic">Boston Daily Globe</hi><lb/> 
23 April 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous]</head> 
 
<p>Mark Twain was a natural, not a forced nor a mere verbal, humorist. 
He was also the first great American humorist and had no professional 
predecessor among all the laugh-provokers of the ages. As American as 
Franklin or Lincoln, his worth, like theirs, is appreciated in every 
land where newspapers or books are read.</p> 
 
<p>The court jester of old had special privileges, and the obsequious 
and sycophantic paid homage to his drolleries in order to curry favor 
with the king.</p> 
 
<p>The jester of democracy has no license from a sovereign to "blow on 
whom he pleases," nor no patent whereby flatterers are led to pay homage 
to his mirth. The fierce light that beats upon a throne is moonlight 
unto sunlight compared with the glaring lime blaze in which the words of 
the popular humorist are tested.</p> 
 
<p>To withstand that test was a great achievement. Mark Twain did that, 
and more; for he never allowed his fun to fossilize into the somber 
platitudes with which some old men try to erase their reputations as 
laugh-makers and obtain standing in the ranks of the solemnly wise. He 
was a humorist to the last. His title was never disputed.</p> 
 
<p>Endowed with abilities which might have enabled him to win fame as an 
interpreter of life by means of serious language, he chose for his 
patroness the comic muse, and was loyal to his choice. Hence he was 
always young and his humor always new, "Age could not wither, nor custom 
stale, his infinite variety." Even amid sorrows that in most cases wring 
the heart till not even hope is left in it, he showered his mellow 
sunshine on the world.</p> 
 
<p>American in humor, he was also American in character. Beneath his 
radiant playfulness with kings and worlds and deep philosophies the 
chords of life responded to the touch of high ideals. His written and 
his spoken words were entertainers of peoples, presidents and princes. 
His unrecorded prayers were deeds.</p> 
 
<p>He had experience of life in all its salient ways yet found no road, 
however rough, that did not have a flower along its marge. Whether 
wanderer, wage earner, author, capitalist or insolvent, or wearing an 
academic crown, whether lover, husband, father, neighbor or friend, his 
private joys or griefs could not raise a bar between him and the 
millions that were gladdened by his smile.</p> 
 
<p>Nor can death come between him and the world. He will live in his works.</p> 
 
<p>Hail, then, thou weaver of lingering laughter, but not farewell.</p> 
 </div2>
</div1> 
 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d23"> 
<head> 
New York Times Obituary<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi><lb/> 
22 April 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous]
</head> 
 
<p>That Samuel L. Clemens was the greatest American humorist of his age 
nobody will deny. Posterity will be left to decide his relative 
position, in letters among the humorists of English literature. It is 
certain that his contemporary fame abroad was equal to his fame at home. 
All Europe recognized his genius, the English people appreciated him at 
his own worth, and the University of Oxford honored him with a degree. 
His writings commanded a higher price in the market than those of any 
other contemporary whose career was solely devoted to literature. His 
"public" was of enormous extent. From "The Jumping Frog" to the "Diary 
of Adam" everything that came from his pen was eagerly read and heartily 
enjoyed by multitudes.</p> 
 
<p>Much that he wrote has already been forgotten, inevitably, and in 
spite of definitive editions and the admirably practical management of 
his business in the later years of his career. But nearly all that 
Jonathan Swift, Fielding, Sterne, and Smollett wrote has been forgotten, 
though their fame, resting on a few books, still lives. Artemus Ward, 
Mark Twain's greatest predecessor as a National jester, is now little 
more than a name. Nasby belonged exclusively to the Reconstruction 
period. For any American humorous writer it would be fit to compare with 
Mark Twain we must go back to Washington Irving. But the author of 
Knickerbocker's ironical history and the Sleepy Hollow legend did not 
surpass, in those denotements of the humorous genius, the author of "The 
Adventures of a Cub Pilot on the Mississippi" and "Huckleberry Finn." 
Indeed, it is hard to say that Irving ever surpassed Clemens. Without 
belittling the first great American prose writer we are compelled to 
doubt if posterity will name him in the same breath with the humorist 
who has just passed away.</p> 
 
<p>The "Innocents Abroad" and "A Tramp Abroad" are likely to be 
remembered among the great travel books of all time. Full of the 
audacity, the wild exaggeration and violent contrasts which distinguish 
the National humor, they are equally remarkable as the veracious record 
of fresh impressions on a fertile and responsive mind. Mr. Clemens's 
more serious works, such as "The Prince and the Pauper," an incursion 
into the field of historical romance. "A Yankee at the Court of King 
Arthur," and "Joan of Arc," have been read by multitudes with great 
delight. He has been quoted in common conversation oftener, perhaps, 
than any of his fellow-countrymen, including Benjamin Franklin and 
Lincoln. He has been honored by misquo tations, too, and the humorous 
sayings of the ancients have been attributed to him, though he never 
borrowed. His wit was his own, and so was his extravagance, and his 
powers of observation never failed him.</p> 
 
<p>We have called him the greatest American humorist. We may leave it an 
open question whether he was not also the greatest American writer of 
fiction. The creator of Mulberry Sellers and Pudd'nhead Wilson, the 
inventor of that Southwestern feud in "Huckleberry Finn," which, with 
all its wildly imaginative details, is still infused with rare pathos, 
has certainly an undying vitality. An emotional and quite unconventional 
sort of man, Clemens was, whose early life was a hard struggle for 
existence. He obtained his education where he could get it. Presumably 
his faults were as large as his merits. Intellectually he was of 
Herculean proportions. His death will be mourned, everywhere, and smiles 
will break through the tears as remembrance of the man's rich gift to 
his era comes to the mourners' minds. However his work may be judged by 
impartial and unprejudiced generations h is fame is imperishable.</p> 
 
  </div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d24"> 
<head> 
Washington Post Obituary<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">The Washington Post</hi><lb/> 
22 April 1910<lb/> 
[anonymous]</head> 
 
<div2 type="section" id="d25"> 
<head>Mark Twain</head> 
 
<p>When Samuel L. Clemens, better known as "Mark Twain," died, there 
passed from this earth a world character.  Wherever civilization was, or 
touched, his pen name, at least, was known.  Mr. George Kennan found in 
an obscure Siberian village but two things to remind him of home, one a 
sackful of peanuts and the other a dilapidated copy of "Innocents 
Abroad."  The natives knew not how to eat the peanuts, nor, in all 
probability, had one of them the slightest inkling as to the contents of 
the book.  Yet both were there, sure precursors of a better day to 
come.</p> 
 
<p>When one of its members dies, Congress adjourns in respect to his 
memory.  Now that Mark Twain has passed away, the world will pause, if 
but for a moment, in its work and its play, its planning, and 
money-getting, to honor him.  For thousands that never saw him felt that 
they knew him, and knew that they loved him.</p> 
 
<p>It has been said of Emerson that he lifted the idols of men from 
their pedestals and placed them reverently on the ground.  Mark simply 
poked the false gods in the ribs, and they came down of their own 
accord.  Herein lay his great work, that he mercifully emancipated human 
beings from their foolish prejudices and their foolish selves.  His was 
not the cynicism of the world weary, but the sturdy irreverence of 
eternal boyhood, and his never failed to embody something of his nature 
in his works, or to impart it to his readers.</p> 
 
<p>We have wept with him at the grave of Adam, gathered "dornics" with 
him in the Holy Land; we have stayed behind and counted the silver 
spoons with the czar after this irrepressible had passed, and then 
hastened on to join him again.  We have traveled up and down the 
Mississippi with him and Huck Finn and the Dolphin, and together have 
hobnobbed with real royalty.  We have studied art with him, to much 
profit, and have come to know, under his guidance, that a good way to 
tell a St. Sebastian was by the arrows, and that it was a man's 
inalienable right to say that Turner's pirate ship looked like a "yellow 
tomcat expiring in a platter of stewed tomatoes," if we thought that 
way.</p> 
 
<p>Now that he has gone, the world will seemingly go on as before.  None 
knew this better than he.  And yet there is a conviction that the scheme 
of life has altered for his having lived here; that sham and pretense 
can never rule as fully again as before he came laughing along.</p> 
 
<p>And how sympathetic he was!  How quickly responsive to the true 
nobility in man, wherever found, in high or low!  He never ridiculed the 
right.</p> 
 
<p>Tears and smiles for loved Mark Twain!  Tears for the passing of such 
a soul from earth, and smiles in memory of his work and in the assurance 
of his happiness beyond.</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="section" id="d26"> 
<head>From <hi rend="italic">The Washington Post</hi><lb/> 
24 April 1910<lb/> 
by Arthur B. Krock</head> 
<lg type="poem"> 
 
<l>Old Innocence has gone abroad, and</l> 
<l>the sea is wide between.</l> 
<l>I saw his hand on the misty wheel as</l> 
<l>he steered for the darkened main</l> 
<l>He took his laugh and he took his pipe</l> 
<l>and the place where his heart had been,</l> 
<l>And he crossed the bar where the</l> 
<l>waters gulped the plumb-line below mark twain.</l> 
<lb/> 
<l>He has steered from the flats and the</l> 
<l>yellow flood that he knows from bed to brim</l> 
<l>To the greenish gush of a stranger</l> 
<l>wave that bathes every western star;</l> 
<l>And "Give me my glasses," I heard him</l> 
<l>say &mdash; for the night of the Lord is dim,</l> 
<l>And the salt spray blinds and the</l> 
<l>wind cuts cold as the ship sails out by the bar.</l> 
<lb/> 
<l>'Twould be time to weep for the good</l> 
<l>gray head that is lost in the driving spray</l> 
<l>Were there not in my study window</l> 
<l>here a boy with a puckered lip,</l> 
<l>And he whistles shrill, "Oh, Buff'lo</l> 
<l>gals, ain't you coming out today?"</l> 
<l>So I know tonight that he'll join</l> 
<l>Huck Finn and go for a pirate trip.</l> 
<lb/> 
<l>'Twould be time to weep for the one</l> 
<l>that's gone did the boys he loved go, too,</l> 
<l>But Tom and Joe and Sid and Huck</l> 
<l>on my study shelves I spy.</l> 
<l>So good-by, Mark Twain, may you steer</l> 
<l>far out; may the wheel at your helm turn true;</l> 
<l>And I'll keep Tom straight while</l> 
<l>you're off to sea, and for Huck &mdash; well, Mark, I'll try.</l> 
</lg> </div2>
 
</div1> 
 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d27"> 
<head> 
Atlanta Constitution Obituary<lb/> 
Mark Twain, World-Servant<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">The Atlanta Constitution</hi><lb/> 
23 April 1910<lb/> 
[anonymous]</head> 
 
<p>Wherever in the civilized world men and women and little children 
love humor and cleanliness, sweetness and far-reaching insight into the 
universal human nature, there will be genuine mourning over the death of 
Samuel L. Clemens, "Mark Twain."</p> 
 
<p>Rarely has a single figure in our national literature towered with 
such unique and encyclopaedic distinction.</p> 
 
<p>Mark Twain was a profound humorist, paradoxical as that statement may 
seem. The shallow merry-maker with his quips and turns and cheaper puns 
and mental acrobatics is common enough in the story of the race. His is 
a faculty that barely scratches the surface of flesh and blood, lacking 
the ability to penetrate to the quick and touch the eternal humanities, 
whether they reside in the soul of the hyper-cultured product of the 
twentieth century, or the semi-barbarian on the outposts of 
civilization.</p> 
 
<p>And this is what Mark Twain accomplished, not spasmodically, but 
virtually in all of his written endeavors. Always he sounded the human 
note. It is true that his brand of humor and humorous philosophy, 
sometimes deftly screening a far more serious motif, was reflective of 
American thought and genius. But in America is a conglomerate of the 
world's races, an amalgam from the melting pot of the best and the worst 
of the old world, so that what civilization reverenced in Twain was the 
glimpse he gave it of a blend of itself, as typified in the universal 
Ame rican.</p> 
 
<p>Little of the slap-stick of the element of boisterousness may be 
found in the work of this master craftsman. Drollery there is in 
abundance, quaintness and charm of style abides alway, sustained and 
intuitive humor is never far absent from his elbow. But the cruder and 
more vulgar effects he avoided instinctively, bringing to bear a 
delicacy tempered with breadth.</p> 
 
<p>Men loved him not only for the fact that he gave them cheer, but that 
his quiet and unfailing courage gave them inspiration. He mocked at 
adversity.  He combatted desolation with a smile and a sweet 
stubbornness that never acknowledged itself beaten.</p> 
 
<p>He was truly a world-servant. And world-wide is the wish that his 
sleep may be sound, broken only by those pleasant dreams that lighten 
the face of slumbering innocence with chastened smiles.</p> 
 
 
  </div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d28"> 
<head> 
Chicago Tribune Obituary<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">The Chicago Daily Tribune</hi><lb/> 
23 April 1910<lb/> 
[anonymous]</head> 
 
<p>Alas, we can no longer smile at Mark Twain's celebrated jest that the 
reports of his death were "greatly exaggerated." The laugh which for 
years has rippled around the world has vanished, and on the coffin of 
Samuel Langhorne Clemens the nations of earth drop the tribute of their 
tears.</p> 
 
<p>But it is not a mere farceur who lies dead today. He was, indeed, a 
fellow of infinite jest and peculiar fancy; he was far more than that, 
however. He could engulf the whole world in a tidal wave of mirth with 
"The Jumping Frog" or "Innocents Abroad," but he could also move it to 
tears with the pathos of "The Prince and the Pauper," sting it with the 
irony of "The Man Who Corrupted Hadleyburg," or freeze its blood with 
horror at the recitals of what Leopold did in the Congo. It is true that 
there are coarse pages in "Roughing It," but where is there a more 
lifelike transcript from nature than "Tom Sawyer" or "Huckleberry Finn"? 
So if the cap and bells lie on his bier today there are plenty of 
tributes to his other qualities to cover them from sight.</p> 
 
<p>Yet it was as a humorist that he made his reputation and place in 
American letters, and as such he will no doubt earn recognition from 
those who come to study his achievements in the future. Taste in humor 
is at best a fickle thing and not to be too much depended upon. Our 
fathers roared at Josh Billings, Artemus Ward, Seba Smith, and Orpheus 
C. Kerr, as they and we older ones have done at Mark Twain's earlier 
efforts. It remains to be seen whether our children will find "Innocents 
Abroad" and "Roughing It" as funny as we thought they were. Ward's humor 
in its evanescent qualities was much like the best of Twain, but the 
present gen eration finds "The Genial Showman" a trifle caviar 
today.</p> 
 
<p>It is not unlikely that Twain realized the shifting and uncertain 
reputation represented by the jester's bauble, and that this accounts 
for the varied nature of his literary output. It is certain that he set 
much more store on what he produced after 1885 than on what he had done 
before, and that he not only dropped the Gargantuan laugh of "Roughing 
It" in his later years, but also confined much of his more glancing wit 
to after dinner speeches and interviews.</p> 
 
<p>This would account in part for his attempts at more serious things, 
his excursion into biography in his "Joan of Arc," his satires of 
society and politics, his melodrama, his identification with various 
civic movements, his delineation of boy life in "Tom Sawyer" and its 
companion book, and his serious effort at producing real fictional 
character divorced entirely from the element of laughter.</p> 
 
<p>At any rate, his humor, however it may be criticised, had a strongly 
native quality. This was as true of his finer as of his coarser moods. 
Andrew Lang speaks of Twain's "almost Mephistophelean coolness, an 
unwearying search after the comic side of serious subjects, after the 
mean possibilities of the sublime &mdash; these with a native sense of 
incongruities and a glorious vein of exaggeration, make up his stock in 
trade." This was certainly true of his earlier days, but for years he 
had substituted for those qualities a fine vein of wit which denies 
analysis as a soap bubble would. With added years his sense of humor 
took on, as he might have said, a more serious phase, and he used it 
valiantly as a weapon against corruption, hypocrisy, and cant.</p> 
 
<p>Well, whatever he was &mdash; jester, satirist, novelist, or reformer &mdash; he 
has left us the memory of many pleasant hours, of a life honestly and 
usefully lived, and of a most genial and lovable personality.</p> 
 
 
 </div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d29"> 
<head> 
L.A. Times Obituary<lb/> 
Fresh May His Memory Remain.<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">The Los Angeles Times</hi><lb/> 
22 April 1910<lb/> 
[anonymous]</head> 
 
<p>It is the decree of fate that Mark Twain return to heaven, which 
loaned the genial humorist to us for a while. He has been intellectual 
sunshine to mankind for two generations.</p> 
 
<p rend="center">[OMITTED BIOGRAPHICAL SUMMARY]</p> 
 
<p>Samuel Clemens was a humorist philosopher. He was as philosophic as 
humorous. His humor dealt almost altogether with human nature in its 
everyday phases, almost in its crude forms. He was born one of the 
common people, and all his life in its formative stages was spent among 
plain people. There is not much edge to his jests. They play around 
their objects as sheet lightning flashes over the sky. They do not harm 
and never cause any fear of danger. But they go to the very heart of 
human nature and sound the depths of its aspirations, aims and hopes. In 
jest Clemens is what Dickens is in story. There is not the pathos that 
marks the "death of Little Nell," but there is as rollicking fun as in 
any page of the "Pickwick Papers."</p> 
 
<p>Sam Clemens was an American humorist. His jokes are broad and 
good-natured. There is the crudeness in them that is found in western 
life of fifty years ago. They lack the subtlety of French wit. The 
delicate touch, the fine point, are not there. It is the thought of the 
plain and of the mining camp whose color is caught, whose essence is 
distilled &mdash; not that of the drawing-room or boulevard.</p> 
 
<p>But that the soul of human nature is preserved in the writings of 
Mark Twain is shown by their popularity wherever the language is 
understood.  A Boston audience laughed at Twain with as much glee as one 
in San Francisco. London enjoyed "Pudd'nhead Wilson" as much as New 
York.  And in the Antipodes the Melbourne Larrigans laughed with as much 
abandon as a New York Bowery boy or a San Francisco hoodlum.  Moreover, 
Oxford undergraduates and university dons sat side by side with the 
common herd of the street, "Townies" and "Gownies" both in uproar at 
Mark Twain's quaint jokes.</p> 
 
 </div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d30"> 
<head> 
New York World Obituary<lb/> 
MARK TWAIN ABROAD 
From <hi rend="italic">The New York World</hi><lb/> 
23 April 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous]</head> 
 
<p>The obituary notices and appreciations of Mark Twain in the foreign 
press reveal an acquaintance with his works and an intimate interest in 
his personality such as it has been the lot of no other American author 
to deserve.  From the comments of the London journals it might be 
inferred that a favorite British writer had passed away, and the 
tributes of the German and Italian press indicate that his death is 
regarded in Berlin and Rome as a personal loss.</p> 
 
<p>One reason of his popularity abroad is no doubt to be found in the 
universality of the sense of humor which makes what New York is laughing 
at laughable in Berlin.  But it was chiefly the very difference of the 
quality of Mark Twain's humor from anything in British or Continental 
humorous literature which appealed to foreign readers.  It was as 
characteristically American as negro minstrelsy or the Wild West, as Dan 
Rice or Buffalo Bill, and was relished accordingly by virtue of its 
originality and contrast.</p> 
 
<p>Foreign and particularly British appreciation of our native authors 
has been largely based on their distinctive Americanism, as in the case 
of Cooper, Walt Whitman, and Bret Harte.  These attributes Mark Twain 
possessed in an unusual degree.  His was a new and racy humor, more 
representatively American than that of any of his predecessors and with 
its roots deeper down in national traits  &mdash;  more democratic than 
Lowell's and with more substance than that of his early contemporaries. 
To Europe, Mark Twain was the American character personified  &mdash;  Uncle 
Sam himself in his drollest mood masking a shrewd philosophy with a 
jest.</p> 
 
 </div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d31"> 
<head> 
Richmond Times Dispatch Obituary<lb/> 
A GREAT MAN PASSES<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">The [Richmond] Times Dispatch</hi><lb/> 
22 April 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous]</head> 
 
 
<p>Few men in American will be more missed than Mark Twain, for few were 
more beloved.  Whether in the Middle West, where he was born and where 
he learned so much of men, or in the East where he lived in later life, 
Mr.  Clemens was easily the first of American characters.  Everybody 
knew of him and everybody felt that he was one writer whose touch was 
true and whose merit was real.</p> 
 
<p>Mark Twain did what perhaps no other American has ever done.  He 
created a distinct literature.  There had been humorists before his time 
 &mdash;  humorists who had been as original, as daring, and as successful as 
was he, but there had been no man who had succeeded in making literature 
of humor.  All that went before was fragmentary, scattered and 
disjointed.  He made it consistent, definite and wholesome.</p> 
 
<p>It is hard to dissect the qualities which made Mark Twain such a 
great literary figure. There is humor in all he wrote, except when he 
turned aside to write a children's story or a serious essay, but there 
is much more.  He had all the powers of description which belong to one 
who knew the Book of Nature.  He loved the river, he loved the fields, 
and he loved those flats along the Mississippi where the sun shines on 
the yellow sand and the cranes drowsily flap their dipping wings.  He 
had, too, a deep knowledge of human nature, which made every character 
that he described live and breathe.  He knew men, through and 
through.</p> 
 
<p>Mark Twain the man was as interesting as Mark Twain the humorist. 
The two, in fact, were one.  The books were the man, and the man was the 
books.  His view of life was sunny, and his nature was kindly, even when 
he had business adversity and domestic trouble which would have broken a 
less fortunate spirit.  He had too a high sense of honor and a deep 
integrity and a true charity, shown in a hundred little incidents which 
he always tried to conceal.  In 1895 the firm of C. L. Webster and 
Company, in which he was interested as a silent partner, went to the 
wall.  Mr.  Clemens was not responsible for the company's debts, but he 
assumed them, and began a long, exhausting lecture tour in order that he 
might return to the firm's creditors every dollar he thought himself in 
honor bound to pay.  He did it, though his health was bad and the season 
was most oppressive.  Then again, on the last day before he was finally 
stricken down, he signed his check for $6,000 to build a library in his 
town.</p> 
 
<p>These things showed the man, and for these things the American people 
loved him.  They knew he was true and generous and kindly, and they saw 
in him that spirit which makes a man great.</p> 
 
 </div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d32"> 
<head> 
St. Louis Post-Dispatch Obituary Notice<lb/> 
From the <hi rend="italic">St. Louis Post-Dispatch</hi><lb/> 
22 April 1910<lb/> 
[Clark McAdams?]</head> 
 
<p>[<hi rend="italic">Instead of an editorial, the paper reprinted this poem, which 
seems to have been written by Clark McAdams, who edited the column "Just 
a Minute," although that isn't explicitly established by the layout of 
the feature.  It isn't a very good poem, but it's worth reading.  Of all 
the accounts of where the name "Mark Twain" came from, this is the only 
one I know that acknowledges that the leadsmen who sang out "Mark Twain" 
on the Mississippi when Clemens was a pilot would all have been African 
American.</hi>]</p> 
 
<p rend="center">JUST A MINUTE.<lb/> 
Written for the Post-Dispatch by Clark McAdams.</p><lb/> 
 
 
 <p rend="center">"Mark Twain"<lb/> 
Reprinted From the Post-Dispatch of October, 
1908.</p> 
 
<lg type="poem"> 
 
 <head>I.</head><lb/> 
 
<l>"<q>MARK TWAIN</q>!"  What a monument  &mdash;  better than 
granite!</l> 
<l>Better than marble, though master should plan it.</l> 
<l>Simply "Mark Twain!" for a life of endeavor,</l> 
<l>Sung on the old Mississippi forever!</l> 
<lb/> </lg>
 
<lg><head>II.</head><lb/> 
<l>His and no other's  &mdash;  and how everlasting!</l> 
<l>Think of the darky his sounding line casting</l> 
<l>Out from the bow till the heavens shall totter,</l> 
<l>Singing "Mark Twain!" for his twelve feet of water.</l> </lg>
 
 <lg><head>III.</head><lb/> 
<l>Years in their trooping and nights in their glory</l> 
<l>Guarding forever that beautiful story  &mdash; </l> 
<l>Silvery bells, and the darkies the while at</l> 
<l>Singing their water-marks up to the pilot.</l> </lg>
 
 <lg><head>IV.</head><lb/> 
<l>Sung when the humorist long has departed  &mdash; </l> 
<l>When the new channels for old ones are charted  &mdash; </l> 
<l>While the great river sings soft as a child could,</l> 
<l>And the sweet echo resounds in the wildwood.</l> </lg>
 
<lg><head>V.</head><lb/> 
<l>Sung when the hoot-owl calls out of the bottom  &mdash; </l> 
<l>When the night air has the crispness of Autumn  &mdash; </l> 
<l>When are new captains in old places whereon</l> 
<l>Stood the old boatman gone boating with Charon.</l></lg> 
 
<lg><head>VI.</head><lb/>  
<l>Sung while the river by blest hills is flowing  &mdash; </l>  
<l>Out where the whistles are moltenly blowing  &mdash; </l> 
<l>Out where the paddles are hollowly pounding,</l>  
<l>And the black stevedore sings at his sounding.</l>  
<lb/>  </lg>

<lg><head>*&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; 
* &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;*</head>
<lb/>  
<l>"Mark Twain!"  What a monument  &mdash;  better than granite!</l>  
<l>Better than marble, though master should plan it.</l> 
<l>Simply "Mark Twain" for a life of endeavor</l> 
<l>Sung on the old Mississippi forever.</l> 
</lg> 
 
</div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d33"> 
<head> 
Some of the Ills That Beset America's Arch Jester<lb/> 
From the <hi rend="italic">Colorado Springs Gazette</hi><lb/> 
22 April 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous]</head> 
 
<p>[<hi rend="italic">This paper didn't run an editorial reaction to MT's death, but 
besides the Associated Press account of that it did print the following 
(often innacurate) chronology of misfortune.  This may have come from 
the AP as well, but I haven't seen it in any other paper.</hi>]</p> 
 
<p>1860 (about)  &mdash;  Mark Twain loses his money, coat, trousers and boots 
playing cards with General Bunker.</p>  
 
<p>1866  &mdash;  He and a friend named Higgins stake out a silver mining claim 
in Nevada.  Twain goes away to care for a sick friend, and Higgins on 
some errand.  Thus they lose a claim that made millions for others.</p> 
 
<p>1894  &mdash;  His entire fortune is swept away in the failure of the 
publishing house of Charles L.  Webster and company, which had been 
financed mainly by himself.</p> 
 
<p>1896  &mdash;  His eldest, most accomplished daughter, Olivia Susan Clemens, 
dies at the hour of her great promise, while her father is abroad.</p> 
 
<p>1897  &mdash;  Reported destitute and dying in London, friends in America 
raise a purse of $3000 for him, but he refuses to accept it, as his 
"case is not hopeless."</p> 
 
<p>1904  &mdash;  His wife, "who was our life," dies in Florence, Italy, 
whither the family had moved in the hope that the climate would restore 
her to health.</p> 
 
<p>1904  &mdash;  In Florence, Italy, he is forced into a lawsuit with the 
Roybandi-Massaglia, from whom he rented the villa in which his wife had 
just died.</p> 
 
<p>1907  &mdash;  He loses his investment of $22,500 cash by the failure of the 
Plasmon company of America, of which he was president and a 
director.</p> 
 
<p>1907  &mdash;  His boys' masterpieces, "Tom Sawyer" and "Huckleberry Finn," 
withheld from youths by Brooklyn public libraries as unfit for young 
minds.</p> 
 
<p>1907  &mdash;  Comptroller Joy of Detroit, Mich., declares Twain's book, "A 
Double-Barreled Detective Story," is literary junk, unfit for a public 
library.</p> 
 
<p>1907  &mdash;  A Massachusetts public library refuses to give shelf room to 
his book, "Eve's Diary," declaring it "shocking."</p> 
 
<p>1909  &mdash;  Illinois prevents his taking an active part in the Congo, a 
crusade which he had long prosecuted with his pen, with King Leopold of 
Belgium pictured as the arch offender.</p> 
 
<p>1909  &mdash;  A life-time votary of tobacco, a "tobacco heart" reduces him 
to four smokes a day, instead of his continuous performance on pipe and 
cigars.</p> 
 
<p>1909  &mdash;  Failure of the Children's theatre, founded by Mark Twain, in 
New York, and representing one of his life-time ambitions.</p> 
 
<p>1909  &mdash;  His book, "Is Shakespeare Dead?"  charged to be partly 
plagiarized from Greenwood's "The Shakespeare Problem Restated."</p> 
 
<p>1909  &mdash;  Broken down by the strain of after-dinner speaking, Mark 
Twain is forced to leave New York and seek quiet and rest in his 
Connecticut villa.</p> 
 
<p>1909  &mdash;  The humorist and his daughter are involved in a humiliating 
controversy regarding a farm given to his former secretary, Mrs. Ralph 
W. Ashcroft, when Mr. Clemens attaches the property on his daughter's 
advice.</p> 
 
<p>1909  &mdash;  Mrs. Charles E. Wack tries to serve Mrs. Gabrilowitsch, the 
former Miss Clara Clemens, with papers in an alienation suit.</p> 
 
<p>1909  &mdash;  Daughter and son-in-law, Ossip Gabrilowitsch's honeymoon 
voyage postponed by the bridegroom's attack of appendicitis.</p> 
 
<p>1909  &mdash;  Jean Clemens, his daughter, is found drowned in the bathtub 
at their home in Redding, Conn.</p> 
 
</div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d34"> 
<head> 
TWAIN'S DEATH<lb/> 
THIS TIME NOT<lb/> 
"EXAGGERATED"<lb/> 
Whole World Quick to Give<lb/> 
Him High Place in Literature<lb/> 
HIS TRUE AMERICANISM<lb/> 
England Calls Him Most Popular<lb/> 
Writer There Since Dickens<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">The Cleveland News</hi><lb/> 
22 April 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous]</head> 
 
<div2 type="section" id="d35"> 
<head>SPECIAL TO THE NEWS</head> 
 
<p>The world today is voicing the thought which seems simultaneously to 
have come to call, that Samuel Clemens (Mark Twain), the report of whose 
death at his home in Redding, Conn., this time is not "exaggerated," was 
the foremost figure in an important field of literature  &mdash;  the American 
school of letters.</p> 
 
<p>In estimating Mark Twain's place in English literature, the dead 
humorist today is most frequently mentioned in connection with another 
great American, Abraham Lincoln, for the significant reason that both 
expressed so characteristically the pure American spirit.</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="section" id="d36"> 
<head>Europe Praises Twain</head> 
 
<p>From abroad comes praise of Twain.  From England, from France, 
Germany and Italy, the abiding places of the world's great literary 
past, is heard appreciation of the position he has gained, not through 
imitation of the literary wealth that preceeded him, but through writing 
that is distinctly American and completely original.</p> 
 
<p>"The American Chaucer" is the London Evening Standard's estimate of 
Twain's position in literature.</p> 
 
<p>"Like Chaucer," it says, "he kept a hospitable heart for what was 
good and healthy.  Since the death of Charles Dickens no writer of 
English has been so universally read, and at the moment of his death 
Mark Twain was known as only one other living writer was known.  Mark 
Twain and Count Tolstoi are inheritors of world-wide fame."</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="section" id="d37"> 
<head>A German Estimate of Twain</head> 
 
<p>The Berliner Zeitung am Mittag, during a two-column estimate of Mr. 
Clemens' work, expresses the opinion that the American writer was loved 
in Germany more than is the whole body of French and English humorists, 
because his humor turned fundamentally upon serious and earnest 
conceptions of life.  The paper says that the American works most widely 
read in Germany are probably those of Emerson and Mark Twain.</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="section" id="d38"> 
<head>T. R. Had His Books in Africa</head> 
 
<p>"It is with sincere regret that I learned of the death of this great 
American author," said Roosevelt in Paris.  "His position, like that of 
Joel Chandler Harris, was unique not only in American letters, but in 
the literature of the world."</p> 
 
<p>"He was not only a great humorist, but a great philosopher, and his 
writings form one of the assets in America's contribution to the world 
of achievement of which we have a right as a nation to be genuinely 
proud."</p> 
 
<p>In the pigskin library which Mr. Roosevelt carried through the 
jungles of Africa were two of the late author's books, "Huckleberry 
Finn" and "Tom Sawyer," and Mr.  Roosevelt says that he read both of 
them several times and always with the greatest interest.</p> 
 
<p>[<hi rend="italic">The story goes on for 36 more paragraphs, quoting Howells, citing 
anecdotes by and about MT, etc.</hi>]</p> 
 
</div2> 

 </div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d39"> 
<head> 
Democracy in Literature<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">The Denver Post</hi><lb/> 
24 April 1910<lb/> 
[Hugh O'Neill]</head> 
 
<p>Even in dying Samuel Langhorne Clemens bequeathed to the literature 
of the moment a touch of unconscious humor.  Estimates of his career as 
a citizen and of his standing as an author were purveyed simultaneously 
with the announcement of his death.  Most of those <hi rend="italic">critiques</hi>  &mdash;  
that's how they spelt them  &mdash;  were unanimous in the opening sentence, 
"Mark Twain is Dead," and were common in choosing as their final 
peroration, "Hail and Farewell."  It was all very affecting and prompt 
and self-reliant.  As an example of "red hot" writing it was inspiring, 
but as a contribution to literary criticism it was worthless.</p> 
 
<p>For it is not criticism, but the crucible of time, that must test the 
writings of Mark Twain and give them their place in permanent fame, 
while comparing him with the other makers of books, for men or boys, is 
a futile and unenlightening endeavor.  He cannot be classed with 
Cervantes, or Stevenson, or LeSage, or Dickens, or any of the other 
numberless authors chosen for his compeers.  His stories conform to none 
of the canons of fiction.  His essays in biography were altogether 
lacking in any evidence of the historical sense.  In his Joan of Arc 
there is a complete absence of comparative values.  Eve's Diary is funny 
in spots and both dull and vulgar where it is not funny.  His attack on 
Christian Science and Mrs. Eddy has already been mercifully forgotten. 
His polemic against the harmless travel book of M. Paul Bourget was in 
poor taste.  And yet both the man in his own personality and in his 
earlier writings was essentially great; as typical and original in the 
democracy of literature as was Lincoln in the statesmanship of 
democracy.</p> 
 
<p>Both Lincoln and Mark Twain were the children of poor parents.  Both 
were self-educated.  They were both the intellectual products of a 
conception of humanity that had no respect for tradition and no patience 
with ritual.  They both viewed life from a shrewd, individual 
standpoint, and they will both endure as much for their personality as 
their achievements.</p> 
 
<p>Had the Confederacy succeeded Lincoln would have lost none of his 
glory.  Had Mark Twain written nothing but Huckleberry Finn, or Tom 
Sawyer, or Roughing It, he would have earned an abiding place in human 
affection and left a permanent record of one passing phase of American 
life.  For Mark Twain, above all else, was a historian, and no history 
that has yet been written of his country contains such records of life 
and character as those books which made him so well beloved of the 
boyhood of the world.  In England, in all the British colonies, in some 
of the countries of Europe, as well as in American, Tom Sawyer and Huck 
Finn have enjoyed, and will continue to enjoy, a popularity equal to 
that of Tom Browne and Gil Blas and Robinson Crusoe; while Life on the 
Mississippi has an attraction for the soul of youthful adventure that 
runs parallel with the boys of Ballantyne and the hero of Treasure 
Island.</p> 
 
<p>Yet Mark Twain was no master of style, as were Stevenson, or 
Cervantes, or LeSage.  His language had, in itself, no particular charm. 
You do not marvel at the mere wizardry of his words as you do at the 
delicate craftsmanship of <hi rend="italic">Catriona</hi>.  He gets his effects by 
obvious methods; he goes after his story in a downright fashion; his 
University was life at large; and, when thousands of his contemporaries 
were getting whipped into shape in the class room and on the campus, 
Mark Twain was taking a post-graduate course on the river boats of the 
Mississippi.  And, had he gone to Yale or Harvard he would have been 
lost to literature.</p> 
 
<p>For, the higher education is essentially aristocratic.  Culture is an 
anesthetic to the broader sense of humor.  Academic thought smiles, but 
never laughs.  Mark Twain as a Bachelor of Arts of Harvard would have 
made an excellent banker, or a first rate Managing Editor; but the life 
that he sucked in with every breath during his crude and youthful days 
would have gone unnoticed, and that Iliad of the West of which he was 
the Homer would have passed away unsung.  For Mark Twain proved in his 
later years that he was an excellent business man.  He died wealthy. 
Wealthier than Stevenson, or Dickens, or Thackeray, or any of our own 
American authors.  And he succeeded in leaving that wealth in spite of 
many financial reverses, and many intimate family sorrows that would 
have denuded men with the "artistic temperament" of whatever "money 
sense" they might have started with.</p> 
 
<p>Also, it is noticeable, that his genius did not strengthen, but 
decreased, as his affluence increased and contact with the sophisticated 
world made his thoughts and observations more conventional.  The quality 
of his literary product fell off just as it fell off Kipling when 
prosperity came to scorch his inspiration.  "Roughing It" was written 
forty years ago.  "Tom Sawyer" was published thirty-five years ago. 
"Huckleberry Finn" was published twenty-four years ago.  Thereafter came 
books, many books, but the freshness that made the earlier stories so 
delightful was absent; the certainty of a large income had sterilized 
his imagination.  Mark Twain was Mark Twain still; a loveable companion; 
a humorous commentator on men and things; one of the conspicuous figures 
of the world; but he was "written out," and his fame must rest on the 
work that he did whilst the glamor of the old West still possessed his 
soul and he must needs write and he wished to live.</p> 
 
<p>As a literary craftsman, then, and not as a financially successful 
author, we must go back thirty years for the fountain of Mark Twain's 
immortality, and it is rich enough in its flow to keep his memory green 
as long as boys are boys.  For Mark Twain was essentially a boys' 
writer.  When he wrote for men, as he did in his later work, he became 
dull, didactical, polemical; his humor smelt of the lamp.  But when he 
wrote for boys, or for the boy that is in some men to the last  &mdash;  for 
which they may thank Heaven  &mdash;  he lined his gallery with characters that 
stand the peers of Tartarin and Jourdan, and Sancho Panza, and Tam 
O'Shanter, and Don Quixote, and Sam Weller.  But to compare him with the 
creators of those other inventions of literary genius is gauche and 
unnecessary; a dull and unilluminating exercise. Indeed, no comparison 
could be more odious.  For, Mark Twain in literature was a law unto 
himself.  He made his own canons of art. Ignoring the methods of the 
schools, he worked in the clay of life with the firm, strong hands of a 
journeyman delving in immediate things, and what he moulded in those 
leaner years will shine firm and clear when his later efforts are 
forgotten.</p> 
 
 </div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d40"> 
<head> 
Chicago Tribune Obituary<lb/> 
From the <hi rend="italic">Vicksburg (Mississippi) Evening Post</hi><lb/> 
22 April 1910<lb/> 
[anonymous]</head> 
 
<p>The millions who have laughed over the writings of the gentle-hearted 
Mark Twain will grieve over his death.  His life was used in bringing 
sunshine and happiness into the lives of others.  He was a great and 
vivid writer and he will be remember for ages.  His tenderness and true 
manhood was perceptible beneath his humor.  It is gratifying that this 
great writer was appreciated, honored and rewarded, as was his due, by 
the American people, and that his closing years, aside from his 
bereavements caused by the ruthless hand of death, have been years of 
ease and happiness.</p> 
 
 
  </div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d41"> 
<head> 
Minneapolis Tribune Obituary Notice<lb/> 
THE HISTORIAN OF AN EPOCH 
From the <hi rend="italic">Minneapolis Morning Tribune</hi><lb/> 
23 April 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous]</head> 
 
<p>Mark Twain will live as the historian of an epoch.  He is a humorist 
because the epoch was humorous.  We begin to realize that as we get away 
from it.  No nation can take a joke at its own expense.</p> 
 
<p>The most vital, native and racy period of American history was the 
nineteenth century.  Before that we imitated Europe.  Since then we have 
begun to imitate Europe again.  But for near a century we lived our own 
national life in our own way, as fresh as the land we spread over, as 
original as the experiences we met.  The period culminated about the 
middle of the century in the middle of the country.  That was the time 
and scene of Clemens' biggest books.</p> 
 
<p>We had grown hot when European tourists laughed at us.  We grew cool 
when our own writers taught us to laugh at ourselves.  He was not the 
first to portray the fugitive type of the American in the making, but he 
was the greatest.  Cooper began it.  His sentimental slush would not 
have outlived him but for the unconscious humor in it, and the fidelity 
to type under all exaggeration.</p> 
 
<p>The New England writers caught and preserved local phases of the new 
human species.  Less known writers of the Middle states added others. 
It was not till the lure of gold drew a thin sheet of plastic American 
population across the continent that the social ferment of new life on 
new soil under new stimuli carried the native type to its highest 
development.  Then came its clearest expression in books.</p> 
 
<p>Again Mark Twain was one of many to make the new literature, Bret 
Harte and the others for California, the post bellum school for the 
South, Howells for the West and the newer New England, caught 
imperishable films of the kind of American people and institutions 
McMasters tries to portray in serious history.  We believe that 
posterity will see this vanished time most plainly in the books of 
Clemens' early period.  They are the supreme Americans.</p> 
 
 </div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d42"> 
<head> 
Detriot Free Press Obituary Notice 
CLEMENS IS DEAD BUT MARK TWAIN LIVES<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">The Detroit Free Press</hi><lb/> 
23 April 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous]
</head> 
 
<p>His name "of record" was Samuel Langhorne Clemens, but he lives in 
the affections of the world as Mark Twain.  Through many years, he made 
the world laugh in pure healthful enjoyment.  He made it chuckle and he 
made it think sane thoughts when it might have become gloomy or morose. 
In dying he caused grief for the first time.</p> 
 
<p>Perhaps one reason why Mark Twain gained so large a place in the 
hearts of his fellow men, was that men understood, or thought they 
understood him.  Few writers have taken the public into their confidence 
in more pleasing and, at times, in more touching manner.  Those who know 
most of the man's history are nowise surprised to hear the verdict of 
his physician, that he died of a broken heart.</p> 
 
<p>Americans at least, realize that underneath the bubbling humor, the 
gentle searching satire that are the most apparent characteristics of 
his later and better work, mere craftmanship aside, there is a solid 
foundation of solid good sense, broad sympathy, keen perception, quick, 
accurate observation, which drag from their hiding places false 
pretense, poor logic, counterfeit charity.  Critics he had and will 
always have, because some natures seem unable to appreciate his genius. 
Mark Twain was never, even at the beginning a mere juggler of words. 
His quips were never aimless.  His funny stories were funny for what 
there was in them.  His "Prince and Pauper" has satire on the social 
order clothed in sobriety of style.  His "Connecticut Yankee in King 
Arthur's Court," displays that satire in its more playful but no less 
effective aspect.</p> 
 
<p>It was in large part his ability to interpret and portray character 
and the condition of humanity that gave Mark Twain his great strength as 
a humorist.  His philosophical outlook was by no means to be despised. 
How delightfully, how lightly he could pillory the villain, the fakir 
and the cheat!  Mark Twain was one of the giants of American literature 
along with Irving, Hawthorne and Poe.  His humor was less gentle than 
that of Irving, but it meant infinitely more, because it probed farther 
into the world soul.  This perhaps was in part because the world dealt 
less gently with him, but chiefly because his perceptions were more 
rapier like.</p> 
 
<p>Mark Twain had his joys and his sorrows.  He was acquainted with 
grief, and his fellow countrymen rejoiced with him and mourned with him 
because they recognized him as one of themselves.  They envied him his 
pipe, his reprehensible habit of writing and smoking in bed, his 
disregard of the rules of mere convention, his affectations, which, 
perhaps after all were only acted satires.  They admired the manhood 
that would not permit him the refuge of the bankruptcy court, but forced 
him into years of privation.  They loved him for his ideal beautiful 
home life, his deep affection for and tender tributes to his wife and 
children.  They will cherish his memory.</p> 
 
 </div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d43"> 
<head> 
Spokesman-Review Obituary Notice<lb/> 
Mark Twain. 
From <hi rend="italic">The (Spokane) Spokesman-Review</hi><lb/> 
22 April 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous]
</head> 
 
<p>The world has had three colossal laughers: Aristophanes of Greece, 
Rabelais of France and Mark Twain of America; and it is not impossible 
that the last will finally be ranked first.</p> 
 
<p>For greatness in humorous literature is as much a matter of variety 
and range of subject as of power and art; and in the scope and richness 
of his subject-matter Clemens, the nineteenth-century American, 
surpassed the sixteenth-century Frenchman and the Greek of the fifth 
century before Christ.  The world of the Athenian was the Mediterranean 
world, that of the Parisian the European world, but that of the Yankee 
was the whole world; and the modern materials of humor and wit are far 
more numerous and far richer than those of medieval and ancient 
days.</p> 
 
<p>Mark Twain was an American of such sort as only western pioneer 
American could create, and his humor was American to the core.  Living 
the rough life of the Mississippi pilot and the western miner and 
reporter, he accumulated funds of hard but humorous experience that he, 
like Cervantes, turned to literary account.  Out of it came "Roughing 
It," which made the country laugh till its sides were sore, to be 
followed by such stories or novels of humor as "Innocents Abroad," "Tom 
Sawyer," "Huckleberry Finn" and "Pudd'nhead Wilson."  There were other 
works, sixteen or more of them, but those named best reveal his genius 
for humorously exaggerated description and sarcastic wit.  No other 
writer so vividly portrayed the irresponsible American boy or so 
adequately expressed the big-hearted, homespun, violent life of the wild 
west.</p> 
 
<p>Twain's character had its serious side, to which Joseph Twitchell, 
his pastor at Hartford, Conn., paid public tribute; and when the failure 
of his publishers ruined him he played the hero as nobly as Scott and 
Grant and redeemed his fortunes.  But he will be remembered as America's 
colossal laugher; and Huckleberry Finn, Pudd'nhead Wilson and Tom Sawyer 
will live with Falstaff, Gargantua and Sancho Panza.</p> 
 
  </div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d44"> 
<head> 
Charleston News &amp; Courier Obituary Notice<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">The (Charleston) News and Courier</hi><lb/> 
22 April 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous]
</head> 
 
<p>The announcement of the death of Mark Twain yesterday will be 
received with sorrow all over the world.  His kindly humor won for him a 
unique place in American life.  Aside from his literary work he was 
known and appreciated.  Domestic sorrow weighed heavily on him, and the 
recent death of his close friend, Mr. H. H. Rogers, accentuated his 
burden of sorrows.  Even so, Mark Twain was cheerful to the end, his 
optimism being present to the last.  He will be greatly missed.  There 
is no other to take his place.</p> 
 </div1> 
 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d45"> 
 
<head> 
Literature's Rewards 
<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">The (Charleston) News and Courier</hi><lb/> 
25 April 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous]
</head> 
 
<p>We are now told by one of Mark Twain's publishers that the author 
probably left a fortune of more than a million dollars.  It is estimated 
that over 5,000,000 of the humorist's books have been published in 
America, and abroad he was the best known and most widely read of all 
contemporaneous American authors, his works having been translated into 
many tongues.  The publisher quoted says that the books of no other 
author, living or dead, are selling more rapidly to-day and he also 
tells us that no other author received more per work for his stories or 
was paid higher royalties for them in book form.</p> 
 
<p>Acceptable information this, not only because all of us loved Mark 
Twain and rejoice to know that his labors were substantially rewarded, 
but because it is gratifying to discover that it is possible for a man 
to make a million dollars honestly, and with a pen!  It may be just as 
well to note, however, that it was not the desire to make money which 
caused Mark Twain to adopt literature as a career.</p> 
 
 </div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d46"> 
<head> 
DEATH OF MARK TWAIN.<lb/> 
Noted Humorist Passes Away At Ripe Old Age.<lb/> 
From the Virginia City (Nevada) <hi rend="italic">Daily Territorial 
Enterprise</hi><lb/> 
22 April 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous]
</head> 
 
<p>Redding, Conn., April 21  &mdash;  Samuel Clemens, known to the people 
generally as Mark Twain, died this evening after an illness of some 
weeks.</p> 
 
<p>Mark Twain began his literary career on the Enterprise, where he was 
employed in the early sixties as a reporter and some of the improbable 
stories he then wrote afterwards made him famous.  Before coming to the 
Comstock he resided for many years at the old mining camp of Aurora.  He 
took first rank as a humorist and there is hardly a person in the 
civilized world who has not read some of his stories.  Twain came to 
Nevada as private secretary to his brother, who had been appointed 
Secretary of Nevada Territory, and experienced the ups and downs of the 
early settlers.  His story, "Roughing It," attracted great attention and 
the sales were great, which put Twain on Easy street and life with him 
had since been easy.</p> 
 
  </div1> 
 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d47"> 
<head> 
<hi rend="bold">MARK TWAIN.</hi> 
<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">The Indianapolis News</hi><lb/> 
22 April 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous]
</head> 
 
<p>The thousands of people who have loved the great author for his works 
seldom thought of him as Samuel Langhorne Clemens.  To them he was 
always Mark Twain, a writer of inimitable humor, whose voluminous 
writings were read with the keenest enjoyment.  His life was long and 
varied.  He had known hardship and he had known failure, but he had 
known as complete literary success as any modern writer.  The success of 
"The Jumping Frog of Calaveras" was probably as great a surprise to him 
as it was to his publishers.  It opened a new variety of humor, which is 
always welcome in America.  When this was followed by "Innocents Abroad" 
and then by "Roughing It" the fame of Mark Twain as a popular writer of 
entertaining books was established.  "Old Times on the Mississippi," 
"Tom Sawyer," and "Huckleberry Finn" gave to the reading public a 
delightful and intimate view of a phase of American life which was 
enjoyed as well by those who were not personally familiar with it as by 
those who were to the manner born.</p> 
 
<p>Mr. Clemens had a genially eccentric personality.  He was always 
saying and doing things that no one else thought of saying or doing. 
But his wit was not vindictive or malicious.  It never cut nor bit.  It 
really came to the point where people always expected him to say 
something that would cause the immediate laugh and would leave no 
after-bitterness to rankle; and he seldom failed them.  Particularly was 
this true when he appeared as a lecturer or an after-dinner speaker, in 
both of which capacities there was a great demand for him until the 
infirmities of age made it necessary for him to husband his strength. 
But even then he did not cease his work.  Mentally he was as active as 
ever and the productions of his pen continued to appear in the magazines 
and in book form until almost the very end.  If anything his imaginings 
appeared to grow quainter with his increasing years.</p> 
 
<p>The sterling integrity of his character was manifested by his heroic 
struggle to meet the obligations of the publishing firm in which he had 
been interested and which failed disastrously.  At an age when most men 
are ready to retire from the fiercer activities of life he gave himself 
no peace and no rest until by his lectures and his pen he had paid off 
every dollar.  It was the feat of Sir Walter Scott over again.</p> 
 
<p>While one thinks of Mark Twain first and foremost as a great 
humorist, yet he was more than that.  Along with his humor there is 
depth of insight  &mdash;  penetration into human life and character, keen and 
searching and true.  As a recent writer has said:</p>  
 
<p><q>Three decades ago the literary specialists and arbiters 
of belles-lettres dismissed Mark Twain with the phrase, "professional 
humorist."  But the critics began to see more clearly as the years 
mellowed "Tom Sawyer" and "Huckleberry Finn" into classics.  Their 
standards became less academic, broader and more humane, and the change 
was marked by a universal acceptance of Mark Twain as a creator of racy 
American types, as an artist who had caught and preserved for posterity 
the rich, quaint flavor in certain fascinating phases of native life.  A 
genuine humorist, yes, let it be said to his eternal honor, yet one who 
was not content with merely tickling the ribs, but who reached the 
hearts that beat beneath them.  He was like Cervantes in making people 
laugh first and think afterward.  Three generations grinned and made 
merry of "Don Quixote" before anyone realized that it was anything more 
than merely a funny tale; the same phenomenon, upon a smaller scale, 
might be recorded of "Huckleberry Finn."</q></p> 
 
<p>There are few persons who have either known Mark Twain or have read 
his works that will no experience a feeling of sorrow at his death.  It 
leaves a void that will probably never be filled in a branch of 
literature that is peculiarly American.  For he was thoroughly American 
in sentiment, manner and methods.</p> 
 
</div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d48"> 
<head> 
Seattle Post-Intelligencer Obituary Notice<lb/> 
Mark Twain. 
<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">The Seattle Post-Intelligencer</hi><lb/> 
22 April 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous]
</head> 
 
<p>The death of Samuel Langhorne Clemens, known throughout the 
enlightened world as Mark Twain, removes a noble figure, and an 
influence of great value, from the literary circles of America.  It has 
been common in this country and abroad to speak of Mark Twain as "the 
American humorist": the apparent exclusiveness of the title is not 
wholly unjustified, for he came nearer realizing the nobility and 
dignity of the American conception of humor, and possessed a keener 
appreciation of the humorous possibilities inhering in American types of 
character than any other writer in the history of the republic.</p> 
 
<p>Because of the grace and inoffensiveness which marked his delineative 
work, his writings possess an enduring quality, and they will long be 
read with increasing interest, pleasure and profit.</p> 
 
<p>Humor of the emphatic sort is a thing of changing quality. Consider, 
for instance, the grotesqueness of the stage and the caricatures of 
current prints.  Men today laugh at that which would have offended the 
men of yesterday, and it is equally certain that the things which amuse 
the men of today will no longer amuse the men of tomorrow.</p> 
 
<p>Mark Twain, with easy and insideous grace, wrote to the smile, and if 
occasionally convulsive laughter marked the pleasant pilgrimage of the 
reader, it was probably because the reader's nature was rich and full to 
overflowing with light and cheery qualities of heart and mind, rather 
than because of any effort on the author's part to distort, and 
exaggerate beyond human semblance, the figures he struck from the 
fancies of the moment; for behind Mark Twain's portraitures, somewhere 
in the sphere of his ample experience and studious observation, real 
pulsing, moving characters could be found to match them, as faithfully, 
in most instances, as Hamlet's mouse trap scene matched players and 
principals in the act which lays bare the brewing villainies of the 
court.</p> 
 
<p>Mark Twain contributed much to the sum of human contentment, and 
while he moved and toiled in a sphere totally different from that which 
Emerson and Lowell, and Longfellow and Holmes and Whitman adorned, he 
has not contributed less enduringly to the prestige and brilliance of 
American literature.</p>  
</div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d49"> 
<head> 
San Francisco Examiner Obituary Notice<lb/> 
A Great Author;<lb/>  
A True American 
<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">The San Francisco Examiner</hi><lb/> 
22 April 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous]
</head> 
 
<p>M<q>ARK TWAIN</q> is dead!  In those four words America 
announces to a weeping world the loss of her foremost literary man. 
Assuredly of all our authors he was "first in the hearts of his 
countrymen."</p> 
 
<p>He was really the chief of our writers, by the only valid test.  He 
could touch the emotional center of more lives than any other.</p> 
 
<p>He was curiously and intimately American.  No other author has such a 
tang of the soil  &mdash;  such a flavor of the average national mind.</p> 
 
<p>Europeans who complained that we denied Walt Whitman, misunderstood 
Emerson and admired only those who write in old world fashions should be 
satisfied, at least, with Mark Twain, and our unwavering taste for 
him.</p> 
 
<p>He was our very own, and we gathered him to our hearts.</p> 
 
<p>In ages to come, if historians and archaeologists would know the 
thoughts, the temper, the characteristic psychology of the American of 
the later nineteenth century he would only need to read "Innocents 
Abroad," "Tom Sawyer," and "Huckleberry Finn."</p> 
 
<p>Mr. Clemens' books were the transcript of his life.  And that life 
was the kind of life that the average American man of his time has 
believed in and admired.</p> 
 
<p>He was the man that hated dogmas and philosophies and loved a flash 
of intellectual light.</p> 
 
<p>He was the man that cared much to get rich, yet will sweat blood to 
pay his debts.  A man of boundless optimism, who has never troubled to 
understand the great tragedies of nations.</p> 
 
<p>To the superficial view he was merely a humorist  &mdash;  a humorist of 
international fame, to be sure  &mdash;  but just a humorist.  But there was 
far more than jocularity in his writing.  If Cervantes "laughed away the 
chivalry of Spain," Mark Twain laughed away a hundred silly foibles of 
his somewhat too ebullient American friends and admirers.</p> 
 
<p>He had, too, that greatest of all elements in the humorist, the power 
of pathos.  With the twist of a few words he could lift the applauding 
hand to dash away a tear.  And often, just between the laugh and the 
cry, there was a place where he drove home a truth in a way that no 
philosopher or moralizing theorist could hope to equal.</p> 
 
<p>He portrayed the life of the lands he knew and loved in his youth  &mdash;  
the wide, unfettered lands of the Mississippi and the farthest West  &mdash;  
in a way to make that life appreciated and loved around the world. 
Foreign critics likened him to Le Sage and gave him an even prouder 
place in the temple of fame.</p> 
 
<p>Sham disgusted Mark Twain, but he did not attack it with fierce 
intensity.  He merely made it ridiculous, and so banished it.  He set 
men to laughing at their own folly and brought them unconsciously to the 
paths of common sense.  He would have chuckled had anyone called him a 
great reformer with a serious mission in life, yet in his graceful way 
he worked out reform after reform in manners and customs, and would not 
pose for applause.</p> 
 
<p>He made his place as a man as well as an author, and he gave to the 
youth of the land an example of rugged honesty well worth their 
emulation.  When financial disaster whelmed his publishing house it 
would have been easy for him to have evaded his debts and escaped his 
creditors.  But he was not run in that sort of mold.  Like Walter Scott 
before him, and our own William T. Coleman in a narrower field, he 
buckled down to work, tossed away all legal technicalities and paid off 
every dollar of his debts so he could face the world with a clear eye, 
even if in a threadbare coat.  And fortune came to him again as a reward 
for his honest toil, so his later years were spent in comparitive ease 
and affluence.</p> 
 
<p>In his home life he was genial and in his friendships a true comrade. 
His hand was ready to help those in need, and his optimism was an 
inspiration for all who yearned for faith to see through the clouds of 
to-day the sunshine of tomorrow.  Ever the friend and counselor of the 
children, he got from his little friends the insight into their lives 
that enabled him to write two books that, had he written nothing else, 
would have made his name immortal.</p> 
 
<p>California and Nevada are especially proud and unusually fond of this 
great hearted gentleman; for it was in this far West that he began his 
career and found his first inspiration.  Many will take down the 
well-thumbed volumes from the shelves and go over again lovingly the 
passages that made Samuel L. Clemens a fireside friend and a boon 
companion of the men and women, cultured or homely, in all the Western 
land.</p>  
 </div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d50"> 
<head> 
Kansas City Star Obituary Notice<lb/> 
MARK TWAIN, HUMANIST
<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">The Kansas City Star</hi><lb/> 
22 April 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous]</head> 
<p>The news of Mark Twain's death will bring, to an extraordinary 
degree, a sense of personal loss to millions of his countrymen.  For his 
writings, grotesque, humorous, serious, always revealed the vivid 
personality behind them.  No other man of his time was so well known to 
the public in all his moods.  Occasionally you find someone  &mdash;  Alexander 
Butts of The Star was a conspicuous example in Kansas City  &mdash;  who is so 
broadly human and has such an intense interest in every side of life 
that instinctively you feel acquainted after the briefest sort of 
meeting.  Mark Twain was a man of this class.  To him, as to the ancient 
philosopher, nothing human was foreign.</p> 
 
<p>The great inventor, the great statesman, the great writer, is the man 
who above all his fellows sees the importance of the obvious.  His 
achievements seem so simple that people say, "Why didn't I think of 
that?"  Theodore Roosevelt has been constantly charged with uttering 
platitudes.  Louis Blanc complained that when Thiers spoke every fool in 
France exclaimed, "Why, that's just what I have been thinking!"  In this 
universal human quality was the power of Mark Twain.  He was much more 
than a humorist.  He was a humanist.  His writings were constantly 
illumined by flashes of the keenest insight into human nature.  He knew 
what all of us feel and think, but what we are deterred from various 
reasons from saying.  Consider, for instance, the characterization of 
the old fashioned Sunday which he imputed to Adam in his Diary":</p> 
 
<p><q>Sunday  &mdash;  pulled through.</q></p> 
 
<p>Which was the way all young people of a generation ago felt, but 
didn't say.  His "Connecticut Yankee in King Arthurs's Court," "Tom 
Sawyer," "Pudd'nhead Wilson," and his travel books abound in 
observations of this sort.  When he wrote of the Congo atrocities in a 
magazine article a few years ago he adopted the expedient of stripping 
King Leopold and standing him in front of a mirror to reflect on the 
futility of existence  &mdash;  for after all a sovereign was only a 
bandy-legged, scrawny-armed creature, with nothing to distinguish him 
from the meanest of his subjects when once the trappings of royalty were 
removed.</p> 
 
<p>After the death of a daughter a dozen years ago Mr. Clemens wrote a 
moving bit of verse for one of the magazines.  An editorial comment on 
it was printed in The Star and a copy of the paper sent him.  His reply 
was so characteristic that it is worth printing:</p> 
 
 
<p><q>I suppose we are all poets when we are under the stress 
of deep feeling, and that when the stress comes often we devote 
ourselves to poetry instead of prose, but are not moved to this when 
intervals of years supervene between the powerful impulses.  I realize 
that my intervals are of the widest, and that consequently I am 
distinctly condemned to prose.  Still, I am satisfied, for I was born 
indolent, and even the indolent can dig prose and get recreation and 
entertainment out of it.</q></p> 
 
<p>Always beneath the humor was the deep feeling that belongs to the 
rich personality.  Indeed, with Mark Twain, his humor was little more 
than the evidence of his sense of values.  He had suffered deeply, but 
he never lost his sense of proportion and he found life worthwhile up to 
the very beginning of the end.</p> 
 
</div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d51"> 
<head> 
Hartford Courant Obituary Notice<lb/> 
MARK TWAIN.
<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">The Hartford Courant</hi><lb/> 
22 April 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous]</head> 
 
<p>Mark Twain did not come to Hartford to live until he was nearly forty 
years old and he lived here only about twenty years, spending a good 
deal of those years abroad; and yet we of Hartford think of him always 
as a Hartford man, though in fact he was a man of all the world.  No 
other citizen of the United States, not General Grant nor Theodore 
Roosevelt, was more universally known and no other American author was 
ever so generally read.  We of Hartford base our claim to him on the 
fact that he identified himself with this community as he did with no 
other, and on the other and still more welcome fact that here he spent 
the happiest and the most useful of his nearly four score years. 
Although he made his home for some time in New York and later settled 
down in Redding, the feeling has never died out here that he belonged to 
Hartford, and this has been intensified by the fact that wherever any 
Hartford traveler went the first question asked of him was whether he 
knew Mark Twain.</p> 
 
<p>The man was original in everything, not least in insisting on being 
referred to as Mark Twain and not as Mr. Clemens.  The essence of wit is 
said by those who undertake to analyze it to be the unexpected, and it 
was the unexpected that Mark Twain was always doing, even to building a 
house with its kitchen to the street and the bricks laid at angles, and 
his humor was inborn and inevitable; it was of the man himself.  Like 
others of literary fame, he was slow in being discovered, but, once 
found out, he among all our distinctive humorists lasted through.  His 
vein was never worked out.  From the publication of the "Jumping Frog" 
he was a man of note, and as we have said already, for many years he was 
the most universally read of the authors of his day or any other 
day.</p> 
 
<p>He enjoyed this as any author would, and he enjoyed it so much that 
it stood in the way very probably of better work from his wonderful 
brain and heart.  If we are not mistaken, the readers of this paragraph 
will generally agree that his finest book was the "Prince and Pauper," 
but it sold the least, and he has been quoted as giving that fact as his 
reason for not following that line any further.  If it sold the least, 
it was presumably desired by the fewest number of people.  It would be 
difficult to determine his most popular work, but a first guess would 
name the "Innocents Abroad," though you can go on from this to a dozen 
others and smile as each title comes to mind.  How entertaining they 
were, and how keen he was in his knowledge of human nature!</p> 
 
<p>But with all that he wrote it was true of him, as it was of his 
old-time associate here, Mr. Warner, that in private conversation at the 
dinner table, about the billiard table, at club meetings and every-day 
accidental meetings, his delightful, spontaneous outpourings were more 
delicious than anything he wrote; they were said and forgotten for lack 
of a Boswell.  Mark Twain enjoyed his success from all points of view. 
The money that he made was mighty welcome to a man who had known poverty 
down to the hunger line, but much of the pleasure of his wealth was in 
the opportunity it gave him for helping others; his charity was broad 
and abundant.  He was singularly companionable and his friends were 
among those whose friendship was a treasure.  In his hospitable home he 
entertained for years almost everybody of literary prominence in the 
country, native or passing traveler.  But, with all his fame, he was 
democratic through and through.  He would receive a friend's call in the 
morning as he lay in bed smoking, for he usually smoked several cigars 
before getting up, and he would go down town without a hat and in his 
slippers and dressing gown.  He was a world celebrity and yet as 
approachable and easy as the least known among those he passed on the 
street.</p> 
 
<p>Here he came and went day by day, and we all felt that he belonged to 
us; here his family grew up, here his best work was done, here many of 
his choicest friendships were formed, and after he left here his 
troubles began.  The first thought in writing of Mark Twain is to quote 
one after another of his whimsical and philosophical sayings and 
anecdotes.  But there is something about his last days that forbids all 
that.  The lights went out for him before life did.  His wife died 
abroad; two of his daughters died tragic deaths.  He himself fell sick 
in far Bermuda, and came back to an empty home to die.  It is all so far 
from the spirit of his earlier years  &mdash;  from the time of his twinkling 
eye and contagious smile and hearty laugh  &mdash;  that one can only say "The 
pity of it, the pity of it!"  He is gone now.  He brightened life in 
that earlier, happier time, for a lot of us; he will continue to 
brighten life as long as people know how to read.</p> 
 
 </div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d52"> 
<head> 
San Francisco Call Obituary Notice<lb/> 
America Mourns for Mark Twain 
<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">The San Francisco Call</hi><lb/> 
23 April 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous]
</head> 
 
<p>M<q>ARK TWAIN</q>  &mdash;  to call him by the name held in 
affectionate regard by all Americans  &mdash;  was a genuine product of the 
west and more particularly of the mining population of the Pacific 
slope.  The broad, liberal spirit of humanity characteristic of "the 
early days" of California and Nevada found at the same time humorous and 
philosophical expression in his works.  Nothing that was human was alien 
to his spirit and temperament.  Although he pricked the follies of the 
time, his humor carried no sting and left no heart burnings.</p> 
 
<p>Mr. Clemens was easily the premier of the illustrious school of 
California humorists and writers of fiction that includes Bret Harte, 
Samuel L. Clemens, Ambrose Bierce and others of less note.  He may be 
said to have learned his trade in the newspaper offices of San Francisco 
and Virginia City.</p> 
 
<p>It is an interesting and suggestive fact that California alone, of 
all the states, has produced a considerable body of literature racy of 
the soil.  Other commonwealths and communities on this continent have 
produced writers of poetry, fiction and humor, but their product might 
have happened anywhere and is for the most part not rooted in the 
soil.</p> 
 
<p>Mark Twain was even more philosopher than humorist.  His work is 
everywhere inspired by a hatred of shams and he took a real pleasure in 
exposing the solemn humbug.  No man in America has contributed more to 
the sane outlook upon life.</p> 
 
 </div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d53"> 
<head> 
Morning Star Obituary Notice<lb/> 
MARK TWAIN, HUMANITARIAN.<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">The (Wilmington, NC) Morning Star</hi><lb/> 
22 April 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous]</head> 
 
<p>Mark Twain is dead, and the world will mourn him.  With a style which 
made free use of colloquialism, which depended for effect largely upon 
American points of view, naturally incomprehensible to other peoples, he 
yet combined the spirit of humor, which is the gift of the heart, in a 
vehicle of charity making universal appeal.</p> 
 
<p>There was and can be but one Mark Twain.  He was of that select 
company which could bear the designation "unique."  He made his own art 
out of his own personality.  He left no "school," because what he was, 
he grew.  Despite his later artistry and workmanship, it may be said 
truthfully that he acquired little.  He was what he was because he was 
born so.  He was a gift to humanity, for which all peoples are the 
better.</p> 
 
<p>We do not think that there is any room for "criticism" of Twain and 
his works.  He made his own standards, and exerted his own appeal.  He 
was found good and wholesome and uplifting.  In all his frolicsome 
humor, underlying all his fantasies, there was a strain of philosophy, a 
hint of satire, and a suggestion of faith that made for the discerning 
both sermon and poem.  More than any other writer he was the apostle of 
the good in that of everyday, of the need in the midst of misery to 
smile, and of the capacity in misfortune to discover a laugh.  He has 
left behind him a tonic without despression, the record of a brave heart 
and an individuality innate with love.</p> 
 
<p>How many of us feel that we know Mark Twain!  That what he wrote was 
written for us, with the intimate frankness of a friend talking over a 
cigar!  In some way his work leaves that impression of confidence 
possible only to the tete a tete.  It is this fact that makes his life 
of struggle, of heartache and sorrow, all the more pitiful because 
through it all he preserved his gift of friendship for the world, and 
poured out, ever fresh, the goodness of a heart that nothing could 
embitter.</p> 
 
<p>It is more than a humorist who has passed.  The world is poorer for 
the loss of one of its humanities.</p> 
 
 </div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d54"> 
<head> 
Harper's Weekly Obituary Notice<lb/> 
Mark Twain 
<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">Harper's Weekly</hi><lb/> 
30 April 1910<lb/> 
[Unsigned; probably George Harvey]
</head> 
 
<p>There is an old man in Russia who is a very great man of letters. 
Last week it was a matter for discussion whether the greatest living 
writer belonged to Russia or the United States.  This week it will be 
conceded that that distinction belongs to Russia, for  
M<q>ARK</q> T<q>WAIN</q> is dead.</p> 
 
<p>He had the great advantage of living his life fully out.  Not only 
his years, but his energies were prolonged, until we may feel that he 
pretty well worked out what was in him.  There will be few to question 
that he was the greatest American writer of his generation.  What may be 
discussed is whether we have ever had his equal.  We have had no one at 
all like him.  If we must compare, we consider H<q>AWTHORNE</q>  
and W<q>HITMAN</q>.  There is nobody else to put in the scales  
with M<q>ARK</q> T<q>WAIN</q>.</p> 
 
<p>It may be a platitude to say that he was a great writer because he 
was born with the necessary gifts.  No one not so born ever became great 
in letters.  What is interesting is that powers so remarkable should 
have been packed into the frame of a child born in a obscure village in 
Missouri, and should have developed in a life entirely dissociated from 
what we are used to think of as literary influences.  From the start he 
went to school to life; learned boys first, then men, and books at his 
convenience.  When boys who have what are called "advantages" are 
studying Latin grammar, M<q>ARK</q> was studying Tom 
Sawyer, Huck Finn, and the Mississippi River.  He learned them, and in 
due time handed them down to be the heritage of American boys, and 
indeed of all American readers.  That is his great achievement, that he 
grasped a great mindful of American life, rough, joyous, and 
picturesque, and put it where it must stay, vital and permanent, but 
convenient for examination.  There is no sign yet of a time when it will 
cease to be examined by crowds of searchers rejoicing in what they have 
found.</p> 
 
<p>He was irreverent as R<q>ABELAIS</q> was irreverent. 
He never revered shams, and since the sham and the true are much mixed 
up in this world, he scared timid folk at times because of his handling 
of the sham part of things that had truth in them.  Respectability never 
got a gyve on him, and yet in his essence he was a man profoundly 
respectable.  He loved truth, justice, and honor, his integrity was 
nobly justified in the gravest difficulties, his affections were deep 
and constant, his sympathies were ready; to the end of his days he was 
master of himself, equal to his task, faithful to his obligations, and 
honorable and helpful man.</p> 
 
  </div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d55"> 
<head> 
Pawtucket Obituary Notice<lb/> 
"MARK TWAIN."
<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">The (Pawtucket, R.I.) Evening Times</hi><lb/> 
23 April 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous]
</head> 
 
<p>There is scarcely in this wide land a person of any acquaintance with 
contemporaneous literature who does not mourn sincerely the passing of 
Samuel Langhorne Clemens, known more frequently by his pen name of "Mark 
Twain."  Among his admirers, also, we may freely reckon those who do not 
ordinarily read much and may never have enjoyed a book or story by this 
gifted author.  Mark Twain had become in his later years a national 
character, famed for his broad philosophy, his interviews on public 
questions and his great kindness of heart and his sweetness of 
disposition.  His frequently expressed his humorous and apt opinions at 
a time when humor and liberality were needed, so that his outpourings 
acted upon the troubled public temper much as oil upon the raging 
waters.  He could at times be terribly severe, as in his strictures upon 
Leopold and the Congo maladministration, but his customary view of life 
and its incidents was tolerant, though often whimsical.  The subtle 
sense of humor and its companion justice never departed from him.</p> 
 
<p>Mr. Clemens was first of all a jester, just as some writers are 
satirists and others have gifts of poetic expression.  He belonged to a 
school which developed a dozen or so of notable associates half a 
century ago.  In pure genius as a humorist of the American type Mark 
Twain was little if any inferior to Artemus Ward, who was the father of 
them all.  He had the same gift of seeing unerringly beneath the 
surface, of saying the totally unperceived, of adducing grotesque 
similarities and associations, and the same splendid humanness and 
optimism.  His humor was not entirely "funny," it was not wit in the 
common sense, but was the produce of a mind working along unconventional 
and unique lines in delightful and refreshing ways.  His point of view 
was ever surprising, but not the less readily grasped and after a little 
experience "reading Mark Twain" was as easy and restful as listening to 
the strains of a sweet and simple melody.  We all remember how all the 
world burst into a simultaneous laugh when it learned that Clemens had 
shed pious tears at the grave of his ancestor Adam and when it read how 
he expressed ignorance of that celebrity to the guide who showed him the 
relics of Columbus.  The western miner "Scott's" interview with the 
minister whose services were desired at a funeral was as rich and 
mirth-provoking as Artemus Ward's brief encounter with a maiden lady 
whom he disturbed when he went up onto his rooftop with a gun to 
celebrate the arrival of a new member in his family.</p> 
 
<p>In his more mature years, however, Mr. Clemens made frequent 
incursions into soberer literature, or fiction, and here such troubles 
as he ever had with the critics began.  It has always seemed to us that 
some of these gentry were influenced by resentment because a humorist 
had dared to attempt novelism.  His most famous work, "Pudd'nhead 
Wilson," "A Connecticut Yankee at King Arthur's Court," "Joan of Arc," 
"The Gilded Age," which he wrote in connection with Charles Dudley 
Warner, and several other pretentious compositions certainly to our mind 
entitle him to a real place in English literature.  His humorous 
instinct often forced him from more magnificent construction, but not 
always, and in his really serious moments he showed another side to his 
literary powers that will be recognized when his detractor's lips are 
shut.</p> 
 
<p>Mr. Clemens was an usually [gentle?] and companionable man.  He was 
an inveterate hater of fraud and hypocrisy, as his writings in and out 
of season testified.  His private integrity, as in the case of Sir 
Walter Scott, impelled him in his old age to return to the lecture 
platform that he might repay a heavy obligation incurred by the collapse 
of a publishing venture in which he was interested.  He made restitution 
to the last penny, although his health even then had begun to fail.  It 
is particularly saddening in reflecting upon the life and character of 
this fine American to recall the poignant sorrows which fell to his lot 
in his latter years and probably shortened his days.  But these he bore 
with a patient resignation that endeared him further to his fellow 
men.</p> 
 
 </div1> 
<div1 type="figure" id="d56"> 
<head> 
Obituary Cartoon 
</head> 
 
<p rend="center"><lb/> 
<q><hi rend="italic">The Denver Post</hi></q> 
  </p></div1> 
<div1 type="figure" id="d57"> 
<head> 
Obituary Cartoon 
</head> 
 
<p rend="center"><lb/> 
<q><hi rend="italic">The Denver Post</hi></q> 
 
  </p></div1> 
<div1 type="figure" id="d58"> 
<head> 
Obituary Cartoon 
</head> 
 
<p rend="center"><lb/> 
<q><hi rend="italic">Spokane Spokesman-Review</hi>, 23 April 
1910</q> 
  </p></div1> 
<div1 type="figure" id="d59"> 
<head> 
Obituary Cartoon 
</head> 
 
<p rend="center"><lb/> 
<q><hi rend="italic">The San Francisco Call</hi></q> 
 
  </p></div1> 
<div1 type="figure" id="d60"> 
<head> 
Obituary Cartoon 
</head> 
 
 
<p rend="center"><lb/> 
<q><hi rend="italic">The St. Louis Post-Dispatch</hi></q> 
 
</p></div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d61"> 
<head> 
Bookman Obituary Notice<lb/> 
Mark Twain  &mdash;  An Appreciation 
<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">Bookman</hi><lb/> 
June 1910<lb/> 
By Henry Alden
</head> 
 
<p>When it is a matter not of chance but of choice, it is interesting to 
note what book a great writer turns to in his last hours &mdash; what Eminence 
of that vast company to which he belongs he, about to die, salutes.</p> 
 
<p>Tennyson breathed his last with Shakespeare's <hi rend="italic">Cymbeline</hi> in his 
hand, open at the place of that spritely dirge beginning with the 
stanza:</p> 
 
<p><q>Fear not thou the heat o' the sun,<lb/> 
Nor the furious winter's rages;<lb/> 
Thou thy worldly task hast done,<lb/> 
Homer hast gone and ta'en they wages.<lb/> 
Golden lads and girls all must,<lb/> 
As chimney sweeps, come to dust.</q></p> 
 
<p>It was this, we feel sure, rather than the drama itself, which 
especially engaged his dying eyes &mdash; this lyric, with its strangely 
playful solemnity and with a touch of quaintness that he, the Master of 
lyrics, had somehow missed and therefore wistfully regarded, accepting 
its novel illumination of his final vision.  The lighter play of fancy 
commends itself to the old in their waning days, however seriously they 
may have taken themselves at their full strength; it gives vivacity and 
grace, even gaiety, to the lengthening shadows.  Isaac, the name Sara 
gave the child of her barren years, means laughter.</p> 
 
<p>Now Mark Twain, for forty years, personally and in letters, the chief 
provoker of the world's laughter, when he was about to die, turned to 
Carlyle's <hi rend="italic">French Revolution</hi>, not by way of reaction, but 
straightforwardly following the course of a passion that had ruled his 
life.  He loved to regard men and women in the open, in action prompted 
by strong impulses.  The characters which most strongly appealed to him 
were developed in this large atmosphere, and Carlyle was a master in the 
portrayal of such characters &mdash; the inside as well as the outside of them. 
Doubtless, too, Mark admired the master's vivid and picturesque 
description and narration as well as the complexity of expression which 
was so foreign to his own.</p> 
 
<p>But my object in alluding to the books selected by authors for 
reading in their last hours is to call attention to another instance 
which seems very significant.  All my mature readers will easily recall 
the stories written for boys and girls by Juliana Horatio Ewing, some 
thirty years ago, showing a rarely delicate sense of humour and pathos. 
This author, in the face of death, turned to Mark Twain's <hi rend="italic">Huckleberry 
Finn</hi> for delight and satisfaction.  That is enough, it seems to me, 
to define Mark Twain's place in our modern humanism.  The spiritual 
kinship which determined this selection is an infallible test, in the 
case of such a woman and at such a time, as to certain essential quality 
in this man's work that is of everlasting value.  <hi rend="italic">Huckleberry 
Finn</hi> appealed to Mrs. Ewing's sensibility as <hi rend="italic">Tom Sawyer</hi> and 
<hi rend="italic">Life on the Mississippi</hi> would have done, because it was a 
creative illumination of frank, genuine, red-blooded boyhood.  It was a 
quality as native as Nature, spontaneous, expansive, with Nature's 
excesses; but it was humanly embodied, mightily self-conscious, 
imperatively demanding attention, after the haughty manner of buoyant 
youth.  We are reminded of Rabelais's Gargantua entering Paris for his 
university course, on a mare as big as six elephants, the whisking of 
whose tail laid low a whole forest.</p> 
 
<p>The effectiveness of this quality of Mark Twain's imagination does 
not always depend upon external grandeurs and striking surprises.  He 
wrote out of a living experience &mdash; that of a boyhood nourished in open 
spaces and stimulated by rough adventure, and of a manhood which, in all 
its contacts and world-wide wanderings, kept alive that boyhood.  But he 
had also mental adventure, not subtly or complexly, yet widely, 
speculative.</p> 
 
<p>There was the same directness and openness here as in his regard of 
external things.  He relished the autobiography of men who, like 
Benvenuto Cellini and Montaigne, frankly and boldly disclosed their most 
intimate dispositions and tempers, and he undertook one himself on so 
expansive a scheme that it could never have been completed, since the 
longer he lived the less were the chances of any conclusion of the 
ever-widening vista.</p> 
 
<p>The art which premeditatively determines the scope of its venture so 
that one sees at every step the curvature of its rounding up &mdash; in a word 
the literary art &mdash; was foreign to Mark Twain's nature.  Some stories are 
self-limited and wind up themselves.  Mark sometimes told such stories, 
but generally we note no conscious organisation of the material he has 
in hand, no literary method.  Whatever art of expression was developed 
in his maturer work was an art which Nature made, not the result of 
syntatic discipline.  In his <hi rend="italic">Joan of Arc</hi> &mdash; the ripest fruit of his 
genius &mdash; the historic sequence gave him a constructive plan not apparent 
in work of his that was wholly inventive.  He could not have written a 
play depending wholly upon invention, meeting the requirements of the 
art, to save his life, but he would have contributed to one made by an 
expert playwright out of his material just those features which would be 
indispensable to a great popular success.</p> 
 
<p>He always wanted room &mdash; the whole open sky &mdash; for his action.  The 
requirement of literary and of the specially dramatic art, as generally 
understood, because of the concentration demanded, imposed a constraint 
he could not tolerate.  But he was master of the eccentric drama, with 
limitless expansion and projection</p>  
 
<p>In his early career he drove hard and with Icarian boldness.  So 
gigantic were some of his practical journalistic jokes when he was 
connected with the Virginia City <hi rend="italic">Enterprise</hi> that he fled 
temporarily from the scene of his exploits to escape their reaction upon 
himself.  There was much in his <hi rend="italic">Innocents Abroad</hi> which appealed 
to only crude taste; but the book promised richer vintages of humour, 
and it won for him a world-wide popularity, which stimulated him to 
greater earnestness in a more natural use of experiences which were 
real, with however much of grotesquery and extravagance he invested 
them.  It may seem strange to use such a word as "earnestness" in 
connection with a humorist's writings, as it would not be in the case of 
Charles Lamb.  Mark Twain was not a humorist in the sense that Lamb 
was &mdash; the two were at antipodes.  Mark inherited from nobody, but, if not 
as purposeful, he was as masterful as Rabelais, Cervantes, and Swift 
were.  He was not learned or literary as those men, and had not their 
kind of conscious purpose, but there was a strain of earnestness in all 
his work &mdash; a Western strain.  Walt Whitman got one year's big whiff of 
the West and it transformed him, made him vastly panoramic and 
megaphonic.  Mark Twain, like Lincoln, was a native of the West, and, 
like him, though in so different a vein, was gigantically in earnest. 
What stern stuff was in him was shown in the wreck of his personal 
fortunes, like that shown in Lincoln when the fortunes of the nation 
were at stake.</p> 
 
<p>Lincoln passed away before Mark Twain became famous.  He found his 
greatest relaxation and relief from the stress of grave responsibilities 
during the war in the writings of professional humourists like Artemus 
Ward and Petroleum Nasby.  Did he miss something in not having Mark 
Twain's humour?  For the purposes served by those other writers, 
possibly not.  Mark, with all his drollery, might have borne down too 
heavily upon him at such a time, however much he might have enjoyed him 
at another.  The two men had too much in common, in their natural mood 
and strain.</p> 
 
<p>If in the main course of his writings &mdash; those which have had the 
widest appreciation &mdash; he so far retained boyhood himself, and embodied it 
in his characters, regardless of age or sex, for Colonel Sellers was a 
boy in one way and Joan of Arc in another &mdash; yet his was not a case of 
arrested development.  He did a man's work manfully.  The mature 
attitude toward life became apparent in his own maturity &mdash; a deepened 
spiritual sensibility; and a considerable proportion of his work is the 
outcome of this riper growth.</p> 
 
<p>In his maturer work, Mark Twain showed a finer and gentler touch, 
grotesquery yielding to grace.  This was apparent in his personality as 
well as in his work.  Misfortune, though repaired, did its work in 
him.</p> 
 
<p>His griefs, which were irreparable, subdued his spirit.  His 
loneliness after the death of his wife was inconsolable, but the absent 
sweetness dwelt in his nature to the end.  What the loneliness meant for 
him I could see, on a well-remembered occasion, when, at a luncheon 
given to a friend and his wife on their departure for Europe, Mark 
"toasted" them, expressing the hope that if either should be drowned in 
shipwreck that fate might be shared by the other!</p> 
 
<p>It is not likely that the future estimate of Mark Twain's work will 
very greatly differ from that put upon it now by his most thoughtful 
readers, the products of his maturer genius &mdash; I do not thereby mean his 
latest, but those in which his earnestness counts most for human meaning 
and value &mdash; may come to have their just place in the general popular 
esteem.</p> 
 
 </div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d62"> 
<head> 
The Public Obituary Notice<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">The Public</hi><lb/> 
29 April 1910<lb/> 
[Anonymous]
</head> 
 
<p>More than one popular jester has gained his reputation and been 
forgotten since Mark Twain's humor caught the public fancy and made the 
man famous.  But his popularity has continued and will doubtless long 
survive his death.  The reason for this cannot be found in any superior 
wit of his humor.  Some humorists who were contemporaries of his but 
whose fame has long since perished, were perhaps more witty than he.  It 
may be found, however, in the serious purposes that stirred his thought 
and vitalized so much of what he wrote.  Mark Twain was witty, but he 
was more than a wit.  He jested, but he was not a clown.  His humor was 
funny, but if the fun of the comedian was in it so also was the humor of 
a sympathetic and earnest social philosopher.  This was the touch that 
has raised Mark Twain's writings far above the joke books, and kept his 
fame fresh through several generations of readers.  His writings have 
the democratic ring-the ring of the democracy of the Golden Rule.  Read 
"Tom Sawyer" or "Huckleberry Finn," and you find democracy rooted in the 
shrewd thought and harum-scarum experiences of natural-minded boys in 
the presence of the conventional un-democracy of grown men.  Read "The 
Yankee at King Arthur's Court" or "The Prince and the Pauper," and in 
democracy's struggle there with the rude selfishness and ignorance of a 
buried past, you find caricatures of the refined ignorance and polished 
selfishness with which democracy struggles now.  The death of this man 
at his age calls for no tears of grief.  He passes out of life normally, 
after doing a life's work so well that it will be a wholesome influence 
with many a generation to come.</p>  
 
<p>The democracy of Mark Twain was of the kind for which The Public 
stands.  Like his sister who went before him, and like her distinguished 
son, the late Samuel E. Moffett (both of whom were devoted to the truth 
that Henry George taught), Mr. Clemens found for his democracy a 
lodgment in that gospel.  One of the testimonials to its work which the 
Public cherishes is a letter from him in which he declares his faith. 
"The Ethics of Democracy," a unified collection of Public editorials had 
been sent to Mr. Clemens because it contained quotations from his pen, 
and in acknowledgment he wrote from Florence:</p> 
 
<p><q>   &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Villa di 
Quarto, Firenze, Jan. 7, 
1904<lb/> 
Dear Mr. Post:<lb/> 
I thank you very much for this book, which I prize for its lucidity, its 
sanity and its moderation, 
and because I believe its gospel.<lb/> 
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Very truly yours,<lb/> 
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;  
<q> S.  L. 
CLEMENS</q></q></p> 
 
<p><hi rend="italic">"Because I believe its gospel."</hi> To all others who believe the 
same gospel we are confident that this assurance of Mark Twain's 
sympathy will add to their appreciation of the democracy strain that 
runs through nearly all his writings.</p> 
 
 </div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d63"> 
<head> 
The Literary Digest Obituary Notice<lb/> 
<hi rend="bold">MARK TWAIN</hi> 
<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">The Literary Digest</hi><lb/> 
30 April 1910<lb/> 
Anonymous
</head> 
 
<p>The tributes called forth by Mark Twain's death show him to have been 
regarded not only as an American of the Americans, but as one of the 
foremost citizens of the world.  "With the exception of Tolstoy," says 
<hi rend="italic">The Morning Leader</hi> (London), "probably there is no writer whose 
death would rouse more universal emotions of respect and regret."  Mr. 
Hamlin Garland is reported through the press as saying that he was "as 
distinctly American as Walt Whitman."  "The work of most writers could 
be produced in any country," he adds, "but I think we, as well as 
everybody in foreign lands, will look upon Twain's work as being as 
closely related to this county as the Mississippi River itself." </p> 
 
<p>Indeed, the Mississippi seems somehow to symbolize him and he it.  A 
dispatch from Paris voices one of the most poignant expressions of 
personal loss among the many that now fill the papers.  Mr. C. B. M. 
Farthing, friend and schoolmate of Mark Twain, and the original 
Huckleberry Finn, said when told of his loss:</p> 
 
<p><q>"The old days are passing.  The men who made them are 
gone, and even the long sweep of the majestic yellow river seems to have 
dwindled and lessened.  The noise of its traffic, the music of its many 
deep-throated voices are practically no more.  The man who caught them 
and froze them into human words for the delight of the world is 
dead."</q></p> 
 
<p>One of those upon whom the mantle of humor which we call "American" 
has fallen, George Ade says:</p> 
 
<p><q>"I read every line Twain wrote, for he was a kind of 
literary god to me.  His influence has already worked itself into the 
literature of our day.  We owe much of our cheerfulness, simplicity, and 
hope to him.  Most of all, Twain grew old beautifully, showing his 
simple, childlike faith for ultimate success throughout all his 
adversities."</q></p> 
 
<p>Among the tributes of personal affection that of President Woodrow 
Wilson, of Princeton, is especially appealing:</p> 
 
<p><q>"All the world knows that in Mark Twain it has lost a 
delightful humorist, a man able to interpret human life with a flavor 
all his own; but only those who had the privilege of knowing him 
personally can feel the loss to the full-the loss of a man of high and 
lovely character, a friend quick to excite and give affection; a citizen 
of the world, who loved every wholesome adventure of the mind or heart; 
an American who spoke much of the spirit of America in speaking his 
native thoughts."</q></p> 
 
<p>"He was one of the most ethical of humorist," says <hi rend="italic">The Daily 
News</hi> (London), to which <hi rend="italic">The Daily Chronicle</hi> (London) adds: 
"His aspect of things is in reality serious and his judgment often 
peculiarly wise."  It is further noted that he had "the ironic gift of 
puzzling people and leaving them divided between seriousness and 
laughter." <hi rend="italic">The Daily Express</hi> (London) thinks "Huckleberry Finn" 
his best work.</p> 
 
<p>Samuel Langhorne Clemens was born November 30, 1835, in the little 
town of Florida, Monroe County, Mo.  His father was accounted a man of 
"education and social importance" in the frontier town of that early 
day.  Three years after the son's birth the family moved to Hannibal on 
the Mississippi, where Samuel at twelve years of age first touched 
printer's ink.  His young life was somewhat adventurous, as the obituary 
in the New York <hi rend="italic">Sun</hi> recounts:</p> 
 
<p><q>"He determined that if he must be a printer he would be a 
tramp printer, and before he was sixteen he had worked in the 
composing-rooms of newspapers in St.  Louis, Cincinnati, Philadelphia, 
and New York.  The river called him back.  In 1851 he returned to 
Hannibal determined to become a pilot, or as it was called, 'to learn 
the river.'  This was not an inexpensive matter.  Master pilots demanded 
$500 to take a cadet and thoroughly instruct him in the business.  Young 
Clemens could not then pay any premium, but he worked for several years 
with the sole end in view, making money as a printer at times, at times 
working as a clerk on river-boats.  In 1857 he was able to satisfy a 
master pilot of his ability to pay the $500 fee, and two years later he 
had a pilot's license, his first boat being the <hi rend="italic">Alonso Child</hi> 
under Captain De Haven.</q></p> 
 
<p><q>"In 1862 he enlisted in the Confederate Army of Gen. 
Sterling Price, but after a few months he returned to St. Louis to join 
his brother Orrin, who had been appointed Secretary of the Territory of 
Nevada as his clerk to Carson City.</q></p> 
 
<p><q>"Up in Esmeralda County, Nev., near the present Goldfield 
mines, in a camp called Aurora, men were finding rich gold quartz in 
surface outcroppings, and the excitement of this 'rush' drew Clemens 
from his desk in Carson City.  The romance of a new mining-camp near the 
very peak of the Sierra Nevada addrest the sympathies of the young 
adventurer more than the hard work of prospecting for pay 
rock.</q></p> 
 
<p><q>"He made no discoveries of importance in mining, but he 
made many acquaintances with stage-drivers, gamblers, and 'bad' men, all 
of whom appear in 'Roughing It.'"</q></p> 
 
<p>After a year of mining-camp life he returned to newspaper work on the 
staff of <hi rend="italic">The Enterprise</hi> in Virginia City, Nev.  It was here that 
some of his broadly humorous articles appeared over the signature "Mark 
Twain," and were copied widely by papers of the Pacific Coast. 
Then:</p>

<p><q>"The San Francisco <hi rend="italic">Call</hi> made an offer to 
the writer of the Mark Twain stories, and Clemens in 1865 went on <hi rend="italic">The 
Call</hi> staff, but he remained there only six months, for the 
mining-camp called again.  In Calaveras County, Cal., he found little 
gold dust, but he did find material for stories which gave him his first 
fame east of the Rockies, the stories in the book 'The Jumping Frog of 
Calaveras County.'</q></p> 
 
<p><q>"In 1866 Clemens went to the Sandwich Islands and wrote 
from there some sketches for the Sacramento <hi rend="italic">Union</hi>, which sketches 
were the basis for his first lectures delivered in San Francisco after 
his return from Honolulu.</q></p> 
 
<p>In the following year the stories of the 'Jumping Frog' book were 
published, and Mark Twain became known in the Eastern States as a writer 
of exaggerated humor.  It was the reputation these stories gained for 
him that prompted some newspapers editors to select Mr. Clemens to go 
with a party of tourists on a journey abroad and write for his employers 
what would now be called a 'syndicate' letter.  This trip resulted 
(1869) in the publication of 'Innocents Abroad,' an extended revision of 
the letters, and with the instant success of that book the writer became 
famous in this country and most of the countries of Europe.</p> 
 
<p><q>"In spite of the very profitable sales of the book, which 
would have warranted the author in devoting all his time to 
book-writing, he soon after his return from that now famous trip became 
editor of the Buffalo <hi rend="italic"> Express</hi>.  This was probably in pursuance 
of a contract entered into before the trip to Europe.  He remained in 
Buffalo only two years, marrying there Miss Olivia Langdon, whose 
acquaintance he had made on the ocean voyage.</q></p> 
 
<p><q>"Mr. Clemens went to Hartford to live, and at once began 
work the material he had gathered while he was not gathering other pay 
ore in the Sierra Nevada Mountains, and out of that material came the 
book 'Roughing It.'  This fixt his reputation as a story-teller and 
humorist, and his work was urgently demanded by editors on both sides of 
the ocean.  Contributing frequently to magazines, he wrote also in the 
following year, collaborating with Charles Dudley Warner, 'The Gilded 
Age,' which was soon successfully dramatized.</q></p> 
 
<p><q>"Next came from his pen what many Americans and nearly 
all English critics consider his best work of fiction, 'The Adventures 
of Tom Sawyer.'  (1876).</q></p> 
 
<p><q>"After writing several other books Mr. Clemens in 1884 
invested largely in the publishing enterprise of the Charles L. Webster 
Company, which had contracted to pay Mrs.  Grant $500,000 for the 
copyright of General Grant's autobiography.  Ten years later the failure 
of this firm left Mr. Clemens in debt far beyond his 
resources.</q></p> 
 
<p><q>"It was believed by his friends and advisers that a 
round-the-world lecture tour would help to recoup Mr. Clemens, and the 
tour was undertaken.  Its success was vastly beyond the most hopeful 
expectations; the author was received everywhere with high social and 
sometimes with civic honors; his lectures were everywhere attended by 
delighted crowds and frequently delivered under the 'patronage' of the 
most distinguished people.  The profits of the tour enabled Mr. Clemens 
to pay every cent he owed and left him a considerable 
balance."</q></p> 
 
<p>Mark Twain's later books were: "A Yankee at the Court of King 
Arthur," 1889; "The American Claimant," 1892; "The 1,000,000 Bank 
Note," 1893; "Pudd'nhead Wilson," 1894; "Tom Sawyer Abroad," 1894; "Joan 
of Arc," 1896; "More Tramps Abroad," 1897; "The Man That Corrupted 
Hadleyburg," 1900; "Christian Science," 1907. </p> 
       
</div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d64"> 
<head> 
Outlook Obituary Notice<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">Outlook</hi><lb/> 
30 April 1910<lb/> 
Anonymous
</head> 
 
<p>It is well within the literal truth to say that no American writer of 
our day has given so large a number of people so great an amount of 
innocent entertainment as Samuel Langhorne Clemens.  This is obviously a 
matter quite apart from the question of the fineness of literary quality 
in his work.  On that point critical opinions differ; there are those 
who consider that Mr. Clemens "Joan of Arc" may claim high place among 
seriously imaginative works of literature, and that in other writings he 
showed at times far more than the talent of the whimsical humorist. 
Certainly in those delightful boys, Tom Sawyer and Huckleberry Finn, and 
in such tales as "The Prince and the Pauper," he did leave in his 
reader's memory-gallery distinct and individual character creations.  It 
is really a tribute to his variety of interest that readers of many 
degrees of culture and taste are champions of half a dozen different 
specimens of his art as entitled to be called favorite and best: one, 
for instance, thinks the "Jumping Frog" inimitable; another deems it 
immensely overrated and prefers the keen irony of "A Connecticut Yankee 
at King Arthur's Court"; others select as deliciously humorous certain 
sketches of Mark Twain's experiences abroad or even bits of his longer 
books like "Roughing It" and "The Gilded Age"; while almost all enjoy 
"Tom Sawyer" and "Huckleberry Finn" because, as one critic has said, 
"the author has here surpassed in that he has vividly portrayed the 
American boy" and given his readers "an adequate impression of the 
large, homely, spontaneous life led by native Americans in the great 
valley of the Mississippi."</p> 
 
<p>Mr. Clemens was half way through his seventy-fifth year when he died 
at "Stormfield," on Thursday of last week.  His early life in Missouri, 
his rambling experiences in mining, steamboat piloting, and newspaper 
work, his first book-success with "Innocents Abroad," the long list of 
romances, stories, and sketches that followed, together with later 
eventful incidents, notable among which was the bestowal of his doctor's 
degree at Oxford three years ago &mdash; all this is familiar to most 
Americans, and much of the story has been told discursively and oddly in 
Mark Twain's own purposely inconsecutive autobiographical papers.  One 
of many tributes to his memory from fellow writers may be quoted-that of 
James Whitcomb Riley:  "The world has lost not only a genius, but a man 
of striking character, of influence, and of boundless resources.  He 
knew the human heart, and he was sincere.  He knew children, and this 
knowledge made him tender."</p> 
 
<p>In personal friendships and family life Mr. Clemens was peculiarly 
fortunate.  He was in certain ways also a national figure.  Repeatedly 
his force and wit were used to strengthen public causes and to encourage 
right doing and right thinking.  No advocacy of public nature, however, 
could have more lasting power than the private example he gave of 
scrupulous honor.  He voluntarily bore for years the burden of financial 
liability incurred in his name through the publishing business in which 
he had been unwise enough to become a partner.  Refusing to accept the 
legal benefits of bankruptcy, he set to work, like Walter Scott, to pay 
his debtors by his pen; and that he not only succeeded but 
re-established his own fortunes, was a general cause for felicitation 
and rejoicing.</p> 
 
<p>Mark Twain's humor had not only the element of exaggeration which is 
said to be more especially characteristic of American writers of this 
class; it had also drollery and unexpected turns, as unlike Artemus Ward 
on the one had as they were distant from Thackeray on the other.  In 
common with most other professed humorists, his flint did not always 
strike fire; there were undoubtedly commonplace and even tedious 
passages; he did not often deal successfully with plot, and sometime he 
mistook the melodramatic for the dramatic.  But his best was so very 
good that his popularity has become fixed and general, and there is no 
doubt that he will continue to be read both here and abroad for many 
years to come.</p> 
 
<p>That Mark Twain more often then not had serious purpose in his 
writing could easily be shown; sometimes that purpose was to hold up to 
contempt despicable or sordid actions or traits of character; sometimes 
that purpose wit was to teach affirmatively and aggressively principles 
of fairness, truth, kindness, and generosity.  Mark Twain's influence 
never tended toward meanness, snobbery, ostentation.  More also than 
most writers with a popular following, he established in his books and 
sketches a feeling of personal friendliness, almost intimacy, with men 
of all sorts; his works are on the shelf of professor and mechanic.  The 
fact that thousands with whom "Mark Twin" is a household word, as the 
name not only of a writer but of an individual, might have to think 
twice before recalling the name Samuel L. Clemens is perhaps unique in 
the history of pseudonyms, and has a significance of its own.</p> 
 
 </div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d65"> 
<head> 
Century Magazine Obituary Notice<lb/> 
MARK TWAIN AS OUR EMMISSARY 
<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">Century Magazine</hi><lb/> 
December 1910<lb/> 
By George Ade</head> 
 
<p>Mark Twain had a large following of admirers who came to regard 
themselves as his personal friends.  Many of them he never met.  Most of 
them never saw him.  All of them felt a certain relationship and were 
flattered by it.  Men and women in all parts of our outspread domain, 
the men especially, cherished a private affection for him.  They called 
him by his first name, which is the surest proof of abiding fondness. 
Andrew Jackson was known as "Andy"; Abraham Lincoln was simply "Abe" to 
every soldier boy; and as a later instance, we have "Teddy."  Some men 
settle down to a kinship with the shirt-sleeve contingent, even when 
they seem indifferent to the favor of the plain multitude.</p> 
 
<p>Mark Twain never practised any of the wiles of the politician in 
order to be cheered at railway stations and have Chautauquas send for 
him.  He did not seem over-anxious to meet the reporters, and he had a 
fine contempt for most of the orthodox traditions cherished by the 
people who loved him.  Probably no other American could have lived 
abroad for so many years without being editorially branded as an 
expatriate.  In some sections of our country it is safer to be an 
accomplice in homicide, or a stand-patter in politics, than it is to be 
an "expatriate."  When Mr.  Clemens chose to take up his residence in 
Vienna he incurred none of the criticism visited upon Mr. William 
Waldorf Astor.  Every one hoped he would have a good time and learn the 
German language.  Then when the word came back that he made his loafing 
headquarters in a place up an alley known as a <hi rend="italic">stube</hi> or a 
<hi rend="italic">rathskeller</hi>, or something like that, all the women of the 
literary clubs, who kept his picture on the high pedestal with the 
candles burning in front of it, decided that <hi rend="italic">stube</hi> meant 
"shrine."  You may be sure that if they can find the place they will 
sink a bronze memorial tablet immediately above the main faucet.</p> 
 
<p>Of course, the early books, such as "Innocents Abroad," "Roughing 
It," and "The Gilded Age" gave him an enormous vogue in every remote 
community visited by book-agents.  The fact that people enjoyed reading 
these cheering volumes and preserved them in the bookcase and moved some 
of the classics by E. P. Roe and Mrs. Southworth in order to make room 
for "Tom Sawyer" and "Huckleberry Finn," does not fully account for the 
evident and accepted popularity of Mark Twain.  Other men wrote books 
that went into the bookcase but what one of them ever earned the special 
privilege being hailed by his first name?</p> 
 
<p>When a man has done his work for many years more or less under the 
supervising eye of the public, the public learns a good many facts about 
him that are in no way associated with his set and regular duties as a 
servant of the public.  Out of the thousand-and-one newspaper mentions 
and private bits of gossip and whispered words of inside information, 
even the man in the street comes to put an estimate on the real human 
qualities of each personage, and sometimes these estimates are 
surprisingly accurate, just as they are often sadly out of focus.</p> 
 
<p>Joseph Jefferson had a place in the public esteem quite apart from 
that demanded by his skill as an actor.  Players and readers of 
newspapers came to know in time that he was a kind and cheery old 
gentleman of blameless life, charitable in his estimates of professional 
associates, a modest devotee of the fine arts, a outdoor sportsman with 
the enthusiasm of a boy, and the chosen associate of a good many eminent 
citizens.  When they spoke of "Joe" Jefferson in warmth and kindness, it 
was not because he played "Rip Van Winkle" so beautifully, but because 
the light of his private goodness had filtered through the mystery 
surrounding every popular actor.  William H. Crane is another veteran of 
the stage who holds the regard of the public.  It knows him as the kind 
of man we should like to invite up to our house to meet the "folks." 
The sororities throb with a feeling of sisterhood for Miss Maude Adams 
because the girls feel sure that she is gracious and charming and 
altogether "nice."</p> 
 
<p>Mark Twain would have stood very well with the assorted grades making 
up what is generally known as the "great public" even if he had done his 
work in a box and passed it out through a knot-hole.  Any one who knew 
our homely neighbors as he knew them and could tell about them in loving 
candor, so that we laughed at them and warmed up to them at the same 
time, simply had to be "all right."  Being prejudiced in his favor, we 
knew that if he wanted to wear his hair in a mop and adopt white 
clothing and talk with a drawl, no one would dare to suggest that he was 
affecting the picturesque.  He was big enough to be different.  Any 
special privilege was his without the asking.  Having earned 100 per 
cent. of our homage he did n't have to strain for new effects.</p> 
 
<p>His devotion to the members of his family and the heroic performance 
in connection with the debts of the publishing house undoubtedly helped 
to strengthen the general regard for him.  Also, the older generation, 
having heard him lecture, could say that they had "met" him.  Every one 
who sat within the soothing presence of the drawl, waiting to be shirked 
up on every second sentence with a half-concealed stroke of drollery, 
was for all time a witness to the inimitable charm of the man and the 
story-teller.</p> 
 
<p>The knowledge of his unaffected democracy became general.  No doubt 
the housewives loved him for his outspoken devotion to home-cooking. 
Has any one told in public the anecdote of his tribute to an humble item 
in the bill of fare?  It was at a dinner party in Washington.  Senator 
Hearst was giving the dinner, and Mark Twain was the guest of honor. 
Here were two transplanted westerners who knew more about roughing it 
than ever appeared in a book.  As the high-priced food was being served 
to them, they talked longingly of the old-fashioned cookery of Missouri. 
The Senator wondered if there was any real corned beef and cabbage left 
in the world.  Mark Twain spoke up in praise of the many old-time 
dishes, reaching his climax when he declared that, in his opinion, 
"Bacon would improve the flavor of an angel!"</p> 
 
<p>Furthermore is it not possible that much of the tremendous liking for 
Mark Twain grew out of his success in establishing our credit abroad? 
Any American who can invade Europe and command respectful attention is 
entitled to triumphal arches when he arrives home.  Our dread and fear 
of foreign criticism are still most acute.  Mrs. Trollope and Captain 
Maryat lacerated our feelings long ago.  Dickens came over to have our 
choicest wild flowers strewn in his pathway and then went home to 
scourge us until we shrieked with pain.  Kipling had fun with us, and 
for years after that we trembled at his approach.  George Bernard Shaw 
peppers away at long range and the "London Spectator" grows peevish 
every time it looks out of the window and sees a drove of Cook tourists 
madly spending their money.</p> 
 
<p>It is a terrible shock to the simple inlander, who has fed upon 
Congessional oratory and provincial editorials, when he discovers that 
in certain European capitals the name "American" is almost a term of 
reproach.  The first-time-over citizen from Spudville or Alfalfa Center 
indicates his protest by wearing a flag on his coat and inviting those 
who sit in darkness to comes over and see what kind of trams are run on 
the Burlington.  The lady, whose voice comes from a point directly 
between the eyes, seeks to correct all the erroneous impressions by 
going to the table d'hote with fewer clothes and more jewels than any 
one had reason to expect.  These two are not as frequently to be seen as 
they were twenty years ago but they are still gleefully held up by our 
critics as being "typical."</p> 
 
<p>Probably they are outnumbered nowadays by the apologetic kind, &mdash; those 
who approach the English accent with trembling determination and who, 
after ordering in French, put a finger on the line so that the waiter 
may be in on the secret.</p> 
 
<p>There are Americans who live abroad and speak of their native land in 
shameful whispers.  Another kind is an explainer.  He becomes fretful 
and involved in the attempt to make it clear to some Englishman with a 
cold and fish-like eye that, as a matter of fact, the lynchings are 
scattered over a large territory, and Tammany has nothing whatever to do 
with the United States Senate, and the millionaire does not crawl into 
the presence of his wife and daughters, and Morgan never can be King, 
and citizens of St. Louis are not in danger of being hooked by moose. 
After he gets through the Englishman says "Really?" and the painful 
incident is closed.</p> 
 
<p>Every man is handicapped and hobbled when he gets out of his own 
bailiwick.  The American is at a special disadvantage in Europe.  If he 
cannot adapt himself to strange customs and social regulations, he 
thinks that he will be set down as an ignoramus.  If he tries to nullify 
or override them he may be regarded as a boor or a barbarian.  Once in a 
while an American, finding himself beset by unfamiliar conditions, 
follows the simple policy of not trying to assimilate new rules or 
oppose them, and merely goes ahead in his own way, conducting himself as 
a human being possessed of the usual number of faculties.  This odd 
performance may be counted upon to excite wonder and admiration. 
Benjamin Franklin tried it out long ago and became the sensation of 
Europe.  General Grant and Colonel Roosevelt got along comfortably in 
all sorts of foreign complications merely by refusing to put on 
disguises and to be play-acting.  But Mark Twain was probably the best 
of our emissaries.  He never waved the starry banner and at the same 
time he never went around begging forgiveness.  He knew the faults of 
his home people and he understood intimately and with a family knowledge 
all of their good qualities and groping intentions and half-formed plans 
for big things in the future; but apparently he did not think it 
necessary to justify all of his private beliefs to men who lived five 
thousand miles away from Hannibal, Missouri.  He had been in all parts 
of the world and had made a calm and unbiased estimate of the relative 
values of men and institutions.  Probably he came to know that all had 
been cut from one piece and then trimmed variously.  He carried with him 
the same placid habit of life that sufficed him in Connecticut, and 
because he was what he pretended to be, the hypercritical foreigners 
doted upon him and the Americans at home, glad to flatter themselves, 
said, "Why certainly he's one of us."</p> 
 
</div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d66"> 
<head> 
American Review of Reviews Obituary Notice<lb/> 
Mark Twain, Artist<lb/> 
From <hi rend="italic">The American Review of Reviews</hi><lb/> 
June 1910<lb/> 
By William Lyon Phelps</head> 
 
<p>If necessity is the mother of invention, misfortune is the mother of 
literature.  When Nathaniel Hawthorne was ejected from the Custom-House 
at Salem he went home in a despondent frame of mind, only to be greeted 
by his wonderful wife's pertinent remark, "Now you can write your book." 
He responded to this stimulus by writing the best book ever written in 
the Western Hemisphere, "The Scarlet Letter."  We learn from a famous 
chapter in "Roughing It" that if Samuel Clemens had not gone to help a 
sick friend, or if his partner had received the note he left for him 
before starting on this charitable expedition, Samuel L. Clemens would 
have been a millionaire.  This episode has since his death been printed 
in a list of the misfortunes that marked his romantic and tragic career. 
But if at that time Mr. Clemens had become a millionaire, and he missed 
it by the narrowest possible margin, he never would have become Mark 
Twain.  He struggled against his destiny with all the physical and 
mental force he possessed.  He tried to make a living by every means 
except literature, and nothing but steady misfortune and dire necessity 
made him walk in the foreordained path.  Mark Twain always regarded 
himself as the plaything of chance; professing no belief in God, he 
never thanked Him for his amazing successes, nor rebelled against Him 
for his sufferings.  But is ever there was a man whose times were in His 
hand, that man was Mark Twain.</p> 
 
<p>Mark Twain was a greater artist than he was humorist; a greater 
humorist than he was philosopher; a greater philosopher than he was 
thinker.  Goethe's well-known remark about Byron, "The moment he thinks, 
he is a child," would in some respects be applicable to Mark Twain.  The 
least valuable part of his work is found among his efforts to rewrite 
history, his critical essays on men and on institutions, and his 
contributions to introspective thought.  His long book on Joan of Arc is 
valuable only for its style; his short book on the Shakespeare-Bacon 
controversy shows appalling ignorance; his defense of Harriet Shelley is 
praiseworthy only in its chivalry; his attack on Fenimore Cooper is of 
no consequence except as a humorous document; his labored volume on 
Christian Science has little significance; and when his posthumous essay 
on the "Meaning of Life" is published, as I am afraid it will be before 
long, it will surprise and depress more readers than it will 
convince.</p> 
 
<p>As a philosopher, Mark Twain was a pessimist as to the value of the 
individual life and an optimist concerning human progress.  He agreed 
with Schopenhauer that non-existence was preferable to existence; that 
sorrow was out of all proportion to happiness.  On the other hand, he 
had absolutely nothing of Carlyle's peculiar pessimism, who regarded the 
human soul as something noble and divine, but insisted that modern 
progress was entirely in the wrong direction, and that things in general 
were steadily growing worse.  Carlyle believed in God and man, but he 
hated democracy as a political principle; Mark Twain apparently believed 
in neither God nor man, but his faith in democracy was so great that he 
almost made a religion out of it.  He was never tired of exposing the 
tyranny of superstition and of unmasking the romantic splendor of 
medieval life.</p> 
 
<p>Mark Twain was one of the foremost humorists of modern times; and 
there are not wanting good critics who already dare to place him with 
Rabelais, Cervantes, and Moliere.  Others would regard such an estimate 
as mere hyperbole, born of transient enthusiasm.  But we all know now 
that he was more than a funmaker; we know that his humor, while purely 
American, had the note of universality.  He tested historical 
institutions, the social life of past ages, political and religious 
creeds, and the future abode of saints by the practical touchstone of 
humor.  Nothing sharpens the eyes of a traveler more than a sense of 
humor; nothing enables him better to make the subsequent story of his 
journey pictorially impressive.  "The Innocents Abroad" is a great book, 
because it represents the wonders of Europe as seen by an unawed 
Philistine with no background; he has his limitations, but at any rate 
his opinions of things are formed <hi rend="italic">after</hi> he sees them, and not 
before.  He looks with his own eyes, not through the colored spectacles 
of convention.  "Roughing It" is still a greater book, because in the 
writing of that no background was necessary, no limitations are felt; we 
know that his testimony is true.  The humor of Mark Twain is American in 
its point of view, in its love of the incongruous, in its fondness for 
colossal exaggeration; but it is universal in that it deals not with 
passing phenomena, or with matters of temporary interest, but with 
essential and permanent aspects of human nature.</p>  
 
<p>As an artist Mark Twain already seems great.  The funniest man in the 
world, he was at the same time a profoundly serious artist, a faithful 
servant of his literary ideals.  The environment, the characterization, 
and the humanity in "Tom Sawyer" remind us of the great novelists, whose 
characters remain in our memory as sharply defined individuals simply 
because they have the touch of nature that makes the whole world kin. 
In other words, "Tom Sawyer" resembles the masterpieces of fiction in 
being intensely local and at the same time universal.  Tom Sawyer is a 
definite personality, but he is also eternal boyhood.  In "Huckleberry 
Finn" we have three characters who are so different that they live in 
different worlds, and really speak different languages, Tom, Huck, and 
Jim; we have an amazingly clear presentation of life in the days of 
slavery; we have a marvelous moving picture of the Father of Waters; 
but, above all, we have a vital drama of humanity, in its nobility and 
baseness, its strength and weakness, its love of truth and its love of 
fraud, its utter pathos and its side-splitting mirth.  Like nearly all 
faithful pictures of the world, it is a vast tragi-comedy.  What does it 
matter if our great American had his limitations and his excrescences? 
To borrow his own phrase, "There is that about the sun that makes us 
forget its spots."</p> 
 
 </div1> 
<div1 type="obituary" id="d67"> 
<head> 
NYC Obituary Notices 
</head> 
<p> 
from <hi rend="italic">The New York American</hi></p> 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
