<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="TwaWarp"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="TwaWarp"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The War Prayer</title>
<title type="sort">war prayer</title>
<author>Twain, Mark, 1835-1910</author>
<respStmt> 
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Robert Bolick</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>Johnnie Wilcox, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">12</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">TwaWarp</idno> 
<date value="2001">2001</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2001 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476433</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The War Prayer</title>
<title type="sort">war prayer</title>
<author>Twain, Mark, 1835-1910</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harper and Row</publisher> 
<pubPlace>N. P.</pubPlace> 
<date value="1923">1923</date> 
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: UVa Library, PS1322 .W3 1968</idno>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Source of Electronic version unvailable.</p>
</note> 
<note>
<p>Front matter from source copy consulted.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing 
part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center 
scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1923">1923</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term> 
<term>prose</term> 
<term>masculine</term> 
<term>Mark Twain</term>
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2001-10">October 2001</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Johnnie Wilcox, Electronic Text Center, University of</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>added TEI.2 header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 
 
<front id="d2"> 
 
<div1 type="epigraph" id="d3"> 
 
 
<p>To Dan Beard, who dropped in to see him,<lb/> 
Clemens read the "War Prayer," stating that<lb/> 
he had read it to his daughter Jean,<lb/> 
and others, who had told him he must not<lb/> 
print it, for it would be regarded as sacrilege. 
</p> 
 
<p>"Still, you are going to publish it, are you not?" 
</p> 
 
<p>Clemens, pacing up and down the room<lb/> 
in his dressing-gown and slippers,<lb/> 
shook his head.<lb/> 
</p> 
 
<p>"No," he said, "I have told the whole truth<lb/> 
in that, and only dead men can tell the truth<lb/> 
in this world.<lb/> 
</p> 
 
<p>"It can be published after I am dead."<lb/> 
</p> 
 
<closer>Mark Twain, A Biography <hi rend="italic">by Albert Bigelow Paine</hi><lb/> 
<hi rend="italic">Harper &amp; Brothers, 1912</hi> 
</closer> 
 
</div1> 
 
</front> 
 
<body id="d4"> 
 
<div1 type="essay" id="d5"> 
<head>The War Prayer <lb/> 
 by Mark Twain</head> 
 
<p>It was a time of great and exalting excitement.  
 
</p><p>The country was up in arms, the war was on, in every breast burned the 
holy fire of patriotism;   
 
</p><p>The drums were beating, the bands playing, the toy pistols popping, the 
bunched firecrackers hissing and spluttering;  
 
</p><p>On every hand and far down the receding and fading spread of roofs and 
balconies a fluttering wilderness of flags flashed in the sun;  
 
</p><p>Daily the young volunteers marched down the wide avenue gay and fine in 
their new uniforms, the proud fathers and mothers and sisters and sweethearts 
cheering them with voices choked with happy emotion as they swung by;  
 
</p><p>Nightly the packed mass meetings listened, panting, to patriot oratory 
which stirred the deepest deeps of their hearts and which they interrupted at 
briefest intervals with cyclones of applause, the tears running down their 
cheeks the while;  
 
</p><p>In the churches the pastors preached devotion to flag and country and 
invoked the God of Battles, beseeching His aid in our good cause in outpouring 
of fervid eloquence which moved every listener.   
 
</p><p>It was indeed a glad and gracious time, and the half-dozen rash spirits 
that ventured to disapprove of the war and cast a doubt upon its righteousness 
straightway got such a stern and angry warning that for their personal safety's 
sake they quickly shrank out of sight and offended no more in that way. 
 
</p><p>Sunday morning came-next day the battalions would leave for the front; 
the church was filled;  
 
</p><p>The volunteers were there, their young faces alight with martial 
dreams-visions of the stern advance, the gathering momentum, the rushing 
charge, the flashing sabers, the flight of the foe, the tumult, the enveloping 
smoke, the fierce pursuit, the surrender!-then home from the war, bronzed 
heroes, welcomed, adored, submerged in golden seas of glory!   
 
</p><p>With the volunteers sat their dear ones, proud, happy, and envied by the 
neighbors and friends who had no sons and brothers to send forth to the field 
of honor, there to win for the flag or failing, die the noblest of noble 
deaths.  The service proceeded; a war chapter from the Old Testament was read; 
the first prayer was said; it was followed by an organ burst that shook the 
building, and with one impulse the house rose, with glowing eyes and beating 
hearts, and poured out that tremendous invocation-</p> 
<lg type="poem"> 
<l><hi rend="italic">God the all-terrible!</hi></l> 
<l><hi rend="italic">Thou who ordainest,</hi></l> 
<l><hi rend="italic">Thunder thy clarion</hi></l> 
<l><hi rend="italic">And lightning thy sword!</hi></l> 
</lg> 
 
<p>Then came the "long" prayer.   None could remember the like of it for 
passionate pleading and moving and beautiful language. The burden of its 
supplication was that an ever-merciful and benignant Father of us all would 
watch over our noble young soldiers and aid, comfort, and encourage them in 
their patriotic work; bless them, shield them in the day of battle and the hour 
of peril, bear them in His mighty hand, make them strong and confident, 
invincible in the bloody onset; help them to crush the foe, grant to them and 
to their flag and country imperishable honor and glory- 
</p><p>An aged stranger entered and moved with slow and noiseless step up the 
main aisle, his eyes fixed upon the minister, his long body clothed in a robe 
that reached to his feet, his head bare, his white hair descending in a frothy 
cataract to his shoulders, his seamy face unnaturally pale, pale even to 
ghastliness.  With all eyes following him and wondering, he made his silent 
way; without pausing, he ascended to the preacher's side and stood there, 
waiting.  With shut lids the preacher, unconscious of his presence, continued 
his moving prayer, and at last finished it with the words, uttered in fervent 
appeal,</p> 
<lg><l><hi rend="italic">Bless our arms,</hi></l> 
<l><hi rend="italic">grant us the victory,</hi></l> 
<l><hi rend="italic">O Lord our God,</hi></l> 
<l><hi rend="italic">Father and Protector</hi></l> 
<l><hi rend="italic">Of our land and flag!"</hi></l></lg> 
 
<p>The stranger touched his arm, motioned him to step aside-which the 
startled minister did-and took his place.   During some moments he surveyed the 
spellbound audience with solemn eyes in which burned an uncanny light; then in 
a deep voice he said: 
 
</p><p> "I come from the Throne-bearing a message from Almighty God!"  The 
words smote the house with a shock; if the stranger perceived it he gave no 
attention.  "He has heard the prayer of His servant your shepherd and will 
grant it if such shall be your desire after I, His messenger, shall have 
explained to you its import-that is to say, its full import.   For it is like 
unto many of the prayers of men, in that it asks for more than he who utters it 
is aware of-except he pause and think. 
 
</p><p> "God's servant and yours has prayed his prayer.  Has paused and taken 
thought?   Is it one prayer?  No, it is two-one uttered, the other not.  Both 
have reached the ear of Him Who heareth all supplications, the spoken and the 
unspoken.   Ponder this-keep it in mind.  If you would beseech a blessing upon 
yourself, beware! Lest without intent you invoke a curse upon a neighbor at the 
same time.  If you pray for the blessing of rain upon your crop which needs it, 
by that act you are possibly praying for a curse upon some neighbor's crop 
which may not need rain and can be injured by it. 
 
</p><p> "You have heard your servant's prayer-the uttered part of it.  I am 
commissioned by God to put into words the other part of it-that part which the 
pastor, and also in your hearts, fervently prayed silently.  And ignorantly and 
unthinkingly?  God grant that it was so!  You heard these words: 'Grant us the 
victory, O Lord our God!"  That is sufficient.  The whole of the uttered prayer 
is compact into those pregnant words.  Elaborations were not necessary.   When 
you have prayed for victory you have prayed for many unmentioned results which 
follow victory-must follow it, cannot help but follow it.  Upon the listening 
spirit of God the Father fell also the unspoken part of the prayer.  He 
commandeth me to put it into words. 
 
</p><p>LISTEN! 
 
</p><p> "O Lord our Father, our young patriots, idols of our hearts, go forth 
to battle-be Thou near them!  With them, in spirit, we also go forth from the 
sweet peace of our beloved firesides to smite the foe.  O Lord our God, help us 
to tear their soldiers to bloody shreds with our shells; help us to cover their 
smiling fields with the pale forms of their patriot dead; help us to drown the 
thunder of the guns with the shrieks of their wounded writhing in pain; help us 
to lay waste their humble homes with a hurricane of fire; help us to wring the 
hearts of their unoffending widows with unavailing grief; help us to turn them 
out roofless with their little children to wander unfriended the wastes of 
their desolated land in rags and hunger and thirst, sports of the sun flames of 
summer and the icy winds of winter, broken in spirit, worn with travail, 
imploring Thee for the refuge of the grave and denied it-for our sakes who 
adore Thee, Lord, blast their hopes, blight their lives, protract their bitter 
pilgrimage, make heavy their steps, water their way with their tears, stain the 
white snow with the blood of their wounded feet!  We ask it, in the spirit of 
love, of Him Who is the Source of Love, and Who is the ever-faithful refuge and 
friend of all that are sore beset and seek His aid with humble and contrite 
hearts.  Amen." 
 
</p><p>After a pause:   
 
</p><p> "Ye have prayed it; if ye still desire it, speak!  The messenger of the 
Most High waits." 
 
 
</p><p>It was believed afterward that the man was a lunatic, because there was 
no sense in what he said.</p> 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
