<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="TwaWhit"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="TwaWhit"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Whittier Birthday Dinner Speech</title>
<title type="sort">whittier birthday dinner speech</title>
<author>Twain, Mark, 1835-1910</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>  
<name>Stephen Railton</name>  
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>  
<name>Tom Palombi, Electronic Text Center</name>  
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">12</num> kilobytes</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>  
<idno type="ETC">TwaWhit</idno>  
<date value="1997-09">September 1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476434</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>  
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Whittier Birthday Dinner Speech</title>
<title level="m">Mark Twain's Speeches</title>
<title type="sort">whittier birthday dinner speech</title>
<author>Mark Twain</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>  
<name/>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<editionStmt>
<p>This 1910 edition publishes Twain's "Whittier Birthday Dinner Speech," which was originally delivered on December 17, 1877.</p>
</editionStmt>  
<extent>pp. 1-16</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harper &amp; Brothers</publisher>  
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>  
<date value="1910">1910</date>  
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted:</idno>
</publicationStmt>  
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>  
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>  
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>  
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>  
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>  
</encodingDesc>  
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>  
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; fiction</term>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
</profileDesc>  
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-09">September 1997</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Tom Palombi, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>  
 
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2"> 

<div1 type="speech" id="d3"> <pb/>
<head>The Whittier Birthday Dinner Speech<lb/> 
17 December 1877</head> 
 
<p>THIS is an occasion peculiarly meet for the digging up of pleasant 
reminiscences concerning literary folk; therefore I will drop lightly 
into history myself. Standing here on the shore of the Atlantic and 
contemplating certain of its largest literary billows, I am reminded of 
a thing which happened to me thirteen years ago, when I had just 
succeeded in stirring up a little Nevadian literary puddle myself, whose 
spume-flakes were beginning to blow thinly Californiaward. I started an 
inspection tramp through the southern mines of California. I was callow 
and conceited, and I resolved to try the virtue of my nom de guerre. 
 
</p><p>I very soon had an opportunity. I knocked at a miner's lonely log 
cabin in the foot-hills of the Sierras just at nightfall. It was snowing 
at the time. A jaded, melancholy man of fifty, barefooted, opened the 
door to me. When he heard my nom de guerre he looked more dejected than 
before. He let me in &mdash; pretty reluctantly, I thought &mdash; and after the 
customary bacon and beans, black coffee and hot whiskey, I took a pipe. 
This sorrowful man had not said three words up to this time. Now he 
spoke up and said, in the voice of one who is secretly suffering, 
"You're the fourth &mdash; I'm going to move." "The fourth what?" said I. 
"The fourth littery man that has been here in twenty-four hours &mdash; I'm 
going to move." "You don't tell me!" said I; "who were the others?" "Mr. 
Longfellow, Mr. Emerson, and Mr. Oliver Wendell Holmes &mdash; consound the 
lot!" 
  
</p><p>You can easily believe I was interested. I supplicated &mdash; three hot 
whiskeys did the rest &mdash; and finally the melancholy miner began. Said 
he: "They came here just at dark yesterday evening, and I let them in of 
course. Said they were going to the Yosemite. They were a rough lot, but 
that's nothing; everybody looks rough that travels afoot. Mr. Emerson 
was a seedy little bit of a chap, red-headed. Mr. Holmes was as fat as a 
balloon; he weighed as much as three hundred, and had double chins all 
the way down to his stomach. Mr. Longfellow was built like a 
prize-fighter. His head was cropped and bristly, like as if he had a wig 
made of hair-brushes. His nose lay straight down his face, like a finger 
with the end joint tilted up. They had been drinking, I could see that. 
And what queer talk they used!  Mr. Holmes inspected this cabin, then he 
took me by the buttonhole, and says he: 
</p>

<lg type="poem">
<l>"'Through the deep caves of thought</l> 
<l>I hear a voice that sings,</l> 
<l>Build thee more stately mansions,</l> 
<l>O my soul!'</l> 
</lg>

<p>"Says I, 'I can't afford it, Mr. Holmes, and moreover I don't want 
to.' Blamed if I liked it pretty well, either, coming from a stranger, 
that way. However, I started to get out my bacon and beans, when Mr. 
Emerson came and looked on awhile, and then he takes me aside by the 
buttonhole and says: 
 
</p>

<lg type="poem">
<l>"'Give me agates for my meat;</l> 
<l>Give me cantharids to eat;</l> 
<l>From air and ocean bring me foods,</l> 
<l>From all zones and altitudes.'</l> 
</lg>

<p>"Says I, 'Mr. Emerson, if you'll excuse me, this ain't no hotel.' You 
see it sort of riled me &mdash; I warn't used to the ways of littery swells. 
But I went on a-sweating over my work, and next comes Mr. Longfellow and 
buttonholes me, and interrupts me. Says he: 
</p>

<lg type="poem">
<l>"'Honor be to Mudjekeewis!</l> 
<l>You shall hear how Pau-Puk-Keewis&mdash;'</l> 
</lg>



<p>"But I broke in, and says I, 'Beg your pardon, Mr. Longfellow, if 
you'll be so kind as to hold your yawp for about five minutes and let me 
get this grub ready, you'll do me proud.' Well, sir, after they'd filled 
up I set out the jug. Mr. Holmes looks at it, and then he fires up all 
of a sudden and yells: 
 
</p>


<lg type="poem">
<l>"'Flash out a stream of blood-red wine!</l> 
<l>For I would drink to other days.'</l> 
</lg>

<p>"By George, I was getting kind of worked up.  I don't deny it, I was 
getting kind of worked up.  I turns to Mr. Holmes, and says I, 'Looky 
here, my fat friend, I'm a-running this shanty, and if the court knows 
herself, you'll take whiskey straight or you'll go dry.' Them's the very 
words I said to him. Now I don't want to sass such famous littery 
people, but you see they kind of forced me.  There ain't nothing 
onreasonable 'bout me; I don't mind a passer of guests a-treadin' on my 
tail three or four times, but when it comes to standing on it it's 
different, 'and if the court knows herself,' I says, 'you'll take 
whiskey straight or you'll go dry.' Well, between drinks they'd swell 
around the cabin and strike attitudes and spout; and pretty soon they 
got out a greasy old deck and went to playing euchre at ten cents a 
corner &mdash; on trust.  I began to notice some pretty suspicious things. 
Mr. Emerson dealt, looked at his hand, shook his head, says: 
 
</p>

<lg type="poem">
<l>"'I am the doubter and the doubt &mdash;' </l>
 
</lg>

<p>and ca'mly bunched the hands and went to shuffling for a new layout. 
Says he: 
 
</p>

<lg type="poem">
<l>"'They reckon ill who leave me out;</l> 
<l>They know now well the subtle ways I keep.</l> 
<l>I pass and deal <hi rend="italic">again!</hi>'</l> 
 
</lg>

<p>Hang'd if he didn't go ahead and do it, too!  Oh, he was a cool one! 
Well, in a minute things were running pretty tight, but all of a sudden 
I see by Emerson's eye he judged he had 'em.  He had already corralled 
two tricks, and each of the others one.  So now he kind of lifts a 
little in his chair and says: 
</p>

<lg type="poem">
<l>"'I tire of globes and aces! &mdash;</l> 
<l>Too long the game is played!'</l> 
</lg>

<p>&mdash; and down he fetched a right bower.  Mr. Longfellow smiles as sweet 
as pie and says: 
</p>

<lg type="poem">
<l>"'Thanks, thanks to thee, my worthy friend,</l> 
<l>For the lesson thou has taught,'</l> 
</lg>

<p>&mdash; and blamed if he didn't down with <hi rend="italic">another</hi> right bower! 
Emerson claps his hand on his bowie, Longfellow claps his on his 
revolver, and I went under a bunk. There was going to be trouble; but 
that monstrous Holmes rose up, wobbling his double chins, and says he, 
'Order, gentlemen; the first man that draws, I'll lay down on him and 
smother him!'  All quiet on the Potomac, you bet! 
 
</p><p>"They were pretty how-come-you-so by now, and they begun to blow. 
Emerson says, 'The nobbiest thing I ever wrote was " Barbara 
Frietchie."' Says Longfellow, 'It don't begin with my "Biglow Papers."' 
Says Holmes, 'My "Thanatopsis" lays over 'em both.' They mighty near 
ended in a fight. Then they wished they had some more company &mdash; and Mr. 
Emerson pointed to me and says: 
</p> 

<lg type="poem">
<l>"'Is yonder squalid peasant all</l> 
<l>That this proud nursery could breed?'</l>
</lg> 
 
<p>He was a-whetting his bowie on his boot &mdash; so I let it pass. Well, 
sir, next they took it into their heads that they would like some music; 
so they made me stand up and sing "When Johnny Comes Marching Home" till 
I dropped &mdash; at thirteen minutes past four this morning. That's what 
I've been through, my friend. When I woke at seven, they were leaving, 
thank goodness, and Mr.  Longfellow had my only boots on, and his'n 
under his arm. Says I, 'Hold on, there, Evangeline, what are you going 
to do with them?' He says, 'Going to make tracks with 'em; because: 
</p> 

<lg type="poem">
<l>"'Lives of great men all remind us</l> 
<l>We can make our lives sublime;</l> 
<l>And, departing, leave behind us</l> 
<l>Footprints on the sands of time.'</l> 
</lg>

<p>As I said, Mr. Twain, you are the fourth in twenty-four hours &mdash; and 
I'm going to move; I ain't suited to a littery atmosphere." 
 
</p><p>I said to the miner, "Why, my dear sir, these were not the gracious 
singers to whom we and the world pay loving reverence alla homage; these 
were impostors." 
 
</p><p>The miner investigated me with a calm eye for a while; then said he, 
"Ah! impostors, were they?  Are <hi rend="italic">you?</hi> 
 
</p><p>I did not pursue the subject, and since then I have not travelled on 
my nom de guerre enough to hurt. Such was the reminiscence I was moved 
to contribute, Mr. Chairman. In my enthusiasm I may have exaggerated the 
details a little, but you will easily forgive me that fault, since I 
believe it is the first time I have ever deflected from perpendicular 
fact on an occasion like this.<lb/> 
 
[<hi rend="italic">From</hi> Mark Twain's Speeches <hi rend="italic">(New York: Harper &amp; Brothers, 
1910): 1-16.</hi>]  
</p> 
 
</div1> 

</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
