<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="VarJers"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
<TEI.2 id="VarJers"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Cases adjudged in the Supreme Court of New-Jersey; relative to the 
manumission of Negroes and others holden in bondage.</title>
<title type="sort">cases adjudged in the supreme court of new jersey relative to the manumission of negroes and others holden in bondage</title>
<author>New Jersey: Justices of the Supreme Court and Attorney Generals</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Readex &mdash; a division of NewsBank Inc.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">59</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
 <idno type="ETC">VarJers</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476442</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>Documentary Sources Database.  American Multiculturalism 
Series.  Unit one.  Documenting the African American Experience.</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Cases adjudged in the Supreme Court of New-Jersey; relative to the 
manumission of Negroes and others holden in bondage.</title>
<title type="sort">cases adjudged in the supreme court of new jersey relative to the manumission of negroes and others holden in bondage</title>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>32 p. ; 21 cm. (8vo)</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Printed for "The New-Jersey Society for Promoting 
the Abolition of Slavery," by Isaac Neale, &mdash;</publisher> 
<pubPlace>Burlington [N.J.]</pubPlace> 
<date value="1794">M,DCC,XCIV. [1794]</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>Early American Imprints, 1st series, no. 27391 
(filmed)</p>
</seriesStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared by TextBase in consultation with David Seaman, 
University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>milestone tag records a pagination number that runs consecutively 
for the whole project.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1794">1794</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term type="references">Evans 27391.</term> 
<term type="references">Morsch, L.M.  New Jersey, 240.</term> 
<term type="subjects">Slavery&mdash;New Jersey&mdash;Emancipation.</term> 
<term type="subjects">Slavery&mdash;New Jersey&mdash;Law.</term> 
<term type="additional">New Jersey. Supreme Court of Judicature.</term> 
<term type="printer">Neale, Isaac, 1767-1796, printer.</term> 
<term type="pubplace">United States&mdash;New Jersey&mdash;Burlington.</term> 
<term type="record">w030228</term> 
<term>African American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 
<front id="d2">  

<titlePage id="d3"> <pb/>  
<titlePart type="main">CASES ADJUDGED IN THE <hi rend="bold">SUPREME 
COURT</hi> OF <hi rend="italic">NEW-JERSEY</hi>; RELATIVE TO THE MANUMISSION OF 
NEGROES AND OTHERS HOLDEN IN BONDAGE. 
</titlePart> 
<epigraph> 
<q>&mdash;&ldquo;<hi rend="bold">GOD</hi> has created men of all nations, of all 
languages, of ALL COLOURS, EQUALLY FREE :</q> 
</epigraph> 
<epigraph> 
<q>&ldquo;<hi rend="bold">SLAVERY</hi>, in all its forms, in all its 
degrees, is a violation of the divine laws, and a degradation of human nature.&rdquo; 
</q></epigraph> 
 
<docImprint> 
BURLINGTON, 
PRINTED FOR &ldquo;THE NEW-JERSEY SOCIETY FOR PROMOTING THE 
ABOLITION OF SLAVERY,&rdquo; BY ISAAC NEALE,&mdash; 
</docImprint><docDate>M,DCC,XCIV.</docDate> 
</titlePage> 
</front> 
 
<body id="d4">  

<div1 type="section" id="d5"> <pb/>
<p> 
AT a general Meeting of the NEW-JERSEY SOCIETY FOR PROMOTING THE 
ABOLITION OF SLAVERY, <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 2, 1793, RESOLVED, 
That the <hi rend="italic">President</hi> of this Society collect and  
have printed, the `Decisions of the Supreme Court in this State,  
relative to the Manumission of Negroes and others, unlawfully  
holden in Bondage.'  
<lb/> 
EXTRACT FROM THE MINUTES, ROBERT SMITH, JUN. SECRETARY. 
</p> 
<p> 
 <pb/>
 
ON the Application of Joseph Bloomfield, Esquire, President of the  
<hi rend="italic">New-Jersey Society for promoting the Abolition of  
Slavery</hi>, I have carefully examined the following Cases with  
the original Entries thereof, in the Minutes of the Supreme Court  
of New-Jersey ; and I do hereby certify, that the same are truly 
taken from the said Minutes, 
</p> 
<signed>GERSHEM CRAFT, for the Clerk of the Supreme Court. 
<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic">November</hi> 20, 1793. 
</signed> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d6"> 
 <pb/>  
<list> 
<head> 
JUSTICES OF THE SUPREME COURT, AND ATTORNEY GENERALS  
<lb/> 
OF THE STATE OF NEW-JERSEY, SINCE 1774. 
</head> 
<item>1774 to May Term 1776 inclusive. 
<lb/> 
Frederick Smyth, Chief Justice.<lb/> 
David Ogden,<lb/> 
Richard Stockton, Justices<lb/> 
Cortland Skinner, Atty. General.<lb/> 
</item> 
<item>1776 September 4.<lb/> 
<lb/> 
William Paterson, Atty. General.<lb/> 
 
</item><item>1777 February 5.<lb/> 
<lb/> 
Robert Morris, Chief Justice.<lb/> 
 
</item><item>15. Isaac Smith,<lb/> 
John Cleves Symmes, Justices.<lb/> 
 
</item><item>1779 June 10.<lb/> 
<lb/> 
David Brearly, Chief Justice. 
 
</item><item>1783 June 13.<lb/> 
<lb/> 
Joseph Bloomfield, Atty. General.<lb/> 
 
</item><item>1788 September 4.<lb/> 
<lb/> 
John Chetwood, Third Justice.<lb/> 
 
</item><item>1789 November 20.<lb/> 
<lb/> 
James Kinsey, Chief Justice. 
</item><item>1792 May 23.<lb/> 
<lb/> 
Aaron D. Woodruff, Atty. General. 
</item></list> 
 
</div1> 
 
 

<div1 type="section" id="d7"> 
<head>CASES ADJUDGED IN THE SUPREME COURT OF <hi rend="italic">NEW-JERSEY</hi>.<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic">November</hi> Term, 1775.<lb/> 
(Minutes, p. 44, 142.) 
<lb/> 
The KING <hi rend="italic">against</hi> ESTHER BARBER and others. 
</head> 
 
<p><hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">for to bring the Body 
of</hi> Beulah, <hi rend="italic">a Negro Girl</hi>. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="bold">B</hi>Y the Admission of the Counsel, it appeared that Beulah the 
Negro Girl, 
brought up by the Habeas Corpus, and now before the Court, is the Daughter of a 
Negro Man and Negro Woman, the first named David, and the other named Dinah, 
both of whom formerly belonged to Caleb Haines, of the City of Burlington, which 
said Negroes David and Dinah, were set free by the said Caleb Haines in his life time, 
and before the Birth of the said Girl Beulah, without having given any Bond pursuant 
to the Act of Assembly, passed in the twelfth and thirteenth Years of her late Majesty 
Queen Ann ; for which Reason the said Manumission was alledged to be void. 
</p><p> 
The Court having heard the Arguments of Counsel, as well for the said Esther Barber 
and others, as for the said Beulah, at the Term of May last, and now again at this 
present Term, and having fully considered thereof <hi rend="italic">are of Opinion</hi>, 
That the 
said Manumission by the said Caleb Haines, of the said David and Dinah, the Parents 
of the said Beulah, was good in Law against the said Caleb 
 
 
<pb n="8"/> 
 
Haines and those claiming under him, notwithstanding the not giving Bond as 
aforesaid ; and that the same Beulah is entitled to her Freedom under the said 
Manumission against the said Caled Haines, and all claiming under him ; and do order 
her the said Beulah to be delivered up from out of the Custody of the said Esther 
Barber and others, in which she hath been illegally detained. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d8"> 
<head><hi rend="italic">April</hi> Term, 1782. 
<lb/> 
The STATE <hi rend="italic">against</hi> JACOBUS VANHUYS. 
</head> 
 
<p><hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">for Negro</hi> Will <hi 
rend="italic">Claiming his Freedom</hi>. 
</p> 
<p> 
<hi rend="bold">T</hi>HE Court having heard the Arguments of Counsel on the Part of 
Negro 
Will, and the Reasons assigned for and against his Freedom, and the Evidence in 
Support thereof : It is ordered by the Court that the said Negro <hi 
rend="italic">Will</hi> be, and 
he is hereby discharged and set Free from the said Jacobus Vanhuys, on Motion of Mr 
Deare. 
</p><p> 
Kinsey, Elias Boudinot, and the Attorney General for the Negro. 
Sergeant, and Paterson, for Defendant. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d9"> 
<head><hi rend="italic">September</hi> Term, 1782. 
<lb/> 
(p. 36.) 
<lb/> 
The STATE <hi rend="italic">against</hi> EDMUND BAINBRIDGE. 
</head> 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">of Negro</hi> Nelly. 
</p> 
<p><hi rend="bold">I</hi>T appearing to the Court, and the said <hi 
rend="italic">Edmund Bainbridge</hi> 
conceding, that the said Negro Nelly was formerly the Property of Edmund 
Bainbridge, the elder, of Maidenhead, deceased, who let his Daughter Abigail, 
  
 
<pb n="9"/> 
 
late the Wife of Thomas Biles, of Bucks County in Pennsylvania, deceased, gave her 
when very young ; that many Years afterwards he made his Will and bequeathed her 
to his said Daughter Abigail, during the Life of his said Daughter, and to her Issue, 
and did further order, that if she should die childless, then the said Negro Nelly should 
be sold, and the Money appropriated as mentioned in his said Will ; that the said 
Abigail Biles who survived her Husband and her Father, did by her Will dated 30th 
April 1779, set forth and declare, that the said Negro Nelly had by her said Father 
been presented to her on a New-Year's Day, when she was a Child, and therefore, 
both from that Gift and from bringing her up, she had a better Right to dispose of her 
than any other Person, and did therein order and direct, that the said Negro Nelly 
should be manumitted and set free, a thing which she had very much at Heart ; that 
the said Negro Nelly resided in the State of Pennsylvania at the Time of the passing 
of the Act for the gradual Abolition of Slavery, 1st March, 1780, and until the first of 
November in the same Year, the Term and Period allowed and fixed in the said Act 
for registering Slaves and for some Time afterwards ; that she was not registered as 
the said Act requires, and that she is not within the Exceptions specified therein. 
</p><p> 
The Court having fully considered the Premises, <hi rend="italic">are unanimously of 
Opinion</hi>, 
That the Manumission of the said Negro Nelly by the said Abigail Biles, Daughter of 
the aforesaid Edmund Bainbridge, is good in Law against all Persons claiming under 
either of them ; the said Edmund Bainbridge, having given her to his said Daughter, 
when she the said Negro Nelly was a Child, and his said Daughter having directed by 
her Will that she should be manumitted ; and further that the said Negro Nelly, not 
having been registered as the above mentioned Act of the State of Pennsylvania 
requires, and therefore entitled to Freedom in that State, is not by Law put in a worse 
Situation here : It is therefore <hi rend="italic">Ordered</hi>, That the said Negro Nelly 
be 
discharged and set at Liberty from the said Edmund Bainbridge. On Motion of Mr. 
<hi rend="italic">Morris</hi> for Mr. <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi>.</p>
 

  
<pb n="10"/> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d10"> 
<head>IN THE SAME TERM OF <hi rend="italic">September</hi>, 1782. 
<lb/> 
(p. 48.) 
<lb/> 
The STATE <hi rend="italic">against</hi> LEWIS Mc. KNIGHT. 
</head> 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">to bring the Body of 
Negro</hi> Caesar Tite. 
</p> 
<p> 
<hi rend="bold">T</hi>HE Defendant having returned the Habeas Corpus, and brought 
up the 
Body of the said Negro Caesar Tite, It is ordered that the Defendant enter into 
Security in the Sum of Two Hundred Pounds to bring up the Body of the said Negro 
Caesar on the second Tuesday in November next, and abide the Judgment of the Court 
respecting the said Negro, and that in Case the said Negro should be adjudged by this 
Court free, that the said Lewis M`Knight shall pay for the Service of the said Negro 
from this Time. 
</p><p> 
Recognizance accordingly. 
</p></div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d11"> 
<head><hi rend="italic">September</hi> Term, 1782. 
<lb/> 
(p. 49.) 
<lb/> 
The STATE <hi rend="italic">against</hi> ENLOES PHILPOT. 
</head> 
<p> 
<hi rend="bold">W</hi>HEREAS, it hath appeared to this Court, upon the Affidavit of 
Jack 
Tappen, that the Defendant holds a certain Anthony Tappen in Bondage and Slavery, 
without lawful Authority for the same as the said Jack alledgeth : therefore, 
<hi rend="italic">Ordered</hi>, on Motion of Mr. Leake for the said Anthony, that a 
Writ of 
<hi rend="italic">Habeas Corpus ad faciendum subjiciendum et Recipiendum</hi> do 
issue, 
returnable to this Court at the next Term.</p>
 
 
<pb n="11"/> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d12"> 
<head><hi rend="italic">November</hi> Term, 1782. 
<lb/> 
(p. 59.) 
<lb/> 
The STATE <hi rend="italic">against</hi> LEWIS Mc. KNIGHT. 
</head> 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">of Negro</hi> Caesar Tite. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="bold">A</hi>GREEABLY to the Command of the within Writ, I have here in 
Court the 
Body of the within mentioned Caesar Tite, and do say that the said Negro Tite is my 
Property, being bought of Kenneth Hankinson, Esquire, for valuable Consideration, 
and he is not a free Man ; but I am willing and desirous to contest that Property by a 
Jury of the Country, agreeably to the Laws of this State, and pray that it may not be 
taken from me without a Trial by Jury, &amp;c. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d13"> 
<head> 
LEWIS Mc. KNIGHT. 
<lb/> 
IN THE SAME TERM OF <hi rend="italic">November</hi>, 1782. 
<lb/> 
(p. 76.) 
<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic">IN THE SAME CAUSE OF</hi>  
The STATE <hi rend="italic">against</hi> LEWIS Mc. KNIGHT. 
</head> 
<p> 
<hi rend="bold">I</hi>T appearing to the Court, that the said Negro Caesar Tite, 
brought up by 
<hi rend="italic">Habeas Corpus</hi>, and now before the Court, heretofore belonged to 
Grace Tite, 
of the County of Monmouth, who by her last Will and Testament ordered that he 
should be free when he attained the Age of Twenty-one Years, till which period he 
was to serve Thomas Leonard of the said County of Monmouth ; that the said Thomas 
Leonard joined the Enemy some Time before the Expiration of the said Service, and 
the said Negro Caesar Tite was sold at Public Vendue, with other confiscated personal 
Property of the said 
 
  
<pb n="12"/> 
 
Thomas Leonard, by the Commissioners of forfeited Estates for the County of 
Monmouth, and bought by David Forman, Esq. who afterwards sold him to Kenneth 
Hankinson, Esq. and he to the said Lewis M`Knight the Defendant ; that no Bond was 
given by the said Grace Tite, pursuant to the Act of Assembly, passed in the twelfth 
and thirteenth Years of the late Queen Ann : And that the said Negro Caesar Tite is 
now above Twenty-one Years old, <hi rend="italic">to wit</hi>, of the Age of about 
Twenty-four 
or Twenty-five. 
</p><p> 
The Court having heard the Arguments of Counsel on both sides, and fully considered 
thereof, <hi rend="italic">are unanimously of Opinion</hi>, That the said Manumission is 
good in 
Law against all Persons claiming under the said Grace Tite, notwithstanding Bond 
was not given as aforesaid ; <hi rend="italic">and do order</hi>, on Motion of Mr. 
Bloomfield for 
the Attorney-General, that the Negro Caesar Tite be discharged and set at Liberty 
from the said Lewis M`Knight. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d14"> 
<head> 
<hi rend="italic">September</hi> Term, 1783. 
<lb/> 
(p. 252. 270.) 
<lb/> 
MERCY HILL <hi rend="italic">against</hi> WILLIAM LEDDELL. 
</head> 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">for Manumission</hi>. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="bold">I</hi>T being alledged by the Counsel, for the said Mercy Hill the 
Plaintiff, that 
she is the Daughter of a certain Jupiter Lee, a Negro Slave, heretofore belonging to 
Samuel Lec of the Town of Swansey in the Colony of Massachusetts Bay, now 
Commonwealth of Massachusetts, and Deliverence Hill, a free-born native Indian 
Woman ; that in her Infancy she was put apprentice to James Power of that Place, 
with whom, or his Assigns she served many Years, and then laboured for her 
Livelihood in different Places as other free Persons usually do ; that long afterwards 
she was by some Means sold as a Slave, and by sundry Transfers and Sales came at 
length into the Possession of the Defendant William Leddell. 
</p><p> 
  
  
<pb n="13"/> 
 
The Court having heard the Testimony, with sundry Affidavits offered and read, to 
prove the Truth of the foregoing Allegations, and having also heard the Arguments 
of Counsel on both Sides, and maturely considered thereof, <hi rend="italic">are 
unanimously of 
Opinion</hi>, That the said Mercy Hill is entitled to her Freedom, and ought not to be 
held in Slavery ; and do accordingly adjudge and order that the said Mercy Hill be 
discharged and set at Liberty from the said William Leddell, on Motion of Mr. Morris 
in behalf of Mercy Hill. 
</p></div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d15"> 
<head>IN THE SAME TERM OF <hi rend="italic">September</hi>, 1783. 
<lb/> 
(p. 286. 295.) 
<lb/> 
The STATE <hi rend="italic">against</hi> TIERCK TENBROECK. 
</head> 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">of Negro</hi> Philip <hi 
rend="italic">for Manumission</hi>. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="bold">T</hi>HE Court having fully considered the Evidence, and the 
Arguments of 
Counsel in this Cause, <hi rend="italic">are unanimously of Opinion</hi>, and do 
adjudge, that the 
said Negro <hi rend="italic">Philip</hi> be discharged and set at Liberty from the said 
Tierck 
Tenbroeck, and also from  John Vanhorne of Rocky-Hill, in the County of Somerset, 
who hath appeared and claimed the said Negro Philip, On Motion of Mr. Paterson for 
the State. 
</p></div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d16"> 
<head><hi rend="italic">May</hi> Term, 1784. 
<lb/> 
(p. 33.) 
<lb/> 
The STATE against ADRIAN POST. 
</head> 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">of Negro</hi> Charles <hi 
rend="italic">and</hi> Wife.  
<hi rend="italic">In November Term</hi>, 1781. (p. 467.) 
</p><p> 
 
<hi rend="bold">O</hi>N the hearing of this Case, the Court adjudged in favor of the 
discharge 
of the Negroes, and ordered the Defendant to deliver them to the Sheriff of Bergen, 
  
  
<pb n="14"/> 
 
to remain in his Custody, until the further Order of the Court. 
</p><p> 
And now, on Motion of Mr. Elias Boudinot for Nicholas Covenhoven, Master of the 
said Negroes, it is ordered by the Court, that the Sheriff of Bergen, do on service of 
this Rule, deliver to the said Nicholas Covenhoven, or his Order, the said Negro 
Charles and Wife. 
</p></div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d17"> 
<head><hi rend="italic">April</hi> Term, 1785. 
<lb/> 
(p. 300.) 
<lb/> 
The STATE against BENJAMIN APPLEGATE. 
</head> 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">of Negro</hi> Peter Ridley, 
<hi rend="italic">claiming to be 
manumitted</hi>. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="bold">T</hi>HE said Negro <hi rend="italic">Peter</hi> being brought into 
Court by Habeas Corpus, and it appearing to the Court on Testimony, that the said 
Negro Peter is the Son of a certain William Ridley, a free Negro and his Wife Dianna, a 
Negro Woman sometime the Property of Dollans Hegeman, and who became free before 
the Birth of the said Negro Peter, and that the said Parents of the said Negro Peter have 
ever since lived and been reputed as free. 
</p><p> 
The Court <hi rend="italic">are of Opinion</hi> and <hi rend="italic">do adjudge</hi>, 
that the said Negro Peter was free-born, and is entitled to be discharged as a free Man ; 
and do order that he be discharged accordingly, on Motion of Mr. Paterson for the State. 
</p></div1>  


 

<div1 type="section" id="d18"> <pb n="15"/> 
<head><hi rend="italic">May</hi> Term, 1785. 
<lb/> 
(p. 358.) 
<lb/> 
The STATE <hi rend="italic">against</hi> JOHN VANHORNE. 
</head> 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">of Negro</hi> Prime, <hi 
rend="italic">claiming his Freedom</hi>. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="bold">T</hi>HE Court in <hi rend="italic">September Term</hi>, 1784. (<hi 
rend="italic">p</hi>. 125.) on return of the <hi rend="italic">Habeas Corpus</hi>, obliged 
Defendant to enter into Recognizance with Security in \cp\140. conditioned for the 
Appearance of the said Negro <hi rend="italic">Prime</hi> at the next Term, to abide 
&amp;c. and not depart &amp;c. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="italic">November Term</hi>, 1784, (<hi rend="italic">p</hi>. 195.) 
Recognizance continued. <hi rend="italic">April 
Term</hi>, 1785, (p. 299.) Argument postponed, and Recognizance continued. 
</p><p> 
And now (<hi rend="italic">May Term</hi>, 1785.) <hi rend="italic">Moore Furman</hi>, 
Esquire, Agent of 
forfeited Estates for the County of Hunterdon, having applied to the Court, and 
represented that the State hath a Claim to the said Negro Prime ; it is ordered by the 
Court that the said Negro Prime be delivered into the Custody of John Anderson, 
Esquire, Sheriff of Hunterdon, until a Trial of the Property can be had, and until the 
further Order of the Court. 
</p></div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d19"> 
<head> 
AFTERWARDS IN THE 
<hi rend="italic">Term of May</hi>, 1786, (p. 128.) 
</head> 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">Moore Furman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Esq</hi>. Agent of Forfeitures for 
the County of 
Hunterdon&mdash;<hi rend="italic">against John Eauhouse</hi>, <hi rend="italic">In 
Detinue</hi>. 
</p><p> 
This action having been brought by Agreement of Parties under the Direction of the 
Court, to try the Property of a certain Negro Prime, and a Verdict and Judgment 
having passed in favor of the Plaintiff, <hi rend="italic">It is ordered</hi> by the Court, 
on the 
Motion of Mr. Houston for the Plaintiff, that the said Negro Prime now in the Custody 
of the Sheriff of Hunterdon, agreeably to an Order of 
 
 
<pb n="16"/> 
 
this Court of May Term last, be delivered to the said Moore Furman, Esq. Agent of 
Forfeitures for the County of Hunterdon. 
<note n="1"><p><hi rend="italic">The Legislature by an Act dated</hi> 21 <hi 
rend="italic">November</hi>, 1786, 
<hi rend="italic">declaring themselves &ldquo;to be desirous of extending the Blessings of 
Liberty,&rdquo; generously manumitted Prime from Slavery. He had been enlisted and 
served in the Army in the late War</hi>. 
</p></note> 
</p></div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d20"> 
<head> 
<hi rend="italic">November</hi> Term, 1785. 
<lb/> 
(p. 519 and 472.) 
<lb/> 
Negro GEORGE against BARNT DE KLYN. 
</head> 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">and complaint of cruel 
Treatment</hi>. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="bold">T</hi>HE hearing of this Cause coming on, and the Evidence being 
gone 
through, Mr. Elias Boudinot on behalf of the Negro, prayed that Mr. De Klyn should 
oblige himself not to send the said Negro George out of the State, and the Court 
having considered thereof, required Mr. De Klyn so to do, which he accordingly did 
in open Court. 
</p></div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d21"> 
<head>IN THE SAME TERM OF <hi rend="italic">November</hi>, 1785. 
<lb/> 
(p. 525.) 
<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic">Negro</hi> QUAMINI <hi rend="italic">against</hi> WILLIAM 
LEDDEL, <hi rend="italic">Esquire</hi>. 
</head> 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">for Manumission</hi>. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="bold">I</hi>T being alledged on the Part of the said Negro Quamini, that 
several Years 
ago he belonged to Dr. Samuel Tuthill, of Morris County, from whom he was 
purchased 
  
 
<pb n="17"/> 
 
by Captain Augustine Bayles of the same County, that the said Captain Bayles, divers 
Times in his Lifetime promised the said Negro Quamini, that if he would be honest, 
faithful, and industrious, he never should serve any other Master, but should be free 
at his the said Captain Bayles's decease ; that the said Captain Bayles on his 
Death-Bed, considering that his Wife would be left very destitute of Help, directed 
that the said Negro Quamini should continue in her Service during her Widowhood, 
and that then he should be free ; that the said Captain Bayles died in the Year 1781, 
or 1782, and that about Two Years ago, Keziah Bayles his Widow intermarried with 
one Thomas Faircloth. 
</p><p> 
The Court having heard the Testimony for establishing the several Facts aforesaid, 
and having duly considered the same, <hi rend="italic">do order</hi>, on Motion of Mr. 
William De 
Hart, that the said Negro Quamini be discharged, and set at Liberty from the said 
William Leddel, Esquire. 
</p></div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d22"> 
<head> 
<hi rend="italic">May</hi> Term 1787. 
<lb/> 
(p. 449.) 
<lb/> 
The STATE <hi rend="italic">against</hi> JACOB PHILLIPS. 
</head> 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">of Negro</hi> Obadiah Gale. 
</p> 
<p><hi rend="bold">T</hi>HE Court having heard the Evidence and Argument of 
Counsel in this 
Cause, <hi rend="italic">do order</hi> that the said Jacob Phillips enter into 
Recognizance in the 
Sum of One Hundred Pounds, conditioned, that the said Jacob Phillips on the 
Twenty-sixth Day of June next, liberate and discharge from his Service the said 
Obadiah Gale, and the Court do further adjudge and order, that on the Twenty-sixth 
Day of June next, the said Obadiah Gale shall be set at Liberty, and go thereof free 
without Day, and that the said Obediah Gale be in Custody of the Sheriff of 
Hunterdon till the said Twenty-sixth Day of June next, unless the Recognizance is 
entered into by the said 
  
   
<pb n="18"/> 
 
Jacob Phillips before one of the Justices of the Supreme Court, on Motion of Mr. Elias 
Boudinot. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d23"> 
<head> 
<hi rend="italic">September</hi> Term, 1787. 
<lb/> 
(p. 36,&mdash;39.) 
<lb/> 
The STATE <hi rend="italic">against</hi> JOHN B. OLIVER <hi rend="italic">and 
his</hi> Wife.</head> 
<p><hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">of Negro</hi> 
Kate.</p> 
<p> 
<hi rend="bold">T</hi>HE Court after hearing the Arguments of Counsel, <hi 
rend="italic">are of Opinion</hi>, that the said John B. Oliver enter into Recognizance in 
Five Hundred Pounds, conditioned that he do not send or suffer to be sent, the Negro 
Kate mentioned in the said Habeas Corpus, out of this State, till the Court shall take 
further Order therein at the next Term. Recognizance entered into accordingly by the 
said John B. Oliver. 
</p><p> 
The Attorney General and Elisha Boudinot for State. 
</p><p> 
Elias Boudinot and Aaron Ogden for Defendants. 
<note><p> Note, <hi rend="italic">The Counsel for the Defendants in this Case, contended 
that they ought not to be compelled to answer the Allegation of Abuse, because, as the 
Habeas Corpus, was in common form to bring the Body, and no Cause in particular 
alledged, they could not be presumed to come prepared to answer any thing but the 
illegal Detainer of the Negro as a Slave, and insisted that they ought not to be compelled 
to answer this until a sufficient Prosecutor should be indorsed on the Habeas Corpus, 
and 
Security given for the Costs : All this the Court over ruled. The Counsel for the 
Defendants undertook that the Negro should not be ill-treated, and the dispute was 
afterwards settled and the Court heard nothing further of the Affair</hi>. 
</p></note></p>
  
 
<pb n="19"/> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d24"> 
<head> 
<hi rend="italic">September</hi> Term, 1788. 
<lb/> 
(p. 356.) 
<lb/> 
The STATE <hi rend="italic">against</hi> DANIEL TAYLOR, Junior. 
</head> 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">for the bringing up a Negro 
Man named</hi> Harry. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="bold">T</hi>HE Habeas Corpus being returned, the Court proceeded to 
consider the 
same, and Counsel both in favor of the Negro, and on behalf of the said Daniel 
Taylor, Jun. being heard ; <hi rend="italic">It is ordered</hi>, that the said Negro Man 
be discharged from being a Slave, and that he serve the said Daniel Taylor, Jun. his 
Master as a Servant for the Space of Six Years, from the First Day of September instant, 
and that from thenceforward he be entirely discharged and free from Servitude. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d25"> 
<head> 
<hi rend="italic">April</hi> Term, 1789. 
<lb/> 
(p. 437.) 
<lb/> 
The STATE <hi rend="italic">against</hi> DAVID LYON. 
</head> 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">of Negro</hi> Margaret Reap, 
<hi rend="italic">claiming her 
Freedom</hi>. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="bold">U</hi>PON the hearing before the Court, it appeared, that Zacheus 
Mayhew, of 
Massachusetts, by Deed of Gift, dated the first Day of <hi rend="italic">March</hi>, 
1750, did give 
a certain Negro Girl called Flora, unto his Daughter, Lucy Little, then the Wife of 
Little&mdash;That the said Lucy Little afterwards being a Widow, and having One 
Son called William Little, intermarried in Massachusetts with a Dr. Joseph Eaton, 
who came from thence with his Wife to Shrewsberry in <hi 
rend="italic">New-Jersey</hi>, and at 
the same Time brought the said Negro Flora with them&mdash;That on the 31st Day 
of <hi rend="italic">August</hi>, 1752, the said Dr. Eaton sold the said Negro Flora with 
a Child she 
then had called 
 
 
<pb n="20"/> 
 
Rose, unto one John Worthley&mdash;That the said John Worthley by Bill of Sale, 
dated 27th <hi rend="italic">September</hi>, 1753, sold the said Negro Flora to one John 
Williams&mdash;That John Williams the 8th of <hi rend="italic">May</hi>, 1754, sold 
the said 
Negro Flora to the aforesaid Dr. Eaton for the Sum of Sixty-Pounds 
York-Money&mdash;That the said Dr. Eaton upwards of Twenty Years ago, and 
about Five Days after one Jacob Dennis had purchased the aforesaid Negro Girl Rose, 
Daughter of the said Flora, of the said John Worthley, he the said Dr. Eaton informed 
the said Jacob Dennis, he was collecting those Negroes for William Little (his 
Son-in-Law)&mdash;that they should return to him again as they belonged to him ; 
and at that Time and often afterwards declared that he was principled against Slavery, 
and that he never intended the said Flora should belong to his Estate, nor should any 
of his Children be benefited by having her as their Property&mdash;It also appeared 
that the said Lucy Eaton survived her said Husband, the said Dr. Eaton&mdash;That 
shortly after the Death of the said Dr. Eaton (<hi rend="italic">to wit</hi>, about 
Seventeen Years 
ago) one Thomas White applied to the said Lucy Eaton to purchase and did purchase 
at private Sale, a small Spinning Wheel, which she then said she had not any further 
Use for, as she had given Flora free who used to spin on the said Wheel&mdash;That 
since that Time the said Flora has passed for, and been esteemed a free Woman, and 
for a considerable Time worked about in the Neighborhood of the said Widow Eaton, 
and in the House of the said Widow, and for the Wife of John Eaton the eldest Son of 
the said Dr. Eaton, and always received her Wages as well from the said John Eaton's 
Wife, as the Neighbours ; and the said Widow Eaton herself promised to compensate 
her therefor&mdash;And it further appeared that whilst the said Flora worked about 
for herself as aforesaid, she intermarried with a certain Joseph Reap, a free Negro, 
with whom the said Flora has ever since lived unmolested and as a free Woman, and 
still continues so to live&mdash;That after the marriage of the said Flora with the said 
Joseph Reap, she had Two Children called Lydia, and <hi rend="italic">Margaret</hi> 
(the present 
Claimant), that these Children lived with their said Father and Mother, who brought 
them up by their own Industry without any Expence or Trouble to any other Person 
whatsoever, until 
 
 
<pb n="21"/> 
 
 
last Fall, when they were taken away from their said Parents without their 
Consent&mdash;That since the said taking, it appears by a certain Instrument of 
Writing, bearing date the 8th Day of <hi rend="italic">January</hi>, 1789, executed under 
the Hand 
and Seal of the aforesaid William Little, (the Son-in-Law of the said Dr. Eaton, and 
for whom the said Dr. Eaton declared as aforesaid, he was collecting the 
Negroes)&mdash;That the said William Little hath manumitted and set at Liberty the 
said Flora and her said Two Children, Lydia and Margaret ; whereupon 
The Court having considered this state of Facts, and the arguments of Counsel on both 
Sides thereupon, <hi rend="italic">are of Opinion</hi>, That, permitting the said Negro 
Woman 
Flora to remain at Liberty for so long a Time, and to work for herself, and having 
intermarried with the said Joseph Reap a free Man, with whom she has ever since 
lived as a free Woman, is such Evidence of Freedom, both of the said Negro Woman 
Flora, and consequently of her Children, as to entitle the said Negro Margaret Reap 
to her Discharge ; and the Court do therefore accordingly <hi rend="italic">order</hi> 
the said Negro Margaret Reap to be discharged and set at Liberty from the said David 
Lyon ; on 
Motion of the Attorney General. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="italic">Bloomfield, Attorney General, and R. Stockton for the 
State</hi>.&mdash; 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="italic">M. Williamson, and Aaron Ogden for Defendant</hi>. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d26"> 
<head>IN THE SAME TERM OF <hi rend="italic">April</hi>, 1789, 
<lb/> 
(p. 438.) 
<lb/> 
The STATE <hi rend="italic">against</hi> JOHN LEIGHTON. 
</head> 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">of Negro</hi> Lydia Reap, 
<hi rend="italic">returnable the first Day of this Term</hi>. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="bold">T</hi>HE Court order an Attachment against the said John Leighton, 
for 
contempt in not returning the said Writ of <hi rend="italic">Habeas Corpus</hi>, 
agreeably to the 
Command thereof, and for divers Expressions made use of by him reflecting on the 
Authority of this Court and its process, on Motion of Mr. Attorney-General. 
 
  
<pb n="22"/> 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d27"> 
<head> 
<hi rend="italic">April</hi> Term, 1790. 
<lb/> 
(p. 42.) 
<lb/> 
The STATE <hi rend="italic">against</hi> LEWIS PRALL <hi rend="italic">and</hi> 
ROBERT ROSS <hi rend="italic">Administrators of</hi> ISAAC PRALL,  
<hi rend="italic">deceased</hi>. 
</head> 
<p><hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">of Negro</hi> Thomas 
<hi rend="italic">claiming his Freedom</hi>. 
[Habeas Corpus returned and filed.] 
</p><p> 
RETURN, 
 
&ldquo;<hi rend="bold">W</hi>E have the Negro in the above Writ named, at the Day 
and Place as by the said Writ we are commanded, <hi rend="italic">and we do 
certify</hi>, that we as Administrators of all and singular the Goods and Chattels, 
Rights and Credits which were of Isaac Prall, deceased, took Possession of said Negro as 
part of the personal Property of the said Isaac Prall, and that there is no other Cause of 
detaining him. 
LEWIS PRALL, ROBERT ROSS, JUN. 
Administrators.&rdquo; 
</p><p> 
Upon the hearing in this Cause, it appeared to the Court that the said Negro Thomas 
belonged to the said Isaac Prall, deceased&mdash;That the Intestate, about Three 
Years before his Death, and frequently afterwards, declared that Tom should never 
have another Master&mdash;That he had been a faithful Servant to him&mdash;That 
they had been born under one Roof, that they had received Sustenance from one 
Breast, and had broke up the Ground, and always lived together ; and continued to 
shew great Affection and Regard for the Negro until his last Sickness, and during that 
Sickness whilst he had his Senses&mdash;That in his last Illness, on the Friday before 
he died, he requested a Person might be sent for to make his Will, at which Time his 
Sister being present, she asked him what he intended to do with his Negroes, he 
replied they should all be sold but Tom, and he should be free ; which Declaration he 
also made the same Day to several others, with this, further, that Tom should not serve 
any other Master&mdash;The Person sent for to write his Will, did not come 'till the 
next Day, when 
 
 
<pb n="23"/> 
 
the Intestate was so deranged in his Mind as to be incapable of making his Will, and 
continued so until he died, which was on the Wednesday following ; that the said 
Intestate, after he was in some measure deranged, continued to shew strong and 
evident Marks of Affection for the said Negro, and of the Continuance of his Design 
and Intention to make him free : It also appeared to the Court that the said Negro had 
always before the Death of the Intestate, and till that Event took place, been much 
attached to his Master, had shewn a great Affection for him, and had behaved himself 
well and faithfully. 
</p><p> 
The Court having considered of the whole Case, and the Arguments of Counsel for 
and against the Manumission of the Negro, <hi rend="italic">are unanimously of 
Opinion</hi>, That 
the frequent and full Declarations of the Intestate, amounted to more than a bare 
Intention of doing something in future ; that even if these Declarations were taken in 
the Sense of a Promise to do something in future, the good Behaviour of the Negro 
which was admitted on all Hands, the evident Continuation of the Affection of the 
Master as long as he had his Senses, and even when in some Measure deprived of 
them, afforded a strong Ground of Presumption of a Contract between the Negro and 
Master for his Freedom, conditionally on his behaving well, which having performed 
on his Part, the Negro was entitled to his Liberty, and that the Performance of the 
Condition on the Part of the Master and his Representatives, might be effected on this 
Habeas Corpus, <hi rend="italic">do therefore adjudge</hi>, That the said Negro Tom 
being entitled 
to his Freedom, be discharged from the Custody of the said Administrators, and all 
the Representatives of the said Isaac Prall, deceased. On the Motion of Mr. 
Bloomfield, Attorney-General. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="italic">Attorney-General, and Elisha Boudinot, for the State. Freelinghuysen and 
Aaron 
Ogden, for Defendants</hi>. 

 
<pb n="24"/> 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d28"> 
<head> 
<hi rend="italic">May</hi> Term, 1790. 
<lb/> 
(p. 85.) 
<lb/> 
The STATE <hi rend="italic">against</hi> TOBIAS HENDRICKSON. 
</head> 
 
<p><hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">of Negro</hi> Jack  
<hi rend="italic">claiming his Freedom.</hi> 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="bold">T</hi>HE Court having considered this Case under all its 
Circumstances, and it appearing that John Coward the former Master,  
under whom Tobias Hendrickson 
claims Title to the Negro, antecedent to the Year 1785, actually entered into an 
Agreement with Jack for his Freedom, the Terms of which have been fully complied 
with ; <hi rend="italic">The Court are therefore of Opinion</hi>, and  
<hi rend="italic">do order</hi>, the said 
Negro Jack to be liberated from the Custody of the said Tobias 
Hendrickson&mdash;But as John Coward the former Master is not before the Court, 
and of Course not heard, and his Interest may be materially concerned, this Judgment 
for the Liberation of the said Jack is not to affect any present or future Claim of the 
said John Coward. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d29"> 
<head> 
<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic">September</hi> Term, 1790. 
<lb/> 
(p. 119.) 
 
The STATE <hi rend="italic">against</hi> JOHN WARE. 
</head> 
<p><hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">of Negro</hi> Jethro <hi 
rend="italic">(Son of Charity Briggs) claiming his Freedom</hi>. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="bold">I</hi>T appearing to the Court that the said Negro Jethro was born on 
the eighth 
Day of <hi rend="italic">September</hi>, 1768, in the County of Cape-May in this State ; 
that his 
Mother Charity Briggs a (Mulatto Woman) was free at the Time of his 
Birth&mdash;That the said Charity was by Indenture bound by the Justices and 
Overseers of the Poor of the Lower Precinct of Cape-May to one Nathaniel Foster, in 
order to bear the Expences of her having had the Small-Pox&mdash;That in the said 
Year of 1768, the said Charity was purchased by a certain John Connel, she 
 

 
<pb n="25"/> 
 
then having the said Jethro an Infant at her Breast&mdash;That afterwards the Time 
of Service of the said Charity was sold by Connel to Captain Jonathan Jenkins, and 
that the said Charity took her said Son with her&mdash;That the said Jethro her Son, 
was brought up by Jenkins until he was sit for Business, and then was sold unto 
Christopher Leaming of the said County of Cape-May, who kept the said Jethro a 
number of Years, and within Two Years last past sold the said Jethro unto John Ware 
of Cumberland, the Defendant now in Court, for the Term of Twelve Years and Eight 
Months, and by Bill of Sale engaged to warrant the Service of the said Negro Jethro 
for the said Term. 
</p><p>And the Court having taken the said Case into Consideration, <hi 
rend="italic">are unanimously of 
Opinion</hi>, That the said Jethro being the Son of a free Woman, and of the Age of 
Twenty-one Years, is now entitled to his Freedom, and do therefore adjudge, that the 
said Negro Jethro (otherwise called <hi rend="italic">Jethro Briggs)</hi> be discharged 
from the 
Custody of the said John Ware, on the Motion of Joseph Bloomfield, Attorney 
General. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d30"> 
<head> 
IN THE SAME TERM OF <hi rend="italic">September</hi>, 1790. 
<lb/> 
(p. 141.) 
<lb/> 
The STATE <hi rend="italic">against</hi> JAMES ANDERSON. 
</head> 
<p><hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">of Negro</hi> Silas <hi 
rend="italic">claiming his Freedom</hi>. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="italic">Returnable Saturday 11th September, and returned accordingly</hi>. 
</p><p> 
The Defendant appears with the Negro, to do and receive, &amp;c. pursuant to 
Recognizance. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="bold">T</hi>HE Case stated by Counsel for, the Opinion of the Court is as 
follows, 
That on the fourth Day of December, 1761, John Horsfield was entitled to Two Negro 
Girls, named Betty and Nelly as Slaves ; and on the said fourth Day of December by 
his last Will and Testament, (then dated) made the following Devise, &ldquo;Item, my 
Two Negro Girls named Betty and Nelly, I leave to be sold by my Executors, hereafter 
named, for the Term of Fifteen Years, and at the end of that Time to be free, and 
 
 
<pb n="26"/> 
 
the Money arising thereby, to be equally divided amongst my Four youngest 
Daughters, and they that buy the said Negro Girls, if the said Girls or either of them 
Misbehave, or become chargeable, it must be at the Risque or Cost of the Buyer.&rdquo; 
That the said Executors sold the said Negro Girls to one Covenhoven, who sold them 
to the present Defendant Anderson, for the Term mentioned in the Will&mdash;That 
Betty had a Child (the Negro Silas) now of full Age, which Child was not born in 
Matrimony. 
</p><p> 
The Court having considered the above State of Facts, are <hi rend="italic">are 
unanimously of  
Opinion</hi>, That on the Death of John Horsfield the Testator, Betty ceased to be a 
Slave, that she ceasing to be a Slave, no Child born of her Body can be deemed so by 
the Birth of such Child during the Fifteen Years, and that the Claim of James 
Anderson to hold the said Negro Silas as a Slave, is not warranted by Law : 
<hi rend="italic">Wherefore it is ordered</hi>, That the same Silas be liberated from the 
illegal 
Detention of the same James Anderson, and he is hereby liberated accordingly, <hi 
rend="italic">ex 
motione</hi> J. Bloomfield, Attorney-General. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="italic">The Attorney-General, Fisher, Howell and Todd for the negro.&mdash;R. 
Stockton and Frelinghysen for defendant</hi>. 
 
<note><p>NOTE. 
 
<hi rend="italic">Chief Justice Kinsey, in giving the Opinion of the Court said</hi>, 
BY the words of the Will taken together, It appears that the Testator intended to 
increase the Daughters' Portions, to effect this Purpose, he ordered the Mother of the 
Negro now before the Court, and another, to be sold by his Executors for the Term of 
Fifteen Years, and every Construction which will not detract from this Intention 
should be made in a Case of this Nature&mdash;It is also evident that the Testator 
foreseeing probably, that some Means might, after his Death, be made use of to 
frustrate his benevolent Design, took care to guard against it, by ordering that 
whoever should purchase these Negroes, the Purchasers should run all Risques, and 
be at all the Expence which should arise from their Misbehaviour, the most probable 
Grounds on which that Attempt might be made&mdash;The Chief Justice was of 
Opinion, that these words take in the Fact which has happened, and the Purchaser 
ought not to avail himself of it by making a Slave of the Child&mdash; 
</p></note> 

 
<pb n="27"/> 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d31"> 
<head> 
IN THE SAME TERM OF <hi rend="italic">September</hi>, 1790. 
<lb/> 
(p. 120.) 
<lb/> 
The STATE <hi rend="italic">against</hi> JOSHUA FARLEY. 
</head> 
<p> 
<hi rend="bold">O</hi>RDERED, that a Habeas Corpus do issue, directed to the said 
Joshua 
Farley for the Body of Negro 
</p><p> 
He thought this might be sufficient to say on the present Occasion, but he would go 
further, and say that in his Opinion, at the Death of the Testator, the two Negro 
Women were not Slaves, no body at that Time had that absolute Property in either, 
which distinguishes the Slave from what we call a Servant, and the Retention of the 
temporary Interest excludes that Supposition intirely&mdash;The Argument made use 
of by the Counsel for the Claimant, from the Word <hi rend="italic">sell</hi>, might 
have had some 
Weight if it had not been coupled with and explained by the particular Time to which 
it applies, but taken together, it is of no kind of Consequence, neither could he give 
his assent to the Idea suggested that both were Slaves until the Expiration of the 
Fifteen Years : Indeed the thought in his Opinion was absurd, for he had no other Idea 
of a Slave but where, the Servitude is perpetual, or in other Words for 
Life&mdash;Neither did he see the Impropriety of supposing, that the Right to 
Freedom subject to the Temporary servitude, might vest in the Negro at the Death of 
the Testator&mdash;If this be so, and if the Misbehaviour of the Mothers were not to 
affect themselves, he could not bring himself to entertain an Opinion that it should 
affect their innocent offspring and make them Slaves : all that Anderson bought was 
the Service of the Mother for a Term of Years, and that too subject to all Risques : As 
the Party buying, had nothing else in Contemplation, no Construction can be unjust 
which gives that Right in the fullest extent to him, and if he suffers by his Bargain, it 
is no more than he undertook to subject himself to, and a Construction of this Nature 
appeared much more Rational than one which subjects a human Creature to be a Slave 
for no Fault of his own. For these Reasons the Court were unanimously of Opinion 
that the Claim of James Anderson is unfounded and the Negro Boy should be 
liberated from his Custody. 
 
 
<pb n="28"/> 
</p><p> 
Joseph here on the first Day of the next Term, <hi rend="italic">ex  me-Linn</hi>. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d32"> 
<head> 
<hi rend="italic">November</hi> Term, 1790. 
<lb/> 
(p. 165.) 
<lb/> 
The STATE <hi rend="italic">against</hi> JOSHUA FARLEY. 
</head> 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">of Negro</hi> Joe <hi 
rend="italic">claiming his Freedom</hi>. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="bold">T</hi>HE said Joshua Farley having returned that the said Negro Joe 
in the Writ 
named, before the coming of the said Writ, was and still is, the Negro Slave of him 
the said Joshua Farley, and that he had, and still hath Right and Title to hold the said 
Joe a Slave during Life ; and thereof tendered an Issue to the Country, and prayed the 
Court that the said Issue so tendered might be tried by a Jury of his Country ; 
whereupon, The Court having heard Counsel, and taking the Matter into 
Consideration, are of Opinion that a Jury in this Case is improper, and therefore do 
refuse the same. 
</p><p> 
The Evidence both for and against the Claim of the said Negro Joe to be set at Liberty, 
being fully heard, and Counsel thereupon on both sides. 
</p><p> 
The Court do adjudge that the said Negro Joe is illegally detained in the Custody of 
the said Joshua Farley, and therefore do order him to be discharged from the said 
Custody and illegal Detention of him the said Joshua Farley, on the Motion of Elisha 
Boudinot. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d33"> 
<head> 
<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic">May</hi> Term, 1791. 
<lb/> 
(p. 248.) 
The STATE <hi rend="italic">against</hi> JOSEPH BEAVERS, JOHN CLIFFORD, <hi 
rend="italic">and</hi> 
JOHN MARTIN, <hi rend="italic">Administrators of</hi> EDWARD CLIFFORD, 
<hi rend="italic">deceased</hi>. 
</head> 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">ad subjiciendum, for the 
Liberation of Negro</hi> 
Abraham Solomons, <hi rend="italic">and Negro</hi> Dolly <hi rend="italic">his 
Wife</hi>. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="italic">The Attorney-General, Elisha Boudinot, and Linn, Counsel for the 
Negroes.&mdash;Leake and Richard Stockton, Counsel for the said 
Administrators</hi>. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="bold">T</hi>HE Defendants having returned the Bodies with the Cause &amp;c. 
&ldquo;That they are the Negro Slaves of 
 
 
<pb n="29"/> 
 
the said Defendants of the Estate of their Intestate, and that they have Right to hold 
them as such, during Life,&rdquo; and thereof having tendered an Issue to the Country, 
and prayed that the same might be tried by a Jury of the Country. 
</p><p> 
The Court considering that this Point was fully argued and determined by them in the 
Case of the State against Joshua Farley, <hi rend="italic">November Term</hi> last, do 
refuse to 
hear any Argument thereupon, and do direct that the Cause be opened and heard 
before the Court in the usual Manner ; whereupon, 
The Court having heard the Return filed and Evidence and Allegations of the Parties, 
<hi rend="italic">do order</hi>, on Motion of Mr. Leake Attorney for the said 
Administrators, that 
the said Abraham and Dolley be remanded into the Custody of the said 
Administrators. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d34"> 
<head> 
IN THE SAME TERM OF <hi rend="italic">May</hi>, 1791. 
<lb/> 
(p. 257.) 
<lb/> 
The STATE <hi rend="italic">against</hi> ABRAHAM PROBASCO. 
</head> 
<p><hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">of Negro</hi> Hagar, <hi 
rend="italic">Wife of</hi> Cornelius 
Wilson, <hi rend="italic">and</hi> Cornelius, Lydia <hi rend="italic">and</hi> Anna <hi 
rend="italic">their Children, praying 
their Freedom, detained by the Defendant, claiming their Service for Life</hi>. 
[Habeas Corpus returned this Term and filed.] 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="bold">T</hi>HE Court having fully heard the Allegations and Proofs of all 
Parties, and 
the Arguments of Counsel thereon ; it appeared to the Court, that the said Negroes 
brought up on the said Writ, were in the Year 1776, the Slaves of William Winds, 
Esq. of the County of Morris  ;&mdash;That the said William Winds, in consideration 
of the good Behaviour of the said Negro Cornelius Wilson the Father, in the said Year 
1776, did manumit and set free the said Cornelius, his Wife Hagar, and all the said 
Children&mdash;That the said Cornelius and his Family built a House on the Lands 
of the said William Winds by his Assistance, and with his Permission, and lived 
thereon as Free Citizens for the Term of Three Years, when the said Cornelius Wilson 
and Wife were taken sick ; on which the said William Winds removed them to a 
House near his own, and took care of them till they recovered, when he employed 
them and paid them 
 
 
<pb n="30"/> 
 
Wages for their Labor as free Persons ; That the said William Winds, fearing they 
might become a burthen on his Estate, urged them to obtain security to indemnify him 
from any Expence in Case of their becoming a Charge&mdash;That thereupon the 
said William Winds gave to the said Negro Cornelus Wilson a Pass to go into the 
County of Monmouth to obtain such Security&mdash;That the said Cornelius 
accordingly went to the said County of Monmouth, and agreed with Abraham 
Probasco the Defendant, that in Consideration of his becoming Security to the said 
William Winds, he and his Family would serve him Five Years&mdash;That the said 
Abraham Probasco in Consequence thereof, came to the said William Winds and 
agreed with him accordingly, and in order to secure the said William Winds, the said 
Abraham Probasco proposed, that the said William Winds should give to the said 
Abraham a Bill of Sale for the said Negroes, and at the end of Five Years, the said 
Abraham would release the said Negroes and set them free : That a Bill of Sale for the 
Consideration of Five Shillings, without any Condition or Reservation was drawn up 
accordingly by the said Abraham, and executed by the said William, and a Receipt 
given by the said Abraham to the said William therefor, calling it a Deed of 
Gift&mdash;That at the Execution of the said Instrument or Bill of Sale, the said 
William Winds mentioned his Fear least the said Abraham should claim the said 
Negroes as Slaves by virtue of the said Bill of Sale, when he and the Witnesses should 
be dead, and declared that altho' he could get Two Hundred Pounds for the said 
Negroes, yet he had given the said Bill of Sale for Five Shillings in order that they 
might be free&mdash;That the said Negroes have faithfully served the said Abraham 
for more than Six Years under the said Agreement, and are still detained by the said 
Abraham who claims their Service for Life by Virtue of the said Bill of Sale. 
The Court therefore having maturely considered the Premises, <hi rend="italic">are 
unanimously 
of Opinion</hi>, That the said Negroes and every of them, be discharged from the 
Custody of the said Abraham Probasco as free Citizens, and they are hereby 
discharged accordingly, on Motion of Mr. Attorney-General, Bloomfield. 
<hi rend="italic">The Attorney General, and R. Stockton for the Negroes. Kirkpatrick for 
Defendant</hi>. 
 
  
<pb n="31"/> 
</p> 
</div1> 
 
<div1 type="section" id="d35"> 
<head> 
<hi rend="italic">September</hi> Term, 1792. 
<lb/> 
(p. 471.) 
<lb/> 
The STATE <hi rend="italic">against</hi> WILLIAM LAIRD. 
</head> 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">of Negro</hi> Rachel <hi 
rend="italic">claiming her Freedom</hi>. 
[<hi rend="italic">The Writ returned and filed</hi>.] 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="bold">T</hi>HE Court taking into Consideration this Case, and it appearing 
to depend 
on the Decision, in the Case of the State against James Anderson, on the Habeas 
Corpus of Negro Silas, <hi rend="italic">September Term</hi>, 1790, ordered, That the 
said Negro 
Rachel be discharged and entirely liberated from the Custody of the said William 
Laird, on the Motion of the Attorney-General. 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d36"> 
<head> 
<hi rend="italic">April</hi> Term, 1793. 
<lb/> 
The STATE <hi rend="italic">against</hi> BENJAMIN COVENHOVEN. 
</head> 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">of Negro</hi> Agnus, <hi 
rend="italic">claiming her Freedom</hi>. 
[<hi rend="italic">The Writ returned and filed</hi>.] 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="bold">T</hi>HE Court having considered this Case, and it appearing that the 
same 
depends on the Decisions in the Case of the State against James Anderson, on the 
Habeas Corpus of Negro Silas, <hi rend="italic">September Term</hi>, 1790, ordered 
that the said 
Negro Agnus be discharged, and entirely liberated from the Custody of the said 
Benjamin Covenhoven, on Motion of the Attorney-General. 
 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" id="d37"> 
<head> 
<hi rend="italic">May</hi> Term, 1793. 
<lb/> 
The STATE <hi rend="italic">against</hi> JAMES PITNEY <hi rend="italic">of the County 
of Morris</hi>. 
</head> 
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">On</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi rend="italic">of Negro</hi> James, <hi 
rend="italic">a Boy about Thirteen Years of Age, claiming his Freedom</hi>. 
</p><p> 
<hi rend="bold">T</hi>HE Case upon the <hi rend="italic">Habeas Corpus</hi> and 
Return, coming before the Court appeared to be as follows, 
</p><p> 
Jasper Smith of the Township of Maidenhead, in the County of Hunterdon, by Will 
bearing Date the 29th Day of <hi rend="italic">November</hi>, 1769, (amongst others) 
made the 
following Devise, &ldquo;And as for all my Negroes, Jack, old Juddy, and young Juddy, 
with all her Children, and with all their Cloaths, Chests, Beds, and Bedding, after my 
Decease, I do hereby order that they are all 
 

 
<pb n="32"/> 
 
by me for ever freed from all Servitude from me or any of mine, and from all others 
whatsoever at my Decease, and that they may go and work for their Living with 
whomsoever they please&rdquo;&mdash;That the said Jasper Smith afterwards 
died&mdash;That notwithstanding the said Will, the said Negroes, and in particular 
the said young Juddy were detained by Joshua Smith, Son of the said Jasper, and one 
of the Devisees named in the said Will, that during such Detention, and before the 
Death of the said Joshua, the Negro James in the present Habeas Corpus named, was 
born of the Body of the said Juddy&mdash;That the said Joshua Smith died, leaving 
Keziah Smith and John Biles his Executors, and the said Negro Juddy and her Son 
James in their Possession&mdash;That on the 9th Day of March, 1790, the said 
Keziah Smith and John Biles, as Executors of the said Joshua Smith, by Bill of Sale 
of that Date, conveyed the said Negro James to James Pitney the Defendant in the 
Habeas Corpus named ; but that no Bond or other Security whatsoever was given by 
the said Jasper Smith, the Master of the said young Juddy and Testator in the Will 
above named, pursuant to the Act of Assembly passed 16th <hi 
rend="italic">November</hi>, 1769 ; whereupon, The Court having taken due 
Consideration, <hi rend="italic">are unanimously of Opinion</hi>, That the said Negro 
Juddy the Mother of the said James, was a free Woman by the Will of the said Jasper 
Smith, the want of Security pursuant to the said Act of Assembly notwithstanding, and 
that consequently the said James her Son is entitled to his Freedom, and do therefore 
<hi rend="italic">order</hi>, that the said James be discharged from the illegal Detention 
of the said James Pitney, and he is discharged accordingly, on the Motion of Mr. 
Bloomfield for the State. 
</p> 
<trailer><hi rend="italic">FINIS</hi>.</trailer> 
</div1> 
</body> 
<back id="d38"> 
<div1 type="errata" id="d39"> 
<list> 
<head>ERRATA.</head> 
 
<item>Page 5, line 4, dele <hi rend="italic">of the State</hi>.</item> 
 
<item>Page 8, after line 7, read <hi rend="italic">Kinsey, Elias Boudinot, and  
Skinner Attorney-General, for the Negro</hi>.</item> 
 
<item><hi rend="italic">Sergeant and Paterson for Defendant</hi>.</item> 
 
<item>Same page, after line 16, dele the names of Counsel.</item> 
 
<item>Page 15, line 24, for <hi rend="italic">Eauhouse</hi> read  
<hi rend="italic">Vanhorne</hi>.</item> 
  
</list> 
</div1> 
</back> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
