<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WalCivi"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="WalCivi"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Civil Rights Movement: Fraud, Sham, and Hoax</title>
<title type="sort">civil rights movement fraud, sham and hoax</title>
<author>Wallace, George C. (George Corley), 1919-</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp> 
<name>nova.cc.purdue.edu</name>  
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic TextCenter</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">46</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WalCivi</idno>  
<date value="1992-02">February 1992</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1992 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476451</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Civil Rights Movement: Fraud, Sham, and Hoax</title>
<title type="sort">civil rights movement fraud, sham and hoax</title>
<author>George C. Wallace</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Publisher</publisher>  
</publicationStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>  
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme 
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed 
of the text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in 
SpeFQue1 for page one of Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1964-07-04">July 4, 1964</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-08">August 1994</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Bryson Clevenger, Jr., U.Va. Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>TEI header added.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="1993-02">February 1993</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>David Seaman</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>minimal TEI tagging and spell-checked</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 
<front id="d2"> 
<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> 
<head>INTRODUCTION</head> 
 
<pb n="1" id="WalCivi1"/> 
 
<p>George C. Wallace, Governor of Alabama from 1962 to 1966, has 
gained enduring fame as one of the south's most articulate and 
uncompromising spokesmen for segregation of the races.  One possible 
reason for his devotion to the cause is suggested by a remark 
attributed to Wallace following his early defeat for the 
governorship 
in 1958, to the effect that his rival had "out-segged" him but 
that it would never happen again.  Thereafter his campaign 
platform became 
"Segregation now, Segregation tomorrow, Segregation forever!" 
</p><p>During the 1962 campaign, Wallace said concerning the 
expected 
government action to enforce desegregation of the schools:  "I 
shall 
refuse to abide by any illegal Federal court order, even to the 
point 
of standing in the schoolhouse door."  Less than a year later, he 
was 
handed an opportunity to make good his boast &mdash; which he promptly 
did by 
standing in the doorway of the University of Alabama to block the 
path 
of two Negro students seeking to register.  With State Troopers 
and 
Highway Patrolmen at his back, Wallace barred the entry into the 
registration building of James A. Hood and Vivian J. Malone, 
along 
with accompanying officials of the Federal government.  In a 
dramatic 
face-to-face encounter on the steps with Deputy United States 
Attorney 
General Nicholas Katzenbach, the Alabama governor responded to 
demands 
that he obey a Federal court order by reading a proclamation 
declaring 
that his aim in barring the door was not "for defiance's sake, 
but for 
the purpose of raising basic and fundamental constitutional 
questions."  Some four hours later, following an executive order 
from 
President John F. Kennedy federalizing the Alabama National Guard 
and 
ordering units of the 31st Division to the campus, Governor 
Wallace 
lifted his personal blockade and stood aside as the two Negro 
students 
registered peacefully at the University. 
</p><p>That was not the end of Governor Wallace's defiance of the 
 
Executive and Judicial arms of the Federal government.  In 
September, 
1963, he dispatched National Guardsmen and State Troopers (under 
the 
notorious Colonel Al Lingo) to various city schools after Federal 
 
court orders had been received calling for an end to segregation 
in 
the classrooms.  In one city, Tuskegee, the Governor closed down 
a 
public school even though the local School Board had already 
agreed to 
the integration order.  Once again President Kennedy had to 
intervene 
by nationalizing the Guard in order to pull the troops away from 
the 
beleaguered schools. 
</p><p>Early in 1964, in protest against the civil rights bill 
before 
Congress, Wallace announced his intention to run for the 
presidency on 
<pb n="2" id="WalCivi2"/> 
a nonparty basis &mdash; and revealed the continuing vitality of the 
politics 
of prejudice by his strong showing in out-of-state Democratic 
primaries.  (As the present speech proudly points out, he polled 
34 
percent of the Democratic vote in Wisconsin, 30 percent in 
Indiana, 
and 43 percent in Maryland.)  Typical of his fiery speeches on 
the 
race issue was the Fourth of July address reprinted here, 
delivered at 
the Southeastern Fairgrounds in Atlanta, Georgia.  Later on 
Wallace 
withdrew his candidacy, evidently satisfied that he had made his 
point 
and could serve the cause best be leaving his supporters free to 
vote 
for the Republican candidate, Barry Goldwater, who also opposed 
the 
civil rights bill.  (As it happened, most of the South held firm 
for 
the Democratic ticket, and Lyndon Johnson won the national 
election in 
a landslide.) 
</p><p>In his Independence Day attack upon the Civil Rights 
program as 
"a fraud, a sham, and a hoax," Governor Wallace focused upon 
three 
sources of evil assertedly linked to the legislation:  an 
expanding 
Federal government, the Supreme Court, and the Communists.  He 
reserved his most extravagant dispraise for the Court:  "there is 
only 
one word to describe the Federal Judiciary today.  That word is 
'lousy.'  They assert more power than claimed by King George III, 
more 
power than Hitler, Mussolini, or Khrushchev ever had. . . .  They 
have 
become arrogant, contemptuous, highhanded, and literal despots." 
given this kind of record on the part of the Court, it was only 
natural to draw the obvious parallel with the machinations of the 
 
Communists.  "I do not call the members of the United States 
Supreme 
Court Communists," said Wallace.  But he did say:  "the record 
reveals 
for the past number of years that the chief, if not the only, 
beneficiaries of the present Court's rulings have been duly and 
lawfully convicted criminals, Communists, atheists and clients of 
 
vociferous left-wing minority groups.  You can't convict a 
Communist 
in our Federal Court System." 
</p><p>The connection of all this with Civil Rights was easy to 
see.  It 
was the Court, Wallace showed, that had set in motion the Civil 
Rights 
movement which now was pressing for equality of treatment and of 
access in the public accommodations of the deep south &mdash; its 
schools, 
buses, lunch counters, playgrounds, swimming pools &mdash; thereby 
threatening to upset a revered and peculiar institution which for 
many 
had become a way of life beyond censure or challenge.  The 
Supreme 
Court, then, was bad enough; but behind the Court lay a deeper 
and 
more insidious threat:  "a left-wing power monster has risen up 
in 
<pb n="3" id="WalCivi3"/> 
this nation," said Wallace.  "It has invaded the Government.  It 
has 
invaded the news media.  It has invaded the leadership of many of 
our 
churches. . . .  It consists of many and various and powerful 
interests, but it has combined into one massive drive and is held 
 
together by the cohesive power of the emotions, setting forth 
civil 
rights as supreme to all." 
</p><p>Nearly two centuries before, in an appeal to the Whigs of 
his own 
day, the great British orator and statesman Edmund Burke has 
observed 
that "when bad men combine, the good must associate; else they 
will 
fall, one by one, an unpitied sacrifice in a contemptible 
struggle." 
Governor Wallace, repeating those ringing phrases almost verbatim 
(but 
without credit), went on to declare his own candidacy and to 
predict 
that the numbers supporting his views across the country were 
enough 
to constitute a "balance of power" and to "control the election 
of 
the President."  That prediction turned out to be less than 
accurate; 
and with the victory of Lyndon Johnson the movement for Civil 
Rights 
and social integration &mdash; for equality of the races before the 
law and 
in the streets &mdash; gained still greater strength and confidence of 
 
ultimate success. 
<lb/> 
GEORGE C. WALLACE 
</p> 
</div1></front> 
<body id="d4"> 
<div1 type="speech"  id="d5"> 
<head>THE CIVIL RIGHTS MOVEMENT: FRAUD, SHAM, AND HOAX</head> 
<pb n="4" id="WalCivi4"/> 
<p>We come here today in deference to the memory of those 
stalwart 
patriots who on July 4, 1776, pledged their lives, their 
fortunes, and 
their sacred honor to establish and defend the proposition that 
governments are created by the people, empowered by the people, 
derive 
their just powers from the consent of the people, and must 
forever 
remain subservient to the will of the people. 
</p><p>Today, 188 years later, we celebrate that occasion and 
find 
inspiration and determination and courage to preserve and protect 
the 
great principles of freedom enunciated in the Declaration of 
Independence. 
</p><p>It is therefore a cruel irony that the President of the 
United 
States has only yesterday signed into law the most monstrous 
piece of 
legislation ever enacted by the United States Congress. 
</p><p>It is a fraud, a sham, and a hoax. 
</p><p>This bill will live in infamy.  To sign it into law at any 
time 
is tragic.  To do so upon the eve of the celebration of our 
independence insults the intelligence of the American people. 
</p><p>It dishonors the memory of countless thousands of our dead 
who 
offered up their very lives in defense of principles which this 
bill 
destroys. 
</p><p>Never before in the history of this nation have so many 
human and 
property rights been destroyed by a single enactment of the 
Congress. 
It is an act of tyranny.  It is the assassin's knife stuck in the 
back 
of liberty. 
</p><p>With this assassin's knife and a blackjack in the hand of 
the 
Federal force-cult, the left-wing liberals will try to force us 
back 
into bondage.  Bondage to a tyranny more brutal than that imposed 
by 
the British monarchy which claimed power to rule over the lives 
of our 
forefathers under sanction of the Divine Right of kings. 
</p><p>Today, this tyranny is imposed by the central government 
which 
claims the right to rule over our lives under sanction of the 
omnipotent black-robed despots who sit on the bench of the United 
 
States Supreme Court. 
</p><p>This bill is fraudulent in intent, in design, and in 
execution. 
</p><p>It is misnamed.  Each and every provision is mistitled. 
It was 
rammed through the congress on the wave of ballyhoo, promotions, 
and 
publicity stunts reminiscent of P. T. Barnum. 
</p><p>It was enacted in an atmosphere of pressure, intimidation, 
and 
even cowardice, as demonstrated by the refusal of the United 
States 
Senate to adopt an amendment to submit the bill to a vote of the 
people. 
</p><pb n="5" id="WalCivi5"/> 
<p>To illustrate the fraud &mdash; it is not a Civil Rights Bill.  It 
is a 
Federal Penal Code.  It creates Federal crimes which would take 
volumes to list and years to tabulate because it affects the 
lives of 
192 million American citizens.  Every person in every walk and 
station 
of life and every aspect of our daily lives becomes subject to 
the 
criminal provisions of this bill. 
</p><p>It threatens our freedom of speech, of assembly, or 
association, 
and makes the exercise of these Freedoms a federal crime under 
certain 
conditions. 
</p><p>It affects our political rights, our right to trial by 
jury, our 
right to the full use and enjoyment of our private property, the 
freedom from search and seizure of our private property and 
possessions, the freedom from harassment by Federal police and, 
in 
short, all the rights of individuals inherent in a society of 
free 
men. 
</p><p>Ministers, lawyers, teachers, newspapers, and every 
private 
citizen must guard his speech and watch his actions to avoid the 
deliberately imposed booby traps put into this bill.  It is 
designed 
to make Federal crimes of our customs, beliefs, and traditions. 
Therefore, under the fantastic powers of the Federal judiciary to 
 
punish for contempt of court and under their fantastic powers to 
regulate our most intimate aspects of our lives by injunction, 
every 
American citizen is in jeopardy and must stand guard against 
these 
despots. 
</p><p>Yet there are those who call this a good bill. 
</p><p>It is people like Senator Hubert Humphrey and other 
members of 
Americans for Democratic Action.  It is people like Ralph McGill 
and 
other left-wing radical apologists. 
</p><p>They called it a good bill before it was amended to 
restore the 
right to trial by jury in certain cases. 
</p><p>Yet a Federal judge may still try one without a jury under 
the 
provisions of this bill.  It was the same persons who said it was 
a 
good bill before the amendment pretending to forbid busing of 
pupils 
from neighborhood schools.  Yet a Federal judge may still order 
busing 
from one neighborhood school to another.  They have done it, they 
will 
continue to do it.  As a matter of fact, it is but another 
evidence of 
the deceitful intent of the sponsors of this bill for them to 
claim 
that it accomplished any such thing. 
</p><p>It was left-wing radicals who led the fight in the Senate 
for the 
so-called civil rights bill now about to enslave our nation. 
</p><p>We find Senator Hubert Humphrey telling the people of the 
United 
<pb n="6" id="WalCivi6"/> 
States that "non-violent" demonstrations would continue to serve 
a 
good purpose through a "long, busy and constructive summer." 
</p><p>Yet this same Senator told the people of this country that 
 
passage of this monstrous bill would ease tensions and stop 
demonstrations. 
</p><p>This is the same Senator who has suggested, now that the 
Civil 
Rights Bill is passed, that the President call the fifty state 
Governors together to work out ways and means to enforce this 
rotten 
measure. 
</p><p>There is no need for him to call on me.  I am not about to 
be a 
party to anything having to do with the law that is going to 
destroy 
individual freedom and liberty in this country. 
</p><p>I am having nothing to do with enforcing a law that will 
destroy 
our free enterprise system. 
</p><p>I am having nothing to do with enforcing a law that will 
destroy 
neighborhood schools. 
</p><p>I am having nothing to do with enforcing a law that will 
destroy 
the rights of private property. 
</p><p>I am having nothing to do with enforcing a law that 
destroys your 
right &mdash; and my right &mdash; to choose my neighbors &mdash; or to sell my 
house to 
whomever I choose. 
</p><p>I am having nothing to do with enforcing a law that 
destroys the 
labor seniority system. 
</p><p>I am having nothing to do with this so-called civil rights 
bill. 
</p><p>The liberal left-wingers have passed it. Now let them 
employ 
some pinknik social engineers in Washington, D.C., To figure out 
what 
to do with it. 
</p><p>The situation reminds me of the little boy looking at the 
blacksmith as he hammered a red-hot horseshoe into the proper 
shape. 
</p><p>After minutes of hammering, the blacksmith took the 
horseshoe, 
splashed it into a tub of water and threw it steaming onto a 
sawdust 
pile. 
</p><p>The little fellow picked up the horseshoe, dropped it 
quickly. 
</p><p>"What's the matter, son," the blacksmith said, "is that 
shoe too 
hot to handle?" 
</p><p>"No sir," the little boy said, "it just don't take me long 
to 
look at a horseshoe." 
</p><p>It's not going to take the people of this country long to 
look at 
the Civil Rights Bill, either. 
</p><p>And they are going to discard it just as quickly as the 
little 
boy tossed away the still hot horseshoe. 
</p><pb n="7" id="WalCivi7"/> 
<p>But I am not here to talk about the separate provisions of the 
 
Federal Penal Code.  I am here to talk about principles which 
have 
been overthrown by the enactment of this bill.  The principles 
that 
you and I hold dear.  The principles for which our forefathers 
fought 
and died to establish and to defend.  The principles for which we 
came 
here to rededicate ourselves. 
</p><p>But before I get into that, let me point out one important 
fact. 
It would have been impossible for the American people to have 
been 
deceived by the sponsors of this bill had there been a 
responsible 
American press to tell the people exactly what the bill 
contained.  If 
they had had the integrity and the guts to tell the truth, this 
bill 
would never have been enacted. 
</p><p>Whoever heard of truth put to the worst in free and open 
encounter?  We couldn't get the truth to the American people. 
</p><p>You and I know that that's extremely difficult to do where 
our 
newspapers are owned by out-of-state interests.  Newspapers which 
are 
run and operated by left-wing liberals, Communist sympathizers, 
and 
members of the Americans for Democratic Action and other 
Communist 
front organizations with high sounding names. 
</p><p>However, we will not be intimidated by the vultures of the 
liberal left-wing press.  We will not be deceived by their lies 
and 
distortions of truth.  We will not be swayed by their brutal 
attacks 
upon the character and reputation of any honest citizen who dares 
 
stand up and fight for liberty. 
</p><p>And, we are not going to be influenced by intellectually 
bankrupt 
editors of the Atlanta Journal and Constitution, one of whom has 
presided over the dissolution of the once great Atlanta 
Constitution. 
</p><p>We can understand his bitterness in his bleak failure, but 
we 
need not tolerate his vituperative and venomous attacks upon the 
integrity and character of our people.  These editors, like many 
other 
left-wingers in the liberal press, are not influenced by 
tradition. 
Theirs is a tradition of scalawags.  Their mealy-mouthed 
platitudes 
disgrace the honored memory of their predecessors &mdash; such men of 
character as Henry Grady, Joel Chandler Harris, and Clarke 
Howell, men 
who made the name of the Atlanta Constitution familiar in every 
household throughout the South.  They are not worthy to shine the 
 
shoes of those great men. 
</p><p>In this connection I want to pay my highest respects and 
compliments to the dedicated men of Atlanta and of Georgia who 
gave to 
the people of their state what is destined to become the true 
voice of 
<pb n="8" id="WalCivi8"/> 
the south.  I have reference to the great newspaper the Atlanta 
Times. 
</p><p>It is a sad commentary on the period in which we live that 
it is 
necessary for the people of a great city to start their own 
newspaper 
in order to get the truth. 
</p><p>I hope you have some success in this venture and I assure 
you 
that there will be many subscribers in the State of Alabama 
including 
myself. 
</p><p>As I have said before, that Federal Penal Code could never 
have 
been enacted into law if we had had a responsible press who was 
willing to tell the American people the truth about what it 
actually 
provides.  Nor would we have had a bill had it not been for the 
United 
States Supreme Court. 
</p><p>Now on the subject of the court let me make it clear that 
I am 
not attacking any member of the United States Supreme Court as an 
 
individual.  However, I do attack their decisions, I question 
their 
intelligence, their common sense and their judgment, I consider 
the 
Federal Judiciary system to be the greatest single threat to 
individual freedom and liberty in the United States today, and 
I'm 
going to take off the gloves in talking about these people. 
</p><p>There is only one word to describe the Federal judiciary 
today. 
That word is "lousy." 
</p><p>They assert more power than claimed by King George III, 
more 
power than Hitler, Mussolini, or Khrushchev ever had.  They 
assert the 
power to declare unconstitutional our very thoughts.  To create 
for us 
a system of moral and ethical values.  To outlaw and declare 
unconstitutional, illegal, and immoral the customs, traditions, 
and 
beliefs of the people, and furthermore they assert the authority 
to 
enforce their decrees in all these subjects upon the American 
people 
without their consent. 
</p><p>This is a matter that has been of great concern to many 
legal 
authorities.  The Council of State Governments composed of 
representatives of the fifty States sponsored the proposal just 
last 
year seeking to curb the powers of this body of judicial tyrants. 
The 
Conference of Chief Justices of all of the state Supreme Courts 
of 
this nation has also issued an historic statement urging judicial 
 
restraint upon the Court. 
</p><p>This latter group said, "the value of a firm statement by 
us lies 
in the fact that we speak as members of all the state appellate 
courts 
with a background of many years experience in the determination 
of 
<pb n="9" id="WalCivi9"/> 
thousands of cases of all kinds.  Surely there are those who will 
 
respect the declaration of what we believe. 
</p><p>"It has long been an American boast that we have a 
government of 
laws and not of men.  We believe that any study of recent 
decisions of 
the supreme court will raise at least considerable doubt as to 
the 
validity of that boast." 
</p><p>in addition, the state legislatures have for years flooded 
the 
Congress with resolutions condemning usurpations of power by the 
Federal judiciary. 
</p><p>The court today, just as in 1776, is deaf to the voices of 
the 
people and their repeated entreaties:  they have become arrogant, 
 
contemptuous, highhanded, and literal despots. 
</p><p>It has been said that power corrupts and absolute power 
corrupts 
absolutely.  There was never greater evidence as to the proof of 
this 
statement than in the example of the present Federal Judiciary. 
</p><p>I want to touch upon just a few of the acts of tyranny 
which have 
been sanctioned by the United States Supreme Court and compare 
these 
acts with the acts of tyranny enumerated in the Declaration of 
Independence. 
</p><p>The colonists objected most strenuously to the imposition 
of 
taxes upon the people without their consent. 
</p><p>Today, the Federal judiciary asserts the same tyrannical 
power to 
levy taxes in Prince Edward County, Virginia, and without the 
consent 
of the people.  Not only that, but they insist upon the power to 
tell 
the people for what purposes their money must be spent. 
</p><p>The colonists stated, "he has refused to pass other laws 
for the 
accommodation of large districts of people, unless those people 
would 
relinquish the right of representation in the legislature, a 
right 
inestimable to them and formidable to tyrants only." 
</p><p>Today, the Federal judiciary, in one of its most recent 
decisions, has deprived the American people of the right to use 
the 
unit system of representation in their own state governments for 
the 
accommodation of large districts of people, and has itself 
prescribed 
the manner in which the people shall structure the legislative 
branch 
of their own government, and have prescribed how the people shall 
 
allocate the legislative powers of state government. 
</p><p>More than that they have even told the American people 
that we 
may not, with a majority of the people voting for the measure, or 
with 
two-thirds of those voting, or even if by unanimous consent, 
adopt a 
<pb n="10" id="WalCivi10"/> 
provision in our state constitutions to allocate the legislative 
power 
of state government in any manner other than as prescribed by the 
 
court. 
</p><p>One justice of the United States Supreme Court said in 
this 
connection, and I quote, "to put the matter plainly, there is 
nothing 
in all the history of this Court's decisions which supports this 
Constitutional rule.  The Court's draconian pronouncement which 
makes 
unconstitutional the legislatures of most of the fifty states 
finds no 
support in the words of the constitution in any prior decision of 
this 
court or in the 175-year political history of our Federal union . 
. . 
These decisions mark a long step backward into the unhappy era 
where a 
majority of the members of this court were thought by many to 
have 
convinced themselves and each other that the demands of the 
constitution were to be measured not by what it says buy by their 
own 
notions of wise political theory." 
</p><p>Two other Justices of the Court said, "such a massive 
repudiation 
of the experience of our whole past in asserting destructively 
novel 
Judicial power demands analysis of the role of this Court and our 
 
Constitutional scheme. . .  It may well impair the Court's 
position as 
the ultimate organ of the Supreme Law of the Land. . ." 
</p><p>The only reason it is the Supreme Law of the Land today is 
 
because we have a President who cares so little for freedom that 
he 
would send the armed forces into the states to enforce the 
dictatorial 
decree. 
</p><p>Our colonist forefather had something to say about that 
too. 
</p><p>The Declaration of Independence cited as an act of tyranny 
the 
fact that, ". . . Kept among us in times of peace standing armies 
 
without the consent of the legislature." 
</p><p>Today, 188 years later, we have actually witnessed the 
invasion 
of the State of Arkansas, Mississippi, and Alabama by the armed 
forces 
of the United States and maintained in the state against the will 
of 
the people and without consent of state legislatures. 
</p><p>It is a form of tyranny worse than that of King George III 
who 
had sent mercenaries against the colonies because today the 
Federal 
Judicial tyrants have sanctioned the use of brother against 
brother 
and father against son by federalizing the National Guard. 
</p><p>In 1776 the colonists also complained that the monarch ". 
. . Has 
incited domestic insurrections among us. . ." 
</p><p>Today, we have absolute proof that the Federal Department 
of 
<pb n="11" id="WalCivi11"/> 
Justice has planned, supervised, financed and protected acts of 
insurrection in the southern states, resulting in vandalism, 
property 
damage, personal injury, and staggering expense to the states. 
</p><p>In 1776 it was charged that the monarchy had asserted 
power to 
". . . Dissolve representative houses and to punish . . . For 
opposing 
with manly firmness his invasions of the rights of the people. . 
. ." 
</p><p>Today, the Federal judiciary asserts the power not only to 
 
dissolve state legislatures but to create them and to dissolve 
all 
state laws and state judicial decrees, and to punish a state 
governor 
by trial without jury ". . . For opposing with manly firmness his 
 
invasions of the rights of the people. . . ." 
</p><p>The colonists also listed as acts of tyranny:  ". . . The 
erection of a multitude of new offices and sent hither swarms of 
officers to harass our people and to eat out their substance. . 
.;" 
</p><p>". . . Suspending our own legislatures and declaring 
themselves 
invested with the power to legislate for us in all cases 
whatsoever;" 
</p><p>". . . Abolishing the free system of the English laws. . 
.;" 
</p><p> &mdash; it had "abdicated government here;" 
</p><p> &mdash; refusing to assent to the laws enacted by the people, 
". . . 
Laws considered most wholesome and necessary for the public 
good;" 
</p><p> &mdash; and ". . . For depriving us in many cases, of the 
benefits of 
trial by jury . . . ; For taking away our charters, abolishing 
our 
most valuable laws, and altering fundamentally form of our 
government; 
for suspending our own legislatures and declaring themselves 
invested 
with power to legislate for us in all cases whatsoever." 
</p><p>The United States Supreme Court is guilty of each and 
every one 
of these acts of tyranny. 
</p><p>Therefore, I echo the sentiments of our forefathers who 
declared: 
"a prince, whose character is thus marked by every act which may 
define a tyrant, is unfit to be the ruler of a free people" 
</p><p>Ladies and gentlemen, I have listed only a few of the many 
acts 
of tyranny which have been committed or specifically sanctioned 
by the 
United States Supreme Court. 
</p><p>I feel it important that you should know and understand 
what it 
is that these people are trying to do.  The written opinions of 
the 
court are filled with double talk, semantics, jargon, and 
meaningless 
phrases.  The words they use are not important.  The ideas that 
they 
represent are the things which count. 
</p><p>It is perfectly obvious from the left-wing liberal press 
and from 
<pb n="12" id="WalCivi12"/> 
the left-wing law journals that what the court is saying behind 
all 
the jargon is that they don't like our form of government. 
</p><p>They think they can establish a better one.  In order to 
do so it 
is necessary that they overthrow our existing form, destroy the 
democratic institutions created by the people, change the 
outlook, 
religion, and philosophy, and bring the whole area of human 
thought, 
aspiration, action and organization, under the absolute control 
of the 
court.  Their decisions reveal this to be the goal of the liberal 
 
element on the court which is in a majority at present. 
</p><p>It has reached the point where one may no longer look to 
judicial 
decisions to determine what the court may do.  However, it is 
possible 
to predict with accuracy the nature of the opinions to be 
rendered. 
One may find the answer in the Communist Manifesto. 
</p><p>The Communists are dedicated to the overthrow of our form 
of 
government.  They are dedicated to the destruction of the concept 
of 
private property.  They are dedicated to the object of destroying 
 
religion as the basis of moral and ethical values. 
</p><p>The Communists are determined that all natural resources 
shall be 
controlled by the central government, that all productive 
capacity of 
the nation shall be under the control of the central government, 
that 
the political sovereignty of the people shall be destroyed as an 
incident to control of local schools.  It is their objective to 
capture the minds of our youth in order to indoctrinate them in 
what 
to think and not how to think. 
</p><p>I do not call the members of the United States Supreme 
Court 
Communists.  But I do say, and I submit for your judgment the 
fact 
that every single decision of the court in the past ten years 
which 
related in any way to each of these objectives has been decided 
against freedom and in favor of tyranny. 
</p><p>A politician must stand on his record.  Let the Court 
stand on 
its record. 
</p><p>The record reveals, for the past number of years, that the 
chief, 
if not the only beneficiaries of the present Court's rulings, 
have 
been duly and lawfully convicted criminals, Communists, atheists, 
and 
clients of vociferous left-wing minority groups. 
</p><p>You can't convict a Communist in our Federal court system. 
 
</p><p>Neither can you convict one of being a Communist in 
Russia, 
China, or Cuba.  The point is that the United States Supreme 
Court 
refuses to recognize the Communist conspiracy and their intent to 
 
"bury us." 
</p><pb n="13" id="WalCivi13"/> 
<p>let us look at the record further with respect to the court's 
contribution to the destruction of the concept of God and the 
abolition of religion. 
</p><p>The Federal court rules that your children shall not be 
permitted 
to read the bible in our public school systems. 
</p><p>Let me tell you this, though.  We still read the bible in 
Alabama 
schools and as long as I am governor we will continue to read the 
 
bible no matter what the Supreme Court says. 
</p><p>Federal courts will not convict a "demonstrator" invading 
and 
destroying private property.  But the Federal courts rule you 
cannot 
say a simple "God is great, God is good, we thank Thee for our 
food," 
in kindergartens supported by public funds. 
</p><p>Now, let us examine the manner in which the Court has 
continuously chipped away at the concept of private property. 
</p><p>It is contended by the left-wing liberals that private 
property is 
merely a legal fiction.  That one has no inherent right to own 
and 
possess property.  The courts have restricted and limited the 
right of 
acquisition of property in life and have decreed its disposition 
in 
death and have ruthlessly set aside the wills of the dead in 
order to 
attain social ends decreed by the court.  The court has 
substituted 
its judgment for that of the testator based on social theory. 
</p><p>The courts assert authority even in decree the use of 
private 
cemeteries. 
</p><p>They assert the right to convert a private place of 
business into 
a public place of business without the consent of the owner and 
without compensation to him. 
</p><p>One justice asserts that the mere licensing of a business 
by the 
state is sufficient to convert it into control by the Federal 
judiciary as to its use and disposition. 
</p><p>Another asserts that the guarantees of equal protection 
and due 
process of law cannot be extended to a corporation. 
</p><p>In one instance, following the edicts of the United States 
 
Supreme Court, a state Supreme Court has ordered and directed a 
private citizen to sell his home to an individual contrary to the 
 
wishes of the owner. 
</p><p>In California we witnessed a state Supreme Court taking 
under 
advisement the question as to whether or not it will compel a 
bank to 
make a load to an applicant on the basis of his race. 
</p><p>We have witnessed the sanction by the courts of 
confiscatory 
taxation. 
</p><pb n="14" id="WalCivi14"/> 
<p>Let us take a look at the attitude of the court with respect 
to 
the control of the private resources of the nation and the 
allocation 
of the productive capacity of the nation. 
</p><p>The Supreme Court decisions have sanctioned enactment of 
the 
civil rights bill. 
</p><p>What this bill actually does is to empower the United 
States 
government to reallocate the entire productive capacity of the 
agricultural economy covered by quotas and acreage allotments of 
various types on the basis of race, creed, color and national 
origin. 
</p><p>It, in effect, places in the hands of the Federal 
government the 
right of a farmer to earn a living, making that right dependent 
upon 
the consent of the Federal government precisely as is the case in 
 
Russia. 
</p><p>The power is there.  I am not in the least impressed by 
the 
protestations that the government will use this power with 
benevolent 
discretion. 
</p><p>We know that this bill authorizes the President of the 
united 
states to allocate all defense productive capacity of this 
country on 
the basis of race, creed, or color. 
</p><p>It does not matter in the least that he will make such 
allocations with restraint.  The face is that it is possible with 
a 
politically dominated agency to punish and to bankrupt and 
destroy any 
business that deals with the Federal government if it does not 
bow to 
the wishes and demands of the president of the United States. 
</p><p>All of us know what the court has done to capture the 
minds of 
our children. 
</p><p>The Federal judiciary has asserted the authority to 
prescribe 
regulations with respect to the management, operation, and 
control of 
our local schools.  The second brown decision in the infamous 
school 
segregation case authorized Federal district courts to supervise 
such 
matters as teacher hiring, firing, promotion, the expenditure of 
local 
funds, both administratively and for capital improvements, 
additions, 
and renovations, the location of new schools, the drawing of 
school 
boundaries, busing and transportation of school children, and, 
believe 
it or not, it has asserted the right in the Federal judiciary to 
pass 
judgment upon the curricula adopted in local public schools. 
</p><p>A comparatively recent Federal court decision in a Florida 
case 
actually entered an order embracing each and every one of these 
assertions of Federal supervision. 
</p><p>In ruling after ruling, the Supreme Court has overstepped 
its 
constitutional authority.  While appearing to protect the 
people's 
<pb n="15" id="WalCivi15"/> 
interest, it has in reality become a judicial tyrant. 
</p><p>It's the old pattern.  The people always have some 
champion whom 
they set over them . . . And nurse into greatness.  This, and no 
other, is the foot from which a tyrant springs, after first 
appearing 
as a protector. 
</p><p>This is another way of saying that the people never give 
up their 
liberties . . . And their freedom . . . But under some delusion. 
</p><p>But yet there is hope. 
</p><p>There is yet a spirit of resistance in this country which 
will 
not be oppressed.  And it is awakening.  And I am sure there is 
an 
abundance of good sense in this country which cannot be deceived. 
 
</p><p>I have personal knowledge of this.  Thirty-four percent of 
the 
Wisconsin Democrats supported the beliefs you and I uphold and 
expound. 
</p><p>Thirty percent of the Democrats in Indiana join us in 
fighting 
this grab for executive power by those now in control in 
Washington. 
</p><p>And, listen to this, forty-three percent of the Democrats 
in 
Maryland, practically in view of the nation's capital, believe as 
you 
and I believe. 
</p><p>So, let me say to you today.  Take heart.  Millions of 
Americans 
believe just as we in this great region of the United States 
believe. 
</p><p>I shall never forget last spring as I stood in the midst 
of a 
great throng of South Milwaukee supporters at one of the greatest 
 
political rallies I have ever witnessed. 
</p><p>A fine-looking man grabbed my hand and said: 
</p><p>"Governor, I've never been south of South Milwaukee, but I 
am a 
Southerner!" 
</p><p>of course, he was saying he believed in the principles and 
 
philosophy of the southern people . . . Of you here today and the 
 
people of my state of Alabama. 
</p><p>He was right. 
</p><p>Being a southerner is no longer geographic.  It's a 
philosophy 
and an attitude. 
</p><p>One destined to be a national philosophy &mdash; embraced by 
millions of 
Americans &mdash; which shall assume the mantle of leadership and 
steady a 
governmental structure in these days of crises. 
</p><p>Certainly I am a candidate for President of the United 
States. 
</p><p>If the left-wingers do not think I am serious &mdash; let them 
consider 
this. 
</p> 
<pb n="16" id="WalCivi16"/> 
<p>I am going to take our fight to the people &mdash; the court of 
public 
opinion &mdash; where truth and common sense will eventually prevail. 
</p><p>At this time, I have definite, concrete plans to get 
presidential 
electors pledged to me on the ballots in the following states: 
</p><p>Florida, Georgia, South Carolina, North Carolina, 
Virginia, New 
York, Indiana, Illinois, Wisconsin, Missouri, Kentucky, Arkansas, 
 
Tennessee, and of course Alabama, Mississippi and Louisiana. 
</p><p>Other states are under serious consideration. 
</p><p>A candidate for President must receive 270 electoral votes 
to 
win. 
</p><p>The states I am definitely going to enter represent 218 
electoral 
votes. 
</p><p>Conservatives of this nation constitute the balance of 
power in 
presidential elections. 
</p><p>I am a conservative. 
</p><p>I intend to give the American people a clear choice.  I 
welcome a 
fight between our philosophy and the liberal left-wing dogma 
which now 
threatens to engulf every man, woman, and child in the United 
States. 
</p><p>I am in this race because I believe the American people 
have been 
pushed around long enough and that they, like you and I, are fed 
up 
with the continuing trend toward a socialist state which now 
subjects 
the individual to the dictates of an all-powerful central 
government. 
</p><p>I am running for President because I was born free.  I 
want to 
remain free.  I want your children and mine and our prosperity to 
be 
unencumbered by the manipulations of a soulless state. 
</p><p>I intend to fight for a positive, affirmative program to 
restore 
constitutional government and to stop the senseless bloodletting 
now 
being performed on the body of liberty by those who lead us 
willingly 
and dangerously close to a totalitarian central government. 
</p><p>In our nation, man has always been sovereign and the state 
has 
been his servant.  This philosophy has made the United States the 
 
greatest free nation in history. 
</p><p>This freedom was not a gift.  It was won by work, by 
sweat, by 
tears, by war, by whatever it took to be &mdash;; and to remain free. 
</p><p>Are we today less resolute, less determined and courageous 
than 
our fathers and our grandfathers? 
</p><p>Are we to abandon this priceless heritage that has carried 
us to 
our present position of achievement and leadership? 
</p><p>I say if we are to abandon our heritage, let it be done in 
the 
open and full knowledge of what we do. 
</p> 
<pb n="17" id="WalCivi17"/> 
<p>We are not unmindful and careless of our future.  We will not 
stand aside while our conscientious convictions tell us that a 
dictatorial Supreme Court has taken away our rights and our 
liberties. 
</p><p>We will not stand idly by while the Supreme Court 
continues to 
invade the prerogatives left rightfully to the states by the 
constitution. 
</p><p>We must not be misled by left-wing incompetent news media 
that 
day after day feed us a diet of fantasy telling us we are bigots, 
 
racists and hate-mongers to oppose the destruction of the 
constitution 
and our nation. 
</p><p>A left-wing monster has risen up in this nation.  It has 
invaded 
the government.  It has invaded the news media.  It has invaded 
the 
leadership of many of our churches.  It has invaded every phase 
and 
aspect of the life of freedom-loving people. 
</p><p>It consists of many and various and powerful interests, 
but it 
has combined into one massive drive and is held together by the 
cohesive power of the emotion, setting forth civil rights as 
supreme 
to all. 
</p><p>But, in reality, it is a drive to destroy the rights of 
private 
property, to destroy the freedom and liberty of you and me. 
</p><p>And, my friends, where there are no property rights, there 
are no 
human rights.  Red China and Soviet Russia are prime examples. 
</p><p>Politically evil men have combined and arranged themselves 
 
against us.  The good people of this nation must now associate 
themselves together, else we will fall one by one, an unpitied 
sacrifice in a struggle which threatens to engulf the entire 
nation. 
</p><p>We can win.  We can control the election of the president 
in 
November. 
</p><p>Our object must be our country, our whole country and 
nothing but 
our country. 
</p><p>If we will stand together &mdash;; the people of this state &mdash;; 
the people 
of my state &mdash;; the people throughout this great region &mdash;; yes, 
throughout 
the United States &mdash;; then we can be the balance of power.  We can 
 
determine who will be the next president. 
</p><p>Georgia is a great state.  Atlanta is a great city.  I 
know you 
will demonstrate that greatness in November by joining Alabama 
and 
other states throughout the south in electing the next president 
of 
the United States. 
</p><p>We are not going to change anything by sitting on our 
hands 
hoping that things will change for the better.  Those who cherish 
 
<pb n="18" id="WalCivi18"/> 
individual freedom have a job to do. 
</p><p>First, let us let ti be known that we intend to take the 
offensive and carry our fight for freedom across this nation.  We 
will 
wield the power that is ours &mdash;; the power of the people. 
</p><p>Let it be known that we will no longer tolerate the boot 
of 
tyranny.  We will no longer hide our heads in the sand.  We will 
reschool our thoughts in the lessons our forefathers knew so 
well. 
</p><p>We must destroy the power to dictate, to forbid, to 
require, to 
demand, to distribute, to edict, and to judge what is best and 
enforce 
that will of judgment upon free citizens. 
</p><p>We must revitalize a government founded in this nation on 
faith 
in god. 
</p><p>I ask that you join with me and that together, we give an 
active 
and courageous leadership to the millions of people throughout 
this 
nation who look with hope and faith to our fight to preserve our 
constitutional system of government with its guarantees of 
liberty and 
justice for all within the framework of our priceless freedoms. 
</p> 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
