<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WarStor"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]>
 
<TEI.2 id="WarStor"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"The Story of Uncle Tom's Cabin."</title>
<title type="sort">the story of uncle toms cabin</title>
<author>Warner, Charles Dudley</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">46</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WarStor</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476457</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"The Story of Uncles Tom's Cabin."</title>
<title type="sort">the story of uncles toms cabin</title>
<author>Charles Dudley Warner</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Houghton, Mifflin and Company</publisher> 
<pubPlace>Boston, New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1896">1896</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>Atlantic Monthly, V.78 1896 Pages311-321</p>
</seriesStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text 
Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Spell-check and verification made 
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center 
scheme 
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the 
text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page 
one of Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1896">1896</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term> 
<term>African American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-08-02">August 2, 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Lorrie S. Chisholm, Electronic Text Center, University of 
Virginia Library System.</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>General TEI tagging, removed unambiguous line-end hyphenation 
and ran electronic spell-check using wp51.</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1">  
 
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="article" id="d3"> <pb n="311"/>  
<head>THE STORY OF UNCLE TOM'S CABIN.</head> 
 
<p>On the 29th of June, 1852, Henry Clay died.  In that month the 
two great political parties, in their national conventions, had 
accepted as a finality all the compromise measures of 1850, and the 
last hours of the Kentucky statesman were brightened by the thought 
that his efforts had secured the perpetuity of the Union. 
</p><p>But on the 20th of March, 1852, there had been an event, the 
significance of which was not taken into account by the political 
conventions or by Clay, which was to test the conscience of the 
nation.  This was the publication of Uncle Tom's Cabin.  Was this 
only an "event," the advent of a new force in politics; was the 
book merely an abolition pamphlet, or was it a novel, one of the 
few great masterpieces of fiction that the world has produced? 
After the lapse of forty-four years and the disappearance of 
African slavery on this continent, it is perhaps possible to 
consider this question dispassionately. 
</p><p>The compromise of 1850 satisfied neither the North nor the 
South.  The admission of California as a free State was regarded by 
Calhoun as fatal to the balance between the free and the slave 
States, and thereafter a fierce agitation sprang up for the 
recovery of this loss of balance, and ultimately for Southern 
preponderance, which resulted in the repeal of the Missouri 
Compromise, the Kansas-Nebraska war, and the civil war.  The 
fugitive slave law was hateful to the North not only because it was 
cruel and degrading, but because it was seen to be a move formed 
for nationalizing slavery.  It was unsatisfactory to the South 
because it was deemed inadequate in its provisions, and because the 
South did not believe the North would execute it in good faith.  So 
unstable did the compromise seem that in less than a year after the 
passage of all its measures, Henry Clay and forty-four Senators and 
Representatives united in a manifesto declaring that they would 
support no man for office who was not known to be opposed to any 
disturbance of the settlements of the compromise.  When, in 
February, 1851, the recaptured fugitive slave, Burns, was rescued 
from the United States officers in Boston, Clay urged the 
investment of the President with extraordinary power to enforce the 
law. 
</p><p>Henry Clay was a patriot, a typical American.  The republic 
and its preservation were the passions of his life.  Like Lincoln, 
who was born in the State of his adoption, he was willing to make 
almost any sacrifice for the maintenance of the Union.  He had no 
sympathy with the system of slavery.  There is no doubt that he 
would have been happy in the belief that it was in the way of 
gradual and peaceful extinction.  With him, it was always the Union 
before state rights and before slavery.  Unlike Lincoln, he had not 
the clear vision to see that the republic could not endure half 
slave and half free.  He believed that the South, appealing to the 
compromises of the Constitution, would sacrifice the Union before 
it would give up slavery, and in fear of this menace he begged the 
North to conquer its prejudices.  We are not liable to overrate his 
influence as a compromising pacificator from 1832 to 1852.  History 
will no doubt say that it was largely due to him that the war on 
the Union was postponed to a date when its success was impossible. 
</p><p>It was the fugitive slave law that brought the North face to 
face with slavery nationalized, and it was the fugitive slave law 
that produced Uncle Tom's Cabin.  The effect of this story was 
immediate and electric.  It went straight to the hearts of tens of 
thousands 
 
<pb n="312"/>  
of people who had never before considered slavery 
except as a political institution for which they had no personal 
responsibility.  What was this book, and how did it happen to 
produce such an effect?  It is true that it struck into a time of 
great irritation and agitation, but in one sense there was nothing 
new in it.  The facts had all been published.  For twenty years 
abolition tracts, pamphlets, newspapers, and books had left little 
to be revealed, to those who cared to read, as to the nature of 
slavery or its economic aspects.  The evidence was practically all 
in,&mdash;supplied largely by the advertisements of Southern newspapers 
and by the legislation of the slaveholding States,&mdash;but it did not 
carry conviction; that is, the sort of conviction that results in 
action.  The subject had to be carried home to the conscience. 
Pamphleteering, convention-holding, sermons, had failed to do this. 
Even the degrading requirements of the fugitive slave law, which 
brought shame and humiliation, had not sufficed to fuse the public 
conscience, emphasize the necessity of obedience to the moral law, 
and compel recognition of the responsibility of the North for 
slavery.  Evidence had not done this, passionate appeals had not 
done it, vituperation had not done it.  What sort of presentation 
of the case would gain the public ear and go to the heart?  If Mrs. 
Stowe, in all her fervor, had put forth first the facts in The Key 
to Uncle Tom's Cabin, which so buttressed her romance, the book 
would have had no more effect than had followed the like 
compilations and arraignments.  What was needed?  If we can 
discover this, we shall have the secret of this epoch-making novel. 
</p><p>The story of this book has often been told.  It is in the 
nature of a dramatic incident of which the reader never tires any 
more than the son of Massachusetts does of the minutest details of 
that famous scene in the Senate Chamber when Webster replied to 
Hayne. 
</p><p>At the age of twenty-four the author was married and went to 
live in Cincinnati, where her husband held a chair in the Lane 
Theological Seminary.  There for the first time she was brought 
into relations with the African race and saw the effects of 
slavery.  She visited slaveholders in Kentucky and had friends 
among them.  In some homes she saw the "patriarchal" institution at 
its best.  The Beecher family were anti-slavery, but they had not 
been identified with the abolitionists, except perhaps Edward, who 
was associated with the murdered Lovejoy.  It was long a reproach 
brought by the abolitionists against Henry Ward Beecher that he 
held entirely aloof from their movement.  At Cincinnati, however, 
the personal aspects of the case were brought home to Mrs. Stowe. 
She learned the capacities and peculiarities of the negro race. 
They were her servants; she taught some of them; hunted fugitives 
applied to her; she ransomed some by her own efforts; every day 
there came to her knowledge stories of the hunger for freedom, of 
the ruthless separation of man and wife and mother and child, and 
of the heroic sufferings of those who ran away from the fearful 
doom of those "sold down South."  These things crowded upon her 
mind and awoke her deepest compassion.  But what could she do 
against all the laws, the political and commercial interests, the 
great public apathy?  Relieve a case here and there, yes.  But to 
dwell upon the gigantic evil, with no means of making head against 
it, was to invite insanity. 
</p><p>As late as 1850, when Professor Stowe was called to Bowdoin 
College, and the family removed to Brunswick, Maine, Mrs. Stowe had 
not felt impelled to the duty she afterwards undertook.  "In fact, 
it was a sort of general impression upon her mind, as upon that of 
many humane people in those days, that the subject was so dark and 
painful a one, so involved in difficulty and obscurity, so utterly 
beyond human hope 
 
<pb n="313"/>  
or help, that it was of no use to read, 
or think, or distress one's self about it."  But when she reached 
New England the excitement over the fugitive slave law was at its 
height.  There was a panic in Boston among the colored people 
settled there, who were daily fleeing to Canada.  Every mail 
brought her pitiful letters from Boston, from Illinois, and 
elsewhere, of the terror and despair caused by the law.  Still more 
was the impressed by the apathy of the Christian world at the 
North, and surely, she said, the people did not understand what the 
"system" was.  Appeals were made to her, who had some personal 
knowledge of the subject, to take up her pen.  The task seemed 
beyond her in every way.  She was not strong, she was in the midst 
of heavy domestic cares, with a young infant, with pupils to whom 
she was giving daily lessons, and the limited income of the family 
required the strictest economy.  The dependence was upon the small 
salary of Professor Stowe, and the few dollars she could earn by an 
occasional newspaper or magazine article.  But the theme burned in 
her mind, and finally took this shape: at least she would write 
some sketches and show the Christian world what slavery really was, 
and what the system was that they were defending.  She wanted to do 
this with entire fairness, showing all the mitigations of the 
"patriarchal" system, and all that individuals concerned in it 
could do to alleviate its misery.  While pondering this she came by 
chance, in a volume of an anti-slavery magazine, upon the 
authenticated account of the escape of a woman with her child on 
the ice across the Ohio River from Kentucky.  She began to 
meditate.  The faithful slave husband in Kentucky, who had refused 
to escape from a master who trusted him, when he was about to be 
sold "down river," came to her as a pattern of Uncle Tom, and the 
scenes of the story began to form themselves in her mind.  "The 
first part of the book ever committed to writing [this is the 
statement of Mrs. Stowe] was the death of Uncle Tom.  This scene 
presented itself almost as a tangible vision to her mind while 
sitting at the communion-table in the little church in Brunswick. 
She was perfectly overcome by it, and could scarcely restrain the 
convulsion of tears and sobbings that shook her frame.  She 
hastened home and wrote it, and her husband being away, read it to 
her two sons of ten and twelve years of age.  The little fellows 
broke out into convulsions of weeping, one of them saying through 
his sobs, 'Oh, mamma, slavery is the most cursed thing in the 
world!'  From that time the story can less be said to have been 
composed by her than imposed upon her.  Scenes, incidents, 
conversations rushed upon her with a vividness and importunity that 
would not be denied.  The book insisted upon getting itself into 
being, and would take no denial." 
</p><p>When two or three chapters were written she wrote to her 
friend, Dr. Bailey, of Washington, the editor of The National Era, 
to which she had contributed, that she was planning a story that 
might run through several numbers of the Era.  The story was at 
once applied for, and thereafter weekly installments were sent on 
regularly, in spite of all cares and distractions.  The 
installments were mostly written during the morning, on a little 
desk in a corner of the dining-room of the cottage in Brunswick, 
subject to all the interruptions of house-keeping, her children 
bursting into the room continually with the importunity of 
childhood.  But they did not break the spell or destroy her 
abstraction.  With a smile and a word and a motion of the hand she 
would wave them off, and keep on in her magician's work.  Long 
afterwards they recalled this, dimly understood at the time, and 
wondered at her power of concentration.  Usually at night the 
chapters were read to the family, who followed the story with 
 
<pb n="314"/>  
intense feeling.  The narrative ran on for nine months, 
exciting great interest among the limited readers of the Era, and 
gaining sympathetic words from the anti-slavery people, but without 
making any wide impression on the public. 
</p><p>We may pause here in the narrative to note two things: the 
story was not the work of a novice, and it was written out of 
abundant experience and from an immense mass of accumulated thought 
and material.  Mrs. Stowe was in her fortieth year.  She had been 
using her pen since she was twelve years old, in extensive 
correspondence, in occasional essays, in short stories and 
sketches, some of which appeared in a volume called The Mayflower, 
published in 1843, and for many years her writing for newspapers 
and periodicals had added appreciably to the small family income. 
She was in the maturity of her intellectual powers, she was trained 
in the art of writing, and she had, as Walter Scott had when he 
began the Waverley Novels at the age of forty-three, abundant store 
of materials on which to draw.  To be sure, she was on fire with a 
moral purpose, but she had the dramatic instinct, and she felt that 
her object would not be reached by writing an abolition tract. 
</p><p>"In shaping her material the author had but one purpose, to 
show the institution of slavery truly, just as it existed.  She had 
visited in Kentucky; had formed the acquaintance of people who were 
just, upright, and generous, and yet slave-holders.  She had heard 
their views, and appreciated their situation; she felt that justice 
required that their difficulties should be recognized and their 
virtues acknowledged.  It was her object to show that the evils of 
slavery were the inherent evils of a bad system, and not always the 
fault of those who had become involved in it and were its actual 
administrators.  Then she was convinced that the presentation of 
slavery alone, in its most dreadful forms, would be a picture of 
such unrelieved horror and darkness as nobody could be induced to 
look at.  Of set purpose, she sought to light up the darkness by 
humorous and grotesque episodes, and the presentation of the milder 
and more amusing phases of slavery, for which her recollection of 
the never-failing wit and drollery of her former colored friends in 
Ohio gave her abundant material." 
</p><p>This is her own account of the process, years after.  But it 
is evident that, whether consciously or unconsciously, she did but 
follow the inevitable law of all great dramatic creators and true 
story-tellers since literature began. 
</p><p>For this story Mrs. Stowe received from the Era the sum of 
three hundred dollars.  Before it was finished it attracted the 
attention of Mr. J. P. Jewett, of Boston, a young and then unknown 
publisher, who offered to issue it in book form.  His offer was 
accepted, but as the tale ran on he became alarmed at its length, 
and wrote to the author that she was making the story too long for 
a one-volume novel; that the subject was unpopular; that people 
would not willingly hear much about it; that one short volume might 
possibly sell, but that if it grew to two that might prove a fatal 
obstacle to its success.  Mrs. Stowe replied that she did not make 
the story, that the story made itself, and that she could not stop 
it till it was done.  The publisher hesitated.  It is said that a 
competent literary critic to whom he submitted it sat up all night 
with the novel, and then reported, "The story has life in it; it 
will sell."  Mr. Jewett proposed to Professor Stowe to publish it 
on half profits if he would share the expenses.  This offer was 
declined, for the Stowes had no money to advance, and the common 
royalty of ten per cent on the sales was accepted. 
</p><p>Mrs. Stowe was not interested in this business transaction. 
She was thinking only of having the book circulated for the effect 
she had at heart.  The intense absorption in the story held her 
until the 
 
<pb n="315"/>  
virtual end in the death of Uncle Tom, and then 
it seemed as if the whole vital force had left her.  She sank into 
a profound discouragement.  Would this appeal, which she had 
written with her heart's blood, go for nothing, as all the prayers 
and tears and strivings had already gone?  When the last proof 
sheets left her hands, "it seemed to her that there was no hope; 
that nobody would read, nobody would pity; that this frightful 
system, which had already pursued its victims into the free States, 
might at last even threaten them in Canada."  Resolved to leave 
nothing undone to attract attention to her cause, she wrote letters 
and ordered copies of her novel sent to men of prominence who had 
been known for their anti-slavery sympathies,&mdash;to Prince Albert, 
Macaulay, Charles Dickens, Charles Kingsley, and Lord Carlisle. 
Then she waited for the result. 
</p><p>She had not long to wait.  The success of the book was 
immediate.  Three thousand copies were sold the first day, within 
a few days ten thousand copies had gone, on the 1st of April a 
second edition went to press, and thereafter eight presses running 
day and night were barely able to keep pace with the demand for it. 
Within a year three hundred thousand copies were sold.  No work of 
fiction ever spread more quickly throughout the reading community 
or awakened a greater amount of public feeling.  It was read by 
everybody, learned and unlearned, high and low, for it was an 
appeal to universal human sympathy, and the kindling of this spread 
the book like wildfire.  At first it seemed to go by acclamation. 
But this was not altogether owing to sympathy with the theme.  I 
believe that it was its power as a novel that carried it largely. 
The community was generally apathetic when it was not hostile to 
any real effort to be rid of slavery.  This presently appeared.  At 
first there were few dissenting voices from the chorus of praise. 
But when the effect of the book began to be evident it met with an 
opposition fiercer and more personal than the great wave of 
affectionate thankfulness which greeted it at first.  The South and 
the defenders and apologists of slavery everywhere were up in arms. 
It was denounced in pulpit and in press, and some of the severest 
things were said of it at the North.  The leading religious 
newspaper of the country, published in New York, declared that it 
was "anti-Christian." 
</p><p>Mrs. Stowe was twice astonished: first by its extraordinary 
sale, and second by the quarter from which the assault on it came. 
She herself says that her expectations were strikingly different 
from the facts.  "She had painted slaveholders as amiable, 
generous, and just.  She had shown examples among them of the 
noblest and most beautiful traits of character; had admitted fully 
their temptations, their perplexities, and their difficulties, so 
that a friend of hers who had many relatives in the South wrote to 
her: 'Your book is going to be the great pacificator; it will unite 
both North and South.'  Her expectation was that the professed 
abolitionists would denounce it as altogether too mild in its 
dealings with slaveholders.  To her astonishment, it was the 
extreme abolitionists who received, and the entire South who rose 
up against it." 
</p><p>There is something almost amusing in Mrs. Stowe's honest 
expectation that the deadliest blow the system ever suffered should 
have been received thankfully by those whose traditions, education, 
and interests were all bound up in it.  And yet from her point of 
view it was not altogether unreasonable.  Her blackest villain and 
most loathsome agent of the system, Legree, was a native of 
Vermont.  All her wrath falls upon the slave-traders, the 
auctioneers, the public whippers, and the overseers, and all these 
persons and classes were detested by the Southerners to the point 
of loathing, and 
 
<pb n="316"/>  
were social outcasts.  The slave-traders 
and the overseers were tolerated as perhaps necessary in the 
system, but they were never admitted into respectable society. 
This feeling Mrs. Stowe regarded as a condemnation of the system. 
</p><p>Pecuniary reward was the last thing that Mrs. Stowe expected 
for her disinterested labor, but it suits the world's notion of the 
fitness of things that this was not altogether wanting.  For the 
millions of copies of Uncle Tom scattered over the world the author 
could expect nothing, but in her own country her copyright yielded 
her a moderate return that lifted her out of poverty and enabled 
her to pursue her philanthropic and literary career.  Four months 
after the publication of the book Professor Stowe was in the 
publisher's office, and Mr. Jewett asked him how much he expected 
to receive.  "I hope," said Professor Stowe, with a whimsical 
smile, "that it will be enough to buy my wife a silk dress."  The 
publisher handed him a check for ten thousand dollars. 
</p><p>Before Mrs. Stowe had a response to the letters accompanying 
the books privately sent to England, the novel was getting known 
there.  Its career in Great Britain paralleled its success in 
America.  In April a copy reached London in the hands of a 
gentleman who had taken it on the steamer to read.  He gave it to 
Mr. Henry Vizetelly, who submitted it to Mr. David Bogue, a man 
known for his shrewdness and enterprise.  He took a night to 
consider it, and then declined it, although it was offered to him 
for five pounds.  A Mr. Gilpin also declined it.  It was then 
submitted to Mr. Salisbury, a printer.  This taster for the public 
sat up with the book till four o'clock in the morning, alternately 
weeping and laughing.  Fearing, however, that this result was due 
to his own weakness, he woke up his wife, whom he describes as a 
rather strong-minded woman, and finding that the story kept her 
awake and made her also laugh and cry, he thought it might safely 
be printed.  It seems, therefore, that Mr. Vizetelly ventured to 
risk five pounds, and the volume was brought out through the 
nominal agency of Clarke &#x0026; Company.  In the first week an edition 
of seven thousand was worked off.  It made no great stir until the 
middle of June, but during July it sold at the rate of one thousand 
a week.  By the 20th of August the demand for it was overwhelming. 
The printing firm was then employing four hundred people in getting 
it out, and seventeen printing-machines, besides hand-presses. 
Already one hundred and fifty thousand copies were sold.  Mr. 
Vizetelly disposed of his interest, and a new printing firm began 
to issue monster editions.  About this time the publishers awoke to 
the fact that any one was at liberty to reprint the book, and the 
era of cheap literature was initiated, founded on American reprints 
which cost the publisher no royalty.  A shilling edition followed 
the one-and-sixpence, and then one complete for sixpence.  As to 
the total sale, Mr. Sampson Low reports: "From April to December, 
1852, twelve different editions (not reissues) were published, and 
within the twelve months of its first appearance eighteen different 
London publishing houses were engaged in supplying the great demand 
that had set in, the total number of editions being forty, varying 
from fine illustrated editions at 15s., 10s., and 7s. 6d. to the 
cheap popular editions of 1s. 9d. and 6d.  After carefully 
analyzing these editions and weighing probabilities with 
ascertained facts, I am able pretty confidently to say that the 
aggregate number of copies circulated in Great Britain and the 
colonies exceeds one and a half millions."  Later, abridgments were 
published. 
</p><p>Almost simultaneously with this furor in England the book made 
its way on the Continent.  Several translations appeared in Germany 
and France, and for the authorized French edition Mrs. Stowe wrote 
a new preface, which served thereafter 
 
<pb n="317"/>  
for most of the European editions.  I find no record of the 
order of the translations of the book into foreign languages, but 
those into some of the Oriental tongues did not appear till several years 
after the great excitement.  The ascertained translations are into 
twenty-three tongues, namely: Arabic, Armenian, Chinese, Danish, 
Dutch, Finnish, Flemish, French, German, Hungarian, Illyrian, 
Italian, Japanese, Polish, Portuguese, modern Greek, Russian, 
Servian, Siamese, Spanish, Swedish, Wallachian, and Welsh.  Into 
some of these languages several translations were made.  In 1878 
the British Museum contained thirty-five editions of the original 
text, and eight editions of abridgments or adaptations. 
</p><p>The story was dramatized in the United States in August, 1852, 
without the consent or knowledge of the author, and was played most 
successfully in the leading cities, and subsequently was acted in 
every capital in Europe.  Mrs. Stowe had neglected to secure the 
dramatic rights, and she derived no benefit from the great 
popularity of a drama which still holds the stage.  From the 
phenomenal sale of a book which was literally read by the whole 
world, the author received only the ten per cent on the American 
editions, and by the laws of her own country her copyright expired 
before her death. 
 
</p><p>The narrative of the rise and fortunes of this book would be 
incomplete without some reference to the response that the author 
received from England and the Continent, and of her triumphant 
progress through the British Isles.  Her letters accompanying the 
special copies were almost immediately replied to, generally in 
terms of enthusiastic and fervent thankfulness for the book, and 
before midsummer her mail contained letters from all classes of 
English society.  In some of them appeared a curious evidence of 
the English sensitiveness to criticism.  Lord Carlisle and Sir 
Arthur Helps supplemented their admiration by a protest against the 
remark in the mouth of one of the characters that "slaves are 
better off than a large class of the population of England."  This 
occurred in the defense of the institution by St. Clare, but it was 
treated by the British correspondents as the opinion of Mrs. Stowe. 
The charge was disposed of in Mrs. Stowe's reply: "The remark on 
that subject occurs in the dramatic part of the book, in the mouth 
of an intelligent Southerner.  As a fair-minded person, bound to 
state for both sides all that could be said, in the person of St. 
Clare, the best that could be said on that point, and what I know 
<hi rend="italic">is</hi> in fact constantly reiterated, namely, that the laboring 
class of the South are in many respects, as to physical comfort, in 
a better condition than the poor in England.  This is the 
slaveholder's stereo-typed apology; a defense it cannot be, unless 
two wrongs make one right." 
</p><p>In April, 1853, Mr. and Mrs. Stowe and the latter's brother, 
Charles Beecher, sailed for Europe.  Her reception there was like 
a royal progress.  She was met everywhere by deputations and 
addresses, and the enthusiasm her presence called forth was 
thoroughly democratic, extending from the highest in rank to the 
lowest.  At Edinburgh there was presented to her a national penny 
offering, consisting of a thousand golden sovereigns on a 
magnificent silver salver, an unsolicited contribution in small 
sums by the people. 
</p><p>At a reception in Stafford House, London, the Duchess of 
Sutherland presented her with a massive gold bracelet, which has an 
interesting history.  It is made of ten oval links in imitation of 
slave fetters.  On two of the links were the inscriptions "March 
25, 1807," the date of the abolition of the slave-trade, and 
"August 1, 1838," the date of the abolition of slavery in all 
British territory.  The third inscription is 
 
<pb n="318"/>  
"562,848&mdash;March 19, 1853," the date of the address of the women of England to 
the women of America on slavery, and the number of the women who 
signed.  It was Mrs. Stowe's privilege to add to these inscriptions 
the following: "Emancipation D. C. Apl. 16, '62;" "President's 
Proclamation Jan. 1, '63;" "Maryland free Oct. 13, '64;" "Missouri 
free Jan. 11, '65;" and on the clasp link, "Constitution amended by 
Congress Jan. 31, '65.  Constitutional Amendment ratified."  Two of 
the links are vacant.  What will the progress of civilization in 
America offer for the links nine and ten? 
</p><p>One of the most remarkable documents which resulted from Uncle 
Tom was an address from the women of England to the women of 
America, acknowledging the complicity in slavery of England, but 
praying aid in removing from the world "our common crimes and 
common dishonor," which was presented to Mrs. Stowe in 1853.  It 
was the result of a meeting at Stafford House, and the address, 
composed by Lord Shaftesbury, was put into the hands of canvassers 
in England and on the Continent, and as far as Jerusalem.  The 
signatures of 562,848 women were obtained, with their occupations 
and residences, from the nobility on the steps of the throne down 
to maids in the kitchen.  The address is handsomely engrossed on 
vellum.  The names are contained in twenty-six massive volumes, 
each fourteen inches high by nine in breadth and three inches 
thick, inclosed in an oak case.  It is believed that this is the 
most numerously signed address in existence.  The value of the 
address, with so many names collected in haphazard fashion, was 
much questioned, but its use was apparent in the height of the 
civil war, when Mrs. Stowe replied to it in one of the most 
vigorous and noble appeals that ever came from her pen.  This 
powerful reply made a profound impression in England. 
</p><p>This is in brief the story of the book.  It is still read, and 
read the world over, with tears and with laughter; it is still 
played to excited audiences.  Is it a great novel, or was it only 
an event of an era of agitation and passion?  Has it the real 
dramatic quality&mdash;the poet's visualizing of human life&mdash;that makes 
works of fiction, of imagination, live?  Till recently, I had not 
read the book since 1852.  I feared to renew acquaintance with it 
lest I should find only the shell of an exploded cartridge.  I took 
it up at the beginning of a three-hours' railway journey.  To my 
surprise the journey did not seem to last half an hour, and half 
the time I could not keep back the tears from my eyes.  A London 
critic, full of sympathy with Mrs. Stowe and her work, recently 
said, "Yet she was not an artist, she was not a great woman."  What 
is greatness?  What is art?  In 1862 probably no one who knew 
General Grant would have called him a great man.  But he took 
Vicksburg.  This woman did something with her pen,&mdash;on the whole, 
the most remarkable and effective book in her generation.  How did 
she do it?  Without art?  George Sand said, "In matters of art 
there is but one rule, to paint and to move.  And where shall we 
find conditions more complete, types more vivid, situations more 
touching, more original, than in Uncle Tom?"  If there is not room 
in our art for such a book, I think we shall have to stretch our 
art a little.  "Women, too, are here judged and painted with a 
master hand."  This subtle critic, in her overpoweringly tender and 
enthusiastic review, had already inquired about the capacity of 
this writer.  "Mrs. Stowe is all instinct; it is the very reason 
that she appears to some not to have talent.  Has she not talent? 
What is talent?  Nothing, doubtless, compared to genius; but has 
she genius?  I cannot say that she has talent as one understands it 
in the world of letters, but she has genius as humanity feels the 
need of genius,&mdash;the genius 
 
<pb n="319"/>  
of goodness, not that of the 
man of letters, but of the saint."  It is admitted that Mrs. Stowe 
was not a woman of letters in the common acceptation of that term, 
and it is plain that in the French tribunal, where form is of the 
substance of the achievement, and which reluctantly overlooked the 
crudeness of Walter Scott, in France where the best English novel 
seems a violation of established canons, Uncle Tom would seem to 
belong where some modern critics place it, with works of the heart, 
and not of the head.  The reviewer is, however, candid: "For a long 
time we have striven in France against the prolix explanations of 
Walter Scott.  We have cried out against those of Balzac, but on 
consideration have perceived that the painter of manners and 
character has never done too much, that every stroke of the pencil 
was needed for the general effect.  Let us learn then to appreciate 
all kinds of treatment, where the effect is good, and where they 
bear the seal of a master hand." 
</p><p>It must be admitted to the art critic that the book is 
defective according to the rules of the modern French romance; that 
Mrs. Stowe was possessed by her subject, and let her fervid 
interest in it be felt; that she had a definite purpose.  That 
purpose was to quicken the sense of responsibility of the North by 
showing the real character of slavery, and to touch the South by 
showing that the inevitable wrong of it lay in the system rather 
than in those involved in it.  Abundant material was in her hands, 
and the author burned to make it serviceable.  What should she do? 
She might have done what she did afterwards in The Key, presented 
to the public a mass of statistics, of legal documents.  The 
evidence would have been unanswerable, but the jury might not have 
been moved by it; they would have balanced it by considerations of 
political and commercial expediency.  I presume that Mrs. Stowe 
made no calculation of this kind.  She felt her course, and went on 
in it.  What would an artist have done, animated by her purpose and 
with her material?  He would have done what Cervantes did, what 
Tourgenieff did, what Mrs. Stowe did.  He would have dramatized his 
facts in living personalities, in effective scenes, in vivid 
pictures of life.  Mrs. Stowe exhibited the system of slavery by a 
succession of dramatized pictures, not always artistically welded 
together, but always effective as an exhibition of the system. 
Cervantes also showed a fading feudal romantic condition by a 
series of amusing and pathetic adventures, grouped rather loosely 
about a singularly fascinating figure. 
</p><p>Tourgenieff, a more consummate artist, in his hunting scenes 
exhibited the effect of serfdom upon society, in a series of scenes 
with no necessary central figure, without comment, and with 
absolute concealment of any motive.  I believe the three writers 
followed their instincts, without an analytic argument as to the 
method, as the great painter follows his when he puts an idea upon 
canvas.  He may invent a theory about it afterwards; if he does 
not, some one else will invent it for him.  There are degrees of 
art.  One painter will put in unnecessary accessories, another will 
exhibit his sympathy too openly, the technique or the composition 
of another can be criticised.  But the question is, is the picture 
great and effective? 
</p><p>Mrs. Stowe had not Tourgenieff's artistic calmness.  Her mind 
was fused into a white heat with her message.  Yet, how did she 
begin her story?  Like an artist, by a highly dramatized scene, in 
which the actors, by a few strokes of the pen, appear as distinct 
and unmistakable personalities, marked by individual peculiarities 
of manner, speech, motive, character, living persons in natural 
attitudes.  The reader becomes interested in a shrewd study of 
human nature, of a section of life, with its various refinement, 
coarseness, fastidiousness and vulgarity, 
 
<pb n="320"/>  
its humor and pathos.  As he goes on he discovers that every character has been 
perfectly visualized, accurately limned from the first; that a type 
has been created which remains consistent, which is never deflected 
from its integrity by any exigencies of plot.  This clear 
conception of character (not of earmarks and peculiarities adopted 
as labels), and faithful adhesion to it in all vicissitudes, is one 
of the rarest and highest attributes of genius.  All the chief 
characters in the book follow this line of absolutely consistent 
development, from Uncle Tom and Legree down to the most aggravating 
and contemptible of all, Marie St. Clare.  The selfish and 
hysterical woman has never been so faithfully depicted by any other 
author. 
</p><p>Distinguished as the novel is by its character-drawing and its 
pathos, I doubt if it would have captivated the world without its 
humor.  This is of the old-fashioned kind, the large humor of 
Scott, and again of Cervantes, not verbal pleasantry, not the 
felicities of Lamb, but the humor of character in action, of 
situations elaborated with great freedom, and with what may be 
called a hilarious conception.  This quality is never wanting in 
the book, either for the reader's entertainment by the way, or to 
heighten the pathos of the narrative by contrast.  The introduction 
of Topsy into the New Orleans household saves us in the dangerous 
approach to melodrama in the religious passages between Tom and St. 
Clare.  Considering the opportunities of the subject, the book has 
very little melodrama; one is apt to hear low music on the entrance 
of little Eva, but we are convinced of the wholesome sanity of the 
sweet child.  And it is to be remarked that some of the most 
exciting episodes, such as that of Eliza crossing the Ohio River on 
the floating ice (of which Mr. Ruskin did not approve), are based 
upon authentic occurrences.  The want of unity in construction of 
which the critics complain is partially explained by the necessity 
of exhibiting the effect of slavery in its entirety.  The parallel 
plots, one running to Louisiana and the other to Canada, are tied 
together by this consideration, and not by any real necessity to 
each other. 
</p><p>There is no doubt that Mrs. Stowe was wholly possessed by her 
theme, rapt away like a prophet in a vision, and that, in her 
feeling at the time, it was written through her quite as much as by 
her.  This idea grew upon her mind in the retrospective light of 
the tremendous stir the story made in the world, so that in her 
later years she came to regard herself as a providential 
instrument, and frankly to declare that she did not write the book; 
"God wrote it."  In her own account, when she reached the death of 
Uncle Tom, "the whole vital force left her."  The inspiration there 
left her, and the end of the story, the weaving together of all the 
loose ends of the plot, in the joining together almost by miracle 
the long separated, and the discovery of the relationships, is the 
conscious invention of the novelist. 
</p><p>It would be perhaps going beyond the province of the critic to 
remark upon what the author considered the central power of the 
story, and its power to move the world, the faith of Uncle Tom in 
the Bible.  This appeal to the emotion of millions of readers 
cannot, however, be overlooked.  Many regard the book as effective 
in regions remote from our perplexities by reason of this grace. 
When the work was translated into Siamese, the perusal of it by one 
of the ladies of the court induced her to liberate all her slaves, 
men, women, and children, one hundred and thirty in all.  "Hidden 
Perfume," for that was the English equivalent of her name, said she 
was wishful to be good like Harriet Beecher Stowe.  And as to the 
standpoint of Uncle Tom and the Bible, nothing more significant can 
be cited than this passage from one of the latest writings of 
Heinrich Heine:&mdash; 
 
<pb n="321"/>  
</p><p>"The reawakening of my religious feelings I owe to that holy 
book the Bible.  Astonishing that after I have whirled about all my 
life over all the dance-floors of philosophy, and yielded myself to 
all the orgies of the intellect, and paid my addresses to all 
possible systems, without satisfaction like Messalina after a 
licentious night, I now find myself on the same standpoint where 
poor Uncle Tom stands,&mdash;on that of the Bible!  I kneel down by my 
black brother in the same prayer!  What a humiliation!  With all my 
science I have come no further than the poor ignorant negro who has 
scarce learned to spell.  Poor Tom, indeed, seems to have seen 
deeper things in the holy book than I. . . .  Tom, perhaps, 
understands them better than I, because more flogging occurs in 
them; that is to say, those ceaseless blows of the whip which have 
aesthetically disgusted me in reading the Gospels and the Acts. 
But a poor negro slave reads with his back, and understands better 
than we do.  But I, who used to make citations from Homer, now 
begin to quote the Bible as Uncle Tom does." 
</p><p>The one indispensable requisite of a great work of imaginative 
fiction is its universality, its conception and construction so 
that it will appeal to universal human nature in all races and 
situations and climates.  Uncle Tom's Cabin does that.  Considering 
certain artistic deficiencies, which the French writers perceived, 
we might say that it was the timeliness of its theme that gave it 
currency in England and America.  But that argument falls before 
the world-wide interest in it as a mere story, in so many 
languages, by races unaffected by our own relation to slavery 
</p><p>It was the opinion of James Russell Lowell that the anti-slavery element in Uncle Tom and Dred stood in the way of a full 
appreciation, at least in her own country, of the remarkable genius 
of Mrs. Stowe.  Writing in 1859, he said, "From my habits and the 
tendency of my studies I cannot help looking at things purely from 
an aesthetic point of view, and what I valued in Uncle Tom was the 
genius, and not the moral."  This had been his impression when he 
read the book in Paris, long after the whirl of excitement produced 
by its publication had subsided, and far removed by distance from 
local influences.  Subsequently, in a review, he wrote, "We felt 
then, and we believe now, that the secret of Mrs. Stowe's power lay 
in that same genius by which the great successes in creative 
literature have always been achieved,&mdash;the genius that 
instinctively goes to the organic elements of human nature, whether 
under a white skin or a black, and which disregards as trivial the 
conventions and fictitious notions which make so large a part both 
of our thinking and feeling. . . .  The creative faculty of Mrs. 
Stowe, like that of Cervantes in Don Quixote and of Fielding in 
Joseph Andrews, overpowered the narrow specialty of her design, and 
expanded a local and temporary theme with the cosmopolitanism of 
genius." 
</p><p>A half-century is not much in the life of a people; it is in 
time an inadequate test of the staying power of a book.  Nothing is 
more futile than prophecy on contemporary literary work.  It is 
safe, however, to say that Uncle Tom's Cabin has the fundamental 
qualities, the sure insight into human nature, and the fidelity to 
the facts of its own time which have from age to age preserved 
works of genius. 
</p> 
                   <signed><hi rend="italic">Charles Dudley Warner.</hi></signed> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
