<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WasFrui"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
<TEI.2 id="WasFrui"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Fruits of Industrial Training</title>
<title type="sort">fruits of industrial training</title>
<author>Washington, Booker T.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">40</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WasFrui</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476461</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Fruits of Industrial Training</title>
<title type="sort">fruits of industrial training</title>
<author>Booker T. Washington</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher> 
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace> 
<date value="1903">1903</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>92</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Washington, Booker T.  "The Fruits of Industrial Training." 
<hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 92 (1903): 453-462.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of 
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1903">1903</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term> 
<term>democracy</term>
</keywords> 
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-08">August 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added header, Tagged with TEI.2-compatible SGML, Parsed against 
teilite.dtd</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2"> 

<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> <pb n="453"/> 
<head>THE FRUITS OF INDUSTRIAL TRAINING. </head> 
 
<p>THE political, educational, social, and economic evolution 
through which the South passed during, say, the first fifteen or 
twenty years after the close of the civil war furnishes one of the 
most interesting periods that any country has passed through. 
</p><p>A large share of the thought and activity of the white South, 
of the black South, and of that section of the North especially 
interested in my race, was directed during the years of the 
Reconstruction period toward politics, or toward matters bearing 
upon what were termed civil or social rights.  The work of 
education was rather slow, and covered a large section of the 
South; still I think I am justified in saying that in the public 
mind the Negro's relation to politics overshadowed nearly every 
other interest.  The education of the race was conducted quietly, 
and attracted comparatively little attention, just as is true at 
the present time.  The appointment of one Negro postmaster at a 
third or fourth rate post office will be given wider publicity 
through the daily press than the founding of a school, or some 
important discovery in science. 
</p><p>With reference to the black man's political relation to the 
state and Federal governments, I think I am safe in saying that for 
many years after the civil war there were sharp and antagonistic 
views between the North and the South, as well as between the white 
South and the black South.  At practically every point where there 
was a political question to be decided in the South the blacks 
would array themselves on one side and the whites on the other.  I 
remember that very soon after I began teaching school in Alabama an 
old colored man came to me just prior to an election.  He said: 
"You can read de newspapers and most of us can't, but dar is one 
thing dat we knows dat you don't, and dat is how to vote down here; 
and we wants you to vote as we does."  He added: "I tell you how we 
does.  We watches de white man; we keeps watching de white man; de 
nearer it gits to election time de more we watches de white man. 
We watches him till we finds out which way he gwine to vote.  After 
we finds out which way he gwine to vote, den we votes exactly de 
other way; den we knows we 's right." 
</p><p>Stories on the other side might be given showing that a 
certain class of white people, both at the polls and in the 
Legislatures, voted just as unreasonably in opposing politically 
what they thought the Negro or the North wanted, no matter how much 
benefit might ensue from a contrary action.  Unfortunately such 
antagonism did not end with matters political, but in many cases 
affected the relation of the races in nearly every walk of life. 
Aside from political strife, there was naturally deep feeling 
between the North and the South on account of the war.  On nearly 
every question growing out of the war, which was debated in 
Congress, or in political campaigns, there was the keenest 
difference and often the deepest feeling.  There was almost no 
question of even a semi-political nature, or having a remote 
connection with the Negro, upon which there was not sharp and often 
bitter division between the North and South.  It is needless to say 
that in many cases the Negro was the sufferer.  He was being ground 
between the upper and nether millstones.  Even to this day it is 
well-nigh impossible, largely by reason of the force of habit, in 
certain states to prevent state and even local campaigns from being 
centred in some form upon the black man.  In states like 
Mississippi, for example, where the Negro ceased nearly a score of 
years ago, by operation of law, to be a determining factor 
<pb n="454"/> 
in politics, he forms in some way the principal fuel for campaign 
discussion at nearly every election.  The sad feature of this is, 
that it prevents the presentation before the masses of the people 
of matters pertaining to local and state improvement, and to great 
national issues like finance, tariff, or foreign policies.  It 
prevents the masses from receiving the broad and helpful education 
which every political campaign should furnish, and, what is equally 
unfortunate, it prevents the youth from seeing and hearing on the 
platform the great political leaders of the two national parties. 
During a national campaign few of the great Democratic leaders 
debate national questions in the South, because it is felt that the 
old antagonism to the Negro politically will keep the South voting 
one way.  Few of the great Republican leaders appear on Southern 
platforms, because they feel that nothing will be gained. 
</p><p>One of the saddest instances of this situation that has come 
within my knowledge occurred some years ago in a certain Southern 
state where a white friend of mine was making the race for Congress 
on the Democratic ticket in a district that was overwhelmingly 
Democratic.  I speak of this man as my friend, because there was no 
personal favor in reason which he would have refused me.  He was 
equally friendly to the race, and was generous in giving for its 
education, and in helping individuals to buy land.  His campaign 
took him into one of the "white" counties, where there were few 
colored people, and where the whites were unusually ignorant.  I 
was surprised one morning to read in the daily papers of a bitter 
attack he had made on the Negro while speaking in this county.  The 
next time I saw him I informed him of my surprise.  He replied that 
he was ashamed of what he had said, and that he did not himself 
believe much that he had stated, but gave as a reason for his 
action that he had found himself before an audience which had heard 
little for thirty years in the way of political discussion that did 
not bear upon the Negro, and that he therefore knew it was almost 
impossible to interest them in any other subject. 
</p><p>But this is somewhat aside from my purpose, which is, I 
repeat, to make plain that in all political matters there was for 
years after the war no meeting ground of agreement for the two 
races, or for the North and South.  Upon the question of the 
Negro's civil rights, as embodied in what was called the Civil 
Rights Bill, there was almost the same sharp line of division 
between the races, and, in theory at least, between the Northern 
and Southern whites,&mdash;largely because the former were supposed to 
be giving the blacks social recognition, and encouraging 
intermingling between the races.  The white teachers, who came from 
the North to work in missionary schools, received for years little 
recognition or encouragement from the rank and file of their own 
race.  The lines were so sharply drawn that in cities where native 
Southern white women taught Negro children in the public schools, 
they would have no dealings with Northern white women who, perhaps, 
taught Negro children from the same family in a missionary school. 
</p><p>I want to call attention here to a phase of Reconstruction 
policy which is often overlooked.  All now agree that there was 
much in Reconstruction which was unwise and unfortunate.  However 
we may regard that policy, and much as we may regret mistakes, the 
fact is too often overlooked that it was during the Reconstruction 
period that a public school system for the education of all the 
people of the South was first established in most of the states. 
Much that was done by those in charge of Reconstruction legislation 
has been overturned, but the public school system still remains. 
True, it has been modified and improved, but the system remains, 
and is every day growing in popularity and strength. 
<pb n="455"/> 
</p><p>As to the difference of opinion between the North and the 
South regarding Negro education, I find that many people, 
especially in the North, have a wrong conception of the attitude of 
the Southern white people.  It is and has been very generally 
thought that what is termed "higher education" of the Negro has 
been from the first opposed by the white South.  This opinion is 
far from being correct.  I remember that, in 1891, when I began the 
work of establishing the Tuskegee Institute in Alabama, practically 
all of the white people who talked to me on the subject took it for 
granted that instruction in the Greek, Latin, and modern languages 
would be one of the main features of our curriculum.  I heard no 
one oppose what he thought our course of study was to embrace.  In 
fact, there are many white people in the South at the present time 
who do not know that instruction in the dead languages is not given 
at the Tuskegee Institute.  In further proof of what I have stated, 
if one will go through the catalogue of the schools maintained by 
the states for Negro people, and managed by Southern white people, 
he will find in almost every case that instruction in the higher 
branches is given with the consent and approval of white officials. 
This was true as far back as 1880.  It is not unusual to meet at 
this time Southern white people who are as emphatic in their belief 
in the value of classical education as a certain element of colored 
people themselves.  In matters relating to civil and political 
rights, the breach was broad, and without apparent hope of being 
bridged; even in the matter of religion, practically all of the 
denominations had split on the subject of the Negro, though I 
should add that there is now, and always has been, a closer touch 
and more cooperation in matters of religion between the white and 
colored people in the South than is generally known.  But the 
breach between the white churches in the South and North remains. 
</p><p>In matters of education the difference was much less sharp. 
The truth is that a large element in the South had little faith in 
the efficacy of the higher or any other kind of education of the 
Negro.  They were indifferent, but did not openly oppose; on the 
other hand, there has always been a potent element of white people 
in all of the Southern states who have stood out openly and bravely 
for the education of all the people, regardless of race.  This 
element has thus far been successful in shaping and leading public 
opinion, and I think that it will continue to do so more and more. 
This statement must not be taken to mean that there is as yet an 
equitable division of the school funds, raised by common taxation, 
between the two races in many sections of the South, though the 
Southern states deserve much credit for what has been done.  In 
discussing the small amount of direct taxes the Negro pays, the 
fact that he pays tremendous indirect taxes is often overlooked. 
</p><p>I wish, however, to emphasize the fact that while there was 
either open antagonism or indifference in the directions I have 
named, it was the introduction of industrial training into the 
Negro's education that seemed to furnish the first basis for 
anything like united and sympathetic interest and action between 
the two races in the South and between the whites in the North and 
those in the South.  Aside from its direct benefit to the black 
race, industrial education has furnished a basis for mutual faith 
and cooperation, which has meant more to the South, and to the work 
of education, than has been realized. 
</p><p>This was, at the least, something in the way of construction. 
Many people, I think, fail to appreciate the difference between the 
problems now before us and those that existed previous to the civil 
war.  Slavery presented a problem of destruction; freedom presents 
a problem of construction. 
<pb n="456"/> 
</p><p>From its first inception the white people of the South had 
faith in the theory of industrial education, because they had 
noted, what was not unnatural, that a large element of the colored 
people at first interpreted freedom to mean freedom from work with 
the hands.  They naturally had not learned to appreciate the fact 
that they had been <hi rend="italic">worked</hi>, and that one of the great lessons 
for freemen to learn is to <hi rend="italic">work</hi>.  They had not learned the vast 
difference between <hi rend="italic">working</hi> and <hi rend="italic">being worked</hi>.  The white 
people saw in the movement to teach the Negro youth the dignity, 
beauty, and civilizing power of all honorable labor with the hands 
something that would lead the Negro into his new life of freedom 
gradually and sensibly, and prevent his going from one extreme of 
life to the other too suddenly.  Furthermore, industrial education 
appealed directly to the individual and community interest of the 
white people.  They saw at once that intelligence coupled with 
skill would add wealth to the community and to the state, in which 
both races would have an added share.  Crude labor in the days of 
slavery, they believed, could be handled and made in a degree 
profitable, but ignorant and unskilled labor in a state of freedom 
could not be made so.  Practically every white man in the South was 
interested in agricultural or in mechanical or in some form of 
manual labor; every white man was interested in all that related to 
the home life,&mdash;the cooking and serving of food, laundering, 
dairying, poultry-raising, and housekeeping in general.  There was 
no family whose interest in intelligent and skillful nursing was 
not now and then quickened by the presence of a trained nurse.  As 
already stated, there was general appreciation of the fact that the 
industrial education of the black people had direct, vital, and 
practical bearing upon the life of each white family in the South; 
while there was no such appreciation of the results of mere 
literary training.  If a black man became a lawyer, a doctor, a 
minister, or an ordinary teacher, his professional duties would not 
ordinarily bring him in touch with the life of the white portion of 
the community, but rather confine him almost exclusively to his own 
race.  While purely literary or professional education was not 
opposed by the white population, it was something in which they 
found little or no interest, beyond a confused hope that it would 
result in producing a higher and a better type of Negro manhood. 
The minute it was seen that through industrial education the Negro 
youth was not only studying chemistry, but also how to apply the 
knowledge of chemistry to the enrichment of the soil, or to 
cooking, or to dairying, and that the student was being taught not 
only geometry and physics, but their application to blacksmithing, 
brickmaking, farming, and what not, then there began to appear for 
the first time a common bond between the two races and cooperation 
between North and South. 
</p><p>One of the most interesting and valuable instances of the kind 
that I know of is presented in the case of Mr. George W. Carver, 
one of our instructors in agriculture at Tuskegee Institute.  For 
some time it has been his custom to prepare articles containing 
information concerning the conditions of local crops, and warning 
the farmers against the ravages of certain insects and diseases. 
The local white papers are always glad to publish these articles, 
and they are read by white and colored farmers. 
</p><p>Some months ago a white land-holder in Montgomery County asked 
Mr. Carver to go through his farm with him for the purpose of 
inspecting it.  While doing so Mr. Carver discovered traces of what 
he thought was a valuable mineral deposit, used in making a certain 
kind of paint.  The interests of the land-owner and the 
agricultural instructor at once became mutual.  Specimens of the 
deposits were taken to the laboratories of the Tuskegee Institute 
<pb n="457"/> 
and analyzed by Mr. Carver.  In due time the land-owner 
received a report of the analysis, together with a statement 
showing the commercial value and application of the mineral.  I 
shall not go through the whole interesting story, except to say 
that a stock company, composed of some of the best white people in 
Alabama, has been organized, and is now preparing to build a 
factory for the purpose of putting their product on the market.  I 
hardly need to add that Mr. Carver has been freely consulted at 
every step, and his services generously recognized in the 
organization of the concern.  When the company was being formed the 
following testimonial, among others, was embodied in the printed 
copy of the circular:&mdash; 
</p><p>"George W. Carver, Director of the Department of Agriculture, 
Tuskegee, Alabama, says:&mdash; 
</p><p>"'The pigment is an ochreous clay.  Its value as a paint is 
due to the presence of ferric oxide, of which it contains more than 
any of the French, Australian, American, Irish, or Welsh ochres. 
Ferric oxides have long been recognized as the essential 
constituents of such paints as Venetian red, Turkish red, oxide 
red, Indian red, and scarlet.  They are most desirable, being quite 
permanent when exposed to light and air.  As a stain they are most 
valuable.'" 
</p><p>In further proof of what I wish to emphasize, I think I am 
safe in saying that the work of the Hampton Normal and Agricultural 
Institute, under the late General S. C. Armstrong, was the first to 
receive any kind of recognition and hearty sympathy from the 
Southern white people, and General Armstrong was perhaps the first 
Northern educator of Negroes who won the confidence and cooperation 
of the white South.  The effects of General Armstrong's 
introduction of industrial education at Hampton, and its extension 
to the Tuskegee Institute in the far South, are now actively and 
helpfully apparent in the splendid work being accomplished for the 
whole South by the Southern Education Board, with Mr. Robert C. 
Ogden at its head, and by the General Education Board, with Mr. 
William H. Baldwin, Jr., as its president.  Without the 
introduction of manual training it is doubtful whether such work as 
is now being wrought through these two boards for both races in the 
South could have been possible within a quarter of a century to 
come.  Later on in the history of our country it will be recognized 
and appreciated that the far-reaching and statesman-like efforts of 
these two boards for general education in the South, under the 
guidance of the two gentlemen named, and with the cooperation and 
assistance of such men as Mr. George Foster Peabody, Dr. Wallace 
Buttrick, Mr. John D. Rockefeller, of the North, and Mr. Edgar 
Gardner Murphy, Chancellor Hill, Dr. Alderman, Dr. McIver, Dr. 
Dabney, and others of the South, will have furnished the material 
for one of the brightest and most encouraging chapters in the 
history of our country.  The fact that we have reached the point 
where men and women who were so far apart twenty years ago can meet 
in the South and discuss freely from the same platform questions 
relating to the industrial, educational, political, moral, and 
religious development of the two races marks a great step in 
advance.  It is true that as yet the Negro has not been invited to 
share in these discussions. 
</p><p>Aside from the reasons I have given showing why the South 
favored industrial education, coupled with intellectual and moral 
training, many of the whites saw, for example, that the Negroes who 
were master carpenters and contractors, under the guidance of their 
owners, could become still greater factors in the development of 
the South if their children were not suddenly removed from the 
atmosphere and occupations of their fathers, and if they 
<pb n="458"/> 
could be taught to use the thing in hand as a foundation for higher 
growth.  Many of the white people were wise enough to see that such 
education would enable some of the Negro youths to become more 
skillful carpenters and contractors, and that if they laid an 
economic foundation in this way in their generation, they would be 
laying a foundation for a more abstract education of their children 
in the future. 
</p><p>Again, a large element of people at the South favored manual 
training for the Negro because they were wise enough to see that 
the South was largely free from the restrictive influences of the 
Northern trades unions, and that such organizations would secure 
little hold in the South so long as the Negro kept abreast in 
intelligence and skill with the same class of people elsewhere. 
Many realized that the South would be tying itself to a body of 
death if it did not help the Negro up.  In this connection I want 
to call attention to the fact that the official records show that 
within one year about one million foreigners came into the United 
States.  Notwithstanding this number, practically none went into 
the Southern states; to be more exact, the records show that in 
1892 only 2278 all told went into the states of Alabama, Arkansas, 
Georgia, Kentucky, Mississippi, North Carolina, South Carolina, 
Tennessee, and Virginia.  One ship sometimes brings as many to New 
York.  Various reasons are given to explain why these foreigners 
systematically avoid the South.  One is that the climate is so hot; 
and another is that they do not like the restrictions thrown about 
the ballot; and still another is the presence of the Negro is so 
large numbers.  Whatever the true reason is, the fact remains that 
foreigners avoid the South, and the South is more and more 
realizing that it cannot keep pace with the progress being made in 
other parts of the country if a third of its population is ignorant 
and without skill. 
</p><p>The South must frankly face this truth, that for a long period 
it must depend upon the black man to do for it what the foreigner 
is now doing for the great West.  If, by reason of his skill and 
knowledge, one man in Iowa learns to produce as much corn in a 
season as four men can produce in Alabama, it requires little 
reasoning to see that Alabama will buy most of her corn from Iowa. 
</p><p>Another interesting result of the introduction of industrial 
education for the Negro has been its influence upon the white 
people of the South, and, I believe, upon the whites of the North 
as well.  This phase of it has proved of interest in making hand 
training a conciliatory element between the races. 
</p><p>In 1883 I was delivering an address on industrial education 
before the colored State Teachers' Association of one of our 
Southern states.  When I had finished, some of the teachers began 
to ask the State Superintendent of Education, who was on the 
programme, some questions about the subject.  He politely but 
firmly stopped the questions by stating that he knew absolutely 
nothing about industrial training, and had never heard it discussed 
before.  At that time there was no such education being given at 
any white institution in that state.  With one or two exceptions 
this case will illustrate what was true of all the Southern states. 
A careful investigation of the subject will show that it was not 
until after industrial education was started among the colored 
people, and its value proved, that it was taken up by the Southern 
white people. 
</p><p>Manual training or industrial and technical schools for the 
whites have, for the most part, been established under state 
auspices, and are at this time chiefly maintained by the states. 
An investigation would also show that in securing money from the 
state legislatures for the purpose of introducing hand work, one of 
the main arguments 
<pb n="459"/> 
used was the existence and success of 
industrial training among the Negroes.  It was often argued that 
the white boys and girls would be left behind unless they had the 
opportunities for securing the same kind of training that was being 
given the colored people.  Although it is, I think, not generally 
known, it is a fact that since the idea of industrial or technical 
education for white people took root within the last few years, 
much more money is spent annually for such education for the whites 
than for the colored people.  Any one who has not looked into the 
subject will be surprised to find how thorough and high grade the 
work is.  Take, for example, the state of Georgia, and it will be 
found that several times as much is being spent at the Industrial 
College for white girls at Milledgeville, and at the technical 
school for whites at Atlanta, as is being spent in the whole state 
for the industrial education of Negro youths.  I have met no 
Southern white educators who have not been generous in their praise 
of the Negro schools for taking the initiative in hand training. 
This fact has again served to create in matters relating to 
education a bond of sympathy between the two races in the South. 
Referring again to the influence of industrial training for the 
Negro in education, in the Northern states I find, while writing 
this article, the following announcement in the advertisement of 
what is perhaps the most high-priced and exclusive girls' seminary 
in Massachusetts:&mdash; 
</p><p>"In planning a system of education for young ladies, with the 
view of fitting them for the greatest usefulness in life, the idea 
was conceived of supplementing the purely intellectual work by a 
practical training in the art of home management and its related 
subjects. 
</p><p>"It was the first school of high literary grade to introduce 
courses in Domestic Science into the regular curriculum. 
</p><p>"The results were so gratifying as to lead to the equipment of 
Experiment Hall, a special building, fitted for the purpose of 
studying the principles of Applied Housekeeping.  Here the girls do 
the actual work of cooking, marketing, arranging menus, and attend 
to all the affairs of a well-arranged household. 
</p><p>"Courses are arranged also in sewing, dressmaking, and 
millinery; they are conducted on a similarly practical basis, and 
equip the student with a thorough knowledge of the subject." 
</p><p>A dozen years ago I do not believe that any such announcement 
would have been made. 
</p><p>Beginning with the year 1877, the Negro in the South lost 
practically all political control; that is to say, as early as 1885 
the Negro scarcely had any members of his race in the national 
Congress or state legislatures, and long before this date had 
ceased to hold state offices.  This was true, notwithstanding the 
protests and fervent oratory of such strong race leaders as 
Frederick Douglass, B. K. Bruce, John R. Lynch, P. B. S. Pinchback, 
and John M. Langston, with a host of others.  When Frederick 
Douglass, the greatest man that the race has produced, died in 
1895, it is safe to say that the Negro in the Southern states, with 
here and there a few exceptions, had practically no political 
control or political influence, except in sending delegates to 
national conventions, or in holding a few Federal positions by 
appointment.  It became evident to many of the wise Negroes that 
the race would have to depend for its success in the future less 
upon political agitations and the opportunity of holding office, 
and more upon something more tangible and substantial.  It was at 
this period in the Negro's development, when the distance between 
the races was greatest, and the spirit and ambition of the colored 
people most depressed, that the idea of industrial or business 
development was introduced 
<pb n="460"/> 
and began to be made prominent. 
It did not take the more level-headed members of the race long to 
see that while the Negro in the South was surrounded by many 
difficulties, there was practically no line drawn and little race 
discrimination in the world of commerce, banking, storekeeping, 
manufacturing, and the skilled trades, and in agriculture, and that 
in this lay his great opportunity.  They understood that, while the 
whites might object to a Negro's being a postmaster, they would not 
object to his being the president of a bank, and in the latter 
occupation they would give him assistance and encouragement.  The 
colored people were quick to see that while the negro would not be 
invited as a rule to attend the white man's prayer-meeting, he 
would be invited every time to attend the stockholders' meeting of 
a business concern in which he had an interest and that he could 
buy property in practically any portion of the South where the 
white man could buy it.  The white citizens were all the more 
willing to encourage the Negro in this economic or industrial 
development, because they saw that the prosperity of the Negro 
meant also the prosperity of the white man.  They saw, too, that 
when a Negro became the owner of a home and was a taxpayer, having 
a regular trade or other occupation, he at once became a 
conservative and safe citizen and voter; one who would consider the 
interests of his whole community before casting his ballot; and, 
further, one whose ballot could not be purchased. 
</p><p>One case in point is that of the twenty-eight teachers at our 
school in Tuskegee who applied for life-voting certificates under 
the new constitution of Alabama, not one was refused registration; 
and if I may be forgiven a personal reference, in my own case, the 
Board of Registers were kind enough to send me a special request to 
the effect that they wished me not to fail to register as a life 
voter.  I do not wish to convey the impression that all worthy 
colored people have been registered in Alabama, because there have 
been many inexcusable and unlawful omissions; but, with few 
exceptions, the 2700 who have been registered represent the best 
Negroes in the state. 
</p><p>Though in some parts of the country he is now misunderstood, 
I believe that the time is going to come when matters can be 
weighed soberly, and when the whole people are going to see that 
president Roosevelt is, and has been from the first, in line with 
this policy,&mdash;that of encouraging the colored people who by 
industry and economy have won their way into the confidence and 
respect of their neighbors.  Both before and since he became 
President I have had many conversations with him, and at all times 
I have found him enthusiastic over the plan that I have described. 
</p><p>The growth of the race in industrial and business directions 
within the last few years cannot perhaps be better illustrated than 
by the fact that what is now the largest secular national 
organization among the colored people is the National Negro 
Business League.  This organization brings together annually 
hundreds of men and women who have worked their way up from the 
bottom to the point where they are now in some cases bankers, 
merchants, manufacturers, planters, etc.  The sight of this body of 
men and women would surprise a large part of American citizens who 
do not really know the better side of the Negro's life. 
</p><p>It ought to be stated frankly here that at first, and for 
several years after the introduction of industrial training at such 
educational centres as Hampton and Tuskegee, there was opposition 
from colored people, and from portions of those Northern white 
people engaged in educational and missionary work among the colored 
people in the South.  Most of those who manifested such opposition 
were actuated by the highest and most honest motives.  From the 
<pb n="461"/> 
first the rank and file of the blacks were quick to see the 
advantages of industrial training, as is shown by the fact that 
industrial schools have always been overcrowded.  Opposition to 
industrial training was based largely on the old and narrow ground 
that it was something that the Southern white people favored, and 
therefore must be against the interests of the Negro.  Again, 
others opposed it because they feared that it meant the abandonment 
of all political privileges, and the higher or classical education 
of the race.  They feared that the final outcome would be the 
materialization of the Negro, and the smothering of his spiritual 
and aesthetic nature.  Others felt that industrial education had 
for its object the limitation of the Negro's development, and the 
branding him for all time as a special hand-working class. 
</p><p>Now that enough time has elapsed for those who opposed it to 
see that it meant none of these things, opposition, except from a 
very few of the colored people living in Boston and Washington, has 
ceased, and this system has the enthusiastic support of the Negroes 
and of most of the whites who formerly opposed it.  All are 
beginning to see that it was never meant that <hi rend="italic">all</hi> Negro youths 
should secure industrial education, any more than it is meant that 
<hi rend="italic">all</hi> white youths should pass through the Massachusetts 
Institute of Technology, or the Amherst Agricultural College, to 
the exclusion of such training as is given at Harvard, Yale, or 
Dartmouth; but that in a peculiar sense a large proportion of the 
Negro youths needed to have that education which would enable them 
to secure an economic foundation, without which no people can 
succeed in any of the higher walks of life. 
</p><p>It is because of the fact that the Tuskegee Institute began at 
the bottom, with work in the soil, in wood, in iron, in leather, 
that it has now developed to the point where it is able to furnish 
employment as teachers to twenty-eight Negro graduates of the best 
colleges in the country.  This is about three times as many Negro 
college graduates as any other institution in the United States for 
the education of colored people employs, the total number of 
officers and instructors at Tuskegee being about one hundred and 
ten. 
</p><p>Those who once opposed this see now that while the Negro youth 
who becomes skilled in agriculture and a successful farmer may not 
be able himself to pass through a purely literary college, he is 
laying the foundation for his children and grandchildren to do it 
if desirable.  Industrial education in this generation is 
contributing in the highest degree to make what is called higher 
education a success.  It is now realized that in so far as the race 
has intelligent and skillful producers, the greater will be the 
success of the minister, lawyer, doctor, and teacher.  Opposition 
has melted away, too, because all men now see that it will take a 
long time to "materialize" a race, millions of which hold neither 
houses nor railroads, nor bank stocks, nor factories, nor coal and 
gold mines. 
</p><p>Another reason for the growth of a better understanding of the 
objects and influence of industrial training is the fact, as before 
stated, that it has been taken up with such interest and activity 
by the Southern whites, and that it has been established at such 
universities as Cornell in the East, and in practically all of the 
state colleges of the great West. 
</p><p>It is now seen that the result of such education will be to 
help the black man to make for himself an independent place in our 
great American life.  It was largely the poverty of the Negro that 
made him the prey of designing politicians immediately after the 
war; and wherever poverty and lack of industry exist to-day, one 
does not find in him that deep spiritual life which the race must 
in the future possess in a higher degree. 
</p><p>To those who still express the fear 
<pb n="462"/> 
that perhaps too 
much stress is put upon industrial education for the Negro I would 
add that I should emphasize the same kind of training for any 
people, whether black or white, in the same stage of development as 
the masses of the colored people. 
</p><p>For a number of years this country has looked to Germany for 
much in the way of education, and a large number of our brightest 
men and women are sent there each year.  The official reports show 
that in Saxony, Germany, alone, there are 287 industrial schools, 
or one such school to every 14,641 people.  This is true of a 
people who have back of them centuries of wealth and culture.  In 
the South I am safe in saying that there is not more than one 
effective industrial school for every 400,000 colored people. 
</p><p>A recent dispatch from Germany says that the German Emperor 
has had a kitchen fitted up in the palace for the single purpose of 
having his daughter taught cooking.  If all classes and 
nationalities, who are in most cases thousands of years ahead of 
the Negro in the arts of civilization, continue their interest in 
industrial training, I cannot understand how any reasonable person 
can object to such education for a large part of a people who are 
in the poverty-stricken condition that is true of a large element 
of my race, especially when such hand training is combined, as it 
should be, with the best education of head and heart. 
</p><signed><hi rend="italic"> Booker T. Washington.</hi></signed> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
