<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WasFair"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="WasFair"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Is the Negro Having a Fair Chance?</title>
<title type="sort">is the negro having a fair chance</title>
<author>Washington, Booker T.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp> 
<name/> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">47</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WasFair</idno> 
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476460</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Is the Negro Having a Fair Chance?</title>
<title level="j">The Century Magazine</title>
<title type="sort">is the negro having a fair chance</title>
<author>Booker T. Washington</author>
</titleStmt> 
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt> 
<extent>pp 46-55</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Century Company</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1912-11">November 1912</date> 
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa Library Call Number: AP2 .C4</idno>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>The Century Illustrated Monthly Magazine, Vol. 85 (New Series Vol. 63), No. 1, November 1912.</p>
</note> 
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images,one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p> 
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1912">1912</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term> 
<term>democracy</term>
</keywords> 
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
<term>prose</term> 
<term>African-American</term>
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-10">October 1996</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Craig Simmons; Electronic Text Center at The University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2"> 
 
<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> <pb n="46"/> 

<head>IS THE NEGRO HAVING A FAIR CHANCE?<lb/> 
BY BOOKER T. WASHINGTON</head> 
 
<div2 type="preface" id="d4"> 
<p> 
IF I were asked the simple, direct question, "Does the negro in 
America have a fair chance?" it would be easy to answer simply, 
"No," and then refer to instances with which every one is familiar 
to justify this reply.  Such a statement would, however, be 
misleading to any one who was not intimately acquainted with the 
actual situation.  For that reason I have chosen to make my answer 
not less candid and direct, I hope, but a little more substantial. 
</p> 
</div2> 
 
<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d5"> 
<head>THE NEGRO TREATED BETTER IN AMERICA THAN ELSEWHERE</head> 
<p> 
ALTHOUGH I have never visited either Africa or the West Indies to 
see for myself the condition of the people in these countries, I 
have had opportunities from time to time, outside of the knowledge 
I have gained from books, to get some insight into actual 
conditions there.  But I do not intend to assert or even suggest 
that the condition of the American negro is satisfactory, nor that 
he has in all things a fair chance.  Nevertheless, from all that I 
can learn I believe I am safe in saying that nowhere are there ten 
millions of black people who have greater opportunities or are 
making greater progress than the negroes in America.</p> 
 
<p>I know that few native Africans will agree with me in this 
statement.  For example, we had at Tuskegee a student from the Gold 
Coast who came to America to study in our Bible Training School and 
incidentally to learn something of our methods of study and work. 
He did not approve at all of our course of study.  There was not 
enough theology, and too much work to suit him.  As far as he was 
concerned, he could not see any value in learning to work, and he 
thought it was a pretty poor sort of country in which the people 
had to devote so much time to labor.  "In my country," he said, 
"everything grows of itself.  We do not have to work.  We can 
devote all our time to the larger life." 
</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d6"> 
<head>LITTLE IMMIGRATION OF NEGROES</head> 
<p> 
IN the last ten years the official records show that 37,000 negroes 
have left other countries to take residence in the United States. 
I can find no evidence to show that any considerable number of 
black people have given up residence in America. 
</p><p>The striking fact is, that negroes from other countries are 
constantly coming into the United States, and few are going out. 
This seems in part to answer the question as to whether the negro 
is having a fair chance in America as compared with any other 
country in which negroes live in any large numbers. 
</p><p>By far the largest number of negro immigrants come from the 
West Indies.  Even Haiti, a free negro republic, furnishes a 
considerable number of immigrants every year.  In all my experience 
and observation, however, I cannot recall a single instance in 
which a negro has left the United States to become a citizen of the 
Haitian Republic.  On the other hand, not a few leaders of thought 
and action among the negroes in the United States are those who 
have given up citizenship in the little Black Republic in order to 
live under the Stars and Stripes.  The majority of the colored 
people who come from the West Indies do so because of the economic 
opportunities which the United States offers them.  Another large 
group, however, comes to get education.  Here at the Tuskegee 
Institute in Alabama we usually have not far from one hundred 
students from South America and the various West Indian Islands. 
In the matter of opportunity to secure the old-fashioned, abstract 
book education several of the West Indian Islands give negroes a 
better chance than is afforded them in most of 
<pb n="47"/> 
our Southern States, but for industrial and technical education they are 
compelled to come to the United States. 
</p><p>In the matter of political and civil rights, including 
protection of life and property and even-handed justice in the 
courts, negroes in the West Indies have the advantage of negroes in 
the United States.  In the island of Jamaica, for example, there 
are about 15,000 white people and 600,000 black people, but of the 
"race problem," in regard to which there is much agitation in this 
country, one hears almost nothing there.  Jamaica has neither mobs, 
race riots, lynchings, nor burnings, such as disgrace our 
civilization.  In that country there is likewise no bitterness 
between white man and black man.  One reason for this is that the 
laws are conceived and executed with exact and absolute justice, 
without regard to race or color. 
</p> 
</div2><div2 type="section" n="3" id="d7"> 
<head>UNEQUAL LAWS THE CAUSE OF RACIAL TROUBLE IN AMERICA</head> 
<p> 
REDUCED to its lowest terms, the fact is that a large part of our 
racial troubles in the United States grow out of some attempt to 
pass and execute a law that will make and keep one man superior to 
another, whether he is intrinsically superior or not.  No greater 
harm can be done to any group of people than to let them feel that 
a statutory enactment can keep them superior to anybody else.  No 
greater injury can be done to any youth than to let him feel that 
because he belongs to this or that race, or because of his color, 
he will be advanced in life regardless of his own merits or 
efforts. 
</p><p>In what I have said I do not mean to suggest that in the West 
Indian Islands there is any more social intermingling between 
whites and blacks than there is in the United States.  The trouble 
in most parts of the United States is that mere civil and legal 
privileges are confused with social intermingling.  The fact that 
two men ride in the same railway coach does not mean in any country 
in the world that they are socially equal. 
</p><p>The facts seem to show, however, that after the West Indian 
negro has carefully weighed his civil and political privileges 
against the economic and other advantages to be found in the United 
States, he decides that, all things considered, he has a better 
chance in the United States than at home.  The negro in Haiti 
votes, but votes have not made that country happy; or have not even 
made it free, in any true sense of the word.  There is one other 
fact I might add to this comparison: nearly all the negro church 
organizations in the United States have mission churches in the 
islands, as they have also in Africa. 
</p><p>Does the negro in our country have a fair chance as compared 
with the native black man in Africa, the home of the negro?  In the 
midst of the preparation of this article, I met Bishop Isaiah B. 
Scott of the Methodist Episcopal Church, one of the strongest and 
most intelligent colored men that I know.  Bishop Scott has spent 
the greater part of his life in the Southern States, but during the 
last seven years he has lived in Liberia and traveled extensively 
on the west coast of Africa, where he has come into contact with 
all classes of European white people.  In answer to my question, 
Bishop Scott dictated the following sentence, which he authorized 
me to use: 
</p><p>"The fairest white man that I have met in dealing with the 
colored man is the American white man.  He understands the colored 
man better because of his contact with him, and he has more respect 
for the colored man who has accomplished something." 
</p><p>Basing my conclusions largely on conversations which I have 
had with native Africans, with negro missionaries, and with negro 
diplomatic officials who have lived in Africa, especially on the 
west coast and in South Africa, I am led to the conclusion that, 
all things considered, the negro in the United States has a better 
chance than he has in Africa. 
</p> 
</div2><div2 type="section" n="4" id="d8"> 
<head>THE NEGRO AS A DEPENDENT RACE</head> 
<p> 
IN certain directions the negro has had greater opportunities in 
the States in which he served as a slave than he has had in the 
States in which he has been for a century or more a free man.  This 
statement is borne out by the fact that in the South the negro 
rarely has to seek labor, but, on the other hand, labor seeks him. 
In all my experience in the Southern States, I have rarely seen a 
negro man or woman seeking labor who did not find it.  In the South 
the negro has business opportunities that he does not have 
elsewhere. 
<pb n="48"/> 
While in social matters the lines are strictly 
drawn, the negro is less handicapped in business in the South than 
any other part of the country.  He is sought after as a depositor 
in banks.  If he wishes to borrow money, he gets it from the local 
bank just as quickly as the white man with the same business 
standing.  If the negro is in the grocery business or in the dry-goods trade, or if he operates a drug store, he gets his goods from 
the wholesale dealer just as readily and on as good terms as his 
white competitor.  If the Southern white man has a dwelling-house, 
a store-house, factory, school, or court-house to erect, it is 
natural for him to employ a colored man as builder or contractor to 
perform that work.  What is said to be the finest school building 
in the city of New Orleans was erected by a colored contractor.  In 
the North a colored man who ran a large grocery store would be 
looked upon as a curiosity.  The Southern white man frequently buys 
his groceries from a negro merchant. 
</p><p>Fortunately, the greater part of the colored people in the 
South have remained as farmers on the soil.  The late census shows 
that eighty per cent. of Southern negroes live on the land. 
</p><p>There are few cases where a black man cannot buy and own a 
farm in the South.  It is as a farmer in the Southern States that 
the masses of my race have economically and industrially the 
largest opportunity.  No one stops to ask before purchasing a bale 
of cotton or a bushel of corn if it has been produced by a white 
hand or a black hand. 
</p><p>The negro now owns, as near as I can estimate, 15,000 grocery 
and dry-goods stores, 300 drug stores, and 63 banks.  Negroes pay 
taxes on between $600,000,000 and $700,000,000 of property of 
various kinds in the United States.  Unless he had had a reasonably 
fair chance in the South, the negro could not have gained and held 
this large amount of property, and would not have been able to 
enter in the commerce of this country to the extent that he has. 
</p> 
</div2><div2 type="section" n="5" id="d9"> 
<head>SKILLED NEGRO LABOR BETTER TREATED IN THE SOUTH THAN IN THE NORTH. 
</head> 
<p> 
As a skilled laborer, the negro has a better opportunity in the 
South than in the North.  I think it will be found generally true 
in the South as elsewhere that wherever the negro is strong in 
numbers and in skill he gets on well with the trades-unions.  In 
these cases the unions seek to get him in, or they leave him alone, 
and in the latter case do not seek to control him.  In the Southern 
States, where the race enters in large numbers in the trades, the 
trades-unions have not had any appreciable effect in hindering the 
progress of the negro as a skilled laborer or as a worker in 
special industries, such as coal-mining, iron-mining, etc.  In 
border cities, like St. Louis, Washington, and Baltimore, however, 
the negro rarely finds work in such industries as brick-laying and 
carpentry.  One of the saddest examples of this fact that I ever 
witnessed was in the City of Washington, where on the campus of 
Howard University, a negro institution, a large brick building was 
in process of erection.  Every man laying brick on this building 
was white, every man carrying a hod was a negro.  The white man, in 
this instance, was willing to erect a building in which negroes 
could study Latin, but was not willing to give negroes a chance to 
lay the bricks in its walls. 
</p><p>Let us consider for a moment the negro in the professions in 
the Southern States.  Aside from school teaching and preaching, 
into which the racial question enters in only a slight degree, 
there remain law and medicine.  All told, there are not more than 
700 colored lawyers in the Southern States, while there are perhaps 
more than 3000 doctors, dentists, and pharmacists.  With few 
exceptions, colored lawyers feel, as they tell me, that they do not 
have a fair chance before a white jury when a white lawyer is on 
the other side of the case.  Even in communities where negro 
lawyers are not discriminated against by juries, their clients feel 
that there is danger in intrusting cases to a colored lawyer. 
Mainly for these two reasons, colored lawyers are not numerous in 
the South; yet, in cases where colored lawyers combine legal 
practice with trading and real estate, they have in several 
instances been highly successful. 
</p> 
</div2><div2 type="section" n="6" id="d10"> 
<head>THE DIFFICULTY OF OBTAINING UNIFORM TREATMENT 
</head> 
<p> 
HERE again, however, it is difficult to generalize.  People speak 
of the "race <pb n="49"/> question" in the South, overlooking the fact 
that each one of the 1300 counties in the Southern States is a law 
unto itself.  The result is that there are almost as many race 
problems as there are counties.  The negro may have a fair chance 
in one county, and have no chance at all in the adjoining county. 
The Hon. Josiah T. Settles, for example, has practised both 
criminal and civil law for thirty years in Memphis.  He tells me 
that he meets with no discrimination on account of his color either 
from judges, lawyers, or juries.  There are other communities, like 
New Orleans and Little Rock, where negro lawyers are accorded the 
same fair treatment, and, I ought to add, that, almost without 
exception, negro lawyers tell me they are treated fairly by white 
judges and white lawyers. 
</p><p>The professional man who is making the greatest success in the 
South is the negro doctor, and I should include the pharmacists and 
dentists with the physicians and surgeons.  Except in a few cities, 
white doctors are always willing to consult with negro doctors. 
</p><p>The young negro physician in the South soon finds himself with 
a large and paying practice, and, as a rule, he makes use of this 
opportunity to improve the health conditions of his race in the 
community.  Some of the most prosperous men of my race in the South 
are negro doctors.  Again, the very fact that a negro cannot buy 
soda-water in a white drug store makes an opportunity for the 
colored drug store, which often becomes a sort of social center for 
the colored population. 
</p><p>From an economic point of view, the negro in the North, when 
compared with the white man, does not have a fair chance.  This is 
the feeling not only of the colored people themselves, but of 
almost every one who has examined into the conditions under which 
colored men work.  But here also one is likely to form a wrong 
opinion.  There is, to begin with, this general difference between 
the North and the South, that whereas in the South there is, as I 
have already suggested, a job looking for every idle man, in the 
North, on the contrary, there are frequently two or three idle men 
looking for every job.  In some of the large cities of the North 
there are organizations to secure employment for colored people. 
For a number of years I have kept in pretty close touch with those 
at the head of these organizations, and they tell me that in many 
cases they have been led to believe that the negro has a harder 
time in finding employment than is actually true.  The reason is 
that those who are out of employment seek these organizations. 
Those who have steady work, in positions which they have held for 
years, do not seek them. 
</p><p>As a matter of fact, I have been surprised to find how large 
a number of colored people there are in Boston, New York, 
Philadelphia, and Chicago who hold responsible positions in 
factories, stores, banks, and other places.  In regard to these 
people one hears very little.  There is a colored man, for example, 
in Cleveland who has been for years private secretary to a railway 
president.  In St. Paul there is a colored man who holds a similar 
position; in Baltimore there is still another colored private 
secretary to a railway president. 
</p> 
</div2><div2 type="section" n="7" id="d11"> 
<head>THE SHIFTING OF OCCUPATIONS. 
</head> 
<p> 
IN recent years there has been a great shifting of employment 
between the races.  A few years ago all the rough work in the 
mines, on the railway, and elsewhere was performed by Irish 
immigrants.  Now this work is done by Poles, Hungarians, and 
Italians.  In cities like New York, Chicago, and Pittsburg one 
finds to-day fewer colored people employed as hotel waiters, 
barbers, and porters than twenty years ago.  In New York, however, 
many colored men are employed in the streets and in the subways. 
In Pittsburg thousands of colored men are employed in the iron 
mills.  In Chicago negroes are employed very largely in the 
packing-houses.  Twenty years ago in these cities there were almost 
no colored people in these industries.  In addition to the changes 
I have mentioned, many colored people have gone into businesses of 
various kinds on their own account.  It should be remembered, also, 
that, while in some trades and in some places discrimination works 
in his favor.  The case in point is the Pullman-car service.  I 
question whether any white man, however efficient, could secure a 
job as a Pullman-car porter.</p> 
<pb n="50"/> 
</div2><div2 type="section" n="8" id="d12"> 
<head>BETTER OPPORTUNITY FOR EDUCATION IN THE NORTH 
</head> 
<p> 
IN the North, as a rule, the negro has the same opportunities for 
education as his white neighbor.  When it comes to making use of 
this education, however, he is frequently driven to a choice 
between becoming an agitator, who makes his living out of the 
troubles of his race, or emigrating to the Southern States, where 
the opportunities for educated colored men are large.  One of the 
greatest sources of bitterness and despondency among colored people 
in the North grows out of their inability to find a use for their 
education after they have obtained it.  Again, they are seldom sure 
of just what they may or may not do.  If one is a stranger in a 
city, he does not know in what hotel he will be permitted to stay; 
he is not certain what seat he may occupy in the theater, or 
whether he will be able to obtain a meal in a restaurant. 
</p> 
</div2><div2 type="section" n="9" id="d13"> 
<head>THE UNCERTAINTY OF TREATMENT OF THE RACE IN THE NORTH 
</head> 
<p> 
THE uncertainty, the constant fear and expectation of rebuff which 
the colored man experiences in the North, is often more humiliating 
and more wearing than the frank and impersonal discrimination which 
he meets in the South.  This is all the more true because the 
colored youth in most of the Northern States, educated as they are 
in the same schools with white youths, taught by the same teachers, 
and inspired by the same ideals of American citizenship, are not 
prepared for the discrimination that meets them when they leave 
school. 
</p><p>Despite all this, it cannot be denied that the negro has 
advantages in the North which are denied him in the South.  They 
are the opportunity to vote and to take part, to some extent, in 
making and administering the laws by which he is governed, the 
opportunity to obtain an education, and, what is of still greater 
importance, fair and unbiased treatment in the courts, the 
protection of the law. 
</p><p>I have touched upon conditions North and South, which, whether 
they affect the negro favorably or adversely, are for the most part 
so firmly entrenched in custom, prejudice, and human nature that 
they must perhaps be left to the slow changes of time.  There are 
certain conditions in the South, however, in regard to which 
colored people feel perhaps more keenly because they believe if 
they were generally understood they would be remedied.  Very 
frequently the negro people suffer injury and wrong in the South 
because they have or believe they have no way of making their 
grievances known.  Not only are they not represented in the 
legislatures, but it is sometimes hard to get a hearing even in the 
press.  On one of my educational campaigns in the South I was 
accompanied by a colored newspaper man.  He was an enterprising 
sort of chap and at every public meeting we held he would manage in 
some way to address the audience on the subject of his paper.  On 
one occasion, after appealing to the colored people for some time, 
he turned to the white portion of the audience. 
</p><p>"You white folks," he said, "ought to read our colored papers 
to find out what colored people are doing.  You ought to find out 
what they are doing and what they are thinking.  You don't know 
anything about us," he added.  "Don't you know a colored man can't 
get his name in a white paper unless he commits a crime?" 
</p><p>I do not know whether the colored newspaper man succeeded in 
getting any subscriptions by this speech or not, but there was much 
truth in his statement. 
</p> 
</div2><div2 type="section" n="10" id="d14"> 
<head>THE GREATEST SOURCE OF DISSATISFACTION TO THE NEGRO IN THE SOUTH 
</head> 
<p> 
ONE thing that many negroes feel keenly, although they do not say 
much about it to either black or white people, is the conditions of 
railway travel in the South. 
</p><p>Now and then the negro is compelled to travel.  With few 
exceptions, the railroads are almost the only great business 
concerns in the South that pursue the policy of taking just as much 
money from the black traveler as from the white traveler without 
feeling that they ought, as a matter of justice and fair play, not 
as a matter of social equality, to give one man for his money just 
as much as another man.  The failure of most of the roads to do 
justice to the negro when he travels is the source of more 
bitterness than any one other matter of which I have any knowledge. 
</p><p>It is strange that the wide-awake men <pb n="51"/> who control the 
railroads in the Southern States do not see that, as a matter of 
dollars and cents, to say nothing of any higher consideration, they 
ought to encourage, not discourage, the patronage of nine millions 
of the black race in the South.  This is a traveling population 
that is larger than the whole population of Canada, and yet, with 
here and there an exception, railway managers do not seem to see 
that there is any business advantage to them in giving this large 
portion of the population fair treatment. 
</p><p>What embitters the colored people in regard to railroad 
travel, I repeat, is not the separation, but the inadequacy of the 
accommodations.  The colored people are given half of a baggage-car 
or half of a smoking-car.  In most cases, the negro portion of the 
car is poorly ventilated, poorly lighted, and, above all, rarely 
kept clean; and then, to add to the colored man's discomfort, no 
matter how many colored women may be in the colored end of the car, 
nor how clean or how well educated these colored women may be, this 
car is made the headquarters for the newsboy.  He spreads out his 
papers, his magazines, his candy, and his cigars over two or three 
seats.  White men are constantly coming into the car and almost 
invariably light cigars while in the colored coach, so that these 
women are required to ride in what is virtually a smoking-car. 
</p><p>On some of the roads colored men and colored women are forced 
to use the same toilet-room.  This is not true of every Southern 
railway.  There are some railways in the South, notably the Western 
Railway of Alabama, which make a special effort to see that the 
colored people are given every facility in the day coaches that the 
white people have, and the colored people show in many ways that 
they appreciate this consideration. 
</p><p>Here is an experience of R. S. Lovinggood, a colored man of 
Austin, Texas.  I know Mr. Lovinggood well.  He is neither a bitter 
nor a foolish man.  I will venture to say that there is not a 
single white man in Austin, Texas, where he lives, who will say 
that Professor Lovinggood is anything but a conservative, sensible 
man. 
</p><p>"At one time," he said to me, in speaking of some of his 
traveling experiences, "I got off at a station almost starved.  I 
begged the keeper of the restaurant to sell me a lunch in a paper 
and hand it out of the window.  He refused, and I had to ride a 
hundred miles farther before I could get a sandwich. 
</p><p>"At another time I went to a station to purchase my ticket. 
I was there thirty minutes before the ticket-office was opened. 
When it did finally open I at once appeared at the window.  While 
the ticket-agent served the white people at one window, I remained 
there beating the other until the train pulled out.  I was 
compelled to jump aboard the train without my ticket and wire back 
to get my trunk expressed.  Considering the temper of the people, 
the separate coach law may be the wisest plan for the South, but 
the statement that the two races have equal accommodations is all 
bosh.  I pay the same money, but I cannot have a chair or a 
lavatory and rarely a through car.  I must crawl out at all times 
of night, and in all kinds of weather, in order to catch another 
dirty 'Jim Crow' coach to make my connections.  I do not ask to 
ride with white people.  I do ask for equal accommodations for the 
same money." 
</p> 
</div2><div2 type="section" n="11" id="d15"> 
<head>LACK OF A "SQUARE DEAL" IN EDUCATION IN THE SOUTH 
</head> 
<p> 
IN the matter of education, the negro in the South has not had what 
Colonel Roosevelt calls a "square deal."  In the North, not only 
the Jew, the Slav, the Italian, many of whom are such recent 
arrivals that they have not yet become citizens and voters, even 
under the easy terms granted them by the naturalization laws of the 
Northern States, have all the advantages of education that are 
granted to every other portion of the population, but in several 
States an effort is now being made to give immigrant peoples 
special opportunities for education over and above those given to 
the average citizen.  In some instances, night schools are started 
for their special benefit.  Frequently schools which run nine 
months in the winter are continued throughout the summer, whenever 
a sufficient number of people can be induced to attend them. 
Sometimes, as for example, in New York State, where large numbers 
of men are employed in digging the Erie Canal and in excavating the 
Croton Aqueduct, camp <pb n="52"/> schools are started where the men 
employed on these public works in the day may have an opportunity 
to learn the English language at night.  In some cases a special 
kind of text-book, written in two or three different languages, has 
been prepared for use in these immigrant schools, and frequently 
teachers are specially employed who can teach in the native 
languages if necessary. 
</p><p>While in the North all this effort is being made to provide 
education for these foreign peoples, many of whom are merely 
sojourners in this country, and will return in a few months to 
their homes in Europe, it is only natural that the negro in the 
South should feel that he is unfairly treated when he has, as is 
often true in the country districts, either no school at all, or 
one with a term of no more than four or five months, taught in the 
wreck of a log-cabin and by a teacher who is paid about half the 
price of a first-class convict. 
</p><p>This is no mere rhetorical statement.  If a negro steals or 
commits a murderous assault of some kind, he will be tried and 
imprisoned, and then, if he is classed as a first-class convict, he 
will be rented out at the rate of $46 per month for twelve months 
in the year.  The negro who does not commit a crime, but prepares 
himself to serve the State as a first-grade teacher, will receive 
from the State for that service perhaps $30 per month for a period 
of not more than six months. 
</p><p>Taking the Southern States as a whole, about $10.23 per capita 
is spent in educating the average white boy or girl, and the sum of 
$2.82 per capita in educating the average black child. 
</p><p>Let me take as an illustration one of our Southern farming 
communities, where the colored population largely outnumbers the 
white.  In Wilcox County, Alabama, there are nearly 11,000 black 
children and 2000 white children of school age.  Last year $3569 of 
the public school fund went for the education of the black children 
in that county, and $30,294 for the education of the white 
children, this notwithstanding that there are five times as many 
negro children as white.  In other words, there was expended for 
the education of each negro child in Wilcox County thirty-three 
cents, and for each white child $15.  In the six counties 
surrounding and touching Wilcox County there are 55,000 negro 
children of school age.  There was appropriated for their education 
last year from the public school fund $40,000, while for the 19,622 
white children in the same counties there was appropriated from the 
public fund $199,000. 
</p><p>There are few, if any, intelligent white people in the South 
or anywhere else who will claim that the negro is receiving justice 
in these counties in the matter of the public school fund. 
Especially will this seem true when it is borne in mind that the 
negro is the main dependence for producing the farm products which 
constitute the chief wealth of that part of Alabama.  I say this 
because I know there are thousands of fair-minded and liberal white 
men in the South who do not know what is actually going on in their 
own States. 
</p><p>In the State of Georgia, negroes represent forty-two per cent. 
of the farmers of the State, and are largely employed as farm 
laborers on the plantations.  Notwithstanding this fact, Georgia 
has two agricultural colleges and eleven district agricultural high 
schools for whites, supported at an annual cost to the State of 
$140,000, while there is only one school where negroes have a 
chance to study agriculture, and to the support of this the State 
contributes only $8000 a year.  When one hears it said that the 
negro farmer of Georgia is incompetent and inefficient as compared 
with the white farmer of Minnesota or Wisconsin, can any one say 
that this is fair to the negro? 
</p><p>Not a few Southern white men see what is needed and are not 
afraid to say so.  A. A. Gunby of Louisiana recently said: "Every 
one competent to speak and honest enough to be candid knows that 
education benefits and improves the negro.  It makes him a better 
neighbor and workman, no matter what you put him at." 
</p><p>Every one agrees that a public library in a city tends to make 
better citizens, keeping people usefully employed instead of 
spending their time in idleness or in committing crime.  Is it 
fair, as is true of most of the large cities of the South, to take 
the negro's money in the form of taxes to support a public library, 
and then to make no provision for the negro using any library?  I 
am glad to say that some of the cities, for instance, Louisville, 
Kentucky, and Jacksonville, Florida, have <pb n="53"/> already provided 
library facilities for their black citizens or are preparing to do 
so. 
</p><p>One excuse that is frequently made in the South for not giving 
the negro a fair share of the moneys expended for education is that 
the negro is poor and does not contribute by his taxes sufficient 
to support the schools that now exist.  True, the negro is poor; 
but in the North that would be a reason for giving him more 
opportunities for education, not fewer, because it is recognized 
that one of the greatest hindrances to progress is ignorance.  As 
far as I know, only two men have ever given thorough consideration 
to the question as to the amount the negro contributes directly or 
indirectly toward his own education.  Both of these are Southern 
white men.  One of them is W. N. Sheats, former Superintendent of 
Education for the State of Florida.  The other is Charles L. Coon, 
Superintendent of Schools at Wilson, North Carolina, and formerly 
connected with the Department of Education for that State. 
</p> 
</div2><div2 type="section" n="12" id="d16"> 
<head>THE NEGRO PAYS MORE THAN HIS SHARE TO EDUCATION IN THE SOUTH. 
</head> 
<p> 
IN his annual report for 1900, Mr. Sheats made a thorough analysis 
of the sources of the school fund in Florida, and of the way in 
which it is distributed between the white and negro schools.  In 
referring to the figures which he obtained, he said: 
 
</p><p>A glance at the foregoing statistics indicates that the 
section of the State designated as "Middle Florida" is considerably 
behind all the rest in all stages of educational progress.  The 
usual plea is that this is due to the intolerable burden of negro 
education, and a general discouragement and inactivity is ascribed 
to this cause.  The following figures are given to show that the 
education of the negroes of Middle Florida does not cost the white 
people of that section one cent.  Without discussing the American 
principle that it is the duty of all property to educate every 
citizen as a means of protection to the State, and with no 
reference to what taxes that citizen may pay, it is the purpose of 
this paragraph to show that the backwardness of education of the 
white people is in no degree due to the presence of the negro, but 
that the presence of the negro has been actually contributing to 
the sustenance of the white schools. 
</p><p>Mr. Sheats shows that the amount paid for negro schools from 
negro taxes or from a division of other funds to which negroes 
contribute indirectly with the whites, amounted to $23,984.  The 
actual cost of negro schools, including their pro rata for 
administration expenses, was $19,467. 
</p><p>"If this is a fair calculation," Mr. Sheats concludes, "the 
schools for negroes are not only no burden on the white citizens, 
but $4525 for negro schools contributed from other sources was in 
some way diverted to the white schools.  A further loss to the 
negro schools is due to the fact that so few polls are collected 
from negroes by county officials." 
</p><p>Mr. Coon, in an address on "Public Taxation and Negro Schools" 
before the 1909 Conference for Education in the South, at Atlanta, 
Georgia, said: 
 
<q type="spoken">The South is spending $32,068,851 on her public schools, both 
white and black, but what part of this sum is devoted to negro 
public schools, which must serve at least forty per cent. of her 
school population?  It is not possible to answer this question with 
absolute accuracy, but it is possible from the several State 
reports to find out the whole amount spent for teachers, and in all 
the States, except Arkansas, what was spent for white and negro 
teachers separately.  The aggregate amount now being spent for 
public teachers of both races in these eleven States is 
$23,856,914, or 74.4 per cent. of the whole amount expended.  Of 
this sum not more than $3,818,705 was paid to negro teachers, or 
twelve per cent. of the total expenditures. 
</q> 
</p> 
<p>He also brought out the fact that in Virginia, if, in addition 
to the direct taxes paid by negroes, they had received their 
proportion of the taxes on corporate property and other special 
taxes, such as fertilizers, liquor, etc., there would have been 
expended on the negro schools $18,077 more than was expended; that 
is, they would have received $507,305 instead of $489,228.  In 
North Carolina there would have been expended $26,539 more than was 
expended, the negroes receiving $429,197 instead of $402,658.  In 
Georgia there would have been expended on the negro schools 
$141,682 more than was expended. 
</p><p>In other words, Superintendent Coon <pb n="54"/> seems to prove that 
negro schools in the States referred to are not only no burden to 
the white tax-payers, but that the colored people do not get back 
all the money for their schools that they themselves pay in taxes. 
In each case there is a considerable amount taken from the negroes' 
taxes and spent somewhere else or for other purposes. 
</p> 
</div2><div2 type="section" n="13" id="d17"> 
<head>CONVICT LABOR A GREAT EVIL IN THE SOUTH 
</head> 
<p> 
IT would help mightily toward the higher civilization for both 
races if more white people would apply their religion to the negro 
in their community, and ask themselves how they would like to be 
treated if they were in the negro's place.  For example, no white 
man in America would feel that he was being treated with justice if 
every time he had a case in court, whether civil or criminal, every 
member of the jury was of some other race.  Yet this is true of the 
negro in nearly all of the Southern States.  There are few white 
lawyers or judges who will not admit privately that it is almost 
impossible for a negro to get justice when he has a case against a 
white man and all the members of the jury are white.  In these 
circumstances, when a negro fails to receive justice, the injury to 
him is temporary, but the injury to the character of the white man 
on the jury is permanent. 
</p><p>In Alabama eighty-five per cent. of the convicts are negroes. 
The official records show that last year Alabama had turned into 
its treasury $1,085,854 from the labor of its convicts.  At least 
$900,000 of this came from negro convicts, who were for the most 
part rented to the coal-mining companies in the northern part of 
the State.  The result of this policy has been to get as many able-bodied convicts as possible into the mines, so that contractors 
might increase their profits.  Alabama, of course, is not the only 
State that has yielded to the temptation to make money out of human 
misery.  The point is, however, that while $900,000 is turned into 
the State treasury from negro-convict labor, to say nothing of 
negro taxes, there came out of the State treasury, to pay negro 
teachers, only $357,585. 
</p><p>I speak of this matter as much in the interest of the white 
man as of the black.  Whenever and wherever the white man, acting 
as a court officer, feels that he cannot render absolute justice 
because of public sentiment, that white man is not free.  Injustice 
in the courts makes slaves of two races in the South, the white and 
the black. 
</p> 
</div2><div2 type="section" n="14" id="d18"> 
<head> 
THE BALLOT TO THE INTELLIGENT NEGRO 
</head> 
<p> 
NO influence could ever make me desire to go back to the conditions 
of Reconstruction days to secure the ballot for the negro.  That 
was an order of things that was bad for the negro and bad for the 
white man.  In most Southern States it is absolutely necessary that 
some restriction be placed upon the use of the ballot.  The actual 
methods by which this restriction was brought about have been 
widely advertised, and there is no necessity for me discussing them 
here.  At the time these measures were passed I urged that, 
whatever law went upon the statute-book in regard to the use of the 
ballot, it should apply with absolute impartiality to both races. 
This policy I advocate again in justice to both white man and 
negro. 
</p><p>Let me illustrate what I mean.  In a certain county of 
Virginia, where the county board had charge of registering those 
who were to be voters, a colored man, a graduate of Harvard 
University, who had long been a resident of the county, a quiet, 
unassuming man, went before the board to register.  He was refused 
on the ground that he was not intelligent enough to vote.  Before 
this colored man left the room a white man came in who was so 
intoxicated that he could scarcely tell where he lived.  This white 
man was registered, and by a board of intelligent white men who had 
taken an oath to deal justly in administering the law. 
</p><p>Will any one say that there is wisdom or statesmanship in such 
a policy as that?  In my opinion it is a fatal mistake to teach the 
young black man and the young white man that the dominance of the 
white race in the South rests upon any other basis than absolute 
justice to the weaker man.  It is a mistake to cultivate in the 
mind of any individual or group of individuals the feeling and 
belief that their happiness rests upon the misery of some one else, 
or that their intelligence is measured by the ignorance of some one 
else; or their wealth by the poverty of some one else.  I do not 
advocate that the negro make politics or the holding of office an 
important thing in <pb n="55"/> his life.  I do urge, in the interest of 
fair play for everybody, that a negro who prepares himself in 
property, in intelligence, and in character to cast a ballot, and 
desires to do so, should have the opportunity. 
</p><p>In these pages I have spoken plainly regarding the South 
because I love the South as I love no other part of our country, 
and I want to see her white people equal to any white people on the 
globe in material wealth, in education, and in intelligence.  I am 
certain, however, that none of these things can be secured and 
permanently maintained except they are founded on justice. 
</p> 
</div2><div2 type="section" n="15" id="d19"> 
<head>THE CRIME OF LYNCHING 
</head> 
<p> 
IN most parts of the United States the colored people feel that 
they suffer more than others as the result of the lynching habit. 
When he was Governor of Alabama, I heard Governor Jelks say in a 
public speech that he knew of five cases during his administration 
of innocent colored people having been lynched.  If that many 
innocent people were known to the governor to have been lynched, it 
is safe to say that there were other innocent persons lynched whom 
the governor did not know about.  What is true of Alabama in this 
respect is true of other States.  In short, it is safe to say that 
a large proportion of the colored people lynched are innocent. 
</p><p>A lynching-bee usually has its origin in a report that some 
crime has been committed.  The story flies from mouth to mouth. 
Excitement spreads.  Few take the time to get the facts.  A mob 
forms and fills itself with bad whisky.  Some one is captured.  In 
case rape is charged, the culprit is frequently taken before the 
person said to have been assaulted.  In the excitement of the 
moment, it is natural that the victim should say that the first 
person brought before her is guilty.  Then comes more excitement 
and more whisky.  Then comes the hanging, the shooting, or burning 
of the body. 
</p><p>Not a few cases have occurred where white people have 
blackened their faces and committed a crime, knowing that some 
negro would be suspected and mobbed for it.  In other cases it is 
known that where negroes have committed crimes, innocent men have 
been lynched and the guilty ones have escaped and gone on 
committing more crimes. 
</p><p>Within the last twelve months there have been seventy-one 
cases of lynching, nearly all of colored people.  Only seventeen 
were charged with the crime of rape.  Perhaps they are wrong to do 
so, but colored people in the South do not feel that innocence 
offers them security against lynching.  They do feel, however, that 
the lynching habit tends to give greater security to the criminal, 
white or black.  When ten millions of people feel that they are not 
sure of being fairly tried in a court of justice, when charged with 
crime, is it not natural that they should feel that they have not 
had a fair chance? 
</p><p>I am aware of the fact that in what I have said in regard to 
the hardships of the negro in this country I throw myself open to 
the criticism of doing what I have all my life condemned 
and everywhere sought to avoid; namely, laying over-emphasis on matters 
in which the negro race in America has been badly treated, and 
thereby overlooking those matters in which the negro has been 
better treated in America than anywhere else in the world. 
</p><p>What has been accomplished in the past years, however, is 
merely an indication of what can be done in the future. 
</p><p>As white and black learn day by day to adjust, in a spirit of 
justice and fair play, those interests which are individual and 
racial, and to see and feel the importance of those fundamental 
interests which are common, so will both races grow and prosper. 
In the long run no individual and no race can succeed which sets 
itself at war against the common good. 
</p> 
 
</div2> 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
