<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WasSign"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
<TEI.2 id="WasSign"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Signs of Progress among the Negroes</title>
<title type="sort">signs of progress among the negroes</title>
<author>Washington, Booker T.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">34</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WasSign</idno> 
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476463</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Signs of Progress among the Negroes</title>
<title level="j">Century Magazine</title>
<title type="sort">signs of progress among the negroes</title>
<author>Booker T. Washington</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Century Magazine</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 59, pp. 472-478</p>
</seriesStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the 
text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of 
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term> 
<term>democracy</term> 
<term>religion</term>
</keywords> 
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term> 
<term>African-American</term>
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994">1994</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Kelly Tetterton, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Minimal TEI tagging</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 
 
<body id="d2"> 

<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> <pb n="472"/> 
<head>  Washington, Booker T.  "Signs of Progress among the Negroes." 
<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic">Century Magazine</hi> 59 (1900): 472-478.</head> 
 
<p>IN addition to the problem of educating eight million negroes in 
our Southern States and ingrafting them into American citizenship, 
we now have the additional responsibility, either directly or 
indirectly, of educating and elevating about eight hundred thousand 
others of African descent in Cuba and Porto Rico, to say nothing of 
the white people of these islands, many of whom are in a condition 
about as deplorable as that of the negroes.  We have, however, one 
advantage in approaching the question of the education of our new 
neighbors. 
</p><p>The experience that we have passed through in the Southern 
States during the last thirty years in the education of my race, 
whose history and needs are not very different from the history and 
needs of the Cubans and Porto Ricans, will prove most valuable in 
elevating the blacks of the West Indian Islands.  To tell what has 
already been accomplished in the South under most difficult 
circumstances is to tell what may be done in Cuba and Porto Rico. 
</p><p>To this end let me tell a story. 
</p><p>In what is known as the black belt of the South &mdash; that is, 
where the negroes outnumber the whites &mdash; there lived before the 
Civil War a white man who owned some two hundred slaves, and was 
prosperous.  At the close of the war he found his fortune gone, 
except that which was represented in land, of which he owned 
several thousand acres.  Of the two hundred slaves a large 
proportion decided, after their freedom, to continue on the 
plantation of their former owner. 
</p><p>Some years after the war a young black boy, who seemed to have 
"rained down," was discovered on the plantation by Mr. S&mdash;, the 
owner.  In daily rides through the plantation Mr. S&mdash; saw this 
boy sitting by the roadside, and his condition awakened his pity, 
for, from want of care, he was covered from head to foot with 
sores, and Mr. S&mdash; soon grew into the habit of tossing him a 
nickel or a dime as he rode by.  In some way this boy heard of the 
Tuskegee Normal and Industrial Institute in Alabama, and of the 
advantages which it offered poor but deserving colored men and 
women to secure an education through their own labor while taking 
the course of study.  This boy, whose name was William, made known 
to the plantation hands his wish to go to the Tuskegee school.  By 
each one "chipping in," and through the efforts of the boy himself, 
a few decent pieces of clothing were secured, and a little money, 
but not enough to pay his railroad fare, so the boy resolved to 
walk to Tuskegee, a distance of about one hundred and fifty miles. 
Strange to say, he made the long distance with an expenditure of 
only twenty cents in cash.  He frankly told every one with whom he 
came in contact where he was going and what he was seeking.  Both 
white and colored people along the route gave him food and a place 
to sleep free of cost, and even the usually exacting ferrymen were 
so impressed with the young negro's desire for an education that, 
except in one case, he was given free ferriage across the creeks 
and rivers. 
</p><p>One can easily imagine his appearance when he first arrived at 
Tuskegee, with his blistered feet and small white bundle, which 
contained all the clothing he possessed. 
</p><p>On being shown into my office his first words were: "I's come. 
S'pose you been lookin' for me, but I didn't come on de railroad." 
Looking up the records, it was found that this young man had been 
given permission to come several months ago, but the correspondence 
had long since been forgotten. 
</p><p>After being sent to the bath-room and provided with a tooth-brush, &mdash;  for the tooth-brush at Tuskegee is the emblem of 
civilization, &mdash; William was assigned to a room, and was given work 
on the school farm of fourteen hundred acres, seven hundred of 
which are cultivated by student labor.  During his first year at 
Tuskegee William worked on the farm during the day, where he soon 
learned to take a deep interest in all that the school was doing to 
teach the students the best and most improved methods of farming, 
and studied for two hours at night 
<pb n="473"/> 
in the class-room after 
his hard day's work was over.  At first he seemed drowsy and dull 
in the night-school, and would now and then fall asleep while 
trying to study; but he did not grow discouraged.  The new 
machinery that he was compelled to use on the farm interested him 
because it taught him that the farm work could be stripped of much 
of the old-time drudgery and toil, and seemed to awaken his 
sleeping intellect.  Soon he began asking the farm-instructors such 
questions as where the Jersey and Holstein cattle came from, and 
why they produced more milk and butter than the common long-tailed 
and long-horned cows that he had seen at home. 
</p><p>His night-school teachers found that he ceased to sleep in 
school, and began asking questions about his lessons, and was soon 
able to calculate the number of square yards in an acre and to tell 
the number of peach-trees required to plant an acre of land.  After 
he had been at Tuskegee two or three months the farm-manager came 
into my office on a cold, rainy day, and said that William was 
virtually barefooted, the soles of his shoes having separated from 
the uppers, though William had fastened them together as best he 
could with bits of wire.  In this condition the farm-instructor 
found him plowing without a word of complaint.  A pair of second-hand shoes was secured for him, and he was soon very happy. 
</p><p>I will not take this part of the story further except to say 
that at the end of his first year at Tuskegee this young man, 
having made a start in his books, and having saved a small sum of 
money above the cost of his board, which was credited to his 
account, entered the next year our regular day-classes, though 
still dividing his time between the class-room and work on the 
farm. 
</p><p>Toward the end of the year he found himself in need of money 
with which to buy books, clothing, etc., and so wrote a carefully 
worded letter to Mr. S&mdash;, the white man on whose plantation he 
had lived, and who had been, in slavery, the owner of his mother. 
</p><p>In the letter he told Mr. S&mdash; how he got to Tuskegee, what 
he was doing, and what his needs were, and asked Mr. S&mdash; to lend 
him fifteen dollars.  Before receiving this letter Mr. S&mdash; had 
not thought once about the boy during his two years' absence; in 
fact, did not know that he had left the plantation. 
</p><p>Mr. S&mdash; was a good deal shocked, as well as amused, over 
such a request from such a source.  The letter went to the 
wastebasket without being answered.  A few weeks later William sent 
a second letter, in which he took it for granted that the first 
letter had not been received.  The second letter shared the same 
fate as the first.  A third letter reached Mr. S&mdash; in a few 
weeks, making the same request.  In answer to the third letter Mr. 
S&mdash; told me that, moved by some impulse which he himself never 
understood, he sent William the fifteen dollars. 
</p><p>Two or three years passed, and Mr. S&mdash; had about forgotten 
William and the fifteen dollars; but one morning while sitting upon 
his porch a bright young colored man walked up and introduced 
himself as William, the boy to whom he used to toss small pieces of 
money, and the one to whom he had sent fifteen dollars. 
</p><p>William paid Mr. S&mdash; the fifteen dollars with interest, 
which he had earned while teaching school after leaving Tuskegee. 
</p><p>This simple experience with this young colored man made a new 
and different person of Mr. S&mdash;, so far as the negro was 
concerned. 
</p><p>He began to think.  He thought of the long past, but he 
thought most of the future, and of his duty toward the hundreds of 
colored people on his plantation and in his community.  After 
careful thought he asked William Edwards to open a school on his 
plantation in a vacant log cabin.  That was seven years ago.  On 
this same plantation at Snow Hill, Wilcox county, Alabama, a county 
where, according to the last census, there are twenty-four thousand 
colored people and about six thousand whites, there is now a school 
with two hundred pupils, five teachers from Tuskegee, and three 
school buildings.  The school has forty acres of land.  In addition 
to the text-book lessons, the boys are taught farming and 
carpentry, and the girls sewing and general house-keeping, and the 
school is now in the act of starting a blacksmith and wheelwright 
department.  This school owes its existence almost wholly to Mr. S&mdash;, 
who gave to the trustees the forty acres of land, and has 
contributed liberally to the building fund, as well as to the pay 
of the teachers.  Gifts from a few friends in the North have been 
received, and the colored people have given their labor and small 
sums in cash.  When the people cannot find money to give, they have 
often given corn, chickens, and eggs.  The school has grown so 
popular that almost every leading white man in the community is 
willing to make a small gift toward its maintenance. 
<pb n="474"/> 
</p><p>In addition to the work done directly in the school for the 
children, the teachers in the Snow Hill school have organized a 
kind of university extension movement.  The farmers are organized 
into conferences, which hold meetings each month.  In these 
meetings they are taught better methods of agriculture, how to buy 
land, how to economize and keep out of debt, how to stop 
mortgaging, how to build school-houses and dwelling-houses with 
more than one room, how to bring about a higher moral and religious 
standing, and are warned against buying cheap jewelry, snuff, and 
whisky. 
</p><p>No one is a more interested visitor at these meetings than Mr. 
S&mdash; himself.  The matter does not end in mere talk and advice. 
The women teachers go right into the cabins of the people and show 
them how to keep them clean, how to dust, sweep, and cook. 
</p><p>When William Edwards left this community a few years ago for 
the Tuskegee school, he left the larger proportion in debt, 
mortgaging their crops every year for the food on which to live. 
Most of them were living on rented land in small one-room log 
cabins, and attempting to pay an enormous rate of interest on the 
value of their food advances.  As one old colored man expressed it, 
"I ain't got but six feet of land, and I is got to die to git dat." 
The little school taught in a cabin lasted only three or four 
months in the year.  The religion was largely a matter of the 
emotions, with almost no practical ideas of morality.  It was the 
white man for himself and the negro for himself, each in too many 
cases trying to take advantage of the other.  The situation was 
pretty well described by a black man who said to me: "I tells you 
how we votes.  We always watches de white man, and we keeps 
watchin' de white man.  De nearer it gits to 'lection-time de more 
we watches de white man.  We keeps watchin' de white man till we 
find out which way he gwine to vote; den we votes 'zactly de odder 
way.  Den we knows we is right." 
</p><p>Now how changed is all at Snow Hill, and how it is gradually 
changing each year!  Instead of the hopelessness and dejection that 
were there a few years ago, there are now light and buoyancy in the 
countenances and movements of the people.  The negroes are getting 
out of debt and buying land, ceasing to mortgage their crops, 
building houses with two or three rooms, and a higher moral and 
religious standard has been established. 
</p><p>Last May, on the day that the school had its closing 
exercises, there were present, besides the hundreds of colored-people, about fifty of the leading white men and women of the 
county, and these white people seemed as much interested in the 
work of the school as the people of my own race. 
</p><p>Only a few years ago in the State of Alabama the law in 
reference to the education of the negro read as follows: "Any 
person or persons who shall attempt to teach any free person of 
color or slave to spell, read, or write shall, upon conviction 
thereof by indictment, be fined in a sum not less than two hundred 
and fifty dollars nor more than five hundred dollars." 
</p><p>Within half a dozen years I have heard Dr. J. L. M. Curry, a 
brave, honest ex-Confederate officer, in addressing both the 
Alabama and Georgia State legislatures, say to those bodies in the 
most emphatic manner that it was as much the duty of the State to 
educate the negro children as the white children, and in each case 
Dr. Curry's words were cheered. 
</p><p>Here at Snow Hill is the foundation for the solution of the 
legal and political difficulties that exist in the South, and the 
improvement of the industrial condition of the negro in Cuba and 
Porto Rico.  This solution will not come all at once, but 
gradually.  The foundation must exist in the commercial and 
industrial development of the people of my race in the South and in 
the West Indian Islands. 
</p><p>The most intelligent whites are beginning to realize that they 
cannot go much higher than they lift the negro at the same time. 
When a black man owns and cultivates the best farm to be found in 
his county he will have the confidence and respect of most of the 
white people in that county.  When a black man is the largest 
taxpayer in his community his white neighbor will not object very 
long to his voting, and having that vote honestly counted.  Even 
now a black man who has five hundred dollars to lend has no trouble 
in finding a white man who is willing to borrow his money.  The 
negro who is a large stockholder in a railroad company will always 
be treated with justice on that railroad. 
</p><p>Many of the most intelligent colored people are learning that 
while there are many bad white men in the South, there are Southern 
whites who have the highest interests of the negro just as closely 
at heart as have any other people in any part of the country.  Many 
of the negroes are learning that it is folly not to cultivate in 
every honorable 
<pb n="475"/> 
way the friendship of the white man who is 
their next-door neighbor. 
</p><p>To describe the work being done in connection with the public 
schools by graduates of Tuskegee and other institutions in the 
South, at such places as Mount Meigs, under Miss Cornelia Bowen; 
Denmark, South Carolina; Abbeville and Newville, Alabama; 
Christiansburg, Virginia, and numbers of other places in the Gulf 
States, would be only to repeat in a larger or smaller degree what 
I have said of Snow Hill. 
</p><p>Not very long after the last national election I visited a 
town in the South, to speak at a meeting which had for its object 
the raising of money to complete the school-house.  The audience 
was about equally divided between white men and women and black men 
and women.  When the time for the collection came it was intensely 
satisfactory to observe that the white side of the audience was 
just as eager to make its small contributions as were the members 
of my own race.  But I was anxious to see how the late election had 
been conducted in that community.  I soon found out that the 
Republican party, composed almost wholly of the black people, was 
represented by an election officer in the person of one of the 
best-educated colored men in the town, that both the Democratic and 
Populist parties were equally well represented, and that there was 
no suspicion of unfairness. 
</p><p>But I wished to go a little deeper, and I soon found that one 
of the leading stores in this community was owned by a colored man; 
that a cotton-gin was owned by a colored man; that the sawmill was 
owned by another colored man.  Colored men had mortgages on white 
men's crops, and vice versa, and colored people not only owned 
land, but in several cases were renting land to white men.  Black 
men were in debt to white men, and white men were in debt to black 
men.  In a word, the industrial and commercial relations of the 
races were interwoven just as if all had been of one race. 
</p><p>An object-lesson in civilization is more potent in compelling 
people to act right than a law compelling them to do so.  Some 
years ago a colored woman who had graduated at Tuskegee began her 
life-work in a Southern community where the force of white public 
sentiment was opposed to the starting of what was termed a "nigger 
school."  At first this girl was tempted to abuse her white sister, 
but she remembered that perhaps the white woman had been taught 
from her earliest childhood, through reading and conversation, that 
education was not good for the negro, that it would result only in 
trouble to the community, and that no amount of abuse could change 
this prejudice. 
</p><p>After a while this colored teacher was married to an educated 
colored man, and they built a little cottage, which, in connection 
with her husband's farm, was a model.  One morning one of the white 
women who had been most intense in her feelings was passing this 
cottage, and her attention was attracted to the colored woman who 
was at work in her beautiful flower-garden.  A conversation took 
place concerning the flowers.  At another time this same white 
woman was so attracted by this flower-garden that she came inside 
the yard, and from the yard she went into the sitting-room and 
examined the books and papers. 
</p><p>This acquaintance has now ripened and broadened, so that to-day there are few people in that community more highly respected 
than this colored family.  What did it all?  This object-lesson. 
No one could explain that away.  One such object-lesson in every 
community in the South is more powerful than all the laws Congress 
can pass in the direction of bringing about right relations between 
blacks and whites. 
</p><p>A few months ago an agricultural county fair, the first ever 
held in that county, was organized and held at Calhoun, Alabama, by 
the teachers in the Calhoun School, which is an offshoot of the 
Hampton Institute.  Both the colored people and numbers of white 
visitors were astonished at the creditable exhibits made by the 
colored people.  Most of these white people saw the school work at 
Calhoun for the first time.  Perhaps no amount of abstract talk or 
advice could have brought them to this school, but the best hog, 
the largest pumpkin, or the most valuable bale of cotton possessed 
a common interest, and it has been a comparatively easy thing to 
extend their interest from the best hog to the work being done in 
the school-room.  Further, this fair convinced these white people, 
as almost nothing else could have done, that education was making 
the negroes better citizens rather than worse; that the people were 
not being educated away from themselves, but with their elevation 
the conditions about them were being lifted in a manner that 
possessed an interest and value for both races. 
</p><p>It was after speaking, not long ago, to the colored people at 
such a county fair in North Carolina that I was asked the next 
morning to speak to the white students at their college, 
<pb n="476"/> 
who gave me as hearty a greeting as I have ever received at 
Northern colleges. 
</p><p>But such forces as I have described &mdash; forces that are gradually 
regenerating the entire South and will regenerate Cuba and Porto 
Rico &mdash; are not started and kept in motion without a central plant &mdash; a 
power-house, where the power is generated.  I cannot describe all 
these places of power.  Perhaps the whole South and the whole 
country are most indebted to the Hampton Institute in Virginia. 
Then there is Fisk University at Nashville, Tennessee; Talladega 
College at Talladega, Alabama; Spelman Seminary, Atlanta 
University, and Atlanta Baptist College at Atlanta; Biddle 
University in North Carolina; Claflin University at Orangeburg, 
South Carolina; and Knoxville College at Knoxville, Tennessee. 
Some of these do a different grade of work, but one much needed. 
</p><p>At Tuskegee, Alabama, starting fifteen years ago in a little 
shanty with one teacher and thirty students, with no property, 
there has grown up an industrial and educational village where the 
ideas that I have referred to are put into the heads, hearts, and 
hands of an army of colored men and women, with the purpose of 
having them become centers of light and civilization in every part 
of the South.  One visiting the Tuskegee Normal and Industrial 
Institute to-day will find eight hundred and fifty students 
gathered from twenty-four States, with eighty-eight teachers and 
officers training these students in literary, religious, and 
industrial work. 
</p><p>Counting the students and the families of the instructors, the 
visitor will find a black village of about twelve hundred people. 
Instead of the old, worn-out plantation that was there fifteen 
years ago, there is a modern farm of seven hundred acres cultivated 
by student labor.  There are Jersey and Holstein cows and Berkshire 
pigs, and the butter used is made by the most modern process. 
</p><p>Aside from the dozens of neat, comfortable cottages owned by 
individual teachers and other persons, who have settled in this 
village for the purpose of educating their children, he will find 
thirty-six buildings of various kinds and sizes, owned and built by 
the school, property valued at three hundred thousand dollars. 
Perhaps the most interesting thing in connection with these 
buildings is that, with the exception of three, they have been 
built by student labor.  The friends of the school have furnished 
money to pay the teachers and for material. 
</p><p>When a building is to be erected, the teacher in charge of the 
mechanical and architectural drawing department gives to the class 
in drawing a general description of the building desired, and then 
there is a competition to see whose plan will be accepted.  These 
same students in most cases help do the practical work of putting 
up the building &mdash; some at the sawmill, the brick-yard, or in the 
carpentry, brickmaking, plastering, painting, and tinsmithing 
departments.  At the same time care is taken to see not only that 
the building goes up properly, but that the students, who are under 
intelligent instructors in their special branch, are taught at the 
same time the principles as well as the practical part of the 
trade. 
</p><p>The school has the building in the end, and the students have 
the knowledge of the trade.  This same principle applies, whether 
in the laundry, where the washing for seven or eight hundred people 
is done, or in the sewing-room, where a large part of the clothing 
for this colony is made and repaired, or in the wheelwright and 
blacksmith departments, where all the wagons and buggies used by 
the school, besides a large number for the outside public, are 
manufactured, or in the printing-office, where a large part of the 
printing for the white and colored people in this region is done. 
Twenty-six different industries are here in constant operation. 
</p><p>When the student is through with his course of training he 
goes out feeling that it is just as honorable to labor with the 
hand as with the head, and instead of his having to look for a 
place, the place usually seeks him, because he has to give that 
which the South wants.  One other thing should not be overlooked in 
our efforts to develop the black man.  As bad as slavery was, 
almost every large plantation in the South during that time was, in 
a measure, an industrial school.  It had its farming department, 
its blacksmith, wheelwright, brickmaking, carpentry, and sewing 
departments.  Thus at the close of the war our people were in 
possession of all the common and skilled labor in the South.  For 
nearly twenty years after the war we overlooked the value of the 
ante-bellum training, and no one was trained to replace these 
skilled men and women who were soon to pass away; and now, as 
skilled laborers from foreign countries, with not only educated 
hands but trained brains, begin to come into the South and take 
these positions once held by us, we are gradually waking up to the 
fact that we must compete with the white man in the industrial 
world if we would hold our own.  No one understands 
<pb n="477"/> 
his 
value in the labor world better than the old colored man. 
Recently, when a convention was held in the South by the white 
people for the purpose of inducing white settlers from the North 
and West to settle in the South, one of these colored men said to 
the president of the convention: "'Fore de Lord, boss, we's got as 
many white people down here now as we niggers can support." 
</p><p>The negro in the South has another advantage.  While there is 
prejudice against him along certain lines, &mdash; in the matter of 
business in general, and the trades especially, &mdash; there is virtually 
no prejudice so far as the native Southern white man is concerned. 
White men and black men work at the same carpenter's bench and on 
the same brick wall.  Sometimes the white man is the "boss," 
sometimes the black man is the boss. 
</p><p>Some one chaffed a colored man recently because, when he got 
through with a contract for building a house, he cleared just ten 
cents; but he said: "All right, boss; it was worth ten cents to be 
de boss of dem white men."  If a Southern white man has a contract 
to let for the building of a house, he prefers the black 
contractor, because he has been used to doing business of this 
character with a negro rather than with a white man. 
</p><p>The negro will find his way up as a man just in proportion as 
he makes himself valuable, possesses something that a white man 
wants, can do something as well as, or better than, a white man. 
</p><p>I would not have my readers get the thought that the problem 
in the South is settled, that there is nothing else to be done; far 
from this.  Long years of patient, hard work will be required for 
the betterment of the condition of the negro in the South, as well 
as for the betterment of the condition of the negro in the West 
Indies. 
</p><p>There are bright spots here and there that point the way. 
Perhaps the most that we have accomplished in the last thirty years 
is to show the North and the South how the fourteen slaves landed 
a few hundred years ago at Jamestown, Virginia, &mdash; now nearly eight 
millions of freemen in the South alone, &mdash; are to be made a safe and 
useful part of our democratic and Christian institutions. 
</p><p>The main thing that is now needed to bring about a solution of 
the difficulties in the South is money in large sums, to be used 
largely for Christian, technical, and industrial education. 
</p><p>For more than thirty years we have been trying to solve one of 
the most serious problems in the history of the world largely by 
passing around a hat in the North.  Out of their poverty the 
Southern States have done well in assisting; many more millions are 
needed, and these millions will have to come before the question as 
to the negro in the South is settled. 
</p><p>There never was a greater opportunity for men of wealth to 
place a few million dollars where they could be used in lifting up 
and regenerating a whole race; and let it always be borne in mind 
that every dollar given for the proper education of the negro in 
the South is almost as much help to the Southern white man as to 
the negro himself.  So long as the whites in the South are 
surrounded by a race that is, in a large measure, in ignorance and 
poverty, so long will this ignorance and poverty of the negro in a 
score of ways prevent the highest development of the white man. 
</p><p>The problem of lifting up the negro in Cuba and Porto Rico is 
an easier one in one respect, even if it proves more difficult in 
others.  It will be less difficult, because there is the absence of 
that higher degree of race feeling which exists in many parts of 
the United States.  Both the white Cuban and the white Spaniard 
have treated the people of African descent, in civil, political, 
military, and business matters, very much as they have treated 
others of their own race.  Oppression has not cowed and unmanned 
the Cuban negro in certain respects as it has the American negro. 
</p><p>In only a few instances is the color-line drawn.  How 
Americans will treat the negro Cuban, and what will be the tendency 
of American influences in the matter of the relation of the races, 
remains an interesting and open question.  Certainly it will place 
this country in an awkward position to have gone to war to free a 
people from Spanish cruelty, and then as soon as it gets them 
within its power to treat a large proportion of the population 
worse than did even Spain herself, simply on account of color. 
</p><p>While in the matter of the relation of the races the problem 
before us in the West Indies is easier, in respect to the 
industrial, moral, and religious sides it is more difficult.  The 
negroes on these islands are largely an agricultural people, and 
for this reason, in addition to a higher degree of mental and 
religious training, they need the same agricultural, mechanical, 
and domestic training that is fast helping the negroes in our 
<pb n="478"/> 
Southern States.  Industrial training will not only help them 
to the ownership of property, habits of thrift and economy, but the 
acquiring of these elements of strength will go further than 
anything else in improving the moral and religious condition of the 
masses, just as has been and is true of my people in the Southern 
States. 
</p><p>With the idea of getting the methods of industrial education 
pursued at Hampton and Tuskegee permanently and rightly started in 
Cuba and Porto Rico, a few of the most promising men and women from 
these islands have been brought to the Tuskegee Normal and 
Industrial Institute, and educated with the view of having them 
return and take the lead in affording industrial training on these 
islands, where the training can best be given to the masses. 
</p><p>The emphasis that I have placed upon an industrial education 
does not mean that the negro is to be excluded from the higher 
interests of life, but it does mean that in proportion as the negro 
gets the foundation, &mdash; the useful before the ornamental, &mdash; in the 
same proportion will he accelerate his progress in acquiring those 
elements which do not pertain so directly to the utilitarian. 
</p><p>Phillips Brooks once said, "One generation gathers the 
material, and the next builds the palaces."  Very largely this must 
be the material-gathering generation of black people, but in due 
time the palaces will come if we are patient. 
</p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
