<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WebDisc"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="WebDisc"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A discourse concerning paper money: in which its principles are laid open; and a method, plain and easy, for 
introducing and    continuing a plenty, without lessening the present value of it, is demonstrated. / by John Webbe</title>
<title type="sort">discourse concerning paper money in which its principles are laid open and a method, plain and easy for introducing and continuing a plenty without lessening the present value of it is demonstrated by john webbe</title>
<author>Brock: Webbe, John</author>
<respStmt> 
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Ronald Michener, University of Virginia</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">7</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WebDisc</idno> 
<date value="2000">2000</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2000 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476466</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>This text is part of the collection for the Leslie Brock Center for the Study of Colonial Currency.</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A discourse concerning paper money: in which its principles are laid open; and a method, plain and easy, for introducing and 
continuing a plenty, without lessening the present value of it, is demonstrated.</title>
<title type="sort">discourse concerning paper money in which its principles are laid open and a method, plain and easy for introducing and continuing a plenty without lessening the present value of it is demonstrated</title>
<author>John Webbe</author>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>1 page</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>W. Bradford</publisher> 
<pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace> 
<date value="1743">1742 or 1743</date> 
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Alderman Library, University of Virginia Microfiche 1077 no. 5308</idno>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This electronic text reproduces only Page 6 out of this pamphlet.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1743">1743</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term> 
<term>prose</term> 
<term>masculine</term> 
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2000-05">May, 2000</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Cynthia Filer, The Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1"> 
 
<front id="d2"> 
<div1 type="introduction" id="d3"> 
 
 
<p> 
The historical circumstances that led Franklin 
to publish his pamphlet are described in detail in Richard A. Lester's 
book, <hi rend="italic">Monetary Experiments Early American and Recent 
Scandanavian</hi>, Chapter III, "Currency Issues to Overcome Depressions 
in Pennsylvania, 1723 and 1729," Princeton University Press, 1939, pp. 
56-111.</p> 
 
<p>John Webbe dismissed Franklin's theory in a 
pamphlet "A Discourse Concerning Paper Money," published in Philadelphia 
in 1743.  The relevant passage follows.</p> 
 
<p>For a modern version of Franklin's theory, see 
Theodore Thayer, "The Land Bank System in the American Colonies," 
<hi rend="italic">Journal of Economic History</hi> vol XIII (1953), pp. 145-59, or 
Bruce Smith, "American Colonial Monetary Regimes: The Failure of the 
Quantity Theory and Some Evidence in Favor of an Alternate View," in 
<hi rend="italic">The Canadian Journal of Economics</hi>, vol 18 (1985), pp. 
531-64.</p> 
 
<p>For a critique of the theory, see Ron Michener, "Fixed Exchange Rates 
and the Quantity Theory in Colonial America," in <hi rend="italic">The 
Carnegie-Rochester Conference Series on Public Policy</hi>, vol 27 
(1987), pp. 233-308.</p> 
</div1> 
</front> 
<body id="d4"> 
<div1 type="section" id="d5"> 
 
<p> 
<pb n="6"/> 
The value of the paper-money of <hi rend="italic">Pennsylvania</hi> notwithstanding 
the obvious manner of accounting for it, is attributed by many to the 
land-security on which it is lent; and in support of this notion, the 
following argument, whoever first broached it, has been printed; which I 
shall <hi rend="italic">particularly</hi> examine; for as it has been <hi rend="italic">generally 
</hi>adopted, it cannot <hi rend="italic">with decency</hi> be condemned in the 
<hi rend="italic">lump</hi>.  It runs thus.  <hi rend="italic">As those who take bills out of the 
banks in</hi> Europe <hi rend="italic">put in money for security, so here we engage 
our Land.  And as bills issued upon money security are money, so bills 
issued upon land security are, in effect, coined land. </hi> Now the 
Banks of <hi rend="italic">Europe</hi> do actually <hi rend="italic">borrow</hi> the money lodged 
with them, and therefore <hi rend="italic">give</hi> their notes as a security for the 
repayment.  But the paper-money-bank of <hi rend="italic">Pennsylvania</hi>, to which 
the argument is applied, does not borrow but <hi rend="italic">lend</hi> money, and 
therefore <hi rend="italic">takes</hi> security from the borrowers for the repayment 
at the times stipulated.  The two cases then, instead of having the 
<hi rend="italic">least</hi> resemblance, being <hi rend="italic">essentially</hi> opposite; it is 
impossible that any conclusion drawn from the one should be applicable 
to the other.  Indeed the bills given by an <hi rend="italic">European</hi> bank have 
the same power as the silver promised by 'em; because the possessors 
have a <hi rend="italic">right</hi> to receive, and do also receive on demand the very 
sums expressed by such bills.  But those of <hi rend="italic">Pennsylvania 
</hi>cannot, for a like reason, nor for any reason, be considered as 
land; for tho' they be lent upon land, yet the possessors have no 
<hi rend="italic">right</hi> to demand from any man, or any body of men, any land for 
'em.</p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
