<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaBeas"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="WhaBeas"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Blond Beast</title>
<title type="sort">blond beast</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">63</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">WhaBeas</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476478</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>"Spencer" changed to "Spence" in line 4 of the third 
full paragraph of page 299.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Blond Beast</title>
<title type="sort">blond beast</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner's Magazine</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1910-09">Sept. 1910</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Volume 48</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Verification made against printed text</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of  
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1910">1910</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman and Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
<head> 
<hi rend="italic"> TALES OF MEN</hi> 
<lb/> 
Wharton, Edith.  "The Blond Beast."   
<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic"> Scribner's Magazine</hi> 48 (Sept. 1910): 291-304. 
</head> 
<pb n="291"/>  
<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d4"> 
<head>I</head> 
<p> 
IT had been almost too easy&mdash;that was young Millner's first 
feeling, as he stood again on the Spence door-step, the great 
moment of his interview behind him, and Fifth Avenue rolling its 
grimy Pactolus at his feet. 
</p><p>Halting there in the winter light, with the clang of the 
ponderous vestibule doors in his ears, and his eyes carried down 
the perspective of the packed interminable thoroughfare, he even 
dared to remember Rastignac's apostrophe to Paris, and to hazard 
recklessly under his small fair moustache: "Who knows?" 
</p><p>He, Hugh Millner, at any rate, knew a good deal already: a 
good deal more than he had imagined it possible to learn in half an 
hour's talk with a man like Orlando G. Spence; and the loud-rumouring city spread out there before him seemed to grin like an 
accomplice who knew the rest. 
</p><p>A gust of wind, whirling down from the dizzy height of the 
building on the next corner, drove sharply through his overcoat and 
compelled him to clutch at his hat.  It was a bitter January day, 
a day of fierce light and air, when the sunshine cut like icicles 
and the wind sucked one into black gulfs at the street corners.  
But Millner's complacency was like a warm lining to his shabby 
coat, and heaving steadied his hat he continued to stand on the 
Spence threshold, lost in the vision revealed to him from the 
Pisgah of its marble steps.  Yes, it was wonderful what the vision 
showed him. . . .  In his absorption he might have frozen fast to 
the door-step if the Rhadamanthine portals behind him had not 
suddenly opened to let out a slim fur-coated figure, the figure, as 
he perceived, of the youth whom he had caught in the act of 
withdrawal as he entered Mr. Spence's study, and whom the latter, 
with a wave of his affable hand, had detained to introduce as "my 
son Draper." 
</p><p>It was characteristic of the odd friendliness of the whole 
scene that the great man should have thought it worth while to call 
back and name his heir to a mere humble applicant like Millner; and 
that the heir should shed on him, from a pale high-browed face, a 
smile of such deprecating kindness.  It was characteristic, 
equally, of Millner, that he should at once mark the narrowness of 
the shoulders sustaining this ingenuous head; a narrowness, as he 
now observed, imperfectly concealed by the wide fur collar of young 
Spence's expensive and badly cut coat.  But the face took on, as 
the youth smiled his surprise at their second meeting, a look of 
almost plaintive good-will: the kind of look that Millner scorned 
and yet could never quite resist. 
</p><p>"Mr. Millner?  Are you&mdash;er&mdash;waiting?" the lad asked, with an 
intention of serviceableness that was like a finer echo of his 
father's resounding cordiality. 
</p><p>"For my motor?  No," Millner jested in his frank free voice.  
"The fact is, I was just standing here lost in the contemplation of 
my luck"&mdash;and as his companion's pale blue eyes seemed to shape a 
question, "my extraordinary luck," he explained, "in having been 
engaged as your father's secretary." 
</p><p>"Oh," the other rejoined, with a faint colour in his sallow 
cheek.  "I'm so glad," he murmured: "but I was sure&mdash;"  He stopped, 
and the two looked kindly at each other. 
</p><p>Millner averted his gaze first, almost fearful of its 
betraying the added sense of his own strength and dexterity which 
he drew from the contrast of the other's frailness. 
</p><p>"Sure?  How could any one be sure?  I don't believe in it 
yet!" he laughed out in the irony of his triumph. 
</p><p>The boy's words did not sound like a mere civility&mdash;Millner 
felt in them an homage to his power. <pb n="292"/>  
</p><p>"Oh, yes: I was sure," young Draper repeated.  "Sure as soon 
as I saw you, I mean." 
</p><p>Millner tingled again with this tribute to his physical 
straightness and bloom.  Yes, he looked his part, hang it&mdash;he 
looked it! 
</p><p>But his companion still lingered, a shy sociability in his 
eye. 
</p><p>"If you're walking, then, can I go along a little way?"  And 
he nodded southward down the shabby gaudy avenue. 
</p><p>That, again, was part of the high comedy of the hour&mdash;that 
Millner should descend the Spence steps at young Spence's side, and 
stroll down Fifth Avenue with him at the proudest moment of the 
afternoon; O. G. Spence's secretary walking abroad with O. G. 
Spence's heir!  He had the scientific detachment to pull out his 
watch and furtively note the hour.  Yes&mdash;it was exactly forty 
minutes since he had rung the Spence door-bell and handed his card 
to a gelid footman, who, openly sceptical of his claim to be 
received, had left him unceremoniously planted on the cold 
tessellations of the vestibule. 
</p><p>"Some day," Miller grinned to himself, "I think I'll take that 
footman as furnace-man&mdash;or to do the boots."  And he pictured his 
marble palace rising from the earth to form the mausoleum of a 
footman's pride. 
</p><p>Only forty minutes ago!  And now he had his opportunity fast!  
And he never meant to let it go!  It was incredible, what had 
happened in the interval.  He had gone up the Spence steps an 
unknown young man, out of a job, and with no substantial hope of 
getting into one: a needy young man with a mother and two limp 
sisters to be helped, and a lengthening figure of debt that stood 
by his bed through the anxious nights.  And he went down the steps 
with his present assured, and his future lit by the hues of the 
rainbow above the pot of gold.  Certainly a fellow who made his way 
at that rate had it "in him," and could afford to trust his star. 
</p><p>Descending from this joyous flight he stooped his ear to the 
discourse of young Spence. 
</p><p>"My father'll work you rather hard, you know: but you look as 
if you wouldn't mind that." 
</p><p>Millner pulled up his inches with the self-consciousness of 
the man who had none to waste.  "Oh, no, I shan't mind that: I 
don't mind any amount of work if it leads to something." 
</p><p>"Just so," Draper Spence assented eagerly.  "That's what I 
feel.  And you'll find that whatever my father undertakes leads to 
such awfully fine things." 
</p><p>Millner tightened his lips on a grin.  He was thinking only of 
where the work would lead him, not in the least of where it might 
land the eminent Orlando G. Spence.  But he looked at his companion 
sympathetically. 
</p><p>"You're a philanthropist like your father, I see?" 
</p><p>"Oh, I don't know."  They had paused at a crossing, and young 
Draper, with a dubious air, stood striking his agate-headed stick 
against the curb-stone.  "I believe in a purpose, don't you?" he 
asked, lifting his blue eyes suddenly to Millner's face. 
</p><p>"A purpose?  I should rather say so!  I believe in nothing 
else," cried Millner, feeling as if his were something he could 
grip in his hand and swing like a club. 
</p><p>Young Spence seemed relieved.  "Yes&mdash;I tie up to that.  There 
<hi rend="italic"> is</hi> a Purpose.  And so, after all, even if I don't agree with my 
father on minor points . . ."  He coloured quickly, and looked 
again at Millner.  "I should like to talk to you about this some 
day." 
</p><p>Millner smothered another smile.  "We'll have lots of talks, 
I hope." 
</p><p>"Oh, if you can spare the time&mdash;!" said Draper, almost humbly. 
</p><p>"Why, I shall be there on tap!" 
</p><p>"For father, not me."  Draper hesitated, with another self-confessing smile.  "Father thinks I talk too much&mdash;that I keep 
going in and out of things.  He doesn't believe in analyzing: he 
thinks it's destructive.  But it hasn't destroyed my ideals."  He 
looked wistfully up and down the clanging street.  "And that's the 
main thing, isn't it?  I mean, that one should have an Ideal."  He 
turned back almost gaily to Millner.  "I suspect you're a 
revolutionist too!" 
</p><p>"Revolutionist?  Rather!  I belong to the Red Syndicate and 
the Black Hand!" Millner joyfully assented. 
</p><p>Young Draper chuckled at the enormity of the joke.  "First 
rate!  We'll have incendiary meetings!"  He pulled an elaborately 
armorial watch from his enfolding <pb n="293"/>  furs.  "I'm so sorry, but 
I must say good-bye&mdash;this is my street," he explained.  Millner, 
with a faint twinge of envy, glanced across at the colonnaded 
marble edifice in the farther corner.  "Going to the club?" he said 
carelessly. 
</p><p>His companion looked surprised.  "Oh, no: I never go <hi rend="italic"> 
there</hi>.  It's too boring."  And he brought out, after one of the 
pauses in which he seemed rather breathlessly to measure the 
chances of his listener's indulgence: "I'm just going over to a 
little Bible Class I have in Tenth Avenue." 

</p><p>Millner, for a moment or two, stood watching the slim figure 
wind its way through the mass of vehicles to the opposite corner; 
then he pursued his own course down Fifth Avenue, measuring his 
steps to the rhythmic refrain: "It's too easy&mdash;it's too easy&mdash;it's 
too easy!" 
</p><p>His own destination being the small shabby flat off University 
Place where three tender females awaited the result of his mission, 
he had time, on the way home, after abandoning himself to a general 
sense of triumph, to dwell specifically on the various aspects of 
his achievement.  Viewed materially and practically, it was a thing 
to be proud of; yet it was chiefly on aesthetic grounds&mdash;because he 
had done so exactly what he had set out to do&mdash;that he glowed with 
pride at the afternoon's work.  For, after all, any young man with 
the proper "pull" might have applied to Orlando G. Spence for the 
post of secretary, and even have penetrated as far as the great 
man's study; but that he, Hugh Millner, should not only have forced 
his way to this fastness, but have established, within a short half 
hour, his right to remain there permanently: well, this, if it 
proved anything, proved that the first rule of success was to know 
how to live up to one's principles. 
</p><p>"One must have a plan&mdash;one must have a plan," the young man 
murmured, looking with pity at the vague faces which the crowd bore 
past him, and feeling almost impelled to detain them and expound 
his doctrine.  But the planlessness of average human nature was of 
course the measure of his opportunity; and he smiled to think that 
every purposeless face he met was a guarantee of his own 
advancement, a rung in the ladder he meant to climb. 
</p><p>Yes, the whole secret of success was to know what one wanted 
to do, and not to be afraid to do it.  His own history was proving 
that already.  He had not been afraid to give up his small but safe 
position in a real-estate office for the precarious adventure of a 
private secretaryship; and his first glimpse of his new employer 
had convinced him that he had not mistaken his calling.  When one 
has a "way" with one&mdash;as, in all modesty, Millner knew he had&mdash;not 
to utilize it is a stupid waste of force.  And when he had learned 
that Orlando G. Spence was in search of a private secretary who 
should be able to give him intelligent assistance in the execution 
of his philanthropic schemes, the young man felt that his hour had 
come.  It was no part of his plan to associate himself with one of 
the masters of finance: he had a notion that minnows who go to a 
whale to learn how to grow bigger are likely to be swallowed in the 
process.  The opportunity of a clever young man with a cool head 
and no prejudices (this again was drawn from life) lay rather in 
making himself indispensable to one of the beneficent rich, and in 
using the timidities and conformities of his patron as the means of 
his scruples about formulating these principles to himself.  It was 
not for nothing that, in his college days, he had hunted the 
hypothetical "moral sense" to its lair, and dragged from their 
concealment the various self-advancing sentiments dissembled under 
its edifying guise.  His strength lay in his precocious insight 
into the springs of action, and in his refusal to classify them 
according to the accepted moral and social sanctions.  He had to 
the full the courage of his lack of convictions. 
</p><p>To a young man so untrammelled by prejudice it was self-evident that helpless philanthropists like Orlando G. Spence were 
just as much the natural diet of the strong as the lamb is of the 
wolf.  It was pleasanter to eat than to be eaten, in a world where, 
as yet, there seemed to be no third alternative; and any scruples 
one might feel as to the temporary discomfort of one's victim were 
speedily dispelled by that larger scientific view which took into 
account the social destructiveness of the benevolent.  Millner was 
persuaded that every individual woe mitigated by the philanthropy 
of Orlando G. Spence added <pb n="294"/>  just so much to the sum-total of 
human inefficiency, and it was one of his favourite subjects of 
speculation to picture the innumerable social evils that may follow 
upon the rescue of one infant from Mount Taygetus. 
</p><p>"We're all born to prey on each other, and pity for suffering 
is one of the most elementary stages of egotism.  Until one has 
passed beyond, and acquired a taste for the more complex forms of 
the instinct&mdash;" 
</p><p>He stopped suddenly, checked in his advance by a sallow wisp 
of a dog which had plunged through the press of vehicles to hurl 
itself between his legs.  Millner did not dislike animals, though 
he preferred that they should be healthy and handsome.  The dog 
under his feet was neither.  Its cringing contour showed an 
injudicious mingling of races, and its meagre coat betrayed the 
deplorable habit of sleeping in coal-holes and subsisting on an 
innutritious diet.  In addition to these physical disadvantages, 
its shrinking and inconsequent movements revealed a congenital 
weakness of character which, even under more favourable conditions, 
would hardly have qualified it to become a useful member of 
society; and Millner was not sorry to notice that it moved with a 
limp of the hind leg that probably doomed it to speedy extinction. 
</p><p>The absurdity of such an animal's attempting to cross Fifth 
Avenue at the most crowded hour of the afternoon struck him as only 
less great than the irony of its having been permitted to achieve 
the feat; and he stood a moment looking at it, and wondering what 
had moved it to the attempt.  It was really a perfect type of the 
human derelict which Orlando G. Spence and his kind were devoting 
their millions to perpetuate, and he reflected how much better 
Nature knew her business in dealing with the superfluous quadruped. 
</p><p>An elderly lady advancing in the opposite direction evidently 
took a less dispassionate view of the case, for she paused to 
remark emotionally: "Oh, you poor thing!" while she stooped to 
caress the object of her sympathy.  The dog, with characteristic 
lack of discrimination, viewed her gesture with suspicion, and met 
it with a snarl.  The lady turned pale and shrank away, a 
chivalrous male repelled the animal with his umbrella, and two idle 
boys backed his action by a vigorous "Hi!"  The object of these 
hostile demonstrations, apparently attributing them not to its own 
unsocial conduct, but merely to the chronic animosity of the 
universe, dashed wildly around the corner into a side street, and 
as it did so Millner noticed that the lame leg left a little trail 
of blood.  Irresistibly, he turned the corner to see what would 
happen next.  It was deplorably clear that the animal itself had no 
plan; but after several inconsequent and contradictory movements it 
plunged down an area, where it backed up against the iron gate, 
forlornly and foolishly at bay. 
</p><p>Millner, still following, looked down at it, and wondered.  
Then he whistled, just to see if it would come; but this only 
caused it to start up on its quivering legs, with desperate turns 
of the head that measured the chances of escape. 
</p><p>"Oh, hang it, you poor devil, stay there if you like!" the 
young man murmured, walking away. 
</p><p>A few yards off he looked back, and saw that the dog had made 
a rush out of the area and was limping furtively down the street.  
The idle boys were in the offing, and he disliked the thought of 
leaving them in control of the situation.  Softly, with infinite 
precautions, he began to follow the dog.  He did not know why he 
was doing it, but the impulse was overmastering.  For a moment he 
seemed to be gaining upon his quarry, but with a cunning sense of 
his approach it suddenly turned and hobbled across the frozen 
grass-plot adjoining a shuttered house.  Against the wall at the 
back of the plot it cowered down in a dirty snow-drift, as if 
disheartened by the struggle.  Millner stood outside the railings 
and looked at it.  He reflected that under the shelter of the 
winter dusk it might have the luck to remain there unmolested, and 
that in the morning it would probably be dead of cold.  This was so 
obviously the best solution that he began to move away again; but 
as he did so the idle boys confronted him. 
</p><p>"Ketch yer dog for yer, boss?" they grinned. 
</p><p>Millner consigned them to the devil, and stood sternly 
watching them till the first stage of the journey had carried them 
around the nearest corner; then, after pausing to look once more up 
and down <pb n="295"/>  the empty street, laid his hand on the railing, 
and vaulted over it into the grass-plot.  As he did so, he 
reflected that, since pity for suffering was one of the most 
elementary forms of egotism, he ought to have remembered that it 
was necessarily one of the most tenacious. 
</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d5"> 
<head>II</head> 

<p>"My chief aim in life?" Orlando G. Spence repeated.  He threw 
himself back in his chair, straightened the tortoise-shell <hi rend="italic"> 
pince-nez</hi>, on his short blunt nose, and beamed down the luncheon 
table at the two young men who shared his repast. 
</p><p>His glance rested on his son Draper, seated opposite him 
behind a barrier of Georgian silver and orchids; but his words were 
addressed to his secretary who, stylograph in hand, had turned from 
the seductions of a mushroom <hi rend="italic"> souffle</hi> in order to jot down, for 
the Sunday <hi rend="italic"> Investigator</hi>, an outline of his employer's views and 
intentions respecting the newly endowed Orlando G. Spence College 
for Missionaries.  It was Mr. Spence's practice to receive in 
person the journalists privileged to impart his opinions to a 
waiting world; but during the last few months&mdash;and especially since 
the vast project of the Missionary College had been in process of 
development&mdash;the pressure of business and beneficence had 
necessitated Millner's frequent intervention, and compelled the 
secretary to snatch the sense of his patron's elucubrations between 
the courses of their hasty meals. 
</p><p>Young Millner had a healthy appetite, and it was not one of 
his least sacrifices to be so often obliged to curb it in the 
interest of his advancement; but whenever he waved aside one of the 
triumphs of Mr. Spence's <hi rend="italic"> chef</hi> he was conscious of rising a step 
in his employer's favour.  Mr. Spence did not despise the pleasures 
of the table, though he appeared to regard them as the reward of 
success rather than as the alleviation of effort; and it increased 
his sense of his secretary's merit to note how keenly the young man 
enjoyed the fare which he was so frequently obliged to deny 
himself.  Draper, having subsisted since infancy on a diet of 
truffles and terrapin, consumed such delicacies with the 
insensibility of a traveller swallowing a railway sandwich; but 
Millner never made the mistake of concealing from Mr. Spence his 
sense of what he was losing when duty constrained him to exchange 
the fork for the pen. 
</p><p>"My chief aim in life!" Mr. Spence repeated, removing his eye-glass and swinging it thoughtfully on his finger.  ("I'm sorry you 
should miss this <hi rend="italic"> souffle</hi>, Millner: it's worth while.)  Why, I 
suppose I might say that my chief aim in life is to leave the world 
better than I found it.  Yes: I don't know that I could put it 
better than that.  To leave the world better than I found it.  It 
wouldn't be a bad idea to use that as a head-line.  <hi rend="italic"> 'Wants to 
leave the world better than he found it.'</hi>  It's exactly the point 
I should like to make in this talk about the College." 
</p><p>Mr. Spence paused, and his glance once more reverted to his 
son, who, having pushed aside his plate, sat watching Millner with 
a dreamy intensity. 
</p><p>"And it's the point I want to make with you, too, Draper," his 
father continued genially, while he turned over with a critical 
fork the plump and perfectly matched asparagus which a footman was 
presenting to his notice.  "I want to make you feel that nothing 
else counts in comparison with that&mdash;no amount of literary success 
or intellectual celebrity." 
</p><p>"Oh, I <hi rend="italic"> do</hi> feel that," Draper murmured, with one of his 
quick blushes, and a glance that wavered between his father and 
Millner.  The secretary kept his eyes on his notes, and young 
Spence continued, after a pause: "Only the thing is&mdash;isn't it?&mdash;to 
try and find out just what <hi rend="italic"> does</hi> make the world better?" 
</p><p>"To <hi rend="italic"> try</hi> to find out?" his father echoed compassionately.  
"It's not necessary to try very hard.  Goodness is what makes the 
world better." 
</p><p>"Yes, yes, of course," his son nervously interposed; "but the 
question is, what <hi rend="italic"> is</hi> good&mdash;" 
</p><p>Mr. Spence, with a darkening brow, brought his fist down 
emphatically on the damask.  "I'll thank you not to blaspheme, my 
son!" 
</p><p>Draper's head reared itself a trifle higher on his thin neck.  
"I was not going to blaspheme; only there may be different ways&mdash;" 
</p><p>"There's where you're mistaken, Draper.  There's only one way: 
there's my way," <pb n="296"/>  said Mr. Spence in a tone of unshaken 
conviction. 
</p><p>"I know, father; I see what you mean.  But don't you see that 
even your way wouldn't be the right way for you if you ceased to 
believe that it was?" 
</p><p>His father looked at him with mingled bewilderment and 
reprobation.  "Do you mean to say that the fact of goodness depends 
on my conception of it, and not on God Almighty's?" 
</p><p>"I do . . . yes . . . in a specific sense . . ." young Draper 
falteringly maintained; and Mr. Spence turned with a discouraged 
gesture toward his secretary's suspended pen. 
</p><p>"I don't understand your scientific jargon, Draper; and I 
don't want to.&mdash;What's the next point, Millner?  (No; no <hi rend="italic"> 
savarin</hi>.  Bring the fruit&mdash;and the coffee with it.)" 
</p><p>Millner, keenly aware that an aromatic <hi rend="italic"> savarin au rhum</hi> was 
describing an arc behind his head previous to being rushed back to 
the pantry under young Draper's indifferent eye, stiffened himself 
against this last assault of the enemy, and read out firmly: <hi rend="italic">" 
What relation do you consider that a man's business conduct should 
bear to his religious and domestic life?"</hi> 
</p><p>Mr. Spence mused a moment.  "Why, that's a stupid question.  
It goes over the same ground as the other one.  A man ought to do 
good with his money&mdash;that's all.  Go on." 
</p><p>At this point the butler's murmur in his ear caused him to 
push back his chair, and to arrest Millner's interrogatory by a 
rapid gesture.  "Yes; I'm coming.  Hold the wire."  Mr. Spence rose 
and plunged into the adjoining "office," where a telephone and a 
Remington divided the attention of a young lady in spectacles who 
was preparing for Zenana work in the East. 
</p><p>As the door closed, the butler, having placed the coffee and 
liqueurs on the table, withdrew in the rear of his battalion, and 
the two young men were left alone beneath the Rembrandts and 
Hobbemas on the dining-room walls. 
</p><p>There was a moment's silence between them; then young Spence, 
leaning across the table, said in the lowered tone of intimacy: 
"Why do you suppose he dodged that last question?" 
</p><p>Millner, who had rapidly taken an opulent purple fig from the 
fruit-dish nearest him, paused in surprise in the act of hurrying 
it to his lips. 
</p><p>"I mean," Draper hastened on, "the question as to the relation 
between business and private morality.  It's such an interesting 
one, and he's just the person who ought to tackle it." 
</p><p>Millner, despatching the fig, glanced down at his notes.  "I 
don't think your father meant to dodge the question." 
</p><p>Young Draper continued to look at him intently.  "You think he 
imagined that his answer really covers the ground?" 
</p><p>"As much as it needs to be covered." 
</p><p>The son of the house glanced away with a sigh.  "You know 
things about him that I don't," he said wistfully, but without a 
tinge of resentment in his tone. 
</p><p>"Oh, as to that&mdash;(may I give myself some coffee?)"  Millner, 
in his walk around the table to fill his cup, paused a moment to 
lay an affectionate hand on Draper's shoulder.  "Perhaps I know him 
<hi rend="italic"> better</hi>, in a sense: outsiders often get a more accurate focus." 
</p><p>Draper considered this.  "And your idea is that he acts on 
principles he has never thought of testing or defining?" 
</p><p>Millner looked up quickly, and for an instant their glances 
crossed.  "How do you mean?" 
</p><p>"I mean: that he's an inconscient instrument of goodness, as 
it were?  A&mdash;a sort of blindly beneficent force?" 
</p><p>The other smiled.  "That's not a bad definition.  I know one 
thing about him, at any rate: he's awfully upset at your having 
chucked your Bible Class." 
</p><p>A shadow fell on young Spence's candid brow.  "I know.  But 
what can I do about it?  That's what I was thinking of when I tried 
to show him that goodness, in a certain sense, is purely 
subjective: that one can't do good against one's principles."  
Again his glance appealed to Millner.  <hi rend="italic">" You</hi> understand me, 
don't you?" 
</p><p>Millner stirred his coffee in a silence not unclouded by 
perplexity.  "Theoretically, perhaps.  It's a pretty question, 
certainly.  But I also understand your father's feeling that it 
hasn't much to do with real life: especially now that he's got to 
make a speech in connection with the founding of this Missionary 
College.  He may think that any hint of internecine strife will 
<pb n="297"/>  weaken his prestige.  Mightn't you have waited a little 
longer?" 
</p><p>"How could I, when I might have been expected to take a part 
in this performance?  To talk, and say things I didn't mean?  That 
was exactly what made me decide not to wait." 
</p><p>The door opened and Mr. Spence re-entered the room.  As he did 
so his son rose abruptly as if to leave it. 
</p><p>"Where are you off to, Draper?" the banker asked. 
</p><p>"I'm in rather a hurry, sir&mdash;" 
</p><p>Mr. Spence looked at his watch.  "You can't be in more of a 
hurry than I am; and I've got seven minutes and a half."  He seated 
himself behind the coffee&mdash;tray, lit a cigar, laid his watch on the 
table, and signed to Draper to resume his place.  "No, Millner, 
don't you go; I want you both."  He turned to the secretary.  "You 
know that Draper's given up his Bible Class?  I understand it's not 
from the pressure of engagements&mdash;"  Mr. Spence's narrow lips took 
an ironic curve under the straight-clipped stubble of his 
moustache&mdash;"it's on principle, he tells me.  He's <hi rend="italic"> principled</hi> 
against doing good!" 
</p><p>Draper lifted a protesting hand.  "It's not exactly that, 
father&mdash;" 
</p><p>"I know: you'll tell me it's some scientific quibble that I 
don't understand.  I've never had time to go in for intellectual 
hair-splitting.  I've found too many people down in the mire who 
needed a hand to pull them out.  A busy man has to take his choice 
between helping his fellow-men and theorizing about them.  I've 
preferred to help.  (You might take that down for the <hi rend="italic"> 
Investigator</hi>, Millner.)  And I thank God I've never stopped to ask 
what made me want to do good.  I've just yielded to the impulse&mdash; 
that's all."  Mr. Spence turned back to his son.  "Better men than 
either of us have been satisfied with that creed, my son." 
</p><p>Draper was silent, and Mr. Spence once more addressed himself 
to his secretary.  "Millner, you're a reader: I've caught you at 
it.  And I know this boy talks to you.  What have you got to say?  
Do you suppose a Bible Class ever <hi rend="italic"> hurt</hi> anybody?" 
</p><p>Millner paused a moment, feeling all through his nervous 
system the fateful tremor of the balance.  "That's what I was just 
trying to tell him, sir&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Ah; you were?  That's good.  Then I'll only say one thing 
more.  Your doing what you've done at this particular moment hurts 
me more, Draper, than your teaching the gospel of Jesus could 
possibly have hurt those young men over in Tenth Avenue."  Mr. 
Spence arose and restored his watch to his pocket.  "I shall want 
you in twenty minutes, Millner." 
</p><p>The door closed on him, and for a while the two young men sat 
silent behind their cigar fumes.  Then Draper Spence broke out, 
with a catch in his throat: "That's what I can't bear, Millner, 
what I simply can't <hi rend="italic"> bear:</hi> to hurt him, to hurt his faith in <hi rend="italic"> 
me!</hi>  It's an awful responsibility, isn't it, to tamper with 
anybody's faith in anything?"</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="section" n="3" id="d6"><head>III</head> 

<p>THE twenty minutes prolonged themselves to forty, the forty to 
fifty, and the fifty to an hour; and still Millner waited for Mr. 
Spence's summons. 
</p><p>During the two years of his secretaryship the young man had 
learned the significance of such postponements.  Mr. Spence's days 
were organized like a railway time-table, and a delay of an hour 
implied a casualty as far-reaching as the breaking down of an 
express.  Of the cause of the present derangement Hugh Millner was 
ignorant; and the experience of the last months allowed him to 
fluctuate between conflicting conjectures.  All were based on the 
indisputable fact that Mr. Spence was "bothered"&mdash;had for some time 
past been "bothered."  And it was one of Millner's discoveries that 
an extremely parsimonious use of the emotions underlay Mr. Spence's 
expansive manner and fraternal phraseology, and that he did not 
throw away his feelings any more than (for all his philanthropy) he 
threw away his money.  If he was bothered, then, it could be only 
because a careful survey of his situation had forced on him some 
unpleasant fact with which he was not immediately prepared to deal; 
and any unpreparedness on Mr. Spence's part was also a significant 
symptom. 
</p><p>Obviously, Millner's original conception of his employer's 
character had suffered extensive modification; but no final outline 
had replaced the first conjectural image.  The two years spent in 
Mr. Spence's service had produced too many contradictory <pb n="298"/>  
impressions to be fitted into any definite pattern; and the chief 
lesson Millner had learned from them was that life was less of an 
exact science, and character a more incalculable element, than he 
had been taught in the schools.  In the light of this revised 
impression, his own footing seemed less secure than he had 
imagined, and the rungs of the ladder he was climbing more slippery 
than they had looked from below.  He was not without the reassuring 
sense of having made himself, in certain small ways, necessary to 
Mr. Spence; and this conviction was confirmed by Draper's 
reiterated assurance of his father's appreciation.  But Millner had 
begun to suspect that one might be necessary to Mr. Spence one day, 
and a superfluity, if not an obstacle, the next; and that it would 
take superhuman astuteness to foresee how and when the change would 
occur.  Every fluctuation of the great man's mood was therefore 
anxiously noted by the young meteorologist in his service; and this 
observer's vigilance was now strained to the utmost by the little 
cloud, no bigger than a man's hand, adumbrated by the banker's 
unpunctuality. 
</p><p>When Mr. Spence finally appeared, his aspect did not tend to 
dissipate the cloud.  He wore what Millner had learned to call his 
"back-door face": a blank barred countenance, in which only an 
occasional twitch of the lids behind his glasses suggested that 
some one was on the watch.  In this mood Mr. Spence usually seemed 
unconscious of his secretary's presence, or aware of it only as an 
arm terminating in a pen.  Millner, accustomed on such occasions to 
exist merely as a function, sat waiting for the click of the spring 
that should set him in action; but the pressure not being applied, 
he finally hazarded: "Are we to go on with the <hi rend="italic"> Investigator</hi>, 
sir?" 
</p><p>Mr. Spence, who had been pacing up and down between the desk 
and the fireplace, threw himself into his usual seat at Millner's 
elbow. 
</p><p>"I don't understand this new notion of Draper's," he said 
abruptly.  "Where's he got it from?  No one ever learned irreligion 
in my household." 
</p><p>He turned his eyes on Millner, who had the sense of being 
scrutinized through a ground-glass window which left him visible 
while it concealed his observer.  The young man let his pen 
describe two or three vague patterns on the blank sheet before him. 
</p><p>"Draper has ideas&mdash;" he risked at last. 
</p><p>Mr. Spence looked hard at him.  "That's all right," he said.  
"I want my son to have everything.  But what's the point of mixing 
up ideas and principles?  I've seen fellows who did that, and they 
were generally trying to borrow five dollars to get away from the 
sheriff.  What's all this talk about goodness?  Goodness isn't an 
idea.  It's a fact.  It's as solid as a business proposition.  And 
it's Draper's duty, as the son of a wealthy man, and the 
prospective steward of a great fortune, to elevate the standards of 
other young men&mdash;of young men who haven't had his opportunities.  
The rich ought to preach contentment, and to set the example 
themselves.  We have our cares, but we ought to conceal them.  We 
ought to be cheerful, and accept things as they are&mdash;not go about 
sowing dissent and restlessness.  What has Draper got to give these 
boys in his Bible Class, that's so much better than what he wants 
to take from them?  That's the question I'd like to have answered?" 
</p><p>Mr. Spence, carried away by his own eloquence, had removed his 
<hi rend="italic"> pince-nez</hi> and was twirling it about his extended fore-finger 
with the gesture habitual to him when he spoke in public.  After a 
pause, he went on, with a drop to the level of private intercourse: 
"I tell you this because I know you have a good deal of influence 
with Draper.  He has a high opinion of your brains.  But you're a 
practical fellow, and you must see what I mean.  Try to make Draper 
see it.  Make him understand how it looks to have him drop his 
Bible Class just at this particular time.  It was his own choice to 
take up religious teaching among young men.  He began with our 
office-boys, and then the work spread and was blessed.  I was 
almost alarmed, at one time, at the way it took hold of him: when 
the papers began to talk about him as a formative influence I was 
afraid he'd lose his head and go into the church.  Luckily he tried 
University Settlement first; but just as I thought he was settling 
down to that, he took to worrying about the Higher Criticism, and 
saying he couldn't go on teaching fairy-tales as history.  I can't 
see that any good ever came of criticizing what our parents 
believed, and it's a queer time for <pb n="299"/>  Draper to 
criticize <hi rend="italic"> 
my</hi> belief just as I'm backing it to the extent of five millions." 
</p><p>Millner remained silent; and, as though his silence were an 
argument, Mr. Spence continued combatively: "Draper's always 
talking about some distinction between religion and morality.  I 
don't understand what he means.  I got my morals out of the Bible, 
and I guess there's enough left in it for Draper.  If religion 
won't make a man moral, I don't see why irreligion should.  And he 
talks about using his mind&mdash;well, can't he use that in Wall Street?  
A man can get a good deal farther in life watching the market than 
picking holes in Genesis; and he can do more good too.  There's a 
time for everything; and Draper seems to me to have mixed up week-days with Sunday." 
</p><p>Mr. Spence replaced his eye-glasses, and stretching his hand 
to the silver box at his elbow, extracted from it one of the long 
cigars sheathed in gold-leaf which were reserved for his private 
consumption.  The secretary hastened to tender him a match, and for 
a moment he puffed in silence.  When he spoke again it was in a 
different note. 
</p><p>"I've got about all the bother I can handle just now, without 
this nonsense of Draper's.  That was one of the Trustees of the 
College with me.  It seems the <hi rend="italic"> Flashlight</hi> has been trying to 
stir up a fuss&mdash;"  Mr. Spence paused, and turned his <hi rend="italic"> pince-nez</hi> 
on his secretary.  "You haven't heard from them?" he asked. 
</p><p>"From the <hi rend="italic"> Flashlight?</hi>  No."  Millner's surprise was 
genuine. 
</p><p>He detected a gleam of relief behind Mr. Spence's glasses.  
"It may be just malicious talk.  That's the worst of good works; 
they bring out all the meanness in human nature.  And then there 
are always women mixed up in them, and there never was a woman yet 
who understood the difference between philanthropy and business."  
He drew again at his cigar, and then, with an unwonted movement, 
leaned forward and mechanically pushed the box toward Millner.  
"Help yourself," he said. 
</p><p>Millner, as mechanically, took one of the virginally cinctured 
cigars, and began to undo its wrappings.  It was the first time he 
had ever been privileged to detach that golden girdle, and nothing 
could have given him a better measure of the importance of the 
situation, and of the degree to which he was apparently involved in 
it.  "You remember that San Pablo rubber business?  That's what 
they've been raking up," said Mr. Spence abruptly. 
</p><p>Millner paused in the act of striking a match.  Then, with an 
appreciable effort of the will, he completed the gesture, applied 
the flame to his cigar, and took a long inhalation.  The cigar was 
certainly delicious. 
</p><p>Mr. Spence, drawing a little closer, leaned forward and 
touched him on the arm.  The touch caused Millner to turn his head, 
and for an instant the glance of the two men crossed at short 
range.  Millner was conscious, first, of a nearer view than he had 
ever had of his employer's face, and of its vaguely suggesting a 
seamed sandstone head, the kind of thing that lies in a corner in 
the court of a museum, and in which only the round enamelled eyes 
have resisted the wear of time.  His next feeling was that he had 
now reached the moment to which the offer of the cigar had been a 
prelude.  He had always known that, sooner or later, such a moment 
would come; all his life, in a sense, had been a preparation for 
it.  But in entering Mr. Spence's service he had not foreseen that 
it would present itself in this form.  He had seen himself 
consciously guiding that gentleman up to the moment, rather than 
being thrust into it by a stronger hand.  And his first act of 
reflection was the resolve that, in the end, his hand should prove 
the stronger of the two.  This was followed, almost immediately, by 
the idea that to be stronger than Mr. Spence's it would have to be 
very strong indeed.  It was odd that he should feel this, since&mdash;as 
far as verbal communication went&mdash;it was Mr. Spence who was asking 
for his support.  In a theoretical statement of the case the banker 
would have figured as being at Millner's mercy; but one of the 
queerest things about experience was the way it made light of 
theory.  Millner felt now as though he were being crushed by some 
inexorable engine of which he had been playing with the lever. . . 
. 
</p><p>He had always been intensely interested in observing his own 
reactions, and had regarded this faculty of self-detachment as of 
immense advantage in such a career as he had planned.  He felt this 
still, even in the act of noting his own bewilderment&mdash;<pb n="300"/> felt 
it the more in contrast to the odd unconsciousness of Mr. Spence's 
attitude, of the incredible candour of his self-abasement and self-abandonment.  It was clear that Mr. Spence was not troubled by the 
repercussion of his actions in the consciousness of others; and 
this looked like a weakness&mdash;unless it were, instead, a great 
strength. . . . 
</p><p>Through the hum of these swarming thoughts Mr. Spence's voice 
was going on.  "That's the only rag of proof they've got; and they 
got it by one of those nasty accidents that nobody can guard 
against.  I don't care how conscientiously a man attends to 
business, he can't always protect himself against meddlesome 
people.  I don't pretend to know how the letter came into their 
hands; but they've got it; and they mean to use it&mdash;and they mean 
to say that you wrote it for me, and that you knew what it was 
about when you wrote it. . . .  They'll probably be after you 
tomorrow&mdash;" 
</p><p>Mr. Spence, restoring his cigar to his lips, puffed at it 
slowly.  In the pause that followed there was an instant during 
which the universe seemed to Hugh Millner like a sounding-board 
bent above his single consciousness.  If he spoke, what thunders 
would be sent back to him from that intently listening vastness? 
</p><p>"You see?" said Mr. Spence. 
</p><p>The universal ear bent closer, as if to catch the least 
articulation of Millner's narrowed lips; but when he opened them it 
was merely to re-insert his cigar, and for a short space nothing 
passed between the two men but an exchange of smoke-rings. 
</p><p>"What do you mean to do?  There's the point," Mr. Spence at 
length sent through the rings. 
</p><p>Oh, yes, the point was there, as distinctly before Millner as 
the tip of his expensive cigar: he had seen it coming quite as soon 
as Mr. Spence.  He knew that fate was handing him an ultimatum; but 
the sense of the formidable echo which his least answer would rouse 
kept him doggedly, and almost helplessly, silent.  To let Mr. 
Spence talk on as long as possible was no doubt the best way of 
gaining time; but Millner knew that his silence was really due to 
his dread of the echo.  Suddenly, however, in a reaction of 
impatience at his own indecision, he began to speak. 
</p><p>The sound of his voice cleared his mind and strengthened his 
resolve.  It was odd how the word seemed to shape the act, though 
one knew how ancillary it really was.  As he talked, it was as if 
the globe had swung around, and he himself were upright on its 
axis, with Mr. Spence underneath, on his head.  Through the ensuing 
interchange of concise and rapid speech there sounded in Millner's 
ears the refrain to which he had walked down Fifth Avenue after his 
first talk with Mr. Spence: "It's too easy&mdash;it's too easy&mdash;it's too 
easy."  Yes, it was even easier than he had expected.  His 
sensation was that of the skilful carver who feels his good blade 
sink into a tender joint. 
</p><p>As he went on talking, this surprised sense of mastery was 
like wine in his veins.  Mr. Spence was at his mercy, after all&mdash; 
that was what it came to; but this new view of the case did not 
lessen Millner's sense of Mr. Spence's strength, it merely revealed 
to him his own superiority.  Mr. Spence was even stronger than he 
had suspected.  There could be no better proof of that than his 
faith in Millner's power to grasp the situation, and his tacit 
recognition of the young man's right to make the most of it.  
Millner felt that Mr. Spence would have despised him even more for 
not using his advantage than for not seeing it; and this homage to 
his capacity nerved him to greater alertness, and made the 
concluding moments of their talk as physically exhilarating as some 
hotly contested game. 
</p><p>When the conclusion was reached, and Millner stood at the 
goal, the golden trophy in his grasp, his first conscious thought 
was one of regret that the struggle was over.  He would have liked 
to prolong their talk for the purely aesthetic pleasure of making 
Mr. Spence lose time, and, better still, of making him forget that 
he was losing it.  The sense of advantage that the situation 
conferred was so great that when Mr. Spence rose it was as if 
Millner were dismissing him, and when he reached his hand toward 
the cigar-box it seemed to be one of Millner's cigars that he was 
taking. 
</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="section" n="4" id="d7"><head>IV</head> 

<p>THERE had been only one condition attached to the transaction: 
Millner was to speak to Draper about the Bible Class. <pb n="301"/>  
</p><p>The condition was easy to fulfil.  Millner was confident of 
his power to deflect his young friend's purpose; and he knew the 
opportunity would be given him before the day was over.  His 
professional duties despatched, he had only to go up to his room to 
wait.  Draper nearly always looked in on him for a moment before 
dinner: it was the hour most propitious to their elliptic 
interchange of words and silences. 
</p><p>Meanwhile, the waiting was an occupation in itself.  Millner 
looked about his room with new eyes.  Since the first thrill of 
initiation into its complicated comforts&mdash;the shower-bath, the 
telephone, the many-jointed reading-lamp and the vast mirrored 
presses through which he was always hunting his scant outfit&mdash; 
Millner's room had interested him no more than a railway-carriage 
in which he might have been travelling.  But now it had acquired a 
sort of historic significance as the witness of the astounding 
change in his fate.  It was Corsica, it was Brienne&mdash;it was the 
kind of spot that posterity might yet mark with a tablet.  Then he 
reflected that he should soon be leaving it, and the lustre of its 
monumental mahogany was veiled in pathos.  Why indeed should he 
linger on in bondage?  He perceived with a certain surprise that 
the only thing he should regret would be leaving Draper. . . . 
</p><p>It was odd, it was inconsequent, it was almost exasperating, 
that such a regret should obscure his triumph.  Why in the world 
should he suddenly take to regretting Draper?  If there were any 
logic in human likings, it should be to Mr. Spence that he 
inclined.  Draper, dear lad, had the illusion of an "intellectual 
sympathy" between them; but that, Millner knew, was an affair of 
reading and not of character.  Draper's temerities would always be 
of that kind; whereas his own&mdash;well, his own, put to the proof, had 
now definitely classed him with Mr. Spence rather than with Mr. 
Spence's son.  It was a consequence of this new condition&mdash;of his 
having thus distinctly and irrevocably classed himself&mdash;that, when 
Draper at length brought upon the scene his shy shamble and his 
wistful smile, Millner, for the first time, had to steel himself 
against them instead of yielding to their charm. 
</p><p>In the new order upon which he had entered, one principle of 
the old survived: the point of honour between allies.  And Millner 
had promised Mr. Spence to speak to Draper about his Bible Class. 
. . . 
</p><p>Draper, thrown back in his chair, and swinging a loose leg 
across a meagre knee, listened with his habitual gravity.  His 
downcast eyes seemed to pursue the vision which Millner's words 
evoked; and the words, to their speaker, took on a new sound as 
that candid consciousness refracted them. 
</p><p>"You know, dear boy, I perfectly see your father's point.  
It's naturally distressing to him, at this particular time, to have 
any hint of civil war leak out&mdash;" 
</p><p>Draper sat upright, laying his lank legs knee to knee. 
</p><p>"That's it, then?  I thought that was it!" 
</p><p>Millner raised a surprised glance.  <hi rend="italic">" What's</hi> it?" 
</p><p>"That it should be at this particular time&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Why, naturally, as I say!  Just as he's making, as it were, 
his public profession of faith.  You know, to men like your father 
convictions are irreducible elements&mdash;they can't be split up, and 
differently combined.  And your exegetical scruples seem to him to 
strike at the very root of his convictions." 
</p><p>Draper pulled himself to his feet and shuffled across the 
room.  Then he turned about, and stood before his friend. 
</p><p>"Is it that&mdash;or is it this?" he said; and with the word he 
drew a letter from his pocket and proffered it silently to Millner. 
</p><p>The latter, as he unfolded it, was first aware of an intense 
surprise at the young man's abruptness of tone and gesture.  
Usually Draper fluttered long about his point before making it; and 
his sudden movement seemed as mechanical as the impulsion conveyed 
by some strong spring.  The spring, of course, was in the letter; 
and to it Millner turned his startled glance, feeling the while 
that, by some curious cleavage of perception, he was continuing to 
watch Draper while he read. 
</p><p>"Oh, the beasts!" he cried. 
</p><p>He and Draper were face to face across the sheet which had 
dropped between them.  The youth's features were tightened by a 
smile that was like the ligature of a wound.  He looked white and 
withered. 
</p><p>"Ah&mdash;you knew, then?" <pb n="302"/>  
</p><p>Millner sat still, and after a moment Draper turned from him, 
walked to the hearth, and leaned against the chimney, propping his 
chin on his hands.  Millner, his head thrown back, stared up at the 
ceiling, which had suddenly become to him the image of the 
universal sounding-board hanging over his consciousness. 
</p><p>"You knew, then?" Draper repeated. 
</p><p>Millner remained silent.  He had perceived, with the surprise 
of a mathematician working out a new problem, that the lie which 
Mr. Spence had just bought of him was exactly the one gift he could 
give of his own free will to Mr. Spence's son.  This discovery gave 
the world a strange new topsy-turvyness, and set Millner's theories 
spinning about his brain like the cabin furniture of a tossing 
ship. 
</p><p>"You <hi rend="italic"> knew</hi>," said Draper, in a tone of quiet affirmation. 
</p><p>Millner righted himself, and grasped the arms of his chair as 
if that too were reeling.  "About this blackguardly charge?" 
</p><p>Draper was studying him intently.  "What does it matter if 
it's blackguardly?" 
</p><p>"Matter&mdash;?" Millner stammered. 
</p><p>"It's that, of course, in any case.  But the point is whether 
it's true or not."  Draper bent down, and picking up the crumpled 
letter, smoothed it out between his fingers.  "The point, is, 
whether my father, when he was publicly denouncing the peonage 
abuses on the San Pablo plantations over a year ago, had actually 
sold out his stock, as he announced at the time; or whether, as 
they say here&mdash;how do they put it?&mdash;he had simply transferred it to 
a dummy till the scandal should blow over, and has meanwhile gone 
on drawing his forty per cent interest on five thousand shares?  
There's the point." 
</p><p>Millner had never before heard his young friend put a case 
with such unadorned precision.  His language was like that of Mr. 
Spence making a statement to a committee meeting; and the 
resemblance to his father flashed out with ironic incongruity. 
</p><p>"You see why I've brought this letter to you&mdash;I couldn't go to 
<hi rend="italic"> him</hi> with it!"  Draper's voice faltered, and the resemblance 
vanished as suddenly as it had appeared. 
</p><p>"No; you couldn't go to him with it," said Millner slowly. 
</p><p>"And since they say here that <hi rend="italic"> you</hi> know: that they've got 
your letter proving it&mdash;"  The muscles of Draper's face quivered as 
if a blinding light had been swept over it.  "For God's sake, 
Millner&mdash;it's all right?" 
</p><p>"It's all right," said Millner, rising to his feet. 
</p><p>Draper caught him by the wrist.  "You're sure&mdash;you're 
absolutely sure?" 
</p><p>"Sure.  They know they've got nothing to go on." 
</p><p>Draper fell back a step and looked almost sternly at his 
friend.  "You know that's not what I mean.  I don't care a straw 
what they think they've got to go on.  I want to know if my 
father's all right.  If he is, they can say what they please." 
</p><p>Millner, again, felt himself under the concentrated scrutiny 
of the ceiling.  "Of course, of course.  I understand." 
</p><p>"You understand?  Then why don't you answer?" 
</p><p>Millner looked compassionately at the boy's struggling face.  
Decidedly, the battle was to the strong, and he was not sorry to be 
on the side of the legions.  But Draper's pain was as awkward as a 
material obstacle, as something that one stumbled over in a race. 
</p><p>"You know what I'm driving at, Millner."  Again Mr. Spence's 
committee-meeting tone sounded oddly through his son's strained 
voice.  "If my father's so awfully upset about my giving up my 
Bible Class, and letting it be known that I do so on conscientious 
grounds, is it because he's afraid it may be considered a criticism 
on something <hi rend="italic"> he</hi> has done which&mdash;which won't bear the test of 
the doctrines he believes in?" 
</p><p>Draper, with the last question, squared himself in front of 
Millner, as if suspecting that the latter meant to evade it by 
flight.  But Millner had never felt more disposed to stand his 
ground than at that moment. 
</p><p>"No&mdash;by Jove, no!  It's not <hi rend="italic"> that</hi>."  His relief almost 
escaped him in a cry, as he lifted his head to give back Draper's 
look. 
</p><p>"On your honour?" the other passionately pressed him. 
</p><p>"Oh, on anybody's you like&mdash;on <hi rend="italic"> yours!"</hi>  Millner could 
hardly restrain a laugh of relief.  It was vertiginous to find 
himself spared, after all, the need of an altruistic lie: he 
perceived that they were the kind he least liked. 
</p><p>Draper took a deep breath.  "You don't&mdash;Millner, a lot depends 
on this&mdash;you don't <pb n="303"/>  really think my father has any ulterior 
motive?" 
</p><p>"I think he has none but his horror of seeing you go straight 
to perdition!" 
</p><p>They looked at each other again, and Draper's tension was 
suddenly relieved by a free boyish laugh.  "It's his 
convictions&mdash;it's just his funny old convictions?" 
</p><p>"It's that, and nothing else on earth!" 
</p><p>Draper turned back to the arm-chair he had left, and let his 
narrow figure sink down into it as into a bath.  Then he looked 
over at Millner with a smile.  "I can see that I've been worrying 
him horribly.  So he really thinks I'm on the road to perdition?  
Of course you can fancy what a sick minute I had when I thought it 
might be this other reason&mdash;the damnable insinuation in this 
letter."  Draper crumpled the paper in his hand, and leaned forward 
to toss it into the coals of the grate.  "I ought to have known 
better, of course.  I ought to have remembered that, as you say, my 
father can't conceive how conduct may be independent of creed.  
That's where I was stupid&mdash;and rather base.  But that letter made 
me dizzy&mdash;I couldn't think.  Even now I can't very clearly.  I'm 
not sure what <hi rend="italic"> my</hi> convictions require of me: they seem to me so 
much less to be considered than his!  When I've done half the good 
to people that he has, it will be time enough to begin attacking 
their beliefs.  Meanwhile&mdash;meanwhile I can't touch his. . . ."  
Draper leaned forward, stretching his lank arms along his knees.  
His face was as clear as a spring sky.  "I <hi rend="italic"> won't</hi> touch them, 
Millner&mdash;Go and tell him so. . . ." 
</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="section" n="5" id="d8"><head>V</head> 

<p>In the study a half hour later Mr. Spence, watch in hand, was 
doling out his minutes again.  The peril conjured, he had recovered 
his dominion over time.  He turned his commanding eye-glasses on 
Millner. 
</p><p>"It's all settled, then?  Tell Draper I'm sorry not to see him 
again to-night&mdash;but I'm to speak at the dinner of the Legal Relief 
Association, and I'm due there in five minutes.  You and he dine 
alone here, I suppose?  Tell him I appreciate what he's done.  Some 
day he'll see that to leave the world better than we find it is the 
best we can hope to do.  (You've finished the notes for the <hi rend="italic"> 
Investigator?</hi>  Be sure you don't forget that phrase.)  Well, good 
evening: that's all, I think." 
</p><p>Smooth and compact in his glossy evening clothes, Mr. Spence 
advanced toward the study door; but as he reached it, his secretary 
stood there before him. 
</p><p>"It's not quite all, Mr. Spence." 
</p><p>Mr. Spence turned on him a look in which impatience was 
faintly tinged with apprehension.  "What else is there?  It's two 
and a half minutes to eight." 
</p><p>Millner stood his ground.  "It won't take longer than that.  
I want to tell you that, if you can conveniently replace me, I'd 
like&mdash;there are reasons why I shall have to leave you." 
</p><p>Millner was conscious of reddening as he spoke.  His redness 
deepened under Mr. Spence's dispassionate scrutiny.  He saw at once 
that the banker was not surprised at his announcement. 
</p><p>"Well, I suppose that's natural enough.  You'll want to make 
a start for yourself now.  Only, of course, for the sake of 
appearances&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Oh, certainly," Millner hastily agreed. 
</p><p>"Well, then: is that all?" Mr. Spence repeated. 
</p><p>"Nearly."  Millner paused, as if in search of an appropriate 
formula.  But after a moment he gave up the search, and pulled from 
his pocket an envelope which he held out to his employer.  "I 
merely want to give this back." 
</p><p>The hand which Mr. Spence had extended dropped to his side, 
and his sand-coloured face grew chalky.  "Give it back?"  His voice 
was as thick as Millner's.  "What's happened?  Is the bargain off?" 
</p><p>"Oh, no.  I've given you my word." 
</p><p>"Your word?"  Mr. Spence lowered at him.  "I'd like to know 
what that's worth!" 
</p><p>Millner continued to hold out the envelope.  "You do know, 
now.  It's worth <hi rend="italic"> that</hi>.  It's worth my place." 
</p><p>Mr. Spence, standing motionless before him, hesitated for an 
appreciable space of time.  His lips parted once or twice under 
their square-clipped stubble, and at last emitted: "How much more 
do you want?" 
</p><p>Millner broke into a laugh.  "Oh, I've got all I want&mdash;all and 
more!" <pb n="304"/>  
</p><p>"What&mdash;from the others?  Are you crazy?" 
</p><p>"No, you are," said Millner with a sudden recovery of 
composure.  "But you're safe&mdash;you're as safe as you'll ever be.  
Only I don't care to take this for making you so." 
</p><p>Mr. Spence slowly moistened his lips with his tongue, and 
removing his <hi rend="italic"> pince-nez</hi>, took a long hard look at Millner. 
</p><p>"I don't understand.  What other guarantee have I got?" 
</p><p>"That I mean what I say?"  Millner glanced past the banker's 
figure at his rich densely coloured background of Spanish leather 
and mahogany.  He remembered that it was from this very threshold 
that he had first seen Mr. Spence's son. 
</p><p>"What guarantee?  You've got Draper!" he said. 
</p> 
 
</div2> 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
