<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaIntr"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
 
<TEI.2 id="WhaIntr"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Introducers</title>
<title type="sort">introducers</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">69</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WhaIntr</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476497</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Introducers</title>
<title type="sort">introducers</title>
<author>Edith Wharton</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Ainslee's</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1906-01">Jan 1906</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>16</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Wharton, Edith.  "The Introducers."  <hi rend="italic">Ainslee's</hi> 16 (Dec. 1905): 139-48; 16 (Jan. 1906): 61-67.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1906-01">Jan 1906</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction ; prose</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-08">August 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added header, Tagged with TEI.2-compatible SGML, Parsed against "teilite" dtd</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
  
<div1 type="part" n="1" id="d3"><pb n="139"/><head> 
                          The INTRODUCERS <lb/> 
 
                         By EDITH WHARTON <lb/>  
 
                          &mdash; <lb/> 
 
                       A STORY IN TWO PARTS </head>

<p>AT nine o'clock on an August morning Mr. Frederick Tilney descended 
the terrace steps of Sea Lodge and strolled across the lawn to the 
cliffs. 
</p><p>The upper windows of the long white facade above the terrace 
were all close-shuttered, for at nine o'clock Newport still sleeps, 
and he who is stirring enough to venture forth at that unwonted 
hour may enjoy what no wealth could buy a little later&mdash;the 
privilege of being alone. 
</p><p>Though Mr. Tilney's habits of life, combined with the elegance 
of his appearance, declared him to be socially disposed, he was not 
insensible to the rarer pleasures of self-communion, and on this 
occasion he found peculiar gratification in the thought of having 
to himself the whole opulent extent of turf and flower border 
between Ochre Point and Bailey's Beach.  The morning was brilliant, 
with a blue horizon line pure of fog, and such a sparkle on every 
leaf and grass blade, and on every restless facet of the ever-moving sea, as would have tempted a less sophisticated fancy to 
visions of wet bows and a leaping stern, or of woodland climbs up 
the course of a mountain stream. 
</p><p>But it was so long since Mr. Tilney had found a savor in such 
innocent diversions, that the unblemished fairness of the morning 
suggested to him only a lazy well-being associated with escape from 
social duties, and the chance to finish the French novel over which 
he had fallen asleep at three o'clock that morning. 
</p><p>It was odd how he was growing to value his rare opportunities 
of being alone.  He who in his earlier years had depended on the 
stimulus of companionship as the fagged diner-out depends on the 
fillip of his first glass of champagne, was now beginning to watch 
for and cherish every momentary escape from the crowd.  It had 
grown to such a passion with him, this craving to have the world to 
himself, that he had overcome the habit of late rising, and learned 
to curtail the complications of his toilet, in order to secure a 
half hour of solitude before he was caught back into the whizzing 
social machinery. 
</p><p>"And talk of the solitude of the desert, it's nothing to the 
Newport cliffs at this hour," he mused, as he threw himself down on 
a shaded seat invitingly placed near the path which follows the 
shore.  "Sometimes I feel as if the sea, and the cliffs, and the 
skyline out there, were all a part of the stupid show&mdash;the 
expensive stage setting of a rottenly cheap play&mdash;to be folded up 
and packed away with the rest of the rubbish when the performance 
is over; and it's good to come out and find it here at this hour, 
all by itself, and not giving a hang for the ridiculous goings-on 
of which it happens to be made the temporary background.  Well&mdash; 
there's one comfort: none of the other fools really <hi rend="italic">see</hi> it&mdash; 
it's here only for those who seek it out at such an hour&mdash;and as 
I'm the only human being who does, it's here only for me, and 
belongs only to me, and not to the impenetrable asses who think 
they own it because they've paid for it at so many thousand dollars 
a foot!" 
</p><p>And Mr. Tilney, throwing out his chest with the irrepressible 
pride of possessorship, cast an eye of approval <pb n="140"/>  along the 
windings of the deserted path which skirted the lawn of Sea Lodge 
and lost itself in the trim shrubberies of the adjoining estate. 
</p><p>"Yes&mdash;it's mine&mdash;all mine&mdash;and this is the only real 
possessorship, after all!  No fear of intruders at this hour&mdash;no 
need of warning signposts, and polite requests to keep to the path.  
I don't suppose anybody ever walked along this path at my hour, and 
I don't care who walks here for the rest of the day!"  But at this 
point his meditations were interrupted by the sight of a white 
gleam through the adjacent foliage; and a moment later all his 
theories as to the habits of his neighbors had been rudely 
shattered by the appearance of a lady who, under the sheltering 
arch of a wide lace sunshade, was advancing indolently toward his 
seat. 
</p><p>"Why, you've got my bench!" she exclaimed, passing before him, 
with merriment and indignation mingling in her eyes as sun and wind 
contended on the ripples behind her. 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Your</hi> bench?" echoed Tilney, rising at her approach, and 
dissembling his annoyance under a fair pretense of hospitality.  
"If ever I thought anything on earth was mine, it's this bench." 
</p><p>The lady, who was young, tall and critical-looking, drew her 
straight brows together and smilingly pondered his assertion. 
</p><p>"I suppose you thought that because it happens to stand in the 
grounds of Sea Lodge instead of Cliffwood&mdash;<hi rend="italic">we</hi> haven't any 
benches, by the way; but my theory is a little different, as it 
happens.  I think things belong only to the people who know how to 
appreciate them." 
</p><p>"Why, so do I&mdash;if the bench isn't mine, at least the theory 
is!" Tilney protested. 
</p><p>"Well, it's mine too, and it makes the bench mine, you see," 
the young lady argued with earnestness, "because hitherto I've been 
the only person who appreciated sitting on it at this hour." 
</p><p>"Ah, hitherto, perhaps&mdash;but not since I arrived here last 
week.  I haven't missed a morning," Tilney declared. 
</p><p>She smiled.  "That explains the misunderstanding.  I've been 
away for a week, and before that no one ever ever sat on my bench 
at this hour." 
</p><p>"And since then no one has ever ever sat on <hi rend="italic">my</hi> bench at 
this hour; but, my dear Miss Grantham," Tilney gallantly concluded, 
"I shall be only too honored if you will make the first exception 
to this rule by sitting on it in my company this morning." 
</p><p>Miss Grantham was evidently a young lady of judicial temper, 
for she weighed this assertion as carefully as the other, before 
answering, with a slight tinge of condescension: "I don't know that 
you have any more right to ask me to sit on <hi rend="italic">my</hi> bench, than I 
have to ask you to sit on <hi rend="italic">yours</hi>, but for my part I am 
magnanimous enough to assume just for once that it's ours." 
</p><p>Tilney bowed his thanks and seated himself at her side.  "I 
realize how magnanimous it is of you," he returned, "for, just as 
you came round the corner, I was saying to myself that this bench 
was really the only thing in the world I could call my own&mdash;" 
</p><p>"And now I've taken half of it away from you!  But then," she 
rejoined, "you've taken the other half from <hi rend="italic"> me;</hi> and as I was 
under the same delusion as yourself, we are both in the same 
situation, and had better accommodate ourselves as best we can to 
the diminished glory of joint ownership." 
</p><p>"It would be ungrateful of me to reject so reasonable a 
proposal; but in return for my consent, would you mind telling me 
how you happen to attach such excessive importance to the ownership 
of this bench?" 
</p><p>"It isn't the bench alone&mdash;it's the bench and the hour.  They 
are the only things I have to myself." 
</p><p>Tilney met her lovely eyes with a look of intelligence.  "Ah, 
that's surprising&mdash;very surprising." 
</p><p>"Why so?" she exclaimed, a little resentfully. 
</p><p>"Because it's so exactly my own feeling." 
</p><p>Miss Grantham smiled and caressed the folds of her lace gown.  
"And is it so surprising that we should happen to have the same 
feelings?" <pb n="141"/>  
</p><p>"Not in all respects, I trust; but I never suspected you of an 
inclination for solitude." 
</p><p>She returned his scrutiny with a glance as penetrating.  
"Well, you don't look like a recluse yourself; yet I think I should 
have guessed that you sometimes have a longing to be alone." 
</p><p>"A longing?  Good heavens, it's a passion, it's becoming a 
mania!" 
</p><p>"Ah, how well I understand that.  It's the only thing that can 
tear me from my bed!" 
</p><p>"I confess one doesn't associate you with the sunrise," he 
said, letting his glance rest with amusement on the intricate 
simplicity of her apparel. 
</p><p>"And you!" she smiled back at him.  "If our friends were to be 
told that Fred Tilney and Belle Grantham were to be found sitting 
on the cliffs at nine o'clock in the morning, the day after the 
Summerton ball&mdash;" 
</p><p>"And that they had come there, not to meet each other, but to 
escape from every one else&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Oh, there's the point: that's what makes it interesting.  If 
we're in the same box why shouldn't we be on the same bench?" 
</p><p>"It requires no argument to convince me that we should.  But 
<hi rend="italic">are</hi> we in the same box?  You see I've just come, and when I saw 
you last night I supposed you were stopping with the Summertons." 
</p><p>She shook her head.  "No, I'm next door, at Cliffwood, for the 
summer." 
</p><p>"At Cliffwood?  With the Bixbys?"  He glanced at the fantastic 
chimneys and profusely carved gables which made the neighboring 
villa rise from its shrubberies like a <hi rend="italic">piece montee</hi> from a 
flower-decked dish. 
</p><p>"Well, why not, if <hi rend="italic"> you're</hi> at Sea Lodge with Mr. Magraw?" 
</p><p>"Oh, I'm only a poor itinerant devil&mdash;" 
</p><p>"And what am I but a circulating beauty?  Didn't you know I'd 
gone into the business too?  I hope you won't let professional 
jealousy interfere with our friendship." 
</p><p>"I'm not sure that I can help it, if you've really gone into 
the business.  But when I last saw you&mdash;where was it?&mdash;oh, in 
Athens&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Things were different, were they not?" she interposed.  "I 
was sketching and you were archaeologizing&mdash;do you remember that 
divine day at Delphi?  Not that you took much notice of me, by the 
way&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Wasn't one warned off the premises by the report that you 
were engaged to Lord Pytchley?" 
</p><p>She colored, and negligently dropped her sunshade between her 
eyes and his.  "Well, I wasn't, you see&mdash;and my sketches were not 
good enough to sell.  So I've taken to this kind of thing instead.  
But I thought you meant to stick to your digging." 
</p><p>He hesitated.  "I was very keen about it for a time; but I had 
a touch of the sun out in Greece that summer; and a rich fellow 
picked me up on his steam yacht and carried me off to the Black Sea 
and then to a salmon river in Norway.  I meant to go back, but I 
dawdled, and the first thing I knew they put another chap in my 
place.  And now I'm Hutchins Magraw's secretary." 
</p><p>He sat staring absently at the distant skyline, and perceiving 
that he was no longer conscious of her presence she quietly shifted 
her sunshade and let her eyes rest for a moment on his moody 
profile. 
</p><p>"Yes&mdash;that's what I call it, too.  I'm Mrs. Bixby's 
secretary&mdash;or Sadie's, I forget which.  But how much writing do you 
do?" 
</p><p>"Well, not much.  The butler attends to the invitations." 
</p><p>"I merely keep an eye on Sadie's spelling, and see that she 
doesn't sign herself 'lovingly' to young men.  Mrs. Bixby has no 
correspondents, and the dinner invitations are engraved." 
</p><p>"And what are your other duties?" 
</p><p>"Oh, the usual things&mdash;reminding Mrs. Bixby not to speak of 
her husband as <hi rend="italic"> Mr. Bixby</hi>, not to send in her cards when people 
are at home, not to let the butler say 'fine claret' in a sticky 
whisper in people's ears, not to speak of town as 'the city,' and 
not to let Mr. Bixby tell what things cost.  Mrs. Bix-<pb n="142"/> by 
takes the bit in her teeth at times, but Sadie is such a dear 
adaptable creature that, when I've broken her of trying to relieve 
her callers of their hats, I shall really have nothing left to do.  
That habit is hard to eradicate, because she is such a good girl, 
and it was so carefully inculcated at her finishing school." 
</p><p>Tilney reflected.  "Magraw is a good fellow too.  There's 
really nothing to do except to tone him down a little&mdash;as you say, 
one feels as if one didn't earn one's keep." 
</p><p>She flashed round upon him instantly.  "Ah, but I didn't say 
that.  I said the ostensible duties were easy&mdash;but how about the 
others?" 
</p><p>He looked at her a little consciously.  "What do you mean by 
the others?" 
</p><p>"I don't know how far you live up to your duties, but I'm 
horribly conscientious about mine.  And of course what we're both 
paid for is to be introducers," she said. 
</p><p>"Introducers?"  He colored slightly and, flinging his arm over 
the back of the bench, turned to command a fuller view of her face.  
"Yes, that is what we're paid for, I suppose." 
</p><p>"And that's what I hate about it, don't you?" 
</p><p>"Uncommonly," he assented with emphasis. 
</p><p>It isn't that the Bixbys are not nice people&mdash;they are, deep 
down, you know&mdash;or at least they would be, if they were leading a 
real life among their real friends.  But the very fact that one is 
abetting them to lead a false life, and renounce and deny their 
past, and impose themselves on people who wouldn't look at them if 
it were not for their money, and who rather resent their intrusion 
as it is&mdash;well, if one oughtn't to be paid well for doing such a 
job as that, I don't know what it is to work for my living!" 
</p><p>Tilney continued to observe with appreciation the dramatic 
play of feature by means of which she expressed her rising disgust 
at her task; but when she ended he merely said in a detached tone: 
"It's charming how you've preserved your illusions." 
</p><p>"My illusions?  Why, I haven't enough left for decency!" 
</p><p>"Oh, yes, you have.  About the Bixbys, and what they would be 
if one hadn't egged them on.  Why not say to yourself that, if they 
were not vulgar at heart, they would never have let themselves be 
taken in by this kind of humbug?" 
</p><p>"Is that what you say about Mr. Magraw?" 
</p><p>"I've told you that Magraw is a good fellow.  But when I ran 
across him he was simply aching to see the show, and all I've done 
is to get him a seat in the front row." 
</p><p>"Yes&mdash;but are you not expected to do something more for him?" 
</p><p>"Something more&mdash;in what line?" 
</p><p>"Well, I think the Bixbys expect me to make a match for 
Sadie." 
</p><p>"The deuce they do!  Well, we'll marry her to my man." 
</p><p>Miss Grantham uttered a cry of dismay.  "Don't suggest it even 
in joke!  Don't you see what a catastrophe it would be?" 
</p><p>"Why should it be a catastrophe?" 
</p><p>"Don't you really see?  In the first place we should both be 
out of a job, and in the second, I should earn the everlasting 
enmity of the Bixbys.  What they want for Sadie is not money but 
position.  Mrs. Bixby tells me that every day." 
</p><p>Tilney received this in meditative silence: then he said with 
a slight laugh: "Well, if position is all they want, why don't you 
choose <hi rend="italic">me</hi> as your candidate?" 
</p><p>Miss Grantham did not echo his laugh; she simply concentrated 
her gaze on his with a slowly deepening interest before answering: 
"It's a funny idea&mdash;but I believe they might do worse." 
</p><p>Tilney's hilarity increased. 
</p><p>"At any rate," she continued, without noticing it, "there's 
one thing that you and no one else can do for them, and I really 
believe that Mrs. Bixby, in her present mood, would be capable of 
rewarding you with her daughter's hand." 
</p><p>"Good heavens!  Then I should have <pb n="143"/>  to take a look at 
Miss Bixby before doing it." 
</p><p>"Oh, Sadie's charming.  Didn't you notice her last night at 
the ball?  I managed to smuggle her in, though I couldn't get the 
others invited.  What Mrs. Bixby wants," Miss Grantham earnestly 
continued, "what she's absolutely sickening for at this moment, is 
to have Sadie invited to Aline Leicester's little Louis XV. dance 
to-morrow night.  And you are the only person in Newport who can do 
it.  I didn't even have a chance to try&mdash;for the very day my 
invitation came I happened to meet Aline, and she said at once: 
'Belle, I see the Bixbys in your eye; but I don't see them in my 
ballroom.'  After that, I tried a little wire-pulling, but it 
simply made her more obstinate&mdash;you know her latest pose is to snub 
the new millionaires; and you are the only person who can persuade 
her to make an exception for the Bixbys.  Aline's family feeling is 
tremendously strong, and every one knows you are her favorite 
cousin." 
</p><p>Tilney listened attentively to this plea; but when it had 
ended he said, with a discouraging gesture: "I was just going to 
try to get an invitation for Magraw!" 
</p><p>"Lump them together, then&mdash;it will be just as easy; and if you 
<hi rend="italic">should</hi> want Mr. Bixby to do anything for you&mdash;such as putting 
you on to a good tip&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Thanks, but I've been put on to too many good tips.  If it 
weren't for the good tips I've had, I should be living like a 
gentleman on my income." 
</p><p>"Well, you'll make Mrs. Bixby think you the most eligible 
young man in Newport.  And if you could persuade Aline to ask Sadie 
to the dinner before the dance&mdash;" 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">" Comme vous y allez!</hi>  What would be my return for that?" 
</p><p>She rose with a charming gesture.  "Who knows, after all?  
Perhaps only the pleasure of doing me a very great favor." 
</p><p>"That settles it.  I'll do what I can.  But how about getting 
your costumes at such short notice?" 
</p><p>"Oh, we cabled out to Worth on the chance."  She held out her 
hand for good-by.  "If only there were something I could do for <hi rend="italic"> 
you!"</hi> 
</p><p>"Well, there is, as it happens," he rejoined with a smile.  
"If I succeed in my attempt, let Magraw dance the cotillon with you 
at Aline's." 
</p><p>She hesitated, visibly embarrassed.  "I should be delighted, 
of course.  I'm engaged already, but that's nothing.  Only&mdash;I'm 
going to be horribly frank&mdash;the Bixbys are rather a heavy load, and 
I'm not sure I can carry your friend too!" 
</p><p>"Oh, yes, you can.  That's my reason for asking you.  You see, 
I really can't help Magraw much.  It takes a woman to give a man a 
start.  Aline will say, 'Oh, bring him, if you choose'&mdash;but when he 
comes she won't take any notice of him, or introduce him to any of 
the nice women.  He was too shy to go to the Summertons' last 
night&mdash;he's really very shy under his loudness&mdash;so Aline's dance 
will be his first appearance in Newport; and if he's seen dancing 
the cotillon with you, at a little <hi rend="italic">souterie</hi> like that, with 
only a handful of people in the room, why, he's made, and my hard 
work is over for the season." 
</p><p>She smiled.  "If you take a fancy to Sadie, perhaps it's over 
for life." 
</p><p>"And if <hi rend="italic">you</hi>&mdash;by George!  No, I don't think I want you to 
dance the cotillon with Magraw." 
</p><p>"Why not?  Do you grudge me a comfortable home for my old 
age?" 
</p><p>He stood gazing at her as though for the first time his eyes 
took in the full measure of her grace. 
</p><p>"No&mdash;but I grudge <hi rend="italic">him</hi> even a cotillon with you." 
</p><p>"Ah, you and I were not made to dance cotillons with one 
another; or do anything together, except conspire at sunrise for 
each other's material advancement.  And that reminds me&mdash;I shan't 
see you again to-day, for we are going to Narragansett on Mr. 
Bixby's yacht, and to-night we have a dinner at home.  But if you 
succeed with Aline, will you send me a line in the evening?" 
<pb n="144"/>  
</p><p>He shook his head as they clasped hands once more.  "No; but 
I'll tell you about it here to-morrow morning." 
</p><p>"Very well&mdash;I'll be punctual!" she called out to him, as she 
sped away through the shrubbery. 
 
 
</p></div1><div1 type="part" n="2" id="d4">
                          <head> II.</head> 
 
<p>It was, in fact, Miss Grantham who was first on the scene the 
next morning; and so eager was she to learn the result of the 
mission with which she had charged her friend, that, instead of 
profiting by her few moments of solitude, she sat watching the path 
and chafing at Mr. Tilney's delay. 
</p><p>When he arrived, politeness restrained the question on her 
lips; but his first word was to assure her of his success.  "You 
are to bring Miss Bixby to the dinner," he announced. 
</p><p>"Oh, thank you, thank you&mdash;you're wonderful!" she exclaimed; 
"and if there's anything in the world I can do&mdash;"  She paused 
suddenly, remembering her side of the compact, and added with 
nobility: "If it is of any possible advantage to Mr. Magraw to make 
my acquaintance, I shall be very glad&mdash;" 
</p><p>She had already observed in Tilney a marked depression of 
manner, which even this handsome reaffirmation of her purpose did 
not dispel. 
</p><p>"Oh," he merely said, "I did not mean to hold you so closely 
to your bargain&mdash;" and with that he seated himself at her side, and 
lapsed into a state of dumb preoccupation. 
</p><p>Miss Grantham suffered this as long as it was possible for a 
young lady of spirit to endure; then she determined to make Mr. 
Tilney aware of her presence by withdrawing it. 
</p><p>"I am afraid," she said, rising with a smile, "that, though 
you welcomed me so handsomely yesterday, my being here seriously 
interferes with your enjoyment of the hour, and I am going to 
propose a compromise.  Since it is agreed that we are joint 
proprietors of this bench, and entitled to an equal share of its 
advantages, and since our sitting on it together practically 
negatives those advantages, I suggest that we occupy it on 
alternate mornings&mdash;and to show my gratitude for the favor you have 
done me, I will set the example by withdrawing to-day." 
</p><p>Tilney met her smile with a look of unrelieved melancholy.  "I 
don't wonder," he said, "that you find solitude less oppressive 
than my company; but since our purpose in seeking this bench is to 
snatch an hour's quiet enjoyment, and since enjoyment of any sort 
is impossible to me to-day, it is obviously you who are entitled to 
remain here, and I who ought to take myself away."  And he held out 
his hand in farewell. 
</p><p>Miss Grantham detained it in hers.  "To have you surrender 
your rights because you are too miserable to enjoy them, leaves me 
with no heart to profit by my own; and if you wish me to remain you 
must stay also, and tell me what it is that troubles you." 
</p><p>She reseated herself as she spoke, and Tilney, with a 
deprecating gesture, resumed his place at her side. 
</p><p>"My dear Miss Grantham, the subject is too trifling to 
mention; I was only trying to calculate how long one could live in 
Venice on a hundred dollars." 
</p><p>"Why in Venice&mdash;and why a hundred dollars?" 
</p><p>"Because, when my passage is paid, it will be all the ready 
money I possess, and I have always heard that one could live very 
moderately in Venice." 
</p><p>Miss Grantham flushed and threw a quick glance at him.  
"You're not thinking of deserting?" she cried, reproachfully. 
</p><p>The young man returned her look.  "Deserting&mdash;whom?" he 
inquired. 
</p><p>"Well, me, if you choose!  You can't think the comfort it's 
been to me, since yesterday, to know that there were two of us.  I 
understand now how humane it is to chain convicts together!" 
</p><p>Tilney considered this with a faint smile.  "How long have you 
been at it?" he asked. 
</p><p>"At the Bixbys?  I joined them last April in Paris." 
</p><p>"Ah, well&mdash;I've been six months <pb n="145"/>  with Magraw.  It 
wasn't so bad when we were yachting and knocking about the world&mdash; 
but since we've taken to society it has become unendurable." 
</p><p>"Yes.  I didn't mind ordering the Bixbys' dresses as much as 
I mind providing opportunities for their wearing them." 
</p><p>"I don't so much mind trotting Magraw about&mdash;though you know 
it's nonsense about your having to dance with him this evening&mdash;" 
</p><p>"No matter about that.  What <hi rend="italic">is</hi> it that bothers you?" 
</p><p>"The whole preposterous situation.  Magraw's the best fellow 
in the world&mdash;but there are moments when he takes me for the 
butler." 
</p><p>"Oh, I know," she sympathized.  "Mrs. Bixby&mdash;" 
</p><p>"That isn't the worst, though: it's the reaction.  He took me 
for the butler yesterday afternoon&mdash;and in the evening I found a 
ruby scarf pin on my dressing table." 
</p><p>But her sympathy was ready for any demand on it.  "I know, I 
know&mdash;" she reiterated; and then, breaking off, she added with a 
mounting color: "You know I couldn't go to the dance to-night if 
Mrs. Bixby didn't pay for my dress." 
</p><p>"Oh, the cases are not the same; and it's different for a 
woman." 
</p><p>"Why are the cases not the same?  And why should I not be 
humiliated by what humiliates you?" 
</p><p>He shrugged his shoulders ironically.  "I'm not humiliated by 
anything that poor Magraw does to me; I'm humiliated by what I do 
to <hi rend="italic"> him!</hi>: 
</p><p>"What you do?" 
</p><p>"Yes.  What right have I to behave like a gentleman, and 
return his scarf pins?" 
</p><p>"At least you do return them?  And I can't return the dresses.  
Oh, it's detestable either way!" she exclaimed. 
</p><p>"Yes, especially when one succumbs to the weakness of hating 
<hi rend="italic">them</hi> instead of one's self.  I hate Magraw this morning," he 
confessed. 
</p><p>She rose with an impatient glance at her watch.  "Dear me, I 
must go.  I promised Sadie to see the dressmaker at half-past nine: 
she's coming to alter our fancy dresses.  You see I felt sure you 
would get Sadie's invitation.  I want you to know her," she 
continued.  "She's really a very nice girl.  I should like her 
immensely if I didn't have to accept so many favors from her." 
</p><p>"Ah, you've just expressed my feeling about Magraw.  I really 
should like your opinion of him," he added. 
</p><p>"Well, you shall have it&mdash;to-morrow morning." 
</p><p>"Here?" he rejoined with sudden interest. 
</p><p>"Why not?  You know I mean to dance with him this evening." 
 
</p><p>The morning after the dance it was Miss Grantham's turn to 
arrive late at the tryst; and when she did so, it was with the air 
of having a duty to discharge rather than a pleasure to enjoy. 
</p><p>"Mr. Tilney," she said, advancing resolutely to the bench on 
which he sat awaiting her, "my only object in coming this morning 
is&mdash;" 
</p><p>He rose with extended hand.  "To let me thank you, I hope, for 
the generous way in which you fulfilled your share of the compact?  
It was awfully good of you to be so nice to Magraw." 
</p><p>She colored vividly, but held his gaze.  "As it happens, I <hi rend="italic"> 
liked</hi> Mr. Magraw.  But if I had known the means you had used to 
obtain his invitation&mdash;" 
</p><p>Tilney colored in turn, but they continued to face each other 
boldly. 
</p><p>"Did Aline betray me?  How like a woman!" he exclaimed. 
</p><p>"I can quite understand," Miss Grantham witheringly continued, 
"the importance you attached to having Mr. Magraw invited to your 
cousin's dance.  <hi rend="italic"> You had to make some return for the scarf pin.</hi>  
But to use my name as a pretext&mdash;to tell Aline Leicester that I was 
trying to marry Mr. Magraw!" 
</p><p>"Oh, I didn't say <hi rend="italic">trying</hi>&mdash;I said you meant to," Tilney 
corrected. 
</p><p>"As if that made it any better!  To let that man think&mdash;" 
</p><p>"He'll never hear of it; and you don't seem to realize that 
it's not easy to extract an invitation from Aline." <pb n="146"/>  
</p><p>"I don't know that it was absolutely necessary that Mr. Magraw 
should receive one!" 
</p><p>Tilney, at this, raised his head with a challenging air.  "You 
appeared to think it absolutely necessary that Miss Bixby should." 
</p><p>"Well&mdash;I don't see&mdash;" 
</p><p>"You don't see how I got <hi rend="italic"> hers?</hi>  I dare say you'll think 
the same method is even more objectionable when the situation is 
reversed&mdash;" 
</p><p>She stared at him with growing disapproval.  "You don't mean 
to say that you let Aline think you wanted to marry Sadie Bixby?" 
</p><p>"I told you there was nothing I wouldn't stoop to.  I suppose 
you think that horribly low." 
</p><p>Her stare resolved itself into a faint sound of laughter.  
"Good heavens, how enchanted Mrs. Bixby will be!" 
</p><p>"The deuce she will&mdash;but of course the joke can easily be 
explained." 
</p><p>"To whom?  To Mrs. Bixby?  I'm glad you think so.  I should 
have said it would be difficult." 
</p><p>"Oh, Mrs. Bixby will never hear of it.  I told Aline in the 
strictest confidence&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Every one at the dance was congratulating me on my conquest 
of Mr. Magraw.  I don't see why Aline should keep one secret and 
not the other." 
</p><p>Tilney's brow darkened ominously.  "Well, at any rate, I'll 
soon undeceive Magraw!" 
</p><p>"A thousand thanks.  And I suppose you leave it to me to 
undeceive Sadie?  She talked of you all the way home.  Of course, 
you're almost the only decent man she's met." 
</p><p>"Ah, then the remedy is simple enough.  You've only to 
introduce a few others." 
</p><p>"Yes, I've thought of that."  Miss Grantham examined him with 
a cold smile.  "But are you quite sure you want me to?" 
</p><p>Tilney met her question with another.  "What on earth do you 
mean?" 
</p><p>"I'm not stupid in such cases, and I could see that Sadie was 
interested.  Did you find her so perfectly impossible?" 
</p><p>"Impossible?  I thought her very pretty." 
</p><p>"That's going to the other extreme&mdash;but she certainly looked 
her best last night.  Still, before deciding, I should want you to 
see her by daylight&mdash;and without the paint&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Oh, she had on very little paint.  One could see her own 
color through it." 
</p><p>"Yes&mdash;she has an unfortunate way of getting red&mdash;" 
</p><p>"At that age I should call it blushing." 
</p><p>Miss Grantham's face grew suddenly stern.  "Of course," she 
said, "I should never forgive myself if you were only trifling with 
Sadie&mdash;" 
</p><p>Tilney paused.  "But if I were in earnest&mdash;?" he suggested. 
</p><p>She gazed at him intently for a moment.  "After all, I might 
be saving her from something worse!" 
 
 
</p><p>                          III. 
 
</p><p>For two mornings after that Tilney, to his secret regret, had 
the bench on the cliffs to himself.  On the third morning he was 
detained indoors somewhat later than usual on pressing business of 
his employer's; and when he emerged from the house he was 
surprised, and considerably dismayed, to find his seat tenanted by 
the incongruous figure of Mr. Hutchins Magraw. 
</p><p>Given his patron's unmatutinal habits, and rooted indifference 
to the beauties of nature, it was impossible to conceive what whim 
had drawn him to so unlikely a spot at so improbable an hour; and 
Tilney's first impulse was to approach the seat, and allay his 
curiosity by direct inquiry.  Hardly, however, had he begun to 
advance when the flutter of a white skirt through the Cliffwood 
shrubberies caused him to retreat abruptly into the covert of lilac 
bushes edging the lawn.  It was by a mere accident, of course, that 
an unknown female, wearing a white gown, happened to be walking 
along the path from that particular direction.  The path was open 
to the public, and there <pb n="147"/>  was no reason to assume any 
coincidence between&mdash; 
</p><p>Tilney drew a sharp breath.  Mr. Magraw had risen and was 
advancing in the direction of the approaching petticoat; and as it 
was impossible for him to recognize its wearer from where he sat, 
it was obvious that he expected some one, and that the invisible 
female was no casual stroller drawn forth by the beauty of the 
morning.  The next moment this conjecture was unpleasantly 
confirmed; for Miss Grantham emerged from the shrubbery, and placed 
her hand in Mr. Magraw's without perceptible surprise.  He, then, 
had also been expected; and she had actually had the effrontery to 
select, as the scene of their tryst, the seat which, by every right 
of friendship, should have been kept sacred to her conversations 
with Fred Tilney! 
</p><p>"The idea of telling him about my bench!"  Resentment of her 
perfidy was for the moment uppermost in Tilney's breast, or was, at 
any rate, the only sentiment to which he chose to give explicit 
expression.  But other considerations surged indignantly beneath 
it&mdash;wonder at woman's unaccountableness, disgust at her facility, 
disappointment, above all, that this one little episode, saved from 
the wreckage of many shattered illusions, should have had so 
premature and unpoetic an ending. 
</p><p>"Magraw&mdash;if only it hadn't been Magraw!" 
</p><p>He had meant to turn away and reenter the house; but a feeling 
of mingled curiosity and wretchedness kept him rooted in his hiding 
place, while he followed with his eyes the broad swaggering back of 
Mr. Hutchins Magraw, as it attended Miss Grantham's slender 
silhouette across the lawn. 
</p><p>"I hadn't realized how disgustingly fat the man has grown.  
One would think a fellow with that outline would know better than 
to rig himself out in a check a foot square, and impale his double 
chin on the points of that preposterous collar!  It's odd how 
little the most fastidious women notice such details.  If they did, 
fewer men would make themselves ridiculous.  Why are they standing 
there, looking up at the house?  Perhaps, after all, it <hi rend="italic">was</hi> an 
accident, their meeting.  No&mdash;they're making straight for the 
bench&mdash;by George, I believe they were looking at the house to make 
sure <hi rend="italic">I</hi> wasn't coming!  Don't be alarmed, my dear Miss Grantham, 
I've no desire to interfere with your amusements.  I see now, 
though, why Magraw was in such a hurry to have me balance his bank 
book this morning.  Just a dodge to keep me indoors, of course.  
It's beastly bad taste, anyhow, to make a poor devil like me go 
over a bank book with such an indecently big balance.  That's the 
kind of thing that makes a man turn socialist.  Why the devil 
should Magraw have all those millions while I&mdash;well, to be sure, 
poor devil, he needs them all to make up for his other 
deficiencies.  I'd like to see how long Belle Grantham would share 
that bench with him if it weren't for his bank account!  It must be 
hard work to talk to Magraw at nine o'clock in the morning.  I 
wonder what the deuce she's saying to him?" 
</p><p>The two objects of Tilney's contemplation had by this time 
settled themselves on the seat which their observer still chose to 
call his own, and something in their attitudes seemed to announce 
that theirs was no transient alighting, but the deliberate 
installation which precedes an earnest talk. 
</p><p>"Well, she could talk to anybody, at any hour of the day or 
night!  That's her trade, poor girl, as much as it is mine.  Only 
I can't see why she should give Magraw <hi rend="italic">my</hi> particular hour.  Now 
that I've given him such a good start they've plenty of other 
chances of meeting.  But perhaps she's afraid of competition, and 
wants to clinch the business by this morning interview.  Poor girl!  
How she must hate it at heart!  I'll do her the justice to say that 
if she had enough to keep body and soul together she'd never look 
at a Magraw.  But if this hand-to-mouth life is hard on a man it's 
ten times worse for a woman&mdash;and her day is over sooner, too.  Poor 
girl!  No wonder she <pb n="148"/>  shrinks at the idea of growing old in 
such a trade.  To see people cooling off, and the newcomers 
crowding her out&mdash;how can I blame her for being afraid to face such 
a future?  Why, I ought to do what I can to help her&mdash;but to help 
her to Magraw!  Bah&mdash;there's something rotten in our social system; 
but it isn't her fault, and only a primitive ass of a man would be 
fool enough to blame her, instead of pitying her as a fellow 
victim." 
</p><p>At this point Miss Grantham started up with an apprehensive 
gesture with which Tilney was painfully familiar.  "She's had to 
look at her watch to realize how time was flying!  She doesn't seem 
to find it goes so slowly with Magraw.  Perhaps my pity's wasted, 
after all.  That's the way she always lingers on after she has said 
she couldn't possibly stay another minute.  Poor Magraw!  She's 
playing him for all she's worth, and I don't suppose he even knows 
he's on the hook.  Oh, I don't blame her&mdash;not in the least!&mdash;only 
I think she might have chosen another place for their meetings.  
Hardened wretch as I am, I was beginning to have a sentiment for 
that bench&mdash;it would never have occurred to me to sit there with 
Miss Bixby, for instance.  It's queer how a woman's taste 
deteriorates when she associates with common men&mdash;but I mean to let 
Miss Grantham know that, though she's welcome to Magraw, she can't 
have my bench into the bargain!" 
</p><p>By this time the couple under observation had completed their 
lingering adieux, the gentleman returning across the lawn to his 
house, while the lady retraced her way toward Cliffwood.  Tilney 
remained in concealment while Mr. Magraw strode by within a few 
feet, the fatuous smile of self-complacency upon his lips; then the 
young man, emerging behind his patron's back, struck across the 
lawn and overtook Miss Grantham as she turned into the adjoining 
grounds. 
</p><p>She paused as she became aware of Tilney's approach, and cast 
a rapid glance in the direction from which he had come; but he had 
taken care not to show himself till Magraw had vanished in the 
shrubberies, and he was quick to note the look of reassurance in 
Miss Grantham's eyes.  She held out her hand, blushing slightly, 
but self-possessed. 
</p><p><hi rend="italic"> "J'ai failli attendre!"</hi> she quoted with an indulgent 
smile; and the smile had well-nigh stung her companion to immediate 
retaliation.  But he meditated a subtler revenge, and dissembling 
his resentment, asked innocently: "Have you been here long?" 
</p><p>"It has certainly seemed so," she replied in the same tone. 
</p><p>"Well, at any rate, my involuntary delay has enabled you to 
enjoy what you originally came out to seek;" and, in reply to her 
puzzled glance, he added pointedly: "The pleasures of solitude." 
</p><p>Unmoved by the thrust, she turned a smiling look on him.  "But 
what if you have made them lose their flavor?" 
</p><p>"Then it was almost worth my while to have stayed away!" 
</p><p>She held out her hand.  "The experiment was so successful that 
you need not try it again," she said sweetly.  "But time flies, and 
I must hasten back into captivity." 
</p><p>He detained her hand to ask sentimentally: "I hope you are not 
losing your taste for freedom?" and she replied, as she hastened 
away: "Come and see&mdash;come and see to-morrow!" 
</p><p>He stood in the path where she had left him, and slowly drew 
from his pocket Mr. Magraw's latest gift&mdash;a jeweled cigarette case.  
He took out the cigarettes, transferred them to his pocket, and 
then, with a free swing of the arm, flung their receptacle into the 
sea. 
</p><p>"Do <hi rend="italic">you</hi> come and see to-morrow!" he muttered, addressing 
himself to Miss Grantham's retreating figure; then he lit a 
cigarette, and walked rapidly back to Sea Lodge. 
</p><p>"I shouldn't have thought it of her!" he said as he entered 
the house. 
 
</p><p>                    TO BE CONCLUDED. 
 
 
 
<pb n="61"/>  
 
</p><p>                     The INTRODUCERS 
 
</p><p>                    By EDITH WHARTON 
 
</p><p>                       &mdash; 
 
</p><p>             A STORY IN TWO PARTS.&mdash;PART II. 
 
 
</p><p>                           IV. 
 
TWO mornings later Tilney, with a beating heart, descended the 
terrace of Sea Lodge, and once more directed himself toward the 
bench on the cliff. 
</p><p>He was not only on time, but a few minutes before the hour; 
yet it was something of a surprise to him to find the bench still 
untenanted.  He seated himself, lit a cigarette with deliberation, 
and drew from his pocket a note stamped <hi rend="italic">Cliffwood</hi> and bearing 
the date of the previous evening. 
</p>
<p>
 "Dear Mr. Tilney," 
 </p>
<p>it ran, "much as I dislike to intrude upon 
the solitude which I know you value so highly, I must ask you to 
spare me a few moments to-morrow morning; and I send this line in 
advance in order that my coming may not interfere with <hi rend="italic"> any other 
arrangements</hi>. 
</p>
 
<p>          "Yours sincerely, 
</p>
 
<p>                    "BELLE GRANTHAM." 
</p>
 

<p>Tilney re-read this note with an air of considerable 
complacency; then he laid it carefully back in his notecase, and 
rose to meet Miss Grantham as she made her appearance around the 
curve of the path. 
</p><p>The morning was chilly, and veiled in a slight haze, too 
translucent to be called a fog, but perceptible enough to cast a 
faint grayness over sea and sky.  Seen in this tempered light, Miss 
Grantham's face seemed to lose its usual vivacity and be subdued to 
the influence of the atmosphere; and her manner of greeting Tilney 
had the same tinge of soberness. 
</p><p>"I must excuse myself," she began, "for again intruding on 
your privacy&mdash;" 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"My</hi> privacy?" Tilney gallantly interposed.  "Was it not 
long since understood between us that the privacy of this spot 
belongs as much to you as to me?" 
</p><p>"Long since&mdash;yes," she replied; "but so much has happened in 
the interval."  She paused, and added in a significant tone: "Since 
I came here yesterday morning, and found you sitting on this bench 
with Sadie Bixby." 
</p><p>Tilney feigned a successful show of embarrassment.  "You came 
here yesterday morning&mdash;?" 
</p><p>"By appointment, as you evidently do <hi rend="italic">not</hi> remember," she 
continued coldly.  "It is a mistake one does not make twice, and my 
only object in asking to see you this morning&mdash;" 
</p><p>"One moment," Tilney interposed.  "Before you go on, I must 
say in my own defense that I assumed our compact about the use of 
this seat had been abrogated when I came out the day before 
yesterday, and found <hi rend="italic">you</hi> sharing it with Magraw." 
</p><p>There was no mistaking the effect of this thrust.  Her color 
rose painfully, and she forced a laugh as she replied: "The day 
before yesterday?  Ah, yes&mdash;that was the morning you were so late.  
Mr. Magraw saw me from the house, and took pity on my deserted 
state." 
</p><p>Tilney colored also at this fresh evidence of her duplicity. 
</p><p>"I beg your pardon&mdash;but does not your memory deceive you?  It 
seemed <pb n="62"/>  to me that Magraw was waiting on the bench, and that 
it was <hi rend="italic">you</hi> who took pity&mdash;if I am not mistaken." 
</p><p>She drew herself up and flashed an outraged glance at him.  
"You were watching us, then?" she exclaimed. 
</p><p>"Oh&mdash;<hi rend="italic"> watching!</hi>  I was merely repairing to our seat at my 
usual hour." 
</p><p>"At your usual hour?  But Mr. Magraw told me you were not 
coming&mdash;that you would be busy all the morning with some writing&mdash;"  
She broke off, seeing herself more deeply involved with each word. 
</p><p>"Some writing he had given me to do?  Precisely," Tilney 
answered with scorn.  "Only, he had underrated either my impatience 
to see you, or my head for figures&mdash;or both." 
</p><p>She received this in an embarrassed silence, and softened by 
her embarrassment he added: "It is not for me to discuss your 
arrangements; but I confess I wondered a little that you chose our 
bench as a meeting-place." 
</p><p>She hesitated a moment, and then said in a deprecating tone: 
"It is the only place where I can see anyone alone!" 
</p><p>"And you wished to see Magraw alone?" 
</p><p>Their eyes met defiantly, but hers fell first as she answered: 
"Yes&mdash;I did wish to." 
</p><p>Tilney bowed ceremoniously.  "In that case, of course, nothing 
remains to be said." 
</p><p>They had both remained standing during this short colloquy, 
but she now seated herself and signed to him to do the same. 
</p><p>"Yes&mdash;something remains for me to say; and it was for the 
purpose of saying it that I asked you to meet me this morning." 
</p><p>Tilney, without replying, placed himself at the opposite end 
of the bench. 
</p><p>"What I wish to ask," she continued in a decisive tone, "is 
your object in meeting Miss Bixby here yesterday." 
</p><p>The temerity of the question was so surprising to her 
companion that for a moment he gazed at her without speaking; then 
he replied with a faint smile: "If there is any right of priority 
in such inquiries, perhaps I am entitled to ask first what was your 
object in meeting Magraw here the day before that." 
</p><p>She repressed her impatience, and returned gently: "The cases 
are surely not quite alike; but I thought I had already given you 
my answer." 
</p><p>"That you wished to see him alone?  Well, I had the same 
object in asking Miss Bixby to meet me." 
</p><p>"But you must see that in the case of a young girl&mdash;especially 
a girl as inexperienced as Sadie&mdash;" 
</p><p>Tilney raised his hand with a deprecating gesture.  "Are you 
not falling into the conventional mistake of assuming that a man 
cannot seek to be alone with a young girl except for the purpose of 
making love to her?" 
</p><p>"Well, what other purpose&mdash;?" 
</p><p>He looked at her calmly.  "Then it was to promote that purpose 
that you asked Magraw to meet you here the day before I met Miss 
Bixby?" 
</p><p>It was Miss Grantham's turn to color, and she fulfilled the 
obligation handsomely.  "I see no object in such cross-questioning&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Ah, pardon me, but it was you who began it." 
</p><p>"It was my duty to question you about Sadie.  You can't 
imagine I do it for my pleasure&mdash;but her parents are too 
inexperienced to protect her." 
</p><p>"To protect her?  Then you consider me hopelessly 
detrimental&mdash;?" 
</p><p>Miss Grantham drew a quick breath.  "Why not have told me at 
once that you wished to marry her?  Every one is saying so, of 
course; but I could not help remembering that your intentions have 
not always been so&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Specific?" he suggested ironically. 
</p><p>"Well, you are still unmarried," she observed. 
</p><p>"Yes," he said musingly.  "It takes a pretty varied experience 
of life to find out that there are worse states than marriage." 
</p><p>Miss Grantham rose with a smile.  "Since you <hi rend="italic">have</hi> found it 
out," she said generously, "I can congratulate you with perfect 
sincerity.  Sadie is a dear little creature&mdash;" <pb n="63"/>  "But too good 
for me?  Is that what you meant to add?" 
</p><p>"No, for when you find out how good she is you'll want to be 
worthy of her." 
</p><p>He received this in silence, but when she held out her hand 
for good-by he said: "I wonder if it's not my duty to protect 
Magraw?  He hasn't even an inexperienced parent." 
</p><p>She met his smile steadily, but he felt the sudden resistance 
of her hand.  "Mr. Magraw," she returned, withdrawing it, "would be 
quite safe if Sadie were." 
</p><p>"If Sadie&mdash;?" 
</p><p>She broke into a laugh.  "If you're planning to take the bread 
out of my mouth, I must do something in the way of self-preservation."  And as he remained silent, feeling a rather tragic 
import under her pleasantry, she added wearily: "I can't begin this 
kind of thing over again&mdash;I simply can't!" 
</p><p>Tilney's discouraged gesture showed his comprehension of her 
words.  "To whom do you say it?" he exclaimed. 
</p><p>"Well, then, let us drop phrases, and admit frankly that we're 
trying to marry each other's wards&mdash;or whatever you choose to call 
them!" 
</p><p>He did not answer, and she continued, with a kind of nervous 
animation: "And that we'll do all we can&mdash;that we <hi rend="italic">honorably</hi> 
can&mdash;to help each other's plans, and see each other through." 
</p><p>The young man still remained silent, his eyes absently fixed 
on the line of sea from which the veil of mist was gradually 
receding; and before he had found a reply a footman, hastening 
across the lawn from the house, broke in upon his meditations. 
</p><p>"Beg pardon, sir, but Mr. Magraw wishes you to come in 
immediately, sir, to answer the telephone for him." 
</p><p>Tilney turned abruptly toward his companion.  "By heaven, yes, 
we'll see each other through!" he exclaimed. 
 
</p><p>Though Tilney and Miss Grantham had parted without any 
reference to future meetings at the same spot, each was now drawn 
to the bench on the cliffs by a new motive&mdash;the not unpardonable 
desire to see if the other had again extended its hospitality to a 
third party. 
</p><p>Their mutual reconnoitering did not, for several mornings, 
carry them farther than the most distant point from which the bench 
was visible; when, perceiving it to be untenanted, they 
respectively retreated, without having discovered each other's 
manoeuvre. 
</p><p>The fifth day, however, was so foggy that distant espionage 
was impossible; and Tilney's suspicions having been aroused by the 
unusual amount of correspondence with which his patron had burdened 
him overnight, he determined to ascertain by direct inspection if 
the sanctity of the bench had again been violated.  It would have 
been hard to say why, in his own thoughts, he still applied such 
terms to the possibility of Miss Grantham's resorting to the spot 
in company with her suitor.  Tilney fully acquiesced in the 
inevitableness of the course they had agreed upon; but if his 
reason accepted the consequences, his sensibilities made the 
process unpleasant to contemplate.  He would have been prepared to 
append his signature to a matrimonial contract drawn up between 
Miss Grantham and his employer; but it irritated him that an 
arrangement so purely utilitarian should be disguised under the 
charming futilities of courtship. 
</p><p>"The real grossness is not in viewing marriage as a business 
partnership, but in pretending that one doesn't," he summed up, as 
he crossed the damp lawn with the waves of gray fog coiling around 
him like a phantom sea. 
</p><p>Through their pale surges he could just discern, as he 
approached the bench, an indeterminate outline hovering near it; 
and the outline proclaiming itself, on nearer inspection, as of his 
own sex, Tilney was about to turn aside when another figure 
appeared from the direction of Cliffwood. 
</p><p>"It's odd," he mused, trying to philosophize upon his own 
discomfiture&mdash;"it's odd how the fog distorts a silhouette.  I could 
have sworn I should <pb n="64"/>  have known hers anywhere, and yet this 
deceptive vapor&mdash;or my nerves, or the two together&mdash;make her look 
so much shorter&mdash;and I'll swear I never saw her swing her arm as 
she walked.  I suppose it comes from associating with a bounder 
like&mdash;" 
</p><p>He drew back with a suppressed exclamation as the small 
feminine outline showed more clearly through a partial break in the 
fog. 
</p><p>"Why, it looks&mdash;no, it can't be!  Hanged if I know, she's so 
bundled up.  Well, it's not <hi rend="italic">she</hi>, at any rate; and if Magraw, at 
this stage of the proceedings, has the indecency to be meeting 
other women here, it's almost my duty to the poor girl to let her 
know before it's too late to break with him." 
</p><p>He was surprised at the immediate sense of lightness which 
this conclusion produced in him.  He was sorry for Miss Grantham, 
of course, when she'd so nearly landed her man; but, hang it, there 
were as good fish in the sea&mdash;and meanwhile she must, at all costs, 
be saved from the humiliation of committing herself farther.  His 
first impulse had been the somewhat cruel one of putting the 
unvarnished facts before her; but farther reflection made him 
shrink from this course, and cast about for some more humane 
expedient. 
</p><p>"If she could only be made to think that she can do better 
than Magraw&mdash;and she ought to, with half a chance, poor child!  I 
can't be wholly sorry that she should not be sacrificed to this 
particular monster&mdash;not that Magraw's not a good fellow in himself; 
I daresay the Minotaur was liked in his own set&mdash;but he should have 
stayed there, that's all." 
</p><p>While engaged in these considerations, Tilney had prudently 
withdrawn into the Cliffwood shrubberies; and he was just deciding 
to effect his escape through the Bixbys' grounds, rather than run 
the chance of being discovered by the tenants of the bench, when, 
on issuing from his retreat, he beheld the indistinct gleam of a 
white dress half way down the Cliffwood lawn.  This time, even 
though the fog had thickened, there was no mistaking the form and 
movement of the shrouded figure; or was it some subtler sense than 
that of sight that so positively assured him of Miss Grantham's 
nearness?  At any rate, he advanced to meet her without a moment's 
hesitation, determined to protect her, by whatever expedient, from 
the embarrassment of interrupting the colloquy on the bench.  He 
had but a moment in which to consider how this should be effected; 
but it was not the first time he had trusted to his gift of 
improvisation in delicate situations, and he was now sustained by 
the unwonted sense of his complete disinterestedness.  The progress 
of his own affairs had in fact made it impossible for him to 
interfere from personal motives; and he thus had the support of 
knowing that his intervention was quite unaffected by selfish 
considerations. 
</p><p>"I'm almost glad," he reflected, "that I <hi rend="italic">am</hi> committed, if 
one of the first consequences is to enable me to act as her friend, 
without any afterthought, or any possibility of her suspecting me 
of not playing fair.  One of my reasons for wanting to settle my 
own future has always been the desire to help her; and little Sadie 
is far too good a girl not to understand&mdash;" 
</p><p>At this point he found himself face to face with Miss 
Grantham, who, suddenly discerning him through the fog, drew back 
with a slight start of surprise. 
</p><p>"I had a feeling that I might meet you this morning," he said 
in a tone of undisguised pleasure; and even as he spoke, his half-formed plan for her rescue began to dissolve in the glow of 
happiness which her nearness always produced.  He was annoyed to 
find that his self-control was so completely at the mercy of her 
presence; but he could no more resist the sudden reaction of his 
pulses from reason to feeling than he could dispel the softly 
enveloping fog which seemed to act as the accomplice of his wishes. 
</p><p>"If I can only make her think she can do better than Magraw," 
he kept mechanically repeating to himself; but the only expedient 
that occurred to him <pb n="65"/>  was one which both prudence and honor 
rejected. 
</p><p>Miss Grantham's first words threw his ideas into still deeper 
confusion. 
</p><p>"Mr. Tilney," she said, without heeding his greeting, "are 
you, or are you not, engaged to Sadie Bixby?" 
</p><p>The abruptness of the inquiry, and the sternness of her tone, 
had a not wholly unpleasing effect on the young man; but their only 
perceptible result was to reduce him to an embarrassed silence. 
</p><p>Miss Grantham gave a faint laugh.  "I suppose I may consider 
myself answered?  And in that case, I have only to apologize for 
asking so indiscreet a question&mdash;" 
</p><p>Tilney cleared his throat nervously.  "I am not aware that I 
have either answered your question or shown that I regarded it as 
indiscreet&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Your silence did both," she returned with some impatience.  
He made no reply, and after a moment's pause she added, with a 
sudden assumption of playfulness: "Well, if this is really to be 
our last meeting, as I suppose it is&mdash;shall we not celebrate it by 
sitting together for a few moments on our dear old bench?" 
</p><p>As she spoke she began to move in the direction of the seat, 
apparently assuming that her companion would offer no opposition to 
her proposal.  But Tilney, with a vague exclamation, laid his hand 
on her arm.  "Don't you think it's rather too damp to sit out of 
doors?" 
</p><p>He reddened under the laugh with which she met this 
incongruous objection. 
</p><p>"My poor friend&mdash;would she really mind so much?  I was foolish 
enough to think you might give me this last morning&mdash;" 
</p><p>"The whole day is at your service," he interposed nervously, 
"but&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Ah, yes; there will always be a <hi rend="italic">but</hi> between us now.  No 
wonder men get on so much better than women; they are so much more 
prudent!  Now, even if I were engaged to Mr. Magraw&mdash;"  She broke 
off, and he fancied he could see her flush through the fog. 
</p><p>He turned on her abruptly.  <hi rend="italic">"Are</hi> you?  There's the point!" 
he exclaimed. 
</p><p>She drew back, slightly disconcerted, but recovering herself 
at once, added in the same playful tone: "I was about to say that, 
even if I <hi rend="italic">were</hi>, I should not feel there was any disloyalty to 
my future in giving this last hour to <hi rend="italic">our</hi> past." 
</p><p>Her light emphasis on the pronoun threw him into a glow of 
pleasure, through which discretion and foresight loomed as remote 
as objects in the fog; but when she added, with a half-sad laugh: 
"I should not hesitate to go back to our bench for the last time&mdash;" 
he broke out, with a fresh leap of apprehension: "Ah, but you 
couldn't, if it meant to you what it does to me!" 
</p><p>He had spoken the words at haphazard, snatching at them as the 
readiest means of diverting her purpose; but once uttered they 
seemed to fill the whole air, and to create a silence which neither 
speaker had, for a moment, the courage to fill. 
</p><p>Womanlike, Miss Grantham was the first to recover her self-possession.  "I am sure," she said sweetly, "that we shall both 
look back often on our quiet morning talks, and I can't think that 
the persons with whom our futures may be associated will be 
defrauded by our treasuring such memories." 
</p><p>She spoke with a sadness so poignant to Tilney that for a 
moment he stood without replying, and during the pause she again 
advanced a few steps nearer to the bench. 
</p><p>The young man broke into a scornful laugh.  <hi rend="italic">" Defrauded?</hi>  
Good heavens&mdash;one can't defraud people of treasures they are 
utterly incapable of valuing!" 
</p><p>She caught this up with a vehemence that surprised him.  "Oh, 
do you feel that too?  It's just what I mean," she exclaimed. 
</p><p>"Feel it&mdash;?"  He stopped before her, blocking her way.  "Do 
you suppose I've felt anything else, night or day, since the 
accursed day when we agreed&mdash;?" 
</p><p>He interrupted himself with a last effort at self-control, and 
she replied in <pb n="66"/>  a low tone of exquisite pleading: "Well, 
then, if you <hi rend="italic">do</hi> feel it, why not go back for a moment to our 
bench?" 
</p><p>Tilney groaned.  "Can't we talk as well here?  Let us walk a 
little way&mdash;we shall be alone anywhere in this fog."  ("Anywhere 
but on that confounded bench," he mentally added.) 
</p><p>Miss Grantham uttered an ironical exclamation.  "Ah, you've 
promised her, I see.  Was it one of the conditions?  In that case, 
of course&mdash;" 
</p><p>"There were no conditions&mdash;and if there had been&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Oh, be careful!  I want to talk of our past, and not of our 
future." 
</p><p>Tilney groaned again.  "If only it <hi rend="italic">could</hi> be our future&mdash;  
Belle, what a beastly bad turn we've done each other, after all!" 
</p><p>"Don't let us talk of the present, either, please."  She laid 
a restraining touch on his arm.  "Why should we give each other 
this pain when it's too late?" 
</p><p>"Too late?"  He paused, remembering that, for him at least, it 
<hi rend="italic">was</hi> too late; but an irresistible impulse prompted him to add: 
"If it hadn't been, tell me at least&mdash;<hi rend="italic"> would you have dared to</hi>, 
Belle?" 
</p><p>They stood looking at each other, mysteriously isolated in the 
magic circle of the fog. 
</p><p>"Dared?  I am daring more now&mdash;more than I have courage for!" 
she murmured, half to herself. 
</p><p>The admission had well-nigh broken down the last barriers of 
Tilney's self-restraint; but at the moment of surrender he suddenly 
recalled his own state of bondage.  He had but to lead Miss 
Grantham to the bench, and she would find herself free; but when 
she turned to reward him as liberators expect to be rewarded, with 
what a sorry countenance must he refuse her gift! 
</p><p>He dropped the hand he had caught in his, and said in a low 
voice: "You were right just now, and I was wrong.  We must not even 
talk of our past, lest we should be tempted to think of our present 
or our future.  I happen to know that I am not doing anyone a 
serious wrong in speaking to you as I have; but my own case is 
different." 
</p><p>"Your own case is different?" Miss Grantham interposed, with 
a sudden change of voice and expression.  "If you think you can 
make love to me without doing Mr. Magraw a serious wrong, I should 
like to know why I may not listen to you without&mdash;" 
</p><p>Tilney received her attack with a disarming humility.  "I said 
the cases were different, because, in a moment of incredible folly, 
I have tried to attract the interest of a trustful, affectionate 
girl&mdash;" 
</p><p>Miss Grantham interrupted him with a laugh.  "Do you mean 
that," she asked ironically, "for a description of Sadie Bixby?" 
</p><p>Her tone aroused an incongruous flash of resentment in Tilney.  
"I see no difficulty," he returned, "in identifying the young lady 
from my words." 
</p><p>"If you really believe them to apply to her, I cannot see how 
you can excuse yourself for being here with me at this moment!"  
She laughed again, and then, to Tilney's surprise, drew nearer, and 
once more laid her hand on his arm. 
</p><p>"My poor friend, it is I who am the real offender, and not 
you.  Believe me, I would not have let you speak to me as you have 
to-day, if I had not known&mdash;if I had not almost felt it my duty to 
be kind to you&mdash;to do what I could to atone&mdash;" 
</p><p>"To be kind to me?  To atone?  What on earth are you talking 
about?" exclaimed Tilney, startled by this unexpected echo of his 
inmost thoughts. 
</p><p>"Alas, it was a foolish impulse, and one which only our old 
friendship could justify.  I forgot for a moment that I was not 
free, in my desire to prepare you&mdash;to console you in advance&mdash;for 
a blow&mdash;" 
</p><p>"A blow?  You're not <hi rend="italic"> married?"</hi> burst from Tilney. 
</p><p>She paused, and gazed at him wonderingly but not unkindly. 
</p><p>"I was speaking of yourself&mdash;yourself and Sadie.  I feel 
myself so deeply to blame&mdash;" 
</p><p>Tilney interrupted her with an air of <pb n="67"/>  inexpressible 
relief.  "We're both to blame for abetting each other in such 
suicidal folly.  As if either of us was made to give up life and 
liberty for a bank-balance!  But I don't reproach you, Belle&mdash;it 
was more my fault than yours; and I deserve that I should be the 
one to pay the penalty!" 
</p><p>"The penalty?  The penalty of marrying Sadie?" she 
breathlessly interposed. 
</p><p>"Of marrying any one but you!" he returned recklessly; and at 
the retort, a veil of sadness fell suddenly upon her eager face. 
</p><p>"It's too late to think of that now; but if you really feel as 
you say&mdash;" 
</p><p>Tilney again cut her short.  "It's too late for me, I know; 
but if <hi rend="italic">you</hi> really feel as you say, thank Heaven, Belle, it's 
not too late for you!" 
</p><p>She drew back a step, and both paused, as though dazed by the 
shock of their flying words.  But as Tilney again approached her, 
she raised her hand and said gravely: "I don't know what you mean, 
but I can explain what <hi rend="italic">I</hi> mean if you'll only&mdash;" 
</p><p>"One moment, please.  I can explain, too, if you'll only&mdash;" 
</p><p>He caught her hand, and began to lead her hurriedly across the 
lawn to the bench. 
</p><p>"Only what?" she panted, trying to keep pace with his flying 
strides; and he called back across his shoulder: "Only come to the 
bench&mdash;and be quick!" 
</p><p>"To the bench?  Why, haven't I been trying all this time to 
take you there?" she cried after him, between tears and laughter. 
</p><p>"Yes; but I didn't know; at least <hi rend="italic">you</hi> didn't know&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Didn't know what?" 
</p><p>"Whom you'd find there!" 
</p><p>She pulled back at this, detaining him forcibly.  "Good 
heavens," she gasped, "do you mean to say that <hi rend="italic"> you've</hi> known all 
this time?" 
</p><p>"Do you think I should have dared to say what I have if I 
hadn't&mdash;?" 
</p><p>"Hadn't known about Sadie&mdash;?" 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">" Sadie?</hi>  I suppose you mean Magraw?" 
</p><p>"Mr. Magraw?"  She stopped short, and snatched her hand away 
with an indignant gesture. 
</p><p>"Mr. Tilney, who do you think is sitting on that bench?" 
</p><p>He faced around on her with equal indignation.  "I don't <hi rend="italic"> 
think:</hi> I know.  Magraw is sitting there with a woman." 
</p><p>"You're utterly mistaken!  I happen to know that it's Sadie 
Bixby who is sitting there with a man." 
</p><p>There was a long pause between them, charged with a gradual 
rush of inner enlightenment; then Tilney suddenly burst into a 
huge, world-defying laugh. 
</p><p>"Well, then, don't you see&mdash;?" 
</p><p>"I don't see anything more than if the fog were inside me!" 
she wailed. 
</p><p>"Don't you see that Magraw and Miss Bixby must be sitting 
there together, and that, in that case, nothing remains for you and 
me but to find a new seat for ourselves?" 
 
</p><trailer>                        THE END.</trailer> 
 
 
</div1>
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
