<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaLine"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;

]>

 
<TEI.2 id="WhaLine"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Line of Least Resistance</title>
<title type="sort">line of least resistance</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">36</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WhaLine</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476502</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Line of Least Resistance</title>
<title type="sort">line of least resistance</title>
<author>Edith Wharton</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>J. P.Lippincott Company</publisher> 
<pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace> 
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>Lippincott's 66 (Oct. 1900): 559-70.</p>
</seriesStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Verification made against printed text.</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-04">April 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Kelly Moulton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>TEI tagging</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="1995-08">August 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Bryson Clevenger, Jr.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Finished TEI tagging; spellchecked against printed text; header</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 

<div1 type="story" id="d3"><head>THE LINE OF LEAST RESISTANCE<lb/> 
                     <lb/> 
<hi rend="italic"> By Edith Wharton</hi> 
<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic"> Author of "The Greater Inclination"</hi></head> <pb n="559"/>  
 
 
<div2 type="part" n="1" id="d4">       <head>I.</head> 
 
<p>MILLICENT was late&mdash;as usual.  Mr. Mindon, returning unexpectedly 
from an interrupted yacht-race, reached home with the legitimate 
hope of finding her at luncheon; but she was still out.  "Was she 
lunching out then?" he asked the butler, who replied, with the air 
of making an uncalled-for concession to his master's curiosity, 
that Mrs. Mindon had given no orders about luncheon.</p><p> 
     Mr. Mindon, on this negative information (it was the kind from 
which his knowledge of his wife's movements was mainly drawn), sat 
down to the grilled cutlet and glass of Vichy that represented his 
share in the fabulous daily total of the chef's book.  Mr. Mindon's 
annual food-consumption probably amounted to about half of one per 
cent. on his cook's perquisites, and of the other luxuries of his 
complicated establishment he enjoyed considerably less than this 
fraction.  Of course, it was nobody's fault but his own.  As 
Millicent pointed out, she couldn't feed her friends on mutton-chops and Vichy because of his digestive difficulty, nor could she 
return their hospitality by asking them to play croquet with the 
children because that happened to be Mr. Mindon's chosen pastime.  
If that was the kind of life he wanted to lead he should have 
married a dyspeptic governess, not a young confiding girl, who 
little dreamed what marriage meant when she passed from her 
father's roof into the clutches of a tyrant with imperfect gastric 
secretions.</p><p> 
     It was his fault, of course, but then Millicent had faults 
too, as she had been known to concede when she perceived that the 
contemplation of her merits was beginning to pall; and it did seem 
unjust to Mr. Mindon that their life should be one long adaptation 
to Millicent's faults at the expense of his own.  Millicent was 
unpunctual&mdash;but that gave a sense of her importance to the people 
she kept waiting; she had nervous attacks&mdash;but they served to 
excuse her from dull dinners and family visits; she was bad-tempered&mdash;but that merely made the servants insolent to Mr. Mindon; 
she was extravagant&mdash;but that simply necessitated Mr. Mindon's 
curtailing his summer holiday and giving a  
<pb n="560"/>  closer attention to business.  If ever a woman had the qualities of her faults, that 
woman was Millicent.  Like the legendary goose, they laid golden 
eggs for her, and she nurtured them tenderly in return.  If 
Millicent had been a perfect wife and mother, she and Mr. Mindon 
would probably have spent their summer in the depressing 
promiscuity of hotel piazzas.  Mr. Mindon was shrewd enough to see 
that he reaped the advantages of his wife's imperfect domesticity, 
and that if her faults were the making of her, she was the making 
of him.  It was therefore unreasonable to be angry with Millicent, 
even if she were late for luncheon, and Mr. Mindon, who prided 
himself on being a reasonable man, usually found some other outlet 
for his wrath.</p><p> 
     On this occasion it was the unpunctuality of the little girls.  
They came in with their governess some minutes after he was seated: 
two small Millicents, with all her arts in miniature.  They 
arranged their frocks carefully before seating themselves and 
turned up their little Greek noses at the food.  Already they 
showed signs of finding fault with as much ease and discrimination 
as Millicent; and Mr. Mindon knew that this was an accomplishment 
not to be undervalued.  He himself, for example, though Millicent 
charged him with being a discontented man, had never acquired her 
proficiency in depreciation; indeed, he sometimes betrayed a 
mortifying indifference to trifles that afforded opportunity for 
the display of his wife's fastidiousness.  Mr. Mindon, though no 
biologist, was vaguely impressed by the way in which that 
accomplished woman had managed to transmit an acquired 
characteristic to her children: it struck him with wonder that 
traits of which he had marked the incipience in Millicent should 
have become intuitions in her offspring.  To rebuke such costly 
replicas of their mother seemed dangerously like scolding 
Millicent&mdash;and Mr. Mindon's hovering resentment prudently settled 
on the governess.</p><p> 
     He pointed out to her that the children were late for 
luncheon.</p><p> 
     The governess was sorry, but Gladys was always unpunctual.  
Perhaps her papa would speak to her.</p><p> 
     Mr. Mindon changed the subject.  "What's that at my feet?  
There's a dog in the room!"</p><p> 
     He looked round furiously at the butler, who gazed impartially 
over his head.  Mr. Mindon knew that it was proper for him to 
ignore his servants, but was not sure to what extent they ought to 
reciprocate his treatment.</p><p> 
     The governess explained that it was Gwendolen's puppy.</p><p> 
     "Gwendolen's puppy?  Who gave Gwendolen a puppy?"</p><p> 
     "Fwank Antwim," said Gwendolen through a mouthful of mushroom 
souffle.</p><p> 
     "Mr. Antrim," the governess suggested, in a tone that 
confessed the futility of the correction.</p> 
<pb n="561"/> <p> 
     <hi rend="italic">" We</hi> don't call him Mr. Antrim; we call him Frank; he likes 
us to," said Gladys icily.</p><p> 
     "You'll do no such thing!" her father snapped.</p><p> 
     A soft body came in contact with his toe.  He kicked out 
viciously, and the room was full of yelping.</p><p> 
     "Take the animal out instantly!" he stormed: dogs were animals 
to Mr. Mindon.  The butler continued to gaze over his head, and the 
two footmen took their cue from the butler.</p><p> 
     "I won't&mdash;I won't&mdash;I won't let my puppy go!" Gwendolen 
violently lamented.</p><p> 
     But she should have another, her father assured her&mdash;a much 
handsomer and more expensive one; his darling should have a prize 
dog; he would telegraph to New York on the instant.</p><p> 
     "I don't want a pwize dog; I want Fwank's puppy!"</p><p> 
     Mr. Mindon laid down his fork and walked out of the room, 
while the governess, cutting up Gwendolen's nectarine, said, as 
though pointing out an error in syntax, "You've vexed your papa 
again."</p><p> 
     "I don't mind vexing papa&mdash;nothing happens," said Gwendolen, 
hugging her puppy; while Gladys, disdaining the subject of dispute, 
contemptuously nibbled caramels.  Gladys was two years older than 
Gwendolen and had outlived the first freshness of her enthusiasm 
for Frank Antrim, who, with the notorious indiscrimination of the 
grown-up, always gave the nicest presents to Gwendolen.</p><p> 
     Mr. Mindon, crossing his marble hall between goddesses whose 
dishabille was still slightly disconcerting to his traditions, 
stepped out on the terrace above the cliffs.  The lawn looked as 
expensive as a velvet carpet woven in one piece; the flower-borders 
contained only exotics; and the stretch of blue-satin Atlantic had 
the air of being furrowed only by the keels of pleasure-boats.  The 
scene, to Mr. Mindon's imagination, never lost the keen edge of its 
costliness; he had yet to learn Millicent's trick of regarding a 
Newport villa as a mere pied &agrave; terre; but he could not help 
reflecting that, after all, it was to him she owed her fine sense 
of relativity.  There are certain things one must possess in order 
not to be awed by them, and it was he who had enabled Millicent to 
take a Newport villa for granted.  And still she was not satisfied!  
She had reached the point where taking the exceptional as a matter 
of course becomes in itself a matter of course; and Millicent could 
not live without novelty.  That was the worst of it: she discarded 
her successes as rapidly as her gowns; Mr. Mindon felt a certain 
breathlessness in retracing her successive manifestations.  And yet 
he had always made allowances: literally and figuratively, he had 
gone on making larger and larger allowances, till his whole income, 
as well as his whole point of view, was practically at Millicent's 
disposal.  But, after all, there was a principle of give and take&mdash; 
if only Millicent could  
<pb n="562"/>  have been brought to see it!  One 
of Millicent's chief sources of strength lay in her magnificent 
obtuseness: there were certain obligations that simply didn't exist 
for her, because she couldn't be brought to see them, and the 
principle of give and take (a favorite principle of Mr. Mindon's) 
was one of them.</p><p> 
     There was Frank Antrim, for instance.  Mr. Mindon, who had a 
high sense of propriety, had schooled himself, not without 
difficulty, into thinking Antrim a charming fellow.  No one was 
more alive than Mr. Mindon to the expediency of calling the Furies 
the Eumenides.  He knew that as long as he chose to think Frank 
Antrim a charming fellow, everything was as it should be and his 
home a temple of the virtues.  But why on earth did Millicent let 
the fellow give presents to the children?  Mr. Mindon was dimly 
conscious that Millicent had been guilty of the kind of failure she 
would least have liked him to detect&mdash;a failure in taste,&mdash;and a 
certain exultation tempered his resentment.  To anyone who had 
suffered as Mr. Mindon had from Millicent's keenness in noting such 
lapses in others, it was not unpleasant to find that she could be 
"bad form."  A sense of unwonted astuteness fortified Mr. Mindon's 
wrath.  He felt that he had every reason to be angry with 
Millicent, and decided to go and scold the governess; then he 
remembered that it was bad for him to lose his temper after eating, 
and, drawing a small phial from his pocket, he took a pepsin tablet 
instead.</p><p> 
     Having vented his wrath in action, he felt calmer, but 
scarcely more happy.  A marble nymph smiled at him from the 
terrace; but he knew how much nymphs cost, and was not sure that 
they were worth the price.  Beyond the shrubberies he caught a 
glimpse of domed glass.  His green-houses were the finest in 
Newport; but since he neither ate fruit nor wore orchids, they 
yielded at best an indirect satisfaction.  At length he decided to 
go and play with the little girls; but on entering the nursery he 
found them dressing for a party, with the rapt gaze and fevered 
cheeks with which Millicent would presently perform the same rite.  
They took no notice of him, and he crept downstairs again.</p><p> 
     His study table was heaped with bills, and as it was bad for 
his digestion to look over them after luncheon, he wandered on into 
the other rooms.  He did not stay long in the drawing-room: it 
evoked too vividly the evening hours when he delved for platitudes 
under the inattentive gaze of listeners who obviously resented his 
not being somebody else.  Much of Mr. Mindon's intercourse with 
ladies was clouded by the sense of this resentment, and he 
sometimes avenged himself by wondering if they supposed he would 
talk to them if he could help it.  The sight of the dining-room 
door increased his depression by recalling the long dinners where, 
with the pantry-draught on his neck, he languished between the 
dullest women of the evening.  He turned away; but the ball-room 
beyond roused even more disturbing associations: an orchestra 
playing all night (Mr. Mindon crept to bed at eleven), carriages 
shouted for under his windows, and a morrow like the day after an 
earthquake.</p><p> 
     In the library he felt less irritated but not more cheerful.  
Mr. Mindon had never quite known what the library was for: it was 
like one of those mysterious ruins over which archaeology endlessly 
disputes.  It could not have been intended for reading, since no 
one in the house ever read, except an under-housemaid charged with 
having set fire to her bed in her surreptitious zeal for fiction; 
and smoking was forbidden there, because the hangings held the odor 
of tobacco.  Mr. Mindon felt a natural pride in being rich enough 
to permit himself a perfectly useless room; but not liking to take 
the bloom from its inutility by sitting in it, he passed on to 
Millicent's boudoir.</p><p> 
     Here at least was a room of manifold purposes, the centre of 
Millicent's complex social system.  Mr. Mindon entered with the awe 
of the modest investor treading the inner precincts of finance.  He 
was proud of Millicent's social activities and liked to read over 
her daily list of engagements and the record of the invitations she 
received in a season.  The number was perpetually swelling, like a 
rising stock.  Mr. Mindon had a vague sense that she would soon be 
declaring an extra dividend.  After all, one must be lenient to a 
woman as hard-working as Millicent.  All about him were the 
evidences of her toil: her writing-table disappeared under an 
avalanche of notes and cards; the waste-paper basket overflowed 
with torn correspondence; and, glancing down, Mr. Mindon saw a 
crumpled letter at his feet.  Being a man of neat habits, he was 
often tried by Millicent's genial disorder; and his customary 
rebuke was the act of restoring the strayed object to its place.</p><p> 
     He stooped to gather the bit of paper from the floor.  As he 
picked it up his eye caught a word; he smoothed the page and read 
on. . . .</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="part" n="2" id="d5"> 
                               <head>II.</head> 
<p> 
     HE seemed to be cowering on the edge of a boiling flood, 
watching his small thinking faculty spin round out of reach on the 
tumult of his sensations.  Then a fresh wave of emotion swept the 
tiny object&mdash;the quivering imperceptible ego&mdash;back to shore, and it 
began to reach out drowned tentacles in a faint effort after 
thought.</p><p> 
     He sat up and glanced about him.  The room looked back at him, 
coldly, unfamiliarly, as he had seen Millicent look when he asked 
her to be reasonable.  And who are you? the walls seemed to say.  
Who am I? Mr. Mindon heard himself retorting.  I'll tell you, by 
God!  I'm the man that paid for you&mdash;paid for every scrap of you: 
silk hangings, china rubbish, glasses, chandeliers,&mdash;every 
Frenchified rag of you.  
<pb n="564"/>  Why, if it weren't for me and my 
money you'd be nothing but a brick-and-plaster shell, naked as the 
day you were built&mdash;no better than a garret or a coal-hole.  Why, 
you wouldn't <hi rend="italic"> be</hi> at all if I chose to tear you down.  I could 
tear the whole house down, if I chose.</p><p> 
     He paused, suddenly aware that his eyes were on a photograph 
of Millicent, and that it was his wife he was apostrophizing.  Her 
lips seemed to shape a "hush:" when he said things she didn't like 
she always told him not to talk so loud.  Had he been talking loud?  
Well, who was to prevent him?  Wasn't the house his and everything 
in it?  Who was Millicent, to bid him hush?</p><p> 
     Mr. Mindon felt a sudden increase of stature.  He strutted 
across the room.  Why, of course, the room belonged to him, the 
house belonged to him, and he belonged to himself!  That was the 
best of it!  For years he had been the man that Millicent thought 
him, the mere projection of her disdain; and now he was himself.</p><p> 
     It was odd how the expression of her photograph changed, 
melting, as her face did, from contempt to cajolery, in one of 
those transitions that hung him breathless on the skirts of her 
mood.  She was looking at him gently now, sadly almost, with the 
little grieved smile that seemed always to anticipate and pardon 
his obtuseness.  Ah, Millicent!  The clock struck and Mr. Mindon 
stood still.  Perhaps she was smiling so now&mdash;or the other way.  He 
could have told the other fool where each of her smiles led.  There 
was a fierce enjoyment in his sense of lucidity.  He saw it all 
now.  Millicent had kept him for years in bewildered subjection to 
exigencies as inscrutable as the decrees of Providence; but now his 
comprehension of her seemed a mere incident in his omniscience.</p><p> 
     His sudden translation to the absolute gave him a curious 
sense of spectatorship: he seemed to be looking on at his own 
thoughts.  His brain was like a brightly lit factory, full of 
flying wheels and shuttles.  All the machinery worked with the 
greatest rapidity and precision.  He was planning, reasoning, 
arguing, with unimagined facility: words flew out like sparks from 
each revolving thought.  But suddenly he felt himself caught in the 
wheels of his terrific logic, and swept round, red and shrieking, 
till he was flung off into space. 
</p><p> 
     The acuter thrill of one sobbing nerve detached itself against 
his consciousness.  What was it that hurt so?  Someone was 
speaking: a voice probed to the central pain,&mdash;</p><p> 
     "Any orders for the stable, sir?"</p><p> 
     And Mr. Mindon found himself the mere mouth-piece of a roving 
impulse that replied,&mdash;</p><p> 
     "No; but you may telephone for a cab for me&mdash;at once."</p> 
<pb n="565"/>  
</div2> 
<div2 type="part" n="3" id="d6"> 
                              <head>III.</head> 
    <p>HE drove to one of the hotels.    He was breathing more easily 
now, restored to the safe level of conventional sensation.  His 
late ascent to the rarefied heights of the unexpected had left him 
weak and exhausted; but he gained reassurance from the way in which 
his thoughts were slipping back of themselves into the old grooves.  
He was feeling, he was sure, just as a gentleman ought to feel; all 
the consecrated phrases&mdash;"outraged honor," "a father's heart," "the 
sanctity of home"&mdash;were flocking glibly at his call.  He had the 
self-confidence that comes of knowing one has on the right clothes.  
He had certainly done the proper thing in leaving the house at 
once; but, too weak and tired to consider the next step, he yielded 
himself to one of those soothing intervals of abeyance when life 
seems to wait submissively at the door.</p><p> 
     As his cab breasted the current of the afternoon drive he 
caught the greeting of the lady with whom he and Millicent were to 
have dined.  He was troubled by the vision of that disrupted 
dinner.  He had not yet reached the point of detachment at which 
offending Mrs. Targe might become immaterial, and again he felt 
himself jerked out of his grooves.  What ought he to do?  
Millicent, now, could have told him&mdash;if only he might have 
consulted Millicent!  He pulled himself together and tried to think 
of his wrongs.</p><p> 
     At the hotel, the astonished clerk led him upstairs, unlocking 
the door of a room that smelt of cheap soap.  The window had been 
so long shut that it opened with a jerk, sending a shower of dead 
flies to the carpet.  Out along the sea-front, at that hour, the 
south-wind was hurrying the waters, but the hotel stood in one of 
the sheltered streets, where in midsummer there is little life in 
the air.  Mr. Mindon sat down in the provisional attitude of a 
visitor who is kept waiting.  Over the fireplace hung a print of 
the Landing of Columbus; a fly-blown portrait of General Grant 
faced it from the opposite wall.  The smell of soap was 
insufferable, and hot noises came up irritatingly from the street.  
He looked at his watch: it was just four o'clock.</p><p> 
     He wondered if Millicent had come in yet, and if she had read 
his letter.  The occupation of picturing how she would feel when 
she read it proved less exhilarating than he had expected, and he 
got up and wandered about the room.  He opened a drawer in the 
dressing-table, and seeing in it some burnt matches and a fuzz of 
hair, shut it with disgust; but just as he was ringing to rebuke 
the house-maid he remembered that he was not in his own house.  He 
sat down again, wondering if the afternoon post were in, and what 
letters it had brought.  It was annoying not to get his letters.  
What would be done about them?  Would they be sent after him?  Sent 
where?  It suddenly occurred to him that he didn't in the least 
know where he was going.  He must be  
<pb n="566"/>  going somewhere, of 
course; he hadn't left home to settle down in that stifling room.  
He supposed he should go to town, but with the heat at ninety the 
prospect was not alluring.  He might decide on Lenox or Saratoga; 
but a doubt as to the propriety of such a course set him once more 
adrift on a chartless sea of perplexities.  His head ached horribly 
and he threw himself on the bed. 
</p><p> 
     When he sat up, worn out with his thoughts, the room was 
growing dark.  Eight o'clock!  Millicent must be dressing&mdash;but no; 
to-night at least, he grimly reflected, she was condemned to the 
hateful necessity of dining alone; unless, indeed, her audacity 
sent her to Mrs. Targe's in the always-acceptable role of the 
pretty woman whose husband has been "called away."  Perhaps Antrim 
would be asked to fill his place!</p><p> 
     The thought flung him on his feet, but its impetus carried him 
no farther.  He was borne down by the physical apathy of a 
traveller who has a week's journey in his bones.  He sat down and 
thought of the little girls, who were just going to bed.  They 
would have welcomed him at that hour: he was aware that they 
cherished him chiefly as a pretext, a sanctuary from bed-time and 
lessons.  He had never in his life been more than an alternative to 
anyone.</p><p> 
     A vague sense of physical apprehension resolved itself into 
hunger stripped of appetite, and he decided that he ought to urge 
himself to eat.  He opened his door on a rising aroma of stale 
coffee and fry.</p><p> 
     In the dining-room, where a waiter offered him undefinable 
food in thick-lipped saucers, Mr. Mindon decided to go to New York.  
Retreating from the heavy assault of a wedge of pie, he pushed back 
his chair and went upstairs.  He felt hot and grimy in the 
yachting-clothes he had worn since morning, and the Fall River boat 
would at least be cool.  Then he remembered the playful throngs 
that held the deck, the midnight hilarity of the waltz-tunes, the 
horror of the morning coffee.  His stomach was still tremulous from 
its late adventure into the unknown, and he shrank from further 
risks.  He had never before realized how much he loved his home.</p><p> 
     He grew soft at the vision of his vacant chair.  What were 
they doing and saying without him?  His little ones were 
fatherless&mdash;and Millicent?  Hitherto he had evaded the thought of 
Millicent, but now he took a doleful pleasure in picturing her in 
ruins at his feet.  Involuntarily he found himself stooping to her 
despair; but he straightened himself and said aloud, "I'll take the 
night-train, then."  The sound of his voice surprised him, and he 
started up.  Was that a footstep outside?&mdash;a message, a note?  Had 
they found out where he was, and was his wretched wife mad enough 
to sue for mercy?  His ironical smile gave the measure of her 
madness; but the step passed on, and he sat down rather blankly.  
The impressiveness of his attitude was being gradually sapped by 
the sense that no one knew where he was.  He had reached the point 
where he could not be sure of remaining inflexible unless someone 
asked him to relent.</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="part" n="4" id="d7"> 
                               <head>IV.</head> 
<p>   AT the sound of a knock he clutched his hat and bag.</p><p> 
     "Mindon, I say!" a genial voice adjured him; and before he 
could take counsel with his newly acquired dignity, which did not 
immediately respond to a first summons, the door opened on the 
reassuring presence of Laurence Meysy.</p><p> 
     Mr. Mindon felt the relief of a sufferer at the approach of 
the eminent specialist.  Laurence Meysy was the past tense of a 
dangerous man: though time-worn, still a favorite; a circulating-library romance, dog-eared by many a lovely hand, and still perused 
with pleasure, though, alas! no longer on the sly.  He was said to 
have wrought much havoc in his youth; and it being now his innocent 
pleasure to repair the damage done by others, he had become the 
consulting physician of injured husbands and imprudent wives.</p><p> 
     Two gentlemen followed him: Mr. Mindon's uncle and senior 
partner, the eminent Ezra Brownrigg, and the Reverend Doctor 
Bonifant, rector of the New York church in which Mr. Mindon owned 
a pew that was almost as expensive as his opera-box.</p><p> 
     Mr. Brownrigg entered silently: to get at anything to say he 
had to sink an artesian well of meditation; but he always left 
people impressed by what he would have said if he had spoken.  He 
greeted his nephew with the air of a distinguished mourner at a 
funeral&mdash;the mourner who consciously overshadows the corpse; and 
Doctor Bonifant did justice to the emotional side of the situation 
by fervently exclaiming, "Thank Heaven, we are not too late!"</p><p> 
     Mr. Mindon looked about him with pardonable pride.  The scene 
suggested something between a vestry-meeting and a conference of 
railway-directors; and the knowledge that he himself was its 
central figure, that even his uncle was an accessory, an incident, 
a mere bit of still-life brushed in by the artist Circumstance to 
throw Mr. Mindon into fuller prominence, gave that gentleman his 
first sense of equality with his wife.  Equality?  In another 
moment he towered above her, picturing her in an attitude of 
vaguely imagined penance at Doctor Bonifant's feet.  Mr. Mindon had 
always felt about the clergy much as he did about his library: he 
had never quite known what they were for; but, with the pleased 
surprise of the pious naturalist, he now saw that they had their 
uses, like every other object in the economy of nature.</p><p> 
     "My dear fellow," Meysy persuasively went on, "we've come to 
have a little chat with you."</p><p> 
     Mr. Brownrigg and the Rector seated themselves.  Mr. Mindon 
 
<pb n="568"/>   
mechanically followed their example, and Meysy, asking the 
others if they minded his cigarette, cheerfully accommodated 
himself to the edge of the bed.</p><p> 
     From the life-long habit of taking the chair, Mr. Brownrigg 
coughed and looked at Doctor Bonifant.  The Rector leaned forward, 
stroking his cheek with a hand on which a massive intaglio seemed 
to be rehearsing the part of the episcopal ring; then his 
deprecating glance transferred the burden of action to Laurence 
Meysy.  Meysy seemed to be surveying the case through the 
mitigating medium of cigarette-smoke.  His view was that of the 
professional setting to rights the blunders of two amateurs.  It 
was his theory that the art of carrying on a love affair was very 
nearly extinct; and he had a far greater contempt for Antrim than 
for Mr. Mindon.</p><p> 
     "My dear fellow," he began, "I've seen Mrs. Mindon&mdash;she sent 
for me."</p><p> 
     Mr. Brownrigg, peering between guarded lids, here interposed 
a "Very proper."</p><p> 
     Of course Millicent had done the proper thing!  Mr. Mindon 
could not repress a thrill of pride at her efficiency.</p><p> 
     "Mrs. Mindon," Meysy continued, "showed me your letter."  He 
paused.  "She was perfectly frank&mdash;she throws herself on your 
mercy."</p><p> 
     "That should be remembered in her favor," Doctor Bonifant 
murmured in a voice of absolution.</p><p> 
     "It's a wretched business, Mindon&mdash;the poor woman's crushed&mdash; 
crushed.  Your uncle here has seen her."</p><p> 
     Mr. Brownrigg glanced suspiciously at Meysy, as though not 
certain whether he cared to corroborate an unauthorized assertion; 
then he said, "Mrs. Brownrigg has <hi rend="italic"> not</hi>."</p><p> 
     Doctor Bonifant sighed: Mrs. Brownrigg was one of his most 
cherished parishioners.</p><p> 
     "And the long and short of it is," Meysy summed up, "that 
we're here as your friends&mdash;and as your wife's friends&mdash;to ask you 
what you mean to do."</p><p> 
     There was a pause.  Mr. Mindon was disturbed by finding the 
initiative shifted to his shoulders.  He had been talking to 
himself so volubly for the last six hours that he seemed to have 
nothing left to say.</p><p> 
     "To do&mdash;to do?" he stammered.  "Why, I mean to go away&mdash;leave 
her&mdash;"</p><p> 
     "Divorce her?"</p><p> 
     "Why,&mdash;y-yes&mdash;yes&mdash;"</p><p> 
     Doctor Bonifant sighed again, and Mr. Brownrigg's lips stirred 
like a door being cautiously unbarred.</p><p> 
     Meysy knocked the ashes off his cigarette.  "You've quite made 
up your mind, eh?"  
<pb n="569"/> </p><p> 
     Mr. Mindon faltered another assent.  Then, annoyed at the 
uncertain sound of his voice, he repeated loudly, "I mean to 
divorce her."</p><p> 
     The repetition fortified his resolve; and his declaration 
seemed to himself against entreaty: their mere presence was a 
pedestal for his wrongs.  The words flocked of themselves, building 
up his conviction like a throng of masons buttressing a weak wall.</p><p> 
     Mr. Brownrigg spoke upon his first pause.  "There's the 
publicity&mdash;it's the kind of thing that's prejudicial to a man's 
business interests.</p><p> 
     An hour earlier the words would have turned Mr. Mindon cold; 
now he brushed them aside.  His business interests, forsooth!  What 
good had his money ever done him?  What chance had he ever had of 
enjoying it?  All his toil hadn't made him a rich man&mdash;it had 
merely made Millicent a rich woman.</p><p> 
     Doctor Bonifant murmured, "The children must be considered."</p><p> 
     "They've never considered me!" Mr. Mindon retorted&mdash;and turned 
afresh upon his uncle.  Mr. Brownrigg listened impassively.  He was 
a very silent man, but his silence was not a receptacle for the 
speech of others&mdash;it was a hard convex surface on which argument 
found no footing.  Mr. Mindon reverted to the Rector.  Doctor 
Bonifant's attitude towards life was full of a benignant 
receptivity; as though, logically, a man who had accepted the 
Thirty-nine Articles was justified in accepting anything else that 
he chose.  His attention had therefore an absorbent quality 
peculiarly encouraging to those who addressed him.  He listened 
affirmatively, as it were.</p><p> 
     Mr. Mindon's spirits rose.  It was the first time that he had 
ever had an audience.  He dragged his hearers over every stage of 
his wrongs, losing sight of the vital injury in the enumeration of 
incidental grievances.  He had the excited sense that at last 
Millicent would know what he had always thought of her.</p><p> 
     Mr. Brownrigg looked at his watch, and Doctor Bonifant bent 
his head as though under the weight of a pulpit peroration.  Meysy, 
from the bed, watched the three men with the air of an expert who 
holds the solution of the problem.</p><p> 
     He slipped to his feet as Mr. Mindon's speech flagged.</p><p> 
     "I suppose you've considered, Mindon, that it rests with you 
to proclaim the fact that you're no longer&mdash;well, the chief object 
of your wife's affection?"</p><p> 
     Mr. Mindon raised his head irritably; interrogation impeded 
the flow of his diatribe.</p><p> 
     "That you&mdash;er&mdash;in short, create the situation by making it 
known?" Meysy glanced at the Rector.  "Am I right, Bonifant?"</p><p> 
     The Rector took meditative counsel of his finger-tips; then 
slowly,  
<pb n="570"/>  as though formulating a dogma, "Under certain 
conditions," he conceded, "what is unknown may be said to be non-existent."</p><p> 
     Mr. Mindon looked from one to the other.</p><p> 
     "Damn it, man&mdash;before it's too late," Meysy followed up, 
"can't you see that <hi rend="italic"> you're</hi> the only person who can make you 
ridiculous?"</p><p> 
     Mr. Brownrigg rose, and Mr. Mindon had the desperate sense 
that the situation was slipping out of his grasp.</p><p> 
     "It rests with you," Doctor Bonifant murmured, "to save your 
children from even the shadow of obloquy."</p><p> 
     "You can't stay here, at any rate," said Mr. Brownrigg 
heavily.</p><p> 
     Mr. Mindon, who had risen, dropped weakly into his chair.  His 
three counsellors were now all on their feet, taking up their hats 
with the air of men who have touched the limit of duty.  In another 
moment they would be gone, and with them Mr. Mindon's audience, his 
support, his confidence in the immutability of his resolve.  He 
felt himself no more than an evocation of their presence; and, in 
dread of losing the identity they had created, he groped for a 
detaining word.  "I sha'n't leave for New York till to-morrow."</p><p> 
     "To-morrow everything will be known," said Mr. Brownrigg, with 
his hand on the door.</p><p> 
     Meysy glanced at his watch with a faint smile.  "It's to-morrow now," he added.</p><p> 
     He fell back, letting the older men pass out; but, turning as 
though to follow, he felt a drowning clutch upon his arm.</p><p> 
     "It's for the children," Mr. Mindon stammered. 
</p> 
</div2> 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
