<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaMuse"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="WhaMuse"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Muse's Tragedy</title>
<title type="sort">muses tragedy</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">37</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">WhaMuse</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476504</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Muse's Tragedy</title>
<title type="sort">muses tragedy</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner's Magazine</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Volume 25</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Verification made against printed text</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of  
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman and Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
<head> 
Wharton, Edith.  "The Muse's Tragedy." 
<lb/>   
<hi rend="italic"> Scribner's Magazine</hi> 25 (Jan. 1899): 77-84. 
</head> 
<pb n="77"/>  

<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d4"> 
<head>   I 
</head> 

<p>DANYERS afterward liked to fancy that he had recognized Mrs. 
Anerton at once; but that, of course, was absurd, since he had seen 
no portrait of her&mdash;she affected a strict anonymity, refusing even 
her photograph to the most privileged&mdash;and from Mrs. Memorall, whom 
he revered and cultivated as her friend, he had extracted but the 
one impressionist phrase:&mdash;"Oh, well, she's like one of those old 
prints where the lines have the value of color." 
</p><p>He was almost certain, at all events, that he had been 
thinking of Mrs. Anerton as he sat over his breakfast in the empty 
hotel restaurant, and that, looking up on the approach of the lady 
who seated herself at the table near the window, he had said to 
himself, <hi rend="italic"> "That might be she."</hi> 
</p><p>Ever since his Harvard days&mdash;he was still young enough to 
think of them as immensely remote&mdash;Danyers had dreamed of Mrs. 
Anerton, the Silvia of Vincent Rendle's immortal sonnet-cycle, the 
Mrs. A. of the "Life and Letters."  Her name was enshrined in some 
of the noblest English verse of the nineteenth century&mdash;and of all 
past or future centuries, as Danyers, from the stand-point of a 
maturer judgment, still believed.  The first reading of certain 
poems&mdash;of the "Antinous," the "Pia Tolomei," the "Sonnets to 
Silvia"&mdash;had been epochs in Danyers's growth, and the verse seemed 
to gain in mellowness, in amplitude, in meaning as one brought to 
its interpretation more experience of life, a finer emotional 
sense.  Where, in his boyhood, he had felt only the perfect, the 
almost austere beauty of form, the subtle interplay of vowel-sounds, the rush and fulness of lyric emotion, he now thrilled to 
the close-packed significance of each line, the allusiveness of 
each word&mdash;his imagination lured hither and thither on fresh trails 
of thought, and perpetually spurred by the sense that, beyond what 
he had already discovered, more marvellous regions lay waiting to 
be explored.  Danyers had written, at college, the prize essay on 
Rendle's poetry (it chanced to be the moment of the great man's 
death); he had fashioned the fugitive verse of his own storm-and-stress period on the forms which Rendle had first given to English 
metre; and when two years later the "Life and Letters" appeared, 
and the Silvia of the sonnets took substance as Mrs. A., he had 
included in his worship of Rendle the woman who had inspired not 
only such divine verse but such playful, tender, incomparable 
prose. 
</p><p>Danyers never forgot the day when Mrs. Memorall happened to 
mention that she knew Mrs. Anerton.  He had known Mrs. Memorall for 
a year or more, and had classified her as a cleverish woman with a 
crazy-quilt mind, who bored one with irrelevant anecdotes about 
celebrities; when one afternoon she remarked, as she put a second 
lump of sugar in his tea: 
</p><p>"Is it right this time?  You're almost as particular as Mary 
Anerton." 
</p><p>"Mary Anerton?" 
</p><p>"Yes, I never <hi rend="italic"> can</hi> remember how she likes her tea.  Either 
its lemon <hi rend="italic"> with</hi> sugar, or lemon <hi rend="italic"> without</hi> sugar, or cream 
without either, and whichever it is must be put into the cup before 
the tea is poured in; and if one hasn't remembered one must begin 
all over again.  I suppose it was Vincent Rendle's way of taking 
his tea and has become a sacred rite." 
</p><p>"Do you <hi rend="italic"> know</hi> Mrs. Anerton?" gasped Danyers, awed by this 
acquaintance with the habits of his divinity. 
</p><p>"And did I once see Shelley plain?  Mercy, yes!  She and I 
were at school together&mdash;she's an American, you know.  We were at 
a <hi rend="italic"> pension</hi> near Tours for nearly a year; then she went back to 
New York, and I didn't see her again until after her marriage.  She 
and Anerton spent a winter in Rome while my husband was attached to 
our Legation there, and she used to be with us a great deal."  Mrs. 
Memorall smiled reminiscently.  "It was <hi rend="italic"> the</hi> winter." 
</p><p>"The winter they first met?" <pb n="78"/>  
</p><p>"Precisely&mdash;but unluckily I left Rome just before the meeting 
took place.  Wasn't it too bad?  I might have been in the 'Life and 
Letters.'  You know he mentions that stupid Madame Vodki, at whose 
house he first met her." 
</p><p>"And did you see much of her after that?" 
</p><p>"Not during Rendle's life.  You know she has lived in Europe 
almost entirely, and though I used to see her occasionally when I 
went abroad, she was always so engrossed, so preoccupied, that one 
felt one wasn't wanted.  The fact is, she cared only about his 
friends&mdash;she separated herself almost entirely from her own people.  
Now, of course, it's different; she's desperately lonely; she's 
taken to writing to me now and then; and last year, when she heard 
that I was going abroad, she asked me to meet her in Venice, and I 
spent a week with her there." 
</p><p>"And Rendle?" 
</p><p>Mrs. Memorall smiled and shook her head.  "Oh, I never was 
allowed a peep at <hi rend="italic"> him;</hi> none of her old friends met him, except 
by accident.  Ill-natured people say that was the reason she kept 
him so long.  If one happened in while he was there, he was hustled 
into Anerton's study, and the husband mounted guard until the 
inopportune visitor had departed.  Anerton, you know, was really 
much more ridiculous about it than his wife.  Mary was too clever 
to lose her head or, at least to show that she'd lost it&mdash;but 
Anerton couldn't conceal his pride in the conquest.  I've seen Mary 
shiver when he spoke of Rendle as <hi rend="italic"> our poet</hi>.  Rendle always had 
to have a certain seat at the dinner-table, away from the draught 
and not too near the fire, and a box of cigars that no one else was 
allowed to touch, and a writing-table of his own in Mary's sitting-room&mdash;and Anerton was always telling one of the great man's 
idiosyncrasies; how he never would cut the ends of his cigars, 
though Anerton himself had given him a gold cutter set with a star-sapphire, and how untidy his writing-table was, and how the house-maid had orders always to bring the waste-paper basket to her 
mistress before emptying it, lest some immortal verse should be 
thrown into the dust-bin." 
</p><p>"The Anertons never separated, did they?" 
</p><p>"Separated?  Bless you, no.  He never would have left Rendle!  
And besides, he was very fond of his wife." 
</p><p>"And she?" 
</p><p>"Oh, he was the kind of man who was fated to make himself 
ridiculous, and she always let him have his way." 
</p><p>From Mrs. Memorall, Danyers further learned that Mrs. Anerton, 
whose husband had died some years before her poet, now divided her 
life between Rome, where she had a small apartment, and England, 
where she went occasionally to stay with those of her friends who 
had been Rendle's.  She had been engaged, for some time after his 
death, in editing some juvenilia which he had entrusted to her 
care; but that task being accomplished, she had been left without 
definite occupation, and Mrs. Memorall, on the occasion of their 
last meeting, had found her listless and out of spirits. 
</p><p>"She misses him too much&mdash;her life is too empty.  I told her 
so&mdash;I told her she ought to marry." 
</p><p>"Oh!" 
</p><p>"Why not, pray?  She's a young woman still&mdash;what many people 
would call young," Mrs. Memorall interjected with a parenthetic 
glance at the mirror.  "Why not accept the inevitable and begin 
over again?  All the King's horses and all the King's men won't 
bring Rendle to life&mdash;and besides, she didn't marry <hi rend="italic"> him</hi> when 
she had the chance." 
</p><p>Danyers winced slightly at this rude fingering of his idol.  
Was it possible that Mrs. Memorall did not see what an anti-climax 
such a marriage would have been?  Fancy Rendle "making an honest 
woman" of Silvia; for so society would have viewed it!  How such a 
reparation would have vulgarized their past&mdash;it would have been 
like "restoring" a masterpiece; and how exquisite must have been 
the perceptions of the woman who, in defiance of appearances, and 
perhaps of her own secret inclination, chose to go down to 
posterity as Silvia rather than as Mrs. Vincent Rendle! 
</p><p>Mrs. Memorall, from this day forth, acquired an interest in 
Danyers's eyes.  She was like a volume of unindexed and discursive 
memoirs, through which he patiently plodded in the hope of finding 
embedded amid layers of dusty twaddle some pre-<pb n="79"/> cious allusion 
to the subject of his thought.  When, some months later, he brought 
out his first slim volume, in which the remodelled college essay on 
Rendle figured among a dozen somewhat overstudied "appreciations," 
he offered a copy to Mrs. Memorall; who surprised him, the next 
time they met, with the announcement that she had sent the book to 
Mrs. Anerton. 
</p><p>Mrs. Anerton in due course wrote to thank her friend.  Danyers 
was privileged to read the few lines in which, in terms that 
suggested the habit of "acknowledging" similar tributes, she spoke 
of the author's "feeling and insight," and was "so glad of the 
opportunity, etc."  He went away disappointed, without clearly 
knowing what else he had expected. 
</p><p>The following spring, when he went abroad, Mrs. Memorall 
offered him letters to everybody, from the Archbishop of Canterbury 
to Louise Michel.  She did not include Mrs. Anerton, however, and 
Danyers knew, from a previous conversation, that Silvia objected to 
people who "brought letters."  He knew also that she travelled 
during the summer, and was unlikely to return to Rome before the 
term of his holiday should be reached, and the hope of meeting her 
was not included among his anticipations. 
</p><p>The lady whose entrance broke upon his solitary repast in the 
restaurant of the Hotel Villa d'Este had seated herself in such a 
way that her profile was detached against the window; and thus 
viewed, her domed forehead, small arched nose and fastidious lip 
suggested a silhouette of Marie Antoinette.  In the lady's dress 
and movements&mdash;in the very turn of her wrist as she poured out her 
coffee&mdash;Danyers thought he detected the same fastidiousness, the 
same air of tacitly excluding the obvious and unexceptional.  Here 
was a woman who had been much bored and keenly interested.  The 
waiter brought her a <hi rend="italic"> Secolo</hi>, and as she bent above it Danyers 
noticed that the hair rolled back from her forehead was turning 
gray; but her figure was straight and slender, and she had the 
invaluable gift of a girlish back. 
</p><p>The rush of Anglo-Saxon travel had not set toward the lakes, 
and with the exception of an Italian family or two, and a hump-backed youth with an <hi rend="italic"> abbe</hi>, Danyers and the lady had the marble 
halls of the Villa d'Este to themselves. 
</p><p>When he returned from his morning ramble among the hills he 
saw her sitting at one of the little tables at the edge of the 
lake.  She was writing, and a heap of books and newspapers lay on 
the table at her side.  That evening they met again in the garden.  
He had strolled out to smoke a last cigarette before dinner, and 
under the black vaulting of ilexes, near the steps leading down to 
the boat-landing, he found her leaning on the parapet above the 
lake.  At the sound of his approach she turned and looked at him.  
She had thrown a black lace scarf over her head, and in this sombre 
setting her face seemed thin and unhappy.  He remembered afterward 
that her eyes, as they met his, expressed not so much sorrow as 
profound discontent. 
</p><p>To his surprise she stepped toward him with a detaining 
gesture. 
</p><p>"Mr. Lewis Danyers, I believe?" 
</p><p>He bowed. 
</p><p>"I am Mrs. Anerton.  I saw your name on the visitors' list and 
wished to thank you for an essay on Mr. Rendle's poetry&mdash;or rather 
to tell you how much I appreciated it.  The book was sent to me 
last winter by Mrs. Memorall." 
</p><p>She spoke in even melancholy tones, as though the habit of 
perfunctory utterance had robbed her voice of more spontaneous 
accents; but her smile was charming. 
</p><p>They sat down on a stone bench under the ilexes, and she told 
him how much pleasure his essay had given her.  She thought it the 
best in the book&mdash;she was sure that he had put more of himself into 
it than into any other; was she not right in conjecturing that he 
had been very deeply influenced by Mr. Rendle's poetry?  <hi rend="italic"> Pour 
comprendre il faut aimer</hi>, and it seemed to her that, in some ways, 
he had penetrated the poet's inner meaning more completely than any 
other critic.  There were certain problems, of course, that he had 
left untouched; certain aspects of that many-sided mind that he had 
perhaps failed to seize&mdash; 
</p><p>"But then you are young," she concluded, gently, "and one 
could not wish you, as yet, the experience that a fuller 
understanding would imply." <pb n="80"/>  
</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d5"> 
<head>                           II 
</head> 

<p>SHE stayed a month at Villa d'Este, and Danyers was with her 
daily.  She showed an unaffected pleasure in his society; a 
pleasure so obviously founded on their common veneration of Rendle 
that the young man could enjoy it without fear of fatuity.  At 
first he was merely one more grain of frankincense on the altar of 
her insatiable divinity; but gradually a more personal note crept 
into their intercourse.  If she still liked him only because he 
appreciated Rendle, she at least perceptibly distinguished him from 
the herd of Rendle's appreciators. 
</p><p>Her attitude toward the great man's memory struck Danyers as 
perfect.  She neither proclaimed nor disavowed her identity.  She 
was frankly Silvia to those who knew and cared; but there was no 
trace of the Egeria in her pose.  She spoke often of Rendle's 
books, but seldom of himself; there was no posthumous conjugality, 
no use of the possessive tense, in her abounding reminiscences.  Of 
the master's intellectual life, of his habits of thought and work, 
she never wearied of talking.  She knew the history of each poem; 
by what scene or episode each image had been evoked; how many times 
the words in a certain line had been transposed; how long a certain 
adjective had been sought, and what had at last suggested it; she 
could even explain that one impenetrable line, the torment of 
critics, the joy of detractors, the last line of "The Old 
Odysseus." 
</p><p>Danyers felt that in talking of these things she was no mere 
echo of Rendle's thought.  If her identity had appeared to be 
merged in his it was because they thought alike, not because he had 
thought for her.  Posterity is apt to regard the women whom poets 
have sung as chance pegs on which they hung their garlands; but 
Mrs. Anerton's mind was like some fertile garden wherein, 
inevitably, Rendle's imagination had rooted itself and flowered.  
Danyers began to see how many threads of his complex mental tissue 
the poet had owed to the blending of her temperament with his: in 
a certain sense Silvia had herself created the Sonnets to Silvia. 
</p><p>To be the custodian of Rendle's inner self, the door, as it 
were, to the sanctuary, had at first seemed to Danyers so 
comprehensive a privilege that he had the sense, as his friendship 
with Mrs. Anerton advanced, of forcing his way into a life already 
crowded.  What room was there, among such towering memories, for so 
small an actuality as his?  Quite suddenly, after this, he 
discovered that Mrs. Memorall knew better: his fortunate friend was 
bored as well as lonely. 
</p><p>"You have had more than any other woman!" he had exclaimed to 
her one day; and her smile flashed a derisive light on his blunder.  
Fool that he was, not to have seen that she had not had enough!  
That she was young still&mdash;do years count?&mdash;tender, human, a woman; 
that the living have need of the living. 
</p><p>After that, when they climbed the alleys of the hanging park, 
resting in one of the little ruined temples or watching, through a 
ripple of foliage, the remote blue flash of the lake, they did not 
always talk of Rendle or of literature.  She encouraged Danyers to 
speak of himself; to confide his ambitions to her; she asked him 
the questions which are the wise woman's substitute for advice. 
</p><p>"You must write," she said, administering the most exquisite 
flattery that human lips could give. 
</p><p>Of course he meant to write&mdash;why not to do something great in 
his turn?  His best, at least; with the resolve, at the outset, 
that his best should be <hi rend="italic"> the</hi> best.  Nothing less seemed possible 
with that mandate in his ears.  How she had divined him; lifted and 
disentangled his groping ambitions; laid the awakening touch on his 
spirit with her creative <hi rend="italic"> Let there be light!</hi> 
</p><p>It was his last day with her, and he was feeling very hopeless 
and happy. 
</p><p>"You ought to write a book about <hi rend="italic"> him</hi>," she went on, 
gently. 
</p><p>Danyers started; he was beginning to dislike Rendle's way of 
walking in unannounced. 
</p><p>"You ought to do it," she insisted.  "A complete 
interpretation&mdash;a summing-up of his style, his purpose, his theory 
of life and art.  No one else could do it so well." 
</p><p>He sat looking at her perplexedly.  Suddenly&mdash;dared he guess? 
</p><p>"I couldn't do it without you," he faltered. <pb n="81"/>  
</p><p>"I could help you&mdash;I would help you, of course." 
</p><p>They sat silent, both looking at the lake. 
</p><p>It was agreed, when they parted, that he should rejoin her six 
weeks later in Venice.  There they were to talk about the book. 
</p> 
</div2> 
<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d6"> 
<head>                           III</head> 
<p>          LAGO D'ISEO, August 14th. 
</p> 
<p>WHEN I said good-by to you yesterday I promised to come back 
to Venice in a week: I was to give you your answer then.  I was not 
honest in saying that; I didn't mean to go back to Venice or to see 
you again.  I was running away from you&mdash;and I mean to keep on 
running!  If <hi rend="italic"> you</hi> won't, <hi rend="italic"> I</hi> 
 must.  Somebody must save you 
from marrying a disappointed woman of&mdash;well, you say years don't 
count, and why should they, after all, since you are not to marry 
me? 
</p><p>That is what I dare not go back to say.  <hi rend="italic"> You are not to 
marry me.</hi>  We have had our month together in Venice (such a good 
month, was it not?) and now you are to go home and write a book&mdash; 
any book but the one we&mdash;didn't talk of!&mdash;and I am to stay here, 
attitudinizing among my memories like a sort of female Tithonus.  
The dreariness of this enforced immortality! 
</p><p>But you shall know the truth.  I care for you, or at least for 
your love, enough to owe you that. 
</p><p>You thought it was because Vincent Rendle had loved me that 
there was so little hope for you.  I had had what I wanted to the 
full; wasn't that what you said?  It is just when a man begins to 
think he understands a woman that he may be sure he doesn't!  It is 
because Vincent Rendle <hi rend="italic"> didn't love me</hi> that there is no hope for 
you.  I never had what I wanted, and never, never, never will I 
stoop to wanting anything else. 
</p><p>Do you begin to understand?  It was all a sham then, you say?  
No, it was all real as far as it went.  You are young&mdash;you haven't 
learned, as you will later, the thousand imperceptible signs by 
which one gropes one's way through the labyrinth of human nature; 
but didn't it strike you, sometimes, that I never told you any 
foolish little anecdotes about him?  His trick, for instance, of 
twirling a paper-knife round and round between his thumb and 
forefinger while he talked; his mania for saving the backs of 
notes; his greediness for wild strawberries, the little pungent 
Alpine ones; his childish delight in acrobats and jugglers; his way 
of always calling me <hi rend="italic"> you</hi>&mdash;<hi rend="italic"> Dear you</hi>, every letter began&mdash;I 
never told you a word of all that, did I?  Do you suppose I could 
have helped telling you, if he had loved me?  These little things 
would have been mine, then, a part of my life&mdash;of our life&mdash;they 
would have slipped out in spite of me (it's only your unhappy woman 
who is always reticent and dignified).  But there never was any 
"our life;" it was always "our lives" to the end. 
</p><p>If you knew what a relief it is to tell someone at last you 
would bear with me, you would let me hurt you!  I shall never be 
quite so lonely again, now that someone knows. 
</p><p>Let me begin at the beginning.  When I first met Vincent 
Rendle I was not yet thirty.  That was twenty years ago.  From that 
time until his death, five years ago, we were fast friends.  He 
gave me fifteen years, perhaps the best fifteen years, of his life.  
The world, as you know, thinks that his greatest poems were written 
during those years; I am supposed to have "inspired" them, and in 
a sense I did.  From the first, the intellectual sympathy between 
us was almost complete; my mind must have been to him (I fancy) 
like some perfectly tuned instrument on which he was never tired of 
playing.  Someone told me of his once saying of me that I "always 
understood;" it is the only praise I ever heard of his giving me.  
I don't even know if he thought me pretty, though I hardly think my 
appearance could have been disagreeable to him, for he disliked to 
be with ugly people.  At all events he fell into the way of 
spending more and more of his time with me.  He liked our house; 
our ways suited him.  He was nervous, irritable; people bored him 
and yet he dreaded solitude.  He took sanctuary with us.  When we 
travelled he went with us; in the winter he took rooms near us in 
Rome.  In England or on the Continent he was always with us for a 
good part of the year.  In small ways I was able to help him in his 
work; he grew dependent on me.  When we were apart <pb n="82"/>  he wrote 
to me continually&mdash;he liked to have me share in all he was doing or 
thinking; he was impatient for my criticism of every new book that 
interested him; I was a part of his intellectual life.  The pity of 
it was that I wanted to be something more.  I was a young woman and 
I was in love with him&mdash;not because he was Vincent Rendle, but just 
because he was he! 
</p><p>People began to talk, of course&mdash;I was Vincent Rendle's Mrs. 
Anerton; when the Sonnets to Silvia appeared, it was whispered that 
I was Silvia.  Wherever he went, I was invited; people made up to 
me in the hope of getting to know him; when I was in London my 
door-bell never stopped ringing.  Elderly peeresses, aspiring 
hostesses, love-sick girls and struggling authors overwhelmed me 
with their assiduities.  I hugged my success, for I knew what it 
meant&mdash;they thought that Rendle was in love with me!  Do you know, 
at times they almost made me think so too?  Oh, there was no phase 
of folly I didn't go through.  You can't imagine the excuses a 
woman will invent for a man's not telling her that he loves her&mdash; 
pitiable arguments that she would see through at a glance if any 
other woman used them!  But all the while, deep down, I knew he had 
never cared.  I should have known it if he had made love to me 
every day of his life.  I could never guess whether he knew what 
people said about us&mdash;he listened so little to what people said; 
and cared still less, when he heard.  He was always quite honest 
and straightforward with me; he treated me as one man treats 
another; and yet at times I felt that he <hi rend="italic"> must</hi> see that with me 
it was different.  If he did see, he made no sign.  Perhaps he 
never noticed&mdash;I am sure he never meant to be cruel.  He had never 
made love to me; it was no fault of his if I wanted more than he 
could give me.  The Sonnets to Silvia, you say?  But what are they?  
A cosmic philosophy, not a love-poem; addressed to Woman, not to a 
woman! 
</p><p>But then, the letters?  Ah, the letters!  Well, I'll make a 
clean breast of it.  You have noticed the breaks in the letters 
here and there, just as they seem to be on the point of growing a 
little&mdash;warmer?  The critics, you may remember, praised the editor 
for his commendable delicacy and good taste (so rare in these 
days!) in omitting from the correspondence all personal allusions, 
all those <hi rend="italic"> details intimes</hi> which should be kept sacred from the 
public gaze.  They referred, of course, to the asterisks in the 
letters to Mrs. A.  Those letters I myself prepared for 
publication; that is to say, I copied them out for the editor, and 
every now and then I put in a line of asterisks to make it appear 
that something had been left out.  You understand?  The asterisks 
were a sham&mdash;<hi rend="italic"> there was nothing to leave out</hi>. 
</p><p>No one but a woman could understand what I went through during 
those years&mdash;the moments of revolt, when I felt that I must break 
away from it all, fling the truth in his face and never see him 
again; the inevitable reaction, when not to see him seemed the one 
unendurable thing, and I trembled lest a look or word of mine 
should disturb the poise of our friendship; the silly days when I 
hugged the delusion that he <hi rend="italic"> must</hi> love me, since everybody 
thought he did; the long periods of numbness, when I didn't seem to 
care whether he loved me or not.  Between these wretched days came 
others when our intellectual accord was so perfect that I forgot 
everything else in the joy of feeling myself lifted up on the wings 
of his thought.  Sometimes, then, the heavens seemed to be opened. 

</p><p>All this time he was so dear a friend!  He had the genius of 
friendship, and he spent it all on me.  Yes, you were right when 
you said that I have had more than any other woman.  <hi rend="italic"> Il faut de 
l'adresse pour aimer</hi>, Pascal says; and I was so quiet, so 
cheerful, so frankly affectionate with him, that in all those years 
I am almost sure I never bored him.  Could I have hoped as much if 
he had loved me? 
</p><p>You mustn't think of him, though, as having been tied to my 
skirts.  He came and went as he pleased, and so did his fancies.  
There was a girl once (I am telling you everything), a lovely being 
who called his poetry "deep" and gave him "Lucile" on his birthday.  
He followed her to Switzerland one summer, and all the time that he 
was dangling after her (a little too conspicuously, I always 
thought, for a Great Man), he was writing to me about his theory of 
vowel-combinations&mdash;or was it his experi-<pb n="83"/> ments in English 
hexameter?  The letters were dated from the very places where I 
knew they were sitting by waterfalls together while he thought out 
adjectives for her hair.  He talked to me about it quite frankly 
afterward.  She was perfectly beautiful, and it had been a pure 
delight to watch her; but she <hi rend="italic"> would</hi> talk, and her mind, he 
said, was "all elbows."  And yet, the next year, when her marriage 
was announced, he went away alone, quite suddenly . . . and it was 
just afterward that he published "Love's Viaticum."  Men are queer! 
</p><p>After my husband died&mdash;I am putting things crudely, you see&mdash;I 
had a return of hope.  It was because he loved me, I argued, that 
he had never spoken; because he had always hoped some day to make 
me his wife; because he wanted to spare me the reproach&mdash;Rubbish!  
I knew well enough, in my heart of hearts, that my one chance lay 
in the force of habit.  He had grown used to me; he was no longer 
young; he dreaded new people and new ways; <hi rend="italic"> il avait pris son 
pli</hi>.  Would it not be easier to marry me? 
</p><p>I don't believe he ever thought of it.  He wrote me what 
people call "a beautiful letter;" he was kind, considerate, 
decently commiserating; then, after a few weeks, he slipped into 
his old way of coming in every afternoon, and our interminable 
talks began again just where they had left off.  I heard later that 
people thought I had shown "such good taste" in not marrying him. 
</p><p>So we jogged on for five years longer.  Perhaps they were the 
best years, for I had given up hoping.  Then he died. 
</p><p>After his death&mdash;this is curious&mdash;there came to me a kind of 
mirage of love.  All the books and articles written about him, all 
the reviews of the "Life," were full of discreet allusions to 
Silvia.  I became again the Mrs. Anerton of the glorious days.  
Sentimental girls and dear lads like you turned pink when somebody 
whispered, "That was Silvia you were talking to."  Idiots begged 
for my autograph&mdash;publishers urged me to write my reminiscences of 
him&mdash;critics consulted me about the reading of doubtful lines.  And 
I knew that, to all these people, I was the woman whom Vincent 
Rendle had loved. 
</p><p>After awhile that fire went out too and I was left alone with 
my past.  Alone&mdash;quite alone; for he had never really been with me.  
The intellectual union counted for nothing now.  It had been soul 
to soul, but never hand in hand, and there were no little things to 
remember him by. 
</p><p>Then there set in a kind of Arctic winter.  I crawled into 
myself as into a snow-hut.  I hated my solitude and yet dreaded 
anyone who disturbed it.  That phase, of course, passed like the 
others.  I took up life again, and began to read the papers and 
consider the cut of my gowns.  But there was one question that I 
could not be rid of, that haunted me night and day.  Why had he 
never loved me?  Why had I been so much to him, and no more?  Was 
I so ugly, so essentially unlovable, that though a man might 
cherish me as his mind's comrade, he could not care for me as a 
woman?  I can't tell you how that question tortured me.  It became 
an obsession. 
</p><p>My poor friend, do you begin to see?  I had to find out what 
some other man thought of me.  Don't be too hard on me!  Listen 
first&mdash;consider.  When I first met Vincent Rendle I was a young 
woman, who had married early and led the quietest kind of life; I 
had had no "experiences."  From the hour of our first meeting to 
the day of his death I never looked at any other man, and never 
noticed whether any other man looked at me.  When he died, five 
years ago, I knew the extent of my powers no more than a baby.  Was 
it too late to find out?  Should I never know <hi rend="italic"> why?</hi> 
</p><p>Forgive me&mdash;forgive me.  You are so young; it will be an 
episode, a mere "document," to you so soon!  And, besides, it 
wasn't as deliberate, as cold-blooded, as these disjointed lines 
have made it appear.  I didn't plan it, like a woman in a book.  
Life is so much more complex than any rendering of it can be.  I 
liked you from the first&mdash;I was drawn to you (you must have seen 
that)&mdash;I wanted you to like me; it was not a mere psychological 
experiment.  And yet in a sense it was that too&mdash;I must be honest.  
I had to have an answer to that question; it was a ghost that had 
to be laid. 
</p><p>At first I was afraid&mdash;oh, so much afraid&mdash;that you cared for 
me only because I was Silvia, that you loved me because you <pb n="84"/>  
thought Rendle had loved me.  I began to think that there was no 
escaping my destiny. 
</p><p>How happy I was when I discovered that you were growing 
jealous of my past; that you actually hated Rendle!  My heart beat 
like a girl's when you told me that you meant to follow me to 
Venice. 
</p><p>After our parting at Villa d'Este my old doubts reasserted 
themselves.  What did I know of your feeling for me, after all?  
Were you capable of analyzing it yourself?  Was it not likely to be 
two-thirds vanity and curiosity, and one-third literary 
sentimentality?  You might easily fancy that you cared for Mary 
Anerton when you were really in love with Silvia&mdash;the heart is such 
a hypocrite!  Or you might be more calculating than I had supposed.  
Perhaps it was you who had been flattering <hi rend="italic"> my</hi> vanity in the 
hope (the pardonable hope) of turning me, after a decent interval, 
into a pretty little essay with a margin. 
</p><p>When you arrived in Venice and we met again&mdash;do you remember 
the music on the lagoon, that evening from my balcony?&mdash;I was so 
afraid that you would begin to talk about the book&mdash;the book, you 
remember, was your ostensible reason for coming.  You never spoke 
of it, and I soon saw that your one fear was that <hi rend="italic"> I</hi> might do 
so&mdash;might remind you of your object in being with me.  Then I knew 
that you cared for me; yes, at that moment really cared!  We never 
mentioned the book once, did we, during that month in Venice? 
</p><p>I have read my letter over; and now I wish that I had said 
this to you instead of writing it.  I could have felt my way then, 
watching your face and seeing if you understood.  But, no, I could 
not go back to Venice; and I could not tell you (though I tried) 
while we were there together.  I couldn't spoil that month&mdash;my one 
month.  It was so good, for once in my life, to get away from 
literature. 
</p><p>You will be angry with me at first&mdash;but, alas! not for long.  
What I have done would have been cruel if I had been a younger 
woman; as it is, the experiment will hurt no one but myself.  And 
it will hurt me horribly (as much as, in your first anger, you may 
perhaps wish), because it has shown me, for the first time, all 
that I have missed. 
</p> 
 
</div2> 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
