<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaPeli"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="WhaPeli"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Pelican</title>
<title type="sort">pelican</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">47</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">WhaPeli</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476507</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Pelican</title>
<title type="sort">pelican</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner's Magazine</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1898">1898</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Volume 24</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Verification made against printed text</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of  
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1898">1898</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman and Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
<head> 
Wharton, Edith.  "The Pelican."   
<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic"> Scribner's Magazine</hi> 24 (Nov. 1898): 620-29. 
</head> 
<pb n="620"/>  

<p> 
SHE was very pretty when I first knew her, with the sweet straight 
nose and short upper lip of the cameo-brooch divinity, humanized by 
a dimple that flowered in her cheek whenever anything was said 
which possessed the outward attributes of humor without its 
intrinsic quality.  For the dear lady was providentially deficient 
in humor: the least hint of the real thing clouded her lovely eye 
like the hovering shadow of an algebraic problem. 
</p><p>I do not think that nature had meant her to be "intellectual"; 
but what can a poor thing do, whose husband has died of drink when 
her baby is hardly six months old, and who finds that her coral 
necklace and her grandfather's edition of the British Dramatists 
are inadequate to the demands of the creditors? 
</p><p>Her mother, the celebrated Irene Astarte Pratt, had written a 
poem in blank verse on "The Fall of Man"; one of her aunts was dean 
of a girl's college; another had translated Euripides&mdash;with such a 
family, the poor child's fate was sealed in advance.  The only way 
of paying her husband's debts and keeping the baby clothed was to 
be intellectual; and, after some hesitation as to the form that her 
mental activity was to take, it was unanimously decided that she 
was to give lectures. 
</p><p>They began by being drawing-room lectures.  The first time I 
saw her she was standing by the piano, against a flippant 
background of Dresden china and photographs, telling a roomful of 
women preoccupied with their spring bonnets all that she thought 
she knew about Greek art.  The ladies assembled to hear her had 
given me to understand that she was "doing it for the baby," and 
this fact, together with the shortness of her upper lip and the 
bewildering co-operation of her dimple, disposed me to listen 
leniently to her dissertation.  Happily, at that time Greek art was 
still, if I may use the phrase, easily handled; it was as simple as 
walking down a museum-gallery lined with pleasant familiar Venuses 
and Apollos.  All the later complications&mdash;the archaic and 
archaistic conundrums; the influences of Assyria and Asia Minor; 
the conflicting attributions and the wrangles of the erudite&mdash;still 
slumbered in the bosom of the future "scientific critic."  Greek 
art in those days began with Phidias and ended with the Apollo 
Belvedere; and a child could travel from one to the other without 
danger of losing its way. 
</p><p>Mrs. Amyot had two fatal gifts: a capacious but inaccurate 
memory, and an extraordinary fluency of speech.  There was nothing 
that she did not remember&mdash;wrongly; but her halting facts were 
swathed in so many layers of cotton-wool eloquence that their 
infirmities were imperceptible to her friendly critics.  Besides, 
she had been taught Greek by the aunt who had translated Euripides; 
and the mere sound of the <hi rend="italic"> ais</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> ois</hi> which she now and 
then not unskilfully let slip (correcting herself, of course, with 
a start, and indulgently mistranslating the phrase), struck awe to 
the hearts of ladies whose only "accomplishment" was French&mdash;if you 
didn't speak too quickly. 
</p><p>I had then but a momentary glimpse of Mrs. Amyot, but a few 
months later I came upon her again in the New England university 
town where the celebrated Irene Astarte Pratt lived on the summit 
of a local Parnassus, with lesser muses and college professors 
respectfully grouped on the lower ledges of the sacred declivity.  
Mrs. Amyot, who, after her husband's death, had returned to the 
maternal roof (even during her father's lifetime the roof had been 
distinctively maternal), Mrs. Amyot, thanks to her upper lip, her 
dimple, and her Greek, was already ensconced in a snug hollow of 
the Parnassian slope. 
</p><p>After the lecture was over it happened that I walked home with 
Mrs. Amyot.  Judging from the incensed glances of two or three 
learned gentlemen who were hov-<pb n="621"/> ering on the door-step when 
we emerged, I inferred that Mrs. Amyot, at that period, did not 
often walk home alone; but I doubt whether any of my discomfited 
rivals, whatever his claims to favor, was ever treated to so 
ravishing a mixture of shyness and self-abandonment, of sham 
erudition and real teeth and hair, as it was my privilege to enjoy.  
Even at the incipience of her public career Mrs. Amyot had a tender 
eye for strangers, as possible links with successive centres of 
culture to which in due course the torch of Greek art might be 
handed on. 
</p><p>She began by telling me that she had never been so frightened 
in her life.  She knew, of course, how dreadfully learned I was, 
and when, just as she was going to begin, her hostess had whispered 
to her that I was in the room, she had felt ready to sink through 
the floor.  Then (with a flying dimple) she had remembered 
Emerson's line&mdash;wasn't it Emerson's?&mdash;that beauty is its own excuse 
for <hi rend="italic"> seeing</hi>, and that had made her feel a little more confident, 
since she was sure that no one <hi rend="italic"> saw</hi> beauty more vividly than 
she&mdash;as a child she used to sit for hours gazing at an Etruscan 
vase on the bookcase in the library while her sisters played with 
their dolls&mdash;and if <hi rend="italic"> seeing</hi> beauty was the only excuse one 
needed for talking about it, why, she was sure I would make 
allowances and not be <hi rend="italic"> too</hi> critical and sarcastic, especially 
if, as she thought probable, I had heard of her having lost her 
poor husband, and how she had to do it for the baby. 
</p><p>Being over-abundantly assured of my sympathy on these points, 
she went on to say that she had always wanted so much to consult me 
about her lectures.  Of course, one subject wasn't enough (this 
view of the limitations of Greek art as a "subject" gave me a 
startling idea of the rate at which a successful lecturer might 
exhaust the universe); she must find others; she had not ventured 
on any as yet, but she had thought of Tennyson&mdash;didn't I <hi rend="italic"> love</hi> 
Tennyson?  She <hi rend="italic"> worshipped</hi> him so that she was sure she could 
help others to understand him; or what did I think of a "course" on 
Raphael or Michaelangelo&mdash;or on the heroines of Shakespeare?  There 
were some fine steel-engravings of Raphael's Madonnas and of the 
Sistine ceiling in her mother's library, and she had seen Miss 
Cushman in several Shakespearian <hi rend="italic"> roles</hi>, so that on these 
subjects also she felt qualified to speak with authority. 
</p><p>When we reached her mother's door she begged me to come in and 
talk the matter over; she wanted me to see the baby&mdash;she felt as 
though I should understand her better if I saw the baby&mdash;and the 
dimple flashed through a tear. 
</p><p>The fear of encountering the author of "The Fall of Man," 
combined with the opportune recollection of a dinner engagement, 
made me evade this appeal with the promise of returning on the 
morrow.  On the morrow, I left too early to redeem my promise; and 
for several years afterward I saw no more of Mrs. Amyot. 
</p><p>My calling at that time took me at irregular intervals from 
one to another of our larger cities, and as Mrs. Amyot was also 
peripatetic it was inevitable that sooner or later we should cross 
each other's path.  It was therefore without surprise that, one 
snowy afternoon in Boston, I learned from the lady with whom I 
chanced to be lunching that, as soon as the meal was over, I was to 
be taken to hear Mrs. Amyot lecture. 
</p><p>"On Greek art?" I suggested. 
</p><p>"Oh, you've heard her then?  No, this is one of the series 
called 'Homes and Haunts of the Poets.'  Last week we had 
Wordsworth and the Lake Poets, to-day we are to have Goethe and 
Weimar.  She is a wonderful creature&mdash;all the women of her family 
are geniuses.  You know, of course, that her mother was Irene 
Astarte Pratt, who wrote a poem on 'The Fall of Man'; N. P. Willis 
called her the female Milton of America.  One of Mrs. Amyot's aunts 
has translated Eurip&mdash;" 
</p><p>"And is she as pretty as ever?" I irrelevantly interposed. 
</p><p>My hostess stared.  "She is excessively modest and retiring.  
She says it is actual suffering for her to speak in public.  You 
know she only does it for the baby." 
</p><p>Punctually at the hour appointed, we took our seats in a 
lecture-hall full of strenuous females in ulsters.  Mrs. Amyot was 
evidently a favorite with these austere sisters, for every corner 
was crowded, and as we entered a pale usher with an educated 
mispronunciation was setting forth to several dejected applicants 
the impossibility of supplying them with seats. <pb n="622"/>  
</p><p>Our own were happily so near the front that when the curtains 
at the back of the platform parted, and Mrs. Amyot appeared, I was 
at once able to establish a rapid comparison between the lady 
placidly dimpling to the applause of her public and the shrinking 
drawing-room orator of my earlier recollections. 
</p><p>Mrs. Amyot was as pretty as ever, and there was the same 
curious discrepancy between the freshness of her aspect and the 
staleness of her theme, but something was gone of the blushing 
unsteadiness with which she had fired her first random shots at 
Greek art.  It was not that the shots were less uncertain, but that 
she now had an air of assuming that, for her purpose, the bull's-eye was everywhere, so that there was no need to be flustered in 
taking aim.  This assurance had so facilitated the flow of her 
circumlocutious diction that, as I listened, I had a curious sense 
that she was performing a trick analogous to that of the conjuror 
who pulls hundreds of yards of white paper out of his mouth.  From 
a large assortment of stock adjectives she chose, with unerring 
deftness and rapidity, the one which taste and discrimination would 
most surely have rejected, fitting out her subject, as it were, 
with a whole wardrobe of slop-shot epithets irrelevant in cut and 
size.  To the invaluable knack of not disturbing the association of 
ideas in her audience, she added the gift of what may be called a 
confidential manner&mdash;so that her fluent generalizations about 
Goethe and his place in literature (the lecture was, of course, 
manufactured out of Lewes's book) had the flavor of personal 
experience, of views sympathetically exchanged with her audience on 
the best way of knitting children's socks, or of putting up 
preserves for the winter.  It was, I am sure, to this personal 
accent&mdash;the moral equivalent of her dimple&mdash;that Mrs. Amyot owed 
her prodigious, her irrational success.  It was her art of 
transposing second-hand ideas into first-hand emotions that so 
endeared her to her feminine listeners. 
</p><p>To anyone not in search of "documents" Mrs. Amyot's success 
was hardly of a kind to make her more interesting, and my curiosity 
flagged with the growing conviction that the "suffering" entailed 
upon her by public speaking was at most a retrospective pang.  I 
was sure that, as a matter of fact, she had reached the point of 
measuring and enjoying her effects, of deliberately manipulating 
her public; and there must indeed have been a certain exhilaration 
in attaining results so considerable by means involving so little 
conscious effort.  Mrs. Amyot's art was simply an extension of 
coquetry: she flirted with her audience. 
</p><p>In this mood of enlightened skepticism I responded but 
languidly to my hostess's suggestion that I should go with her that 
evening to see Mrs. Amyot.  The aunt who had translated Euripides 
was at home on Saturday evenings, and one met "thoughtful" people 
there, my hostess explained: it was one of the intellectual centres 
of Boston.  My mood remained distinctly resentful of any connection 
between Mrs. Amyot and intellectuality, and I declined to go; but 
the next day I met Mrs. Amyot in the street. 
</p><p>She stopped me reproachfully.  She had heard that I was in 
Boston; why had I not come last night?  She had been told that I 
was at her lecture; and it had frightened her&mdash;yes, really, almost 
as much as years ago in Hillbridge.  She never <hi rend="italic"> could</hi> get over 
that stupid shyness, and the whole business was as distasteful to 
her as ever; but what could she do?  There was the baby&mdash;he was a 
big boy now, and boys were <hi rend="italic"> so</hi> expensive!  But did I really 
think she had improved the least little bit?  And why wouldn't I 
come home with her now, and see the boy, and tell her frankly what 
I had thought of the lecture?  She had plenty of flattery&mdash;people 
were <hi rend="italic"> so</hi> kind, and every one knew that she did it for the baby&mdash; 
but what she felt the need of was criticism, severe, discriminating 
criticism like mine&mdash;oh, she knew that I was dreadfully 
discriminating! 
</p><p>I went home with her and saw the boy.  In the early heat of 
her Tennyson-worship Mrs. Amyot had christened him Lancelot, and he 
looked it.  Perhaps, however, it was his black velvet dress and the 
exasperating length of his yellow curls, together with the fact of 
his having been taught to recite Browning to visitors, that raised 
to fever heat the itching of my palms in his Infant-Samuel-like 
presence.  I have since had reason to think that he would <pb n="623"/>  
have preferred to be called Billy, and to hunt cats with the other 
boys in the block: his curls and his poetry were simply another 
outlet for Mrs. Amyot's irrepressible coquetry. 
</p><p>But if Lancelot was not genuine, his mother's love for him 
was.  It justified everything&mdash;the lectures <hi rend="italic"> were</hi> for the baby, 
after all.  I had not been ten minutes in the room before I was 
pledged to help Mrs. Amyot to carry out her triumphant fraud.  If 
she wanted to lecture on Plato she should&mdash;Plato must take his 
chance like the rest of us!  There was no use, of course, in being 
"discriminating."  I preserved sufficient reason to avoid that 
pitfall, but I suggested "subjects" and made lists of books for her 
with a fatuity that became more obvious as time attenuated the 
remembrance of her smile; I even remember thinking that some men 
might have cut the knot by marrying her, but I handed over Plato as 
a hostage, and escaped by the afternoon train. 
</p><p>The next time I saw her was in New York, when she had become 
so fashionable that it was a part of the whole duty of woman to be 
seen at her lectures.  The lady who suggested that of course I 
ought to go and hear Mrs. Amyot, was not very clear about anything 
except that she was perfectly lovely, and had had a horrid husband, 
and was doing it to support her boy.  The subject of the discourse 
(I think it proved to be on Ruskin) was clearly of minor 
importance, not only to my friend, but to the throng of well-dressed and absent-minded ladies who rustled in late, dropped their 
muffs and pocket-books, and undisguisedly lost themselves in the 
study of each other's apparel.  They received Mrs. Amyot with 
warmth, but she evidently represented a social obligation like 
going to church, rather than any more personal interest; in fact, 
I suspect that every one of the ladies would have remained away, 
had it been ascertainable that none of the others were coming. 
</p><p>Whether Mrs. Amyot was disheartened by the lack of sympathy 
between herself and her hearers, or whether the sport of arousing 
it had become a task, she certainly imparted her platitudes with 
less convincing warmth than of old.  Her voice had the same 
confidential inflections, but it was like a voice reproduced by a 
gramophone: the real woman seemed far away.  She had grown stouter 
without losing her dewy freshness, and her smart gown might have 
been taken to indicate either the potentialities of a settled 
income, or a politic concession to the taste of her hearers.  As I 
listened I reproached myself for ever having suspected her of self-deception in declaring that she took no pleasure in her work.  I 
was sure now that she did it only for Lancelot, and judging from 
the size of her audience and the price of the tickets I concluded 
that Lancelot must be receiving a liberal education. 
</p><p>I was living in New York that winter, and in the rotation of 
dinners I found myself one evening at Mrs. Amyot's side.  The 
dimple came out at my greeting as punctually as a cuckoo in a Swiss 
clock and I detected the same automatic quality in the tone in 
which she made her usual pretty demand for advice.  She was like a 
musical-box charged with popular airs.  They succeeded one another 
with breathless rapidity, but there was a moment after each when 
the cylinders scraped and whizzed. 
</p><p>Mrs. Amyot, as I found when I called upon her, was living in 
a pleasant flat, with a sunny sitting-room full of flowers and a 
tea-table that had the air of expecting visitors.  She owned that 
she had been ridiculously successful.  It was delightful, of 
course, on Lancelot's account.  Lancelot had been sent to the best 
school in the country, and if things went well and people didn't 
tire of his silly mother he was to go to Harvard afterward.  During 
the next two or three years Mrs. Amyot kept her flat in New York, 
and radiated art and literature upon the suburbs.  I saw her now 
and then, always stouter, better dressed, more successful and more 
automatic: she had become a lecturing-machine. 
</p><p>I went abroad for a year or two and when I came back she had 
disappeared.  I asked several people about her, but life had closed 
over her.  She had been last heard of as lecturing&mdash;still 
lecturing&mdash;but no one seemed to know when or where. 
</p><p>It was in Boston that I found her at last, forlornly swaying 
to the oscillations of an overhead strap in a crowded trolley-car.  
Her face had so changed that I lost myself in a startled reckoning 
of the time that <pb n="624"/>  had elapsed since our parting.  She spoke 
to me shyly, as though aware of my hurried calculation, and 
conscious that in five years she ought not to have altered so much 
as to upset my notion of time.  Then she seemed to set it down to 
her dress, for she nervously gathered her cloak over a gown that 
asked only to be concealed, and shrank into a vacant seat behind 
the line of prehensile bipeds blocking the aisle of the car. 
</p><p>It was perhaps because she so obviously avoided me that I felt 
for the first time that I might be of use to her; and when she left 
the car I made no excuse for following her. 
</p><p>She said nothing of needing advice and did not ask me to walk 
home with her, concealing, as we talked, her transparent 
preoccupations under the mask of a sudden interest in all that I 
had been doing since she had last seen me.  Of what concerned her, 
I learned only that Lancelot was well and that for the present she 
was not lecturing&mdash;she was tired and her doctor had ordered her to 
rest.  On the doorstep of a shabby house she paused and held out 
her hand.  She had been so glad to see me and perhaps if I were in 
Boston again&mdash;the tired dimple, as it were, bowed me out and closed 
the door upon the conclusion of the phrase. 
</p><p>Two or three weeks later, at my club in New York, I found a 
letter from her.  In it she owned that she was troubled, that of 
late she had been unsuccessful, and that, if I chanced to be coming 
back to Boston, and could spare her a little of that invaluable 
advice which&mdash;.  A few days later the advice was at her disposal. 
</p><p>She told me frankly what had happened.  Her public had grown 
tired of her.  She had seen it coming on for some time, and was 
shrewd enough in detecting the causes.  She had more rivals than 
formerly&mdash;younger women, she admitted, with a smile which could 
still afford to be generous&mdash;and then her audiences had grown more 
critical and consequently more exacting.  Lecturing&mdash;as she 
understood it&mdash;used to be simple enough.  You chose your topic&mdash; 
Raphael, Shakespeare, Gothic Architecture, or some such big 
familiar "subject"&mdash;and read up about it for a week or so at the 
Athenaeum or the Astor Library, and then told your audience what 
you had read.  Now, it appeared, that simple process was no longer 
adequate.  People had tired of familiar "subjects"; it was the 
fashion to be interested in things that one hadn't always known 
about&mdash;natural selection, animal magnetism, sociology and 
comparative folk-lore; while, in literature, the demand had become 
equally difficult to meet, since Matthew Arnold had introduced the 
habit of studying the "influence" of one author on another.  She 
had tried lecturing on influences, and had done very well as long 
as the public was satisfied with the tracing of such obvious 
influences as that of Turner on Ruskin, of Schiller on Goethe, of 
Shakespeare on the English drama; but such investigations had soon 
lost all charm for her too-sophisticated audiences, who now 
demanded either that the influence or the influenced should be 
absolutely unknown, or that there should be no perceptible 
connection between the two.  The zest of the performance lay in the 
measure of ingenuity with which the lecturer established a relation 
between two people who had probably never heard of each other, much 
less read each other's works.  A pretty Miss Williams with red hair 
had, for instance, been lecturing with great success on the 
influence of the Rosicrucians upon the poetry of Keats, while 
somebody else had given a "course" on the influence of St. Thomas 
Aquinas upon Professor Huxley. 
</p><p>Mrs. Amyot, warmed by my evident participation in her 
distress, went on to say that the growing demand for evolution was 
what most troubled her.  Her grandfather had been a pillar of the 
Presbyterian ministry, and the idea of her lecturing on Darwin or 
Herbert Spencer was deeply shocking to her mother and aunts.  In 
one sense the family had staked its literary as well as its 
spiritual hopes on the literal inspiration of Genesis: what became 
of "The Fall of Man" in the light of modern exegesis? 
</p><p>The upshot of it was that she had ceased to lecture because 
she could no longer sell tickets enough to pay for the hire of a 
lecture-hall; and as for the managers, they wouldn't look at her.  
She had tried her luck all through the Eastern States and as far 
South as Washington; but it was of no use, and unless she could get 
hold of some new subjects&mdash;or, better still, of <pb n="625"/>  some new 
audiences&mdash;she must simply go out of the business.  That would mean 
the failure of all she had worked for, since Lancelot would have to 
leave Harvard.  She paused, and wept some of the unbecoming tears 
that spring from real grief.  Lancelot, it appeared, was to be a 
genius.  He had passed his opening examinations brilliantly; he had 
"literary gifts"; he had written beautiful poetry, much of which 
his mother had copied out in reverentially slanting characters upon 
the pages of a velvet-bound volume which she drew from a locked 
drawer. 
</p><p>Lancelot's verse struck me as nothing more alarming than 
growing-pains; but it was not to learn this that she had summoned 
me.  What she wanted was to be assured that he was worth working 
for, an assurance which I managed to convey by the simple strategy 
of remarking that the poems reminded me of Swinburne&mdash;and so they 
did, as well as of Browning, Tennyson, Rossetti, William Morris, 
and all the other poets who supply young authors with original 
inspirations. 
</p><p>This point being satisfactorily established, it remained to be 
decided by what means his mother was, in the French phrase, to pay 
herself the luxury of a poet.  It was obvious that this indulgence 
could be bought only with counterfeit coin, and that the one way of 
helping Mrs. Amyot was to become a party to the circulation of such 
currency.  My fetish of intellectual integrity went down like a 
ninepin before the appeal of a woman no longer young and distinctly 
foolish, but full of those dear contradictions and irrelevances 
that will always make flesh and blood prevail against a syllogism.  
When I took leave of Mrs. Amyot I had promised her a dozen letters 
to Western universities and had half-pledged myself to sketch out 
for her a lecture on the reconciliation of science and religion. 
</p><p>In the West she achieved a success which for a year or more 
embittered my perusal of the morning papers.  The fascination which 
lures the murderer back to the scene of his crime drew my eye to 
every paragraph celebrating Mrs. Amyot's last brilliant lecture on 
the influence of something upon somebody; and her own letters&mdash;she 
overwhelmed me with them&mdash;spared me no detail of the entertainment 
given in her honor by the Palimpsest Club of Omaha or of her 
reception at the University of Leadville.  The college professors 
were especially kind: she assured me that she had never before met 
with such discriminating sympathy.  I winced under the adjective, 
which cast a sudden light upon the vast machinery of fraud that I 
had set in motion.  All over my native land, men of hitherto 
unblemished integrity were conniving with me in urging their 
friends to go and hear Mrs. Amyot lecture on the reconciliation of 
science and religion!  My only hope was that, somewhere among the 
number of my accomplices, Mrs. Amyot might find one who would marry 
her in the defense of his literary convictions. 
</p><p>None, apparently, resorted to such heroic measures; for about 
two years later I was startled by the announcement that Mrs. Amyot 
was lecturing in Trenton, N. J., on modern theosophy in the light 
of the Vedas.  The following week she was at Newark, discussing 
Schopenhauer in the light of recent psychology.  The week after 
that I was on the deck of an ocean steamer, reconsidering my share 
in Mrs. Amyot's triumphs with the impartiality with which one views 
an episode that is being left behind at the rate of twenty knots an 
hour.  After all, I had been helping a mother to educate her son. 
</p><p>The next decade of my life was spent in Europe, and when I 
came home the recollection of Mrs. Amyot had become as inoffensive 
as one of those pathetic ghosts who are said to strive in vain to 
make themselves visible to the living.  I did not even notice the 
fact that I no longer heard her spoken of; she had dropped like a 
dead leaf from the bough of memory. 
</p><p>A year or two after my return I was condemned to one of the 
worst punishments that a worker can undergo&mdash;an enforced holiday.  
The doctors who pronounced the inhuman sentence decreed that it 
should be worked out in the South, and for a whole winter I carried 
my cough, my thermometer and my idleness from one fashionable 
orange-grove to another.  In the vast and melancholy sea of my dis-occupation I clutched like a drowning man at any human driftwood 
within reach.  I took a critical and depreciatory interest <pb n="626"/>  
in the coughs, the thermometers and the idleness of my fellow-sufferers; but to the healthy, the occupied, the transient I clung 
with undiscriminating enthusiasm. 
</p><p>In no other way can I explain, as I look back upon it, the 
importance which I attached to the leisurely confidences of a new 
arrival with a brown beard who, tilted back at my side on a hotel 
veranda hung with roses, imparted to me one afternoon the simple 
annals of his past.  There was nothing in the tale to kindle the 
most inflammable imagination, and though the man had a pleasant 
frank face and a voice differing agreeably from the shrill 
inflections of our fellow-lodgers, it is probable that under 
different conditions his discursive history of successful business 
ventures in a Western city would have affected me somewhat in the 
manner of a lullaby. 
</p><p>Even at the time I was not sure that I liked his agreeable 
voice.  It had a sonorous assertiveness out of keeping with the 
humdrum character of his recital, as though a breeze engaged in 
shaking out a table-cloth should have fancied itself inflating a 
banner.  But this criticism may have been a mere mark of my own 
fastidious humor, for the man seemed a simple fellow, satisfied 
with his middling fortunes, and already (he was not much past 
thirty) deep-sunk in conjugal content. 
</p><p>He had just entered upon an anecdote connected with the 
cutting of his eldest boy's teeth, when a lady whom I knew, 
returning from her late drive, paused before us for a moment in the 
twilight, with the smile which is the feminine equivalent of beads 
to savages. 
</p><p>"Won't you take a ticket?" she said, sweetly. 
</p><p>Of course I would take a ticket&mdash;but for what? I ventured to 
inquire. 
</p><p>"Oh, that's <hi rend="italic"> so</hi> good of you&mdash;for the lecture this evening.  
You needn't go, you know; we are none of us going; most of us have 
been through it already at Aiken and at Saint Augustine and at Palm 
Beach.  I've given away my tickets to some new people who've just 
come from the North, and some of us are going to send our maids, 
just to fill up the room." 
</p><p>"And may I ask to whom you are going to pay this delicate 
attention?" 
</p><p>"Oh, I thought you knew&mdash;to poor Mrs. Amyot.  She's been 
lecturing all over the South this winter; she's simply <hi rend="italic"> haunted</hi> 
me ever since I left New York&mdash;and we had six weeks of her at Bar 
Harbor last summer!  One has to take tickets, you know, because 
she's a widow and does it for her son&mdash;to pay for his education.  
She's so plucky and nice about it, and talks about him in such a 
touching unaffected way, that everybody is sorry for her, and we 
all simply ruin ourselves in tickets.  I do hope that boy's nearly 
educated!" 
</p><p>"Mrs. Amyot?  Mrs. Amyot?" I repeated.  "Is she <hi rend="italic"> still</hi> 
educating her son?" 
</p><p>"Oh, do you know about her?  Has she been at it long?  There's 
some comfort in that, for I suppose when the boy's provided for the 
poor thing will be able to take a rest&mdash;and give us one!" 
</p><p>She laughed and extended her hand.  "Here's your ticket.  Did 
you say <hi rend="italic"> tickets</hi>&mdash;two?  Oh, thanks.  Of course you needn't go." 
</p><p>"But I mean to go.  Mrs. Amyot is an old friend of mine." 
</p><p>"Do you really?  That's awfully good of you.  Perhaps I'll go 
too if I can persuade Charlie and the others to come.  And I 
wonder"&mdash;in a well-directed aside&mdash;"if your friend&mdash;?" 
</p><p>I telegraphed her under cover of the dusk that my friend was 
of too recent standing to be drawn into her charitable toils, and 
she masked her mistake under a rattle of friendly adjurations not 
to be late, and to be sure to keep a seat for her, as she had quite 
made up her mind to go even if Charlie and the others wouldn't. 
</p><p>The flutter of her skirts subsided in the distance, and my 
neighbor, who had half turned away to light a cigar, made no effort 
to reopen the conversation.  At length, fearing that he might have 
overheard the allusion to himself, I ventured to ask if he were 
going to the lecture that evening. 
</p><p>"Much obliged&mdash;I have a ticket," he said, abruptly. 
</p><p>This struck me as in such bad taste that I made no answer; and 
it was he who spoke next. 
</p><p>"Did I understand you to say that you were an old friend of 
Mrs. Amyot's?" 
</p><p>"I think I may claim to be, if it is the same Mrs. Amyot whom 
I had the pleasure of knowing many years ago.  My Mrs. Amyot used 
to lecture too&mdash;" <pb n="627"/>  
</p><p>"To pay for her son's education?" 
</p><p>"I believe so." 
</p><p>"Well&mdash;see you later." 
</p><p>He got up and walked into the house. 
</p><p>In the hotel drawing-room that evening there was but a meagre 
sprinkling of guests, among whom I discovered my brown-bearded 
friend sitting alone on a sofa, with his head against the wall.  It 
was certainly not curiosity to see Mrs. Amyot which had impelled 
him to attend the performance, for it would have been impossible 
for him, without shifting his position, to command the improvised 
platform at the end of the room.  When I looked at him he seemed 
lost in contemplation of the chandelier. 
</p><p>The lady from whom I had purchased my tickets fluttered in 
late, unattended by Charlie and the others, and assuring me that 
she should <hi rend="italic"> scream</hi> if we had the lecture on Ibsen&mdash;she had heard 
it three times already that winter.  A glance at the programme 
reassured her: it informed us (in the lecturer's own slanting hand) 
that Mrs. Amyot was to lecture on the Cosmogony. 
</p><p>After a long pause, during which the small audience coughed 
and moved its chairs and showed signs of regretting that it had 
come, the door opened, and Mrs. Amyot stepped upon the platform.  
Ah, poor lady! 
</p><p>Someone said "Hush!" the coughing and chair-shifting subsided, 
and she began. 
</p><p>It was like looking at one's self early in the morning in a 
cracked mirror.  I had no idea that I had grown so old.  As for 
Lancelot, he must have a beard.  A beard?  The word struck me, and 
without knowing why I glanced across the room at my bearded friend 
on the sofa.  Oddly enough he was looking at me, with a half-defiant, half-sullen expression; and as our glances crossed, and 
his fell, the conviction came to me that <hi rend="italic"> he was Lancelot</hi>. 
</p><p>I don't remember a word of the lecture; and yet there were 
enough of them to have filled a good-sized dictionary.  The stream 
of Mrs. Amyot's eloquence had become a flood: one had the 
despairing sense that she had sprung a leak, and that until the 
plumber came there was nothing to be done about it. 
</p><p>The plumber came at length, in the shape of a clock striking 
ten; my companion, with a sigh of relief, drifted away in search of 
Charlie and the others; the audience scattered with the 
precipitation of people who had discharged a duty; and, without 
surprise, I found my brown-bearded acquaintance at my elbow. 
</p><p>We stood alone in the big bare-floored room, under the flaring 
chandelier. 
</p><p>"I think you told me this afternoon that you were an old 
friend of Mrs. Amyot's?" he began awkwardly. 
</p><p>I assented. 
</p><p>"Will you come in and see her?" 
</p><p>"Now?  I shall be very glad to, if&mdash;" 
</p><p>"She's ready; she's expecting you," he interposed. 
</p><p>He offered no further explanation, and I followed him in 
silence.  He led me down the long corridor, and pushed open the 
door of a sitting-room. 
</p><p>"Mother," he said, closing the door after we had entered, 
"here's the gentleman who says he used to know you." 
</p><p>Mrs. Amyot, who sat in an easy-chair stirring a cup of 
bouillon, looked up with a start.  She had evidently not seen me in 
the audience, and her son's description had failed to convey my 
identity.  I saw a frightened look in her eyes; then, like a frost 
flower on a window-pane, the dimple expanded on her wrinkled cheek, 
and she held out her hand to me. 
</p><p>"I'm so glad," she said, "so glad!" 
</p><p>She turned to her son, who stood watching us.  "You must have 
told Lancelot all about me&mdash;you've known me so long!" 
</p><p>"I haven't had time to talk to your son&mdash;since I knew he was 
your son," I explained. 
</p><p>Her brow cleared.  "Then you haven't had time to say anything 
very dreadful?" she said, with a laugh. 
</p><p>"It is he who has been saying dreadful things," I returned, 
trying to fall in with her tone. 
</p><p>I saw my mistake.  "What things?" she faltered. 
</p><p>"Making me feel how old I am by telling me about his 
children." 
</p><p>"My grandchildren!" she exclaimed, with a blush. 
</p><p>"Well, if you choose to put it so." 
</p><p>She laughed again, vaguely, and was silent.  I hesitated a 
moment, and then put out my hand. 
</p><p>"I see that you are tired.  I shouldn't <pb n="628"/>  have ventured 
to come in at this hour if your son&mdash;" 
</p><p>The son stepped between us.  "Yes, I asked him to come," he 
said to his mother, in his clear self-assertive voice.  <hi rend="italic">" I</hi> 
haven't told him anything yet; but you've got to&mdash;now.  That's what 
I brought him for." 
</p><p>His mother straightened herself, but I saw her eye waver. 
</p><p>"Lancelot&mdash;" she began. 
</p><p>"Mr. Amyot," I said, turning to the young man, "if your mother 
will allow me to come back to-morrow, I shall be very glad&mdash;" 
</p><p>He struck his hand hard against the table on which he was 
leaning. 
</p><p>"No, sir!  It won't take long, but it's got to be said now." 
</p><p>He moved nearer to his mother, and I saw his lip twitch under 
his beard.  After all, he was younger and less sure of himself than 
I had fancied. 
</p><p>"See here, mother," he went on, "there's something here that's 
got to be cleared up, and as you say this gentleman is an old 
friend of yours it had better be cleared up in his presence.  Maybe 
he can help explain it&mdash;and if he can't, it's got to be explained 
to <hi rend="italic"> him</hi>." 
</p><p>Mrs. Amyot's lips moved, but she made no sound.  She glanced 
at me helplessly and reseated herself.  My early inclination to 
thrash Lancelot was beginning to reassert itself.  I took up my hat 
and moved toward the door. 
</p><p>"Mrs. Amyot is certainly under no obligation to explain 
anything whatever to me," I said, curtly. 
</p><p>"Well!  She's under an obligation to me, then&mdash;to explain 
something in your presence."  He turned to her again.  "Do you know 
what the people in this hotel are saying?  Do you know what he 
thinks&mdash;what they all think?  That you're doing this lecturing to 
support me&mdash;to pay for my education!  They say you go round telling 
them so.  That's what they buy the tickets for&mdash;they do it out of 
charity.  Ask him if it isn't what they say&mdash;ask him if they 
weren't joking about it on the piazza before dinner.  The others 
think I'm a little boy, but he's known you for years, and he must 
have known how old I was.  <hi rend="italic"> He</hi> must have known it wasn't to pay 
for my education!" 
</p><p>He stood before her with his hands clenched, the veins beating 
in his temples.  She had grown very pale, and her cheeks looked 
hollow.  When she spoke her voice had an odd click in it. 
</p><p>"If&mdash;if these ladies and gentlemen have been coming to my 
lectures out of charity, I see nothing to be ashamed of in that&mdash;" 
she faltered. 
</p><p>"If they've been coming out of charity to <hi rend="italic"> me</hi>," he 
retorted, "don't you see you've been making me a party to a fraud?  
Isn't there any shame in that?"  His forehead reddened.  "Mother!  
Can't you see the shame of letting people think that I was a d&mdash; 
beat, who sponged on you for my keep?  Let alone making us both the 
laughing-stock of every place you go to!" 
</p><p>"I never did that, Lancelot!" 
</p><p>"Did what?" 
</p><p>"Made you a laughing-stock&mdash;" 
</p><p>He stepped close to her and caught her wrist. 
</p><p>"Will you look me in the face and swear you never told people 
that you were doing this lecturing business to support me?" 
</p><p>There was a long silence.  He dropped her wrist, and she 
lifted a limp handkerchief to her frightened eyes.  "I did do it&mdash; 
to support you&mdash;to educate you"&mdash;she sobbed. 
</p><p>"We're not talking about what you did when I was a boy.  
Everybody who knows me knows I've been a grateful son.  Have I ever 
taken a penny from you since I left college ten years ago?" 
</p><p>"I never said you had!  How can you accuse your mother of such 
wickedness, Lancelot?" 
</p><p>"Have you never told anybody in this hotel&mdash;or anywhere else 
in the last ten years&mdash;that you were lecturing to support me?  
Answer me that!" 
</p><p>"How can you," she wept, "before a stranger?" 
</p><p>"Haven't you said such things about me to strangers?" he 
retorted. 
</p><p>"Lancelot!" 
</p><p>"Well&mdash;answer me, then.  Say you haven't, mother!"  His voice 
broke unexpectedly and he took her hand with a gentler touch.  
"I'll believe anything you tell me," he said, almost humbly. 
</p><p>She mistook his tone and raised her head with a rash clutch at 
dignity. <pb n="629"/>  
</p><p>"I think you had better ask this gentleman to excuse you 
first." 
</p><p>"No, by God, I won't!" he shouted.  "This gentleman says he 
knows all about you and I mean him to know all about me too.  I 
don't mean that he or anybody else under this roof shall go on 
thinking for another twenty-four hours that a cent of their money 
has ever gone into my pockets since I was old enough to shift for 
myself.  And he sha'n't leave this room till you've made that clear 
to him." 
</p><p>He stepped back as he spoke and put his shoulders against the 
door. 
</p><p>"My dear young gentleman," I said, politely, "I shall leave 
this room exactly when I see fit to do so&mdash;and that is now.  I have 
already told you that Mrs. Amyot owes me no explanation of her 
conduct." 
</p><p>"But I owe you an explanation of mine&mdash;you and every one who 
has bought a single one of her lecture tickets.  Do you suppose a 
man who's been through what I went through while that woman was 
talking to you in the porch before dinner is going to hold his 
tongue, and not attempt to justify himself?  No decent man is going 
to sit down under that sort of thing.  It's enough to ruin his 
character.  If you're my mother's friend, you owe it to me to hear 
what I've got to say." 
</p><p>He pulled out his handkerchief and wiped his forehead. 
</p><p>"Good God, mother!" he burst out suddenly, "what did you do it 
for?  Haven't you had every thing you wanted ever since I was able 
to pay for it?  Haven't I paid you back every cent you spent on me 
when I was in college?  Have I ever gone back on you since I was 
big enough to work?"  He turned to me with a laugh.  "I thought she 
did it to amuse herself&mdash;and because there was such a demand for 
her lectures.  <hi rend="italic"> Such a demand!</hi>  That's what she always told me.  
When we asked her to come out and spend this winter with us in 
Minneapolis, she wrote back that she couldn't because she had 
engagements all through the South, and her manager wouldn't let her 
off.  That's the reason why I came all the way on here to see her.  
We thought she was the most popular lecturer in the United States, 
my wife and I did!  We were awfully proud of it too, I can tell 
you."  He dropped into a chair, still laughing. 
</p><p>"How can you, Lancelot, how can you!"  His mother, forgetful 
of my presence, was clinging to him with tentative caresses.  "When 
you didn't need the money any longer I spent it all on the 
children&mdash;you know I did." 
</p><p>"Yes, on lace christening dresses and life-size rocking-horses 
with real manes!  The kind of thing that children can't do 
without." 
</p><p>"Oh, Lancelot, Lancelot&mdash;I loved them so!  How can you believe 
such falsehoods about me?" 
</p><p>"What falsehoods about you?" 
</p><p>"That I ever told anybody such dreadful things?" 
</p><p>He put her back gently, keeping his eyes on hers.  "Did you 
never tell anybody in this house that you were lecturing to support 
your son?" 
</p><p>Her hands dropped from his shoulders, and she flashed round 
upon me in sudden anger. 
</p><p>"I know what I think of people who call themselves friends and 
who come between a mother and her son!" 
</p><p>"Oh, mother, mother!" he groaned. 
</p><p>I went up to him and laid my hand on his shoulder. 
</p><p>"My dear man," I said, "don't you see the uselessness of 
prolonging this?" 
</p><p>"Yes, I do," he answered, abruptly, and before I could 
forestall his movement he rose and walked out of the room. 
</p><p>There was a long silence, measured by the decreasing 
reverberations of his footsteps down the wooden floor of the 
corridor. 
</p><p>When they ceased I approached Mrs. Amyot, who had sunk into 
her chair.  I held out my hand and she took it without a trace of 
resentment on her ravaged face. 
</p><p>"I sent his wife a seal-skin jacked at Christmas!" she said, 
with the tears running down her cheeks. 

</p></div1></body></text></TEI.2> 
