<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaR2Ef"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

 
<TEI.2 id="WhaR2Ef"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Ethan Frome</title>
<title type="sort">ethan frome</title>
<author>Wharton review: Anonymous</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">11</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WhaR2Ef</idno> 
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476521</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">
<hi rend="italic">Ethan Frome</hi> in: Current Fiction.</title>
<title level="j">Nation. A Weekly Journal Devoted to Politics, Literature, Science, Drama, Music, Art and Finance.</title>
<title type="sort">ethan frome in current fiction</title>
<author>Anonymous</author>
</titleStmt> 
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition.</p>
</editionStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>New York Evening Post Company</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York, N.Y.</pubPlace> 
<date value="1911">1911</date>
</publicationStmt>  
<seriesStmt>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">The Nation</hi> 93, 26 Oct. 1911: 396-97.</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>UVa ed. AP2.N2</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p> 
<p>Spell-check and verification made 
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1911">1911</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
<term>prose</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-03">March 1996</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Deirdre A. Johnson, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added header and basic TEI markup</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><head><pb n="396"/> <hi rend="italic">Ethan Frome</hi>. By Edith Wharton. New York: Charles 
Scribner's Sons.</head> 
 
<p>More than ten years ago Mrs. Wharton published a short story 
called &laquo;The Duchess at Prayer.&raquo; Since that time we have cherished 
an estimate of her powers which no intermediate accession to her 
repertory has raised, nor even, to speak truth, quite justified.  
Practised, cosmopolitan, subtle, she has seemed, on the whole, to 
covet most earnestly the refinements of Henry James. In spite of 
her habit of a franker approach, her consistent rating of matter 
above manner, and the gravitation   &mdash;   we should hesitate to say 
transfer   &mdash;   of her interest from exotic to native themes; we might 
have been reasonably content to rank her as the greatest pupil of 
a little master, were it not for the appearance of &laquo;Ethan Frome.&raquo;  
This startling fulfilment recalls not only the promise of the early 
story, but its revelation of a more potent influence   &mdash;   the 
inspiriting example of a greater novelist to whom Mr. James's 
<hi rend="italic">devoirs</hi> have been paid in the phrase, &laquo;The master of us 
all.&raquo; Exactly how much the inception and execution of &laquo;The Duchess 
at Prayer&raquo; owed to Balzac's &laquo;La grande Breteche&raquo; is beyond our 
present point, which is, specifically, that the excellence of Mrs. 
Wharton's work in this case outstripped the charge of imitation, 
and allied her with that company of splendid talents whom neither 
magnificence nor the catastrophes of passion can abash. 
</p><p>There is certainly no imitative strain in &laquo;Ethan Frome.&raquo; The 
style is assured and entirely individual, the method direct and 
firm in its grasp upon substantial fact. Yet here is the 
companion-piece to the &laquo;Duchess,&raquo; a variation upon the same theme 
of triumphant malice and tortured love, evoking the same emotions.  
And here as there the genius of a place presides, and the scene and 
the hour conspire to meet the racial temper. But there is this 
great difference: in the place of sumptuous memories, decaying 
under the sultry oppression of Italian noon, she was, at heart, a 
stranger; whereas she writes now of New England as one writes of 
home, plainly, and with a wealth of understanding and familiar 
allusion. Even the arrangement of the narrative is designed to fit 
the life described and its probabilities rather than to satisfy any 
precious scruples. A winter-bound stranger in an out-of-the-way 
Massachusetts hamlet recognizes in the limping figure of Ethan 
Frome the &laquo;ruin of a man,&raquo; and apprehends some singular misfortunes 
behind his obvious plight. The sparse comment of a community 
respectful of privacies and little indulgent to curiosity yields 
but scanty information. Out of the native's penury come at length 
hours of enforced companionship, the daily rides to the station 
during which &laquo;Frome drove in silence, the reins loosely held in his 
left hand, his brown, seamed profile, under the helmet-like peak of 
the cap, relieved against the banks of snow.&raquo; 
</p><p>&laquo;It was that night,&raquo; explains the visitor, &laquo;that I found the 
clue to Ethan Frome, and began to put together this vision of his 
story.&raquo; Such an approach could not be improved, forbearing, as it 
does, to violate the seal of silence; nor could, we think, the 
conclusion of village confidences be spared, with its ultimate 
breaking down of reserve between the initiated, its natural cadence 
of secret curiosity, and its softening echo of unavailing human 
sympathy. 
</p><p>Surely, the melancholy spirit that haunts the remoter byways 
of rural New England has entered into this chronicle; over all its 
scenes breathe the benumbing and isolating rigors of her winters, 
a sense of invisible fetters, a consciousness of depleted 
resources, a reticence and self-contained endurance that even the 
houses know how to express, retired from the public way, or turned 
sideways to preserve a secluded entrance. Yet it is with a softly-breathed strain of native romance that the drama opens. As well 
try to transplant arbutus from its native habitat as to dissociate 
this exquisite burgeoning of passion from its homely circumstances 
and the inflexible trammels of a local speech meant for taciturnity 
rather than expression. Thriving on meagre opportunities and 
pleasures   &mdash;   the coasting, the picnic, the walk home from the &laquo;church 
sociable&raquo;   &mdash;   and on the sharing of frugal household cares, the love 
between the young farmer and the little dependent who inefficiently 
&laquo;helped&raquo; in his home, spread like a secret flowering too innocent 
and too fragrant to escape the wife's malicious eye. The 
<pb n="397"/> 
brave and fragile figure of Mattie Silvers is not an idealized one, 
although this is the type of New England girlhood whose modesty and 
touch of fairy grace have been the subject of much poetry. 
</p><p>The wife who stands for fate in this drama is a curious and 
repugnant figure. She introduces the same vein of close-mouthed 
malignity which darkens local history. The helpless fear and 
loathing she inspires in her husband is the essence of supernatural 
terror without its obsolete husk of ignorance. By showing this 
instance of a hypochondriac roused by jealousy out of a &laquo;sullen 
self-absorption&raquo; and transformed into a mysterious alien presence, 
an evil energy secreted from the long years of silent brooding, 
Mrs. Wharton touches on a very radical identity. We realize that 
the same gloating satisfaction that made the wife smile upon the 
parting lovers, had something to do with her capabilities as a 
nurse. Her pleasure at the sight of pain she had inflicted   &mdash;   was 
it, perchance, from such an evil spring that her strength was drawn 
for the long years of drudgery between two cripples? 
</p><p>No hero of fantastic legend was ever more literally hag-ridden 
than was Ethan Frome. The profound irony of his case is that it 
required his own goodness to complete her parasitic power over him.  
Without his innate honesty and his sense of duty he could have 
escaped her demands and her decrees, refused the money for her 
nostrums and &laquo;doctor books,&raquo; followed the vision of a new free life 
&laquo;out West.&raquo; In his submission to obligation and in his thwarted 
intellectual aspirations he typifies the remnant of an exceptional 
race whose spiritual inheritance has dwindled amid hard conditions 
until all distinction is forfeited except that of suffering; but 
which still indicates its quality, if only by its capacity for 
suffering. 
</p><p>The wonder is that the spectacle of so much pain can be made 
to yield so much beauty. And here the full range of Mrs. Wharton's 
imagination becomes apparent. There is possible, within the gamut 
of human experience, an exaltation of anguish which makes a 
solitude for itself, whose direct contemplation seals the impulse 
of speech and strikes cold upon the heart. Yet sometimes in 
reflection there is revealed, beneath the writhing torment, the 
lineaments of a wronged and distorted loveliness. It is the 
piteous and intolerable conception which the Greeks expressed in 
the Medusa head that Mrs. Wharton has dared to hold up to us anew, 
but the face she shows us is the face of our own people. 
</p> 
</div1> 

</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
