<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaR1Su"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
 
<TEI.2 id="WhaR1Su"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Some Stories of the Month</title>
<title type="sort">some stories of the month</title>
<author>Wharton review: Boynton, H. W.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">8</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WhaR1Su</idno> 
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476517</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This electronic text is an excerpt from a longer review. Comment in square brackets [] was added by the creator of the electronic version, to clarify an antecedent.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Some Stories of the Month</title>
<title level="j">Bookman</title>
<title type="sort">some stories of the month</title>
<author>H. W. Boynton</author>
</titleStmt> 
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition.</p>
</editionStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Dodd, Mead &amp; Company</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York, N. Y.</pubPlace> 
<date value="1917">1917</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Bookman</hi> 46 (Sept. 1917): 93-94.</p>
</seriesStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p> 
<p>Spell-check and verification made 
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1917">1917</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
<term>prose</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords> 
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-03">March 1996</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Deirdre A. Johnson, Electronic Text Center, University of 
Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added header and basic TEI markup</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2"> 

<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="93" id="WhaR1Su93"/>  

<p>Her [Miss Wilkins] own New England, the scene of the early 
tales, is an affair of black and white, of strong crude forces and 
repressions. Such is the New England of Mrs. Wharton in <hi rend="italic">Ethan 
Frome</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Summer</hi>. But while Miss Wilkins's voice had 
always a certain raw tang of the native, altogether lacked grace 
and flexibility, <hi rend="italic">was</hi> the voice of rustic New England, Mrs. 
Wharton has had the task of subduing her rich and varied and 
worldly instrument to its provincial theme. She has succeeded; 
<hi rend="italic">Summer</hi> shows all the virtue of her style and none of its 
weakness. Here is no routine 
<pb n="94" id="WhaR1Su94"/>elegance, no languor of 
disillusion, no bite of deliberate satire. As in <hi rend="italic">Ethan 
Frome</hi>, this writer who has come perilously near being the idol 
of snobs shows herself as an interpreter of life in its elements, 
stripped of the habits and inhibitions of the polite world. The 
story lacks the tragic completeness of the earlier one, has indeed 
a species of happy ending,&mdash;an ending, at worst, of pathos not 
without hope. The scene is the New England village of North 
Dormer, once as good as its neighbours, but now deserted and 
decaying in its corner among the hills. It is vignetted in a few 
sentences at the beginning: &laquo; little wind moved among the round 
white clouds on the shoulders of the hills, driving their shadows 
across the fields and down the grassy road that takes the name of 
street when it passes through North Dormer. The place lies high 
and in the open, and lacks the lavish shade of the more protected 
New England villages. The clump of weeping willows about the duck 
pond, and the Norway spruces in front of the Hatchard gate, cast 
almost the only roadside shadow between lawyer Royall's house and 
the point where, at the other end of the village, the road rises 
above the church and skirts the black hemlock wall enclosing the 
cemetery.&raquo; The Hatchards are the great people of the place, with 
an elderly spinster still solvent and in residence, and a Memorial 
Library bearing musty witness to that distinguished and now 
extinguished author, Honorius Hatchard, who had hobnobbed with 
Irving and Halleck, back in the forties. Another old family are 
the Royalls. Their present representative is the middle-aged 
lawyer who, after showing promise elsewhere, has returned to North 
Dormer while still a young man, for the apparent purpose of going 
to seed there at his leisure. Above the village, though at 
distance&mdash;fastness of a strange community of outlaws and 
degenerates&mdash;towers the craggy mountain from which, years back, 
Lawyer Royall has rescued a child. As Charity Royall she grows up 
in his household, and after his wife's death becomes its 
unchallenged ruler. Her little liking for Royall himself he has 
destroyed by making, in his &laquo;lonesomeness,&raquo; a single false step 
toward her. Her own lonely lot in unyouthful North Dormer is 
lightened only by the vague dreams of girlhood. Then the fairy 
prince comes in the person of a young architect from the city whom 
certain local relics of fine building have attracted to the 
neighbourhood, and whom a swift romance with the girl Charity holds 
there. She becomes his mistress, he deserts her in her &laquo;trouble,&raquo; 
she turns desperately to the haunt of her people, &laquo;the Mountain&raquo;; 
and is rescued for a second time and finally by Lawyer Royall. In 
her marriage with the aging man whom she has scorned there is, we 
really believe, some chance of happiness, or at least content.  
Young love is dead, but old love is ready to creep into its place.  
Mrs. Wharton has often been accused of bitterness; let her critics 
note that the whole effect of this powerful story hangs upon our 
recognition of the power of simple human goodness&mdash;not 
&laquo;virtuousness,&raquo; but faithful, unselfish devotion of one sort or 
another&mdash;to make life worth living. 
</p><p>Until the end itself, <hi rend="italic">Summer</hi> has seemed to be moving, 
as <hi rend="italic">Ethan Frome</hi> moved, toward some grim catastrophe. 
</p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
 
 
