<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaRefu"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

 
<TEI.2 id="WhaRefu"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Refugees</title>
<title type="sort">refugees</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">65</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WhaRefu</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476525</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Refugees</title>
<title type="sort">refugees</title>
<author>Edith Wharton</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Saturday Evening Post</publisher> 
<pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace> 
<date value="1919">18 January 1919</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>191</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Wharton, Edith.  "The Refugees."  Saturday Evening Post 191,  
18 January 1919: 3-5, 53, 57, 61.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1919">18 January 1919</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-08">August 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added header, Tagged with TEI.2-compatible SGML, Parsed against "teilite" dtd</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1"> 
 
 
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> <pb n="3"/> 
<head> 
                   THE REFUGEES BY EDITH WHARTON <lb/>
                    ILLUSTRATED BY F. R. GRUGER 
</head> 
<p>ON SEPTEMBER 8, 1914, Charley Durand stood helplessly blinking 
through his spectacles at the throng of fugitives which the 
Folkestone train had just poured out on the platform of Charing 
Cross. 
</p><p>He was aware of a faint haze on the spectacles, which he 
usually kept clear of the slightest smirch.  It had been too 
prolonged, too abominable, too soul-searching, the slow torture of 
his hours of travel with the stricken multitude in which he had 
found himself entangled on the pier at Boulogne. 
</p><p>Charley Durand, professor of Romance languages in a Western 
university, had been spending the first weeks of a hard-earned 
sabbatical holiday in wandering through Flanders and Belgium, and 
on the fatal second of August had found himself at Louvain, whose 
university a year or two previously had honored him with a degree. 
</p><p>He had left Belgium at once, and deeply disturbed by the 
dislocation of his plans had carried his shaken nerves to a lost 
corner of Normandy, where he had spent the ensuing weeks in trying 
to think the war would soon be over. 
</p><p>It was not that he was naturally hard or aloof about it, or 
wanted to be; but the whole business was so contrary to his 
conception of the universe and his fagged mind at the moment was so 
incapable of prompt readjustment that he needed time to steady 
himself.  Besides, his conscience told him that his first duty was 
to get back unimpaired to the task which just enabled him to keep 
a mother and two sisters above want.  His few remaining francs had 
gone to the various relief funds whose appeals penetrated even to 
his lost corner; and he therefore decided that the prudent course, 
now that everybody said the horror was certainly going to last till 
November, would be to slip over to cheap lodgings in London and 
bury his nose in the British Museum. 
</p><p>This decision, as it chanced, had coincided with the 
annihilation of Louvain and Malines.  News of the rapid German 
advance had not reached him; but at Boulogne he had found himself 
caught in the central eddy of fugitives, tossed about among them 
like one of themselves, pitched on the boat with them, dealt with 
compassionately but firmly by the fagged officials at Folkestone, 
jammed into a cranny of the endless train, had chocolate and buns 
thrust on him by ministering angels with high heels and powdered 
noses, and shyly passed these refreshments on to the fifteen dazed 
fellow travelers packed into his compartment. 
</p><p>His first impulse had been to turn back and fly the sight at 
any cost.  But his luggage had already passed out of his keeping, 
and he had not the courage to forsake it.  Moreover, a slight 
congenital lameness made flight in such circumstances almost 
impossible.  So after a fugitive had come down heavily on his lame 
foot he resigned himself to keeping in the main current and letting 
it sweep him onto the boat. 
</p><p>Once on board he had hastened to isolate himself behind a 
funnel, in an airless corner reeking of oil and steam, while the 
refugees, abandoned to unanimous seasickness, became for the time 
an indistinguishable animal welter.  But the run to London had 
brought him into closer contact with them.  It was impossible to 
sit for three mortal hours with an unclaimed little boy on one's 
lap, opposite a stony-faced woman holding a baby that never stopped 
crying, and not give them something more than what remained of 
one's chocolate and buns.  The woman with the child was bad enough; 
though perhaps less perversely moving than the little blond thing 
with long soiled gloves who kept staring straight ahead and moaning 
"My furs!  Oh, my furs!"  But worst of all was the old man at the 
other end of the compartment, the motionless old man in a frayed 
suit of professorial black, with a face like a sallow bust on a 
bracket in a university library. 
</p><p>It was the face of Durand's own class and of his own 
profession, and it struck him as something not to be contemplated 
without dire results to his nervous system.  He was glad the old 
man did not speak to him, but only waved away with a silent bow the 
sandwich he awkwardly offered; and glad that he himself was 
protected by a slight [illustration omitted] <pb n="4"/>  stammer, which 
agitation always increased, from any attempt at sustained 
conversation with the others.  But in spite of these safeguards the 
run to London was dreadful. 
</p><p>On the platform at Charing Cross he stood motionless, trying 
to protect his lame leg and yet to take up as little room as 
possible, while he waited for the tide to flow by and canalize 
itself.  There was no way in which he could help the doomed 
wretches; he kept repeating that without its affording him the 
least relief.  He had given away his last available penny, keeping 
barely enough to pay for a few frugal weeks in certain grimy 
lodgings he knew of off Bedford Square; and he could do nothing for 
the moment but take up as little space as possible till a break in 
the crowd should let him hobble through to freedom.  But that might 
not be for another hour; and meanwhile helplessly he gazed at the 
scene through misty spectacles. 
</p><p>The refugees were spread out about him in a stagnant mass, 
through which, over which almost, there squeezed, darted, skimmed 
and criss-crossed the light battalions of the benevolent.  People 
with badges were everywhere, philanthropists of both sexes and all 
ages, sorting, directing, exhorting, contradicting, saying "Wee, 
wee," and "Oh, no," and "This way, please.  Oh, dear, what is 'this 
way' in French?" and "I beg your pardon, but that bed warmer 
belongs to my old woman"; and industriously adding, by all the 
means known to philanthropy, to the distress and bewilderment of 
their victims. 
</p><p>Durand saw the old professor slip by alone, as if protected by 
his silent dignity.  He saw other stricken faces that held 
benevolence at bay.  One or two erect old women with smooth hair 
and neat black bonnets gave him a sharper pang than the disheveled; 
and he watched with positive anguish a mother pausing to straighten 
her little boy's collar. 
</p><p>Suddenly he was aware of a frightened touch on his arm. 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Oh, monsieur, je roux en prie, venez!</hi>  Do come!" 
</p><p>The voice was a reedy pipe, the face that of a little elderly 
lady so frail and dry and diaphanous that she reminded him in her 
limp, dust-colored garments of a last year's moth shaken out of the 
curtains of an empty room. 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Je roux en prie!"</hi> she repeated, with a plaintive 
stress on the last word.  Her intonation was not exactly French, 
but he supposed it was some variety of provincial Belgian, and 
wondered why it sounded so unlike anything he had been hearing.  
Her face was as wild as anything so small and domesticated could 
be.  Tears were running down her thin cheeks, and the hand on his 
sleeve twitched in its cotton glove.  <hi rend="italic">"Mais oui, mais oui</hi>," 
he found himself reassuring her.  Her look of anxiety disappeared, 
and as he drew the cotton glove through his arm the tears seemed to 
be absorbed into her pale wrinkles. 
</p><p>"So many of them obviously want to be left alone; here's one 
who wants to be looked after," he thought to himself, with a 
whimsical satisfaction in the discovery, as he yielded to the 
gentle pull on his arm. 
</p><p>He was of a retiring nature, and compassion, far from making 
him expansive, usually contracted his faculties to the point of 
cowardice; but the scenes he had traversed were so far beyond any 
former vision of human wretchedness that all the defenses of his 
gentle egotism had broken down and he found himself suddenly happy 
and almost proud at having been singled out as a rescuer.  He 
understood the passionate wish of all the rescuers to secure a 
refugee and carry him or her away in triumph against all 
competitors; and while his agile mind made a rapid sum in division 
his grasp tightened on the little old lady's arm and he muttered to 
himself: "They shan't take her from me if I have to live on dry 
bread!" 
</p><p>With a victim on his arm&mdash;and one who looked the part so 
touchingly&mdash;it was easier to insinuate his way through the crowd, 
and he fended off all the attempts of fair highwaymen to snatch his 
prize from him with an energy in which the prize ably seconded him. 
</p><p>"No, no, no!" she repeated in soft, piping English, tightening 
her clutch as he tightened his; and presently he discovered that 
she had noticed his lameness, and with her free hand was making 
soft fierce dabs at the backs and ribs that blocked their advance. 
</p><p>"You're lame too.  Did they do it?" she whispered, falling 
into French again; and he said chivalrously: "Oh, yes&mdash;but it 
wasn't their fault." 
</p><p>"The savages!  I shall never feel in that way about them&mdash; 
though it's noble of you," she murmured; and the inconsequence of 
this ferocity toward her fellow sufferers struck him as rather 
refreshingly feminine.  Like most shy men he was dazzled by 
unreasonable women. 
</p><p>"Are you in very great pain?" she continued as they reached 
the street. 
</p><p>"Oh, no&mdash;not at all.  I beg you won't&mdash;  The trouble is&mdash;" he 
broke off, confronted by an unforeseen difficulty. [illustration 
omitted] 
</p><p>"What is your trouble?" she sighed, leaning her little head 
toward him. 
</p><p>"Why&mdash;I&mdash;the fact is I don't know London; or England; 
<hi rend="italic">jamais ete</hi>," he confessed, merging the two languages in a 
vain effort at fluency. 
</p><p>"But of course&mdash;why should you?  Only trust me." 
</p><p>"Ah, you do know it, then?" 
</p><p>What luck to have found a refugee who could take care of him!  
He vowed her half his worldly goods on the spot. 
</p><p>"She was busy signaling a hansom, and did not answer.  "Is 
this all your luggage?" 
</p><p>A porter had followed with it.  He felt that he ought to have 
been asking her for hers, but dared not, fearing a tragic answer.  
He supposed she had been able to bring away nothing but her shabby 
cloak and the little knobby bag that had been prodding his ribs 
ever since they had linked arms. 
</p><p>"How lucky to have been able to save so much!" she sighed as 
his bags and boxes were laboriously hoisted to the hansom. 
</p><p>"Yes&mdash;in such a struggle," he agreed; and wondered if she was 
a little flighty as she added: "I suppose you didn't bring your 
mattress?  Not that it matters in the very least.  Quick, get in!" 
she shrieked out abruptly, pushing him past her into the hansom, 
and adding as she scrambled in and snapped the doors shut: "My 
sister-in-law&mdash;she's so grasping&mdash;I don't want her to see us." 
</p><p>She pushed up the lid and cried out a name unfamiliar to her 
companion, but to which horse and driver instantly responded. 
</p><p>Durand sank back without speaking.  He was bewildered and 
disconcerted, and her last words had shocked him.  "My sister-in-law&mdash;she's so grasping."  The refugees, then, poor souls, were torn 
by the same family jealousies as more prosperous mortals.  
Affliction was supposed to soften, but apparently in such monstrous 
doses it had the opposite effect.  He had noticed on the journey 
symptoms of this reciprocal distrust among the herded creatures.  
It was no doubt natural: but he wished his little refugee had not 
betrayed the weakness. 
</p><p>The thought of the sister-in-law they were deserting&mdash;perhaps 
as helpless and destitute as his own waif&mdash;brought a protest to his 
stammering tongue. 
</p><p>"Ought&mdash;oughtn't we to take her with us?  Hadn't we better 
turn back?" 
</p><p>"For Caroline?  Oh, no, <hi rend="italic">non</hi>, no!"  She screamed it in 
every tongue.  <hi rend="italic">"Cher monsieur</hi>, please!  She's sure to have 
her own.  Such heaps of them!" 
</p><p>Ah&mdash;it was jealousy then; jealousy of the more favored sister-in-law, who was no doubt younger and handsomer, and had been fought 
over by rival rescuers, while she, poor pet, had had to single one 
out for herself.  Well, Durand felt he would not have exchanged her 
for a beauty&mdash;so frail, fluttered, plaintive did she seem, so small 
a vessel to contain so great a woe. 
</p><p>Suddenly it struck him that it was she who had given the order 
to the driver.  He was more and more bewildered, and ashamed of his 
visible incompetence. 
</p><p>"Where are we going?" he faltered. 
</p><p>"For tea&mdash;there's plenty of time, I do assure you; and I'm 
fainting for a little food." 
</p><p>"So am I," he admitted; adding to himself: "I'll feed the poor 
thing, and then we'll see what's to be done." 
</p><p>How he wished he hadn't given away all but his last handful of 
shillings!  His poverty had never been so humiliating to him.  What 
right had he to be pretending to help a refugee?  It was as much as 
he could do to pay the hansom and give her her tea.  And then?  A 
dampness of fear broke over him, and he cursed his cowardice in not 
having told her at once to make another choice. 
</p><p>"But supposing nobody else had taken her?" he thought, 
stealing a look at her small pointed profile and the pale wisps of 
hair under her draggled veil.  Her insignificance was complete, and 
he decided that he had probably been her last expedient. 
</p><p>It would be odd if it proved that she was also his.  He 
remembered hearing that some of the rich refugees had been able to 
bring their money with them, and his mind strayed away to the 
whimsical possibility of being offered a post with emoluments by 
the frightened creature who was so determined not to let him go. 
</p><p>"If only I knew London," he thought regretfully, "I might be 
worth a good salary to her.  The queer thing is that she seems to 
know it herself." 
</p><p>Both sat silent, absorbed in their emotions. 
</p><p>It was certainly an odd way to be seeing London for the first 
time; but he was glad to be traveling at horse pace instead of 
whirling through his thronged sensations in a motor cab. 
</p><p>"Trafalgar Square&mdash;yes.  How clever of you!  <hi rend="italic">Les Lions de 
Milord Nelson!"</hi> she explained. 
</p><p>They drove on, past palaces and parks. 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Maison du Grand Duc.  Arc de triomphe de marbre</hi>," she 
successively enlightened him, sounding like a gnat in a megaphone.  
He leaned and gazed, forgetting her and himself in an ecstasy of 
assimilation.  In the golden autumn haze London loomed mightier and 
richer than his best dreams of it. 
 
 
</p><p>                           II 
 
THE hansom stopped and they entered a modest tea room not too 
densely crowded. 
</p><p>"I wanted to get away from that awful mob," she explained, 
pushing back her veil as they seated themselves at a table with 
red-and-white napkins and a britannia sugar bowl. 
</p><p>"Crumpets&mdash;lots of crumpets and jam," she instructed a 
disdainful girl in a butterfly cap, who languished away with the 
order to the back of the shop. 
</p><p>"Durand sat speechless, overwhelmed by his predicament.  Tea 
and crumpets were all very well&mdash;but afterward, what? 
</p><p>He felt that his silence was becoming boorish, and leaned 
forward over the metal teapot.  At the same instant his protegee 
leaned, too, and simultaneously they brought out the question: 
</p><p>"Where were you when it broke out?" 
</p><p>"At Louvain," he answered; and she shuddered. 
</p><p>"Louvain&mdash;how terrible!" 
</p><p>"And you, madame?" 
</p><p>"I?  At Brussels." 
</p><p>"How terrible!" he echoed. <pb n="5"/>  
</p><p>"Yes."  Her eyes filled with tears.  "I had such kind friends 
there." 
</p><p>"Ah, of course.  Naturally." 
</p><p>She poured the tea and pushed his cup to him.  The haughty 
girl reappeared with sodden crumpets, which looked to him like 
manna steeped in nectar.  He tossed off his tea as if it had been 
champagne, and courage began to flow through his veins.  Never 
would he desert the simple creature who had trusted him!  Let no 
one tell him that an able-bodied man with brains and education 
could not earn enough in a city of this size to support himself and 
this poor sparrow. 
</p><p>The sparrow had emptied her cup, too, and a soft pink suffused 
her cheeks, effacing the wrinkles, which had perhaps been only 
lines of worry.  He began to wonder if after all she was much more 
than forty.  Rather absurd for a man of his age to have been 
calling a woman of forty an old lady! 
</p><p>Suddenly he saw that the sense of security, combined with the 
hot tea and the crumpets, was beginning to act on her famished 
system like a dangerous intoxicant, and that she was going to tell 
him everything&mdash;or nearly everything.  She bent forward, her elbows 
on the table, the cotton gloves drawn off her thin hands, which 
were nervously clenched under her chin.  He noticed a large 
sapphire on one of them. 
</p><p>"I can't tell you&mdash;I can't tell you how happy I am!" she 
faltered with swimming eyes. 
</p><p>He remained silent, through sheer embarrassment, and she went 
on: "You see, I'd so completely lost hope&mdash;so completely.  I 
thought no one would ever want me.  They all told me at home that 
no one would&mdash;my nieces did, and everybody.  They taunted me with 
it."  She broke off and glanced at him appealingly.  "You do 
understand English, don't you?" 
</p><p>He assented, still more bewildered, and she went on: "Oh, then 
it's so much easier&mdash;then we can really talk!  No&mdash;our train 
doesn't leave for nearly two hours.  You don't mind my talking, do 
you?  You'll let me make a clean breast of it?  I must!" 
</p><p>She touched with a clawlike finger the narrow interval between 
her shoulders and added: "For weeks I've been simply suffocating 
with longing." 
</p><p>An uncomfortable redness rose in Charley Durand's forehead.  
With these foreign women you could never tell; his brief 
Continental experiences had taught him that.  After all, he was not 
a monster, and several ladies had already attempted to prove it to 
him.  There had been one adventure&mdash;on the way home to his hotel at 
Louvain, after dining with the curator of prehistoric antiquities&mdash; 
one adventure of which he could not think even now without feeling 
as if he were in a Turkish bath, with no marble slab to cool off 
on. 
</p><p>But this poor lady!  Of course he was mistaken.  He blushed 
anew at his mistake. 
</p><p>"They all laughed at me&mdash;jeered at me; Caroline and my nieces 
and all of them.  They said it was no use trying&mdash;they'd failed, 
and how was I going to succeed?  Even Caroline has failed 
hitherto&mdash;and she's so dreadfully determined.  And of course for a 
married woman it's always easier, isn't it?" 
</p><p>She appealed to him with anxious eyes, and his own sank behind 
his protecting spectacles.  Easier for a married woman!  After all, 
perhaps he hadn't been mistaken.  He had heard of course that in 
the highest society the laxity was even worse. 
</p><p>"It's true enough"&mdash;she seemed to be answering him&mdash;"that the 
young, good-looking women get everything away from us.  There's 
nothing new in that; they always have.  I don't know how they 
manage it; but I'm told they were on hand when the very first 
boatload of refugees arrived.  I understand the young Duchess of 
Bolchester and Lady Ivy Trantham were down at Folkestone with all 
the Trantham motors&mdash;and from that day to this, though we've all 
had our names down on the government list, not one of us&mdash;not one 
human being at Lingerfield&mdash;has had so much as an application from 
the committee. 
</p><p>"And when I couldn't stand it any longer, and said I was going 
up to town myself, to wait at the station and seize one of the poor 
things before any of those unscrupulous women had got him they said 
it was just like me to make a show of myself for nothing.  But, 
after all, you see Caroline sneaked off after me without saying 
anything, and was making a show of herself too.  And when I saw her 
she evidently hadn't succeeded, for she was running about all 
alone, looking as wild as she does on sales days at Harrod's.  
Caroline is very extravagant, and doesn't mind what she spends; but 
she never can make up her mind between bargains, and rushes about 
like a madwoman till it's too late.  But oh, how humiliating for 
her to go back to the hall without a single refugee!" 
</p><p>The speaker broke off with a faint laugh of triumph, and wiped 
away her tears. 
</p><p>Charley Durand sat speechless.  The crumpet had fallen from 
his fork and his tea was turning gray; but he was unconscious of 
such minor misfortunes. 
</p><p>"I don't&mdash;I don't understand," he began; but as he spoke he 
perceived that he did. 
</p><p>It was as clear as daylight; he and his companion had taken 
each other for refugees, and she was passionately pressing upon him 
the assistance he had been wondering how on earth he should manage 
to offer her! 
</p><p>"Of course you don't, I explain so badly.  They've always told 
me that," she answered eagerly.  "Fancy asking you if you'd brought 
your mattress, for instance&mdash;what you must have thought!  But the 
fact is I'd made up my mind you were going to be one of those poor 
old women in caps who take snuff and spill things, and who have 
always come away with nothing but their beds and a saucepan.  They 
all said at Lingerfield: 'If you get even a deaf old woman you're 
lucky.'  And so I arranged to give you&mdash;I mean her&mdash;one of the 
rooms in the postmistress' cottage, where I've put an old bedstead 
that the vicar's coachman's mother died in, but the mattress had to 
be burnt.  Whereas of course you're coming to me&mdash;to the cottage, 
I mean.  And I haven't even told you where it is or who I am!  Oh, 
dear, it's so stupid of me; but you see Kathleen and Agatha and my 
sister-in-law all said 'Of course poor Audrey'll never get 
anybody'; and I've had the room standing ready for three weeks all 
but the mattress&mdash;and even the vicar's wife had begun to joke about 
it with my brother.  Oh, my brother's Lord Beausedge&mdash;didn't I tell 
you?" 
</p><p>She paused, breathless, and then added with embarrassment: "I 
don't think I ever made such a long speech in my life." 
</p><p>He was sure she hadn't, for as she poured out her confession 
it had been borne in on him that he was listening 
</p><p>              <hi rend="italic">(Continued on Page 53)</hi> 
[illustration omitted] <pb n="53"/>  
</p><p>                      THE REFUGEES 
</p><p>             <hi rend="italic">(Continued from Page 5)</hi> 
not to a habitual battler but to the uncontrollable outburst of a 
shy woman grown inarticulate through want of listeners.  It was 
harrowing, the arrears of self-confession that one guessed behind 
her torrent of broken phrases. 
</p><p>"I can't tell you," she began again, as if she had perceived 
his sympathy, "the difference it's going to make for me at home&mdash;my 
bringing the first refugee; and its being&mdash;well, someone like you." 
</p><p>Her blushes deepened, and she lost herself again in the 
abasing sense of her inability to explain. 
</p><p>"Well, my name at any rate," she burst out, "is Audrey 
Rushworth; and I'm not married." 
</p><p>"Neither am I," said her guest, smiling. 
</p><p>American fashion, he was groping to produce a card.  It would 
really not be decent in him to keep up the pretense a moment 
longer, and here was an easy way to let her know of her mistake.  
He pushed the card toward her, and as he did so his eye fell on it 
and he saw, too late, that it was one of those he had rather 
fatuously had engraved in French for his Continental travels: 
 
</p><p>                     CHARLES DURAND 
</p><p>             PROFESSEUR DES LANGUES ROMANES 
</p><p>               A L'UNIVERSITE DE LA SALLE 
</p><p>      DOCTEUR DE LETTRES DE L'UNIVERSITE DE LOUVAIN 
 
</p><p>She scanned the inscription and raised a reverent glance to 
him.  <hi rend="italic">"Monsieur le Professeur?</hi>  I'd no idea!  Though I 
suppose I ought to have known at once.  Oh, I do hope," she cried, 
"you won't find Lingerfield too unbearably dull!"  She added as if 
it were wrung from her: "Some people think my nieces rather 
clever." 
</p><p>The professor of Romance languages sat fascinated by the 
consequences of his last blunder.  That card seemed to have been 
dealt out by the finger of Fate.  Supposing he went to Lingerfield 
with her&mdash;just to see what it was like? 
</p><p>He had always pined to see what an English countryseat was 
like; and Lingerfield was apparently important.  He shook off the 
mad notion with an effort.  "I'll drive with her to the station," 
he thought, "and just lose myself in the crowd.  That will be the 
easiest way of all." 
</p><p>"There are three of them&mdash;Agatha, Kathleen and Clio.  But 
you'll find us all hopelessly dull," he heard her repeating. 
</p><p>"I shall&mdash;I certainly shan't&mdash;I mean, of course, how could I?" 
he stammered. 
</p><p>It was so much like her own syntax that it appeared to satisfy 
her. 
</p><p>"No&mdash;I pay!" she cried, darting between him and the advancing 
waitress.  "Shall we walk?  It's only two steps."  And seeing him 
looking about for the vanished hansom: "Oh, I sent the luggage on 
at once by the cab driver.  You see, there's a good deal of it, and 
there's such a hideous rush at the booking office at this hour.  
He'll have given it to a porter&mdash;so please don't worry!" 
</p><p>Firm and elastic as a girl, she sprang through the doorway, 
while, limping silently at her side, he stared at the decisive fact 
that his luggage was once more out of his keeping. 
 
 
</p><p>                           III 
 
CHARLEY DURAND, his shaving glass told him, was forty-five, 
decidedly bald, with an awkward limp, scant-lashed blue eyes 
blinking behind gold spectacles, a brow that he believed to be 
thoughtful and a chin that he knew to be weak.  His height was 
medium, his figure sedentary, with the hollows and prominences all 
in the wrong places; and he wore ready-made clothes in protective 
colors, and square-toed boots with side elastics, and stammered 
whenever it was all-important to speak fluently. 
</p><p>But his Sister Mabel, who knew him better than the others, had 
once taken one of his cards and run a pen through the word 
"Languages," leaving simply "Professor of Romance"; and in his 
secret soul Charley Durand knew that she was right. 
</p><p>He had in truth a dramatic imagination without the power of 
expression.  Instead of writing novels he read them; instead of 
living adventures he dreamed them.  Being naturally modest he had 
long since discovered his limitations, and decided that all his 
imagination would ever do for him was to give him a greater freedom 
of judgment than his neighbors had.  Even that was something to be 
thankful for; but now he began to ask himself if it was enough. 
</p><p>Professor Durand had read L'Abbesse de Jouarre and knew that 
in moments of extreme social peril superior persons often felt 
themselves justified in casting conventional morality to the winds.  
He had no thought of proceeding to such extremes; but he did wonder 
if, at the hour when civilization was shaken to its base, he, 
Charley Durand, might not at last permit himself forty-eight hours 
of romance. 
</p><p>His audacity was fortified by the fact that his luggage was 
out of his control, for he could hardly picture any situation more 
subversive than that of being separated from his toothbrush and his 
reading glasses.  But the difficulty of explaining himself if he 
went any farther in the adventure loomed larger as they approached 
the station; and as they crossed its crowded threshold, and Miss 
Rushworth said "Now we'll see about your things," he saw a fresh 
possibility of escape and cried out: "No, no!  Please find places.  
I'll look for my luggage." 
</p><p>He felt on his arm the same inexorable grasp that had steered 
him through the labyrinth of Charing Cross. 
</p><p>"You're quite right.  We'll get our seats first; in such a 
crowd it's safer!" she answered gayly, and guided him toward a 
second-class compartment.  He had always heard the aristocracy 
traveled second class in England.  "Besides," she continued as she 
pounced on two window seats, "the baggage is sure to be in the van 
already.  Or if it isn't you'd never find it.  All the refugees in 
England seem to be traveling by this train!" 
</p><p>They did indeed&mdash;and how tell her that there was one less in 
the number than she imagined?  A new difficulty had only just 
occurred to him.  It was easy enough to explain to her that she had 
been mistaken; but if he did, how justify the hours he had already 
spent in her company?  Could he tell the sister of Lord Beausedge 
that he had taken her for a refugee?  The statement would seem too 
preposterous. 
</p><p>Desperation nerved him to unconsidered action.  The train was 
not leaving yet&mdash;there was still time for the confession. 
</p><p>He scrambled to the seat opposite his captor's and rashly 
spoke: "I ought to tell you&mdash;I must apologize&mdash;apologize abjectly&mdash; 
for not explaining sooner&mdash;" 
</p><p>Miss Rushworth turned pale, and leaning forward caught his 
wrist in her thin claws. 
</p><p>"Ah, don't go on!" she gasped. 
</p><p>He lost his last hold on self-possession. 
</p><p>"Not go on?" 
</p><p>"Don't you suppose I know?  Didn't you guess that I knew all 
along?" 
</p><p>He paled, too, and then crimsoned, all his old suspicions 
rushing back on him. 
</p><p>"How could I not," she pursued, "when I saw all those heaps of 
luggage?  Of course I knew at once you were rich, and didn't 
need,"&mdash;but her wistful eyes were wet&mdash;"need anything I could do 
for you.  But you looked so lonely, and your lameness, and the 
moral anguish.  I don't see, after all, why we should open our 
houses only to pauper refugees; and anyhow it's not my fault, is 
it, if the committee simply wouldn't send me any?" 
</p><p>"But&mdash;but&mdash;" he desperately began; and then all at once his 
stammer caught him, and an endless succession of b's issued from 
his helpless throat. 
</p><p>With exquisite tact Miss Rushworth smiled away his confusion. 
</p><p>"I won't listen to another word; not one!  Oh, duck your head, 
quick!" she shrieked in another voice, flattening herself back into 
her corner. 
</p><p>Durand recognized the same note of terror with which she had 
hailed her sister-in-law's approach at Charing Cross.  It was 
needless for her to add faintly: "Caroline." 
</p><p>As she did so a plumed and determined head surged up into the 
window frame and an astonished voice exclaimed: "Audrey!" 
</p><p>A moment later four ladies, a maid laden with parcels and two 
bushy Chow dogs had possessed themselves of all that remained of 
the compartment; and Durand as he squeezed himself into his corner 
was feeling the sudden relief that comes with the cessation of 
virtuous effort.  He had seen at a glance that there was nothing 
more to be done. 
</p><p>The young ladies with Lady Beausedge were visibly her 
daughters.  They were of graduated heights, beginning with a very 
tall one; and were all thin, conspicuous and queerly dressed, 
suggesting to the bewildered professor bad copies of originals he 
had never seen.  None of them took any notice of him, and the dogs 
after smelling his ankles contemptuously followed their example. 
</p><p>It would indeed have been difficult during the first moments 
for any personality less masterful than Lady Beausedge's to assert 
itself in her presence.  So prevalent was she that Durand found 
himself viewing her daughters, dogs and attendant as her mere 
fringes and attributes, and thinking with terror "She's going to 
choose the seat next to me," when in reality is was only the 
youngest and thinnest of the girls who was settling herself at his 
side with a play of parcels as sharp as elbows. 
</p><p>Lady Beausedge was already assailing her sister-in-law: 
</p><p>"I'd no idea you meant to run up to town to-day, Audrey.  You 
said nothing of it when you dined with us last night." 
</p><p>Miss Rushworth's eyes fluttered apprehensively from Lady 
Beausedge's awful countenance to the timorous face of the professor 
of Romance languages, who had bought a newspaper and was deep in 
its inner pages. 
</p><p>"Neither did you, Caroline&mdash;" Miss Rushworth began with 
unexpected energy; and the thin girl next to Durand laughed. 
</p><p>"Neither did I what?  What are you laughing at, Clio?" 
</p><p>"Neither did you say you were coming up to town, mother." 
</p><p>Lady Beausedge glared, and the other girls giggled.  Even the 
maid stooped over the dogs to conceal an appreciative smile.  It 
was evident that baiting Lady Beausedge was a popular if dangerous 
amusement. 
</p><p>"As it happens," said the lady of Lingerfield, "the committee 
telephoned only this morning." 
</p><p>Miss Rushworth's eyes brightened.  She grew almost arch.  
"Ah&mdash;then you came up about refugees?" 
</p><p>"Naturally."  Lady Beausedge shook out her boa and opened the 
Pall Mall Gazette. 
</p><p>"Such a fight!" groaned the tallest girl, who was also the 
largest, vividest and most expensively dressed. 
</p><p>"Yes; it was hardly worth while.  Anything so grotesquely 
mismanaged!" 
</p><p>The young lady called Clio remarked in a quiet undertone: 
"Five people and two dogs to fetch down one old woman with a pipe." 
</p><p>"Ah, you have got one?" murmured Miss Rushworth, with what 
seemed to the absorbed Durand a fiendish simulation of envy. 
</p><p>"Yes," her sister-in-law grudgingly admitted.  "But, as Clio 
says, it's almost an insult to have dragged us all up to town.  
They'd promised us a large family, with a prima donna from the 
Brussels Opera&mdash;so useful for Agatha's music; and two orphans 
besides.  I suppose Ivy Trantham got them all, as usual."  She 
paused, and added more condescendingly: "After all, Audrey, you 
were right not to try to do anything through the committee." 
</p><p>"Yes; I think one does better without," Miss Rushworth replied 
with extreme gentleness. 
</p><p>"One does better without refugees, you mean?  I dare say we 
shall find it so.  I've no doubt the Bidchester set has taken all 
but the utterly impossible ones." 
</p><p>"Not all," said Miss Rushworth. 
</p><p>Something in her tone caused her nieces to exchange an 
astonished glance and Lady Beausedge to rear her head from the Pall 
Mall Gazette. 
</p><p>"Not all," repeated Miss Rushworth. 
</p><p>The eldest girls broke into an excited laugh.  "Aunt Audrey&mdash; 
you don't mean you've got an old woman with a pipe too?" 
</p><p>"No.  Not an old woman."  She paused and waved her hand in 
Durand's direction.  <hi rend="italic">"Monsieur le Professeur Durand, de 
l'Universite de Louvain</hi>&mdash;my sister-in-law, my nieces.  He 
speaks English," she added in a whisper. 
 
 
</p><p>                           IV 
 
CHARLEY DURAND'S window was very low and wide, and quaintly 
trellised.  There was no mistaking it, it was a "lattice"&mdash;a real 
one, with old bluish panes set in sturdy black moldings, not the 
stage variety made of plate glass and papier-mache that he had seen 
in the sham cottage of aesthetic suburbs at home. 
</p><p>When he pushed it open a great branch of yellow roses brushed 
his face, and a 
</p><p>          <hi rend="italic">(Continued on Page 57)</hi> <pb n="57"/>  
</p><p>             <hi rend="italic">(Continued from Page 53)</hi> 
dewy clematis gazed in at him with purple eyes.  Below lay a 
garden, incredibly velvety, flower-filled, and inclosed in yew 
hedges so high that it seemed, under the low twilight sky, as 
intimate and shut in as Miss Rushworth's low-ceilinged drawing-room, which, in its turn, was as open to the air and as full of 
flowers as the garden. 
</p><p>But all England, that afternoon, as his train traversed it, 
had seemed like some great rich garden roofed in from storm and 
dust and disorder.  What a wonderful place, and what a miracle to 
have been thus carried into the very heart of it!  All his scruples 
vanished in the enchantment of this first encounter with the 
English country. 
</p><p>When he had bathed and dressed and descended the black-oak 
stairs he found his hostess waiting in the garden.  She was 
hatless, with a pale scarf over her head, and a pink spot of 
excitement on each withered cheek. 
</p><p>"I should have preferred a quiet evening here; but since 
Caroline made such a point of our dining at the hall&mdash;" she began. 
</p><p>"Of course, of course!  It's all so lovely," said her guest 
recklessly.  He would have dined at Windsor Castle with composure.  
After the compact and quintessential magic of the cottage nothing 
could surprise or overwhelm him. 
</p><p>They left the garden by a dark-green door in a wall of old 
peach-colored brick, and walked in the deepening twilight across a 
field and over a stile.  A stile!  He remembered pictures and 
ballads about helping girls over stiles, and lowered his eyes 
respectfully as Miss Rushworth's hand rested on his in the descent. 
</p><p>The next moment they were in the spacious shade of a sort of 
Forest of Arden, with great groups of bossy trees standing apart, 
and deer flashing by at the end of ferny glades. 
</p><p>"Is it&mdash;are we&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Oh, yes.  This is Lingerfield.  The cottage is on the edge of 
the park.  It's not a long walk if we go by the chapel and through 
the cloisters." 
</p><p>The very words oppressed him with their too-crowding 
suggestions.  There was a chapel in the park&mdash;there were cloisters!  
Lingerfield had an ecclesiastical past&mdash;had been an abbey, no 
doubt.  But even such associations paled in the light of the 
reality.  As they came out of the shadow of the trees they 
recovered a last glow of daylight.  In it lay a gray chapel 
delicately laced and pinnacled; and beyond the chapel the arcade of 
the cloister, a lawn with one domed cedar, and a gabled Tudor 
house, its bricks still rosy in the dusk, and a gleam of sunset 
caught in its many-windowed front. 
</p><p>"How&mdash;how long the daylight lasts in England!" said Professor 
Durand, choking with emotion. 
</p><p>The drawing-room into which he had followed Miss Rushworth 
seemed full of people and full of silence.  Professor Durand had 
never had on a social occasion such an impression of effortless 
quiet.  The ladies about the big stone chimney and between the 
lamplit tables, if they had not been so discordantly modern in 
dress and attitude, might have been a part of the shadowy past. 
</p><p>Only Lady Beausedge, strongly corseted, many-necklaced, her 
boa standing out from her bare shoulders like an Elizabethan ruff, 
seemed to Durand majestic enough for her background.  She suggested 
a composite image of Bloody Mary and the late Queen. 
</p><p>He was just recovering from the exchange of silences that had 
greeted his entrance when he discovered another figure worthy of 
the scene.  It was Lord Beausedge, standing in the window and 
glancing disgustedly over the evening paper. 
</p><p>Lord Beausedge was as much in character as his wife; only he 
belonged to a later period.  He suggested stocks and nankeen 
trousers, a Lawrence portrait, port wine, fox-hunting, the 
Peninsular War, the Indian Mutiny, every Englishman doing his duty, 
and resistance to the Reform Bill.  It was portentous that one 
person, wearing modern clothes and reading a newspaper, should so 
epitomize a vanished age. 
</p><p>He made a step or two toward his guest, took him for granted, 
and returned to the newspaper. 
</p><p>"Why&mdash;why do we all fidget so at home?" Professor Durand 
wondered vaguely. 
</p><p>"Gwen and Ivy are always late," said Lady Beausedge, as though 
answering a silence. 
</p><p>Miss Rushworth looked agitated. 
</p><p>"Are they coming from Trantham?" she asked. 
</p><p>"Not him.  Only Gwen and Ivy.  Agatha telephoned, and Gwen 
asked if they might." 
</p><p>After that everyone sat silent again for a long time without 
any air of impatience or surprise.  Durand had the feeling that 
they all&mdash;except perhaps Lord Beausedge&mdash;had a great deal to say to 
him, but that it would be very slow in coming to the surface.  
Well&mdash;so much the better; time was no consideration, and he was 
glad not to crowd his sensations. 
</p><p>"Do you know the duchess?" asked Lady Beausedge suddenly. 
</p><p>"The duchess?" 
</p><p>"Gwen Rochester.  She's coming.  She wants to see you. 
</p><p>"To see me?" 
</p><p>"When Agatha telephoned that you were here she chucked a 
dinner somewhere else, and she's rushing over from Trantham with 
her sister-in-law. 
</p><p>Durand looked helplessly at Miss Rushworth and saw that her 
cheeks were pink with triumph.  The Duchess of Bolchester was 
coming to see her refugee! 
</p><p>"Do people here just chuck dinners like that?" he asked with 
a faint facetiousness. 
</p><p>"When they want to," said Lady Beausedge simply.  The 
conversation again came to a natural end. 
</p><p>It revived with feverish vivacity on the entrance of two tall 
and emaciated young women, who drifted in after Lord Beausedge had 
decided to ring for dinner, and who wasted none of their volubility 
in excusing their late arrival. 
</p><p>These apparitions, who had a kind of limp loveliness totally 
unknown to the professor of Romance languages, he guessed to be the 
Duchess of Bolchester and Lady Ivy Trantham, the most successful 
refugee raiders of the district.  They were dressed in pale frail 
garments and hung with barbaric beads and bangles, and as soon as 
he saw them he understood why he had thought the daughters of the 
house looked like bad copies&mdash;all except the youngest, whom he was 
beginning to single out from her sisters. 
</p><p>He was not sure whether, during the rapid murmur of talk that 
followed, someone breathed his name to the newcomers; but certainly 
no one told him which of the two ladies was which; or indeed made 
any effort to draw him into the conversation.  It was only when the 
slightly less tall addressed the taller one as Gwen that he 
remembered this name was that of the duchess. 
</p><p>She had swept him with a smiling glance of her large, sweet, 
vacant eyes, and he had the impression that she, too, had things to 
say to him, but that the least strain on her attention was too 
great an effort, and that each time she was about to remember who 
he was something else distracted her. 
</p><p>The thought that a duchess had chucked a dinner to see him had 
made him slightly giddy; and the humiliation of finding that once 
they were confronted she had forgotten what she had come for was 
painful even to his disciplined humility. 
</p><p>But Professor Durand was not without his modest perspicacity, 
and little by little he began to guess that this absence of 
concentration and insistence was part of a sort of leisurely 
holiday spirit unlike anything he had ever known.  Under the low-voiced volubility and restless animation of these young women&mdash;whom 
the daughters of the house intensely imitated&mdash;he felt a great 
central inattention.  Their strenuousness was not fatiguing because 
it did not insist but blew about like thistledown from topic to 
topic.  He saw that his safety lay in this fact, and reassurance 
began to steal over him as he understood that the last danger he 
was exposed to was that of being too closely interrogated. 
</p><p>"If I'm an impostor," he thought, "at least no one here will 
find it out." 
</p><p>And then just as he had drawn this sage conclusion, he felt 
the sudden pounce of the duchess' eye.  Dinner was over and the 
party had regrouped itself in a great book-paneled room, before the 
carved chimney piece of which she stood lighting her cigarette like 
a duchess on the cover of a novel. 
</p><p>"You know I'm going to carry you off presently," she said 
gayly. 
</p><p>Miss Audrey Rushworth was sitting in a sofa corner beside her 
youngest niece, whom she evidently found less intimidating than the 
others.  Durand instinctively glancing toward them saw the elder 
lady turn pale, while Miss Clio Rushworth's swinging foot seemed to 
twinkle with malice. 
</p><p>He bowed as he supposed one ought to bow when addressed by a 
duchess. 
</p><p>"Off for a talk?" he hazarded playfully. 
</p><p>"Off to Trantham.  Didn't they tell you?  I'm giving a big 
garden party for the Refugee Relief Fund, and I'm looking for 
somebody to give us a lecture on Atrocities.  That's what I came 
for," she added ingenuously. 
</p><p>There was a profound silence, which Lord Beausedge, lifting 
his head from the Times, suddenly broke. 
</p><p>"Damn bad taste, all that sort of thing," he remarked, and 
continued his reading. 
</p><p>"But Gwen, dear," Miss Rushworth faltered, "your garden party 
isn't till the nineteenth." 
</p><p>The duchess looked surprised.  She evidently had no head for 
dates. 
</p><p>"Isn't it, Aunt Audrey?  Well, it doesn't matter, does it?  I 
want him all the same.  We want him awfully, Ivy, don't we?"  She 
shone on Durand.  "You'll see such lots of your own people at 
Trantham.  The Belgian Minister and the French Ambassador are 
coming down for the lecture.  You'll feel less lonely there." 
</p><p>Lady Beausedge intervened with authority: "I think I have a 
prior claim, my dear Gwen.  Of course Audrey was not expecting 
anyone&mdash;anyone like Professor Durand; and at the cottage he might&mdash; 
he might&mdash;but here, with your uncle, and the girls all speaking 
French&mdash;"  She turned to Durand with a hospitable smile. 
</p><p>"Your room's quite ready; and of course my husband will be 
delighted if you like to use the library to prepare your lecture 
in.  We'll send the governess cart for your traps to-morrow."  She 
fixed her firm eyes on the duchess.  "You see, dear, it was all 
quite settled." 
</p><p>Lady Ivy Trantham spoke up: "It is not a bit of use, Aunt 
Carrie.  Gwen can't give him up."  Being apparently unable to 
master the professor's name the sisters-in-law continued to 
designate him by the personal pronoun.  "The committee has given us 
a prima donna from the Brussels Opera to sing the Marseillaise and 
the what-ye-may-call-it Belgian anthem, but there are lots of 
people coming just for the Atrocities." 
</p><p>"Oh, we must have the Atrocities!" the duchess echoed.  She 
looked musingly at Durand's pink, troubled face.  "He'll do them 
awfully well," she concluded, talking about him as if he were deaf. 
</p><p>"We must have somebody who's accustomed to lecturing.  People 
won't put up with amateurs," Lady Ivy reenforced her. 
</p><p>Lady Beausedge's countenance was dark with rage. 
</p><p>"A prima donna from the Brussels Opera!  But the committee 
telephoned me this morning to come up and meet a prima donna!  It's 
all a mistake her being at Trantham, Gwen!" 
</p><p>"Well," said the duchess serenely.  "I dare say it's all a 
mistake his being here."  She looked more and more tenderly on the 
professor. 
</p><p>"But he's not here: he's with me at the cottage!" cried Miss 
Rushworth, springing up with sudden resolution.  "It's too absurd 
and undignified, this&mdash;this squabbling." 
</p><p>"Yes; don't let's squabble.  Come along," said the duchess, 
slipping her long arm through Durand's as Miss Rushworth's had been 
slipped through it at Charing Cross. 
</p><p>The subject of this flattering but agitating discussion had 
been struggling ever since it began, with a nervous contraction of 
the throat.  When at length his lips opened only a torrent of 
consonants rushed from them, finally followed by the cryptic 
monosyllables: "I'm not!" 
</p><p>"Not a professional?  Oh, but you're a professor&mdash;that'll do!" 
cried Lady Ivy Trantham briskly, while the duchess, hugging his arm 
closer, added in a voice of persuasion: "You see, we've got one at 
Trantham already, and we're so awfully afraid of him that we want 
you to come and talk to him.  You must." 
</p><p>"I mean, n-n-not a r-r-ref&mdash;" gasped out the desperate Durand. 
</p><p>Suddenly he felt his other arm caught by Miss Clio Rushworth, 
who gave it a deep and eloquent pinch.  At the same time their eyes 
met, and he read in hers entreaty, command and the passionate 
injunction to follow her lead. 
</p><p>"Poor Professor Durand&mdash;you'll take us for red Indians on the 
war trail!  Come to the dining room with me and I'll give you a 
glass of champagne.  I saw the curry was too strong for you," this 
young lady insinuatingly declared. 
</p><p>Durand with one of his rare flashes of self-possession had 
converted his stammer into a strangling cough, and released by the 
duchess made haste to follow his rescuer out of the room.  He kept 
up his racking cough while they crossed the hall, and by the time 
they reached the dining room tears of congestion were running down 
behind his spectacles, and he sank into a chair and rested his 
elbows despairingly on a corner of the great mahogany table. 
</p><p>Miss Clio Rushworth disappeared behind a tall screen and 
returned with a glass of champagne.  "Anything in it?" she inquired 
pleasantly, and smiled at his doleful gesture of negation. 
</p><p>He emptied his glass and cleared his throat; but before he 
could speak she held up a silencing hand. 
</p><p>"Don't&mdash;don't!" she said. 
</p><p>He was startled by this odd echo of her aunt's entreaty, and 
a little tired of being hurled from one cryptic injunction to 
another. 
</p><p>"Don't what?" he questioned sharply. 
</p><p>"Make a clean breast of it.  Not yet.  Pretend you are, just 
a little longer, please." 
</p><p>"Pretend I am&mdash;" 
</p><p>"A refugee."  She sat down opposite him, her sharp chin 
supported on crossed hands.  "I'll tell you why." 
</p><p>But Professor Durand was not listening.  A momentary rapture 
of relief at being found out had been succeeded by a sick dread of 
the consequences.  He tried to read the girl's thin ironic face, 
but her eyes and smile were inscrutable. 
</p><p>"Miss Rushworth, at least let me tell you&mdash;" 
</p><p>She shook her head kindly but firmly.  "That you're not a 
German spy in disguise?  Bless you, don't you suppose I can guess 
what's happened?  I saw it the moment we got into the railway 
carriage.  I suppose you came over from Boulogne in the refugee 
train, and when poor dear Aunt Audrey pounced on you you began to 
stammer and couldn't explain." 
</p><p>Oh, the blessed balm of her understanding!  He drew a deep 
breath of gratitude, and faltered, smiling back at her smile: "It 
was worse than that.  Much worse.  I took her for a refugee too.  
We rescued each other!" 
</p><p>A peal of youthful mirth shook the mighty rafters of the 
Lingerfield dining room.  Miss Clio Rushworth buried her face and 
sobbed. 
</p><p>"Oh, I see&mdash;I see&mdash;I see it all!" 
</p><p>"No you don't&mdash;not quite&mdash;not yet!" he gurgled back at her. 
</p><p>"Tell me then; tell me everything!" 
</p><p>And he told her; told her quietly, succinctly and without a 
stammer, because under her cool kindly gaze he felt himself at last 
in an atmosphere of boundless comprehension. 
</p><p>"You see, the adventure fascinated me; I won't deny that," he 
ended, laying bare the last fold of his duplicity. 
</p><p>This, for the first time, seemed to stagger her. 
</p><p>"The adventure&mdash;an adventure with Aunt Audrey?" 
</p><p>They smiled at each other a little.  "I meant, the adventure 
of England&mdash;I've never been in England before&mdash;and of a baronial 
hall.  It is baronial?  In short, of just exactly what's been 
happening to me.  The novelty, you see&mdash;but how should you see?&mdash; 
was irresistible.  The novelty, and all the old historic 
associations.  England's in our blood, after all."  He looked about 
him at the big, dusky, tapestried room.  "Fancy having seen this 
kind of thing only on the stage!  Yes, I was drawn on by 
everything&mdash;by everything I saw and heard from the moment I set 
foot in London.  Of course if I hadn't been I should have found an 
opportunity of explaining; or I could have bolted away from her at 
the station." 
</p><p>"I'm so glad you didn't.  That's what I'm coming to," said the 
girl.  "You see, it's been&mdash;how shall I explain?&mdash;more than an 
adventure for Aunt Audrey.  It's literally the first thing that's 
ever happened to her." 
</p><p>Professor Durand blushed to the roots of his hair. 
</p><p>"I don't understand," he said feebly. 
</p><p>"No.  Of course not.  Any more, I suppose, than I really 
understand what Lingerfield represents to an American.  And you 
would have had to live at Lingerfield for generations and 
generations to understand Aunt Audrey.  You see, nothing much ever 
happened to the unmarried women of her time.  Most of them were 
just 
</p><p>          <hi rend="italic">(Concluded on Page 61)</hi> <pb n="61"/>  
</p><p>             <hi rend="italic">(Concluded from Page 57)</hi> 
put away in cottages covered with clematis and forgotten.  Aunt 
Audrey has always been forgotten&mdash;even the refugee committee forgot 
her.  And my father and mother, and her other brothers and sisters, 
and my sisters and I&mdash;I'm afraid we've always forgotten her too." 
</p><p>"Not you," said Professor Durand with sudden temerity. 
</p><p>Miss Clio Rushworth smiled.  "I'm very fond of her: and then 
I've been a little bit forgotten myself."  She paused a moment and 
continued: "All this would take too long to explain.  But what I 
want to beg of you is this&mdash;let her have her adventure, give her 
her innings, keep up the pretense a little longer.  None of the 
others have guessed, and I promise to get you away safely before 
they do.  Just let Aunt Audrey have her refugee for a bit, and 
triumph over Lingerfield and Trantham. . . .  The duchess?  Oh, 
I'll arrange that too.  Slip back to the cottage now&mdash;this way, 
across the lawn, by the chapel&mdash;and I'll say your cough was so 
troublesome that you rushed back to put on a mustard plaster.  I'll 
tell Gwen you'll be delighted to give the lecture&mdash;" 
</p><p>Durand raised his hands in protest but she went on gayly: 
"Why, don't you see that the more you hold out the more she'll want 
you?  Whereas if you accept at once and even let her think you're 
going over to stop at Trantham as soon as your cough is better 
she'll forget she's ever asked you. . . .  Insincere, you say?  
Yes, of course; a little.  But have you considered what would have 
happened if you hadn't choked just now and had succeeded in 
shouting out that you were an impostor?" 
</p><p>A cold chill ran down Charley Durand's spine as his masterful 
adviser set forth this forgotten aspect of the case. 
</p><p>"Yes&mdash;I do see.  I see it's for the best." 
</p><p>"Well&mdash;rather!"  She pushed him toward a window opening on the 
lawn.  "Be off now&mdash;and do play up, won't you?  I'll promise to 
stick by you and see you out of it if only you'll do as I ask." 
</p><p>Their hands met in a merry grasp of complicity, and as he fled 
away through the moonlight he carried with him the vision of her 
ugly vivid face and wondered how such a girl could ever think she 
could be forgotten. 
 
 
</p><p>                            V 
 
A GOOD many things had happened before he stood again on the pier 
at Boulogne. 
</p><p>It was in April, 1918, and he was buttoned into a too-tight 
uniform, on which he secretly hoped the Y. M. C. A. initials were 
not always the first things to strike the eye of the admiring 
spectator. 
</p><p>It was not that he was ungrateful to the great organization 
which had found a task for him in its ranks; but that he could 
never quite console himself for the accident of having been born a 
few years too soon to be wearing the real uniform of his country.  
That would indeed have been romance beyond his dreams; but he had 
long ago discovered that he was never to get beyond the second-best 
in such matters.  None of his adventures would ever be written with 
a capital. 
</p><p>Still, he was very content; and never more so than now that he 
was actually in France again, in touch and in sound of the mighty 
struggle that had once been more than his nerves could bear, but 
that they could bear now with perfect serenity because he and his 
country, for all they were individually worth, had a stake in the 
affair and were no longer mere sentimental spectators. 
</p><p>The scene, novel as it was because of the throngs of English 
and American troops that animated it, was still in some of its 
details pathetically familiar.  For the German advance in the north 
had set in movement the native populations of that region, and 
among the fugitives some forlorn groups had reached Boulogne and 
were gathered on the pier, much as he had seen them four years 
earlier.  Only in this case they were in dozens instead of 
hundreds, and the sight of them was harrowing more because of what 
they symbolized than from their actual numbers. 
</p><p>Professor Durand was no more in quest of refugees than he had 
been formerly.  He had been dispatched to Boulogne to look after 
the library of a Y. M. C. A. canteen, and was standing on the pier 
looking vaguely about him for a guide with the familiar initials on 
his collar. 
</p><p>In the general confusion, he could discover no one who took 
the least interest in his problem, and he was waiting resignedly in 
the sheltered angle formed by two stacks of packing cases when he 
suddenly remembered that he had always known the face he was 
looking at was not one to forget. 
</p><p>It was that of a dark thin girl in khaki, with a slouch hat 
and leggings, and her own unintelligible initials on her shoulder, 
who was giving firm directions to a large orderly in a British Army 
motor. 
</p><p>As Durand looked at her she looked at him.  Their eyes met, 
and she burst out laughing. 
</p><p>"Well, you do have the queerest-looking tunics in your army!" 
she exclaimed as their hands clasped. 
</p><p>"I know we do&mdash;and I'm too fat.  But you knew me?" the 
professor cried triumphantly. 
</p><p>"Why, of course!  I should know your spectacles anywhere," 
said Miss Clio Rushworth gayly.  She finished what she was saying 
to the orderly, and then came back to the professor. 
</p><p>"What a lark!  What are you?  Oh, Y. M. C. A., of course.  
With the British, I suppose?"  They perched on the boxes and 
exchanged confidences, while Durand inwardly hoped that the man who 
ought to be looking for him was otherwise engaged. 
</p><p>Apparently he was, for their talk continued to ramble on 
through a happy labyrinth of reminiscences spangled with laughter. 
</p><p>"And when they found out&mdash;weren't they too awfully horrified?" 
he asked at last, blushing at the mere remembrance. 
</p><p>She shook her head with a smile.  "They never did&mdash;nobody 
found out but father, and he laughed for a week.  I wouldn't have 
had anyone else know for the world.  It would have spoiled all Aunt 
Audrey's fun if Lingerfield had known you weren't a refugee.  To 
this day you're her great adventure." 
</p><p>"But how did you manage it?  I don't see yet." 
</p><p>"Come round to our canteen to-night and I'll tell you." 
</p><p>She stood up and shoved her cigarette case into the pocket of 
the tunic that fitted so much better than his. 
</p><p>"I tell you what&mdash;as your man hasn't turned up come over to 
the canteen now and see Aunt Audrey." 
</p><p>Professor Durand paled in an unmartial manner. 
</p><p>"Oh, is Miss Rushworth here?" 
</p><p>"Rather!  She's my chief.  Come along." 
</p><p>"Your chief?  He wavered again, his heart failing him. 
</p><p>"Really&mdash;won't it be better for me not to?  Suppose&mdash;suppose 
she should remember me?" 
</p><p>Miss Rushworth's niece laughed.  "I don't believe she will, 
she's so blind.  Besides, what if she did?  She's seen a good many 
refugees since your day.  You see, they've become rather a drug on 
the market, poor dears.  And Aunt Audrey's got her head full of 
other things now." 
</p><p>She had started off at her long swift stride, and he was 
hurrying obediently after her. 
</p><p>The big brown canteen was crowded with soldiers who were being 
variously refreshed by young ladies in trig khaki.  At the other 
end of the main room Miss Clio Rushworth turned a corner and 
entered an office.  Durand followed her. 
</p><p>At the office desk sat a lady with eye-glasses on a sharp 
nose.  She wore a colonel's uniform, with several decorations, and 
was bending over the desk busily writing. 
</p><p>A young girl in a nurse's dress stood beside her, as if 
waiting for an order, and flattened against the wall of the room 
sat a row of limp, disheveled, desolate beings&mdash;too evidently 
refugees. 
</p><p>The colonel lifted her head quickly and glanced at her niece 
with a resolute and almost forbidding eye. 
</p><p>"Not another refugee, Clio&mdash;not one!  I absolutely refuse.  
We've not a hole left to put them in, and the last family you sent 
me went off with my mackintosh and my electric lamp." 
</p><p>She bent again sternly to her writing.  As she looked up her 
glance strayed carelessly over Professor Durand's congested 
countenance, and then dropped to the desk without a sign of 
recognition. 
</p><p>"Oh, Aunt Audrey&mdash;not one, not just one?" the colonel's niece 
pleaded. 
</p><p>"It's no use, my dear.  Now don't interrupt, please. . . .  
Here are the bulletins, nurse." 
</p><p>Colonel Audrey Rushworth shut her lips with a snap and her pen 
drove on steadily over the sheets of official letter paper. 
 
</p><p>When Professor Durand and Clio Rushworth stood outside of the 
canteen again in the spring sunshine they looked long at each other 
without speaking. 
</p><p>Charley Durand, under his momentary sense of relief, was aware 
of a distinct humiliation. 
</p><p>"I see I needn't have been afraid!" he said, forcing an 
artificial laugh. 
</p><p>"I told you so.  The fact is, Aunt Audrey has a lot of other 
things to think about nowadays.  There's no danger of her being 
forgotten&mdash;it's she who does the forgetting now."  She laid a 
commiserating hand on his arm.  "I'm sorry&mdash;but you must excuse 
her.  She's just been promoted again and she's going to marry the 
Bishop of the Kamerun next month." </p>
 
</div1>
</body> 
 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
 
