<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaR1Ef"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>      
<TEI.2 id="WhaR1Ef"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"Ethan Frome." In: The Bigger Issues and Some Recent Books.</title>
<title type="sort">ethan frome in the bigger issues and some recent books</title>
<author>Wharton review: Cooper, Frederic Taber</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">6</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WhaR1Ef</idno> 
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476513</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>UVa ed. AP2.B78</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"Ethan Frome." In: The Bigger Issues and Some Recent Books.</title>
<title level="j">Bookman</title>
<title type="sort">ethan frome in the bigger issues and some recent books</title>
<author>Frederic Taber Cooper</author>
</titleStmt>  
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition.</p>
</editionStmt>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Dodd, Mead &amp;Company</publisher>  
<pubPlace>New York, N. Y.</pubPlace>  
<date value="1911">1911</date>
</publicationStmt>  
<seriesStmt>
<p>Bookman Vol. XXXIV. No. 3, November, 1911 p.312</p>
</seriesStmt>  
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>  
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>  
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>  
<p>Spell-check and verification made  
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p>  
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>  
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme   
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>  
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's  
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of   
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>  
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1911">1911</date>
</creation>  
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>  
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction</term>
<term>prose</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
</profileDesc>  
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-03">March 1996</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Deirdre A. Johnson, Electronic Text Center, University of  
Virginia</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added header and basic TEI markup</item>
</change>  
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>  
  
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2">  
<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="312" id="WhaR1Ef312"/>   



<p>It is hard to forgive Mrs. Wharton for the utter  
remorselessness of her latest volume, <hi rend="italic">Ethan Frome</hi>, for  
nowhere has she done anything more hopelessly, endlessly grey with  
blank despair.  Ethan Frome is a man whose ambitions long ago  
burned themselves out.  He early spent his vitality in the daily  
struggle of winning a bare sustenance from the grudging soil of a  
small New England farm.  An invalid wife, whose imaginary ailments  
thrived on patent medicines, doubled his burden.  And then, one  
day, a pretty young cousin, left destitute, came to live on the  
farm, and brought a breath of fragrance and gladness into the  
gloom.  Neither Ethan nor the cousin meant to do wrong; it was  
simply one of those unconscious, inevitable attachments, almost  
primitive in its intensity.  It never was even put into words,  
until the day when Ethan's wife, perhaps because of a smouldering  
jealousy, perhaps because the motive she gave was the true one,  
namely that the girl was shiftless and incompetent, sent her out  
into the world to shift for herself.  It is while driving her over  
to the railway station that Ethan consents to the girl's wish that  
just once more he will take her coasting down a long hill, that is  
a favourite coasting place throughout the neighbourhood.  It is a  
long, steep, breathless rush, with a giant tree towering up near  
the foot, to be dexterously avoided at the last moment.  It is  
while he holds the girl close to him on the sled, that a ghastly  
temptation comes to Ethan, and he voices it: How much easier,  
instead of letting her go away, to face unknown struggles, while he  
remained behind, eating his heart out with loneliness&mdash;how much  
easier merely to forget to steer!  One shock of impact, and the end  
would come.  And to this the girl consents.  And neither of them  
foresees that not even the most carefully planned death is  
inevitable, and that fate is about to play upon them one of its  
grimmest tricks, and doom them to a life-long punishment, she with  
a broken back, he with a warped and twisted frame, tied beyond  
escape to the slow starvation of the barren farm, and grudgingly  
watched over by the invalid wife, scarcely more alive than  
themselves.  Art for art's sake is the one justification of a piece  
of work as perfect in technique as it is relentless in substance.  
</p>  
  
</div1>  
</body>  
</text>  
</TEI.2>
