<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaSeed"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="WhaSeed">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Seed of the Faith.</title>
<title type="sort">seed of the faith</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp> 
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">78</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">WhaSeed</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476527</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>"Cadi" changed to to "Caid" in line 3 of paragraph 14 on page 32.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Seed of the Faith</title>
<title type="sort">seed of the faith</title>
<author>Edith Wharton</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner's Magazine</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1919">1919</date>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Verification made against printed text.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme 
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of 
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl> 
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1919">1919</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-06">June 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Moulton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>TEI tagging</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2">
 
<div1 type="section" n="1" id="d3"> <head>
Wharton, Edith.  "The Seed of the Faith."  <lb/> 
<hi rend="italic"> Scribner's Magazine</hi> 65 (Jan. 1919): 17-33.<lb/>                           I</head> 
 
 
 
<pb n="17"/>  
 
 
 
 
<p>THE blinding June sky of Africa hung over the town.  In the 
doorway 
of an Arab coffee-house a young man stood listening to the 
remarks 
exchanged by the patrons of the establishment, who lay in torpid 
heaps on the low shelf bordering the room.</p><p> 
     The young man's caftan was faded to a dingy brown, but the 
muslin garment covering it was clean, and so was the turban wound 
about his shabby fez.</p><p> 
     Cleanliness was not the most marked characteristic of the 
conversation, to which he lent a listless ear.  It was no 
prurient 
curiosity that fixed his attention on this placid exchange of 
obscenities; he had lived too long in Morocco for obscenities not 
to have lost their savor.  But he had never quite overcome the 
fascinated disgust with which he listened, nor the hope that one 
among the talkers would suddenly reveal some sense of a higher 
ideal of what, at home, the earnest women he knew used solemnly 
to 
call a Purpose.  He was sure that, some day, such a sign would 
come, and then&mdash;</p><p> 
     Meanwhile, at that hour, there was nothing on earth to do in 
Eloued but to stand and listen. . .</p><p> 
     The bazaar was beginning to fill up.  Looking down the 
vaulted 
tunnel which led to the coffee-house the young man watched the 
thickening throng of shoppers and idlers.  The fat merchant whose 
shop faced the end of the tunnel had just ridden up and rolled 
off 
his mule, while his black boy unbarred the door of the niche hung 
with embroidered slippers where the master throned.  The young 
man 
in the faded caftan, watching the merchant scramble up and sink 
into his cushions, wondered for the thousandth time what he 
thought 
about all day in his dim stifling kennel, and what he did when he 
was away from it . . . for no length of residence in that dark 
land 
seemed to bring one nearer to finding out what the heathen 
thought 
and did when the eye of the Christian was off him.</p><p> 
     Suddenly a wave of excitement ran through the crowd.  Every 
head turned in the same direction, and even the camels bent their 
frowning faces and stretched their necks all one way, as animals 
do 
before a storm.  A wild hoot had penetrated the bazaar, howling 
through the long white tunnels and under the reed-woven roofs 
like 
a Djinn among dishonored graves.  The heart of the young man 
began 
to beat.</p><p> 
     "It sounds," he thought, "like a motor. . ."</p><p> 
     But a motor at Eloued!  There was one, every one knew, in 
the 
Sultan's Palace.  It had been brought there years ago by a 
foreign 
Ambassador, as a gift from his sovereign, and was variously 
reported to be made entirely of aluminum, platinum, or silver.  
But 
the parts had never been put together, the body had long been 
used 
for breeding silk-worms&mdash;a not wholly successful experiment&mdash;and 
the acetylene lamps adorned the Pasha's gardens on state 
occasions.  
As for the horn, it had been sent as a gift, with a choice 
panoply 
of arms, to the Caid of the Red Mountain; but as the india-rubber 
bulb had accidentally been left behind, it was certainly not the 
Caid's visit which the present discordant cries announced. . 
.</p><p> 
     "Hullo, you old dromedary!  How's the folks up-state?" cried 
a ringing voice; the awe-struck populace gave way, and a young 
man 
in linen duster and motor-cap, slipping under the interwoven 
necks 
of the astonished camels, strode down the tunnel with an air of 
authority and clapped a hand on the dreamer in the 
doorway.</p><p> 
     "Harry Spink!" the other gasped in a startled whisper, and 
with an intonation as un-African as his friend's.  At the same 
instant he glanced over his shoulder, and his mild lips formed a 
cautious "sh." <pb n="18"/> </p><p> 
     "Who'd you take me for&mdash;Gabby Delys?" asked the newcomer 
gayly; then, seeing that this topical allusion hung fire: "And 
what 
the dickens are you 'hushing' for, anyhow?  You don't suppose, do 
you, that anybody in the bazaar thinks you're a native?  
D'ye'ever 
look at your chin?  Or that Adam's apple running up and down you 
like a bead on a billiard-marker's wire?  See here, Willard Bent. 
. ."</p><p> 
     The young man in the caftan blushed distressfully, not so 
much 
at the graphic reference to his looks as at the doubt cast on his 
disguise.</p><p> 
     "I do assure you, Harry, I pick up a great deal of . . . of 
useful information . . . in this way. . ."</p><p> 
     "Oh, get out," said Harry Spink cheerfully.  "You believe 
all 
that still, do you?  What's the good of it all, anyway?"</p><p> 
     Willard Bent passed a hand under the other's arm and led him 
through the coffee-house into an empty room at the back.  They 
sat 
down on a shelf covered with matting and looked at each other 
earnestly.</p><p> 
     "Don't <hi rend="italic">you</hi> believe any longer, Harry Spink?" asked 
Willard 
Bent.</p><p> 
     "Don't have to.  I'm travelling for rubber now."</p><p> 
     "Oh, merciful heaven!  Was that your automobile?"</p><p> 
     "Sure."</p><p> 
     There was a long silence, during which Bent sat with bowed 
head gazing on the earthen floor, while the bead in his throat 
performed its most active gymnastics.  At last he lifted his eyes 
and fixed them on the tight red face of his companion.</p><p> 
     "When did your faith fail you?" he asked.</p><p> 
     The other considered him humorously.  "Why&mdash;when I got onto 
this job, I guess."</p><p> 
     Willard Bent rose and held out his hand.</p><p> 
     "Good-by. . .  I must go. . .  If I can be of any use . . . 
you know where to find me. . ."</p><p> 
     "Any use?  Say, old man, what's wrong?  Are you trying to 
shake me?"  Bent was silent, and Harry Spink continued 
insidiously: 
"Ain't you a mite hard on me?  I thought the heathen was just 
what 
you was laying for?"</p><p> 
     Bent smiled mournfully.  "There's no use trying to convert a 
renegade."</p><p> 
     "That what I am?  Well&mdash;all right.  But how about the 
others?  
Say&mdash;let's order a lap of tea and have it out right here."</p><p> 
     Bent seemed to hesitate; but at length he rose, put back the 
matting that screened the inner room, and said a word to the 
proprietor.  Presently a scrofulous boy with gazelle eyes brought 
a brass tray bearing glasses and pipes of <hi rend="italic">kif</hi>, gazed 
earnestly 
at the stranger in the linen duster, and slid back behind the 
matting.</p><p> 
     "Of course," Bent began, "a good many people know I am a 
Baptist missionary"&mdash;(<hi rend="italic">"No?"</hi> from Spink, 
incredulously)&mdash;"but in 
the crowd of the bazaar they don't notice me, and I hear things. 
. 
."</p><p> 
     "Golly!  I should suppose you did."</p><p> 
     "I mean, things that may be useful.  You know Mr. 
Blandhorn's 
idea. . ."</p><p> 
     A tinge of respectful commiseration veiled the easy 
impudence 
of the drummer's look.  "The old man still here, is he?"</p><p> 
     "Oh, yes, of course.  He will never leave Eloued."</p><p> 
     "And the missus&mdash;?"</p><p> 
     Bent again lowered his naturally low voice.  "She died&mdash;a 
year 
ago&mdash;of the climate.  The doctor had warned her; but Mr. 
Blandhorn 
felt a call to remain here."</p><p> 
     "And she wouldn't leave without him?"</p><p> 
     "Oh, <hi rend="italic"> she</hi> felt a call, too . . . among the women. . 
."</p><p> 
     Spink pondered.  "How many years you been here, 
Willard?"</p><p> 
     "Ten next July," the other responded, as if he had added up 
the weeks and months so often that the reply was always on his 
lips.</p><p> 
     "And the old man?"</p><p> 
     "Twenty-five last April.  We had planned a celebration . . . 
before Mrs. Blandhorn died.  There was to have been a testimonial 
offered . . . but, owing to her death, Mr. Blandhorn preferred to 
devote the sum to our dispensary."</p><p> 
     "I see.  How much?" said Spink sharply.</p><p> 
     "It wouldn't seem much to you.  I believe about fifty 
pesetas. 
. ."</p><p> 
     "Two pesetas a year?  Lucky the Society looks after you, 
ain't 
it?" <pb n="19"/> </p><p> 
     Willard Bent met his ironic glance steadily.  "We're not 
here 
to trade," he said with dignity.</p><p> 
     "No&mdash;that's right, too."  Spink reddened slightly.  "Well, 
all 
I meant was&mdash;look at here, Willard, we're old friends, even if I 
did go wrong, as I suppose you'd call it.  I was in this thing 
near 
on a year myself, and what always tormented me was this: <hi rend="italic"> What 
does it all amount to?"</hi></p><p> 
     "Amount to?"</p><p> 
     "Yes.  I mean, what's the results?  Supposing you was a 
fisherman.  Well, if you fished a bit of river year after year, 
and 
never had a nibble, you'd do one of two things, wouldn't you?  
Move 
away&mdash;or lie about it.  See?"</p><p> 
     Bent nodded without speaking.  Spink set down his glass and 
busied himself with the lighting of his long, slender pipe.  
"Say, 
this mint-julep feels like old times," he remarked.</p><p> 
     Bent continued to gaze frowningly into his untouched glass.  
At length he swallowed the sweet decoction at a gulp, and turned 
to 
his companion.</p><p> 
     "I'd never lie . . ." he murmured.</p><p> 
     "Well&mdash;"</p><p> 
     "I'm&mdash;I'm still&mdash;waiting. . ."</p><p> 
     "Waiting&mdash;?"</p><p> 
     "Yes.  The wind bloweth where it listeth.  If St. Paul had 
stopped to count . . . in Corinth, say.  As I take it"&mdash;he looked 
long and passionately at the drummer&mdash;"as I take it, the thing is 
to <hi rend="italic"> be</hi> St. Paul."</p><p> 
     Harry Spink remained unimpressed.  "That's all talk&mdash;I heard 
all that when I was here before.  What I want to know is: What's 
your bag?  How many?"</p><p> 
     "It's difficult&mdash;"</p><p> 
     "I see: like the pigs.  They run around so!"</p><p> 
     Both the young men were silent, Spink pulling at his pipe, 
the 
other sitting with bent head, his eyes obstinately fixed on the 
beaten floor.  At length Spink rose and tapped the missionary on 
the shoulder.</p><p> 
     "Say&mdash;s'posin' we take a look around Corinth?  I got to get 
onto my job to-morrow, but I'd like to take a turn round the old 
place first."</p><p> 
     Willard Bent rose also.  He felt singularly old and tired, 
and 
his mind was full of doubt as to what he ought to do.  If he 
refused to accompany Harry Spink, a former friend and fellow 
worker, it might <hi rend="italic"> look</hi> like running away from his 
questions. . 
.</p><p> 
     They went out together. 
 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="2" id="d4"><head> 
                                II</head> 
<p> 
     THE bazaar was seething.  It seemed impossible that two more 
people should penetrate the throng of beggars, pilgrims, traders, 
slave women, water-sellers, hawkers of dates and sweetmeats, 
leather-gaitered country-people carrying bunches of hens head 
downward, jugglers' touts from the market-place, Jews in black 
caftans and greasy turbans, and scrofulous children reaching up 
to 
the high counters to fill their jars and baskets.  But every now 
and then the Arab "Look out!" made the crowd divide and flatten 
itself against the stalls, and a long line of donkeys loaded with 
water-barrels or bundles of reeds, a string of musk-scented 
camels 
swaying their necks like horizontal question-marks, or a great 
man 
perched on a pink-saddled mule and followed by slaves and 
clients, 
swept through the narrow passage without other peril to the 
pedestrians than that of a fresh exchange of vermin.</p><p> 
     As the two young men drew back to make way for one of these 
processions, Willard Bent lifted his head and looked at his 
friend 
with a smile.  "That's what Mr. Blandhorn says we ought to 
remember&mdash;it's one of his favorite images.</p><p> 
     "What is?" asked Harry Spink, following with attentive gaze 
the movements of a young Jewess whose uncovered face and bright 
head-dress stood out against a group of muffled Arab 
women.</p><p> 
     Instinctively Willard's voice took on a hortatory 
roll.</p><p> 
     "Why, the way this dense mass of people, so heedless, so 
preoccupied, is imperceptibly penetrated&mdash;"</p><p> 
     "By a handful of asses?  That's so.  But the asses have got 
some kick in 'em, remember!"</p><p> 
     The missionary flushed to the edge of his fez, and his mild 
eyes grew dim.  It was the old story: Harry Spink invariably got 
the better of him in bandying words&mdash;and the interpretation of 
allegories had never been his strong point.  Mr. Blandhorn always 
managed to make them <pb n="20"/>  sound unanswerable, 
whereas on his 
disciple's lips they fell to pieces at a touch.  What <hi rend="italic"> was</hi> 
it 
that Willard always left out?</p><p> 
     A mournful sense of his unworthiness overcame him, and with 
it 
the discouraged vision of all the long months and years spent in 
the struggle with heat and dust and flies and filth and 
wickedness, 
the long, lonely years of his youth that would never come back to 
him.  It was the vision he most dreaded, and turning from it he 
tried to forget himself in watching his friend.</p><p> 
     "Golly!  The vacuum-cleaner ain't been round since my last 
visit," Mr. Spink observed, as they slipped in a mass of offal 
beneath a butcher's stall.  "Let's get into another soukh&mdash;the 
flies here beat me."</p><p> 
     They turned into another long lane chequered with an 
interweaving of black reed-shadows.  It was the saddlers' 
quarter, 
and here an even thicker crowd wriggled and swayed between the 
cramped stalls hung with bright leather and spangled 
ornaments.</p><p> 
     "Say!  It might be a good idea to import some of this stuff 
for Fourth of July processions&mdash;Knights of Pythias and secret 
societies' kinder thing," Spink mused, pausing before the 
brilliant 
spectacle.  At the same moment a lad in an almond-green caftan 
sidled up and touched his arm.</p><p> 
     Willard's face brightened.  "Ah, that's little Ahmed&mdash;you 
don't remember him?  Surely&mdash;the water-carrier's boy.  Mrs. 
Blandhorn saved his mother's life when he was born, and he still 
comes to prayers.  Yes, Ahmed, this is your old friend Mr. 
Spink."</p><p> 
     Ahmed raised prodigious lashes from seraphic eyes and 
reverently surveyed the face of his old friend.  "Me 
'member."</p><p> 
     "Hullo, old chap . . . why, of course . . . so do I," the 
drummer beamed.  The missionary laid a brotherly hand on the 
boy's 
shoulder.  It was really providential that Ahmed&mdash;whom they 
hadn't 
seen at the Mission for more weeks than Willard cared to count&mdash; 
should have "happened by" at that moment: Willard took it as a 
rebuke to his own doubts.</p><p> 
     "You'll be in this evening for prayers, won't you, Ahmed?" 
he 
said, as if Ahmed never failed them.  "Mr. Spink will be with 
us."</p><p> 
     "Yessir," said Ahmed with unction.  He slipped from under 
Willard's hand, and outflanking the drummer approached him from 
the 
farther side.</p><p> 
     "Show you Souss boys dance?  Down to old Jewess's, Bab-el-Soukh," he breathed angelically.</p><p> 
     Willard saw his companion turn from red to a wrathful 
purple.</p><p> 
     "Get out, you young swine, you&mdash;do you hear me?"</p><p> 
     Ahmed grinned, wavered and vanished, engulfed in the 
careless 
crowd.  The young men walked on without speaking. 
 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="3" id="d5"><head> 
                                III</head> 
<p> 
     IN the market-place they parted.  Willard Bent, after some 
hesitation, had asked Harry Spink to come to the Mission that 
evening.  "You'd better come to supper&mdash;then we can talk quietly 
afterward.  Mr. Blandhorn will want to see you," he suggested; 
and 
Mr. Spink had affably acquiesced.</p><p> 
     The prayer-meeting was before supper, and Willard would have 
liked to propose again that his friend should come to that also; 
but he did not dare.  He said to himself that Harry Spink, who 
had 
been merely a lay assistant, might have lost the habit of 
reverence, and that it would be too painful to risk his 
scandalizing Mr. Blandhorn.  But that was only a sham reason; and 
Willard, with his incorrigible habit of self-exploration, fished 
up 
the real one from a lower depth.  What he had most feared was 
that 
there would be no one at the meeting.</p><p> 
     During Mrs. Blandhorn's lifetime there had been no reason 
for 
such apprehension: they could always count on a few people.  Mrs. 
Blandhorn, who had studied medicine at Ann Arbor, Michigan, had 
early gained renown in Eloued by her miraculous healing powers.  
The dispensary, in those days, had been beset by anxious-eyed 
women 
who unwound skinny fig-colored children from their dirty 
draperies; 
and there had even been a time when Mr. Blandhorn had appealed to 
the Society for a young lady missionary to assist his wife.  But, 
for reasons not quite clear to Willard Bent, Mrs. Blandhorn, a 
thin-lipped, determined little woman, had <pb n="21"/>  
energetically 
opposed the coming of this youthful "Sister," and had declared 
that 
their Jewish maid servant, old Myriem, could give her all the aid 
she needed.</p><p> 
     Mr. Blandhorn yielded, as he usually did&mdash;as he had yielded, 
for instance, when one day, in a white inarticulate fury, his 
wife 
had banished her godson, little Ahmed (whose life she had saved), 
and issued orders that he should never show himself again except 
at 
prayer-meeting, and accompanied by his father.  Mrs. Blandhorn, 
small, silent and passionate, had always&mdash;as Bent made out in his 
long retrospective musings&mdash;ended by having her way in the 
conflicts that occasionally shook the monotony of life at the 
Mission.  After her death the young man had even suspected, 
beneath 
his superior's sincere and vehement sorrow, a lurking sense of 
relief.  Mr. Blandhorn had snuffed the air of freedom, and had 
been, for the moment, slightly intoxicated by it.  But not for 
long.  Very soon his wife's loss made itself felt as a lasting 
void.</p><p> 
     She had been (as Spink would have put it) "the whole show"; 
had led, inspired, organized her husband's work, held it 
together, 
and given it the brave front it presented to the unheeding 
heathen.  
Now the heathen had almost entirely fallen away, and the too 
evident inference was that they had come rather for Mrs. 
Blandhorn's pills than for her husband's exhortations.  Neither 
of 
the missionaries had avowed this discovery to the other, but to 
Willard at least it was implied in all the circumlocutions and 
evasions of their endless talks.</p><p> 
     The young man's situation had been greatly changed by Mrs. 
Blandhorn's death.  His superior had grown touchingly dependent 
on 
him.  Their conversation, formerly confined to parochial matters, 
now ranged from abstruse doctrinal problems to the question of 
how 
to induce Myriem, who had deplorably "relapsed," to keep the 
kitchen cleaner and spend less time on the roofs.  Bent felt that 
Mr. Blandhorn needed him at every moment, and that, during any 
prolonged absence, something vaguely "unfortunate" might happen 
at 
the Mission.</p><p> 
     "I'm glad Spink has come; it will do him good to see 
somebody 
from outside," Willard thought, nervously hoping that Spink (a 
good 
fellow at bottom) would not trouble Mr. Blandhorn by any of his 
"unsettling" questions.</p><p> 
     At the end of a labyrinth of lanes, on the farther side of 
the 
Jewish quarter, a wall of heat-cracked clay bore the inscription: 
"American Evangelical Mission."  Underneath a door opened into a 
court where an old woman in a bright head-dress sat under a fig-tree pounding something in a mortar.</p><p> 
     She looked up, and, rising, touched Bent's draperies with 
her 
lips.  Her small face, withered as a dry medlar, was full of an 
ancient wisdom: Mrs. Blandhorn had certainly been right in 
trusting 
Myriem.</p><p> 
     A narrow house-front looked upon the court.  Bent climbed 
the 
steep stairs to Mr. Blandhorn's study.  It was a small room with 
a 
few dog-eared books on a set of rough shelves, the table at which 
Mr. Blandhorn wrote his reports for the Society, and a mattress 
covered with a bit of faded carpet on which he slept.  Near the 
window stood Mrs. Blandhorn's sewing-machine: it had never been 
moved since her death.</p><p> 
     The missionary was sitting in the middle of the room, in the 
rocking-chair which had also been his wife's.  His large veined 
hands were clasped about its arms and his head rested against a 
patchwork cushion tied to the back by a shoe-lace.  His mouth was 
slightly open, and a deep breath, occasionally rising to a 
whistle, 
proceeded with rhythmic regularity from his delicately cut 
nostrils.  Even surprised in sleep he was a fine man to look 
upon; 
and when, at the sound of Bent's approach, he opened his eyes and 
pulled himself out of his chair, he became magnificent.  He had 
taken off his turban, and thrown a handkerchief over his head, 
which was shaved like an Arab's for coolness.  His long beard was 
white, with the smoker's yellow tinge about the lips; but his 
eyebrows were jet-black, arched and restless.  The gray eyes 
beneath them shed a mild benedictory beam, confirmed by the smile 
of a mouth that might have seemed weak if the beard had not so 
nearly concealed it.  But the forehead menaced, fulminated or 
awed 
with the ever-varying play of the eyebrows.  Willard Bent never 
beheld that forehead without thinking of Sinai.  
<pb n="22"/> </p><p> 
     Mr. Blandhorn brushed some shreds of tobacco from his white 
djellabah and looked impressively at his assistant.</p><p> 
     "The heat is really overwhelming," he said, as if excusing 
himself.  He readjusted his turban, and then asked: "Is 
everything 
ready down-stairs?"</p><p> 
     Bent assented, and they went down to the long bare room 
where 
the prayer-meetings were held.  In Mrs. Blandhorn's day it had 
also 
served as the dispensary, and a cupboard containing drugs and 
bandages stood against the wall under the text: "Come unto me, 
all 
ye that labor and are heavy laden."</p><p> 
     Myriem, abandoning her mortar, was vaguely "tidying" the 
Arab 
tracts and leaflets that lay on the divan against the wall.  At 
one 
end of the room stood a table covered with a white cloth, with a 
Bible lying on it; and to the left a sort of pulpit-lectern, from 
which Mr. Blandhorn addressed his flock.  In the doorway squatted 
Ayoub, a silent gray-headed negro: Bent, on his own arrival at 
Eloued, ten years earlier, had found him there in the same place 
and the same attitude.  Ayoub was supposed to be a rescued slave 
from the Soudan, and was shown to visitors as "our first 
convert."  
He manifested no interest at the approach of the missionaries, 
but 
continued to gaze out into the sun-baked court cut in half by the 
shadow of the fig-tree.</p><p> 
     Mr. Blandhorn, after looking about the empty room as if he 
were surveying the upturned faces of an attentive congregation, 
placed himself at the lectern, put on his spectacles, and turned 
over the pages of his prayer-book.  Then he knelt and bowed his 
head in prayer.  His devotions ended, he rose and seated himself 
in 
the cane armchair that faced the lectern.  Willard Bent sat 
opposite in another armchair.  Mr. Blandhorn leaned back, 
breathing 
heavily, and passing his handkerchief over his face and brow.  
Now 
and then he drew out his watch, now and then he said: "The heat 
is 
really overwhelming."</p><p> 
     Myriem had drifted back to her fig-tree, and the sound of 
the 
pestle mingled with the drone of flies on the window-pane.  
Occasionally the curses of a muleteer or the rhythmic chant of a 
water-carrier broke the silence; once there came from a 
neighboring 
roof the noise of a short catlike squabble ending in female 
howls; 
then the afternoon heat laid its leaden hush on all 
things.</p><p> 
     Mr. Blandhorn opened his mouth and slept.</p><p> 
     Willard Bent, watching him, thought with wonder and 
admiration 
of his past.  What had he not seen, what secrets were not hidden 
in 
his bosom?  By dint of sheer "sticking it out" he had acquired to 
the younger man a sort of visible sanctity.  Twenty-five years of 
Eloued!  He had known the old mad torturing Sultan, he had seen, 
after the defeat of the rebels, the long line of prisoners 
staggering in under a torrid sky, chained wrist to wrist, and 
dragging between them the putrefying bodies of those who had died 
on the march.  He had seen the Great Massacre, when the rivers 
were 
red with French blood, and Mr. Blandhorn had hidden an officer's 
wife and children in the rat-haunted drain under the court; he 
had 
known robbery and murder and intrigue, and all the dark 
maleficence 
of Africa; and he remained as serene, as confident and guileless, 
as on the day when he had first set foot on that evil soil, 
saying 
to himself (as he had told Willard): "Thou shalt tread upon the 
lion and adder: the young lion and the dragon shalt thou trample 
under feet."</p><p> 
     Willard Bent hated Africa; but it awed and fascinated him.  
And as he contemplated the splendid old man sleeping opposite 
him, 
so mysterious, so childlike and so weak (Mrs. Blandhorn had left 
him no doubts on that point), the disciple marvelled at the power 
of the faith which had armed his master with a sort of infantine 
strength against such dark and manifold perils.</p><p> 
     Suddenly a shadow fell in the doorway, and Bent, roused from 
his dream, saw Harry Spink tiptoeing past the unmoved Ayoub.  The 
drummer paused and looked with astonishment from one of the 
missionaries to the other.  "Say," he asked, "is prayer-meeting 
over?  I thought I'd be round in time."</p><p> 
     He spoke seriously, even respectfully; it was plain that he 
felt flippancy to be out of place.  But Bent suspected a lurking 
malice under his astonishment: he was sure Harry Spink had come 
to 
"count heads." <pb n="23"/> </p><p> 
     Mr. Blandhorn, wakened by the voice, stood up 
heavily.</p><p> 
     "Harry Spink!  Is it possible you are amongst us?"</p><p> 
     "Why, yes, sir&mdash;I'm amongst.  Didn't Willard tell you?  I 
guess Willard Bent's ashamed of me."</p><p> 
     Spink, with a laugh, shook Mr. Blandhorn's hand, and glanced 
about the empty room.</p><p> 
     "I'm only here for a day or so&mdash;on business.  Willard'll 
explain.  But I wanted to come round to meeting&mdash;like old times.  
Sorry it's over."</p><p> 
     The missionary looked at him with a grave candor.  "It's not 
over&mdash;it has not begun.  The overwhelming heat has probably kept 
away our little flock."</p><p> 
     "I see," interpolated Spink.</p><p> 
     "But now," continued Mr. Blandhorn with majesty, "that two 
or 
three are gathered together in His name, there is no reason why 
we 
should wait.&mdash;Myriem!  Ayoub!"</p><p> 
     He took his place behind the lectern and began: "Almighty 
and 
merciful Father&mdash;" 
 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="4" id="d6"><head> 
                                IV</head> 
<p> 
     THE night was exceedingly close.  Willard Bent, after 
Spink's 
departure, had undressed and stretched himself on his camp-bed; 
but 
the mosquitoes roared like lions, and lying down made him more 
wakeful.</p><p> 
     "In any Christian country," he mused, "this would mean a 
thunder-storm and a cool-off.  Here it just means months and 
months 
more of the same thing."  And he thought enviously of Spink, who, 
in two or three days, his "deal" concluded, would be at sea 
again, 
heading for the north.</p><p> 
     Bent was honestly distressed at his own state of mind: he 
had 
feared that Harry Spink would "unsettle" Mr. Blandhorn, and, 
instead, it was he himself who had been unsettled.  Old 
slumbering 
distrusts and doubts, bursting through his surface-apathy, had 
shot 
up under the drummer's ironic eye.  It was not so much Spink, 
individually, who had loosened the crust of Bent's indifference; 
it 
was the fact of feeling his whole problem suddenly viewed and 
judged from the outside.  At Eloued, he was aware, nobody, for a 
long time, had thought much about the missionaries.  The French 
authorities were friendly, the Pasha was tolerant, the American 
consul at Mogador had always stood by them in any small 
difficulties.  But beyond that they were virtually non-existent.  
Nobody's view of life was really affected by their presence in 
the 
great swarming mysterious city: if they should pack up and leave 
that night, the story-tellers of the market would not interrupt 
their tales, or one less bargain be struck in the bazaar.  Ayoub 
would still doze in the door, and old Myriem continue her secret 
life on the roofs. . .</p><p> 
     The roofs were of course forbidden to the missionaries, as 
they are to men in all Moslem cities.  But the Mission-house 
stood 
close to the walls, and Mr. Blandhorn's room, across the passage, 
gave on a small terrace overhanging the court of a caravansary 
upon 
which it was no sin to look.  Willard wondered if it were any 
cooler on the terrace.</p><p> 
     Some one tapped on his open door, and Mr. Blandhorn, in 
turban 
and caftan, entered the room shading a small lamp.</p><p> 
     "My dear Willard&mdash;can you sleep?"</p><p> 
     "No, sir."  The young man stumbled to his feet.</p><p> 
     "Nor I.  The heat is really . . .  Shall we seek relief on 
the 
terrace?"</p><p> 
     Bent followed him, and having extinguished the lamp Mr. 
Blandhorn led the way out.  He dragged a strip of matting to the 
edge of the parapet, and the two men sat down on it side by 
side.</p><p> 
     There was no moon, but a sky so full of stars that the city 
was outlined beneath it in great blue-gray masses.  The air was 
motionless, but every now and then a wandering tremor stirred it 
and died out.  Close under the parapet lay the bales and saddle-packs of the caravansary, between vaguer heaps, presumably of 
sleeping camels.  In one corner the star-glitter picked out the 
shape of a trough brimming with water, and stabbed it with long 
silver beams.  Beyond the court rose the crenellations of the 
city 
walls, and above them one palm stood up like a tree of 
bronze.</p><p> 
     "Africa&mdash;" sighed Mr. Blandhorn.</p><p> 
     Willard Bent started at the secret echo of his own thoughts. 
<pb n="24"/> </p><p> 
     "Yes.  Never anything else, sir&mdash;"</p><p> 
     "Ah&mdash;" said the old man.</p><p> 
     A tang-tang of stringed instruments, accompanied by the 
lowing 
of an earthen-ware drum, rose exasperatingly through the night.  
It 
was the kind of noise that, one knew, had been going on for hours 
before one began to notice it, and would go on, unchecked and 
unchanging, for endless hours more: like the heat, like the 
drought&mdash;like Africa.</p><p> 
     Willard slapped at a mosquito.</p><p> 
     "It's a party at the wool-merchant's, Myriem tells me," Mr. 
Blandhorn remarked.  It really seemed as if, that night, the 
thoughts of the two men met without the need of words.  Willard 
Bent was aware that, for both, the casual word had called up all 
the details of the scene: fat merchants in white bunches on their 
cushions, negresses coming and going with trays of sweets, 
champagne clandestinely poured, ugly singing-girls yowling, slim 
boys in petticoats dancing&mdash;perhaps little Ahmed among 
them.</p><p> 
     "I went down to the court just now.  Ayoub has disappeared," 
Mr. Blandhorn continued.</p><p> 
     "Of course.  When I heard in the bazaar that that black 
caravan was in from the south I knew he'd be off. . ."</p><p> 
     Mr. Blandhorn lowered his voice.  "Willard&mdash;have you reason 
to 
think . . . that Ayoub joins in their rites?"</p><p> 
     "Myriem has always said he was a Hamatcha, sir.  Look at 
those 
queer cuts and scars on him. . .  It's a much bloodier sect than 
the Aissaouas."</p><p> 
     Through the nagging throb of the instruments came a sound of 
human wailing, cadenced, terrible, relentless, carried from a 
long 
way off on a lift of the air.  Then the air died, and the wailing 
with it.</p><p> 
     "From somewhere near the Potters' Field . . . there's where 
the caravan is camping," Willard murmured.</p><p> 
     The old man made no answer.  He sat with his head bowed, his 
veined hands grasping his knees; he seemed to his disciple to be 
whispering fragments of Scripture.</p><p> 
     "Willard, my son, this is our fault," he said at 
length.</p><p> 
     "What&mdash;?  Ayoub?"</p><p> 
     "Ayoub is a poor ignorant creature, hardly more than an 
animal.  Even when he witnessed for Jesus I was not very sure the 
Word reached him.  I refer to&mdash;to what Harry Spink said this 
evening. . .  It has kept me from sleeping, Willard Bent."</p><p> 
     "Yes&mdash;I know, sir."</p><p> 
     "Harry Spink is a worldly minded man.  But he is not a bad 
man.  He did a manly thing when he left us, since he did not feel 
the call.  But we have felt the call, Willard, you and I&mdash;and 
when 
a man like Spink puts us a question such as he put this evening 
we 
ought to be able to answer it.  And we ought not to want to avoid 
answering it."</p><p> 
     "You mean when he said: <hi rend="italic"> 'What is there in it for 
Jesus'?"</hi></p><p> 
     "The phrase was irreverent, but the meaning reached me.  He 
meant, I take it: 'What have your long years here profited to 
Christ?'  You understood it so&mdash;?"</p><p> 
     "Yes.  He said to me in the bazaar: <hi rend="italic"> 'What's your 
bag?'"</hi></p><p> 
     Mr. Blandhorn sighed heavily.  For a few minutes Willard 
fancied he had fallen asleep; but he lifted his head and, 
stretching his hand out, laid it on his disciple's arm.</p><p> 
     "The Lord chooses His messengers as it pleaseth Him; I have 
been awaiting this for a long time."  The young man felt his arm 
strongly grasped.  "Willard, you have been much to me all these 
years; but that is nothing.  All that matters is what you are to 
Christ . . . and the test of that, at this moment, is your 
willingness to tell me the exact truth, as you see it."</p><p> 
     Willard Bent felt as if he were a very tall building, and 
his 
heart a lift suddenly dropping down from the roof to the cellar.  
He stirred nervously, releasing his arm, and cleared his throat; 
but he made no answer.  Mr. Blandhorn went on:</p><p> 
     "Willard, this is the day of our accounting&mdash;of <hi rend="italic"> my</hi> 
accounting.  What have I done with my twenty-five years in 
Africa?  
I might deceive myself as long as my wife lived&mdash;I cannot now."  
He 
added, after a pause: "Thank heaven <hi rend="italic"> she</hi> never doubted. . 
."</p><p> 
     The younger man, with an inward shiver, remembered some of 
Mrs. Blandhorn's confidences.  "I suppose that's what marriage 
is," 
he mused&mdash;"just a fog, like everything else."  
<pb n="25"/> </p><p> 
     Aloud he asked: "Then why should <hi rend="italic"> you</hi> doubt, 
sir?"</p><p> 
     "Because my eyes have been opened&mdash;"</p><p> 
     "By Harry Spink?" the disciple sneered.</p><p> 
     The old man raised his hand.  "'Out of the mouths of 
babes&mdash;'  
But it is not Harry Spink who first set me thinking.  He has 
merely 
loosened my tongue.  He has been the humble instrument compelling 
me to exact the truth of you."</p><p> 
     Again Bent felt his heart dropping down a long dark shaft.  
He 
found no words at the bottom of it, and Mr. Blandhorn continued: 
"The truth and the whole truth, Willard Bent.  We have 
failed&mdash;<hi rend="italic"> 
I</hi> have failed.  We have not reached the souls of these 
people.  
Those who still come to us do so from interested motives&mdash;or, 
even 
if I do some few of them an injustice, if there is in some a 
blind 
yearning for the light, is there one among them whose eyes we 
have 
really opened?"</p><p> 
     Willard Bent sat silent, looking up and down the long years, 
as if to summon from the depths of memory some single incident 
that 
should permit him to say there was.</p><p> 
     "You don't answer, my poor young friend.  Perhaps you have 
been clearer-sighted; perhaps you saw long ago that we were not 
worthy of our hire."</p><p> 
     "I never thought that of you, sir!"</p><p> 
     "Nor of yourself?  For we have been one&mdash;or so I 
believed&mdash;in 
all our hopes and efforts.  Have you been satisfied with <hi rend="italic"> 
your</hi> 
results?"</p><p> 
     Willard saw the dialectical trap, but some roused force in 
him 
refused to evade it.</p><p> 
     "No, sir&mdash;God knows."</p><p> 
     "Then I am answered.  We have failed: Africa has beaten us.  
It has always been my way, as you know, Willard, to face the 
truth 
squarely," added the old man who had lived so long in dreams; 
"and 
now that this truth has been borne in on me, painful as it is, I 
must act on it . . . act in accordance with its discovery. . 
."</p><p> 
     He drew a long breath, as if oppressed by the weight of his 
resolution, and sat silent for a moment, fanning his face with a 
corner of his white draperies.</p><p> 
     "And here too&mdash;here too I must have your help, Willard," he 
began presently, his hand again weighing on the young man's arm.  
"I will tell you the conclusions I have reached; and you must 
answer me&mdash;as you would answer your Maker."</p><p> 
     "Yes, sir."</p><p> 
     The old man lowered his voice.  "It is our lukewarmness, 
Willard&mdash;it is nothing else.  We have not witnessed for Christ as 
His saints and martyrs witnessed for Him.  What have we done to 
fix 
the attention of these people, to convince them of our zeal, to 
overwhelm them with the irresistibleness of the Truth?  Answer me 
on your word&mdash;what have we done?"</p><p> 
     Willard pondered.  "But the saints and martyrs . . . were 
persecuted, sir."</p><p> 
     <hi rend="italic">" Persecuted!</hi>  You have spoken the word I 
wanted."</p><p> 
     "But the people here," Willard argued, "don't <hi rend="italic"> want</hi> 
to 
persecute anybody.  They're not fanatical unless you insult their 
religion."</p><p> 
     Mr. Blandhorn's grasp grew tighter.  "Insult their religion! 
 
That's it . . . to-night you find just the words. . ."</p><p> 
     Willard felt his arm shake with the tremor that passed 
through 
the other's body.  "The saints and martyrs insulted the religion 
of 
the heathen&mdash;they spat upon it, Willard&mdash;they rushed into the 
temples and knocked down the idols.  They said to the heathen: 
'Turn away your faces from all your abominations,' and after the 
manner of men they fought with the beasts at Ephesus.  What is 
the 
Church on earth called?  The Church Militant!  You and I are 
soldiers of the Cross."</p><p> 
     The missionary had risen and stood leaning against the 
parapet, his right arm lifted as if he spoke from a pulpit.  The 
music at the wool-merchant's had ceased, but now and then, 
through 
the midnight silence, there came an echo of ritual howls from the 
Potter's Field.</p><p> 
     Willard was still seated, his head thrown back against the 
parapet, his eyes raised to Mr. Blandhorn.  Following the gesture 
of the missionary's lifted hand, from which the muslin fell back 
like the sleeve of a surplice, the young man's gaze was led 
upward 
to another white figure, hovering small and remote above their 
<pb n="26"/>  heads.  It was a Muezzin leaning from his airy balcony to 
drop 
on the blue-gray masses of the starlit city the cry: "Only Allah 
is 
great!"</p><p> 
     Mr. Blandhorn saw the white figure too, and stood facing it 
with motionless raised arm.</p><p> 
     "Only Christ is great, only Christ crucified!" he suddenly 
shouted in Arabic with all the strength of his broad 
lungs.</p><p> 
     The figure paused, and seemed to Willard to bend over, as if 
peering down in their direction; but a moment later it had moved 
to 
the other corner of the balcony, and the cry fell again on the 
sleeping roofs:</p><p> 
     "Allah&mdash;Allah&mdash;only Allah!"</p><p> 
     "Christ&mdash;Christ&mdash;only Christ crucified!" roared Mr. 
Blandhorn, 
exalted with wrath and shaking his fist at the aerial 
puppet.</p><p> 
     The puppet once more paused and peered; then it moved on and 
vanished behind the flank of the minaret.</p><p> 
     The missionary, still towering with lifted arm, dusky-faced 
in 
the starlight, seemed to Willard to have grown in majesty and 
stature.  But presently his arm fell and his head sank into his 
hands.  The young man knelt down, hiding his face also, and they 
prayed in silence, side by side, while from the farther corners 
of 
the minaret, more faintly, fell the infidel call.</p><p> 
     Willard, his prayer ended, looked up, and saw that the old 
man's garments were stirred as if by a ripple of air.  But the 
air 
was quite still, and the disciple perceived that the tremor of 
the 
muslin was communicated to it by Mr. Blandhorn's body.</p><p> 
     "He's trembling&mdash;trembling all over.  He's afraid of 
something.  What's he afraid of?"  And in the same breath Willard 
had answered his own question: "He's afraid of what he's made up 
his mind to do." 
 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="5" id="d7"><head> 
                                 V</head> 
<p> 
     TWO days later Willard Bent sat in the shade of a ruined 
tomb 
outside the Gate of the Graves and watched the people streaming 
in 
to Eloued.  It was the eve of the feast of the local saint, Sidi 
Oman, who slept in a corner of the Great Mosque, under a segment 
of 
green-tiled cupola, and was held in deep reverence by the country 
people, many of whom belonged to the powerful fraternity founded 
in 
his name.</p><p> 
     The ruin stood on a hillock beyond the outer wall.  From 
where 
the missionary sat he overlooked the fortified gate and the 
irregular expanse of the Potter's Field, with its primitive 
furnaces built into hollows of the ground between ridges shaded 
by 
stunted olive-trees.  On the farther side of the trail which the 
pilgrims followed on entering the gate lay a sun-blistered 
cemetery, where hucksters traded between the crooked gravestones 
and the humblest caravans camped in a waste of refuse, offal and 
stripped date-branches.  A cloud of dust, perpetually subsiding 
and 
gathering again, hid these sordid details from Bent's eyes, but 
not 
from his imagination.</p><p> 
     "Nowhere in Eloued," he thought with a shudder, "are the 
flies 
as fat and blue as they are inside that gate."</p><p> 
     But this was a fugitive reflection: his mind was wholly 
absorbed in what had happened in the last forty-eight hours, and 
what was likely to happen in the next.</p><p> 
     "To think," he mused, "that after ten years I don't really 
know him! . . .  A laborer in the Lord's vineyard&mdash;shows how much 
good I am!"</p><p> 
     His thoughts were moody and oppressed with fear.  Never, 
since 
his first meeting with Mr. Blandhorn, had he pondered so deeply 
the 
problem of his superior's character.  He tried to deduce from the 
past some inference as to what Mr. Blandhorn was likely to do 
next; 
but, as far as he knew, there was nothing in the old man's 
previous 
history resembling the midnight scene on the Mission 
terrace.</p><p> 
     That scene had already had its repercussion.</p><p> 
     On the following morning, Willard, drifting as usual about 
the 
bazaar, had met a friendly French official, who, taking him 
aside, 
had told him there were strange reports abroad&mdash;which he hoped 
Mr. 
Bent would be able to deny. . .  In short, as it had never been 
Mr. 
Blandhorn's policy to offend the native population, or insult 
their 
religion, the Administration was confident that . . .</p><p> 
     Surprised by Willard's silence, and visi-<pb n="27"/> bly annoyed at 
being obliged to pursue the subject, the friendly official, 
growing 
graver, had then asked what had really occurred; and, on 
Willard's 
replying, had charged him with an earnest recommendation to his 
superior&mdash;a warning, if necessary&mdash;that the government would not, 
under any circumstances, tolerate a repetition. . .  "But I dare 
say it was the heat?" he concluded; and Willard weakly 
acquiesced.</p><p> 
     He was ashamed now of having done so; yet, after all, how 
did 
he know it was <hi rend="italic"> not</hi> the heat?  A heavy sanguine man like 
Mr. 
Blandhorn would probably never quite accustom himself to the long 
strain of the African summer.  "Or his wife's death&mdash;" he had 
murmured to the sympathetic official, who smiled with relief at 
the 
suggestion.</p><p> 
     And now he sat overlooking the enigmatic city, and asking 
himself again what he really knew of his superior.  Mr. Blandhorn 
had come to Eloued as a young man, extremely poor, and dependent 
on 
the pittance which the Missionary Society at that time gave to 
its 
representatives.  To ingratiate himself among the people (the 
expression was his own), and also to earn a few pesetas, he had 
worked as a carpenter in the bazaar, first in the soukh of the 
ploughshares and then in that of the cabinet makers.  His skill 
in 
carpentry had not been great, for his large eloquent hands were 
meant to wave from a pulpit, and not to use the adze or the 
chisel; 
but he had picked up a little Arabic (Willard always marvelled 
that 
it remained so little), and had made many acquaintances&mdash;and, as 
he 
thought, some converts.  At any rate, no one, either then or 
later, 
appeared to wish him ill, and during the massacre his house had 
been respected, and the insurgents had even winked at the aid he 
had courageously given to the French.</p><p> 
     Yes&mdash;he had certainly been courageous.  There was in him, in 
spite of his weaknesses and his vacillations, a streak of moral 
heroism that perhaps only waited its hour. . .  But hitherto his 
principle had always been that the missionary must win converts 
by 
kindness, by tolerance, and by the example of a blameless 
life.</p><p> 
     Could it really be Harry Spink's question that had shaken 
him 
in this belief?  Or was it the long-accumulated sense of 
inefficiency that so often weighed on his disciple?  Or was it 
simply the call&mdash;did it just mean that their hour had 
come?</p><p> 
     Shivering a little in spite of the heat, Willard pulled 
himself together and descended into the city.  He had been seized 
with a sudden desire to know what Mr. Blandhorn was about, and 
avoiding the crowd he hurried back by circuitous lanes to the 
Mission.  On the way he paused at a certain corner and looked 
into 
a court full of the murmur of water.  Beyond it was an arcade 
detached against depths of shadow in which a few lights 
glimmered.  
White figures, all facing one way, crouched and touched their 
foreheads to the tiles, the soles of their bare feet, wet with 
recent ablutions, turning up as their bodies swayed forward.  
Willard caught the scowl of a beggar on the threshold, and 
hurried 
past the forbidden scene.</p><p> 
     He found Mr. Blandhorn in the meeting-room, tying up Ayoub's 
head.</p><p> 
     "I do it awkwardly," the missionary mumbled, a safety-pin 
between his teeth.  "Alas, my hands are not <hi rend="italic"> hers</hi>."</p><p> 
     "What's he done to himself?" Willard growled; and above the 
bandaged head Mr. Blandhorn's expressive eyebrows 
answered.</p><p> 
     There was a dark stain on the back of Ayoub's faded shirt, 
and 
another on the blue scarf he wore about his head.</p><p> 
     "Ugh&mdash;it's like cats slinking back after a gutter-fight," 
the 
young man muttered.</p><p> 
     Ayoub wound his scarf over the bandages, shambled back to 
the 
doorway, and squatted down to watch the fig-tree.</p><p> 
     The missionaries looked at each other across the empty 
room.</p><p> 
     "What's the use, sir?" was on Willard's lips; but instead of 
speaking he threw himself down on the divan.  There was to be no 
prayer-meeting that afternoon, and the two men sat silent, gazing 
at the back of Ayoub's head.  A smell of disinfectants hung in 
the 
heavy air. . .</p><p> 
     "Where's Myriem?" Willard asked, to say something.</p><p> 
     "I believe she had a ceremony of some sort . . . a family 
affair. . ."</p><p> 
     "A circumcision, I suppose?"</p><p> 
     Mr. Blandhorn did not answer, and Willard was sorry he had 
made the suggestion.  It would simply serve as another reminder 
of 
their failure. . . <pb n="28"/> </p><p> 
     He stole a furtive glance at Mr. Blandhorn, nervously 
wondering if the time had come to speak of the French official's 
warning.  He had put off doing so, half hoping it would not be 
necessary.  The old man seemed so calm, so like his usual self, 
that it might be wiser to let the matter drop.  Perhaps he had 
already forgotten the scene on the terrace; or perhaps he thought 
he had sufficiently witnessed for the Lord in shouting his insult 
to the Muezzin.  But Willard did not really believe this: he 
remembered the tremor that had shaken Mr. Blandhorn after the 
challenge, and he felt sure it was not a retrospective 
fear.</p><p> 
     "Our friend Spink has been with me," said Mr. Blandhorn 
suddenly.  "He came in soon after you left."</p><p> 
     "Ah?  I'm sorry I missed him.  I thought he'd gone, from his 
not coming in yesterday."</p><p> 
     "No; he leaves to-morrow morning for Mogador."  Mr. 
Blandhorn 
paused, still absently staring at the back of Ayoub's neck; then 
he 
added: "I have asked him to take you with him."</p><p> 
     "To take me&mdash;Harry Spink?  In his automobile?" Willard 
gasped.  
His heart began to beat excitedly.</p><p> 
     "Yes.  You'll enjoy the ride.  It's a long time since you've 
been away, and you're looking a little pulled down."</p><p> 
     "You're very kind, sir; so is Harry."  He paused.  "But I'd 
rather not."</p><p> 
     Mr. Blandhorn, turning slightly, examined him between half-dropped lids.</p><p> 
     "I have business for you&mdash;with the consul," he said with a 
certain sternness.  "I don't suppose you will object&mdash;"</p><p> 
     "Oh, of course not."  There was another pause.  "Could you 
tell me&mdash;give me an idea&mdash;of what the business is, sir?"</p><p> 
     It was Mr. Blandhorn's turn to appear perturbed.  He 
coughed, 
passed his hand once or twice over his beard, and again fixed his 
gaze on Ayoub's inscrutable nape.</p><p> 
     "I wish to send a letter to the consul."</p><p> 
     "A letter?  If it's only a letter, couldn't Spink take 
it?"</p><p> 
     "Undoubtedly.  I might also send it by post&mdash;if I cared to 
transmit it in that manner.  I presumed," added Mr. Blandhorn 
with 
threatening brows, "that you would understand I had my 
reasons&mdash;"</p><p> 
     "Oh, in that case, of course, sir&mdash;"  Willard hesitated, and 
then spoke with a rush.  "I saw Lieutenant Lourdenay in the 
bazaar 
yesterday&mdash;" he began.</p><p> 
     When he had finished his tale Mr. Blandhorn meditated for a 
long time in silence.  At length he spoke in a calm voice.  "And 
what did you answer, Willard?"</p><p> 
     "I&mdash;I said I'd tell you&mdash;"</p><p> 
     "Nothing more?"</p><p> 
     "No.  Nothing."</p><p> 
     "Very well.  We'll talk of all this more fully . . . when 
you 
get back from Mogador.  Remember that Mr. Spink will be here 
before 
sunrise.  I advised him to get away as early as possible on 
account 
of the Feast of Sidi Oman.  It's always a poor day for foreigners 
to be seen about the streets." 
 
</p> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="section" n="6" id="d8"><head> 
                                VI</head> 
<p> 
     AT a quarter before four on the morning of the Feast of Sidi 
Oman Willard Bent stood waiting at the door of the 
Mission.</p><p> 
     He had taken leave of Mr. Blandhorn the previous night, and 
stumbled down the dark stairs on bare feet, his bundle under his 
arm, just as the sky began to whiten around the morning 
star.</p><p> 
     The air was full of a mocking coolness which the first ray 
of 
the sun would burn up; and a hush as deceptive lay on the city 
that 
was so soon to blaze with religious frenzy.  Ayoub lay curled up 
on 
his door-step like a dog, and old Myriem, presumably, was still 
stretched on her mattress on the roof.</p><p> 
     What a day for a flight across the desert in Harry's tough 
little car!  And after the hours of heat and dust and glare, how 
good, at twilight, to see the cool welter of the Atlantic, a 
spent 
sun dropping into it, and the rush of the stars. . .  Dizzy with 
the vision, Willard leaned against the door-post with closed 
eyes.</p><p> 
     A subdued hoot aroused him, and he hurried out to the car, 
which was quivering and growling at the nearest corner.  The 
drummer nodded a welcome, and they began to wind cautiously 
between 
sleeping animals and huddled heaps of humanity till they reached 
the nearest gate.</p><p> 
     On the waste-land beyond the walls the people of the 
caravans 
were already stirring, and pilgrims from the hills streaming 
across 
the palmetto scrub under embla-<pb n="29"/> zoned banners.  
As the sun 
rose the air took on a bright transparency in which distant 
objects 
became unnaturally near and vivid, like pebbles seen through 
clear 
water: a little turban-shaped tomb far off in the waste looked as 
lustrous as ivory, and a tiled minaret in an angle of the walls 
seemed to be carved of turquoise.  How Eloued lied to eyes 
looking 
back on it at sunrise!</p><p> 
     "Something wrong," said Harry Spink, putting on the brake 
and 
stopping in the thin shade of a cork-tree.  They got out, and 
Willard leaned against the tree and gazed at the red wall of 
Eloued.  They were already about two miles from the town, and all 
around them was the wilderness.  Spink shoved his head into the 
bonnet, screwed and greased and hammered, and finally wiped his 
hands on a black rag and called out: "I thought so&mdash;  Jump 
in!"</p><p> 
     Willard did not move.</p><p> 
     "Hurry up, old man.  She's all right, I tell you.  It was 
just 
the carburetor."</p><p> 
     The missionary fumbled under his draperies and pulled out 
Mr. 
Blandhorn's letter.</p><p> 
     "Will you see that the consul gets this to-morrow?"</p><p> 
     "Will I&mdash;what the hell's the matter, Willard?"  Spink 
dropped 
his rag and stared.</p><p> 
     "I'm not coming.  I never meant to."</p><p> 
     The young men exchanged a long look.</p><p> 
     "It's no time to leave Mr. Blandhorn&mdash;a day like this," 
Willard continued, moistening his dry lips.</p><p> 
     Spink shrugged and sounded a faint whistle.  
"Queer&mdash;!"</p><p> 
     "What's queer?"</p><p> 
     "He said just the same thing to me about <hi rend="italic"> you</hi>&mdash;wanted 
to 
get you out of Eloued on account of the goings-on to-day.  He 
said 
you'd been rather worked up lately about religious matters, and 
might do something rash that would get you both into 
trouble."</p><p> 
     "Ah&mdash;" Willard murmured.</p><p> 
     "And I believe you might, you know&mdash;you look sorter 
funny."</p><p> 
     Willard laughed.</p><p> 
     "Oh, come along," his friend urged, disappointed.</p><p> 
     "I'm sorry&mdash;I can't.  I had to come this far, so that he 
wouldn't know.  But now I've got to go back.  Of course what he 
told you was just a joke&mdash;but I must be there to-day to see that 
nobody bothers him."</p><p> 
     Spink scanned his companion's face with friendly flippant 
eyes.  "Well, I give up&mdash;  What's the <hi rend="italic"> use</hi>, when he don't 
want 
you?  Say," he broke off, "what's the truth of that story about 
the 
old man's having insulted a marabout in a mosque night before 
last?  
It was all over the bazaar&mdash;"</p><p> 
     Willard felt himself turn pale.  "Not a marabout.  It was&mdash; 
where did you hear it?" he stammered.</p><p> 
     "All over&mdash;the way you hear stories in these places."</p><p> 
     "Well&mdash;it's not true."  Willard lifted his bundle from the 
motor and tucked it under his arm.  "I'm sorry, Harry&mdash;I've got 
to 
go back," he repeated.</p><p> 
     "What?  The Call, eh?"  The sneer died on Spink's lips, and 
he 
held out his hand.  "I'm sorry, too.  So long."  He turned the 
crank of the motor, scrambled into his seat, and called back over 
his shoulder: "What's the <hi rend="italic"> use</hi>, when he don't want 
you?"</p><p> 
     Willard was already laboring home across the plain. 
</p><p> 
     After struggling along for half an hour in the heavy sand he 
crawled under the shade of an abandoned well, and sat down to 
ponder.  Two courses were open to him, and he had not yet been 
able 
to decide between them.  His first impulse was to go straight to 
the Mission, and to present himself to Mr. Blandhorn.  He felt 
sure, from what Spink had told him, that the old missionary had 
sent him away purposely, and the fact seemed to confirm his 
apprehensions.  If Mr. Blandhorn wanted him away, it was not 
through any fear of his imprudence, but to be free from his 
restraining influence.  But what act did the old man contemplate, 
in which he feared to involve his disciple?  And if he were 
really 
resolved on some rash measure, might not Willard's unauthorized 
return merely serve to exasperate his resolve, and hasten 
whatever 
action he had planned?</p><p> 
     The other step the young man had in mind was to go secretly 
to 
the French Administration, and there drop a hint of what he 
feared.  
It was the course his sober judgment commended.  The echo of 
Spink's "What's the use?" was in his <pb n="30"/>  ears.  
It was the 
expression of his own secret doubt.  What <hi rend="italic"> was</hi> the use?  
If 
dying could bring any of these darkened souls to the light . . . 
well, that would have been different.  But what least sign was 
there that it would do anything but rouse their sleeping blood-lust?</p><p> 
     Willard was oppressed by the thought that had always lurked 
beneath his other doubts.  They talked, he and Mr. Blandhorn, of 
the poor ignorant heathen&mdash;but were not they themselves equally 
ignorant in everything that concerned the heathen?  What did they 
know of these people, of their antecedents, the origin of their 
beliefs and superstitions, the meaning of their habits and 
passions 
and precautions?  Mr. Blandhorn seemed never to have been 
troubled 
by this question, but it had weighed on Willard ever since he had 
come across a quiet French ethnologist who was studying the 
tribes 
of the Middle Atlas.  Two or three talks with this traveller&mdash;or 
listenings to him&mdash;had shown Willard the extent of his own 
ignorance.  He would have liked to borrow books, to read, to 
study; 
but he knew little French and no German, and he felt confusedly 
that there was in him no soil sufficiently prepared for facts so 
overwhelmingly new to root in it. . .  And the heat lay on him, 
and 
the little semblance of his missionary duties deluded him . . . 
and 
he drifted. . .</p><p> 
     As for Mr. Blandhorn, he never read anything but the 
Scriptures, a volume of his own sermons (printed by subscription, 
to commemorate his departure for Morocco), and&mdash;occasionally&mdash;a 
back number of the missionary journal that arrived at Eloued at 
long intervals, in thick, mouldy batches.  Consequently no doubts 
disturbed him, and Willard felt the hopelessness of grappling 
with 
an ignorance so much deeper and denser than his own.  Whichever 
way 
his mind turned, it seemed to bring up against the blank wall of 
Harry Spink's: "What's the use?" 
</p><p> 
       .       .       .       .       .       .       .       . 
</p><p> 
     He slipped through the crowds in the congested gateway, and 
made straight for the Mission.  He had decided to go to the 
French 
Administration, but he wanted first to find out from the servants 
what Mr. Blandhorn was doing, and what his state of mind appeared 
to be.</p><p> 
     The Mission door was locked, but Willard was not surprised; 
he 
knew the precaution was sometimes taken on feast-days, though 
seldom so early.  He rang, and waited impatiently for Myriem's 
old 
face in the crack; but no one came, and below his breath he 
cursed 
her with expurgated curses.</p><p> 
     "Ayoub&mdash;<hi rend="italic"> Ayoub!"</hi> he cried, rattling at the door; but 
still 
there was no answer.  Ayoub, apparently, was off too.  Willard 
rang 
the bell again, giving the three long pulls of the "emergency 
call": it was the summons that always roused Mr. Blandhorn.  But 
no 
one came.</p><p> 
     Willard shook and pounded, and hung on the bell till it 
tinkled its life out . . . but all in vain.  The house was empty: 
Mr. Blandhorn was evidently out with the others.</p><p> 
     Disconcerted by this unexpected discovery, the young man 
turned and plunged into the red clay purlieus behind the Mission. 
 
He entered a mud hut where an emaciated dog, dozing on the 
threshold, lifted a recognizing lid, and let him by.  It was the 
house of Ahmed's father, the water-carrier, and Willard knew it 
would be empty at that hour.</p><p> 
     A few minutes later there emerged into the crowded streets a 
young American dressed in a black coat of vaguely clerical cut, 
with a soft felt hat shading his flushed cheek-bones, and a bead 
running up and down his nervous throat.</p><p> 
     The bazaar was already full of a deep holiday rumor, like 
the 
rattle of wind in the palm-tops.  The young man in the clerical 
coat, sharply examined as he passed by hundreds of long Arab 
eyes, 
slipped into the lanes behind the soukhs, and by circuitous 
passages gained the neighborhood of the Great Mosque.  His heart 
was hammering against his black coat, and under the buzz in his 
brain there boomed out insistently the old question: "What's the 
use?"</p><p> 
     Suddenly, near the fountain that faced one of the doors of 
the 
Great Mosque, he saw the figure of a man dressed like himself.  
The 
eyes of the two men met across the crowd, and Willard pushed his 
way to Mr. Blandhorn's side.</p><p> 
     "Sir, why did you&mdash;why are you&mdash;?  I'm back&mdash;I couldn't help 
it," he gasped out disconnectedly.</p><p> 
     He had expected a vehement rebuke; <pb n="31"/>  but 
the old 
missionary only smiled on him sadly.</p><p> 
     "It was noble of you, Willard . . . I understand. . ."  He 
looked at the young man's coat.  "We had the same 
thought&mdash;again&mdash; 
at the same hour."  He paused, and drew Willard into the empty 
passage of a ruined building behind the fountain.  "But what's 
the 
use&mdash;what's the use?" he exclaimed.</p><p> 
     The blood rushed to the young man's forehead.  "Ah&mdash;then you 
feel it too?"</p><p> 
     Mr. Blandhorn continued, grasping his arm: "I've been 
out&mdash;in 
this dress&mdash;ever since you left; I've hung about the doors of the 
Medersas, I've walked up to the very threshold of the Mosque, 
I've 
leaned against the wall of Sidi Oman's shrine; once the police 
warned me, and I pretended to go away . . . but I came back . . . 
I pushed up closer . . . I stood in the doorway of the Mosque, 
and 
they saw me . . . the people inside saw me . . . and no one 
touched 
me . . . I'm too harmless . . . <hi rend="italic"> they don't believe in 
me!"</hi></p><p> 
     He broke off, and under his struggling eyebrows Willard saw 
the tears on his old lids.</p><p> 
     The young man gathered courage.  "But don't you see, sir, 
that's the reason it's no use?  We don't understand them any more 
than they do us; they know it, and all our witnessing for Christ 
will make no difference."</p><p> 
     Mr. Blandhorn looked at him sternly.  "Young man, no 
Christian 
has the right to say that."</p><p> 
     Willard ignored the rebuke.  "Come home, sir, come home . . 
. 
it's no use. . ."</p><p> 
     "It was because I foresaw you would take this view that I 
sent 
you to Mogador.  Since I was right," exclaimed Mr. Blandhorn, 
facing round on him fiercely, "how is it you have disobeyed me 
and 
come back?"</p><p> 
     Willard was looking at him with new eyes.  All his majesty 
seemed to have fallen from him with his Arab draperies.  How 
short 
and heavy and weak he looked in his scant European clothes!  The 
coat, tightly strained across the stomach, hung above it in loose 
wrinkles, and the ill-fitting trousers revealed their wearer's 
impressive legs as slightly bowed at the knees.  This diminution 
in 
his physical prestige was strangely moving to his disciple.  What 
was there left, with that gone&mdash;?</p><p> 
     "Oh, do come home, sir," the young man groaned.  "Of course 
they don't care what we do&mdash;of course&mdash;"</p><p> 
     "Ah&mdash;" cried Mr. Blandhorn, suddenly dashing past him into 
the 
open.</p><p> 
     The rumor of the crowd had become a sort of roaring chant.  
Over the thousands of bobbing heads that packed every cranny of 
the 
streets leading to the space before the Mosque there ran the 
mysterious sense of something new, invisible, but already 
imminent.  
Then, with the strange Oriental elasticity, the immense throng 
divided, and a new throng poured through it, headed by riders 
ritually draped, and overhung with banners that seemed to be 
lifted 
and floated aloft on the shouts of innumerable throats.  It was 
the 
Pasha of Eloued coming to pray at the tomb of Sidi Oman.</p><p> 
     Into this mass Mr. Blandhorn plunged and disappeared, while 
Willard Bent, for an endless minute, hung back in the shelter of 
the passage, the old "What's the use?" in his ears.</p><p> 
     A hand touched his sleeve, and a cracked voice echoed the 
words.</p><p> 
     "What's the use, master?"  It was old Myriem, clutching him 
with scared face and pulling out a limp djellabah from under her 
holiday shawl.</p><p> 
     "I saw you . . . Ahmed's father told me. . ."  (How 
everything 
was known in the bazaars!)  "Here, put this on quick, and slip 
away.  They won't trouble you. . ."</p><p> 
     "Oh, but they will&mdash;they <hi rend="italic"> shall!"</hi> roared Willard, in 
a 
voice unknown to his own ears, as he flung off the old woman's 
hand 
and, trampling on the djellabah in his flight, dashed into the 
crowd at the spot where it had swallowed up his master.</p><p> 
     They would&mdash;they <hi rend="italic"> should!</hi>  No more doubting and 
weighing 
and conjecturing!  The sight of the weak unwieldy old man, so 
ignorant, so defenseless and so convinced, disappearing alone 
into 
that red furnace of fanaticism, swept from the disciple's mind 
every thought but the single passion of devotion.</p><p> 
     "That he lay down his life for his friend&mdash;"  If he couldn't 
bring himself to believe in any other reason for what he 
<pb n="32"/>  was 
doing, that one seemed suddenly to be enough. . . 
</p><p> 
     The crowd let him through, still apparently indifferent to 
his 
advance.  Closer, closer he pushed to the doors of the Mosque, 
struggling and elbowing through a mass of people so densely 
jammed 
that the heat of their breathing was in his face, the rank taste 
of 
their bodies on his parched lips&mdash;closer, closer, till a last 
effort of his own thin body, which seemed a mere cage of ribs 
with 
a wild heart dashing against it, brought him to the doorway of 
the 
Mosque, where Mr. Blandhorn, his head thrown back, his arms 
crossed 
on his chest, stood steadily facing the heathen multitude.</p><p> 
     As Willard reached his side their glances met, and the old 
man, glaring out under prophetic brows, whispered, without moving 
his lips: "Now&mdash;<hi rend="italic"> now!"</hi></p><p> 
     Willard took it as a signal to follow, he knew not where or 
why: at that moment he had no wish to know.</p><p> 
     Mr. Blandhorn, without waiting for an answer, had turned, 
and, 
doubling on himself, sprung into the great court of the Mosque.  
Willard breathlessly followed, the glitter of tiles and the 
blinding sparkle of fountains in his dazzled eyes. . .</p><p> 
     The court was almost empty, the few who had been praying 
having shortened their devotions and joined the Pasha's train, 
which was skirting the outer walls of the Mosque to reach the 
shrine of Sidi Oman.  Willard was conscious of a moment of 
detached 
reconnoitring: once or twice, from the roof of a deserted college 
to which the government architect had taken him, he had looked 
down 
furtively on the forbidden scene, and his sense of direction told 
him that the black figure speeding across the blazing mirror of 
tiles was making for the hall where the Koran was expounded to 
students.</p><p> 
     Even now, as he followed, through the impending sense of 
something dangerous and tremendous, he had the feeling that after 
all the effort of will pumped up by his storming heart to his 
lucid 
brain might conceivably end in some pitiful anticlimax in the 
French Administration offices.</p><p> 
     "They'll treat us like whipped puppies&mdash;" he groaned.</p><p> 
     But Mr. Blandhorn had reached the school, had disappeared 
under its shadowy arcade, and emerged again into the sunlight, 
clutching a great parchment Koran.</p><p> 
     "Ah," thought Willard, <hi rend="italic">" now&mdash;!"</hi></p><p> 
     He found himself standing at the missionary's side, so close 
that they must have made one black blot against the white-hot 
quiver of tiles.  Mr. Blandhorn lifted up the Book and 
spoke.</p><p> 
     "The God whom ye ignorantly worship, Him declare I unto 
you," 
he cried in halting Arabic.</p><p> 
     A deep murmur came from the turbaned figures gathered under 
the arcade of the Mosque.  Swarthy faces lowered, eyes gleamed 
like 
agate, teeth blazed under snarling lips; but the group stood 
motionless, holding back, visibly restrained by the menace of the 
long arm of the Administration.</p><p> 
     "Him declare I unto you&mdash;Christ crucified!" cried Mr. 
Blandhorn.</p><p> 
     An old man, detaching himself from the group, advanced 
across 
the tiles and laid his hand on the missionary's arm.  Willard 
recognized the delegate of the Caid.</p><p> 
     "You must restore the Book," the delegate said gravely to 
Mr. 
Blandhorn, "and leave this court immediately; if not&mdash;"</p><p> 
     He held out his hand to take the Koran.  Mr. Blandhorn, in a 
flash, dodged the restraining arm, and, with a strange new 
elasticity of his cumbrous body, rolling and bouncing across the 
court between the dazed spectators, gained the gateway opening on 
the market-place behind the Mosque.  The centre of the great 
dusty 
space was at the moment almost deserted.  Mr. Blandhorn sprang 
forward, the Koran clutched to him, Willard panting at his heels, 
and the turbaned crowd after them, menacing but still visibly 
restrained.</p><p> 
     In the middle of the square Mr. Blandhorn halted, faced 
about 
and lifted the Koran high above his head.  Willard, rigid at his 
side, was obliquely conscious of the gesture, and at the same 
time 
aware that the free space about them was rapidly diminishing 
under 
the mounting tide of people swarming in from every quarter.  The 
faces closest were no longer the gravely wrathful countenances of 
the <pb n="33"/>  Mosque, but lean fanatical masks of 
pilgrims, beggars, 
wandering "saints" and miracle-makers, and dark tribesmen of the 
hills careless of their creed but hot to join in the halloo 
against 
the hated stranger.  Far off in the throng, bobbing like a float 
on 
the fierce sea of turbans, Willard saw the round brown face of a 
native officer frantically fighting his way through.  Now and 
then 
the face bobbed nearer, and now and then a tug of the tide rolled 
it back.</p><p> 
     Willard felt Mr. Blandhorn's touch on his arm.</p><p> 
     "You're with me&mdash;?"</p><p> 
     "Yes&mdash;"</p><p> 
     The old man's voice sank and broke.  "Say a word to . . . 
strengthen me . . . I can't find any . . . Willard," he 
whispered.</p><p> 
     Willard's brain was a blank.  But against the blank a phrase 
suddenly flashed out in fire, and he turned and spoke to his 
master.  <hi rend="italic">" Say among the heathen that the Lord 
reigneth."</hi></p><p> 
     "Ah&mdash;"  Mr. Blandhorn, with a gasp, drew himself to his full 
height and hurled the Koran down at his feet in the dung-strown 
dust.</p><p> 
     "Him, Him declare I unto you&mdash;Christ crucified!" he 
thundered: 
and to Willard, in a fierce aside: "Now spit!"</p><p> 
     Dazed a moment, the young man stood uncertain; then he saw 
the 
old missionary draw back a step, bend forward, and deliberately 
spit upon the sacred pages.</p><p> 
     "This . . . is abominable . . ." the disciple thought; and, 
sucking up the last drop of saliva from his dry throat, he also 
bent and spat.</p><p> 
     "Now trample&mdash;<hi rend="italic"> trample!"</hi> commanded Mr. Blandhorn, his 
arms 
stretched out, towering black and immense, as if crucified 
against 
the flaming sky; and his foot came down on the polluted 
Book.</p><p> 
     Willard, seized with the communicative frenzy, fell on his 
knees, tearing at the pages, and scattering them about him, 
smirched and defiled in the dust.</p><p> 
     "Spit&mdash;spit!  Trample&mdash;trample! . . .  Christ!  I see the 
heavens opened!" shrieked the old missionary, covering his eyes 
with his hands.  But what he said next was lost to his disciple 
in 
the rising roar of the mob which had closed in on them.  Far off, 
Willard caught a glimpse of the native officer's bobbing head, 
and 
then of Lieutenant Lourdenay's scared face.  But a moment later 
he 
had veiled his own face from the sight of the struggle at his 
side.  
Mr. Blandhorn had fallen on his knees, and Willard heard him cry 
out once: "Amy!  Amy!"  It was his wife's name.</p><p> 
     Then the young man was himself borne down, and darkness 
descended on him.  Through it he felt the sting of separate pangs 
indescribable, melting at last into a general mist of pain.  He 
remembered Stephen, and thought: "Now they're stoning me&mdash;" and 
tried to struggle up and reach out to Mr. Blandhorn. . .</p><p> 
     But the market-place seemed suddenly empty, as though the 
throng of their assailants had been demons of the desert, the 
thin 
spirits of evil that dance on the noonday heat.  Now the dusk 
seemed to have dispersed them, and Willard looked up and saw a 
quiet star above a wall, and heard the cry of the Muezzin 
dropping 
down from a near-by minaret: "Allah&mdash;Allah&mdash;only Allah is 
great!"</p><p> 
     Willard closed his eyes, and in his great weakness felt the 
tears run down between his lids.  A hand wiped them away, and he 
looked again, and saw the face of Harry Spink stooping over 
him.</p><p> 
     He supposed it was a dream-Spink, and smiled a little, and 
the 
dream smiled back.</p><p> 
     "Where am I?" Willard wondered to himself; and the 
dream-Spink 
answered: "In the hospital, you infernal fool.  I got back too 
late&mdash;"</p><p> 
     "You came back&mdash;?"</p><p> 
     "Of course.  Lucky I did&mdash;!  I saw this morning you were off 
your base."</p><p> 
     Willard, for a long time, lay still.  Impressions reached 
him 
slowly, and he had to deal with them one by one, like a puzzled 
child.</p><p> 
     At length he said: "Mr. Blandhorn&mdash;?"</p><p> 
     "They did for him in no time; I guess his heart was weak . . 
. I don't think he suffered.  Anyhow, if he did he wasn't sorry; 
I 
know, because I saw his face before they buried him. . .  Now you 
lie still, and I'll get you out of this to-morrow," he commanded, 
waving a fly-cloth above Willard's sunken head.</p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
