<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhaVerd"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="WhaVerd"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Verdict</title>
<title type="sort">verdict</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">25</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">WhaVerd</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476532</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Verdict</title>
<title type="sort">verdict</title>
<author>Wharton, Edith</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner's Magazine</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1908-06">June 1908</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Volume 43</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>Verification made against printed text</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of  
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1908">1908</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995">1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added.</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
<head> 
Wharton, Edith.  "The Verdict."   
<lb/> 
<hi rend="italic"> Scribner's Magazine</hi> 43 (June 1908): 689-693. 
</head> 
<pb n="689"/>  

<p> 
I HAD always thought Jack Gisburn rather a cheap genius&mdash;though a 
good fellow enough&mdash;so it was no great surprise to me to hear that, 
in the height of his glory, he had dropped his painting, married a 
rich widow, and established himself in a villa on the Riviera.  
(Though I rather thought it would have been Rome or Florence.) 
</p><p>"The height of his glory"&mdash;that was what the women called it.  
I can hear Mrs. Gideon Thwing&mdash;his last Chicago sitter&mdash;deploring 
his unaccountable abdication.  "Of course it's going to send the 
value of my picture 'way up; but I don't think of that, Mr. 
Rickham&mdash;the loss to Arrt is all I think of."  The word, on Mrs. 
Thwing's lips, multiplied its <hi rend="italic"> rs</hi> as though they were reflected 
in an endless vista of mirrors.  And it was not only the Mrs. 
Thwings who mourned.  Had not the exquisite Hermia Croft, at the 
last Grafton Gallery show, stopped me before Gisburn's "Moon-dancers" to say, with tears in her eyes: "We shall not look upon 
its like again"? 
</p><p>Well!&mdash;even through the prism of Hermia's tears I felt able to 
face the fact with equanimity.  Poor Jack Gisburn!  The women had 
made him&mdash;it was fitting that they should mourn him.  Among his own 
sex fewer regrets were heard, and in his own trade hardly a murmur.  
Professional jealousy?  Perhaps.  If it were, the honour of the 
craft was vindicated by little Claude Nutley, who, in all good 
faith, brought out in the Burlington a very handsome "obituary" on 
Jack&mdash;one of those showy articles stocked with random 
technicalities that I have heard (I won't say by whom) compared to 
Gisburn's painting.  And so&mdash;his resolve being apparently 
irrevocable&mdash;the discussion gradually died out, and, as Mrs. Thwing 
had predicted, the price of "Gisburns" went up. 
</p><p>It was not till three years later that, in the course of a few 
weeks' idling on the Riviera, it suddenly occurred to me to wonder 
why Gisburn had given up his painting.  On reflection, it really 
was a tempting problem.  To accuse his wife would have been too 
easy&mdash;his fair sitters had been denied the solace of saying that 
Mrs. Gisburn had "dragged him down."  For Mrs. Gisburn&mdash;as such&mdash; 
had not existed till nearly a year after Jack's resolve had been 
taken.  It might be that he had married her&mdash;since he liked his 
ease&mdash;because he didn't want to go on painting; but it would have 
been hard to prove that he had given up his painting because he had 
married her. 
</p><p>Of course, if she had not dragged him down, she had equally, 
as Miss Croft contended, failed to "lift him up"&mdash;she had not led 
him back to the easel.  To put the brush into his hand again&mdash;what 
a vocation for a wife!  But Mrs. Gisburn appeared to have disdained 
it&mdash;and I felt it might be interesting to find out why. 
</p><p>The desultory life of the Riviera lends itself to such purely 
academic speculations; and having, on my way to Monte Carlo, caught 
a glimpse of Jack's balustraded terraces between the pines, I had 
myself borne thither the next day. 
</p><p>I found the couple at tea beneath their palm-trees; and Mrs. 
Gisburn's welcome <pb n="690"/>  was so genial that, in the ensuing weeks, 
I claimed it frequently.  It was not that my hostess was 
"interesting": on that point I could have given Miss Croft the 
fullest reassurance.  It was just because she was <hi rend="italic"> not</hi> 
interesting&mdash;if I may be pardoned the bull&mdash;that I found her so.  
For Jack, all his life, had been surrounded by interesting women: 
they had fostered his art, it had been reared in the hot-house of 
their adulation.  And it was therefore instructive to note what 
effect the "deadening atmosphere of mediocrity" (I quote Miss 
Croft) was having on him. 
</p><p>I have mentioned that Mrs. Gisburn was rich; and it was 
immediately perceptible that her husband was extracting from this 
circumstance a delicate but substantial satisfaction.  It is, as a 
rule, the people who scorn money who get most out of it; and Jack's 
elegant disdain of his wife's big balance enabled him, with an 
appearance of perfect good-breeding, to transmute it into objects 
of art and luxury.  To the latter, I must add, he remained 
relatively indifferent; but he was buying Renaissance bronzes and 
eighteenth-century pictures with a discrimination that bespoke the 
amplest resources. 
</p><p>"Money's only excuse is to put beauty into circulation," was 
one of the axioms he laid down across the Sevres and silver of an 
exquisitely appointed luncheon-table, when, on a later day, I had 
again run over from Monte Carlo; and Mrs. Gisburn, beaming on him, 
added for my enlightenment: "Jack is so morbidly sensitive to every 
form of beauty." 
</p><p>Poor Jack!  It had always been his fate to have women say such 
things of him: the fact should be set down in extenuation.  What 
struck me now was that, for the first time, he resented the tone.  
I had seen him, so often, basking under similar tributes&mdash;was it 
the conjugal note that robbed them of their savour?  No&mdash;for, oddly 
enough, it became apparent that he was fond of Mrs. Gisburn&mdash;fond 
enough not to see her absurdity.  It was his own absurdity he 
seemed to be wincing under&mdash;his own attitude as an object for 
garlands and incense. 
</p><p>"My dear, since I've chucked painting people don't say that 
stuff about me&mdash;they say it about Victor Grindle," was his only 
protest, as he rose from the table and strolled out onto the sunlit 
terrace. 
</p><p>I glanced after him, struck by his last word.  Victor Grindle 
was, in fact, becoming the man of the moment&mdash;as Jack himself, one 
might put it, had been the man of the hour.  The younger artist was 
said to have formed himself at my friend's feet, and I wondered if 
a tinge of jealousy underlay the latter's mysterious abdication.  
But no&mdash;for it was not till after that event that the <hi rend="italic"> rose 
Dubarry</hi> drawing-rooms had begun to display their "Grindles." 
</p><p>I turned to Mrs. Gisburn, who had lingered to give a lump of 
sugar to her spaniel in the dining-room. 
</p><p>"Why <hi rend="italic"> has</hi> he chucked painting?" I asked abruptly. 
</p><p>She raised her eyebrows with a hint of good-humoured surprise. 
</p><p>"Oh, he doesn't <hi rend="italic"> have</hi> to now, you know; and I want him to 
enjoy himself," she said quite simply. 
</p><p>I looked about the spacious white-panelled room, with its <hi rend="italic">
famille-verte</hi> vases repeating the tones of the pale damask 
curtains, and its eighteenth-century pastels in delicate faded 
frames. 
</p><p>"Has he chucked his pictures too?  I haven't seen a single one 
in the house." 
</p><p>A slight shade of constraint crossed Mrs. Gisburn's open 
countenance.  "It's his ridiculous modesty, you know.  He says 
they're not fit to have about; he's sent them all away except one&mdash; 
my portrait&mdash;and that I have to keep upstairs." 
</p><p>His ridiculous modesty&mdash;Jack's modesty about his pictures?  My 
curiosity was growing like the bean-stalk.  I said persuasively to 
my hostess: "I must really see your portrait, you know." 
</p><p>She glanced out almost timorously at the terrace where her 
husband, lounging in a hooded chair, had lit a cigar and drawn the 
Russian deerhound's head between his knees. 
</p><p>"Well, come while he's not looking," she said, with a laugh 
that tried to hide her nervousness; and I followed her between the 
marble Emperors of the hall, and up the wide stairs with terra-cotta nymphs poised among flowers at each landing. 
</p><p>In the dimmest corner of her boudoir, amid a profusion of 
delicate and distinguished objects, hung one of the familiar oval 
canvases, in the inevitable garlanded frame.  The mere outline of 
the frame called up all Gisburn's past! <pb n="691"/>  
</p><p>Mrs. Gisburn drew back the window-curtains, moved aside a <hi rend="italic">
jardiniere</hi> full of pink azaleas, pushed an arm-chair away, and 
said: "If you stand here you can just manage to see it.  I had it 
over the mantel-piece, but he wouldn't let it stay." 
</p><p>Yes&mdash;I could just manage to see it&mdash;the first portrait of 
Jack's I had ever had to strain my eyes over!  Usually they had the 
place of honour&mdash;say the central panel in a pale yellow or <hi rend="italic"> rose 
Dubarry</hi> drawing-room, or a monumental easel placed so that it took 
the light through curtains of old Venetian point.  The more modest 
place became the picture better; yet, as my eyes grew accustomed to 
the half-light, all the characteristic qualities came out&mdash;all the 
hesitations disguised as audacities, the tricks of prestidigitation 
by which, with such consummate skill, he managed to divert 
attention from the real business of the picture to some pretty 
irrelevance of detail.  Mrs. Gisburn, presenting a neutral surface 
to work on&mdash;forming, as it were, so inevitably the background of 
her own picture&mdash;had lent herself in an unusual degree to the 
display of this false virtuosity.  The picture was one of Jack's 
"strongest," as his admirers would have put it&mdash;it represented, on 
his part, a swelling of muscles, a congesting of veins, a 
balancing, straddling and straining, that reminded one of the 
circus-clown's ironic efforts to lift a feather.  It met, in short, 
at every point the demand of lovely woman to be painted "strongly" 
because she was tired of being painted "sweetly"&mdash;and yet not to 
lose an atom of the sweetness. 
</p><p>"It's the last he painted, you know," Mrs. Gisburn said with 
pardonable pride.  "The last but one," she corrected herself&mdash;"but 
the other doesn't count, because he destroyed it." 
</p><p>"Destroyed it?"  I was about to follow up this clue when I 
heard a footstep and saw Jack himself on the threshold. 
</p><p>As he stood there, his hands in the pockets of his velveteen 
coat, the thin brown waves of hair pushed back from his white 
forehead, his lean sunburnt cheeks furrowed by a smile that lifted 
the tips of a self-confident moustache, I felt to what a degree he 
had the same quality as his pictures&mdash;the quality of looking 
cleverer than he was. 
</p><p>His wife glanced at him deprecatingly, but his eyes travelled 
past her to the portrait. 
</p><p>"Mr. Rickham wanted to see it," she began, as if excusing 
herself.  He shrugged his shoulders, still smiling. 
</p><p>"Oh, Rickham found me out long ago," he said lightly; then, 
passing his arm through mine: "Come and see the rest of the house." 
</p><p>He showed it to me with a kind of naive suburban pride: the 
bath-rooms, the speaking-tubes, the dress-closets, the trouser-presses&mdash;all the complex simplifications of the millionaire's 
domestic economy.  And whenever my wonder paid the expected tribute 
he said, throwing out his chest a little: "Yes, I really don't see 
how people manage to live without that." 
</p><p>Well&mdash;it was just the end one might have foreseen for him.  
Only he was, through it all and in spite of it all&mdash;as he had been 
through, and in spite of, his pictures&mdash;so handsome, so charming, 
so disarming, that one longed to cry out: "Be dissatisfied with 
your leisure!" as once one had longed to say: "Be dissatisfied with 
your work!" 
</p><p>But, with the cry on my lips, my diagnosis suffered an 
unexpected check. 
</p><p>"This is my own lair," he said, leading me into a dark plain 
room at the end of the florid vista.  It was square and brown and 
leathery: no "effects"; no bric-a-brac, none of the air of posing 
for reproduction in a picture weekly&mdash;above all, no least sign of 
ever having been used as a studio. 
</p><p>The fact brought home to me the absolute finality of Jack's 
break with his old life. 
</p><p>"Don't you ever dabble with paint any more?" I asked, still 
looking about for a trace of such activity. 
</p><p>"Never," he said briefly. 
</p><p>"Or water-colour&mdash;or etching?" 
</p><p>His confident eyes grew dim, and his cheeks paled a little 
under their handsome sunburn. 
</p><p>"Never think of it, my dear fellow&mdash;any more than if I'd never 
touched a brush." 
</p><p>And his tone told me in a flash that he never thought of 
anything else. 
</p><p>I moved away, instinctively embarrassed by my unexpected 
discovery; and as I turned, my eye fell on a small picture above 
the mantel-piece&mdash;the only object breaking the plain oak panelling 
of the room. 
</p><p>"Oh, by Jove!" I said. 
</p><p>It was a sketch of a donkey&mdash;an old tired donkey, standing in 
the rain under a wall. <pb n="692"/>  
</p><p>"By Jove&mdash;a Stroud!" I cried. 
</p><p>He was silent; but I felt him close behind me, breathing a 
little quickly. 
</p><p>"What a wonder!  Made with a dozen lines&mdash;but on everlasting 
foundations.  You lucky chap, where did you get it?" 
</p><p>He answered slowly: "Mrs. Stroud gave it to me." 
</p><p>"Ah&mdash;I didn't know you even knew the Strouds.  He was such an 
inflexible hermit." 
</p><p>"I didn't&mdash;till after. . . .  She sent for me to paint him 
when he was dead." 
</p><p>"When he was dead?  You?" 
</p><p>I must have let a little too much amazement escape through my 
surprise, for he answered with a deprecating laugh: "Yes&mdash;she's an 
awful simpleton, you know, Mrs. Stroud.  Her only idea was to have 
him done by a fashionable painter&mdash;ah, poor Stroud!  She thought it 
the surest way of proclaiming his greatness&mdash;of forcing it on a 
purblind public.  And at the moment I was <hi rend="italic"> the</hi> fashionable 
painter." 
</p><p>"Ah, poor Stroud&mdash;as you say.  Was <hi rend="italic"> that</hi> his history?" 
</p><p>"That was his history.  She believed in him, gloried in him&mdash; 
or thought she did.  But she couldn't bear not to have all the 
drawing-rooms with her.  She couldn't bear the fact that, on 
varnishing days, one could always get near enough to see his 
pictures.  Poor woman!  She's just a fragment groping for other 
fragments.  Stroud is the only whole I ever knew." 
</p><p>"You ever knew?  But you just said&mdash;" 
</p><p>Gisburn had a curious smile in his eyes. 
</p><p>"Oh, I knew him, and he knew me&mdash;only it happened after he was 
dead." 
</p><p>I dropped my voice instinctively.  "When she sent for you?" 
</p><p>"Yes&mdash;quite insensible to the irony.  She wanted him 
vindicated&mdash;and by me!" 
</p><p>He laughed again, and threw back his head to look up at the 
sketch of the donkey.  "There were days when I couldn't look at 
that thing&mdash;couldn't face it.  But I forced myself to put it here; 
and now it's cured me&mdash;cured me.  That's the reason why I don't 
dabble any more, my dear Rickham; or rather Stroud himself is the 
reason." 
</p><p>For the first time my idle curiosity about my companion turned 
into a serious desire to understand him better. 
</p><p>"I wish you'd tell me how it happened," I said. 
</p><p>He stood looking up at the sketch, and twirling between his 
fingers a cigarette he had forgotten to light.  Suddenly he turned 
toward me. 
</p><p>"I'd rather like to tell you&mdash;because I've always suspected 
you of loathing my work." 
</p><p>I made a deprecating gesture, which he negatived with a good-humoured shrug. 
</p><p>"Oh, I didn't care a straw when I believed in myself&mdash;and now 
it's an added tie between us!" 
</p><p>He laughed slightly, without bitterness, and pushed one of the 
deep arm-chairs forward.  "There: make yourself comfortable&mdash;and 
here are the cigars you like." 
</p><p>He placed them at my elbow and continued to wander up and down 
the room, stopping now and then beneath the picture. 
</p><p>"How it happened?  I can tell you in five minutes&mdash;and it 
didn't take much longer to happen. . . .  I can remember now how 
surprised and pleased I was when I got Mrs. Stroud's note.  Of 
course, deep down, I had always <hi rend="italic"> felt</hi> there was no one like him--only I had gone with the stream, echoed the usual platitudes about 
him, till I half got to think he was a failure, one of the kind 
that are left behind.  By Jove, and he <hi rend="italic"> was</hi> left behind&mdash;because 
he had come to stay!  The rest of us had to let ourselves be swept 
along or go under, but he was high above the current&mdash;on 
everlasting foundations, as you say. 
</p><p>"Well, I went off to the house in my most egregious mood&mdash; 
rather moved, Lord forgive me, at the pathos of poor Stroud's 
career of failure being crowned by the glory of my painting him!  
Of course I meant to do the picture for nothing&mdash;I told Mrs. Stroud 
so when she began to stammer something about her poverty.  I 
remember getting off a prodigious phrase about the honour being <hi rend="italic">
mine</hi>&mdash;oh, I was princely, my dear Rickham!  I was posing to myself 
like one of my own sitters. 
</p><p>"Then I was taken up and left alone with him.  I had sent all 
my traps in advance, and I had only to set up the easel and get to 
work.  He had been dead only twenty-four hours, and he died 
suddenly, of heart disease, so that there had been no preliminary 
work of destruction&mdash;his face was clear and untouched.  I had met 
him once or twice, years before, and thought him insignificant and 
dingy.  Now I saw that he was superb. 
</p><p>"I was glad at first, with a merely aes-<pb n="693"/> thetic 
satisfaction: glad to have my hand on such a 'subject.'  Then his 
strange life-likeness began to affect me queerly&mdash;as I blocked the 
head in I felt as if he were watching me do it.  The sensation was 
followed by the thought: if he <hi rend="italic"> were</hi> watching me, what would he 
say to my way of working?  My strokes began to go a little wild&mdash;I 
felt nervous and uncertain. 
</p><p>"Once, when I looked up, I seemed to see a smile behind his 
close grayish beard&mdash;as if he had the secret, and were amusing 
himself by holding it back from me.  That exasperated me still 
more.  The secret?  Why, I had a secret worth twenty of his!  I 
dashed at the canvas furiously, and tried some of my bravura 
tricks.  But they failed me, they crumbled.  I saw that he wasn't 
watching the showy bits&mdash;I couldn't distract his attention; he just 
kept his eyes on the hard passages between.  Those were the ones I 
had always shirked, or covered up with some lying paint.  And how 
he saw through my lies! 
</p><p>"I looked up again, and caught sight of that sketch of the 
donkey hanging on the wall near his bed.  His wife told me 
afterward it was the last thing he had done&mdash;just a note taken with 
a shaking hand, when he was down in Devonshire recovering from a 
previous heart attack.  Just a note!  But it tells his whole 
history.  There are years of patient scornful persistence in every 
line.  A man who had swum with the current could never have learned 
that mighty up-stream stroke. . . . 
</p><p>"I turned back to my work, and went on groping and muddling; 
then I looked at the donkey again.  I saw that, when Stroud laid in 
the first stroke, he knew just what the end would be.  He had 
possessed his subject, absorbed it, recreated it.  When had I done 
that with any of my things?  They hadn't been born of me&mdash;I had 
just adopted them. . . . 
</p><p>"Hang it, Rickham, with that face watching me I couldn't do 
another stroke.  The plain truth was, I didn't know where to put 
it&mdash;<hi rend="italic"> I had never known</hi>.  Only, with my sitters and my public, a 
showy splash of colour covered up the fact&mdash;I just threw paint into 
their faces. . . .  Well, paint was the one medium those dead eyes 
could see through&mdash;see straight to the tottering foundations 
underneath.  Don't you know how, in talking a foreign language, 
even fluently, one says half the time not what one wants to but 
what one can?  Well&mdash;that was the way I painted; and as he lay 
there and watched me, the thing they called my 'technique' 
collapsed like a house of cards.  He didn't sneer, you understand, 
poor Stroud&mdash;he just lay there quietly watching, and on his lips, 
through the gray beard, I seemed to hear the question: 'Are you 
sure you know where you're coming out?' 
</p><p>"If I could have painted that face, with that question on it, 
I should have done a great thing.  The next greatest thing was to 
see that I couldn't&mdash;and that grace was given me.  But, oh, at that 
minute, Rickham, was there anything on earth I wouldn't have given 
to have Stroud alive before me, and to hear him say: 'It's not too 
late&mdash;I'll show you how'? 
</p><p>"It <hi rend="italic"> was</hi> too late&mdash;it would have been, even if he'd been 
alive.  I packed up my traps, and went down and told Mrs. Stroud.  
Of course I didn't tell her <hi rend="italic"> that</hi>&mdash;it would have been Greek to 
her.  I simply said I couldn't paint him, that I was too moved.  
She rather liked the idea&mdash;she's so romantic!  It was that that 
made her give me the donkey.  But she was terribly upset at not 
getting the portrait&mdash;she did so want him 'done' by some one showy!  
At first I was afraid she wouldn't let me off&mdash;and at my wits' end 
I suggested Grindle.  Yes, it was I who started Grindle: I told 
Mrs. Stroud he was the 'coming' man, and she told somebody else, 
and so it got to be true. . . .  And he painted Stroud without 
wincing; and she hung the picture among her husband's things. . . 
." 
</p><p>He flung himself down in the arm-chair near mine, laid back 
his head, and clasping his arms beneath it, looked up at the 
picture above the chimney-piece. 
</p><p>"I like to fancy that Stroud himself would have given it to 
me, if he'd been able to say what he thought that day." 
</p><p>And, in answer to a question I put half-mechanically&mdash;"Begin 
again?" he flashed out.  "When the one thing that brings me 
anywhere near him is that I knew enough to leave off?" 
</p><p>He stood up and laid his hand on my shoulder with a laugh.  
"Only the irony of it is that I <hi rend="italic"> am</hi> still painting&mdash;since 
Grindle's doing it for me!  The Strouds stand alone, and happen 
once&mdash;but there's no exterminating our kind of art." 
</p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
