<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhiCala"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
   
]> 
 
<TEI.2 id="WhiCala"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Calamus poems : from Leaves of Grass (1860)</title>
<title type="sort">calamus poems from leaves of grass 1860</title>
<author>Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Tom Lukas</name> 
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp> 
<name>Edward Gaynor</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>Tom Lukas, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">50</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WhiCala</idno> 
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476541</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Page images and manuscript images have been included from the print version.</p>
</note> 
</notesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Calamus Poems: Leaves of Grass</title>
<title type="sort">calamus poems leaves of grass</title>
<author>Walt Whitman</author>
</titleStmt> 
<editionStmt>
<p>3rd Edition.</p>
</editionStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Thayer and Eldridge</publisher> 
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace> 
<date value="1860">1860</date>
</publicationStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p> 
<p>Spell-check and verification made 
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions 
for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1860">1860</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>poetry</term>
</keywords> 
<keywords>
<term>24-bit color; 400 dpi</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-07">July, 1996</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Tom Lukas</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>added TEI-2 tagging, added page images</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2"> 

<div1 type="poem" n="1" id="d3"> <pb n="341" id="WhiCala341"/> 

<head>Calamus<lb/>1.</head> 
<l>In paths untrodden,</l> 
<l>In the growth by margins of pond waters,</l> 
<l>Escaped from the life that exhibits itself,</l> 
<l>From all the standards hitherto published&mdash;from 
    the pleasures, profits, conformities,</l> 
<l>Which too long I was offering to feed my Soul;</l> 
<l>Clear to me now, standards not yet published&mdash; 
 clear to me that my Soul,</l> 
<l>That the Soul of the man I speak for, feeds, rejoices 
only in comrades;</l> 
<l>Here, by myself, away from the clank of the world,</l> 
<l>Tallying and talked to here by tongues aromatic,</l> 
<l>No longer abashed&mdash;for in this secluded spot I can 
respond as I would not dare elsewhere,</l> 
<l>Strong upon me the life that does not exhibit itself, 
yet contains all the rest,</l> 
<l>Resolved to sing no songs to-day but those of manly 
attachment,</l> 
<l>Projecting them along that substantial life,</l> 
<l>Bequeathing, hence, types of athletic love</l>                                
 
<pb n="342" id="WhiCala342"/> 
 
<l>Afternoon, this delicious Ninth Month, in my forty-first year,</l> 
<l>I proceed, for all who are, or have been, young 
men,</l> 
<l>To tell the secret of my nights and days,</l> 
<l>To celebrate the need of comrades.</l> 
</div1> 
 
<div1 type="poem" n="2" id="d4"> <pb n="343" id="WhiCala343"/> 
<head>2.</head> 
<l>Scented herbage of my breast,</l> 
<l>Leaves from you I yield, I write, to be perused best afterwards,</l> 
<l>Tomb-leaves, body leaves, growing up above me, above death,</l> 
<l>Perennial roots, tall leaves&mdash;O the winter shall not freeze you, delicate leaves,</l> 
<l>Every year shall you bloom again&mdash;Out from where you retired, you shall emerge again;</l> 
<l>O I do not know whether many, passing by, will discover you, or inhale your faint odor&mdash;but I  
    believe a few will;</l> 
<l>O slender leaves! O blossoms of my blood!  I permit you to tell, in your own way, of the heart 
that is under you,</l> 
<l>O burning and throbbing&mdash;surely all will one day be accomplished;</l> 
<l>O I do not know what mean, there underneath yourselves&mdash;you are not happiness,</l> 
<l>You are often more bitter than I can bear&mdash;you burn and sting me,</l> 
<pb n="344" id="WhiCala344"/> 
<l>Yet you are very beautiful to me, you faint-tinged roots&mdash;you make me think of Death,</l> 
<l>Death is beautiful from you&mdash;(what indeed is beautiful, except Death and Love?)</l> 
<l>O I think it is not for life I am chanting here my chant of lovers&mdash;I think it must be for 
Death,</l> 
<l>For how calm, how solemn it grows, to ascend to the atmosphere of lovers,</l> 
<l>Death or life I am then indifferent&mdash;my soul declines to prefer,</l> 
<l>I am not sure but the high Soul of lovers welcomes death most;</l> 
<l>Indeed, O Death, I think now these leaves mean precicely the same as you mean;</l> 
<l>Grow up taller, sweet leaves, that I may see! Grow up out of my breast!</l> 
<l>Spring away from the concealed heart there!</l> 
<l>Do not fold yourselves so in you pink-tinged roots, timid leaves!</l> 
<l>Do not remain down there so ashamed, herbage of my breast!</l> 
<l>Come, I am determined to unbare this broad breast of mine&mdash;I have long enough stifled and 
choked;</l> 
<l>Emblematic and capricious blades, I leave you&mdash;now you serve me not,</l>  
<l>Away! I will say what I have to say, by itself,</l>  
<l>I will escape from the sham that was proposed to me,</l> 
<l>I will sound myself and comrades only&mdash;I will never again utter a call, only their call,</l> 
<l>I will raise, with it, immortal reverberations through The States,</l> 
<l>I will give an example to lovers, to take permanent shape and will through The States;</l> 
 
<pb n="345" id="WhiCala345"/> 
 
<l>Through me shall the words be said to make death exhilarating,</l> 
<l>Give me your tone therefore, O Death, that I may accord with it,</l> 
<l>Give me yourself&mdash;for I see that you belong to me now above all, and are folded together 
above all&mdash;you Love and Death are,</l> 
<l>Nor will I allow you to balk me any more with what I was calling life,</l> 
<l>For now it is conveyed to me that you are the purports essential,</l> 
<l>That you hide in these shifting forms of life, for reasons&mdash;and that they are mainly for you,</l> 
<l>That you, beyond them, come forth, to remain, the real reality,</l> 
<l>That behind the mask of materials you patiently 
wait, no matter how long,</l> 
<l>That you will one day, perhaps, take control of all,</l> 
<l>That you will perhaps dissipate this entire show of appearance,</l> 
<l>That may be you are what it is all for&mdash;but it does not last so very long,</l> 
<l>But you will last very long.</l></div1>
 
<div1 type="poem" n="3" id="d5"> <pb n="346" id="WhiCala346"/> 
<head>3.</head> 
<lg type="stanza" n="1"> 
<head>1.</head> 
 
<l>Whoever you are holding me now in hand,</l> 
<l>Without one thing all will be useless,</l> 
<l>I give you fair warning, before you attempt me further,</l> 
<l>I am not what you supposed, but far different.</l> 
</lg> 
<lg type="stanza" n="2"> 
<head>2.</head> 
<l>Who is he that would become my follower?</l> 
<l>Who would sign himself a candidate for my affections? Are you he?</l> 
</lg> 
<lg type="stanza" n="3"> 
<head>3.</head> 
<l>The way is suspicious&mdash;the result slow, uncertain, may-be destructive;</l> 
<l>You would have to give up all else&mdash;I alone would expect to be your God, sole and 
exclusive,</l> 
<l>Your novitiate would even then be long and exhausting,</l> 
<l>The whole past theory of your life, and all conformity to the lives around you, would have to 
be abandoned;</l> 
<l>Therefore release me now, before troubling yourself any further&mdash;Let go your hand from my  
shoulders,</l> 
<l>Put me down, and depart on your way.</l></lg> 
 
<lg type="stanza" n="4"> 
<head>4.</head> 
<l>Or else, only by stealth, in some wood, for trial,</l> 
<l>Or back of a rock, in open air,</l> 
<l>(for in any roofed room of a house I emerge not&mdash;nor in company,</l> 
<l>And in the libraries I lie as one dumb, a gawk, or unborn, or dead,)</l> 
<l>But just possibly with you on a high hill&mdash;first watching lest any person, for miles around, 
approach unawares,</l> 
<l>Or possibly with you sailing at sea, or on the beach of 
the sea, or some quiet island,</l> 
<l>Here to put your lips upon mine I permit you,</l> 
<l>With the comrade's long-dwelling kiss, or the new 
husband's kiss,</l> 
<l>For I am the new husband, and I am the comrade.</l> 
</lg> 
 
 
<pb n="347" id="WhiCala347"/>      
<lg type="stanza" n="5"> 
<head>5.</head> 
<l>Or, if you will, thrusting me beneath your clothing,</l> 
<l>Where I may feel the throbs of your heart, or rest 
upon your hip,</l> 
<l>Carry me when you go forth over land and sea;</l> 
<l>For thus, merely touching you, is enough&mdash;is best</l> 
<l>And thus, touching you, would I silently sleep and be 
carried eternally.</l> 
</lg> 
<lg type="stanza" n="6"> 
<head>6.</head> 
<l>But these leaves conning, you con at  peril,</l> 
<l>For these leaves, and me, you will not understand,</l> 
<l>They will elude you at first, and still more afterward&mdash;I will certainly elude you,</l> 
<l>Even while you should think you had unquestionably caught me, behold!</l> 
<l>Already you see I have escaped from you.</l></lg> 
<lg type="stanza" n="7"> 
<head>7.</head> 
<l>For it is not for what I have put into it that I have 
written this book,</l> 
<l>Nor is it by reading it you will acquire it,</l> 
<l>Nor do those know me best who admire me, and  
vauntingly praise me,</l> 
<l>Nor will the candidates for my love, (unless at most a 
very few,) prove victorious,</l> 
<l>Nor will my poems do good only&mdash;they will do just 
as much evil, perhaps more,</l> 
<l>For all is useless without that which you may guess 
at many times and not hit&mdash;that which I hinted at,</l> 
<l>Therefore release me and depart on your way.</l></lg></div1> 

<div1 type="poem" n="4" id="d6"> <pb n="348" id="WhiCala348"/> 
<head>4</head> 
 
<l>These I, singing in spring, collect for lovers,</l> 
<l>(For who but I should understand lovers, and all their sorrow and joy?</l> 
<l>And who but I should be the poet of comrades?)</l> 
<l>Collecting, I traverse the garden, the world&mdash;but soon I pass the gates,</l> 
<l>Now along the pond-side&mdash;now wading in a little, fearing not the wet,</l> 
<l>Now by the post-and-rail fences, where the old stones thrown there, picked from the fields, 
have accumulated,</l> 
<l>Wild-flowers and vines and weeds come up through the stones, and partly cover 
them&mdash;Beyond these I pass,</l> 
<l>Far, far in the forest, before I think where I get,</l> 
<l>Solitary, smelling the earthly smell, stopping now and then in silence,</l> 
<l>Alone I had thought&mdash;yet soon a silent troop gathers around me,</l> 
<l>Some walk by my side, and some behind, and some embrace my arms or neck,</l> 
<l>They, the spirits of friends, dead or alive&mdash;thicker they come, a great crowd, and I in the 
middle,</l> 
<l>Collecting, dispensing, singing in spring, there I wander with them,</l> 
<l>Plucking something for tokens&mdash;something for these, till I hit upon a theme&mdash;tossing toward 
whoever is near me,</l> 
 
<pb n="349" id="WhiCala349"/> 
 
<l>Here! lilac, with a branch of pine,</l> 
<l>Here, out of my pocket, some moss which I pulled off a live-oak in Florida, as it hung trailing 
down,</l> 
<l>Here, some pinks and laurel leaves, and a handful of sage,</l> 
<l>And here what I now draw from the water, wading in the pond-side,</l> 
<l>(O here I last saw him that tenderly loves me&mdash;and returns again, never to separate from 
me,</l> 
<l>And this, O this shall henceforth be the token of comrades&mdash;this calamus-root shall,</l> 
<l>Interchange it, youths, with each other!  Let none render it back!)</l> 
<l>And twigs of maple, and a bunch of wild orange, and chestnut,</l> 
<l>And stems of currents, and plum-blows, and the aromatic cedar;</l> 
<l>These I, compassed around by a thick cloud of spirits,</l> 
<l>Wandering, point to, or touch as I pass, or throw them loosely from me,</l> 
<l>Indicating to each one what he shall have&mdash;giving something to each,</l> 
<l>But what I drew from the water by the pond-side, that I reserve,</l> 
<l>I will give of it&mdash;but only them that love, as I myself am capable of loving.</l> 
</div1> 

 <div1 type="poem" n="5" id="d7"> <pb n="350" id="WhiCala350"/>   
<head>5.</head> 
<lg type="stanza" n="1"> 
<head>1.</head> 
<l>States!</l> 
<l>Were you looking to be held together by the lawyers?</l> 
<l>By an agreement on a paper? Or by arms?</l> 
</lg> 
<lg type="stanza" n="2"> 
<head>2.</head> 
<l>Away!</l> 
<l>I arrive, bringing these, beyond all the forces of courts and arms,</l> 
<l>These! to hold you together as firmly as the earth itself is held together.</l> 
</lg> 
<lg type="stanza" n="3"> 
<head>3.</head> 
<l>The old breath of life, ever new,</l> 
<l>Here!  I pass it by contact to you, America.</l></lg> 
 
<lg type="stanza" n="4"> 
<head>4.</head> 
<l>O mother! have you done much for me?</l> 
<l>Behold, there shall from me be much done for you.</l></lg> 
<lg type="stanza" n="5"> 
<head>5.</head>  
<l>There shall from me be a new friendship&mdash;It shall be called after my name,</l> 
<l>It shall circulate through The States, indifferent of place,</l> 
<l>It shall twist and intertwist them through and around each other&mdash;Compact shall they be, 
showing new signs,</l> 
<l>Affection shall solve every one of the problems of 
freedom,</l> 
<l>Those who love each other shall be invincible,</l> 
<l>They shall finally make America completely victorious, in my name.</l> 
</lg> 
<lg type="stanza" n="6"> 
<head>6.</head>  
<l>One from Massachusetts shall be comrade to a Missourian,</l> 
<l>One from Maine or Vermont, and a Carolinian and an Oregonese, shall be friends triune, more 
precious to each other than all the riches of the earth.</l></lg> 
<lg type="stanza" n="7"> 
<head>7.</head>  
<l>To Michigan shall be wafted perfume from Florida,</l> 
<l>To Mannahatta from Cuba or Mexico</l> 
<l>Not the perfume of flowers, but sweeter, and wafted beyond death.</l></lg> 
 
 
<lg type="stanza" n="8"> 
<head>8.</head>  
<l>No danger shall balk Columbia's lovers,</l> 
<l>If need be, a thousand shall sternly immolate themselves for one,</l> 
<l>The Kanuck shall be willing to lay down his life for the Kansian, and the Kansian for the 
Kanuck, on due need.</l></lg> 
<lg type="stanza" n="9"> 
<head>9.</head>  
<l>It shall be customary in all directions, in the houses and streets, to see manly affection,</l> 
<l>The departing brother or friend shall salute the remaining brother or friend with a 
kiss.</l></lg> 
<lg type="stanza" n="10"> 
<head>10.</head>  
<l>There shall be innovations,</l> 
<l>There shall be countless linked hands&mdash;namely, the Northeasterner's, and those of the interior, 
and all their brood,</l> 
<l>These shall be masters of the world under a new power,</l> 
<l>They shall laugh to scorn the attacks of all the remainder of the world.</l></lg> 
 
 
<pb n="351" id="WhiCala351"/>  
<lg type="stanza" n="11"> 
<head>11.</head>  
<l>The most dauntless and rude shall touch face to face lightly,</l> 
<l>The dependance of liberty shall be lovers,</l> 
<l>The continuance of Equality shall be comrades.</l></lg> 
<lg type="stanza" n="12"> 
<head>12.</head> 
<l>These shall tie and band stronger than hoops of iron,</l> 
<l>I, extatic, O partners! O lands! henceforth with the love of lovers tie you.</l> 
</lg> 
<lg type="stanza" n="13"> 
<head>13.</head> 
<l>I will make the continent indissoluble,</l> 
<l>I will make the most splendid race the sun ever yet shone upon,</l> 
<l>I will make divine magnetic lands.</l></lg> 
<lg type="stanza" n="14"> 
<head>14.</head> 
<l>I will plant companionship thick as trees along all the rivers of America, and along the shores 
of the great lakes, and all over the prairies,</l> 
<l>I will make inseparable cities, with their arms about each other's necks.</l></lg> 
<lg type="stanza" n="15"> 
<head>15.</head>  
<l>For you these, from me, O Democracy, to serve you ma femme!</l> 
<l>For you! for you, I am trilling these songs.</l></lg></div1> 
 
<div1 type="poem" n="6" id="d8"> 
<head>6.</head> 
 
<l>Not heaving from my ribbed breast only,</l> 
<l>Not in sighs at night, in rage, dissatisfied with myself,</l> 
<l>Not in those lang-drawn, ill-suppressed sighs,</l> 
<l>Not in many an oath and promise broken,</l> 
<l>Not in my willful and salvage soul's volition,</l> 
<pb n="352" id="WhiCala352"/> 
<l>Not in the subtle nourishment of the air,</l> 
<l>Not in this beating and pounding at my temples and wrists,</l> 
<l>Not in the curious systole and diastole within, which will one day cease,</l> 
<l>Not in many a hungry wish, told to the skies only,</l> 
<l>Not in cries, laughter, defiances, thrown from me when alone, far in the wilds,</l> 
<l>Not in husky pantings through clenched teeth,</l> 
<l>Not in sounded and resounded words&mdash;chattering words, echoes, dead words,</l> 
<l>Not in the murmers of my dreams while I sleep,</l> 
<l>Nor in the limbs and senses of my body, that take you and dismiss you continually&mdash;Not 
there,</l> 
<l>Not in any of all of them, O adhesiveness! O pulse of my life!</l> 
<l>Need I that you exist and show yourself, any more than in these songs.</l></div1>  
 
 
<div1 type="poem" n="7" id="d9"> 
                   <head>7.</head> 
 
<l>Of the terrible question of appearances,</l> 
<l>Of the doubts, the uncertainties after all,</l> 
<l>That may-be reliance and hope are but speculations after all,</l> 
<l>That may-be identity beyond the grave is a beautiful fable only,</l> 
<l>May-be the things I perceive&mdash;the animals, plants, men, hills, shining and flowing waters,</l> 
 
<pb n="353" id="WhiCala353"/> 
 
<l>The skies of day and night&mdash;colors, densities, forms&mdash;May-be these are, (as doubtless they are,) 
only apparitions, and the real something has yet to be known,</l> 
<l>(How often they dart out of themselves, as if to confound me and mock me!</l> 
<l>How often I think neither I know, nor any man knows, aught of them;)</l> 
<l>May-be they only seem to me what they are, (as doubtless they indeed but seem,) as from my 
present point of view&mdash;And might prove, (as of course they would,) naught of what they appear, 
or naught any how, from entirely changed points of view;</l> 
<l>To me, these, and the like of these, are curiously answered by my lovers, my dear friends;</l> 
<l>When he whom I love travels with me, or sits a long while holding me by the hand,</l> 
<l>When the subtle air, the impalpable, the sense that words and reason hold not, surround us and 
   pervade us,</l> 
<l>Then I am charged with untold and untellable wisdom&mdash;I am silent&mdash;I require nothing 
further,</l> 
<l>I cannot answer the question of appearances, or that of identity beyond the grave,</l> 
<l>But I walk or sit indifferent&mdash;I am satisfied,</l> 
<l>He ahold of my hand has completely satisfied me.</l></div1> 

<div1 type="poem" n="8" id="d10">  
<pb n="354" id="WhiCala354"/> 
<head>8.</head> 
 
<l>Long I thought that knowledge alone would suffice me&mdash;O if I could but obtain 
knowledge!</l> 
<l>Then my lands engrossed me&mdash;Lands of the prairies, Ohio's land, the southern savannas, 
engrossed me&mdash;For them I would live&mdash;I would be their  
orator;</l> 
<l>Then I met the examples of the old and new heroes&mdash;I heard of warriors, sailors, and all 
dauntless persons&mdash;And it seemed to me that I too had it in me to be as dauntless as any&mdash;and 
would be so;</l> 
<l>And then, to enclose all, it came to me to strike up the songs of the New World&mdash;And then I 
believed my life must be spent singing;</l> 
<l>But now take notice, land of the prairies, land of the south savannas, Ohio's land,</l> 
<l>Take notice, you Kanuck woods&mdash;and you Lake Huron&mdash;and all that with you roll toward 
Niagra&mdash;and you Niagra also,</l> 
<l>And you, California mountains&mdash;That you each and all find somebody else to be your singer of 
songs,</l> 
<l>For I can be your singer of songs no longer&mdash;One who loves me is jealous of me, and 
withdraws me from all but love,</l> 
<l>With the rest I dispense&mdash;I sever from what I thought would suffice me, for it does not&mdash;it is 
now empty and tasteless to me,</l> 
<l>I heed knowledge, and the grandeur of The States, and the example of heroes, no more,</l> 
 
<pb n="355" id="WhiCala355"/> 
 
<l>I am indifferent to my own songs&mdash;I will go with him I love,</l> 
<l>It is to be enough for us that we are together&mdash;We never separate again.</l></div1> 
 
<div1 type="poem" n="9" id="d11"> 
<head>9.</head> 
 
<l>Hours continuing long, sore and heavy-hearted,</l> 
<l>Hours of the duck, when I withdrew to a lonesome and unfrequented spot, seating myself, 
leaning my face in my hands;</l> 
<l>Hours sleepless, deep in the night, when I go forth, speeding swiftly the country roads, or 
through the city streets, or pacing miles and miles, stifiling plaintive cries;</l> 
<l>Hours discouraged, distracted&mdash;for the one I cannot content myself without, soon I saw him 
content himself without me;</l> 
<l>Hours when I am forgotten, (O weeks and months are passing, but I believe I am never to 
forget!)</l> 
<l>Sullen and suffering hours! (I am ashamed&mdash;but it is useless&mdash;I am what I am;)</l> 
<l>Hours of my torment&mdash;I wonder if other men ever have the like, out of the like feelings?</l> 
<l>Is there even one other like me&mdash;distracted&mdash;his friend, his lover, lost to him?</l> 
<l>Is he too as I am now?  Does he still rise in the morning, dejected, thinking who is lost to him? 
and at night, awaking, think who is lost?</l> 
 
<pb n="356" id="WhiCala356"/> 
 
<l>Does he too harbor his friendship silent and endless? harbor his anguish and passion?</l> 
<l>Does some stray reminder, or the casual mention of a name, bring the fit back upon him, 
taciturn and deprest?</l> 
<l>Does he see himself reflected in me? In these hours, does he see the face of his hours 
reflected?</l> 
</div1> 
<div1 type="poem" n="10" id="d12"> 
<head>10.</head> 
 
<l>You bards of ages hence! when you refer to me, mind not so much my poems,</l> 
<l>Nor speak of me that I prophesied of The States, and led them the way of their Glories;</l> 
<l>But come, I will take you down underneath this impassive exterior&mdash;I will tell you what to say 
of me:</l> 
<l>Publish my name and hang up my picture as that of the tenderest lover,</l> 
<l>The friend, the lover's portrait, of whom his friend, his lover, was fondest,</l> 
<l>Who was not proud of his songs, but of measureless ocean of love within him&mdash;and freely 
poured it forth,</l> 
<l>Who often walked lonesome walks, thinking of his dear friends, his lovers,</l> 
<l>Who pensive, away from one he loved, often lay sleepless and dissatisfied at night,</l> 
<l>Who knew too well the sick, sick dread lest the one he loved might secretly be indifferent to 
him,</l> 
 
<pb n="357" id="WhiCala357"/> 
 
<l>Whose happiest days were far away, through fields, in woods, on hills, he and another, 
wandering hand in hand, they twain, apart from other men,</l> 
<l>Who oft as he sauntered the streets, curved with his arm the shoulder of his friend&mdash;while the 
arm of his friend rested upon him also.</l> 
</div1> 
 
<div1 type="poem" n="11" id="d13"> 
<head>11.</head> 
 
 
<l>When I heard at the close of the day how my name had been received with plaudits in the 
capitol, still it was not a happy night for me that followed;</l> 
<l>And else, when I caroused, or when my plans were accomplished, still I was not happy;</l> 
<l>But the day when I rose at dawn from the bed of perfect health, refreshed, singing, inhaling the 
ripe breath of autumn,</l> 
<l>When I saw the full moon in the west grow pale and disappear in the morning light,</l> 
<l>When I wandered alone over the beach, and, undressing, bathed, laughing with the cool waters, 
and saw the sun rise,</l> 
<l>And when I thought how my dear friend, my lover, was on his way coming, O then I was 
happy;</l> 
<l>O then each breath tasted sweeter&mdash;and all that day my food nourished me more&mdash;And the 
beautiful day passed well,</l> 
<l>And the next came with equal joy&mdash;And with the next, at evening, came my friend;</l> 
 
<pb n="358" id="WhiCala358"/> 
 
<l>And that night, while all was still, I heard the waters roll slowly continually up the shores,</l> 
<l>I heard the hissing rustle of the liquid and sands, as directed to me, whispering, to congratulate 
me,</l> 
<l>For the one I love most lay sleeping by me under the same cover in the cool night,</l> 
<l>In the stillness, in the autumn moonbeams, his face was inclined toward me,</l> 
<l>And his arm lay lightly around my breast&mdash;And that night I was happy.</l></div1> 
 
<div1 type="poem" n="12" id="d14"> 
<head>12.</head> 
 
<l>Are you the new person drawn toward me and asking something significant from me?</l> 
<l>To begin with, take warning&mdash;I am probably far different from what you suppose;</l> 
<l>Do you suppose you will find in me your ideal?</l> 
<l>Do you think it is easy to have me become your lover?</l> 
<l>Do you think the friendship of me would be unalloyed satisfaction?</l> 
<l>Do you suppose I am trusty and faithful?</l> 
<l>Do you see no further than this fa&ccedil;ade&mdash;this smooth and tolerant manner of me?</l> 
<l>Do you suppose yourself advancing on real ground toward a real heroic man?</l> 
<l>Have you no thought, O dreamer, that it may be all maya, illusion?  O the next step my 
precipitate you!</l> 
<pb n="359" id="WhiCala359"/> 
 
<l>O let some past deceived one hiss in your ears, howmany have prest on the same as you are 
pressing now,</l> 
<l>How many have fondly supposed what you are supposing now&mdash;only to be 
disappointed.</l></div1> 
 
<div1 type="poem" n="13" id="d15"> 
<head>13.</head> 
 
<l>CALAMUS taste,</l> 
<l>(For I must change the strain&mdash;these are not to be pensive leaves, but leaves of joy,)</l> 
<l>Roots and leaves unlike any but themselves,</l> 
<l>Scents brought to men and women from the wild woods, and from the pond-side,</l> 
<l>Breast-sorrel and pinks of love&mdash;fingers that wind around tighter than vines,</l> 
<l>Gushes from the throats of birds, hid I the foliage of trees, as the sun is risen,</l> 
<l>Breezes of land and love&mdash;Breezes set from living shores out to you on the living sea&mdash;to you, 
O sailors!</l> 
<l>Frost-mellowed berries, and Third-Month twigs, offered fresh to young persons wandering out 
in the fields when the winter breaks up,</l> 
<l>Love-buds, put before you and within you, whoever you are,</l> 
<l>Buds to be unfolded on the old terms,</l> 
<l>If you bring the warmth of the sun to them, they will open, and bring form, color, perfume, to 
you,</l> 
<l>If you become the aliment and the wet, they will become flowers, fruits, tall branches and 
trees,</l> 
 
<pb n="360" id="WhiCala360"/> 
 
<l>They are comprised in you just as much as in themselves&mdash;perhaps more than in 
themselves,</l> 
<l>They are not comprised in one season or succession, but many successions,</l> 
<l>They have come slowly up out of the earth and me, and are to come slowly up out of 
you.</l></div1> 
 
<div1 type="poem" n="14" id="d16"> 
<head>14.</head> 
 
<l>NOT heat flames up and consumes,</l> 
<l>Not sea-waves hurry in and out,</l> 
<l>Not the air, delicious and dry, the air of the ripe summer, bears lightly along white down-balls 
of myriads of seeds, wafted, sailing gracefully, to drop where they may,</l> 
<l>Not these&mdash;O none of these, more than the flames of me, consuming, burning for his love 
whom I love!</l> 
<l>O none, more than I, hurrying in and out;</l> 
<l>Does the tide hurry, seeking something, and neve give up?  O I the same;</l> 
<l>O nor down-balls, nor perfumes, nor the high rain-emitting clouds, are borne through the open 
air,</l> 
<l>Any more than my Soul is borne through the open air,</l> 
<l>Wafted in all directions, O love, for friendship, for you.</l></div1> 
 

<div1 type="poem" n="15" id="d17"> <pb n="361" id="WhiCala361"/> 
<head>15.</head> 
 
<l>O DROPS of me! trickle, slow drops,</l> 
<l>Candid, from me falling&mdash;drip, bleeding drops,</l> 
<l>From wounds made free you whence you were prisoned,</l> 
<l>From my face&mdash;from my forehead and lips,</l> 
<l>From my breast&mdash;from within where I was concealed&mdash;Press forth, red drops&mdash;confession 
drops,</l> 
<l>Stain every page&mdash;stain every song I sing, every word I say, bloody drops,</l> 
<l>Let them know you scarlet heat&mdash;let them glisten,</l> 
<l>Saturate them with yourself, all ashamed and wet,</l> 
<l>Glow upon all I have written or shall write, bleeding drops,</l> 
<l>Let it all be seen in your light, blushing drops.</l></div1> 
 
<div1 type="poem" n="16" id="d18"><head>16.</head> 



<lg type="stanza" n="1"> 
<head>1.</head>  
<l>WHO is now reading this?</l></lg> 
<lg type="stanza" n="2"> 
<head>2.</head> 
<l>May-be one is now reading this who knows some wrong-doing of my past life,</l> 
<l>Or may-be a stranger is reading this who has secretly loved me,</l> 
<l>Or may-be one who meets all my grand assumptions and egotisms with derision,</l> 
<l>Or may-be one who is puzzled at me.</l></lg> 
 
<pb n="362" id="WhiCala362"/> 
<lg type="stanza" n="3"> 
<head>3.</head> 
<l>As if I were not puzzled at myself!</l> 
<l>Or as if I never deride myself! (O conscience struck! O self-convicted!)</l> 
<l>Or as if I do not secretly love strangers!  (O tenderly, a long time, and never avow it;)</l> 
<l>Or as if I did not see, perfectly well, interior in myself, the stuff of wrong-doing,</l> 
<l>Or as if it could cease transpiring from me until it must cease.</l></lg></div1> 
 
<div1 type="poem" n="17" id="d19"> 
<head>17.</head> 
 
<l>OF him I love day and night, I dreamed I heard he was dead,</l> 
<l>And I dreamed I went where they had buried him I love&mdash;but he was not in that place,</l> 
<l>And I dreamed I wandered, searching among burial places, to find him,</l> 
<l>And I found that every place was a burial-place,</l> 
<l>The houses full of life were equally full of death, (this house is now,)</l> 
<l>The streets, the shipping, the places of amusement, the Chicago, Boston, Philadelphia, the 
Mannahatta, were as full of the dead as of the living,</l> 
<l>And fuller, O vastly fuller, of the dead than of the  living;</l> 
<l>&mdash;And what I dreamed I will henceforth tell to every person and age,</l> 
<l>And I stand henceforth bound to what I dreamed;</l> 
<l>And now I am willing to disregard burial-places, and dispense with them,</l> 
 
<pb n="363" id="WhiCala363"/> 
   
<l>And if the memorials of the dead were put up indifferently everywhere, even in the room 
where I eat or sleep, I should be satisfied,</l> 
<l>And if the corpse of any one I love, of if my own corpse, be duly rendered to powder, and 
poured in the sea, I shall be satisfied,</l> 
<l>Or if it be distributed to the winds, I shall be satisfied.</l></div1> 
 
 
 
<div1 type="poem" n="18" id="d20"> 
<head>18.</head> 
<l>City of my walks and joys!</l> 
<l>City whom that I have lived and sung there will one day make you illustrious,</l> 
<l>Not the pageants of you&mdash;not your shifting tableaux, your spectacles, repay me,</l> 
<l>Not the interminable rows of your houses&mdash;nor the ships at the wharves,</l> 
<l>Nor the processions in the streets, nor the bright windows, with goods in them,</l> 
<l>Nor to converse with learned persons, or bear my share in the soiree or feast;</l> 
<l>Not those&mdash;but, as I pass, O Manhattan! Your frequent and swift flash of eyes offering me 
love,</l> 
<l>Offering me the response of my own&mdash;these repay me,</l> 
<l>Lovers, continual lovers, only repay me.</l> 
</div1> 
 
<div1 type="poem" n="19" id="d21"><pb n="364" id="WhiCala364"/>  
<head>19.</head> 
<lg type="stanza" n="1"> 
<head>1.</head> 
<l>Mind you the the timid models of the rest, the majority?</l> 
<l>Long I minded them, but hence I will not&mdash;for I have adopted models for myself, and now 
offer them to The Lands.</l></lg> 
 
<lg type="stanza" n="2"> 
<head>2.</head>  
<l>Behold this swarthy and unrefined face&mdash;these gray eyes,</l> 
<l>This beard&mdash;the white wool, unclipt upon my neck,</l> 
<l>My brown hands, and the silent manner of me, without charm;</l> 
<l>Yet comes one, a Manhattanese, and ever at parting, kisses me lightly on the lips with robust 
love,</l> 
<l>And I, in the public room, or on the crossing of the street, or on the ship's deck, kiss him in 
return;</l> 
<l>We observe that salute of American comrades, land and sea,</l> 
<l>We are those two natural and nonchalant persons.</l></lg></div1> 
 
<div1 type="poem" n="20" id="d22"> 
<head>20.</head> 
 
<l>I SAW in Louisiana a live-oak growing,</l> 
<l>All alone stood it, and the moss hung down from the branches,</l> 
<l>Without any companion it grew there, uttering joyous leaves of dark green,</l> 
<l>And its look, rude, lusty, made me think of myself.</l> 
 
<pb n="365" id="WhiCala365"/> 
 
<l>But I wondered how it could utter joyous leaves, standing alone there, without its friend, its 
     lover near&mdash;for I knew I could not,</l> 
<l>And I broke off a twig with a certain number of leaves upon it, and twined around it a little 
moss,</l> 
<l>And brought it away&mdash;and I have placed it in sight in my room,</l>  
<l>It is not needed to remind me as if my own dear friends,</l> 
<l>(For I believe lately I think of little else than of them,)</l> 
<l>Yet it remains to me a curious token&mdash;it makes me think of manly love;</l> 
<l>For all that, and though the live-oak glistens there in Louisiana, solitary, in a wide flat 
space,</l> 
<l>Uttering joyous leaves all its life, without a friend, a lover, near,</l> 
<l>I know very well I could not.</l></div1> 
 
<div1 type="poem" n="21" id="d23"> 
<head>21.</head> 
 
<l>MUSIC always round me, unceasing, unbeginning&mdash;yet long untaught I not hear,</l> 
<l>But now the chorus I hear, and am elated,</l> 
<l>A tenor, strong, ascending, with power and health, with glad notes of day-break I hear,</l> 
<l>A soprano, at intervals, sailing buoyantly over the tops of immense waves,</l> 
<l>A transparent base, shuddering lusciously under and through the universe,</l> 
 
                                 
 
<pb n="366" id="WhiCala366"/> 
 
<l>The triumphant tutti&mdash;the funeral wailings, with sweet flutes and violins&mdash;All these I fill myself 
with</l> 
<l>I hear not the volumes of sound merely&mdash;I am moved by the exquisite meanings, 
I listen to the different voices winding in and out, striving, contending with fiery vehemence to 
excel each other in emotion,</l> 
<l>I do not think the performers know themselves&mdash;but now I think I begin to know 
them.</l></div1> 
 
<div1 type="poem" n="22" id="d24"> 
<head>22.</head> 
 
<l>PASSING stranger! You do not know how longingly I look upon you,</l> 
<l>You must be he I was seeking, or she I was seeking, (It comes to me, as of a dream,)</l> 
<l>I have somewhere surely lived a life of joy with you,</l> 
<l>All is recalled as we flit by each other, fluid, affectionate, chaste, matured,</l> 
<l>You grew up with me, were a boy with me, or a girl with me,</l> 
<l>I ate with you, and slept with you&mdash;your body has become not yours only, nor left my body 
mine only,</l> 
<l>You give me the pleasure of your eyes, face, flesh, as we pass&mdash;you take of my beard, breast, 
hands, in return,</l> 
<l>I am not to speak to you&mdash;I am to think of you when I sit alone, or wake a night alone,</l> 
 
<pb n="367" id="WhiCala367"/> 
 
<l>I am to wait&mdash;I do not doubt I am to meet you again,</l> 
<l>I am to see to it that I do not lose you.</l></div1> 
 
<div1 type="poem" n="23" id="d25"> 
<head>23.</head> 
 
<l>THIS moment as I sit alone, yearning and thoughtful, it seems to me there are other men in 
other lands, yearning and thoughtful;</l> 
<l>It seems to me I can look over and behold them, in Germany, Italy, France, Spain&mdash;Or far, far 
away, in China, or in Russia or India&mdash;talking other dialects;</l> 
<l>And it seems to me if I could know these men better, I should become attached to them, as I 
do to men in my own lands,</l> 
<l>It seems to me they are as wise, beautiful, benevolent, as any in my own lands;</l> 
<l>O I know we should be brethren and lovers,</l> 
<l>I know I should be happy with them.</l></div1> 
 
<div1 type="poem" n="24" id="d26"> 
<head>24.</head> 
 
<l>I hear it is charged against me that I seek to destroy institutions;</l> 
<l>But really I am neither for nor against institutions,</l> 
<l>(What indeed have I in common with them?&mdash;Or what with the destruction of them?)</l> 
 
<pb n="368" id="WhiCala368"/> 
 
<l>Only I will establish in the Manahatta, and in every city of These States, inland and 
seaboard,</l> 
<l>And in the fields and woods, and above every keel little or large, that dents the water, 
Without edifices, or rules, or trustees, or any argument,</l> 
<l>The institution of the dear love of comrades.</l> 
</div1> 
 
<div1 type="poem" n="25" id="d27"> 
<head>25.</head> 
 
<l>THE prairie-grass dividing&mdash;its own odor breathing,</l> 
<l>I demand of it the spiritual corresponding,</l> 
<l>Demand the most copious and close companionship of men,</l> 
<l>Demand the blades to rise of words, acts, beings,</l> 
<l>Those of the open atmosphere, coarse, sunlit, fresh, nutritious,</l> 
<l>Those that go their won gait, erect, stepping with freedom and command&mdash;leading, not 
following,</l> 
<l>Those with a never-quell'd audacity&mdash;those with sweet and lusty flesh, clear of taint, choice and 
chary of its love-power,</l> 
<l>Those that look carelessly in the faces of the Presidents and Governors, as to say, <hi rend="italic">Who are 
you?</hi></l> 
<l>Those of earth-born passion, simple, never constrained, never obedient,</l> 
<l>Those of inland America.</l></div1> 
 
<div1 type="poem" n="26" id="d28"> <pb n="369" id="WhiCala369"/> 
<head>26.</head> 
<l>WE two boys together clinging,</l> 
<l>One the other never leaving,</l> 
<l>Up and down the roads going&mdash;North and South excursions making,</l> 
<l>Power enjoying&mdash;elbows stretching&mdash;fingers clutching,</l> 
<l>Armed and fearless&mdash;eating, drinking, sleeping, loving,</l> 
<l>No law less than ourselves owning&mdash;sailing, soldiering, thieving, threatening,</l> 
<l>Misers, menials, priests, alarming&mdash;air breathing, water drinking, on the turn of the sea-beach 
dancing,</l> 
<l>With birds singing&mdash;With fishes swimming&mdash;With trees branching and leafing, 
Cities wrenching, ease scorning, statutes mocking, feebleness chasing,</l> 
<l>Fulfilling our foray.</l></div1> 
 
<div1 type="poem" n="27" id="d29"> 
<head>27.</head> 
 
<l>O Love!</l> 
<l>O dying&mdash;always dying!</l> 
<l>O the burials of me, past and present!</l> 
<l>O me, while I stride ahead, material, visible, imperious as ever!</l> 
 
<pb n="370" id="WhiCala370"/> 
 
<l>O me, what I was for years, now dead, (I lament not&mdash;I am content;)</l> 
<l>O to discourage myself from those corpses of me, which I turn and look at, where I cast 
them!</l> 
<l>To pass on, (O living! Always living!) And leave the corpses behind!</l></div1> 
 
<div1 type="poem" n="28" id="d30"> 
<head>28.</head> 
 
<l>When I peruse the conquered fame of heroes, and the victories of mighty generals, I do not 
envy the generals,</l> 
<l>Nor the President in his Presidency, nor the rich in his great house;</l> 
<l>But when I read of the brotherhood of lovers, how it was with them,</l> 
<l>How through life, through dangers, odium, unchanging, long and long,</l> 
<l>Through youth, and through middle and old age, how unfaltering, how affectionate and 
faithful they were,</l> 
<l>Then I am pensive&mdash;I hastily put down the book, and walk away, filled with the bitterest 
envy.</l></div1> 
 

<div1 type="poem" n="29" id="d31"> <pb n="371" id="WhiCala371"/> 
<head>29.</head> 
<l>One flitting glimpse, caught through an interstice,</l> 
<l>Or a crowd of workmen and drivers in a bar room, around the stove, late of a winter 
night&mdash;And I unremarked, seated in a corner;</l> 
<l>Of a youth who loves me, and whom I love, silently approaching, and seating himself near, 
that he may hold me by the hand;</l> 
<l>A long while, amid the noises of coming and going&mdash;of drinking and oath and smutty jest,</l> 
<l>There we two, content, happy in being together, speaking little, perhaps not a word.</l></div1> 
 
<div1 type="poem" n="30" id="d32"> 
<head>30.</head> 
 
<l>A PROMISE and gift to California,</l> 
<l>Also to the great Pastoral Plains, and for Oregon:</l> 
<l>Sojourning east a while longer, soon I travel to you, to remain, to teach robust American 
love;</l> 
<l>For I know very well that I and robust love belong among you, inland, and along the Western 
Sea,</l> 
<l>For These States tend inland, and toward the Western Sea&mdash;and I will also.</l></div1> 
 

<div1 type="poem" n="31" id="d33"> <pb n="372" id="WhiCala372"/> 
<head>31</head> 
<lg type="stanza" n="1"> 
 
<head>1.</head> 
<l>WHAT ship, puzzled at sea, cons for the true reckoning?</l> 
<l>Or, coming in, to avoid the bars, and follow the channel, a perfect pilot needs?</l> 
<l>Here, sailor! Here, ship!  Take aboard the most perfect pilot,</l> 
<l>Whom, in a little boat, putting off, and rowing, I, hailing you, offer.</l></lg> 
 
<lg type="stanza" n="2"> 
<head>2.</head>  
<l>What place is besieged, and vainly tries to raise the siege?</l> 
<l>Lo! I send to that place a commander, swift, brave, immortal,</l> 
<l>And with him horse and foot&mdash;and parks of artillery,</l> 
<l>And artillerymen, the deadliest that ever fired gun.</l></lg></div1> 
 
<div1 type="poem" n="32" id="d34"> 
<head>32.</head> 
 
<l>WHAT think you I take my pen in hand to record?</l> 
<l>The battle-ship, perfect-model'd, majestic, that I saw pass the offing to-day under full sail?</l> 
<l>The splendors of the past day? Or the splendor of the night that envelops me?</l> 
<l>Or the vaunted glory and growth of the great city spread around me?&mdash;No;</l> 
<l>But I record of two simple men I saw to-day, on the pier, in the midst of the crowd, parting 
the parting of dear friends,</l> 
<l>The one to remain hung on the other's neck, and passionately kissed him,</l> 
<l>While the one to depart, tightly prest the one to remain in his arms.</l></div1> 
 
<div1 type="poem" n="33" id="d35"> 
<head>33.</head> 
 
<l>No labor-saving machine,</l> 
<l>Nor discovery have I made,</l> 
<l>Nor will I be able to leave behind me any wealthy bequest to found a hospital or library,</l> 
<l>Nor reminiscence of any deed of courage, for America,</l> 
<l>Nor literary success, nor intellect&mdash;nor book for the book-shelf;</l> 
<l>Only these carols, vibrating through the air, I leave,</l> 
<l>For comrades and lovers.</l></div1> 
 
 <div1 type="poem" n="34" id="d36"> 
<head>34.</head> 
 
<l>I DREAMED in a dream, I saw a city of invincible to the attacks of the whole of the rest of 
the earth,</l> 
<l>I dreamed that was the new City of Friends,</l> 
<l>Nothing was greater there than the quality of robust love&mdash;it led the rest,</l> 
<l>It was seen every hour in actions of the men of that city,</l> 
<l>And in all their looks and words.</l></div1> 
                          
<div1 type="poem" n="35" id="d37"><pb n="373" id="WhiCala373"/><head>35.</head> 
 
<l>To you of New England,</l> 
<l>To the man of the Seaside State, and of Pennsylvania,</l> 
<l>To the Kanadian of the north&mdash;to the Southerner I love,</l> 
<l>These, with perfect trust, to depict you as myself&mdash;the germs are in all men;</l> 
<l>I believe the main purport of These States is found a supurb friendship, exalt&eacute;  
previously unknown,</l> 
<l>Because I perceive it waits, and has been always waiting, latent in all men.</l></div1> 
 
 <div1 type="poem" n="36" id="d38"> 
<head>36.</head> 
 
<l>EARTH! My likeness!</l> 
<l>Though you look so impassive, ample and spheric there,</l> 
<l>I now suspect that is not all;</l> 
<l>I now suspect there is something fierce in you, eligible to burst forth;</l> 
<l>For an athlete is enamoured of me&mdash;and I of him,</l> 
<l>But toward him there is something fierce and terrible in me, eligible to burst forth,</l> 
<l>I dare not tell it in words&mdash;not even in these songs.</l></div1> 
 

 <div1 type="poem" n="37" id="d39"> <pb n="374" id="WhiCala374"/> 
<head>37.</head> 
 
<l>A LEAF for hand in hand!</l> 
<l>You natural persons old and young! You on the Eastern Sea, and you on the Western!</l> 
<l>You on the Mississippi, and on the branches and bayous of the Mississippi!</l> 
<l>You friendly boatmen and mechanics! You roughs!</l> 
<l>You twain! And all the processions moving along the streets!</l> 
<l>I wish to infuse myself among you till I see it common for you to walk hand in hand.</l></div1> 
 
 <div1 type="poem" n="38" id="d40"> 
<head>38.</head> 
 
<l>PRIMEVAL my love for the women I love,</l> 
<l>O bride! O wife! More resistless, more enduring than I can tell, the thought of you!</l> 
<l>Then separate, as disembodied, the purest born,</l> 
<l>The ethereal, the last athletic reality, my consolation,</l> 
<l>I ascend&mdash;I float in the regions of your love, O man,</l> 
<l>O sharer of my roving life.</l></div1> 
 
 <div1 type="poem" n="39" id="d41"> 
<head>39.</head> 
 
<l>SOMETIMES with one I love, I fill myself with rage, for fear I effuse unreturned love;</l> 
<l>But now I think there is no unreturned love&mdash;the pay is certain, one way or another,</l> 
 
<pb n="375" id="WhiCala375"/> 
 
<l>Doubtless I could not have perceived the universe, or written one of my poems, if I had not 
freely given myself to comrades, to love.</l></div1> 
 <div1 type="poem" n="40" id="d42"> 
<head>40.</head> 
 
<l>THAT shadow, my likeness, that goes to and fro, seeking a livelihood, chattering, 
chaffering,</l> 
<l>How often I find myself standing and looking at it where it fits,</l> 
<l>How often I question and doubt whether that is rally me;</l> 
<l>But in these, and among my lovers, and carolling my songs,</l> 
<l>O I never doubt whether that is really me.</l></div1> 
 
 <div1 type="poem" n="41" id="d43"> 
<head>41.</head> 
<lg type="stanza" n="1"> 
<head>1.</head> 
<l>AMONG the men and women, the multitude, I percieve one, picking me out by secret and 
divine signs,</l> 
<l>Acknowledging none else&mdash;not parent, wife, husband, brother, child, any nearer than I am;</l> 
<l>Some are baffled&mdash;But that one is not&mdash;that one knows me.</l></lg> 
 
<lg type="stanza" n="2"> 
<head>2.</head> 
<l>Lover and perfect equal!</l> 
<l>I meant that you should discover me so, by my faint indirections,</l> 
<l>And I, when I meet you, mean to discover you by the like in you.</l></lg> 
</div1> 
 

 <div1 type="poem" n="42" id="d44"> <pb n="376" id="WhiCala376"/> 
<head>42.</head> 
 
<l>To the young man, many things to absorb, to engraft, to develop, I teach, to help him become 
&eacute;l&egrave;ve of mine,</l> 
<l>But if blood like mine circle not in his veins,</l> 
<l>If he be not silently selected by lovers, and do not silently select lovers,</l> 
<l>Of what use is it that he seek to become &eacute;l&egrave;ve of  mine?</l></div1> 
 
 <div1 type="poem" n="43" id="d45"> 
<head>43.</head> 
 
<l>O YOU whom I often and silently come where you are, that I may be with you,</l> 
<l>As I walk by your side, or sit near, or remain in the same room with you,</l> 
<l>Little you know the subtle electric fire that for your sake is playing within me.</l></div1> 
 
 <div1 type="poem" n="44" id="d46"> 
<head>44.</head> 
<l>HERE my last words, and the most baffling,</l> 
<l>Here the frailest leaves of me, and yet my strongest lasting,</l> 
<l>Here I shade down and hide my thoughts&mdash;I do not expose them,</l> 
<l>And yet they expose me more than all my other poems.</l></div1> 
                                
<div1 type="poem" n="45" id="d47"> <pb n="377" id="WhiCala377"/> 

<head>45.</head> 
<lg type="stanza" n="1"> 
<head>1.</head> 
<l>FULL of life, sweet-blooded, compact, visible,</l> 
<l>I forty years old the Eighty-third Year of The States,</l> 
<l>To one a century hence, or any number of centuries hence,</l> 
<l>To you, yet unborn, these, seeking you.</l></lg> 
<lg type="stanza" n="2"> 
<head>2.</head> 
<l>When you read these, I, that I was visible, am become invisible;</l> 
<l>Now it is you, compact, viable, realizing my poems, seeking me,</l> 
<l>Fancying how happy you were, if I could be with you, and become your lover;</l> 
<l>Be it as if I were with you. Be not too certain but I am now with you.</l></lg></div1> 

</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
