<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WhiFrap"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
 
]> 
<TEI.2 id="WhiFrap"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Fra Paolo Sarpi</title>
<title type="sort">fra paolo sarpi</title>
<author>White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>  
<name>Charles Keller</name>  
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>  
<name/>  
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">74</num> kilobytes</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>  
<idno type="ETC">WhiFrap</idno>  
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476542</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>  
<notesStmt>  
<note>
<p>This electronic text combines the two sections of this essay, published in vol. 93, no. 555 (January 1904) and no. 556 (February 1904).</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>  
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Fra Paolo Sarpi</title>
<title level="j">The Atlantic Monthly: A Magazine of Literature, Science, Art, and Politics. Vol. 93, nos. 555 and 556.</title>
<title type="sort">fra paolo sarpi</title>
<author>Andrew Dickson White</author>
</titleStmt>  
<extent>pages 45-54 and 225-233</extent>  
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Houghton, Mifflin and Company. | The Riverside Press.</publisher>  
<pubPlace>Boston and New York. | Cambridge, Mass.</pubPlace>  
<date value="1904">1904</date>  
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa library, call no.: AP2.A8</idno>
</publicationStmt>  
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>  
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>  
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>  
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>  
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>  
</encodingDesc>  
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1904">1904</date>
</creation>  
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>  
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
</profileDesc>  
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-10">October 1997</date>  
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>  
<name>Greg Murray, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>  
<item>Added TEI header and tags. Footnotes have been renumbered sequentially within each of the two sections of the essay. Page numbers of original print source have been retained.</item>
</change>  
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>  
 
 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
 
<div1 type="essay" id="d3">  <pb n="45"/>   
<head>FRA PAOLO SARPI.</head> 
 
<div2 type="section" id="d4"> 
<head>I.</head> 
 
<p>A THOUGHTFUL historian tells us that, 
between the fourteenth century and the 
nineteenth, Italy produced three great 
men. As the first of these, he names 
Machiavelli, who, he says, "taught the 
world to understand political despotism 
and to hate it;" as the second, he names 
Sarpi who "taught the world after 
what manner the Holy Spirit guides the 
Councils of the Church;" and as the 
third, Galileo, who "taught the world 
what dogmatic theology is worth when 
it can be tested by science." 
</p><p>I purpose now to present the second 
of these. As a <hi rend="italic">man</hi>, he was by far the 
greatest of the three and, in various 
respects, the most interesting, for he not 
only threw a bright light into the most 
important general council of the Church 
and revealed to Christendom the methods 
which there prevailed,&mdash;in a book which 
remains one of the half-dozen classic 
histories of the world,&mdash;but he fought the 
most bitter fight for humanity against 
the papacy ever known in any Latin nation, 
and won a victory by which the 
whole world has profited ever since. 
Moreover, he was one of the two foremost 
Italian statesmen since the Middle 
Ages, the other being Cavour. 
</p><p>He was born at Venice in 1552, and 
it may concern those who care to note 
the subtle interweaving of the warp and 
woof of history that the birth year of 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
this most resourceful foe that Jesuitism 
ever had was the death year of St. 
Francis Xavier, the noblest of Jesuit 
apostles. 
</p><p>It may also interest those who study 
the more evident evolution of cause and 
effect in human affairs to note that, like 
most strong men, he had a strong mother; 
that while his father was a poor shopkeeper 
who did little and died young, 
his mother was wise and serene. 
</p><p>From his earliest boyhood, he showed 
striking gifts and characteristics. He 
never forgot a face once seen, could take 
in the main contents of a page at a 
glance, spoke little, rarely ate meat, and, 
until his last years, never drank wine. 
</p><p>Brought up, after the death of his 
father, first by his uncle, a priest, and 
then by Capella, a Servite monk, in 
something better than the usual priestly 
fashion, he became known, while yet in 
his boyhood, as a theological prodigy. 
Disputations in his youth, especially one 
at Mantua, where, after the manner of 
the time, he successfully defended several 
hundred theses against all comers, 
attracted wide attention, so that the 
Bishop gave him a professorship, and 
the Duke, who, like some other crowned 
heads of those days,&mdash;notably Henry 
VIII. and James I.,&mdash;liked to dabble 
in theology, made him a court theologian. 
But the duties of this position were 
uncongenial: a flippant duke, fond of 
putting questions which the wisest theologian 
   <pb n="46"/>   
could not answer, and laying out 
work which the young scholar evidently 
thought futile, apparently wearied him. 
He returned to the convent of the Servites 
at Venice, and became, after a few 
years' novitiate, a friar, changing, at the 
same time, his name; so that, having been 
baptized Peter, he now became Paul. 
</p><p>His career soon seemed to reveal another 
and underlying cause of his return: 
he evidently felt the same impulse 
which stirred his contemporaries, Lord 
Bacon and Galileo; for he began devoting 
himself to the whole range of scientific 
and philosophical studies, especially 
to mathematics, physics, astronomy, 
anatomy, and physiology. In these he 
became known as an authority, and before 
long was recognized as such through 
out Europe. It is claimed, and it is not 
improbable, that he anticipated Harvey in 
discovering the circulation of the blood, 
and that he was the forerunner of noted 
discoveries in magnetism. Unfortunately 
the loss of the great mass of his papers 
by the fire which destroyed his convent 
in 1769 forbids any full estimate of his 
work; but it is certain that among those 
who sought his opinion and advice were 
such great discoverers as Acquapendente, 
Galileo, Torricelli, and Gilbert of Colchester, 
and that every one of these referred 
to him as an equal, and indeed as 
a master. It seems also established that 
it was he who first discovered the valves 
of the veins, that he made known the 
most beautiful function of the iris,&mdash;its 
contractility,&mdash;and that various surmises 
of his regarding heat, light, and sound 
have since been developed into scientific 
truths. It is altogether likely that, had 
he not been drawn from scientific pursuits 
by his duties as a statesman, he 
would have ranked among the greater 
investigators and discoverers, not only 
of Italy, but of the world. 
</p><p>He also studied political and social 
problems, and he arrived at one conclusion 
which, though now trite, was then 
novel,&mdash;the opinion that the aim of punishment 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
should not be vengeance, but 
reformation. In these days and in this 
country, where one of the most serious of 
evils is undue lenity to crime, this opinion 
may be imputed to him as a fault; 
but in those days, when torture was the 
main method in procedure and in penalty, 
his declaration was honorable both to 
his head and heart. 
</p><p>With all his devotion to books, he 
found time to study men. Even at 
school, he had seemed to discern those 
who would win control. They discerned 
something in him also; so that close 
relations were formed between him and 
such leaders as Contarini and Morosini, 
with whom he afterwards stood side by 
side in great emergencies. 
</p><p>Important missions were entrusted to 
him. Five times he visited Rome to 
adjust perplexing differences between 
the papal power and various interests 
at Venice. He was rapidly advanced 
through most of the higher offices in his 
order, and in these he gave a series of 
decisions which won the respect of all 
entitled to form an opinion. 
</p><p>Naturally he was thought of for high 
place in the Church, and was twice presented 
for a bishopric; but each time he 
was rejected at Rome,&mdash;partly from 
family claims of less worthy candidates, 
partly from suspicions regarding his 
orthodoxy. It was objected that he did 
not find the whole doctrine of the Trinity 
in the first verse of Genesis, that he 
corresponded with eminent heretics of 
England and Germany, that he was not 
averse to reforms, that, in short, he was 
not inclined to wallow in the slime from 
which had crawled forth such huge 
incarnations of evil as John XXIII., 
Julius II., Sixtus IV., and Alexander VI. 
</p><p>His orthodox detractors have been 
wont to represent him as seeking vengeance 
for his non-promotion; but his 
after career showed amply that personal 
grievances had little effect upon him. It 
is indeed not unlikely that when he saw 
bishoprics for which he knew himself 
   <pb n="47"/>   
well fitted given as sops to poor creatures 
utterly unfit in morals or intellect, 
he may have had doubts regarding the 
part taken by the Almighty in selecting 
them; but he was reticent, and kept on 
with his work. In his cell at Santa Fosca, 
he quietly and steadily devoted himself to 
his cherished studies; but he continued 
to study more than books or inanimate 
nature. He was neither a bookworm nor 
a pedant. On his various missions he 
met and discoursed with churchmen and 
statesmen concerned in the greatest 
transactions of his time, notably at Mantua 
with Oliva, secretary of one of the greatest 
ecclesiastics at the Council of Trent; 
at Milan with Cardinal Borromeo, by far 
the noblest of all who sat in that assemblage 
during its eighteen years; in Rome 
and elsewhere with Arnauld Ferrier, 
who had been French Ambassador at the 
Council, Cardinal Severina, head of the 
Inquisition, Castagna, afterward Pope 
Urban VII., and Cardinal Bellarmine, 
afterward Sarpi's strongest and noblest 
opponent. 
</p><p>Nor was this all. He was not content 
with books or conversations; steadily he 
went on collecting, collating, and testing 
original documents bearing upon the 
great events of his time. The result of 
all this the world was to see later. 
</p><p>He had arrived at middle life and won 
wide recognition as a scholar, scientific 
investigator, and jurist, when there came 
the supreme moment of a struggle which 
had involved Europe for centuries,&mdash;a 
struggle interesting not only the Italy 
and Europe of those days, but universal 
humanity for all time. 
</p><p>During the period following the fall of 
the Roman Empire of the West there 
had been evolved the temporal power of 
the Roman Bishop. It had many vicissitudes. 
Sometimes, as in the days of St. 
Leo and St. Gregory, it based its claims 
upon noble assertions of right and justice, 
and sometimes, as in the hands of pontiffs 
like Innocent VIII. and Paul V., it 
sought to force its way by fanaticism. 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
Sometimes it strengthened its authority 
by real services to humanity, and sometimes 
by such monstrous frauds as the 
Forged Decretals. Sometimes, as under 
Popes like Gregory VII. and Innocent 
III., it laid claim to the mastership of the 
world, and sometimes, as with the majority 
of the pontiffs during the two centuries 
before the Reformation, it became 
mainly the appanage of a party or faction 
or family. 
</p><p>Throughout all this history, there appeared 
in the Church two great currents 
of efficient thought. On one side had 
been developed a theocratic theory, giving 
the papacy a power supreme in temporal 
as well as in spiritual matters throughout 
the world. Leaders in this during the 
Middle Ages were St. Thomas Aquinas 
and the Dominicans; leaders in Sarpi's 
days were the Jesuits, represented especially 
in the treatises of Bellarmine at 
Rome and in the speeches of Laynez at 
the Council of Trent.<ref target="n1.1">[1]</ref> 
 
</p><p>But another theory, hostile to the 
despotism of the Church over the State, had 
been developed through the Middle Ages 
and the Renaissance;&mdash;it had been 
strengthened mainly by the utterances 
of such men as Dante, &AElig;gidio Colonna, 
John of Paris, Ockham, Marsilio of 
Padua, and Laurentius Valla. Sarpi 
ranged himself with the latter of these 
forces. Though deeply religious, he 
recognized the God-given right of earthly 
governments to discharge their duties 
independent of church control. 
</p><p>Among the many centres of this struggle 
was Venice. She was splendidly 
religious&mdash;as religion was then understood. 
She was made so by her whole 
environment. From the beginning she 
had been a seafaring power, and seafaring 
men, from their constant wrestle with 
dangers ill understood, are prone to seek 
and find supernatural forces. Nor was 
this all. Later, when she had become 
   <pb n="48"/>   
rich, powerful, luxurious, licentious, and 
refractory to the priesthood, her most 
powerful citizens felt a need of atoning 
for their many sins by splendid religious 
foundations. So her people came to live 
in an atmosphere of religious observance, 
and the bloom and fruitage of their religious 
hopes and fears are seen in the whole 
history of Venetian art,&mdash;from the rude 
sculptures of Torcello and the na&iuml;ve mosaics 
of San Marco to the glowing altarpieces 
and ceilings of John Bellini, Titian, 
and Tintoretto and the illuminations of 
the Grimani Psalter. No class in Venice 
rose above this environment. Doges and 
Senators were as susceptible to it as were 
the humblest fishermen on the Lido. In 
every one of those glorious frescoes in 
the corridors and halls of the Ducal Palace 
which commemorate the victories of 
the Republic, the triumphant Doge or 
Admiral or General is seen on his knees 
making acknowledgment of the divine 
assistance. On every Venetian sequin, 
from the days when Venice was a power 
throughout the earth to that fatal year 
when the young Bonaparte tossed the 
Republic over to the House of Austria, 
the Doge, crowned and robed, kneels 
humbly before the Saviour, the Virgin, or 
St. Mark. In that vast Hall of the Five 
Hundred, the most sumptuous room in 
the world, there is spread above the heads 
of the Doge and Senators and Councilors, 
as an incentive to the discharge of 
their duties on earth, a representation of 
the blessed in Heaven. 
</p><p>From highest to lowest, the Venetians 
lived, moved, and had their being in this 
religious environment, and, had their Republic 
been loosely governed, its external 
policy would have been largely swayed 
by this all-pervading religious feeling, 
and would have become the plaything of 
the Roman Court. But a democracy has 
never been maintained save by the delegation 
of great powers to its chosen leaders. 
It was the remark of one of the foremost 
American Democrats of the nineteenth 
century, a man who received the 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
highest honors which his party could 
bestow, that the Constitution of the 
United States was made, not to promote 
Democracy, but to check it. This statement 
is true, and it is as true of the Venetian 
Constitution as of the American.<ref target="n1.2">[2]</ref> 
 
</p><p>But while both the republics recognized 
the necessity of curbing Democracy, the 
difference between the means employed 
was world-wide. The founders of the 
American Republic gave vast powers and 
responsibilities to a president and 
unheard-of authority to a supreme court; 
in the Venetian Republic the Doge was 
gradually stripped of power, but there 
was evolved the mysterious and unlimited 
authority of the Senate and Council 
of Ten. 
</p><p>In these sat the foremost Venetians, 
thoroughly imbued with the religious 
spirit of their time; but, religious as they 
were, they were men of the world, trained 
in the polities of all Europe and especially 
of Italy. 
</p><p>In a striking passage, Guizot has shown 
how the Crusaders who went to the Orient 
by way of Italy and saw the papacy near 
at hand came back skeptics. This same 
influence shaped the statesmen of Venice. 
The Venetian Ambassadors were the foremost 
in Europe. Their Relations are 
still studied as the clearest, shrewdest, 
and wisest statements regarding the men 
and events in Europe at their time. All 
were noted for skill; but the most skillful 
were kept on duty at Rome. There 
was the source of danger. The Doges, 
Senators, and controlling Councilors had, 
as a rule, served in these embassies, and 
they had formed lucid judgments as to 
Italian courts in general and as to the 
Roman Court in particular. No men had 
known the Popes and the Curia more 
thoroughly. They had seen Innocent 
VIII. buy the papacy for money. They 
had been at the Vatican when Alexander 
VI. had won renown as a secret murderer. 
They had seen, close at hand, the merciless 
   <pb n="49"/>   
cruelty of Julius II. They had carefully 
noted the crimes of Sixtus IV., 
which culminated in the assassination of 
Julian de' Medici beneath the dome of 
Florence at the moment the Host was uplifted. 
They had sat near Leo X. while 
he enjoyed the obscenities of the 
Calandria and the Mandragora,&mdash;plays 
which, in the most corrupt of modern cities, 
would, in our day, be stopped by the 
police. No wonder that, in one of their 
dispatches, they speak of Rome as "the 
<hi rend="italic">cloaca</hi> of the world."<ref target="n1.3">[3]</ref> 
 
</p><p>Naturally, then, while their religion 
showed itself in wonderful monuments of 
every sort, their practical sense was shown 
by a steady opposition to papal encroachments. 
</p><p>Of this combination of zeal for religion 
with hostility to ecclesiasticism we have 
striking examples throughout the history 
of the Republic. While, in every 
other European state, cardinals, bishops, 
priests, and monks were given leading 
parts in civil administration and, in some 
states, a monopoly of civil honors, the 
Republic of Venice not only excluded all 
ecclesiastics from such posts, but, in cases 
which touched church interests, she excluded 
even the relatives of ecclesiastics. 
When church authority decreed that commerce 
should not be maintained with infidels 
and heretics, the Venetian merchants 
continued to deal with Turks, Pagans, 
Germans, Englishmen, and Dutchmen 
as before. When the Church decreed 
that the taking of interest for money was 
sin, and great theologians published in 
Venice some of their mightiest treatises 
demonstrating this view from Holy Scripture 
and the Fathers, the Venetians continued 
borrowing and lending money on 
usance. When efforts were made to enforce 
that tremendous instrument for the 
consolidation of papal power, the bull 
In Coena Domini, Venice evaded and 
even defied it. When the Church frowned 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
upon anatomical dissections, the Venetians 
allowed Andreas Vesalius to make 
such dissections at their University of 
Padua. When Sixtus V., the strongest 
of all the Popes, had brought all his powers, 
temporal and spiritual, to bear against 
Henry IV. of France as an excommunicated 
heretic, and seemed ready to hurl 
the thunderbolts of the Church against 
any power which should recognize him, 
the Venetian Republic not only recognized 
him, but treated his Ambassador 
with especial courtesy. When the other 
Catholic powers, save France, yielded to 
papal mandates and sent no representatives 
to the coronation of James I. of 
England, Venice was there represented. 
When Pope after Pope issued endless 
diatribes against the horrors of toleration, 
the Venetians steadily tolerated in their 
several sorts of worship Jews and Greeks, 
Mohammedans and Armenians, with Protestants 
of every sort who came to them 
on business. When the Roman Index 
forbade the publication of most important 
works of leading authors, Venice demanded 
and obtained for her printers 
rights which were elsewhere denied. 
</p><p>As to the religious restrictions which 
touched trade, the Venetians in the public 
councils, and indeed the people at 
large, had come to know perfectly what 
the papal theory meant,&mdash;with some of 
its promoters, fanaticism, but with the 
controlling power at Rome, revenue, revenue 
to be derived from retailing dispensations 
to infringe the holy rules. 
</p><p>This peculiar antithesis&mdash;nowhere 
more striking than at Venice, on the one 
side, religious fears and hopes; on the 
other, keen insight into the ways of 
ecclesiasticism&mdash;led to peculiar compromises. 
The bankers who had taken interest 
upon money, the merchants who had 
traded with Moslems and heretics, in 
their last hoers frequently thought it best 
to perfect their title to salvation by turning 
   <pb n="50"/>   
over large estates to the Church. 
Under the sway of this feeling, and especially 
of the terrors infused by priests 
at deathbeds, mortmain had become in 
Venice, as in many other parts of the 
world, one of the most serious of evils. 
Thus it was that the clergy came to possess 
between one fourth and one third of 
the whole territory of the Republic, and 
in its Bergamo district more than one 
half; and all this was exempt from taxation. 
Hence it was that the Venetian 
Senate found it necessary to devise a 
legal cheek which should make such absorption 
of estates by the Church more 
and more difficult. 
</p><p>There was a second cause of trouble. 
In that religious atmosphere of Venice, 
monastic orders of every sort grew 
luxuriantly, not only absorbing more and 
more land to be held by the dead hand, 
thus escaping the public burdens, but 
ever absorbing more and more men and 
women, and thus depriving the state of 
any healthy and normal service from 
them. Here, too, the Senate thought it 
best to interpose a check: it insisted that 
all new structures for religious orders 
must be authorized by the State. 
</p><p>Yet another question flamed forth. 
Of the monks of every sort swarming 
through the city, many were luxurious 
and some were criminal. On these last, 
the Venetian Senate determined to lay 
its hands, and in the first years of the 
seventeenth century all these questions, 
and various other matters distasteful to 
the Vatican, culminated in the seizure 
and imprisonment of two ecclesiastics 
charged with various high crimes,&mdash;among these rape and murder. 
</p><p>There had just come to the papal 
throne Camillo Borghese, Paul V.,&mdash;strong, bold, determined, with the highest 
possible theory of his duties and of his 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
position. In view of his duty toward himself, 
he lavished the treasures of the 
faithful upon his family, until it became 
the richest which had yet risen in Rome; 
in view of his duty toward the Church, 
he built superbly, and an evidence of the 
spirit in which he wrought is his name, 
in enormous letters, still spread across 
the fa&ccirc;ade of St. Peter's. As to his 
position, he accepted fully the theories and 
practices of his boldest predecessors, and 
in this he had good warrant; for St. 
Thomas Aquinas and Bellarmine had 
furnished him with convincing arguments 
that he was divinely authorized to rule the 
civil powers of Italy and of the world.<ref target="n1.4">[4]</ref> 
 
</p><p>Moreover there was, in his pride, something 
akin to fanaticism. He had been 
elected by one of those sudden movements, 
as well known in American caucuses as in 
papal conclaves, when, after a deadlock, 
all the old candidates are thrown over, 
and the choice suddenly falls on a new 
man. The cynical observer may point 
to this as showing that the laws governing 
elections, under such circumstances, 
are the same, whether in party caucuses 
or in church councils; but Paul, in this 
case, saw the direct intervention of the 
Almighty, and his disposition to magnify 
his office was vastly increased thereby. 
He was especially strenuous, and one of 
his earliest public acts was to send to the 
gallows a poor author, who, in an unpublished 
work, had spoken severely regarding 
one of Paul's predecessors. 
</p><p>The Venetian laws checking mortmain, 
taxing church property, and requiring 
the sanction of the Republic before 
the erection of new churches and 
monasteries greatly angered him; but 
the crowning vexation was the seizure 
of the two clerics. This aroused him 
fully. He at once sent orders that they 
be delivered up to him, that apology be 
   <pb n="51"/>   
made for the past and guarantees given 
for the future, and notice was served that, 
in case the Republic did not speedily 
obey these orders, the Pope would excommunicate 
its leaders and lay an interdict 
upon its people. It was indeed a 
serious contingency. For many years 
the new Pope had been known as a hard, 
pedantic ecclesiastical lawyer, and now 
that he had arrived at the supreme 
power, he had evidently determined to 
enforce the high medi&aelig;val supremacy of 
the Church over the State. Everything 
betokened his success. In France he had 
broken down all opposition to the decrees 
of the Council of Trent. In Naples, 
when a magistrate had refused to disobey 
the civil law at the bidding of 
priests, and the viceroy had supported 
the magistrate, Pope Paul had forced the 
viceroy and magistrate to comply with 
his will by threats of excommunication. 
In every part of Italy,&mdash;in Malta, in 
Savoy, in Parma, in Lucca, in Genoa,&mdash;and finally even in Spain, he had pettifogged, 
bullied, threatened, until his opponents 
had given way. Everywhere he 
was triumphant; and while he was in the 
mood which such a succession of triumphs 
would give he turned toward Venice.<ref target="n1.5">[5]</ref> 
 
</p><p>There was little indeed to encourage 
the Venetians to resist; for, while the 
interests of other European powers were 
largely the same as theirs, current political 
intrigues seemed likely to bring Spain 
and even France into a league with the 
Vatican. 
 
</p><p>To a people so devoted to commerce, yet so religious, the threat 
of an interdict was serious indeed. All church services were to cease; 
the people at large, no matter how faithful, were to be as brute 
beasts,&mdash;not to be legally married,&mdash;not to be consoled by the 
sacraments,&mdash;not to be shriven, and virtually not to be buried; other 
Christian peoples were to be forbidden all dealings with them, under 
pain of excommunication; their 
 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
commerce was to be delivered over to 
the tender mercies of any and every other 
nation; their merchant ships to be as 
corsairs; their cargoes, the legitimate 
prey of all Christendom; and their people, 
on sea and land, to be held as enemies 
of the human race. To this was 
added, throughout the whole mass of the 
people, a vague sense of awful penalties 
awaiting them in the next world. Despite 
all this, the Republic persisted in asserting 
its right. 
</p><p>Just at this moment came a diplomatic 
passage between Pope and Senate like a 
farce before a tragedy, and it has historical 
significance, as showing what resourceful 
old heads were at the service of 
either side. The Doge Grimani having 
died, the Vatican thought to score a point 
by promptly sending notice through its 
Nuncio to Venice that no new election 
of a Doge could take place if forbidden 
by the Pope, and that, until the Senate 
had become obedient to the papacy, no 
such election would be sanctioned. But 
the Senate, having through its own Ambassador 
received a useful hint, was quite 
equal to the occasion. It at once declined 
to receive this or any dispatch from the 
Pope on the plea, made with redundant 
courtesy and cordiality, that, there being 
no Doge, there was no person in Venice 
great enough to open it. They next as 
politely declined to admit the papal Nuncio 
on the ground that there was nobody 
worthy to receive him. Then they proceeded 
to elect a Doge who could receive 
both Nuncio and message,&mdash;a sturdy opponent 
of the Vatican pretensions, Leonardo 
Donato. 
</p><p>The Senate now gave itself entirely 
to considering ways and means of warding 
off the threatened catastrophe. Its first 
step was to consult Sarpi. His answer 
was prompt and pithy. He advised two 
things: first, to prevent, at all hazards, 
any publication of the papal bulls in Venice 
or any obedience to them; secondly, 
   <pb n="52"/>   
to hold in readiness for use at any moment 
an appeal to a future Council of the 
Church. 
</p><p>Of these two methods, the first would 
naturally seem by far the more difficult. 
So it was not in reality. In the letter 
which Sarpi presented to the Doge, he 
devoted less than four lines to the first 
and more than fourteen pages to the 
second. As to the first remedy, severe 
as it was and bristling with difficulties, 
it was, as he claimed, a simple, natural, 
straightforward use of police power. As 
to the second, the appeal to a future 
Council was to the Vatican as a red flag 
to a bull. The very use of it involved 
excommunication. To harden and strengthen 
the Doge and Senate in order that 
they might consider it as an ultimate 
possibility, Sarpi was obliged to show from 
the Scriptures, the Fathers, the Councils, 
the early Popes, that the appeal to a 
Council was a matter of right. With wonderful 
breadth of knowledge and clearness 
of statement he made his points and 
answered objections. To this day, his 
letter remains a masterpiece.<ref target="n1.6">[6]</ref> 
 
</p><p>The Republic utterly refused to yield, 
and now, in 1606, Pope Paul launched 
his excommunication and interdict. In 
meeting them, the Senate took the course 
laid down by Sarpi. The papal Nuncio 
was notified that the Senate would receive 
no paper from the Pope; all ecclesiasties, 
from the Patriarch down to the 
lowest monk, were forbidden, under the 
penalties of high treason, to make public 
or even to receive any paper whatever 
from the Vatican; additional guards were 
placed at the city gates, with orders to 
search every wandering friar or other 
suspicious person who might, by any 
possibility, bring in a forbidden missive; 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
a special patrol was kept, night and day, 
to prevent any posting of the forbidden 
notices on walls or houses; any person 
receiving or finding one was to take it 
immediately to the authorities, under the 
severest penalties, and any person found 
concealing such documents was to be punished 
by death. 
</p><p>At first some of the clergy were refractory. 
The head of the whole church 
establishment of Venice, the Patriarch 
himself, gave signs of resistance; but the 
Senate at once silenced him. Sundry 
other bishops and high ecclesiastics made 
a show of opposition; and they were 
placed in confinement. One of them 
seeming reluctant to conduct the usual 
church service, the Senate sent an executioner 
to erect a gibbet before his door. 
Another, having asked that he be allowed 
to await some intimation from the 
Holy Spirit, received answer that the 
Senate had already received directions 
from the Holy Spirit to hang any person 
resisting their decree. The three religious 
orders which had showed most 
opposition&mdash;Jesuits, Theatins, and 
Capuchins&mdash;were in a semi-polite manner 
virtually expelled from the Republic.<ref target="n1.7">[7]</ref> 
 
</p><p>Not the least curious among the results 
of this state of things was the war 
of pamphlets. From Rome, Bologna, and 
other centres of thought, even from Paris 
and Frankfort, polemic tractates rained 
upon the Republic. The vast majority 
of their authors were on the side of the 
Vatican, and of this majority the leaders 
were the two cardinals so eminent in 
learning and logic, Bellarmine and Baronius; 
but, single-handed, Sarpi was, by 
general consent, a match for the whole 
opposing force.<ref target="n1.8">[8]</ref> 
 
</p><p>Of all the weapons then used, the 
   <pb n="53"/>   
most effective throughout Europe was 
the solemn protest drawn by Sarpi and 
issued by the Doge. It was addressed 
nominally to the Venetian ecclesiastics, 
but really to Christendom, and both as to 
matter and manner it was Father Paul 
at his best. It was weighty, lucid, pungent, 
and deeply in earnest,&mdash;in every 
part asserting fidelity to the Church and 
loyalty to the papacy, but setting completely 
at naught the main claim of Pope 
Paul: the Doge solemnly declaring himself 
"a prince who, in temporal matters, 
recognizes no superior save the Divine 
Majesty." 
</p><p>The victory of the friar soon began to 
be recognized far and near. Men called 
him by the name afterward so generally 
given him,&mdash;the <hi rend="italic">"terribile frate</hi>." The 
Vatican seemed paralyzed. None of its 
measures availed, and it was hurt, rather 
than helped, by its efforts to pester and 
annoy Venice at various capitals. At 
Rome, it burned Father Paul's books and 
declared him excommunicated; it even 
sought to punish his printer by putting 
into the Index not only all works that he 
had ever printed, but all that he might 
ever print. At Vienna, the papal Nuncio 
thought to score a point by declaring that 
he would not attend a certain religious 
function in case the Venetian Ambassador 
should appear; whereupon the Venetian 
announced that he had taken physic 
and regretted that he could not be present,&mdash;whereat all Europe laughed. 
</p><p>Judicious friends in various European 
cabinets now urged both parties to recede 
or to compromise. France and Spain 
both proffered their good offices. The 
offer of France was finally accepted, 
and the French Ambassador was kept 
running between the Ducal Palace and 
the Vatican until people began laughing 
at him also. The emissaries of His Holiness 
begged hard that, at least, appearances 
might be saved; that the Republic 
would undo some of its measures before 
the interdict was removed, or at least 
would seem to do so, and especially that 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
it would withdraw its refusals before the 
Pope withdrew his penalties. All in vain. 
The Venetians insisted that they had 
committed no crime and had nothing to 
retract. The Vatican then urged that the 
Senate should consent to receive absolution 
for its resistance to the Pope's authority. 
This the Senate steadily refused; 
it insisted, "Let His Holiness put things 
as before, and we will put things as before; 
as to his absolution, we do not need 
it or want it; to receive it would be to 
acknowledge that we have been in the 
wrong." Even the last poor sop of all 
was refused: the Senate would have no 
great "function" to celebrate the termination 
of the interdict; they would not 
even go to the mass which Cardinal Joyeuse 
celebrated on that occasion. The 
only appearance of concession which the 
Republic made was to give up the two 
ecclesiastics to the French Ambassador as 
a matter of courtesy to the French king; 
and when this was done, the Ambassador 
delivered them to the Pope; but Venice 
especially reserved all the rights she had 
exercised. All the essential demands of 
the papacy were refused, and thus was 
forever ended the papal power of laying 
an interdict upon a city or a people. 
From that incubus, Christendom, thanks 
to Father Paul and to Venice, was at last 
and forever free. 
</p><p>The Vatican did, indeed, try hard to 
keep its old claim in being. A few years 
after its defeat by Fra Paolo, it endeavored 
to reassert in Spain the same authority 
which had been so humbly acknowledged 
there a few years before. 
It was doubtless felt that this most pious 
of all countries, which had previously 
been so docile, and which had stood 
steadily by the Vatican against Venice 
in the recent struggle, would again set 
an example of submission. Never was 
there a greater mistake: the Vatican received 
from Spanish piety a humiliating 
refusal. 
</p><p>Next it tried the old weapons against 
the little government at Turin. For 
   <pb n="54"/>   
many generations the House of Savoy 
had been dutifully submissive to religious 
control; nowhere out of Spain had heresy 
been treated more cruelly; yet here, 
too, the Vatican claim was spurned. But 
the final humiliation took place some 
years later under Urban VIII.,&mdash;the 
same pontiff who wrecked papal infallibility 
on Galileo's telescope. He tried 
to enforce his will on the state of Lucca, 
which, in the days of Pope Paul, had submitted 
to the Vatican decrees abjectly; 
but that little republic now seized the 
weapons which Sarpi had devised, and 
drove the papal forces out of the field: 
the papal excommunication was, even by 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
this petty government, annulled in Venetian 
fashion and even less respectfully.<ref target="n1.9">[9]</ref> 
 
</p><p>Thus the world learned how weak the 
Vatican hold had become. Even Pope 
Paul learned it, and, from being the 
most strenuous of modern pontiffs, he 
became one of the most moderate in 
everything save in the enrichment of his 
family. Thus ended the last serious 
effort to coerce a people by an interdict, 
and so, one might suppose, would end the 
work of Father Paul. Not so. There 
was to come a second chapter in his biography, 
more instructive, perhaps, than 
the first,&mdash;a chapter which has lasted 
until our own day. 
</p><p>A. D. White. 
</p> 
 
<note id="n1.1"><seg type="note-symbol">[1]</seg> <p>This has been admirably shown by N. R. F. 
Brown in his Taylorian Lecture, pages 229-234, 
in volume for 1889-99.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n1.2"><seg type="note-symbol">[2]</seg> <p>See Horatio Seymour's noted article in the 
North American Review.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n1.3"><seg type="note-symbol">[3]</seg> <p>For Sixtus IV. and his career, with the tragedy in the 
Cathedral of Florence see Villari's Life of Machiavelli, English 
Edition, vol. ii. pp. 341, 342. For the passages in the dispatches 
referred to, <hi rend="italic">vide</hi> ibid. vol. i. p. 198.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n1.4"><seg type="note-symbol">[4]</seg> <p>For details of these cases of the two monks, see Pascolato. Fra 
Paolo Sarpi, Milano, 1893, pp. 126-128. For the Borghese avarice, see 
Ranke's Popes, vol. iii. pp. 9-20. For the development of Pope Paul's 
theory of government, see Ranke, vol. ii. p. 345, and note in which 
Bellarmine's doctrine is cited textually; also Bellarmine's 
Selbstbiographie, herausgegeben von D&ouml;llinger und Rensch Bonn, 
1887.  pp. 181, <hi rend="italic">et seq</hi>.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n1.5"><seg type="note-symbol">[5]</seg> <p>For letters showing the craven submission of Philip 
III. of Spain at this time, see Cornet, Paolo V. e la Republica Veneta, 
Vienna, 1859, p. 285.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n1.6"><seg type="note-symbol">[6]</seg> <p>For Sarpi's advice to the Doge, see Bianchi Giovini, 
vol. i. pp. 216, <hi rend="italic">et seq</hi>. The document is given fully in the 
Lettere di F. P. S., Firenze, 1863, vol. i. pp. 17, <hi rend="italic">et seq</hi>.; also 
in Machi, Storia del Consiglio dei Dieci, cap.  xxiv., where the bull of 
excommunication is also given.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n1.7"><seg type="note-symbol">[7]</seg> <p>For interesting details regarding the departure of 
the Jesuits, see Cornet, Paolo V. e la Republica Veneta, pp. 
277-279.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n1.8"><seg type="note-symbol">[8]</seg> <p>In the library of Cornell University are 
no less than nine quartos filled with selected 
examples of these polemics on both sides.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n1.9"><seg type="note-symbol">[9]</seg> <p>The proofs&mdash;and from Catholic sources&mdash;that it was 
the Pope who condemned Galileo's doctrine of the earth's movement about 
the sun, and not merely the Congregation of the Index, the present 
writer has given in his History of the Warfare of Science with Theology, 
vol. i. chap. iii.</p></note> 
 
</div2> 
 
 
 
   <pb n="225"/>   
 
<div2 type="section" id="d5"> 
<head>II.</head> 
 
<p>THE Venetian Republic showed itself 
duly grateful to Sarpi. The Senate 
offered him splendid presents and 
entitled him "Theologian of Venice." 
The presents he refused, but the title 
with its duty, which was mainly to 
guard the Republic against the encroachments 
of the Vatican, he accepted, 
and his life in the monastery of 
Santa Fosca went on quietly, simply, 
laboriously, as before. The hatred now 
felt for him at Rome was unbounded. 
It corresponded to the gratitude at 
Venice. Every one saw his danger, and 
he well knew it. Potentates were then 
wont to send assassins on long errands, 
and the arm of the Vatican was especially 
far-reaching and merciless. It 
was the period when Pius V, the Pope 
whom the Church afterwards proclaimed 
a saint, commissioned an assassin to 
murder Queen Elizabeth.<ref target="n2.1">[1]</ref> 
 
</p><p>But there was in Father Paul a trust 
in Providence akin to fatalism. Again 
and again he was warned, and among 
those who are said to have advised him 
to be on his guard against papal assassins 
was no less a personage than his 
greatest controversial enemy,&mdash;Cardinal 
Bellarmine. It was believed by 
Sarpi's friends that Bellarmine's Scotch 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
ideas of duty to humanity prevailed over 
his Roman ideas of fealty to the Vatican, 
and we may rejoice in the hope that 
his nobler qualities did really assert 
themselves against the casuistry of his 
brother prelates which sanctioned assassination. 
</p><p>These warnings were soon seen to be 
well founded. On a pleasant evening 
in October, 1607, a carefully laid trap 
was sprung. Returning from his day's 
work at the Ducal Palace, Father Paul, 
just as he had crossed the little bridge 
of Santa Fosca before reaching his convent, 
was met by five assassins. Two 
of his usual attendants had been drawn 
off by the outburst of a fire in the 
neighborhood; the other two were old men 
who proved useless. The place was well 
chosen. The descent from the bridge 
was so narrow that all three were obliged 
to march in single file, and just at this 
point these ruffians from Rome sprang 
upon him in the dusk, separated him 
from his companions, and gave him, in 
a moment, fifteen dagger thrusts, two 
in his throat and one&mdash;a fearful gash&mdash;on the side of his head, and then, 
convinced that they had killed him, escaped 
to their boats, only a few paces 
distant. 
</p><p>The victim lingered long in the hospital, 
but his sound constitution and 
   <pb n="226"/>   
abstemious habits stood him in good 
stead. Very important among the qualities 
which restored him to health were 
his optimism and cheerfulness. An early 
manifestation of the first of these was 
seen when, on regaining consciousness, 
he called for the stiletto which had been 
drawn from the main wound and, running 
his fingers along the blade, said 
cheerily to his friends, "It is not filed." 
What this meant, any one knows who 
has seen in various European collections 
the daggers dating from the "ages of 
faith" cunningly filed or grooved to hold 
poison.<ref target="n2.2">[2]</ref> 
 
</p><p>As an example of the second of these 
qualities, we may take his well-known 
reply when, to the surgeon dressing the 
wound made by the "style" or stiletto,&mdash;who spoke of its "extravagance," 
rudeness, and yet ineffectiveness,&mdash;Fra 
Paolo quietly answered that in these 
characteristics could be recognized the 
<hi rend="italic">style</hi> of the Roman Curia. 
</p><p>Meantime the assassins had found 
their way back to Rome, and were welcomed 
with open arms; but it is some 
comfort to know that later, when such 
conscience as there was throughout Italy 
and Europe showed intense disgust at 
the proceeding, the Roman Court treated 
them coldly and even severely. 
</p><p>The Republic continued in every way 
to show Sarpi its sympathy and gratitude. 
It made him many splendid offer, 
which he refused; but two gifts he accepted. 
One was full permission to explore 
the Venetian archives, and the other 
was a little doorway, cut through the 
garden wall of his monastery, enabling 
him to reach his gondola without going 
through the narrow and tortuous path 
he had formerly taken on his daily 
journey to the public offices. This 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
humble portal still remains. Beneath 
few triumphal arches has there ever 
passed as great or as noble a conqueror.<ref target="n2.3">[3]</ref> 
 
</p><p>Efforts were also made to cajole him,&mdash;to induce him to visit Rome, with 
fine promises of recognition and honor, 
and with solemn assurances that no 
harm should come to him; but he was 
too wise to yield. Only a few years 
previously he had seen Giordano Bruno 
lured to Rome and burned alive on the 
Campo dei Fiori. He had seen his 
friend and correspondent, Fra Fulgentio 
Manfredi, yield to similar allurements 
and accept a safe conduct to Rome, 
which, though it solemnly guaranteed 
him against harm, proved as worthless 
as that of John Huss at the Council 
of Constance; the Inquisition torturing 
him to death on the spot where, six 
years earlier, it had burned Bruno. He 
had seen his friend, the Archdeacon 
Ribetti, drawn within the clutch of the 
Vatican, only to die of "a most painful 
colic" immediately after dining with 
a confidential chamberlain of the Pope, 
and, had he lived a few months longer, 
he would have seen his friend and confidant, 
Antonio de Dominis, Archbishop 
of Spalato, to whom he had entrusted 
a copy of his most important work, enticed 
to Rome and put to death by the 
Inquisition. Though the Vatican exercised 
a strong fascination over its enemies, 
against Father Paul it was powerless; 
he never yielded to it, but kept 
the even tenor of his way.<ref target="n2.4">[4]</ref> 
 
</p><p>In the dispatches which now passed, 
comedy was mingled with tragedy. 
Very unctuous was the expression by 
His Holiness of his apprehensions regarding 
"dangers to the salvation" 
and of his "fears for the souls" of the 
   <pb n="227"/>   
Venetian Senators, if they persisted in 
asserting their own control of their own 
state. Hardly less touching were the 
fears expressed by the good Oratorian, 
Cardinal Baronius, that "a judgment 
might be brought upon the Republic" 
if it declined to let the Vatican have 
its way. But these expressions were 
not likely to prevail with men who had 
dealt with Machiavelli. 
</p><p>Uncompromising as ever, Father 
Paul continued to write letters and 
publish treatises which clenched more 
and more firmly into the mind of Venice 
and of Europe the political doctrine 
of which he was the apostle,&mdash;the doctrine 
that the State is rightfully independent 
of the Church,&mdash;and throughout 
the Christian world he was recognized 
as victor. 
</p><p>Nothing could exceed the bitterness 
of the attacks upon him, though some 
of them, at this day, provoke a smile. 
While efforts were made to discredit 
him among scholars by spurious writings 
or by interpolations in genuine writings, 
efforts equally ingenious were made to 
arouse popular hostility. One of these 
was a painting which represented him 
writhing amid the flames of hell, with 
a legend stating, as a reason for his 
punishment, that he had opposed the 
Holy Father. 
</p><p>Now it was indeed, in the midst of 
ferocious attacks upon his reputation and 
cunning attempts upon his life, that he 
entered a new and most effective period 
of activity. For years, as the adviser 
of Venice, he had studied, both as a 
historian and as a statesman, the greatest 
questions which concerned his country, 
and especially those which related 
to the persistent efforts of the Vatican 
to encroach upon Venetian self-government. 
The results of these studies he 
had embodied in reports which had 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
shaped the course of the Republic; and 
now, his learning and powers of thought 
being brought to bear upon the policy 
of Europe in general, as affected by 
similar papal encroachments, he began 
publishing a series of treatises, which 
at once attracted general attention.<ref target="n2.5">[5]</ref> 
 
</p><p>First of these, in 1608, came his 
work on the Interdict. Clearly and 
concisely it revealed the nature of the 
recent struggle, the baselessness of the 
Vatican claims, and the solidarity of 
interest between Venice and all other 
European states regarding the question 
therein settled. This work of his as a 
historian clenched his work as a statesman; 
from that day forward no nation 
has even been seriously threatened with 
an interdict. 
 
</p><p>Subsidiary works followed rapidly from his pen, strengthening the 
civil power against the clerical; but in 1610 came a treatise, which 
marked an epoch,&mdash;his History of Ecclesiastical Benefices.<ref 
target="n2.6">[6]</ref> In this he dealt with a problem which had 
become very serious, not only in Venice, but in every European state, 
showed the process by which vast treasures had been taken from the 
control of the civil power and heaped up for ecclesiastical pomp and 
intrigue, pointed out special wrongs done by the system to the Church as 
well as the State, and advocated a reform which should restore this 
wealth to better uses. His arguments spread widely and sank deep, not 
only in Italy, but throughout Europe, and the nineteenth century has 
seen them applied effectively in every European country within the Roman 
obedience. 
 
</p><p>In 1611 he published his work on 
the Inquisition at Venice, presenting 
historical arguments against the 
uses which ecclesiasticism, under papal 
guidance, had made of that tribunal. 
   <pb n="228"/>   
These arguments spread far, and developed 
throughout Europe those views of 
the Inquisition which finally led to its 
destruction. Minor treatises followed, 
dealing with state questions arising 
between the Vatican and Venice, each 
treatise&mdash;thoroughly well reasoned and 
convincing&mdash;having a strong effect on 
the discussion of similar public questions 
in every other European nation. 
</p><p>In 1613 came two books of a high 
order, each marking an epoch. The 
first of these was upon the Right of 
Sanctuary, and in it Sarpi led the way, 
which all modern states have followed, 
out of the old, vicious system of sanctioning 
crime by sheltering criminals. 
The cogency of his argument and the 
value of its application gained for him 
an especial tribute by the best authority 
on such questions whom Europe had 
seen,&mdash;Hugo Grotius. 
</p><p>Closely connected with this work was 
that upon the Immunity of the Clergy. 
Both this and the previous work were 
in the same order of ideas, and the 
second fastened into the European mind 
the reasons why no state can depend 
upon the Church for the punishment of 
clerical criminals. His argument was 
a triumphant vindication of Venice in 
her struggle with Paul V on this point; 
but it was more than that. It became 
the practical guide of all modern states. 
Its arguments dissipated the last efforts 
throughout Europe to make a distinction, 
in criminal matters, between the 
priestly caste and the world in general. 
</p><p>Among lesser treatises which followed 
is one which has done much to 
shape modern policy regarding public 
instruction. This was his book upon 
the Education given by the Jesuits. 
One idea which it enforced sank deep 
into the minds of all thoughtful men,&mdash;his statement that Jesuit maxims develop 
"sons disobedient to their parents, 
citizens unfaithful to their country, and 
subjects undutiful to their sovereign." 
Jesuit education has indeed been maintained, 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
and evidences of it may be 
seen in various European countries. 
The traveler in Italy constantly sees in 
the larger Italian towns long lines of 
young men and boys, sallow, thin, and 
listless, walking two and two, with 
priests at each end of the coffle. These 
are students taking their exercise, and 
an American or Englishman marvels as 
he remembers the playing fields of his 
own country. Youth are thus brought 
up as milksops, to be graduated as scapegraces. The strong men who control 
public affairs, who lead men and originate 
measures in the open, are not 
bred in Jesuit forcing-houses. Even the 
Jesuits themselves have acknowledged 
this, and perhaps the strongest of all 
arguments supplementary to those given 
by Father Paul were uttered by Padre 
Curci, eminent in his day as a Jesuit 
gladiator, but who realized finally the 
impossibility of accomplishing great 
things with men moulded by Jesuit 
methods. 
</p><p>All these works took strong hold upon 
European thought. Leading men in all 
parts of Europe recognized Sarpi as both 
a great statesman and a great historian. 
Among his English friends were such men 
as Lord Bacon and Sir Henry Wotton; 
and his praises have been sounded by 
Grotius, by Gibbon, by Hallam, and by 
Macaulay. Strong, lucid, these works 
of Father Paul have always been especially 
attractive to those who rejoice 
in the leadership of a master mind. 
</p><p>But in 1619 came the most important 
of all,&mdash;a service to humanity 
hardly less striking than that which he 
had rendered in his battle against the 
Interdict,&mdash;his history of the Council 
of Trent. 
</p><p>His close relations to so many of the 
foremost men of his day and his long 
study in public archives and private 
libraries bore fruit in this work, which 
takes rank among the few great, enduring 
historical treatises of the world. 
Throughout, it is vigorous and witty, 
but at the same time profound; everywhere 
   <pb n="229"/>   
it bears evidences of truthfulness 
and is pervaded by sobriety of judgment. 
Its pictures of the efforts or 
threats by representatives of various 
great powers to break away from the 
papacy and establish national churches; 
its presentation of the arguments of 
anti-papal orators on one side and of 
Laynez and his satellites on the other; 
its display of acts and revelations of 
pretexts; its penetration into the whole 
network of intrigue, and its thorough 
discussion of underlying principles,&mdash;all are masterly. 
</p><p>Though the name of the author was 
concealed in an anagram, the book was 
felt, by the Vatican party, to be a blow 
which only one man could have dealt, 
and the worst blow which the party had 
received since its author had defeated 
the Interdict at Venice. Efforts were 
made, by outcries and calumnies, to discredit 
the work, and they have been continued 
from that day to this, but in 
vain. That there must be some gaps 
and many imperfections in it is certain; 
but its general character is beyond the 
reach of ultramontane weapons. The 
blow was felt to be so heavy that the 
Jesuit Pallavicini was empowered to 
write a history of the Council to 
counterbalance it, and his work was well 
done; but Ranke, the most unprejudiced 
of judges, comparing the two, 
assigns the palm to Father Paul. His 
book was immediately spread throughout 
Europe; but of all the translations, 
perhaps the most noteworthy was the 
English. Sarpi had entrusted a copy 
of the original to his friend, Antonio 
de Dominis, Archbishop of Spalato, 
and he, having taken refuge in England, 
had it translated there, the authorship 
being ascribed on the title-page 
to "Pietro Soave Polano." This English 
translation was, in vigor and pith, 
worthy of the original. In it can be 
discerned, as clearly as in the original, 
that atmosphere of intrigue and brutal 
assertion of power by which the Roman 
Curia, after packing the Council with 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
petty Italian bishops, bade defiance to 
the Catholic world. This translation, 
more than all else, has enabled the 
English-speaking peoples to understand 
what was meant by the Italian historian 
when he said that Father Paul "taught 
the world how the Holy Spirit guides 
the Great Councils of the Church." It 
remains cogent down to this day; after 
reading it one feels that such guidance 
might equally be claimed for Tammany 
Hall. 
</p><p>Although Father Paul never acknowledged 
the authorship of the history of 
the Council of Trent, and although his 
original copy, prepared for the press, 
with his latest corrections, still remains 
buried in the archives at Venice, the 
whole world knew that he alone could 
have written it. 
</p><p>But during all these years, while 
elaborating opinions on the weightiest 
matters of state for the Venetian Senate, 
and sending out this series of books 
which so powerfully influenced the attitude 
of his own and after generations 
toward the Vatican, he was working 
with great effect in yet another field. 
With the possible exception of Voltaire, 
he was the most vigorous and influential 
letter-writer during the three hundred 
years which separated Erasmus 
from Thomas Jefferson. Voltaire certainly 
spread his work over a larger 
field, lighted it with more wit, and 
gained by it more brilliant victories; 
but as regards accurate historical knowledge, 
close acquaintance with statesmen, 
familiarity with the best and 
worst which statesmen could do, sober 
judgment and cogent argument, the 
great Venetian was his superior. Curiously 
enough, Sarpi resembles the 
American statesman more closely than 
either of the Europeans. Both he and 
Jefferson had the intense practical 
interest of statesmen, not only in the 
welfare of their own countries, but in 
all the political and religious problems 
of their times. Both were keenly alive 
to progress in the physical sciences, 
   <pb n="230"/>   
wherever made. Both were wont to 
throw a light veil of humor over very 
serious discussions. Both could use, 
with great effect, curt, caustic description: 
Jefferson's letter to Governor 
Langdon satirizing the crowned heads 
of Europe, as he had seen them, has a 
worthy pendant in Fra Paolo's pictures 
of sundry representatives of the Vatican. 
In both these writers was a deep 
earnestness which, at times, showed itself 
in prophetic utterances. The amazing 
prophecy of Jefferson against American 
slavery, beginning with the words, 
"I tremble when I remember that God 
is just," which, in the light of our civil 
war, seems divinely inspired, is paralleled 
by some of Sarpi's utterances 
against the unmoral tendencies of Jesuitism 
and Ultramontanism; and these 
too seem divinely inspired as one reads 
them in the light of what has happened 
since in Spain, in Sicily, in Naples, in 
Poland, in Ireland, and in sundry South 
American republics. 
</p><p>The range of Sarpi's friendly relations 
was amazing. They embraced 
statesmen, churchmen, scholars, scientific 
investigators, diplomatists in every 
part of Europe, and among these Galileo 
and Lord Bacon, Grotius and Mornay, 
Salmasius and Casaubon, De Thou 
and Sir Henry Wotton, Bishop Bedell 
and Vossius, with a great number of 
others of nearly equal rank. Unfortunately 
the greater part of his correspondence 
has perished. In the two 
small volumes collected by Polidori, 
and in the small additional volume of 
letters to Simon Contarini, Venetian 
Ambassador at Rome, unearthed a few 
years since in the Venetian archives by 
Castellani, we have all that is known. 
It is but a small fraction of his epistolary 
work, but it enables us to form a 
clear opinion. The letters are well 
worthy of the man who wrote the history 
of the Council of Trent and the 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
protest of Venice against the Interdict. 
</p><p>It is true that there has been derived 
from these letters, by his open enemies 
on one side and his defenders of a 
rather sickly conscientious sort on the 
other, one charge against him: this is 
based on his famous declaration, "I 
utter falsehood never, but the truth not 
to every one." ("La falsit&agrave; non dico 
mai mai, ma la verit&agrave; non a  
ogniuno.")<ref target="n2.7">[7]</ref> 
Considering his vast responsibilities 
as a statesman and the terrible dangers 
which beset him as a theologian; 
that in the first of these capacities 
the least misstep might wreck the great 
cause which he supported, and that in 
the second such a misstep might easily 
bring him to the torture chamber and 
the stake, normally healthful minds 
will doubtless agree that the criticism 
upon these words is more Pharisaic than 
wholesome. 
 
</p><p>Sarpi was now spoken of, more than 
ever, both among friends and foes, as 
the <hi rend="italic">"terribile frate</hi>." Terrible to the 
main enemies of Venice he indeed was, 
and the machinations of his opponents 
grew more and more serious. Efforts 
to assassinate him, to poison him, to 
discredit him, to lure him to Rome, or 
at least within reach of the Inquisition, 
became almost frantic; but all in vain. 
He still continued his quiet life at the 
monastery of Santa Fosca, publishing 
from time to time discussions of questions 
important for Venice and for Europe, 
working steadily in the public service 
until his last hours. In spite of his 
excommunication and of his friendships 
with many of the most earnest Protestants 
of Europe, he remained a son of 
the church in which he was born. His 
life was shaped in accordance with its 
general precepts, and every day he heard 
mass. So his career quietly ran on 
until, in 1623, he met death calmly, 
without fear, in full reliance upon the 
   <pb n="231"/>   
divine justice and mercy. His last 
words were a prayer for Venice. 
</p><p>He had fought the good fight. He 
had won it for Venice and for humanity. 
For all this, the Republic had, in 
his later years, tried to show her gratitude, 
and he had quietly and firmly refused 
the main gifts proposed to him. 
But now came a new outburst of grateful 
feeling. The Republic sent notice 
of his death to other powers of Europe 
through its Ambassadors in the terms 
usual at the death of royal personages; in 
every way, it showed its appreciation of 
his character and services, and it crowned 
all by voting him a public monument. 
</p><p>Hardly was the decree known, when 
the Vatican authorities sent notice that, 
should any monument be erected to 
Sarpi, they would anew and publicly 
declare him excommunicate as a heretic. 
At this, the Venetian Senate hesitated, 
waited, delayed. Whenever afterwards 
the idea of carrying out the 
decree for the monument was revived, 
there set in a storm of opposition from 
Rome. Hatred of the terrible friar's 
memory seemed to grow more and more 
bitter. Even rest in the grave was 
denied him. The church where he was 
buried having been demolished, the question 
arose as to the disposition of his 
bones. To bury them in sacred ground 
outside the old convent would arouse 
a storm of ecclesiastical hostility, with 
the certainty of their dispersion and 
desecration; it seemed impossible to secure 
them from priestly hatred: therefore 
it was that his friends took them 
from place to place, sometimes concealing 
them in the wall of a church here, 
sometimes beneath the pavement of a 
church there, and for a time keeping 
them in a simple wooden box at the 
Ducal Library. The place where his 
remains rested became, to most Venetians, 
unknown. All that remained to 
remind the world of his work was his 
portrait in the Ducal Library, showing 
the great gash made by the Vatican 
assassins. 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
</p><p>Time went on, and generations came 
which seemed to forget him. Still 
worse, generation after generation came, 
carefully trained by clerical teachers to 
misunderstand and hate him. But these 
teachers went too far; for, in 1771, 
nearly one hundred and fifty years after 
his death, the monk Vaerini gathered 
together, in a pretended biography, 
all the scurrilities which could 
be imagined, and endeavored to bury 
the memory of the great patriot beneath 
them. This was too much. The old 
Venetian spirit, which had so long lain 
dormant, now asserted itself: Vaerini 
was imprisoned and his book suppressed. 
</p><p>A quarter of a century later the Republic 
fell under the rule of Austria, and 
Austria's most time-honored agency in 
keeping down subject populations has 
always been the priesthood. Again 
Father Paul's memory was virtually 
proscribed, and in 1803 another desperate 
attempt was made to cover him with 
infamy. In that year appeared a book 
entitled The Secret History of the Life 
of Fra Paolo Sarpi, and it contained 
not only his pretended biography, but 
what claimed to be Sarpi's own letters 
and other documents showing him to be 
an adept in scoundrelism and hypocrisy. 
Its editor was the archpriest Ferrara of 
Mantua; but on the title-page appeared, 
as the name of its author, Fontanini, 
Archbishop of Ancira, a greatly respected 
prelate who had died nearly 
seventy years before, and there was also 
stamped, not only upon the preliminary, 
but upon the final page of the work, the 
approval of the Austrian government. 
To this was added a pious motto from 
St. Augustine, and the approval of Pius 
VII was distinctly implied, since the 
work was never placed upon the Index, 
and could not have been published at 
Venice, stamped as it was and registered 
with the privileges of the University, 
without the consent of the Vatican. 
</p><p>The memory of Father Paul seemed 
likely now to be overwhelmed. There 
was no longer a Republic of Venice to 
   <pb n="232"/>   
guard the noble traditions of his life 
and service. The book was recommended 
and spread far and wide by preachers 
and confessors. 
</p><p>But at last came a day of judgment. 
The director of the Venetian archives 
discovered and had the courage to announce 
that the work was a pious fraud 
of the vilest type; that it was never 
written by Fontanini, but that it was 
simply made up out of the old scurrilous 
work of Vaerini, suppressed over thirty 
years before. As to the correspondence 
served up as supplementary to the 
biography, it was concocted from letters 
already published, with the addition of 
Jesuitical interpolations and of  
forgeries.<ref target="n2.8">[8]</ref> 
Now came the inevitable reaction, 
and with it the inevitable increase of 
hatred for Austrian rule and the inevitable 
question, how, if the Pope is the 
infallible teacher of the world in all matters 
pertaining to faith and morals, could 
he virtually approve this book, and why 
did he not, by virtue of his divine 
inerrancy, detect the fraud and place its 
condemnation upon the Index. The only 
lasting effect of the book, then, was to 
revive the memory of Father Paul's 
great deeds and to arouse Venetian 
pride in them. The fearful scar on his 
face in the portrait spoke more eloquently 
than ever, and so it was that, 
early in the nineteenth century, many 
men of influence joined in proposing a 
suitable and final interment for the poor 
bones, which had seven times been buried 
and reburied, and which had so long 
been kept in the sordid box at the Ducal 
Library. The one fitting place of burial 
was the cemetery of San Michele. 
To that beautiful island, so near the 
heart of Venice, had, for many years, 
been borne the remains of leading Venetians. 
There, too, in more recent days, 
have been laid to rest many of other 
lands widely respected and beloved. 
 
</p><p>But the same persistent hatred which, 
in our own day, grudged and delayed 
due honors at the tombs of Copernicus 
and Galileo among Catholics, and of 
Humboldt among Protestants, was still 
bitter against the great Venetian scholar 
and statesman. It could not be forgotten 
that he had wrested from the Vatican 
the most terrible of its weapons. 
But patriotic pride was strong, and finally 
a compromise was made: it was arranged 
that Sarpi should be buried and 
honored at his burial as an eminent man 
of science, and that no word should be 
spoken of his main services to the Republic 
and to the world. On this condition 
he was buried with simple honors. 
</p><p>Soon, however, began another chapter 
of hatred. There came a pope who added 
personal to official hostility. Gregory 
XVI, who in his earlier days had been 
abbot of the monastery of San Michele, 
was indignant that the friar who had 
thwarted the papacy should lie buried 
in the convent which he himself had 
formerly ruled, and this feeling took 
shape, first, in violent speeches at Rome, 
and next, in brutal acts at Venice. The 
monks broke and removed the simple 
stone placed over the remains of Father 
Paul, and when it was replaced, they 
persisted in defacing and breaking it, 
and were only prevented from dragging 
out his bones, dishonoring them and casting 
them into the lagoon, by the weight 
of the massive, strong, well-anchored 
sarcophagus, which the wise foresight of 
his admirers had provided for them. 
At three different visits to Venice, the 
present writer sought the spot where 
they were laid, and in vain. At the 
second of these visits, he found the 
Patriarch of Venice, under whose rule 
various outrages upon Sarpi's memory 
had been perpetrated, pontificating 
gorgeously about the Grand Piazza; but at 
his next visit there had come a change. 
   <pb n="233"/>   
The monks had disappeared. Their insults 
to the illustrious dead had been 
stopped by laws which expelled them 
from their convent, and there, little 
removed from each other in the vestibule 
and aisle of the great church, were the 
tombs of Father Paul and of the late 
Patriarch side by side; the great patriot's 
simple gravestone was now allowed 
to rest unbroken. 
</p><p>Better even than this was the reaction 
provoked by these outbursts of ecclesiastical 
hatred. It was felt, in Venice, 
throughout Italy, and indeed throughout 
the world, that the old decree for 
a monument should now be made good. 
The first steps were hesitating. First, 
a bust of Father Paul was placed among 
those of great Venetians in the court of 
the Ducal Palace; but the inscription 
upon it was timid and double-tongued. 
Another bust was placed on the Pincian 
Hill at Rome, among those of the most 
renowned sons of Italy. This was not 
enough: a suitable monument must be 
<milestone unit="column"/> 
erected. Yet it was delayed, timid men 
deprecating the hostility of the Roman 
Court. At last, under the new Italian 
monarchy, the patriotic movement became 
irresistible, and the same impulse 
which erected the splendid statue to 
Giordano Bruno on the Piazza dei Fiori 
at Rome,&mdash;on the very spot where he 
was burned,&mdash;and which adorned it 
with the medallions of eight other martyrs 
to ecclesiastical hatred, erected in 
1892, two hundred and seventy years 
after it had been decreed, a statue, 
hardly less imposing, to Paolo Sarpi, 
on the Piazza Santa Fosca at Venice, 
where he had been left for dead by the 
Vatican assassins. There it stands, 
noble and serene,&mdash;a monument of 
patriotism and right reason, a worthy 
tribute to one who, among intellectual 
prostitutes and solemnly constituted 
impostors, stood forth as a true man, the 
greatest of his time,&mdash;one of the greatest 
of all times,&mdash;an honor to Venice, 
to Italy, and to humanity. 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Andrew D. White</hi>. 
</p> 
 
<note id="n2.1"><seg type="note-symbol">[1]</seg> <p>This statement formerly led to violent denials by 
ultramontane champions; but in 1870 it was made by Lord Acton, a Roman 
Catholic, one of the most learned of modern historians, and when it was 
angrily denied, he quietly cited the official life of Pope Pius in the 
Acta Sanctorum, published by the highest church authority.  This was 
final; denial ceased, and the statement is no longer questioned. For 
other proofs in the line of Lord Acton's citation, see Bellarmine's 
Selbstbiographie, cited in a previous article, pp. 306, <hi rend="italic">et 
seq</hi>.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n2.2"><seg type="note-symbol">[2]</seg> <p>There is a remarkable example of a beautiful dagger, 
grooved to contain poison, in the imperial collection of arms at 
Vienna.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n2.3"><seg type="note-symbol">[3]</seg> <p>The present writer has examined with care the spot 
where the attack was made, and found that never was a scoundrelly plot 
better conceived or more fiendishly executed. He also visited what was 
remaining of the convent in April, 1902, and found the little door as 
serviceable as when it was made.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n2.4"><seg type="note-symbol">[4]</seg> <p>A copy of Manfredi's "safe conduct" is given by 
Castellani, Lettere Inedite di F. P. S., p. 12, note. Nothing could be 
more explicit.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n2.5"><seg type="note-symbol">[5]</seg> <p>For the extent to which these attacks were carried, 
see the large number in the Sarpi collection at the Cornell University 
Library, especially volume ix.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n2.6"><seg type="note-symbol">[6]</seg> <p>The old English translation of this book, published 
in 1736 at Westminster, is by no means a very rare book, and it affords 
the general reader perhaps the most accessible means of understanding 
Fra Paolo's simplicity, thoroughness, and vigor.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n2.7"><seg type="note-symbol">[7]</seg> <p>For this famous utterance, see notes of 
conversations given by Christoph, Burggraf von 
Dohna, in July, 1608, in Briefe und Acten zur 
Geschichte des Dreissigj&auml;hrigen Krieges, M&uuml;nchen, 
1874, p. 79.</p></note> 
 
<note id="n2.8"><seg type="note-symbol">[8]</seg> <p>For a full and fair statement of the researches 
which exposed this pious fraud, see Castellani, Prefect of the Library 
of St. Mark, preface to his Lettere Inedite di F. P. S., p.  xvii. For 
methods used in interpolating or modifying passages in Sarpi's writings, 
see Bianchi Giovini, Biografia di Sarpi, Zurigo, 1847, vol. ii. pp. 135, 
<hi rend="italic">et seq</hi>.</p></note> 
 
</div2> 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
