<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WilConf"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
 
<TEI.2 id="WilConf"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Conflict Ended</title>
<title type="sort">conflict ended</title>
<author>Wilkins, Mary E.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp> 
<name>creator of image(s)</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>Catherine Tousignant, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">30</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WilConf</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476545</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Conflict Ended</title>
<title>Harper's Magazine</title>
<title type="sort">conflict ended</title>
<author>Mary E. Wilkins</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harper's Magazine</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1886-02">February 1886</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Volume 72, pages 470-476.  UVA library AP2 H3</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1886">1886</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-12">December 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Catherine Tousignant, UVA Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added TEI header; converted markup to TEI.</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 
<div1 type="story" id="d3"> 
<head> 
Wilkins, Mary E.  "A Conflict Ended."  <hi rend="italic">Harper's New Monthly 
Magazine</hi> 72 (Feb. 1886): 470-476. 
</head> 
 
<pb n="470"/>  
 
<p>IN Acton there were two churches, an Orthodox and a Baptist.  They 
stood on opposite sides of the road, and the Baptist edifice was a 
little farther down than the other.  On Sunday morning both bells 
were ringing.  The Baptist bell was much larger, and followed 
quickly on the soft peal of the Orthodox with a heavy brazen clang 
which vibrated a good while.  The people went flocking through the 
street to the irregular jangle of the bells.  It was a very hot 
day, and the sun beat down heavily; parasols were bobbing over all 
the ladies' heads. 
</p><p>More people went into the Baptist church, whose society was 
much the larger of the two.  It had been for the last ten years&mdash; 
ever since the Orthodox had settled a new minister.  His advent had 
divided the church, and a good third of the congregation had gone 
over to the Baptist brethren, with whom they still remained. 
</p><p>It is probable that many of them passed their old sanctuary 
to-day with the original stubborn animosity as active as ever in 
their hearts, and led their families up the Baptist steps with the 
same strong spiritual pull of indignation. 
</p><p>One old lady, who had made herself prominent on the 
opposition, trotted by this morning with the identical wiry 
vehemence which she had manifested ten years ago.  She wore a full 
black silk skirt, which she held up inanely in front, and allowed 
to trail in the dust in the rear. 
</p><p>Some of the stanch Orthodox people glanced at her amusedly.  
One fleshy, fair-faced girl in blue muslin said to her companion, 
with a laugh: "See that old lady trailing her best black silk by to 
the Baptist.  Ain't it ridiculous how she holds on showing out?  I 
heard some one talking about it yesterday." 
</p><p>"Yes." 
</p><p>The girl colored up confusedly.  "Oh dear!" she thought to 
herself.  The lady with her had an unpleasant history connected 
with this old church quarrel.  She was a small, bony woman in a 
shiny purple silk, which was strained very tightly across her sharp 
shoulder-blades.  Her bonnet was quite elaborate with flowers and 
plumes, as was also her companion's.  In fact, she was the village 
milliner, and the girl was her apprentice. 
</p><p>When the two went up the church steps, they passed a man of 
about fifty, who was sitting thereon well to one side.  He had a 
singular face&mdash;a mild forehead, a gently curving mouth, and a 
terrible chin, with a look of strength in it that might have 
abashed mountains.  He held his straw hat in his hand, and the sun 
was shining full on his bald head. 
</p><p>The milliner half stopped, and gave an anxious glance at him; 
then passed on.  In the vestibule she stopped again. <pb n="471"/>  
</p><p>"You go right in, Margy," she said to the girl.  "I'll be 
along in a minute." 
</p><p>"Where be you going, Miss Barney?" 
</p><p>"You go right in.  I'll be there in a minute." 
</p><p>Margy entered the audience-room then, as if fairly brushed in 
by the imperious wave of a little knotty hand, and Esther Barney 
stood waiting until the rush of entering people was over.  Then she 
stepped swiftly back to the side of the man seated on the steps.  
She spread her large black parasol deliberately, and extended the 
handle toward him. 
</p><p>"No, no, Esther; I don't want it&mdash;I don't want it." 
</p><p>"If you're determined on setting out in this broiling sun, 
Marcus Woodman, you jest take this parasol of mine an' use it." 
</p><p>"I don't want your parasol, Esther.  I&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Don't you say it over again.  Take it." 
</p><p>"I won't&mdash;not if I don't want to." 
</p><p>"You'll get a sun-stroke." 
</p><p>"That's my own lookout." 
</p><p>"Marcus Woodman, you take it." 
</p><p>She threw all the force there was in her intense, nervous 
nature in her tone and look, but she failed in her attempt, because 
of the utter difference in quality between her own will and that 
with which she had to deal.  They were on so different planes that 
hers slid by his with its own momentum; there could be no contact 
even of antagonism between them.  He sat there rigid, every line of 
his face stiffened into an icy obstinacy.  She held out the parasol 
toward him like a weapon. 
</p><p>Finally she let it drop at her side, her whole expression 
changed. 
</p><p>"Marcus," said she, "how's your mother?" 
</p><p>He started.  "Pretty well, thank you, Esther." 
</p><p>"She's out to meeting, then?" 
</p><p>"Yes." 
</p><p>"I've been a-thinking&mdash;I ain't drove jest now&mdash;that maybe I'd 
come over an' see her some day this week." 
</p><p>He rose politely then.  "Wish you would, Esther.  Mother'd be 
real pleased, I know." 
</p><p>"Well, I'll see&mdash;Wednesday, p'rhaps, if I ain't too busy.  I 
must go in now; they're 'most through singing." 
</p><p>"Esther&mdash;" 
</p><p>"I don't believe I can stop any longer, Marcus." 
</p><p>"About the parasol&mdash;thank you jest the same if I don't take 
it.  Of course you know I can't set out here holding a parasol; 
folks would laugh.  But I'm obliged to you all the same.  Hope I 
didn't say anything to hurt your feelings?" 
</p><p>"Oh no; why, no, Marcus.  Of course I don't want to make you 
take it if you don't want it.  I don't know but it would look 
kinder queer, come to think of it.  Oh dear! they are through 
singing." 
</p><p>"Say, Esther, I don't know but I might as well take that 
parasol, if you'd jest as soon.  The sun is pretty hot, an' I might 
get a headache.  I forgot my umbrella, to tell the truth." 
</p><p>"I might have known better than to have gone at him the way I 
did," thought Esther to herself, when she was seated at last in the 
cool church beside Margy.  "Seems as if I might have got used to 
Marcus Woodman by this time." 
</p><p>She did not see him when she came out of church; but a little 
boy in the vestibule handed her the parasol, with the remark, "Mr. 
Woodman said for me to give this to you." 
</p><p>She and Margy passed down the street toward home.  Going by 
the Baptist church, they noticed a young man standing by the 
entrance.  He stared hard at Margy. 
</p><p>She began to laugh after they had passed him.  "Did you see 
that fellow stare?" said she.  "Hope he'll know me next time." 
</p><p>"That's George Elliot; he's that old lady's son you was 
speaking about this morning." 
</p><p>"Well, that's enough for me." 
</p><p>"He's a real good, steady young man." 
</p><p>Margy sniffed. 
</p><p>"P'rhaps you'll change your mind some day." 
</p><p>She did, and speedily, too.  That glimpse of Margy Wilson's 
pretty, new face&mdash;for she was a stranger in the town&mdash;had been too 
much for George Elliot.  He obtained an introduction, and soon was 
a steady visitor at Esther Barney's house.  Margy fell in love with 
him easily.  She had never had much attention from the young men, 
and he was an engaging young fellow, small and bright-eyed, though 
with a nervous persistency like his mother's in his manner. 
</p><p>"I'm going to have it an understood thing," Margy told Esther, 
after her lover had become constant in his attentions, <pb n="472"/>  
"that I'm going with George, and I ain't going with his mother.  I 
can't bear that old woman." 
</p><p>But poor Margy found that it was not so easy to thrust 
determined old age off the stage, even when young Love was flying 
about so fast on his butterfly wings that he seemed to multiply 
himself, and there was no room for anything else, because the air 
was so full of Loves.  That old mother with her trailing black 
skirt and her wiry obstinacy, trotted as unwaveringly through the 
sweet stir as a ghost through a door. 
</p><p>One Monday morning Margy could not eat any breakfast, and 
there were red stains around her blue eyes. 
</p><p>"Why, what's the matter, Margy?" asked Esther, eying her 
across the little kitchen table. 
</p><p>"Nothing's the matter.  I ain't hungry any to speak of, that's 
all.  I guess I'll go right to work on Mis' Fuller's bonnet." 
</p><p>"I'd try an' eat something if I was you.  Be sure you cut that 
velvet straight, if you go to work on it." 
</p><p>When the two were sitting together at their work in the little 
room back of the shop, Margy suddenly threw her scissors down.  
"There!" said she, "I've done it; I knew I should.  I've cut this 
velvet bias.  I knew I should cut everything bias I touched to-day." 
</p><p>There was a droll pucker on her mouth; then it began to 
quiver.  She hid her face in her hands and sobbed.  "Oh, dear, 
dear, dear!" 
</p><p>"Margy Wilson, what is the matter?" 
</p><p>"George and I&mdash;had a talk last night.  We've broke the 
engagement, an' it's killing me.  An' now I've cut this velvet 
bias.  Oh, dear, dear, <hi rend="italic">dear</hi>, dear!" 
</p><p>"For the land's sake, don't mind anything about the velvet.  
What's come betwixt you an' George?" 
</p><p>"His mother&mdash;horrid old thing!  He said she'd got to live with 
us, and I said she shouldn't.  Then he said he wouldn't marry any 
girl that wasn't willing to live with his mother, and I said he 
wouldn't ever marry me, then.  If George Elliot thinks more of his 
mother than he does of me, he can have her.  I don't care.  I'll 
show him I can get along without him." 
</p><p>"Well, I don't know, Margy.  I'm real sorry about it.  George 
Elliot's a good, likely young man; but if you didn't want to live 
with his mother, it was better to say so right in the beginning.  
And I don't know as I blame you much: she's pretty set in her 
ways." 
</p><p>"I guess she is.  I never could bear her.  I guess he'll find 
out&mdash;" 
</p><p>Margy dried her eyes defiantly, and took up the velvet again.  
"I've spoilt this velvet.  I don't see why being disappointed in 
love should affect a girl so's to make her cut bias." 
</p><p>There was a whimsical element in Margy which seemed to roll 
uppermost along with her grief. 
</p><p>Esther looked a little puzzled.  "Never mind the velvet, 
child: it ain't much, anyway."  She began tossing over some ribbons 
to cover her departure from her usual reticence.  "I'm real sorry 
about it, Margy.  Such things are hard to bear, but they can be 
lived through.  I know something about it myself.  You knew I'd had 
some of this kind of trouble, didn't you?" 
</p><p>"About Mr. Woodman, you mean?" 
</p><p>"Yes, about Marcus Woodman.  I'll tell you what 'tis, Margy 
Wilson, you've got one thing to be thankful for, and that is that 
there ain't anything ridickerlous about this affair of yourn.  That 
makes it the hardest of anything, according to my mind&mdash;when you 
know that everybody's laughing, and you can hardly help laughing 
yourself, though you feel 'most ready to die." 
</p><p>"Ain't that Mr. Woodman crazy?" 
</p><p>"No, he ain't crazy; he's got too much will for his common-sense, that's all, and he will teeter the sense a little too far 
into the air.  I see all through it from the beginning.  I could 
read Marcus Woodman jest like a book." 
</p><p>"I don't see how in the world you ever come to like such a 
man." 
</p><p>"Well, I s'pose love's the strongest when there ain't any good 
reason for it.  They say it is.  I can't say as I ever really 
admired Marcus Woodman much.  I always see right through him; but 
that didn't hinder my thinking so much of him that I never felt as 
if I could marry any other man.  And I've had chances, though I 
shouldn't want you to say so." 
</p><p>"You turned him off because he went to sitting on the church 
steps?" 
</p><p>"Course I did.  Do you s'pose I was going to marry a man who 
made a laughing-stock of himself that way?" 
</p><p>"I don't see how he ever come to do it.  It's the funniest 
thing I ever heard of." 
</p><p>"I know it.  It seems so silly nobody 'd believe it.  Well, 
all there is about it, <pb n="473"/>  Marcus Woodman's got so much 
mulishness in him it makes him almost miraculous.  You see, he got 
up an' spoke in that church meeting when they had such a row about 
Mr. Morton's being settled here&mdash;Marcus was awful set again' him.  
I never could see any reason why, and I don't think he could.  He 
said Mr. Morton wa'n't doctrinal; that was what they all said; but 
I don't believe half of 'em knew what doctrinal was.  I never could 
see why Mr. Morton wa'n't as good as most ministers&mdash;enough sight 
better than them that treated him so, anyway.  I always felt that 
they was really setting him in a pulpit high over their heads by 
using him the way they did, though they didn't know it. 
</p><p>"Well, Marcus spoke in that church meeting, an' he kept 
getting more and more set every word he said.  He always had a way 
of saying things over and over, as if he was making steps out of 
'em, an' raising of himself up on 'em, till there was no moving him 
at all.  And he did that night.  Finally, when he was up real high, 
he said, as for him, if Mr. Morton was settled over that church, 
he'd never go inside the door himself as long as he lived.  
Somebody spoke out then&mdash;I never quite knew who 'twas, though I 
suspected&mdash;an' says, 'You'll have to set on the steps, then, 
Brother Woodman.' 
</p><p>"Everybody laughed at that but Marcus.  He didn't see nothing 
to laugh at.  He spoke out awful set, kinder gritting his teeth.  
'I will set on the steps fifty years before I'll go into this house 
if that man's settled here.' 
</p><p>"I couldn't believe he'd really do it.  We were going to be 
married that spring, an' it did seem as if he might listen to me; 
but he wouldn't.  The Sunday Mr. Morton begun to preach, he begun 
to set on them steps, an' he's set there ever since, in all kinds 
of weather.  It's a wonder it 'ain't killed him; but I guess it's 
made him tough." 
</p><p>"Why, didn't he feel bad when you wouldn't marry him?" 
</p><p>"Feel bad?  Of course he did.  He took on terribly.  But it 
didn't make any difference; he wouldn't give in a hair's breadth.  
I declare it did seem as if I should die.  His mother felt awfully 
too&mdash;she's a real good woman.  I don't know what Marcus would have 
done without her.  He wants a sight of tending and waiting on; he's 
dreadful babyish in some ways, though you wouldn't think it. 
</p><p>"Well, it's all over now, as far as I'm concerned.  I've got 
over it a good deal, though sometimes 't makes me jest as mad as 
ever to see him setting there.  But I try to be reconciled, and I 
get along jest as well, mebbe, as if I'd had him&mdash;I don't know.  I 
fretted more at first than there was any sense in, and I hope you 
won't." 
</p><p>"I ain't going to fret at all, Miss Barney.  I may cut bias 
for a while, but I sha'n't do anything worse." 
</p><p>"How you do talk, child!" 
</p><p>A good deal of it was talk with Margy; she had not as much 
courage as her words proclaimed.  She was capable of a strong 
temporary resolution, but of no enduring one.  She gradually 
weakened as the days without her lover went on, and one Saturday 
night she succumbed entirely.  There was quite a rush of business, 
but through it all she caught some conversation between some 
customers&mdash;two pretty young girls. 
</p><p>"Who was that with you last night at the concert?" 
</p><p>"That&mdash;oh, that was George Elliot.  Didn't you know him?" 
</p><p>"He's got another girl," thought Margy, with a great throb. 
</p><p>The next Sunday night, coming out of meeting with Miss Barney, 
she left her suddenly.  George Elliot was one of a waiting line of 
young men in the vestibule.  She went straight up to him.  He 
looked at her in bewilderment, his dark face turning red. 
</p><p>"Good evening, Miss Wilson," he stammered out, finally. 
</p><p>"Good evening," she whispered, and stood looking up at him 
piteously.  She was white and trembling. 
</p><p>At last he stepped forward and offered her his arm suddenly.  
In spite of his resentment, he could not put her to open shame 
before all his mates, who were staring curiously.  When they were 
out in the dark, cool street, he bent over her.  "Why, Margy, what 
does all this mean?" 
</p><p>"Oh, George, let her live with us, please.  I want her to.  I 
know I can get along with her if I try.  I'll do everything I can.  
Please let her live with us." 
</p><p>"Who's <hi rend="italic">her?"</hi> 
</p><p>"Your mother." 
</p><p>"And I suppose <hi rend="italic">us</hi> is you and I?  I thought that was all 
over, Margy; ain't it?" 
</p><p>"Oh, George, I am sorry I treated you so." <pb n="474"/>  
</p><p>"And you are willing to let mother live with us now?" 
</p><p>"I'll do anything.  Oh, George!" 
</p><p>"Don't cry, Margy.  There's nobody's looking&mdash;give us a kiss.  
It's been a long time; 'ain't it, dear?  So you've made up your 
mind that you're willing to let mother live with us?" 
</p><p>"Yes." 
</p><p>"Well, I don't believe she ever will, Margy.  She's about made 
up her mind to go and live with my brother Edward, whether or no.  
So you won't be troubled with her.  I dare say she might have been 
a little of a trial as she grew older." 
</p><p>"You didn't tell me." 
</p><p>"I thought it was your place to give in, dear." 
</p><p>"Yes, it was, it was, George." 
</p><p>"I'm mighty glad you did.  I tell you what it is, dear, I 
don't know how you've felt, but I've been pretty miserable lately." 
</p><p>"Poor George!" 
</p><p>They passed Esther Barney's house, and strolled along half a 
mile further.  When they returned, and Margy stole softly into the 
house and upstairs, it was quite late, and Esther had gone to bed.  
Margy saw the light was not out in her room, so she peeped in.  She 
could not wait till morning to tell her. 
</p><p>"Where have you been?" said Esther, looking up at her out of 
her pillows. 
</p><p>"Oh, I went to walk a little way with George." 
</p><p>"Then you've made up?" 
</p><p>"Yes." 
</p><p>"Is his mother going to live with you?" 
</p><p>"No; I guess not.  She's going to live with Edward.  But I 
told him I was willing she should.  I've about made up my mind it's 
a woman's place to give in mostly.  I s'pose you think I'm an awful 
fool." 
</p><p>"No, I don't; no, I don't, Margy.  I'm real glad it's all 
right betwixt you an' George.  I've seen you weren't very happy 
lately." 
</p><p>They talked a little longer; then Margy said "Good-night," 
going over to Esther and kissing her.  Being so rich in love made 
her generous with it.  She looked down into the older woman's thin, 
red-cheeked face sweetly.  "I wish you were as happy as I," said 
she.  "I wish you and Mr. Woodman could make up too." 
</p><p>"That's an entirely different matter.  I couldn't give in in 
such a thing as that." 
</p><p>Margy looked at her; she was not subtle, but she had just come 
out triumphant through innocent love and submission, and used the 
wisdom which she had gained thereby. 
</p><p>"Don't you believe," said she, "if you was to give in the way 
I did, that he would?" 
</p><p>Esther started up with an astonished air.  That had never 
occurred to her before.  "Oh, I don't believe he would.  You don't 
know him; he's awful set.  Besides, I don't know but I'm better off 
the way it is." 
</p><p>In spite of herself, however, she could not help thinking of 
Margy's suggestion.  Would he give in?  She was hardly disposed to 
run the risk.  With her peculiar cast of mind, her feeling for the 
ludicrous so keen that it almost amounted to a special sense, and 
her sensitiveness to ridicule, it would have been easier for her to 
have married a man under the shadow of a crime than one who was the 
deserving target of gibes and jests.  Besides, she told herself, it 
was possible that he had changed his mind, that he no longer cared 
for her.  How could she make the first overtures?  She had not 
Margy's impulsiveness and innocence of youth to excuse her. 
</p><p>Also, she was partly influenced by the reason which she had 
given Margy: she was not so very sure that it would be best for her 
to take any such step.  She was more fixed in the peace and pride 
of her old maidenhood than she had been in her young, and more shy 
of disturbing it.  Her comfortable meals, her tidy housekeeping, 
and her prosperous work had become such sources of satisfaction to 
her that she was almost wedded to them, and jealous of any 
interference. 
</p><p>So it is doubtful if there would have been any change in the 
state of affairs if Marcus Woodman's mother had not died toward 
spring.  Esther was greatly distressed about it. 
</p><p>"I don't see what Marcus is going to do," she told Margy.  "He 
ain't any fitter to take care of himself than a baby, and he won't 
have any housekeeper, they say." 
</p><p>One evening, after Marcus's mother had been dead about three 
weeks, Esther went over there.  Margy had gone out to walk with 
George, so nobody knew.  When she reached the house&mdash;a white 
cottage on a hill&mdash;she saw a light in the kitchen window. 
</p><p>"He's there," said she.  She knocked on the door softly.  
Marcus shuffled over <pb n="475"/>  to it&mdash;he was in his stocking feet&mdash; 
and opened it. 
</p><p>"Good evening, Marcus," said she, speaking first. 
</p><p>"Good evening." 
</p><p>"I hadn't anything special to do this evening, so I thought 
I'd look in a minute and see how you was getting along." 
</p><p>"I ain't getting along very well; but I'm glad to see you.  
Come right in." 
</p><p>When she was seated opposite him by the kitchen fire, she 
surveyed him and his surroundings pityingly.  Everything had an 
abject air of forlornness; there was neither tidiness nor comfort.  
After a few words she rose energetically.  "See here, Marcus," said 
she, "you jest fill up that tea-kettle, and I'm going to slick up 
here a little for you while I stay." 
</p><p>"Now, Esther, I don't feel as if&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Don't you say nothing.  Here's the tea-kettle.  I might jest 
as well be doing that as setting still." 
</p><p>He watched her, as she flew about putting things to rights, in 
a way that made her nervous; but she said to herself that this was 
easier than sitting still and gradually leading up to the object 
for which she had come.  She kept wondering if she ever could 
accomplish it.  When the room was in order, finally, she sat down 
again, with a strained-up look in her face. 
</p><p>"Marcus," said she, "I might as well begin.  There was 
something I wanted to say to you to-night." 
</p><p>He looked at her, and she went on: 
</p><p>"I've been thinking some lately about how matters used to be 
betwixt you an' me, and it's jest possible&mdash;I don't know&mdash;but I 
might have been a little more patient than I was.  I don't know as 
I'd feel the same way now if&mdash;" 
</p><p>"Oh, Esther, what do you mean?" 
</p><p>"I ain't going to tell you, Marcus Woodman, if you can't find 
out.  I've said full enough; more'n I ever thought I should." 
</p><p>He was an awkward man, but he rose and threw himself on his 
knees at her feet with all the grace of complete unconsciousness of 
action.  "Oh, Esther, you don't mean, do you?&mdash;you don't mean that 
you'd be willing to&mdash;marry me?" 
</p><p>"No; not if you don't get up.  You look ridickerlous." 
</p><p>"Esther, do you mean it?" 
</p><p>"Yes.  Now get up." 
</p><p>"You ain't thinking&mdash;I can't give up what we had the trouble 
about any more now than I could then." 
</p><p>"Ain't I said once that wouldn't make any difference?" 
</p><p>At that he put his head down on her knees and sobbed. 
</p><p>"Do, for mercy sake, stop.  Somebody'll be coming in.  'Tain't 
as if we was a young couple." 
</p><p>"I ain't going to till I've told you about it, Esther.  You 
ain't never really understood.  In the first of it, we was both 
mad; but we ain't now, and we can talk it over.  Oh, Esther, I've 
had such an awful life!  I've looked at you, and&mdash;  Oh, dear, dear, 
dear!" 
</p><p>"Marcus, you scare me to death crying so." 
</p><p>"I won't.  Esther, look here&mdash;it's the gospel truth: I 'ain't 
a thing again' Mr. Morton now." 
</p><p>"Then why on earth don't you go into the meeting-house and 
behave yourself?" 
</p><p>"Don't you suppose I would if I could?  I can't, Esther&mdash;I 
can't." 
</p><p>"I don't know what you mean by 'can't.'" 
</p><p>"Do you s'pose I've took any comfort sitting there on them 
steps in the winter snows an' the summer suns?  Do you s'pose I've 
took any comfort not marrying you?  Don't you s'pose I'd given all 
I was worth any time the last ten year to have got up an' walked 
into the church with the rest of the folks?" 
</p><p>"Well, I'll own, Marcus, I don't see why you couldn't if you 
wanted to." 
</p><p>"I 'ain't sure as I see myself, Esther.  All I know is I can't 
make myself give it up.  I can't.  I ain't made strong enough to." 
</p><p>"As near as I can make out, you've taken to sitting on the 
church steps the way other men take to smoking and drinking." 
</p><p>"I don't know but you're right, Esther, though I hadn't 
thought of it in that way before." 
</p><p>"Well, you must try to overcome it." 
</p><p>"I never can, Esther.  It ain't right for me to let you think 
I can." 
</p><p>"Well, we won't talk about it any more to-night.  It's time I 
was going home." 
</p><p>"Esther&mdash;did you mean it?" 
</p><p>"Mean what?" 
</p><p>"That you'd marry me anyway?" 
</p><p>"Yes, I did.  Now do get up.  I do hate to see you looking so 
silly." 
</p><p>Esther had a new pearl-colored silk gown, and a little mantle 
like it, and a bonnet trimmed with roses and plumes, <pb n="476"/>  and 
she and Marcus were married in June. 
</p><p>The Sunday on which she came out a bride they were late at 
church; but late as it was, curious people were lingering by the 
steps to watch them.  What would they do?  Would Marcus Woodman 
enter that church door which his awful will had guarded for him so 
long? 
</p><p>They walked slowly up the steps between the watching people.  
When they came to the place where he was accustomed to sit, Marcus 
stopped short and looked down at his wife with an agonized face. 
</p><p>"Oh, Esther, I've&mdash;got&mdash;to stop." 
</p><p>"Well, we'll both sit down here, then." 
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"You?"</hi> 
</p><p>"Yes; I'm willing." 
</p><p>"No; you go in." 
</p><p>"No, Marcus; I sit with you on our wedding Sunday. 
</p><p>Her sharp, middle-aged face as she looked up at him was fairly 
heroic.  This was all that she could do: her last weapon was used.  
If this failed, she would accept the chances with which she had 
married, and before the eyes of all these tittering people she 
would sit down at his side on these church steps.  She was 
determined, and she would not weaken. 
</p><p>He stood for a moment staring into her face.  He trembled so 
that the by-standers noticed it.  He actually leaned over toward 
his old seat as if wire ropes were pulling him down upon it.  Then 
he stood up straight, like a man, and walked through the church 
door with his wife. 
</p><p>The people followed.  Not one of them even smiled.  They had 
felt the pathos in the comedy. 
</p><p>The sitters in the pews watched Marcus wonderingly as he went 
up the aisle with Esther.  He looked strange to them; he had almost 
the grand mien of a conqueror. 
</p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
