<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WilOldA"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
<TEI.2 id="WilOldA"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">An Old Arithmetician</title>
<title type="sort">old arithmetician</title>
<author>Wilkins, Mary E.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">26</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WilOldA</idno> 
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476550</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>The print version was not illustrated.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">An Old Arithmetician</title>
<title type="sort">old arithmetician</title>
<author>Mary E. Wilkins</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp> 
<name/>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harper's Monthly</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1885">1885</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Harper's Monthly</hi> 71 (Sept. 1885): 611-615.</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Note:  On page 613, para. 25, line 1, Ms. Boss has changed "Lizzy to 
"Lizzie for consistency's sake.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1885">1885</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-12">December 1995</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Deirdre Johnson, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Header added, basic TEI markup added</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 

<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="611"/>  <head>                       AN OLD ARITHMETICIAN.</head> 
<p> 
A STRONG soft south wind had been blowing the day before, and the 
trees had dropped nearly all their leaves.  There were left only a 
few brownish-golden ones dangling on the elms, and hardly any at 
all on the maples.  There were many trees on the street, and the 
fallen leaves were heaped high.  Mrs. Wilson Torry's little door 
yard was ankle deep with them.  The air was full of their odor, 
which could affect the spirit like a song, and mingled with it was 
the scent of grapes. 
</p><p>The minister had been calling on Mrs. Torry that afternoon, 
and now he stood facing her on the porch, taking leave.  He was 
very young, and this was his first parish.  He was small and light 
and mild-looking; still he had considerable nervous volubility.  
The simple village women never found him hard to entertain. 
</p><p>Now, all at once, he made an exclamation, and fumbled in his 
pocket for a folded paper.  "There," said he, "I nearly forgot 
this.  Mr. Plainfield requested me to hand this to you, Mrs. Torry.  
It is a problem which he has been working over; he gave it to me to 
try, and wanted me to propose, when I called, that you should see 
what you could do with it." 
</p><p>She seized it eagerly.  "Well, I'll see what I can do; but you 
an' he mustn't make no great calculations on me.  You know I don't 
know anything about the 'rithmetic books an' the rules they hev 
nowadays; but I'm willin' to try." 
</p><p>"Oh, you'll have it done while Mr. Plainfield and I are 
thinking of it, Mrs. Torry." 
</p><p>"You 'ain't neither of you done it, then?" 
</p><p>"He had not at last accounts, and&mdash;I have not," replied the 
young man, laughing, but coloring a little. 
</p><p>The old lady's eyes gleamed as she looked at him, then at the 
paper.  "I dare say I can't make head nor tail of it," said she, 
"but I'll see what I can do by-an'-by." 
</p><p>She had something of a childish air as she stood there.  She 
was slender, and so short that she was almost dwarfed; her 
shoulders were curved a little by spinal disease.  She had a small 
round face, and a mouth which widened out innocently into smiles as 
she talked.  Her eyes looked out directly at one, like a child's; 
over them loomed a high forehead with bulging temples covered with 
deep wrinkles. 
</p><p>"You have always been very fond of mathematics, haven't you, 
Mrs. Torry?" said the minister, in his slow retreat. 
</p><p>"Lor', yes.  I can't remember the time when I wa'n't crazy to 
cipher." 
</p><p>"Arithmetic is a very fascinating study, I think," remarked 
the minister, trying to slide easily off the subject and down the 
porch steps. 
</p><p>"'Tis to me.  An' there's somethin' I was thinkin' about this 
very forenoon&mdash;seein' all them leaves on the ground made me, I 
s'pose.  It's always been a sight of comfort to me to count.  When 
I was a little girl I'd 'most rather count than play.  I used to 
sit down an' count by the hour together.  I remember a little 
pewter porringer I had, that I used to fill up with beans an' count 
'em.  Well, it come into my head this forenoon what a blessed 
privilege it would be to count up all the beautiful things in this 
creation.  Just think of countin' all them red an' gold-colored 
leaves, an' all the grapes an' apples in the fall; an' when it come 
to the winter, all the flakes of snow, an' the sparkles of frost; 
an' when it come to the spring, all the flowers, and blades of 
grass, an' the little new light green leaves.  I don' know but 
you'll think it ain't exactly reverent, but it does seem to me that 
I'd rather do that than sing in the other world.  Mebbe somebody 
does have to do the countin'; mebbe it's singin' for some." 
</p><p>She stared up into the warm blue air, in which the bare 
branches of the trees glistened, with a sweet, solemn wonder in her 
old face. 
</p><p>The minister in a bewildered way pondered all the old woman 
had said, as he rustled down the street.  Later, Mr. Plainfield 
(the young high-school teacher) and he would have discussion over 
it.  They often talked over Mrs. Wilson Torry. 
</p><p>After her caller had gone, the old woman entered the house.  
On the left of the little entry was the best room, where she had 
been entertaining the minister; on the right, the kitchen.  A young 
girl was in there eating an apple.  She looked up when Mrs. Torry 
stood in the door. 
</p><p>"He's gone, ain't he?" said she. 
</p><p>"Why, Letty, when did you come?" 
</p><p>"A few minutes ago.  School's just out.  I came in the back 
door, and heard him talking, so I kept still." 
</p><p>"Why didn't you come in an' see him?" <pb n="612"/>  
</p><p>"Oh, I didn't want to see him.  What you got there, grandma?" 
</p><p>"Nothin' but a sum the minister brought me to do.  He an' Mr. 
Plainfield have been workin' over it." 
</p><p>"Couldn't they do it?" 
</p><p>"Well, he said they hadn't neither of 'em done it yet." 
</p><p>"Is it awful hard?" 
</p><p>"I don' know.  I 'ain't looked at it yet." 
</p><p>"Let me see.  He didn't get it out of any of our books, I 
know.  We never had anything like this." 
</p><p>"I s'pose it's one he come across somewhere.  I guess I'll sit 
down and look at it two or three minutes." 
</p><p>An old bureau stood against the wall; on it were arranged four 
religious newspapers in the exact order of their issues, the latest 
on top, Farmers' Almanacs for the last four years filed in the same 
way, and a slate surmounted by an old arithmetic.  The pile of 
newspapers was in the middle; the slate and almanacs were on either 
end. 
</p><p>Letty, soberly eating her apple, watched her grandmother 
getting out the arithmetic and slate.  She was a pretty young girl; 
her small innocent face, in spite of its youthful roundness and 
fairness, reminded people of Mrs. Torry's. 
</p><p>"I don't think much of Mr. Plainfield, anyhow," said she, as 
the click of her grandmother's pencil on the slate began; "and he 
knows I don't.  He overheard me telling Lizzie Bascom so to-day.  
He came right up behind us on the street, and I know he heard.  You 
ought to have seen his face!" 
</p><p>"I don't see what you've got agin him," remarked Mrs. Torry, 
absently, as she dotted down figures. 
</p><p>"I haven't much of anything that I know of against him, only 
I don't think he's much of a teacher.  He can't to examples as 
quickly as you, I know, and I don't think a man has any business to 
be school-teaching if he can't do examples as quickly as an old 
lady." 
</p><p>Mrs. Torry stopped her work, and fixed her round unwinking 
eyes full on the girl's face. 
</p><p>"Letty Torry, there's some things you don't understand.  You 
never will understand 'em, if you live to be as old as Methuseleh, 
as far as that's concerned.  But you'll get so you know the things 
<hi rend="italic">air</hi>.  Sometimes it don't make any difference if anybody's 
ignorant, an' 'ain't got any book-learnin'; air old, an' had a 
hard-workin' life.  There'll be somethin' in 'em that everybody 
else 'ain't got; somethin' that growed, an' didn't have to be 
learned.  I've got this faculty; I can cipher.  It ain't nothin' 
agin Mr. Plainfield if he 'ain't got it; it's a <hi rend="italic">gift</hi>." 
</p><p>Her voice took on a solemn tone and trembled.  Letty looked at 
her with childish wonder.  "Well," said she, with a subdued manner, 
"he has no right to teach, anyhow, without it.  I guess I'll have 
another apple.  I was real hungry." 
</p><p>So Letty ate another apple silently while her grandmother 
worked at the problem again. 
</p><p>She did not solve it as easily as usual.  She worked till 
midnight, her little lamp drawn close to her on the kitchen table; 
then she went to bed, with the answer still in doubt. 
</p><p>"It ain't goin' to do for me to set up any longer," said she, 
forlornly, as she replaced the slate on the bureau.  "I shall be 
sick if I do.  But I declare I don't see what's got into me.  I 
hope I ain't losin' my faculty." 
</p><p>She could not sleep much.  The next morning, as soon as their 
simple breakfast was eaten and Letty had gone to school, she seated 
herself with her slate and pencil. 
</p><p>When Letty came home at noon she found her grandmother still 
at work, and no dinner ready. 
</p><p>"I do declare!" cried the old woman.  "You don't mean to say 
you're home, Letty!  It <hi rend="italic">ain't</hi> twelve o'clock, is it?" 
</p><p>"Course it is; quarter past." 
</p><p>"I 'ain't got one mite of dinner ready, then.  I've been so 
took up with the sum I hadn't no idea how the time was goin'.  I 
don' know what you will do, child." 
</p><p>"Oh, I'll get some bread and milk, grandma; just as soon have 
it as anything else.  Got the problem done?" 
</p><p>"No, I 'ain't.  I feel real bad about your dinner.  I'll 
kindle up a fire now an' fry you an egg&mdash;there be time enough." 
</p><p>"I'd rather have bread and milk." 
</p><p>After Letty had gone to school for the afternoon, and Mrs. 
Torry had been working fruitlessly for an hour longer, she dropped 
her pencil. 
</p><p>"I declare," said she, "I'm afraid I am losin' my faculty!" 
</p><p>Tears stood in her eyes.  "I won't give up that I am, anyhow," 
said she, and took the pencil again. <pb n="613"/>  
</p><p>When Letty returned in the latter part of the afternoon, she 
scarcely knew it, with the full meaning of the word.  She saw her, 
but her true consciousness was so full of figures that Letty's fair 
face could only look in at the door. 
</p><p>Letty ran in hastily; a young girl was waiting for her 
outside.  "Oh, grandma," cried Letty, "Lizzie's going to Ellsworth 
to do an errand for her mother; she's coming back on the last 
train.  Can't I go with her?" 
</p><p>Her grandmother stared at her for a minute and made no answer. 
</p><p>"She's got tickets for both of us.  Can't I go, grandma?" 
</p><p>"Yes." 
</p><p>Letty smoothed her hair a little, and put on her best hat; 
then she went. 
</p><p>"Good-by," said she, looking back at the intend old figure; 
but she got no answer. 
</p><p>"Grandma's so taken up with an example she's got that she 
doesn't know anything," she told her friend when she was outside.  
"She didn't answer when I said good-by; she forgot to get dinner 
to-day too." 
</p><p>Mrs. Torry worked on and on.  She never looked up nor thought 
of anything else until it grew so dark that she could not see her 
figures.  "I'll have to light the lamp," said she, with a sigh. 
</p><p>After it was lit she went to work again.  She never thought of 
wanting any supper, though she had eaten nothing since morning. 
</p><p>The kitchen clock struck seven&mdash;Letty should have been home 
then&mdash;eight, and nine, but she never noticed it.  A few minutes 
afterward some one knocked on the door.  She ciphered on.  Then the 
knocks were repeated, louder and quicker. 
</p><p>"Somebody's knockin', I guess," she muttered, and opened the 
door.  Mr. Plainfield stood there.  He was a handsome young man 
with rosy cheeks; he was always smiling.  He looked past her into 
the room inquiringly.  "Is Letty at home?" said he. 
</p><p>"Letty?" 
</p><p>"Yes, Letty.  Is she at home?" 
</p><p>"Why, yes, she's here.  Letty!" 
</p><p>"Has she gone to bed?" 
</p><p>"Why, yes, I guess she has."  Mrs. Torry opened the door at 
the foot of the stairs.  "Letty!  Letty!" 
</p><p>"I guess she must be asleep," said she, turning to the young 
man, who had stepped into the kitchen.  "Want me to go up an' see?  
Did you want anything pertickler?" 
</p><p>He hesitated.  "If you had&mdash;just as soon&mdash;I&mdash;had something 
special&mdash;" 
</p><p>The old woman climbed the steep, uncarpeted stairs, feebly, 
with a long pat on every step.  She came down faster, reckless of 
her trembling uncertainty.  "She ain't there!  Letty's gone!  Where 
is she?" 
</p><p>"You knew she went to Ellsworth with Lizzie?" 
</p><p>"No, I didn't." 
</p><p>"Why, she said something to you about it, didn't she?" 
</p><p>"I don't know whether she did or not." 
</p><p>"Lizzie just told me that she missed her in the depot.  She 
left her there for a minute while she went back for something she 
had forgotten.  When she came back she was gone.  The train was all 
ready, and Lizzie thought she must be on it, so she got on herself.  
She did not see her in the depot here, and has been crying about 
it, and afraid to tell till just now.  I came right over as soon as 
I knew about it." 
</p><p>"Oh, Letty!  Letty!  Where's Letty?  Oh, Mr. Plainfield, you 
go an' find her!  Go right off!  You will, won't you?  Letty allers 
liked you." 
</p><p>"I always liked Letty," said the young man, brokenly.  "I'll 
find her&mdash;don't you worry." 
</p><p>"You'll go right off now?" 
</p><p>"Of course I will; I won't wait a minute." 
</p><p>"Oh, Letty, Letty!  Where is she?  What shall I do?  That 
little bit of a thing&mdash;and she was always one of the frightened 
kind&mdash;out all alone; an' it's night!  She never went to Ellsworth 
alone in her hull life.  She didn't know nothin' about the town, 
an' she didn't have a cent of money in her pocket." 
</p><p>"I'll send Mrs. Bascom over to stay with you," Mr. Plainfield 
called back as he hurried off. 
</p><p>Soon Mrs. Bascom came, poking her white, nervous face in the 
door inquiringly.  "She 'ain't come?" 
</p><p>"No.  Oh, Mis' Bascom, what shall I do?" 
</p><p>"Oh, Mis' Torry, I do feel so bad about it I don't know what 
to do.  If Lizzie had only told before! but there she was upstairs 
crying, and afraid to tell.  I've been scolding her, but she felt 
so bad I had to stop.  She called me, an' told me finally; an' I 
guess 'twa'n't long before Mr. Plainfield started off, to find out 
if she <hi rend="italic">was</hi> <pb n="614"/>  home.  It was lucky he was boarding with 
us.  He'll find her if anybody can; he's as quick as lightning.  He 
turned white's a sheet when I told him." 
</p><p>"Oh, Mis' Bascom!" 
</p><p>"Now, don't give up so, Mis' Torry.  He'll find her.  She 
can't be very far off.  You'll see her walking in here first thing 
you know.  He's got a real fast team, an' he's started for 
Ellsworth now.  He went past me like a streak when I was coming up 
the road.  He'll have her back safe and sound before morning." 
</p><p>"Oh, Letty!  Letty!  Oh, what shall I do?  It's my own fault, 
every mite of it's my own fault.  'Tis; you don't know nothin' 
about it.  The minister brought me a sum, he an' Mr. Plainfield had 
been workin' on, to do, yesterday afternoon, an' I jest sat an' 
ciphered half the night, an' all day.  I didn't know no more what 
Letty asked me, when she came in from school, than nothin' at all.  
I didn't more'n half know when she come.  I didn't know nothin' but 
them figgers, an' now Letty's lost, an' it's my fault." 
</p><p>"Why, you might have let her gone if you'd known." 
</p><p>"I guess I shouldn't let her gone, all alone with your Lizzie, 
to come home after dark in the last train, little delicate thing as 
she was.  I guess I shouldn't; an' I guess I should have started up 
an' done something, if I'd known, when she wasn't here at train 
time.  I didn't get the sum done, an' I'm glad of it; it seems to 
me jest as if I was losin' my faculty as I'm growin' older, an' I 
hope I am." 
</p><p>"Now don't talk so, Mis' Torry.  Sit down an' try to be calm.  
You'll be sick." 
</p><p>"I guess there ain't much bein' calm.  I tell you what 'tis, 
Mis' Bascom.  I've been a wicked woman.  I've been thinkin' so much 
of this faculty I've had for cipherin' that I've set it afore 
everything&mdash;I hev.  Only yesterday that poor child didn't hev any 
dinner but crackers an' milk, 'cause I was so took up with the sum 
that I forgot it.  An' she was jest as patient as a lamb about it; 
said she'd rather hev crackers an' milk than anything else.  Oh, 
dear! dear!" 
</p><p>"Don't cry, Mis' Torry." 
</p><p>"I can't help it.  It don't make no difference what folks are 
born with a faculty for&mdash;whether it's cipherin', or singin', or 
writin' poetry&mdash;the love that's betwixt human beings an' the help 
that's betwixt 'em ought to come first.  I've known it all the 
time, but I've gone agin it, an' now I've got my pay.  What shall 
I do?" 
</p><p>Mrs. Bascom remained with her all night, but she could not 
pacify her in the least.  She was nearly distracted herself.  She 
was fearful that her Lizzie might be blamed. 
</p><p>The next day people flocked to the house to inquire if there 
was any news from Letty, and to comfort her grandmother.  Sympathy 
seemed fairly dripping like fragrant oil from these simple, honest 
hearts; but the poor old woman got no refreshing influence from it.  
She kept on her old strain in their ears.  She had lost Letty, and 
it was all her own fault, and what should she do?  Mr. Plainfield 
did not come home.  The minister took his place in school.  Nothing 
was heard until noon; then a telegram from the teacher came.  He 
thought he was on Letty's track, he said; they should hear again. 
</p><p>Next day there was a second message: Letty was safe; coming 
home as soon as possible.  The following day passed then, and not 
another word came.  The old grandmother's faith and hope seemed to 
have deserted her.  She knew Letty was not found; she never would 
be found.  She and Mr. Plainfield were both lost now.  Something 
dreadful had happened to both of them. 
</p><p>"The worst of it is," she told Mrs. Bascom one afternoon, with 
a fierce indignation at herself, "I can't help thinkin' about that 
awful sum now after all that's happened.  Them figgers keep 
troopin' into my head right in the midst of my thinkin' about 
Letty.  It's all I can do to let that slate alone, an' not take it 
off the bureau.  But I won't&mdash;I won't if it kills me not to.  An' 
all the time I jest despise myself for it; a-lettin' my faculty for 
cipherin' get ahead of things that's higher an' sacreder.  I do 
think I've lost my faculty now, an' I 'most hope I hev.  But it 
won't make no difference 'bout Letty now.  Oh dear! dear!  What 
shall I do?" 
</p><p>On the fourth day after Letty's disappearance, between six and 
seven o'clock in the evening, Mrs. Torry was sitting alone in her 
kitchen.  The last sympathizer had gone home to eat her supper. 
</p><p>The distressed old woman had drank* a cup of tea; that was all 
she would touch.  The pot was still on the stove.  There was a soft 
yellow light from the lamp over the room.  The warm air was full of 
the fragrance of boiling tea. <pb n="615"/>  
</p><p>Mrs. Torry sat looking over at the bureau.  She would have 
looked the same way if she had been starving and seen food there. 
</p><p>"Oh," she whispered, "if&mdash;I could&mdash;only work on that sum a 
little while, it does seem as if 'twould comfort me more'n 
anything.  Oh Lord!  I wonder if I was to blame?  'Twas the way I 
was made, an' I couldn't help that.  P'rhaps I should hev let Letty 
gone, an' she'd been lost, anyway.  I wonder if I hev lost my 
faculty?" 
</p><p>She sat there looking over at the slate.  At last she rose and 
started to cross the room.  Midway she stopped. 
</p><p>"Oh, what am I doin'?  Letty's lost, an' I'm goin' to 
cipherin'!  S'pose she should come in an' ketch me?  She'd be so 
hurt she'd never get over it.  She wouldn't think I cared anything 
about her." 
</p><p>She stood looking at the slate and thinking for a moment.  
Then her face settled into a hard calm. 
</p><p>"Letty won't come back&mdash;she won't never come back.  I might as 
well cipher as anything else." 
</p><p>She went across the room, got the slate and pencil, and 
returned to her seat.  She had been ciphering for a minute or so 
when a sound outside caused her to start and stop.  She sat with 
mouth open and chin trembling, listening.  The sound came nearer; 
it was at the door.  Of all the sweet sounds which had smote that 
old woman's ears since her birth&mdash;songs of birds, choral hymns, 
Sabbath bells&mdash;there had been none so sweet as this.  It was 
Letty's thin girlish treble which she heard just outside the door. 
</p><p>For a second, as she sat listening, her face was rapt, 
angelic; in spite of its sallowness and wrinkles it might have 
figured in an altarpiece.  Then it changed.  The slate was in her 
lap.  What would Letty think? 
</p><p>It was all passing swiftly; the door-latch rattled; she 
slipped the slate under her gingham apron, and sat still. 
</p><p>"Oh, poor grandma!" cried Letty, running in; "you've been 
frightened 'most to death about me, haven't you?"  She bent over 
her grandmother and laid her soft pretty cheek against hers. 
</p><p>"Oh, Letty!  I didn't think you'd ever come back." 
</p><p>"I have; but I did have the dreadfulest time.  I got carried 
'way out West on an express train.  Just think of it!  I got on the 
wrong train while I was waiting for Lizzie.  I was frightened 
almost to death.  But Mr. Plainfield telegraphed ahead.  He found 
out where I was going, and they took me to a hotel; and then he 
came for me.  You haven't said anything to Mr. Plainfield, 
grandma." 
</p><p>The young man was standing smiling behind Letty.  She looked 
astonished when her grandmother did not rise to speak to him, but 
sat perfectly still as she uttered some broken thanks. 
</p><p>"Why, grandma, you ain't sick, are you?" said she. 
</p><p>"No&mdash;I ain't sick," said her grandmother, with a meek tone. 
</p><p>When Mr. Plainfield left, in a few moments, Letty gave a half-defiant, half-ashamed glance at her grandmother, and followed him 
out, closing the door. 
</p><p>When she returned, Mrs. Torry was standing by the table 
pouring out a cup of tea for her.  The slate was in its usual place 
on the bureau. 
</p><p>"Grandma," said Letty, blushing innocently, "I thought I ought 
to say something to Mr. Plainfield, you know.  I hadn't, and I knew 
he heard what I said to Lizzie that day.  I thought I ought to ask 
his pardon, when he'd done so much for me.  I've made up my mind 
that I do like him.  There's other things besides doing arithmetic 
examples." 
</p><p>"I guess there is, child.  Them things is all second.  I think 
I'd rather have a man who hadn't got any special faculty, if I was 
goin' to git married." 
</p><p>"Nobody said anything about getting married, grandma." 
</p><p>Pretty soon Letty went to bed.  She was worn out with her 
adventures. 
</p><p>"Ain't you going too, grandma?" asked she, turning around, 
lamp in hand, at the foot of the stairs. 
</p><p>"Pretty soon, child; pretty soon.  I've&mdash;got a little 
somethin' I want to do first." 
</p><p>The grandmother sat up till nearly morning working over the 
problem.  Once in a while she would lay down her slate and climb 
upstairs and peep into Letty's little peaceful girl-chamber to see 
if she was safe. 
</p><p>"If I have got that dear child, and 'ain't lost my faculty, 
it's more'n I deserve," muttered she, as she took her slate the 
last time. 
</p><p>The next evening the minister came over.  "So Letty's come," 
he said, when Mrs. Torry opened the door. 
</p><p>"Yes, Letty's come, and&mdash;I've got that sum, you gave me, 
done."</p></div1></body></text></TEI.2> 
 
 
 
 
 
