<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WilPris"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
<TEI.2 id="WilPris"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Prism</title>
<title type="sort">prism</title>
<author>Wilkins, Mary E.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">27</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WilPris</idno> 
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476552</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Prism</title>
<title type="sort">prism</title>
<author>Mary E. Wilkins</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Century Magazine</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1901">1901</date>
</publicationStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of  
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1901">1901</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-10">October 1994</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Monique Dull</name>
</respStmt>
<item>conversion to basic TEI-conformant markup</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 

<text id="d1">  
 
<body id="d2"> 

<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head>Wilkins, Mary E.  "The Prism."<lb/>
<hi rend="italic"> Century Magazine</hi> 62 (1901):  469-474. 
</head> 
<pb n="469"/>  
<p>There had been much rain that season, and the vegetation was 
almost tropical.  The wayside growths were jungles to birds and 
insects, and very near them to humans.  All through the long 
afternoon of the hot August day, Diantha Fielding lay flat on her 
back under the lee of the stone wall which bordered her 
stepfather's, Zenas May's, south mowing-lot.  It was pretty warm 
there, although she lay in a little strip of shade of the tangle 
of blackberry-vines, poison-ivy, and the gray pile of stones; but 
the girl loved the heat.  She experienced the gentle languor 
which is its best effect, instead of the fierce unrest and 
irritation which is its worst.  She left that to rattlesnakes and 
nervous women.  As for her, in  
 
<pb n="470"/>  
times of extreme heat, she 
hung over life with tremulous flutters, like a butterfly over a 
rose, moving only enough to preserve her poise in the scheme of 
things, and realizing to the full the sweetness of all about her. 
</p><p>She heard, as she lay there, the voice of a pine-tree not 
far away&mdash;a solitary pine which was full of gusty sweetness; she 
smelled the wild grapes, which were reluctantly ripening across 
the field over the wall that edged the lane; she smelled the 
blackberry-vines; she looked with indolent fascination at the 
virile sprays of poison-ivy.  It was like innocence surveying 
sin, and wondering what it was like.  Once her stepmother, Mrs. 
Zenas May, had been poisoned with ivy, and both eyes had been 
closed thereby.  Diantha did not believe that the ivy would so 
serve her.  She dared herself to touch it, then she looked away 
again. 
</p><p>She heard a far-carrying voice from the farm-house at the 
left calling her name.  "Diantha!  Diantha!"  She lay so still 
that she scarcely breathed.  The voice came again.  She smiled 
triumphantly.  She knew perfectly well what was wanted: that she 
should assist in preparing supper.  Her stepmother's married 
daughter and her two children were visiting at the house.  She 
preferred remaining where she was.  Her sole fear of disturbance 
was from the children.  They were like little ferrets.  Diantha 
did not like them.  She did not like children very well under any 
circumstances.  To her they seemed always out of tune; the jar of 
heredity was in them, and she felt it, although she did not know 
enough to realize what she felt.  She was only twelve years old, 
a child still, though tall for her age. 
</p><p>The voice came again.  Diantha shifted her position a 
little; she stretched her slender length luxuriously; she felt 
for something which hung suspended around her neck under her 
gingham waist, but she did not then remove it.  "Diantha!  
Diantha!" came the insistent voice. 
</p><p>Diantha lay as irresponsive as the blackberry-vine which 
trailed beside her like a snake.  Then she heard the house door 
close with a bang; her ears were acute.  She felt again of that 
which was suspended from her neck.  A curious expression of 
daring, of exultation, of fear, was in her face.  Presently she 
heard the shrill voices of children; then she lay so still that 
she seemed fairly to obliterate herself by silence and 
motionlessness. 
</p><p>Two little girls in pink frocks came racing past; their 
flying heels almost touched her, but they never saw her. 
</p><p>When they were well past, she drew a cautious breath, and 
felt again of the treasure around her neck. 
</p><p>After a while she heard the soft padding of many hoofs in 
the heavy dust of the road, a dog's shrill bark, the tinkle of a 
bell, the absent-minded shout of a weary man.  The hired man was 
driving the cows home.  The fragrance of milk-dripping udders, of 
breaths sweetened with clover and meadow-grass, came to her.  
Suddenly a cold nose rubbed against her face; the dog had found 
her out.  But she was a friend of his.  She patted him, then 
pushed him away gently, and he understood that she wished to 
remain concealed.  He went barking back to the man.  The cows 
broke into a clumsy gallop; the man shouted.  Diantha smelled the 
dust of the road which flew over the field like smoke.  She heard 
the children returning down the road behind the cows.  When the 
cows galloped, they screamed with half-fearful delight.  Then it 
all passed by, and she heard the loud clang of a bell from the 
farm-house. 
</p><p>Then Diantha pulled out the treasure which was suspended 
from her neck by an old blue ribbon, and she held it up to the 
low western sun, and wonderful lights of red and blue and violet 
and green and orange danced over the shaven stubble of the field 
before her delighted eyes.  It was a prism which she had stolen 
from the best-parlor lamp&mdash;from the lamp which had been her own 
mother's, bought by her with her school-teaching money before her 
marriage, and brought by her to grace her new home. 
</p><p>Diantha Fielding, as far as relatives went, was in a curious 
position.  First her mother died when she was very young, only a 
few months old; then her father had married again, giving her a 
stepmother; then her father had died two years later, and her 
stepmother had married again, giving her a stepfather.  Since 
then the stepmother had died, and the stepfather had married a 
widow with a married daughter, whose two children had raced down 
the road behind the cows.  Diantha often felt in a sore 
bewilderment of relationships.  She had not even a cousin of her 
own; the dearest relative she had was the daughter of a widow 
whom a cousin of her mother's had married for a second wife.  The 
cousin was long since dead.  The wife was living, and Diantha's 
little step second cousin, as she reckoned it, lived in the old 
homestead which had belonged to Diantha's grandfather, across the 
way from the May farm-house.  It was a gambrel-roof, half-ruinous 
structure, well  
 
<pb n="471"/>  
banked in front with a monstrous growth 
of lilacs, and overhung by a great butternut-tree. 
</p><p>Diantha knew well that she was heaping up vials of cold 
wrath upon her head by not obeying the supper-bell, but she lay 
still.  Then Libby came&mdash;Libby, the little cousin, stepping very 
cautiously and daintily; for she wore slippers of her mother's, 
which hung from her small heels, and she had lost them twice 
already. 
</p><p>She stopped before Diantha.  Her slender arms, terminating 
in hands too large for them, hung straight at her sides in the 
folds of her faded blue-flowered muslin.  Her pretty little heat-flushed face had in it no more speculation than a flower, and no 
more changing.  She was like a flower, which would blossom the 
same next year, and the next year after that, and the same until 
it died.  There was no speculation in her face as she looked at 
Diantha dangling the prism in the sunlight, merely unimaginative 
wonder and admiration. 
</p><p>"It's a drop off your best-parlor lamp," said she, in her 
thin, sweet voice. 
</p><p>"Look over the field, Libby!" cried Diantha, excitedly. 
</p><p>Libby looked. 
</p><p>"Tell me what you see, quick!" 
</p><p>"What I see?  Why, grass and things." 
</p><p>"No, I don't mean them; what you see from this." 
</p><p>Diantha shook the prism violently. 
</p><p>"I see a lot of different colors dancing," replied Libby, 
"same as you always see.  Addie Green had an ear-drop that was 
broken off their best-parlor lamp.  Her mother gave it to her." 
</p><p>"Don't you see anything but different lights?" 
</p><p>"Of course I don't.  That's all there is to see." 
</p><p>Diantha sighed. 
</p><p>"That drop ain't broken," said the other little girl.  "How 
did she happen to let you have it?"  By "she" Libby meant 
Diantha's stepmother. 
</p><p>"I took it," replied Diantha.  She was fastening the prism 
around her neck again. 
</p><p>Libby gasped and stared at her.  "Didn't you ask her?" 
</p><p>"If I'd asked her, she'd said no, and it was my own mother's 
lamp.  I had a right to it." 
</p><p>"What'll she do to you?" 
</p><p>"I don't know, if she finds out.  I sha'n't tell her, if I 
can help it without lying." 
</p><p>Diantha fastened her gingham frock securely over the prism.  
Then she rose, and the two little girls went home across the dry 
stubble of the field. 
</p><p>"I didn't go when she called me, and I didn't go when the 
supper-bell rang," said Diantha. 
</p><p>Libby stared at her wonderingly.  She had never felt an 
impulse to disobedience in her life; she could not understand 
this other child, who was a law unto herself.  She walked very 
carefully in her large slippers. 
</p><p>"What'll she do to you?" she inquired. 
</p><p>Diantha tossed her head like a colt. 
</p><p>"She won't do anything, I guess, except make me go without 
my supper.  If she does, I ain't afraid; but I guess she won't, 
and I'd a heap rather go without my supper than go to it when I 
don't want to." 
</p><p>Libby looked at her with admiring wonder.  Diantha was 
neatly and rigorously, rather than tastefully, dressed.  Her dark 
blue-and-white gingham frock was starched stiffly; it hung 
exactly at the proper height from her slender ankles; she wore a 
clean white collar; and her yellow hair was braided very tightly 
and smoothly, and tied with a punctilious blue bow.  In strange 
contrast with the almost martial preciseness of her attire was 
the expression of her little face, flushed, eager to enthusiasm, 
almost wild, with a light in her blue eyes which did not belong 
there, according to the traditions concerning little New England 
maidens, with a feverish rose on her cheeks, which should have 
been cool and pale.  However, that had all come since she had 
dangled the prism in the rays of the setting sun. 
</p><p>"What did you think you saw when you shook that ear-drop off 
the lamp?" asked Libby; but she asked without much curiosity. 
</p><p>"Red and green and yellow colors, of course," replied 
Diantha, shortly. 
</p><p>When they reached Diantha's door, Libby bade her good night, 
and sped across the road to her own house.  She stood a little in 
fear of Diantha's stepmother, if Diantha did not.  She knew just 
the sort of look which would be directed toward the other little 
girl, and she knew from experience that it might include her.  
>From her Puritan ancestry she had a certain stubbornness when 
brought to bay, but no courage of aggression; so she ran. 
</p><p>Diantha marched in.  She was utterly devoid of fear. 
</p><p>Her stepmother, Mrs. Zenas May, was washing the supper 
dishes at the kitchen sink.  All through the house sounded a high 
sweet voice which was constantly off the 
 
<pb n="472"/>  
key, singing a lullaby to the two little girls, who had to go to bed directly 
after they had finished their evening meal. 
</p><p>Mrs. Zenas May turned around and surveyed Diantha as she 
entered.  There was nothing in the least unkind in her look; it 
was simply the gaze of one on a firm standpoint of existence upon 
another swaying on a precarious balance&mdash;the sort of look a woman 
seated in a car gives to one standing.  It was irresponsible, 
while cognizant of the discomfort of the other person. 
</p><p>"Where were you when the supper-bell rang?" asked Mrs. Zenas 
May.  She was rather a pretty woman, with an exquisitely cut 
profile.  Her voice was very even, almost as devoid of 
inflections as a deaf-and-dumb person's.  Her gingham gown was 
also rigorously starched.  Her fair hair showed high lights of 
gloss from careful brushing; it was strained back from her blue-veined temples. 
</p><p>"Out in the field," replied Diantha. 
</p><p>"Then you heard it?" 
</p><p>"Yes, ma'am." 
</p><p>"The supper-table is cleared away," said Mrs. May.  That was 
all she said.  She went on polishing the tumblers, which she was 
rinsing in ammonia water. 
</p><p>Diantha glanced through the open door and saw the dining-room table with its chenille after-supper cloth on.  She made no 
reply, but went up-stairs to her own chamber.  That was very 
comfortable&mdash;the large south one back of her step-parents'.  Not 
a speck of dust was to be seen in it; the feather-bed was an even 
mound of snow.  Diantha sat down by the window, and gazed out at 
the deepening dusk.  She felt at the prism around her neck, but 
she did not draw it out, for it was of no use in that low light.  
She could not invoke the colors which it held.  Her chamber door 
was open.  Presently she heard the best-parlor door open, and 
heard quite distinctly her stepmother's voice.  She was speaking 
to her stepfather. 
</p><p>"There's a drop broken off the parlor lamp," said she. 
</p><p>There was an unintelligible masculine grunt of response. 
</p><p>"I wish you'd look while I hold the lamp, and see if you can 
find it on the floor anywhere," said her stepmother.  Her voice 
was still even.  The loss of a prism from the best-parlor lamp 
was not enough to ruffle her outward composure. 
</p><p>"Don't you see it?" she asked, after a little. 
</p><p>Again came the unintelligible masculine grunt. 
</p><p>"It is very strange," said Mrs. May.  "Don't look any more." 
</p><p>She never inquired of Diantha concerning the prism.  In 
truth, she believed one of her grandchildren, whom she adored, to 
be responsible for the loss of the glittering ornament, and was 
mindful of the fact that Diantha's mother had originally owned 
that lamp.  So she said nothing, but as soon as might be 
purchased another, and Diantha kept her treasure quite 
unsuspected. 
</p><p>She did not, however, tremble in the least while the search 
was going on down-stairs.  She had her defense quite ready.  To 
her sense of justice it was unquestionable.  She would simply say 
that the lamp had belonged to her own mother, consequently to 
her; that she had a right to do as she chose with it.  She had 
not the slightest fear of any reproaches which Mrs. May would 
bring to bear upon her.  She knew she would not use bodily 
punishment, as she never had; but she would have stood in no fear 
of that. 
</p><p>Diantha did not go to bed for a long time.  There was a full 
moon, and she sat by the window, leaning her two elbows on the 
sill, making a cup of her hands, in which she rested her peaked 
chin, and peered out. 
</p><p>It was nearly nine o'clock when some one entered the room 
with heavy, soft movements, like a great tame dog.  It was her 
stepfather, and he had in his hand a large wedge of apple-pie. 
</p><p>"Diantha," he said, in a loud whisper, "you gone to bed?" 
</p><p>"No, sir," replied Diantha.  She liked her stepfather.  She 
was always aware of a clumsy, covert partizanship from him. 
</p><p>"Well," said he, "here's a piece of pie.  You hadn't ought 
to go to bed without any supper.  You'd ought to come in when the 
bell rings another time, Diantha." 
</p><p>"Thank you, father," said Diantha, reaching out her hand for 
the pie. 
</p><p>Zenas May, who was large and shaggily blond, with a face 
like a great blank of good nature, placed a heavy hand on her 
little, tightly braided head, and patted it. 
</p><p>"Better eat your pie and go to bed," he said.  Then he 
shambled down-stairs very softly, lest his wife hear him. 
</p><p>Diantha ate her pie obediently, and went to bed, and with 
the first morning sunlight she removed her prism from her neck, 
and flashed it across the room, and saw what she saw, or what she 
thought she saw. 
</p><p>Diantha kept the prism, and nobody except Libby knew it, and 
she was quite safe with a secret.  While she did not in the  
 
<pb n="473"/>   
least comprehend, she was stanch.  Even when she grew older 
and had a lover, she did not tell him; she did not even tell him 
when she was married to him that Diantha Fielding always carried 
a drop off the best-parlor lamp, which belonged to her own 
mother, and when she flashed it in the sunlight she thought she 
saw things.  She kept it all to herself.  Libby married before 
Diantha, before Diantha had a lover even.  Young men, for some 
reason, were rather shy of diantha, although she had a little 
property in her own right, inherited from her own father and 
mother, and was, moreover, extremely pretty.  However, her 
prettiness was not of a type to attract the village men as 
quickly as Libby's more material charms.  Diantha was very thin 
and small, and her color was as clear as porcelain, and she gave 
a curious impression of mystery, although there was apparently 
nothing whatever mysterious about her. 
</p><p>But her turn came.  A graduate of a country college, a 
farmer's son, who had worked his own way through college, had now 
obtained the high school.  He saw Diantha, and fell in love with 
her, although he struggled against it.  He said to himself that 
she was too delicate, that he was a poor man, that he ought to 
have a more robust wife, who would stand a better chance of 
discharging her domestic and maternal duties without a breakdown.  
Reason and judgment were strongly developed in him.  His passion 
for Diantha was entirely opposed to both, but it got the better 
of him.  One afternoon in August when Diantha was almost twenty, 
he, passing by her house, saw her sitting on her front doorstep, 
stopped, and proposed a little stroll in the woods, and asked her 
to marry him. 
</p><p>"I never thought much about getting married," said Diantha.  
Then she leaned toward him as if impelled by some newly developed 
instinct.  She spoke so low that he could not hear her, and he 
asked her over. 
</p><p>"I never thought much about getting married," repeated 
Diantha, and she leaned nearer him. 
</p><p>He laughed a great triumphant laugh, and caught her in his 
arms. 
</p><p>"Then it is high time you did, you darling," he said. 
</p><p>Diantha was very happy. 
</p><p>They lingered in the woods a long time, and when they went 
home, the young man, whose name was Robert Black, went in with 
her, and told her stepmother what had happened. 
</p><p>"I have asked your daughter to marry me, Mrs. May," he said, 
"and she has consented, and I hope you are willing." 
</p><p>Mrs. May replied that she had no objections, stiffly, 
without a smile.  She never smiled.  Instead of smiling, she 
always looked questioningly even at her beloved grandchildren.  
They had lived with her since their mother's death, two pretty, 
boisterous girls, pupils of Robert Black, who had had their own 
inevitable little dreams regarding him, as they had had regarding 
every man who came in their way. 
</p><p>When their grandmother told them that Diantha was to marry 
the hero who had dwelt in their own innocently bold air-castles 
of girlish dreams, they started at first as from a shock of 
falling imaginations; then they began to think of their attire as 
bridesmaids. 
</p><p>Mrs. Zenas May was firmly resolved that Diantha should have 
as grand a wedding as if she had been her own daughter. 
</p><p>"Folks sha'n't say that she didn't have as good an outfit 
and wedding as if her own mother had been alive to see to it," 
she said. 
</p><p>As for Diantha, she thought very little about her outfit or 
the wedding, but about Robert.  All at once she was possessed by 
a strong angel of primal conditions of whose existence she had 
never dreamed.  She poured out her very soul; she made 
revelations of the inmost innocences of her nature to this 
ambitious, faithful, unimaginative young man.  She had been some 
two weeks betrothed, and they were walking together one 
afternoon, when she showed him her prism. 
</p><p>She no longer wore it about her neck as formerly.  A dawning 
unbelief in it had seized her, and yet there were times when to 
doubt seemed to doubt the evidence of her own senses. 
</p><p>That afternoon, as they were walking together in the lonely 
country road, she stopped him in a sunny interval between the 
bordering woods, where the road stretched for some distance 
between fields foaming with wild carrot and mustard, and swarmed 
over with butterflies, and she took her prism out of her pocket 
and flashed it full before her wondering lover's eyes. 
</p><p>He looked astonished, even annoyed; then he laughed aloud 
with a sort of tender scorn. 
</p><p>"What a child you are, dear!" he said.  "What are you doing 
with that thing?" 
</p><p>"What do you see, Robert?" the girl  
 
<pb n="474"/>  
cried eagerly, and there was in her eyes a light not of her day and generation, 
maybe inherited from some far-off Celtic ancestor&mdash;a strain of 
imagination which had survived the glaring light of latter days 
of commonness. 
</p><p>He eyed her with amazement; then he looked at the gorgeous 
blots and banners of color over the fields. 
</p><p>"See?  Why, I see the prismatic colors, of course.  What 
else should I see?" he asked. 
</p><p>"Nothing else?" 
</p><p>"No.  Why, what else should I see?  I see the prismatic 
colors from the refraction of the sunlight." 
</p><p>Diantha looked at the dancing tints, then at her lover, and 
spoke with a solemn candor, as if she were making confession of 
an alien faith.  "Ever since I was a child, I have seen, or 
thought so&mdash;" she began. 
</p><p>"What, for heaven's sake?" he cried impatiently. 
</p><p>"You have read about&mdash;fairies and&mdash;such things? 
</p><p>"Of course.  What do you mean, Diantha?" 
</p><p>"I have seen, or thought so, beautiful little people moving 
and dancing in the broken lights across the fields." 
</p><p>"For heaven's sake, put up that thing, and don't talk such 
nonsense, Diantha!" cried Robert, almost brutally.  He had paled 
a little. 
</p><p>"I have, Robert." 
</p><p>"Don't talk such nonsense.  I thought you were a sensible 
girl," said the young man. 
</p><p>Diantha put the prism back in her pocket. 
</p><p>All the rest of the way Robert was silent and gloomy.  His 
old doubts had revived.  His judgment for the time being got the 
upper hand of his passion.  He began to wonder if he ought to 
marry a girl with such preposterous fancies as those.  He began 
to wonder if she were just right in her mind. 
</p><p>He parted from her coolly, and came the next evening, but 
remained only a short time.  Then he stayed away several days.  
He called on Sunday, then did not come again for four days.  On 
Friday Diantha grew desperate.  She went by herself out in the 
sunny field, walking ankle-deep in flowers and weeds, until she 
reached the margin of a little pond on which the children skated 
in winter.  Then she took her prism from her pocket and flashed 
it in the sunlight, and for the first time she failed to see what 
she had either seen, or imagined, for so many years. 
</p><p>She saw only the beautiful prismatic colors flashing across 
the field in bars and blots and streamers of rose and violet, of 
orange and green.  That was all.  She stooped, and dug in the 
oozy soil beside the pond with her bare white hands, and made, as 
it were, a little grave, and buried the prism out of sight.  Then 
she washed her hands in the pond, and waved them about until they 
were dry.  Afterward she went swiftly across the field to the 
road which her lover must pass on his way from school, and, when 
she saw him coming, met him, blushing and trembling. 
</p><p>"I have put it away, Robert," she said.  "I saw nothing; it 
was only my imagination." 
</p><p>It was a lonely road.  He looked at her doubtfully, then he 
laughed, and put an arm around her. 
</p><p>"It's all right, little girl," he replied; "but don't let 
such fancies dwell in your brain.  This is a plain, common world, 
and it won't do." 
</p><p>"I saw nothing; it must have been my imagination," she 
repeated.  Then she leaned her head against her lover's shoulder.  
Whether or not she had sold her birthright, she had got her full 
measure of the pottage of love which filled to an ecstasy of 
satisfaction her woman's heart. 
</p><p>She and Robert were married, and lived in a pretty new 
house, from the western windows of which she could see the pond 
on whose borders she had buried the prism.  She was very happy.  
For the time being, at least, all the mysticism in her face had 
given place to an utter revelation of earthly bliss.  People said 
how much Diantha had improved since her marriage, what a fine 
housekeeper she was, how much common sense she had, how she was 
such a fitting mate for her husband, whom she adored. 
</p><p>Sometimes Diantha, looking from a western window, used to 
see the pond across the field, reflecting the light of the 
setting sun, and looking like an eye of revelation of the earth; 
and she would remember that key of a lost radiance and a lost 
belief of her own life, which was buried beside it.  Then she 
would go happily and prepare her husband's supper. 
</p> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
