<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WooCapt"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
<TEI.2 id="WooCapt"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Capture of a Slaver</title>
<title type="sort">capture of a slaver</title>
<author>Wood, J. Taylor</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">50</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WooCapt</idno> 
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476560</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Capture of a Slaver</title>
<title type="sort">capture of a slaver</title>
<author>J. Taylor Wood</author>
</titleStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 86</p>
</seriesStmt> 
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 451-463</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of  
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction; prose</term> 
<term>African American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-08">August 1994</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Minimal TEI tagging</item>
</change> 
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Margaret Konkol</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML and fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2"> 

<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
<head>Wood, J. Taylor.  "The Capture of a Slaver." 
<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 86 (1900): 451-463.
</head>
 <pb n="451"/> 
<p>FROM 1830 to 1850 both Great Britain and the United States, by 
joint convention, kept on the coast of Africa at least eighty guns 
afloat for the suppression of the slave trade.  Most of the vessels 
so employed were small corvettes, brigs, or schooners; steam at 
that time was just being introduced into the navies of the world. 
</p><p>Nearly fifty years ago I was midshipman on the United States 
brig Porpoise, of ten guns.  Some of my readers may remember these 
little ten-gun coffins, as many of them proved to be to their 
crews.  The Porpoise was a fair sample of the type; a full-rigged 
brig of one hundred and thirty tons, heavily sparred, deep waisted, 
and carrying a battery of eight twenty-four-pound carronades and 
two long chasers; so wet that even in a moderate breeze or sea it 
was necessary to batten down; and so tender that she required 
careful watching; only five feet between decks, her quarters were 
necessarily cramped and uncomfortable, and, as far as possible, we 
lived on deck.  With a crew of eighty all told, Lieutenant Thompson 
was in command, Lieutenant Bukett executive officer, and two 
midshipmen were the line officers.  She was so slow that we could 
hardly hope for a prize except by a fluke.  Repeatedly we had 
chased suspicious craft only to be out-sailed. 
</p><p>At this time the traffic in slaves was very brisk; the demand 
in the Brazils, in Cuba, and in other Spanish West Indies was 
urgent, and the profit of the business so great that two or three 
successful ventures would enrich any one.  The slavers were 
generally small, handy craft; fast, of course; usually schooner-rigged, and carrying flying topsails and forecourse.  Many were 
built in England or elsewhere purposely for the business, without, 
of course, the knowledge of the builders, ostensibly as yachts or 
traders.  The Spaniards and Portuguese were the principal 
offenders, with occasionally an English-speaking renegade. 
</p><p>The slave depots, or barracoons, were generally located some 
miles up a river.  Here the slaver was secure from capture and 
could embark his live cargo at his leisure.  Keeping a sharp 
lookout on the coast, the dealers were able to follow the movements 
of the cruisers, and by means of smoke, or in other ways, signal 
when the coast was clear for the coming down the river and sailing 
of the loaded craft.  Before taking in the cargoes they were always 
fortified with all the necessary papers and documents to show they 
were engaged in legitimate commerce, so it was only when caught in 
<hi rend="italic">flagrante delicto</hi> that we could hold them. 
</p><p>We had been cruising off the coast of Liberia doing nothing, 
when we were ordered to the Gulf of Guinea to watch the Bonny and 
Cameroons mouths of the great Niger River.  Our consort was H.M. 
schooner Bright, a beautiful craft about our tonnage, but with half 
our crew, and able to sail three miles to our two.  She was an old 
slaver, captured and adapted as a cruiser.  She had been very 
successful, making several important captures of full cargoes, and 
twice or thrice her commanding officer and others had been 
promoted.  Working our way slowly down the coast in company with 
the Bright, we would occasionally send a boat on shore to 
reconnoitre or gather any information we could from the natives 
through our Krooman interpreter.  A few glasses of rum or a string 
of beads would loosen the tongue of almost any one.  At Little 
Bonny we heard that two vessels were some miles up the river, ready 
to sail, 
<pb n="452"/>  
and were only waiting until the coast was clear.  
Captain James, of the Bright, thought that one, if not both, would 
sail from another outlet of the river, about thirty miles to the 
southward, and determined to watch it. 
</p><p>We both stood to that direction.  Of course we were watched 
from the shore, and the slavers were kept posted as to our 
movements.  They supposed we had both gone to the Cameroons, 
leaving Little Bonny open; but after dark, with a light land 
breeze, we wore round and stood to the northward, keeping offshore 
some distance, so that captains leaving the river might have 
sufficient offing to prevent their reaching port again or beaching 
their craft.  At daybreak, as far as we could judge, we were about 
twenty miles offshore to the northward and westward of Little 
Bonny, in the track of any vessel bound for the West Indies.  The 
night was dark with occasional rain squalls, when the heavens would 
open and the water come down in a flood.  Anxiously we all watched 
for daylight, which comes under the equator with a suddenness very 
different from the prolonged twilight of higher latitudes.  At the 
first glimmer in the east every eye was strained on the horizon, 
all eager, all anxious to be the first to sight anything within our 
vision.  The darkness soon gave way to gray morn.  Day was dawning, 
when suddenly a Krooman by my side seized my hand and, without 
saying a word, pointed inshore.  I looked, but could see nothing.  
All eyes were focused in that direction, and in a few minutes the 
faint outline of a vessel appeared against the sky.  She was some 
miles inshore of us, and as the day brightened we made her out to 
be a brigantine (an uncommon rig in those days), standing across 
our bows, with all studding sails set on the starboard side, indeed 
everything that could pull, including water sails and save-all.  We 
were on the same tack heading to the northward.  We set everything 
that would draw, and kept off two points, bringing the wind abeam 
so as to head her off. 
</p><p>The breeze was light and off the land.  We had not yet been 
seen against the darker western horizon, but we knew it could only 
be a few minutes longer before their sharp eyes would make us out.  
Soon we saw the studding sails and all kites come down by the run 
and her yards braced up sharp on the same tack as ours.  We also 
hauled by the wind.  At sunrise she was four points on our weather 
bow, distant about four miles.  We soon perceived that she could 
outsail our brig and if the wind held would escape.  Gradually she 
drew away from us until she was hull down.  Our only hope now was 
that the land breeze would cease and the sea breeze come in.  As 
the sun rose we gladly noticed the wind lessening, until at eleven 
o'clock it was calm.  Not a breath ruffled the surface of the sea; 
the sun's rays in the zenith were reflected as from a mirror; the 
waters seemed like molten lead. 
</p><p>I know of nothing more depressing than a calm in the tropics, 
&mdash; a raging sun overhead, around an endless expanse of dead sea, and 
a feeling of utter helplessness that is overpowering.  What if this 
should last? what a fate!  The Rime of the Ancient Mariner comes to 
our mind.  Come storm and tempest, come hurricanes and blizzards, 
anything but an endless stagnation.  For some hours we watched 
earnestly the horizon to the westward, looking for the first dark 
break on the smooth sea.  Not a cloud was in the heavens.  The brig 
appeared to be leaving us either by towing or by sweeps; only her 
topgallant sail was above the horizon.  It looked as if the sea 
breeze would desert us.  It usually came in about one o'clock, but 
that hour and another had passed and yet we watched for the first 
change.  Without a breeze our chances of overhauling the stranger 
were gone.  Only a white speck like the wing of a gull 
<pb n="453"/>  
now 
marked her whereabouts on the edge of the horizon, and in another 
hour she would be invisible even from the masthead. 
</p><p>When we were about to despair, our head Krooman drew the 
captain's attention to the westward and said the breeze was coming.  
We saw no signs of it, but his quick eye had noticed light feathery 
clouds rising to the westward, a sure indication of the coming 
breeze.  Soon we could see the glassy surface ruffled at different 
points as the breeze danced over it, coming on like an advancing 
line of skirmishers; and as we felt its first gentle movement on 
our parched faces, it was welcome indeed, putting new life into all 
of us.  The crew needed no encouragement to spring to their work.  
As the little brig felt the breeze and gathered steerageway, she 
was headed for the chase, bringing the wind on her starboard 
quarter.  In less than five minutes all the studding sails that 
would draw were set, as well as everything that would pull.  The 
best quartermaster was sent to the wheel, with orders to keep the 
chase directly over the weather end of the spritsail yard.  The 
captain ordered the sails wet, an expedient I never had much faith 
in, unless the sails are very old.  But as if to recompense us for 
the delay, the breeze came in strong and steady.  Our one hope now 
was to follow it up close, and to carry it within gunshot of the 
brig, for if she caught it before we were within range she would 
certainly escape.  All hands were piped to quarters, and the long 
eighteen-pounder on the forecastle was loaded with a full service 
charge; on this piece we relied to cripple the chase.  We were now 
rapidly raising her, and I was sent aloft on the fore topsail yard, 
with a good glass to watch her movements.  Her hull was in sight 
and she was still becalmed, though her head was pointed in the 
right direction, and everything was set to catch the coming breeze.  
She carried a boat on each side at the davits like a man-of-war, 
and I reported that I could make out men securing them.  They had 
been towing her, and only stopped when they saw us drawing near. 
</p><p>Anxiously we watched the breeze on the water as it narrowed 
the sheen between us, and we were yet two miles or more distant 
when she first felt the breeze.  As she did so we hoisted the 
English blue ensign, &mdash; for the fleet at this time was under a Rear 
Admiral of the Blue, &mdash; and fired a weather gun, but no response was 
made.  Fortunately the wind continued to freshen and the Porpoise 
was doing wonderfully well.  We were rapidly closing the distance 
between us.  We fired another gun, but no attention was paid to it.  
I noticed from the movements of the crew of the brig that they were 
getting ready for some manoeuvre, and reported to the captain.  He 
divined at once what the manoeuvre would be, and ordered the braces 
be led along, hands by the studding-sail halyards and tacks, and 
everything ready to haul by the wind.  We felt certain now of the 
character of our friend, and the men were already calculating the 
amount of their prize money.  We were now within range, and must 
clip her wings if possible. 
</p><p>The first lieutenant was ordered to open fire with the 
eighteen-pounder.  Carefully the gun was laid, and as the order 
"fire" was given, down came our English flag, and the stop of the 
Stars and Stripes was broken at the gaff.  The first shot touched 
the water abeam of the chase and ricochetted ahead of her.  She 
showed the Spanish flag.  The captain of the gun was ordered to 
elevate a little more and try again.  The second shot let daylight 
through her fore topsail, but the third was wide again. 
</p><p>Then the sharp, quick order of the captain, "Fore topsail yard 
there, come down on deck, sir!" brought me down on the run.  "Have 
both cutters cleared away and ready for lowering," were my 
<pb n="454"/>  
orders as I reached the quarter-deck.  Practice from the bow 
chasers continued, but the smoke that drifted ahead of us 
interfered with the accuracy of the firing, and no vital part was 
touched, though a number of shots went through her sails.  The 
captain in the main rigging never took his eye from the Spaniard, 
evidently expecting that as a fox when hard pressed doubles on the 
hounds, the chase would attempt the same thing.  And he was not 
disappointed, for when we had come within easy range of her, the 
smoke hid her from view for a few minutes, and as it dispersed the 
first glimpse showed the captain that her studding sails had all 
gone, and that she had hauled by the wind, standing across our 
weather bow.  Her captain had lost no time in taking in his 
studding sails; halyards, tacks, and sheets had all been cut 
together and dropped overboard. 
</p><p>It was a bold and well-executed manoeuvre, and we could not 
help admiring the skill with which she was handled.  However, we 
had been prepared for this move.  "Ease down your helm."  "Lower 
away.  Haul down the studding sails."  "Ease away the weather 
braces.  Brace up."  "Trim down the head sheets," were the orders 
which followed in rapid succession, and were as quickly executed.  
The Spaniard was now broad on our lee bow, distant not more than 
half a mile, but as she felt the wind which we brought down she 
fairly spun through the water, exposing her bright copper.  She was 
both head-reaching and outsailing us; in half an hour she would 
have been right ahead of us, and in an hour the sun would be down.  
It was now or never.  We could bring nothing to bear except the gun 
on the forecastle.  Fortunately it continued smooth, and we were no 
longer troubled with smoke.  Shot after shot went hissing through 
the air after her; a number tore through the sails or rigging, but 
not a spar was touched nor an important rope cut.  We could see 
some of her crew aloft reeving and stopping braces and ready to 
repair any damage done, working as coolly under fire as old man-of-war's men.  But while we were looking, down came the gaff of her 
mainsail, and the gaff-topsail fell all adrift; a lucky shot had 
cut her peak halyards.  Our crew cheered with a will.  "Well done, 
Hobson; try it again!" called the captain to the boatswain's mate, 
who was captain of the gun. 
</p><p>After the next shot, the topgallant yard swayed for a few 
minutes and fell forward.  The order was given to cease firing; she 
was at our mercy.  We were rapidly nearing the chase, when she 
backed her topsail.  We kept off, and when within easy range of the 
carronades "hove to" to windward.  Lieutenant Bukett was ordered to 
board her in the first cutter and take charge.  I followed in the 
second cutter, with orders to bring the captain on board with his 
papers.  A few strokes sent us alongside of a brig about our 
tonnage, but with a low rail and a flush deck.  The crew, some 
eighteen or twenty fine-looking seamen, were forward eagerly 
discussing the situation of affairs.  The captain was aft with his 
two officers, talking to Lieutenant Bukett.  He was fair, with 
light hair curling all over his head, beard cut short, about forty 
years of age, well set up, with a frame like a Roman wrestler, 
evidently a tough customer in a rough-and-ready scrimmage. 
</p><p>He spoke fairly good English, and was violently denouncing the 
outrage done to his flag; his government would demand instant 
satisfaction for firing upon a legitimate trader on the high seas.  
I have the lieutenant Captain Thompson's orders, to bring the 
captain and his papers on board at once.  His harangue was cut 
short by orders to get on board my boat.  He swore with a terrible 
oath that he would never leave his vessel.  "Come on board, men," 
said I, and twenty of our crew were on deck in a jiffy.  I 
stationed my coxswain, Parker, 
<pb n="455"/>  
at the cabin companion way 
with orders to allow no one to pass.  "Now," said Lieutenant Bukett 
to the Spaniard, "I will take you on board in irons unless you go 
quietly."  He hesitated a moment, then said he would come as soon 
as he had gone below to bring up his papers.  "No, never mind your 
papers; I will find them," said the lieutenant, for he saw the 
devil in the Spaniard's eyes, and knew he meant mischief.  Our 
captive made one bound for the companion way, however, and seizing 
Parker by the throat hurled him into the water ways as if he had 
been a rag baby.  But fortunately he slipped on a small grating and 
fell on his knees, and before he could recover himself two of our 
men threw themselves upon him. 
</p><p>I closed the companion way.  The struggle was desperate for a 
few minutes, for the Spaniard seemed possessed of the furies, and 
his efforts were almost superhuman.  Twice he threw the men from 
him across the deck, but they were reinforced by Parker, who, 
smarting under his discomfiture, rushed in, determined to down him.  
I was anxious to end it with my pistol, but Lieutenant Bukett would 
not consent.  The Spaniard's officers and men made some 
demonstration to assist, but they were quickly disposed of: his two 
mates were put in irons and the crew driven forward.  Struggling, 
fighting, every limb and every muscle at work, the captain was 
overpowered; a piece of the signal halyards brought his hands 
together, and handcuffs were slipped on his wrists.  Only then he 
succumbed, and begged Lieutenant Bukett to blow out his brains, for 
he had been treated like a pirate. 
</p><p>Without doubt if he had reached the cabin he would have blown 
up the vessel, for in a locker over the transom were two open kegs 
of powder.  I led him to my boat, assisted him in, and returned to 
the Porpoise.  As soon as the Spaniard reached the deck the captain 
ordered his irons removed, and expressed his regret that it had 
been necessary to use force.  The prisoner only bowed and said 
nothing.  The captain asked him what his cargo consisted of.  He 
replied, "About four hundred blacks bound to the Brazils." 
</p><p>I was then ordered to return to the brig, bring on board her 
crew, leaving only the cook and steward, and to take charge of the 
prize as Lieutenant Bukett, our first lieutenant, was not yet 
wholly recovered from an attack of African fever.  The crew of 
twenty men, when brought on board, consisted of Spaniards, Greeks, 
Malays, Arabs, white and black, but had not one Anglo-Saxon.  They 
were ironed in pairs and put under guard. 
</p><p>From the time we first got on board we had heard moans, cries, 
and rumblings coming from below, and as soon as the captain and 
crew were removed, the hatches had been taken off, when there arose 
a hot blast as from a charnel house, sickening and overpowering.  
In the hold were three or four hundred human beings, gasping, 
struggling for breath, dying; their bodies, limbs, faces, all 
expressing terrible suffering.  In their agonizing fight for life, 
some had torn or wounded themselves or their neighbors dreadfully; 
some were stiffened in the most unnatural positions.  As soon as I 
knew the condition of things I sent the boat back for the doctor 
and some whiskey.  It returned bringing Captain Thompson, and for 
an hour or more we were all hard at work lifting and helping the 
poor creatures on deck, where they were laid out in rows.  A little 
water and stimulant revived most of them; some, however, were dead 
or too far gone to be resuscitated.  The doctor worked earnestly 
over each one, but seventeen were beyond human skill.  As fast as 
he pronounced them dead they were quickly dropped overboard. 
</p><p>Night closed in with our decks covered so thickly with the 
ebony bodies that with difficulty we could move about; 
<pb n="456"/>  
fortunately they were as quiet as so many snakes.  In the meantime 
the first officer, Mr. Block, was sending up a new topgallant yard, 
reeving new rigging, repairing the sails, and getting everything 
ataunto aloft.  The Kroomen were busy washing out and fumigating 
the hold, getting ready for our cargo again.  It would have been a 
very anxious night, except that I felt relieved by the presence of 
the brig which kept within hail.  Soon after daybreak Captain 
Thompson came on board again, and we made a count of the captives 
as they were sent below; 188 men and boys, and 166 women and girls.  
Seeing everything snug and in order the captain returned to the 
brig, giving me final orders to proceed with all possible dispatch 
to Monrovia, Liberia, land the negroes, then sail for Porto Praya, 
Cape de Verde Islands, and report to the commodore.  As the brig 
hauled to the wind and stood to the southward and eastward I dipped 
my colors, when her crew jumped into the rigging and gave us three 
cheers, which we returned. 
</p><p>As she drew away from us I began to realize my position and 
responsibility: a young midshipman, yet in my teens, commanding a 
prize, with three hundred and fifty prisoners on board, two or 
three weeks' sail from port, with only a small crew.  From the 
first I kept all hands aft except two men on the lookout, and the 
weather was so warm that we could all sleep on deck.  I also 
ordered the men never to lay aside their pistols or cutlasses, 
except when working aloft, but my chief reliance was in my 
knowledge of the negro, &mdash; of his patient, docile disposition.  Born 
and bred a slave he never thought of any other condition, and he 
accepted the situation without a murmur.  I had never heard of 
blacks rising or attempting to gain their freedom on board a 
slaver. 
</p><p>My charges were all of a deep black; from fifteen to twenty-five years of age, and, with a few exceptions, nude, unless copper 
or brass rings on their ankles or necklaces of cowries can be 
described as articles of dress.  All were slashed, or had the scars 
of branding on their foreheads and cheeks; these marks were the 
distinguishing features of different tribes or families.  The men's 
hair had been cut short, and their heads looked in some cases as if 
they had been shaven.  The women, on the contrary, wore their hair 
"a la pompadour;" the coarse kinky locks were sometimes a foot or 
more above their heads, and trained square or round like a boxwood 
bush.  Their features were of the pronounced African type, but, 
notwithstanding this disfigurement, were not unpleasing in 
appearance.  The figures of all were very good, straight, well 
developed, some of the young men having bodies that would have 
graced a Mercury or an Apollo.  Their hands were small, showing no 
evidences of work, only the cruel marks of shackles.  These in some 
cases had worn deep furrows on their wrists or ankles. 
</p><p>They were obedient to all orders as far as they understood 
them, and would, I believe, have jumped overboard if told to do so.  
I forbade the men to treat them harshly or cruelly.  I had the sick 
separated from the others, and allowed them to remain on deck all 
the time, and in this way I partly gained their confidence.  I was 
anxious to learn their story.  Fortunately one of the Kroomen found 
among the prisoners a native of a tribe living near the coast, and 
with him as interpreter was able to make himself understood.  After 
a good deal of questioning I learned that most of them were from a 
long distance in the interior, some having been one and some two 
moons on the way, traveling partly by land and partly by river 
until they reached the coast.  They had been sold by their kings or 
by their parents to the Arab trader for firearms or for rum.  Once 
at the depots near the coast, they were sold by the Arabs or other 
traders to the slave captains for from twenty-<pb n="457"/>  
five to fifty 
dollars a head.  In the Brazils or West Indies they were worth from 
two to five hundred dollars.  This wide margin, of course, 
attracted unscrupulous and greedy adventurers, who if they 
succeeded in running a few cargoes would enrich themselves. 
</p><p>Our daily routine was simple.  At six in the morning the rope 
netting over the main hatch which admitted light and air was taken 
off, and twenty-five of each sex were brought up, and seated in two 
circles, one on each side of the deck.  A large pan of boiled paddy 
was then placed in the centre by the cook and all went to work with 
their hands.  A few minutes sufficed to dispose of every grain; 
then one of the Kroomen gave each of them a cup of water from a 
bucket.  For half an hour after the meal they had the liberty of 
the deck, except the poop, for exercise, to wash and to sun 
themselves; for sunshine to a negro is meat and drink.  At the end 
of this time they were sent below and another fifty brought up, and 
so on until all had been fed and watered.  Paddy or rice was the 
staple article of food.  At dinner boiled yams were given with the 
rice.  Our passengers were quartered on a flying deck extending 
from the foremast to a point twenty feet abaft the main hatch from 
which came light and air.  The height was about five feet; the men 
had one side and the women the other.  Of course there was no 
furnishing of any kind, but all lay prone upon the bare deck in 
rows. 
</p><p>Every morning after breakfast the Kroomen would rig the force 
pump, screw on the hose and drench them all, washing out thoroughly 
between decks.  They appeared to enjoy this, and it was cooling, 
for be it remembered we were close under the equator, the 
thermometer dancing about 90 deg.  As the water was sluiced over 
them they would rub and scrub each other.  Only the girls would try 
not to get their hair wet, for they were at all times particular 
about their headdress.  It may be that this was the only part of 
their toilet that gave them any concern. 
</p><p>The winds were baffling and light, so we made but slow 
progress.  Fortunately frequent rains, with sometimes a genuine 
tropical downpour or cloud-burst, gave us an opportunity of 
replenishing our water casks, and by spreading the awnings we were 
able to get a good supply.  I found on inspection that there were 
at least thirty days' provisions on board, so on this score and 
that of water I felt easy.  I lived on deck, seldom using the 
cabin, which was a veritable arsenal, with racks of muskets and 
cutlasses on two sides, many more than the captain needed to arm 
his crew, evidently intended for barter.  Two or three prints of 
his favorite saints, ornamented with sharks' teeth, hung on one 
bulkhead.  A well-thrummed mandolin and a number of French novels 
proved him to be a musical and literary fellow, who could probably 
play a bolero while making a troublesome slave walk a plank.  I 
found also some choice vintages from the Douro and Bordeaux snugly 
stowed in his spirit locker, which proved good medicines for some 
of our captives, who required stimulants.  Several of the girls 
were much reduced, refused nearly all food, and were only kept 
alive by a little wine and water.  Two finally died of mere 
inanition.  Their death did not in the least affect their fellows, 
who appeared perfectly indifferent and callous to all their 
surroundings, showing not the least sympathy or desire to help or 
wait on one another. 
</p><p>The fifth day after parting from the brig we encountered a 
tropical storm.  The sun rose red and angry, and owing to the great 
refraction appeared three times its natural size.  It climbed 
lazily to the zenith, and at noon we were shadowless.  The sky was 
as calm as a vault, and the surface of the water was like burnished 
steel.  The heat became so stifling that even the Africans were 
<pb n="458"/>  
gasping for breath, and we envied them their freedom from all 
impediments.  The least exertion was irksome, and attended with 
extreme lassitude.  During the afternoon thin cirri clouds, flying 
very high, spread out over the western heavens like a fan.  As the 
day lengthened they thickened to resemble the scales of a fish, 
bringing to mind the old saying, "A mackerel sky and a mare's 
tail," etc.  The signs were all unmistakable, and even the gulls 
recognized a change, and, screaming, sought shelter on our spars.  
Mr. Block was ordered to send down all the light yards and sails; 
to take in and furl everything, using storm gaskets, except on the 
fore and main storm staysails; to lash everything on deck; to 
batten down the hatches, except one square of the main; see all the 
shifting boards in place, so that our living cargo would not be 
thrown to leeward higgledy-piggledy, and to take four or five of 
the worst cases of the sick into the cabin and lay them on the 
floor. 
</p><p>The sun disappeared behind a mountainous mass of leaden-colored clouds which rose rapidly in the southern and western 
quarters.  To the eastward, also, the signs were threatening.  
Night came on suddenly as it does in the tropics.  Soon the 
darkness enveloped us, a palpable veil.  A noise like the march of 
a mighty host was heard, which proved to be the approach of a 
tropical flood, heralded by drops as large as marbles.  It churned 
the still waters into a phosphorescent foam which rendered the 
darkness only more oppressive.  The rain came down as it can come 
only in the Bight of Benin.  The avalanche cooled us, reducing the 
temperature ten or fifteen degrees, giving us new life, and 
relieving our fevered blood.  I told Mr. Block to throw back the 
tarpaulin over the main hatch and let our dusky friends get some 
benefit of it.  In half an hour the rain ceased, but it was as calm 
and ominous as ever. 
</p><p>I knew this was but the forerunner of something worse to 
follow, and we had not long to wait, for suddenly a blinding flash 
of lightning darted through the gloom from east to west, followed 
by one in the opposite direction.  Without intermission, one blaze 
after another and thunder crashing until our eyes were blinded and 
our ears deafened, a thousand times ten thousand pieces of 
artillery thundered away.  We seemed utterly helpless and 
insignificant.  "How wonderful are Thy works," came to my mind.  
Still no wind; the brig lay helpless. 
</p><p>Suddenly, as a slap in the face, the wind struck us, &mdash; on the 
starboard quarter, fortunately.  "Hard-a-starboard."  "Hanl aft 
port fore staysail sheet," I called.  But before she could gather 
way she was thrown down by the wind like a reed.  She was "coming 
to" instead of "going off," and I tried to get the main storm 
staysail down but could not make myself heard.  She was lying on 
her broadside.  Luckily the water was smooth as yet.  The main 
staysail shot out of the boltropes with a report like a twelve-pounder, and this eased her so that if the fore staysail would only 
hold she would go off.  For a few minutes all we could do was to 
hold on, our lee rail in the water; but the plucky little brig 
rallied a little, her head went off inch by inch, and as she 
gathered way she righted, and catching the wind on our quarter we 
were off like a shot out of a gun.  I knew we were too near the 
vortex of the disturbance for the wind to hang long in one quarter, 
so watched anxiously for a change.  The sea rose rapidly while we 
were running to the northward on her course, and after a lull of a 
few minutes the wind opened from the eastward, butt end foremost, 
a change of eight points.  Nothing was to be done but heave to, and 
this in a cross sea where pitch, weather roll, lee lurch, followed 
one another in such earnest that it was a wonder her masts were not 
switched out of her. 
</p><p>I passed an anxious night, most concerned 
<pb n="459"/>  
about the 
poor creatures under hatches, whose sufferings must have been 
terrible.  To prevent their suffocating I kept two men at the main 
hatch with orders to lift one corner of the tarpaulin whenever 
possible, even if some water did go below.  Toward morning the wind 
and the sea went down rapidly, and as the sun rose it chased the 
clouds off, giving us the promise of a fine day.  When the cook 
brought me a cup of coffee, I do not know that I ever enjoyed 
anything more.  Hatches off, I jumped down into the hold to look 
after my prisoners.  Battered and bruised they lay around in heaps.  
Only the shifting boards had kept them from being beaten into an 
indistinguishable mass.  As fast as possible they were sent on 
deck, and the sun's rays, with a few buckets of water that were 
thrown over them, accomplished wonders in bringing them to life and 
starting them to care for their sore limbs and bruises. 
</p><p>One boy, when I motioned for him to go on deck, pointed 
quietly to his leg, and upon examination I found a fracture just 
above the knee.  Swelling had already commenced.  I had seen limbs 
set, and had some rough idea how it should be done.  So while 
getting some splints of keg staves and bandages ready, I kept a 
stream of water pouring on the fracture, and then ordered two men 
to pull the limb in place, and it took all their strength.  That 
done I put on the splints and wrapped the bandages tightly.  Three 
weeks later I landed him in a fair way of recovery. 
</p><p>Gradually I allowed a larger number of the blacks to remain on 
deck, a privilege which they greatly enjoyed.  To lie basking in 
the sun like saurians, half sleeping, half waking, appeared to 
satisfy all their wishes.  They were perfectly docile and obedient, 
and not by word, gesture, or look did they express any 
dissatisfaction with orders given them.  But again for any little 
acts of kindness they expressed no kind of appreciation or 
gratitude.  Physically they were men and women, but otherwise as 
far removed from the Anglo-Saxon as the oyster from the baboon, or 
the mole from the horse. 
</p><p>On the fourteenth day from parting with the brig we made the 
palms on Cape Mesurado, the entrance to Monrovia Harbor.  A light 
sea breath wafted us to the anchorage, a mile from the town, and 
when the anchor dropped from the bows and the chain ran through the 
hawse pipe, it was sweet music to my ears; for the strain had been 
great, and I felt years older than when I parted from my messmates.  
A great responsibility seemed lifted from my shoulders, and I 
enjoyed a long and refreshing sleep for the first time in a 
fortnight.  At nine the next morning I went on shore and reported 
to the authorities, the officials of Liberia, of which Monrovia is 
the capital. 
</p><p>This part of the African coast had been selected by the United 
States government as the home of emancipated slaves; for prior to 
the abolition excitement which culminated in the war, numbers of 
slaves in the South had been manumitted by their masters with the 
understanding that they should be deported to Liberia, and the 
Colonization Society, an influential body, comprising some of the 
leading men, like Madison, Webster, and Clay, had assisted in the 
same work.  The passages of the negroes were paid; each family was 
given a tract of land and sufficient means to build a house.  
Several thousand had been sent out, most of whom had settled at 
Monrovia, and a few at other places on the coast.  They had made no 
impression on the natives.  On the contrary, many of them had 
intermarried with the natives, and the off-spring of these unions 
had lost the use of the English tongue, and had even gone back to 
the life and customs of their ancestors, sans clothing, sans 
habitations, and worship of a fetich. 
</p><p>Of course there were some notable exceptions, especially 
President Roberts, who proved himself a safe and prudent ruler, 
taking into consideration his surroundings 
<pb n="460"/>  
and the material 
with which he had to work.  The form of government was modeled 
after that of the United States, but it was top-heavy.  Honorables, 
colonels, and judges were thicker than in Georgia.  Only privates 
were scarce; for nothing delights a negro more than a little show 
or a gaudy uniform.  On landing I was met by a dark mulatto, 
dressed in a straw hat, blue tail coat, silver epaulettes, linen 
trousers, with bare feet, and a heavy cavalry sabre hanging by his 
side.  With him were three or four others in the same rig, except 
the epaulettes.  He introduced himself as Colonel Harrison, chief 
of police.  I asked to be directed to the custom house. 
</p><p>The collector proved to be an old negro from Raleigh, N. C., 
gray as a badger, spectacled, with manners of Lord Grandison and 
language of Mrs. Malaprop.  I reported my arrival, and asked 
permission to land my cargo as soon as possible.  He replied that 
in a matter of so much importance, devolving questions of momentous 
interest, it would be obligatory on him to consult the Secretary of 
the Treasury.  I said I trusted he would so facilitate affairs that 
I might at an early hour disembarrass myself of my involuntary 
prisoners.  I returned on board, and the day passed without any 
answer.  The next morning I determined to go at once to 
headquarters and find out the cause of the delay by calling on the 
President. 
</p><p>He received me without any formality.  I made my case as 
strong as possible, and pressed for an immediate answer.  In reply 
he assured me he would consult with other members of his cabinet, 
and give me a final answer the next morning.  That evening I dined 
with him <hi rend="italic">en famille</hi>, and recognized some old Virginia dishes on 
the table.  The next morning I waited impatiently for his decision, 
having made up my mind however, if it was unfavorable, to land my 
poor captives, be the consequences what they might. 
</p><p>About eleven o'clock a boat came off with an officer in full 
uniform, who introduced himself as Colonel Royal, bearer of 
dispatches from his Excellency the President.  He handed me a 
letter couched in diplomatic language, as long as some of his 
brother presidents' messages on this side of the Atlantic.  I had 
hardly patience to read it.  The gist of it was, I might not land 
the captives at Monrovia, but might land them at Grand Bassa, about 
a hundred and fifty miles to the eastward; that Colonel Royal would 
accompany me with orders to the governor there to receive them.  
This was something I had not anticipated, and outside of my 
instructions.  However, I thought it best to comply with the wishes 
of the government of our only colony. 
</p><p>Getting under way we stood to the southward and eastward, 
taking advantage of the light land and sea breeze, keeping the 
coast close aboard.  The colonel had come on board without any 
impediments, and I wondered if he intended to make the voyage in 
his cocked hat, epaulettes, sword, etc.  But soon after we had 
started he disappeared and emerged from the cabin bareheaded, 
barefooted, and without clothing except a blue dungaree shirt and 
trousers.  Like a provident negro, having stowed away all his 
trappings, he appeared as a roustabout on a Western steamer.  But 
he had not laid aside with his toggery any of his important and 
consequential airs.  He ran foul of Mr. Block, who called him Mr. 
Cuffy, and ordered him to give him a pull with the main sheet.  The 
colonel complained to me that he was not addressed by his name or 
title, and that he was not treated as a representative of his 
government should be.  I reprimanded Mr. Block, and told him to 
give the visitor all his title.  "All right, sir, but the colonel 
must keep off the weather side of the deck," growled the officer.  
The cook, the crew, and even the Kroomen, all took their cue from 
the first officer, and the colonel's lot was made most unhappy. 
</p><p>On the third day we reached Grand 
<pb n="461"/>  
Bassa, and anchored 
off the beach about two miles, along which the surf was breaking so 
high that any attempt to land would be hazardous.  Toward evening 
it moderated, and a canoe with three naked natives came off.  One 
I found could speak a little English.  I told him to say to the 
governor that I would come on shore in the morning and see him, and 
land my cargo at the same time. 
</p><p>The next morning at sunrise we were boarded by a party of 
natives headed by one wearing a black hat half covered with a 
tarnished silver band, an old navy frock coat, much too small, 
between the buttons of which his well-oiled skin showed clearly.  
A pair of blue flannel trousers completed his outfit.  An 
interpreter introduced him as King George of Grand Bassa.  With him 
were about a dozen followers, each one wearing a different sort of 
garment &mdash; and seldom more than a single one &mdash; representing old 
uniforms of many countries.  Two coats I noticed were buttoned up 
the back. 
</p><p>The king began by saying that he was and always had been a 
friend of the Americans; that he was a big man, had plenty of men 
and five wives, etc.  While he was speaking, a white-bearded old 
colored gentleman came over the gangway, dressed in a linen 
roundabout and trousers, with a wide-brimmed straw hat.  At the 
same time Colonel Royal came up from the cabin in <hi rend="italic">grande tenue</hi> 
and introduced us to the Hon. Mr. Marshall, governor of Bassa, 
formerly of Kentucky. 
</p><p>In a few minutes he explained the situation.  With a few 
settlers he was located at this place, on the frontier of the 
colony, and they were there on sufferance only from the natives.  
I told him Colonel Royal would explain my mission to him and the 
king.  The colonel, bowing low to the king, the governor, and 
myself, and bringing his sword down with a thud on the deck, drew 
from between the bursting buttons of his coat the formidable 
document I had seen at Monrovia, and with most impressive voice and 
gesture commenced to read it.  The king listened for a few minutes, 
and then interrupted him.  I asked the interpreter what he said.  
He replied, "King say he fool nigger; if he comes on shore he give 
him to Voodoo women."  Then turning his back he walked forward.  
The colonel dropped his paper, and drawing his sword, in the most 
dramatic manner claimed protection in the name of the government, 
declaring that he had been insulted.  I told him to keep cool, 
since he was certainly safe as long as he was on board my ship.  He 
grumbled and muttered terrible things, but subsided gradually like 
the departing thunder of a summer storm. 
</p><p>I arranged the landing of the passengers with Governor 
Marshall, whom I found a sensible, clear-headed old man, ready to 
cooperate in every way.  But he suggested that I had better consult 
the king before doing anything.  I did so, and he at once said they 
could not land.  I told the interpreter to say they would be landed 
at once and put under the protection of the governor; that if the 
king or his people hurt them or ran them off I would report it to 
our commodore, who would certainly punish him severely.  Finding me 
determined, he began to temporize, and asked that the landing be 
put off until the next day, that he might consult with his head 
people, for if I sent them on shore before he had done so they 
would kill them.  "If that is the case," I replied, "I will hold 
you on board as a hostage for their good behavior."  This threat 
surprised him, and he changed his tactics.  After a little powwow 
with some of his followers, he said that if I would give him fifty 
muskets, twenty pounds of powder, the colonel's sword, and some red 
cloth for his wives, I might land them.  I replied that I had not 
a musket to spare nor an ounce of powder, that the colonel was a 
high officer of his government, and that he of course would not 
give up his uniform.  Fortunately the colonel had retired to 
<pb n="462"/>  
the cabin and did not hear this modest demand, or he would 
have been as much outraged as if his sable Majesty had asked for 
him to be served "roti a l'Ashantee."  However, I told the king I 
would send his wives some cloth and buttons.  He grunted his 
approval but returned again to the charge, and asked that he might 
choose a few of the captives for his own use, before landing.  
"Certainly not," I answered, "neither on board nor on shore," and 
added that he would be held accountable for their good treatment as 
free men and women.  He left thoroughly disappointed and bent on 
mischief. 
</p><p>In the meantime Mr. Block had made all preparations for 
landing, and had the boats lowered and ranged alongside, with 
sufficient rice to last the blacks a week or ten days.  The men and 
boys were sent first.  When they were called up from the hold and 
ordered into the boats not one of them moved.  They evidently 
divined what had been going on and dreaded leaving the vessel, 
though our Kroomen tried to explain that they would be safe and 
free on shore.  The explanation was without effect, however, and 
they refused to move.  The could only understand that they were 
changing masters, and they preferred the present ones.  Sending 
three or four men down, I told them to pass up the negroes one at 
a time.  Only a passive resistance was offered, such as one often 
sees exhibited by cattle being loaded on the cars or on a steamer, 
and were silent, not uttering a word of complaint.  By noon the men 
were all on shore, and then we began with the girls.  They were 
more demonstrative than the men, and by their looks and gestures 
begged not to be taken out of the vessel.  I was much moved, for it 
was a painful duty, and I had become interested in these beings, so 
utterly helpless, so childlike in their dependence on those around 
them.  And I could not help thinking what their fate would be, 
thrown upon the shore hundreds of miles from their homes, and among 
a people strange to them in language. 
</p><p>Even Mr. Block was deeply stirred.  "He had not shipped," he 
said, "for such work."  I went to my cabin and left him in charge.  
In the course of an hour he reported, "All ashore, sir."  I told 
him to have the gig manned and I would go on shore with Colonel 
Royal, and get a receipt from Governor Marshall for my late cargo.  
The colonel declined to accompany me, alleging sickness and 
requesting me to get the necessary papers signed.  No doubt he felt 
safer on board than within reach of King George. 
</p><p>We landed through the surf on a sandy beach, on which the 
waves of the Atlantic were fretting.  Near by was a thick grove of 
cocoanut trees, under which in groups of four and five were those 
who had just been landed.  They were seated on the ground, their 
heads resting on their knees, in a position of utter abnegation, 
surrounded by three or four hundred chattering savages of all ages, 
headed by the king.  With the exception of him and a few of his 
head men, the clothing of the company would not have covered a rag 
baby.  They were no doubt discussing the appearance of the 
strangers and making their selections. 
</p><p>I found the governor's house and the houses of the few 
settlers some distance back on a slight elevation.  The governor 
was comfortably, though plainly situated, with a large family 
around him.  He gave me a receipt for the number of blacks landed, 
but said it would be impossible for him to prevent the natives from 
taking and enslaving them.  I agreed with him, and said he must 
repeat to the king what I had told him.  Then bidding him good-by 
I returned on board, sad and weary as one often feels after being 
relieved of a great burden.  At the same time I wondered whether 
the fate of these people would have been any worse if the captain 
of the slaver had succeeded in landing them in the Brazils or the 
West Indies.  Sierra Leone 
<pb n="463"/>  
being a crown colony, the 
English could land all their captives there and provide for them 
until they were able to work for themselves.  In this respect they 
had a great advantage over us. 
</p><p>Getting under way, I proceeded to Monrovia to land Colonel 
Royal, and then to Porto Praya, our squadron's headquarters.  There 
I found Commodore Gregory in the flagship corvette Portsmouth, and 
reported to him.  Soon after the Porpoise came in, and I joined my 
old craft, giving up my command of the captured slaver rather 
reluctantly. </p>
<signed>
                              <hi rend="italic">J. Taylor Wood.</hi>
</signed> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
