<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="WyaStep"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]> 
<TEI.2 id="WyaStep"> 
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Stephen Crane.</title>
<title type="sort">stephen crane</title>
<author>Crane review: Wyatt, Edith</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
<name>Judy Boss</name> 
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>  
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt> 
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">14</num> kilobytes</extent> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace> 
<idno type="ETC">WyaStep</idno> 
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476565</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt> 
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Stephen Crane.</title>
<title>The New Republic. v. 4, no. 45, 1915</title>
<title type="sort">stephen crane</title>
<author>Crane review: Edith Wyatt</author>
</titleStmt> 
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition.</p>
</editionStmt> 
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Republic Publishing Company Inc.</publisher> 
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace> 
<date value="1915">1915</date>
</publicationStmt> 
<seriesStmt>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">The New Republic</hi> 4, 11 September 1915: 148-150.</p>
</seriesStmt> 
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc> 
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text 
Center.</p>
</projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p> 
<p>Spell-check and verification made 
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p> 
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the 
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p> 
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl> 
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's 
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of  
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc> 
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1915">1915</date>
</creation> 
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage> 
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term> 
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc> 
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-01">January 1996</date> 
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp> 
<name>Deirdre Johnson, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia.</name>
</respStmt> 
<item>Added header and basic TEI markup.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="d1"> 
<body id="d2"> 

 
<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> 
<head>                       Stephen Crane</head> <pb n="148" id="WyaStep148"/> 
<p> 
WHATEVER is deeply thought is well written, in the view of M. Remy 
de Gourmont.  The observation has an aerial beauty.  From its 
outlook one instinctively casts a revisiting glance of speculation 
at well written places in expression one had lost awhile, to find 
how deeply thought they are. 
</p><p>In this speculative glance, not long since, I chanced to be 
arrested by the memory of Stephen Crane.  Endowed with a genius for 
direct expression, he was able in his short existence to present a 
surprising number of penetrating ascertainments of American life, 
with a high degree of clarity and power. 
</p><p>One encounters occasionally a popular conception of Stephen 
Crane as the author of one or two slight prose tales, and a few 
lines of grotesque verse&mdash;a writer of fragmentary achievement, with 
a talent of distinct originality, but somewhat narrow.  The 
conception has come into being, doubtless from our widespread 
custom of asking concerning each subsequent work of an author 
whether it is just like his first book, and of ignoring the 
subsequent work if it is not.  With many authors this is the only 
means we have of supporting a certain, correct, traditional 
attitude of consistent disappointment in their efforts.  The 
prevalence of the attitude is attested by the celebrated response 
of a veteran editor of <hi rend="italic">Punch</hi> to a friend's remark that 
<hi rend="italic">Punch</hi> wasn't as good as it used to be: "No, it never was." 
</p><p>To interested readers of Stephen Crane's work, no impression 
of it could be further than the fabular <pb n="149" id="WyaStep149"/> repute we have 
mentioned from the facts of his productive career as a writer.  
Before his death in his thirtieth year, Stephen Crane had published 
eleven books.  While none of these is a large book, it is true, 
they are for the most part of remarkable concentration and 
substance, and of a marked variety in subject, in kind, in tone, 
and in treatment&mdash;historical essays, special articles, poetry and 
fiction; among these publications there are perhaps forty short 
stories, and five very dissimilar brief novels, ranging from the 
sustained tragedy of "Maggie" to mockery's lightest touch in "The 
Third Violet." 
</p><p>"The line of Sesshu," says a critic of Japanese line-drawing, 
"vibrates with the nervous force of the artist's hand."  With the 
exception of "Active Service," a work composed, as one understands, 
in illness, and two or three of the Mexican tales, which are rather 
standardized and weakly handled, the description might characterize 
all these contributive pieces of fiction. 
</p><p>The world of misery, the world of poverty, the very presence 
of exploiting meanness, of the impulse to pride oneself on using 
human beings and casting them aside, rises in the tale of "Maggie."  
A story of the "poor among the poor," of a warm-hearted, pleasure-loving girl, a stitcher in a collar-factory, who is betrayed and 
deserted by a barkeeper and remains in poverty through the last 
despair of unsuccess in her final calling as a street-walker, the 
novel is all narrated in the first-hand terms of crowded life, the 
terms of the life of New York tenements, tenement-streets and 
saloons, selectively rendered, without comment, without shallow 
judgments, with the searching and complete humor of the desire of 
truth in our exploitational world, where Maggie's exploiter is 
himself exploited.  Much "happens" in both this book and "George's 
Mother"&mdash;sins, shames, gaieties, injustices.  Delicately 
analytical, the method of the narratives spreads no analysis upon 
the page.  They proceed by a realization of the movement, color, 
sound, odor, form and contact of their scene and incident, often 
desperate incident, wrought by struggling characters in their 
course through the wilds of a random civilization. 
</p><p>One touch of dulness which makes many novels kin, purporting 
falsely to be realistic, is a lack of unified expression.  Relating 
much about lives, they tell us nothing at all about life.  They 
fail in the power of seizing some one positive, though hitherto 
undiscriminated, aspect of creation&mdash;something as actual and yet as 
intangible as the look of an individual countenance&mdash;and thus miss 
the nameless fusion which illuminates a realized presentment.  It 
is in this faculty of penetrating social criticism, of a vivid, 
well-chosen focus of the human circles and aims he presents, that 
Stephen Crane excels and interests. 
</p><p>We have no more spirited portrait of the mob-meanness of our 
democracy&mdash;the peculiarly American disgrace that shames us among 
nations&mdash;than his short story, "The Monster," a chronicle of the 
cruelty of the people of an eastern town to a negro maimed in 
recovering from a fire the child of the town's best doctor.  The 
completely miserable performance of these people; their laudation 
of poor Henry Johnson; their editorial on his heroism when it is 
supposed he is dead; and their disapprobation of him after he is 
saved by Dr. Trescott's skill and returns to live among them, in 
his disfigurement and idiocy, faceless, and horrible to look upon; 
their insistence that he be taken out of the town to spare their 
sensibilities; and their desertion and ruin of the career of Dr. 
Trescott, his one friend&mdash;all this is of the best stuff of tragedy, 
a living likeness to the wilds of a cowardly tyranny, splendidly 
and thoroughly understood and told, and of the same piece of 
appreciation of the minds and motives of men as Kent's blinding. 
</p><p>If the pity and terror of democracy's mob-meanness are vividly 
revealed by Stephen Crane, so is the inspiration and swing of 
democracy's impulse to keep in line. 
</p>
<p>On the morning of July 2nd, I sat on San Juan hill and 
watched Lawton's division come up.  I was absolutely 
sheltered, but still where I could look into the faces of men 
who were trotting up under fire.  There wasn't a high heroic 
face among them.  They were all men intent on business.  That 
was all.  It may seem to you that I am trying to make 
everything a squalor.  That would be wrong.  I feel that 
things were of the sublime.  They were not of our shallow and 
preposterous fictions.  They stood out in a simply majestic 
commonplace.  It was the behavior of men on the street.  It 
was the behavior of men.  In one way, each man was just 
pegging along at the heels of still another man who&mdash;  It was 
that in the flat and obvious way.  In another way it was 
pageantry, the pageantry of the accomplishment of naked duty. 
One cannot speak of it&mdash;the spectacle of the common man 
serenely doing his work, his appointed work.  It is the one 
thing in the universe which makes one fling expression to the 
winds and be satisfied to simply feel.</p> 

<p>This passage from a special article in "War Memories" is 
quoted not only as an instance of Stephen Crane's manner in giving 
the reader the peculiar special light on the countenance of the 
situation he describes, but as an example of the extraordinary 
directness of that manner. 
</p><p>"Direct treatment of subject."  In the last few years we have 
heard the phrase much used by the Imagists.  Stephen Crane's two 
slender volumes of verse, "The Black Riders" and "War Is Kind,"<pb n="150" id="WyaStep150"/> have just now a timely interest from their achievement in a 
certain art of poetic expression regarded by numbers of persons&mdash; 
though certainly not, one believes, by the Imagists themselves&mdash;as 
only recently attempted.  As both Stephen Crane and most of the 
Imagists are American poets it is curious to compare their likeness 
and divergence on this special point&mdash;"direct treatment of 
subject"&mdash;which is, according to Mr. Richard Aldington, the 
Imagists' first tenet. 
</p><p>To my own perception, with all deference to the Imagists' 
seriousness of purpose, and with a liking for their poetry though 
by no means an abject worship of it, this power of direct treatment 
in which Stephen Crane's verses excel is an art absent even from 
the aim of most of the poems the Imagists themselves regard as 
their most distinctive work&mdash;poems such as "After Ch'u Youan," 
"Acon, (after Joannes Baptista Amaltheus)" and "To Atthis (after 
the mss. of Sappho now in Berlin.)" 
</p><p>With the same brevity, exactitude and simplicity of outline 
which characterize Stephen Crane's verses, these poems of the 
Imagists' treat certain situations in existence, by no means in the 
method of a straightforward, first-hand understanding, but very 
indirectly, and through the media of the spirit and manner of 
certain remote, approved civilizations and habits of thought.  
Their charm, the charm of classic echo or historic fancy, has the 
scholarly grace and lovely refinement of line of a Wedgwood design.  
But this treatment of subject, while both simple and precise, is by 
no means direct.  Akin to the Imagists' work in several attractive 
attributes, in this peculiar quality of an authentic, first-hand 
vision, Stephen Crane's poems seem to me to evince a far deeper and 
better conception than the Imagists' of direct expression in 
poetry. 
</p><p>Here is a love poem: 
</p>
<lg type="poem"><l>     Should the wide world roll away,</l> 
<l>     Leaving black terror,</l> 
<l>     Limitless night,&mdash;</l> 
<l>     Nor God, nor man, nor place to stand</l> 
<l>     Would be to me essential</l> 
<l>     If thou and thy white arms were there,</l> 
<l>     And the fall to doom a long way.</l> 
</lg>
<p>Here is a characterization: 
</p>
<lg type="poem"><l>     With eye and with gesture</l> 
<l>     You say you are holy.</l> 
<l>     I say you lie.</l> 
<l>     For I did see you</l> 
<l>     Draw away your coats</l> 
<l>     From the sin upon the hands</l> 
<l>     Of a little child.</l> 
<l>     Liar!</l> 
</lg> 
<p>Who are the men who are creators?  Who will express truly the 
quality of his own knowledge of life; and leave behind a moving 
image that he has conceived of our own mortal ways&mdash;our little ways 
and large ways, in a fast-changing universe? 
</p><p>Such a creator was Stephen Crane.  In his static lines of 
verse, in the lyric movement of his stories, vibrate unforgettable 
and authentic moods of the very nature of our country&mdash;the smell of 
the wet turf along the shaded house-walls, the pluming maple-tops, 
the muteness of neighbor and neighbor, the scorching breath of 
injustice, the air of wartime memories on cloudy bluff and valley, 
the wind's will blowing through the soul of youth, death in 
struggle everywhere, and the strength of love stronger than death, 
and the failures and the prides of our mortality. 
</p>
<lg type="fragment">
<l>     Oh, nothing, nothing, commonest things,</l> 
<l>     A touch, a sound, a glimpse, a breath!</l> 
</lg>
<p>Again you turn, and look again and listen to the sense and 
spirit of his clear-voiced pages, and perceive you had forgotten 
how well written they are in remembering how deeply they are 
thought.</p> 
<signed>                                        EDITH WYATT.</signed> 
 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
</text> 
</TEI.2> 
 
 
 
 
