<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AdeMark"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;


]>

<TEI.2 id="AdeMark">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mark Twain and the Old Time Subscription Book</title>
<title type="sort">mark twain and the old time subscription book</title>
<author>Twain, Mark: related material: Ade, George</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Stephen Railton</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">8</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AdeMark</idno>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475656</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mark Twain and the Old Time Subscription Book</title>
<title level="j">The American Review of Reviews, Vol. XLI, No. 6</title>
<title type="sort">mark twain and the old time subscription book</title>
<author>George Ade</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>p. 703</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Review of Reviews Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1910-06">June 1910</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVA Library call number AP 2 .R42 v.41 1910</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1910">1910</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; non-fiction</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-06">June 1997</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Carol Osborne, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="article" id="d3">
	<pb n="703" id="AdeMark703"/>
<head>[from <hi rend="italic">The American Review of Reviews</hi>, June 1910]
<lb/>
Mark Twain and the Old Time Subscription Book
<lb/>
By George Ade</head>

<p>M<hi rend="small-caps">ARK TWAIN</hi> should be doubly blessed for
saving the center table from utter dullness.  Do you remember that
center table of the seventies?  The marbled top showed glossy in the
subdued light that filtered through the lace curtains, and it was clammy
cold even on hot days.  The heavy mahogany legs were chiseled into
writhing curves from which depended stern geometrical designs or
possibly bunches of grapes.  The Bible had the place of honor and was
flanked by subscription books.  In those days the house never became
cluttered with the ephemeral six best sellers.  The new books came a
year apart, and each was meant for the center table, and it had to be so
thick and heavy and emblazoned with gold that it could keep company with
the bulky and high-priced Bible.</p>

<p>Books were bought by the pound.  Sometimes the agent was a
ministerial person in black clothes and a stove-pipe hat.  Maiden ladies
and widows, who supplemented their specious arguments with private tales
of woe, moved from one small town to another feeding upon prominent
citizens.  Occasionally the prospectus was unfurled by an undergraduate
of a freshwater college working for the money to carry him another
year.</p>

<p>The book agents varied, but the book was always the same, &mdash; many
pages, numerous steel engravings, curly-cue tail-pieces, platitudes,
patriotism, poetry, sentimental mush.  One of the most popular, still
resting in many a dim sanctuary, was known as "Mother, Home, and
Heaven."  A ponderous collection of "Poetical Gems" did not involve the
publishers in any royalty entanglements. Even "The Lives of the
Presidents" and "Noble Deeds of the Great and Brave" gave every evidence
of having been turned out as piece-work by needy persons temporarily
lacking employment on newspapers.  Let us not forget the "Manual of
Deportment and Social Usages," from which the wife of

 <pb n="704" id="AdeMark704"/>

an agriculturalist could learn the meaning of R.S.V.P. and the form to be
employed in acknowledging an invitation to a levee.</p>

<p>Nobody really wanted these books.  They were purchased because the
agents knew how to sell them, and they seemed large for the price, and,
besides, every well-furnished home had to keep something on the center
table.</p>

<p>Subscription books were dry picking for boys.  Also they were
accessible only on the Sabbath after the weekly scouring.  On week-days
the boys favored an underground circulating library, named after Mr.
Beadle, and the hay-mow was the chosen reading room.  Let one glorious
exception be made in the case of "Dr. Livingstone's Travels in Africa,"
a subscription book of forbidding size, but containing many pictures of
darkies with rings in their noses.</p>

<p>Just when front-room literature seemed at its lowest ebb, so far as
the American boy was concerned, along came Mark Twain.  His books
looked, at a distance, just like the other distended, diluted, and
altogether tasteless volumes that had been used for several decades to
balance the ends of the center table.  The publisher knew his public, so
he gave a pound of book for every fifty cents, and crowded in plenty of
wood-cuts and stamped the outside with golden bouquets and put in a
steel engraving of the author, with a tissue paper veil over it, and
"sicked" his multitude of broken-down clergymen, maiden ladies, grass
widows, and college students on to the great American public.</p>

<p>Can you see the boy, a Sunday morning prisoner, approach the book
with a dull sense of foreboding, expecting a dose of Tupper's
"Proverbial Philosophy"?  Can you see him a few minutes later when he
finds himself linked arm-in-arm with Mulberry Sellers or Buck Fanshaw or
the convulsing idiot who wanted to know if Christopher Columbus was
sure-enough dead?  No wonder he curled up on the hair-cloth sofa and
hugged the thing to his bosom and lost all interest in Sunday-school.
"Innocents Abroad" was the most enthralling book ever printed until
"Roughing It" appeared.  Then along came "The Gilded Age," "Life on the
Mississippi," and "Tom Sawyer," one cap sheaf after another.  While
waiting for a new one we read the old ones all over again. </p>

<p>The new uniform edition with the polite little pages, high-art
bindings, and all the boisterous wood-cuts carefully expurgated can
never take the place of those lumbering subscription books.  They were
the early friends and helped us to get acquainted with the most amazing
story-teller that ever captivated the country boys and small-town boys
all over America.</p>

<p>While we are honoring Mark Twain as a great literary artist, a
philosopher, and a teacher, let the boys of the seventies add their
tribute.  The knew him for his miracle of making the subscription book
something to be read and not merely looked at.  He converted the Front
Room from a Mausoleum into a Temple of Mirth.</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>


