<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AlgGran"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>


<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="AlgGran">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Grand'ther Baldwin's Thanksgiving</title>
<title type="sort">grandther baldwins thanksgiving</title>
<author>Alger, Horatio, 1832-1899</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>William Roach</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">8</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AlgGran</idno>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475662</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Grand'ther Baldwin's Thanksgiving</title>
<title level="m">Grand'ther Baldwin's Thanksgiving, with other ballads and poems.</title>
<title type="sort">grandther baldwins thanksgiving</title>
<author>Horatio Alger</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>First American edition.</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Loring</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
<date value="1875">1875</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa Library PS1029 .A3G7 1875</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1875">1875</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>poetry</term>
<term>Young Readers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-05">May 1997</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Christine Ruotolo, Electroninc Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="poem" id="d3">
	<pb n="7" id="AlgGran7"/>
<head>GRAND'THER BALDWIN'S THANKSGIVING.</head>

<lg type="couplet"><l><hi rend="small-caps">Underneath</hi> protecting branches, from the highway just aloof,
</l><l>Stands the house of Grand'ther Baldwin, with its gently sloping roof.</l></lg>

<lg type="couplet"><l>Square of shape and solid-timbered, it was standing, I have heard,
</l><l>In the days of Whig and Tory, under royal George the Third.</l></lg>

<lg type="couplet"><l>Many a time, I well remember, I have gazed with childish awe
</l><l>At the bullet-hole remaining in the sturdy oaken door,</l></lg>

   <pb n="8" id="AlgGran8"/>
<lg type="couplet"><l>Turning round half-apprehensive (recking not how time had fled)
</l><l>Of the lurking savage foeman from whose musket it was sped.</l></lg>

<lg type="couplet"><l>Not far off, the barn, plethoric with the autumn's harvest spoils,
</l><l>Holds the farmer's well-earned trophies -the guerdon of his toils;</l></lg>

<lg type="couplet"><l>Filled the lofts with hay, sweet-scented, ravished from the meadows
green,
</l><l>While beneath are stalled the cattle, with their quiet, drowsy mien.</l></lg>

<lg type="couplet"><l>Deep and spacious are the grain-bins, brimming o'er with nature's gold;
</l><l>Here are piles of yellow pumpkins on the barn-floor loosely rolled.</l></lg>

   <pb n="9" id="AlgGran9"/>
<lg type="couplet"><l>Just below in deep recesses, safe from wintry frost and chill,
</l><l>There are heaps of ruddy apples from the orchard on the hill.</l></lg>

<lg type="couplet"><l>Many a year has Grand'ther Baldwin in the old house dwelt in peace,
</l><l>As his hair each year grew whiter, he has seen his herds increase.</l></lg>

<lg type="couplet"><l>Sturdy sons and comely daughters, growing up from childish plays,
</l><l>One by one have met life's duties, and gone forth their several ways.</l></lg>

<lg type="couplet"><l>Hushed the voice of childish laughter, hushed is childhood's merry
tone,
</l><l>By the fireside Grand'ther Baldwin and his good wife sit alone.</l></lg>

   <pb n="10" id="AlgGran10"/>
<lg type="couplet"><l>Yet once within the twelvemonth, when the days are short and drear,
</l><l>And chill winds chant the requiem of the slowly fading year,</l></lg>

<lg type="couplet"><l>When the autumn work is over, and the harvest gathered in,
</l><l>Once again the old house echoes to a long unwonted din.</l></lg>

<lg type="couplet"><l>Logs of hickory blaze and crackle in the fireplace huge and high,
</l><l>Curling wreaths of smoke mount upward to the gray November sky.</l></lg>

<lg type="couplet"><l>Ruddy lads and smiling lasses, just let loose from schooldom's cares,
</l><l>Patter, patter, race and clatter, up and down the great hall stairs.</l></lg>

   <pb n="11" id="AlgGran11"/>
<lg type="couplet"><l>All the boys shall hold high revel; all the girls shall have their
way,&mdash;
</l><l>That's the law at Grand'ther Baldwin's upon each Thanksgiving Day.</l></lg>

<lg type="couplet"><l>From the parlor's sacred precincts, hark! a madder uproar yet;
</l><l>Roguish Charlie's playing stage-coach, <hi rend="italic">and the stage-coach has upset!</hi></l></lg>

<lg type="couplet"><l>Joe, black-eyed and laughter-loving, Grand'ther's specs his nose
across,
</l><l>Gravely winks at brother Willie, who is gayly playing horse.</l></lg>

<lg type="couplet"><l>Grandma's face is fairly radiant; Grand'ther knows not how to frown,
</l><l>Though the children, in their frolic, turn the old house upside down.</l></lg>

   <pb n="12" id="AlgGran12"/>
<lg type="couplet"><l>For the boys may hold high revel, and the girls must have their way;
</l><l>That's the law at Gran'ther Baldwin's upon each Thanksgiving Day.</l></lg>

<lg type="couplet"><l>But the dinner -ah! the dinner -words are feeble to portray
</l><l>What a culinary triumph is achieved Thanksgiving Day!</l></lg>

<lg type="couplet"><l>Fairly groans the board with dainties, but the turkey rules the roast,
</l><l>Aldermanic at the outset, at the last a fleshless ghost.</l></lg>

<lg type="couplet"><l>Then the richness of the pudding, and the flavor of the pie,
</l><l>When you've dined at Grandma Baldwin's you will know as well as I.</l></lg>

   <pb n="13" id="AlgGran13"/>
<lg type="couplet"><l>When, at length, the feast was ended, Grand'ther Baldwin bent his head,
</l><l>And, amid the solemn silence, with a reverent voice, he said:&mdash;</l></lg>

<lg type="couplet"><l>"Now unto God, the Gracious One, we thanks and homage pay,
</l><l>Who guardeth us, and guideth us, and loveth us alway!</l></lg>

<lg type="couplet"><l>"He scatters blessings in our paths, He giveth us increase,
</l><l>He crowns us with His kindnesses, and granteth us His peace.</l></lg>

<lg type="couplet"><l>"Unto himself, our wandering feet, we pray that He may draw,
</l><l>And may we strive, with faithful hearts, to keep His holy law!"</l></lg>

   <pb n="14" id="AlgGran14"/>
<lg type="couplet"><l>His simple words in silence died; a moment's hush, and then
</l><l>From all the listening hearts there rose a solemn-voiced Amen!</l></lg>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

