<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AndEngl"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;


]>
<TEI.2 id="AndEngl">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The New Englander</title>
<title type="sort">new englander</title>
<author>Anderson, Sherwood, 1876-1941</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">39</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AndEngl</idno>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475671</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The New Englander</title>
<title level="j">The Dial, Volume 70, Number 2</title>
<title type="sort">new englander</title>
<author>Sherwood Anderson</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 143-158</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Dial Publishing Company, Inc.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1921-02">February, 1921</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa library, Call no: AP2 .D48</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1921">1921</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; fiction</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-05">May, 1997</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Carolyn M. Fay, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" id="d3">
	<pb n="143"/>
<head>THE NEW ENGLANDER <lb/> BY SHERWOOD ANDERSON </head>
<p>
HER name was Elsie Leander and her girlhood was spent on her
father's farm in Vermont. For several generations the
Leanders had all lived on the same farm and had all married thin
women, and so she was thin. The farm lay in the shadow of a
mountain and the soil was not very rich. From the beginning and
for several generations there had been a great many sons and few
daughters in the family. The sons had gone west or to New York
City and the daughters had stayed at home and thought such
thoughts as come to New England women who see the sons of their
father's neighbours slipping, away, one by one, into the West.

</p><p>Her father's house was a small white frame affair, and when you
went out at the back door, past a small barn and a chicken house,
you got into a path that ran up the side of a hill and into an
orchard. The trees were all old and gnarled. At the back of the
orchard the hill dropped away and bare rocks showed.

</p><p>Inside the fence a large grey rock stuck high up out of the
ground.  As Elsie sat with her back to the rock, with a mangled
hillside at her feet, she could see several large mountains,
apparently but a short distance away, and between herself and the
mountains lay many tiny fields surrounded by neatly built stone walls.
Everywhere rocks appeared. Large ones, too heavy to be moved, stuck
out of the ground in the centre of the fields. The fields were like
cups filled with a green liquid that turned grey in the fall and white
in the winter. The mountains, far off but apparently near at hand,
were like giants ready at any moment to reach out their hands and take
the cups one by one and drink off the green liquid. The large rocks in
the fields were like the thumbs of the giants.

</p><p>Elsie had three brothers, born ahead of her, but they had all
gone away. Two of them had gone to live with her uncle in the
West and her elder brother had gone to New York City where he
had married and prospered. All through his youth and manhood
her father had worked hard and had lived a hard life, but his son
in New York City had begun to send money home, and after that
<pb n="144"/>


things went better. He still worked every day about the barn or in the
fields but he did not worry about the future. Elsie's mother did house
work in the mornings and in the afternoons sat in a rocking chair in
her tiny living room and thought of her sons while she crocheted table
covers and tidies for the backs of chairs. She was a silent woman,
very thin and with very thin bony hands. She did not ease herself into
a rocking chair but sat down and got up suddenly, and when she
crocheted her back was as straight as the back of a drill sergeant.

</p><p>The mother rarely spoke to the daughter. Sometimes in the
afternoons as the younger woman went up the hillside to her place by
the rock at the back of the orchard, her father came out of the barn
and stopped her. He put a hand on her shoulder and asked where she was
going. "To the rock," she said and her father laughed. His laughter
was like the creaking of a rusty barn door hinge and the hand he had
laid on her shoulder was thin like her own hands and like her mother's
hands. The father went into the barn shaking his head. "She's like her
mother. She is herself like a rock," he thought. At the head of the
path that led from the house to the orchard there was a great cluster
of bayberry bushes. The New England farmer came out of his barn to
watch his daughter go along the path, but she had disappeared behind
the bushes. He looked away past his house to the fields and to the
mountains in the distance. He also saw the green cup-like fields and
the grim mountains. There was an almost imperceptible tightening of
the muscles of his half worn-out old body. For a long time he stood in
silence and then, knowing from long experience the danger of having
thoughts, he went back into the barn and busied himself with the
mending of an agricultural tool that had been mended many times before.

</p><p>The son of the Leanders who went to live in New York
City was the father of one son, a thin sensitive boy who looked
like Elsie. The son died when he was twenty-three years old
and some years later the father died and left his money to the
old people on the New England farm. The two Leanders who
had gone west had lived there with their father's brother, a
farmer, until they grew into manhood. Then Will, the younger,
got a job on a railroad. He was killed one winter morning. It
was a cold snowy day and when the freight train he was in charge
<pb n="145"/>



of as conductor left the city of Des Moines, he started to run over
the tops of the cars. His feet slipped and he shot down into space.
That was the end of him.

</p><p>Of the new generation there was only Elsie and her brother
Tom, whom she had never seen, left alive. Her father and mother
talked of going west to Tom for two years before they came to a
decision. Then it took another year to dispose of the farm and
make preparations. During the whole time Elsie did not think
much about the change about to take place in her life.

</p><p>The trip west on the railroad train jolted Elsie out of herself.
In spite of her detached attitude toward life she became excited.  Her
mother sat up very straight and stiff in the seat in the sleeping car
and her father walked up and down in the aisle. After a night when the
younger of the two women did not sleep but lay awake with red burning
cheeks and with her thin fingers incessantly picking at the
bed-clothes in her berth while the train went through towns and
cities, crawled up the sides of hills and fell down into forest-clad
valleys, she got up and dressed to sit all day looking at a new kind
of land. The train ran for a day and through another sleepless night
in a flat land where every field was as large as a farm in her own
country. Towns appeared and disappeared in a continual procession. The
whole land was so unlike anything she had ever known that she began to
feel unlike herself. In the valley where she had been born and where
she had lived all her days everything had an air of finality. Nothing
could be changed. The tiny fields were chained to the earth. They were
fixed in their places and surrounded by aged stone walls. The fields
like the mountains that looked down at them were as unchangeable as the
passing days. She had a feeling they had always been so, would always
be so.

</p><p>Elsie sat like her mother upright in the car seat and with a back
like the back of a drill sergeant. The train ran swiftly along
through Ohio and Indiana. Her thin hands like her mother's
hands were crossed and locked. One passing casually through the
car might have thought both women prisoners handcuffed and
bound to their seats. Night came on and she again got into her
berth Again she lay awake and her thin checks became flushed,
but she thought new thoughts. Her hands were no longer gripped
together and she did not pick at the bed clothes. Twice during
<pb n="146"/>



the night she stretched herself and yawned, a thing she had never
in her life done before. The train stopped at a town on the
prairies, and as there was something the matter with one of the
wheels of the car in which she lay the trainsmen came with flaming
torches to tinker it. There was a great pounding and shouting.
When the train went on its way she wanted to get out of her berth
and run up and down in the aisle of the car. The fancy had come
to her that the men tinkering with the car wheel were new men out
of the new land who had broken with strong hammers the doors
of her prison away. They had destroyed for ever the programme
she had made for her life.

</p><p>Elsie was filled with joy at the thought that the train was still
going on into the West. She wanted to go on for ever in a straight
line into the unknown. She fancied herself no longer on a train
and imagined she had become a winged thing flying through space.
Her long years of sitting alone by the rock on the New England
farm had got her into the habit of expressing her thoughts aloud.
Her thin voice broke the silence that lay over the sleeping car and
her father and mother, both also lying awake, sat up in their berth
to listen.

</p><p>Tom Leander, the only living male representative of the new
generation of Leanders, was a loosely built man of forty inclined to
corpulency. At twenty he had married the daughter of a neighbouring
farmer, and when his wife inherited some money she and Tom moved into
the town of Apple Junction in Iowa where Tom opened a grocery. The
venture prospered as did Tom's matrimonial venture. When his brother
died in New York City and his father, mother, and sister decided to
come west Tom was already the father of a daughter and four sons.

</p><p>On the prairies north of town and in the midst of a vast level
stretch of corn fields, there was a partly completed brick house that
had belonged to a rich farmer named Russell, who had begun to build
the house intending to make it the most magnificent place in the
county, but when it was almost completed he had found himself without
money and heavily in debt. The farm, consisting of several hundred
acres of corn land, had been split into three farms and sold. No one
had wanted the huge unfinished brick house.  <pb n="147"/>


For years it had stood vacant, its windows staring out over the
fields that had been planted almost up to the door.

</p><p>In buying the Russell house Tom was moved by two motives.
He had a notion that in New England the Leanders had been
rather magnificent people. His memory of his father's place in
the Vermont valley was shadowy, but in speaking of it to his wife
he became very definite. "We had good blood in us, we Leanders,"
he said, straightening his shoulders. "We lived in a big house.
We were important people."

</p><p>Wanting his father and mother to feel at home in the new place,
Tom had also another motive. He was not a very energetic man
and, although he had done well enough as keeper of a grocery, his
success was largely due to the boundless energy of his wife. She
did not pay much attention to her household and her children, like
little animals, had to take care of themselves, but in any matter
concerning the store her word was law.

</p><p>To have his father the owner of the Russell Place Tom felt would
establish him as a man of consequence in the eyes of his neighbours.
"I can tell you what, they're used to a big house," he said to his
wife. "I tell you what, my people are used to living in style."

</p><p>The exaltation that had come over Elsie on the train wore away
in the presence of grey empty Iowa fields, but something of the effect
of it remained with her for months. In the big brick house life went
on much as it had in the tiny New England house where she had always
lived. The Leanders installed themselves in three or four rooms on the
ground floor. After a few weeks the furniture that had been shipped by
freight arrived and was hauled out from town in one of Tom's grocery
wagons. There were three or four acres of ground covered with great
piles of boards the unsuccessful farmer had intended to use in the
building of stables. Tom sent men to haul the boards away and Elsie's
father prepared to plant a garden. They had come west in April and as
soon as they were installed in the house ploughing and planting began
in the fields near by. The habit of a lifetime returned to the
daughter of the house.  In the new place there was no gnarled orchard
surrounded by a half-ruined stone fence. All of the fences in all of
the fields that stretched away out of sight to the north, south, east,
and west were <pb n="148"/>


made of wire and looked like spider webs against the blackness of
the ground when it had been freshly ploughed.

</p><p>There was however the house itself. It was like an island rising
out of the sea. In an odd way the house, although it was less than
ten years old, was very old. Its unnecessary bigness represented
an old impulse in men. Elsie felt that. At the east side there
was a door leading to a stairway that ran into the upper part of
the house that was kept locked. Two or three stone steps led up
to it. Elsie could sit on the top step with her back against the
door and gaze into the distance without being disturbed. Almost
at her feet began the fields that seemed to go on and on for ever.
The fields were like the waters of a sea. Men came to plough and
plant. Giant horses moved in a procession across the prairies.
A young man who drove six horses came directly toward her. She
was fascinated. The breasts of the horses as they came forward
with bowed heads seemed like the breasts of giants. The soft
spring air that lay over the fields was also like a sea. The horses
were giants walking on the floor of a sea. With their breasts they
pushed the waters of the sea before them. They were pushing the
waters out of the basin of the sea. The young man who drove
them was also a giant.

</p><p>Elsie pressed her body against the closed door at the top of the
steps. In the garden back of the house she could hear her father at
work. He was raking dry masses of weeds off the ground preparatory to
spading the ground for a family garden. He had always worked in a tiny
confined place and would do the same thing here. In this vast open
place he would work with small tools, doing little things with
infinite care, raising little vegetables. In the house her mother
would crochet little tidies. She herself would be small. She would
press her body against the door of the house, try to get herself out
of sight. Only the feeling that sometimes took possession of her, and
that did not form itself into a thought, would be large.

</p><p>The six horses turned at the fence and the outside horse got
entangled in the traces. The driver swore vigorously. Then he
turned and stared at the pale New Englander and with another
oath pulled the heads of the horses about and drove away into the
distance. The field in which he was ploughing contained two
hundred acres. Elsie did not wait for him to return but went into
<pb n="149"/>


the house and sat with folded arms in a room. The house she
thought was a ship floating in a sea on the floor of which giants
went up and down.

</p><p>May came and then June. In the great fields work was always
going on and Elsie became somewhat used to the sight of the young
man in the field that came down to the steps. Sometimes when he
drove his horses down to the wire fence he smiled and nodded.

</p><p>In the month of August, when it is very hot, the corn in Iowa
fields grows until the corn stalks resemble young trees. The corn
fields become forests. The time for the cultivating of the corn
has passed and weeds grow thick between the corn rows. The
men with their giant horses have gone away. Over the immense
fields silence broods.

</p><p>When the time of the laying-by of the crop came that first
summer after Elsie's arrival in the West her mind, partially
awakened by the strangeness of the railroad trip, awakened again.
She did not feel like a staid thin woman with a back like the back
of a drill sergeant, but like something new and as strange as the
new land into which she had come to live. For a time she did not
know what was the matter. In the field the corn had grown so
high that she could not see into the distance. The corn was like
a wall and the little bare spot of land on which her father's house
stood was like a house built behind the walls of a prison. For a
time she was depressed, thinking that she had come west into a
wide open country, only to find herself locked up more closely
than ever.

</p><p>An impulse came to her. She arose and going down three or
four steps seated herself almost on a level with the ground.

</p><p>Immediately she got a sense of release. She could not see over
the corn but she could see under it. The corn had long wide leaves
that met over the rows. The rows became long tunnels running away into
infinity. Out of the black ground grew weeds that made a soft carpet
of green. From above light sifted down. The corn rows were
mysteriously beautiful. They were warm passageways running out into
life. She got up from the steps, and walking timidly to the wire fence
that separated her from the field, put her hand between the wires and
took hold of one of the corn stalks.  <pb n="150"/>


For some reason after she had touched the strong young stalk and
had held it for a moment firmly in her hand she grew afraid.
Running quickly back to the step she sat down and covered her
face with her hands. Her body trembled. She tried to imagine
herself crawling through the fence and wandering along one of the
passageways. The thought of trying the experiment fascinated
but at the same time terrified. She got quickly up and went into
the house.

</p><p>One Saturday night in August Elsie found herself unable to
sleep. Thoughts, more definite than any she had ever known before,
came into her mind. It was a quiet hot night and her bed stood near a
window. Her room was the only one the Leanders occupied on the second
floor of the house. At midnight a little breeze came up from the south
and when she sat up in bed the floor of corn tassels lying below her
line of sight looked in the moonlight like the face of a sea just
stirred by a gentle breeze.

</p><p>A murmuring began in the corn and murmuring thoughts and
memories awoke in her mind. The long wide succulent leaves had begun
to dry in the intense heat of the August days and as the wind stirred
the corn they rubbed against each other. A call, far away, as of a
thousand voices arose. She imagined the voices were like the voices of
children. They were not like her brother Tom's children, noisy
boisterous little animals, but something quite different, tiny little
things with large eyes and thin sensitive hands.  One after another
they crept into her arms. She became so excited over the fancy that
she sat up in bed and taking a pillow into her arms held it against
her breast. The figure of her cousin, the pale sensitive young Leander
who had lived with his father in New York City and who had died at the
age of twenty-three, came sharply into her mind. It was as though the
young man had come suddenly into the room. She dropped the pillow and
sat waiting, intense, expectant.

</p><p>Young Harry Leander had come to visit his cousin on the New
England farm during the late summer of the year before he died.
He had stayed there for a month and almost every afternoon had
gone with Elsie to sit by the rock at the back of the orchard. One
afternoon when they had both been for a long time silent he began
<pb n="151"/>


to talk. "I want to go live in the West," he said. "I want to go
live in the West. I want to grow strong and be a man," he
repeated. Tears came into his eyes.

</p><p>They got up to return to the house, Elsie walking in silence
beside the young man. The moment marked a high spot in her
life. A strange trembling eagerness for something she had not
realized in her experience of life had taken possession of her.
They went in silence through the orchard but when they came to
the bayberry bush her cousin stopped in the path and turned to
face her. "I want you to kiss me," he said eagerly, stepping
toward her.

</p><p>A fluttering uncertainty had taken possession of Elsie and had
been transmitted to her cousin. After he had made the sudden
and unexpected demand and had stepped so close to her that his
breath could be felt on her cheek, his own cheeks became scarlet
and his hand that had taken her hand trembled. "Well, I wish
I were strong. I only wish I were strong," he said hesitatingly
and turning walked away along the path toward the house.

</p><p>And in the strange new house, set like an island in its sea of
corn, Harry Leander's voice seemed to arise again above the fancied
voices of the children that had been coming out of the fields.
Elsie got out of bed and walked up and down in the dim light
coming through the window. Her body trembled violently. "I
want you to kiss me," the voice said again and to quiet it and to
quiet also the answering voice in herself she went to kneel by the
bed and taking the pillow again into her arms pressed it against
her face.

</p><p>Tom Leander came with his wife and family to visit his father
and mother on Sundays. The family appeared at about ten o'clock in the
morning. When the wagon turned out of the road that ran past the
Russell Place Tom shouted. There was a field between the house and the
road and the wagon could not be seen as it came along the narrow way
through the corn. After Tom had shouted, his daughter Elizabeth, a
tall girl of sixteen, jumped out of the wagon. All five children came
tearing toward the house through the corn. A series of wild shouts
arose on the still morning air.
</p><p>The groceryman had brought food from the store. When the
<pb n="153"/>

horse had been unhitched and put into a shed he and his wife began to
carry packages into the house. The four Leander boys, accompanied by
their sister, disappeared into the near-by fields. Three dogs that had
trotted out from town under the wagon accompanied the children. Two or
three children and occasionally a young man from a neighbouring farm
had come to join in the fun. Elsie's sister-in-law dismissed them all
with a wave of her hand. With a wave of her hand she also brushed
Elsie aside. Fires were lighted and the house reeked with the smell of
cooking. Elsie went to sit on the step at the side of the house. The
corn fields that had been so quiet rang with shouts and with the
barking of dogs.

</p><p>Tom Leander's oldest child, Elizabeth, was like her mother, full
of energy. She was thin and tall like the women of her father's
house but very strong and alive. In secret she wanted to be a lady
but when she tried her brothers, led by her father and mother,
made fun of her. "Don't put on airs," they said. When she got
into the country with no one but her brothers and two or three
neighbouring farm boys she herself became a boy. With the boys
she went tearing through the fields, following the dogs in pursuit
of rabbits. Sometimes a young man came with the children from
a near-by farm. Then she did not know what to do with herself.
She wanted to walk demurely along the rows through the corn but
was afraid her brothers would laugh and in desperation outdid
the boys in roughness and noisiness. She screamed and shouted
and running wildly tore her dress on the wire fences as she
scrambled over in pursuit of the dogs. When a rabbit was caught
and killed she rushed in and tore it out of the grasp of the dogs.
The blood of the little dying animal dripped on her clothes. She
swung it over her head and shouted.

</p><p>The farm hand who had worked all summer in the field within
sight of Elsie became enamoured of the young woman from town.  When
the groceryman's family appeared on Sunday mornings he also appeared
but did not come to the house. When the boys and dogs came tearing
through the fields he joined them. He was also self-conscious and did
not want the boys to know the purpose of his coming and when he and
Elizabeth found themselves alone together he became embarrassed. For a
moment they walked together in silence. In a wide circle about them,
in the forest of the <pb n="153"/>


corn, ran the boys and dogs. The young man had something he
wanted to say, but when he tried to find words his tongue became
thick and his lips felt hot and dry. "Well," he began, "let's you
and me&mdash;"

</p><p>Words failed him and Elizabeth turned and ran after her
brothers and for the rest of the day he could not manage to get her
out of their sight. When he went to join them she became the
noisiest member of the party. A frenzy of activity took possession
of her. With hair hanging down her back, with clothes torn, and
with cheeks and hands scratched and bleeding she led her brothers
in the endless wild pursuit of the rabbits.

</p><p>The Sunday in August that followed Elsie Leander's sleepless
night was hot and cloudy. In the morning she was half ill and
as soon as the visitors from town arrived she crept away to sit on the
step at the side of the house. The children ran away into the
fields. An almost overpowering desire to run with them, shouting
and playing along the corn rows took possession of her. She arose
and went to the back of the house. Her father was at work in
the garden, pulling weeds from between rows of vegetables. Inside
the house she could hear her sister-in-law moving about. On the
front porch her brother Tom was asleep with his mother beside him.
Elsie went back on the step and then arose and went to where the
corn came down to the fence. She climbed awkwardly over and
went a little way along one of the rows. Putting out her hand
she touched the firm hard stalks and then, becoming afraid, dropped
to her knees on the carpet of weeds that covered the ground. For
a long time she stayed thus listening to the voices of the children
in the distance.

</p><p>An hour slipped away. Presently it was time for dinner and her
sister-in-law came to the back door and shouted. There was an
answering whoop from the distance and the children came running
through the fields. They climbed over the fence and ran shouting
across her father's garden. Elsie also arose. She was about to attempt
to climb back over the fence unobserved when she heard a rustling in
the corn. Young Elizabeth Leander appeared. Beside her walked the
ploughman who but a few months earlier had planted the corn in the
field where Elsie now stood.  <pb n="154"/>


She could see the two people coming slowly along the rows. An
understanding had been established between them. The man
reached through between the corn stalks and touched the hand of
the girl who laughed awkwardly and running to the fence climbed
quickly over. In her hand she held the limp body of a rabbit the
dogs had killed.

</p><p>The farm hand went away and when Elizabeth had gone into the
house Elsie climbed over the fence. Her niece stood just within the
kitchen door holding the dead rabbit by one leg. The other leg had
been torn away by the dogs. At sight of the New England woman, who
seemed to look at her with hard unsympathetic eyes, she was ashamed
and went quickly into the house. She threw the rabbit upon a table in
the parlour and then ran out of the room. Its blood ran out on the
delicate flowers of a white crocheted table cover that had been made
by Elsie's mother.

</p><p>The Sunday dinner with all the living Leanders gathered about
the table was gone through in a heavy lumbering silence. When the
dinner was over and Tom and his wife had washed the dishes they went
to sit with the older people on the front porch. Presently they were
both asleep. Elsie returned to the step at the side of the house but
when the desire to go again into the cornfields came sweeping over her
she got up and went indoors.

</p><p>The woman of thirty-five tip-toed about the big house like a
frightened child. The dead rabbit that lay on the table in the
parlour had become cold and stiff. Its blood had dried on the
white table cover. She went upstairs but did not go to her own
room. A spirit of adventure had hold of her. In the upper part
of the house there were many rooms and in some of them no glass
had been put into the windows. The windows had been boarded
up and narrow streaks of light crept in through the cracks between
the boards.

</p><p>Elsie tip-toed up the flight of stairs past the room in which she
slept and opening doors went into other rooms. Dust lay thick
on the floors. In the silence she could hear her brother snoring as
he slept in the chair on the front porch. From what seemed a far
away place there came the shrill cries of the children. The cries
became soft. They were like the cries of unborn children that had
called to her out of the fields on the night before.
</p><p>Into her mind came the intense silent figure of her mother sitting
<pb n="155"/>


on the porch beside her son and waiting for the day to wear itself
out into night. The thought brought a lump into her throat. She
wanted something and did not know what it was. Her own mood
frightened her. In a windowless room at the back of the house
one of the boards over a window had been broken and a bird had
flown in and become imprisoned.

</p><p>The presence of the woman frightened the bird. It flew wildly
about. Its beating wings stirred up dust that danced in the air.
Elsie stood perfectly still, also frightened, not by the presence of
the bird but by the presence of life. Like the bird she was a
prisoner. The thought gripped her. She wanted to go outdoors where her
niece Elizabeth walked with the young ploughman through the corn, but
was like the bird in the room&mdash;a prisoner. She moved restlessly about.
The bird flew back and forth across the room.  It alighted on the
window sill near the place where the board was broken away. She stared
into the frightened eyes of the bird that in turn stared into her
eyes. Then the bird flew away, out through the window, and Elsie
turned and ran nervously downstairs and out into the yard. She climbed
over the wire fence and ran with stooped shoulders along one of the
tunnels.

</p><p>Elsie ran into the vastness of the cornfields filled with but one
desire. She wanted to get out of her life and into some new and
sweeter life she felt must be hidden away somewhere in the fields.
After she had run a long way she came to a wire fence and crawled
over. Her hair became unloosed and fell down over her shoulders.
Her cheeks became flushed and for the moment she looked like a
young girl. When she climbed over the fence she tore a great
hole in the front of her dress. For a moment her tiny breasts
were exposed and then her hand clutched and held nervously the
sides of the tear. In the distance she could hear the voices of the
boys and the barking of the dogs. A summer storm had been
threatening for days and now black clouds had begun to spread
themselves over the sky. As she ran nervously forward, stopping
to listen and then running on again, the dry corn blades brushed
against her shoulders and a fine shower of yellow dust from the
corn tassels fell on her hair. A continued crackling noise accompanied
<pb n="156"/>


her progress. The dust made a golden crown about her
head. From the sky overhead a low rumbling sound, like the
growling of giant dogs, came to her ears.

</p><p>The thought that having at last ventured into the corn she
would never escape became fixed in the mind of the running
woman. Sharp pains shot through her body. Presently she was
compelled to stop and sit on the ground. For a long time she
sat with her closed eyes. Her dress became soiled. Little insects
that live in the ground under the corn came out of their holes and
crawled over her legs.

</p><p>Following some obscure impulse the tired woman threw herself on
her back and lay still with closed eyes. Her fright passed.  It was
warm and close in the room-like tunnels. The pain in her side went
away. She opened her eyes and between the wide green corn blades could
see patches of a black threatening sky. She did not want to be alarmed
and so closed her eyes again. Her thin hand no longer gripped the tear
in her dress and her tiny breasts were exposed. They expanded and
contracted in little spasmodic jerks. She threw her hands back over
her head and lay still.

</p><p>It seemed to Elsie that hours passed as she lay thus, quiet and
passive under the corn. Deep within her there was a feeling that
something was about to happen, something that would lift her out of
herself, that would tear her away from her past and the past of her
people. Her thoughts were not definite. She lay still and waited as
she had waited for days and months by the rock at the back of the
orchard on the Vermont farm when she was a girl. A deep grumbling
noise went on in the sky overhead but the sky and everything she had
ever known seemed very far away, no part of herself.

</p><p>After a long silence, when it seemed to her that she was lost
from herself as in a dream, Elsie heard a man's voice calling.
"Aho, aho, aho," shouted the voice and after another period of
silence there arose answering voices and then the sound of bodies
crashing through the corn and the excited chatter of children. A
dog came running along the row where she lay and stood beside
her. His cold nose touched her face and she sat up. The dog
ran away. The Leander boys passed. She could see their bare
legs flashing in and out across one of the tunnels. Her brother
had become alarmed by the rapid approach of the thunder storm
<pb n="157"/>


and wanted to get his family to town. His voice kept calling
from the house and the voices of the children answered from the
fields.

</p><p>Elsie sat on the ground with her hands pressed together. An
odd feeling of disappointment had possession of her. She arose
and walked slowly along in the general direction taken by the
children. She came to a fence and crawled over, tearing her dress
in a new place. One of her stockings had become unloosed and
had slipped down over her shoe top. The long sharp weeds had
scratched her leg so that it was criss-crossed with red lines, but
she was not conscious of any pain.

</p><p>The distraught woman followed the children until she came
within sight of her father's house and then stopped and again sat
on the ground. There was another loud crash of thunder and
Tom Leander's voice called again, this time half angrily. The
name of the girl Elizabeth was shouted in loud masculine tones
that rolled and echoed like the thunder along the aisles under the
corn.

</p><p>And then Elizabeth came into sight accompanied by the young
ploughman. They stopped near Elsie and the man took the girl
into his arms. At the sound of their approach Elsie had thrown
herself face downward on the ground and had twisted herself into
a position where she could see without being seen. When their
lips met her tense hands grasped one of the corn stalks. Her lips
pressed themselves into the dust. When they had gone on their
way she raised her head. A dusty powder covered her lips.

</p><p>What seemed another long period of silence fell over the fields.
A strong wind began to blow and the corn rocked back and forth.
The murmuring voices of unborn children, her imagination had
created in the whispering fields, became a vast shout. The wind
blew harder and harder. The corn stalks were twisted and bent.
Elizabeth went thoughfully [sic] out of the field and climbing the fence
confronted her father. "Where you been? What you been a
doing?" he asked. "Don't you know we got to get out of here?"

</p><p>When Elizabeth went toward the house Elsie followed, creeping
on her hands and knees like a little animal, and when she had come
within sight of the fence surrounding the house she sat on the ground
and put her hands over her face. Something within herself was being
twisted and whirled about as the tops of the <pb n="158"/>


corn stalks were now being twisted and whirled by the wind. She
sat so that she did not look toward the house and when she opened
her eyes she could again see along the long mysterious aisles.

</p><p>Her brother, with his wife and children, went away. By turning
her head Elsie could see them driving at a trot out of the yard back
of her father's house. With the going of the younger woman the farm
house in the midst of the cornfield rocked by the winds seemed the
most desolate place in the world.

</p><p>Her mother came out at the back door of the house. She ran to
the steps where she knew her daughter was in the habit of sitting and
then in alarm began to call. It did not occur to Elsie to answer.
The voice of the older woman did not seem to have anything to do with
herself. It was a thin voice and was quickly lost in the wind and in
the crashing sound that arose out of the fields. With her head turned
toward the house Elsie stared at her mother who ran wildly around the
house and then went indoors. The back door of the house went shut with
a bang.

</p><p>The storm that had been threatening broke with a roar. Broad
sheets of water swept over the cornfields. Sheets of water swept over
the woman's body. The storm that had for years been gathering in her
also broke. Sobs arose out of her throat. She abandoned herself to a
storm of grief that was only partially grief.  Tears ran out of her
eyes and made little furrows through the dust on her face. In the
lulls that occasionally came in the storm she raised her head and
heard, through the tangled mass of wet hair that covered her ears and
above the sound of millions of rain-drops that alighted on the earthen
floor inside the house of the corn, the thin voices of her mother and
father calling to her out of the Leander house.  </p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

