<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AndRabb"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="AndRabb">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Rabbit-pen</title>
<title type="sort">rabbit pen</title>
<author>Anderson, Sherwood, 1876-1941</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name>creator of image(s)</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">20</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AndRabb</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475672</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"The Rabbit-pen"</title>
<title type="sort">the rabbit pen</title>
<author>Anderson, Sherwood</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<date value="1914">1914</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Harper's Monthly 129
(July 1914): 207-210.</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1914">1914</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996">Mar. 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jan Horner</name>
</respStmt>
<item>TEI header &amp; footer added.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" id="d3">
	<pb n="207"/>
<head>Anderson, Sherwood.  "The Rabbit-pen." <hi rend="italic">Harper's Monthly</hi> 129
(July 1914): 207-210.  </head>

<p>IN a wire pen beside the gravel path, Fordyce, walking in the
garden of his friend Harkness and imagining marriage, came upon a
tragedy.  A litter of new-born rabbits lay upon the straw scattered
about the pen.  They were blind; they were hairless; they were
blue-black of body; they oscillated their heads in mute appeal.  In
the center of the pen lay one of the tiny things, dead.  Above the
little dead body a struggle went on.  The mother rabbit fought the
father furiously.  A wild fire was in her eyes.  She rushed at the
huge fellow again and again.
</p><p>The man who had written two successful novels stood trembling
in the path.  He saw the father rabbit and the furious little
mother struggling in the midst of the new life scattered about the
pen, and his hands shook and his lips grew white.  He was afraid
that the mother of the litter would be killed in the struggle.  A
cry of sympathy broke from his lips.  "Help here!  Help!  There is
murder being done!" he shouted.
</p><p>Out at the back door of the house came Gretchen, the
housekeeper.  She ran rapidly down the gravel path.  Seeing the
struggle going on in the wire pen, she knelt, and, tearing open a
little door, dragged the father rabbit out of the pen.  In her
strong grasp the father rabbit hung by his ears, huge and
grotesque.  He kicked out with his heels.  Turning, she flung him
through an open window into a child's play-house standing amid the
shrubbery beside the path.
</p><p>Fordyce stood in the path, looking at the little dead rabbit
in the center of the pen.  He thought that it should be taken away,
and wondered how it might be done.  He tried to think of himself
reaching through the little door into the cage and taking the
little blue-black dead thing into his hand; but the housekeeper,
coming from the child's playhouse with a child's shovel in her
hand, reached into the pen and threw the body over the shrubbery
into the vegetable-garden beyond.
</p><p>Fordyce followed her&mdash;the free-walking, straight-backed
Gretchen&mdash;into the stable at the end of the gravel path.  He
heard her talking, in her bold, quick way, to Hans, the stableman.
He wondered what she was saying that made Hans smile.  He sat on a
chair by the stable door, watching her as she walked back to the
house.
</p><p>Hans, the stableman, finished the righting of things in the
home of the rabbits.  The tragedy was effaced; the dead rabbit
buried among the cabbages in the garden.  Into the wire pen Hans
put fresh, new straw.  Fordyce wondered what Gretchen had said to
Hans in that language.  He was overcome by her efficiency.  "She
knew what to do, and yet, no doubt, like me, she knew nothing of
rabbits," he thought, lost in wonder.
</p><p>Hans came back into the stable and began again polishing the
trimmings of a harness hanging on the wall.  "He was trying to kill
the young males," he explained in broken English.
</p><p>Fordyce told Harkness of the affair of the rabbit-pen.  "She
was magnificent," he said.  "She saved all of that new life while
I stood by, trembling and impotent.  I went up to my room and sat
thinking of her.  She should be spending her days caring for new
life, making it fine and purposeful, and not be counting sheets and
wrangling with the iceman for an old, worn-out newspaper hack like
you."
</p><p>Joe Harkness had laughed.  "Same old sentimental, susceptible
Frank," he had shouted, joyously.  "Romancing about every woman you
see, but keeping well clear of them, just the same."

</p><p>Sitting on the wide veranda in the late afternoon, Fordyce
read a book.  He <pb n="208"/>  was alone, so it was his own book.  As he
read, he wondered that so many thousands of people had failed to
buy and appreciate it.  Between paragraphs he became entangled in
one of his own fancies&mdash;the charming fancies that never became
realities.  He imagined himself the proud husband of Gretchen, the
housekeeper.
</p><p>Fordyce was always being a proud husband.  Scarcely a week
passed without the experience.  It was satisfying and complete.  He
felt now that he had never been prouder husband to a more beautiful
or more capable woman than Gretchen.  Gretchen was complete.  She
was a Brunnhilde.  Her fine face, crowned by thick, smooth hair,
and her quiet, efficient manner, brought a thrill of pride.  He saw
himself getting off the train in the evening at some Chicago suburb
and walking through the shady streets to the frame house where
Gretchen waited at the door.
</p><p>Glancing up, his eyes rested on the wide emerald lawn.  In the
shrubbery, Hans, the stableman, worked with a pair of pruning-shears.  Fordyce began thinking of the master of the house and its
mistress, Ruth&mdash;the brown-eyed, soft-voiced Ruth with the boyish
freckles.  Joe, comrade of the struggling newspaper days, was
married to pretty Ruth and her fortune, and went off to meetings of
directors in the city, as he had done this afternoon.  "Good old
Joe," thought Fordyce, with a wave of tenderness.  "For him no more
uncertainties, no more heartaches."
</p><p>From the nursery at the top of the house came the petulant
voices of the children.  They were refusing to be off to bed at the
command of their mother, refusing to be quiet, as they had been
refusing her commands all afternoon.  They romped and shouted in
the nursery, throwing things about.  Fordyce could hear the clear,
argumentative voice of the older boy.
</p><p>"Don't be obstinate, mother," said the boy; "we will be quiet
after a while."
</p><p>The man sitting on the veranda could picture the gentle
mother.  She would be standing in the doorway of the nursery&mdash;the
beautiful children's room with the pictures of ships on the walls&mdash;
and there would be the vague, baffled uncertain look in her eyes.
She would be trying to make herself severe and commanding, and the
children would be defying her.  The listening man closed his book
with a bang.  A shiver of impatience ran through him.  "Damn!" he
said, swiftly.  "Damn!"
</p><p>From below-stairs came the sharp clicking sound of footsteps.
A voice, firm and purposeful, called up to the nursery.
<hi rend="italic">"Schweig!"</hi> commanded the voice of Gretchen, the housekeeper.
</p><p>Above-stairs all became quiet.  The mother, coming slowly
down, joined Fordyce on the veranda.  They sat together discussing
books.  They talked of the work of educators among children.
</p><p>"I can do nothing with my own children," said Ruth Harkness.
"They look to that Gretchen for everything."
</p><p>In the house Fordyce could hear the housekeeper moving about,
up and down the stairs, and in and out of the living room; he could
see her through the windows and the open doors.  She went about
silently, putting the house in order.  Above in the nursery all was
peace and quiet.

</p><p>Fordyce stayed on as a guest at Cottesbrooke, finishing his
third book.  With him stayed Gretchen, putting the house in order
for the winter; Harkness, with Ruth, the two boys and the servants,
had gone to the city home.  It was autumn, and the brown leaves
went dancing through the bare shrubbery on the lawn.  In his
overcoat Frank now sat on the veranda and looked at the hurrying
leaves.  He was being one of the leaves.
</p><p>"I am dead and brown and without care, and that is I now being
blown by the wind across the dead grass," he told himself.
</p><p>At the end of the veranda, near the carriage entrance, stood
his trunk.  His brown bag was by his feet.
</p><p>Out through the door of the house came Gretchen.  She stood by
the railing at the edge of the veranda, talking.  "I am not
satisfied with this family," she said.  "I shall be leaving them.
There is too much money."
</p><p>She turned, waving her hand and talking vehemently.  "It is of
no account to save," she declared.  "I am <pb n="209"/>  best at the
saving.  In this house all summer I have made the butter for the
table from cream that has spoiled.  Things were wasted in the
kitchen and I have stopped that.  It has passed unnoticed.  I know
every sheet, every towel.  Is it appreciated?  Master Harkness and
mistress&mdash;they do not know that I know, and do not care.  The sour
cream they would see thrown to the pig.  Uh!&mdash;It is of no use to be
saving here."
</p><p>Fordyce thought that he was near to being a real husband.  It
came into his mind to spring from his chair and beseech this frugal
woman to come and save the soured cream in a frame house in a
Chicago suburb.  While he hesitated, she turned and disappeared
into the house.  <hi rend="italic">"Auf Wiedersehen!"</hi> she called to him over
her shoulder.
</p><p>He went along the veranda and climbed into the carriage.  He
went slowly, looking back at the door through which she had
disappeared.  He was thinking of the day in the green summer when
he had stood in the gravel path by the wire rabbit-pen, watching
her straighten out the affair in the family of the rabbits.  As on
that day, he now felt strangely impotent and incapable.  "I should
be taking things into my own hands," he reflected, while Hans drove
the carriage along the road under the bare trees.

</p><p>Now it was February, with the snow lying piled along the edges
of the city streets.  Sitting in the office of his friend Harkness,
Fordyce, looking through the window, could see the lake, blue and
cold and lonely.
</p><p>Fordyce turned from the window to his friend, at work among
the letters on the desk.  "It is of no avail to look sternly and
forbiddingly at me," he said.  "I will not go away.  I have sold
the book I wrote at your house, and have money in my pocket.  Now
I will take you to dine with me, and after the dinner I will get on
a train and start on a trip to Germany.  There is a reason why I
should learn to speak the German language.  I hear housekeepers
talking to stablemen about the doings of rabbits in pens, and it
gets into my mind that I don't know what they say.  They may
whisper secrets of life in that language.  I have a wish to know
everything, and I shall begin by knowing the German language.
Perhaps I shall get me a wife over there and come home a proud and
serious husband.  It would be policy for you to drop letter-signing
and come to dine with me while yet I am a free man."
</p><p>In the restaurant they had come to the cigars, and Harkness
was talking of life in his house.  He was talking intimately, as a
man talks only to one who is near and dear to him.
</p><p>"I have been unhappy," said Harkness.  "A struggle has gone on
in which I have lost."
</p><p>His friend said nothing.  Putting down his cigar, he fingered
the thin stem of the glass that sat before him.
</p><p>"In Germany I engaged Gretchen," said Harkness, talking
rapidly.  "I got her for the management of our house and for the
boys.  They were unruly, and Ruth could do nothing with them.  Also
we thought it would be well for them to know the German language.
</p><p>"In our house, after we got Gretchen, peace came.  The boys
stayed diligently at their lessons.  When in the school-room at the
top of the house they were unruly, Gretchen came to the foot of the
stairs, <hi rend="italic">'Schweig!'</hi> she shouted, and they were intent upon
their lessons.
</p><p>"In the house Gretchen went about quietly.  She did the work
of the house thoroughly.  When I came home in the evening the toys
of the children no longer were scattered about underfoot.  They
were gathered into the boxes put into the nursery for the purpose.
</p><p>"Our two boys sat quietly with us at the evening meal.  When
they had been well-mannered they looked for approval to Gretchen,
who talked to them in German.  Ruth did not speak German.  She sat
at the table, looking at the boys and at Gretchen.  She was unhappy
in her own home, but I did not know why.
</p><p>"One evening when the boys had gone up-stairs with Gretchen
she turned to me, saying intensely, 'I <hi rend="italic">hate</hi> German!'  I
thought her over-tired.  'You should see a physician for the
nerves,' I said.
</p><p>"And then came Christmas.  It was a German Christmas with
German cakes and a tree for each of the boys.  Gretchen and I had
planned it one evening when Ruth was in bed with a headache.
<pb n="210"/>
</p><p>"The gifts on our Christmas trees were magnificent.  They were
a surprise to me.  Ruth and I had not believed in costly gifts, and
now Ruth had loaded the trees with them.  The trees were filled
with toys, costly mechanical toys for each of our two boys.  With
them she had planned to win the boys.
</p><p>"The boys were beside themselves with joy.  They ran about the
room shouting.  They played with the elaborate toys upon the floor.
</p><p>"Ruth took the gifts from the trees.  In the shadow by the
door stood Gretchen.  She was silent.  When the boys got the
packages from the trees they ran to her, shouting, <hi rend="italic">'Mach' es
auf!  Mach' es auf!  Tante Gretchen!'</hi>
</p><p>"I was happy.  I thought we were having a beautiful Christmas.
The annoyance I had felt at the magnificence of Ruth's gifts passed
away.
</p><p>"And then, in one moment, the struggle that had smoldered
under the surface of the lives of the two women in my house burst
forth.  Ruth, my gentle Ruth, ran out into the middle of the floor,
shouting in a shrill, high voice, 'Who is mother here?  Whose
children are these?'
</p><p>"The two boys clung to the dress of Gretchen.  They were
frightened and cried.  Gretchen went out of the room, taking them
with her.  I could hear her quick, firm footsteps on the stairs.
</p><p>"Gretchen put the two boys into their white beds in the
nursery.  At her word they ceased weeping.
</p><p>"In the center of the room they had left, lighted only by the
little electric bulbs in the branches of the Christmas trees, stood
Ruth.  She stood in silence, looking at the floor, and trembling.
</p><p>"I looked at the door through which our boys had gone at the
command of Gretchen.  I did not look at Ruth.  A flame of
indignation burned in me.  I felt that I should like to take her by
the shoulders and shake her."
</p><p>Fordyce had never seen his friend so moved.  Since his visit
to Cottesbrooke he had been thinking of his old comrade as a man in
a safe harbor&mdash;one peacefully becalmed behind the breakwater of
Ruth and her fortune, passing his days untroubled, secure in his
happiness.
</p><p>"My Ruth is wonderful," declared Harkness, breaking in on
these reflections.  "She is all love and truth.  To me she had been
more dear than life.  We have been married all these years and
still like a lover I dream of her at night.  Sometimes I get out of
bed and creep into her room, and, kneeling there in the darkness,
I kiss the strands of her hair that lie loose upon the pillow.
</p><p>"I do not understand why it is not with our boys as it is with
me," he said simply.  "To myself I say, 'Her love should conquer
all.'"
</p><p>Before the mind of Fordyce was a different picture&mdash;the
picture of a strong, straight-backed woman running down a gravel
path to a wire rabbit-pen.  He saw her reach through the door, and,
taking the father rabbit by the ears, throw him through the window
of the child's play-house.  "She could settle the trouble in the
rabbit's pen," he thought, "but this was another problem."
</p><p>Harkness talked again.  "I went to where Ruth stood trembling
and took her in my arms," he said.  "I made up my mind that I would
send Gretchen back to Germany.  It was my love for Ruth that had
made my life.  In a flash I saw how she had been crowded out of her
place in her own home by that able, quiet, efficient woman."
</p><p>Harkness turned his face away from the eyes of his friend.
"She lay in my arms and I ran my hand over her hot little head," he
said.  'I couldn't keep it back any longer, Joe; I couldn't help
saying it,' she cried.  'I have been a child, and I have lost a
fight.  If you will let me, I will try now to be a woman and a
mother.'"
</p><p>Fordyce took his eyes from the face of his friend.  For relief
he had been feeding an old fancy.  He saw himself walking up a
gravel path to the door of a German house.  The house would be in
a village, and there would be formal flower-pots by the side of the
gravel path.
</p><p>"To what place in Germany did she go, this Gretchen?" he
demanded.
</p><p>Harkness shook his head.  "She married Hans, the stableman,
and they went away together," he said.  "In my house the mechanical
toys from the Christmas tree lie about underfoot.  We are planning
to send our boys to a private school.  They are pretty hard to
control."
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
