<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AndRuss"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;


]>

<TEI.2 id="AndRuss">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">To the Russian Soldier</title>
<title type="sort">to the russian soldier</title>
<author>Andreyev, Leonid</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">10</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AndRuss</idno>
<date value="1998">1998</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1998 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475673</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">To the Russian Soldier</title>
<title level="j">The Yale Review, Vol. VII, No. 2 (Jan. 1918)</title>
<title type="sort">to the russian soldier</title>
<author>Leonid Andreyev</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
<name>Wilbur L. Cross</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 225-228</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Yale Publishing Association, Inc.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New Haven, Connecticut</pubPlace>
<date value="1918">1918</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVA Library call number AP2 .Y2 v.7 1917-18</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1918">1918</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1998-05">May, 1998</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Carol Osborne, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI tags and header</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="article" id="d3">
	<pb n="225"/>
<head>TO THE RUSSIAN SOLDIER<lb/>
By LEONID ANDR&Eacute;EV</head>

<p>SOLDIER, what hast thou been under Nicholas the Secone?
Thou hast been a slave of the autocrat.  Conscience,
honor, love for the people, were beaten out of thee in
merciless training by whip and stick.
</p><p>"Kill thy father and thy mother if they raise their hands
against me," commanded the autocrat, &mdash; and thou becamest
a parricide.
</p><p>"Kill thy brother and thy sister, thy dearest friend and
everyone who raises a hand against me," commanded the
autocrat, &mdash; and thou didst kill thy brother and thy dearest
friend, and becamest like Cain, shedding the blood of
thy kin.
</p><p>When the gray coats appeared in the streets and the rifles
and bayonets glittered &mdash; we knew what that meant: it was
death stalking!  It meant death to those innocent and
hungry ones who thirsted for brighter life and raised their
voices bravely against the tyrant.  It meant death, destruction,
peril, tears, and horror.  Thou wast terrible, Soldier!
</p><p>But thou wast brave in the field, Russian Soldier. . . .
Thou wast a martyr, but thou wast never a traitor, nor a
coward, Soldier!
</p><p>The Russian people loved thee secretly for this and waited
for thy awakening. . . .  They called to thee: "Come to us,

   <pb n="226"/>

beloved brother!  Come to thy people.  The people are
waiting for thee!"
</p><p>Soldier, what hast thou been in the days of the Revolution?
</p><p>Thou hast been our love, our happiness, our pride.  We
did not know as yet who thou wast.  We were still in dread
of the gray coats, we still mistrusted the dashing cossacks.
And dost thou remember, Soldier, how the heart of the
people leaped when the first blow of the cossack's sabre fell
not on the head of his brother but on that of the
policeman-executioner?  Dost thou remember it?
</p><p>But still we were not able to believe.  Already our hearts
were overcome with joy, happiness took our breath away,
but still we did not believe.  How is it possible to believe all
at once in freedom?
</p><p>Yet the soldiers are bringing it with them!  They are
coming, stalwart, brave, beautiful, in their armed power.
They are coming to give their life for freedom.  As yet they
themselves do not know whether they are all awakened.  The
Tsar's hirelings shoot at them from the roofs and from
behind street corners.  The soldiers expect only death, yet
they are coming, stalwart, brave, beautiful!
</p><p>Then we believed them.  The throne of the Romanovs
cracked with a noise heard throughout the world.  For the
first time in our life soldiers' bullets sang a new song &mdash; not
the song of death, of shame, and of degradation, but the
wonderful song of freedom and of joy. . . .
</p><p>And what hast thou become now, Soldier?
</p><p>When cursing, drunken, thou didst come tearing down
peaceful streets in thy automobiles, threatening women and
children with guns, bragging, debauching, swearing the
basest of oaths &mdash; didst thou hear the answer of the people?
"Be accursed!  Be accursed!"  Thou didst shoot in mad
frenzy, and the people yelled fearlessly to thee: "Be
accursed!"

   <pb n="227"/>

</p><p>Scoundrel!  With quick-firing guns didst thou threaten;
yet invalids, old men, and women grabbed at thy rifle with
their bare hands and tore it away from thee.  And thou
didst give it away, overcome with shame, helpless, sweating,
ugly.
</p><p>Soldier!  How many didst thou kill in those days?  How
many orphans hast thou made?  How many bereaved
mothers hast thou left inconsolable?  Dost thou hear the
words that their lips whisper?  The lips from which thou
hast banished forever the smile of happiness? &mdash; "Murderer,
Murderer!"
</p><p>But what of mothers?  What of orphans?  A moment
came unforeseen and still more terrible.  Thou hast betrayed
Russia.  Thou hast thrown thy native land that nourished
thee under the feet of the enemy, thou Soldier, our sole
defense!
</p><p>Everything is entrusted to thee: the life and welfare of
Russia; our fields and forests; our peaceful rivers; our
villages and cities; our temples and those who are praying
in them.
</p><p>And all this thou hast betrayed, Soldier! &mdash; the quiet fields,
and the young, buoyant liberty.  Behind thy back grain
was ripening in the fields &mdash; Russia's sacred treasury; now
the Germans will reap it.  Under thy protection the people
were working in their villages; now they are running along
all the highways, leaving dead in their wake.  Children and
old men are weeping &mdash; they have no roof over their heads,
no home, only death staring into their faces.
</p><p>Ah! how thou didst run from the enemy, Russian Soldier!
Never before has the world seen such a rout, such a mob of
traitors.  It knew the one Judas, while here were tens of
thousands of Judases running past each other, galloping,
throwing down rifles, quarrelling, and still boasting of their
"meetings."  What are they hurrying for?  They hurry to
betray their native land.  They do not even wait for the

   <pb n="228"/>

Germans to shoot, so great is their haste to betray Russia,
so ready are they to deliver her almost by force into the hands
of the astounded enemy.
</p><p>And what hast thou done to thy officers, Soldier?  See,
what piles of them lie in the fields appealing to the all-merciful
and all-forgiving God with their still, sightless eyes!
They called thee &mdash; thou didst not obey.  They went alone to
their death &mdash; and they died.  They died, Soldier!
</p><p>And what hast thou done to thy comrades?  Traitor!
Dost thou see their bodies?  Dost thou see the ditches where
careless German hands have thrown them?  It is thou who
didst kill them!
</p><p>But look ahead of thee, Soldier!  Dost thou see that terrible
structure that is being erected in Russia?
</p><p>It is the scaffold.
</p><p>And for whom is it?  For thee, Soldier!  For thee, traitor
and coward, who hast betrayed Russia and her liberty.  Thou
seest, but thou dost not understand as yet.  Thou dost not
understand our sorrow.
</p><p>Was Russia not happy in having destroyed the scaffold
as it seemed forever, and in giving its accursed memory to
oblivion.  But now it grows again, unwelcome, sinister, evil,
like the shadows of night.
</p><p>Thou hast torn the body of Russia.  Now thou desirest
to tear her heart and soul &mdash; thou, Soldier.
</p><p>Thou, Soldier, whom we loved and whom we still love.
</p><p>Arise! &mdash; Look at thy country which is calling in distress.
</p><p>Awake! &mdash; If cruel fate has no laurels of victory in store
for thee, put the crown of thorns on thy head.  Through it
thou shalt find expiation, through it thou shalt regain our
love.
</p><p>Russia is dying, Russia is calling to thee:
</p><p>"Arise, dear Soldier!"</p>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

