<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="Ano1Wha"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="Ano1Wha">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">About Mrs. Wharton, in "Chronicle and Comment"</title>
<title type="sort">about mrs wharton, in chronicle and comment</title>
<author>Wharton review: Anonymous</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">9</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">Ano1Wha</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475675</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">About Mrs. Wharton, in "Chronicle and Comment"</title>
<title level="j">The Bookman</title>
<title type="sort">about mrs wharton, in chronicle and comment</title>
<author>Wharton review: Anonymous</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>Volume 16, Number 1</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>11-12.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Dodd Mead &amp; Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1902-09">September 1902</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Copy consulted: UVA Library call number AP2 .B78</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions
for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1902">1902</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-05">May 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Catherine Tousignant</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">
<div1 type="bio" id="d3"><pb n="11" id="Ano1Wha11"/>
<head>About Mrs. Wharton. </head>

<p>According to certain chroniclers in the daily press, Mrs. Wharton
is going to write no more long novels, but will devote herself to
serious historical composition.  We are glad that she has abjured long
novels, but deplore her intention of becoming an historian.  There are
scores of historians busily at work, many of them very good ones, but
where shall we find another writer who could give us such remarkable
work as that contained in <hi rend="italic">The Greater Inclination?</hi> It is pure
perversity to give up doing the thing that one can do best in order to
waste time over that which many others can do better.  We have a
certain right to speak out frankly on this subject, because we were
among the very first to greet Mrs. Wharton as a writer of very rare
gifts and of unusual distinction.

</p><p>Her <hi rend="italic">Valley of Decision</hi> was only a <hi rend="italic">succes
d'estime</hi>, written beautifully in parts and with some brilliant
episodes, yet not a book that compelled one to read it to the end.
The conception of it was large and spacious&mdash;in fact, too much so
for any woman to carry out successfully.  Only a man, and very much
of a man, ever has grip enough and mental muscularity enough for
such a thing as that.

</p><p>What has most interested us in <hi rend="italic">The Valley of Decision</hi>
is the illustration which it affords of a fact upon which we are
given to harping&mdash;the fact that a writer's best work finds most
critics and book reviewers afraid to praise it, because they have
no real minds of their own.  Later, when the work in question has
made its way into favour, they all get out their vocabulary of
praise and dump it upon the writer's next production&mdash;which may not
be more than fair to middling.  Witness the case of Mrs. Wharton.
Her <hi rend="italic">Greater Inclination</hi>, which was most remarkable, obtained
only meagre and neutral notice from the chuckle-heads of criticism.
Then their mistake gradually became obvious even to themselves, and
so they thought to make up for it by going into spasms of
admiration over <hi rend="italic">The Valley of Decision</hi>, which is by no means
remarkable at all.  The belated and sapient dicta about Mrs.
Wharton's "well-known charm of style," her "distinguished touch"
and all that sort of thing were, under the circumstances, both
amusing and exasperating.

</p><p>Some time ago a correspondent wrote to ask us why Mrs. Wharton
called her first book of stories <hi rend="italic">The Greater Inclination</hi>.  We
didn't answer that letter at the time, because we were too busy to
deal with it satisfactorily; but now we are going to dispose of it
once for all.  Our correspondent (a lady) says that she has long
wanted to know this thing, but has never yet felt like asking any one,
because she has heard so many persons speak scornfully of those who
are unable to understand the pertinence of the title.  This makes us
smile sardonically.  The truth is that no one really knows what Mrs.
Wharton meant by it, but every one is afraid to say so.  Hence,
whenever a literary conversation is started up and this particular
topic seems likely to arise, some one present always comments with a
superior smile on the fact that there actually exist persons who don't
see the point of Mrs. Wharton's title.  Then all the company laugh a
forced and guilty laugh, as if to say:  "Really?  Is any one so stupid
as not to see <hi rend="italic">that?</hi>" If somebody would
only get up and say: "Well! what <hi rend="italic">>is</hi> the
point?" it would be the biggest sort of a bombshell.  Hundreds, nay,
thousands, of literary clubs would be dissipated for all eternity if
only one member in each had the courage to ask that question.  But
nobody, so far, has ever had the courage, and the game of bluff has
continued successfully, lo, these several years.

</p><p>Probably Mrs. Wharton, when she called her book of stories
collectively <hi rend="italic">The Greater Inclination</hi> had vaguely in mind the
notion that the greater inclination&mdash;that which is really greater&mdash;
always in  <pb n="12" id="Ano1Wha12"/>  the end prevails.  You may not yourself
be always conscious of what it is that you most want&mdash;you mistrust
your own motives and desires&mdash;yet your final, decisive action is
determined by the secret, subliminal, subtle preference which tips the
scale in its own favour every time.  This rather indefinite title
fitted most of the stories in Mrs. Wharton's book.  It would also fit
the great majority of all the stories ever written&mdash;for it is
difficult to write any story which does not in some way bring in the
play of motive and the conflict of desire.  <hi rend="italic">Crucial Instances</hi>
also applies to most narratives of human life.  <hi rend="italic">The Touchstone</hi>
would have been a good title for the novel which Mrs. Wharton actually
called <hi rend="italic">The Valley of Decision</hi>; and <hi rend="italic">The Valley of
Decision</hi> would have fitted the story of <hi rend="italic">The Touchstone</hi>
perfectly.  Hence, all of Mrs. Wharton's titles might have been
shuffled and dealt over in a new order to her different books; for
each one fits every other book just as well as it does the book to
which she gave it.  So let our correspondent cheer up and not be
intimidated by supercilious bluffers any more.
</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

