<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AnoCrop"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="AnoCrop">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Watching the Crops</title>
<title type="sort">watching the crops</title>
<author>Anonymous</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">13</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AnoCrop</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475680</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Watching the Crops</title>
<title type="sort">watching the crops</title>
<author>Anonymous</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harper's Weekly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1890-10-04">4 Oct. 1890</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 34</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 770-771</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1890">1890</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-08">August 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>minimal TEI tagging</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">



<div1 type="article" id="d3"><pb n="770"/>
<head>"Watching the Crops."</head>


<p>THE members of civilized and artificially organized
communities, who buy their food at markets, can gain from their own
experience but little idea of the watchful and anxious interest
attending the care of growing crops by those populations who must
depend directly upon the product of their fields for subsistence.
To the inhabitants of purely agricultural districts a loss of the
annual harvest means deprivation, and perhaps hunger and famine;
and naturally they have a constant realization of the fact that the
welfare of their whole community is bound up in the promise of the
heading wheat and tasselling corn.  Between seed-time and harvest
the husbandman's task is an incessant and arduous one.  Weeds must
be kept down, every means of diminishing the ill effects of drought
or of over-moisture must be adopted, the danger from floods
obviated as far as possible, and vigilant guard kept that marauders
shall not deprive him of the reward of his labors.
</p><p>One of these conditions requisite for security supplies the
motive of Mr. Charles Graham's drawing depicting a characteristic
bit of New Mexico life.  The landscape features of the scene
present an aspect not dissimilar to certain parts of Egypt, Syria,
and Palestine.  There is the same clear air, high lights, and wide
desert spaces bounded by plateaus and sand hills, and winding
through the flat sandy valley, a silver stretch of river, its banks
bordered by occasional trees &mdash; in New Mexico sycamores and cotton-woods &mdash; growing singly and in clumps.  The low, flat-roofed, thick-walled houses of sun-baked brick, of tints akin to the soil, add to
this impression, and the Oriental aspect of the country is
sustained in many of the structures, implements, and customs of its
people.  In the open fields are the threshing-floors of beaten
clay, upon which sheep, goats, or asses trample the wheat from the
straw, and the grain is afterward winnowed by the process of
tossing it from blankets into the air; and in secluded communities
the juice yet is trodden from the grape in rawhide tubs by the
naked feet of men and women, and fermented into wine in great
<hi rend="italic">ollas</hi>, or earthen jars as large as barrels.  In these by-places,
oxen, as in patriarchal times, draw the wooden one-handled plough
or creaking cumbrous wooden cart by means of yokes stretched across
their horns.
</p><p>On eminences overlooking the New Mexico valleys, within
available distance of some stream or large spring, stand the
singular-looking towns of the Pueblo Indians, in which the houses
of the compact blocks are built with stories rising one above the
other in terrace fashion.  At some distance from each of these
pueblos, on valley lands &mdash; located not too near the bottoms, where
floods might ravage them &mdash; are the fields, orchards, and vineyards
belonging to these quaint townsfolk.  The main acequia, or
irrigating canal, its banks hidden in places by drooping osier-willows, conveys water from the distant river along the hill-sides,
up which to the inexperienced eye it seems actually to climb to the
fields; there, by means of small ditches and embankments, it is
distributed over the surface, transforming the barren reddish loam
or gray sand into areas of inexhaustible fertility.  The beauty of
these oases of green fields, orchards, and vineyards, revealed in
contrast with the boundless surrounding desert, is exceeding.
</p><p>The Indians, for the most part, cultivate their lands in a
communal way.  Their system of apportionment of labor, and the
return of its products to the separate households, is one little
understood by outsiders, but seemingly perfectly satisfactory to
themselves.  Among this people, however, by time-honored custom,
some families hold, each in its own right, a special tract, with
its vines, fruit trees, and patches of tillage.
</p><p>But in these Arcadian precincts, no less than in other rural
communities in all places and times, the "foxes that destroy the
vines" are not absent, and must be guarded against, lest the
husbandman be deprived of the fruits of his labor.  The enemies to
his crops in this region are vagrant domestic animals, which,
disregarding the trifling brush fences or low mud walls that
enclose the fields, delight to break into these inviting confines
to trample and devour.  The birds of the air come in multitudes to
carry away the grain and peck and scratch the fruit.  Worst of all
are the <hi rend="italic">ladrones</hi> &mdash; thieves of the human species &mdash; who come with
bags and baskets to despoil the vineyards and orchards.  The visits
of all these marauders must be anticipated, and measures taken to
prevent their depredations.
</p><p>Hence the visitor to New Mexico often sees in the midst of
fields, apart from the houses of the Indian towns, watching
stations standing in situations that command a complete view and
easy access to every part of the tract.  From these stations a
sentinel guards the crops from the beginning of their time of
ripening until the harvest season has ended.  These structures
sometimes are scaffolds upon which is a shelter, but usually they
consist of an adobe house of one room, upon the flat roof of which
upright forked poles support an awning of leafy branches that
protect the watcher from the sun.  Such outposts form a picturesque
feature of these ancient fields, some of which tracts have been
under constant cultivation for hundreds of years, their soil,
enriched annually with the deposit from the muddy water turned over
them in the process of irrigation, showing no signs of
impoverishment.
</p><p>The house stations commonly belong to individual Indians
having lands of their own, who at the beginning of the farming
season leave their homes in the town, and move with their families
into these summer abodes, and there dwell in sight of the domain
which they cultivate until the gathering of the crops has been
completed.  Upon the roof of the station shown in the picture, the
Indian crouching, wrapped in his coarse wide-barred blanket, has
just taken his place to serve as sentinel over the productive
vineyard before him.  Crouched motionless, his gun at hand &mdash; which
he will not be slow to use on any human trespasser &mdash; his watchful
eye surveys the tract that he has to guard, and notes

<pb n="771"/>
everything that moves in the broad expanse beyond, while the Indian
whom he has relieved takes his departure.  Through day and night
these patient watchers attend the growth and ripening in their
order of the wheat and barley, the beans, melons, squashes, Chili
peppers, and the apricots, peaches, apples, and grapes, until all
of these products have been harvested.  With the husking of the
Indian corn, the last crop to be gathered &mdash; a work performed amid
laughter and merry-making by all the people of the village &mdash; there
comes the harvest feast, the time of the greatest rejoicing of the
year.
</p><p>To this lonely watcher upon the housetop what thoughts may
come during his long vigils of the past glories of his race, the
history of which as a civilized people stretches back into the
mists of American mythology!  What stirring of hereditary impulses,
what satisfaction to the soul may he feel during his long watches,
the instinctive aptitude for which has become part of his being
through his descent from ancestors that so guarded their fields in
the days of the Toltec and Aztec migrations southward through New
Mexico to the vale of Anahuac!  Does he brood over the dark story
of the wrongs to his race perpetrated by the victorious mail-clad
Spaniards that in past centuries conquered and so long oppressed
his people; whose black-robed priests imposed upon them a religious
observance alien to the glowing sun-worship of his forefathers?  No
one outside the councils of the tribe can fathom the thoughts and
deeper feelings of this reserved and mysterious people, educated
under sorrows into the policy of a profound secretiveness.  Who can
tell what superstitious meaning he attaches to the wonderful
highway, the existence of which is denoted by the distant scream of
the railway locomotive dashing past his pueblo over the rails that
have bound the country in bands of iron?  To his simple mind what
voice of spirit powers passes along the wires that carry the
lightning messages from city to city across the space that
comprises all the world he knows?
</p><p>But this he realizes, that the years have seen the power of
his Spanish oppressors fade and fall to naught in his land, and
have restored to his people a freedom as great as ever they enjoyed
in the best of the old days.  Within the tract, usually four square
leagues, in which each pueblo stands, the inhabitants have
virtually the control of their own affairs, independent of any
other authority, and in his city there are enjoyed greater
municipal privileges than are possessed by the citizens of any
other civilized community on earth.  After the days of the
Inquisition the Pueblo Indians possessed, even under Spanish and
Mexican rule, a great measure of independence and liberty.  The
coming of the English-speaking race from Eastern regions unknown to
his simple geography brought him no menace, but rather greater
safety, for they confirmed his old Spanish charters of domain, and
secured him the undisturbed possession of his lands.
</p><p>But the race is a dying race, which has nearly lived out its
time, and slowly and not unhappily is passing away.  The 9200
inhabitants of the pueblos in New Mexico of ten years ago are shown
by the present census to be only 8278, and this decrease has taken
place without the occurrence of any unusual epidemic among the
tribes and without war.  Unassimilating with the whites, except in
the way of hospitable usage and friendly business intercourse,
holding to the last their proud seclusion, city after city, like
Pecos and Cuyamonge will gradually become empty of their
inhabitants, until of their habitations none shall be left, and
heaps of adobe ruins and shattered walls alone remain to mark the
long history of this most picturesque and interesting people.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
