<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AnoEngl"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOgrk1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-grk1.ent"> %ISOgrk1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;


]>


<TEI.2 id="AnoEngl">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">English Views of Stephen Crane.</title>
<title type="sort">english views of stephen crane</title>
<author>Crane review: Anonymous</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">10</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AnoEngl</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475682</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>The print version was not illustrated.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">English Views of Stephen Crane.</title>
<title>The Literary Digest, no. 21, 1900.</title>
<title type="sort">english views of stephen crane</title>
<author>Crane review: Anonymous</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition.</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Funk &amp; Wagnalls Company.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Literary Digest</hi> 21 (1900): 12.</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
<language id="el">Greek</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-01">January 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Deirdre Johnson, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header and basic TEI markup.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
<pb n="12" id="AnoEngl12"/>

<head>                  ENGLISH VIEWS OF STEPHEN CRANE.</head>
<p>
THE late Mr. Stephen Crane was, as is well known, much more of a
prophet in England than in his own country, and during his latter
years he found it pleasant to make his home in a land where his
work met with such warm appreciation.  Since his death, the English
critical journals have with little or no exception expressed a high
judgment of his literary abilities.  <hi rend="italic">The Academy</hi> (June 9)
says: </p>

<p>"'The Red Badge of Courage' was published when he was twenty-five.  This study of the psychological side of war, of its effect
on a private soldier, justly won for him immediate recognition.
Critics of all schools united in praise of that remarkable book,
and the more wonderful did the performance appear when it became
known that he had never seen a battle, that the whole was evolved
from his imagination, fed by a long and minute study of military
history.  It is said that when he returned from the Graeco-Turkish
war he remarked to a friend: 'The Red Badge is all right.'  It was
all right.
</p><p>"The same swift and unerring characterization, the same keen
vision into the springs of motives, the same vivid phrasing, marked
'George's Mother.'  Here, as in most of his other stories, and in
all his episodes, the environment grows round the characters.  He
takes them at some period of emotional or physical stress, and,
working from within outward, with quick, firm touches, vivifies
them into life.  Nowhere is this more evident than in the short
sketches and studies that were, probably, after 'The Red Badge of
Courage,' the real expression of his genius.  His longer novels,
tho not wanting in passages that show him at his best, suggest that
in time he would have returned to the earlier instinct that
prompted him to work upon a small canvas.
</p><p>"As a writer he was very modern.  He troubled himself little
about style or literary art.  But&mdash;rare gift&mdash;he saw for himself,
and, like Mr. Steevens, he knew in a flash just what was essential
to bring the picture vividly to the reader.  His books are full of
images and similes that not only fulfil their purpose of the
moment, but live in the memory afterward.  A super-refined literary
taste might object to some of his phrases&mdash;to such a sentence as
this, for example: 'By the very last star of truth, it is easier to
steal eggs from under a hen than it was to change seats in the
dingey,' to his colloquialisms, to the slang with which he peppers
the talk of his men&mdash;but that was the man who looked at things with
his own eyes, and was unafraid of his prepossessions.  His gift of
presenting the critical or dramatic moments in the lives of men and
women was supreme.  We could give a hundred examples."</p>

<p>Referring to "The Red Badge of Courage," <hi rend="italic">The Westminster
Gazette</hi> (June 5) says:

</p><p>"The whole work was the outcome of an intensely vivid
imagination joined with exhaustive study of all available documents
and expressed as to its literary form in language which, if
occasionally over-labored, was for the most part picturesque and
powerful to the last degree.  Mr. Crane's indebtedness to Kipling
was not difficult to detect, while Bret Harte and Mark Twain were
other writers suggested by certain qualities of his work.  Perhaps
we may reproduce in this connection what was said in this journal
concerning another example of Mr. Stephen Crane's work&mdash;the volume
of sketches and studies, to wit, entitled 'The Open Boat.'  Mr.
Crane, it was observed, is chiefly concerned to study character at
special moments of stress and emotion, to depict a scene as it
flashed on his imagination, regardless of anything that came before
or anything that is to follow after.  The men in 'The Open Boat,'
who through a livelong night are in momentary terror of being
swamped, all the while seeing themselves and each other with that
peculiar intensity of vision which accompanies an acute crisis,
could not be more poignantly described.  This is descriptive
narrative of the highest order.  Or again, to pass to something
less acute, the scenes in Mexico City, the race between Old Pop and
Freddie, the kid from New York and the kid from San Francisco, with
a hundred minute yet decisive touches, catching just the salient
points of the crowd, and the landscape, and the blazing sun, are
vividly colored and intensely real.  The details are minute, yet
extraordinarily well selected.  You can scarcely find a wasted
stroke or a random stroke in the whole volume."</p>

<p>Several of the English journals note the resemblance between
Stephen Crane's career and that of the late G. W. Steevens, who was
born in the same year.  Says <hi rend="italic">Literature</hi> (June 9):

</p><p>"Like Steevens he was a man of letters who became a war
correspondent from love of adventure and the desire to be in touch
with the vivid realities of life; like Steevens he has died young,
without having accomplished the best work of which those who knew
him well believed him to be capable, as the result of maladies
contracted while campaigning&mdash;tho not, like Steevens, in a
beleaguered city.  During the Cuban war he suffered first from
malarial and then from yellow fever.  His two illnesses permanently
weakened his constitution.  He was taken for rest and change to
Badenweiler, in the Black Forest, but, even in that invigorating
air, could not recover.  The book by which he will be remembered
is, without doubt, 'The Red Badge of Courage,' introduced to
English readers by Mr. Heinemann.  It describes a battle,
identified by military historians with the battle of
Chancellorsville, and is a marvelous study of the psychology of the
soldier&mdash;the more marvellous when one remembers that, when he wrote
the book, the author had never seen a war, and was only about five-and-twenty years of age.  'Maggie, a Girl of the Streets,' a book
describing slum life in New York, also attracted a good deal of
attention from the critics if not from the general public; but it
was too full of the lurid realism in which very young men delight,
to win favor with those who hold, with Aristotle, that
<foreign lang="el">&tgr;&ogr; &agr;&igr;&sgr;&khgr;&rgr;&ogr;&ngr;</foreign>&mdash;the merely ugly&mdash;is out of place in works of art."
</p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>




