<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AnoLast"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="AnoLast">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Last of Stephen Crane.</title>
<title type="sort">last of stephen crane</title>
<author>Crane review: Anonymous</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">9</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AnoLast</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475687</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Last of Stephen Crane.</title>
<title>The Literary Digest, no. 21, 1900.</title>
<title type="sort">last of stephen crane</title>
<author>Crane review: Anonymous</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition.</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Funk &amp; Wagnalls Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Literary Digest</hi> 21, 1 Dec. 1900: 647.</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-01">January 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Deirdre Johnson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header and basic TEI markup.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
<pb n="647" id="AnoLast647"/>

<head>THE LAST OF STEPHEN CRANE.</head>
<p>
THE collection of stories about the Spanish-American war upon which
Mr. Crane was engaged at the time of his death, has lately appeared
in book form under the title "Wounds in the Rain."  <hi rend="italic">The St.
James's Gazette</hi> (London, September 27) thinks that in a few of
the stories he rises almost, tho not quite, to the level of his
masterpiece, "The Red Badge of Courage."  It says:

</p><p>"The stories are shorter, there is not the same irresistible
sequence of things, nor the pauseless, violent sweep of thought and
deed which made 'The Red Badge' wonderful.  Yet, just as in that
book, there are some sentences which only Mr. Crane would, or
perhaps could, have written.  Take this from 'The Clan of No-Name.'
Eight men fire a volley at a Spanish blockhouse: 'Then they laughed
and yelled insulting language, for they knew that, as far as the
Spaniards were concerned, the surprise was as much as having a
diamond bracelet turn to soap.'  In some other of his books, Mr.
Crane wrote once of a soldier's knees 'turning to bread.'  Take
another instance: 'On the way he passed many things: bleeding men
carried by comrades; others making their way grimly, with
encrimsoned arms; then the little settlement of the hospital squad;
men on the ground everywhere, many in the path; one young captain
dying, with great gasps, his body pale blue and glistening, like
the inside of a rabbit's skin.'
</p><p>"That is a trick, or call it a habit, of Mr. Crane; a few
commonplace sentences, with perhaps a word like 'encrimsoned'
gleaming in them; more commonplace words, dull and short; and then
the horror of some homely comparison which does its work cleanly
and quickly, yet leaves the wound of a queer weapon behind it.
Perhaps owing to the fact that Mr. Crane writes of what he saw, not
what he imagined, there is less of this kind of work in 'Wounds in
the Rain' than in the 'Red Badge of Courage.'  But there is the
same humor, the same power of making the behavior of his fighting
soldiers subjective doings of his own, and the same picturesque
language and pithy slang as Mr. Crane set down in so masterly a
fashion in his first war story.  Here and there he hits his reader
too hard.  He wishes to insist on the fact that a red-headed
Spanish corpse lay near the enemy's trenches.  He therefore uses
the words 'red-headed' nine times in thirty-three lines.  Or he
wishes to point out that promotion in the army comes slowly: 'I
knew the kind.  First lieutenants at forty years of age, captains
at fifty, majors at 102, lieutenant-colonels at 620, full colonels
at 1,000, and brigadiers at 9,768,295 plus.  A man had to live two
billion years to gain eminent rank in the regular army at that
time.'
</p><p>"But of Mr. Crane's other manner, in which, on the whole, he
is at his best, is not this excellent?</p>

<p>Now Gates had a singular adventure on the second morning after
his arrival at Atlanta to take his post as a major in the 307th.
</p><p>He was in his tent, writing, when suddenly the flap was flung
away and a tall young private stepped inside.
</p><p>"Well, Maje," said the newcomer, genially, "how goes it?"
</p><p>The major's head flashed up, but he spoke without heat.
</p><p>"Come to attention and salute."
</p><p>"Huh!" said the private.
</p><p>"Come to attention and salute."
</p><p>The private looked at him in resentful amazement, and then
inquired:
</p><p>"Ye ain't mad, are ye?  Ain't nothin' to get huffy about, is
there?"
</p><p>"I&mdash;.  Come to attention and salute."
</p><p>"Well," drawled the private, as he stared, "seein' as ye are
so darn perticular, I don't care if I do&mdash;if it'll make yer meals
set on yer stomick any better."
</p><p>Drawing a long breath and grinning ironically, he lazily
pulled his heels together and saluted with a flourish.
</p><p>"There," he said, with a return to his earlier genial manner.
"How's that suit ye, Maje?"
</p><p>There was a silence which to an impartial observer would have
seemed pregnant with dynamite and bloody death.  Then the major
cleared his throat and coldly said:
</p><p>"And now, what is your business?"
</p><p>"Who&mdash;me?" asked the private.  "Oh, I just sorter dropped in."
With a deeper meaning he added: "Sorter dropped in in a friendly
way, thinkin' ye was mebbe a different kind of a feller from what
ye be."
</p><p>The inference was clearly marked.
</p><p>It was now Gates's turn to stare, and stare he unfeignedly
did.
</p><p>"Go back to your quarters," he said at length.
</p><p>The volunteer became very angry.
</p><p>"Oh, ye needn't be so up-in-th'-air, need ye?  Don't know's
I'm dead anxious to inflict my company on yer since I've had a good
look at ye.  There may be men in this here battalion what's had
just as much edjewcation as you have, and I'm damned if they ain't
got better <hi rend="italic">manners</hi>.  Good-mornin'," he said, with dignity;
and, passing out of the tent, he flung the flap back in place with
an air of slamming it as if it had been a door.</p>

<p>"Mr. Crane wrote little that is, in its own way, better than
that.  The pity is that of all kinds of work which he did we shall
see nothing new again."
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
