<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AnoMary"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="AnoMary">

<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mary Somerville</title>
<title type="sort">mary somerville</title>
<author>Anonymous</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">19</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AnoMary</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475690</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mary Somerville</title>
<title type="sort">mary somerville</title>
<author>Anonymous</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 5</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 568-571</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text
Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are
composed of the text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as
in SpeFQue1 for page one of Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1860">1860</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-03">March 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Timothy O. Jarrett</name>
</respStmt>
<item>changed COCOA tags to TEI tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> <pb n="568"/>
<head>"Mary Somerville."</head>

<p>THERE have been in every age a few women of genius who have
become the successful rivals of man in the paths which they have
severally chosen.  Three instances are of our time.  Mrs. Browning is
called a poet even by poets; the artists admit that Rosa Bonheur is a
painter; and the mathematicians accord to Mary Somerville a high rank
among themselves.</p>
<p>"In pure mathematics," said Humboldt, "Mrs. Somerville is
strong."  Of no other woman of the age could the remark have been
made; and this would probably be true, were the walks of science as
marked by the feminine footprint as are those of literature.  To read
mathematical works is an easy task; the formulae can be learned and
their meaning apprehended: to read the most profound of them, with
such appreciation that one stands side by side with the great minds who
originated them, requires a higher order of intellect; and far-reaching
indeed is that which, pondering in the study on a few phenomena known
by observation, develops the theory of worlds, traces back for ages their
history, and sketches the outline of their future destiny.</p>
<p>Caroline Herschel, the sister of Sir William, was doubtless gifted
with much of the Herschel talent, and, under other circumstances, her
mind might have turned to original research; but she belonged rather to
the last century, and Hanover was not a region favorable to intellectual
efforts in her sex.  She lived the life of a simple-hearted, truth-loving
woman; most worthy of the name she bore, she made notes for her
brother, she swept the heavens and found comets for him, she computed
and tabulated his observations; it seems never to have occurred to her to
be other than the patient, helping sister of a truly great man.</p>
<p>Mrs. Somerville's life has been more individual.  She is the
daughter of Admiral Fairfax, and was born in Fifeshire, Scotland,
December 26, 1780, in the house of her uncle, the father of her present
husband.</p>
<p>The home training and the school education of the daughters of
Great Britain are very unlike those of their American sisters.  The
manners and customs of the Old World change so slowly, that one can
scarcely assent to a remark made by Sir John Herschel: &mdash; "The
Englishman sticks to his old ways, but is not cemented to them."  The
Englishwoman submits to authority from her infancy; belonging to the
middle class, she does not expect the higher education of the nobility; a
woman, she is not supposed to desire to enter into the studies of her
brothers.  A governess, generally the daughter of a curate, who prefers
this position to that of "companion" to a fine lady, is provided for her in
her early years.  If the choice be fortunate and the parents watchful, the
young girl is thoroughly taught in a few branches of what are commonly
considered feminine studies.  She learns to read and to speak French;
tutors are employed for music and drawing: every young lady above the
rank of the tradesman's daughter plays well upon the piano; every one
has her portfolio of drawings, in which sketches from Nature can always
be found, and frequently the family portraits.  The history of the country
is considered a study suitable for girls; the Englishman expects that his
daughter shall know something of the past, of which he is so justly
proud.</p>
<p>But the more solid book-learning given to the girls of New
England, even in the public schools, is known only to the daughters of
the higher classes, and among them an instance like that of Lady Jane
Grey could scarcely now be found.  As the girls and boys are never
taught in the same schools, no taste is aroused by the example of manly
studies.  An English girl is astonished to hear that an American

 <pb n="569"/>
girl passes a public examination, like her brothers, and with them
competes for prizes; she doubts the truthfulness of some of the
representations of life found in American novels; and so little is the
freedom of manners understood, that the American traveller is frequently
asked, &mdash; "Can it really be as Mrs. Stowe represents in America?  Does a
young lady really give a party herself?"</p>
<p>The difference that one would expect is found between the women
of England or Scotland and the women of New England.  The young
Englishwoman is tasteful and elegant, mindful of all the proprieties and
graces of social life; she speaks slowly and cautiously, and gives her
opinions with great modesty.  These are not at present the characteristics
of the American girl.</p>
<p>Mary Fairfax passed through the usual routine.  At fourteen she
had read the books to be found in her father's house, including the few
works on Navigation which were necessary to him in his profession.
She had thus obtained an idea of the world of science, and it was dull to
return to worsted-work for amusement.  The needle, which has been the
fetter of so many women, became, however, in her hand, magnetic, and
pointed her to her destiny.  She was in the habit of taking her work into
her brother's study, and listening to his recitations; the revelations of
Geometry were thus opened to her; she listened and worked for a time,
until the desire to know more of this region of form and law, of
harmony and of relations, became too strong to be resisted; the worsted
was thrown aside, and she ventured to ask the tutor to instruct her.  The
honest man told her that he was no mathematician; he could lend her
Euclid, but he could do no more.</p>
<p>The first great step was now taken; Euclid was quickly read; other
books were borrowed from other friends; Bonnycastle's and Euler's
Algebra were obtained, and she exulted in the use of those mystic
symbols, x, y, and z.  Her parents looked on with indifference; so that
the music were not neglected and the governess reported well of her
studies, they felt there was no harm in her amusing herself as she chose.
When the days of the governess were over, the young lady "came out" in
Edinburgh, and mingled much with the best society.  This most
picturesque city had long been the resort of the most gifted minds; men
of literature and men of science made the charm of its winter life.
Never was it more the gathering-place of intellect than in the early part
of this century; but there was no room for a woman of genius, and the
young girl's friends advised her to conceal her pursuits.  Move as
quietly, however, and as unobtrusively as she might in the brilliant
circle, her genius was not without recognition.  There was a word of
encouragement from Professor Playfair.  "Persevere in your study," said
he; "it will be a source of happiness to you when all else fails; for it is
the study of truth."  She had a champion, too, in the dreaded critic,
Jeffrey.  "I am told," said a friend, writing to him, "that the ladies of
Edinburgh are literary, and that one of them sets up as a blue-stocking
and an astronomer."  "The lady of whom you speak," replied Jeffrey,
"may wear blue stockings, but her petticoats are so long that I have
never seen them."</p>
<p>Mrs. Somerville has been twice married.  Her first husband, a
gentleman of the name of Greig, regarded her pursuits as her parents
had, simply with indifference.  Dr. Somerville, her present husband, has
taken the utmost pains to secure her time for her studies, and has himself
relieved her from many household cares.</p>
<p>The simplicity of character which belonged to her in early life was
not lost when her reputation became established.  The Royal Society,
whose doors do not open at every knock, admitted her to membership,
and, by their order, her bust was sculptured by Chantrey, and now
adorns the hall of the Society in Somerset House.  During the sittings for
this purpose, a lady, a friend of the sculptor,

 <pb n="570"/>   begged him to introduce her to Mrs. Somerville.
Chantrey consented, and made a dinner-party for the purpose.  The two
ladies were placed side by side at table, and the benevolent artist rejoiced
to perceive, from the flow of talk, that they were mutually pleased.  The
next day, to his astonishment, his friend called on him in a state of great
indignation, believing herself the victim of a practical joke.  "How could
you do so?" said she.  "You knew that I did not want to know
<hi rend="italic">that</hi> Mrs. Somerville; I wanted to know the astronomer: that
lady talked of the theatre, the opera, and common things."</p>
<p>The anecdote so often told of Laplace's compliment is literally
true.  Mrs. Somerville dined with this great geometer in Paris.  "I write
books," said Laplace, "that no one can read.  Only two women have
ever read the 'Mecanique Celeste'; both are Scotch women: Mrs. Greig
and yourself."</p>
<p>Upon the "Mecanique Celeste" Mrs. Somerville's greatest work is
founded.  "I simply translated Laplace's work," said she, "from algebra
into common language."  That is, she did what very few men and no
other woman could do.  It is of this work of Laplace that Bonaparte said,
"I will give to it my first <hi rend="italic">six months</hi> of leisure."  The student
who reads it by the aid of Dr. Bowditch's notes has little idea of the
difficulties to be met in the original work.  Even Dr. Bowditch himself
said, "I never come across one of Laplace's 'Thus it plainly appears,'
without feeling sure that I have got hours of hard study before me, to fill
up the chasm and show <hi rend="italic">how</hi> it plainly appears."</p>
<p>This "translation into common language" was undertaken at the
request of Lord Brougham, who desired a mathematical work suited to
the "Library of Useful Knowledge."  The manuscript was submitted to
Sir John Herschel, who expressed himself "delighted with it, &mdash; that it
was a book for posterity, but quite above the class for which Lord
Brougham's course was intended."  It was published at once, and
became the text-book for the students of Cambridge.</p>
<p>"The Connection of the Physical Sciences" and the "Physical
Geography" are the later works of Mrs. Somerville.  These volumes
have probably been more read in our country than in Europe; for it is a
common remark of the scientific writers of Great Britain, that their
"readers are found in the United States."  They contain vast collections
of facts in all branches of Physical Science, connected together by the
delicate web of Mrs. Somerville's own thought, showing an amount and
variety of learning to be compared only to that of Humboldt.</p>
<p>Provided with an "open sesame" to her heart, in the shape of a
letter from her old friend, Lady Herschel, we sought the acquaintance of
Mrs. Somerville in the spring of 1858.  She was at that time residing in
Florence, and, sending the letter and a card to her by the servant, we
awaited the reply in the large Florentine parlor, in the fireplace of which
a wood-fire blazed, suggestive of English comfort, &mdash; a suggestion which
in Italy rarely becomes a reality.</p>
<p>There was the usual delay; then a footstep came slowly through the
outer room, and a very old man, exceedingly tall, with a red silk
handkerchief around his head, entered, and introduced himself as Doctor
Somerville.  He is proud of his wife; a pardonable weakness in any man,
especially so in the husband of Mary Somerville.  He began at once to
talk of her.  "Mrs. Somerville," he said, "was much interested in the
Americans, for she claimed a connection with the family of Washington.
Washington's half-brother, Lawrence, married Anne Fairfax, who was
of the Scotch family of that name.  When Mrs. Somerville's father, as
Lieutenant Fairfax, was ordered to America, General Washington wrote
to him as a family relative, and invited him to his house.  Lieutenant
Fairfax applied to his commanding officer for leave to accept the
invitation, and it was refused; they never met.  Much to the regret of the
Somervilles, the letter of

 <pb n="571"/>
Washington has been lost.  The Fairfaxes of Virginia are of the same
family, and occasionally some member of the American branch visits his
Scotch cousins."</p>
<p>While Doctor Somerville was talking of these things, Mrs.
Somerville came tripping into the room, speaking with the vivacity of a
young person.  She was seventy-seven years old, but appeared twenty
years younger.  Her face is pleasing, the forehead low and broad, the
eyes blue, &mdash; the features so regular, that, as sculptured by Chantrey, in
the bust at Somerset House, they convey the idea of a very handsome
woman.  Neither this bust nor the picture of her, however, gives a
correct impression, except in the outline of the head and shoulders.  She
spoke with a strong Scotch accent, and was slightly affected by
deafness.</p>
<p>At this time, Mrs. Somerville was re-writing her "Physical
Geography."  She said that she worked as well as when she was
younger, but was more quickly fatigued; yet, in order to gain time, she
had given up her afternoon nap, without apparent injury to her health.
Her working hours were in the morning, and she never refused a visitor
after noon.  For her first work she said she computed a good deal; and
here she stepped quickly into an adjoining room, and brought out a mass
of manuscript computations made for that work, the mere sight of which
would give a headache to most women.  The conversation was rather of
the familiar and chatty order, and marked by great simplicity.  She
touched upon the recent discoveries in chemical science, &mdash; upon
California, its gold and its consequences, some good from which she
thought would be found in the improvement of seamanship, &mdash; on the
nebulae, more and more of which she thought would be resolved, while
yet there might exist irresolvable nebulous matter, such as composed the
tails of comets, or the satellites of the planets, which she thought had
other uses than as their subordinates.  Of Doctor Whewell's attempt to
prove that our planet is the only one inhabited she spoke with
disapprobation; she said she believed that the other planets might be
inhabited by beings of a higher order than ourselves.</p>
<p>On subsequent visits, Mrs. Somerville had much to say of the
Americans.  She regretted that she so rarely received scientific articles
from America; the papers of Lieutenant Maury alone reached her.  She
spoke of the late Doctor Bowditch with great interest, and said she had
had some correspondence with one of his sons; of Professor Pierce as a
great mathematician; and she was much interested in the successful
photography of the stars by Mr. Whipple.  To a traveller, thousands of
miles from home, the mere mention of familiar names is cheering.</p>

<p>Mrs. Somerville resides in Florence on account of the health of her
husband.  A little garden, well-stocked with rosebushes, which she
shows with great pride to her visitors, furnishes her with a means of
healthy recreation after her severe studies.  Her children are a son by
Mr. Greig and two daughters by Doctor Somerville.  In early life, Mrs.
Somerville was a fine musician; the daughters have inherited this talent;
and having lived long in Florence, they speak Italian with a perfect
accent.  "I speak Italian," said Mrs. Somerville; "but no one could ever
take me for other than a Scotchwoman."</p>
<p>No one can make the acquaintance of this remarkable woman
without increased admiration for her.  The ascent of the steep and rugged
path of science has not unfitted her for the drawing-room circle; the
hours of devotion to close study have not been incompatible with the
duties of the wife and the mother; the mind that has turned to rigid
demonstration has not thereby lost its faith in the truths which figures
will not prove.  "I have no doubt," said she, in speaking of the heavenly
bodies, "that in another state of existence we shall know more about
these things."</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
