<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AnoOcta"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>
<TEI.2 id="AnoOcta">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Octave Thanet</title>
<title type="sort">octave thanet</title>
<author>Anonymous</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">11</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AnoOcta</idno>
<date value="1999">1999</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1999 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476657</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Octave Thanet</title>
<title level="j">The Reader Magazine</title>
<title type="sort">octave thanet</title>
<author>Anonymous</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Bobbs-Merrill Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>Indianapolis</pubPlace>
<date value="1904" certainty="ca">Vol. 3, no.4 (Mar. 1904)-v.6, no.3 (Aug. 1905).</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: UVa Library, Microfilm S-867</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1904">1904</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1999-03">March 1999</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>June Griffin, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="article" id="d3">
<head><hi rend="bold">"OCTAVE THANET"</hi><lb/>
A LITTLE BIOGRAPHY WHICH WILL BE FOLLOWED FROM TIME TO
TIME BY OTHER SKETCHES OF MEN AND WOMEN
WHO ARE WRITING TO-DAY</head>
<p>
WHEN, a decade ago, some one asked "Octave Thanet" to state
where she would like to live, her reply was: "Nowhere all the year
round."  And if you care to make an attempt to trace Miss French's
whereabouts you will very likely discover that she is living up to her
declaration.  A modern captain of industry
is not more at home anywhere than this
delightful writer of short stories &mdash; a literary lapidary she might well
be termed, so absolutely clean-cut and brilliant is her work.  Miss
French has been complimented by pastmasters of the art of literary
criticism for work of a widely diversified character.  She shows a
remarkable familiarity with life in our bustling west, as well as with
that of our less assertive south.  We marvel at this, when we
consider that her birth and education is of New England.  However,
the fact that fate compelled her to take up residence in Iowa, and
inclination led her to spend a part of the year in the south, accounts
for those characteristics in her work that are reflective of the
sections, and which might possibly puzzle an unsophisticated reader
concerning the personality of the author.
</p>

<p>Miss French was born at Andover, Massachusetts, in 1850, and
was educated at the Abbott Academy in that town, though her
residence at the beginning of that period was Davenport, Iowa, to
which place her father had gone because of failing health &mdash; a man
of education, and keenly appreciative of literature and art.  Mr.
French was descended from William French, a colonial legislator
and Indian fighter.  On her maternal grandmother's side, Miss
French is descended from the Endicotts, the Richardsons, the
Danforths, and other historic families of New England.  Her
education predisposed Miss French to the fascinations of economics
and philosophy, and she early dabbled in matters which would have
warped her nature and placed her in the ranks of the blue-stockings.
Happily, editors stood between the ambitious young woman and
what would have been a mere avocation, and when she turned her
attention, after polite admonitions, to stories which reflected
something of her naturally sunny disposition and a keen insight into
human nature, they began to take notice of her talents.  Little
wonder, then, that when asked: "Who are your heroes in real life?"
Miss French answered with promptness: "Magazine editors!"

<pb n="587"/>

</p><p>It was in 1878, about, that Miss French sent her first story in the
line of her newly realized vocation to <hi rend="italic">Lippincott's
Magazine</hi>, which the editor accepted and for which he sent
her a check for $42.  This was "A Communist's Wife," and really
marks the starting-point in Miss French's literary career, which has
since largely devoted itself to realistic portraiture.  This faculty is
discernible in an extraordinary degree in those stories founded on
her sojourns on the plantation at Clover Bend, on the Black River of
Arkansas.  This plantation and incidents connected therewith have
been described with painstaking exactness in her stories called
"Otto the Knight," "Whitsun Harp, Regulator," "Ma' Bowlin'" and
"The Mortgage on Jeffy."
</p><p>The final critical estimate of "Octave Thanet's" genius will rest
on an article of thirty pages in the <hi rend="italic">Revue des Deux
Mondes</hi>, written some years ago by Mme. Blanc, the gifted
French author and critic who, in a visit to this country, sought out
Miss French and formed her acquaintance.  "It has only been since I
have myself visited the west and the new south of the United
States," wrote Mme. Blanc, "that I have been able to realize fully
the minute fidelity in the description of things and people which
makes each of the short stories of 'Octave Thanet' a little
masterpiece of honest and piquant realism.  But a long time
previously, in Paris, without yet knowing either their setting or the
characters which had inspired them, I had been conscious of the true
fineness of what these stories gave us; that warm, broad, and sincere
heartbeat of true human life which filled them from one end to the
other."  No doubt Mme. Blanc was amazed, too, at the fact that the
"Stories of a Western Town," with which she had become
acquainted in her own far-away Paris, were to stand her in stead of a
guide book when she visited "Octave Thanet's" western preserves.
And she was delighted, we may well believe, in visiting Alice
French at the Black River plantation to discover how, away off in
the land of Nowhere, one may live the idyllic life and at the same
time engage in useful pursuits.  It was here, as has been said, that
Miss French gained that intimate knowledge of the phase of human
nature which stands out so vividly in her southern stories.  She is a
close observer of people and customs, and anything out of the
ordinary is sure to attract her attention.  As an instance of this
faculty of observation and application, a newspaper paragraph
concerning the mortgaging of a child was the basis of "The
Mortgage on Jeffy," one of her most striking productions.
</p><p>"Octave Thanet's" personality is of that character which appeals
to enthusiastic admiration, and she makes friends easily by reason
of a fusion of qualities more or less rare in her sex &mdash; judgment, tact,
sympathy, tolerance, and tenderness &mdash; with true feminine fondness
for all those things in social life which distinguish the gentlewoman.
Society makes large demands upon her time, and whether in
Chicago, Indianapolis, Memphis, New York, or Boston, Miss
French necessarily responds to its exactions, so that one wonders
how she finds time to accomplish her literary work.  A striking
phase of "Octave Thanet's" kaleidoscopic quality is the possession
of a keen sense of the genuinely humorous, an attribute commonly
ascribed to the exclusive possession of man &mdash; humor which
"softens with mirth the inequalities of existence," of which we have
striking proof in the testimony of one of her intimate acquaintances:
"It is impossible to convey in words the impression she makes upon
one; her humor and pathos are both elusive, and exist largely in her
personality and manner.  One can no more catch and cage them for
inspection than one can cage the fragrance of wild grape blossoms
in spring, or the rollicking 'chink' of the bobolink, rioting in

<pb n="588"/>

June meadows.  To get an epitome of her qualities, one should have
seen her, of a summer evening, clad as Mrs. Jarley, covered with
decorations from every crowned head in the world &mdash; all carefully
purchased at Siegel-Cooper's &mdash; and reading testimonials, local and
otherwise, to the value of her waxworks, when her voice was not
utterly drowned by the shouts and screams of laughter from her
audience.  The point of this will be appreciated when I say that the
audience was largely composed of factory girls from New York
City, and the performance was Miss French's way of adding to their
pleasure during their vacation."
</p><p>Alice French belongs to a long list of women's clubs in various
parts of the country as well as to the Women's Industrial and
Educational Union of Boston, the classification of which Miss
French passes up as a companion problem to that which has to do
with the age of Ann.
</p><p>For the most part, the books published by Miss French consist of
short stories, many of which have appeared in the magazines.  The
complete list would be a long one.  She has, however, published
nine volumes, as follows: "Knitters of the Sun" (1887 &mdash; Houghton,
Mifflin &amp; Co.); "Expiation" (1890 &mdash; Scribners); "Otto the Knight"
(1893 &mdash; Houghton, Mifflin &amp; Co.); "Stories of a Western Town"
(1893 &mdash; Scribners); "An Adventure in Photography" (1893 &mdash;
Scribners); "The Missionary Sheriff" (1897 &mdash; Harpers); "A Book of
True Lovers" (1898 &mdash; McClure); "The Heart of Toil" (1898 &mdash;
Scribners); "A Slave to Duty" (1900 &mdash; H. S. Stone &amp; Co.).
</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
