<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AnoSlav"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="AnoSlav">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Slave's Story</title>
<title type="sort">slaves story</title>
<author>Anonymous</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">30</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AnoSlav</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475692</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Slave's Story</title>
<title type="sort">slaves story</title>
<author>Anonymous</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Putnam's Monthly Magazine</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1857-06">June 1857</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Volume 9: 614-620.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1857-06">June 1857</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>African American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-10">October 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header; Tagged with TEI.2-compatible SGML; Parsed against
teilite.dtd.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">


<body id="d2">
<div1 type="essay" id="d3"><pb n="614"/>
<head>A SLAVE'S STORY.
<address><addrLine>[&mdash; COUNTY, VIRGINIA,
<date value="1857-02-23">February 23d, 1857.</date></addrLine></address></head>

<salute>To the Editor of Putnam's Monthly.</salute>

<p>SIR:&mdash;I send you a sketch of a slave who died lately at my
house, and who was once my property.
</p><p>                 *     *     *     *     *
</p><p> The slave-question is becoming more and more prominent, and I
have thought it well to give a simple, faithful narrative of a
slave's experience and views.  The sketch has not been gotten up
for effect, but has been written as an authentic illustration of
the results, moral and physical, of the system.  Though the owner
of slaves, I have always advocated some plan of gradual
emancipation <hi rend="italic">by our own state</hi>, and, therefore, have no
motive for concealing anything in relation to the effects of
slavery.  I have given, exactly, Ralph's narrative&mdash;many facts in
which I could myself establish, and verify others by unquestionable
evidence.
</p><signed>           Your obedient servant,
                          &mdash; &mdash;] </signed>
</div1>

<div1 type="bio" id="d4">

<p>I WAS born about the year 1794, on a large plantation, thirty odd
miles above Richmond, Virginia, and was descended, in the third
generation, from imported Africans, and, probably, from some of the
darkest of the native race; for my parents as well as myself were
pretty black&mdash;more so than slaves generally are now.  My parents
belonged to a gentleman supposed to be wealthy, residing in
Williamsburg, who had been a member of the King's Council, and
afterwards of the House of Delegates.  Of course, he seldom visited
his distant estate, but intrusted it&mdash;comprising more than six
thousand acres, and slaves enough to cultivate it&mdash;to the
management and the honesty of an overseer.  As in most other cases,
the overseer managed very well for himself, but not so well for his
employer; and, at the death of my parents' master, his debts and
legacies encumbered his estate so much, that his only son, who then
removed to the lands before-mentioned, and whom I designate as my
master, found himself compelled to sell immediately a portion of
the slaves.  My parents and their five children&mdash;including myself,
then an infant&mdash;were amongst those sold.  But their kind master did
the best he could for them, and sold the whole family, privately,
to some man very near or beyond the mountains.  The contrast
between their new situation and the mild government of their young
master, soon rendered my parents greatly dissatisfied; and, after
a few months, they both absconded from the purchaser, leaving their
four elder children, whom they never saw again, and taking me with
them.  They found their way back to their former neighborhood, and,
for a summer and part of autumn, were concealed in a large body of
woods on their former master's premises.  Of course, all the
neighboring slaves soon knew their lurking-place, and supplied them
with food, and often with shelter.  At length the young master was
informed, in some way, of the circumstance; and, with that kindness
which distinguished him through life, he repurchased my parents and
myself, at considerable loss and inconvenience.
</p><p> The running away of slaves, that is, their concealment on or
near their master's premises, or sometimes at a distance of several
miles, is inevitable.  The exercise of arbitrary and irresponsible
power will produce a determination to counteract or escape from its
effects.  In almost every instance, the fear or the infliction of
bodily punishment drives the slave to the woods.  Few of those who
lurk about the neighborhood abscond, because such a life is
preferable to that on the plantation, and many resort to it in the
hope that the master's desire for them to return to their labor
will induce him to overlook a fault which the slave persuades
himself does not deserve stripes.  A few, repugnant to labor, or
rendered desperate by harsh usage, will resort to almost any
expedient to escape.  In one instance, I knew two men to live more
than a year in a cave, in a large wood, about a mile from their
master's house.  The stock on the adjacent farms supplied them with
meat, and bread was easily gotten from their fellow-slaves&mdash;for, in
almost every such case, regular communication is kept up
<pb n="615"/>
between the fugitive and his class, always in the night, and the
runaway often visits the adjacent cabins.  This is done with all
possible precaution, lest some white person detect them.  But they
never fear a betrayal by one of their own race; nor will the hope
of reward or the fear of punishment generally extort any
information that might lead to the capture of the fugitive.  The
cave of the two men was discovered by means of the smoke issuing
from its mouth, and they were carried to their owner.  Yet even
these never resorted to such a life again.  One was sold about
twenty years afterward, to a neighbor; the other died at a great
age, the property of his master's grandson.  Many slave-owners feel
such compassion for the runaway, upon the general ground that he
has been <hi rend="italic">driven</hi> to the step, that they will make no effort
to capture him.  I knew a gentleman to come suddenly upon one fast
asleep in a large wood.  He awoke the man, asked him a few
questions, and, after advising him to return to his master, with a
request from himself not to punish him, he left him.
</p><p> My earliest recollection of myself is, as a little, black,
dirty, uncombed, and unwashed animal, scantily covered with odds
and ends of cotton or woolen garments in cool weather, and in the
warm season neither having nor desiring any other covering than my
own dark skin.  And this was universal amongst children, whether
male or female, until nine or ten years old.  The truth is, the
whites in that locality were in a remote situation, at a distance
from the frequented roads, and far behind most parts of the state
in intelligence and improvement.  Raising tobacco was the one sole
object in life.  They ate tobacco&mdash;they breathed tobacco&mdash;they
talked tobacco&mdash;and they worked tobacco, all day long, and often
far into the night, from the beginning to the end of the year.  A
crop, occupying so much time, and requiring so much attention,
compelled both whites and blacks to neglect everything else; and,
generally, the former were ignorant and exacting, the latter
debased and barbarous, with scarcely a want fully satisfied, and
with little more intelligence than the beasts that perish.  Since
the period I speak of, the march of improvement has reached even
that secluded neighborhood, and the condition of all classes has
greatly improved.
</p><p> I sat in the ashes, or made dirt-pies in the sand, or hunted
for berries or birds' nests, until old enough to carry a pail of
water on my head; and then I was made, by my parents, the carrier
of everything not beyond my strength.  I have heard of Indians
called Flatheads, because of the shape given to their skulls by
pressure.  But, if pressure <hi rend="italic">can</hi> flatten the human head, my
race should all be thus deformed; for, in childhood, our heads are
the universal vehicles of transportation.  It may be that our
skulls are mercifully fashioned a little thicker than those of the
whites or Indians, in anticipation of this drudgery.  A year or two
later, I became the carrier of water and food to the hands in the
fields; and then was advanced to the post of cow-driver and
attendant on the dairy-maid.  Now I began to be noticed by my
master, and came gradually to be considered in his employment, and
began to plow and attend to horses.
</p><p> My young master, being a bachelor, was much from home; and as
soon as I could manage a horse pretty well, I became his
attendant&mdash;his <hi rend="italic">body-servant</hi>, as such were called&mdash;on his
journeys; he on one horse and I on another, with his portmanteau,
as large as myself, strapped behind my saddle.  I was now in that
privileged station, from which I looked down with contempt, not
only on most of my own race, but on all poor white folks, as we
called all who had not a fair share of property or intelligence.
My position as attendant on a gentleman-bachelor of large property,
who traveled a good deal, and was at all times kind to his
dependents, was, perhaps, the most pleasant that slavery can
exhibit.  If my master thought it necessary to reprove me, 'twas
always more in kindness than in anger, and to blows he never
resorted.  In fact, I was too much indulged to fulfill properly my
duties as a slave.  When at home, I now became the waiter in the
house, and a kind of doer of all work about the premises, and,
consequently, avoided altogether subjection to the overseer.  My
master intrusted the management of his lands and field-hands too
much, perhaps, to overseers&mdash;those dreaded and despised obstacles
between slaves and their owners, who commonly have no bowels of
compassion for the slave, and little care for the interests of the
master.  Overseers are fruitful causes
<pb n="616"/>
of disturbance and resistance.  Most slaves submit at once to the most unjust
treatment from the master, but shrink with horror from the
overseer's hands.  They think correction belongs of right to the
master, the they know the overseer cares nothing for them; nor do
they ever expect his justice to be tempered with mercy.  It is
true, the severity of the overseer's rule is usually in the ratio
of the master's requirement; so that, if the latter be considerate,
not in haste to be rich, he overrules the overseer and protects his
negroes pretty well.  This was remarkably the case with my master.
</p><p> A material circumstance in my life now occurred.  My master's
father had emancipated an elderly negro, named Joe, before such
acts were prohibited, and had conveyed to him about sixty acres of
land, part of my present master's estate.  This old man and his
wife now brought from Williamsburg a young female relation named
Sally, with her husband and one or two children, who were all free.
Sally was one of the most beautiful of women.  I have never seen
one of her color I thought comparable to her.  I soon became madly
in love.  I knew that what is called the marriage tie is usually of
little obligation amongst slaves; and that free negroes, being no
better taught, if as well, were probably not more virtuous.  And
how can the slave be expected to observe the marriage vows?  In
most cases they make none&mdash;plight no troth&mdash;have a sort of
understanding that their agreement shall continue until one or both
choose to form some other tie.  And even if wishing to continue
faithful unto death, they know their master deems their vows null
and void, if he choose to separate them; and he often does thus
without scruple, by selling one or both.  When their superiors
disregard their slaves' obligations, the slaves will think lightly
of them, too; and this utter contempt of the whites for the
sacredness of marriage amongst
<pb n="617"/>
slaves, has done more to demoralize and brutalize the slave than all
the other personal wrongs he suffers.  This brings them all, the good and
the bad, to a common level.  A common lot befalls them all.  The
<hi rend="italic">sentiment</hi> that should exist in marriage, is excluded or
crushed by the necessity of their condition; and the tie becomes a
mere <hi rend="italic">liaison</hi>, founded upon the instinct of the brute.  But
to proceed: I determined, if possible, to get Sally from her
husband, and make her my wife; and, after much delay, and more that
cannot be told, I found she was not superior to her race or her
condition.  For a good while, she might be said to have two
husbands; but finally her first husband went back, with his own
children, to Williamsburg, in company with old Joe, who had sold
his land, and Sally became my acknowledged wife.  My master
strongly disapproved my conduct; but, always kind to the unthankful
and the evil, her permitted me, as he did his other men, to build
a cabin on the margin of the forest, and thither I carried Sally.
And now, after the lapse of more than thirty years, and I am
tottering on the brink of the grave, I cannot say that I feel any
great compunction for having taken another man's wife to be my
wife.  So common has destiny or necessity made it, that we think it
sanctioned by custom, and that our masters are responsible for
whatever of wrong there be in it.
</p><p> Sally bore me several children, and in a few years I had a
large family to maintain.  My wife and children were free, and my
master, after giving them a house and patch of ground, fuel, and a
supply of meal weekly, and having more than enough of his own
slaves to provide for, could not be expected to give them more.
Sally, I regret to say, was too much given to sloth and
improvidence&mdash;those plague-spots inherited from our ancestors, and
fostered by our condition here.  Most of my time, during the day,
being given to my master's interests, necessity compelled me to
resort to expedients, to which my own depraved nature and the
example of other slaves already tempted me.  There were, in our
vicinity, plenty of <hi rend="italic">poor white folks</hi>, as we contemptuously
called them, whom we cordially despised, but with whom we carried
on a regular traffic at our master's expense.
</p><p> I became a constant dealer in grain and tobacco with certain
white men, who purchased grain at a few cents or a pint of whisky
per bushel, and tobacco at about the same rate.  My master, I now
believe, suspected that he was unmercifully robbed; but with a
Christian forbearance, as rare as it is injudicious, preferred
suffering wrong to punishing the wrong-doer.  The overseer had tact
enough to know that he should not be more vigilant than his
employer required; and thus we could carry on our operations by
night, almost without fear of detection.  Most of my master's men
cultivated a few square yards in corn and tobacco, merely as a
pretext for reaping a large crop, and I followed the example.
Tobacco was our favorite crop.  Its value, compared with its
weight, was much greater than that of grain, and a man's shoulders
could bear off, in one night, what would bring a sum sufficient for
a week or two.  Sometimes a daring theft would provoke a general
search throughout the neighborhood, and those so unlucky as to be
detected, were severely punished.  On one occasion only this was my
misfortune.  A neighbor discovered some stolen tobacco in
possession of one of his men.  To this man I had intrusted some, to
be carried with his to Richmond.  This we had permission to do.
But the man had, at least, received some stolen tobacco, and 'tis
probable I had added to my store in the same way, though, at this
distance of time, I cannot be sure.  We were both carried before a
magistrate, and punished with forty stripes, save one, most
vigorously applied.
</p><p> But these little mischances never long interrupted our
operations.  We thought&mdash;and slaves will always think&mdash;they have a
right&mdash;of the kind which the whites call a <hi rend="italic">moral</hi> right&mdash;to
a fair proportion of the proceeds of their labor, and that any
means are excusable towards securing that portion.  Hence, theft
from the master is generally deemed a light offense, if not
strictly justifiable.  They think the master defrauds them
publicly, and they will steal from him privately, and that the
secret act is no worse than the open injury.  In fact, slavery not
only renders the slave dishonest, but it makes the poorest whites
dishonest, too.  The facility with which they can make enormous
profits by their trade with slaves, and the impunity afforded by
their legal privileges, tempt them beyond what their feeble
<pb n="618"/>
moral sense can bear, and they become the most vicious and
despicable creatures upon earth, whether black or white.
</p><p> My children, as they became large enough to be useful, were
placed in the surrounding families, or I should have found it
impossible to support them, by fair means or foul; and after all,
my family lived poorly enough.  After some years the neighboring
whites began to demand the removal of this family of free blacks,
either because they suspected it to be the centre of the nocturnal
traffic, or because their presence might render the slaves
dissatisfied.  This demand soon became general and loud; and my
master, thinking it best to yield to the increasing discontent,
advised Sally to move elsewhere.  She was about to set off to
Williamsburg, when she was taken sick, it was never known of what
disease&mdash;some thought it brought on by grief&mdash;and after a few weeks
she was snatched from me by a greater, but not more inexorable,
power than the white neighbors.  I was then more than forty years
old, and had some of our younger children with me.  They were
placed with my mother and other women on the plantation, and I
found myself a lonely and discontented man.  I believed myself to
have been cruelly wronged in some way.  I could not clearly decide
whether by the neighbors, or by the world, or by the laws of the
land, and I became morose, quarrelsome, and vengeful.  Like Cain,
my hand was against every man, and every man's hand against me.  I
avoided much communication, for several years, with my fellow-slaves, and became careless and reckless.  I could not then
perceive, in my wife's death, a just retribution and requital of
her first husband's wrongs.  I could not perceive that justice was
meted to me as I had measured it to him.  But now I hope I can say,
that whatever may have been my actual <hi rend="italic">guilt</hi> in winning her,
I deserved to lose her.
</p><p> Now, sole occupant of my cabin, I was too much engaged out of
doors to render it comfortable, nor did I care how dirty or untidy
it was.  I disregarded the little luxuries coveted by some slaves.
A stool or a broken chair sufficed for a seat; a rude bedstead of
undressed boards, with some old clothes or blankets, ministered
adequately to my rest; and a gridiron, a skillet, and old hoe, a
small pot, and one or two plates, supplied an abundant kitchen
apparatus.  In cold weather, the numerous crevices between the
logs, which I was too careless to fill with clay, admitted such
draughts of air that the only comfortable spot was the corner in
the ample fireplace, and there, on my rough stool, with my shins
almost in the fire, I passed the night&mdash;when not on some secret
expedition.  I raised a few fowls and a pig, annually; but the
permission to have the latter is not often granted.
</p><p> My master had an only child, a daughter, who was now about to
be married; but, a few weeks before that event, he died, after a
painful and lingering illness.  He had all his life been
embarrassed by his father's debts, and had sold, from time to time,
at least five-sixths of his land, and many slaves.  The remaining
slaves felt a painful interest in their master's death, and the
marriage of their young mistress.  They were about to fall into the
hands of a man of whom they knew little, and who, they thought,
could not be as kind and forbearing as their old master.  None were
sold to pay debts, and we all came, almost imperceptibly, into the
possession of the young mistress's husband, and soon found it
necessary to be more regular in our duties.  I had so long done
much as I pleased, that I was still headstrong and heedless; but
not many months after my new master assumed authority, I paid so
little regard to some directions, that he instructed the overseer
to chastise me.  This astonished, but subdued me.  I had not had
stripes inflicted since the affair of the tobacco; but, somehow or
other, I felt that I deserved correction, and I believe the
significant hint had a salutary effect on all the slaves.  Our
master was neither exacting nor unkind&mdash;indulgent as far as he
thought reasonable&mdash;but requiring a fair performance of the various
duties and labors of the farm.  I now became more regular at my
work and in my habits, and in a year or two took another wife, a
slave, on a plantation five or six miles distant.  I say I
<hi rend="italic">took</hi> a wife, for we literally <hi rend="italic">took</hi> each other, the
<hi rend="italic">taking</hi> constituting the marriage.  This time, also, I took
another man's wife, but he had been dead a year or more.  I had the
usual permission to go to my wife's house every Saturday afternoon,
and return on Monday morning.
<pb n="619"/>
I still had my cabin at home; but it became, if possible, more
uncomfortable and more neglected than ever, because I was content to make
any shift for five nights in the week, relying upon the rest and repose of the
other two to relieve the strain on my faculties.
</p><p> A few years after I got my second wife, and when I was about
fifty-five years old, my master removed to what is called the
Valley of Virginia.  Nearly all my living children were in
Richmond, and, at my request, I was permitted to go thither, to be
hired.  But I had other views.  I thought, after my master's
removal to a great distance, I might, with my children's help, live
uncontrolled in Richmond.  I therefore took care neither to be
hired, nor to return to my master.  After a while he understood my
device, and made a deed of gift of me to a relative of his wife,
who lived in the neighborhood he had left.  This cousin, finding I
was lurking about my old home&mdash;for I was afraid to remain long in
Richmond&mdash;requested me, through some of his slaves, to come to him.
Afraid of being apprehended, I thought it best to comply; but not
believing that I owed service to any but the master over the
mountains, I neglected my duties, and, in truth, was unmanageable.
After a short trial, this, my third master, sold me in Richmond,
for fifty dollars.  I now found myself condemned to harder labor
than ever before.  I was required to do more than my age or
strength could bear, was scantily fed and clothed, and was often
punished.  I now bitterly lamented my folly in not going with my
second master over the mountains, and, for a long time, I tried to
mature some plan for reaching him.  I got, from one of his men, who
had been to the valley, and was then hired in Richmond, some little
information about the route; and, at length, after undergoing, for
five or six years, more hardships than in my whole previous life,
one night, in the month of May, I fled from Richmond and my hard
master, and began, on foot, a journey of one hundred and fifty
miles, through a country, the greater part of which was entirely
unknown to me.  I traveled almost wholly at night, because I knew
there was great danger of being apprehended as a runaway.  I had
only a few cents, and provisions for a day or two&mdash;was in rags&mdash;and
weak and emaciated from age and the excesses of my early life.  But
the belief that, if I could reach my best friends, I should be
treated with kindness during the little remnant of life, encouraged
me to struggle on.  When my means were exhausted, I occasionally
begged a little food from other slaves, and sometimes got
directions for the way.  Once over the mountains, I found nobody
molested negroes, and I traveled more by day; and, at length, worn
down with weariness and want, I knew I must be near the desired
haven.  A house was pointed out, by a passing slave, as the home of
my former master; but, even then, I was afraid to approach by day.
At last, towards night, I ventured up to a house which, I was
confident, was occupied by slaves.  As I reached the door, I was
met by a young man with a light, whom I remembered as a boy some
eight years before.  To his inquiry&mdash;"Who are you?"&mdash;I made no
reply; when he held the light to my face, and immediately shouted:
"Why, if here ain't our Ralph."  I had thus safely accomplished
what very few slaves could hope to do, and what my fellow-slave in
Richmond asserted to be impossible.
</p><p> I was kindly received, and my pressing wants were at once
supplied.  My flight from my legal owner was soon known.  My
protector well knew he was liable to prosecution for harboring a
runaway; but I was infirm and nearly past labor, and he was too
humane to take any steps to restore me to my owner, or to refuse to
support me.  He never inquired the name of that owner, nor do I
believe he ever knew it.  After some time, finding no warning of my
flight in the Richmond papers, he inferred that my master did not
care to recover me, and permitted me to work in the garden.  I was
not required to do so, and what I did was done willingly.  My
protector would sometimes tell me, in jest, that he must inform my
master where I was concealed; but I believe he said it only as a
means of putting me on my good behavior.  I soon discovered slavery
to be entirely different in that part of the valley.  Almost
universally slaves are abundantly fed and clothed, and corporeal
punishment is rare.  They are civilly treated by all classes of
whites, and are very seldom required to show a pass.  In this
farming and grazing country, the labor is light, except in harvest
and in thrashing; and
<pb n="620"/>
nowhere in Virginia is slavery so tolerable as in the valley.
</p><p> And now, after enjoying, for more than two years, that rest
which my feeble old age requires, I find myself hastening to the
grave; and in what frame of mind?  Many of the slaves, with whom I
was brought up, were members of the Baptist church, and, I now
believe, were consistently pious, according to their knowledge.
But I had always scoffed at religion and the religious.  I loved
too well the wages of iniquity to think of a hereafter; or, if I
did, it was in a way common to many of my race&mdash;that a merciful God
would not punish us here, and in the next life too&mdash;that, after a
life of slavery, he would give us our reward.  But, with death
close at hand, my blindness and ignorance are, I hope, a little
dispelled.  In my imperfect, and, I fear, improper, way, I try to
ask God's mercy, and to put my trust in the Saviour; but 'tis all
dark before me, and I fear that, in a little while, it will be said
of me, he died as a dog dieth.  Weak to prostration, and with the
swollen frame of dropsy, I can only wait till my change comes,
often crying out, "God be merciful to me a sinner."
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="note" id="d5">
<p> Very soon after the above was written, the old man died,
somewhat suddenly.  When he reached his last home, it was evident
a great change had taken place in him&mdash;a change so remarkable as to
excite the surprise of his fellow-servants.  Though he had been
notorious for his harsh, turbulent disposition, and his utter
disregard for the rights of other slaves, he was now quiet and
gentle, and always ready to do little offices of kindness.  He was
occasionally heard to pray; but, having become deaf, he spoke but
little.  We have no doubt he is embraced in the divine rule of
justice, that "to whom little has been given, of him will little be
required."
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
