<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AnoShep"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="AnoShep">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Elizabeth Sara Sheppard</title>
<title type="sort">elizabeth sara sheppard</title>
<author>Anonymous</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">20</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AnoShep</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475691</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Elizabeth Sara Sheppard</title>
<title type="sort">elizabeth sara sheppard</title>
<author>Anonymous</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<date value="1862">1862</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>10</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 498-502</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text
Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are
composed of the text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as
in SpeFQue1 for page one of Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1862">1862</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-03">March 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Timothy O. Jarrett</name>
</respStmt>
<item>changed COCOA tags to TEI tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">



	<div1 type="article" id="d3"> <pb n="498"/>
<head>"Elizabeth Sara Sheppard."  <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 10 (Oct. 1862):
498-502. </head>

<p>
YOU ask from me some particulars of the valued life so recently
closed.  Miss Sheppard was my friend of many years; I was with her to
the last hour of her existence; but this is not the time for other than a
brief notice of her career, and I comply with your request by sending
you a slight memorial, hardly full enough for publication. </p>
<p>Elizabeth Sara Sheppard, the authoress of "Charles Auchester,"
"Counterparts," etc., was born at Blackheath, in England.  Her father
was a clergyman of unusual scholastic attainments, and took high honors
at St. John's College, Oxford.  Mr. Sheppard, on the mother's side,
could number Hebrew ancestors, and this was the pride of his second
daughter, the subject of this notice.  Her love for the whole Hebrew race
amounted to a passion, which found its expression in the romance of
"Charles Auchester."</p>
<p>Very early she displayed a most decided poetic predisposition, --writing, when but ten years old, with surprising facility on every
possible subject.  No metre had any difficulties for her, and no theme
seemed dull to her vivid intelligence, &mdash; her fancy being roused to action
in a moment, by the barest hint given either by Nature or Art.  Her first
drama was written at this early age; it was called "Boadicea," and was
composed immediately after she had been shown a field at Islington
where this queen is said to have pitched her tent.  Any one who asked
was welcome to "some verses by 'Little Lizzie,'" written in her peculiar
and fairy-like hand, (for when very young, her writing was remarkable
for its extreme smallness and finish,) given with child-like simplicity,
and artless ignorance of the worth of what she bestowed with a kiss and
a smile.</p>
<p>Her poems were composed at once, with scarcely a correction.
Her earlier ones, for the most part, were written at the corner of a large
table, covered with the usual heaps of "after-lessons," in a school-room,
where some twenty enfranchised girls were putting away copy-books,
French grammars, etc., and getting out play-boxes and fancy-work, with
the common amount of chatter and noise.  Contrasted with such young
persons, this child looked like a strange, unearthly creature, &mdash; her large,
dark gray eye full of inspiration, and every movement of her frame and
tone of her voice instinct with delicate energy.</p>
<p>At the same age she would extemporize for hours on the organ,
after wreathing the candlesticks with garden-flowers which she had
brought in her hand, &mdash; their scent, she would say, suggesting the wild,
sweet fancies which her fingers seemed able to call forth on the shortest
notice.  Persons straying into the church, as they often did, attracted by
the sound of music, would declare the performer to be an experienced
masculine musician.</p>
<p>When but a year older, she was an excellent Latin scholar, and, to
use her father's words, she might then have "gone in for honors at
Oxford."  French she spoke and wrote fluently, besides reading Goethe
and Schiller with avidity, and translating as fast as she read, &mdash; Schiller
having always the preference.  At fourteen she began the study of
Hebrew, of which language she was a worshipper, and could not at that
early age even let Greek alone.  Her wonderful power of seizing on the
genius of a language, and becoming for the time a foreigner in spirit,
was noticed by all her teachers; her ear was so delicate that no subtile
inflection ever escaped her, nor any idiom.</p>
<p>And now she surprised her most intimate friend by the present of a
prose story, sent to her, when absent, in chapters by the post.  This was
succeeded by many other tales, and finally by "Charles Auchester," --which romance, as well as that of "Counterparts," was written in

 <pb n="499"/>
the few hours she could command after her teaching was over: for in her
mother's school she taught music the greater part of every day, &mdash; both
theoretically and practically, &mdash; and also Latin.</p>
<p>Her health, always delicate, suffered wofully from this constant
strain, and caused her to experience the most painful exhaustion, which,
however, she never permitted to be an excuse for shirking an occupation
naturally distasteful to her, &mdash; and doubly so, that through all the din of
practice her thousand fancies clamored like caged birds eager for
liberty.</p>
<p>The moment her hour of leisure came, she would hide herself with
her best loved work in the quietest corner she could find; sometimes it
was a little room in-doors, sometimes the summer-house, sometimes
under a large mulberry-tree; and thus "Charles Auchester" and
"Counterparts" were written, the former without one correction, &mdash; sheet
after sheet, flung from her hand in the ardor of composition, being
picked up and read by the friend who was in all her literary secrets.  At
last this same friend, finding she had no thought of publication, in a
moment of playful daring, persuaded her to send the manuscript to
Benjamin Disraeli, and he introduced it to his publishers.  I quote from
his letter to the author, which may not be out of place here: &mdash; </p>
<p>"No greater book will ever be written upon music, and it will one
day be recognized as the imaginative classic of that divine art."</p>
<p>"Counterparts" and other tales soon followed.  And about the same
date she presented, anonymously, a volume of stories to the young
daughter of Mr. John Hullah, of "Part Music" celebrity.  They were in
manuscript printing, (if such a term may be used,) written by her own
hand, and remarkable for their curious beauty.  The heading of each
story was picked out in black and gold.  The stories are named
"Adelaide's Dream," "Little Wonder, or, The Children's Fairy," "The
Bird of Paradise," "Spromkari," (from a Scandinavian legend,) "The
First Concert," "The Concert in the Hollow Tree," "Uncle, or, Which is
the Prettiest?" "Little Ernest," "The Nautilus Voyage."  These stories are
illustrated, and have a lovely dedication to the little lady for whom they
were written.</p>
<p>The author had attended the "Upper Singing-Schools" for the sake
of more musical experience.  Yet she then sang at sight perfectly, with
any number of voices.  She has left three published songs, dedicated to
the Marchioness of Hastings, and a large number of manuscript
poems.</p>
<p>Her character was in perfect keeping with the high tone of her
books.  Noble, generous, and self-forgetting, tender and most faithful in
friendship, burning with indignation at injustice shown to another,
longing to find virtues instead of digging for faults,&mdash;
her greatest
suffering arose from pained surprise, when persons proved themselves
less noble than she had deemed them.</p>
<p>Her rich imagination and slender purse were open to all beggars,
but for herself she asked nothing, and was constantly a willing sufferer
from her own inability to toady a patron or to make a good bargain with
a publisher.</p>
<p>She felt most warmly for her friends in America, whose
comprehension of her views, and honest, open appreciation of her books,
inspired her with an ardent desire to write for them a romance in her
very best manner.  She had sketched two, and, doubtful which to
proceed with first, contemplated sending both to an American friend for
his decision; but constant suffering stayed her hand.</p>
<p>In the early spring she grew weaker day by day, and died on the
18th of March, at Brixton, in England, at the age of thirty-two.</p>
<p>Those who loved either her person or her works will find her place
forever empty. </p>
<p>Among her manuscript papers I found this sketch, which has a
peculiar significance now that the writer has passed away.  It has never
been printed.</p>

 <pb n="500"/>
<p>                  A NICHE IN THE HEART </p>
<p>I HAD been wandering, almost all day, in the cathedral of a town
at some distance from London.  I had sketched its carved pulpit, one or
two cherub faces looking down from its columns, some of its best
reliefs, and its oldest monument.  It was evening, and I could no longer
see to draw, though pencillings of light still fell on the pavement through
the larger windows, whose colors were softened like those of the lunar
rainbow; and still the edges of the stalls were gilded with the last gleams
of sunset, though the seats were filled already with those phantoms
which twilight seems to create in such a place.  The monuments looked
calmer and less formal than when daylight bared all their defects of
design or finish; they seemed now worthy of their position beneath the
vaulted roof, and even adjuncts themselves to the harmony of the
architecture.  One among them, noticeable in the daytime for its refined
workmanship, now gleamed out fresher and whiter than the rest, as was
natural, for it had been placed there but a little while; but it had besides
more <hi rend="italic">expression</hi>, in its very simplicity, than such-like
mementos of stone or marble usually contain.  This was the memento of
a husband's regret, and, as such, touching, however vain: a delicate
form drooping on a bier, at whose head stood an angel, with an infant in
his arms, which he raised to heaven with an air of triumph; while at the
foot of the death-bed a figure knelt, in all the relaxed abandonment of
woe.  Marvellously, and out of small means, the chisel had conveyed
this impression; for the kneeling figure was mantled from head to foot,
and had its face hidden in the folds of the drapery which skirted the bier,
&mdash; veiled, like the face of the tortured father in the old tragic tale.</p>

<p>While I gazed, I insensibly approached the still group; and while
musing what manner of grief it might be, which could solace by
perpetuating its mere image, I observed two other persons, whose
entrance I had not been aware of, but whose attention was evidently
directed to what had attracted mine.  They were a lady and a gentleman,
and the latter seemed actually supporting the former, who leaned heavily
upon his arm, as it appeared from her manner of carriage, so weakly and
wearily she stood.  Her form was extremely slight, and the outline of her
countenance sharp from attenuation, and in that uncertain light, or rather
shade, she looked almost as pale as the carved faces before us.  The
gentleman, who was of a stately height, bent over her with an anxious
air, while she gazed fixedly upon the monument.  Her silence seemed to
oppress him, for after a minute or two he asked her whether it was not
very beautiful.  "You know," she answered, in one of those low voices
that are more impressive than the loudest, "You know I always suspect
those memorials.  I would rather have a niche in the heart."</p>
<p>They passed on, and left me standing there.  I know not whether
the fragile speaker has earned the monument she desired, whether those
feeble footsteps have found their repose, &mdash; "a quiet conscience in a quiet
breast," &mdash; but her words struck me, and I have often thought of them
since.</p>
<p>There is always something which seems less than the intention in a
monument to heroism or to goodness, the patriot of the country, or the
missionary of civilization.  Every one feels that the graves of War, the
many in the one, where link is welded to link in the chain of glory, are
more sublime, more sacred, than the exceptional mausoleum.  Every one
has been struck with repugnant melancholy in the city church-yard,
where tomb presses against tomb, and multitude in death destroys
identity, saving where the little greatness of wealth or rank may provide
itself a separate railing or an overtopping urn.  Even in the more
suggestive solitude of the country, one cannot but contrast the few
hillocks here and there carefully weeded, and their trained and tended
rose-bushes, with the many more neglected and sunken, whose distained
stones

 <pb n="501"/>
the brier-tangle half conceals, and whose forget-me-nots have long since
died for want of water.  One may even muse unprofitably (despite the
moralist) in our picturesque cemeteries, and as unprofitably in those
abroad, with their crowds of crosses and monotony of immortal wreaths.
In fact, whether on grounds philosophical or religious, it is not good to
brood on mortality for itself alone; better rather to recall the living past,
and in the living present prepare for the perfect future.</p>
<p>None die to be forgotten who deserve to be remembered.  Even
the fame for which some are ardent to sacrifice their lives, enjoyed early
at that crisis of existence we call <hi rend="italic">success</hi>, will in most cases
change the desire for renown into a necessity, and stimulate the mind to
the lowest motive but one, ambition, &mdash;  possibly, to emulation, the
lowest of all.  Fame is valuable simply as the test of excellence; and
there is a certain kind of popularity, sudden alike in its rise and
subsidency, which deserves not the other and lasting name, for it fails to
soothe that intellectual conscience which a great writer has declared to
exist equally with the moral conscience.  After all, it is a question
whether fame is as precious to the celebrated during their lifetime as it is
to those who love them, or who are attached to them by interest.</p>
<p>There are persons who die and are forgotten, when their exit from
the stage of human affairs is a source of advantage to their survivors.
Witness those possessed of large fortunes, which they have it in their
power to bequeath, and over whose dwellings of mortality vigilant
relations hover like the carrion-fowl above the dying battle-steed.  I
remember a good story to this effect, in which a lady and gentleman
took a grateful vow to pic-nic annually, on the anniversary of his death,
at the tomb of a relation who had greatly enriched them.  They did so,
actually, <hi rend="italic">once</hi>; succeeding years saw them no more at the
solemn tryst.</p>
<p>Even as to those who have excelled in art, or portrayed in
language the imaginative side of life, it may be that their works abide
and they not be recognized in them, that their words may be echoed in
many tongues while the writer is put out of the question almost as
entirely as he who carved the first hieroglyph on the archaic stone.  It
will ever be found, whether in works or words, that what touches the
heart rather than what strikes the fancy, what draws the tear rather than
excites the smile, will embalm the memory of the man of genius.  But of
all post-humous distinctions the noblest is that awarded to the
philanthropist; even the meed of the man of science, which consists in
the complete working of some great discovery skilfully applied, falls
short of the reward of those who have contributed their utmost to the
physical improvement and social elevation of man, &mdash; from the
munificent endowment whose benefits increase and multiply in each
succeeding generation, to the smallest seed of charity scattered by the
frailest hand, as sure as the strong to gather together at the harvest its
countless sheaves.  To fill a niche in a heart, or a niche in each of a
thousand hearts, &mdash; <hi rend="italic">either</hi> a holier place than that of the poet,
who lives in the imagination he renders restless, or that of the hero, who
renders the mind more restless still for his suggestion of the glory which
may surround a name, a glory rather to be dreaded than desired, &mdash; too
often, in such cases, must evil be done or tolerated that good may be
brought forth.</p>
<p>Then there is consolation for those not gifted either with worldly
means or powers of mind or healthful daring.  Some will ever remember
and regret the man or woman who carries true feeling into the affairs of
life, important or minute: gentle courtesies, heart-warm words, delicate
regards, &mdash; as surely part of consummate charity as the drop is a portion
of the deep whose fountains it helps to fill.  Precious, too, is self-denial,
not austerely invoked from conscience by the voice of duty, but welling
from the heart as a natural and necessary return for all it owes to a
Power it cannot reward.  It has been

 <pb n="502"/>
said, that, to be respected in old age, one should be kind to <hi rend="italic">little
children</hi> all one's life.  May we not, therefore, show just such
helpful tenderness to the childlike or appealing weakness of every person
with whom we have to do? &mdash; for few hearts, alas! have not a weak
string.  Then no burden shall be left to the last hour, except that of
mortality, of which time itself relieves us kindly, &mdash; nor shall we have an
account to settle with the future to which it consigns the faithful.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
