<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="ArnCivi"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>


<TEI.2 id="ArnCivi">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Civilisation in the United States</title>
<title type="sort">civilisation in the united states</title>
<author>Arnold, Matthew</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Stephen Railton</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">33</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">ArnCivi</idno>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475695</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Civilisation in the United States</title>
<title level="j">The Nineteenth Century, Vol. XXIII, No. 134</title>
<title type="sort">civilisation in the united states</title>
<author>Matthew Arnold</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 481-496</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Kegan Paul, Trench, &amp; Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
<date value="1888-04">April 1888</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVA Library call number AP4 .N7 v. 23</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1888">1888</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
<language id="de">German</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; non-fiction</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-06">June 1997</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Carol Osborne, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="article" id="d3">
	<pb n="486" id="ArnCivi486"/>
	<head><hi rend="italic">From</hi> Civilization in the United States.<lb/>
	By Matthew Arnold</head>
	
<p>The Nineteenth Century<lb/>Vol. XXIII.&mdash;No. 134. April 1888.<lb/></p>

<p>...But we must get nearer still to the heart of the question raised
as to the character and worth of American civilisation. I have said how
much the word civilisation really means&mdash;the humanisation of man in
society; his making progress there towards his true and full humanity.
Partial and material achievement is always being put forward as
civilisation. We hear a nation called highly civilised by reason of its
industry, commerce, and wealth, or by reason of its liberty or equality,
or by reason of its numerous churches, schools, libraries, and
nevrspapers. But there is something in human nature, some instinct of
growth, some law of perfection, which rebels against this narrow account
of the matter. And perhaps what human nature demands in civilisation,
over and above all those obvious things which first occur to our
thoughts&mdash;what human nature, I say, demands in civilisation, if it is to
stand as a high and satisfying civilisation, is best described by the
word <hi rend="italic">interesting</hi>. Here is the extraordinary charm of the old

 <pb n="487" id="ArnCivi487"/>
Greek civilisation&mdash;that it is so <hi rend="italic">interesting</hi>. Do not tell me
only, says human nature, of the magnitude of your industry and commerce;
of the beneficence of your institutions, your freedom, your equality; of
the great and growing number of your churches and schools, libraries and
newspapers; tell me also if your civilisation&mdash;which is the grand name
you give to all this development&mdash;tell me if your civilisation is
<hi rend="italic">interesting</hi>.</p>

<p>An American friend of mine, Professor Norton, has lately published
the early letters of Carlyle. If any one wants a good antidote to the
unpleasant effect left by Mr. Froude's <hi rend="italic">Life of Carlyle</hi>, let him
read those letters. Not only of Carlyle will those letters make him
think kindly, but they will also fill him with admiring esteem for the
qualities, character, and family life, as there delineated, of the
Scottish peasant. Well, the Carlyle family were numerous, poor, and
struggling.  Thomas Carlyle, the eldest son, a young man in wretched
health and worse spirits, was fighting his way in Edinburgh. One of his
younger brothers talked of emigrating. 'The very best thing he could
do!' we should all say. Carlyle dissuades him. 'You shall never,' he
writes, 'you shall never seriously meditate crossing the great Salt Pool
to plant yourself in the Yankee-land. That is a miserable fate for any
one, at best; never dream of it. Could you banish yourself from all that
is interesting to your mind, forget the history, the glorious
institutions, the noble principles of old Scotland&mdash;that you might eat a
better dinner, perhaps?'</p>

<p>There is our word launched&mdash;the word <hi rend="italic">interesting</hi>. I am not
saying that Carlyle's advice was good, or that young men should not
emigrate. I do but take note, in the word <hi rend="italic">interesting</hi>, of a
requirement, a cry of aspiration, a cry not sounding in the imaginative
Carlyle's own breast only, but sure of a response in his brother's
breast also, and in human nature.</p>

<p>Amiel, that contemplative Swiss whose journals the world has been
reading lately, tells us that 'the human heart is, as it were, haunted
by confused reminiscences of an age of gold; or rather, by aspirations
towards a harmony of things which every day reality denies to us.' He
says that the splendour and refinement of high life is an attempt by the
rich and cultivated classes to realise this ideal, and is 'a form of
poetry.' And the interest which this attempt awakens in the classes
which are not rich or cultivated, their indestructible interest in the
pageant and fairy tale, as to them it appears, of the life in castles
and palaces, the life of the great, bears witness to a like imaginative
strain in them also, a strain tending after the elevated and the
beautiful. In short, what Goethe describes as 'was uns alle
b&#228;ndigt, <hi rend="italic">das Gemeine</hi>&mdash;that which holds us all in bondage,
the common and ignoble,' is, notwithstanding its admitted prevalence,
contrary to a deep-seated instinct of human nature and repelled by it.
Of civilisation, which is to humanise us

 <pb n="488" id="ArnCivi488"/>
in society, we demand, before we will consent to be satisfied with
it&mdash;we demand, however much else it may give us, that it shall give us,
too, the <hi rend="italic">interesting</hi>.</p>

<p>Now, the great sources of the <hi rend="italic">interesting</hi> are distinction
and beauty: that which is elevated, and that which is beautiful. Let us
take the beautiful first, and consider how far it is present in American
civilisation. Evidently this is that civilisation's weak side. There is
little to nourish and delight the sense of beauty there. In the
long-settled States east of the Alleghanies the landscape in general is
not interesting, the climate harsh and in extremes. The Americans are
restless, eager to better themselves and to make fortunes; the
inhabitant does not strike his roots lovingly down into the soil, as in
rural England. In the valley of the Connecticut you will find farm after
farm which the Yankee settler has abandoned in order to go West, leaving
the farm to some new Irish immigrant. The charm of beauty which comes
from ancientness and permanence of rural life the country could not yet
have in a high degree, but it has it in an even less degree than might
be expected. Then the Americans come originally, for the most part, from
that great class in English society amongst whom the sense for conduct
and business is much more strongly developed than the sense for beauty.
If we in England were without the cathedrals, parish churches, and
castles of the catholic and feudal age, and without the houses of the
Elizabethan age, but had only the towns and buildings which the rise of
our middle class has created in the modern age, we should be in much the
same case as the Americans. We should be living with much the same
absence of training for the sense of beauty through the eye, from the
aspect of outward things. The American cities have hardly anything to
please a trained or a natural sense for beauty. They have buildings
which cost a great deal of money and produce a certain
effect&mdash;buildings, shall I say, such as our Midland Station at St.
Pancras; but nothing such as Somerset House or Whitehall. One architect
of genius they had&mdash;Richardson. I had the pleasure to know him; he is
dead, alas! Much of his work was injured by the conditions under which
he was obliged to execute it; I can recall but one building, and that of
no great importance, where he seems to have had his own way, to be fully
himself; but that is indeed excellent. In general, where the Americans
succeed best in their architecture&mdash;in that art so indicative and
educative of a people's sense for beauty&mdash;is in the fashion of their
villa-cottages in wood. These are often original and at the same time
very pleasing, but they are pretty and coquettish, not beautiful. Of the
really beautiful in the other arts, and in literature, very little has
been produced there as yet. I asked a German portrait-painter, whom I
found painting and prospering in America, how he liked the country? 'How
<hi rend="italic">can</hi> an artist like it?' was his answer. The American artists
live chiefly

 <pb n="489" id="ArnCivi489"/>
in Europe; all Americans of cultivation and wealth visit Europe more and
more constantly. The mere nomenclature of the country acts upon a
cultivated person like the incessant pricking of pins.  What people in
whom the sense for beauty and fitness was quick could have invented, or
could tolerate, the hideous names ending in <hi rend="italic">ville</hi>, the
Briggsvilles, Higginsvilles, Jacksonvilles, rife from Maine to Florida;
the jumble of unnatural and inappropriate names everywhere? On the line
from Albany to Buffalo you have, in one part, half the names in the
classical dictionary to designate the stations; it is said that the
folly is due to a surveyor who, when the country was laid out, happened
to possess a classical dictionary; but a people with any artist-sense
would have put down that surveyor. The Americans meekly retain his
names; and indeed his strange Marcellus or Syracuse is perhaps not much
worse than their congenital Briggsville.</p>

<p>So much as to beauty, and as to the provision, in the United States, for the sense of beauty. As to
distinction, and the interest which human nature seeks from enjoying the effect made upon it by
what is elevated, the case is much the same. There is very little to create such an effect, very much
to thwart it. Goethe says somewhere that 'the thrill of awe is the best thing humanity has':&mdash;</p>
<p><q><foreign lang="de">
Das Schaudern ist der Menschheit bestes Theil.
</foreign>
</q></p>
<p>But, if there be a discipline in which the Americans are wanting, it is the discipline of awe and
respect. An austere and intense religion imposed on their Puritan founders the discipline of
respect, and so provided for them the thrill of awe; but this religion is dying out. The Americans
have produced plenty of men strong, shrewd, upright, able, effective; very few who are highly
distinguished. Alexander Hamilton is indeed a man of rare distinction; Washington, though he has
not the high mental distinction of Pericles or Caesar, has true distinction of style and character.
But these men belong to the pre-American age. Lincoln's recent American biographers declare
that Washington is but an Englishman, an English officer; the typical American, they say, is
Abraham Lincoln. Now Lincoln is shrewd, sagacious, humorous, honest, courageous, firm; he is a
man with qualities deserving the most sincere esteem and praise, but he has not distinction.</p>

<p>In truth everything is against distinction in America, and against the sense of elevation to be
gained through admiring end respecting it. The glorification of 'the average man,' who is quite a
religion with statesmen and publicists there, is against it. The addiction to 'the funny man,' who is
a national misfortune there, is against it. Above all, the newspapers are against it.</p>

<p>It is often said that every nation has the government it deserves.
What is much more certain is that every nation has the newspapers

 <pb n="490" id="ArnCivi490"/>
it deserves. The newspaper is the direct product of the want felt;
the supply answers closely and inevitably to the demand. I suppose no one knows what the
American newspapers are, who has not been obliged, for some length of time, to read either those
newspapers or none at all. Powerful and valuable contributions occur scattered about in them. But
on the whole, and taking the total impression and effect made by them, I should say that if one
were searching for the best means to efface and kill in a whole nation the discipline of respect, the
feeling for what is elevated, one could not do better than take the American newspapers. The
absence of truth and soberness in them, the poverty in serious interest, the personality and
sensation-mongering, are beyond belief. There are a few newspapers which are in whole, or in
part, exceptions. The <hi rend="italic">New York Nation</hi>, a weekly paper, may be paralleled with the
<hi rend="italic">Saturday Review</hi> as it was in its old and good days; but the <hi rend="italic">New York Nation</hi> is
conducted by a foreigner, and has an extremely small sale. In general, the daily papers are such
that when one returns home one is moved to admiration and thankfulness not only at the great
London papers, like the <hi rend="italic">Times</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">Standard</hi>, but quite as much at the great
provincial newspapers too&mdash;papers like the <hi rend="italic">Leeds Mercury</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Yorkshire Post</hi>
in the north of England, like the <hi rend="italic">Scotsman</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Glasgow Herald</hi> in
Scotland.</p>

<p>The Americans used to say to me that what they valued was news, and that this their newspapers
gave them. I at last made the reply: 'Yes, news for the servants' hall!' I remember that a New York
newspaper, one of the first I saw after landing in the country, had a long account, with the
prominence we should give to the illness of the German Emperor or the arrest of the Lord Mayor
of Dublin, of a young woman who had married a man who was a bag of bones, as we say, and
who used to exhibit himself as a skeleton; of her growing horror in living with this man, and
finally of her death. All this in the most minute detail, and described with all the writer's powers of
rhetoric. This has always remained by me as a specimen of what the Americans call news.</p>

<p>You must have lived amongst their newspapers to know what they are. If I relate some of my own
experiences, it is because these will give a clear enough notion of what the newspapers over there
are, and one remembers more definitely what has happened to oneself. Soon after arriving in
Boston, I opened a Boston newspaper and came upon a column headed: 'Tickings.' By
<hi rend="italic">tickings</hi> we are to understand news conveyed through the tickings of the telegraph. The
first 'ticking' was: 'Matthew Arnold is sixty-two years old'&mdash;an age, I must just say in passing,
which I had not then reached. The second 'ticking' was: 'Wales says, Mary is a darling;' the
meaning being, that the Prince of Wales expressed great admiration for Miss Mary Anderson. This
was at Boston, the

 <pb n="491" id="ArnCivi491"/>
American Athens. I proceeded to Chicago. An evening paper was given me
soon after I arrived; I opened it, and found under a large-type heading, '<hi rend="italic">We have seen him
arrive</hi>,' the following picture of myself: 'He has harsh features, supercilious manners, parts his
hair down the middle, wears a single eyeglass and ill-fitting clothes.' Notwithstanding this rather
unfavourable introduction I was most kindly and hospitably received at Chicago. It happened that
I had a letter for Mr. Medill, an elderly gentleman of Scotch descent, the editor of the chief
newspaper in those parts, the <hi rend="italic">Chicago Tribune</hi>. I called on him, and we conversed
amicably together. Some time afterwards, when I had gone back to England, a New York paper
published a criticism of Chicago and its people, purporting to have been contributed by me to the
<hi rend="italic">Pall Mall Gazette</hi> over here. It was a poor hoax, but many people were taken in and were
excusably angry, Mr. Medill of the <hi rend="italic">Chicago Tribune</hi> amongst the number. A friend
telegraphed to me to know if I had written the criticism. I, of course, instantly telegraphed back
that I had not written a syllable of it. Then a Chicago paper is sent to me; and what I have the
pleasure of reading, as the result of my contradiction, is this: 'Arnold denies; Mr. Medill [my old
friend] refuses to accept Arnold's disclaimer; says Arnold is a cur.'</p>

<p>I once declared that in England the born lover of ideas and of light could not but feel that the sky
over his head is of brass and iron. And so I say that, in America, he who craves for the interesting
in civilisation, he who requires from what surrounds him satisfaction for his sense of beauty, his
sense for elevation, will feel the sky over his head to be of brass and iron. The human problem,
then, is as yet solved in the United States most imperfectly; a great void exists in the civilisation
over there: a want of what is elevated and beautiful, of what is interesting.</p>

<p>The want is grave; it was probably, though he does not exactly bring it out, influencing Sir Lepel
Griffin's feelings when he said that America is one of the last countries in which one would like to
live. The want is such as to make any educated man feel that many countries, much less free and
prosperous than the United States, are yet more truly civilised; have more which is interesting,
have more to say to the soul; are countries, therefore, in which one would rather live.</p>

<p>The want is graver because it is so little recognised by the mass of
Americans; nay, so loudly denied by them. If the community over there
perceived the want and regretted it, sought for the right ways of
remedying it, and resolved that remedied it should be; if they said, or
even if a number of leading spirits amongst them said: 'Yes, we see what
is wanting to our civilisation, we see that the average man is a danger,
we see that our newspapers are a scandal, that bondage to the common and
ignoble is our snare; but under

 <pb n="492" id="ArnCivi492"/>
the circumstances our civilisation could
not well have been expected to begin differently. What you see are
<hi rend="italic">beginnings</hi>, they are crude, they are too predominantly
material, they omit much, leave much to be desired&mdash;but they could not
have been otherwise, they have been inevitable, and we will rise above
them;' if the Americans frankly said this, one would have not a word to
bring against it. One would <hi rend="italic">then</hi> insist on no shortcoming, one
would accept their admission that the human problem is at present quite
insufficiently solved by them, and would press the matter no further.
One would congratulate them on having solved the political problem and
the social problem so successfully, and only remark, as I have said
already, that in seeing clear and thinking straight on <hi rend="italic">our</hi>
political and social questions, we have great need to follow the example
they set us on theirs.</p>

<p>But now the Americans seem, in certain matters, to have agreed, as a
people, to deceive themselves, to persuade themselves that they have
what they have not, to cover the defects in their civilisation by
boasting, to fancy that they well and truly solve, not only the
political and social problem, but the human problem too. One would say
that they do really hope to find in tall talk and inflated sentiment a
substitute for that real sense of elevation which human nature, as I
have said, instinctively craves&mdash;and a substitute which may do as well
as the genuine article. The thrill of awe, which Goethe pronounces to be
the best thing humanity has, they would fain create by proclaiming
themselves at the top of their voices to be 'the greatest nation upon
earth,' by assuring one another, in the language of their national
historian, that 'American democracy proceeds in its ascent as uniformly
and majestically as the laws of being, and is as certain as the decrees
of eternity.'</p>

<p>Or, again, far from admitting that their newspapers are a scandal,
they assure one another that their newspaper press is one of their most
signal distinctions. Far from admitting that in literature they have as
yet produced little that is important, they play at treating American
literature as if it were a great independent power; they reform the
spelling of the English language by the insight of their average man.
For every English writer they have an American writer to match. And him
good Americans read; the Western States are at this moment being
nourished and formed, we hear, on the novels of a native author called
Roe, instead of those of Scott and Dickens. Far from admitting that
their average man is a danger, and that his predominance has brought
about a plentiful lack of refinement, distinction, and beauty, they
declare in the words of my friend Colonel Higginson, a prominent critic
at Boston, that 'Nature said, some years since: "Thus far the English is
my best race, but we have had Englishmen enough; put in one drop more of
nervous fluid and make the American." And with that drop a new range of
promise

 <pb n="493" id="ArnCivi493"/>
opened on the human race, and a lighter, finer, more highly
organised type of mankind was born.' Far from admitting that the
American accent, as the pressure of their climate and of their average
man has made it, is a thing to be striven against, they assure one
another that it is the right accent, the standard English speech of the
future. It reminds me of a thing in Smollet's dinner-party of authors.
Seated by 'the philosopher who is writing a most orthodox refutation of
Bolingbroke, but in the meantime has just been presented to the Grand
Jury as a public nuisance for having blasphemed in an alehouse on the
Lord's day'&mdash;seated by this philosopher is 'the Scotchman who is giving
lectures on the pronunciation of the English language.'</p>

<p>The worst of it is, that all this tall talk and self-glorification meets with hardly any rebuke from
sane criticism over there. I will mention, in regard to this, a thing which struck me a good deal. A
Scotchman who has made a great fortune at Pittsburg, a kind friend of mine, one of the most
hospitable and generous of men, Mr. Andrew Carnegie, published a year or two ago a book called
<hi rend="italic">Triumphant Democracy</hi>, a most splendid picture of American progress. The book is full of
valuable information, but religious people thought that it insisted too much on mere material
progress, and did not enough set forth America's deficiencies and dangers. And a friendly
clergyman in Massachusetts, telling me how he regretted this, and how apt the Americans are to
shut their eyes to their own dangers, put into my hands a volume written by a leading minister
among the Congregationalists, a very prominent man, which he said supplied a good antidote to
my friend Mr. Carnegie's book. The volume is entitled <hi rend="italic">Our Country</hi>. I read it through. The
author finds in evangelical Protestantism, as the orthodox Protestant sects present it, the grand
remedy for the deficiencies and dangers of America. On this I offer no criticism; what struck me,
and that on which I wish to lay stress, is, the writer's entire failure to perceive that such
self-glorification and self-deception as I have been mentioning is one of America's dangers, or
even that it is self-deception at all. He himself shares in all the self-deception of the average man
among his countrymen, he flatters it. In the very points where a serious critic would find the
Americans most wanting he finds them superior; only they require to have a good dose of
evangelical Protestantism still added. 'Ours is the elect nation,' preaches this reformer of American
faults&mdash;'ours is the elect nation for the age to come. We are the chosen people.' Already, says he,
we are taller and heavier than other men, longer lived than other men, richer and more energetic
than other men, above all, 'of finer nervous organisation' than other men. Yes, this people, who
endure to have the American newspaper for their daily reading, and to have their habitation in
Briggsville, Jacksonville, and Marcellus&mdash;this people is of finer, more delicate nervous
organisation than other

 <pb n="494" id="ArnCivi494"/>
nations! It is Colonel Higginson's 'drop more of nervous fluid over again.
This 'drop' plays a stupendous part in the American rhapsody of self-praise. Undoubtedly the
Americans are highly nervous, both the men and the women. A great Paris physician says that he
notes a distinct new form of nervous disease, produced in American women by worry about
servants. But this nervousness, developed in the race out there by worry, overwork, want of
exercise, injudicious diet, and a most trying climate&mdash;this morbid nervousness our friends ticket as
the fine susceptibility of genius, and cite it as a proof of their distinction, of their superior capacity
for civilisation! 'The roots of civilisation are the nerves,' says our Congregationalist instructor
again; 'and, other things being equal, the finest nervous organisation will produce the highest
civilisation. Now, the finest nervous organisation is ours.'</p>

<p>The new West promises to beat in the game of brag even the stout champions I have been
quoting. Those belong to the old Eastern States; and the other day there was sent to me a
Californian newspaper which calls all the Easterners 'the unhappy denizens of a forbidding clime,'
and adds: 'The time will surely come when all roads will lead to California. Here will be the home
of art, science, literature, and profound knowledge.'</p>

<p>Common-sense criticism, I repeat, of all this hollow stuff there is in America next to none. There
are plenty of cultivated, judicious, delightful individuals there. They are our hope and America's
hope; it is through their means that improvement must come. They know perfectly well how false
and hollow the boastful stuff talked is; but they let the storm of self-laudation rage, and say
nothing. For political opponents and their doings there are in America hard words to be heard in
abundance; for the real faults in American civilisation, and for the foolish boasting which prolongs
them, there is hardly a word of regret or blame, at least in public. Even in private, many of the
most cultivated Americans shrink from the subject, are irritable and thin-skinned when it is
canvassed. Public treatment of it, in a cool and sane spirit of criticism, there is none. In vain I
might plead that I had set a good example of frankness, in confessing over here, that, so far from
solving our problems successfully, we in England find ourselves with an upper class materialised,
a middle class vulgarised, and a lower class brutalised. But it seems that nothing will embolden an
American critic to say firmly and aloud to his countrymen and to his newspapers, that in America
they do not solve the human problem successfully, and that with their present methods they never
can. Consequently the masses of the American people do really come to believe all they hear
about their finer nervous organisation, and the rightness of the American accent, and the
importance of American literature; that is to say, they see things not as they are, but as they would
like them to be; they deceive themselves

 <pb n="495" id="ArnCivi495"/>
totally. And by such self-deception they shut against
themselves the door to improvement, and do their best to make the reign of <hi rend="italic">das Gemeine</hi>
eternal. In what concerns the solving of the political and social problem they see clear and think
straight; in what concerns the higher civilisation they live in a fool's paradise. This it is which
makes a famous French critic speak of 'the hard unintelligence of the people of the United
States'&mdash;la dure inintelligence des Am&#233;ricains du Nord&mdash;of the very people who in general
pass for being specially intelligent&mdash;and so, within certain limits, they are. But they have been so
plied with nonsense and boasting that outside those limits, and where it is a question of things in
which their civilisation is weak, they seem, very many of them, as if in such things they had no
power of perception whatever, no idea of a proper scale, no sense of the difference between good
and bad. And at this rate they can never, after solving the political and social problem with
success, go on to solve happily the human problem too, and thus at last to make their civilisation
full and interesting.</p>

<p>To sum up, then. What really dissatisfies in American civilisation is the want of the
<hi rend="italic">interesting</hi>, a want due chiefly to the want of those two great elements of the interesting,
which are elevation and beauty. And the want of these elements is increased and prolonged by the
Americans being assured that they have them when they have them not. And it seems to me that
what the Americans now most urgently require, is not so much a vast additional development of
orthodox Protestantism, but rather a steady exhibition of cool and sane criticism by their men of
light and leading over there. And perhaps the very first step of such men should be to insist on
having for America, and to create if need be, better newspapers.</p>

<p>To us, too, the future of the United States is of incalculable importance. Already we feel their
influence much, and we shall feel it more. We have a good deal to learn from them; we shall find
in them, also, many things to beware of, many points in which it is to be hoped our democracy
may not be like theirs. As our country becomes more democratic, the malady here may no longer
be that we have an upper class materialised, a middle class vulgarised, and a lower class
brutalised. But the predominance of the common and ignoble, born of the predominance of the
average man, is a malady too. That the common and ignoble is human nature's enemy, that, of
true human nature, distinction and beauty are needs, that a civilisation is insufficient where these
needs are not satisfied, faulty where they are thwarted, is an instruction of which we, as well as
the Americans, may greatly require to take fast hold, and not to let go. We may greatly require to
keep, as if it were our life, the doctrine that we are failures after all, if we cannot eschew vain
boasting and vain imaginations, eschew what flatters in us the common and ignoble, and approve
things that are truly excellent.</p>

 <pb n="496" id="ArnCivi496"/>
<p>I have mentioned evangelical Protestantism. There is a text which evangelical Protestantism&mdash;and
for that matter Catholicism too&mdash;translates wrong and takes in a sense too narrow. The text is that
well-known one: 'Except a man be born again he cannot see the kingdom of God.' Instead of
<hi rend="italic">again</hi>, we ought to translate <hi rend="italic">from above</hi>; and instead of taking the kingdom of God
in the sense of a life in Heaven above, we ought to take it, as its speaker meant it, in the sense of
the reign of saints, a renovated and perfected human society on earth, the ideal society of the
future. In the life of such a society, in the life <hi rend="italic">from above</hi>, the life born of inspiration or
<hi rend="italic">the spirit</hi>&mdash;in that life elevation and beauty are not everything; but they are much, and they
are indispensable. Humanity cannot reach its ideal while it lacks them: 'Except a man be born
<hi rend="italic">from above</hi>, he cannot have part in the society of the future.'</p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>


