<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AusBask"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="AusBask">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Basket Maker</title>
<title type="sort">basket maker</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">16</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AusBask</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475700</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Basket Maker</title>
<title type="sort">basket maker</title>
<author>Mary Austin</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<date value="1903">1903</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>91</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 235-238</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1903">1903</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-11">November 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>TEI tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="235"/>
<head>
Austin, Mary.
"The Basket Maker."
<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 91 (1903): 235-238.<lb/>
</head>
<p>"A MAN," says Seyavi of the campoodie, "must have a woman, but
a woman who has a child will do very well."
</p><p>That was perhaps why, when she lost her mate in the dying
struggle of his race, she never took another, but set her wit to
find for herself and her young son.  No doubt she was often put to
it in the beginning to find food for them both.  The Paiutes had
made their last stand at the border of the Bitter Lake; battle-driven they died in its waters, and the land filled with cattlemen
and adventurers for gold: this while Seyavi and the boy lay up in
the caverns of the Black Rock and ate tule roots and fresh-water
clams that they dug out of the slough bottoms with their toes.  In
the interim, while the tribes swallowed their defeat, and before
the rumor of war died out, they must have come very near to the
bare core of things.  That was the time Seyavi learned the
sufficiency of mother wit, and how much more easily one can do
without a man than might at first be supposed.
</p><p>To understand the fashion of any life, one must know the land
it is lived in and the procession of the year.  This valley is a
narrow one, a mere trough between hills, a draught for storms,
hardly a crow's flight from the sharp Sierras of the Snows to the
curled, red and ochre, uncomforted, bare ribs of Waban.  Midway of
the grove runs a burrowing, dull river, nearly a hundred miles from
where it cuts the lava flats of the north to its widening in a
thick, tideless pool of a lake.  Hereabouts the ranges have no
foothills, but rise up steeply from the bench lands above the
river.  Down from the Sierras, for the east ranges have almost no
rain, pour glancing white floods toward the lowest land, and all
beside them lie the campoodies, brown wattled brush heaps, looking
east.
</p><p>In the river are mussels, and reeds that have edible white
roots, and in the soddy meadows tubers of joint grass; all these at
their best in the spring.  On the slope the summer growth affords
seeds; up the steep the one-leaved pines, an oily nut.  That was
really all they could depend upon, and that only at the mercy of
the little gods of frost and rain.  For the rest it was cunning
against cunning, caution against skill, against quacking hordes of
wild fowl in the tulares, against pronghorn and bighorn and deer.
You can guess, however, that
<pb n="236"/>
all this warring of rifles and
bowstrings, this influx of overlording whites, had made game wilder
and hunters fearful of being hunted.  You can surmise also, for it
was a crude time and the land was raw, that the women became in
turn the game of the conquerors.
</p><p>There used to be in the Little Antelope a she dog, stray or
outcast, that had a litter in some forsaken lair, and ranged and
foraged for them, slinking savage and afraid, remembering and
mistrusting humankind, wistful, lean, and sufficient for her young.
I have thought Seyavi might have had days like that, and have had
perfect leave to think, since she will not talk of it.  Paiutes
have the art of reducing life to its lowest ebb and yet saving it
alive on grasshoppers, lizards, and strange herbs, and that time
must have left no shift untried.  It lasted long enough for Seyavi
to have evolved the philosophy of life which I have set down at the
beginning.  She had gone beyond learning to do for her son, and
learned to believe it worth while.
</p><p>In our kind of society, when a woman ceases to alter the
fashion of her hair, you guess that she has passed the crisis of
her experience.  If she goes on crimping and uncrimping with the
changing mode, it is safe to suppose she has never come up against
anything too big for her.  The Indian woman gets nearly the same
personal note in the pattern of her baskets.  Not that she does not
make all kinds, carriers, water-bottles, and cradles, &mdash; these are
kitchen ware, &mdash; but her works of art are all of the same piece.
Seyavi made flaring, flat-bottomed bowls, cooking pots really when
cooking was done by dropping hot stones into water-tight food
baskets, and for decoration a design in colored bark of the
procession of plumed crests of the valley quail.  In this pattern
she had made cooking pots in the golden spring of her wedding year,
when the quail went up two and two to their resting places about
the foot of Oppapago.  In this fashion she made them when, after
pillage, it was possible to reinstate the housewifely crafts.
Quail ran then in the Black Rock by hundreds, &mdash; so you will still
find them in fortunate years, &mdash; and in the famine time the women cut
their long hair to make snares when the flocks came morning and
evening to the springs.
</p><p>Seyavi made baskets for love and sold them for money, in a
generation that preferred iron pots for utility.  Every Indian
woman is an artist, &mdash; sees, feels, creates, but does not
philosophize about her processes.  Seyavi's bowls are wonders of
technical precision, inside and out the palm finds no fault with
them, but the subtlest appeal is in the sense that warns us of
humanness in the way the design spreads into the flare of the bowl.
There used to be an Indian woman at Olancha who made bottle-neck
trinket baskets in the rattlesnake pattern, and could accommodate
the design to the swelling bowl and flat shoulder of the basket
without sensible disproportion, and so cleverly that you might own
one a year without thinking how it was done; but Seyavi's baskets
had a touch beyond cleverness.  The weaver and the warp lived next
to the earth and were saturated with the same elements.  Twice a
year, in the time of white butterflies and again when young quail
ran neck and neck in the chaparral, Seyavi cut willows for basketry
by the creek where it wound toward the river against the sun and
sucking winds.  It never quite reached the river except in far
between times of summer flood, but it always tried, and the willows
encouraged it as much as they could.  You nearly always found them
a little farther down than the trickle of eager water.  The Paiute
fashion of counting time appeals to me more than any other
calendar.  They have no stamp of heathen gods nor great ones, nor
any succession of moons as have red men of the East and North, but
count forward and back by the progress of the season; the time of
<pb n="237"/>
<hi rend="italic">taboose</hi>, before the trout begin to leap, the end of the
pinon harvest, about the beginning of deep snows.  So they get
nearer the sense of the season, which runs early or late according
as the rains are forward or delayed.  But whenever Seyavi cut
willows for baskets was always a golden time, and the soul of the
weather went into the wood.  If you had ever owned one of Seyavi's
golden russet cooking bowls with the pattern of plumed quail, you
would understand all this without saying anything.
</p><p>Before Seyavi made baskets for the satisfaction of desire, for
that is a house-bred theory of art that makes anything more of it,
she danced and dressed her hair.  In those days, when the spring
was at flood and the blood pricked to the mating fever, the maids
chose their flowers, wreathed themselves, and danced in the
twilights, young desire crying out to young desire.  They sang what
the heart prompted, what the flower expressed, what boded in the
mating weather.
</p><p>"And what flower did you wear, Seyavi?"
</p><p>"I, ah, &mdash; the white flower of twining (clematis), on my body
and my hair, and so I sang: &mdash;
</p>
<l>"I am the white flower of twining</l>
<l>Little white flower by the river,</l>
<l>Oh, flower that twines close by the river;</l>
<l>Oh, trembling flower!</l>
<l>So trembles the maiden heart."</l>
<p>
So sang Seyavi of the campoodie before she made baskets, and in her
later days laid her arms upon her knees and laughed in them at the
recollection.  But it was not often she would say so much, never
understanding the keen hunger I had for bits of lore and the "fool
talk" of her people.  She had fed her young son with meadow larks'
tongues, to make him quick of speech; but in late years was loath
to admit it, though she had come through the period of unfaith in
the lore of the clan with a fine appreciation of its beauty and
significance.
</p><p>"What good will your dead get, Seyavi, of the baskets you
burn?" said I, coveting them for my own collection.
</p><p>Thus Seyavi, "As much good as yours of the flowers you strew."
</p><p>Oppapago looks on Waban, and Waban on Coso and the Bitter
Lake, and the campoodie looks on these three; and more, it sees the
beginning of winds along the foot of Coso, the gathering of clouds
behind the high ridges, the spring flush, the soft spread of wild
almond bloom on the mesa.  These first you understand are the
Paiute's walls, the other his furnishings.  Not the wattled hut is
his home, but the land, the winds, the hill front, the stream.
These he cannot duplicate at any furbisher's shop as you who live
within doors, who if your purse allows may have the same home at
Sitka and Samarcand.  So you see how it is that the homesickness of
an Indian is often unto death, since he gets no relief from it;
neither wind nor weed nor skyline, nor any aspect of the hills of
a strange land sufficiently like his own.  So it was when the
government reached out for the Paiutes, they gathered into the
Northern Reservation only such poor tribes as could devise no other
end of their affairs.  Here, all along the river, and south to
Shoshone land, live the clans who owned the earth, fallen into the
deplorable condition of hangers-on.  Yet you hear them laughing at
the hour when they draw in to the campoodie after labor, when there
is a smell of meat and the steam of the cooking pots goes up
against the sun.  Then the children lie with their toes in the
ashes to hear tales; then they are merry, and have the joys of
repletion and the nearness of their kind.  They have their hills,
and though jostled, are sufficiently free to get some fortitude for
what will come.  For now you shall hear the end of the basket
maker.
</p><p>In her best days Seyavi was most like Deborah, deep bosomed,
broad in the hips, quick in counsel, slow of speech, esteemed of
her people.  This was that Seyavi who reared a man by her own
<pb n="238"/>
hand, her own wit, and none other.  When the townspeople began
to take note of her &mdash; and it was some years after the war before
there began to be any towns &mdash; she was then in the quick maturity of
primitive women; but when I knew her she seemed already old.
Indian women do not often live to great age, though they look
incredibly steeped in years.  They have the wit to win sustenance
from the raw material of life without intervention, but they have
not the sleek look of the women whom the social organization
conspires to nourish.  Seyavi had somehow squeezed out of her daily
round a spiritual ichor that kept the skill in her knotted fingers
long after the accustomed time, but that also failed.  By all
counts she would have been about sixty years old when it came her
turn to sit in the dust on the sunny side of the wickiup, with
little strength left for anything but looking.  And in time she
paid the toll of the smoky huts and became blind.  This is a thing
so long expected by the Paiutes that when it comes they find it
neither bitter nor sweet, but tolerable because common.  There were
three other blind women in the campoodie, withered fruit on a
bough, but they had memory and speech.  By noon of the sun there
were never any left in the campoodie but these or some mother of
weanlings, and they sat to keep the ashes warm upon the hearth.  If
it were cold, they burrowed in the blankets of the hut; if it were
warm, they followed the shadow of the wickiup around.  Stir much
out of their places they hardly dared, since one might not help
another; but they called, in high, old cracked voices, gossip and
reminder across the ash heaps.
</p><p>Then, if they have your speech or you theirs, and have an hour
to spare, there are things to be learned of life not set down in
any books, folk tales, famine tales, love and longsuffering and
desire, but no whimpering.  Now and then one or another of the
blind keepers of the camp will come across to where you sit
gossiping, tapping her way among the kitchen middens, guided by
your voice that carries far in the clearness and stillness of mesa
afternoons.  But suppose you find Seyavi retired into the privacy
of her blanket, you will get nothing for that day.  There is no
other privacy possible in a campoodie.  All the processes of life
are carried on out of doors or behind the thin, twig-woven walls of
the wickiup, and laughter is the only corrective for behavior.
Very early the Indian learns to possess his countenance in
impassivity, to cover his head with his blanket.  Something to wrap
around him is as necessary to the Paiute as to you your closet to
pray in.
</p><p>So in her blanket Seyavi, sometime basket maker, sits by the
unlit hearths of her tribe and digests her life, nourishing her
spirit against the time of the spirit's need, for she knows in fact
quite as much of these matters as you who have a larger hope,
though she has none but the certainty that having borne herself
courageously to this end she will not be reborn a coyote.
</p>
<signed><hi rend="italic">Mary Austin.</hi></signed>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
