<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AusDulc"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;

]>

<TEI.2 id="AusDulc">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Agua Dulce</title>
<title type="sort">agua dulce</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss ( )</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">17</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AusDulc</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475703</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Agua Dulce</title>
<title level="j">Harper's Weekly</title>
<title type="sort">agua dulce</title>
<author>Mary Austin</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harper &amp; Brothers</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1999-08-28">28 Aug 1909</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>53</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Austin, Mary.  "Agua Dulce."  <hi rend="italic">Harper's Weekly</hi> 53, 28 Aug.  1909: 22-23.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1909-08-28">28 August 1909</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Native American</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-03">March 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<item>on page 22, paragraph 9, line 1, I have changed 'when to "when.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="1996-03">March 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header; Tagged with TEI.2-compatible SGML; Parsed against local "teilite" dtd.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">



<front id="d2">
<titlePage id="d3"><pb n="22"/>
<docTitle><titlePart type="main">
                            Agua Dulce
</titlePart></docTitle>
<byline>By <docAuthor>Mary Austin</docAuthor>

                   ILLUSTRATIONS BY DENMAN FINK</byline>
</titlePage>
</front>

<body id="d4">
<div1 type="story" id="d5">

<p>THE Los Angeles special got in so late that day that if the driver
of the Mojave stage had not, from having once gone to school to me,
acquired the habit of minding what I said, I should never have made
it.  I hailed it from the station, and he swung the four about in
the wide street as the wind swept me toward the racked old coach in
a blinding whirl of dust.
</p><p>It wrapped my skirts about the iron gear of the coach as I
climbed to the seat beside the driver, and, as we dropped the town
behind us, lifted my hat and searched out my hairpins.  But it was
the desert wind<note type="omission"><p>[illustration omitted]</p></note> and the smell it carried was
the smell of marrow-fat weed and gilias after the sun goes down;
so, because I had been very unhappy away from it, and was now drunk
with the joy of renewal, and as in my case there would be no time
for a toilet proper to the road until we came to the Eighteen-Mile
House, I was satisfied merely to cling to the pitching front of the
coach and let the wind do what it would.  The sky was alight and
saffron-tinted, the mountains bloomed with violet shadows; as we
came whirling by the point of Dead-Man we saw the wickiups of the
Paiutes, and the little hearth fires all awink among the sage.
They had a look of home.
</p><p>"There's some," said the driver to the desert at large, "that
thinks Indians ain't properly folks, but just a kind of cattle;"
then, as we jolted forward in a chuck, he swore deeply and brought
the team about, putting back my instinctive motion to steady the
lurching stage with a gesture so sharp and repellent that I sat up
suddenly in offence.
</p><p>"Don't you go for to mind me," he said, only half mindful
himself of what he had done, and went on staring after the hearth
fires of the Paiutes.  By which I knew there was a story there that
had something to do with the twilight fires and the homey look of
the little huts.  Hours later, when we came out on the mesa above
Red Rock, white star-froth flecking the black vault over us and the
road white between the miles of low black sage before, we had got
to this point in it.
</p><p>"It was out there," he said, waving his whip toward the gulf
of blackness, "when I was doin' assessment work for McKenna, nigh
to the end of nowhere, I . . . took up with an Indian woman."  He
hurried past this admission with intent to cover it from possible
reproach, telling how McKenna had dumped him with three months'
grub by a water-hole called Agua Dulce, distant a mile or two from
the claims he was expected to work.
</p><p>"Because," he said, "it was cheaper than packin' water, me
bein' alone, and McKenna, for some reason I never rightly guessed,
keen to keep the business on the quiet.  McKenna would be visitin'
me once a month or so, and I 'lowed I wouldn't be lonesome much,"
he laughed, "and I didn't after I . . . took up with Catameneda.
</p><p>"Seems like white women can't get to understand why a man
takes up with a mahala.  They think it's just badness and so
they're down on it . . . maybe it is with some. . . . but not when
they are like . . . like me . . . and Catameneda. . . .  There's
something away down in a man that his own womenfolks never
understand . . . an' you spend all your life trying to keep them
from understanding . . . though when there's one that does she
plays hell with you. . . .  It ain't badness. . . .  I don't know
rightly what, only it ain't all bad . . . but Catameneda . . . she
understood . . . and I was glad to have her."
</p><p>The wind died along the sage and there was no sound under
heaven louder than the grind of the wheels and the clink of the
harness chains.  Presently he returned upon his track to say that
he had been a month at Agua Dulce, going and returning from the
mines each day to his little camp kit, laid under a square of
canvas with stones upon it to keep it from the wind.  He had cached
the bulk of his supplies behind the spring and congratulated
himself on it when at the close of one day he found a camp of
Indians at Agua Dulce.
</p><p>"You know how it is with these desert tribes," said the stage-driver, "every camp looks as if it might have been there for a
hundred years, and when they go there's no more left than a last
year's bird-nest.  They just scramble up out of nothing and melt
away in the sand like a horned toad.  But they was friendly . . .
sort of . . . when you got to know them . . . and the men talked
English considerable. . . .  Evenings, when a kind of creepy chill
comes on, they get around their little fires and crack their jokes
. . . good jokes, too . . . there was one old buck real comical .
. . he used to explain them in English afterward.  And when they
sang their songs . . . when the fires were lit and the voices came
out of the dark, and you couldn't see the dirt nor the color of
their skins, you would sort of forget they wasn't your own folks.
</p><p>"And so," he said after a longer silence, "when the camp went
on another <hi rend="italic">pasear</hi> . . . Catameneda . . . she stayed."  That
was all I was ever to know of that phase of it.  "Catameneda . .
stayed."  That and the flicker in his voice cast up from the things
in him that only the Indian woman could understand, that lit the
situation through his scanty speech like the glow of those vanished
fires.
</p><p>. . . "It was a sort of pretty place at Agua Dulce," said he.
"The spring came out from the black rock into a basin with a gurgly
sound.  There was a pink flowering bush behind it and a smitch of
green where it ran over into the sand . . . and the rest was sage-brush, little and low; and crumply, colored hills.  There were
doves came and built in the flowering shrubs, for they hadn't no
fear of man . . . and 'Maneda, she fed them."
</p><p>He was silent, letting his whip-lash trail outside in the
sand, and I had a long time in which to consider how young he was,
and how much younger he must have been when he drank sweet water
out there at Agua Dulce, before he began again.
</p><p>"She was mighty lovin'," he said, and suddenly I saw the whole
tale, as I had constructed it ahead of his halting speech, fall
apart and rebuild itself to a larger plan as he went on to say how,
when he came from the mine at night and had no caress for her, she
would begin to droop and to grieve, to flood with tears and heavy
sobbing like a hurt child, which he could still in a moment with a
hand upon her hair.  And how he would pretend a harshness at times,
to see her flash and glow with the assurance of tenderness renewed,
which he laughed at her for never learning.  Sweet water indeed, at
Agua Dulce!
</p><p>By this time I knew the story had come to some uncommon end
that lifted it beyond the vulgar adventure of satiety and
desertion, for there was no yellowness in the boy that he should
blab upon the tenderness of women.  There was a good hour yet until
we came to Coyote Holes, and I meant to have it all out of him by
then.  The end had come very quickly.  It began in their growing
careless through happiness and neglecting the cache.  Then one day
when he was at the mine, and Catameneda setting snares for quail in
the black rock, a thieving prospector rifled it and left them
wofully short of food.  Five days of desertness lay between them
and any possible base of supplies, and McKenna was not due until
the twenty-ninth.  They took stock and decided to hold out on short
rations until he came.  They were very merry about it, being so
young, and Catameneda knew the way to piece out their fare with
roots and herbs.  She promised him he should learn to eat lizards
yet, as Indians do.  And then suddenly the boy fell sick of a
dysentery, which he thought might have come from some mistaken
economy of Catameneda's in the matter of canned food.  And while he
was prostrated with that, came the sand-storm.  The girl had sensed
it, Indian fashion, days before it came, but he was loggy with
weakness and the want of proper care, and let her warning pass.
Then came a night of gusty flaws; the morning showed a wall of
yellow cloud advancing on them from the south.
</p><p>All that country around Agua Dulce is solid rock, and
fluctuant sand that moves before the wind with a small shrill
rustle, and no trail can lie in it when the wind blows more than
twenty-four hours.  On this occasion it blew for three days.
</p><p>"Time was," said the driver, "I'd lie awake nights to mill it
over and over.  Times I'd think I could have done better, times
again I didn't know as I could.  I was too sick to think much and
'Maneda was mighty uneasy, all for gettin' forward on the trail to
meet McKenna who would be comin' toward <pb n="23"/>  us.  She calculated
he would stop at Beeman's till the storm was past, not knowin' we
were short.  And the wind would blow three days.  I don't know how
she knew, but she knew.  She kept holding up her fingers to show me
how many days, and forgetting what English I had taught her; and
between that and me being fair locoed with sickness, I gave in.  I
don't know if we wouldn't have done better to stick it out at Agua
Dulce.  And again I don't know as we would."
</p><p>They took the canteen and such food as they had and set out
for the next water-hole; by noon the sand-storm overtook them.  The
push of the wind was steady and they tacked along the edge of it
without too much discomfort.  The boy was pitifully weak, and
Catameneda laughed as she braced him with her firm young body.  The
dark fell early, the wind increased and roared against them, the
boy chilled in the night, grew feverish, and Catameneda was reduced
to hiding the canteen to save their scanty drink.  By all counts
they should have reached the first water-hole that day, but did not
until the next noon.  And the storm had been before them.  The sand
lay clean white and drifted smooth over all that place.  Come
another winter, the spring would work its way to the surface
perhaps, but now they could not so much as guess where to dig for
it.  They walked on and on, Catameneda leading with his hand in
hers.  This day they faced the wind.  The girl's hair blew back and
he held it to his eyes to shield them from the tormenting sting of
the sand.  The water and food held out better than he expected.
</p><p>He said that he thought Catameneda must have waked him in the
night when there was a lull in the wind, for he seemed to remember
crawling long distances on hands and knees, and other times he
leaned upon her body and heard her voice, but did not seem to see
her.  Always they travelled in a fury of wind and a biting smother
of sand.
</p><p>"I don't know how 'Maneda pulled me through," he said, "but
she did.  All I remember was the beginning of the basalt wall at
the root of Black Mountain, and right away after that the drip of
the spring, though it's two mile from where the rock begins.  I was
long past bein' hungry, but I jest naturally swallowed in that
water; and it ain't any great water neither, not like the water at
Agua Dulce.  But Catameneda she didn't seem to care for none."
</p><p>He paused so long here that if I had not known his kind very
well I should have thought it all the story he meant to let me
have, but at last:
</p><p>"I reckon I was light-headed," he said, "else I should have
sensed what was the matter, but I don't know but it was best as it
was.  I couldn't have done nothin'.  We lay on the sand far spent
and sick, the wind was going down and we could breathe better under
the wall.  I heard her kind of choke up every little, and by and by
she was talking quiet-like, in her own language, and I made out she
wanted her mother . . . she wasn't more than seventeen, I should
think. . . .  It was cold, too, and I'd lost my blanket somewhere
back on the trail, not bein' able to say where. . . .  I snuggled
her up in my arms, kind of shivery-like . . . and by and by . . .
she knew me, puttin' her hand up to my face a way she had . . . and
sayin' in English, as I had taught her . . . 'Vera good boy, mucha
like.' . . .  And it didn't seem no time at all after that when it
was broad morning and the wind was down . . . her hair on my face
. . . and she was heavy on my arm. . . .
</p><p>"I sat up and laid her on the sand. . . .  It was too much for
her . . . all she had been through . . . bein' so young . . . and
she had given me all the food and all the water . . . though I
hadn't felt to know it before.  I knew it as soon as I looked at
her. . . .  I reckon she had a hemorrhage or something . . . there
was blood on her face and sleeves like she wiped it from her
mouth."
</p><p>Out in the blackness toward Agua Dulce a coyote howled, and
night freshened for a sign of morning.
</p><p>"McKenna came through by noon and we buried her," he finished,
simply, "under a pink flowering bush because she loved it.  I
worked on a ranch in the valley for two years after that. . . .  I
couldn't<note type="omission"><p>[illustration omitted]</p></note> seem to abide the desert for a
spell . . . nor the little fires . . . but I got over that . . .
you know how that is."
</p><p>"Yes, I know how that is."
</p><p>"But I don't suppose anybody knows," he went on, reflectively,
"how it is that I don't think of her dead any more, nor any of that
hard time we had . . . only sometimes when it's spring like this
and I smell sage-brush burning . . . it reminds me . . . of some
loving way she had out there . . . at Agua Dulce."
</p><p>A man's story like that is always so much more satisfactory
because he tells you all the story there is, what happened to him
and how he felt about it, supposing his feelings are any part of
the facts in the case, but with a woman it is not so.  She never
knows much about her feelings unless they are pertinent to the
story, and then she leaves them out.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

