<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AusFrus"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="AusFrus">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Frustrate</title>
<title type="sort">frustrate</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">23</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AusFrus</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475705</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Frustrate</title>
<title type="sort">frustrate</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Edited by</resp>
<name>editor</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Century Magazine</publisher>
<date value="1912-01">Jan. 1912</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Vol. 83</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Verification made against printed text</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1912">1912</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman and Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head>
Austin, Mary.  "Frustrate."
<lb/>
Author of "The Land of Little Rain," "The Arrow-maker," etc.
</head>
<pb n="467"/>
<p>
I KNOW that I am a disappointed woman and that nobody cares at all
about it, not even Henry; and if anybody thought of it, it would
only be to think it ridiculous.  It is ridiculous, too, with my
waist, and not knowing how to do my hair or anything.  I look at
Henry sometimes of evenings, when he has his feet on the fender,
and wonder if he has the least idea how disappointed I am.  I even
have days of wondering if Henry isn't disappointed, too.  He might
be disappointed in himself, which would be even more dreadful; but
I don't suppose we shall ever find out about each other.  It is
part of my disappointment that Henry has never seemed to want to
find out.
</p><p>There are people who think it is somehow discreditable to be
disappointed; and whatever comes, you must pretend to like it, and
just keep on pretending.  I don't know why.  It must be that some
things are right in life and some others are not, and unless
somebody has the courage to speak up about it, I don't know how we
are ever to find it out.  I don't see, if nobody else is hurt by
it, why we shouldn't have what we like out of life; and if there's
a way of getting or not getting it, people have a right to know.
Sometimes I think if I'd known a little more, just a very little .
. . !
</p><p>It all began, I suppose, in the kind of people I was brought
up among.  They'd none of them had the kind of things I wanted, so
of course they couldn't tell me anything about the way to get them.
There was my mother.  She had to work hard, and had never been
anywhere but to a Methodist conference and once to the capital when
father was a delegate or something, and her black silk had been
turned twice; but she didn't seem the least disappointed.  I think
it must have been the way things were between her and my father.
Father died when I was sixteen, so I couldn't tell much about it,
but I know mother never so much as thought of marrying again.  She
was like a person who has had a full meal, but I&mdash;I am just kind of
hungry . . . <hi rend="italic"> always</hi>.  My mother never talked to me about her
relations to my father.  Mothers didn't; it wasn't thought
suitable.  I think sometimes, if she had, it might have made a
difference about my marrying Henry.
</p><p>The trouble was in the beginning, that though I knew the world
was all full of exciting, interesting things, I thought they came
to you just by living.  I had no idea there was a particular way
you had to go to work to get them.  I think my people weren't the
kind to make very nice discriminations about experiences or
anything.  They wouldn't have thought one way of being in love, for
instance, was much better or different from another.  They had
everything sort of ticketed off and done with: such as that all
church-members were happier than unbelievers, and all men naturally
more competent and intelligent than their women.  They must have
known, some of them, that things didn't always work out that way;
but they never let on about it&mdash;anyway, not to us young people.
And if married couples weren't happy together, it wasn't considered
decent to speak of it.
</p><p>I suppose that was what got me to thinking that all the deep
and high and shining things that I had a kind of instinct went with
being married, belonged to it naturally, and, when you had found a
suitable man, came along in their proper place without much
thinking.  And that was about all I knew when Henry proposed to me
at the Odd Fellows' Festival.  We were both on the <pb n="468"/>
decoration committee, and drove out to the old Lawson place that
afternoon for roses.  I remember the feel of them against my cheek,
hot and sweet, and the smell of the syringa, and a great gold-and-black butterfly that fled and flitted down the green country road,
mottled black and gold with shadows.  Things like that gave me a
strange kind of excitement, and yet a kind of lonesomeness, too, so
I didn't mind Henry holding my hand between us in the buggy.  I
thought he must be feeling something of the same sort, and it
didn't seem friendly to take my hand away.  But I did take it away
a moment later when he proposed.  It turned me kind of cold.  Of
course I meant to accept him after a while.  I liked him, and he
was what my folks called suitable; but I seemed to want a little
time to think about it.
</p><p>Henry didn't want me to think.  He kept hinting, and that
evening under the grape-arbor at the minister's, where we had gone
to get the sewing society's ice-cream freezer, he kissed me.  I'd
heard about engaged kisses, but this wasn't anything but just a
kiss&mdash;like when you have been playing drop the handkerchief.  I'd
always had a feeling that when you had an engaged kiss something
beautiful happened.  There were times afterward when it almost
seemed about to, and I would want to be kissed again to see if the
next time . . .  Henry said he was glad I had turned out to have an
affectionate disposition.
</p><p>My family thought I was doing well to marry Henry.  He had no
bad habits, and his people were well-to-do; and then I wasn't
particularly pretty or rich or anything.  I had never been very
popular with young men; I was too eager.  Not for them, you
understand; but just living and doing things seemed to me such a
good game.  I suppose it is difficult for some folks to understand
how you can be excited by the way a shadow falls, or a bird singing
on a wet bough; and somehow young men seemed to get the idea that
the excitement had something to do with them.  It made them feel as
if something was expected of them; and you know how it is with
young men: they sort of pull back from the thing that is expected
of them just because it is expected.  I always thought it rather
small, but I suppose they can't help it.  There was a woman I met
at Fairshore who explained how that was; but I didn't know it then,
and I was rather sensitive about it.  Anyway, it came about that I
hadn't many beaux, and my mother was a good deal relieved when I
settled down to Henry.  And we hadn't any more than got the
furniture as we wanted it when I discovered that there hadn't
anything happened at all!  Instead of living with my mother, I was
just living with Henry; I've never done anything else.
</p><p>There are things nobody ever tells young girls about marriage.
Sometimes I think it is because, if they knew how to estimate their
experience in the beginning, there is such a lot they wouldn't go
on with; and when I was married, nobody ever thought of anything
but that you had to go on with it.  There were times when it seemed
as if all it needed was just going on: there was a dizzying point
just about to be reached from which Henry and I should really set
out for somewhere.
</p><p>It took me fifteen years to realize that we hadn't set out for
anything, and would never get anywhere in particular.
</p><p>I know I tried.  Times I would explain to Henry what I wanted
until he seemed to want it as much as I did; and then we would
begin whatever we had to do,&mdash;at least I would begin,&mdash;and then I
would find out that Henry had forgotten what we were doing it for&mdash;
like the time we saved to set out the south lot in apricots, and
Henry bought water-shares with the money.  He said it would be
cheaper to own the water for the apricots; but then we hadn't
anything left to pay for the planting, and the man who had sold
Henry the shares turned out not to own them.  After a while I gave
up saving.
</p><p>The trouble was, Henry said, I was too kind of simple.  It
always seemed to me, if you wanted things, you picked out the one
nearest to you, and made a mark so you could keep tab on whether
you were getting it or not; and then you picked out the next
nearest, and went for that, and after a while you had all of them.
But Henry said when it came to business it was a good deal more
complicated, and you had to look on all sides of a thing.  Henry
was strong on looking on all sides; anybody that had any kind of
reasonableness could always get over him, like that man with the
water-shares.  That was when I was trying to make myself believe
that if <pb n="469"/>  we could get a little money together, we might be
in things.  I had been reading the magazines, and I knew that there
were big, live things with feelers out all over creation, and if I
could just get the least little tip of one. . . .  But I knew it
wasn't money.  When I wasn't too sick and overworked and worn out
trying to keep track of Henry's reasons, I knew that the thing I
was aching for was close beside me . . . when I heard the wind walk
on the roof at night, . . . or heard music playing . . . and I
would be irritated with Henry because he couldn't help me lay hold
of it.  It is ridiculous, I know, but there were times when it
seemed to me if Henry had been fatter, it would have helped some.
I don't mean to say that I had wanted to marry a fat man, but Henry
hadn't filled out any, not like it seems men ought to: he just got
dry and thinner.  It used to make me kind of exasperated.  Henry
was always patient with me; he thought it was because I hadn't any
children.  He would have liked children.  So would I when I thought
I was to have one, but I was doing my own housework, and I was
never strong.  I cried about it a good deal at the time; but I
don't suppose I really wanted it very much or I would have adopted
one.  I will tell you&mdash;there are women that want children just for
the sake of having them, but the most of them want them because
there is a man&mdash;  And the man they want gets to hear of it, and
whenever a woman is any way unhappy, they think all she needs is a
baby.  But there's something else ought to happen first, and I
never gave up thinking it was going to happen; all the time I kept
looking out, like Sister Anne in the fairy-tale, and it seemed to
me a great many times I saw dust moving.  I never understood why we
couldn't do things right here at home&mdash;big things.  There were
those people I'd read about in Germany&mdash;just plain carpenters and
butchers and their wives&mdash;giving passion-plays.  They didn't know
anything about plays; they just felt grateful, and they did
something like they felt.  I spoke to the minister's wife about it
once&mdash;not about a passion-play, of course, that wouldn't have done;
but about our just taking hold of something as if we thought we
were as good as those Germans,&mdash;but she didn't seem to think we
could.  She kind of pursed up her mouth and said, "Well, we must
remember that they had the advantage of having lived abroad."  It
was always like that.  You had to have lived somewhere or been
taught or had things different; you couldn't just start right off
from where you were.  It was all of a piece with Henry's notion of
business; there was always some kind of queer mixed-up-ness about
it that I couldn't understand.  But still I didn't give up thinking
that somehow I was going to pull the right string at last, and then
things would begin to happen.  Not knowing what it was I wanted to
happen, I couldn't be expected to realize that it couldn't happen
now on account of my being married to Henry.  It was at Fairshore
that I found out.
</p><p>It was when we had been married eighteen years that Aunt Lucy
died and left me all her property.  It wasn't very much, but it was
more than Henry would ever have, and I just made up my mind that I
was going to have the good of it.  Henry didn't make any objection,
and the first thing I did was to go down to Fairshore for the
summer.  I chose Fairshore because I had heard about all the
authors and painters being there.  You see, when you never have any
real life except what you get from reading, you have a kind of
feeling that writers are the only real <hi rend="italic"> own</hi> folks you've got.
You even get to thinking sometimes that maybe, if you had known how
to go about it, you could have written yourself, though perhaps
you'd feel that way about bridge-building or soldiering, if it was
the only real kind of work you saw much of.  Not that I ever
thought I could write; but I had so many ideas that were exactly
like what I'd read that I thought if I could only just get somebody
to write them for me&mdash;  But you can't; they've all got things of
their own.  Still, you would think the way they get inside the
people they write about that they would be able to see what is
going on inside of you, and be a little kind.
</p><p>You see, it had come over me that away deep inside of me there
was a really beautiful kind of life, singing, and burning blue and
red and gold as it sang, and there were days when I couldn't bear
to think of it wasting there and nobody to know.
</p><p>Not that Henry didn't take an interest in me,&mdash;his kind of
interest,&mdash;if I was sick or hurt, or seeing that I had a
comfortable <pb n="470"/>  chair.  But if I should say to Henry to lean
upon my heart and listen to the singing there, he would have sent
for the doctor.  Nobody talks like that here in Castroville: only
in books I thought I had heard the people calling to one another
quietly and apart over all the world, like birds waking in a wood.
I've wondered since I came back from Fairshore if people put things
in books because they would like to have them that way.
</p><p>It is difficult to tell what happened to me at Fairshore.  It
didn't really happen&mdash;just the truth of things coming over me in a
slow, acrid dribble.  Sometimes in the night I can feel the
recollection of it all awash at the bottom of my heart, cold and
stale.  But nothing happened.  Nobody took any notice of me but one
woman.  She was about my age, plain-looking and rather sad.  I'd be
proud to mention her name; but I've talked about her a great deal,
and, with all my being so disappointed, it isn't so bad but it
might be worse if everybody got to find out about it.  She was
really a much greater writer than the rest of them; but, I am
ashamed to say it, just at first, perhaps because she was so little
different from me on the outside, and perhaps just because she was
a woman, I didn't seem to care much about her.  I don't know why I
shouldn't say it, but I did want to have something to do with
interesting men.  People seem to think that when a woman is married
she has got all that's coming to her; but we're not very different
from men, and <hi rend="italic"> they</hi> have to have things.  There are days
sometimes when it seems to me that never to have known any kind of
men but Henry and the minister and old man Truett, who does our
milking, would be more than I could bear.  I thought if I could get
to know a man who was big enough so I couldn't walk all around him,
so to speak,&mdash;somebody that I could reach and reach and not find
the end of,&mdash;I shouldn't feel so&mdash;so frustrated.  There was a man
there who wrote things that made you feel like that,&mdash;as if you
could take hands with him and go out and rescue shipwrecked men and
head rebellions.  And when I tried to talk to him, I found him
looking at me the way young men used to before I married Henry&mdash;as
if he thought I wanted something, and it was rather clever of him
not to give it to me.  It was after that that I took to sitting
with the writer woman.  I'd noticed that though the men seemed to
respect her, and you saw them in corners sometimes reading
manuscripts to her, they never took her to walk, or to see the moon
rise, or the boats come in.  They spent all that on the pretty
women, young and kind of empty-headed.  I'd heard them talk when
they thought I wasn't listening.  And the writer woman sat about
with the other women, and didn't seem to mind it.
</p><p>I hoped when people saw me with her, they'd think it was
because she was so famous, and not guess how terrible it was to
find yourself all at once a middle-aged woman sitting on a bench,
and all the world going by as if it was just what they expected.
It came over me that here were all the things I had dreamed
about,&mdash;the great sea roaring landward, music, quick and gay;
looks, little incidents,&mdash;and I wasn't in it; I wasn't in it at
all.
</p><p>I suppose the writer woman must have seen how it was with me,
but I thought at first she was talking of herself.
</p><p>"It's all very wonderful out there, isn't it?" she said,
looking toward the blue water and the beach shining like a shell,
with the other writers and painters walking up and down and making
it into world stuff.  "Very wonderful&mdash;when you have the price to
pay for it!"
</p><p>"It <hi rend="italic"> is</hi> expensive."  I was thinking of the hotel, but I saw
in a minute she meant something else.
</p><p>"The price you pay," she said, "it isn't being fit to be in
the Great World or being able to appreciate it when you're in; it
is what you contribute to keep other people in, I suppose."
</p><p>I must have said something about not being able to see what
the kind of women who were in contributed&mdash;just girls and flirty
kind of married women.
</p><p>"It's a kind of game, keeping other people in," said the
writer woman.  "They don't know much else, but they know the game.
We are, most of us," she said, "like those matches that will not
light unless they are struck upon the box: there is a particular
sort of person that sets us off.  It's a business, being that sort
of person."
</p><p>"If anybody could only learn it&mdash;"  I tried to seem only
polite.
</p><p>"It is the whole art," she said, "of putting yourself into
your appearance."  She <pb n="471"/>  laughed.  "I have too much waist for
that sort of thing.  I have my own game."
</p><p>I seemed suddenly to want to get away to my room and think
about it.  I know it is absurd at my age, but I lay on the bed and
cried as I hadn't since they told me my baby hadn't lived.  For I
knew now that all that beautiful life inside me couldn't be born
either, for I was one who had to have help to be worth anything to
myself, and I didn't know the game.  I had never known it.
</p><p>All the time I had been thinking that all I needed was to find
the right person; and now I understood that, so far as anybody
could guess, I wasn't the right person myself.  I hadn't the art of
putting myself into my appearance.  I'm shy about talk, and my arms
are too fat, and my skirts have a way of hanging short in front.
</p><p>I've thought about it a great deal since.  It doesn't seem
fair.  Nobody told me about it when I was a girl; I think nobody
tells girls.  They just have to sort of find it out; and if they
don't, nobody cares.  All they did tell me was about being good,
and you will be happy; but it isn't so.  There is a great deal more
to it than that, and it seems as if people ought to know.  I think
we are mostly like that in Castroville: we've got powers and
capacities 'way down in us, but we don't know anything about
getting them out.  We think it is living when we have got
upholstered furniture and a top buggy.  I know people who think it
is worth while never to have lived in a house without a cupola.
But all the time we are not in the game.  We do not even know there
is a game.
</p><p>Sometimes I think, if it would do me any good, I could turn in
and learn it now.  I watched them at Fairshore, and it seemed to me
it could be learned.  I have wild thoughts sometimes,&mdash;such
thoughts as men have when they go out and snatch things,&mdash;but it
wouldn't do me any good.  Henry's folks were always long-lived, and
there are days when I am so down that I am glad to have even Henry.
As long as people see us going about together they can't know&mdash;
I'm rather looking forward to getting old now.  I think perhaps I
sha'n't ache so.  But I <hi rend="italic"> should</hi> like to know how much Henry
understands.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
