<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AusGold"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="AusGold">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Pot of Gold</title>
<title type="sort">pot of gold</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">21</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AusGold</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475706</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Page 491: "The map maker laugher." An error in the printed text
for "laughed"?</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Pot of Gold</title>
<title type="sort">pot of gold</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Edited by</resp>
<name>editor</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Munsey's Magazine</publisher>
<date value="1901-07">July 1901</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Vol. 25</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Verification made against printed text</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1901">1901</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman and Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head>
Austin, Mary.  "The Pot of Gold."
<lb/>
<hi rend="italic"> Munsey's Magazine</hi> 25 (July 1901): 491-495.
<lb/>
WHAT FERROL FOUND AND WHAT HE LOST IN THE PLAIN OF BITTER WATERS
</head>
<pb n="491"/>

<p>"THE thing is impossible."
</p><p>"Yes&mdash;but there's the pot; you can see for yourself."
</p><p>"Oh, that's likely enough.  You can't strike down to bed rock
anywhere in this country without getting colors.  The impossibility
is that you should find the place it came from, or, finding it,
that it should be profitable to work."
</p><p>"I wasn't thinking of working it."
</p><p>"Well, what <hi rend="italic"> do</hi> you want with it?"
</p><p>"Oh, to sell!"
</p><p>The map maker laugher.  "Ferrol," he said, "you haven't a
rudiment of conscience; not a trace."
</p><p>"Oh, come, it's not so bad as that.  People always bite at
these stories of buried treasure and lost mines.  They like to be
fooled that way.  And as for finding it, there is no great
difficulty about that, I take it.  A pot like this won't outlast a
generation, and these fellows get the material for their artifacts
from the same places time out of mind.  And gold has to be thick
where an Indian can't scoop up a handful of clay to make him a
cooking pot without getting it.  Why, man, the thing fairly reeks
with gold, good yellow gold."
</p><p>The map maker did not speak.  He bent above his instruments;
his lips moved softly as he worked.  The expedition was camped in
the swale of the Dripping Spring, where its waters gathered in a
rock basin under the wild almonds.  The desert fell away towards
Death Valley.  A blanket stretched upon tent stakes stood between
them and the sky.  Behind a hill shoulder Chio kept the camp for
his women folk, beginning to be incredibly busy, like ants, with
seeds and roots, dried grasshoppers, and the flesh of chuckwallas.
</p><p>Ferrol had found a cooking pot of an old, crude sort, shot
through with grains of yellow gold, in Chio's cooking camp.
</p><p>"I will not sell the pot," said Chio to all his chaffering.
</p><p>"Come, now, what will you do one of these days when the pot is
broken?  With the money I will give, you can buy iron pots that
will outlast you many such."
</p><p>"It has lasted since my father's time.  Will the pots of the
white man last longer than that?"
</p><p>"Confound the old rascal!" said Ferrol to himself.  "But tell
me, Chio, you who know so much, was the pot made by your own
people, or came it from the south?"
</p><p>"Of my own people, surely; what should I do with a pot of the
Arizonas?"
</p><p>"And made hereabouts?  I should like to know.  Perhaps, since
you will not sell, I shall make me a pot for myself."
</p><p>Tuyomai looked up from the fire she was stirring and laughed.
</p><p>"Tuyomai, go into the house," said her father.
</p><p>Ferrol knelt on the sand, sketching rapidly with his finger.
"Look, Chio, here is the desert; here is Armagossa; here the
Dripping Spring.  These are the mountains.  Is it here you make
pots?"
</p><p>"I think so; I no know," said Chio, relapsing from his own
speech into broken English, after the manner of Indians who do not
wish to understand.
</p><p>Ferrol gave him a cigar and began again.  "Is it here towards
the getting up of the sun?  Here?"
</p><p>"Maybe so&mdash;I think so, long time my people not make um.  I no
know."
</p><p>Ferrol, sweeping his map out with his hand, got up, laughing.
As he stood, the day lapsed suddenly.  The alpen-glow flowed in
evenly across the dead levels of burnt earths, and the round
browed, shouldering hills.  "A rainbow land," he said, and laughed
again a whimsical assent to his own conceit.  "A rainbow land, and
a pot of gold at the end of it!"
</p><p>Going back by the way he came, Fer-<pb n="492"/> rol met the bright,
regardful glance of Tuyomai from the chinks of the thin, twig woven
walls of the wickiup.  "The women," he said, struck by a sudden
thought.  "The women, of course; they are the pot makers.  I'll go
for the girl."
</p><p>The expedition had finished its work, and was for returning by
way of Pilot Knob, and thence across the Valley of Salt Wells to
the stage road going south.  Ferrol, it was given out by the map
maker, would forge north and east to the unnamed purple barrows
touching the desert rim, on the trail of some prehistoric ruins of
which he had word from Chio.
</p><p>"If you must go," said the map maker, "for goodness' sake,
don't let the expedition know what wild goose's feather has set you
off.  If this should get to headquarters, it would spoil your
chance of getting on the Peruvian expedition, and you know you've
set your heart on that."
</p><p>"Oh, that's all right!  Besides, it is really true&mdash;about the
ruins, I mean.  Tuyomai says they did not make the pot, but found
it near an ancient pottery.  The old man lied, it seems.  And
Tuyomai says that there are ruins there of hewn stone with pictures
on them.  Besides, I can hardly help finding something in this
country; why, man, it's in the air.  Tuyomai says&mdash;"
</p><p>"Does the girl go with you?" asked the map maker brutally.
</p><p>Ferrol laughed.  He had a quick insight and facility, and a
merry temper, that made him invaluable in difficult expeditions.
He had done some notable things, too, but the adventurous blood of
the Celt stood him in evil stead.  He liked the credit which his
work brought him, but government expeditions have limitations, and
more than anything else Ferrol desired a fortune, that he might go
adventuring upon his own account.  Clear through the soul of him he
loved a happy chance better than the price of conscious toil; so
now he would be off to the impossible borders of a barren land, on
the edge of the dry season, seeking a rainbow end.  But the map
maker was wrong about the girl.  Ferrol had no notion of burdening
a difficult way with woman's gear.
</p><p>The trail, straight away to the Borax Marsh, and north to the
red hill that the Defiance twisted through, and east again by the
California Girl, would bring him to the end of the mining country,
and thence across to the nameless hills as best he might.  The
landmarks the girl had given him were sure: a white, wind
sculptured chalk cliff, the tilted beds of vermilion earth, and the
black, cleaving outcrop between two beds of clay&mdash;coal, perhaps.
Well, that might be worth while also.  Ferrol counted two months to
his hazard, and made dry camp by starlight, having walked on into
the gentle night wide eyed with the first fever of his enterprise.
In the dark behind him a coyote howled, and he could hear the soft
<hi rend="italic"> push, push</hi>, of the burrowing owls clearing out of the trail,
and the crisping of sand under human foot.  Ferrol drew his
revolver and dropped it again, catching the stir of a woman's
dress.
</p><p>"Who?" he called across the gloom.
</p><p>"Tuyomai&mdash;I have brought you the pot."  She put it down from
her head and stooped beside it, still and wearied.
</p><p>"Oh, yes, the pot.  So the old man changed his mind, did he?"
</p><p>"My father does not know.  He is an old man&mdash;and the pot would
be mine."
</p><p>"Quite so.  Well, this is awkward; I have only a little silver
with me.  Will this do?"
</p><p>The girl did not move.  "Why should I take money?" she said.
"I have brought my father's pot.  And I cannot go back."
</p><p>The sky filled and filled with unwinking stars, and the soft
gloom grew into sound in the love notes of the burrowing owls.
Ferrol remembered, in the night, to be grateful that the expedition
had traveled well away from Dripping Spring the day before.
Waking, it fell in with his desert mood to see Tuyomai moving
softly, and not without grace, between him and the kindling fire.
Well, she knew, if any knew, where were the beds of golden sand,
and the time was past when the tribe would arise hot on his path
for the theft of a girl and a cooking pot.
</p><p>When they came to the Borax Marsh, the girl had wit enough to
turn out of the trail and wait for him on the other side; and again
when they came to the <pb n="493"/>  Defiance, where Ferrol replenished
his store; but by the time they came to the California Girl, he was
past caring.
</p><p>The thing began to take the color of a lotus eating dream; a
man and a woman free of all things in a big new land, a woman of
shining, gold colored limbs and black, deep lighted eyes, who loved
him dearly; a strong young life that trod the hills with him,
resourceful, tireless, and unafraid.  Ferrol thought how good the
days of the first pair must have been.  He thought once of the
women he had known, and forgot them utterly.
</p><p>Tuyomai had the wisdom of her people in foodful roots and
berries and the flesh of wild things.  The days broke softly
luminous upon rayed blossomings, and the dewless nights were deep
and sweet with sleep.
</p><p>All this time they had not found the golden sands.  Old
potteries they found, and strewn shards, clay beds of surpassing
qualities, mineral earths, chrome and vermilion, and huge
outcroppings of wasteful ore, but never the thing they sought.
</p><p>At the end of eight weeks Ferrol found, at the Defiance, a
letter from the map maker, calling him several kinds of a fool, for
the Peruvian expedition had been made up suddenly without him.
Ferrol sent in a report on the deposits of mineral earths, and went
back to the hills and Tuyomai.
</p><p>In golden noons, under the almond bushes, he taught her to
write upon the sands, and began to explore the lore of her people,
and to learn how many things a man may drop out of his life without
making himself unhappy.  So they fared along the rim of the aching
sand wastes, exploring the washes of forgotten streams, until they
came again to the Dripping Spring, where Tuyomai built him a
wattled hut; and while Ferrol dozed, she sat under the creosote
brushes, pondering, and writing upon the sand.  Ferrol came upon
one of these scrawls one day&mdash;his own name written large, and aside
and falteringly "Mrs. Ferrol."  He wiped it out hastily with his
foot, Tuyomai accepting the omen silently as becomes a woman of her
race.
</p><p>When the heat began to beat down the hollow of the valley,
insistent and palpable, they got them up to the high ridges and the
scant shadows of the fox-tail pines, and, when the heat was past,
back to the spring.  Here Ferrol built a hut such as miners use in
the rainless hills, for by this time he knew all that was in the
mind of Tuyomai when she wrote upon the sand.
</p><p>He meant, when he had made all safe for her, to go back to his
own; but when the fire was lit and the stars burned in the velvet
void, and Tuyomai huddled against his feet, silent as he was
silent, glowing when he glowed, he found that the taste of life was
good.  And always the cooking pot pricked him towards the golden
quest.  The desert wantoned with his intimate desires, kindled, and
promised, and withheld.  In the next luminous hollow, the farther
hidden hills&mdash;everywhere the secret pressed and warmed him.  And
the message of the imperturbable hills is that one must take no
account of mere days.
</p><p>The mail came up from Minton, and supplies in the ore wagon of
the Defiance.  Prospectors hailed him in his wanderings; gipsy
bands of Indians shifted from Panniment to Pilot Knob, and back by
way of the Dripping Spring, and Tuyomai made friends with their
women against her time of need.  By the time the almonds flowered
again, one came and dwelt by them in a little leafy hut, and
Tuyomai, gone back in time of stress to the habit of her kind, bore
him a son lying under the wattles by the rill of the spring.
</p><p>Ferrol showed his pot to the miners he met.  The things he
knew about it and the things he hoped were blown about in the
common talk, even as far as Angustora, and came back to him as a
thing long established and believed, of a forgotten treasure in a
hidden hill.  It would have been better for Ferrol in those days if
the little horned snake of the desert had bitten him, for there is
more wealth in that unstinted land than a man can look upon and
keep perfectly sane.  So in the end Ferrol went mad, stark, desert
mad; in all else orderly of speech and judgment, but mad.  And
Tuyomai made him very comfortable.
</p><p>Meanwhile the child grew and arrived at the age of speech.  At
first the bright blackness of its eyes and hair, so much <pb n="494"/>
darker against the mitigated blackness of its skin, was an offense
to Ferrol; but the clinging of its hands went through and through
him.
</p><p>By the time the boy could pull himself up babbling by his
father's knee, Ferrol understood that this was a son of his own
begetting, and required to be named.  "Light on the Mountain,"
Tuyomai called him, "Sweetwater," "Little Coyote," and the like
foolish women's phrases, but as yet he had no name by which a man
might be known.
</p><p>"And what will you be called, sonny?" said Ferrol, giving the
child a finger to hold by.
</p><p>"Very good," laughed Tuyomai.  "As thou art the great sun of
all my days, so he shall be Sunny, my little sun."  Tuyomai's
English lapsed in those days, since Ferrol had a fancy for speaking
her own speech.
</p><p>So Sonny he was called, and when he could run at his father's
heels for the better part of a day, Ferrol found no fault with his
life, though his fortune was not yet made, and he had not yet begun
his great work upon mineral deposits, with the promise of which he
sopped the promptings of an old ambition.
</p><p>Upon a day when the light broke rayed and luminous from every
blossoming herb, and the creosote, spreading down into the swale of
the spring, fretted the soft air with new leafage, Ferrol set forth
across the hills, and the child got up unbidden from his play to
follow.  Tuyomai, plaiting a basket under the wattles, saw them go.
</p><p>About noon the mail carrier from Minton called to her from the
road that he had seen the child straying alone on the Argus trail,
going further away from home.  Tuyomai knew instantly what had
happened.  Ferrol had not seen the child following, or, seeing, had
bidden him home, and Sonny had turned out of the trail to explore
on his own account.
</p><p>Tuyomai filled a canteen and the pitch smeared wicker water
bottle that her people use, took food, and bethought herself how
she might let Ferrol know, if he returned and found them gone.
"Sonny Ferrol passed this way," she wrote upon the door, for so
Ferrol had taught her to mark their trail when they two journeyed
out towards Armagossa in an unforgotten spring.  Then, her English
failing, she filled up the space with crude sketches, and cast
about from the beaten path to pick up the boy's trail with the
native craft and patience that wins against all speed.
</p><p>Ferrol, coming home about the time the twilight purple began
to fill between the hollow of the desert and the hollow sky, found
the writing on the door, and understood.  He looked at the embers
dead upon the hearth and the day dying along the hills; he ran to
the spring for water, and ate as he ran, knowing what was before
him.  Seeing the water bottle gone, he cast about for another
vessel that might hold water, and there, on the chimneypiece, stood
the cooking pot, in the net Tuyomai had made to carry it by.  He
caught it up as he ran, and thrust it gurgling into the spring.
</p><p>Ferrol found and followed the double trail until the night
closed.  He spent the dark hours fruitlessly, going down to the
cabin of a man he knew for help, and finding none.  At dawn he
picked up the trail where Tuyomai had marked it, Indian fashion, as
she went.  Ferrol had the explorer's instinct for topography, could
make straight away to a given landmark, and keep direction clear,
but he had not the Indian's trained faculties for tracking, and in
stony ground he was baffled.  It takes a strong man to deal with a
barren land and the madness that lies in the heart of it.  If he
knows no landmarks, and cannot pick up his back tracks, he is not
like to see his starting point again, and none but a skilled
tracker, following fast, shall find him.  Consider now if it be a
child that is lost, with the mother following, and the father hard
upon the trail of both.
</p><p>Ferrol followed the woman's trail, understanding by its
windings that she followed some trace of the child that he lacked
wit to see.  But there were traces later which he could understand,
body prints where it had stumbled, blood upon the cutting edges of
the black rocks, and crushed twigs where the child had thrust his
face in the midst of the thorns to be free of the burning sun.
</p><p>So he came at last, quite spent, and with little water, to a
place where all <pb n="495"/>  trace of the child failed, and the woman
had lain down and mourned over it.  From thence a strong, steady
trail ran down across a limitless, wind beaten sand flat.  Under
all the sky nothing moved to the eye, nor any speck showed that
might be a living thing; but that way the woman had gone, grief
crazed or moved by some swift certain hope, and that way went
Ferrol, for the woman had been to him as his wife, and the child
was his child.
</p><p>The desert has taken many men in its time, and the thirst
consumes like fire.  Ferrol was already far spent when he came to
the plain.  In the night a wind arose and covered all the trails
with drifted sand.
</p><p>The cabin stood by the Dripping Spring until the sun warped it
asunder, and a miner from Panniment way carried off the timbers to
patch his own dwelling; and there, when the door swings outward and
the light is strong, one might read a penciled scrawl, "Sonny
Ferrol passed this way."  In one of the wandering Indian tribes
that drift about the desert rim are a dull, withered woman, neither
young nor old, and a half white boy who answers to the name of
Sonny.
</p><p>Somewhere out in the plain of Bitter Waters are the bones of
a man, and away on the sand flat, where he cast it from him when he
ran in madness, and the hills mocked him as he ran&mdash;somewhere in
that rainbow land lies the pot of gold.

</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
