<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AusHour"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="AusHour">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The White Hour</title>
<title type="sort">white hour</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">24</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AusHour</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475708</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>changed "Augustora" to "Angustora" in line 9 of paragraph 4.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The White Hour</title>
<title type="sort">white hour</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Munsey's Magazine</publisher>
<date value="1903-04">April 1903</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Vol. 29</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Verification made against printed text</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1903-04">April 1903</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head>
Austin, Mary.  "The White Hour."
<lb/>
<hi rend="italic"> Munsey's Magazine</hi> 29 (April 1903): 88-92.
<lb/>
HOW EVALY JOHN, THE Paiute GIRL, BRIEFLY REALIZED THE AMBITION OF
HER FATHER, THE MEDICINE MAN.</head>

<pb n="88"/>

<p>
WHEN it was told Mono John that a daughter was born to him, he
named her after the most admirable white woman he knew, Eva Lee
Matheson, teacher of the Tres Pinos school.  He named her by ear,
so that the child came to be called Evaly.  Later, when she went to
school, and understood that children must be known by their
father's names, she called herself Evaly John.
</p><p>The naming his daughter for the village teacher meant more to
Mono John than the mere name's sake.  It was a devotion and a
consecration.  By dim and unguessed ways there had come to the
medicine man of the Paiutes a perception of knowledge as power,
especially that knowledge peculiar to white men, which must reside
in his people before the two races could come together upon
anything like equable terms.  Had he not seen, had he not proved?
By as much as he could spell a little, sign his name, make change,
and count the days of the month, could he not match himself better
against his white employer than his tribesmen?  Knowledge, then,
the mastery of books and plows and groaning mills, was to bring
back the great day of the Paiutes.
</p><p>Mono John hugged this perception to himself as it had been a
revelation, and found himself able, although he was then in middle
life and all his sons were dead, to rejoice that a daughter was
born.  It had not happened to him to see men as school-teachers,
and how else was knowledge to come to the campoodie of Tres Pinos
except one of their own women rose to that office?
</p><p>Concerning this matter you must have a word of explanation.
The Indians of Angustora had a longer exemption from over-lording
whites than most Western tribes; but the invaders came at last,
with the discovery of rich ores in those desert-compassed hills;
and after the first sharp resistance, made more futile by the
certainty of what had befallen their affiliated clans, the Paiutes
fell into the estate of hangers on.  Afterwards the arm of the
government reached out and gathered most of the tribe into the
Northern Reservation; but those of Angustora, finding life still
tolerable, and loving the land too much, chose to fend for
themselves, trusting the crafts and the gods of their fathers.
</p><p>They prospered better, on the whole, than their brothers of
the Reservation.  The land was big enough to keep them and a few
small mining towns without elbowing; their necessities kept them
active, and the standard of living in the settlements was not yet
too complex to serve as an example.  They established their
campoodies on the water borders near the towns, finding employment
on the ranches and among cattle men, and acquired an aptitude for
ready made clothing and tinned foods.  The women washed for the
village housewives, and copied the styles of their gowns, with
delicate stitchery and amazing hues; and all the evil that the
white people did the Paiutes did after them.
</p><p>Although the Indians of Angustora drew no rations, the
government gave them a gentle shove now and then along the line of
their noblest bent.  So it happened at Black Rock and Maverick that
when the little Paiutes grew too many and mischievous for the
gardens and orchards, the Indian commissioner sent them a teacher
and an order that they should be put to school.  Tres Pinos was the
smallest of the settlements, with perhaps a score of children; and
until the daughter of Mono John had seen the pink flush of wild
almond creep six times up the mesa from the town, there had never
been a Paiute put to school at Tres Pinos.
</p><p>Indians are good at waiting; so all those six summers Mono
John made no <pb n="89"/>  sign except what might have been guessed from
the fact that he was never heard to wish that Evaly had been a son.
What he meant, briefly, was that she should study to become a
teacher to her tribe.
</p><p>There is no law against Indian children attending the public
schools of the whites, only a prejudice; so when Mono John brought
his daughter to the schoolhouse door there seemed to be no reason
why she should not come in; provided, said the teacher, that she
was kept clean.  If you had seen Evaly's home, you might have
thought that an impossible condition.  It was like all Paiute huts,
a mere hole in the ground, planted round with willow boughs bent
over to form a dome, thatched with reeds and sod, snug, smoky, and
foul with the reek of unwashed bodies.  But somehow out of her love
and hand-craftiness the mother contrived to send the child daily in
clean cotton frocks, with braided hair, and a handkerchief&mdash;which
was washed every night&mdash;pinned to her belt; in short, not very
different from the children of the village.  How much of desire and
renunciation, pride, faith, and simple savagery, went down the
trail with her was hidden under the bronze impassivity of the
Indian, but enough of it filtered through to the teacher to make
her more than kind to shy, dumb, unsmiling little Evaly John.
</p><p>Every Friday the medicine man stood at the schoolhouse door to
hear the report of her progress, and found himself moved almost to
tears with pride of achievement when she was able to write his name
and her own.
</p><p>Things moved on in this fashion for half a dozen years, not
altering the faith and pride of Mono John, who was happily unaware
of what had been plain to the teacher for this long time.  Evaly
was dull; patient, untiring, lovable, but hopelessly dull.  In all
the time that she went to school&mdash;nearly ten years&mdash;she never got
beyond the third reader and the multiplication table, which latter
she did not understand.  The school at Tres Pinos grew to two
departments, but Evaly stayed on in the primary room until she was
head and shoulders taller than any child in it.  So, as her slow
wit perceived that the other children mocked her, she suffered as
martyrs do, until the teacher, in an unaccustomed flash of
understanding, moved her to the larger room.  There, though she
kept her old books, she moved and sat with children of her age.
</p><p>Evaly was not interesting, not even pretty, as many Paiute
children are, but stolid, broad-faced, with expressionless little
eyes, and coarse black hair growing low on her forehead.  How much
of all this was plain to Mono John can hardly be guessed, nor is it
of any use speculating what he would have done about it in any
case.  What happened was so much better, and, though grievous,
kinder, leaving no sting of thinking that Evaly failed of anything
required of her.
</p><p>Mono John was the medicine man of his campoodie; for though he
had sense of things as they should be, he was a Paiute of the
Paiutes.  Medicine men are chosen as the lot falls, but no one who
knows Indians can deny the existence of considerable clairvoyant
power among them, and more than a little knowledge of healing
herbs.  So though he was called upon to cure and curse, to detect
thefts and foretell events, Mono John maintained his position with
dignity and authority for fifteen years.  It is the law of the
Paiutes that when a medicine man loses three patients he must die
at the hands of the tribesmen, and every incumbent enters the
office with that understanding.
</p><p>Of his post and all that pertained to it, of his pride and
authority, of his growing unfaith in charms, Mono John talked to
Evaly.  Of the traditions of his people, and their spiritual
significance which the unwise take for fact, and of his revelation
concerning this thing called education, he talked often and long,
while the twilight fell and the rosy peak of Oppapago swam above
the dark.  To his wife, except as it concerned the love and care of
Evaly, he said little, for it is not seemly for a medicine man to
talk much with his women; but this chosen one, wise in the books of
white men, teacher to be, it was fit to counsel and instruct.
Evaly lifted her dull eyes to him, loving and believing, and burned
smolderingly towards the thought of that day when she should <pb n="90"/>
be white.  For this was the sense they had of the brotherhood of
man; that all that stood between brown and white was a matter of
books and ways and doings.  If either of them had a thought that
she might fail of her high emprise, each hid it carefully from the
other.  No doubt there were those in the campoodie who shook their
heads, and those who believed.
</p><p>So the time drew on towards the winter when Evaly should be
sixteen years old, and she still blundering in long division.  It
had been a bad year all through, the spring rains scanty and long
delayed, little water in the creeks, and few quail mating.  Late,
bitter frosts nipped the blossoms of the one-leaved pines, and cut
off from the Indians their winter store of oily pine nuts.  Along
in the fall of that year broke out an epidemic of pneumonia, or
something resembling it, carrying off great numbers of both white
and brown.  It was a quick sickness that took the strong and hardy
between two breaths.  It raged first among the whites, especially
among the mining camps in the north end of the valley, working
southward in the course of a month.  Then it broke out in the
campoodie, and ran with amazement and dismay the length of
Angustora.  The medicine men could do nothing, though they wearied
themselves with incantations; the drugs which came in bottles at
the stores lost their virtue; the white doctors, though they saved
some patients, could do nothing for those who lived in the leafy
huts and slept upon the ground.
</p><p>When a people wax fat and well content they run after strange
things, but in the hour of famine or pestilence they return to the
gods of their fathers.  Lax as the Paiutes had been of old customs,
they had not forgotten.  In all the campoodies there began to be
murmurs against the medicine men.  There had not been one killed in
the valley for fifteen years, partly because for the last killing
the whites had executed summary justice, and perhaps because there
had been no real occasion.  By a skilful use of his prerogatives,
which include the right to refuse attendance if another doctor has
been first called, and by keeping discreetly out of the reach of
doubtful cases, a medicine man may avoid the penalty for a long
time.
</p><p>But now in every hut there was mourning, in every mind
apprehension; unless help came swiftly there would be killing done
in the campoodie.  Word went out that there would be a gathering of
clans in each district to choose new medicine men&mdash;nothing said
about those still in office, but much understood.
</p><p>To Evaly and Mono John it came with the force of a death
warrant.  For whatever the medicine man of Tres Pinos believed, the
old customs bound.  Paiute he was, and after the manner of the
Paiutes he would die, even though he knew it to be foolishly.  It
came to this with him, that he said dumbly in his own fashion:
"Father, forgive them, they know not what they do"; but because of
the child who had not come to full years, he would have avoided it
if he could.
</p><p>Rumor of the impending tragedy ran in the wickiups and reached
even the whites in the towns.  At Black Rock the government teacher
stirred up influential citizens to warn and admonish the Paiutes;
but here at Tres Pinos the pestilence bit sore, and the townspeople
were busy with their own griefs.
</p><p>The medicine dance was set for Thursday night.  On Sunday Mono
John heard of it.
</p><p>"It is the law," he said, but he looked at Evaly and his heart
shook.
</p><p>His wife went into the hut and covered her head with her
blanket.  On Monday they heard what was done at Black Rock, and how
the counsels of white men prevailed.
</p><p>"Is there not one," said Evaly, "who could persuade the
people?"
</p><p>"None that they would hear," said her father, "unless it might
be Johnson Sides, and he is at Winnemucca."
</p><p>"Bring him, my father."
</p><p>"Daughter, I am watched, I dare not go away; and I have no
son."
</p><p>Johnson Sides was a very great man among the affiliated clans
of the Paiutes&mdash;an orator by gift, a high priest in authority,
notably a man of pacific tendencies and modern ideas.  Winnemucca
lay within the reservation, two hundred miles north. <pb n="91"/>
</p><p>Evaly's slow wit traveled the length of the whole affair.
Then came a glow as of reflected fires upon her face; she stood up,
her bosom filling, and you could see how tall and strong she was.
</p><p>"These people are fools," she said.  "I will go, my father."
</p><p>Mono John looked up, and was smit with the glow of her
exaltation.
</p><p>"Go," he said.  He stood up, and she leaned her young body
against him; so much of a caress was permitted a medicine man of
the Paiutes.  Some message, some assurance, passed between them
without words.
</p><p>The railroad that runs past Tres Pinos is a small affair,
twisting and looping in the desert hills to tap the mines of that
region.  It crosses the lands of the Paiutes under consideration
that they may ride free at will in either direction.  They ride in
empty freight cars, if there are any, or on the platforms or tops
of the passenger cars, but never inside.
</p><p>The daily train at that time passed through Tres Pinos about
four in the morning.  On Tuesday before the medicine dance, the
daughter of Mono John crept out of the willow scrub beside the
station where she had spent the night, and crouched on the rear
platform of the one passenger coach.  The wind blew coldly, foul
with dust and cinders; towards daylight a chilly rain came on.  It
drove upon her with the wind, and dripped from the roof of the car.
Evaly drew her blanket over her head and possessed her soul in the
inimitable patience of her kind.  There were no other passengers,
and it was nearly noon before the train men discovered her.  The
promptings of human kindness were not supposed, in that region, to
include Indians; but there might have been some appeal in the fact
that she was a woman and young.  They gave her leave to come into
the caboose, where there was shelter and a fire.  She sat down
dumbly to steam in her wet garments.  Something in the urgency of
her errand made a kind of isolation for her.  Her eyes burned
dully, and in the long waits at stations had a hunted look.  The
men offered her broken food at noon, which she hardly tasted; but
she said thanks very prettily for a cup of coffee.
</p><p>So they wore through Tuesday as the train crawled up the
summit of a treeless range.  At night, because she knew the men
would use their bunks, Evaly crept out to the platform again,
shivering and sleepless, drawing her breath lightly not to wake a
slumbering pain in her side.
</p><p>They had crossed the range, speeding on a high, windy mesa,
when Evaly dropped off at a little way station to watch the remnant
of the night out among the freight bales.  This was Winnemucca, a
settlement of half a hundred Indian families, the real capital of
the Paiutes.  Here she would find Johnson Sides.  What she would
do, or what say, she had not questioned; no doubt her great need
would bear her out.
</p><p>Daybreak found her making the round of the wattled huts,
asking for Johnson Sides.  It was part of the serious exaltation of
her mood that she felt no dismay to learn that he was gone to
Haiwai, a matter of fifteen miles inland.  Well, she would go also
to Haiwai.  How?  Ah!  Evaly, who did not understand the
multiplication table, and played with colored kindergarten papers,
had grown a woman in the night and used a woman's means.
</p><p>She gave the young men a sidelong glance and a smile.  All the
girls at Tres Pinos, she said, could ride.
</p><p>The young men snickered and nudged one another, and one
swaggered a little.  "Were all the girls of Tres Pinos as pretty as
she?"
</p><p>That was a true word, for the flush of fever and the beauty of
high resolve lightened and brightened her face.
</p><p>"Much prettier," said Evaly, "and the young men more polite."
</p><p>So at the end of a quarter of an hour of chaffing and shy
glances, Evaly was riding a borrowed horse out towards Haiwai,
sitting astride, as Indian women do, and spurring cruelly, herself
driven by a keener spur.  The south bound train passed Winnemucca
that night at eleven, and would reach Tres Pinos about the
beginning of the medicine dance.  Please God or whatever power,
they would be in time, and Johnson Sides should save her father!
</p><p>This was Evaly's white hour.  All the Indian woman's habit of
servility, all <pb n="92"/>  the youth's awe of greatness, all the
primitive reverence for old laws, fell away from her.  Those
ignorant, blind savages at Tres Pinos would kill her father if
Johnson Sides, who was, like herself, of the elect and enlightened,
came not quickly.
</p><p>In the end Johnson Sides came.  It was just the sort of
missionary effort that pleased his Christian soul, just the sort of
situation that appealed to his savage dramatic sense.
</p><p>Meanwhile Mono John had only evil looks and mutterings from
his people.  On Wednesday he heard how they had killed Winnenap at
Maverick, and after that walked a little apart that he might meet
his fate fairly.  If the blow could be deferred until Evaly
returned it might be avoided.
</p><p>The preparations for "big medicine" went forward.  The ground
was cleared and the fetish pole set up.  Thursday night fell, the
fire was lit, and the old men gathered in to council.  Mono John
took his place with ears strained for the whistle of the train.
Send it would not be late!  Outside the circle of the council fire
the women rocked themselves and wailed for the dead.  Out in the
sage the coyotes mocked them.  "Oh&mdash;oo-o-ah!" wailed the women,
"Ah-oo-aah!" the coyotes.
</p><p>Bitterly, sullenly, but with every show of ceremony the
council proceeded, harking back to the time and the law of the
fathers.  Still there was no train, and the dance for "big
medicine" began.
</p><p>This is the fashion of a Paiute big medicine dance.  It takes
place in a circular corral of wattled brush opening towards the
east.  In the center stands a peeled pine sapling hung with
fetishes, in front of it a fire.  A little to one side sit old men
musicians, who keep up a kind of castanet rattle with split willow
wands and a droning accompaniment of meaningless syllables, like
the burden of old ballads.  Round about in a circle sit the clan.
</p><p>Mono John and two others stood up in the flare of the fire,
stripped to the buckskin loin cloth, brave with paint and feathers.
They began with the chanting of old songs, and leaped to the rhythm
in the leaping light.  On the turn of the medicine dance hung the
issues of life and death.  The leaping and stamping, the chanting,
the clack of the willow, went on and on; the pulse beat with it,
the breath sobbed in the body.  The flood of savage emotion surged
up with it, fell away, and increased like a tide.  All through it
Mono John felt for the moment of hypnotic control when he might
reestablish his ascendency.  Somewhere out on the slope of White
Mountain the train was held by a hot box, and the medicine man,
straining for the roar of its incoming, lost ground.  Body and soul
wearied under the strain.  The moment came&mdash;and went against him.
</p><p>Towards midnight, when the fire was burned to a red eye in the
ash, and the ground under them was beaten to an impalpable fine
dust, there went a bright gleam from man to man of the clan.  It
leaped to the head of the dancer on his left, a keen, new hatchet
murderously bright; high above the chanting rang the voices of the
young men in the death song of the Paiutes.  Then into the dim-lit
circle by the fetish pole stepped Johnson Sides, dropping his
blanket as it had been the slough of old customs, and began the
speech of his life.
</p><p>It was a good speech, too, by all accounts, beginning at the
point where the frenzy left off, and cunningly drawn out, past the
point of reaction to exhaustion.  As for the medicine man, he
turned his back on his people and the reserve of sixty years, and
hugged his daughter to his heart.  Nor did he hear the end any more
than the beginning of Johnson Sides' speech, being busy in the hut,
laboring to relieve his daughter of the pain which gripped her.
</p><p>The rain, the cold, and the spiritual strain had effected what
neither the medicine man nor the doctor brought out from Tres Pinos
could remedy.  So it happened that in dying the daughter of Mono
John added the final argument to the purely human inefficiency of
the medicine man.
</p><p>And this I take it was purely kind, for all the learning the
patient labor had compassed, all the force and power that should
have pieced out the long, lean years, had been burned out in
Evaly's one white hour.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
