<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AusMaha"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="AusMaha">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mahala Joe</title>
<title type="sort">mahala joe</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">38</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AusMaha</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475712</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mahala Joe</title>
<title type="sort">mahala joe</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<date value="1904">1904</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Volume 94</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Verification made against printed text</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1904">1904</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman and Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="section" n="1" id="d3">
<head>
Austin, Mary.  "Mahala Joe."<lb/>
  <hi rend="italic"> Atlantic Monthly</hi> 94 (1904): 44-53.
</head>
<pb n="44"/>

<p>IN the campoodie of Three Pines, which you probably know
better by its Spanish name of Tres Pinos, there is an Indian, well
thought of among his own people, who goes about wearing a woman's
dress, and is known as Mahala Joe.  He should be about fifty years
old by this time, and has a quiet, kindly face.  Sometimes he tucks
up the skirt of his woman's dress over a pair of blue overalls when
he has a man's work to do, but at feasts and dances he wears a
ribbon around his waist and a handkerchief on his head as the other
mahalas do.  He is much looked to because of his knowledge of white
people and their ways, and if it were not for the lines of deep
sadness that fall in his face when at rest, one might forget that
the woman's gear is the badge of an all but intolerable shame.  At
least it was so used by the Paiutes, but when you have read this
full and true account of how it was first put on, you may not think
it so.
</p><p>Fifty years ago the valley about Tres Pinos was all one sea of
moving grass and dusky, greenish sage, cropped over by deer and
antelope, north as far as Togobah, and south to the Bitter Lake.
Beside every considerable stream which flowed into it from the
Sierras was a Paiute campoodie, and all they knew of white people
was by hearsay from the tribes across the mountains.  But soon
enough cattlemen began to push their herds through the Sierra
passes to the Paiutes' feeding-ground.  The Indians saw them come,
and though they were not very well pleased, they held still by the
counsel of their old men; night and day they made medicine and
prayed that the white men might go away.
</p><p>Among the first of the cattlemen in the valley about Tres
Pinos was Joe Baker, who brought a young wife, and built his house
not far from the campoodie.  The Indian women watched her curiously
from afar because of a whisper that ran among the wattled huts.
When the year was far gone, and the sun-cured grasses curled
whitish brown, a doctor came riding hard from the fort at Edawick,
forty miles to the south, and though they watched they did not see
him ride away.  It was the third day at evening when Joe Baker came
walking toward the campoodie, and his face was set and sad.  He
carried something rolled in a blanket, and looked anxiously at the
women as he went between the huts.  It was about the hour of the
evening meal, and the mahalas sat about the fires watching the
cooking pots.  He came at last opposite a young woman who sat
nursing her child.  She had a bright, pleasant face, and her little
one seemed about six months old.  Her husband stood near and
watched them with great pride.  Joe Baker knelt down in front of
the mahala, and opened the roll of blankets.  He showed her a day-old baby that wrinkled up its small face and cried.
</p><p>"Its mother is dead," said the cattleman.  The young Indian
mother did not know English, but she did not need speech to know
what had happened.  She looked pitifully at the child, and at her
husband timidly.  Joe Baker went and laid his rifle and cartridge
belt at the Paiute's feet.  The Indian picked up the gun and
fingered it; his wife smiled.  She put down her own child, and
lifted the little white stranger to her breast.  It nozzled against
her and hushed its crying; the young mother laughed.
</p><p>"See how greedy it is," she said; "it is truly white."  She
drew up the blanket around the child and comforted it.
</p><p>The cattleman called to him one of the <pb n="45"/>  Indians who
could speak a little English.
</p><p>"Tell her," he said, "that I wish her to care for the child.
His name is Walter.  Tell her that she is to come to my house for
everything he needs, and for every month that he keeps fat and well
she shall have a fat steer from my herd."  So it was agreed.
</p><p>As soon as Walter was old enough he came to sleep at his
father's house, but the Indian woman whom he called Ebia came every
day to tend him.  Her son was his brother, and Walter learned to
speak Paiute before he learned English.  The two boys were always
together, but as yet the little Indian had no name.  It is not the
custom among Paiutes to give names to those who have not done
anything worth naming.
</p><p>"But I have a name," said Walter, "and so shall he.  I will
call him Joe.  That is my father's name, and it is a good name,
too."
</p><p>When Mr. Baker was away with the cattle Walter slept at the
campoodie, and Joe's mother made him a buckskin shirt.  At that
time he was so brown with the sun and the wind that only by his
eyes could you tell that he was white; he was also very happy.  But
as this is to be the story of how Joe came to the wearing of a
woman's dress I cannot tell you all the plays they had, how they
went on their first hunting, nor what they found in the creek of
Tres Pinos.
</p><p>The beginning of the whole affair of Mahala Joe must be laid
to the arrow-maker.  The arrow-maker had a stiff knee from a wound
in a long gone battle, and for that reason he sat in the shade of
his wickiup, and chipped arrow points from flakes of obsidian that
the young men brought him from Togobah, fitting them to shafts of
reeds from the river marsh.  He used to coax the boys to wade in
the brown water and cut the reeds, for the dampness made his knee
ache.  They drove bargains with him for arrows for their own
hunting, or for the sake of the stories he could tell.  For an
armful of reeds he would make three arrows, and for a double armful
he would tell tales.  These were mostly of great huntings and old
wars, but when it was winter, and no snakes in the long grass to
overhear, he would tell Wonder-stories.  The boys would lie with
their toes in the warm ashes, and the arrow-maker would begin.
</p><p>"You can see," said the arrow-maker, "on the top of Waban the
tall boulder looking on the valleys east and west.  That is the
very boundary between the Paiute country and Shoshone land.  The
boulder is a hundred times taller than the tallest man, and thicker
through than six horses standing nose to tail; the shadow of it
falls all down the slope.  At mornings it falls toward the Paiute
peoples, and evening it falls on Shoshone land.  Now on this side
of the valley, beginning at the campoodie, you will see a row of
pine trees standing all upstream one behind another.  See, the long
branches grow on the side toward the hill, and some may tell you it
is because of the way the wind blows, but I say it is because they
reach out in a hurry to get up the mountain.  Now I will tell you
how these things came about.
</p><p>"Very long ago all the Paiutes of this valley were ruled by
two brothers, a chief and a medicine man, Winnedumah and Tinnemaha.
They were both very wise, and one of them never did anything
without the other.  They taught the tribes not to war upon each
other, but to stand fast as brothers, and so they brought peace
into the land.  At that time there were no white people heard of,
and game was plenty.  The young honored the old, and nothing was as
it is now."
</p><p>When the arrow-maker came to this point, the boys fidgeted
with their toes, and made believe to steal the old man's arrows to
distract his attention.  They did not care to hear about the
falling off of the Paiutes; they wished to have the tale.  Then the
arrow-maker would hurry on to the time when there arose a war
between the Paiutes and the Shoshones. <pb n="46"/>   Then Winnedumah put
on his war bonnet, and Tinnemaha made medicine.  Word went around
among the braves that if they stood together man to man as
brothers, then they should have this war.
</p><p>"And so they might," said the arrow-maker, "but at last their
hearts turned to water.  The tribes came together on the top of
Waban.  Yes; where the boulder now stands, for that is the boundary
of our lands, for no brave would fight off his own ground for fear
of the other's medicine.  So they fought.  The eagles heard the
twang of the bowstring, and swung down from White Mountain.  The
vultures smelled the smell of battle, and came in from Shoshone
land.  Their wings were dark like a cloud, and underneath the
arrows flew like hail.  The Paiutes were the better bowmen, and
they caught the Shoshone arrows where they struck in the earth and
shot them back again.  Then the Shoshones were ashamed, and about
the time of the sun going down they called upon their Medicine Men,
and one let fly a magic arrow,&mdash;for none other would touch him,&mdash;
and it struck in the throat of Tinnemaha.
</p><p>"Now when that befell," went on the arrow-maker, "the braves
forgot the word that had gone before the battle, for they turned
their backs to the Medicine Man, all but Winnedumah, his brother,
and fled this way from Waban.  Then stood Winnedumah by Tinnemaha,
for that was the way of those two, whatever happened, one would not
leave the other.  There was none left to carry on the fight, and
yet since he was so great a chief the Shoshones were afraid to take
him, and the sun went down.  In the dusk they saw a bulk, and they
said, 'He is still standing,' but when it was morning light they
saw only a great rock, so you see it to this day.  As for the
braves who ran away, they were changed to pine trees, but in their
hearts they are cowards yet, therefore they stretch out their arms
and strive toward the mountain.  And that," said the arrow-maker,
"is how the tall stones came to be on the top of Waban.  But it was
not in my day nor my father's."  Then the boys would look up at
Winnedumah, and were half afraid, and as for the tale, they quite
believed it.
</p><p>The arrow-maker was growing old.  His knee hurt him in cold
weather, and he could not make arrow points fast enough to satisfy
the boys, who lost a great many in the winter season shooting at
ducks in the tulares.  Walter's father promised him a rifle when he
was fifteen, but that was years away.  There was a rock in the
canon behind Tres Pinos with a great crack in the top.  When the
young men rode to the hunting they shot each an arrow at it, and if
it stuck it was a promise of good luck.  The boys scaled the rock
by means of a grapevine ladder, and pried out the old points.  This
gave them an idea.
</p><p>"Upon Waban where the fighting was, there must be a great many
arrow points," said Walter.
</p><p>"So there must be," said Joe.
</p><p>"Let us go after them," said the white boy; but the other
dared not, for no Paiute would go within a bowshot of Winnedumah;
nevertheless, they talked the matter over.
</p><p>"How near would you go?" asked Walter.
</p><p>"As near as a strong man might shoot an arrow," said Joe.
</p><p>"If you will go so far," said Walter, "I will go the rest of
the way."
</p><p>"It is a two days' journey," said the Paiute, but he did not
make any other objection.
</p><p>It was a warm day of spring when they set out.  The cattleman
was off to the river meadow, and Joe's mother was out with the
other mahalas gathering taboose.
</p><p>"If I were fifteen, and had my rifle, I would not be afraid of
anything," said Walter.
</p><p>"But in that case we would not need to go after arrow points,"
said the Indian boy.
</p><p>They climbed all day in a bewildering waste of boulders and
scrubby trees.  They could see Winnedumah shining <pb n="47"/>  whitely on
the ridge ahead, but when they had gone down into the gully with
great labor, and up the other side, there it stood whitely just
another ridge away.
</p><p>"It is like the false water in the desert," said Walter.  "It
goes farther from you, and when you get to it there is no water
there."
</p><p>"It is magic medicine," said Indian Joe.  "No good comes of
going against medicine."
</p><p>"If you are afraid," said Walter, "why do you not say so.  You
may go back if you like, and I will go on by myself."
</p><p>Joe would not make any answer to that.  They were hot and
tired, and awed by the stillness of the hills.  They kept on after
that, angry and apart; sometimes they lost sight of each other
among the boulders and underbrush.  But it seemed that it must
really have been as one or the other of them had said, for when
they came out on a high mesa presently there was no Winnedumah
anywhere in sight.  They would have stopped then and taken counsel,
but they were too angry for that, so they walked on in silence, and
the day failed rapidly, as it will do in high places.  They began
to draw near together and to be afraid.  At last the Indian boy
stopped and gathered the tops of bushes together, and began to
weave a shelter for the night, and when Walter saw that he made it
large enough for two he spoke to him.
</p><p>"Are we lost?" he said.
</p><p>"We are lost for to-night," said Joe, "but in the morning we
will find ourselves."
</p><p>They ate dried venison and drank from the wicker bottle, and
huddled together because of the dark and the chill.
</p><p>"Why do we not see the stone any more?" asked Walter in a
whisper.
</p><p>"I do not know," said Joe.  "I think it has gone away."
</p><p>"Will he come after us?"
</p><p>"I do not know.  I have on my elk's tooth," said Joe, and he
clasped the charm that hung about his neck.  They started and
shivered, hearing a stone crash far away as it rolled down the
mountain side, and the wind began to move among the pines.
</p><p>"Joe," said Walter, "I am sorry I said that you were afraid."
</p><p>"It is nothing," said the Paiute.  "Besides, I am afraid."
</p><p>"So am I," whispered the other.  "Joe," he said again after a
long silence, "if he comes after us what shall we do?"
</p><p>"We will stay by each other."
</p><p>"Like the two brothers, whatever happens," said the white boy,
"forever and ever."
</p><p>"We are two brothers," said Joe.
</p><p>"Will you swear it?"
</p><p>"On my elk's tooth."
</p><p>Then they each took the elk's tooth in his hand and made a vow
that whether Winnedumah came down from his rock, or whether the
Shoshones found them, come what would, they would stand together.
Then they were comforted, and lay down holding each other's hands.
</p><p>"I hear some one walking," said Walter.
</p><p>"It is the wind among the pines," said Joe.
</p><p>A twig snapped.  "What is that?" said the one boy.
</p><p>"It is a fox or a coyote passing," said the other, but he knew
better.  They lay still, scarcely breathing, and throbbed with
fear.  They felt a sense of a presence approaching in the night,
the whisper of a moccasin on the gravelly soil, the swish of
displaced bushes springing back to place.  They saw a bulk shape
itself out of the dark; it came and stood over them, and they saw
that it was an Indian looking larger in the gloom.  He spoke to
them, and whether he spoke in a strange tongue, or they were too
frightened to understand, they could not tell.
</p><p>"Do not kill us!" cried Walter, but the Indian boy made no
sound.  The man took Walter by the shoulders and lifted him up.
</p><p>"White," said he.
</p><p>"We are brothers," said Joe; "we have sworn it." <pb n="48"/>
</p><p>"So," said the man, and it seemed as if he smiled.
</p><p>"Until we die," said both the boys.  The Indian gave a grunt.
</p><p>"A white man," he said, "is&mdash;White."  It did not seem as if
that was what he meant to say.
</p><p>"Come, I will take you to your people.  They search for you
about the foot of Waban.  These three hours I have watched you and
them."  The boys clutched at each other in the dark.  They were
sure now who spoke to them, and between fear and fatigue and the
cramp of cold they staggered and stumbled as they walked.  The
Indian stopped and considered them.
</p><p>"I cannot carry both," he said.
</p><p>"I am the older," said Joe; "I can walk."  Without any more
words the man picked up Walter, who trembled, and walked off down
the slope.  They went a long way through the scrub and under the
tamarack pines.  The man was naked to the waist, and had a quiver
full of arrows on his shoulder.  The buckthorn branches whipped and
scraped against his skin, but he did not seem to mind.  At last
they came to a place where they could see a dull red spark across
an open flat.
</p><p>"That," said the Indian, "is the fire of your people.  They
missed you at afternoon, and have been looking for you.  From my
station on the hill I saw."  Then he took the boy by the shoulders.
</p><p>"Look you," he said, "no good comes of mixing white and brown,
but now that the vow is made, see to the keeping of it."  Then he
stepped back from them and seemed to melt into the dark.  Ahead of
them the boys saw the light of the fire flare up with new fuel, and
shadows moved between them and the flame, which they knew for the
figures of their friends.  Swiftly as two scared rabbits they ran
on toward the glow.
</p><p>When Walter and Joe had told them the story at the campoodie,
the Paiutes made a great deal of it, especially the arrow-maker.
</p><p>"Without a doubt," he said, "it was Winnedumah who came to
you, and not, as some think, a Shoshone who was spying on our land.
It is a great mystery.  But since you have made a vow of brothers,
you should keep it after the ancient use."  Then he took a knife of
obsidian and cut their arms, and rubbed a little of the blood of
each upon the other.
</p><p>"Now," he said, "you are one fellowship and one blood, and
that is as it should be, for you were both nursed at one breast.
See that you keep the vow."
</p><p>"We will," said the boys solemnly, and they went out into the
sunlight very proud of the blood upon their bared arms, holding by
each other's hands.
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="2" id="d4">
<head>                           II</head>

<p>When Walter was fifteen his father gave him a rifle, as he had
promised, and a word of advice with it.
</p><p>"Learn to shoot quickly and well," he said, "and never ride
out from home without it.  No one can tell what this trouble with
the Indians may come to in the end."
</p><p>Walter rode straight to the campoodie.  He was never happy in
any of his gifts until he had showed them to Joe.  There was a
group of older men at the camp, quartering a deer which they had
brought in.  One of them, called Scar-Face, looked at Walter with
a leering frown.
</p><p>"See," he said, "they're arming the very children with guns."
</p><p>"My father promised it to me many years ago," said Walter.
"It is my birthday gift."
</p><p>He could not explain why, and he grew angry at the man's
accusing tone, but after it he did not like showing his presents to
the Indians.
</p><p>He called Joe, and they went over to a cave in the black rock
where they had kept their boyish treasures, and planned their plays
since they were children.  Joe thought the rifle a beauty, and
turned it over admiringly in the shadow of the cave.  They tried
shooting at a mark, and then decided to go up Oak Creek for a
<pb n="49"/>
shot at the gray squirrels.  There they sighted a band of
antelope that led them over a tongue of hills into Little Round
Valley, where they found themselves at noon twelve miles from home
and very hungry.  They had no antelope, but four squirrels and a
grouse.  The two boys made a fire for cooking in a quiet place by
a spring of sweet water.
</p><p>"You may have my rifle to use as often as you like," said
Walter, "but you must not lend it to any one in the campoodie,
especially to Scar-Face.  My father says he is the one who is
stirring up all this trouble with the whites."
</p><p>"The white men do not need any one to help them get into
trouble," said Joe.  "They can do that for themselves."
</p><p>"It is the fault of the Indians," said Walter.  "If they did
not shoot the cattle the white men would leave them alone."
</p><p>"But if the white men come first to our lands with noise and
trampling and scare away the game, what then will they shoot?"
asked the Paiute.
</p><p>Walter did not make any answer to that.  He had often gone
hunting with Joe and his father, and he knew what it meant to walk
far, and fasting, after game made shy by the rifles of cattlemen,
and at last to return empty to the campoodie, where there were
women and children with hungry eyes.
</p><p>"Is it true," he said after a while, "that Scar-Face is
stirring up all the Indians in the valley?"
</p><p>"How should I know," said Joe; "I am only a boy, and have not
killed big game.  I am not admitted to the counsels of the old men.
What does it matter to us whether of old feuds or new?  Are we not
brothers sworn?"
</p><p>Then, as the dinner was done, they ate each of the other's
kill, for it was the custom of the Paiutes at that time that no
youth should eat game of his own killing until he was fully grown.
As they walked homeward the boys planned to get permission to go up
on Waban, for a week, after mountain sheep, before the snows began.
</p><p>Mr. Baker looked grave when Walter spoke to him.
</p><p>"My boy," he said, "I wish you would not plan long trips like
this without first speaking to me.  It is hardly safe in the
present state of feeling among the Indians to let you go with them
in this fashion.  A whole week, too.  But as you have already
spoken of it, and it has probably been talked over in the
campoodie, for me to refuse now would look as if I suspected
something, and might bring about the thing I most fear."
</p><p>"You should not be afraid for me with Joe, father, for we are
brothers sworn," said Walter, and he told his father how they had
mixed the blood of their arms in the arrow-maker's hut after they
had come back from their first journey on Waban.
</p><p>"Well," said Mr. Baker, who had not heard of this before, "I
know that they set a great store by these superstitious customs,
but I have not much faith in the word of a Paiute when he is
dealing with a white man.  However, you had better go on with this
hunting trip.  Take Hank with you and Joe's father, and do not be
gone more than five days at the outside."
</p><p>Hank was one of Mr. Baker's vaqueros, and very glad to get off
for a few days hunting on the blunt top of Waban.  On the Monday
following they left the Baker ranch for the mountain.  As the two
boys rode up the boulder-strewn slope it set them talking of the
first time they had gone that way on their fruitless hunt for arrow
points about the foot of Winnedumah, and of all that happened to
them at that time.  The valley lay below them full of purple mist,
and away by the creek of Tres Pinos the brown, wattled huts of the
campoodie like great wasps' nests stuck in the sage.  Hank and
Joe's father, with the pack horses, were ahead of them far up the
trail; Joe and Walter let their own ponies lag, and the nose of one
touched the flank of the other, as they climbed slowly up the
steep, and the boys turned their faces to each other, as if they
had some vague warning that they would <pb n="50"/>  not ride so and talk
familiarly again, as if the boiling anger of the tribes in the
valley had brewed a sort of mist that rose up and gloomed the
pleasant air on the slope of Waban.
</p><p>"Joe," said Walter, "my father says if it came to a fight
between the white settlers and the Paiutes, that you would not hold
by the word we have passed."
</p><p>"That is the speech of a white man," said Joe.
</p><p>"But would you?" the other insisted.
</p><p>"I am a Paiute," said Joe; "I will hold by my people, also by
my word; I will not fight against you."
</p><p>"Nor I against you, but I would not like to have my father
think you had broken your word."
</p><p>"Have no care," said the Indian, "I will not break it."
</p><p>Mr. Baker looked anxiously after his son as he rode to the
hunting on Waban; he looked anxiously up that trail every hour
until the boy came again, and that, as it turned out, was at the
end of three days.  For the trouble among the Indians had come to
something at last,&mdash;the wasps were all out of nest by the brown
creeks, and with them a flight of stinging arrows.  The trouble
began at Cottonwood, and the hunting party on Waban the second day
out saw a tall, pale column of smoke that rose up from the notch of
the hill behind the settlement, and fanned out slowly into the pale
blueness of the sky.
</p><p>It went on evenly, neither more nor less, thick smoke from a
fire of green wood steadily tended.  Before noon another rose from
the mouth of Oak Creek, and a third from Tunawai.  They waved and
beckoned to one another, calling to counsel.
</p><p>"Signal fires," said Hank; "that means mischief."
</p><p>And from that on he went with his rifle half cocked, and
walked always so that he might keep Joe's father in full view.  By
night that same day there were seven smoke trees growing up in the
long valley, and spreading thin, pale branches to the sky.  Then
was no zest left in the hunt, and on the morning they owned it.
Walter was worried by what he knew his father's anxiety must be.
Then the party began to ride down again, and always Hank made the
Indian go before.  Away by the foot of Oppapago rose a black volume
of smoke, thick, and lighted underneath by flames.  It might be the
reek of a burning ranch-house.  The boys were excited and afraid.
They talked softly and crowded their ponies together on the trail.
</p><p>"Joe," said Walter whisperingly, "if there is battle you will
have to go to it."
</p><p>"Yes," said Joe."
</p><p>"And you will fight; otherwise they will call you a coward,
and if you run away they will kill you."
</p><p>"So I suppose," said Joe.
</p><p>"Or they will make you wear a woman's dress like To-go-na-tee,
the man who got up too late."  This was a reminder from one of the
arrow-maker's tales.  "But you have promised not to fight."
</p><p>"Look you," said the Indian boy; "if a white man came to kill
me I would kill him.  That is right.  But I will not fight you nor
your father's house.  That is my vow."
</p><p>The white boy put out his hand, and laid it on the flank of
the foremost pony.  The Indian boy's fingers came behind him, and
crept along the pony's back until they reached the other hand.
They rode forward without talking.
</p><p>Toward noon they made out horsemen riding on the trail below
them.  As it wound in and out around the blind gullies they saw and
lost sight of them a dozen times.  At last, where the fringe of the
tall trees began, they came face to face.  It was Mr. Baker and a
party of five men; they carried rifles and had set and anxious
looks.
</p><p>"What will you have?" said Indian Joe's father as they drew up
before him under a tamarack pine.
</p><p>"My son," said the cattleman.
</p><p>"Is there war?" said the Indian.
</p><p>"There is war.  Come, Walter."
</p><p>The boys were still and scared.  Slowly <pb n="51"/>  Hank and Walter
drew their horses out of the path and joined the men.  Indian Joe
and his father passed forward on the trail.
</p><p>"Do them no harm," said Joe Baker to those that were with him.
</p><p>"Good-by, Joe," said Walter half aloud.
</p><p>The other did not turn his head, but as he went they noticed
that he had bared his right arm from the hunting shirt, and an inch
above the elbow showed a thin, white scar.  Walter had the twin of
that mark under his flannels.
</p><p>Mr. Baker did not mind fighting Indians; he thought it a good
thing to have their troubles settled all at once in this way, but
he did not want his son mixed up in it.  The first thing he did
when he got home was to send him off secretly by night to the fort,
and from there he passed over the mountains with other of the
settlers' families under strong escort, and finally went to his
mother's people in the East, and was put to school.  As it turned
out he never came back to Tres Pinos; he does not come into this
story any more.
</p><p>When the first smoke rose up that showed where the fierce hate
of the Paiutes had broken into flame, the Indians took their women
and children away from the pleasant open slopes, and hid them in
deep canons in secret places of the rocks.  There they feathered
arrows, and twisted bowstrings of the sinew of deer.  And because
there were so many grave things done, and it was not the custom for
boys to question their elders, Joe never heard how Walter had been
sent away.  He thought him still at the ranch with his father, and
it is because of this mistake that there is any more story at all.
</p><p>You may be sure that, of those two boys, Joe's was the deeper
loving for, besides having grown up together, Walter was white,
therefore thinking himself, and making the other believe it, the
better of the two.  But for this Walter made no difference in his
behavior; had Joe to eat at his table, and would have him sleep in
his bed, but Joe laughed, and lay on the floor.  All this was
counted a kindness and a great honor in the campoodie.  Walter
could find out things by looking in a book, which was sheer magic,
and had taught Joe to write a little, so that he could send word by
means of a piece of paper, which was cleverer than the tricks Joe
had taught him, of reading the signs of antelope and elk and deer.
The white boy was to the Indian a little of all the heroes and
bright ones of the arrow-maker's tales come alive again.  Therefore
he quaked in his heart when he heard the rumors that ran about the
camp.
</p><p>The war began about Cottonwood, and ran like wildfire that
licked up all the ranches in its course.  Then the whites came
strongly against the Paiutes at the Stone Corral, and made an end
of the best of their fighting men.  Then the Indians broke out in
the north, and at last it came to such a pass that the very boys
must do fighting, and the women make bowstrings.  The cattlemen
turned in to Baker's ranch as a centre, and all the northern
campoodies gathered together to attack them.  They had not much to
hope for, only to do as much killing as possible before the winter
set in with the hunger and the deep snows.
</p><p>By this time Joe's father was dead; and his mother had brought
the boy a quiver full of arrows and a new bowstring, and sent him
down to the battle.
</p><p>And Joe went hotly enough to join the men of the other
village, nursing his bow with great care, remembering his father,
but when he came to counsel and found where the fight must be, his
heart turned again, for he remembered his friend.  The braves
camped by Little Round Valley, and he thought of the talk he and
Walter had there; the war party went over the tongue of hills, and
Joe saw Winnedumah shining whitely on Waban, and remembered his
boyish errand, the mystery of the tall, strange warrior that came
upon them in the night, their talk in the hut of the arrow-maker,
and the vow that came afterward.
</p><p>The Indians came down a ravine to-<pb n="52"/> ward Tres Pinos, and
there met a band of horses which some of their party had run in
from the ranches; among them was a pinto pony which Walter had used
to ride, and it came to Joe's hand when he called.  Then the boy
wondered if Walter might be dead, and leaned his head against the
pony's mane; it turned its head and nickered softly at his ear.
</p><p>The war party stayed in the ravine until it grew dark, and Joe
watched how Winnedumah swam in a mist above the hills long after
the sun had gone quite down, as if in his faithfulness he would
outwatch the dark; and then the boy's heart was lifted up to the
great chief standing still by Tinnemaha.  "I will not forget," he
said.  "I, too, will be faithful."  Perhaps at this moment he
expected a miracle to help him in his vow as it had helped
Winnedumah.
</p><p>In the dusk the mounted Indians rode down by the Creek of Tres
Pinos.  When they came by the ruined hut where his father had
lived, Joe's heart grew hot again, and when he passed the arrow-maker's he remembered his vow.  Suddenly he wheeled his pony in the
trail, hardly knowing what he would do.  The man next to him laid
an arrow across his bow and pointed it at the boy's breast.
</p><p>"Coward," he whispered, but an older Indian laid his hand on
the man's arm.
</p><p>"Save your arrows," he said.  Then the ponies swept forward in
the charge, but Joe knew in an instant how it would be with him.
He would be called false and a coward, killed for it, driven from
the tribe, but he would not fight against his sworn brother.  He
would keep his vow.
</p><p>A sudden rain of arrows flew from the advancing Paiutes; Joe
fumbled his and dropped it on the ground.  He was wondering if one
of the many aimed would find his brother.  Bullets answered the
arrow flight.  He saw the braves pitch forward, and heard the
scream of wounded ponies.
</p><p>He hoped he would be shot; he would not have minded that; it
would be better than being called a coward.  And then it occurred
to him, if Walter and his father came out and found him when the
fight was done, they would think that he had broken his word.  The
Paiutes began to seek cover, but Joe drove out wildly from them,
and rode back in the friendly dark, and past the ruined campoodie,
to the black rocks.  There he crept into the cave which only he and
Walter knew, and lay on his face and cried, for though he was an
Indian he was only a boy, and he had seen his first fight.  He was
sick with the thoughts of his vow.  He lay in the black rocks all
the night and the day, and watched the cattlemen and the soldiers
ranging all that county for the stragglers of his people, and
guessed that the Paiute had made the last stand.  Then in the
second night he began to work back by secret paths to the mountain
camp.  It never occurred to him not to go.  He had the courage to
meet what waited for him there, but he had not the heart to go to
it in the full light of day.  He came in by his mother's place, and
she spat upon him, for she had heard how he had carried himself in
the fight.
</p><p>"No son of mine," said she.
</p><p>He went by the women and children and heard their jeers.  His
heart was very sick.  He went apart and sat down and waited what
the men would say.  There were few of them left about the dying
fire.  They had washed off their war paint, and their bows were
broken.  When they spoke at last it was with mocking and sad scorn.
</p><p>"We have enough of killing," said the one called Scar-Face.
"Let him have a woman's dress and stay to mend the fire."
</p><p>So it was done in the presence of all the camp; and because he
was a boy, and because he was an Indian, he said nothing of his
vow, nor opened his mouth in his defense, though his heart quaked
and his knees shook.  He had the courage to wear the badge of being
afraid all his life.  They brought him a woman's dress, though they
were all too sad for much laughter, and in the morning he set to
bringing the wood for the fire.
</p><p>Afterward there was a treaty made be-<pb n="53"/> tween the Paiutes
and the settlers, and the remnant went back to the campoodie of
Tres Pinos, and Joe learned how Walter had been sent out of the
valley in the beginning of the war, but that did not make any
difference about the woman's dress.  He and Walter never met again.
He continued to go about in dresses, though in time he was allowed
to do a man's work, and his knowledge of English helped to restore
a friendly footing with the cattlemen.  The valley filled very
rapidly with settlers after that, and under the slack usage of the
tribe, Mahala Joe, as he came to be known, might have thrown aside
his woman's gear without offense, but he had the courage to wear it
to his life's end.  He kept his sentence as he kept his vow, and
yet it is certain that Walter never knew.

</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text></TEI.2>
