<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="AusSier"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>


<TEI.2 id="AusSier">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Shepherd of the Sierras</title>
<title type="sort">shepherd of the sierras</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">18</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">AusSier</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475716</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Shepherd of the Sierras</title>
<title type="sort">shepherd of the sierras</title>
<author>Austin, Mary</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Edited by</resp>
<name>editor</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<date value="1900-07">July 1900</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Vol. 86</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Verification made against printed text</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head>
Austin, Mary.  "A Shepherd of the Sierras."
<lb/> <hi rend="italic"> Atlantic Monthly</hi> 86 (July 1900): 54-58.
</head>
<pb n="54"/>

<p>THE two ends of this story belong, one to Pierre Jullien, and
the other to the lame coyote in the pack of the Ceriso.  Pierre
will have it that the Virgin is at the bottom of the whole affair.
However that may be, it is known that Pierre Jullien has not lost
so much as a lamb of the flocks since the burning of Black
Mountain.
</p><p>Black Mountain stands up eastward against the Ceriso, its
broken ridges spiked with clumps of pine, and its canons dark with
tamarack reaches and forests of silver fir.  And in the meadows of
Black Mountain Pierre Jullien feeds his flocks from year's end to
year's end; a little excursion down to the Ceriso when the snows
are heavy and the rains tearing at its foundations, and another to
the east slope for the shearing, but never out of sight or shadow
of it.
</p><p>Certainly the Virgin had something to do with Pierre's having
a flock in the first place; a hired shepherd, he, who between good
will and the wine cup could never get away from a shearing with
more than enough to clothe him for the year to come.  And finally,
by misadventure and unwise counsel, it fell out that Pierre was not
hired to go with the sheep for all of one year.
</p><p>It is said that when Pierre heard of this, and heard it in no
friendly manner from Lebecque who had got the place for himself,
that he called for another bottle.  He pledged his friends and his
luck, he whistled merrily to his dogs; he was for the hills.  For
what has a man bred to the hills to do with the town?  The airs of
it made him sick.  The sights and sounds of it, good enough to gape
at once in a year's wanderings, were a vexation and a confusion.
So he made back to Black Mountain with his dogs, to live by the
knowledge of it that had taken so many years to the gathering.  He
built him a hut, he cut him firewood, he tracked the wild bee to
the hiving rocks and the bear to the thickets of thimbleberries.
He set him traps and snares, for such of the wild creatures as are
not fit for food have pelts that may be sold.  Once in a month or
so he fared forth to town across the Ceriso for a cup of wine and
a taste of gossip, a bit of sugar and a morsel of flour.
Altogether Pierre Jullien was well content.
</p><p>There blows a great wind in the west before the rains; a
nerve-racking, eddying wind that gathers small dust and sand and
goes roaring with it across the open places.  It was about the time
of high wind when Pierre went down to the town, and he fought up
across the Ceriso in the teeth of it.  By all counts he should have
stayed safe with his dogs until the wind was done, but withal
Pierre had a tender heart.  He thought of his traps.  Doubtless it
would have been better if wild creatures could do without being
trapped, but since it was not so, it is best to trap them as gently
as possible.  So because he had not visited his traps for two days
Pierre must needs be fighting the high wind across the Ceriso.
<pb n="55"/>  He made better work of it than the dogs who whimpered and
slunk, knowing very well it was no sort of a day for an honest
beast to be abroad in.  The wind bit them, it beat and battered
them, and scoured them with fine sand.  There was no looking in
such a wind; only feeling the ground underfoot and knowing the way
by the rise of it.  And in the midst of their labor a plaintive cry
broke and scattered against the dead wall of the wind.  The dogs
whined to hear it; clearly, to travel such a day was rank folly,
but lost sheep&mdash;that was another matter.
</p><p>"Nay, nay, 'tis none of your minding," said Pierre.  "Well,
then, if you must, be off!"  Not one of the three but knew what had
happened.  A flock caught in the open must be well shepherded to
hold in such a wind; once scattered it may take days to bring them
together again.  The dogs found the ewe and brought it to Pierre,
and were off again as he gave the word, wriggling, yelping, and
panting with delight.  This was old times indeed!  They had great
work of it, the man and the dogs, wrestling in the smother of the
wind rocking up and down the hollow of the crater.  But they
brought the stragglers together, a score or more of them, and held
them under the lee of a hill until the wind was laid.  About mid-afternoon its spent wings trailed the dust, its breath shook the
tops of the sage, and no more.  The air was warm; it was clear and
smelt of the earth.  Pierre and his sheep went forth to look for
the master of the flock.  They worked up the south slope whence all
the Ceriso lay open as the hollow of a hand, and saw the hill-folk
beginning to stir about their business, but no sheep.  Pierre was
an honest man, and shepherd who knew how serious a thing it might
be to lose twenty sheep of the flock in a single wind.  He stayed
that night in the Ceriso and until the middle of the morning,
holding the sheep well toward the middle of the valley.  By that
time a good shepherd should have picked them up again, but none
came.  The brand was strange.  Many flocks passed the Ceriso at
that season, going hastily, because of scant pasturage, to winter
in the South.  Pierre drove the sheep to Black Mountain, and no
question was ever raised.  As for the sheep they were very well
content, and the dogs were happy to be at their work again.
</p><p>So Pierre Jullien became a shepherd in his own right, and in
the glacier meadows of Black Mountain the flock increased beyond
expectation.  Who shall say that the Virgin did not have a hand in
it?  Not Pierre Jullien, at any rate; he was careful to return
thanks as often as he went to church, which was at least once in
the year.  But Pierre kept his traps going.  Sheep, according to
the law of the beasts, were to be eaten, and beasts, according to
Pierre Jullien, to be caught.  He trapped a bear cub, wildcats, a
fox now and then, and a wolverine, but not often a coyote.  A
coyote is a thief and the son of a thief.  He will spring a trap
and eat the bait.  He will gnaw a rope and let a staked horse go
free; steal the <hi rend="italic">jerke</hi> drying on the trees, and the bacon
hanging against the wall; nose into a still camp and steal anything
he can lay jaws upon.  Ettienne Picquard will have it that he will
steal the frying pan off the fire if there is a smell of meat about
it.  These are the things that Pierre Jullien believed about the
coyotes; and first and last they stole a good many of Pierre's
lambs.  Nevertheless, his flock increased until it had become two
bands, and Pierre, going down to the shearing, brought Ettienne
Picquard to help him tend them.
</p><p>Ettienne had gone afar with his portion, foraging into the
pastures claimed by the flocks of the C+ brand.  For Ettienne
dearly loved a wrangle, and would as lieve fight for the pasture of
Pierre Jullien's sheep as anything else.  And one morning Pierre
woke with the smell <pb n="56"/>  of smoke in his nostrils.  It was a
smell of green wood, not the thin blue ghost of a smoke that
quavered up from his own well-banked fire, but the rank, acrid
smell of a forest burning.  Pierre should know that smell.  From
what dropped coals of a hunter's pipe, from what slothful
shepherd's camp, the fire broke, or what woodman's stupid greed lit
the close-locked ranks of living pines only the wood creatures
knew, and could not tell.  Pierre thought of Ettienne and the sheep
and wished them well.  The wind set well away from him; the fire
would drive out many pests, and the burnt districts made better
feed in a year or so.  Without doubt everything fell out for the
best.
</p><p>The fire began in a tamarack canon and spread upward all one
week slowly.  The smoke rose from it a white, heaven-pointing
spire, a wraith, a warning; and fanned out at last a wan,
fluttering beacon.  It tiptoed, it swayed, and genuflected, and
shook itself in an agony of entreatment.  But no one came to put
out the fire.  Quenching a forest fire is a difficult matter; and
then it is always some one else's business.  Only the mountain knew
how long it had been growing, those pines that went out in a flare
and a little crackling, and nobody cared.  At the end of a week a
wind rose and drove the fire straight across the mountain toward
Pierre Jullien's meadow.  Pierre's hut stood in a little island of
pines on a knoll swept about by a strip of meadow and a running
stream.  Thence he fed out with the home flock as far as he might
to the gentian hollows deep set among the rifted hills.
</p><p>When the pillar of smoke cast up by the burning forest grew
red by night Pierre went cautiously, keeping the flocks close and
watching every turn of the wind.  It dropped a little and the fire
with it.  Then Pierre, to save the home pasture, moved the flock
across the ridge away from the fire.  He made all safe in his
house, and trusted to his luck and the chances of the wind.  If the
fire would come, it would come; it was not to be stayed for all
Pierre's stopping at home.  The new meadow was deep set and fenced
about with barrenness, so that Pierre and his dogs could lie in the
sun and watch the portentous smoke above the mountains.  That the
fire was heavy and coming his way he had known by the wild wood
creatures that pushed by his meadow with an incessant panting and
padding of feet.  Seven deer drank at his brook in the gray of the
morning, wings whirred steadily, and at all hours hoofed creatures
broke through the thickets of ceanothus, all with incredible haste,
but dumbly, heralded by the noise of their going.  And in the night
the wind whipped the fire along the steep, and about the meadow
where Pierre was lying with his sheep.  It rioted in the resin-dripping pines, sung as it wrestled with them, and grew merry as it
raged.
</p><p>The sound of its singing woke Pierre and the sheep in the
middle hours.  But the dogs, mindful of the blethering flocks, held
them faithfully, huddling toward Pierre, who wept with his face
upon his hands.  "Oh, my house," he whimpered, "my dear house!"  He
had built it of the soil and what grew therein; it was part of the
mountain, and part of him; and it was all his home.
</p><p>With the fire, cattle broke into the meadow from the roaring
wood, and an antlered stag, snorting with fear, thrust into the
midst of them.  Quail and small fourfooted things fled, mad and
blind with terror, past the haven into the wood and fire again, and
when the morning cut the smoke that overhung, Pierre was aware of
a wild-cat that licked a dead kitten between him and the flame.
</p><p>Lastly out of the blaze limped a coyote, dragging a crushed
foot, and deeply burned across the flank.  Eight hours the fire
panted about the meadow, tugged and strained toward them from the
pines, <pb n="57"/>  and Pierre, trampling blazing brands, smothering
sparks, heartening and helping, knew himself a brother to beasts,
and yet more a man.  For, ever as he moved, the dumb shouldering
cattle shifted their place a little, not to lose the sense of his
presence, the sheep pressed to his knees, the dogs came whimpering
and went back to their stations comforted.  The coyote, dressing
his burn with his tongue, laid nose to the ground as Pierre went
by, and cried with the pain of his hurt as a child might.
</p><p>The fire ripped and tore at the heart of the wood and poured
the bitter smoke above them thick and hot, and through all Pierre
could hear the water hissing among burning logs, and the breathy
whine of the cat above her dead.  Pierre thought how she must have
come from hunting to her lair and found the fire before her.  It
was written in her singed and cinder-blackened coat how she had won
her way far and slowly, heat driven, carrying her dead by turns,
her mother's grief having way even in the dreadful hollow of the
singing flames.  "Mother of God," said the simple heart of Pierre
Jullien, "but I set me no more traps for the mothers of wild
things."
</p><p>The danger passed with the day, and the stream, cut off in
mid-morning by the falling timbers, came back to the meadow.
Pierre divided his jerke with the cat and the coyote, and woke in
the night, at the crash of falling trees, to catch the glow of
their unwinking, regardful eyes.
</p><p>The stag left at the dawn, going down the canon with wide
fearful leaps amid the burning, and after him the cattle picked out
a way along the water courses.  From where the wood had been rose
up the ghost of a forest; for every tree an uptrailing, wavering
smoke-spirit, topped by umbrageous clouds, and flame-flowers broke
and blossomed in dissolving embers.  The wild-cat, putting as much
space as possible between her and the dogs, grown fearful with the
passing of the fire, essayed the smoke forest by one and another of
the trails she had known, breaking away at last by well-considered
bounds, and looking back to the trampled meadow and the sheep
huddling between Pierre and the lame coyote.
</p><p>The coyote, made unhappy by the broadening day, drew up to the
meadow's edge, but having put foot among the hot ashes, set up his
drawling whine looking back toward Pierre.  "Stay where thou art,
friend," said the shepherd.  "It will be long before you can abide
the smell of fire."  Pierre fed him that day with the offal of a
sheep he had killed for his own eating, and ever as he busied
himself about the flock the coyote came and smelled of all the
places where he had been.  "Thou wilt know me again by that token,"
said Pierre, "and I you by that burnt flank, should you fall into
any trap of mine."  And being in a merry mood Pierre upbraided him
with the evil ways of his kind, until the coyote slunk abashed from
the sound of his voice to the edge of the clearing.
</p><p>It was the third day, and a blessed rain was falling, before
Pierre could make way with his flock across the burned district,
looking back from the top of the ridge to see the lame coyote
getting himself clumsily down to the lower levels, looking back
also at Pierre.  Now, by good fortune which fell little short of a
miracle, Pierre found his house unhurt, only the outer ring of
pines heat shriveled past any spring's redeeming.  And as for
Ettienne, the fire had not been near him.
</p><p>The burned coyote eschewed a forest country thereafter, and
going down to the sagebrush levels joined the pack on the east side
of the Ceriso.  Pierre saw him there the first time he came thither
feeding with his flocks, and knew him by his rocking, three-legged
gait, and the long scar, newly healed, upon his flank.  That the
coyote knew him Pierre affirms, for, seeing him, the howler dropped
upon <pb n="58"/>  his haunches dog fashion and waited until the flock had
gone by.  And this is true, that Pierre has given up his traps and
yet has not lost by beasts so much as a weanling.  And the
shepherds of Black Mountain and the Ceriso, and as far north as the
hills of Augustora, are divided between the opinion of Pierre, who
will protest that it is the work of the Virgin, and the opinion of
Ettienne Picquard, who says that Pierre has lived like a wild
creature so long that the beasts mistake him for one of themselves.
But for myself, I think, as I said at the beginning, this end of
the story belongs to the lame coyote.
</p><p>                              <hi rend="italic"> Mary Austin.</hi>
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
