<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="BoyDead"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>


<TEI.2 id="BoyDead">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Novel's Deadliest Friend</title>
<title type="sort">novels deadliest friend</title>
<author>Boyce, Neith</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss ( )</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">10</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">BoyDead</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475746</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Novel's Deadliest Friend</title>
<title type="sort">novels deadliest friend</title>
<author>Neith Boyce</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Bookman</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1901-09">September 1901</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>14</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>"The Novel's Deadliest Friend."  <hi rend="italic">Bookman</hi> 14
(Sept. 1901): 27-28.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1901-09">September 1901</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-08">August 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header; Tagged with TEI.2-compatible SGML, Parsed against
"teilite" dtd.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">


<div1 type="article" id="d3">
	<pb n="27"/>
<head>THE NOVEL'S DEADLIEST FRIEND</head>

<p>About a century has passed since woman's fondness began to
spoil the English novel.  Up to Fielding's day, it appears, some
good fortune preserved the lusty youth of Fiction from woman's
blighting eye; or perhaps the simple appetite of youth made a
defence, as the roast of beef and the flagon of ale protected Tom
Jones from the blandishments of the strange lady in the inn.  But
this protection likewise was only temporary; and Fielding,
Thackeray said in tears, was the last novelist in England "that
dared to paint a man."  Thackeray went away from an interview with
his editor, with that remark, to write into <hi rend="italic"> Pendennis</hi> those
paragraphs which preserve the hero's virtue&mdash;and ever since
masculine heroes have been made to fit feminine ideals.  Woman
never has liked the Tom Jones type of hero&mdash;the conquering,
destroying, self-indulgent young animal.  She likes splendour and
dash, but still demands that the hero shall represent somehow the
idea of self-sacrifice, of mortification of the flesh, and above
all, of constancy.  It was Thackeray, again, who said that woman
would forgive Nero all his other sins if only he had been a good
family man.  And this fits in with what Count Tolstoy has said
recently, that woman is less noble, less self-sacrificing, than
man, since man will sacrifice his family for an idea, while woman
won't.  It seems, then, to be fairly well established that the
heights of self-sacrifice are beyond woman.  And in imposing her
lower ideals upon the novel she has done the harm that male
novelists still deplore.  As she has prevented the hero of the
novel from soaring to the lonely peaks which she can't reach
herself, so also she forbids him to ramp through the pleasant
meadows, witlessly enjoying himself.  She condemns him to stern
probation and as many labours as Hercules had, and all to what end?
That he may kneel at her feet for his reward.  The modern novel
simply flatters woman's egregious vanity.  But what to do about it?
How to prevent woman reading and buying books?  As long as she does
so the manful efforts of the novelist to uphold his art must come
to naught.
</p><p>It used to be thought and said not many years ago that the
young person caused the trouble; but the higher education has
practically eliminated her, and yet the novel is as badly off as
before.  Indeed, in France, where the young person was never
terrifying, the novel has been debased all the same by the
influence of woman, who, educated, intelligent and married, is all
the more pernicious.  Count Tolstoy points out the damnatory
evidence in contemporary French literature that "in France
everything centres in women, and women have complete control of
life;" in particular, Maupassant, "the man of greatest talent in
these days," is "depraved and centres all his fiction in women."
Women, Tolstoy explains, besides their lack of moral qualities, are
also mentally deficient.  They "cling to old absurdities."  It
cannot be denied that they do&mdash;romance, for example.  It must be
admitted, too, that they will not sacrifice their own ideas of what
<pb n="28"/>  makes an interesting story or a proper hero.  Self-sacrificing man writes to please them.  Hence, woman drags the
novel down.
</p><p>Mr. Howells more than intimated in his recent article on
historical romances that women are mainly responsible for the
recent "welter of overwhelming romance" in Anglo-Saxendom.  Women&mdash;
that is, and golf.  Golf leads to muscular ideals among women, and
muscular ideals lead to romance, to the "spilth of blood" and "the
horrid din of the swashbuckler swashing on his buckler."  Mr.
Howells said that women, especially with us, are the "repository of
such refinement as we have attained," but also that "their tastes
and manners have been coarsened by sharing the rude sports and
boyish games of men."  However, women are not as bad as their
influence; very few of them, probably, really enjoy athletics as
much as they pretend, Mr. Howells thought, and very few probably
are fond of novels of adventure.  Yet athletics have flourished and
novels of adventure super-abound, because women do not know what
they want, or won't say.
</p><p>Not content, however, with the harm she can do by simply
buying and reading novels, woman has insisted on writing them.
Having set the pace for romantic novels, she has tried to write
romance.  But the <hi rend="italic"> Evening Post</hi> and the editor of a literary
weekly are agreed that woman cannot do the "genuinely romantic
novel&mdash;the novel of incident."  She does a base imitation of it
simply "to please the popular taste and sell her books," but the
real thing is beyond her.  This is pointed out by the editor of the
literary weekly, who says: "Let the men attend to the novel of
fight and fury, and the women to the delineation of domestic
virtues and faults.  We shall get a sounder literature thus than we
shall if the women attempt to enter into the fighting nature of
man, which they never understand and for which they have no
sympathy."
</p><p>This is, no doubt, sound advice; but has not the critic made
a mistake in saying that woman's forte lies in the delineation of
character?  Are not most great critics agreed that to delineate
character, even domestic virtues and faults, is the office of the
highest type of novel, while the novel of incident, of fight and
fury, is of a distinctly inferior sort?  There is some illogicality
here.  Woman seems to be getting some credit that does not belong
to her.
</p><p>Another thing she is responsible for is the "American boom" in
books, which so astonishes English readers and rouses the envy of
avaricious English authors, according, at least, to the London
<hi rend="italic"> Daily Telegraph</hi>.  Why do American books boom so enormously?  How
does it happen that the successful American novel sells three
hundred thousand copies when the English, if very successful, sells
fifty thousand?  The <hi rend="italic"> Daily Telegraph</hi> answers wisely, because of
the enormous population the American publisher has to deal with&mdash;a
feminine population, for American men do not read.  But is it a
good thing&mdash;for them or for the novel&mdash;that American wives and
daughters should absorb three hundred thousand copies of some
romance?  The author who has written a really good, unpopular thing
thinks not, and the critic agrees with him.  No, it is impossible
to be an artist and please three hundred thousand women.  There is
something gross in these figures; the refined intelligence shrinks
from the idea of such a crowd.  By taking the novel in such
quantities woman has brought it down to the level of the bargain-counter.  Can true art be bought below cost?
</p><p>The worst is, there is no hope for the future.  More women are
buying and reading every year.</p>
<trailer>                                 <hi rend="italic"> Neith Boyce.</hi></trailer>




</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
