<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="BraAmer"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="BraAmer">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Negro in American Fiction</title>
<title type="sort">negro in american fiction</title>
<author>Brawley, Benjamin</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">26</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">BraAmer</idno>
<date value="1998">1998</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1998 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475747</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Negro in American Fiction</title>
<title level="j">The Dial, volume 60</title>
<title type="sort">negro in american fiction</title>
<author>Benjamin Brawley</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 445-450</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Henry O. Shepard Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
<date value="1916">1916</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: The University of Virginia Library, volume 61</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1916">1916</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
<term>African American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1998-06">June 1998</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Anne Stinehart, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">



<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> 
	<pb n="435"/>
<head><hi rend="italic">THE NEGRO IN AMERICAN FICTION.</hi></head>

<p>
     Ever since Sydney Smith sneered at American books a hundred years ago, honest critics
have asked themselves if the literature of the United States was not really open to the charge of
provincialism. Within the last year or two the argument has been very much revived; and an
English critic, Mr. Edward Garnett, writing in "The Atlantic Monthly," has pointed out that with
our predigested ideas and made-to-order fiction we not only discourage individual genius but
make it possible for the multitude to think only such thoughts as have passed through a sieve.
Our most popular novelists, and sometimes our most respectable writers, see only the sensation
that is uppermost for the moment in the mind of the crowd, &mdash; divorce, graft, tainted meat or
money, &mdash;  and they proceed to cut the cloth of their fiction accordingly. Mr. Owen Wister, a
"regular practitioner" of the novelist's art, in substance admitting the weight of these charges,
lays the blame on our crass democracy which utterly refuses to do its own thinking and which is
satisfied only with the tinsel and gewgaws and hobbyhorses of literature. And no theme has
suffered so much from the coarseness of the mob-spirit in literature as that of the Negro.
</p><p>As a matter of fact, the Negro in his problems and strivings offers to American writers the
greatest opportunity that could possibly be given them to-day. It is commonly agreed that only
one other large question, that of the relations of capital and labor, is of as much interest to the
American public; and even this great issue fails to possess quite the appeal offered by the Negro
from the social standpoint. One can only imagine what a Victor Hugo, detached and
philosophical, would have done with such a theme in a novel. When we see what actually has
been done, &mdash; how often in the guise of fiction a writer has preached a sermon or shouted a
political creed or vented his spleen, &mdash; we are not exactly proud of the art of novel-writing as it
has been developed in the United States of America. Here was opportunity for tragedy,
   <pb n="446"/>
for comedy, for the subtle portrayal of all the relations of man with his fellow man, for faith and
hope and love and sorrow. And yet, with the Civil War fifty years in the distance, not one novel
or one short story of the first rank has found its inspiration in this great theme. Instead of such
work we have consistently had traditional tales, political tracts, and lurid melodramas.
</p><p>Let us see who have approached the theme, and just what they have done with it, for the
present leaving out of account all efforts put forth by Negro writers themselves.
</p><p>The names of four exponents of Southern life come at once to mind, &mdash; George W. Cable,
Joel Chandler Harris, Thomas Nelson Page, and Thomas Dixon; and at once, in their outlook
and method of work, the first two become separate from the last two.   Cable and Harris have
looked toward the past, and have embalmed vanished or vanishing types. Mr. Page and Mr.
Dixon, with their thought on the present (though for the most part they portray the recent past),
have used the novel as a vehicle for political propaganda.
</p><p>It was in 1879 that "Old Creole Days" evidenced the advent of a new force in American
literature; and on the basis of this work, and of "The Grandissimes" which followed, Mr. Cable
at once took his place as the foremost portrayer of life in old New Orleans. By birth, by
temperament, and by training he was thoroughly fitted for the task to which he set himself. His
mother was from New England, his father of the stock of colonial Virginia; and the stern
Puritanism of the North was mellowed by the gentler influences of the South. Moreover, from
his long apprenticeship in newspaper work in New Orleans he had received abundantly the
knowledge and training necessary for his work. Setting himself to a study of the Negro of the old
regime, he made a specialty of the famous &mdash; and infamous &mdash; quadroon society of Louisiana of
the third and fourth decades of the last century. And excellent as was his work, turning his face
to the past in manner as well as in matter, from the very first he raised the question propounded
by this paper. In his earliest volume there was a story entitled "'Tite Poulette," the heroine of
which was a girl amazingly fair, the supposed daughter of one Madame John. A young
Dutchman fell in love with 'Tite Poulette, championed her cause at all times, suffered a beating
and stabbing for her, and was by her nursed back to life and love. In the midst of his perplexity
about joining himself to a member of another race, came the word from Madame John that the
girl was not her daughter, but the child of yellow fever patients whom she had nursed until they
died, leaving their infant in her care. Immediately upon the publication of this story, the author
received a letter from a young woman who had actually lived in very much the same situation as
that portrayed in "'Tite Poulette," telling him that his story was not true to life and that he knew it
was not, for Madame John really <hi rend="italic">was</hi> the mother of the heroine.  Accepting the criticism,
Mr. Cable set about the composition of "Madame Delphine," in which the situation is somewhat
similar, but in which at the end the mother tamely makes a confession to a priest. What is the
trouble? The artist is so bound by circumstance and hemmed in by tradition that he simply has
not the courage to launch out into the deep and work out his human problems for himself. Take a
representative portrait from "The Grandissimes":
</p>

<p><q>Clemence had come through ages of African savagery, through fires that do not refine, but
that blunt and blast and blacken and char; starvation, gluttony, drunkenness, thirst, drowning,
nakedness, dirt, fetichism, debauchery, slaughter, pestilence, and the rest &mdash; she was their heiress;
they left her the cinders of human feelings. . .  She had had children of assorted colors &mdash; had one
with her now, the black boy that brought the basil to Joseph; the others were here and there,
some in the Grandissime households or field-gangs, some elsewhere within occasional sight,
some dead, some not accounted for.  Husbands &mdash; like the Samaritan woman's. We know she was
a constant singer and laugher.</q>

Very brilliant of course; and yet Clemence is a relic, not a prophetess.
</p><p>Still more of a relic is Uncle Remus. For decades now, this charming old Negro has been held
up to the children of the South as the perfect expression of the beauty of life in the glorious
times "befo' de wah," when every Southern gentleman was suckled at the bosom of a "black
mammy." Why should we not occasionally attempt to paint the Negro of the new day &mdash;
intelligent, ambitious, thrifty, manly? Perhaps he is not so poetic; but certainly the human
element is greater.
</p><p>To the school of Cable and Harris belong also of course Miss Grace King and Mrs. Ruth
McEnery Stuart, a thoroughly representative piece of work being Mrs. Stuart's "Uncle
   <pb n="447"/>
'Riah's Christmas Eve." Other more popular writers of the day, Miss Mary Johnston and Miss
Ellen Glasgow for instance, attempt no special analysis of the Negro. They simply take him for
granted as an institution that always has existed and always will exist, as a hewer of wood and
drawer of water, from the first flush of creation to the sounding of the trump of doom.
</p><p>But more serious is the tone when we come to Thomas Nelson Page and Thomas Dixon. We
might tarry for a few minutes with Mr. Page to listen to more such tales as those of Uncle
Remus; but we must turn to living issues. Times have changed. The grandson of Uncle Remus
does not feel that he must stand with his hat in his hand when he is in our presence, and he even
presumes to help us in the running of our government. This will never do; so in "Red Rock" and
"The Leopard's Spots" it must he shown that he should never have been allowed to vote anyway,
and those honorable gentlemen in the Congress of the United States in the year 1865 did not
know at all what they were about. Though we are given the characters and setting of a novel, the
real business is to show that the Negro has been the "sentimental pet" of the nation all too long.
By all means let us have an innocent white girl, a burly Negro, and a burning at the stake, or the
story would be incomplete.
</p><p>We have the same thing in "The Clansman," a "drama of fierce revenge." But here we are
concerned very largely with the blackening of a man's character. Stoneman (Thaddeus Stevens
very thinly disguised) is himself the whole Congress of the United States. He is a gambler, and
"spends a part of almost every night at Hall &amp; Pemberton's Faro Place on Pennsylvania Avenue."
He is hysterical, "drunk with the joy of a triumphant vengeance." "The South is conquered soil,"
he says to the President (a mere figure-head, by the way), "I mean to blot it from the map."
Further: "It is but the justice and wisdom of heaven that the Negro shall rule the land of his
bondage. It is the only solution of the race problem. Wait until I put a ballot in the hand of every
Negro, and a bayonet at the breast of every white man from the James to the Rio Grande."
Stoneman, moreover, has a mistress, a mulatto woman, a "yellow vampire" who dominates him
completely.  "Senators, representatives, politicians of low and high degree, artists,
correspondents, foreign ministers, and cabinet officers hurried to acknowledge their fealty to the
uncrowned king, and hail the strange brown woman who held the keys of his house as the first
lady of the land." This, let us remember, was for some months the best-selling book in the
United States. A slightly altered version of it has very recently commanded such prices as were
never before paid for seats at a moving picture entertainment; and with "The Traitor" and "The
Southerner" it represents our most popular treatment of the gravest social question in American
life! "The Clansman" is to American literature exactly what a Louisiana mob is to American
democracy. Only too frequently, of course, the mob represents us all too well.
</p><p>Turning from the longer works of fiction to the short story, I have been interested to see how
the matter has been dealt with here. For purposes of comparison I have selected from ten
representative periodicals as many distinct stories, no one of which was published more than ten
years ago; and as these are in almost every case those stories that first strike the eye in a
periodical index, we may assume that they are thoroughly typical. The ten are: "Shadow," by
Harry Stillwell Edwards, in the "Century" (December, 1906) ; "Callum's Co'tin': A Plantation
Idyl," by Frank H. Sweet, in "The Craftsman" (March, 1907); "His Excellency the Governor," by
L. M. Cooke, in "Putnam's" (February, 1908); "The Black Drop," by Margaret Deland, in
"Collier's Weekly" (May 2 and 9, 1908); "Jungle Blood," by Elmore Elliott Peake, in
"McClure's" (September, 1908); "The Race-Rioter," by Harris Merton Lyon, in the "American"
(February, 1910) ; "Shadow," by Grace MacGowan Cooke and Alice MacGowan, in
"Everybody's" (March. 1910) ; "Abram's Freedom," by Edna Turpin, in the "Atlantic"
(September, 1912); "A Hypothetical Case," by Norman Duncan, in "Harper's" (June, 1915); and
"The Chalk Game," by L. B. Yates, in "The Saturday Evening Post" (June 5, 1915). For high
standards of fiction I think we may safely say that, all in all, the periodicals here mentioned are
representative of the best that America has to offer. In some cases the story cited is the only one
on the Negro question that a magazine has published within the decade.
   <pb n="448"/>
</p><p>"Shadow" (in the "Century") is the story of a Negro convict who for a robbery committed at
the age of fourteen was sentenced to twenty years of hard labor in the mines of Alabama. An
accident disabled him, however, and prevented his doing the regular work for the full period of
his imprisonment. At twenty he was a hostler, looking forward in despair to the fourteen years of
confinement still waiting for him. But the three little girls of the prison commissioner visit the
prison. Shadow performs many little acts of kindness for them, and their hearts go out to him.
They storm the governor and the judge for his pardon, and present the Negro with his freedom as
a Christmas gift. The story is not long, but it strikes a note of genuine pathos.
</p><p>"Callum's Co'tin'" is concerned with a hard-working Negro, a blacksmith, nearly forty, who
goes courting the girl who called at his shop to get a trinket mended for her mistress. At first he
makes himself ridiculous by his finery; later he makes the mistake of coming to a crowd of
merrymakers in his working clothes. More and more, however, he storms the heart of the girl,
who eventually capitulates. From the standpoint simply of craftsmanship, the story is an
excellent piece of work.
</p><p>"His Excellency the Governor" deals with the custom on Southern plantations of having, in
imitation of the white people, a Negro "governor" whose duty it was to settle minor disputes. At
the death of old Uncle Caleb, who for years had held this position of responsibility, his son Jubal
should have been the next in order. He was likely to be superseded, however, by loud-mouthed
Sambo, though urged to assert himself by Maria, his wife, an old house-servant who had no
desire whatever to be defeated for the place of honor among the women by Sue, a former
field-hand. At the meeting where all was to be decided, however, Jubal with the aid of his fiddle
completely confounded his rival and won. There are some excellent touches in the story; but, on
the whole, the composition is hardly more than fair in literary quality.
</p><p>"The Black Drop," throughout which we see the hand of an experienced writer, analyzes the
heart of a white boy who is in love with a girl who is almost white, and who when the test
confronts him suffers the tradition that binds him to get the better of his heart. "But you will still
believe that I love you?" he asks, ill at ease as they separate. "No, of course I can not believe
that," replies the girl.
</p><p>"Jungle Blood" is the story of a simple-minded, simple-hearted Negro of gigantic size who in
a moment of fury kills his pretty wife and the white man who has seduced her. The tone of the
whole may be gleaned from the description of Moss Harper's father: "An old darky sat drowsing
on the stoop. There was something ape-like about his long arms, his flat, wide-nostriled nose,
and the mat of gray wool which crept down his forehead to within two inches of his eyebrows."
</p><p>"The Race-Rioter" sets forth the stand of a brave young sheriff to protect his prisoner, a
Negro boy, accused of the assault and murder of a little white girl. Hank Egge tries by every
possible subterfuge to defeat the plans of a lynching party, and finally dies riddled with bullets
as he is defending his prisoner. The story is especially remarkable for the strong and sympathetic
characterization of such contrasting figures as young Egge and old Dikeson, the father of the
dead girl.
</p><p>"Shadow" (in "Everybody's") is a story that depends for its force very largely upon incident. It
studies the friendship of a white boy, Ranny, and a black boy, Shadow, a relationship that is
opposed by both the Northern white mother and the ambitious and independent Negro mother.
In a fight, Shad breaks a collar-bone for Ranny; later he saves him from drowning. In the face of
Ranny's white friends, all the harsher side of the problem is seen; and yet the human element is
strong beneath it all. The story, not without considerable merit as it is, would have been
infinitely stronger if the friendship of the two boys had been pitched on a higher plane. As it is,
Shad is very much like a dog following his master.
</p><p>"Abram's Freedom" is at the same time one of the most clever and one of the most provoking
stories with which we have to deal. It is a perfect example of how one may walk directly up to
the light and then deliberately turn his back upon it. The story is set just before the Civil War. It
deals with the love of the slave Abram for a free young woman, Emmeline. "All his life he had
heard and used the phrase 'free nigger' as a term of contempt. What, then, was this vague feeling,
not definite enough yet to be a wish or
   <pb n="449"/>
even a longing?" So far, so good. Emmeline inspires within her lover the highest ideals of
manhood, and he becomes a hostler in a livery-stable, paying to his master so much a year  for
his freedom. Then comes the astounding and forced conclusion. At the very moment when, after
years of effort, Emmeline has helped her husband to gain his freedom (and when all the slaves
are free as a matter of fact by virtue of the Emancipation Proclamation), Emmeline. whose
husband has special reason to be grateful to his former master, says to the lady of the house: "Me
an' Abram ain't got nothin' to do in dis worl' but to wait on you an' master."
</p><p>In "'A Hypothetical Case" we again see the hand of a master-craftsman. Is a white boy
justified in shooting a Negro who has offended him? The white father is not quite at ease,
quibbles a good deal, but finally says Yes. The story, however, makes it clear that the Negro did
not strike the boy. He was a hermit living on the Florida coast and perfectly abased when he met
Mercer and his two companions. When the three boys pursued him and finally overtook him, the
Negro simply held the hands of Mercer until the boy had recovered his temper. Mercer in his
rage really struck himself.
</p><p>"The Chalk Game" is the story of a little Negro jockey who wins a race in Louisville only to
be drugged and robbed by some "flashlight" Negroes who send him to Chicago. There he
recovers his fortunes by giving to a group of gamblers the correct "tip" on another race, and he
makes his way back to Louisville much richer by his visit. Throughout the story emphasis is
placed upon the superstitious element in the Negro race, an element readily considered by men
who believe in luck.
</p><p>Of these ten stories, only five strike out with even the slightest degree of independence.
"Shadow" (in the "Century") is not a powerful piece of work, but it is written in tender and
beautiful spirit.  "The Black Drop" is a bold handling of a strong situation. "The Race-Rioter"
also rings true, and in spite of the tragedy there is optimism in this story of a man who is not
afraid to do his duty.  ''Shadow" (in "Everybody's") awakens all sorts of discussion, but at least
attempts to deal honestly with a situation that might arise in any neighborhood at any time. "A
Hypothetical Case" is the most tense and independent story in the list.
</p><p>On the other hand, "Callum's Co'tin'" and "His Excellency the Governor," bright comedy
though they are, belong after all to the school of Uncle Remus. "Jungle Blood" and "The Chalk
Game" belong to the class that always regards the Negro as an animal, a minor, a plaything, &mdash;
but never as a man. ''Abram's Freedom," exceedingly well written for two-thirds of the way, falls
down hopelessly at the end. Many old Negroes after the Civil War preferred to remain with
their former masters; but certainly no young woman of the type of Emmeline would sell her
birthright for a mess of pottage.
</p><p>Just there is the point. That the Negro is ever to be taken seriously is incomprehensible to
some people. It is the story of "The Man that Laughs" over again. The more Gwynplaine protests,
the more outlandish he becomes to the House of Lords.
</p><p>We are simply asking that those writers of fiction who deal with the Negro shall be
thoroughly honest with themselves, and not remain forever content to embalm old types and
work over outworn ideas. Rather should they sift the present and forecast the future. But of
course the editors must be considered. The editors must give their readers what the readers want;
and when we consider the populace, of course we have to reckon with the mob. And the mob
does not find anything very attractive about a Negro who is intelligent, cultured, manly, and who
does not smile. It will be observed that in no one of the ten stories above mentioned, not even in
one of the five remarked most favorably, is there a Negro of this type. Yet he is obliged to come.
America has yet to reckon with him. The day of Uncle Remus as well as of Uncle Tom is over.
</p><p>Even now, however, there are signs of better things. Such an artist as Mr. Howells, for
instance, has once or twice dealt with the problem in excellent spirit. Then there is the work of
the Negro writers themselves. The numerous attempts in fiction made by them have most
frequently been open to the charge of crassness already considered; but Paul Laurence Dunbar,
Charles W. Chesnutt, and W. E. Burghardt DuBois have risen above the crowd. Mr. Dunbar, of
course, was better in poetry than in prose. Such a short story as "Jimsella," however, exhibited
considerable
   <pb n="450"/>
technique. "The Uncalled" used a living topic, treated with only partial success. But for the most
part, Mr. Dunbar's work looked toward the past. Somewhat stronger in prose is Mr. Chesnutt.
"The Marrow of Tradition" is not much more than a political tract, and "The Colonel's Dream"
contains a good deal of preaching; but "The House behind the Cedars" is a real novel. Among his
short stories, "The Bouquet" may be remarked for technical excellence, and "The Wife of His
Youth" for a situation of unusual power. Professor DuBois's "The Quest of the Silver Fleece"
contains at least one strong dramatic situation; but the author is a sociologist and essayist rather
than a novelist. The grand epic of the race is yet to be produced.
</p><p>Some day we shall work out the problems of our great country. Some day we shall not have a
state government set at defiance, and the massacre of Ludlow. Some day our little children will
not slave in mines and mills, but will have some chance at the glory of God's creation; and some
day the Negro will cease to be a problem and become a human being. Then, in truth, we shall
have the Promised Land. But until that day comes let those who mould our ideals and set the
standards of our art in fiction at least be honest with themselves and independent. Ignorance we
may for a time forgive; but a man has only himself to blame if he insists on not seeing the
sunrise in the new day.
</p>

<closer>
<signed>
BENJAMIN BRAWLEY.
</signed>
</closer>

</div1>



</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

