<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="BraOdds"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="BraOdds">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">An Odd Sort of Popular Book</title>
<title type="sort">odd sort of popular book</title>
<author>Bradford, Gamaliel</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Charles Keller</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">29</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">BraOdds</idno>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475749</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">An Odd Sort of Popular Book</title>
<title level="j">The Atlantic Monthly: A Magazine of Literature, Science, Art, and Politics. Vol. 93, no. 558.</title>
<title type="sort">odd sort of popular book</title>
<author>Gamaliel Bradford, Jr.</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pages 548-554</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Houghton, Mifflin and Company. | The Riverside Press.</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston and New York. | Cambridge, Mass.</pubPlace>
<date value="1904-04">April 1904</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: UVa library, call no.: AP2.A8</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1904">1904</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; non-fiction</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-10">October 1997</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">



<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> <pb n="548"/>
<head>AN ODD SORT OF POPULAR BOOK.</head>

<p>MULTIPLICITY of editions does not
make a book a classic. Otherwise Worcester's
Dictionary and Mrs. Lincoln's
Cook-Book might almost rival Shakespeare.
Nevertheless, when a work
which has little but its literary quality to
recommend it achieves sudden and permanent
popularity, it is safe to assume
that there is something about it which will
repay curious consideration. As to the
popularity of The Anatomy of Melancholy
there can be no dispute. "Scarce any
book of philology in our land hath, in
so short a time, passed through so many
editions," says old Fuller; though why
"philology"? The first of these editions
appeared in 1621. It was followed
by four others during the few years preceding
the author's death in 1640. Three
more editions were published at different
times in the seventeenth century. The
eighteenth century was apparently contented
to read Burton in the folios; but
the book was reprinted in the year 1800,
and since then it has been issued in various
forms at least as many as forty times,
though never as yet with what might be
called thorough editing.
</p><p>Quantity of approval is in this case well
supported by quality. Milton showed
his admiration, as usual, by imitation.
Sterne conveyed passage after passage
almost bodily into Tristram Shandy.
Southey's odd book, The Doctor, follows
Burton closely in manner and often in
matter. Dr. Johnson said that The
Anatomy of Melancholy was the only
book that ever took him out of bed two
hours sooner than he wished to rise; large
commendation surely, and I have never
found any other, even of the most devout
Burtonians, quite ready to echo it.
Lamb was a reader, adorer, and imitator;
Keats, the first two, at any rate. Finally,
Mr. Saintsbury assures us that "for
reading either continuous or desultory,
<milestone unit="column"/>
either grave or gay, at all times of life
and in all moods of temper, there are
few authors who stand the test of practice
so well as the author of The Anatomy
of Melancholy." For all that, I would
not advise the general reader to buy a
copy in too great haste. He will, perhaps,
find it easier to read about the book
than to read it.
</p><p>What we know of the life of Robert
Burton is a very small matter, as is the
case with so many of his greater
contemporaries. He was born at Lindley
in Leicestershire in 1577, thirteen years
after Shakespeare, four years after Ben
Jonson. He was at school at Sutton-Coldfield in Warwickshire and at Nuneaton
till he was seventeen. He then
went to Brasenose College. In 1599 he
was elected student of Christ Church.
In 1614 he received the degree of B. D.,
and in 1616 he became vicar of St.
Thomas in the west suburb of Oxford.
About 1630 he added to this cure the
rectory of Segrave in Leicestershire.
Besides the Anatomy he wrote a Latin
comedy, Philosophaster, unusually clever
and brilliant in its kind. He died in
1640, and was buried in the choir of
Christ Church Cathedral. The little bit
of gossip narrated by wood is amusingly
illustrative of the mythical character so
apt to attach itself to the solitary scholar.
It seems that Burton's death occurred at
or very near the time which had been
foretold by himself from the calculation
of his own nativity; in consequence of
which "several of the students did not
forbear to whisper among themselves
that, rather than there should be a mistake
in the calculation, he sent up his soul
to heaven through a slip about his neck."
With the exception of a few other bits
of doubtful gossip and of the full text
of his will, this is all of importance that
has come down to us about the author of
   <pb n="549"/>
the Anatomy. It is rather brief, certainly,
when one realizes that, if he had
lived two hundred and fifty years later,
he would probably have been honored
with two solid volumes of so-called
biography, like many another much less
worthy of it.
</p><p>Far more than most great writers,
however, Burton left the reflection of his
life and character in his work, and The
Anatomy of Melancholy may be called
one of the most intensely personal books
that were ever written. To be sure, the
author does not constantly and directly
refer to himself and his own affairs.
Nevertheless, the impress of his spirit is
felt on every page.
</p><p>Several of the biographical facts above
mentioned are derived from casual remarks
dropped here and there throughout
the book. Of his mother, Mistress
Dorothy Burton, he says that she had
"excellent skill in chirurgery, sore eyes,
aches, etc.," and that she had "done many
famous and good cures upon divers poor
folks that were otherwise destitute of
help." He gives us a reminiscence of
his boyhood: "They think no slavery in
the world (as once I did myself) like to
that of a grammar scholar." He speaks
with a grain of bitterness of a younger
brother's lot: "I do much respect and
honor true gentry and nobility; I was
born of worshipful parents myself, in
an ancient family; but I am a younger
brother, it concerns me not."
</p><p>He gives us many glimpses of his
lonely scholar's life. In his youth he
was ambitious: "I was once so mad to
bussell abroad and seek about for preferment,
tyre myself, and trouble all my
friends." But the world is cold, friendship
formal and touches not the heart:
"I have had some such noble friends,
acquaintance, and scholars, but most part
they and I parted as we met; they gave
me as much as I requested and that
was&mdash;." His habits are those of the
recluse and ascetic: "I am a bachelor
myself and lead a monastic life in a college."
<milestone unit="column"/>
"I am <hi rend="italic">aqu&aelig; potor</hi>, drink no
wine at all." Yet he loves the sweet of
nature too, if the bitter thirst of
knowledge would permit: "No man ever
took more delight in springs, woods,
groves, gardens, walks, fishponds, rivers,
etc." Force of circumstance, lack of
opportunity, younger brotherhood, timidity,
have kept him secluded within the
walls of great libraries, have piled huge
dusty tomes on the human beating of his
heart. "I have lived a silent, sedentary,
solitary, private life in the University,
as long almost as Xenocrates in Athens,
to learn wisdom as he did, penned up
most part in my study." Yet if the
Fates had willed otherwise, the man
would have been consenting. Let us
note right here that this is the whole
charm of Burton and his great book. It
is no dry treatise of a gray-haired pedant,
thumbing contentedly forever dull volumes
of mouldy tradition. For all its
quaint garb and thorny aspect, it is a
great human document, the work of a
man whose bodily life was passed in his
study, but whose senses were all keenly,
pantingly alert to catch the motion of
the wide world beyond. Beauty&mdash;he
adores beauty. "This amazing, confounding,
admirable beauty; 't is nature's
crown, gold, and glory." Love&mdash;Oh, how he could have loved! "I confess
I am but a novice, a contemplator
only," he writes of it; "yet <hi rend="italic">homo sum</hi>,
I am a man, and not altogether inexpert
in this subject." Like Flaubert, he
doubtless leaned forth from his study
window on many a moonlit night, and
heard a company of revelers with merry
song and pleasant jest, and caught the
dim flutter of a white gown, and found
all his books and learning mere dust beside
the laughter and the passion of the
world.
</p><p>And so he grew melancholy, as often
happens in such cases. When a man gets
these fits on him, he may either rush out
into active life for the sake of contrast,
he may marry, or go into politics, or do
   <pb n="550"/>
something even more rash and criminal;
or he may cut his throat; or he may write
a book. On the whole, the last method
is the most to be recommended. Burton
adopted it; and, with hom&oelig;opathic
ingenuity, he wrote a book on melancholy
itself. "I write against melancholy, by
being busy, to avoid melancholy....
Shall I say, my mistress melancholy, my
Egeria, or my evil genius?"
</p><p>The loose and literary sense in which
Burton uses the word melancholy is characteristic
of the tone of his book. Without
really attempting any precise definition,
or, rather, having confused the
reader with a multitude of definitions
taken from all the authors under the sun,
he proceeds to include every form of nervous
depression, from a mere temporary
fit of the blues to acute or chronic mania
and insanity. At the same time, being a
man of a logical and systematic turn of
mind, he imposes on others, and perhaps
on himself, with a great show of formal
and scientific treatment. The work is
mapped out into divisions, partitions,
sections, members, subsections, arranged in
as awful order of deduction as Euclid or
the Ethics of Spinoza. But let no one be
alarmed. This is pure matter of form.
The author speaks of what he likes, when
he likes. Occasionally he takes the pains
to recognize that he is digressing, as in
the delicious chapters entitled A Digression
of Spirits, A Digression of Air.
And then, with a sigh, he tries to call
himself back to the work in hand;
"But my melancholy spaniels quest, my
game is sprung, and I must suddenly
come down and follow." The game leads
him into strange places, however. The
vast and checkered meadow of the human
heart is his hunting-ground. Melancholy
is the skeleton in the closet, always
popping out at odd times and in
unexpected corners; but he keeps it
wreathed with bright flowers, and made
sweet with strange and subtle savors, and
brilliant and sparkling with jewels of
quaint wit and wandering fancy. Nevertheless,
<milestone unit="column"/>
when he does discuss his subject
itself, he has bits of sound common sense,
useful to-day and always, like his
recommendation of "the three Salernitan
Doctors, D. Merryman, D. Diet, and
D. Quiet, which cure all diseases."
</p><p>Some one may object that this saying
is quoted and not Burton's own invention.
Certainly, Burton is the greatest quoter
in literature, far surpassing even Montaigne.
His mind was full of the thoughts
of others, and he poured them forth together
with his own in inextricable mixture.
He was a man drenched, drowned
in learning, not learning of the quick,
smart, practical, modern type, which enables
its possessor to give interviews on
the inhabitants of Mars and testify on
poisons at a murder trial, but medi&aelig;val
learning, drowsy, strange, unprofitable,
and altogether lovely. In the discussion
of these melancholy matters all preceding
literature is laid under contribution,
not only the classics, but countless writers
of the Middle Ages, doubtless respectable
in their own day and possibly
in Burton's, but now so dead that the
reader stares and gasps at them and
wonders whether his author is not inventing
references, like the Oracle in
the Innocents Abroad. Melanelius, Ruffus,
A&euml;tius describe melancholy "to be
a bad and pievish disease." Hercules
de Saxonia approves this opinion, as
do Fucheius, Arnoldus, Guianerius, and
others&mdash;not unnaturally. Paulus takes
a different view, and Halyabbas still another.
Aret&aelig;us calls it "a perpetual anguish
of the soul, fastened on one thing,
without an ague." In this brilliant but
hazy statement the absence of ague is at
least a comfort. It is disquieting, indeed,
to find that "this definition of his
Merrialis taxeth;" but we are reassured
by the solid support of &AElig;lianus Montaltus.
And so on.
</p><p>Pure pedantry, you will say. Well,
yes. It would be, if Burton were not
saved from the extreme of pedantry by
a touch of humor, which makes you
   <pb n="551"/>
somehow feel that he does not take all
this quite seriously himself. Yet it is
very hard for him to look at anything
except through the eyes of some remote
authority. We have heard him speak
of his mother's excellent cures. It seems
that one of her favorite remedies was "an
amulet of a spider in a nutshell lapped
in silk," super-sovereign for the ague.
Burton finds it hard to swallow this; it
was "most absurd and ridiculous; for
what has a spider to do with a fever?"
Ah, but one day "rambling amongst
authors (as often I do) I found this very
medicine in Dioscorides, approved by
Matthiolus, repeated by Aldrovandus.
. . . I began to have a better opinion
of it, and to give more credit to amulets."
I can see from here Mistress
Dorothy Burton's lovely scorn at being
confirmed by Dioscorides. What did
she care for Dioscorides? Did she not
have the recipe from her great-aunt, and
has she not proved it a dozen times herself?
</p><p>This trick of constant quoting has led
some shallow people to set Burton down
as a mere quoter and nothing else. There
could be no greater mistake. It is the
activity and independence of his own
mind which make him so eager to watch
and compare the minds of others; and
while he profited by their thinking, he
was abundantly able to do his own, as
every page of his book shows. One need
ask no better specimen, of strong, shrewd,
satirical reflection than the sketch of a
Utopian commonwealth in the introduction
which purports to be by Democritus
Junior; and of many other passages we
may say the same.
</p><p>Nor was our author lacking in deep,
human sympathy, although his solitary
life and keen intellect disposed him to
be a trifle cynical. The celebrated bit
with the refrain "Ride on!"&mdash;so brilliantly
imitated by Sterne&mdash;shows a pitiful
appreciation of sorrow and misery,
which, indeed, are abundantly recognized
everywhere in the Anatomy.
<milestone unit="column"/>
</p><p>But perhaps the most characteristic
illustration of Burton's intense appetite
for humanity is his frequent reference
to common daily life and manners.
M. Anatole France tells us that the author
of The Imitation must certainly have
been a man of the world before he betook
himself to his lonely cell and pious meditation.
If Burton never was a man of
the world, he would certainly have liked
to be one. He peers out from behind
the bars of his cell and catches every
possible glimpse of the curious things
which are shut away from him. Shreds
of fashion, hints of frivolity, quips of
courtiers, the flash of swords and glittering
of jewels,&mdash;he will find a place for
them. Woman fascinates him especially,&mdash;that singular creature who apparently
cares nothing for books and study, laughs,
weeps, scolds, caresses, without any reasonable
cause whatever. Certainly no
philosopher should take any notice of
her,&mdash;yet they all do. And he exhausts
himself in cunning heaps of observation,
vain interrogations of mysterious boudoirs:
"Why do they make such glorious
shows with their scarfs, feathers, fans,
masks, furs, laces, tiffanies, ruffs, falls,
calls, cuffs, damasks, velvets, tinsel, cloth
of gold, silver, tissue? With colors of
heavens, stars, planets; the strength of
metals, stones, odors, flowers, birds, beasts,
fishes, and whatsoever Africk, Asia,
America, sea, land, art and industry of
man can afford? why do they use such
novelty of inventions; such new-fangled
tires; and spend such inestimable sums
on them? . . . Why is it but, as a day-net catcheth larks, to make young men
stoop unto them?" And old philosophers
also, he might have added.
</p><p>I have taken this passage from the
section on Love Melancholy; for Burton
devotes a large portion of his work
to that delightful subject. He feels it
necessary to make some apology for entering
upon it. Some persons will think
it hardly becoming in so grave, reverend,
and dignified a gentleman,&mdash;a clergy-man
   <pb n="552"/>
too. But he has good authors on
his side: " I excuse myself with Peter
Godefridus, Valleriola, Ficinus, Langius,
Cadmus Milesius, who writ fourteen
books of love." Surely, he would be
very critical who should ask more than
this.
</p><p>The apology once made, with what
gusto he sets forth, how he luxuriates
in golden tidbits from love's delicate
revels! "A little soft hand, pretty little
mouth, small, fine, long fingers, 'tis that
which Apollo did admire in Daphne."
"Of all eyes (by the way) black are
most amiable, enticing, and fair." "Oh,
that pretty tone, her divine and lovely
looks, her everything lovely, sweet, amiable,
and pretty, pretty, pretty." Is it
not the mere ecstasy of amorous frenzy?
Again, he gives us a very banquet, a rosy
wreath of old, simple English names, a
perfect old-fashioned garden: "Modest
Matilda, pretty, pleasing Peg, sweet, singing
Susan, mincing, merry Moll, dainty,
dancing Doll, neat Nancy, jolly Jone,
nimble Nell, kissing Kate, bouncing Bess
with black eyes, fair Phillis, with fine
white hands, fiddling Frank, tall Tib,
slender Sib, etc." Do you not hear their
merry laughter, as he heard it in his dim
study, a dream of fair faces and bright
forms twisting, and turning, and flashing
back and forth under the harvest
moon?
</p><p>Yet, after all, love is a tyrant and a
traitor, a meteor rushing with blind fury
among the placid orbs of life. What is
a man to make of these wild contrasts
and tragical transitions? At one moment
the lover seems to be on the pinnacle
of felicity, "his soul sowced,
imparadised, imprisoned in his lady; he
can do nothing, think of nothing but her;
she is his cynosure, Hesperus, and Vesper,
his morning and evening star, his
goddess, his mistress, his life, his soul,
his everything; dreaming, waking, she
is always in his mouth; his heart, eyes,
ears, and all his thoughts are full of her."
But then something goes wrong and the
<milestone unit="column"/>
note is altogether changed. "When this
young gallant is crossed in his love, he
laments, and cries, and roars downright.
`The virgin's gone and I am gone,
she 's gone, she 's gone, and what shall
I do? Where shall I find her? whom
shall I ask? what will become of me?
I am weary of this life, sick, mad, and
desperate.' "
</p><p>It becomes the sage, then, to be clear
of these toys. If he is to write about
Love Melancholy, let him cure it. Let
him hold up a warning to the unwary.
What is the use of days and nights spent
in toiling over learned authors, if the
young and foolish are not to have the
benefit of one's experience? If only the
young and foolish would profit! If only
the unwary would beware! Still we
must do our part. Let us remind them
that beauty fades. It is a rather well-known fact, but youth is so prone to forget
it. "Suppose thou beholdest her
in a frosty morning, in cold weather, in
some passion or perturbation of mind,
weeping, chafing, etc., riveled and ill-favored to behold.... Let her use all
helps art and nature can yield; be like
her, and her, and whom thou wilt, or all
these in one; a little sickness, a fever,
small-pox, wound, scar, loss of an eye or
limb, a violent passion, mars all in an
instant, disfigures all." Then let us exalt
the charms of a bachelor's life. It
has its weak points, as I feel, writing
here alone in the dust and chill, with nothing
but books about me, no prattle of
children, no merry chatter of busy
women. But what then? It is quieter,
after all. "Consider how contentedly,
quietly, neatly, plentifully, sweetly, and
how merrily he lives! He hath no man
to care for but himself, none to please,
no charge, none to control him, is tied to
no residence, no cure to serve, may go
and come when, whither, live where he
will, his own master, and do what he
list himself." Nevertheless, it all sounds
a little hollow, and as I sit here in the
winter midnight with my old pipe, I
   <pb n="553"/>
wonder if it might not have been otherwise.
</p><p>I have made my quotations with very
little skill, if the ingenious reader does
not by this time feel that Burton was in
his way a great master of style. His
skill and power as a writer, more than
anything else, show that he was not a
mere pedant or Dryasdust. It is true,
he himself disclaims any such futile
preocoupation. He has not "amended the
style, which now flows remissly, as it
was first conceived." His book is "writ
with as small deliberation as I do ordinarily
speak, without all affectation
of big words, fustian phrases, jingling
terms." But the facts belie him, and one
shudders to think what must have been
his idea of the big words he does not
use. A careful collation of the first edition
of the Anatomy with the last published
in the author's lifetime not only
shows a great number of additions and
alterations, but proves conclusively that
these changes were made, in many cases,
with a view to style and to style only.
Take a single instance. In the first edition
Burton wrote: "If it be so that the
earth is a moon, then are we all lunatic
within." Later he amplified this as follows,
with obvious gain in the beauty of
the phrase: "If it be so that the earth
is a moon, then are we also giddy,
vertiginous, and lunatic within this
sublunary maze." Amended, I think, but
oh, for the "big words, fustian phrases,
jingling terms"!
</p><p>Yes, Burton was a master of style.
He could bend language to his ends and
do as he willed with it. If he is often
rough, harsh, wanton in expression, it
is simply because, like Donne, he chose
to be so. Does he wish to tell a plain
story? Who can do it more lightly, simply,
briefly? "An ass and a mule went
laden over a brook, the one with salt, the
other with wool; the mule's pack was wet
by chance; the salt melted, his burden
the lighter; and he thereby much eased.
He told the ass, who, thinking to speed
<milestone unit="column"/>
as well, wet his pack likewise at the next
water; but it was much the heavier, he
quite tired."
</p><p>Does he wish to paint the foul and
horrible? I know of nothing in Swift
or Zola more replete with the luxury
of hideousness than the unquotable description
of the defects which infatuated
love will overlook,&mdash;a description which
Keats tells a correspondent he would give
his favorite leg to have written. Here,
as in so many passages I have quoted,
Burton piles up epithet after epithet, till
it seems as if the dictionary would be
exhausted,&mdash;a trick which, by the bye,
he may have caught from Rabelais, and
which would become very monotonous,
if it were not applied with such wonderful
variety and fertility.
</p><p>Then, at his will, the magician can
turn with ease from the bitter to the
sweet. When he touches love or beauty,
all his ruggedness is gone. His words
become full of grace, of suave, vague
richness, of delicacy, of mystery, as in
the phrase which Southey quotes in The
Doctor: "For peregrination charms our
senses with such unspeakable and sweet
variety that some count him unhappy
that never traveled, a kind of prisoner,
and pity his case, that from his cradle to
his old age beholds the same still; still,
still the same, the same." Or, to take a
more elaborate picture, see this, which
might be a Tintoretto or a Spenser:
"Witty Lucian, in that pathetical love-passage or pleasant description of Jupiter's
stealing of Europa and swimming
from Ph&oelig;nicia to Crete, makes the sea
calm, the winds hush, Neptune and Amphitrite
riding in their chariot to break
the waves before them, the Tritons dancing
round about with every one a torch;
the sea-nymphs, half-naked, keeping time
on dolphins' backs and singing Hymen&aelig;us;
Cupid nimbly tripping on the top
of the waters; and Venus herself coming
after in a shell, strawing roses and flowers
on their heads."
</p><p>I have dwelt thus long on Burton's
   <pb n="554"/>
style because it is absolutely characteristic,
and because it proves by its eminent
artistic qualities that he was not simply
a compiler and quoter, but a thinking
and feeling man, a strong, shrewd, passionate
temperament, gazing with intense
interest out of his scholastic windows
at the strange and moving spectacle
of life. In his fullness and abundance
he, more than any other English author,
recalls Montaigne, whom he quotes so
frequently: he has less fluidity, more
conventional prejudice, but also more
sincerity, more robust moral force. Again,
he in a certain sense resembles a greater
than Montaigne, his own greatest
contemporary, Shakespeare, whom he also
quotes enough to show that he knew and
loved his writings, at any rate, if not
himself. Shakespeare's work is like a glorious
piece of tapestry, a world of rich
and splendid hues, woven into a thousand
shapes of curious life. Burton's
is like the reverse side of the same: all
the bewildering wealth of color, but
rough, crude, misshapen, undigested.
</p><p>One of the characteristic oddities of
Burton's style is his perpetual use of the
phrase <hi rend="italic">etc</hi>. When his quick and fluent
pen has heaped together all the nouns or
adjectives in heaven and in earth, and
in the waters under the earth, he completes
the picture with the vast, vague
<milestone unit="column"/>
gesture of an <hi rend="italic">etc</hi>. Take an often-quoted
passage in the introduction, in which he
describes his own life as an observer and
contemplator: "Now come tidings of
weddings, maskings, mummeries, entertainments,
jubilees, embassies, tilts and
tournaments, trophies, triumphs, revels,
sports, plays; then again, as in a new-shifted scene, treasons, cheating tricks,
robberies, enormous villanies in all kinds,
funerals, burials, death of princes, new
discoveries, expeditions, now comical,
then tragical matters; to-day we hear of
new lords and officers created, to-morrow
of some great men deposed, and
again of fresh honors conferred; one is
let loose, another imprisoned; one purchaseth,
another breaketh; he thrives,
his neighbor turns bankrupt; now plenty,
then again dearth and famine; one runs,
another rides, wrangles, laughs, weeps,
etc."
</p><p>So we may sum up The Anatomy of
Melancholy in an <hi rend="italic">etc</hi>. The general tone
of the book, with its infinite multiplicity,
reminds one of nothing more than of the
quaint blending of mirth, mystery, and
spiritual awe so deliciously expressed in
Stevenson's baby couplet,&mdash;
</p>

<lg type="verse">
<l>"The world is so full of a number of things,</l>
<l> I'm sure we should all be as happy as kings."</l>
</lg>

<p>Only Burton would have laid a mischievous
and melancholy emphasis on should.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Gamaliel Bradford, Jr</hi>.
</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

