<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="BroCurr"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;

]>
<TEI.2 id="BroCurr">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Currency Act of 1751 / by Great Britain</title>
<title type="sort">currency act of 1751 by great britain</title>
<author>Brock: Great Britain</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Ronald Michener, University of Virginia</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">17</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">BroCurr</idno>
<date value="2000">2000</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2000 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475752</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>This text is part of the collection for the Leslie Brock Center for the Study of Colonial Currency.</p>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Currency Act of 1751</title>
<title level="j">The statutes at large, from Magna Charta to the end of the last Parliament, 1761.  By Owen Ruffhead.</title>
<title type="sort">currency act of 1751</title>
<author>Great Britain</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>2 pages</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>M. Basket</publisher>
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
<date value="1763">1763</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Law Library, University of Virginia  U.K. .18 .R922 1763 V. 7</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1763">1763</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2000-04">April, 2000</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Cynthia Filer, The Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<front id="d2">
<div1 type="introduction" id="d3">


<p>The text of the Currency Act of 1751, reproduced below, can be found
in <hi rend="underline">The Statutes at Large</hi>, London: Printed for
Mark Basket, 1769, Vol. 7, pp. 403-4, (24 George II, chapter 53).&nbsp;
It was enacted on June 10, 1751 by the Parliament of Great
Britain.&nbsp; Parliament had been
debating the wisdom of intervening in the colonies monetary
affairs for over a decade, and this act was the result of that debate.</p>

</div1>
</front>

<body id="d4">
<div1 type="decree" id="d5">
<head>C A P. LIII.</head>

<p>An Act to regulate and restrain Paper Bills of Credit in his
Majesty's Colonies or Plantations of <hi rend="italic">Rhode Island</hi> and
<hi rend="italic">Providence</hi> Plantations, <hi rend="italic">Connecticut</hi>, the
<hi rend="italic">Massachusets Bay</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">New Hampshire</hi> in
<hi rend="italic">America</hi>; and to prevent the same being legal Tenders in
Payments of Money.</p>

<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d6">

<p>[I.] WHEREAS the Act of Parliament made in the sixth Year of her late
Majesty Queen <hi rend="italic">Anne</hi>, intituled<note rend="right"><p>6 Ann.
<unclear cert="good">c. 30.</unclear></p></note> <hi rend="italic">An Act for ascertaining
the Rate of foreign Coins in her Majesty's Plantations in</hi> America,
hath been intirely frustrated in his Majesty's said Colonies of
<hi rend="italic">Rhode Island</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Providence</hi> Plantations,
<hi rend="italic">Connecticut</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Massachusets Bay</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">New
Hampshire</hi> in <hi rend="italic">America</hi>, by their creating and issuing, from
Time to Time, great Quantities of Paper Bills of Credit, by virtue of
Acts of Assembly, Orders, Resolutions or Votes, made or passed by their
respective Assemblies, and making legal the Tender of such Bills of
Credit in Payment for Debts, Dues and Demands; which Bills of Credit
have, for many Years past, been depreciating in their Value, by means
whereof all Debts of late Years have been paid and satisfied with a much
less Value than was contracted for, which hath been a great
Discouragement and Prejudice to the Trade and Commerce of his Majesty's
Subjects, by occasioning Confusion in Dealings, and lessening of Credit
in those Parts: Therefore, for the more effectual preventing and
remedying of the said Inconveniencies, may it please your most Excellent
Majesty, that it may be enacted; and be it enacted by the King's most
Excellent Majesty, by and with the Advice and Consent of the Lords
Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament
assembled, and by the Authority of the same, That from and after the
twenty-ninth Day of <hi rend="italic">September</hi> one thousand seven hundred and
fifty-one, it shall not be<note rend="right"><p>No Act to pass for
<unclear cert="good">creating</unclear> Paper Bills of Credit,</p></note>
lawful for the Governor, Council or Assembly for the Time being, or any
of them, or for the Lieutenant Governor, or
Person presiding or acting as Governor or Commander in Chief, for the
Time being, within all or any of the aforesaid Colonies or Plantations
of <hi rend="italic">Rhode Island</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Providence</hi> Plantations,
<hi rend="italic">Connecticut</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Massachusets Bay</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">New
Hampshire</hi>, to make or pass, or give his or their Assent to the
making or passing of any Act, Order, Resolution or Vote, within any of
the said Colonies or Plantations, whereby any Paper Bills or Bills of
Credit, of any Kind or Denomination whatsoever, shall be created or
issued under any Pretence whatsoever; or whereby the Time limited, or
the Provision made, for the calling in,<note rend="right"><p>or for
protracting the Time for the calling in such, or for depreciating or
reissuing the same.</p></note> sinking or discharging of such
Paper Bills, or Bills of Credit, as are already subsisting and passing
in Payment, within any of the said Colonies or Plantations, shall be
protracted or postponed; or whereby any of them shall be depreciated in
Value, or whereby the same shall be ordered or allowed to be re-issued,
or to obtain a new and further Currency; and that all such Acts, Orders,
Resolutions or Votes, which shall or may be passed or made, after the
said twenty-ninth Day of <hi rend="italic">September</hi> one thousand seven hundred
and fifty-one, within all or any of the said Colonies or Plantations,
shall be, and are hereby declared to be null and void, and of no Force
or Effect whatsoever.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d7">

<p>II. And be it further enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That all
such Paper Bills, or Bills of Credit<note rend="right"><p>Bills of Credit
now subsisting, to be called in.</p></note> as are now subsisting, and passing
in Payments, within any of the said Colonies or Plantations of <hi rend="italic">Rhode
Island</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Providence</hi> Plantations, <hi rend="italic">Connecticut</hi>,
<hi rend="italic">Massachusets Bay</hi> and <hi rend="italic">New Hampshire</hi>, shall be duly and
punctually called in, sunk and discharged, according to the Tenor of and
within the Periods limited by the respective Acts, Orders, Votes or
Resolutions, for creating and issuing, or continuing the same
respectively, unless where the same have been altered by any subsequent
Act or Acts of Assembly; and in that Case, that the same be discharged
according to the Tenor mentioned in the said Act or Acts of Assembly;
and that no such Paper Bills, or Bills of Credit, shall, from and after
such Periods so limited, as aforesaid be any longer current in all or any
of the said Colonies or Plantations respectively.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="3" id="d8">

<p>III. Provided nevertheless, That nothing in this Act contained shall
extend, or be construed to extend,<note rend="right"><p>Acts may pass for
issuing Bills of Credit for the current Service of the Year,
&amp;c.</p></note> to restrain any Governor or
Governors, Council or Assembly, within any of the said Colonies or
Plantations, from making or passing any Act or Acts of Assembly in any
of the said Colonies or Plantations, for the creating and issuing of
such Paper Bills, or Bills of Credit, in lieu of, and for securing such
reasonable Sum or Sums of Money, as shall be requisite for the current
Service of the Year; so as by such Act or Acts of Assembly, whereby such
Paper Bills, or Bills of Credit, shall be created or issued, sufficient
Provision be made to secure the calling in, discharging and sinking of
the same, within a short reasonable Time not exceeding the Space of two
Years, to be computed from the Dates of the respective Acts whereby such
Paper Bills, or Bills of Credit, were created and issued; any Thing
herein before contained to the contrary thereof in any wise
notwithstanding. </p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="4" id="d9">

<p>IV. Provided also, That nothing herein contained shall extend, or be
construed to extend to restrain any<note rend="right"><p>and for
extraordinary Emergencies, in case of War or Invasion.</p></note> Governor
or Governors, Council or Assembly, within any of the said Colonies or
Plantations, from making or
passing any Act or Acts of Assembly, in any of the said Colonies or
Plantations, for creating and issuing such Paper Bills, or Bills of
Credit, in lieu of and for securing such reasonable Sum or Sums of Money
as shall, at any Time hereafter, be necessary or expedient upon sudden
and extraordinary Emergencies of Government, in case of War and
Invasion, so as in every such Act or Acts of Assembly for the Emission
of Paper Bills, or Bills of Credit, so issued as aforesaid, due Care be
taken to ascertain the real Value of all such principal Sum or Sums for
which the same shall be so made, created and issued as aforesaid, and
also the Interest to be paid thereon; and so as Care be likewise taken,
in the said Act or Acts, to establish and provide an ample and
sufficient Fund for the calling in, discharging and sinking, within as
short and reasonable a Time as may be, not exceeding five Years at the
farthest, all the said Bills, by actual Payment of all and every the Sum
and Sums of Money for which the same shall be so made, created
and issued as aforesaid, with the Interest due thereon.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="5" id="d10">

<p>V. And whereas there are now subsisting and passing in Payment,
within the said Colonies and Plantations, divers Kinds of Paper Bills,
or Bills of Credit, of various Denominations, which have been heretofore
created and issued within the said Colonies and Plantations, or some of
them, on Loans and otherwise, whereby private Persons and their Estates
stand liable to, and bound for the Discharge of the Sums by them
borrowed and received on such Loans; without the Payment of which Sums
(in case any Difficulty or Obstruction should arise in the Payment
thereof) such Paper Bills, or Bills of Credit so issued on such Loans,
cannot be called in, discharged and sunk, according to the Tenor of the
respective Acts, Orders, Votes or Resolutions, by virtue whereof the
same have been so respectively issued. For the providing a Remedy for
such Inconveniencies, be it further enacted by the Authority aforesaid,
That all such Paper Bills, or Bills of Credit, of what Kind or
Denomination soever, which have at any Time heretofore been
created and issued on such Loans, within of the said Colonies or
Plantations, be duly<note rend="right"><p>Bills of Credit on Loans, to be
called in.</p></note> called in, and discharged and sunk, according to the
Tenor of the respective Orders, Votes or Resolutions, for creating and
issuing, or
continuing the same respectively, in like manner as all other Paper
Bills, or Bills of Credit, already subsisting within the said Colonies
or Plantations, are herein before required to be called in, discharged
and sunk. </p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="6" id="d11">

<p>VI. And be it further enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That all
Persons who have borrowed and<note rend="right"><p>Persons who have
borrowed Money on Loans, &amp;c. compellable to cischarge the
same.</p></note> taken up any Sum or Sums of Money on
Loans, for the Discharge whereof they and their respective Estates stand
bound, shall be required and compelled, by all due and legal Means, to
satisfy and discharge the Sums by them borrowed, according to the Terms
of such Loans respectively, and the true Intent and Meaning thereof,
except as is herein before excepted; and in case any Deficiency or Loss
shall happen by Failure of the Security so taken on such Loans
respectively, that the same, and every Part thereof, shall be supplied
and made good by an adequate Tax or Imposition, to be equally and
rateably assessed, levied and raised within the said Colonies or
Plantations respectively, where such Loss or Deficiency shall so happen.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="7" id="d12">

<p>VII. And be it further enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That from
and after the twenty-ninth Day<note rend="right"><p>No Paper Currency to
be deemed a legal Tender.</p></note> of <hi rend="italic">September</hi> one thousand seven
hundred and fifty-one, no Paper Currency, or Bills of Credit, of any
Kind or Denomination, which may be made, created or issued in any of the
said Colonies or Plantations, pursuant to the Provisions herein before
made in this Act, shall be a legal Tender in Payment of any private
Bargains, Contracts, Debts, Dues or Demands whatsoever, within the said
Colonies or Plantations, or any of them.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="8" id="d13">

<p>VIII. Provided, That nothing herein contained shall extend, or be
construed to extend to make any of the Bills now subsisting in any of the
said Colonies a legal Tender.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="9" id="d14">

<p>IX. And be it further enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That if any
Governor or Commander in Chief<note rend="right"><p>Penalty on Governor
giving his Assent to any Act contrary to this Act.</p></note> for the Time
being, in all or any of his Majesty's said Colonies or Plantations,
whether commissioned by his
Majesty, or elected by the People, shall, from and after the said
twenty-ninth Day of <hi rend="italic">September</hi> one thousand seven hundred and
fifty-one, give his Assent to any Act of Assembly, Order, Resolution or
Vote, for the Emission or Issuing of any Paper Bills, or Bills of
Credit, of any Kind or Denomination whatsoever; or for prolonging the
Time limited for calling in and sinking any such Paper Bills, or Bills
of Credit, as are now subsisting and passing in Payment; or for
	re-issuing or depreciating the same, contrary to the <note rend="right"><p><hi rend="italic">Concerning Plantations see further 29 Geo. 2. c. 5
&amp; 35. 30 Geo. 2. c. 9.</hi></p></note> true Intent and
Meaning of this Act; such Act, Order; Resolution, or Vote, shall be
<hi rend="italic">ipso facto</hi> null and void, and such Governor or Commander in Chief
shall be immediately dismissed from his Government, and for ever after
rendered incapable of any publick Office or Place of Trust.</p>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
