<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="BroEter"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="BroEter">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Eternal Feminine</title>
<title type="sort">eternal feminine</title>
<author>Brodhead, Eva Wilder</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">36</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">BroEter</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475753</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Eternal Feminine</title>
<title type="sort">eternal feminine</title>
<author>Eva Wilder Brodhead</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Century Magazine</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-10">October 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman, Monique Dull</name>
</respStmt>
<item>conversion to basic TEI-conformant markup</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head> Brodhead, Eva Wilder.  "The Eternal Feminine: A Story of Colorado."
<hi rend="italic"> Century Magazine</hi> 59 (1900): 761-767.
</head>
<pb n="761"/>
<p>
A faint smile glimmered across Mrs. Herritt's fair, faded face as
she sat on her porch in the waning light of the October afternoon,
rocking tranquilly, and regarding with suave interest a certain
active little scene which the main street of the Colorado town
presented.  She sat long and lax in the low chair.  About the soft
attenuation of her figure the folds of a daintily sprigged print
gown fell loose and starchless, with an effect frankly free of any
pretension either esthetic or modish.  There was a similar accent,
artless and unfashionable, in the slack, smooth coiling of Mrs.
Herritt's heavy light hair, in which a dull fawn tint was subduing
the yellower hue of youth.  She had, upon the whole, the air of one
more solicitous to please herself than the public, and the innocent
blueness of her eyes, though a little frustrated of convincing
candor by reason of the triangular droop of the lids, still added
to her outward person a final note of unaspiring simplicity.
</p><p>Behind Mrs. Herritt the house door stood open.  The paint was
scaling from its battered panels, and the vista of worn oil-cloth
which it disclosed showed a surface through which the canvas
structure was nibbling.  A child's toys and the scattered leaves of
a book lay about the porch floor, and a wiry vine overhead was
casting its copper leaves down in a perpetual little clatter.  Some
of these fell on Mrs. Herritt's folded hands, but her attention
remained fixed upon the throng of well-dressed women who were still
issuing from the door of the town hall half a square away.
</p><p>The action and attire of this loquacious group contributed a
sudden look of life and color to the almost deserted adobe-colored
street.  From the snow-patched peaks, drawn up in solemn bivouac
along the west, mild shadows were falling.  On Old Baldy the sun
lay in a last amber haze, the glow of which, crossing the town's
commercial block of pink brick, its coal-grimed mine tipples and
fans, its gathering of miners' paintless dwellings, of Mexican mud
huts, and of pretty, ornate, jig-sawed cottages, widened
illimitably on the outer plains.  These, vestured in the wan chrome
of autumnal grama-and buffalo-grass, were without accident, except
for a solitary butte to the north, which, rising in a gray majestic
pile, like an aged fortress, conferred the pathos of an extreme
contrast upon the town.  Everything looked trifling and crude in
the face of the hoar mass.  The red roofs of the better houses
perking through the thin cottonwoods might have been thrust in
place by a child's inconsequent hand; the very church spires were
fantastic; while the Truex house, a massive aggregation of pink and
buff sandstone, looming in aristocratic isolation at the end of the
street, offered its florid vulgarity to the vast mournfulness of
the scene in a sort of complacent antithesis.
</p><p>It was very quiet.  The voices of the throng of women carried
far, in a sound of such enthusiastic accord as made Mrs. Herritt
graphically aware of the nature of the business which had, that
afternoon, been forward in the Women's Political League.  That it
had with fervent unanimity declared for Mr. Truex, or rather for
the party of which he was a congressional nominee, seemed certain.
Such an action on the league's part was indeed natural and
inevitable.  Truex was the personage of the town, a man of
financial account as mine-owner and merchant, and of that genial
turn of temper which no sane person finds pleasure in withstanding.
He was popular, and might have had political honors long before
this had he wished them.  The fact that he had not wished them
before, and was suspected of not particularly wishing them now,
added to his candidacy an element which the women of the league
found charming.  It was a sort of personal tribute to each of them
that the ambitions of his daughter should have coerced his final
acquiescence.  It showed the power of woman's eloquence, and was a
triumph to the whole sex.  They all liked to feel that they could
have a

<pb n="762"/>
hand in rewarding a compliance which presented
features so modest and retiring.  To thrust the crown upon an
unwilling Caesar is always a pleasant business.  If you happen to
know him in a friendly and familiar sort, the joy grows: it is a
commonplace of psychology that the single vivid detail rivets the
mind more forcibly than acres of abstraction.  Hence, in the
candidacy of its fellow-townsman the league found itself, for the
first time, regarding the party, hitherto nothing more than a dim
agglomeration of lofty principles, with quite a new and enthralling
interest.  In working for its success there would now be the
concrete satisfaction of watching results in a neighbor's
household; of seeing glory close at hand in Helen Truex's person;
and of observing the pageant of millinery and chiffon which must
naturally attend the expansion of her career.
</p><p>Mrs. Herritt could see Helen in the throng.  The girl, so long
burdened with the rule of her father's widowed house and the
formation of his character, already showed in her small, keen face
something of the care that yokes with empire.  Among the others she
seemed a kind of nerve-center, which vibrated force.  Every one
seemed charged with it&mdash;every one except the secretary of the
league, who seemed at intervals to be quietly suggesting to Helen
the lateness of the hour.
</p><p>The secretary was tall and beautiful, even at the distance,
and Mrs. Herritt, catching the air of dignity and moderation in her
attitude, breathed a word of tribute.  "If they were all like
that!" she said to herself.  As she saw how Miss Truex rested her
hand on the secretary's arm, Mrs. Herritt remembered that current
gossip ascribed to Helen a design of domestic happiness for her
father, and that Esther Burley was the one whom she had chosen to
add luster to the honors of state and to soothe its cares.
</p><p>Whatever Esther's own views of this matter might be, Mrs.
Herritt could observe no change in her looks when Mr. Truex
himself, emerging presently from his office, fell into the
applausive hands of the league.  His big, cordial face and broad
shoulders rose above the stir of flowers and feathers in stalwart
relief.  He seemed to be making jokes, for a wind of light laughter
came up the street.
</p><p>"They've been serious so long they're ready to be amused at
anything," commented Mrs. Herritt.  "Ah, they're looking this way!
They've been telling Mr. Truex what a rousing vote they mean to
give him.  They've said there wasn't a woman in town that wouldn't
go to the polls on election day, and just then they've remembered
me!"
</p><p>The league was certainly gazing toward the Herritt house,
while Truex, escaping from the throng, repeatedly shook his head
with a gesture of interdiction.
</p><p>"They want to appoint a committee to call on me, and he's
telling them not to," surmised the lady on the porch; "but they
will&mdash;they have!"  She added presently, in speculative fashion:
"Miss Burley and Mrs. Wiles seem to be their choice&mdash;the West as it
was and as it is.  Ah, they've started!"
</p><p>There was assuredly a certain air of objective about the two
women who could now be seen coming down the street.  Beside Miss
Burley, a stately figure in her severe frock of dark blue, waddled
a short, stout person, over whose ears a limp straw hat was firmly
tied.  Mrs. Wiles's weather-beaten face shone unabashed above the
straight neckband of a black calico gown, frankly adjusted down the
baggy waist with white agate buttons.  As her attire was now, it
had been in those early days when she helped her husband to winnow
and wash gold from the surface soil of foot-hill streams, working
beside him with pan and rocker, or shoveling dirt into the head of
their little sluice.  Times had changed.  The hopes and hazards of
the West were equally diminished; a bit of mica in a pebble
underfoot, save in favored places, no longer had power to make the
heart swell in wild surmise.  The land had evolved into a
civilization the complexities of which embraced universal suffrage
and the ladies' tailor; but Mrs. Wiles, in accepting the privilege
of one, had not seen fit to adopt the ideals of the other.  She was
called very "genuine."  The league had a way of drawing the
attention of visitors to this quality in the pioneer woman; but its
tone was always unconsciously apologetic, as if it realized the
incompetence of moral grandeur to atone for so aggressive an oddity
of attire and manner.
</p><p>"We're sent to give you a straight talk," announced Mrs.
Wiles, undoing the Herritt gate; "though, 's I told 'em all, 'it
won't assay nothing.  'Tain't no use to go prospectin' for votes
round Mis' Herritt,' I told 'em.  'You might as well look for free
gold in a head of cabbage.'"
</p><p>Mrs. Herritt stood with hospitably extended hands.  "You make
a joke, then, of my weakness!" she complained lightly, in a soft,
flagging voice.
</p><p>"Well, we want you should vote for Jim Truex," panted the
older woman, sinking on

<pb n="763"/>
the door-step.  "We aim to round up
and corral for him every last vote there is in this town.  He's a
fine man.  And though of course we all know you got a notion ag'in'
ladies operatin' at the polls, why, we jest laid off to ask you to
drop all that for once, and walk up and put your ticket in with the
rest of us like a little man.  That's the proposition."
</p><p>Esther's glowing young face expanded in laughing appreciation
of this.  She leaned against the porch post, and its leafy tangles
framed with glittering bronze the gloss of her dark hair and the
serene oval of her cheek.
</p><p>"But not if you have convictions against it," she excepted,
regarding Mrs. Herritt, who had relapsed into her chair as if
seeking sanctuary.  "Of course we wouldn't persecute you, but, as
Mrs. Wiles forcibly says, we all think so well of Mr. Truex&mdash;" her
tone had an effect of trembling never so little, and Mrs. Herritt
surmised a deeper warmth of color in the young woman's face, though
she went on almost at once&mdash;"that&mdash;that we hope to have a most
liberal showing in November.  Yet we couldn't ask you to overthrow
a principle for us, Mrs. Herritt."
</p><p>"Indeed, no!" broke in Mrs. Herritt, with an accent of timid
impetuosity; "no, no!  I've no principles, but only just feelings
against women&mdash;poor, weak, fallible women&mdash;taking part in public
affairs.  That's all.  If I could nerve myself to&mdash;to vote at all,
I would surely do so for Mr. Truex.  But I shrink only to fancy
leaving my little, humble sphere for such a thing.  I am not like
you two&mdash;strong and brave, and knowing all about parliamentary
usages and that.  I have no ambitions.  I'm only a home body.  I
admire and&mdash;and respect those who have time for clubs and debates
and such; but just for myself I have only one aim and object, and
that is my family."
</p><p>"Well, but our clubs are for our families as much as for
ourselves," protested Esther.  "What we get from their associations
isn't just the personal pleasure.  It's all that derived value
which finally shows in the good of our households.  We can't be
narrow without the chance of hurting those we love.  It isn't
merely to get warm ourselves, though that would be reason enough,
that we want to be out in the sunshine of progress!"
</p><p>"Oh, that word!" mourned Mrs. Herritt.  "It makes me quite
faint.  I can't feel that progress ought to be expected from us
women.  We are not the ones to push forward; it is our sweeter
mission to&mdash;to&mdash;"
</p><p>"Stand stock-still and block the hull stream?"
</p><p>"Not that, Mrs. Wiles, but to maintain the equilibrium of
life."  Mrs. Herritt sighed her satisfaction in this lofty
utterance.  "It is for man in his rugged strength to rush forth to
battle with the fierce world.  Woman's place is to greet him
tenderly when he returns scarred and wounded, and draw him into the
sanctuary of home.  I feel this so strongly, though I say it in a
poor little feeble way!  I am only one of 'the soft and milky
rabble of womankind,' as my noble husband often says in his fond,
foolish fashion.  I can't argue about it.  I couldn't make any
telling points; I'm not smart, you know.  I can only say over again
that my whole life is just to keep a fire aglow upon the sacred
hearth of home."
</p><p>"But, land sakes!  Mis' Herritt," demurred Mrs. Wiles, in a
sort of exasperation, "a person won't build a fire no worse for
knowin' B from a bull's foot!"
</p><p>"And then, too," cut in Esther, "you forget that industrial
conditions have changed since the world was young.  Women can't all
stay in their tents tending the fire, while their men sally forth
to the hunt.  And since so many women must themselves go forth, it
doesn't seem wise or kind that those who have not to face this
necessity should make a virtue of nestling comfortably in the
inglenook."
</p><p>"It would be cruel of them," acquiesced Mrs. Herritt, as
composedly as if the analogy were her own.  "My heart is <hi rend="italic"> so</hi>
with all women who must rush wearily forth to toil!"  She sighed
over this disheveled and panting image, and added that what she
most feared for her sex thus occupied in daily combat with the
world was a loss of the bloom which was its supreme charm.
</p><p>"Huh! in my opinion, the bloom that can't stay on while a
woman's earnin' her livin' is mostly finicky fluff, that's better
blowed away.  A peach is a heap cleaner eatin' with the fuzz off."
</p><p>Mrs. Wiles's picturesque outburst failed, perhaps, of full
effect by reason of a wild, childish cry which just now arose in
the house.  There was a patter of feet in the hall, and a small
girl of thirteen appeared in the doorway, breathless and agitated,
stumbling over the folds of a long checked apron, and exhibiting in
her rolled-up sleeves a pair of thin red arms.
</p><p>"Don't be scared, mother," she besought.  "It was only Billy.
He was helpin' me make the tea, and he scalded himself.  I

<pb n="764"/>
put flour on.  Was that right?  And he's stuffin' a towel in his
mouth now so's not to give you a headache."
</p><p>"Brave little man!"
</p><p>"And, mother dear, will I put the steak on now?  I got the
table set."
</p><p>"Yes, love.  I trust you've remembered, Jenny, what mother
likes to see on the table?"
</p><p>Jenny's anxious little face flushed.  She cast a furtive eye
at the visitors.  "Mother," she said huskily, "Mrs. Lusk wouldn't
give me no chrysanthemums.  I told her you liked me always to have
flowers on the table, and she said she'd robbed her plants for us
for 'bout as long as she was going to.  She said we'd better turn
in and raise our own flowers, and not depend on our neighbors for
our decorations.  She said she didn't blame <hi rend="italic"> me</hi> none, but
that&mdash;"
</p><p>"Never mind, Jenny.  Poor Mrs. Lusk!  She doesn't understand.
Don't grieve about it.  Mother knows you did your best."
</p><p>The child's face beamed as she turned away.
</p><p>"Jenny is learning to be a perfect little housewife,"
explained the mother, with an air of modest pride.  "I do feel that
our young girls should all be instructed in the simple domestic
arts.  I am always explaining to Jenny that to be learned in modest
household lore is woman's best knowledge.  She quite hates her
school work now, and I allow her to stay home largely.  After all,
a girl's truest education is at the mother's side, isn't it?"
</p><p>"She don't look over-strong to be tacklin' all these here
domestic arts," commented Mrs. Wiles, rising.
</p><p>Her comment fell harmless upon Mrs. Herritt, who scented, it
seemed, a rose of compliment in the thorns of her guest's remark.
</p><p>"Yes, Jenny looks frail.  A young girl ought always to suggest
something delicate and flower-like, oughtn't she?  And must you
really go?"
</p><p>"Why not, when we're weighed down with a sense of failure?"
smiled Esther.
</p><p>Mrs. Herritt had risen also, and the two stood facing each
other: the one vigorous and vital in her young freshness; the other
listlessly poised, a slight, sinuous shape, which seemed to melt
into the creeping dimness of the twilight as into some natural
element.
</p><p>"You won't think hard of me because I want to keep my door
shut tight against the distant roaring of life?" she implored.
</p><p>"Law, no!" groaned Mrs. Wiles, and she added to Esther, as the
two emerged into the street.  "What'd be the use?"
</p><p>Miners with scarlet panaches of flame in their flat caps were
thronging the way.  Along in the press of them shambled a worn,
elderly man, whose shoulders bent as if in reminiscence of the desk
he had just left in one of the mine offices beyond.  He deflected
toward the Herritt gate.  At its clang Miss Burley looked
irresistibly back.  Mrs. Herritt, still standing on the steps, was
holding forth her long, persuasive hands in fond greeting.
</p><p>"You are a wee bit late," she complained tenderly, "my big man
of men!  Yes, I am sitting here in the gloaming, dreaming my little
feminine dreams, and waiting for some one.  Run in, love, and see
if the tea is all right, will you?  And be sure the twins have
their faces washed, won't you?  And, Edward dear, hand me my shawl--it's so lovely here in the twilight!"
</p><p>"I can't figure that woman out no way in the world," admitted
Mrs. Wiles.  "She's as plausible as a salted claim.  You never know
if she's a straight proposition or if she's selling you out.  You
can't go back of what she says without seeming to go back on your
own sex scandalous, and you can't agree with her without&mdash;
without&mdash;"
</p><p>"Appearing to fix the ideal position of woman somewhere
between that of an odalisk and a squaw!"
</p><p>"That's the time you struck it rich!" applauded the other,
while Esther added: "Mrs. Herritt has got more sex than strength of
character.  You might say that though the weft of her humanity is
sleazy, the feminine qualities are splashed on it large, as in
fresco, with a scene-painter's brush.  She makes a cult of the
pattern, and if we admit that the design is good, it is hard to
object to the ritual of worship.  That's why she's so baffling.
Her conventionalism amounts to heterodoxy.  But we won't worry
about our lack of success with her, Mrs. Wiles.  One vote won't
matter."
</p><p>One vote, indeed, as the outcome attested, would have made no
feature in the sweep of Truex's majority.  Those counties concerned
with him showed a flattering unanimity of conviction.  The Mexican
vote alone might almost have carried the day for him, and Helen, as
she went over these returns, commenting upon the largeness of her
father's Spanish-American contingency, cried out suddenly that he
owed much of it to her friend.
</p><p>"Esther did it," she said, fastening her eloquent and meaning
glance upon him.  "Her speaking Spanish gave her a great pull with
the Mexicans.  She talked to the

<pb n="765"/>
women.  She talked to the
men.  It was splendid to hear her, and even better to look at her."
</p><p>"It's certainly good to look at Esther," conceded Truex.
</p><p>"Good!  I believe only the West could produce a woman so
wholesome and splendid, with the candor and sweetness of a child,
yet like Pallas Athene herself, 'mighty and wise and benignant.'
She is cut out for a statesman's wife, papa, and she's going to be
one!"
</p><p>Truex gave way to his mirthful satisfaction either in his
daughter's fervor or her plan.
</p><p>"And how do you know that this goddess is prepared to look
with favor on an old mustache like me?  See here, Nell; of course
you carry me around in your pocket: but how about Esther?"
</p><p>Helen let the paper slip through her hands.  "Papa," she began
eagerly, and stopped.  "No," she sighed, "no!  I can only assure
you of her&mdash;esteem.  If you want to know more, you must inquire
further."  She roughened his shaggy black hair affectionately.
"And you will?  Say you will!"
</p><p>Truex leaned slumberously back in his chair.  "I don't see why
you want me to marry."
</p><p>"I want you to be happy."
</p><p>"Ain't I happy?"
</p><p>"Well&mdash;happier, then."
</p><p>"Oh, well, we'll see.  After we come back from Washington,
Nell, we'll lay our heads together."
</p><p>Helen had the wisdom to rest her plea upon this prospect.  It
might be madness to defer, but undue pressure was preferably to be
avoided in securing her aims.  She felt, however, reasonably sure
of their success, insomuch as the idea which she set before her
father was one certain to grow upon his fancy.  The path she had
chalked out for him would more and more allure him as he regarded
its bowery turns.  There could be no doubt of this, and she left
her generous sentiment and romantic enterprise hopefully to the
adjusting agency of time.
</p><p>During their absence from the West the subject often came up
in a casual and playful way.  Of himself Truex would refer to it.
The prospect, indeed, seemed to Helen so secure that her greeting
of Esther, upon the return from Washington in the spring, had an
almost emotional tenderness.
</p><p>They merged a common feeling of consciousness in a review of
what had happened in town during the months of Helen's Eastern
experiences.
</p><p>"Of course you heard of Mr. Herritt's death?" said Esther.
"It was early in the winter."
</p><p>"I suppose he couldn't have left his family very well provided
for?" inquired Helen.  Her instinct of universal responsibility
began already to unfold an anxious wing.
</p><p>"There was a small insurance, I believe.  But no one has
ventured to think of such a thing as ways and means in the face of
Mrs. Herritt's grief.  I never saw any one so smothered in crape!
It is enough to kill her, and she told me she hoped it would; that
she believed the true wife should fail and fade away when widowed,
as a flower does when its stalk is broken.  She said she thought
the whole idea of the suttee was founded in a beautiful truth."
</p><p>"Maybe it is when you get to the bottom of it, Esther.  All
Mrs. Herritt's notions have a fundamental germ of truth.  That's
what makes her so impregnable.  There's always a grain of true ore
in her tinsel."
</p><p>"You should see her now to realize her full scope.  She's an
idyllic widow.  I had to own it, though I knew if I admitted any
argument of hers, personal or otherwise, I should soon find myself
pledged to the whole social system of the middle ages.  But her
long, sagging black stuffs, her heavy-lidded eyes, that dull pale
hair done carelessly, as if in the abstraction of woe, even the way
in which her hands crept piteously together, all this gave me a
rich sense of artistic rightness.  I was ashamed of myself, Helen,
because the tears in my eyes somehow gave me a kind of poetic
pleasure."
</p><p>"I see.  Her bereavement is like her wifehood, perfectly
selfish, correct, and irrefutable.  A bewildering and fascinating
exhibition it must be."
</p><p>"Helen," said Esther, solemnly, "if you could see those black-frocked children hanging about her, not as other children hang
about a mother, demanding her attention and making the little
appeal of childhood, but pressing their services upon her, stepping
on tiptoe, vying with one another for her least absent word or
look!  It's a revelation.  When I saw those baby hearts expanding
in love and strength to meet their mother's needs, I began to
wonder if courage and devotion on her part might not have failed of
so triumphant a result as their opposites secured without effort.
I began to understand the force of the theory of which Mrs.
Herritt's life is an embodiment; I began to feel its charm; I began
to understand the terrible strength that lies in consistent

<pb n="766"/>
weakness."  She caught her breath, and added: "Yet I couldn't be
sure I wasn't suffering a hallucination in getting an impression so
subversive of all accepted ideas about motherhood."
</p><p>"No wonder.  When one begins to observe how broad and
beautiful the moral results of selfishness are, he may well
question his sanity."
</p><p>"Mayn't he!  Well, you go to see her, Helen.  She'll juggle
with your notions, and then you'll understand me.  The things you
thought you had hold of to all eternity will suddenly appear airy
nothings, and what seemed airy nothings become the great dominant
facts of life.  Go, Helen!"
</p><p>"I will, I will.  Some one ought to find out what she is going
to do.  Poor thing!  She sees herself in a dim romantic mist, and
she's got a knack of enforcing this view on others; but she can't
hocus-pocus bread into her children's mouths."
</p><p>"No, dear.  Yet somehow I don't seem to worry about her.  To
relax the system is to meet accident with the minimum shock.  I
don't believe fate can hurt her much, for she has this truth in her
philosophy."
</p><p>Mrs. Herritt and her affairs, as it fell out, were destined to
occupy Helen in short order.  Upon that very evening, when Mr.
Truex came home about sunset, there was a look so unwontedly grave
upon his good-looking face that Helen at once made inquiry
concerning it.
</p><p>"No," said he; "nothing is wrong&mdash;that is, with me.  But I've
had a sad little experience this afternoon.  I don't know when
anything has touched me so.  I am a hard-headed fellow&mdash;"
</p><p>"You haven't a soft fiber in you!" acquiesced his girl, with
tender irony.
</p><p>"&mdash;and things don't usually move me much; but the way she came
into the office, pale, shrinking&mdash;it might have been an ogre's den!
You see, she'd got it in her head that I was very bitter about her
not voting for me&mdash;"
</p><p>"It was Mrs. Herritt, then?"
</p><p>"Didn't I say so?  And she began by begging me to forgive her.
She said that she'd always felt that politics were 'way beyond her
depth; that they were for strong men to grapple with; and that Mr.
Herritt had always encouraged her little foolish qualms.  She said
home had always been her shrine&mdash;"
</p><p>"That's her very tone!  Go on!"
</p><p>"Well, she went on to say how she admired independent,
courageous, big-brained women, who dared to go right out in the
world and offer battle&mdash;"
</p><p>"'Offer battle'!"  How like her!  She makes us all appear
great raw-boned Amazons."
</p><p>"I don't know where you get such a notion," objected her
father, letting down his brows; "I'm telling you she spoke of her
great respect for progressive, intelligent women, and could only
blush for her own timidity and ignorance."
</p><p>"She gives an insidious effect of self-effacement, certainly.
Maybe I'm hard on her, after all.  Go on!  Don't puff your lips,
papa!"
</p><p>"Well, my dear, if you haven't any sympathy for a poor,
heartbroken little woman!" he exclaimed.  "However, she wants to
place a mortgage on her cottage, and they sent her to me.  It seems
Herritt left little, and there are debts."
</p><p>"It's only seven months since he died.  What's become of the
insurance, I wonder?"
</p><p>Truex shook his head amusedly.  "That's the pathetic part.
This poor soul, without thinking of the future, spent most of it in
putting up an expensive monument to her husband.  Her only thought,
she said, was to express, at any cost, her devotion to his memory.
She&mdash;she cried when she told me."
</p><p>"She should have thought of her children before doing such a
thing with her little money."
</p><p>"Women are hard as nails to one another," commented Truex.
This venerable sentiment seemed to strike him as fresh, and he
repeated it.  "Now, even I, hard-fisted old codger as I am, saw
something affecting in her forgetting everything but her sorrow.
This looking round the corners of your grief to see what's beyond
it&mdash;oh, it's all right.  A wise person would do it.  But she isn't
that kind.  She isn't a woman of resources, but, as she said sadly,
just one of those unaspiring souls whose empire is the hearth, and
whose emblem is the loom and wheel."
</p><p>"If she'd said the sewing-machine and cook-stove it wouldn't
have sounded so well, would it?  And did you make the loan?  I hope
you did."
</p><p>"Yes."  He rose, stretching his vast frame, while his eyes, as
Helen followed their glance, seemed to fasten with a certain half-absent, half-startled expression on the beckoning finger which the
new moon bent white from the lilac sky.  He seemed aware of seeing
something new.
</p><p>Helen said whimsically: "Isn't it slim and bright?  I would
like to give it to Esther to wear in her hair."  And as her father
laughed at this and patted her head, she exulted over the security
of her hopes.</p>

<pb n="767"/>
<p>As summer passed away, things seemed indeed to be proceeding
favorably toward their fruition.  Before the departure for the East
everything must be settled, and along in late October Helen saw an
opportunity of pushing her purpose to achievement.  There was to be
a social gathering in the big house, and Helen had settled upon
this occasion as being singularly appropriate to the announcement
of her father's betrothal.  To the accomplishment of the scheme
nothing was lacking but the consent of those interested, and to
secure that of one of them Helen determined on immediate measures.
</p><p>It happened to be a chill night of fall when she settled this
point.  A snowy breath whistled down from the divide, rattling
crisply in the dying trees, and enhancing with its wintry bluster
the homely implication of cheer in the pinon-stick fire, before
which Helen sat in the library.  It was ten o'clock.  She expected
momently to hear her father returning from one of those business
meetings which of late not only engrossed his evenings, but sent
him home with a clouded brow and flagging step.  He had seemed
unwilling to discuss with her whatever it was in his legislative or
commercial pursuits that worried him.  She had therefore learned to
withdraw her anxious curiosity.  And now, as she heard his key in
the latch, she smoothed her brow of any hint of questioning and ran
to meet him.
</p><p>For once, however, Mr. Truex bore no air of heaviness; a
gladsome alacrity the rather marked his motions.  There was even a
boyish gaiety in his manner as he surprised Helen with an embrace
of unusual warmth.  She took this unwonted demonstration fondly.
</p><p>"Oh, papa," she murmured, "I won't be first much longer!  I
want it to be so, and yet&mdash;"
</p><p>"Truex sat down by the fire.  He laughed.  "Well, you'll
always be important, I guess.  And&mdash;er&mdash;how do you know there's
going to be&mdash;some one?"
</p><p>Helen drew away from him, struck with something significant in
his tone.
</p><p>"Papa! what have you been up to?  Oh, you've asked her!  I
know, I know!  And she said?  But I know what she said!"
</p><p>"She was a long time saying it, Nell.  I've been on pins and
needles for weeks.  I've been obliged to you for not asking me
questions.  But to-night!  Yes, it's all right.  I never expected
to feel as much like a boy again."
</p><p>The jubilant ring of his voice smote Helen unexpectedly.  She
had meant him to be happy, but&mdash;so happy?  She felt herself
suddenly projected into a great solitude, and the tears sprang to
her eyes.
</p><p>"I'm glad," she whispered; "but it's a kind of lonesome
feeling somehow."
</p><p>"Lonesome!  You'll never be that, Nellie.  Indeed, I feel that
almost her sole reason for taking me is on your account.  A
motherless girl, she said in her sweet way, appealed to her beyond
words.  She understands you perfectly, Nell.  I knew I was safe
when I made her admit that what you needed was a mother to whom you
could devote yourself in loving service.  And then finally she
whispered that if anything could touch her buried heart to life it
would be such an appeal to her womanhood.  Why, Helen!"
</p><p>"'Buried heart'!"  What&mdash;who?  She drew herself together.
"Tell me who&mdash;I am to serve&mdash;so lovingly.  It seems not to be
Esther."
</p><p>"Why, you know I mean Mrs. Herritt?  Of course you know.  Lucy
her name is.  She laughs and calls it a plain little everyday name,
just like herself.  Lucy!"  He repeated it fatuously, then fetched
a breath of resolution and continued in another tone:  "That about
Miss Burley, now.  It couldn't be, Nellie.  She is magnificent.
Lucy often dwells on her qualities, and says she is exactly like
some lines she saw somewhere&mdash;something about 'Glowing with valor
and beauty, and strong for labor and battle.'  But a man doesn't
care for that heroic kind of thing in a wife.  It's too much of a
strain&mdash;like living in a cathedral and having oratorios for
breakfast.  A man like me, weighted with national affairs, wants
peace in his home.  The immense pressure he's under makes it
necessary for him to find rest in the ministrations of a sweet,
submissive spirit."  He went on hymning his needs and exploiting
the range of mild and emollient qualities which these demanded for
their alleviation.  There was a new effect of importance upon him.
Happiness had expanded in him latent sources of joyous egotism.  He
was authoritative and eloquent; subconscious modes of being seemed
to rise and overflow his ordinary surfaces with strange prismatic
colors.
</p><p>Helen stumbled to her feet, a little dazed with the sight of
it all.  "However it is," she said gently, "I am glad," and she let
him reach out for her, and add to his satisfaction the little
detail of her assent.
</p><p>"If you could hear Lucy praise you up, Nell&mdash;your cleverness
and energy, and a dozen other things!  There is so much, she says,
that you must teach her&mdash;docile little soul!"
</p><p>"Ah," smiled Helen, darkly, "she has nothing to learn of me&mdash;
or of any woman!"
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
