<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="Bur6Nar"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>
<TEI.2 id="Bur6Nar">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Modest Inquiry Into The Nature
Of Witchcraft, By John Hale, 1702 ;
from Narratives of the Witchcraft Cases, 1648-1706</title>
<title type="sort">modest inquiry into the nature of witchcraft, by john hale 1702 from narratives of the witchcraft cases 1648 1706</title>
<author>Burr, George Lincoln, 1857-1938</author>
<editor>Burr, George Lincoln, 1857-1938</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Apex Data Services, Inc.</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>Apex Data Services and the
University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">96</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">Bur6Nar</idno>
<date value="1998">1998</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1998 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476587</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Modest Inquiry Into The Nature Of Witchcraft, By John Hale, 1702</title>
<title level="m">Narratives of the Witchcraft Cases, 1648-1706</title>
<title type="sort">modest inquiry into the nature of witchcraft, by john hale 1702</title>
<editor>Burr, George Lincoln, 1857-1938</editor>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1998-12">December 1998</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Stephen Ramsay, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item/>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">

<div1 type="work" id="d3">
<head>A MODEST INQUIRY INTO THE NATURE OF WITCHCRAFT, BY JOHN HALE, 1702</head>

<div2 type="section" id="d4">
<pb n="397"/>
<head>INTRODUCTION</head>

<p><hi rend="small-caps">The</hi> Rev. John Hale (1636-1700), a native
of the colony and a graduate of Harvard in its class of 1657, had since 1665 been
pastor at Beverly, the parish lying north of Salem, from which it was severed by
a narrow arm of the sea, and at the west adjoining yet more closely Salem
Village, through which lay the land route connecting Beverly with Salem and with
Boston. Many of those connected with the beginnings of the witch panic had,
prior to the erection of the Village parish, been in attendance at the Beverly
church. Some were still so; and the spreading suspicion soon invaded this parish
itself. It was not strange, then, that from the first, as we have seen already,
Hale's interest in the proceedings was close and attentive.<ref target="n350">[350]</ref> There can be no
question that, as Calef says, &ldquo;he had been very forward in these
Prosecutions,&rdquo; and, like his neighbor pastors Parris and Noyes, had held
the most credulous views as to the worth of the testimony of the
&ldquo;afflicted.&rdquo; How those views changed after the accusation of his
loved and honored wife we have also seen;<ref target="n351">[351]</ref> and of all this he himself tells us
with a touching sincerity in the pages now to follow. His little book is no
apology, but a manly attempt to make amends for what he now felt to be error
by setting forth to others what he had learned. Judge Sewall, who likewise had
repented of his error and likewise frankly owned it, records in

<pb n="398"/>

his diary on November 19, 1697, when he was on a visit to Salem: &ldquo;Mr.
Hale and I lodg'd together: He discours'd me about writing a History of the
Witchcraft; I fear lest he go into the other extream.&rdquo;</p>


<p>The Rev. John Higginson (1616-1708), the aged senior pastor of Salem,
who writes for Hale the introduction, is also no stranger to us;<ref target="n352">[352]</ref> and we have seen
what reason there is to think him hesitant all along as to the proceedings. Yet
how far he had been from incredulity as to human dealings with the Devil appears
not only from his own words here, but from the materials he furnished Increase
Mather for his <hi rend="italic">Providences</hi>.<ref target="n353">[353]</ref> Perhaps he, too,
consulted Judge Sewall as to his part in the little book; for before the words just
cited the latter writes: &ldquo;Mr. Higginson comes as far as Brother's to see
me; which I wonder'd at.&rdquo;</p>


<p>Though completed early in 1698 &mdash; since Higginson had read it before
signing his introduction on March 23 &mdash; the book, as may be seen from its
imprint, was not published till 1702, after Hale's death. Perhaps that was its
author's wish: so, Judge Sewall tells us,<ref target="n354">[354]</ref> Higginson withheld his treatise on
periwigs. The <hi rend="italic">Modest Enquiry</hi> is now one of the
rarest books in the literature of witchcraft. Its single reimpression (Boston, 1771)
is said to be yet rarer than the original. Happily, that part of the book which
narrates the story of the Salem episode was taken up by Cotton Mather into his
<hi rend="italic">Magnalia</hi> (at the end of his Book VI.); and from that
work, though it gives Hale due credit, it is often quoted as if Mather's
own.<ref target="n355">[355]</ref></p>



<div3 type="notes" id="d5">
<head>Notes</head>

<note id="n350"><seg type="note-symbol">[350].</seg> <p>See above, pp. 158, 184, 342, 344, 350, 369. More
than once (as against Bridget Bishop and Dorcas Hoar) he himself became a
witness as to the reputation or career of the accused. That already then there was
thought of his writing upon the subject may perhaps be inferred from Cotton
Mather's letter quoted on p. 206; and see also p. 214.</p></note>

<note id="n351"><seg type="note-symbol">[351].</seg> <p>See p. 369, and note 1.</p></note>

<note id="n352"><seg type="note-symbol">[352].</seg> <p>See above, pp. 245, 248, note 2.</p></note>

<note id="n353"><seg type="note-symbol">[353].</seg> <p><hi rend="italic">Mather Papers</hi>, pp. 282-287.</p></note>

<note id="n354"><seg type="note-symbol">[354].</seg> <p><hi rend="italic">Diary</hi>, I. 463-464.</p></note>

<note id="n355"><seg type="note-symbol">[355].</seg> <p>As to Hale's career see a memoir in Mass. Hist. Soc., <hi
rend="italic">Collections</hi>, third series, VII. 255-269; also Sibley, <hi
rend="italic">Harvard Graduates</hi>, I. 509-520, and authorities there
cited.</p></note>
</div3>
</div2>

<pb n="399"/>

<div2 type="section" id="d6">
<head>HALE'S A MODEST INQUIRY</head>

<p><hi rend="italic">A Modest Enquiry Into the Nature of Witchcraft, and
How Persons Guilty of that Crime may be Convicted: And the means used for
their Discovery Discussed, both Negatively and Affirmatively, according to
Scripture and Experience</hi>.</p>


<p><hi rend="italic">By John Hale, Pastor of the Church of Christ in
Beverley, Anno Domini</hi> 1697.</p>


<p><hi rend="italic">When they say unto you, seek unto them that have
Familiar Spirits and unto Wizzards, that peep, etc., To the Law and to the
Testimony; if they speak not according to this word, it is because there is no light
in them. Isaiah VIII</hi>. 19. 20. <hi rend="italic">That which I see not
teach thou me, Job</hi> 34. 32.</p>


<p><hi rend="italic">Boston in N. E. Printed by B. Green and J. Allen,
for Benjamin Eliot under the Town House</hi>. 1702<ref target="n356">[356]</ref></p>


<p>Any general Custom against the Law of God is void. St. Germans, <hi
rend="italic">Abridgment of Common Law</hi>. Lib. 1. C. 6.</p>


<p>Omnium legum est inanis censura nisi Divin&aelig; legis imaginem
gerat.<ref target="n357">[357]</ref>
Finch, <hi rend="italic">Common Law</hi>. Lib. 4. C. 3.</p>


<p>Where a Law is grounded upon a Presumption, if the Presumption fail the
Law is not to be holden in Conscience. <hi rend="italic">Abridgment of C.
Law</hi>. Lib. 1. C. 19.<ref target="n358">[358]</ref></p>


<div3 type="notes" id="d7">
<head>Notes</head>

<note id="n356"><seg type="note-symbol">[356].</seg> <p>Title-page of original.</p></note>

<note id="n357"><seg type="note-symbol">[357].</seg> <p>&ldquo;No law hath any validity unless it bear the image of divine
law.&rdquo;</p></note>

<note id="n358"><seg type="note-symbol">[358].</seg> <p>Reverse of title-page.</p></note>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d8">
<head>An Epistle to the Reader.</head>

<p><hi rend="small-caps">It</hi> hath been said of Old, That Time is the
Mother of Truth, and Truth is the Daughter of Time. It is the Prerogative of the
God of Truth, to know all the truth in all things at once and together: It is also
his Glory to conceal a matter, Prov. 25. 2, And to bring the truth to light in that
manner and measure, and the times appointed, as it pleaseth him; it is

<pb n="400"/>

our duty in all humility, and with fear and trembling, to search after truth,
knowing that secret things belong to God, and only things revealed belong to us,
and so far as they are revealed; for in many things it may be said, what God is
doing we know not now; but we, or others that succeed us, shall know hereafter.
Omitting other Examples, I shall Instance only in the matter of Witchcraft, which
on the Humane side, is one of the most hidden Works of Darkness, managed by
the Rulers of the darkness of this World, to the doing of great spoil amongst the
Children of men: And on the Divine side, it is one of the most awful and
tremendous Judgments of God which can be inflicted on the Societies of men,
especially when the Lord shall please for his own Holy Ends to Enlarge Satans
Commission in more than an ordinary way.</p>


<p>It is known to all men, that it pleased God some few years ago, to suffer
Satan to raise much trouble amongst us in that respect, the beginning of which
was very small, and looked on at first as an ordinary case which had fallen out
before at several times in other places, and would be quickly over. Only one or
two persons belonging to Salem Village about five miles from the Town being
suspected were Examined, etc. But in the progress of the matter, a multitude of
other persons both in this and other Neighbour Towns, were Accused, Examined,
Imprisoned, and came to their Trials, at Salem, the County Town, where about
Twenty of them Suffered as Witches; and many others in danger of the same
Tragical End: and still the number of the Accused increased unto many Scores;
amongst whom were many Persons of unquestionable Credit, never under any
grounds of suspicion of that or any other Scandalous Evil. This brought a general
Consternation upon all sorts of People, doubting what would be the issue of such
a dreadful Judgment of God upon the Country; but the Lord was pleased suddenly
to put a stop to those proceedings, that there was no further trouble, as hath been
related by others. But it left in the minds of men a sad remembrance of that
sorrowful time; and a Doubt whether some Innocent Persons might not Suffer,
and some guilty Persons Escape. There is no doubt but the Judges and Juries
proceeded in their Integrity, with a zeal of God against Sin, according to their
best light, and according to Law and Evidence; but there is

<pb n="401"/>




a Question yet unresolved, Whether some of the Laws, Customs and Principles
used by the Judges and Juries in the Trials of Witches in England (which were
followed as Patterns here) were not insufficient and unsafe.</p>


<p>As for my Self, being under the Infirmities of a decrepit Old Age, I stirred
little abroad, and was much disenabled (both in body and mind) from Knowing
and judging of Occurrents and Transactions of that time: But my Reverend
Brother Mr. Hale, having for above Thirty Years been Pastor of the Church at
Beverly (but Two Miles from Salem, where the Tryals were) was frequently
present, and was a diligent Observer of all that passed, and being one of a
Singular Prudence and Sagacity, in searching into the narrows of things: He hath
(after much deliberation) in this Treatise, related the Substance of the Case as it
was, and given Reasons from Scripture against some of the Principles and
Practises then used in the Tryals of Witchcraft; and said something also in a
Positive way, and shewing the right Application that is to be made of the whole,
and all this in such a pious and modest Manner, as cannot be offensive to any,
but may be generally acceptable to all the lovers of Truth and Peace.</p>


<p>I am the more willing to accompany him to the Press, because I am
perswaded such a Treatise as this is needful and useful, upon divers accounts.
As,</p>


<p>1. That the Works of God may be known; and that God may be more
acknowledged and adored, in his Justice, and in his Mercy: in his Justice, by
letting loose Evil Angels, to make so great a spoyl amongst us as they did, for
the Punishment of a declining People: And in his Mercy, by Counter-manding of
Satans Commission, and keeping of him in Chains of restraint, that he should
proceed no further. Psal. 83, last.</p>


<p>2. That the Truth of things may be more fully known, so far as God shall
please to reveal the same in the use of lawful means; for the Judgments of God
are a great deep, and he is wont to make known truth by degrees; and Experience
teacheth us, there is need of more to be said than hath been yet, for the clearing
up of difficulties about the matter of Witchcraft. We ought to be fellow helpers
to the truth. 3 Epistle of John, 8. v.</p>


<p>3. That whatever Errors or Mistakes we fell into, in the

<pb n="402"/>




dark hour of Temptation that was upon us, may be (upon more light) so
discovered, acknowledged and disowned by us, as that it may be a matter of
Warning and Caution to those that come after us, that they may not fall into the
like. 1 Cor. 10. 11. <hi rend="italic">F&aelig;lix quem faciunt aliena
pericula cautum</hi>.<ref target="n359">[359]</ref></p>


<p>4. And that it may Occasion the most Learned and Pious men to make a
further and fuller Enquiry into the matter of Witchcraft, especially into the
positive part, How Witches may be so discovered, that innocent persons may be
preserved, and none but the guilty may suffer. Prov. 17. 15.</p>


<p>Verily whosoever shall by the Grace of God be enabled to Contribute
further light in this matter, will do good Service to God and Men in his
Generation.</p>


<p>I would also propound and leave it as an Object of Consideration to our
Honoured Magistrates and Reverend Ministers, Whether the &aelig;quity of that
Law in Leviticus, Chap. 4, for a Sin offering for the Rulers and for the
Congregation, in the case of Sins of Ignorance, when they come to be known, be
not Obliging, and for direction to us in a Gospel way.</p>


<p>Now the Father of Lights and Mercies grant unto us, that Mercy and Truth
may meet together, that righteousness and peace may kiss each other, that the
Glory of God may dwell in our Land; and that it may be said of New England,
The Lord Bless thee, O Habitation of Justice and Mountain of Holiness,</p>


<p>Finally, That the Blessing of Heaven may go along with this little Treatise
to attain the good Ends thereof, is, and shall be the Prayer of him who is daily
waiting for his Change, and looking for the Mercy of the Lord Jesus Christ unto
Eternal Life.</p>

<closer>
<signed><hi rend="small-caps">John Higginson</hi>,</signed>
<dateline><date value="1697-03-23">March 23d, 1697, 8.</date> <name type="place"><hi
rend="italic">Pastor of the Church, of Salem. &aelig;tatis</hi>
82.
<ref target="n360">[360]</ref></name></dateline>
</closer>
</div2>
<div2 type="notes" id="d9">

<head>Notes</head>

<note id="n359"><seg type="note-symbol">[359].</seg> <p>&ldquo;Happy the man whom the perils of others make
cautious.&rdquo;</p></note>
<note id="n360"><seg type="note-symbol">[360].</seg> <p>&ldquo;In the 82d year of his age.&rdquo; As to the aged senior pastor
of Salem see p. 398.</p></note>


</div2>

<div2 type="section" id="d10">
<head>The Preface to the Christian Reader.</head>

<p><hi rend="small-caps">The</hi> Holy Scriptures inform us that the
Doctrine of Godliness is a great Mystery, containing the Mysteries of the

<pb n="403"/>

Kingdom of Heaven: Mysteries which require great search for the finding out:
And as the Lord hath his Mysteries to bring us to Eternal Glory; so Satan hath
his Mysteries to bring us to Eternal Ruine: Mysteries not easily understood,
whereby the depths of Satan are managed in hidden wayes. So the Whore of
Babylon makes the Inhabitants of the Earth drunk with the Wine of her
Fornication, by the Mystery of her abominations, Rev. 17. 2. And the man of Sin
hath his Mystery of iniquity whereby he deceiveth men through the working of
Satan in signes and lying wonders, 2 Thes. 2. 3, 7, 9.</p>


<p>And among Satans Mysteries of iniquity, this of Witchcraft is one of the
most difficult to be searched out by the Sons of men; as appeareth by the great
endeavours of Learned and Holy men to search it out, and the great differences
that are found among them, in the rules laid down for the bringing to light these
hidden works of darkness. So that it may seem presumption in me to undertake
so difficult a Theam, and to lay down such rules as are different from the
Sentiments of many Eminent writers, and from the Presidents and practices of
able Lawyers; yea and from the Common Law it self.</p>


<p>But my Apology for this undertaking is;</p>


<p>1. That there hath been such a dark dispensation by the Lord, letting loose
upon us the Devil, <hi rend="italic">Anno.</hi> 1691 and 1692,<ref target="n361">[361]</ref> as we
never experienced before: And thereupon apprehending and condemning persons
for Witchcraft; and nextly acquitting others no less liable to such a charge; which
evidently shew we were in the dark, and knew not what to do; but have gone too
far on the one or other side, if not on both. Hereupon I esteemed it necessary for
some person to Collect a Summary of that affair, with some animadversions upon
it, which might at least give some light to them which come after, to shun those
Rocks by which we were bruised, and narrowly escaped Shipwrack upon. And
I have waited five years for some other person to undertake it, who might doe it
better than I can, but find none; and judge it better to do what I can, than that
such a work should be left undone. Better sincerely though weakly done, then not
at all, or with such a byas of prejudice as will put false glosses upon that which
was managed

<pb n="404"/>

with uprightness of heart, though there was not so great a spirit of
discerning, as were to be wished in so weighty a Concernment.</p>


<p>2. I have been present at several Examinations and Tryals, and knew
sundry of those that Suffered upon that account in former years, and in this last
affair, and so have more advantages than a stranger, to give account of these
Proceedings.</p>


<p>3. I have been from my Youth trained up in the knowledge and belief of
most of those principles I here question as unsafe to be used. The first person that
suffered on this account in New-England, about Fifty years since, was my
Neighbour, and I heard much of what was charged upon her, and others in those
times; and the reverence I bore to aged, learned and judicious persons, caused me
to drink in their principles in these things, with a kind of Implicit Faith. <hi
rend="italic">Quo semel est imbuta recens servabit odorem, Testa
diu</hi>.<ref target="n362">[362]</ref> A Child will not easily forsake the principles he hath been trained
up in from his Cradle.</p>


<p>But observing the Events of that sad Catastrophe, <hi rend="italic">Anno
</hi> 1692, I was brought to a more strict scanning of the principles I had
imbibed, and by scanning, to question, and by questioning at length to reject
many of them, upon the reasons shewed in the ensuing Discourse. It is an
approved saying <hi rend="italic">Nihil certius, quam quod ex dubio fit
certum</hi>;<ref target="n363">[363]</ref> No truth more certain to a man, than that which he hath
formerly doubted or denied, and is recovered from his error, by the convincing
evidence of Scripture and reason. Yet I know and am sensible, that while we
know but in part, man is apt in flying from a discovered error, to run into the
contrary extream.</p>

<p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Incidit in Scyllam qui vult vitare
Charybdim</hi>.<ref target="n364">[364]</ref></p>


<p>The middle way is commonly the way of truth. And if any can shew me a
better middle way than I have here laid down, I shall be ready to embrace it: But
the conviction must not be by vinegar or drollery, but by strength of
argument.</p>


<p>4. I have had a deep sence of the sad consequence of mis

<pb n="405"/>


takes in matters Capital; and their impossibility of recovering when compleated.
And what grief of heart it brings to a tender conscience, to have been unwittingly
encouraging of the Sufferings of the innocent. And I hope a zeal to prevent for
the future such sufferings is pardonable, although there should be much weakness,
and some errors in the pursuit thereof.</p>


<p>5. I observe the failings that have been on the one hand, have driven some
into that which is indeed an extream on the other hand, and of dangerous
consequences, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> To deny any such persons to be
under the New Testament, who by the Devils aid discover Secrets, or do work
wonders. Therefore in the latter part of this discourse, I have taken pains to prove
the Affirmative, yet with brevity, because it hath been done already by Perkins
of <hi rend="italic">Witchcraft</hi>.<ref target="n365">[365]</ref> Glanvil his
<hi rend="italic">Saducismus Triumphatus</hi>,<ref target="n366">[366]</ref> Pt. 1. p. 1 to 90 and Pt. 2.
p. 1 to 80. Yet I would not be understood to justify all his notions in those
discourses, but acknowledge he hath strongly proved the being of Witches.</p>


<p>6. I have special reasons moving me to bear my testimony about these
matters, before I go hence and be no more; the which I have here done, and I
hope with some assistance of his Spirit, to whom I commit my self and this my
labour, even that God whose I am and whom I serve: Desiring his Mercy in Jesus
Christ to Pardon all the Errors of his People in the day of darkness; and to enable
us to fight with Satan by Spiritual Weapons, putting on the whole Armour of
God.</p>


<p>And tho' Satan by his Messengers may buffet Gods Children, yet there's
a promise upon right <hi rend="italic">Resisting, he shall flee from
them</hi>, Jam. 4. 7. <hi rend="italic">And that all things shall work
together for the good of those that Love the Lord</hi>, Rom. 8. 28. So that I
believe Gods Children shall be gainers by the assaults of Satan, which occasion'd
this Discourse; which that they may, is the Prayer of, Thine in the Service of the
Gospel.</p>

<closer>
<signed><hi rend="small-caps">John Hale</hi>.</signed>
<dateline><name type="place"><hi
rend="small-caps">Beverly</hi>,</name> <date value="1697-12-15">Decemb. 15th,
1697.</date></dateline>
</closer>
</div2>

<div2 type="notes" id="d11">
<head>Notes</head>

<note id="n361"><seg type="note-symbol">[361].</seg> <p>&ldquo;1691&rdquo; because the troubles began before March 25.</p></note>

<note id="n362"><seg type="note-symbol">[362].</seg> <p>Literally, &ldquo;the fresh-made pot will long retain the odor in which
once 'tis steeped.&rdquo; The line is from Horace.</p></note>

<note id="n363"><seg type="note-symbol">[363].</seg> <p>Literally, &ldquo;nothing is surer than what out of doubt is made
sure.&rdquo;</p></note>

<note id="n364"><seg type="note-symbol">[364].</seg> <p>&ldquo;Into Scylla falls he who tries to keep clear of
Charybdis.&rdquo;</p></note>

<note id="n365"><seg type="note-symbol">[365].</seg> <p>See above, p. 304, note 3.</p></note>

<note id="n366"><seg type="note-symbol">[366].</seg> <p><hi rend="italic">Saducismus Triumphatus</hi> was the name
given Glanvill's book in the enlarged edition (1681) brought out after the author's
death by Henry More. In later impressions the word becomes <hi
rend="italic">Sadducismus</hi>. As to Glanvill, see above, p.
5.</p></note>
</div2>


<pb n="406"/>

<div2 type="section" id="d12">
<head>A MODEST ENQUIRY, INTO THE NATURE OF WITCHCRAFT Chapter I.</head>

<p><hi rend="italic">Sect.</hi> 1. The Angels who kept not their First
Estate, by Sin against God, lost their primitive purity, and glorious Excellency,
as to their moral qualifications, and became unclean, wicked, envious, lyars, and
full of all wickedness, which as Spirits they are capable of. Yet I do not find in
Scripture that they lost their natural abilities of understanding or power of
Operation.</p>


<p>1. As for their Understanding, they are called <hi rend="italic">Daimon
</hi> (which we Translate Devil) because they are full of wisdom, cunning,
skill, subtilty and knowledge. He hath also the name of Serpent from his subtilty,
2 Cor. 11. 3. And his knowledge in the Scriptures, and wittiness to pervert them,
appears by his quoting Scripture to our Saviour when he tempted him. Mat.
4.</p>


<p>And as there be many Devils, and these active, quick, swift and piercing
Spirits, so they going to and fro in the earth, and walking up and down in it, have
advantages to know all the actions of the Children of men, both open and secret,
their discourses, consultations, and much of the inward affections of men thereby;
though still its Gods prerogative immediately to know the heart. Jer. 17.
10.</p>


<p>2. As to their natural power as Spirits, its very great, if not equal to that
of the Holy Angels: For,</p>


<p>1. They are called <hi rend="italic">Principalities and Powers</hi>.
Rom. 8. 38. Eph. 6. 12. Col. 2. 14, 15, compared with Heb. 2. 14, 15. Now
these are names given to the Holy Angels. Eph. 1. 21, and 3. 10.</p>


<p>2. They are called, <hi rend="italic">Rulers of the darkness of this
world, the Prince of the power of the Air</hi>. Eph. 6. 12 and 2. 2.</p>


<p>3. Such was their power that they contended with Michael and the Angels
about the Body of Moses. 2 Pet. 2. 11. Jude 9. That is, as I conceive, about
preventing the Burial of the Body of Moses: For it's said, Deut. 34. 6, The Lord
buried him, and no man knoweth of his Sepulcher to this day.

<pb n="407"/>

That is, he did it by the Ministry of Angels (for the Lord gave the Law, Exod.
20. 1, and that it was by the Ministry of Angels, see Gal. 3. 19. so probably was
the burial of Moses's Body) and the Devils endeavour if possible, to discover
Moses's Body, or place of its burial, that they might draw Israel to commit
Idolatry in worshipping at his Tomb (as our Popish Fore-fathers did at Thomas
Beckets in Kent) from the Veneration they had to him as their Law giver.</p>


<p>4. The Devils actings against Job, Chap. 1 and 2, and what he did to the
Gadarene Swine, etc., Shew his great power. So that we may conclude, had the
Devils liberty to reveal all that they know of the affairs of mankind, or to do all
that is in their power to perform, they would bring dreadful confusions and
desolations upon the World.</p>


<p><hi rend="italic">Sect.</hi> 2. The way God governs Devils is by
Chains. 2 Pet. 2. 4. Jude 6 ver. Rev. 20. 1, 2, 7, 8, whereby they are kept
Prisoners. Men are governed by Laws, by convictions of Conscience. Rom. 2.
12, 13, 14, 15. By Scripture Rules, Humane Laws, and also by Gods Spirit. 1
John 2. 20. But Devils have no such Laws, or tenderness of Conscience to bridle
or restrain them. But the Lord hath his Chains, which are called Everlasting, and
are always lasting; so that they are never wholly without a Chain. This Chain is
sometimes greater and shorter, other times lesser and longer, as the Lord
pleaseth, for his own Glory, Rev. 20. 1, 2, 7, 8. For as the <hi
rend="italic">wrath of man praiseth the Lord, and the remainder of wrath he
doth restrain</hi>, Psal. 76. 10, So may we say of the Devils wrath.</p>


<p><hi rend="italic">Sect.</hi> 3. The Devil is full of malice against
man, and frames his designs against him, chiefly to destroy his Soul, as, 1 Pet.
5. 8, 2 Cor. 11. 3, and other Scriptures abundantly testify. Hence probably at
sometimes he doth not all the hurt to mans Body that he could, lest thereby he
should awaken man to repentance and prayer; he seeks to keep men in a false
peace. Luk. 11. 21. Yet at other times he disturbs and afflicts men in Body and
Estate; as Scripture and experience shew. Among the Devices Satan useth to ruine
man, one is to allure him into such a familiarity with him, that by Sorceries,
Inchantments, Divinations, and such like, he may lead them Captive at his
pleasure. This snare of his we are warned against, Deut. 18. 10, 11, and in other
Scriptures. This Sin

<pb n="408"/>

of men hearkening after Satan in these ways, is called Witchcraft; of which it is
my purpose to treat: But first I shall speak something Historically what hath been
done in New England, in prosecution of persons suspected of this Crime.</p>


<p><hi rend="italic">Sect.</hi> 4. Several persons have been Charged
with and suffered for the Crime of Witchcraft in the Governments of the
Massachusetts, New Haven, or Stratford<ref target="n367">[367]</ref> and Connecticut, from the year 1646
to the year 1692.</p>


<p><hi rend="italic">Sect.</hi> 5. The first was a Woman of
Charlestown, <hi rend="italic">Anno
</hi> 1647 or 48.<ref target="n368">[368]</ref> She was suspected partly because that after some angry
words passing between her and her Neighbours, some mischief befel such
Neighbours in their Creatures, or the like: partly because some things supposed
to be bewitched, or have a Charm upon them, being burned, she came to the fire
and seemed concerned.</p>


<p>The day of her Execution, I went in company of some
Neighbours,<ref target="n369">[369]</ref> who
took great pains to bring her to confession and repentance. But she constantly
professed her self innocent of that crime: Then one prayed her to consider if God
did not bring this punishment upon her for some other crime, and asked, if she
had not been guilty of Stealing many years ago; she answered, she had stolen
something, but it was long since, and she had repented of it, and there was Grace
enough in Christ to pardon that long agoe; but as for Witchcraft she was wholly
free from it, and so she said unto her Death.</p>


<p><hi rend="italic">Sect.</hi> 6. Another that suffered on that account
some time after, was a Dorchester Woman.<ref target="n370">[370]</ref> And upon the day of her

<pb n="409"/>

Execution Mr. Thompson Minister at Brantry,<ref target="n371">[371]</ref> and J. P.<ref target="n372">[372]</ref> her former Master
took pains with her to bring her to repentance, And she utterly denyed her guilt
of Witchcraft: yet justifyed God for bringing her to that punishment: for she had
when a single woman played the harlot, and being with Child used means to
destroy the fruit of her body to conceal her sin and shame, and although she did
not effect it, yet she was a Murderer in the sight of God for her endeavours, and
shewed great penitency for that sin; but owned nothing of the crime laid to her
charge.</p>


<p><hi rend="italic">Sect.</hi> 7. Another suffering in this kind was a
Woman of Cambridge, against whom a principal evidence was a Water-town
Nurse, who testifyed, that the said Kendal (so was the accused called) did bewitch
to Death a Child of Goodman Genings of Watertown; for the said Kendal did
make much of the Child, and then the Child was well, but quickly changed its
colour and dyed in a few hours after. The Court took this evidence among others,
the said Genings not knowing of it. But after Kendal was Executed (who also
denyed her guilt to the Death,) Mr. Rich. Brown knowing and hoping better
things of Kendal, asked said Genings if they suspected her to bewitch their Child,
they answered No. But they judged the true cause of the Childs Death to be thus,
<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> The Nurse had the night before carryed out the
Child and kept it abroad in the Cold a long time, when the red gum was come out
upon it, and the Cold had struck in the red gum, and this they judged the cause
of the Childs death. And that said Kendal did come in that day and make much
of the Child, but they apprehended no wrong to come to the Child by her. After
this the said Nurse was put into Prison for Adultery, and there delivered of her
base Child, and Mr. Brown went to her and told her, It was just with God to
leave her to this wickedness

<pb n="410"/>

as a Punishment for her Murdering goody Kendal by her false witness bearing.
But the Nurse dyed in Prison, and so the matter was not farther inquired
into.</p>


<p>There was another Executed, of Boston <hi rend="italic">Anno</hi>
1656. for that crime.<ref target="n373">[373]</ref> And two or three of Springfield, one of which confessed;
and said the occasion of her familiarity with Satan was this: She had lost a Child
and was exceedingly discontented at it and longed; Oh that she might see her
Child again! And at last the Devil in likeness of her Child came to her bed side
and talked with her, and asked to come into the bed to her, and she received it
into the bed to her that night and several nights after, and so entred into covenant
with Satan and became a Witch.<ref target="n374">[374]</ref> This was the only confessor in these times in
that Government.</p>


<p><hi rend="italic">Sect</hi>. 8. Another at Hartford, <hi
rend="italic">viz</hi>. Mary Johnson, men-tioned in <hi
rend="italic">Remarkable Providences</hi>, p. 62, 63,<ref target="n375">[375]</ref> Confessed her self
a Witch. Who upon discontent and slouthfulness agreed with the Devil to do her
work for her, and fetch up the Swine. And upon her immoderate laughter at the
running of the Swine, as the Devil drove them, as she her self said, was suspected and upon examination confessed. I have also heard of a Girl at New Haven
or Stratford, that confessed her guilt.<ref target="n376">[376]</ref> But all others denyed it unto the death
unless one Greensmith, at Hartford.<ref target="n377">[377]</ref></p>


<p><hi rend="italic">Sect</hi>. 9. But it is not my purpose to give a full
relation of all that have suffered for that Sin, or of all the particulars

<pb n="411"/>

charged upon them, which probably is now impossible, many witnessing <hi
rend="italic">Viva voce</hi>, those particulars which were not fully
recorded. But that I chiefly intend is to shew the principles formerly acted upon
in Convicting of that Crime; which were such as these.</p>


<p>1. The first great principle laid down by a person Eminent for Wisdom,
Piety and Learning<ref target="n378">[378]</ref> was; That the Devil could not assume the shape of an
innocent person in doing mischief unto mankind: for if the Lord should suffer
him in this he would subvert the course of humane Justice, by bringing men to
suffer for what he did in their Shapes.</p>


<p>2. Witchcraft being an habitual Crime, one single witness to one Act of
Witchcraft, and another single witness to another such fact, made two witnesses
against the Crime and the party suspected.</p>


<p>3. There was searching of the bodies of the suspected for such like teats,
or spots (which writers speak of) called the Devils marks; and if found, these
were accounted a presump-tion at least of guilt in those that had them.</p>


<p>4. I observed that people laid great weight upon this; when things supposed
to be bewitched were burnt, and the suspected person came to the fire in the time
of it.<ref target="n379">[379]</ref> Although that Eminent person
above said<ref target="n380">[380]</ref> condemned this way of tryal,
as going to the Devil to find the Devil.</p>


<p>5. If after anger between Neighbours mischief followed, this oft bred
suspicion of Witchcraft in the matter. In fine, the presumptions and convictions
used in former times were for substance the same which we may read of in
Keeble of the

<pb n="412"/>

Common Law,<ref target="n381">[381</ref> and in Bernard,<ref target="n382">[382]</ref> and other Authors of that subject.</p>


<p><hi rend="italic">Sect</hi>. 10. About 16 or 17 years since was
accused a Woman of Newbury,<ref target="n383">[383]</ref> and upon her tryal the Jury brought her in
Guilty. Yet the Governour Simon Bradstreet Esq. and some of the Magistrates
repreived her, being unsatisfyed in the Verdict upon these grounds.</p>


<p>1. They were not satisfyed that a Specter doing mischief in her likeness,
should be imputed to her person, as a ground of guilt.</p>


<p>2. They did not esteem one single witness to one fact, and another single
witness to another fact, for two witnesses, against the person in a matter Capital.
She being reprived, was carried to her own home, and her Husband (who was
esteemed a Sincere and understanding Christian by those that knew him) desired
some Neighbour Ministers, of whom I was one, to meet together and discourse
his Wife; the which we did: and her discourse was very Christian among us, and
still pleaded her innocence as to that which was laid to her charge. We did not
esteem it prudence for us to pass any definitive Sentance upon one under her
circumstances, yet we inclined to the more charitable side.</p>


<p>In her last Sickness she was in much darkness and trouble of Spirit, which
occasioned a Judicious friend to examine her strictly, Whether she had been guilty
of Witchcraft, but she said No: But the ground of her trouble was some impatient
and passionate Speeches and Actions of hers while in Prison, upon the account
of her suffering wrongfully; whereby she had provoked the Lord, by putting some
contempt upon his word. And in fine, she sought her pardon and comfort from
God in Christ, and dyed so far as I understood, praying to and resting upon God
in Christ for Salvation.</p>


<p><hi rend="italic">Sect</hi>. 11. The next that Suffered was an Irish
Woman of Boston,<ref target="n384">[384]</ref> suspected to bewitch John Goodwins Children, who upon her
Tryal did in Irish (as was testified by the Interpreters) confess her self guilty, and
was condemned out of her own

<pb n="413"/>

mouth; (as Christ saith, Luk. 19. 22. <hi rend="italic">Out of thine own
mouth will I Judge thee</hi>.) The History of which is published by Mr.
Cotton Mather, (and attested by the other Ministers of Boston and Charlstown.)
in his Book, Entituled, <hi rend="italic">Memorable Providences</hi>,
Printed <hi rend="italic">Anno</hi> 1689.<ref target="n385">[385]</ref> Thus far of the History of
Witches before the year, 1692.</p>



<div3 type="notes" id="d13">
<head>Notes</head>

<note id="n367"><seg type="note-symbol">[367].</seg> <p><hi rend="italic">I. e.</hi>, &ldquo;New Haven (or
Stratford)&rdquo;: Hale was not sure (see p. 410) whether the
case in mind was at New Haven or at Stratford. Stratford, though so near New
Haven, was under the Connecticut government. Under that of New Haven there
were, so far as is known, no witch-executions.</p></note>

<note id="n368"><seg type="note-symbol">[368].</seg> <p>Margaret Jones, executed at Boston on June 15, 1648. See
Winthrop, <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi>, II. 344-345 (of the
edition in this series, II. 397 of ed. of 1853), and Poole in
<hi rend="italic">Memorial History of Boston</hi>, II. 135-137; also, above,
p. 363, note 2 &mdash; for it was doubtless to Margaret Jones that the resolution
as to &ldquo;watchinge&rdquo; referred, and it suggests that her accusation too
may have been the outcome of the witch-hunt which had just been raging in the
Puritan counties of England. She was not, as thinks Hale, the first New England
victim; in Connecticut Alse Young was hanged, May 26, 1647.</p></note>

<note id="n369"><seg type="note-symbol">[369].</seg> <p>The writer was then a boy of twelve.</p></note>

<note id="n370"><seg type="note-symbol">[370].</seg> <p>Doubtless that &ldquo;H. Lake's wife, of Dorchester, whom,&rdquo; as
Nathaniel Mather in 1684 wrote to his brother Increase of having heard,
&ldquo;the devill drew in by appearing to her in the likenes, and acting the part
of a child of hers then lately dead, on whom her heart was much set.&rdquo;
(See <hi rend="italic">Mather Papers</hi>, p. 58, and Poole in
<hi rend="italic">N. E. Hist. and Gen. Register</hi>, XXIV. 3,
note.) Mather had lived in Dorchester prior to his migration to England,
about 1650; but, as he had been in constant communication with friends in
America, it is not at all sure that his knowledge of this case antedates his leaving.
In Hale's account there seems some confusion with the case of Mary Parsons (p.
410).</p></note>

<note id="n371"><seg type="note-symbol">[371].</seg> <p>Braintree.</p></note>

<note id="n372"><seg type="note-symbol">[372].</seg> <p>Probably John Phillips of Dorchester &mdash; the conjecture is
Farmer's.</p></note>

<note id="n373"><seg type="note-symbol">[373].</seg> <p>Mrs. Ann Hibbins, widow of one of the foremost men in Boston and said
to have been a sister of Governor Bellingham. (See <hi
rend="italic">Records of Massachusetts</hi>, IV., pt. 1, p. 269;
Hutchinson, <hi rend="italic">Massachusetts</hi>, second ed., I. 187-188;
<hi rend="italic">Me-morial History of Boston</hi>, II.
138-141.)</p></note>

<note id="n374"><seg type="note-symbol">[374].</seg> <p>This was the case of Mary Parsons and her husband Hugh, whom she
accused (1651). (See Drake, <hi rend="italic">Annals of
Witchcraft</hi>, pp. 64-72, and especially the appended papers of Hugh
Parsons's case, pp. 219-258. The originals of these papers are now in the New
York Public Library. Others, from the Suffolk court files, are printed in the <hi
rend="italic">N. E. Hist. and Gen. Register</hi>, XXXV.
152-153.)</p></note>

<note id="n375"><seg type="note-symbol">[375].</seg> <p>Not in the <hi rend="italic">Remarkable Providences</hi> of
Increase Mather, but in the <hi rend="italic">Memorable Providences</hi>
of Cotton Mather at the pages named (see above, pp.
135-136).</p></note>

<note id="n376"><seg type="note-symbol">[376].</seg> <p>Probably that &ldquo;Goody Bassett&rdquo; who was on trial at Stratford
in 1651 (<hi rend="italic">Connecticut Records</hi>, I. 220), and of whom
we know from testimony given at New Haven in 1654 (<hi
rend="italic">New Haven Records</hi>, II. 83) that she was condemned and
that she confessed.</p></note>

<note id="n377"><seg type="note-symbol">[377].</seg> <p>See above, pp. 19-20.</p></note>

<note id="n378"><seg type="note-symbol">[378].</seg> <p>When in 1669 the Connecticut court asked the ministers their opinion as
to this point, they answered in almost these words (see Taylor, <hi
rend="italic">The Witchcraft Delusion in Colonial Connecticut</hi>, p.
58). This opinion is said to be in the hand-writing of the Rev. Gershom
Bulkeley, the author of <hi rend="italic">Will and Doom</hi>. But it does
not follow that he was its author, much less that he was the originator of this
dictum. Whatever its source, it is to be suspected that it had originally nothing
to do with &ldquo;spectral evidence,&rdquo; but was only a protest against such
pleas as that of the bishop who, caught under the bed of a nun, maintained later
that the cul-prit was only the Devil impersonating him. On Bulkeley and his
rational atti-tude toward later charges of witchcraft, see his <hi
rend="italic">Will and Doom</hi> (Conn. Hist. Soc., <hi
rend="italic">Collections</hi>, III.), introduction and pp.
233-235.</p></note>

<note id="n379"><seg type="note-symbol">[379].</seg> <p>See above, p. 239, note 1.</p></note>

<note id="n380"><seg type="note-symbol">[380].</seg> <p>See above, in paragraph 1.</p></note>

<note id="n381"><seg type="note-symbol">[381].</seg> <p>What is meant, as is clear from Hale's later quotations, is Keble's <hi
rend="italic">Assis-tance to Justices</hi>. See above, p. 163, note
2.</p></note>

<note id="n382"><seg type="note-symbol">[382].</seg> <p>See above, p. 304, note 5.</p></note>

<note id="n383"><seg type="note-symbol">[383].</seg> <p>Mrs. Morse. See above, pp. 23-31.</p></note>

<note id="n384"><seg type="note-symbol">[384].</seg> <p>Goody Glover. See above, pp. 100 ff.</p></note>

<note id="n385"><seg type="note-symbol">[385].</seg> <p>See above, pp. 91 ff.</p></note>
</div3>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" id="d14">
<head>Chapter II.</head>

<p>I. In the latter end of the year 1691,<ref target="n386">[386]</ref> Mr. Samuel Paris, Pastor of the
Church in Salem-Village, had a Daughter of Nine, and a Neice of about Eleven
years of Age, sadly Afflicted of they knew not what Distempers; and he made his
application to Physitians, yet still they grew worse: And at length one Physitian
gave his opinion, that they were under an Evil Hand. This the Neighbours quickly
took up, and concluded they were bewitched. He had also an Indian Man servant,
and his Wife who afterwards confessed, that without the knowledge of their
Master or Mistress, they had taken some of the Afflicted persons Urine, and
mixing it with meal had made a Cake, and baked it, to find out the Witch, as they
said. After this, the Afflicted persons cryed out of the Indian Woman, named
Tituba, that she did pinch, prick, and griev-ously torment them, and that they
saw her here and there, where no body else could. Yea they could tell where she
was, and what she did, when out of their humane sight. These Children were
bitten and pinched by invisible agents; their arms, necks, and backs turned this
way and that way, and returned back again, so as it was impossible for them to
do of themselves, and beyond the power of any Epileptick Fits, or natural Disease
to effect. Sometimes they were taken dumb, their mouths stopped, their throats
choaked, their limbs wracked and tormented so as might move an heart of stone,
to sympathize with them, with bowels of compassion for them. I will not enlarge
in the description of their cruel Sufferings, because they were in all things
afflicted as bad as John Good-wins Children at Boston, in the year 1689. So that
he that

<pb n="414"/>

will read Mr. Mathers Book of <hi rend="italic">Memorable
Providences</hi>, page 3, etc., may Read part of what these Children, and
afterwards sundry grown persons suffered by the hand of Satan, at Salem Village,
and parts adjacent, <hi rend="italic">Anno</hi> 1691, 2. Yet there was
more in these Sufferings, than in those at Boston, by pins in-visibly stuck into
their flesh, pricking with Irons, (As in part published in a Book Printed 1693,
<hi rend="italic">viz. The Wanders of the Invisible World</hi>).<ref target="n387">[387]</ref> Mr.
Paris seeing the distressed condition of his Family, desired the presence of some
Worthy Gentle-men of Salem, and some Neighbour Ministers to consult to-gether at his House; who when they came, and had enquired diligently into the
Sufferings of the Afflicted, concluded they were preternatural, and feared the
hand of Satan was in them.</p>


<p>II. The advice given to Mr. Paris by them was, that he should sit still and
wait upon the Providence of God to see what time might discover; and to be
much in prayer for the discovery of what was yet secret. They also Examined
Tituba, who confessed the making a Cake, as is above mentioned, and said her
Mistress in her own Country was a Witch, and had taught her some means to be
used for the discovery of a Witch and for the prevention of being bewitched, etc.
But said that she her self was not a Witch.</p>


<p>III. Soon after this, there were two or three private Fasts at the Ministers
House, one of which was kept by sundry Neighbour Ministers, and after this,
another in Publick at the Village, and several days afterwards of publick
Humiliation, during these molestations, not only there, but in other Con-gregations for them. And one General Fast by Order of the General Court,
observed throughout the Colony to seek the Lord that he would rebuke Satan, and
be a light unto his people in this day of darkness.<ref target="n388">[388]</ref></p>


<p>But I return to the History of these troubles. In a short time after other
persons who were of age to be witnesses, were molested by Satan, and in their
fits cryed out upon Tituba and Goody O. and S. G.<ref target="n389">[389]</ref> that they or Specters in their
Shapes did grievously torment them; hereupon some of their Village

<pb n="415"/>




Neighbours complained to the Magistrates at Salem, desiring they would come
and examine the afflicted and accused to-gether; the which they did: the effect
of which examination was, that Tituba confessed she was a Witch, and that she
with the two others accused did torment and bewitch the com-plainers, and that
these with two others whose names she knew not, had their Witch-meeting
together; relating the times when and places where they met, with many other cir-cumstances to be seen at large. Upon this the said Tituba and O. and S. G. were
committed to Prison upon suspicion of acting Witchcraft. After this the said
Tituba was again ex-amined in Prison, and owned her first confession in all
points, and then was her self afflicted and complained of her fellow Witches
tormenting of her, for her confession, and accusing them, and being searched by
a Woman, she was found to have upon her body the marks of the Devils
wounding of her.</p>


<p>IV. Here were these things rendred her confession credi-ble. (1.) That at
this examination she answered every ques-tion just as she did at the first. And
it was thought that if she had feigned her confession, she could not have
remembred her answers so exactly. A lyar we say, had need of a good memory,
but truth being always consistent with it self is the same to day as it was
yesterday. (2.) She seemed very peni-tent for her Sin in covenanting with the
Devil. (3.) She be-came a sufferer her self and as she said for her confession.
(4.) Her confession agreed exactly (which was afterwards veri-fied in the other
confessors) with the accusations of the afflicted. Soon after these afflicted persons
complained of other persons afflicting of them in their fits, and the number of the
afflicted and accused began to increase. And the success of Tituba's confession
encouraged those in Authority to examine others that were suspected, and the
event was, that more confessed themselves guilty of the Crimes they were
suspected for. And thus was this matter driven on.</p>


<p>V. I observed in the prosecution of these affairs, that there was in the
Justices, Judges and others concerned, a con-scientious endeavour to do the thing
that was right. And to that end they consulted the Presidents<ref target="n390">[390]</ref> of former times and
precepts laid down by Learned Writers about Witchcraft.

<pb n="416"/>




As Keeble on the <hi rend="italic">Common Law</hi>, Chapt.
Conjuration, (an Author approved by the Twelve Judges of our
Nation.)<ref target="n391">[391]</ref> Also
Sir Mathew Hales <hi rend="italic">Tryal of Witches</hi>, Printed <hi
rend="italic">Anno</hi> 1682.<ref target="n392">[392]</ref> Glan-vils <hi rend="italic">Collection
of sundry tryals in England and Ireland</hi>, in the years 1658, 61, 63, 64,
and 81.<ref target="n393">[393]</ref> Bernards <hi
rend="italic">Guide to Jurymen</hi>,<ref target="n394">[394]</ref> Baxter and
R. Burton, their Histories about Witches and their discoveries.<ref target="n395">[395]</ref> Cotton Mather's
<hi rend="italic">Memorable Providences relating to Witchcrafts</hi>,
Printed <hi rend="italic">Anno</hi> 1689.</p>


<p>VI. But that which chiefly carried on this matter to such an height, was the
increasing of confessors till they amounted to near about Fifty: and four or six
of them upon their tryals owned their guilt of this crime, and were condemned
for the same, but not Executed. And many of the confessors con-firmed their
confessions with very strong circumstances: As their exact agreement with the
accusations of the afflicted; their punctual agreement with their fellow confessors;
their relating the times when they covenanted with Satan, and the reasons that
moved them thereunto; their Witch meetings, and that they had their mock
Sacraments of Baptism and the Supper, in some of them; their signing the Devils
book: and some shewed the Scars of the wounds which they said were made to
fetch blood with, to sign the Devils book; and some

<pb n="417"/>




said they had Imps to suck them, and shewed Sores raw where they said they
were sucked by them.</p>


<p>VII. I shall give the Reader a tast of these things in a few Instances. The
Afflicted complained that the Spectres which vexed them, urged them to set their
Hands to a Book represented to them (as to them it seemed) with threatnings of
great torments, if they signed not, and promises of ease if they obeyed.</p>


<p>Among these D. H.<ref target="n396">[396]</ref> did as she said (which sundry others confessed
afterwards) being overcome by the extremity of her pains, sign the Book
presented, and had the promised ease; and immediately upon it a Spectre in her
Shape afflicted another person, and said, I have signed the Book and have ease,
now do you sign, and so shall you have ease. And one day this afflicted person
pointed at a certain place in the room, and said, there is D. H., upon which a
man with his Rapier struck at the place, though he saw no Shape; and the
Afflicted called out, saying, you have wounded her side, and soon after the
afflicted person pointed at another place, saying, there she is; whereupon a man
struck at the place, and the afflicted said, you have given her a small prick about
the eye. Soon after this, the said D. H. confessed her self to be made a Witch by
signing the Devils Book as above said; and declared that she had afflicted the
Maid that complained of her, and in doing of it had received two wounds by a
Sword or Rapier, a small one about the eye, which she shewed to the
Magistrates, and a bigger on the side of which she was searched by a discreet
woman, who reported, that D. H. had on her side the sign of a wound newly
healed.</p>


<p>This D. H. confessed that she was at a Witch Meeting at Salem Village,
where were many persons that she named, some of whom were in Prison then or
soon after upon suspicion of Witchcraft: And the said G. B.<ref target="n397">[397]</ref> preached to them,
and such a Woman was their Deacon, and there they had a Sacra-ment.</p>


<p>VIII. Several others after this confessed the same things

<pb n="418"/>




with D. H. In particular Goody F.<ref target="n398">[398]</ref> said
(<hi rend="italic">Inter alia</hi><ref target="n399">[399]</ref>)
that she with two others (one of whom acknowledged the same) Rode from
Andover to the same Village Witch meeting upon a stick above ground, and that
in the way the stick brake, and gave the said F. a fall: whereupon, said she, I got
a fall and hurt of which I am still sore. I happened to be present in Prison when
this F. owned again her former confession to the Magistrates. And then I moved
she might be further ques-tioned about some particulars: It was answered, the
Magis-trates had not time to stay longer; but I should have liberty to Examine
her farther by my self; The which thing I did; and I asked her if she rode to the
Meeting on a Stick; she said, yea. I enquired what she did for Victuals; she
answered that she carried Bread and Cheese in her pocket, and that she and the
Andover Company came to the Village before the Meeting began, and sat down
together under a tree and eat their food, and that she drank water out of a Brook
to quench her thirst. And that the Meeting was upon a plain grassy place, by
which was a Cart path, and sandy ground in the path, in which were the tracks
of Horses feet. And she also told me how long they were going and returning.
And some time after told me, she had some trouble upon her spirit, and when I
enquired what? she said, she was in fear that G. B. and M. C.<ref target="n400">[400]</ref> would kill her;
for they appeared unto her (in Spectre, for their persons were kept in other
Rooms in the Prison) and brought a sharp pointed iron like a spindle, but four
square, and threatned to stab her to death with it; because she had confessed her
Witchcraft, and told of them, that they were with her, and that M. C. above
named was the person that made her a Witch. About a month after the said F.
took occasion to tell me the same Story of her fears that G. B. and E.
C.<ref target="n401">[401]</ref> would
kill her, and that the thing was much upon her Spirits.</p>


<p>IX. It was not long before M. L.<ref target="n402">[402]</ref> Daughter of said F. confessed that she
rode with her Mother to the said Witch

<pb n="419"/>




Meeting, and confirmed the substance of her Mothers Confes-sion. At another
time, M. L. junior the Grand Daughter, aged about seventeen years, confesseth
the substance of what her Grand mother and Mother had related, and declareth,
that when they with E. C.<ref target="n403">[403]</ref> rode on a stick or pole in the Air, She the said
Grand-Daughter with R. C.<ref target="n404">[404]</ref> Rode upon another; (and she said R. C.
acknowledged the same) and that they sat their hands to the Devils Book. And
(<hi rend="italic">inter alia</hi>) said, &ldquo;O Mother, why did you
give me to the Devil?&rdquo; twice or thrice over. The Mother said, she was
sorry at the heart for it, it was through that wicked one. Her Daughter bid her
repent and call upon God. And said, &ldquo;Oh Mother, your wishes are now
come to pass! for how often have you wished that the Devil would fetch me away
alive?&rdquo; And then said, &ldquo;Oh! my heart will break within
me&rdquo;; Then she wept bitterly, crying out, &ldquo;O Lord comfort me, and
bring out all the Witches.&rdquo; And she said to her Grandmother, &ldquo;O
Grandmother, why did you give me to the Devil? Why did you perswade me, O
Grand-mother do not deny it.&rdquo; Then the Grandmother gave account of
several things about their confederates and acts of Witch-crafts too long to
rehearse.</p>



<div3 type="notes" id="d15">
<head>Notes</head>

<note id="n386"><seg type="note-symbol">[386].</seg> <p><hi rend="italic">I. e.</hi>, in February and March of the year we
call 1692. As to all this story see above the parallel narratives of Lawson
(pp. 147 ff.) and Calef (pp. 341 ff.).</p></note>

<note id="n387"><seg type="note-symbol">[387].</seg> <p>See above, pp. 205 ff.</p></note>

<note id="n388"><seg type="note-symbol">[388].</seg> <p>This fast, enacted on May 6, was celebrated on May 26, 1692 (Massachu-setts <hi rend="italic">Acts and Resolves</hi>, VII. 459).</p></note>

<note id="n389"><seg type="note-symbol">[389].</seg> <p>Sarah Osborn and Sarah Good.</p></note>

<note id="n390"><seg type="note-symbol">[390].</seg> <p>Precedents.</p></note>

<note id="n391"><seg type="note-symbol">[391].</seg> <p>See above, p. 163, note 2. &ldquo;Conjuration&rdquo;
is the heading given by Keble to his section on witchcraft (pp. 217-220).</p></note>

<note id="n392"><seg type="note-symbol">[392].</seg> <p>The account is not Sir Matthew's own, nor yet an official record, but one
taken down &ldquo;for his own satisfaction&rdquo; &ldquo;by a Person then
Attending the Court,&rdquo; and so did not till 1682 find its way into print. As
we have seen (p. 215, note 1) it was embodied by Cotton Mather in his <hi
rend="italic">Wonders</hi>.</p></note>

<note id="n393"><seg type="note-symbol">[393].</seg> <p>See above, pp. 5-6.</p></note>

<note id="n394"><seg type="note-symbol">[394].</seg> <p>See above, p. 304, note 5.</p></note>

<note id="n395"><seg type="note-symbol">[395].</seg> <p>Baxter's <hi rend="italic">Certainty of the Worlds of Spirits</hi>
(1691), really a collection of witch stories, has been earlier described (p. 98, note
2). The name of &ldquo;R. Bur-ton,&rdquo; or &ldquo;R. B.,&rdquo; the
pseudonym under which the prolific London publisher Nathaniel Crouch
concealed his identity, is attached to a multitude of chap-books; but that here in
question was undoubtedly his <hi rend="italic">The Kingdom of Darkness
</hi> (London, 1688), a pictorial &ldquo;history of d&aelig;mons, specters,
witches, apparitions, possessions, disturbances, and other wonderful and
supernatural delusions, mis-chievous feats, and malicious impostures of the
Devil,&rdquo; &ldquo;together with a preface obviating the common objections
and allegations of the Sadduces and Atheists of the age.&rdquo; It is, in other
words, a credulous hodge-podge of all the older witch and devil tales that could
be packed into its duodecimo pages; tales made vivid by its startling frontispiece
and the crude but awful woodcuts that adorn its text.</p></note>

<note id="n396"><seg type="note-symbol">[396].</seg> <p>Deliverance Hobbs &mdash; called by error &ldquo;Deborah&rdquo; on
p. 347. The court record of her examination may be found in <hi
rend="italic">Records of Salem Witchcraft</hi>, II. 186-192.</p></note>

<note id="n397"><seg type="note-symbol">[397].</seg> <p>George Burroughs.</p></note>

<note id="n398"><seg type="note-symbol">[398].</seg> <p>Ann Foster. See above, pp. 244, 366. As her son later
alleged, she &ldquo;suffered imprisonment twenty-one weeks and upon her Tryall
was condemned for supposed witchcraft... and died in prison.&rdquo;</p></note>

<note id="n399"><seg type="note-symbol">[399].</seg> <p>&ldquo;Among other things.&rdquo;</p></note>

<note id="n400"><seg type="note-symbol">[400].</seg> <p>Martha Carrier. See above, pp. 241-244.</p></note>

<note id="n401"><seg type="note-symbol">[401].</seg> <p>Doubtless a printer's error for M. C. (Martha Carrier).</p></note>

<note id="n402"><seg type="note-symbol">[402].</seg> <p>Mary Lacy. See pp. 244, 366. Though condemned, she
escaped death.</p></note>

<note id="n403"><seg type="note-symbol">[403].</seg> <p>Again a misprint for M. C. (see Mary Lacy's testimony in <hi
rend="italic">Records of Salem Witchcraft</hi>, II. 140: &ldquo;her mother
Foster, Goody Carrier and herself rid upon a pole to Salem Village
meeting&rdquo;).</p></note>

<note id="n404"><seg type="note-symbol">[404].</seg> <p>Richard Carrier, son of Martha.</p></note>
</div3>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" id="d16">
<head>Chapter III.</head>

<p>Nextly I will insert the Confession of a man about Forty years of Age, W.
B.,<ref target="n405">[405]</ref> which he wrote himself in Prison, and sent to the Magistrates, to confirm
his former Confession to them, <hi rend="italic">viz</hi>.</p>


<p>God having called me to Confess my sin and Apostasy in that fall in giving
the Devil advantage over me appearing to me like a Black, in the evening to set
my hand to his Book, as I have owned to my shame. He told me that I should not
want so doing. At Salem Village, there being a little off the Meeting-House,
about an hundred five Blades,<ref target="n406">[406]</ref> some with Rapiers by their side, which was called
and might be more for ought I know by B and Bu.<ref target="n407">[407]</ref> and the

<pb n="420"/>




Trumpet sounded, and Bread and Wine which they called the Sacrament, but I
had none; being carried over all on a Stick, never being at any other Meeting. I
being at Cart a Saturday last, all the day, of Hay and English Corn, the Devil
brought my Shape to Salem, and did afflict M. S.<ref
target="n408">[408]</ref> and R. F.<ref target="n409">[409]</ref> by clitching my
Hand; and a Sabbath day my Shape afflicted A. M.<ref target="n410">[410]</ref> and at night afflicted M. S.
and A. M. E. I.<ref target="n411">[411]</ref> and A. F.<ref target="n412">[412]</ref> have been my Enticers to this great abomination,
as one have owned and charged her to her Sister with the same. And the design
was to Destroy Salem Village, and to begin at the Ministers House, and to
destroy the Church of God, and to set up Satans Kingdom, and then all will be
well. And now I hope God in some measure has made me something sensible of
my sin and apostasy, begging pardon of God, and of the Honourable Magistrates
and all Gods people, hoping and promising by the help of God, to set to my heart
and hand to do what in me lyeth to destroy such wicked worship, humbly begging
the prayers of all Gods People for me, I may walk humbly under this great
affliction and that I may procure to my self, the sure mercies of David, and the
blessing of Abraham.</p>


<p>Concerning this Confession. (1) Note it was his own free act in Prison. (2)
He saith the Devil like a Black. This he had before explained to be like a Black
man. (3) That on a certain day was heard in the Air the sound of a Trumpet at
Salem Village nigh the Meeting-House, and upon all enquiry it could not be found
that any mortal man did sound it. (4) The three persons he saith the Devil in his
Shape afflicted, had been as to the times and manner afflicted as he confesseth.
(5) That E. I. confessed as much as W. B. chargeth her with. (6) Many others
confessed a Witch Meeting, or Witch meetings at the Village as well as he.</p>


<p>Note also that these Confessors did not only witness against themselves, but
against one another; and against many if not all those that Suffered for that
Crime. As for example, when

<pb n="421"/>




G. B.<ref target="n413">[413]</ref> was Tryed, seven or eight of these Confessors severally called, said, they
knew the said B. and saw him at a Witch-Meeting at the Village, and heard him
exhort the Company to pull down the Kingdom of God, and set up the Kingdom
of the Devil. He denied all, yet said he justified the Judges and Jury in
Condemning of him; because there were so many positive witnesses against him:
But said he dyed by false Witnesses. I seriously spake to one that witnessed (of
his Exhorting at the Witch Meeting at the Village) saying to her; You are one that
bring this man to Death, if you have charged any thing upon him that is not true,
recal it before it be too late, while he is alive. She answered me, she had nothing
to charge her self with, upon that account.</p>


<p>M. C.<ref target="n414">[414]</ref> had to witness against her, two or three of her own Children, and
several of her Neighbours that said they were in confederacy with her in their
Witchcraft.</p>


<p>A. F.<ref target="n415">[415]</ref> Had three of her Children, and some of the Neighbours, her own
Sister, and a Servant, who confessed themselves Witches, and said, she was in
confederacy with them: But alas, I am weary with relating particulars; those that
would see more of this kind, let them have recourse to the Records.</p>


<p>By these things you see how this matter was carried on, <hi
rend="italic">viz.</hi> chiefly by the complaints and accusations of the
Afflicted, Bewitched ones, as it was supposed, and then by the Confessions of the
Accused, condemning themselves, and others. Yet experience shewed that the
more there were apprehended, the more were still Afflicted by Satan, and the
number of Confessors increasing, did but increase the number of the Accused,
and the Executing some, made way for the apprehending of others; for still the
Afflicted complained of being tormented by new objects as the former were
removed. So that those that were concerned, grew amazed at the numbers and
quality of the persons accused and feared that Satan by his wiles had inwrapped
innocent persons under the imputation of that Crime.

<pb n="422"/>




And at last it was evidently seen that there must be a stop put, or the Generation
of the Children of God would fall under that condemnation.</p>


<p>Henceforth therefore the Juries generally acquitted such as were Tried,
fearing they had gone too far before. And Sir William Phips, Governour,
Reprieved all that were Condemned, even the Confessors, as well as others. And
the Confessors generally fell off from their Confessions; some saying, they
remembred nothing of what they said; others said they had belied themselves and
others. Some brake Prison and ran away, and were not strictly searched after,
some acquitted, some dismissed and one way or other all that had been accused
were set or left at liberty.</p>


<p>And although had the times been calm, the condition of the Confessors
might have called for a <hi rend="italic">melius
inquirendum</hi>,<ref target="n416">[416]</ref> yet
considering the combustion<ref target="n417">[417]</ref> and confusion this matter had brought us unto; it
was thought safer to under do than over do, especially in matters Capital, where
what is once compleated cannot be retrieved: but what is left at one time, may be
corrected at another, upon a review and clearer discovery of the state of the Case.
Thus this matter issued somewhat abruptly.</p>



<div3 type="notes" id="d17">
<head>Notes</head>

<note id="n405"><seg type="note-symbol">[405].</seg> <p>William Barker, of Andover.</p></note>

<note id="n406"><seg type="note-symbol">[406].</seg> <p>Bravoes.</p></note>

<note id="n407"><seg type="note-symbol">[407].</seg> <p>Bishop and Burroughs?</p></note>

<note id="n408"><seg type="note-symbol">[408].</seg> <p>Martha Sprague.</p></note>

<note id="n409"><seg type="note-symbol">[409].</seg> <p>Rose Foster.</p></note>

<note id="n410"><seg type="note-symbol">[410].</seg> <p>Abigail Martin.</p></note>

<note id="n411"><seg type="note-symbol">[411].</seg> <p>Elizabeth Johnson. Her daughter, of the same name, was also accused and
confessed (see p. 382, note 4, above).</p></note>

<note id="n412"><seg type="note-symbol">[412].</seg> <p>Abigail Falkner. She and her sister Elizabeth Johnson were daughters of
the Rev. Francis Dane (or Deane), senior pastor at Andover, who seems from the
first to have stood against the panic and who was largely instrumental in ending
it. All those here accused were Andover folk, neighbors of Barker. See as to
them Mrs. Bailey's chapter on &ldquo;Witchcraft at Andover&rdquo; (in her
<hi rend="italic">Historical Sketches of Andover</hi>).</p></note>

<note id="n413"><seg type="note-symbol">[413].</seg> <p>George Burroughs.</p></note>

<note id="n414"><seg type="note-symbol">[414].</seg> <p>Martha Carrier.</p></note>

<note id="n415"><seg type="note-symbol">[415].</seg> <p>Abigail Falkner (see pp. 366, 420). &ldquo;She was
urged,&rdquo; says the record, &ldquo;to confes the truth for the creddit of hir
Town,&rdquo; but &ldquo;she refused to do it, saying God would not require her
to confess that that she was not guilty of&rdquo; (<hi rend="italic">Records
of <unclear></unclear> Witchcraft</hi>, II. 128-135, where may also be
found the evidence against her). She was condemned, but not executed.</p></note>

<note id="n416"><seg type="note-symbol">[416].</seg> <p>&ldquo;Better investigation&rdquo; &mdash; <hi
rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, a writ for a fresh inquiry.</p></note>

<note id="n417"><seg type="note-symbol">[417].</seg> <p>Excitement.</p></note>
</div3>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" id="d18">
<head>Chapter IV.</head>

<p>Here was generally acknowledged to be an error (at least on the one hand)
but the Querie is, Wherein?</p>


<p>[<hi rend="italic">A</hi>.] 1. I have heard it said, That the
Presidents<ref target="n418">[418]</ref> in England were not so exactly followed, because in those there had
been previous quarrels and threatnings of the Afflicted by those that were
Condemned for Witchcraft; but here, say they, not so. To which I answer.</p>


<p>1. In many of these cases there had been antecedent personal quarrels, and
so occasions of revenge; for some of those Condemned, had been suspected by
their Neighbours several years, because after quarrelling with their Neighbours,
evils had befallen those Neighbours. As may be seen in the Printed Tryals of S.
M. and B. B.<ref target="n419">[419]</ref> and others: See <hi
rend="italic">Wonders of the</hi>

<pb n="423"/>

<hi rend="italic">Invisible World</hi>, Page 105 to 137.<ref target="n420">[420]</ref> And
there were other like Cases not Printed.</p>


<p>2. Several confessors acknowledged they engaged in the quarrels of other
their confederates to afflict persons. As one Timothy Swan suffered great things
by Witchcrafts, as he supposed and testifyed. And several of the confessors said
they did so torment him for the sake of one of their partners who had some
offence offer'd her by the said Swan. And others owned they did the like in the
behalf of some of their confederates.<ref target="n421">[421]</ref></p>


<p>3. There were others that confessed their fellowship in these works of
darkness, was to destroy the Church of God (as is above in part rehearsed) which
is a greater piece of revenge then<ref target="n422">[422]</ref> to be avenged upon one particular
person.</p>


<p>[<hi rend="italic">A</hi>.] 2. It may be queried then, How doth it
appear that there was a going too far in this affair.</p>


<p>1. By the numbers of the persons accused which at length increased to
about an hundred and it cannot be imagined that in a place of so much
knowledge, so many in so small a compass of Land should so abominably leap
into the Devils lap at once.</p>


<p>2. The quality of several of the accused was such as did bespeak better
things, and things that accompany salvation. Persons whose blameless and holy
lives before did testify for them. Persons that had taken great pains to bring up
their Children in the nurture and admonition of the Lord: Such as we had Charity
for, as for our own Souls: and Charity is a Christian duty commended to us. 1
Cor. 13 Chapt., Col. 3. 14, and in many other Scriptures.</p>


<p>3. The number of the afflicted by Satan dayly increased, till about Fifty
persons were thus vexed by the Devil. This gave just ground to suspect some
mistake, which gave advantage to the accuser of the Brethren<ref target="n423">[423]</ref> to make a breach
upon us.</p>


<p>4. It was considerable <ref target="n424">[424]</ref> that Nineteen were Executed, and all denyed the
Crime to the Death, and some of them were

<pb n="424"/>




knowing persons, and had before this been accounted blameless livers. And it is
not to be imagined, but that if all had been guilty, some would have had so much
tenderness as to seek Mercy for their Souls in the way of Confession and sorrow
for such a Sin. And as for the condemned confessors at the Bar (they being
reprieved) we had no experience whether they would stand to their
Self-condemning confessions, when they came to dye.</p>


<p>5. When this prosecution ceased, the Lord so chained up Satan, that the
afflicted grew presently well. The accused are generally quiet, and for five years
since, we have no such molestations by them.</p>


<p>6. It sways much with me that I have since heard and read of the like
mistakes in other places. As in Suffolk in England about the year 1645 was such
a prosecution, until they saw that unless they put a stop it would bring all into
blood and confusion.<ref target="n425">[425]</ref> The like hath
been in France, till 900 were put to Death,<ref target="n426">[426]</ref>
And in some other places the like; So that N. England is not the only place
circumvented by the wiles of the wicked and wisely Serpent in this kind.</p>


<p>Wierus <hi rend="italic">de Pr&oelig;stigiis Demonum</hi>, p.
678,<ref target="n427">[427]</ref> Relates, That an Inquisitor in the Subalpine Valleys, enquired after Women
Witches, and consumed above an hundred in the Flames, and daily made new
offerings to Vulcan of those that needed Helebore more than Fire,<ref target="n428">[428]</ref> Until the
Country peole rose and by force of Arms hindred him, and refer the matter to the
Bishop. Their Husbands, men of good Faith, affirmed that in that very time they
said of them, that they played and danced under a tree, they were in bed with
them.</p>

<pb n="425"/>


<p>R. Burton of Witches, etc. p. 158,<ref target="n429">[429]</ref> Saith, That in Chelmsford in Essex,
<hi rend="italic">Anno</hi> 1645, were Thirty tryed at once before Judge
Coniers, and Fourteen of them hanged, and an hundred more contained in several
Prisons in Suffolk and Essex.</p>


<p>If there were an Error in the proceedings in other places, and in N.
England, it must be in the principles proceeded upon in prosecuting the suspected,
or in the misapplication of the principles made use of. Now as to the case at
Salem, I conceive it proceeded from some mistaken principles made use of; for
the evincing whereof, I shall instance some principles made use of here, and in
other Countrys also, which I find defended by learned Authors writing upon that
Subject.<ref target="n430">[430]</ref></p>



<div3 type="notes" id="d19">
<head>Notes</head>

<note id="n418"><seg type="note-symbol">[418].</seg> <p>Precedents.</p></note>

<note id="n419"><seg type="note-symbol">[419].</seg> <p>Susannah Martin and Bridget Bishop.</p></note>

<note id="n420"><seg type="note-symbol">[420].</seg> <p>At pp. 223-236, above.</p></note>

<note id="n421"><seg type="note-symbol">[421].</seg> <p>Timothy Swan, aged thirty, died early in February, 1692/3 (<hi
rend="italic">N. E. Hist. and Gen. Reg.</hi>, II. 380; Mrs. Bailey, <hi
rend="italic">Historical Sketches of Andover</hi>, p. 237).</p></note>

<note id="n422"><seg type="note-symbol">[422].</seg> <p>Than.</p></note>

<note id="n423"><seg type="note-symbol">[423].</seg> <p><hi rend="italic">I. e.</hi>, Satan (see Rev. xii.
10).</p></note>

<note id="n424"><seg type="note-symbol">[424].</seg> <p>Deserving of consideration.</p></note>

<note id="n425"><seg type="note-symbol">[425].</seg> <p>The famous witch-hunt in which Matthew Hopkins was the leading spirit
(1645-1646).</p></note>

<note id="n426"><seg type="note-symbol">[426].</seg> <p>What is in thought is doubtless the boast of Nicolas Remy (Remigius), on
the title-page of his <hi rend="italic">D&oelig;monolatreia</hi> (1595),
that his book rests on the trials of nine hundred, put to death for witchcraft within
fifteen years; but this was in Lorraine, not yet a part of France, though in close
relations with it.</p></note>

<note id="n427"><seg type="note-symbol">[427].</seg> <p>Lib. VI., cap. 20, of this notable book by which the eminent Rhenish
physician Wierus (Johann Weyer, 1515-1588) gave to the zeal of the witch-haters
its first effective check. This passage, however, he borrows bodily from the <hi
rend="italic">Parergon Juris</hi> (VIII. 22) of an earlier opponent of witch
persecution, the Italian jurist Andrea Alciati.</p></note>

<note id="n428"><seg type="note-symbol">[428].</seg> <p><hi rend="italic">I. e.</hi>, those crazed more than criminal:
hellebore was counted a cure for insanity.</p></note>

<note id="n429"><seg type="note-symbol">[429].</seg> <p>See p. 416, note 5. &ldquo;Burton&rdquo; has merely
inserted into his <hi rend="italic">Kingdom of Darkness</hi> (pp. 148-159)
the contents of the contemporary <hi rend="italic">True and Exact
Relation</hi> (1645) which narrates this Essex persecution.</p></note>

<note id="n430"><seg type="note-symbol">[430].</seg> <p>The following chapters (V.-XVII.) are devoted to the nature of witchcraft
and the proper means for its detection.</p></note>
</div3>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" id="d20">
<head>Chapter XVIII.</head>

<p>I shall conclude this Discourse with some Application of the whole.</p>


<p>1. We may hence see ground to fear, that there hath been a great deal of
innocent blood shed in the Christian World, by proceeding upon unsafe
principles, in condemning persons for Malefick Witchcraft.<ref target="n431">[431]</ref></p>


<p>2. That there have been great sinful neglects in sparing others, who by their
divinings about things future, or discovering things secret, as stollen Goods, etc.,
or by their informing of persons and things absent at a great distance, have
implored the assistance of a familiar spirit, yet coloured over with specious
pretences, and have drawn people to enquire of them: A sin frequently forbidden
in Scripture, as Lev. 19. 31 and 20. 6, Isa. 8. 19, 20. and yet let alone, and in
many parts of

<pb n="426"/>

the World, have been countenanced in their diabolical skill and profession;
because they serve the interest of those that have a vain curiosity, to pry into
things God hath forbidden, and concealed from discovery by lawful means. And
of others that by their inchantments, have raised mists, strange sights, and the
like, to beget admiration, and please Spectators, etc., When as<ref target="n432">[432]</ref> these divinations
and operations are the Witchcraft more condemned in Scripture than the
other.</p>


<p>3. But to come nigher home, we have cause to be humbled for the mistakes
and errors which have been in these Colonies, in their Proceedings against
persons for this crime, above fourty years ago and downwards, upon insufficient
presumptions and presidents<ref target="n433">[433]</ref> of our Nation, whence they came. I do not say, that
all those were innocent, that suffered in those times upon this account. But that
such grounds were then laid down to proceed upon, which were too slender to
evidence the crime they were brought to prove; and thereby a foundation laid to
lead into error those that came after. May we not say in this matter, as it is, Psal.
106. 6. <hi rend="italic">We have sinned with our fathers?</hi> And as,
Lam. 5. 7. <hi rend="italic">Our fathers have sinned and are not, and we
have born their iniquities?</hi> And whether this be not one of the sins the
Lord hath been many years contending with us for, is worthy our serious enquiry.
If the Lord punished Israel with famine three years for a sin of misguided zeal
fourty years before that, committed by the breach of a Covenant made four
hundred years before that: 2 Sam. 21. 1, 2, Why may not the Lord visit upon us
the misguided zeal of our Predecessors about Witchcraft above fourty years ago,
even when that Generation is gathered to their Fathers.</p>


<p>4. But I would come yet nearer to our own times, and bewail the errors and
mistakes that have been in the year 1692. In the apprehending too many we may
believe were innocent, and executing of some, I fear, not to have been
condemned; by following such traditions of our fathers, maxims of the Common
Law, and Presidents2 and Principles, which now we may see weighed in the
balance of the Sanctuary, are found too light. I heartily concur with that direction
for our publick prayers, emitted December 17, 1696, by our General Assembly,
in an order for a general Fast, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> &ldquo;That
God

<pb n="427"/>

would shew us what we know not, and help us wherein we have done amiss, to
do so no more: And especially that whatever mistakes on either hand, have been
fallen into, either by the body of this people, or any order of men, referring to
the late tragedy raised among us by Satan and his Instruments, through the awful
Judgment of God: He would humble us therefore, and pardon all the errors of his
Servants and People, that desire to love his Name, and be attoned to his
land.&rdquo; I am abundantly satisfyed that those who were most concerned to
act and judge in those matters, did not willingly depart from the rules of
righteousness. But such was the darkness of that day, the tortures and
lamentations of the afflicted, and the power of former presidents, that we walked
in the clouds, and could not see our way. And we have most cause to be humbled
for error on that hand, which cannot be retrieved. So that we must beseech the
Lord, that if any innocent blood hath been shed, in the hour of temptation, the
Lord will not lay it to our charge, but be merciful to his people whom he hath
redeemed, Deut. 21. 8, And that in the day when he shall visit, he will not visit
this sin upon our land, but blot it out, and wash it away with the blood of Jesus
Christ.</p>


<p>5. I would humbly propose whether it be not expedient, that some what
more should be publickly done then<ref target="n434">[434]</ref> yet hath, for clearing the good name and
reputation of some that have suffered upon this account, against whom the
evidence of their guilt was more slender, and the grounds for charity for them
more convincing. And this (in order to our obtaining from the Lord farther
reconciliation to our land,) and that none of their surviving relations, may suffer
reproach upon that account. I have both read and heard of several in England,
that have been executed for Capital crimes, and afterwards upon sence of an error
in the process against them, have been restored in blood and honour by some
publick act. My Lord Cook<ref target="n435">[435]</ref> relates a story. A man going to correct a Girle his
Neice, for some offence, in an upper room, the Girle strove to save her self, till
her nose bled, and wiping it with a cloath, threw the bloody cloath out at the
window, and cryed Murder; and then ran down staires, got away and hid her self.
Her Uncle was prosecuted by her friends upon suspicion of

<pb n="428"/>

Murdering her, because she could not be found. He declared that she made her
escape, as above said. Then time was allowed him to bring her forth, but he
could not hear of her within the time, and fearing he should dy if she could not
be found, procures another Girle very like her, to appear in Court, and declare
she was his Neice that had been missing: But her relations examine this
counterfeit, until they find her out, and she confesseth she was suborned and
counterfeited the true Neice. Upon these presumptions the man was found guilty
of Murdering his Neice, and thereupon executed. And after his execution his true
Neice comes abroad and shews her self alive and well. Then all that saw it were
convinced of the Uncles innocency, and vanity of such presumptions. The
Printing and Publishing of this relation Vindicates the good name of the Uncle,
from the imputation of the crime of Murder. And this is one end of this present
discourse, to take off (so far as a discourse of this nature can) infamy from the
names and memory of such sufferers in this kind, as do not deserve the
same.</p>


<p>6. Here it may be suitable for us to enquire, What the Lord speaks to us
by such a stupendeous providence, in his letting loose Satan upon us in this
unusual way? <hi rend="italic">Ans.</hi> 1. We may say of this, as our
Saviour said of his washing his disciples feet, Joh. 13. <hi
rend="italic">What I do thou knowest not now, but thou shalt know hereafter.
The Judgments of the Lord are a great deep</hi>, Psal. 36. 6. <hi
rend="italic">How unsearchable are his judgments, and his ways past finding
out</hi>. 2. Yet somewhat of his counsel at present for our instruction may be
known, by comparing the Word and works of God together.</p>


<p>1. As when Joshua the high Priest though an holy chosen man of God,
stood before the Angel, Satan stood at his right hand to resist him, or to be his
adversary: And the advantage Satan had was by the filthy garments Joshua was
clothed with before the Angels: That is, some iniquity which yet was not passed
away, Zech. 3. 1, 3, 4. So we may say here were among Gods own Children
filthy garments. The sins of Lukewarmness, loss of our first love,
unprofitableness under the Gospel, slumbering and sleeping in the wise, as well
as foolish Virgins, worldliness, pride, carnal security, and many other sins. By
these and such like sins the accuser of the Brethren

<pb n="429"/>

got advantage to stand at our right hand (the place of an Accuser in Courts of
Justice) and there accuse us and resist us.</p>


<p>2. When the Egyptians refused to let Israel go to sacrifice and keep a feast
to the Lord in the Wilderness: The Lord cast upon [them] the fierceness of his
wrath, by sending Evil Angels among them, Psal. 78. 49. Egypts sins were (1.)
Coveteousness; they would not let Israel go, because they gained by their labours.
(2.) Contempt of God and his Instituted Worship, and Ordinances. They did not
count them of such concernment, that Israel should go into the Wilderness to
observe them. Both these sins have too much increased in our Land. (1.)
Coveteousness, an inordinate love of the World gave Satan advantage upon us.
(2.) Contempt of Gods Worship and Instituted Ordinances. The Errand of our
Fathers into this Wilderness, was to Sacrifice to the Lord; that is, to worship God
in purity of heart and life, and to wait upon the Lord, walking in the faith and
order of the Gospel in Church fellowship; that they might enjoy Christ in all his
Ordinances. But these things have been greatly neglected and despised by many
born, or bred up in the Land. We have much forgotten what our Fathers came
into the Wilderness to see. The sealing Ordinances of the Covenant of Grace in
Church-Communion have been much slighted and neglected; and the fury of this
Storm raised by Satan hath fallen very heavily upon many that lived under these
neglects. The Lord sends Evil Angels to awaken and punish our negligence: And
to my knowledge some have been hereby excited to enter into the Chamber of
Gods Ordinances, to hide themselves, until the indignation be over past.</p>


<p>3. David when he removed the Ark from Kirjathjearim, had the Ark put
into a new Cart, which should have been carried by the Kohathites. Numb. 3. 31.
And David thought this was right, until the Lord slew Uzza for touching the Ark:
But then he looked more exactly into the will of God; and confesseth that the
Lord made a breach upon them, because they sought him not after the due order,
1 Chron. 13. 5, 7, 9, 10, and 15. 11, 12, 13. Had not the Lord made that breach
upon them, they had persisted securely in their error. So I may say in this case.
In the prosecution of Witchcraft, we

<pb n="430"/>




sought not the Lord after the due order; but have proceeded after the methods
used in former times and other places, until the Lord in this tremendous way
made a breach upon us. And hereby we are made sensible that the methods
formerly used are not sufficient to prove the guilt of such a crime. And this I
conceive was one end of the Lords letting Satan loose to torment and accuse so
many; that hereby we may search out the truth more exactly. For had it not been
for this dreadful dispensation, many would have lived and dyed in that error,
which they are now convinced of.</p>


<p>4. The Lord delivered into the hand of Satan the Estate, Children, and
Body of Job, for the tryal of Jobs faith and patience, and proof of his perfection
and uprightness. So the Lord hath delivered into Satans hand mens Children and
Bodies, yea names and estates into Satans hand for the tryal of their faith and
patience, and farther manifestation of the sincerity of their professions.</p>


<p>7.<ref target="n436">[436]</ref> From that part of the discourse which shews the power of Satan to
torment the bodies, and disturb the minds of those, he is let loose upon, Chap.
6, I would infer, that Satan may be suffered so to darken the minds of some pious
Souls, as to cause them to destroy themselves by drowning, hanging, or the like.
And when he hath so far prevailed upon some, that formerly lived a Christian
life, but were under the prevalency of a distracting Melancholy at their latter end,
We may have Charity that their Souls are Saved, notwithstanding the sad
conclusion of their lives. I speak not to excuse any that having the free use of
their reason willingly destroy themselves, out of pride, discontent, impatience,
etc. Achitophel who out of height of Spirit because his Counsel was not followed,
and to prevent Davids executing of him, for his rebellion and treason, destroyed
himself, hath left his name to stink unto all generations.<ref target="n437">[437]</ref> And Judas who for his
unparalelled treachery in betraying his Master, and the Lord of life, was justly
left to hange himself; and the rope breaking or slipping he fell down head long,
or with his face down ward, so that he burst asunder in the midst, and all his
bowels gushed out, Math. 27. 5. with Act. 1. 13, left by his sin and punishment
in the last act of

<pb n="431"/>




his life the black character of a Son of perdition. But those that being out of their
right minds, and hurried by an evil Spirit, as persons under a force to be their
own executioners, are not always to be ranked with these.</p>


<p>8. Seeing we have been too fierce against supposed Malefick Witchcraft,
let us take heed we do not on the contrary become too favourable to divining
Witchcraft: And become like Saul who was too zealous against the Gibeonites,
and at last turned to seek after one that had a familiar Spirit, to his own
destruction. Let us not, if we can help it, suffer Satan to set up an ensuring office
for stolen Goods. That after he hath brought the curse of God into the house of
the thief, by tempting him to steal, he may not bring about the curse into the
houses of them from whom the goods were stolen, by alluring them to go to the
god of Ekron to enquire. That men may not give their Souls to the Devil in
exchange, for his restoring to them their goods again, in such a way of
divination. The Lord grant it may be said of New England, as is prophecyed of
Judah, Mic. 5. 12. <hi rend="italic">I will cut off Witchcrafts out of thine
hand, and thou shalt have no more soothsayers</hi>.</p>


<p>9. Another extream we must beware of, is, <hi
rend="italic">viz.</hi> Because our fathers in the beginning times of this
Land, did not see so far into these mysteries of iniquity, as hath been since
discovered, Let us not undervalue the good foundations they laid for God and his
people, and for us in Church and Civil Government. For Paul that eminent
Apostle knew but in part; no wonder then, if our Fathers were imperfect men. In
the purest times in Israel, there were some Clouds of ignorance over-shadowing
of them. Abraham, David, and the best Patriarchs were generally ignorant of the
sin of Polygamy. And although Solomon far exceeded Nehemiah in wisdom; yet
Nehemiah saw farther into the evil of Marrying Outlandish Women, than that
wisest of Kings, and meer fallen men. Neh. 13. 26. Josiah kept the Passeover
more exactly, than David, and all the Reforming Kings of Judah, 2 Chron. 35.
18.</p>


<p>All the godly Judges and Kings of Judah were unacquainted with, and so
negligent of the right observation of the feast of Tabernacles, until it came to
Nehemiahs time: And he understood and revived an ordinance of God, that lay
buried in oblivion, near about a thousand years. Now he that shall

<pb n="432"/>




reject all the good in doctrine and practice, which was maintained, professed and
practiced by so many Godly leaders, because of some few errors found among
them, will be found to fight against God. A dwarf upon a giants shoulders, can
see farther than the giant.</p>


<p>It was a glorious enterprize of the beginners of these Colonies, to leave
their native Country to propagate the Gospel: And a very high pitch of faith, zeal,
and courage that carryed them forth, to follow the Lord into this wilderness, into
a land that was not sown. Then was New England holiness to the Lord, and all
that did devour them, or attempted so to do, did offend, and evil did come upon
them. And the Lord did graciously remember this kindness of their Youth, and
love of their Espousals; In granting them many eminent tokens of his favour; by
his presence with them in his Ordinances, for the Conversion of Souls, and
edifying and comforting the hearts of his Servants: By signal answering their
prayers in times of difficulty: By protecting them from their Enemies; By guiding
of, and providing for them in a Desart. And the Lord will still remember this
their kindness unto their Posterity, unless that by their Apostasy from the Lord,
they vex his Holy Spirit, to turn to be their Enemy: And thereby cut off the
Entail of his Covenant Mercies; which God forbid. <hi rend="italic">Oh that
the Lord may be with us, as he was with our Fathers; and that he may not leave
us, nor forsake us!</hi></p>

<trailer>
<hi rend="italic">
Finis</hi>.
</trailer>
</div2>
<div2 type="notes" id="d21">


<head>Notes</head>

<note id="n431"><seg type="note-symbol">[431].</seg> <p>&ldquo;Black Witches, or Malefick Witches,&rdquo; explains Hale a
little earlier, are those &ldquo;who by their enchantments do call in the Devils
aid, for revenge, to do hurt to the bodies and health of their neighbours, or to
their cattle, goods, and the like. These are the persons commonly called Witches,
and against whom the spirits of men and the laws of men are most bent, for their
prosecution and punishment.&rdquo;</p></note>

<note id="n432"><seg type="note-symbol">[432].</seg> <p><hi rend="italic">I. e.</hi>, &ldquo;whenas&rdquo;:
whereas.</p></note>

<note id="n433"><seg type="note-symbol">[433].</seg> <p>Precedents.</p></note>

<note id="n434"><seg type="note-symbol">[434].</seg> <p>Than.</p></note>

<note id="n435"><seg type="note-symbol">[435].</seg> <p>Sir Edward Coke.</p></note>

<note id="n436"><seg type="note-symbol">[436].</seg> <p>Such is the numbering of the original.</p></note>

<note id="n437"><seg type="note-symbol">[437].</seg> <p>The story of Ahithophel is to be found in II Samuel xv.-xvii.</p></note>

<pb n="433"/>

<p>THE VIRGINIA CASE OF GRACE SHERWOOD, 1706</p>

</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

