<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="BurMons"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>


<TEI.2 id="BurMons">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"Le Monsieur de la Petite Dame</title>
<title type="sort">le monsieur de la petite dame</title>
<author>Burnett, Frances Hodgson</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Charles Keller</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">62</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">BurMons</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475767</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"Le Monsieur de la Petite Dame"</title>
<title>Scribner's Monthly</title>
<title type="sort">le monsieur de la petite dame</title>
<author>Frances Hodgson Burnett</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Frances Hart &amp; Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1877-06">June, 1877</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Scribner's Monthly, Vol. 14, June, 1877, No.2, pp.
224-236.</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic
Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding
line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text
Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed
of the text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in
AusEmma1 for page one of Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1877-06">June, 1877</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
<language id="fre">French</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
<term>Young Readers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-11">November, 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Bryson Clevenger, Jr.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>TEI header, TEI tagging</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">



<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="224"/>
<head>
"LE MONSIEUR DE LA PETITE DAME."<lb/>
by<lb/>
Frances Hodgson Burnett<lb/>
SCRIBNER'S MONTHLY<lb/>
VOL. XIV.<lb/>           JUNE, 1877. <lb/>             NO. 2.<lb/>
pp. 224-236</head>

<p>IT was Madame who first entered the box, and Madame was bright
with youthful bloom, bright with jewels, and, moreover, a beauty.
She was a little creature, with childishly large eyes, a low,
white forehead, reddish-brown hair, and Greek nose and mouth.
</p>
<p>"Clearly," remarked the old lady in the box opposite, "not a
Frenchwoman.  Her youth is too girlish, and she has too petulant
an air of indifference."
</p>
<p>This old lady in the box opposite was that venerable and
somewhat severe aristocrat, Madame de Castro, and having gazed
for a moment or so a little disapprovingly at the new arrival,
she turned her glasses to the young beauty's companion and
uttered an exclamation.
</p>
<p>It was at Monsieur she was looking now.  Monsieur had followed
his wife closely, bearing her fan and bouquet and wrap, and had
silently seated himself a little behind her and in the shadow.
</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">" Ciel!"</hi> cried Madame de Castro, "what an ugly
little man!" </p>
<p>It was not an unnatural exclamation.  Fate had not been so
kind to the individual referred to as she might have been&mdash;in
fact she had been definitely cruel.  He was small of figure,
insignificant, dark, and wore a patient sphynx-like air of
gravity.  He did not seem to speak or move, simply sat in the
shadow holding his wife's belongings, apparently almost entirely
unnoticed by her.
</p>
<p>"I don't know him at all," said Madame de Castro; "though that
is not to be wondered at, since I have exiled myself long enough
to forget and be forgotten by half Paris.  What is his name?"
</p>
<p>The gentleman at her side&mdash;a distinguished-looking old young
man, with a sarcastic smile&mdash;began with the smile, and ended with
a half laugh. </p>
<p>"They call him," he replied, "Le Monsieur de la petite Dame.
His name is Villefort."
</p>
<p>"Le Monsieur de la petite Dame," repeated Madame, testily.
"That is a title of new Paris&mdash;the Paris of your American and
English.  It is villainously ill-bred."
</p>
<p>M. Renard's laugh receded into the smile again, and the smile
became of double significance.
</p>
<p>"True," he acquiesced, "but it is also villainously apropos.
Look for yourself."
</p>
<p>Madame did so, and her next query, after she had dropped her
glass again, was a sharp one.
</p>
<p>"Who is she&mdash;the wife?"
</p>
<p>"She is what you are pleased to call one of our Americans!
You know the class,"&mdash;with a little wave of the hand,&mdash;"rich,
unconventional; comfortable people, who live well and dress well,
and have an incomprehensibly <hi rend="italic"> naive</hi> way of going to
impossible places and doing impossible things by way of
enjoyment.  Our fair friend there, for instance, has probably
been round the world upon several occasions, and is familiar with
a number of places and objects of note fearful to contemplate.
They came here as tourists, and became fascinated with

<pb n="225"/> European life.  The most overwhelming punishment
which could be inflicted upon that excellent woman, the mother,
would be that she should be compelled to return to her New York,
or Philadelphia, or Boston, whichsoever it may be."
</p>
<p>"Humph!" commented Madame.  "But you have not told me the
name." </p>
<p>"Madame Villefort's?  No, not yet.  It was Trent&mdash;Mademoiselle
Bertha Trent."
</p>
<p>"She is not twenty yet," said Madame, in a queer, grumbling
tone.  "What did she marry that man for?"
</p>
<p>"God knows," replied M. Renard, not too devoutly, "Paris does
not." </p>
<p>For some reason best known to herself, Madame de Castro looked
angry.  She was a shrewd old person, with strong whims of her
own, even at seventy.  She quite glared at the pretty American
from under her bushy eyebrows. </p>
<p>"Le Monsieur de la petite Dame!" she fumed.  "I tell you it is
low&mdash;<hi rend="italic"> low</hi> to give a man such names."
</p>
<p>"Oh!" returned Renard, shrugging his shoulders, "we did not
give it to him.  It was an awkward servant who dubbed him so at
first.  She was new to her position, and forgot his name, and
being asked who had arrived, stumbled upon this <hi rend="italic"> bon mot:
`Un monsieur, Madame&mdash;le monsieur de la petite dame</hi>,'&mdash;and,
being repeated and tossed lightly from hand to hand, it has
become at last an established witticism, albeit bandied under
breath." </p>
<p>It was characteristic of the august De Castro that during the
remainder of the evening's entertainment she should occupy
herself more with her neighbors than with the opera.  She aroused
M. Renard to a secret ecstasy of mirth by the sharp steadiness of
her observation of the inmates of the box opposite them.  She
talked about them, too, in a tone not too well modulated,
criticising the beautifully dressed little woman, her hair, her
eyes, her Greek nose and mouth, and, more than all, her
indifferent expression and her manner of leaning upon the edge of
her box and staring at the stage as if she did not care for, and
indeed scarcely saw, what was going on upon it. </p>
<p>"That is the way with your American beauties," she said.
"They have no respect for things.  Their people spoil them&mdash;their
men especially.  They consider themselves privileged to act as
their whims direct.  They have not the gentle timidity of French
women.  What French girl would have the <hi rend="italic"> sang froid</hi> to
sit in one of the best boxes of the Nouvelle Opera and regard,
with an actual air of <hi rend="italic"> ennui</hi>, such a performance as
this.  She does not hear a word that is sung."
</p>
<p>"And we&mdash;do we hear?" bantered M. Renard.
</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">" Pouf!"</hi> cried Madame.  "We!  We are world-dried and
weather-beaten.  We have not a worm-eaten emotion between us.
I am seventy, and you, who are thirty-five, are the older of the
two.  Bah!  At that girl's age I had the heart of a dove."
</p>
<p>"But that is long ago," murmured M. Renard, as if to himself.
It was quite human that he should slightly resent being classed
with an unamiable grenadier of seventy.
</p>
<p>"Yes!" with considerable asperity.  "Fifty years!"  Then, with
harsh voice and withered face melted suddenly into softness quite
<hi rend="italic"> naive, "Mon Dieu!"</hi> she said, "Fifty years since Arsene
whispered into my ear at my first opera, that he saw tears in my
eyes!"
</p>
<p>It was at this instant that there appeared in the Villefort
box a new figure,&mdash;that of a dark, slight young man of graceful
movements,&mdash;in fact, a young man of intensely striking
appearance.  M. Villefort rose to receive him with serious
courtesy, but the pretty American was not so gracious.  Not until
he had seated himself at her side and spoken to her did she turn
her head and permit her eyes simply to rest upon his face.
</p>
<p>M. Renard smiled again.
</p>
<p>"Enter," he remarked in a low tone,&mdash;enter M. Ralph
Edmonstone, the cousin of Madame."
</p>
<p>His companion asked no questions, but he proceeded, returning
to his light and airy tone:
</p>
<p>"M. Ralph Edmonstone is a genius," he said.  "He is an artist,
he is a poet, he is also a writer of subtle prose.  His sonnets
to Euphrasie&mdash;in the day of Euphrasie&mdash;awakened the admiration of
the sternest critics: they were so tender, so full of purest
fire!  Some of the same critics also could scarcely choose
between these and his songs to Aglae in her day, or Camille in
hers.  He is a young man of fine fancies, and possesses the
amiable quality of being invariably passionately in earnest.  As
he was serious in his sentiments yesterday, so he will be to-morrow, so he is to-day."
</p>
<p>"To-day!" echoed Madame de Castro.  "Nonsense!"
</p>
<p>Madame Villefort did not seem to talk much.  It was M. Ralph
Edmondstone who conversed, and this, too, with so much of the
charm of animation that it was pleasurable even to be a mere
looker-on.  One involuntarily strained one's ears to  catch a
VOL.  XIV.&mdash;15.

<pb n="226"/> sentence,&mdash;he was so eagerly absorbed, so full of
rapid, gracefully unconscious and unconventional gesture.
</p>
<p>"I wonder what he is saying?"  Madame de Castro was once
betrayed into exclaiming.
</p>
<p>Something metaphysical, about a poem, or a passage of music,
or a picture,&mdash;or perhaps his soul," returned M. Renard.  "His
soul is his strong point,&mdash;he pets it and wonders at it.  He puts
it through its paces.  And yet, singularly enough, he is never
ridiculous&mdash;only fanciful and <hi rend="italic"> naive</hi>.  It is his soul
which so fascinates women."
</p>
<p>Whether this last was true of other women or not, Madame
Villefort scarcely appeared fascinated.  As she listened, her
eyes still rested upon his eager, mobile face, but with a
peculiar expression,&mdash;an expression of critical attention, and
yet one which somehow detracted from her look of youth, as if she
weighed his words as they fell from his lips and classified them
without any touch of the enthusiasm which stirred within himself.
</p>
<p>Suddenly she rose from her seat and addressed her husband, who
immediately rose also.  Then she spoke to M. Edmondstone, and
without more ado, the three left the box,&mdash;the young beauty, a
little oddly, rather followed than accompanied by her
companions,&mdash;at the recognition of which circumstance Madame de
Castro uttered a series of sharp ejaculations of disapproval.
</p>
<p>"Bah!  Bah!" she cried.  "She is too young for such airs!&mdash;as
if she were Madame l'Imperatrice herself!  Take me to my
carriage.  I am tired also." </p>
<p>Crossing the pavement with M. Renard, they passed the carriage
of the Villeforts.  Before its open door stood M. Villefort and
Edmondstone, and the younger man, with bared head, bent forward
speaking to his cousin. </p>
<p>"If I come to-morrow," he was saying, you will be at home,
Bertha?" </p>
<p>"Yes."
</p>
<p>"Then, good-night,"&mdash;holding out his hand,&mdash;"only I wish so
that you would go to the Aylmers' instead of home.  That <hi rend="italic">
protegee</hi> of Mrs. Aylmer's&mdash;the little singing girl&mdash;would
touch your heart with her voice.  On hearing her, one thinks at
once of some shy wild bird high in a clear sky,&mdash;far enough
above earth to have forgotten to be timid."
</p>
<p>"Yes," came quietly from the darkness within the carriage;
"but I am too tired to care about voices just now.  Good-night,
Ralph!" </p>
<p>M. Renard's reply of "God knows, Paris does not," to Madame de
Castro's query as to why Madame Villefort had married her
husband, contained a strong element of truth, and yet there were
numbers of Parisian-Americans, more especially the young, well-looking and masculine, who at the time the marriage had taken
place had been ready enough with sardonic explanations. </p>
<p>"There are women who are avaricious enough to sell their
souls," they cried; "and the maternal Trent is one of them.  The
girl is only to blame for allowing herself to be bullied into the
match."
</p>
<p>"But the weak place in this argument," said M. Renard, "is
that the people are too rich to be greatly influenced by money.
If there had been a title,&mdash;but there was no title."
</p>
<p>Neither did Bertha Trent comport herself like a cowed
creature.  She took her place in society as Madame Villefort in
such a manner as could give rise to no comment whatever; only one
or two of the restless inquisitive wondered if they had not been
mistaken in her.  She was, as I have said already, a childishly
small and slight creature,&mdash;the kind of woman to touch one with
suggestions of helplessness and lack of will; and yet,
notwithstanding this, a celebrated artist&mdash;a shrewd, worldly-wise
old fellow&mdash;who had painted her portrait, had complained that he
was not satisfied with it because he had not done justice to "the
obstinate endurance in her eye."
</p>
<p>It was to her cousin, Ralph Edmondstone, he had said this with
some degree of testiness, and Edmondstone had smiled and answered
: </p>
<p>"What! have you found that out?  Few people do."
</p>
<p>At the time of the marriage Edmondstone had been in Rome
singeing his wings in the light of the eyes of a certain Marchesa
who was his latest poetic passion.  She was not his first fancy,
nor would she be his last, but she had power enough for the time
being to have satisfied the most exacting of women. </p>
<p>He was at his banker's when he heard the news spoken of as the
latest item from American Paris, and his start and exclamation of
disgust drew forth some cynical after-comment from men who envied
him.
</p>
<p>"Who?" he said, with indiscreet impatience.  "That undersized
sphynx of a Villefort?  Faugh!"
</p>
<p>But insignificant though he might be, it was M. Villefort who
had won, and if he was nothing more, he was at least a faithful

<pb n="227"/> attendant.  Henceforth, those who saw his wife
invariably saw him also,&mdash;driving with her in her carriage,
riding with her courageously if ungracefully, standing or seated
near her in the shadow of her box at the Nouvelle Opera, silent,
impassive, grave, noticeable only through the contrast he
afforded to her girlish beauty and bloom.
</p>
<p>"Always there!" commented a sharp American belle of mature
years, "like an ugly little Conscience."
</p>
<p>Edmondstone's first meeting with his cousin after his return
to Paris was accidental.  He had rather put off visiting her, and
one night, entering a crowded room, he found himself standing
behind a girl's light figure and staring at an abundance of
reddish-brown hair.  When, almost immediately the pretty head to
which this hair belonged turned with a slow, yet involuntary-looking movement toward him, he felt that he became excited
without knowing why.</p>
<p>      "Ah, Bertha!" he exclaimed.</p>
<p>She smiled a little and held out her hand, and he immediately
became conscious of M. Villefort being quite near and regarding
him seriously. </p>
<p>It was the perverseness of fate that he should find in Bertha
Villefort even more than he had once seen in Bertha Trent, and
there had been a time when he had seen a great deal in Bertha
Trent.  In the Trent household he had been a great favorite.  No
social evening or family festivity had seemed complete without
his presence.  The very children had felt that they had a claim
upon his good-humor and his tendency to break forth into
whimsical frolic.  Good Mrs. Trent had been wont to scold him and
gossip with him.  He had read his sonnets and metaphysical
articles to Bertha, and occasionally to the rest; in fact his
footing in the family was a familiar and firmly established one.
But since her marriage Bertha had become a little
incomprehensible, and on that account a little more interesting.
He was sure she had developed, but could not make out in what
direction.  He found occasion to reproach her sometimes with the
changes he found in her. </p>
<p>"There are times when I hardly know you," he would say, "you
are so finely orthodox and well controlled.  It was not so with
you once, Bertha.  Don't&mdash;don't become that terrible thing, a
fine lady, and worse still, a fine lady who is <hi rend="italic">
desillusionee</hi>."
</p>
<p>It baffled him that she never appeared much moved by his
charges.  Certainly she lived the life of a "fine lady,"&mdash;a
brilliant life, a luxurious one, a life full of polite
dissipation.  Once, when in a tenderly fraternal mood, he
reproached her with this also, she laughed at him frankly. </p>
<p>"It is absinthe," she said.  "It is my absinthe at least, and
who does not drink a little absinthe&mdash;of one kind or another?"
</p>
<p>He was sincerely convinced that from this moment he understood
and had the right to pity and watch over her.  He went oftener to
see her.  In her presence he studied her closely, absent he
brooded over her.  He became impatiently intolerant of M.
Villefort and prone to condemn him, he scarcely knew for what.
</p>
<p>"He has no dignity&mdash;no perception," was his mental decision.
"He has not even the delicacy to love her, or he would have the
tenderness to sacrifice his own feelings and leave her to herself
I could do it for a woman I loved."
</p>
<p>But M. Villefort was always there,&mdash;gravely carrying the
shawls, picking up handkerchiefs, and making himself useful. </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">" Imbecile!"</hi> muttered M. Renard under cover of his
smile and his mustache, as he stood near his venerable patroness
the first time she met the Villeforts.
</p>
<p>"Blockhead!" stealthily ejaculated that amiable aristocrat.
But though she looked grimly at M. Villefort, M. Renard was
uncomfortably uncertain that it was he to whom she referred. </p>
<p>"Go and bring them to me," she commanded.  "Go and bring them
to me before some one else engages them.  I want to talk to that
girl." </p>
<p>It was astonishing how agreeable she made herself to her
victims when she had fairly entrapped them.  Bertha hesitated a
little before accepting her offer of a seat at her side, but once
seated she found herself oddly amused.  When Madame de Castro
chose to rake the embers of her seventy years, many a lively coal
discovered itself among the ashes.
</p>
<p>Seeing the two women together, Edmondstone shuddered in
fastidious protest.
</p>
<p>"How could you laugh at that detestable old woman?" he
exclaimed on encountering Bertha later in the evening.  "I wonder
that M. Villefort would permit her to talk to you.  She is a
wicked, cynical creature, who has the hardihood to laugh at her
sins instead of repenting of them. </p>
<p>"Perhaps that is the reason she is so amusing," said Bertha.
</p>
<p>Edmondstone answered her with gentle mournfulness.</p>


<pb n="228"/>
<p>"What!" he said.  "Have you begun to say such things?  You
too, Bertha&mdash;"
</p>
<p>The laugh with which she stopped him was both light and hard.
</p>
<p>"Where is M. Villefort?" she asked.  "I have actually not seen
him for fifteen minutes.  Is it possible that Madame de Castro
has fascinated him into forgetting me?"
</p>
<p>Edmondstone went to his hotel that night in a melancholy mood.
He even lay awake to think what a dreary mistake his cousin's
marriage was.  She had been such a tender and easily swayed
little soul as a girl, and now it really seemed as if she was
hardening into a woman of the world.  In the old times he had
been wont to try his sonnets upon Bertha as a musician tries his
chords upon his most delicate instrument.  Even now he remembered
certain fine, sensitive expressions of hers which had thrilled
him beyond measure. </p>
<p>"How could she marry such a fellow as that&mdash;how could she?" he
groaned.  "What does it mean?  It must mean something."
</p>
<p>He was pale and heavy-eyed when he wandered round to the
Villeforts' the following morning.  M. Villefort was sitting with
Bertha and reading aloud.  He stopped to receive their visitor
punctiliously and inquire after his health.
</p>
<p>"M. Edmondstone cannot have slept well," he remarked. </p>
<p>"I did not sleep at all," Edmondstone answered, "and naturally
have a headache."
</p>
<p>Bertha pointed to a wide lounge of the <hi rend="italic"> pouf</hi> order.
</p>
<p>"Then go to sleep now," she said, "M. Villefort will read.
When I have a headache he often reads me to sleep, and I am
always better on awaking." </p>
<p>Involuntarily Edmondstone half frowned.  Absurdly enough, he
resented in secret this amiability on the part of M. Villefort
toward his own wife.  He was quite prepared to be severe upon the
reading, but was surprised to be compelled to acknowledge that M.
Villefort read wondrously well, and posi-tively with hints of
delicate perception.  His voice was full and yet subtly flexible.
Edmondstone tried to protest against this also, but uselessly.
Finally he was soothed, and from being fretfully wide-awake
suddenly passed into sleep as Bertha had commanded.  How long his
slumber lasted he could not have told all at once.  He found
himself aroused and wide-awake as ever.  His headache had
departed; his every sense seemed to have gained keenness.  M.
Villefort's voice had ceased, and for a few seconds utter dead
silence reigned.  Then he heard the fire crackling, and shortly
afterward a strange, startling sound&mdash;a sharp grasping sob! </p>
<p>The pang which seized upon him was strong indeed.  In one
moment he seemed to learn a thousand things by intuition&mdash;to
comprehend her, himself, the past.  Before he moved he knew that
Villefort was not in the room, and he had caught a side glimpse
of the pretty blue of Bertha's dress. </p>
<p>But he had not imagined the face he saw when he turned his
head to look at her.  She sat in a rigid attitude, leaning
against the high cushioned back of her chair, her hands clasped
above her head.  She stood at the fire with eyes wide and
strained, with the agony of tears unshed, and amid the rush of
all other emotions he was peculiarly conscious of being touched
by the minor one of his recognition of her look of extreme youth--the look which had been wont to touch people in the girl, Bertha
Trent.  He had meant to speak clearly, but his voice was only a
loud whisper when be sprang up, uttering her name.
</p>
<p>"Bertha!  Bertha!  Bertha!" as he flung himself upon his knees
at her side.
</p>
<p>Her answer was an actual cry, and yet it reached no higher
pitch than his own intense whisper.
</p>
<p>"I thought you were asleep?"
</p>
<p>Her hands fell and he caught them.  His sad impassioned face
bowed itself upon her palms.
</p>
<p>"I am awake, Bertha," he groaned.  "I am awake&mdash;at last." </p>
<p>She regarded him with a piteous, pitying glance.  She knew him
with a keener, sadder knowledge than he would ever comprehend;
but she did not underestimate the depth of his misery at this one
overwhelming moment.  He was awake indeed and saw what he had
lost.
</p>
<p>"If you could but have home with me a little longer," he said.
"If I had only not been so shallow and so blind.  If you could
but have borne with me a little longer!"
</p>
<p>"If I could but have home with myself a little longer," she
answered.  "If I could but have home a little longer with my poor
base pride!  Because I suffered myself, I have made another
suffer too."
</p>
<p>He knew she spoke of M. Villefort, and the thought jarred upon
him. </p>
<p>"He does not suffer," he said.  "He is not of the fiber to
feel pain." </p>

<pb n="229"/>
<p>And he wondered why she shrank from him a little, and answered
with a sad bitterness:
</p>
<p>"Are you sure?  You did not know that I&mdash;"
</p>
<p>"Forgive me," he said brokenly, the face he lifted, haggard
with his unhappiness.  "Forgive me, for I have lost so much."
</p>
<p>She wasted few words and no tears.  The force and suddenness
of his emotion and her own had overborne her into this strange
unmeant confession; but her mood was unlike his,&mdash;it was merely
receptive.  She listened to his unavailing regrets, but told him
little of her own past.
</p>
<p>"It does not matter," she said drearily.
</p>
<p>It is all over.  Let it rest.  The pain of to-day and to-morrow is enough for us.  We have borne yesterday; why should we
want it back again?" </p>
<p>And when they parted she said only one thing of the future:
</p>
<p>"There is no need that we should talk.  There is nothing for
us beyond this point.  We can only go back.  We must try to
forget&mdash;and be satisfied with our absinthe."
</p>
<p>Instead of returning to his hotel, Edmondstone found his way
to the Champs Elysees, and finally to the Bois.  He was too
wretched to have any purpose in his wanderings.  He walked
rapidly, looking straight before him and seeing nobody.  He
scarcely understood his own fierce emotions.  Hitherto his
fancies had brought him a vague rapture; now he experienced
absolute anguish.  Every past experience had become trivial.
What happiness is so keen as one's briefest pain?  As he walked
he lived again the days he had thrown away.  He remembered a
thousand old, yet new, phases of Bertha's girlhood.  He thought
of times when she had touched or irritated or pleased him.  When
he had left Paris for Rome she had not bidden him good-bye.
Jenny, her younger sister, had told him that she was not well.
</p>
<p>"If I had seen her then," he cried inwardly, "I might have
read her heart&mdash;and my own."
</p>
<p>M. Renard, riding a very tall horse in the Bois, passed him
and raised his eyebrows at the sight of his pallor and his fagged
yet excited look. </p>
<p>"There will be a new sonnet," he said to himself.  "A sonnet
to Despair or Melancholy or Loss."
</p>
<p>Afterward, when society became a little restive and eager, M.
Renard looked on with sardonic interest.
</p>
<p>"That happy man, M. Villefort," he said to Madame de Castro,
"is a good soul&mdash;a good soul.  He has no small jealous follies,"
and his smile was scarcely a pleasant thing to see.

</p>
<p>"There is nothing for us beyond this past," Bertha had said,
and Edmonstone had agreed with her hopelessly.
</p>
<p>But he could not quite break away.  Sometime for a week the
Villeforts missed him, and then again they saw him every day.  He
spent his mornings with them, joined them in their drives, at
their opera-box or at the entertainments of their friends.  He
also fell into his old place in the Trent household, and listened
with a vague effort at interest to Mrs. Trent's maternal gossip
about the boys' college expenses, Bertha's household and Jenny's
approaching social <hi rend="italic"> debut</hi>.  He was continually full of
a feverish longing to hear of Bertha,&mdash;to hear her name spoken,
her ingoings and outcomings discussed, her looks, her belongings.
</p>
<p>"The fact is," said Mrs. Trent, as the winter advanced, "I am
anxious about Bertha.  She does not look strong.  I don't know
why I have not seen it before, but all at once I found out
yesterday that she is really thin.  She was always slight and
even a little fragile, but now she is actually thin.  One can see
the little bones in her wrists and fingers.  Her rings and her
bracelets slip about quite loosely."
</p>
<p>"And talking of being thin, mother," cried Jenny, who was a
frank, bright sixteen-year-old, "Look at cousin Ralph himself.
He has little hollows in his cheeks, and his eyes are as much too
big as Bertha's.  Is the sword wearing out the scabbard, Ralph?
That is what they always say about geniuses, you know."
</p>
<p>"Ralph has not looked well for some time," said Mrs. Trent.
"As for Bertha, I think I shall scold her a little, and M.
Villefort too.  She has been living too exciting a life.  She is
out continually.  She must stay at home more and rest.  It is
rest she needs."
</p>
<p>"If you tell Arthur that Bertha looks ill&mdash;" began Jenny.
</p>
<p>Edmonstone turned toward her sharply.
</p>
<p>"Arthur!" he repeated.  "Who is Arthur?"
</p>
<p>Mrs. Trent answered with a comfortable laugh.
</p>
<p>"It is M. Villefort's name," she said, though none of us call
him Arthur but Jenny.  Jenny and he are great friends."
</p>

<pb n="230"/>
<p>"I like him better than any one else," said Jenny stoutly.
"And I wish to set a good example to Bertha, who never calls him
anything but M. Villefort, which is absurd.  Just as if they had
been introduced to each other about a week ago."
</p>
<p>"I always hear him address her as Madame Villefort," reflected
Edmondstone, somewhat gloomily.
</p>
<p>"Oh yes!" answered Jenny, "that is his French way of studying
her fancies.  He would consider it taking an unpardonable liberty
to call her `Bertha,' since she only favors him with `M.
Villefort.'  I said to him only the other day, `Arthur, you are
the oddest couple!  You're so grand and well-behaved, I cannot
imagine you scolding Bertha a little, and I have never seen you
kiss her since you were married.'  I was half frightened after I
had said it.  He started as if he had been shot, and turned as
pale as death.  I really felt as If I had done something
frightfully improper."
</p>
<p>"The French are so different from the Americans," said Mrs.
Trent, "particularly those of M. Villefort's class.  They are
beautifully punctilious, but I don't call it quite comfortable,
you know." </p>
<p>Her mother was not the only person who noticed a change in
Bertha Villefort.  Before long it was a change so marked that all
who saw her observed it.  She had become painfully frail and
slight.  Her face looked too finely cut, her eyes had shadowy
hollows under them, and were always bright with a feverish
excitement.
</p>
<p>"What is the matter with your wife?" demanded Madame de Castro
of M. Villefort.  Since their first meeting she had never
loosened her hold upon the husband and wife, and had particularly
cultivated Bertha.
</p>
<p>There was no change in the expression of M. Villefort; but he
was strangely pallid as he made his reply.
</p>
<p>"It is impossible for me to explain, Madame."
</p>
<p>"She is absolutely attenuated," cried Madame.  "She is like a
spirit.  Take her to the country&mdash;to Normandy&mdash;to the sea&mdash;
somewhere!  She will die if there is not a change.  At twenty,
one should be as plump as a young capon." </p>
<p>A few days after this, Jenny Trent ran in upon Bertha as she
lay upon a lounge, holding an open book, but with closed eyes.
She had come to spend the morning, she announced.  She wanted to
talk&mdash;about people, about her dress, about her first ball which
was to come off shortly.
      "And Arthur says&mdash;" she began.
</p>
<p>Bertha turned her head almost as Edmondstone had done.
"Arthur," she repeated.
</p>
<p>For the second time Jenny felt a little embarrassed.  "I mean
M. Villefort," she said, hesitantly.
</p>
<p>She quite forgot what she had been going to say, and for a
moment or so regarded the fire quite gravely.  But naturally this
could not last long.  She soon began to talk again, and it was
not many minutes before she found M. Villefort in her path once
more.
</p>
<p>"I never thought I could like a Frenchman so much," she said
in all enthusiastic good faith.  "At first, you know," with an
apologetic half laugh, "I wondered why you had not taken an
American instead, when there were so many to choose from, but now
I understand it.  What beautiful tender things he can say,
Bertha, and yet not seem in the least sentimental.  Everything
comes so simply right from the bottom of his heart.  Just think
what he said to me yesterday when he brought me those flowers.
He helps me with mine, and it is odd how things will cheer up and
grow for him.  I said to him, `Arthur, how is it that no flower
ever fails you?' and he answered in the gentlest quiet way,
`Perhaps because I never fail them.  Flowers are like people,&mdash;
one must love and be true to them, not only to-day and to-morrow,
but every day&mdash;every hour&mdash;always.'  And he says such things so
often.  That is why I am so fond of him."
</p>
<p>As she received no reply, she turned toward the lounge.
Bertha lay upon it motionless and silent,&mdash;only a large tear
trembled on her cheek.  Jenny sprung up, shocked and checked, and
went to her.
</p>
<p>"Oh, Bertha!" she cried, "how thoughtless I am to tire you so,
you poor little soul!  Is it true that you are so weak as all
that?  I heard mamma and Arthur talking about it, but I scarcely
believed it.  They said you must go to Normandy and be nursed."
</p>
<p>"I don't want to go to Normandy," said Bertha.  "I&mdash;I am too
tired.  I only want to lie still and rest.  I have been out too
much." </p>
<p>Her voice, however, was so softly weak that in the most
natural manner Jenny was subdued into shedding a few tears also,
and kissed her quite fervently.
</p>
<p>"Oh, Bertha!" she said, "you must do anything&mdash;anything that
will make you well&mdash;if it is only for Arthur's sake.  He loves
you so&mdash;so terribly."

<pb n="231"/>
      Whereupon Bertha laughed a little hysterically.
</p>
<p>"Does he," she said, "love me so `terribly?'  Poor M.
Villefort!" </p>
<p>She did not go to Normandy, however, and still went into
society, though not as much as had been her habit.  When she
spent her evenings at home, some of her own family generally
spent them with her, and M. Villefort or Edmondstone read aloud
or talked.
</p>
<p>In fact, Edmondstone came oftener than ever.  His anxiety and
unhappiness grew upon him and made him moody, irritable and
morbid. </p>
<p>One night, when M. Villefort had left them alone together for
a short time, he sprang from his chair and came to her couch,
shaken with suppressed emotion.
</p>
<p>"That man is killing you!" he exclaimed.  "You are dying by
inches!  I cannot bear it!"
</p>
<p>"It is not he who is killing me," she answered; and then M.
Villefort returned to the room with the book he had been in
search of. </p>
<p>In this case Edmondstone's passion took new phases.  He wrote
no sonnets, painted no pictures.  He neglected his work, and
spent his idle hours in rambling here and there in a gloomy,
unsociable fashion. </p>
<p>"He looks," said M. Renard, "as if his soul had been playing
him some evil trick."
</p>
<p>He had at first complained that Bertha had taken a capricious
fancy to Madame de Castro, but in course of time he found his way
to the old woman's <hi rend="italic"> salon</hi> too, though it must be
confessed that Madame herself never showed him any great favor.
But this he did not care for.  He only cared to sit in the same
room with Bertha, and watch her every movement with a miserable
tenderness.
</p>
<p>One night, after regarding him cynically for some time, Madame
broke out to Bertha with small ceremony.
</p>
<p>"What a fool that young man is!" she exclaimed.  "He sits and
fairly devours you with his eyes.  It is bad taste to show such
an insane passion for a married woman."
</p>
<p>It seemed as if Bertha lost at once her breath and every drop
of blood in her body, for she had neither breath nor color when
she turned and looked Madame de Castro in the face.
</p>
<p>"Madame," she said, "if you repeat that to me, you will never
see me again&mdash;never!"
</p>
<p>Upon which Madame snapped her up with some anger at being so
rebuked for her frankness.
</p>
<p>"Then it is worse than I thought," she said.
</p>
<p>It was weeks before she saw her young friend again.  Indeed,
it required some clever diplomacy to heal the breach made, and
even in her most amusing and affectionate moods, she often felt
afterward that she was treated with a reserve which held her at
arm's length.
</p>
<p>By the time the horse-chestnuts bloomed pink and white on the
Avenue des Champs Elysees, there were few people in the Trent and
Villefort circles who had not their opinions on the subject of
Madame Villefort and her cousin. </p>
<p>There was a mixture of French and American gossip and comment,
frank satire, or secret remark.  But to her credit be it spoken,
Madame de Castro held grim silence, and checked a rumor
occasionally with such amiable ferocity as was not without its
good effect.
</p>
<p>The pink and white blossoms were already beginning to strew
themselves at the feet of the pedestrians, when one morning M.
Villefort presented himself to Madame and discovered her sitting
alone in the strangest of moods. </p>
<p>"I thought I might have the pleasure of driving home with
Madame Villefort.  My servant informed me that I should find her
here."       Madame de Castro pointed to a chair.
      "Sit down," she commanded.
</p>
<p>M. Villefort obeyed her in some secret but well-concealed
amazement.  He saw that she was under the influence of some
unusual excitement.  Her false front was pushed fantastically
away, her rouge and powder were rubbed off in patches, her face
looked set and hard.  Her first words were abominably blunt. </p>
<p>"M. Villefort," she said, "do you know what your acquaintances
call you?"
</p>
<p>A deep red rose slowly to his face, but he did not answer.
</p>
<p>"Do you know that you are designated by them by an absurd
title&mdash;that they call you in ridicule `Le Monsieur de la petite
Dame?'  Do you know that?"
</p>
<p>His look was incomprehensible, but he bowed gravely. </p>
<p>"Madame," he answered, "since others have heard the title so
often, it is but natural that I myself should have heard it more
than once." </p>

<pb n="232"/>
<p>She regarded him in angry amazement.  She was even roused to
rapping upon the floor with her gold-headed cane.
</p>
<p>"Does it not affect you?" she cried.  "Does it not move you to
indignation?"
</p>
<p>"That, Madame," he replied, "can only be my affair.  My
friends will allow me my emotions at least."
</p>
<p>Then she left her chair and began to walk up and down,
striking the carpet hard with her cane at every step.
</p>
<p>"You are a strange man," she remarked.
</p>
<p>Suddenly, however, when just on the point of starting upon a
fresh tour, she wheeled about and addressed him sharply.
</p>
<p>"I respect you," she said; "and because I respect you, I will
do you a good turn."
</p>
<p>She made no pretense at endeavoring to soften the blow she was
about to bestow.  She drew forth from her dress a letter, the
mere sight of which seemed to goad her to a mysterious
excitement.
</p>
<p>"See," she cried; "it was M. Ralph Edmondstone who wrote
this,&mdash;it was to Madame Villefort it was written.  It means ruin
and dishonor.  I offer it to you to read."
</p>
<p>M. Villefort rose and laid his hand upon his chair to steady
himself. </p>
<p>"Madame," he answered, "I will not touch it."
</p>
<p>She struck herself upon her withered breast.
</p>
<p>"Behold me!" she said.  <hi rend="italic">" Me!</hi> I am seventy years
old!  Good God! seventy!  I am a bad old woman, and it is said I
do not repent of my sins.  I, too, have been a beautiful young
girl.  I, too, had my first lover.  I, too, married a man who had
not won my heart.  It does not matter that the husband was worthy
and the lover was not,&mdash;one learns that too late.  My fate was
what your wife's will be if you will not sacrifice your pride and
save her."
</p>
<p>"Pride!" he echoed in a little hollow voice.  "My pride,
Madame!"       She went on without noticing him:
</p>
<p>"They have been here this morning&mdash;both of them.  He followed
her, as he always does.  He had a desperate look which warned me.
Afterward I found the note upon the floor.  Now will you read
it?"
</p>
<p>"Good God!" he cried, as he fell into his chair again, his
brow sinking into his bands.
</p>
<p>"I have read it," said Madame, with a tragic gesture, "and I
choose to place one stumbling-block in the path that would lead
her to an old age like mine.  I do not like your Americans; but I
have sometimes seen in her girl's face a proud, heroic endurance
of the misery she has brought upon herself, and it has moved me.
And this letter&mdash;you should read it, to see how such a man can
plead.  It is a passionate cry of despair&mdash;it is a poem in
itself.  I, myself, read it with sobs in my throat and tears in
my eyes.  `If you love me!&mdash;If you have ever loved me!' he cries,
`for God's sake!&mdash;for love's sake!&mdash;if there is love on earth&mdash;if
there is a God in heaven, you will not let me implore you&mdash;in
vain!'  And his prayer is that she will leave Paris with him to-night&mdash;to-night!  There!  Monsieur, I have done.  Behold the
letter!  Take it or leave it, as you please."  And she flung it
upon the floor at his feet.
</p>
<p>She paused a moment, wondering what he would do.
</p>
<p>He bent down and picked the letter up.
      "I will take it," he said.
</p>
<p>All at once he had become calm, and when he rose and uttered
his last words to her, there was upon his face a faint smile.
</p>
<p>"I, too," he said,&mdash;"I, too, Madame, suffer from a mad and
hopeless passion, and thus can comprehend the bitterness of M.
Edmondstone's pangs.  I, too, would implore in the name of love
and God,&mdash;if I might,&mdash;but I may not."  And so he took his
departure.
</p>
<p>Until evening Bertha did not see him.  The afternoon she spent
alone and in writing letters, and having completed and sealed the
last, she went to her couch and tried to sleep.  One entering the
room, as she lay upon the violet cushions, her hands at her
sides, her eyes closed, might well have been shocked.  Her
spotless pallor, the fine sharpness of her face, the shadows
under her eyes, her motionlessness, would have excused the
momentary feeling.  But she was up and dressed for dinner when M.
Villefort presented himself.  Spring though it was, she was
attired in a high, close dress of black velvet, and he found her
almost cowering over the open fire-place.  Strangely enough, too,
she fancied that when she looked up at him she saw him shiver, as
if he were struck with a slight chill also.
</p>
<p>"You should not wear that," he said, with a half smile at her
gown.       "Why?" she asked.
</p>
<p>"It makes you so white&mdash;so much like a too early lily.  But&mdash;
but perhaps you thought of going out?"
      "No," she answered; "not to-night."
      He came quite close to her.
</p>
<p>"If you are not too greatly fatigued," he

<pb n="233"/> said, "it would give me happiness to take you with me
on my errand to your mother's house.  I must carry there my
little birthday gift to your sister," smiling again.
</p>
<p>An expression of embarrassment showed itself upon her face.
</p>
<p>"Oh!" she exclaimed, "to think that I had forgotten it!  She
will feel as if I did not care for her at all."
      She seemed for the moment quite unhappy.
      "Let me see what you have chosen."
</p>
<p>He drew from his pocket a case and opened it.
</p>
<p>"Oh!" she cried, "how pretty and how suitable for a girl."
</p>
<p>They were the prettiest, most airy set of pearls imaginable.
</p>
<p>She sat and looked at them for a few seconds thoughtfully, and
then handed them back.
</p>
<p>"You are very good, and Jenny will be in ecstasies," she said.
</p>
<p>"It is a happiness to me to give her pleasure," he returned.
"I feel great tenderness for her.  She is not like the young
girls I have known.  Her innocence is of a frank and noble
quality, which is better than ignorance.  One could not bear that
the slightest shadow of sin or pain should fall upon her.  The
atmosphere surrounding her is so bright with pure happiness and
the courage of youth."
      Involuntarily he held out his hand.
</p>
<p>"Will you&mdash;" he began.  His voice fell and broke.  "Will you
go with me?" he ended.
      He saw that she was troubled.
      "Now?" she faltered.
      "Yes&mdash;now."
</p>
<p>There was a peculiar pause,&mdash;a moment, as it seemed to him, of
breathless silence.  This silence she broke by her rising slowly
from her seat.
</p>
<p>"Yes," she responded, "I will go.  Why should I not?"
*      *      *      *      *      *      *

</p>
<p>It was midnight when they left the Trents', and Jenny stood
upon the threshold, a bright figure in a setting of brightness,
and kissed her hand to them as they went down the steps.
</p>
<p>"I hope you will be better to-morrow, Arthur," she said.
He turned quickly to look up at her.
      "I?"
</p>
<p>"Yes.  You look so tired.  I might say haggard, if it was
polite." </p>
<p>"It would not be polite," said Bertha, "so don't say it.
Good-night, Jenny!"
</p>
<p>But when they were seated in the carriage she glanced at her
husband's face.
</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">" Are</hi> you unwell?" she asked.
</p>
<p>He passed his hand quickly across his forehead.
</p>
<p>"A little fatigued," he replied.  "It is nothing.  To-morrow&mdash;
to-morrow it will be all over."
</p>
<p>And so silence fell upon them.
</p>
<p>As they entered the drawing-room a clock chimed the half hour.
</p>
<p>"So late as that!" exclaimed Bertha, and sank into a chair
with a faint laugh.  "Why, to-day is over," she said.  It is to-morrow." </p>
<p>M. Villefort had approached a side table.  Upon it lay a
peculiar-looking oblong box.
      "Ah," he said, softly, "they have arrived."
      "What are they?" Bertha asked.
</p>
<p>He was bending over the box to open it, and did not turn
toward her, as he replied:
</p>
<p>It is a gift for a young friend of mine,&mdash;an odd one,&mdash;a brace
of pistols.  He has before him a long journey in the East, and he
is young enough to have a fancy for firearms."
</p>
<p>He was still examining the weapons when Bertha crossed the
room on her way upstairs, and she paused an instant to look at
them.
</p>
<p>"They are very handsome," she said.  "One could almost wear
them as ornaments."
</p>
<p>"But they would have too threatening a look," he answered,
lightly. </p>
<p>As he raised his eyes they met hers.  She half started
backward, moved by a new sense of the haggardness of his face.
</p>
<p>"You <hi rend="italic"> are</hi> ill!" she exclaimed.  "You are as
colorless as marble."
</p>
<p>"And you, too," he returned, still with the same tender
lightness.  "Let us hope that our `to-morrow' will find us both
better, and you say it is to-morrow now.  Good-night!"
</p>
<p>She went away without saying more.  Weary as she was, she knew
there was no sleep for her, and after dismissing her maid, she
threw herself upon the lounge before the bedroom fire and lay
there.  To-night she felt as if her life had reached its climax.
She burst into a passion of tears. </p>
<p>"Jenny!  Jenny!" she cried, "how I envy&mdash;how I envy you!" </p>
<p>The recollection of Jenny shining in her pretty gala dress,
and delighting in her birthday presents, and everybody else's
pride and affection, filled her with a morbid misery and terror.
She covered her face with her hands as she thought of it.
</p>
<p>"Once," she panted, "as I looked at her

<pb n="234"/> to-night for a moment, I almost hated her.  Am I so
bad as that?&mdash;am I?" </p>
<p>Scarcely two seconds afterward she had sprung to her feet and
was standing by the side of her couch, her heart beating with a
rapid throb of fright, her limbs trembling.  A strange sound had
fallen suddenly upon the perfect silence of the night&mdash;a sound
loud, hard and sharp&mdash;the report of a pistol!  What dread seized
her she knew not.  She was across the room and had wrenched the
door open in an instant, then with flying feet down the corridor
and the staircase.  But half way down the stairs she began to cry
out aloud, "Arthur!  Arthur!" not conscious of her own voice&mdash;
"Arthur, what is it?"  The door of the drawing-room flew open
before the fierce stroke of her palm. </p>
<p>M. Villefort stood where she had left him; but while his left
hand supported his weight against the table, his right was thrust
into his breast.  One of the pistols lay at his feet.
</p>
<p>She thought it was Death's self that confronted her in his
face, but he spoke to her, trying faintly to smile.
</p>
<p>"Do not come in," he said, "I have met with&mdash;an accident.  It
is nothing.  Do not come in.  A servant&mdash;"
</p>
<p>His last recollection was of her white face and white
draperies as he fell and somehow, dizzy, sick and faint as he
was, he seemed to hear her calling out, in a voice strangely like
Jenny's, "Arthur!  Arthur!" </p>
<p>In less than half an hour the whole house was astir.  Upstairs
physicians were with the wounded man, down-stairs Mrs. Trent
talked and wept over her daughter, after the manner of all good
women.  She was fairly terrified by Bertha's strange shudderings,
quick, strained breath, and dilated eyes.  She felt as if she
could not reach her&mdash;as if she hardly made herself heard.
</p>
<p>"You must calm yourself, Bertha," she would say.  "Try to calm
yourself.  We must hope for the best.  Oh! how could it have
happened!" </p>
<p>It was in the midst of this that a servant entered with a
letter, which he handed to his mistress.  The envelope bore upon
it nothing but her own name.
</p>
<p>She looked at it with a bewildered expression.
      "For me?" she said.
</p>
<p>"It fell from Monsieur's pocket as we carried him upstairs,"
replied the man.
</p>
<p>"Don't mind it now, Bertha," said her mother.  "Ah! poor M.
Villefort!" </p>
<p>But Bertha opened it mechanically and was reading it.

</p>
<p>At first it seemed as if it must have been written in a
language she did not understand; but after the first few
sentences a change appeared.  Her breath came and went more
quickly than before&mdash;a kind of horror grew in her eyes.  At the
last she uttered a low, struggling cry.  The paper was crushed in
her hand, she cast one glance around the room as if in
bewildering search for refuge, and flung herself upon her
mother's breast.
</p>
<p>"Save me, mother!" she said.  "Help me!  If he dies now, I
shall go mad!"
</p>
<p>Afterward, in telling her story at home, good Mrs. Trent
almost broke down.
</p>
<p>"Oh, Jenny!" she said.  "Just to think of the poor fellow's
having had it in his pocket then!  Of course I did not see it,
but one can fancy that it was something kind and tender&mdash;perhaps
some little surprise he had planned for her.  It seemed as if she
could not bear it.
</p>
<p>M. Villefort's accident was the subject of discussion for many
days.  He had purchased a wonderful pair of pistols as a gift for
a young friend.  How it had happened that one had been loaded
none knew; it was just possible that he had been seized with the
whim to load it himself&mdash;at all events, it had gone off in his
hands.  An inch&mdash;nay, half an inch&mdash;to the right and Madame
Villefort, who flew down-stairs at the sound of the report, would
only have found a dead man at her feet.
</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">" Ma foi!"</hi> said M. Renard, repressing his smile;
"this is difficult for Monsieur, but it may leave `<hi rend="italic"> la
petite Dame</hi>' at liberty."
</p>
<p>Madame de Castro flew at him with flashing eyes.
</p>
<p>"Silence!" she said, "if you would not have me strike you with
my cane."  And she looked as if she were capable of doing it.
</p>
<p>Upon his sick bed M. Villefort was continually haunted by an
apparition&mdash;an apparition of a white face and white draperies,
such as he had seen as he fell.  Sometimes it was here, sometimes
there, sometimes near him, and sometimes indistinct and far away.
Sometimes he called out to it and tried to extend his arms; again
he lay and watched it murmuring gentle words, and smiling
mournfully.
</p>
<p>Mrs. Trent and the doctor were in despair.  Madame Villefort
obstinately refused to be forced from her husband's room.  There
were times when they thought she might sink and die there
herself.  She would not even leave it when they obliged her to
sleep.  Having been slight and frail from ill health

<pb n="235"/> before, she became absolutely attenuated.  Soon all
her beauty would be gone.
</p>
<p>"Do you know," said Mrs. Trent to her husband, "I have found
out that she always carries that letter in her breast?  I see her
put her hand to it in the strangest way a dozen times a day."
</p>
<p>One night, awakening from a long sleep to a clearer mental
consciousness than usual, M. Villefort found his apparition
standing over him. </p>
<p>She stood with one hand clinched upon her breast, and she
spoke to him. </p>
<p>"Arthur!" she said,&mdash;"Arthur, do you know me?"
      He answered her, "Yes."
</p>
<p>She slipped down upon her knees, and held up in her hand a
letter crushed and broken.
</p>
<p>"Try to keep your mind clear while you listen to me," she
implored.  "Try&mdash;try! I must tell you, or I shall die.  I am not
the bad woman you think me.  I never had read it&mdash;I had not seen
it.  I think he must have been mad.  Once I loved him, but he
killed my love himself.  I could not have been bad like that.
Jenny!&mdash;mother!&mdash;Arthur! believe me! believe me!" </p>
<p>In this supreme moment of her anguish and shame she forgot all
else.  She stretched forth her hands, panting.
</p>
<p>"Believe me!  It is true!  Try to understand!  Some one is
coming!  Say one word before it is too late!"
</p>
<p>"I understand," he whispered, "and I believe."  He made a weak
effort to touch her hand, but failed.  He thought that perhaps it
was the chill and numbness of death which stole over him and held
him bound.  When the nurse, whose footsteps they had heard,
entered, she found him lying with glazed eyes, and Madame
Villefort fallen in a swoon at the bedside.
</p>
<p>And yet, from this time forward the outside world began to
hear that his case was not so hopeless after all.
</p>
<p>"Villefort will possibly recover," it was said at first; then,
"Villefort improves, it seems;" and, at last, "Villefort is out
of danger.  Who would have thought it?"
</p>
<p>Nobody, however, could say that Madame had kept pace with her
husband.  When Monsieur was sufficiently strong to travel, and
was advised to do so, there were grave doubts as to the propriety
of his wife's accompanying him.       But she would not listen to
those doubts.
</p>
<p>"I will not stay in Paris," she said to her mother.  "I want
to be free from it, and Jenny has promised to go with us."
</p>
<p>They were to go into Normandy, and the day before their
departure Ralph Edmondstone came to bid them good-bye.
</p>
<p>Of the three he was by far the most haggard figure, and when
Bertha came down to meet him in the empty drawing-room, he became
a wretched figure with a broken, hopeless air.  For a few seconds
Bertha did not speak, but stood a pace or two away looking at
him.  It seemed, in truth, as she waited there in her dark nun-like dress, that nearly all her beauty had left her.  There
remained only her large sad eyes and pretty hair, and the
touching look of extreme youth.  In her hand she held the crushed
letter. </p>
<p>"See!" she said at last, holding this out to him, "I am not so
bad&mdash;so bad as that."
</p>
<p>He caught it from her hand and tore it into fragments.  He was
stabbed through and through with shame and remorse.  After all,
his love had been strong enough here, and his comprehension keen
enough to have made him repent in the dust of the earth, in his
first calm hour, the insult he had put upon her.
</p>
<p>"Forgive me!" he cried; "oh, forgive me! "
</p>
<p>The few steps between them might have been a myriad miles.
</p>
<p>"I did love you&mdash;long ago," she said; "but you never thought
of me.  You did not understand me then&mdash;nor afterward.  All this
winter my love has been dying a hard death.  You tried to keep it
alive, but&mdash;you did not understand.  You only humiliated and
tortured me.  And I knew that if I had loved you more, you would
have loved me less.  See!" holding up her thin hand, "I have been
worn out in the struggle between my unhappiness and remorse and
you."
</p>
<p>"You do not know what love is!" he burst forth, stung into
swift resentment.
      A quick sob broke from her.
</p>
<p>"Yes, I do," she answered.  "I&mdash;I have seen it."
</p>
<p>"You mean M. Villefort!" he cried in desperate jealous misery.
"You think that he &mdash;"
</p>
<p>She pointed to the scattered fragments of the letter. </p>
<p>"He had that in his pocket when he fell," she said.  "He
thought that I had read it.  If I had been your wife, and you had
thought so, would you have thought that I was worth trying to
save&mdash;as he tried to save me?" </p>
<p>"What?" he exclaimed, shamefacedly.  "Has he seen it?"</p>

<pb n="236"/>
<p>"Yes," she answered, with another sob, which might have been
an echo of the first.  "And that is the worst of all."
</p>
<p>There was a pause, during which he looked down at the floor,
and even trembled a little.
</p>
<p>"I have done you more wrong than I thought," he said. </p>
<p>"Yes," she replied; "a thousand-fold more."
</p>
<p>It seemed as if there might have been more to say, but it was
not said. </p>
<p>In a little while he roused himself with an effort.
</p>
<p>"I am not a villain," he said.  "I can do one thing.  I can go
to Villefort&mdash;if you care."
</p>
<p>She did not speak.  So he moved slowly away until he reached
the door.  With his hand upon the handle he turned and looked
back at her. </p>
<p>"Oh! it is good-bye&mdash;good-bye!" he almost groaned.
      "Yes."
</p>
<p>He could not help it&mdash;few men could have done so.  His
expression was almost fierce as he spoke his next words.
</p>
<p>"And you will love him&mdash;yes, you will love <hi rend="italic"> him</hi>."
</p>
<p>"No," she answered, with bitter pain.  "I am not worthy."
   *      *      *      *      *      *      *

</p>
<p>It was a year or more before the Villeforts were seen in Paris
again, and Jenny enjoyed her wanderings with them wondrously.  In
fact, she was the leading member of the party.  She took them
where she chose,&mdash;to queer places, to ugly places, to impossible
places, but never from first to last to any place where there
were not, or at least had not been, Americans as absurdly erratic
as themselves.
</p>
<p>The winter before their return they were at Genoa among other
places; and it was at Genoa that one morning, on opening a
drawer, Bertha came upon an oblong box, the sight of which made
her start backward and put her hand to her beating side.  M.
Villefort approached her hurriedly.  An instant later, however,
he started also and shut the drawer.
</p>
<p>"Come away," he said, taking her hand gently.  "Do not remain
here." </p>
<p>But he was pale, too, and his hand was unsteady.  He led her
to the window and made her sit down.
</p>
<p>"Pardon me," he said.  "I should not have left them there."
</p>
<p>"You did not send them to your friend," she faltered. </p>
<p>"No."
</p>
<p>He stood for a moment or so, and looked out of the window at
the blue sea which melted into the blue sky, at the blue sky
which bent itself into the blue sea, at the white sails flecking
the deep azure, at the waves hurrying in to break upon the sand.
</p>
<p>"That&mdash;" he said at length, tremulously, and with pale lips,
"that was false."
</p>
<p>"Was false!" she echoed.
</p>
<p>"Yes," hoarsely, "it was false.  There was no such friend.  It
was a lie&mdash;they were meant only for myself."
</p>
<p>She uttered a low cry of anguish and dread.
</p>
<p>"Ah, <hi rend="italic"> mon Dieu!"</hi> he said.  "You could not know.  I
understood all, and had been silent.  I was nothing&mdash;a jest&mdash;`
<hi rend="italic">le monsieur de la petite dame</hi>,' as they said,&mdash;only that.
I swore that I would save you.  When I bade you adieu that night,
I thought it was my last farewell.  There was no accident.  Yes&mdash;
there was one.  I did not die, as I had intended.  My hand was
not steady enough.   And since then&mdash;"
</p>
<p>She rose up, crying out to him as she had done on that
terrible night. </p>
<p>"Arthur!"  Arthur!"
</p>
<p>He came closer to her.
</p>
<p>"Is it true," he said,&mdash;"is it true that my prayers have not
been in vain?  Is it true that at last&mdash;at last, you have
learned&mdash;have learned&mdash;" </p>
<p>She stretched forth her arms to him.</p>
<p>"It is true!" she cried.  "Yes, it is true!&mdash;it is true!</p>


<lg type="stanza">
                        <head>WITH THEE</head>
<l>I'D rather walk through shower with thee,</l>
<l>Than with another when the air</l>
<l>Is soft with summer, and as fair</l>
<l>The heavens above us as a sea</l>
<l>Of dim, unfathomed sapphire, where</l>
<l>Slow drifting on a liquid sky,</l>
<l>The white-sailed ships of God float by.</l>
</lg>
<lg type="stanza">
<l>Sweeter in storm to be with thee,</l>
<l>Dark waters 'round us, and the roar</l>
<l>Of breakers on an unseen shore</l>
<l>Resounding louder on the lee,&mdash;</l>
<l>Than with another, sailing o'er</l>
<l>A rippling lake, where angry gale</l>
<l>May never rend the silken sail.</l>
</lg>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

