<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CanFoot"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="CanFoot">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">At the Foot of Hemlock Mountain</title>
<title type="sort">at the foot of hemlock mountain</title>
<author>Canfield, Dorothy</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">29</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CanFoot</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475783</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Judy Boss has made the following changes to the text:
<table>
<row>
<cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">p. 749, para. 6, line 5:</cell>
<cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Hillsboro to Hillsboro'</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">p. 751, para. 5, line 9:</cell>
<cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Ghosts, to "Ghosts,"</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">p. 752, para. 2, line 14:</cell>
<cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">not?" to not?</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">At the Foot of Hemlock Mountain</title>
<title type="sort">at the foot of hemlock mountain</title>
<author>Dorothy Canfield</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Scribner's</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1908-12">Dec. 1908</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Scribner's Magazine</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1908">1908</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-02">February 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Monique Dull, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Conversion to basic TEI-conformant markup</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
	<pb n="748"/>
<head> AT THE FOOT OF HEMLOCK MOUNTAIN
</head>
<p>"In connection with this phase of the problem of
transportation it must be remembered that the rush of population to
the great cities is no temporary movement.  It is caused by a final
revolt against that malignant relic of the dark ages, the country
village, and by a healthy craving for the deep, full life of the
metropolis, for contact with the vitalizing stream of humanity."&mdash;
PRITCHELL'S "Handbook of Economics," page 247.
</p>
<p>SOMETIMES people from Hillsboro' leave our forgotten valley, high
among the Green Mountains, and "go down to the city," as the phrase
runs.  They always come back exclaiming that they should think New
Yorkers would just die of lonesomeness, and crying out in an
ecstasy of relief that it does seem so good to get back where there
are some folks.  After the desolate isolation of city streets,
empty of humanity, filled only with hurrying ghosts, the vestibule
of our church on prayer-meeting night fills one with an exalted
realization of the great numbers of the human race.  It is like
coming into a warmed and lighted room, full of friendly faces,
after wandering long by night in a forest peopled only with
flitting shadows.  In the phantasmagoric pantomime of the city, we
forget that there are so many real people in all the world, so
diverse, so unfathomably human as those who meet us in the little
post-office on the night of our return to Hillsboro'.
</p><p>Like any other of those gifts of life which gratify insatiable
cravings of humanity, living in a country village conveys a
satisfaction which is incommunicable.  A great many authors have
written about it, just as a great many authors have written about
the satisfaction of being in love, but in the one as in the other
case, the essence of the thing escapes.  People rejoice in
sweethearts because all humanity craves love, and they thrive in
country villages because they crave human life.  Now the living
spirit of neither of these things can be caught in a net of words.
All the foolish, fond doings of lovers may be set down on paper by
whatever eavesdropper cares to take the trouble, but no one can
realize from that record anything of the glory in the hearts of the
unconscious two.  All the queer grammar and insignificant surface
eccentricities of village character may be ruthlessly reproduced in
every variety of dialect, but no one can guess from that record the
abounding flood of richly human life which pours along the village
street.
</p><p>This tormenting inequality between the thing felt and the
impression conveyed had vexed us unceasingly until one day Simple
Martin, the town fool, who always says our wise things, said one of
his wisest.  He was lounging by the watering-trough one sunny day
in June, when a carriage-load of "summer folk" from Granville over
the mountain stopped to water their horses.  They asked him as they
always, always ask all of us, "For mercy's sake, what do you people
<hi rend="italic">do</hi> all the time, away off here, so far from everything?"
</p><p>Simple Martin was not irritated, or perplexed, or rendered
helplessly inarticulate by this question, as the rest of us had
always been.  He looked around him at the lovely, sloping lines of
Hemlock Mountain, at the Necronsett River singing in the sunlight,
at the familiar, friendly faces of the people in the street, and he
answered in astonishment at the ignorance of his questioners, <hi rend="italic">"Do?</hi>  Why, we jes' <hi rend="italic">live!"</hi>
</p><p>We felt that he had explained us once and for all.  We had
known that, of course, but we hadn't before, in our own phrase,
"sensed it."  We just live.  And sometimes it seems to us that we
are the only people in America engaged in that most wonderful
occupation.  We know, of course, that we must be wrong in thinking
this, and that there must be countless other Hillsboro's scattered
everywhere, rejoicing as we do in an existence which does not
necessarily make us care-free or happy, which does not in the least
absolve us from the necessity of working hard (for Hillsboro' is
unbelievably poor in money), but which does keep us alive in every
fibre of our sympathy and thrilling with the consciousness of the
life of others. <pb n="749"/>
</p><p>A common and picturesque expression for a common experience
runs, "It's so noisy I can't hear myself think."  After a visit to
New York we feel that its inhabitants are so deafened by the
constant blare of noisy confusion that they can't feel themselves
live.  The steady sufferers from this complaint do not realize
their condition.  They find it on the whole less trouble <hi rend="italic">not</hi> to
feel themselves live, and they are most uneasy when chance forces
them to spend a few days (on shipboard, for instance) where they
are not protected by ceaseless and aimless activity from the
consciousness that they are themselves.  They cannot even conceive
the bitter-sweet, vital taste of that consciousness as we villagers
have it, and they cannot understand how arid their existence seems
to us without this unhurried, penetrating realization of their own
existence and of the meaning of their acts.  We do not blame city
dwellers for not having it, we lose it when we venture into their
maelstrom.  Like them, we become dwarfed by overwhelming numbers,
and shrivelled by the incapacity to "sense" the humanity of the
countless human simulacra about us.  But we do not stay where we
cannot feel ourselves live!  We hurry back to the shadow of Hemlock
Mountain, feeling that to love life one does not need to be what is
usually called happy, one needs only to live.
</p><p>It cannot be, of course, that we are the only community to
discover this patent fact; but we know no more of the others than
they of us.  All that we hear from that part of America which is
not Hillsboro' is the wild yell of excitement going up from the
great cities, where people seem to be doing everything that was
ever done or thought of except just living.  City dwellers make
money, make reputations (good and bad), make museums and subways,
make charitable institutions, make with a hysteric rapidity, like
excited spiders, more and yet more complications in the mazy
labyrinths of their lives, but they never make each others'
acquaintances . . . and that is all that is worth doing in the
world.
</p><p>We, who live in Hillsboro', know that they are to be pitied,
not blamed, for this fatal omission.  We realize that only in
Hillsboro' and places like it can one have "deep, full life and
contact with the vitalizing stream of humanity."  We know that in
the very nature of humanity the city is a small and narrow world,
the village a great and wide one, and that the utmost efforts of
city dwellers will not avail to break the bars of the prison where
they are shut in, each with his own kind.  They may look out from
the windows upon a great and varied throng, as the beggar munching
a crust may look in at a banqueting hall, but the people they are
forced to live with are exactly like themselves; and that way lies
not only monomania but an ennui that makes the blessing of life
savorless.
</p><p>If this does not seem the plainest possible statement of fact
take a concrete instance.  Can a banker in the city by any
possibility come to know what kind of an individual is the remote
impersonal creature who waits on him in a department store?  Most
bankers recognize with a misguided joy this natural wall between
themselves and people who are not bankers, and add to it as many
stones of their own quarrying as possible; but they are not shut
off from all the quickening diversity of life any more effectually
than the college-settlement boys' Sunday-school brand of banker.
The latter may try as hard as he pleases, he simply cannot achieve
real acquaintanceship with a "storekeeper," as we call them, any
more than the clerk can achieve real acquaintanceship with him.
Lack of any elements of common life form as impassable a barrier as
lack of a common language, whereas with us all the life we have is
common.  Every one is needed to live it.
</p><p>There can be no city dweller of experience who does not know
the result of this herding of the same kind of people together,
this intellectual and moral inbreeding.  To the accountant who
knows only accounts, the world comes to seem like one great ledger,
and account-keeping the only vital pursuit in life.  To the banker
who knows only bankers, the world seems one great bank filled with
money, accompanied by people.  The prison doors of uniformity are
closed inexorably upon them.
</p><p>And then what happens?  Why, when anything goes wrong with
their trumpery account books, or their trashy money, these poor
folk are like blind men who have lost their staves.  With all the
world before them they dare not continue to go forward.  We in
Hillsboro' are sorry for the account-<pb n="750"/> keepers who disappear
forever, fleeing from all who know them because their accounts have
come out crooked, we pity the banker who blows out his brains when
something has upset his bank; but we can't help feeling with this
compassion an admixture of the extreme impatience we have for those
Prussian school-boys who jump out of third-story windows because
they did not reach a certain grade in their Latin examinations.
Life is not accounts, or banks, or even Latin examinations, and it
is a sign of inexperience to think it so.  The trouble with the
despairing banker is that he has never had a chance to become aware
of the comforting vastness of the force which animates him, in
common with all the rest of humanity, to which force a bank failure
is no apocalyptic end of Creation, but a mere incident or trial of
strength like a fall in a slippery road.  Absorbed in his solitary
progress, the banker has forgotten that his business in life is not
so much to keep from falling as to get up again and press forward.
</p><p>If the man to whom the world was a bank had not been so
inexorably shut away from the bracing, tonic shock of knowing men
utterly diverse, to whom the world was just as certainly only a
grocery store, or a cobbler's bench, he might have come to believe
in a world that is none of these things and is big enough to take
them all in; and he might have been alive this minute, a credit to
himself, useful to the world and doubtless very much more agreeable
to his family than in the days of his blind arrogance.
</p><p>The pathetic feature of this universal inexperience among city
dwellers of real life and real people is that it is really entirely
enforced and involuntary.  At heart they crave knowledge of real
life and sympathy with their fellow-men as starving men do food.
In Hillsboro' we explain to ourselves the enormous amount of novel-reading and play-going in the great cities as due to a perverted
form of this natural hunger for human life.  If people are so
situated they can't get it fresh, they will take it canned, which
is undoubtedly good for those in the canning business; but we feel
that we who have better food ought not to be expected to treat it
very seriously.  We can't help smiling at the life-and-death
discussions of literary people about their preferences in style and
plot and treatment . . . their favorite brand on the can, so to
speak.
</p><p>To tell the truth, all novels seem to us badly written, they
are so faint and faded in comparison to the brilliant colors of the
life which palpitates up and down our village street, called by
strangers, "so quaint and sleepy-looking."  What does the author of
a novel do for you, after all, even the best author?  He presents
to you people not nearly so interesting as your next-door
neighbors, makes them do things not nearly so exciting as what
happened to your grandfather, and doles out to you in meagre
paragraphs snatches of that comprehending and consolatory
philosophy of life, which long ago you should have learned to
manufacture for yourself out of every incident in your daily
routine.  Of course, if you don't know your next-door neighbors,
and have never had time to listen to what happened to your
grandfather, and are too busy catching trains to philosophize on
those subjects if you did know them, no more remains to be said.
By all means patronize the next shop you see which displays in its
show windows canned romances, adventures, tragedies, farces, and
the like line of goods.  Live vicariously, if you can't at first
hand; but don't be annoyed at our pity for your method of passing
blindfold through life.
</p><p>And don't expect to find such a shop in our village.  To open
one there would be like trying to crowd out the great trees on
Hemlock Mountain by planting a Noah's Ark garden among them.
Romances, adventures, tragedies, and farces . . . why, we are the
characters of those plots.  Every child who runs past the house
starts a new story, every old man whom we leave sleeping in the
burying-ground by the Necronsett River is the ending of another .
. . or perhaps the beginning of a sequel.  Do you say that in the
city a hundred more children run past the windows of your apartment
than along our solitary street, and that funeral processions cross
your every walk abroad?  True, but they are stories written in a
tongue incomprehensible to you.  You look at the covers, you may
even flutter the leaves and look at the pictures, but you cannot
tell what they are all about.  You are like people bored and
yawning at a performance of a tragedy by Sophocles, because<pb n="751"/>
the actors speak in Greek.  So dreadful and moving a thing as a
man's sudden death may happen before your eyes, but you do not know
enough of what it means to be moved by it.  For you it is not
really a man who dies.  It is the abstract idea of a man, leaving
behind him abstract possibilities of a wife and children.  You knew
nothing of him, you know nothing of them, you shudder, look the
other way, and hurry along, your heart a little more blunted to the
sorrows of others, a little more remote from your fellows even than
before.
</p><p>All Hillsboro' is more stirred than that, both to sympathy and
active help, by the news that Mrs. Brownell has broken her leg.  It
means something unescapably definite to us, about which we not only
can, but must take action.  It means that her sickly oldest
daughter will not get the care she needs if somebody doesn't go to
help out; it means that if we do not do something that bright boy
of hers will have to leave school, just when he is in the way of
winning a scholarship in college; it means, in short, a crisis in
several human lives, which by the mere fact of being known calls
forth sympathy as irresistibly as sunshine in May opens the leaf
buds.
</p><p>Just as it is only one lover in a million who can continue to
love his mistress during a lifetime of absolute separation from
her, so it is one man in a million who can continue his sympathy
and interest in his fellow-men without continual close contact with
them.  The divine feeling of responsibility for the well-being of
others is diluted and washed away in great cities by the
overwhelming impersonal flood of vast numbers; in villages it is
strengthened by the sight, apparent to the dullest eyes, of
immediate personal and visible application.  In other words, we are
not only the characters of our unwritten stories, but also part
authors.  Something of the final outcome depends upon us, something
of the creative instinct of the artist is stirred to life within
every one of us . . . however unconscious of it in our countrified
simplicity we may be.  The sympathy we feel for a distressed
neighbor has none of the impotent sterility of a reader's sympathy
for a distressed character in a book.  There is always a chance to
try to help, and if that fail, to try again and yet again.  Death
writes the only <hi rend="italic">Finis</hi> to our stories, and since a chance to
start over again has been so unfailingly granted us here, we cannot
but feel that Death may mean only turning over another page.
</p><p>I suppose we do not appreciate the seriousness of fiction-writing, nor its importance to those who cannot get any nearer to
real life.  And yet it is not that we are unprogressive.  Our young
people, returning from college, or from visits to the city, freshen
and bring up to date our ideas on literature as rigorously as they
do our sleeves and hats; but after a short stay in Hillsboro' even
these conscientious young missionaries of culture turn away from
the feeble plots of Ibsen and the tame inventions of Bernard Shaw
to the really exciting, perplexing, and stimulating events in the
life of the village grocer.
</p><p>In "Ghosts," Ibsen preaches a terrible sermon on the
responsibility of one generation for the next, but not all his
relentless logic can move you to the sharp throb of horrified
sympathy you feel as you see Nelse Pettingrew's poor mother run
down the street, her shawl flung hastily over her head, framing a
face of despairing resolve, such as can never look at you out of
the pages of a book.  Somebody has told her that Nelse has been
drinking again and "is beginning to get ugly."  For Hillsboro' is
no model village, but the world entire, with hateful forces of evil
lying in wait for weakness.  Who will not lay down "Ghosts" to
watch, with a painfully beating heart, the progress of this living
"Mrs. Alving" past the house, leading, persuading, coaxing the
burly weakling, who will be saved from a week's debauch if she can
only get him safely home now, and keep him quiet till "the fit goes
by."
</p><p>At the sight everybody in Hillsboro' realizes that Nelse "got
it from his father," with a penetrating sense of the tragedy of
heredity, quite as stimulating to self-control in the future as
Ibsen is able to make us feel in "Ghosts."  But we know something
better than Ibsen, for Mrs. Pettingrew is no "Mrs. Alving."  She is
a plain, hard-featured woman who takes in sewing for a living, and
she is quite unlettered, but she is a general in the army of
spiritual forces.  She does not despair, she does not give up like
the half-hearted mother in "Ghosts," she does not waste her <pb n="752"/>  strength in concealments; she stands up to her enemy and
fights.  She fought the wild beast in Nelse's father, hand to hand,
all his life, and he died a better man than when she married him.
Undaunted, she fought it in Nelse as a boy, and now as a man; and
in the flowering of his physical forces when the wind of his youth
blows most wildly through the hateful thicket of inherited
weaknesses she generally wins the battle.
</p><p>And this she has done with none of the hard, consistent
strength and intelligence of your make-believe heroine in a book,
so disheartening an example to our faltering impulses for good.
She has been infinitely human and pathetically fallible; she has
cried out and hesitated and complained and done the wrong thing and
wept and failed and still fought on, till to think of her is, for
the weakest of us, like a bugle call to high endeavor.  Nelse is
now a better man than his father, and we shut up "Ghosts" with
impatience that Ibsen should have selected that story to tell out
of all the tales there must have been in the village where <hi rend="italic">he</hi>
lived.
</p><p>Now imagine if you can . . . for I cannot even faintly
indicate to you . . . our excitement when Nelse begins to look
about him for a wife.  In the first place, we are saved by our
enforced closeness to real people from wasting our energies in the
profitless outcry of economists, that people like Nelse should be
prohibited from having children.  It occurs to us that perhaps the
handsome fellow's immense good-humor and generosity are as good
inheritance as the selfishness and cold avarice of priggish young
Horace Gallatin, who never drinks a drop.  Perhaps at some future
date all people who are not perfectly worthy to have children will
be kept from it by law.  In Hillsboro', we think, that after such
a decree the human race would last just one generation; but that is
not the point now.  The question is, will Nelse find a wife who
will carry on his mother's work, or will he not?
</p><p>If you think you are excited over a serial story because you
can't guess if "Lady Eleanor" really stole the diamonds or not, it
is only because you have no idea of what excitement is.  You are in
a condition of stagnant lethargy compared to that of Hillsboro'
over the question whether Nelse will marry Ellen Brownell, "our
Ellen," or Flossie Merton, the ex-factory girl, who came up from
Montpelier to wait at the tavern, and who is said to have a taste
for drink herself.
</p><p>Old Mrs. Perkins, whom everybody had thought sunk in
embittered discontent about the poverty and isolation of her last
days, roused herself not long ago and gave Ellen her cherished
tortoise-shell back-comb, and her pretty white silk shawl to wear
to village parties; and racked with rheumatism, as the old woman
is, she says she sits up at night to watch the young people go back
from choir rehearsal so that she can see which girl Nelse is
"beauing home."  Could the most artfully contrived piece of fiction
more blessedly sweep the self-centred complainings of old age into
generous and vitalizing interest in the lives of others?
</p><p>As for the "pity and terror," the purifying effects of which
are so vaunted in Greek tragedies, could AEschylus himself have
plunged us into a more awful desolation of pity than the day we saw
old Squire Marvin being taken along the street on his way to the
insane asylum?  All the self-made miseries of his long life were in
our minds, the wife he had loved and killed with the harsh violence
of a nature he had never learned to control, the children he had
adored unreasonably and spoiled and turned against, and they on him
with a violence like his own, the people he had tried to benefit
with so much egotistic pride mixed in his kindness that his favors
made him hated, his vanity, his generosity, his despairing outcries
against the hostility he had so well earned . . . at the sight of
the end of all this there was no heart in Hillsboro' that was not
wrung with a pity and terror more penetrating and purifying even
than Shakespeare has made the centuries feel for Lear.
</p><p>Ah, at the foot of Hemlock Mountain we do not need books to
help us feel the meaning of life!
</p><p>Nor do we need them to help us feel the meaning of death.
You, in the cities, living with a feverish haste in the present
only, and clutching at it as a starving man does at his last crust,
you cannot understand the comforting sense we have of belonging
almost as much to the past and future as to the present.  Our own
youth is not dead <pb n="753"/>  to us as yours is, from the lack of
anything to recall it to you, and people we love do not slip
quickly into that bitter oblivion to which the dead are consigned
by those too hurried to remember.  They are not remembered
perfunctorily for their "good qualities" which are carved on their
tomb-stones, but all the quaint and dear absurdities which make up
personality, are embalmed in the leisurely, peaceable talk of the
village, still enriched by all that they brought to it.  We are not
afraid of the event which men call death, because we know that, in
so far as we have deserved it, the same homely immortality awaits
us.
</p><p>Every spring, at the sight of the first cowslip, our old
people laugh and say to each other, "Will you <hi rend="italic">ever</hi> forget how
Aunt Dorcas used to take us children out cowslipping, and how she
never would lift her skirt to cross the log by the mill, and always
fell in the brook?"  The log has mouldered away a generation ago,
the mill is only a heap of blackened timbers, but as they speak,
they are not only children again, but Aunt Dorcas lives again for
them and for us who never saw her . . . dear, silly, kind old Aunt
Dorcas, past-mistress in the lovely art of spoiling children.  Just
so the children we have spoiled, the people we have lived with,
will continue to keep us living with them.  We shall have time to
grow quite used to whatever awaits us after the tangled rosebushes
of Hillsboro' burying-ground bloom over our heads, before we shall
have gradually faded painlessly away from the life of men and
women.  We sometimes feel that, almost alone in the harassed and
weary modern world, we love that life, and yet we are the least
afraid to leave it.
</p><p>It is usually dark when the shabby little narrow-gauge train
brings us home to Hillsboro' from wanderings in the great world,
and the big pond by the station is full of stars.  Up on the hill
the lights of the village twinkle against the blurred mass of
Hemlock Mountain, and above them the stars again.  It is very
quiet, the station is black and deserted, the road winding up to
the village glimmers uncertainly in the starlight, and dark forms
hover vaguely about.  Strangers say that it is a very depressing
station at which to arrive, but we know better.  There is no
feeling in the world like that with which one starts up the white
road, stars below him in the quiet pool, stars above him in the
quiet sky, friendly lights showing the end of his journey is at
hand, and the soft twilight full of voices all familiar, all
welcoming.
</p><p>Poor old Uncle Abner Rhodes, returning from an attempt to do
business in the city, where he had lost his money, his health, and
his hopes, said he didn't see how going up to Heaven could be so
very different from walking up the hill from the station with
Hemlock Mountain in front of you.  He said it didn't seem to him as
though even in Heaven you could feel more than then that you had
got back where there are some folks, that you had got back home.
</p><p>Sometimes when the stars hang very bright over Hemlock
Mountain and the Necronsett River sings loud in the dusk, we
remember the old man's speech, and, though we smile at his
simplicity, we think, too, that the best which awaits us can only
be very much better, but not so very different from what we have
known here.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
