<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CanScru"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="CanScru">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"The Scrubwoman" / by Dorothy Canfield; Author of "Moonshine," "The Story of Ralph Miller," etc.</title>
<title type="sort">the scrubwoman by dorothy canfield author of moonshine, the story of ralph miller etc</title>
<author>Canfield, Dorothy</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">36</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CanScru</idno>
<date value="2000">2000</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2000 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475789</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"The Scrubwoman"</title>
<title level="j">Munsey`s Magazine</title>
<title type="sort">the scrubwoman</title>
<author>Dorothy Canfield</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>7 pages</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1907-01">January 1907</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source Copy Consulted: Alderman Library UVA AP2 .M8 v.36 1906-07</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1907-01">January 1907</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>feminine</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2000-01">January 2000</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>J. Nathaniel Goldsmith, The Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head><hi rend="bold">THE SCRUBWOMAN</hi><lb/>

BY DOROTHY CANFIELD<lb/>

AUTHOR OF "MOONSHINE," "THE STORY OF RALPH MILLER," ETC.
</head>

<div2 type="part" n="1" id="d4">
<pb n="412"/>
<p>HENRY RANDOLPH shook his
white head in an impatient gesture
of dissent, and continued the discussions
with a tenderly exasperated
disregard of his cousin's scruples.  "No,
no, Alice, dear, this is no time to split
hairs on what it's proper to speak about.
It's infamous, I know, that I should be
talking to you about it &mdash; nobody but a
woman should; but, my dear child, how
<hi rend="italic">can</hi> I go and leave you so?  And there's
nobody else <hi rend="italic">to</hi> speak.  You might as well
have no brother at all as one in the
navy."
</p><p>Mrs. Smithers's resigned, though unpeaceful, drooping attitude changed at
this to a sudden nervous tension.  She
clasped and unclasped her thin hands,
and spoke with a little rush of eagerness.
"Ah! that's it, Cousin Henry.  If I
could only see my brother oftener, he
might be able to do something."  She
relapsed again into listless despondency
and continued dully: "But I don't
suppose he would ever see anything at
all the matter.  My husband would be
so different with him &mdash; <hi rend="italic">you</hi> know how
Will is to outsiders."
</p><p>Randolph struck one hand into the
other fiercely.  "I do!  I do!  But what's
the use of knowing him now, when
you've been married ten years?  Oh, if
I'd only been here instead of on the
other side of the globe when he first
went to Washington and met you!  Why,
in Heaven's name, your parents &mdash;"
He checked himself abruptly.  "No, I
can't blame them &mdash; poor, simple souls!
They never had any worldly discernment.  You're just like them."
</p><p>Mrs. Smithers spoke in a naively solemn and hesitant way.  "I hope it's not
wicked, Cousin Henry, but I'm some-times glad they died so soon after my
marriage &mdash; and that Tom is always away
on his vessel.  They couldn't help any,
and I'm glad they don't have to suffer
with me.  I'm sorry it makes you so sad,
cousin, on your first visit home in so
many years.  I'm afraid I've not been
able to make you very happy."
</p><p>At this Randolph roared out in indignant tenderness: "Good Heavens,
Alice, don't be such a perfectly angelic
idiot!  If you endure it day after day,
and have for ten years, and will as long
as he or you live, don't you suppose a
great hulking brute of a man like me
can bear just to hear about it?"
</p><p>The woman stirred uneasily in her
chair.  "Oh, please, dear cousin, don't
speak so.  I know I've done very wrong
to let you know it all, but, seeing somebody who belongs to me after all this
long, lonely life in New York &mdash; I'm
afraid I haven't been very brave.  I
may not have so much more to bear than
other women.  Will, you know, is never
brutally unkind, as so many husbands
are &mdash; he has never struck me &mdash; we live
in this expensive apartment; the children go to the best schools; I always
have plenty of money to spend &mdash;"
</p><p>She ended, quavering off into silence
before the gathering wrath in the old
man's eyes.  He caught her up grimly:
"Yes, you have plenty of money to
spend, but I notice you do your own
work most of the time.  Your husband
makes the apartment such a hell on earth
with his devilish ingenuity that you
couldn't keep a maid for a week &mdash; not
for any price."
</p><p>Alice interrupted him eagerly: "But,
no &mdash; I have old Belle, the scrubwoman,
you know.  She's been with me almost
ever since I was married &mdash; ever since we
came to this house to live.  She cleans
the halls and stairways of this building,
and so she's always on hand to come in


<pb n="413"/>

and help me out.  She does all the rough
work, and she won't let me do anything
she can manage to prevent.  She's so
faithful and strong, and so kind to me,
I forget all about her dreadful looks
and profanity; and you couldn't <hi rend="italic">drive</hi>
her away.  She never seems even to hear
the things Will says to her."
</p><p>The man's voice was bitter as he answered gloomily: "Actually the best
friend &mdash; the <hi rend="italic">only</hi> friend you are allowed
to have is that frightful old harridan
I see around here.  I wonder you allow
her to be with the children.  I've never
heard her speak without an oath, and little Jack is so &mdash;"
</p><p>The mention of the child was like an
electric shock to the mother.  She sprang
to her feet, and running to the tall old
man, she caught one of his hands in
hers with a gesture of distraction.  "Oh,
Cousin Henry, every time I hear Jack's
name it makes me remember Will's
threat to send him away.  It's only because of that I spoke to you at all.  I
could <hi rend="italic">not</hi> bear to have him go from me
to a strange school.  It would kill him."
</p><p>The man suddenly gave a deep sob
of pity, and gathered the frail, weeping woman into his arms.  The silence
which followed was broken by the entrance from the dining-room of a small
woman of uncertain age, in dingy attire, carrying a pail of water in one bony
hand and a large cleaning-cloth in the
other.  Without noticing the silent couple by the window, she dropped heavily to her knees and began to wipe up
the edge of bare floor showing about
the carpet.  Randolph spoke, and she
turned, startled, showing a face blurred
and battered by hardship, but instantly
alive in the keenest interest in the conversation.
</p><p>"Alice, dear, unless you'll simply
drop everything and come away with me
to my home, I don't see any way out."
</p><p>Mrs. Smithers recoiled at this and
spoke with a passionate denial: "Why,
how <hi rend="italic">can</hi> you think of my doing that!
How could I leave the children?
They're all I live for &mdash; all that keeps me
from going crazy!"
</p><p>"You could bring the children along.
They'd do well in Buenos Ayres."
</p><p>"He'd come and take them from
me.  I've been all over that so many
times with myself.  And I've read that
the children are never allowed to stay
with the mother if she has run away.  If
I could only just snatch them up and
hide from him &mdash; all of us; but he's
so clever and I'm so stupid he'd find
us out right away, and then I &mdash; he'd
never let me see them again."
</p><p>The old man drew a long breath, in
an evident attempt to control himself,
but vainly, for he broke out so fiercely
that the scrubwoman sat up on her
heels electrified.  "Damnation!  I beg
your pardon, Allie, dear, but it just
tears me in pieces to see you so.
Confound the fellow!  Why doesn't he
just once go a step too far and give
some ground for divorce?  The hellish
cunning of him! &mdash; to care so well for
your outward wants and to murder
inch by inch your self-respect, your love
for your children, your pride &mdash; your very
soul!"
</p><p>He stopped her feeble gesture of protest with a furious torrent of words.
"No, don't talk to me.  I've seen it, and
I know.  Tom may be fooled by his
smooth ways, but I've seen Mexican
half-breeds before now.  Sometimes I
think it a mistake, his having had an
American father &mdash; he's all greaser, every
inch of him!  I heard stories about
him as a boy when I was in Bocas del
Toro.  When he was ten years old he
was caught burning a cat over a slow
fire &mdash; half-breed Injun and Spaniard,
just like his mother.  No, he gets his
business sense from old Smithers, all
right.  And, good Lord! he gets those
cold, pale eyes from him!"
</p><p>He shuddered at the picture and went
on in a mounting fury: "Allie, unless
you give up the children or divide them,
there's nothing anybody can do to help.
It's incredible there should be such a
situation in a civilized country, but it's
so.  The mere fact that you are tortured
day by day in a thousand subtle ways no
decent man could even think of is as
nothing, because he doesn't strike you.  A
jury or judge would take no more cognizance of your mental agony than &mdash;
your old scrubwoman!"
</p><p>At this mention of her the woman
started guiltily from her position of
strained and intent eavesdropping and
let her cloth fall into the pail with a


<pb n="414"/>

splash.  The two turned, and, seeing her,
lowered their voices, Mrs. Smithers trying in vain to repress her sobbing.
</p><p>Randolph went over to her and laid
one hand tenderly on her shoulder.  Oh,
I know you won't think of leaving the
children.  You couldn't, of course.  But,
Allie, do this for me, at least: promise me that the next time you see Tom &mdash;
and may it be soon, or you won't keep
your reason &mdash; <hi rend="italic">tell</hi> him!  Tell him what
your married life is.  He's your big
brother, and I feel that he'll be able to
help you somehow.  Promise me that!
Don't send me away quite hopeless over
your future."
</p><p>In a confused murmur of sobs and
broken sentences the promise came:
"Yes, yes, I promise.  I somehow feel,
too, that if he really knows &mdash; he can
help &mdash; but there's so much even he can't
know.  Oh, I wish I had a mother!  If
my mother had only lived!"</p></div2>

<div2 type="part" n="2" id="d5"><head>II</head>

<p>INTO this atmosphere of quivering agitation dropped suddenly the quiet, silvery tinkle of the door-bell.  It shocked
them all into attitudes of expectation.
Mrs. Smithers stopped her sobbing with
a convulsive effort and sat up straight,
shivering uncontrollably and motioning
the scrubwoman to hurry.  "Oh, that
must be Will!  He mustn't see me so
upset.  Belle, hurry!  <hi rend="italic">Do</hi> hurry and
open for him; he can't bear to be kept
waiting.  I'd go myself, but he doesn't
like to see me do it.  Oh, Belle, please,
<hi rend="italic">please</hi> hurry!"
</p><p>The significance of her terror-stricken disquiet pierced the old man with a
savage thrust of pity and sympathy, but
the scrubwoman did not lift a heavy
finger the quicker for it.  She finished
wiping up a spot on the floor, wrung her
cloth out deliberately, and hung it over
the pail before she rose to her feet and
went down the long, narrow hall with
the ungainly walk of women who have
long worked beyond their strength.
Randolph and his cousin waited and together caught a sudden breath when
from the recesses of the hall came a
smooth, penetrating voice saying with
an indescribably insulting accent: "Out
of my way, you hag!"
</p><p>Rapid steps came down the hall, and
a tall man with a very black beard and
pale-blue eyes entered the room, bringing with him the lowering atmosphere
of a thunder-storm.  As he caught sight
of Randolph his face smoothed itself
into a cordial smile, and advancing, he
insisted on taking the older man's hand
in a hearty gasp.  When he spoke, his
voice had a warm intonation of pleased
surprise.  "Why, Cousin Henry, this
is a welcome sight.  I understood that
you were to be off to-day, and that we
were once more a desolate family, without a relative to our names."
</p><p>He took off his coat and hat as he
spoke and gave them to the scrubwoman,
who stood with the apprehensive, repellent gaze of an ill-treated ash-cat.  She
turned to go out with them, and as she
disappeared down the hall Randolph
noticed, with a qualm of disgust, as another detail in the nightmare which surrounded him, that she spat fiercely on
the hat.  He roused himself and said to
the newcomer stiffly: "There was some
accident to the engines, and the boat
won't sail until to-night, so I came back
to &mdash;"
</p><p>Smithers interrupted him with a
cheery laugh as he began opening some
letters on the table and glancing over
them.  "It's an ill wind, <hi rend="italic">et cetera</hi>.  I
dare say little Allie was no end glad to
see you again.  She's not much company
for herself at any time, and when the
children are still in the country and she's
been spoiled by so much of your delightful companionship, I fancy my little child-wife got pretty dull."
</p><p>He looked them both full in the face
as he delivered this speech, and smiled
at their wincing under his accent.  The
scrubwoman, moving the furniture
about, suddenly set a chair down with
so furious an energy that they all
started.
</p><p>"Oblige me, Belle, by being a little
quieter," said Smithers mildly, and
laughed aloud as he caught Randolph's
eye.  Still smiling, he went rattling on,
as he read a letter:
</p><p>"Do you know, my dear Cousin
Henry, you're the only relative who's
been to see us since the very first years
of our married life?  Alice doesn't
know her other forty-second cousins
very well, and, to tell the truth, they


<pb n="415"/>

don't seem to enjoy our simple life.  Too
bad, eh, Allie?"
</p><p>His voice dropped into an absent murmur, and he lost himself in the letter.
Randolph crossed the room to the window where his cousin stood and drew her
to him.  "I'm going now, dear child," he
said in a low tone, "but it's like tearing
a piece of my heart out to leave you so.
It seems to me, sometimes, I must go distracted thinking of you.  But it's one
ray of light in my darkness that you've
promised to speak to Tom and appeal
to him to help you.  And remember, let
me know if I can ever help and &mdash;"
</p><p>Smithers laid down his letter and
turned toward them with so openly black
a look of suspicion that the old man
answered as though he had been questioned.
</p><p>"I'm telling Alice, William," he said
defiantly, "that if she ever needs me
I'll come from the ends of the earth."
</p><p>The younger man smiled again, so
that his wife caught her breath and
clung convulsively to her cousin.  He
waved his hand genially.  "Ah, very
good of you &mdash; very kind, I'm sure.  Alice
will, of course, let you know at any
time if there is something you can do
for her."  He added dryly: "I'll see
that she does myself."  Randolph turned
his back on him and kissed Alice on
the forehead.  "Good-by, little girl.
Heaven bless you!" he said, in an unsteady voice.
</p><p>The scrubwoman stood up to show
him the door, drying her distorted hands
on her torn apron.  She made a
furtive wipe at her eyes, and sniffed
loudly with a grotesque contortion of
her face.  Smithers turned on her suddenly, so that she dodged and lifted an
arm in guard.  He spoke with the most
careful gentleness:
</p><p>"Don't bother to show Mr. Randolph
the door, Belle.  I'll go myself.  No,
don't protest, my dear cousin.  It's the
last time.  I'm not going to let a servant's face be the last one you see in my
house &mdash; and such a face!"  The two
disappeared down the hall, Smithers
ahead, talking animatedly.</p></div2>

<div2 type="part" n="3" id="d6"><head>III</head>

<p>BELLE dropped her cloth and hastened
heavily to where Alice sat.  Her hard
face was set in lines of grim resolution.
She spoke in a hoarse whisper, looking
continually over her shoulder toward the
hall.  "Ma'am &mdash; Mrs. Smithers &mdash; don't
give up to him so!  Paste him one when
he comes back.  Git ahead of him and
he'd let you alone.  Give him fits before he has a chance to git started."
</p><p>Alice looked up in amazement, and
spoke with a childish attempt at dignity.  "Belle, you forget yourself!"
</p><p>Her husband came back into the room
with his rapid, noiseless tread, cast a black
look at the two women, and went again
to his mail.  There was a silence which
was ominous.  The scrubwoman went on
stolidly with her work, and Alice waited
in trembling suspense for the first words.
Smithers finished a letter and held it
up, saying in a low, measured tone:
"If you've quite finished your furtive
conversation with your especial friend,
you may care to know that this letter
is from Jack.  I believe you preserve
the pose of being devoted to your children."
</p><p>He pocketed the letter in answer to
an imploring gesture for it from his
wife, and went on: "No, there's no
need for you to read it.  I can tell you
all that's necessary for you to know.
He's hurt his foot again."
</p><p>His wife screamed out at this, striking
her hands together in anguish.  "Oh,
Will!  His lame foot?  How badly?"
</p><p>The man gathered the letters together
and threw some loose envelopes in the
waste-paper basket before he answered.
Then he said sardonically: "It makes
me smile to see the way you carry out
your attitude about that.  If you care
so much about it, it's a wonder you carefully arranged matters so he would be
lame."
</p><p>The mother quivered as though under a physical blow.  "Oh, Will, how
<hi rend="italic">can</hi> you?"
</p><p>Her tormentor went on: "How
could <hi rend="italic">you?</hi>  It was just pure carelessness on your part letting him fall &mdash; <hi rend="italic">you,</hi>
a mother of children!  I wonder that
you can look at the ugly little cripple
without hating yourself."
</p><p>He listened impatiently to her feeble
attempt at self-justification.  "Why,
Will, you know I was thrown myself,
and fell all those steps.  The doctor


<pb n="416"/>

has always said that if I hadn't held
him up he would have been killed,
and &mdash;"
</p><p>"Confound the doctor!  You got
around him with your soft ways the same
way you did me before I knew
what a fool you were.  Besides, it would
be better for Jack if he <hi rend="italic">were</hi> dead.  It
makes me sick to see him hobbling about.
Anyhow, the fact remains that you were
supposed to be taking care of him and
let him fall.  I notice other mothers
seem to be able to avoid those little accidents."
</p><p>He walked into the study, kicking
viciously at Belle's pail and partly over-turning it, so that the water ran out on
the carpet.  As the door slammed the
scrubwoman looked apprehensively at
Mrs. Smithers, who returned the look
sadly.
</p><p>"Belle, you know I've always been
good to you."
</p><p>The workwoman brightened at the
words and answered fervently, in a
hoarse, cracked voice: "Yes, ma'am,
Lord knows I know."
</p><p>Her mistress continued seriously, as
though speaking to a naughty child:
"There's one thing, though, I can't allow.  You must not speak to me as you
did just now, or I can never have you
here again."
</p><p>The shapeless body of the other
drooped humbly under the reproof.
"Just as you say, ma'am.  I couldn't
help myself that time, but I won't never
again.  I couldn't live if I had to quit
workin' for you.  I'm scrubbin' here in
the house for less than I could git somewheres else just so's I can git to see you.
Why, ma'am &mdash; Mrs. Smithers &mdash; I'd go
through hell every day to see you!"
</p><p>She flinched again at the deprecating
hand of her mistress, and hung her head,
shamefaced, at the exhortation: "Oh,
Belle, you <hi rend="italic">shouldn't</hi> use such language."
</p><p>The pathos of the unlovely figure
went to Alice's heart.  "Never mind
this time, Belle.  You do a great deal
for <hi rend="italic">me,</hi> too.  I couldn't have got
along without you, a great many times,
and it makes me very happy to think
that I'm not so weak that I can't help
somebody a little."
</p><p>The hard-featured face of the other
suddenly broke into grotesque lines of
emotion.  She spoke incoherently, sitting ungracefully on her heels and wiping her eyes with the cleaning-cloth between her sentences.  "Oh, ma'am, it
just busts me wide open to have you
say I help you.  When a body's had all
done for them you've done for me &mdash;
keeping me at all! &mdash; I know how I look
and how rough I talk.  There isn't another lady in the world that would have
me around, and with the kids and all!
And then to give me kind words and
looks, and helpin' me through with the
typhoid, and goin' to that darned hospital to see me!  Not if I live to be a
million, which Lord forbid!  I couldn't
never forget how you looked when you
came in the ward with all them flowers,
as though I was anybody, and standin'
by me all that month when they thought
I'd swiped the silver.  You're the only
livin' soul as ever give me a kind word
since I can't remember.  I never did anything but fight anywheres else but here.
It's just been hell every minute.  I cud
ha' died like a dog and never knowed
what it was to have anybody so much
as say &mdash; oh, ma'am, Mrs. Smithers &mdash;"
</p><p>She paused, breathless, choked by emotion, unable to express herself, but staring at her mistress, a look of doglike devotion in her somber eyes.
</p><p>As Alice smiled sweetly at her with
a wistful look of gratitude, she came
to herself, and began her work again,
sniffing unpleasantly and drawing the
back of her hand across her nose from
time to time.
</p><p>She moved a picture which stood on
the floor to another part of the room,
looking at it curiously and at Alice timidly, finally summing up courage to say:
"Would it be too darn much trouble,
ma'am, to tell me what this picture's
about?"
</p><p>"That?  Oh, that's a glacier &mdash; ice,
you know, on top of a mountain &mdash; and
two men are tied together with a rope.
One of them has just slipped into a
great, deep hole, and he's getting out his
knife to cut the rope, so he won't drag
the other man after him."
</p><p>Belle seemed unconvinced.  "But
then he'll fall, won't he?"
</p><p>Alice replied absently, looking at the
picture of a child on the mantel.  "Yes,
but the other man, his friend will be


<pb n="417"/>

saved."  She fell into a reverie, from
which she was recalled by the other's insistent questioning: "What do
the words underneath mean, please,
ma'am?"
</p><p>"I forget what they do call it.
What are the words?"
</p><p>Belle followed the letters with a
gnarled forefinger and read laboriously:
"Greater love hath no man," and listened with a painful face of endeavor to
the explanation: "Oh, that's from the
Bible, where it says, 'Greater love hath
no man than this, that a man lay down
his life for his friend.'  It means, you
know, that &mdash;"</p></div2>

<div2 type="part" n="4" id="d7"><head>IV</head>

<p>THE door from the study opened, and
she started eagerly toward her husband.
"Oh, Will, won't you tell me about
Jack's foot now?  Did he hurt it
badly?"
</p><p>Smithers looked at her with a side-wise twist of his mouth and said evenly: "I see your usual careful house-keeping in that large spot of dirty
water on the carpet."
</p><p>Belle and Alice both faced him,
amazed, and Alice cried impulsively:
"Why, Will, you upset the &mdash;"
</p><p>He cut her off with one of his blighting looks.  "It's curious how I am to
blame for everything that happens.  I
don't suppose your peerless beauty, there,
is capable of getting me a bottle of beer,
is she?  As usual, we are without any
other servants.  I dare say that I am
also to blame for your incapacity to
keep any help in the house.  It seems as
though, with all the money you have for
service, you might be able to keep somebody besides that harridan.  I suppose
the fact is you're jealous of any one who
doesn't resemble your old eyesore.  Oh,
don't explain.  You needn't be afraid
I'd ever think you capable of such a live
flesh-and-blood sentiment.  Milk and
water can't burn."  He addressed himself threateningly to  Belle:  "Will you
get some beer, or won't you?"
</p><p>She answered him sullenly: "The
liquor man ain't sent the beer yet."
</p><p>The man's smoothness broke into an
ugly cold fury.  He advanced upon his
wife, so that she shrank into herself in
terror.  "Alice, your incompetence is
simply maddening!  You know the doctor has ordered me to drink beer.  You
seem actually to plan to thwart any
measures for my good.  I'm not surprised
that you show no interest in my health.
Indeed, I dare say you would be very
glad if &mdash;"
</p><p> "Oh, <hi rend="italic">no,</hi> Will!" shrieked his wife, in
an agony of protest.  "Don't!  I can't
bear to hear you say such a dreadful
thing!"
</p><p>The sight of her agitation seemed to
restore him to his usual cold control of
himself.  He eyed her with a smile.
"The extraordinary ease with which
your guilty imagination fills out my sentences is something surprising, even to
me &mdash; used as I am to your affection for
your husband.  I'm going out to the
kitchen myself to see if I can't find a
bottle which your vigilant handmaid has
sequestered for her own use."
</p><p>In the moment of his absence the
scrubwoman raised her gaunt frame
again in exhortation: "Oh, blame it all,
ma'am &mdash; if you would &mdash; just once &mdash; just
try it on!"
</p><p>Alice hushed her, with a frantic fear
of being overheard, and turned to her
husband, who entered the room with a
bottle of beer, which he opened with a
deft strength and half emptied into a
glass.  The two women followed his
most trivial actions with a fascinated
gaze.  The first draft seemed to relax him, for he leaned back in his chair,
wiping his beard and looking neutrally
at his wife.  "Have you heard anything
lately from Tom, Alice?" he asked.
</p><p>Alice flushed up into a timid desire to
please him in this brief interlude of
peace.  "No, Will, not for a long time.
How kind of you to think of him!  I
long to hear from him so.  I can't tell
you!  I think I should almost <hi rend="italic">die</hi> of
happiness to see him again."
</p><p>She drew away in a drooping submission under her husband's curt "Oh,
don't be sickening!  Every time I try
to have a little reasonable conversation
with you you turn my stomach.  It's
enough to drive any man with a nerve
in his body mad with irritation &mdash; your
fawning ways.  I'm sorry for myself!
It's not my fault.  Any woman with a
spark of grit in her &mdash; you make me
hate myself as well as you &mdash;"  He


<pb n="418"/>

interrupted himself sharply, pointing
tensely into a corner of the room.  "A
mouse!  Alice, have you or have you
not used that poison I got for you?"
</p><p>"Oh, Will," she fluttered protestingly, "I'm so afraid to have it around!  I
haven't seen any mice for a long time,
and I thought traps &mdash; the children &mdash;"
</p><p>Smithers struck his hand heavily on
the table, with a loud oath: "Can't a
man be safe from vermin in his own
home because he has a fool for a wife?"
</p><p>He rushed out, and Belle again approached with her ignorant, vacant look
of curiosity.  "Why are you so afraid
of that stuff, ma'am?"
</p><p>Mrs. Smithers shuddered.  "Oh,
Belle, it's poison &mdash; deadly poison &mdash; and
the least little drop of it in anything we
eat would kill us.  And when the children are here &mdash;"
</p><p>Their whispered colloquy was interrupted by Smithers's entrance, bearing
a small bottle, which he placed on the
mantelpiece in a complete and significant
silence.  As he seated himself he said
coldly: "I hope I shall not have to
wait until we are attacked in our beds
by the rats before you decide to be reasonable."  He fixed his pale eyes on her.
"Alice, this is as good a time as ever
to tell you that I have decided to send
Jack to school &mdash; a military school in Wisconsin."
</p><p>Belle uttered a loud exclamation at
this, which was lost in the high hysterical wail of Mrs. Smithers's voice,
"Will, I don't want to seem to doubt
your judgment, but I really know more
about Jack's health than you can, and
I know he can't <hi rend="italic">live</hi> without the most
anxious care.  A <hi rend="italic">military</hi> school &mdash; why,
he's lame!  And so far away!  And
Jack is only nine &mdash; a baby &mdash; a baby!"
</p><p>She flung herself upon him, kneeling
with imploring hands and awaiting his
answer in a breathless suspense.  He
waited a long time before speaking, and
then finished his glass of beer and set
it down carefully.  "Quite what I expected &mdash; just the silly exhibition of yourself that I am used to.  And you expect
me to leave my children to be brought
up by an hysterical idiot like that!  I had
not finally decided, but I do so now,
that the other two would be better in
a sane and reasonable atmosphere, which
unfortunately, owing to my choice
of a wife, I cannot give them in my
own house.  Elsie and Harry, as soon
as they come home from the country,
shall go abroad under the charge of a
French governess."
</p><p>His wife's face did not change at all.
She slipped slowly to the floor in an
unconscious heap, and her face did not
alter from its expression of stupefied
horror.</p></div2>

<div2 type="part" n="5" id="d8"><head>V</head>

<p>THE scrubwoman darted to her mistress and knelt by her in a passion of
anxiety.  When Smithers put her roughly on one side and gathered his wife's
body into his arms she scratched and
struck at him like a cat, with an incoherent burst of objurgation.  The man
paid no attention to her, carrying his
wife down the long hall with an easy
strength and disappearing for a moment
into a side room.
</p><p>Belle was still on her knees, a squat
figure of hatred, when he emerged again,
closed the door after him, and came
back down the hall whistling "The
Campbells Are Coming."  At the entrance to the parlor he looked at her in
complete silence till she cringed abjectly.  At this he smiled, and said in a tone
of finality: "That will be enough
from you, Belle.  One more such incident and I'll have you dismissed from
the apartment and the building.  Do you
understand?"
</p><p>She nodded faintly, and started up in
a servile haste to answer the door-bell,
bringing back a letter which she placed
on Mrs. Smithers's desk, saying significantly: "It's for your <hi rend="italic">wife,</hi> Mr. Smithers."
</p><p>He cast her a sidelong look of contemptuous warning and opened the letter with a swift deftness, reading it
aloud in an inarticulate mumble, which
at times rose into a clear note of scornful emphasis.
</p><p>"Dear little sister &mdash; unexpectedly find
we're ordered for &mdash; stopping a day
in New York &mdash; hope you can get down to
the vessel &mdash; you'll need to start as soon
as you get this, for we are to &mdash; hope you
can manage it, for it will be the last
chance in two years!"
</p><p>The last sentence he read quite distinctly,


<pb n="419"/>

in a tone of triumph, and gave
a short laugh as he tore the letter in two.
</p><p>At the sound, the scrubwoman sprang
toward him, her face convulsed.  "Don't
you dare tear up that letter from her
brother!  I'll &mdash; I'll &mdash;"  She struggled
to wrest it away in an animal-like frenzy.
He struck her from him with a blow so
powerful that she reeled to the other side
of the room, but, although the action was
violent, he did not lose his uncanny
smoothness, and held her distant from
him and impotently speechless by his
cold eye.
</p><p>"I said, Belle, that another time I
would lose my patience with you.  That
has happened.  When you finish your
work in this room you will leave the
apartment, and you will not come back
&mdash; either here or to the building."  He
cut short her paroxysm of horror with a
gesture so fierce that she cowered like a
whipped dog.  "Not a word from you,"
he said; "I've heard enough.  I'm going into the study now, and when I
come out I expect you to be gone.  And
don't dare go near your mistress."
</p><p>He crossed the room with his graceful, vigorous step, paused at the door,
said in his ordinary tone, "Bring me in
the rest of that beer, will you," opened
the door, and closed it with a resolute
jerk back of him.
</p><p>The movement jarred a picture standing on the floor near the door, and it
fell down with a splintering crash of
broken glass, which turned the scrubwoman's eye in that direction.  There
was a moment's silence, and then, without rising from her crouching position,
she crept across the floor to where it lay
and looked at it dully, making no movement to set it up.
</p><p>And then suddenly she rose staggering to her feet, rushed heavily to the
mantel, and seized the bottle which stood
there.  With a sort of insane and extravagant haste she emptied its contents and
the beer into a glass at the same moment,
and reeled across the room to the study,
knocking on the door with a hand hysterically shaking.  Smithers's hand appeared, took the glass, and the door was
again shut.  The scrubwoman leaned
against the wall with her eyes closed
until the sound of a heavy fall was heard
from the other room.  She recoiled from
the wall at this and walked blindly and
aimlessly about the room.
</p><p>A sound of deep groans came through
the closed door.  The scrubwoman hastened to the entrance into the hall and
drew over it a heavy porti&egrave;re.
</p><p>"Help!  Help!" called Smithers's
voice faintly.  "Help! &mdash; I'm poisoned!"
</p><p>The scrubwoman began taking the
scraps of the torn letter out of the waste-paper basket and laying them carefully
on Mrs. Smithers's desk.
</p><p>There was a confused sound of struggle and the crash of an overturned chair.
The scrubwoman lifted up the broken
picture and put it on the table, standing
by it and absently smoothing out a place
in the paper torn by the splintered glass.
</p><p>"Oh, help!" came in a choking gasp
from beyond the closed door, and then in
a supreme effort, <hi rend="italic">"Alice!"</hi>
</p><p>At the sound of the name the scrubwoman smiled for the first time and
stood listening intently.
</p><p>There was a profound silence.  She
waited, and then walked softly across
the floor to where Mrs. Smithers's shawl
was lying across a chair.  Still smiling,
she held this to her face in a passion of
tenderness.  "Oh, the poor, dear, <hi rend="italic">good-for-nothing</hi> lady!" she said.</p></div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
