<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CatTrea"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="CatTrea">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Treasure of Far Island</title>
<title type="sort">treasure of far island</title>
<author>Cather, Willa Sibert</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">49</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CatTrea</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475798</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>I have made the following changes to the text: on page 244, paragraph 3, line 1, "yester'year" has become "yesteryear"; on page 247, paragraph 3, line 9, I have omitted the unnecessary quotation mark after "water."</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Treasure of Far Island</title>
<title type="sort">treasure of far island</title>
<author>Willa Sibert Cather</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>234-249</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>J.T. and E. Buckingham</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston, Mass.</pubPlace>
<date value="1902-10-27">n.s. 27 (Oct. 1902)</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy not available</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1902">1902</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-10">October, 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jessamy Town, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
	<div1 type="work" id="d3">
<pb n="234"/>
<head><hi rend="bold">The Treasure of Far Island</hi>
<lb/>By Willa Sibert Cather
</head>

<div2 type="chapter" n="1" id="d4">
<head>I.</head>

<lg type="epigraph">
<l>"Dark brown is the river,</l>
<l rend="indent">Golden is the sand;</l>
<l>It flows along forever,</l>
<l rend="indent">With trees on either hand."</l>
<lb/>
<l><hi rend="italic">&mdash;Robert Louis Stevenson.</hi></l>
</lg>

<p>
FAR ISLAND is an oval sand bar, half a mile in length and perhaps a
hundred yards wide, which lies about two miles up from Empire City in a
turbid little Nebraska river.  The island is known chiefly to the
children who dwell in that region, and generation after generation of
them have claimed it; fished there, and pitched their tents under the
great arched tree, and built camp fires on its level, sandy
outskirts.  In the middle of the island, which is always above water
except in flood time, grow thousands of yellow-green creek willows and
cottonwood seedlings, brilliantly green, even when the hottest winds
blow, by reason of the surrounding moisture.  In the summer months,
when the capricious stream is low, the children's empire is extended
by many rods, and a long irregular beach of white sand is exposed
along the east coast of the island, never out of the water long enough
to acquire any vegetation, but dazzling white, ripple marked, and full
of possibilities for the imagination.  The island is No-Man's-Land;
every summer a new chief claims it and it has been called by many
names; but it seemed particularly to belong to the two children who
christened it Far Island, partially because they were the original
discoverers and claimants, but more especially because they were of
that favored race whom a New England sage called the true land-lords
and sea-lords of the world.  </p><p>One afternoon, early in June, the
Silvery Beaches of Far Island were glistening in the sun like pounded
glass, and the same slanting yellow rays that scorched the sand beat
upon the windows of the passenger train from the East as it swung into
the Republican Valley from the uplands.  Then a young man dressed in a
suit of gray tweed changed his seat in order to be on the side of the
car next the river.  When he crossed the car several women looked up
and smiled, for it was with a movement of boyish abandon and an
audible chuckle of delight that he threw himself into the seat to
watch for the shining curves of the river as they unwound through the
trees.  He was sufficiently distinguished in appearance to interest
even tired women at the end of a long, sultry day's travel.  As the
train rumbled over a trestle built above a hollow grown up with
sunflowers and ironweed, he sniffed <pb n="235"/>  with delight
the rank odor, familiar to the prairie bred man, that is exhaled by
such places as evening approaches.  "Ha," he murmured under his breath,
"there's the white chalk cliff where the Indians used to run the
buffalo over Bison Leap&mdash;we kids called it&mdash;the remote sea wall of the
boy world.  I'm getting home sure enough.  And heavens! there's the
island, Far Island, the Ultima Thule; and the arched tree, and Spy
Glass Hill, and the Silvery Beaches; my heart's going like a boy's.
'Once on a day he sailed away, over the sea to Skye.'" </p><p>He sat
bolt upright with his lips tightly closed and his chest swelling, for
he was none other than the original discoverer of the island, Douglass
Burnham, the playwright&mdash;our only playwright, certain critics
content&mdash;and, for the first time since he left it a boy, he was coming
home.  It was only twelve years ago that he had gone away, when Pagie
and Temp and Birkner and Shorty Thompson had stood on the station
siding and waved him good-by, while he shut his teeth to keep the tears
back; and now the train bore him up the old river valley, through the
meadows where he used to hunt for cat-tails, along the streams where he
had paddled his canvas boat, and past the willow-grown island where he
had buried the pirate's treasure,&mdash;a man with a man's work done and the
world well in hand.  Success had never tasted quite so sweet as it
tasted then.  The whistle sounded, the brakeman called Empire City, and
Douglass crossed to the other side of the car and looked out toward the
town, which lay half a mile up from the station on a low range of
hills, half hidden by the tall cottonwood trees that still shaded its
streets.  Down the curve of the track he could see the old railroad
"eating house," painted the red Burlington color; on the hill above
the town the standpipe towered up from the tree-tops.  Douglass felt
the years dropping away from him.  The train stopped.  Waiting on the
platform stood his father and a tall spare man, with a straggling
colorless beard, whose dejected stoop and shapeless hat and ill
fitting clothes were in themselves both introduction and biography.
The narrow chest, long arms, and skinny neck were not to be mistaken.
it was Rhinehold Birkner, old Rhine who had not been energetic enough
to keep up his father's undertaking business, and who now sold sewing
machines and parlor organs in a feeble attempt to support an invalid
wife and ten children, all colorless and narrow chested like himself.
Douglass sprang from the platform and grasped his father's hand.
</p><p>"Hello, father, hello, Rhine, where are the other fellows?  Why,
that's so, you must be the only one left.  Heavens! how we <hi rend="italic">have</hi>
scattered.  What a lot of talking we two have got before us."
</p><p>Probably no event had transpired since Rhine's first baby was
born that had meant so much to him as Douglass's return, but he only
chuckled, putting his limp, rough hand into the young man's smooth,
warm one, and ventured,&mdash; </p><p>"Jest the same old coon, Doug."
</p><p>"How's mother, father?" Doug-<pb n="236"/> lass asked as
he hunted for his checks.  </p><p>"She's well, son, but she thought
she couldn't leave supper to come down to meet you.  She has been
cooking pretty much all day and worrying for fear the train would be
late and your supper would spoil."  </p><p>Of course she has.  When I
am elected to the Academy mother will worry about my supper."
Douglass felt a trifle nervous and made a dash for the shabby little
street car which ever since he could remember had been drawn by mules
that wore jingling bells on their collars.  </p><p>A silence settled
down over the occupants of the car as the mules trotted off.  Douglass
felt that his father stood somewhat in awe of him, or at least in awe
of that dread Providence which ordered such dark things as that a
hard-headed, money-saving real estate man should be the father of a
white fingered playwright who spent more on his fads in a year than
his father had saved by the thrift of a lifetime.  All the hundred
things Douglass had had to say seemed congested upon his tongue, and
though he had a good measure of that cheerful assurance common to
young people whom the world has made much of, he felt a strange
embarrassment in the presence of this angular gray-whiskered man who
used to warm his jacket for him in the hayloft.  </p><p>His mother was
waiting for him under the bittersweet vines on the porch, just where
she had always stood to greet him when he came home for his college
vacations, and, as Douglass had lived in a world where the emotions
are cultivated and not despised, he was not ashamed of the lump that
rose in his throat when he took her in his arms.  She hurried him out
of the dark into the parlor lamplight and looked him over from head to
foot to assure herself that he was still the handsomest of men, and
then she told him to go into her bedroom to wash his face for supper.
She followed him, unable to take her eyes from this splendid creature
whom all the world claimed but who was only hers after all.  She
watched him take off his coat and collar, rejoicing in the freshness
of his linen and the whiteness of his skin; even the color of his silk
suspenders seemed a matter of importance to her.  </p><p>"Douglass,"
she said impressively, "Mrs. Governor gives a reception for you
to-morrow night, and I have promised her that you will read some
selections from your plays."  </p><p>This was a matter which was very
near Mrs. Burnham's heart.  Those dazzling first nights and receptions
and author's dinners which happened out in the great world were merely
hearsay, but it was a proud day when her son was held in honor by the
women of her own town, of her own church; women she had shopped and
marketed and gone to sewing circle with, women whose cakes and
watermelon pickles won premiums over hers at the county fair.
</p><p>"Read?" ejaculated Douglass, looking out over the towel and
pausing in his brisk rubbing, "why, mother, dear, I can't read, not any
more than a John rabbit.  Besides, <pb n="237"/>  plays aren't
meant to be read.  Let me give them one of my old stunts; 'The Polish
Boy' or 'Regulus to the Carthaginians.'" </p><p>"But you must do it,
my son; it won't do to disappoint Mrs.  Governor.  Margie was over
this morning to see about it.  She has grown into a very pretty
girl."  When his mother spoke in that tone Douglass acquiesced, just
as naturally as he helped himself to her violet water, the same kind,
he noticed, that he used to covertly sprinkle on his handkerchief when
he was primping for Sunday school after she had gone to church.
</p><p>"Mrs. Governor still leads the pack, then?  What a civilizing
influence she has been in this community.  Taught most of us all the
manners we ever knew.  Little Margie has grown up pretty, you say?
Well, I should never have thought it.  How many boys have I slugged for
yelling 'Reddy, go dye your hair green' at her.  She was not an
indifferent slugger herself and never exactly stood in need of
masculine protection.  What a wild Indian she was!  Game, clear
through, though!  I never found such a mind in a girl.  But <hi rend="italic">is</hi>
she a girl?  I somehow always fancied she would grow up a man&mdash;and a
ripping fine one.  Oh, I see you are looking at me hard!  No, mother,
the girls don't trouble me much."  His eyes met hers laughingly in the
glass as he parted his hair.  "You spoiled me so outrageously that
women tell me frankly I'm a selfish cad and they will have none of me."
</p><p>His mother handed him his coat with a troubled glance.  "I was
afraid, my son, that some of those actresses&mdash;" </p><p>The young man
laughed outright.  "Oh, never worry about them, mother.  Wait till
you've seen them at rehearsals in soiled shirt-waists wearing out
their antiques and doing what they call 'resting' their hair.  Poor
things!  They have to work too hard to bother about being attractive."
</p><p>He went out into the dining-room where the table was set for him
just as it had always been when he came home on that same eight o'clock
train from college.  There were all his favorite viands and the old
family silver spread on the white cloth with the maidenhair fern
pattern, under the soft lamplight.  It had been years since he had
eaten by the mild light of a kerosene lamp.  By his plate stood his
own glass that his grandmother had given him with "For a Good Boy"
ground on the surface which was dewy from the ice within.  The other
glasses were unclouded and held only fresh water from the pump, for
his mother was very economical about ice and held the most exaggerated
views as to the pernicious effects of ice water on the human stomach.
Douglass only got it because he was the first dramatist of the country
and a great man.  When he decided that he would like a cocktail and
asked for whiskey, his mother dealt him out a niggardly tablespoonful,
saying, "That's as much as you ought to have at your age, Douglass."
When he went out into the kitchen to greet the old servant and get
some ice for his <pb n="238"/>  drink, his mother hurried after
him crying with solicitude,&mdash; </p><p>"I'll get the ice for you,
Douglass.  Don't you go into the refrigerator; you always leave the
ice uncovered and it wastes."  </p><p>Douglass threw up his hands,
"Mother, whatever I may do in the world I shall never be clever enough
to be trusted with that refrigerator.  'Into all the chambers of the
palace mayest thou go, save into this thou shalt not go.'" And now he
knew he was at home, indeed, for his father stood chuckling in the
doorway, washing his hands from the milking, and the old servant threw
her apron over her head to stifle her laughter at this strange
reception of a celebrity.  The memory of his luxurious rooms in New
York, where he lived when he was an artist, faded dim; he was but a
boy again in his father's house and must not keep supper waiting.
</p><p>The next evening Douglass with resignation accompanied his
father and mother to the reception given in his honor.  The town had
advanced somewhat since his day; and he was amused to see his father
appear in an apology for a frock coat and a black tie, such as
Kentucky politicians wear.  Although people wore frock coats nowadays
they still walked to receptions, and as Douglass climbed the hill the
whole situation struck him as farcical.  He dropped his mother's arm
and ran up to the porch with his hat in his hand, laughing.  "Margie!"
he called, intending to dash through the house until he found her.
But in the vestibule he bumped up against something large and
splendid, then stopped and caught his breath.  A woman stood in the
dark by the hall lamp with a lighted match in her hand.  She was in
white and very tall.  The match burned but a moment; a moment the
light played on her hair, red as Etruscan gold and piled high above
the curve of the neck and head; a moment upon the oval chin, the lips
curving upward and red as a crimson cactus flower; the deep, gray,
fearless eyes; the white shoulders framed about with darkness.  Then
the match went out, leaving Douglass to wonder whether, like Anchises,
he had seen the vision that should forever blind him to the beauty of
mortal women.  </p><p>"I beg your pardon," he stammered, backing
toward the door, "I was looking for Miss Van Dyck.  Is she&mdash;" Perhaps
it was a mere breath of stifled laughter, perhaps it was a recognition
by some sense more trustworthy than sight and subtler than mind; but
there seemed a certain familiarity in the darkness about him, a
certain sense of the security and peace which one experiences among
dear and intimate things, and with widening eyes he said softly,&mdash;
</p><p>"Tell me, is this Margie?"  </p><p>There was just a murmur of
laughter from the tall, white figure.  "I was going to be presented to
you in the most proper form, and now you've spoiled it all.  How are
you, Douglass, and did you get a whipping this time?  You've played
hooky longer than usual.  Ten years, isn't it?"  She put out her hand
in the dark and he took it and drew it through his arm.
</p>


<pb n="239"/>

<p>"No, I didn't get a whipping, but I may get worse.  I
wish I'd come back five years ago.  I would if I had known," he said
promptly.  </p><p>The reading was just as stupid as he had said it
would be, but his audience enjoyed it and he enjoyed his audience.
There was the old deacon who had once caught him in his watermelon
patch and set the dog on him; the president of the W. C. T. U., with
her memorable black lace shawl and cane, who still continued to send
him temperance tracts, mindful of the hundredth sheep in the parable;
his old Sunday school teacher, a good man of limited information who
never read anything but his Bible and Teachers' Quarterly, and who had
once hung a cheap edition of "Camille" on the church Christmas tree
for Douglass, with an inscription on the inside to the effect that the
fear of the Lord is the beginning of Wisdom.  There was the village
criminal lawyer, one of those brilliant wrecks sometimes found in
small towns, who, when he was so drunk he could not walk, used to lie
back in his office chair and read Shakespeare by the hour to a little
barefoot boy.  Next him sat the rich banker who used to offer the boys
a quarter to hitch up his horse for him, and then drive off,
forgetting all about the quarter.  Then there were fathers and mothers
of Douglass's old clansmen and vassals who were scattered all over the
world now.  After the reading Douglass spent half an hour chatting
with nice tiresome old ladies who reminded him of how much he used to
like their tea-cakes and cookies, and answering labored compliments
with genuine feeling.  Then he went with a clear conscience and light
heart whither his eyes had been wandering ever since he had entered
the house.  </p><p>"Margie, I needn't apologize for not recognizing
you, since it was such an involuntary compliment.  However did you
manage to grow up like this?  Was it boarding school that did it?  I
might have recognized you with your hair down, and oh, I'd know you
anywhere when you smile!  The teeth are just the same.  Do you still
crack nuts with them?"  </p><p>"I haven't tried it for a long time.
How remarkably little the years change you, Douglass.  I haven't seen
you since the night you brought out 'The Clover Leaf,' and I heard
your curtain speech.  Oh, I was very proud of our Pirate Chief!"
</p><p>Douglass sat down on the piano stool and looked searchingly into
her eyes, which met his with laughing frankness.  </p><p>"What! you
were in New York then and didn't let me know?  There was a day when
you wouldn't have treated me so badly.  Didn't you want to see me just
a little bit&mdash;out of curiosity?"  </p><p>"Oh, I was visiting some
school friends who said it would be atrocious to bother you, and the
newspapers were full of interesting details about your being so busy
that you ate and got shaved at the theatre.  Then one's time isn't
one's own when one is visiting, you know."  She saw the hurt
expression on his face and repented, add-<pb n="240"/> ing gayly,
"But I may as well confess that I kept a sharp lookout for you on the
street, and when I did meet you you didn't know me."  </p><p>"And you
didn't stop me?  That's worse yet.  How in Heaven's name was I to know
you?  Accost a goddess and say, 'Oh yes, you used to be a Pirate Chief
and wear a butcher knife in your belt.' But I hadn't grown into an
Apollo, save the mark! and you knew me well enough.  I couldn't have
passed you like that in a strange land."  </p><p>"No, you do your duty
by your countrymen, Douglass.  You haven't grown haughty.  One by one
our old townspeople go out to see the world and bring us back tales of
your glory.  What unpromising specimens have you not dined and wined
in New York!  Why even old Skin Jackson, when he went to New York to
have his eyes treated, you took to the Waldorf and to the Players'
Club, where he drank with the Immortals.  How do you have the courage
to do it?  <hi rend="italic">Did</hi> he wear those dreadful gold nugget shirt studs
that he dug up in Colorado when we were young?"  </p><p>"Even the
same, Margie, and he scored a hit with them.  But you are dodging the
point.  When and where did you see me in New York?"  </p><p>"Oh, it
was one evening when you were crossing Madison Square.  You were
probably going to the theatre for Flashingham and Miss Grew were with
you and you seemed in a hurry."  Margie wished now that she had not
mentioned the incident.  "I remember that was the time I so deeply
offended your mother on my return by telling her that Miss Grew had
announced her engagement to you.  How did it come out?  She certainly
did announce it."  </p><p>"Doubtless, but it was entirely a
misunderstanding on the lady's part.  We never were anything of the
sort," said Douglass impatiently.  "That is a disgusting habit of
Edith's; she announces a new engagement every fortnight as
mechanically as the butler announces dinner.  About once a month she
calls the dear Twelfth Night girls together to a solemn high tea and
gently breaks the news of a new engagement, and they kiss and cry over
her and say the things they have said a dozen times before and go away
tittering.  Why she has been engaged to every society chap in New York
and to the whole Milton family, with the possible exception of Sir
Henry, and her papa has cabled his blessing all over the known world
to her.  But it is a waste of time to talk about such nonsense; don't
let's," he urged.  </p><p>"I think it is very interesting; I don't
indulge in weekly engagements myself.  But there is one thing I do
want to know, Douglass; I want to know how you did it."  </p><p>"Did
what?"  </p><p>Margie threw out her hands with an impetuous gesture.
"Oh, all of it, all the wonderful things you have done.  You remember
that night when we lay on the sand bar&mdash;" </p><p>"The Uttermost
Desert," interrupted Douglass softly.  </p><p>"Yes, the Uttermost
Desert, and in the light of the driftwood fire we planned the conquest
of the world? <pb n="241"/>  Well, other people plan, too, and
fight and suffer and fail the world over, and a very few succeed at
the bitter end when they are old and it is no longer worth while.  But
you have done it as they used to do it in the fairy tales, without
soiling your golden armor, and I can't find one line in your face to
tell me that you have suffered or found life bitter to your tongue.
How have you cheated fate?"  </p><p>Douglass looked about him and saw
that the guests had thronged about the punchbowl, and his mother,
beaming in her new black satin, was relating touching incidents of his
infancy to a group of old ladies.  He leaned forward, clasped his
hands between his knees, and launched into an animated description of
how his first play written at college, had taken the fancy of an old
school friend of his father's who had turned manager.  The second, a
political farce, had put him fairly on his feet.  Then followed his
historical drama, "Lord Fairfax," in which he had at first failed
completely.  He told her of those desperate days in New York when he
would draw his blinds and work by lamplight until he was utterly
exhausted, of how he fell ill and lost the thread of his play and used
to wander about the streets trying to beat it out of the paving stones
when the very policemen who jostled him on the crossings knew more
about "Lord Fairfax" than he.  </p><p>As he talked he felt the old
sense of power, lost for many years; the power of conveying himself
wholly to her in speech, of awakening in her mind every tint and
shadow and vague association that was in his at the moment.  He quite
forgot the beauty of the woman beside him in the exultant realization
of comradeship, the egoistic satisfaction of being wholly understood.
Suddenly he stopped short.  </p><p>"Come, Margie, you're not playing
fair, you're telling me nothing about yourself.  What plays have you
been playing?  Pirate or enchanted princess or sleeping beauty or
Helen of Troy, to the disaster of men?"  </p><p>Margie sighed as she
awoke out of the fairyland.  Doug's tales were as wonderful as ever.
</p><p>"Oh, I stopped playing long ago.  I have grown up and you have
not.  Some one has said that is wherein geniuses are different; they
go on playing and never grow up.  So you see you're only a case of
arrested development, after all."  </p><p>"I don't believe it, you
play still, I can see it in your eyes.  And don't say genius to me.
People say that to me only when they want to be disagreeable or tell
me how they would have written my plays.  The word is my bogie.  But
tell me, are the cat-tails ripe in the Salt Marshes, and will your
mother let you wade if the sun is warm, and do the winds still smell
sharp with salt when they blow through the mists at night?"
</p><p>"Why, Douglass, did the wind always smell salty to you there
too?  It does to me yet, and you know there isn't a particle of salt
there.  Why did we ever name them the Salt Marshes?"  </p><p>Because
they <hi rend="italic">were</hi> the Salt Marshes and couldn't have had any
<pb n="242"/>  other name any more than the Far Island could.  I
went down to those pestiferous Maremme marshes in Italy to see whether
they would be as real as our marshes, but they were not real at all;
only miles and miles of bog.  And do the nightingales still sing in
the grove?"  </p><p>"Yes.  Other people call them ring doves&mdash;but they
still sing there."  </p><p>"And you still call them nightingales to
yourself and laugh at the density of big people?"  </p><p>"Yes,
sometimes."  </p><p>Later in the evening Douglass found another
opportunity, and this time he was fortunate enough to encounter Margie
alone as she was crossing the veranda.  </p><p>"Do you know why I have
come home in June, instead of July as I had intended, Margie?  Well,
sit down and let me tell you.  They don't need you in there just now.
About a month ago I changed my apartment in New York, and as I was
sorting over my traps I came across a box of childish souvenirs.
Among them was a faded bit of paper on which a map was drawn with
elaborate care.  It was the map of an island with curly blue lines all
around it to represent water, such as we used always to draw around
the continents in our geography class.  On the west coast of the
island a red sword was sticking upright in the earth.  Beneath this
scientific drawing was an inscription to the effect that '<hi rend="italic">whoso
should dig twelve paces west of the huge fallen tree, in direct line
with the path made by the setting sun on the water on the tenth day of
June, should find the great treasure and his heart's desire!</hi>'"
</p><p>Margie laughed and applauded gently with her hands.  "And so you
have come to dig for it; come two thousand miles almost.  There's a
dramatic situation for you.  I have my map still, and I've often
contemplated going down to Far Island and digging, but it wouldn't have
been fair, for the treasure was really yours, after all."
</p><p>"Well, you are going now, and on the tenth day of June, that's
next Friday, for that's what I came home for, and I had to spoil the
plans and temper of a manager and all his company to do it."
</p><p>"Nonsense, there are too many mosquitoes on Far Island and I
mind them more than I used to.  Besides there are no good boats like
the <hi rend="italic">Jolly Rodger</hi> nowadays."  </p><p>"We'll go if I have to
build another <hi rend="italic">Jolly Rodger</hi>.  You can't make me believe you are
afraid of mosquitoes.  I know too well the mettle of your pasture.
Please do, Margie, please."  He used his old insidious coaxing tone.
</p><p>"Douglass, you have made me do dreadful things enough by using
that tone of voice to me.  I believe you used to hypnotize me.  Will
you never, never grow up?"  </p><p>"Never so long as there are
pirate's treasures to dig for and you will play with me, Margie.  Oh,
I wish I had some of the cake that Alice ate in Wonderland and could
make you a little girl again."  </p><p>That night, after the household
was asleep, Douglass went out for a walk about the old town, treading
the ways he had trod when he was a


<pb n="243"/>

founder of cities and a
leader of hosts.  But he saw few of the old landmarks, for the blaze
of Etruscan gold was in his eyes, and he felt as a man might feel who
in some sleepy humdrum Italian village had unearthed a new marble
goddess, as beautiful as she of Milo; and he felt as a boy might feel
who had lost all his favorite marbles and his best pea shooter and the
dog that slept with him, and had found them all again.  He tried to
follow, step by step, the wonderful friendship of his childhood.
</p><p>A child's normal attitude toward the world is that of the
artist, pure and simple.  The rest of us have to do with the solids of
this world, whereas only their form and color exist for the painter.
So, in every wood and street and building there are things, not seen
of older people at all, which make up their whole desirableness or
objectionableness to children.  There are maps and pictures formed by
cracks in the walls of bare and unsightly sleeping chambers which make
them beautiful; smooth places on the lawn where the grass is greener
than anywhere else and which are good to sit upon; trees which are
valuable by reason of the peculiar way in which the branches grow, and
certain spots under the scrub willows along the creek which are in a
manner sacred, like the sacrificial groves of the Druids, so that a
boy is almost afraid to walk there.  Then there are certain carpets
which are more beautiful than others, because with a very little help
from the imagination they become the rose garden of the Thousand and
One Nights; and certain couches which are peculiarly adapted for
playing Sindbad in his days of ease, after the toilsome voyages were
over.  A child's standard of value is so entirely his own, and his
peculiar part and possessions in the material objects around him are
so different from those of his elders, that it may be said his rights
are granted by a different lease.  To these two children the entire
external world, like the people who dwelt in it, had been valued
solely for what they suggested to the imagination, and people and
places alike were merely stage properties, contributing more or less
to the intensity of their inner life. </p>
</div2>


<div2 type="chapter" n="2" id="d5">
<head>II.</head>

<lg type="epigraph">
<l>"Green leaves a-floating</l>
<l>Castles of the foam,</l>
<l>Boats of mine a-boating</l>
<l>When will all come home?"</l>
</lg>

<p>Sand Douglass as they pulled from the mill wharf out into the rapid
current of the river, which that morning seemed the most beautiful and
noble of rivers, an enchanted river flowing peacefully out of Arcady
with the Happy Isles somewhere in the distance.  The ripples were
touched with silver and the sky was as blue as though it had just been
made to-day; the cow bells sounded faintly from the meadows along the
shore like the bells of fairy cities ringing on the day the prince
errant brought home his bride; the meadows that sloped to the water's
edge were the greenest in all the world because they were the meadows
of the long ago; and the flowers that grew there <pb n="244"/>
were the freshest and sweetest of growing things because once, long
ago in the golden age, two children had gathered other flowers like
them, and the beauties of vanished summers were everywhere.  Douglass
sat in the end of the boat, his back to the sun and his straw hat
tilted back on his head, pulling slowly and feeling that the day was
fine rather than seeing it; for his eyes were fixed upon his helmsman
in the other end of the boat, who sat with her hat in her lap, shading
her face with a white parasol, and her wonderful hair piled high on
her head like a helmet of gleaming bronze.  </p><p>Of all the
possessions of their childhood's Wonderland, Far Island had been
dearest; it was graven on their hearts as Calais was upon Mary
Tudor's.  Long before they had set foot upon it the island was the
goal of their loftiest ambitions and most delightful imaginings.  They
had wondered what trees grew there and what delightful spots were
hidden away under the matted grapevines.  They had even decided that a
race of kindly dwarfs must inhabit it and had built up a civilization
and historic annals for these imaginary inhabitants, surrounding the
sand bar with all the mystery and enchantment which was attributed to
certain islands of the sea by the mariners of Greece.  Douglass and
Margie had sometimes found it expedient to admit other children into
their world, but for the most part these were but hewers of wood and
drawers of water, who helped to shift the scenery and construct the
balcony and place the king's throne, and were no more in the
atmosphere of the play than were the supers who watched Mr. Keane's
famous duel with Richmond.  Indeed Douglass frequently selected the
younger and more passive boys for his vassals on the principle that
they did as they were bid and made no trouble.  But there is something
of the explorer in the least imaginative of boys, and when Douglass
came to the building of his famous boat, the <hi rend="italic">Jolly Rodger</hi>, he
found willing hands to help him.  Indeed the sawing and hammering, the
shavings and cut fingers and blood blisters fell chiefly to the lot of
dazzled lads who claimed no part in the craft, and who gladly trotted
and sweated for their board and keep in this fascinating play world
which was so much more exhilarating than any they could make for
themselves.  </p><p>"Think of it, Margie, we are really going back to
the island after so many years, just you and I, the captain and his
mate.  Where are the other gallant lads that sailed with us then?"
</p><p>"Where are the snows of yesteryear?" sighed Margie softly.  "It
is very sad to grow up."  </p><p>"Sad for them, yes.  But we have
never grown up, you know, we have only grown more considerate of our
complexions," nodding at the parasol.  "What a little mass of freckles
you used to be, but I liked you freckled, too.  Let me see: old Temp
is commanding a regiment in the Philippines, and Bake has a cattle
ranch in Wyoming, Mac is a government clerk in Washington, Jim keeps
his father's hardware store, poor Ned and Shorty went down in
<pb n="245"/>  a catboat on the Hudson while they were at college
(I went out to hunt for the bodies, you know), and old Rhine is
selling sewing machines; he never did get away at all, did he?"
</p><p>"No, not for any length of time.  You know it used to frighten
Rhine to go to the next town to see a circus.  He went to Arizona once
for his lungs, but his family never could tell where he was for he
headed all his letters 'Empire City, Nebraska,' from habit."
</p><p>"Oh, that's delightful, Margie, you must let me use that.  Rhine
would carry Empire City through Europe with him and never know he was
out of it.  Have I told you about Pagie?  Well, you know Pagie is
travelling for a New York tailoring house and I let his people make
some clothes for me that I had to give to Flashingham's valet.  When
he first came to town he tried to be gay, with his fond mother's
prayers still about him, a visible nimbus, and the Sunday school boy
written all over his open countenance and downy lip and large, white
butter teeth.  But I know, at heart, he still detested naughty words
and whiskey made him sick.  One day I was standing at the Hoffman
House bar with some fellows, when a slender youth, who looked like a
nice girl masquerading as a rake, stepped up and ordered a claret and
seltzer.  The whine was unmistakable.  I turned and said, even before
I had looked at him squarely, 'Oh, Pagie! if your mother saw you here!"
</p><p>"Poor Pagie!  I'll warrant he would rather have had bread and
sugar.  Do you remember how, at the Sunday school concerts on
Children's Day, you and Pagie and Shorty and Temp used to stand in a
row behind the flower wreathed pulpit rail, all in your new
round-about suits with large silk bows tied under your collars, your
hands behind you, and assure us with sonorous voices that you would
come rejoicing bringing in the sheaves?  Somehow, even then, I never
doubted that you would do it."  </p><p>The keel grated on the sand and
Douglass sprang ashore and gave her his hand.  </p><p>"Descend, Oh,
Miranda, upon your island!  Do you know, Margie, it makes me seem
fifteen again to feel this sand crunching under my feet.  I wonder if
I ever again shall feel such a thrill of triumph as I felt when I
first leaped upon this sand bar?  None of my first nights have given me
anything like it.  Do you remember <hi rend="italic">really</hi>, and did you feel the
same?"  </p><p>"Of course I remember, and I knew that you were playing
a double r&ocirc;le that day, and that you were really the
trail-breaker and world-finder inside of the pirate all the while.
Here are the same ripple marks on the Silvery Beaches, and here is the
great arched tree, let's run for it."  She started fleetly across the
glittering sand and Douglass fell behind to watch with immoderate joy
that splendid, generous body that governed itself so well in the open
air.  There was a wholesomeness of the sun and soil in her that was
utterly lacking in the women among whom he had lived for so long.  She
had preserved that strength of arm and <pb n="246"/>  freedom of
limb that had made her so fine a playfellow, and which modern modes of
life have well-nigh robbed the world of altogether.  Surely, he
thought, it was like that that Diana's women sped after the stag down
the slopes of Ida, with shouting and bright spear.  She caught an
overhanging branch and swung herself upon the embankment and, leaning
against the trunk of a tree, awaited him flushed and panting, her
bosom rising and falling with her quick drawn breaths.  </p><p>"Why
did you close the tree behind you, Margie?  I have always wanted to
see just how Dryads keep house," he exclaimed, brushing away a dried
leaf that had fallen on her shoulder.  </p><p>"Don't strain your
inventive powers to make compliments, Douglass; this is your vacation
and you are to rest your imagination.  See, the willows have scarcely
grown at all.  I'm sure we shall hear Pagie whimpering over there on
the Uttermost Desert where we marooned him, or singing hymns to keep
up his courage.  Now for the Huge Fallen Tree.  Do you suppose the
floods have moved it?"  </p><p>They struck through the dense willow
thicket, matted with fragrant wild grapevines which Douglass beat down
with his spade, and came upon the great white log, the bleached
skeleton of a tree, and found the cross hacked upon it, the rough
gashes of the hatchet now worn smooth by the wind and rain and the
seething of spring freshets.  Near the cross were cut the initials of
the entire pirate crew; some of them were cut on gravestones now.  The
scrub willows had grown over the spot where they had decided the
treasure must lie, and together they set to work to break them away.
Douglass paused more than once to watch the strong young creature
beside him, outlined against the tender green foliage, reaching high
and low and snapping the withes where they were weakest.  He was still
wondering whether it was not all a dream picture, and was half afraid
that his man would call him to tell him that some piqued and faded
woman was awaiting him at the theatre to quarrel about her part.
</p><p>"Still averse to manual labor, Douglass?" she laughed as she
turned to bend a tall sapling.  "The most remarkable thing about your
enthusiasm was that you had only to sing of the glories of toil to make
other people do all the work for you."  </p><p>"No, Margie, I was
thinking very hard indeed&mdash;about the Thracian women when they broke
the boughs wherewith they flayed unhappy Orpheus."  </p><p>"Now,
Douglass, you'll spoil the play.  A sentimental pirate is impossible.
Pagie was a sentimental pirate and that was what spoiled him.  A
little more of this and I will maroon you upon the Uttermost Desert."
</p><p>Douglass laughed and settled himself back among the green boughs
and gazed at her with the abandoned admiration of an artist
contemplating a masterpiece.  </p><p>When they came to the digging of
the treasure a little exertion was enough to unearth what had seemed
hidden so fabulously deep in olden time.  The chest was rotten and
fell <pb n="247"/>  apart as the spade struck it, but the glass
jar was intact, covered with sand and slime.  Douglass spread his
handkerchief upon the sand and weighted the corners down with pebbles
and upon it poured the treasure of Far Island.  There was the
manuscript written in blood, a confession of fantastic crimes, and the
Spaniard's heart in a bottle of alcohol, and Temp's Confederate bank
notes, damp and grewsome to the touch, and Pagie's rare tobacco tags,
their brilliant colors faded entirely away, and poor Shorty's bars of
tinfoil, dull and eaten with rust.  </p><p>"And, Douglass," cried
Margie, "there is your father's silver ring that was made from a
nugget; he whipped you for burying it.  You remember it was given to a
Christian knight by an English queen, and when he was slain before
Jerusalem a Saracen took it and we killed the Saracen in the desert
and cut off his finger to get the ring.  It is strange how those wild
imaginings of ours seem, in retrospect, realities, things that I
actually lived through.  I suppose that in cold fact my life was a
good deal like that of other little girls who grow up in a village; but
whenever I look back on it, it is all exultation and romance,&mdash;sea
fights and splendid galleys and Roman triumphs and brilliant caravans
winding through the desert."  </p><p>"To people who live by
imagination at all, that is the only life that goes deep enough to
leave memories.  We were artists in those days, creating for the day
only; making epics sung once and then forgotten, building empires that
set with the sun.  Nobody worked for money then, and nobody worked for
fame, but only for the joy of the doing.  Keats said the same thing
more elegantly in his May Day Ode, and we were not so unlike those
Hellenic poets who were content to sing to the shepherds and forget
and be forgotten, 'rich in the simple worship of a day.'" </p><p>"Why,
Douglass," she cried as she bent her face down to the little glass
jar, "it was really our childhood that we buried here, never guessing
what a precious thing we were putting under the ground.  That was the
real treasure of Far Island, and we might dig up the whole island for
it but all the king's horses and all the king's men could not bring it
back to us.  That voyage we made to bury our trinkets, just before you
went away to school, seems like unconscious symbolism, and somehow it
stands out from all the other good times we knew then as the happiest
of all."  She looked off where the setting sun hung low above the
water.  </p><p>"Shall I tell you why, Margie?  That was the end of our
childhood, and there the golden days died in a blaze of glory, passed
in music out of sight.  That night, after our boat had drifted away
from us, when we had to wade down the river hand in hand, we two, and
the noises and the coldness of the water frightened us, and there were
quicksands and sharp rocks and deep holes to shun, and terrible things
lurking in the woods on the shore, you cried in a different way from
the way you sometimes cried when you hurt yourself, and I found that I
loved <pb n="248"/>  you afraid better than I had ever loved you
fearless, and in that moment we grew up, and shut the gates of Eden
behind us, and our empire was at an end."  </p><p>"And now we are only
kings in exile," sighed Margie, softly, "who wander back to look down
from the mountain tops upon the happy land we used to rule."
</p><p>Douglass took her hand gently; "If there is to be any Eden on
earth again for us, dear, we must make it with our two hearts."
</p><p>There was a sudden brightness of tears in her eyes, and she drew
away from him.  "Ah, Douglass, you are determined to spoil it all.  It
is you who have grown up and taken on the ways of the world.  The play
is at an end for me."  She tried to rise, but he held her firmly.
</p><p>"From the moment I looked into your eyes in the vestibule that
night we have been parts of the same dream again.  Why, Margie, we
have more romance behind us than most men and women ever live."
</p><p>Margie's face grew whiter, but she pushed his hand away and the
look in her eyes grew harder.  "This is only a new play, Douglass, and
you will weary of it to-morrow.  I am not so good at playing as I used
to be.  I am no longer content with the simple worship of a day."
</p><p>In her touch, in her white face, he divined the greatness of
what she had to give.  He bit his lip and answered, "I think you owe
me more confidence than that, if only for the sake of those days when
we trusted each other entirely."  </p><p>She turned with a quick flash
of remorseful tenderness, as she used to do when she hurt him at
play.  "I only want to keep you from hurting us both, Douglass.  We
neither of us could go on feeling like this.  It's only the dregs of
the old enchantment.  Things have always come easily to you, I know,
for at your birth nature and fortune joined to make you great.  But
they do not come so to me; I should wake and weep."  </p><p>"Then
weep, my princess, for I will wake you now!"  </p><p>The fire and
fancy that had so bewitched her girlhood that no other man had been
able to dim the memory of it came furiously back upon her, with arms
that were new and strange and strong, and with tenderness stranger
still in this wild fellow of dreams and jests; and all her vows never
to grace another of his Roman triumphs were forgotten.  </p><p>"You
are right, Margie; the pirate play is ended and the time has come to
divide the prizes, and I choose what I chose fifteen years ago.  Out
of the spoils of a lifetime of crime and bloodshed I claimed only the
captive princess, and I claim her still.  I have sought the world over
for her, only to find her at last in the land of lost content."
</p><p>Margie lifted her face from his shoulder, and, after the manner
of women of her kind, she played her last card rhapsodically.  "And
she, O Douglass! the years she has waited have been longer than the
waiting of Penelope, and she has woven a thousand webs of dreams by
night and torn them asunder by day, and looked out across the Salt
Marshes for the night train, and still <pb n="249"/>  you did not
come.  I was only your pensioner like Shorty and Temp and the rest,
and I could not play anything alone.  You took my world with you when
you went and left me only a village of mud huts and my loneliness."
</p><p>As her eyes and then her lips met his in the dying light, he
knew that she had caught the spirit of the play, and that she would
ford the river by night with him again and never be afraid.
</p><p>The locust chirped in the thicket; the setting sun threw a
track of flame across the water; the willows burned with fire and were
not consumed; a glory was upon the sand and the river and upon the
Silvery Beaches; and these two looked about over God's world and saw
that it was good.  In the western sky the palaces of crystal and gold
were quenched in night, like the cities of old empires; and out of the
east rose the same moon that has glorified all the romances of the
world,&mdash;that lighted Paris over the blue &AElig;gean and the feet of
young Montague to the Capulets' orchard.  The dinner hour in Empire
City was long past, but the two upon the island wist naught of these
things, for they had become as the gods, who dwell in their golden
houses, recking little of the woes and labors of mortals, neither
heeding any fall of rain or snow.  </p>

</div2>
</div1>
</body>

</text>

</TEI.2>
