<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="ChaEffe"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="ChaEffe">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Effects of Negro Suffrage</title>
<title type="sort">effects of negro suffrage</title>
<author>Chalmers, H.H.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">26</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">ChaEffe</idno>
<date value="1998">1998</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1998 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475799</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Effects of Negro Suffrage</title>
<title level="j">North American Review, volume 132</title>
<title type="sort">effects of negro suffrage</title>
<author>H.H. Chalmers</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 239-248</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>D. Appleton and Company</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1881">1881</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: The University of Virginia Library, call number AP2.N7, volume 132</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1881">1881</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
<term>African American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1998-06">June 1998</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Anne Stinehart, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">



<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> <pb n="239"/>
<head>THE EFFECTS OF NEGRO SUFFRAGE.</head>


<p>
     THIRTEEN years have elapsed since, by act of Congress, negro suffrage was established in
ten States of the Union, and ten years since, by amendment of the federal Constitution, it was
made universal throughout the nation.
</p><p>     The enfranchisement of so large a mass of new electors, and the instant elevation of so much
of ignorance and pauperism to complete equality with wealth and intelligence, was never before,
in the history of the world, wrought by a single legislative act. In several of the States it put the
representatives of that race who alone knew anything of public affairs, or of private virtue, in a
hopeless minority as compared with that race who had ever been barbarians save when they were
slaves, and who were destitute alike of property, education, or morality. Whatever may have
been the motives of those who inaugurated the scheme, &mdash; whether they were prompted by
considerations of patriotic devotion to the public good and by a sense of justice to the helpless
blacks, or whether they sought the perpetuation of partisan supremacy, &mdash; it must be admitted by
their most devoted adherents that they took the risk of a tremendous political experiment.
Desperate indeed must have been the ills that afflicted the body politic to justify a treatment so
heroic.
</p><p>     We are not yet sufficiently removed from the strife evoked by these measures to do impartial
justice to the motives of their authors, but time enough has elapsed to enable us to see something
of the practical workings of the hazardous venture, and as he who lives in the present and for the
future is concerned more with consequences than with causes, it will be at once more easy and
more profitable to estimate effects than to divine motives. The most superficial effect of the
enfranchisement of the blacks has been to give them the balance of power in
   <pb n="240"/>
all our recent political struggles. There has been no presidential election, since the suffrage was
conferred upon them, in which the result would not have been different if their votes had been
eliminated from the contest. Certainly this is true of the last two elections. In that event, Mr.
Tilden's majority would have been enormous before the people and quite overwhelming in the
electoral college. He would have carried every Southern State, and a considerable number of
Northern ones in which, by the assistance of negro votes, Mr. Hayes was successful.
</p><p>     In 1880, the subtraction of the negro vote would have given to the Democrats the States of
Ohio and Indiana both in October and November, and in the latter month would have given to
Hancock New York, Connecticut, and perhaps other Northern States. While the adherents of the
successful party will, of course, consider the effect of the negro vote beneficial to the country in
preventing such results, it is a noteworthy fact that the <hi rend="italic">white race</hi>, who have made
America what it is, and who are regarded by foreign nations as constituting the American
people, have twice, if not thrice, been, by negro suffrage, denied the rulers of their choice.
     </p><p>But this is a mere surface view of the subject, and these are, it is to be hoped, only the
temporary and accidental results of negro enfranchisement. Its deeper and more lasting effects
are to be found in that demoralization of our politics which has sprung from the debasement of
the elective franchise. It was madness to suppose that the body of electors could be swollen by
the sudden injection into it of such an enormous mass of ignorance, pauperism, and immorality
without debasing the value of the franchise in popular estimation, and without breaking down, in
great measure, our reverence for the ballot-box as the supreme arbiter of our disputes. That these
effects have already been partially wrought is quite apparent. Never was the atmosphere of
American politics so rife with charges and suspicions of bribery and fraud in conducting
elections and ascertaining their results as in the last ten years, and these things seem to increase
with each recurring election. At the South, there can be no doubt that bad men engage in and
good men shut their eyes to political practices which, in other days, all parties would have made
haste to visit with exemplary punishment. At the North, the raising of large sums of money is
deemed essential to the inauguration of every canvass, and the
   <pb n="241"/>
question of how much money the friends of a candidate for nomination can raise, is more often
asked in party conventions than the question what are his qualifications for the office.
</p><p>     Returning-boards organized to count in the party candidates, ballot-boxes surrounded by
swarms of paid party officials shameless assessments on the salaries of public officers, cipher
dispatches breathing corruption in every line, electoral commissions composed of the highest in
the land, where each member is sworn to decide like a judge, and where each member votes like
a partisan, &mdash; these are the new devices, these the confessed practices which shame our recent
politics, and are fast breaking down American reverence for the ballot-box. Some of them are
the immediate, and all, perhaps, to some extent, the remote results of negro suffrage. Some are
directly traceable to it, and all have sprung from that general political demoralization and that
wide-spread popular belief that elections no longer elect which, if it did not originate with the
enfranchisement of the blacks, certainly then received its greatest impetus. In the winter of
1876-7, a distinguished professor of a New England university delivered an address on the evils
to be apprehended from the debasement of the suffrage by the wholesale enfranchisement of
ignorance and poverty. President Grant, in his last annual message to Congress, dwelt upon the
same topic, and suggested that some steps be taken to remedy the evils likely to ensue from it.
</p><p>     These views met the approval of the "New York Tribune" and other leading journals, and
while it is true they found utterance at a time when the then recent presidential election was
supposed, perhaps, to have resulted disastrously to the Republican party, and they have not been
followed up by similar advice under circumstances more favorable to that organization, their
inherent wisdom is not thereby, we may venture to hope, essentially diminished.
</p><p>     But it is in the Southern States that the blighting effects of negro suffrage are most apparent,
and yet, strange to say, it is there too that we find the greatest compensatory benefits resulting
from it. In 1867 the negroes of the South were mere inhabitants, not citizens of the States in
which they dwelt. Civil rights, to a limited extent, had been conferred upon them, but in many
respects they were an alien people &mdash; dwelling among but not a part of the population by which
they were surrounded.
</p><p>     That one-half of the people of a State should be legally
   <pb n="242"/>
deemed and treated as outcasts and pariahs, of a caste so low as to leave them virtually at the
mercy of the other half, would eventually have resulted in a most deplorable state of society. If
the strong arm of the federal government had interposed for the purpose of enforcing perfect
equality of civil and legal rights, and had provided for a slow and gradual acquisition of political
equality by standards of time and education and property, it might not have subserved so well the
party purposes of those who were foremost in the work of reconstruction, but surely it would
have wrought better and more wisely for the republic.
</p><p>     The ballot indeed has won for the newly enfranchised every civil and legal right, but fearful
has been the price which the country has paid for it, and direful the consequences. The
reconstruction acts manifestly if not avowedly proceeded upon the theory that the whites were
unfit to rehabilitate their upturned governments, and that this duty must be devolved upon the
negroes. While the whole of the latter were suddenly enfranchised, large classes of the former,
embracing the most cultured and experienced, were disfranchised, and as the ingenuity of
President Johnson's legal advisers sought to limit the number of the disfranchised classes,
successive acts of Congress made them yet more sweeping. While the scheme was nominally
submitted to the vote of the people of the States affected by it, no election was permitted to
stand that did not result in its favor, and in some of the States repeated elections were ordered
until the desired result was compelled. When negro domination had by these methods been
established, there ensued a scene of incompetence, profligacy, and pillage, the like of which has
never disgraced the annals of any English-speaking people.
</p><p>     It was wealth plundered by pauperism, intelligence dominated by ignorance, America ruled
by Ethiopia.
</p><p>     A vivid picture of the disgraceful scenes of this period is set forth in the "Prostrate State," a
work written by J. S. Pike, a Northern Republican, and a staff correspondent of the "New York
Tribune." If this book could be put into the hands of all our people, it would give them a more
truthful idea of the reconstruction era than is likely to be derived from the pages of "A Fool's
Errand" and of "Bricks without Straw." Mr. Pike's book fails, however, to afford an adequate
conception of one of the notable features of these grotesque caricatures on government, namely,
their utter want of power to maintain their own existence.
   <pb n="243"/>
There never was a day during the time that they were permitted to live when five hundred
resolute men could not have overthrown them in a few hours. And this fact was as well
understood by the rulers as by the ruled. It found signal illustration in the city of New Orleans,
on the 14th of September, 1874, when a few hundred members of the "White League" in less
than fifteen minutes put to rout the whole force of the State government, who were advised in
advance of the intended attack, and had prepared to resist it. After a few ill-directed volleys, the
State forces (negroes with a few white allies) fled in every direction, &mdash; the rank and file to the
swamps, and the leaders to the United States Custom-house, &mdash; and in all the State of Louisiana
not a hand was raised to restore them to power. Their overthrow was complete, and to all
appearances final, and so quickly accomplished that a distinguished gentleman visiting the city
at the time remarked that he "was sitting in the St. Charles Hotel" when "the revolution" broke
out, and though he hastened with all convenient speed to the scene of conflict, which was five
hundred yards distant, "the revolution" was over before he could get there. But at a word from
Washington the whites quietly remitted the reins of government to the hands of their trembling
rulers, and returned to their obedience.
</p><p>     As easy as it was to throw off these shackles by force, it was well-nigh impossible to do so by
the ballot-box. Apart from the numerical majorities which the blacks possessed in several States
and large sections of other States, so skillfully were the election laws framed for the promotion
of fraud, and so unscrupulous the men who counted the votes, that it was simply impossible by
any ordinary method of conducting elections to dislodge them from power. Mr. Pike thus clearly
states the situation in this regard:
</p>
    <q> "One of the great discouragements to regular and sustained efforts on the part of the whites to
resist negro sway in South Carolina has been the frauds practiced on the ballot-box. These have
been so great and audacious that voting became a farce. The party in the majority counted in
whomever they wanted elected, without any reference to the votes cast. The following testimony
discloses a worse state of things in South Carolina on this subject than ever was before seen
since voting was invented. It shows that men who were elected by a majority of thousands were
deliberately counted out, and their adversaries declared elected by overwhelming majorities. The
result has been that at the last election no voting was done in numerous districts, except by the
dominant party in the State."</q>
   <pb n="244"/>
<p>
     At length, when longer endurance became impossible; when taxes, already swollen a
thousand per cent. on former rates, were mounting still higher and threatening confiscation of all
property; when, despite these enormous levies, the bonded indebtedness grew year by year more
enormous; when millions of acres of land had already been forfeited for
unpaid taxes;<ref target="n1">[*]</ref> when all
industries were paralyzed, and the very soil seemed reluctant to bring forth its accustomed fruits,
the maddened whites burst their bonds &mdash; burst them under the forms of law and the guise of the
ballot-box, since federal power would not otherwise permit, but by means in some instances,
certainly, which a firm believer in the efficacy of the ballot-box would find it difficult to defend.
For crimes against liberty, which by comparison sink into insignificance, the people of England
brought a king to the scaffold and drenched their island in blood. For misgovernment and
corruption far less disgraceful and ruinous, the people of France guillotined a royal family and
exterminated the flower of their nobility. Let not those who have not felt the bitterness of such a
tyranny judge the whites of the South too harshly. Let it be remembered that in no time or clime
have the Caucasian race ever consented to live with the inferior ones <hi rend="italic">save as ru1ers</hi>. The
British in India, the French in Guiana, the Dutch in South Africa, the Spaniards in South
America, and our own forefathers on this continent, have abundantly demonstrated that the
white man will not be governed by the black man or the red. Sentimentalists may deplore, but
statesmen must recognize this as a fixed and irreversible fact.
</p><p>     Numbers in such a matter count for nothing. Not all the navies of the world could transport
Chinese enough to our Pacific slope to establish them there as the governing race. The Congress
of the United States might enfranchise them, but the armies of the United States could not keep
them permanently in power. No county in Massachusetts or New York would long submit to be
governed by any number of negroes who might suddenly be transplanted from the rice-fields of
Carolina or the canebrakes of Louisiana.
   <pb n="245"/>
</p><p>     The Northern man believes that the political solidity of the Southern whites bodes evil to the
republic. The Southern man knows that the solidity of the blacks, if allowed to grasp the reins of
power, involves ills so great that any remedy is better than the disease. Happily for the country,
unmistakable signs point to a disintegration of this solidity on both sides. If the whites of the
South, on the one hand, are made to see and feel that a Republican administration at Washington
neither means a relegation of their States to negro domination, nor exclusion of their section
from the practical benefits of government, nor an ostracism of themselves from public affairs;
and if the negroes, on the other hand, can be made to believe that a Democratic administration
does not threaten their enslavement or disfranchisement, this disintegration will grow daily more
rapid. But then, undoubtedly, a new evil will appear, and indeed has already begun to appear in
some sections. The deep devotion of the negro to the Republican party, and his belief that his
own salvation depended upon its success, has in the past enabled thieves and scoundrels to
plunder in the name of Republicanism; but it has at least had the merit of preserving the negro
himself from venality in the exercise of his ballot. When elections cease in his imagination to be
fraught with his liberty, and he realizes that he has no other interest in them than the rest of the
community, the enormous negro vote of the South will afford a field for the arts of the
demagogue and the briber such as the world has never seen. Without property or thrift, highly
emotional, and painfully timid, venality is as certain to follow as night follows day. They will be
bought and sold, and coaxed and bullied by unscrupulous men, and led in droves to the polls, if
not like "dumb-driven cattle," certainly most unlike free men who "know their rights, and,
knowing, dare maintain."
</p><p>     That this will become the complexion of Southern politics when the races cease to be divided
on the race line, is as certain as any proposition in political ethics. Even where the vote is not the
subject of individual purchase, it will naturally drift, as recently illustrated in Virginia, to the
side of demagoguery and of bad faith in public morals. How are republican institutions to be
preserved under such circumstances? Let us look the question fairly in the face, discarding all
prejudice, and laying aside all passion. What is the remedy for these evils? How is a government
to be carried on by universal suffrage
   <pb n="246"/>
where a majority of the electors are so unfit for the trust, and where the difficulty is
immeasurably increased by antipathies of race and the memories of two hundred years of
masterhood on one side and slavery on the other? Eventually, perhaps, by education and the
healing effects of time, but this is a slow process. Two full generations will elapse, even with the
most lavish expenditures of money (and nobly are the whites of the South meeting the burden of
such expenditures), before the mere book education can be made general.
</p><p>     White immigration would promise ultimate relief if it could be induced, but population and
capital alike shrink from contact with negro association, and from the danger of negro rule. It
is quite commonly said that immigration is repelled by Southern solidity and intolerance of
political dissent. That this is erroneous, and that the true reason is found in the unwillingness of
white laborers to come in contact with the negro, and of capitalists to seek investments where
his domination may bring confiscation, is abundantly demonstrated by the fact that Georgia
attracts more capital and Texas more immigration than any other Southern States. Nowhere are
the whites more solid or the Democratic majorities so large. It is the assurance of continued
white supremacy that permits the soil and climate of these States to exert their natural
attractions. Granting that education and immigration will ultimately solve the problem, what is
to be the condition of the people of the South during all the weary years that must intervene?
</p><p>     How long will it take to eradicate that inborn sense of superiority which every white man
feels, that instinctive recognition of his own inferiority that every negro evinces in his every
action? How long has it taken in the Northern States? Is it not just as apparent there now as it is
at the South? Will it ever cease to exist? So long as it remains, what sort of government must
there be in States where a majority, or very large minority, of the electors are the recognized
inferiors of the remainder in every aspect of life, save at the ballot-box, and this inferiority
springs, not from the personal merits of the voters, but from the inextinguishable differences of
race? How many years must elapse before some elegant and accomplished negro will lead out
the mistress of the White House to a state dinner, or an American President be glad to wed his
daughter to a millionaire whose face is as black as his diamonds may be glittering?
   <pb n="247"/>
</p><p>     These are social questions, it is true; but how can perfect political equality co-exist with a
social inferiority dependent, not upon personal merit or pecuniary advantages, but solely upon
race, and where the social inferior threatens at every election to become the political superior?
What madness will it be for the national government to attempt again, as the Hon. Geo. S.
Boutwell intimates, to interfere for the purpose of adjusting these questions in favor of the
blacks! They must be left to be settled by the people affected by them. In their settlement, what
is most needed is a clear apprehension of the situation, and calm and dispassionate consideration
on both sides of the Potomac and Ohio, and with this view the people on either side must fully
understand certain fixed facts. The men of the South must understand once for all that the
negroes, as negroes, and because their skins are black, can never be disfranchised. Their right to
vote, as a race, is as fixed and irreversible as their freedom, and the fifteenth amendment to the
national Constitution is no more likely to be repealed than the thirteenth.
</p><p>     They must understand further that governments cannot live by the means which revolutions
justify, any more than health can be maintained by the strong medicines sometimes necessary to
preserve life. The ballot-box must speak the unbiased verdict of all the lawful electors, and that
verdict must be made wise, not by force or fraud, but by such limitations on the right of suffrage
as will no longer leave intelligence and virtue at the mercy of brutality and crime.  Standards of
education and property must be enacted which for a time will disfranchise many, and to the
attainment of which, by the rising generation, the State and national governments must afford
every possible facility and aid. In this work the men of the North must aid and not obstruct. They
must understand, once for all, that the Anglo-Saxon race will not be governed by the African,
and, if they are wise, they will content themselves with aiding those who propose that the
African shall be wisely, justly, and fairly governed by the Anglo-Saxon. They must never forget
that they themselves forced this stupendous problem on the people of the South, against all their
protests and all their struggles to prevent it.
</p><p>     They must hold as enemies to both sections, as fire-brands and pestilent demagogues, those
who would stir the fires of sectional ill-will or race hatred in order to infuse spirit into a
   <pb n="248"/>
canvass, or carry an election. They must not denounce the whole Southern people as
negro-haters or bulldozers, but know and realize that everywhere throughout the South there are
thousands of earnest, thoughtful, and patriotic men who spend anxious days and sleepless nights
pondering a problem that seems impossible of solution. If the South, writhing like Laocoon in
the coils of the serpent, sometimes strikes out wildly, blindly, madly, in vain attempts to
extricate herself, it ill becomes those who fastened the monster upon her to deride or denounce
her ill-advised and frantic efforts.
</p><p>     She has the right to demand from the people of the North, and especially from the Republican
party, sympathy, not obloquy, counsel, not condemnation, and, even for the excesses and
misdeeds into which her sufferings may hurry her, the tender compassion which dropped a tear
upon the record of Uncle Toby's oath. </p>

<p>H. H. CHALMERS. </p>


<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">*</seg> <p> In 1875, one-fifth of the entire area of the State of Mississippi had been forfeited for
unpaid taxes. The enormous amount of 6,500,000 acres of land (10,000 square miles) had been
swallowed up by taxation which was virtually confiscation. This was an area larger than the
States of Massachusetts and Delaware combined.</p></note>




</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

