<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CheHann"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="CheHann">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Hot-Foot Hannibal</title>
<title type="sort">hot foot hannibal</title>
<author>Chesnutt, Charles Waddell, 1858-1932</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">32</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CheHann</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475806</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Hot-Foot Hannibal</title>
<title type="sort">hot foot hannibal</title>
<author>Charles W. Chesnutt</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 83</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 49-56</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library
Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text
Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are
composed of the text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as
in SpeFQue1 for page one of Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-02">February 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Timothy O. Jarrett</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<pb n="49"/>
<head>Chesnutt, Charles W.  "Hot-Foot Hannibal."
<hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 83 (1899): 49-56.</head>

<p>"I HATE you and despise you!  I wish never to see you or speak
to you again!"</p>
<p>"Very well; I will take care that henceforth you have no
opportunity to do either."</p>
<p> These words &mdash; the first in the passionately vibrant tones of my
sister-in-law, and the latter in the deeper and more restrained accents of
an angry man &mdash; startled me from my nap.  I had been dozing in my
hammock on the front piazza, behind the honeysuckle vine.  I had been
faintly aware of a buzz of conversation in the parlor, but had not at all
awakened to its import until these sentences fell, or, I might rather say,
were hurled upon my ear.  I presume the young people had either not
seen me lying there, &mdash; the Venetian blinds opening from the parlor
windows upon the piazza were partly closed on account of the heat, &mdash; or
else in their excitement they had forgotten my proximity.</p>
<p> I felt somewhat concerned.  The young man, I had remarked, was
proud, firm, jealous of the point of honor, and, from my observation of
him, quite likely to resent to the bitter end what he deemed a slight or an
injustice.  The girl, I knew, was quite as high-spirited as young
Murchison.  I feared she was not so just, and hoped she would prove
more yielding.  I knew that her affections were strong and enduring, but
that her temperament was capricious, and her sunniest moods easily
overcast by some small cloud of jealousy or pique.  I had never
imagined, however, that she was capable of such intensity as was
revealed by these few words of hers.  As I say, I felt concerned.  I had
learned to like Malcolm Murchison, and had heartily consented to his
marriage with my ward; for it was in that capacity that I had stood for a
year or two to my wife's younger sister, Mabel.  The match thus rudely
broken off had promised to be another link binding me to the kindly
Southern people among whom I had not long before taken up my
residence.</p>
<p> Young Murchison came out of the door, cleared the piazza in two
strides without seeming aware of my presence, and went off down the
lane at a furious pace.  A few moments later Mabel began playing the
piano loudly, with a touch that indicated anger and pride and
independence and a dash of exultation, as though she were really glad
that she had driven away forever the young man whom the day before
she had loved with all the ardor of a first passion.</p>
<p> I hoped that time might heal the breach and bring the two young
people together again.  I told my wife what I had overheard.  In return
she gave me Mabel's version of the affair.</p>
<p> "I do not see how it can ever be settled," my wife said.  "It is
something more than a mere lovers' quarrel.  It began, it is true, because
she found fault with him for going to church with that hateful Branson
girl.  But before it ended there were things said that no woman of any
spirit could stand.  I am afraid it is all over between them."</p>
<p> I was sorry to hear this.  In spite of the very firm attitude taken
by my wife and her sister, I still hoped that the quarrel would be made
up within a day or two.  Nevertheless, when a week had passed with no
word from young Murchison, and with no sign of relenting on Mabel's
part, I began to think myself mistaken.</p>
<p> One pleasant afternoon, about ten days after the rupture, old
Julius drove the rockaway up to the piazza, and my wife, Mabel, and I
took our seats for a drive to a neighbor's vineyard, over on the
Lumberton plankroad.</p>

<pb n="50"/>
<p> "Which way shall we go," I asked, &mdash; "the short road or the long
one?"</p>
<p> "I guess we had better take the short road," answered my wife.
"We will get there sooner."</p>
<p> "It's a mighty fine dribe roun' by de big road, Mis' Annie,"
observed Julius, "en it doan take much longer to git dere."</p>
<p> "No," said my wife, "I think we will go by the short road.  There
is a bay tree in blossom near the mineral spring, and I wish to get some
of the flowers."</p>
<p> "I 'spec's you'd find some bay trees 'long de big road, ma'am,"
said Julius.</p>
<p> "But I know about the flowers on the short road, and they are the
ones I want."</p>
<p> We drove down the lane to the highway, and soon struck into the
short road leading past the mineral spring.  Our route lay partly through
a swamp, and on each side the dark, umbrageous foliage, unbroken by
any clearing, lent to the road solemnity, and to the air a refreshing
coolness.  About half a mile from the house, and about halfway to the
mineral spring, we stopped at the tree of which my wife had spoken, and
reaching up to the low-hanging boughs I gathered a dozen of the
fragrant white flowers.  When I resumed my seat in the rockaway, Julius
started the mare.  She went on for a few rods, until we had reached the
edge of a branch crossing the road, when she stopped short.</p>
<p> "Why did you stop, Julius?" I asked.</p>
<p> "I didn', suh," he replied.  "'T wuz de mare stop'.  G' 'long
dere, Lucy!  W'at you mean by dis foolis'ness?"</p>
<p> Julius jerked the reins and applied the whip lightly, but the mare
did not stir.</p>
<p> "Perhaps you had better get down and lead her," I suggested.  "If
you get her started, you can cross on the log and keep your feet
dry."</p>
<p> Julius alighted, took hold of the bridle, and vainly essayed to
make the mare move.  She planted her feet with even more evident
obstinacy.</p>
<p> "I don't know what to make of this," I said.  "I have never known
her to balk before.  Have you, Julius?"</p>
<p> "No, suh," replied the old man, "I nebber has.  It's a cu'ous thing
ter me, suh."</p>
<p> "What's the best way to make her go?"</p>
<p> "I 'spec's, suh, dat ef I'd tu'n her roun' she'd go de udder
way."</p>
<p> "But we want her to go this way."</p>
<p> "Well, suh, I 'low ef we des set heah fo' er fibe minutes, she'll
sta't up by herse'f."</p>
<p> "All right," I rejoined, "it is cooler here than any place I have
struck to-day.  We'll let her stand for a while, and see what she
does."</p>
<p> We had sat in silence for a few minutes, when Julius suddenly
ejaculated, "Uh huh!  I knows w'y dis mare doan go.  It des flash 'cross
my reccommemb'ance."</p>
<p> "Why is it, Julius?" I inquired.</p>
<p> "Ca'se she sees Chloe."</p>
<p> "Where is Chloe?" I demanded.</p>
<p> "Chloe's done be'n dead dese fo'ty years er mo'," the old man
returned.  "Her ha'nt is settin' ober yander on de udder side er de
branch, unner dat willer tree, dis blessed minute."</p>
<p> "Why, Julius!" said my wife, "do you see the haunt?"</p>
<p> "No'm," he answered, shaking his head, "I doan see 'er, but de
mare sees 'er."</p>
<p> "How do you know?" I inquired.</p>
<p> "Well, suh, dis yer is a gray hoss, en dis yer is a Friday; en a
gray hoss kin alluz see a ha'nt w'at walks on Friday."</p>
<p> "Who was Chloe?" said Mabel.</p>
<p> "And why does Chloe's haunt walk?" asked my wife.</p>
<p> "It's all in de tale, ma'am," Julius replied, with a deep sigh.  "It's
all in de tale."</p>
<p> "Tell us the tale," I said.  "Perhaps, by the time you get through,
the haunt will go away and the mare will cross."</p>
<p> I was willing to humor the old man's

<pb n="51"/>
fancy.  He had not told us a story for some time; and the dark and
solemn swamp around us; the amber-colored stream flowing silently and
sluggishly at our feet, like the waters of Lethe; the heavy, aromatic scent
of the bays, faintly suggestive of funeral wreaths, &mdash; all made the place
an ideal one for a ghost story.</p>
<p> "Chloe," Julius began in a subdued tone, "use' ter b'long ter ole
Mars' Dugal' McAdoo &mdash; my ole marster.  She wuz a ladly gal en a
smart gal, en ole mis' tuk her up ter de big house, en l'arnt her ter wait
on de w'ite folks, 'tel bimeby she come ter be mis's own maid, en
'peared ter 'low she run de house herse'f, ter heah her talk erbout it.  I
wuz a young boy den, en use' ter wuk about de stables, so I knowed
ev'ythin' dat wuz gwine on roun' de plantation.</p>
<p> "Well, one time Mars' Dugal' wanted a house boy, en sont down
ter de qua'ters fer hab Jeff en Hannibal come up ter de big house nex'
mawnin'.  Ole marster en ole mis' look' de two boys ober, en 'sco'sed
wid deyse'ves fer a little w'ile, en den Mars' Dugal' sez, sezee: &mdash;
</p>
<p> "'We laks Hannibal de bes', en we gwine ter keep him.  Heah,
Hannibal, you'll wuk at de house fum now on.  En ef you're a good
nigger en min's yo' bizness, I'll gib you Chloe fer a wife nex' spring.
You other nigger, you Jeff, you kin go back ter de qua'ters.  We ain'
gwine ter need you.'</p>
<p> "Now Chloe had be'n standin' dere behin' ole mis' dyoin' all er
dis yer talk, en Chloe made up her min' fum de ve'y fus' minute she sot
eyes on dem two dat she didn' lak dat nigger Hannibal, en wa'n't nebber
gwine keer fer 'im, en she wuz des ez sho' dat she lak Jeff, en wuz
gwine ter set sto' by 'im, whuther Mars' Dugal' tuk 'im in de big house
er no; en so co'se Chloe wuz monst'us sorry w'en ole Mars' Dugal' tuk
Hannibal en sont Jeff back.  So she slip' roun' de house en waylaid Jeff
on de way back ter de qua'ters en tol' 'im not ter be downhea'ted, fer
she wuz gwine ter see ef she couldn' fin' some way er 'nuther ter git rid
er dat nigger Hannibal, en git Jeff up ter de house in his place.</p>
<p> "De noo house boy kotch on monst'us fas', en it wa'n't no time
ha'dly befo' Mars' Dugal' en ole mis' bofe 'mence' ter 'low Hannibal
wuz de bes' house boy dey eber had.  He wuz peart en soopl', quick ez
lightnin', en sha'p ez a razor.  But Chloe didn' lak his ways.  He wuz so
sho' he wuz gwine ter git 'er in de spring, dat he didn' 'pear ter 'low he
had ter do any co'tin', en w'en he'd run 'cross Chloe 'bout de house,
he'd swell roun' 'er in a biggity way en say:</p>
<p> "'Come heah en kiss me, honey.  You gwine ter be mine in de
spring.  You doan 'pear ter be ez fon' er me ez you oughter be.'</p>
<p> "Chloe didn' keer nuffin' fer Hannibal, en hadn' keered nuffin'
fer 'im, en she sot des ez much sto' by Jeff ez she did de day she fus'
laid eyes on 'im.  En de mo' fermilyus dis yer Hannibal got, de mo'
Chloe let her min' run on Jeff, en one ebenin' she went down ter de
qua'ters en watch', 'tel she got a chance fer ter talk wid 'im by hisse'f.
En she tol' Jeff fer ter go down en see ole Aun' Peggy, de cunjuh-'oman
down by de Wim'l'ton Road, en ax her fer ter gib 'im sump'n ter he'p
git Hannibal out'n de big house, so de w'ite folks 'u'd sen' fer Jeff
ag'in.  En bein' ez Jeff didn' hab nuffin' ter gib Aun' Peggy, Chloe gun
i'm a silber dollah en a silk han'kercher fer ter pay her wid, fer Aun'
Peggy nebber lak ter wuk fer nobody fer nuffin'.</p>
<p> "So Jeff slip' off down ter Aun' Peggy's one night, en gun 'er de
presents he brung, en tol' er all 'bout 'im en Chloe en Hannibal, en ax'
'er ter he'p 'im out.  Aun' Peggy tol' 'im she'd wuk 'er roots, en fer
'im ter come back de nex' night, en she'd tell 'im w'at she c'd do fer
'im.</p>
<p> "So de nex' night Jeff went back, en

<pb n="52"/>
Aun' Peggy gun 'im a baby-doll, wid a body made out'n a piece er
co'n-stalk, en wid splinters fer a'ms en legs, en a head made out'n
elderberry peth, en two little red peppers fer feet.</p>
<p> "'Dis yer baby-doll,' sez she, 'is Hannibal.  Dis yer peth head is
Hannibal's head, en dese yer pepper feet is Hannibal's feet.  You take
dis en hide it unner de house, on de sill unner de do', whar Hannibal'll
hafter walk ober it ev'y day.  En ez long ez Hannibal comes anywhar
nigh dis baby-doll, he'll be des lak it is &mdash;  light-headed en hot-footed; en
ef dem two things doan git 'im inter trouble mighty soon, den I'm no
cunjuh-'oman.  But w'en you git Hannibal out'n de house, en git all thoo
wid dis baby-doll, you mus' fetch it back ter me, fer it's monst'us
powerful goopher, en is liable ter make mo' trouble ef you leabe it layin'
roun'.'</p>
<p> "Well, Jeff tuk de baby-doll, en slip' up ter de big house, en
whistle' ter Chloe, en w'en she come out he tol' 'er w'at ole Aun' Peggy
had said.  En Chloe showed 'im how ter git unner de house, en w'en he
had put de cunjuh-doll on de sill he went 'long back ter de qua'ters &mdash; en
des waited.</p>
<p> "Nex' day, sho' 'nuff, de goopher 'mence' ter wuk.  Hannibal
sta'ted in de house soon in de mawnin' wid a armful er wood ter make a
fier, en he hadn' mo' d'n got 'cross de do'sill befo' his feet begun ter
bu'n so dat he drap' de armful er wood on de flo' en woke ole mis' up
an hour sooner'n yuzhal, en co'se ole mis' didn' lak dat, en spoke sha'p
erbout it.</p>
<p> "W'en dinner-time come, en Hannibal wuz help'n de cook kyar
de dinner f'm de kitchen inter de big house, en wuz gittin' close ter de
do' what he had ter go in, his feet sta'ted ter bu'n en his head begun ter
swim, en he let de big dish er chicken en dumplin's fall right down in de
dirt, in de middle er de ya'd, en de w'ite folks had ter make dey dinner
dat day off'n col' ham en sweet pertaters.</p>
<p> "De nex' mawnin' he overslep' hisse'f, en got inter mo' trouble.
Atter breakfus', Mars' Dugal' sont 'im ober ter Mars' Marrabo Utley's
fer ter borry a monkey wrench.  He oughter be'n back in ha'f an hour,
but he come pokin' home 'bout dinner'time wid a screw-driver stidder a
monkey wrench.  Mars' Dugal' sont ernudder nigger back wid de
screw-driver, en Hannibal didn' git no dinner.  'Long in de atternoon,
ole mis' sot Hannibal ter weedin' de flowers in de front gyahden, en
Hannibal dug up all de bulbs ole mis' had sont erway fer, en paid a lot
er money fer, en tuk 'em down ter de hawg-pen by de ba'nya'd, en fed
'em ter de hawgs.  W'en ole mis' come out in de cool er de ebenin', en
seed w'at Hannibal had done, she wuz mos' crazy, en she wrote a note
en sont Hannibal down ter de obserseah wid it.</p>
<p> "But w'at Hannibal got fum de oberseah didn' 'pear ter do no
good.  Ev'y now en den 'is feet'd 'mence ter torment 'im, en 'is min'
'u'd git all mix' up, en his conduc' kep' gittin' wusser en wusser, 'tel
fin'ly de w'ite folks couldn' stan' it no longer, en Mars' Dugal' tuk
Hannibal back down ter de qua'ters.</p>
<p> "'Mr. Smif,' sez Mars' Dugal' ter de oberseah, 'dis yer nigger
has tu'nt out so triflin' yer lately, dat we can't keep 'im at de house no
mo', en I's fotch' 'im ter you ter be straighten' up.  You's had 'casion
ter deal wid 'im once, so he knows w'at ter expec'.  You des take 'im in
han', en lemme know how he tu'ns out.  En w'en de han's comes in fum
de fiel' dis ebenin' you kin sen' dat yaller nigger Jeff up ter de house.
I'll try 'im, en see ef he's any better'n Hannibal.'</p>
<p> "So Jeff went up ter de big house, en pleas' Mars' Dugal' en ole
mis' en de res' er de fambly so well dat dey all got ter lakin' 'im
fus'rate, en dey'd 'a' fergot all 'bout Hannibal ef it hadn' be'n fer de
bad repo'ts w'at come up fum de qua'ters 'bout 'im fer a mont' er so.
Fac' is dat Chloe en Jeff wuz so int'rusted in one ernudder since Jeff

<pb n="53"/>
be'n up ter de house, dat dey fergot all about takin' de baby-doll back
ter Aun' Peggy, en it kep' wukkin fer a w'ile, en makin' Hannibal's feet
bu'n mo' er less, 'tel all de folks on de plantation got ter callin' 'im
Hot-Foot Hannibal.  He kep' gittin' mo' en mo' triflin', 'tel he got de
name er bein' de mos' no 'countes' nigger on de plantation, en Mars'
Dugal' had ter th'eaten ter sell 'im in de spring; w'en bimeby de
goopher quit wukkin', en Hannibal 'mence' ter pick up some en make
folks set a little mo' sto' by 'im.</p>
<p> "Now, dis yer Hannibal was a monst'us sma't nigger, en w'en he
got rid er dem so' feet his min' kep' runnin' on 'is udder troubles.
Heah th'ee er fo' weeks befo' he'd had a' easy job, waitin' on de w'ite
folks, libbin off'n de fat er de lan', en promus' de fines' gal on de
plantation fer a wife in de spring, en now heah he wuz back in de
co'nfiel', wid de oberseah a-cussin' en a r'arin' ef he didn' get a ha'd
tas' done; wid nuffin' but co'n bread en bacon en merlasses ter eat; en
all de fiel-han's makin' rema'ks, en pokin' fun at 'im ca'se he be'n sont
back fum de big house ter de fiel'.  En de mo' Hannibal studied 'bout it
de mo' madder he got, 'tel he fin'ly swo' he wuz gwine ter git eben wid
Jeff en Chloe ef it wuz de las' ac'.</p>
<p> "So Hannibal slipped 'way fum de qua'ters one Sunday en hid in
de co'n up close ter de big house, 'tel he see Chloe gwine down de road.
He waylaid her, en sezee: &mdash; </p>
<p> "'Hoddy, Chloe?'</p>
<p> "'I ain't got no time fer ter fool wid fiel'-han's,' sez Chloe,
tossin' her head; 'W'at you want wid me, Hot-Foot?'</p>
<p> "'I wants ter know how you en Jeff is gittin' 'long.'</p>
<p> "'I 'lows dat's none er yo' bizness, nigger.  I doan see w'at
'casion any common fiel'-han' has got ter mix in wid de 'fairs er folks
w'at libs in de big house.  But ef it'll do you any good ter know, I
mought say dat me en Jeff is gittin' 'long mighty well, en we gwine ter
git married in de spring, en you ain' gwine ter be 'vited ter de weddin'
nuther.'</p>
<p> "'No, no!' sezee, 'I wouldn' 'spec' ter be 'vited ter de weddin', &mdash;
a common, low-down fiel'-han' lak <hi rend="italic">I</hi> is.  But I's glad ter
heah you en Jeff is gittin' 'long so well.  I didn' knowed but w'at he had
'mence' ter be a little ti'ed.'</p>
<p> "'Ti'ed er me?  Dat's rediklus!' sez Chloe.  'W'y, dat nigger lubs
me so I b'liebe he'd go th'oo fier en water fer me.  Dat nigger is des
wrop' up in me.'</p>
<p> "'Uh huh,' sez Hannibal, 'den I reckon is mus' be some udder
nigger w'at meets a 'oman down by de crick in de swamp ev'y Sunday
ebenin', ter say nuffin' 'bout two er th'ee times a week.'</p>
<p> "'Yas, hit is ernudder nigger, en you is a liah w'en you say it
wuz Jeff.'</p>
<p> "'Mebbe I is a liah, en mebbe I ain' got good eyes.  But 'less'n I
<hi rend="italic">is</hi> a liah, en 'less'n I <hi rend="italic">ain'</hi> got good eyes, Jeff is
gwine ter meet dat 'oman dis ebenin' long 'bout eight o'clock right down
dere by de crick in de swamp 'bout halfway betwix' dis plantation en
Mars' Marrabo Utley's.'</p>
<p> "Well, Chloe tol' Hannibal she didn' b'liebe a wud he said, en
call' 'im a low-down nigger who wuz tryin' ter slander Jeff 'ca'se he
wuz mo' luckier'n he wuz.  But all de same, she couldn' keep her min'
fum runnin' on w'at Hannibal had said.  She 'membered she'd heared
one er de niggers say dey wuz a gal ober at Mars' Marrabo Utley's
plantation w'at Jeff use' ter go wid some befo' he got 'quainted wid
Chloe.  Den she 'mence' ter figger back, en sho' 'nuff, dey wuz two er
th'ee times in de las' week w'en she'd be'n he'p'n de ladies wid dey
dressin' en udder fixin's in de ebenin', en Jeff mought 'a' gone down ter
de swamp widout her knowin' 'bout it at all.  En den she 'mence' ter
'member little things w'at she hadn' tuk no notice of befo', en w'at 'u'd
make it 'pear lak Jeff had sump'n on his min'.</p>
<p> "Chloe set a monst'us heap er sto' by Jeff, en would 'a' done
mos' anythin'

<pb n="54"/>
fer 'im, so long ez he stuck ter her.  But Chloe wuz a mighty jealous
'oman, en w'iles she didn' b'liebe w'at Hannibal said, she seed how it
<hi rend="italic">could</hi> 'a' be'n so, en she 'termine' fer ter fin' out fer herse'f
whuther it <hi rend="italic">wuz</hi> so er no.</p>
<p> "Now, Chloe hadn' seed Jeff all day, fer Mars' Dugal' had sont
Jeff ober ter his daughter's house, young Mis' Ma'g'ret's, w'at libbed
'bout fo' miles fum Mars' Dugal's, en Jeff wuzn' 'spected home 'tel
ebenin'.  But des atter supper wuz ober, en w'iles de ladies wuz settin'
out on de piazzer, Chloe slip' off fum de house en run down de road, &mdash;
dis yer same road we come; en w'en she got mos' ter de crick &mdash; dis yer
same crick right befo' us &mdash; she kin' er kip' in de bushes at de side er de
road, 'tel fin'ly she seed Jeff settin' on de back on de udder side er de
crick, &mdash; right under dat ole willer tree droopin' ober de watah yander.
En ev'y now en den he'd git up en look up de road to'ds Mars'
Marrabo's on de udder side er de swamp.</p>
<p> "Fus' Chloe felt lak she'd go right ober de crick en gib Jeff a
piece er her min'.  Den she 'lowed she better be sho' befo' she done
anythin'.  So she helt herse'f in de bes' she could, gittin' madder en
madder ev'ry minute, 'tel bimeby she seed a 'oman comin' down de
road on de udder side fum to'ds Mars' Marrabo Utley's plantation.  En
w'en she seed Jeff jump up en run to'ds dat 'oman, en th'ow his a'ms
roun' her neck, po' Chloe didn' stop ter see no mo', but des tu'nt roun'
en run up ter de house, en rush' up on de piazzer, en up en tol' Mars'
Dugal' en ole mis' all 'bout de baby-doll, en all 'bout Jeff gittin' de
goopher fum Aun' Peggy, en 'bout w'at de goopher had done ter
Hannibal.</p>
<p> "Mars' Dugal' wuz monst'us mad.  He didn' let on at fus' lak he
b'liebed Chloe, but w'en she tuk en showed 'im whar ter fin' de
baby-doll, Mars' Dugal' tu'nt w'ite ez chalk.</p>
<p> "'What debil's wuk is dis?' sezee.  'No wonder de po' nigger's
feet eetched.  Sump'n got ter be done ter l'arn dat ole witch ter keep her
han's off'n my niggers.  En ez fer dis yer Jeff, I'm gwine ter do des
w'at I promus', so de darkies on dis plantation'll know I means w'at I
sez.'</p>
<p> "Fer Mars' Dugal' had warned de han's befo' 'bout foolin' wid
cunju'ation; fac', he had los' one er two niggers hisse'f fum dey bein'
goophered, en he would 'a' had ole Aun' Peggy whip' long ago, on'y
Aun' Peggy wuz a free 'oman, en he wuz 'feard she'd cunjuh him.  En
wi'les Mars' Dugal' say he didn' b'liebe in cunj'in' en sich, he 'peared
ter 'low it wuz bes' ter be on de safe side, en let Aun' Peggy
alone.</p>
<p> "So Mars' Dugal' done des ez he say.  Ef ole mis' had ple'd fer
Jeff he mought 'a' kep' 'im.  But ole mis' hadn' got ober losin' dem
bulbs yit, en she nebber said a wud.  Mars' Dugal' tuk Jeff ter town
nex' day en' sol' 'im ter a spekilater, who sta'ted down de ribber wid
'im nex' mawnin' on a steamboat, fer ter take 'im ter Alabama.</p>
<p> "Now, w'en Chloe tol' ole Mars' Dugal' 'bout dis yer baby-doll
en dis udder goopher, she hadn' ha'dly 'lowed Mars' Dugal' would sell
Jeff down Souf.  Howsomeber, she wuz so mad wid Jeff dat she 'suaded
herse'f she didn' keer; en so she hilt her head up en went roun' lookin'
lak she wuz rale glad 'bout it.  But one day she wuz walkin' down de
road, w'en who sh'd come 'long but dis yer Hannibal.</p>
<p> "W'en Hannibal seed 'er he bus' out laffin' fittin' fer ter kill:
'Yah, yah, yah! ho, ho, ho! ha, ha, ha!  Oh, hol' me, honey, hol' me, er
I'll laf myse'f ter def.  I ain' nebber laf' so much sence I be'n
bawn.'</p>
<p> "'W'at you laffin' at, Hot-Foot?'</p>
<p> "'Yah, yah, yah!  W'at I laffin' at?  W'y, I's laffin' at myse'f,
tooby sho', &mdash; laffin' ter think w'at a fine 'oman I made.'</p>
<p> "Chloe tu'nt pale, en her hea't come up in her mouf.</p>

<pb n="55"/>
<p> "'W'at you mean, nigger?' sez she, ketchin' holt er a bush by de
road fer ter stiddy herse'f.  'W'at you mean by de kin' er 'oman you
made?'</p>
<p> "W'at do I mean?  I means dat I got squared up wid you fer
treatin' me de way you done, en I got eben wid dat yaller nigger Jeff fer
cuttin' me out.  Now, he's gwine ter know w'at it is ter eat co'n bread
en merlasses once mo', en wuk fum daylight ter da'k, en ter hab a
oberseah dribin' 'im fum one day's een' ter de udder.  I means dat I sont
wud ter Jeff dat Sunday dat you wuz gwine ter be ober ter Mars'
Marrabo's visitin' dat ebenin', en you want i'm ter meet you down by de
crick on de way home en go de rest er de road wid you.  En den I put
on a frock en a sun-bonnet en fix' myse'f up ter look lak a 'oman; en
w'en Jeff seed me comin' he run ter meet me, en you seed 'im, &mdash; fer I
had be'n watchin' in de bushes befo' en 'skivered you comin' down de
road.  En now I reckon you en Jeff bofe knows w'at it means ter mess
wid a nigger lak me.'</p>
<p> "Po' Chloe hadn' heared mo' d'n half er de las' part er w'at
Hannibal said, but she had heared 'nuff to l'arn dat dis nigger had fooler
her en Jeff, en dat po' Jeff hadn' done nuffin', en dat fer lovin' her too
much en goin' ter meet her she had cause' 'im ter be sol' erway whar
she'd nebber, nebber see 'im no mo'.  De sun mought shine by day, de
moon by night, de flowers mought bloom, en de mawkin'-birds mought
sing, but po' Jeff wuz done los' ter her fereber en fereber.</p>
<p> "Hannibal hadn' mo' d'n finish' w'at he had ter say, w'en Chloe's
knees gun 'way unner her, en she fell down in de road, en lay dere half
a' hour er so befo' she come to.  W'en she did, she crep' up ter de
house des ez pale ez a ghos'.  En fer a mont' er so she crawled roun' de
house, en 'peared ter be so po'ly dat Mars' Dugal' sont fer a doctor; en
de doctor kep' on axin' her questions 'tel he foun' she wuz des pinin'
erway fer Jeff.</p>
<p> "W'en he tol' Mars' Dugal', Mars' Dugal' lafft, en said he'd fix
dat.  She could hab de noo house boy fer a husban'.  But ole mis' say,
no, Chloe ain' dat kinder gal, en dat Mars' Dugal' should buy Jeff
back.</p>
<p> "So Mars' Dugal' writ a letter ter dis yer spekilater down ter
Wim'l'ton, en tol' ef he ain' done sol' dat nigger Souf w'at he bought
fum 'im, he'd lak ter buy 'm back ag'in.  Chloe 'mence' ter pick up a
little w'en ole mis' tol' her 'bout dis letter.  Howsomeber, bimeby Mars'
Dugal' got a' answer fum de spekilater, who said he wuz monst'us
sorry, but Jeff had fell ove'boa'd er jumped off'n de steamboat on de
way ter Wim'l'ton, en got drownded, en co'se he couldn' sell 'im back,
much ez he'd lak ter 'bleedge Mars' Dugal'.</p>
<p> "Well, atter Chloe heared dis she pu'tended ter do her wuk, en
ole mis' wa'n't much mo' use ter nobody.  She put up wid her, en hed
de doctor gib her medicine, en let 'er go ter de circus, en all so'ts er
things fer ter take her min' off'n her troubles.  But dey didn' none un
'em do no good.  Chloe got ter slippin' down here in de ebenin' des lak
she 'uz comin' ter meet Jeff, en she'd set dere unner dat willer tree on
de udder side, en wait fer 'im, night atter night.  Bimeby she got so bad
de w'ite folks sont her ober ter young Mis' Ma'g'ret's fer ter gib her a
change; but she runned erway de fus' night, en w'en dey looked fer 'er
nex' mawnin' dey foun' her co'pse layin' in de branch yander, right
'cross fum whar we're settin' now.</p>
<p> "Eber sence den," said Julius in conclusion, "Chloe's ha'nt comes
eve'y ebenin' en sets down unner dat willer tree en waits fer Jeff, er e'se
walks up en down de road yander, lookin' en lookin', en' [sic] waitin'
en waitin', fer her sweethea't w'at ain' nebber, nebber come back ter her
no mo'."</p>
<p> There was silence when the old man had finished, and I am sure I
saw a tear

<pb n="56"/>
in my wife's eye, and more than one in Mabel's.</p>
<p> "I think, Julius," said my wife after a moment, "that you may
turn the mare around and go by the long road."</p>
<p> The old man obeyed with alacrity, and I noticed no reluctance on
the mare's part.</p>
<p> "You are not afraid of Chloe's haunt, are you?" I asked
jocularly.</p>
<p> My mood was not responded to, and neither of the ladies
smiled.</p>
<p> "Oh no," said Annie, "but I've changed my mind.  I prefer the
other route."</p>
<p> When we had reached the main road and had proceeded along it
for a short distance, we met a cart driven by a young negro, and on the
cart were a trunk and a valise.  We recognized the man as Malcolm
Murchison's servant, and drew up a moment to speak to him.</p>
<p> "Who's going away, Marshall?" I inquired.</p>
<p> "Young Mistah Ma'colm gwine 'way on de boat ter Noo Yo'k dis
ebenin', suh, en I'm takin' his things down ter de wharf, suh."</p>
<p> This was news to me, and I heard it with regret.  My wife looked
sorry, too, and I could see that Mabel was trying hard to hide her
concern.</p>
<p> "He's comin' 'long behin', suh, en I 'spec's you'll meet 'im up
de road a piece.  He's gwine ter walk down ez fur ez Mistah Jim
Williams's, en take de buggy fum dere ter town.  He 'spec's ter be gone
a long time, suh, en say prob'ly he ain' nebber comin' back."</p>
<p> The man drove on.  There were a few words exchanged in an
undertone between my wife and Mabel, which I did not catch.  Then
Annie said: "Julius, you may stop the rockaway a moment.  There are
some trumpet-flowers by the road there that I want.  Will you get them
for me, John?"</p>
<p> I sprang into the underbrush, and soon returned with a great
bunch of scarlet blossoms.</p>
<p> "Where is Mabel?" I asked, noting her absence.</p>
<p> "She has walked on ahead.  We shall overtake her in a few
minutes."</p>
<p> The carriage had gone only a short distance when my wife
discovered that she had dropped her fan.</p>
<p> "I had it where we were stopping.  Julius, will you go back and
get it for me?"</p>
<p> Julius got down and went back for the fan.  He was an
unconscionably long time finding it.  After we got started again we had
gone only a little way, when we saw Mabel and young Murchison
coming toward us.  They were walking arm in arm, and their faces were
aglow with the light of love. </p>
<p> I do not know whether or not Julius had a previous understanding
with Malcolm Murchison by which he was to drive us round by the long
road that day, nor do I know exactly what motive influenced the old
man's exertions in the matter.  He was fond of Mabel, but I was old
enough, and knew Julius well enough, to be skeptical of his motives.  It
is certain that a most excellent understanding existed between him and
Murchison after the reconciliation, and that when the young people set
up housekeeping over at the old Murchison place Julius had an
opportunity to enter their service.  For some reason or other, however,
he preferred to remain with us.  The mare, I might add, was never
known to balk again.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Charles W. Chesnutt.</hi>
</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

