<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CheOrac"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="CheOrac">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Oracle of the Dog</title>
<title type="sort">oracle of the dog</title>
<author>Chesterton, G. K.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">51</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CheOrac</idno>
<date value="1993">1993</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1993 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475811</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>created for Alan Howard's ENLT 255 class,
spring 1994</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Great Detective Stories</title>
<title type="sort">great detective stories</title>
<author>G. K. Chesterton</author>
<respStmt>
<resp/>
<name>Willard Huntington Wright</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1927">1927</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>University of Virginia library copy: PN6014.W7 1927</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>spell-check and verification made against printed text using WordPerfect
spell checker</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing
part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the
text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for
page one of Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1926">1926</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-01">January 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Scanned in electronically; errors due to scanning cleaned up;
TEI tagging added; spellchecked; unambiguous line-end hyphenation
removed</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
	
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<pb n="263" id="CheOrac263"/>

<head>THE ORACLE OF THE DOG
<lb/>
BY G. K. CHESTERTON</head>


<p>"YES," said Father Brown, "I always like a dog, so long as he
isn't spelt backwards."
</p><p>Those who are quick in talking are not always quick in
listening. Sometimes even their brilliancy produces a sort of
stupidity. Father Brown's friend and companion was a young
man with a stream of ideas and stories, an enthusiastic young
man named Fiennes, with eager blue eyes and blond hair that
seemed to be brushed back, not merely with a hair-brush but with
the wind of the world as he rushed through it. But he stopped
in the torrent of his talk in a momentary bewilderment before
he saw the priest's very simple meaning.
</p><p>"You mean that people make too much of them?" he said.
"Well, I don't know. They're marvelous creatures. Sometimes
I think they know a lot more than we do."
</p><p>Father Brown said nothing; but continued to stroke the head
of the big retriever in a half-abstracted but apparently soothing
fashion.
</p><p>"Why," said Fiennes, warming again to his monologue,
"there was a dog in the case I've come to see you about; what
they call the 'Invisible Murder Case,' you know. It's a strange
story, but from my point of view the dog is about the strangest
thing in it. Of course, there's the mystery of the crime itself,
and how old Druce can have been killed by somebody else when
he was all alone in the summer-house&mdash;"
</p><p>The hand stroking of the dog stopped for a moment in its
rhythmic movement; and Father Brown said calmly, "Oh, it
was a summer-house, was it? "
</p><p>"I thought you'd read all about it in the papers," answered
Fiennes. " Stop a minute; I believe I've got a cutting that will
give you all the particulars." He produced a strip of newspaper
from his pocket and handed it to the priest, who began to read
it, holding it close to his blinking eyes with one hand while the
<pb n="264" id="CheOrac264"/>
other continued its half-conscious caresses of the dog. It looked
like the parable of a man not letting his right hand know what
his left hand did.
</p><p>"Many mystery stories, about men murdered behind locked
doors and windows, and murderers escaping without means of
entrance and exit, have come true in the course of the extraordinary
events at Cranston on the coast of Yorkshire, where
Colonel Druce was found stabbed from behind by a dagger that
has entirely disappeared from the scene, and apparently even
from the neighborhood.
</p><p>"The summer-house in which he died was indeed accessible
at one entrance, the ordinary doorway which looked down the
central walk of the garden towards the house. But by a combination
of events almost to be called a coincidence, it appears
that both the path and the entrance were watched during the
crucial time, and there is a chain of witnesses who confirm each
other. The summer-house stands at the extreme end of the garden,
where there is no exit or entrance of any kind. The central
garden path is a lane between two ranks of tall delphiniums,
planted so close that any stray step off the path would leave its
traces; and both path and plants run right up to the very mouth
of the summer-house, so that no straying from that straight
path could fail to be observed, and no other mode of entrance
can be imagined.
</p><p>"Patrick Floyd, secretary of the murdered man, testified that
he had been in a position to overlook the whole garden from the
time when Colonel Druce last appeared alive in the doorway to
the time when he was found dead; as he, Floyd, had been on the
top of a step-ladder clipping the garden hedge. Janet Druce,
the dead man's daughter, confirmed this, saying that she had sat
on the terrace of the house throughout that time and had seen
Floyd at his work. Touching some part of the time, this is again
supported by. Donald Druce, her brother, who overlooked the
garden standing at his bedroom window in his dressing-gown, for
he had risen late. Lastly the account is consistent with that
given by Dr. Valentine, a neighbor, who called for a time to
talk with Miss Druce on the terrace, and by the Colonel's solicitor,
Mr. Aubrey Traill, who was apparently the last to see the
murdered man alive&mdash;presumably with the exception of the
murderer.
</p><p>"All are agreed that the course of events was as follows:
<pb n="265" id="CheOrac265"/>
about half-past three in the afternoon, Miss Druce went down
the path to ask her father when he would like tea; but he said
he did not want any and was waiting to see Traill, his lawyer,
who was to be sent to him in the summer-house. The girl then
came away and met Traill coming down the path; she directed
to her father and he went in as directed. About half an
hour afterwards he came out again, the Colonel coming with
him to the door and showing himself to all appearance in health
and even high spirits. He had been somewhat annoyed earlier
in the day by his son's irregular hours, but seemed to recover his
temper in a perfectly normal fashion, and had been rather
markedly genial in receiving other visitors, including two of his
nephews who came over for the day. But as these were out
walking during the whole period of the tragedy, they had no
evidence to give. It is said, indeed, that the Colonel was not on
very good terms with Dr. Valentine, but that gentleman only
had a brief interview with the daughter of the house, to whom
he ;s supposed to be paying serious attentions.
</p><p>"Traill, the solicitor, says he left the Colonel entirely alone
in the summer-house, and this is confirmed by Floyd's bird's-eye view of the garden, which showed nobody else passing the
only entrance. Ten minutes later Miss Druce again went down
the garden and had not reached the end of the path, when she
saw her father, who was conspicuous by his white linen coat,
lying in a heap on the floor. She uttered a scream which brought
others to the spot, and on entering the place they found the
Colonel lying dead beside his basket-chair, which was also upset.
Dr. Valentine, who was still in the immediate neighborhood,
testified that the wound was made by some sort of stiletto, entering
under the shoulder-blade and piercing the heart. The police
have searched the neighborhood for such a weapon, but no trace
of it can be found."
</p><p>"So Colonel Druce wore a white coat, did he?" said Father
Brown as he put down the paper.
</p><p>"Trick he learnt in the tropics," replied Fiennes with some
wonder. "He'd had some queer adventures there, by his own
account; and I fancy his dislike of Valentine was connected
with the doctor coming from the tropics, too. But it's all an
infernal puzzle. The account there is pretty accurate; I didn't
see the tragedy, in the sense of the discovery; I was out walking
<pb n="266" id="CheOrac266"/>
with the young nephews and the dog&mdash;the dog I wanted to tell
you about. But I saw the stage set for it as described: the
straight lane between the blue flowers right up to the dark entrance,
and the lawyer going down it in his blacks and his silk
hat, and the red head of the secretary showing high above the
green hedge as he worked on it with his shears. Nobody could
have mistaken that red head at any distance; and if people say
they saw it there all the time, you may be sure they did. This
red-haired secretary Floyd is quite a character; a breathless,
bounding sort of fellow, always doing everybody's work as he
was doing the gardener's. I think he is an American; he's certainly
got the American view of life; what they call the viewpoint,
bless 'em."
</p><p>"What about the lawyer?" asked Father Brown.
</p><p>There was a silence and then Fiennes spoke quite slowly for
him. "Traill struck me as a singular man. In his fine black
clothes he was almost foppish, yet you can hardly call him
fashionable. For he wore a pair of long, luxuriant black whiskers
such as haven't been seen since Victorian times. He had
rather a fine grave face and a fine grave manner, but every now
and then he seemed to remember to smile. And when he showed
his white teeth he seemed to lose a little of his dignity and there
was something faintly fawning about him. It may have been
only embarrassment, for he would also fidget with his cravat
and his tie-pin, which were at once handsome and unusual, like
himself. If I could think of anybody&mdash;but what's the good,
when the whole thing's impossible? Nobody knows who did it.
Nobody knows how it could be done. At least there's only one
exception I'd make, and that's why I really mentioned the whole
thing. The dog knows."
</p><p>Father Brown sighed and then said absently: "You were there
as a friend of young Donald, weren't you? He didn't go on your
walk with you?"
</p><p>"No," replied Fiennes smiling. "The young scoundrel had
gone to bed that morning and got up that afternoon. I went
with his cousins, two young officers from India, and our conversation
was trivial enough. I remember the elder, whose name
I think is Herbert Druce and who is an authority on horse-breeding, talked about nothing but a mare he had bought and
the moral character of the man who sold her-while his brother
Harry seemed to be brooding on his bad luck at Monte Carlo.
I only mention it to show you, in the light of what happened on
<pb n="267" id="CheOrac267"/>
our walk, that there was nothing psychic about us. The dog was
the only mystic in our company."
</p><p>"What sort of a dog was he?" asked the priest.
</p><p>"Same breed as that one," answered Fiennes. "That's what
started me off on the story, your saying you didn't believe in
believing in a dog. He's a big black retriever named Nox, and a
suggestive name too; for I think what he did a darker mystery
than the murder. You know Druce's house and garden are by
the sea; we walked about a mile from it along the sands and
then turned back, going the other way. We passed a rather
curious rock called the Rock of Fortune, famous in the neighborhood
because it's one of those examples of one stone barely
balanced on another, so that a touch would knock it over. It
is not really very high, but the hanging outline of it makes it
look a little wild and sinister; at least it made it look so to me,
for I don't imagine my jolly young companions were afflicted
with the picturesque. But it may be that I was beginning to
feel an atmosphere; for just then the question arose of whether
it was time to go back to tea, and even then I think I had a
premonition that time counted for a good deal in the business.
Neither Herbert Druce nor I had a watch, so we called out to
his brother, who was some paces behind, having stopped to light
his pipe under the hedge. Hence it happened that he shouted
out the hour, which was twenty past four, in his big voice
through the growing twilight; and somehow the loudness of it
made it sound like the proclamation of something tremendous.
His unconsciousness seemed to make it all the more so; but
that was always the way with omens; and particular ticks of
the clock were really very ominous things that afternoon. According
to Dr. Valentine's testimony, poor Druce had actually
died just about half-past four.
</p><p>"Well, they said we needn't go home for ten minutes, and we
walked a little farther along the sands, doing nothing in particular&mdash;
throwing stones for the dog and throwing sticks into
the sea for him to swim after. But to me the twilight seemed to
grow oddly oppressive and the very shadow of the top-heavy
Rock of Fortune lay on me like a load. And then the curious
thing happened. Nox had just brought back Herbert's walking-stick out of the sea and his brother had thrown his in also. The
dog swam out again, but just about what must have been the
stroke of the half-hour, he stopped swimming. He came back
again on to the shore ana stood in front of us. Then he suddenly
<pb n="268" id="CheOrac268"/>
threw up his head and sent up a howl or wail of woe,
if ever I heard one in the world.
</p><p>"'What the devil's the matter with the dog?' asked Herbert;
but none of us could answer. There was a long silence after
the brute's wailing and whining died away on the desolate
shore; and then the silence was broken. As I live, it was broken
by a faint and far-off shriek, like the shriek of a woman from
beyond the hedges inland. We didn't know what it was then;
but we knew afterwards. It was the cry the girl gave when
she first saw the body of her father."
</p><p>"You went back, I suppose," said Father Brown patiently.
"What happened then?"
</p><p>"I'll tell you what happened then," said Fiennes with a grim
emphasis. "When we got back into that garden the first thing
we saw was Traill the lawyer; I can see him now with his black
hat and black whiskers relieved against the perspective of the
blue flowers stretching down to the summer-house, with the sunset
and the strange outline of the Rock of Fortune in the distance.
His face and figure were in shadow against the sunset;
but I swear the white teeth were showing in his head and he
was smiling.
</p><p>"The moment Nox saw that man, the dog dashed forward
and stood in the middle of the path barking at him madly,
murderously, volleying out curses that were almost verbal in
their dreadful distinctness of hatred. And the man doubled up
and fled along the path between the flowers."
</p><p>Father Brown sprang to his feet with a startling impatience.
</p><p>"So the dog denounced him, did he?" he cried. "The oracle
of the dog condemned him. Did you see what birds were flying,
and are you sure whether they were on the right hand or the left?
Did you consult the augurs about the sacrifices? Surely you
didn't omit to cut open the dog and examine his entrails. That
is the sort of scientific test you heathen humanitarians seem to
trust when you are thinking of taking away the life and honor
of a man."
</p><p>Fiennes sat gaping for an instant before he found breath to
say, "Why, what's the matter with you? What have I done
now?"
</p><p>A sort of anxiety came back into the priest's eyes&mdash;the anxiety
of a man who has run against a post in the dark and wonders for
a moment whether he has hurt it.
<pb n="269" id="CheOrac269"/>
</p><p>"I'm most awfully sorry," he said with sincere distress. "I
beg your pardon for being so rude; pray forgive me."
</p><p>Fiennes looked at him curiously. "I sometimes think you
are more of a mystery than any of the mysteries," he said. "But
anyhow, if you don't believe in the mystery of the dog, at least
you can't get over the mystery of the man. You can't deny
that at the very moment when the beast came back from the
sea and bellowed, his master's soul was driven out of his body
by the blow of some unseen power that no mortal man can
trace or even imagine. And as for the lawyer, I don't go only
by the dog; there are other curious details too. He struck me
as a smooth, smiling, equivocal sort of person; and one of his
tricks seemed like a sort of hint. You know the doctor and the
police were on the spot very quickly; Valentine was brought back
when walking away from the house, and he telephoned instantly.
That, with the secluded house, small numbers, and enclosed
space, made it pretty possible to search everybody who could have
been near; and everybody was thoroughly searched&mdash;for a
weapon. The whole house, garden, and shore were combed for a
weapon. The disappearance of the dagger is almost as crazy as
the disappearance of the man."
</p><p>"The disappearance of the dagger," said Father Brown, nodding.
He seemed to have become suddenly attentive.
</p><p>"Well," continued Fiennes, "I told you that man Traill had
a trick of fidgeting with his tie and tie-pin&mdash;especially his tie-pin. His pin, like himself, was at once showy and old-fashioned.
It had one of those stones with concentric colored rings that look
like an eye; and his own concentration on it got on my nerves,
as if he had been a Cyclops with one eye in the middle of his
body. But the pin was not only large but long; and it occurred
to me that his anxiety about its adjustment was because it was
even longer than it looked; as long as a stiletto in fact."
</p><p>Father Brown nodded thoughtfully. "Was any other instrument
ever suggested?" he asked.
</p><p>"There was another suggestion," answered Fiennes, "from one
of the young Druces&mdash;the cousins, I mean. Neither Herbert nor
Harry Druce would have struck one at first as likely to be of
assistance in scientific detection; but while Herbert was really
the traditional type of heavy Dragoon, caring for nothing but
horses and being an ornament to the Horse Guards, his younger
brother Harry had been in the Indian Police and knew something
about such things. Indeed in his own way he was quite
<pb n="270" id="CheOrac270"/>
clever; and I rather fancy he had been too clever; I mean he had
left the police through breaking some red-tape regulations and
taking some sort of risk and responsibility of his own. Anyhow,
he was in some sense a detective out of work, and threw himself
into this business with more than the ardor of an amateur.
And it was with him that I had an argument about the weapon&mdash;
an argument that led to something new. It began by his countering
my description of the dog barking at Traill; and he said
that a dog at his worst didn't bark, but growled."
</p><p>"He was quite right there," observed the priest.
</p><p>"This young fellow went on to say that, if it came to that,
he'd heard Nox growling at other people before then; and
among others at Floyd the secretary. I retorted that his own
argument answered itself; for the crime couldn't be brought
home to two or three people, and least of all to Floyd, who was
as innocent as a harum-scarum schoolboy, and had been seen by
everybody all the time perched above the garden hedge with his
fan of red hair as conspicuous as a scarlet cuckatoo. 'I know
there's difficulties anyhow,' said my colleague, 'but I wish you'd
come with me down the garden a minute. I want to show you
something I don't think anyone else has seen.' This was on the
very day of the discovery, and the garden was just as it had
been: the step-ladder was still standing by the hedge, and just
under the hedge my guide stooped and disentangled something
from the deep grass. It was the shears used for clipping the
hedge, and on the point of one of them was a smear of blood."
</p><p>There was a short silence, and then Father Brown said suddenly,
"What was the lawyer there for?"
</p><p>"He told us the Colonel sent for him to alter his will,"
answered Fiennes. "And, by the way, there was another thing
about the business of the will that I ought to mention. You
see, the will wasn't actually signed in the summer-house that
afternoon."
</p><p>"I suppose not," said Father Brown; "there would have to
be two witnesses."
</p><p>"The lawyer actually came down the day before and it was
signed then; but he was sent for again next day because the old
man had a doubt about one of the witnesses and had to be reassured."
</p><p>"Who were the witnesses?" asked Father Brown.
</p><p>"That's just the point," replied his informant eagerly, "the
witnesses were Floyd the secretary and this Dr. Valentine, the
<pb n="271" id="CheOrac271"/>
foreign sort of surgeon or whatever he is; and the two have a
quarrel. Now I'm bound to say that the secretary is something
of a busybody. He's one of those hot and headlong people whose
warmth of temperament has unfortunately turned mostly to
pugnacity and bristling suspicion; to distrusting people instead
of to trusting them. That sort of red-haired red-hot fellow is
always either universally credulous or universally incredulous;
and sometimes both. He was not only a Jack of all trades, but
he knew better than all tradesmen. He not only knew everything,
but he warned everybody against everybody. All that
must be taken into account in his suspicions about Valentine;
but in that particular case there seems to have been something
behind it. He said the name of Valentine was not really Valentine.
He said he had seen him elsewhere known by the name of
De Villon. He said it would invalidate the will; of course he
was kind enough to explain to the lawyer what the law was on
that point. They were both in a frightful wax."
</p><p>Father Brown laughed. "People often are when they are to
witness a will," he said, "for one thing, it means that they can't
have any legacy under it. But what did Dr. Valentine say?
No doubt the universal secretary knew more about the doctor's
name than the doctor did. But even the doctor might have some
information about his own name."
</p><p>Fiennes paused a moment before he replied.
</p><p>"Dr. Valentine took it in a curious way. Dr. Valentine is a
curious man. His appearance is rather striking but very foreign.
He is young but wears a beard cut square; and his face
is very pale, dreadfully pale and dreadfully serious. His eyes
have a sort of ache in them, as if he ought to wear glasses or
had given himself a headache with thinking; but he is quite
handsome and always very formally dressed, with a top hat and
a dark coat and a little red rosette. His manner is rather cold
and haughty, and he has a way of staring at you which is very
disconcerting. When thus charged with having changed his
name, he merely stared like a sphinx and then said with a little
laugh that he supposed Americans had no names to change. At
that I think the Colonel also got into a fuss and said all sorts
of angry things to the doctor; all the more angry because of the
doctor's pretensions to a future place in his family. But I
shouldn't have thought much of that but for a few words that I
happened to hear later, early in the afternoon of the tragedy.
I don't want to make a lot of them, for they weren't the sort of
<pb n="272" id="CheOrac272"/>
words on which one, would like, in the ordinary way, to play the
eavesdropper. As I was passing out towards the front gate
with my two companions and the dog, I heard voices which told
me that Dr. Valentine and Miss Druce had withdrawn for a moment
into the shadow of the house, in an angle behind a row of
flowering plants, and were talking to each other in passionate
whisperings&mdash;sometimes almost like hissings; for it was something
of a lovers' quarrel as well as a lovers' tryst. Nobody
repeats the sort of things they said for the most part; but in an
unfortunate business like this I'm bound to say that there was
repeated more than once a phrase about killing somebody. In
fact, the girl seemed to be begging him not to kill somebody,
or saying that no provocation could justify killing anybody;
which seems an unusual sort of talk to address to a gentleman
who has dropped in to tea."
</p><p>"Do you know," asked the priest, ''whether Dr. Valentine
seemed to be very angry after the scene with the secretary and
the Colonel&mdash;I mean about witnessing the will?"
</p><p>"By all accounts," replied the other, "he wasn't half so
angry as the secretary was. It was the secretary who went away
raging after witnessing the will."
</p><p>"And now," said Father Brown, "what about the will
itself?"
</p><p>"The Colonel was a very wealthy man, and his will was
important. Traill wouldn't tell us the alteration at that stage,
but I have since heard, only this morning in fact, that most of
the money was transferred from the son to the daughter. I told
you that Druce was wild with my friend Donald over his dissipated
hours."
</p><p>"The question of motive, has been rather over-shadowed by
the question of method," observed Father Brown thoughtfully.
"At that moment, apparently, Miss Druce was the immediate
gainer by the death."
</p><p>"Good Cod! What a cold-blooded way of talking," cried
Fiennes, staring at him. "You don't really mean to hint that
she "
</p><p>"Is she going to marry that Dr. Valentine?" asked the
other.
</p><p>"Some people are against it," answered his friend. "But he
is liked and respected in the place and is a skilled and devoted
surgeon."
</p><p>"So devoted a surgeon," said Father Brown, "that he had
<pb n="273" id="CheOrac273"/>
surgical instruments with him when he went to call on the
young lady at tea-time. For he must have used a lancet or
something, and he never seems to have gone home."
</p><p>Fiennes sprang to his feet and looked at him in a heat of
inquiry. "You suggest he might have used the very same
lancet&mdash;"
</p><p>Father Brown shook his head. "All these suggestions are
fancies just now," he said. "The problem is not who did it or
what did it, but how it was done. We might find many men and
even many tools&mdash;pins and shears and lancets. But how did a
man get into the room? How did even a pin get into it?"
</p><p>He was staring reflectively at the ceiling as he, spoke, but as
he said the last words his eye cocked in an alert fashion as if
he had suddenly seen a curious fly on the ceiling.
</p><p>"Well, what would you do about it?" asked the young man.
"You have a lot of experience, what would you advise now?"
</p><p>"I'm afraid I'm not much use," said Father Brown with a
sigh. "I can't suggest very much without having ever been
near the place or the people. For the moment you can only go
on with local inquiries. I gather that your friend from the
Indian Police is more or less in charge of your inquiry down
there. I should run down and see how he is getting on. See
what he's been doing in the way of amateur detection. There
may be news already."
</p><p>As his guests, the biped and the quadruped, disappeared,
Father Brown took up his pen and went back to his interrupted
occupation of planning a course of lectures on the Encyclical
Rerum Novarum. The subject was a large one and he had to
re-cast it more than once, so that he was somewhat similarly
employed some two days later when the big black dog again
came bounding into the room and sprawled all over him with
enthusiasm and excitement. The master who followed the dog
shared the excitement if not the enthusiasm. He had been
excited in a less pleasant fashion, for his blue eyes seemed
to start from his head and his eager face was even a little
pale.
</p><p>"You told me," he said abruptly and without preface, "to
find out what Harry Druce was doing. Do you know what he's
done?"
</p><p>The priest did not reply, and the young man went on in jerky
tones:
</p><p>"I'll tell you what he's done. He's killed himself."
<pb n="274" id="CheOrac274"/>
</p><p>Father Brown's lips moved only faintly, and there was nothing
practical about what he was saying&mdash;nothing that had anything
to do with this story or this world.
</p><p>"You give me the creeps sometimes," said Fiennes. "Did
you&mdash;did you expect this?"
</p><p>"I thought it possible," said Father Brown; "that was why
I asked you to go and see what he was doing. I hoped you
might not be too late."
</p><p>"It was I who found him," said Fiennes rather huskily. "It
was the ugliest and most uncanny thing I ever knew. I went
down that old garden again and I knew there was something
new and unnatural about it besides the murder. The flowers
still tossed about in blue masses on each side of the black
entrance into the old gray summer-house; but to me the blue
flowers looked like blue devils dancing before some dark cavern
of the underworld. I looked all around; everything seemed to be
in its ordinary place. But the queer notion grew on me that
there was something wrong with the very shape of the sky.
And then I saw what it was. The Rock of Fortune always rose
in the background beyond the garden hedge and against the
sea. And the Rock of Fortune was gone."
</p><p>Father Brown had lifted his head and was listening intently.
</p><p>"It was as if a mountain had walked away out of a landscape
or a moon fallen from the sky; though I knew, of course, that
a touch at any time would have tipped the thing over. Something
possessed me and I rushed down that garden path like
the wind and went crashing through that hedge as if it were a
spider's web. It was a thin hedge really, though its undisturbed
trimness had made it serve all the purposes of a wall. On the,
shore I found the loose rock fallen from its pedestal; and poor
Harry Druce lay like a wreck underneath it. One arm was
thrown round it in a sort of embrace as if he had pulled it
down on himself; and on the broad brown sands beside it, in
large crazy lettering, he had scrawled the words, "The Rock of
Fortune falls on the Fool."
</p><p>"It was the Colonel's will that did that," observed Father
Brown. "The young man had staked everything on profiting
himself by Donald's disgrace, especially when his uncle sent for
him on the same day as the lawyer, and welcomed him with so
much warmth. Otherwise he was done; he'd lost his police
job; he was beggared at Monte Carlo. And he killed himself
when he found he'd killed his kinsman for nothing."
<pb n="275" id="CheOrac275"/>
</p><p>"Here, stop a minute!" cried the staring Fiennes. "You're
going too fast for me."
</p><p>"Talking about the will, by the way," continued Father
Brown calmly, "before I forget it, or we go on to bigger things,
there was a simple explanation, I think, of all that business
about the doctor's name. I rather fancy I have heard both
names before somewhere. The doctor is really a French nobleman
with the title of the Marquis de Villon. But he is also an
ardent Republican and has abandoned his title and fallen back
on the forgotten family surname. 'With your Citizen Riquetti
you have puzzled Europe for ten days.'"
</p><p>"What is that?" asked the young man blankly.
</p><p>"Never mind," said the priest. "Nine times out of ten it is
a rascally thing to change one's name; but this was a piece of
fine fanaticism. That's the point of his sarcasm about Americans
having no names&mdash;that is, no titles. Now in England the
Marquis of Hartington is never called Mr. Hartington; but in
France the Marquis de Villon is called M. de Villon. So it
might well look like a change of name. As for the talk about
killing, I fancy that also was a point of French etiquette. The,
doctor was talking about challenging Floyd to a duel, and the
girl was trying to dissuade him."
</p><p>"Oh, I see," cried Fiennes slowly. "Now I understand what
she meant."
</p><p>"And what is that about?" asked his companion, smiling.
</p><p>"Well," said the young man, "it was something that happened
to me just before I found that poor fellow's body; only
the catastrophe drove it out of my head. I suppose it's hard to
remember a little romantic idyll when you've just come on top of
a tragedy. But as I went down the lanes leading to the Colonel's
old place, I met his daughter walking with Dr. Valentine. She
was in mourning of course, and he always wore black as if he were
going to a funeral; but I can't say that their faces were very
funereal. Never have I seen two people looking in their own
way more respectably radiant and cheerful. They stopped and
saluted me and then she told me they were married and living
in a little house on the outskirts of the town, where the doctor
was continuing his practise. This rather surprised me, because
I knew that her old father's will had left her his property; and
I hinted at it delicately by saying I was going along to her
father's old place and had half expected to meet her there. But
she only laughed and said, "Oh, we've given up all that. My
<pb n="276" id="CheOrac276"/>
husband doesn't like heiresses." And I discovered with some
astonishment they really had insisted on restoring the property
to poor Donald; so I hope he's had a healthy shock and will
treat it sensibly. There was never much really the matter with
him; he was very young and his father was not very wise. But
it was in connection with that that she said something I didn't
understand at the time; but now I'm sure it must be as you
say. She said with a sort of sudden and splendid arrogance that
was entirely altruistic:
</p><p>"'I hope it'll stop that red-haired fool from fussing any more
about the will. Does he think my husband, who has given up a
crest and a coronet as old as the Crusades for his principles,
would kill an old man in a summer-house for a legacy like that?'
Then she laughed again and said, 'My husband isn't killing
anybody except in the way of business. Why, he didn't even ask
his friends to call on the secretary.' Now, of course, I see what
she meant."
</p><p>"I see part of what she meant, of course," said Father
Brown. "What did she mean exactly by the secretary fussing
about the will?"
</p><p>Fiennes smiled as he answered. "I wish you knew the
secretary, Father Brown. It would be a joy to you to watch
him make things hum, as he calls it. He made the house of
mourning hum. He filled the funeral with all the snap and
zip of the brightest sporting event. There was no holding him,
after something had really happened. I've told you how he used
to oversee the gardener as he did the garden, and how he instructed
the lawyer in the law. Needless to say, he also instructed
the surgeon in the practise of surgery; and as the
surgeon was Dr. Valentine, you may be sure it ended in accusing
him of something worse than bad surgery. The secretary
got it fixed in his red head that the doctor had committed the
crime; and when the police arrived he was perfectly sublime.
Need I say that he became on the spot the greatest of all amateur
detectives? Sherlock Holmes never towered over Scotland Yard
with more Titanic intellectual pride and scorn than Colonel
Druce's private secretary over the police investigating Colonel
Druce's death. I tell you it was a joy to see him. He strode
about with an abstracted air, tossing his scarlet crest of hair
and giving curt impatient replies. Of course it was his demeanor
during these days that made Druce's daughter so wild
with him. Of course he had a theory. It's just the sort of
<pb n="277" id="CheOrac277"/>
theory a man would have in a book; and Floyd is the sort of
man who ought to be in a book. He'd be better fun and less
bother in a book."
</p><p>"What was his theory?" asked the other.
</p><p>"Oh, it was full of pep," replied Fiennes gloomily. "It
would have been glorious copy if it could have held together
for ten minutes longer. He said the Colonel was still alive
when they found him in the summer-house and the doctor killed
him with the surgical instrument on pretense of cutting the
clothes."
</p><p>"I see," said the priest. "I suppose he was lying flat on his
face on the mud floor as a form of siesta."
</p><p>"It's wonderful what hustle will do," continued his informant.
"I believe Floyd would have got his great theory into the papers
at any rate, and perhaps had the doctor arrested, when all these
things were blown sky high as if by dynamite by the discovery
of that dead body lying under the Rock of Fortune. And that's
what we come back to after all. I suppose the suicide is almost
a confession. But nobody will ever know the whole story."
</p><p>There was a silence, and then the priest said modestly, "I
rather think I know the whole story."
</p><p>Fiennes stared. "But look here," he cried, "how do you
come to know the whole story, or to be sure it's the true story?
You've been sitting here a hundred miles away writing a sermon;
do you mean to tell me you really know what happened already?
If you've really come to the end, where in the world do you
begin? What started you off with your own story?"
</p><p>Father Brown jumped up with a very unusual excitement and
his first exclamation was like an explosion.
</p><p>"The dog!" he cried. "The dog, of course! You had the
whole story in your hands in the business of the dog on the
beach, if you'd only noticed the dog properly."
</p><p>Fiennes stared still more. "But you told me before that my
feelings about the dog were all nonsense, and the dog had
nothing to do with it."
</p><p>"The dog had everything to do with it," said Father Brown,
"as you'd have found out if you'd only treated the dog as a
dog and not as God Almighty judging the souls of men."
</p><p>He paused in an embarrassed way for a moment, and then
said, with a rather pathetic air of apology:
</p><p>"The truth is, I happen to be awfully fond of dogs. And
it seemed to me that in all this lurid halo of dog superstitions
<pb n="278" id="CheOrac278"/>
nobody was really thinking about the poor dog at all. To begin
with a small point, about his barking at the lawyer or growling
at the secretary. You asked how I could guess things a hundred
miles away; but honestly it's mostly to your credit, for you
described people so well that I know the types. A man like
Traill who frowns usually and smiles suddenly, a man who
fiddles with things, especially at his throat, is a nervous, easily
embarrassed man. I shouldn't wonder if Floyd, the efficient
secretary, is nervy and jumpy too; those Yankee hustlers often
are. Otherwise he wouldn't have cut his fingers on the shears
and dropped them when he heard Janet Druce scream.
</p><p>"Now dogs hate nervous people. I don't know whether they
make the dog nervous too; or whether, being after all a brute,
he is a bit of bully; or whether his canine vanity (which is
colossal) is simply offended at not being liked. But anyhow
there was nothing in poor Nox protesting against those people,
except that he disliked them for being afraid of him. Now I
know you're awfully clever, and nobody of sense sneers at
cleverness. But I sometimes fancy, for instance, that you are too
clever to understand animals. Sometimes you are too clever to
understand men, especially when they act almost as simply as
animals. Animals are very literal; they live in a world of
truisms. Take this case; a dog barks at a man and a man runs
away from a dog. Now you do not seem to be quite simple
enough to see the fact; that the dog barked because he disliked
the man and the man fled because he was frightened of the dog.
They had no other motives and they needed none. But you
must read psychological mysteries into it and suppose the dog
had super-normal vision, and was a mysterious mouthpiece of
doom. You must suppose the man was running away, not from
the dog but from the hangman. And yet, if you come to think
of it, all this deeper psychology is exceedingly improbable. If
the dog really could completely and consciously realize the
murderer of his master, he wouldn't stand yapping as he might
at a curate at a tea-party; he's much more likely to fly at his
throat. And on the other hand, do you really think a man who
had hardened his heart to murder an old friend and then walk
about smiling at the old friend's family, under the eyes of his
old friend's daughter and postmortem doctor&mdash;do you think a
man like that would be doubled up by mere remorse because a
dog barked? He might feel the tragic irony of it; it might
shake his soul, like any other tragic trifle. But he wouldn't
<pb n="279" id="CheOrac279"/>
rush madly the length of a garden to escape from the only witness
whom he knew to be unable to talk. People have a panic
like that when they are frightened, not of tragic ironies, but of
teeth. The whole thing is simpler than you can understand.
</p><p>"But when we come to that business by the seashore, things
are much more interesting. As you stated then, they were much
more puzzling. I didn't understand that tale of the dog going
in and out of the water; it didn't seem to me a doggy thing to
do. If Nox had been very much upset about something else, he
might possibly have refused to go after the stick at all. He'd
probably go off nosing in whatever direction he suspected the
mischief. But when once a dog is actually chasing a thing, a
stone or a stick or a rabbit, my experience is that he won't stop
for anything but the most peremptory command, and not always
for that. That he should turn around because his mood changed
seems to me unthinkable."
</p><p>"But he did turn around," insisted Fiennes, "and came back
without the stick."
</p><p>"He came back without the stick for the best reason in the
world," replied the priest. "He came back because he couldn't
find it. He whined because he couldn't find it. That's the
sort of thing a dog really does whine about. A dog is a devil of
a ritualist. He is as particular about the precise routine of a
game as a child about the precise repetition of a fairy-tale. In
this case something had gone wrong with the game. He came
back to complain seriously of the conduct of the stick. Never
had such a thing happened before. Never had an eminent and
distinguished dog been so treated by a rotten old walking-stick."
</p><p>"Why, what had the walking-stick done?" inquired the
young man.
</p><p>"It had sunk," said Father Brown.
</p><p>Fiennes said nothing, but continued to stare, and it was the
priest who continued:
</p><p>"It had sunk because it was not really a stick, but a rod of
steel with a very thin shell of cane and a sharp point. In other
words, it was a sword-stick. I suppose a murderer never got rid
of a bloody weapon so oddly and yet so naturally as by throwing
it into the sea for a retriever."
</p><p>"I begin to see what you mean," admitted Fiennes; "but
even if a sword-stick was used, I have no guess of how it was
used."
<pb n="280" id="CheOrac280"/>
</p><p>"I had a sort of guess," said Father Brown, "right at the
beginning when you said the word summer-house. And another
when you said that Druce wore a white coat. As long as everybody
was looking for a short dagger, nobody thought of it;
but if we admit a rather long blade like a rapier, it's not so
impossible."
</p><p>He was leaning back, looking at the ceiling, and began like
one going back to his own first thoughts and fundamentals.
</p><p>"All that discussion about detective stories like the Yellow
Room, about a man found dead in sealed chambers which no
one could enter, does not apply to the present case, because it is
a summer-house. When we talk of a Yellow Room, or any
room, we imply walls that are really homogeneous and impenetrable.
But a summer-house is not made like that; it is often
made, as it was in this case, of closely interlaced but still
separate boughs and strips of wood, in which there are chinks
here and there. There was one of them just behind Druce's
back as he sat in his chair up against the wall. But just as the
room was a summer-house, so the chair was a basket-chair. That
also was a lattice of loopholes. Lastly, the summer-house was
close up under the hedge; and you have just told me that it was
really a thin hedge. A man standing outside it could easily see,
amid a network of twigs and branches and canes, one white spot
of the Colonel's coat as plain as the white of a target.
</p><p>"Now, you left the geography a little vague; but it was
possible to put two and two together. You said the Rock of
Fortune was not really high; but you also said it could be seen
dominating the garden like a mountain-peak. In other words, it
was very near the end of the garden, though your walk had
taken you a long way round to it. Also, it isn't likely the young
lady really howled so as to be heard half a mile. She gave an
ordinary involuntary cry, and yet you heard it on the shore.
And among other interesting things that you told me, may I remind
you that you said Harry Druce had fallen behind to light
his pipe under a hedge."
</p><p>Fiennes shuddered slightly. "You mean he drew his blade
there and sent it through the hedge at the white spot. But surely
it was a very odd chance and a very sudden choice. Besides, he
couldn't be certain the old man's money had passed to him, and
as a fact it hadn't."
</p><p>Father Brown's face became animated.
</p><p>"You misunderstand the man's character," he said, as if he
<pb n="281" id="CheOrac281"/>
himself had known the man all his life. "A curious but not unknown
type of character. If he had really known the money
would come to him, I seriously believe he wouldn't have done it.
He would have seen it as the dirty thing it was."
</p><p>"Isn't that rather paradoxical?" asked the other.
</p><p>"This man was a gambler," said the priest, "and a man in
disgrace for having taken risks and anticipated orders. It was
probably for something pretty unscrupulous, for every imperial
police is more like a Russian secret police than we like to think.
But he had gone beyond the line and failed. Now, the temptation
of that type of man is to do a mad thing precisely because
the risk will be wonderful in retrospect. He wants to say,
'Nobody but I could have seized that chance or seen that it was
then or never. What a wild and wonderful guess it was, when
I put all those things together; Donald in disgrace; and the
lawyer being sent for; and Herbert and I sent for at the same
time&mdash;and then nothing more but the way the old man grinned
at me and shook hands. Anybody would say I was mad to
risk it; but that is how fortunes are made, by the man mad
enough to have a little foresight.' In short, it is the vanity
of guessing. It is the megalomania of the gambler. The more
incongruous the coincidence, the more instantaneous the decision,
the more likely he is to snatch the chance. The accident,
the very triviality, of the white speck and the hole in the hedge
intoxicated him like a vision of the world's desire. Nobody
clever enough to see such a combination of accidents could be
cowardly enough not to use them! That is how the devil talks to
the gambler. But the devil himself would hardly have induced
that unhappy man to go down in a dull, deliberate way and kill
an old uncle from whom he'd always had expectations. It would
be too respectable."
</p><p>He paused a moment; and then went on with a certain quiet
emphasis.
</p><p>"And now try to call up the scene, even as you saw it yourself.
As he stood there, dizzy with his diabolical opportunity,
he looked up and saw that strange outline that might have been
the image of his own tottering soul; the one great crag poised
perilously on the other like a pyramid on its point and remembered
that it was called the Rock of Fortune. Can you
guess how such a man at such a moment would read such a
signal? I think it strung him up to action and even to vigilance.
He who would be a tower must not fear to be a toppling
<pb n="282" id="CheOrac282"/>
tower. Anyhow, he acted; his next difficulty was to cover his
tracks. To be found with a sword-stick, let alone a blood-stained sword-stick, would be fatal in the search that was certain
to follow. If he left it anywhere, it would be found and probably
traced. Even if he threw it into the sea the action might be
noticed, and thought noticeable&mdash;unless indeed he could think
of some more natural way of covering the action. As you know,
he did think of one, and a very good one. Being the only one
of you with a watch, he told you it was not yet time to return,
strolled a little farther and started the game of throwing in
sticks for the retriever. But how his eyes must have rolled
darkly over all that desolate seashore before they alighted on the
dog!"
</p><p>Fiennes nodded, gazing thoughtfully into space. His mind
seemed to have drifted back to a less practical part of the
narrative.
</p><p>"It's queer," he said, "that the dog really was in the story
after all."
</p><p>"The dog could almost have told you the story, if he could
talk," said the priest. "All I complain of is that because he
couldn't talk, you made up his story for him, and made him
talk with the tongues of men and angels. It's part of something
I've noticed more and more in the modern world, appearing
in all sorts of newspaper rumors and conversational catch-words; something that's arbitrary without being authoritative.
People readily swallow the untested claims of this, that, or the
other. It's drowning all your old rationalism and scepticism,
it's coming in like a sea; and the name of it is superstition." He
stood up abruptly, his face heavy with a sort of frown, and went
on talking almost as if he were alone. "It's the first effect of
not believing in God that you lose your common sense, and
can't see things as they are. Anything that anybody talks
about, and says there's a good deal in it, extends itself indefinitely
like a, vista in a nightmare. And a dog is an omen and
a cat is a mystery and a pig is a mascot and a beetle is a scarab,
calling up all the menagerie of polytheism from Egypt and old
India; Dog Anubis and great green-eyed Pasht and all the holy
howling Bulls of Bashan; reeling back to the bestial gods of the
beginning, escaping into elephants and snakes and crocodiles;
and all because you are frightened of four words: 'He was made
Man."'
</p><p>The young man got up with a little embarrassment, almost as
<pb n="283" id="CheOrac283"/>
if he had overheard a soliloquy. He called to the dog and left
the room with vague but breezy farewells. But he had to call
the dog twice, for the dog had remained behind quite motionless
for a moment, looking up steadily at Father Brown as the wolf
looked at St. Francis.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
