<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CheProg"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="CheProg">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The March of Progress</title>
<title type="sort">march of progress</title>
<author>Chesnutt, Charles Waddell, 1858-1932</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">27</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CheProg</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475814</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The March of Progress</title>
<title type="sort">march of progress</title>
<author>Charles W. Chesnutt</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Edited by</resp>
<name>editor</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Publisher
<name>Century Magazine</name>
</publisher>
<date value="1901-01">Jan. 1901</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Vol. 61.3</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Verification made against printed text</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1901">1901</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction;  prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-01">January 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>David Seaman and Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header and basic TEI SGML encoding added</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head>
Chesnutt, Charles W.  "The March of Progress."
<lb/>
<hi rend="italic"> Century Magazine</hi> 61.3 (Jan. 1901): 422-428.
<lb/>
Author of "The Conjure Woman," "The Wife of His Youth," etc.
</head>
<pb n="422"/>

<p>THE colored people of Patesville had at length gained the object
they had for a long time been seeking&mdash;the appointment of a
committee of themselves to manage the colored schools of the town.
They had argued, with some show of reason, that they were most
interested in the education of their own children, and in a
position to know, better than any committee of white men could,
what was best for their children's needs.  The appointments had
been made by the county commissioners during the latter part of the
summer, and a week later a meeting was called for the purpose of
electing a teacher to take charge of the grammar school at the
beginning of the fall term.
</p><p>The committee consisted of Frank Gillespie, or "Glaspy," a
barber, who took an active part in local politics; Bob Cotten, a
blacksmith, who owned several houses and was looked upon as a
substantial citizen; and Abe Johnson, commonly called "Ole Abe" or
"Uncle Abe," who had a large family, and drove a dray, and did odd
jobs of hauling; he was also a class-leader in the Methodist
church.  The committee had been chosen from among a number of
candidates&mdash;Gillespie on account of his political standing, Cotten
as representing the solid element of the colored population, and
Old Abe, with democratic impartiality, as likely to satisfy the
humbler class of a humble people.  While the choice had not pleased
everybody,&mdash;for instance, some of the other applicants,&mdash;it was
acquiesced in with general satisfaction.  The first meeting of the
new committee was of great public interest, partly by reason of its
novelty, but chiefly because there were two candidates for the
position of teacher of the grammar school.
</p><p>The former teacher, Miss Henrietta Noble, had applied for the
school.  She had taught the colored children of Patesville for
fifteen years.  When the Freedmen's Bureau, after the military
occupation of North Carolina, had called for volunteers to teach
the children of the freedmen, Henrietta Nobel had offered her
services.  Brought up in a New England household by parents who
taught her to fear God and love her fellow-men, she had seen her
father's body brought home from a Southern battle-field and laid to
rest in the village cemetery; and a short six months later she had
buried her mother by his side.  Henrietta had no brothers or
sisters, and her nearest relatives were cousins living in the far
West.  The only human being in whom she felt any special personal
interest was a certain captain in her father's regiment, who had
paid her some attention.  She had loved this man deeply, in a
maidenly, modest way; but he had gone away without speaking, and
had not since written.  He had escaped the fate of many others, and
at the close of the war was alive and well, stationed in some
Southern garrison.
</p><p>When her mother died, Henrietta had found herself possessed
only of the house where she lived and the furniture it contained,
neither being of much value, and she was thrown upon her own
resources for a livelihood.  She had a fair education and had read
many good books.  It was not easy to find employment such as she
desired.  She wrote to her Western cousins, and they advised her to
come to them, as they thought they could do something for her if
she were there.  She had almost decided to accept their offer, when
the demand arose for teachers in the South.  Whether impelled by
some strain of adventurous blood from a Pilgrim ancestry, or by a
sensitive pride that <pb n="423"/>  shrank from dependence, or by some dim
and unacknowledged hope that she might sometime, somewhere, somehow
meet Captain Carey&mdash;whether from one of these motives or a
combination of them all, joined to something of the missionary
spirit, she decided to go South, and wrote to her cousins declining
their friendly offer.
</p><p>She had come to Patesville when the children were mostly a mob
of dirty little beggars.  She had distributed among them the cast-off clothing that came from their friends in the North; she had
taught them to wash their faces and to comb their hair; and
patiently, year after year, she had labored to instruct them in the
rudiments of learning and the first principles of religion and
morality.  And she had not wrought in vain.  Other agencies, it is
true, had in time cooperated with her efforts, but any one who had
watched the current of events must have been compelled to admit
that the very fair progress of the colored people of Patesville in
the fifteen years following emancipation had been due chiefly to
the unselfish labors of Henrietta Noble, and that her nature did
not belie her name.
</p><p>Fifteen years is a long time.  Miss Noble had never met
Captain Carey; and when she learned later that he had married a
Southern girl in the neighborhood of his post, she had shed her
tears in secret and banished his image from her heart.  She had
lived a lonely life.  The white people of the town, though they
learned in time to respect her and to value her work, had never
recognized her existence by more than the mere external courtesy
shown by any community to one who lives in the midst of it.  The
situation was at first, of course, so strained that she did not
expect sympathy from the white people; and later, when time had
smoothed over some of the asperities of war, her work had so
engaged her that she had not had time to pine over her social
exclusion.  Once or twice nature had asserted itself, and she had
longed for her own kind, and had visited her New England home.  But
her circle of friends was broken up, and she did not find much
pleasure in boarding-house life; and on her last visit to the North
but one, she had felt so lonely that she had longed for the dark
faces of her pupils, and had welcomed with pleasure the hour when
her task should be resumed.
</p><p>But for several reasons the school at Patesville was of more
importance to Miss Noble at this particular time than it ever had
been before.  During the last few years her health had not been
good.  An affection of the heart similar to that from which her
mother had died, while not interfering perceptibly with her work,
had grown from bad to worse, aggravated by close application to her
duties, until it had caused her grave alarm.  She did not have
perfect confidence in the skill of the Patesville physicians, and
to obtain the best medical advice had gone to New York during the
summer, remaining there a month under the treatment of an eminent
specialist.  This, of course, had been expensive and had absorbed
the savings of years from a small salary; and when the time came
for her to return to Patesville, she was reduced, after paying her
traveling expenses, to her last ten-dollar note.
</p><p>"It is very fortunate," the great man had said at her last
visit, "that circumstances permit you to live in the South, for I
am afraid you could not endure a Northern winter.  You are getting
along very well now, and if you will take care of yourself and
avoid excitement, you will be better."  He said to himself as she
went away: "It's only a matter of time, but that is true about us
all; and a wise physician does as much good by what he withholds as
by what he tells."
</p><p>Miss Noble had not anticipated any trouble about the school.
When she went away the same committee of white men was in charge
that had controlled the school since it had become part of the
public-school system of the State on the withdrawal of support from
the Freedmen's Bureau.  While there had been no formal engagement
made for the next year, when she had last seen the chairman before
she went away, he had remarked that she was looking rather fagged
out, had bidden her good-by, and had hoped to see her much improved
when she returned.  She had left her house in the care of the
colored woman who lived with her and did her housework, assuming,
of course, that she would take up her work again in the autumn.
</p><p>She was much surprised at first, and later alarmed, to find a
rival for her position as teacher of the grammar school.  Many of
her friends and pupils had called on her since her return, and she
had met a number of the people at the colored Methodist church,
where she taught in the Sunday-school.  She had many friends and
supporters, but she soon found out that her opponent had
considerable strength.  There had been a time when she would have
withdrawn and left him a clear field, but at the present moment it
<pb n="424"/>  was almost a matter of life and death to her&mdash;certainly the
matter of earning a living&mdash;to secure the appointment.
</p><p>The other candidate was a young man who in former years had
been one of Miss Noble's brightest pupils.  When he had finished
his course in the grammar school, his parents, with considerable
sacrifice, had sent him to a college for colored youth.  He had
studied diligently, had worked industriously during his vacations,
sometimes at manual labor, sometimes teaching a country school, and
in due time had been graduated from his college with honors.  He
had come home at the end of his school life, and was very naturally
seeking the employment for which he had fitted himself.  He was a
"bright" mulatto, with straight hair, an intelligent face, and a
well-set figure.  He had acquired some of the marks of culture,
wore a frock-coat and a high collar, parted his hair in the middle,
and showed by his manner that he thought a good deal of himself.
He was the popular candidate among the progressive element of his
people, and rather confidently expected the appointment.
</p><p>The meeting of the committee was held in the Methodist church,
where, in fact, the grammar school was taught, for want of a
separate school-house.  After the preliminary steps to effect an
organization, Mr. Gillespie, who had been elected chairman, took
the floor.
</p><p>"The principal business to be brought befo' the meet'n' this
evenin'," he said, "is the selection of a teacher for our grammar
school for the ensuin' year.  Two candidates have filed
applications, which, if there is no objection, I will read to the
committee.  The first is from Miss Noble, who has been the teacher
ever since the grammar school was started."
</p><p>He then read Miss Noble's letter, in which she called
attention to her long years of service, to her need of the
position, and to her affection for the pupils, and made formal
application for the school for the next year.  She did not, from
motives of self-respect, make known the extremity of her need; nor
did she mention the condition of her health, as it might have been
used as an argument against her retention.
</p><p>Mr. Gillespie then read the application of the other
candidate, Andrew J. Williams.  Mr. Williams set out in detail his
qualifications for the position: his degree from Riddle University;
his familiarity with the dead and living languages and the higher
mathematics; his views of discipline; and a peroration in which he
expressed the desire to devote himself to the elevation of his race
and assist the march of progress through the medium of the
Patesville grammar school.  The letter was well written in a bold,
round hand, with many flourishes, and looked very aggressive and
overbearing as it lay on the table by the side of the sheet of
small note-paper in Miss Noble's faint and somewhat cramped
handwriting.
</p><p>"You have heard the readin' of the applications," said the
chairman.  "Gentlemen, what is yo' pleasure?"
</p><p>There being no immediate response, the chairman continued:
</p><p>"As this is a matter of consid'able importance, involvin' not
only the welfare of our schools, but the progress of our race, an'
as our action is liable to be criticized, whatever we decide,
perhaps we had better discuss the subjec' befo' we act.  If nobody
else has anything to obse've, I will make a few remarks."
</p><p>Mr. Gillespie cleared his throat, and, assuming an oratorical
attitude, proceeded:
</p><p>"The time has come in the history of our people when we should
stand together.  In this age of organization the march of progress
requires that we help ourselves, or be forever left behind.  Ever
since the war we have been sendin' our child'n to school an'
educatin' 'em; an' now the time has come when they are leavin' the
schools an' colleges, an' are ready to go to work.  An' what are
they goin' to do?  The white people won't hire 'em as clerks in
their sto's an' factories an' mills, an' we have no sto's or
factories or mills of our own.  They can't be lawyers or doctors
yet, because we haven't got the money to send 'em to medical
colleges an' law schools.  We can't elect many of 'em to office,
for various reasons.  There's just two things they can find to do&mdash;
to preach in our own pulpits, an' teach in our own schools.  If it
wasn't for that, they'd have to go on forever waitin' on white
folks, like their fo'fathers have done, because they couldn't help
it.  If we expect our race to progress, we must educate our young
men an' women.  If we want to encourage 'em to get education, we
must find 'em employment when they are educated.  We have now an
opportunity to do this in the case of our young friend an' fellow-citizen, Mr. Williams, whose eloquent an' fine-lookin' letter ought
to make us feel proud of him an' of our race.
</p><p>"Of co'se there are two sides to the question.  We have got to
consider the claims of Miss Noble.  She has been with us a long
<pb n="425"/>  time an' has done much good work for our people, an' we'll
never forget her work an' frien'ship.  But, after all, she has been
paid for it; she has got her salary regularly an' for a long time,
an' she has probably saved somethin', for we all know she hasn't
lived high; an', for all we know, she may have had somethin' left
her by her parents.  An' then again, she's white, an' has got her
own people to look after her; they've got all the money an' all the
offices an' all the everythin',&mdash;all that they've made an' all that
we've made for fo' hundred years,&mdash;an' they sho'ly would look out
for her.  If she don't get this school, there's probably a dozen
others she can get at the North.  An' another thing: she is gettin'
rather feeble, an' it 'pears to me she's hardly able to stand
teachin' so many child'n, an' a long rest might be the best thing
in the world for her.
</p><p>"Now, gentlemen, that's the situation.  Shall we keep Miss
Noble, or shall we stand by our own people?  It seems to me there
can hardly be but one answer.  Self-preservation is the first law
of nature.  Are there any other remarks?"
</p><p>Old Abe was moving restlessly in his seat.  He did not say
anything, however, and the chairman turned to the other member.
</p><p>"Brother Cotten, what is yo' opinion of the question befo' the
board?"
</p><p>Mr. Cotten rose with the slowness and dignity becoming a
substantial citizen, and observed:
</p><p>"I think the remarks of the chairman have great weight.  We
all have nothin' but kind feelin's fer Miss Noble, an' I came here
to-night somewhat undecided how to vote on this question.  But
after listenin' to the just an' forcible arguments of Brother
Glaspy, it 'pears to me that, after all, the question befo' us is
not a matter of feelin', but of business.  As a business man, I am
inclined to think Brother Glaspy is right.  If we don't help
ourselves when we get a chance, who is goin' to help us?"
</p><p>"That bein' the case," said the chairman, "shall we proceed to
a vote?  All who favor the election of Brother Williams&mdash;"
</p><p>At this point Old Abe, with much preliminary shuffling, stood
up in his place and interrupted the speaker.
</p><p>"Mr. Chuhman," he said, "I s'pose I has a right ter speak in
dis meet'n?  I <hi rend="italic"> s'pose</hi> I is a member er dis committee?"
</p><p>"Certainly, Brother Johnson, certainly; we shall be glad to
hear from you."
</p><p>"I s'pose I's got a right ter speak my min', ef I is po' an'
black, an' don' weah as good clo's as some other members er de
committee?"
</p><p>"Most assuredly, Brother Johnson," answered the chairman, with
a barber's suavity, "you have as much right to be heard as any one
else.  There was no intention of cuttin' you off."
</p><p>"I s'pose," continued Abe, "dat a man wid fo'teen child'n kin
be 'lowed ter hab somethin' ter say 'bout de schools er dis town?"
</p><p>"I am sorry, Brother Johnson, that you should feel slighted,
but there was no intention to igno' yo' rights.  The committee will
be please' to have you ventilate yo' views."
</p><p>"Ef it's all be'n an' done reco'nized an' 'cided dat I's got
de right ter be heared in dis meet'n', I'll say w'at I has ter say,
an' it won't take me long ter say it.  Ef I should try ter tell all
de things dat Miss Noble has done fer de niggers er dis town, it'd
take me till ter-morrer mawnin'.  Fer fifteen long yeahs I has
watched her incomin's an' her outgoin's.  Her daddy was a Yankee
kunnel, who died fighting fer ou' freedom.  She come heah when we&mdash;
yas, Mr. Chuhman, when you an' Br'er Cotten&mdash;was jes sot free, an'
when none er us didn' have a rag ter ou' backs.  She come heah, an'
she tuk yo' child'n an' my child'n, an' she teached 'em sense an'
manners an' religion an' book-l'arnin'.  When she come heah we
didn' hab no chu'ch.  Who writ up No'th an' got a preacher sent to
us, an' de fun's ter buil' dis same chu'ch-house we're settin' in
ter-night?  Who got de money f'm de Bureau to s'port de school?
An' when dat was stop', who got de money f'm de Peabody Fun'?  Talk
about Miss Noble gittin' a sal'ry!  Who paid dat sal'ry up ter five
years ago?  Not one dollah of it come outer ou' pockets!
</p><p>"An' den, w'at did she git fer de yuther things she done?  Who
paid her fer de gals she kep' f'm throwin' deyse'ves away?  Who
paid fer de boys she kep' outer jail?  I had a son dat seemed to
hab made up his min' ter go straight ter hell.  I made him go ter
Sunday-school, an' somethin' dat woman said teched his heart, an'
he behaved hisse'f, an' I ain' got no reason fer ter be 'shame' er
'im.  An' I can 'member, Br'er Cotten, when you didn' own fo'
houses an' a fahm.  An' when yo' fus wife was sick, who sot by her
bedside an' read de Good Book ter 'er, w'en dey wuzn' nobody else
knowed how ter read it, an' comforted her on her way across de
col', dahk ribber?  An' dat ain' all I kin <pb n="426"/>  'member, Mr.
Chuhman!  When yo' gal Fanny was a baby, an' sick, an' nobody
knowed what was de matter wid 'er, who sent fer a doctor, an' paid
'im fer comin', an' who he'ped nuss dat chile, an' tol' yo' wife
w'at ter do, an' save' dat chile's life, jes as sho' as de Lawd has
save' my soul?
</p><p>"An' now, aftuh fifteen yeahs o' slavin' fer us, who ain't got
no claim on her, aftuh fifteen yeahs dat she has libbed 'mongs' us
an' made herse'f one of us, an' endyoed havin' her own people look
down on her, aftuh she has growed ole an' gray wukkin' fer us an'
our child'n, we talk erbout turnin' 'er out like a' ole hoss ter
die!  It 'pears ter me some folks has po' mem'ries!  Whar would we
'a' be'n ef her folks at de No'th hadn' 'membered us no bettuh?
An' we hadn' done nothin', neither, fer dem to 'member us fer.  De
man dat kin fergit w'at Miss Noble has done fer dis town is
unworthy de name er nigger!  He oughter die an' make room fer some
'spectable dog!
</p><p>"Br'er Glaspy says we got a' educated young man, an' we mus'
gib him sump'n' ter do.  Let him wait; ef I reads de signs right he
won't hab ter wait long fer dis job.  Let him teach in de primary
schools, er in de country; an' ef he can't do dat, let 'im work
awhile.  It don't hahm a' educated man ter work a little; his
fo'fathers has worked fer hund'eds of years, an' we's worked, an'
we're heah yet, an' we're free, an' we's gettin' ou' own houses an'
lots an' hosses an' cows&mdash;an' ou' educated young men.  But don't
let de fus thing we do as a committee be somethin' we ought ter be
'shamed of as long as we lib.  I votes fer Miss Noble, fus, las',
an' all de time!"
</p><p>When Old Abe sat down the chairman's face bore a troubled
look.  He remembered how his baby girl, the first of his children
that he could really call his own, that no master could hold a
prior claim upon, lay dying in the arms of his distracted young
wife, and how the thin, homely, and short-sighted white teacher had
come like an angel into his cabin, and had brought back the little
one from the verge of the grave.  The child was a young woman now,
and Gillespie had well-founded hopes of securing the superior young
Williams for a son-in-law; and he realized with something of shame
that this later ambition had so dazzled his eyes for a moment as to
obscure the memory of earlier days.
</p><p>Mr. Cotten, too, had not been unmoved, and there were tears in
his eyes as he recalled how his first wife, Nancy, who had borne
with him the privations of slavery, had passed away, with the
teacher's hand in hers, before she had been able to enjoy the
fruits of liberty.  For they had loved one another much, and her
death had been to them both a hard and bitter thing.  And, as Old
Abe spoke, he could remember, as distinctly as though they had been
spoken but an hour before, the words of comfort that the teacher
had whispered to Nancy in her dying hour and to him in his
bereavement.
</p><p>"On consideration, Mr. Chairman," he said, with an effort to
hide a suspicious tremor in his voice and to speak with the dignity
consistent with his character as a substantial citizen, "I wish to
record my vote fer Miss Noble."
</p><p>"The chair," said Gillespie, yielding gracefully to the
majority, and greatly relieved that the responsibility of his
candidate's defeat lay elsewhere, "will make the vote unanimous,
and will appoint Brother Cotten and Brother Johnson a committee to
step round the corner to Miss Noble's and notify her of her
election."
</p><p>The two committeemen put on their hats, and, accompanied by
several people who had been waiting at the door to hear the result
of the meeting, went around the corner to Miss Noble's house, a
distance of a block or two away.  The house was lighted, so they
knew she had not gone to bed.  They went in at the gate, and Cotten
knocked at the door.
</p><p>The colored maid opened it.
</p><p>"Is Miss Noble home?" said Cotten.
</p><p>'Yes; come in.  She's waitin' ter hear from the committee."
</p><p>The woman showed them into the parlor.  Miss Noble rose from
her seat by the table, where she had been reading, and came forward
to meet them.  They did not for a moment observe, as she took a
step toward them, that her footsteps wavered.  In her agitation she
was scarcely aware of it herself.
</p><p>"Miss Noble," announced Cotten, "we have come to let you know
that you have be'n 'lected teacher of the grammar school fer the
next year."
</p><p>"Thank you; oh, thank you so much!" she said.  "I am very
glad.  Mary"&mdash;she put her hand to her side suddenly and tottered&mdash;
"Mary, will you&mdash;"
</p><p>A spasm of pain contracted her face and cut short her speech.
She would have fallen had Old Abe not caught her and, with Mary's
help, laid her on a couch.
</p><p>The remedies applied by Mary, and by the <pb n="427"/>  [illustration
omitted] <pb n="428"/>  physician who was hastily summoned, proved
unavailing.  The teacher did not regain consciousness.
</p><p>If it be given to those whose eyes have closed in death to
linger regretfully for a while about their earthly tenement, or
from some higher vantage-ground to look down upon it, then
Henrietta Noble's tolerant spirit must have felt, mingling with its
regret, a compensating thrill of pleasure; for not only those for
whom she had labored sorrowed for her, but the people of her own
race, many of whom, in the blindness of their pride, would not
admit during her life that she served them also, saw so much
clearer now that they took charge of her poor clay, and did it
gentle reverence, and laid it tenderly away amid the dust of their
own loved and honored dead.

TWO weeks after Miss Noble's funeral the other candidate took
charge of the grammar school, which went on without any further
obstacles to the march of progress.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
