<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CheSand"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="CheSand">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Po' Sandy</title>
<title type="sort">po sandy</title>
<author>Chesnutt, Charles Waddell, 1858-1932</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">27</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CheSand</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475815</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Po' Sandy</title>
<title type="sort">po sandy</title>
<author>Charles W. Chesnutt</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1888">1888</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 61</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 605-611</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library
Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text
Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are
composed of the text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as
in SpeFQue1 for page one of Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1888">1888</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-03">March 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Timothy O. Jarrett</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">



<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="605"/>
<head>
Chesnutt, Charles W.  "Po' Sandy."  <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 61 (1888):
605-611. </head>

<p>ON the northeast corner of my vineyard in central North Carolina,
and fronting on the Lumberton plank-road, there stood a small frame
house, of the simplest construction.  It was built of pine lumber, and
contained but one room, to which one window gave light and one door
admission.  Its weather-beaten sides revealed a virgin innocence of paint.
Against one end of the house, and occupying half its width, there stood a
huge brick chimney: the crumbling mortar had left large cracks between
the bricks; the bricks themselves had begun to scale off in large flakes,
leaving the chimney sprinkled with unsightly blotches.  These evidences
of decay were but partially concealed by a creeping vine, which extended
its slender branches hither and thither in an ambitious but futile attempt
to cover the whole chimney.  The wooden shutter, which had once
protected the unglazed window, had fallen from its hinges, and lay
rotting in the rank grass and jimson-weeds beneath.  This building, I
learned when I bought the place, had been used as a school-house for
several years prior to the breaking out of the war, since which time it
had remained unoccupied, save when some stray cow or vagrant hog had
sought shelter within its walls from the chill rains and nipping winds of
winter.</p>
<p> One day my wife requested me to build her a new kitchen.  The
house erected by us, when we first came to live upon the vineyard,
contained a very conveniently arranged kitchen; but for some occult
reason my wife wanted a kitchen in the back yard, apart from the
dwelling-house, after the usual Southern fashion.  Of course I had to
build it.</p>
<p> To save expense, I decided to tear down the old school-house, and
use the lumber, which was in a good state of preservation, in the
construction of the new kitchen.  Before demolishing the old house,
however, I made an estimate of the amount of material contained in it,
and found that I would have to buy several hundred feet of new lumber
in order to build the new kitchen according to my wife's plan.</p>
<p> One morning old Julius McAdoo, our colored coachman,
harnessed the gray mare to the rockaway, and drove my wife and me
over to the saw-mill from which I meant to order the new lumber.  We
drove down the long lane which led from our house to the plank-road;
following the plank-road for about a mile, we turned into a road running
through the forest and across the swamp to the sawmill beyond.  Our
carriage jolted over the half-rotted corduroy road which traversed the
swamp, and then climbed the long hill leading to the saw-mill.  When
we reached the mill, the foreman had gone over to a neighboring
farm-house, probably to smoke or gossip, and we were compelled to
await his return before we could transact our business.  We remained
seated in the carriage, a few rods from the mill, and watched the
leisurely movements of the mill-hands.  We had not waited long before a
huge pine log was placed in position, the machinery of the mill was set
in motion, and the circular saw began to eat its way through the log,
with a loud whirr which resounded throughout the vicinity of the mill.
The sound rose and fell in a sort of rhythmic cadence, which, heard
from where we sat, was not unpleasing, and not loud enough to prevent
conversation.  When the saw started on its second journey through the
log, Julius observed, in a lugubrious tone, and with a perceptible
shudder: &mdash; </p>
<p> "Ugh! but dat des do cuddle my blood!"</p>

<pb n="606"/>
<p> "What's the matter, Uncle Julius?" inquired my wife, who is of a
very sympathetic turn of mind.  "Does the noise affect your
nerves?"</p>
<p> "No, Miss Annie," replied the old man, with emotion, "I ain'
narvous; but dat saw, a-cuttin' en grindin' thoo dat stick er timber, en
moanin', en groanin', en sweekin', kyars my 'memb'ance back ter ole
times, en 'min's me er po' Sandy."  The pathetic intonation with which
he lengthened out the "po' Sandy" touched a responsive chord in our
own hearts."</p>
<p> "And who was poor Sandy?" asked my wife, who takes a deep
interest in the stories of plantation life which she hears from the lips of
the older colored people.  Some of these stories are quaintly humorous;
others wildly extravagant, revealing the Oriental cast of the negro's
imagination; while others, poured freely into the sympathetic ear of a
Northern-bred woman, disclose many a tragic incident of the darker side
of slavery.</p>
<p> "Sandy," said Julius, in reply to my wife's question, "was a
nigger w'at useter b'long ter ole Mars Marrabo McSwayne.  Mars
Marrabo's place wuz on de yuther side'n de swamp, right nex' ter yo'
place.  Sandy wuz a monst'us good nigger, en could do so many things
erbout a plantation, en alluz 'ten ter his wuk so well, dat w'en Mars
Marrabo's chilluns growed up en married off, dey all un 'em wanted dey
daddy fer ter gin 'em Sandy fer a weddin' present.  But Mars Marrabo
knowed de res' wouldn' be satisfied ef he gin Sandy ter a'er one un 'em;
so w'en dey wuz all done married, he fix it by 'lowin' one er his
chilluns ter take Sandy fer a mont' er so, en den ernudder for a mont' er
so, en so on dat erway tel dey had all had 'im de same lenk er time; en
den dey would all take him roun' ag'in, 'cep'n oncet in a w'ile w'en
Mars Marrabo would len' 'im ter some er his yuther kinfolks 'roun' de
country, w'en dey wuz short er han's; tel bimeby it go so Sandy didn'
hardly knowed whar he wuz gwine ter stay fum one week's een ter de
yuther.</p>
<p> "One time w'en Sandy wuz lent out ez yushal, a spekilater come
erlong wid a lot er niggers, en Mars Marrabo swap' Sandy's wife off fer
a noo 'oman.  W'en Sandy come back, Mars Marrabo gin 'im a dollar,
en 'lowed he wuz monst'us sorry fer ter break up de fambly, but de
spekilater had gin 'im big boot, en times wuz hard en money skase, en
so he wuz bleedst ter make de trade.  Sandy tuk on some 'bout losin' his
wife, but he soon seed dey want no use cryin' ober spilt merlasses; en
bein' ez he lacked de looks er de noo 'ooman, he tuk up wid her atter
she b'n on de plantation a mont' er so.</p>
<p> "Sandy en his noo wife got on mighty well tergedder, en de
niggers all 'mence' ter talk about how lovin' dey wuz.  W'en Tenie wuz
tuk sick oncet, Sandy useter set up all night wid 'er, en den go ter wuk
in de mawnin' des lack he had his reg'lar sleep; en Tenie would 'a done
anythin' in de worl' for her Sandy.</p>
<p> "Sandy en Tenie hadn' b'en libbin' tergedder fer mo' d'n two
mont's befo' Mars Marrabo's old uncle, w'at libbed down in Robeson
County, sent up ter fine out ef Mars Marrabo couldn' len' 'im er hire
'im a good han' fer a mont' er so.  Sandy's marster wuz one er dese yer
easy-gwine folks w'at wanter please eve'ybody, en he says yas, he could
len' 'im Sandy.  En Mars Marrabo tole Sandy fer ter git ready ter go
down ter Robeson nex' day, fer ter stay a mont' er so.</p>
<p> "Hit wuz monst'us hard on Sandy fer ter take 'im 'way fum
Tenie.  Hit wuz so fur down ter Robeson dat he didn' hab no chance er
comin' back ter see her tel de time wuz up; he wouldn' a' mine comin'
ten er fifteen mile at night ter see Tenie, but Mars Marrabo's uncle's
plantation wuz mo' d'n forty mile off.  Sandy wuz mighty sad en cas'
down atter w'at Mars Marrabo tole 'im, en he says ter Tenie, sezee: &mdash;
</p>

<pb n="607"/>
<p> "'I'm gittin monstus ti'ed er dish yer gwine roun' so much.  Here
I is lent ter Mars Jeems dis mont', en I got ter do so-en-so; en ter Mars
Archie de nex' mont', en I got ter do so-en-so; den I got ter go ter Miss
Jinnie's: en hit's Sandy dis en Sandy dat, en Sandy yer en Sandy dere,
tel it 'pears ter me I ain' got no home, ner no marster, ner no mistiss,
ner no nuffin'.  I can't eben keep a wife: my yuther ole 'oman wuz sole
away widout my gittin' a chance fer ter tell her good-by; en now I got
ter go off en leab you, Tenie, en I dunno whe'r I'm eber gwine ter see
yer ag'in er no.  I wisht I wuz a tree, er a stump, er a rock, er sump'n
w'at could stay on de plantation fer a w'ile.'</p>
<p> "Atter Sandy got thoo talkin', Tenie didn' say naer word, but des
sot dere by de fier, studyin' en studyin'.  Bimeby she up'n says: &mdash;
</p>
<p> "'Sandy, is I eber tole you I wuz a cunjuh-'ooman?'</p>
<p> "Co'se Sandy hadn' nebber dremp' er nuffin lack dat, en he made
a great miration w'en he hear w'at Tenie say.  Bimeby Tenie went on: &mdash;
</p>
<p> "'I ain' goophered nobody, ner done no cunjuh-wuk fer fifteen yer
er mo; en w'en I got religion I made up my mine I wouldn' wuk no mo'
goopher.  But dey is some things I doan b'lieve it's no sin fer ter do; en
ef you doan wanter be sent roun' fum pillar ter pos', en ef you doan
wanter go down ter Robeson, I kin fix things so yer won't haf ter.  Ef
you'll des say de word, I kin turn yer ter w'ateber yer wanter be, en yer
kin stay right whar yer wanter, ez long ez yer mineter.'</p>
<p> "Sandy say he doan keer; he's willin' fer ter do anythin' fer ter
stay close ter Tenie.  Den Tenie ax 'im ef he doan wanter be turnt inter
a rabbit.</p>
<p> "Sandy say, 'No, de dogs mout git atter me.'</p>
<p> "'Shill I turn yer ter a wolf?' sez Tenie.</p>
<p> "'No, eve'ybody's skeered er a wolf, en I doan want nobody ter
be skeered er me.'</p>
<p> "'Shill I turn yer ter a mawkin'-bird?'</p>
<p> "'No, a hawk mout ketch me.  I wanter be turnt inter sump'n
w'at'll stay in one place.'</p>
<p> "'I kin turn yer ter a tree,' sez Tenie.  'You won't hab no mouf
ner years, but I kin turn yer back oncet in a w'ile, so yer kin git sump'n
ter eat, en hear w'at's gwine on.'</p>
<p> "Well, Sandy say dat'll do.  En so Tenie tuk 'im down by de
aidge er de swamp, not fur fum de quarters, en turnt 'im inter a big
pine-tree, en sot 'im out mongs' some yuther trees.  En de nex'
mawnin', ez some er de fiel' han's wuz gwine long dere, dey seed a tree
w'at dey didn' 'member er habbin' seed befo; it wuz monst'us quare, en
dey wuz bleedst ter 'low dat dey hadn' 'membered right, er e'se one er
de saplin's had be'n growin' monst'us fas'.</p>
<p> "W'en Mars Marrabo 'skiver' dat Sandy wuz gone, he 'lowed
Sandy had runned away.  He got de dogs out, but de las' place dey could
track Sandy ter wuz de foot er dat pine-tree.  En dere de dogs stood en
barked, en bayed, en pawed at de tree, en tried ter climb up on it; en
w'en dey wuz tuk roun' thoo de swamp ter look fer de scent, dey broke
loose en made fer dat tree ag'in.  It wuz de beatenis' thing de w'ite folks
eber hearn of, en Mars Marrabo 'lowed dat Sandy must a' clim' up on
de tree en jump' off on a mule er sump'n, en rid fur 'nuff fer ter spile
de scent.  Mars Marrabo wanted ter 'cuse some er de yuther niggers er
heppin Sandy off, but dey all 'nied it ter de las'; en eve'ybody knowed
Tenie sot too much by Sandy fer ter he'p 'im run away whar she couldn'
nebber see 'im no mo'.</p>
<p> "W'en Sandy had be'n gone long 'nuff fer folks ter think he done
got clean away, Tenie useter go down ter de woods at night en turn 'im
back, en den dey'd slip up ter de cabin en set by de

<pb n="608"/>  fire en talk.  But dey ha' ter be monst'us keerful, er
e'se somebody would a seed 'em, en dat would a spile de whole thing;
so Tenie alluz turnt Sandy back in de mawnin' early, befo' anybody wuz
a'stirrin'.</p>
<p> "But Sandy didn' git erlong widout his trials en tribberlations.
One day a woodpecker come erlong en 'mence' ter peck at de tree; en de
nex' time Sandy wuz turnt back he had a little roun' hole in his arm, des
lack a sharp stick be'n stuck in it.  Atter dat Tenie sot a sparrer-hawk fer
ter watch de tree; en w'en de woodpecker come erlong nex' mawnin' fer
ter finish his nes', he got gobble' up mos' fo' he stuck his bill in de
bark.</p>
<p> "Nudder time, Mars Marrabo sent a nigger out in de woods fer
ter chop tuppentime boxes.  De man chop a box in dish yer tree, en
hack' de bark up two er th'ee feet, fer ter let de tuppentime run.  De
nex' time Sandy wuz turnt back he had a big skyar on his lef' leg, des
lack it be'n skunt; en it tuk Tenie nigh 'bout all night fer ter fix a mixtry
ter kyo it up.  Atter dat, Tenie sot a hawnet fer ter watch de tree; en
w'en de nigger come back ag'in fer ter cut ernudder box on de yuther
side'n de tree, de hawnet stung 'im so hard dat de ax slip en cut his foot
nigh 'bout off.</p>
<p> "W'en Tenie see so many things happenin' ter de tree, she
'cluded she'd ha' ter turn Sandy ter sump'n e'se; en atter studyin' de
matter ober, en talkin' wid Sandy one ebenin', she made up her mine fer
ter fix up a goopher mixtry w'at would turn herse'f en Sandy ter foxes,
er sump'n, so dey could run away en go some'rs whar dey could be free
en lib lack w'ite folks.</p>
<p> "But dey ain' no tellin' w'at's gwine ter happen in dis worl'.
Tenie had got de night sot fer her en Sandy ter run away, w'en dat ve'y
day one er Mars Marrabo's sons rid up ter de big house in his buggy, en
say his wife wuz monst'us sick, en he want his mammy ter len' 'im a
'ooman fer ter nuss his wife.  Tenie's mistiss say sen Tenie; she wuz a
good nuss.  Young mars wuz in a tarrible hurry fer ter git back home.
Tenie wuz washin' at de big house dat day, en her mistiss say she should
go right 'long wid her young marster.  Tenie tried ter make some 'scuse
fer ter git away en hide tel night, w'en she would have eve'ything fix'
up fer her en Sandy; she say she wanter go ter her cabin fer ter git her
bonnet.  Her mistiss say it doan matter 'bout de bonnet; her
head-hankcher wuz good 'nuff.  Den Tenie say she wanter git her bes'
frock; her mistiss say no, she doan need no mo' frock, en w'en dat one
got dirty she could git a clean one whar she wuz gwine.  So Tenie had
ter git in de buggy en go 'long wid young Mars Dunkin ter his
plantation, w'ich wuz mo' d'n twenty mile away; en dey want no chance
er her seein' Sandy no mo' tel she come back home.  De po' gal felt
monst'us bad erbout de way things wuz gwine on, en she knowed Sandy
mus' be a wond'rin' why she didn' come en turn 'im back no
mo'.</p>
<p> "W'iles Tenie wuz away nussin' young Mars Dunkin's wife, Mars
Marrabo tuk a notion fer ter buil' 'im a noo kitchen; en bein' ez he had
lots er timber on his place, he begun ter look 'roun' fer a tree ter hab de
lumber sawed out'n.  En I dunno how it come to be so, but he happen
fer ter hit on de ve'y tree w'at Sandy wuz turnt inter.  Tenie wuz gone,
en dey wa'n't nobody ner nuffin' fer ter watch de tree.</p>
<p> "De two men w'at cut de tree down say dey nebber had sech a
time wid a tree befo': dey axes would glansh off, en didn' 'pear ter
make no progress thoo de wood; en of all de creakin', en shakin', en
wobblin' you eber see, dat tree done it w'en it commence' ter fall.  It
wuz de beatenis' thing!</p>
<p> "W'en dey got de tree all trim' up, dey chain it up ter a timber
waggin, en start fer de saw-mill.  But dey had a hard time gittin' de log
dere: fus' dey

<pb n="609"/>  got stuck in de mud w'en dey wuz gwine crosst de
swamp, en it wuz two er th'ee hours befo' dey could git out.  W'en dey
start' on ag'in, de chain kep' a-comin' loose, en dey had ter keep
a-stoppin' en a-stoppin' fer ter hitch de log up ag'in.  W'en dey
commence' ter climb de hill ter de saw-mill, de log broke loose, en roll
down de hill en in mongs' de trees, en hit tuk nigh 'bout half a day mo'
ter git it haul' up ter de saw-mill.</p>
<p> "De nex' mawnin' atter de day de tree wuz haul' ter de saw-mill,
Tenie come home.  W'en she got back ter her cabin, de fus' thing she
done wuz ter run down ter de woods en see how Sandy wuz gittin' on.
W'en she seed de stump standin' dere, wid de sap runnin' out'n it, en de
limbs layin' scattered roun', she nigh 'bout went out'n her mine.  She
run ter her cabin, en got her goopher mixtry, en den foller de track er de
timber waggin ter de saw-mill.  She knowed Sandy couldn' lib mo' d'n a
minute er so ef she turn' him back, fer he wuz all chop' up so he'd a
be'n bleedst ter die.  But she wanted ter turn 'im back long ernuff fer ter
'splain ter 'im dat she hadn' went off a-purpose, en lef' 'im ter be chop'
down en sawed up.  She didn' want Sandy ter die wid no hard feelin's
to'ds her.</p>
<p> "De han's at de saw-mill had des got de big log on de kerridge,
en wuz startin' up de saw, w'en dey seed a 'oman runnin up de hill, all
out er bref, cryin' en gwine on des lack she wuz plumb 'stracted.  It wuz
Tenie; she come right inter de mill, en th'owed herse'f on de log, right
in front er de saw, a-hollerin' en cryin' ter her Sandy ter fergib her, en
not ter think hard er her, fer it wa'n't no fault er hern.  Den Tenie
'membered de tree didn' hab no years, en she wuz gittin' ready fer ter
wuk her goopher mixtry so ez ter turn Sandy back, w'en de mill-hands
kotch holt er her en tied her arms wid a rope, en fasten' her to one er de
posts in de saw-mill; en den dey started de saw up ag'in, en cut de log
up inter bo'ds en scantlin's right befo' her eyes.  But it wuz mighty hard
wuk; fer of all de sweekin', en moanin', en groanin', dat log done it
w'iles de saw wuz a-cuttin' thoo it.  De saw wuz one er dese yer
ole-timey, up-en-down saws, en hit tuk longer dem days ter saw a log
'en it do now.  Dey greased de saw, but dat didn' stop de fuss; hit kep'
right on, tel finely dey got de log all sawed up.</p>
<p> "W'en de oberseah w'at run de saw-mill come fum brekfas', de
han's up en tell him 'bout de crazy 'ooman &mdash; ez dey s'posed she wuz--w'at had come runnin' in de saw-mill, a-hollerin' en gwine on, en tried
ter th'ow herse'f befo' de saw.  En de oberseah sent two er th'ee er de
han's fer ter take Tenie back ter her marster's plantation.</p>
<p> "Tenie 'peared ter be out'n her mine fer a long time, en her
marster ha' ter lock her up in de smoke-'ouse tel she got ober her spells.
Mars Marrabo wuz monst'us mad, en hit would a made yo' flesh crawl
fer ter hear him cuss, caze he say de spekilater w'at he got Tenie fum
had fooled 'im by wukkin' a crazy 'oman off on him.  Wiles Tenie wuz
lock up in de smoke-'ouse, Mars Marrabo tuk'n' haul de lumber fum de
saw-mill, en put up his noo kitchen.</p>
<p> "W'en Tenie got quiet' down, so she could be 'lowed ter go
'roun' de plantation, she up'n tole her marster all erbout Sandy en de
pine-tree; en w'en Mars Marrabo hearn it, he 'lowed she wuz de wuss
'stracted nigger he eber hearn of.  He didn' know w'at ter do wid Tenie:
fus' he thought he'd put her in de po'-house; but finely, seein' ez she
didn' do no harm ter nobody ner nuffin', but des went roun' moanin', en
groanin', en shakin' her head, he 'cluded ter let her stay on de plantation
en nuss de little nigger chilluns w'en dey mammies wuz ter wuk in de
cotton-fiel'.</p>
<p> "De noo kitchen Mars Marrabo buil' wuzn' much use, fer it hadn'
be'n put

<pb n="610"/>  up long befo' de niggers 'mence' ter notice quare
things erbout it.  Dey could hear sump'n moanin' en groanin' 'bout de
kitchen in de night-time, en w'en de win' would blow dey could hear
sump'n a-hollerin' en sweekin' lack hit wuz in great pain en sufferin'.
En hit got so atter a w'ile dat hit wuz all Mars Marrabo's wife could do
ter git a 'ooman ter stay in de kitchen in de daytime long ernuff ter do
de cookin'; en dey wa'n't naer nigger on de plantation w'at wouldn'
rudder take forty dan ter go 'bout dat kitchen atter dark, &mdash; dat is, 'cep'n
Tenie; she didn' pear ter mine de ha'nts.  She useter slip 'roun' at night,
en set on de kitchen steps, en lean up agin de do'-jamb, en run on ter
herse'f wid some kine er foolishness w'at nobody couldn' make out; fer
Mars Marrabo had th'eaten' ter sen' her off'n de plantation ef she say
anything ter any er de yuther niggers 'bout de pine-tree.  But somehow
er nudder de niggers foun' out all 'bout it, en dey knowed de kitchen
wuz ha'anted by Sandy's sperrit.  En bimeby hit got so Mars Marrabo's
wife herse'f wuz skeered ter go out in de yard atter dark.</p>
<p> "W'en it come ter dat, Mars Marrabo tuk 'n' to' de kitchen down,
en use' de lumber fer ter buil' dat ole school-'ouse w'at youer talkin'
'bout pullin' down.  De school-'ouse wuzn' use' 'cep'n' in de daytime,
en on dark nights folks gwine 'long de road would hear quare soun's en
see quare things.  Po' ole Tenie useter go down dere at night, en wander
'roun' de school-'ouse; en de niggers all 'lowed she went fer ter talk wid
Sandy's sperrit.  En one winter mawnin', w'en one er de boys went ter
school early fer ter start de fire, w'at should he fine but po' ole Tenie,
layin' on de flo', stiff, en cole, en dead.  Dere didn' 'pear ter be nuffin'
pertickler de matter wid her, &mdash; she had des grieve' herse'f ter def fer
her Sandy.  Mars Marrabo didn' shed no tears.  He thought Tenie wuz
crazy, en dey wa'n't no tellin' w'at she mout do nex'; en dey ain' much
room in dis worl' fer crazy w'ite folks, let 'lone a crazy nigger.</p>
<p> "Hit wa'n't long atter dat befo' Mars Marrabo sole a piece er his
track er lan' ter Mars Dugal' McAdoo, &mdash; <hi rend="italic">my</hi> ole marster, &mdash;
en dat's how de ole school-house happen to be on yo' place.  W'en de
wah broke out, de school stop', en de ole school-'ouse be'n stannin'
empty ever sence, &mdash; dat is, 'cep'n' fer de ha'nts.  En folks sez dat de
ole school-'ouse, er any yuther house w'at got any er dat lumber in it
w'at wuz sawed out'n de tree w'at Sandy wuz turnt inter, is gwine ter be
ha'nted tel de las' piece er plank is rotted en crumble' inter dus'."</p>

<p> Annie had listened to this gruesome narrative with strained
attention.</p>
<p> "What a system it was," she exclaimed, when Julius had finished,
"under which such things were possible!"</p>
<p> "What things?" I asked, in amazement.  "Are you seriously
considering the possibility of a man's being turned into a tree?"</p>
<p> "Oh, no," she replied quickly, "not that;" and then she added
absently, and with a dim look in her fine eyes, "Poor Tenie!"</p>
<p> We ordered the lumber, and returned home.  That night, after we
had gone to bed, and my wife had to all appearances been sound asleep
for half an hour, she startled me out of an incipient doze by exclaiming
suddenly, &mdash; </p>
<p> "John, I don't believe I want my new kitchen built out of the
lumber in that old school-house."</p>
<p> "You wouldn't for a moment allow yourself," I replied, with
some asperity, "to be influenced by that absurdly impossible yarn which
Julius was spinning to-day?"</p>
<p> "I know the story is absurd," she replied dreamily, "and I am not
so silly as to believe it.  But I don't think I should ever be able to take
any pleasure in that kitchen if it were built out of that lumber.  Besides,
I think the

<pb n="611"/>  kitchen would look better and last longer if the lumber
were all new."</p>
<p> Of course she had her way.  I bought the new lumber, though not
without grumbling.  A week or two later I was called away from home
on business.  On my return, after an absence of several days, my wife
remarked to me, &mdash; </p>
<p> "John, there has been a split in the Sandy Run Colored Baptist
Church, on the temperance question.  About half the members have
come out from the main body, and set up for themselves.  Uncle Julius
is one of the seceders, and he came to me yesterday and asked if they
might not hold their meetings in the old school-house for the
present."</p>
<p> "I hope you didn't let the old rascal have it," I returned, with
some warmth.  I had just received a bill for the new lumber I had
bought.</p>
<p> "Well," she replied, "I could not refuse him the use of the house
for so good a purpose."</p>
<p> "And I'll venture to say," I continued, "that you subscribed
something toward the support of the new church?"</p>
<p> She did not attempt to deny it.</p>
<p> "What are they going to do about the ghost?" I asked, somewhat
curious to know how Julius would get around this obstacle.</p>
<p> "Oh," replied Annie, "Uncle Julius says that ghosts never disturb
religious worship, but that if Sandy's spirit <hi rend="italic">should</hi> happen to
stray into meeting by mistake, no doubt the preaching would do it
good."</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Charles W. Chesnutt.</hi></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
