<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="ColIndi"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="ColIndi">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Notes Among the Indians</title>
<title type="sort">notes among the indians</title>
<author>Colyer, Vincent</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">59</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">ColIndi</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475826</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Notes Among the Indians</title>
<title type="sort">notes among the indians</title>
<author>Vincent Colyer</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>G. P. Putnam's Sons</publisher>
<pubPlace>New Rochelle, N.Y.</pubPlace>
<date value="1869-09">September -October 1869</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>21, 22</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Colyer, Vincent.  "Notes Among the Indians&mdash;I."
<hi rend="italic">Putnam's</hi> 21 (n.s. 4) (Sept. 1869): 367-374. AND
Colyer, Vincent.  "Notes Among the Indians&mdash;II."  <hi rend="italic">Putnam's</hi>
     22 (n.s. 4) (Oct. 1869): 474-480.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1869-09">September and October 1869</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-12">December 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header; Tagged with TEI.2-compatible SGML; Parsed against "teilite"
dtd.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">



<front id="d2">
<titlePage id="d3"><pb n="367"/>
<docTitle>
<titlePart type="main">SHALL THE RED-MEN BE EXTERMINATED?</titlePart>
<titlePart type="sub">
NOTES OF TOURS AMONG THE WILDER TRIBES OF ARIZONA, NEW MEXICO, MONTANA,
COLORADO, AND THE INDIAN TERRITORY.
</titlePart></docTitle>
</titlePage>

<div1 type="note" id="d4">

<p>[The author of these notes, Mr. VINCENT COLYER, was sent out in
February last, with credentials from President Grant and from the
U. S. Indian Commission, to learn from actual observation the
condition and the needs of the "savages" of our Western domain.
His journies are to be extended to other territories, including
Alaska.  We do not propose to give his official and routine
reports.  Our readers will be interested rather in the personal
incidents and adventures, which we print from Mr. Colyer's original
and unrevised note-book and letters written on the spots described,
believing that these will furnish some new light on the immediate
problem, "Shall the Aborigines be Exterminated?"</p>
<signed>&mdash;<hi rend="italic">Editor</hi>.]</signed>
</div1>
</front>
<body id="d5">
<div1 type="part" n="1" id="d6">

<div2 type="introduction" id="d7">


<p> Two years ago we received from Hon. E. D. Morgan, than U. S.
Senator from New York, a copy of the Report on the Condition of our
Indian Tribes, made by the joint committee of Congress at its
session in 1867.
</p><p> This Report could not but excite deep feeling in regard to the
way the Indians had been neglected, and shame and indignation at
the outrageous wrongs which had been perpetrated upon them by our
people.
</p><p> Comparing opinions with others, we met with so prompt and
sympathetic a response, that a public meeting was called, held, and
a committee of gentlemen of well-known philanthropic and Christian
character appointed to organize a systematic effort to remedy the
evil after the manner of the United States Christian Commission of
late war-memory.
</p><p> It was called the U. S. Indian Commission, and one of its
first acts was to memorialize Congress to devote more attention to
Indian affairs, and appoint a more watchful guardianship over the
monies appropriated for the tribes.
</p><p> In this memorial the name of Lieutenant-General Sherman was
favorably commended in connection with Indian affairs, and it was,
we think, responded to by the U. S. Senate's inserting a clause in
the Indian Appropriation Bill of 1868, placing half a million of
dollars to be expended under General Sherman's supervision.
</p><p> The selection of General Sherman of Generals Hazen and Harney,
and giving them control of the two great Indian reservations in the
southern Indian territory, and Northern Dakota, with funds ample
for the commencement of the great work of restraining and
civilizing the wild tribes of the plains, followed soon after.
</p><p> Meanwhile, circular letters containing condensed selections of
the more startling facts contained in the Report as first referred
to, and an address to the people, prepared by our President, were
published in nearly all the great newspapers of the day, and widely
circulated.
</p><p> Early in January, 1868, the Commission received a letter from
Major-General Hazen, dated in November past, asking that one of
their number be sent to examine personally, and report upon the
condition of the tribes under his care at Camp Wichita, I. T.
</p><p> The Commission promptly responded to this, and I was selected
for the duty.
</p><p> Obtaining from the gentlemen of the Commission the necessary
funds to defray expenses, with the understanding that I was to
receive no pay for my services, and securing from General Grant an
order providing me an escort and transportation whenever necessary,
in the middle of February I started on my journey.
</p><p> A heavy snow-storm which met me at Fort Leavenworth, a
prolonged interview
<pb n="368"/> with Major (now General) Forsyth, then
in the surgeon's care at that post, suffering acutely from wounds
which he had received in his encounter with Indians, and some very
loud curses which greeted me as an "Indian Peace Commissioner" by
a Kansas official, warned me that I was not on a "pleasure
excursion."
</p><p> At Fort Leavenworth, Colonel Michael Sheridan, the General's
brother, informed me of the condition of the Osage Indians.
Attention to this tribe had been called by the statements widely
published in the papers at the time of the purchase of the immense
tract of land, eight million acres, belonging to them in southern
Kansas, by a company of speculators.
</p><p> Information from a most trustworthy, though private source,
had informed us, on leaving New York, of the unfair means brought
to bear upon the Indians to effect this purchase.
</p><p> Our telegram, that the Osages had eaten their beef raw&mdash;
digestive organs included&mdash;and that they would henceforth forever
be paupers on the Government, being widely published by the
Associated Press, attracted general attention.
</p><p> The Home Committee promptly followed up this stirring notice
by a "remonstrance to Congress" against this iniquitous treaty.
</p><p> I do not know whether we have effectually killed or only
scotched the snake, but a wail went up from the land-jobbers in
Kansas immediately after, that their "Osage land bill was in a
discouraging condition;" so loud, that I trust it is killed.  On my
return home through Lawrence, Kansas, handbills were posted by the
U. S. Land Agent, offering Osage lands to <hi rend="italic">actual settlers</hi> in
"quarter sections," one hundred and sixty acres, at government
prices.
</p><p> If we have thus aided in securing to our industrious poor a
chance to get a home at a fair price, and have the money go into
the U. S. Treasury instead of the pockets of private speculators,
we have not labored in vain.
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="statement" id="d8">
<head>                    GENERAL STATEMENT.</head>

<p> I first visited the "half-civilized" tribes along the
southeastern border of Kansas and Western Arkansas.  The
Kaskaskias, Neoshos, and other of the confederated bands, and the
Cherokees, Creeks, Seminoles, Chickasaws, and others.  I wanted to
learn what means had been employed to civilize them, and to see the
result.  I found them as decent and cleanly in their personal
appearance and habitations, their cabins and out-houses as well
constructed, and their fences, farming-tools, and stock as well
cared for as by the majority of the white people, their immediate
neighbors.
</p><p> They owe their civilization to the missionaries who have most
faithfully and efficiently worked among them for the past half
century, supported by the liberal contributions of the Christian
people of the Eastern, Middle, and Southern States.  With the
exception of the Osage Mission, which is Roman Catholic, they are
all Protestant missions.  Presbyterians, Moravian, Baptist,
Methodist, Episcopalian, have all united in the good work.
</p><p> The Cherokees are the most advanced in education of all the
tribes in the United States, though in orderly living, I think, the
Pueblos of New Mexico surpass them.  Many of the gentlemen at the
head of the nation are half-breeds; men of culture and refinement,
with whom it is a delight to associate.
</p><p> The <hi rend="italic">"Reservation"</hi> system has in the main proved a
success with them, though, like all theories, it may be pushed too
far.
</p><p> To collect a tribe together out of its straggling, roving,
savage life, and bring it into a condition where it can be handled,
where it can be protected from its more powerful neighbors, and
also protect its weaker neighbors from the bad men belonging to it,
and to afford teachers and civilizers of every kind an opportunity
to work, the Reservation system must be adopted.  But when a tribe
has advanced as far as the Cherokees have in civilization, a larger
and broader policy must be introduced.  It <pb n="369"/>  is like the
Chinese or Japanese building a wall around themselves, adopting the
teaching of Confucius, not of our Saviour.
</p><p> The war, in its dreadful ravages among them, has done great
good to the Cherokees.  It has killed the old factions and broken
down the middle wall of partition between the half-breeds and full-bloods.  All of them now see that they must be united, or the
Cherokee nation goes to the wall.  The half-breeds are looking more
affectionately upon the full-bloods, as the proper field of labor
for their most devoted efforts; and both factions are now so poor
that there is nothing for the one to be envious of in the other.
Even the old animosities of "North and South" have to be abandoned,
and a common adversity has made them common friends.
</p><p> They have a glorious heritage: 1.  In a good name, earned by
an unselfish, heroic life in the past.
</p><p> 2.  In the advantage which that reputation gives them in
placing them at the head, or nearly so, of all the Indian tribes of
America; and
</p><p> 3.  In natural resources of soil, climate, and geographical
position.
</p><p> Their country is superb.  Agreeably diversified with hill and
plain, well wooded and watered; coal, iron, and fertilizers of the
soil near at hand; mild and temperate climate; sheltered from the
colder north winds by their hills, and refreshed against the hot
air of the south by the many springs and streams which water the
valleys; and located on a line where very soon many railroads must
meet, their situation is most hopeful.
</p><p> I next visited the Seminoles.  What American of forty years,
does not remember the old cry about the Seminoles of Florida&mdash;
twenty years ago or less.  They were called "rattlesnakes&mdash;vile
reptiles only fit for manure, and to be shot whenever seen."  We
were told, and our people believed, that nothing could ever be done
with the Seminoles, and yet, there I found them living quietly in
their neat log-cabins, working their farms, and sending their
children to school, with as much earnestness as their white
neighbors.  About fifteen years ago they were removed from Florida,
and placed where we found them in this country.
</p><p> Rev. Mr. Ramsey, the missionary from the Presbyterian Board,
has charge of one of their schools.  It was in vacation, April,
when I was there, and he was at work on his farm.  The Seminoles
gather around him as he ploughs, and watch his straight furrows
with the intensest interest.  His Virginia rail-fence, run by line,
straight as an arrow, attracts their intelligent attention and
imitation.
</p><p> I visited the cabin of "Long John," their chief.  He is a
splendid specimen of his race: tall, well-formed; cheerful and open
face.  In the late war he was a sergeant in the Indian regiment on
the Union side.  On the walls of his bedroom he has a portrait of
Abraham Lincoln, which he regards with peculiar affection.  He
called my attention to it with a most expressive wave of his hand
from his heart towards it in reverence and manly esteem.  He has an
ingenious contrivance for raising up the box from the running gear
of his wagon, so that he can substitute the frame of a hay rack in
its place.  It is all under cover, sheltered from rain.  He called
my attention to it with evident pride and delight.  Mr. Ramsey told
me that he was an earnest and consistent member of his church.  And
yet he is one of those who fifteen years ago were "rattlesnakes,
and to be shot on sight, like other reptiles."
</p><p> The mission among the Creek Indians, I had not time to visit.
It is said to be the most successful of any in the United States.
The Rev. Mr. Robinson has charge of it, assisted by Mr. Worcester,
son of the distinguished missionary, Dr. Worcester, who labored so
heroically for forty years among the Cherokees.  A daughter of Dr.
Worcester also had a school for the colored children at the Creek
agency which has done much good.
</p><p> The colored people have equal rights in all things with the
Indians.  In this <pb n="370"/>  our red brethren set us a good example;
they not only admit them to citizenship among them, but generously
share with them all its privileges of free admission to schools,
equal use of school funds, and rights to the land and labor.
</p><p> Driven out of Texas in large numbers under the influence of
the old prejudice against their race, the blacks are fortunate in
being welcomed so warmly by the Creeks.
</p><p> I will now continue the story from my letters. </p>
</div2>

<div2 type="letter" id="d9">
<head><address><addrLine>HEADQUARTERS, U.S.A., MEDICINE BLUFF, WACHITA MOUNTAINS.

Indian Territory, <date value="1869-03-29">March 29, 1869.</date>
</addrLine></address>
</head>
<salute>DEAR C&mdash;:</salute>
<p>&mdash;  At last I have arrived at the extreme southern
end of my journey, just one month and nineteen days, or six weeks,
from the day I left New York.
</p><p> Major-General Hazen left Fort Arbuckle with me on Friday noon,
and camped on the edge of a green field and small stream of water,
fifteen miles west, this side of Arbuckle, that evening.  As I had
a four-mule wagon, loaded with our rations and forage for twenty
days, remaining, and three barrels of garden-seeds, hoes, &amp;c., for
the Indians, to carry, which moved slowly, we parted company the
next morning, and the General came on a half day before me.
</p><p> The route for this last trip of seventy-two miles was the most
interesting of any I have yet travelled over.  The wild character
of the scenery, so barren and in large part so entirely
uninhabited; the quantity of game, wild ducks, geese, plover,
quail, prairie chickens, swans, wolves, antelope, deer, &amp;c.,
constantly in sight, made it particularly exciting.
</p><p> The wolves were very bold, frequently being within easy musket
range, and surrounding our lonely camp at night with their watchful
cries.  The deer and antelope at times were equally near, and the
flocks of birds spoken of were in sight every hour.
</p><p> We had the full moon, and clear beautiful weather; one slight
thunder-shower of half an hour being the only exception.
</p><p> The grass is already beginning to appear, green and
refreshing, and the mules are thriving on it finely.
</p><p> General Hazen has prepared a tent, with fireplace, bed, &amp;c.,
for my comfort, and I am now writing this under its hospitable
roof.  Major-General Grierson, of famous history in the raiding
line during the last war, commands the military of this department,
General Hazen's duties being really only those of Indian agent,
&amp;c., and he received me, as did all the other army officers, most
cordially.
</p><p> There are large numbers of Indians here encamped about our
tent, and they are some of the most uncivilized and war-like of all
our tribes.
</p><p> The women and men are some of them half-naked, and nearly all
are in their native costume of blanket and buffalo robe, with bow
and arrow, or carbine with revolvers.  They are nearly all mounted
on ponies, and seem awkward when dismounted.  They are the finest
riders in the world, and when seen moving about on their ponies and
horses with their bright-colored blankets, are the most picturesque
people imaginable.  The children are especially interesting, bright
and intelligent looking.  While I was in the General's tent at
dinner, three of the warlike tribe of Cheyennes, the first that
have arrived, presented themselves at the General's tent door.  He
was delighted to see them.  They are the first of a band of six
hundred that are coming in a day or two.  They were each over six
feet high, wiry, and tough in their build, and quite dignified and
grave in their manners.
</p><p> How I wish a Horace Vernet were here to fix upon canvas the
superb pictures of Indian life around us, equalling his famous
"Abd'el Kadir."
</p><p> I am to go with General Hazen to-morrow to put the first
plough and plant the first seed in the new ground of this
Reservation.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="letter" id="d10">
<head><address><addrLine>MEDICINE BLUFF CREEK,
Southern Indian Territory, <date value="1869-04-09">April 9, 1869. </date></addrLine>
</address>
</head>
<p> To-day I had an interview with Little Raven, Chief of the
Arapahoes, in the <pb n="371"/>  tent of Major-General Grierson, and got
a distinct statement from him as to the entire ignorance of himself
and his people, and also of the Cheyennes, about the precise
location of the Reservation set off for them by U. S. Peace
Commissioners in 1867.  It was because the Cheyennes under Black
Kettle and the Arapahoes under Little Raven were not on the
Reservation, that they, with their tribes, were held guilty, and
this was <hi rend="italic">one</hi> of the reasons why they were attacked by
General Custer at the battle of the Washita last Fall.  You may
remember that Colonel Wynkoop stated that he thought they were on
their Reservation at the time they were attacked.  You see now how
easily these people are made to sign treaties, of the character of
which they are not familiar, and are afterwards so severely dealt
with for not understanding.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="statement" id="d11">
<head>STATEMENT. </head>

<p> Little Raven, Chief of the Arapahoes, being questioned as to
his knowledge of the location of the Reservation allotted to his
people and the Cheyennes, by the Medicine Lodge Treaty in 1867,
declared, in our presence, that at the time he signed the Treaty,
he fully supposed the land on the Upper Arkansas, between Bent's
Fort and the Rocky Mountains, was the Reservation, being the same
as previously set apart to them in the treaty of 1865; and he
believes that the Cheyennes were also of that opinion.  Nor had he
any doubt about it, until he met General Sheridan at Medicine Bluff
Headquarters, 15th of February, 1869, and until to-day he did not
know precisely where the new Reservation was located.
</p><p> Little Raven says he supposes that this misunderstanding arose
from the hasty way in which the treaty was made and read to them,
and by mistaken interpretation.
</p><signed> (Signed)<name>       LITTLE RAVEN,
           Chief of the Arapahoes, X, his mark.
               </name><name> B. H. GRIERSON,
           Col. and Brevt. Major-General, U.S.A.
               </name><name> VINCENT COLYER.
               </name><name> H. P. JONES, U.S. Interpreter.
               </name><name> HENRY E. ALVORD,
                Captain 10th U.S. Cavalry. </name>
</signed>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d12">

<p> After Little Raven had got through, a party of twenty-six
Southern Cheyennes, with their head chiefs Little Robe, Minnimic,
and others, came up, and had a little talk.  They are a fine-looking body of men, and when on horseback beat any thing in the
way of cavalry I have ever seen.
</p><p> They tell their version of General Custer's meeting with them.

</p></div2>

<div2 type="statement" id="d13">
<head>STATEMENT. </head>

<p> "At an interview had with Little Robe, Minnimic, or Bald
Eagle, Red Moon, Grey Eyes, and other chiefs of the Cheyennes, held
in the Head-Quarters tent of Major-General Grierson, they gave the
following account of their interview with General Custer on the 8th
or 9th of March, 1869.
</p><p> "The Indians were on their way to Camp Supply, and this
interview with him turned them back and delayed their progress
there.
</p><p> "The first notice they, the Cheyennes, had of the approach of
Major-General Custer and his regiment, was from a Cheyenne woman
who had been captured by General Custer in the fight against Black
Kettle, on the Washita.  She had been turned loose, or ran away,
from General Custer some days before.  The chiefs went out to see,
and met General Custer coming in with two men.  He went into
Medicine Arrow's tent, and shook hands, and a young man came in and
told them that there were a great many troops coming on the war-path, which frightened the women, and they immediately began to
saddle up their ponies; but the chiefs went out and quieted them
down.
</p><p> "Thirty of the chiefs and warriors then went over to visit
General Custer and his camp.  He surrounded them with his soldiers,
and told them he was going to keep them.  They immediately drew
their revolvers, and said that if they were to die, they would die
in trying to escape; and they made a rush, and all but three broke
through the guard.  They were desperate and determined and brave
about it, so they were allowed to go unguarded.  General <pb n="372"/>
Custer told the chiefs to go and bring in two white women, who were
in their camp, or he would hang the three young men.  They brought
him the two white women, and then expected that he would release
the three young men; but he would not do so.  Sometimes he would
talk good and sometimes bad to them; they could not understand him.
He staid near them only a little while, and started for Camp
Supply.  He told them he wanted them to follow him on to Camp
Supply; but he talked so strangely to them, they would not trust
him.  This over, seventy lodges started for this post.  They left
the others, about one hundred and twenty lodges, on the headwaters
of the Washita; but the interview with Custer was on the North
Fork, or a small branch of the Red River.  They say that there were
thirteen men, sixteen women, and nine children killed at the
Washita fight.  Eagle Head, or Minnimic, then said that he wanted
to speak.  He first shook hands with us, and then said that he
wanted to speak good only.  That three of their men came down to
see us, and returning, reported that we had treated them kindly,
and wished to see the others, and that they had now come to see us.
He said that they were hungry, and wanted some food for themselves
and for their people.  That they were willing to go up to their
Reservation with Little Raven and the Arapahoes, if he and they
were willing.  Little Raven being present, was asked, and he said
he was willing, and would be glad to have them go with them, if the
Cheyennes were willing.
</p><p> "So it was agreed upon that they should go up to the
Reservation together.
</p>
<signed>(Signed)  <name>HENRY BRADLEY,
                        Interpreter.
           </name><name>VINCENT COLYER,
                        Witness.
</name>
</signed>
</div2>
<div2 type="letter" id="d14">

<p> To-day General Hazen, Colonel Boone,<ref target="Note1">*</ref> and myself visited the
farms of the Agency, set the ploughs in motion, and selected the
location for the Mission School.  The buildings and farms will
occupy a beautiful island plateau of nearly two hundred acres of
rich bottom land, surrounded by Cache Creek, and one of its
branches, fringed with tall trees.

</p>
<note id="Note1"><seg type="note-symbol"> *</seg> <p>U. S. Indian Agent.  He is a grandson of the famous Colonel
Boone of Kentucky, and said to be an excellent man.</p></note>

</div2>
<div2 type="letter" id="d15">
<head><address><addrLine>HEADQUARTERS, MEDICINE CREEK,
Southern Indian Territory, <date value="1869-04-09">April 9, 1869. </date></addrLine>
</address>
</head>
<p> Yesterday I visited the Agency of the Affiliated Bands of
Indians at the Wacheta Agency.  They number about seven hundred
souls, and are the remnants of what were once quite important and
intelligent tribes&mdash;the Wichetas, Kerchees, Caddoes, Wacoes, and
others.  Their Agency is located about twenty-two miles north of
this post, on the Washita river, in the midst of a beautiful and
fertile plain, named the Eureka Valley.  All the way up we found
the prairies dotted with daisies of blue, purple, pink, and white
colors, and other small flowers, some of which were quite fragrant.
The valley was covered with new grass, long enough to wave in the
wind.  Our mules, which have suffered for the want of hay, enjoyed
themselves highly in the evening, munching it, omitting their usual
practice of taking a roll immediately after unharnessing.  The
first evening was spent in sketching the ranch and some of the
squaws and papooses, and the night was passed in General Hazen's
ambulance; our party consisted of the General; Colonel Boone,
Indian Agent; a gentleman invited; Mr. Jones, interpreter, and
Captain Gray, a witness required by law to vouch for the
correctness of the issue of goods to the Indians.
</p><p> We were up in time to see a beautiful sunrise across the
prairie, and after an hour or two spent in sketching the locality,
we saw the Indians arriving on horseback.
</p><p> They came in groups of two or three, and as most of them were
attired in gay colors and shining ornaments, and all are superb
riders, they made a most picturesque scene.
</p><p> I kept my pencil busily at work all the morning, interrupted
occasionally by the curiosity of the squaws and papooses looking
over my shoulder.  They manifested great interest in what I was
doing, and with mingled expressions of wonder and delight called
each other's attention to it.  On another occasion, with the
Apaches, I found myself very unpopular while sketching, the art
being considered by them as possessing magic, and they declared it
to be "bad medicine;" a name they give to all offensive or
injurious things.  They sent for their medicine man, or doctor,
whose skill consists chiefly in performing certain incantations and
magic arts, whereby the evil spirit and disease is driven away.
When this medicine man, a most ill-favored Indian, arrived, he
looked over my shoulder, being watched intently by the other
Indians, and declared that it was "bad medicine," spit at it, and
soon they all looked daggers at me.  Of course I discontinued the
work, and ever since then I have been particular, either to make my
sketches when they were not observing me, or first explain through
the interpreter what I wished to do.  When it is thus explained to
them, I never have any trouble.
</p><p> But to return to my story.  When the tribes had all assembled,
and the goods had been parcelled out to them in five separate lots,
one for each tribe, the chiefs assembled together, and General
Hazen sent for me.  The interpreter, Mr. Philip McCusky, informed
us that the chiefs wished to speak to us, and invited General Hazen
to commence the talk.
</p></div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d16">
<head>
INTERVIEW WITH THE WICHITAS, WACOES, CADDOES, KECHAS, AND OTHERS,
<date value="1869-04-07">APRIL 7, 1869. </date>
</head>
<p> General Hazen commenced the talk by informing the assembled
chiefs that he was happy to meet them, that the goods which would
be distributed among them were not a part of their regular annuity,
but were those which had been sent on for the Comanches and Kiowas
last year, who burned their store and grain house and destroyed
their corn.  That he had given them these goods because they were
peaceful and industrious.  That he had bought ploughs and garden
seeds for them, and employed farmers to instruct them, and would
continue to watch over their interests.
</p><p> Colonel Boone, the Indian Agent, then spoke to them in the
same friendly way, and assured them that the Government would do
all it could for them.
</p><p> General Hazen then introduced me to them, telling them that I
had been sent out here by a society of good men of much power and
influence, and that the new Father at Washington had told him and
all other Generals and soldiers, to see that I was protected and
allowed to see the Indians.  They said, "Good, good," to each
other, and waited to hear from me.
</p><p> I told them "they had many warm and strong friends where I
came from.  That there were good and bad white men, as well as good
and bad Indians.  That now the good white men had united together,
to take care of the good Indians, and that, relying on the Great
Spirit, they would help them.  That when the Indians were at peace,
prosperous, and happy, we rejoiced and were glad; but when they
were at war, unfortunate, or in distress, we were unhappy and much
troubled.  I told them that our new Father at Washington was their
friend, and repeated the words of General Grant's 'inaugural' to
them.  That we wished to establish schools among them, and asked
them if they would send their children to them."
</p><p> The Chief of the Wacoes, Good Buffalo, then replied, "That he
was glad to see our faces.  That this was a happy day for himself
and for his people.  That the Indian was like the white man.  The
Great Spirit had made them both, only He had made the white man
wiser than the Indian.  That He had put him on a broader road, and
told him to take care of the Indian, and show him the way.  That so
far they had not found the road.  That they were worse off than
when they started, but that to-day they hoped to find the road.
Long time ago his father took <pb n="373"/>  the white man by the hand,
and now they wished to do the same.  This land they saw all around
them for many miles belonged to their fathers.  That the bones of
his people lie where the Post is being built.  That he hoped his
people would never be made to leave this country.  That they had
been a long time looking for a school-house and a teacher, and were
glad to now hear that they were to have them."
</p><p> Wa-tu-pi, Chief of the Caddoes, then said that he wished to
speak.  That I "had come a long way to see them, and he was glad.
That he was much pleased to see so many chiefs present to hear this
talk.  The Caddoes, when they first knew the white people, had been
helped by them; but that they were now forgotten.  His people, like
the Wichitas, knew how to plough and plant corn.  He hoped I would
look and see how poor his people were."
</p><p> I told him I saw it, and it made me very unhappy.
</p><p> The Caddoes once owned and occupied the country which now
forms the State of Louisiana.  At present they have no land
assigned to them, and are literally homeless wanderers.  What a
pity they have not able advocates like Mrs. General Gaines!
</p><p> The chiefs noticed that I was taking notes of their reply, and
asked the interpreter "what I was doing that for."  He told them it
was to show my friends at home and the Great Father at Washington.
They said, "Wano, Wano," "Good, Good."  They said they hoped I
would put it all down.
</p><p> I was deeply impressed with the whole scene, and left with a
much higher opinion of the Indian race than I have had heretofore.
</p><p> After the talk the squaws took the goods and distributed a
share to each squaw and papoose present.  The women and children
sat around in a circle, and the squaws with the goods occupied the
centre.
</p><p> About three o'clock we left the Agency grounds, and rode over
to the Wichita village, about three miles northeast, up the Eureka
Valley. </p>
</div2>
<trailer>[TO BE CONTINUED.]</trailer>
</div1>





<div1 type="part" n="2" id="d17">
	<pb n="474"/>
<head>NOTES AMONG THE INDIANS.<lb/>
	II.<lb/>
THE WITCHITA VILLAGE.</head>

<div2 type="section" id="d18">
<head><address><addrLine>MEDICINE BLUFF, WITCHITA MOUNTAINS,
April 4, <hi rend="italic">via</hi> KANSAS CITY, April 20. </addrLine>
</address></head>
<p> THE Indian chiefs Roman Nose, Little Big-Mouth, Yellow Bear,
and Old Storm, with six hundred of their people, the Arapahoes,
came in yesterday and reported themselves as ready to go on their
new reservation, north of the Cameron River.  At the suggestion of
General Hazen, I had a talk with their principal chief, Little
Robe.  I told him what the President had said in his message, that
he would favor all efforts to civilize, Christianize, and admit to
the rights of citizenship the Indians, and asked him if he thought
that his people would care to learn to read and write, plough the
field, plant corn, and live in cabins.  He said that his people
wished to follow the face of the white man, and learn his ways;
that they would welcome teachers on their new reservation, and
treat them as good brothers.  General Grierson, in command here,
built new bridges over the streams, located his new post, and is
nipping in the bud all licentiousness in the camp.
</p><p> "What a strange spectacle greets the <pb n="475"/>  eye&mdash;a level
plain, dotted with <hi rend="italic">'huge hay-stacks!'"</hi> exclaimed friend
R&mdash;; "but how symmetrical and beautiful; thirty to forty feet
high, and as regularly built as though they were laid out by rules
of geometry!"
</p><p> As we near them we soon discover that our hay-stacks are the
houses of the Witchitas, built of straw, thatched layer upon layer,
with stout bindings of willow-saplings, tied together with buffalo-hide or stripped hickory.  Out of the top the smoke issues, and
around an oval opening or door at the side, a crowd of naked men
and women hover in questioning solicitude at our coming.
</p><p> On one side of the door a porch is erected, running along some
twenty feet or more, with coverings of small branches for shade,
and a raised floor of hickory poles, two feet from the ground, for
a summer afternoon's siesta.
</p><p> The men are good-natured, and the women cheerful, though more
naked than any we have seen.  They invite you with much politeness
to walk in; and, accepting their hospitality, you find yourself in
a commodious, clean, and comfortable dwelling.
</p><p> In the centre is the fire, small and economical as the Indian
always makes it.  Around the sides the beds are fitted up on bunks
raised three feet from the floor, built of split-boards, tied
together with cords made from buffalo-hide.  The floor is hard-packed earth, clean as it can be.  The builders have wisely and
unconsciously made the best of their circumstances.  The grass,
willow-saplings, buffalo-hide, &amp;c., are all found close at hand;
and out of these, which would have been to us impracticable
materials for house-building, the Witchitas have constructed most
convenient habitations.
</p><p> Watermelon patches with neat fences are near at hand.  The
fields show marks of earnest cultivation, and the people, though
evidently very, very poor, are yet glad-hearted and hopeful.
</p><p> Driving back home at a rapid pace, our teams started from the
willow brakes great flocks of plover.  The General let fly his
shot, and we had eight as fat and delicious birds for supper as any
one click of the trigger usually brings.
</p><p> As the twilight deepened, we left the straw-houses, cool
verandas, naked men and women, gardens, and plover of the poor
Witchitas, and it was quite dark when we returned to the Agency
building.  An Indian lament over the death of a warrior arrested
our attention, and mingling with the plaintive cry of the "Whip-poor-will," in the ghostly branches of the cotton-wood near by,
lent a melancholy tone to the close of the day.
</p><p> The Indian women were in a smoke-blackened tepe across the
Washita.  The flickering light of their nearly extinct fire
revealed their shadowy forms kneeling prostrate on the earth,
cutting themselves with knives, and pulling their hair.  They
sobbed and cried with a grief piteous to hear.
</p><p> Turning from this painful picture, we went into the Ranch.  It
was in this Ranch that General Hazen informed me he held his final
talk with Black Kettle, the chief of the Cheyennes, when he came to
sue for peace, and search for his Reservation.  As the General had
kept notes of the interview, and the name of this chief already
occupies a place in our Indian history quite as notable as that of
Black Hawk, or Red Jacket, I requested copies of them from him, and
with some other papers, necessary to a clear understanding of the
facts, submit them.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" id="d19">
<head>MOKE-TAY-A-TO, OR BLACK KETTLE&mdash;WHAT CAUSED HIS DEATH?

<hi rend="italic">Extract from Memorandum Record of Indian Affairs at Old Fort
Cobb, Indian Territory, November 1868.</hi> </head>


	<div3 type="subsection" id="d20">
<head><date value="1868-11-15"> <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 15, 1868.</date></head>

<p>&mdash;Arrived: Black Kettle and Little
Robe, chiefs of the Cheyenne tribe of Indians; were well received
by me, and some rations issued to them.  They promised to await the
return of General Hazen from Fort Arbuckle.
</p><p><date value="1868-11-16"> <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 16, 1868.</date>&mdash;Arrived: Little Big Mouth, Spotted
Wolf, and Little Horse, chiefs of the Arapahoe tribe of <pb n="476"/>
Indians; were treated by me the same as the Cheyennes, and also
consented to wait and see General Hazen.
</p><p><date value="1868-11-21"> <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 20 and 21, 1868.</date>&mdash;An interview took place
between General Hazen and the delegations of Cheyennes and
Arapahoes, headed by Black Kettle and Little Big Mouth.  The
following is from notes taken of the remarks of each.

</p>
</div3>
	<div3 type="subsection" id="d21">

<p>               BLACK KETTLE, CHEYENNE CHIEF,
said: I always feel well while I am among these friends of mine,
the Witchitas, Wacoes, and affiliated bands, and I never feel
afraid to go among the white men here, because I know them to be my
friends also.
</p><p> The Cheyennes when south of the Arkansas did not wish to
return to the north side, but our Father (agent) sent for us, and
we were told we had better go there, as we should be paid well for
so doing, by feeding, etc.
</p><p> The Cheyennes do not fight the people this side of the
Arkansas, and do not trouble Texas, but north of the Arkansas they
are almost always at war.
</p><p> I do not represent all the Cheyennes; some are still north of
the Arkansas.  I come from a point on the Washita River, about one
day's ride from Antelope Hills.  Near me there are over one hundred
lodges of my tribe, only a part of them are my followers.  I have
always done my best to keep my young men quiet, but some of them
will not listen.  When recently north of the Arkansas, some of them
were fired upon, and then the war began.  I have not since been
able to keep my young men at home.
</p><p> I have come here and seen all my friends among the Indians,
and have also seen that the white men are my friends, and it makes
me happy.  I should like to stop fighting, and come here soon with
my people, and stay here with these Indian friends of mine, and be
fed until the war is over.  But I only control part of the
Cheyennes.</p>
</div3>
	<div3 type="subsection" id="d22">


<p>             LITTLE BIG MOUTH, ARAPAHOE CHIEF,
said: I have come down here a long way to the country in which I
was born; the country between the Witchita Mountains and the
mountains on the Arkansas, where I roamed when a boy, to see all
these Indians&mdash;my friends&mdash;and to have a talk.
</p><p> I look upon you (General Hazen) as the representative of the
Great Father (the President).  I would not have come near you had
I wished to do wrong, but come because I want to do right.
</p><p> I never would have gone north of the Arkansas again, but my
Father there, the agent, continually sent for me, time after time,
and finally I went.  As soon as we got there we got into trouble.
</p><p> My people wish no trouble, but, although we have come back
south of the Arkansas, the soldiers follow us, and continue
fighting.  We want no more fighting, and we want you to send out
and stop these soldiers from coming against us.  I wish you to send
a paper to our Great Father, at Washington, at once, to have this
fighting stopped, that we want no more of it.  Although my kinsmen
have been killed, we will forget it, and we wish for Peace.

</p>
</div3>
	<div3 type="subsection" id="d23">


<p>           MAJOR-GENERAL W. B. HAZEN, U. S. A.,
said: The Great Father at Washington sent for me when I was away
out in New Mexico, because I had been much with the Indians, and
liked them, to come here and take care of all the Cheyennes,
Arapahoes, Apaches, Kiowas and Comanches, to look after them and
their agents, to get them on to their Reservations, as provided in
the Medicine Lodge Treaty.  Before I could come from New Mexico,
the Cheyennes and Arapahoes had gone to war, so that I could not
see them; but I saw the others at Fort Larned, and I have come here
as I promised them.
</p><p> I was sent here as a peace-chief; all here is to be peace, and
we will keep the faith; but north of the Arkansas is General
Sheridan, the great war-chief.  I cannot control him, and he has
all the soldiers, who are fighting the Cheyennes and Arapahoes.  I
cannot deal with the tribes who are at war until after they have
made peace with the <pb n="477"/>  troops who are fighting them;
therefore, you must go back to your country, and if the soldiers
come to attack you, you must remember they are not from me, but
from that great war-chief, and with him you must make Peace.
</p><p> The people in Kansas and Texas, and in the east are all one
people, and when peace comes, it must be with all these places
alike.
</p><p> <hi rend="italic">Then</hi> I will go with you and your agent on to your
Reservation, and look out for you there.
</p><p> I am satisfied that you want peace; that is has not been you,
but your bad men who have made war; and I will do all I can for you
to have peace made.</p>
</div3>

	<div3 type="subsection" id="d24">

<p> <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 22, 1868.&mdash;The Cheyenne and Arapahoe
delegation started to-day for their camps on the Upper Washita.
[A true extract from my private notes.]
HENRY E. ALVORD,
Captain Tenth Regt. Cavalry, U. S. A.
CAMP WITCHITA, INDIAN TY., April 12, 1869.

</p><p> Seven days after this interview, Black Kettle's band was
attacked by General Custer on the banks of the Washita, and their
chief was killed. </p>
</div3>

	<div3 type="subsection" id="d25">
<head>THE ORDERS UNDER WHICH GENERAL HAZEN REFUSED BLACK KETTLE'S OFFERS
OF PEACE.<lb/>
HEADQUARTERS, MILITARY DIVISION OF THE MISSOURI,
<address><addrLine>ST. LOUIS, MO.,<date value="1868-09-26"> September 26, 1868.</date></addrLine></address><lb/>
General W. B. HAZEN,
Fork Harker, Kansas.</head>
<salute>GENERAL:</salute> <p>I advise you through the Indians themselves to give
out general notice that all Comanches, Kiowas, Cheyennes, and
Arapahoes, that wish to escape the effects of the present Indian
war, should now remove to the Reservation assigned them in their
treaty at the Medicine Lodge; that you will have their agencies
removed there, and their annuity goods delivered them, provided
they manifest a proper spirit of peace, and that, pending the
fulfilment of the treaty stipulations, you will use your means in
hand to provide them food at Fort Cobb.
*          *          *          *          *          *
</p><p> I have already reported to the proper department of Government
my wish, that the agencies of these Indians should be removed to
the Canadian at once, that annuity goods should not be issued at
Forts Larned or Dodge, but at the head agencies, and that these
annuities should consist in chief of food.
</p><p> I propose that General Sheridan shall prosecute the war with
vindictive earnestness against all hostile Indians till they are
obliterated or beg for mercy, and therefore all who want peace must
get out of the theatre of war, which will not reach the Reservation
committed to your care, unless absolutely necessary.
*          *          *          *          *          *
</p>
<signed>I am with respect,
      Your obedient servant,
 (Signed)            <name>W. T. SHERMAN,
                   Lieutenant-General.</name>
 Official copy,
      <name>CHAS G. RENNEY,
 Bt. Capt. U. S. A.,
      Disb'g Officer.</name></signed>
</div3>
<div3 type="notice" id="d26">
<head>                       BY TELEGRAPH.
                             <date value="1868-10-09">October 9, 1868.</date>
Major-General P. H. SHERIDAN,            Fort Hays, Kansas.
The following telegram is just received from General Sherman:
                               CHICAGO, ILL., October</head>
<salute>To General W. A. NICHOLS:</salute>
<p> Telegraph to General Sheridan that he may proceed on the fact
of hostility against all Indians outside of Hazen's Reservation.
* * *  Hazen must be ready to proceed to Fort Cobb, where, in
connection with the Indian agents, Boone and Wynkoop, he may invite
hostile Indians to come and locate on Reservation.  After notice is
sent to all Indians acceptable to him, Hazen should go to Fort
Cobb, establish himself there, and if the Indians do not come, it
is not his or our fault. </p>
<signed> (Signed)                           W. T. SHERMAN.</signed>
</div3>
<div3 type="letter" id="d27">
<head><address><addrLine>HEADQUARTERS MILITARY DIVISION OF THE MISSOURI,
           ST. LOUIS, MO., <date value="1868-10-13">October 13, 1868.</date></addrLine>
</address>
Brevet-Major General W. B. HAZEN,
                Fort Cobb,
 (via Fort Arbuckle),     Indian Territory.</head>
<salute> GENERAL: </salute><p>I want you to go to Fort Cobb, and to make provisions
for all <pb n="478"/>  the Indians who come there to keep out of the war;
and I prefer that no war-like proceedings be made from that
quarter.  Both of the agents, Boone and Wynkoop, are ordered there
also with the annuity goods, which, under a resolution of the
Indian Peace Commission, are to be distributed by them to such
Indians as you may approve of.  The object is, for the War and
Interior Departments to afford peaceful Indians every possible
protection, support, and encouragement, while the troops proceed
against all outside of the Reservation as hostile; and it may be
that General Sheridan will be forced to invade the Reservation in
pursuit of hostile Indians.  If so, I will instruct him to do all
he can to spare the well-disposed, but their only safety now is in
rendezvousing at Fort Cobb.  <hi rend="italic">I will approve and justify any
expense, or any thing you may do to encourage Indians to come on to
that Reservation, there to remain at peace</hi>, while I will urge
General Sheridan to push his measures for the utter destruction and
subjugation of all who are outside in a hostile attitude.
</p><p> I wish you to remain at Fort Cobb, or in that vicinity as
patiently as you can, looking to the time when all that are left of
the Kiowas, Comanches, Apaches, Cheyennes, and Arapahoes are
gathered there.  Afterward at our leisure they can be conducted to
and established on their appropriate Reservations as defined in the
Medicine Lodge Treaty.
</p><signed> I am with respect,
     Your obedient servant,
(Signed)  <name>          W. T. SHERMAN,
       Lieutenant-General, Commanding.</name></signed>
</div3>
<div3 type="letter" id="d28">
<head><address><addrLine>HEADQUARTERS, SOUTHERN INDIAN TERRITORY,
FORT COBB, <date value="1868-11-10">November 10, 1868.</date></addrLine></address>
Lieut.-Gen. SHERMAN, U. S. A.</head>
<salute> SIR: </salute><p>* * *  After the promulgation of that order (General
Order No. 4), the Cheyennes and Arapahoes included in my district
became hostile, and I have considered them since that time as
beyond my authority, until these shall be turned over by General
Sheridan, who is now dealing with them. * * *
</p><p> Had there been an agent here with good and active assistants,
as provided by law, these Indians, the Comanches and Kiowas, would
probably have never left their Reservations.  <hi rend="italic">They do not yet
know the limits of their country, nor the place for their ultimate
self-maintenance on it.</hi>  Colonel Leavenworth established
himself at a place singularly unsuited for their permanent home,
and seemed to do nothing looking toward establishing the Government
scheme of colonization.  <hi rend="italic">I would call attention also to the
facts just stated as equally true with the Cheyennes and
Arapahoes</hi> and their agent.  He established himself at Fort
Larned, a hundred miles north of their Reservation, and the Indians
were invited there, most of them going against their will.  Had
they been placed where they belong, or had the agent, with the
assistants provided by the Government, gone and remained there,
<hi rend="italic">the Indians would have remained, and the present war in all
probability would not have taken place</hi>.
</p><p> The Indians here, account for the present war as follows:
Being about Larned, where abundant access was had to whiskey, a war
party went to attack the Pawnees, their old foes, and were beaten;
when returning, and on the settlements, one of them rode to a home
for something to eat, without any intention of doing harm.  A man
came to the door, and ordered him away.  The Indian not knowing
what was said to him, continued to ride toward the house, and the
citizen came out with a shot-gun and fired on him.  At that the
fracas commenced, and war followed.  It is evident that it was not
premeditated, as the Cheyennes were trading away their arms just
issued by their agent in large numbers, up to the day of the
outbreak.
*          *          *          *          *          *
</p><signed>      I am, most respectfully, &amp;c.,
 (Signed)  <name>               W. B. HAZEN,
                     Brevet-Major-General.</name></signed>
</div3>
<div3 type="letter" id="d29">
<head><address><addrLine>HEADQUARTERS, SOUTHERN INDIAN TERRITORY,
FORT COBB, Indian Territory, <date value="1868-11-21">Nov. 21, 1868. </date>
</addrLine></address></head>

<salute>To Lieut-Gen. SHERMAN, U. S. A.</salute>
<p> SIR: The Cheyenne chief, Black Kettle, <pb n="479"/>  and Arapahoe
chief, Big Mouth, came here to ask for peace for their bands.  I
enclose their talk (page 476).  Black Kettle represents a large
part of the Cheyennes, known as the Southern Cheyennes, or those
who were at Larned when the war commenced; and Big Mouth speaks for
all or nearly all of the Southern Arapahoes.  He was accompanied by
the chief, Spotted Wolf, and Black Kettle by Little Robe.  They
started of their own accord, but met one of my scouts, who told
them to come on.  To have made peace with them would have brought
to my camp most of those now on the war-path south of the Arkansas;
and as General Sheridan is to punish those at war, and might follow
them in afterward, a second Chevington affair might occur which I
could not prevent.  I do not understand that I am to treat for
peace, but would like definite instructions in this and like cases.
To make peace with these people would probably close the war, but
perhaps not permanently.  I should prefer that General Sheridan
should make peace with these parties. * * *
</p><signed>(Signed)                                W. B. HAZEN.</signed>
</div3>
<div3 type="letter" id="d30">
<head><address>
<addrLine>HEADQUARTERS, MILITARY DIVISION OF THE MISSOURI,
      ST. LOUIS, MO., <date value="1868-11-23">November 23, 1868.</date>
</addrLine></address>
General W. B. HAZEN,
 Southern Indian Reservation,
      Fort Cobb, Indian Territory. </head>

<salute> DEAR GENERAL: </salute><p>I have this morning received your most
interesting letter of the 7th of November with contents, which I
have sent to the Secretary of War, as we are determined that
Congress shall know all that it is possible for us to convey, to
enable it to make a final disposition of this Indian question this
winter.
*          *          *          *          *          *
</p><p> I see clearly the difficulties that you have to deal with. *
* *  In my instructions to General Sheridan, I used this language:
</p><p> "The establishment of General Hazen at Fort Cobb with fifty
thousand dollars, and the clothing and stores which the Indian
Bureau have agreed to supply, is the result of the action of the
Indian Peace Commission, which aimed to hold out the olive branch
with one hand, and the sword in the other.  <hi rend="italic">But it is not
thereby intended that any hostile Indians shall make use of that
establishment as a refuge from a just punishment for acts already
done.</hi>  Your military control over that Reservation is as
perfect as over Kansas, and if hostile Indians retreat within that
Reservation, they are by no means to escape a deserved punishment,
but they may be followed even to Fort Cobb, captured and punished.
But in any event you need some place to put your captives and
prisoners, and Fort Cobb can be used for that purpose, as well as
a place of refuge for such Indians as in good faith want to keep
out of the war.  Therefore I should deem it unwise to organize a
force to go out in search of hostile Indians from that quarter,
until after it is known that hostile Indians are actually near by;
and even then every appearance about Fort Cobb should be suggestive
of an earnest desire to afford a place of refuge, where the
peaceable Indians may receive food, and be safe against our troops,
as well as against the hostile Indians who may try to involve them
in the common war.
</p><p> "In all my correspondence with the Indian Department I have
insisted on this Fort Cobb establishment, in preference to
embracing the whole Reservation, because I saw how difficult it
would be for your troops in the field to cease pursuit at its very
boundary; but if the friendly Indians rendezvous about Fort Cobb,
General Hazen can demand the surrender of all who have committed
acts of outrage before issuing a pound of food, and these should be
seized and held, or placed in confinement at Fort Gibson or
Arbuckle there to await your orders."
*          *          *          *          *          *
</p><signed> Keep me well advised.                   Truly yours,
      (Signed)               <name>W. T. SHERMAN,
                                  Lieutenant-General. </name></signed>
</div3>
</div2>
<div2 type="story" id="d31">
<head>HOW A COMANCHE CHIEF IMITATED HIS GREAT FATHER.</head>
<p> Ten-Bears, chief of the Pennetecker <pb n="480"/>  Comanches, called
to see the General a short time ago, to know, "What about this
farming he heard so much talk about, that they wanted all the
Indians to set about?"  "He had been on to Washington" some two or
three years since, and "Washington hadn't said any thing to him
about farming."
</p><p> "What did he talk about?" asked the General.
</p><p> "Why, he told me that all the country out here was my own, and
that I could go about as much as I pleased, so long as I did not
take any scalps nor steal any stock."
</p><p> "Oh, well! that was at that time, but now he wants you to farm
it.  He plants corn&mdash;all Americans plant corn;" said the General.
</p><p> "Ugh!" said Ten-Bears, smoking most vigorously on his little
short pipe, and smacking his lips with increasing vehemence.  "Ugh!
Well, I tell you what, you build me a large white house like the
one Washington lives in, and I will plant corn too."
</p><p> The General was nonplussed.

</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="story" id="d32">
<head>AN INDIAN MAGNANIMOUS.</head>

<p> This morning we rode over to the camp of the Arapahoes by
invitation of the chiefs Little Raven and Yellow Bear.
</p><p> The air was bracing and clear; the sunlight playing on the
beds of purple daisies across the fresh green prairie most
attractively.
</p><p> General Grierson and Captain Alvord cantered alongside on two
very lean horses, while General Hazen and Mr. R&mdash; invited me
into their four-mule ambulance.
</p><p> The stout fatherly form of Little Raven led the way, with
Yellow Bear as aid-de-camp.
</p><p> Suddenly the quiet of our drowsiness was aroused by the
appearance of a large grey wolf near us, over the hill.
</p><p> Quickly Yellow Bear was summoned to ride after and shoot him.
</p><p> Yellow Bear trotted off, leisurely at first, and then faster
and swifter, till he appeared to be close upon him.  He drew his
arrow and brought it steadily in the bow, ready to shoot the wolf;
held it so for a minute, riding rapidly the while, and then
suddenly checked his pony, put up his bow, and rode leisurely back
toward us, leaving the wolf unharmed.
</p><p> We wondered, and asked why he did not shoot him?  He said:
<hi rend="italic">"The wolf was sick; Arapahoe never kills sick animals."</hi>
</p><p> He did not need Mr. Bergh's interference.

</p></div2>
<div2 type="section" id="d33">
<head>AN INDIAN VILLAGE.</head>

<p> We arrived at the Arapahoe camp about noon.  About ninety
lodges were scattered irregularly along the banks of a small
stream, well-shaded with cotton-wood just budding into green.
</p><p> Groups of warriors and children, with here and there a woman,
could be seen among the tents.  The lodges were made of buffalo
skins, erected on poles about fifteen feet high, sugar-loaf shape,
with openings fringed with the ends of the poles sticking up, and
blackened with smoke at the top.  A small oval opening served for
a door, with movable skins to cover it from the cold or storms.
</p><p> Before many of these tepes, were stuck up straight poles,
about as long as a lance, with bright-colored flags, shields, or
feathers&mdash;the mark or sign of the owner being within.  Dogs and
children abounded; the latter naked, the former over-furred.  The
children were lively, and seemed delighted to see us.  The women
were busy, as usual, at their conventional employments, dressing
buffalo robes and cooking.</p>

</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
