<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CooEcli"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="CooEcli">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Eclipse</title>
<title type="sort">eclipse</title>
<author>Cooper, James Fenimore</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">34</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CooEcli</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475833</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>The print version was not illustrated.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Eclipse</title>
<title type="sort">eclipse</title>
<author>James Fenimore Cooper</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
<name>S.F.C.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Putnam's Monthly Magazine</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1869">1869</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Putnam's Monthly Magazine</hi> 21 (n.s. 4) (Sept. 1869): 352-359.</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1869">1869</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-12">December 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Deirdre Johnson, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Header added, basic TEI markup added</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">

<div1 type="introduction" id="d3">
<pb n="352"/>
<head>                            THE ECLIPSE. <lb/>

         FROM AN UNPUBLISHED MS. OF JAMES FENIMORE COOPER.
<lb/>Putnam's Monthly Magazine 21 (n.s. 4) (Sept. 1869): 352-359.
</head>

<p>     <hi rend="italic">Note by the Editor</hi>.&mdash;During Mr. Cooper's residence at
Paris, he wrote, at the request of an English friend, his
recollections of the great eclipse of 1806.  This article, which is
undated, must have been written about the year 1831, or twenty-five
years after the eclipse.  His memory was at that period of his life
very clear and tenacious, where events of importance were
concerned.  From some accidental cause, this article was never sent
to England, but lay, apparently forgotten, among Mr. Cooper's
papers, where it was found after his death.  At the date of the
eclipse, the writer was a young sailor of seventeen, just returned
from a cruise.  At the time of writing these recollections, he had
been absent from his old home in Otsego County some fifteen years,
and his affectionate remembrance of the ground may be traced in
many little touches, which would very possibly have been omitted
under other circumstances.  </p>                       
	<closer><signed>S.F.C.</signed></closer>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" id="d4">
<p>  THE eclipse of the sun, which you have requested me to
describe, occurred in the summer of 1806, on Monday, the 16th of
June.  Its greatest depth of shadow fell upon the American
continent, somewhere about the latitude of 42 deg.  I was then on
a visit to my parents, at the home of my family, among the
Highlands of Otsego, in that part of the country where the eclipse
was most impressive.  My recollections of the great event, and the
incidents of the day, are as vivid as if they had occurred but
yesterday.
</p><p>  Lake Otsego, the headwaters of the Susquehanna, lies as nearly
as possible in latitude 42 deg.  The village, which is the home of
my family, is beautifully situated at the foot of the lake, in a
valley lying between two nearly parallel ranges of heights, quite
mountainous in character.  The Susquehanna, a clear and rapid
stream, flowing from the southeastern shore of the lake, is crossed
by a high wooden bridge, which divides the main street of the
little town from the lawns and meadows on the eastern bank of the
river.  Here were all the materials that could be desired, lake,
river, mountain, wood, and the dwellings of man, to give full
effect to the varied movement of light and shadow through that
impressive day.
</p><p>  Throughout the belt of country to be darkened by the eclipse,
the whole population were in a state of almost anxious expectation
for weeks before the event.  On the eve of the 16th of June, our
family circle could think or talk of little else.  I had then a
father and four brothers living, and as we paced the broad hall of
the house, or sat about the family board, our conversation turned
almost entirely upon the movements of planets and comets,
occultations and eclipses.  We were all exulting in the feeling
that a grand and extraordinary spectacle awaited us&mdash;a spectacle
which millions then living could never behold.  There may have been
a tinge of selfishness in the feeling that we were thus favored
beyond others, and yet, I think, the emotion was too intellectual
in its character to have been altogether unworthy.
</p><p>  Many were the prophecies regarding the weather, the hopes and
fears expressed by different individuals, on this important point,
as evening drew near.  A passing cloud might veil the grand vision
from our sight; rain or mist would sadly impair the sublimity of
the hour.  I was not myself among the desponding.  The great
barometer in the hall&mdash;one of the very few then found in the State,
west of Albany&mdash;was carefully consulted.  It was propitious.  It
gave promise of dry weather.  Our last looks that night, before
sleep fell on us, were turned toward the starlit heavens. <pb n="353"/>
</p><p>  And the first movement in the morning was to the open window&mdash;
again to examine the sky.  When I rose from my bed, in the early
morning, I found the heavens serene, and cloudless.  Day had
dawned, but the shadows of night were still lingering over the
valley.  For a moment, my eye rested on the familiar view&mdash;the
limpid lake, with its setting of luxuriant woods and farms, its
graceful bay and varied points, the hills where every cliff and
cave and glen had been trodden a thousand times by my boyish feet&mdash;
all this was dear to me as the face of a friend.  And it appeared
as if the landscape, then lovely in summer beauty, were about to
assume something of dignity hitherto unknown&mdash;were not the shadows
of a grand eclipse to fall upon every wave and branch within a few
hours!  There was one object in the landscape which a stranger
would probably have overlooked, or might perhaps have called
unsightly, but it was familiar to every eye in the village, and
endowed by our people with the honors of an ancient landmark&mdash;the
tall gray trunk of a dead and branchless pine, which had been
standing on the crest of the eastern hill, at the time of the
foundation of the village, and which was still erect, though rocked
since then by a thousand storms.  To my childish fancy, it had
seemed an imaginary flag-staff, or, in rustic parlance, the
"liberty pole" of some former generation; but now, as I traced the
familiar line of the tall trunk, in its peculiar shade of silvery
gray, it became to the eye of the young sailor the mast of some
phantom ship.  I remember greeting it with a smile, as this was the
first glance of recognition given to the old ruin of the forest
since my return.
</p><p>  But an object of far higher interest suddenly attracted my
eye.  I discovered a star&mdash;a solitary star&mdash;twinkling dimly in a
sky which had now changed its hue to a pale grayish twilight, while
vivid touches of coloring were beginning to flush the eastern sky.
There was absolutely no other object visible in the heavens&mdash;cloud
there was none, not even the lightest vapor.  That lonely star
excited a vivid interest in my mind.  I continued at the window
gazing, and losing myself in a sort of day-dream.  That star was a
heavenly body, it was known to be a planet, and my mind was filling
itself with images of planets and suns.  My brain was confusing
itself with vague ideas of magnitude and distance, and of the time
required by light to pierce the apparently illimitable void that
lay between us&mdash;of the beings who might inhabit an orb like that,
with life, feeling, spirit, and aspirations like my own.
</p><p>  Soon the sun himself rose into view.  I caught a glimpse of
fiery light glowing among the branches of the forest, on the
eastern mountain.  I watched, as I had done a hundred times before,
the flushing of the skies, the gradual illuminations of the
different hills, crowned with an undulating and ragged outline of
pines, nearly two hundred feet in height, the golden light gliding
silently down the breast of the western mountains, and opening
clearer views of grove and field, until lake, valley, and village
lay smiling in one cheerful glow of warm sunshine.
</p><p>  Our family party assembled early.  We were soon joined by
friends and connections, all eager and excited, and each provided
with a colored glass for the occasion.  By nine o'clock the cool
air, which is peculiar to the summer nights in the Highlands, had
left us, and the heat of midsummer filled the valley.  The heavens
were still absolutely cloudless, and a more brilliant day never
shone in our own bright climate.  There was not a breath of air,
and we could see the rays of heat quivering here and there on the
smooth surface of the lake.  There was every appearance of a hot
and sultry noontide.
</p><p>  We left the house, and passed beyond the grounds into the
broad and grassy street which lay between the gates and the lake.
Here there were no overhanging branches to obstruct the view; the
heavens, the wooded mountains, and the limpid sheet of water before
us, were all distinctly seen.  As the hour for the eclipse drew
near, our eagerness and <pb n="354"/>  excitement increased to an almost
boyish impatience.  The elders of the party were discussing the
details of some previous eclipse: leaving them to revive their
recollections, I strolled away, glass in hand, through the
principal streets of the village.  Scarce a dwelling, or a face, in
the little town, that was not familiar to me, and it gave
additional zest to the pleasure of a holiday at home, to meet one's
townsfolk under the excitement of an approaching eclipse.  As yet
there was no great agitation, although things wore a rather unusual
aspect for the busy hours of a summer's day.  Many were busy with
their usual tasks, women and children were coming and going with
pails of water, the broom and the needle were not yet laid aside,
the blacksmith's hammer and the carpenter's plane were heard in
passing their shops.  Loaded teams, and travellers in waggons, were
moving through the streets; the usual quiet traffic at the village
counters had not yet ceased.  A farm-waggon, heavily laden with
hay, was just crossing the bridge, coming in from the fields, the
driver looking drowsy with sleep, wholly unconscious of the
movement in the heavens.  The good people in general, however, were
on the alert; at every house some one seemed to be watching, and
many groups were passed, whose eager up-turned faces and excited
conversation spoke the liveliest interest.  It was said, that there
were not wanting one or two philosophers of the skeptical school,
among our people, who did not choose to commit themselves to the
belief in a total eclipse of the sun&mdash;simply because they had never
seen one.  Seeing is believing, we are told, though the axiom
admits of dispute.  But what these worthy neighbors of ours had not
seen, no powers of reasoning, or fulness of evidence, could induce
them to credit.  Here was the dignity of human reason!  Here was
private judgment taking a high stand!  Anxious to witness the
conversion of one of these worthies, with boyish love of fun I went
in quest of him.  He had left the village, however, on business.
But, true to his principles, before mounting his horse that
morning, he had declared to his wife that <hi rend="italic">"he was not running
away from that eclipse;"</hi> nay, more, with noble candor, he
averred that if the eclipse did overtake him, in the course of his
day's journey, <hi rend="italic">"he would not be above acknowledging it!"</hi>
This was highly encouraging.
</p><p>  I had scarcely returned to the family party, left on the
watch, when one of my brothers, more vigilant, or with clearer
sight than his companions, exclaimed that he clearly saw a dark
line, drawn on the western margin of the sun's disc!  All faces
were instantly turned upwards, and through the glasses we could
indeed now see a dusky, but distinct object, darkening the sun's
light.  An exclamation of delight, almost triumphant, burst
involuntarily from the lips of all.  We were not to be
disappointed, no cloud was there to veil the grand spectacle; the
vision, almost unearthly in its sublime dignity, was about to be
revealed to us.  In an incredibly short time, the oval formation of
the moon was discerned.  Another joyous burst of delight followed,
as one after another declared that he beheld with distinctness the
dark oval outline, drawn against the flood of golden light.
Gradually, and at first quite imperceptibly to our sight, that dark
and mysterious sphere gained upon the light, while a feeling of
watchful stillness, verging upon reverence, fell upon our excited
spirits.
</p><p>  As yet there was no change perceptible in the sunlight falling
upon lake and mountain; the familiar scene wore its usual smiling
aspect, bright and glowing as on other days of June.  The people,
however, were now crowding into the streets&mdash;their usual labors
were abandoned&mdash;forgotten for the moment&mdash;and all faces were turned
upward.  So little, however, was the change in the power of the
light, that to a careless observer it seemed more the gaze of
faith, than positive perception, which turned the faces of all
upward.  Gradually a fifth, and even a fourth, of the sun's disc
became obscured, and <pb n="355"/>  still the unguarded eye could not
endure the flood of light&mdash;it was only with the colored glass that
we could note the progress of the phenomenon.  The noon-day heat,
however, began to lessen, and something of the coolness of early
morning returned to the valley.
</p><p>  I was looking upward, intently watching for the first moment
where the dark outline of the moon should be visible to the naked
eye, when an acquaintance passed.  "Come with me!" he said quietly,
at the same moment drawing his arm within my own, and leading me
away.  He was a man of few words, and there was an expression in
his face which induced me to accompany him without hesitation.  He
led me to the Court House, and from thence into an adjoining
building, and into a room then occupied by two persons.  At a
window, looking upward at the heavens, stood a figure which
instantly riveted my attention.  It was a man with haggard face,
and fettered arms, a prisoner under sentence of death.  By his side
was the jailor.
</p><p>  A painful tragedy had been recently enacted in our little
town.  The schoolmaster of a small hamlet in the county had beaten
a child under his charge very severely&mdash;and for a very trifling
error.  The sufferer was a little girl, his own niece, and it was
said that natural infirmity had prevented the child from clearly
pronouncing certain words which her teacher required her to utter
distinctly.  To conquer what he considered the obstinacy of the
child, this man continued to beat her so severely that she never
recovered from the effects of the blows, and died some days after.
The wretched man was arrested, tried for murder, condemned, and
sentenced to the gallows.  This was the first capital offence in
Otsego County.  It produced a very deep impression.  The general
character of the schoolmaster had been, until that evil hour, very
good, in every way.  He was deeply, and beyond all doubt
unfeignedly, penitent for the crime into which he had been led,
more, apparently, from false ideas of duty, than from natural
severity of temper.  He had been entirely unaware of the great
physical injury he was doing the child.  So great was his
contrition, that public sympathy had been awakened in his behalf,
and powerful petitions had been sent to the Governor of the State,
in order to obtain a respite, if not a pardon.  But the day named
by the judge arrived without a return of the courier.  The Governor
was at his country-house, at least eighty miles beyond Albany.  The
petition had been kept to the last moment, for additional
signatures, and the eighty miles to be travelled by the courier,
after reaching Albany, had not been included in the calculation.
No despatch was received, and there was every appearance that there
would be no reprieve.  The day arrived&mdash;throngs of people from
Chenango, and Unadilla, and from the valley of the Mohawk, poured
into the village, to witness the painful, and as yet unknown,
spectacle of a public execution.  In looking down, from an elevated
position, upon the principal street of the village that day, it had
seemed to me paved with human faces.  The hour struck, the prisoner
was taken from the jail, and, seated, as is usual, on his coffin,
was carried to the place of execution, placed between two ministers
of the gospel.  His look of utter misery was beyond description.
I have seen other offenders expiate for their crimes with life, but
never have I beheld such agony, such a clinging to life, such
mental horror at the nearness of death, as was betrayed by this
miserable man.  When he approached the gallows, he rose from his
seat, and wringing his fettered hands, turned his back upon the
fearful object, as if the view were too frightful for endurance.
The ministers of the gospel succeeded at length in restoring him to
a decent degree of composure.  The last prayer was offered, and his
own fervent "Amen!" was still sounding, hoarse, beseeching, and
almost despairing, in the ears of the crowd, when the respite made
its tardy appearance.  A short reprieve was granted, and the
prisoner was carried back to the miserable<pb n="356"/> cell from which
he had been drawn in the morning.
</p><p>  Such was the wretched man who had been brought from his
dungeon that morning, to behold the grand phenomenon of the
eclipse.  During the twelve-month previous, he had seen the sun but
once.  The prisons of those days were literally dungeons, cut off
from the light of day.  That striking figure, the very picture of
utter misery, his emotion, his wretchedness, I can never forget.
I can see him now, standing at the window, pallid and emaciated by
a year's confinement, stricken with grief, his cheeks furrowed with
constant weeping, his whole frame attesting the deep and ravaging
influences of conscious guilt and remorse.  Here was a man drawn
from the depths of human misery, to be immediately confronted with
the grandest natural exhibition in which the Creator deigns to
reveal his Omnipotence to our race.  The wretched criminal, a
murderer in fact, though not in intention, seemed to gaze upward at
the awful spectacle, with an intentness and a distinctness of
mental vision far beyond our own, and purchased by an agony
scarcely less bitter than death.  It seemed as if, for him, the
curtain which veils the world beyond the grave, had been lifted.
He stood immovable as a statue, with uplifted and manacled arms and
clasped hands, the very image of impotent misery and wretchedness.
Perhaps human invention could not have conceived of a more powerful
moral accessory, to heighten the effect of the sublime movement of
the heavenly bodies, than this spectacle of penitent human guilt
afforded.  It was an incident to stamp on the memory for life.  It
was a lesson not lost on me.
</p><p>  When I left the Court House, a sombre, yellowish, unnatural
coloring was shed over the country.  A great change had taken
place.  The trees on the distant heights had lost their verdure and
their airy character; they were taking the outline of dark pictures
graven upon an unfamiliar sky.  The lake wore a lurid aspect, very
unusual.  All living creatures seemed thrown into a state of
agitation.  The birds were fluttering to and fro, in great
excitement; they seemed to mistrust that this was not the gradual
approach of evening, and were undecided in their movements.  Even
the dogs&mdash;honest creatures&mdash;became uneasy, and drew closer to their
masters.  The eager, joyous look of interest and curiosity, which
earlier in the morning had appeared in almost every countenance,
was now changed to an expression of wonder or anxiety or
thoughtfulness, according to the individual character.
</p><p>  Every house now gave up its tenants.  As the light failed more
and more with every passing second, the children came flocking
about their mothers in terror.  The women themselves were looking
about uneasily for their husbands.  The American wife is more apt
than any other to turn with affectionate confidence to the stronger
arm for support.  The men were very generally silent and grave.
Many a laborer left his employment to be near his wife and
children, as the dimness and darkness increased.
</p><p>  I once more took my position beside my father and my brothers,
before the gates of our own grounds.  The sun lay a little
obliquely to the south and east, in the most favorable position
possible for observation.  I remember to have examined, in vain,
the whole dusky canopy in search of a single cloud.  It was one of
those entirely unclouded days, less rare in America than in Europe.
The steadily waning light, the gradual approach of darkness, became
the more impressive as we observed this absolutely transparent
state of the heavens.  The birds, which a quarter of an hour
earlier had been fluttering about in great agitation, seemed now
convinced that night was at hand.  Swallows were dimly seen
dropping into the chimneys, the martins returned to their little
boxes, the pigeons flew home to their dove-cots, and through the
open door of a small barn we saw the fowls going to roost.
</p><p>  The usual flood of sunlight had now become so much weakened,
that we could look upward long, and steadily, <pb n="357"/>  without the
least pain.  The sun appeared like a young moon of three or four
days old, though of course with a larger and more brilliant
crescent.  Looking westward a moment, a spark appeared to glitter
before my eye.  For a second I believed it to be an optical
illusion, but in another instant I saw it plainly to be a star.
One after another they came into view, more rapidly than in the
evening twilight, until perhaps fifty stars appeared to us, in a
broad, dark zone of the heavens, crowning the pines on the western
mountain.  This wonderful vision of the stars, during the noontide
hours of day, filled the spirit with singular sensations.
</p><p>  Suddenly one of my brothers shouted aloud, "The moon!"
Quicker than thought, my eye turned eastward again, and there
floated the moon, distinctly apparent, to a degree that was almost
fearful.  The spherical form, the character, the dignity, the
substance of the planet, were clearly revealed as I have never
beheld them before, or since.  It looked grand, dark, majestic, and
mighty, as it thus proved its power to rob us entirely of the sun's
rays.  We are all but larger children.  In daily life we judge of
objects by their outward aspect.  We are accustomed to think of the
sun, and also of the moon, as sources of light, as etherial, almost
spiritual, in their essence.  But the positive material nature of
the moon was now revealed to our senses, with a force of
conviction, a clearness of perception, that changed all our usual
ideas in connection with the planet.  This was no interposition of
vapor, no deceptive play of shadow; but a vast mass of obvious
matter had interposed between the sun above us and the earth on
which we stood.  The passage of two ships at sea, sailing on
opposite courses, is scarcely more obvious than this movement of
one world before another.  Darkness like that of early night now
fell upon the village.
</p><p>  My thoughts turned to the sea.  A sailor at heart, already
familiar with the face of the ocean, I seemed, in mental vision, to
behold the grandeur of that vast pall of supernatural shadow
falling suddenly upon the sea, during the brightest hour of the
day.  The play of light and shade upon the billows, always full of
interest, must at that hour have been indeed sublime.  And my fancy
was busy with pictures of white-sailed schooners, and brigs, and
ships, gliding like winged spirits over the darkened waves.
</p><p>  I was recalled by a familiar and insignificant incident, the
dull tramp of hoofs on the village bridge.  A few cows, believing
that night had overtaken them, were coming homeward from the wild
open pastures about the village.  And no wonder the kindly
creatures were deceived, the darkness was now much deeper than the
twilight which usually turns their faces homeward; the dew was
falling perceptibly, as much so as at any hour of the previous
night, and the coolness was so great that the thermometer must have
fallen many degrees from the great heat of the morning.  The lake,
the hills, and the buildings of the little town were swallowed up
in the darkness.  The absence of the usual lights in the dwellings
rendered the obscurity still more impressive.  All labor had
ceased, and the hushed voices of the people only broke the absolute
stillness by subdued whispering tones.
</p><p>  "Hist!  The whippoorwill!" whispered a friend near me; and at
the same moment, as we listened in profound silence, we distinctly
heard from the eastern bank of the river the wild, plaintive note
of that solitary bird of night, slowly repeated at intervals.  The
song of the summer birds, so full in June, had entirely ceased for
the last half hour.  A bat came flitting about our heads.  Many
stars were now visible, though not in sufficient number to lessen
the darkness.  At one point only in the far distant northern
horizon, something of the brightness of dawn appeared to linger.
</p><p>  At twelve minutes past eleven, the moon stood revealed in its
greatest distinctness&mdash;a vast black orb, so nearly obscuring the
sun that the face of the <pb n="358"/>  great luminary was entirely and
absolutely darkened, though a corona of rays of light appeared
beyond.  The gloom of night was upon us.  A breathless intensity of
interest was felt by all.  There would appear to be something
instinctive in the feeling with which man gazes at all phenomena in
the heavens.  The peaceful rainbow, the heavy clouds of a great
storm, the vivid flash of electricity, the falling meteor, the
beautiful lights of the aurora borealis, fickle as the play of
fancy,&mdash;these never fail to fix the attention with something of a
peculiar feeling, different in character from that with which we
observe any spectacle on the earth.  Connected with all grand
movements in the skies there seems an instinctive sense of inquiry,
of anxious expectation; akin to awe, which may possibly be traced
to the echoes of grand Christian prophecies, whispering to our
spirits, and endowing the physical sight with some mysterious
mental prescience.  In looking back to that impressive hour, such
now seem to me the feelings of the youth making one of that family
group, all apparently impressed with a sensation of the deepest
awe&mdash;I speak with certainty&mdash;a clearer view than I had ever yet had
of the majesty of the Almighty, accompanied with a humiliating,
and, I trust, a profitable sense of my own utter insignificance.
That movement of the moon, that sublime voyage of the worlds, often
recurs to my imagination, and even at this distant day, as
distinctly, as majestically, and nearly as fearfully, as it was
then beheld.
</p><p>  A group of silent, dusky forms stood near me; one emotion
appeared to govern all.  My father stood immovable, some fifteen
feet from me, but I could not discern his features.  Three minutes
of darkness, all but absolute, elapsed.  They appeared strangely
lengthened by the intensity of feeling and the flood of
overpowering thought which filled the mind.
</p><p>  Thus far the sensation created by this majestic spectacle had
been one of humiliation and awe.  It seemed as if the great Father
of the Universe had visibly, and almost palpably, veiled his face
in wrath.  But, appalling as the withdrawal of light had been, most
glorious, most sublime, was its restoration!  The corona of light
above the moon became suddenly brighter, the heavens beyond were
illuminated, the stars retired, and light began to play along the
ridges of the distant mountains.  And then a flood of grateful,
cheering, consoling brightness fell into the valley, with a
sweetness and a power inconceivable to the mind, unless the eye has
actually beheld it.  I can liken this sudden, joyous return of
light, after the eclipse, to nothing of the kind that is familiarly
known.  It was certainly nearest to the change produced by the
swift passage of the shadow of a very dark cloud, but it was the
effect of this instantaneous transition, multiplied more than a
thousand fold.  It seemed to speak directly to our spirits, with
full assurance of protection, of gracious mercy, and of that Divine
love which has produced all the glorious combinations of matter for
our enjoyment.  It was not in the least like the gradual dawning of
day, or the actual rising of the sun.  There was no gradation in
the change.  It was sudden, amazing, like what the imagination
would teach us to expect of the advent of a heavenly vision.  I
know that philosophically I am wrong; but, to me, it seemed that
the rays might actually be seen flowing through the darkness in
torrents, till they had again illuminated the forest, the
mountains, the valley, and the lake with their glowing, genial
touch.
</p><p>  There was another grand movement, as the crescent of the sun
reappeared, and the moon was actually seen steering her course
through the void.  Venus was still shining brilliantly.
</p><p>  This second passage of the moon lasted but a moment, to the
naked eye.  As it ceased, my eye fell again on the scene around me.
The street, now as distinctly seen as ever, was filled with the
population of the village.  Along the line of road stretching for
a mile from the valley, against the side of the mountain, were
twenty waggons bearing travellers, or teams from among the hills.
All had stopped on their course, impelled, apparently, by
unconscious reverence, as much as by curiosity, while every face
was turned toward heaven, and every eye drank in the majesty of the
sight.  Women stood in the open street, near me, with streaming
eyes and clasped hands, and sobs were audible in different
directions.  Even the educated and reflecting men at my side
continued silent in thought.  Several minutes passed, before the
profound impressions of the spectacle allowed of speech.  At such
a moment the spirit of man bows in humility before his Maker.
</p><p>  The changes of the unwonted light, through whose gradations
the full brilliancy of the day was restored, must have been very
similar to those by which it had been lost, but they were little
noted.  I remember, however, marking the instant when I could first
distinguish the blades of grass at my feet&mdash;and later again
watching the shadows of the leaves on the gravel walk.  The white
lilies in my mother's flower-garden were observed by others among
the first objects of the vegetation which could be distinguished
from the windows of the house.  Every living creature was soon
rejoicing again in the blessed restoration of light after that
frightful moment of a night at noon-day.
</p><p>  Men who witness any extraordinary spectacle together, are apt,
in after-times, to find a pleasure in conversing on its
impressions.  But I do not remember to have ever heard a single
being freely communicative on the subject of his individual
feelings at the most solemn moment of the eclipse.  It would seem
as if sensations were aroused too closely connected with the
constitution of the spirit to be irreverently and familiarly
discussed.  I shall only say that I have passed a varied and
eventful life, that it has been my fortune to see earth, heavens,
ocean, and man in most of their aspects; but never have I beheld
any spectacle which so plainly manifested the majesty of the
Creator, or so forcibly taught the lesson of humility to man as a
total eclipse of the sun.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
