<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CraAdol"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="CraAdol">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Revenge of the Adolphus</title>
<title type="sort">revenge of the adolphus</title>
<author>Crane, Stephen, 1871-1900</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">43</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CraAdol</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475836</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Pictures have not been included from the print version,
which could not be obtained.  Text has been checked against the
microfilm.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Revenge of the <hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi>
</title>
<title level="j">Collier's Weekly</title>
<title type="sort">revenge of the adolphus</title>
<author>Stephen Crane</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>24</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>13-14, 19, 24-25.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Crowell-Collier Publishing Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>Springfield, Ohio</pubPlace>
<date value="1899-10-28">28 October, 1899</date>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction;  prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-05">May 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Catherine Tousignant</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="story" id="d3">
	<pb n="13"/>
<head>The Revenge of the ADOLPHUS<lb/>
by Stephen Crane
</head>

<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d4">
<head>I</head>

<p>"STAND BY!"

</p><p>Shackles had come down from the bridge of the <hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi>
and flung this command at three fellow-correspondents, who, in the
galley, were busy with pencils trying to write something exciting
and interesting from four days' quiet cruising.  They looked up
casually.  "What for?"  They did not intend to arouse for nothing.
Ever since Shackles had heard the men of the navy directing each
other to stand by for this thing and that thing, he had used the
two words as his pet phrase and was continually telling his friends
to stand by.  Sometimes its portentous and emphatic reiteration
became highly exasperating, and men were apt to retort sharply.
"Well, I am standing by, ain't I?"  On this occasion they detected
that he was serious.  "Well, what for?" they repeated.  In his
answer Shackles was reproachful as well as impressive.  "Stand by?
Stand by for a Spanish gunboat!&mdash;a Spanish gunboat in chase!  Stand
by for two Spanish gunboats&mdash;both of them in chase!"

</p><p>The others looked at him for a brief space, and were almost
certain that they saw truth written upon his countenance.
Whereupon they tumbled out of the galley and galloped up to the
bridge.  The cook, with a mere inkling of tragedy, was now out on
the lower deck bawling, "What's the matter?  What's the matter?
What's the matter?"  Aft, the grimy head of a stoker was thrust
suddenly up through the deck, so to speak.  The eyes flashed in a
quick look astern, and then the head vanished.  The correspondents
were scrambling on the bridge.  "Where's my opry glasses?  Here&mdash;
let me take a look.  Are they Spaniards, Captain?  Are you sure?"

</p><p>The skipper of the <hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi> was at the wheel.  The
pilot-house was so arranged that he could not see astern without
hanging forth from one of the side windows, but apparently he had made
early investigation.  He did not reply at once.  At sea he never
replied at once to questions.  At the very first Shackles had
discovered the merits of this deliberate manner, and had taken delight
in it.  He invariably detailed his talk with the captain to the other
correspondents.  "Look here.  I've just been to see the skipper.  I
said, 'I would like to put into Cape Haytien.' Then he took a little
think.  Finally he said, 'All right.' Then I said, 'I suppose we'll
need to take on more coal there?' He took another little think.
Finally he said, 'Yes.' I said, 'Ever ran into that port before?' He
took another little think.  Finally he said, 'Yes.' I said, 'Have a
cigar?' He took another little think.  See?  There's where I fooled
'im."

</p><p>While the correspondents spun the hurried questions at him,
the captain of the <hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi> stood with his brown hands on
the wheel and his cold glance aligned straight over the bow of his
ship.

</p><p>"Are they Spanish gunboats, Captain?  Are they, Captain?"

</p><p>After a profound pause, he said: "Yes."  The four
correspondents hastily and in perfect time presented their backs to
him and fastened their gaze on the pursuing foe.  They saw a dull,
gray curve of sea going to the feet of the high green and blue
coast-line of northeastern Cuba, and on this sea were two miniature
ships, with clouds of iron-colored smoke pouring from their
funnels.

</p><p>One of the correspondents strode elaborately to the pilot-house.  "Aw&mdash;Captain," he drawled, "do you think they can catch
us?"

</p><p>The captain's glance was still aligned over the bow of his
ship.  Ultimately he answered, "I don't know."

</p><p>From the top of the little <hi rend="italic">Adolphus's</hi> stack thick, dark
smoke swept level for a few yards, and then went rolling to leeward
in great, hot, obscuring clouds.  From time to time the grimy head
was thrust through the lower deck, the eyes took the quick look
astern, and then the head vanished.  The cook was trying to get
somebody to listen to him.  "Well, you know, my sons, it won't be
no fun to be ketched by them Spaniards.  By George, it
<hi rend="italic">won't</hi>.  Look here, what do you think they'll do to us, hey?
Say, I don't like this, you know.  I'm jiggered if I do."  The sea,
cut by the hurried bow of the <hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi>, flung its waters
astern in the formation of a wide angle, and the lines of the angle
ruffled and hissed as they fled, while the thumping screw tormented
the water at the stern.  The frame of the steamer underwent regular
convulsions as in the strenuous sobbing of a child.

</p><p>The mate was standing near the pilot-house.  Without looking
at him, the captain spoke his name:  "Ed!"

</p><p>"Yes, sir," cried the mate with alacrity.

</p><p>The captain reflected for a moment.  Then he said, "Are they
gainin' on us?"

</p><p>The mate took another anxious survey of the race.  "No&mdash;o&mdash;
yes, I think they are&mdash;a little."

</p><p>After a pause the captain said: "Tell the chief to hook her up
more."

</p><p>The mate, glad of an occupation in these tense minutes, flew
down to the engine-room door.  "Skipper says hook 'er up more!" he
bawled.

</p><p>The head of the chief engineer appeared&mdash;a grizzly head, now
wet with oil and sweat.  "What?" he shouted angrily.  It was as if
he had been propelling the ship with his own arms.  Now he was told
that his best was not good enough.  "What?  Hook 'er up more?  Why,
she can't carry another pound, I tell you!  Not another ounce!
We&mdash;"  Suddenly he ran forward and climbed to the bridge.
"Captain," he cried in the loud, harsh voice of one who lived
usually amid the thunder of machinery, "she can't do it, sir!  By
Gawd, she can't!  She's turning over now faster than she ever did
in her life, and we'll all blow to hell&mdash;"

</p><p>The low-toned, impassive voice of the captain suddenly checked
the chief's clamor.  "I'll blow her up," he said, "but I won't get
ketched if I can help it."  Even then the listening correspondents
found a second in which to marvel that the captain had actually
explained his point of view to another human being.

</p><p>The engineer stood blank.  Then suddenly he cried, "All right,
sir!"  He threw a hurried look of despair at the correspondents,
the deck of the <hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi>, the pursuing enemy, Cuba, to the
sky, and the sea; he vanished in the direction of his post.

</p><p>A correspondent was suddenly regifted with the power of
prolonged speech.  "Well, you see, the game is up, tight.  See!  We
can't get out of it.  The skipper will blow up the whole bunch
before he'll let his ship be taken, and the Spaniards are gaining.
Well, that's what comes from going to war in an eight-knot tub."
He bitterly accused himself, the others, and the dark, sightless,
indifferent world.

</p><p>This certainty of coming evil affected each one differently.
One was made garrulous; one kept absent-mindedly snapping his
fingers and gazing at the sea; another stepped nervously to and
fro, looking everywhere as if for employment for his mind.  As for
Shackles, he was silent and smiling; but it was a new smile that
caused the lines about his mouth to

   <pb n="14"/>

betray quivering weakness.  And each man looked at the others to
discover their degree of fear, and did his best to conceal his own,
holding his crackling nerves with all his strength.

</p><p>As the <hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi> rushed on, the sun suddenly emerged
from behind gray clouds, and its rays dealt Titanic blows, so that
in a few minutes the sea was a glowing blue plain, with the golden
shine dancing at the tips of the waves.  The coast of Cuba glowed
with light.  The pursuers displayed detail after detail in the new
atmosphere.  The voice of the cook was heard in high vexation.  "Am
I to git dinner as usual?  How do I know?  Nobody tells me what to
do!  Am I to git dinner as usual?"

</p><p>The mate answered ferociously:  "Of course you are!  What do
you s'pose?  Ain't you the cook, you condemned ijit?"

</p><p>The cook retorted in a mutinous scream:  "Well, how would I
know?  If this ship is goin' to blow up&mdash;"</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d5">
<head>II</head>


<p>THE captain called from the pilot-house:  "Mr. Shackles!  Oh,
Mr. Shackles!"

</p><p>The correspondent moved hastily to a window.

</p><p>"What is it, captain?"

</p><p>The skipper of the <hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi> raised a battered finger
and pointed over the bows.  "See 'er?" he asked, laconic but
quietly jubilant.  Another steamer was smoking at full speed over
the sunlit seas.  A great billow of pure white was on her bows.

</p><p>"Great Scott!" cried Shackles: "another Spaniard?"

</p><p>"No," said the captain; "that there is a United States
cruiser."

</p><p>"What?"  Shackles was dumbfounded into muscular paralysis.
"No!  Are you sure?"

</p><p>The captain nodded.  "Sure.  Take the glass.  See her ensign?
Two funnels; two masts with fighting tops.  She ought to be the
<hi rend="italic">Chancellorville</hi>."

</p><p>Shackles choked.  "Well, I'm blowed!"

</p><p>"Ed!" said the captain.

</p><p>"Yessir!"

</p><p>"Tell the chief there is no hurry."

</p><p>Shackles suddenly bethought him of his companions.  He dashed
to them and was full of quick scorn of their gloomy faces.  "Hi,
brace up there!  Are you blind?  Can't you see her?"

</p><p>"See what?"

</p><p>"Why, the <hi rend="italic">Chancellorville</hi>, you blind mice!" roared
Shackles.  "See 'er?  See 'er?  See 'er?"

</p><p>The others sprang up, saw, and collapsed.  Shackles was a
madman for the purpose of distributing the news.  "Cook!" he
shrieked;  "don't you see 'er, cook?  Great Scott, man, don't you
see 'er?"  He ran to the lower deck and howled his information
everywhere.  Suddenly, the whole ship smiled.  Men clapped each
other on the shoulder and joyously shouted.  The captain thrust his
head from the pilot-house to look back at the Spanish ships.  Then
he looked at the American cruiser.  "Now, we'll see," he said,
grimly and vindictively to the mate.  "Guess somebody else will do
some runnin'."  The mate chuckled.

</p><p>The two gunboats were still headed hard for the
<hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi>, and she kept on her way.  The American cruiser was
coming swiftly.  "It's the <hi rend="italic">Chancellorville!"</hi> cried Shackles.
"I know her.  We'll see a fight at sea, my boys!  A fight at sea!"
The enthusiastic correspondents pranced in Indian revels.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Chancellorville</hi>&mdash;2000 tons, 18.6 knots, ten 5-inch
guns&mdash;came on tempestuously, sheering the water high with her sharp
bow.  From her funnels the smoke raced away in driven sheets.  She
loomed with extraordinary rapidity, like a ship bulging and growing
out of the sea.  She swept by the <hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi> so close that one
could have thrown a walnut on board.  She was a glistening grey
apparition, with a blood-red water-line, with brown gun-muzzles and
white-clothed motionless Jack-tars; and in her rush she was silent,
deadly silent.  Probably there entered the mind of every man on
board of the <hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi> a feeling of almost idolatry for this
living thing, stern, but, to their thought, incomparably beautiful.
They would have cheered but that each man seemed to feel that a
cheer would be too puny a tribute.

</p><p>It was at first as if she did not see the <hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi>.
She was going to pass without heeding this little vagabond of the
high seas.  But suddenly a megaphone gaped over the rail of her
bridge, and a voice was heard measuredly, calmly intoning:
"Halloa&mdash;there!  Keep&mdash;well&mdash;to&mdash;the&mdash;north'ard&mdash;and&mdash;out of my&mdash;
way&mdash;and I'll&mdash;go&mdash;in&mdash;and&mdash;see&mdash;what&mdash;those&mdash;people&mdash;want."  Then
nothing was heard but the swirl of water.  In a moment the
<hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi> was looking at a high gray stern.  On the quarter-deck sailors were poised about the breech of the after-pivot gun.

</p><p>The correspondents were revelling.  "Captain," yelled
Shackles, "we can't miss this!  We must see it!"

</p><p>But the skipper had already flung over the wheel.  "Sure," he
answered, almost at once, "we can't miss it."

</p><p>The cook was arrogantly, grossly triumphant.  His voice rang
on the lower deck.  "There, now!  How will the Spinachers like
that?  Now, it's our turn!  We've been doin' the runnin' away, but
now we'll do the chasin'!"  Apparently feeling some twinge of
nerves from the former strain, he suddenly demanded: "Say, who's
got any whiskey?  I'm near dead for a drink."

</p><p>When the <hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi> came about, she laid her course for
a position to the northward of a coming battle, but the situation
suddenly became complicated.  When the Spanish ships discovered the
identity of the ship that was steaming toward them they did not
hesitate over their plan of action.  With one accord they turned
and ran for port.  Laughter arose from the <hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi>.  The
captain broke his orders, and instead of keeping to the northward,
he headed in the wake of the impetuous <hi rend="italic">Chancellorville</hi>.  The
correspondents crowded on the bow.

</p><p>The Spaniards, when their broadsides became visible, were seen
to be ships of no importance&mdash;mere little gun-boats for work in the
shallows at the back of the reefs; and it was certainly discreet to
refuse encounter with the 5-inch guns of the
<hi rend="italic">Chancellorville</hi>.  But the joyful <hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi> took no
account of this discretion.  The pursuit of the Spaniards had been
so ferocious that the quick change to heels-over-head flight filled
that corner of the mind which is devoted to the spirit of revenge.
It was this that moved Shackles to yell taunts futilely at the
faraway ships.  "Well, how do you like it, eh?  How do you like
it?"  The <hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi> was drinking compensation for her
previous agony.

</p><p>The mountains of the shore now shadowed high into the sky, and
the square white houses of a town could be seen near a vague cleft
which seemed to mark the entrance to a port.  The gunboats were now
near to it.

</p><p>Suddenly white smoke streamed from the bow of the
<hi rend="italic">Chancellorville</hi> and developed swiftly into a great bulb
which drifted in fragments down the wind.  Presently the deep-throated boom of the gun came to the ears on board the
<hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi>.  The shot kicked up a high jet of water into the
air astern of the last gunboat.  The black smoke from the funnels
of the cruiser made her look like a collier on fire, and in her
desperation she tried many more long shots, but presently the
<hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi>, murmuring disappointment, saw the
<hi rend="italic">Chancellorville</hi> sheer from the chase.

</p><p>In time they came up with her, and she was an indignant ship.
Gloom and wrath was on the forecastle, and wrath and gloom was on the
quarter-deck.  A sad voice from the bridge said, "Just missed 'em."
Shackles gained permission to board the cruiser, and in the cabin he
talked to Lieutenant-Commander Surrey, tall, bald-headed and angry.

</p><p>"Shoals," said the captain of the <hi rend="italic">Chancellorville</hi>,  "I
can't go any nearer, and those gunboats could steam along a stone
sidewalk if only it was wet."  Then his bright eyes became
brighter.  "I tell you what!  The <hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Holy
Moses</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic">Mongolian</hi> are on station off Nuevitas.
If you will do me a favor&mdash;why, to-morrow I will give those people
a game!"</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="3" id="d6">
<head>III</head>


<p>THE <hi rend="italic">Chancellorville</hi> lay all night watching off the port
of the two gunboats, and soon after daylight, the lookout descried
three smokes to the westward, and they were later made out to be
the <hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Holy Moses</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi>,
the latter tagging hurriedly after the United States vessels.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi> had been a harbor tug, but she was now the
U.S.S. <hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi>, by your leave.  She carried a 6-pounder
forward and a 6-pounder aft, and her main point was her conspicuous
vulnerability.  The <hi rend="italic">Holy Moses</hi> had been the private yacht of
a Philadelphia millionnaire.  She carried six 6-pounders, and her
main point was the chaste beauty of the officers' quarters.

</p><p>On the bridge of the <hi rend="italic">Chancellorville</hi>, Lieutenant-Commander Surrey surveyed his squadron with considerable
satisfaction.  Presently he signalled to the lieutenant who
commanded the <hi rend="italic">Holy Moses</hi> and to the boatswain who commanded
the <hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi> to come aboard the flagship.  This was all very
well for the captain of the yacht, but it was not so easy for the
captain of the tugboat, who had two heavy lifeboats swung fifteen
feet above the water.  He had been accustomed to talking with
senior officers from his own pilot-house through the intercession
of the blessed megaphone.  However, he got a lifeboat over-side and
was pulled to the <hi rend="italic">Chancellorville</hi> by three men&mdash;which cut
his crew almost into halves.

</p><p>In the cabin of the <hi rend="italic">Chancellorville</hi>, Surrey disclosed to
his two captains his desires concerning the Spanish gunboats, and they
were glad of being ordered down from the Nuevitas station, where life
was very dull.  He also announced that there was a shore battery,
containing, he believed, four field-guns&mdash;three-decimal-twos.  His
draught&mdash;he spoke of it as his draught&mdash;would enable him to go in
close enough to engage the battery at moderate range, but he pointed
out that the main parts of the attempt to destroy the Spanish
gun-boats must be left to the <hi rend="italic">Holy Moses</hi> and the
<hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi>.  His business, he thought, could only be to keep the
air so singing about the ears of the battery that the men at the guns
would be unable to take an interest in the dash of the smaller
American craft into the bay.

</p><p>The officers spoke in their turns.  The commander of the
<hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi> announced that he saw no difficulties.  The squadron
would follow the flagship in line, ahead the flagship would engage
the batteries as soon as possible, she would turn to starboard when
the depth of water forced her to do so, and the <hi rend="italic">Holy Moses</hi>
and the <hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi> would run past her into the bay and fight
the Spanish ships wherever they were to be found.  The commander of
the <hi rend="italic">Holy Moses</hi>, after some moments of dignified thought,
said that he had no suggestions to make that would better this
plan.

</p><p>Surrey pressed an electric bell; a marine orderly appeared; he
was sent with a message.  The message brought the navigating
officer of the <hi rend="italic">Chancellorville</hi> to the cabin, and the four
men nosed over a chart.

</p><p>In the end Surrey declared that he had made up his mind, and
the juniors remained in expectant silence for three minutes while
he stared at the bulkhead.  Then he said that the plan of the
<hi rend="italic">Chicken's</hi> commander seemed to him correct in the main.  He
would make one change.  It was that he should first steam in and
engage the battery, and the other vessels should remain in their
present positions until he signalled them to run into the bay.  If
the squadron steamed ahead in line, the battery could, if it chose,
divide its fire between the flagship and the vessels constituting
the more important attack.  He had no doubt, he said, that he could
soon silence the battery by tumbling the earthworks on to the guns
and driving away the men, even if he did not succeed in hitting the
pieces.  Of course, he had no doubt of being able to silence the
battery in twenty minutes.  Then he would signal for the <hi rend="italic">Holy
Moses</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi> to make their rush, and of course
he would support them with his fire as much as conditions enabled
him.  He arose then, indicating that the conference was at an end.
In the few moments more that all four men remained in the cabin,
the talk changed its character completely.  It was now unofficial,
and the sharp badinage concealed furtive affections, academy
friendships, the feelings of old-time ship-mates, hiding everything
under a veil of jokes.  "Well, good luck to you, old boy!  Don't
get that valuable packet of yours sunk under you.  Think how it
would weaken the navy.  Would you mind buying me three pairs of
pajamas in the town yonder?  If your engines get disabled, tote her
under your arm.  You can do it.  Good-by, old man; don't forget to
come out all right."

</p><p>When the commanders of the <hi rend="italic">Holy Moses</hi> and the
<hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi> emerged from the cabin they strode the deck with a
new step.  They were proud men.  The marine on duty above their
boats looked at them curiously and with awe.  He detected something
which meant action, conflict.  The boats' crews saw it also.  As
they pulled their steady stroke they studied fleetingly the face of
the officer in the stern-sheets.  In both cases they perceived a
glad man, and yet a man filled with a profound consideration of the
future.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="4" id="d7">
<head>IV</head>


<p>A BIRD-LIKE whistle stirred the decks of the
<hi rend="italic">Chancellorville</hi>.  It was followed by the hoarse bellowings
of the boatswain's mate.  As the cruiser turned her bow toward the
shore, she happened to steam near the <hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi>.  The usual
calm voice hailed the despatch-boat.  "Keep&mdash;that&mdash;gauze undershirt
of yours&mdash;well&mdash;out of the&mdash;line of fire."

</p><p>"Ay, ay, sir!"

</p><p>The cruiser then moved slowly toward the shore, watched by
every eye in the smaller American vessels.  She was deliberate and
steady, and this was reasonable, even to the impatience of the
other craft, because the wooded shore was likely to suddenly
develop new factors.  Slowly she swung to starboard, smoke belched
over her, and the roar of a gun came along the water.

</p><p>The battery was indicated by a long, thin streak of yellow
earth.  The first shot went high, ploughing the chaparral on the
hillside.  The <hi rend="italic">Chancellorville</hi> wore an air for a moment of
being deep in meditation.  She flung another shell, which landed
squarely on the earth-work, making a great dun cloud.  Before the
smoke had settled, there was a crimson flash from the battery.  To
the watchers at sea, it was smaller than a needle.  The shot made
a geyser of crystal water, four hundred yards from the
<hi rend="italic">Chancellorville</hi>.

</p><p>The cruiser, having made up her mind, suddenly went at the
battery hammer and tongs.  She moved to and fro casually, but the
thunder of her guns was gruff and angry.  Sometimes she was quite
hidden in her own smoke, but with exceeding regularity the earth of
the battery spurted into the air.  The Spanish shells for the most
part went high and wide of the cruiser, jetting the water far away.

</p><p>Once a Spanish gunner took a festive side-show chance at the
waiting group of the three ships.  It went like a flash over the
<hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi>, singing a wistful, metallic note.  Whereupon the
<hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi> broke hurriedly for the open sea, and men on the
<hi rend="italic">Holy Moses</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi> laughed hoarsely and
cruelly.  The correspondents had been standing excitedly on top of the
pilot-house, but at the passing of the shell they promptly eliminated
themselves by dropping with a thud to the deck below.  The cook again
was giving tongue.  "Oh, say, this won't do!  Oh, this ain't no good!
We ain't no armored cruiser, you know.  If one of them shells hits
us&mdash;well, we finish right there.  'Tain't like as if it was our
business, foolin' round within the range of them guns.  There's no
sense in it.  Them other fellows don't seem to mind it, but it's their
business.  If it's your <hi rend="italic">business</hi>, you go ahead and do it; but
if it ain't, you&mdash;look at that, would you?"

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Chancellorville</hi> had set up a spread of flags, and
the <hi rend="italic">Holy Moses</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi> were steaming in.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="5" id="d8">
<head>V</head>


<p>THEY on the <hi rend="italic">Chancellorville</hi> sometimes could see into
the bay, and they perceived the enemy's gunboats moving out as if
to give battle.  Surrey feared that this impulse would not endure,
or that it was some mere pretence for the edification of the
townspeople and the garrison, so he hastily directed that signals
be made ordering in  the <hi rend="italic">Holy Moses</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi>.
Thankful for small favors, they came on like charging horsemen.
The battery had ceased firing.  As the two auxiliaries passed under
the stern of the cruiser, the megaphone hailed them:  "You&mdash;will&mdash;
see&mdash;the&mdash;en&mdash;e&mdash;my&mdash;soon&mdash;as&mdash;you&mdash;round&mdash;the&mdash;point.  A&mdash;fine&mdash;
chance.  Good&mdash;luck."

</p><p>As a matter of fact, the Spanish gunboats had not been
informed of the presence of the <hi rend="italic">Holy Moses</hi> and the
<hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi> off the bar, and they were just blustering down the
bay over the protective shoals to make it appear that they scorned
the <hi rend="italic">Chancellorville</hi>.  But suddenly from around the point
there burst into view a steam yacht, closely followed by a harbor
tug.  The gunboats took one swift look at this horrible sight, and
fled screaming.

   <pb n="19"/>


</p><p>Lieutenant Reigate, commanding the <hi rend="italic">Holy Moses</hi>, had
under his feet a craft that was capable of some speed, although
before a solemn tribunal one would have to admit that she
conscientiously belied almost everything that the contractors had
said of her originally.  Boatswain Pent, commanding the
<hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi>, was in possession of an utterly different kind.
The <hi rend="italic">Holy Moses</hi> was an antelope; the <hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi> was a man
who could carry a piano on his back.  In this race Pent had the
mortification of seeing his vessel outstripped badly.

</p><p>The entrance of the two American craft had a curious effect
upon the shores of the bay.  Apparently every one had slept in the
assurance that the <hi rend="italic">Chancellorville</hi> could not cross the bar, and
that the <hi rend="italic">Chancellorville</hi> was the only hostile ship.
Consequently the appearance of the <hi rend="italic">Holy Moses</hi> and the
<hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi> created a curious and complete emotion.  Reigate on the
bridge of the <hi rend="italic">Holy Moses</hi> laughed when he heard the bugles
shrilling, and saw through his glasses the wee figures of men running
hither and thither on the shore.  It was the panic of the china when
the bull entered the shop.  The whole bay was bright with sun.  Every
detail of the shore was plain.  From a brown hut abeam of the <hi rend="italic">Holy
Moses</hi> some little men ran out waving their arms and turning their
tiny faces to look at the enemy.  Directly ahead, some four miles,
appeared the scattered white houses of a town, with a wharf and some
schooners in front of it.  The gunboats were making for the town.
There was a stone fort on the hill overshadowing, but Reigate
conjectured that there was no artillery in it.

</p><p>There was a sense of something intimate and impudent in the
minds of the Americans.  It was like climbing over a wall and
fighting a man in his own garden.  It was not that they could be in
any wise shaken in their resolve; it was simply that the
overwhelmingly Spanish aspect of things made them feel like gruff
intruders.  Like many of the emotions of war-time, this emotion had
nothing at all to do with war.

</p><p>Reigate's only commissioned subordinate called up from the bow
gun, "May I open fire, sir?  I think I can fetch that last one."

</p><p>"Yes."

</p><p>Immediately the 6-pounder crashed, and in the air was the
spinning wire noise of the flying shot.  It struck so close to the
last gun-boat that it appeared that the spray went aboard.  The
swift-handed men at the gun spoke of it: "Gave 'em a bath that time
anyhow.  First one they've ever had.  Dry 'em off this time, Jim."

</p><p>The young ensign said: "Steady."  And so the <hi rend="italic">Holy Moses</hi>
raced in, firing, until the whole town, water-front and shipping
was as plain as if it had been done on paper by a mechanical
draughts-man.  The gunboats were trying to hide in the bosom of the
town.  One was frantically tying up to the wharf, and the other was
anchoring within a hundred yards of the shore.  The Spanish
infantry, of course, had dug trenches along the beach, and suddenly
the air over the <hi rend="italic">Holy Moses</hi> sang with bullets.  The shore-line thrummed with musketry; also some antique shells screamed.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="6" id="d9">
<head>VI</head>

<p>THE <hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi> was doing her best.  Pent's posture at the
wheel seemed to indicate that her best was about thirty-four knots.
In his eagerness he was braced as if he alone was taking in a
10,000-ton battleship through Hellgate.

</p><p>But the <hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi> was not too far in the rear, and Pent
could see clearly that he was to have no minor part to play.  Some
of the antique shells had struck the <hi rend="italic">Holy Moses</hi>, and he
could see the escaped steam shooting up from her.  She lay close
inshore, and was lashing out with four 6-pounders as if this was
the last opportunity she would have to fire them.  She had made the
Spanish gunboats very sick.  A solitary gun on the one moored to
the wharf was from time to time firing wildly, otherwise the
gunboats were silent.  But the beach in front of the town was a
line of fire.  The <hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi> headed for the <hi rend="italic">Holy Moses</hi>,
and, as soon as possible, the 6-pounder in her bow began to crack
at the gunboat moored to the wharf.

</p><p>In the meantime the <hi rend="italic">Chancellorville</hi> prowled off the
bar, listening to the firing, anxious, acutely anxious, and feeling
her impotency in every inch of her smart, steel frame.  And in the
meantime the <hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi> squatted on the waves and brazenly
waited for news.  One could thoughtfully count the seconds, and
reckon that in this second and that second a man had died&mdash;if one
chose.  But no one did it.


   <pb n="24"/>


</p><p>Undoubtedly the spirit was that the flag should come away with
honor, honor complete, perfect leaving no loose unfinished end over
which the Spaniards could erect a monument of satisfaction,
glorification.  The distant guns boomed to the ears of the silent
blue-jackets at their stations on the cruiser.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi> steamed up to the <hi rend="italic">Holy Moses</hi> and
took into her nostrils the odor of steam, gunpowder and burned
things.  Rifle-bullets simply streamed over them both.  In the
merest flash of time, Pent took into his remembrance the body of a
dead quartermaster on the bridge of his consort.  The two
megaphones lifted together, but Pent's eager voice cried out first:
"Are you injured, sir?"

</p><p>"No, not completely.  My engines can get me out after&mdash;after
we have sunk those gunboats."  The voice had been utterly
conventional, but it changed to sharpness:  "Go in and sink that
gunboat at anchor."

</p><p>As the <hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi> rounded the <hi rend="italic">Holy Moses</hi> and started
inshore, a man called to him from the depths of finished disgust:
"They're takin' to their boats, sir."  Pent looked and saw the men of
the anchored gunboat lower their boats and pull like mad for shore.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi>, assisted by the <hi rend="italic">Holy Moses</hi>, began
a methodical killing of the anchored gunboat.  The Spanish infantry
on shore fired frenziedly at the <hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi>.  Pent, giving the
wheel to a waiting sailor, stepped out to a point where he could
see the men at the guns.  One bullet spanged past him and into the
pilot-house.  He ducked his head into the window.  "That hit you,
Murry?" he inquired with interest.

</p><p>"No, sir," cheerfully responded the man at the wheel.

</p><p>Pent became very busy superintending the fire of his absurd
battery.  The anchored gun-boat simply would not sink.  It evinced
that unnatural stubbornness which is sometimes displayed by
inanimate objects.  The gunboat at the wharf had sunk as if she had
been scuttled, but this riddled thing at anchor would not even take
fire.  Pent began to grow flurried&mdash;privately.  He could not stay
there forever.  Why didn't the pig-headed gunboat admit its
destruction?  Why&mdash;

</p><p>He was at the forward gun when one of his engineers came to
him, and after saluting, said serenely: "The men at the after-gun
are all down, sir."

</p><p>It was one of those curious lifts which an enlisted man,
without in any way knowing it, can give his officer.  The impudent
tranquillity of the man at once set Pent to rights, and the
engineer departed admiring the extraordinary coolness of his
captain.

</p><p>The next few moments contained little but heat, an odor,
applied mechanics, and an expectation of death.  Pent developed a
fervid and amazed appreciation of the men, his men: men he knew
very well, but strange men.  What explained them?  He was doing his
best because he was captain of the <hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi>, and he lived or
died by the <hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi>.  But what could move these men to watch
his eye in bright anticipation of his orders, and then obey them
with enthusiastic rapidity?  What caused them to speak of the
action as some kind of joke&mdash;particularly when they knew he could
overhear them?  What manner of men?  And he anointed them secretly
with his fullest affection.

</p><p>Perhaps Pent did not think all this during the battle.
Perhaps he thought it so soon after the battle that his full mind
became confused as to the time.  At any rate, it stands as an
expression of his feeling.

</p><p>The enemy had gotten a field-gun down to the shore, and with
it, they began to throw 3-inch shells at the <hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi>.  In this
war it was usual that the down-trodden Spaniards, in their ignorance,
should use smokeless powder, while the Americans, by the power of the
consistent, everlasting, three-ply, wire-woven, double-back-action
imbecility of a hayseed government, used powder which on sea and on
land cried their position to heaven; and accordingly, good men got
killed without reason.  At first, Pent could not locate the field-gun
at all; but as soon as he found it, he ran aft with one man and
brought the after 6-pounder again into action.  He paid little heed to
the old gun-crew.  One was lying on his face apparently dead; another
was prone, with a wound in the chest; while the third sat with his
back to the deck-house holding a smitten arm.  This last one called
out huskily, "Give 'em hell, sir."

</p><p>The minutes of the battle were either days, years, or they
were flashes of a second.  Once Pent, looking up, was astonished to
see three shell holes in the <hi rend="italic">Chicken's</hi> funnel&mdash;made
surreptitiously, so to speak.  "If we don't silence that field-gun she'll sink us, boys."  The eyes of the man sitting with his
back against the deck-house were looking from out his ghastly face
at the new gun-crew.  He spoke with the supreme laziness of a
wounded man:  "Give 'em hell."  Pent felt a sudden twist of his
shoulder.  He was wounded&mdash;slightly.  The anchored gunboat was in
flames.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="7" id="d10">
<head>VII</head>


<p>PENT took his little bloodstained towboat out to the <hi rend="italic">Holy
Moses</hi>.  The yacht was already under way for the bay entrance.
As they    <pb n="25"/>   were passing out of range, the Spaniards heroically
redoubled their fire&mdash;which is their custom.  Pent, moving busily
about the decks, stopped suddenly at the door of the engine-room.
His face was set and his eyes were steely.  He spoke to one of the
engineers.  "During the action I saw you firing at the enemy with
a rifle.  I told you once to stop, and then I saw you at it again.
Pegging away with a rifle is no part of your business.  I want you
to understand that you are in trouble."  The humbled man did not
raise his eyes from the deck.  Presently the <hi rend="italic">Holy Moses</hi>
displayed an anxiety for the <hi rend="italic">Chicken's</hi> health.

</p><p>"One killed and four wounded, sir."

</p><p>"Have you enough men left to work your ship?"

</p><p>After deliberation Pent answered, "No, sir."

</p><p>"Shall I send you assistance?"

</p><p>"No, sir.  I can get to sea all right."

</p><p>As they neared the point they were edified by the sudden
appearance of a serio-comic ally.  The <hi rend="italic">Chancellorville</hi> at last
had been unable to stand the strain, and sent in her launch with an
ensign, five seamen, and a number of marksmen marines.  She swept
hotfoot around the point, bent on terrible slaughter; the 1-pounder
of her bow presented a formidable appearance.  The <hi rend="italic">Holy Moses</hi>
and the <hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi> laughed until they brought indignation to the
brow of the young ensign.  But he forgot it when with some of his men
he boarded the <hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi> to do what was possible for the
wounded.  The nearest surgeon was aboard the <hi rend="italic">Chancellorville</hi>.
There was absolute silence on board the cruiser as the <hi rend="italic">Holy
Moses</hi> steamed up to report.  The blue-jackets listened with all
their ears.  The commander of the yacht spoke slowly into his
megaphone: "We have&mdash;destroyed&mdash;the two&mdash; gunboats&mdash;sir."

</p><p>There was a burst of confused cheering on the forecastle of
the <hi rend="italic">Chancellorville</hi>, but an officer's cry quelled it.

</p><p>"Very&mdash;good.  Will&mdash;you&mdash;come aboard?"

</p><p>Correspondents were already on the deck of the cruiser, and
although for a time they learned only that the navy can preserve a
classic silence, they in the end received the story which is here
told.  Before the last of the wounded were hoisted aboard the
cruiser the <hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi> was on her way to Key West.  When she
arrived at that port of desolation, Shackles fled to file the
telegrams and the other correspondents fled to the hotel for
clothes, good clothes, clean clothes; and food, good food, much
food; and drink, much drink, any kind of drink.

</p><p>Days afterward, when the officers of the noble squadron
received the newspapers containing an account of their performance
they looked at each other somewhat dejectedly: "Heroic assault&mdash;
grand daring of Boatswain Pent&mdash;superb accuracy of the <hi rend="italic">Holy
Moses'</hi> fire&mdash;gallant tars of the <hi rend="italic">Chicken</hi>&mdash;their names
should be remembered as long as America stands&mdash;terrible losses of
the enemy&mdash;"

</p><p>When the Secretary of the Navy ultimately read the report of
Lieutenant-Commander Surrey he had to prick himself with a dagger
in order to remember that anything at all out of the ordinary had
occurred.</p>

<p>THE END</p>

</div2>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
