<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CraBoer"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="CraBoer">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Great Boer Trek</title>
<title type="sort">great boer trek</title>
<author>Crane, Stephen, 1871-1900</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">30</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CraBoer</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475838</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Great Boer Trek</title>
<title level="j">Cosmopolitan</title>
<title type="sort">great boer trek</title>
<author>Stephen Crane</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>Volume 29, 1900</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Hearst Corp.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Text originally published in Cosmopolitan 29 (June 1900)</p>
</note>
<note>
<p>Note [Judy Boss]:  On page 155, line 49, changed "hight"
to "height"; on page 157, line 46, changed "Umkunguhloon" to
"Umkungunhloon."</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions
for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-04">April 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Matthew G. Kirschenbaum, University of Virginia Library
Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI.2-conformant header and tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="work" id="d3"><pb n="153"/>
<head>THE GREAT BOER TREK.<lb/>
BY STEPHEN CRANE.</head>

<p>WHEN, in 1806, Cape Colony finally passed into the hands of the
British government, it might well have seemed possible for the
white inhabitants to dwell harmoniously together.  The Dutch
burghers were in race much the same men who had peopled England and
Scotland.  There was none of that strong racial and religious
antipathy which seems to make forever impossible any lasting
understanding between Ireland and her dominating partner.</p>
     <p>The Boers were more devoid of Celtic fervors and fluctuations
of temperament than the English themselves; in religion Protestant,
by nature hard-working, thrifty, independent, they would naturally,
it seems, have called for the good will and respect of their
conquerors.  But the two peoples seemed to have been keenly aware
of each other's failings from the first.  To the Boers, the English
seemed prejudiced and arrogant beyond mortal privilege; the English
told countless tales of the Boers' trickery, their dullness, their
boasting, their indolence, their bigotry.  The burghers had
transplanted the careful habits of their home in the Netherlands to
a different climate and new conditions.  In South Africa they were
still industrious and thrifty, and their somewhat gloomy religion
was more strongly rooted than ever.  Although they lived nomadic
lives on the frontier, yet they had made themselves substantial
dwellings within the towns; the streets were blossoming bowers of
trees and shrubs; their flocks and herds increased, their fields
produced mightily.  In the courts of law they had shown conspicuous
ability whilst acting as heemraden; they had made good elders and
deacons in their churches, and good commandants and field cornets
in war&mdash;the ever-recurring conflicts with the Kaffirs.</p>
     <p>Many observers have noted the strong similarity of thought and
character between the Dutchmen and the Scotchmen.  There is the
same thrift which is often extreme parsimony, combined with great
hospitality, the same dogged obstinacy, and the same delight in
overreaching in all matters of business and bargain-driving.
Moreover, their religious ideals bear the strongest resemblance one
to the other.  In his character as a colonist the Boer certainly
showed magnificent qualities; he could work and endure and fight.
But in spite of his dour sanctimoniousness, he was not a perfect
person, any more than his brother Briton.  The English missionaries
objected to his treatment of the natives, but there was never any
of the terrible cruelty practised that the Spaniards used toward
the natives during their colonization of Mexico&mdash;nor that of
various French, English and Portuguese adventurers in Africa during
the seventeenth century.  But the fact remains that the entire race
of Hottentots has been modified through the Dutch occupation; it is
said that no pure-blooded Hottentot remains.  This amalgamation was
treated by the Boers as a commonplace thing.  That habit of theirs
of producing scriptural authority for all their acts must have
begun with their settlement in Cape Colony.</p><p>
     The "bastards," as they were openly called, were well treated,
brought up as Christians and to lead a tolerably civilized life.
The English missionaries were filled with disgust at this state of
things, and the Boers were denounced from missionary platforms
throughout England.  Undoubtedly the missionaries were right, but
the Boers, alas, are not the only white race who have taken this
patriarchal attitude toward the natives of the country they were
engaged in colonizing.  The missionaries in their other charges
were fanatical and ridiculous; they described the Boers as cruel
barbarians, because they would not allow the vermin-haunted
Hottentots to join them at family prayers in their "best rooms."
The Colonial office acted on these representations, and refused to
listen to any complaints of the Boers.  As they numbered less than
ten thousand, and English emigrants were constantly pouring into
the colony, the Boers were considered of little importance to the
government; it was not imagined that they could do anything
effectual in the way of resistance.  In short, they, who had been
the ruling race in the colony for over a century, were now
<pb n="154"/>
a subject race; they were hampered and restricted on every side.</p><p>
     The first grievance of the Boers was the attitude of the
English missionaries.  Some of these were men of really high
religious ideals, but most of them were politicians.  Mr.
Vanderkemp and Mr. Read, missionaries of the London society, who
had taken black wives, and announced themselves champions of the
black race against the white, had sent to England reports of a
number of murders and outrages said to have been committed upon
Hottentots by the Dutch colonists.  By order of the British
government fifty-eight white men and women were put upon their
trial for these crimes in 1812, and over a thousand witnesses,
black and white, were called to give evidence.  Several cases of
assault were proved, and punished, but none of the serious charges
was substantiated.  In 1814 a farmer, Frederick Bezuidenhout,
quarreled with his native servant, and refused to appear at a court
of justice to answer the charge of ill treatment.  A company of
Hottentots was sent to arrest him; he fired on them and they shot
him dead.  A company of about fifty men joined an insurrection
under the leadership of Bezuidenhout's brother Jan, but a strong
force of Boers aided the government in putting down this rebellion;
all surrendered but Jan, who was shot and killed.</p><p>
     Lord Charles Somerset, who drew a salary of ten thousand
pounds a year, with four residences, was Governor at the time.  He
was arbitrary as a prince, and afterward suppressed a liberal
newspaper and forbade public meetings.  The prisoners taken were
tried&mdash;they were thirty-nine in number&mdash;and six were sentenced to
death, while the others all received some form of punishment.
Somerset was entreated to annul the death sentence, but would do so
only in one instance.  The remaining five were executed in the
presence of their friends, and the scaffold broke with their
weight; they were all unconscious and were resuscitated.  When they
had been brought to consciousness their friends vehemently besought
Somerset to reprieve them, but he was firm in his refusal and they
were hanged again.</p><p>
     This event caused a lasting bitterness among the Boers; the
place of execution is known as Slachter's Nek to this day.  In
1823, the Dutch courts of justice were abolished with their
landrosts and heemraden, and in the place of them English courts
were established, with magistrates, civil commissioners and
justices of the peace.  The burgher senate was abolished, also, and
notices were sent to the old colonists that all documents addressed
to the government must be written in English.  Soon after, a case
was to be tried at the circuit court at Worcester, and one of the
judges removed it to Cape Town because there was not a sufficient
number of English-speaking men to form a jury, though the prisoner
and the witnesses could speak Dutch only, and whatever they said
had to be translated in court.  The judges were divided in their
opinion as to whether it were necessary for every juryman to speak
English; in 1831 an ordinance was issued defining the
qualifications of jurymen and a knowledge of English was not one of
them.  But in the mean time the Boers had been greatly embittered
by their exclusion from the jury-box.  They would not write
memorials about it to the government, because they refused to write
English.</p><p>
     During the years of English occupation the frontier
aggressions of the Kaffirs were of frequent occurrence.  The
document called, "An Earnest Representation and Historical Reminder
to H. M. Queen Victoria, in view of the Present Crisis, by P. J.
Joubert," published a few months ago, contains this reference to
the frontier wars: "Natives molested them [the Boers]; they were
murdered, robbed of their cattle, their homes were laid waste.
Unspeakable horrors were inflicted on their wives and daughters.
The Boer was called out for commando service at his own expense,
under command and control of the British, to fight the Kaffirs.
While on commando, his cattle were stolen by Kaffirs.  After, they
were made to wait until troops re-took the cattle, which were
afterward publicly sold as lost in the presence of their owners,
the Boers being informed that they should receive compensation&mdash;not
in money or goods, neither in rest nor peace, but instead,
indignities and abuse were heaped on them.  They were told that
they should be satisfied at not being punished as the instigators
of the disturbance."</p><pb n="155"/>
     <p>As far back as 1809, Hottentots were prohibited from wandering
about the country without passes, and from 1812, Hottentot children
who had been maintained for eight years by the employers of their
parents, were bound as apprenticed for ten years longer.  The
missionaries were dissatisfied with these restrictions; both of
them were removed by an ordinance passed July, 1828, when vagrant
Hottentots began to wander over the country at will.  Farming
became almost impossible; the farm-laborers became vagabonds and
petty thefts took place constantly.</p><p>
     Early in 1834, Sir Benjamin D'Urban, called "the Good," was
appointed Governor.  A legislative council was then granted the
colony, but its powers were not great.</p><p>
     The Boers had never been greatly in favor (many opposed it
strongly) of slavery, but they had yielded to the general custom
and over three million pounds was invested in slaves throughout the
colony in 1834.  Sir Benjamin D'Urban proclaimed the emancipation
of the slaves, who had been set free throughout the British Empire,
in August, 1833.  This freeing was to take effect in Cape Colony on
the 1st of December, 1834.</p><p>
     The news of the emancipation was felt to be a relief, but the
terms on which it was conducted were productive of unending
trouble.  The slave-owners of Cape Colony were awarded less than a
million and a quarter for their slaves&mdash;and the imperial government
refused to send the money to South Africa; each claim was to be
proved before commissioners in London, when the amount would be
paid in stock.  To make a journey of one hundred days to London
was, of course, impossible to the farmers; they were at the mercy
of agents who made their way down to the colony and purchased the
claims, so that the colonist received sometimes a fifth, sometimes
a sixth, or less, of the value of his slaves.  The colonists had
hoped that a vagrant act would have been passed by the Council when
the slaves were freed, to keep them from being still further
overrun by this large released black population, but this was not
done.</p><p>
     In 1834, the first band of emigrants left the colony&mdash;forty-five men under a leader named Louis Triechard, from the division of
Albany.  He was a violent-tempered man, and so loudly opposed to
the government that Col. Harry Smith offered a reward of five
hundred cattle for his apprehension.  He left then at once, being
of the class of Boers on the frontier who lived in their wagons, as
though they were ships at sea, and had no settled habitation.  His
party was joined, before it left the colonial border, by Johannes
Rensburg.  Together they had thirty wagons.  They traveled
northward.  All but two of Rensburg's party were killed, and those
of Triechard's party who escaped the savages reached Delagoa Bay in
1838, after terrible hardships, where they received great kindness
from the Portuguese.  But their sufferings had been so great that
only twenty-six lived to be shipped to Natal.  But before the
emigration reached its height another Kaffir war came on.  There
was a tremendous invasion of savages, between twelve and twenty
thousand warriors, who swept along the frontier, killing,
plundering and burning.  December, 1834, under Col. Harry Smith a
large force was raised; they marched into Kaffirland, and defeated
and dispersed the invaders, who were compelled to sue for peace.
As a security for the future, Sir Benjamin D'Urban, who was also at
the front, issued a proclamation, declaring British sovereignty to
be extended over the territory of the defeated tribes as far as the
Kei River.  But while the people were still suffering from the
effects of the invasion, an order came from Lord Glenelg&mdash;who
became Secretary of State for the Colonies in April, 1835&mdash;
peremptorily ordering that the new territory must be immediately
given up, on the ground that it had been unjustly acquired.</p><p>
     The Boers now felt that no security existed for life or
property on the frontier; all the support of the British government
was given&mdash;with a philanthropy stimulated by the missionaries&mdash;to
the black races as against the Boer farmers.  The feeling had now
become general among them that they must escape British rule at any
cost.  They left their homes and cultivated fields and gardens&mdash;the
homes of over a century's growth&mdash;and started into the wilds.
Purchases of the vacated property <pb n="156"/> were not frequent; a
house sometimes was sold for an ox; many of them were simply left,
with no sale having been made.  All over the frontier districts the
great wagons set out, loaded with household goods, provisions and
ammunition, to seek new homes farther north.  Each party had its
commandant and was generally made up of families related to each
other.  When the pasturage was good, the caravans would sometimes
rest for weeks together, while the cows and oxen, horses and sheep
and goats, grazed.  General Joubert declares that they were
followed as far as the Orange River by British emissaries who
wanted to be sure that they took no arms nor ammunition with them.
However, he adds, the Boers were able to <hi rend="italic">conceal</hi> their
weapons&mdash;a fact that seems a very modern instance, indeed.</p><p>
     North of the Orange River the colonists regarded themselves as
quite free, for Great Britain had declared officially that she
would not enlarge her South African possessions.</p><p>
     The emigrants were ridiculed for leaving their homes for the
wilderness&mdash;"for freedom and grass," and were called professional
squatters.  One English writer said: "The frontier Boer looks with
pity on the busy hives of humanity in cities, or even in villages;
and regarding with disdain the grand, but to him unintelligible,
results of combined industry, the beauty and excellence of which he
cannot know, because they are intellectually discerned, he tosses
up his head like a wild horse, utters a neigh of exultation, and
plunges into the wilderness."</p><p>
     The number of "trekkers" has been estimated at from five
thousand to ten thousand.  The tide of emigration (they went
generally in small bands) flowed across the Orange River and then
followed a course for some distance parallel with the Quathtamba
Mountains.  By this route the warlike Kaffirs were evaded, the only
native tribes passed through being small disorganized bodies.  Near
the Vaal River, however, resided the powerful Matabele nation,
under the famous Moselekatze, a warrior of Zulu birth, who had
established himself there and brought into complete subjection all
the neighboring tribes.</p><p>
     One band of emigrants under Commandant Hendrik Potgieter, a
man of considerable ability, arrived at the banks of the Vet River,
a tributary of the Vaal.  Here he found a native chief who lived in
constant dread of Moselekatze, who sold to Potgieter the land
between the Vet and the Vaal Rivers, for a number of cattle,
Potgieter guaranteeing him protection from Moselekatze.  After a
while, Commandant Potgieter, with a party, went to explore the
country, and traveled north to the Zoutpansberg, where the
fertility of the soil seemed encouraging.  They also believed that
communication with the outer world could be opened through Delagoa
Bay, so that the country seemed to offer every advantage for
settlement.  In high spirits they came back to rejoin their
families, but a hideous surprise awaited them; they found only
mutilated corpses.  Expecting an immediate return of the Matabele
who had massacred his people, Potgieter made a strong laager on a
hill, by lashing fifty wagons together in a circle, and filling all
the open spaces, except a narrow entrance, with thorn-trees.
Presently the Matabele returned, and with great shouts and yells
stormed the camp, rushing up to the wagon-wheels and throwing
assegais.  But the Boers, with their powerful "roers," or elephant-guns, kept such a rapid and skilful fire, while the women kept the
spare guns reloaded, that the Matabele were forced to retire, but
they drove with them all the cattle of the party.  They left one
hundred and fifty-five dead, and one thousand one hundred of their
spears were afterward picked up.</p><p>
     The emigrants in the laager were left without the means of
transportation, and very little food, while they had lost forty-six
of their people.  But fortunately they were near the third band of
emigrants under Commandant Gerrit Maritz, who encamped near the
mission station at Thaba Ntshu, and now sent oxen to carry away
Potgieter and the others.  Also a native chief, Marroco, brought
them milk and Kaffir corn, and pack-oxen to help them away.  It was
resolved to revenge the massacre, to follow up Moselekatze and
punish him.  One hundred and seven Boers mustered for this service,
besides forty half-breeds, and a few blacks to take care of the
horses.  A deserter from the <pb n="157"/>  Matabele army acted as guide.
The commando surprised Mosega, one of the principal military towns,
and killed four hundred.  Then setting fire to the kraal, they
drove seven thousand head of cattle back to Thaba Ntshu.
Potgieter's party then formed a camp on the Vet (they called it
Winburg), which was joined by many families from the colony.
Another band soon reached Thaba Ntshu, under Pieter Retief, a man
of great intelligence.  June 6th, 1837, a general assembly of Boers
was held at Winburg, when a provisional constitution, consisting of
nine articles, was adopted.  The supreme legislative power was
intrusted to a single elective chamber, termed the Volksraad, the
fundamental law was declared to be the Dutch, a court of landrost
and heemraden was created, and the chief executive authority was
given to Retief, with the title of Commandant-General.  One article
provided that all who joined the community must have no connection
with the London Missionary Society.</p><p>
     New bands of emigrants were constantly arriving, and some of
them wished to go into Natal, although the condition of the camp at
Winburg was very satisfactory.  Pieter Uys, one of their leaders,
had visited Natal before, and had been impressed with its beauty
and fertility.  Retief finally decided to go and see for himself if
Dingaan, the Zulu chief, would dispose of some land below the
mountain.</p><p>
     While he was gone, a second expedition against the Matabele
set out, consisting of one hundred and thirty-five farmers, under
Potgieter and Pieter Uys.  They found Mosega with twelve thousand
warriors, brave and finely trained, but at the end of nine days'
warfare, Moselekatze fled to the north, after a loss of something
like one thousand men.  Commandant Potgieter now issued a
proclamation declaring that the whole of the territory overrun by
the Matabele, and now abandoned by them, was forfeited to the
Boers.  It included the greater part of the present South African
Republic, fully half of the present Orange Free State, and the
whole of Southern Bechuanaland to the Kalahari Desert, except that
part occupied by the Batlapin.  This immense tract of land was then
almost uninhabited, and must have remained so if the Matabele had
not been driven out.</p><p>
     Much has been written of the beauties of Natal, with its
shores washed by the Indian Ocean, its rich soil, luxuriant
vegetation and noble forests.  When Pieter Retief first saw it from
the Drakensberg Mountains, it was under the despotic rule of the
Zulu chief Dingaan, who had succeeded Tshaka, the "Napoleon of
Africa," the slayer of a million human beings.  A few Englishmen,
who were allowed to live at the port, gladly welcomed the
emigrants, and took them to Dingaan's capital, called
Umkungunhloon, acting as guides and interpreters.  There was an
English missionary clergyman living there, called Owen.  Dingaan
received them graciously and supplied them with chunks of beef from
his own eating-mat, and huge calabashes of millet beer.  But when
Retief spoke about Natal, the despot set him a task, such as one
reads of in folk-lore legends.  Retief might have Natal for his
countrymen to live in, if he would recover a herd of seven hundred
cattle that had been recently stolen from him by Sikouyela, a
Mantater chief.  Retief accepted the condition, and actually made
Sikouyela restore the cattle, which he drove back to Dingaan.  The
Boers at Winburg felt distrustful of Dingaan, and dreaded to have
Pieter Retief trust himself again in the tyrant's hands.  But in
February, 1838, Retief started with seventy persons, armed and
mounted, with thirty attendants.  Again Dingaan received them
hospitably, and empowered the missionary Owen to draw up a document
granting to Retief the country between the Tugela and the
Umzimvooboo.  But just as the emigrants were ready to leave, they
were invited into a cattle-kraal to see a war-dance, and requested
to leave their arms outside the door.  While sitting down they were
overpowered and massacred, the horror-stricken Owen being a witness
of the sight.</p><p>
     Immediately after the massacre, Dingaan sent out his forces
against all the emigrants on the eastern side of the Drakensberg.
Before daylight they attacked the encampments at Blaanwkrauz River
and the Bush-man River&mdash;ten miles apart.  It was a complete
surprise and a terrible slaughter of the Boers, although a brave
defense was made.  The township which has since arisen near the
scene of the conflict still <pb n="158"/>  bears the name of Weemen&mdash;the
place of wailing.</p><p>
     As soon as the emigrants on the west of the Drakensberg heard
of the disasters, they formed a band of about eight hundred men to
punish Dingaan for his treachery.  But they were led into ambush,
and finally defeated by the Zulus, and forced to retreat after a
tremendous loss of life.  The condition of the emigrants was now
one of terrible distress and privation.  They had many widows and
orphans to provide for.  The Governor of Cape Colony sent word to
them to return, and there were many who felt willing to go, but it
was the women of the party who sternly refused to go back; they
preferred liberty, although that liberty had cost them so dear.  In
November, 1838, Andries Pretorius arrived in Natal from Graaff
Reinet and was at once elected Commandant-General.  He organized a
force of four hundred and sixty-four men and marched toward
Umkungunhloon.  He took with him a sufficient number of wagons to
form a laager; wherever the camp was pitched it was surrounded by
fifty-seven wagons; all the cattle were brought within the
inclosure, the whole force joining in prayers and the singing of
psalms.  The army made a vow that if victorious they would build a
church, and set apart a thanksgiving day each year to commemorate
it.  The church in Pietermaritzburg and the annual celebration of
Dingaan's bear witness that they kept their pledge.  They were not
fighting for revenge.  On three occasions the scouts brought in
some captured Zulus, and Pretorius sent them back to Dingaan to say
that if he would restore the land he had granted Retief he would
enter into negotiations for peace.</p><p>
     Dingaan's reply came in the form of an army ten thousand or
twelve thousand strong, which attacked the camp on December 16,
1838.  For two hours the Zulus tried to force their way into the
laager, while the Boer guns and the small artillery made dreadful
havoc in their ranks.  When at length they broke and fled, over
three thousand Zulu corpses lay on the ground and a stream that
flowed through the battle-field was crimson.  It has been known
ever since as the Blood River.</p><p>
     Pretorius marched on to Umkungunhloon as soon as possible, but
Dingaan had set the place on fire and fled.</p><p>
     Dingaan, with the remainder of his forces, retired farther
into Zululand.  There, soon after, his brother, Pauda, revolted,
and fled with a large following into Natal, where he sought the
protection of the Boers.  Another and final expedition was made
against Dingaan in January, 1840, the farmers having Pauda with
four thousand of his best warriors as an ally.  By February 10th,
Dingaan was a fugitive in the country of a hostile tribe, who soon
killed him, and the emigrant farmers were the conquerors of
Zululand.  On that day Pauda was appointed and declared to be "King
of the Zulus" in the name and behalf of the Volksraad at
Pietermaritzburg, where the Boers established their seat of
government as "The South African Society of Natal."</p><p>
     Four days afterward, a proclamation was issued at the same
camp, signed by Pretorius and four commandants under him, declaring
all the territory between the Black Imfolosi and the Umzimvooboo
Rivers to belong to the emigrant farmers.  "The national flag was
hoisted," says a chronicler, "a salute of twenty-one guns fired,
and a general hurrah given throughout the whole army, while all the
men as with one voice called out: 'Thanks to the great God who by
his grace has given us the victory!'"</p><p>
     Now that the "trekkers" had freed South Africa from the
destructive Zulu power, and had driven the Matabele away, they
wished to settle in Natal, and rest from the nomadic existence that
had so long been theirs.  But the British now came forward to hunt
them on again.  The Governor of Cape Colony, Sir George Napier,
proclaimed that "the occupation of Natal by the emigrants was
unwarrantable," and directed that "all arms and ammunition should
be taken from them, and the port closed against trade."</p><p>
     What followed&mdash;the British bombardment of the port, the Dutch
surrender, are well-known facts of history.  May 12, 1848, Natal
was proclaimed a British colony, and the emigrants again took to
their wagons, crossing the Vaal.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
