<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CraBaby"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
]>

<TEI.2 id="CraBaby">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"An Ominous Baby"</title>
<title type="sort">an ominous baby</title>
<author>Crane, Stephen, 1871-1900</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">9</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CraBaby</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475837</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"An Ominous Baby"</title>
<title level="j">The Arena 9 (May 1894)</title>
<title type="sort">an ominous baby</title>
<author>Stephen Crane</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Arena Publishing Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston, MA</pubPlace>
<date value="1894-05">May 1894</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>The Arena, Vol. 9</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>UVa. Library Call Number: AP 2 .A6</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1894-05">May 1894</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-01-24">January 24, 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jennifer Hanna</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI-compatible header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">



<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="819"/>
<head>AN OMINOUS BABY.<lb/>
                         BY STEPHEN CRANE.</head>

<p>A BABY was wandering in a strange country.  He was a tattered
child with a frowsled wealth of yellow hair.  His dress, of a
checked stuff, was soiled and showed the marks of many conflicts
like the chain-shirt of a warrior.  His sun-tanned knees shone
above wrinkled stockings which he pulled up occasionally with an
impatient movement when they entangled his feet.  From a gaping
shoe there appeared an array of tiny toes.
</p><p>He was toddling along an avenue between rows of stolid, brown
houses.  He went slowly, with a look of absorbed interest on his
small, flushed face.  His blue eyes stared curiously.  Carriages
went with a musical rumble over the smooth asphalt.  A man with a
chrysanthemum was going up steps.  Two nursery-maids chatted as
they walked slowly, while their charges hob-nobbed amiably between
perambulators.  A truck wagon roared thunderously in the distance.
</p><p>The child from the poor district made way along the brown
street filled with dull gray shadows.  High up, near the roofs,
glancing sun-rays changed cornices to blazing gold and silvered the
fronts of windows.  The wandering baby stopped and stared at the
two children laughing and playing in their carriages among the
heaps of rugs and cushions.  He braced his legs apart in an
attitude of earnest attention.  His lower jaw fell and disclosed
his small even teeth.  As they moved on, he followed the carriages
with awe in his face as if contemplating a pageant.  Once one of
the babies, with twittering laughter, shook a gorgeous rattle at
him.  He smiled jovially in return.
</p><p>Finally a nursery maid ceased conversation and, turning, made
a gesture of annoyance.
</p><p>"Go 'way, little boy," she said to him.  "Go 'way.  You're all
dirty."
</p><p>He gazed at her with infant tranquillity for a moment and then
went slowly off, dragging behind him a bit of rope he had acquired
in another street.  He continued to investigate the new scenes.
The people and houses struck him with interest as would flowers and
trees.  Passengers had to avoid the small, absorbed figure in the
middle of the sidewalk.  They glanced at <pb n="820"/>  the intent baby
face covered with scratches and dust as with scars and powder
smoke.
</p><p>After a time, the wanderer discovered upon the pavement, a
pretty child in fine clothes playing with a toy.  It was a tiny
fire engine painted brilliantly in crimson and gold.  The wheels
rattled as its small owner dragged it uproariously about by means
of a string.  The babe with his bit of rope trailing behind him
paused and regarded the child and the toy.  For a long while he
remained motionless, save for his eyes, which followed all
movements of the glittering thing.
</p><p>The owner paid no attention to the spectator but continued his
joyous imitations of phases of the career of a fire engine.  His
gleeful baby laugh rang against the calm fronts of the houses.
After a little, the wandering baby began quietly to sidle nearer.
His bit of rope, now forgotten, dropped at his feet.  He removed
his eyes from the toy and glanced expectantly at the other child.
</p><p>"Say," he breathed, softly.
</p><p>The owner of the toy was running down the walk at top speed.
His tongue was clanging like a bell and his legs were galloping.
An iron post on the corner was all ablaze.  He did not look around
at the coaxing call from the small, tattered figure on the curb.
</p><p>The wandering baby approached still nearer and, presently,
spoke again.  "Say," he murmured, "le' me play wif it?"
</p><p>The other child interrupted some shrill tootings.  He bended
his head and spoke disdainfully over his shoulder.
</p><p>"No," he said.
</p><p>The wanderer retreated to the curb.  He failed to notice the
bit of rope, once treasured.  His eyes followed as before the
winding course of the engine, and his tender mouth twitched.
</p><p>"Say," he ventured at last, "is dat yours?"
</p><p>"Yes," said the other, tilting his round chin.  He drew his
property suddenly behind him as if it were menaced.  "Yes," he
repeated, "it's mine."
</p><p>"Well, le' me play wif it?" said the wandering baby, with a
trembling note of desire in his voice.
</p><p>"No," cried the pretty child with determined lips.  "It's
mine!  My ma-ma buyed it."
</p><p>"Well, tan't I play wif it?"  His voice was a sob.  He
stretched forth little, covetous hands.
</p><p>"No," the pretty child continued to repeat.  "No, it's mine."
</p><p>"Well, I want to play wif it," wailed the other.  A sudden,
fierce frown mantled his baby face.  He clenched his thin hands and
advanced with a formidable gesture.  He looked some wee battler in
a war. <pb n="821"/>
</p><p>"It's mine!  It's mine," cried the pretty child, his voice in
the treble of outraged rights.
</p><p>"I want it," roared the wanderer.
</p><p>"It's mine!  It's mine!"
</p><p>"I want it!"
</p><p>"It's mine!"
</p><p>The pretty child retreated to the fence, and there paused at
bay.  He protected his property with outstretched arms.  The small
vandal made a charge.  There was a short scuffle at the fence.
Each grasped the string to the toy and tugged.  Their faces were
wrinkled with baby rage, the verge of tears.
</p><p>Finally, the child in tatters gave a supreme tug and wrenched
the string from the other's hands.  He set off rapidly down the
street, bearing the toy in his arms.  He was weeping with the air
of a wronged one who has at last succeeded in achieving his rights.
The other baby was squalling lustily.  He seemed quite helpless.
He wrung his chubby hands and railed.
</p><p>After the small barbarian had got some distance away, he
paused and regarded his booty.  His little form curved with pride.
A soft, gleeful smile loomed through the storm of tears.  With
great care, he prepared the toy for travelling.  He stopped a
moment on a corner and gazed at the pretty child whose small figure
was quivering with sobs.  As the latter began to show signs of
beginning pursuit, the little vandal turned and vanished down a
dark side street as into a swallowing cavern.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
