<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CraRest"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>
<TEI.2 id="CraRest">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">`God Rest Ye Merry Gentlemen.'</title>
<title type="sort">god rest ye merry gentlemen</title>
<author>Crane, Stephen, 1871-1900</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">43</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CraRest</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475845</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">`God Rest Ye Merry Gentlemen.'</title>
<title level="j">The Cornhill Magazine</title>
<title type="sort">god rest ye merry gentlemen</title>
<author>Stephen Crane</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>577-592</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Smith, Elder, &amp; Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Cornhill Magazine, 76, n.s. 6 (May 1899); Copy consulted: UVA Library call number AP4 .C8</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic TextCenter.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification madeagainst printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and thetrailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versionsfor general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text'sunique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-07">July 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Catherine Tousignant, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">


<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="577"/>
<head><hi rend="italic">'GOD REST YE, MERRY GENTLEMEN.'</hi>
<ref target="n1">[1]</ref></head>

<p>LITTLE NELL, sometimes called the Blessed Damosel, was a war
correspondent for the <hi rend="italic">New York Eclipse</hi>, and at sea on the
despatch boats he wore pyjamas, and on shore he wore whatever fate
allowed him, which clothing was in the main unsuitable to the climate.
He had been cruising in the Caribbean on a small tug, awash always,
habitable never, wildly looking for Cervera's fleet; although what he was
going to do with four armoured cruisers and two destroyers in the event
of his really finding them had not been explained by the managing editor.
The cable instructions read: 'Take tug; go find Cervera's fleet.'  If his
unfortunate nine-knot craft should happen to find these great twenty-knot
ships, with their two spiteful and faster attendants, Little Nell had
wondered how he was going to lose them again.  He had marvelled, both
publicly and in secret, on the uncompromising asininity of managing
editors at odd moments, but he had wasted little time.  The <hi rend="italic">Jefferson
G. Johnson</hi> was already coaled, so he passed the word to his skipper,
bought some tinned meats, cigars, and beer, and soon the <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
sailed on her mission, tooting her whistle in graceful farewell to some
friends of hers in the bay.
</p><p>So the <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi> crawled giddily to one wave-height after
another, and fell aslant, into one valley after another for a longer period
than was good for the hearts of the men, because the <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi> was
merely a harbour-tug, with no architectural intention of parading the high
seas, and the crew had never seen the decks all white water like a mere
sunken reef.  As for the cook, he



<pb n="578"/>

blasphemed hopelessly hour in and hour out, meanwhile pursuing the
equipment of his trade frantically from side to side of the galley.
Little Nell dealt with a great deal of grumbling, but he knew it was
not the real evil grumbling.  It was merely the unhappy words of men
who wished expression of comradeship for their wet, forlorn,
half-starved lives, to which, they explained, they were not
accustomed, and for which, they explained, they were not properly
paid.  Little Nell condoled and condoled without difficulty.  He laid
words of gentle sympathy before them, and smothered his own misery
behind the face of a reporter of the <hi rend="italic">New York Eclipse</hi>.  But
they tossed themselves in their cockleshell even as far as Martinique;
they knew many races and many flags, but they did not find Cervera's
fleet.  If they had found that elusive squadron, this timid story
would never have been written; there would probably have been a
lyric.  The <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi> limped one morning into the Mole St.
Nicholas, and there Little Nell received this despatch: 'Can't
understand your inaction.  What are you doing with the boat?  Report
immediately.  Fleet transports already left Tampa.  Expected
destination near Santiago.  Proceed there immediately.  Place yourself
under orders.&mdash;Rogers.  <hi rend="italic">Eclipse.</hi>'

</p><p>One day, steaming along the high luminous blue coast of Santiago
province, they fetched into view the fleets, a knot of masts and funnels,
looking incredibly inshore, as if they were glued to the mountains.  Then
mast left mast, and funnel left funnel, slowly, slowly, and the shore
remained still, but the fleets seemed to move out toward the eager
<hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>.  At the speed of nine knots an hour the scene separated
into its parts.  On an easily rolling sea, under a crystal sky, black-hulled
transports&mdash;erstwhile packets&mdash;lay waiting, while grey cruisers and
gunboats lay near shore, shelling the beach and some woods.  From their
grey sides came thin red flashes, belches of white smoke, and then over
the waters sounded boom&mdash;boom&mdash;boom-boom.  The crew of the
<hi rend="italic">Jefferson G. Johnson</hi> forgave Little Nell all the suffering of a
previous fortnight.
</p><p>To the westward, about the mouth of Santiago harbour, sat a row of
castellated grey battleships, their eyes turned another way, waiting.
</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi> swung past a transport whose decks and
rigging were aswarm with black figures, as if a tribe of bees had alighted
upon a log.  She swung past a cruiser indignant at being left

<pb n="579"/>
out
of the game, her deck thick with white-clothed tars watching the play of
their luckier brethren.  The cold blue lifting seas tilted the big ships
easily, slowly, and heaved the little ones in the usual sinful way, as if
very little babes had surreptitiously mounted sixteen-hand trotting
hunters.  The <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi> leered and tumbled her way through a
community of ships.  The bombardment ceased, and some of the
troopships edged in near the land.  Soon boats black with men and towed
by launches were almost lost to view in the scintillant mystery of light
which appeared where the sea met the land.  A disembarkation had
begun.  The <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi> sped on at her nine knots, and Little Nell
chafed exceedingly, gloating upon the shore through his glasses, anon
glancing irritably over the side to note the efforts of the excited tug.
Then at last they were in a sort of a cove, with troopships, newspaper
boats, and cruisers on all sides of them, and over the water came a great
hum of human voices, punctuated frequently by the clang of engine-room
gongs as the steamers man&oelig;uvred to avoid jostling.
</p><p>In reality it was the great moment&mdash;the moment for which men,
ships, islands, and continents had been waiting for months; but somehow
it did not look it.  It was very calm; a certain strip of high green rocky
shore was being rapidly populated from boat after boat; that was all.
Like many preconceived moments, it refused to be supreme.
</p><p>But nothing lessened Little Nell's frenzy.  He knew that the army
was landing&mdash;he could see it; and little did he care if the great moment
did not look its part&mdash;it was his virtue as a correspondent to recognise the
great moment in any disguise.  The <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi> lowered a boat for
him, and he dropped into it swiftly, forgetting everything.  However, the
mate, a bearded philanthropist, flung after him a mackintosh and a bottle
of whisky.  Little Nell's face was turned toward those other boats filled
with men, all eyes upon the placid, gentle, noiseless shore.  Little Nell
saw many soldiers seated stiffly beside upright rifle barrels, their blue
breasts crossed with white shelter tent and blanket-rolls.  Launches
screeched; jack-tars pushed or pulled with their boathooks; a beach was
alive with working soldiers, some of them stark naked.  Little Nell's boat
touched the shore amid a babble of tongues, dominated at that time by a
single stern voice, which was repeating, 'Fall in, B Company!'
</p><p>He took his mackintosh and his bottle of whisky and invaded


<pb n="580"/>

Cuba.  It was a trifle bewildering.  Companies of those same men
in blue and brown were being rapidly formed and marched off across a
little open space&mdash;near a pool&mdash;near some palm trees&mdash;near a house&mdash;into
the hills.  At one side, a mulatto in dirty linen and an old straw hat was
hospitably using a machete to cut open some green cocoanuts for a group
of idle invaders.  At the other side, up a bank, a block-house was burning
furiously; while near it some railway sheds were smouldering, with a
little Rogers' engine standing amid the ruins, grey, almost white, with
ashes until it resembled a ghost.  Little Nell dodged the encrimsoned
block-house, and proceeded where he saw a little village street lined with
flimsy wooden cottages.  Some ragged Cuban cavalry-men were
tranquilly tending their horses in a shed which had not yet grown cold of
the Spanish occupation.  Three American soldiers were trying to explain
to a Cuban that they wished to buy drinks.  A native rode by, clubbing his
pony, as always.  The sky was blue; the sea talked with a gravelly accent
at the feet of some rocks; upon its bosom the ships sat quiet as gulls.
There was no mention, directly, of invasion&mdash;invasion for war&mdash;save in
the roar of the flames at the block-house; but none even heeded this
conflagration, excepting to note that it threw out a great heat.  It was
warm, very warm.  It was really hard for little Nell to keep from thinking
of his own affairs: his debts, other misfortunes, loves, prospects of
happiness.  Nobody was in a flurry; the Cubans were not tearfully
grateful; the American troops were visibly glad of being released from
those ill transports, and the men often asked, with interest, 'Where's the
Spaniards?'  And yet it must have been a great moment!  It was a
<hi rend="italic">great</hi> moment!
</p><p>It seemed made to prove that the emphatic time of history is not the
emphatic time of the common man, who throughout the change of
nations feels an itch on his shin, a pain in his head, hunger, thirst, a lack
of sleep; the influence of his memory of past firesides, glasses of beer,
girls, theatres, ideals, religions, parents, faces, hurts, joy.
</p><p>Little Nell was hailed from a comfortable verandah, and, looking
up, saw Walkley of the <hi rend="italic">Eclipse</hi>, stretched in a yellow and green
hammock, smoking his pipe with an air of having always lived in that
house, in that village.  'Oh, dear little Nell, how glad I am to see your
angel face again!  There! don't try to hide it; I can see it.  Did you bring a
corkscrew too?  You're superseded

<pb n="581"/>

as master of the slaves.  Did
you know it?  And by Rogers, too!  Rogers is a Sadducee, a cadaver and
a pelican, appointed to the post of chief correspondent, no doubt, because
of his rare gift of incapacity.  Never mind.'
</p><p>'Where is he now?' asked Little Nell, taking seat on the steps.
</p><p>'He is down interfering with the landing of the troops,' answered
Walkley, swinging a leg.  'I hope you have the <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi> well
stocked with food as well as with cigars, cigarettes and tobaccos, ales,
wines and liquors.  We shall need them.  There is already famine in the
house of Walkley.  I have discovered that the system of transportation for
our gallant soldiery does not strike in me the admiration which I have
often felt when viewing the management of an ordinary bun-shop.  A
hunger, stifling, jammed together amid odours, and everybody irritable&mdash;ye gods, how irritable!  And so I&mdash;  Look! look!'
</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Jefferson G. Johnson</hi>, well known to them at an
incredible distance, could be seen striding the broad sea, the smoke
belching from her funnel, headed for Jamaica.  'The Army Lands in
Cuba!' shrieked Walkley.  'Shafter's Army Lands near Santiago!  Special
type!  Half the front page!  Oh, the Sadducee!  The cadaver!  The
pelican!'
</p><p>Little Nell was dumb with astonishment and fear.  Walkley,
however, was at least not dumb.  'That's the pelican!  That's Mr. Rogers
making his first impression upon the situation.  He has engraved himself
upon us.  We are tattooed with him.  There will be a fight to-morrow,
sure, and we will cover it even as you found Cervera's fleet.  No food, no
horses, no money.  I am transport-lame; you are sea-weak.  We will never
see our salaries again.  Whereby Rogers is a fool.'
</p><p>'Anybody else here?' asked Little Nell wearily.
</p><p>'Only young Point.'  Point was an artist on the <hi rend="italic">Eclipse</hi>.  'But
he has nothing.  Pity there wasn't an almshouse in this God-forsaken
country.  Here comes Point now.'  A sad-faced man came along carrying
much luggage.  'Hello, Point! lithographer <hi rend="italic">and</hi> genius, have you
food?  Food.  Well, then, you had better return yourself to Tampa by
wire.  You are no good here.  Only one more little mouth to feed.'
</p><p>Point seated himself near Little Nell.  'I haven't had anything to eat
since daybreak,' he said gloomily, 'and I don't care much, for I am simply
dog-tired!'
</p><p>'Don't tell <hi rend="italic">me</hi> you are dog-tired, my talented friend,' cried

<pb n="582"/>

Walkley from his hammock.  'Think of me.  And now what's to be done?'
</p><p>They stared for a time disconsolately at where, over the rim of
the sea, trailed black smoke from the <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>.  From the
landing-place below and to the right came the howls of a man who was
superintending the disembarkation of some mules.  The burning
block-house still rendered its hollow roar.  Suddenly the men-crowded
landing set up its cheer, and the steamers all whistled long and
raucously.  Tiny black figures were raising an American flag over a
block-house on the top of a great hill.

</p><p>'That's mighty fine Sunday stuff,' said Little Nell.  'Well, I'll go and
get the order in which the regiments landed, and who was first ashore,
and all that.  Then I'll go and try to find General Lawton's headquarters.
His division has got the advance, I think.'
</p><p>'And lo! I will write a burning description of the raising of the flag,'
said Walkley.  'While the brilliant Point buskies for food&mdash;and makes
damn sure he gets it,' he added fiercely.
</p><p>Little Nell thereupon wandered over the face of the earth, threading
out the story of the landing of the regiments.  He only found about fifty
men who had been the first American soldiers to set foot on Cuba, and of
these he took the most probable.  The army was going forward in detail,
as soon as the pieces were landed.  There was a house something like a
crude country tavern&mdash;the soldiers in it were looking over their rifles and
talking.  There was a well of water quite hot&mdash;more palm trees&mdash;an
inscrutable background.
</p><p>When he arrived again at Walkley's mansion he found the verandah
crowded with correspondents in khaki, duck, dungaree, and flannel.
They wore riding-breeches, but that was mainly forethought.  They could
see now that fate intended them to walk.  Some were writing copy, while
Walkley discoursed from his hammock.  Rhodes&mdash;doomed to be shot in
action some days later&mdash;was trying to borrow a canteen from men who
had one, and from men who had none.  Young Point, wan, utterly worn
out, was asleep on the floor.  Walkley pointed to him.  'That is how he
appears after his foraging journey, during which he ran all Cuba through
a sieve.  Oh, yes; a can of corn and a half-bottle of lime juice.'
</p><p>'Say, does anybody know the name of the commander of the 26th
Infantry?'

<pb n="583"/>

</p><p>'Who commands the first brigade of Kent's Division?'
</p><p>'What was the name of the chap that raised the flag?'
</p><p>'What time is it?'
</p><p>And a woeful man was wandering here and there with a cold pipe,
saying plaintively, 'Who's got a match?  Anybody here got a match?'
</p><p>Little Nell's left boot hurt him at the heel, and so he removed it,
taking great care and whistling through his teeth.  The heated dust was
upon them all, making everybody feel that bathing was unknown and
shattering their tempers.  Young Point developed a snore which brought
grim sarcasm from all quarters.  Always, below, hummed the traffic of
the landing-place.
</p><p>When night came Little Nell thought best not to go to bed until late,
because he recognised the mackintosh as but a feeble comfort.  The
evening was a glory.  A breeze came from the sea, fanning spurts of
flame out of the ashes and charred remains of the sheds, while overhead
lay a splendid summer-night sky, aflash with great tranquil stars.  In the
streets of the village were two or three fires, frequently and suddenly
reddening with their glare the figures of low-voiced men who moved
here and there.  The lights of the transports blinked on the murmuring
plain in front of the village; and far to the westward Little Nell could
sometimes note a subtle indication of a playing search-light, which alone
marked the presence of the invisible battleships, half-mooned about the
entrance of Santiago Harbour, waiting&mdash;waiting&mdash;waiting.
</p><p>When Little Nell returned to the verandah he stumbled along a
man-strewn place, until he came to the spot where he left his mackintosh;
but he found it gone.  His curses mingled then with those of the men
upon whose bodies he had trodden.  Two English correspondents, lying
awake to smoke a last pipe, half rose and looked at him lazily.  'What's
wrong, old chap?' murmured one.  'Eh?  Lost it, eh?  Well, look here;
come here and take a bit of my blanket.  It's a jolly big one.  Oh, no
trouble at all, man.  There you are.  Got enough?  Comfy?  Good-night.'
</p><p>A sleepy voice arose in the darkness.  'If this hammock breaks, I
shall hit at least ten of those Indians down there.  Never mind.  This is
war.'
</p><p>The men slept.  Once the sound of three or four shots rang across
the windy night, and one head uprose swiftly from the

<pb n="584"/>

verandah, two eyes looked dazedly at nothing, and the head as swiftly
sank.  Again a sleepy voice was heard.  'Usual thing!  Nervous
sentries!' The men slept.  Before dawn a pulseless, penetrating chill
came into the air, and the correspondents awakened, shivering into a
blue world.  Some of the fires still smouldered.  Walkley and Little
Nell kicked vigorously into Point's framework.  'Come on, brilliance!
Wake up, talent!  Don't be sodgering.  It's too cold to sleep, but
it's not too cold to hustle.' Point sat up dolefully.  Upon his face
was a childish expression.  'Where are we going to get breakfast?' he
asked, sulking.

</p><p>'There's no breakfast for you, you hound!  Get up and hustle.'
Accordingly they hustled.  With exceeding difficulty they learned that
nothing emotional had happened during the night, save the killing of two
Cubans who were so secure in ignorance that they could not understand
the challenge of two American sentries.  Then Walkley ran a gamut of
commanding officers, and Little Nell pumped privates for their
impressions of Cuba.  When his indignation at the absence of breakfast
allowed him, Point made sketches.  At the full break of day the
<hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi>, an <hi rend="italic">Eclipse</hi> despatch boat, sent a boat ashore
with Tailor and Shackles in it, and Walkley departed tearlessly for
Jamaica, soon after he had bestowed upon his friends much tinned goods
and blankets.
</p><p>'Well, we've got our stuff off,' said Little Nell.  'Now Point and I
must breakfast.'
</p><p>Shackles, for some reason, carried a great hunting-knife, and with it
Little Nell opened a tin of beans.
</p><p>'Fall to,' he said amiably to Point.
</p><p>There were some hard biscuits.  Afterwards they&mdash;the four of them&mdash;marched off on the route of the troops.  They were well loaded with
luggage, particularly young Point, who had somehow made a great
gathering of unnecessary things.  Hills covered with verdure soon
enclosed them.  They heard that the army had advanced some nine miles
with no fighting.  Evidences of the rapid advance were here and there&mdash;coats, gauntlets, blanket-rolls on the ground.  Mule-trains came herding
back along the narrow trail to the sound of a little tinkling bell.  Cubans
were appropriating the coats and blanket-rolls.
</p><p>The four correspondents hurried onward.  The surety of impending
battle weighed upon them always, but there was a

<pb n="585"/>

score of
minor things more intimate.  Little Nell's left heel had chafed until it
must have been quite raw, and every moment he wished to take seat by
the roadside and console himself from pain.  Shackles and Point disliked
each other extremely, and often they foolishly quarrelled over something,
or nothing.  The blanket-rolls and packages for the hand oppressed
everybody.  It was like being burned out of a boarding-house, and having
to carry one's trunk eight miles to the nearest neighbour.  Moreover,
Point, since he had stupidly overloaded, with great wisdom placed
various cameras and other trifles in the hands of his three less-burdened
and more sensible friends.  This made them fume and gnash, but in
complete silence, since he was hideously youthful and innocent and
unaware.  They all wished to rebel, but none of them saw their way clear,
because&mdash;they did not understand&mdash;but somehow it seemed a barbarous
project&mdash;no one wanted to say anything&mdash;cursed him privately for a little
ass, but&mdash;said nothing.  For instance, Little Nell wished to remark, 'Point,
you are not a thoroughbred in a half of a way.  You are an inconsiderate,
thoughtless little swine.'  But, in truth, he said, 'Point, when you started
out you looked like a Christmas-tree.  If we keep on robbing you of your
bundles there soon won't be anything left for the children.'  Point asked
dubiously, 'What do you mean?'  Little Nell merely laughed with
deceptive good-nature.
</p><p>They were always very thirsty.  There was always a howl for the
half-bottle of lime juice.  Five or six drops from it were simply heavenly
in the warm water from the canteens.  Point seemed to try to keep the
lime juice in his possession, in order that he might get more benefit of it.
Before the war was ended the others found themselves declaring
vehemently that they loathed Point, and yet when men asked them the
reason they grew quite inarticulate.  The reasons seemed then so small, so
childish, as the reasons of a lot of women.  And yet at the time his
offences loomed enormous.
</p><p>The surety of impending battle still weighed upon them.  Then it
came that Shackles turned seriously ill.  Suddenly he dropped his own
and much of Point's traps upon the trail, wriggled out of his blanket-roll,
flung it away, and took seat heavily at the roadside.  They saw with
surprise that his face was pale as death, and yet streaming with sweat.
</p><p>'Boys,' he said in his ordinary voice, 'I'm clean played out.

<pb n="586"/>
I can't go another step.  You fellows go on, and leave me to come as soon
as I am able.'
</p><p>'Oh, no, that wouldn't do at all,' said Little Nell and Tailor together.
</p><p>Point moved over to a soft place, and dropped amid whatever traps
he was himself carrying.
</p><p>'Don't know whether it's ancestral or merely from the&mdash;sun&mdash;but I've
got a stroke,' said Shackles, and gently slumped over to a prostrate
position before either Little Nell or Tailor could reach him.
</p><p>Thereafter Shackles was parental; it was Little Nell and Tailor who
were really suffering from a stroke, either ancestral or from the sun.
</p><p>'Put my blanket-roll under my head, Nell, me son,' he said gently.
'There now!  That is very nice.  It is delicious.  Why, I'm all right, only&mdash;only tired.'  He closed his eyes, and something like an easy slumber came
over him.  Once he opened his eyes.  'Don't trouble about me,' he
remarked.
</p><p>But the two fussed about him, nervous, worried, discussing this
plan and that plan.  It was Point who first made a business-like statement.
Seated carelessly and indifferently upon his soft place, he finally blurted
out:
</p><p>'Say!  Look here!  Some of us have got to go on.  We can't all stay
here.  Some of us have got to go on.'
</p><p>It was quite true; the <hi rend="italic">Eclipse</hi> could take no account of
strokes.  In the end Point and Tailor went on, leaving Little Nell to bring
on Shackles as soon as possible.  The latter two spent many hours in the
grass by the roadside.  They made numerous abrupt acquaintances with
passing staff officers, privates, muleteers, many stopping to inquire the
wherefore of the death-faced figure on the ground.  Favours were done
often and often, by peer and peasant&mdash;small things, of no consequence,
and yet warming.
</p><p>It was dark when Shackles and Little Nell had come slowly to
where they could hear the murmur of the army's bivouac.
</p><p>'Shack,' gasped Little Nell to the man leaning forlornly upon him, 'I
guess we'd better bunk down here where we stand.'
</p><p>'All right, old boy.  Anything you say,' replied Shackles, in the bass
and hollow voice which arrives with such condition.
</p><p>They crawled into some bushes, and distributed their belongings
upon the ground.  Little Nell spread out the blankets, and

<pb n="587"/>
generally played housemaid.  Then they lay down, supperless, being too
weary to eat.  The men slept.
</p><p>At dawn Little Nell awakened and looked wildly for Shackles,
whose empty blanket was pressed flat like a wet newspaper on the
ground.  But at nearly the same moment Shackles appeared, elate.
</p><p>'Come on,' he cried; 'I've rustled an invitation for breakfast.'
</p><p>Little Nell came on with celerity.
</p><p>'Where?  Who?' he said.
</p><p>'Oh! some officers,' replied Shackles airily.  If he had been ill the
previous day, he showed it now only in some curious kind of deference
he paid to Little Nell.
</p><p>Shackles conducted his comrade, and soon they arrived at where a
captain and his one subaltern arose courteously from where they were
squatting near a fire of little sticks.  They wore the wide white trouser-stripes of infantry officers, and upon the shoulders of their blue campaign
shirts were the little marks of their rank; but otherwise there was little
beyond their manners to render them different from the men who were
busy with breakfast near them.
</p><p>The breakfast was of canned tomatoes stewed with hard bread,
more hard bread, and coffee.  It was very good fare, almost royal.
Shackles and Little Nell were absurdly grateful as they felt the hot bitter
coffee tingle in them.  But they departed joyfully before the sun was
fairly up, and passed into Siboney.

</p><p>The beach at Siboney was furious with traffic, even as had been
the beach at Daqueri.  Launches shouted, jack-tars prodded with their
boathooks, and load of men followed load of men.  Straight,
parade-like, on the shore stood a trumpeter playing familiar calls to
the troop-horses who swam towards him eagerly through the salt seas.
Crowding closely into the cove were transports of all sizes and ages.
To the left and to the right of the little landing-beach green hills
shot upward like the wings in a theatre.  They were scarred here and
there with block-houses and rifle-pits.  Up one hill a regiment was
crawling, seemingly inch by inch.  Shackles and Little Nell walked
among palms and scrubby bushes, near pools, over spaces of sand
holding little monuments of biscuit-boxes, ammunition-boxes, and
supplies of all kinds.  Some regiment was just collecting itself from
the ships, and the men made great patches of blue on the brown sand.

</p><p>Shackles asked a question of a man accidentally: 'Where's
<pb n="588"/>
that regiment going to?'  He pointed to the force that was crawling up the
hill.  The man grinned, and said, 'They're going to look for a fight!'
</p><p>'Looking for a fight!' said Shackles and Little Nell together.  They
stared into each other's eyes.  Then they set off for the foot of the hill.
The hill was long and toilsome.  Below them spread wider and wider a
vista of ships quiet on a grey sea; a busy, black dis-embarkation-place;
tall, still, green hills; a village of well-separated cottages; palms; a bit of
road; soldiers marching.  They passed vacant Spanish trenches; little
twelve-foot block-houses.  Soon they were on a fine upland near the sea.
The path, under ordinary conditions, must have been a beautiful wooded
way.  It wound in the shade of thickets of fine trees, then through rank
growths of bushes with revealed and fantastic roots, then through a
grassy space which had all the beauty of a neglected orchard.  But always
from under their feet scuttled noisy land-crabs, demons to the nerves,
which is some way possessed a semblance of moon-like faces upon their
blue or red bodies, and these faces were turned with expressions of
deepest horror upon Shackles and Little Nell as they sped to overtake the
pugnacious regiment.  The route was paved with coats, hats, tent and
blankets, rolls, ration-tins, haversacks&mdash;everything but ammunition belts,
rifles and canteens.
</p><p>They heard a dull noise of voices in front of them&mdash;men talking too
loud for the etiquette of the forest&mdash;and presently they came upon two or
three soldiers lying by the roadside, flame-faced, utterly spent from the
hurried march in the heat.  One man came limping back along the path.
He looked to them anxiously for sympathy and comprehension.  'Hurt m'
knee.  I swear I couldn't keep up with th' boys.  I had to leave 'm.  Wasn't
that tough luck?'  His collar rolled away from a red muscular neck, and
his bare forearms were better than stanchions.  Yet he was almost
babyishly tearful in his attempt to make the two correspondents feel that
he had not turned back because he was afraid.  They gave him scant
courtesy, tinctured with one drop of sympathetic yet cynical
understanding.  Soon they overtook the hospital squad; men addressing
chaste language to some pack-mules; a talkative sergeant; two amiable
cool-eyed young surgeons.  Soon they were amid the rear troops of the
dismounted volunteer cavalry regiment which was moving to attack.  The
men strode easily along, arguing one to another on ulterior matters.  If
they were going into battle, they either did
<pb n="589"/>
not know it or they
concealed it well.  They were more like men going into a bar at one
o'clock in the morning.  Their laughter rang through the Cuban woods.
And in the meantime, soft, mellow, sweet, sang the voice of the Cuban
wood-dove, the Spanish guerilla calling to his mate&mdash;forest music; on the
flanks, deep back on both flanks, the adorable wood-dove, singing only
of love.  Some of the advancing Americans said it was beautiful.  It
<hi rend="italic">was</hi> beautiful.  The Spanish guerilla calling to his mate.  What
could be more beautiful?
</p><p>Shackles and Little Nell rushed precariously through waist-high
bushes until they reached the centre of the single-filed regiment.  The
firing then broke out in front.  All the woods set up a hot sputtering; the
bullets sped along the path and across it from both sides.  The thickets
presented nothing but dense masses of light green foliage, out of which
these swift steel things were born supernaturally.
</p><p>It was a volunteer regiment going into its first action, against an
enemy of unknown force, in a country where the vegetation was thicker
than fur on a cat.  There might have been a dreadful mess; but in military
matters the only way to deal with a situation of this kind is to take it
frankly by the throat and squeeze it to death.  Shackles and Little Nell felt
the thrill of the orders.  'Come ahead, men!  Keep right ahead, men!
Come on!'  The volunteer cavalry regiment, with all the willingness in the
world, went ahead into the angle of a V-shaped Spanish formation.
</p><p>It seemed that every leaf had turned into a soda-bottle and was
popping its cork.  Some of the explosions seemed to be against the men's
very faces, others against the backs of their necks.  'Now, men!  Keep
goin' ahead.  Keep on goin'.'  The forward troops were already engaged.
They, at least, had something at which to shoot.  'Now, captain, if you're
ready.'  'Stop that swearing there.'  'Got a match?'  'Steady, now, men.'
</p><p>A gate appeared in a barbed-wire fence.  Within were billowy fields
of long grass, dotted with palms and luxuriant mango trees.  It was
Elysian&mdash;a place for lovers, fair as Eden in its radiance of sun, under its
blue sky.  One might have expected to see white-robed figures walking
slowly in the shadows.  A dead man, with a bloody face, lay twisted in a
curious contortion at the waist.  Some one was shot in the leg, his pins
knocked cleanly from under him.
</p><p>'Keep goin', men.'  The air roared, and the ground fled reelingly
under their feet.  Light, shadow, trees, grass.  Bullets
<pb n="590"/>  spat from
every side.  Once they were in a thicket, and the men, blanched and
bewildered, turned one way, and then another, not knowing which way to
turn.  'Keep goin', men.'  Soon they were in the sunlight again.  They
could see the long scant line, which was being drained man by man&mdash;one
might say drop by drop.  The musketry rolled forth in great full measure
from the magazine carbines.  'Keep goin', men.'  'Christ, I'm shot!'
'They're flankin' us, sir.'  'We're bein' fired into by our own crowd, sir.'
'Keep goin', men.'  A low ridge before them was a bottling establishment
blowing up in detail.  From the right&mdash;it seemed at that time to be the far
right&mdash;they could hear steady, crashing volleys&mdash;the United States regulars
in action.
</p><p>Then suddenly&mdash;to use a phrase of the street&mdash;the whole bottom of
the thing fell out.  It was suddenly and mysteriously ended.  The
Spaniards had run away, and some of the regulars were chasing them.  It
was a victory.
</p><p>When the wounded men dropped in the tall grass they quite
disappeared, as if they had sunk in water.  Little Nell and Shackles were
walking along through the fields, disputing.
</p><p>'Well, damn it, man!' cried Shackles, 'we <hi rend="italic">must</hi> get a list of
the killed and wounded.'
</p><p>'That is not nearly so important,' quoth Little Nell, academically, 'as
to get the first account to New York of the first action of the army in
Cuba.'
</p><p>They came upon Tailor, lying with a bared torso and a small red
hole through his left lung.  He was calm, but evidently out of temper.
'Good God, Tailor!' they cried, dropping to their knees like two pagans;
'are you hurt, old boy?'
</p><p>'Hurt?' he said gently.  'No, 'tis not so deep as a well nor so wide as
a church-door, but 'tis enough, d' you see?  You understand, do you?
Idiots!'
</p><p>Then he became very official.  'Shackles, feel and see what's under
my leg.  It's a small stone, or a burr, or something.  Don't be clumsy now!
Be careful!  Be careful!'  Then he said, angrily, 'Oh, you didn't find it at
all.  Damn it!'
</p><p>In reality there was nothing there, and so Shackles could not have
removed it.  'Sorry, old boy,' he said, meekly.
</p><p>'Well, you may observe that I can't stay here more than a year,' said
Tailor, with some oratory, 'and the hospital people have their own work
in hand.  It behoves you, Nell, to fly to Siboney, arrest a despatch boat,
get a cot and some other things, and some minions to carry me.  If I get
once down to the base
<pb n="591"/>
I'm all right, but if I stay here I'm dead.
Meantime Shackles can stay here and try to look as if he liked it.'
</p><p>There was no disobeying the man.  Lying there with a little red hole
in his left lung, he dominated them through his helplessness, and through
their fear that if they angered him he would move and&mdash;bleed.
</p><p>'Well?' said Little Nell.
</p><p>'Yes,' said Shackles, nodding.
</p><p>Little Nell departed.
</p><p>'That blanket you lent me,' Tailor called after him, 'is back there
somewhere with Point.'
</p><p>Little Nell noted that many of the men who were wandering among
the wounded seemed so spent with the toil and excitement of their first
action that they could hardly drag one leg after the other.  He found
himself suddenly in the same condition.  His face, his neck, even his
mouth, felt dry as sun-baked bricks, and his legs were foreign to him.
But he swung desperately into his five-mile task.  On the way he passed
many things: bleeding men carried by comrades; others making their way
grimly, with encrimsoned arms; then the little settlement of the hospital
squad; men on the ground everywhere, many in the path; one young
captain dying, with great gasps, his body pale blue, and glistening, like
the inside of a rabbit's skin.  But the voice of the Cuban wood-dove, soft,
mellow, sweet, singing only of love, was no longer heard from the wealth
of foliage.
</p><p>Presently the hurrying correspondent met another regiment coming
to assist&mdash;a line of a thousand men in single file through the jungle.
'Well, how is it going, old man?'  'How is it coming on?'  'Are we doin'
'em?'  Then, after an interval, came other regiments, moving out.  He had
to take to the bush to let these long lines pass him, and he was delayed,
and had to flounder amid brambles.  But at last, like a successful pilgrim,
he arrived at the brow of the great hill overlooking Siboney.  His
practised eye scanned the fine broad brow of the sea with its clustering
ships, but he saw thereon no <hi rend="italic">Eclipse</hi> despatch boats.  He
zigzagged heavily down the hill, and arrived finally amid the dust and
outcries of the base.  He seemed to ask a thousand men if they had seen
an <hi rend="italic">Eclipse</hi> boat on the water, or an <hi rend="italic">Eclipse</hi> correspondent
on the shore.  They all answered, 'No.'
</p><p>He was like a poverty-stricken and unknown suppliant at a foreign
Court.  Even his plea got only ill-hearings.  He had expected the news of
the serious wounding of Tailor to appal the
<pb n="592"/>
other
correspondents, but they took it quite calmly.  It was as if their sense of
an impending great battle between two large armies had quite got them
out of focus for these minor tragedies.  Tailor was hurt&mdash;yes?  They
looked at Little Nell, dazed.  How curious that Tailor should be almost
the first&mdash;how <hi rend="italic">very</hi> curious&mdash;yes!  But, as far as arousing them to
any enthusiasm of active pity, it seemed impossible.  He was lying up
there in the grass, was he?  Too bad, too bad, too bad!
</p><p>Little Nell went alone and lay down in the sand with his back
against a rock.  Tailor was prostrate up there in the grass.  Never mind.
Nothing was to be done.  The whole situation was too colossal.  Then
into his zone came Walkley the invincible.
</p><p>'Walkley!' yelled Little Nell.  Walkley came quickly, and Little Nell
lay weakly against his rock and talked.  In thirty seconds Walkley
understood everything, had hurled a drink of whisky into Little Nell, had
admonished him to lie quiet, and had gone to organise and manipulate.
When he returned he was a trifle dubious and backward.  Behind him
was a singular squad of volunteers from the <hi rend="italic">Adolphus</hi>, carrying
among them a wire-woven bed.
</p><p>'Look here, Nell!' said Walkley, in bashful accents; 'I've collected a
battalion here which is willing to go bring Tailor; but&mdash;they say&mdash;you&mdash;can't you show them where he is?'
</p><p>'Yes,' said Little Nell, arising.
</p><p>  .       .       .       .       .       .       .
</p><p>When the party arrived at Siboney, and deposited Tailor in the best
place, Walkley had found a house and stocked it with canned soups.
Therein Shackles and Little Nell revelled for a time, and then rolled on
the floor in their blankets.  Little Nell tossed a great deal.  'Oh, I'm so
tired.  Good God, I'm tired.  I'm&mdash;tired.'
</p><p>In the morning a voice aroused them.  It was a swollen, important,
circus voice, saying, 'Where is Mr. Nell?  I wish to see him immediately.'
</p><p>'Here I am, Rogers,' cried Little Nell.
</p><p>'Oh, Nell,' said Rogers, 'here's a despatch to me which I thought you
had better read.'
</p><p>Little Nell took the despatch.  It was: 'Tell Nell can't understand his
inaction; tell him come home first steamer from Port Antonio, Jamaica.'
</p>

<signed>STEPHEN CRANE.</signed>
</div1>
</body>
<back id="d4">
<div1 type="notes" id="d5">

<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">Copyright,</seg> <p>1899, by Stephen Crane, in the United States of
America.</p></note>

</div1>

</back>
</text>
</TEI.2>
