<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CraSelf"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>
<TEI.2 id="CraSelf">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Self-Made Man</title>
<title type="sort">self made man</title>
<author>Crane, Stephen, 1871-1900</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">15</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CraSelf</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475848</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Self-Made Man</title>
<title level="j">Cornhill Magazine</title>
<title type="sort">self made man</title>
<author>Stephen Crane</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp.324-329</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Smith, Elder, &amp; Co.,</publisher>
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
<date value="1899-03">March 1899</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Cornhill Magazine : AP4 .C8</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic TextCenter.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and thetrailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text'sunique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>prose; fiction</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">



<body id="d2">
	<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head type="main"> <hi rend="italic">A SELF-MADE MAN.</hi></head>
<head type="sub"><hi rend="italic">AN EXAMPLE OF SUCCESS THAT ANY ONE CAN FOLLOW.</hi></head>

<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d4">
	<pb n="324"/>
<p>TOM had a hole in his shoe.  It was very round and very uncomfortable,
particularly when he went on wet pavements.  Rainy days made him feel
that he was walking on frozen dollars, although he had only to think for a
moment to discover he was not.</p>
   <p>He used up almost two packs of playing cards by means of putting
four cards at a time inside his shoe as a sort of temporary sole, which
usually lasted about half a day.  Once he put in four aces for luck.  He
went down town that morning and got refused work.  He thought it
wasn't a very extraordinary performance for a young man of ability, and
he was not sorry that night to find his packs were entirely out of
aces.</p>
    <p>One day, Tom was strolling down Broadway.  He was in pursuit of
work, although his pace was slow.  He had found that he must take the
matter coolly.  So he puffed tenderly at a cigarette and walked as if he
owned stock.  He imitated success so successfully that if it wasn't for the
constant reminder (king, queen, deuce, and tray) in his shoe, he would
have gone into a store and bought something.</p>
    <p>He had borrowed five cents that morning of his landlady, for his
mouth craved tobacco.  Although he owed her much for board, she had
unlimited confidence in him, because his stock of self-assurance was
very large indeed.  And as it increased in a proper ratio with the amount
of his bills, his relations with her seemed on a firm basis.  So he strolled
along and smoked, with his confidence in fortune in nowise impaired by
his financial condition.</p>
    <p>Of a sudden he perceived an old man seated upon a railing, and
smoking a clay pipe.</p>
    <p>He stopped to look because he wasn't in a hurry, and because it was
an unusual thing on Broadway to see old men seated upon railings and
smoking clay pipes.</p>
   <p>And to his surprise the old man regarded him very intently in
return.  He stared, with a wistful expression, into Tom's face, and he
clasped his hands in trembling excitement.</p>

<pb n="325"/>
    <p>Tom was filled with astonishment at the old man's strange
demeanour.  He stood, puffing at his cigarette, and tried to understand
matters.  Failing, he threw his cigarette away, took a fresh one from his
pocket, and approached the old man.</p>
    <p>'Got a match?' he inquired pleasantly.</p>
    <p>The old man, much agitated, nearly fell from the railing as he
leaned dangerously forward.</p>
    <p>'Sonny, can you read?' he demanded, in a quavering voice.</p>
     <p>'Certainly I can,' said Tom encouragingly.  He waived the affair of
the match.</p>
    <p>The old man fumbled in his pocket.  'You look honest, sonny.  I've
been lookin' fer an honest feller fur a'most a week.  I've set on this railing
fur six days,' he cried plaintively.</p>
     <p>He drew forth a letter and handed it to Tom.  'Read it fur me, sonny,
read it,' he said coaxingly.</p>
     <p>Tom took the letter and leaned back against the railings.  As he
opened it and prepared to read, the old man wriggled like a child at a
forbidden feast.</p>
     <p>Thundering trucks made frequent interruptions and seven men in a
hurry jogged Tom's elbow, but he succeeded in reading what follows:</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="letter" id="d5">

<opener>
<address>
<addrLine>'Office of Ketchum R. Jones, Attorney-at-Law,</addrLine>
<addrLine> 'Tin Can, Nevada, May 19, 18&mdash;.</addrLine>
<addrLine>'RUFUS WILKINS, ESQ.</addrLine>
</address>
</opener>
    <salute> 'DEAR SIR,&mdash;</salute>
<p>I have as yet received no acknowledgment of the draft
from the sale of the north section lots, which I forwarded to you on June
25.  I would request an immediate reply concerning it. </p>
     <p>'Since my last I have sold the three corner lots at five thousand
each.  The city grew so rapidly in that direction that they were surrounded
by brick stores almost before you would know it.  I have also sold for
four thousand dollars the ten acres of outlying sage-bush which you once
foolishly tried to give away.  Mr. Simpson, of Boston, bought the tract.
He is very shrewd, no doubt, but he hasn't been in the West long.  Still, I
think if he holds it for about a thousand years he may come out all
right.</p>
    <p>'I worked him with the projected-horse-car-line gag.  Inform me of
the address of your New York attorneys and I will send on the papers.
Pray do not neglect to write me concerning the draft sent on June
25.</p>
    <p>'In conclusion I might say that if you have any eastern friends
<pb n="326"/>  who are after good western investments, inform them of the
glorious future of Tin Can.  We now have three railroads, a bank, an
electric-light plant, a projected-horse-car line, and an art society.  Also, a
saw manufactory, a patent car-wheel mill, and a Methodist church.  Tin
Can is marching forward to take her proud stand as the metropolis of the
West.  The rose-hued future holds no glories to which Tin Can does not&mdash;' Tom stopped abruptly.  'I guess the important part of the letter came
first,' he said.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d6">

    <p>'Yes,' cried the old man, 'I've heard enough.  It is just as I thought.
George has robbed his dad.'</p>
    <p>The old man's frail body quivered with grief.  Two tears trickled
slowly down the furrows of his face.</p>
     <p>'Come, come, now,' said Tom, patting him tenderly on the back.
'Brace up, old feller.  What you want to do is to get a lawyer and go put
the screws on George.'</p>
     <p>'Is it really?' asked the old man eagerly.</p>
     <p>'Certainly it is,' said Tom.</p>
     <p>'All right,' cried the old man, with enthusiasm; 'tell me where to get
one.'  He slid down from the railing and prepared to start off.</p>
     <p>Tom reflected.  'Well,' he said finally, 'I might do for one
myself.'</p>
     <p>'What!' shouted the old man in a voice of admiration, 'are you a
lawyer as well as a reader?'</p>
     <p>'Well,' said Tom again, 'I might appear to advantage as one.  All you
need is a big front,' he added slowly.  He was a profane young man.</p>
     <p>The old man seized him by the arm.  'Come on, then,' he cried, 'and
we'll go put the screws on George.'</p>
     <p>Tom permitted himself to be dragged by the weak arms of his
companion around a corner and along a side-street.  As they proceeded,
he was internally bracing himself for a struggle, and putting large bales
of self-assurance around where they would be likely to obstruct the
advance of discovery and defeat.</p>
     <p>By the time they reached a brown stone house, hidden away in a
street of shops and warehouses, his mental balance was so admirable that
he seemed to be in possession of enough information and brains to ruin
half the city, and he was no more concerned about the king, queen, deuce
and tray than if they had been discards that didn't fit his draw.  Too, he
infused so much confidence and courage into his companion, that the old
man went along the
<pb n="327"/>
street breathing war, like a decrepit hound
on the scent of new blood.</p>
     <p>He ambled up the steps of the brown stone house as if he were
charging earthworks.  He unlocked the door, and they passed along a
dark hall-way.  In a rear room they found a man seated at table engaged
with a very late breakfast.  He had a diamond in his shirt front, and a big
of egg on his cuff.</p>
     <p>'George,' said the old man in a fierce voice that came from his aged
throat with a sound like the crackle of burning twigs, 'here's my lawyer,
Mr.&mdash;er&mdash;ah&mdash;Smith, and we want to know what you did with the draft that
was sent on June 25th.'</p>
     <p>The old man delivered the words as if each one was a musket shot.
George's coffee spilled softly upon the table-cover, and his fingers
worked convulsively upon a slice of bread.  He turned a white,
astonished face toward the old man and the intrepid Thomas.</p>
     <p>The latter, straight and tall, with a highly legal air, stood at the old
man's side.  His glowing eyes were fixed upon the face of the man at the
table.  They seemed like two little detective cameras taking pictures of
the other man's thoughts.</p>
     <p>'Father, what d-do you mean?' faltered George, totally unable to
withstand the two cameras and the highly legal air.</p>
     <p>'What do I mean?' said the old man with a feeble roar, as from an
ancient lion; 'I mean that draft&mdash;that's what I mean.  Give it up, or we'll&mdash;we'll&mdash;' he paused to gain courage by a glance at the formidable figure at
his side, 'we'll put the screws on you.'</p>
     <p>'Well, I was&mdash;I was only borrowin' it for 'bout a month,' said
George.</p>
     <p>'Ah,' said Tom.</p>
     <p>George started, glared at Tom, and then began to shiver like an
animal with a broken back.</p>
     <p>There were a few moments of silence.  The old man was fumbling
about in his mind for more imprecations.  George was wilting and
turning limp before the glittering orbs of the valiant attorney.  The latter,
content with the exalted advantage he had gained by the use of the
expression, 'Ah,' spoke no more, but continued to stare.</p>
     <p>'Well,' said George finally, in a weak voice, 'I s'pose I can give you
a check for it, though I was only borrowin' it for 'bout a month.  I don't
think you have treated me fairly, father, with your <pb n="328"/>
lawyers, and
your threats, and all that.  But I'll give you the check.'</p>
     <p>The old man turned to his attorney.  'Well?' he asked.  Tom looked
at the son and held an impressive debate with himself.  'I think we may
accept the check,' he said coldly, after a time.</p>
     <p>George arose and tottered across the room.  He drew a check that
made the attorney's heart come privately into his mouth.  As he and his
client passed triumphantly out, he turned a last highly legal glare upon
George that reduced that individual to a mere paste.</p>
     <p>On the sidewalk the old man went into a spasm of delight and
called his attorney all the admiring and endearing names there were to be
had.</p>
     <p>'Lord, how you settled him!' he cried ecstatically.  They walked
slowly back toward Broadway.  'The scoundrel,' murmured the old man.
'I'll never see 'im again.  I'll desert 'im.  I'll find a nice quiet
boarding-place, and&mdash;'</p>
    <p>'That's all right,' said Tom.  'I know one.  I'll take you right up,'
which he did.</p>
     <p>He came near being happy ever after.  The old man lived at
advanced rates in the front room at Tom's boarding-house.  And the latter
basked in the proprietress's smiles, which had a commercial value and
were a great improvement on many we see.</p>
     <p>The old man, with his quantities of sage-bush, thought Thomas
owned all the virtues mentioned in high-class literature, and his opinion,
too, was of commercial value.  Also, he knew a man who knew another
man who received an impetus which made him engage Thomas on terms
that were highly satisfactory.  Then it was that the latter learned he had
not succeeded sooner because he did not know a man who knew another
man.</p>
     <p>So it came to pass that Tom grew to be Thomas G. Somebody.  He
achieved that position in life from which he could hold out for good
wines when he went to poor restaurants.  His name became entangled
with the name of Wilkins in the ownership of vast and valuable tracts of
sage-bush in Tin Can, Nevada.</p>
     <p>At the present day he is so great that he lunches frugally at high
prices.  His fame has spread through the land as a man who carved his
way to fortune with no help but his undaunted pluck, his tireless energy,
and his sterling integrity.</p>
<pb n="329"/>
    <p>Newspapers apply to him now, and he writes long signed articles to
struggling young men, in which he gives the best possible advice as to
how to become wealthy.  In these articles he, in a burst of glorification,
cites the king, queen, deuce, and tray, the four aces, and all that.  He
alludes tenderly to the nickel he borrowed and spent for cigarettes as the
foundation of his fortune.</p>
     <p>'To succeed in life,' he writes, 'the youth of America have only to
see an old man seated upon a railing and smoking a clay pipe.  Then go
up and ask him for a match.'</p>

                                      <closer><signed>STEPHEN CRANE.</signed></closer>

</div2>
		</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI.2>

