<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CraSerg"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="CraSerg">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Sergeant's Private Madhouse</title>
<title type="sort">sergeants private madhouse</title>
<author>Crane, Stephen, 1871-1900</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">21</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CraSerg</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475849</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>The creator of the electronic text has added the omitted
apostrophe to the contraction: 'em  in page 1, paragraph 11.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"The Sergeant's Private Madhouse"</title>
<title level="j">The Saturday Evening Post, 172</title>
<title type="sort">the sergeants private madhouse</title>
<author>Stephen Crane</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>George R. Graham &amp; Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>Philadelphia, PA</pubPlace>
<date value="1899-09-30">September 30, 1899</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>The Saturday Evening Post, Vol 172</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>UVa. Library Call Number: AP 2 .S2</p>
</note>
<note>
<p>The print copy was unavailable for examination.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899-09-30">September 30, 1899</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-01-24">January 24, 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jennifer Hanna</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI-compatible header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="story" id="d3">
	<pb n="214"/>
<head>
<hi rend="italic">The</hi> SERGEANT'S Private<lb/>
                             MADHOUSE<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">By</hi> Stephen Crane<lb/>
             <hi rend="italic">Copyright, 1899, in Great Britain</hi></head>


<p>THE moonlight was almost steady blue flame, and all this radiance
was lavished out upon a still, lifeless wilderness of stunted trees
and cactus plants.  The shadows lay upon the ground, pools of black
and sharply outlined, resembling substances, fabrics, and not
shadows at all.  From afar came the sound of the sea coughing among
the hollows in the coral rocks.
</p><p>The land was very empty; one could easily imagine that Cuba
was a simple, vast solitude; one could wonder at the moon taking
all the trouble of this splendid illumination.  There was no wind;
nothing seemed to live.
</p><p>But in a particular, large group of shadows lay an outpost of
some forty United States marines.  If it had been possible to
approach them from any direction without encountering one of their
sentries, one could have gone stumbling among sleeping men, and men
who sat waiting, their blankets tented over their heads; one would
have been in among them before one's mind could have decided
whether they were men or devils.  If a marine moved, he took the
care and the time of one who walks across a death-chamber.  The
Lieutenant in command reached for his watch, and the nickel chain
gave forth the slightest tinkling sound.  He could see the glisten
in five or six pairs of eyes that turned to regard him.  His
Sergeant lay near him, and he bent his face down to whisper: "Who's
on post behind the big cactus bush?"
</p><p>"Dryden," rejoined the Sergeant just over his breath.

</p><p>After a pause the lieutenant murmured: "He's got too many
nerves.  I shouldn't have put him there."  The Sergeant asked if he
should crawl down and look into affairs at Dryden's post.  The
young officer nodded assent, and the Sergeant, softly cocking his
rifle, went away on his hands and knees.  The Lieutenant, with his
back to a dwarf tree, sat watching the Sergeant's progress for the
few moments that he could see him moving from one shadow to
another.  Afterward the officer waited to hear Dryden's quick but
low-voiced challenge; but time passed, and no sound came from the
direction of the post behind the cactus bush.
</p><p>The Sergeant, as he came nearer and nearer to this cactus
bush&mdash;a number of peculiarly dignified columns throwing shadows of
inky darkness&mdash;had slowed his pace, for he did not wish to trifle
with the feelings of the sentry.  He was expecting his stern hail,
and was ready with the immediate answer which turns away wrath.  He
was not made anxious by the fact that he could not as yet see
Dryden, for he knew that the man would be hidden in a way practiced
by sentry marines since the time when two men had been killed by a
disease of excessive confidence on picket.  Indeed, as the Sergeant
went still nearer he became more and more angry.  Dryden was
evidently a most proper sentry.
</p><p>Finally he arrived at a point where he could see him seated in
the shadow, staring into the bushes ahead of him, his rifle ready
on his knee.  The Sergeant in his rage longed for the peaceful
precincts of the Washington Marine Barracks, where there would have
been no situation to prevent the most complete non-commissioned
oratory.  He felt indecent in his capacity of a man able to creep
up to the back of a G Company member on guard duty.  Never mind; in
the morning, back at camp&mdash;
</p><p>But suddenly he felt afraid.  There was something wrong with
Dryden.  He remembered old tales of comrades creeping out to find
a picket seated against a tree, perhaps upright enough, but stone
dead.  The Sergeant paused and gave the inscrutable back of the
sentry a long stare.  Dubious, he again moved forward.  At three
paces he hissed like a little snake.  Dryden did not show a sign of
hearing.  At last the Sergeant was in a position from which he was
able to reach out and touch Dryden on the arm.  Whereupon was
turned to him the face of a man livid with mad fright.  The
Sergeant grabbed him by the wrist and with discreet fury shook him.
"Here!  Pull yourself together!"

</p><p>Dryden paid no heed, but turned his wild face from the
newcomer to the ground in front.  "Don't you see 'em, Sergeant?
Don't you see 'em?"
</p><p>"Where?" whispered the Sergeant.
</p><p>"Ahead and a little on the right flank.  A reg'lar skirmish
line.  Don't you see 'em?"
</p><p>"Naw," whispered the Sergeant.
</p><p>Dryden began to shake.  He began moving one hand from his head
to his knee, and from his knee to his head rapidly, in a way that
is without explanation.  "I don't dare fire," he wept.  "If I do
they'll see me, and oh, how they'll pepper me!"
</p><p>The Sergeant, lying on his belly, understood one thing.
Dryden had gone mad.  Dryden was the March Hare.  The old man
gulped down his uproarious emotions as well as he was able, and
used the most simple device.  "Go," he said, "and tell the
Lieutenant, while I cover your post for you."
</p><p>"No!  They'd see me!  And they'd pepper me!  Oh, how they'd
pepper me!"
</p><p>The Sergeant was face to face with the biggest situation of
his life.  In the first place, he knew that at night a large or a
small force of Spanish guerrillas was never more than easy rifle-range from any marine outpost, both sides maintaining a secrecy as
absolute as possible in regard to their real position and strength.
Everything was on a watch-spring foundation.  A loud word might be
paid for by a night attack which would involve five hundred men who
needed their sleep, not to speak of some of them who would need
their lives.  The slip of a foot and the rolling of a pint of
gravel might go from consequence to consequence until various crews
went to general quarters on their ships in the harbor, their
batteries booming as the swift searchlight flashed through the
foliage.  Men would get killed&mdash;notably the Sergeant and Dryden&mdash;
and the outposts would be cut off, and the whole night would be one
pitiless turmoil.  And so Sergeant George H. Peasley began to run
his private madhouse behind the cactus bush.

</p><p>"Dryden," said the Sergeant, "you do as I told you, and go
tell the Lieutenant."
</p><p>"I don't dare move," shivered the man.  "They'll see me if I
move; they'll see me.  They're almost up now.  Let's hide&mdash;"
"Well, then you stay here a moment and I'll go and&mdash;"
</p><p>Dryden turned upon him a look so tigerish that the old man
felt his hair move.  "Don't you stir!" he hissed.  "You want to
give me away?  You want them to see me?  Don't you stir!"  The
Sergeant decided not to stir.
</p><p>He became aware of the slow wheeling of eternity, its majestic
incomprehensibility of movement.  Seconds, moments, were quaint
little things, tangible as toys, and there were billions of them,
all alike.
</p><p>"Dryden," he whispered at the end of a century, in which,
curiously, he had never joined the marine corps at all, but had
taken to another walk of life and prospered greatly in it&mdash;"Dryden,
this is all foolishness!"
</p><p>He thought of the expedient of smashing the man over the head
with his rifle, but Dryden was so supernaturally alert that there
surely would issue some small scuffle, and there could be not even
the fraction of a scuffle.  The Sergeant relapsed into the
contemplation of another century.  His patient had one fine virtue.
He was in such terror of the phantom skirmish line that his voice
never went above a whisper, whereas his delusion might have
expressed itself in coyote yells and shots from his rifle.  The
Sergeant, shuddering, had visions of how it might have been&mdash;the
mad private leaping into the air and howling and shooting at his
friends, and making them the centre of the enemy's eager attention.
This, to his mind, would have been conventional conduct for a
maniac.  The trembling victim of an idea was somewhat puzzling.
The Sergeant decided that from time to time he would reason with
his patient.  "Look here, Dryden, you don't see any real Spaniards.
You've been drinking or&mdash;something.  Now&mdash;"
</p><p>But Dryden only glared him into silence.  Dryden was inspired
with such a profound contempt of him that it had become hatred.
"Don't you stir!"  And it was clear that if the Sergeant did stir
the mad private would introduce calamity.  "Now," said Peasley to
himself, "If those guerrillas <hi rend="italic">should</hi> take a crack at us to-night, they'd find a lunatic asylum in front, and it would be
astonishing."
</p><p>The silence of the night was broken by the quick, low voice of
a sentry to the left some distance.  The breathless stillness
brought an effect to the words as if they had been spoken in one's
ear.
</p><p>"Halt!  Who's there?  Halt, or I'll fire!"  Bang!
</p><p>At the moment of sudden attack, particularly at night, it is
improbable that a man registers much detail of either thought or
action.  He may afterward say: "I was here."  He may say: "I was
there"; "I did this"; "I did that."  But there remains a great
incoherency because of the tumultuous thought which seethes through
the head.
</p><p>"Is this defeat?"  At night in a wilderness, and against
skillful foes half seen, one does not trouble to ask if it is also
death.  Defeat is death, then, save for the miraculous ones.  But
the exaggerating, magnifying first thought subsides in the ordered
mind of the soldier, and he knows, soon, what he is doing, and how
much of it.  The Sergeant's immediate impulse had been to squeeze
close to the ground and listen&mdash;listen; above all else, listen.
But the next moment he grabbed his private asylum by the scruff of
its neck, jerked it to its feet, and started to retreat upon the
main outpost.
</p><p>To the left, rifle-flashes were bursting from the shadows.  To
the rear, the Lieutenant was giving some hoarse order or caution.
Through the air swept some Spanish bullets, very high, as if they
had been fired at a man in a tree.  The private asylum came on so
hastily that the Sergeant found he could remove his grip, and soon
they were in the midst of the men of the outpost.  Here there was
no occasion for enlightening the Lieutenant.  In the first place,
such surprises require statement, question and answer.  It is
impossible to get a grossly original and fantastic idea through a
man's head in less than one minute of rapid talk, and the Sergeant
knew that the Lieutenant could not spare the minute.  He himself
had no minute to devote to anything but the business of the
outpost.  And the madman disappeared from his ken, and he forgot
about him.
</p><p>It was a long night, and the little fight was as long as the
night.  It was heartbreaking work.  The forty marines lay in an
irregular oval.  From all sides the Mauser bullets sang low and
swift.  The occupation of the Americans was to prevent a rush, and
to this end they potted carefully at the flash of a Mauser&mdash;save
when they got excited for a moment, in which case their magazines
rattled like a great Waterbury watch.  Then they settled again to
a systematic potting.

</p><p>The enemy were not of the regular Spanish forces, but of a
corps of guerrillas, native-born Cubans, who preferred the flag of
Spain.  They were all men who knew the craft of the woods and were
all recruited from the district.  They fought more like red Indians
than any people but the red Indians themselves.  Each seemed to
possess an individuality, a fighting individuality, which is only
found in the highest order of irregular soldier.  Personally, they
were as distinct as possible, but through equality of knowledge and
experience they arrived at concert of action.  So long as they
operated in the wilderness they were formidable troops.  It
mattered little whether it was daylight or dark, they were mainly
invisible.  They had schooled from the Cubans insurgent to Spain.
As the Cubans fought the Spanish troops, so would these particular
Spanish troops fight the Americans.  It was wisdom.
</p><p>The marines thoroughly understood the game.  They must lie
close and fight until daylight, when the guerrillas would promptly
go away.  They had withstood other nights of this kind, and now
their principal emotion was a sort of frantic annoyance.
</p><p>Back at the main camp, whenever the roaring volleys lulled,
the men in the trenches could hear their comrades of the outpost
and the guerrillas pattering away interminably.  The moonlight
faded and left an equal darkness upon the wilderness.  A man could
barely see the comrade at his side.  Sometimes guerrillas crept so
close that the flame from their rifles seemed to scorch the faces
of the marines, and the reports sounded as if within two or three
inches of their very noses.  If a pause came, one could hear the
guerrillas gabbling to each other in a kind of delirium.  The
Lieutenant was praying that the ammunition would last.  Everybody
was praying for daylight.
</p><p>A black hour came finally when the men were not fit to have
their troubles increase.  The enemy made a wild attack on one
portion of the oval which was held by about fifteen men.  The
remainder of the force was busy enough, and the fifteen were
naturally left to their devices.  Amid the whirl of it, a loud
voice suddenly broke out in song:
</p>
<l>     "The minstrel boy to the war has gone,</l>
<l>        In the ranks of death you'll find him;</l>
<l>      His father's sword he has girded on,</l>
<l>        And his wild harp slung behind him."</l>

<p>"Who the deuce is that?" demanded the Lieutenant from a throat
full of smoke.  There was almost a full stop of the firing.  The
Americans were puzzled.  Practical ones muttered that the fool
should have a bayonet-hilt shoved down his throat.  Others felt a
thrill at the strangeness of the thing.  Perhaps it was a sign!
</p>
<l>     "While shepherds watched their flocks by night,</l>
<l>        All seated on the ground,</l>
<l>      The angel of the Lord came down,</l>
<l>        And glory shone around."</l>
<p>This croak was as lugubrious as a coffin.  "Who is it?  Who is
it?" snapped the Lieutenant.  "Stop him, somebody!"
</p><p>"It's Dryden, sir," said old Sergeant Peasley as he felt
around in the darkness for his madhouse.  "I can't find him&mdash;yet."
</p><p>"Please, oh, please&mdash;oh, do not let me fall!
</p><p>You're&mdash;gurgh&mdash;ugh&mdash;"
</p><p>The Sergeant had pounced upon him.
</p><p>The singing had had an effect upon the Spaniards.  At first
they had fired frenziedly at the voice, but they soon <pb n="215"/>
ceased, perhaps from sheer amazement.  Both sides took a spell of
meditation.
</p><p>The Sergeant was having some difficulty with his charge.
"Here, you, grab 'im!  Take 'im by the throat!  Be quiet, you
idiot!"
</p><p>One of the fifteen men who had been hard pressed called out,
"We've only got about one clip apiece, Lieutenant.  If they come
again&mdash;"
</p><p>The Lieutenant crawled to and fro among his men, taking clips
of cartridges from those who had many.  He came upon the Sergeant
and his madhouse.  He felt Dryden's belt and found it simply
stuffed with ammunition.  He examined Dryden's rifle and found in
it a full clip.  The madhouse had not fired a shot.  The Lieutenant
distributed these valuable prizes among the fifteen men.  As they
gratefully took them, one said, "If they had come again hard enough
they would have had us, sir&mdash;maybe."

</p><p>But the Spaniards did not come again.  At the first indication
of daybreak they fired their customary good-by volley.  The marines
lay tight while the slow dawn crept over the land.  Finally the
Lieutenant arose among them, and he was a bewildered man, but very
angry.  "Now, where is that idiot, Sergeant?"
</p><p>"Here he is, sir," said the old man cheerfully.  He was seated
on the ground beside the recumbent Dryden, who, with an innocent
smile on his face, was sound asleep.
</p><p>"Wake him up," said the Lieutenant briefly.
</p><p>The Sergeant shook the sleeper.  "Here, Minstrel Boy, turn
out.  The Lieutenant wants you."
</p><p>Dryden climbed to his feet and saluted the officer with a
dazed and childish air.  "Yes, sir."
</p><p>The Lieutenant was obviously having difficulty in governing
his feelings, but he managed to say with calmness: "You seem to be
fond of singing, Dryden?  Sergeant, see if he has any whiskey on
him."
</p><p>"Sir?" said the madhouse, stupefied.  "Singing&mdash;fond of
singing?"

</p><p>Here the Sergeant interposed gently, and he and the Lieutenant
held palaver apart from the others.  The marines, hitching more
comfortably their almost empty belts, spoke with grins of the
madhouse.  "Well, the Minstrel Boy made 'em clear out.  They
couldn't stand it.  But&mdash;I wouldn't want to be in his boots.  He'll
see fireworks when the old man interviews him on the uses of grand
opera in modern warfare.  How do you think he managed to smuggle a
bottle along without us finding it out?"
</p><p>When the weary outpost was relieved and marched back to camp,
the men could not rest until they had told a tale of the voice in
the wilderness.  In the meantime the Sergeant took Dryden aboard a
ship, and to those who assumed charge of the man he defined him as
"the most useful crazy man in the service of the United States."</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
