<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CraSeco"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="CraSeco">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Second Generation</title>
<title type="sort">second generation</title>
<author>Crane, Stephen, 1871-1900</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">50</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CraSeco</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475847</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Judy Boss has made the following changes to the text:
PAGE	PARA.	LINE	ORIGINAL	CHANGED TO
 736 	23		'I'll		I'll
 738	 3	7	fetlessly	fecklessly
 743			IV		IV.
 748			VI		VI.
 752	 6	1  	The		'The
 752	 9	2  	abode		 adobe</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Second Generation</title>
<title level="j">Cornhill Magazine</title>
<title type="sort">second generation</title>
<author>Stephen Crane</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Smith, Elder &amp; Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
<date value="1899-12">December 1899</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Cornhill Magazine 80 (n.s. 7), 734-753. Copy consulted:
University of Virginia Library call number Microfilm S-299, 550CM. V. 76-80,
July 1897-Dec.1899, Reel 15.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using
WordPerfect spell checker.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing
part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to
aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed
of the text'sunique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for
page one of Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-07">July 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jessamy Town, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">


<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<pb n="734"/>
<head>THE SECOND GENERATION<ref target="n1">[1]</ref>
<lb/>
BY STEPHEN CRANE</head>

<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d4">
<head>I.</head>
<p>
CASPER CADOGAN resolved to go to the tropic wars and do
something.  The air was blue and gold with the pomp of soldiering, and
in every ear rang the music of military glory.  Casper's father was a
United States senator, from the great state of Skowmulligan, where the
war fever ran very high.  Chill is the blood of many of the sons of
millionaires, but Casper took the fever and posted to Washington.  His
father had never denied him anything, and this time all that Casper
wanted was a little captaincy in the army, just a simple little captaincy.
</p><p>The old man had just been entertaining a delegation of respectable
bunco-steerers from Skowmulligan, who had come to him on a matter
which is none of the public's business.  Bottles of whisky and boxes of
cigars were still on the table in the sumptuous private parlour.  The
senator had said, 'Well, gentlemen, I'll do what I can for you.'  By this
sentence he meant whatever he meant.
</p><p>Then he turned to his eager son.  'Well, Casper?'  The youth poured
out his modest desires.  It was not altogether his fault.  Life had taught
him a generous faith in his own abilities.  If any one had told him that he
was an ordinary damned fool, he would have opened his eyes wide at the
person's lack of judgment.  All his life people had admired him.
</p><p>The Skowmulligan war-horse looked with quick disapproval into
the eyes of his son.  'Well, Casper,' he said slowly, 'I am of the opinion
that they've got all the golf experts and tennis champions, and cotillion
leaders, and piano tuners, and billiard markers they really need as
officers.  Now, if you were a soldier&mdash;'
</p><p>'I know,' said the young man, with a gesture, 'but I'm not exactly a
fool, I hope, and I think if I get a chance, I can do something.  I'd like to
try, I would indeed.'
</p><p>The senator drank a neat whisky and lit a cigar.  He


<pb n="735"/>
assumed an attitude of ponderous reflection.  'Y-yes; but this
country is full of young men who are not fools.  Full of 'em.'
</p><p>Casper fidgeted in the desire to answer that while he admitted the
profusion of young men who were not fools, he felt that he himself
possessed interesting and peculiar qualifications which would allow him
to make his mark in any field of effort which he seriously challenged.
But he did not make this graceful statement, because he sometimes
detected something ironic in his father's temperament.  The
Skowmulligan war-horse had not thought of expressing an opinion of his
own ability since the year 1865, when he was young like Casper.

</p><p>'Well, well,' said the senator finally, 'I'll see about
it&mdash;I'll see about it.' The young man was obliged to await the end of
his father's characteristic method of thought.  The war-horse never
gave a quick answer, and if people tried to hurry him, they seemed
able to arouse in him only a feeling of irritation against making a
decision at all.  His mind moved like the wind, but practice had
placed a Mexican bit in the mouth of his judgment.  This old man of
light quick thought had taught himself to move like an ox-cart.
Casper said, 'Yes, sir.' He withdrew to his club, where, to the
affectionate inquiries of some envious friends, he replied, 'The old
man is letting the idea soak.'

</p><p>The mind of the war-horse was decided far sooner than Casper
expected.  In Washington a large number of well-bred handsome young
men were receiving appointments as lieutenants, as captains, and
occasionally as majors.  They were a strong, healthy, clean-eyed,
educated collection.  They were a prime lot.  A German field-marshal
would have beamed with joy if he could have seen them&mdash;to send to
school.  Anywhere in the world they would have made a grand show as
material, but, intrinsically, they were not lieutenants, captains, and
majors.  They were fine men.  Individual to individual, American
manhood overmatches the best in Europe; but manhood is only an
essential part of a lieutenant, a captain, or a major.  But at any
rate it had all the logic of going to sea in a bathing-machine.
</p><p>The senator found himself reasoning that Casper was as good as
any of them, and better than many.  Presently he was bleating here and
there that his boy should have a chance.  'The boy's all right, I tell
you, Henery.  He's wild to go, and I don't see why they shouldn't give
him a show.  He's got plenty of nerve, and he's keen as a whip-lash.
I'm going to get him an appointment

<pb n="736"/> and if you can do anything to help it along, I wish you
would.' Then he betook himself to the White House and the War
Department and made a stir.  People think that administrations are
always slavishly, abominably anxious to please the machine.  They are
not; they wish the machine sunk in red fire, for by the power of ten
thousand past words, looks, gestures, writings, the machine comes
along and takes the administration by the nose and twists it, and the
administration does not even yell.  The huge force which carries an
election to success looks reproachfully at the administration, and
says, 'Give me a penny!' That is a very small amount with which to
reward a colossus.  </p><p>The Skowmulligan war-horse got his penny
and took it to his hotel, where Casper was moodily reading
war-rumours.  'Well, my boy, here you are.' Casper was a captain and
commissary on the staff of Brigade-General Reilly, Commander of the
Second Brigade of the First Division of the Thirtieth Army Corps.  'I
had to work for it,' said the senator grimly.  'They talked to me as
if they thought you were some sort of empty-headed idiot.  None of 'em
seemed to know you personally.  They just sort of took it for
granted.  Finally, I got pretty hot in the collar.' He paused a
moment; his heavy grooved face set hard; his blue eyes shone.  He
clapped a hand down upon the handle of his chair.  'Casper, I've got
you into this thing, and I believe you'll do all right, and I'm not
saying this because I distrust either your sense or your grit.  But I
want you to understand you've <hi rend="italic">got to make a go of
it</hi>.  I'm not going to talk any twaddle about your country, and
your country's flag.  You understand all about that.  But, now, you're
a soldier, and there'll be this to do and that to do, and fightin' to
do, and you've got to do <hi rend="italic">every damned one of
'em</hi> right up to the handle.  I don't know how much of a shindy
this thing is goin' to be, but any shindy is enough to show how much
there is in a man.  You've got your appointment, and that's all I can
do for you; but I'll thrash you with my own hands, if, when the army
gets back, the other fellows say my son is <hi rend="italic">
nothin' but a good-lookin' dude</hi>.' </p>

<p>He ceased,
breathing heavily.  Casper looked bravely and frankly at his father
and answered, in a voice which was not very tremulous, 'I'll do my
best.  This is my chance; I'll do my best with it.' </p><p>The senator
had a marvellous ability of transition from one manner to another.
Suddenly he seemed very kindly.  'Well,

<pb n="737"/>
that's all
right, then.  I guess you'll get along all right with Reilly.  I know him
well, and he'll see you through.  I helped him along once.  And now
about this commissary business.  As I understand it, a commissary is a
sort of caterer in a big way.  That is, he looks out for a good many more
things than a caterer has to bother his head about.  Reilly's brigade has
probably from two to three thousand men in it, and in regard to certain
things you've got to look out for every man of 'em every day.  I know
perfectly well you couldn't successfully run a boarding-house in Ocean
Grove.  How you goin' to manage for all these soldiers, hey?  Thought
about it?'
</p><p>'No,' said Casper, injured.  'I didn't want to be a commissary.  I
wanted to be a captain of the line.'
</p><p>'They wouldn't hear of it.  They said you would have to take a staff
appointment where people could look after you.'
</p><p>'Well, let them look after me,' cried Casper resentfully; 'but when
there's any fighting to be done, I guess I won't necessarily be the last
man.'
</p><p>'That's it,' responded the senator.  'That's the spirit.'  They both
thought that the problem of war would eliminate to an equation of actual
battle.
</p><p>Ultimately, Casper departed into the south to an encampment in
salty grass under pine trees.  Here lay an army corps twenty thousand
strong.  Casper passed into the dusty sunshine of it, and for many weeks
he was lost to view.
</p>
<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">[1]</seg><p>Copyright 1899 by Stephen Crane in the United States of America.</p></note>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d5">
<head>II.</head>
<div3 type="subsection" id="d6">
<p>
'OF course, I don't know a damn thing about it,' said Casper, frankly and
modestly, to a circle of his fellow staff officers.  He was referring to the
duties of his office.
</p><p>Their faces became expressionless; they looked at him with eyes in
which he could fathom nothing.  After a pause, one politely said: 'Don't
you?'  It was the inevitable two words of convention.
</p>

<p>'Why,' cried Casper, 'I didn't know what a commissary officer was
until I <hi rend="italic">was</hi> one.  My old guv'nor told me.
He'd looked it up in a book somewhere, I suppose.  But I didn't know.'
</p>

<p>'Didn't you?'
</p><p>The young man's face glowed with sudden humour.  'Do


<pb n="738"/>
you know&mdash;the word was intimately associated in my mind with camels.
Funny, eh?  I think it came from reading that rhyme of Kipling's about
the commissariat camel.'
</p><p>'Did it?'
</p><p>'Yes; funny, isn't it?  Camels!'
</p><p>The brigade was ultimately landed at Siboney, as part of an army to
attack Santiago.  The scene at the landing sometimes resembled the
inspiriting daily drama at the approach to the Brooklyn Bridge.  There
was a great bustle, during which the wise man kept his property gripped
in his hands lest it might march off into the wilderness in the pocket of
one of the striding regiments.  Truthfully, Casper should have had frantic
occupation; but men saw him wandering fecklessly here and there,
crying: 'Has any one seen my saddle-bags?  Why, if I lose 'em, I'm ruined.
I've got everything packed away in 'em&mdash;everything.'
</p><p>They looked at him gloomily and without attention.  'No,' they said.
It was to intimate that they would not give three whoops in Hades if he
had lost his nose, his teeth, and his self-respect.  Reilly's brigade
collected itself from the boats and went off, each regiment's soul burning
with anger because some other regiment was in advance of it.  Moving
along through the scrub and under the palms, men talked mostly of things
that did not pertain to the business in hand.
</p><p>General Reilly finally planted his headquarters in some tall grass
under a mango tree.  'Where's Cadogan?' he said suddenly, as he took off
his hat and smoothed the wet grey hair from his brow.  Nobody knew.
</p><p>'I saw him looking for his saddle-bags down at the landing,' said an
officer dubiously.
</p><p>'Bother him!' said the General contemptuously.  'Let him stay there.'
</p><p>Three venerable regimental commanders came, saluted stiffly, and
sat in the grass.  There was a pow-wow, during which Reilly explained
much that the division-commander had told him.  The venerable colonels
nodded; they understood.  Everything was smooth and clear to their
minds.  But still the colonel of the 44th Regular Infantry murmured about
the commissariat.  His men&mdash;  And then he launched forth in a sentiment
concerning the privations of his men, in which you were confronted with
his feeling that his men&mdash;his men&mdash;were the only creatures of importance
in the universe, which feeling was entirely correct for him.  Reilly
grunted.  He did what most


<pb n="739"/>
commanders did&mdash;he set the
competent line to do the work of the incompetent part of the staff.
</p><p>In time Casper came trudging along the road, merrily swinging his
saddle-bags.  'Well, General,' he cried as he saluted, 'I found 'em.'  'Did
you?' said Reilly.  Later an officer rushed to him tragically.  'General,
Cadogan is off there in the bushes eatin' potted ham and crackers all by
himself.'  The officer was sent back into the bushes for Casper, and the
General sent Casper with an order.  Then Reilly and the three venerable
colonels, grinning, partook of potted ham and crackers.  'Tashe a' right,'
said Reilly with his mouth full.  'Dorsey, see if 'e got some'n else.'
</p><p>'Mush be selfish young pig,' said one of the colonels, with his
mouth full.  'Who's he, General?'
</p><p>'Son&mdash;Sen'tor Cad'gan&mdash;ol' frien' mine&mdash;damn 'im.'

</p></div3>

<div3 type="letter" id="d7">
<p>Casper wrote a letter:</p>

<p>'Dear Father,</p>

<p>&mdash;I am sitting under a tree using the
flattest part of my canteen as a desk.  Even as I write the division
ahead of us is moving forward, and we don't know what moment the storm
of battle may break out.  I don't know what the plans are.  General
Reilly knows, but he is so good as to give me very little of his
confidence.  In fact, I might be part of a forlorn hope from all to
the contrary I've heard from him.  I understood you to say, in
Washington, that you at one time had been of some service to him; but,
if that is true, I can assure you he has completely forgotten it.  At
times his manner to me is little short of being offensive; but, of
course, I understand that it is only the way of a crusty old soldier
who has been made boorish and bearish by a long life among the
Indians.  I dare say I shall manage it all right without a row.  When
you hear that we have captured Santiago, please send me by first
steamer a box of provisions and clothing&mdash; particularly sardines,
pickles, and light-weight underclothing.  The other men on the staff
are nice quiet chaps, but they seem a bit crude.  There has been no
fighting yet, save the skirmish by Young's brigade.  Reilly was
furious because we couldn't get in it.  I met General Peel yesterday.
He was very nice.  He said he knew you well when he was in Congress.
Young Jack May is on Peel's staff; I knew him well in College.  We
spent an hour talking over old times.  Give my love to all at
home.'</p></div3>
<div3 type="subsection" id="d8">
<p>The march was leisurely.  Reilly and his staff strolled out to the
head of the long sinuous column, and entered the sultry gloom of the
forest.  Some less fortunate regiments had to wait


<pb n="740"/>
among the
trees at the side of the trail, and, as Reilly's brigade passed them, officer
called to officer, class-mate to class-mate, in which rang a note of
everything from Westpoint to Alaska.  They were going into an action in
which they, the officers, would lose over a hundred in killed and
wounded&mdash;officers alone; and these greetings, in which many nicknames
occurred, were in many cases farewells, such as one pictures being given
with ostentation, solemnity, fervour.  'There goes Gory Widgeon!  Hello,
Gory!  Where you starting for? eh, Gory?'
</p><p>Casper communed with himself, and decided that he was not
frightened.  He was eager and alert; he thought that now his obligation to
his country, or himself, was to be faced, and he was mad to prove to old
Reilly and the others that after all he was a very capable soldier.
</p>
</div3>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="3" id="d9">
<head> III.</head>
<p>
OLD Reilly was stumping along the line of his brigade and mumbling
like a man with a mouthful of grass.  The fire from the enemy's position
was incredible in its swift fury, and Reilly's brigade was setting its share
of a very bad ordeal.  The old man's face was of the colour of a tomato,
and in his rage he mouthed and sputtered strangely.  As he pranced along
his thin line, scornfully erect, voices arose from the grass beseeching him
to take care of himself.  At his heels scrambled a bugler, with pallid skin
and clenched teeth, a chalky trembling youth, who kept his eye on old
Reilly's back and followed it.
</p><p>The old gentleman was quite mad.  Apparently he thought the
whole thing a dreadful mess; but now that his brigade was irrevocably in
it, he was full tilting here and everywhere to establish some
irreproachable immaculate kind of behaviour on the part of every man-jack
in his brigade.  The intentions of the three venerable colonels were
the same.  They stood behind their lines, quiet, stern, courteous, old
fellows, admonishing their regiments to be very pretty in the face of such
a hail of magazine-rifle and machine-gun fire as has never in this world
been fronted, save by the beardless savages when the white man has
found occasion to take his burden to some new place.
</p><p>And the regiments were pretty.  The men lay on their little stomachs
and got peppered according to the law, and said nothing as the good
blood pumped out into the grass; and even if a solitary


<pb n="741"/>  rookie tried to get a decent reason to move to some haven
of rational men, the cold voice of an officer made him look criminal
with a shame that was a credit to his regimental education.  Behind
Reilly's command was a bullet-torn jungle, through which it could not
move as a brigade; ahead of it were Spanish trenches on hills.  Reilly
considered that he was in a fix, no doubt, but he said this only to
himself.  Suddenly he saw on the right a little point of blue-shirted
men already halfway up the hill.  It was some pathetic fragment of the
6th United States Infantry.  Chagrined, shocked, horrified, Reilly
bellowed to his bugler, and the chalk-faced youth unlocked his teeth
and sounded the charge by rushes.  The men formed hastily and grimly,
and rushed.  Apparently there awaited them only the fate of
respectable soldiers.  But they went because of the opinions of the
others, perhaps.  They went because no low-down, loud-mouthed,
pie-faced lot of jail-birds, such as the 27th Infantry, could do
anything that they could not do better.  They went because Reilly
ordered it.  They went because they went.  </p><p>And yet not a man of
them to this day has made a public speech explaining precisely how he
did the whole thing, and detailing with what initiative and ability he
comprehended and defeated a situation which he did not comprehend at
all.  </p><p>Reilly never saw the top of the hill.  He was heroically
striving to keep up with his men when a bullet ripped quietly through
his left lung, and he fell back into the arms of the bugler, who
received him as he would have received a Christmas present.  The three
venerable colonels inherited the brigade in swift succession.  The
senior commanded for about fifty seconds, at the end of which he was
mortally shot.  The junior colonel ultimately arrived with a lean and
puffing little brigade at the top of the hill.  The men lay down and
fired volleys at whatever was practicable.

</p><p>In and out of the ditch-like trenches lay the Spanish dead,
lemon-faced corpses dressed in shabby blue-and-white ticking.  Some
were huddled down comfortably, like sleeping children; one had died in
the attitude of a man flung back in a dentist's chair; one sat in the
trench with its chin sunk despondently to its breast; few preserved a
record of the agitation of battle.  With the greater number it was as
if death had touched them so gently, so lightly, that they had not
known of it.  Death had

<pb n="742"/>
come to them more in the form of an opiate than of a
bloody blow.
</p><p>But the arrived men in the blue shirts had no thought of the sallow
corpses.  They were eagerly exchanging a hail of shots with the Spanish
second line, whose ash-coloured entrenchments barred the way to a city
white amid trees.  In the pauses the men talked.
</p><p>'We done the best.  Old E company got there.  Why, one time the
hull of P company was <hi rend="italic">behind</hi> us.  Hell!'
</p><p>'Jones, he was the first man up.  I saw 'im.'
</p><p>'<hi rend="italic">Which</hi> Jones?'
</p><p>'Did you see ol' Two-bars runnin' like a land crab?  Made good
time, too.  He hit only in the high places.  He's all right.'
</p><p>'The lootenant is all right, too.  He was a good ten yards ahead of
the best of us.  I hated him at the post, but for this here active service
there's none of 'em can touch him.'
</p><p>'This is mighty different from being at the post.'
</p>

<p>'Well, we done it, an' it wasn't b'cause <hi
rend="italic">I</hi> thought it could be done.  When we started, I
ses to m'self: "Well, here goes a lot a' damned fools."' </p>

<p>''Tain't over yet.'
</p><p>'Oh, they'll never git us back from here.  If they start to chase us
back from here, we'll pile 'em up so high the last ones can't climb over.
We've come this far an' we'll stay here.  I ain't done pantin'.'
</p><p>'Anything is better than packin' through that jungle, an' gettin'
blistered from front, rear, an' both flanks.  I'd rather tackle another hill
than go trailin' in them woods so thick you can't tell whether you are one
man or a division of cav'lry.'
</p><p>'Where's that young kitchen-soldier, Cadogan, or whatever his name
is?  Ain't seen him to-day.'
</p><p>'Well, I seen him.  He was right in with it.  He got shot, too, about
half up the hill, in the leg.  I seen it.  He's all right.  Don't worry about
him.  He's all right.'
</p><p>'I seen 'im, too.  He done his stunt.  As soon as I can git this piece
of barbed-wire entanglement out a' me throat, I'll give 'im a cheer.'
</p><p>'He ain't shot at all, b'cause there he stands there.  See 'im?'
</p><p>Rearward, the grassy slope was populous with little groups of men
searching for the wounded.  Reilly's brigade began to dig with its
bayonets, and shovel with its meat-ration cans.
</p>
</div2>

<pb n="743"/>


<div2 type="section" n="4" id="d10">
<head>IV.</head>
<p>
SENATOR CADOGAN paced to and fro in his private parlour, and
smoked small brown weak cigars.  These little whisps seemed utterly
inadequate to console such a ponderous satrap.
</p><p>It was the evening of the 1st of July, 1898, and the senator was
immensely excited, as could be seen from the superlatively calm way in
which he called out to his private secretary, who was in an adjoining
room.  The voice was serene, gentle, affectionate, low.  'Baker, I wish
you'd go over again to the War Department and see if they've heard
anything about Casper.'
</p><p>A very bright-eyed hatchet-faced young man appeared in a
doorway, pen still in hand.  He was hiding a nettle-like irritation behind
all the finished audacity of a smirk, sharp, lying, trustworthy young
politician.  'I've just got back from there, sir,' he suggested.
</p><p>The Skowmulligan war-horse lifted his eyes and looked for a short
second into the eyes of his private secretary.  It was not a glare or an
eagle glance; it was something beyond the practice of an actor; it was
simply meaning.  The clever private secretary grabbed his hat and was at
once enthusiastically away.  'All right, sir,' he cried, 'I'll find out.'
</p><p>The War Department was ablaze with light, and messengers were
running.  With the assurance of a retainer of an old house, Baker made
his way through much small-calibre vociferation.  There was rumour of a
big victory; there was rumour of a big defeat.  In the corridors various
watch-dogs arose from their armchairs and asked him of his business in
tones of uncertainty, which in no wise compared with their previous
habitual deference to the private secretary of the war-horse of
Skowmulligan.
</p><p>Ultimately Baker arrived in a room where some kind of a head-clerk sat
feverishly writing at a roller-topped desk.  Baker asked a
question, and the head-clerk mumbled profanely without lifting his head.
Apparently he said, 'How in the blankety-blank blazes do I know?'
</p><p>The private secretary let his jaw fall.  Surely some new spirit had
come suddenly upon the heart of Washington, a spirit which Baker
understood to be almost defiantly indifferent to the wishes of Senator
Cadogan, a spirit which was not even courteously oily.


<pb n="744"/>
What could it mean?  Baker's fox-like mind sprang wildly to a conception of
overturned factions, changed friends, new combinations.  The assurance
which had come from a broad political situation suddenly left him, and
he could not have been amazed if some one had told him that Senator
Cadogan now controlled only six votes in the State of Skowmulligan.
'Well,' he stammered in his bewilderment, 'well&mdash;there isn't any news of
the old man's son, hey?'  Again the head-clerk replied blasphemously.
</p><p>Eventually Baker retreated in disorder from the presence of this
head-clerk, having learned that the latter did not give a &mdash; if Casper
Cadogan was sailing through Hades on an ice-yacht.
</p><p>Baker assailed other and more formidable officials.  In fact, he
struck as high as he dared.  They, one and all, flung him short hard
words, even as men pelt an annoying cur with pebbles.  He emerged from
the brilliant light, from the groups of men with anxious puzzled faces,
and as he walked back to the hotel, he did not know if his name was
Baker or Cholmondeley.
</p><p>However, as he walked up the stairs to the senator's rooms, he
continued to concentrate his intellect upon a manner of speaking.
</p><p>The war-horse was still pacing his parlour and smoking.  He paused
at Baker's entrance.  'Well?'
</p><p>'Mr. Cadogan,' said the private secretary coolly, 'they told me at the
department that they did not give a gawd dam whether your son was alive
or dead.'
</p><p>The senator looked at Baker and smiled gently.  'What's that, my
boy?' he asked in a soft and considerate voice.
</p><p>'They said&mdash;' gulped Baker with a certain tenacity.  'They said that
they didn't give a gawd dam whether your son was alive or dead.'
</p><p>There was a silence for the space of three seconds.  Baker stood
like an image; he had no machinery for balancing the issues of this kind
of a situation, and he seemed to feel that if he stood as still as a stone
frog he would escape the ravages of a terrible senatorial wrath which was
about to break forth in a hurricane speech which would snap off trees and
sweep away barns.
</p><p>'Well,' drawled the senator lazily, 'who did you see, Baker?'
</p><p>The private secretary resumed a certain usual manner of breathing.
He told the names of the men whom he had seen.
</p><p>'Ye-e-es,' remarked the senator.  He took another little

<pb n="745"/>  brown cigar and held it with a thumb and first finger,
staring at it with the calm and steady scrutiny of a scientist
investigating a new thing.  'So they don't care whether Casper is
alive or dead, eh?  Well&mdash;maybe they don't.  That's all right.
However, I think I'll just look in on 'em and state my views.'
</p><p>When the senator had gone, the private secretary ran to the
window and leaned far out.  Pennsylvania Avenue was gleaming silver
blue in the light of many arc-lamps; the cable trains groaned along to
the clangour of gongs; from the window the walks presented a hardly
diversified aspect of shirt-waists and straw hats; sometimes a newsboy
screeched.  </p> <p>Baker watched the tall heavy figure of the senator
moving out to intercept a cable train.  'Great Scot!' cried the
private secretary to himself, 'there'll be three distinct kinds of
grand, plain, practical fireworks.  The old man is going for 'em.  I
wouldn't be in Lascum's boots.  Ye gods, what a row there'll be!' </p>
<p>In due time the senator was closeted with some kind of deputy
third-assistant battery-horse in the offices of the War Department.
The official obviously had been told off to make a supreme effort to
pacify Cadogan, and he certainly was acting according to his
instructions.  He was almost in tears; he spread out his hands in
supplication, and his voice whined and wheedled.  'Why, really, you
know, senator, we can only beg you to look at the circumstances.  Two
scant divisions at the top of that hill; over a thousand men killed
and wounded; the lines so thin that any strong attack would smash our
army to flinders.  The Spaniards have probably received reinforcements
under Pando; Shafter seems to be too ill to be actively in command of
our troops; Lawton can't get up with his division before to-morrow.
We are actually expecting&mdash;no, I won't say expecting&mdash;but we would not
be surprised&mdash;nobody in the department would be surprised if, before
daybreak, we were compelled to give to the country the news of a
disaster, which would be the worst blow the national pride has ever
suffered.  Don't you see?  Can't you see our position, senator?'
</p><p>The senator, with a pale but composed face, contemplated the
official with eyes that gleamed in a way not usual with the big
self-controlled politician.  </p><p>'I'll tell you frankly, sir,'
continued the other.  'I'll tell you frankly that at this moment we
don't know whether we are a-foot or a-horseback. Everything is in the
air.  We don't know

<pb n="746"/>
whether we have won a
glorious victory or simply got ourselves in a devil of a fix.'
</p><p>The senator coughed.  'I suppose my boy is with the two divisions
at the top of that hill?  He's with Reilly.'
</p><p>'Yes; Reilly's brigade is up there.'
</p><p>'And when do you suppose the War Department can tell me if he is
all right?  I want to know.'
</p><p>'My dear senator&mdash;frankly, I don't know.  Again I beg you to think of
our position&mdash;the army in a muddle; its General thinking that he must fall
back; and yet not sure that he <hi rend="italic">can</hi> fall back without losing the
army.  Why, we're worrying about the lives of sixteen thousand men and
the self-respect of the nation, senator.'
</p><p>'I see,' observed the senator, nodding his head slowly.  'And
naturally the welfare of one man's son doesn't&mdash;how do they say it?&mdash;doesn't
cut any ice.'
</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="section" n="5" id="d11">
<head>V.</head>
<p>
AND in Cuba it rained.  In a few days Reilly's brigade discovered that by
their successful charge they had gained the inestimable privilege of
sitting in a wet trench and slowly but surely starving to death.  Men's
tempers crumbled like dry bread.  The soldiers, who so cheerfully,
quietly, and decently had captured positions which the foreign experts
had said were impregnable, now, in turn, underwent an attack which was
furious as well as insidious.  The heat of the sun alternated with rains
which boomed and roared in their falling like mountain cataracts.  It
seemed as if men took the fever through sheer lack of another
occupation.  During the days of battle none had had time to get even a
tropic headache, but no sooner was that brisk period over than men began
to shiver and shudder by squads and platoons.  Rations were scarce
enough to make a little fat strip of bacon seem of the size of a corner lot,
and coffee-grains were pearls.  There would have been godless
quarrelling over fragments if it were not that with these fevers came a
great listlessness, so that men were almost content to die, if death
required no exertion.
</p><p>It was an occasion which distinctly separated the sheep from the
goats.  The goats were few enough, but their qualities glared out like
crimson spots.
</p><p>One morning Jamson and Ripley, two captains in the 44th

<pb n="747"/>
Foot, lay under a flimsy shelter of sticks and palm branches.  Their
dreamy dull eyes contemplated the men in the trench which went to left
and right.  To them came Casper Cadogan, moaning.  'By gawd,' he said,
as he flung himself wearily on the ground, 'I can't stand much more of
this, you know.  It's killing me.'  A bristly beard sprouted through the
grime on his face; his eyelids were crimson; an indescribably dirty shirt
fell away from his roughened neck; and at the same time various lines of
evil and greed were deepened on his face, until he practically stood forth
as a revelation, a confession.  'I can't stand it.  By gawd, I can't.'
</p><p>Stanford, a lieutenant under Jamson, came stumbling along towards
them.  He was a lad of the class of '98 at Westpoint.  It could be seen that
he was flaming with fever.  He rolled a calm eye at them.  'Have you any
water, sir?' he said to his captain.  Jamson got upon his feet and helped
Stanford to lay his shaking length under the shelter.  'No, boy,' he
answered gloomily.  'Not a drop.  You got any, Rip?'
</p><p>'No,' answered Ripley, looking with anxiety upon the young officer.
'Not a drop.'
</p><p>'You, Cadogan?'
</p><p>Here Casper hesitated oddly for a second, and then, in a tone of
deep regret, made answer: 'No, captain; not a mouthful.'
</p><p>Jamson moved off weakly.  'You lay quietly, Stanford, and I'll see
what I can russle.'
</p><p>Presently, Casper felt that Ripley was steadily regarding him.  He
returned the look with one of half-guilty questioning.  'God forgive you,
Cadogan,' said Ripley, 'but you are a damn beast.  Your canteen is full of
water.'
</p><p>Even then the apathy in their veins prevented the scene from
becoming as sharp as the words sound.  Casper strutted like a child, and
at length merely said: 'No, it isn't.'  Stanford lifted his head to shoot a
keen proud glance at Casper, and then turned away his face.
</p><p>'You lie,' said Ripley.  'I can tell the sound of a full canteen
as far as I can hear it.'
</p><p>'Well, if it is, I&mdash;I must have forgotten it.'
</p><p>'You lie; no man in this army just now forgets whether his canteen
is full or empty.  Hand it over.'
</p><p>Fever is the physical counterpart of shame, and when a man has had
the one, he accepts the other with an ease which would revolt his healthy
self.  However, Casper made a desperate struggle

<pb n="748"/>
to preserve the forms.  He arose, taking the string from
his shoulder, passed the canteen to Ripley.  But, after all, there was
a whine in his voice, and the assumption of dignity was really a
farce.  'I think I had better go, captain.  You can have the water if
you want it, I'm sure.  But&mdash;but I fail to see&mdash;I fail to see what
reason you have for insulting me.' </p><p>'Do you?' said Ripley
stolidly.  'That's all right.' </p><p>Casper stood for a terrible
moment.  He simply did not have the strength to turn his back on
this&mdash;this affair.  It seemed to him that he must stand for ever and
face it.  But when he found the audacity to look again at Ripley, he
saw the latter was not at all concerned with the situation.  Ripley,
too, had the fever.  The fever changes all laws of proportion.  Casper
went away.  </p><p>'Here, youngster; here's your drink.'
</p><p>Stanford made a weak gesture.  'I wouldn't touch a drop from his
damned canteen, if it was the last water in the world,' he murmured, in
his high boyish voice.  </p><p>'Don't you be a young jackass,' quoth
Ripley, tenderly.  </p><p>The boy stole a glance at the canteen.  He
felt the propriety of arising and hurling it after Casper; but he,
too, had the fever.  </p><p>'Don't you be a young jackass,' said
Ripley again.  </p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="6" id="d12">
<head>VI.</head>
<p> SENATOR CADOGAN was
happy.  His son had returned from Cuba, and the 8.30 train that
evening would bring him to the station nearest to the
stone-and-red-shingled villa which the senator and his family occupied
on the shores of Long Island Sound.  The senator's steam yacht lay
some hundred yards from the beach.  She had just returned from a trip
to Montauk Point, where the senator had made a gallant attempt to gain
his son from the transport on which he was coming from Cuba.  He had
fought a brave sea fight with sundry petty little doctors and ship
officers, who had raked him with broadsides describing the laws of
quarantine, and they had used inelegant speech to a United States
senator as he stood on the bridge of his own steam yacht.  These men
had grimly asked him to tell exactly how much better was Casper than
any other returning soldier.  </p><p>But the senator had not given
them a long fight.  In fact, the truth came to him quickly, and with
almost a blush he had

<pb n="749"/>
ordered the yacht back to
her anchorage off the villa.  As a matter of fact, the trip to Montauk
Point had been undertaken largely from impulse.  Long ago, the senator
had decided that, when his boy returned, the greeting should have
something Spartan in it.  He would make a welcome such as most
soldiers get.  There would be no flowers and carriages when the other
poor fellows got none.  He should consider Casper as a soldier.  That
was the way to treat a man.  But, in the end, a sharp acid of anxiety
had worked upon the iron old man, until he had ordered the yacht to
take him out and make a fool of him.  The result filled him with a
chagrin which caused him to delegate to the mother and sisters the
entire business of succouring Casper at Montauk Point camp.  He had
remained at home conducting the huge correspondence of an active
national politician and waiting for this son, whom he so loved, and
whom he so wished to be a man of a certain strong taciturn shrewd
ideal.  The recent yacht voyage he now looked upon as a kind of
confession of his weakness, and he was resolved that no more signs
should escape him.  </p><p>But yet his boy had been down there against
the enemy and among the fevers.  There had been grave perils, and his
boy must have faced them.  And he could not prevent himself from
dreaming through the poetry of fine actions, in which visions his
son's face shone out manly and generous.  During these periods, the
people about him, accustomed as they were to his silence and calm in
time of stress, considered that affairs in Skowmulligan might be most
critical.  In no other way could they account for this exaggerated
phlegm.  </p><p>On the night of Casper's return he did not go to
dinner, but had a tray sent to his library where he remained writing.
At last he heard the spin of the dogcart's wheels on the gravel of the
drive, and a moment later there penetrated to him the sound of joyful
feminine cries.  He lit another cigar; he knew that it was now his
part to hide with dignity the moment when his son should shake off
that other welcome and come to him.  He could still hear them; in
their exuberance they seemed to be capering like school-children.  He
was impatient, but this impatience took the form of a polar stolidity.
</p><p>Presently there were quick steps and a jubilant knock at his
door.  'Come in,' he said.  In came Casper, thin, yellow, and in
soiled khaki.  </p><p>'They almost tore me to pieces,' he cried,
laughing.  'They

<pb n="750"/>
danced around like wild things.'
Then, as they shook hands, he dutifully said, 'How are you, sir?'
</p><p>'How are you, my boy?' answered the senator casually, but
kindly.  </p><p>'Better than I might expect, sir,' cried Casper
cheerfully.  'We had a pretty hard time, you know.' </p><p>'You look
as if they'd given you a hard run,' observed the father, in a tone of
slight interest.  </p><p>Casper was eager to tell.  'Yes, sir,' he
said rapidly.  'We did indeed.  Why, it was awful!  We&mdash;any of
us&mdash;were lucky to get out of it alive.  It wasn't so much the
Spaniards, you know; the army took care of them all right.  It was the
fever and the&mdash;you know, we couldn't get anything to eat.  And the
mismanagement&mdash;why, it was frightful.' </p><p>'Yes, I've heard,' said
the senator.  A certain wistful look came into his eyes, but he did
not allow it to become prominent.  Indeed, he suppressed it.  'And
you, Casper, I suppose you did your duty?' </p><p>Casper answered with
becoming modesty: 'Well, I didn't do more than anybody else, I don't
suppose; but&mdash;well, I got along all right, I guess.' </p><p>'And this
great charge up San Juan Hill?' asked the father slowly.  'Were you in
that?' </p><p>'Well&mdash;yes, I was in it,' replied the son.  </p><p>The
senator brightened a trifle.  'You were, eh?  In the front of it?  Or
just sort of going along?' </p><p>'Well&mdash;I don't know; I couldn't tell
exactly.  Sometimes I was in front of a lot of them, and sometimes I
was&mdash;just sort of going along.' </p>

<p>This time the senator emphatically brightened.  'That's all right,
then.  And of course&mdash;of <hi rend="italic">course</hi> you
performed your commissary duties correctly?' </p><p>The question
seemed to make Casper uncommunicative and sulky.  'I did when there
was anything to do,' he answered.  'But the whole thing was on the
most unbusiness-like basis you can imagine.  And they wouldn't tell
you anything.  Nobody would take time to instruct you in your duties,
and, of course, if you didn't know a thing, then your superior officer
would swoop down on you and ask you why in hell such and such a thing
wasn't done in such and such a way.  Of course I did the best I
could.' </p><p>The senator's countenance had again become sombrely


<pb n="751"/>
indifferent.  'I see.  But you weren't
directly rebuked for incapacity, were you?  No, of course you
weren't.  But&mdash;I mean&mdash;did any of your superior officers suggest that
you were "no good," or anything of that sort&mdash;I mean&mdash;did you come off
with a clean slate.' </p><p>Casper took a small time to digest his
father's meaning.  'Oh, yes, sir,' he cried at the end of his
reflection.  'The commissary was in such a hopeless mess, anyhow, that
nobody thought of doing anything but curse Washington.' </p><p>'Of
course,' rejoined the senator harshly.  'But supposing that you had
been a competent and well-trained commissary-officer?  What then?'
</p><p>Again the son took time for consideration, and in the end
deliberately replied: 'Well, if I had been a competent and well-trained
commissary, I would have sat there and eaten up my heart and cursed
Washington.' </p><p>'Well, then, that's all right.  And now about this
charge up San Juan?  Did any of the generals speak to you afterwards,
and say that you had done well?  Didn't any of them see you?'
</p><p>'Why, no-o-o, I don't suppose they did&mdash;any more than I did
them.  You see, this charge was a big thing, and covered lots of
ground, and I hardly saw anybody excepting a lot of the men.'
</p><p>'Well, but didn't any of the men see you?  Weren't you ahead
some of the time, leading them on, and waving your sword?'
</p><p>Casper burst into laughter.  'Why, no.  I had all I could do to
scramble along and try to keep up.  And I didn't want to go up at all.'
</p><p>'Why?' demanded the senator.  </p><p>'Because&mdash;because the
Spaniards were shooting so much.  And you could see men falling&mdash;and
the bullets rushed around you in&mdash;by the bushel.  And then at last it
seemed that if we once drove them away from the top of the hill there
would be less danger.  So we all went up.' </p><p>The senator chuckled
over his description.  'And you didn't flinch at all?' </p><p>'Well,'
rejoined Casper humorously, 'I won't say I wasn't frightened.'
</p><p>'No, of course not.  But, then, you did not let anybody know
it?' </p><p>'Of course not.'</p>


<pb n="752"/>
<p>'You understand, naturally, that I am bothering you with all these
questions because I desire to hear how my only son behaved in the
crisis.  I don't want to worry you with it; but if you went through
the San Juan charge with credit, I'll have you made a major.'
</p><p>'Well,' said Casper, 'I wouldn't say I went through that charge
with credit.  I went through it all good enough, but the enlisted men
around went through it in the same way.' </p><p>'But weren't you
encouraging them, and leading them on by your example?' </p><p>Casper
smirked.  He began to see a point.  'Well, sir,' he said, with a
charming hesitation.  'Aw&mdash;er&mdash;I&mdash; Well, I dare say I was doing my
share of it.' </p><p>The perfect form of the reply delighted the
father.  He could not endure blatancy; his admiration was to be won
only by a bashful hero.  Now he beat his hand impulsively down upon
the table.  'That's what I wanted to know; that's it exactly.  I'll
have you made a major next week.  You've found your proper field at
last.  You stick to the army, Casper, and I'll back you up.  That's
the thing.  In a few years it will be a great career.  The United
States is pretty sure to have an army of about a hundred and fifty
thousand men.  And, starting in when you did, and with me to back you
up&mdash;why, we'll make you a general in seven or eight years.  That's the
ticket.  You stay in the army.' The senator's face was flushed with
enthusiasm, and he looked eagerly and confidently at his son.
</p><p>But Casper had pulled a long face.  'The army?' he said, 'stay
in the army?' </p><p>The senator continued to outline quite
rapturously his idea of the future.  'The army, evidently, is just the
place for you.  You know as well as I do that you have not been a
howling success, exactly, in anything else which you have tried.  But,
now, the army just suits you.  It is the kind of career which
specially suits you.  Well, then, go in and go at it hard.  Go in to
win.  Go at it.' </p><p>'But&mdash;' began Casper.  </p><p>The senator
interrupted swiftly.  'Oh, don't worry about that part of it.  I'll
take care of all that.  You won't get jailed in some Arizona adobe for
the rest of your natural life.  There won't be much more of that,
anyhow; and, besides, as I say, I'll look after all that end of it.
The chance is splendid.  A young, healthy, and

<pb n="753"/>
intelligent man, with the start you've already got and with my
backing, can do anything&mdash;anything.  There will be a lot of active
service&mdash;oh, yes, I'm sure of it&mdash;and everybody
 who&mdash;' </p><p>'But,' said Casper, wan, desperate, heroic, 'father, I
don't care to stay in the army.' </p><p>The senator lifted his eyes,
and his face darkened.  'What?' he said, 'what's that?' He looked at
Casper.  </p><p>The son became tightened and wizened like an old miser
trying to withhold gold.  He replied, with a sort of idiot obstinacy,
'I don't care to stay in the army.' </p><p>The senator's jaw clinched
down, and he was dangerous.  But, after all, there was something
mournful somewhere.  'Why, what do you mean?' he asked gruffly.
</p><p>'Why, I couldn't get along, you know.  The&mdash;the&mdash;' </p><p>'The
what?' demanded the father, suddenly uplifted with thunderous anger.
'The what?' </p><p>Casper's pain found a sort of outlet in mere
irresponsible talk.  'Well, you know, the other men, you know.  I
couldn't get along with them, you know.  They're peculiar, somehow.
Odd; I didn't understand them, and they didn't understand me.  We&mdash;we
didn't hitch, somehow.  They're a queer lot.  They've got funny
ideas.  I don't know how to explain it exactly, but&mdash;somehow&mdash;I don't
like 'em.  That's all there is to it.  They're good fellows enough, I
know, but&mdash;' </p><p>'Oh, well, Casper,' interrupted the senator.  Then
he seemed to weigh a great fact in his mind.  'I guess&mdash;' He paused
again in profound consideration.  'I guess&mdash;' He lit a small brown
cigar.  'I guess you are no good.'</p>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
