<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="CraUptu"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>
<TEI.2 id="CraUptu">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Upturned Face</title>
<title type="sort">upturned face</title>
<author>Crane, Stephen, 1871-1900</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">12</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">CraUptu</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &#xa9; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:476840</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Upturned Face</title>
<title level="j">Ainslee's Magazine 5 March 1900</title>
<title type="sort">upturned face</title>
<author>Stephen Crane</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Ainslee's Magazine</publisher>
<date value="1900-03-05">5 March 1900</date>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text'sunique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1900-03-05">5 March 1900</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-09">September 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Tom Lukas</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Tagged in accordance with TEI-2</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
<head>   THE UPTURNED FACE<lb/> BY STEPHEN CRANE</head>
<pb n="108"/>

<div2 type="section" n="1" id="d4">
<head>I.</head>
<p><figure rend="block"><figDesc>[illustration omitted] </figDesc></figure></p>

<p>"WHAT will we do now?" said the adjutant, troubled and
excited.
</p><p>"Bury him," said Timothy Lean.
</p><p>The two officers looked down close to their toes where lay the
body of their comrade.  The face was chalk-blue; gleaming eyes
stared at the sky.  Over the two upright figures was a windy sound
of bullets, and on the top of the hill, Lean's prostrate company of
Spitzbergen infantry was firing measured volleys.
</p><p>"Don't you think it would be better&mdash;" began the adjutant.  "We
might leave him until to-morrow."
</p><p>"No," said Lean, "I can't hold that post an hour longer.  I've got
to fall back, and we've got to bury old Bill."
</p><p>"Of course," said the adjutant at once.  "Your men got
intrenching tools?"
</p><p>Lean shouted back to his little firing line, and two men came
slowly, one with a pick, one with a shovel.  They stared in the
direction of the Rostina sharpshooters.  Bullets cracked near their
ears.  "Dig here," said Lean, gruffly.  The men, thus caused to lower
their glances to the turf, became hurried and frightened merely
because they could not look to see whence the bullets came.  The
dull beat of the pick striking the earth sounded amid the swift snap
of close bullets.  Presently the other private began to shovel.
</p><p>"I suppose," said the adjutant, slowly, "we'd better search his
clothes for . . . things.
</p><p>Lean nodded; together in curious abstraction they looked at the
body.  Then Lean stirred his shoulders, suddenly arousing himself.
"Yes," he said, "we'd better see . . . what he's got."  He dropped to
his knees and approached his hands to the body of the dead officer.
But his hands wavered over the buttons of the tunic.  The first
button was brick-red with drying blood, and he did not seem to dare
to touch it.
</p><p>"Go on," said the adjutant, hoarsely.
</p><p>Lean stretched his wooden hand, and his fingers fumbled
blood-stained buttons. . . .  At last he arose with a ghastly face.  He
had gathered a watch, a whistle, a pipe, a tobacco pouch, a
handkerchief, a little case of cards and papers.  He looked at the
adjutant.  There was a silence.  The adjutant was feeling that he had
been a coward to make Lean do all the grizzly business.
</p><p>"Well," said Lean, "that's all, I think.  You have his sword and
revolver."
</p><p>"Yes," said the adjutant, his face working.  And then he burst
out in a sudden strange fury at the two privates.  "Why don't you
hurry up with that grave?  What are you doing, anyhow?"
</p><p>Even as he cried out in this passion, the two men were laboring
for their lives.  Ever overhead, the bullets were spitting.
</p><p>The grave was finished.  It was not a masterpiece&mdash;poor little
shallow thing.  Lean and the adjutant again looked at each other in a
curious, silent communication.
</p><p>Suddenly the adjutant croaked out a weird laugh.  It was a
terrible laugh which had its origin in that part of the mind which
<pb n="109"/>
is first moved by the singing of the nerves.  "Well," he said,
humorously to Lean, "I suppose we had best tumble him in."
</p><p>"Yes," said Lean.  The two privates stood waiting bent over on
their implements.  "I suppose," said Lean, "it would be better if we
laid him in ourselves."
</p><p>"Yes," said the adjutant.  Then apparently remembering that he
had made Lean search the body, he stooped with great fortitude and
took hold of the dead officer's clothing.  Lean joined him.  Both
were particular that their fingers should not feel the corpse.  They
tugged away; the corpse lifted, heaved, toppled, flopped into the
grave, and the two officers, straightening, looked at each other.
They sighed with relief.
</p><p>The adjutant said: "I suppose we should . . . we should say
something.  Do you know the service, Tim?"
</p><p>"They don't read the service until the grave is filled in," said
Lean.
</p><p>"Don't they?" said the adjutant, shocked that he had made the
mistake.  "Oh, well," he cried, suddenly, "let us . . . let us say
something. . . . while he can hear us."
</p><p>"All right," said Lean.  "Do you know the service?"
</p><p>"I can't remember a line of it," said the adjutant.
</p><p>Lean was extremely dubious.  "I can repeat two lines out&mdash;"
</p><p>"Well, do it," said the adjutant.  "Go as far as you can.  That's
better than nothing.  And . . . the beasts have got our range exactly."
</p><p>Lean looked at his two men.  "Attention!" he barked.  The
privates came to attention with a click, looking much aggrieved.
The adjutant lowered his helmet to his knee.  Lean, bare-headed,
stood over the grave.  The Rostina sharpshooters fired briskly.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"O, Father, our friend has sunk in the deep waters of death,
but his spirit has leaped toward Thee as the bubble arises from the
lips of the drowning.  Perceive, we beseech, O, Father, the little
flying bubble and&mdash;"</hi>
</p><p>Lean, although husky and ashamed, had suffered no hesitation
up to this point, but he stopped with a hopeless feeling and looked
at the corpse.
</p><p>The adjutant moved uneasily.  <hi rend="italic">"And from Thy superb
heights&mdash;"</hi> he began, and then he, too, came to an end.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"And from Thy superb heights,"</hi> said Lean.
</p><p>The adjutant suddenly remembered a phrase in the back part of
the Spitzbergen burial service, and he exploited it with the
triumphant manner of a man who has recalled everything and can
go on.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Oh, God, have mercy&mdash;"</hi>
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Oh, God, have mercy&mdash;"</hi> said Lean.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"'Mercy,'"</hi> repeated the adjutant, in a quick failure.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">"'Mercy,'"</hi> said Lean.  And then he was moved by some
violence of feeling, for he turned suddenly upon his two men and
tigerishly said: "Throw the dirt in."
</p><p>The fire of the Rostina sharpshooters was accurate and
continuous.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="section" n="2" id="d5">
<head>II.</head>

<p>One of the aggrieved privates came forward with his shovel.
He lifted his first shovel load of earth, and for a moment of
inexplicable hesitation, it was held poised above this corpse which,
from its chalk-blue face, looked keenly out from the grave.  Then
the soldier emptied his shovel on&mdash;on the feet.
</p><p>Timothy Lean felt as if tons had been swiftly lifted from off
his forehead.  He had felt that perhaps the private might empty the
shovel on&mdash;on the face.  It had been emptied on the feet.  There was
a great point gained there.  The adjutant began to babble.  "Well, of
course . . . a man we've messed with all these years . . . impossible .
. . you can't, you know, leave your intimate friends rotting on the
field . . .  Go on, for God's sake, and shovel, <hi rend="italic">you</hi>."
</p><p>The man with the shovel suddenly ducked, grabbed his left
arm with his right and looked at his officer for orders.  Lean picked
the shovel from the ground.  "Go to the rear," he said to the
wounded man.  He also addressed the other private.
</p><p>"You get under cover, too.  I'll . . . I'll finish this business."
</p><p>The wounded man scrambled hastily for the top of the ridge
without devoting any glances to the direction from whence the
bullets came, and the other man followed at an equal pace, but he
was different in that he looked back anxiously three times.  This is
merely the way&mdash;often&mdash;of the hit and the unhit.
</p><p>Timothy Lean filled the shovel, hesitated, and then in a
movement which was like a gesture of abhorrence, he flung the dirt
into the grave, and as it landed it made a sound&mdash;plop.  Lean
suddenly paused and mopped his brow&mdash;a tired laborer.
</p><p>"Perhaps we have been wrong," said the adjutant.  His glance
wavered stupidly.  "It
<pb n="110"/>
[illustration omitted]
might have
been better if we hadn't buried him just at this time.  Of course, if
we advance to-morrow, the body would have been&mdash;"
</p><p>"Damn you," said Lean.  "Shut your mouth.  He was not the
senior officer."
</p><p>He again filled the shovel and flung in the earth.  . . . .  For a
space, Lean worked frantically, like a man digging himself out of
danger. . . .  Soon there was nothing to be seen but the chalk-blue
face.  Lean filled the shovel. . . .  "Good Good [sic]," he cried to the
adjutant, why didn't you turn him somehow when you put him in?
This&mdash;"
</p><p>The adjutant understood.  He was pale to the lips.  "Go on,
man," he cried, beseechingly, almost in a shout. . . .  Lean swung
back the shovel; it went forward in a pendulum curve.  When the
earth landed it made a sound&mdash;plop.</p>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
