<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DarVoya"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="DarVoya">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Voyages of Conrad</title>
<title type="sort">voyages of conrad</title>
<author>Dargan, E. Preston</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>Text prepared by the 1997-98 J. Wallace Sieg Graduate Fellow Lisa Spiro
for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">23</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">DarVoya</idno>
<date value="1998">1998</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1998 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475857</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Voyages of Conrad</title>
<title level="j">The Dial, vol. 66</title>
<title type="sort">voyages of conrad</title>
<author>E. Preston Dargan</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 638-641</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>The Dial</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1919-06-28">1919, June 28</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: University of Virginia Library call number AP 2 .D48 vol. 66</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1919">1919</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1998-06">June 1998</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Lisa Spiro, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
	<pb n="638"/>
	<head>The Voyages of Conrad</head>

<p>IN 1873, A POLISH LAD of fifteen, walking in the Alps with his tutor, dismayed that gentleman
by a declaration of independence. He proposed to give up his country and career, in order to take
his chances on the sea. A few years later he was sailing on the Mediterranean, that "nursery of
the craft." Then he realized his dream by becoming associated with the English flag &mdash;
incidentally learning the English language. He went on far voyages, seeing little of Europe for a
quarter of a century. Finally, he accomplished his second transformation: the Polish lad became
a great writer of English. The boy was named Jozef Korzeniowski   the writer is known to fame
as Joseph Conrad.
</p><p>The adventurous spirit thus manifest is characteristic of Conrad's mind and work. Romance is
his great word, genuinely romantic are his favorite heroes. He arrays them against the manifold
visage and challenge of the seven seas.  He is primarily the psychologist of mariners, he is Henry
James on a South Sea Island.
</p><p>Let us follow some of his rovings. The real voyages of Jozef Korzeniowski concern us only as
a basis for the fictional adventures that his double, Conrad, has narrated. We know that a dozen
actual ships and scenes served as a springboard for his imagination. The publishers of his tales
have recently charted for us the voyages undertaken by his dream-ships in seas that often Conrad
alone has adequately celebrated. We will cruise with these ships, not in chronological order, but
widening out from the author's favorite center. Usually his ports of call are found in Malaysian
waters and his ordinary beat is that of his hero, Heyst   "a circle with a radius of eight hundred
miles drawn round a point in North Borneo." This point is approximately the scene of Almayer's
Folly, with which book we begin to cruise.
</p><p>The original of Almayer, inadequate and shiftless dreamer, had been studied along the muddy
banks of the Pantai, where the story unrolls. The breath of this poisonous backwater eats into the
characters and the sunset gold of the Pantai symbolizes the vain greed of Almayer. Swathed in
mist, the river hides a pair of lovers and their canoe; it is a sleeping world, wherein all the ardent
life of the tropics is transferred to the beating hearts of Dain and Nina. Finally &mdash; and this is the
actual voyage &mdash; Almayer watches his daughter and her lover depart in a violent brazen light; he
watches the vanishing canoe that holds their embracing figures, and he dies in his curses,
unforgiving and abandoned.
</p><p>The ardor and chivalry of the Malays, their passionate pride, again fascinates Conrad in
Karain. Our circle now widens out to include the Archipelago around Borneo.   Karain's mad
avenging journey, as he tells it, proceeds from the monster-shaped Celebes, past "a great
mountain burning in the midst of water," past myriad islands that are scattered like shards from
the gun of a demiurge, to Java, with its stone campongs and its slavish population. Then on to
unhealthy Delli, where a blossoming thicket hid Karain and his brother-in-arms, the two
avengers; and there the deluded Malay kills his friend instead of the too ravishing woman who
should have been the victim.
</p><p>This is an intensely tragic voyage. The more epic and comic Typhoon is a tale of endurance
and conquest.   Reaching beyond the Philippines, its scene is laid near the northernmost point of
the Malaysian circle. In the narrow dangerous China seas, near Formosa, the Nan-Shan
encountered one of the worst storms ever recorded. She was saved by the dullness and obstinacy
of her Captain MacWhirr, a man &mdash; witness his name &mdash; of no imagination. Just as his stupid
dutiful letters home are barely read by a yawning family, so does his imperviousness disgust
Jukes, the livelier chief mate. MacWhirr has never yet been in a great storm, but you feel that, as
a crustacean, he is prepared for one. He greets the danger-signals with the obvious remark: that
there must be "some dirty weather knocking about."  It becomes a Typhoon and knocks
everybody about: the officers scurrying on their duties from pillar to post; the cargo, namely two
hundred coolies, who presently begin sliding to and fro in a mass of boxes, pigtails, and dollars.
They are roped in like an unruly herd. Jukes plunges down to the engine-room and from that
gleaming Inferno the boat seems submerged by the greatest blow yet; tons of water descend,
sufficient to wipe out everything; those in the engine-room stare at one another aghast; and
through the speaking-tube the captain's voice goes on unperturbed, attending strictly to business.
</p><p>When the Nan-Shan was virtually a wreck and the wind fell, they were caught in the circular
whirl of the hurricane; but the captain and the boat kept their heads up and came to anchorage,
to the astonishment of Jukes, the reader, and all the seamen, in the harbor. Mrs. MacWhirr, in a
far-off, forty-pound


   <pb n="639"/>

house, stifled a yawn at the captain's dull account of his voyage.
</p><p>On the other side of the Archipelago are the peregrinations told of in The End of the Tether.
The blind Captain Whalley touches bottom as mate of the coasting craft Sofala, which beats up
and down  its  sixteen-hundred-mile  circular  route through the Malacca Straits. Needing the
money for his daughter, Captain Whalley has descended to this from much greater voyages. To
hold his position, he has concealed his oncoming blindness, depending on the eyes of his faithful
Malay serang. But he is suspected by his worthless officers, one of whom, near Pangu Bay, piles
the steamer up on the reef &mdash; and the captain will not survive his charge.
</p><p>Such is the third Journey in Conrad's chief volume of nouvelles. The others of the trilogy are
Youth and Heart of Darkness, both of which are reminiscences. Who has not read Youth, that
record of gallantry, endurance, romance, and humor? It tells of Marlow's very first voyage,
beginning far out of our circle, but aiming for the "white" of it, for that Bangkok which is the
scene of Falk and from which Conrad's own first command set sail. Marlow's boat was the Judea
&mdash; "all rust, dust, grime &mdash; soot aloft, dirt on deck." But on her stern she bore the imperative and
romantic motto "Do or Die." And Bangkok for Marlow promised all the thrill and wonder of the
unknown East.
</p><p>Bound first for an English port to load on with coal, the Judea spent a week in getting to the
Yarmouth Roads. There was a gale; she shifted ballast; the crew were set to the "grave-diggers'
work" of righting her. After long delay in loading, she had a collision with a steamer, and waited
three weeks more. Another gale, 300 miles W. of the Lizards, tore up the old ship and the crew
turned to endless pumping. But still the battered craft threw out "like an appeal, like a defiance,
like a cry to the clouds without mercy, the words written on her stern: 'Judea, London. Do or
Die.'" And for Marlow, aetat. 20, the faith, the endeavor, the imagination of Youth were in that
cry.
</p><p>Their deck-house was blown away and they put back to Falmouth. Three times they put back
to Falmouth. The crew refused, and no wonder, to trust that leaky and bewitched hooker, now
six months on the road to Bangkok and not yet clear of England. You ask if they ever reached
Bangkok? Almost. They finally got to the Indian Ocean, they neared Java Head &mdash; when the coal
caught fire.  Still sailing for Bangkok, "Do or Die," they fought that fire for days and just as they
seemed to conquer it, the cargo blew up. The ship herself blew up, after a steamer had taken the
wreck in tow. But the crew had saved all they could, and Marlow, in charge of his own boat,
presently sighted Java &mdash; his first vision of the East, "the East of the ancient narrators,
mysterious, resplendent, and somber." The Judea did and died; her second mate had begun to
live.
</p><p>From the year of grace 1900 dates the personal history of Lord Jim and the record of the
pilgrim-ship, the Patna. She was a rusty lean cosmopolite, who at some Eastern port took on her
cargo of eight hundred faithful ignorant cattle-like pilgrims. Her officers, barring the untried
Jim, were all scamps and bullies. Unlike the men of the Judea and the Nan-Shan, these fellows
are not true seamen; and that, with Conrad, always spells disaster.   His picture of the early part
of the voyage is one of his greatest pieces of descriptive writing.  After clearing the Strait, the
Patna headed through the "one-degree" passage for the Red Sea, borne down by an oppressive
sun, sailing on a stagnant ocean. Under a slender shaving of a moon, not far from where the
Arabian Sea joins the Red, something happened. A collision with a derelict shook the ship and
the souls upon her. The scared officers, believing her about to sink, took to the boats, abandoned
the Patna and her pilgrims.
</p><p>In the record, shifted and twisted from a dozen angles, we feel all of human dread and
cowardice, all of human pity for the doomed eight hundred, who yet were not doomed but
successfully towed by a French gunboat into Aden.  The Patna was saved. Only her officers were
damned. The rest of the story, dealing with the "case" of Jim; his wanderings like those of the
accursed Jew, his atonement in savage Patusan, will concern us later.
</p><p>In a previous voyage, described in The Nigger of the Narcissus we meet with foul weather off
the Cape and with that admirable cook, who at the height of the storm accomplishes the miracle
of making coffee.  His declaration "as long as she swims I will cook" becomes the motto of the
desperate and dauntless boat. For here we are in the presence of "the dumb courage of men
obscure, forgetful, and enduring." Throughout the windings of their limited and superstitious
souls there has passed the taut shiver of responsibility, of "Do or Die." The Narcissus is no
Patna. It is with admiration and fellowship that Conrad bids these seamen farewell. It has been
said that this story best "conjures up the actual spirit of a voyage," the smell of the ocean, the
ship moving through the tropical heat.
</p><p>We have already twice swung around the Cape n Conrad's wake; his farther reaches take us
into he penetralia of the West African Coast. As a


   <pb n="640"/>

boy he had dreamed of the dark and dreadful Congo. In the incomparable Heart of Darkness,
under the witching spell of the narrator Marlow, we are taken far up this river, which,
resembling an "immense snake uncoiled," buries its tail in the tenebrous wilderness. Kurtz, that
leader of men, has lost both his moral sense and his life. An expedition has been sent to pluck
him out. The steamboat crawled along the gloomy silent Congo; it was "like traveling back to
the earliest beginnings of the world, when the big trees were kings."   An uncertain channel, a
sluggish atmosphere, wonderfully conveyed in the telling, saurians on sandbanks, and especially
the "stillness of an implacable force, vengefully watching."  It had watched poor Kurtz to some
purpose, for when, after experiences with cannibals, ivory, attacks from the jungle &mdash; when you,
I, and Marlow reach the heart of darkness, we find that its powers have driven Kurtz to
headhunting, megalomania, and the point of death.
</p><p>Far-flung tangents from the circle are traced by other voyages which may be briefly
summarized. There is the transatlantic venture by which the hero of Romance comes to peril and
thirst and the most adorable of stately senoritas on the Spanish Main. There is the savage brute
of a boat (Sydney to London) which slays a passenger every trip and whose cruel anchor catches
up and crushes the mate's sweetheart before his eyes. There is the Ferndale (London to Port
Elizabeth), on which occurs the singular incident narrated in that obscure book, Chance. If
Victory has most of Stevenson in its scheme, Chance has most of Henry James in its method.
Gradually Conrad has become more interested in souls than in ships; also he stays longer and
more persuasively in the society of women.
</p><p>That brings us to his inland voyages, which are of two kinds, geographical and psychological.
As regards the first kind, for over twenty years Conrad scarcely saw the continent of Europe, and
the journeyings which traverse that continent &mdash; such tales as Under Western Eyes &mdash; are to my
thinking almost negligible. But the voyages of discovery into the varieties of human hearts and
situations demand fuller treatment. They demand first of all some reckoning with the author's
philosophy.
</p><p>Traveling always from one place to another, shifting imaginatively from standpoint to
standpoint, Conrad has naturally come to view life as a great panorama, and art as an
adventurous cruise. Life is a succession of scenes and the "master of the show" is the goddess
Maia.  Illusion is the word most frequently on Conrad's lips &mdash; illusions of youth, of hope, in fact
the "darkness of a world of illusions" in which his best-beloved romantic characters appear as
beautiful vanishing figureheads. Sombre and splendid, they come, they flash, they go. "Ports are
no good, ships rot, men go to the devil." Conrad's pessimism becomes more sardonic and
matter-of-fact in his later books.  But throughout he is saved by his absolute love of the sea and
seamen, and by his belief in a certain steadiness and sturdiness which is essentially nautical. We
have seen how he displays courage and character in his best sailors.  Again, the artistic compass
by which he steers swings resolutely to the pole of Truth. Sincerity and a kind of austere control
guide this romantic realist who can on the one hand define literary criticism as a high adventure
of personality &mdash; exactly like Anatole France &mdash; and on the other achieve restraint in the deepest
emotion of Lord Jim or Lena.
</p><p>Conrad is professedly not "literary " in the special sense. He lived only for the sea and did not
write a line until his thirty-sixth year. It is natural then that the sea's rhythm should be found in
his sentences, something of her swift fickleness in his restless eye.  He has often compared
artistic creation to voyaging.   Each effort is like the "everlasting somber stress of the winter
passage around Cape Horn." Each story gets under way as leisurely as the Judea. There are
voyages into the consciousness of a hundred heroes, into the thwarted spirit of Kurtz, into the
self-deception of the Nigger, a voyage of discovery to learn simply that Captain Whalley is
blind, another outward tragedy that ends in inner Victory.  From this mental and moral Odyssey I
will detail only a few episodes, which will likewise serve as specimens of Conrad's constructive
technique.  There are two main sorts: the voyage that flits from one interest, group, or situation
to another, using each cursorily as a port of call; the voyage which proceeds from one
psychological standpoint to another, plumbing the depths of each soul, through its own narrative
and confession.
</p><p>Of the first kind, the epic story of Nostromo &mdash; regarded by some as Conrad's greatest &mdash; is
typical. We know the immense labor that went into this presentation (based on almost no
experience) of a South American republic. The result, I believe, is a tangle, a too intricate web.
The adventurous interest is to find the pattern, which is not zero as in musical comedy, but
nearer infinity, as in Balzac. In fact, Balzac's method rules.  From an initial situation, in medias
res, we travel back to one set of people and then to another, with fresh digressions and dossiers,
eddies and whirlpools.  We sink into the maelstrom of an individual experience


   <pb n="641"/>

to emerge into the muddy froth of revolutionary parties. We are led astray by an undated
log-book, which produces much confusion of time and place. We are frustrated by unclear
sequences and contrary winds and we chart our course in a dozen directions.
</p><p>To this excessive ramble one is justified in preferring the stiller depths of Lord Jim. Here
Conrad nearly attains his desired unity of effect, the atmospheric steeping which is the essence
of his romanticism. Here, at least, there is a single subject, a mountain of a subject, which we
cruise around and see through the eyes of several observers.  The author uses his pet device of
first-person narration.   The reminiscent and gloomy Marlow first appears here and tells us, too
lengthily, nearly the whole story of Jim's failure and rehabilitation. But that is only one point of
view. There is also the inner circle of Jim's own consciousness, gradually becoming distinct.
There are the successive sidelights thrown episodically by the self-sufficient Brierly, by the
French captain, with his touchstone of honor, by the merchant who retrieves and establishes Jim
in Patusan. There are the crowning lights thrown by Jim's dusky sweetheart and his chivalrous
brother-in-arms &mdash; spotlights for the catastrophe.
</p><p>Here again space and time are introverted or confused, but the main end is gained and we
have a progressively ascending study of one temperament mirrored through several others. . . In
Chance, these others are quite evidently of the sort usually chosen by Henry James: the
first-person narrator, curious but limited in knowledge, the dull conventional couple who guard
the unfortunate heroine, the viewpoint of the romantic captain who weds and saves her.
</p><p>But it is in Victory that we find the happiest amalgamation of the true Conrad with his
cosmopolitan masters &mdash; for certainly his technique is much more exotic than English. With
Victory we are in the heart of Malaysia again and we are furthermore in the hearts of the various
actors in this passionate drama.  The magnanimous self-tormented Heyst is set off against the
cupidity and villainies of old Schomberg, Ricardo, and "plain Mr. Jones." With most of these we
stay for several chapters, while each expounds his attitude and outlook. They are loosely
enclosed within two outer rings of observation, that of the semi-detached narrator and of the
peripatetic Captain Davidson, who brings news of Heyst and the girl on the island. The triumph
of the book is the girl herself, her gradual rise from a dull sulkiness &mdash; Conrad is strangely fond
of sulky women &mdash; to participation in Heyst's scheme for her rescue, and finally to an
overwhelming gratitude reaching the point of self-immolation. Her growth in consciousness and
effectiveness is a marvel of psychological portrayal, set amid stirring deeds. The Spanish heroine
of the Arrow of Gold (Doubleday, Page; 1919) is, on the other hand, already fully grown; almost
as grown as her creator, in her strange mingling of deep romance and disillusionment.
</p><p>Mr. Richard Curie, Conrad's biographer and critic, has found over ninety strongly realized
characters in his work. What a power of vision is needed to conceive sharply all these diverse
types! The creative mind has roamed from the duellist Feraud, of Napoleon's time, to the
chivalrous dark-skinned Dain, from caged and restless English girls (Bessie Carvil, Flora de
Barral) to the romantic Ninas and Seraphinas of exotic strain.  Literally from China to Peru
Conrad has voyaged and observed.  He has depicted vast rivers and "those seas of God" in all
their myriad changes &mdash; sunny smiles hurrying into darkness, sluggish peace alternating with riot
and cruelty. Much has he traveled in the realms of gold &mdash; so much that the deferent reviewer can
see only two more major adventures for him to undertake. The first would be to visit this
country, as he once proposed to do. May he long delay the great Departure, the uncertain
landfall of the second voyage!</p>
<closer>
<signed>

                                   E. PRESTON DARGAN.
</signed>
</closer>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

