<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DavBlin"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="DavBlin">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Blind Tom</title>
<title type="sort">blind tom</title>
<author>Davis, Rebecca Harding, 1831-1910</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">26</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">DavBlin</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475860</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Blind Tom</title>
<title level="j">Atlantic Monthly</title>
<title type="sort">blind tom</title>
<author>Rebecca Harding Davis</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>First Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>pp. 580-585</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1862-11">Nov. 1862</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Atlantic Monthly, volume 10, November 1862.</p>
</note>
<note>
<p>Copy Consulted, UVA call no. S-1440, reel 2</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification madeagainst printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the
text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for
page one of Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1862">1862</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-09">September 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Michele Ierardi, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">



<div1 type="story" id="d3">
	<pb n="580"/>
<head>BLIND TOM.</head>

<epigraph><lg type="couplet"><l>Only a germ in a withered flower,</l>
<l>That the rain will bring out&mdash;sometime.</l></lg></epigraph>

<p>SOMETIME in the year 1850, a tobacco-planter in Southern
Georgia (Perry H. Oliver by name) bought a likely negro woman
with some other field-hands.  She was stout, tough-muscled,
willing, promised to be a remunerative servant; her baby, however,
a boy a few months old, was only thrown in as a makeweight to the
bargain, or rather because Mr. Oliver would not consent to separate
mother and child.  Charity only could have induced him to take the
picaninny, in fact, for he was but a lump of black flesh, born blind,
and with the vacant grin of idiocy, they thought, already stamped on
his face.  The two slaves were purchased, I believe, from a trader: it
has been impossible, therefore, for me to ascertain where Tom was
born, or when.  Georgia field-hands are not accurate as Jews in
preserving their genealogy; <hi rend="italic">they</hi> do not anticipate a Messiah.
A white man, you know, has that vague hope unconsciously latent
in him, that he is, or shall give birth to, the great man of his race, a
helper, a provider for the world's hunger: so he grows jealous with
his blood; the dead grandfather may have presaged the possible son;
besides, it is a debt he owes to this coming Saul to tell him whence
he came.  There are some classes, free and slave, out of whom
society has crushed this hope: they have no clan, no family-names
among them, therefore.  This idiot-boy, chosen by God to be
anointed with the holy chrism, is only "Tom,"&mdash;"Blind Tom," they
call him in all the Southern States, with a kind cadence always,
being proud and fond of him; and yet&mdash;nothing but Tom?  That is
pitiful.  Just a mushroom-growth,&mdash;unkinned, unexpected, not hoped
for, for generations, owning no name to purify and honor and give
away when he is dead.  His mother, at work to-day in the Oliver
plantations, can never comprehend why her boy is famous; this gift
of God to him means nothing to her.  Nothing to him, either, which
is saddest of all; he is unconscious, wears his crown as an idiot
might.  Whose fault is that?  Deeper than slavery the evil lies.
</p> <p>Mr. Oliver did his duty well to the boy, being an observant and
thoroughly kind master.  The plantation was large, heartsome, faced
the sun, swarmed with little black urchins, with plenty to eat, and
nothing to do.
</p> <p>All that Tom required, as he fattened out of baby-into
boyhood, was room in which to be warm, on the grass-patch, or by
the kitchen-fires, to be stupid, flabby, sleepy,&mdash;kicked and petted
alternately by the other hands.  He had a habit of crawling
<pb n="581"/>
up on the porches and verandas of the mansion and squatting there
in the sun, waiting for a kind word or touch from those who went in
and out.  He seldom failed to receive it.  Southerners know nothing
of the physical shiver of aversion with which even the Abolitionists
of the North touch the negro: so Tom, through his very helplessness,
came to be a sort of pet in the family, a playmate, occasionally, of
Mr. Oliver's own infant children.  The boy, creeping about day after
day in the hot light, was as repugnant an object as the lizards in the
neighboring swamp, and promised to be of as little use to his
master.  He was of the lowest negro type, from which only field-hands
can be made,&mdash;coal-black, with protruding heels, the ape-jaw,
blubber-lips constantly open, the sightless eyes closed, and the head
thrown far back on the shoulders, lying on the back, in fact, a habit
which he still retains, and which adds to the imbecile character of
the face.  Until he was seven years of age, Tom was regarded on the
plantation as an idiot, not unjustly; for at the present time his
judgment and reason rank but as those of a child four years old.  He
showed a dog-like affection for some members of the household,&mdash;a
son of Mr. Oliver's especially,&mdash;and a keen, nervous sensitiveness to
the slightest blame or praise from them,&mdash;possessed, too, a low
animal irritability of temper, giving way to inarticulate yelps of
passion when provoked.  That is all, so far; we find no other
outgrowth of intellect or soul from the boy: just the same record as
that of thousands of imbecile negro-children.  Generations of
heathendom and slavery have dredged the inherited brains and
temperaments of such children tolerably clean of all traces of power
or purity,&mdash;palsied the brain, brutalized the nature.  Tom apparently
fared no better than his fellows.
</p> <p>It was not until 1857 that those phenomenal powers latent in
the boy were suddenly developed, which stamped him the anomaly
he is to-day.
</p> <p>One night, sometime in the summer of that year, Mr. Oliver's
family were wakened by the sound of music in the drawing-room:
not only the simple airs, but the most difficult exercises usually
played by his daughters, were repeated again and again, the touch of
the musician being timid, but singularly true and delicate.  Going
down, they found Tom, who had been left asleep in the hall, seated
at the piano in an ecstasy of delight, breaking out at the end of each
successful fugue into shouts of laughter, kicking his heels and
clapping his hands.  This was the first time he had touched the
piano.
</p> <p>Naturally, Tom became a nine-days' wonder on the plantation.
He was brought in as an after-dinner's amusement; visitors asked for
him as the show of the place.  There was hardly a conception,
however, in the minds of those who heard him, of how deep the
cause for wonder lay.  The planters' wives and daughters of the
neighborhood were not people who would be apt to comprehend
music as a science, or to use it as a language; they only saw in the
little negro, therefore a remarkable facility for repeating the airs
they drummed on their pianos,&mdash;in a different manner from theirs, it
is true,&mdash;which bewildered them.  They noticed, too, that, however
the child's fingers fell on the keys, cadences followed, broken,
wandering, yet of startling beauty and pathos.  The house-servants,
looking in through the open doors at the little black figure perched
up before the instrument, while unknown, wild harmony drifted
through the evening air, had a better conception of him.  He was
possessed; some ghost spoke through him: which is a fair enough
definition of genius for a Georgian slave to offer.
</p> <p>Mr. Oliver, as we said, was indulgent.  Tom was allowed to
have constant access to the piano; in truth, he could not live without
it; when deprived of music now, actual physical debility followed:
the gnawing Something had found its food at last.  No attempt was
made, however, to give him any scientific musical teaching; nor&mdash;I
wish it distinctly borne in mind
<pb n="582"/>
&mdash;has he ever at any time
received such instruction.
</p> <p>The planter began to wonder what kind of a creature this was
which he had bought, flesh and soul.  In what part of the unsightly
baby-carcass had been stowed away these old airs, forgotten by
every one else, and some of them never heard by the child but once,
but which he now reproduced, every note intact, and with whatever
quirk or quiddity of style belonged to the person who originally had
sung or played them?  Stranger still the harmonies which he had
never heard, had learned from no man.  The sluggish breath of the
old house, being enchanted, grew into quaint and delicate whims of
music, never the same, changing every day.  Never glad: uncertain,
sad minors always, vexing the content of the hearer,&mdash;one
inarticulate, unanswered question of pain in all, making them one.
Even the vulgarest listener was troubled, hardly knowing why,&mdash;how
sorry Tom's music was!
</p> <p>At last the time came when the door was to be opened, when
some listener, not vulgar, recognizing the child as God made him,
induced his master to remove him from the plantation.  Something
ought to be done for him; the world ought not to be cheated of this
pleasure; besides&mdash;the money that could be made!  So Mr. Oliver,
with a kindly feeling for Tom, proud, too, of this agreeable monster
which his plantation had grown, and sensible that it was a more
fruitful source of revenue than tobacco-fields, set out with the boy,
literally to seek their fortune.
</p> <p>The first exhibition of him was given, I think, in Savannah,
Georgia; thence he was taken to Charleston, Richmond, to all the
principal cities and towns in the Southern States.
</p> <p>This was in 1858.  From that time until the present Tom has
lived constantly an open life, petted, feted, his real talent befogged
by exaggeration, and so pampered and coddled that one might
suppose the only purpose was to corrupt and wear it out.  For these
reasons this statement is purposely guarded, restricted to plain,
known facts.
</p> <p>No sooner had Tom been brought before the public than the
pretensions put forward by his master commanded the scrutiny of
both scientific and musical skeptics.  His capacities were subjected
to rigorous tests.  Fortunately for the boy: for, so tried,&mdash;harshly, it is
true, yet skilfully,&mdash;they not only bore the trial, but acknowledged
the touch as skilful; every day new powers were developed, until he
reached his limit, beyond which it is not probable he will ever pass.
That limit, however, establishes him as an anomaly in musical
science.
</p> <p>Physically, and in animal temperament, this negro ranks next
to the lowest Guinea type: with strong appetites and gross bodily
health, except in one particular, which will be mentioned hereafter.
In the every-day apparent intellect, in reason or judgment, he is but
one degree above an idiot,&mdash;incapable of comprehending the
simplest conversation on ordinary topics, amused or enraged with
trifles such as would affect a child of three years old.  On the other
side, his affections are alive, even vehement, delicate in their
instinct as a dog's or an infant's; he will detect the step of any one
dear to him in a crowd, and burst into tears, if not kindly spoken to.
</p> <p>His memory is so accurate that he can repeat, without the loss
of a syllable, a discourse of fifteen minutes in length, of which he
does not understand a word.  Songs, too, in French or German, after
a single hearing, he renders not only literally in words, but in notes,
style, and expression.  His voice, however, is discordant, and of
small compass.
</p> <p>In music, this boy of twelve years, born blind, utterly ignorant
of a note, ignorant of every phase of so-called musical science,
interprets severely classical composers with a clearness of
conception in which he excels, and a skill in mechanism equal to
that of our second-rate artists.  His concerts usually include any
themes selected by the audience from the higher
<pb n="583"/>
grades of
Italian or German opera.  His comprehension of the meaning of
music, as a prophetic or historical voice which few souls utter and
fewer understand, is clear and vivid: he renders it thus, with
whatever mastery of the mere material part he may possess,
fingering, dramatic effects, etc.: these are but means to him, not an
end, as with most artists.  One could fancy that Tom was never
traitor to the intent or soul of the theme.  What God or the Devil
meant to say by this or that harmony, what the soul of one man
cried aloud to another in it, this boy knows, and is to that a faithful
witness.  His deaf, uninstructed soul has never been tampered with
by art-critics who know the body well enough of music, but nothing
of the living creature within.  The world is full of these vulgar souls
that palter with eternal Nature and the eternal Arts, blind to the
Word who dwells among us therein.  Tom, or the d&aelig;mon in
Tom, was not one of them.
</p> <p>With regard to his command of the instrument, two points
have been especially noted by musicians: the unusual frequency of
occurrence of <hi rend="italic">tours de force</hi> in his playing, and the scientific
precision of his manner of touch.  For example, in a progression of
augmented chords, his mode of fingering is invariably that of the
schools, not that which would seem natural to a blind child never
taught to place a finger.  Even when seated with his back to the
piano, and made to play in that position (a favorite feat in his
concerts,) the touch is always scientifically accurate.
</p> <p>The peculiar power which Tom possesses, however, is one
which requires no scientific knowledge of music in his audiences to
appreciate.  Placed at the instrument with any musician, he plays a
perfect bass accompaniment to the treble of music <hi rend="italic">heard for the
first time as he plays</hi>.  Then taking the seat vacated by the other
performer, he instantly gives the entire piece, intact in brilliancy and
symmetry, not a note lost or misplaced.  The selections of music by
which this power of Tom's was tested, two years ago, were
sometimes fourteen and sixteen pages in length; on one occasion, at
an exhibition at the White House, after a long concert, he was tried
with two pieces,&mdash;one thirteen, the other twenty pages long, and was
successful.
</p> <p>We know of no parallel case to this in musical history.  Grimm
tells us, as one of the most remarkable manifestations of Mozart's
infant genius, that at the age of nine he was required to give an
accompaniment to an aria which he had never heard before, and
without notes.  There were false accords in the first attempt, he
acknowledges; but the second was pure.  When the music to which
Tom plays <hi rend="italic">secondo</hi> is strictly classical, he sometimes balks
for an instant in passages; to do otherwise would argue a creative
power equal to that of the master composers; but when any chordant
harmony runs through it, (on which the glowing negro soul can
seize, you know,) there are no "false accords," as with the infant
Mozart.  I wish to draw especial attention to this power of the boy,
not only because it is, so far as I know, unmatched in the
development of any musical talent, but because, considered in the
context of his entire intellectual structure, it involves a curious
problem.  The mere repetition of music heard but once, even when,
as in Tom's case, it is given with such incredible fidelity, and after
the lapse of years, demands only a command of mechanical skill,
and an abnormal condition of the power of memory; but to play
<hi rend="italic">secondo</hi> to music never heard or seen implies the
comprehension of the full drift of the symphony in its current,&mdash;a
capacity to create, in short.  Yet such attempts as Tom has made to
dictate music for publication do not sustain any such inference.
They are only a few light marches, gallops, etc., simple and
plaintive enough, but with easily detected traces of remembered
harmonies: very different from the strange, weird improvisations of
every day.  One would fancy that the mere attempt to bring this
mysterious genius within him in bodily presence before the outer
world woke,
<pb n="584"/>
too, the idiotic nature to utter its reproachful,
unable cry.  Nor is this the only bar by which poor Tom's soul is put
in mind of its foul bestial prison.  After any too prolonged effort,
such as those I have alluded to, his whole bodily frame gives way,
and a complete exhaustion of the brain follows, accompanied with
epileptic spasms.  The trial at the White House, mentioned before,
was successful, but was followed by days of illness.
</p> <p>Being a slave, Tom never was taken into a Free State; for the
same reason his master refused advantageous offers from European
managers.  The highest points North at which his concerts were
given were Baltimore and the upper Virginia towns.  I heard him
sometime in 1860.  He remained a week or two in the town, playing
every night.
</p> <p>The concerts were unique enough.  They were given in a great
barn of a room, gaudy with hot, soot-stained frescoes, chandeliers,
walls splotched with gilt.  The audience was large, always; such as a
provincial town affords: not the purest bench of musical criticism
before which to bring poor Tom.  Beaux and belles, siftings of old
country families, whose grandfathers trapped and traded and
married with the Indians,&mdash;the savage thickening of whose blood
told itself in high cheekbones, flashing jewelry, champagne-bibbing,
a comprehension of the tom-tom music of schottisches and
polkas; money-made men and their wives, cooped up by
respectability, taking concerts when they were given in town, taking
the White Sulphur or Cape May in summer, taking beef for dinner,
taking the pork-trade in winter,&mdash;<hi rend="italic">toute la vie en programme;</hi>
the <hi rend="italic">d&eacute;bris</hi> of a town, the roughs, the boys, school-children,
&mdash;Tom was nearly as well worth a quarter as the negro-minstrels; here and
there a pair of reserved, home-sick eyes, a
peculiar, reticent face, some whey-skinned ward-teacher's, perhaps,
or some German cobbler's, but hints of a hungry soul, to whom
Beethoven and Mendelssohn knew how to preach an unerring
gospel.  The stage was broad, planked, with a drop-curtain behind,
&mdash;the Doge marrying the sea, I believe; in front, a piano and chair.
</p> <p>Presently, Mr. Oliver, a well-natured looking man, (one
thought of that,) came forward, leading and coaxing along a little
black boy, dressed in white linen, somewhat fat and stubborn in
build.  Tom was not in a good humor that night; the evening before
had refused to play altogether; so his master perspired anxiously
before he could get him placed in rule before the audience, and
repeat his own little speech, which sounded like a Georgia
after-dinner gossip.  The boy's head, as I said, rested on his back,
his
mouth wide open constantly; his great blubber lips and shining
teeth, therefore, were all you saw when he faced you.  He required
to be petted and bought like any other weak-minded child.  The
concert was a mixture of music, whining, coaxing, and promised
candy and cake.
</p> <p>He seated himself at last before the piano, a full half-yard
distant, stretching out his arms full-length, like an ape clawing for
food,&mdash;his feet, when not on the pedals, squirming and twisting
incessantly,&mdash;answering some joke of his master's with a loud "Yha!
yha!"  Nothing indexes the brain like the laugh; this was idiotic.
</p> <p>"Now, Tom, boy, something we like from Verdi."
</p> <p>The head fell farther back, the claws began to work, and those
of his harmonies which you would have chosen as the purest
exponents of passion began to float through the room.  Selections
from Weber, Beethoven, and others whom I have forgotten,
followed.  At the close of each piece, Tom, without waiting for the
audience, would himself applaud violently, kicking, pounding his
hands together, turning always to his master for the approving pat
on the head.  Songs, recitations such as I have described, filled up
the first part of the evening; then a musician from the audience went
upon the stage to put the boy's powers to the final test.  Songs and
intricate symphonies were given, which it was most improbable the
boy could ever have
<pb n="585"/>
heard; he remained standing, utterly
motionless, until they were finished, and for a moment or two after,
&mdash;then, seating himself, gave them without the break of a note.
Others followed, more difficult, in which he played the bass
accompaniment in the manner I have described, repeating instantly
the treble.  The child looked dull, wearied, during this part of the
trial, and his master, perceiving it, announced the exhibition closed,
when the musician (who was a citizen of the town, by-the-way)
drew out a thick roll of score, which he explained to be a Fantasia
of his own composition, never published.
</p> <p><hi rend="italic">"This</hi> it was impossible the boy could have heard;
there could be no trick of memory in this; and on this trial,"
triumphantly, "Tom would fail."
</p> <p>The manuscript was some fourteen pages long,&mdash;variations on
an inanimate theme.  Mr. Oliver refused to submit the boy's brain to
so cruel a test; some of the audience, even, interfered; but the
musician insisted, and took his place.  Tom sat beside him,&mdash;his
head rolling nervously from side to side,&mdash;struck the opening
cadence, and then, from the first note to the last, gave the
<hi rend="italic">secondo</hi> triumphantly.  Jumping up, he fairly shoved the
man from his seat, and proceeded to play the treble with more
brilliancy and power than its composer.  When he struck the last
octave, he sprang up, yelling with delight:&mdash;
</p> <p>"Um's got him, Massa! um's got him!" cheering and rolling
about the stage.
</p> <p>The cheers of the audience&mdash;for the boys especially did not
wait to clap&mdash;excited him the more.  It was an hour before his master
could quiet his hysteric agitation.
</p> <p>That feature of the concerts which was the most painful I have
not touched upon: the moments when his master was talking, and
Tom was left to himself,&mdash;when a weary despair seemed to settle
down on the distorted face, and the stubby little black fingers,
wandering over the keys, spoke for Tom's own caged soul within.
Never, by any chance, a merry, childish laugh of music in the
broken cadences; tender or wild, a defiant outcry, a tired sigh
breaking down into silence.  Whatever wearied voice it took, the
same bitter, hopeless soul spoke through all: "Bless me, even me,
also, O my Father!"  A something that took all the pain and pathos
of the world into its weak, pitiful cry.
</p> <p>Some beautiful caged spirit, one could not but know, struggled
for breath under that brutal form and idiotic brain.  I wonder when it
will be free.  Not in this life: the bars are too heavy.
</p> <p>You cannot help Tom, either; all the war is between you.  He
was in Richmond in May.  But (do you hate the moral to a story?) in
your own kitchen, in your own back-alley, there are spirits as
beautiful, caged in forms as bestial, that you <hi rend="italic">could</hi> set free,
if you pleased.  Don't call it bad taste in me to speak for them.  You
know they are more to be pitied than Tom,&mdash;for they are dumb.
</p>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

