<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DavInau"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="DavInau">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Inaugural Address</title>
<title type="sort">inaugural address</title>
<author>Davis, Jefferson</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Naked Word</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">15</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">DavInau</idno>
<date value="2000">2000</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2000 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475863</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Inaugural Address</title>
<title type="sort">inaugural address</title>
<author>Jefferson Davis</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>This e-text is based on the Naked Word e-text; however, the text was checked against a fuller version of the speech in THE LIFE
OF JEFFERSON DAVIS, by Frank H. Alfriend (Cincinnati &amp; Chicago: Caxton Publishing, 1868); passages from Alfriend have been added and
the Alfriend punctuation has been preferred.</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>645 pp.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Caxton Publishing</publisher>
<pubPlace>Cincinnati &amp; Chicago</pubPlace>
<date value="1868">1868</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Alderman Library E467.1 .D26A39 1868 copy 2</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Based on text in Alfriend`s LIFE OF JEFFERSON DAVIS.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1861">1861</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
<term>American Civil War</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2000-04">April 2000</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Matthew M. Davis, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Changed HTML tags to SGML, added missing text &amp; header.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>


<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="speech" id="d3">
<head> The Inaugural Address of Jefferson Davis</head>

<p>Montgomery, Alabama, February 18, 1861</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Gentlemen of the Congress of the Confederate States of America, Friends
and Fellow Citizens:</hi></p>

<p>Called to the difficult and responsible station of Chief Executive of the Provisional
Government that you have instituted, I approach the discharge of the duties assigned to
me with an humble distrust of my abilities, but with a sustaining confidence in the wisdom
of those who are to guide and aid me in the administration of public affairs, and an
abiding faith in the virtue and patriotism of the people.</p>

<p>Looking forward to the speedy establishment of a permanent government to take
the place of this, and which, by its greater moral and physical power, will be better
able to combat with the many difficulties which arise from the conflicting interests
of separate nations, I enter upon the duties of the office, to which I have
been chosen, with the hope that the beginning of our career, as a Confederacy,
may not be obstructed by hostile opposition to our enjoyment of the separate
existence and independence which we have asserted, and, with the blessing of
Providence, intend to maintain. Our present condition, achieved in
a manner unprecedented in the history
of nations, illustrates the American idea that governments rest upon the
consent of the governed, and that it is the right of the people to alter
or abolish governments whenever they become destructive of the ends for
which they were established.</p>

<p>The declared purpose of the compact of the union from which
we have withdrawn was "to establish justice, insure domestic tranquillity,
provide for the common defence, promote the general welfare, and secure the
blessings of liberty to ourselves and our posterity;" and when in the judgment
of the sovereign States now composing this Confederacy it has been perverted
from the purposes for which it was ordained, and ceased to answer the ends
for which it was established, a peaceful appeal to the ballot-box, declared,
that so far as they were concerned, the government created by that compact
should cease to exist. In this they merely asserted the right which the
Declaration of Independence of 1776 defined to be inalienable. Of the time
and occasion of this exercise they, as sovereigns, were the final judges, each
for itself. The impartial, enlightened verdict of mankind will vindicate
the rectitude of our conduct; and He, who knows the hearts of men, will judge
of the sincerity with which we labored to preserve the government of our
fathers in its spirit. The right solemnly proclaimed
at the birth of the States, and which has been
affirmed and reaffirmed in the bills of rights of the States subsequently
admitted into the Union of 1789, undeniably recognizes in the people the
power to resume the authority delegated for the purposes of government. Thus
the sovereign States, here represented, proceeded to form this Confederacy;
and it is by the abuse of language that their act has been denominated a
revolution. They formed a new alliance, but within each State its government
has remained, and the rights of person and property have not been disturbed.
The agent through whom they communicated with foreign nations is changed,
but this does not necessarily interrupt their international relations.</p>

<p>Sustained
by the consciousness that the transition from the former Union to the present
Confederacy has not proceeded from a disregard on our part of our just
obligations, or any failure to perform every constitutional duty; moved by
no interest or passion to invade the rights of others; anxious to cultivate
peace and commerce with all nations, if we may not hope to avoid war, we
may at least expect that posterity will acquit us of having needlessly engaged
in it. Doubly justified by the absence of wrong on our part, and by wanton
aggression on the part of others, there can be no use to doubt the courage
and patriotism of the people of the Confederate States will be found equal
to any measures of defence which honor and security may require.</p>

<p>An agricultural people, whose chief interest is the export of a commodity
required in every manufacturing country, our true policy is peace and the
freest trade which our necessities will permit. It is alike our interest,
and that of all those to whom we would sell and from whom we would buy, that
there should be the fewest practicable restrictions upon the interchange
of commodities. There can be but little rivalry between ours and any
manufacturing or navigating community, such as the North-eastern States of
the American Union. It must follow, therefore, that a mutual interest would
invite good-will and kind offices. If, however, passion or lust of dominion
should cloud the judgment or inflame the ambition of those States, we must
prepare to meet the emergency, and maintain, by the final arbitrament of the
sword, the position which we have assumed among the nations of the earth.
We have entered upon the career of independence, and it must be inflexibly
pursued.  Through many years of controversy with our late associates, the
Northern States, we have vainly endeavored to secure tranquillity, and obtain
respect for the rights to which we were entitled. As a necessity, not a choice,
we have resorted to the remedy of separation, and henceforth our energies
must be directed to the conduct of our own affairs, and the perpetuity of
the Confederacy which we have formed. If a just perception of mutual interest
shall permit us peaceably to pursue our separate political career, my most
earnest desire will have been fulfilled; but if this be denied to us, and the
integrity of our territory and jurisdiction be assailed, it will but remain
for us, with firm resolve, to appeal to arms and invoke the blessing of Providence
on a just cause.</p>

<p>As a consequence of our new condition, and with a view to meeting anticipated wants,
it will be necessary to provide for the speedy and efficient organization of the
Executive Department, having special charge of foreign intercourse, finance, military
affairs, and the postal service.</p>

<p>For purposes of defense, the Confederate States may, under ordinary circumstances,
rely mainly upon the militia; but it is deemed advisable, in the present condition
of affairs, that there should be a well-instructed and disciplined army, more
numerous than would usually be required for a peace establishment. I also suggest
that, for the protection of our harbors and commerce on the high seas, a navy adapted
to those objects will be required.  These necessities have doubtless engaged the
attention of Congress.</p>

<p>With a Constitution differing only from that of our fathers, in so far as it
is explanatory of their well-known intent, freed from the sectional conflicts
which have interfered with the pursuit of the general welfare, it is not
unreasonable to expect that States, from which we have recently parted, may
seek to unite their fortunes with ours under the government which we have
instituted. For this your Constitution makes adequate provision; but beyond
this, if I mistake not the judgment and will of the people, a reunion with
the States from which we have separated is neither practicable nor desirable.
To increase the power, develop the resources, and promote the happiness of
the Confederacy, it is requisite that there should be so much of homogeneity
that the welfare of every portion shall be the aim of the whole.  Where this does
not exist, antagonisms are engendered which must and should result in separation.</p>

<p>Actuated solely by a desire to preserve our own rights, and to promote our
own welfare, the separation of the Confederate States has been marked by
no aggression upon others, and followed by no domestic convulsion. Our industrial
pursuits have received no check; the cultivation of our fields has progressed
as heretofore; and even should we be involved in war, there would be no
considerable diminution in the production of the staples which have constituted
our exports, in which the commercial world has an interest scarcely less
than our own. This common interest of producer and consumer can only be
intercepted by an exterior force, which should obstruct its transmission to
foreign markets&mdash;a course of conduct which would be detrimental to manufacturing
and commercial interests abroad.
Should reason guide the action of the Government from which we have separated,
a policy so detrimental to the civilized world, the Northern States included,
could not be dictated by even the strongest desire to inflict injury upon us;
but if otherwise, a terrible responsibility will rest upon it, and
the suffering of millions will bear testimony to the folly and wickedness
of our aggressors. In the meantime, there will remain to us, besides the ordinary
remedies before suggested, the well-known resources for retaliation upon
the commerce of an enemy.</p>

<p>Experience in public stations, of subordinate grade to this which your
kindness has conferred, has taught me that care, and toil, and disappointment,
are the price of official elevation.  You will see many errors to forgive,
many deficiencies to tolerate, but you shall not find in me either a want of
zeal or fidelity to the cause that is to me highest in hope and of most eduring
affection. Your generosity has bestowed upon me an undeserved distinction&mdash;one
which I neither sought nor desired. Upon the continuance of that sentiment,
and upon your wisdom and patriotism, I rely to direct and support me in the
performance of the duty required at my hands.</p>

<p>We have changed the constituent parts but not
the system of our Government. The Constitution formed by our fathers is that
of these Confederate States. In their exposition of it, and in the judicial
construction it has received, we have a light which reveals its true meaning.</p>

<p>Thus instructed as to the just interpretation of the instrument, and ever
remembering that all offices are but trusts held for the people, and that
delegated powers are to be strictly construed, I will hope, by due diligence
in the performance of my duties, though I may disappoint your expectations,
yet to retain, when retiring, something of the good-will and confidence which
will welcome my entrance into office.</p>

<p>It is joyous, in the midst of perilous times, to look around upon a people
united in heart, where one purpose of high resolve animates and actuates the
whole, where the sacrifices to be made are not weighed in the balance against
honor, right, liberty, and equality. Obstacles may retard&mdash;but they cannot
long prevent&mdash;the progress of a movement sanctioned by its justice and sustained
by a virtuous people. Reverently let us invoke the God of our fathers to
guide and protect us in our efforts to perpetuate the principles which, by
his blessing, they were able to vindicate, establish, and transmit to their
posterity, and with a continuance of His favor, ever gratefully acknowledged,
we may hopefully look forward to success, to peace, and to prosperity.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
