<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DavTime"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="DavTime">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">An Old-Time Love Story</title>
<title type="sort">old time love story</title>
<author>Davis, Rebecca Harding, 1831-1910</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name>creator of image(s)</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">13</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">DavTime</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475865</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"An Old-Time Love Story"</title>
<title type="sort">an old time love story</title>
<author>Davis, Rebecca Harding</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<date value="1908">1908</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Century Magazine 77 (Dec. 1908): 219-221.</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center
scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1908">1908</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-02">Feb. 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jan Horner</name>
</respStmt>
<item>TEI header &amp; footer added</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">


<body id="d2">
<div1 type="story" id="d3">
	<pb n="219"/>
<head>
Davis, Rebecca Harding.  "An Old-Time Love Story."
     <hi rend="italic">Century Magazine</hi> 77 (Dec. 1908): 219-221.
<lb/>
 Author of Silhouettes of American Life," "Bits of Gossip," etc.
</head>



<p>
ON the shelves of the libraries of our historical societies are
many privately printed volumes, the histories of American families
whose ancestors settled here in early days.  They usually are dull
reading enough, but we sometimes find in them fragments of real
life more strange and tragic than any fiction.
</p><p>Here are one or two incidents picked out of these dusty
unpublished volumes.  They are facts, and give us a glimpse of the
ideas which our forefathers had of love and honor.  After the
stories of modern marriages and divorce to which we are accustomed
lately, they have to me a queer and welcome flavor, something like
an Arab meal of figs and bread and water after a dinner at a Paris
cafe.

THESE old records show that of all the immigrants who sought homes
in this country, none came with higher purposes than the Swedes.
</p><p>"I will open in the wilderness," said Gustavus Adolphus, in
his edict, "a home where every man can earn his bread, and worship
God as he chooses."
</p><p>His promise was kept after he was gone.
</p><p>The Swedes who first came here were for the most part
laborers, though free-born.  Some convicts who arrived were sent
back again, "lest the souls of the heathen should be corrupted by
them."
</p><p>Many of the new-comers lived in caves and well-nigh starved.

Their desperate efforts were watched at home with prayers and high
hopes.  Even the wild little Queen Christina kept her far-off
subjects in mind and tried to help them.  She built churches for
them, some of which are still standing on the Delaware.  She sent
out gospelers to this mysterious continent on <pb n="220"/>
the other
side of the globe to rescue the souls of the savages.  These holy
men were regarded with awe in Sweden as messengers of Christ, going

out to martyrdom for Him.
</p><p>One whose name was Snorr, a man from the inland, stayed in
Gothenburg several months, waiting for a ship.  He was a lean,
gray, hungry-looking man, who spoke seldom.  People feared to
approach him, feeling that his soul dwelt apart with God.
</p><p>When the young queen expressed her wish that the
missionaries
should marry before they went out to New Sweden, the pastors of the

churches in Gothenburg consulted and found a wife for Dr. Snorr in
a healthy girl named Aggie Kyn, the niece of a farmer living near
the town.  She was a plump, fair-skinned, good-tempered young woman

who never had given any thought to lovers.  When they told her that

she was chosen to help the doctor in his holy work, she cried a
good deal, being sure that the cannibals would cook and eat her.
She begged them at least to wait until her cousin Peter Kalm would
come home and give them his opinion.  But the case was immediate,
and Peter was in Norway, and probably would not be back for months.

He had gone to hunt for the eggs of an insect which was killing the

grain.  Most people thought it was a fool, half-witted thing just
fit for Peter to do.  He had been thrown out of the classes in
Latin and arithmetic when he was a boy, being too dull to learn.
He was a man now, and knew nothing of books.  Being a rich farmer's

son, that mattered little.  He used to live in the woods and grub
incessantly in the earth, and there was not a plant above ground,
nor a worm nor beetle under it, that he did not know as an old
friend, with all its habits and ways.  Peter himself was a big,
clean, blue-eyed man, much liked by everybody; for, if he knew
nothing of Latin or arithmetic, he understood and had a joke and
kind word for every man or dog in Gothenburg.  As for women, the
word meant nothing but Aggie to him.  They had been nursed together

at his mother's breast, they had slept in the same cradle, had
thumped each other when they were angry, and kissed to make
friends.  She knitted his stockings and made his shirts for him,
and he chose her a new gown every year at the fair.  From dawn
until night he was the concern of her thoughts, and she was to him
the only woman in the world.  It never occurred to him, indeed,
that there was any other.  He had not told her that he loved her,
for that never had occurred to him either.
</p><p>When he came back late that summer, with his eggs in a tin
box, Aggie did not run down the road to meet him.  At the house
they told him that she had married a strange old man and sailed to
the other side of the world to teach the cannibals of Christ.
</p><p>Those of us who are women can guess how it had gone with
Aggie.  She knew that the town looked on her with awe and envy when

she was chosen; the lean old man she believed to be a kind of
angel; and the unseen, awful majesty of the queen and, back of her,

God Himself, were urging her to go.
</p><p>She had gone.
</p><p>After that I find no mention of Peter except a brief note
that
the degree of professor of natural history was conferred on him by
the University of Stockholm.  He became the highest authority on
insects and moths then in the world, living much in the woods.  But

apparently he never found out that there was another woman in God's

universe.
</p><p>There are, however, more frequent mentions of Dr. Snorr.  He

landed with his wife at Philadelphia, and at once, like the other
immigrants, dug a cave in the hillside for a home.  Aggie helped to

dig it, being, in fact, stronger than he.  The cave was big enough
to hold a bed and a table.  There were logs for a floor.  When the
doctor went out to preach to the poor Swedes who were hungry for
the word of God, Aggie worked day after day, trying to make the
place like a home.  But on rainy days the mud would ooze up from
the ground, and worms and even snakes crawled out of the walls.
The soul of the old man was on fire with the Holy Spirit; but
Aggie's heart grew more sodden and cold every day.
</p><p>In a few months all the money which they had brought from
Sweden was gone.  The people in the settlement were as poor as
themselves.  Many died of ague, others starved to death.  The
minister toiled for them night and day; he was always kind to his
wife, but his heart was in his work. <pb n="221"/>
</p><p>In the spring, Aggie worked in the field for a month or two
to
get food for them.  Then her baby came, and soon the fever attacked

her husband.  She took care of them both.  The neighbors were sorry

for the white-faced, weak woman, but they themselves were sick and
starving, and could not help her.
</p><p>When, in the autumn, the ship <hi rend="italic">Key of Calmar</hi> made its
voyage to Gothenburg, Peter found in the records it brought a
black-lined notice, "Died of fever on May 10, Jacob Snorr, Pastor
and Doctor."
</p><p>And below, under other black lines, were the words, "Died on

May 20, Agnes Snorr, of fever.
</p><p>After that, for a year or two, the people of Gothenburg
talked
of the holy minister and his wife with awe.  They were martyrs;
they had given their lives to preach Christ to the heathen; they
were with him now in glory.  It was a favorite subject when they
gathered around the fire.  But whenever Peter came in, they talked
of other things.  It was known that in all this time he never once
had spoken Aggie's name.  There was a dull suspicion that he blamed

the zealous good folk who had sent her out to her death; and when
in the second year it was known that the professor was going out to

study the plants and insects of New Sweden, every woman knew that
his errand was to find the place where she lay.  One thing was
plain: he had grown lean and silent.  He was not the man he had
been.
</p><p>Peter's voyage was long and dreary.  The passengers were a
gay
crowd, noisy with their hopes and plans; but all that he cared for
in the vast new continent was a grave.
</p><p>The ship came into port late at night.  By dawn the leading
citizens, led by Governor Bezelius, boarded her to welcome the
famous professor, and brought him to shore with great rejoicings.

When he was alone with the governor in his house, he said:
</p><p>"I should like to go alone to the grave of Dr. Snorr."
</p><p>"Surely, surely," said Bezelius.  "The God's Acre is near
by.
He lies there, with his child beside him."
</p><p>Peter stood up.  He staggered, and tried to speak, but was
dumb for a minute.
</p><p>"His wife&mdash;lies beside him," he said at length.
</p><p>"Not at all," said the old man, cheerfully; "not at all.
Frau
Snorr is with us still.  There is her hut under that oak-tree&mdash;
Why&mdash;" as his guest, white and trembling, made for the door.
"Hola!  Is that so?  Well, God be praised!"  He ran to the window
and watched the professor go down the road.  Out of the hut came a
lean, bent woman, carrying a basket.  She did not raise her eyes
until the man came up to her and took it out of her hands.
</p><p>"I'll carry your load," he said; "I'll go with you&mdash;to the
end, Aggie."
</p><p>He did not know what he said.
</p><p>There was a wedding that very day at the governor's house.
</p><p>We find in the records, years later, notices of journeys
made
through all the settlements by the professor in search of insects
and plants.  He was always accompanied by his wife.
</p><p>They ventured among the reputed cannibals of Florida to
bring
back alligators' eggs, and penetrated far into Canada in search of
a certain butterfly.  After one or two years there are allusions to

the advent of a plump, blue-eyed baby.  Soon after its appearance
I note that Professor Kalm returned home and settled down to
collegiate work in Sweden.
</p><p>How many men in every generation have dismounted from
Pegasus
at middle age and taken to plowing with some dull hack, slaves for
the rest of their lives to the needs of their children!
</p><p>Hereafter, history is silent about Kalm and his wife.  But
Linnaeus, who was his nearest friend, gave his name to the American

laurel, and so to-day, as soon as June comes, he being dead, that
most beautiful of flowers calls his memory to life in every valley
and on every peak of our mountains.
</p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
