<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DawHave"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="DawHave">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Have We Failed with the Indian?</title>
<title type="sort">have we failed with the indian</title>
<author>Dawes, Henry L.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">22</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">DawHave</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475867</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Have We Failed with the Indian?</title>
<title type="sort">have we failed with the indian</title>
<author>Henry L. Dawes</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 84</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 280-285</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text
Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of
the text's unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in
SpeFQue1 for page one of Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction; prose</term>
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-04">April 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Timothy Jarrett</name>
</respStmt>
<item>minimal TEI markup</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">


<div1 type="article" id="d3">
<pb n="280"/>

<p>WHEN the public mind is directed to a discussion of the wisest
and safest attitude toward other alien races whose future has been put in
our keeping, our policy with the Indians becomes an object lesson
worthy of careful and candid study.  It is for this purpose that attention
is here invited to what that policy has come to be, and what it has thus
far accomplished.  The treatment of the Indian has been the subject of
much study and experiment that has proved fruitless.  Only by the
process of elimination after experiment have the multitude of ephemeral
and ineffective methods given way to one which has at last come to hold
undivided public support for a time long enough to test its
efficacy.</p>
<p>The present Indian policy of the government is of comparatively
recent date.  It is hardly yet twenty-five years since the first step was
taken.  The beginning was small and tentative, but the policy has steadily
grown in the public confidence and in the enlargement of effort, until,
judged by results, it now stands justified.  Before its adoption the attitude
of the government toward the different tribes was in general that of kind,
patient care.  There were exceptional cases in this treatment, &mdash; instances
of hardship, injustice, and wrong, &mdash; not to be defended; traceable,
however, almost always to unfit stewards and unfaithful public servants,
and not to the deliberate act of the government itself.  The prevailing
idea was that of guardianship of an uncivilized race among us,

<pb n="281"/>  incapable of self-support or self-restraint, over which
public safety as well as the dictates of humanity required the exercise of
a constant, restraining care, until it should fade out of existence in the
irresistible march of civilization.  It very soon became apparent that
under this treatment the race did not diminish, but, by reason of
protection from the slaughter of one another in wars among themselves
and from diseases inseparable from savage life, it increased in number.
This increase in population calling for more room, we were confronted
with another problem not before taken into account.  Emigration was
yearly swelling in numbers, and marching like an army with banners
upon the public domain and over into Indian reservations.  These
conditions, impossible to change, forced upon the country a change in its
Indian policy.  This army of newcomers was invading and appropriating
to the uses of civilization the reservations which the increasing number
of the Indian race was making more and more necessary for its own
support.  There would soon be little unoccupied room for either race,
and it was plain that the two could not live together, and that the one
must speedily crowd out the other.  What was to become of the
untutored, defenseless Indian, when he found himself thus pushed out of
the life and home of the reservation, and cut off from the hunting and
fishing which furnished the only and scanty supply of his daily wants?  It
was plain that if he were left alone he must of necessity become a tramp
and beggar with all the evil passions of a savage, a homeless and lawless
poacher upon civilization, and a terror to the peaceful citizen.</p>
<p>It was this condition which forced on the nation its present Indian
policy.  It was born of sheer necessity.  Inasmuch as the Indian refused
to fade out, but multiplied under the sheltering care of reservation life,
and the reservation itself was slipping away from him, there was but one
alternative: either he must be endured as a lawless savage, a constant
menace to civilized life, or he must be fitted to become a part of that life
and be absorbed into it.  To permit him to be a roving savage was
unendurable, and therefore the task of fitting him for civilized life was
undertaken.</p>
<p>This, then, is the present Indian policy of the nation, &mdash; to fit the
Indian for civilization and to absorb him into it.  It is a national work.  It
is less than twenty-five years since the government turned from the
policy of keeping him on reservations, as quiet as possible, out of the
way of civilization, waiting, with no excess of patience, for the race to
fade out of existence and to cease from troubling.  It was in 1877 that
the nation made the first appropriation from its own treasury to fit for its
own citizenship this portion of the human race living under its own flag
and constitution, but without legal status or constitutional immunities.
They were sometimes called in political phraseology savages, and
sometimes wards or dependents, but generally savages, because no other
word came so near expressing their status and character.  The first
appropriation was a mere pittance of $20,000; it was given only after a
hard struggle.  But the first step met with encouragement, and the next
year the sum was increased to $30,000, and then to $60,000, and in two
years more it became $125,000.  The policy has at last so grown in
public confidence that, while there is still much discussion of the best
methods of expenditure, not a word is heard among the lawgivers for its
abandonment.  It has in the meantime so broadened in its scope that the
appropriations for this work have increased from year to year, till this
year (1899) it has risen to $2,638,390.</p>
<p>This vast outlay would of itself justify an inquiry into results.  But
an inquiry is demanded for another reason, because the assumed
"failure" of our Indian policy is quoted in discussions of the

<pb n="282"/>  attitude of the nation toward other alien peoples and
our treatment of them.  An eminent preacher, on last Thanksgiving Day,
declared to a large congregation, "I should rather be a Malay subject to
Spain than an American Indian subject to the Indian Bureau."  A leading
religious weekly of the widest circulation, discussing the same subject,
stated that "our treatment of the Indian has been a miserable failure."
There appeared also in one of the oldest of our magazines an article, by
one whose sincerity and ability no one has ever questioned, demanding a
radical departure, an abandonment of our present Indian policy.  Men of
less note, thus encouraged, are turning great microscopic power upon the
government's treatment of the Indian for the last twenty-five years, in
search of support for these arguments.  It does not seem out of place,
then, again to call public attention to what has been done for the Indian,
and to see whether our present policy is a failure.</p>
<p>The contrast between the small beginning and the last appropriation
itself indicates a public confidence based on merit.  Much more would
the aggregate of the outlay, if we should count it up, make imperative
the inquiry, What else than success could possibly have induced
adherence to so costly an outlay?  The aggregate of all sums
appropriated for this purpose since the first $20,000 in 1877 amounts to
$29,352,344.  Previous Indian policies had been shifting and ephemeral
enough to promise a dozen changes during the period that the present
policy has continued.  Before this hardly one had outlived the
administration that originated it, and sometimes two or three would come
and go in a single presidential term.  But when, in 1877, the government
made its first appropriation, of $20,000, to educate the Indian up to a
self-supporting citizenship, the money was expended in conjunction with
benevolent contributions, and with the interest on funds belonging to the
Indians, in support of 48 small boarding schools and 102 day schools
with 3598 pupils.  These schools were opened at the different
reservations most promising for such an experiment.  The result of each
year's work since this small beginning explains the constantly increasing
public confidence and additional expenditure as well as the enlargement
of the work.  There are now 148 well-equipped boarding schools and
295 day schools, engaged in the education of 24,004 children, with an
average attendance of 19,671.  How near this comes to including the
whole number of children of school age, in a total population of a
quarter of a million of Indians, every inquirer can form a pretty close
estimate for himself.</p>
<p>No one will deny that, at this rate of progress, the facilities for the
education of Indian children will soon reach, if they have not already
reached, those enjoyed by their white neighbors in the remote regions of
the West.  The results thus far are of a most encouraging character.  A
personal examination, by competent and reliable officials, of all these
schools, and as far as possible of the life of every person who has gone
out from them, shows that seventy-six per cent of them are proving
themselves, in the language of the present wise and broad-minded
commissioner who has this work in charge, "good average men and
women, capable of dealing with the ordinary problems of life, and of
taking their place in the great body politic of our country."  This is an
army of missionaries going forth among their own people, speaking the
language, clothed with the equipment, and inspired with the hopes and
ambitions of civilized life.  Its value cannot be overestimated.  It is to
this ultimate end that these schools are conducted.  Industrial education
which will fit the pupil for independent manhood is the necessity which
justifies

<pb n="283"/>  the undertaking.  Whatever else may await these youth,
they must be able to meet the demands of the life which will surround
them, or they will fail.  If they are to be farmers, as most of them must
be, it is of vastly more importance to them, in the outset, to be taught
the requirements of a successful farmer, &mdash; irrigation, grain-raising,
grazing, herding, &mdash; than to be taught any amount of book-learning or
culture.  This dominating purpose of the Indian school is the test of its
usefulness.  The result of its work thus far has not failed to stand the
test.</p>
<p>But the work does not stop with the rising generation of the race;
it embraces also the adult Indian.  The home, no less in savage than in
civilized life, is the centre of the influences that shape and determine
character.  Neglect of it is neglect of the future.  Soon after the
beginning of appropriations for Indian schools, Congress, in what is
called the Severalty Act, provided for every Indian capable of
appreciating its value, and who chose to take it, a homestead of one
hundred and sixty acres to heads of families, and a smaller number to
other members, inalienable and untaxable for twenty-five years, to be
selected by him on the reservation of his tribe.  If he prefer to abandon
his tribe and go elsewhere, he may take his allotment anywhere on the
public domain, free of charge.  No English baron has a safer title to his
manor than has each Indian to his homestead.  He cannot part with it for
twenty-five years without the consent of Congress, nor can the United
States, without his consent, be released from a covenant to defend his
possession for the same period.  This allotment carries with it also all the
rights, privileges, and immunities of an American citizen; opens to these
Indians, as to all other citizens, the doors of all the courts; and extends
to them the protection of all the laws, national and state, which affect
any other citizen.  Any Indian, if he prefers not to be a farmer,
incumbered with one of these homesteads, may become a citizen of the
United States, and reside and prosecute any calling in any part of the
United States, as securely under this law as any one else, by taking up
his residence separate and apart from his tribe, and adopting the habits of
civilized life.  Thus every door of opportunity is thrown wide open to
every adult Indian, as well as to those of the next generation.</p>
<p>This recognition of the home and family as a force in Indian
civilization became a part of the present policy of dealing with the race
only twelve years ago.  These are some of its results: 55,467 individual
Indians, including a few under former treaty stipulations, have taken
their allotments, making an aggregate of 6,708,628 acres.  Of these,
30,000 now hold complete patents to their homes, and the rest are
awaiting the perfection and delivery of their title deeds.  More than
15,000 are heads of families now holding permanent homes, &mdash;
permanent for twenty-five years, at least.  Around these are gathered the
lesser allotments of the other members of each family.  Every adult male
landholder stands at the polls and in the courts in the full rights of
American citizenship.</p>
<p>Not alone in these statistics are manifest the evidences of
permanent advance of the race toward the goal of orderly, self-supporting citizenship.  Bloody Indian wars have ceased.  The slaughter
of warring clans and the scalping of women and children fleeing from
burning wigwams are no longer recorded.  Geronimo himself has
become a teacher of peace.  The recent unfortunate difficulty with the
Chippewas in Minnesota, caused more by lack of white than of red
civilization, is no exception.  We are at peace with the Indian all along
the border, and the line between the Indian and the white settlements is
fast fading out.  The pioneer goes forth to trade and barter with the red
man as

<pb n="284"/>  safely as he does with his white neighbor, and returns
at night to his defenseless home with less apprehension of peril to those
within than when scouts and sentinels mounted guard over it.  This
change has come quite as much from causes at work among the Indians
themselves as from the influence of those who have the shaping of our
policy.  During these twelve years, families and adult Indians without
families, in all more than 30,000, have found homes of their own on
Indian lands, and are maintaining themselves by farming, stock-raising,
and other pursuits to which peace is essential, and have themselves
become peacemakers.  Results from this brief experiment cannot be put
into figures, but statistics recently published by authority as substantially
correct are a sufficient and unanswerable argument in its support.  From
them it appears that these new-born Indian farmers have already fenced
for their own farms 1,066,368 acres, from which they have realized,
beyond what they themselves consumed, of vegetables, grain, hay, stock,
and other farm products, the sum of $1,220,517.  It is needless to say
that this is a peace establishment more effective to prevent outbreaks
among these Indians than all the bayonets relied on in the past for that
purpose.  In the Carlisle industrial school, the earliest and most
persistent in developing the industrial faculties of Indian pupils, the
scholars have a savings bank of their own, conducted by themselves, in
which they deposit their earnings during the summer months.  These
deposits have aggregated as much as $15,000.  From them they often, of
their own motion, disburse, in various benevolent enterprises connected
with the work, percentages of each deposit.</p>
<p>There is another side of this question yet to be considered.  What
has the church been able to do under this policy?  Bishop Hare, who has
devoted his life to the uplifting of the Indian in the diocese of the two
Dakotas, tells of a dozen Indian clergymen, and more than fifty deacons
and catechists, engaged in missionary work among the Sioux alone, and
1600 Indian communicants in the Episcopal church.  The Indian women
in his diocese contributed in one year $2000 for missionary purposes.
There are 33,000 Sioux, and 8000 are members of various churches.
The Presbyterians, working among the Indians in other parts of the
country, report nearly 5000 church members and 4000 enrolled in their
Sunday schools, who gave in one year for missions $2600, besides $3400
toward their own support.  Equally encouraging are reports from other
denominations in all parts of the field where the national policy of
making self-supporting citizens has taken root.  The aggregate of church
communicants is 28,351.</p>
<p>Other features of the work are not less successful.  Not the least is
the manhood it has inspired and the hope it has awakened in the Indian.
It is dawning upon him that he was made for something, and he is
beginning to care for the morrow.  Pride in his children, in his home and
its surroundings, is prompting effort and stimulating desire to excel.  He
no longer doubts and distrusts, and is daily growing more and more sure
that the hand held out to him is for guidance and help, and not for
betrayal or spoliation.</p>
<p>Such is the purpose of the present Indian policy of the nation, and
these are some of its results.  It is not all it should be, and there is yet
need of the ever mending hand of the legislator as well as the watchful
eye of the administrator.  But the work has passed beyond the stage of
experiment, and has won a permanent place in the conduct of public
affairs.  Those whose hands and hearts are in the work no longer
criticise, but labor to improve.  When such results have been
accomplished in the green tree, what may we not hope for in the dry?

<pb n="285"/> </p>
<p>But let it ever be kept in mind that, after all, the civilization of the
Indian cannot be enacted.  The function of the law in this work is little
more than the clearing of the way, the removal of disabilities, the
creation of opportunities, and the shelter and protection of agencies
elsewhere vitalized.  The one vitalizing force, without which all else will
prove vain, is the Indian's own willingness to adopt civilized life.  Until
this is quickened into activity, everything else will wilt and perish like a
plant without root.  Every effort must recognize this cardinal principle.
Much can be done to kindle in him a desire for a better life and to nurse
its beginnings, building it up to an aggressive force; but until this exist,
any attempt, through legislation or in any other way, to impose
civilization upon the race will prove a failure.  When that desire and
hope for a better life shall begin to prevail over savage instincts, if the
law shall then have made the way clear and the path plain, and,
co-operating with outside efforts to strengthen and mature the new
impulses, shall have made sure the rewards of civilization and the
immunities of citizenship, it will have fulfilled its purpose.  This is the
endeavor of the Indian policy of to-day.  Opening up so wide a field, and
imposing an obligation for increased effort on every friend of the race,
whatever may be his theory, it may calmly await the first stone from any
of those who can claim Scriptural authority for casting it.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
