<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DawIndi"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="DawIndi">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"The Indian Territory."</title>
<title type="sort">the indian territory</title>
<author>Dawes, Henry L.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">20</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">DawIndi</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475868</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Electronic version checked by xerox copy received from
Interlibrary Loan Service.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Indian Territory</title>
<title type="sort">indian territory</title>
<author>Hon. Henry L. Dawes, LL.D.</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Independent Publications</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">The Independent</hi>
</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Vol.52, 25 Oct. : Pages 2561-2565.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions
for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp/>
<name>Lorrie S. Chisholm, Electronic Text Center, University of
Virginia Library System.</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Minimal Tei tagging, removed unambiguous line-end hyphenation,
ran electronic spell check using wp51.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">


<div1 type="story" id="d3">
	<pb n="2561"/>
<head>The Indian Territory.*
<lb/>
By the Hon. Henry L. Dawes, LL.D.
<lb/>
FORMERLY UNITED STATES SENATOR FROM MASSACHUSETTS, AND
CHAIRMAN OF THE DAWES COMMISSION FOR THE FIVE CIVILIZED TRIBES
<lb/>
*This paper was read at the Lake Mohonk Indian Conference.&mdash; EDITOR.
</head>


<p>IN order to understand the purpose for which the Commission to the
Five Civilized Tribes was created, and the present condition of
their work, it will be necessary to refresh our memories as to the
conditions which caused its appointment.  So much of the past of
these tribes as is essential for this purpose is briefly this.
These tribes are the Cherokees, the Choctaws, the Chickasaws, the
Creeks, and the Seminoles, numbering about 64,000 at the last
census.  Seventy years ago they were living on their own lands in
Georgia, North Carolina and Mississippi, and to induce them to
surrender these lands to the white men of the States where they
were situated, the United States gave them in exchange the Indian
Territory.  In the treaties made with them we conveyed the title to
the lands directly to the tribes for the use of the people of the
tribes to hold as long as they maintained their tribal
organizations and occupied them.  This stipulation prevented their
parting with them without the consent of the United States.  We
stipulated in these treaties that they should have the right to
establish their own governments without our interference, such
governments as they pleased, not in conflict with the constitution
of the United States.  We also covenanted with them that we would
keep all the white people out of their territory.  Having thus set
them up for themselves in a territory far west of any of the
States, beyond all further trouble, as it was thought, we left them
to do as they pleased for forty years.
</p><p>During that time they set up governments after the pattern of
our own, at least on paper, with a chief magistrate chosen for a
fixed term, a legislative council and courts.  They were more
advanced in civilization than any other Indians in the country, tho
hardly enough so to justify the name by which they have been
distinguished from the rest of the race.  The expectation upon
which these transactions were based was that they were sufficiently
civilized, so that thus isolated they would go on under the
influence of our example to the attainment of our own civilization
and our Government in all essential characteristics.  This
expectation was far from being realized, for during that time they
had made little if any progress.  They

<pb n="2562"/>
had become slaveholders and thereby made all labor of the master disreputable,
and idleness worked its natural results.  A few grew rich while the
less intelligent many in consequence grew poor.  Their governments
in all departments fell under control of these same few, who used
them for their own gain, and their children every year, for lack of
training and proper education, fell back of their parents in all
the qualities essential to progress in civilization.
</p><p>At the breaking out of the Civil War they had made but little,
if any, progress, and in many respects their condition was less
hopeful than in the beginning.  They cast in their fortunes with
the Confederates during the war, and were the victims of spoliation
to a terrible degree by the armies of both sides.  At its end they
were well nigh beggars, stripped of everything valuable and
wretchedly helpless.  We then entered into new treaties with them
with some modifications of the old ones, not changing, however, the
nature of their title to their lands.  Slavery in the Territory was
abolished by these treaties and the tribes stipulated to receive
their freedmen into perfect equality of citizenship, with the right
to an allotment of a specific number of acres of their land
whenever their lands were allotted.
</p><p>On this new basis they began anew in 1866, but under
conditions and amid environments still less favorable to any
development of well ordered governments.  They were no longer
isolated from outside influences.  States, as well as these
Indians, had moved westward and were pressing upon their very
borders.  Their lands had become valuable by the discovery of vast
deposits of coal and other material.  Cotton fields of great extent
and promise were developing, and vast areas of grazing lands were
tempting the herdsmen of Texas.  In the new treaties they had
consented to the building of a railroad from north to south across
their Territory, and the Missouri, Kansas &amp; Texas road was built
through its entire length from the north to its southern boundary,
bringing in its train white employees at every station, and with
them all necessary supplies, breaking down beyond repair all treaty
obligation to exclude white occupation.  Besides all this, white
labor had taken the place of slave labor.  In short, more than
three hundred thousand white non-citizens had under various
conditions taken up permanent residence in the Territory.  These
people had no legal status or right among them.  Some were there on
invitation, some had come as hired laborers, and some were there on
sufferance.  They had come to stay, and the obligation of the
treaty to keep them out had become a dead letter.  Yet these three
hundred thousand had no title to a foot of land, had no voice in
the government under which they lived, and no protection from its
officials or laws, were excluded from its courts and their children
from its schools.  They built towns on land to which they had no
other title than a permit of no legal value, for which they paid
tribute to some irresponsible holder, and governed them as best
they could.  Thirty thousand white children of school age were
being left without any other provision for education than such as
could be afforded from the scanty earnings of the pioneer.  Then
came a worse evil into their midst.  The Territory became a refuge
for fugitives from the justice of neighboring States.  Warrants of
arrest could not follow them across the line, and no provision of
the constitution or of law required their extradition.
</p><p>It is not necessary to enlarge upon the deplorable condition
into which these elements were sure to plunge the Territory, from
which its government, such as it was, in the hands of comparatively
a handful of the population, could have no power to relieve it.
And we had bound ourselves to stand aloof and not interfere,
whatever might take place.  That such a government should exist in
the midst of the States of the Union independent of us, yet under
the same flag, was an impossible anomaly of itself.  It also
contained elements of discord which under any circumstances made
the maintenance of peace and orderly government within its own
borders for any length of time next to impossible.  It had become
peopled by two races in which the one owning the soil and having
control of all the functions of government was to the other race as
less than one to three, making certain sooner or later an outbreak
for relief, violent and bloody, like all other conflicts of races
for power.
</p><p>Under these conditions it was that in

<pb n="2563"/>
1893 the Government felt compelled to undertake the removal of this menace
to its own peace as well as to that of the Territory itself, by an
effort to induce these anomalous governments with their communal
land titles to exchange them for political institutions and land
tenure in harmony with our own.  The task was to obtain their
consent to so great and radical a change, for all these conditions
were titles vested and guaranteed by treaty, which could not be
changed without their consent.  It was for this purpose that the
Commission was created in 1893, and for which it is still engaged.
</p><p>The first task before the Commission, and that which has
proved the most difficult, was obtaining agreements with them that
any change at all should be made.  In addition to the traditional
pertinacity with which the race clings to its own customs and ways
it encountered adverse interests and business investments that had
grown up and been fostered under existing governments, as well as
distrust so natural and constant in all negotiations with Indians
and the difficulty of comprehension of the full meaning of the
proposed change.  A recital of details would not be profitable.
Suffice it to say that after repeated failures and after repeated
rejections of agreements signed, sometimes by the tribes and
sometimes by Congress, agreements have finally been signed and
ratified with the Choctaws, Chickasaws and Seminoles, providing for
the allotment of all their lands, except such as are reserved for
town sites and public uses, among such persons as shall finally be
found by the Commission to be citizens, the substitution of United
States laws and courts for those heretofore in force in these
tribes, the expenditure of their revenues by United States
officers, and the supervision of their schools by officials
appointed in Washington.  A time in the future is also fixed in
each when the tribal governments shall give place altogether to
governments territorial in character.
</p><p>The Cherokees and Creeks declined to treat with the Commission
at all for a long time, till the patience of Congress was exhausted
and in 1898 a law was enacted requiring to be done substantially
the same things in these tribes that had been agreed upon by the
others, excepting the allotment of their land in fee, which could
not be done without their consent.  Instead the Commission was
required to allot the use of the surface only.  It was provided
that any change in the provisions of this law might be effected by
agreements duly ratified by both Congress and the tribes
respectively.  Accordingly agreements were entered into during the
last winter with both these tribes substantially like those already
effected with the others, but too late to be ratified before the
adjournment of Congress.  There is every reason to believe that
they will be duly ratified at an early day.  When that is done,
there will be agreements with all the tribes for the changes
desired, in substantial uniformity in all essentials and in harmony
with the institutions and laws of the adjacent States.
</p><p>These agreements require much work still to be done in
carrying out their provisions.  These agreements require the
Commission to allot the lands of the tribes to citizen Indians
alone and make it the judges of the question who are such Indians,
subject to an appeal by aggrieved parties to the United States
courts.  They are required in so determining to strike from all
existing citizenship rolls all names in their opinion wrongfully
there, to add all names wrongfully excluded and to admit all new
applicants entitled, in their opinion, to citizenship according to
the laws and usages of the respective tribes.  This requires of
them a judicial determination on evidence offered on every name in
the whole roll of citizens in all the five tribes, about which
there is question, and on all new names of applicants.  The
impression got abroad that blood, however attenuated, without
regard to the other requirements of the laws and usages of the
tribes, entitled one to admission to citizenship.  Accordingly
crowds of applicants came from all the adjacent States, and even
from Northwestern States, for the first time into the Territory,
claiming citizenship upon some claim of Indian blood in their
veins, regardless of residence and citizenship elsewhere all their
lives.
</p><p>The Commission was compelled to pass judicially upon more than
7,500 such claims embracing in classes and families, relying on the
same facts, very

<pb n="2564"/>
many thousand more up to the close of the
last fiscal year.  In the vast majority of these cases the evidence
failed to disclose blood enough to sustain anything beyond
imagination or pretence.  Through all this maze and this labor the
Commission has completed the roll of the Seminoles and nearly so of
the Choctaws and Chickasaws, the much larger part of the Creeks,
and are beginning the like work among the Cherokees.  After this
they are required to allot these lands to such only as appear on
these rolls.  But this is to be done in a manner quite different
from that of the government on the reservations, where little more
is required besides setting off a given number of acres of land of
uniform quality to each Indian found on the agency roll in such
part of the reservation as seems best to the allotting
Commissioner.  Such a method of allotting the Indian Territory in
its present condition would be manifestly unjust.  The construction
of railroads through its length and breadth, the influx of 300,000
non-citizens building large and flourishing towns, and inaugurating
business enterprises of great importance, and the discovery of coal
deposits of great value, all these have contributed so to unsettle
relative values that the greatest injustice would be inflicted if
allotment were to be made by equality in acres.  All citizens have
an equal right in the value of their lands, and when allotted that
equality must be preserved.  Yet an allotment of fifty acres near
a railroad station, or near the town of Ardmore or Muskogee, or in
the neighborhood of a working coal mine, would be worth more than
one of two or three hundred acres situated in some parts of the
Territory.  Therefore it is required that allotment shall be made
by equality of value as near as possible, taking into consideration
the fertility of the soil, location and all other elements of
value, so that when completed each allottee will have his equal
share in value without regard to the number of acres.
</p><p>This just requirement has imposed upon the Commission the most
difficult and perplexing of all its labors.  It requires a personal
knowledge of the conditions affecting the value of every acre of
land in a Territory as large as the State of Indiana, if it is to
be of any service in such an adjustment, and an instinct to
distinguish between real and fancy values.  This has been its
endeavor in its efforts to discharge this important, but
exceedingly difficult portion of their duty.  They have completed
that work also in the Seminole country, so that now all
preliminaries to final allotment to the members of that tribe are
completed.  The final allotment there will be commenced at an early
day.  In the Creek and the Choctaw and Chickasaw tribes good
progress has been made in the same work, and its completion there
also is near at hand.  It will be undertaken in the Cherokee tribe
as soon as the necessary force now engaged elsewhere can be
liberated for that purpose.  There is much other detail connected
with this work which it would be neither interesting nor
instructive to recount here.  What has been described will enable
the conference to form an estimate of the character and progress of
the work.
</p><p>That so much time has been spent by the Commission and such
care taken in matters preliminary to final allotment has arisen
from the belief that a just and wise system of land tenure is the
basis upon which the superstructure of a prosperous State must
ultimately arise, and the conviction that any misstep here would be
attended with irreparable injury.  It has, therefore, been the
especial endeavor of the Commission that no mistake in these
preliminaries which it could avoid should jeopardize success.  It
is now carrying on the work under conditions more favorable and
encouraging than at any time heretofore.  A great change has, since
the beginning, come over the attitude toward them and their work of
the people most affected by it.  Distrust has disappeared and
opposition ceased.  In their place hearty co-operation of those
influential in the control of affairs is helping to push on the
work.  Most able and earnest men are at the head of their
respective governments, giving effective aid in securing a wise and
speedy solution of the difficult problems before them.  Within a
few weeks past the chief magistrates of two of these tribes, the
Chickasaws and Creeks, have delivered their annual messages to
their respective Legislative Councils, treating largely, and in the
most hopeful tone, of their future, and urging wise measures in
view of the new

<pb n="2565"/>
conditions confronting them.  These
messages would well become the Governors of the oldest of the
States in the propriety and ability as well as temper and style in
which they presented matters concerning the welfare of their
people.  The guidance of such men is full of promise that statehood
in the near future is sure to come to a Territory so rich in all
the elements of a healthy growth.
</p>

<trailer>PITTSFIELD, MASS.</trailer>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
