<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DouColo"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>
<TEI.2 id="DouColo">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"The Color Line"</title>
<title type="sort">the color line</title>
<author>Douglass, Frederick, 1817?-1895</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">30</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">DouColo</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475879</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"The Color Line"</title>
<title type="sort">the color line</title>
<author>Frederick Douglass</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Editor</resp>
<name>James Russell Lowell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st Edition</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<pubPlace>Boston, MA</pubPlace>
<date value="1881-06">June 1881</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>North American Review (132)</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1881-05">May 1881</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term>
<term>democracy</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>African American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995-12">December 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Monique Dull, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to basic TEI.2-conformant markup; edited TEI.2 header;
checked bibliographic information with print edition, University of
Virginia Library AP 2.N7 v. 132 1881</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">



<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
	<pb n="567"/>
<head>THE COLOR LINE.</head>

<p>Few evils are less accessible to the force of reason, or more
tenacious of life and power, than a long-standing prejudice.  It is
a moral disorder, which creates the conditions necessary to its own
existence, and fortifies itself by refusing all contradiction.  It
paints a hateful picture according to its own diseased imagination,
and distorts the features of the fancied original to suit the
portrait.  As those who believe in the visibility of ghosts can
easily see them, so it is always easy to see repulsive qualities in
those we despise and hate.
</p><p>Prejudice of race has at some time in their history afflicted
all nations.  "I am more holy than thou" is the boast of races, as
well as that of the Pharisee.  Long after the Norman invasion and
the decline of Norman power, long after the sturdy Saxon had shaken
off the dust of his humiliation and was grandly asserting his great
qualities in all directions, the descendants of the invaders
continued to regard their Saxon brothers as made of coarser clay
than themselves, and were not well pleased when one of the former
subject race came between the sun and their nobility.  Having seen
the Saxon a menial, a hostler, and a common drudge, oppressed and
dejected for centuries, it was easy to invest him with all sorts of
odious peculiarities, and to deny him all manly predicates.  Though
eight hundred years have passed away since Norman power entered
England, and the Saxon has for centuries been giving his learning,
his literature, his language, and his laws to the world more
successfully than any other people on the globe, men in that
country still boast their Norman origin and Norman perfections.
This superstition of former greatness serves to fill out the
shriveled sides of a meaningless race-pride which holds over after
its power has vanished.  With a very different lesson from the one
this paper is designed <pb n="568"/>  to impress, the great Daniel Webster
once told the people of Massachusetts (whose prejudices in the
particular instance referred to were right) that they "had
conquered the sea, and had conquered the land," but that "it
remained for them to conquer their prejudices."  At one time we are
told that the people in some of the towns of Yorkshire cherished a
prejudice so strong and violent against strangers and foreigners
that one who ventured to pass through their streets would be pelted
with stones.
</p><p>Of all the races and varieties of men which have suffered from
this feeling, the colored people of this country have endured most.
They can resort to no disguises which will enable them to escape
its deadly aim.  They carry in front the evidence which marks them
for persecution.  They stand at the extreme point of difference
from the Caucasian race, and their African origin can be instantly
recognized, though they may be several removes from the typical
African race.  They may remonstrate like Shylock &mdash; "Hath not a Jew
eyes? hath not a Jew hands, organs, dimensions, senses, affections,
passions? fed with the same food, hurt with the same weapons,
subject to the same diseases, healed by the same means, warmed and
cooled by the same summer and winter, as a Christian is?" &mdash; but such
eloquence is unavailing.  They are negroes &mdash; and that is enough, in
the eye of this unreasoning prejudice, to justify indignity and
violence.  In nearly every department of American life they are
confronted by this insidious influence.  It fills the air.  It
meets them at the workshop and factory, when they apply for work.
It meets them at the church, at the hotel, at the ballot-box, and
worst of all, it meets them in the jury-box.  Without crime or
offense against law or gospel, the colored man is the Jean Valjean
of American society.  He has escaped from the galleys, and hence
all presumptions are against him.  The workshop denies him work,
and the inn denies him shelter; the ballot-box a fair vote, and the
jury-box a fair trial.  He has ceased to be the slave of society.
He may not now be bought and sold like a beast in the market, but
he is the trammeled victim of a prejudice, well calculated to
repress his manly ambition, paralyze his energies, and make him a
dejected and spiritless man, if not a sullen enemy to society, fit
to prey upon life and property and to make trouble generally.
</p><p>When this evil spirit is judge, jury, and prosecutor, nothing
<pb n="569"/>  less than overwhelming evidence is sufficient to overcome
the force of unfavorable presumptions.
</p><p>Everything against the person with the hated color is promptly
taken for granted; while everything in his favor is received with
suspicion and doubt.
</p><p>A boy of this color is found in his bed tied, mutilated, and
bleeding, when forthwith all ordinary experience is set aside, and
he is presumed to have been guilty of the outrage upon himself;
weeks and months he is kept on trial for the offense, and every
effort is made to entangle the poor fellow in the confused meshes
of expert testimony (the least trustworthy of all evidence).  This
same spirit, which promptly assumes everything against us, just as
readily denies or explains away everything in our favor.  We are
not, as a race, even permitted to appropriate the virtues and
achievements of our individual representatives.  Manliness,
capacity, learning, laudable ambition, heroic service, by any of
our number, are easily placed to the credit of the superior race.
One drop of Teutonic blood is enough to account for all good and
great qualities occasionally coupled with a colored skin; and on
the other hand, one drop of negro blood, though in the veins of a
man of Teutonic whiteness, is enough of which to predicate all
offensive and ignoble qualities.  In presence of this spirit, if a
crime is committed, and the criminal is not positively known, a
suspicious-looking colored man is sure to have been seen in the
neighborhood.  If an unarmed colored man is shot down and dies in
his tracks, a jury, under the influence of this spirit, does not
hesitate to find the murdered man the real criminal, and the
murderer innocent.
</p><p>Now let us examine this subject a little more closely.  It is
claimed that this wonder-working prejudice &mdash; this moral magic that
can change virtue into vice, and innocence to crime; which makes
the dead man the murderer, and holds the living homicide harmless &mdash;
is a natural, instinctive, and invincible attribute of the white
race, and one that cannot be eradicated; that even evolution itself
cannot carry us beyond or above it.  Alas for this poor suffering
world (for four-fifths of mankind are colored), if this claim be
true!  In that case men are forever doomed to injustice,
oppression, hate, and strife; and the religious sentiment of the
world, with its grand idea of human brotherhood, its "peace on
earth and good-will to men," and its golden rule, must be voted a
dream, a delusion, and a snare. <pb n="570"/>
</p><p>But is this color prejudice the natural and inevitable thing
it claims to be?  If it is so, then it is utterly idle to write
against it, preach, pray, or legislate against it, or pass
constitutional amendments against it.  Nature will have her course,
and one might as well preach and pray to a horse against running,
to a fish against swimming, or to a bird against flying.
Fortunately, however, there is good ground for calling in question
this high pretension of a vulgar and wicked prepossession.
</p><p>If I could talk with all my white fellow-countrymen on this
subject, I would say to them, in the language of Scripture: "Come
and let us reason together."  Now, without being too elementary and
formal, it may be stated here that there are at least seven points
which candid men will be likely to admit, but which, if admitted,
will prove fatal to the popular thought and practice of the times.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">First.</hi>  If what we call prejudice against color be
natural, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, a part of human nature itself, it follows
that it must be co-extensive with human nature, and will and must
manifest itself whenever and wherever the two races are brought
into contact.  It would not vary with either latitude, longitude,
or altitude; but like fire and gunpowder, whenever brought
together, there would be an explosion of contempt, aversion, and
hatred.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Secondly.</hi>  If it can be shown that there is anywhere on
the globe any considerable country where the contact of the African
and Caucasian is not distinguished by this explosion of race-wrath,
there is reason to doubt that the prejudice is an ineradicable part
of human nature.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Thirdly.</hi>  If this so-called natural, instinctive
prejudice can be satisfactorily accounted for by facts and
considerations wholly apart from the color features of the
respective races, thus placing it among the things subject to human
volition and control, we may venture to deny the claim set up for
it in the name of human nature.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Fourthly.</hi>  If any considerable number of white people
have overcome this prejudice in themselves, have cast it out as an
unworthy sentiment, and have survived the operation, the fact shows
that this prejudice is not at any rate a vital part of human
nature, and may be eliminated from the race without harm.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Fifthly.</hi>  If this prejudice shall, after all, prove to
be, in its essence and in its natural manifestation, simply a
prejudice <pb n="571"/>  against condition, and not against race or color,
and that it disappears when this or that condition is absent, then
the argument drawn from the nature of the Caucasian race falls to
the ground.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Sixthly.</hi>  If prejudice of race and color is only
natural in the sense that ignorance, superstition, bigotry, and
vice are natural, then it has no better defense than they, and
should be despised and put away from human relations as an enemy to
the peace, good order, and happiness of human society.
</p><p><hi rend="italic">Seventhly.</hi>  If, still further, this averson* to the
negro arises out of the fact that he is as we see him, poor,
spiritless, ignorant, and degraded, then whatever is humane, noble,
and superior, in the mind of the superior and more fortunate race,
will desire that all arbitrary barriers against his manhood,
intelligence, and elevation shall be removed, and a fair chance in
the race of life be given him.
</p><p>The first of these propositions does not require discussion.
It commends itself to the understanding at once.  Natural qualities
are common and universal, and do not change essentially on the
mountain or in the valley.  I come therefore to the second point &mdash;
the existence of countries where this malignant prejudice, as we
know it in America, does not prevail; where character, not color,
is the passport to consideration; where the right of the black man
to be a man, and a man among men, is not questioned; where he may,
without offense, even presume to be a gentleman.  That there are
such countries in the world there is ample evidence.  Intelligent
and observing travelers, having no theory to support, men whose
testimony would be received without question in respect of any
other matter, and should not be questioned in this, tell us that
they find no color prejudice in Europe, except among Americans who
reside there.  In England and on the Continent, the colored man is
no more an object of hate than any other person.  He mingles with
the multitude unquestioned, without offense given or received.
During the two years which the writer spent abroad, though he was
much in society, and was sometimes in the company of lords and
ladies, he does not remember one word, look, or gesture that
indicated the slightest aversion to him on account of color.  His
experience was not in this respect exceptional or singular.
Messrs.  Remond, Ward, Garnet, Brown, Pennington, Crummell, and
Bruce, all of them colored, and some of them black, bear the same
testimony.  If what these gentleman say (and it can be corroborated
by <pb n="572"/>  a thousand witnesses) is true there is no prejudice
against color in England, save as it is carried there by
Americans &mdash; carried there as a moral disease from an infected
country.  It is American, not European; local, not general;
limited, not universal, and must be ascribed to artificial
conditions, and not to any fixed and universal law of nature.
</p><p>The third point is: Can this prejudice against color, as it is
called, be accounted for by circumstances outside and independent
of race or color?  If it can be thus explained, an incubus may be
removed from the breasts of both the white and the black people of
this country, as well as from that large intermediate population
which has sprung up between these alleged irreconcilable extremes.
It will help us to see that it is not necessary that the Ethiopian
shall change his skin, nor needful that the white man shall change
the essential elements of his nature, in order that mutual respect
and consideration may exist between the two races.
</p><p>Now it is easy to explain the conditions outside of race or
color from which may spring feelings akin to those which we call
prejudice.  A man without the ability or the disposition to pay a
just debt does not feel at ease in the presence of his creditor.
He does not want to meet him on the street, or in the market-place.
Such meeting makes him uncomfortable.  He would rather find fault
with the bill than pay the debt, and the creditor himself will soon
develop in the eyes of the debtor qualities not altogether to his
taste.
</p><p>Some one has well said, we may easily forgive those who injure
us, but it is hard to forgive those whom we injure.  The greatest
injury this side of death, which one human being can inflict on
another, is to enslave him, to blot out his personality, degrade
his manhood, and sink him to the condition of a beast of burden;
and just this has been done here during more than two centuries.
No other people under heaven, of whatever type or endowments, could
have been so enslaved without falling into contempt and scorn on
the part of those enslaving them.  Their slavery would itself stamp
them with odious features, and give their oppressors arguments in
favor of oppression.  Besides the long years of wrong and injury
inflicted upon the colored race in this country, and the effect of
these wrongs upon that race, morally, intellectually, and
physically, corrupting their morals, darkening their minds, and
twisting their bodies and limbs out <pb n="573"/>  of all approach to
symmetry, there has been a mountain of gold &mdash; uncounted millions of
dollars &mdash; resting upon them with crushing weight.  During all the
years of their bondage, the slave master had a direct interest in
discrediting the personality of those he held as property.  Every
man who had a thousand dollars so invested had a thousand reasons
for painting the black man as fit only for slavery.  Having made
him the companion of horses and mules, he naturally sought to
justify himself by assuming that the negro was not much better than
a mule.  The holders of twenty hundred million dollars' worth of
property in human chattels procured the means of influencing press,
pulpit, and politician, and through these instrumentalities they
belittled our virtues and magnified our vices, and have made us
odious in the eyes of the world.  Slavery had the power at one time
to make and unmake Presidents, to construe the law, dictate the
policy, set the fashion in national manners and customs, interpret
the Bible, and control the church; and, naturally enough, the old
masters set themselves up as much too high as they set the manhood
of the negro too low.  Out of the depths of slavery has come this
prejudice and this color line.  It is broad enough and black enough
to explain all the malign influences which assail the newly
emancipated millions to-day.  In reply to this argument it will
perhaps be said that the negro has no slavery now to contend with,
and that having been free during the last sixteen years, he ought
by this time to have contradicted the degrading qualities which
slavery formerly ascribed to him.  All very true as to the letter,
but utterly false as to the spirit.  Slavery is indeed gone, but
its shadow still lingers over the country and poisons more or less
the moral atmosphere of all sections of the republic.  The money
motive for assailing the negro which slavery represented is indeed
absent, but love of power and dominion, strengthened by two
centuries of irresponsible power, still remains.
</p><p>Having now shown how slavery created and sustained this
prejudice against race and color, and the powerful motive for its
creation, the other four points made against it need not be
discussed in detail and at length, but may only be referred to in
a general way.
</p><p>If what is called the instinctive aversion of the white race
for the colored, when analyzed, is seen to be the same as that
which men feel or have felt toward other objects wholly apart from
<pb n="574"/>  color; if it should be the same as that sometimes exhibited
by the haughty and rich to the humble and poor, the same as the
Brahmin feels toward the lower caste, the same as the Norman felt
toward the Saxon, the same as that cherished by the Turk against
Christians, the same as Christians have felt toward the Jews, the
same as that which murders a Christian in Wallachia, calls him a
"dog" in Constantinople, oppresses and persecutes a Jew in Berlin,
hunts down a socialist in St. Petersburg, drives a Hebrew from an
hotel at Saratoga, that scorns the Irishman in London, the same as
Catholics once felt for Protestants, the same as that which
insults, abuses, and kills the Chinaman on the Pacific slope &mdash; then
may we well enough affirm that this prejudice really has nothing
whatever to do with race or color, and that it has its motive and
mainspring in some other source with which the mere facts of color
and race have nothing to do.
</p><p>After all, some very well informed and very well meaning
people will read what I have now said, and what seems to me so just
and reasonable, and will still insist that the color of the negro
has something to do with the feeling entertained toward him; that
the white man naturally shudders at the thought of contact with one
who is black &mdash; that the impulse is one which he can neither resist
nor control.  Let us see if this conclusion is a sound one.  An
argument is unsound when it proves too little or too much, or when
it proves nothing.  If color is an offense, it is so, entirely
apart from the manhood it envelops.  There must be something in
color of itself to kindle rage and inflame hate, and render the
white man generally uncomfortable.  If the white man were really so
constituted that color were, in itself, a torment to him, this
grand old earth of ours would be no place for him.  Colored objects
confront him here at every point of the compass.  If he should
shrink and shudder every time he sees anything dark, he would have
little time for anything else.  He would require a colorless world
to live in &mdash; a world where flowers, fields, and floods should all be
of snowy whiteness; where rivers, lakes, and oceans should all be
white; where all the men, and women, and children should be white;
where all the fish of the sea, all the birds of the air, all the
"cattle upon a thousand hills," should be white; where the heavens
above and the earth beneath should be white, and where day and
night should not be divided by light and darkness, but the world
should be one eternal<pb n="575"/>  scene of light.  In such a white
world, the entrance of a black man would be hailed with joy by the
inhabitants.  Anybody or anything would be welcome that would break
the oppressive and tormenting monotony of the all-prevailing white.
</p><p>In the abstract, there is no prejudice against color.  No man
shrinks from another because he is clothed in a suit of black, nor
offended with his boots because they are black.  We are told by
those who have resided there that a white man in Africa comes to
think that ebony is about the proper color for man.  Good old
Thomas Whitson &mdash; a noble old Quaker &mdash; a man of rather odd
appearance &mdash; used to say that even he would be handsome if he could
change public opinion.
</p><p>Aside from the curious contrast to himself, the white child
feels nothing on the first sight of a colored man.  Curiosity is
the only feeling.  The office of color in the color line is a very
plain and subordinate one.  It simply advertises the objects of
oppression, insult, and persecution.  It is not the maddening
liquor, but the black letters on the sign telling the world where
it may be had.  It is not the hated Quaker, but the broad brim and
the plain coat.  It is not the hateful Cain, but the mark by which
he is known.  The color is innocent enough, but things with which
it is coupled make it hated.  Slavery, ignorance, stupidity,
servility, poverty, dependence, are undesirable conditions.  When
these shall cease to be coupled with color, there will be no color
line drawn.  It may help in this direction to observe a few of the
inconsistencies of the color-line feeling, for it is neither
uniform in its operations nor consistent in its principles.  Its
contradictions in the latter respect would be amusing if the
feeling itself were not so deserving of unqualified abhorrence.
Our Californian brothers, of Hibernian descent, hate the Chinaman,
and kill him, and when asked why they do so, their answer is that
a Chinaman is so industrious he will do all the work, and can live
by wages upon which other people would starve.  When the same
people and others are asked why they hate the colored people, the
answer is that they are indolent and wasteful, and cannot take care
of themselves.  Statesmen of the South will tell you that the negro
is too ignorant and stupid properly to exercise the elective
franchise, and yet his greatest offense is that he acts with the
only party intelligent enough in the eyes of the nation to
legislate for the country.  In one breath they tell us that the
negro is so weak in intellect, and so <pb n="576"/>  destitute of manhood,
that he is but the echo of designing white men, and yet in another
they will virtually tell you that the negro is so clear in his
moral perceptions, so firm in purpose, so steadfast in his
convictions, that he cannot be persuaded by arguments or
intimidated by threats, and that nothing but the shot-gun can
restrain him from voting for the men and measures he approves.
They shrink back in horror from contact with the negro as a man and
a gentleman, but like him very well as a barber, waiter, coachman,
or cook.  As a slave, he could ride anywhere, side by side with his
white master, but as a freeman, he must be thrust into the smoking-car.  As a slave, he could go into the first cabin; as a freeman,
he was not allowed abaft the wheel.  Formerly it was said he was
incapable of learning, and at the same time it was a crime against
the State for any man to teach him to read.  To-day he is said to
be originally and permanently inferior to the white race, and yet
wild apprehensions are expressed lest six millions of this inferior
race will somehow or other manage to rule over thirty-five millions
of the superior race.  If inconsistency can prove the hollowness of
anything, certainly the emptiness of this pretense that color has
any terrors is easily shown.  The trouble is that most men, and
especially mean men, want to have something under them.  The rich
man would have the poor man, the white would have the black, the
Irish would have the negro, and the negro must have a dog, if he
can get nothing higher in the scale of intelligence to dominate.
This feeling is one of the vanities which enlightenment will
dispel.  A good but simple-minded Abolitionist said to me that he
was not ashamed to walk with me down Broadway arm-in-arm, in open
daylight, and evidently thought he was saying something that must
be very pleasing to my self-importance, but it occurred to me, at
the moment, this man does not dream of any reason why I might be
ashamed to walk arm-in-arm with him through Broadway in open
daylight.  Riding in a stage-coach from Concord, New Hampshire, to
Vergennes, Vermont, many years ago, I found myself on very pleasant
terms with all the passengers through the night, but the morning
light came to me as it comes to the stars; I was as Dr. Beecher
says he was at the first fire he witnessed, when a bucket of cold
water was poured down his back &mdash; "the fire was not put out, but he
was."  The fact is, the higher the colored man rises in the scale
of society, the less prejudice does he meet. <pb n="577"/>
</p><p>The writer has met and mingled freely with the leading great
men of his time, &mdash; at home and abroad, in public halls and private
houses, on the platform and at the fireside, &mdash; and can remember no
instance when among such men has he been made to feel himself an
object of aversion.  Men who are really great are too great to be
small.  This was gloriously true of the late Abraham Lincoln,
William H. Seward, Salmon P. Chase, Henry Wilson, John P. Hale,
Lewis Tappan, Edmund Quincy, Joshua R. Giddings, Gerrit Smith, and
Charles Sumner, and many others among the dead.  Good taste will
not permit me now to speak of the living, except to say that the
number of those who rise superior to prejudice is great and
increasing.  Let those who wish to see what is to be the future of
America, as relates to races and race relations, attend, as I have
attended, during the administration of President Hayes, the grand
diplomatic receptions at the executive mansion, and see there, as
I have seen, in its splendid east room, the wealth, culture,
refinement, and beauty of the nation assembled, and with it the
eminent representatives of other nations, &mdash; the swarthy Turk with
his "fez," the Englishman shining with gold, the German, the
Frenchman, the Spaniard, the Japanese, the Chinaman, the Caucasian,
the Mongolian, the Sandwich Islander, and the negro, &mdash; all moving
about freely, each respecting the rights and dignity of the other,
and neither receiving nor giving offense.</p>
<lg type="citation">
<l>     "Then let us pray that come it may,</l>
<l>      As come it will for a' that,</l>
<l>      That sense and worth, o'er a' the earth,</l>
<l>      May bear the gree, and a' that;</l>

<l>     "That man to man, the world o'er,</l>
<l>      Shall brothers be, for a' that."</l>
</lg>
<trailer>FREDERICK DOUGLASS.</trailer>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
