<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DouDisc"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>
<TEI.2 id="DouDisc">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Discourse Concerning the Currencies of the British Plantations in America / by William Douglass</title>
<title type="sort">discourse concerning the currencies of the british plantations in america by william douglass</title>
<author>Brock: Douglass, William</author>
<editor>Bullock, Charles J.</editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Ronald Michener, University of Virginia</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">106</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">DouDisc</idno>
<date value="2000">2000</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2000 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475880</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>This text is part of the collection for the Leslie Brock Center for the Study of Colonial Currency.</p>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Discourse Concerning the Currencies of the British Plantations in America.  Especially with Regard to their Paper Money
More Particularly, In Relation to the Province of the Massachusetts-Bay, in New England.</title>
<title level="j">Economic Studies</title>
<title type="sort">discourse concerning the currencies of the british plantations in america especially with regard to their paper money more particularly, in relation to the province of the massachusetts bay in new england</title>
<author>William Douglass</author>
<editor>Charles J. Bullock</editor>
</titleStmt>
<extent>65 pages</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>American Economic Association</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1897-10">October, 1897</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Ivy Stacks, University of Virginia HB 1 .E42 v. 2 1897</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>The source copy of this text contains an introduction and footnotes written by Charles J. Bullock which have not been
included in this electronic version.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1740">1740</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2000-05">May, 2000</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Cynthia Filer, The Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<front id="d2">
<div1 type="introduction" id="d3">
<p>This pamphlet is probably the single most famous pamphlet on colonial
monetary history.  The American Economic Association reprinted it in
October 1897 as Vol. II. No. 5 of a series entitled &ldquo;Economic
Studies.&rdquo; The reprint includes a detailed biography of Douglass,
written by Charles Bullock.  When Andrew McFarland Davis republished the
pamphlet in &ldquo;Colonial Currency Reprints&rdquo; he included his own
commentary.  There had been some doubt about when and where the pamphlet
was originally published; Bullock accepts the view that it was first
published in London.  Davis presents convincing evidence that the Boston
edition of the pamphlet is the original, and that it was published in
the spring of 1740.

</p><p>Douglass was argumentative, opinionated, and an uncompromising
hard money advocate.  His belligerent prose, conservative views, and
debtor-creditor interpretation of colonial monetary history all run
counter to the tastes of modern historians; consequently, many view him
with disdain.  Economists have been more apt to admire his analytical
ability.  For example, Douglass was perhaps the first person to explain
the so-called &ldquo;Fisher effect.&rdquo; The
&ldquo;Fisher
effect&rdquo; &mdash; named for Irving Fisher, a 20th century economist who made it
famous &mdash; is the tendency of expected inflation to increase interest
rates.  In Douglass's Postscript, you will find a remarkable analysis of
the balance of payments, accurately anticipating what is now known as
the &ldquo;monetary approach to the balance of
payments.&rdquo;

</p><p>The hyperlinks in the text take you to errata that Douglass
provided when he wrote the Postscript to the Discourse.</p>

</div1>

<titlePage id="d4">
	<pb/>
<docTitle>
<titlePart type="main">
A DISCOURSE <lb/>
CONCERNING THE CURRENCIES <lb/>
OF THE <lb/>
BRITISH PLANTATIONS <lb/>
IN <lb/>
AMERICA.<lb/>
</titlePart>

<titlePart type="sub">
<hi rend="italic">Especially with Regard to their</hi> Paper Money<lb/>
More Particularly,<lb/>
In Relation to the Province of the<lb/>
MASSACHUSETTS-BAY,<lb/>
IN <lb/>
NEW ENGLAND. <lb/>
</titlePart>
</docTitle>

<byline>BY <docAuthor>WILLIAM DOUGLASS. M.D.</docAuthor></byline><lb/>

<docImprint>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>: Printed and sold by <name>S. Kneeland &amp; T.
Green</name>,<lb/>
over against the Prison in Queenstreet.  <date value="1740">1740.</date>
</docImprint>
</titlePage>
</front>

<body id="d5">

<div1 type="decree" id="d6">
<head>A DISCOURSE CONCERNING THE CURRENCIES OF THE BRITISH PLANTATIONS
IN AMERICA, ETC.</head>

<pb n="292"/>

<pb n="293"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">The many Schemes at present upon the Anvil in</hi> Boston,<hi rend="italic">
for emitting enormous Quantities of Paper Currencies; are the Occasion
of this Discourse.  The Writer does not vainly pretend to dictate to
Government, or prescribe to Trade; but with a sincere Regard to the
publick Good, has taken some Pains, to collect, digest, and set in a
proper Light, several Facts and Political Experiences especially
relating to Paper Currencies; which tho' plain in themselves, are not
obvious to every Body.  If any Expressions should sound harsh, they are
not to be understood as a Reflection upon this Province in general: It
was always my Opinion, That the Province of the
</hi>Massachusetts-Bay<hi rend="italic">, is by far the most vigorous and promising
Plant (with proper Cultivation) of all the British Plantations; in the
best of Countries at Times, bad Administrations, and private evil Men of
Influence have prevailed.  The Author is not a transient Person, who
from Humour or Caprice, or other Views may expose the Province; but is
by Inclination induced, and by Interest obliged to study the Good of the
Country.</hi>

</p><p>All Commerce naturally is a <hi rend="italic">Truck Trade</hi>, exchanging
Commodities which we can spare (or their Value) for Goods we are in want
of.<hi rend="italic"> Silver it self is a Merchandize</hi>,

<pb n="294"/>
and being the least variable of all others, is by general Consent made
the <hi rend="italic">Medium of Trade</hi>.  If a Country can be supposed to have no
Dealings but within it self; the Legislature or tacit Consent of the
People, may appoint or receive any Currency at Pleasure: But a trading
Country must have regard to the universal commercial Medium, which is
Silver; or cheat, and trade to a Disadvantage: It is true, that in some
Countries of Europe <hi rend="italic">Billon</hi> (a base mixture of Metals) is used
for small Change, but not as a Medium of Trade.

</p><p>Every Country or Society have their own peculiar Regulations,
which may be called their <hi rend="italic">Municipal</hi>, or By-Laws in Trade: but
the universal trading Part of the World, as one tacit Confederacy have
fallen into some<hi rend="italic"> general Rules</hi>, which by Custom of Merchants
are become as Fundamental: One of these is a <hi rend="italic">Silver Medium of
Trade</hi>, that all Contracts (Specialties excepted) are understood to
be payable in this Medium, being always of the same fixed Value, or
easily adjusted by the

<pb n="295"/>
<hi rend="italic">Par</hi>, and accidental small Differences of Exchange from one
Country to another.

</p><p>There can therefore be no other proper <hi rend="italic">Medium</hi> of Trade,
but Silver, or Bills of Exchange and Notes of Hand payable in Silver at
certain <hi rend="italic">U'sos</hi> or Periods,
which by a currant Discount are reducible to Silver ready Money, at any
Time.  The Debitor Party (I am ashamed to mention it) being the
prevailing Party in all our Depreciating-Paper-Money Colonies, do
wickedly endeavour to delude the unthinking Multitude, by perswading
them, that all Endeavours of the Governour, or Proposals and Schemes of
private Societies, to introduce a Silver Medium, or a Credit upon a
Silver Bottom, to prevent the honest and industrious Creditor from being
defrauded; are Impositions upon the Liberty and Property of the People.

</p><p>Depreciating the Value of <hi rend="italic">nummary Denominations</hi>, to
defraud the Creditors of the Publick and of private

<pb n="296"/>
Persons; by Proclamations of Sovereigns, by Recoinages, and by a late
Contrivance of a depreciating Paper-Credit-Currency; were never
practised but in notoriously bad Administrations.

</p><p>All over <hi rend="italic">Europe</hi> for many Ages preceeding the 14th
Century, the <hi rend="italic">nummary</hi> Pound, and the <hi rend="italic">Ponderal</hi> or Pound
Weight of Silver were the same: but in some following Ages in bad
Administrations the Values of nummary Denominations were gradually
reduced; as

<pb n="297"/>
in <hi rend="italic">England</hi> to 4 oz. Silver value (upon all Occasions I use the
nearest round Numbers) one third of its original Value; in
<hi rend="italic">Holland</hi> the Pound <hi rend="italic">Ulams</hi> (6 Guilders) to 2 oz. Silver
being only one sixth of its original Value.  A general Stop has been put
to those notorious publick Frauds ever since Trade began to flourish;
the civil Governments becoming more polite, found it their Interest in
Affairs of a <hi rend="italic">Medium</hi> of Trade, to be advised by the more knowing
and experienced Traders: Thus, since the Reign of <hi rend="italic">Edward</hi> VI.
<hi rend="italic">in England</hi>, the Shilling Denomination hath lost only 2 gr.
Silver.  We have two or three Instances of late in <hi rend="italic">Europe</hi>, that
have deviated from that <hi rend="italic">Maxim</hi> of a fixed Value of Silver in
Trade; these were in arbitrary Governments, under most arbitrary
Administrations.  1.<hi rend="italic">France by Recoinages</hi> from A. 1689, to the
wise Administration of <hi rend="italic">Cardinal Fluery</hi>, was obliged to defraud
the Subject, to maintain unjust Wars and Rapines upon its Neighbours,
and lessen'd the Value of nummary Denominations from a <hi rend="italic">Mark</hi> of
Silver at 27 <hi rend="italic">Livres</hi> to 80 <hi rend="italic">Livres.</hi> 2.  <hi rend="italic">The King of
Spain</hi> A. 1688 lowered his Denominations 25 <hi rend="italic">per Cent</hi>. A
heavy Piece of <hi rend="italic">Eight</hi> formerly 8 <hi rend="italic">Ryals</hi> Plate, passed
for 10 <hi rend="italic">Ryals</hi> currant. 3.  <hi rend="italic">Sweden</hi> under the
Administration of Baron <hi rend="italic">Gortz</hi>.

</p><p>In all Sovereignties in <hi rend="italic">Europe</hi> where
<hi rend="italic">Paper-Money</hi> was introduced, great Inconveniencies happened;
upon canceling this Paper Medium all those Inconveniencies did vanish.
1.  In <hi rend="italic">Sweden, Baron Gortz</hi>, by imposing


<pb n="298"/>
<hi rend="italic">Government Notes</hi> (and <hi rend="italic">Munt tokyns</hi>) reduced the People
to extreme Misery (this was one of the principal Crimes alledged against
him when he suffered capital Punishment) but these being called in, and
the <hi rend="italic">Coin</hi> settled upon the same Foundation as it was before
<hi rend="italic">Charles</hi> XIIth Accession, <hi rend="italic">Sweden</hi> flourished as
formerly.  2.  The late <hi rend="italic">Regent of France</hi>, by the Advice of Mr.
<hi rend="italic">Law</hi>, did form a Project <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1720, and by his arbitrary
Power, endeavoured to put it on Execution; to defraud State Creditors
and others, by banishing of Silver Currency, and by substituting a
<hi rend="italic">Paper Credit</hi>: the Effect was, the greatest Confusion, and
almost utter Subversion of their Trade and Business: The <hi rend="italic">Remedy</hi>
was (Mr. <hi rend="italic">Law</hi> having sneak'd off, became a <hi rend="italic">Profugus</hi>,
and at last died obscurely) after a few Months the Court of
<hi rend="italic">France</hi> were obliged to ordain, that there should be no other
legal Tender but Silver-Coin; and Commerce was flourished in
<hi rend="italic">France</hi> more than ever.  At present, under the wise
Administration of Cardinal <hi rend="italic">Fleury</hi> (who allows no Paper
Currencies, nor Re-coinages, which had the same Effect in depreciating
nummary Denominations in <hi rend="italic">France</hi>, that frequent and large
Emissions of Paper-Money

<pb n="299"/>
have in our Colonies) their Trade, bids fair to outdo the Maritime
Powers (as <hi rend="italic">Great Britain</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Holland</hi> are called) and
has a much better Effect in advancing
the Wealth and Glory of <hi rend="italic">France</hi>, than the Romantick butcherly
Schemes of Conquest over their Neighbours, under the Administrations of
<hi rend="italic">Richelieu</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Mazarine</hi> and others, in the Reigns of
<hi rend="italic">Lewis</hi> XIII and XIV.  3. In <hi rend="italic">Great Britain</hi> A. 1716, were
current four and a half Millions of Pounds Sterling in <hi rend="italic">Exchequer
Notes</hi>, being the largest Quantity current at one Time: although
they bore about half of legal Interest, and not equal to one third of
the concomitant national Silver Currency; they laboured much in
Circulation, and the Government to prevent their being depreciated, was
obliged to give considerable <hi rend="italic">Premiums</hi> to the <hi rend="italic">Bank</hi> for
cancelling some of them, and circulating the remainder.

</p><p>It is not easily to be accounted for, how <hi rend="italic">England,
France</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Holland</hi>, have tacitly allowed their several
<hi rend="italic">American Colonies</hi>; by <hi rend="italic">Laws</hi> of their several Provinces,
by <hi rend="italic">Chancerings</hi> in their Courts of Judicature, and by
<hi rend="italic">Custom</hi>; to depreciate from Time to Time, the Value of their
original Denominations, to defraud their Principals and Creditors in
<hi rend="italic">Europe</hi>.  The <hi rend="italic">British Plantations</hi> have not only varied,
from Sterling, but have also very much varied from one another; to the
great Confusion of Business, and Damage of the Merchant.  This

<pb n="300"/>
will appear plain by inserting at one View the State of the Currencies
in the several British Plantations; whereof some are per
<hi rend="italic">Exchange</hi>, some in <hi rend="italic">Spanish Silver</hi> Coin, and some in
<hi rend="italic">Paper Money</hi> called Colony or Province Bills of publick Credit.

<pb n="301"/>
</p><p>Originally and for some Years following in all the<hi rend="italic"> English
American Colonies</hi>, 5<hi rend="italic">s</hi>. Denomination was equal to an
English Crown Sterl. after some Time <hi rend="italic">Pieces of Eight</hi>, being the
general Currency of all foreign American Colonies, became also their
Currency; and they remitted or gave Credit to the Merchants at Home (by
Home is meant <hi rend="italic">Great Britain</hi>) a Piece of Eight (value 4 s. 6d.
Sterl.) For a Crown or 5 s. Sterl. <hi rend="italic">this was a Fraud of 11 per
Cent</hi>.  In sundry of our Colonies were enacted Laws against passing
of light Pieces of Eight; these Laws not being put in Execution,<hi rend="italic">
heavy and light Pieces of Eight passed promiscuously</hi>; and as it
always happens, a bad Currency drove away the good Currency; heavy
Pieces of Eight were ship'd off.  This current Money growing daily
lighter, a Difference was made between heavy Money which became
Merchandize, and light Money in which they paid their Debts gradually
from 10, 15, 20, to 25 per Cent. as at present in <hi rend="italic">Jamaica: this was
another and continued Course of cheating their Creditors and Employers
at Home</hi>.  From a Complaint of Merchants and others dealing to the
Plantations; Q. <hi rend="italic">Anne</hi> by Proclamation, and the Parliament of
Great Britain, afterwards by the <hi rend="italic">Proclamation Act</hi>, ordered,
that after <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1709, <hi rend="italic">A heavy Piece of Eight and other Pieces
in Proportion to


<pb n="302"/>
their Weight, in all our Colonies should pass not exceeding 6 s. Denomination</hi>.
This Act continues to be observed in none of our
Colonies, excepting in <hi rend="italic">Barbadoes</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Bermudas</hi>.
<hi rend="italic">Virginia</hi> Currency was formerly, and continues still better than
what the Act directs.

</p><p>In <hi rend="italic">NEWFOUNDLAND</hi>, all large Sums are transacted in<hi rend="italic">
Sterling Bills of Exchange;</hi> small Dealings are in <hi rend="italic">English
Coin</hi> Sterling Value, and in<hi rend="italic"> Pieces of Eight</hi> at 4
<hi rend="italic">s</hi>. 6 <hi rend="italic">d</hi>. being the Sterling Value.

</p><p>In <hi rend="italic">NOVA SCOTIA</hi>; The <hi rend="italic">Sterling Bills of Exchange</hi>
on the pay of the Troops, Garrison, and Train, Supply there with what they may have occasion
for from <hi rend="italic">New England</hi>: Small Dealings are in <hi rend="italic">New England
publick Bills, and in French Coin</hi> from Cape <hi rend="italic">Breton</hi>; one
<hi rend="italic">Livre</hi> equal to 4s. New England Currency: At <hi rend="italic">Canso</hi> Fish
and Oil are purchased by <hi rend="italic">Bills of Exchange New England</hi>money upon <hi rend="italic">Boston</hi>.

</p><p>In the four Colonies of <hi rend="italic">New England</hi>, viz.<hi rend="italic"> New
Hampshire, Massachusetts Bay, Rhode Island</hi> and
<hi rend="italic">Connecticut</hi>, their Currency being Paper, is promiscuously the
same.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">NEW HAMPSHIRE</hi> (too diminutive for a separate Province,
of small Trade and Credit) their <hi rend="italic">Publick Bills are so much
counterfeited</hi> they scarce obtain a Currency; hence it is (the
Governour's Instruction is also a
Bar)

<pb n="303"/>
that at present, their outstanding Bills of publick Credit, some on
Funds of Taxes, some on Loan, do not exceed &#163;12,000, gradually to
be cancelled by <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 1742.  Their ordinary charge of
Government is about &#163;1500 <hi rend="italic">New England</hi> Currency per Annum.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">MASSACHUSETTS-BAY:</hi> This being more especially the scene
of our Discourse, we shall be more particular.  At the first settling of
the<hi rend="italic"> New England</hi>

<pb n="304"/>
Colonies; their Medium was Sterling Coin at Sterling Value, and Barter;
some Part of their Taxes was paid in Provisions and other Produce,
called <hi rend="italic">Stock in the Treasury</hi>.  When they got into Trade a heavy
piece of Eight passed at 5 <hi rend="italic">s. A.</hi> 1652, <hi rend="italic">They proceeded to
coin Silver Shillings, six Pences, and three Pences, at the Rate of 6s.
to a heavy Piece of Eight;</hi> Silver continued current at this Rate by
sundry subsequent Acts of Assembly till A. 1705, by a Resolve of the
General court Silver was to pass at 7<hi rend="italic">s. per Oz</hi>.  <hi rend="italic">A</hi>.
1706 the Courts of Judicature chancered Silver to 8<hi rend="italic">s. per Oz</hi>.
in satisfying of Debts, being nearly after the Rate of 6<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> a
light Piece of Eight as then current.  At this Rate Silver and Province
Bills continued upon <hi rend="italic">Par</hi> until <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1714, the Assembly
or Legislature fell into the Error of making from Time to Time large
superfluous Sums of <hi rend="italic">Paper Money upon Loans</hi>, and the Emissions
for Charges of Government not cancellable for many Years, so that these
<hi rend="italic">Publick Bills have been continually depreciating for these last 26
Years, and are now arrived to 29 s. per Oz. Silver.</hi></p>

<pb n="305"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">Massachusetts-Bay was the Leader of Paper Currencies in our
Colonies. </hi> Their first Emission was of &#163;40,000 <hi rend="italic">A.</hi>
1690 &amp; 1691, to pay off the publick Debts incurr'd by that
expensive, tho' unsuccessful,
Expedition against <hi rend="italic">Canada</hi>; of this Sum &#163;10,000 was
cancelled and burnt in <hi rend="italic">October A.</hi> 1691: In the following Years
no more new Emissions, but some Re-emissions of the remainder, and that
only for the necessary Charges of Government, called in by Rates or
Taxes within the year; the last Remission of these Bills was <hi rend="italic">A.</hi>
1701, of &#163;9,000 Bills all this Period continued at the Rate of
6<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> a heavy Piece of Eight, and were called <hi rend="italic">Old Charter
Bills</hi>.  <hi rend="italic">A.</hi>1702 began new Emissions of Province Bills; but,
as it ought to be in all wise Administrations, cancelled by Taxes of the
same and next following Year, until <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1704, the Rates for
calling them in, were in Part postponed two Years; they began
<hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1707 to postpone them in Part for three Years; <hi rend="italic">A.</hi>
1709 for 4 Years; <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1710 for 5 Years; <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1711 for 6
Years; <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1715 for 7 Years; <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1721 for 12 Years;
<hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1722 for 13 Years: <hi rend="italic">Thus unnaturally instead of providing
for Posterity, they proceeded to involve them in Debt</hi>.  This long
publick Credit and the enormous publick Loans, have depreciated our
Province Bills to the small Value they bear at present; the Issues and
cancellings of their Bills being for a long Series of years too tedious
to be particularly and minutely inserted.

</p><p>The Province of the <hi rend="italic">Massachusetts-Bay</hi> besides the

<pb n="306"/>
Emission &amp; Re-emissions of the &#163;40,000 old Charter Bills, have
since <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1702 emitted and re-emitted Bills of publick Credit,
&#163;1,132,500 upon Fund of <hi rend="italic">Taxes</hi>, and &#163;310,000 upon
<hi rend="italic">Loans</hi>, being in all near one and a half Million; whereof about
&#163;230,000 still outstanding, and if publick Faith be better kept
will be gradually cancelled by <hi rend="italic">A.</hi>1742.  The ordinary Charges of
Government may be about &#163;40,000 <hi rend="italic">New England</hi> Currency per
Ann.<hi rend="italic"> Exchange with Great Britain 450 per Cent. Advance</hi>, or five
and an half <hi rend="italic">New England</hi> for one Sterl.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">RHODE-ISLAND</hi>, their first Emissions were <hi rend="italic">A</hi>.

<pb n="307"/>
1710, towards paying more readily their Quota of Charges on the
Expedition against <hi rend="italic">Port Royal </hi>(now <hi rend="italic">Annapolis Royal</hi>) in
<hi rend="italic">Nova Scotia</hi>, and have emitted from Time to Time, in all
&#163;399,300 whereof only &#163;19,300 upon Funds of <hi rend="italic">Taxes</hi> for
Government Charges, and &#163;360,000 upon <hi rend="italic">Loans</hi>, whereof there
is at present outstanding (all upon Loans) &#163;330,000 circiter;
which, if their publick Faith should chance to be kept in Time coming,
will not be finished cancelling until <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1759.  The Interest of
those publick Loans defreys the Charges of Government, and of their Towns.

</p><p>I shall embrace this Opportunity of exemplifying the Iniquity of
Colony publick Bills of Credit by the Instance of <hi rend="italic">Rhode-Island</hi>,
a small Colony containing about 18,000 Souls, under an old Charter very
lax and general; they admit of no Instructions from the <hi rend="italic">King</hi>,
Council, or Board of Trade and Plantations; the <hi rend="italic">King</hi> having no
Representative or <hi rend="italic">Commissioned Governour</hi> in their Legislature.
This handful of People have lately made a <hi rend="italic">very profitable Branch of
Trade and Commerce by negociating their own Paper Money in various
Shapes;</hi> their Money being Loans of Paper Credit called Bills, from
their Government to private Persons upon Lands Security; to be repaid
not in the same real Value, but in the same depreciating fallacious
Denominations.

</p><p>1.  Their first Loan was <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1715 for 10 Years, but have
by subsequent Acts postponed and prolonged the Payments, so that the
last Payment was <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1738, thus <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1715 Exchange was at
65 <hi rend="italic">per Cent</hi>. with <hi rend="italic">England</hi>, <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1738 Exchange
was at 400 <hi rend="italic">per Cent</hi>. Advance; that

<pb n="308"/>
is for &#163;100 Sterl. Value received, they pay only after the Rate of
&#163;33 Sterl.  Suppose further, that the same Person upon the same
Land Security, borrows again of the new Emission <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1738, this
&#163;33 Sterl. Value; and, as formerly by repeated large Emissions,
Exchange becomes as at present in <hi rend="italic">North-Carolina</hi>10 for 1 Sterl.
by <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1758 the period of this Loan,<hi rend="italic"> the original &#163;100
Sterl. Value will be redeemed with &#163;16 Sterl. Value</hi>.  And if
this Paper Money Loan Trade, could be supposed to continue, the Land
Security would gradually vanish, <hi rend="italic">the Land redeem'd and the Debt paid
with nothing. </hi>

</p><p>2.  They who take up this Loan Money are called <hi rend="italic">Sharers</hi>;
and for the first ten Years pay into the Treasury 5 <hi rend="italic">per Cent</hi>.
per Annum Interest; and for the other ten Years pay 10 <hi rend="italic">per
Cent</hi>. per Annum of the Principal, without Interest.  The
<hi rend="italic">Sharers</hi> let out this Money, in their own &amp; neighbouring
Colonies at 10 <hi rend="italic">per Cent</hi>. for the said twenty Years (some let it
at a higher Interest) is at the Expiration of the twenty years &#163;300
for every &#163;100 Loan, Principal and simple Interest; for which only
&#163;150 is paid into the Colony Treasury, &amp; &#163;150 is clear
Gain: <hi rend="italic">So that in this Shape for every &#163;100,000 Emission, their
People in the space of twenty Years, have after the Rate of
&#163;150,000 clear Profits. </hi>

</p><p>3.  In another Shape; upon a new Emission, Interest is made with
the <hi rend="italic">Managers</hi>, to obtain Shares in the Loan: the Sharers
immediately sell (or may sell) their <hi rend="italic">Privilege</hi>, as it is
called, for <hi rend="italic">ready Money Praemium</hi>; at the Emission <hi rend="italic">A</hi>.
1738 the Praemium was 35 <hi rend="italic">per Cent</hi>:

<pb n="309"/>
that is, <hi rend="italic">the Emission of &#163;100,000 does immediately produce
after the Rate of &#163;35,000 ready Money profit</hi>.

</p><p>4.  <hi rend="italic">Rhode-Island</hi> purchases from their neighbouring large
Province of the <hi rend="italic">Massachusetts-Bay</hi>, all Sorts of British and
Foreign Goods with this Paper Manufacture which costs nothing, which
enables them to rival us in Trade, particularly in that valuable Branch
of it to the West India Islands, and to which by some unaccountable
Infatuation we give a Currency; while at the same Time our Merchants
cannot make Returns by any Colony Paper Money, for these Goods; it is
true, sometimes they bring us Molasses from the Sugar Islands.  We have
a late good Law against the Currency of such Bills, but not being put in
Execution, is of no Effect.  <hi rend="italic">The only Reason that can be assigned
for giving the Rhode-Island Bills a Currency</hi>, is, that they are
received in all Payments by Consent: The same Reason may hold good for
passing of any Bills, even the &#163;500,000 lately proposed without
Fund or Period; and of counterfeit Bills, as in Fact some Bills of
<hi rend="italic">Connecticut</hi> of small Denominations, tho' known to be
Counterfeit, have a currency.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">CONNECTICUTT</hi>, a Charter Colony of industrious
Husbandmen, having, with much Prudence emitted only small Quantities of
Bills; Silver would have continued with them at 8 s. Per Oz. as it did
in <hi rend="italic">New York</hi> their neighbouring Government westward, if their
People had not given a Currency to the publick Bills of their Brethren,
in the neighbouring Colonies of <hi rend="italic">New England. Connecticut</hi>
emitted Bills only for the present necessary

<pb n="310"/>
Charges of Government upon Funds of <hi rend="italic">Taxes</hi>, until <hi rend="italic">A.</hi>
1733, having granted a <hi rend="italic">Charter</hi> for Trade and Commerce to a
Society in <hi rend="italic">New-London</hi>, this Society manufactured some Bills of
their own, but their Currency being soon at a Stand; the Government were
obliged in Justice to the Possessors, to emit &#163;50,000 upon <hi rend="italic">Loan
</hi>to enable those concerned in the Society to pay off their Society
Bills in Colony Bills; their Charter was vacated, and a wholsome Law
enacted, <hi rend="italic">That for any single Person, or Society of Persons to emit
and pass Bills for Commerce or in imitation of Colony Bills, Penalty
should be as in Case of Forgery, or of counterfeiting Colony Bills.</hi>
Their first Emission of Colony Bills was in <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1709, and may
have emitted in all &#163;155,000 whereof only the above &#163;50,000
upon Loan. There are at present outstanding about &#163;60,000 which
will be gradually cancelled by <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1742, if the present good
Assistants (Council) continue to be annually elected.  They have at
Times been guilty of emitting small Sums for the present Supply of
Government (by oversight and not with any sinister Design) without
annexing a Fund or Period; but have soon after been cancelled by Taxes.
Their ordinary charge of Government does not exceed &#163;3,000 <hi rend="italic">New
England</hi> Currency per Annum.</p>

<pb n="311"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">N.B.</hi> This promiscuous Currency in the four Governments
of<hi rend="italic"> New England</hi>, that is, one Colony giving a Currency to the
enormous Paper Credit Emissions of one of the other Colonies, has the
same Effect as if that Colony did emit Bills of its own: thus <hi rend="italic">the
King's Instructions to the commissioned Governments are evaded</hi>, by
the popular Charter Governments, rendring them of no Effect, having as
it were no Dependance on the Crown.<hi rend="italic"> A Parliamentary Regulation is
the only adequate Remedy.</hi>

</p><p><hi rend="italic">NEW-YORK</hi> chancered Proclamation Money to 8 s. per Oz. of
Silver, at the same Time and for the same Reasons, as has been said of
<hi rend="italic">Massachusetts-Bay</hi> Government: <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1709 towards the
charge of an intended Expedition against <hi rend="italic">Canada</hi> (upon this same
Occasion, began the first Paper Money Emissions of <hi rend="italic">New Jerseys</hi>
&amp; <hi rend="italic">Connecticut</hi>) they issued &#163;13,000 publick Bills of
Credit bearing Interest: <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1710 the Interest was taken off
upon pretence, that it occasion'd them to be hoarded up as Bonds, and
did frustrate their Currency; and &#163;10,000 more Bills without
Interest were issued.  All these Bills being small Sums and faithfully
paid off &amp; sunk in Taxes, <hi rend="italic">did not affect Exchange with England.</hi>

</p><p><hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1714.  By <hi rend="italic">collusion</hi> of the Governour,
Council and Representatives, a large Sum of &#163;27,680 in Bills, was

<pb n="312"/>
issued, to pay off Government Debts, whereoff some Part consisted of
<hi rend="italic">their own ill founded Claims</hi>; gradually to be cancelled by
<hi rend="italic">Excise</hi> on Liquors to <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1734: these were issued with
the <hi rend="italic">Royal</hi> Assent. . . <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1717 for paying of Government
Charges &amp; Debts were issued &#163;16,607 without waiting for the
<hi rend="italic">Royal</hi> Approbation, gradually to be cancelled by a <hi rend="italic">Duty
</hi>upon Wines and Rum for 17 Years and <hi rend="italic">Excise</hi> continued from
<hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1734 to <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1739: this Emission was connived at by
the <hi rend="italic">Boards</hi> of Council, Trade and Plantations at Home; lest many
Persons who had <hi rend="italic">bona fide</hi> received them for valuable
Considerations, might suffer by their being suppressed.  Which
Indulgence this Government have abused, by never waiting for the Royal
Assent in their future Emissions.

</p><p>In the intermediate Years were some small Emissions for Charges
of Government, and regularly cancelled. . . <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1734 issued
&#163;12,000 in Bills for <hi rend="italic">Fortifications</hi> to be gradually sunk
before <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1746 by <hi rend="italic">Imposts</hi> . . . <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1738
issued &#163;48,300 Bills, whereof &#163;40,000 upon Loan; all to be
sunk and paid in by <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1750: this rais'd Exchange to 70 <hi rend="italic">per
Cent</hi>. and Silver to 9 s. 3 d. per Oz.  <hi rend="italic">The Lieut. Governour to
obtain of the People a Governour's Allowance consented to humour them in
this Emission.</hi>

</p><p><hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1739, the Funds being otherways applied, it was found
that <hi rend="italic">contrary to publick Faith</hi>, &#163;15,000 of the Emissions
<hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1714 &amp; 1717 were still current, and fifteen Years more
upon <hi rend="italic">Excise</hi> were enacted to cancel them.  So that now there is
about &#163;70,000 in Bills of <hi rend="italic">New-York</hi> current.</p>

<pb n="313"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">NEW JERSIES</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> A.</hi> 1709, issued &#163;3,000 publick
Bills of Credit upon the intended Expedition against <hi rend="italic">Canada</hi>;
and <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1711 upon another intended <hi rend="italic">Canada</hi> Expedition
&#163;5,000 more Bills were emitted, to be cancelled gradually before
<hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1713; but were by Acts of Assembly <hi rend="italic">postponed</hi>, &amp;
many bills of both Emissions were currant <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1723.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1724 emitted &#163;40,000 in Bills whereof some small
Part was to cancel the old outstanding Bills, and the rest upon Loan, to
be paid in gradually in twelve Years.  This being <hi rend="italic">too large an
Emission</hi> for a small Colony, their Bills became of less Value than
those of <hi rend="italic">New-York</hi>; but being yearly <hi rend="italic">in good Faith</hi>,
sunk, they became equal, and after some years 2 s. in the Pound better
than <hi rend="italic">New-York</hi> Bills.  This is a Demonstration, that the Quantity of

<pb n="314"/>
Paper Money increasing or faithfully decreasing, sinks or raises the
Value of it. . . <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1733, was issued &#163;20,000 more upon
Loan to be gradually paid in sixteen Years: this Emission <hi rend="italic">fell</hi>
their Bills to near Par with <hi rend="italic">New-York</hi>. . . <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1734,
the first Loan of <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1724, being near sunk, the Assembly
enacted a &#163;40,000 Loan, but was not issued till <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1736,
having then obtain'd the <hi rend="italic">Royal</hi> Approbation, and <hi rend="italic">passed
scarce at Par with New-York</hi>; but upon the <hi rend="italic">New-York</hi>
Emission of &#163;48,300 <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1738, the <hi rend="italic">Jersey</hi> Bills
were 6 d. in the Pound better than <hi rend="italic">New-York</hi> Bills, and 1 s. in
the Pound better than those of <hi rend="italic">Pensylvania</hi>.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Jersey</hi> Bills keep their Credit better than those of
<hi rend="italic">Pensylvania</hi> and <hi rend="italic">New-York</hi> for these two Reasons, 1.
<hi rend="italic">New-York</hi> bills not being current in <hi rend="italic">Pensylvania</hi>, and
<hi rend="italic">Pensylvania</hi> Bills not being current in <hi rend="italic">New-York</hi>; but
<hi rend="italic">Jersey</hi> Bills current in both, all Payments between
<hi rend="italic">New-York</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Pensylvania</hi> are made in <hi rend="italic">Jersey</hi>
Bills.  2. In the <hi rend="italic">Jerseys</hi> failure of the Loan Payments, at the
Day appointed; is equivalent to
Judgment, and thereafter only 30 Days Redemption of Mortgages is allowed.

</p><p>The 5 <hi rend="italic">per Cent</hi>. Interest of publick Loans defrays all
<hi rend="italic">Charges of Government</hi>.  In the <hi rend="italic">Jerseys</hi> at present
about &#163;60,000 in publick Bills current all upon Loan.

</p><p>In the two Governments of <hi rend="italic">PENSYLVANIA</hi> their

<pb n="315"/>
Currency continued Silver Proclamation Value, until <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1723:
The three Upper counties (strictly called <hi rend="italic">Pensylvania</hi>) emitted
upon Loan &#163;15,000 in Bills, and <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1724 emitted
&#163;30,000 more; but <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1726 finding that in strictness of
the two preceeding Acts &#163;6100 part of the Capital of &#163;45,000
was sunk, the Encouragers of Paper Money procured an Act for re-emitting
what should be annually paid in of the remainder by the Borrowers; and
<hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1729 emitted &#163;30,000 which have generally been
continued out by <hi rend="italic">re-emitting Acts</hi> from Time to Time.
<hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1739 they made an Addition of about &#163;11,100 upon Loan
on the same Terms; so that at present they have &#163;80,000 all upon
Loan.  Exchange with <hi rend="italic">London 75 per Cent</hi>. before Emissions of
Paper Money it was only 33 <hi rend="italic">per Cent</hi>.

</p><p>The three Lower Counties have also Paper Currency in small
Quantities, and upon the same footing.

</p><p>In MARYLAND Silver continued at Proclamation Value until
<hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1734, with a considerable Concomitant <hi rend="italic">Truck Trade</hi>
as a <hi rend="italic">Medium</hi>, viz. <hi rend="italic">Tobacco</hi>; they then emitted
&#163;90,000 in Bills, which tho' payable to the Possessors in Sterling
well secured, the Sum being too large, and the Periods too long, viz.
three partial Payments of 15 Years Periods each; <hi rend="italic">Exchange
immediately rose from </hi>33 <hi rend="italic">to</hi> 100 <hi rend="italic">per Cent</hi>. </p>

<pb n="316"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">VIRGINIA</hi> has the same considerable <hi rend="italic">Truck Trade
Medium</hi>, viz. <hi rend="italic">Tobacco</hi>; and with regard to Silver Currency
have kept their Integrity better than the other Colonies.  It is true,
<hi rend="italic">Lord Culpeper</hi> their Governour, about <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1680, by an
arbitrary Proceeding in the Quality of the King's Representative, did,
by virtue of his own Proclamation, alter the Value of their Silver Coin
for his own Profit, to defraud an English Regiment then paid off and
disbanded, (this Regiment was sent from <hi rend="italic">England</hi> to quell an
Insurrection or mutiny in <hi rend="italic">Virginia</hi> under <hi rend="italic">Bacon</hi>) but
soon finding, that it occasioned much Confusion in Business, and did
particularly affect his own Perquisites; he reduced it again to the
former Standard.  Silver a few Years ago was 6 s. A Crown British, or 6
s. 3 d. per Oz. Silver, at present it is 6 s. 8 d. per Oz. of Silver,
and &#163;5 per Oz. Gold; <hi rend="italic">is</hi> 25 <hi rend="italic">per Cent. worse than
Sterling</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">NORTH CAROLINA</hi>, an inconsiderable Colony scarce capable
of any Fund for Paper Emissions; have notwithstanding &#163;40,000 upon
<hi rend="italic">Loan</hi>, and &#163;12,500 upon Funds of <hi rend="italic">Taxes</hi>.  At
present Exchange is settled

<pb n="317"/>
by their Legislature at 10 <hi rend="italic">North
Carolina for 1 Sterling</hi>.

</p><p>In <hi rend="italic">SOUTH CAROLINA</hi> their first Emission of publick Paper
Credit was <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1702, towards the Charges of an Expedition
against <hi rend="italic">St. Augustine</hi>.  Their Legislature have been most
<hi rend="italic">notoriously guilty of breach of publick Faith</hi> in not cancelling
their Bills.  Besides the Emissions for ordinary Charges of Government,
and their Expeditions against the <hi rend="italic">North Carolina Indians A</hi>.
1711, and against the <hi rend="italic">Southern Indians A</hi>. 1715, they have large
Sums upon <hi rend="italic">Loans</hi>.  They may have at present outstanding about
&#163;250,000 in Province Bills (whereof above &#163;100,000 without
Fund or Period) besides private Notes of substantial Merchants
negociated, payable upon Demand in Province Bills; they have also a
valuable <hi rend="italic">Truck</hi>, viz. <hi rend="italic">Rice</hi>.  Their present Exchange
with <hi rend="italic">London</hi> as settled by their Legislature to

<pb n="318"/>
ascertain the Value of Debts contracted, <hi rend="italic">is 8 South Carolina for 1
Sterling</hi>.

</p><p>In the new Colony of <hi rend="italic">GEORGIA</hi>, their Currency are the
Trustees <hi rend="italic">sola Bills Sterling:</hi> The Funds are the Allowances by
Parliament, and private Subscriptions to carry on the settlement.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">PROVIDENCE</hi> including the rest of the <hi rend="italic">Bahama</hi>
Islands is scarce reckoned a Colony.

</p><p>In <hi rend="italic">BERMUDAS</hi> a Colony of Sea Carriers; their <hi rend="italic">Currency
continues Proclamation</hi> Value.</p>

<pb n="319"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">BARBADOES:</hi> Their Currency is Proclamation Value, by weight
6<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> 10<hi rend="italic">d. farthing</hi> per Oz. Silver.  By the Advice of
Mr. <hi rend="italic">W.</hi> from <hi rend="italic">New England</hi>, they made the Experiment of a
Paper Currency, and emitted &#163;16,000 upon the Negroe <hi rend="italic">Tax</hi>
Fund, and soon after &#163;80,000 more upon <hi rend="italic">Loan</hi>; these Bills
immediately fell 40 <hi rend="italic">per Cent</hi>. below Silver, and upon Complaint
were directly suppressed by an Order from<hi rend="italic"> England; and some of the
Possessors who gave them a Currency</hi> have Quantities of them to show
as a Monument of this Folly, and of Paper Money becoming waste Paper.

</p><p>Here as in all our Sugar Island, <hi rend="italic">Sugar</hi> according to its
Quality at the Market Price, serves as a <hi rend="italic">Truck Medium</hi> to pay
Debts.<hi rend="italic"> The Par of Exchange is 33 per Cent</hi>. but generally lower
and in favour of <hi rend="italic">Barbadoes</hi>.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">CARRIBEE LEEWARD ISLANDS</hi> of<hi rend="italic"> Antegoe, Newis, St.
Christophers, Montserrat, &amp; the Virgins</hi>, have depreciated from
Silver Proclamation Value to 8 <hi rend="italic">s</hi>. per Oz. in the same Manner as
has been said of <hi rend="italic">Massachusetts-Bay</hi>; but never proceeded to that
Fraud, Paper Money: light Pieces of eight are current by Tale.
<hi rend="italic">Exchange 50 per Cent. Advance</hi>. </p>

<pb n="320"/>
<p>In <hi rend="italic">JAMAICA</hi> formerly a heavy Piece of Eight current at
5<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> but light Money taking Place as a Currency; the heavy Money
was ship'd off in course of Time at 10, 15, 20 &amp; 25 <hi rend="italic">per
Cent</hi>. as at present, Difference.  At this time a light Piece of
eight passes at 5<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> a heavy Piece of Eight at 6<hi rend="italic">s.</hi>
3<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> and Silver at 7<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> 2<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> per Oz.<hi rend="italic"> The Par
of Exchange with London is about 36 per Cent. difference</hi>, but
generally higher and in favour of <hi rend="italic">London</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">Thus we see, that particularly in our Paper Money Colonies,
the Currencies have incredibly depreciated from Sterling, and from one
another.  Exchange with Great Britain being at this Time</hi> (Febr.
1739)<hi rend="italic"> in New England </hi>450 <hi rend="italic">per Cent. in New-York, Jerseys,
&amp; Pennsylvania</hi> 70 <hi rend="italic">to </hi>75 <hi rend="italic">per Cent. in</hi> Maryland
100 <hi rend="italic">per Cent. in North
Carolina</hi> 900 <hi rend="italic">per Cent. in
South Carolina</hi> 700 <hi rend="italic">per Cent. worse than Sterling</hi>.

</p><p>To make a Bill or Note bearing no Interest, and not payable till
after a dozen or score of Years, a legal
Tender (under the highest
Penalties as in <hi rend="italic">New-York</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Jerseys</hi>) in Payment of
Debts, is the highest of <hi rend="italic">despotick</hi> and arbitrary Government:
France never made their State Bills a common Tender.  Our Paper Money
Colonies have carried the Iniquity still further; the Popular or
<hi rend="italic">Democratick</hi> Part of the Constitution are generally in Debt, and
by their too great Weight or Influence in Elections, have made a
depreciating Currency, a Tender for Contracts done may Years before;
that is,<hi rend="italic"> they impose upon the Creditor side in private
Contracts</hi>, which the most despotick Powers never assumed.  An
Instance of a still further arbitrary Proceeding in relation

<pb n="321"/>
to Paper Money was an Act of Assembly in <hi rend="italic">New Jerseys A</hi>. 1723,
whereby <hi rend="italic">Executions for Debt were stayed until Paper Money should be
issued</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Mystery of the infatuation of our Colonies running
Headlong into a depreciating Paper Currency may be this</hi>: In many of
our Plantations of late Years, by bad Management and Extravagancies, the
Majority of the People are become <hi rend="italic">Debtors</hi>, hence their Elected
Representation in the Legislature have a great Chance to be generally of
the Debtors Side: or in other Words, the <hi rend="italic">Representatives</hi> being
generally Freeholders, and many of them <hi rend="italic">much in Debt</hi>; by large
Emissions their Lands rise in Denomination Value while their Debts
become really less, and the Creditor is defrauded in Part of his Debt.
Thus our Colonies have defrauded more in a few years than bad
Administrations in <hi rend="italic">Europe</hi> have formerly done in some Centuries.
The great Damage done to the generous Merchants at Home, and to the
industrious fair Dealers amongst our selves; call aloud, for some speedy
and effectual Relief from the supreme Legislature of the <hi rend="italic">Parliament
of Great Britain</hi>.

</p><p>There is an Argument, which tho' not much attended to here, may
be of some Weight at Home, viz.<hi rend="italic"> That the Government at Home ought to
connive at Paper Money in the Colonies</hi>, because by indulging them
in this Error, all the Silver which they acquire from Time to Time is
sent to <hi rend="italic">Great Britain</hi>; and by the <hi rend="italic">chimaera</hi> of a
fallacious Cash, Extravagancies are encouraged in favour of a great


<pb n="322"/>
Consumption of British Goods:<hi rend="italic"> This ought to be an Argument with us
against that Paper Currency</hi>, which tends to turn the Ballance of
Trade so much against us.  It is true, That <hi rend="italic">Great Britain</hi>
naturally ought to reap some Profit by its Plantation Improvements; but
a good Farmer improves his Lands not
by working them out of Heart (as the Term is) but by manuring them, that
they may yield the better Crops; besides, what the British Merchants
lose in their Returns by the Colony Bills depreciating, and by the
Bankruptcy of their Factors and Dealers here; is much more then what
<hi rend="italic">Great Britain</hi> gets, on the abovesaid Accounts.

</p><p>In the Sequel of this Discourse, I shall 1, Enumerate the
Inconveniencies and bad Effects of our large Emissions of Paper Money.
2. Endeavour to remove the Prejudices which some designing Men have
infused into the Minds of the Populace in favour of Bills of Credit.  3.
Consider several Projections or Schemes to rectify our Currency and
present Circumstances, or to prevent their growing worse.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Mischiefs arising from a large Paper Currency are,</hi>

</p><p>I.  With regard to <hi rend="italic">the particular and immediate Sufferers
thereby </hi>.

</p><p>1.  <hi rend="italic">The Labourers and Trades-men</hi>, who is all Countries,
are the Heads which feed the Belly
of the Common Wealth, and therefore<hi rend="italic"> deserve our chief Regard</hi>.
How much they have suffered and continue to suffer is obvious: For
Instance, a Carpenter when Silver was at 8<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> per Oz. his Wages
were 5<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> a Day all Cash.  The

<pb n="323"/>
Town House <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1712 was built at this Rate; whereas at present
<hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1739. from the bad influence of Paper Money Silver being
29<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> per Oz. he has only 12 s. a Day, equal only to
3<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> 4<hi rend="italic">d.</hi> of former Times; and even this is further
reduced, by obliging him to take one half in Shop Goods at 25 per Cent.
or more Advance above the Money Price: this Iniquity still grows, by
reducing the Goods Part to the least vendable; the Shopkeeper refusing
to let them have Provisions, West India goods, or Goods of <hi rend="italic">Great
Britain</hi> that are in Demand.

</p><p>To make the Case more familiar, Suppose a Tradesman laying in his
Winter Store, when Wages were at 5 s. with one Day's Labour he purchases
15 Pound of Butter being 4d per Pound (I use Butter because it rises the
most uniformly of all Provisions) at present his 12 s a Day purchases
only 7 Pound of Butter at 20 d a Pound.  <hi rend="italic">The Clergy</hi> or settled
Preachers to Congregations in <hi rend="italic">Boston</hi>, no Offence in classing
them with Labourers, when Silver was at 5 s. had &#163;3 per Week, at
present Silver at 29 s. per Oz. they have only &#163;6 to &#163;8 equal
to 40 s. of former Times.

</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Shopkeepers</hi> are become as it were Bankers between
the Merchants and Tradesmen, and do impose upon both egregiously.  Shop
Notes that great and insufferable Grievance of Tradesmen, were not in
Use until much Paper Money took Place: this Pay in Goods

<pb n="324"/>
which generally are of no necessary Use (Provisions and West India Goods
at this Time are removed from that Denomination) encourage Extravagance
in Apparel and Furniture much above our Condition.

</p><p>2.  <hi rend="italic">The Merchants of Great Britain Adventurers to New
England, because of their largest Dealings have suffered most</hi>.
Their Goods are here generally sold at a long Credit, while the
Denominations of the Money in which they are to be paid, continues
depreciating; so that they are paid in a less Value than was contracted
for: thus our Bills have successively depreciated from 8 s. per Oz.
Silver <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1713, to 29s. in this Year 1739; that is, if we could
suppose the same Person to have constantly followed this Trade (without
extraordinary Hits) for that space of Time,<hi rend="italic"> he must have reduced his
Estate after the rate of 8s. only for 29s.</hi> For every Shilling in
the Pound that Silver rises in Price, or, which is the same, for every
Shilling in the Pound that the Denominations of our Paper Money
depreciates, the Creditor actually looses 5 per Cent. of his Debt.

</p><p>There have been from Time to Time <hi rend="italic">seeking Factors</hi>, who
to procure Business from Home, have entred into Engagements which could
not possibly be complied with: these having little or nothing of their
own to loose, soon make desperate Work of it; become Bankrupts, and from
a general insensibility of discredit, do notwithstanding keep their
Countenance as before.

</p><p>Many <hi rend="italic">Factors</hi> to dazle their Employers for a Time, and in
the mean while to procure more Consignments; send Home a high Account of
Sales, by the Shopkeepers

<pb n="325"/>
giving a great Advance in Consideration of a very long Credit, and to be
drawn out in Shop Notes.  This Practice has so much prevailed, that it
is now become a fixed tho' pernicious and ruinous Custom.

</p><p>As Paper Money pays no Debts abroad, the Factor is obliged to
give an extra Quantity of it, to purchase Silver, and other Returns;
which can be exported, to satisfy Debts; in this Shape also the Merchant
becomes a Sufferer.

</p><p>3.  <hi rend="italic">Widows, Orphans, Funds for Charity at Interest</hi>, and
all other Creditors; by Bonds, Notes &amp; Book Debts, acquired by
Industry, good Management, and Frugality; are great Sufferers from Time
to Time: For Instance, from Autumn <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1733 to Autumn
<hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1734 Silver rose from 22 s. to 27 s. per Oz.  this was a
Loss of 23 per Cent. of the Principal.

</p><p>II.  <hi rend="italic">The repeated large Emissions of Paper Money are the
Cause of the frequent rise of the Price of Silver and Exchange</hi>;
that is, of the publick Bills of Currency depreciating in all the Paper
Money Colonies; which do as regularly follow the same, as the Tides do
the <hi rend="italic">Phases</hi> or course of the Moon.  When no larger Sums are
emitted for some time, than what are cancelled of former Emissions;
Silver and Exchange are at a Stand; when less is emitted than cancelled
(which seldom happens) Silver and Exchange do fall.  This is plain to a
kind of Demonstration, from the Instance in the History of our Paper
Money Emissions in <hi rend="italic">New England</hi>.

</p><p>After Silver had rose <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1706 to 8 s. per Oz. by light
Pieces of Eight superseding the heavy Pieces; it continued

<pb n="326"/>
at that Rate, while Paper Emissions did not exceed a due Proportion to
the current Silver.  <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1714 we emitted &#163;50,000 upon Loan,
and <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1715 in <hi rend="italic">Rhode-Island</hi> &#163;40,000 besides
Emissions on distant Funds for Charges of Government; in the Autumn A.
1715 Silver became 15 per Cent. Advance above 8 s. that is about 9 s. 2
d. per Oz.  <hi rend="italic">Massachusetts-Bay A</hi>. 1717 emitted &#163;100,000
upon Loan and a very long Period; Silver rose to 12 s. per Oz.
<hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1721 <hi rend="italic">Massachusetts-Bay</hi> emitted &#163;50,000 and
<hi rend="italic">Rhode-Island</hi> &#163;40,000 upon Loan, Silver <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1722
became 14<hi rend="italic"> s.</hi> per Oz.  From that Time a chargeable Indian War,
required large Emissions, and Silver rose to 16 s. per Oz it continued
at this Rate till <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1728, Emissions not being larger than
Cancellings.  <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1727 <hi rend="italic">Massachusetts-Bay</hi> emitted
&#163;60,000 and <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1728 <hi rend="italic">Rhode-Island</hi> emitted
&#163;40,000 upon Loans; Silver became 18 s. per Oz.  <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1731
<hi rend="italic">Rhode-Island</hi> emitted &#163;60,000 upon Loan.  (<hi rend="italic">N.B.</hi>
Besides the several Loans in the course of this History, all the Charges
of he four Governments, were defrayed by Paper Emissions) and Silver
became <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1732, 21 s. per Oz.  <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1733
<hi rend="italic">Massachusetts-Bay</hi> emitted &#163;76,000 upon Funds of Taxes,
<hi rend="italic">Rhode-Island</hi> &#163;104,000 upon Loan and Taxes,
<hi rend="italic">Connecticut</hi> &#163;50,000 upon Loan, and <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1734 Silver
became 27 s. per Ounce.  From <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1734 to <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1738 more
Bills were cancelled than emitted, Exchange fell from 440 to 400 per
Cent. Advance.  <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1738 <hi rend="italic">Rhode-Island</hi> emitted
&#163;100,000 upon Loan, Silver rose from 27 s. to 29 s. per Oz.

</p><p>In <hi rend="italic">New England</hi>, as in all other trading Countries,

<pb n="327"/>
from some particular Accident, and Circumstances, there happened at
Times, some small fluctuations in Exchange, without any Regard to
Emissions of Paper Money.  At all Times, when Returns in Ship Building,
Whale Oil and Fins, Naval Stores &amp;c. turn out well at Home; Silver
and Exchange here suffer a small fall: at other Times when these prove
bad Returns, Silver and Exchange rise a small Matter; the most noted
Instance was <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1729, when the usual Returns to <hi rend="italic">Great
Britain</hi> turned to bad Account; the Merchants from Home, directed
their Factors here, to make Remittances in Silver or Exchange only, and
at any Rate; together with an Agency from this Province and that of
<hi rend="italic">Connecticut</hi>, fitted out with a Silver Supply; Silver rose very
considerably, but after a few Months fell again to the former Price.

</p><p>The Instance of <hi rend="italic">Barbadoes</hi> must put this Assertion beyond
all Dispute with sober thinking honest Men.  <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1702 by the
Perswasion of Mr. <hi rend="italic">W</hi>. from New England, <hi rend="italic">Barbadoes</hi>
emitted &#163;16,000 Bills of publick Credit on a Fund of 3 s. 9 d.
Negroe Tax; at first they passed at a Discount, but no more being
emitted, and the Period of cancelling being short, they rose again to
near <hi rend="italic">Par</hi>: this encouraged them to make an enormous Emission of
&#163;80,000 Bills on Land Security at 4 per Cent. Principal payable
after 5 Years: These Bills immediately fell 40 per Cent. below Silver:
by an Order from Home, they were soon suppressed, and their Currency
became Silver Value as before. That Province has ever since kept their
Currency up to Proclamation

<pb n="328"/>
Value, Ballance of Trade in their favour, Exchange to <hi rend="italic">Great
Britain</hi> being generally under 33 per Cent. the Par.

</p><p>III. <hi rend="italic">Large repeated Emissions of publick Bills of Credit,
called Paper Money, is no addition to the Medium of Trade</hi>.  No
Country can have an indefinite or unlimitted Credit; the further a
Country endeavours to stretch its Credit beyond a certain Pitch, the
more it depreciates.  The Credit of a Country may be compared to that of
a private Trader; if his Credit is equal to &#163;100,000 Sterl. his
Notes of Hand for &#163;100,000 will be as good as Silver; if it be
known that he passes Notes of Hand for &#163;200,000 Sterling. their
full Credit will be suspected and eventually be worth no more than his
real Credit &#163;100,000 Sterl: if he can be supposed to utter
&#163;500,000 Bills or Notes, his &#163;5 Note will be worth only 20 s.
Sterl.

</p><p>In <hi rend="italic">New England A</hi>. 1713 there were about <hi rend="italic">two
thirds</hi> Bills to <hi rend="italic">one third</hi> Silver current, equally to 8 s.
per Oz Silver Value; there being an Allowance of 5 per Cent. in all
publick Payments in favour of Bills only, gave them a Credit beyond
their natural Stretch. At that Time the publick Bills of the four
Provinces were about &#163;175,000 at 8 s. per Oz. Silver value (we use
always the nearest round Numbers) is 438,000 Oz. Value, with 219,000 Oz
of Silver Currency is 657,000 Oz. Silver Value. <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1718 the
publick bills of <hi rend="italic">New England</hi> were &#163;300,000 (Silver all
drove away by the worse Currency of Bills) at 12 s. per Oz. Silver; is
500,000 Oz. Value in Silver. <hi rend="italic">A.</hi>1731<hi rend="italic"> New England</hi>

<pb n="329"/>
publick Bills were &#163;470,000 at 20 s. per Silver, is 470,000 Oz.
Silver value.  <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1739 the current Paper Money of <hi rend="italic">New
England</hi> was &#163;630,000 at 29 s. per Oz. Silver is in value
434,000 Oz. Silver.  Here it is plain that the more Paper Money we emit
our real Value of Currency or <hi rend="italic">Medium</hi> becomes less, and <hi rend="italic">what
we emit beyond the Trading Credit of the Country does not add to the
real Medium, but rather diminishes from it, by creating an Opinion
against us, of bad Oeconomy and sinking Credit</hi>.

</p><p>A Country may exceed in any Commodity or <hi rend="italic">Medium</hi>,
excepting in that universally Staple Commodity and Medium Silver; and a
smaller Quantity of any other Commodity or Medium will turn to the same
or better Account than a larger.  In <hi rend="italic">Holland</hi> upon a too large
Importation of Spices, they destroy some Part, to keep up the Value of
Spices.  Not long since in <hi rend="italic">Virginia</hi>, finding that Tobacco
(their Currency as well as Export) by its too large Cultivation began to
depreciate; by Act of Assembly they restricted it to 1000 l. wt. per
Annum per Tythable.  In <hi rend="italic">Maryland A</hi>. 1734 &amp; <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1735
for the same Reason they burnt 150
l. wt. per Rateable.  If our House of Representatives allow our Paper
Money to be cancelled in course, and be sparing in the Manufacture of
more; the Value of the remainder, would be equal to the Value of the
whole now current, or proposed to be added to the Currency.</p>


<pb n="330"/>
<p>It is therefore vain and inconsistent to make <hi rend="italic">Provincial</hi> or
Municipal Bills of Credit, for a Medium of general Trade: Merchants know
how to find their own Tools or <hi rend="italic">Medium</hi> of Trade, better than any
Civil Administration can prescribe: in Fact, they who call out loudest
for this Paper <hi rend="italic">Medium</hi>, are not our large Traders; but such as
would take up Money at any bad lay, <hi rend="italic">viz</hi>. the Idle, those in
desperate Circumstances, and the Extravagant; who never can have any
other Claim to Money but by Fraud; we must except some who tho'
naturally honest are misguided.  Publick Bills of Credit in a proper

<pb n="331"/>
Sense are only to defray the incident Charges of Government which may
accrue, before the proper Ways and Means of Taxes can take Place; but so
soon as can be, to be cancelled by those Taxes.  We know of no Country
in <hi rend="italic">Europe</hi>, where Exchequer Notes, State Bills, or other Bills
of publick Credit, have been issued by the Government for a
<hi rend="italic">Medium</hi> of Trade.

</p><p>IV.  <hi rend="italic">This infatuation in favour of Paper Money has had a
mutinous bad Effect upon the Civil Government, in several of our
Colonies</hi>.  The Representatives of the People, have frequently
refused to provide for the necessary Charges of Government, and other
wholesome Laws; because the Governours &amp; Councils, would not (in
breach of their Instructions from the Crown) concur in emitting large
Sums of Paper Money to defraud the industrious Creditor and fair Dealer.
I shall mention only a few Instances.  In <hi rend="italic">S. Carolina A</hi>. 1719
the People deposed the Proprietors Governour on this Account: it is
true, the <hi rend="italic">King</hi> did not much resent this Mutiny; perhaps, that
the Proprietors might be weary of their Property and government; and
accordingly seven of the eight Proprietors, for a small Consideration,
did <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1729 resign and sell to the Crown: Upon Governour
<hi rend="italic">Johnson's</hi> arrival in <hi rend="italic">S. Carolina A</hi>. 1731, there had
been no Supply granted in the four preceeding Years.  The Government of
the <hi rend="italic">Massachusetts-Bay</hi>, has from Time to Time been distressed,
by our Representatives refusing Supplies for the necessary Charges of
Government, and other publick Affairs neglected on this Account: <hi rend="italic">Our
present Governour's Fortitude and steady

<pb n="332"/>
Adherence to the King's Instructions, &amp; his having shortned the long
Periods of Emissions for Charges of Government (I am under no Obligation
to flatter) are highly laudable</hi>.  <hi rend="italic">New Hampshire
</hi>Representatives for five Years preceeding <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1736 granted
no Supply. As the French humour of building Forts, to protect their
Settlements against an Enemy; and as
the Spanish humour of Devotion, in building Churches and Convents, is
perverted, by their becoming Nurseries of Idleness and other Vices; so
the <hi rend="italic">English Liberty and Property of the Subject</hi>, in many of our
Plantations are somewhat abused, to levelling and licentiousness; it is
true, all Men are naturally equal, but Society requires subordination.

</p><p>V.  <hi rend="italic">Long Credit, is not one of the least of the bad Effects
of Paper Money</hi>.  People run in Debt, endeavour after a long Credit,
and refuse paying their Debts when due; because while Bills are
continually depreciating, the longer the Debt is outstanding, they pay
their Creditors with a less and less Value, than was contracted for. Sir
<hi rend="italic">Alexander Cumings</hi> in his Defence wrote <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1729

<pb n="333"/>
says, that in his Time in <hi rend="italic">South Carolina</hi>, pay, after twelve
Months, was reckoned as ready Money. Long Credit thus obtained, does in
its turn, forward a bad Currency, they go Hand in Hand.  A Creditor
after being long out of his Money, chuses rather to take the bad
Currency and run the Risque of passing it off again (as was the Case of
the <hi rend="italic">Rhode-Island</hi> Emissions <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1733 &amp; 1738) than of
losing his Debt, if another Creditor should take it, and the Debtor
afterwards become Insolvent.

</p><p>With ready Money or short Credit, Business goes on brisk and
easy.  <hi rend="italic">Long Credit</hi> occasions the unthinking of all Conditions
and Occupations, to involve themselves.  A Merchant over-trades himself,
a Shopkeeper buys more Goods, and at a greater Advance than he can
afterwards comply with; the Countryman buys and Mortgages Lands, to his
final Ruin.

</p><p>VI.  <hi rend="italic">Insensibility of Discredit, does naturally follow long
Credit</hi>: All Shame and Modesty is banished even in the Creditor;
who, tho' formerly a modest forbearing man, is now obliged to Dun
incessantly or lose his Debt.  Ready Money and short Credit, give a
quick Circulation; the quicker the Circulation, the less Quantity of
<hi rend="italic">Medium</hi> is required to carry on the same Trade and Business;
long Credit, and insensibility of Discredit, have the contrary Effect.
There are at present extant of <hi rend="italic">New England</hi> publick Bills of
Credit about &#163;630,000 a much larger Sum than ever was extant at any
other Time; yet Money was never so scarce and Debts worse paid:<hi rend="italic">
People chuse rather to hoard it up</hi>, and wait for better Times, than
put it out and not be able to recover it

<pb n="334"/>
again, but after an unreasonable Length of Time and much Trouble; Money
hoarded up, is the same as if not in being, as to Currency.  If a
Shopkeeper does not clear with his Merchant, till after two or three
Years due; he is notwithstanding esteem'd as honest as his Neighbour:
Our Courts are full of plain Bonds, and Notes of Hand; Appeals on them
are allowed, Executions delay'd &amp;c.  This insensibility of
Discredit, breaks all Friendship; it makes a Man cautious of lending his
Money to his best Friend, and nearest Relation.

</p><p>A general Clamour for a depreciating Paper Currency, is a certain
Sign of the Country being generally in bad Circumstances, that is,
<hi rend="italic">in Debt;</hi> because all Creditors who by their Industry and
Frugality have acquired Rents, Bonds, Notes and Book Debts, loose by its
depreciating; and the Debtors (the Idle and Extravagant Part of the
People) come off easy by the Creditors loss. Seeing they who are
desperately in Debt, and want to pay a smaller Value than contracted
for, or <hi rend="italic">they who have nothing to loose, are generally of the Party
for Paper Money;</hi> this ought to be a strong Prejudice against it,
with sober thinking Men.

</p><p>We have <hi rend="italic">some prevailing Customs and some Laws in force</hi>,
which seem to encourage this <hi rend="italic">insensibility of Discredit</hi> in
Debtors; 1.<hi rend="italic"> A Maxim amongst Shopkeepers;</hi> That the most ready
Way to grow rich, without any Expence of Industry; is, to run boldly in
Debt, procure a long Credit, after Time of Payment is elapsed to bear
Dunning with a good Face, and finally to let the Debt take its full
Course in the Law, which further requires

<pb n="335"/>
twelve Months or more, at a small Cost: Notwithstanding this Chain of
Iniquity, the Debtor keeps his Countenance, and many Factors continue to
trust him with their Employers Goods as formerly.  2.<hi rend="italic"> Estates too
easily allowed to be represented as Insolvent;</hi> whereby Creditors
are defrauded of some Part of their Due.  3. <hi rend="italic">Appeals upon plain
Bonds, Notes of Hand, and Defaults,</hi> to the great Relief of the
fraudulent Debtor, and the Damage of the honest Creditor.  4.
<hi rend="italic">Sheriffs</hi> impune <hi rend="italic">delay of Executions</hi>, while the
Creditor is allowed neither Interest nor Damage upon the Debt.  5.
<hi rend="italic">The too general Laws for the relief of insolvent Debtors,</hi>
whereby the Fraudulent, the Idle, and the Extravagant, when sent to
Goal; are too soon, and at too easy a Rate turned loose to follow the
same Courses.  What I have here said,<hi rend="italic"> cannot be understood in
contempt of our Legislative Authority;</hi> because of that valuable
Privilege belonging to our Constitution, viz. of repealing, amending, or
explaining what Laws from Experience may be found to require the same.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Arguments current amongst the Populace in favour of Paper
Money are </hi>,

</p><p>I. In most of the Paper Money Colonies one
of the principal Reasons alledged for their first Emissions; was, <hi rend="italic">to
prevent Usurers imposing high Interest upon Borrowers, from the scarcity
of Silver Money.</hi> It is true, that in all Countries the increased
Quantity of Silver, falls the Interest or use of Money; but large
Emissions of Paper Money does naturally rise the Interest to make good
the sinking Principal: for Instance, in the

<pb n="336"/>
Autumn <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1727 Silver was
at 26 s. to 27 s. per Oz. but by a
large <hi rend="italic">Rhode Island</hi> Emission, it became in Autumn 1739, 29 s.
per Oz. this is 7 per Cent. loss of Principal, therefore the Lender to
save his Principal from sinking requires 13 per Cent. natural Interest
(our legal Interest being 6 per Cent.) for that Year.  In Autumn
<hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1733 Silver was 22 s. per Oz. by large Emissions it became
27 s. in the Autumn <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1734; is 22 per Cent. loss of Principal,
and the Lender to save his Principal requires 28 per Cent. <hi rend="italic">natural
Interest</hi> for that Year. Thus <hi rend="italic">the larger the Emissions, natural
Interest becomes the higher;</hi> therefore the Advocates of Paper Money
(who are generally indigent Men, and Borrowers) ought not to complain,
when they hire Money at a dear nominal Rate.</p>

<pb n="337"/>
<p>If Bills were to depreciate after a certain Rate, Justice might be
done to both contracting Parties, by imposing the loss, which the
Principal may sustain in any certain space of Time (the Period of
Payment) upon the Interest of a bond or Price of Goods: but as
depreciations are uncertain, great Confusions in Dealings happen.

</p><p>II. <hi rend="italic">That the Merchants arbitrary Rise upon the Price of
Goods, does from Time to Time depreciate the Denominations of our Paper
Money,</hi> is imposed upon the unthinking Part the People, as a certain
Truth, by designing Men.  It is certain, that in all Countries of
<hi rend="italic">Europe</hi>, where by Recoinages or Proclamations, the current
Specie has been debased; the nominal Price of Goods did naturally rise
in Proportion: is it not more natural to say, that formerly in
<hi rend="italic">France</hi> their recoinings or lessening the Value of their
Denominations, did rise the Price of Goods; than to say that the Rise of
the Price of Goods, was the Cause of their Recoinages.  A continued Rise
on Goods in general is from a depreciating <hi rend="italic">Medium</hi>; but
fluctuations in particular Goods, are from the Quantities and Demand;
thus <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1739 Provisions the most Staple of all Commodities have
been cheap, <hi rend="italic">viz</hi>. Wheat at 10 s. per Bushel, Silver being 29 s.
per Ounce, whereas <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1738 Wheat was at 18 s. per Bushel, when
Silver was only 27 s. per Oz.

</p><p>When a large Emission can be foreseen the Price of Goods rises;
because being sold upon long Credit, the effects of the Emission will
take Place before the time of Payment: hence it is that <hi rend="italic">generally
the Price of Goods Advances, before Exchange and Silver do rise; </hi>

<pb n="338"/>
Exchange and Silver being bought with ready Money, cannot take Place
until the Addition is made to the Currency by this new Emission, and
then only gradually as the Merchant receives his Pay; thus the large
Emissions of <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1733 did not bring Silver to its height, 27 s.
per Oz. until Autumn, <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1734:  Hence proceeds that inculcated
Fallacy of the Advance on Goods rising the Price of Silver and Exchange.
The same Reason for Lenders of Money, imposing a high Interest, holds in
the Rise of the Price of Goods: Custom has given a long Credit,
Insensibility of Discredit makes it still longer, and before the
Merchant is paid, the Currency is become much depreciated.

</p><p>III. <hi rend="italic">The Sticklers for Paper-Credit requiring long Periods,
as well as large Emissions is a most unnatural Desire</hi>.  Some of the
<hi rend="italic">Massachusetts-Bay</hi> Loan, of <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1717 is still
outstanding <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1739: The several <hi rend="italic">Rhode-Island</hi> Loans do
not terminate in less than 20 Years: By this unnaturalContrivance they oblige
Posterity to supply the Extravagancies of their Parents and Ancestors,
instead of the common and natural Instinct of Parents providing for
their Children.

</p><p>IV. <hi rend="italic">It is not repeated large Emissions of a base
Paper-Currency, but our Imports exceeding our Exports, that occasions
Silver to be ship'd off in Ballance; therefore we are not to expect a
Silver-Currency supposing all Bills cancelled.</hi> Before Paper-Money
took Place in <hi rend="italic">New England</hi>, Silver abounded in Currency as much
and perhaps more, than in many of our Colonies: Our Exports

<pb n="339"/>
are always in Demand, viz. Ship-building, all Branches of Fishery,
Naval-Stores to <hi rend="italic">Great Britain</hi>, Logwood from the Bay of
<hi rend="italic">Honduras</hi>, Lumber, Stock, and other Provisions to the other
Colonies; and (<hi rend="italic">Bermudians</hi> excepted) our Navigation is the
cheapest of all Carriers.  Silver began to be generally ship'd off as
paper became the Currency; which gave the Merchant the Liberty of
shipping off his Silver as Merchandise, which otherways he must have
kept as Cash, seeing no business can be carried on to Advantage without
Cash.  In all Countries if a bad <hi rend="italic">Medium</hi> is introduced, People
take care to secure the better <hi rend="italic">Mediums</hi> and they are no more
current.

</p><p>The Fallacy of Quantities of Paper-Money, has increased our
superfluous Imports, much beyond what was in former Times.  The<hi rend="italic">
seeking Factors</hi> upon a large Emission, advise the Merchant in
<hi rend="italic">Great Britain</hi>, that Money being now very Plenty, a large
Quantity of

<pb n="340"/>
Goods will sell: Accordingly a Glut of Goods is sent to <hi rend="italic">New
England</hi>, more than can be sold for ready Money and short Credit;
the Consequence is, a long Credit, with its consequential Multitude of
Evils; that is Returns or Exports in full, are never, or not, till after
a long Time, ship'd off.

</p><p>Our Paper-Money being only passable amongst our selves, is the
Reason, why,<hi rend="italic"> they who deal only in buying and selling a Shore, get
the most Money;</hi> all their Profits are upon our selves, and run no
Risque of Precarious Returns; while the generous Merchant looses upon
his Exports to a foreign Market.  This is a ruinous Case.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">As Paper-Money grows scarce, Imports will be less, and be
sold cheaper;</hi> no Country can want a true real Medium of Trade,
while their Exports exceed their Imports: Let us then lessen our Imports
by our Frugality, and add to our Exports by our Industry; and we shall
have no occasion for this <hi rend="italic">chimerical ill founded Medium, Paper
Money</hi>.

</p><p>V. <hi rend="italic">The goodly Appearance, which Boston and the Country in
general at present, make in fine Houses, Equipage, and Dress, is owing
to Paper Money.</hi> All our Plantations from some Infatuation, are
inclinable to run into Prodigality, Profuseness, and Show: these Paper
Loans (from publick or private Schemes) upon long Periods, give the
unthinking and unwary, Opportunities of involving themselves, by thus
sinking what they have borrowed; by repeated emissions, they have
Opportunities of paying a former Debt, by running further in Debt, till
at length they become Insolvents.

<pb n="341"/>
People do not consider, that all Emissions upon Funds of Taxes or upon
Loans, is running the Country more and more in Debt, and will in Course
fall heavy upon every Individual.  Never were greater Complaints of want
of Money, while at the same Time, never more extravagance in Equipages
and Dress.<hi rend="italic"> Boston, like a Private Man of small Fortune, does not
become richer but poorer, by a rich goodly Appearance</hi>.

</p><p>What Part of these Emissions have we laid out in Improvements of
Produce, or Manufacture?  Not any.  It is true, it gave some Men
Opportunities of building Vessels and running into Trade; but their
Education and Experience not laying that Way, and having no other Bottom
of their own, they soon became <hi rend="italic">broken Merchants</hi>.

</p><p>Expending in fine Houses &amp; Apparel what ought to have
purchased Exports, is one of the Reasons, why Ballance of Trade is
against us.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">There is another Fund for all this finery</hi>, and of which
we ought not to boast, but be ashamed. By the Means of a depreciating
Currency the Merchant at Home, has been paid in less Value, than was
contracted for; his Loss was our Gain.  Several Factors from Time to
Time, have by Artifice, &amp; Assurance, procured large Commissions from
Home, and with Effrontery and Insensibility of Discredit, have become
Bankrupts: Thus the Produce of these Effects remained here, and makes
good in some Sense, that Position of Dr. <hi rend="italic">Mandevilles</hi>; Private
Vices are publick Benefits.

</p><p>VI. <hi rend="italic">This Country formerly had but a small Trade,

<pb n="342"/>
now our Trade being much enlarged, we require a large Medium.</hi> This
like all Arguments commonly used to pervert the People is very
unnatural: because the more a Country grows in good Trade, the more true
<hi rend="italic">Medium</hi> of Trade it acquires, and would have no Occasion, to
have recourse to a fallacious <hi rend="italic">Succedanium</hi> or Shift.
Notwithstanding the vast Floods of Paper Money lately emitted, and our
Trade also more general; we find that in former Times, the People were
more willing and able to pay high Rates, than at present.  The first
Assembly upon the new Charter, did in<hi rend="italic"> June A.</hi> 1692, lay a Tax
of &#163;30,000 (equal to upwards of &#163;120,000 present Currency)
payable within the Year, <hi rend="italic">viz</hi>. one half before 25th of
<hi rend="italic">December A</hi>. 1692, and the other half before 1st of <hi rend="italic">May</hi>
1693; towards paying off Charges formerly incurred by the
<hi rend="italic">Canada</hi> Expedition and Charges of that Year.  <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 1694
the Tax was &#163;17,589 (equal of upwards of &#163;70,000 present
Currency) towards paying off the Government Charges of that and the
preceeding Year.  Whereas, we who reckon our selves so much increased in
Trade at present <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1739 refuse a small Rate of about only
&#163;50,000 towards paying Government Charges incurred <hi rend="italic">A</hi>.
1728, <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1733, and <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1737.

</p><p>VII. <hi rend="italic">How can we pay our Taxes and Debts, if the Government do
not make large Emissions of Paper Money?</hi> In all Countries excepting
in Paper Money Colonies, the People support the Government; it is absurd
to imagine that a Government finds Money for its People, it is the
People who by their Trade and Industry,

<pb n="343"/>
provide not only for their own Subsistence, but also for the Support of
Government, and to find their own <hi rend="italic">Tools</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Medium</hi> of
Trade.  It is true, the Government, that is, the Stewards of the
Publick, may by the Consent of their Principals, the collective Body of
the People; raise Money upon the Credit of the Real and Personal Estates
of the People: but this in Propriety of Speech, is not making (or
acquiring) of Money as we term it, but the reverse: A Prodigal who
involves his Estate to raise ready Money, is it not ridiculous to say he
has made so much Money; whereas in effect he has spent so much Money by
sinking some Part of his Estate.  The unthinking Part of our People do
not consider, that <hi rend="italic">every Emission of Paper Credit called Money, is
laying a heavy Tax upon us,</hi> which in Time will contribute to our
Misery: and is really analogous to the Negroes in <hi rend="italic">Guinea</hi>, who
sell their Progeny into Slavery, for the sake of raising some ready Pence.

</p><p>Our present Rates, are only a calling in Bills formerly Emitted,
and therefore are supposed in being, and do not require a new Emission.
This Cry is the same, as if a private Person borrows of another
&#163;100 payable after some Time, and in the mean while by profuseness
and bad Oeconomy, becomes incapable of satisfying the Debt when the Term
of Payment is come: but says to the Lender, you use me very ill, if you
do not lend me &#163;200 to enable me to pay the first &#163;100 and for
other Occasions: If the Lender proceeds thus to indulge the Borrower,
this bad Husband must at length be reduced to a State of Bankruptcy:
<hi rend="italic">Province Bills are as much a

<pb n="344"/>
Debt upon the collective Body of the People; as a private Man's Bonds
and Notes of Hand, are of a Debt upon himself.</hi>

</p><p>VIII.  <hi rend="italic">The Emission of &#163;35,000 to 40,000 per Ann. for
the ordinary Charges of Government, is a small insignificant addition to
our Currency; publick Loans have been found inconvenient; let us then
emit large Sums in Province Bills (the charge of making Bills is a
Trifle) towards publick Edifices, Fortifications, Guarda Costas,
Bridges, Castles in the Air, or any Thing, tho' of no Use or
Consequence: they will draw out larger Sums, and considerably increase
our Currency</hi>. They do not consider, that this contracting a large
unnecessary Debt, to be redeemed after some years, by heavy Rates and
Taxes, will occasion a Clamour, perhaps a Mutiny, worse than the present
groundless Complaints of Oppression.  Such unnecessary Impositions are
frequently Grounds of Complaint in the People against some Governours;
but that the People should thus impose upon themselves, is one of the
unnatural Effects of Paper Money.

</p><p>IX. <hi rend="italic">Seeing, there is like to be no Stop to our Infatuation in
receiving the depreciating Bills of</hi> Rhode-Island; <hi rend="italic">why should
they reap all the Profit in our Ruin: why should not some of our
merciful Selves</hi> (as the Authors of the 500,000 Scheme call
themselves) partake with them in the Plunder, by taking the Advantage of
our present Indispositions &amp; Weakness, Carry the Imposition further
than that of <hi rend="italic">Rhode-Island</hi>; even beyond what could have entred
into the Heart of Man, at any other

<pb n="345"/>
Time or Place, to conceive: I mean the emitting of 500,000 in Notes
without Fund or Period; a Project, to outdo the <hi rend="italic">Rhode-Islanders</hi>
in Fraud, &amp; to make these Bills more current, because worse than
those of <hi rend="italic">Rhode-Island</hi>: it is almost incredible to what a Pitch
of Iniquity some People are arrived, even prophanely to lard their
Proposals with Scripture Phrases, <hi rend="italic">to impose upon the Vulgar waste
Paper, instead of a valuable Medium</hi>.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">The several Projections or Schemes which occur at present,
towards rectifying our Currency, or at least to prevent its growing
worse, are </hi>

</p><p>I. Of a publick Nature

</p><p>1.  <hi rend="italic">Is palliative, to prevent its growing worse, by bringing
it to a Standard.</hi> By Act of Assembly let <hi rend="italic">the Governour and
Council be impowred, with the Advice of Merchants, to settle once or
twice a Year the Price of Exchange to London, or of Silver, in Province
Bills;</hi> all Bonds, Notes, and Book Debts when paid, shall be
received in Province Bills equal in Value to the Exchange or Price of
Silver, as it was thus settled at the Time of contracting: For Instance,
if I contract for &#163;500 <hi rend="italic">New England</hi> Bills of Credit when
the Exchange is settled at 5 <hi rend="italic">New England</hi> for 1 Sterling, and
when the Contract is to be satisfied, Exchange is settled at 6 for 1; I
must pay the true or Sterling value, which is &#163;600 <hi rend="italic">New
England</hi> Bills; this is strict Equity and natural Justice, it will
effectually obviate the fraudulent Practices of those who are constantly
clamouring for more Province Bills, and prevent the neighbouring

<pb n="346"/>
Colonies from imposing their depreciating Bills upon us.  Both
<hi rend="italic">Carolina's</hi> have given us a successful Precedent.

</p><p>2. As private Credit, being under Coercion, is better than
publick Faith, which being above the Law, is lawless.<hi rend="italic"> Let the
Legislature give a Sanction to some Society, of good substantial Men,
who may be willing to emit Bills upon a good Silver Bottom</hi>,
continually meliorating at a small Rate,<hi rend="italic"> v.g.</hi> 3 per Cent. per
Ann. to prevent their being hoarded up; and receivable in Taxes and all
publick Payments: Such bills will soon bring a Discount upon all other
Bills.  We have at this Time (<hi rend="italic">Christmas A</hi> 1739) a remarkable
Instance of private credit being good, and publick Faith of no Account:
<hi rend="italic">Merchants</hi> Notes (a private Emission some Years ago upon a
Silver Bottom) are sold at 33 per Cent. Advance, their true Value above
common Currency; at the same Time, <hi rend="italic">our Province Bills of the new
Tenor,</hi> which in <hi rend="italic">good Faith</hi> are 25 <hi rend="italic">per Cent</hi>.
better than the other Currencies, pass promiscuously with the bad
Currencies at <hi rend="italic">Par</hi>.

</p><p>3. Let <hi rend="italic">Massachusetts-Bay Bills</hi> only, be receivable by
the Treasurer of the Province, Counties, &amp; Towns; all Bills of the
old Tenor when brought into their Treasury, to issue no more: <hi rend="italic">that
all publick Bills hereafter to be emitted, be of the Nature of our late
Bills of a new Tenor</hi>, with this additional Clause, &ldquo;And after the
last of <hi rend="italic">December A</hi>. . . . the Treasurer is hereby directed,
without further Advice or Order, to pay to the Bearer . . . Silver or .
. .Gold upon Sight&rdquo; : The fund for bringing in this Silver and Gold from
abroad, to be Impost

<pb n="347"/>
upon Goods, Tonnage, and Light-House Money, payable in Silver or Gold
only.  At the several Emissions, let there be an equal Sum taxed on
subsequent years within the Period; and these Taxes at the same Time
assessed on the several Towns, ordering the Province Treasurer at the
stated Times to issue out his Warrants accordingly without further
Order; to prevent breach of Faith in future Assemblies, refusing to
assess the Taxes of the Year, which is the same as postponing.  thus all
these Bills will have the<hi rend="italic"> Credit of a Silver Bottom</hi>, tho' in
their nature they will be cancelled in Course by Taxes, before the
Period of redeeming them by <hi rend="italic">Silver</hi> arrive; that is,<hi rend="italic"> there
will be none left to make a Demand upon the Treasury:</hi> the Silver
lodged, will, after the Period, be ready for any Exigency of Government.
In Fact, if breach of publick Faith do not intervene; <hi rend="italic">the present
Bills of the new Tenor will, by the end of</hi> December <hi rend="italic">A</hi>.
1742 <hi rend="italic">bring Silver to</hi> 20 <hi rend="italic">s. per Oz</hi>. . . Let all new
Emissions be in <hi rend="italic">Bills of a second new Tenor</hi>, two for three of
the first new Tenor, payable in Silver or Gold after the last of
<hi rend="italic">December A</hi>. . . if not paid in by Taxes as above.  Thus
<hi rend="italic">Silver will be brought to</hi>13 <hi rend="italic">s</hi>. 4 <hi rend="italic">d. per Oz</hi>. .
. Finally, after some Years let all future Emissions be in <hi rend="italic">Bills of
a third new Tenor</hi> 1 for 2 of the second Tenor, payable in Silver or
Gold after the last of <hi rend="italic">December A</hi>. . . with the forementioned
Circumstances; <hi rend="italic">Silver will then be</hi> 6 <hi rend="italic">s</hi>. 8 <hi rend="italic">d. per
Oz</hi>.  It is plain, that &#163;100,000 of this last Money, will be a
larger <hi rend="italic">Medium</hi> of Trade, than &#163;400,000 of the present
Currency.<hi rend="italic"> This promises best, and would be a

<pb n="348"/>
gradual, gentle, and easy Method of making our Currency as valuable as
that of Virginia,</hi> which is the most valuable of all our Colony
Currencies.

</p><p>4. <hi rend="italic">The Parliament of Great Britain</hi> are at this Time,
perhaps, taking some more <hi rend="italic">summary Method</hi> of setling our
<hi rend="italic">Plantation Currencies</hi> towards redressing the injured Merchants
at Home, and the fair Dealers in the Colonies; they made some Steps
towards it last Sessions of Parliament.  It is probable they may abridge
the Plantations of this Privilege which they have assumed, of making
their <hi rend="italic">publick Bills of Credit, a Tender</hi> at any Rate they please
to impose, which is <hi rend="italic">equal to the King's Prerogative in Coins</hi>.
And to prevent private Societies, from <hi rend="italic">bubbling</hi> the People;
perhaps, they may extend, the Act 6th of <hi rend="italic">Annae</hi>, to the
Plantations, viz. <hi rend="italic">That no Partnership exceeding Six shall act as
Bankers</hi>.

</p><p>II.  <hi rend="italic">Private Schemes</hi>.  It happens unluckily for our
Paper Money Advocates, that, at this Time when the Parliament are about
redressing these Grievances, they should <hi rend="italic">madly</hi> advance many
more Schemes (some fraudulent, some foolish, and some good, but
impracticable) than ever before for multiplying of Paper Money; this
makes good the old Saying, <hi rend="italic">Quem Deus vult perdere, prius
dementat</hi>. </p>

<pb n="349"/>
<p>All <hi rend="italic">Private Banks</hi> for large Sums upon Subscription, have the
same bad Consequence which attends publick Loans, viz. <hi rend="italic">a Snare to
the People</hi>, by giving the unwary, and the Prodigal, Opportunities
of borrowing, that is, of involving &amp; ruining themselves.  Our
<hi rend="italic">Legislature</hi> from Experience, are become sensible of this Error,
and for many Years have issued no publick Loans.

</p><p>1 <hi rend="italic">Land Banks</hi>.  The famous Mr. <hi rend="italic">Law</hi>, noted for
his Knowledge in the Chances of the Games called Hazard, and for these
Fallacies called Sharping: in favour of a Land Bank, being preferable to
Silver, says, That<hi rend="italic"> Land mortgaged serves for Money, and
Culture</hi>, or Produce at the same Time; whereas Silver cannot serve
for Money, and Plate at the same Time.  As he did not understand Trade,
he did not consider that<hi rend="italic"> Silver serves for Money and
Merchandize</hi> at the same Time, and that Trade is more profitable
than Agriculture.  A Land Credit or Bank may do in a Country of no
Trade: but it is ridiculous to imagine that it can serve as a
<hi rend="italic">Medium</hi> for foreign Commerce: it cannot be shipt off as
Merchandize or Returns, as is the Case of Silver; it cannot be
transferred by Bills of Exchange; for so many Ounces of Silver received
in <hi rend="italic">Boston</hi>, I can draw upon my Correspondent for so many Ounces
of Silver payable in <hi rend="italic">London</hi>, but for so many Acres of Land made
over to me in <hi rend="italic">New England</hi>, I cannot draw upon England for any
Number of Acres, quantity and quality adjusted.

</p><p>In a Country where the Denominations of their Currency
depreciates, Land being fixed in itself, rises in Denomination Value,
whilst what is owing upon the land

<pb n="350"/>
becomes so much less as the Denominations do depreciate: Hence it is,
that a Land Bank is so much desired, by those who are in Debt or
Mortgage, or who desire to run in Debt by Mortgaging their Lands.

</p><p>2. <hi rend="italic">A Credit or Bank of Produce, and Manufacture</hi>, will
never answer in a Country where Idleness and Indolence prevails; a late
large<hi rend="italic"> Bounty upon Hemp</hi> did not encourage the raising of any
considerable Quantity thereof: it would prove a most perplexed labouring
Affair, <hi rend="italic">viz</hi>. inspecting the Quality, settling from Time to Time
the Market Price, Deficiencies in Case of bad Crops, and other
Misfortunes: Notes payable at these <hi rend="italic">unweildy Stores</hi>, would be
of the same nature, and attended with the same Inconveniencies, as the
so much deservedly exclaimed against Shop Notes.  In the Infancy of
Countries, particularly of this <hi rend="italic">Province</hi>, some Part of the
Taxes were paid in Produce, called <hi rend="italic">Stock in the Treasury</hi>; but
as our foreign Trade did grow, it was found most convenient to
discontinue it.

</p><p>I shall exemplify our present Projections of Banks upon Land,
Produce, or Manufacture; by only one Instance.  <hi rend="italic">The Bubble of</hi>
&#163;450,000<hi rend="italic"> upon Land and
Produce</hi>, which fills by Subscriptions a great Pace; the Subscribers
by their Articles give their <hi rend="italic">Twelve Directors a Negative in the
whole Management;</hi> a Power never before heard of in any Society of
Bankers or joint Stocks; it is true, they deserve it; because, by the
Face of their Bills, the Directors or <hi rend="italic">Signers promise to circulate
the whole</hi>&#163;450,000.  But is it possible, that any Man who gives
himself the Trouble of thinking seriously, can

<pb n="351"/>
imagine, that 12 Men of small Fortunes (who perhaps do not trade for
&#163;30,000 per Ann.) should in their Trade, immediately circulate
&#163;450,000?  Can it be supposed possible to <hi rend="italic">negotiate Notes of so
great a Sum, upon so small a Bottom?</hi> In short, this Scheme is so
full of Inconsistencies, that it seems to<hi rend="italic"> exceed any of the
Bubbles</hi> (which were upwards of 100 in Number) projected in
<hi rend="italic">London</hi>, in that Year of Bubbles <hi rend="italic">A.</hi>1720.

</p><p>3. <hi rend="italic">A Credit upon a Silver Fund</hi> well regulated as to
Periods and Discounts, would answer, if there were no concomitant bad
Currency; but as a bad Currency already prevails, and will in all
probability increase; by two Years Charges of this Government to be
emitted at once; by a &#163;100,000 <hi rend="italic">Rhode-Island</hi> Emission,
which they may throw in upon us at Pleasure; and by a new Emission of
&#163;100,000 from <hi rend="italic">Connecticut</hi>, which they have been
endeavouring from Time to Time, by trying to drop a majority of the
present <hi rend="italic">Assistants</hi> or Council; Silver will then rise in Price,
and these Notes on a Silver Bottom becoming more valuable, will be
hoarded up, lie dormant, and<hi rend="italic"> answer no Design of a Currency:</hi> It
is true,<hi rend="italic"> they will secure to the Possessor his Principal with a
growing Interest;</hi> but as to Currency they are worse than common
Bills, which being daily let upon Bond to circulate and promote
Business, tho' at the same Time the Owner or Creditor sinks part of his
Principal, by its

<pb n="352"/>
depreciating; and his Interest is ill paid from a general insensibility
of Discredit.  <hi rend="italic">Such Bills will never obtain a Currency, until they
force a Discount upon the bad Currency</hi>.

</p><p>An Experiment of this Kind, has already been made by the<hi rend="italic">
Merchants Notes</hi> so called, without any good Effect: they never
became a Currency; they prov'd a Snare to many of the Subscribers and
Borrowers; Silver did rise in Price as much and perhaps more, than if
they had never been emitted.  Any Scheme of this Nature if upon a longer
Period, will on that Account, be the more defective.

</p><p>If the Scheme for emitting Company Notes or <hi rend="italic">Bills, to be paid
after </hi>15<hi rend="italic"> Years, with Silver at </hi>20<hi rend="italic"> s. per Oz.</hi> can
be so contrived, as to bring a growing Discount upon the bad Currency;
it will be of the greatest Service to this Province.  It seems to bid
fair for it (I am no Undertaker nor Promoter thereof, and therefore may
be deeded <hi rend="italic">impartial</hi>) the Undertakers are Men of known Probity,
of the best Estates and of the largest Trade in this Place: by their
Articles they oblige themselves under high pecuniary Penalties, to
circulate these Bills at a certain annually growing Value, until they
arrive at 20 s. per Oz. and, in conformity to a late Law of this
Province, to refuse all future Emissions of the neighbouring
Governments, unless founded upon a Silver Bottom.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">It may perhaps be advisable to suspend the Execution of any
Paper Money Schemes, as the Affair of Colony Paper Credit, is this
present Sessions, under the immediate

<pb n="353"/>
Consideration of the Parliament of Great Britain, our supreme and
absolute Lawgiver: lest the Subscribers (Undertakers) or Possessors of
these Bills and Notes should suffer some considerable Damage, by their
peremptory Suppression</hi>.

</p><p>The Projectors of the many various private Banks for Currency,
seem to presume too much upon the Indulgence or <hi rend="italic">Connivance or our
Legislature</hi>: Some audaciously question their Power to prevent the
People from <hi rend="italic">bubbling</hi> one another, (being as they call it) an
<hi rend="italic">Act of Liberty and Property to pass and receive Notes of Hand;</hi>
others impudently impeach the Integrity of the Majority of the
Legislature, as being in a private Capacity Promoters and Encouragers of
these <hi rend="italic">Bubbles</hi>.  Doubtless our Legislature, as the <hi rend="italic">natural
Guardians</hi> of the People, will compassionately prevent their ruining
themselves; by proper Laws, such as those in <hi rend="italic">Great Britain 6th
Annae</hi> against Bankers, and sundry Acts against Bubbles; or to go no
further for a Precedent, that of our neighbouring Colony
<hi rend="italic">Connecticut, A.</hi> 1733, against private Society or Bank Bills.
There seems, at least for the present, an absolute Necessity to suppress
those which will unavoidably have a riotous Consequence; I mean the
passing upon the unwary, for a valuable Consideration, <hi rend="italic">Bills without
any true Fund or Bottom:</hi> Such Bills soon stop in Currency, and the
poor innocent Possessors, the Tradesmen and Artificers, who for special
Reasons (as they express it) are made their <hi rend="italic">Dupes</hi>, will be
provoked to use the Persons and Effects

<pb n="354"/>
of the Projectors and Signers of those Bills in a <hi rend="italic">riotous</hi>
Manner.  Our Assembly did formerly effectually suppress the pernicious
Bubbles of private <hi rend="italic">Lotteries</hi>.  Our Law enacted in <hi rend="italic">January,
A.</hi> 1738, may be extended, so as to comprehend private Societies
amongst our selves.  <hi rend="italic">This Act forbids passing or receiving Bills to
be issued by the neighbouring Governments, unless redeemable by lawful
Money,</hi> (Silver Proclamation Value)<hi rend="italic"> upon good Security, (to
appear upon the face of the Bill) within ten Years after their first Emission</hi>.

</p><p>While this Affair of <hi rend="italic">Colony Paper Money</hi> is under
Consideration of Parliament for Redress; it will appear as a <hi rend="italic">daring
Presumption</hi>, to proceed to large Emissions, especially in those
Colonies who have <hi rend="italic">valuable Charters</hi> to lose.  I mention this
with a particular regard to <hi rend="italic">Connecticut</hi>, who have hitherto
behaved well; but at present their Eastern Borders being tainted by a
bad (I had almost said <hi rend="italic">abandoned</hi>) Neighbourhood, the Colony in
general ought to be upon their Guard.

</p><p>In redressing this Error, in which many of our Plantations have
obstinately persisted for many years: it is to be hoped the<hi rend="italic">
Parliament of Great Britain,</hi> will not use any rigorous sudden
Methods; but give us Time gently &amp; gradually to extricate our
Selves; That we may be allowed upon any sudden extraordinary publick
Exigences to emit <hi rend="italic">Government Notes</hi> to be a Tender only in
publick Taxes, and to be called in as soon as may be by subsequent
Taxes: that publick bills may never be a Tender in Trade and Business.
As to the calling in of publick Bills already extant; in those

<pb n="355"/>
Governments where the Periods are short (<hi rend="italic">in New-Hampshire,
Massachusetts-Bay, and Connecticut</hi>, they do not extend beyond
<hi rend="italic">A</hi>. 1742) they may be allowed to run their Course: Where the
Periods are long; if upon <hi rend="italic">Taxes</hi>, as the Governments have the
Privilege of Taxing at any Time, they may be required to assess the same
at any Time sooner; if upon <hi rend="italic">Loan</hi> the Borrowers may be obliged
to pay in yearly for a few Years a certain Part of the Debt, but if they
insist upon the original long Period, let the Governments give
<hi rend="italic">Premium's</hi> upon all such Bills, as they are brought in; thus few
or none of these Bills will be left with the Borrowers, and at the
Expiration of the Periods of the Loans, they must pay in lawful Money
Proclamation Value; which they will by all Means endeavour to avoid, by
paying as is directed.

</p><p>FINIS.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
