<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DouSumm"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>
<TEI.2 id="DouSumm">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A summary, historical and political, of the first planting, progressive improvements, and present state of the
British    settlements in North-America... / by William Douglass</title>
<title type="sort">summary, historical and political of the first planting progressive improvements and present state of the british settlements in north america by william douglass</title>
<author>Brock: Douglass, William</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Ronald Michener, University of Virginia</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">20</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">DouSumm</idno>
<date value="2000">2000</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2000 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475886</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>This text is part of the collection for the Leslie Brock Center for the Study of Colonial Currency.</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>This electronic text is a reproduction of the footnote on pages 509-512 of Volume I and the footnote on page 88 of Volume II
of Douglass`s text.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A summary, historical and political, of the first planting, progressive improvements, and present state of the British
settlements in North-America...</title>
<title type="sort">summary, historical and political of the first planting progressive improvements and present state of the british settlements in north america</title>
<author>William Douglass</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>5 pages</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Rogers and Fowle</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
<date value="1752">1749-1752</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Alderman Library, University of Virginia, Micfich 1077 no. 6307</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1752">1749-1752</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2000-05">May, 2000</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Cynthia Filer, The Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<front id="d2">
<div1 type="introduction" id="d3">


<p>William Douglass, author of the Discourse
and Postscript, also wrote a contemporary
history. Perhaps it is surprising, in light of Douglass's hard money
views, that he did not approve of the currency
reform. In part, the explanation is political: Douglass disliked
Governor Shirley, and the currency reform had been a cooperative effort
managed by Thomas Hutchinson and Governor Shirley. Douglass was
politically aligned with a group of Boston merchants who supported the
previous governor, Governor Belcher. They had many reasons for opposing
Shirley: religious, ethical, political and economic. Belcher was a
dissenter, while Shirley was an Anglican. Shirley's supporters had used
underhanded methods to discredit Belcher and obtain his dismissal. Once
in power, Shirley aligned himself with former land bankers. The land
bankers and merchants shared a deep-seated mutual antagonism. The
merchants viewed the land bankers as wild-eyed inflationists, while the
land bankers resented the heavy-handed methods Belcher and the merchants
had used to crush the land bank. When King George's war began, Shirley
used his influence with the land bankers in the assembly to lead the
colony into several costly military expeditions. Financing the
expeditions with newly printed money fueled inflation. The expeditions also brought high
taxes, which combined with the loss of men, crippled the colonies
commerce. Shirley's enemies were taking their complaints to London, and
they felt they were making headway, and that Shirley would shortly be
dismissed in disgrace. Douglass's <hi rend="italic">Summary</hi> was written, in part,
as an anti-Shirley diatribe to be used in this endeavor. </p>

<p>When the currency reform was enacted, Douglass and his merchant
friends were deeply suspicious. What were Shirley and his
inflation-loving land-banker allies up to, they wondered? Whatever it
was, they were sure it was no good. Some felt Shirley would reform the
currency as a way to save himself from being dismissed. Others suspected
financial skullduggery. Douglass's innuendoes regarding Bollan should be
interpreted as reflecting such suspicions: Bollan was Shirley's
son-in-law. Others felt that the currency reform was a ruse, and after
it had served its political purpose, Shirley would find a way to renege.
</p>

<p>Most of the following excerpt, which comes from one of Douglass's
many discursive footnotes, must have been originally composed in early
1749 (1748 under the old calendar) immediately after the currency reform
was adopted. From what is written, the reimbursement money had not yet
arrived in the colony, which definitely places it before September of
1749. Moreover, Douglass writes about agent Palmer is if he is living:
Palmer died in the summer of 1749. The final paragraph of this excerpt
comes from another footnote that appears much later in the text, and it
seems to have been composed in 1750, after the actual implementation of
the reform had begun. </p> </div1>
</front>


<body id="d4">
<div1 type="note" id="d5">


<pb n="509"/>

<p>It is arrogant, in some Measure seditious, and a great Sin against
the divine Institution of Society; for any Person or Persons, to exclaim
against the Acts of Legislature; the following are only some private
Speculations, concerning the negotiating of the late
<hi rend="italic">Cape-Breton</hi> Expedition Reimbursement Money, and the <hi rend="italic">sudden
Transition</hi> from an immense base Paper-Currency, to that good and
universal Medium of Silver Money. </p>

<p>1. The late Act for receiving and negotiating our
<hi rend="italic">Reimbursement</hi> Money granted by the Parliament of
<hi rend="italic">Great-Britain</hi>, Impowers Sir <hi rend="italic">Peter Warren</hi>, Mr.
<hi rend="italic">Bollan</hi>, and Mr. <hi rend="italic">Palmer</hi>, or two of them, the said
<hi rend="italic">Bollan</hi> to be one; perhaps giving the Negative to Mr.
<hi rend="italic">Bollan</hi>, may disgust the other two Gentlemen, so as to prevent
their acting, and consequently occasion a further Delay of the
<hi rend="italic">Reimbursement</hi>; did not, Mr. <hi rend="italic">Bollan's</hi> being formerly
appointed sole Agent in this Affair, disgust his Fellow Provincial Agent
Mr. <hi rend="italic">Kilby</hi>, a Gentleman of Knowledge and Spirit in transacting
of Business; and occasion a Memorial of Merchants and others,
<hi rend="italic">Sept</hi>. 21. 1748, to the Treasury of <hi rend="italic">Great-Britain</hi>, to
delay the Remittance of the <hi rend="italic">Reimbursement</hi> Money, for Reasons
therein specified? This Delay is a Damage to the Country after the Rate
(I mean the Interest of the Money) of 11,000&pound;. Sterl: or 110,000&pound;.
Old Tenor per Annum; as if some Debtors Managers, studied Methods to
delay the <hi rend="italic">Melioration</hi> of the Denominations of our Currencies,
by clogging the Affair. </p>

<p>2. The Amount of our Provincial Debt (that is of our publick Bills,
or Paper Currency) <hi rend="italic">Anno</hi> 1748 was about 2,405,000&pound;. Old
Tenor; by this Act a Part of it 712,000&pound;. is to be sunk by very heavy
Rates upon a reduced poor people, in the Years 1748 and 1749; and the
remaining 1,693,000&pound;. Old Tenor, is to be redeemed or exchanged by
the Reimbursement Silver; Commissions, Freight, Insurance, and some
petty Charges being first deducted. </p>

<p>I use the Words, a poor reduced People, 1. In Conformity to sundry
Expressions used at several Times by the House of Representatives, in
their Messages to the Governor, &ldquo;with publick Taxes we

<pb n="510"/>
are burdened almost to Ruin.&rdquo; &mdash; &ldquo;the Province is at a
prodigious daily Charge beyond their Strength, which has involved us in
a prodigious Load of Debt, and in a manner exhausted our
Substance.&rdquo; &mdash; &ldquo;Although the same Disposition remains, yet we
are in a manner incapable to promote (the <hi rend="italic">British</hi> Interest) it
for the future.&rdquo; 2. The Loss of about 3000 robust, labouring young
Men by Expeditions; Major <hi rend="italic">Little</hi> lately Commander of the
<hi rend="italic">Massachusetts-Bay</hi> Reinforcements sent to <hi rend="italic">Annapolis</hi> in
<hi rend="italic">Nova-Scotia</hi>, in his Book published in <hi rend="italic">London</hi> 1748,
concerning the Nature of the present Trade of our Northern Colonies,
writes, that by multiplied Expeditions they had lost 7000 Men, and many
Thousands perverted to Idleness: here I may, by Way of Amusement
observe, that according to the Estimates of Political Arithmeticians, in
all well settled Countries the Numbers of Males and Females are nearly
equal (some are very particular, and suppose 18 Male Births, to 17
Female Births) therefore as we have lately by Expeditions lost about
Three Thousand <hi rend="italic">young Men</hi>, there remains with us a Ballance of
Three Thousand <hi rend="italic">young Women</hi>, good Breeders, but idle in that
Respect; the Ballance may be transferred to settle <hi rend="italic">Nova-Scotia</hi>,
under the Cover of some Regiments of Soldiers, that must be disbanded,
which in the Interim may be transported to <hi rend="italic">Nova-Scotia</hi>,
cantoned, and continued in Pay for two or three Years, with Portions of
Land, at an easy Quit-rent; thus the <hi rend="italic">French</hi> Settlers, our
perfidious Subjects may be elbowed out. 3. The inconceivable Decay of
our Trade and Business: Fishery and Ship-building are the most
considerable Articles: formerly from <hi rend="italic">Marblehead</hi> our principal
Cod-Fishery-Port, there were about 160 Fishing Scooners, upon the Stocks
in <hi rend="italic">Boston</hi> 7000 Ton of Top-sail Vessels, at present not much
exceeding 2000 Tons. 4. Some of our Townships, and consequently their
Proportion of Taxes, have lately by the Determination of the King in
Council, been set off to the neighbouring Governments of
<hi rend="italic">New-Hampshire</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Rhode-Island</hi>. 5. The late sudden and
considerably enhanced Pay of the three Negatives of the Legislature,
notwithstanding Exchange, Silver, and Necessaries of Life (Cloathing
growing cheaper) being nearly at the same Price <hi rend="italic">Anno</hi> 1747 and
1748. </p>

<p>3. Our Combination of Debtors who formerly were for postponing of
Paper Money, all of a sudden inconsistently with their proper Character,
<hi rend="italic">quicquid id iest timeo</hi>, are for sinking all Paper Currency in
the Space of a Year or two; we may without Breach of Charity suspect
their hurrying the Province into a State of Confusion, that they may
fish in troubled Waters; perhaps as Paper-Currency arrived by Degrees,


<pb n="511"/>
to a vast Sum, and great Depreciation; it would be more natural to sink
it gradually in the Space of half a Dozen, or half a Score of Years; and
by Act of Parliament (not by precarious Instructions) no more
Paper-Money to be emitted, a Governor consenting to any such Emissions
to be rendred incapable and mulcted. Notwithstanding that I always was a
professed Enemy to all Paper, as being a base fallacious, and fraudulent
Contrivance of a Currency, I cannot avoid thinking that this is the most
salutary Method. </p>

<p>4. The honest and honourable Way of paying a Bill, is, according to
the Face of the Bill, that is, all Bills with us of 6<hi rend="italic">s</hi>. in the
face of the Bills, should be paid in a Piece of Eight; whereas by the
Act 1748, a Piece of Eight shall be received in Payments for
11<hi rend="italic">s</hi>. 3<hi rend="italic">d</hi>. New Tenor; thus these Bills in their own
pernicious Nature, from <hi rend="italic">Anno</hi> 1742 to 1748 have suffered a
Discount of about 10<hi rend="italic">s</hi>. in the Pound: Mr. <hi rend="italic">S&mdash;l&mdash;y</hi> in a
Speech or Message in Relation to the first Emission of these New Tenor
Bills insinuates, that he had contrived Bills which could not
depreciate: But notwithstanding, these Bills have greatly depreciated in
passing through several Hands, and as it is impossible to adjust the
Proportion of Depreciation in each of these Heads, it is
<hi rend="italic">unreasonable</hi> that the <hi rend="italic">last Possessor</hi> should have the
Allowance of the successive Depreciations: Therefore the Assembly in
Equity have allowed the Possessor only the current Value, but here the
Assembly seem to allow themselves to be Bankrupts at the Rate of
10<hi rend="italic">s</hi>. in the Pound, from 1742 to 1748. Perhaps if a Piece of
Eight had been in the new Projection enacted equal to 12<hi rend="italic">s</hi>. New
Tenor, which is 48<hi rend="italic">s</hi>. Old Tenor, the general Price amongst
Merchants; it would have been no Injustice to the Possessors, it would
have prevented their being hoarded up, and the Reimbursement Money would
have paid off about 6 <hi rend="italic">per Cent</hi> more of our Debts, that is,
cancelled so much more of our <hi rend="italic">iniquitous Currency</hi>. N.B.
Perhaps, the stating of a Piece of Eight (seven Eights of an Ounce of
Silver) at 6<hi rend="italic">s</hi>. Currency, and one Ounce of Silver at
6<hi rend="italic">s</hi>. 8<hi rend="italic">d</hi>. is out of Proportion: the true Proportion is
6<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> 10<hi rend="italic">d</hi>. two 7ths. </p>

<p>5. In Place of sending over the Reimbursement in foreign Silver-Coin,
if the Provincial Treasurer were empowered from Home and here, to draw
partial Bills for the same upon the <hi rend="italic">British</hi> Treasury, or where
else it may be lodged; this would save Commissions, Insurance, Freight,
and small Charges, to the Value of about 12,000&pound;. Sterling upon the
183,000&pound;. Reimbursement, sufficient to discharge 120,000&pound;. Old
Tenor, of our Debts. I shall not say that private pecuniary Views, but
not Oeconomy are in the Case. </p>

<p>Upon the Supposition of this Reimbursement Money being remitted


<pb n="512"/>
by Bills of Exchange, consulting the best Advantage of the Province;
perhaps by appropriating one half of the Reimbursement for that End,
910,000&pound;. O.T. of our Debt or Bills would in the most expeditious
Manner be instantly sunk; all Merchants, Shop-keepers, and others would
gladly purchase with our Paper such good and punctual Bills, preferable
to any other private Bills of Exchange: The other half of the
Reimbursement to be by the like Bills of Exchange purchased here by
Silver to introduce a silver Currency, the <hi rend="italic">only proper commercial
Medium;</hi> providentially in Favour of this Purpose, we have lately
had imported a Capture from the <hi rend="italic">Spaniards</hi> of 54 Chests of
Silver, which the Owners would gladly have exchanged for such Bills; all
Merchants and others in <hi rend="italic">New-England</hi> and the adjacent Provinces
who send Pieces of Eight Home as Returns, or to purchase fresh Goods,
would be fond of bringing their Silver to purchase good Bills free from
all the Charges of other Remittances; Thus besides a Silver Currency
commencing, of 910,000&pound;. Old Tenor Value, we shall have a remaining
Paper-Currency of 1,495,000 to be cancelled gradually by Rites and other
Taxes, suppose in 10 Years, is about 150,000&pound;. Old Tenor, or
37,500&pound;. New Tenor <hi rend="italic">per Annum</hi>; thus the two Years 1748 and
1749, perhaps oppressively loaded, will be much eased, and the
infatuated Paper-Currency Men made easy by sinking of it gradually; with
the Proviso of an Act of Parliament prohibiting, <hi rend="italic">for ever</hi>
hereafter, any more publick Bills of Credit to be emitted. </p>

<p>This remaining 1,493,000&pound;. Paper Currency, abstracting from the
910,000&pound;. Silver, Part of the Reimbursement, is more than a
sufficient Medium for Trade and Business, in a quick Circulation, in the
Province of <hi rend="italic">Massachusetts-Bay.</hi> Let us recollect, that in the
latter part of Governor <hi rend="italic">Belcher's</hi> Administration 1741,
immediately preceeding Governor <hi rend="italic">Shirley's</hi> Accession, this
Province in its full Vigour and Extent of Trade, seemed to be
sufficiently supplied, by a Sum not exceeding 160,000&pound;. A Fund for
Taxes not assessed, for Taxes assessed but not collected, and for
Arrears of Loans; let us suppose a like Sum of 160,000&pound; from the
neighbouring Governments, obtained a Credit of Circulation with us (the
four Colonies of <hi rend="italic">New-England</hi> hitherto as to Currencies have
been as one Province) makes 320,000&pound;.; at that Time Silver was at
29<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> per Ounce, at this Time 1748 it is 58<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> per
Ounce; therefore upon this Foundation we must suppose 640,000&pound;. Old
Tenor Value, the Medium
sufficient or requisite for our Trade and Business, whereas we have
allowed 1,495,000&pound;. Old Tenor Value, being more than double that Sum,
to remain for a Paper Currency.<ref target="n1">[1]</ref> </p>

<p>A Stranger may think it unaccountable that in the Beginning of
Governor <hi rend="italic">Shirley</hi>'s Administration, <hi rend="italic">Anno</hi> 1741, the
projected speedy cancelling of about 130,000 Old Tenor Bills by the
Taxes for 1741 should be judged too oppressive for one Year, and was
therefore divided amongst three subsequent Years; whereas the
103,000\243. New Tenor, or 412,000 Old Tenor, Taxes of 1748 (although,
we ahve the Reimbursement Money, to alleviate this grievous Weight)
toward the End of his Administration, is not lightned. </p>


<note id="n1"><seg type="note-symbol">[1]</seg> <p>Douglass is underestimating Massachusetts
currency in circulation in 1741. Brock shows &pound;359,919.</p></note>
</div1>

<div1 type="note" id="d6">


<pb n="88"/>

<p>N.B. To annihilate Plantation Currencies in a general Sense, is very
laudable; but to do it suddenly or in the Space of one Year, when there
is no other Medium or Currency; puts a Stop to all Trade and Business;
this Obstruction may divert our Commerce into some other Channel; We
have a notable Instance of this in the Province of
<hi rend="italic">Massachusetts-Bay,</hi> 1750. </p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
