<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DowPath"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;

]>

<TEI.2 id="DowPath">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Paths of Hope for the Negro: Practical Suggestions of a Southerner</title>
<title type="sort">paths of hope for the negro practical suggestions of a southerner</title>
<author>Dowd, Jerome</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">22</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">DowPath</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475888</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Paths of Hope for the Negro: Practical Suggestions of a Southerner</title>
<title type="sort">paths of hope for the negro practical suggestions of a southerner</title>
<author>Jerome Dowd</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Century Magazine</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 61</p>
</seriesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1900">1900</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
<term>African American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-11">November 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Monique Dull, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>basic conversion to TEI-conformant markup</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-06">June 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted sgml to xml.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="essay" id="d3">
<pb n="278"/>


<head>Dowd, Jerome.  "Paths of Hope for the Negro: Practical Suggestions
of a Southerner."  <hi rend="italic"> Century Magazine</hi> 61.2 (Dec. 1900):
278-281.</head>

<p>It is too late in the day to discuss whether it would have been
better had the Negro never been brought into the Southern States.
If his presence here has been beneficial, or is ever to prove so,
the price of the benefit has already been dearly paid for.  He was
the occasion of the deadliest and most expensive war in modern
times.  In the next place, his presence has corrupted politics and
has limited statesmanship to a mere question of race supremacy.
Great problems concerning the political, industrial, and moral life
of the people have been subordinated or overshadowed, so that,
while important strides have been made elsewhere in the
investigation of social conditions and in the administration of
State and municipal affairs, in civil-service reform, in the
management of penal and charitable institutions, and in the field
of education, the South has lagged behind.
</p><p>On the charts of illiteracy and crime the South is represented
by an immense black spot.  Such are a few items of the account.  It
will require millions more of dollars and generations more of
earnest work before the total cost is met of bringing the black man
to this side of the globe.  But the debt has been incurred and must
be liquidated.
</p><p>The welfare of the Negro is bound up with that of the white
man in many important particulars:
</p><p>First, the low standard of living among the blacks keeps down
the wages of all classes of whites.  So long as the Negroes are
content to live in miserable huts, wear rags, and subsist upon hog
fat and cow-pease, so long must the wages of white people in the
same kind of work be pressed toward the same level.  The higher we
raise the standard of living among the Negroes, the higher will be
the wages of the white people in the same occupations.  The low
standard of the Negroes is the result of low productive power.  The
less intelligent and skilled the Negroes are, the less they can
produce, whether working for themselves or others, and hence, the
less will be the total wealth of the country.
</p><p>But it may be asked, When the standard of living of the
Negroes is raised, will not wages go up, and will not that be a
drawback?  Certainly wages will go up, because the income of all
classes will be increased.  High wages generally indicate high
productive power and general wealth, while low wages indicate the
opposite.  Only benefits can arise from better wages.
</p><p>In the next place, the Negro's propensity to crime tends to
excite the criminal tendencies of the white man.  The South enjoys
the distinction of having the highest percentage of crime in all
the civilized world, and the reason is that the crimes of the one
race provoke counter-crimes in the other.
</p><p>The physical well-being of the one race has such a conspicuous
influence upon that of the other that the subject requires no
elaboration.  The uncleanliness of person and habits of the Negroes
in their homes and in the homes of their employers tends to
propagate diseases, and thus impairs the health and increases the
death-rate of the whole population.
</p><p>Again, the lack of refinement in intellect, manners, and dress
among the Negroes is an obstacle to the cultivated life of the
whites.  Ignorance and the absence of taste and self-respect in
servants result in badly kept homes and yards, destruction of
furniture and ware, ill-prepared food, poor table service, and a
general lowering of the standard of living.  Furthermore, the
corrupt, coarse, and vulgar language of the Negroes is largely
responsible for the jumbled and distorted English spoken by many of
the Southern whites.
</p><p>Seeing that the degradation of the Negro is an impediment to
the progress and civilization of the white man, how may we effect
an improvement in his condition?
</p><p>First, municipalities should give more attention to the
streets and alleys that traverse Negro settlements.  In almost
every town in the South there are settlements, known by such names
as "New Africa," "Haiti," "Log Town," "Smoky Hollow," or "Snow
Hill," exclusively inhabited by Negroes.
<pb n="279"/>

These settlements
are often outside the corporate limits.  The houses are built along
narrow, crooked, and dirty lanes, and the community is without
sanitary regulations or oversight.  These quarters should be
brought under municipal control, the lanes widened into streets and
cleaned, and provision made to guard against the opening of similar
ones in the future.
</p><p>In the next place, property-owners should build better houses
for the Negroes to live in.  The weakness in the civilization of
the Negroes is most pronounced in their family life.  But
improvement in this respect is not possible without an improvement
in the character and the comforts of the houses they live in.  Bad
houses breed bad people and bad neighborhoods.  There is no more
distinctive form of crime than the building and renting of houses
unfit for human habitation.
</p><p>Scarcely second in importance to improvements in house
architecture is the need among Negroes of more time to spend with
their families.  Employers of Negro labor should be less exacting
in the number of hours required for a day's work.  Many domestic
servants now work from six in the morning until nine and ten
o'clock at night.  The Southern habit of keeping open shopping-places until late at night encourages late suppers, retains cooks,
butlers, and nurses until bedtime, and robs them of all home life.
If the merchants would close their shops at six o'clock, as is the
custom in the North, the welfare of both races would be greatly
promoted.
</p><p>Again, a revolution is needed in the character of the Negro's
religion.  At present it is too largely an affair of the emotions.
He needs to be taught that the religious life is something to grow
into by the perfection of personality, and not to be jumped into or
sweated into at camp-meetings.  The theological seminaries and the
graduate preachers should assume the task of grafting upon the
religion of the Negro that much sanity at least.
</p><p>A reform is as much needed in the methods and aims of Negro
education.  Up to the present Negro education has shared with that
of the white man the fault of being top-heavy.  Colleges and
universities have developed out of proportion to, and at the
expense of, common schools.  Then, the kind of education afforded
the Negro has not been fitted to his capacities and needs.  He has
been made to pursue courses of study parallel to those prescribed
for the whites, as though the individuals of both races had to fill
the same positions in life.  Much of the Negro's education has had
nothing to do with his real life-work.  It has only made him
discontented and disinclined to unfold his arms.  The survival of
the Negroes in the race for existence depends upon their retaining
possession of the few bread-winning occupations now open to them.
But instead of better qualifying themselves for these occupations
they have been poring over dead languages and working problems in
mathematics.  In the meantime the Chinaman and the steam-laundry
have abolished the Negro's wash-tub, trained white "tonsorial
artists" have taken away his barber's chair, and skilled painters
and plasterers and mechanics have taken away his paint-brushes and
tool-chests.  Every year the number of occupations open to him
becomes fewer because of his lack of progress in them.  Unless a
radical change takes place in the scope of his education, so that
he may learn better how to do his work, a tide of white immigration
will set in and force him out of his last stronghold, domestic
service, and limit his sphere to the farm.
</p><p>All primary schools for the Negroes should be equipped for
industrial training in such work as sewing, cooking, laundering,
carpentry, and house-cleaning, and, in rural districts, in
elementary agriculture.
</p><p>Secondary schools should add to the literary courses a more
advanced course in industrial training, so as to approach as nearly
as possible the objects and methods of the Tuskegee and Hampton
Industrial and Normal Schools.  Too much cannot be said in behalf
of the revolution in the life of the Negro which the work of these
schools promises and, in part, has already wrought.  The writer is
fully aware that education has a value aside from and above its
bread-winning results, and he would not dissuade the Negro from
seeking the highest culture that he may be capable of; but it is
folly for him to wing his way through the higher realms of the
intellect without some acquaintance with the requirements and
duties of life.
</p><p>Changes are needed in the methods of Negro education as well
as in its scope.  Educators should take into account, more than
they have yet done, the differences in the mental characteristics
of the two races.  It is a well-established fact that, while the
lower races possess marked capacity to deal with simple, concrete
ideas, they lack power of generalization, and soon fatigue in the
realm of the abstract.  It is also well known that the inferior
races, being deficient in generalization, which is a subjective
process, are
<pb n="280"/>

absorbed almost entirely in the things that
are objective.  They have strong and alert eyesight, and are
susceptible to impressions through the medium of the eye to an
extent that is impossible to any of the white races.  This fact is
evidenced in the great number of pictures found in the homes of the
Negroes.  In default of anything better, they will paper their
walls with advertisements of the theater and the circus, and even
with pictures from vicious newspapers.  They delight in street
pageantry, fancy costumes, theatrical performances, and similar
spectacles.  Factories employing Negroes generally find it
necessary to suspend operations on "circus day."  They love stories
of adventure and any fiction that gives play to their imaginations.
All their tastes lie in the realm of the objective and the
concrete.
</p><p>Hence, in the school-room stress should be laid on those
studies that appeal to the eye and the imagination.  Lessons should
be given in sketching, painting, drawing, and casting.  Reprints of
the popular works of art should be placed before the Negroes, that
their love for art may be gratified and their taste cultivated at
the same time.  Fancy needlework, dress-making, and home
decorations should also have an important place.  These studies,
while not contributing directly to bread-winning, have a refining
and softening influence upon character, and inspire efforts to make
the home more attractive.  The more interest we can make the Negro
take in his personal appearance and in the comforts of his home,
the more we shall strengthen and promote his family life and raise
the level of his civilization.
</p><p>The literary education of the Negro should consist of
carefully selected poems and novels that appeal to his imagination
and produce clear images upon his mind, excluding such literature
as is in the nature of psychological or moral research.
Recitations and dialogues should be more generally and more
frequently required.  In history emphasis should be given to what
is picturesque, dramatic, and biographical.
</p><p>Coming to the political phase of the Negro problem, there is
a general agreement among white men that the Southern States cannot
keep pace with the progress of the world as long as they are
menaced by Negro domination, and that, therefore, it is necessary
to eliminate the Negro vote from politics.  When the Negroes become
intelligent factors in society, when they become thrifty and
accumulate wealth, they will find the way to larger exercise of
citizenship.  They can never sit upon juries to pass upon life and
property until they are property-owners themselves, and they can
never hold the reins of government by reason of mere superiority of
numbers.  Before they can take on larger political responsibilities
they must demonstrate their ability to meet them.
</p><p>The Negroes will never be allowed to control State governments
so long as they vote at every election upon the basis of color,
without regard whatever to political issues or private convictions.
If the Negroes would divide their votes according to their
individual opinions, as the lamented Charles Price, one of their
best leaders, advised, there would be no danger of Negro domination
and no objection to their holding offices which they might be
competent to fill.  But as there is no present prospect of their
voting upon any other basis than that of color, the white people
are forced to accept the situation and protect themselves
accordingly.  Years of bitter and costly experience have
demonstrated over and over again that Negro rule is not only
incompetent and corrupt, but a menace to civilization.  Some people
imagine that there is something anomalous, peculiar, or local in
the race prejudice that binds all Negroes together; but this clan
spirit is a characteristic of all savage and semi-civilized
peoples.
</p><p>It should be well understood by this time that no foreign race
inhabiting this country and acting together politically can
dominate the native whites.  To permit an inferior race, holding
less than one tenth of the property of the community, to take the
reins of government in its hands, by reason of mere numerical
strength, would be to renounce civilization.  Our national
government, in making laws for Hawaii, has carefully provided for
white supremacy by an educational qualification for suffrage that
excludes the semi-civilized natives.  No sane man, let us hope,
would think of placing Manila under the control of a government of
the Philippine Islands based upon universal suffrage.  Yet the
problem in the South and the problem in the Philippines and in
Hawaii differ only in degree.
</p><p>The only proper safeguard against Negro rule in States where
the blacks outnumber or approximate in number the whites lies in
constitutional provisions establishing an educational test for
suffrage applicable to black and white alike.  If the suffrage is
not thus limited it is necessary for the whites to resort to
technicalities and ballot laws, to bribery or intimidation.  To set
up an educational
<pb n="281"/>

test with a "grandfather clause," making
the test apply for a certain time to the blacks only, seems to an
outsider unnecessary, arbitrary, and unjust.  The reason for such
a clause arises from the belief that no constitutional amendment
could ever carry if it immediately disfranchised the illiterate
whites, as many property-holding whites belong to that class.  But
the writer does not believe in the principle nor in the necessity
for a "grandfather clause."  If constitutional amendments were to
be submitted in North Carolina and Virginia applying the
educational test to both races alike after 1908, the question would
be lifted above the level of party gain, and would receive the
support of white men of all parties and the approbation of the
moral sentiment of the American people.  A white man who would
disfranchise a Negro because of his color or for mere party
advantage is himself unworthy of the suffrage.  With the suffrage
question adjusted upon an educational basis the Negroes would have
the power to work out their political emancipation, the white
people having made education necessary and provided the means for
attaining it.
</p><p>When the question of Negro domination is settled the path of
progress of both races will be very much cleared.  Race conflicts
will then be less frequent and race feeling less bitter.  With more
friendly relations growing up, and with more concentration of
energy on the part of the Negroes in industrial lines, the
opportunities for them will be widened and the task of finding
industrial adjustment in the struggle for life made easier.  The
wisest and best leaders among the Negroes, such as Booker
Washington and the late Charles Price, have tried to turn the
attention of the Negroes from politics to the more profitable
pursuits of industry, and if the professional politician would
cease inspiring the Negroes to seek salvation in political
domination over the whites, the race issue would soon cease to
exist.
</p><p>The field is broad enough in the South for both races to
attain all that is possible to them.  In spite of the periodic
political conflicts and occasional local riots and acts of
individual violence, the relations between the races, in respect to
nine tenths of the population, are very friendly.  The general
condition has been too often judged by the acts of a small
minority.  The Southern people understand the Negroes, and feel a
real fondness for those that are thrifty and well behaved.  When
fairly treated the Negro has a strong affection for his employer.
He seldom forgets a kindness, and is quick to forget a wrong.  If
he does not stay long at one place, it is not that he dislikes his
employer so much as that he has a restless temperament and craves
change.  His disposition is full of mirth and sunshine, and not a
little of the fine flavor of Southern wit and humor is due to his
influence.  His nature is plastic, and while he is easily molded
into a monster, he is also capable of a high degree of culture.
Many Negroes are thoroughly honest, notwithstanding their bad
environment and hereditary disposition to steal.  Negro servants
are trusted with the keys to households to an extent that,
probably, is not the case among domestics elsewhere in the
civilized world.
</p><p>It is strange that two races working side by side should
possess so many opposite traits of character.  The white man has
strong will and convictions and is set in his ways.  He lives an
indoor, monotonous life, restrains himself like a Puritan, and is
inclined to melancholy.  The prevalence of Populism throughout the
South is nothing but the outcome of this morbid tendency.  Farmers
and merchants are entirely absorbed in their business, and the
women, especially the married women, contrast with the women of
France, Germany, and even England, in their indoor life and
disinclination to mingle with the world outside.  Public parks and
public concerts, such as are found in Europe, which call out
husband, wife, and children for a few hours of rest and communion
with their friends, are almost unknown in the South.  The few
entertainments that receive sanction generally exclude all but the
well-to-do by the cost of admission.  The life of the poor in town
and country is bleak and bare to the last degree.
</p><p>Contrasting with this tendency is the free-and-easy life of
the blacks.  The burdens of the present and the future weigh
lightly upon their shoulders.  They love all the worldly
amusements; in their homes they are free entertainers, and in their
fondness for conversation and love of street life they are equal to
the French or Italians.
</p><p>May we not hope that the conflict of these two opposite races
is working out some advantages to both, and that the final result
will justify all that the conflict has cost?
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

