<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DriLess"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="DriLess">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Lesson to My Ghost</title>
<title type="sort">lesson to my ghost</title>
<author>Drinkwater, John</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">7</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">DriLess</idno>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475895</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Lesson to My Ghost</title>
<title level="j">North American Review</title>
<title type="sort">lesson to my ghost</title>
<author>John Drinkwater</author>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 668-669</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>North American Review Corporation</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted: Alderman Library, Call Number AP2 .N7</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>November 1920</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>The North American Review, Vol. Vol. 212, No. 5, November 1920.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1920">1920</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>poetry</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997-01">January 1997</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Stephen Ramsay, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">




<div1 type="poem" id="d3">
	<pb n="668"/>
<head>A LESSON TO MY GHOST<lb/>
BY JOHN DRINKWATER</head>

<lg type="verse">
<l>Shall it be said that the wind's gone over</l>
<l>The hill this night, and no ghost there?</l>
<l>Not the shape of an old-time lover</l>
<l>Pacing the old road, the high road there?</l>
<l>By the peacock tree, the tree that spreads its branches</l>
<l>Like a proud peacock's tail (so my lady says),</l>
<l>Under a cloudy sky, while the moon launches</l>
<l>Scattered beams of light along the dark silences?</l>
<l>I will be a ghost there, though I yet am breathing,</l>
<l>A living presence still in tight cottage walls,</l>
<l>Sitting by the fire whose smoke goes wreathing</l>
<l>Over fields and farmyards and farmyard stalls.</l>
<l>As a player going to rehearse his faring,</l>
<l>I will be my ghost there before my bones are dust,</l>
<l>Bid it learn betimes the sock it shall be wearing</l>
<l>When it bids the clay good-bye as all ghosts must.</l>
<l>Hush, then; upstairs sleep my lady and her mother;</l>
<l>The cat curls the night away, and will not stir;</l>
<l>Beams of lamp and beech-log cross one another,</l>
<l>No wind walks in the garden there.</l>
<l>Go my ghost, it calls you, the high road, the winding,</l>
<l>Written by the moonlight on the sleeping hill;</l>
<l>I will watch the ashes, you go finding</l>
<l>The way you shall walk for generations still.</l>
<l>The window-latch is firm, the curtain does not tremble,</l>
<l>The wet grass bends not under your tread,</l>
<l>Brushing you shake not the dew from the bramble,</l>
<l>They hear no gate who lie abed.</l>
<l>Nodding I stare at the hearth, but I see you,</l>
<l>My half-wit travels with you the road;</l>
<l>There shall be your kingdom when death shall free you,</l>
<l>When body's wit is neither leash nor goad.</l>
<l>Past the peacock branches proudly gliding,</l>
<l>Your own ghost now, I know, I know,</l>
<l>You look to the moon on the hill-top riding,</l>
<l>The mares in the meadow sleep as you go.</l>
<l>Your eyes that are dark yet great for divining</l>
<l>Brood on the valleys of wood and plough,</l>
<l>
<pb n="669"/>
</l>
<l>And you stand where the silver flower is shining</l>
<l>Of cherry against the black holly bough.</l>
<l>Rehearse, O rehearse, as you pass by the hedgerows,</l>
<l>Remembrance of all that was my bright will,</l>
<l>That so my grave of whispers and echoes</l>
<l>May rest for the ghost that is yet on the hill.</l>
<l>The primroses burn and the cowslips cover</l>
<l>The starry meadows as heaven is clad,</l>
<l>Learn them all, O ghost, as a lover,</l>
<l>So shall your coming again be glad.</l>
<l>The inn-sign hangs in the windless watches,</l>
<l>You pass the shadowy piles of stone</l>
<l>Under the walls where the hawthorn catches</l>
<l>Shapes from the moon that are not its own.</l>
<l>Wander, wander down by the cresses,</l>
<l>Over the crest of the hill, between</l>
<l>The brown lych-gate and the cider presses,</l>
<l>Past the well and across the green.</l>
<l>Heed me my ghost, my heir. To-morrow,</l>
<l>Or soon, my body to ash must fall,</l>
<l>Heed me, my ghost, my heir. To-morrow,</l>
<l>Heed me, ghost, and I shall not sorrow&mdash;</l>
<l>Learn this beauty, O learn it all.</l>
<l>Night goes on, the beech-log's ended,</l>
<l>Half-wit's drowsy, and doctrine done,&mdash;</l>
<l>Ghost, come home from the road; befriended</l>
<l>My moon shall be when I leave the sun.</l>
</lg>

                         <signed>JOHN DRINKWATER.</signed>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
