<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DubFree"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="DubFree">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Freedmen's Bureau</title>
<title type="sort">freedmens bureau</title>
<author>Du Bois, W. E. Burghardt</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">46</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">DubFree</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475897</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Freedmen's Bureau</title>
<title type="sort">freedmens bureau</title>
<author>W. E. Burghardt Du Bois</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1901">1901</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 87</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 354-365</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1901">1901</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term>
<term>democracy</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction; prose</term>
<term>African American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-08">August 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>minimal TEI tagging</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="article" id="d3">
<head>Du Bois, W. E. Burghardt.  "The Freedmen's Bureau."  <hi rend="italic">Atlantic
Monthly</hi> 87 (1901): 354-365.</head>

<pb n="354"/>

<p>THE problem of the twentieth century is the problem of the
color line; the relation of the darker to the lighter races of men
in Asia and Africa, in America and the islands of the sea.  It was
a phase of this problem that caused the Civil War; and however much
they who marched south and north in 1861 may have fixed on the
technical points of union and local autonomy as a shibboleth, all
nevertheless knew, as we know, that the question of Negro slavery
was the deeper cause of the conflict.  Curious it was, too, how
this deeper question ever forced itself to the surface, despite
effort and disclaimer.  No sooner had Northern armies touched
Southern soil than this old question, newly guised, sprang from the
earth, &mdash; What shall be done with slaves?  Peremptory military
commands, this way and that, could not answer the query; the
Emancipation Proclamation seemed but to broaden and intensify the
difficulties; and so at last there arose in the South a government
of men called the Freedmen's Bureau, which lasted, legally, from
1865 to 1872, but in a sense from 1861 to 1876, and which sought to
settle the Negro problems in the United States of America.
</p><p>It is the aim of this essay to study the Freedmen's Bureau, &mdash;
the occasion of its rise, the character of its work, and its final
success and failure, &mdash; not only as a part of American history, but
above all as one of the most singular and interesting of the
attempts made by a great nation to grapple with vast problems of
race and social condition.
</p><p>No sooner had the armies, east and west, penetrated Virginia
and Tennessee than fugitive slaves appeared within their lines.
They came at night, when the flickering camp fires of the blue
hosts shone like vast unsteady stars along the black horizon: old
men, and thin, with gray and tufted hair; women with frightened
eyes, dragging whimpering, hungry children; men and girls, stalwart
and gaunt, &mdash; a horde of starving vagabonds, homeless, helpless, and
pitiable in their dark distress.  Two methods of treating these
newcomers seemed equally logical to opposite sorts of minds.  Said
some, "We have nothing to do with slaves."  "Hereafter," commanded
Halleck, "no slaves should be allowed to come into your lines at
all; if any come without your knowledge, when owners call for them,
deliver them."  But others said, "We take grain and fowl; why not
slaves?"  Whereupon Fremont, as early as August, 1861, declared the
slaves of Missouri rebels free.  Such radical action was quickly
countermanded, but at the same time the opposite policy could not
be enforced; some of the black refugees declared themselves
freemen, others showed their masters had deserted them, and still
others were captured with forts and plantations.  Evidently, too,
slaves were a source of strength to the Confederacy, and were being
used as laborers and producers.  "They constitute a military
resource," wrote the Secretary of War, late in 1861; "and being
such, that they should not be turned over to the enemy is too plain
to discuss."  So the tone of the army chiefs changed, Congress
forbade the rendition of fugitives, and Butler's "contrabands" were
welcomed as military laborers.  This complicated rather than solved
the problem; for now the scattering fugitives became a steady
stream, which flowed faster as the armies marched.
</p><p>Then the long-headed man, with care-chiseled face, who sat in
the White House, saw the inevitable, and emancipated the slaves of
rebels on New Year's, 1863.  A month later Congress called
earnestly for the Negro soldiers whom
<pb n="355"/>
the act of July,
1862, had half grudgingly allowed to enlist.  Thus the barriers
were leveled, and the deed was done.  The stream of fugitives
swelled to a flood, and anxious officers kept inquiring: "What must
be done with slaves arriving almost daily?  Am I to find food and
shelter for women and children?"
</p><p>It was a Pierce of Boston who pointed out the way, and thus
became in a sense the founder of the Freedmen's Bureau.  Being
specially detailed from the ranks to care for the freedmen at
Fortress Monroe, he afterward founded the celebrated Port Royal
experiment and started the Freedmen's Aid Societies.  Thus, under
the timid Treasury officials and bold army officers, Pierce's plan
widened and developed.  At first, the able-bodied men were enlisted
as soldiers or hired as laborers, the women and children were
herded into central camps under guard, and "superintendents of
contrabands" multiplied here and there.  Centres of massed freedmen
arose at Fortress Monroe, Va., Washington, D. C., Beaufort and Port
Royal, S. C., New Orleans, La., Vicksburg and Corinth, Miss.,
Columbus, Ky., Cairo, Ill., and elsewhere, and the army chaplains
found here new and fruitful fields.
</p><p>Then came the Freedmen's Aid Societies, born of the touching
appeals for relief and help from these centres of distress.  There
was the American Missionary Association, sprung from the <hi rend="italic">
Amistad</hi>, and now full grown for work, the various church
organizations, the National Freedmen's Relief Association, the
American Freedmen's Union, the Western Freedmen's Aid Commission, &mdash;
in all fifty or more active organizations, which sent clothes,
money, school-books, and teachers southward.  All they did was
needed, for the destitution of the freedmen was often reported as
"too appalling for belief," and the situation was growing daily
worse rather than better.
</p><p>And daily, too, it seemed more plain that this was no ordinary
matter of temporary relief, but a national crisis; for here loomed
a labor problem of vast dimensions.  Masses of Negroes stood idle,
or, if they worked spasmodically, were never sure of pay; and if
perchance they received pay, squandered the new thing
thoughtlessly.  In these and in other ways were camp life and the
new liberty demoralizing the freedmen.  The broader economic
organization thus clearly demanded sprang up here and there as
accident and local conditions determined.  Here again Pierce's Port
Royal plan of leased plantations and guided workmen pointed out the
rough way.  In Washington, the military governor, at the urgent
appeal of the superintendent, opened confiscated estates to the
cultivation of the fugitives, and there in the shadow of the dome
gathered black farm villages.  General Dix gave over estates to the
freedmen of Fortress Monroe, and so on through the South.  The
government and the benevolent societies furnished the means of
cultivation, and the Negro turned again slowly to work.  The
systems of control, thus started, rapidly grew, here and there,
into strange little governments, like that of General Banks in
Louisiana, with its 90,000 black subjects, its 50,000 guided
laborers, and its annual budget of $100,000 and more.  It made out
4000 pay rolls, registered all freedmen, inquired into grievances
and redressed them, laid and collected taxes, and established a
system of public schools.  So too Colonel Eaton, the superintendent
of Tennessee and Arkansas, ruled over 100,000, leased and
cultivated 7000 acres of cotton land, and furnished food for 10,000
paupers.  In South Carolina was General Saxton, with his deep
interest in black folk.  He succeeded Pierce and the Treasury
officials, and sold forfeited estates, leased abandoned
plantations, encouraged schools, and received from Sherman, after
the terribly picturesque march to the sea, thousands of the
wretched camp followers.
<pb n="356"/>
</p><p>Three characteristic things one might have seen in Sherman's
raid through Georgia, which threw the new situation in deep and
shadowy relief: the Conqueror, the Conquered, and the Negro.  Some
see all significance in the grim front of the destroyer, and some
in the bitter sufferers of the lost cause.  But to me neither
soldier nor fugitive speaks with so deep a meaning as that dark and
human cloud that clung like remorse on the rear of those swift
columns, swelling at times to half their size, almost engulfing and
choking them.  In vain were they ordered back, in vain were bridges
hewn from beneath their feet; on they trudged and writhed and
surged, until they rolled into Savannah, a starved and naked horde
of tens of thousands.  There too came the characteristic military
remedy: "The islands from Charleston south, the abandoned
ricefields along the rivers for thirty miles back from the sea, and
the country bordering the St. John's River, Florida, are reserved
and set apart for the settlement of Negroes now made free by act of
war."  So read the celebrated field order.
</p><p>All these experiments, orders, and systems were bound to
attract and perplex the government and the nation.  Directly after
the Emancipation Proclamation, Representative Eliot had introduced
a bill creating a Bureau of Emancipation, but it was never
reported.  The following June, a committee of inquiry, appointed by
the Secretary of War, reported in favor of a temporary bureau for
the "improvement, protection, and employment of refugee freedmen,"
on much the same lines as were afterward followed.  Petitions came
in to President Lincoln from distinguished citizens and
organizations, strongly urging a comprehensive and unified plan of
dealing with the freedmen, under a bureau which should be "charged
with the study of plans and execution of measures for easily
guiding, and in every way judiciously and humanely aiding, the
passage of our emancipated and yet to be emancipated blacks from
the old condition of forced labor to their new state of voluntary
industry."
</p><p>Some half-hearted steps were early taken by the government to
put both freedmen and abandoned estates under the supervision of
the Treasury officials.  Laws of 1863 and 1864 directed them to
take charge of and lease abandoned lands for periods not exceeding
twelve months, and to "provide in such leases or otherwise for the
employment and general welfare" of the freedmen.  Most of the army
officers looked upon this as a welcome relief from perplexing
"Negro affairs;" but the Treasury hesitated and blundered, and
although it leased large quantities of land and employed many
Negroes, especially along the Mississippi, yet it left the virtual
control of the laborers and their relations to their neighbors in
the hands of the army.
</p><p>In March, 1864, Congress at last turned its attention to the
subject, and the House passed a bill, by a majority of two,
establishing a Bureau for Freedmen in the War Department.  Senator
Sumner, who had charge of the bill in the Senate, argued that
freedmen and abandoned lands ought to be under the same department,
and reported a substitute for the House bill, attaching the Bureau
to the Treasury Department.  This bill passed, but too late for
action in the House.  The debate wandered over the whole policy of
the administration and the general question of slavery, without
touching very closely the specific merits of the measure in hand.
</p><p>Meantime the election took place, and the administration,
returning from the country with a vote of renewed confidence,
addressed itself to the matter more seriously.  A conference
between the houses agreed upon a carefully drawn measure which
contained the chief provisions of Charles Sumner's bill, but made
the proposed organization a department independent of both the War
<pb n="357"/>
and Treasury officials.  The bill was conservative, giving
the new department "general superintendence of all freedmen."  It
was to "establish regulations" for them, protect them, lease them
lands, adjust their wages, and appear in civil and military courts
as their "next friend."  There were many limitations attached to
the powers thus granted, and the organization was made permanent.
Nevertheless, the Senate defeated the bill, and a new conference
committee was appointed.  This committee reported a new bill,
February 28, which was whirled through just as the session closed,
and which became the act of 1865 establishing in the War Department
a "Bureau of Refugees, Freedmen, and Abandoned Lands."
</p><p>This last compromise was a hasty bit of legislation, vague and
uncertain in outline.  A Bureau was created, "to continue during
the present War of Rebellion, and for one year thereafter," to
which was given "the supervision and management of all abandoned
lands, and the control of all subjects relating to refugees and
freedmen," under "such rules and regulations as may be presented by
the head of the Bureau and approved by the President."  A
commissioner, appointed by the President and Senate, was to control
the Bureau, with an office force not exceeding ten clerks.  The
President might also appoint commissioners in the seceded states,
and to all these offices military officials might be detailed at
regular pay.  The Secretary of War could issue rations, clothing,
and fuel to the destitute, and all abandoned property was placed in
the hands of the Bureau for eventual lease and sale to ex-slaves in
forty-acre parcels.
</p><p>Thus did the United States government definitely assume charge
of the emancipated Negro as the ward of the nation.  It was a
tremendous undertaking.  Here, at a stroke of the pen, was erected
a government of millions of men, &mdash; and not ordinary men, either, but
black men emasculated by a peculiarly complete system of slavery,
centuries old; and now, suddenly, violently, they come into a new
birthright, at a time of war and passion, in the midst of the
stricken, embittered population of their former masters.  Any man
might well have hesitated to assume charge of such a work, with
vast responsibilities, indefinite powers, and limited resources.
Probably no one but a soldier would have answered such a call
promptly; and indeed no one but a soldier could be called, for
Congress had appropriated no money for salaries and expenses.
</p><p>Less than a month after the weary emancipator passed to his
rest, his successor assigned Major General Oliver O. Howard to duty
as commissioner of the new Bureau.  He was a Maine man, then only
thirty-five years of age.  He had marched with Sherman to the sea,
had fought well at Gettysburg, and had but a year before been
assigned to the command of the Department of Tennessee.  An honest
and sincere men, with rather too much faith in human nature, little
aptitude for systematic business and intricate detail, he was
nevertheless conservative, hard-working, and, above all, acquainted
at first-hand with much of the work before him.  And of that work
it has been truly said, "No approximately correct history of
civilization can ever be written which does not throw out in bold
relief, as one of the great landmarks of political and social
progress, the organization and administration of the Freedmen's
Bureau."
</p><p>On May 12, 1865, Howard was appointed, and he assumed the
duties of his office promptly on the 15th, and began examining the
field of work.  A curious mess he looked upon: little despotisms,
communistic experiments, slavery, peonage, business speculations,
organized charity, unorganized almsgiving, &mdash; all reeling on under
the guise of helping the freedman, and all enshrined in the
<pb n="358"/>
smoke and blood of war and the cursing and silence of angry men.
On May 19 the new government &mdash; for a government it really was &mdash;
issued its constitution; commissioners were to be appointed in each
of the seceded states, who were to take charge of "all subjects
relating to refugees and freedmen," and all relief and rations were
to be given by their consent alone.  The Bureau invited continued
cooperation with benevolent societies, and declared, "It will be
the object of all commissioners to introduce practicable systems of
compensated labor," and to establish schools.  Forthwith nine
assistant commissioners were appointed.  They were to hasten to
their fields of work; seek gradually to close relief
establishments, and make the destitute self-supporting; act as
courts of law where there were no courts, or where Negroes were not
recognized in them as free; establish the institution of marriage
among ex-slaves, and keep records; see that freedmen were free to
choose their employers, and help in making fair contracts for them;
and finally, the circular said, "Simple good faith, for which we
hope on all hands for those concerned in the passing away of
slavery, will especially relieve the assistant commissioners in the
discharge of their duties toward the freedmen, as well as promote
the general welfare."
</p><p>No sooner was the work thus started, and the general system
and local organization in some measure begun, than two grave
difficulties appeared which changed largely the theory and outcome
of Bureau work.  First, there were the abandoned lands of the
South.  It had long been the more or less definitely expressed
theory of the North that all the chief problems of emancipation
might be settled by establishing the slaves on the forfeited lands
of their masters, &mdash; a sort of poetic justice, said some.  But this
poetry done into solemn prose meant either wholesale confiscation
of private property in the South, or vast appropriations.  Now
Congress had not appropriated a cent, and no sooner did the
proclamations of general amnesty appear than the 800,000 acres of
abandoned lands in the hands of the Freedmen's Bureau melted
quickly away.  The second difficulty lay in perfecting the local
organization of the Bureau throughout the wide field of work.
Making a new machine and sending out officials of duly ascertained
fitness for a great work of social reform is no child's task; but
this task was even harder, for a new central organization had to be
fitted on a heterogeneous and confused but already existing system
of relief and control of ex-slaves; and the agents available for
this work must be sought for in an army still busy with war
operations, &mdash; men in the very nature of the case ill fitted for
delicate social work, &mdash; or among the questionable camp followers of
an invading host.  Thus, after a year's work, vigorously as it was
pushed, the problem looked even more difficult to grasp and solve
than at the beginning.  Nevertheless, three things that year's work
did, well worth the doing: it relieved a vast amount of physical
suffering; it transported 7000 fugitives from congested centres
back to the farm; and, best of all, it inaugurated the crusade of
the New England schoolma'am.
</p><p>The annals of this Ninth Crusade are yet to be written, the
tale of a mission that seemed to our age far more quixotic than the
quest of St. Louis seemed to his.  Behind the mists of ruin and
rapine waved the calico dresses of women who dared, and after the
hoarse mouthings of the field guns rang the rhythm of the alphabet.
Rich and poor they were, serious and curious.  Bereaved now of a
father, now of a brother, now of more than these, they came seeking
a life work in planting New England schoolhouses among the white
and black of the South.  They did their work well.  In that first
year they taught 100,000 souls, and more.
<pb n="359"/>
</p><p>Evidently, Congress must soon legislate again on the hastily
organized Bureau, which had so quickly grown into wide significance
and vast possibilities.  An institution such as that was well-nigh
as difficult to end as to begin.  Early in 1866 Congress took up
the matter, when Senator Trumbull, of Illinois, introduced a bill
to extend the Bureau and enlarge its powers.  This measure
received, at the hands of Congress, far more thorough discussion
and attention than its predecessor.  The war cloud had thinned
enough to allow a clearer conception of the work of emancipation.
The champions of the bill argued that the strengthening of the
Freedmen's Bureau was still a military necessity; that it was
needed for the proper carrying out of the Thirteenth Amendment, and
was a work of sheer justice to the ex-slave, at a trifling cost to
the government.  The opponents of the measure declared that the war
was over, and the necessity for war measures past; that the Bureau,
by reason of its extraordinary powers, was clearly unconstitutional
in time of peace, and was destined to irritate the South and
pauperize the freedmen, at a final cost of possibly hundreds of
millions.  Two of these arguments were unanswered, and indeed
unanswerable: the one that the extraordinary powers of the Bureau
threatened the civil rights of all citizens; and the other that the
government must have power to do what manifestly must be done, and
that present abandonment of the freedmen meant their practical
enslavement.  The bill which finally passed enlarged and made
permanent the Freedmen's Bureau.  It was promptly vetoed by
President Johnson, as "unconstitutional," "unnecessary," and
"extrajudicial," and failed of passage over the veto.  Meantime,
however, the breach between Congress and the President began to
broaden, and a modified form of the lost bill was finally passed
over the President's second veto, July 16.
</p><p>The act of 1866 gave the Freedmen's Bureau its final form, &mdash;
the form by which it will be known to posterity and judged of men.
It extended the existence of the Bureau to July, 1868; it
authorized additional assistant commissioners, the retention of
army officers mustered out of regular service, the sale of certain
forfeited lands to freedmen on nominal terms, the sale of
Confederate public property for Negro schools, and a wider field of
judicial interpretation and cognizance.  The government of the un-reconstructed South was thus put very largely in the hands of the
Freedmen's Bureau, especially as in many cases the departmental
military commander was now made also assistant commissioner.  It
was thus that the Freedmen's Bureau became a full-fledged
government of men.  It made laws, executed them and interpreted
them; it laid and collected taxes, defined and punished crime,
maintained and used military force, and dictated such measures as
it thought necessary and proper for the accomplishment of its
varied ends.  Naturally, all these powers were not exercised
continuously nor to their fullest extent; and yet, as General
Howard has said, "scarcely any subject that has to be legislated
upon in civil society failed, at one time or another, to demand the
action of this singular Bureau."
</p><p>To understand and criticise intelligently so vast a work, one
must not forget an instant the drift of things in the later
sixties: Lee had surrendered, Lincoln was dead, and Johnson and
Congress were at loggerheads; the Thirteenth Amendment was adopted,
the Fourteenth pending, and the Fifteenth declared in force in
1870.  Guerrilla raiding, the ever present flickering after-flame
of war, was spending its force against the Negroes, and all the
Southern land was awakening as from some wild dream to poverty and
social revolution.  In a time of perfect calm, amid willing
neighbors and streaming wealth, the
<pb n="360"/>
social uplifting of
4,000,000 slaves to an assured and self-sustaining place in the
body politic and economic would have been an herculean task; but
when to the inherent difficulties of so delicate and nice a social
operation were added the spite and hate of conflict, the Hell of
War; when suspicion and cruelty were rife, and gaunt Hunger wept
beside Bereavement, &mdash; in such a case, the work of any instrument of
social regeneration was in large part foredoomed to failure.  The
very name of the Bureau stood for a thing in the South which for
two centuries and better men had refused even to argue, &mdash; that life
amid free Negroes was simply unthinkable, the maddest of
experiments.  The agents which the Bureau could command varied all
the way from unselfish philanthropists to narrow-minded busybodies
and thieves; and even though it be true that the average was far
better than the worst, it was the one fly that helped to spoil the
ointment.  Then, amid all this crouched the freed slave, bewildered
between friend and foe.  He had emerged from slavery: not the worst
slavery in the world, not a slavery that made all life unbearable, &mdash;
rather, a slavery that had here and there much of kindliness,
fidelity, and happiness, &mdash; but withal slavery, which, so far as
human aspiration and desert were concerned, classed the black man
and the ox together.  And the Negro knew full well that, whatever
their deeper convictions may have been, Southern men had fought
with desperate energy to perpetuate this slavery, under which the
black masses, with half-articulate thought, had writhed and
shivered.  They welcomed freedom with a cry.  They fled to the
friends that had freed them.  They shrank from the master who still
strove for their chains.  So the cleft between the white and black
South grew.  Idle to say it never should have been; it was as
inevitable as its results were pitiable.  Curiously incongruous
elements were left arrayed against each other: the North, the
government, the carpetbagger, and the slave, here; and there, all
the South that was white, whether gentleman or vagabond, honest man
or rascal, lawless murderer or martyr to duty.
</p><p>Thus it is doubly difficult to write of this period calmly, so
intense was the feeling, so mighty the human passions, that swayed
and blinded men.  Amid it all two figures ever stand to typify that
day to coming men: the one a gray-haired gentleman, whose fathers
had quit themselves like men, whose sons lay in nameless graves,
who bowed to the evil of slavery because its abolition boded untold
ill to all; who stood at last, in the evening of life, a blighted,
ruined form, with hate in his eyes.  And the other, a form hovering
dark and mother-like, her awful face black with the mists of
centuries, had aforetime bent in love over her white master's
cradle, rocked his sons and daughters to sleep, and closed in death
the sunken eyes of his wife to the world; ay, too, had laid herself
low to his lust and borne a tawny man child to the world, only to
see her dark boy's limbs scattered to the winds by midnight
marauders riding after Damned Niggers.  These were the saddest
sights of that woeful day; and no man clasped the hands of these
two passing figures of the present-past; but hating they went to
their long home, and hating their children's children live to-day.
</p><p>Here, then, was the field of work for the Freedmen's Bureau;
and since, with some hesitation, it was continued by the act of
1868 till 1869, let us look upon four years of its work as a whole.
There were, in 1868, 900 Bureau officials scattered from Washington
to Texas, ruling, directly and indirectly, many millions of men.
And the deeds of these rulers fall mainly under seven heads, &mdash; the
relief of physical suffering, the overseeing of the beginnings of
free labor, the buying and selling of land, the establishment of
schools, the paying of bounties, the administration
<pb n="361"/>
of
justice, and the financiering of all these activities.  Up to June,
1869, over half a million patients had been treated by Bureau
physicians and surgeons, and sixty hospitals and asylums had been
in operation.  In fifty months of work 21,000,000 free rations were
distributed at a cost of over $4,000,000, &mdash; beginning at the rate of
30,000 rations a day in 1865, and discontinuing in 1869.  Next came
the difficult question of labor.  First, 30,000 black men were
transported from the refuges and relief stations back to the farms,
back to the critical trial of a new way of working.  Plain, simple
instructions went out from Washington, &mdash; the freedom of laborers to
choose employers, no fixed rates of wages, no peonage or forced
labor.  So far so good; but where local agents differed <hi rend="italic">toto
coelo</hi> in capacity and character, where the personnel was
continually changing, the outcome was varied.  The largest element
of success lay in the fact that the majority of the freedmen were
willing, often eager, to work.  So contracts were written, &mdash; 50,000
in a single state, &mdash; laborers advised, wages guaranteed, and
employers supplied.  In truth, the organization became a vast labor
bureau; not perfect, indeed, &mdash; notably defective here and there, &mdash;
but on the whole, considering the situation, successful beyond the
dreams of thoughtful men.  The two great obstacles which confronted
the officers at every turn were the tyrant and the idler: the
slaveholder, who believed slavery was right, and was determined to
perpetuate it under another name; and the freedman, who regarded
freedom as perpetual rest.  These were the Devil and the Deep Sea.
</p><p>In the work of establishing the Negroes as peasant proprietors
the Bureau was severely handicapped, as I have shown.
Nevertheless, something was done.  Abandoned lands were leased so
long as they remained in the hands of the Bureau, and a total
revenue of $400,000 derived from black tenants.  Some other lands
to which the nation had gained title were sold, and public lands
were opened for the settlement of the few blacks who had tools and
capital.  The vision of landowning, however, the righteous and
reasonable ambition for forty acres and a mule which filled the
freedmen's dreams, was doomed in most cases to disappointment.  And
those men of marvelous hind-sight, who to-day are seeking to preach
the Negro back to the soil, know well, or ought to know, that it
was here, in 1865, that the finest opportunity of binding the black
peasant to the soil was lost.  Yet, with help and striving, the
Negro gained some land, and by 1874, in the one state of Georgia,
owned near 350,000 acres.
</p><p>The greatest success of the Freedmen's Bureau lay in the
planting of the free school among Negroes, and the idea of free
elementary education among all classes in the South.  It not only
called the schoolmistress through the benevolent agencies, and
built them schoolhouses, but it helped discover and support such
apostles of human development as Edmund Ware, Erastus Cravath, and
Samuel Armstrong.  State superintendents of education were
appointed, and by 1870 150,000 children were in school.  The
opposition to Negro education was bitter in the South, for the
South believed an educated Negro to be a dangerous Negro.  And the
South was not wholly wrong; for education among all kinds of men
always has had, and always will have, an element of danger and
revolution, of dissatisfaction and discontent.  Nevertheless, men
strive to know.  It was some inkling of this paradox, even in the
unquiet days of the Bureau, that allayed an opposition to human
training, which still to-day lies smouldering, but not flaming.
Fisk, Atlanta, Howard, and Hampton were founded in these days, and
nearly $6,000,000 was expended in five years for educational work,
$750,000 of which came from the freedmen themselves.
<pb n="362"/>
</p><p>Such contributions, together with the buying of land and
various other enterprises, showed that the ex-slave was handling
some free capital already.  The chief initial source of this was
labor in the army, and his pay and bounty as a soldier.  Payments
to Negro soldiers were at first complicated by the ignorance of the
recipients, and the fact that the quotas of colored regiments from
Northern states were largely filled by recruits from the South,
unknown to their fellow soldiers.  Consequently, payments were
accompanied by such frauds that Congress, by joint resolution in
1867, put the whole matter in the hands of the Freedmen's Bureau.
In two years $6,000,000 was thus distributed to 5000 claimants, and
in the end the sum exceeded $8,000,000.  Even in this system, fraud
was frequent; but still the work put needed capital in the hands of
practical paupers, and some, at least, was well spent.
</p><p>The most perplexing and least successful part of the Bureau's
work lay in the exercise of its judicial functions.  In a
distracted land where slavery had hardly fallen, to keep the strong
from wanton abuse of the weak, and the weak from gloating
insolently over the half-shorn strength of the strong, was a
thankless, hopeless task.  The former masters of the land were
peremptorily ordered about, seized and imprisoned, and punished
over and again, with scant courtesy from army officers.  The former
slaves were intimidated, beaten, raped, and butchered by angry and
revengeful men.  Bureau courts tended to become centres simply for
punishing whites, while the regular civil courts tended to become
solely institutions for perpetuating the slavery of blacks.  Almost
every law and method ingenuity could devise was employed by the
legislatures to reduce the Negroes to serfdom, &mdash; to make them the
slaves of the state, if not of individual owners; while the Bureau
officials too often were found striving to put the "bottom rail on
top," and give the freedmen a power and independence which they
could not yet use.  It is all well enough for us of another
generation to wax wise with advice to those who bore the burden in
the heat of the day.  It is full easy now to see that the man who
lost home, fortune, and family at a stroke, and saw his land ruled
by "mules and niggers," was really benefited by the passing of
slavery.  It is not difficult now to say to the young freedman,
cheated and cuffed about, who has seen his father's head beaten to
a jelly and his own mother namelessly assaulted, that the meek
shall inherit the earth.  Above all, nothing is more convenient
than to heap on the Freedmen's Bureau all the evils of that evil
day, and damn it utterly for every mistake and blunder that was
made.
</p><p>All this is easy, but it is neither sensible nor just.  Some
one had blundered, but that was long before Oliver Howard was born;
there was criminal aggression and heedless neglect, but without
some system of control there would have been far more than there
was.  Had that control been from within, the Negro would have been
reenslaved, to all intents and purposes.  Coming as the control did
from without, perfect men and methods would have bettered all
things; and even with imperfect agents and questionable methods,
the work accomplished was not undeserving of much commendation.
The regular Bureau court consisted of one representative of the
employer, one of the Negro, and one of the Bureau.  If the Bureau
could have maintained a perfectly judicial attitude, this
arrangement would have been ideal, and must in time have gained
confidence; but the nature of its other activities and the
character of its personnel prejudiced the Bureau in favor of the
black litigants, and led without doubt to much injustice and
annoyance.  On the other hand, to leave the Negro in the hands of
Southern courts was impossible.
<pb n="363"/>
</p><p>What the Freedmen's Bureau cost the nation is difficult to
determine accurately.  Its methods of bookkeeping were not good,
and the whole system of its work and records partook of the hurry
and turmoil of the time.  General Howard himself disbursed some
$15,000,000 during his incumbency; but this includes the bounties
paid colored soldiers, which perhaps should not be counted as an
expense of the Bureau.  In bounties, prize money, and all other
expenses, the Bureau disbursed over $20,000,000 before all of its
departments were finally closed.  To this ought to be added the
large expenses of the various departments of Negro affairs before
1865; but these are hardly extricable from war expenditures, nor
can we estimate with any accuracy the contributions of benevolent
societies during all these years.

</p><p>Such was the work of the Freedmen's Bureau.  To sum it up in
brief, we may say: it set going a system of free labor; it
established the black peasant proprietor; it secured the
recognition of black freemen before courts of law; it founded the
free public school in the South.  On the other hand, it failed to
establish good will between ex-masters and freedmen; to guard its
work wholly from paternalistic methods that discouraged self-reliance; to make Negroes landholders in any considerable numbers.
Its successes were the result of hard work, supplemented by the aid
of philanthropists and the eager striving of black men.  Its
failures were the result of bad local agents, inherent difficulties
of the work, and national neglect.  The Freedmen's Bureau expired
by limitation in 1869, save its educational and bounty departments.
The educational work came to an end in 1872, and General Howard's
connection with the Bureau ceased at that time.  The work of paying
bounties was transferred to the adjutant general's office, where it
was continued three or four years longer.
</p><p>Such an institution, from its wide powers, great
responsibilities, large control of moneys, and generally
conspicuous position, was naturally open to repeated and bitter
attacks.  It sustained a searching congressional investigation at
the instance of Fernando Wood in 1870.  It was, with blunt
discourtesy, transferred from Howard's control, in his absence, to
the supervision of Secretary of War Belknap in 1872, on the
Secretary's recommendation.  Finally, in consequence of grave
intimations of wrongdoing made by the Secretary and his
subordinates, General Howard was court-martialed in 1874.  In each
of these trials, and in other attacks, the commissioner of the
Freedmen's Bureau was exonerated from any willful misdoing, and his
work heartily commended.  Nevertheless, many unpleasant things were
brought to light: the methods of transacting the business of the
Bureau were faulty; several cases of defalcation among officials in
the field were proven, and further frauds hinted at; there were
some business transactions which savored of dangerous speculation,
if not dishonesty; and, above all, the smirch of the Freedmen's
Bank, which, while legally distinct from, was morally and
practically a part of the Bureau, will ever blacken the record of
this great institution.  Not even ten additional years of slavery
could have done as much to throttle the thrift of the freedmen as
the mismanagement and bankruptcy of the savings bank chartered by
the nation for their especial aid.  Yet it is but fair to say that
the perfect honesty of purpose and unselfish devotion of General
Howard have passed untarnished through the fire of criticism.  Not
so with all his subordinates, although in the case of the great
majority of these there were shown bravery and devotion to duty,
even though sometimes linked to narrowness and incompetency.
</p><p>The most bitter attacks on the Freedmen's Bureau were aimed
not so much at its conduct or policy under the law as
<pb n="364"/>
at
the necessity for any such organization at all.  Such attacks came
naturally from the border states and the South, and they were
summed up by Senator Davis, of Kentucky, when he moved to entitle
the act of 1866 a bill "to promote strife and conflict between the
white and black races . . . by a grant of unconstitutional power."
The argument was of tremendous strength, but its very strength was
its weakness.  For, argued the plain common sense of the nation, if
it is unconstitutional, unpracticable, and futile for the nation to
stand guardian over its helpless wards, then there is left but one
alternative: to make those wards their own guardians by arming them
with the ballot.  The alternative offered the nation then was not
between full and restricted Negro suffrage; else every sensible
man, black and white, would easily have chosen the latter.  It was
rather a choice between suffrage and slavery, after endless blood
and gold had flowed to sweep human bondage away.  Not a single
Southern legislature stood ready to admit a Negro, under any
conditions, to the polls; not a single Southern legislature
believed free Negro labor was possible without a system of
restrictions that took all its freedom away; there was scarcely a
white man in the South who did not honestly regard emancipation as
a crime, and its practical nullification as a duty.  In such a
situation, the granting of the ballot to the black man was a
necessity, the very least a guilty nation could grant a wronged
race.  Had the opposition to government guardianship of Negroes
been less bitter, and the attachment to the slave system less
strong, the social seer can well imagine a far better policy: a
permanent Freedmen's Bureau, with a national system of Negro
schools; a carefully supervised employment and labor office; a
system of impartial protection before the regular courts; and such
institutions for social betterment as savings banks, land and
building associations, and social settlements.  All this vast
expenditure of money and brains might have formed a great school of
prospective citizenship, and solved in a way we have not yet solved
the most perplexing and persistent of the Negro problems.
</p><p>That such an institution was unthinkable in 1870 was due in
part to certain acts of the Freedmen's Bureau itself.  It came to
regard its work as merely temporary, and Negro suffrage as a final
answer to all present perplexities.  The political ambition of many
of its agents and proteges led it far afield into questionable
activities, until the South, nursing its own deep prejudices, came
easily to ignore all the good deeds of the Bureau, and hate its
very name with perfect hatred.  So the Freedmen's Bureau died, and
its child was the Fifteenth Amendment.
</p><p>The passing of a great human institution before its work is
done, like the untimely passing of a single soul, but leaves a
legacy of striving for other men.  The legacy of the Freedmen's
Bureau is the heavy heritage of this generation.  Today, when new
and vaster problems are destined to strain every fibre of the
national mind and soul, would it not be well to count this legacy
honestly and carefully?  For this much all men know: despite
compromise, struggle, war, and struggle, the Negro is not free.  In
the backwoods of the Gulf states, for miles and miles, he may not
leave the plantation of his birth; in well-nigh the whole rural
South the black farmers are peons, bound by law and custom to an
economic slavery, from which the only escape is death or the
penitentiary.  In the most cultured sections and cities of the
South the Negroes are a segregated servile caste, with restricted
rights and privileges.  Before the courts, both in law and custom,
they stand on a different and peculiar basis.  Taxation without
representation is the rule of their political life.  And the result
of all this is, and in nature must have been, lawlessness and
<pb n="365"/>
crime.  That is the large legacy of the Freedmen's Bureau, the
work it did not do because it could not.

</p><p>I have seen a land right merry with the sun; where children
sing, and rolling hills lie like passioned women, wanton with
harvest.  And there in the King's Highway sat and sits a figure,
veiled and bowed, by which the traveler's footsteps hasten as they
go.  On the tainted air broods fear.  Three centuries' thought has
been the raising and unveiling of that bowed human heart, and now,
behold, my fellows, a century new for the duty and the deed.  The
problem of the twentieth century is the problem of the color line.
</p>
<signed>                              <hi rend="italic">W. E. Burghardt Du Bois.</hi>
</signed>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
