<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DubStri"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="DubStri">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Strivings of the Negro People</title>
<title type="sort">strivings of the negro people</title>
<author>Du Bois, W. E. Burghardt</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">19</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">DubStri</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475899</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Strivings of the Negro People</title>
<title type="sort">strivings of the negro people</title>
<author>W. E. Burghardt Du Bois</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1897">1897</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 80</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 194-198</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1897">1897</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>CORD</term>
<term>democracy</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
<keywords>
<term>African American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-08">August 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Minimal TEI tagging</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="article" id="d3">
<pb n="194"/>
<head>
Du Bois, W. E. Burghardt.  "Strivings of the Negro People."<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 80 (1897): 194-198.</head>

<p>BETWEEN me and the other world there is ever an unasked
question: unasked by some through feelings of delicacy; by others
through the difficulty of rightly framing it.  All, nevertheless,
flutter round it.  They approach me in a half-hesitant sort of way,
eye me curiously or compassionately, and then, instead of saying
directly, How does it feel to be a problem? they say, I know an
excellent colored man in my town; or, I fought at Mechanicsville;
or, Do not these Southern outrages make your blood boil?  At these
I smile, or am interested, or reduce the boiling to a simmer, as
the occasion may require.  To the real question, How does it feel
to be a problem? I answer seldom a word.
</p><p>And yet, being a problem is a strange experience, &mdash; peculiar
even for one who has never been anything else, save perhaps in
babyhood and in Europe.  It is in the early days of rollicking
boyhood that the revelation first bursts upon one, all in a day, as
it were.  I remember well when the shadow swept across me.  I was
a little thing, away up in the hills of New England, where the dark
Housatonic winds between Hoosac and Taghanic to the sea.  In a wee
wooden schoolhouse, something put it into the boys' and girls'
heads to buy gorgeous visiting-cards &mdash; ten cents a package &mdash; and
exchange.  The exchange was merry, till one girl, a tall newcomer,
refused my card, &mdash; refused it peremptorily, with a glance.  Then it
dawned upon me with a certain suddenness that I was different from
the others; or like, mayhap, in heart and life and longing, but
shut out from their world by a vast veil.  I had thereafter no
desire to tear down that veil, to creep through; I held all beyond
it in common contempt, and lived above it in a region of blue sky
and great wandering shadows.  That sky was bluest when I could beat
my mates at examination-time, or beat them at a foot-race, or even
beat their stringy heads.  Alas, with the years all this fine
contempt began to fade; for the world I longed for, and all its
dazzling opportunities, were theirs, not mine.  But they should not
keep these prizes, I said; some, all, I would wrest from them.
Just how I would do it I could never decide: by reading law, by
healing the sick, by telling the wonderful tales that swam in my
head, &mdash; some way.  With other black boys the strife was not so
fiercely sunny: their youth shrunk into tasteless sycophancy, or
into silent hatred of the pale world about them and mocking
distrust of everything white; or wasted itself in a bitter cry.
Why did God make me an outcast and a stranger in mine own house?
The "shades of the prison-house" closed round about us all: walls
strait and stubborn to the whitest, but relentlessly narrow, tall,
and unscalable to sons of night who must plod darkly on in
resignation, or beat unavailing palms against the stone, or
steadily, half hopelessly watch the streak of blue above.
</p><p>After the Egyptian and Indian, the Greek and Roman, the Teuton
and Mongolian, the Negro is a sort of seventh son, born with a
veil, and gifted with second-sight in this American world, &mdash; a world
which yields him no self-consciousness, but only lets him see
himself through the revelation of the other world.  It is a
peculiar sensation, this double-consciousness, this sense of always
looking at one's self through the eyes of others, of measuring
one's soul by the tape of a world that looks on in amused contempt
and pity.  One ever feels his two-ness, &mdash; an American, a Negro; two
souls, two thoughts, two unreconciled strivings; two warring ideals
in one dark body, whose dogged strength alone keeps it from being
torn asunder.
<pb n="195"/>
The history of the American Negro is the
history of this strife, &mdash; this longing to attain self-conscious
manhood, to merge his double self into a better and truer self.  In
this merging he wishes neither of the older selves to be lost.  He
does not wish to Africanize America, for America has too much to
teach the world and Africa; he does not wish to bleach his Negro
blood in a flood of white Americanism, for he believes &mdash; foolishly,
perhaps, but fervently &mdash; that Negro blood has yet a message for the
world.  He simply wishes to make it possible for a man to be both
a Negro and an American without being cursed and spit upon by his
fellows, without losing the opportunity of self-development.
</p><p>This is the end of his striving: to be a co-worker in the
kingdom of culture, to escape both death and isolation, and to
husband and use his best powers.  These powers, of body and of
mind, have in the past been so wasted and dispersed as to lose all
effectiveness, and to seem like absence of all power, like
weakness.  The double-aimed struggle of the black artisan, on the
one hand to escape white contempt for a nation of mere hewers of
wood and drawers of water, and on the other hand to plough and nail
and dig for a poverty-stricken horde, could only result in making
him a poor craftsman, for he had but half a heart in either cause.
By the poverty and ignorance of his people the Negro lawyer or
doctor was pushed toward quackery and demagogism, and by the
criticism of the other world toward an elaborate preparation that
overfitted him for his lowly tasks.  The would-be black savant was
confronted by the paradox that the knowledge his people needed was
a twice-told tale to his white neighbors, while the knowledge which
would teach the white world was Greek to his own flesh and blood.
The innate love of harmony and beauty that set the ruder souls of
his people a-dancing, a-singing, and a-laughing raised but
confusion and doubt in the soul of the black artist; for the beauty
revealed to him was the soul-beauty of a race which his larger
audience despised, and he could not articulate the message of
another people.
</p><p>This waste of double aims, this seeking to satisfy two
unreconciled ideals, has wrought sad havoc with the courage and
faith and deeds of eight thousand thousand people, has sent them
often wooing false gods and invoking false means of salvation, and
has even at times seemed destined to make them ashamed of
themselves.  In the days of bondage they thought to see in one
divine event the end of all doubt and disappointment; eighteenth-century Rousseauism never worshiped freedom with half the
unquestioning faith that the American Negro did for two centuries.
To him slavery was, indeed, the sum of all villainies, the cause of
all sorrow, the root of all prejudice; emancipation was the key to
a promised land of sweeter beauty than ever stretched before the
eyes of wearied Israelites.  In his songs and exhortations swelled
one refrain, liberty; in his tears and curses the god he implored
had freedom in his right hand.  At last it came, &mdash; suddenly,
fearfully, like a dream.  With one wild carnival of blood and
passion came the message in his own plaintive cadences: &mdash; </p>

<l>          "Shout, O children!</l>
<l>             Shout, you're free!</l>
<l>           The Lord has bought your liberty!"</l>

<p>Years have passed away, ten, twenty, thirty.  Thirty years of
national life, thirty years of renewal and development, and yet the
swarthy ghost of Banquo sits in its old place at the national
feast.  In vain does the nation cry to its vastest problem, &mdash; </p>

<l>"Take any shape but that, and my firm nerves</l>
<l> Shall never tremble!"</l>

<p>The freedman has not yet found in freedom his promised land.
Whatever of lesser good may have come in these years of change, the
shadow of a deep disappointment rests upon the Negro people,
<pb n="196"/>
&mdash; a disappointment all the more bitter because the unattained
ideal was unbounded save by the simple ignorance of a lowly folk.
</p><p>The first decade was merely a prolongation of the vain search
for freedom, the boom that seemed ever barely to elude their
grasp, &mdash; like a tantalizing will-o'-the-wisp, maddening and
misleading the headless host.  The holocaust of war, the terrors of
the Kuklux Klan, the lies of carpet-baggers, the disorganization of
industry, and the contradictory advice of friends and foes left the
bewildered serf with no new watchword beyond the old cry for
freedom.  As the decade closed, however, he began to grasp a new
idea.  The ideal of liberty demanded for its attainment powerful
means, and these the Fifteenth Amendment gave him.  The ballot,
which before he had looked upon as a visible sign of freedom, he
now regarded as the chief means of gaining and perfecting the
liberty with which war had partially endowed him.  And why not?
Had not votes made war and emancipated millions?  Had not votes
enfranchised the freedmen?  Was anything impossible to a power that
had done all this?  A million black men started with renewed zeal
to vote themselves into the kingdom.  The decade fled away, &mdash; a
decade containing, to the freedman's mind, nothing but suppressed
votes, stuffed ballot-boxes, and election outrages that nullified
his vaunted right of suffrage.  And yet that decade from 1875 to
1885 held another powerful movement, the rise of another ideal to
guide the unguided, another pillar of fire by night after a clouded
day.  It was the ideal of "book-learning;" the curiosity, born of
compulsory ignorance, to know and test the power of the cabalistic
letters of the white man, the longing to know.  Mission and night
schools began in the smoke of battle, ran the gauntlet of
reconstruction, and at last developed into permanent foundations.
Here at last seemed to have been discovered the mountain path to
Canaan; longer than the highway of emancipation and law, steep and
rugged, but straight, leading to heights high enough to overlook
life.
</p><p>Up the new path the advance guard toiled, slowly, heavily,
doggedly; only those who have watched and guided the faltering
feet, the misty minds, the dull understandings of the dark pupils
of these schools know how faithfully, how piteously, this people
strove to learn.  It was weary work.  The cold statistician wrote
down the inches of progress here and there, noted also where here
and there a foot had slipped or some one had fallen.  To the tired
climbers, the horizon was ever dark, the mists were often cold, the
Canaan was always dim and far away.  If, however, the vistas
disclosed as yet no goal, no resting-place, little but flattery and
criticism, the journey at least gave leisure for reflection and
self-examination; it changed the child of emancipation to the youth
with dawning self-consciousness, self-realization, self-respect.
In those sombre forests of his striving his own soul rose before
him, and he saw himself, &mdash; darkly as through a veil; and yet he saw
in himself some faint revelation of his power, of his mission.  He
began to have a dim feeling that, to attain his place in the world,
he must be himself, and not another.  For the first time he sought
to analyze the burden he bore upon his back, that dead-weight of
social degradation partially masked behind a half-named Negro
problem.  He felt his poverty; without a cent, without a home,
without land, tools, or savings, he had entered into competition
with rich, landed, skilled neighbors.  To be a poor man is hard,
but to be a poor race in a land of dollars is the very bottom of
hardships.  He felt the weight of his ignorance, &mdash; not simply of
letters, but of life, of business, of the humanities; the
accumulated sloth and shirking and awkwardness of decades and
centuries shackled his hands and feet.  Nor was
<pb n="197"/>
his burden
all poverty and ignorance.  The red stain of bastardy, which two
centuries of systematic legal defilement of Negro women had stamped
upon his race, meant not only the loss of ancient African chastity,
but also the hereditary weight of a mass of filth from white
whoremongers and adulterers, threatening almost the obliteration of
the Negro home.
</p><p>A people thus handicapped ought not to be asked to race with
the world, but rather allowed to give all its time and thought to
its own social problems.  But alas! while sociologists gleefully
count his bastards and his prostitutes, the very soul of the
toiling, sweating black man is darkened by the shadow of a vast
despair.  Men call the shadow prejudice, and learnedly explain it
as the natural defense of culture against barbarism, learning
against ignorance, purity against crime, the "higher" against the
"lower" races.  To which the Negro cries Amen! and swears that to
so much of this strange prejudice as is founded on just homage to
civilization, culture, righteousness, and progress he humbly bows
and meekly does obeisance.  But before that nameless prejudice that
leaps beyond all this he stands helpless, dismayed, and well-nigh
speechless; before that personal disrespect and mockery, the
ridicule and systematic humiliation, the distortion of fact and
wanton license of fancy, the cynical ignoring of the better and
boisterous welcoming of the worse, the all-pervading desire to
inculcate disdain for everything black, from Toussaint to the
devil, &mdash; before this there rises a sickening despair that would
disarm and discourage any nation save that black host to whom
"discouragement" is an unwritten word.
</p><p>They still press on, they still nurse the dogged hope, &mdash; not a
hope of nauseating patronage, not a hope of reception into charmed
social circles of stock-jobbers, pork-packers, and earl-hunters,
but the hope of a higher synthesis of civilization and humanity, a
true progress, with which the chorus "Peace, good will to men,"</p>
<l>          "May make one music as before,</l>
<l>           But vaster."</l>
<p>Thus the second decade of the American Negro's freedom was a
period of conflict, of inspiration and doubt, of faith and vain
questionings, of <hi rend="italic">Sturm and Drang</hi>.  The ideals of physical
freedom, of political power, of school training, as separate all-sufficient panaceas for social ills, became in the third decade dim
and overcast.  They were the vain dreams of credulous race
childhood; not wrong, but incomplete and over-simple.  The training
of the schools we need to-day more than ever, &mdash; the training of deft
hands, quick eyes and ears, and the broader, deeper, higher culture
of gifted minds.  The power of the ballot we need in sheer self-defense, and as a guarantee of good faith.  We may misuse it, but
we can scarce do worse in this respect than our whilom masters.
Freedom, too, the long-sought, we still seek, &mdash; the freedom of life
and limb, the freedom to work and think.  Work, culture, and
liberty, &mdash; all these we need, not singly, but together; for to-day
these ideals among the Negro people are gradually coalescing, and
finding a higher meaning in the unifying ideal of race, &mdash; the ideal
of fostering the traits and talents of the Negro, not in opposition
to, but in conformity with, the greater ideals of the American
republic, in order that some day, on American soil, two world races
may give each to each those characteristics which both so sadly
lack.  Already we come not altogether empty-handed: there is to-day
no true American music but the sweet wild melodies of the Negro
slave; the American fairy tales are Indian and African; we are the
sole oasis of simple faith and reverence in a dusty desert of
dollars and smartness.  Will America be poorer if she replace her
brutal, dyspeptic blundering with the light-hearted but determined
Negro humility; or her coarse, cruel wit with loving,
<pb n="198"/>
jovial good humor; or her Annie Rooney with Steal Away?
</p><p>Merely a stern concrete test of the underlying principles of
the great republic is the Negro problem, and the spiritual striving
of the freedmen's sons is the travail of souls whose burden is
almost beyond the measure of their strength, but who bear it in the
name of an historic race, in the name of this land of their
fathers' fathers, and in the name of human opportunity.
</p>
<signed> <hi rend="italic">W. E. Burghardt Du Bois.</hi></signed>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
