<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="DunMist"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="DunMist">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mr. Cornelius Johnson, Office-Seeker</title>
<title type="sort">mr cornelius johnson, office seeker</title>
<author>Dunbar, Paul Laurence</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">25</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">DunMist</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475903</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Mr. Cornelius Johnson, Office-Seeker</title>
<title level="j">The Cosmopolitan</title>
<title type="sort">mr cornelius johnson, office seeker</title>
<author>Paul Laurence Dunbar</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>26</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>420-424</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Internatinal Magazine Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1899-02">February, 1899</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Copy consulted: UVA Library call number AP2 .C8</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions
for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction;  prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-05">May 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Catherine Tousignant</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" id="d3"> <pb n="420"/>
<head>MR. CORNELIUS JOHNSON, OFFICE-SEEKER.<lb/>
BY PAUL LAURENCE DUNBAR.</head>

<p>IT was a beautiful day in balmy May and the sun shone pleasantly on
Mr. Cornelius Johnson's very spruce Prince Albert suit of gray as he
alighted from the train in Washington.  He cast his eyes about him,
and then gave a sigh of relief and satisfaction as he took his bag
from the porter and started for the gate.  As he went along, he looked
with splendid complacency upon the less fortunate mortals who were
streaming out of the day coaches.  It was a Pullman sleeper on which
he had come in.  Out on the pavement he hailed a cab, and giving the
driver the address of a hotel, stepped in and was rolled away.  Be it
said that he had cautiously inquired about the hotel first and found
that he could be accommodated there.

</p><p>As he leaned back in the vehicle and allowed his eyes to roam
over the streets, there was an air of distinct prosperity about him.
It was in evidence from the tips of his ample patent-leather shoes to
the crown of the soft felt hat that sat rakishly upon his head.  His
entrance into Washington had been long premeditated, and he had got
himself up accordingly.

</p><p> It was not such an imposing structure as he had fondly
imagined, before which the cab stopped and set Mr. Johnson down.  But
then he reflected that it was about the only house where he could find
accommodation at all, and he was content.  In Alabama one learns to be
philosophical.  It is good to be philosophical when the proprietor of
a cafe fumbles vaguely around in the region of his hip pocket and
insinuates that he doesn't want one's custom.  But the visitor's ardor
was not cooled for all that.  He signed the register with a flourish,
and bestowed a liberal fee upon the shabby boy who carried his bag to
his room.

</p><p>Mr. Cornelius Johnson always spoke in a large and important
tone.  He said the simplest thing with an air so impressive as to give
it the character of a pronouncement.  Indeed, his voice naturally was
round, mellifluous and persuasive.  He carried himself always as if he
were passing under his own triumphal arch.  Perhaps, more than
anything else, it was these qualities of speech and bearing that had
made him invaluable on the stump in the recent campaign in Alabama.
Whatever it was that held the secret of his power, the man and
principles for which he had labored triumphed, and he had come to
Washington to reap his reward.  He had been assured that his services
would not be forgotten, and it was no intention of his that they
should be.

</p><p>After a while he left his room and went out, returning later
with several gentlemen from the South and a Washington man.  There is
some freemasonry among these office-seekers in Washington that throws
them inevitably together.  The men with whom he returned were such
characters as the press would designate as "old wheel-horses" or
"pillars of the party."  They all adjourned to the bar, where they had
something at their host's expense.  Then they repaired to his room,
whence for the ensuing two hours the bell and the bell-boy were kept
briskly going.

</p><p>The gentleman from Alabama was in his glory.  His gestures as
he held forth were those of a gracious and condescending prince.  It
was his first visit to the city, and he said to the Washington man: "I
tell you, sir, you've got a mighty fine town here.  Of course, there's
no opportunity for anything like local pride, because it's the
outsiders, or the whole country, rather, that makes it what it is, but
that's nothing.  It's a fine town, and I'm right sorry that I can't
stay longer."

</p><p>"How long do you expect to be with us, Professor?" inquired Mr.
Toliver, the horse who had bent his force to the party wheel in the
Georgia ruts.

</p><p>"Oh, about ten days, I reckon, at the furthest.  I want to
spend some time sight-seeing.  I'll drop in on the Congressman from my
district to-morrow, and call a little later on the President."

</p><p>"Uh, huh!" said Mr. Toliver.  He had been in the city for some
time.

</p><p>"Yes, sir, I want to get through with my little matter and get
back home.  I'm    <pb n="421"/>   not asking for much, and I don't
anticipate any trouble in securing what I desire.  You see, it's just
like this, there's no way for them to refuse us.  And if any one
deserves the good things at the hands of the administration, who more
than we old campaigners who have been helping the party through its
fights from the time that we had our first votes?"

</p><p>"Who, indeed?" said the Washington man.

</p><p>"I tell you, gentlemen, the administration is no fool.  It
knows that we hold the colored vote down there in our vest pockets and
it ain't going to turn us down."

</p><p>"No, of course not, but sometimes there are delays&mdash;"

</p><p>"Delays, to be sure, where a man doesn't know how to go about
the matter.  The thing to do is to go right to the center of authority
at once.  Don't you see?"

</p><p>"Certainly, certainly," chorused the other gentlemen.

</p><p>Before going, the Washington man suggested that the new-comer
join them that evening and see something of society at the capital.
"You know," he said, "that outside of New Orleans, Washington is the
only town in the country that has any colored society to speak of, and
I feel that you distinguished men from different sections of the
country owe it to our people that they should be allowed to see you.
It would be an inspiration to them."

</p><p>So the matter was settled, and promptly at 8:30 o'clock Mr.
Cornelius Johnson joined his friends at the door of his hotel.  The
gray Prince Albert was scrupulously buttoned about his form, and a
shiny top hat replaced the felt of the afternoon.  Thus clad, he went
forth into society, where he need be followed only long enough to note
the magnificence of his manners and the enthusiasm of his reception
when he was introduced as Prof. Cornelius Johnson, of Alabama, in a
tone which insinuated that he was the only really great man his state
had produced.

</p><p>It might also be stated as an effect of this excursion into
Vanity Fair, that when he woke the next morning he was in some doubt
as to whether he should visit his Congressman or send for that
individual to call upon him.  He had felt the subtle flattery of
attention from that section of colored society which imitates&mdash;only
imitates, it is true, but better than any other, copies&mdash;the
kindnesses and cruelties, the niceties and deceits, of its white
prototype.  And for the time, like a man in a fog, he had lost his
sense of proportion and perspective.  But habit finally triumphed and
he called upon the Congressman, only to be met by an under-secretary
who told him that his superior was too busy to see him that morning.

</p><p>"But&mdash;"

</p><p>"Too busy," repeated the secretary.

</p><p>Mr. Johnson drew himself up and said: "Tell Congressman Barker
that Mr. Johnson, Mr. Cornelius Johnson, of Alabama, desires to see
him.  I think he will see me."

</p><p>"Well, I can take your message," said the clerk, doggedly, "but
I tell you now it won't do you any good.  He won't see any one."

</p><p>But in a few moments an inner door opened and the young man
came out followed by the desired one.  Mr. Johnson couldn't resist the
temptation to let his eyes rest on the underling in a momentary glance
of triumph as Congressman Barker hurried up to him, saying:  "Why,
why, Cornelius, how'do, how'do?  Ah, you came about that little
matter, didn't you?  Well, well, I haven't forgotten you; I haven't
forgotten you."

</p><p>The colored man opened his mouth to speak, but the other
checked him and went on: "I'm sorry, but I'm in a great hurry now.
I'm compelled to leave town to-day, much against my will, but I shall
be back in a week; come around and see me then.  Always glad to see
you, you know.  Sorry I'm so busy now; good-morning, good-morning."

</p><p>Mr. Johnson allowed himself to be politely, but decidedly,
guided to the door.  The triumph died out of his face as the reluctant
good-morning fell from his lips.  As he walked away, he tried to look
upon the matter philosophically.  He tried to reason with himself&mdash;to
prove to his own consciousness that the Congressman was very busy and
could not give the time that morning.  He wanted to make himself
believe that he had not been slighted or treated with scant ceremony.
But, try as he would, he continued to feel an obstinate,

   <pb n="422"/>

nasty sting that would not let him rest, nor forget his
reception.  His pride was hurt.  The thought came to him to go at once
to the President, but he had experience enough to know that such a
visit would be vain until he had seen the dispenser of patronage for
his district.  Thus, there was nothing for him to do but to wait the
necessary week.  A whole week!  His brow knitted as he thought of it.

</p><p>In the course of these cogitations, his walk brought him to his
hotel, where he found his friends of the night before awaiting him.
He tried to put on a cheerful face.  But his disappointment and
humiliation showed through his smile, as the hollows and bones through
the skin of a cadaver.

</p><p>"Well, what luck?" asked Mr. Toliver, cheerfully.

</p><p>"Are we to congratulate you?" put in Mr. Perry.

</p><p>"Not yet, not yet, gentlemen.  I have not seen the President
yet.  The fact is&mdash;ahem&mdash;my Congressman is out of town."

</p><p>He was not used to evasions of this kind, and he stammered
slightly and his yellow face turned brick-red with shame.

</p><p>"It is most annoying," he went on, "most annoying.  Mr. Barker
won't be back for a week, and I don't want to call on the President
until I have had a talk with him."

</p><p>"Certainly not," said Mr. Toliver, blandly.  "There will be
delays."  This was not his first pilgrimage to Mecca.

</p><p>Mr. Johnson looked at him gratefully.  "Oh, yes; of course,
delays," he assented; "most natural.  Have something."

</p><p>At the end of the appointed time, the office-seeker went again
to see the Congressman.  This time he was admitted without
question, and got the chance to state his wants.  But somehow there
seemed to be innumerable obstacles in the way.  There were certain
other men whose wishes had to be consulted; the leader of one of
the party factions, who, for the sake of harmony had to be
appeased.  Of course, Mr. Johnson's worth was fully recognized, and
he would be rewarded according to his deserts.  His interests would
be looked after.  He should drop in again in a day or two.  It took
time, of course, it took time.

</p><p>Mr. Johnson left the office unnerved by his disappointment.  He
had thought it would be easy to come up to Washington, claim and get
what he wanted, and after a glance at the town, hurry back to his home
and his honors.  It had all seemed so easy&mdash;before election; but now&mdash;

</p><p>A vague doubt began to creep into his mind that turned him sick
at heart.  He knew how they had cheated Davis, of Louisiana.  He had
heard how they had once kept Brotherton, of Texas&mdash;a man who had spent
all his life in the service of his party&mdash;waiting clear through a
whole administration, at the end of which the opposite party had come
into power.  All the stories of disappointment and disaster that he
had ever heard came back to him, and he began to wonder if some one of
these things was going to happen to him.

</p><p>Every other day for the next two weeks he called upon Barker,
but always with the same result.  Nothing was clear yet, until one day
the bland legislator told him that considerations of expediency had
compelled them to give the place he was asking for to another man.

</p><p>"But what am I to do?" asked the helpless man.

</p><p>"Oh, you just bide your time.  I'll look out for you.  Never
fear."

</p><p>Until now, Johnson had ignored the gentle hints of his friend,
Mr. Toliver, about a boarding-house being more convenient than a
hotel.  Now he asked him if there was a room vacant where he was
staying, and finding that there was, he had his things moved thither
at once.  He felt the change keenly, and although no one really paid
any attention to it, he believed that all Washington must have seen
it, and hailed it as the first step in his degradation.

</p><p>For a while the two together made occasional excursions to a
glittering palace down the street, but when the money had grown lower
and lower Mr. Toliver had the knack of bringing "a little something"
to their rooms without a loss of dignity.  In fact, it was in these
hours with the old man, over a pipe and a bit of something, that
Johnson was most nearly cheerful.  Hitch after hitch had occurred in
his plans, and day after day he had come home unsuccessful and
discouraged.  The crowning disappointment, though, came when,
   <pb n="423"/>   after a long session that lasted even up into the
hot days of summer, Congress adjourned and his one hope went away.
Johnson saw him just before his departure, and listened ruefully as he
said: "I tell you, Cornelius, now, you'd better go on home, get back
to your business and come again next year.  The clouds of battle will
be somewhat dispelled by then and we can see clearer what to do.  It
was too early this year.  We were too near the fight still, and there
were party wounds to be bound up and little factional sores that had
to be healed.  But next year, Cornelius, next year we'll see what we
can do for you."

</p><p>His constituent did not tell him that even if his pride would
let him go back home a disappointed applicant, he had not the means
wherewith to go.  He did not tell him that he was trying to keep up
appearances and hide the truth from his wife, who, with their two
children, waited and hoped for him at home.

</p><p>When he went home that night, Mr. Toliver saw instantly that
things had gone wrong with him.  But here the tact and delicacy of the
old politician came uppermost and, without trying to draw his story
from him&mdash;for he already divined the situation too well&mdash;he sat for a
long time telling the young man stories of the ups and downs of men
whom he had known in his long and active life.

</p><p>They were stories of hardship, deprivation and discouragement.
But the old man told them ever with the touch of cheeriness and the
note of humor that took away the ghastly hopelessness of some of the
pictures.  He told them with such feeling and sympathy that Johnson
was moved to frankness and told him his own pitiful tale.

</p><p>Now that he had some one to whom he could open his heart,
Johnson himself was no less willing to look the matter in the face,
and even during the long summer days, when he had begun to live upon
his wardrobe, piece by piece, he still kept up; although some of his
pomposity went, along with the Prince Albert coat and the shiny hat.
He now wore a shiny coat, and less showy head-gear.  For a couple of
weeks, too, he disappeared, and as he returned with some money, it was
fair to presume that he had been at work somewhere, but he could not
stay away from the city long.

</p><p>It was nearing the middle of autumn when Mr. Toliver came home
to their rooms one day to find his colleague more disheartened and
depressed than he had ever seen him before.  He was lying with his
head upon his folded arm, and when he looked up there were traces of
tears upon his face.

</p><p>"Why, why, what's the matter now?" asked the old man.  "No bad
news, I hope."

</p><p>"Nothing worse than I should have expected," was the choking
answer.  "It's a letter from my wife.  She's sick and one of the
babies is down, but"&mdash;his voice broke&mdash;"she tells me to stay and fight
it out.  My God, Toliver, I could stand it if she whined or accused me
or begged me to come home, but her patient, long-suffering bravery
breaks me all up."

</p><p>Mr. Toliver stood up and folded his arms across his big chest.
"She's a brave little woman," he said gravely.  "I wish her husband
was as brave a man."  Johnson raised his head and arms from the table
where they were sprawled, as the old man went on: "The hard conditions
of life in our race have taught our women a patience and fortitude
which the women of no other race have ever displayed.  They have
taught the men less, and I am sorry, very sorry.  The thing that as
much as anything else made the blacks such excellent soldiers in the
civil war was their patient endurance of hardship.  The softer
education of more prosperous days seems to have weakened this
quality.  The man who quails or weakens in this fight of ours against
adverse circumstances would have quailed before&mdash;no, he would have run
from, an enemy on the field."

</p><p>"Why, Toliver, your mood inspires me.  I feel as I could go
forth to battle cheerfully."  For the moment, Johnson's old pomposity
had returned to him, but in the next, a wave of despondency bore it
down.  "But that's just it; a body feels as if he could fight if he
only had something to fight.  But here you strike out and
hit&mdash;nothing.  It's only a contest with time.  It's
waiting&mdash;waiting&mdash;waiting!"

</p><p>"In this case, waiting is fighting."

</p><p>"Well, even that granted, it matters not how grand his cause,
the soldier needs his rations."    <pb n="424"/>

</p><p>"Forage," shot forth the answer like a command.

</p><p>"Ah, Toliver, that's well enough in good country, but the army
of office-seekers has devastated Washington.  It has left a track as
bare as lay behind Sherman's troopers."  Johnson rose more
cheerfully.  "I'm going to the telegraph office," he said as he went
out.

</p><p>A few days after this, he was again in the best of spirits,
for there was money in his pocket.

</p><p>"What have you been doing?" asked Mr. Toliver.

</p><p>His friend laughed like a boy.  "Something very imprudent, I'm
sure you will say.  I've mortgaged my little place down home.  It did
not bring much, but I had to have money for the wife and the children,
and to keep me until Congress assembles; then I believe that
everything will be all right."

</p><p>Mr. Toliver's brow clouded and he sighed.

</p><p>On the reassembling of the two Houses, Congressman Barker was
one of the first men in his seat.  Mr. Cornelius Johnson went to see
him soon.

</p><p>"What, you here already, Cornelius?" asked the legislator.

</p><p>"I haven't been away," was the answer.

</p><p>"Well, you've got the hang-on, and that's what an office-seeker
needs.  Well, I'll attend to your matter among the very first.  I'll
visit the President in a day or two."

</p><p>The listener's heart throbbed hard.  After all his waiting,
triumph was his at last.

</p><p>He went home walking on air, and Mr. Toliver rejoiced with
him.  In a few days came word from Barker: "Your appointment was sent
in to-day.  I'll rush it through on the other side.  Come up to-morrow
afternoon."

</p><p>Cornelius and Mr. Toliver hugged each other.

</p><p>"It came just in time," said the younger man; "the last of my
money was about gone, and I should have had to begin paying off that
mortgage with no prospect of ever doing it."

</p><p>The two had suffered together, and it was fitting that they
should be together to receive the news of the long-desired happiness,
so arm in arm they sauntered down to the Congressman's office about
five o'clock the next afternoon.  In honor of the occasion, Mr.
Johnson had spent his last dollar in redeeming the gray Prince Albert
and the shiny hat.  A smile flashed across Barker's face as he noted
the change.

</p><p>"Well, Cornelius," he said, "I'm glad to see you still
prosperous-looking, for there were some alleged irregularities in your
methods down in Alabama, and the Senate has refused to confirm you.  I
did all I could for you, but&mdash;"

</p><p>The rest of the sentence was lost, as Mr. Toliver's arms
received his friend's fainting form.

</p><p>"Poor devil!" said the Congressman.  "I should have broken it
more gently."

</p><p>Somehow Mr. Toliver got him home and to bed, where for nine
weeks he lay wasting under a complete nervous give-down.  The little
wife and the children came up to nurse him, and the woman's ready
industry helped him to such creature comforts as his sickness
demanded.  Never once did she murmur; never once did her faith in him
waver.  And when he was well enough to be moved back, it was money
that she had earned, increased by what Mr. Toliver, in his generosity
of spirit, took from his own narrow means, that paid their
second-class fare back to the South.

</p><p>During the fever-fits of his illness, the wasted politician
first begged piteously that they would not send him home unplaced, and
then he would break out in the most extravagant and pompous boasts
about his position, his Congressman and his influence.  When he came
to himself, he was silent, morose and bitter.  Only once did he melt.
It was when he held Mr. Toliver's hand and bade him good-bye.  Then
the tears came into his eyes, and what he would have said was lost
among his broken words.

</p><p>As he stood upon the platform of the car as it moved out, and
gazed at the white dome and feathery spires of the city, growing
into gray indefiniteness, he ground his teeth, and raising his
spent hand, shook it at the receding view.  "Damn you! damn you!"
he cried.  "Damn your deceit, your fair cruelties; damn you, you
hard, white liar!"</p>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>


