<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="EchNewe"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>

<TEI.2 id="EchNewe">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A New England Literary Colony</title>
<title type="sort">new england literary colony</title>
<author>Echols, E. Sherman</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">19</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">EchNewe</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475945</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A New England Literary Colony</title>
<title level="j">Munsey's Magazine</title>
<title type="sort">new england literary colony</title>
<author>E. Sherman Echols</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>Volume 13</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>647-650.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Frank A. Munsey</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1895-09">September 1895</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Copy consulted: UVA Library call number AP2 .M8</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions
for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1895">1895</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>non-fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-05">May 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Catherine Tousignant</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">
<div1 type="essay" id="d3"> <pb n="647"/>
<head>A NEW ENGLAND LITERARY COLONY.<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">"Nook Farm" at Hartford, and the notable group of writers who have
settled there&mdash;Glimpses of the home life of Mark Twain, Harriet Beecher
Stowe, Charles Dudley Warner, and their neighbors.</hi></head>

<p>GROUPED together in and about the old New England city of Hartford
are some of the best known literary people in this country.  Their
homes form what might almost be called a literary colony, and so close
are their lives that one thinks instinctively of the old saying,
"Birds of a feather flock together."  Here are the adjoining homes of
Harriet Beecher Stowe, Samuel L. Clemens (Mark Twain), Charles Dudley
Warner, William E.  Gillette, the noted writer and actor of the drama,
Richard Burton, poet and literary critic, and Isabella Beecher Hooker,
philanthropist and writer on sociology.

</p><p>It is not mere accident that the charming homes of these noted
writers are thus side by side.  They are inclosed in what was formerly
known as "Nook Farm," and still bears the name.  The nucleus of the
colony was formed by the buying of Nook Farm by the families of
Isabella Beecher Hooker and William Gillette, who are closely related.
Harriet Beecher Stowe is Mrs. Hooker's sister, and it was natural that
she should be drawn thither.  The city of Hartford could not offer a
fairer site than that selected by Mr. Clemens, in a neighborhood of
culture, refinement, and natural beauties; and to Mr. Warner and to Mr.
Burton the magnet of a literary atmosphere must have been strong.

</p><p>These homes of genius are adjoining, and are all within a
stone's throw of each other&mdash;though I am sure the inmates never throw
stones, for they are on the most friendly terms.

</p><p>Mr. Clemens, who "has made more people laugh than any other
living writer," has a house which is decidedly unique in design, and
would at once be singled out from many fine residences in the same
locality, because of its unusual appearance.  The site is one that
combines the best of city and country.  The house is built on an
elevation above the roadway, towards which slopes a faultlessly graded
and grassy lawn.  The architecture cannot be designated as any
particular style.  It seems rather to have been a fancy of the
designer, who must have sought to carry variety of outline and detail
as far as it could go within artistic bounds.  As a result, it carries
a distinctive individuality.

</p><p>The structure is of brick, in which variety of color is
prominent.  In the rear of the house, and entirely hidden from view
from the street, is a large, broad, covered balcony, beautifully
floored.  This is a symbol of hospitality, and was built for the sole
purpose of serving teas and holding banquets with congenial souls
during the warmer months of the year. From the roadway one singles
out what looks like an offshoot from the main building, jutting out
from one side of the front of the house.  It is of one story and one
room size, extending out on the lawn and overlooking it on three
sides.  It is isolated from the household&mdash;an ideal study or work
room, you would imagine.  But in point of fact, prosaic as it sounds,
this is the kitchen.  "Mark Twain built his kitchen in front of his
house," as passers by observe with a smile at what they regard as an
instance of the eccentricities of genius.

</p><p>In the original building the kitchen was in the rear, but it
was found small, inconvenient, and inadequate to the needs of the
household, and so the house was relegated to the rear and the kitchen
put in front, as that was the only available spot.  The effect on the
architectural appearance of the building is certainly unique.
Combined with the setting of trees and grassy slopes, the place has
something of the appearance of a lodge house.

</p><p>Reaching out from the house on the west, and sloping down to a
beautiful little valley through which a diminutive river winds lazily
along, stretches a chestnut grove.  In winter the river is alive with
skaters.  Groups of children pass you, and you hear them saying,
"Where are you going skating?" to which the usual answer is, "Oh! to
Mark Twain's."

</p><p>When Mr. Clemens went abroad last year, he left word with his
gardener to give the    <pb n="648"/>   children the use of his
chestnut grove.  The children felt this to be a right royal grant, and
the autumn following the grounds resounded with their shouts and merry
making.

</p><p>The interior of the Mark Twain house is made artistic and
interesting by various rich and antique pieces of furniture and
bric-&agrave;-brac, collected by Mr. and Mrs. Clemens on their travels
abroad.  Mr. Clemens' own work room is on the top floor; but for the
past two years he has spent most of his time on the wing, with his wife
and his three daughters.  One of these daughters, while in London
recently, was asked a question about one of her father's latest
books.  She replied, quite characteristically, "Really I can't give an
opinion.  Papa is the nicest thing in the world, but oh, dear, I do
wish he was not a famous funny man!"

</p><p>In the absence of its inmates the house is left in charge of a
man and wife, who look closely after its interests; the flowers are
culled daily from the large greenhouse adjoining, and disposed of.

</p><p>In the mellow glow of an autumnal day the outlook from this
beautiful home has tempted many an artist's eye.

</p><p>Next to Mr. Clemens on the south is the home of Charles Dudley
Warner.  Their rear yards are divided by a low fence, but a much used
and very friendly looking gate joins them.  Mr. Warner's home is
surrounded by a noble grove of the original monarchs of the forest, and
in this setting seems so complete as to need no other accompaniment.

</p><p>The house is colonial in style, spacious and hospitable, and
stands uninclosed among the magnificent trees.  It is quite an imposing
structure as seen from a distance.  To the west, at the foot of a
steep bank, winds the little river, which seems very generally to be
called "Mark Twain's."

</p><p>Mr. Warner's "Summer in a Garden" is not associated with his
present abode, but was written in another home&mdash;a house near by, where
the town looks into the country.  A deep ravine, wild and picturesque,
is on one side of it, and the "garden" on two others.

</p><p>A Southern lady, who had been greatly charmed with the character
of <hi rend="italic">Polly</hi> in "My Summer in a Garden," and who had supposed the
original of the character to be the author's wife, was greatly
disappointed when told that Mrs. Warner's name was not Polly at all.
She declared that she was ready to cry with vexation and
disappointment, and that she would never again be quite as enchanted
with the book, because she had learned to love Mrs. Warner as
<hi rend="italic">Polly</hi>.  "Backlog Studies" was also written in this earlier home.

</p><p>The interior of Mr. Warner's present home is artistic without
being luxurious.  It is genial, cheerful, and hospitable; trophies of
its inmates' travels are placed here and there, and many beautiful
pictures and engravings adorn the walls.  Every part of the house is
more or less of a library, for books are everywhere.  Mr. Warner's
study is on the third floor.  He is very methodical in his literary
labors, and can lay his hand in an instant on whatever he desires.  Of
Mrs. Warner it is said that whoever is so favored as to spend an
evening in this charming atmosphere, will go away wishing to write an
article on the home and its mistress.  She is president of the Memnon
Club, which has justly gained a reputation for devotion to the best in
music and literature, and through which Hartford has been able to
enjoy the talent of some of the most famous artists.

</p><p>East of Mr. Clemens, its grounds adjoining his, is the home of
Harriet Beecher Stowe.  The house is an unassuming cottage, facing the
east.  The plot of ground on which it stands is planted with shrubbery
and bright with flowers.  The interior of the home is tasteful and
refined in all its appointments; the rooms are large, comfortable,
hospitable, and by no means lacking in artistic adornment.

</p><p>There are abundant proofs of literary culture to be seen on all
sides.  The place is quite a treasure house of relics, and
testimonials of reverence to this gifted woman, whose memory will ever
be enshrined in the hearts of the people, are everywhere to be seen.
I am informed that it is Mrs. Stowe's intention to bequeath to the
public, in some fashion, many of these valuable relics, including a
collection of her original manuscripts.

</p><p>Although you see many marks of genius in the house of this noted
woman, it is still difficult to realize that you are actually in the
home of one of the most famous authors of the age.  She has lost her
active interest in the affairs that formerly absorbed her time and
energies.  Only the fairest weather tempts her out, and she is no
longer able to take the long country walks which in former years were
her greatest delight.  But in her advanced age her fondness for
children and music is just as warm and spontaneous as during her
active life.  Childish and happy, she is most affectionately

   <pb n="649"/>

cared for by her twin daughters, Harriet and Eliza.

</p><p>The home of William E. Gillette adjoins that of Charles Dudley
Warner on the south.  You follow a delightful winding road that leads
around among the trees to its door.  In summer it is so completely
hidden in this miniature forest that you would scarcely suspect its
existence until you are at its very portals, and then you are
overwhelmed with surprise at its beauty of setting.  You hardly care
to study the design and architecture of the house, but drink in with a
long inspiration the beauty of the whole.  There is a restfulness
about the place, and a seclusion that seems to shut you off completely
from all the bustle and hurry of the busy streets a few blocks away
from you.  Seemingly you are in some sylvan bower in the heart of the
country.

</p><p>To this spot Mr. Gillette always comes when worn with his
literary and theatrical labors.  He was born in Hartford in 1853.  As
a boy he had been famous among his playfellows for his proficiency in
the language of dogs, cats, and poultry, and as he grew up he
developed a taste for the stage.  This, however, was not to the minds
of his parents, who had a thorough New England prejudice against all
actor folk.  In later years it was through his neighbor, Mark Twain,
that he first obtained a position with John T. Raymond and appeared at
the Globe Theater, Boston, in "The Gilded Age."  Later, turning toward
dramatic authorship, he set to work on a piece called "The Professor,"
taken from a character sketch.  This was followed by "Esmeralda," in
the writing of which Mr.  Gillette assisted Frances Hodgson Burnett.
Many of his later comedies have been adaptations from German and
French sources.  In "Too Much Johnson"&mdash;which, with Mr. Gillette in
the principal r&ocirc;le, was one of the popular successes of the
last season in New York&mdash;he owed the central idea of a part of the
piece to a French play, but beyond this the comedy is an original
conception.

</p><p>East of Mr. Warner's home, with adjoining grounds, is the home
of Richard Burton, author, critic, and poet, at one time professor of
literature at the Johns Hopkins University, and now literary critic on
the Hartford <hi rend="italic">Courant</hi>.  He is a versatile, bright, and most
interesting speaker, and his lectures on literature are artistic and
scholarly.  Of his work as a poet the following may be taken as a
specimen:</p>

<lg type="verse"><l>We walk with fellow mortals cheek by jowl;</l>
<l>   We clasp warm hands; by interchange of speech</l>
<l>   Do strive to show our meanings each to each&mdash;</l>
<l>The undercurrents of our central soul.</l>
<l>Yet what may know my brother of the goal</l>
<l>   Whereto I would attain and cannot reach?</l>
<l>   And how know I what saints he does beseech</l>
<l>With secret tears, or what his joy and dole?</l></lg>

<lg type="verse"><l>Such thoughts begat a greater thought than these,</l>
<l>   To leave them dwarfed and starveling far behind;</l>
<l>How wide and wonderful the sympathies</l>
<l>   Of God must be, than mortal measures higher,</l>
<l>To comprehend the hordes of humankind,</l>
<l>   And know the darling of each heart's desire.</l></lg>

<p>Mr. Burton's home is the most modern in build of the group, but its
design is antique.  It is not large or imposing in appearance, and is
colonial in style.  With its long, slanting roof, the irregularity of
its windows, and its delightful portico, the place has a great
fascination for a lover of this style.  It is shingled in natural wood.

</p><p>Isabella Beecher Hooker lives opposite the former home of Mr.
Warner.  She is the youngest sister of the late Henry Ward Beecher.
She married a successful lawyer of Hartford, and has been a very close
student of social, political, and religious questions.  Her work in
later life developed into a series of "conversations," extending to
Boston, New York, and other cities.  Her best known work is
"Womanhood, Its Sanctities and Fidelities."  She is well known, too,
for her platform work.

</p><p>Mrs. Hooker's home is a charming spot.  The house is of the
Gothic order, large and rambling.  Under its roof have been welcomed
many distinguished people.  It is set far back from the road, from
which it can be approached on two sides, and marks the confines of
Nook Farm on the east.  It is inclosed in ample grounds, set with rare
trees, in the shade of which Mrs. Hooker loves all friendly minded
people to roam at will.

</p><p>Hartford also claims the home of Anne Trumbull Slossen, beloved
by American readers for her clever stories of country life, of which
"Fishin' Jimmy" is fairly representative.

</p><p>Mrs. Slossen's home is just beyond the heart of the city.  In
winter you would see in it little to distinguish it from the other
attractive homes on Asylum Avenue, unless it were the look of
loneliness and isolation it generally bears, for the author makes her
home in New York during the greater part of the year, and the old
homestead is closed.  But in the summer it carries a notable
individuality.  It is a veritable "wild wood"

   <pb n="650"/>

among its sister homes.  All sorts of native shrubs, plants, and
flowers have been set out in the garden in front of the house; and as
nature alone nourishes these relics of field and wood, they grow in the
wildest confusion.  Set in the midst of highly cultivated lawns, the
effect is certainly interesting and charming; and though, to an
unsympathetic eye, it may give the home an air of neglect, it is
restful and refreshing to lovers of unadorned and untrammeled nature.

</p><p>Mrs. Slossen is a charming hostess.  Interested in all
educational matters, she has been pre&euml;minently the friend of
students, who, deprived of the home atmosphere, and among strangers,
have found at her hearth-stone a gracious welcome, and the direct
inspiration that her personality gives.

</p><p><hi rend="italic">E. Sherman Echols.</hi></p>
</div1>
</body>

</text>
</TEI.2>

