<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="FarBird"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
]>
<TEI.2 id="FarBird">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Bird of Love</title>
<title type="sort">bird of love</title>
<author>Far, Sui Sin</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">16</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">FarBird</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475953</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Bird of Love</title>
<title level="j">New England Magazine</title>
<title type="sort">bird of love</title>
<author>Sui Sin Far</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>Volume 43</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>25-27.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>J. T. and E. Buckingham</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
<date value="1910-09">September 1910</date>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Copy checked against microfilm.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic TextCenter.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text'sunique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1910">1910</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-05">May 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<item>I have made the following changes to the text:
Page 25 para. 20: ever] every;
Page 25 para. 20: Berkley] Berkeley;
Page 26 para. 1: ko-tow] kow-tow;
Page 26 para. 11: "With] With;
Page 26 para. 17: alway, always;] always, always;;
Page 27 para. 1: accross] across;
Page 27 para. 13: old Li Wung] old Li Wang;
Page 27 para. 22: she.  Oh,] she.  "Oh,</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="1996-05">May 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<item>In addition, I have altered two instances of transposed lines:
     On page 25, /"And I become too great to be ashamed./   "You do
love me then, eh Pau Tsu?"/[blank line]/queried the young man./
has become /"And I become too great to be ashamed./[blank line]/"You
do love me then, eh Pau Tsu?"/ queried the young man./
     On page 27, /young charges, they found them not, and/cries.
Where could the children have/ much perturbed, rent the air with
their/gone?  The beach was a lonely one,/ has become /young charges,
they found them not, and/ much perturbed, rent the air with their/ cries.
Where could the children have/ gone?  The beach was a lonely one,/</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="1996-05">May 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp/>
<name>Catherine Tousignant</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">



<body id="d2">
	<div1 type="story" id="d3"> <pb n="25"/>
<head><hi rend="bold">The Bird of Love</hi><lb/>
<hi rend="italic">By</hi> SUI SIN FAR</head>


<div2 type="chapter" id="d4">
<head>I</head>
<p>THEY were two young people with heads hot enough and hearts true
enough to believe that the world was well lost for love, and they were
Chinese.

</p><p>They sat beneath the shade of a cluster of tall young pines forming
a perfect bower of greenness and coolness on the slope of Strawberry
hill.  Their eyes were looking oceanwards, following a ship nearing the
misty horizon.  Very loving yet very serious were their faces and voices.
That ship, sailing from west to east, carried from each a message to his
and her kin&mdash;a message which humbly but firmly set forth that they were
resolved to act upon their belief and to establish a home in the new
country, where they would ever pray for blessings upon the heads of
those who could not see as they could see nor hear as they could hear.

</p><p>"My mother will weep when she reads," sighed the girl.

</p><p>"Pau Tsu," the young man asked, "Do you repent?"

</p><p>"No," she replied, "But&mdash;"

</p><p>She drew from her sleeve a letter written on silk paper.

</p><p>The young man ran his eye over the closely penciled characters.

</p><p>"'Tis very much in its tenor like what my father wrote to me," he
commented.


</p><p>"Not that."


</p><p>Pau Tsu indicated with the tip of her pink forefinger a paragraph
which read:

</p><p>"Are you not ashamed to confess that you love a youth who is not
yet your husband?  Such disgraceful boldness will surely bring upon your
head the punishment you deserve.  Before twelve moons go by, you will
be an Autumn Fan."

</p><p>The young man folded the missive and returned it to the girl whose
face was averted from his.

</p><p>"Our parents," said he, "knew not love in its springing and growing,
its bud and blossom.  Let us, therefore, respectfully read their angry
letters, but heed them not.  Shall I not love you dearer and more faithfully
because you became mine at my own request and not at my father's?
And Pau Tsu, be not ashamed."

</p><p>The girl lifted radiant eyes.

</p><p>"Listen," said she, "When you, during your vacation went on that
long journey to New York, to beguile the time I wrote a play.  My
heroine is very sad, for the one she loves is far away and she is much
tormented by enemies.  They would make her ashamed of her love.  But
this is what she replies to one cruel taunt.</p>

<lg type="verse"><l>When Memory sees his face and hears
     his voice</l>
<l>The Bird of Love within my heart sings
     sweetly</l>
<l>So sweetly, and so clear and jubilant,</l>
<l>That my little Home Bird, Sorrow,</l>
<l>Hides its head under its wing,</l>
<l>And appeareth as if dead.</l></lg>

<lg type="verse"><l>Shame!  Ah, speak not that word to one
     who loves,</l>
<l>For loving, all my noblest, tenderest feelings are awakened,</l>
<l>And I become too great to be ashamed.</l></lg>

<p>"You do love me then, eh Pau Tsu?" queried the young man.

</p><p>"If it is not love, what is it?" softly answered the girl.

</p><p>Happily chatting they descended the green hill.  Their holiday was
over.  A little later Liu Venti was on the ferry boat which leaves every
half hour for the western shore, bound for the Berkeley Hills, opposite
the Golden Gate, and Pau    <pb n="26"/>   Tsu was in her room at the San
Francisco Seminary, where her father's ambition to make her the equal in
learning of the son of Liu Jusong, had pleased her.</p>

</div2><div2 type="chapter" id="d5">
<head>II</head>


<p>"I was a little fellow of just about their age when my mother first
taught me to kow-tow to my father and run to greet him when he came
into the house," said Liu Venti, speaking of the twins who were playing
on the lawn.

</p><p>"Dear husband!" replied Pau Tsu, "you are thinking of home&mdash;even
as I.  This morning I thought I heard my mother's voice, calling to me as I
have so often heard her on sunny mornings in the Province of the Happy
River.  She would flutter her fan at me in a way which was all her own.
And my father.  Oh, my kind old father!"

</p><p>"Aye," responded Liu Venti, "our parents loved us!"

</p><p>"Let us go home," said Pau Tsu after a while.

</p><p>Liu Venti started.  Pau Tsu's words echoed the wish of his own
heart.  But he was not as bold as she.

</p><p>"How can we?" he asked.  "Have not our parents sworn that they
will never forgive us?"

</p><p>"The light within me today," replied Pau Tsu, "reveals that our
parents sorrow because they have thus sworn.  Liu Venti, ought we not to
make our parents happy, even if we have to do so against their will?"

</p><p>"I would that we could," replied Liu Venti, "but there is to be
overcome your father's hatred for my father and my father's hatred for
yours."

</p><p>A shadow crossed Pau Tsu's face; but only for a moment.  It lifted
as she softly said: "Love is stronger than hate."

</p><p>Little Waking Eyes ran up and clambered upon his father's knee.

</p><p>"Me too," cried Little Sleeping Eyes, following him.  With chubby
fists he pushed his brother aside and mounted his father also.

</p><p>Pau Tsu looked across at her husband and sons.

</p><p>"The homes of our parents," said she, "are empty of the voices of
little ones."

</p><p>Three moons later, Liu Venti and Pau Tsu, with mingled sorrow
and hope in their hearts, bade good bye to their little sons and sent them
across the sea, offerings of love to parents of whom both son and
daughter remembered nothing but love and kindness, yet from whom that
son and daughter were estranged by a poisonous thing called Hate.</p>

</div2><div2 type="chapter" id="d6">
<head>III</head>


<p>Two little boys were playing together on a beach.  One gazed across
the sea with wondering eyes.  A thought had come&mdash;a memory.  "Where
is father and mother?" he asked, turning to his brother.  The other little
boy gazed bewildered back at him and echoed: "Where is father and
mother?"

</p><p>Then the two little fellows sat down in the sand and began to talk to
one another in a queer little old fashioned way of their own.  Their little
mouths drooped pathetically; they propped their chubby little faces in
their hands and heaved queer little sighs.

</p><p>There was father and mother one time&mdash;always, always; father and
mother and Sung Sung.  Then there was the big ship and Sung Sung only,
and the big water.  After the big water, grandfathers and grandmothers,
and Little Waking Eyes had gone to live with one grandfather and
grandmother and Little Sleeping Eyes had gone to live with another
grandfather and grandmother.  And Little Waking Eyes and Little
Sleeping Eyes had been good and had not cried at all.  Had not father and
mother said that grandfathers and grandmothers were just the same as
fathers and mothers?

</p><p>"Just the same as fathers and mothers," repeated Little Waking Eyes
to Little Sleeping Eyes, and Little Sleeping Eyes nodded his head and
solemnly repeated: "Just the same as fathers and mothers."

</p><p>Then all of a sudden Little Waking Eyes stood up, rubbed his fists
into his eyes and shouted: "I want my father and mother, I want my father
and mother!"  And Little Sleeping Eyes stood up and cried out strong and
bold: "Let us go seek them.  Let us go seek."</p>
   <pb n="27"/>

</div2><div2 type="chapter" id="d7">
<head>IV</head>


<p>So it happened that when the two new Sung Sungs who had been
having their fortunes told by an itinerant fortune teller some distance
down the beach, returned to where they had left their young charges, they
found them not, and much perturbed, rent the air with their cries.  Where
could the children have gone?  The beach was a lonely one, several miles
from the seaport city where lived the grandparents of the children.
Behind the beach, the bare land rose for a little way back up the sides and
across hills to meet a forest dark and dense.

</p><p>Said one Sung Sung to another, looking towards this forest: "One
might as well search for a pin at the bottom of the ocean as search for the
children there.  Besides, it is haunted with evil spirits."

</p><p>"A-ya, A-ya, A-ya!" cried the other, "Oh, what will my master and
mistress say if I return home without Little Sleeping Eyes who is the
golden plum of their hearts."

</p><p>"And what will my master and mistress do to me if I enter their
presence without Little Waking Eyes.  I verily believe that the sun shines
for them only when he is around."

</p><p>For over an hour the two distracted servants walked up and down
the beach, calling the names of their little charges; but there was no
response.</p>

</div2><div2 type="chapter" id="d8">
<head>V</head>


<p>Under the quiet stars they met&mdash;the two old men who had quarrelled
in student days, and who ever since had cultivated hate for each other.
The cause of their quarrel had long since been forgotten; but in the fertile
soil of minds irrigated with the belief that the superior man hates long
and well, the seed of hate had germinated and flourished.  Was it not
because of that hate that their children were exiles from the homes of
their fathers&mdash;those children who had met in a foreign land, and in spite
of their fathers' hatred, had linked themselves in love.

</p><p>They spread their fans before their faces, each pretending not to see
the other, while their servants enquired, "What news of the honorable
little ones?"

</p><p>"No news," came the answer from either side.

</p><p>The old men pondered sadly and silently.  Finally Liu Jusong said
to his servants: "I will search in the forest."

</p><p>"So also will I," announced Li Wang.

</p><p>Liu Jusong lowered his fan.  For the first time in many years, he
allowed his eyes to rest on the countenance of his old college friend, and
that one time friend returned his glance.  But the servant men shuddered:

</p><p>"It is the haunted forest," they cried.  "Oh, honorable masters,
venture not amongst evil spirits!"

</p><p>But old Li Wang laughed them to scorn as also did Liu Jusong.

</p><p>"Give me a lantern," bade Li Wang, "I will search alone.  Thy
grandson is my grandson and mine is thine."

</p><p>"Aye," responded Li Wang.

</p><p>And love being stronger than hate, the two old men entered the
forest together, searched for their children together and found them
together.</p>

</div2><div2 type="chapter" id="d9">
<head>VI</head>


<p>"How many moons, Liu Venti, since our little ones went from us?"
sighed Pau Tsu.

</p><p>She was pale and sad and in her eyes was a yearning expression
that had not been always there.

</p><p>"Nearly five," returned Liu Venti.

</p><p>"Sometimes," said Pau Tsu, "I feel I cannot any longer bear their
absence."

</p><p>She took from her bosom two little shoes, one red, one blue.

</p><p>"Their first," said she.  "Oh, my sons, my little sons!"

</p><p>"Now, dear wife," said Liu Venti, "you must not grieve like that.
The little ones are happy and all will some day be well."

</p><p>A messenger boy approached, handed Liu Venti a message and
slipped away.

</p><p>Liu Venti read:
</p><p>"May the bamboo ever wave.  Son and daughter, return to
your parents and your children."
</p><p>Liu Jusong,<lb/>
Li Wang.</p>

</div2>
	</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

