<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="FarChin"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="FarChin">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Chinese Ishmael</title>
<title type="sort">chinese ishmael</title>
<author>Far, Sui Sin</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">22</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">FarChin</idno>
<date value="1996">1996</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1996 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475954</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Images omitted from the print version,
which could not be obtained.  Text has been checked against the
microfilm.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Chinese Ishmael</title>
<title level="j">Overland Monthly</title>
<title type="sort">chinese ishmael</title>
<author>Sui Sin Far</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>n.s. 34</p>
</editionStmt>
<extent>43-49.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Overland Monthly Pub. Co.</publisher>
<pubPlace>San Fransisco</pubPlace>
<date value="1899-07">July 1899</date>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>Spell-check and verification made
against printed text using WordPerfect spell checker.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>The images exist as archived TIFF images, one or more JPEG versions
for general use, and thumbnail GIFs.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1899">1899</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1996-05">May 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<item>I have made the following changes to the text:
page 44, para. 3, line 3  ways that] ways than;
page 44, para. 5, line 4  Japanese.] Japanese.";
page 46, para. 23, line 4  Hop, Wo] Hop Wo</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="1996-05">May 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Catherine Tousignant</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="1996-05">May 1996</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Catherine Tousignant</name>
</respStmt>
<item>I have corrected the spelling of the author's name, erroneous in
the print version, from "Fah" to "Far."  I have changed the text and
the appropriate fields in the header.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" id="d3"> <pb n="43"/>
<head>A CHINESE ISHMAEL<lb/>
BY SUI SIN FAR</head>

<p>IN THE light of night, on the detached rocks near the Cliff House,
the sea-lions are clambering and growling; the waters of the Pacific
are foaming around them, and their young, in the clefts of the
rookeries, are drifting into dreamland on lullabies sung by the waves.

</p><p>Mark that great fellow ensconced on a rocky pedestal.  Why does
he roar so restlessly and complainingly?  I wonder, if he could speak,
if he would tell where Leih Tseih and Ku Yum lie.  I almost fancy that
he sees the lovers quiet and still under the waters.


</p><p>Ku Yum leant over the balcony of the big lodging-house on Dupont
Street.  She was very tired, for she was a delicate little thing and
her tiny hands and feet were kept moving all day; her mistress had a
heart like a razor and a tongue to match.  Underneath the balcony
there passed a young man, and as he went by, some spirit whispered in
Ku Yum's ear, "Let fall a Chinese lily."

</p><p>Ku Yum obeyed the spirit, and the young man, whose name was
Leih Tseih, raised his eyes, and seeing Ku Yum, loved her.  The Chinese
lily he lifted from the ground and carried it away in his sleeve.
Thereafter every day, going backward and forward to his work, Leih
Tseih passed under the balcony where he had first seen Ku Yum, but the
maiden no longer leaned over the railing.  She had grown shy, and
contented herself with peeping out of the door of the upper room.  At
last Leih Tseih, who was beside himself with love, threw her a note
wrapped around a stone.  Ku Yum caught and demurely retired with it;
but just as she was placing it in the sole of her shoe her mistress
came behind her and twisted it out of her fingers.

</p><p>"You wicked, wicked thing!" cried the woman.  "How dare you
keep company with a bad man!"

</p><p>Poor little Ku Yum's transparent face flushed.

</p><p>"If I am a wicked thing, a bad man is fit company for me," she
cried.  "But he who wrote me that is a superior man."

</p><p>At that her mistress fell to beating her with a little switch.
Ku Yum screamed; but instead of receiving help, her mistress's husband
appeared and relieved his wife as switcher, having a stronger arm.

</p><p>There lived on the floor just below the Lee Chus, the owners of
Ku Yum, a woman who had compassion on the slave-girl.  She too had seen
Leih Tseih pass and the tossing up of the note, and had said to
herself, "Now, there are a fine-looking young man and a pearl of a girl
becoming acquainted.  May they be happy!"

</p><p>So when Ku Yum's screams rent the air, her heart swelled big
with pity, and though she dared not interfere between mistress and
maid, she resolved to watch for Leih Tseih and tell him what she knew
concerning Ku Yum.

</p><p>When Leih Tseih learned what had befallen the girl of his heart
for his sake, the blood rushed to his head, and he would have leapt up
the stairs and carried Ku Yum away by force, but A-Chuen, the woman,
restrained him, saying: "Be discreet, and I will assist you; be rash,
and you will lose all."

</p><p>"But," demurred Leih Tseih, "if a man will not enter a tiger's
lair, how can he obtain her whelps?"

</p><p>"By coaxing them out," replied A-Chuen.

</p><p>Then the woman and the young man conferred together, and it
came to pass that when the stars were in the sky, Ku Yum, in a
peach-colored blouse, a present from a cousin in China, stood with
downcast eyes in A-Chuen's sitting-room and listened to words from her
lover.  She could not be induced to look at Leih Tseih, but he caught
the shine of her eyes underneath the lids, and thought her as sweet as
a li-chee.

</p><p>"Dear child," said A-Chuen, "do not tremble so; you are with
friends."

</p><p>Then Leih Tseih told how he had planned to remove her from the
people    <pb n="44"/>   who had treated her so cruelly.  A-Chuen,
who had an old husband who loved her well enough to do all that she
wished, would leave the house on Dupont Street and take a small house
for herself.  There Ku Yum should safely abide.  Meanwhile, A-Chuen
with amiable and flattering words would induce the Lee Chus to allow
Ku Yum to come to A-Chuen's room to work some embroidery on garments
for her husband's store, thereby preventing Ku Yum from being abused.

</p><p>"You are very good and very kind," responded Ku Yum.  "But
unless I am bought from the Lee Chus, I cannot leave them.  I have
heard them talking of an offer that Lum Choy has made for me.  It is
dollars and dollars, and before many moons go by I fear I shall be
obliged to be his."

</p><p>"Who is Lum Choy?" asked Leih Tseih, his face white with anger
and surprise.

</p><p>"He is a very ugly man," said Ku Yum, "and there is a scar right
across his forehead.  But he has made money, they say, in more ways
than the way of labor."

</p><p>"And you wish to be sold to him?" queried Leih Tseih jealously.

</p><p>"That I did not say," replied Ku Yum, "but this I do say: I am
only a slave, but still a Chinese maiden.  He is a man who, wishing to
curry favor with the white people, wears American clothes, and when it
suits his convenience passes for a Japanese."

</p><p>"Shame on him!" cried A-Chuen.

</p><p>"Kind friend," said Leih Tseih to A-Chuen, "if you so please, I
would speak to Ku Yum alone."

</p><p>A-Chuen left the room, and Leih Tseih, seating himself beside Ku
Yum said, "I would like to tell you of myself."

</p><p>"What you like to tell, I like to hear," replied Ku Yum.

</p><p>"Then, listen," said Leih Tseih.  "I am the son of a high
mandarin, but being possessed of a turbulent and unruly spirit I ran
away from home in my eighteenth year and through the agency of the Six
Companies came to San Francisco.  Here I obtained work, but the
Gambling Cash Tiger had all of my thoughts, and it came to pass in the
heat of a game, when I saw my adversary, the very Lum Choy you speak
of, playing me false, that I struck at him with a knife and left him
lying wounded.  I escaped punishment and followed a seafaring-man's
life for several years.  Then came shipwreck and drifting for days
alone upon the mighty waters, and my soul at last was humbled; and one
solemn night, when naught could be heard save the washing of the waves
against the side of my small boat, I acknowledged with sorrow to the
Parent of All that I had indeed wandered far from the path of virtue,
and vowed, if my life were spared, to follow my conscience,&mdash;for I had
indeed been the bad man your mistress called me."

</p><p>"Good or bad," cried little Ku Yum, "you are you and I am I."
And she patted his hand shyly to show that what she had heard had not
changed her feelings.  Then she added, "And now I vow I will never be
Lum Choy's, but ever yours, who have the grace of the well-born."

</p><p>Leih Tseih smiled and exclaimed, "What a woman!" and declared
that he loved every inch of her skin and the spirit that dwelt behind
her eyes.

</p><p>"I was picked up by a sailing-vessel bound for San Francisco,"
continued Leih Tseih, "and since returning to this city, I have
conformed to virtue in every respect.  I sought work and I obtained
it.  I have saved money&mdash;almost sufficient to pay to the Six Companies
the amount of my indebtedness.  It was with the object of relieving
myself of that obligation that I saved.  But now, my Ku Yum, that sum
will take you and me together far away from here to another city on
the other side of this world.  What do you say?"

</p><p>Little Ku Yum shook her head.

</p><p>"I told my mistress," said she, "that you were a superior man."

</p><p>"So be it," returned Leih Tseih, rebuked, "I will take the
punishment I deserve, and after my debt has been paid will wait for you
until I have made money enough to buy you."

</p><p>"No; when you have paid your debt and are able to take me away,
I will fly with you wherever and whenever you wish."

</p><p>"Even though I steal you."

</p><p>"That I will consider a righteous theft.  Besides, the sooner
you are out of this city

   <pb n="45"/>

<note><p>illustration omitted</p></note>

   <pb n="46"/>

the better.  Are you not afraid that you may be recognized and thrown
into prison?"

</p><p>"I am not afraid.  Life on the ocean transformed me both
inwardly and outwardly."

</p><p>"That may be, but I fear for you now.  Be careful, I pray you.
If you meet Lum Choy there will be trouble; and should he become aware
that you and I have met, he would be a bloodhound on your track."

</p><p>"Well, for your sake I will watch and be cautious."

</p><p>When A-Chuen reappeared, Leih Tseih said, "Kind woman, we have
agreed when the proper time comes to seek another city where we can be
united.  Here there are laws to separate us, but none to bind."

</p><p>Which was true; for how could Leih Tseih and Ku Yum ask either
Chinese priest or American in San Francisco to make them man and wife?

</p><p>"One might as well look for a pin at the bottom of the ocean,"
growled Lum Choy.

</p><p>He spoke to the Lee Chus, who had been vainly searching for
weeks for Ku Yum.

</p><p>"Well, it may be that she has given herself to the sea,"
answered Lee Chu, who was not very bright.

</p><p>"Imbeciles!" was his wife's quick rejoinder as she snapped her
eyes at the men.  "A girl with a new lover can always be found&mdash;by
him."

</p><p>"What do you mean?" asked Lum Choy.

</p><p>"Why, this: Ku Yum had a lover who passed here every day.  It
is to his embraces, not to those of cold water that Ku Yum has given
herself.  The shameful thing!  If I had her here I would tear her eyes
out."

</p><p>Lum Choy's face had become livid.

</p><p>"Do you know this man?" said he.  "If so, I will trace her
through him."

</p><p>"I should know him were I to see him," said Lee Chu's wife,
"but he has not passed for three or four weeks.  I had the letter
which he wrote to Ku Yum, but the girl stole it from me before she
left."

</p><p>"He will pass again," replied Lum Choy.  "Ku Yum is not here
now, so he does not make this his way.  But he must pass some time.
Tell me the hour when he was wont to go by and I will watch day after
day and never weary until I have run him down."


</p><p>The presidents of the Six Companies had met together in the
council hall.

</p><p>The chief of the Sam Yups, an imposing man with thought-refined
features, was urging the advisability of expending a sum of money for
the relief of some sick laborers, when a rapping was heard, followed by
the entrance of the Six Companies' secretary, who approached the aged
chief of the Hop Wos and whispered a few words in his ear.

</p><p>"You can admit him," responded the old man.

</p><p>The secretary left the room, and in a few minutes returned with
a repulsive-looking fellow whose forehead bore a huge scar.

</p><p>"This is Lum Choy," announced the secretary.

</p><p>"Well," Lum Choy, what is your complaint?" inquired the Hop Wo
chief.

</p><p>"My complaint," said Lum Choy, in a high, rasping voice, "is
that living in this city is a man named Leih Tseih, who owes this
honorable body the cost of his transportation from China to America,
and as well sundry other taxes.  His debt is of many years' standing,
yet he works as a free man and himself receives the good of every cent
he earns.  More than this, Leih Tseih is a fugitive criminal, having
some five years ago assaulted a man with murderous intent and escaped
the consequences of his crime.  I, Lum Choy, am the man he assaulted,
and bear on my forehead the mark of his knife.  I also complain that
this Leih Tseih has abducted a slave girl named Ku Yum, or rather,
stolen her from one Lee Chu, and that he has secreted her in a house
on Stockton Street, to which I can lead you.  And I petition that you
engage officers of the law to capture this lawless man, and that you
prosecute him, as it is in order for the Six Companies so to do."

</p><p>There were a few seconds of silence after Lum Choy had finished
speaking; then the Sam Yup chief arose.  He regarded gravely the mean
figure of Lum Choy, and said: "Presidents of the Yeong Wo, Kong Chow,
Yan Wo, Hop Wo and Ning Yeong Societies, you may remember that
   <pb n="47"/>   less than one month ago I delivered over to the Six
Companies' Fund a sum of money, which, as I then stated, had been paid
to me by one of our delinquent emigrants, whose name I had been
requested by him to withhold.  You did not press me to reveal that
name, but the time has come to do so.  The man who paid me that money
was Leih Tseih, and the amount, as shown [illustration omitted] in our
books, covers the whole of his indebtedness.  We, therefore, have no
legal claim against Leih Tseih, and are not authorized to punish him
for the deeds which Lum Choy has charged him with."

</p><p>Lum Choy could not restrain himself.  "What!" he cried, "the
powerful Six Companies have no jurisdiction over the men they have
brought to this country?"

</p><p>"In some cases we have," replied the Hop Wo chief suavely; "but
this case lies with the American courts.  Although so many years have
elapsed since Leih Tseih assaulted you, I believe you still have
recourse against him, and as you are one of our men, we will certainly
do what we can to assist you in avenging yourself according to law."

</p><p>"But the slave girl, Ku Yum?"

</p><p>"Are you interested in her?" queried the Sam Yup.

</p><p>"I am," returned Lum Choy.  "I have paid a large sum for her,
which Lee Chu will not refund, and it was on the day that she was to
have come to me that she fled with Leih Tseih.  In my search for her I
discovered the man, and I have    <pb n="48"/>   made no mistake, for
day after day, night after night, I have dogged his footsteps."

</p><p>The chief of the Ning Yeongs then said: "Lum Choy has suffered
grievous wrongs, and we must do all in our power to assist him in
bringing his wronger to justice; but the purchase of slave-girls,
which is just and right in our own country, is not lawful in America.
Therefore, the task of recovering Ku Yum cannot be undertaken by the
Six Companies.  It must be intrusted to the hands of private parties
and conducted secretly.  Otherwise Lum Choy and Lee Chu will have as
much to answer for, according to the law of this country, as had Leih
Tseih."

</p><p>"And," rejoined the Sam Yup president, "that being so, I would
advise Lum Choy to let matters rest.  He who strives for a woman makes
much trouble for himself.  Besides, is it not better to forgive an
injury than to avenge one?"

</p><p>"Great and noble are your sentiments, benevolent Sam Yup chief,"
broke in Lum Choy, with a scarcely concealed sneer; "but they are not
the sentiments of a man who has been injured as I have been, and I will
have vengeance if it costs me my life."

</p><p>With these words he left the council-room.  Desire for a woman,
hate for a man, had changed the nature of the once shrewd and
clear-headed Lum Choy, and his mind was fired with one idea&mdash;vengeance.

</p><p>"If," meditated he in the darkness of midnight, "I imprison Leih
Tseih for a few months, perhaps a year, Ku Yum will be his at the end
of that time and love him more than ever.  If I use secret means to
obtain Ku Yum, and do obtain her, the sweetness of the fruit will not
be for me, for her mind and heart will be with my rival.  If I kill
Leih Tseih, Ku Yum's spirit will follow his, for that is the way with
women who dare what she has dared.  What, then, can I do to satisfy
myself and draw Ku Yum's heart from Leih Tseih?  This only&mdash;kill Lum
Choy and make Leih Tseih his murderer.  Oho! devils, I shall soon be
one of you!  And now I must arrange so that he shall be the last
person with me.  I know where I can obtain a knife of his, and I know
how I can lure him here.  He will be overjoyed with my offer to
relinquish my claim on Ku Yum for a small tax on his weekly wages, and
while he is pouring out his gratitude to me for abandoning my
vengeance, I will dabble him well with blood from a cut arm.  He must
come here in the dusk of the evening and immediately after his
departure, the deed will be done.  Ha, ha! what a revenge!"

</p><p>"Your eyes are strange; there is blood on your garments!"
cried Ku Yum to Leih Tseih, who without warning had appeared before
her.

</p><p>Leih Tseih's set face relaxed.

</p><p>"Be not afraid, my bird," said he; "but to-night you and I must
part."

</p><p>"Part!  O, no, no!"  She sprang to his side and caught his hand.

</p><p>"It is true.  I am hunted again.  Lum Choy has been found dead
with a knife in his heart.  I was the last person seen to enter his
room.  And as you see, my garments are blood-stained."

</p><p>For a second the girl shrank back; then, alas for the lost soul
of Lum Choy, pressed closer to her lover and whispered in his ear, "If
all men save Leih Tseih were killed by Leih Tseih, still would Ku Yum
remain with Leih Tseih."

</p><p>"I am unworthy," murmured Leih Tseih, brokenly.  "Though I am
guiltless of the deed for which I know they will condemn me, yet my
past has been such that it justifies the condemnation.  But you, O
sweetest heart! you must forget me!"

</p><p>Ku Yum shook her head.  "I can die, but I cannot do what you
have asked of me."

</p><p>Some silent seconds, then Leih Tseih said in a clear voice, "We
will die together&mdash;you and I."

</p><p>"Ah! that will be happiness&mdash;to enter the spirit-land, hand in
hand.  When my cousins in China hear of it, they will say, 'How fine!
Our cousin, Ku Yum, who was a slave-girl on earth, walks the Halls of
Death with the son of a high mandarin.'"


</p><p>To the Cliff they sped.  Arrived where from a parapet they could
leap into the Pacific, they embraced tenderly and were gone.  None can
point to the spot where life with all its troubles ended, for their
   <pb n="49"/>   bodies were never found; but in that part of San
Francisco called the City of the Chinese it is whispered from lip to
ear that the spirits of Leih Tseih and Ku Yum have passed into a pair
of beautiful sea-lions who wander in the moonlight over the rocks,
meditating on life and love and sorrow.</p>
</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

