<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="FinTrai"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="FinTrai">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Trail of the Plume-Hunter</title>
<title type="sort">trail of the plume hunter</title>
<author>Finley, William L.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">25</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">FinTrai</idno>
<date value="1994">1994</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1994 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475957</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Trail of the Plume-Hunter</title>
<title type="sort">trail of the plume hunter</title>
<author>William L. Finley</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Atlantic Monthly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1910">1910</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>Volume 106</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>pp. 373-379</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in SpeFQue1 for page one of
Spenser's Faerie Queene.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1910">1910</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; prose</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1994-08">August 1994</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Kelly Tetterton</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Minimal TEI tagging</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<body id="d2">




<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="373"/>
<head>
Finley, William L.  "The Trail of the Plume-Hunter."<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Atlantic Monthly</hi> 106 (1910): 373-379.</head>


<p>ALL the morning we plodded the level stretch of sand and sage
in the heat that danced and quivered over the floor of the valley.
In the afternoon we reached the base of the high headland that cuts
like the prow of a huge ocean liner into the heart of Harney
Valley.  The trail led straight over a shaled-off pile of boulders,
and zig-zagged up the slope.
</p><p>'What a day for rattlesnakes!' panted my companion, as he
paused to mop his face.
</p><p>I was on the point of answering, when a gray streak flashed
almost under my feet.  I heard a swish that sent fear shivering
through every nerve in my body.  I thought the grandfather of all
big rattlers had struck me in forty places at once, as with a
thundering whir the sage-hen broke from cover and sailed down the
slope.
</p><p>The rest of the winding trail I trod with trembling and
cautious step.  When we reached the summit, we gladly swung the
cameras from our backs.
<pb n="374"/>
The whole valley rolled out before
us.  Off to the south lay the land of our quest, the marshes of the
Malheur.  The wide wastes were silent in the summer sun, hazy, far
away, mysterious.
</p><p>When a boy, I had watched the wedges of geese cutting
southward each autumn, and the other flocks of wild fowl winging
silently on their way.  Each spring I saw the bands returning.  How
these sights kindled my imagination, these processions, so full of
mystery, that moved up and down the highway of the clouds!  The
land where these flocks lived lured me like the 'castles in Spain.'
It was a lure I have never forgotten; it was deeper than childish
fancy.  Now, after many years of waiting, I stood looking out over
this land of innumerable flocks, that had lain far beyond the
northern rim of my home hills.
</p><p>It must be a part of Nature's plan to mould each person with
individual tastes, and give him a hobby of his own.  She mothered
the Anglo-Saxon.  She breathed into his nostrils the breath of the
wild outdoors.  She led him to adventure.  His spirit thrived and
waxed strong in cruising unknown rivers, in exploring untraversed
lands, in luring elusive fish, and in trailing wild animals.  But
the olden days have long passed.  Nature has seen man take
advantage of her wild creatures by his innumerable inventions.  She
sees him to-day, like a mythological god, able to slay from afar
with his bolts, for the hunt has long ceased to be a game of fair
play.
</p><p>The satisfaction of life is in the living, not in death, which
is said to bring its reward.  So in the chase.  The camera tests
the mettle more than the gun.  Success is more difficult.  Reward
is more lasting.  It is truer sport.  Where once there was the
desire to possess the skin of every bird, one finds himself set
with eagerness to photograph these creatures at home, and the fancy
grows so strong that it fastens one's soul in a grip that makes the
hobby an essential part of his life's aim.
</p><p>For the past ten years we had spent every summer season
hunting with the camera.  We had studied and pictured some of the
rarest and wildest of western birds.  During all this time we had
a longing to photograph one bird, one of a species that science has
called <hi rend="italic">candidissima</hi>, divinely fair.  One summer we hunted in
southern California, where these birds formerly nested.  Another
summer we explored the great Klamath marshes of southern Oregon.
We cruised up Klamath River, circled Lower Klamath Lake twice,
paddled down Lost River, and traversed Tule or Rhett Lake from end
to end.  We sloshed through mucky flats of alkali, waded
treacherous mosquito-infested bogs, all because we were eager to
study and photograph the white heron at home in the marsh.
</p><p>'You nevaire git dose w'ite cranes 'less right away.  Ah've
seen t'ousans dose long w'ites; dey all gone,' an old trapper had
told me.
</p><p>After several years of wandering, I began to think that his
words were true.  We had hunted where one might think no human
being had ever been, but long before we had traveled over these
apparently unknown regions, plumers had preceded us.  We followed
in their trails.  We camped where they had camped.  We had traveled
hundreds of miles, exploring the haunts where white herons used to
live, but up to the summer of 1908 we had not seen a single one of
these birds.
</p><p>The white-heron colony in the willows at Clear Lake had been
shot out a few days in advance of us in the summer of 1905.  When
we reached the Big Bend Ranch, one of the cowboys told me he had
heard 'poppin' like a Chiny New Year festival,' along the
<pb n="375"/>
north shore of Tule Lake.  Shooting at this season could mean
nothing but plume-hunting.
</p><p>'Were they after white herons or grebes?' I asked.
</p><p>'They used to be some white cranes down there, and they might
be a few left,' he replied.
</p><p>It was almost hoping against hope to find a white heron in
this locality, but the next morning we bought a week's provisions,
and set out down Lost River to see what we could find.  We camped
that night in an abandoned stack-yard near the mouth of the river.
We poled on down the lake several miles till we came to the wreck
of an old cabin on a grass island, <hi rend="italic">sans</hi> doors, <hi rend="italic">sans</hi> windows
and a part of the roof.
</p><p>Climbing out over the bow of the boat into the shallow water,
we dragged her to shore and entered the cabin.  The empty shells
and feathers scattered about the ashes of the camp-fire told me it
was where the grebe-hunters had camped.  At the side of the cabin
I picked up the end of a broken paddle.  It was marked with a
peculiar brand that joined the two letters H. A.  On the smooth
surface were some numbers, 267, 22-, 208, and other figures that
added up to over twelve hundred.  Fifty feet from the ashes of the
campfire, I found the skinning place.  A square chunk of wood had
served for a chopping-block.  I saw three piles of wings each of
which would have filled a washtub; enough others were scattered
about to make a cartload.  Here were the bodies of dead grebes
tossed aside after the plumage had been stripped from their
breasts.  Each was marked by a buzzing throng of flies that swarmed
up at our approach and settled back.  On the left I counted a
hundred rotting carcasses in one place.  All the winds of heaven
could hardly ventilate such a spot.  I turned back, sickened at the
sight.
</p><p>Out through the tules where we had expected to find birds
thick about their floating homes, we began to find deserted nests.
Along both sides of a narrow slough, in a space of fifty yards, I
counted forty-seven platform homes.  Most of these were deserted.
In some I saw eggs never to be hatched.  Beside several nests I
picked up dead grebe chicks that had climbed out in search of food
dead parents would never bring.  I saw other homes where young
grebes were starving and burning to death in the sun.  Gray chicks
were piping faintly for food.  Worst of all were sights that
brought the tears.  I saw a grebe mother that had been shot, and
not been found by the plume-hunters, &mdash; a mother lying dead beside
her home.  In a small bunch of tules I saw a grebe baby trying to
crawl under a dead mother's wing, &mdash; cold, helpless, starving.  I can
hear him yet.
</p><p>Thus it was that we saw the passing of the great grebe colony
along the northern end of Tule Lake.  It was not the first colony
of birds we had seen annihilated, but it left a deeper impression
than any such sight I had seen before, or have seen since.  Many
another colony of grebes, terns, and white herons has met the same
fate in this extensive marsh region.
</p><p>There were many lakes farther to the east.  Most promising, as
our last chance for the white heron, were Malheur and Harney lakes,
two hundred miles away.  When we had failed in the Klamath country
in 1905, we had made a resolve to try the marshes of the Malheur.
</p><p>Three years had now passed since we hunted the Klamath.  Our
longing to visit the Malheur country had at last been gratified.
Two weeks ago we had landed at the Dalles, and had covered a
stretch of almost four hundred miles.  Here we were standing on the
high head-land looking out over the
<pb n="376"/>
land of our quest.
Here spread at our feet was a domain for wild fowl unsurpassed in
the United States.
</p><p>This is historic ground for the bird man.  In the early
seventies the well-known ornithologist, the late Captain Charles
Bendire, was stationed at Camp Harney on the southern slope of the
Blue Mountains, straight across the valley from where we stood.  He
gave us the first account of the bird-life in this region.  He saw
the wonderful sights of the nesting multitudes.  He told of the
colonies of white herons that lived in the willows along the lower
Silvies River.  There was the river itself winding across the
valley through sage, rye-grass flats, and tule marshes, its trail
marked by a growth of willow and alder.
</p><p>Two days ago we had followed this trail, and searched out
these places to photograph the white heron.  As we approached the
trees, said to be alive with birds, all was silent.
</p><p>'We're on the wrong trail again,' my companion had suggested;
but pushing through the willows, I saw big nests in the trees on
both sides of the river.  Strange to say, not a single bird!  I
clambered up to one of the lower nests, and found a rough platform
of sticks upon which lay the bleached bones of two herons.  I
climbed another and another.  Each home was a funeral pyre.
</p><p>'Epidemic?' said my companion.
</p><p>'Yes, of plume-hunters!' I retorted.
</p><p>Here was a great cemetery in the silence of the marsh.  But
one nest was inhabited.  A long-eared owl was in possession,
sitting on five eggs.  As we approached, she spread her wings, and
left without a sound.  Ill-omened creature brooding eggs and bones!
</p><p>Standing here high above the valley, with my field-glass I
picked out the very spot of this great bird-massacre that we had
visited.
</p><p>'I hope we find no more like that,' said my companion as he
tightened the camera-straps about his shoulders, and started off
down the trail toward the lake.
</p><p>We were both confident that somewhere down in that distant sea
of green tules, we could find at least one place where white herons
were nesting.
</p><p>From a distance the marsh was a deceptive, level sea of green.
The ocean surface tells nothing of a thousand hidden wonders; so
the marsh.  The charm is in the untrodden stretches.  The plain
yields to the plough, the forest to the axe, but I hope the
unmeasured extent of the tules will defy civilization to the end.
It looked like a primeval wilderness, as wild as when the first
white man blazed a trail into the Oregon forest.  I knew that
hunters and trappers plied the streams and the waters of the lake
itself.  But the tules looked untouched, a maze that was
forbidding, impenetrable.
</p><p>On the south side of the lake, at the site of the historical
old Sod House, a large spring rises at the base of the gravelly
hill, and winds out through the meadow-land.  For a mile it
meanders along till it comes to the main part of the tule marsh, &mdash;
thousands of floating islands between which flow narrow channels
that are endless in their windings.  The main body of the lake is
still a mile beyond the place where the spring branch enters the
tule jungle.  The tules grow from eight to twelve feet high, so
that when one enters the mass, he has no landmarks, unless,
perchance, he can read signs in the heavens above.
</p><p>We launched our flat-bottomed boat in the spring branch and
set out, anxious to get the lay of the land and see some of the
birds.  We passed from the spring branch into the serpentine
meanderings among the tules.
</p><p>In one place I heard a pair of sora
<pb n="377"/>
rails chattering
anxiously.  We shoved the nose of the boat into the tule mass that
covered the water like an immense haycock.  As I crawled out over
the bow and stepped on the springy mass, the footing seemed safe,
for I did not sink in above my shoes.  One needed a pair of
snowshoes to walk on the surface.  By throwing myself forward, and
gathering under me an armful of buoyant tules, I made my way for
twenty feet, with the excited pair of rails leading me on.
Suddenly I struck a weak place in the tule floor that let me drop
into the muck beyond my middle.  With the aid of an oar that was
thrown me, I struggled back to the boat.
</p><p>We were now in danger of losing our way.  A little farther on
I left my handkerchief on top of a bunch of tules for a sign-post.
Still farther I stuck up a pole we had in the boat to mark our way
back.
</p><p>'We'll pick these up on our return,' I said.
</p><p>We swung around a tule island, working back in the direction
from which we had come.
</p><p>'I am beginning to lose my bearings,' said my companion.  But
I had already lost mine.
</p><p>My first trip to Boston, that took me underground, overground,
and up and down crooked streets, was as clear as wandering down a
country lane in comparison to the embarrassment I felt when I tried
to find my way in the narrow, walled-in Venetian streets that
circled these islands like a maze for about ten miles east and
west.
</p><p>'The thing to do is to go back over the same track we came,'
I ventured; so we immediately turned about and spent the rest of
the afternoon in trying to do it, but we never saw the handkerchief
or the pole again.
</p><p>We had no food, nothing to drink but alkali water, and were
wet, with no chance of getting dry, so we had to find our way out.
The sun was setting, so we knew east from west.  We paddled as
nearly as possible in the direction in which we had come.  When at
last we reached the end of a blind channel where the foundation of
the tules seemed firmer, we decided to cut for shore by the
shortest route.  We floundered through the tules, sinking in the
black muck of the marsh for some distance.  We were suddenly
confronted by a deep slough.
</p><p>'Even the old tub of a boat looks better than this,' said my
companion.
</p><p>We turned back again.
</p><p>As the clumsy craft floated out into the channel, and I sat
straddling the bow, dangling my feet in the water to get rid of the
mud, it seemed as if Nature had surely done her best to make the
tule swamp unfit for man.  The rails ran lightly through the
jungle, the blue herons stood fishing in the marginal water, the
red-wings and tule wrens clung to the swaying stems, the muskrats
paddled homeward with tails waving contentedly to and fro; they all
had places to sleep.
</p><p>Darkness settled over the marsh.  The stars glittered, the
wind whispered in the tule-tops, the birds were asleep.
</p><p>It was almost noon the next day when by chance we struck the
channel that led us out of the maze, and back to camp.  We had
learned the art of blazing a trail that we could follow through the
tules, and after resting a day from our initial efforts, we
outfitted for a week's trip, and set out down the spring branch.
This time we kept a straight course to the north until we reached
the main body of the lake.  All day long we hunted and watched the
birds, lining them with our field-glasses as they flew back and
forth over the lake.  We saw no signs of white herons.  We knew of
no way out, where we could strike a camping spot, without
<pb n="378"/>
returning the way we had come.  As night came on, we located a good
big muskrat house.
</p><p>I never knew just what a muskrat was good for till I crawled
out rather gingerly upon the roof of this house.  I flattened the
top.  It made a raft large enough for both of us to stretch out
upon.  As we couldn't sleep in the boat, we spread our blankets on
the rat-house.  The question uppermost was, how long the dwelling
would float with such heavy tenants on the roof.
</p><p>'If the rats decided to remove the underpinning in the night,
the laugh would be on us,' I said.
</p><p>However, the rat-house lasted till daylight; but after
spending the night somewhat in suspense in such wobbly,
incommodious quarters, I crawled out of my blankets and by a
misstep slipped into the cold muck to my middle.
</p><p>That day we found a colony where the great blue heron nested.
White herons were formerly common here, both species nesting
together.  Not a single white bird left!
</p><p>We returned at night to our rat quarters, but the roof was
several inches out of plumb.  We slept till about two o'clock in
the morning, when it began to rain.  We were in the predicament of
having too much water above as well as below.  Covering our boat
and equipment with canvas, we arranged a small cover for ourselves.
We spent the rest of the night sitting back to back with knees up
and toes out, wondering why we were not built like muskrats.
</p><p>The morning of the third day the muskrat house showed wear.
We cut a lot of dry tules, and tried to patch the roof, but one
side began to sink, so we set out hunting for another flat.
</p><p>We spent the next four days hunting here and there through the
vast extent of tule islands and water, searching and keeping watch
all day, trying to find white herons.  Late one afternoon we came
to a place where another big colony of blue herons was nesting.  We
had been seeking this place.  Malheur Lake is divided into several
parts by the long lines of tule islands.  We were in the northern
part.  The colony was on two long tule islands that lined up with
Pine Knob and the east end of Wright's Point.  On the north end is
a big cane-brake.
</p><p>We sat in the boat at the edge of the cane-brake, and watched
the big birds as they sailed over, dropped in, and departed.  We
were tired from the long day's search.  I did not then know the
story as I know it now; but hidden in the end of this cane-brake a
hunter had had his blind, ten years before.
</p><p>That summer of 1898 was eventful in white-heron history here
on Malheur Lake.  Early in the season two men had arrived at
Narrows, bought lumber, and built a flat-bottomed, double-ended
boat.  They set out from Narrows with a small outfit.  They fought
mosquitoes day and night as we had, they drank the alkali water,
they slept in the boat or on muskrat houses while they hunted up
and down the waters of the lake and the tule islands.  They saw the
great flocks of white pelicans, cormorants, terns, gulls, grebes
and other birds.  They saw the white herons in slow stately flight
wherever they went, but it was not till after several days that
they located the big colony here on the island by the cane-brake,
the greatest colony they had ever seen.  What a sight it must have
been, thousands of these birds, dazzling white in the sun, coming
and going from the feeding grounds, and hovering over their homes!
</p><p>On all sides were the homes, built up a foot or two from the
surface, each having three or four frowsy-headed youngsters or as
many eggs.  At each
<pb n="379"/>
end of the colony a plumer sat hidden
in his blind.  At the first crack of the gun, a great snowy bird
tumbled headlong near its nest.  As the shot echoed across the
lake, it sounded the doom of the heron colony.  Terror-stricken, on
every side white wings flapped, till the air was completely filled.
Shot followed shot unremittingly as the minutes passed into hours.
Still the heron mothers came to hover over this scene of death and
destruction.  Mother-love was but the lure to slaughter.
</p><p>by two o'clock in the afternoon, the day's shoot ended.  It
took the rest of the day for the hunters to collect the dead and
take the plumes.  Stripping the plumes is rapid work.  It takes but
a slash of the knife across the middle of the back, a cut down each
side, and a swift jerk.
</p><p>Long after dark the plumers heard the steady quacking clatter
of young herons crying to be fed.  Far into the night, hoarse
croaks sounded over the still lake, greetings of those birds that
had spent the day fishing in distant swamps.  It argued good
shooting again for the morrow.
</p><p>The second day was a repetition of the first.  Heron numbers
thinned rapidly.  Here on these two islands, the plumers harvested
a crop that yielded twelve hundred dollars in a day and a half.
They collected a load of plumes worth their weight in gold.  Were
the California days of '49 much better?
</p><p>Malheur has seen many such massacres, but none so great as
that.  Little did we know of these facts as we sat watching the
blue herons coming and going, expecting to find at least a few
white herons somewhere about the locality.
</p><p>The next day a heavy thunder-shower blew up from the south.
We had no way of escaping its fury, so we took the drenching as
cheerfully as possible.  We didn't care much, for although we were
wet half the time, we didn't seem to catch cold.  We were rapidly
reaching that stage of muskrat existence where a condition of
watersoak was a part of our normal environment.
</p><p>The following day we found the biggest colony of gulls and
white pelicans I have ever seen.  It was the sight of a lifetime.
As we approached, out came a small delegation to meet us.  When we
got up to the colony, the whole city turned out in our honor.  I
have seen big bird-colonies before, but never one like this.  I was
so excited I tripped over one of the oars, and fell overboard with
three plate-holders in my hand.
</p><p>After hunting for seven days we returned to camp for more
provisions, and set out to visit another part of the lake.  This
time we stayed out for nine days, and saw &mdash; two white herons!  At
the time we thought these must be part of a group that nested
somewhere about the lake; yet more likely they were a single stray
bird that came our way twice.  I am satisfied that of the thousands
of white herons formerly nesting on Malheur, not a single pair of
birds is left.
</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
