<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="FitRuba"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>
<TEI.2 id="FitRuba">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Rubaiyat of Omar Khayyam (1st and 5th editions)</title>
<title type="sort">rubaiyat of omar khayyam 1st and 5th editions</title>
<author>Fitzgerald, Edward</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
<name/>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">71</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">FitRuba</idno>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475958</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Rubaiyat of Omar Khayyam</title>
<title type="sort">rubaiyat of omar khayyam</title>
<author>Fitzgerald, Edward</author>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<p>1st and 5th editions. Note that this "5th edition" is a version of
what is normally called the 4th editiuon, with minor variations (mostly
in accidentals).</p>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Grosset &amp; Dunlap</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1900" certainty="uncertain">1900</date>
<idno type="callNo">Print copy consulted:</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data.</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p>Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1900" certainty="uncertain">1900</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction; poetry</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1997">1997</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Stephen Ramsay, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added TEI header and tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="d1">

<front id="d2">
<div1 type="contents" id="d3">
<head>Contents</head>
<list>
<item>INTRODUCTION         13</item>

<item>FIRST VERSION        22</item>

<item>FIFTH VERSION       173</item>
</list>
</div1>

<div1 type="introduction" id="d4">
<head>OMAR KHAYYAM: THE ASTRONOMER-POET OF PERSIA</head>

<pb n="13"/>

<p>OMAR KHAYY&Aacute;M was born at Naish&aacute;p&uacute;r in
Khorass&aacute;n in the latter half of our Eleventh, and died
within
the First Quarter of our Twelfth Century.  The Slender Story of
his Life is curiously twined about
that of two
other very considerable Figures in their Time and Country:
one of whom tells the Story of all Three.  This was Niz&aacute;m
ul
Mulk, Vizier to Alp Arsl&aacute;n the Son, and Malik Shah the
Grandson, of Toghrul Beg the Tartar, who had wrested Persia
from the feeble Successor of Mahm&uacute;d the Great, and founded
that Seljukian Dynasty which finally roused Europe into the
Crusades.  This Niz&aacute;m ul Mulk, in his <hi
rend="italic">Wasiyat</hi> &mdash; or <hi
rend="italic">Testament</hi>
 &mdash; which he wrote and left as a Memorial for future Statesmen
 &mdash; relates the following, as quoted in the <hi
rend="italic">Calcutta Review</hi>, No.
59, from Mirkhond's History of the Assassins.
</p><p>"'One of the greatest of the wise men of Khorass&aacute;n
was
the Im&aacute;m Mowaffak of Naish&aacute;p&uacute;r, a man highly
honored
and reverenced, &mdash; may God rejoice his soul; his illustrious
years exceeded eighty-five, and it was the universal belief that
every boy who read the Koran or studied the traditions in his
presence, would assuredly attain to honor and happiness.  For
this cause did my father send me from T&uacute;s to
Naish&aacute;p&uacute;r with
Abd-us-samad, the doctor of law, that I might employ myself
<pb n="14"/>
in study and learning under the guidance of that illustrious
teacher.  Towards me he ever turned an eye of favor and kindness,
and as his pupil I felt for him
extreme affection and devotion, so that I passed four years in
his service.  When I first
came there, I found two other pupils of mine own age newly
arrived, Hakim Omar Khayy&aacute;m, and the ill-fated Ben
Sabb&aacute;h.
Both were endowed with sharpness of wit and the highest
natural powers; and we three formed a close friendship together.
When the Im&aacute;m rose
from his lectures, they used to
join me, and we repeated to each other the lessons we had
heard.  Now Omar was a native of Naish&aacute;p&uacute;r, while
Hasan
Ben Sabb&aacute;h's father was one Ali, a man of austere life and
practise, but heretical in his creed and doctrine.  One day
Hasan said to me and to Khayy&aacute;m, "It is a universal belief
that the pupils of the Im&aacute;m Mowaffak will attain to
fortune.
Now, even if we <hi rend="italic">all</hi> do not attain
thereto, without doubt one
of us will; what then shall be our mutual pledge and bond?"
We answered, "Be it what you please."  "Well," he said, "let
us make a vow, that to whomsoever this fortune falls, he
shall share it equally with the rest, and reserve no pre-eminence
for himself."  "Be it so," we both
replied, and on those
terms we mutually pledged our words.  Years rolled on, and I
went from Khorass&aacute;n to Transoxiana, and wandered to
Ghazni and Cabul; and when I returned, I was invested with
office, and rose to be administrator of affairs during the
Sultanate of Sultan Alp Arsl&aacute;n.'
</p><p>"He goes on to state, that years passed by, and both his
old
school-friends found him out, and came and claimed a share
in his good fortune, according to the school-day vow.  The
Vizier was generous and kept his word.  Hasan demanded a
place in the government, which the Sultan granted at the
Vizier's request; but discontented with a gradual rise, he
plunged into the maze of intrigue of an oriental court, and,
<pb n="15"/>
failing in a base attempt to supplant his benefactor, he was
disgraced and fell.  After many mishaps and wanderings,
Hasan became the head of the Persian sect of the <hi
rend="italic">Ismailians</hi>,
 &mdash; a party of fanatics who had long murmured in obscurity,
but rose to an evil eminence under the guidance of his strong
and evil will.  In <hi rend="small-caps">A.D.</hi> 1090, he seized the castle of
Alam&uacute;t, in
the province of R&uacute;dbar, which lies in the mountainous
tract
south of the Caspian Sea; and it was from this mountain
home he obtained that evil celebrity among the Crusaders as
the OLD MAN OF THE MOUNTAINS, and spread terror
through the Mohammedan world; and it is yet disputed
where the word <hi rend="italic">Assassin</hi>, which they have
left in the language of modern
Europe as their
dark memorial, is derived
from the <hi rend="italic">hashish</hi>, or opiate of
hemp-leaves (the Indian
<hi rend="italic">bhang</hi>), with which they maddened
themselves to the sullen
pitch of oriental desperation, or from the name of the founder
of the dynasty, whom we have seen in his quiet collegiate
days, at Naish&aacute;p&uacute;r.  One of the countless victims
of the Assassin's dagger was
Niz&aacute;m ul Mulk himself, the old school-boy
friend.<ref target="FitRub1">[1]</ref>
</p><p>"Omar Khayy&aacute;m also came to the Vizier to claim his
share;
but not to ask for title or office.  'The greatest boon you can
confer on me,' he said, 'is to let me live in a corner under the
shadow of your fortune, to spread wide the advantages of
Science, and pray for your long life and prosperity.'  The Vizier
tells us, that when he found Omar was really sincere in his
refusal, he pressed him no further, but granted him a yearly
pension of 1200 <hi rend="italic">mithk&aacute;ls</hi> of gold
from the treasury of
N&aacute;ishap&uacute;r.

<pb n="16"/>

</p><p>"At Naish&aacute;p&uacute;r thus lived and died Omar
Khayy&aacute;m, 'busied,'
adds the Vizier, 'in winning knowledge of every kind, and
especially in Astronomy, wherein he attained to a very high
pre-eminence.  Under the Sultanate of Malik Shah, he came
to Merv, and obtained great praise for his proficiency in
science, and the Sultan showered favors
upon him.'
</p><p>"When the Malik Shah determined to reform the calendar,
Omar was one of the eight learned men employed to do it;
the result was the <hi rend="italic">Jal&aacute;li</hi> era (so
called from
<hi rend="italic">Jal&aacute;l-ud-din</hi>, one
of the king's names) &mdash; 'a computation of time,' says Gibbon,
'which surpasses the Julian, and approaches the accuracy of
the Gregorian style.'  He is also the author of some astronomical
tables,
entitled 'Z&iacute;iji-Maliksh&aacute;h&iacute;,'
and the French have
lately republished and translated an Arabic Treatise of his
on Algebra.
</p><p>"His Takhallus or poetical name (Khayy&aacute;m) signifies
a
Tent-maker, and he is said to have at one time exercised that
trade, perhaps before Niz&aacute;m-ul-Mulk's generosity raised
him
to independence.  Many Persian poets similarly derive their
names from their occupations; thus we have Att&aacute;r, 'a
druggist,' Assar, 'an oil presser,'
etc.<ref target="FitRub2">[2]</ref>  Omar himself alludes to
his
name in the following whimsical lines: &mdash;


<q><lg type="verse"><l>      "'Khayy&aacute;m, who stitched the tents of science,</l>
<l>        Has fallen in grief's furnace and been suddenly
burned;</l>
<l>        The shears of Fate have cut the tent ropes of his
life,</l>
<l>        And the broker of Hope has sold him for nothing!'</l>
</lg></q>
</p>

<p>"We have only one more anecdote to give of his Life, and
that relates to the close; it is told in the anonymous preface
which is sometimes prefixed to his poems; it has been printed
in the Persian in the Appendix to Hyde's <hi
rend="italic">Veterum Persarum</hi>
<pb n="17"/>
<hi rend="italic">Religio</hi>, p. 499; and D'Herbelot alludes
to it in
his Bibliotheque, under <hi rend="italic">Khiam</hi>.<ref
target="FitRub2">[3]</ref>&mdash;

</p><p>"'It is written in the chronicles of the ancients that
this
King of the Wise, Omar Khayy&aacute;m, died at
Naish&aacute;p&uacute;r in the
year of the Hegira, 517 (A.D. 1123); in science he was unrivaled,
&mdash; the very paragon of his age.
Khwajah Niz&aacute;mi of
Samarcand, who was one of his pupils, relates the following
story: "I often used to hold conversations with my teacher,
Omar Khayy&aacute;m, in a garden; and one day he said to me,
'My tomb shall be in a spot where the north wind may scatter
roses over it.'  I wondered at the words he spake, but I knew
that his were no idle words.<ref target="FitRub4">[4]</ref>
Years
after, when I chanced to
revisit Naish&aacute;p&uacute;r, I went to his final
resting-place, and lo!
it was just outside a garden, and trees laden with fruit
stretched their boughs over the garden wall, and dropped
their flowers upon his tomb, so that the stone was hidden
under them."'"
</p><p>Thus far &mdash; without fear of Trespass &mdash; from the <hi
rend="italic">Calcutta Review</hi>.
The writer of
it, on reading in India this story of Omar's
Grave, was reminded, he says, of Cicero's Account of finding
Archimedes' Tomb at Syracuse, buried in grass and weeds.  I
think Thorwaldsen desired to have roses grow over him; a

<pb n="18"/>

wish religiously fulfilled for him to the present day, I believe.
However, to return to Omar.
</p><p>Though the Sultan "shower'd Favors upon him," Omar's
Epicurean Audacity of Thought and Speech caused him to be
regarded askance in his own Time and Country.  He is said
to have been especially hated and dreaded by the S&uacute;fis,
whose
Practise he ridiculed, and whose Faith amounts to little more
than his own, when stript of the Mysticism and formal recognition
of Islamism under which Omar
would not hide.  Their
Poets, including H&aacute;fiz, who are (with the exception of
Firdausi) the most considerable in
Persia, borrowed largely, indeed, of Omar's material, but turning
it to a mystical Use
more convenient to Themselves and the People they addressed;
a People quite as quick of Doubt as of Belief; as keen of Bodily
sense as of Intellectual; and delighting in a cloudy composition
of both, in which they could float
luxuriously between
Heaven and Earth, and this World and the Next, on the wings
of a poetical expression, that might serve indifferently for
either.  Omar was too honest of Heart as well of Head for
this.  Having failed (however mistakenly) of finding any
Providence but Destiny, and any World but This, he set about
making the most of it; preferring rather to soothe the Soul
through the Senses into Acquiescence with Things as he saw
them, than to perplex it with vain disquietude after what they
<hi rend="italic">might</hi> be.  It has been seen, however,
that his Worldly Ambition was not
exorbitant; and
he very likely takes a humorous
or perverse pleasure in exalting the gratification of Sense
above that of the Intellect, in which he must have taken great
delight, although it failed to answer the Questions in which
he, in common with all men, was most vitally interested.
</p><p>For whatever Reason, however, Omar as before said, has
never been popular in his own Country, and therefore has
been but scantily transmitted abroad.  The MSS. of his Poems,
<pb n="19"/>
mutilated beyond the average Casualties of Oriental
Transcription, are so rare in the East as
scarce to have reacht Westward at all, in spite of all the
acquisitions of Arms and Science.
There is no copy at the India House, none at the Bibliotheque
Nationale of Paris.  We know but of one in England: No. 140
of the Ouseley MSS. at the Bodleian, written at Shir&aacute;z,
A.D.
1460.  This contains but 158 Rub&aacute;iy&aacute;t.  One in the
Asiatic Society's Library at
Calcutta (of which we have a Copy), contains (and yet incomplete)
516, though swelled to that by
all
kinds of Repetition and Corruption.  So Von Hammer speaks
of <hi rend="italic">his</hi> Copy as containing about 200,
while Dr. Sprenger catalogues the
Lucknow MS. at
double that number.<ref target="FitRub5">[5]</ref>  The
Scribes,
too, of the Oxford and Calcutta MSS. seem to do their Work
under a sort of Protest; each beginning with a Tetrastich
(whether genuine or not), taken out of its alphabetical order;
the Oxford with one of Apology; the Calcutta with one of
Expostulation, supposed (says a Notice prefixed to the MS.)
to have arisen from a Dream, in which Omar's mother asked
about his future fate.  It may be rendered thus: &mdash;

<q><lg type="verse"><l>"O Thou who burn'st in Heart for those who burn</l>
<l>In Hell, whose fires thyself shall feed in turn,</l>
<l>How long be crying, 'Mercy on them, God!'</l>
<l>Why, who art Thou to teach, and He to learn?"</l>
</lg></q>
</p>

<p>The Bodeleian Quatrain pleads Pantheism by way of
Justification.
<q><lg type="verse"><l>"If I myself upon a looser Creed</l>
<l>Have loosely strung the Jewel of Good deed,</l>
<l>Let this one thing for my Atonement plead:</l>
<l>That One for Two I never did misread."</l>
</lg></q>
<pb n="20"/>
</p><p>The Reviewer,<ref target="FitRub6">6</ref>
to whom I owe the Particulars of Omar's
Life, concludes his Review by comparing him with Lucretius,
both as to natural Temper and Genius, and as acted upon by
the Circumstances in which he lived.  Both indeed were men
of subtle, strong, and cultivated Intellect, fine Imagination,
and Hearts passionate for Truth and Justice; who justly revolted
from their Country's false
Religion, and false, or
foolish, Devotion to it; but who fell short of replacing what
they subverted by such better <hi rend="italic">Hope</hi> as
others, with no better
Revelation to guide them, had yet made a Law to themselves.
Lucretius indeed, with such material as Epicurus furnished,
satisfied himself with the theory of a vast machine fortuitously
constructed, and acting by a Law
that implied no Legislator; and so composing himself into a
Stoical rather than
Epicurean severity of Attitude, sat down to contemplate the
mechanical drama of the Universe which he was part Actor
in; himself and all about him (as in his own sublime description
of the Roman Theater) discolored
with the lurid reflex
of the Curtain suspended between the Spectator and the Sun.
Omar, more desperate, or more careless of any so complicated
System as resulted in nothing but hopeless Necessity, flung
his own Genius and Learning with a bitter or humorous jest
into the general Ruin which their insufficient glimpses only
served to reveal; and, pretending sensual pleasure, as the
serious purpose of Life, only <hi rend="italic">diverted</hi>
himself with speculative
problems of Deity, Destiny, Matter and Spirit, Good and
Evil, and other such questions, easier to start than to run
down, and the pursuit of which becomes a very weary sport
at last!
</p><p>With regard to the present Translation.  The original
Rub&aacute;iy&aacute;t (as, missing an Arabic Guttural, these <hi
rend="italic">Tetrastichs</hi>
are more musically called) are independent Stanzas, consist




<pb n="21"/>
ing each of four Lines of equal, though varied, Prosody;
sometimes <hi rend="italic">all</hi>
rhyming, but
oftener (as here imitated) the third
line a blank.  Somewhat as in the Greek Alcaic, where the
penultimate line seems to lift and suspend the Wave that falls
over in the last.  As usual with such kind of Oriental Verse,
the Rub&aacute;iy&aacute;t follow one another according to
Alphabetic
Rhyme &mdash; a strange succession of Grave and Gay.  Those here
selected are strung into something of an Eclogue, with perhaps
a less than equal proportion of the "Drink and make-merry,"
which (genuine or not) recurs over-frequently in the Original.
Either way, the Result is sad enough: saddest perhaps when
most ostentatiously merry: more apt to move Sorrow than
Anger toward the old Tentmaker, who, after vainly endeavoring to
unshackle his Steps from
Destiny, and to catch some
authentic Glimpse of <hi rend="small-caps">TO-MORROW</hi>, fell back upon
<hi rend="small-caps">TO-DAY</hi>
(which has outlasted so many To-morrows!) as the only Ground he
had got to
stand upon, however momentarily slipping from under his Feet.</p>

<signed>EDWARD J. FITZGERALD</signed>
</div1>
<div1 type="notes" id="d5">

<note id="FitRub1"><seg type="note-symbol">[1]</seg> <p>Some of Omar's Rub&aacute;iy&aacute;t
warn us of the danger of Greatness, the instability of Fortune, and while
advocating Charity to all Men, recommending us to be too intimate with none.
Att&aacute;r makes Niz&aacute;m-ul-Mulk use the very words of his
friend Omar [Rub. xxviii.], "When Niz&aacute;m-ul-Mulk was in the Agony
(of
Death) he said, 'Oh God!  I am passing away in the hand of the
wind.'"</p></note>

<note id="FitRub2"><seg type="note-symbol">[2]</seg> <p>Though all these, like our Smiths,
Archers, Millers, Fletchers, etc., may simply
retain the Surname of an hereditary calling.</p></note>

<note id="FitRub3"><seg type="note-symbol">[3]</seg> <p>"Philosophe Musulman qui a ve&ccirc;u en
Odeur de
Saintet&eacute; dans sa Religion, vers la Fin du premier et le
Commencement du second Siecle," no part of which, except the
"Philosophe,"
can apply to our Khayy&aacute;m.</p></note>

<note id="FitRub4"><seg type="note-symbol">[4]</seg> <p>The Rashness of the Words, according to
D'Herbelot,
consisted in being so opposed to those in the Koran: "No Man
knows where
he shall die." &mdash; This story of Omar reminds me of another so
naturally &mdash;
and when one remembers how wide of his humble mark the noble
sailor aimed
&mdash; so pathetically told by Captain Cook &mdash; not by Doctor
Hawkworth &mdash; in
his Second Voyage (1. 374).  When leaving Ulietea, "Oreo's last
request
was for me to return.  When he saw he could not obtain that
promise, he
asked the name of my <hi rend="italic">Marai</hi>
(burying-place).  As
strange a question as this was, I hesitated not a moment to tell
him
'Stepney';  the parish in which I live when in London.  I was
made to
repeat it several times over till they could pronounce it; and
then
'Stepney Marai no Toote' was echoed through an hundred mouths at
once.  I
afterwards found the same question had been put to Mr. Forster by
a man on
shore; but he gave a different, and indeed more proper answer, by
saying,
'No man who used the sea could say where he should be
buried.'"</p></note>

<note id="FitRub5"><seg type="note-symbol">[5]</seg> <p>"Since this paper was written" (adds the
Reviewer
in a note), "we have met with a Copy of a very rare Edition,
printed at
Calcutta in 1836.  This contains 438 Tetrastichs, with an
Appendix
containing 54 others not found in some MSS."</p></note>

<note id="FitRub6"><seg type="note-symbol">[6]</seg> <p>Professor Cowell.
</p></note>


</div1>
</front>

<body id="d6">

<div1 type="poem" id="d7"><pb n="22"/>
<head>RUBAIYAT OF OMAR KHAYYAM: FIRST EDITION</head>

<lg type="stanza" n="I">

<head>I</head>

<l>Awake! for Morning in the Bowl of Night
</l><l>Has flung the Stone that puts the Stars to Flight:
</l><l rend="indent">And Lo! the Hunter of the East has caught
</l><l>The Sult&aacute;n's Turret in a Noose of Light.
</l>
</lg>

<lg type="stanza" n="II"><head>II</head>

<l>Dreaming when Dawn's Left Hand was in the Sky
</l><l>I heard a Voice within the Tavern cry,
</l><l rend="indent">"Awake, my Little ones, and fill the Cup
</l><l>Before Life's Liquor in its Cup be dry."


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="III"><head>III</head>

<l>And, as the Cock crew, those who stood before
</l><l>The Tavern shouted &mdash; "Open then the Door.
</l><l rend="indent">You know how little while we have to stay,
</l><l>And, once departed, may return no more."
</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza" n="IV">
<head>IV</head>

<l>Now the New Year reviving old Desires,
</l><l>The thoughtful Soul to Solitude retires,
</l><l rend="indent">Where the W<hi rend="small-caps">HITE</hi> H<hi rend="small-caps">AND</hi> OF
M<hi rend="small-caps">OSES</hi> on
the Bough
</l><l>Puts out, and Jesus from the Ground suspires.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="V"><head>V</head>

<l>Ir&aacute;m indeed is gone with all its Rose,
</l><l>And Jamsh&yacute;d's Sev'n-ring'd Cup where no one knows;
</l><l rend="indent">But still the Vine her ancient Ruby yields,
</l><l>And still a Garden by the Water blows.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="VI"><head>VI</head>

<l>And David's Lips are lock't; but in divine
</l><l>High piping P&eacute;levi, with "Wine!  Wine!  Wine!
</l><l rend="indent"><hi rend="italic">Red</hi> Wine!" &mdash; the
Nightingale cries to the Rose
</l><l>That yellow Cheek of hers to'incarnadine.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="VII"><head>VII</head>

<l>Come, fill the Cup, and in the Fire of Spring
</l><l>The Winter Garment of Repentance fling:
</l><l rend="indent">The Bird of Time has but a little way
</l><l>To fly &mdash; and Lo! the Bird is on the Wing.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="VIII"><head>VIII</head>

<l>And look &mdash; a thousand Blossoms with the Day
</l><l>Woke &mdash; and a thousand scatter'd into Clay:
</l><l rend="indent">And this first Summer Month that brings the
Rose
</l><l>Shall take Jamsh&yacute;d and Kaikob&aacute;d away.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="IX"><head>IX</head>

<l>But come with old Khayy&aacute;m, and leave the Lot
</l><l>Of Kaikob&aacute;d and Kaikhosr&uacute; forgot:
</l><l rend="indent">Let Rustum lay about him as he will,
</l><l>Or H&aacute;tim Tai cry Supper &mdash; heed them not.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="X"><head>X</head>

<l>With me along some Strip of Herbage strown
</l><l>That just divides the desert from the sown,
</l><l rend="indent">Where name of Slave and Sult&aacute;n scarce
is known
</l><l>And pity Sult&aacute;n M&aacute;hm&uacute;d on his Throne.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XI"><head>XI</head>

<l>Here with a Loaf of Bread beneath the Bough,
</l><l>A Flask of Wine, a Book of Verse &mdash; and Thou
</l><l rend="indent">Beside me singing in the Wilderness &mdash;
</l><l>And Wilderness is Paradise enow.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XII"><head>XII</head>
 <l>

"How sweet is mortal Sovranty!" &mdash; think some: </l>
<l>Others &mdash; "How blest the Paradise to come!"
</l><l rend="indent">Ah, take the Cash in hand and waive the
Rest;
</l><l>Oh, the brave Music of a <hi rend="italic">distant</hi>
Drum!


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XIII"><head>XIII</head>

<l>Look to the Rose that blows about us &mdash; "Lo,
</l><l>Laughing," she says, "into the World I blow:
</l><l rend="indent">At once the silken Tassel of my Purse
</l><l>Tear, and its Treasure on the Garden throw."


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XIV"><head>XIV</head>

<l>The Worldly Hope men set their Hearts upon
</l><l>Turns Ashes &mdash; or it prospers; and anon,
</l><l rend="indent">Like Snow upon the Desert's dusty Face
</l><l>Lighting a little Hour or two &mdash; is gone.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XV"><head>XV</head>

<l>And those who husbanded the Golden Grain,
</l><l>And those who flung it to the Winds like Rain,
</l><l rend="indent">Alike to no such aureate Earth are turn'd
</l><l>As, buried once, Men want dug up again.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XVI"><head>XVI</head>

<l>Think, in this batter'd Caravanserai
</l><l>Whose Doorways are alternate Night and Day,
</l><l rend="indent">How Sult&aacute;n after Sult&aacute;n with
his Pomp
</l><l>Abode his Hour or two, and went his way.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XVII"><head>XVII</head>

<l>They say the Lion and the Lizard keep
</l><l>The Courts where Jamsh&yacute;d gloried and drank deep:
</l><l rend="indent">And Bahr&aacute;m, that great Hunter &mdash; the
Wild Ass
</l><l>Stamps o'er his Head, and he lies fast asleep.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XVIII"><head>XVIII</head>

<l>I sometimes think that never blows so red
</l><l>The Rose as where some buried Caesar bled;
</l><l rend="indent">That every Hyacinth the Garden wears
</l><l>Dropt in its Lap from some once lovely Head.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XIX"><head>XIX</head>

<l>And this delightful Herb whose tender Green
</l><l>Fledges the River's Lip on which we lean &mdash;
</l><l rend="indent">Ah, lean upon it lightly! for who knows
</l><l>From what once lovely Lip it springs unseen!


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XX"><head>XX</head>

<l>Ah! my Beloved, fill the Cup that clears
</l><l><hi rend="small-caps">TO-DAY</hi> of past Regrets and future Fears &mdash;
</l><l rend="indent"><hi rend="italic">To-morrow?</hi> &mdash; Why,
To-morrow I may be
</l><l>Myself with Yesterday's Sev'n Thousand Years.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXI"><head>XXI</head>

<l>Lo! some we loved, the loveliest and the best
</l><l>That Time and Fate of all their Vintage prest,
</l><l rend="indent">Have drunk their Cup a Round or two before,
</l><l>And one by one crept silently to Rest.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXII"><head>XXII</head>

<l>And we, that now make merry in the Room
</l><l>They left, and Summer dresses in new Bloom,
</l><l rend="indent">Ourselves must we beneath the Couch of Earth
</l><l>Descend, ourselves to make a Couch &mdash; for whom?


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXIII"><head>XXIII</head>

<l>Ah, make the most of what we yet may spend,
</l><l>Before we too into the Dust Descend;
</l><l rend="indent">Dust into Dust, and under Dust, to lie,
</l><l>Sans Wine, sans Song, sans Singer and &mdash; sans End!


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXIV"><head>XXIV</head>

<l>Alike for those who for <hi rend="small-caps">TO-DAY</hi> prepare,
</l><l>And those that after a <hi rend="small-caps">TO-MORROW</hi> stare,
</l><l rend="indent">A Muezz&iacute;n from the Tower of Darkness
</l><l>cries "Fools! your Reward is neither Here nor There."

</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXV"><head>XXV</head>

<l>Why, all the Saints and Sages who discuss'd
</l><l>Of the Two Worlds so learnedly, are thrust
</l><l rend="indent">Like foolish Prophets forth; their Words to
Scorn
</l><l>Are scatter'd, and their Mouths are stopt with Dust.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXVI"><head>XXVI</head>

<l>Oh, come with old Khayy&aacute;m, and leave the Wise
</l><l>To talk; one thing is certain, that Life flies;
</l><l rend="indent">One thing is certain, and the Rest is Lies;
</l><l>The Flower that once has blown for ever dies.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXVII"><head>XXVII</head>

<l>Myself when young did eagerly frequent
</l><l>Doctor and Saint, and heard great Argument
</l><l rend="indent">About it and about: but evermore
</l><l>Came out by the same Door as in I went.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXVIII"><head>XXVIII</head>

<l>With them the Seed of Wisdom did I sow,
</l><l>And with my own hand labour'd it to grow:
</l><l rend="indent">And this was all the Harvest that I reap'd
&mdash;
</l><l>
"I came like Water, and like Wind I go."


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXIX"><head>XXIX</head>

<l>Into this Universe, and <hi rend="italic">why</hi> not
knowing,
</l><l>Nor <hi rend="italic">whence</hi>, like Water willy-nilly
flowing:
</l><l rend="indent">And out of it, as Wind along the Waste,
</l><l>I know not <hi rend="italic">whither</hi>, willy-nilly
blowing.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXX"><head>XXX</head>

<l>What, without asking, hither hurried <hi
rend="italic">whence</hi>?
</l><l>And, without asking, <hi rend="italic">whither</hi>
hurried hence!
</l><l rend="indent">Another and another Cup to drown
</l><l>The Memory of this Impertinence!


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXXI"><head>XXXI</head>

<l>Up from Earth's Centre through the seventh Gate
</l><l>I rose, and on the Throne of Saturn sate,
</l><l rend="indent">And many Knots unravel'd by the Road;
</l><l>But not the Knot of Human Death and Fate.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXXII"><head>XXXII</head>

<l>There was a Door to which I found no Key:
</l><l>There was a Veil past which I could not see:
</l><l rend="indent">Some little Talk awhile of <hi rend="small-caps">ME</hi> and
<hi rend="small-caps">THEE</hi>
</l><l>There seemed &mdash; and then no more of <hi rend="small-caps">THEE</hi> and
<hi rend="small-caps">ME</hi>.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXXIII"><head>XXXIII</head>

<l>Then to the rolling Heav'n itself I cried,
</l><l>Asking, "What Lamp had Destiny to guide
</l><l rend="indent">Her little Children stumbling in the Dark?"
</l><l>And &mdash; "A blind understanding!" Heav'n replied.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXXIV"><head>XXXIV</head>

<l>Then to this earthen Bowl did I adjourn
</l><l>My Lip the secret Well of Life to learn:
</l><l rend="indent">And Lip to Lip it murmur'd &mdash; "While you
live,
</l><l>Drink! &mdash; for once dead you never shall return."


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXXV"><head>XXXV</head>

<l>I think the Vessel, that with fugitive
</l><l>Articulation answer'd, once did live,
</l><l rend="indent">And merry-make; and the cold Lip I kiss'd
</l><l>How many Kisses might it take &mdash; and give.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXXVI"><head>XXXVI</head>

<l>For in the Market-place, one Dusk of Day,
</l><l>I watch'd the Potter thumping his wet Clay:
</l><l rend="indent">And with its all obliterated Tongue
</l><l>It murmur'd &mdash; "Gently, Brother, gently, pray!"


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXXVII"><head>XXXVII</head>

<l>Ah, fill the Cup: &mdash; what boots it to repeat
</l><l>How Time is slipping underneath our Feet:
</l><l rend="indent">Unborn <hi rend="small-caps">TO-MORROW</hi> and dead
<hi rend="small-caps">YESTERDAY</hi>,
</l><l>Why fret about them if <hi rend="small-caps">TO-DAY</hi> be sweet!

</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXXVIII"><head>XXXVIII</head>

<l>One Moment in Annihilation's Waste,
</l><l>One moment, of the Well of Life to taste &mdash;
</l><l rend="indent">The Stars are setting, and the Caravan
</l><l>Starts for the dawn of Nothing &mdash; Oh, make haste!

</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXXIX"><head>XXXIX</head>

<l>How long, how long, in infinite Pursuit
</l><l>Of This and That endeavour and dispute?
</l><l rend="indent">Better be merry with the fruitful Grape
</l><l>Than sadden after none, or bitter, Fruit.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XL"><head>XL</head>

<l>You know, my Friends, how long since in my House
</l><l>For a new Marriage I did make Carouse:
</l><l rend="indent">Divorced old barren Reason from my Bed,
</l><l>And took the Daughter of the Vine to Spouse.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XLI"><head>XLI</head>

<l>For "I<hi rend="small-caps">s"</hi> and "I<hi rend="small-caps">s-NOT"</hi> though <hi
rend="italic">with</hi>
</l><l>Rule and Line,
</l><l>And, <hi rend="small-caps">"UP-AND-DOWN"</hi> <hi
rend="italic">without</hi>, I could
define,
</l><l rend="indent">I yet in all I only cared to know,
</l><l>Was never deep in anything but &mdash; Wine.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XLII"><head>XLII</head>

<l>And lately, by the Tavern Door agape,
</l><l>Came stealing through the Dusk an Angel Shape,
</l><l rend="indent">Bearing a vessel on his Shoulder; and
</l><l>He bid me taste of it; and 'twas &mdash; the Grape!


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XLIII"><head>XLIII</head>

<l>The Grape that can with Logic absolute
</l><l>The Two-and-Seventy jarring Sects confute:
</l><l rend="indent">The subtle Alchemist that in a Trice
</l><l>Life's leaden Metal into Gold transmute.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XLIV"><head>XLIV</head>

<l>The mighty Mahm&uacute;d, the victorious Lord,
</l><l>That all the misbelieving and black Horde
</l><l rend="indent">Of Fears and Sorrows that infest the Soul
</l><l>Scatters and slays with his enchanted Sword.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XLV"><head>XLV</head>

<l>But leave the Wise to wrangle, and with me
</l><l>The Quarrel of the Universe let be:
</l><l rend="indent">And, in some corner of the Hubbub coucht,
</l><l>Make Game of that which makes as much of Thee.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XLVI"><head>XLVI</head>

<l>For in and out, above, about, below,
</l><l>'Tis nothing but a Magic Shadow-show,
</l><l rend="indent">Play'd in a Box whose Candle is the Sun,
</l><l>Round which we Phantom Figures come and go.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XLVII"><head>XLVII</head>

<l>And if the Wine you drink, the Lip you press,
</l><l>End in the Nothing all Things end in &mdash; Yes &mdash;
</l><l rend="indent">Then fancy while Thou art, Thou art but what
</l><l>Thou shalt be &mdash; Nothing &mdash; Thou shalt not be less.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XLVIII"><head>XLVIII</head>

<l>While the Rose blows along the River Brink,
</l><l>With old Khayy&aacute;m the Ruby Vintage drink:
</l><l rend="indent">And when the Angel with his darker Draught
</l><l>Draws up to thee &mdash; take that, and do not shrink.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XLVIX"><head>XLVIX</head>
 <l>
'Tis all a Chequer-board of Nights and Days </l>
<l>Where Destiny with Men for Pieces plays:
</l><l rend="indent">Hither and thither moves, and mates, and
slays,
</l><l>And one by one back in the Closet lays.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="L"><head>L</head>

<l>The Ball no Question makes of Ayes and Noes,
</l><l>But Right or Left as strikes the Player goes;
</l><l rend="indent">And He that toss'd Thee down into the Field,
</l><l><hi rend="italic">He</hi> knows about it all &mdash;
H<hi rend="small-caps">E</hi> knows &mdash; HE
knows!


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LI"><head>LI</head>

<l>The Moving Finger writes; and, having writ,
</l><l>Moves on: nor all thy Piety nor Wit
</l><l rend="indent">Shall lure it back to cancel half a Line,
</l><l>Nor all thy Tears wash out a Word of it.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LII"><head>LII</head>

<l>And that inverted Bowl we call The Sky,
</l><l>Whereunder crawling coop't we live and die,
</l><l rend="indent">Lift not thy hands to <hi
rend="italic">It</hi> for help &mdash; for It
</l><l>Rolls impotently on as Thou or I.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LIII"><head>LIII</head>

<l>With Earth's first Clay They did the Last Man's knead,
</l><l>And then of the Last Harvest sow'd the Seed:
</l><l rend="indent">Yea, the first Morning of Creation wrote
</l><l>What the Last Dawn of Reckoning shall read.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LIV"><head>LIV</head>

<l>I tell Thee this &mdash; When, starting from the Goal,
</l><l>Over the shoulders of the flaming Foal
</l><l rend="indent">Of Heav'n Parw&iacute;n and Mushtar&iacute;
they flung,
</l><l>In my predestin'd Plot of Dust and Soul


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LV"><head>LV</head>

<l>The Vine had struck a Fibre; which about
</l><l>It clings my Being &mdash; let the S&uacute;fi flout;
</l><l rend="indent">Of my Base Metal may be filed a Key,
</l><l>That shall unlock the Door he howls without.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LVI"><head>LVI</head>

<l>And this I know: whether the one True Light,
</l><l>Kindle to Love, or Wrath consume me quite,
</l><l rend="indent">One Glimpse of It within the Tavern caught
</l><l>Better than in the Temple lost outright.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LVII"><head>LVII</head>

<l>Oh Thou who didst with Pitfall and with Gin
</l><l>Beset the Road I was to wander in,
</l><l rend="indent">Thou wilt not with Predestination round
</l><l>Enmesh me, and impute my Fall to Sin?


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LVIII"><head>LVIII</head>

<l>Oh Thou, who Man of baser Earth didst make,
</l><l>And who with Eden didst devise the Snake;
</l><l rend="indent">For all the Sin wherewith the Face of Man
</l><l>Is blacken'd, Man's Forgiveness give &mdash; and take!
</l><l rend="indent">             *  *  *  *  *


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LIX"><head type="main">LIX</head>

<head type="sub">KUZA &mdash; N&Aacute;MA</head>

<l>Listen again.  One Evening at the Close
</l><l>Of Ramaz&aacute;n, ere the better Moon arose,
</l><l rend="indent">In that old Potter's Shop I stood alone
</l><l>With the clay Population round in Rows.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LX"><head>LX</head>

<l>And strange to tell, among that Earthen Lot
</l><l>Some could articulate, while others not:
</l><l rend="indent">And suddenly one more impatient cried &mdash;
</l><l>"Who <hi rend="italic">is</hi> the Potter, pray, and who the
Pot?"


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXI"><head>LXI</head>

<l>Then said another &mdash; "Surely not in vain
</l><l>My substance from the common Earth was ta'en,
</l><l rend="indent">That He who subtly wrought me into Shape
</l><l>Should stamp me back to common Earth again."


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXII"><head>LXII</head>

<l>Another said &mdash; "Why, ne'er a peevish Boy
</l><l>Would break the Bowl from which he drank in Joy;
</l><l rend="indent">Shall He that <hi rend="italic">made</hi>
the Vessel in pure Love
</l><l>And Fansy, in an after Rage destroy!"


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXIII"><head>LXIII</head>

<l>None answer'd this; but after Silence spake
</l><l>A Vessel of a more ungainly Make:
</l><l rend="indent">"They sneer at me for leaning all awry;
</l><l>What? did the Hand then of the Potter shake?"


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXIV"><head>LXIV</head>

<l>Said one &mdash; "Folks of a surly Tapster tell,
</l><l>And daub his Visage with the Smoke of Hell;
</l><l rend="indent">They talk of some strict Testing of us &mdash;
Pish!
</l><l>He's a Good Fellow, and 'twill all be well."


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXV"><head>LXV</head>

<l>Then said another with a long-drawn Sigh,
</l><l>"My Clay with long oblivion is gone dry:
</l><l rend="indent">But, fill me with the old familiar Juice,
</l><l>Methinks I might recover by-and-bye!"


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXVI"><head>LXVI</head>

<l>So, while the Vessels one by one were speaking,
</l><l>One spied the little Crescent all were seeking:
</l><l rend="indent">And then they jogg'd each other, "Brother!
Brother!
</l><l>Hark to the Porter's Shoulder-knot a-creaking!"
</l><l rend="indent">             *  *  *  *  *


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXVII"><head>LXVII</head>

<l>Ah, with the Grape my fading Life provide,
</l><l>And wash my Body whence the life has died,
</l><l rend="indent">And in a Windingsheet of Vineleaf wrapt,
</l><l>So bury me by some sweet Gardenside.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXVIII"><head>LXVIII</head>

<l>That ev'n my buried Ashes such a Snare
</l><l>Of Perfume shall fling up into the Air,
</l><l rend="indent">As not a True Believer passing by
</l><l>But shall be overtaken unaware.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXIX"><head>LXIX</head>

<l>Indeed, the Idols I have loved so long
</l><l>Have done my Credit in Men's Eye much wrong:
</l><l rend="indent">Have drown'd my Honour in a shallow Cup,
</l><l>And sold my Reputation for a Song.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXX"><head>LXX</head>

<l>Indeed, indeed, Repentance oft before
</l><l>I swore &mdash; but was I sober when I swore?
</l><l rend="indent">And then and then came Spring, and Rose-in
 hand
</l><l>My thread-bare Penitence a-pieces tore.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXXI"><head>LXXI</head>

<l>And much as Wine has play'd the Infidel,
</l><l>And robb'd me of my Robe of Honour &mdash; well,
</l><l rend="indent">I often wonder what the Vintners buy
</l><l>One half so precious as the Goods they sell.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXXII"><head>LXXII</head>

<l>Alas, that Spring should vanish with the Rose!
</l><l>That Youth's sweet-scented Manuscript should close!
</l><l rend="indent">The Nightingale that in the Branches sang,
</l><l>Ah, whence, and whither flown again, who knows?


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXXIII"><head>LXXIII</head>
<l>Ah, Love! could thou and I with Fate conspire
</l><l>To grasp this sorry Scheme of Things entire,
</l><l rend="indent">Would not we shatter it to bits &mdash; and then
</l><l>Re-mould it nearer to the Heart's Desire!


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXXIV"><head>LXXIV</head>


<l>Ah, Moon of my Delight who know'st no wane,
</l><l>The Moon of Heav'n is rising once again:
</l><l rend="indent">How oft hereafter rising shall she look
</l><l>Through this same Garden after me &mdash; in vain!


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXXV"><head>LXXV</head>

<l>And when Thyself with shining Foot shall pass
</l><l>Among the Guests Star-scatter'd on The Grass,
</l><l rend="indent">And in Thy joyous Errand reach the Spot
</l><l>Where I made one &mdash; turn down an empty Glass!
</l>
 <l>
  TAM&Aacute;m SHUD.
</l>
</lg>
</div1>
<div1 type="poem" id="d8">
<head>RUB&Aacute;IY&Aacute;T OF OMAR
KHAYY&Aacute;M: FIFTH EDITION </head>

<lg type="stanza" n="I"><head>I.</head>

<l>WAKE! For the Sun, who scatter'd into flight
</l><l>The Stars before him from the Field of Night,
</l><l rend="indent">Drives Night along with them from Heav'n,
and strikes
</l><l>The Sult&aacute;n's Turret with a Shaft of Light.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="II"><head>II.</head>

<l>Before the phantom of False morning died,
</l><l>Methought a Voice within the Tavern cried,
</l><l rend="indent">"When all the Temple is prepared within,
</l><l>"Why nods the drowsy Worshiper outside?"


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="III"><head>III.</head>

<l>And, as the Cock crew, those who stood before
</l><l>The Tavern shouted &mdash; "Open then the Door!
</l><l rend="indent">"You know how little while we have to stay,
</l><l>And, once departed, may return no more."


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="IV"><head>IV.</head>

<l>Now the New Year reviving old Desires,
</l><l>The thoughtful Soul to Solitude retires,
</l><l rend="indent">Where the WHITE HAND OF MOSES on the Bough
</l><l>Puts out, and Jesus from the Ground suspires.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="V"><head>V.</head>

<l>Ir&aacute;m indeed is gone with all his Rose,
</l><l>And Jamsh&yacute;d's Sev'n-ring'd Cup where no one knows;
</l><l rend="indent">But still a Ruby kindles in the Vine,
</l><l>And many a Garden by the Water blows.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="VI"><head>VI.</head>

<l>And David's lips are lockt; but in divine
</l><l>High-piping Pehlev&iacute;, with "Wine! Wine! Wine!
</l><l rend="indent">"Red Wine!" &mdash; the Nightingale cries to the
Rose
</l><l>That sallow cheek of hers to' incarnadine.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="VII"><head>VII.</head>

<l>Come, fill the Cup, and in the fire of Spring
</l><l>Your Winter garment of Repentance fling:
</l><l rend="indent">The Bird of Time has but a little way
</l><l>To flutter &mdash; and the Bird is on the Wing.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="VIII"><head>VIII.</head>

<l>Whether at Naish&aacute;p&uacute;r or Babylon,
</l><l>Whether the Cup with sweet or bitter run,
</l><l rend="indent">The Wine of Life keeps oozing drop by drop,
</l><l>The Leaves of Life keep falling one by one.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="IX"><head>IX.</head>

<l>Each Morn a thousand Roses brings, you say:
</l><l>Yes, but where leaves the Rose of Yesterday?
</l><l rend="indent">And this first Summer month that brings the
Rose
</l><l>Shall take Jamsh&yacute;d and Kaikob&aacute;d away.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="X"><head>X.</head>

<l>Well, let it take them!  What have we to do
</l><l>With Kaikob&aacute;d the Great, or Kaikhosr&uacute;?
</l><l rend="indent">Let Z&aacute;l and Rustum bluster as they
will,
</l><l>Or H&aacute;tim call to Supper &mdash; heed not you.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XI"><head>XI.</head>

<l>With me along the strip of Herbage strown
</l><l>That just divides the desert from the sown,
</l><l rend="indent">Where name of Slave and Sult&aacute;n is
forgot &mdash;
</l><l>And Peace to Mahm&uacute;d on his golden Throne!


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XII"><head>XII.</head>

<l>A Book of Verses underneath the Bough,
</l><l>A Jug of Wine, a Loaf of Bread &mdash; and Thou
</l><l rend="indent">Beside me singing in the Wilderness &mdash;
</l><l>Oh, Wilderness were Paradise enow!


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XIII"><head>XIII.</head>

<l>Some for the Glories of This World; and some
</l><l>Sigh for the Prophet's Paradise to come;
</l><l rend="indent">Ah, take the Cash, and let the Credit go,
</l><l>Nor heed the rumble of a distant Drum!


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XIV"><head>XIV.</head>

<l>Look to the blowing Rose about us &mdash; "Lo,
</l><l>Laughing," she says, "into the world I blow,
</l><l rend="indent">At once the silken tassel of my Purse
</l><l>Tear, and its Treasure on the Garden throw."


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XV"><head>XV.</head>

<l>And those who husbanded the Golden grain,
</l><l>And those who flung it to the winds like Rain,
</l><l rend="indent">Alike to no such aureate Earth are turn'd
</l><l>As, buried once, Men want dug up again.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XVI"><head>XVI.</head>

<l>The Worldly Hope men set their Hearts upon
</l><l>Turns Ashes &mdash; or it prospers; and anon,
</l><l rend="indent">Like Snow upon the Desert's dusty Face,
</l><l>Lighting a little hour or two &mdash; is gone.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XVII"><head>XVII.</head>

<l>Think, in this batter'd Caravanserai
</l><l>Whose Portals are alternate Night and Day,
</l><l rend="indent">How Sult&aacute;n after Sult&aacute;n with
his Pomp
</l><l>Abode his destined Hour, and went his way.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XVIII"><head>XVIII.</head>

<l>They say the Lion and the Lizard keep
</l><l>The courts where Jamsh&yacute;d gloried and drank deep:
</l><l rend="indent">And Bahr&aacute;m, that great Hunter &mdash; the
Wild Ass
</l><l>Stamps o'er his Head, but cannot break his Sleep.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XIX"><head>XIX.</head>

<l>I sometimes think that never blows so red
</l><l>The Rose as where some buried Caesar bled;
</l><l rend="indent">That every Hyacinth the Garden wears
</l><l>Dropt in her Lap from some once lovely Head.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XX"><head>XX.</head>

<l>And this reviving Herb whose tender Green
</l><l>Fledges the River-Lip on which we lean &mdash;
</l><l rend="indent">Ah, lean upon it lightly! for who knows
</l><l>>From what once lovely Lip it springs unseen!

</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXI"><head>XXI.</head>

<l>Ah, my Beloved, fill the Cup that clears
</l><l>TO-DAY of past Regrets and future Fears:
</l><l rend="indent"><hi rend="italic">To-morrow</hi> &mdash; Why,
To-morrow I may be
</l><l>Myself with Yesterday's Sev'n thousand Years.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXII"><head>XXII.</head>

<l>For some we loved, the loveliest and the best
</l><l>That from his Vintage rolling Time hath prest,
</l><l rend="indent">Have drunk their Cup a Round or two before,
</l><l>And one by one crept silently to rest.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXIII"><head>XXIII.</head>

<l>And we, that now make merry in the Room
</l><l>They left, and Summer dresses in new bloom,
</l><l rend="indent">Ourselves must we beneath the Couch of Earth
</l><l>Descend &mdash; ourselves to make a Couch &mdash; for whom?


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXIV"><head>XXIV.</head>

<l>Ah, make the most of what we yet may spend,
</l><l>Before we too into the Dust descend;
</l><l rend="indent">Dust into Dust, and under Dust to lie,
</l><l>Sans Wine, sans Song, sans Singer, and &mdash; sans End!


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXV"><head>XXV.</head>

<l>Alike for those who for TO-DAY prepare,
</l><l>And those that after some TO-MORROW stare,
</l><l rend="indent">A Muezz&iacute;n from the Tower of Darkness
cries,
</l><l>
"Fools! your Reward is neither Here nor There."


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXVI"><head>XXVI.</head>

<l>Why, all the Saints and Sages who discuss'd
</l><l>Of the Two Worlds so wisely &mdash; they are thrust
</l><l rend="indent">Like foolish Prophets forth; their Words to
Scorn
</l><l>Are scatter'd, and their Mouths are stopt with Dust.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXVII"><head>XXVII.</head>

<l>Myself when young did eagerly frequent
</l><l>Doctor and Saint, and heard great argument
</l><l rend="indent">About it and about: but evermore
</l><l>Came out by the same door where in I went.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXVIII"><head>XXVIII.</head>

<l>With them the seed of Wisdom did I sow,
</l><l>And with mine own hand wrought to make it grow;
</l><l rend="indent">And this was all the Harvest that I reap'd
&mdash;
</l><l>"I came like Water, and like Wind I go."


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXIX"><head>XXIX.</head>

<l>Into this Universe, and <hi rend="italic">Why</hi> not
knowing
</l><l>Nor <hi rend="italic">Whence</hi>, like Water willy-nilly
flowing;
</l><l rend="indent">And out of it, as Wind along the Waste,
</l><l>I know not <hi rend="italic">Whither</hi>, willy-nilly
blowing.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXX"><head>XXX.</head>

<l>What, without asking, hither hurried <hi
rend="italic">Whence?</hi>
</l><l>And, without asking, <hi rend="italic">Whither</hi>
hurried hence!
</l><l rend="indent">Oh, many a Cup of this forbidden Wine
</l><l>Must drown the memory of that insolence!


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXXI"><head>XXXI.</head>

<l>Up from Earth's Center through the Seventh Gate
</l><l>I rose, and on the Throne of Saturn sate,
</l><l rend="indent">And many a Knot unravel'd by the Road;
</l><l>But not the Master-knot of Human Fate.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXXII"><head>XXXII.</head>

<l>There was the Door to which I found no Key;
</l><l>There was the Veil through which I might not see:
</l><l rend="indent">Some little talk awhile of M<hi rend="small-caps">E</hi> and
T<hi rend="small-caps">HEE</hi>
</l><l>There was &mdash; and then no more of T<hi rend="small-caps">HEE</hi> and
M<hi rend="small-caps">E</hi>.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXXIII"><head>XXXIII.</head>

<l>Earth could not answer; nor the Seas that mourn
</l><l>In flowing Purple, of their Lord Forlorn;
</l><l rend="indent">Nor rolling Heaven, with all his Signs
reveal'd
</l><l>And hidden by the sleeve of Night and Morn.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXXIV"><head>XXXIV.</head>

<l>Then of the T<hi rend="small-caps">HEE IN</hi> M<hi rend="small-caps">E</hi> who works behind
</l><l>The Veil, I lifted up my hands to find
</l><l rend="indent">A lamp amid the Darkness; and I heard,
</l><l>As from Without &mdash;
"T<hi rend="small-caps">HE</hi> M<hi rend="small-caps">E</hi>
W<hi rend="small-caps">ITHIN</hi> T<hi rend="small-caps">HEE
BLIND</hi>!"
</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXXV"><head>XXXV.</head>

<l>Then to the Lip of this poor earthen Urn
</l><l>I lean'd, the Secret of my Life to learn:
</l><l rend="indent">And Lip to Lip it murmur'd &mdash; "While you
live,
</l><l>
"Drink! &mdash; for, once dead, you never shall return."


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXXVI"><head>XXXVI.</head>

<l>I think the Vessel, that with fugitive
</l><l>Articulation answer'd, once did live,
</l><l rend="indent">And drink; and Ah! the passive Lip I kiss'd,
</l><l>How many Kisses might it take &mdash; and give!


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXXVII"><head>XXXVII.</head>

<l>For I remember stopping by the way
</l><l>To watch a Potter thumping his wet Clay:
</l><l rend="indent">And with its all-obliterated Tongue
</l><l>It murmur'd &mdash; "Gently, Brother, gently, pray!"


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXXVIII"><head>XXXVIII.</head>

<l>And has not such a Story from of Old
</l><l>Down Man's successive generations roll'd
</l><l rend="indent">Of such a clod of saturated Earth
</l><l>Cast by the Maker into Human mold?


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XXXIX"><head>XXXIX.</head>

<l>And not a drop that from our Cups we throw
</l><l>For Earth to drink of, but may steal below
</l><l rend="indent">To quench the fire of Anguish in some Eye
</l><l>There hidden &mdash; far beneath, and long ago.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XL"><head>XL.</head>

<l>As then the Tulip for her morning sup
</l><l>Of Heav'nly Vintage from the soil looks up,
</l><l rend="indent">Do you devoutly do the like, till Heav'n
</l><l>To Earth invert you &mdash; like an empty Cup.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XLI"><head>XLI.</head>

<l>Perplext no more with Human or Divine,
</l><l>To-morrow's tangle to the winds resign,
</l><l rend="indent">And lose your fingers in the tresses of
</l><l>The Cypress-slender Minister of Wine.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XLII"><head>XLII.</head>

<l>And if the Wine you drink, the Lip you press,
</l><l>End in what All begins and ends in &mdash; Y<hi rend="small-caps">ES</hi>;
</l><l rend="indent">Think then you are T<hi rend="small-caps">O-DAY</hi> what
Y<hi rend="small-caps">ESTERDAY</hi>
</l><l>You were &mdash; T<hi rend="small-caps">O-MORROW</hi> you shall not be less.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XLIII"><head>XLIII.</head>

<l>So when that Angel of the darker Drink
</l><l>At last shall find you by the river-brink,
</l><l rend="indent">And, offering his Cup, invite your Soul
</l><l>Forth to you Lips to quaff &mdash; you shall not shrink.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XLIV"><head>XLIV.</head>

<l>Why, if the Soul can fling the Dust aside,
</l><l>And naked on the Air of Heaven ride,
</l><l rend="indent">Were't not a Shame &mdash; were't not a Shame for
him
</l><l>In this clay carcass crippled to abide?


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XLV"><head>XLV.</head>

<l>'Tis but a Tent where takes his one day's rest
</l><l>A Sult&aacute;n to the realm of Death addrest;
</l><l rend="indent">The Sult&aacute;n rises, and the dark Ferrash
</l><l>Strikes, and prepares it for another Guest.
</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XLVI"><head>XLVI.</head>

<l>And fear not lest Existence closing your
</l><l>Account, and mine, should know the like no more;
</l><l rend="indent">The Eternal S&aacute;k&iacute; from that
Bowl has pour'd
</l><l>Millions of Bubbles like us, and will pour.
</l></lg>

<lg type="stanza" n="XLVII"><head>XLVII.</head>

<l>When You and I behind the Veil are past,
</l><l>Oh, but the long, long while the World shall last,
</l><l rend="indent">Which of our Coming and Departure heeds
</l><l>As the Sea's self should heed a pebble-cast.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XLVIII"><head>XLVIII.</head>

<l>A Moment's Halt &mdash; a momentary taste
</l><l>Of B<hi rend="small-caps">EING</hi> from the Well amid the Waste &mdash;
</l><l rend="indent">And Lo! &mdash; the phantom Caravan has reach'd
</l><l>The N<hi rend="small-caps">OTHING</hi> it set out from &mdash; Oh, make haste!


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XLIX"><head>XLIX.</head>

<l>Would you that spangle of Existence spend
</l><l>About <hi rend="small-caps">THE SECRET</hi> &mdash; quick about it, Friend!
</l><l rend="indent">A Hair perhaps divides the False from True
&mdash;
</l><l>And upon what, prithee, may life depend?


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="L"><head>L.</head>

<l>A Hair perhaps divides the False and True;
</l><l>Yes; and a single Alif were the clue &mdash;
</l><l rend="indent">Could you but find it &mdash; to the
Treasure-house,
</l><l>And peradventure to T<hi rend="small-caps">HE</hi> M<hi rend="small-caps">ASTER</hi> too;


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LI"><head>LI.</head>

<l>Whose secret Presence through Creation's veins
</l><l>Running Quicksilver-like eludes your pains;
</l><l rend="indent">Taking all shapes from M&aacute;h to
M&aacute;hi and
</l><l>They change and perish all &mdash; but He remains;


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LII"><head>LII.</head>

<l>A moment guessed &mdash; then back behind the Fold
</l><l>Immerst of Darkness round the Drama roll'd
</l><l rend="indent">Which, for the Pastime of Eternity,
</l><l>He doth Himself contrive, enact, behold.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LIII"><head>LIII.</head>

<l>But if in vain, down on the stubborn floor
</l><l>Of Earth, and up to Heav'n's unopening Door,
</l><l rend="indent">You gaze T<hi rend="small-caps">O-DAY</hi>, while You are You
&mdash; how then
</l><l>T<hi rend="small-caps">O-MORROW</hi>, when You shall be You no more?


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LIV"><head>LIV.</head>

<l>Waste not your Hour, nor in the vain pursuit
</l><l>Of This and That endeavor and dispute;
</l><l rend="indent">Better be jocund with the fruitful Grape
</l><l>Than sadden after none, or bitter, Fruit.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LV"><head>LV.</head>

<l>You know, my Friends, with what a brave Carouse
</l><l>I made a Second Marriage in my house;
</l><l rend="indent">Divorced old barren Reason from my Bed,
</l><l>And took the Daughter of the Vine to Spouse.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LVI"><head>LVI.</head>

<l>For "Is" and "Is-not" though with Rule and Line
</l><l>And "U<hi rend="small-caps">P-AND-DOWN"</hi> by Logic I define,
</l><l rend="indent">Of all that one should care to fathom, I
</l><l>Was never deep in anything but &mdash; Wine.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LVII"><head>LVII.</head>

<l>Ah, by my Computations, People say,
</l><l>Reduce the Year to better reckoning? &mdash; Nay,
</l><l rend="indent">'Twas only striking from the Calendar
</l><l>Unborn To-morrow and dead Yesterday.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LVIII"><head>LVIII.</head>

<l>And lately, by the Tavern Door agape,
</l><l>Came shining through the Dusk an Angel Shape
</l><l rend="indent">Bearing a Vessel on his Shoulder; and
</l><l>He bid me taste of it; and 'twas &mdash; the Grape!


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LIX"><head>LIX.</head>

<l>The Grape that can with Logic absolute
</l><l>The Two-and-Seventy jarring Sects confute:
</l><l rend="indent">The sovereign Alchemist that in a trice
</l><l>Life's leaden metal into Gold transmute;


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LX"><head>LX.</head>

<l>The mighty Mahm&uacute;d, Allah-breathing Lord,
</l><l>That all the misbelieving and black Horde
</l><l rend="indent">Of Fears and Sorrows that infest the Soul
</l><l>Scatters before him with his whirlwind Sword.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXI"><head>LXI.</head>

<l>Why, be this Juice the growth of God, who dare
</l><l>Blaspheme the twisted tendril as a Snare?
</l><l rend="indent">A Blessing, we should use it, should we not?
</l><l>And if a Curse &mdash; why, then, Who set it there?


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXII"><head>LXII.</head>

<l>I must abjure the Balm of Life, I must,
</l><l>Scared by some After-reckoning ta'en on trust,
</l><l rend="indent">Or lured with Hope of some Diviner Drink,
</l><l>To fill the Cup &mdash; when crumbled into Dust!


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXIII"><head>LXIII.</head>

<l>Of threats of Hell and Hopes of Paradise!
</l><l>One thing at least is certain &mdash; <hi
rend="italic">This</hi> Life flies;
</l><l rend="indent">One thing is certain and the rest is Lies;
</l><l>The Flower that once has blown for ever dies.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXIV"><head>LXIV.</head>

<l>Strange, is it not? that of the myriads who
</l><l>Before us pass'd the door of Darkness through,
</l><l rend="indent">Not one returns to tell us of the Road,
</l><l>Which to discover we must travel too.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXV"><head>LXV.</head>

<l>The Revelations of Devout and Learn'd
</l><l>Who rose before us, and as Prophets burn'd,
</l><l rend="indent">Are all but Stories, which, awoke from Sleep
</l><l>They told their comrades, and to Sleep return'd.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXVI"><head>LXVI.</head>

<l>I sent my Soul through the Invisible,
</l><l>Some letter of that After-life to spell:
</l><l rend="indent">And by and by my Soul return'd to me,
</l><l>And answer'd "I Myself am Heav'n and Hell:"


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXVII"><head>LXVII.</head>

<l>Heav'n but the Vision of fulfill'd Desire,
</l><l>And Hell the Shadow from a Soul on fire,
</l><l rend="indent">Cast on the Darkness into which Ourselves,
</l><l>So late emerged from, shall so soon expire.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXVIII"><head>LXVIII.</head>

<l>We are no other than a moving row
</l><l>Of Magic Shadow-shapes that come and go
</l><l rend="indent">Round with the Sun-illumined Lantern held
</l><l>In Midnight by the Master of the Show;


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXIX"><head>LXIX.</head>

<l>But helpless Pieces of the Game He plays
</l><l>Upon this Chequer-board of Nights and Days;
</l><l rend="indent">Hither and thither moves, and checks, and
slays,
</l><l>And one by one back in the Closet lays.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXX"><head>LXX.</head>

<l>The Ball no question makes of Ayes and Noes,
</l><l>But Here or There as strikes the Player goes;
</l><l rend="indent">And He that toss'd you down into the Field,
</l><l><hi rend="italic">He</hi> knows about it all &mdash;
<hi rend="small-caps">HE</hi> knows &mdash; HE
knows!


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXXI"><head>LXXI.</head>

<l>The Moving Finger writes; and, having writ,
</l><l>Moves on: nor all your Piety nor Wit
</l><l rend="indent">Shall lure it back to cancel half a Line,
</l><l>Nor all your Tears wash out a Word of it.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXXII"><head>LXXII.</head>

<l>And that inverted Bowl they call the Sky,
</l><l>Whereunder crawling coop'd we live and die,
</l><l rend="indent">Lift not your hands to <hi
rend="italic">It</hi> for help &mdash; for It
</l><l>As impotently moves as you or I.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXXIII"><head>LXXIII.</head>

<l>With Earth's first Clay They did the Last Man knead,
</l><l>And there of the Last Harvest sow'd the Seed:
</l><l rend="indent">And the first Morning of Creation wrote
</l><l>What the Last Dawn of Reckoning shall read.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXXIV"><head>LXXIV.</head>

<l>Y<hi rend="small-caps">ESTERDAY</hi> <hi rend="italic">This</hi> Day's Madness
did prepare;
</l><l>T<hi rend="small-caps">O-MORROW</hi>'s Silence, Triumph, or Despair:
</l><l rend="indent">Drink! for you not know whence you came, nor
why:
</l><l>Drink! for you know not why you go nor where.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXXV"><head>LXXV.</head>

<l>I tell you this &mdash; When, started from the Goal,
</l><l>Over the flaming shoulders of the Foal
</l><l rend="indent">Of Heav'n Parw&iacute;n and Mushtar&iacute;
they flung,
</l><l>In my predestined Plot of Dust and Soul.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXXVI"><head>LXXVI.</head>

<l>The Vine had struck a fiber: which about
</l><l>It clings my Being &mdash; let the Dervish flout;
</l><l rend="indent">Of my Base metal may be filed a Key
</l><l>That shall unlock the Door he howls without.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXXVII"><head>LXXVII.</head>

<l>And this I know: whether the one True Light
</l><l>Kindle to Love, or Wrath consume me quite,
</l><l rend="indent">One Flash of It within the Tavern caught
</l><l>Better than in the Temple lost outright.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXXVIII"><head>LXXVIII.</head>

<l>What! out of senseless Nothing to provoke
</l><l>A conscious Something to resent the yoke
</l><l rend="indent">Of unpermitted Pleasure, under pain
</l><l>Of Everlasting Penalties, if broke!


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXXIX"><head>LXXIX.</head>

<l>What! from his helpless Creature be repaid
</l><l>Pure Gold for what he lent him dross-allay'd &mdash;
</l><l rend="indent">Sue for a Debt he never did contract,
</l><l>And cannot answer &mdash; Oh the sorry trade!


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXXX"><head>LXXX.</head>

<l>Oh Thou, who didst with pitfall and with gin
</l><l>Beset the Road I was to wander in,
</l><l rend="indent">Thou wilt not with Predestined Evil round
</l><l>Enmesh, and then impute my Fall to Sin!


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXXXI"><head>LXXXI.</head>

<l>Oh Thou, who Man of baser Earth didst make,
</l><l>And ev'n with Paradise devise the Snake:
</l><l rend="indent">For all the Sin wherewith the Face of Man
</l><l>Is blacken'd &mdash; Man's forgiveness give &mdash; and take!
</l><l>
    *    *    *    *    *    *


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXXXII"><head>LXXXII.</head>

<l>As under cover of departing Day
</l><l>Slunk hunger-stricken Ramaz&aacute;n away,
</l><l rend="indent">Once more within the Potter's house alone
</l><l>I stood, surrounded by the Shapes of Clay.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXXXIII"><head>LXXXIII.</head>

<l>Shapes of all Sorts and Sizes, great and small,
</l><l>That stood along the floor and by the wall;
</l><l rend="indent">And some loquacious Vessels were; and some
</l><l>Listen'd perhaps, but never talk'd at all.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXXXIV"><head>LXXXIV.</head>

<l>Said one among them &mdash; "Surely not in vain
</l><l>My substance of the common Earth was ta'en
</l><l rend="indent">And to this Figure molded, to be broke,
</l><l>Or trampled back to shapeless Earth again."


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXXXV"><head>LXXXV.</head>

<l>Then said a Second &mdash; "Ne'er a peevish Boy
</l><l>Would break the Bowl from which he drank in joy;
</l><l rend="indent">And He that with his hand the Vessel made
</l><l>Will surely not in after Wrath destroy."


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXXXVI"><head>LXXXVI.</head>

<l>After a momentary silence spake
</l><l>Some Vessel of a more ungainly Make;
</l><l rend="indent">"They sneer at me for leaning all awry:
</l><l>What! did the Hand then of the Potter shake?"


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXXXVII"><head>LXXXVII.</head>

<l>Whereat some one of the loquacious Lot &mdash;
</l><l>I think a S&uacute;fi pipkin &mdash; waxing hot &mdash;
</l><l rend="indent">"All this of Pot and Potter &mdash; Tell me then,
</l><l>Who is the Potter, pray, and who the Pot?"


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXXXVIII"><head>LXXXVIII.</head>
 <l>
"Why," said another, "Some there are who tell
</l><l>Of one who threatens he will toss to Hell
</l><l rend="indent">The luckless Pots he marr'd in making &mdash;
Pish!
</l><l>He's a Good Fellow, and 'twill all be well."


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="LXXXIX"><head>LXXXIX.</head>
<l>
"Well," murmured one, "Let whoso make or buy,
</l><l>My Clay with long Oblivion is gone dry:
</l><l rend="indent">But fill me with the old familiar Juice,
</l><l>Methinks I might recover by and by."


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XC"><head>XC.</head>

<l>So while the Vessels one by one were speaking,
</l><l>The little Moon look'd in that all were seeking:
</l><l rend="indent">And then they jogg'd each other, "Brother!
Brother!
</l><l>Now for the Porter's shoulders' knot a-creaking!"

</l><l>    *    *    *    *    *    *


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XCI"><head>XCI.</head>

<l>Ah, with the Grape my fading life provide,
</l><l>And wash the Body whence the Life has died,
</l><l rend="indent">And lay me, shrouded in the living Leaf,
</l><l>By some not unfrequented Garden-side.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XCII"><head>XCII.</head>

<l>That ev'n buried Ashes such a snare
</l><l>Of Vintage shall fling up into the Air
</l><l rend="indent">As not a True-believer passing by
</l><l>But shall be overtaken unaware.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XCIII"><head>XCIII.</head>

<l>Indeed the Idols I have loved so long
</l><l>Have done my credit in this World much wrong:
</l><l rend="indent">Have drown'd my Glory in a shallow Cup,
</l><l>And sold my reputation for a Song.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XCIV"><head>XCIV.</head>

<l>Indeed, indeed, Repentance oft before
</l><l>I swore &mdash; but was I sober when I swore?
</l><l rend="indent">And then and then came Spring, and
Rose-in-hand
</l><l>My thread-bare Penitence apieces tore.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XCV"><head>XCV.</head>

<l>And much as Wine has play'd the Infidel,
</l><l>And robb'd me of my Robe of Honor &mdash; Well,
</l><l rend="indent">I wonder often what the Vintners buy
</l><l>One half so precious as the stuff they sell.


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XCVI"><head>XCVI.</head>

<l>Yet Ah, that Spring should vanish with the Rose!
</l><l>That Youth's sweet-scented manuscript should close!
</l><l rend="indent">The Nightingale that in the branches sang,
</l><l>Ah whence, and whither flown again, who knows!


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XCVII"><head>XCVII.</head>

<l>Would but the Desert of the Fountain yield
</l><l>One glimpse &mdash; if dimly, yet indeed, reveal'd,
</l><l rend="indent">To which the fainting Traveler might spring,
</l><l>As springs the trampled herbage of the field!


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XCVIII"><head>XCVIII.</head>

<l>Would but some wing&eacute;d Angel ere too late
</l><l>Arrest the yet unfolded Roll of Fate,
</l><l rend="indent">And make the stern Recorder otherwise
</l><l>Enregister, or quite obliterate!


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="XCIX"><head>XCIX.</head>

<l>Ah Love! could you and I with Him conspire
</l><l>To grasp this sorry Scheme of Things entire,
</l><l rend="indent">Would not we shatter it to bits &mdash; and then
</l><l>Re-mold it nearer to the Heart's Desire!
</l><l>    *    *    *    *    *    *


</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="C"><head>C.</head>

<l>Yon rising Moon that looks for us again &mdash;
</l><l>How oft hereafter will she wax and wane;
</l><l rend="indent">How oft hereafter rising look for us
</l><l>Through this same Garden &mdash; and for <hi
rend="italic">one</hi> in vain!

</l></lg><lg type="stanza" n="CI"><head>CI.</head>

<l>And when like her, oh S&aacute;k&iacute;, you shall pass
</l><l>Among the Guests Star-scatter'd on the Grass,
</l><l rend="indent">And in your joyous errand reach the spot
</l><l>Where I made One &mdash; turn down an empty Glass!
</l></lg>

<closer>              TAMAM. </closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
