<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="FreEman"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

]>

<TEI.2 id="FreEman">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Emancipation</title>
<title type="sort">emancipation</title>
<author>Freeman, Mary Eleanor Wilkins, 1852-1930</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>Judy Boss</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">40</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">FreEman</idno>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 1995 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:475965</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Emancipation</title>
<title type="sort">emancipation</title>
<author>Mary E. Wilkins Freeman</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Harper's Monthly</publisher>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date value="1915-12">December 1915</date>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<p>132</p>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Freeman, Mary E. Wilkins.  "Emancipation."  <hi rend="italic">Harper's Monthly</hi>
     132 (Dec. 1915): 27-35.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All quotation marks retained as data</p>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the
trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme
to aid in establishing analytical groupings</p>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl>
<p>ID elements are given for each page element and are composed of the text's
unique cryptogram and the given page number, as in AusEmma1 for page one of
Jane Austen's Emma.</p>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1915-12">December 1915</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>fiction ; prose</term>
<term>Women Writers</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="1995">1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Judy Boss, University of Omaha</name>
</respStmt>
<item>page 28, paragraph 2 changed
"she was was here,"  to
she was here,"</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="1995-08">August 1995</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>Jamie L Spriggs, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Added header, Tagged with TEI.2-compatible SGML, Parsed against "teilite" dtd</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted SGML to XML. Fixed tagging.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">

<div1 type="story" id="d3"><pb n="27"/>
<head>
                      Emancipation<lb/>
            <hi rend="italic">BY MARY E. WILKINS FREEMAN</hi></head>

<p>OLD Billy Thomas sat beside the window.  He had the weekly
religious newspaper on his knee.  He was not reading it.  He never
read it.  If questioned, he could not have told why he so
apparently cherished it.  There was certainly no affectation about
Billy, and least of all affectation with regard to religion.  He
was a very good old man, leavened to his own amusement with a
queer, childish mischievousness bordering upon the malicious.  This
leaven might not have developed had it not been for his daughter
Esther, who all unwittingly was especially fitted to produce such
development.  Now Esther was not at home.  She had gone down street
on an errand.
</p><p>Billy was very carefully attired.  His collar was immaculate.
Esther had brushed his coat twice that very day.  Billy, left to
himself, would never have brushed his coat.  He had arrived at an
age when his house of life had become to a certain degree perfectly
uninteresting to him.  All he asked of it was a comfortable
acquiescence with his wishes.  He desired no rheumatic pains.
Stiffness he recognized as incident to his endurance in his present
form upon the earth; he bore that with cheerful stolidity.  He
wished for warmth and food for that worn old habitation of flesh,
and he wished more than for anything else for a certain freedom.
That he did not have.  Esther very innocently prevented that.
Billy was like a child who frets because he is not allowed to kick
and sprawl and change monotonous order to disorder.  In reality,
Billy practically wished to make his mud-pies of life instead of
sitting there so carefully combed and brushed, with his religious
newspaper unread on his knees.  He was thinking about his daughter
with a sort of rueful love and admiration and dissent.  He said to
himself, as he often said to Sam Ellis: "Esther is the salt of the
earth.  She's as pretty as they make 'em, and neat, and a good
cook, and she does her duty by me, and she has a hard time of it.
She would have a harder if she didn't naturally expect so much of
men-folks and make allowances.  My daughter is as good and pretty
a woman as you can find in a week of Sundays, but sometimes I
sorter wish she was as easy-goin' as her ma was.  Maybe if her ma
had lived Esther would have been more like her.  She wouldn't have
tried half as hard and she would have been a darned sight better
off, and so would other folks."
</p><p>Billy, thinking of Esther, realized that his heart, loving as
it was toward her, inclined toward rebellion.  A queer expression
was in his bright old eyes.  Suddenly he crumpled the religious
paper viciously, and threw it down on the floor.  Then he stamped
on it.  Then he looked alarmed.  He bent over stiffly, gathered it
up and refolded it.  Then he looked out of the window at the yard
and the horse-chestnut-tree holding its young umbrella-shaped
leaves over its straight trunk.  Old Billy gazed, and his face&mdash;a
very simple old face as to line and feature&mdash;became complex.
</p><p>He looked away from the window at the room perfectly ordered.
There was not a speck of dust.  The vases on the mantel-shelf stood
each in its appointed place.  The books on the table were arranged
in exact little piles.  The lamp stood in the mathematical center.
The table-cover hung with absolute correctness.  The chairs were
ranged about the room as if by line and rule.  Not one picture hung
off the true level.
</p><p>Old Billy regarded everything gloomily.  After a while he got
up and walked past the table, and without apparent intent knocked
against it.  A little vase containing exactly six daffodils was
upset.  The water trickled slowly over the chenille table-cloth and
dripped to <pb n="28"/>  the floor.  A pile of books was pushed awry.  Old
Billy next encountered a steel engraving, "The Landing of the
Pilgrim Fathers."  After he had passed, the picture hung decidedly
off the plumb-line.  Then old Billy, on his way back to his chair,
stumbled over a mat and left it turned up at one end.
</p><p>He sat down and regarded things with a grin.  He looked like
a malevolent child.  He was an old man, but full of wiry strength.
His thick, gray hair and beard had the outward spring of strong
wire.  His eyes were sparklingly alert.
</p><p>Old Billy gazed out of the window.  It was nearly time for
Esther's return.  He was still uneasy.  He gazed as far down the
road as he could, but saw no sign of Esther.  He rose quickly and
fairly ran out of the room.  He returned, and again jostled the
table and "The Landing of the Pilgrim Fathers," and this time he
touched the mantel-shelf.  When he sat down again he could see
distinctly a shadow, as of dust, over the front of the shelf and on
the glass of the picture.  Another pile of books on the table was
awry.  Old Billy raised a hand with the forefinger stiffly crooked,
and rubbed it across the crystal-like window.  There was left a
smear, as of lard.  Old Billy put his hands on the under side of
his coat-tails and rubbed off the butter and flour on them.  Then
he chuckled.  "Ruther guess Betsey would laugh till she cried, ef
she was here," he said aloud.  When Esther entered he was reading
his religious weekly.
</p><p>"All wrapped up in your paper, father?" she remarked in her
clear, fine voice.  Old Billy read on.  Esther crossed the room to
put away her hat and coat.  She removed the hat carefully and put
it on the closet shelf; removed her coat, adjusted it over a
hanger, and replaced it upon its hook.  Then she turned, her thin
hands mechanically smoothing her satin-smooth hair.
</p><p>Esther was a pretty creature in an unassertive fashion.  She
was made of charming shadows instead of colors; of charming delays
rather than progressions.  Her soft hair, neither black nor brown,
although glossy, showed no highlights; her smooth cheeks, flawless
in texture, had no bloom; her gray eyes gave out no sparks of
inward fire even when Esther was firm.
</p><p>Esther was firm after a curious fashion.  She never ordered,
but her attitude was in itself equivalent to a whole broadside of
orders.  She never raised her voice, she often did not express a
wish, but her silence held the force of ultimate command.  Her aged
father, retaining, as he still did in very high measure, the fire
of youth, was no match for her.  His rebellious desires, his
impatience for his own way, were blunted before her as before a
porcelain wall of purest, impenetrable femininity.  Billy's Betsey,
easy-going as she had been, had possessed a temper which her man
could meet in fair fight, and either win or be worsted.  Esther had
apparently no temper whatever.  She had simply character, resistant
in its primary quality.  Old Billy never argued with his daughter.
He was reduced to the slyness of petty diplomacy.  The time was at
hand when he would once more gather himself up for a last
aggressive move, but it had not yet arrived.  He continued to sit
perfectly still, with his eyes fixed upon the printed page before
him.
</p><p>Esther surveyed the disorder of the room.  Old Billy felt her
eyes turn toward him.  He made no sign.  He knew from past
experience that she would not exclaim nor question.  Esther
straightened carefully "The Landing of the Pilgrim Fathers," the
vases on the shelf, the pile of books on the table.  She glided out
of the room and returned with cloths.  She wiped the water from the
overturned vase.  She replaced the daffodils.  She dusted off the
flour.  After she had straightened and dusted everything, and
readjusted the rug which Billy had kicked, she put away the duster.
Billy never raised his eyes.
</p><p>Then, Esther saw the smear on the window-glass.  Even then she
did not exclaim.  She stood staring at it.  The faintest pink had
come over her smooth cheeks.  Her eyes, while still devoid of
sparkle, were alive with wonder.  At last she spoke.
</p><p>"Have you been having some bread and butter, father?" she
asked.
</p><p>Billy apparently did not hear.
</p><p>"Have you been having some bread and butter, father?" repeated
Esther.  [illustration omitted, page unnumbered] <pb n="29"/>
</p><p>"Hey?"
</p><p>"Have you been having some bread and butter?"
</p><p>"No, Esther, I 'ain't," replied Billy, and returned again to
his paper.
</p><p>Esther said no more.  She again went out for a cloth.  This
time she brought a basin of hot water and some polishing-powder.
She could not well reach the window, and Billy moved, hitching his
chair slightly.
</p><p>Esther worked, cleaning off the smear and polishing the glass.
She eyed it, not quite satisfied.  When she went out, evidently to
try her polish on the outside, thinking that some of the trouble
must be there, Billy clapped his hand over his mouth and nearly
choked with repressed mirth.  When Esther appeared on the other
side of his window with her polish, he was reading his paper with
an intensely sober face.
</p><p>Billy enjoyed himself immensely.  These little tricks were his
only amusement.  He loved his daughter, but deep-rooted in his
nature was the love of mischief, even against one whom he loved.
He derived a peculiar pleasure from its exercise in the case of
Esther, because she was so completely unsuspecting.  What she did
suspect her father did not even dream.  Had he dreamed it, he would
have enjoyed it to the full.  Poor Esther Thomas feared her father
was gradually losing his wits from old age.  She had a fair amount
of reason.  She knew perfectly well in what a state of order and
cleanliness she had left the house when she went out.  She knew, of
course, that flour and lard do not of their own volition get on
tables and shelves and windows.  Her father had been the only
person in the house.  Esther was aware that her father must be the
culprit.  He had put her order in disorder; he had sprinkled flour
over spotless surfaces; he had smeared the clear window-glass.
Esther knew this, but her mind could grasp no motive within reason
for the deeds.  She had no conception of mischief for the sake of
mischief, of uneasiness finding its safety-valve.  She therefore
told herself sadly that "poor father was failing," and she must be
even more watchful regarding her duty toward him.
</p><p>Esther Thomas was a sweet woman.  She was sweet like a flower,
blooming only under certain restrictions, facing always one way.
After she had cleaned the window she went into the kitchen and
washed carefully the cloth and her hands.
</p><p>While she was there, old Billy, gazing out, saw Sam Ellis.
Right opposite the Thomas house was the little grocery-store.  Sam
was standing on the piazza gazing longingly over at Billy.  Billy
shook his head, raised his hand, and went through an elaborate code
of signals: Sam understood.  When Esther re-entered the room her
father was having a hard coughing-spell.  Old Billy had rather
violent attacks of asthma.  Esther went to the little chimney
cupboard for a bottle of medicine.
</p><p>"It ain't&mdash;there," strangled Billy.
</p><p>"Why, where is it, father?"
</p><p>"I&mdash;used up&mdash;the last on't&mdash;some days ago&mdash;while you was out,
and I threw the bottle away.  No use of old medicine-bottles
settin' round," Billy coughed and wheezed.
</p><p>Esther went to the closet and got her hat and coat.  Old
Billy, still coughing, watched her slyly.
</p><p>"Where you&mdash;goin'?"
</p><p>"Down to the drug-store to get another bottle of your
medicine.  Keep perfectly still while I am gone, father.  I will be
back as soon as I can."
</p><p>Billy coughed.  He found it rather difficult to desist after
he had watched his daughter out of sight.  He still coughed while
frantically beckoning Sam Ellis on the grocery piazza.
</p><p>Sam shambled over and entered, grinning.  Sam was a shabby
figure.  He came from a good old family, but he was the last shred
of it, swaying and fraying before the winds of destiny, with nobody
of his kith or kin to mend him, or brush him; or attend generally
to his physical welfare.  He lived alone in a corner of the old
Ellis house.  Dreadful tales were told by good housekeepers about
the state of that house and especially Sam's corner.  Carpets had
not been taken up for half a century.  Moth and rust reigned
undisputed.  However, Sam was a happier man than Billy.  He had all
that is sometimes left to the aged of the world, his own way, and
he loved it.
</p><p>Billy gazed at him when he entered, <pb n="30"/>  with a queer
affection and envy.  The two old men loved each other.  Billy
envied; Sam pitied.
</p><p>"How did ye manage it?" queried Sam.
</p><p>"Had a coughin'-spell, and the medicine was all gone."  He
winked and coughed again in spite of himself.
</p><p>"You hadn't ought to take liberties with that cough," said
Sam, anxiously.  Out of a jungle of crisscross lines of white hairs
covering his face his blue eyes gleamed tenderly upon his friend.
His bald head rose dome-like and shining, but his white beard
covered his cheeks and fell upon his breast.  He had been a
handsome man.  He had never married, but he had had in his youth
his love-affair.  The girl whom he had loved had died.
</p><p>Sam could not quite understand Billy's attitude with regard to
his daughter.  "Why d'ye have to manoeuver that way to get a minute
to see me?" he queried, with regard to the cough-medicine.  "Now
Esther always seems to me real mild and gentle."
</p><p>"She is.  Esther's the salt of the earth, and she never gets
mad nor speaks up," declared Billy.
</p><p>"Then why&mdash;"
</p><p>"If she did get mad I wouldn't feel called upon to manoeuver.
She and me could fight it out, and I guess I'd get my own way,"
said Billy.
</p><p>Sam took his venerable pipe out of his pocket.  He looked
inquiringly at Billy, who shook his head.
</p><p>Sam replaced the pipe.  "S'pose it wouldn't do," he admitted.
</p><p>"She would smell it," said Billy.  "I don't never smoke mine
except once in a while in summer-time, when I can get down in the
orchard, and the wind ain't toward the house, and she's gone out
anyway."
</p><p>"What does she say?"
</p><p>"She don't say nothin'.  She don't even sniff round the way
some women would.  Esther is a lady, if she is my daughter.  I jest
know it wouldn't do for me to smoke my old pipe around the house as
long as she's livin' here, so I keep it in the lowermost secretary
drawer."
</p><p>Sam regarded Billy thoughtfully.  He got up and peered down
the street.
</p><p>"It ain't time for her yet," said Billy.
</p><p>Sam thrust his face close to Billy's and whispered, "When is
she goin' to git married to the parson?"
</p><p>"She ain't never goin' to as long as I live."
</p><p>"How d'ye know?"
</p><p>"She told him so.  She said it was her duty to stay right here
and take care of me.  He acted real nice about it; said I would be
jest as welcome to live with 'em as if I was his own father.  But
she told him he couldn't leave his mother, and neither of 'em said
anything, but both of 'em knew that wouldn't work&mdash;old lady
Comstock livin' with her daughter-in-law's pa."
</p><p>Sam chuckled.  "Golly!  You couldn't hev said your soul was
your own, sure enough," he remarked.
</p><p>Billy chuckled in response.  "Reckon you're right.  Betwixt
Esther's holdin' her tongue and the old lady not holdin' hers, it'd
been a case of the upper and nether millstones," said he.  "Esther
and Willard both knew that wouldn't do, and Esther, she won't leave
me nohow."
</p><p>"You could git along."
</p><p>Billy fairly snorted.  "Git along!  I ruther reckon I could!
I could git Sarah Miles to come here.  She's spry and a good
housekeeper, and she 'ain't never tried to have her way.  She
'ain't got any way.  She'd keep house, and you could about live
here.  We could do jest as we was a mind to."
</p><p>"But Esther's sot."
</p><p>"When it comes to what she thinks is her duty, Esther is more
than sot.  She's growed to it."
</p><p>"Willard Comstock always liked her, and a minister ought to
have a wife."
</p><p>"Esther told him not to come here again.  She said it would
make talk, and he'd better marry some one else.  She said, 'As long
as father lives, my duty is right here.'  It made me feel kind of
queer."  Old Billy's voice was pathetic.  "Seems as if old folks
hadn't ought to stand in the way of young ones, but how in Sam Hill
be they goin' to git out till the Lord calls 'em?"
</p><p>"Near as I can see, you ain't in the way."
</p><p>"No, I ain't, but she thinks I'm her duty, and there's no use
tryin' to reason her out of it." <pb n="31"/>
</p><p>"An' he ain't comin' any more?"
</p><p>"He 'ain't been here for months, and I can see she's feelin'
sort of miserable about it."
</p><p>"Why don't he stick it out an' come?  I guess when I was his
age I'd have stepped right over her duty an' trompled it down."
</p><p>"Ef he would only come!" reflected Billy.  "He used to come to
tea sometimes."  Suddenly he sat up.  His face assumed the
expression of eager mischief that it had worn when he had made his
expedition into the pantry for the flour and lard.  His eyes
snapped.  He slapped his knee.  "By hookey!" said he.  "I'll git
Willard Comstock here to tea this very night."
</p><p>Sam eyed him, as excited as his friend.  "How will you
manage?" he demanded.  For answer Billy rapped madly on the window.
</p><p>"What you doin' that for?"
</p><p>"I'm goin' to send the little Abbott boy to invite him.  Eddy
Abbott is such a good little boy, nobody can suspicion anything
ain't all right.  Esther, she's got plenty of cake and a floating-island.  She baked this mornin'.  I'll do it."  Billy beckoned
frantically.
</p><p>A little boy on the street outside, moving waveringly on
roller-skates, turned a pretty face toward the window.
</p><p>"Come in here a minute.  Come in here a minute," said Billy.
</p><p>The boy could not have heard him, but he saw the beckoning old
hand.  He navigated with difficulty up the front walk to the door,
where Billy met him.
</p><p>When Billy returned to the sitting-room he looked rather pale
but triumphant.  "Eddy Abbott is going to tell Willard Comstock
that Miss Esther Thomas invites him to take tea with her and her pa
at six o'clock to-night," he whispered.
</p><p>"Guess I'd better light out," said Sam, rising.
</p><p>"Guess you'd better.  It's most time for her to come home."
</p><p>"Ain't you goin' to shave or put on a clean collar; or
nothin'?"
</p><p>"Can't, unless I want her to suspicion somethin'."
</p><p>"Well," said Sam.  He lounged out, and presently Billy saw him
seated in an arm-chair on the grocery piazza.  He was smoking his
pipe.  He waved his hand imperceptibly.  Then Esther appeared,
walking rather hurriedly down the street with her little parcel
from the drug-store.
</p><p>"I guess I feel some better," Billy said when his daughter
entered, bottle and spoon in hand.
</p><p>"You had better take it, anyway, father.  You are not
breathing properly now."
</p><p>Billy murmured something about "not spilin' his appetite for
supper," but he took his dose.  Esther went out in the kitchen.
Billy rose and peeped out stealthily.  Esther was mixing biscuits.
Billy nodded approvingly and returned to his seat.
</p><p>He had begun to smell the biscuits baking when he saw a young
man coming hastily up the street.  He gave a sigh of relief.  Billy
had realized the risk he had run of getting a message of refusal by
little Eddy Abbott, and his daughter's discovery of the plot.  Now
that the young man was accepting, he knew that all would be well.
However puzzled Esther Thomas might be, she would say nothing when
a guest appeared at tea-time.  She had a great sense of
hospitality.  She might have refused to see Willard in the evening,
but at tea-time his welcome was assured, however bewildered she
might be.
</p><p>After Willard entered, Billy, gazing across at the grocery,
saw Sam Ellis double up with laughter.  He chuckled softly to
himself.  Esther had ushered the minister into the best parlor.
She came hurrying out to her father.
</p><p>"The minister has come to tea," she whispered.  Her cheeks
were softly blushing.
</p><p>"Did you ask him?"
</p><p>Esther shook her head.  "I don't understand it," she
whispered, "but he has come.  Go into the bedroom, father, and let
me brush your hair and coat.  You won't have time to shave.  Are
your hands clean?  Of, father! come out in the kitchen and wash
your hands."
</p><p>When Billy was fairly tidy and back in his chair, he looked
across at the grocery.  Sam still sat smoking on the piazza.  The
minister was now in the sitting-room.  Billy nodded solemnly,
<pb n="32"/>
with warning finger raised.  Sam nodded solemnly in response.
</p><p>Willard Comstock, discoursing to Billy about a recent death in
the village, with absent eyes upon Esther, a graceful vision moving
about in the next room, saw neither signal.  Billy, talking to the
minister, saw presently his dear Sam lounge down the street.  He
pictured him getting his solitary meal in his littered corner of
the old colonial house.  He wished, with the pathetic wish of age
and essential loneliness, to be with him there.  What had he&mdash;old,
with tastes reverting to those of childhood&mdash;to do with this fine
young clergyman who loved his daughter?  Poor old Billy wanted to
be in his own tracks of life&mdash;those tracks which he and his wife
Betsey had followed so easily.
</p><p>He did not like the supper which Esther finally served.  The
dining-table glittered with the best china and silver, and a piece
or two of cut-glass.  Apple-blossoms in a green bowl decorated the
center.  Esther had prepared a salad, very pretty, but strange to
Billy's old-fashioned taste.  The minister praised it.  Billy felt
a slight scorn.  Esther had thin slices of pink ham.  Billy liked
thick slices, but on account of the guest had to put up with the
thin.  Billy, silently eating, reflected how fortunate it was that
Willard Comstock had a mother.  Otherwise he would be obliged to
live with Willard and Esther.  It would be perfectly peaceful, but
the restraint of those bonds of Christian grace would be
insupportable.
</p><p>The next afternoon Esther went to the sewing society, and
Billy, as soon as the coast was clear, started to see Sam.  He
stole out of the house, locking the kitchen door and putting the
key under the mat on the porch, and taking a back road.  The main
one led by the church in whose chapel the sewing-society was
meeting.
</p><p>Billy was slightly lame, but he moved quickly.  He was afraid
that Sam might not be at home, but the other old man met him at the
door, his blue eyes gleaming with fond welcome out of his furze of
white hair.
</p><p>Billy entered, and was blest, to his conviction, with the
utmost which earth had to bestow.  It was seldom he got such a
chance as this.  When he entered the room in which Sam Ellis spent
most of his time, he looked about him blissfully.  It suited him.
It was his ideal of perfect comfort.  It was the large stately
south room of the old mansion.  There were paneled walls and a
wonderful mantelpiece, and the doors were marvelous.  There were
pieces of fine old mahogany furniture, and everything had been made
completely subservient to the use of the human creature who owned
it, and was, to Billy's mind, fulfilling its ultimate destiny.
</p><p>The tapestry carpet was fairly wonderful in its accumulation
of colors over and above the original patterns.  The paneled walls
were brown with smoke and drab with dust, and spotted like leopards
in bas-relief until they had taken on the aspect of deliberate,
although bizarre, decoration.  The chairs and the deep old sofa
were worn into the exact comfortable needs of human forms.  A
stovepipe had been fitted into an iron fireboard covering the great
fireplace, and there was a cooking-stove.  Before it stood a
kitchen table.  That was covered by a very smooth, clean cloth of
linen, and it glittered with an old solid-silver service.  The
cloth of linen and the bright silver at first seemed curiously at
odds with the room, and yet they were not.  They were made
subservient, as all else there, to the human need.
</p><p>Sam Ellis, sole remnant of his family, required perfect
cleanliness with regard to his meals, and his bedroom was
immaculate.  Every week his laundry was carefully attended to.
Much of Sam's slender income was spent for cleanliness, although
the general aspect of his living-room went far to deny it.
</p><p>Dust was everywhere.  Sam was philosophical about dust.
"Folks are silly, fussin' so about dust," he was wont to remark.
"Dust has to be somewhere.  When it's layin' on the chairs and
tables it's out of mischief.  You ain't breathin' it in.  What
folks want to go round stirrin' up dust for when it's quiet and out
of mischief, beats me."
</p><p>That afternoon old Billy settled down in his favorite chair,
a worn, leather-<pb n="33"/> covered rocker which fitted his old bones
with luxuriousness of comfort.  He drew a long sigh of content.
After a while he filled his pipe, and the two men smoked, and the
room was afloat with curling wreaths and eddies of rank smoke.
However, Billy's face wore an expression of anxiety.  Sam watched
him.
</p><p>"Didn't pan out the way you wanted it to last night, I
reckon," he said at length.
</p><p>Billy sniffed disgustedly.  "No, it didn't," he grunted.  "Too
much talk about duty.  Nothin' but duty.  Land!  I wonder whether
folks are really so much better than they was when you and I was
young.  Near as I can recollect, there wasn't anywhere near so much
said about duty."
</p><p>"Then Esther and Willard think it ain't their duty to get
married?"
</p><p>Billy shook his head.  "I listened.  Had to.  Esther thinks
it's her duty not to tell me things to worrit me.  Drat her duty!
An' there ain't any way left, if I feel as if I had ought to know
things, except to listen.  So I listened last night.  They was
settin' in the best parlor, and the door won't shut tight.  I stole
down, dreadful still, in my stockin' feet, after they thought I was
abed, and I listened.  Lord A'mighty, Sam, I ain't the only duty.
They are stuck fast ag'in."
</p><p>"What else?"
</p><p>"Willard's ma."
</p><p>Sam leaned back and laughed.  "Maria Comstock is just plumb
crazy to have Willard get married and leave her in peace with her
sister, Mis' Plummer," said he.  "She told me so only day before
yesterday.  She was gettin' along, as spry as you please, down to
the store.  She stepped out like a young girl, and her black-silk
skirts was swishin', and her bunnit strings flyin', and her head
up.  I stopped and spoke to her.  You know Maria and me used to
sort of go together when we was children.  I've always thought that
if somebody else hadn't come up for her, Maria and me might have
made a match of it.  She was a real pretty girl, and as smart as
they make 'em, and she ain't got over it yet.  I thought I'd sort
of hint about Willard, and she spoke her mind right out.  'Why on
earth,' said she, 'Willard and Esther want to act the way they do
is beyond me.  Near as I can find out, Esther thinks it's her duty
not to leave her pa, and she thinks her pa and me wouldn't get
along if Willard took him here or she took me there.  And we surely
would not,' says Maria.  'We surely would not, because I don't want
any such arrangement, and I wouldn't stand havin' that old man
around a minute.'  I'm tellin' you just what she said," stated Sam,
apologetically, to Billy.  "You know what Maria is."
</p><p>"I don't mind," said Billy.
</p><p>"'I want Willard to get married, the sooner the better, and
leave me and sister Addie Plummer in peace,' says Maria.  'We are
livin' in the old Comstock house, anyway, and folks are thinkin' it
sort of hard because the minister don't go to live in that nice new
parsonage they've built.  Willard and Esther can get married, and
Esther's pa can have somebody come and keep house for him, if he
don't want to live with them and they don't want him.'"
</p><p>Sam hesitated and then laughed.
</p><p>"What did she say next?" asked Billy.
</p><p>"Well, Maria did say she thought you were sort of cranky, and
maybe it would work out better for you not to live with them."
</p><p>Billy laughed.  "Maria and me have got just exactly the same
opinions," said he.
</p><p>Sam chuckled.  "I near snorted right out in her face when she
said that.  Maria was always smart as a whip, and good-lookin',
but, gee whiz! stand out of the way when you hear her petticoats
swishin'.  But I swan, now she's in the right of it.  She says she
and her sister can be a heap more comfortable if Willard gets
married.  She says their help is gittin' old, and it's nothin' but
tend door, and answer the telephone, and entertain ministers
exchangin'.  She says it ain't any work for elderly women.  Then
she says they have to entertain a lot besides, and poor folks are
always comin' for some charity just at meal-times.  Lord! poor
Maria Comstock don't want duty done by her any more than you do,
Billy.  And I've been thinkin' about Serrah Miles.  What do you
want to bother with her for?  Here's this big house, and you and me
could git along enough sight better together <pb n="34"/>  than either of
us could with any woman housekeeper.  I have Mis' Doty come in
every week, and wash and iron, and that's all we need done.  I can
cook to beat any woman round here; and I don't want any arrangin'
of my belongin's so I can't find a durned thing when I want it.
You could rent your house, Billy, and that would give you and
Esther a little extra.  Of course, it wouldn't cost you nothin' to
live here, but money is money."
</p><p>"Yes, it is," assented Billy.  He sighed.  "Tell you what
'tis, Sam: livin' here with you, and both of us doin' jest as we
are a mind to, would be too much for this world, I guess.  I'd feel
as I used to with Betsey.  Betsey used to let me smoke all over the
house.  She said tobacco ashes was clean dirt, and good to keep out
moths.  I dunno but Betsey would have smoked herself if I'd tried
to make her.  And I could set anywhere I wanted to, and tip my
chair back, and lean my head agin' any wall-paper in the house.
And if I put a thing down anywhere, I'd find it right there six
months from then.  Betsey never picked up my things so I couldn't
find 'em.  And that 'Landin' of the Pilgrim Fathers' always used to
hang with the left side 'way down, and every time I see it hangin'
straight it makes me homesick.  Esther's a good daughter, though."
</p><p>"Lord, yes! she's good enough, but she's too everlastin' stuck
on her duty to know when it's barkin' everybody else's shins!"
</p><p>"I don't know what to do," said Billy, despondently.  "She and
Willard talked real decided last night."
</p><p>Sam Ellis started up.  "There's Eddy Abbott," he said.  He
rushed to the door and called: "Hullo, Eddy!  Eddy, come here a
minute."
</p><p>Sam admitted the small boy, as pink-faced and gentle as a
little girl.  "You wait a minute, Eddy," said Sam.
</p><p>Eddy stood immovable, waiting.  He was an obedient child.  He
did not even shift his weight from one foot to the other.  He did
not even stare about the room while Sam wrote two notes at the old
secretary.
</p><p>"Here, Eddy," said Sam.  "You give this one to the minister,
and the other to Miss Esther Thomas.  She's at the sewing-circle in
the vestry.  Here, you wait a minute, Eddy."  Sam took the lid from
an earthen jar which stood on a magnificent old mahogany table, and
brought forth two very large brown doughnut twists.  "Here, Eddy,"
said Sam.
</p><p>"Thank you," said Eddy.  He stowed away the notes carefully in
his little coat pocket, took the doughnuts, and walked away eating
them.
</p><p>"I fried them doughnuts yesterday," said Sam.  "I don't want
none of your fancy cakes, but I do like good solid doughnuts and
pies; and what's more, I can make 'em to suit me better than any
woman I've known sence my own mother."
</p><p>"What did you say in them notes?"
</p><p>"I said somethin' that's goin' to bring duty to a head, jest
like a bile," said Sam, and roared at his own joke.
</p><p>Billy looked a little alarmed, then he also laughed.
</p><p>"Now we'll set back an' wait," said Sam.
</p><p>Esther was the first to arrive.  She came hurrying down the
street.  Sam met her at the door.
</p><p>"Is father here?  What is the matter?" she asked.  She was a
little out of breath.  Sam, looking over her heaving shoulder,
draped with soft gray cloth, could see Willard Comstock
approaching.  He was walking rapidly.  Sam's notes had been
peremptory.
</p><p>"Now don't you be one mite scared, Esther," said Sam.  "There
ain't anything to be scared about.  Your father's in here, and we
are goin' to settle things.  Why, here's Willard.  Hullo, Willard.
Walk right in."
</p><p>Willard Comstock, tall and pale, and gentle of expression,
with a square chin which seemed to denote that gentleness might
have to win, at times, in hard battle, did walk in.  He and Esther
exchanged glances of bewilderment.
</p><p>"Nothing is the matter with father, is there?" Esther asked.
Her serene voice was a little tremulous.
</p><p>"Land, no!  He's as right as a cricket.  No, don't go in
there.  That's the room where I live, mostly.  I lived there all
winter, and I've got my cookin'-stove in there.  The spring's so
late I ain't moved it out into the kitchen.  I'm goin'
[illustration omitted] <pb n="35"/>  to next week.  Here, you come in this
room.  There's dust, but we are all made of dust and we hadn't
ought to mind if we do see it layin' round loose."
</p><p>Sam ushered them into a fairly stately apartment.  It was very
large, the ceiling high, and the woodwork was a masterpiece of
domestic architecture, patiently wrought by hands long since folded
in the grave.  The furniture was covered with red damask.  Long
curtains of red damask, caught back by gilt scroll-work, hung at
the windows.  There was a Turkey carpet, and old portraits and
engravings.  The room was dark and damp.
</p><p>Sam opened a window, and a great sighing breath of blooming
lilacs from a rank growth outside entered the room.  He opened
another, and a shaft of sunlight marked by floating dust-motes
crossed the room.  They all sat down.  Sam began to speak.
</p><p>"I know all about it," said he.  "I know you two young folks,
that ain't gittin' any younger whilst you're waitin', want to get
married and set up your own home.  And I know Esther thinks it's
her duty to stay single and take care of her pa.  And Willard
thinks it's his to stay single and take care of his ma.
</p><p>"Now I'm goin' to preach to the minister and the minister's
wife.  Who be you, either one of you, to set up for knowin' what
your duty is before other folks that's older?  Esther's father
wants her to get married.  He thinks the world of her, and he knows
she's always devoted her life to him, but&mdash;he don't want her to!
And Willard's ma; she knows Willard has devoted his life to her,
and&mdash;she don't want him to!
</p><p>"Billy, here, and Maria, both just want their son and daughter
to get married and look out for their own interests, and let them
alone to look out for theirs.  Billy knows he'd be a lot happier
livin' here with me, and havin' his harmless little way that ain't
goin' to hurt his immortal soul one mite.  And Maria knows she's
goin' to be a lot happier livin' with her sister than she is with
a man messin' 'round, no matter if he is her own son and the salt
of the earth.  Maria is all worn out playin' the second religious
fiddle.  She's too old.
</p><p>"So both of you, Willard and Esther, have been thinkin' you
were doin' your duty and feelin' real miserable over it when you
wasn't neither one of you doin' your duty at all.  What you haven't
neither one of you sensed is that enough sight oftener than folks
realize doin' their duty is havin' their own way and lettin' other
folks have theirs."
</p><p>Willard and Esther looked at each other.
</p><p>"It is so," said Sam Ellis, with a magnificent gesture of
authority.
</p><p>After Willard and Esther had gone, Sam began to make
preparations for supper.  It was a cold day for May.  Sam was to
have a hot supper.
</p><p>Billy watched him, fairly grinning with delight.  "Say, Sam,"
said he, "s'pose it's settled?"
</p><p>"Sure," said Sam.  "They'll get married right off and then you
and me will bunk together.  Here, you peel these onions and slice
'em thin."
</p><p>"Fried onions!" gasped Billy.
</p><p>"As prime a beefsteak as ever you laid your eyes on and fried
onions," proclaimed Sam, "and hot baked potatoes and coffee and
doughnuts."
</p><p>"I 'ain't had any fried onions since Betsey died," said Billy.
"She and I used to have 'em twice a week, regular.  Esther would
have had 'em if I'd asked her, but I never asked her.  It would
have been a real trial to her."
</p><p>"I ain't sayin' anything against your daughter," said Sam,
"but sometimes I've really wondered if many folks spoke the truth
when they said they didn't like onions."
</p><p>"I guess Esther don't really like 'em," said Billy.
</p><p>"Well, I dare say she don't.  We do, and we can have 'em every
day in the week if we want to.  Slice 'em thin, Billy."
</p><p>"Beefsteak and fried onions," said Billy, thoughtfully.
</p><p>Sam, on his way to the stove with the beefsteak, looked at
Billy, and Billy looked at him.  In both faces was the expression
of men who have regained freedom and found her dearer than they
remembered.
</p><p>"I guess now we'll all be happy, and do our duty, and have our
own way," said Sam.
</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>



